<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="109841eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
HgSMMESi
M 1205-9712 22,00 F
INTERVIEW WITH RENE DEPESTRE
ENVIRONMENT: CLIMATE CHANGE-THE GREAT DEBATE
HERITAGE: POTOSÍ (BOLIVIA)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TTgÄ° Nikon
international photo competition
The international jury for the competition on the theme of Peace in everyday life met at Unesco Headquarters
on 29 October 1997. It awarded the Unesco Courier- Nikon Prize to:
Eric Lesdema
for "War games"
It also awarded a Special Jury Prize to:
Jordis Antonia Schlösser
for "Havana"
and honourable mentions to:
Florian Haerdter
for "The Goutte d'Or quarter, Paris"
and
Didier Lefèvre
for "Kabul"
The members of the jury were:
Chairman:
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN,
writer
Laurent Abadjian,
photo editor, Libération newspaper
Manoucher Deghati,
correspondent, AFP
Colin Jacobson,
photo editor, senior research fellow, University of Wales Cardiff
Marloes Krijnen,
Managing Director, World Press Photo Foundation
Simon Njami,
Editor-in-Chief of the Revue Noire
Adel Rifaat,
Director of the Unesco Courier
Mark Sealy,
Director of Autograph, the Association of Black Photographers
Keiichi Tahara,
artist/photographer
The prize-winning photos and those that particularly attracted the juries' attention during
the shortlisting process and the final selection will be published in forthcoming issues of the
Unesco Courier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
47
René Depestre
A noted Franco-Haitian writer looks back
over his nomadic life.
THE TREASURE OF THE CERRO RICO
by Pascale Absi
An originalfolk culture in the mining city of
Potosí (Bolivia), whose fabulous silver
deposits once made it a bywordfor riches.
contents
DECEMBER 1997
ISLANDS
A WORLD APART
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat	5
Islands of the imagination	6
by Robert Baudry
Iceland's hidden fire 11
by Thor Vilhjálmsson
The Pacific: the coming of the ancestors	14
by Antonio Guerreiro
Solstice islands	17
by Edouard J. Maunick
The trials of Ulysses 18
by Jacques Lacarrière
What, my brother, is an island?	22
by Lokenath Bhattacharya
Easter Island's last secret 24
by Luis Mizón
Cuba's gold	28
by Eduardo Manet
Fact file 31
Consultant:/,uis Mizón
Commentary Federico Mayor
GREENWATCH Climate change: the great debate by France Bequette 40
LISTENING Isabelle Leymarle talks to Steve Tu rre 44
Cover:
Bora Bora in the Society Islands (French Polynesia).
© Yann Arthus Bertrand/Erath from Above/UNESCO
REFLECTIONS Funding a new home for Egypt's ancient treasures bySamir Gharib
AL'HORS
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1997
45
49
50
THE UNESCO ^>URIERB DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
th& unesco
Courier
^"^50th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Pans CEDEX 15, France
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68.57 45
e mail unesco couner@unesco org
Internet' http //www unesco org
Director: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition Roy Malkin
French edition. Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition Araceli Ortiz de Urbma
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 90)
Documentation: José Banaag
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68, 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 87)
Film duplication: Daniel Meister
Secretariat Annie Brächet
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian. Irma Utkina (Moscow)
German" Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi. Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch. BartChnstiaens (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay Sidm Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili Leonard J Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene. Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese Feng Mmgxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian1 Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Smhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish Rutta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque* Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai DuangtipSunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Pashto Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa1 Ahyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian Volodymyr Vasihuk (Kiev)
Galician. Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax. (33) (0)1.45 68.57.45
Subscriptions- Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Dm
(Tel (33) (0)1.45 68.49.19)
Customer service Michel Ravassard,
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45 68 45 91)
Accounts (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 65)
Shipping Daniel Meister (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 47 50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel.: (33) (0)1 45,68.45 65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years 396 FF
Students' 1 year 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues. 72 FF
Developing countries*
1 year. 132 French francs 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual ameles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author's name Non-copyright photos will
be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nec¬
essarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the
Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100
U S A , (3) N C R Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc , 111 West 40th
Street, New York. U S A ; (4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mansfield Road,
Wooster, Ohio 44691. USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - DECEMBER 1997
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N M P.P
Photocomposition, photogravure:
Le Courrier de I'Unesco
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z I. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041 5278 N° 12-1997-OP1-97-565 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50 51
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1097
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
í
month by month
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
Britain and Japan are island nations,
economically powerful and highly
influentialin world affairs. But as islands they
do not haunt our dreams. Jules Verne's
mysterious island, Robert Louis Stevenson's
Treasure Island and the island of Sindbad the
Sailor on the other handthough they do not
exist Linger on in our dreams into adult life.
This issue is mainly concerned with realislands
thatare also dream islands, with the myths that
have been woven around them and with the
interplay they generate between the imaginary
and the real.
Islands are not the only things that inspire
dreams. Deserts, mountains and twilight can also
take us out of humdrum reality and lift us high
above our everyday selves. But some islands
inspire dreams with a very special quality of their
own, the quality of evoking wonder. While the
Sahara may be propitious to meditation, it does
not fill us with wonder, as do Easter Island and
Ithaka.
Why do such places have this very special,
very elusive feelto them? Perhaps because it is
possible to live on an island and feel one is
living in another world, because the island-
dweller's existence will never be an ordinary one.
Islanders experience a sense of apartness, an
awareness of the unreal within the real, of the
permanent presence of the unexpected, a strange
destiny in which every moment is an adventure.
Jacques Lacarrière puts it very well when he
suggests that deep within this experience of a
duality there may be a voyage into the deepest
recesses of our own being, a long quest, starting
out from what we believe ourselves to be, to
discover what we really are, a winding odyssey
that begins by taking us faraway from ourselves
and ends by bringing us faceto face with the
ultimate truth about ourselves.
Is our nostalgia for the wonderful island
perhaps a metaphor for our yearning for the
absolute? This is one of the avenues for
exploration presentedwith the compliments of
the seasonin this December issue.
THE UNESCO ^>URIERI DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Islands of the imagination
BY ROBERT BAUDRY
A guided tour of some of world literature's many
fictional islands
Islands occupy a special place in our
mythologies, often as the scene of mys¬
terious or extraordinary occurrences. Being
cut off from the rest of the world, they are
depicted as sanctuaries where human contact
can be fled and danger escaped, or as places of
réclusion where atonement may be sought.
Clustered together, they offer many a bay and
inlet where boats can land. They may be the
abodes of monsters. Upon their shores tem¬
ples may be erected for the performance of
bloody sacrifices; there, pirates may alight,
bearing stolen treasures. Or they may be the
last gateway to paradise.
Because of all these associations islands have
always enjoyed special favour in the eyes of
storytellers, particularly those who write of
the supernatural.
But what is the supernatural? It may be
defined as that which arouses in us a sense of
mystery, a fascination before the revelation of
Another World. This is the first theme of
interest to us here the division between our
world and another world. But this other
world is itself ambiguous: like Janus, it has
two faces, one magical, the other monstrous.
Two different worlds
Detached from the mainland, islands mark a
separation from the everyday world. By their
very nature, they suggest an individual iden¬
tity, standing in opposition to a collective
destiny. Representing in each case a world apart ,
turned in on themselves, islands are governed
by laws different from those that hold sway
in other lands.
Already in the thirteenth-century parody of
Romance epic Aucassin et Nicolette, the place
chosen to represent the very opposite of our
world was an island, the island of Torelore,
where women make war, where men give birth,
and so on. J
The mainland is the place of ordinary life; |
islands are where extraordinary things hap- %
pen. They are the theatre of fabulous dreams, S
far removed from reality. Then again, where the i
mainland is represented in secular terms, |
islands embody the sacred, being the site of ¡
temples where sacrifices are performed with !
good or evil intent. And in contradistinction |
with our world of the living, islands often
symbolize the inaccessible realm of the dead.
The solitude of islands
The word "island" comes from the Latin in¬
sula and carries a sense of solitude, isolation,
loneliness. A patch of land surrounded by the
sea, a motionless boat washed by the waves, it
is the perfect symbol of man, at once pro¬
tected from his fellows and unhappily separate
from them. Ambivalence again!
One thinks of course of all the Robinsons
shipwrecked on a lonely shore, confined
within a universe closed in upon itself. But,
tellingly enough, the supreme example may
be said to be Jean-Jacques Rousseau. Ill at ease
in company, a lover of solitude, he sought
refuge on the island of Saint-Pierre in the mid¬
dle of Lake Biel in Switzerland, but found
that the spot still was not isolated enough for
his taste. So, having dispatched his lunch, he
cast off in a boat which he left to drift upon
the current. And there, in this floating island,
lulled by the lapping of the waves, he gave
himself up to daydreams that gradually devel¬
oped into a trance of ecstasy (Rêveries du
promeneur solitaire, 1782).
A place of refuge
Small wonder then that this place of solitude
has so often been seen as a refuge for those who
wish to flee human society and all its trials.
What better illustration of this could be
"The embarkation of Tristan
and Iseult", a miniature from a
15th-century manuscript of the
Tristan romance.
A longer version of this
article has appeared in Ile des
merveilles, Mirage, miroir,
mythe, Actes du Colloque
organisé à Cerisy-la-Salle
parle CERMEIL (Centre
de Recherches sur le
Merveilleux), L'Harmattan
publishers, Paris, 1997.
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER '997
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
A detail from L'île
rieureuse("The Happy
Isle") by the French
artist Paul Albert
Besnard (1849-1934).
found than that offered by the French writer
Henri Bosco in L'Enfant et la rivière (1945).
Borne away by the current to an island on the
Durance river while asleep in a boat, the young
hero discovers a quarry where cruel nomads are
torturing a boy of his age. He sets him free and,
stealing a boat, escapes with him to an oxbow
lake off the river. There they shake off the fears
aroused in them by their sinister pursuers. They
thus find themselves doubly on an island: in
stagnant waters protected by a wall of brush¬
wood amidst hostile lands; and in a boat
moored in those waters, forming so to speak an
island within an island. What surer refuge fro m
the fury of those who would do them harm ?
The island as a stepping-stone
Such places can be reached only at the end of a
long journey. This embodies a process of initi¬
ation which often leads the hero from one island
to another, each representing a different experi¬
ence, until he reaches the ultimate island, the
ultima Thule, a fabulous land that the early
European geographers regarded as the further¬
most northern limit of the known world.
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER I 997
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Everyone knows Homer's Odyssey and
Sindbad the Sailor, one of the episodes in the
famous collection of Arabian tales known as
The Thousand and One Nights. Fewerpeople
know the early Irish epic known as The Voyage
ofBrendan, which recounts the maritime expe¬
dition of the ancient Celtic god Brendan,
threading his way through a labyrinth of fab¬
ulous islands, each more extraordinary than
the last, or the later Voyage de Maëlduin. Sur¬
prisingly, The Voyage of Brendan was to be
adapted into Latin in the ninth century under
the title of the Navigatio sancti Brandini, with
the Celtic god becoming a Christian saint; and
then, around 1121, into Anglo-Norman, by
an archdeacon of Rouen, Benoit, before being
widely translated and circulated in Europe.
Aplace ofatonement
But islands are not always shelters, refuges,
havens of grace; nor momentary halts on the
way to some other destiny. Enclosed by the sea,
they can naturally serve as places of atonement.
What better example is there of this than
Robinson Crusoe (1719)? It tells the story of a
young man who, instead of minding his own
business in England and earning a living like
his parents, takes it into his head to follow a
perverse bent for adventure. Providence there¬
fore punishes him for the crime of scorning
the pursuit of honest trade at home by casting
him upon an inhospitable desert island, unin¬
habited by man or beast, without food or
tools. Such is the real meaning that Daniel Defoe
wished to give to his story. However, the old
myth of the blessed isle exercised so powerful
a hold on his readers' imaginations that before
long this place of purgatory came to be seen as
a paradise and inspired a score of imitations,
known generically as "Robinsonnades".
The home ofmonsters
Offering as they do a setting different from
that of the ordinary world, remote islands
naturally lend themselves to visions of mon¬
sters who are assumed to be their denizens.
Thus it was that Ulysses was at one
moment exposed to the danger of being
turned into a swine by the perfidious but
enticing enchantress Circe and, at another,
shipwrecked on the island of the Cyclops
where he ran a serious risk of ending up like his
companions as the one-eyed giant's breakfast.
But perhaps the most fabulous catalogue of
island monsters created by the fertile Celtic
imagination as embodied in the visions of sea¬
farers is to be found in The Voyage of Bren¬
dan and, in particular, in Le voyage de Maël¬
duin, which speaks of one island inhabited
by starving ants as big as ponies and another
by a fearsome horse with razor-sharp hooves
bristling with blue claws.
Following this tradition of island monsters,
later writers added their own: the creatures
devised by a mad scientist in The Island ofDoc¬
tor Moreau (1 896) by H. G. Wells; the charming
cannibals in Typee (1846) by Herman Melville on
Nuku-Hiva in the Marquesas Islands; the loath¬
some figure of the sadist Vorski sacrificing and
crucifying his victims on the sinister island of
Sarek at the far end of the earth in L'île aux
trente cercueils (1920) by Maurice Leblanc.
Right, detail showing Iceland
(top left) and marine monsters
from a map of Scandinavia by
Olaus Magnus (1490-1557), a
Swedish ecclesiastic and
scholar whose history of the
northern peoples appeared in
many editions and
translations.
8 THE UNESCO I OURIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
And in our own time, was it not on an
island that the safari hunters discovered the
abominable King Kong, the giant ape in the
famous American film (1933) directed by Mcr-
ian Cooper and Ernest B. Schoedsack?
The home offairies
But just as, in the world of the imagination,
islands may be depicted as being the abodes
of monsters, so they may also be regarded as
the home of fairies. The bewitching, terrifying
Circe in the Odyssey finds a counterpoint in
the friendly and helpful Calypso. The dan¬
gers and horrors encountered during Le voy¬
age de Maëlduin alternate with wondrous
experiences. On one island grow magical apples
whose sweet juices provoke an ecstasy akin to
death. On another there is a palace reached by
a crystal bridge where a fairy woman dwells.
She offers the companions a cheese in which,
as in the legend of the Graal, each one finds the
taste he most prefers in the world. For them,
the three months they spend in the palace last
three years and end only with the appearance
of a fantastic bird, the bird of their regained
youth	
And what fabulous figures have been imag¬
ined by storytellers and writers: the fair Iseult,
worker of miracles in Ireland, towards whom
Tristan lets his coracle drift at the will of wind
and waves; or the Fair Queen ruling over
Andersen's The Garden ofParadise who per¬
fumes with flowers the Island of Bliss, a
delightful place where death is unknown and
where the hero is carried by the cast wind; or
again, the charming female Robinson por¬
trayed by Jean Giraudoux in Suzanne et le
Pacifique (1921).
Treasure Island
The secret wonders so readily associated with
islands may thus be embodied in places of
enchantment or fairy figures, but they may
also take the form of fabulous treasures. The
most perfect examples of islands containing
such treasures are of course depicted in The
Count of Monte-Cristo (1845) by Alexandre
Dumas and Treasure Island (1883), by Robert
Louis Stevenson.
This powerful myth still exercises its full
fascination today. Pierre Mac Orlan in Le chant
de l'équipage (1918) sends his hero to the
West Indies in seach of pirates' treasure, which
he finally discovers much nearer home an
adventure similar to that which befalls the
protagonist ofJean-Marie Gustave Le Clézio's
recent novel Le chercheur d'or (1985). And
why not also mention Red Rackham 's Trea¬
sure, the strip cartoon adventure featuring
Tintin drawn by Hergé, ever keen to revive
the old legends that haunt us?
A 17th-century Persian
miniature depicting a voyage
by Sindbad the Sailor, a hero
of The Thousand and One
Nights.
The last stage in an initiatory
journey
So numerous are the horrors and obstacles
bestrewing the path of the hero, so many
exploits must he perform in order to reach
his goal, that his progress towards his island
destination often resembles an initiatory jour¬
ney which culminates in a revelation.
Ulysses, embarked upon his circuitous
journey that leads from one island to another,
finally returns home where he is able at last
to address the shade of his dead mother.
Gilliat, by surmounting all the tribulations of
cold, water, hunger, thirst and fear, achieves
merit, only to be disappointed before finding
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER I 997
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
a consummation in his fatal union with the
sea, as related by Victor Hugo in Les Tra¬
vailleurs de la Mer (1866).
Elsa Morante's L'Isola di Arturo (1957)
also ends with an initiation which includes
the ultimate ordeal, the revelation of the last
and cruellest mystery of life. And in his alle¬
gorical tale AlHayyibn Yaqzàn, the twelfth-
century Moorish philosopher Ibn Tufayl
describes a kind of Muslim Robinson Crusoe
who, after being abandoned as a child on an
island close to India, is able by himself, in this
place conducive to meditation, to discover the
laws of nature and to penetrate intuitively to
the mystic truths.
The other side
We now come to the very edge of the world,
where the other face of reality is revealed.
In Homer's Odyssey, the island of the
Phaeacians, skilled seafarers accustomed to
rowing from one world to another, embodies
this idea of passing over, of moving from one
reality to another. In Le voyage de Maëlduin,
what the hero perceives is also an island, but a
strange island divided by a wall. On one side
of the wall are black sheep, on the other, white
sheep. When a white sheep is moved to the
other side, it at once turns black. When a black
sheep joins the white sheep, it immediately
becomes white. The wall is clearly a bound¬
ary separating two worlds.
Paradise
All these islands are but ports of call, last out¬
posts, places of initiation, gateways to the
island of the Other World, final goal of the
Adventure and of the Quest, crowning point
of this labyrinthine journey. Islands of the
Blessed in the Hesperidean gardens of Greek
mythology; Emain Ablach, the Faery Isle of
the Celts, the Island of the Dead, from Pro-
copius to Maurice Leblanc such are some of
the myriad guises assumed by the same theme.
It is always an ideal island, the island of
another world. Where else indeed does Gil-
gamesh, the earliest Babylonian epic, place the
terrestrial paradise, other than on a remote
and inaccessible island, at the furthermost lim¬
its of the Earth, beyond the waters of death?
Why, from Plato to Aldous Huxley, from
Thomas More to Tommaso Campanella, have
the perfect cities of so many Utopias been
located on islands? Surely for no reason other
than a desire to leave behind the paltry routines
of everyday life and recreate elsewhere the ideal
city to which we aspire.
Journey's end
We have been able to do no more here than
touch on some of the huge number of works
centred on islands.
It is none the less clear from the few exam¬
ples cited that the myth of a wondrous isle has
enjoyed such exceptional favour because it nat¬
urally lends itself to the traditional themes of
the narrative art, particularly adventure stories
and tales of the supernatural: escape away fro m
and out of the world, sea and mountain, soli¬
tude and shelter, treasure, fairies and monsters,
paradise and ecstasy, and many others.
All these themes form a kind of constella¬
tion with the island at the centre, around
which they gravitate as though by magnet¬
ism, like so many planets around the sun. And
these planets may in turn suggest other themes
which, by association, cause us to envelop in
mystery any island at all, no matter how ordi¬
nary in itself, and to identify it with the fab¬
ulous realm of myth.
A print by the Japanese
artist Andô Hiroshige
(1797-1858). It is one of a
series entitled Tôkaidô
gojûsan tsugi ("Fifty-three
Stages of theTokaido"),
published in 1833-1834.
10 ) QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Iceland's hidden fire
BYTHORVILHJÁLMSSON
*%* _ ,*%
© Ragnar Axelsson/Liaison Inl/Hoa Qui, Pans
The modern-
minded
traditionalists
and hard-headed
dreamers who
live on an island
of extremes
Iceland, an island in the North
Atlantic ocean, is a land of
glaciers, volcanoes and
geysers. The capital, Reykjavik,
top, is located on Faxa Bay In
the southwest of the island.
Iceland. Not a very inviting name for the
prospective tourist turning the atlas
round with an indolent finger while looking for
somewhere to relax. What can people make of
it, especially since another country that reaches
all the way to the North Pole and is little more
than snow and ice is called Greenland?
But unalluring though its name may
sound, Iceland is a country that invites and
welcomes people who possess the gift of
curiosity, are ready to use their eyes and ears,
and let their sense of fantasy revel in the unique
scenery that awaits them. People of the kind
described in the Bible as "seeing they do not
see and hearing they do not hear" would be
well advised to go elsewhere
People who live surrounded by sea have a
particular way of perceiving themselves and the
world. For Icelanders, the ocean has always been
both an invitation and a deterrent and in spite
of modern technology it still is. Through the
centuries young seafarers who braved its perils
to reach other countries and other people passed
a rite of initiation into adulthood. They
returned matured by their experience, accepted
as people worth listening to, people with a tale
to tell. Homecomers were ready to feel and
understand more profoundly their own
scenery, the magic of their own island.
For centuries the people of Iceland looked
out at the sea and the sky from shore, cliff or
mountain, their backs itching where wings
tried to sprout. In the blue opening of the
clouds on a overcast day they saw golden tow¬
ers beaming at them, princesses winking fro m
balconies, and crowd-packed streets. All the
wonders of diversity lay before them. The
courts of kings waited to be immortalized by
the gift of poetry that ripens in solitude and
grows in silence.
Loneliness and silence
Behind them lay a vast country whose land¬
scapes by turns wild and protective, mild and
fierce, hostile and gentle are constantly being
shaped by warring extremes. Fire lurks beneath
the glacier's shining white shield where it meets
the cloudless sky. You feel that nothing is
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1 997 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
remote and that you can see all the way to the
end of the world. You see the lava-fields ruffled
into contorted figures imprisoning eerie beings,
monsters sacralized in stone, anguished souls
waiting to be released from the purifying tor¬
tures of Purgatory. For centuries they have
moaned in the wind as they watched the soli¬
tary traveller go about his business.
These travellers were richly endowed by
the storytelling of their people of their
grandmothers, of the taciturn, reluctantly elo¬
quent farmer-fishermen who were their fathers
and grandfathers. They grew up in a demand¬
ing land which offered the senses food for
observation and thought. They benefited from
having to learn very early how to survive the
sudden whims of unpredictable nature, and
bear the burden of loneliness and silence
amidst the wind's roar. The distance between
one farm and the next may be so great that
you have time, while crossing a mountain or
finding your way through a blizzard, to com¬
pose in your mind a yarn to tell the people on
the farm you are making for and satisfy their
hunger for news, for words, for sagas.
Telling stories has carried the Icelanders
through the centuries, through good times and
bad. It was in Iceland that the Sagas, that body
of universal literature, were written in the thir¬
teenth and fourteenth centuries, mainly in a
language that could be easily understood in all
THE UNESCO ^>URIER DECEMBER 1997
Svartsengl geothermal
plant, above, provides
Reykjavik with hot water. The
diversion of its surplus
production into a lava field
has given rise to the Blue
Lagoon (foreground), whose
mineral-rich waters have a
temperature varying from
25to35°C.
the countries of the north, as well as in Viking
settlements in Ireland, Yorkshire and other
parts of the British Isles, and in Normandy.
It has actually been said that Icelanders do not
take any fact entirely seriously unless it can be
used in a story or a poem. On a superficial
acquaintance, this may not seem true of modern
Icelanders who seem to be absorbed in the super¬
fluities of fashion, technological gadgetry and
other wonders of modernity. But it is part of
our nature, a result of the fact that we lead dou¬
ble lives, being at the same time ultra-modern
and ancient, natural and supernatural, surrealis¬
tic dreamers and super-realistic technicians.
The Viking spirit
It is often said that Icelanders can trace their
ancestry back to the Viking seafarers who came
from rocky northern countries and learned
how to build boats that elegantly resisted the
fury of the raging Atlantic. The Vikings had
already sailed southwards and eastwards before
settling in Iceland. They had penetrated into
the vastness of Russia, voyaged up the Seine to
Paris, and journeyed to Sicily and Rome. Then,
with only the stars to guide them, they found
this strange island and settled there. Before that
they had made landfall in Ireland and took
slaves from this civilized nation with a rich lit¬
erary tradition.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Rugged moorland
landscape of Manalaugard in
the south of Iceland.
In 930 the settlers in Iceland established
the Althing, today the world's oldest parlia¬
ment. In the year 1000 paganism was officially
renounced and Christianity was accepted. The
slaves brought from Ireland merged with the
Viking people, losing their language but fer¬
tilizing their masters' creativity. Civilization
develops as the vanquished enrich their rulers'
souls and become the ultimate victors.
In 1262 we lost our independence to the
Norwegian king and later to the Danish king¬
dom, under which we remained as a kind of
colony. Our situation gradually deteriorated
and a chapter in our history ended in 1550
with the downfall of the Catholic church,
which had been the only effective bulwark
against foreign royal power and colonization.
With Protestantism we moved into the dark
ages of our existence. "Everyone died who
could", says a character in a book by our
Nobel prize-winning writer Halldôr Laxness.
Our risorgimento was partly due to an explo¬
sion of poetry and romanticism in the last
century led by realistic leaders who gained first
autonomy in internal affairs, then home rule
at the turn of the century, virtual indepen¬
dence by the end of the First World War, and
finally the re-establishment of a completely
independent republic in 1944.
After independence Icelandic society was
jerked out of its medieval pattern of life and
work. Until then life had been limited to herd¬
ing and cultivating barely fertile ground,
rounding up sheep in autumn and bringing
them home from their summer mountain pas¬
tures. As the men of the farm cut the grass,
they would recite epic poems whose words
were carried away by the wind. Serious con¬
versation was rare with anyone except your
dog and, on Sundays, your horse. On the rare
occasions when a foreigner appeared in your
farmstead he was led into your lowly grass-
thatched abode and then you sent for the cler¬
gyman to converse with him in Latin. For
centuries, fishing was done by small crews in
rowing boats.
This may be all behind us, but it is still
within us. Our isolation has been definitely
broken. Now we go up into the mountains to
seek anew its ancient privileges, and recharge
our spirit in the wilderness beside a rushing
brook while torrents roar in canyons in the
background and the colours explode into our
eyes.
THE UNESCO COURIER DECEMBER 1997 lo
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A ritual canoe race on Iriomote
in Japan's Ryukyu Islands. It
takes place during Shichi, a
festival held to obtain a new
year blessing from gods and
ancestors.
Creation myths
and ancestor
worship are
widespread in the
Pacific islands
o 10 GUERREIROBY
a ecoming of
a e
The world of islands that is the Pacific
Ocean embraces very many different
cultures. But from the Ryukyus of Japan, to
Samoa and Tahiti, local mythology largely
agrees on how the islands came into being.
In the Japanese archipelago of Yaeyama,
rituals and oral tradition recall the customs
of Oceania. A myth current in one of these
islands, Ishigaki-jima, tells how the gods and
the ancestors created them.
Once upon a time, it goes, the sun god
ordered another god, Amang, to come down
from the sky to create an island on earth.
Amang did so and mixed sand and earth with
the end of his spear. From this mixture, the
first island sprang. Then, in the pandanus palm
forest which grew up on the island, he created
the hermit crab, amang-cha. Next he gave the
crab human seed, and a pair of human beings,
a man and a woman, eventually emerged fro m
the crab's hole in the sand.
On the west coast of the neighbouring
THE UNESCO (gUIUER • OtCI.MHfR 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
island of Iriomote-jima, the inhabitants use
annual events, such as the year-end sabani canoe
races, to invoke the blessing of the gods and
the ancestors for the coming year. Such bene¬
diction is in the form of theyuu, which brings
prosperity and plant growth from beyond
the horizon, from the sky or from the deep
vague places where the gods and the ancestors
also live.
At the festival of Soru (in the seventh lunar
month), the dead and the ancestors are invited
back to the village, to the houses where they
were born. There they receive offerings, and cel¬
ebrations in their honour go on for three
nights. A group of masked young people, the
Anggama, conjure up through dance the com¬
munity of the dead and the ancestors.
From nature to culture
The man and the woman from the story of the
creation are the ancestors of those who set¬
tled in the Yaeyama islands. Many variants of
this myth are to be found in the islands of
Hateruma, Taketomi and Miyako. Among the
Austronesians of Belau, Samoa and Tahiti, the
creation is seen in a similar way out of chaos,
with life descending from the sky to the earth
A modern wooden figurehead
from an Asmat dugout canoe.
The Asmats are a fishing people
of New Guinea.
© Charles Lénars, Pans Jayapura University museum
A canoe race held during a folk
festival in Papeete harbour,
Tahiti (French Polynesia).
or the sea. In the stories, small sea creatures
such as fish, crabs, worms or shellfish give
birth to a child or to the first human couple.
Often the couple consists of a brother and
a sister, whose incest becomes the foundation
of human society. The couple's first child is
usually an aquatic creature or an incomplete
human being.
In the Ryukyu Islands as in Polynesia, these
myths go along with stories about floating
islands or floating lands that the gods have
immobilized through various stratagems to cre¬
ate the world of islands which humans gradu¬
ally settled. The creation myths usually present
this settlement as a transition from nature to
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Ritual offerings are made to
the tutelary god on the island
of Iriomote (Ryukyu Islands,
Japan). Far left, the offerings
being prepared by the
priestess. Left, the "divine
family"the priestess, her
brother and two assistants
during the prayer ceremony.
Below left, a stone tiki on
Huahine in the Society Islands
(French Polynesia). The tiki, a
highly schematic engraved or
sculpted portrait of a man, is a
widespread feature of
Oceanian art.
k culture. They hark back to the way of life of
ancient maritime communities in Southeast Asia
^ and on the edges of the East China Sea, based on
fishing and gathering seaweed and shellfish.
The original link
For the Pacific peoples, genealogy, traced fro m
a founding ancestor, establishes an order of
precedence among all the clans and descendants
or "houses" which make up an island society.
Such genealogy is part of the "framework of
origins" which brings together the status of
communities, social ranks and individual titles
according to criteria legitimized by myths and
ancient stories about settlement of the islands.
The Polynesians "remember" the ancestral
migrations which brought them to the islands
where they now live. Oral history preserves
the names of major ancestors who came from
the other side of the ocean and are revered as
gods. All the details of these voyages (the
names of canoes, the chiefs, priests and the
famous artists, as well as the objects, plants
and animals they brought with them) are
familiar to the descendants of the founders.
In the minds of the indigenous peoples,
the origins of the islands and their settlement
are connected. This link is ritually reaffirmed
at great annual festivals. Veneration for ances¬
tors permeates all social life. Once upon a time
they came from the sky and the sea, and now
they turn up in the islanders' dreams, enabling
the living to communicate with the spiritual
world of gods and impersonal natural forces.
These relationships with the ancestors take
many forms. Some prestigious goods, like cer¬
emonial objects or those used in rites such as
births, marriages and funerals, have a collective
value, because they make the link between the
ancestors and the living the transmission of
spiritual power (mana), the ancestors' bless¬
ing of the living.
Depictions of ancestors, whether full-face,
sitting or standing, are among the most pow¬
erful works of art in Oceania. In wood, stone
or ivory, they are found from eastern Indone¬
sia to Polynesia. The finest and most dramatic
examples are on the eastern edge of the Pacific,
on Easter Island, where the huge moai erected
on dry-stone terraces by the shore recall the
mana of the divine ancestors to which the
inhabitants of the island once gave sacrifice.
The long-eared moai look out across the sea
whence the spirits of the ancestors came, sen¬
tinels of the route they took. H
Opposite page, the shores of
Whitsunday Island,
Queensland (Australia).
© Yann Arthus-Bertrand/Tarth from /Iboire/UNESCO
16
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Solstice islands
BY EDOUARD J. MAUNICK
Departing sun darting into abysses
who know that lands to lands are joined
that beneath the vast ocean vestments
roots advance from islands to peninsulas
from archipelagos to continents from here all
around
that everything and everyone come together
from east to west from pole to pole
in a singular place of transient flesh
what can be seen other than the trace
of a long immemorial journey
with the equator as unique compass
and You and me and Us and the Others
sailing between life and death
thinking we know it all and knowing nothing
betrayed by the witch of History
with her deep draughts of fake solitude
(Two stanzas from "Les îles solstices", a poem
published in Désert-Archipel ¡1983] by
Edouard J. Maunick. Translated from French by Michael
Fineberg)
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
F* i '¿I
i.-*
The triáis of Ulysses
BY JACQUES LACARRIERE
There are more than 1,360 Greek islands.
Many are just bare rocks, home to a few
seagulls. Others are a little bigger but have no
water or other resources. They too are unin¬
habited, except by wild goats and seals. I've
been to many of these small islands and always
come away with the same feeling of having
lived for a few hours like one of my great
childhood heroes, Robinson Crusoe. I feel
like that even if I know lots of other people
have been there before me.
I would sit on an outcrop a few metres
above the sea, amid bushes of thyme and
orégano buzzing with bees, and watch fish¬
ing boats and yachts pass in the distance. They
couldn't see me. Mocking, crabby-sounding
gulls wheeled above me, staring and shrieking
at me, even louder when I went near their nests.
Their agonized cries always sound like the
laments and entreaties of desperate people,
which explains the old Greek belief that these
creatures were actually people changed into
gulls as a result of a curse.
There is nothing imaginary about these lit¬
tle islands, but their unusual, unexpected or
odd appearance and the danger they represent
for sailors must have won them an aura of
uncertainty and mystery from the earliest
times. People also wonder why some more
than others among the hundreds of islands
in the Aegean Sea have given rise to enduring
legends of Greek folklore.
Take Anaphi, a small volcanic islet between
Crete and Santorini whose name, already
known in ancient times, means "island of rev¬
elation". It has practically no vegetation and
just a port and a village and a single spring.
The island reputedly rose up out of the sea
on the orders of Apollo to give refuge to the
Argonauts caught in a night-time tempest.
Legend says the Argonauts saw the island
when a huge flash suddenly lit up the whole
18
THE UNESCO ^)URI ER1DECEV1BER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
sky and revealed it to them. The same kind of
thing is said about many islands in the
Mediterranean and in all seas in volcanic areas
of the world-islands that suddenly rise up
and then disappear as quickly as they came,
but are never forgotten.
To the ancient Greeks, islands were not the
product of natural phenomena but were usu-
ally the result of a god's wish. Hence the idea
of their uncertain destiny, that even the biggest
and apparently most solid of them could sud-
denly slip beneath the waves like Atlantis.
They are shifting universes, unstable and
threatened, at the mercy of the elements and
the whims of the gods. Zeus himself couldn't
make a whole continent disappear at once, but
an island he could.
And so the Greeks' dream island is also a
utopia from which danger and uncertainty have
been banished, islands of tranquillity in a
chaotic world, isolated but also protected, places
where you can live off your own resources. In
short, a paradise where nothing is forbidden,
where there is no serpent and above all no sur-
veillance or interference by the gods.
World history is full of imaginary islands.
They include Alcina (in Ariosto's Orlando
Furioso), Altruria (in William Dean Howells'
novel A Traveller from Altruria), Antangil
Amodern
poet's fresh
interpretation of
the meaning of
the Homeric
hero's epic voyage
"Ulysses and His Companions
Embarking after the Trojan
War", a 14th-century Italian
miniature.
Polyphemus the Cyclops
has his eye put out by
his prisoner, Ulysses.
Detail from a 7th·century·B.C.
Greek amphora.
(inJoachim du Moulin's History ofthe Great
and Admirable Kingdom of Antangil),
Atlantis (described by Plato in the Critias),
Balnibarbi, Laputa and Glubdubdrib (in
Jonathan Swift's Gulliver's Travels), Barataria
(dreamed up by Cervantes), Bensalem (in
Francis Bacon's Nova Atlantis), the Island of
the Blest (described by Lucian of Samosata in
his True History), the Island at the End of the
Earth (Edgar Allan Poe), Edgar Rice Bur-
roughs' Caspak, Circe's island and Calypso's
island in the Odyssey, lkaria (in Etienne
Cabct's Icarie) and the island of the Immor-
tals Qorge Luis Borges).
I will stop the list here, at the letter I,
because it will take too long to get to U and
the distant lands of Utopia and anyway the
letter I is especially interesting when talking
about Greek islands.
An epic homeward journey
Only three of them start with I-los, the sup-
posed birthplace of Homer, Ikaria, where
Icarus is said to have falien to earth on his
flight from Crete, and Ithaka, the birthplace of
Ulysses. Of the three, Ithaka has played a key
part in Greek dreams about their islands.
Ulysses' wife Penelope was also from there, as
was his son Tclemachus. It was where the voy-
age to Tray began and where it ended. In
Homer's epic, it was the ideal island-a place to
settle, but also a place you left and returned to,
a place apart from the world but living from
its links with it.
Ulysses is an excellent example of an inhab-
itant of such a place-someone often away fro m
the island, sometimes exiled, someone who felt
intensely homesick. This was even the first ~
o
a
"o
~-"" 9
TH( UMSCO (9UIUlR. DlClM6LR 1991
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
meaning of nostalgia, a Greek word which
means pain or longing (algos) to return home
(nostos), To be or feel nostalgic is to want to
return to your native land, which time or dis¬
tance separate you from and which becomes, in
the hearts and dreams of faraway sailors, what
was later, in the songs of the troubadours, the
dream and the desire for the distant princess.
So what about Ulysses the nostalgic? At
the end of the Trojan War, after ten years away,
Ulysses wanted only one thing to return to
Ithaka, his island, and get back his throne and
his Penelope. But the pride, the touchiness,
even hatred of the gods got in the way. Posei¬
don, god of the oceans, did not forgive
Ulysses for causing the defeat of the Trojans
through his invention and use of the Trojan
Horse, and did all he could to stop him
returning to Ithaka.
With a fair wind and fine weather, a good
boat would take a month and a half to get
from Troy to Ithaka. It took Ulysses ten years,
during which he lost all his companions one
after another and endured a whole string of
mishaps which are still an epic catalogue of
the monsters and marvels of the sea.
But the point about this eventful home¬
ward voyage is that it was precisely when he
reached Greek waters, where everything should
have been perfectly familiar to him, that he
encountered all the monsters and marvels in an
entirely imaginary context.
Don't look for the Laistrygonian islands,
the land of the Cyclopes, the rocks of the
Sirens, the palace of Circe or Calypso's cave.
They're everywhere and nowhere. Each rock,
creek, gully, cove, gulf or bay, every mountain,
cave, ravine or gorge can conjure them up. Even
the land of the dead where Ulysses ventured
after visiting the palace of Circe can be identi¬
fied as several places in Greece and Italy.
A voyage ofself-revelation
But the striking misfortunes which befell
Ulysses turned what was to have been, or
should have been a routine j ourney into a voy¬
age of personal initiation and self-revelation.
He did not, like other sailors, just have to face
the sea, the wind, the waves and the tempests,
or just human or natural enemies. He came face
to face with the inhuman, the horrific, even the
hellish.
Navigation has never involved such chal¬
lenges and excesses and only Ulysses and his
mythical cousin Jason had to confront these
extraordinary things, running into and grap¬
pling with the creatures of imaginary worlds.
At some points in the Odyssey, you get the
feeling that Ulysses, like Lewis Carroll's Alice
in Wonderland, is passing through the look¬
ing-glass of reality to find himself on the other
side of time and space.
20
Every journey should have a purpose and
every dream a goal. For a long time, perhaps
since the beginning, the trials of Ulysses
whether instigated by Poseidon or due to the
negligence or foolhardiness of Ulysses' com¬
panions have been regarded as obstacles,
delays and arduous detours on his return jour¬
ney. As time wasted fighting monsters, avoid¬
ing the Sirens, consulting the dead and even
falling into the lily-white arms of Calypso.
Everything in fact weather, companions,
monsters and gods seemingly conspired to
stop the islander from returning to his island.
Ulysses' hopes and strength were worn down
by these struggles. After so many years, what
is the value of a king without subjects, a hus¬
band without a wife, an islander without an
island? Without Ithaka, Ulysses was like
someone with a vital organ missing. He lacked
all that he needed homeland, subjects, wife
and palace in order to become again what he
had always been: a ruler.
But heaven and earth conspired against him
and a relentless god brought storms. All the
challenges posed to Ulysses by monsters and
phantoms, the illusions and the shadows that
he had either to outwit or fight head on and
that are seen as so many perhaps inevitable
delays on his journey home were also, when
the story of the voyage was told, so many
songs, expectations and hopes in the hearts of
listeners and later, of readers.
An innerjourney
There is another possible interpretation a
stronger and more solid one, I think of these
tragic and turbulent travels, with the con¬
stantly-delayed return and the endless ordeals.
It was made at the beginning of this century
by a Greek Alexandrian poet, Constantine
Cavafy, in a poem called Ithaka, which lays
bare the hidden meaning of the myth by shin¬
ing an unexpected new light on the trials of
> G"URIERB DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
i#p-«tm
Ulysses the islander. Cavafy said the real mean¬
ing of the Odyssey was that the things sent
to try Ulysses were not obstacles to his home¬
coming but vitally enriching detours so that
he would return to Ithaka matured by his vic¬
tories and the things he had learned.
Ulysses left Troy as a soldier, a sailor and a
war hero and finally reached Ithaka after learn¬
ing the secrets of life, death, strength and wis¬
dom. He left as a man and returned as Man. The
trials not only hardened him but changed his
spirit. He triumphed over brute force (the
Laistrygonians), over monsters (the Cyclopes),
over magic spells and having his men turned
into animals (Circe), over feigned seduction
(the Sirens) and even the irresistible charms
of love with the nymph Calypso. So to his
warrior feats at the gates of Troy, he added
the triple crown of wisdom, truth and love.
Through his trials, he had a complete experi¬
ence of body, heart and mind.
Cavafy said the real purpose of the voyage
was not to arrive but simply for it to take
place. For Ulysses, it was as much a return to
Ithaka as a long, vast and fertile return to him¬
self. Cavafy obliges us to re-read the Odyssey,
the greatest poem of discovery to be written
about the sea, in this completely different
light. Ithaka is the opposite of a promised
land. It is a conquered land, conquered from
the elements and from worldly illusions. A
land conquered through the slow, difficult
but inspiring lessons learned from encoun¬
ters with monsters, women and islands.
You who dream of being Ulysses, remem¬
ber that if you meet a Circe, a Calypso or a
Nausicaa, you will one day have to leave them
if you want to find your Penelope again. And
when the trials are over, the sea will murmur to
the Islander on the shores of the rediscovered
Ithaka the names of those he had to vanquish
or love before he could become a man. Like the
Nereids of the foaming sea and memory, like
the spray of the waves, healers at last.
"The Return of Ulysses", a
15th-century painting (Sienese
school) on a large Italian
wooden coffer or cassóne.
Here is this magic poem:
When you set outfor Ithaka
ask that your way be long,
full ofadventure, full of instruction.
The Laistrygonians and the Cyclops,
angry Poseidon do not fear them:
such as these you will neverfind
as long as your thought is lofty, as long as a rare
emotion touch your spirit and your body.
The Laistrygonians and the Cyclops,
angry Poseidon you will not meet them
unless you carry them in your soul,
unless your soul raise them up before you.
Ask that your way be long.
At many a summer dawn to enter
with what gratitude, what joy
ports seen for the first time;
to stop at Phoenician trading centres,
and to buy good merchandise,
mother ofpearl and coral, amber and ebony,
and sensuous perfumes ofevery kind,
sensuous perfumes as lavishly as you can;
to visit many Egyptian cities,
to gather stores ofknowledge from the learned.
Have Ithaka always in your mind.
Your arrival there is what you are destinedfor.
But do not in the least hurry the journey.
Better that it last for years,
so that when you reach the island you are old,
rich with allyou have gained on the way,
not expecting Ithaka to give you wealth.
Ithaka gave you the splendid journey.
Without her you would not have set out.
She hasn 't anything else to give you.
And ifyou find herpoor, Ithaka has not
deceived you.
So wise have you become, ofsuch experience,
that already you will have understood what
these Ithakas mean.
(From Six Poets ofModern Greece. Chosen, translated
and introduced by Edmund Keelcy and Philip
Sherrard. Published by Thames and Hudson, London,
1960 © Edmund Keeley and Philip Sherrard 1960)
i QuTHE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER I 997
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
What, my brother, is an island?
BY LOKENATH BHATTACHARYA
Where the waters
of the Ganges
meet the ocean The memory of a folk-song heard in
childhood, in a dialect of Bengali, comes
back to me:
What, my brother, is an island once you've
left it?
It's nothing, nothing, nothing.
What, my brother, is an island if it's not
yourself?
In our ancient texts, too, insularity is the
self, covering and surpassing the universe. They
describe Jambudvîpa (island of Jambu) as one
of the seven immense insular land masses, all
symbols of fertility and abundance and each
surrounded by one of the seven seas of salt
water, sugar-cane juice, wine, clarified butter,
curds, milk and fresh water. Jambudvîpa is
India itself, marked at its centre by the golden
mountain Meru, on which stands an enor-
mous jambu (rose-apple) tree.
Another tale almost as old as eternity
describes the meeting of the Ganges with the
ocean. The Sanskrit epic, the Mahâbhârata,
tells how the sage Kapila, lost in meditation in
the nether world, burned to ashes all the 16,000
sons of Sagara, a king of the Solar race.
Another sage, Bhagîratha, through long
asceticism and persistent prayers, made the
river Ganges descend from heaven to sanctify
the victims' ashes, thereby creating the ocean,
one of the Sanskrit words for which is sâgara,
from the name of the king, Sagara.
To celebrate that sacred event, a three-day
Pilgrims sailing to the island
of Sagar in the Ganges delta.
22 THE UNESCO ^URIERB DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
A sandbank In the Ganges near
the Indian city of Kanpur.
bathing festival and fair are held each year on
the Indian island of Sâgar near Calcutta in the
Ganges Delta, a huge, low-lying, densely pop¬
ulated, fertile area belonging partly to India
but mostly to Bangladesh.
The delta's westernmost island, Sâgar is
awesome and mysterious in appearance, and
regularly swept by cyclones. It is here that the
Ganges once met the ocean, and although
The island and the pilgrimage also feature
in Kapâlakundalâ, a love story set against a
background of gruesome rites published in
1866 by the pioneering Bengali novelist
Bankim Chandra Chatterjee. Kapâlakundalâ is
a vivid account of how a young man return¬
ing from the Sâgar Island pilgrimage rescues an
innocent maiden from the clutches of a prac¬
titioner of human sacrifice, a hermit-priest
strictly speaking the ocean is now further whose body is smeared with ashes from a
away, sky and water remain the island's all-
pervasive backdrop.
The festival is attended by many millions
of people devotees, saints, frauds, cheats,
tourists, all combined representing all Hindu
sects and all the states of India. Some of the
sâdhus (holy men) who make the pilgrimage
funeral pile and who holds, as a cup, a skull in
his left hand. The maiden and the young hero
are destined to be his victims, a fate from
which they narrowly escape.
Such esoteric practices were once a part of life
in this region. The very shape of the Ganges
Delta, with the vast tract of forest and swamp
to Sâgar are ascetics who stay naked all the year forming its lower part and known as the Sun-
round and practise the most rigorous physi- derbans, evokes the human female organ (yoni) ,
cal disciplines. They live as hermits, and this and the cults and images associated with it:
pilgrimage is the only occasion when they womb, vulva, origin, source, nest, home,
leave the isolation of their caves in the And thus it is that the cycle becomes corn-
Himalayas, where the descent of the Ganges plete and we return to our starting point:
originally took place. what, my brother, is an island?
THE UNESCO CpUR!ER EJECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
5?'
-mM
m
© Frank Lechenet/Hârnisphëres, Pans
Easter Island's last secret
BY LUIS M1Z0N
The only Polynesian island where traces of
an indigenous script have been discovered
Top, a sanctuary of giant
statues or moai near the shore
of Easter Island. Some moai
wear a kind of headpiece of red
volcanic tuff.
The azure waves which break on the
shores of Easter Island have come all the
way from the far edge of the Pacific Ocean a
thought which makes the place seem even more
isolated than it looks. In the night sky, the
bright stars of the southern hemisphere seem
to be far-off sister isles exchanging winked
messages with the huge stone statues that dot
the island like a tribe of dozing giants.
Easter Island has many faces obscure,
extraordinary and mysterious. There's the
island you see, as described by explorers, and
then the hidden one, of caves and tunnels and
the secret lore its inhabitants share. There's the
island whose history is lost in the mists of
time and the island depicted by scientists,
artists and travellers. All these dimensions
overlap, interlace and whisper to the others,
like so many primal echoes. Works of art and
tourist trinkets apart, Easter Island is a place
the West has invented to fantasize about.
From the air, it looks like a boomerang
hurled from another planet slap into the mid¬
dle of the ocean. A 1 1 8 sq. km triangle of rock
with its high point to the northeast, facing
towards the islets of Polynesia, and its flat
part in the southwest, looking towards the
24
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
far distant coast of Chile. At each corner of
the triangle is a volcano. In the left-hand cor¬
ner is the almost-perfect cone of Rano Kau. In
the right-hand one, Rano Rarako, on whose
slopes are the biggest group of giant stone
statues (moai). In the northern corner is Rano
Aroi, next to Mount Terevaka. Nearly all the
islanders live in the village of Hanga Roa, near
Rano Kau.
The nearest inhabited land is 3,500 km
away.
W,;'V.,
A mysterious script
Easter Island is the only Polynesian island
where ancient writing has been found. Its
meaning is an impenetrable secret.
Even though it was confined to such a small
geographical area and used by the tiny handful
of people who lived there, the writing shows
evidence of a sophisticated civilization. Who
were these people? When did they get there and
where did they come from? Did they bring
their civilization and writing with them? What
feelings, thoughts and values did these incom¬
prehensible markings once convey?
Landing on this remote spot in the middle
of the Pacific vastness can only have been a
mistake or the result of a mishap or piece of
good fortune. The discovery of the island in
1722 by Europeans, in the person of the
Dutch Admiral Jacob Roggeveen, was a bad
Detail of a rongo-rongo or
"talking wood" tablet from
Easter Island.
A rock painting depicting the
Bird-Man, the focus of an
Easter Island cult.
omen. The island's population then was 4,000;
it had been reduced to 1,800 by 1863, 600 by
1 870, a mere 200 five years after that, and only
a few more in 1911. The nineteenth century
was ruthless with non-European cultures.
Easter Island's only resource was its manpower
and a few patches of farmland. But its poverty
hardly protected it against colonial rapacity.
In 1862, a fleet of pirate slavers from Peru
came looking for workers for the guano indus¬
try and made off with more than 1 ,000 of the
islanders, including their king, Kaimokau, his
son Maurata and the elders who could read
the writing on the stone tablets known as
rongo-rongo.
The French consul in Lima eventually man¬
aged to get a hundred-odd of the deported
islanders repatriated, but by then they were
infected with smallpox and on their return they
contaminated the rest of the population. The
secret of the Easter Island script probably died
with the victims of this catastrophic epidemic.
The earliest research on the inscriptions was
done between 1 864 and 1886, when an attempt
was made to categorize the markings or compare
them with other undeciphered scripts from
ancient India, for example. There were three
stages in these attempts at decipherment, each
linked with a figure symbolizing a period of the
island's history and a specific tablet.
The bishop of Tahiti's tablet
Easter Island had about 1,000 inhabitants when
the French merchant ship Tampico, captained by
Jean-Baptiste Dutrou-Bornier and carrying the
missionary Father Gaspar Zumbohm, anchored
THE UNESCO lOURIER B DECEMBER 1997
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
In the 19th century Westerners
demolished the last moa/still
standing upright. Right,
sailors from the French frigate
F/oresurrounded by angry
¡slanders in 1872.
offshore in 1866. Two years later, Dutrou-
Bornier settled on the island, marrying, or rather
kidnapping, Koreto Kuapurunga, who claimed
to be queen of the island, and joining forces
with an Anglo-Tahitian called John Brander.
That same year, 1 868, Fr Zumbohm decided
to return to Valparaiso. Since he would pass
through Tahiti, the Easter Islanders asked him
to take a gift to its bishop, MgrTepanoJaussen,
as a mark of respect. When the offering, a huge
ball of plaited hair 1 00 metres long, was unrav¬
elled in front of the bishop, a wooden tablet
bearing strange markings was found inside.
An elderly islander in the missionary party,
Urupano Hinapote, explained that it was a
rongo-rongo, one of the revered tablets which
recorded the island's most ancient traditions
but which nobody could decipher since the
elders who knew the secrets of the script had
died. The bishop wrote to the missionary who
had stayed behind on the island, Fr Hyp-
polyte Roussel, and asked him to send him as
many of the tablets as he could find. Roussel
sent him six, noting that the markings on
them probably meant nothing, that the
islanders did not know what they meant and
that those who said they did were liars.
But the bishop was convinced the discov¬
ery was important and he eventually found, on
a Tahitian plantation, an interpreter called
Metoro Tau Aure. As soon as he gave him one
of these tablets covered with geometric,
26
anthropomorphic and zoomorphic signs, he
began a religious chant, apparently reading the
signs from bottom to top and left to right,
and turning the tablet upside down at the end
of each line to read the next one. This is a vari¬
ant of a form of writing known as "boustro-
phedon" (literally "turning like oxen in
ploughing") and is similar to certain ancient
Greek inscriptions where alternate lines are
written in opposite directions. Unfortunately,
the bishop's interpreter chanted the same thing
whichever tablet he was given to "read."
Captain Dutrou-Bornier's stick
When Ignacio Gana, captain of a Chilean
corvette, the O'Higgins, landed at Easter
Island in 1870, Dutrou-Bornier gave him a
chieftain's stick covered with markings which
experts consider the finest example of rongo-
rongo in existence.
Gana gave the stick, along with two tablets
with markings on them, to a scholar at the
Santiago Natural History Museum, Rodulfo
Philippi, explaining that the Easter Islanders
had such reverence for the markings that they
were obviously sacred to them.
Philippi at once sent plaster casts of the
tablets to various experts around the world,
notably an English scholar, Pack Harrison,
who was mystified by what he took to be a
kind of cartoon strip. Not one of the experts
THE UNESCO Ç)URIEI DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Giant heads carved out of soft
volcanic tuff may represent
important figures in the
history of Easter Island.
consulted could find the key to the mysteri¬
ous markings.
Thomson 's attempts at
translation
William Thomson was the purser on the Amer¬
ican ship Mohican which stopped at Easter
Island in 1886. Three years later, the U.S.
National Museum published his history of the
island, the most detailed written until then.
Before reaching the island, the Mohican
had stopped in Tahiti, where Thomson pho¬
tographed the tablets in the bishop's posses¬
sion. Once on Easter Island, he searched for an
islander who could translate the inscriptions.
He came across an old man, Ure Vaeike, who
was very reluctant to help him but was even¬
tually persuaded by money. The old man
seemed to regard translating the markings as
something dangerous for his soul.
As soon as he saw the photos of the tablets
he began to chant quickly. But, just as with
Metoro Tau Aure, he did not seem to be read¬
ing the text. He too recited the same things
whichever one he was shown.
In the end, he confessed to Thomson that
nobody on the island could read the mark
ings but that they were definitely important,
like a book written in a foreign language one
did not understand. According to Thomson,
Ure Vaeike's "poetic translation" of the mark¬
ings was as follows:
"My daughter's canoe which has never been
beaten by enemy tribes. My daughter's canoe
has not been destroyed by the plot of Honiti.
It's always victorious in all battles. Nothing
could force my daughter to drink the poison
from the obsidian cup. How can I console
myself when powerful seas separate us? Oh
my daughter! My daughter! The great liquid
path stretches to the horizon. My daughter, oh
my daughter. I shall swim through deep waters
to find you, my daughter, oh my daughter!"
Experts now think some of the Easter
Island markings are perhaps words, though
they may not be full sentences or at all gram¬
matical. They may just be notes to help the
passing-down of oral traditions, especially
genealogical records.
Maybe these mysterious inscriptions have
the same message for us as the island itself.
Perhaps they simply invite us to ponder on the
fragility of all human endeavour. For the
moment they remain poems dedicated to
silence.
) f^URIITHE UNESCO lO IER B DECEMBER 1997
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Cuba's gold
BY EDUARDO MANET
Once upon a time
there was a
beautiful island . . .
Engraving above shows
Havana, capital of Cuba, as it
was in 1851, a time when
Cuba's sugar industry was
expanding and its population
was growing.
I I like to imagine the first encounter
between the Spaniards and the Indians
of Cuba. The Spaniards disembark as con¬
quistadors with drums and trumpets. Hel-
meted and booted, they carry halberds and
muskets, and wield sabres and swords. The
Cuban Indians savour earthly delights. They
lie naked or almost in their hammocks and
smoke the rolled-up tobacco leaves they are
so fond of.
A monk who sailed with Christopher
Columbus remarked on the splendour of
Cuba's plant and animal life and its magnificent
sunsets. In the glowing sky a festival of colours
would modulate from blue to pink, then to
orange, green and purple before melting into
a deeper, denser blue just before nightfall.
But the Spaniards had other priorities than
contemplating the beauty of sunsets. Discov¬
ering, conquering and colonizing the New
World cost the Spanish crown dear. Colum¬
bus, who had left Europe to search for the
fastest and most economical silk and spice
route, was eventually relieved of his command.
An army of battle-hardened soldiers and war¬
like adventurers began hunting throughout
the region for gold, fighting among them¬
selves to the death and terrorizing, corrupting
and enslaving the indigenous population.
The feverish search for El Dorado ("the
land of gold"), a mythical land honeycombed
with gold mines, fuelled legend and inspired
perilous expeditions. Looking for gold, find¬
ing gold and sending galleons-full of it back to
Spain grew into an obsession.
The Indian population of Cuba, the "pearl
of the West Indies", was mobilized to strip
the island of its gold, but the conquistadors
were cruelly disappointed; they did not find
a single nugget. Exhausted by forced labour
and decimated by disease brought by the
Europeans, the island's inhabitants were
almost completely wiped out.
The triumph ofsugar
The colonists soon found consolation else¬
where. The island abounded in other forms
of wealth. The sybaritic society of the Old
World discovered that sugar of rare quality
could be grown in Cuba. What could be more
delicious after a copious meal than a sweet
dessert, a cup of beautiful, anthracite-black
28
THE UNESCO ^)UR1IER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
coffee along with a glass of Cuban rum and
one of the cigars that would become world
famous as Havanas?
This was the Cuban "gold" found by the
first colonists. Not precious metal but tobacco,
rum, coffee and especially sugar. And because the
sugar cane on the island proved to be of such
exceptional quality, there was no point in tak¬
ing the trouble to develop other, less reliable
crops. Growing sugar as a single crop was offi¬
cially encouraged. Fields of sugar cane would
soon stretch as far as the eye could see, and
monoculture would turn into monomania.
With the rise of Cuban patriotism in the
nineteenth century, voices were raised against
the risk that a single crop might eventually
strangle the country's economy. But even after
the Cuban people had achieved a hard-won
independence, the cultivation of sugar cane as
a single crop continued its triumphant march.
A good many of the hectares of sugar-cane
fields that had belonged to the Spanish or the
Creoles were transferred to Cuban business¬
men and American companies. The produc¬
tion rhythm imposed its law on the island's
economy. When the price of sugar rose, the
Cubans profited; when it went down, the cane-
cutters and the needy fell into dire poverty.
All Cuban patriots wanted to do some¬
thing about this. In the schools it was taught
that the country's future lay in crop diversi¬
fication, in an economic blend that would
strike a balance between the different sources
of wealth tobacco, coffee, minerals and fruit.
It is hardly surprising then that after the
revolution of 1 958 the new leaders launched a
massive programme of industrialization and
diversification of the Cuban economy. Farm¬
ing went from strength to strength as Cuba
began a new chapter in its history that was
designed to put an end to the dominance of
sugar cane, a symbol of the past.
Golden sands
But realism soon led the country's leaders to
change their minds. Cuban sugar became a
force on the world market and brought in
foreign currency. At the same time, Cuba
broke off relations with the United States,
and came to rely on sugar as a basis for trade
with the Soviet Union and the Eastern bloc
countries. Tobacco, rum, coffee, fruit, zinc
and nickel mines and fish were part of the
island's resources, but sugar cane, as always,
dominated the economy. It was as much a part
Harvesting sugar cane in
Vinales (Cuba).
A contemporary engraving of a
Cuban sugar plantation in the
late 17th century.
of Cuban reality as the island's beaches and
palm trees, its Havanas, its torrential rains, its
music and its climate.
Today the situation has changed consider¬
ably. Since the seismic shocks that transformed
the world political scene in the 1980s with the
implosion of the Soviet Union and the fall of
the Berlin wall, sugar has become one of the
most unstable products on the international
THE UNESCO lOURIER B DECEMBER I 997
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
market. The well fed and health-conscious West
has banished it from the table. Sugar substi¬
tutes and other sweeteners have taken over. The
following comparison says it all: in 1914 Lidia
Quatania, star of Cabiria, an Italian film that
became an international hit, was the embodi¬
ment of female pulchritude. She and her volup¬
tuous curves made the perfect advertising image
for the sugar Cuba then sold in massive quan¬
tities. In 1997 one need only look at the fash¬
ion shows on Western television and the fili¬
form silhouettes of the top models today's
dream creatures to understand the uncertain-
tics of the sugar market.
But to return to Christopher Columbus.
The first tourist to set foot on Cuban soil,
he exclaimed that the island was "the most
beautiful land in the world". The library in
Seville which houses the archives of the colo¬
nization of the Americas contains thousands
of pages on the early days of colonization that
corroborate this description and constitute a
collection of tourist brochures before their
time.
Cuba has kept its beautiful beaches and
palm trees intact. Why not profit from this
bounty? All that had to be done was to set up
a tourist development strategy, a hotel infra¬
structure and to adapt to today's joint-venture
system. Tourism is the most hybrid of indus¬
tries. Tourists from all over the world Ger¬
mans, Mexicans, Spanish, Swiss, Belgians,
French, Italians and many other nationali¬
ties now relax on Cuba's soft sands.
Let me conclude by describing an imagi¬
nary scene. A Cuban beach. A beautiful glow¬
ing sunset. A hammock is stretched between
two coconut trees. Lounging in it is an Indian
chief smoking tobacco leaves. Two beautiful
Indian women are fanning him with palm
leaves. Diego Velazquez, a Spanish conquista¬
dor, surrounded by cuirassed soldiers armed
to the teeth, impatiently addresses the reclin¬
ing chief. "We want gold!" he demands in a
strong castilian accent.
"Gold?" queries the Chief gently, "but. . ."
His hand sweeps nonchalantly, politely and
elegantly towards the beach, the sea, the sky
and the sun. "Gold, señor? You have it before
you. This is our gold."
A floor show in a Havana
nightclub.
30
> ^>URIITHE UNESCO lO IER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
FACT FILE LAND, SEA AND PEOPLE
UNESCO'S ISLAND AGENDA
In 1990 Unesco created a unit to act as a focal point
within its Secretariat for those of its small Member
Statesmainly islands in the developing worldthat
do not have permanent delegations at Unesco Head¬
quarters. The unit's task is to ensure that these small
states participate fully in Unesco activities and that
Unesco is responsive to their needs.
The states (of which there are 28, plus 3 Asso¬
ciate Members) have been selected according to the fol¬
lowing criteria, which were flexibly applied: a surface
area less than 10,000 km2; a population of less than 1
million, and a per capita gross national product (GNP)
of about $2,000. The countries belong to the following
regions: Africa (Cape Verde, Comoros, Lesotho, Sao
Tome and Principe, Seychelles and Swaziland);
Asia/Pacific (Cook Islands, Fiji, Kiribati, Maldives, Mar¬
shall Islands, Nauru, Niue, Samoa, Solomon Islands,
Tonga, Tuvalu, Vanuatu); Caribbean (Antigua and Bar¬
buda, Bahamas, Belize, Dominica, Grenada, St. Kitts
and Nevis, St. Lucia, St. Vincent and the Grenadines,
Suriname), plus the three Associate Members (Aruba,
the British Vi rgin Islands and the Netherlands Antilles).
They face particularly acute environmental and
development problems because of their ecologically
fragile and vulnerable natural heritage, small size, geo¬
graphical isolation, geological formation, scarcity of
natural resources, and the natural hazards to which
they are exposed (earthquakes, volcanic eruptions,
tsunamis, cyclones, typhoons, floods, landslides and
droughts). These problems are worsened by soil ero¬
sion, groundwater contamination, deforestation in
upland areas, over-use of herbicides and the pollution
of rivers and coastal waters.
Places of cultural and biological blending, these
small countries have nurtured societies that are in
many cases multiracial and multilingual and gifted
with a remarkable capacity for adaptation. They are
an original source of inspiration for the exploration of
new paradigms and partnerships on local, regional
and worldwide levels.
AMINA OSMAN
For further information:
Unit for Relations with Small Member States
Bureau for External Relations
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 18 61
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 55 39
E-mail: a.kramp@unesco.org
In 1996 Unesco launched an Environment and Development in Coastal
Regions and Small Islands (CSI) initiative in order to help Member
States achieve environmentally sound, socially equitable and culturally
appropriate development of their coastal areas. These areas contain
many of the world's richest ecosystems, and their resources make a
sizeable contribution to world food security. About 60% of the world's
population lives within 60 km of the sea. To co-ordinate planning and
action on behalf of the sound development of coastal regions, the CSI
supports an integrated approach drawing on the experience accumu¬
lated by Unesco's natural science and social science sectors. Key
themes include freshwater management, sustaining biological diver¬
sity, migration from inland areas to coastal urban centres, the social
impacts of coastal erosion and sea-level rise.
For further information:
Environment and Development in Coastal Regions and in Small Islands
(CSI)
UNESCO, 1, rue Miollis
75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 58 08
E-mail: csi@unesco.org
Website: http://www.unesco.org/csl
INTERNATIONAL YEAR OF THE REEF
1997 has been declared the International Year of the Reef (IYOR). This
worldwide campaign is designed to encourage the conservation and
sustainable use of coral reefs and associated seagrass and man¬
grove ecosystems.
For further Information:
Website: http://www.coral.org/IYOR
THE INTERNATIONAL SCIENTIFIC COUNCIL
FOR ISLAND DEVELOPMENT (INSULA)
INSULA is an international non-governmental organization created in
1989 at the instigation of Unesco's Man and the Biosphere Pro¬
gramme (MAB) in order to bring together and mobilize the skills of
national, regional and international authorities concerned with the sus¬
tainable development of islands and small island states. It encourages
technical co-operation, especially in culture and in training personnel,
in the exchange of information and experience through its publications
and the organization of national and international conferences and
seminars.
A recently launched campaign entitled "Let's Adopt an Atoll"
has begun to raise funds to help the 1,000-odd inhabitants of the
Micronesian islet of Falalop start up or develop activities to com¬
pensate for the loss in the year 2000 of the financial aid they have been
receiving since 1986 from the United States.
For further information:
INSULA
c/o Unesco, Division of Ecological Sciences
1, rue Miollis
75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 40 56
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 58 04
E-mail: insula@speedy.grolier.fr
Website: http://www.insula.org
THE UNESCO lOURIER B DECEMBER 1997
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
FACT FILE Island World
TWENTY KEY ISSUES
IN ISLAND DEVELOPMENT
1. Sustainable development Islands are less able to absorb environ¬
mental effects than larger areas. Understanding and implementing strate¬
gies of sustainable development are major challenges for island com¬
munities.
2. Diversity. Islands vary considerably in size and population. The problems
they confront derive in varying degrees from their smallness, a limited
resource base and their susceptibility to storm damage and drought.
3. Open, specialized economies: Often dependent for foreign exchange
on the export of one or two specialist crops, small islands may be obliged
to import many consumer goods, including food.
4. Private sector involvement: The private sector has much to contribute
to development policy. Transnational and local companies have a major
responsibility with regard to waste management, toxic materials control
and energy conservation.
5. Distortions in island economies: Social transfer payments can lead
to distortions of the economy whose effects have not always been fully rec¬
ognized.
6. Transport: Transport services between small islands and the outside
world are often difficult to establish and costly.
7. Demographic issues: Small islands are subject to cycles of rapid demo¬
graphic change that go far beyond those related to the balance between
natural birth- and death-rates.
8. Employment Small population size and migration mean that the fine
balance between supply and demand of human resources is easily upset.
9. Decision-making: Integration of scientific concepts into managing
island environments is often given low political priority.
10. Natural resources: Natural resources, on which sustainable devel¬
opment ultimately depends, are among the most vulnerable sectors of an
island's assets.
11. Forestry. Conservation of forest cover is vital for small islands to pro¬
tect their watersheds and guard against soil erosion.
12. Land management Land-use problems on islands largely result from
the conflict between change and development and traditional systems,
resulting In the fragmentation of landholdings.
13. Water. Only the largest and wettest high islands have ample water
resources, and even on some of these there are seasonal shortages.
14. Energy. Many islands depend almost totally on imported fossil fuels,
although use of wood and charcoal continues. Solar energy is already
important on some islands and biogas digesters are in use in a few areas.
15. Conservation: Small islands are often sites of rare but fragile ecosys¬
tems, many of which are in danger of disappearing through lack of con¬
servation policies.
16. Coastal and marine ecosystems: Unregulated industrial and tourist
development projects can cause permanent damage.
17. Fisheries: Island fisheries in the tropics and the Mediterranean are
mainly small-scale and conducted on artisanal lines. Fishing for export is
hampered by poor catching, storing and marketing capacities.
18. Agriculture: Island agricultural systems range from subsistence farm¬
ing to the production of export cash crops. The fall In demand for sugar¬
cane and copra has been a serious blow to certain island economies.
19. Industry. The smallness of islands is a severe constraint on indus¬
trial development. There is, however, some scope for value-adding semi-
manufacture.
20. Tourism and allied services: tourism means heavy investment in Infra¬
structure.
32
THE UNESCO ^)URII1ER «DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Heritage Sites Australia: Fraser Island (1992),
Lord Howe Island (1982)
Canada: Anthony Island (1981)
Chile: Rapa Nui National Park, Easter
Island (1995)
Ecuador: Galapagos Islands (1978)
Indonesia: Komodo National Park
(Komodo Islands) (1991)
Japan: Yakushima (Yaku Island)
(1993)
Mozambique: Island of Mozambique
(1991)
United Kingdom: St. Kilda Island
(1986); Henderson Island (1988);
Gough Island Wildlife Reserve
(1995)
Senegal: Island of Gorée (1978)
Seychelles: Aldabra Atoll (1982)
Viet Nam: Ha Long Bay (1994)
Left, Komodo National Park
(Indonesia). Below, Fraser Island
(Australia), the world's largest sand
island. Below left, Ha Long Bay, In the
Gulf of Tonkin (Viet Nam).
m
TSH M»; .
i «W* - ' ttSaVflVflH E* '
- i ¿jj&r-'" ^^"¿iiJ^^J
1 : »*
1 ' ~ -
ÁI'/ ïipp «¿aï
m J
. *»
JÎÊB JH ^9
13p«"-
*5j j3
i B^H 11 *«r
¡%
'
-
1
" . \
-
-
jfc
-¿SB ^r
^S bVbt'
Sk
. '^k
'
' v
_j
bSThMk l¿ki_ 'h	
BIBLIOGRAPHY
Publications on sale at:
Unesco Publishing, 1 rue Miollis, 75732
Pans Cedex 15, France.
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 43 00
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 57 41
Website:
http://www.unesco.org/publishing
* Educational strategies for small
island states
(Fundamentals of educational planning
44), by D. Atchoarena, 1993
Small Countries, a wealth of
cultures, Unesco Courier, October 1986
Islands ' culture and development
(Future-oriented studies), 1991
Education in small states
(Prospects, quarterly review of
education no. 80), 1991
Asia Pacific Arts Directory, T. Dolling,
3 vols., 1996
Scientific diving: a general code of
practice, N. Flemming (ed.), 2nd ed.,
1996
Hydrology and water resources of
small islands: a practical guide (Studies
and reports in hydrology 49), A. Falkland
(ed.), 1991
* Sustainable development and
environmental management of small
islands (Man and the Biosphere Series
5), W. Beller, P. d'Ayala and P. Hein
(eds.), 1990
DISCOGRAPHY
Compact discs in the Unesco Collection
of Traditional Music of the World on sale
at the Unesco Bookshop,
7, Place de Fontenoy,
75352 Paris 07 SP, France,
Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68 22 22
Bali. Folk music
Bali. Court music and Banjar music
Corsica. Religious music of oral
tradition
Cuba. Folk music
Greece. Vocal monodies
Greece. Traditional music
Hong Kong. Instrumental music
Indonesia. Music from West Java
Ireland. Traditional music of today
Japan. Ainu songs
Java. Vocal art
Java. Sundanese folk music
Sicily. Music for Holy Week
Solomon Islands. Fataleka and Baegu
music from Malaita
THE UNESCO lOURIER B DECEMBER 1997
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY ederico Mayor
UNESCO AT WORK:
peace, development
and democracy
Through its work in education, science, culture and
communication, UNESCO seeks to free the individual. It
combats poverty, exclusion and violence, promotes
tolerance and multicultural dialogue and helps to pro¬
tect human diversity.
Convinced that it is only through freeing the indi¬
vidual that the political participation essential for
democratic coexistence can develop, UNESCO defends
human rights and the "personal sovereignty" of each
and every one. Democratic values give strength and
cohesion to the unlimited diversity of the human species
and promote its unity. UNESCO does not represent a
particular civilization but all countries without excep¬
tion: it represents humanity as a whole.
Its mission is to build peace in people's minds by con¬
tributing to human development within a framework of
justice and freedom, for the right to peace is a premise
on which all other human rights are based. With this
in mind, UNESCO encourages all citizens to learn about
and respect the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights. These rights are neither given nor received;
they are put into practice on a day-to-day basis. They
are indivisible. Exercise of and respect for human
rights underpin the three great principles that inspired
the founders of the United Nations system: peace, jus¬
tice and freedom. While states and other entities or
institutions cannot grant these rights they must ensure
that they are respected.
UNESCO maintains contact with all peoples and all
sections of society in order to encourage the general
mobilization that is needed to bring about the transition
from the law of the strong to the law of reason, from a
culture of war based on coercion and power to a cul¬
ture of peace based on dialogue and persuasion.
34
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Discouraging war and strengthening peace are two
sides of the same coin. Democracies do not have to be vul-
nerable. Citizens must feel that they are protected by the
rule oflaw and take pride in its enforcemeut. For these
reasons we need a new concept of security and of the role
of the armed forces. Astronomical sums are today ear-
marked by states to protect their territory from potential
international enemies. Civil society is left completely
exposed, and watches with dismay the establishment of
regimes which fill daily life with terror and suffering,
while intensive and profitable trading in weapons of
mass destruction continues all over the world.
Ashared reponsibility
The seeds of non-violence, tolerance and solidarity must
be sown very early. This is the only way in which peace
can become cultural, i.e. inherent in the organization of
life in society. We must plant the seeds today if they are
to bear fruit tomorrow. This germination will take place
in the schools. This is why education is the key to the dif-
ferent future that we desire for our children.
Education frees individuals and empowers them to
shape their future, to accept or reject according to
their own judgement, to act always "by their own
lights". The prime beneficiaries of this education are,
of course, the excluded, but lifelong education is of
concern to all, rich and poor, scholars and the wider
public, heads of government and ordinary citizens.
For living together in a spirit of good understanding is
a collective and shared responsibility.
This is UNESCO's field of action. It promotes the
transfer of knowledge and the access of all to the com-
munications media, without which reforming ideas do
not circulate. Freedom of expression is a prerequisite
of justice. And laws are only just if all citizens have the
right to express their views.
This is why UNESCO is constantly reminding gov-
ernments that education is a fundamental right for all
and as such must be accorded political and budgetary
priority by states. A country's development depends on
improving the level of education of its people. There
is a direct link between reorganizing budgetary prior-
ities in this way and the achievement of sustainable
socio-economic development. Subsidies and loans from
outside sources can make a valuable contribution for
a time, but external aid can never replace a nation's
political commitment to the education of all its citizens
as a matter of top priority.
The conscience of humanity
Education is a priority mission for UNESCO, but not its
only task. These tasks are many, and all are linked to
the promotion of the ideal of peace set forth in the Pre-
amble to its Constitution.
UNESCO works to safeguard the heritage-natural,
cultural (tangible and intangible), genetic and ethi-
cal-and fosters creativity in an endeavour to build the
cultural hcritage of the future. Through far-reaching
programmes on the environment (Man and the Bios-
phere, oceanography, hydrology and geology) and in
the social sciences (MOST), UNESCO encourages sci-
entific rigour in research and fosters the establishment
of exchange networks for reflection and training capa-
ble of providing rapid and sound solutions to many of
the questions facing humanity. The World Science
Conference to be held in 1999 will present a retro-
spective of the major scientific achievements of the
century.
The Universal Declaration on the Human Genome,
based on the excellent work carried out over the past
five years hy the International Bioethics Committee, is
the first ethical and legal framework of worldwide
scope on a subject that is profoundly scientific and
human, as well as being a major standard-setting con-
tribution made to humanity by UNESCO.
It must never be forgotten, however, that at the end
of the day it is up to nations to put all these ideals into
practice by ineorporating guidelines into their laws and
striving to reach the goals that they, with others, have
set at international conferences. In accordance with its
mandate UNESCO is required to denounce any situations
or actions that are contrary to the standards and ethical
values so clearly laid down in its Constitution. For
UNESCO is also a conscience of humanity. •
THE. UNE.SCO GUJUE.R. DECEMBER 19Q7
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
H E R I T A 6 E
The treasure o ERRO RICO
by Pascale Absi
Indigenous miners who work the ore-rich mountain of Potosí
(Bolivia) believe it to be the incarnation of Pachamama, an Andean
god. The city has featured on the World Heritage List since 1987.
Paraguay
Argentina
The Royal Mint (Casa Real de Moneda), below, was completely
rebuilt between 1759 and 1773 by Salvador Villa and Luis Cabello.
It is one of the finest examples of Potosi's colonial architecture.
The history of the Bolivian
city of Potosí began in
1545 when the Spanish began
mining silver deposits in a moun¬
tain which became known as the
Cerro Rico. Within a few years a
rich settlement studded with opu¬
lent baroque churches, theatres
and the mansions of the colonial
bourgeoisie had grown up at the
foot of this 4,000-metre-high
peak, and soon Potosí had a bigger
population than that of London,
Paris or Amsterdam. Fabulous
fiestas were organized by the
wealthy mine-owners. It is said
that a silver bridge stretching
from Potosí to Madrid could have
been built with the ore extracted
from the mountain by the Indians
during the colonial period.
But first and foremost Potosí
was a mining camp whose fortunes
were closely linked to its veins of
ore and to the vicissitudes of inter¬
national markets. After a period
of great wealth, decline set in, and
in the mid-1980s plummeting
prices brought an end to the tin
cycle that had begun at the turn
of the century. The state-run
mines closed, and Potosí was
plunged deep in crisis.
Today it is the capital of the
poorest department in the Bolivian
Andes. Of its 120,000 or so inhab¬
itants, more than 7,000 miners
men, women and children orga¬
nized in co-operatives still work
night and day deep within the
mountain. Mining methods have
barely changed since colonial
times, and because of the com¬
bined effect of accidents, silico¬
sis, poor diet and lack of medical
care, the average life expectancy of
workers is no more than fifty.
GIVETHAT YOU MAY RECEIVE
One August day in 1996 more than
a hundred women from Potosi's
mining co-operatives decided to
occupy the summit of Cerro Rico
to protest against their working
conditions and the policy of priva¬
tizing ore deposits for the benefit
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The mining city of
Potosí. In
background, the
baroque cathedral
designed by Manuel
de Sanahuja. It was
not completed until
1838.
of multinational companies. Their
action also had a cultural aim: to
protect the Cerro Rico from the
intrusion of the modern technolo¬
gies used by the big companies
that would threaten its geologi¬
cal stability. One side of the sum¬
mit had already caved in, partly
destroying the mountain's char¬
acteristic conical shape.
The city's entire population
rallied behind the mining women,
whose struggle is far more than a
mere defence of Potosí as a his¬
toric symbol. For everyone, miners
and farmers alike, the Cerro Rico
is the incarnation of Pachamama,
an Andean divinity associated with
the earth's fertility.
The mine workers, who belong
to the region's indigenous,
Queehua-speaking communities,
still have plots of land in the places
from which they came. They often
return to the countryside to do
farm work, attend festivals, or
assume some kind of political
office. Townsfolk and miners they
may be, but they are not cut off
from the rural world. The mining
culture has been built around a
conception of the world rooted in
rural life: you must give in order
to receive; people are not the rulers
of the world, but must negotiate
continually with the forces of
nature in order to gain access to
its wealth. The Potosí miners
believe that the Spirit of the moun¬
tain is the real owner of the mineral
deposits that people are allowed to
mine (but only in exchange for
offerings).
THE GODS OFTHE MOUNTAIN
The present equilibrium between
the workers and their mountain is
the culmination of a long process
of taming the vital forces of the
Cerro, which was intact in 1545
when the Spanish discovered the
existence of fabulous deposits of
silver within it. The Cerro Rico is a
sacred mountain on whose summit
stands a ¡dace ofworship. The min¬
ers say that it has exacted a toll of
human lives in exchange for being
exploited. The earliest sacrifice
was made by the Indians who came
to Potosí to do compulsory service
for the Spanish crown and died in
their thousands in the bowels of
the mountain. It is their blood, so it
is said, that gives the mountain its
singular red colour. Nowadays,
sated at long last, the Cerro Rico
lets people five in exchange for more
modest offerings.
The Europeans appropriated
the souls of the indigenous popu¬
lation as well as the riches of
South America. The Spanish soon
replaced the divinity of the moun¬
tain by the Madonna de la Cande¬
laria (Our Lady of Candlemas).
They built chapels along the
mountain roads, and placed a
cross on the summit. Pagan ele¬
ments that could not be assimi¬
lated by the Catholic missionaries
(ancestor worship, for example)
were considered to be devil-wor¬
ship and condemned.
Today the miners divide their
loyalties between two divinities,
Pachamama and Tío. Pachamama
is associated with the mountain and
is personified at the entrance to
each mine by an effigy of the Vir¬
gin Mary, whose protection the min¬
ers solicit. She is also the wife of
Tío, the god of mine shafts and the
lord ofmining and mineral deposits. I
THE UNESCO í3,URIER1DECEMBER 19Q7 ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Represented by mud stat¬
uettes placed here and there
along the mine galleries, Tío has
inherited horns, hooves, forked
tail and the nickname diablo from
the European image of the devil.
Yet the moral idea of the devil
and the Manichean division into
good and evil propounded by the
Catholic Church have never been
totally integrated into Andean con¬
cepts of the vital forces of Nature.
The devil of the mine punishes
workers who fail to make offer¬
ings to him not because he is evil
but because he is hungry. He is
held responsible for most of the
mortal accidents due to roof-falls
or suffocation on these occasions
he is said to have eaten his vic¬
tims. Propitiatory rites therefore
consist largely of feeding the mine
divinities in order to solicit their
wealth and win protection from
their gargantuan appetites. Every
Friday miners gather around one
of Tío 's statuettes, pour a spot of
alcohol at his feet, lay a few coca
leaves on his outstretched hands
and place a lighted cigarette
between his lips. During the dry
season, the miners improve his
rations by sacrificing llamas.
Tío is a strangely anthropo¬
morphic figure, sitting amongst
the men as if he were one of their
number and being included in
A miner examines a
shard of ore he has
just hacked from the
shaft wall.
their conversations. He is a work¬
mate, almost a friend. He can even
be heard of an evening in the
silence of the abandoned mine,
emptying a wheelbarrow or hack¬
ing away at the rock. Some miners
tell how, when they arrive at their
posts in the morning, they find
their work already partly done.
Sometimes dressed as a miner,
with helmet, lamp and cloven
hooves, jewels, blond hair and out-
sized sex, Tío has been known to
appear to a miner working alone in
the galleries and guide him to a
particularly rich seam or suggest
they make some kind of pact. In
return for greater wealth, he will
ask the miner for exceptional
offerings, such as his soul or a
human sacrifice.
A WORKMATE AND A GOD
The capture of a miner's soul
through a pact with Tío is only the
extreme manifestation of the influ¬
ence of diabolical forces on human
beings. According to Potosí min¬
ers , going down the mine turns you
into something of a devil yourself.
When they first start work, the
men of the Cerro fall victim to an
initiatory disease corresponding to
the temporary seizure of their soul
by Tío. This event, regarded as a
baptism, marks their entrance into
the circle of devils, an essential
qualification for work underground
and a guarantee of the quality of
their output.
There is a tenuous dividing line
between the devil who becomes a
miner and the miner who becomes
a devil. In the mine their roles are
interchangeable; the man becomes
Pachamama's lover. Mining is
described as a fertile sexual rela¬
tionship: the miners talk about lift¬
ing the skirts and using their crow¬
bar to deflower the woman-
mountain whom they fertilize with
their offerings and deliver each
day of her minerals.
The same energy circulates
between the miners and the spirits
H
of the mountain. They say in the
Cerro that men give life to the mine
with their breath, just as the mine
gives life to men. Just as mines cave
in when they are no longer
exploited, miners fall ill and die
when they no longer go to work.
One August morning in 1996
the women members of the co¬
operatives came to defend this
fragile balance which is threat¬
ened by large-scale mining of the
Cerro Rico. In the evening of the
fourth day of their occupation, as
they were preparing to pour a liba¬
tion to Pachamama from a bottle
of spirits they had brought with
them to fight the bitter cold, one
of them told me, "You know, all
these machines will spell the end of
the Cerro. It might even collapse,
and that would make Pachamama
very angry. ..." H
38
THE UNESCO Ç)URII1ER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The Cerro Rico.
In Potosí it is said
that the mountain
owes its reddish
colour to the blood of
the thousands of
miners who have
perished working
deep within it.
THE SPANISH KING'S SILVER
The great days of Potosí were in the early 17th century when it
was the biggest mining and industrial complex in South Amer¬
ica. Twenty-two successive lagunas or reservoirs equipped with
locks fed water to an artificial watercourse {La Rivera) which
powered 140 ingenios or mills where the silver ore was ground,
mixed with mercury and melted into bars in fireclay kilns known
as huayras or guayras before being stamped with the official
mark of the Spanish Royal Mint. This was known as the patio
mining technique.
Potosí had a population of 160,000 at that time. Each year
some 13,000 Indians, bound under the mita system of forced
labour, came to the city with their families, about 60,000 peo¬
ple in all. Drawn from all over the high Andean plateau, these
peoples of diverse ethnic origins played a big hand in shaping
the city as it is today. The indigenous people's district is still
divided into 17 parishes, an echo of the 17 Andean provinces sub¬
jected to the mita.
Even today, five of the 22 reservoirs still provide about 80,000
people with water. The entire chain of production has been pre¬
served intactmines to dams, aqueducts, refineries and kilns.
Many other traces of Potosi's past glory and prosperity have
also survived. There are some 22 parish or monastic churches,
some dating from the 16th century, numerous mansions in the
Spanish town centre. Above all, there is the Royal Mint, which was
rebuilt between 1759 and 1773. About 2,000 colonial buildings
have been identified, the oldest being the Casa Vicaria (1615). The
blend of baroque and local (Mestizo) architectural styles that
began to appear in the second half of the 17th century can be seen
in the churches of La Compañía (1700-1707), Santa Teresa
(1685), San Lorenzo (1728-1744) and San Martin.
In 1630 a fracture In an embankment wall caused a lot of
damage In the indigenous district. Rebuilding work went on
into the 18th century. Mining activity continued until Bolivian
independence in 1825, after which its decline, which had already
begunproduction methods had remained unchanged for a
century and a halfbecame steeper.
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBE RI9Ï7 *J
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
Climate change:
the great debate
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
| Some people see the Third
Conference of the States Par¬
ties to the Framework Convention
on Climate Change, which is being
held in Kyoto (Japan) this month, as
the last chance to fight global warm¬
ing by taking urgent mandatory
steps. Others see it as a chance to
argue with the pessimistic predic¬
tions of most scientists.
One might ask why, just for
safety's sake, every country doesn't
immediately agree to curb green¬
house gas emissions. The answer is
that the necessary steps would be
unpopular, would lose votes and cost
a great deal. Governments handle
energy and transport matters with
kid gloves.
IS IT GETTING WARMER OR NOT?
In the past, people cither adjusted
to the climate or migrated. These
days, humanity seems capable of
influencing climate itself. Accord¬
ing to the World Meteorological
Organization (WMO) we have
altered, and are continuing to alter,
the balance of gases in the atmos¬
phere. This is especially true of the
greenhouse gases carbon dioxide
(C02), methane (CH4) and nitrous
oxide (N20) as well as water
vapour, which is the largest con¬
tributor to the natural greenhouse
effect, but whose presence in the
atmosphere is not directly affected
by human activity.
These gases make up only 0.1%
of the earth's atmosphere, which is
78% nitrogen and 21% oxygen.
Without the greenhouse effect
caused by the presence of an enve¬
lope of these gases, the earth would
be 30°C colder than it is. Since the
beginning of the industrial era, we
have produced enormous quantities
of C02 by burning fossil fuels, and
by cutting down forests we have
reduced the planet's natural capac¬
ity to absorb it. Stock breeding and
agriculture produce mostly methane
and nitrous oxide. If gas emissions
continue to grow at the present rate,
the amount of C02 in the atmos¬
phere will have doubled between
1750 and the beginning of the 21st
century, and will perhaps even triple
between now and the year 2100.
Painter Erik
Victor's fanciful
depiction of
Cologne
(Germany) and its
cathedral In the
year 2050, after
the polar icecaps
have melted
because of global
warming.
A computer-
generated world
map (1993)
showing rise In
surface air
temperatures If
carbon dioxide
emissions double.
The model predicts
dramatic warming
of northern
hemisphere
winters.
Temperature
increases are
colour-coded from
pale yellow (0-2°
C) to red (8-12°C).
Admittedly the situation is wor¬
rying, but some aspects of it are still
a matter of debate. Respected scien¬
tists at the University of Virginia and
the Massachusetts Institute of Tech¬
nology (MIT) argue that if the earth
has got warmer over the past 20 years,
the atmosphere has cooled because of
aerosols (ash from volcanic eruptions
or combustion, for example), and that
logically, the more industrialized
northern hemisphere should be warm¬
ing more than the southern, whereas
the opposite is happening. They also
say that modelling of the earth's cli¬
mate does not take into account the
clouds which can cool the lower
reaches of the atmosphere.
But the facts are stubborn. The
planet has become between 0.3°C
and 0.6°C warmer in the past cen¬
tury, the hottest for 600 years. In
the same period, the sea level has
risen by between 10 and 25 cen¬
timetres.
Facing the doubters is a formi¬
dable adversary: the Intergovern¬
mental Panel on Climat Change,
which was set up in 1988 jointly by
WMO and the United Nations Envi¬
ronment Programme (UNEP) and
involves 2,000 scientists around the
world. The Group was mandated to
assess the state of existing knowl¬
edge about climate change; the envi¬
ronmental and socio-economic
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
impacts of such change ; and possible
response strategies. Its First Assess¬
ment report, published in 1990, pro¬
vided the scientific and technical
basis for the United Nations Frame¬
work Convention on Climate Change,
whose ratification procedure was
opened at the Earth Summit held
in Rio de Janeiro in 1992. By May
1997, 166 countries had ratified the
Convention.
GOOD AND BAD PERFORMERS
Some countries have fulfilled their
commitments and taken steps to
limit C02 emissions. Early in 1997
the World Wide Fund For Nature
(WWF) published a list of good and
bad performers. Germany, for exam¬
ple, is set to meet its commitments to
cut its C02 emissions (800 million
tonnes a year) by the year 2000. The
Germans are expected to push at
Kyoto for further emission reduc¬
tions by 2005.
New Zealand, however, which
produces less than 300 million tonnes
annually, has no plans to reduce its
emissions and does not accept the
need to act urgently. Russia, with
more than 800 million tonnes (10.2%
of world C02 emissions in 1996), has
the same attitude. Next comes China
(13.5%), then Europe (19.6%), and
finally the leading polluter, the
United States (25%). Japan, the
A 3-dimensional
model of
temperature and
soil-moisture
differences
assuming twice
the 1993 levels of
atmospheric
carbon dioxide.
Blue band at top
indicates
stratospheric
levels where the
air has cooled by
more than 2°C,
while the lower red
band indicates a
rise of more than
5°C in low-level air.
In green: increased
soil-moisture
levels; in yellow,
decreased soil-
moisture levels.
world's fifth major polluter (5.6%),
does not intend to reduce emissions
by more than 5%. But it is in the
United States that the situation
seemed to be most inflexible when
the U.S. Senate unanimously passed
a resolution on 25 July stating it
would not ratify any climate agree¬
ment that did not require the par¬
ticipation of the developing world.
Since then things have changed
and President Bill Clinton announced
at a press conference on 22 October
1997 that he will propose at Kyoto to
reduce U. S . greenhouse gas emissions
to the 1990 level between 2008 and
2012, and to reduce them even fur¬
ther in the following five years. A $5-
billion budget will be earmarked for
the development of clean technolo¬
gies and industrialists will have nine
months to prepare pollution reduc¬
tion plans. President Clinton also reaf¬
firmed the need for participation by
developing countries. He noted that
a tonne of carbon emitted in
Argentina has the same effect as a
tonne of carbon emitted in the United
States. In principle developing coun¬
tries would only have to accept tar¬
gets beyond 2010.
The U.S. Information Agency's
Jim Fuller has said that his country
will present a draft treaty on world
climate change to the Kyoto con¬
ference. "The commitment to reach
legally binding targets and timeta¬
bles has sparked controversy in the
United States," he writes. " envi¬
ronmentalists and scientists who sup¬
port curbs on greenhouse gases say
they are crucial to preventing future
disaster. But some scientists and
industry representatives dispute the
accuracy of future warming predic¬
tions and oppose limits on energy
consumption they say will cause
irreparable harm to the U.S. econ¬
omy." He went on to say that "Most
studies suggest that reducing green¬
house gas emissions 20% below
1990 levels by the year 2010 . . .
would reduce the gross domestic
product of the United States by 1%
to 2% and cost nearly $100,000 mil¬
lion per year."
WE'RE ALL IN THE SAME BOAT
But why, it may be asked, should
poor countries limit their emissions
when the rich countries of the North
are mainly responsible for global
warming?
Robert Wolcott, of the U.S. Envi¬
ronmental Protection Agency (EPA),
believes it is not a question of past
but future responsibility. "Emissions
of developing countries are and will
be increasing at a far more rapid rate
as they move through what you could
think of almost as a corridor of tech¬
nologies," he notes. "They will be
adopting technologies that are more
or less currently in place or have
recently been in place in the devel¬
oped world." This is why the EPA
advocates "a climate technology
transfer program in which we will join
with our developed-world partners
to supply the most advanced and
appropriate technology to emergent
economies to facilitate their sus¬
tained growth economically, but in
the least greenhouse-gas intensive
fashion."
The EPA is also considering a
greenhouse gas emissions trading sys¬
tem. This would involve fixing an
) (ouTHE UNESCO lOURIER B DECEMBER 1997
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
The effects on
Ponderosa Pine
seedlings of an
atmosphere
containing twice
as much carbon
dioxide than
today's level are
being tested in
this special,
bubble-like
laboratory.
ï annual worldwide maximum emis¬
sion level. Then a maximum level
would be worked out for each coun¬
try, taking into account various fac¬
tors, and ensuring that all the indi¬
vidual country levels, when added
up, did not exceed the fixed world¬
wide level. Each country would then
grant greenhouse gas emission
allowances to companies within the
limit assigned to it. The trading
mechanism would work in the fol¬
lowing way: a country or a company
emitting less greenhouse gases than
its authorized total would be enti¬
tled to sell to another country or
SOURCES
Climate Change Information Kit, co-produced by the UN, UNEP,
UNDP, WMO, UNITAR and the Convention on Climate Change.
(Fax: [(41) 22] 733 28 29, e-mail: <gorre-daleE@gateway.wmo.ch>,
lnternet:<http ://www.wmo.ch>)
Understanding Climate Change: A Beginner's Guide to the UN
Framework Convention, United Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP).
(Fax: [(41) 22] 797 34 64, e-mail: <iuc@unep.ch>, Internet:
<http ://www.unep.ch>
IPCC Second Assessment: Climate Change 1995,
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change.
An Introduction to Simple Climate Models used in the IPCC
Second Assessment Report (Technical Paper II), WMO, UNEP.
Stabilization ofAtmospheric Greenhouse Gases: Physical,
Biological and Socio-Economic Implications (Technical Paper III),
WMO, UNEP.
Explaining Climate Change, World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF).
(Fax: [(41) 22] 364 42 38; e-mail: <climate.campaign@wwfus.org>)
company a "pollution allowance"
corresponding to the gap between
its real and authorized emission rate.
Wolcott recognizes though that
these ideas are causing concern in
some countries which view them "as
a form of carbon colonialism . . . and
feel that this puts them under the
influence of, and even control of,
investors from the developed world."
ALL OR NOTHING
A preparatory meeting for the Kyoto
conference was held in Bonn (Ger¬
many), the headquarters of the UN
Convention on Climatic Change, in
August 1997. The Convention's
Executive Secretary, Michael Zam-
mit Cutajar, has admitted the con¬
ference was a failure. "We are all
worried about the slow progress at
the Bonn meeting," he said. "There's
only a short time now to build up
the necessary political will to pro¬
duce a solid agreement at Kyoto."
Such lack of political will , which
was also evident at the June 1997
Earth Summit in New York, is dis¬
turbing and bodes ill for the Kyoto
conference. The oil and coal indus¬
tries, as well as the most unenlight¬
ened industrialists, fear for their
profits, since they might well be
heavily taxed.
On the other hand, Kyoto will be
a special opportunity to promote
clean energy sources which, when
developed, could at last be gener¬
ally affordable.
ENERGY RETURNS
TO MOZAMBIQUE
After 12 years of silence, the Cabora
Bassa hydroelectric dam in north¬
western Mozambique is humming
again. Built on the Zambezi River ¡n
the early 1970s, Africa's biggest
power plant came under constant
attack during a decade of civil war.
Lines were cut, pylons blown up and
service pathways mined. The return
of peace meant that repairs could
begin in 1995. From the end of 1997,
it should be producing 2,000
megawatts a year for neighbouring
South Africa. About 200 MW of that
will be fed back through the South
African grid to supply Mozambique's
capital, Maputo, which is close to the
South African border. Mozambique will
no longer have to buy power from its
big neighbour but just pay a transit fee,
which will save about $10 million a
year.
WORLD FRESHWATER
RESOURCES
The United Nations system and the
World Bank have published ajoint Com¬
prehensive Assessment of the Fresh¬
water Resources of the World. The 33-
page brochure, including maps and
explanatory diagrams, provides a sit¬
uation report combined with specific
suggestions and a strategy for fair dis¬
tribution and efficient use of water.
The document is available from
Unesco's International Hydrological
Programme.
IHP, Division of Water Sciences, 1 Rue
Miollis, 75732 Pans Cedex 15, France. Fax:
(33)(0)145685811
e-mail: ihp@unesco.org
Website:
http:/www.pangea.org/orgs/unesco
MINERAL EXPLORERS TURN
TO AFRICA
Until recently the trend for interna¬
tional mining companies has been to
explore in Latin America, but with back¬
ing from the Multilateral Investment
Guarantee Agency (MIGA), a World
Bank affiliate, investors are now turn¬
ing to Africa, with its abundance of
gold, precious stones and almost every
imaginable mineral. The MIGA encour¬
ages foreign investment in developing
countries by providing them with guar¬
antees against political and non-com-
42 ) QuiHIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
w o L d
mercial risks. The mineral deposits
are in remote areas, and their extrac¬
tion creates jobs and helps to allevi¬
ate poverty. African ministers attend¬
ing a MIGA-sponsored symposium
stressed the need to involve local com¬
munities and safeguard the environ¬
ment. This is going to be an uphill job
since mining usually causes consider¬
able pollution.
THE ELEPHANTS
O F ALGIERS
At Algiers' Ben Aknoun Zoo, two baby
elephants were born four months apart
in the winter of 1996-97, one of an
Asian, the other of an African mother.
This happy event was particularly
remarkable because African elephants
are not known to breed in captivity. The
304-hectare park has 814 animals and
the 12 elephants there drink 300 litres
of water and eat 300 kg of fodder per
day. The zoo is short of money, how¬
ever, and its future is in doubt.
MEDICINAL PLANTS COULD
FACE EXTINCTION
A recent World Bank report warns
about a probable over-harvesting of
medicinal plants in the developing
world, where some 4 billion people
depend heavily on natural medicines
for their daily health. Global trade in
medicinal plants now exceeds $1 tril¬
lion. They are harvested without any
kind of regulation and do not benefit
from research support, unlike other
cash crops. "Unless you watch how
you cultivate and harvest your medic¬
inal plants," says John Lambert, one of
the report's authors, "you're not going
to have them much longer. "
KENYA
BECOMES WORLD'S LEADING
TEA EXPORTER
World tea production reached a record
2,691,000 tonnes in 1996. Export
earnings from tea increased food secu¬
rity in producing countries and for
farming families. According to the UN
Food and Agriculture Organization
(FAO), in 1994-95 tea represented 55%
of agricultural export earnings in Sri
Lanka and 33% in Kenya. Kenya
became the world's leading tea
exporter in 1996, with 244,200
tonnes, with Sri Lanka a close second
with 244,000 tonnes. The leading
importer was the United Kingdom
(148,500 tonnes).
CONTAMINATED
CHILDREN
For 30 years, small-scale smelters
around the Bolivian town of El Alto have
spewed out toxic waste and fumes con¬
taining lead, arsenic, zinc and
chromium. Soil and air analysis has
shown abnormally high concentrations
of lead and arsenic, which are extremely
harmful to the nervous system. A recent
study showed younger children were
most vulnerable, with more lead
detected in their blood and more arsenic
in their urine. Health officials hope the
study will lead to a regional programme
to monitor the environment around the
smelters.
A CAR
OR A HOUSE?
YOU CHOOSE
The Scottish city of Edinburgh has
come up with an imaginative scheme
to make life pleasanter. An old railway
goods yard near the city centre is to
be replaced by about 100 homes sur¬
rounded by a landscaped garden. But
if you want one of the homes, you're
not allowed to be a car-owner. Free
heating will come from steam gener¬
ated by nearby factories, and energy
for lighting will be drawn from rooftop
solar panels. Waste water will be recy¬
cled for use in cleaning and bathrooms
will use rainwater. As for those cars,
you can hire one from a council-run
"pool."
KENYA'S ENERGY- SAVING
COOKERS
Three billion people in the world cook
their food on simple wood fires in metal
containers. The loss of energy is enor¬
mous. A solution has been found in
Kenya in the form of the j/to, a cheap
oven shaped like an hour-glass. The
charcoal goes in the bottom part, and
the top part, which is for the food, has
a ceramic lining. The first rough mod¬
els have been redesigned and craft-
workers are now turning out some
20,000 jikos a month. Over a million
are in use throughout the country. I
IVORY
TRADE RESUMES
After a seven-year worldwide ban on
ivory trading, Botswana, Namibia and
Zimbabwe were authorized to resume
trading (with a single country, Japan),
at this summer's meeting of States
Parties to the International Conven¬
tion on Trade in Threatened Fauna and
Flora Species, held in Harare (Zim¬
babwe). The reason for the decision is
to use up the 3 countries' ivory stocks,
estimated at more than 50 tonnes,
according to the World Wide Fund for
Nature (WWF). With this in view, ele¬
phants will be transferred from Appen¬
dix I to Appendix II of the Convention.
But sales will be closely monitored and
measures taken to prevent a resur¬
gence of elephant poaching in coun¬
tries not covered by the decision. It is
agreed that proceeds from sales will
go towards nature conservation. I
/>JbT3*yV ~,
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1997
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
LISTENING
American trombonist and composer
Steve Turre combines respect for tradition
with openness to all types of music.
How did you first get interested in jazz?
Steve Tune: Coming from a musically gifted
family especially my mother, who is a
pianist and flamenco dancer I always knew
I'd be a musician. It's my vocation in life.
At home we listened to all kinds of music
jazz, boogie-woogie, classical, Latino, blues,
gospel, rock, whatever. In my parents' day
they met at a Count Basic dance you
danced to jazz. But it's become less rhyth¬
mical now, which explains why it's lost some
of its public. Latino music on the other hand
has a great beat and has a considerable fol¬
lowing today. I love a good beat. Everything
in nature is rhythmical. Music without a
beat lacks vitality.
When I was about nine or ten, I began
playing the trombone in the school band.
Two or three years later I joined a band
where my older brother plaj ed the sax. In
1972 I went on a European tour with Kay
Charles (my younger brother, Pete, is now
his drummer). The following year I took
part in a jam-session at the Keystone Cor¬
ner in San Francisco, and Art Blakey asked
me to ¡day with his band.
You are sometimes called a Chkano musician.
Are you happy with that label?
S. T.: Absolutely not. The word "Chirano"
mainly applies to Los Angeles where it
means people of Mexican descent who usu¬
ally belong to the underprivileged social
classes. Whereas I grew up in the Bay Area
near San Francisco (northern California).
I have Mexican roots, but I am American,
and like any American, I'm a blend of var¬
ious nationalities. I don't want to be
restricted by my roots or get locked into
clichés for the rest of my life. I want to be
myself with my individuality intact.
Some Latin American jazz musicians often
complain that the critics respect them more
when they play "pure" jazz rather than Latin
Jazz, music which is, however, just as interesting
and hard to play. Have you run into any such
prejudices in your career?
S. T.: Yes. The problem often comes from
record companies or promoters. Some
labels, for example, make a distinction
between white jazz and black jazz. If you
Isabelle Leymarie talks to
Steve Turre
have a Latin American background and you
nin a band, they tend to consider ) ou exclu¬
sively as a player of Latin jazz. And even
though I love Latin rhythms, I'm a jazz
musician, and I stand by my jazz records.
I don't like having labels stuck on me. I'm
interested in all sorts of music.
Besides your work as a trombonist, for the
past few years you've become especially well
known for playing conches and seashells, from
which you coax haunting sounds. Your seashell
solos with Dizzy Gillespie's United Nations
Orchestra were one of the highlights of his
concerts. How did you discover these unorthodox
instruments?
S. T.: Kahsaan Koland Kirk had a seashell
he let me play. I loved to blow into it.
Conches and seashells were the predeces¬
sors of brass instruments, but it was only in
1978 while on tour in Mexico with the
Woody Shaw sextet that I had my eyes
opened to seashells. I'd never been to Mex¬
ico. Wc were going to perforin in several
towns, and my mother gave me the phone
number of some of her relatives. I invited
them to the concert, and that evening,
Woody decided to play a piece in which
we used seashells. The audience loved it,
and after the concert my family asked me
if I knew that the Aztecs used to blow into
seashells. I didn't in fact. Next I went to
Mexico City's Anthropological Museum and
saw some wonderful seashells, and then to
Teotiliuacán, where I found bas-reliefs
showing men blowing into seashells or
conches. Up till then I didn't feel confi¬
dent enough to use them. But after that I
felt something click inside and began play
ing without worrying about what people
might think.
Aztec priests used sacred conches. In the
Caribbean the Maroonsescaped slavesand
Haitian countryfolk also used conches to
communicate. Conches are both a sacred symbol
and a symbol of freedom. Do you do anything to
the conches and seashells before playing them?
S. T.i Yes. I taught myself by trial and error.
I file and trim them. I've got them in all
sizes and compose according to the ones
I've got at hand. Small seashells produce
high notes; big ones produce lower notes.
For the past five or six years I've also been
collecting animal horns, which are still used
in certain forms of traditional African
music. Fitted with a special mouthpiece,
they produce interesting sounds and
rhythms. I've created something new with
my seashells, but I use them for the dif¬
ferent tonal colours they give. They fill out
my instrumental palette. The "Shell
Choir", my set of seashells, are part of my
musical luggage just like other experi¬
ments. But I'm a trombonist most of all.
The trombone is my main instrument, and
I can change timbre and colours by using all
sorts of mutes.
Do you get as much pleasure from composing
as you do from playing?
5. T.: If j ou lead a band, it's to play your
own music. I've already played the whole
traditional repertoire of jazz for the trom¬
bone, and I want to do something differ¬
ent. At school I studied harmonics and
basic musical theory, but I mostly learned
to compose from the great arrangers and by
watching how music is made. I had the
opportunity to compose the score for a
ühn, Anna Oz, directed by a young French
filmmaker, Eric Rochant. You can hear my
seashells in it with a few additions. I'd like
to do more films, but I prefer playing. I've
found a way of expressing myself and a
style I feel comfortable with, and I get
enormous satisfaction from it. I
Discography:
Steve Turre, Verve 314 537 L33-2 (1997)
44
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
Funding
a new home
for Egypt's
ancient
treasures
bySamirGharib
Cairo Museum possesses what is regarded
as the world's richest collection of Egypt¬
ian antiquities, comprising some 176,000 items.
Only 40,000 of them are on display, however.
The rest are stacked in the museum's basement
areas.
The museum has never been enlarged since it
was built at the beginning of the century. Some
renovation and modernization work has been car¬
ried out, particularly on the electrical installa¬
tions and the surveillance and alarm systems,
and a new room for the royal mummies is now
open to the public, after being closed for many
years for reasons connected with Islamic law.
The main achievement in recent years has prob¬
ably been the recording of over 135,000 items on
CD-ROM but these are merely drops in the
ocean.
On average, a new archaeological site, is dis¬
covered every month in Egypt. As there are no
regional museums, the rooms and corridors of An exhibition hall of the Cairo
the Cairo Museum are bursting at the seams with Museum. In centre, a statue of
. r , . -ii Ramses II.
more and more artelacts, and it is impossible to
observe scientific standards of display. The base¬
ment areas are so crammed that it is almost
impossible to get into them. Valuable objects
are piling up and mouldering down there, doomed
to slow degeneration. Security problems and
management difficulties further aggravate the
situation, while the museum's location on Al
Tahrir Square, one of the world's most congested
thoroughfares, means that it is threatened by
pollution and by vibration from the underground
railway that passes beneath it.
The only solution would be to build a spa-
© Grandadam/Hoa Qui Pans
cioiis new museum, in compliance with modern
scientific standards, on a protected site. This
would make Egypt the world centre for the study
of Egyptian civilizations, would greatly increase
tourist revenue, contribute to the development
of research and enable management of all the
country's museums and sites to be centralized.
For archaeology, it would contribute to the devel¬
opment of reliable conservation methods, edu¬
cation and the media would also benefit and, last
but not least, it would help in the creation of
new jobs and the training of specialists.
In 1992, a plot of land of lllfeddans (about
45
THEUNÏSCO Qouri:ER «DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
68 hectares) near Giza and the Saqqara site was
allotted to the new museum by presidential
decree, but in its five-year budget adopted at
the same time the government set aside only 75
million Egyptian pounds (about $20 million) for
the project, a sum incommensurate with the
total construction cost, then estimated at $700
million.
The Italian government made available two
billion lire to finance a feasibility study. An Italo-
Egyptian commission of experts was set up and
began work in January 1993. Its conclusions were
public three years later: the building of the
new museum should proceed in tandem with the
restructuring of the present museum; the col¬
lections should be divided between the two
The upraised arms on this
statue adorning the tomb of
the Pharoah Awlbr'hor
symbolize the ruler's ka, the
energy principle that inhabits
gods and humans.
museums, and the new one should also house a
large specialized library, restoration laborato¬
ries, a data bank, an information agency, rooms
for young visitors, separate rooms for permanent
and temporary exhibitions, an auditorium, a pub¬
lications bureau, photographic laboratories, and
so forth.
No decision has as yet been taken about the
distribution of the collections. Various propos¬
als are being studied, the main aim being to avoid
duplication.
But the real problem is a financial one. The
Egyptian government is not in a position to make
available the two billion pounds needed to carry
out the project, and the present scale of its foreign
debt is such that it cannot contract any new loans.
On the other hand the governments of the rich
countries, all of which have their own problems,
are unable to help with the project's financing.
There is no doubt, however, that the project
is economically viable. The museum has every
chance of becoming a major attraction for the
world's Egyptologists and providing a windfall
for national and international tourism. It will very
likely double the number of tourists visiting
Egypt, which now stands at one and a half million
a year. Successfully managed, it should thus be
able to draw three million visitors, representing
a revenue of $30 million from admission fees
alone, not counting other sources of income,
which should double this sum again. The
museum could therefore cover its construction
costs in less than a dozen years.
Egyptian banks alone could put together the
capital needed for the building of the museum
and then entrust its management to an interna¬
tional company. The Egyptian government could
take the initiative in setting up a company in
which it would itself be a small stakeholder and
put shares on sale on the Egyptian and interna¬
tional markets. Such a solution, which is in line
with the government's present privatization pol¬
icy, would furthermore enable it to control the
movement of objects of artistic worth: neither
private enterprises nor individuals would be able
to take any such object out of the country with¬
out the agreement of the authorities. The Egypt¬
ian law-enforcement agency responsible for the
protection of the heritage would obviously be
in charge of security for the new museum, as it
is for the present one.
If the public sector docs not have the
resources to finance the project, let the private
sector step in! I
46
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
THIS MONTH'S INTERVIEW
René Depestre
Between utopia
and reality
Your life as an adult and as a poet began with
what you later called "a triple badge of rebellion"
proud négritude, impassioned surrealism, and the
idea of revolution. Today only the surrealism part
seems to have survived.
R.D.: It's a long story. When André Breton came
to Haiti at the end of 1945, his visit coincided
with an exhibition of the Cuban painter Wifredo
Lam's paintings and a series of lectures given by
the Martinique poet Aimé Césaire. This really
fired the imagination of us young Haitian artists
and writers. At that time we knew nothing about
what was happening in the surrealist movement
in France. For young people combatting Presi¬
dent Elie Lescot's dreadful dictatorship, surre¬
alism was the lifeblood of revolt. Contact with
Breton had a contagious effect on us. After his
first lecture in a Port-au-Prince cinema, we
brought out a special issue of our new magazine
La Ruche as a tribute to him. We went to prison
for our pains and the magazine was banned.
What Breton discovered in Haiti, and made
us discover too, was that surrealism wasn't just
an aesthetic doctrine but something that could
be part of a people's way of looking at the world;
that there was a kind of grassroots surrealism.
This restored our self-confidence. Wc saw that
this sense of wonder we had secretly been a bit
ashamed of and associated with a kind of under¬
development was actually our weapon. Breton
told us that in France "we launched surrealism
as a movement based on intellectual foundations,
you in Haiti learned all about it in the cradle."
In other words, surrealism was something inher¬
ent in the Caribbean. Voodoo, a product of
Franco-African syncretism, is an example of reli-
A Fran co-Haiti an poet,
essayist and award-
winning novelist looks
back on his nomadic life,
speaks out against
totalitarian ideologies
and reaffirms his
attachment to public
spiritedness based on
planet-wide solidarity
and mutual respect.
Interview by
JasminaSopova
gious surrealism. The behaviour of the voodoo
gods is supremely surrealist.
H So surrealism for you is much more than a
literary movement.
K.D.: Much more. Many European writers, start¬
ing with the German Romantics and even before
that, had a surrealist approach. I'm sure if you
looked closely at Egyptian, Japanese or Chinese
culture, you'd find surrealist elements there too.
For ine, surrealism is a way of injecting the super¬
natural into everyday life. You find it e\ crywhere.
But some people, like Haitians or Brazilians,
display it more boldly than others.
How do you explain the emergence of the
Duvaliers in a society imbued with a sense of the
magical?
R.D.: The magical has even marked Haitian pol¬
itics. Our history has thrown up dictators who
practised a kind of tragic perversion of magic.
This is how the "tonton macoute" which is a
folk concept, an incarnation of evil, a kind of
Nazi, a Haitian SS-man came to exist. Haitian
folklore is a tug-of-war between good and evil.
The elder Duvalier, "Papa Doc," used the forces
of black magic to plunge the country into a total¬
itarian surrealism.
But there's more to it than this demoniacal
aspect. From the December morning in 1492
when Christopher Columbus discovered Haiti
and was transfixed by what he saw, the historic,
baroque tale of Haiti cannot be separated from
American wondrous realism. A sense of the won¬
drous (South American magic realism) has
become part and parcel of Haitians' view of the
world and the sustenance of their third of the
THE UNESCO IpURIER B DECEMBER 1 997
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
island of Ilispaniola, where the best and the
worst rub shoulders like the dearest of friends,
when they are not locked in terrible combat.
You have celebrated the communist utopia in
your poems.
R.D.: The Marxist utopia, with all its lies and
repressive nightmares, took over my work and
my life as a poet until the moment I broke with
Stalinism. After living in places which had a huge
"strategic" importance in the turmoil of our cen¬
tury Moscow, Prague, Beijing, Hanoi and
Havana I realized that what was meant by
"socialist revolution" in those places was not the
opposite of the Haitian terror regime, but
another form of the same perversion. Instead of
promoting the heritage of the rights of man and
the citizen, "the revolution" defiled the auton¬
omy of women and men and carried out, at their
expense, the most amazing hijack of ideals and
dreams in all human history.
What has become of the "revolutionary ideal"
which drew you from Haiti to Europe and then on to
Cuba?
R.D.: I ardently believed in revolution. For me it
became a kind of natural state, like breathing,
walking or swimming. And it nearly destroyed
my integrity as a citizen and a writer. The ideal
of revolution seriously impoverished my personal
store of poetry and tenderness which, when I
was twenty, made me think of my future work as
a state of wonder and oneness with the world. It
made my literary career that of a writer who
performed psychological and intellectual som¬
ersaults and sudden existential about-turns a
kind of carnival of uncertainties and inconsis¬
tencies, adrift in the furious currents of the cen¬
tury's passions and ideals. The treasure islands
invented by the utopias and mythologies of rev¬
olution went up in smoke with the great dreams
of our youthuniting the idea of transforming
the world (Karl Marx) with that of changing life
(Arthur Rimbaud).
The word "utopia" as used by Marxists has a
pejorative meaning for you. But doesn't the world
need utopias?
R.D.: Octavio Paz has defined utopias as "the
dreams of reason." We're just emerging from a
terrible nightmare of reason. The nineteenth
century, a critical age if ever there was one, gave
birth to the idea of a revolutionary utopia. But
the totally legitimate dream of earlier philoso¬
phers did not turn into the major transformation
of human lives they had hoped for, nor into
unprecedented progress for humankind. The
generous aspirations of critical thought imposed
on us, under the bogus label of "real socialism,"
48
In place of the notion
of realpolitik, which is
at the root of most of
the woes of people
and societiesand
which still flourishes
to an extraordinary
degree in
governmentI offer
the notion of
realutopia.
an absolutism the like of which we had never
seen before.
In saying this I do not wish to denigrate the
idea of utopia as such. Old age reminds me these
days that I don't have much time left and that I
must hasten to express things I've kept to myself
all my life. And hopefully express them with
grace and maturity. So, in a way, I'm summing up
my life's nomadic journey. And all self-criticism
leads one to utopia. But hardened observer that
I am, I deeply distrust a historical concept that
this century's revolutions have debased. In place
of the notion of realpolitik, which is at the root
of most of the woes of people and societies and
which still flourishes to an extraordinary degree
in government, I offer the notion »[realutopia.
Could you explain what you mean by realutopia":
R.D.: It's an aesthetic concept which enables
me to unite the various parts of my Franco-Hait¬
ian creole-ness as a writer. Doctors and physiol¬
ogists call synergy the links between several ele¬
ments which combine in a single function and a
common effect. The idea oí realutopia leads me
to a kind of aesthetic and literary synergy which
points in a single direction the multitude of expe¬
riences that I owe to magical reality, to négri¬
tude, to sun-kissed eroticism and to the creóle
fantasizing of Haitians, which is the surrealism
of the humbled and the hurt.
So you haven't entirely turned your back on
négritude?
R.D.: I've always mistrusted the idea of négritude
because I did not think it was possible to con¬
stitute an anthropology which is the exact oppo¬
site of the one which devalued us and down¬
graded us as "Blacks". You can't just transfer to
a Black context what is said and done in terms of
Whites. Aimé Césaire referred to this phenom¬
enon as turning Gobineau upside down. I realized
we had to create our own aesthetic and ideol¬
ogy without falling into "anti-racist racism."
That's why I said goodbye to négritude at the
same time as I dropped Marxism. I've only stuck
with surrealism, which is still one of my working
tools. I use both ends of the tool the scholarly
and the popular. But I mistrust surrealism too.
Breton leaned towards the occult, trying to link
surrealism with certain cabbalistic and Talmudic
traditions a shadowy area in the history of
thought but no less interesting for that which
are the equivalent of looking for the philoso¬
pher's stone. I don't go along with that at all.
I've rejected the ideals of my youth and today
I work with the tragic experiences which in my
case they led to.
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
How do you see the world these days?
R.D.: The idea of revolution has been buried
and history marches on, with its media-fed pro¬
cession of horrors and marvels. The myth of a
great consummation of the body and the mind
died of natural causes in a big So\iet-stylc bed.
The corpse is still warm and already the spark of
totalitarianism has reappeared in the shape of
religious fundamentalism. All kinds of ethno-
nationalist savagery, supposedly under the ban¬
ner of a campaign to renew faithless societies, are
building monuments to obscurantism, terrorism
and new banditry by the state. On the borders of
the West, the idea of a fundamentalist utopia has
taken the place of a revolutionary one.
How can literature inspire people to embark on
the adventure of a new renaissance?
R.D.: The answer to that is shaped by a context
of fundamentalist horrors, intcr-eth nie massacres
and racist and nationalist violence. It's one of a
planet completely ruled by market forces.
Thanks to the rational instruments of the
rule of law and democracy, the institution of the
market has survived all attacks on it. But most
people now think the democracy of the mar¬
ket its basis and the way it works needs to
be overhauled. Or else life in society is going to
become a great planet-wide casino. So it's in the
interests of the victorious marketplace to do
something about the chaotic and aggressive con¬
ditions in which the globalization of human
affairs is taking place.
Bold steps should be taken to make good use
of the world's heritage of democratic experi-
I see the bold
imagination of poets
and writers at the
forefront of the values
shared by the world's
cultures.
ence, the rich store of rules of citizenship and the
art of living together which is to be found in
Western civil societies, the most developed and
experienced in terms of law, liberties, justice
and solidarity. We should be able to turn the
current haphazard process of globalization into
an unprecedented Immunization of relations
between indh ¡duals and nation-states. The inter¬
national ci\il society which is growing up amid
disorder and uncertainty needs the oxygen of
world-wide public-spiritedness and the idea of
solidarity that will be conducive to fair distrib¬
ution of the values and principles which are now
the shared property of the global village.
Who could promote this global public-
spiritedness?
R.D.: I see the bold imagination of poets and writ¬
ers at the forefront of the values shared by the
world's cultures. Our works, each with its own
strictly aesthetic identity, should help scientists
and politicians to revamp our old ideas about good
and evil, to revive a sense of the sacred which is
being lost and to devise a more balanced rela¬
tionship between North and South, and East and
West. This would be in a new world order where
the necessary rules of commerce, tempered by a
new sense of meaning and new ideals, could express
a fresh balance between nature and history. To
advance further without risking disaster, the spirit
of the market should now be endowed with cer¬
tain ethical features, such as meaning, laws of
citizenship and an art of living together based on
mutual respect and sympathy between the world's
peoples and societies.
AUTHORS
ROBERT BAUDRY, of Belgium, is professor emeritus at the University of Katanga
(Democratic Republic of Congo) and president of the Centre for Study and Research
on the wonderful, the strange and the unusual in literature. He is currently preparing
for publication a book on the quest for the Grail in modern times.
THOR VILHJÁLMSSON, of Iceland, is a writer, a painter and co-founder of the
Icelandic cultural review Birtmgur. His novels published in English include Quick,
Quick, said the bird (1968), The Beatle's Cry (1970) and Moonsicle (1976). He is
also the author of a book of poetry composed in English, The Deep Blue Sea,
Pardon the Ocean (Loonbooks, Northeast Harbour, U.S.A.). His novelïïie Grey
Moss Glows, which won the Nordic Council Prize for literature in 1988, will be
published shortly in English.
ANTONIO GUERREIRO, a French ethnologist and film-maker, is associate
researcher at the Southeast Asian Research Institute in Aix-en-Provence (France).
He co-edited a special issue of the French magazine /Autrement (no. 11, 1991)
devoted to the Indonesian island of Borneo.
EDOUARD J. MAUNICK is a Mauritian poet and writer. Notable among his
published works are Ensoleillé vif (which won the Apollinaire Prize in 1976),
Anthologie personnelle (1984) and Paroles pour solder la mer (1989).
JACQUES LACARRIÈRE, a French writer, has published a vast body of work
including (in English translation) The God Possessed (Dutton, New York, 1964),
and The Gnostics (Peter Owen, London, 1977/City Lights, San Francisco, 1989).
LOKENATH BHATTACHARYA, an Indian poet and essayist, has published some
thirty works in India, including The Virgin Fish of Babughat (1975), The Prose
Poems ofLokenath Bhattacharya (1971) and The Drum of the Guru (1973).
LUIS MIZÓN, a Chilean poet and essayist, is the author of many books, including
a novel, El hombre del cerro plomo (1991) and a collection of poems, Jardin de
rumas (1992).
EDUARDO MANET is a French novelist and playwright of Cuban origin. Among his
recent published works in French are L'île du lézard vert (1994) and Rhapsodie
cubaine (1996). The script of his play The Nuns was published by Calder (London)
in 1970.
PASCALE ABSI of France, is the author of an anthropological study on the
miners of Potosí.
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American journalist specializing in environmental
questions.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American musicologist, has recently published La
musique sud-américaine, Rythmes et danses d'un continent ("South American
Music, a Continent's Rhythms and Dances", Gallimard, Pans, 1997).
SAMIR GHARIBisan Egyptian journalist and art critic.
CORRECTION
Page 27 of our October 1997 issue ("Natural Disasters, Be Prepared!") contains an error.
The phrase "Most of the 100,000 people who died in the 1991 Bangladesh cyclone. . . ."
should begin: "Most of the 200,000 people who died	*
> GuiTHE UNESCO ÍOURIER B DECEMBER 1997 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER
JANUARY« MICROFINANCE
Interview with Johan Gattung (N. Batic).
Reaching the unreached (S. Rahman). A new
weapon in the war on poverty (J. Garson).
Three golden rules (M. Otero). Where credit
is due. . . (R. P. Christen). A bank for the poor
(M. Yunus). Microfinance in Indonesia (M.
S. Robinson). Latin America: ACCIÓN
speaks louder than words (M. Otero). Enter¬
prise in Africa (K. Mutua). Village banking: a
report from 5 countries (R. Scofield). Three
microcredit schemes in Europe (M. Nowak).
Commentary: Education, seedbed of the
future (F. Mayor). Grcenwatch: People and
plants (F. Bcquette). Heritage: Colonia del
Sacramento (E. Bailby). Listening: Interview
with David Sanchez (I. Leymarie).
FEBRUARY« RADIO,
A FUTURE FOR SOUND
Interview with Alain dc Libera (R. Sabbaghi).
On the crest of the waves (H. Bourges). The
first half century, 1895-1945 (B. Blin). The
second half century, 1945-1995 (G. Price). A
public service (K. Ebbcscn). From short wave
to satellite (R. Gallon and D. Seligsohn). By
the people, for the people (C. A. Arnaldo).
Villages find their voice (W. Jayaweera and L.
Tabing). All power to the microphone! (A.
Ogancssian). Commentary: Energy for all (F.
Mayor). Heritage: Mr. Jefferson's dream house
(F. Lcary). Grcenwatch: Earthwatching satel¬
lites (F. Bcquette).
MARCH «PLURAL CITIES
Interview with Prcdrag Matvejevic and
Vidosav Stevanovic (J. Sopova). Tangier:
myths and memories (T Ben Jelloun). New
York blues (J. Charyn). Bombay: one and
many (L. R. Jagga). Marseilles: port of call
and recall (E. Temimc). La Paz: a tale of two
cities (L. Pacheco). Vancouver, or the spirit
of place (H. Ditmars). The spirit of diversity
(A. Barrak). Commentary: Science and society
(1) (F. Mayor). Heritage: Notre-Dame
d'Amiens (C. Romane). Grcenwatch: Large
dams (F. Bcquette). Reflections: The world is
a sanctuary (H. Skolimowski). Listening:
Rediscovering Lili Boulanger (I. Leymarie).
APRIL THE BODY AND THE SELF
Interview with Mario Luzi (M. Rosi). Face val¬
ues (D. Le Breton). An invisible river (S.
Nagatomo). The body and the book (D. Biale).
A language of its own (M. B. Priso). From self¬
hood to salvation (R. Maitra). The garden of
delights (A. Mcddeb). Commentary: Science
and society (2) (F. Mayor). Heritage: TeWahi-
pounamu, New Zealands's pristine wilderness
(A.-M. Johnson). Grcenwatch: Gardens: a cul¬
tural flowering (F. Bcquette). Listening: Inter¬
view with Rido Bayonne (I. Leymarie).
MAY« LANDSCAPE WITH FIGURES
Interview with Aimé Césaire (A. T. Melsan).
Reading the landscape (Y. Bergcret). Thresh¬
olds of divinity (M. Ninomiya). Sicilian flights
(J.-F. Patricola). Colourful language (G. Piña-
Contrcras). Say it with flowers (Y. E. Ioan-
nou). What's in a name? (L. Mizón). Fact file:
The world network of biosphere reserves.
Commentary: Science and Society (3) (F.
Mayor). Heritage: The Island of Mozambique
(P. Lagcs). Grcenwatch: Gardens of the Far
East (F. Bcquette). Listening: Ethiopia's azmari
minstrels (I. Leymarie). Anniversary: Aleko
Konstantinov (1 863-1897) (G. Danaïlov).
JUNE HOW IDEAS TRAVEL
On the road (F.-B. Huyghe). Manuscripts on
the move (G. Messadic). Best-sellers and gos¬
sip-mongers in 1 8th-ccntury France (R. Darn-
ton). 'Words have no legs, yet they walk' (Y.
Tata Cissc). The mixed signals of globaliza¬
tion (S. Gucmriche). Cyberspace: a planetary
network of people and ideas (J. C. Nyiri). The
test of time (L. Merzeau). Fact file: Safe¬
guarding the documentary heritage; Routes of
dialogue. Commentary: From ideal to action
(F. Mayor). Grcenwatch: Save our soils! (F.
Bcquette). Heritage: Palmyra, faces that belong
to eternity (M. Zibawi). Ancient and modern
Egypt come face to face (S. Gharib). Inter¬
view with Viviane Forrester (E. Reichmann).
JULY-AUGUST PORTRAITS
OF WOMEN
IN YOUNG PEOPLE'S LITERATURE
and
UNESCO'S SECRET.
Japan: Breaking the stereotype (A. Sueyoshi).
East Africa: Silent partners (E. Lcdi Barongo).
Former USSR: From ideology to love (J.
Prosalkova). North America: Mothers and
daughters (E. Liebs). UNESCO's secret, an
LBRZ and ZKRR adventure (Alteau and C.
Doxuan). Declaration: The human right to
peace (F. Mayor). Sarajevo's battered soul (P.
d'Erm). Albania's threatened heritage (Y.
Aliçka). Grcenwatch: Forests: a breathing
space for the planet (F. Bcquette). Heritage:
the divine faces of Tcothihuacán (C. Romane).
UNESCO in action: adult education for tomor¬
row (C. Mcintosh). Reflections: letters from
Asia (D. Sinor). Interview with Mstislav Ros-
tropovich (I. Leymarie).
SEPTEMBER «THE STATE
OF THE WORLD HERITAGE
What is the world heritage? (Dossier). The
World Heritage Convention, 25 years on (B.
von Drostc). Vive la différence! (C. Fabrizio).
An idea whose time has come (P. Nora). Cul¬
tural landscapes (D. Lowenthal). Past and pre¬
sent: a creative dialogue (J. Rigaud). The Mod
ern Movement (M. Kuipers). In youthful
hands (I. Kvisteroy). Words and deeds (G.
Zouain). The North-South gap (L. Rajk). A
vigilant eye (M. Björnstad). Sacred mountains
(E. Bernbaum). A canal in southern France (F.
Bordry). Three highland villages in Japan (H.
Saito and N. Inaba). Commentary: The her¬
itage, memory of the future (F. Mayor).
Grcenwatch: A waste-free farm (F. Bequette).
Interview with Youssef Chahine (M. Fargeon).
OCTOBER NATURAL DISASTERS,
BE PREPARED!
Safety first! (B. Rouhban). A decade for inter¬
national action (F. Press). Nature on the ram¬
page (W. W. Hays). Making cities safer (M.
Erdik). The do's and don'ts of risk reduc¬
tion (B. Carby). Sounding the alarm (F. Fer-
rucci). Women in the front line (D. Guha-
Sapir). Insurance: halting an ominous trend
(G. Berz). Commentary: Water and civiliza¬
tion (F. Mayor). Grcenwatch: New Caledonia:
threats to biodiversity (F. Bequette). Her¬
itage: Taxila, the cradle of Gandhara art (L.
Gourret). Reflections: Spreading the word
(O. Vallet). Interview with Manuel Elkin
Patarroyo (F. Romero).
NOVEMBER I ITHEATRE'S CHANGING
SCENE
Theatre for tomorrow (R. Schechner). Rules
made to be broken (J. -P. Guingané). An art in
search of its roots (R. Maitra). Shingeki's rest¬
less century (O. Yoshio). A common home
(A. Smeliansky). The birth of modern Arab
theatre (G. Maleh). The theatre of the
oppressed (A. Boal). Fact file: The Interna¬
tional Theatre Institute. Commentary: Sci¬
ence education and sustainable development
(F. Mayor). Greenwatch: Seaweed at your ser¬
vice (F. Bequette). Heritage: Ironbridge Gorge
(N. Cossons). Interview with Andrée Che¬
did (M. Leca).
DECEMBER «ISLANDS
A WORLD APART
Islands of the imagination (R. Baudry). Ice¬
land's hidden fire (T. Vilhjálmsson). The
Pacific: the coming of the ancestors (A Guer-
rciro). Solstice islands (E. Maunick). The tri¬
als of Ulysses (J. Lacarrière). What, my
brother, is an island? (L. Bhattacharya). Easter
Island's last secret (L. Mizón). Cuba's gold
(E. Manet). Commentary: Peace, development
and democracy: UNESCO at work (F. Mayor).
Heritage: The treasure of the Cerro Rico (P.
Absi). Greenwatch: Climate change (F.
Bequette). Reflections: A new home for
Egypt's ancient treasures (S. Gharib). Listen¬
ing: Interview with Steve Turre (I. Leymarie).
Interview with René Depestre (J. Sopova).
50
THE UNESCO lOURIER DECEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Unesco on line via Internet
Currently on-line are: an index of the contents of the last
22 issues of the Unesco Courier, Unesco press releases,
addresses, fax, telex and electronic mail numbers of
Unesco's regional offices, National Commissions and Unesco
Slubs, the directory of Unesco databases and information
ervices, colour images of the Japanese Garden and other
rchitectural sites at Unesco Headquarters, as well as works
, f art such as Henry Moore's reclining sculpture.
A splendid contemporary work to serve as a lasting
reminder of hope and peace.
WJ4&*
A I S S A N C t
SMtAIEVO PHILHARMONIC ORCHESTRA
iÜÜl JUME- Bkeion- Honore
StAVWI-KOtlIOVIC-GlOVWW
ReJ.CD:74Mi52160-2
SPONSORED BY UNESCO
ilvJl EVO
Stiles to benefit the Smajcvo Pliilhcit moiiic Oidiestiu
RENAISSANCE
The revival of a city, of a people, of hope
The first recording Of
the Sarajevo Philharmonic Orchestra
since the war
KS specially composed by :
arre, Eric Breton, Josip Slavenski,
Petar Konjovic, Asim Horozic, Riccardo Giovannini.
Performed by the Sarajevo Philharmonic Orchestra
under the direction of Ernst Schelle and Emir Nuhanovic.
CTiÜCkCi. Distribution by BiVlC^
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
IN THE NEXT ISSUE:
IN PRAISE OF FRUGALITY
INTERVIEW WITH
LUIS SEPÚLVEDA
HERITAGE
MOUNT ATHOS (GREECE)
ENVIRONMENT
CITIES: RESIDENTS TO THE RESCUE
]]>
</page>
</document>
