<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="110425eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
f
,
> * mm tomwwlife?
' f
,<
* t
.. >
ÏiH'li
I M I
301 22,00
INTERVIEW VfITH LUIS SEPÚLVEDA '
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTERS?̂*
:':
	
;
»--». imimB	
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered for
publication in this feature. Your
photo should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of architecture
or any other subject which seems
to be an example of cultural
cross-fertilization.
Alternatively, you could send us
pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all
photographs.
ET LE VENT DE
SFAX
1997, pastel and ink
(81 cm x 65 cm)
by Jean-Baptiste Belvisi
Doors of buildings in the
Medina of Tunis are
depicted in this pastel by
Jean-Baptiste Belvisi, a
Tunisian-born artist who
lives in France. Together
with members of his family
and figures from Arab
mythology, they are a
recurrent theme of Belvisi's
work, which seeks to
recreate the atmosphere of
his Tunisian childhood. The
artist makes extensive use
of pastel to evoke the
colours reflected on the
doors of the old city in the
morning and evening light,
and says, "My pastel stick is
my bridge between East and
West." As a sign of his
desire to strengthen the
fragile link between the two
worlds, he used the
expression Trait d'union
("Hyphen") as the title for
a recent exhibition held in
Tunisia of his works on the
door motif.
© Jean Baptiste Belvisi. Nantes
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
the unesco Courier
47
Luis Sepúlveda
An avard-uinning Chilean novelist and
traveller talks about bis adventurous career
marked by prison and exile.
38
Mount Athos (Greece)
Treasures from I I fountain "
on display to an internationalpublic
¡or the first time.
Cover:
Fietsfeest '96("Bicycle Festival") held in Amsterdam
(The Netherlands) in July 1996 attracted more than
15,000 cyclists.
© Roland Nooteboom, Amsterdam
contents
JANUARY 1998
Frugality
a way to a better life?
Monthby month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat	5
A subversive idea	6
by Paul Ekins
Is frugality a virtue? 10
by James Griffin
Plain living and high thinking	14
An imaginary interview with the Greek philosopher Epicurus
Three exceptional figures 15
by Adam Roberts
From zero towards one	17
Interview with Shioun Michiko Nakasato
Waste not, want not 20
by Hisanori Isomura
An economy of sharing	23
by Marie Roué
Making a little go a long way 26
by Babacar Sail
Pedal power 30
by Benoît Lambert
Fact file	33
Consultants: Arthur Gillette, Adam Roberts and Miki Nozawa
Commentary Federico Mayor
GREENWATCH Cities: residents to the rescue by France Bequette
LISTENING Toto la Momposina by Isabelle Leymarie
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
AUTHORS
36
42
46
50
50
THE UNESCO IpURIER JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TBfe. UNESCO
Courier
^^51st YEAR
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31. rue François Bonvm, 75732 Pans CEDEX 15, France
Fax (33) (0)1 45 68.57.45
e-mail unesco courier@unesco.org
Internet: http //www unesco org
Director: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition Roy Malkin
French edition Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbma
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag
(Tel (33) (0)1 45.68. 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press'
Solange Beim (Tel, (33) (0) 1.45.68 46 87)
Film duplication: Daniel Meister
Secretariat: Annie Brächet
(Tel (33) (0)1.45 68 47 15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean' (Tel. (33} (0) 1.45 68 45 69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian Irma Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian GianlucaFormichi (Rome)
Hindi Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian AkbarZargar (Teheran)
Portuguese. Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili. Leonard J Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese1 Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian, Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek. Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Smhala Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish. Rntta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai. Duangtip Sunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese1 Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax: (33) (0) 1.45 68.57.45
Subscriptions. Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68 45.65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45,68.49 19)
Customer service: Michel Ravassard,
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45.68.45.91)
Accounts: (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68.45 65)
Shipping Daniel Meister (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45.68 47.50}
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel. (33) (0)1 45,68 45 65
1 year 211 French francs 2 years' 396 FF.
Students 1 year 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues 72 FF
Developing countries
1 year. 132 French francs 2 years. 211 FF
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author's name Non-copyright photos will
be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be relumed
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nec¬
essarily represent the opinions of Umesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the
Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micio-
film and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700
Paris, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Micnigan 48100
U S A , (3) N C R Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc.. Ill West 40th
Street, New York. U,S A , {4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mansfeld Road,
Wooster, Onio 44691. USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - JANUARY 1998
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N M PP.
Photocomposition, photogravure
Le Courrier de I'Unesco
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.I. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 1-1998-0PI-97-566 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50 51.
month by month
by Bah gat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
© Roland Nooteboom. Amsterdam
THE UNESCO (oURI!ER JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
This issue explores the idea of frugality in its most positive sense. Not as
deprivation enforced by lack of resources or as willed abstinence but as
moderation of conducteating habits being only one aspect of thisresponding to a need
to strike a balance and to draw an acceptable line between the necessary and the
superfluous.
But who should draw this line? And according to what criteria? Here there is
considerable room for subjective opinion. Even if it is accepted that a minimum of
quantitative, objective needs must be met in terms of food, clothing and housing, it is
clearthat history, culture, tradition and hierarchies of values are bound to have a big say
when it comes to defining quality of life. To take just one example among many, the idea of
well-being is bound to vary depending on whether or not one is used to the standards of
comfort associated with the consumer society.
For the consumer society is here challenged on two counts. Philosophically in the
sense thatit artificially stokes up certain needs; economically in the sense that satisfaction
of these needs, which have now spread all overthe world, is only possible for the few and
provokes mounting frustration among the many.
Nowhere in these pages does frugality appear as a counsel of despair, a call for the
victims of the consumer society to tighten their belts. It is presented instead as an
alternative philosophy, a vision of life that replaces today's malfunctions and distortions
with a sense of balance, on the social and human scale, between needs and resources,
especially between material needs and ethical, aesthetic and recreational aspirations.
What remains to be seen is whether such an attempt to find a way between materialism
and the spiritual aspects of life can be successful.
THE UNESCO lOURIER JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A subversive idea BY PAUL EKINS
The values of frugality fly in the face of the prevailing
economic order
It is doubtful whether many people
would subscribe openly and explicitly to
the notion that human happiness derives
exclusively, or even mainly, from the con¬
sumption of goods and services, or that the
only, or even main, way of increasing that
happiness is to increase consumption. So it is
surprising that this notion has come to exer¬
cise a near-dictatorial power over public pol¬
icy, and thence over the way societies are run
and over the directions in which they are con¬
strained to develop. How has this situation
come about? What results has it had? What
would be the rationale for, and some of the
implications of, an alternative view of how
human happiness comes about, in which fru¬
gality plays a significant role?
Clearly all living things need to consume in
order to stay alive, and humans are no excep¬
tion. The use of matter and energy is neces¬
sary to sustain our bodies and to protect us
from hostile environments. Many, but not
all, human societies have also sought to achieve
more than this by generating (often through
the use of slave or forced labour) surpluses
over and above basic consumption needs in
order to build civilizations. But until rela¬
tively modern times the goal of such civiliza¬
tions was not simply to increase aggregate con¬
sumption. While they seem to have been no
less fond of wealth and power than modern
Windfarm turbines in the state
of Gujarat, northwest India.
societies, they also had complex belief systems
which provided them with explanations of
human life and purpose that went far beyond
accumulation and consumption.
Economic growth:
benefits ana costs
It was the conceptualization of " the economy"
as a macro-social entity, and of economics as a
macro-social science, rather than as household
management (which is the root meaning of the
word) that began to stress the importance of
consumption as an end in itself. Adam Smith,
often called the father of economics, wrote:
"Consumption is the sole end and purpose of
all production." As the economy has come to
dominate public discourse, and as the only goal
of economics is to increase consumption, which
it views as synonymous with human welfare,
this has become the prime objective of modern
societies. No matter what the question, in prac¬
tical politics economic growth is the answer.
This primacy is acknowledged in the collective
term used to describe Western industrial soci¬
eties: consumer societies.
At least for those who tried it first the pro¬
ject of increasing consumption has been phe¬
nomenally successful in its own terms. Eco¬
nomic output in the early industrialized
economies has increased by orders of magni¬
tude over the last 200 years. This has brought
many benefits to the populations which have
participated in this growth. These benefits
should be neither denied nor belittled. They
are so obvious to those who do not yet have
them that in practically every country of the
world their achievement has become the prin¬
cipal social project.
But with these benefits have gone costs.
Most obviously the explosion of consump¬
tion, coupled with the growth of human pop¬
ulation, and the vast increase in the use of energy
and materials that have accompanied them, have
put unprecedented pressure on natural systems.
Other costs are less easy to measure and
quantify but are no less keenly perceived. The
processes of capitalistic accumulation through
competition in markets, the promotion of
which is now generally considered to take pri¬
ority over all other social objectives, have led to
what can only be described as profound social
unease. Social institutions, like the family or
community, disintegrate or degenerate; anti¬
social behaviour crime, vandalism, drug
abuse proliferates; unemployment becomes
less cyclical and more structural at higher levels,
THE UNESCO lOURIER |ANUARYI99S
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Children at play in Bahía
(Brazil).
and threatens previously secure white-collar
employees; countries that try to sustain com¬
prehensive systems of social security find them
an unsustainable economic burden, those that
do not experience sharp increases in inequality;
and, finally, social values of trust, integrity and
public service are eroded by the increasing iden¬
tification of personal success with private gain.
Clearly not all these phenomena are equally
evident in all countries, but they are ever more
apparent in both industrialized and industri¬
alizing societies. Not only are they negative
effects in themselves, but they threaten to ren¬
der the growth process unsustainable. Growth
in all the old industrial economies is substan¬
tially slower in the 1990s than in previous
decades. It is at least possible that these
economies are beginning to experience social as
well as environmental limits to growth. This is
potentially traumatic in a society for which
economic growth is the be all and end all of
social purpose. Perhaps it is time to ask whether
there are other sources of human happiness
which could be given a higher social profile and
receive greater emphasis in public policy.
Once sources of human happiness apart
from consumption start to be identified, they
seem so obvious that it is difficult to under¬
stand how they were ever allowed to be mar¬
ginalized by the quest for economic growth or
compromised by its consequences. They
include: stable, caring families; secure, con¬
vivial communities; meaningful and satisfying
work; good health; a sense of personal identity
and social purpose; a diverse, beautiful and
sustainable natural environment; and open,
participatory and democratic societies.
Clearly these sources of happiness are inter¬
related in many different ways. Equally clearly
they can be, and have been, adversely affected
by a pursuit of economic growth that does
not recognize their value. A question then
arises as to what concept may be able to tem¬
per modern societies' obsession with growth
in order to give weight to some of these other
sources of human happiness. This is where the
idea of frugality may have a role to play.
Downshifting
In a society devoted to consumption, it is
hard not to identify frugality with notions of
sacrifice, of "doing without" or "giving things
up". Such identifications are, however, mis¬
placed. Certainly frugality implies modest
consumption and simplicity in personal
lifestyle. But these are not motivated by
abstract asceticism or self-denial, but from a
perception that frugality in consumption per¬
mits a greater emphasis to be placed on other
aspects of human experience, which are actually
more personally rewarding and fulfilling than
consumption. Far from entailing self-denial,
frugality in this reading is a means of libera¬
tion. An all-absorbing concern with con¬
sumption is replaced by the pursuit of other
values that yield more happiness.
This may seem fanciful, but in fact just
THE UNESCO f^URIEI I JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
such a calculus is at the heart of the growing
movement of "downshifting" which has taken
place in recent years, especially in the United
States. Downshifters are people who, by
reducing their employment commitments,
and therefore their income, have chosen some
or all of the following: to have more time
with their families; to contribute to their com¬
munities; to do more work of their own
choosing; to experience less stress; to reduce
their impact on, and/or increase their contact
with the natural environment. So much
momentum had this movement gathered by
1995 that the Wall Street Journal was openly
speculating whether so many people refraining
from market-based consumption could have
a depressing effect on share prices. Such a con¬
cern well expresses how deeply subversive fru¬
gality is of the prevailing economic order.
However, a commitment to frugality in
order to have the time and attention to con¬
centrate on other sources of human happiness
and fulfilment is entirely in line with some
recent theories of human motivation and behav¬
iour. For example, the American psychologist
and philosopher Abraham Maslow postulated
that humans have a hierarchy of needs, in that
they seek first to satisfy material needs of com¬
fortable survival and security, then are con¬
cerned with social needs, including being
accepted and esteemed by their social group,
and then direct their energies towards the sat¬
isfaction of self-actualization needs, seeking to
act in accordance with ideals of love, truth, jus¬
tice and aesthetics in order to realize a higher
human purpose. In this framework increasing
material consumption is irrelevant to human
fulfilment once a reasonable standard of living
has been attained. The striving for further con¬
sumption is indicative of psychological fixa¬
tion and immaturity, a failure to progress to the
realization of higher human potentialities.
The Chilean economist Manfred Max-Neef's
"Some societies had belief
systems which provided
explanations of human life
that went beyond
accumulation and
consumption." Above, the
Forum, ancient Rome's
religious, political and
business centre. Watercolour
by Theodor Hoffbauer (1914).
A family living on the island of
e Mindanao (Philippines).
classification of human needs is similar, except
that he rejects Maslow's hierarchical arrange¬
ment, believing that satisfaction of material
and non-material needs is sought simultane¬
ously. He identifies nine fundamental human
needs (subsistence, affection, protection, under¬
standing, participation, leisure, creation, iden¬
tity, freedom), satisfaction of which is sought
through four modes of experience (being, hav¬
ing, doing, interacting). The means of satisfac¬
tion Max-Neef calls " satisfiers " . Some satisfiers
only satisfy the needs to which they are
directed, while others synergistically satisfy
other needs as well. Less positively, there are
"pseudo-satisfiers", which do not really sat¬
isfy the relevant need; "inhibitors", which sat¬
isfy one need but simultaneously inhibit the
satisfaction of others; and "violators" which
militate against the satisfaction even of the need
to which they are directed. Examples of these
non-satisfiers might be status symbols (which
unsuccessfully seek to address the need for
THE UNESCO f3>URIER |ANUARY I
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
identity), over-indulgence in watching televi¬
sion (a leisure pursuit which inhibits creativity)
and the arms race (which sought to give both
sides protection but ended up making them
both less secure). From this perspective over¬
emphasis on material consumption is often
evidence of a counter-productive fixation with
pseudo-satisfiers, inhibitors or violators. Con¬
versely, embracing frugality can be a means óf
liberation from negative satisfiers involving
material consumption, in order to concentrate
on satisfying needs of which consumption is
not and cannot be an authentic satisfier.
It seems, therefore, that frugality is a valid,
and perhaps a necessary, value of a society that is
truly promotive of human fulfilment. This
raises questions as to why it occupies little or no
space in the social psyches of industrial cultures,
and why frugality as a value (if not material
deprivation as a fact) is increasingly being driven
out of societies worldwide. The answer to the
second question is largely historical and has to
do with power and empire. Put crudely, cul¬
tures geared to increasing material consumption
developed more powerful weapons than those
which valued frugality, permitting the former to
conquer, and colonize or enslave the latter. Decol¬
onization and independence generally failed to
restore traditional values of frugality, the resid¬
ual of which have suffered a further sustained
assault from the globalization of Western com¬
merce, culture and consumerism.
Unresolved contradictions
The answer to the first question renders very
problematic the rediscovery of frugality in cap¬
italist industrial societies. In such societies, where
the achievement of greater material consump¬
tion has become the dominant social objective,
economic growth is a condition not just of sup¬
posed greater human well-being, but also of
basic economic stability. Capitalism operates
through the generation of economic surplus
that accumulates into capital and generates more
production through investment. Unless eco¬
nomic growth is in prospect, capitalists will not
invest. Economic growth requires increased con¬
sumption, even in the richest societies in the
world. Such a requirement is hardly consistent
with a resurgence of frugality.
Moreover, under capitalism, work is orga¬
nized as employment. The profitability of
business is increased when labour becomes
more productive, and the whole thrust of
technological development has been and is to
raise labour productivity. Yet without eco¬
nomic growth increased labour productivity
in a given labour force means greater unem¬
ployment, with all its attendant personal mis¬
ery and social strain. If a new commitment to
frugality were to hold back growth in con-
"Perhaps It is time to ask
whether there are other
sources of human happiness
apart from consumption."
Above, a shopping street in
Tokyo (Japan).
sumption, but the forces increasing labour
productivity were to continue to operate, then
frugality would have produced unemploy¬
ment, which is hardly a recipe for human hap¬
piness even among the more frugally inclined.
Developing new institutions and ways of
working that can resolve the contradictions
between frugality as an individual value and the
social need under capitalism for investment,
economic growth and more jobs, will not be
easy. It will only happen, of course, if the quest
for frugality becomes a far more widespread
and potent social movement than is currently
the case even with regard to downshifting in the
United States. If greater adherence to the value
of frugality is indeed a necessary part of the
solution to the environmental destruction and
social degeneration brought about by materi¬
alistic consumerism, the transition whereby
frugality is either accommodated to capitalism,
or transforms it into a different social and eco¬
nomic system, is likely to be a rough ride.
THE UNESCO lOURIER 1JANUARY199S
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Is frugality a
virtue?
BY JAMES GRIFFIN
If not an end in itself, frugality can
lead to a better quality of life
Does frugality have some sort of ethi¬
cal status? Or is it just an optional "life¬
style" admirable in its way, perhaps, but
admirable as lavish life-styles can be too? Is
frugality any more firmly rooted in values
than luxury is?
Or is it, perhaps, valuable only in special
circumstances, when food or clothes or other
goods are in short supply and sparing con¬
sumption is only good sense? Is it a virtue in
the Third World but not in the First? Is it
appropriate in some settings and wildly inap¬
propriate in others?
Well, let us see where frugality might fit
into ethics. It is not a virtue, at least in the
sense that philosophers use that word. It may
be a virtue in a popular, everyday sense: that is,
generally a good thing, a thing to be admired
or praised. I shall come back to that possibil¬
ity in a moment. By a "virtue" philosophers
mean a disposition that will carry one through
typical trying circumstances in life, when,
without the virtue, one's spirit would be either
deficient or in excess.
Temperance is the classic virtue closest to
frugality. A temperate person does not react to
testing circumstances with either too much
heat or too little, too much desire or too little.
Temperance is defined as striking a certain sort
of desirable balance. But what is suspicious
about frugality is, precisely, that it stands res¬
olutely at one extreme: sparing use. But why is
that the right balance? And balance between
what vices? On one side oí sparing use we might
see waste. But what is on the other side ? On the
other side we might see hurtful under¬
consumption. But why should we regard fru¬
gality as the ideal balance between these two
10
evils ? One could go well beyond frugality into
a fairly liberal use of goods without crossing
over into waste. Why is this greater liberality
not the more desirable balance?
Nor, I think, is frugality intrinsically valu¬
able. Imagine, first, a frugal life: I am careful and
sparing in all that I use; I consume enough for
health but no more than is required for me
to meet simple, basic needs. Now imagine a
non-frugal life: I am less vigilant about and
more liberal in what I use; I consume more
than is strictly needed for my basic needs but
I do not waste anything. Now, if one sees each
The cultivation of "deep
personal relations" Is an
aspect of the good life that
societies based on
consumption tend to
relegate to the
background. Above,
Mayan clay figurines (8th-
11th centuries, Campeche,
Mexico).
THE UNESCO f3>URil1ER IANUARY I99S
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The quest to understand
metaphysical and moral issues
Is also widely regarded as an
element of the good life. Below,
the Japanese monk-poet
Fujiwara no Nobuzane (ink and
paper, 12th-13th centuries).
of these lives simply as the lives I have just
described and apart from any consequences
that they might have, is there any reason to say
that one is better than the other? I at least can
see no reason to think so.
So if a frugal life is in some way valuable, it
must be because of the things that it leads to.
It must be, not intrinsically valuable, but
instrumentally valuable.
And here, it seems to me, there is an inter¬
esting case. Frugality strikes most modern
people as out of date and that no doubt for
different reasons. It seems appropriate to a life
of scarcity and as the world grows richer, fru¬
gality grows irrelevant. And Freud will have
had something to do with it: we suspect that
behind a frugal exterior there is an unattractive,
anal-retentive interior. But, most of all, our
modern value system seems to have gone over
to a form of consumerism. We are dominated
by an economic model of the quality of life.
A human is seen as a complex of desires. The
quality of a human life is seen as in direct pro¬
portion to the satisfaction of these desires.
The social sciences, and through them the pop¬
ular consciousness, are dominated by this
desire-satisfaction model of value.
But its dominance is now, fortunately,
weakening. The theory is poor. One cannot
equate what makes a person's life good with
what satisfies that person's desires. It is possi¬
ble in fact, all too common for a person's
desires to be satisfied and the person be no
better off. For example, I may desire revenge on
someone indeed it may be the strongest
desire in my life yet find that when I have it
I am no better off, even possibly worse off.
An instrumentforgood
Nothing becomes valuable just by being
desired. Some things in life just are valuable
and others not. That is a strong claim, and a
much disputed one in philosophy, but it
seems to me right. I think that, with experi¬
ence, we can compile a list of the valuable
things in life the things that may not make
absolutely any life better (people are too var¬
ious for that) but that make normal human
lives better. My list would contain at least
these unsurprising things: enjoyment, deep
personal relations, accomplishing something
in the course of one's life, understanding cer¬
tain basic metaphysical and moral matters,
autonomy, and liberty.
Consumerism is not just weak in theory. It
does not work out happily in practice either.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
One all too common feature of the life of a
modern consumer is that one set of desires is
satisfied only to be succeeded by a new set,
with no advance in quality of life. These con-
sumerist desires often form a treadmill. One
runs but makes no real advance. When that
happens, it is clear that one has lost sight of
values. What arc really valuable are the things
on the list that I just mentioned. And other
things are valuable, valuable in a secondary,
instrumental way, if they lead to the values
on the list.
This, it seems to me, is where frugality
comes in. It is valuable if, and only if, a frugal
style of life is generally conducive to some of
B the UNESCO Courier January 1998
Above, Virgil meditating on
his poem TheAeneid, flanked
by the muses Clio and
Melpomene. A Roman mosaic
from Tunisia (3rd century
B.C).
the values on the list. There is much to be said
for that. A frugal life avoids the more value-
destroying forms of consumerism. A frugal
life tends to be a simple life, and, though sim¬
plicity in life is not guaranteed to put one in
touch with real values, it substantially increases
the chances that one will be. Many of us, fro m
time to time, have had the experience of living
more simply than we usually do and finding
ourselves, as a result, more in harmony with
what matters in life. Of course, we return to
our everyday life and lose this precious insight.
That is another reason why a frugal life-style
can be valuable. One's style of life not only
can embody values; it can also be the best way
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
to open one's eyes to values that one would
otherwise be blind to.
That is to say that frugality can, in this
instrumental way, be a personal good. It can
also be a community good. A frugal commu¬
nity can save and invest for a better future.
Frugality can also be a global good indeed, a
little more frugality may be necessary simply
to avoid global disaster. We consume fossil
fuels without serious constraint. We justify
ourselves with the thought that advancing
technology will be sure to come up with sub¬
stitutes for them. But just as good? Without
undesirable side-effects? We do not really
know. And our consumerism pollutes the
atmosphere, producing global warming. We
certainly do not know all the consequences
in store for us from that.
But I must not end with praise of frugality.
My life is better for my living simply on holi¬
days, consuming much less than I normally do.
But then I live in the prosperous part of the
world. I choose simplicity. But millions of peo¬
ple are forced to consume sparingly. They are
destitute. Their lives are not better for it. The big
killer in the world is not war or periodic famine.
It is something undramatic and unreported:
chronic malnutrition. Chronic hunger, some
claim, kills eighteen to twenty million people
annually, which is over twice the number that
died annually in the Second World War. Their
sparing consumption is nothing but evil.
"A frugal life tends to be a
simple life and increases one's
chances of being in touch with
real values." Right, a woman
writing. (Detail from an
Iranian fresco,16th-17th
centuries).
the unesco Courier ianuary 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Posterity has seen you as a pleasure-seeker and
your philosophy as pure hedonismthe opposite of
the truth, since your whole philosophy of pleasure
revolves around the idea of moderation. But what is
it based on?
Epicurus: Firstly, on the idea that pleasure is
the beginning and end of a happy life. We seek
pleasure only when we are suffering as a result
of the absence of pleasure, and when wc are
not suffering, it is of no concern to us. Sec¬
ondly, on an ordering of our desires: some
are necessary, others merely natural, and yet
others vain. By necessary desires we mean those
that relieve some pain, like the desire to drink
when we are thirsty; by natural but not nec¬
essary desires, we mean those that simply
diversify our pleasures without relieving
pain like the desire to drink good wine.
Among vain desires is the desire to offer
wreathes or erect statues.
Desires which, if unfulfilled, do not cause
pain are not necessary. They involve an appetite
that may easily be restrained whenever it is
hard to satisfy, or when it is harmful. Nat¬
ural desires whose non-fulfillment does not
Plain living
and high thinking
AN IMAGINARY INTERVIEW WITH
THE GREEK PHILOSOPHER EPICURUS
A bust of the Greek
philosopher Epicurus
(341-270 B.C.) from
Herculanum (Italy,
3rd century B.C.)
cause pain and which take the form of a violent
appetite are desires formed by an empty mind.
Such pleasure as they bring comes not from
them but from our vanity.
In what forms of behaviour is this ethic
expressed in daily life?
Epicurus: The simplest of dishes give as much
pleasure as a groaning board when the suffer¬
ing caused by want is absent. B read and water
afford the keenest of pleasures to those long
deprived of them. Leading a simple, modest
life is thus a good way to stay healthy, and
moreover enables a man to face up stout-heart¬
edly to the tasks that life imposes and to bet¬
ter appreciate occasional high living, and for¬
tifies him against the fickleness of fortune.
Hence, when we say that pleasure is the
supreme good, we are not speaking of the plea¬
sures of the debauchee, nor of sensual aban¬
don, as is claimed by certain ignorant persons
who take issue with us and misrepresent our
thinking. We are speaking of the absence of
physical suffering and of moral disquiet; for
neither drunken revelry nor continual feasting,
nor the enjoyment to be had from consorting
with catamites and women, nor yet that deriv¬
ing from tables heavy laden with fish and
meats, none of these afford a happy life, but
reasonable and sober habits, reason ever seek¬
ing after legitimate causes of election or aver¬
sion and rejecting any opinions that might
greatly trouble the soul.
The principle underlying all this, and at
the same time its greatest benefit, is prudence.
It must be adjudged superior to philosophy
itself, since it is the source of all the virtues,
which teach us that happiness cannot be
attained without prudence, honesty and jus¬
tice, and that these things cannot be obtained
without pleasure. Indeed, the virtues origi¬
nate from a happy life, which in turn is insep¬
arable from the virtues.
Adapted from Peri biân dogmatôn km
apophthegmatôn ton en philosophia eudokimêsantôn
("Lives, teachings and sayings of famous
philosophers") by Diogenes Laertius
THE UNESCO ÇpURI ER JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Three exceptional figures
BY ADAM ROBERTS
Frugality as a moral and
political protest against
the established order
Epictetus
(50-125 A.D.)
I Frugality implies care or sparingness in the use or supply of
food and other resources. The first "frugal" people were
those who lived by gathering fruit (fruges in Latin), and were des¬
ignated as frugal by the Romans, whose life has also been described
as "a frugal thing, sparing in food, temperate in drink, modest in
clothing, cleanly in habit." I would suggest that a frugal person is
one who is able to make informed decisions concerning his or her
use of resources, and does so believing that moderate consumption
allows other pleasures or benefits to be enjoyed.
The lifestyles of frugal individuals illustrate how the idea of "fru¬
gality" differs from others such as meanness or prudence. If frugal¬
ity is to do with making rational choices about consumption and how
to live one's life, frugal persons must have the opportunity not to be
frugal and yet choose to be this way. To adopt a frugal way of life is to
adopt an ethical, if not a political, position. Here are some examples:
Stoicism was prominent between 300
B.C. and 1 80 A.D., as a philosophy
and a guide to right conduct. Roman
Stoics were interested, almost exclu¬
sively, in ethical and political issues of
concern to all people, not only the
privileged few. Four beliefs characterize
the Stoics' view of the world: that all
people are radically equal and part of
the natural universe; that there are nat¬
ural laws; that a person should live in
perfect conformity with nature; and
that fate is determined. The text
Encheiridion contains Epictetus'
thoughts, many of which reflect his
attitude towards consumption and
frugality. Here is his advice to a young
man sitting down to a great feast: "But
if when things are set in front of you,
you do not take them but despise
them, then you will not only share a
banquet with the gods but also be a
ruler along with them." Here is a sign
that frugality is a political action.
Choosing to control, strictly, how
you consume is a controversial act.
Epictetus warned about this too, and
discouraged his followers from show¬
ing off: "When you have become
adapted to living cheaply as far as your
body is concerned, do not make a
show of it, and if you drink water do
not say at every opening that you
drink water. If you wish to train your¬
self to hardship, do it for yourself and
not for those outside." D
THE UNESCO lOURIER |ANUARY 1998
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Henry David
Thoreau
(1817-1862)
A young, Harvard-educated Ameri¬
can, Henry Thoreau chose in 1845
to live alone for two years in a wooden
forest hut not far from Concord
(Massachusetts). While his university
contemporaries were away making
small fortunes, trading and dealing,
Thoreau built his hut using a few hand
tools and some old planks, planted
beans and listened to the water ripple in
Waiden pond. Ridding himself of the
trappings of a "civilized life" and try¬
ing to live sclf-sufficicntly, he was
repeating the experience of the early
American settlers. The difference was
that he wrote about it, and celebrated
the virtues of a simple life. "The ancient
philosophers, Chinese, Hindoo, Per¬
sian and Greek, were a class than which
none has been poorer in outward
riches, none so rich inward," he
enthused, hoping to emulate them in
both respects. His book Waiden (1854)
is a manifesto against modern indus
trial life and an account of the two
years when he drank water from his
pond, had a diet of pulses and pos¬
sessed a minimum of objects. He wrote
that he would rather "sit on a pump¬
kin and have it all to myself, than be
crowded on a velvet cushion." In his
hut there were only three chairs: one
for solitude, two for friendship and
three for society.
He did all this by choice, aware that
he had an option to return from such
a life to a more "comfortable" one, but
confident that "the so-called comforts
of life arc . . . positive hindrances to the
elevation of mankind." However,
Thoreau eventually chose to opt out of
his life-style, and after two years he
returned from the woods to write and
publish his book. But because of his
experience he felt he had become a wiser
observer of human life "from the van¬
tage point of what we should call vol¬
untary poverty."
Mahatma Gandhi
(1869-1948)
y
s
¿The Great Soul" Gandhi is a pow-
I crful example of a man who used
issues of frugality and poverty in his
philosophy, politics and private life.
In 1888, when he moved from India
to Britain, he joined the London Veg¬
etarian Society. There he met George
Bernard Shaw and the travelling lec¬
turer and socialist Edward Carpenter,
who was then known as the "British
Thoreau". At that time he read the
Bbagavadgita, which would become
his "spiritual dictionary", and became
fascinated by two Sanskrit words in
particular, aparigraha (non-posses¬
sion) and samabhava (equability).
These influences led Gandhi to have an
"irresistible attraction to a life of sim¬
plicity, manual labour and austerity",
and the belief that man has to jettison
the material goods that cramp the life
of the spirit.
Ever since St. Francis of Assisi
sought a life of poverty, chastity and
humility, those who have preached such
values have been seen as dangerous by
authorities. Thus, when Gandhi moved
to South Africa and set up as a farmer
near Durban, where he and his friends
could live a simple life by the sweat of
their brow, he took the first step
towards becoming a controversial polit¬
ical activist. Gilbert Murray later
warned, about Gandhi, that "Persons in
power should be very careful how they
deal with a man who cares nothing for
sensual pleasure, nothing for riches,
nothing for comfort or praise."
Six years later, Gandhi moved nearer
to Johannesburg, and set up another
farm, which he named Tolstoy, after
the great Russian writer with whom
he corresponded. Soon he began his
political career, campaigning against
racial laws in South Africa and the
removal of voting rights from
"coloured" voters. Back in India, he
took frugality to its extreme, by con¬
ducting fasts for political ends (he also
fasted to "stir the conscience and
remove mental sluggishness"). In 1947
he fasted in an attempt to stop riot¬
ing between Hindu and Muslim com¬
munities in Calcutta. Four months
later, in Delhi, such a fast brought
about another communal truce.
16 D^URITHE UNESCO V^pumtR JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
From zero
towards one
INTERVIEW WITH SHIOUN MICHIKO NAKASATO
s,
Are the drawings shown here inspired by
calligraphy, like most of your works?
Michiko Nakasato: Yes. In calligraphy you try
to express yourself simply with lines and dots
using two colours, black and white. White
signifies space, which changes its features
according to what you write on the sheet. It
could be spring or autumn, for example,
depending on what the artist wants. When
you make the first stroke on a white sheet of
paper, you should imagine doing it on the
ocean. This first stroke is very important. You
are making a mark on a vast space where there
is nothing, and with this stroke the whole
space becomes alive too. I thought of this when
I did these drawings.
What does the word 'frugality' signify to you?
M. N.: I associate the notion of frugality with
the presence of a sti'ong individuality. It is not
something imposed by others. It is a deter¬
mination to return to a life in which there arc
only essential elements. Of course these ele¬
ments differ from one person to another. Each
person's choice must be respected.
What do you mean by the title 'From zero
towards one'?
THE UNESCO lOURIER |A\UARY 1998
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
la lb le
M. N.: I have always looked upon the number
one as something extraordinary. Zero is the
state where there is nothing. With the arrival of
one, there is a birth. The distance between zero
and one is not measurable. One is also differ¬
ent from other numbers in the sense that it is
the only number we can call single; all the oth¬
ers (except for 0) are plural. In today's world
there is too much esteem for quantity and a
neglect of the individual.
Could you explain the drawings to us?
M. N.: In the first set there is nothing at first.
Then a stroke appears, and suddenly the space
becomes alive. Then a second stroke arrives.
This time there is an encounter. The notion
of distance is created and the two strokes com¬
municate with each other.
The process in the second set is similar, but
the impression it gives is very different. The
first stroke is powerful, and as the second
stroke crosses the first, there is a sort of shock.
The communication here is more violent; you
feel a vibration in the space.
In the last set, another type of space is cre¬
ated. There is tranquillity. Even when the second
one touches the first and new spaces are created
here and there, the atmosphere remains calm.
I am not trying to say here what is right or
wrong. I am just trying to show how space
can be influenced by the movement of an indi¬
vidual. To me one plus one is not two, it is an
encounter of one individual with another.
-
Interview by IVIiki Nozawa 2b
18
THE UNESCO lOURIER JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
I
I
I
3a
I
í
/
3b
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Waste not, want not
BYHISANORI ISOMUR
,*&
In today's consumer society traditional
Japanese values based on moderation
are more relevant than ever
LTheJapanese have never sought to tame
nature; they have endeavoured to bring
nature closer to them and to live in symbio¬
sis with it. The Japanese garden, for example,
which is a re-creation of nature, is entirely
based on the principle oishakkei (literally, a
"borrowing of landscape"), whereby a real fea¬
ture of the landscape is introduced into an
artificial setting, and a bonsai may be regarded
as an artificial, miniaturized symbol standing
for nature in its entirety.
In the formal gardens of Western coun¬
tries, the artistic conception is human-cen¬
tred. People cut and prune trees into sym¬
metrical shapes and build fountains whose
jets present a reverse image of waterfalls, and
statues are erected and arranged for ornamen¬
tal effect. Japanese gardens, on the other hand,
seem at first sight merely to be a downscaled
version of nature, and the signs of human
handiwork are unobtrusive, if not invisible.
A 'floating' life
in a 'floating' world
For the Japanese, nature and the world are syn¬
onymous. Over the centuries, they have
accordingly developed a way of life based on
moderation and respect for everyday objects.
But Japan is today a consumer society, and
the Japanese have become very materialistic.
Contrary to a common misconception,
Japan was already an economic power in the
sixteenth century, and its standard of living
may well have been even higher then than it is
now. At the time of the Ashikaga shogunate
(the Muromachi period, 1337-1573), the coun¬
try was very prosperous, as may be judged
20 d(oiTHE UNESCO lOURIER (ANUARÏ 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
"The tea ceremony is a
sequence of ritual gestures
and a moment of harmony
encompassing the world in its
entirety." Left, a photo of the
tea ceremony taken in the late
19th century.
from the splendour of the temples of that
period, a prime example being the Kinkaku-ji,
or Golden Pavilion, in Kyoto. However the
influence of Buddhism, Zen Buddhism in par¬
ticular, produced a reaction against such osten¬
tation and a "renaissance" of aesthetic and
moral criteria, a return to a tradition that
emphasized simplicity, sobriety and purity
of form, as typified in architecture by the
shôin style in sixteenth-century architecture.
This aesthetic is reflected inJapanese classical
literature. The author of the Heike monogatari
("The Tale of the Heike", second half of the
twelfth century), for example, considers all for¬
tune to be fleeting and all prosperity to be
doomed sooner or later to disappear. The com¬
bined influence of Buddhist culture and the
hard living conditions caused by a rugged climate
have led the Japanese to regard life on earth as a
"floating" life, constantly changing and finally
vanishing. The term ukiyo means both "float¬
ing world" and "world of privation".
For the Japanese, the ideal of beauty is to
be found in communion with nature. The tea
ceremony, an art that proceeds from the zen
aesthetic, is not only a sequence of ritual ges¬
tures but a moment of harmony encompass¬
ing the world in its entirety. It was codified in
the sixteenth century by Sen no Rikyû, who
also created the wabi sabi aesthetic beauty
shorn of all ostentation that charms by its
simplicity underpinned by the Buddhist
teaching that plenty cannot endure and is not
to be found in immoderation. What should be
respected is the transience of things.
A tradition ofmoderation
Respect for all things is thus a traditional atti¬
tude in Japan. There arc some colloquial expres¬
sions, mottainai for instance, that express the
chary national attitude to any kind of waste.
Older people can remember saving water all
their lives, though water is plentiful every¬
where in Japan. There is a single bathtub for
each household, and people use it in the
evenings after washing outdoors. But habits
are changing and Japanese girls who used to
wash their hair in the morning (asa-shan) now
shampoo it again in the evening (yoru-shan).
Grandparents also used to tell their grand¬
children not to leave so much as a single grain
of rice in their bowls, an attitude that was in
fact prevalent in all countries before waste was
urged upon us by the consumer society. The
Japanese have an insulting term for someone
who wastes things monogoroshi, "killer of
objects". Anyone to whom it is applied is a
kind of social outcast since, according to an
idea whose roots go back to animism, even
inert objects have a soul.
On a more down-to-earth level, we learn
from sixteenth- and seventeenth-century
archives that the reason why there were so few
"Moderation was prevalent
before waste was urged upon
us by the consumer society."
Right, a car dump in Japan.
. I
THE UNESCO lOURIER [ANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
waste-bins in Japanese cities was that people
then made a point of using every object as
long as possible.
"In Japan Zen Buddhism
produced a return to a
tradition that emphasized
simplicity, sobriety and purity
of form." Above, a zen garden
in Kyoto (Japan).
"A bonsai may be regarded as
a miniaturized symbol of
nature. The traditional way of
life in Japan, in communion
with nature, was founded on
moderation and respect for
Changing times, changing ways
Since the 1950s, Japan has modelled itself on
the United States, a land of plenty where to be
frugal is a vice and to consume a virtue. This
trend, which is affecting more and more coun¬
tries, inevitably raises problems. If a country
like China, for example, were to indulge in everyday objects." A dwarf
unrestrained mass consumption, the earth's tree raised in a Pot <below>-
., 1-11 the bonsai typifies the
resources would very likely soon run out. Japanese ¡deal of the garden
Twenty years ago I bought a German car. It as a re-creation of nature,
has so far done 280,000 km and I am still using
it, to the derisive amusement of some of my
friends, most of whom change cars every other
year. The dynamism of the Japanese economy
is fuelled by such behaviour patterns on the
part of consumers. In fact, the law itself encour¬
ages people not to hang on too long to the
same material goods. Motor vehicles, for exam¬
ple, have to undergo a thorough roadworthi¬
ness test after seven years, and an annual test
thereafter. The test costs the equivalent of about
$900, and it costs about $1,100 to send a vehi¬
cle to the scrapyard an incentive on the part of
the authorities to sell as soon as possible.
Since the earth's resources are limited, it is
essential that our ways of life should change,
that we find a new "global way of life". In a
22
the UNESCO Courier ianuary 1998
White Paper on the life of the nation, the
Japanese Government has advocated a return to
tradition, an idea summed up in the expression
"progress in tradition". With modern tech¬
nology it is possible to conserve energy and
protect the environment while at the same
time maintaining a growth rate conducive to
the raising of living standards. We, the con¬
sumer countries, should therefore work
together to find a middle way that encourages
neither American-style waste nor withdrawal
into the past.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
An economy of sharing
BY MARIE ROUE
There is no place
for selfish
individualism in
nomadic hunter-
gatherer societies
Bushmen in the Kalahari
Desert (Botswana).
| There are two radically different ways
I for members of a society to satisfy all
their needs: by producing a lot, as in Western
societies, or by not wanting a lot, as in those
the American anthropologist Marshall Sahlins
has called "Zen" societies. The "Zen" way cho¬
sen by hunter-gatherer societies is to stop pro¬
ducing food as soon as they consider that the
quantity in hand has reached a level sufficient
for their needs.
It has been shown, and statistically con¬
firmed, that, contrary to a widespread mis¬
conception, population groups who live by
hunting, fishing and gathering do not live in
utter privation, nor are they constantly in
search of permanently inadequate food. On
the contrary, they may be said to have created
"the first affluent society", spending only a
few hours a day on meeting their material
needs and keeping the rest of their time free for
recreational and social activities. It is only
observers who are unaware of these people's
cultural values who find their few plain pos
sessions so inadequate. Nomads, for instance,
set particular store by light, portable objects,
but this does not make them poor. One
observer has testified that "their extremely
limited material possessions relieve them of
all cares with regard to daily necessities and
permit them to enjoy life."
Sharing and solidarity
However, not all hunter-gatherers live in an
earthly paradise where they need only to stoop
to pick fruit and vegetables and where game
animals give themselves up voluntarily. There are
some groups or families within these societies
who can never manage, or can manage only at
certain times, to meet all their needs, while any
group is bound at times to include individuals
who are too sick, too young or too old to take
part in productive activities, and disaster can
sometimes befall the harvest or the hunt. It is
in such circumstances that the sharing of
resources becomes especially important.
What is the point of sharing? Some
23
THE UNESCO ÇîURIIER JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Inuits hunting for seal in
Greenland.
observers claim that it fulfils the same func¬
tion that of risk limitation in "traditional"
societies as insurance policies do in Western
societies. By sharing a surplus that in any case
could not be consumed in the immediate
future, individuals or families are ensuring
that other members of the group will do the
same for them when the time comes. Other
observers, however, are not entirely satisfied
with this materialist explanation, since it pre¬
supposes an egalitarian, turn-and-turn-about
system, when in fact that is far from being
the case, and it is rare for those who are never
on the giving end to be excluded from the
benefits of sharing. Why, in that case, do the
Every summer the Cree Indians
of Chisasibi (Quebec, Canada)
gather on the site of their
former village. Below, meals
are prepared jointly and
served to everyone present.
ablest hunters who, as everyone knows, pro¬
duce more than they can consume, continue to
hunt large animals when nearly all the meat
will be consumed by people other than their
own kith and kin? For prestige and the atten¬
dant social advantages, to qualify as a hus¬
band, a son-in-law, a partner in some under¬
taking or simply an envied neighbour these
are some of the possible reasons.
One good turn
deserves another
Beyond these reasons of self-interest, how¬
ever, underlying the good hunters' generosity
is a whole outlook that is intolerant of selfish
individualism. In the past, Western mission¬
aries and travellers often misinterpreted atti¬
tudes quite unlike those that prevailed in the
villages where they themselves grew up. Seeing
how Eskimos and Bushmen feasted when
food was abundant, so that sometimes there
was nothing left over for lean times to come,
they reproached them for their lack of fore¬
sight and their gluttony. But in fact feasting is
another way of redistributing to the com¬
munity as a whole the foodstuffs brought
back by its more fortunate members, thus
strengthening the social fabric.
There arc also rules of sharing whereby
"one good turn deserves another" through¬
out life, as with the Arviligjuarmiut Inuits
when they share a seal they have killed as a
team working together. Each member of the
E unesco Rubier January 199s
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
team always receives the same part of the beast
and indeed takes his name from it "my
shoulder", "my head", and so on.
Some of the peoples living in the Arctic
and sub-Arctic regions believe that the ani¬
mals caught by a hunter have given themselves
to him, so it is not surprising, for example,
that among the Cree Indians of Quebec the
hunter's generosity to his companions in the
hunt should match that of his quarry. If the
favour was not returned, the cycle would be
broken and the animals would not let them¬
selves be caught. Similarly, when a feast is given
everything must go, a custom that astonished
those who first observed the Algonquins' way
of life and is still maintained today. When the
whole village visitors included is invited
to a feast, guests will find a plastic bag by the
side of their plates, an invitation to them to
take away anything left over when they have
eaten enough, to be shared with those who
could not be present.
Many peoples the Mbuti of the former
Zaire, the Canadian Cree and Inuit, the Batck
of Malaysia and the Nayaka of southern India,
to name but a few are ignorant of the West¬
ern dichotomy between nature and nurture. In
many cases, they see their relationship with
the natural world of animals, plants and places
A group of Danis, a people
living in Bauern Valley, western
New Guinea (Irian Jaya),
prepare a meal. Their economy
is based on farming, food-
gathering in the forest, fishing
and hunting.
from which they receive gifts as a genuine
child-parent relationship. They therefore
regard sharing nature giving to humans or
humans giving to one another as an essential
part of their lives, expressing an outlook on
the world that could be described, in Nurit
Bird-David's words, as a "cosmic economy
of sharing".
A Bedouin encampment
In Iraq.
THE UNESCO lOURIER JANUARY 1998
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Making a little
go a long way
BY BABACAR SALL
Needy African societies governed by an ethic
of sparing, caring and sharing
Pupils at an open-air school in
Senegal work in the shade of a
tree.
In some parts of Africa frugality is a
quality that is central to social and eco¬
nomic life, partly because poverty has become
so taken for granted in recent years. The Wolof
language has an expression for it: doy lu, which
may be translated as self-sufficiency.
Society is built around the idea of potential
scarcity, and sharing and solidarity are highly
regarded. Seeking personal profit is frowned
on. Building up your own stock of something
means taking away from the group a resource
which it could otherwise use. This has given
rise to an ethic of parsimony and sharing.
Drinking, eating, spending and having a
good time should be done on the basis of
"keep nothing for yourself which could be
useful to someone else", to quote a Wolof
saying. Keeping a share of something for some¬
one else is seen as a way to avoid excess.
Frugality permeates the daily life of Sahe-
lian nomads such as the Peul even in a situation
of abundance. Housing is spartan, light and
made of easy-to-dismantle vegetable matter.
The basic diet consists of dairy products.
Above all, water is using very sparingly.
Another Wolof proverb "tomorrow isn't
today's guest, but we must put something aside
for it" shows how far saving, forced on peo¬
ple by an unpredictable food supply, is rooted
in people's mentalities. Excessive consumption
upsets the future sharing of a product. Most
Senegalese believe God does not give things but
entrusts them to a person's care. In return, peo¬
ple carefully look after what does not belong to
them but which they are given to share.
26
THE UNESCO lOURIER JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
In Mall, a Dogon farmer
sprinkles his field with water
during the dry season. Such sharing, essential when there is per¬
petual scarcity, governs all social activities
work, income, joy and unhappiness. But this
modern-day harmony only works because of
its ties to a traditional solidarity.
A home-grown
developmentproject
Drought in the 1970s and the widespread
poverty it brought helped to intensify this
frugality in social and official relationships.
Even development projects based themselves
on low-cost methods of organization and
approaches.
The Malian village of Sanankoroba, which
is usually held up as an economic develop¬
ment success story, shows how a mixture of
local organization and modern equipment can
have good and lasting results.
The villagers launched a development pro¬
ject along their own lines in 1984 with the
help of a twinning agreement with the Quebec
town of St. Elizabeth. Instead of foreigners
taking the decisions, the villagers used their
own methods. Public meetings were held and
the supreme tribal authority, the council of
elders, was consulted. The council decided to
extend the decision-making process to other
age-groups, which served as links to different
THE UNESCO COURIER JANUARY 1998 U»7
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
tribes and to associations of women, young
people and professionals. The council then
gave its opinion and decided how the project
should be carried out.
The 24-member committee that was set up
contained two new elements it had five
women on it and a local farmer as its chairman,
despite the participation of people who had
been trained in developed countries. This break
with the classic pattern of development aid
organization shows a determination to adapt to
local physical conditions. Also, rather than tak¬
ing the name given to the project by the Que-
beckers "Des mains pour demain," or "Hands
for the Future" the villagers chose a name
closer to their way of thinking: Benkadi, or
"good understanding". This name stressed that
the project's goal is unity and social cohesion
rather than transformation and planning, as A technical adviser (right) and
.. , , . , a villager collaborate on a
conveyed by the Canadians name. development project in a rice-
paddy on Morfil island
(Senegal).
So there were two ways of looking at the
project. The Western approach was to shape
the future by technical mastery of time and
space, based on the belief that agricultural
problems are essentially technical and can be
solved by technical means. The African
approach did not systematically take on board
such a concept, since it regards the future as
God's responsibility, so that the relationship
between technical power and divine power
requires careful handling.
These different ways of thinking did not
prevent fruitful co-operation. The main thing
for the villagers of Sanankoroba was to express
their own values in a productive manner with
foreign help, and they managed to do that very-
well. The project led to better integration of
several usually dependent social categories such
as young people, women and lower classes. It
also checked emigration to the capital, Bamako,
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A meeting at a micro finance
bank for the needy in a
Gambian village.
and the newly-irrigated fields and bountiful
orchards even lured many back to the village.
Street schools
Another example, this time involving educa¬
tion, shows that consumption of knowledge,
like consumption of anything else, requires
that the product offered be carefully chosen
and adapted to immediate needs.
In Senegal, non-attendance at school, which
mostly affects country areas, has spread to the
towns, with nearly 40 per cent of school-age
children not attending. A system set up by
the government to tackle the problem in pri¬
mary schools in poor areas a half-day of
lessons daily, with some children coming in
the morning and others in the afternoon
has proved inadequate.
The situation has given rise to the creation of
"street schools", mostly in Dakar, with impro¬
vised classes in the street or in the yard of a house
and plain wooden benches. The many children
who attend these schools show how popular
they are, especially as the fees are modest. Among
the subjects taught are human rights, theatre,
Arab language and environmental education.
One basic difference from the state schools is
that classes are usually in the children's mother
tongue rather than French. Another is that the
"street schools" meet the general demand for
children to be taught not in a selective way but
by giving them the basic knowledge to cope
with the society they live in.
The same kind of priorities, springing
from constant scarcity and structural ineffi¬
ciency, apply in the economic and financial
sphere. This has led to rival mail distribution
networks and even banking services mainly
between African states and European coun¬
tries with immigrant populations, like France.
They are run on non-capitalist principles such
as trust and personal and blood relationships.
The "banks for the poor" are another example
of adapting a consumer-oriented capitalist sys¬
tem to local conditions where modest con¬
sumption patterns are the rule.1
All these initiatives, carried out in condi¬
tions of scarcity, poverty and sometimes suffi¬
ciency but never abundance, show that even
needy people can build community projects
with what they have. In this way the link-up
between frugality, economy and society leads
to a new work ethic and gives an example to the
world at a time of increasing breakdown of social
ties and environmental degradation. Perhaps the
ball is now in the rich countries' court	
1 Sec the Unesco Courier, January 1997,
Microfinance helping the poor to help themselves.
Editor
THE UNESCO lOURIER |ANUARY 1998
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
\
'", Pedal power
s i
BY BENOIT LAMBERT
***&>&^ .^-
.... ,i
A clean form of
transport rides
into town
Top, The New Invented Sociable
or The Lover and His Hobby. An
English engraving made in
1819.
Doubts are now being raised about the
aura almost of majesty that sur¬
rounds motor vehicles, which, despite being
too noisy and too big and guzzling too much
energy, have long been regarded as symbols of
national economic success and individual sta¬
tus. Since the 1992 Rio Conference and the
cries of alarm that went up from the scientific
community about threats to the stability of
the earth's ecosystem, transport policies and
especially policies in regard to the car have been
under fire from all sides.
Bicycles have seized this opportunity to
go on to the offensive. Fifty times lighter than
cars, they have plenty going for them. They are
non-polluting, nifty, silent and healthy. The
number of cars in circulation worldwide will
reach the billion mark in twenty-five years or
even less, and this at a time of climate change.
A certain measure of self-restraint in terms of
individual mobility is thus an essential pre¬
caution to be taken to preserve the environ¬
ment, and in fact more and more city-dwellers
want to live in conditions of less pollution
and stress. Cycles, especially when taken in
conjunction with public transport, seem to
provide an answer to this new-found aspira¬
tion to win back the streets and public places
from colonization by the car.
In Amsterdam in March 1994, the Euro¬
pean Union set up a network of car-free cities,
to which sixty towns, including Aosta,
Athens, Barcelona, Bremen, Granada, Gronin¬
gen, Lisbon, Nantes, Reykjavik and Stras¬
bourg, now belong. The main aims are to pro¬
mote policies for sustainable development,
encourage a gradual reduction in the use of
private cars in towns, and serve as an interna¬
tional forum for the pooling of experience in
this field.
The best results achieved so far have been in
Copenhagen, where bicycles are regarded as a
means of transport in the full sense of the
term, and account for 33 per cent of jour¬
neys a share equal to that of public trans¬
port and private motor vehicles. Although,
admittedly, the local terrain lends itself to this
mode of locomotion, it should be pointed
out that the climate the wind in particular
is a considerable disincentive, which never¬
theless does nothing to discourage the towns¬
people. One of the reasons for the bike's
success is the fact that there is an almost unbro¬
ken network of cycle lanes along the streets
and the main thoroughfares. Since 1962, the
policy has been to reduce the number of park¬
ing spaces for cars, often to make way for cycle
lanes, with the result that motor traffic has
gone down by 10 per cent since 1970.
Cycles are small machines that have had a
big impact all over the world with people of
all ages, male and female, rich and poor. In
30 D^JUITHE UNESCO lOURIER JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
their quiet way they have helped to shape the
modern world. In the Western countries, at
the turn of this century workers were using
them to get to work, and in this way, while
themselves being an important industrial
product, they contributed to the process of
industrialization and to countries' economic
prosperity.
A breath offresh air
It was, moreover, thanks to the bicycle that a
wind of freedom blew through people's pat¬
terns of behaviour. Weekends in the country
began with the bicycle and, when youth hos¬
tels first appeared in the early 1930s, so did a
new form of tourism, the cycling holiday. The
New Woman on her bicycle became an emblem
of emancipation, so potent that when under¬
graduates at Cambridge (U.K.) protested in
1897 against the admission of women they
hanged a bicycling woman in effigy.
Pedal power is of great importance in the
developing countries, enabling doctors to get
around quickly in wartime in Nicaragua,
allowing foodstuffs to be moved from one
to another of the three markets in Riobamba,
Ecuador, heavy goods to be transported on
Cyclists in Copenhagen
(Denmark).
Stone carving from Pura
Maduwe Karang Temple (Bali)
shows a temple official on a
bicycle made of flowers.
tricycles in Hanoi (Viet Nam), fresh bread to
be distributed to 22,000 sales outlets by 800
tricycles in Bogotá (Colombia), and so on.
In Bogotá again, 100 km of streets are
closed to motor traffic on Sundays for recre¬
ational use by cyclists, and hundreds of thou¬
sands of people take advantage of these ciclovtas
THE UNESCO lOURIER JANUARY 1998
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
dominicales. In China, where there are over
400 million cycles nearly as many as there
are cars in the world! over 80 per cent of indi¬
vidual journeys are made this way.
Less caloriesper kilometre
For use in town, cycles compare very
favourably in many respects with other means
of transport.
Efficiency: the modern bike has the high¬
est ratio of distance covered to energy input of
any means of transport; at an average speed of
17 km an hour, a cyclist uses between three
and four times less energy per kilometre than
a pedestrian;
Resources: Marcia Lowe, of the World-
watch Institute in Washington, has calculated
that it takes a hundred times less raw material
and energy to make a cycle than it does to
make a car;
Health: a British Medical Association
report published in 1992 pointed out that
cycling is one of the simplest and most effec¬
tive ways of keeping fit;
Cost: the cost of creating a cycle track in
Britain is anything from 67 to 230 times less
per mile than that of building a road, and even
the most expensive bike will always be far
more affordable than a car.
Cycling to a healthier world
Some commentators state categorically that
sustainable development is not feasible without
multimodal mobility combining public trans¬
port and two-wheelers. The irony of the situ¬
ation is that just when the industrialized coun¬
tries are starting to realize the virtues of the
velocipede, some of the developing countries are
trying to clear them off the streets, believing
The modern bike:
a blend of hi-tech
and simplicity
The Lightning
P-38.
Advanced technologies can now
be integrated into bicycles in a
way that can revolutionize their
use. In 1994, a Japanese firm
launched a bike with a small electric
motor and two sensors which calculate the cyclist's effort and his or her
speed. A built-in microcomputer then works out the extra power to be supplied to
the pedal-wheel in order to maximize the rider's performance, e.g. when setting off,
on a gradient or with a head windinconveniences that put many people off as soon
as they are in the saddle.
The Dutch engineer Alan Lentz has developed another interesting innovation, a
solar-powered trailer. The prototype won first prize in the 1993 Dutch Solar Bike
Design Competition, which rewards the best suggestions for the combined use of
solar power and the bicycle. A solar panel connected to a battery is built into the lid
of the trailer and powers a small electric motor that drives the hub. The power
generated is enough to propel the loaded trailer and can even push the bike. For
campers, the battery can supply power for lights, radio, electric razor or any other
electrical apparatus.
An impressive range of increasingly practical accessories is now available.
Furthermore, the one-hour speed record held by the "horizontal" cycleso called
because the rider is in a lying position with his feet up in front of him and back
archedIs 77 kilometres, as against 55 kilometres for a conventional machine. The
horizontal cycle was invented at the beginning of the century and broke a number of
speed records, but was banned from international competitions in 1934because it
was so efficient it enabled lower-rated riders to beat competitors riding conventional
machines! Fortunately, since the 1970s associations for the promotion of human-
powered vehicles in the United States and Europe have revived the horizontal bike.
The back support given by the seat increases the power of propulsion and makes
such bikes much more comfortable. B.L.
There are millions of cyclists In
China. Below, a typical Beijing
street scene.
their replacement by motorized vehicles to be
the outward and visible sign of modernization.
This begs the question as to what "moder¬
nity" means today. Shouldn't we be standing
up for the idea of "cyclomodernity", using
the bicycle to treat the planet's ills ? It has been
reckoned that by the year 2005, more than
half the world's population will be living in
towns and cities, and that by 2025 the num¬
ber of city-dwellers will have doubled to five
billion. At the same time, the worldwide pro¬
liferation of cars has resulted in the "auto¬
mobile phenomenon" becoming almost co¬
extensive with what Pierre Teilhard de Chardin
called the "human phenomenon". In these cir¬
cumstances, bikes come to symbolize a simple
life attuned to the limitations of our bio¬
sphere and responding to the new demands
from a growing number of city-dwellers for
a less motorized environment.
32
THE UNESCO J^pURIER JANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
FACT FILE
Youth finds use
for waste
In 1994 UNESCO's Division of Youth and Sports Activ¬
ities conducted a survey on youth, recycling and devel¬
opment involving 120 youth organizations worldwide
with members aged 25 or younger. Contrary to the
widely held belief that young people who have grown up
in a world bombarded with new products and advertis¬
ing are trapped in a consumer culture, the survey showed
that many young people in both industrialized and
developing countries are taking part in a range of inven¬
tive recycling schemes whose objectives include waste
reduction, environmental education, reconsideration of
current development patterns, job creation for young
people and the socially disadvantaged, and international
co-operation. Their common denominator is that they
all find a use for what is normally regarded as "waste".
The survey gave rise to a Unesco programme,
"Youth and Recycling for Sustainable Development",
which held a World Forum in Nagoya (Japan) from 7 to
12 March 1996 attended by young people from 14 coun¬
tries who swapped ideas and experiences. A number of
practical initiatives were described, including a recycling
programme by the Iumi Tugetha youth group ("You
Bicycle spare
parts sent from
France to Burkina
Faso.
During a field trip,
participants in the
World Forum on
Youth Recycling
for Sustainable
Development
(1996, Nagoya,
Japan) polish
rusty tools in a
recycling
workshop run by
young people in
Asahi-cho, Aichi
prefecture.
and Me Together" in pidgin) from Papua New Guinea
who recover non-ferrous scrap metal and process it for
export. Another project in Pakwach (Uganda) employs
youngsters to collect scrap metal and use it to make
hammers, chisels and other tools.
Other schemes arc based on North-South co-oper¬
ation. A group of young people in France are running a
"Bicycles for Africa" programme, whereby discarded
bicycles arc collected and shipped to a partner group in
Burkina Faso, where they are repaired and sold cheaply.
The German Association for the Promotion of Training
and Employment (GAB) collects and reconditions used
hospital equipment, household appliances and tools and
sends them to Africa and Eastern Europe. A joint Cana¬
dian-Filipino scheme called Race Against Waste orga¬
nizes a competition to make toys from waste in order to
raise awareness of environmental issues in hundreds of
schools in Canada and the Philippines.
The Nagoya Statement signed by participants at the
Forum, "Make Haste Against Waste" (see page 35), rec¬
ognizes the value of recycling initiatives taken by young
people all over the world and identifies some of the
obstacles they have encountered. It emphasizes that recy¬
cling is not an end in itself but a tool in the service of sus¬
tainable development, and calls on educators, NGOs,
the media, artists, consumer groups, businesses, gov¬
ernments and United Nations agencies to support recy¬
cling in policy and practice.
Results of the Forum include the development of the
international network of youth recycling groups, the
promotion of their activities in the media and the exten¬
sive distribution of the Forum Report. A quarterly
newsletter, YARN (Youth and Recycling Newsletter),
was started to serve as a link between the informal group
network. Many Forum participants have been commu¬
nicating with each other and new groups have been join¬
ing the network. Many new partners have received con¬
tainers filled with tools, sewing machines and bicycles.
Japan's Niwano Peace Foundation is awarding a grant
for research designed to set the activities of young recy-
clcrs into an ethical and historical context. A CD-Rom is
being produced to present some of the most innovative
recycling schemes to schoolchildren and young people.
These international initiatives offer training and
333 Quthe unesco Courier January iq98
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
employment opportunities to young people who are
outside the social and economic mainstream and, in the
name of sustainable development, present alternatives
to the "throw-away" society. In so doing they are ben¬
eficial to young people in both the developing world
and industrialized countries.
A second Forum to be held in Brazil sometime in
1998 will have the following agenda:
*" evaluation and discussion of progress made since the
first Forum;
*" presentation of research findings into recycling's eth¬
ical implications, followed by a debate;
extension of the youth-group network;
*" involvement of other sectors (media, private enter¬
prise) in the global recycling project;
*" the raising of awareness about the need for sustain¬
able development and redefinition of the North-South
relationship.
The Forum will be organized in close co-operation
with Brazilian institutions including the Ministry of
the Environment, municipalities, NGOs and universi¬
ties. Working groups will discuss specific themes and
try to come up with concrete proposals. An exhibition
of recycled items and materials will be open to the pub¬
lic, which will be invited to take part in presentations and
discussions as at the Nagoya Forum.
Since the Forum will be taking place in Brazil, venue
of the 1992 Earth Summit, the relationship of "Youth and
Recycling for Sustainable Development" to Agenda 21
will certainly be one of the meeting's major themes.
Miki Nozawa
Toys made from
recycled materials.
Right, a miniature
bicycle
(Mozambique).
Below, a tricycle
rickshaw and a
racing bike (Viet
Nam).
FOR FURTHER INFORMATION:
Division of Youth and Sports Activities
Unesco
1, rue Miollis
75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Tel:(33)(0)145 68 38 57
Fax: (33)(0)1 45 68 57 25
E-mail: m.nozawa@unesco.org
Internet address:
http://www.unesco.org/youth
PUBLICATIONS DISTRIBUTED FREE OF
CHARGE FROM THE ADDRESS AT LEFT:
*» Y.A.R.N. (Youth and Recycling
Newsletter) (also available in French)
** Final Report of the First World Forum
on Youth Recycling for Development,
Nagoya, 1996
»» Youth recycling - From Waste to
Development, Glyn Roberts, 1994
Project 2000+ and recycling
Since 1996, Project 2000+: Scientific and Technological Literacy for All, developed
by Unesco's Section for Science and Technology Education, has made recycling activ¬
ities one of its major components. Experimental projects have been launched in a num¬
ber of countries to find out how far this activity can help to develop scientific and tech¬
nological knowledge and skills, as well as reinforcing environmental awareness
among secondary school students.
These activities are being carried out by school science and technology clubs.
They give students the opportunity to learn more about the environment, broaden
their horizons and practise their scientific and technological knowledge and skills.
The students also organize periodical school "recycled objects and materials
fairs", where members of the local community can purchase recycled materi¬
als at very low prices.
FOR FURTHER INFORMATION
Contact Mr. Orlando Hall Rose
Section for Science and Technology Education
Education Sector
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Tel: (33)(0)1 45 68 56 26
Fax: (33)(0)145 6808 16
E-mail: c.thiounn@unesco.org
Recover, recycle, reuse,
repair...
Collect plastics, metals, glass and paper to make use of
the raw materials they contain.
Reuse or recycle old clothes. Unused medicines can be
used in parts of the world with fewer resources.
Reject unnecessary packaging when shopping. Take
cloth bags or baskets and reuse plastic bags.
Use second-hand and recycled products. Check the
ecological quality of recycled products.
Whenever possible, use products that can be reloaded
or refilled. Turn down discardable products.
Compost food remains. The result is valuable fertilizer
for crops or gardens.
34
THE UNESCO lOURIER I
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
THE NAGOYA STATEMENT
adopted at the conclusion of the first World Forum on
Youth Recycling for Development (1996)
(Excerpts)
Young people all over the world are tak¬
ing initiatives to recycle at the local,
national and international levels. In both
developed and developing countries, and
sometimes involving these countries in
innovative partnerships, these youth Ini¬
tiatives:
are genuinely useful, productive and
of direct value to people and the environ¬
ment;
« bring immediate economic returns
by provldlngjobs and increasing income,
particularly of young people; and by gen¬
erating useful products and resources;
mobilize young people with various
abilities, educate and develop both tech¬
nical and social skills that enhance con¬
viviality and young people's integration
into the community;
* promote partnerships in furtherance
of international co-operation for social jus¬
tice, equity and development;
are drawn from or in some cases actu¬
ally revive indigenous knowledge systems
and orient young people towards sustain¬
able practices and lifestyles	
In order to be holistic and effective, recy¬
cling should be:
economically viable, enhancing the
economic standing of those involved and
opening up the possibility of developing
local/domestic production, thereby reduc¬
ing imports.
promoting social justice by addressing
the disparities between developed and
developing countries;
* engendering values of stewardship,
community and responsible lifestyles;
using safe and appropriate technol¬
ogy and encouraging innovation;
showing gender, generational and cul¬
tural sensitivity by enhancing the partici¬
pation of disadvantaged and marginalized
groups in all stages of recycling	
We, the participants in this Forum,
commit ourselves to:
« strengthening our institutions and our
recycling for sustainable development
efforts with a view to achieving self-
reliance;
* continuing to communicate and co¬
operate with each other; sharing tech¬
nologies, models and information; and
evolving new forms of collaboration involv¬
ing developed and developing countries;
evolving, committing to and propa¬
gating a Code of Ethics on recycling for
sustainable development;
« Linking up with other sectors involved
in research and development;
« doing all these things in the convivial
spirit of "luml Tugetha" (the name in pid¬
gin of a Papua New Guinea youth recycling
scheme).
Abandoned bikes become 'feet of life'
In Japan many bicycles are abandoned, and local authorities have a hard time cop¬
ing with the problem.
A project to donate these bicycles to other countries has been launched by
MCCOBA (Municipal Co-ordinating Committee for Overseas Bicycle Assistance) and
JOICFP (Japanese Organization for International Co-operation in Family Planning
Inc.). The former, a consortium of 15 local authorities, supplies the bikes, while the
latter is in charge of accepting them in recipient countries.
Once collected by MCCOBA, the bicycles are recycled and either sold to local
residents or donated overseas. To date, 17,350 recycled bikes have been shipped
free of charge to 41 countries via JOICFP and other projects, with transportation
costs financed by local authorities.
JOICFP, which is engaged in village development activities in developing coun¬
tries, is the project co-ordinator. Recycled bikes are given to villagers who have
received training in family planning and health care. Bicycles are used as a means
of communication and to transport food in remote areas. In Tanzania they are
known as the "feet of life". An umbrella, a knapsack and boots are provided with
each bicycle for the rainy season.
In Mozambique farm and health workers
get around on mountain bikes.
Bicycles for Africa
In Burkina Faso, the bicycle is nicknamed "the iron horse" and is an
important means of transportation. In recent years, however, the
price of a new bicycle has soared 500 per cent, putting it on a par
with a rural family's annual income.
In France on the other hand bicycles are discarded by the thou¬
sands, in the Chambéry area aloneChambery is a sister city to
Ouahigouya in Burkina Faso1,000 bicycles are discarded every year.
Young people in Chambéry have taken to collecting them from tips, retail¬
ers and police stations and sending them to Ouahigouya, where they
are sold to local people for one-third of the price of a new bicycle.
In Burkina Faso the bicycles are dismantled, repaired and reassem¬
bled. This work ¡s performed by persons with physical disabilities,
unemployed persons and those on the margins of society. This pro¬
gramme has been useful in creating jobs and in fostering self-reliance.
More than 3,000 bicycles have been collected over the past few years.
Future goals include Improving the system for sorting bicycles in
France, increasing the qualifications of African workers and obtaining
cheaper spare parts.
FOR FURTHER INFORMATION CONTACT:
Mr. Nicolas Mercat
180, chemin des Ballons
73370 Le Bourget, France
Tel: (33)(0)4 79 25 39 29
Fax: (33)(0)4 79 69 05 57
Mr. Moussa Bologo
ECU BP 362,
Ouahigouya, Burkina Faso
Tel/Fax: 226 550 740
Water, energy,
paper and glass
The average person in an industrialized country uses nearly twice
as much water as someone in the developing world and nearly 10
times as much as someone in sub-Saharan Africa.
The average US or Canadian citizen uses about twice as
much commercial energy as a resident of the United Kingdom,
France or Germany, 10 times that of a Jordanian, 50 times that
of a Guatemalan, 100 times that of a Vietnamese and 500 times
that of a person living in Chad or Burkina Faso.
A person born in Finland uses over 27 times more printing and
writing paper than the average person in the developing world.
The Nordic countries recycle two-thirds of their glass bottles
and jars; North Americans recycle only about one-fourth of theirs.
the unesco Courier |amjaryi998
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
commentary Federico Mayor
Sharingan ethic
for the future
Let us cast our minds hack to the world situation as it was
in 1945. In that fateful year the North was in ruins and
a sombre post-war mood prevailed. In the South, the
struggle to achieve freedom from colonial domination
was already under way, and in many cases a pre-war
atmosphere reigned. The founders of UNESCO decided to
confront this civilization of weapons with the weapons of
civilization. They took inspiration from the radiantly sim¬
ple idea of constructing peace in the minds of men
through education, science, culture and the free flow of
ideas in short by communication.
In the prophetic words of the French poet Paul Valéry,
they intended to build a "league of minds" as well as a
League of Nations. At the same time they were deter¬
mined that this international forum should serve the eth¬
ical goals which the world community set for itself: peace,
the intellectual and moral solidarity of humanity and its
common prosperity, freedom and justice.
As the intellectual institution of the United Nations
system, UNESCO has been entrusted ever since its incep¬
tion with an ethical mission. In this capacity, it must con¬
demn wrongs, whatever their origin, wherever they occur
and whatever form they take. UNESCO must have the
courage to raise its voice and take action. It must not
allow itself to tolerate the intolerable. To my mind this mis¬
sion is today more timely and urgent than ever. UNESCO
can and must make its presence felt in the world by
the force of ideas and above all by setting an example.
In less than three years' time, the world will enter
the third millennium. It is now, when the twenty-first
century is already knocking on UNESCO's door that we
must think about the Organization's future shape. UNESCO
36 r
W THE UNESCO lOURIER JANUARY 1908
will become increasingly forward-looking, because the
Internet, the protection of the human genome, the increas¬
ing development of what Nestor Garcia Canclini has
called "hybrid cultures", the rapid emergence of "virtual
cultures", lifelong education for adults and the revolu¬
tion in the efficient use of environmental and energy
resources are all 21st-century issues.
Development is now in jeopardy. We cannot close our
eyes to poverty and indebtedness, exclusion and discrim¬
ination, non-stop degradation of the environment, exploita¬
tion, persecution and marginal ization affecting whole pop¬
ulations especially indigenous populations the scandal
of famine, illiteracy, intolerance, violence, war, social
instability and even after racial apartheid the threat
of social and urban apartheid, which is gradually under¬
mining the foundations of democracy. On no account
should wc bequeath to posterity this grievous legacy.
Can we accept the fact that almost one-third of the
population of the least developed countries die before the
age of forty or that 20 per cent of the inhabitants of the
planet share 1.1 per cent of world income? As Mr. James
Wolfensohn, the President of the World Bank, recently
pointed out, there can be no satisfactory economic devel¬
opment without parallel social development.
The answer to the challenge of poverty is contingent
upon sharing, which is to my mind the mainspring of
UNESCO's mission. The duty to share is but another form
of the duty of solidarity, that "intellectual and moral sol¬
idarity" of humanity which is the only possible basis for
a true and lasting peace.
We must share in time as well as in space. Our duty
is to think of future generations. What do we want to
pass on to our children? The prospect of a better future,
or chronic poverty? Opportunities for all, or hardship
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
for a quarter or even a third of humanity? A living envi- by half, ensure universal primary education, and give
ronmcnt, or a planet without a future? women an educational level equal to that of men." Mr.
An ethical approach to the future must recognize the Wally N'Dow, Secretary-General of the World City Sum-
vital responsibility of today's generations towards future mit, Habitat II, has said that "The resources exist to pro-
generations. It is now that we must lay the foundations of vide every man, woman and child on this earth with safe
this ethic if we wish to build the peaceful conditions nee- water and sanitation and a roof over their heads" for less
essary for development in the next century. At a time than $100 per person. It is through such investment in
when people all over the world are acting as though development and human security that arms will one day
they had rights over the people of tomorrow we are start- give way to the ballot box, and the force of reason will
ing to realize that wc arc compromising the full exercise finally be victorious over the logic of force,
of human rights by future generations. Hence the estab- "If the people begin to act, the leaders will follow." I
lishment of UNESCO's International Biocthies Committee. remember that sticker on the bumper of a ear in Atlanta,
Hence the Declaration on the Protection of the Human which reminded me that by joining forces and by creat-
Genome, the first universal standard-settinginstrument ing synergies we can change the world. That was the
in the field of living matter. Hence the Declaration on the message of Martin Luther King, Mahatma Gandhi, Mother
Responsibility of the Present Generations towards Future Teresa, and the founding fathers of the United Nations
Generations, which may, I believe, mark the beginning of and UNESCO. It was the message of all my predecessors as
a genuine worldwide awareness that could lead to prae- Director-General oÍ'Un'ESCO, and I am sure it will also be
tical initiatives. that of my successor. To
Genetics clearly procrastinate is to betray
involves ethical issues; the future by default,
less obvious are the ethi- UNESCO ITlUSt COndemil WfOligS, The participation of
cal dimensions of other , , , everyone and the responsi-
aspectsofthecommonher- whatever their origin, wherever bmty of citizcns arc thc
itage of humanity which we ft ^^ rf whatever fQm^ securest foundations of a
have the duty to preserve J J living luture based on trust
and pass on: the scientific {9^ ft must ^gyg ^g COll^ge tO aml th(! caPacity oí human
heritage (i.e. knowledge), beings to change, to build
the natural heritage, the fSlSe itS V0ÍCe dPCt take aCtlOfl. It their own lives and to fos-
cultural heritage, and ter the spirit of continuing
above all the axiological "lUSt ílOt allOW ltSelf tO tomate the intellectual, cultural and
heritage, by which I mean intnlorahlo biological development, the
the set of values, few in (lowing river that is our sub-
number, that in all cul- stance. Now is the time for
tures and in all ages illus- us to rephrase the Cartesian
trate the greatness of cogito for the citizen of the
human beings and the force of humanism. twenty-first century and say: "I am involved, therefore I
These values were slowly and painfully shaped, at a am."If I am not involved, I may count as a statistic and my
cost of struggle, suffering and sacrifice. They are part of vote may be counted at election time, but I do not really
a common past in which we are rooted and which enables count. This is why education is the only true democratic
us to see our way into the future. The great risk we run issue. As the International Commission on Education for the
is to forget the past. Without memory ethics would be a Twenty-First Century chaired by Mr. Jacques Delors has
disembodied force. Without the opportunity to compare shown us, education does not only mean learning to know,
it would be an arbitrary absolute. The values of human learning to do or learning to be; it also means learning to live
ethics are what has given us, and will give us, the together, and hence to build tomorrow's society,
strength to find unity in diversity. But above all we must dare to love. Today's biggest
A great deal can be done with slender means. Accord- deficit is not an economic deficit, hut a deficit of love,
ing to the United Nations Development Programme's lat- Education without love, without sharing, without soll¬
est World Development Report, it would be enough for darity with others is dust and ashes, a dead letter, empty
the developing countries to redirect 4 per cent of their talk and abstract words. As the African proverb has it:
military expenditure "in order to reduce adult illiteracy Love is the only thing that increases when it is shared.
D Ql)U.the unesco Courier ianuary i9oe
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
HERITAGE
0 LY MOUNTAIN
by PlutarchosTheocharides
Ten centuries of uninterrupted creative effort shaped the
architecture and art treasures of Mount Athos, which was
placed on the World Heritage List in 1988.
The katholikon or main church (at right) of the Monastery of
St. Panteleimon, which was rebuilt In the early 19th century.
Mount Athos, a rocky head¬
land soaring 2,000 metres
out of the Aegean Sea, is the most
easterly of the three promontories
of the Greek peninsula of
Chalkidiki. The peninsula's rugged
terrain and inhospitahle coastline
make settlement and communica¬
tions on it extremely difficult.
There is evidence that five towns
existed there in Antiquity, but
later, after the destruction and rav¬
ages of the early Middle Ages, the
site appears to have attracted only
anchorites and monks.
The origins of monastic life on
Athos are lost in legend. The ear¬
liest historical sources attesting
to the presence of a solid religious
structure date from the ninth cen¬
tury. At that time the monks lived
ascetic lives in isolated huts or
kellia that were in many cases
interconnected to form small
monastic communities or lavras.
There also seems to have been a
rudimentary form of central orga¬
nization, perhaps not unlike the
monastic republic that developed
later. But cenobitic monasteries
(where the monks have everything
in common) were only found out¬
side the peninsula in the nearby
inhabited regions.
The first cenobitic monastery
on Athos (the Great Lavra) was
founded by Athanasius the
Athonite in 963 and was soon fol¬
lowed by others. By the middle of
the eleventh century there were
no less than 200 "monasteries",
but numbers fluctuated consider¬
ably during the Byzantine period,
and it was only under the Ottoman
occupation that the numbers and
types of monasteries on Mount
Athos stabilized into more or less
their present state. When
Stavronikita Monastery was
founded in the mid -sixteenth cen¬
tury, the number of monasteries
was fixed at twenty, the present
W THE UNESCO COURIER JANUARY I99B
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Stavronikita, the
smallest monastery
on Mount Athos.
Dedicated to St.
Nicholas, it was
rebuilt in the 16th
century by Jeremy I,
the Patriarch of
Constantinople.
number. During the same period,
the kellia, some of which replaced
defunct monastic communities,
gradually came under the control
of the twenty monasteries. At the
end of the seventeenth century,
sketes large communities depen¬
dent on the monasteries were
founded. The first of these foun¬
dations were "idiorrhythmic"
(each monk living at his own
rhythm); later ones were cenobitic.
Throughout their history, both
under the Byzantine and Ottoman
Empires, the large monasteries
wielded exceptional economic
power and enjoyed a privileged
position. Their main sources of
wealth were the exploitation of
large estates (metochia), dona¬
tions received from sovereigns and
other prominent people and, in
later times, from zefeies (long-
term fund-raising trips) made by
monks to the Orthodox countries
where Athos always exercised
great spiritual influence.
These spiritual and material
factors had important repercus¬
sions on building activity on Mount
Athos. Athonite architecture
reflects architectural ambition and
a diversity of influences the latter
being particularly apparent in the
later (eighteenth-twentieth cen¬
tury) buildings. This marriage of
different cultural and architec¬
tural inputs and the use of crafts¬
men from different regions gave
rise to organic building complexes
which served as prototypes for
other Orthodox countries. After
the fall of Constantinople in 1453
and the Ottoman dissolution of the
Byzantine empire, Mount Athos,
which was directly subject to the
Patriarch of Constantinople,
became one of the most important
centres of artistic activity in the
Orthodox world and perhaps its
leading architectural centre.
In the late fourteenth century,
Mount Athos entered a period of
economic depression which lasted
until the end of the fifteenth cen¬
tury and, for some monasteries,
until the early sixteenth. The pop¬
ulation, which in its two great peri¬
ods of expansion (the eleventh and
fourteenth centuries) is reckoned
to have numbered about 6,000 and
4,000 monks respectively, proba¬
bly fell to around 1,500. But as
the fifteenth century came to a
close, a new period of activity
began with the renovation ofbuild¬
ings, the construction of imposing
fortifications and the extension of
the enclosures in some monasteries.
This activity came to an end at
the beginning of the seventeenth
century, when Mount Athos again
gradually sank into decline, this
time until the. mid-eighteenth cen¬
tury. From the second half of the
eighteenth century until the Greek
War of Independence of 1821,
there was a renaissance during
which some, of the idiorrhythmic
monasteries converted to the ceno¬
bitic way of life. New construction
work continued until the end of
the nineteenth century, and the
main architectural imprint on
Mount Athos today is that of the
eighteenth and nineteenth cen¬
turies. From 1850 on, Russian
monks flocked to the peninsula,
bringing with them an entirely dif¬
ferent kind of architecture. At the
turn of the century construction
activity again slackened and was
then interrupted by the First
World War. Mount Athos fell bark
into a deep sleep from which it is
only now emerging.
r ;
THE UNESCO COURIER JANUARY I 008 ^1
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
THE GARDEN
OF THE VIRGIN
by Christine Quenon
According to legend, after the Res¬
urrection, the Virgin Mary and St.
John the Evangelist set sail for
Cyprus to visit Lazarus. During the
\ oyagc they were caught in a violent
storm and their ship was cast onto
the eastern shore of Mount Athos.
Captivated by the beauty of the
place, Mary prayed to her son and
asked him to grant her sovereignty
over the mountain. A heavenly voice
replied, saying, "May this place he
yours, may it he your garden and
your paradise and a haven of peace
for all those who seek salvation."
This is why the monks called Mount
Athos "The Carden of the Virgin",
and the Greeks called it "Ilagios
0,-os"the "Holy Mountain".
In the Middle Ages a charter
issued by the Byzantine emperor
defined the rules of monastic life,
which have changed little since
then. The Virgin Mary is the only-
Silver incense casket
in the shape of
a 5-domed church
(early 19th century).
The figure of St.
Stephen is depicted
on the side.
A 16th-century icon
from Stavronikita
Monastery depicting
the Annunciation. It
was painted on wood
by Theophanis, a
master of the Cretan
School.
female presence. Only men are
allowed to live on the Holy Moun¬
tain. Since the 1920s, Mount Athos
has been a theocratic republic
which enjoys a certain amount of
autonomy within the Creek state. It
is comprised of twenty monaster¬
ies. This number is immutable.
CHURCHES, TREASURES AND
LIBRARIES
The monasteries of Mount Athos are
usually girdled by a fortified outer
wall. Each one has a central church,
or kutholikon in many cases a
medieval Byzantine church painted
red on the outside and surrounded
by dependencies. The interior of the
church, as at Vatopedi monastery, is
decorated with frescoes, icons and
mosaics. The monastery usually
houses a treasury which the monks
are reluctant to show visitors and
which may contain reliquaries, icons
and cult objects like the 14th-cen¬
tury jasper, silver gilt and enamel
chalice, a masterpiece of Byzantine
craftsmanship, preserved at Vato¬
pedi Monastery, and Emperor
Nicephorus II Phocas's vestments,
which are kept in one of the penin¬
sula's most beautiful monasteries,
the Great Lavra. The monastic,
libraries are often rich in ancient man¬
uscripts, some dating from the 4th
century. The Creat Lavra library, for
example, contains more than 2,000
manuscripts and 5,000 volumes.
To fully appreciate the beauty
of these monasteries, which blend
harmoniously into the beautifully
preserved landscape, it is best to
approach them from the sea. Some,
like the monasteries of St. Grego-
riou, Vatopedi and St. Panteleimon,
are located on the shore. Others, like
Dionysiou, the Great Lavra, St. Paul
and Simonopetra, perch on hilltops or
rocky outcrops. With its jumble of
roofs, towers, bell-towers and crenel-
Iations each monastery is a village.
Small white buildings with wooden
balconies cling to high, monumental
walls.
APLACE
OF SANCTUARY
The monasteries are divided into two
groups. In the cenobitic monaster¬
ies, governed by a single rule, every¬
thing is done in common: the monks
live under the same roof, join in the
same prayers throughout the day
and night, share meals and work, and
have no personal possessions. In what
are know n as "idiorrhy tlnnic" monas¬
teries each monk lives at his "own
rhythm", owns his own cell, is not
obliged to do any communal work
and can freely use any income he
may have. For the monks in these
monasteries sharing is limited to liv¬
ing under the same roof and attend¬
ing certain services together.
Other forms of religious life on
Mount Athos fall outside these two
major categories and include
anchorites, hermits who live alone in
secluded cells or in groups of two or
three in remote houses with their
own chapels, and gyrovagues itin¬
erant, mendicant monks.
The Athonite monks use the
Julian calendar, and their day
begins at sunset, not midnight. The
bell that signals the start of a day of
prayer and work is tolled at one
o'clock in the morning.
The monks come from all over the
Orthodox world. After a period of
decadence, monastic life is today
experiencing a renaissance and
attracting new vocations. The
Athonite school is also open to young
men who do not wish to make a life¬
long commitment to the monastic life.
Many of the monasteries are under¬
going major restoration work. The
monks and anchori tes w ho li\ e in this
sanctuary are keeping alive the con¬
templative tradition of the Orthodox
Church. H
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
THETREASURES OF MOUNT ATHOS
WEM "*?,*.
-
The embrace of the
Apostles Peterand
Paul, a symbol of
ecumenical peace
and the unity of the
churches. Fragment
of a late 12th-century
fresco from Vatopedi
Monastery.
Portrait of Matthew
the Evangelistand
the opening page of
his Gospel. They form
part of a 13th-
century illuminated
manuscript of the
four Gospels from
Dionysiou
Monastery.
Some of the masterpieces of Byzantine and
post-Byzantine sacred art housed in the
monasteries of Mount Athos were publicly
displayed for the first time at a recent exhi¬
bition held in Thessaloniki (Greece). The
exhibition, entitled The Treasures of Mount
Athos, was organized jointly by the Holy
Community of Mount Athos and the Orga¬
nization for the Cultural Capital of Europe
Thessaloniki 1997. It was held at Thessa-
loniki's Museum of Byzantine Culture from
21 June to 31 December 1997.
The exhibition, whose unifying theme
was the spirituality that informs all aspects
of life on Mount Athos, was divided into four
sections: natural environment, architecture,
daily life and worship, andthe centrepiece
of the showthe treasures of the monastic
heritage. On display was an exceptional col¬
lection of sacred art objects and other pieces
(1,500 in all) selected from among those
accumulated by the monastic community
over the centuries in the fields of architec¬
ture, sculpture and, most especially, paint¬
ing and the minor arts: icons (fixed and
portable), mosaics, fragments of frescoes,
silverwork, stone and wood carving, embroi¬
dery, ceramics, illuminated manuscripts,
chrysobulls (edicts issued by the Byzantine
emperors), archive documents and rare
books.
A remarkable catalogue has been published
in Greek and English: Treasures of Mount
Athos, 671 pp., Thessaloniki, 1997. For fur¬
ther information, contact the Museum of
Byzantine Culture, Thessaloniki (Greece).
Tel: (30 31) 87 08 29 and 87 08 30 or 87 08
31. Fax: (30 31) 87 08 32.
Left, the Nativity
scene embroidered
on a 17th-century
red satin py/e from
Simonopetra
Monastery. The
py/e ¡s a veil hung
in front of the
central door of the
iconostasis, a
wooden screen
separating the nave
from the sanctuary
in Eastern
churches.
Portrait of St.
Catherine as a
princess. A
painting on wood
(late 15th-early
16th c.) from
Simonopetra
Monastery.
dQuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER JANUARY 1998
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
A Tokyo street
(Japan).
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
I In the next ten years, the
I number of people living in
cities will rise to around 3.3 bil¬
lion. Tokyo already has a popula¬
tion of 27 million, Sào Paulo
(Brazil) 16.4 million, and Bombay
15 million. World Bank forecasts
show as much as 80 per cent of
the developing countries' economic
growth occurring in the cities and
major conurbations.
There are both positive and neg¬
ative aspects to these developments.
As the Organization for Economic
Co-operation and Development
(OECD) points out in a recent study
on Innovative policies for sustain¬
able urban development, "At each
| Cities:
residents to
the rescue
stage in the history ofurbanisation,
environmental conditions in cities
were improved dramatically. The
process was often slow, but over
time, many epidemic diseases have
been controlled, the supply of clean
water and the removal of wastes
have become routine, the risks of
fire have been contained, and stan¬
dards of comfort and cleanliness
have risen to unprecedented levels .
Cities could not have become as
large and as numerous as they are
now ifenvironmental conditions had
remained unchanged."
In a curious way, the pollution
that cities suffer is largely due to
their wealth. The rich consume a
great deal more energy, water,
building materials and other goods
than the poor, and thus produce
much more waste. This is what is
happening, for example, in the
cities in south-east Asia and Latin
America where rapid industrial¬
ization is taking place only the
rich enjoy the benefits of piped
water and refuse collection.
INCREASINGLY
INSANITARY
CONDITIONS
There is another, often tragic,
aspect to this situation. The poor¬
est of the poor are reduced to liv¬
ing in outer-edge shantytowns in
extremely insanitary conditions
and, lacking the resources to deal
with the problem, the city as a
whole has to endure congestion and
air and water pollution. In Africa,
where some towns and cities are
expanding at a rate of over 7 per
cent a year, municipal sanitation
departments are no longer able to
cope, and it is estimated that as
many as 30 per cent of the popu¬
lation are without running water.
According to a remarkable
report that was published recently1 ,
in many of the world's major cities
runaway population growth, an epi¬
demic of Aids and rising social ten¬
sions have been combined in the last
few years with a steep drop in
incomes. The population living on
the outer edges of the cities con¬
tinues to grow apace, hundreds of
thousands of people are without
running water and 15 per cent of
themwithout sanitation of any sort.
Various voluntary bodies and
non-governmental organizations
have got together, often success¬
fully, to work out solutions. In
Abidjan, an original refuse-collec¬
tion scheme has resulted in the
seashore being cleared of rubbish
and has also given regular employ¬
ment to hundreds of people. Sim¬
ilar schemes have been initiated in
Nairobi, Accra and Ndola (Zam¬
bia), where small-scale enterprises
producing bricks have been set up ,
thus not only providing their
1. "The Urban Environment", appearing in
World liesources, A guide to the global
environment, 1996-97, a report compiled
by the World Resources Institute, ihe
United .Nations Environment Programme,
the United Nations Development
Programme and the World Rank.
I IANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
employees with an income but
turning out a cheap, good-quality
building material. Another exam¬
ple of "informal" employment
cited in the same report concerns
a refuse recycling project in Hanoi
(Viet Nam), collecting and cleaning
chicken bones which end up in
Italian pharmacies as calcium sup¬
plements sold at high prices. The
problem is, however, that these
informal activities are much less
well paid than "traditional" jobs.
In the thirteen countries studied in
the report, the average income in
the parallel economy was well
below the official poverty line.
WATER AND THE
ENVIRONMENTAL CRISIS
One key problem concerns the avail¬
ability of clean water. Some progress
has been achieved as a result of the
International DrinkingWater Supply
and Sanitation Decade, but in 1994
at least 220 million people still
lacked a source of drinking water
near their homes. In some cases,
communities of 500 or more inhab¬
itants are served by a single tap. In
some towns, communal taps func¬
tion for only a few hours a day, so
that people cannot build up suffi¬
cient reserves of water for their per¬
sonal needs if it takes too long to
fetch or if the water has to be car¬
ried long distances.
As there are no proper sanitation
measures, the disadvantaged mem-
Washing in water
from a broken
water main,
Bombay (India).
Women in Nairobi
(Kenya) make
bricks for their
own use and
for sale.
bers of the population ha\ e to drink
dirty water, fish in polluted streams,
and eat vegetables that have been
grown by the side of refuse tips.
A further major problem arises
from the threefold harmful impact
of cities on the environment: urban
development on agricultural land,
the extraction and exhaustion of
natural resources, and the dumping
of refuse. The area covered by
downtown Sào Paulo has grown in
fifty years from 180 sq km to more
than 900 sq km, while that of
greater Sâo Paulo now stands at an
incredible 8,000 sq km! The pro¬
ductive areas of land or water
from which food for the cities
comes are gradually vanishing.
Growing pressure on coastal
regions, where nearly a billion peo¬
ple now live, is doing serious dam¬
age to the marine environment.
Development activities pose a
threat to nearly half the world's
coasts. In the diminutive island
state of Singapore, for example,
land is in such short supply that
6,000 hectares have been
reclaimed from the sea, increasing
the land area by 10 per cent in rela¬
tion to what it was thirty years ago.
A hundred and fifty years of recla¬
mation along San Francisco Bay,
the most densely built-up estuary
in the United States, have reduced
the area of the bay by a third.
RESIDENTS TAKE THINGS IN
HAND
The report on the urban environ¬
ment gives many examples of local
schemes being launched, in both
developed and developing coun¬
tries, to keep these harmful
effects in check.
The city of Graz (Austria) had
an idea for reducing pollution from
automobile and machine produc¬
tion, footwear manufacturing and
brewing. A partnership was estab¬
lished with the Chemical Engi¬
neering Institute of the city's Uni¬
versity of Technology, allowing the
companies concerned to set up a
project team to develop a cleaner
production programme. In six years,
not only was the volume of toxic and
solid wastes reduced by 50 per
cent, but production costs also fell,
in some cases by 60 per cent.
Cajamarca (Peru) is one of the
world's poorest cities, with a sub¬
stantial infant mortality rate. The
river Kilish, from which most of
the population get their drinking
water, is seriously polluted. The
provincial authorities devolved
some of their powers on to neigh¬
bourhood councils in the town and
the surrounding countryside, and
these bodies have given top prior¬
ity to water delivery systems. They
are also terracing the badly eroded
slopes of the Andes, establishing
seed banks, introducing health ser¬
vices and carrying out a programme
of refuse collection and park
improvement.
In Colombia's second largest city,
Cali, 350,000 people werelivingin
squalid shacks in the Aguablanca
settlement. To help them make
decent homes for themselves, the
Carvajal Foundation built a ware¬
house selling good-quality building
D \3>URITHE UNESCO lOURIER |ANUARYI998
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
materials at wholesale prices, while
the local school of architecture pro¬
vides plans for simple, solid houses.
The prices of foodstuffs have gone
down since local grocery-store own¬
ers were given some training in man¬
agement techniques, and infant
mortality has been cut by two-
thirds, thanks to the work of vol¬
unteers from the community,
trained by the Foundation to edu¬
cate families in nutrition and
health care.
Towns originally offered people
a place of refuge, of mutual help
and culture. According to nine¬
teenth-century town-planning the¬
orists, they should supply all human
needs. They were supposed to be
the very stuff of civilization. That
was not to be, and therefore when¬
ever the authorities throw in their
hands, dismayed by the scale of the
problems and lacking the political
will, money or resources to cope with
them, personal initiatives are those
most likely to succeed.
FURTHER READING
World resources, A guide to the
global environment 1996-97, The
urban environment, Oxford
University Press, 1996
Innovative policies for
sustainable urban development,
The ecological city, OECD, 1996
A district of
Singapore built on
landfill.
initiatives
A model project
in Brazil
The "Pirajá Memorial Project" is a scheme run by the Centro de Edu-
cctçùo Ambiental Sao Bartolomeu, an environmental education centre in
Salvador, Bahia State, Brazil. Its main aims are the affirmation of cul¬
tural identity and citizenship, and the protection of the environment. The
Pirajá Metropolitan Park, created north-east of Salvador in 1978, is a
1,550-hectare forest reserve surrounded by overcrowded shantytowns
where living conditions are appalling. Malnutrition and cholera are rife,
infant mortality is high. Young people are exposed to violence, racism and
drugs. Many drop out of school.
The park is of great historical and cultural importance, since it was
at Pirajá that a famous battle for Brazil's independence took place. It
was also here that the Jesuits built their first Indian village and that
quilombos (piares where runaway slaves gathered) were later set up. It
is now under violent assault from several quarters: the extremely varied
wildlife is being savagely hunted down, the plant life devastated and the
rivers polluted by refuse, and forest fires are frequent. Black people's
contribution to Brazilian history and culture Salvador being the city
with the largest black population outside of Africa is being ignored,
and places where the rites oicundomble, the Afro-Brazilian religion, were
celebrated are being destroyed. The park's living heritage seemed to be
sinkinginto oblivion.
In 1991 , the Project selected a number of local young people, aged 14
to 18, to work as guides, make contact with other young people and act
as outreach agents in schools and in the community at large. Twenty-six
teachers and 700 students were then recruited to replant and restore
the candomble sites. A library was opened in 1995 and an environmental
education programme was started, offering students a chance to take
part in practical activities, including school vegetable gardens. Seeing
the good work that was being done, UNESCO decided to make Pirajá Park
an experimental zone of the Mata Atlántica Biosphere Reserve.
In 1996, the Project published a newspaper, put on a play, set up craft
workshops for children, spread its activities to other schools, mobilized
public opinion, and asked artists to act as "militants" in the cause of the
park. So many initiatives have been launched that they cannot all be listed
here. Work is now proceeding on the establishment of an open-air museum
to draw attention to the region's history and culture, and the local pop¬
ulation is being encouraged to learn more about nature and respect it.
These activities form part of a wider socio-economic development strat¬
egy for the region, one of the poorest in the world. The United Nations
Children's Fund (UNICEF) and several non-governmental organizations
are already participating, and help of any kind for this fine project
would be welcome.
Projeto Memorial Pirajá
Centro de Educa çâo Ambiental Sao Bartolomeu
Praça 15 de novembro 17 - Terreiro de Jesus
Salvador/BA 40. 025-010 Brazil
Telephone and Fax: (55) 71 3219903
44
THE UNESCO ^)URIER |ANUARY ITO8
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
world
ROOTS, TUBERS AND GREEN
BANANAS
Roots such as manioc and tubers
such as potatoes, sweet potatoes
and yams are, together with plan¬
tains, the staple foods of over 1.5
billion of the world's population.
Some 650 million tons of these
foods are produced a year, 70 per
cent in the countries of the South.
Their cultivation is an issue of such
importance that a network for the
promotion of tropical starch-pro¬
ducing plants (PROAMYL-CIO) has
been set up, linking a hundred or
so full-time researchers from
CIRAD, France's International Cen¬
tre for Co-operation in Agricultural
Research for Development, INRA,
the French National Institute for
Agricultural Research, and
ORSTOM, the French Institute of
Scientific Research for Develop¬
ment in Co-operation.
PROAMYL-CIO, BP 5035,
34032 Montpellier Cedex 1. France
Fax: (33) (01) 04 67 61 12 23.
E-mail: proamyl@cirad.fr
WORMS RID SOIL OF OIL
Australia's Murdoch University in
Perth has carried out a study on
the capacity of earthworms to
decontaminate oil-polluted soils.
Worms aerate the soil and enrich
it with nutriments. When they
ingest hydrocarbons their colour
changes from pale pink to black,
but they revert to their original
colour when they have eaten
organic wastes, their usual food.
An oil company experimentally
spread its sludge in a field which
was later ploughed. Micro-organ¬
isms in the soil decomposed the
light parts of the sludge. The
wo rms dealt with the heavy parts.
RESTORING SPAIN'S FORESTS
In 1993, the Madrid Community
Administration offered the Span¬
ish branch of the World Wide Fund
for Nature (WWF) the use of an
experimental farm near the village
of Alcalá de Henares. WWF-Spain
joined forces with ONCE, Spain's
National Organization for the
Blind, which helps the sight-
impaired and other disabled peo¬
ple. Twenty disabled people who
have been given training In nursery
techniques collect seeds in the
wild and sow them. Last year, one
million trees were raised and
sales totalled nearly $162,000.
Some of the trees go to restore
damaged woodlands or protected
areas such as the Delta del Ebro
and Collsegola national parks on
the Mediterranean coast.
GETTING RID OF LEADED
PETROL
The World Bank has this year pub¬
lished a report on the dangers of
leaded petrol in Eastern and Cen¬
tral Europe. While some 18 coun¬
tries, including Brazil, Thailand,
Canada and the United States
have now phased it out, the coun¬
tries in this region have not done
so. In Budapest (Hungary), for
instance, 90 per cent of airborne
lead comes from vehicle exhaust.
Children are most at risk from the
neurological damage and heart
disease associated with lead expo¬
sure. The report recommends tax¬
ing leaded fuel more heavily than
unleaded and helping refineries
upgrade to new technology. The
reduction in health care expendi¬
ture should more than cover the
costs involved.
MYSTERY IN NIGER
Hydrologists from France's
ORSTOM Institute recently came
upon a puzzling phenomenon.
Although rainfall has been declin¬
ing since the 1960s in West Africa,
the Sahel in particular, the under¬
ground water level near Niamey,
capital of Niger, is rising, despite
a serious twenty-year drought. The
reason is that the plant cover has
changed, the cultivated area
around Niamey increasing from
12 to 63 per cent of the total. Rain¬
water runoff thus increases, as a
result of several factors. The crust
that forms on the surface of irri¬
gated land is only slightly perme¬
able, there are fewer obstacles (in
the form of twigs and grasses) to
runoff, and the activity of crea¬
tures for instance
which used to be conducive to infil¬
tration into the soil surface, has
been reduced. Hence, rainwater
gathers in low-lying spots and fil¬
ters down underground, swelling
the reserves of the aquifers.
CONTRABAND CFCS
It is ten years since the signing of
the Montreal Protocol, whereby
the use of "ozone-munching"
chemicals was to be eliminated.
The number of signatories has
risen from the original 24 coun¬
tries to 163. Some Western coun¬
tries have already reduced the
release of these substances by
half, while other countries like
China and Brazil are making
efforts to follow suit. Unfortu¬
nately, it is reckoned that the ille¬
gal trade in one of the com¬
poundschlorofluorocarbons or
CFCsamounts to roughly 20,000
tonnes a year, and some unscrupu¬
lous producers even advertise
their wares on the Internet. The
ozone layer may have to wait until
2050 to heal itself.
PESTICIDES DUMPED IN
AFRICA
More than 20,000 tonnes of dete¬
riorated pesticides are currently
stocked in Africa, amounting to a
fifth of the total stored in developing
countries. This estimate by the
Food and Agriculture Organization
of the United Nations (FAO) is
alarming. More than 70 tonnes
have been recorded in Benin alone.
These highly dangerous products
are largely intended for agriculture,
but they are also found in aerosol
form in markets and shops, dis¬
played beside foodstuffs. It would
cost from $80 to $100 million to
get rid of them.
THE UNESCO CpuRIER JANUARY 1908
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Listening Joto la Momposina BY ISABELLE LEYMARIE
A Colombian singer iiith a tremendous voice, Toto la Momposina
(Sonia Bazanta) is an internationally known exponent of the rich musical
tradition ofher country's Atlantic seaboard.
I Toto la Momposina is a singer and
I dancer who releases seismic forces
on stage. "The maelstrom of brass and
drums and the colourful costumes made
me think of hack home," said a young
South African dancer after one of Toto's
concerts. " There's the same enthusiasm
and energy that you find in Zulu music."
Toto's band features a trumpet, a bom-
bardino (a precursor of the oboe family), a
guitar and a double bass as well as folk
instruments such as the tiple (a small
twelve-string guitar) and agaïta (a bamboo
or cactus-wood Amerindian ilute). She also
has a percussion section that weaves com¬
plex rhythms with various kinds of drums,
including the deep-toned bombo, bongos,
claves, maracas, guache (seed-filled tubes
that are shaken) and marimbulas (drums
containing small strips of metal). "Drums
make you react in an instinctive and spon¬
taneous way," she explains, "and the music
I perform is basically percussive."
Five-hundred-year-old music
Toto belongs to the fourth generation of a
family of musicians (her father is a drum¬
mer, her mother a singer and dancer). She
was born in Talaigua, a village on Mompos
Island (whence her nickname), in the north¬
ern reaches of Colombia's Magdalena River.
An intensely musical area, this lush, trop
ical region was originally inhabited by Indi¬
ans and then during the colonial period
became a haven for Maroons (fugitive
slaves), who built fortified communities
known 'as palenques.
The best known palenque, located near
Cartagena, was founded in 1608 under the
leadership of the African-born King
Benkos. It still exists, and ancient Angolan
customs are practised there. Maroons and
Indians often intermarried, producing off¬
spring who prized their freedom and orig¬
inality. Musically speaking, Colombia's
Atlantic coast is part of the Caribbean
world, and over the years has produced a
host of intense musical genres that have
emerged from a blend of the African,
Amerindian and Spanish cultures.
As a child, Toto learned the chande,
the mapalé, thefandango, the currulao,
the porro, the puya, the merengue and
the cumbia, all of which are secular or
sacred musical forms. She also learned the
art of the cantadoras, female singers who
improvise coplas (verse couplets). She took
part in fiestas, wakes and ceremonies in
neighbouring villages, listened to the rhyth¬
mic songs of itinerant salesmen and was
taught by many musicians, including the
wonderful cantadora Ramona Ruiz, who
visited the family home.
She made up her mind to devote the
rest of her life to upholding her region's
musical traditions. "You could describe
our music as an enterprise that began 500
years ago," she explains, "a process that
has developed and changed but perpetu¬
ates the village traditions from which it
has emerged. What we want to do is inject
our own energy into it, develop it to the
full and help to strengthen our national
musical identity. We want to help our coun¬
try's music express the culture of all our
people." The baton of tradition has already
been taken up by her son and daughters,
who play in her band, not to mention her
granddaughter, Maria del Mar, who moves
happily around the stage during some of
their concerts.
Humanist and mystic
Toto began her professional career in 1968.
With her own band she has made several
European and Latin American tours. After
a stay in Paris where she studied the his¬
tory of dance at the Sorbonne, sometimes
sang in train stations and on street corners
and cut two records: Tofo La Momposina
(Auvidisc) and Colombia, Music from the
Atlantic Coast (Aspic), she returned to
Colombia. "I was falling prey to ethno-musi-
cologists and needed to recharge my bat¬
teries." She then studied the bolero in
Cuba and incorporated the son, the
guaracha, the rumba and other Cuban
beats popular in Colombia into her reper¬
toire and travelled all over the world.
She dislikes the term folklore which,
she feels, designates ossified forms of
expression, and prefers to talk of tradi¬
tional music or, making a punning refer¬
ence to "folklore", conflor ("with a flower")
music. With its roots in the soil and in tune
with the cosmic order, her country's music
possesses inexhaustible vitality. "At home,"
she says, "the rural people have always
composed music based on nature, and when
music comes from the land, its language
knows no frontiers. When I listen to drum¬
mers from Senegal or the Congo, I can hear
affinities with Cuban, Brazilian and Colom¬
bian drummers."
"Upholding my cultural heritage inter¬
nationally is a mission for me," she says,
"but the road is not easy. There can't be
any stars in this field. I have a spiritual
idea of my art."
DISCOGRAPHY
La Candela Viva (Real World, 1992)
Carmelina (Indigo, 1997)
the unesco Courier ianuary iwa
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
this month's interview
Novelist
in exile
Luis SepúLveda
What sort of a childhood did you have?
Luis Sepúlveda: I was lucky enough to have a
normal childhood in a family which was imbued
with the spirit of curiosity and which gave me the
urge and the opportunity to travel. From the
age of fourteen onwards, I used to spend my hol¬
idays backpacking around Chile which is 5,000
km from north to south and the neighbouring
countries, Peru, Bolivia, Argentina and Uruguay.
What about your studies?
L.S.: After secondary school in Santiago, I stud¬
ied theatre production at the National Univer¬
sity. In 1969, 1 was given a five-year scholarship
to continue my drama studies at Moscow Uni¬
versity, but it was withdrawn after five months on
account of "misconduct" I had made friends
with some dissidents, who in my opinion were
producing the best art in the Soviet Union. I had
to go back to Chile.
How did you become a writer?
L.S.: Through reading, especially the great
authors of adventure stories like Jules Verne,
Jack London and Robert Louis Stevenson. We
read a lot at home. My grandfather, who was a
Spanish anarchist, loved books and had a small
library. I think the urge to write came from read¬
ing Francisco Coloana, a Chilean writer.
What was your first book?
L.S.: It came out in 1966, a collection of very bad
juvenile poetry I shall never have republished. I
went on writing because I had acquired a taste for
it, but without believing myself to be a writer.
Then one day a friend put together a dozen of
my stories into a book, Crónicas de Pedro Nadie,
and sent it to Cuba, where it won the Casa de las
Americas Prize in 1969. Later it was published in
Colombia and Argentina, and I started to be knov\ n
throughout Latin America. I'd become a writer
Internationally-known
Chilean novelist Luis
Sepúlveda is a defender
offreedomandofthe
environment who has
experienced prison and
exile. Here he talks
about a career in which
political commitment
and a passion for
writing are intertwined.
Interview by
Bernard Magnier
through force of circumstance! I was also writ¬
ing for the theatre and the radio, which I think is
excellent training for a writer because of the need
to meet deadlines.
You had a political role at the same time...
L.S.: While writing I was also politically active,
first as a leader of the student movement and
then in the Salvador Allende administration,
especially in the department of cultural affairs.
I acted as a mediator between the government
and big business, and I also worked for the
department of cultural affairs. I was in charge of
a series of cheap editions of classics of world lit¬
erature for the general public.
Then came the 1973 putsch. . .
L.S.: I was jailed for two-and-a-half years. I
obtained a conditional release through the efforts
of the German branch of Amnesty International
but was then kept under house arrest. I man¬
aged to escape and went underground for nearly
a year. With the help of a friend who was head
of the Alliance Française in Valparaiso I was
able to find work. We set up a drama group that
became the first cultural focus of resistance,
but 1 was rearrested and given a life sentence
for treason and subversion, finally reduced to
twenty-eight years, thanks to my defence lawyer.
This time you were well and truly jailed. . .
L.S.: No, in fact the German section of Amnesty
International interv ened again on my behalf and
my prison sentence was commuted to eight years'
THE UNESCO f_OURl ER IANUARY 1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
exile, so in 1977 I left the prison for the airport
to fly to Sweden, where I was to teach Spanish lit¬
erature. At the first stopover, Buenos Aires, I
managed to make my getaway.
H That was the start of a long exile. ..
L.S.: Yes, I went first to Uruguay but many of my
friends there, as in Argentina, which was then a
dictatorship, were dead or in prison, so I went on
to Brazil, to Sâo Paulo, but had to leave there for
Paraguay, where I couldn't stay because of the
regime. I went from there to Bolivia and then to
Peru, finally taking up residence in Ecuador
after a great friend of mine, the novelist and poet
Jorge Enrique Adoum, had invited me to attend
a meeting of Latin American writers there. In
Quito I was director of the Alliance Française
theatre and founded a theatrical company and
then I took part in a UMiSCO expedition to assess
the impact of colonization on the Shuar Indians.
Was that important for you?
L.S.: Enormously important. I shared the life of
the Shuars for seven months. It was a decisive
experience that changed my whole outlook. I
suddenly realized what it really meant to be
Latin American, to belong to a multicultural,
multilingual continent over ninety languages,
not counting Spanish and Portuguese with its
own conceptions of time and history, its own rites.
I realized that the Marxism-Leninism I had grown
up with was not a recipe that could be applied
to a continent whose population is mainly rural
and stands in a close relationship of dependence
and protecti veness with nature. I worked in con¬
tact with the Indian organizations and I drew up
the first literacy teaching plan for the Ibambura
peasants' federation, in the Andes.
Then you went on again to another country. . .
L.S.: Yes, but I went on writing short stories the
whole time and I had plans 'for longer works. In
1979, I joined the Simon Bolivar international
brigade, which was fightingin Nicaragua. Imme¬
diately after the victory of the revolution, I
started working as a journalist writing on inter¬
national affairs, but the following year I decided
to leave Nicaragua and go to Europe.
You decided to live in Germany. Why was that?
L.S.: I chose Hamburg as my base because I had
learned German in prison out of admiration for
German literature, especially the romantics,
Novalis and Hölderlin, without whom it is impos¬
sible to understand modern literature and Latin
American literature in particular.
THE UNESCO (oURIER JANUARY I99R
BIBLIOGRAPHY
Un viejo que leía novelas de
amor. Published in English
as The Old Man Who Read
Love Stories, Souvenir Press,
London, 1993 (translated by
Peter Bush)
Patagonia Express.
Published in English as Full
Circle: A South American
journey, Lonely Planet
Publications, Melbourne,
1996 (translated by Chris
Andrews)
I also have a strong emotional rapport with
Hamburg: it has links with Valparaiso that go
back to the heroic days of sail. In addition, Ham¬
burg is the place with the greatest concentration
of media in Europe, sol had the opportunity to
work for the press and write for television. I did
a great deal of journalism, which gave me the
opportunity to travel widely and spend much
time in Latin America and in Africa.
It was in Hamburg in 1982 that I first came
into contact with Greenpeace. I joined in their
struggle for the environment. For five years, until
1987, I was a crewman on one of their ships.
Later I acted as co-ordinator between various
branches of Greenpeace.
What about your writing in the meantime?
L.S.: I never stopped. My first novel, Un viejo
que leía novelas de amor, (The Old Man Who
Read Lore Stories) came out in 1989, followed by
a second, El mundo delfín del mundo. They
have been translated into many languages. I also
kept on writing for the theatre.
Has living in Europe changed your attitude to
Latin America? Do you feel farther away from it now
or closer to it?
L.S.: I feel much more Latin American than if I
were living in Latin America. But I don't think it
necessary to come to Europe to write Latin Amer¬
ican literature. I can write anywhere in the world.
Distance, I must admit, does have the advantage
of offering a panoramic overview of the conti¬
nent and the reality of life there. The challenge
in these circumstances is to keep yourself well
enough informed to be able to understand the
changes taking place and the reasons for those
changes, which I do by going back every year
I have an excellent information network back
home in the shape of my friends who live there.
That being said, my time in Europe is a rather
happy and persistent accident that has undeni¬
ably left its mark on me. I have soaked up Euro¬
pean culture.
Do these different influences come together in
some way?
L.S.: Literature is one and indivisible. Different
writers take different paths but they all lead to
the same destination. Literature is a great broth¬
erhood. Jean-Marie Gustave Le Clézio, for exam¬
ple, is a European writer but he spends much of
his time in Mexico and his outlook is such that we
regard him more as a Latin American writer!
Latin America is a continent of contradictions
and wide differences but in some respects it is
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
also an extension of Europe, a continent of emi¬
grants. Borges referred to us Latin Americans of
the southern cone of the continent as Europeans
born in exile. Our way of life follows European
models. We are republics, we fought for our
independence and our political sovereignty, pat¬
terned on that of the French revolution, and the
great poetical founder-figures of our modern lit¬
erature, such as Kuben Dario or Vicente Iluido-
bro, are undeniably mature Europeans.
What makes you write?
L.S.: I write simply because I like writing. I don't
want to do anything else. I gave up journalism
to devote myself entirely to literature. This may
sound like the answer of someone who has been
privileged oran anarchist, but I do what I like
doing and I make my living doing it.
I don't regard writing as a gift from the gods,
a privilege accorded to a certain caste. It's just
a job! It makes me laugh when I hear of authors
who claim to suffer a lot when writing. If they
suffer so much, why do they write they don't
have to be masochists.
M Do you rework your books a lot?
L.S.: Yes, a lot. I'm a very disciplined worker
and I don't regard them as finished unless I have
been over them at least ten times from begin¬
ning to end.
Your books are short. Is that a deliberate
choice? Is there a rhythm you feel obliged to follow?
L.S.: Length and style depend on the story you
want to tell. I have cut fifty pages out of some of
my novels because they got in the way, they inter¬
rupted the flow I wanted to give them.
Is concern for the environment winning out over
the political commitment that typified so many Latin
American writers of the previous generation?
L.S.: They go hand in hand. Literature cannot
change reality, but it can reflect reflect upon
a very important aspect of it. Rediscovering eco¬
logical dignity is very much a political struggle.
Some present-day writers, like Paco Taibo or Rolo
Diez, are just as politically committed as their
predecessors were, but they approach political
matters from the angle of historical memory, by
reference to what has happened and what should
neither be forgotten nor recur. Their approach
is critical, not without passion but far removed
from perfunctory militancy.
Geography getting its revenge on history?
L.S.: A revenge that is all the more necessary
I want to
stimulate my
readers to think
and to sharpen
their awareness
of others
now that the new world order, although it has
done away with the East-West confrontation, is
constantly and increasingly exacerbating the
North-South confrontation.
Latin America is part of the South. We are
alone, but it is better to be alone than to keep
bad company. A political project can't be built
in a day. Our conception of lime must inevitably
be different from the North's conception, but we
have the time.
Do you write to forget barbarism or to
denounce it?
L.S.: All that concerns me as a writer is that my
readers should come to the same conclusion as
my characters, that they should take notice of
what is happening to them and think. I respect
readers' freedom, and 1 have abolutely no wish to
impose anything on them. All I aim to do is give
them food for thought, thus helping them to
discover the rules governing relationships with
others, the rules of respect for others, with their
culture and their traditions, and to sharpen their
awareness of others, which is, incidentally, a tra¬
dition in adventure-story writing.
How do you explain your fascination with travel
and with the extremes of the natural world, the
southern seas or the Amazonian forest?
L.S.: I am not a city person. I like to spend a cer¬
tain lime in towns, but I need to come face to face
with the elemental forces of nature, to proveto
myself that I can survive on my own, relying on
myself, and also to prove that the individual can
live without being dependent on ihe stale.
Or on other people?
L.S.: No, not on other people. We always need
other people. Humans are social animals, but
they oughtn't to get involved in relationships
based on dependence or domination.
You are internationally famous. How does that
affect you?
L.S.: Success came as a pleasant surpise, but
my character hasn't changed. I'm happy to have
freedom of movement and be free to decide what
to do with my time, but it is above all a great
responsibility to bear. I have an ethical posilion
in relation to life and an aesthetic position in
relation to literature. 1 would like the distinction
to be understood, so that readers could say "I
like Sepiilveda's books but 1 don't agree with
his views" or "I like what he writes, so I would
like to know his views". Literature is a means to
an end. M
THE UNESCO (7>URI ER JANUARY 1998
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
A REMARKABLE DICTIONARY
OF CARIBBEAN ENGLISH
I wish to express my appreciation for the superb, eclectic
coverage in your June 1997 issue ("How ideas travel"). I
was struck by the variety of very interesting articles on sub¬
jects ranging from best sellers of the eighteenth century
and the cyberspace virtual library to the interview with
Viviane Forrester.
I should like to commend to you a remarkable work by
Professor Richard Allsopp, the Oxford Dictionary of
Caribbean English Usage. Perhaps you could review it or
interview the author in a forthcoming issue. Caribbean Eng¬
lish has been influenced by several different African, Indian,
Chinese and Portuguese languages and various forms of
"British English". It is a tremendous blend1
WILLIAM HERBERT
Vancouver (Canada)
RADIO MILESTONE
I read with great interest your February 1997 issue ("Radio,
a future for sound"). In the "Milestones in radio" feature,
however, I was disappointed to see no mention of the
world's f rst regular radio broadcasts, which began on 27
August 1920 from Buenos Aires's El Teatro Coliseo. Broad¬
casting from this station, under the name LR2, has con¬
tinued right until today.
The author may not know of the Buenos Aires event,
but Unesco cannot be unaware of the birth of this regular
radio service. In many countries 27 August Is celebrated as
"World Radio Day" in commemoration of this first broadcast
made from Buenos Aires.
ENRIQUE BRAVO
Buenos Aires (Argentina)
Thankyou for pointing this out. Editor
UNESCO RADIO
As a great radio fan and a faithful reader of your magazine,
I particularly enjoyed your issue on radio.
You reported on Unesco Radio but failed to mention its
wave-length and air times.
P.JAMET
Argenteuil (France)
Unesco's radio programmes are mostly used by national
radio networks, and we cannot give dates and times of
broadcasts in advance.
English-language programmes are, however, broadcast
on short wave by Nexus-International Broadcasting Associ¬
ation and Radio for Peace International. For information about
frequency and programme schedules, please contact:
THE UNESCO COURIER
will be taking part in EXPOLANGUES, the
international fair of languages, cultures and
travel, which is being held from 28 January to 1
February 1998 in the Grande Halle de la Villette,
Paris. The Courier's 27 language editions are
testimony of a respect for cultural diversity fully
shared by EXPOLANGUES, which presents a
broad spectrum of language teaching techniques
through a lively approach to the cultures of which
they are part. Japan is this year's guest of honour.
For further information, contact
REED-OIP, 11 rue du Colonel Pierre Avia,
Botte postale 571
75726 Paris Cedex 15 France.
Tel: [33(0)] 141 90 47 60
Fax: [33 (O)] 141 90 47 69
*- Nexus-International Broadcasting Association, PO Box
10980, 1-20110 Milano, Italy. Tel: + 39 2 266 6971 or +39
337 297788: Fax: + 392 70638151; email: info@nexus.org
« Radio For Peace International, P. 0. Box 88, Santa Ana,
Costa Rica. Tel: 506 249 1821; Fax: 506 249 1095; email:
rfpicr§sol.racsa.co.cr Editor
NAMING NAMES
The Interview with Viviane Forrester in your June 1997 issue
("How ideas travel") was particularly interesting because It
clearly named those responsible for the present economic
situation. Most of the time your contributors write very
well about poverty and destitution, war and peace, but
unlike Vivane Forrester they never explain the reasons why
the problems exist.
I wonder who will take the initiative of bringing together
groups and individuals to denounce the present situation
and, setting political divisions aside, to draw up a social blue¬
print that names the common "enemy" and proposes
sound solutions? More than pious wishes and compas¬
sionate words are needed. Is this what the Courier Intends
to do? I am grateful to see that you have made a first step.
ANDRÉ PILET
Amfreville-s/les-Munts (France)
ASKING 'WHY' NOT 'HOW
In his discussion of ethics and genetics in his "Science and
Society (3)" Commentary in the May 1997 issue ("Land¬
scape with Figures"), Unesco's Director-General squarely
addresses the issue of the responsibility of scientists.
Instead of questioning the ways we use science (the
"how"), I believe It Is increasingly urgent to ask the question
"why" . Why, for example, did we choose to produce energy
using the atom when we can do so using water, wind and
sun? If we had asked this question fifty or sixty years ago,
we could have avoided putting atomic energy to other uses.
In the field of bloethics, the right question to ask is not
"how can we produce a perfect baby?" but "why should we
produce a perfect baby?"
Addressing a problem by asking "why" rather than
"how" is a far broader approach to problem-solving in the
contemporary world.
PHILIPPE RECLUS
Saint-Barthélemy-le-Pin (France)
A DYNAMIC UNESCO
ASSOCIATED SCHOOL
We should like to give you some information about our
activities in the 1996-1997 school year.
Shortly after the start of the year, we translated the
wonderful texts of Unesco posters on Tolerance, Peace
and Improving Human Relations; then we photocopied,
coloured and distributed them to the other schools on
our island.
In December we held an evening dedicated to Unesco's
50th anniversary, at the end of which we exhibited and
sold stationery produced by Unicef (the United Nations
Children's Fund).
In May 1997 In the context of the "Other countries,
other cultures" project, we organized an evening devoted to
the Kalas, a mountain people of Pakistan, provided back¬
ground information about them and sold postcards to
raise money to help them complete the new school they are
building.
Finally, despite complications arising from the political
situation, we continue to have close ties of friendship with
the Turkish school in GulQk.
Unesco Associated Schools
The teachers and pupils of Aghia Marina primary school,
Leros (Greece)
AUTHORS
PAUL EKINS, of the United Kingdom, is Senior
Lecturer in the Environmental Policy Unit of the
Department of Economics at Keele University,
where his research focuses on the conditions
and policies for achieving an environmentally
sustainable economy. He is the author of A
New World Order(Routledge, 1992) and co-
editor of Global Warming and Energy Demand
(Routledge, 1995). In 1994 he received the
UNEP Global 500 Award "for outstanding
environmental achievement".
JAMES GRIFFIN, of the United States, is
White's Professor of Moral Philosophy at
Oxford University (U.K.). He recently published
Wittgenstein's Logical Atomism (1997,
Thoemmes Press).
ADAM ROBERTS, of the United Kingdom,
helped to prepare the first World Forum on
Youth Recycling for Development (1996) and is
currently engaged in research on the ethical
implications of recycling.
SHIOUN MICHIKO NAKASATO, of Japan, is an
award-winning artist and calligraphier whose
work has been widely exhibited, especially in
France and Japan.
HISANORI ISOMURA, a Japanese journalist, is
a former director of Japanese National Radio
and Television (NHK) in Tokyo. He is currently a
special adviser to the Director-General of Unesco
and president of the Japanese Cultural Centre in
Paris. His published work Includes The World at
That Time, a three-volume history of diplomacy
in the post-war years.
MARIE ROUÉ, a French ethnologist specializing
in Arctic and sub-Arctic societies, is a research
officer at her country's National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS).
BABACAR SALL, a Senegalese socio-
economist and adviser on development issues,
is a lecturer at the University of Paris-V. The
author of many scientific articles and a
contributor to numerous literary publications,
he is presently director of Sociétés africaines et
diaspora, a social science review published by
L'Harmattan, Paris.
BENOÎT LAMBERT, of Canada, is a teaching
assistant in the law and political science faculty
of the University of Geneva, where he Is writing
a thesis on "the international movement
against the excessive use of automobiles". He
has published several articles on the bicycle as
a means of transport.
MIKI NOZAWA is a member of Unesco's Division
of Youth and Sports Activities.
PLUTARCHOSTHEOCHARIDES.aGreek
architect, has written many articles on the
history of architecture, especially relating to
Mount Athos.
CHRISTINE QUENON is a French journalist.
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American
journalist specializing In environmental
questions.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American
musicologist, has recently published La musique
sud-américaine, Rythmes et danses d'un
continentfSouth American Music, a Continent's
Rhythms and Dances", Gallimard, Pans, 1997).
BERNARD MAGN1ER is a French literary
journalist who specializes in African literature.
50 dQuiTH£ UNESCO ^URIER JANUARY I9"8
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO LINE
Currently on line are: tables of contents for the latest issues
of the Unesco Courier, information on all of Unesco's
and activities, Unesco press releases, Unesco
ents, publications, the directory of Unesco databases and
formation services and addresses, faxes, phone numbers
d e-mail numbers of Unesco clubs, National Commissions
d regional offices.
Language Learning & Teaching
Language Study Abroad
Translation
for the /£t
International Market
Publishing
Multimedia
Work Experience and
Employment Abroad
Assessment of §
Linguistic skills
Career Guidance .
Cyberlangues
Conferences I
Workshops
Hours Open
to the General Public:
from Thursday 29 January
to Saturday 31 January
from 10:00 a.m. to 7:00 p.m
Sunday 1 February
10.00 a.m. to 6.00 p.m.
Trade day:
Wednesday 28 January JL
9:30 a.m. - 9:00 p.m. MA
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
IN THE NEXT ISSUES
x**%**<
v. :
MEDICINE AND OJLTUtf g < ' £*r£S
HERITAGE . , /", » ' - A
BANSKA STIAVNICA* A WÏNING|TOp IffSLOV '
*V*tf JjW *- ***àk+.
]]>
</page>
</document>
