<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="114699eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
theC o u rie r
January 1999
Gearing up for
t h e g ranny boom
Shanghai
reborn 
Soils
in torment
Museums hoist 
their new coloursBE L G I Q U E: 160 FB. C A N A DA : 5,75 $. E S PA Ñ A : 550 PTA S. F R A N C E : 22 FF NEDERLAND: 8 F L .P O RT U G A L : 700 ESC. S U I S S E : 5,50 FS. UNITED KINGDOM: £ 2 . 3 0
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
52nd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Jany Lesseur
Amy Otchet
Jasmina Sopova
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat
Page layout and photoengraving:Eric Frogé
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,A l c i n o
Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian:Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher copies
are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
a u t h o r ’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
r e q u e s t . Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UN E S C O o r
those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the UN E S C O Courier staff. Th e
boundaries on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the United
N a t i o n s. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform
( m i c r o film and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de
Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,A n n
A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition,
Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ;( 4 )
Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,Wo o s t e r, O h i o
4 4 6 9 1 , U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - JANUARY 1999
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Paris by
UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e. Periodicals postage paid at Champlain
NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N°1-1999-OPI 99-578 A
C o n t e n t s
January 1999
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 Shanghai reborn Georgui Pinkhasov, Chen Danyan
EDITORIAL
9 A time for hope Federico Mayor
PLANET
10 Soils in torment Sophie Boukhari
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Denmark:Building blocks of learning Jesper Heldgaard
DOSSIER
17 Gearing up
for the granny boom
18 The longevity revolution Robert Butler
21 Aging Chinese face a welfare gap Huang Yan
22 Finland’s youthful oldies Ethirajan Anbarasan
23 Hard choices for the Third World Nana Apt
24 Indian elders with nowhere to go
26 Lebanon:there’s no place like home Caroline Donati
27 Argentina’s penniless pensioners Jorge Göttling
28 Sage or spoilsport? Bernadette Puijalon and Jacqueline Trincaz
30 Let the good times roll Amy Otchet
31 African youth makes a takeover bid Codou Bop
32 ‘When are we leaving?’ Roy Malkin
34 Old age’s new horizons
36 The Stoic way Enrique Lynch
ETHICS
37 Debt relief:a creditable solution? Angela Travis
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 Museums hoist their new colours René Rivard
CONNEXIONS
43 Can papers net a profit? Jany Lesseur
45 Writers bloc to defend their rights Ethirajan Anbarasan
TALKING TO…
46 Yordan Radichkov, the improbable Bulgarian
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
S h a n g h a i
r e b o r n
Thronged with pedestrians and traffic,
Nanjing Road is one of booming 
Shanghai’s main thoroughfares.
Shanghai today is an immense building site
bristling with cranes and scaffolding.
Photos by
Georgi Pinkhasov
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A night out in a disco.
Shanghai girls prepare for a white wedding.
Night-time on the Bund,
the famous waterfront promenade built 
by the colonial powers a century ago.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Shanghai was once a colonial gateway into China,
then went into eclipse. Today it is a vast building
site bidding to rise as high as New York
Chen Danyan*
■
In the nineties, Shanghai has exploded like a Chinese firecracker.Yet this is not
its first explosive boom.That occurred some 80 years ago. Shanghai used to be
a small fishing port carved into British, French,American and Japanese
spheres of influence.While it was carved up, Shanghai grew into the largest
metropolis in Asia. In the seventies, Shanghai lost its lustre.When night fell, the city
was dark as the corridors and toilets in many homes which were dimly lit by the
30-watt energy-saving bulbs then popular across the city. The river banks were
dotted with courting couples who had no rooms of their own and no cafés or parks
to go to.The riverside became the only place where they could meet.
Today Shanghai, like a “prodigal son”, is working frantically to make up for
whatever time it has wasted, harbouring an ambition to overtake Hong Kong in its
development and to emulate New York or other big cities of the world.
In the old parts of the city, houses can be seen on all sides with the same big
s i g n : “ To be demolished”. Whole neighbourhoods have been pulled dow n , a n d
where a wall still remains one can tell by the blotches and stains on it that here
stood a dining table and there a low bed in which someone must have sat reading
Shopping fever takes hold of the city.
* Shanghai-based Chinese writer.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
with his greasy head against the wa l l . Old buildings of the colonial period are
being levelled one after another at night by blasting, to be replaced by skyscrapers
with glass outer wa l l s. In the dow n t own area, an overhead highway and a subway
are being built simultaneously, and the whole city resounds at night with thudding
p i l e d ri ve rs at wo r k . If the we ather happens to be dry for a couple of day s , the trees
along the streets will be covered with dust. Some say Shanghai is simply a gi a n t
c o n s t ruction site; o t h e rs say it looks as if it had just surv i ved an indiscri m i n at e
b o m b i n g . People who have been away from a particular area for a few months are
apt to lose their way when they come back, and this has been an experience shared
by many old dwe l l e rs of the city. People tend to complain about taxi dri ve rs
making detours to cheat their customers without realizing that they too are
constantly trying to find their way. The city map of Shanghai has to be updat e d
e ve ry three months.
Huge German supermarkets have started to trade in Shanghai. So have big
Japanese department stores, luxury shops from New York’s Fifth Avenue and
Haagen Dazs ice-cream parlour s. Many other commodities have found their way to
Shanghai as well, such as Shell petrol, French perfume, Swiss chocolate and Philips
electrical appliances. There are also Irish pubs, Kobe style cafés, Bordeaux wine
shops, hard rock bars and even Tex-Mex restaurants, now very much in vogue in
Europe. After long years of impoverishment, people in Shanghai, infused with an
urge for material possession, are now rushing in all directions into shops, real estate
agencies, banks and all other places where money can be made and spent.
In the streets, pedestrians vie for passage with motor vehicles: shoddy taxis
converted from 125cc Happiness brand motorcycles, air-conditioned coaches,
swarms of motorized pedicabs ferrying first-grade pupils and trailing black smoke
behind them, shaky push carts full of construction debris, and imported Cadillacs
belonging to foreign businessmen. In the narrow streets built in the twenties, people
and cars go busily on their way. This is Shanghai today. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Street scene in the Pudong district,
the city’s new financial and
commercial centre.
Pedestrians, cyclists and 
motor traffic on Waibadu bridge.
Occupants of old Shanghai
move on as their homes are
demolished.
Lunch break in Huangpu park.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
An economic powerhouse
8 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Shanghai is the beacon of the liberalized
Chinese economy and the symbol of its
opening up to the world of international
business. Reform has been speedier and more
radical there than anywhere else in China, and
more foreign capital and state-of-the-art
technology is pouring into Shanghai than into
any other Chinese city.
Situated at the mouth of the Yangtze river,
Shanghai is China’s most populous conurbation,
with 13 million inhabitants. It comprises the city
itself (375 sq. km.) and a dozen satellite towns in
a quadrilateral measuring 120 km (north-south)
by 100 km (east-west).
At the start of the 19th century, it already
had half a million inhabitants. It then became the
main port of entry for colonial powers seeking to
penetrate the Chinese Empire. To some extent it
became a backwater after the communists took
power in 1949 and did not start prospering again
until it was declared a “special economic zone”
in the early 1990s.
The city’s economy is run by a local council
which reports directly to the central government.
It grew by 14 per cent a year between 1992 and
1 9 9 6 , easing off to 12.7 per cent in 1997.Fo r e i g n
direct investment was running at around $10
billion a year during the same period.The average
wage has tripled since 1990 and annual per
capita income is now over $3,000, compared with
only $860 for the rest of China (1997).
The city’s pride is its heavy industry
( s t e e l w o r k s, electric power stations, r e fineries and
s h i p y a r d s ) , machine-tool factories, c o m p u t e r
p l a n t s, textile mills, port activity and especially
finance—the Shanghai stock exchange, P u d o n g ,
is China’s equivalent of Wall Street.
But the effects of the Asian economic crisis
are beginning to be felt. Annual growth has
dropped below 10 per cent and foreign direct
investment fell by almost half in 1997.
Restructuring of state-owned fir m s, in the form of
mergers or shutdowns, has pushed up
u n e m p l o y m e n t , which is officially between 7 and
8 per cent but is thought to be double that.Air
and water pollution and poor waste disposal are
also causing concern. ■
Twilight in the old city.
Shanghai
Beijing ●
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E D I TO R I A L
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 9
■
In twelve months we enter the year 2000:what better time to chart a new course,by
working together every day to make possible a new society of peace,a society based
upon the democratic ideals enshrined in UN E S C O’s Constitution: l i b e rt y, j u s t i c e ,
equality and solidarity?
There can be no lasting peace without sustainable deve l o p m e n t . There can be no
d e velopment without lifelong educat i o n , without democracy, the sharing of resources to
avoid the immense disparities separating the developed from the less developed countri e s.
Within eve ry country, some citizens want for nothing, while others lack almost eve ry t h i n g .
The century that is drawing to a close has seen great discoveries and inventions, of
which antibiotics and telecommunications are but two, but the logic of force has preva i l e d
at a terrible cost—the lives of millions of human beings,m a ny of them in the flower of their
youth.Nothing of value has ever been achieved by violence and coercion.
We cannot continue to be indifferent to the wasting of our resources in the production
of weapons to be used against enemies, whether actual or potential.We cannot tolerate the
fact that , for economic reasons, thousands of helpless children are victims of sexual abu s e
or exploitation at work.We cannot continue to allow water to be polluted, forests to be
destroyed,the air of our planet to be contaminated.We cannot accept the predominance
of one culture over all others; nor can we afford to lose the diversity of the physical and
spiritual heritage that we must pass on to future generations.
We must say all together: enough is enough! Let us draw new hope from the turbu l e n t
h i s t o ry of the twentieth century.Through non-violent rebellion, c r e at i ve resistance and
refusal to accept the unacceptable, let us take steps to ease the transition to dialogue,
tolerance and reasoned consideration of that which divides us, and invent imagi n at i ve
s o l u t i o n s.
The Nobel Peace laureates,with UNESCO and the United Nations,have launched an
international appeal to transform the culture of war and violence into a culture of peace
and reconciliation.This initiative demands the participation of everyone,within families,
communities, nations and regions, and offers values that can inspire young people and
future generations to shape a world of justice,solidarity, liberty and prosperity.
Let us all, c h i l d r e n , young people, women and men of all ages, unite around this
manifesto and create a global movement for a culture of peace and non-violence. Let us
make our voices heard by decision-makers ,p a r l i a m e n t a ri a n s ,m ayo rs.Let us make full use
of the media to arouse the conscience and commitment of the world, working, giving,
sharing, reducing the distances that have divided us,healing the wounds that have given
us pain.
Let us dare to take up the challenge and fashion together this new future, and start ri g h t
away to prepare for the year 2000,the International Year for the Culture of Peace. ■
A time
for hope
Federico Mayor
The International Year for the Culture of Peace
proclaimed by the General Assembly of the United
Nations will begin at the end of this year. Now is
the time to start preparing to take part
We must say all together:
enough is enough! Let us
draw new hope from the
turbulent history of the
twentieth century. Through
non-violent rebellion,
creative resistance and
refusal to accept the
unacceptable, let us take
steps to ease the transition
to dialogue, tolerance and
reasoned consideration of
that which divides us, and
invent imaginative
solutions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
P L A N E T
■
“ We drink wat e r , we breathe air, but we
d o n ’t eat soil. It feeds us only
i n d i r e c t l y,” s ays A u s t rian pedologi s t
(soil expert) W i n f ried Blum, s e c r e t a ry -
general of the International Union of Soil
Science (IUSS). S o i l s , he say s , are the
forgotten part of the env i r o n m e n t . L i k e
most of his colleagues, he thinks it’s high
time the situation changed. “ We have to
make people realize we ’re destroying the
basis of all our lives,” he says.
There are no regularly updat e d
statistics, and the rate and extent at which
soils are deteri o r ating are a matter of
d e b at e . The French Scientific Research
Institute for Development in Co-operat i o n
( O R S TOM) notes that estimates in any
one region can va ry as much as 100 per
cent.
Damaging 
human activity
In A f ri c a , soil deteri o r ation statistics are
p a rticularly exaggerated because they are
linked to desertification. But in countries
south of the Sahara, the soil is not
necessarily degraded. Desertification may
be the result of a series of ye a rs of drought,
s ays Alain Ruellan, f o rmer president of the
I U S S . “Sometimes all it needs is some rain
and some farmers to bring it back to life.”
But scientists are virtually unanimous
about one thing: human activity is
increasingly damaging soils all over the
wo r l d . Soils constitute a fragile living
e nvironment which teems with biologi c a l
and physiochemical processes. T h e y
become degraded when erosion carri e s
them towards ri ve rs and the sea faster than
they can regenerate themselves nat u r a l l y.
Soils also become exhausted when they
cannot renew themselves, either naturally
or as a result of external inputs such as
manure.
Soil erosion worldwide affects an area
the size of the United Kingdom—more
Soils in  
The earth’s thin coat of soil, which
helps to feed us and is vital for
planetary ecosystems and climatic
balance, is becoming increasingly
threadbare
Soil erosion in Burkina Fa s o.
than 200,000 sq. k m . , s ays Blum. “ B u t
erosion is not the main problem,” s ay s
R u e l l a n , who stresses the importance of
c o m p a c t i o n , which modifies soils’
b i o l o gical activity and the circulation of
water. Data gathered by the Netherlands-
based Intern ational Soil Reference and
I n f o rm ation Centre (ISRIC) are
d i s t u r b i n g . The Centre says erosion now
affects more than 20 million sq. k m .
According to the UN Food and A gri c u l t u r e
Organization (FAO), at least 12 million of
them (an area bigger than China) have been
damaged by human activity in the past half
c e n t u ry. O ve r grazing by animals is
reckoned to have damaged 6.8 million sq.
km. (including 2.4 million in Africa and 2
million in Asia) and deforestation almost 6
million sq.km.
O ve r grazing and deforestat i o n
i m p ove rish the soil by destroying barri e rs to
erosion and depriving it of the organic
m atter which it normally gets through
ve g e t ation cove r. In addition, poor fa rm i n g
methods have damaged 5.5 million sq. k m .
and collecting fir e wood 1.4 million.
Expanding cities and industries have
d e graded several hundred thousand sq.k m .
of good soil. In the United Stat e s , 3 0 , 0 0 0
s q . k m . of fa rmland were lost to
u r b a n i z at i o n , road construction and mining
b e t ween 1967 and 1975.
Water and 
wind erosion
Things seem likely to get worse. FAO
estimates that at the present rate of decay,
2.5 million sq. k m . of fa rmland could
become barren by the year 2050. I S R I C
s ays water erosion is by far the most
common cause of soil degr a d at i o n ,
affecting about 11 million sq.k m . After that
comes wind erosion (5.5 million sq. km.)
and the action of chemical products (2.4
million sq. k m ) . Only 220,000 sq. k m . o f
soil are thought to be damaged by
p o l l u t i o n , almost 90 per cent of it in
Europe.
In the last few decades, d e ve l o p i n g
countries have followed the industrialized
world by adopting more intensive farming
m e t h o d s. Brazil is a good example. S o i l
d e gr a d ation began there four centuries ago,
when Europeans arri ved and deforestat i o n
b e g a n , s ays soil scientist José Pereira de
Quieroz Neto. It gathered speed in the 19th
c e n t u ry as coffee and sugar plantat i o n s
spread, and since the 1970s the growth of
e x p o rt agr o - i n d u s t ry has ravaged the
e nv i r o n m e n t . In just five ye a rs , b e t we e n
1975 and 1980, Brazil rose to be the wo r l d ’s
third biggest producer of soybeans after the
United States and China. It also became
one of the countries with the highest
amounts of agro-toxins per hectare going
into the soil.
“ We switched from small subsistence
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
torment
‘Soil is a resource
that must be
protected and
managed, like water,
forests and the air. Its
role in the
environment should
be valued more
highly.’
fa rms to big highly-mechanized estat e s ,”
s ays Pereira de Queiroz Neto. “ Fa rm
m a c h i n e ry sales rose 2,000 per cent
between 1975 and 1995.All this threw the
s o i l ’s biological structure and processes into
confusion and increased soil erosion four or
five f o l d . To d ay, b e t ween 200 and 250
million tonnes of soil are lost each year in
the state of São Paulo alone”. Multiply that
by 30 and you get a rough nat i o n w i d e
figure.
A reservoir
of greenhouse gases
Up to now, soils have been mainly
r e g a r d e d ,quite wrongly, as a basis for other
a c t i v i t i e s , s ays Marc Lat h a m , director of
F r a n c e ’s National Centre for A gr o n o m i c
Studies of Hot Countries (CNEARC). S o i l
is a limited resource. “It’s a resource that
must be protected and managed, like wat e r ,
forests and the air. Its role in the
e nvironment should be valued more
h i g h l y.” And that role is not a small one.
The eart h ’s surface is an enormous and
f r a gile biological reactor which prov i d e s
food for plants. It is also the home of most
land animal species and ensures the quality
of wat e r , which is filtered as it passes
through it.And it helps to create an overall
climatic equilibrium.
Soils have recently entered into the
s c i e n t i fic debate about global wa rm i n g .
“They are both a source and a sink for
What is soil?
■ Soil is the skin that coats the earth’s
s u r fa c e . It may be only a few millimetres
thick or several dozen metres. It cove rs two -
thirds of the total land area but only 22 per
cent of this (or 5.5 per cent of the eart h ’s total
s u r face) is suitable for fa rm i n g .
Soil is formed from rocks which are
broken down by the combined action of
wat e r ,a i r , and animal and plant life.
“In the begi n n i n g,”s ays French nat u r a l i s t
Y ves Coineau, “there was just rock. T h e n
lichens attached themselves to it, animals
came and ate the lichens and dust
accumulated. Then grass appeared and
attacked part of the rock’s surface with its
roots. The plant created organic matter,
which then decomposed and mixed in with
the debris from the rock. Gradually, very
s l ow l y, a small layer of earth form e d .”
A centimetre of earth may take betwe e n
50 and 2,000 ye a rs to form , depending on
the locat i o n . In other words it is not a rapidly
r e n e wable resource.
Soil is the least understood of the eart h ’s
major env i r o n m e n t s.“99 per cent of people,
whether they’re teachers or decision-makers ,
c a n ’t tell you what soil is,” s ays Alain Ruellan,
f o rmer president of the Intern ational Union
of Soil Science (IUSS). It is hard to see soil.
You have to make an effort to look at it, b y
bending down or digging holes. A b ove all,
says Ruellan, “soil, the source of life, is
identified with death, because bodies are
bu ried in it.” ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
P L A N E T
The squeeze on good earth
H u m a n - i n d u c e d
soil degra d a t i o n
of nitrous oxide emissions in intensive l y -
fa rmed regions where large quantities of
nitrous fertilizers are used.
Soils are also a fa bulous reservoir of
greenhouse gases.They contain two and a
half times more carbon, in organic matter
(humus and biomass), than all the
ve g e t ation on the planet, s ays Blum. T h e
amount of carbon in the soil varies widely.
D e s e rt soil, which has between 0.1 per cent
■ Is soil degradation a threat to our food
supply? At first glance, it doesn’t seem
s o : only half the wo r l d ’s arable land is being
farmed. But this can give a false sense of
security. There’s no point in having good
soils if you can’t use them, and rich soil is
often in places where there is no water and
where there are no people to farm it.
In the Middle East and in south and
east A s i a , where population pressures are
strong, there is no virgin land left to farm,
so the danger of soil degr a d ation is
growing. In the Amazon,in Siberia and in
some parts of A f ri c a , such as Zaire, there is
a lot of virgin land but hardly anyone to
farm it.
To bridge this gap between supply and
d e m a n d , some countries have tried to
resettle people, but such efforts have
usually been spectacular fa i l u r e s.“ Fa rm e rs
h ave ended up begging in city streets,” s ay s
greenhouse gases,” s ays Blum. Soil gi ve s
off large amounts of carbon dioxide.When
human activity causes erosion or soil loss,
the soil is no longer deep or rich enough to
store carbon, and carbon dioxide is either
released into the atmosphere or carri e d
directly to the sea. Soil is also responsible
for a third of all methane emissions,
especially in ri c e - gr owing areas in the
t r o p i c s. In addition, it produces 70 per cent
A l g e rian soil scientist Rabah Lahmar. I n
his recent book, Des sols et des hommes ( “ S o i l
and Pe o p l e ” ) , he describes a disastrous
e x p e riment in Indonesia, where the
g ove rnment sent people from Java to
B o rneo to clear the land and start up fa rm s.
W h at can be done about fertile land
where there is no water? The problem is a
serious one:the world’s irrigated areas are
only increasing by 1 per cent each year. In
the 1960s and 1970s, they were gr owing by
10 per cent a year.
The cocktail of population gr owth and soil
d e gr a d ation could become explosive and lead
to countless conflicts over good land. T h e
demand for food is going to gr ow, w h i l e
availability of fa rmland per capita in poor
c o u n t ries is expected to halve by the ye a r
2 0 1 0 , according to FAO—from 0.85 hectares
per person to 0.4. ■
Ozone hole
reaches 
record size
In 1998, the hole which forms each year in the
Antarctic ozone layer during the southern
h e m i s p h e r e ’s springtime reached an all-time
record size for the second half of September.
Satellite pictures taken by the US National
Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOA A )
showed that its area was 25 million sq. k m . —
about two and a half times the area of Europe
(from the Atlantic to the Urals). The last biggest
hole recorded in September was 22 million sq. k m .
in 1993.
The ozone layer in the stratosphere protects
humans, other living creatures and the world’s
ecosystems from the sun’s ultra-violet radiation.
The hole, which in September 1998 extended as
far as the southern tip of Argentina and Chile,
exposes people to greater risk of sunburn,skin
cancer and cataracts.
The situation would have been even more
serious if 165 countries had not pledged at a
conference in Montreal in 1987 to gradually stop
producing and using chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs).
These chemical compounds, which are used as
refrigerants and aerosol propellants, a r e
destroying the ozone layer and causing holes at
the South Pole and (to a lesser extent) at the
North Po l e. The Montreal Protocol came into
effect in 1995 for industrialized countries. O t h e r
nations must get in line with it by the year 2005
but have been asked to do so earlier if possible.
It will take at least 60 years for CFCs to disappear
completely from the stratosphere.
Some experts say the recent widening of the
hole above the Antarctic may be due to the
exceptional cold—up to minus 90° C—in the
stratosphere during the southern hemisphere’s
w i n t e r. The very low temperatures help form
polar clouds which also destroy the ozone layer.
Three researchers at the US National
Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA)’s
Goddard Institute for Space Studies say the
unusual cold is partly due to the emission of
greenhouse gases. These warm the lower
reaches of the atmosphere, they say, but cool the
stratosphere, which is between 12 and 27 km.
above the earth.
The 150 or so balloons which will be launched
into the stratosphere above the Antarctic starting
in October 2000 as part of the international
Stratéole programme should provide more
information about the factors involved in the
hole’s highly complicated chemistry. ■
■ Water erosion
■ Wind erosion
■ Chemical
degradation
■ Physical degradation
■ Stable
■ Deserts, glaciers, mountains
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
Industry asked to
clean up
its act
In 1998, Environics International, a priva t e
institute in Toronto (Canada), c o - o r d i n a t e d
for the second year running a worldwide survey
examining attitudes towards environmental
issues. The latest poll focused on the average
c i t i z e n ’s expectations in regard to corporate
and government commitment to protecting the
environment.During the first quarter of 1998,
34,475 people were surveyed in 30 countries1 o n
five continents representing 68 per cent of the
world’s population. In 19 of the 30 countries
c o n c e r n e d , most people polled considered that
business and industry do not make a big effort
to ensure a clean environment. The highest
rates of those who believe companies are not
doing enough to curb pollution are from Greece
(88 per cent of those polled),Argentina (76 per
cent), Turkey (73 per cent) and Russia (72 per
c e n t ) . The lowest rates are in Germany and
Indonesia (39 per cent), China (36 per cent)
and South Africa (35 per cent).
People want governments to do more
about the situation.In all the countries except
Finland, Nigeria and Indonesia, over 50 per
cent of those polled said they believe that
existing regulations do not go far enough or
are extremely inadequate.
Should other alternatives be tried to
compel companies and industries to pollute
less or not at all? The idea of increasing
financial incentives for “clean” companies or
granting them tax breaks is considered a
good one in the United States, C a n a d a ,
Germany and Fr a n c e. The Ja p a n e s e,
Colombians and Finns prefer publishing
pollution statistics to embarrass offending
companies into cleaning up their acts. The
1997 survey revealed that,in the 24 countries
where the poll was taken, sensitiveness to
environmental issues ran very high—70 to 90
per cent of those polled said they were very or
fairly concerned, including in developing
nations. ■
1.Argentina,Australia,Brazil,Canada,Chile, China,
C o l o m b i a , Fi n l a n d , Fr a n c e, G e r m a n y, G r e e c e,
Hungary, India,Indonesia,Italy, Japan, Kazakhstan,
M e x i c o, N i g e r i a , New Zealand, Po l a n d , R u s s i a ,
South Africa, South Korea, Spain, Turkey, United
Kingdom,Uruguay, United States and Venezuela.
First steps to a world soil c o n v e n t i o n
and 0.2 per cent of organic mat t e r , t r a p s
much less of it than forest soil (2-8 per cent
organic matter) or peat bog, which is up to
90 per cent organic matter.
The still-unanswered question is
whether soils absorb more greenhouse gas
than they produce. In other wo r d s , can they
fix and store the amount of excess carbon
d i oxide which is produced by human
activity and is causing global warming? “It
depends a lot on local conditions,” s ay s
B l u m . “The best soils for this are deep ones
b e n e ath forests in temperate parts of
Europe and in some tropical regi o n s.”
Stocks of carbon can also be renewed by
m a s s i ve reforestat i o n , with pri o rity going
to regions which have been damaged and
made unfit for agriculture.
The effect of global wa rming on soils is
also ve ry hard to figure out. The Sahara
D e s e rt is undoubtedly going to spread,
scientists say. But at the same time, h u g e
land areas near the poles will thaw as ice
melts. In a few decades time, we might be
able to gr ow wheat in nort h e rn Canada and
Siberia. ■
Sophie Boukhari
■ “ C o n s i d e ring the centuries or
millennia required for soil formation,
it is important not to allow valuable time
to pass but to move rapidly towards the
sustainable use of soils. Therefore it is of
paramount importance to expand the
C o nvention on Desert i fic ation into a
comprehensive Soil Convention for the
sustainable use of soils worldwide.” The
scientists who wrote this passage, taken
from the introduction to a recent
proposal for a convention on the
sustainable use of soils, did not mince
their wo r d s. The convention on
desertification, which was adopted at the
Rio Earth Summit in June 1992 and
came into effect in December 1996, is
weak. The “convention for Africa”, as it
was once nicknamed, only applies to arid
or semi-arid regions. It is only a step.
“Desertification is a localized problem,
but soil degradation affects the whole
p l a n e t ,” s ays Alain Ruellan, f o rm e r
president of the International Union of
Soil Science (IUSS).
So the scientists got down to wo r k . A
p r e l i m i n a ry text was published in July 1998
by the founders of the Tutzing “ T i m e
Ecology”project, based at the Evangelical
Academy in Tutzing, a southern suburb of
Munich (Germany).The idea had been in
the air since the Rio conference, s ay s
M a rtin Held, leader of the
m u l t i d i s c i p l i n a ry project. “Then leading
e nvironmental experts like David Pimentel
of Cornell Unive rsity (New York state) and
H a rtmut Grassl, head of the World Climat e
Research Progr a m m e , asked us to draft the
text of a convention,” he says.
At a meeting held in Tutzing from 22-
25 November 1998, the IUSS wa s
m a n d ated to conduct extensive
international consultations about the text,
especially among all those who use the soil,
such as fa rm e rs , urban planners and
N G O s. So the process towards final United
Nations adoption of a convention has only
just begun.If it lasts as long as that leading
to adoption of the convention on
d e s e rt i fic at i o n , the new treaty might get off
the ground around the year 2015. ■
+ …
● I S R I C, t e l : 31 317 47 17 11
I n t e r n e t :w w w. i s r i c. n l
● International Union of Soil Science,
I n t e r n e t :w w w. c i ra d . f r / i s s s / a i s s e. h t m l
● FAO, t e l : 39 06 570 51
Internet: www.fao.org
S o u r c e :U N E P, I S R I C .
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
Building blocks of  
In a world of cut-throat competition, Denmark is a European
leader in worker training and education. The LEGO group offers
its employees courses that are not directly related to their jobs
in a bid to educate ‘the whole person’
■
“Danish industries are way ahead of
i n d u s t ries in other European
c o u n t ries when it comes to training
and upgrading the skills of employe e s ,” s ay s
C h ristian Braad, a consultant at the
E d u c ational Department of the
Confederation of Danish Industries.
In a labour force survey carried out in
1996 by Eurostat , the European Union
S t atistics Office, more than 8 million
Europeans over 30 years of age were asked
whether they had received any kind of
teaching or training in the four we e k s
preceding the interv i e w. Denmark came
out on top with around 12 per cent of
respondees answe ring “ ye s ” , more than
three times the EU average.
“And we are not resting on our laurels,”
Braad continues.“ E d u c ation is increasingly
becoming a focus area for both small and
large companies.Whereas opportunities for
education once went mainly to employees
in high positions and skilled wo r k e rs ,t h e r e
is now a marked trend for unskilled wo r k e rs
to be offered—or even required to at t e n d —
various kinds of educational courses.With
increasing globalization companies have to
be flexible,and so does the workforce.”
Braad adds that the flexible and
i n d e p e n d e n t , but gove rn m e n t - s u b s i d i z e d ,
Danish system of skills training centres is an
indispensable tool to achieve this.The system
was introduced in the 1960s to offer short
courses for workers as a response to
increasing use of technology and demand for
q u a l i fied labour. L at e r , other kinds of adult
e d u c ation were ava i l a b l e , focusing more on
“ s o f t ” issues not directly related to specific
job skills.
“The system can accommodate the
special needs of individual companies,”
Braad say s , “and at the same time offer
general training and education which is not
job- or company - s p e c i fic. In the short term
companies may complain that their
e m p l oyees are taught things that they
cannot directly use in their present job. O n
the other hand it increases the mobility of
the wo r k f o r c e , and this is important for
Danish industries in general.”
Two reasons are cited to explain why
“ s o f t ” c o u rses which seek to educate “ t h e
whole pers o n ” are increasingly used by big
Danish companies and why employees are
encouraged to take them. One is the need
for a more widely educated workforce as a
result of the general trend to delegate powe rs
to floor level—to replace foremen with self-
g ove rning gr o u p s.The other is an increased
focus on quality control as the responsibility
of each individual rather than of outside
c o n t r o l l e rs.
Right from the start the Danish
government subsidized workers attending
training courses. Today it pays around 70
per cent of an employe e ’s salary while he or
she is on a course; the employer pays the
r e s t . In some cases the gove rnment eve n
refunds the topping up of the salary.
Education
for unskilled workers
Most Danish companies make use of the
s y s t e m , but some big companies have taken
the lead in developing new kinds of cours e s.
One of them is the LEGO group, a toy-
m a n u fa c t u ring firm which employs close on
10,000 people worldwide.The success of
LEGO, a term formed from the Danish
words “Leg Godt” ( “ p l ay we l l ” ) , has been
largely built on 8-studded plastic bri c k s ,e a c h
m e a s u ring just under 5 cm3, which can be
pressed together and assembled into a wide
range of toy constru c t i o n s. Some 189 billion
of them were moulded between 1949 and
the end of 1997. The company has a
workforce of 4,300 at the bustling town of
B i l l u n d ,where LEGO was founded in 1932.
In 1987 LEGO set up its ow n
Danish workers are three times more likely to have access to education and training than workers
elsewhere in Europe.
Education is a priority for small and 
large businessses—and their workforce—as they adapt to
globalization
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
  l e a r n i n g
e d u c ational department and increasingly
focused on unskilled wo r k e rs and soft
c o u rses on such subjects as “ P r e p a ri n g
yourself for education”,“Improving basic
reading and writing skills”, E n g l i s h ,
information technology, management and
team bu i l d i n g . LEGO employees are
encouraged to take courses both duri n g
work-time and during their time off, t h at
do not necessarily have any relevance to
their jobs.Around 1,500 people have taken
p a rt in the courses since 1995. A l t h o u g h
there are no statistics to prove it, L E G O
feels sure that the courses have a positive
impact on job sat i s faction and productivity.
“In a fast changing wo r l d ,w h at you did
yesterday will not suffice tomorrow,” says
Ku rt A u l b j e r g, head of LEGO’s human
resource development depart m e n t .
“ Traditional skills-upgrading courses are
not sufficient. Our approach to education
has to be much more broadminded.”
In other wo r d s , the LEGO gr o u p
cannot afford only to make use of the hands
of its employe e s. The company wants the
whole person.
Poul Erik Pe t e rs e n , a metal worker and
shop steward for 150 metal workers, went
on a personality cours e . He started off
feeling sceptical.
“I have been on several job-relat e d
c o u rses to upgrade special skills,” Pe t e rs e n
s ay s ,“and nobody questions the relevance of
this kind of educat i o n . Since becoming a
shop steward two ye a rs ago, I have also
attended a six-week course laid on by my
trade union. But being on a course that
focuses on your personality rather than yo u r
professional skills is quite another story. A l l
of a sudden you are being questioned about
w h at you do when you are off the job. D o
you have skills, e x p e riences or talents that
can make you perform better at wo r k ? ”
Pe t e rsen cites the case of a yo u n g
secretary who had to get a signature from
her superior for every piece of expenditure
she endorsed from her depart m e n t , n o
m atter how small. “ D u ring a course she
mentioned that she was the treasurer of a
big sports association and responsible for
an annual budget of around $40,000.As a
consequence she was gi ven more
responsibility in her daily wo r k , t h u s
relieving her superior of simple duties and
increasing her own job satisfaction.”
Made-to-measure
training courses
Pe t e rsen is in favour of a flexible approach
whereby each employee can more or less
design his or her own educational plan.
“With so many people from ve ry different
b a c k gr o u n d s , you cannot make the same
c o u rses compulsory for eve ryo n e ,” he say s.
“ T h at would have a negat i ve impact on
m o t i vat i o n .We have to realize that people
who have worked here for many ye a rs ,w h o
joined us immediately after school,and who
h ave been used to taking orders ,m ay not be
The LEGO group has had its own educational department since 1987.
Even unskilled workers must be capable of taking responsibilities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
When schools
fall down on the
job
Primary school enrolment is steadily growing
around the world,including in developing
c o u n t r i e s, where the number of pupils rose from
305 million (77 per cent of all school-age
children) in 1970 to nearly 561 million (86 per
cent) in 1995. It is increasing faster than the
population in most countries except in sub-
Saharan Africa,where the number of children
out of school grew by 12 million between 1985
and 1995.
The numbers speak for themselves, but what
about the quality of education provided? Th e
question is an urgent one. Going to school is
one thing,graduating from it is another. In the
industrialized countries, 99 per cent of children
completed primary school in 1994-95,but only
just over half managed to do so in the least
developed countries. In the developing world
as a whole, only three out of four children fin i s h
primary school and can read.
What about the rest? A study done in China
showed that nearly half the children in rural
areas who drop out of primary school work on
farms and that 7.5 per cent have part-time jobs,
a figure which rises to more than 27 per cent
among their urban counterparts. Both in urban
and rural areas, more than a third of children
stay at home.
Some 250 million children aged from five to
14 in developing countries are forced to earn a
living and half of them combine work, school
and other unpaid activities. Th r e e - fifths of all
child workers live in Asia and a third in Africa.
Paid work is both the cause and the result of
dropping out of school, which remains one of
the biggest problems of basic education.
A new UN E S C O report entitled W a s t e d
Opportunities: When Schools Fail looks at the
problem of wastage in the school system and
gives many examples of original steps being
taken to stop it. ■
For more information,contact:
International Consultative Forum on Education for
All
UNESCO
7 Place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France.
Tel:+33 (0)1 45 68 08 35
Fax:+33 (0)1 45 68 56 29
E-mail:efa@unesco.org
Website:http://www.education.unesco.org/efa
16 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
prepared for change, to take responsibility
and become students again.” On the other
h a n d , Pe t e rsen adds, “all employees must
prepare themselves for this. Otherwise we
will lose out to other countri e s. ”
B e n ny Pe t e rs e n , a shop stewa r d
representing 70 unskilled wo r k e rs , a gr e e s.
“Life—and working life in part i c u l a r — h a s
become a process of ongoing educat i o n ,”h e
s ay s. He joined the LEGO group 20 ye a rs
a g o, and he has lost track of the number of
c o u rses he has attended since then. In his
opinion one of the best courses is the one-
week course on “ P r e p a ring yo u rself for
e d u c at i o n ” .
“It may not look ve ry relevant to most
wo r k e rs and I have met quite a few who we r e
ve ry sceptical beforehand,” he say s. “But to
me it shows that ‘soft issues’ like psychology
are as relevant and important as hard skills.”
The LEGO group makes wide use of
local education institutions, using their
regular courses as well as courses specially
designed for its employe e s.“ We are extremely
f o rt u n ate in that Denmark has this highly
d e veloped system of skills training centres
and other educational institutions that offer
a va riety of courses that are flexible to the
needs of local bu s i n e s s ,” explains A u l b j e r g .
“ R e p r e s e n t at i ves of local municipalities
and counties sit on the boards of these
i n s t i t u t i o n s ,and trade unions and employe rs ’
associations are also represented. This
ensures a ve ry close dialogue between the
institutions and local companies and enables
the institutions to respond ve ry quickly to
local needs. If the LEGO group starts up a
new production facility in a regi o n , we talk
with the local schools and can have special
c o u rses designed to meet our needs.”
“This benefits both the employer and
the employe e ,” Poul Erik Pe t e rsen say s. “ I n
fa c t , it can also be used as a means to
a c h i e ve job securi t y.The LEGO group and
most other big companies have peak
p e riods eve ry ye a r , but also periods with
less wo r k . D u ring off-peak peri o d s
e m p l oyees are often laid off or moved to
other depart m e n t s. With good planning
these periods can be used for cours e s ,
which—again—is to the benefit of all of us.”
But Aulbjerg emphasizes that the
g ove rnment subsidy is not the driving force
behind his company ’s education policy. “ I t
is based on our needs and pri o ri t i e s ,” h e
says,“and in some cases we have declined
subsidies that we were entitled to.” ■
Jesper Heldgaard
Skills gaps
in the workforce
The available training facilities are clearly
insufficient and too often inaccessible.
According to the UIE study, c a rried out in
six industrialized countri e s ,b e t ween 14 and
43 per cent of adults had spent at least six
h o u rs in training during the previous ye a r.
B e t ween a third and a half of them paid for
training out of their own pocket, despite the
fact that big firms in industrialized countri e s
spend between one and five per cent of their
p e rmanent wage bill on such training.
G ove rnment aid is negligible and, a c c o r d i n g
to the study,c o m p rises less than 20 per cent
of all adult training bu d g e t s.
The second big problem is that links
b e t ween this form of training and
traditional education methods leave much
to be desired and prevent the deve l o p m e n t
of joint efforts in the field.
In developing countries, such training
obviously does not reach the huge inform a l
s e c t o r. B u t , especially in big companies,
there is more and more training. ■
■ Adult education used to be a luxury,
but today it has become an imperative,
especially in commercial companies.
In a “ k n owledge economy ” ,
competitivity depends on “ h u m a n
r e s o u r c e s ” yet skills gaps are glari n g l y
apparent in much of the labour force.The
US gove rn m e n t ’s adult educat i o n
d e p a rt m e n t , for example, reckons that
almost half of A m e rican wo r k e rs are “ at
risk”,in the sense that they don’t have the
n e c e s s a ry educational base to be trained in
areas where jobs will be opening up in the
next 20 years.
But the pressure is on for short - t e rm
p r o fit a b i l i t y.As a result, the first to be trained
a r e ,p a r a d ox i c a l l y, c o m p a n i e s ’b e s t - q u a l i fie d ,
most reliable wo r k e rs , who also tend to be
m e n . Those on temporary or part - t i m e
contracts are pretty much left out in the cold.
A study carried out by UN E S C O’s
I n t e rn ational Institute for Education (UIE) in
H a m burg says a “dual learning society” i s
e m e r ging and “the skills gap” is widening.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 17
Gearing up
for the granny
boom 
“A society for all ages” is the slogan of the International Year of Older Persons, which the
General Assembly of the United Nations has decided to observe in 1999.
In taking this decision, the General Assembly wanted to draw attention to the extent and
implications of the “longevity revolution”. The “granny and grandad boom”—especially the
granny boom, since on average women live longer than men—is becoming a virtually universal
phenomenon. Worldwide, the number of persons aged 65 and over will have increased fourfold
between 1955 and 2025, and their percentage of the total population will have doubled (from
5.3 per cent in 1965 to 10 per cent in 2025).
In the more developed countries, where one person in five will be elderly, traditional policies
towards aging are running out of steam, and two major social advances—the lowering of the
retirement age and publicly financed pension schemes—are being widely contested.The problem
is even more acute in the developing countries, where three-quarters of the world’s older people
will be living 25 years from now. States are not providing care, traditional family structures are
breaking down, and private mutual aid schemes are few and far between.As yet, however, no
moves have been made in these countries to defuse this demographic time-bomb.
There is a big risk that a kind of apartheid may develop between older people and a working
population which would regard the elderly as an economic burden. Elderly people should not be
segregated in this way by ageism.They must have opportunities to use their availability, their
experience, their talents and their generosity in exchange for the solidarity they have the right
to expect. It is through this kind of give-and-take that the world’s “greying” societies will be
able to maintain or rediscover their unity. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
The longevity  
■
O ver the past hundred ye a rs a silent and
unprecedented revolution in longevity has
occurred: people living in the industrialized
world have on average gained 25 ye a rs of life, t h a n k s
largely to reduction of deaths at childbirth and
infancy, and to control of diseases associated with
old age. This is nearly equal to life expectancy
advances over the preceding 5,000 years. In many
c o u n t ri e s , the 85-plus age group is the most rapidly
growing.
The next century may bring even more
d r a m atic increases. P r e vention and elimination of
disease along with control over the aging process
itself could push our life spans from a wo r l d
average of 66 ye a rs today to closer to 110 or 120
ye a rs — w h at scientists believe to be our “ n at u r a l
life span” because many individuals have lived that
l o n g . Some scientists talk of pushing the
b o u n d a ries further by gaining control over the
genes that determine longevity.
But our enhanced life spans do not come
without a price. As the demographic balance
increasingly tips to the elderly, societies are seeing
their cultural, political and economic orders put
to the test.
Among the most basic questions facing us are:
At a time when the welfare state is coming under
at t a c k , who will be responsible for the fin a n c i a l
s u p p o rt of the aged, the state or the individual? W i l l
the aging of societies lead to economic stagnation?
Will the aged form a politically powerful minority
and if so, what demands will that group make? In
In the coming century the human life span may rise
as high as 120 years. What are the implications of an
aging world?
* The International Longevity
Center-USA,New York
extending our time on this planet, will we also be
able to maintain quality of life, or are we doomed to
pass our later ye a rs in sickness, frailty and fin a n c i a l
incertitude? Culturally, will some of the attention
now concentrated on youth shift to the elderly? As
women outlive men in most of the industri a l i z e d
world, many of the challenges associated with old
age are particularly pertinent to them.
In extending our time on this
planet, will we also be able to
maintain quality of life?
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 19
The granny boom
  re v o l u t i o n Robert Butler*
Our gr e ater longevity has brought fundamental
changes to our lives in ways that we either take for
granted or of which we are hardly awa r e . Fo r
e x a m p l e , in 1920, a 10-year-old in the US only had
a 40 per cent chance of having two of his or her
possible four grandparents alive.Today, that figure
is 80 per cent.Thus, despite romantic images of a
tighter-knit family of former day s , in fa c t ,t o d ay we
h ave a much gr e ater proportion of multi-
generational families than ever before.
In many way s , life is improving for the aged.
For example, in the 1950s the average age of
admissions into nursing homes was 65. N ow the
age is closer to 81. To d ay, older people in
i n d u s t rialized countries also have more choices
about how they live: assisted living, home care or
community-based care, for example. M o r b i d i t y
r ates are falling as a result of progress against heart
disease and stroke.
‘Silver industries’ 
to cater for the over-50s
One of the most fundamental issues is how to
s u p p o rt the aged fin a n c i a l l y. Different societies have
come up with different approaches. Despite its
c u rrent economic difficulties, Japan adheres to a
system under which the state provides for
institutional and home care of the elderly. T h e
United States is leading the way in a profit - o ri e n t e d ,
managed care system, which emphasizes primary
c a r e , disease prevention and monitoring of
d i s t ri bu t i o n . H owe ve r , the US is not going fa r
enough nor moving rapidly enough gi ven the
t r a j e c t o ry of old age. M e a n w h i l e , the former Sov i e t
Union has made major cutbacks in health care
while slashing pension benefits as well.
So far much of our thinking about the aged has
focused on them as a financial bu r d e n . But that
attitude ignores fundamental facts that suggest to
some extent that the ve ry opposite is tru e .To d ay in
the US pension funds amount to $2.7 tri l l i o n .T h i s
is money that helps provide capital for investment
in production of goods and serv i c e s , e ve ry t h i n g
from roads to computer software start - u p s. O ve r a l l ,
in the US, pension funds account for a quarter of all
capital formation.
We must also remember that the aged represent
an important group of consumers with ve ry specific
n e e d s. T h u s , in  Ja p a n , for example, a range of
“ s i l ver industri e s ” has gr own up to cater to the
h o u s i n g, t r ave l ,r e c r e ation and other needs of those
over 50.Similarly, in the United States companies
talk increasingly about the senior or mature market.
In recognition of the potential of this market, a
number of publishers and electronic community
builders have set up Internet web sites targeted at
the aged, complete with advertisements aimed at
Growth of the population aged 65 and over (in millions)
1965 ■ 1995 ■ 2025 ■
S o u r c e s : World Population Prospects - The 1996 Revision, New Yo r k , United Nations, 1 9 9 8 , and 
The Sex and Age Distribution of the World’s Populations - The 1996 Revision, New Yo r k , United Nations, 1 9 9 7 .
178
5.3
371
6.5
802
10
88
9
157
13.5
247
20.2
903
8
214
4.7
555
8.1
8
3.1
17
3.0
46
3.9
World More developed
regions
Less developed
regions
Least
developed
countries
World More developed
regions
Less developed
regions
Least
developed
countries
Growth of the population aged 65 and over as a percentage 
of total population
%
800
700
600
500
400
300
200
100
0
20
15
10
5
0
winning their custom. M e a n w h i l e , in at t e m p t i n g
to add to their bottom lines, p h a rm a c e u t i c a l s
companies increasingly concentrate on needs of the
e l d e r l y : in industrialized countries those over 65
constitute roughly 15 per cent of the populat i o n
but account for some 30 per cent of
pharmaceuticals used.
Po l i t i c a l l y, the elderly will become a more
p owerful group with whom political parties in
democratic countries at least will have to reconcile
their policies. In the US, for example, the “ b a b y
b o o m e rs ,” b o rn between 1946 and 1964 will begi n
to retire in the year 2008.In the decade beginning
from 2020, they will constitute 20 per cent of the
US population and as much as 30 per cent of the
e l e c t o r at e .Political candidates will no doubt have to
pay increasing attention to their needs.
As societies struggle to address the challenges of
a ging populat i o n s , mere reorganization of the serv i c e s
to the elderly is no longer adequat e .We require a
And the Lord said, M y
s p i rit shall not alwa y s
s t ri ve with man, fo r
t h at he also is fle s h : ye t
his days shall be an
h u n d red and twe n t y
ye a rs.
Genesis VI, 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
redesign of the way we approach the needs of the
e l d e r l y. In order for redesign to take place, some of our
basic assumptions about the nature and character of
old age must be questioned. This is already
h a p p e n i n g . B e ginning in the 1950s, i n d u s t ri a l i z e d
society began to perceive old age not as a period of life
t h at is biologically fixe d , but as one that is mutable.
The feel-good 
factor
There are a number of reasons for these
c h a n ging views. For one, the self-image of the aged
has been changi n g . I n c r e a s i n g l y, they now see
t h e m s e l ves as vibrant and energetic and are not
willing to let life end at retirement. S e c o n d l y,
gerontologists now have a better understanding of
the underlying mechanism of aging itself. This is
leading to an appreciation of the possibility and
reality of interve n t i o n s , both preve n t at i ve and
therapeutic.
The gr owing demographic weight of the elderly
is forcing us to reevaluate many of our old views.
Since people are living longer, should they not wo r k
longer as well? To that question I would gi ve a
qualified yes. In the US, if we do not change our
at t i t u d e s , we may by around the year 2020 have
some 60 million idle people in retirement not
c o n t ri buting to society. We cannot afford to have
so many people idle. Passage of the A g e
D i s c ri m i n ation Act in 1988 was a step forward as it
no longer made retirement dependent on age itself.
The market place has already absorbed millions of
women and minorities, so there is no reason why
jobs should not be found for older people as well.
Yet there are still many challenges ahead of us.
The developing world has not generally enjoye d
the same increase in longevity and decreased birth
r ates that have been seen in industrialized countri e s.
Sixty per cent of persons over the age of 60
c u rrently live in the developing world and this is
expected to increase to 80 per cent by around the
year 2025. T h u s , there will be profound social,
8.6
10.5
15.2
12.2
20.1
34.1
6.7 7.8
12.3
6 5.6 6.5
% World More developed
regions
Less developed
regions
Least
developed
countries
The over 65s as a percentage of the population aged 15-64 years
1950 ■ 1995 ■ 2025 ■
S o u r c e : World Population Monitoring 1996, New Yo r k , United Nations, 1 9 8 8 , and The Sex and Age Distribution of the
World’s Populations - The 1996 Revision, New Yo r k , United Nations, 1 9 9 7 .
35
30
25
20
15
10
5
0
Life expectancy:
two big 
e x c e p t i o n s
People are living longer in many parts of the world,
but at least two world regions constitute an exception
to this trend,according to a forthcoming United Nations
p u b l i c a t i o n , World Population Prospects—the 1998
Revision.
In sub-Saharan Africa,the Aids pandemic is raging.
The worst-hit countries are mostly in the south—South
A f r i c a , B o t s wa n a , M a l a w i , M o z a m b i q u e, N a m i b i a ,
Zambia and Zimbabwe—except for Kenya and Rwa n d a .
More than 10 per cent of the population in this
region is infected with HIV, the virus which leads to A i d s.
This means that life expectancy at birth is falling.It has
already dropped from 53.4 years in the period 1985-1990
to 47.6 for 1995-2000,and is expected to fall further to
47.1 in the period 2010-2015. Without the pandemic,
the figures would have been respectively 54.2, 58 and
63.4 years. So Aids will have caused a drop of 16.3 years
in life expectancy over a quarter of a century.
A similar, though much smaller trend is developing in
three Asian countries (Cambodia, India and Thailand),
where the pandemic is expected to cut life expectancy by an
average 1.6 years over the same period, and in two Latin
American nations (Brazil and Haiti), where the predicted
drop is 1.4 years.
In the former eastern bloc countries, life expectancy
has been growing more slowly than elsewhere and is
now falling. The trend began in the fading years of
communism and has since gathered speed mainly for
economic reasons (the massive reduction in pensions)
and because of social factors (loosening family ties). L i f e
expectancy at birth in Russia, which rose from 67.6 to
69.2 years between 1980 and 1985,fell to 66.5 in 1990
and 64.4 in 1995. It is also dropping in Ukraine (from
70.4 in 1985 to 68.8 in 1995),Belarus (71.3 to 69.6) and
Bulgaria (71.6 to 71.2), though the figure is stationary in
Romania (69.5 years). ■
+ …
● “Longevity and quality of
l i f e : a worldwide re v o l u t i o n ”
was the theme of the third
congress of the International
Council for Global Health
P r o g r e s s, which was held at
UN E S C O’s Paris Headquarters
from 18 to 20 May 1998. Th e
proceedings will be published by
Plenum Publishing Corporation,
New Yo r k .
+ …
● Régine Boutra i s,
International Council for
Global Health Pro g re s s,
Te l : +33 (0) 1 45 59 37 00
Fa x : +33 (0) 1 45 59 38 85 
E - m a i l :c i p g s @ c l u b - i n t e r n e t
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 21
The granny boom
To me, old age is
a l ways fifteen ye a rs
older than I am.
Bernard Baruch (1879-1965),
United States
Aging Chinese
face a w e l f a re g a p
The state welfare system is being dismantled, but a new pension scheme 
is not yet ready to take over
■
Liu Cunwa used to be a farmer in Sujiakou
Village in north China’s Shanxi Prov i n c e .
Now in his seventies, no longer able to work
and with no children to take care of him,Liu begs
or waits for hand-outs from villagers to get by.
Like millions of other elderly in the wo r l d ’s
fastest aging developing country, Liu has fa l l e n
through the gaps as the stat e - run cradle-to-
c r e m ation we l fare system is being dismantled and
a new old-age pension regime based on We s t e rn
models is slowly being bu i l t .
The gove rnment will have to work fast to fil l
the gaps. China is the wo r l d ’s fastest agi n g
d e veloping country. Within the next 30 ye a rs ,
there will be an estimated 275 million people—
more than the present total population of the
United States—in China over the age of 60.T h at
will mean roughly one in five people will be in
retirement or close to it.As a result of a one-child
family policy aimed at stopping the country ’s
e x p l o s i ve population gr ow t h , the financial bu r d e n
will become heavier for the shrinking proport i o n
of working people.
Pension reform:
a high priority
Tr a d i t i o n a l l y, the aged could rely on the
s u p p o rt of their children and gr a n d c h i l d r e n .A f t e r
C h i n a ’s 1949 communist revolution people like
Liu were guaranteed food, c l o t h i n g, medical care,
housing and bu rial expenses through the collective
fa rm .
Under the free-market reforms begun in the
l ate 1970s, Chinese rural families are once again
independent fa rm e rs. While the move to pri vat e
farming has made many parts of rural China rich,
it has also left the aged once again dependent on
either their families or themselves.
So far the gove rnment is only beginning to
introduce pension schemes in the country s i d e .
As a result of today’s one-child
family policy the task of
supporting tomorrow’s elderly
will fall on a shrinking
population of working people.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
■
With a rapidly aging population and a huge
p r o p o rtion of its elderly people opting for
early retirement, Finland is facing the
prospect of unprecedented labour short a g e .T h e
r ate of greying in Finland is faster than in other
European Union countries and the number of
young wo r k e rs replacing the retiring elders is not
p r o p o rt i o n at e .
The average age of the Finnish population is on
the rise owing partly to changes in the age groups
and partly to the increased life expectancy rat e .
To d ay the elderly constitute 15 per cent of the total
population of around five million.This reflects the
fact that Finland witnessed a higher birth rate than
a ny other country during the We s t ’s post-World Wa r
II baby boom.
Though the stat u t o ry retirement age is 65 ye a rs ,
80 per cent of the population retire before they
reach 60 years of age.Carin Lindqvist-Virtanen, a
senior researcher at the Ministry of Social Affairs,
Helsinki,says that if the present trend to take early
retirement continues “then it will cause seri o u s
problems for the labour market in the future as not
m a ny young people will be there to replace the
r e t i ring wo r k e rs. The massive exodus [into
retirement] could also weaken the financial position
of the pension scheme.”
Among Finnish men, p a rt i c i p ation in the labour
market for the 55-59 group is among the lowest of
the Organization of Economic Co-operation and
D e velopment (OECD) countri e s. One main reason
F i n l a n d ’s 
youthful o l d i e s
Finland’s baby-boomers are taking early retirement and there aren’t enough
youngsters to replace them 
for this deve l o p m e n t , analysts say, has been the
g ove rn m e n t ’s encouragement of early retirement
during the economic recession of the early 1990s.
This included favourable options like handsome
pension and unemployment benefits allow i n g
people to retire comfortably at the age of 55.
Age discri m i n ation has been cited by social
scientists as another factor leading employees to
take early retirement. According to a report by
F i n l a n d ’s National Committee on A ging policy,
elderly people are subject to discri m i n ation and
receive degrading treatment.“The elderly are still
frequently treated as economically non-productive
p e o p l e , a care burden or encumbrance and a
medical problem,” it says.
The government has also been discussing the
possibility of raising the retirement age to 67 years
to tackle the labour shortage problem. H owe ve r ,
critics argue that there is little point in doing that
until more people can be encouraged to work up to
the statutory retirement age of 65 years.
The Finnish government last year launched a
five-year programme to stop age discrimination in
the wo r k p l a c e .Annikki Korhonen, senior Adviser at
the National Research and Development Centre
for We l fare and Health, s ays that this Nat i o n a l
P r o gramme for A ging Wo r k e rs (NPAW) seeks to
i n i t i ate a change in attitude which will help improve
the position of aging wo r k e rs and reduce the exodus
of labour. ■
Ethirajan Anbarasan
There has been much more progress on this front in
the cities, but even there progress has been slow.
Before the free-market economic reform s ,s t at e -
owned enterp rises provided for the elderly. N ow
the central gove rnment is cutting back on subsidies
to those enterp ri s e s , forcing them to look at the
bottom line. Recognizing that stat e - run enterp ri s e s
wo n ’t reach profitability without shedding their
social we l fare responsibilities, the gove rnment is
trying to find new ways of providing social safety
n e t s. T h u s , pension reform is being gi ven a high
priority. And none too soon either: elderly people
h ave recently mounted protests in a number of large
cities to press their companies to honour pension
commitments.
The aim is eventually to have a national pension
scheme with individuals, their employe rs and
insurance firms providing the bulk of retirement
f u n d s. The gove rnment is to be responsible only
for supplements.At the moment, t h o u g h ,m u n i c i p a l
governments are handling pension reforms in the
best way they see fit.
For example, in Foshan City in the southern
province of Guangdong, a pension fund has been
set up with employe rs contri buting an amount
e q u i valent to 10 per cent of wo r k e rs ’ wa g e s.Wo r k e rs
pay four per cent of their pay to the fund.
“The first step is always difficult to take,” said
Zhou Xiaochuan, President of the Constru c t i o n
Bank of China, calling for further pension reform at
the earliest possible dat e . “Otherwise China’s
pension system will face serious problems in the
decade between 2010 and 2020.” ■
Huang Yan in Beijing
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 23
The granny boom
■
In developing countries the elderly make up a
smaller proportion of the population than they
do in developed regi o n s , but their numbers are
growing much faster than those of the rest of the
p o p u l at i o n . In fa c t , as the World Health
O r g a n i z at i o n ’s 1998 Wo rld Health Report p o i n t s
o u t , “Most of the increase in older populations will
occur in developing countries, which will face the
most serious challenges in providing a ‘ we l fa r e
package’of services for their older people.”
Most low-income developing countries have
hardly begun to face up to the aging of their
p o p u l at i o n s , for reasons which are unders t a n d a b l e .
M a ny countries in tropical A f ri c a , for example, a r e
confronted with urgent problems including rapid
p o p u l ation gr ow t h , high infant and child mort a l i t y,
and excessive rural-urban migration.
Rampant urbanization
According to one study, the size of the older
p o p u l ation in developing countries was expected to
increase by almost 90 per cent between 1980 and
2 0 0 0 , and by over 300 per cent by 2025.1 There are
considerable regional va ri ations in this gr ow t h . I n
A f ri c a , for example, little change in the age stru c t u r e
of the population is expected until 2025. In East A s i a ,
h owe ve r , gr owth will be substantial, while China
stands out as the most rapidly aging society, with a
p o p u l ation structure that by 2025 will be closer to that
of the developed regions than it is today.
U r b a n i z ation has been an essential part of most
c o u n t ri e s ’ d e velopment in recent decades, and in
d e veloped regions there is a disproport i o n at e
r e p r e s e n t ation of older persons in urban areas and
inner subu r b s. In the developing countries the age
s t ructures of urban populations seem to be follow i n g
this trend, but at the same time certain specific
r e gional and national tendencies are apparent. I n
Hard choices for
theThird World Nana Apt*
A f ri c a , for example,older persons are more likely to
l i ve in rural areas than their counterp a rts in other
world regi o n s. In A s i a , there has been a trend towa r d s
u r b a n i z ation of the elderly, although a substantial
m a j o rity still remain in rural areas. It is expected
t h at by 2000 older persons in Latin A m e rica are
more likely to live in urban than rural areas.
Weakened family ties
Economic and social fa c t o rs are bound to have an
a d ve rse impact on the situation of older people duri n g
the process of urbanization and industri a l i z ation that
is currently underway in the developing countri e s.
T h at process gradually weakens traditional fa m i l y
p at t e rns which provide social roles for older pers o n s
and ensure that they play a pivotal role in society
e ven as they advance in age.The crucial question is
whether cultural norms in these countries will remain
strong enough for families to maintain their ties to the
elderly as the dependency burden increases.
The gr owth in the numbers of older people in the
d e veloping world is taking place in a context where
traditional obligations are changi n g, and the domestic
a rrangements of the intergenerational family which
traditionally supported older persons are under threat .
The indicat o rs increasingly reveal a trend away from
the traditional perceptions and practices of obligat i o n s
t owards respect and care for the elderly.
S u p p o rt for the gr owing numbers of older
people will largely depend on informal serv i c e s
provided by their kinsfolk. However, neglect and
i s o l ation of the elderly are surfacing in many A f ri c a n
c o u n t ri e s , for example, where only a relat i vely small
number of people in formal employment are entitled
to social security.
L ow wages and job insecurity make it hard for
younger A f ricans living in cities to support their
elderly kin, just as their counterp a rts in rural areas are
finding it hard to meet the needs of the rural elderly.
In one study on the views of Ghanaian youth on
a gi n g, 81 per cent of those questioned expressed
the opinion that it was no longer feasible for yo u n g
families to live with their elderly relat i ve s.2
Clearly, the domestic separation of the urban
elderly from the traditional structure is a reflexion
of the changing nature of the traditional family in
Africa.There is an evident difference of loyalties
between the newer urbanized conjugal family and
* Centre for Social Policy Studies,
University of Ghana
1.El-Badry, M.A.“Aging in Developing Countries: One
more population problem?” In Economic and Social
Implications of Aging, United Nations,New York,1988.
2.Apt, N.A. Ghanaian Youth on Aging (1991).
Developing countries beset with a host of
other urgent problems have not yet begun to
cope with the needs of aging populations
T h ey expected nothing.
T h ey we re sitting
quietly in the ga rd e n ,i n
damp wicker ch a i rs .. . .
T h ey ga zed at the sea,
the cl o u d s, the hills, t h e
closed tanneri e s,
d e relict for ye a rs, h a l f
ru i n e d
like ancient temples. . . .
T h e n
a boat whistled in the
d i s t a n c e.The three old
men looked at each
o t h e r
and nodded their
heads for they knew
it hadn’t whistled fo r
t h e m .T h ey had
a l ready left.
Yannis Ritsos (1909- ),
Greece
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
■
In India, where the traditional joint fa m i l y
system is breaking down and there is a dearth
of homes for the aged, most elderly people
face an uncertain future.
I n d i a , the wo r l d ’s second most populous nat i o n ,
has more aged people than the entire population of
F r a n c e . Official statistics show that there were 56
million Indians above 60 ye a rs of age in 1991,
amounting to 6.5 per cent of the total population of
844 million. Only 10 per cent of them have a pension
and access to some form of health scheme.The rest
h ave no health care, insurance or assured fin a n c i a l
s u p p o rt . More Indian elders will be in a similar
s i t u ation as gove rnment projections indicate that the
60-plus population could double between 1991 and
2 0 1 6 .
Traditionally, the average Indian’s life centred
on the family. Joint families were the norm and the
elderly stayed with their sons and relat i ve s. A n a l y s t s
s ay mass migr ation from the countryside to the
cities and ove rs e a s , coupled with changing social
va l u e s , h ave led to the disintegr ation of multi-
g e n e r ational fa m i l i e s.As a result,m a ny aged people
are left to fend for themselves.
Even today, moving into an old people’s home
carries a social stigma because it suggests that one
has been abandoned by one’s own children. B u t
many elders have no choice. However, Indian old
people’s homes are already overcrowded.
According to a directory issued by the Centre for
the We l fare of the Aged (CEWA ) ,a non-gove rn m e n t a l
o r g a n i z at i o n , in 1995 India had about 500
g ove rnment-funded homes for the aged, of which 17
per cent were for wo m e n .Most of these homes are ru n
by Christian missionaries and charitable foundat i o n s.
These homes are the only option for those with little
or no money.Together with some 200 pri vate homes,
these institutions,both gove rnment-aided and pri vat e ,
can handle only 30,000 people.
“The waiting list is long and substantial
numbers of elders belonging to the poor and the
l ower middle class will never find a place in
g ove rnment-funded homes,” s ays T. K rishnan Nair,
s e c r e t a ry of the CEWA .“In the last 10 ye a rs ,p ri vat e
homes have appeared which only cater to upper
middle class and rich elders. These homes charge
exorbitant prices which elders from the middle-
class and poor sectors of society can’t afford.”
Of the homes that exist, many fall far short of
p r oviding basic amenities like clean water and good
food.The main problem,social workers say, is that
there are no rules and no organization to keep tabs
Indian elders with
n o w h e re to go
A ging is the most
u n expected event in a
m a n ’s life.
Leon Trotsky (1879-1940),
Russia
the extended traditional family. However,it would
be a mistake to think that this development is simply
the outcome of the adoption of “modern” values
and at t i t u d e s ;i n f r a s t ructural and structural fa c t o rs
are invo l ve d . Urban housing conditions, f o r
e x a m p l e , go a long way to explaining these changes.
In rural Ghana, a c c o m m o d ation can easily be
provided for all social categories. Shortage of land
is not a factor and simple additional dwellings are
c o n s t ructed out of local mat e rials as the need ari s e s.
Urban accommodation on the other hand usually
has to be paid for with cash and landlords often
impose a limit on the number of persons entitled to
inhabit their propert y. These fa c t o rs all bri n g
pressure to bear on fa m i l i e s , especially large fa m i l i e s.
Longevity creates the possibility that household
and kinship structures will contain four or five
generations, whereas previously three generations
was the predominant form . In other wo r d s , t h e
working generation will be called on to take care of
its parents, grandparents and great grandparents.
H owe ve r ,p o l i cy discussions continue to be held in
The highest and 
lowest life expectancy
at birth (1997)*
* The 5 countries where life
expectancy at birth is highest for
the 2 sexes:
Ja p a n 8 0
C a n a d a 7 9
F ra n c e 7 9
S w e d e n 7 9
S w i t z e r l a n d 7 9
* The 5 countries where life
expectancy at birth is lowest for
the 2 sexes:
S i e r ra Leone 3 8
M a l a w i 4 1
U g a n d a 4 1
R w a n d a 4 2
Z a m b i a 4 3
S o u r c e : Yearbook of Labour Statistics,
International Labour Office, G e n e va ,
1 9 9 7
The few old people’s homes are overcrowded and
traditional family solidarity is breaking down
Life expectancy at birth
■1950-1955 ■1990-1995 ■2025-2030
Wo r l d
M a l e 45           62     7 1
Fe m a l e 48              66
7 6
M o re developed re g i o n s
M a l e 64   70
7 6
Fe m a l e 6 9
7 8 8 2
Less developed re g i o n s
M a l e 40                 61      7 0
Fe m a l e 42                  64       7 4
S o u r c e : World Population Prospects - The 1996 Revision, New Yo r k ,U n i t e d
N a t i o n s, 1 9 9 8 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 25
The granny boom
■
HelpAge Intern ational (HAI) is one of the
wo r l d ’s biggest networks of not-for-profit
o r g a n i z ations invo l ved in community
activities designed with and for older people. I t
has 57 members wo r l d w i d e , most of them in less
d e veloped countries of A f ri c a , Asia and Lat i n
A m e ri c a . In countries where confli c t , disaster or
social transition have created particularly acute
s i t u at i o n s , HelpAge Intern ational ru n s
p r o grammes to support some of the most
vulnerable older people, in many cases by
strengthening the capacity of local organizations to
address their needs. HAI is active in such fie l d s
as health care, income and food securi t y,
ophthalmic wo r k , training and educat i o n ,
e m e r g e n cy relief, c a r e , a d vo c a cy and research.
One of its chief aims is to increase the invo l ve m e n t
of older people in project planning and
m a n a g e m e n t .
In one HAI-supported village project in
C a m b o d i a , older people have started up ri c e
b a n k s , from which participants borr ow rice for
food or sow i n g, refunding it with interest—in
rice—after the harve s t . Some of the “ p r o f i t ” i s
d i s t ri buted free to frail older people in the village.
In South A f rica HAI is working with the
Muthande Society for the Aged (MUSA) on a
t h r e e - year literacy project in six centres in
D u r b a n . A team of older people trained as literacy
t u t o rs are running courses in Zulu, English and
n u m e r a cy, with lessons designed to help students
cope with real-life challenges—pension form s ,
b i l l s , telephone numbers and sewing pat t e rn s. ■
+ …
● h t t p : / / w w w. h e l p a g e. o rg
Percentage 
of over-65s who are
economically active
(1996)*
* The 5 countries where the rate of
the economically active population
over 65 is particularly low:
L u x e m b o u rg 1 . 6
S p a i n 1 . 8
F i n l a n d 1 . 8
F ra n c e 2 . 2
A u s t r i a 2 . 9
* the 5 countries where 
the rate of the economically active
population over 65 
is particularly high:
B a n g l a d e s h 5 2 . 2
Gambia ( 1 9 9 3 ) 4 8 . 5
Sudan ( 1 9 9 3 ) 4 7 . 1
Tonga ( 1 9 9 4 ) 4 3 . 0
P h i l i p p i n e s 4 2 . 2
S o u r c e : Yearbook of Labour Statistics,
International Labour Office, G e n e va ,
1 9 9 7
t e rms of three-generation models. If the deve l o p i n g
world is to depend on kinship as the key mechanism
for the care of older persons and if this mechanism
is to continue when family size is declining, policy
c o n c e rn must focus on supporting fa m i l i e s
c o m p rising four or five and not simply three
g e n e r at i o n s. Building social policies anchored in the
family will clearly require strong public and
community complementary measures.
Who will care for the very old?
In the developing wo r l d , the increasing numbers
of the ve ry old will have major effects on the pat t e rn s
of exchange and reciprocity between generations.
G r e at grandparents are unlikely to enjoy the
financial and residential autonomy of their
counterparts in the industrial world.They are also
unlikely to displace the “ yo u n g - o l d ” in the
performance of key household functions such as
child care, food preparation and ensuring household
s e c u rity which have been at the heart of
i n t e r g e n e r ational exchanges within the three-
generation household structure.
If low and middle income countries are to depend
upon the family as the key structure in providing for
the social part i c i p ation and care of the “ o l d - o l d ” ,
then much of the responsibility for this will fall upon
the shoulders of the yo u n g - o l d .Although care for the
old-old is still likely to be provided within the
f r a m e work of kinship, it is increasingly likely to be
p r ovided outside the household. In Malay s i a ,Fiji and
the Philippines, older people are already less likely to
be living with children than the younger old.
As the demographic balance alters the political
balance between youth and age, so changes in the
labelling of the older person are to be expected. In the
i n d u s t rial wo r l d , these changes are already begi n n i n g
to occur. In the developing countri e s , the process is
likely to take longer. H owe ve r , the development of a
g e n e r ational politics in the industrial world will
i n fluence the development of the political capacity of
older persons in the developing wo r l d .A d vo c a cy by the
lobbying institutions of older persons in the industri a l
world should help to raise the profile of older people’s
interests in the developing wo r l d .
The emergence of the four- to five - g e n e r at i o n a l
world will necessarily result in altered social roles and
identities for the old.The aging of society will also,u n l e s s
existing inequalities are addressed, result in the
a c c e n t u ation of gender disparities in respect of we a l t h
and quality of life. G i ven these considerat i o n s , s t e p s
must be taken to develop new bases of sociability and
esteem for older generat i o n s. New technology can be
h a rnessed to increase the political capacity and enhance
the sociability of older pers o n s.It can provide a technical
b ridge for linking older persons globally and enable the
old of the developing world to gain direct assistance from
their counterp a rts in the developed wo r l d . It also
p r ovides new opportunities for older persons to
p a rt i c i p ate in shaping the research and policy agenda
a p p r o p ri ate to an aging wo r l d . ■
Helping the elderly
help themselves
HelpAge International runs a host of support projects,
especially in developing countries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
Charitable organizations look after the elderly when the family 
and the state can’t cope
L e b a n o n :t h e re ’s no place l i ke home
■
“ Family solidarity still exists in Lebanon, a n d
most elderly people still live with their
families,” says Abla Sebai, a member of the
c o u n t ry ’s National Committee for Old Pe o p l e ,
which was founded a year ago. In fact,83 per cent
of over-60s still live with their relatives. But, in a
trend which may spread throughout the Arab wo r l d ,
links between generations are more and more
strained and there is now a gr owing number of
lonely and very poor elderly people.
Aunt Marie has tears in her eyes as she looks at
pictures from her yo u t h . Her only remaining
r e l at i ve is a niece, living abroad, and a nephew who
only makes fleeting visits every fortnight.She is 75
and lives alone in the east Beirut suburb of
A s h r a fieh in one room furnished with a bed and
t wo sofa s. She walks with difficulty and is part of the
61 per cent of the population without health
i n s u r a n c e .The social security authorities cut people
off as soon as they retire.“Less than 10 per cent of
the working population receives an adequat e
pension,” says Sebai.
Joseph Tautal, a founder-member of the Rifak
al-Darb organization set up in 1994 to help the
aged poor in A s h r a fie h ,s ays that “67 old people are
living alone and without resources in this
n e i g h b o u r h o o d . Some of them beg in the streets of
Beirut.” He says people,“especially the youth, are
still mostly unaware of the problem but a move m e n t
is gr owing among church congr e g ations and
h u m a n i t a rian groups because there is no system
which helps the elderly living alone.”
S e ven per cent of Lebanese are over 65, t h e
highest proportion of old people in the Arab wo r l d ,
where the average is reckoned to be four per cent.
By 2021, the Lebanese figure is expected to reach
eight per cent and 12.8 per cent four ye a rs after
t h at .“At present, there are many young Lebanese,”
s ays Lebanese demographer Hala Naufa l , “ bu t
there is a clear aging trend which is going to spread
to the other Arab countries.”
A long waiting list
H owe ver there is still no gove rnment policy
concerning the elderly, much less for people living
a l o n e . E ven preliminary studies have not been
d o n e . So eve rything depends on chari t a b l e
o r g a n i z at i o n s. And because of a serious lack of
money and resources, the 37 non-gove rn m e n t a l
o r g a n i z ations which are doing the gove rn m e n t ’s
job have gi ven pri o rity to caring for old people who
are ill.
S t .G e o r g e ’s Home, which is linked to the Greek
Orthodox Church, has been taking in the elderly
since 1874.“Sixty of our 133 beds are unusable,”
s ays Father Demetrios Khoury,who runs the home.
“The state doesn’t pay its due and 68 per cent of the
old people with no family left don’t pay anything.”
Within two ye a rs , he hopes to have 220 beds
ava i l a b l e . For the time being, he is turning away
new patients who cannot pay, even if they are ill.
But the home still has a long waiting list.
The situation is the same at the Dar al-Ajaza
al-Islami Hospital, a pri vate clinic run by the
Muslim community.“With 3,000 beds for an ove r -
65 population of 225,000, we have a real problem,”
s ays the hospital’s gerontologi s t . “There aren’t
m a ny people in my fie l d .There are only seven of us
officially registered with the Doctor’s Guild, four of
us since 1995, and demand is gr owing all the time.”
In three ye a rs , only four new institutions for the
elderly have been opened.
M o r e over the economic crisis and the trend
towards individualism which the war years created
have set off developments and changes in lifestyles
which have eaten away at family solidari t y.
“Increasingly, families say they no longer have the
space, time or money to look after relatives,” says
M rs We h b é , director of the Wehbé Home for old
people who are ill.
Families are getting poorer and 34 per cent of
the population lives below the pove rty line.
“Women are the people who look after old people
at home,” s ays Sebai.“But more and more of them
h ave outside jobs. In 15 ye a rs time, the situat i o n
will be really critical.” ■
Carole Donati in Beirut
Family lunch in a Beirut street.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 27
The granny boom
A rg e n t i n a ’s penniless p e n s i o n e rs
■
Argentina is a country where old people are
p o o r. Badly treated economically and socially,
they are society’s cast-offs, forgotten in the
dark recesses of memory.
They represent 12 per cent of the total
p o p u l at i o n , yet they are shabbily treated by the
government, which relegates them to the sidelines
of society.There are 4,500,000 over-60s,and only
2,800,000 of them receive some kind of old age
p e n s i o n . More than 1,500,000 people have no
insurance coverage what e ver and live in dire
poverty.
Official economic adjustment policies have
a lways targeted the pension system. In 1992,
b owing to pressure from the World Bank, P r e s i d e n t
Carlos Menem’s gove rnment reduced the benefit s
paid to most pensioners to $150 a month.The bu l k
of Argentine society is unperturbed by this stat e
of affa i rs and looks on the fate of its elders with
i n d i f f e r e n c e .
One quarter of the pensioners still receive $150
a month, an absurdly small amount which is not
e ven enough to pay for the medicines they need.
Some 50 per cent of the 1,500,000 recipients of
pensions get less than $350 a month and, at the
top of the scale, f e wer than three per cent get more
than $1,000.
The story of the Integral Medical Care
P r o gramme (PAMI) illustrates the decline in
benefits available to retired people. T h e
p r o gramme was established in 1971 and in its
early ye a rs it was an efficient medical and social
s e rvices agency which operated on its own funds.
Its current statutes empower it to administer its
own resources, which come from the
c o n t ri butions made by active and retired wo r k e rs
and compulsory employer contri bu t i o n s. U n t i l
the 1980s, on an annual budget not exceeding
$ 1 , 7 0 0 , 0 0 0 , PAMI covered the entire country
and opened a total of 55 new health care centres.
At the present time, this 
we l fare agency has a budget of $2,400,000 
for providing care for 4,000,000 regi s t e r e d
m e m b e rs but it contracts the work out to serv i c e
p r ov i d e rs because it does not have the releva n t
i n f r a s t ru c t u r e .
Cutbacks in 
medical services
The quality of the services provided has
steadily declined over the past ten ye a rs , d u ri n g
which PAMI was managed by eight different
a d m i n i s t r at o rs or presidents, who were suspected
or accused of taking part in or countenancing the
o p e r ation of parallel medical or health care
n e t wo r k s. B ri b e ry and corruption we r e
commonplace and the credibility, e f f i c i e n cy and
functioning of the system suffered. On more than
one occasion, PAMI was virtually insolve n t .To d ay,
old people are suffering from the sudden cutback
in services that are essential to their surv i va l ,s u c h
as medicines, care by family doctors and the
postponement of surgical operat i o n s , owing to the
failure to pay anaesthetists.
Since the early 1990s, retired people
d e m o n s t r ate eve ry We d n e s d ay in front of the
parliament bu i l d i n g .This eve n t , which in its heyday
mobilized more than 10,000 demonstrat o rs and
brought traffic to a halt in Buenos Aires, has now
almost become reduced to a picturesque
happening. Since the death in 1996 of the protest
l e a d e r , N o rma Plá, a pensioner who resorted to
such unconventional tactics as chaining herself to
the railings of the parliament building and
organizing a popular demonstration in front of the
l aw court s , it has lost its widespread appeal and
i m p a c t . As the gove rnment rejected its eve ry
d e m a n d , the members of the movement lost heart .
But penniless though they may be, t h e
p e n s i o n e rs still enjoy one enviable bonus—they
constitute 20 per cent of the electorat e . It is a
strange paradox that there is no nat i o n w i d e
m ovement to press for the rights and interests of
retired people. ■
Jorge Göttliing in Buenos Aires
Retirees are
the front-line
victims of
economic 
belt-tightening
policies
E ven if yo u ’ve got one
foot in the gra ve there ’s
no reason why yo u
should tread on others.
François Mauriac (1885-1970),
France
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
In these systems where the oral tradition
p r e va i l s ,k n owledge is the property of the ve ry old—
not so much technical know l e d g e , which anyo n e
can soon absorb,as “mythical knowledge”that no
young person can take away from them.Those who
possess the secret of the sacred myth that descri b e s
the gr o u p ’s ori gi n s , k n ow the profound meaning
of things and the Law of the A n c e s t o rs , in other
words the principle that governs and regulates the
social order. Myth engenders ritual,the repetition
of the primordial gesture, making the elderly the
officiants of the domestic cult, capable of uttering
Sage o r
spoilsport?
Bernadette Puijalon
and Jacqueline Trincaz*
sacred words,unleashing vital good or evil powers
and issuing blessings and curses.
The elderly have a vitally import a n t
e d u c ational role because of their mastery of
k n ow l e d g e . As well as telling young generat i o n s
about my t h , they must transmit the history of the
group and its social ru l e s , of which they are the
g u a r d i a n s. Transmission takes place in stages,
especially during the initiation ceremonies which
are milestones in the education process, e n a b l i n g
the elderly to keep part of the secret knowledge as
long as possible and guaranteeing their cultural,
r e l i gious and political hegemony. G e r o n t o c r at i c
p ower is rooted in this system. “The process is
s i m p l e ,” s ays French anthropologist Louis V i n c e n t
T h o m a s. It consists of “ c o n f i s c ating basic
k n ow l e d g e , then serving it to the rising age gr o u p s
in precisely-measured doses at we l l - c a l c u l at e d
i n t e rvals through a language rich in symbols and
highly emotional resonances.”
Benefactions
from beyond the grave
A ging is thus a process of acquisition, and the
image of the elderly is highly positive . An old man
is wise. He sets an example and has cheated deat h
by drawing inspiration from the gr o u p ’s va l u e s. H e
does not fear deat h , which will reunite him with his
a n c e s t o rs and enable him to continue being useful
to the community by eternally making
b e n e factions to his descendants. E nv i s a ging life as
■
Old age is as much a historical and cultural
c o n s t ruct as a natural phenomenon. It is
based on biologi c a l ,d e m o gr a p h i c, e c o n o m i c
and political fa c t o rs , but it is also built on the image
of old age—in some cases positive , in others less
so—that each society shapes in conformity with its
values and its conception of what constitutes an
ideal human being.
Some cultures have emphasized the positive
side of gr owing old by viewing human
d e velopment as a lifelong process in which the
a ging individual accumulates qualities and
e x p e ri e n c e s. One example of this can be found in
the traditional rural societies of A f ri c a , where social
d i f f e r e n t i ation is based on age, which establishes
the superi o rity of the older over the yo u n g e r
g e n e r at i o n . In these societies the elderly are few in
number but they play a big role.
*Anthropologists, University of
Paris XII 
In Africa the aged are the guardians of
knowledge and power; in the West they are all
too often regarded as an encumbrance
Those who possess the secret 
of the sacred myth that describes
the group’s origins, know the
profound meaning of things and
the Law of the Ancestors
A ceremony of initiation into
adulthood (Kenya).
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 29
The granny boom
an ongoing progression that continues after deat h
leads to a conception of old age as the last stage of
an ascension towards fullness of knowledge and
p owe r.
W h at We s t e rn societies call loss of fa c u l t i e s ,
disability and degeneration are symptoms of a
m e t a m o rphosis towards a higher stage. If an old
p e rson can’t keep to the point, perhaps he is talking
with the ancestor s. If he goes blind or deaf, he is
seeing and listening to the spirits. If he shrivels up
and finds it hard to get about, he has become a
s p i ri t . A c c o m p l i s h e d , close to God and the
a n c e s t o rs , he lives as one of the elect. In such a
society people enjoy aging and saying they are old—
e ven ve ry, ve ry old. The term has many positive
associations. Adding “wise”would be redundant.
The quest 
for eternal youth
We s t e rn societies, on the other hand, d i v i d e
the human life span into successive periods in
which phases of gr ow t h , m at u rity and climax are
f o l l owed by decline and fa l l , leading to the
i n e v i t a b l e , i rr e ve rsible end. Faced with the
unprecedented increase in life expectancy and the
e ve r - gr owing number of elderly pers o n s , t h e s e
societies have two wat c h wo r d s : i n d i v i d u a l
resistance to aging and the solidarity of all with
the poorest elderly people.
Since old age is neither desirable nor enviable,
people should try and delay its onset as long as
p o s s i b l e . They have no right to squander their
capital of yo u t h f u l n e s s ; they must resist the rava g e s
Old and young in Moscow’s central market.
In Western societies
this time of life is dominated
by negative images
of time by leading healthy lives and taking
a d vantage of all the remedies science has to offer—
p i l l s , health creams or surgery. The purpose of
p r e ve n t i ve action against old age is not to develop a
p e rs o n ’s capacities for living but to reject this stage
of life because it is viewed as degrading.
This struggle is a matter of individual
responsibility and the “losers”—those who fail to
s t ay young in mind and body when they fall ill,
suffer bereavement or have an accident—feel guilty.
For them, life has taken a sudden,drastic turn .T h e y
have entered old age, the age of dependence.The
criterion upon which this transition is based is not
social or cultural but biological. It depends on an
i n d i v i d u a l ’s physical capacities rather than on his or
her chronological age. In We s t e rn societies this time
of life is dominated by negat i ve images—loneliness,
incapacity and social uselessness.
C a ring is the key wo r d . When old age is
synonymous with inadequacy and decline,certain
things have to be done.Social workers specializing
in geriatric care use special assessment methods to
decide what kind of assistance should be gi ven and
w h at resources should be used, from geri at ri c
medicine to long-term care facilities.This process
has a logic of its own and raises the question of the
cost of dependence, which strengthens the
overwhelming image of the elderly as an economic
bu r d e n .N e ve r ,p e r h a p s , has a society done so much
for its oldest members.They benefit from economic
and social protection, but the image society has of
them is deeply negative.
Segregation 
between age groups
H i s t o rians have shown that a society’s image of
individuals at a given stage of life has a significant
bearing on the way they are treated. Paradoxically,
Western societies,where there are more and more
elderly people, organize an unprecedented form of
s e gr e g ation between the age gr o u p s.Young and old
p u rsue different activities in different places at
different times. The harmonious mingling of the
ages in a shared setting no longer exists.
In A f ri c a , the transform ation of the traditional
context by such processes as urbanizat i o n ,
schooling and the development of a culture based
on the written wo r d , the intermingling of
p o p u l at i o n s , the spread of new religions and the
a rri val of new, more individualistic values are
diluting if not destroying the community system
and gerontocracy. K n owledge and power have
changed hands.Those societies may be witnessing
the “twilight of the old”. H owe ve r , no society
remains frozen.And even when the age pyramid is
t u rned upside down—when more people start
a p p e a ring at the top than at the bottom, as in the
West or in some Asian countries that have
implemented proactive birth control policies—
s o l i d a rity may still have a role to play — but only if
a process of gi ve-and-take between generations is
restored to human relat i o n s h i p s. ■
The wo rst thing ab o u t
aging is that you stay
yo u n g.
Jean Cocteau (1889-1963),
France
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
the salon and bedroom will alert security guards.“ O n l y
in A m e ri c a ,” laughs Michael Sykes, a builder at
H e rs h e y ’s Mill.“ We don’t just sell a home but a lifestyle.
We ’re cat e ring to baby-boomers who feel they’ve
worked hard and deserve a carefree life.” So social
a c t i v i t i e s , from Yiddish classes to bingo,are organized
b e t ween tennis games and a swim at the pool, w h i l e
maintenance crews look after the gardening. G u a r d
p atrols along with wooden and concrete gates enclosing
the community offer a sense of security and prestige.
You wo n ’t find any teenagers blasting their stereos.A t
H e rs h e y ’s Mill,as in other adult communities across the
c o u n t ry, federal law stipulates that 80 per cent of
d wellings for the elderly must be occupied by at least
one person over the age of 55.The remaining 20 per
cent is open to those over 43. But residence is stri c t l y
forbidden for anyone under the age of 18.
“ I t ’s like a resort here,” s ays Tom Carr o l l , a
H e rs h e y ’s Mill resident.“When you get to my age,6 2 ,
l i f e ’s about having fun, f u n , f u n . No more kids to
s u p p o rt or so many things to bu y.”About 80 per cent
of residents are retired.“But that doesn’t mean we ’r e
not bu s y,”s ays Carr o l l ,who proudly unveils the “ B a r b i e
doll house”he is building in the community wo o d - s h o p.
“ I t ’s for the gr a n d k i d s.Eight of the 10 of them live within
20 miles of here.Who needs ’em any closer?”
More people like Carroll are choosing to stay in
adult communities close to where they raised their
families instead of moving to retirement hot-spots like
F l o rida and A ri z o n a . Already about 10 per cent of
A m e ricans over 55 live in these communities and more
are spri n ging up, p a rticularly in nort h e a s t e rn stat e s
like Pe n n s y l vania where about 25 per cent of the
p o p u l ation falls in this age gr o u p.
Not eve ryone is so charmed by the lifestyle.“ We like
d i ve rs i t y,” s ays Bill Hoffman, who has decided not to
m ove in after visiting the community. “It can be
depressing to always be around older people.” C h u c k
Hennessy just signed the mortgage for a new home at
H e rs h e y ’s Mill. “Where I live now, I have all kinds of
n e i g h b o u rs—couples of all colours ,s i n g l e s ,l e s b i a n s. I
like that mixture”, which he wo n ’t find in the
overwhelmingly white new neighbourhood.“But aside
from the occasional part y, there wa s n ’t enough
socializing to miss.”For Lucille Jo r g e n s o n , the lack of
d i ve rsity is compensated by “a sense of oneness”f o r g e d
by common interests.“My husband and I moved here
because we felt comfortable in knowing that if one of
us died,the other would be established in a community
of people our age,with activities we could take part in.”
The downside of such a tightly-knit community lies
in the many rules to follow, c ove ring eve rything from
where kids can play to the obligat o ry white window
c u rtains to ensure a classic look from the outside.“ I t ’s a
problem when our grandkids visit,”s ays Martha Tu rn e y.
“I’m allowed to rollerblade,but my six-year-old gr a n d s o n
i s n ’t .”As her husband Bob explains,“A lot of people have
trouble adjusting to this group mentality but they get ove r
i t .There are also those who just love to argue over the
t rivial rules like where you place a flower pot.But then
a g a i n ,you’ll always find people who need to argue about
s o m e t h i n g .W h at else do they have to do?” ■
Amy Otchet,West Chester, U S A
Looking for a carefree lifestyle in the US, the
over-50s flock to gated communities which
keep youngsters out 
■
“ H e e e - h aw ! ” rips from a row of dye d - b l o n d
wo m e n ,h i p - sw i n ging to the “hot tamale”d a n c e
step and grinning wide to the twangs of country
m u s i c. N o, this is not a bar scene in a b-grade mov i e
about lonesome cow b oy s.I t ’s 10 o’clock in the morn i n g
in a suburb outside of the nort h e a s t e rn US city of
P h i l a d e l p h i a . These gals are out for fun and fit n e s s ,
making the most of their retirement at the Four Seasons
at Hers h e y ’s Mill,one of the many “adult communities”
mushrooming in affluent areas across the United Stat e s.
At first sight, it looks like a typical middle-class
n e i g h b o u r h o o d , with new single-story homes and
postage stamp lawns at a starting price of about a
q u a rter of a million dollars. But on a Tu e s d ay morn i n g
when most of A m e rican suburbia resembles a no-
m a n ’s land with kids in school and adults at wo r k ,t h i s
area is bustling with golfers on the 18-hole cours e ,
j o g g e rs along wooded trails and couples congr e g at i n g
in the local restaurant for a lecture on art history.A n d
a look inside the homes offers other signs that this
community is designed for older people. There are
ve ry few stairs to climb and the light switches are all
placed low on the walls to minimize any painful
stretching of an art h ritic shoulder. And in case of a
health emergency or a bu r g l a ry, t wo “panic bu t t o n s ”i n
Let the good times
ro l l
It takes a long time to
grow yo u n g.
Pablo Picasso (1881-1973),
Spain
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 31
The granny boom
■
In A f rica gerontocracy is dying.The traditional
p o l i t i c a l , social and economic order dominat e d
by the elders seems doomed to extinction.
The elders exercised—and still do, though to
a much lesser extent—authority in the context of
a ru r a l , clan-based society where technical, s o c i a l
and religious knowledge was acquired during a
long process. Tr a d i t i o n a l l y, the oldest fa m i l y
member managed the land, the main productive
r e s o u r c e . He divided it up, d i s t ri buted the reve n u e s
and decided how unconsumed products should be
u s e d . Management of agricultural surpluses gave
rise to the main source of his powe r. He receive d
and gave girls in marri a g e , since he alone was able
to provide them with a dow ry.The younger males
were thus dependent on him when they took a wife.
M a rriage was a decisive step towards social
promotion and claiming a birt h ri g h t . An elder
could use his wealth to increase the number of his
w i ves and strengthen his social ties.
The elder’s power also had a political and
r e l i gious basis. He presided over the village’s destiny
by taking part in the council of elders and
a d m i n i s t e ring the ancestor cult. As a member of
secret organizations he helped enforce respect for
the social order and sanctioned anyone who broke
African youth makes a t a ke o v e r
The upheavals that have rocked African societies in the past half-century have
undermined the elders’ traditional power base
the ru l e s. The elder was the master, e ven though
he consulted the younger members of the
community, especially on family matters. He was
t r e ated with deep respect.Young people and wo m e n
adopted a submissive attitude towards him.
When individualism 
erodes clan structures
Most A f rican societies are pat ri l i n e a l , a n d
women and children live with the husband’s fa m i l y.
Women had an inferior social stat u s.They acquired
influence with the onset of menopause, w h i c h
brought their condition closer to that of the men,
but never obtained the right to represent or head
the fa m i l y. E ven after reaching an advanced age,
they were barred from taking part in official
decision-making and enjoyed no economic or
social powe r. At best, they wielded their authori t y
in the pri vate arena, especially over their daughters -
i n - l aw.
In the recent past a series of events and
d e velopments have enabled youth to supplant
their elders. C o l o n i z at i o n , the arri val of
C h ristianity and Islam and the implementat i o n
and subsequent spread of the market economy
and the wa g e - e a rning system have placed more
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
emphasis on the individual than the clan and
taken a toll on traditional stru c t u r e s. But the
d e c i s i ve fa c t o rs in the emancipation of yo u n g
people have been education and urbanizat i o n .
In the 1940s and 1950s, the small minori t y
admitted to We s t e rn unive rsities played a key role in
t r a n s f o rming A f rican societies and ousting their
elders from positions of power.Western education
discredited the wisdom of the elders. Now, “those
who know”are those who have gone to school and
a r e , t h e r e f o r e , yo u n g . Their studies, which they
p u rsue in tow n , enable them to escape from the
elders’control.
D u ring the colonial peri o d , p ri m a ry schools,
missions and colleges of education helped train a
group of yo u n g, s k i l l e d , “ e d u c at e d ” A f ri c a n s
including teachers , civil servants and health
wo r k e rs. Some turned away from their fellow
A f ricans and A f rican va l u e s , while others gr e w
aware of colonial oppression and became close to
the working class forming in the cities.They were in
the vanguard of political and labour struggles as
well as the battle for independence. Most of the
earliest African heads of state were young. But by
c l i n ging to power until an advanced age, some have
lent credence to the idea that the A f ri c a n
gerontocracy has not had its last word.
The spread of 
Western values
The overall development of A f rican society
n e ve rtheless continues to undermine the
g e r o n t o c r a cy ’s foundat i o n s. U r b a n i z ation has dealt
a blow to an essentially rural-based political
o r g a n i z at i o n . In the 1940s, economic activities
began shifting towards the cities.Young people are
the most mobile group, capable of adapting to city
l i f e , to new technology and to modern forms of
wo r k .They are also more receptive to the spread of
We s t e rn va l u e s ,c o nve yed by the school system, t h e
a d m i n i s t r ation and the media. G r a n t e d , young city-
d we l l e rs are still attached to the villages where they
were born . But by living far from their
c o m m u n i t i e s , they are gradually adopting new
lifestyles and becoming self-sufficient. A more
individualistic society is taking shape in which the
r e l ationships of domination and allegiance betwe e n
young people and the old generations are dying
o u t .A ny young man who can afford to can now get
m a rri e d . E ven in the country s i d e , which is
intensifying its exchanges with the cities, t h e s e
developments are having an effect.
But on two counts change is coming slowe r.
F i rs t , gender inequality persists and wo m e n ,
including in the cities, are still subject to the
goodwill of the men in their fa m i l i e s. S e c o n d ,m o s t
young A f ricans remain dependent on the gr o u p
because of low urbanization and school at t e n d a n c e
rates,unemployment and poverty.The question of
whether they will be able to take over the reins from
their parents is posed today in dramatic terms. ■
Codou Bop in Dakar
‘ When are
we l e a v i n g ?’
■
JB is an elderly retired professional man who
l i ves quietly in an English provincial city. E a r l y
in 1997 his 77-year-old wife was diagnosed as
suffering from Alzheimer’s disease, an age-related
d e g e n e r at i ve brain disorder which affects memory,
thinking, behaviour and emotion.
The first sign that something was seri o u s l y
amiss had come two ye a rs before, when IM had
gone to London to visit friends. She had failed to
a rri ve and returned home, h aving completely
forgotten where she was going.Before that,during
a question-and-answer session at an academic
g at h e ri n g, she had been uncharacteristically lost
for words.The couple saw their doctor who asked
IM who the Prime Minister was. She said she had
no idea but that surely it didn’t mat t e r. T h e r e
f o l l owed a series of brain scans and exhaustive
m e m o ry and language tests, as a result of which
she was diagnosed as being in the early stages of
Alzheimer’s.
Inexorable
mental decline
Alzheimer’s disease is the most common form
of dementia, a malady that afflicts one in 20 people
over the age of 65. It affects all groups in society
irrespective of social class,gender,ethnic group or
g e o graphical locat i o n . According to curr e n t
e s t i m at e s , by the year 2000 there will be roughly
18 million people with dementia in the wo r l d ,a b o u t
two-thirds of them Alzheimer victims.
Tr e atment is in its infa n cy and as yet nothing
seems to slow the sufferer’s inexorable mental decline.
The disorder’s first stage may seem relat i vely benign.
After all, most people as they age lose mental
s h a rp n e s s , misplace things, forget people’s names
and suffer other minor mental lapses.From then on,
h owe ve r ,i t ’s downhill all the way.“ A l z h e i m e r ’s is like
an insidious fog,” JB say s , “barely noticeable until
e ve rything around has disappeared.After that it is no
longer possible to believe that a world outside the
fog exists.”
As the disease progr e s s e s , the patient becomes
dependent on others for help with all aspects of daily
l i f e .This care is usually provided by the immediat e
family and the period of dependency can last for
m a ny ye a rs. “Alzheimer sufferers are not alway s
g e n t l e ,” JB notes, and caring for a loved one with
A l z h e i m e r ’s disease has been described as calling for
A husband’s moving chro n i c l e
of his wife’s descent into
A l z h e i m e r ’s disease
Sometimes her fa c e
will suddenly appear
with terri f y i n g
i n a p p ro p ri at e n e s s
b e fo re her in a mirro r.
She knows that if she’s
p at i e n t , its ga ze will
b re a k ,d e m u re l y,
d e c o ro u s l y,
like a we l l - t a u g h t
ch i l d ’s,
it will turn from her as
though it we re
e m b a rrassed by the
s e c re t s
of this awful hide-and
s e e k .
If she fo rge t s, t h o u g h ,
and glances back
aga i n , it will still be in
t h e re,
f u r t i vely wat ch i n g,
c ry i n g.
C.K. Williams (1936- ),
United States
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 33
The granny boom
the patience of Jo b , the wisdom of Solomon and the
s e l flessness of a saint.
A few months ago JB published a beautifully wri t t e n
short memoir of his wife,describing their lives together
“Then”(before the onset of Alzheimer’s) and “Now”, a
s e ries of vignettes of IM’s tragic descent into mental
n u l l i t y. S e rialized in the press, it struck a powerful chord
among many who are not only facing a more prolonged
old age than that of their forebears but may be coping
with the decline of someone to whom they are close.
IM’s case is particularly heart-rending in view of what
she had done before she began,as she put it,to sail into
the darkness. She is Iris Murdoch, one of the century’s
most gifted novelists writing in English and an author
with a devoted readership worldwide (her works have
been translated into 23 languages).Her husband,JB,is
John Bayley, a noted literary critic and former Oxford
professor.1
For over forty ye a rs Iris Murdoch had been engr o s s e d
in writing fiction and philosophy. In 27 novels published
b e t ween 1954 and 1995, she had created a vivid wo r l d
peopled by intelligent and intensely human figures whose
exceptional capacities for feeling and thinking were tested
in situations that were often macabre, comic and
m e l o d r a m at i c. She also wrote about philosophy, i n c l u d i n g
a critical study of Sartre (1953) and M e t a p hysics as a
Guide to Mora l s ( 1 9 9 2 ) . She had created and carri e d
the novels entirely in her head, planning them for
months before effortlessly writing them dow n .N ow
she no longer knows their titles.
A voyage 
into darkness
B ay l e y ’s memoir plunges the reader into the
world of sufferer and carer. To d ay Iris Murdoch
can no longer talk coherently or remember where
she is or has been.The day begins and ends with the
tussles of dressing (“most days a happy and comic
business”) and undressing. Around ten in the
morning it’s time for the Teletubbies,an animated
c a rtoon show on children’s television, which Iri s
watches “with something approaching glee.” S h e
is equally absorbed in sports progr a m m e s ,a l t h o u g h
she does not know the play or the scores.When she
t w i t t e rs away incomprehensibly Bayley fin d s
himself sustaining the illusion of a conversation by
uttering meaningless sentences of his own.When
they go out of doors she absently picks up stones
and twigs and brings them home. Her only
coherent phrase, which she repeats again and again,
i s : “When are we leav i n g ? ” She has a prodigi o u s
appetite for sleep. I t ’s some kind of consolation that
she does not seem aware of what she’s lost. “ I ’ m
grateful that there isn’t what you might call clear-
e yed despair going on. There is a kind of animal
t rust in the person she is with.” B ayley is quite
d e void of self-pity; his love for Murdoch shines
from every sentence. He gets through the days by
keeping bu s y. Jokes are import a n t , the sillier the
better to try to get a smile which “transforms her
face, bringing it back to what it was, and with an
added glow that can seem almost supernatural.”.
He tries to take the short view of things, n e ve r
looking beyond the next meal. Once he loses
control and explodes into anger as Iris goes on
meaninglessly watering the house plants.
“Like being chained to a corpse, isn’t it?” says
the wife of a fellow sufferer. He disagrees,refusing
to feel that Iris Murdoch’s individuality is absorbed
into “the common symptoms of a clinical
c o n d i t i o n ” . He accepts that eventually he will need
outside help, but “Like someone who knows he
cannot for much longer avoid going out into the
cold I still shrink from the need for professional
care . . . e ven the efforts of kind fri e n d s.All that is to
come, but let us postpone it while we can.”
Meanwhile the disease has oddly intensifie d
their togethern e s s. For ye a rs they had each been
engrossed in their own work, in a kind of conjugal
solitude.“Now we are together for the first time. .
. . E ve ry day we are physically closer; and Iri s ’s little
‘mouse cry’,as I think of it,signifying loneliness in
the next room, the wish to be back beside me, s e e m s
less and less forlorn , more simple, more nat u r a l .
She is not sailing into the dark: the voyage is over,
and under the dark escort of Alzheimer’s she has
arrived somewhere.So have I.” ■
Roy Malkin 
‘I’m grateful that there isn’t what you might call
clear-eyed despair going on. There is a kind of animal
trust in the person she is with.’
1. Iris, A Memoir of Iris
Murdoch, by John Bayley,
Gerald Duckworth & Co.
Ltd., London, 1998. To be
published also in French,
Dutch, German and
Swedish.
“She now has a great fear of trees.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
Old age’s
■
“When I was wo r k i n g,I liked having apprentices
and passing my skills on to young people,” s ay s
H e n ri Gueri n o t , a French cabinet-maker who
regards his retirement as just another kind of activity.
At 83, he is as enthusiastic as ever and still teaching his
craft to yo u n g s t e rs between the ages of nine and 14.
His passion has proved infectious. More than a
decade ago, in the French city of Tr oye s ,he was the firs t
retired person to get invo l ved in an association called
“ L’Outil en main” ( “ L e t ’s Pick Up Our Wo r k t o o l s ” ) ,
which was set up to encourage contact between yo u n g
people and retired craftwo r k e rs.Through it,the elderly
can stay active and continue to feel useful.
To d ay more than 100 elderly people are follow i n g
G u e ri n o t ’s example and teaching children outside
school hours such skills as carp e n t ry, g l a s s - m a k i n g,
s t o n e - c u t t i n g, c o n s t ruction and plumbing. T h e
e x p e ri e n c e ,p atience and wisdom of the old wo r k e rs
go well with the inquisitive n e s s , talent and
aw k wardness of the young people, all making for the
kind of tender complicity familiar to gr a n d p a r e n t s
Today’s elderly people are
increasingly reluctant to be
sidelined into inactivity when
they retire from full-time
work. To satisfy their
appetite for enjoyment and
achievement, retirees are
getting involved in a host of
activities, from universities
for older people to senior
citizens’ Internet clubs.
Many of them are making a
notable contribution to
society using their
knowledge and experience to
help bridge the generation
gap.
+ …
● L’Outil en main:
23 rue Pierre-Gauthier,
10000 Troyes.
Tel:(33-3) 25 73 35 88.
● Mouvement de 
la Flamboyance:
4 Bd du Temple, 75011 Paris.
Tel:(33-1) 42 52 20 21
F rench seniors bridge the divide
and gr a n d c h i l d r e n .
Strengthening ties between generations is also
the goal of another French move m e n t ,
“ F l a m b oya n c e ” , whose members are retired people
who each year stage a series of cultural and sport i n g
e vents (known as “Le printemps des générat i o n s ” ,o r
“The Dawn of New Generations”) all over the country.
The proceeds go towards helping the least fort u n at e
young people to get a start in life.
The amounts raised—between 5,000 francs
($1,000) and 50,000 francs ($10,000) from each
e vent—are modest but they can work wo n d e rs.
Examples include a 17-year-old girl who was able to
complete her training as a personal care-prov i d e r ,
which she had had to break off due to lack of money,
another girl who got a computer so she could do
s e c r e t a rial work at home and a young man who had
his driving school fees paid for so he could become a
m e s s e n g e r.
Last year some 15 jobs were created in this way for
needy young people. Not a large number, but an
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 35
The granny boom
new horizons
■
At the age of 60 or thereabouts, m a ny people
come to the end of their working live s ,but this does
not mean that they no longer have any urge to
l e a rn . According to figures from the Pa ri s - b a s e d
I n t e rn ational A s s o c i ation of Unive rsities of the T h i r d
Age (AIUTA ) ,there are more than 1,700 senior citizens’
u n i ve rsities worldwide cat e ring for these etern a l
s t u d e n t s.
Although their structures and management methods
differ widely from one country to another, u n i ve rs i t i e s
for the elderly usually share a desire to help older people
p l ay a full part in cultural and social life.They do not
award degr e e s ,and they do not require their students to
h ave any particular qualific ation when they enroll.
One successful example of this type of institution
was set up at Shimizu, in Ja p a n , in 1985. D u ring the
last academic ye a r , it had 2,500 students. At this
“ u n i ve rsity for vo l u n t a ry students”, which has been
awarded a prize by the Japanese gove rnment for “ t h e
valuable contri bution it has made as an adult educat i o n
■
In September 1998, D r. Jason Grinnell was the
winner of a contest organized by the
S e n i o rsSearch company to find the wo r l d ’s oldest
I n t e rnet surfer.At 96 ye a rs of age, Jason moves about
the Net like a fish in wat e r.“I have seen the birth of the
a u t o m o b i l e ,a i rp l a n e ,t e l e p h o n e , radio and television.
N ow the computer and the Internet have opened a
whole new world for my wife Theresa and my s e l f
t h at , God willing, we will continue to explore for
m a ny ye a rs to come”,s ays Dr. G ri n n e l l ,whose interest
in computers began when he was 89.
A retired Texas doctor, Jason Grinnell is by no
means the only elderly person to use the computer for
sending or receiving e-mail, shopping online or merely
looking through pages on which there is no short a g e
of cookery recipes or adve rtisements for dream cru i s e s.
S e n i o rs S e a r c h ’s aims are clear from its slogan:“the only
search directory exclusively for the over-50 age gr o u p ” .
A nybody over 50 can become a member free of charge
and explore the sections on offer, which include
antiques and collections, a rt galleries and museums,
books or social clubs.
S e n i o r N e t , a non profit-making organizat i o n
set up in California twe l ve ye a rs ago with the aim of
teaching older people to use modern technologi e s ,
has another of the best-known homepages most
I t ’s never too late to surf
Eternal students
widely consulted by this cat e g o ry of the public.
With its 27,000 members , SeniorNet receive s
500,000 visits a month, most of them from surfer
veterans in the United States and Canada with an
average age of 68.Its annual budget stands at $1.5
million,one-third of which comes from members’
subscriptions and the remaining two-thirds from
a d ve rt i s e rs and donations from foundations and
c o m p a n i e s , which have no hesitation in funding
this type of venture, since “in exchange, they get
good publicity and tax breaks,” explains A n n
Wrixon,the organization’s executive director.
Other sites choose to foster relations betwe e n
g e n e r at i o n s.This is the case of the French C y b e rp a p y
site on which older people help yo u n g s t e rs with their
h o m e work—something they have done all their live s
but can now do by computer.C r e ated and funded by
the Boulanger corp o r ate foundat i o n , it consists of a
large electronic mailbox divided into seven theme
a r e a s — l i t e r at u r e ,h i s t o ry and geogr a p hy, l a n g u a g e s ,
p h i l o s o p hy, c o m p o s i t i o n , m at h e m atics and the
p hysical sciences—to which pupils send in their
q u e s t i o n s. In practice, the older people, who do not
gi ve their names or occupat i o n s , reply within 24
h o u rs. The questions and answe rs are constantly
monitored by a team of professionals. ■
e s t a b l i s h m e n t ” , there is no age-limit for either students
or teachers.The teachers are vo l u n t e e rs ,as well as the
s t u d e n t s , enrolment fees are reasonable and there is
ample opportunity to make new fri e n d s.
Shimizu has one male student for eve ry four
females and the most common age bracket ranges
b e t ween 60 and 70, although there is an increasing
number of older students attending classes in dancing,
d r a m a , the humanities or manual wo r k .
The aim is to gi ve old people the opportunity to
study by providing them with knowledge enabling
them to lead better, h e a l t h i e r , richer and happier
l i ve s. In the opinion of Dr Tak Kwa n - K o n g, a specialist
in geri at rics and editor-in-chief of The Jo u rnal of the
Hong Kong Geri at rics Society,“This type of institution
is something to be encouraged, especially nowa d ay s
when elderly people have often been gi ven a negat i ve
i m a g e . E xercising the mind can maintain mental
fit n e s s , just as physical exercise can maintain phy s i c a l
fit n e s s. An appropri ate life-style, r ather than dru g s ,
+ …
● h t t p : / / w w w. s e n i o rs s e a rc h . c o m
● h t t p : / / w w w. s e n i o r n e t . o rg
● h t t p : / / w w w. c y b e r p a p y. c o m
When I happen
to stop and look
in the depths
of my bright mirro r,
a l a s, an unknown 
old man
seems to meet my eye.
Kakinomoto No Hitomaro
(681?-729), Japan
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
■
The Greek philosopher Plato believed that
p h i l o s o p h e rs are wise men who devote their live s
to learning how to die and that philosophy,
among other things, is a long and difficult learn i n g
process which teaches us to gr ow old and face up to
the climactic moment of our live s.There is nothing
melancholy about this process of “ l e a rning to die”.O n
the contrary, it means that it is only towards the end
of our days that we are really able to profit from life and
confront the imminence of death with fortitude and
d e t e rm i n ation and without despondency. In the minds
of the ancients, living to a ripe old age offered not so
much respect from society as a reassurance that they
would pass on gently from the world of the living to the
kingdom of the dead.
The culture of Antiquity suggested that two
f o rms of existence were wo rt hy of emulat i o n :t h at of
heroes like Achilles who enjoy a short and action-
packed life, and that of venerable elders who learn to
lead quiet and secret inner lives in accordance with
the ideal of Stoicism. In a way, it was impossible to
e nvisage these pat t e rns of individual behaviour in
i s o l ation from each other, and the models for living
they offered were highlighted when the two we r e
c o n t r a s t e d .As a result, our cultural tradition has for
c e n t u ries made an almost religious cult of the two
archetypes pers o n i fied by the hero and the elder.
According to the form e r , the hero’s brave ry is a
quality which makes it possible to confront the ri s k s
and vicissitudes of life and which steels the character.
The second conjures up an image of the experi e n c e
and peace of mind which, so the Roman philosopher
Seneca believe d , only comes with old age, in other
words when the desires of the flesh forsake us and the
mind becomes detached from sensuality and soars in
fli g h t .To cut a long story short , the ancients felt that
it was best to die either ve ry young or ve ry old, s i n c e
old age, in spite of its disadva n t a g e s , was the age of
reason in which the mind finally tri u m p h s.
H owe ve r , we no longer live in the age of ancient
Greece or the Renaissance or even of old-fa s h i o n e d
bourgeois society, which also flu c t u ated betwe e n
the ideal of the hero and the culture of the pat ri a r c h .
Ours is a society which has left traditional values
behind and is dangerously inclined to offer an
e x c l u s i vely technological solution to all life’s
p r o b l e m s. I t ’s not so much that we disregard the
value of the experience or tradition which used to
f o rm a natural part of the knowledge of ve ry old
people as that we have learned that no wise pers o n ,
however retentive or sharp their memory may be,
can remember as much as a computer, as the
champion chess-player Gary Kasparov discovered
(although he, i n c i d e n t a l l y, is still regarded as being
a young man).
Enduring suffering and solitude
Our collective ideal is machine-like, and we know
t h at when machines gr ow old they are taken out of
commission and dismantled and their parts recy c l e d ,
or else they are sent to the scrapyard to be broken up.
We do the same with our old people so that ,a l t h o u g h
technology has succeeded in extending the limits of
our useful lives as never before and in balancing our
d i e t , and is gradually unravelling all the secrets of our
b o d i e s , it does not seem to have found a sat i s fa c t o ry
a n swer to living in old age.The religion of modern i t y
only wo rships youthful gods. Our world has come to
be populated by splendid young people who are
s u p e r ficial and pampered and whose impulsive
b e h aviour knows no bounds, and by gr ow i n g
n u m b e rs of old people who, as the French thinker
Jean Baudrillard has observe d , inhabit a kind of  T h i r d
World of existence.People with no future and painful
m e m o ries of a past in which nobody is interested, t h e
denizens of this Third World are condemned to live in
a mundane present dedicated to generating profit s
for the powerful cosmetics and mass touri s m
i n d u s t ries and for the pension and insurance system
t h at manages wo r k e rs ’s av i n g s. No matter how much
technology may have improved their lot, the status of
old people bears no resemblance to the remedy for all
ills preached by the ancient Stoics.The onset of old
age not only brings the threat of sufferings that we r e
not known in the past,such as A l z h e i m e r ’s disease,bu t
is also compounded by such misfortunes as solitude,
to which there is no easy answe r. Only by adopting a
new Stoicism, a rule for living which teaches us how
to gr ow old and die, as it did in the past, shall we be
able to prevent the gr e ater life expectancy due to
technical progress from bri n ging new and painful
e x p e riences in its wa k e . ■
The Stoic way
Enrique Lynch*
In a world devoted to the cult of
youth and the machine, classical
Greek philosophy can help us to
grow old gracefully
*Autonomous university of
Barcelona (Spain)
H ow much go o d n e s s
and humour do yo u
need to bear the horro r
of old age? The ga rd e n
outside and the flowe rs
in the bedroom are
b e a u t i f u l , but the
s p ring is, as we say in
Vi e n n a ,“a fa rc e ” .
I have fin a l l y
d i s c ove red wh at it
means to feel cold.
Sigmund Freud (1856-1939),
Austria
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
The suffering caused 
by Hurricane Mitch and
the financial tempests
rattling the global
economy bring new
reasons to lighten the
debt of the poorest
countries
■
The deva s t ation wrought by
Hurricane Mitch in November was
horrific. In three days, the hurricane
wiped out 20 years of development in the
region, according to UN agencies, leaving
thousands of people dead and reportedly
about three million homeless.
But as gove rnments and intern at i o n a l
o r g a n i z ations tried to mobilize funds for
relief effort s , another debate reared its head:
should Nicaragua and Honduras, both low
i n c o m e ,h e avily indebted countries badly hit
by Hurricane Mitch, continue to pay a total
of $2 million a day in debt repay m e n t s —
money which could provide temporary
housing for 800,000 people?
The British Secretary of State for
I n t e rn ational Deve l o p m e n t , Clare Short ,
s t ated early on that debt relief was “ a n
i rr e l e va n c e ” when the pri o rity lay in
avoiding cholera and “pulling people out
of the mud”. But a few days lat e r
Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon
Brown called on all creditors to support a
t wo - year morat o rium on debt serv i c e
payments.
This shift in thinking reflects a gr ow i n g
realization as to just how bad things have
gotten for the wo r l d ’s poorest nat i o n s. S i n c e
at least the mid-1990s, a few deve l o p i n g
countries have simply stopped servicing a
large portion of  their debts—that is pay i n g
the interest and principal on loans. T h e
reason is simple: their gove rnments are
e f f e c t i vely bankru p t . Mozambique and
Nicaragua are only able to pay a third of
their scheduled debt service (the amount
of repayments on all loans).For Nicaragua,
this fraction amounts to $221 million a
year—three times that which the
government spends on health.
Bankrupt 
states
By 1996, it was clear even to the wo r l d ’s
major creditors that something had to be
d o n e . When middle or high income
c o u n t ries like Brazil, Jordan or Russia have
run into problems managing their debts,
the standard approach has been to
reschedule or push back their serv i c e
p ayments through agreements generally
brokered by multilateral organizations like
the Intern ational Monetary Fund (IMF)
o r , in the case of commercial lending, b y
the Pa ris Club, an informal group of
creditor gove rnments with a perm a n e n t
secretariat in the French Treasury.
But loan rescheduling cannot solve the
problems of the poorest countri e s. T h e i r
financial crises have been so extreme that
they generally manage to service just half of
their total debts.
The World Bank proposed the HIPC
( H e avily Indebted Poor Countri e s )
I n i t i at i ve in 1996 (see box ) . The aim wa s
to enable poor countries to get a more
secure financial footing. This was “ g o o d
news for the poor,” according to the bank
p r e s i d e n t , James Wo l f e n s o h n . “ T h i s
i n i t i at i ve is a breakthrough . . . It deals with
debt in a comprehensive way to gi ve
c o u n t ries the possibility of exiting from
unsustainable debt.”
Under the HIPC Initiat i ve , c r e d i t o rs
a gree to share the burden of cutting debts
including for, the first time, t h o s e
stemming from World Bank and
I n t e rn ational Monetary Fund (IMF)
l o a n s. The World Bank determines the
“ s u s t a i n a b l e ”l e vel at which a country can
Debt re l i e f:
a creditable solution?
Angela Tr a v i s *
*Media Officer for the Jubilee 2000
Coalition
A demonstration in favour of debt relief for poor countries held in Birmingham (UK) in May 1998.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
E T H I C S
manage a debt and the creditors cut their
p o rtions respective l y. A list of 41 countri e s
has been drawn up, identifying when and
h ow much debt relief should be expected.
It is estimated that another 25 countri e s
will eventually be added to the list.
H owe ve r , the plan looks better on paper
than in practice. In short , the HIPC
i n i t i at i ve delive rs too little, too lat e ,
according to critics and non-gove rn m e n t a l
o r g a n i z ations campaigning for Third Wo r l d
debt relief. Only two countri e s , U g a n d a
and Bolivia, h ave had their debts lightened,
while another five are slated for assistance
in 1999. O t h e rs like Tanzania and Ethiopia
cannot expect anything until 2002.
In understanding the HIPC
s h o rt c o m i n g s , it is important to remember
t h at many of the poorest countries have
long been paying less than half the
scheduled debt serv i c e .I t ’s a bit like hav i n g
t wo loans, but only being able to pay
interest on the second one. If the bank
w rites off the first loan, your bank balance
will look better, but your payments on the
second loan continue, so you do not gain
a ny additional benefit s.
Consider the case of Uganda, the first
country to benefit from HIPC.Under  the
i n i t i at i ve , its total debt has been reduced
by just 11 per cent.The story is the same for
Mozambique, due to receive relief in June
1 9 9 9 . Although the country ’s total debt
(about $5.8 billion in 1996) will drop by
$1.4 billion, much of this is
“ u n r e c ove r a b l e ” debt—meaning debt the
g ove rnment wa s n ’t expected to repay
regardless of HIPC.
M o z a m b i q u e ’s debt service will only
fall from $112 million a year to $100
m i l l i o n , a saving equivalent to about 80
cents per capita.
While reducing total debt is important
to keep a country’s books looking healthy,
the key to finding new resources to invest in
education or health services, for example,
lies in cutting those debts that countri e s
actually service and not those considered
unrecoverable.
For Jean-Louis Sarbib,World Bank vice
p0resident for Africa, HIPC is “not really
about wiping off debt . . . It’s just making
sure that these countries can remain good
credit risks. . . .The idea of HIPC is in fact
to allow you to continue to be a good
financial citizen of the world community.”
But why not simply write off the debts
and service payments to offer a  fresh start to
poor countries? G. G o n d we , D e p u t y
Director of the IMF’s A f rican Depart m e n t
outlined some key concerns in the F i n a n c i a l
Ti m e s in August 1998: “Who would lend
again to recipients of such cancellat i o n ?
W h at guarantee is there that the money
s aved would be put to effective use?”
G o n d we is referring to the fa m i l i a r
argument of moral hazard: w riting off debts
and service payments will reduce the
incentive to better manage finances in the
future and may worsen already poor credit
ratings.This argument is valid when loans
h ave been made for sound economic
i nve s t m e n t s. But what about money loaned
not pri m a rily for investment reasons, bu t
r ather for political reasons to win allies or to
increase foreign exports? 
There is no scarcity of cases of
politically motivated lending. P r e s i d e n t s
Marcos of the Philippines, S u h a rto of
Indonesia and Mobutu Sese Seko of the
former Zaire were all grateful recipients of
loans from the We s t . Nicaragua and
Mozambique were equally well supported
by the former Soviet Union. Ve ry little
attention was paid to how the money was
used or abused.
“ O n e - fifth of all developing country
debt consists of loans gi ven to prop up
compliant dictat o rs ,” insists Jo s e p h
H a n l o n ,p o l i cy officer with the Jubilee 2000
C o a l i t i o n , which regroups NGOs,
grassroots movements and trade unions in
40 countries to push for Third World debt
r e l i e f. “But when the dictat o rs fa l l , it is
expected that their democratically elected
s u c c e s s o rs should repay those debts.
Lenders must take a much greater share of
the responsibility and accept the losses.”
Popular pressure
for debt cancellation
There is another key question: who will
b e n e fit from debt relief? There is a genuine
concern that blanket debt relief will not be
used to reduce pove rty and improve
e d u c ation or sanitation systems.
D e m o c r a cy is still young in many
d e veloping countri e s. M a ny don’t have
official watchdogs or independent media
strong enough to examine gove rn m e n t
policy.
For the World Bank, the solution lies in
linking debt relief to strict adherence to
IMF structural adjustment policies.
Tanzania and Ethiopia, for example, h ave
Only two countries, Uganda and Bolivia,
have had their debt burden lightened, while
another five are slated for assistance in
1999. Others like Tanzania and Ethiopia
cannot expect anything until 2002.
suffered from delays in relief because they
did not make the  adjustments deemed
n e c e s s a ry. But does such macro-economic
adjustment ensure that the poor will 
b e n e fit ?
O x fam argues that additional “ h u m a n ”
measures must be put in place.The Bri t i s h
NGO proposes that for every dollar saved
through debt relief, the gove rnment spends
an equivalent amount on health, e d u c at i o n
and sanitat i o n . Although criticized for
encroaching on the decision-making powe r
of gove rn m e n t s , this approach has the
a d vantage of reassuring creditors that debt
relief will not be wasted.
For the time being, this kind of human
The aftermath of Hurricane Mitch in a
Nicaraguan village.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
Outlawing
excision
Several African countries have banned the
ancient ritual of excision.The latest is Côte
d’Ivoire, where a bill is expected to go before
parliament early this year.
Wo m e n ’s campaigners have welcomed the
m o v e.Such mutilations often involve cutting the
c l i t o r i s, and sometimes the labia,with dirty razor
blades or broken glass and frequently lead to
d e a t h .There are no figures because such deaths
are usually hidden,or blamed on something else.
If the law gets passed, anyone who excises a
female may be jailed up to five years and fined
$ 4 , 0 0 0 .H o w e v e r, the legislation will be difficult
to apply. Non-excised women are considered
i n c o m p l e t e, and more likely to have lovers
before marriage, a deterrent for prospective
husbands. “It’s part of the culture, and parents
are ashamed when their little girls are not
excised,” says Geneviève Bro-Grebe, president
of the Ivoirian Network of Wo m e n ’s
O r g a n i z a t i o n s.“And it makes a lot of money for
those who practice excision.It’s a big feast, a
big event for society as a whole.”
As Gueï Bah Ko n é , a woman who used to
excise girls but decided to stop after working
with women’s groups, e x p l a i n s, “during the
excision period in December, I could excise up to
20 girls a day. In return,their parents gave me
sheep, cows, and money. Now I earn nothing.”
Another stumbling block is illiteracy:68 per
cent of Côte d’Ivoire’s women can’t read
newspapers informing them of their new rights.
So the task of spreading the message has been
left to NGOs, l i ke the Ivoirian Association for
the Defence of Women (AIDF).Constance Yai,
the AIDF president, has been traveling the
country explaining the dangers of excision and
the related HIV risks. She says many people
m i s t a kenly think excision is required under
Islamic law.
Burkina Fa s o, N i g e r i a , G u i n e a , and Ghana
have all adopted laws banning excision, but it is
still widely carried out.As in Côte D’Ivoire, half
the women in Guinea are excised. In Ghana,
where about 20 per cent of women are excised,
several women were recently tried and
sentenced for continuing their mutilation trade.
■
A multi-speed road to rescue
■ E ven before Hurricane Mitch, N i c a r a g u a
and Honduras applied for debt relief through
the HIPC Initiat i ve .A decision for Nicaragua is
expected within months,s ays Jeff Kat z ,p ri n c i p a l
economist for the initiat i ve , while “ H o n d u r a s ’
qualifying track record was a little more
a m b i g u o u s , so we will have to see.”
K atz points out that the “special needs”o f
c o u n t ries facing post-conflict situations are
already recognized.“ Post-disaster situat i o n s
present many of the same issues. One could
a r g u e — e ven more than in a post-confli c t
s i t u at i o n — t h at the country concerned is not
responsible for a disaster occurri n g,”he say s.
It can take up to six ye a rs for a country to
r e c e i ve debt relief under the HIPC Initiat i ve .
The relief should come only after a country
works out a structural adjustment progr a m m e
with the World Bank and IMF and then
d e m o n s t r ates that it can adhere to those
p o l i c i e s.At the end of this peri o d , the country
could see its loans reduced if principal and
interest payments exceed limits considered
u n s u s t a i n a b l e . For example, debt serv i c e
charges are considered unmanageable if they
amount to more than 20 per cent of the va l u e
of a country ’s annual export s.
H owe ve r , HIPC relief can be quicker for
c o u n t ries that demonstrate both need and
good behav i o u r.For example,as of Nove m b e r
1 9 9 8 ,Uganda and Bolivia were receiving debt
relief because of their relat i vely strong track
records in adhering to structural adjustment
p o l i c i e s.Burkina Fa s o,Côte d’Ivo i r e ,G u ya n a ,
Mali and Mozambique are now slated for
a s s i s t a n c e .The total amount of debt reductions
already agreed is wo rth about six billion dollars
in terms of the nominal value of principal and
interest payments ori ginally due.
Of cours e , a lot of these debts were not
going to be paid any way. But the beauty of
H I P C , s ays Kat z , is that it cleans up the
accounting books of these countries so that
they can continue to receive intern at i o n a l
assistance instead of being forced to rely on
high interest commercial loans. “Debt relief
is just part of the financial picture in reducing
p ove rty and promoting sustainable
d e ve l o p m e n t ,” he say s. “A larger part for
most countries will be new grants and new
flows of va rying concessional resources.”
C ritics maintain that relat i vely little has
been done to help poor countries manage
their debts in comparison to the billions of
d o l l a rs mobilized by the intern at i o n a l
community to rescue middle and high income
c o u n t ri e s , such as during the Asian cri s i s.
“These are ve ry different kinds of money,”s ay s
K at z .“At the World Bank,we have the capital
base which enables us to relat i vely easily and
quickly borr ow money to re-lend to South
K o r e a . But in the case of a poor country, t h e
money that we make available to them is not
on commercial term s. It is ve ry highly
concessional [minimal service charges].T h at
money is essentially tax-paye rs ’m o n e y,w h i c h
means that it is ve ry hard to mobilize.” ■
+ …
● h t t p : / / w w w. w o r l d b a n k . o rg / h i p c
d e velopment pers p e c t i ve is essentially
ignored by creditors. However, the World
Bank has agreed to review the HIPC
I n i t i at i ve this ye a r. Instead of waiting for
a ny major changes, the gove rnments of
N o r way, Finland and Japan have decided to
begin canceling debts independently.
Two fa c t o rs help explain this
m o m e n t u m . F i rs t , popular pressure is
gr ow i n g . In May 1998, for example, 7 0 , 0 0 0
people formed a human chain around the
l e a d e rs attending the G8 summit in
B i rmingham (UK). S e c o n d l y, the prospect
of global economic recession is forcing
creditors to change their way of thinking.
The financial crashes in East Asia and
Russia sent shock waves around the
i n t e rn ational financial community. T h e
frantic bailouts of South Korea,Thailand,
Indonesia and Russia have pressed the IMF
to come to the rescue with over $140 billion
in finance.
The current climate of recession has
highlighted the reasons for raising the calls
for poor country debt relief. It is difficult to
believe claims made by creditors that they
cannot afford further debt relief.The HIPC
I n i t i at i ve for the poorest would cost just $8
billion—a pittance compared to the billions
a l l o c ated to push back the debt payments of
middle income countri e s. Ja p a n , f o r
e x a m p l e , which is far deeper in recession
than European or North A m e ri c a n
c o u n t ri e s , has managed to cancel $500
million wo rth of debts owed by deve l o p i n g
countries.
Canceling effectively unpayable debts
owed by the poorest countries may turn out
to be a sensible policy for all creditors. As
well as the strong moral argument for debt
r e l i e f, there could be sound fin a n c i a l
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F T H E T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
The last two decades have seen an explosion in the number of museums and
a transformation of their place in society
Museums hoist their
new colours René Rivard*
■
Museums reached a turning-point at
the end of the 1960s. They tried to
s m a rten themselves up, to revive their
job of teaching the public and to at t r a c t
more visitors. M a ny new ones opened—
more than half the wo r l d ’s 25,000
museums started up during the past 50
ye a rs. E ven the idea of what a museum
should be has changed considerably and
given rise to a broad range of variations.
Museums were invented at the end of
the 19th century as places to gat h e r
together and preserve the finest examples of
human ingenuity and present them to the
p u b l i c. Early museums often lacked the
resources to look after their collections
properly and exhibit them at t r a c t i ve l y.T h e y
became dull, grey places which we r e
cramped and increasingly dusty.
These days greyness is rare. In fa c t , I
would divide museums into seven main
c at e g o ries and associate each one with a
c o l o u r: orange for “ i n t e rp r e t at i ve ”
m u s e u m s , green for those with an
e c o l o gical approach, ye l l ow for
community-centred museums, blue for
those which aim to share knowledge, gold
for museums which go in for the
s p e c t a c u l a r , s i l ver for bu s i n e s s - o ri e n t e d
museums and mauve for museums of
remembrance.
Interpretation—a watershed 
in museum history
The interpretative movement began in
the 1950s in US national parks such as the
Grand Canyo n , Ye l l owstone and the
F l o rida Everglades and spread throughout
the English-speaking world, from Canada
to Australia via the United Kingdom,
reaching as far as English-speaking
countries in Africa.
I n t e rp r e t ation marks a wat e rshed in the
h i s t o ry of museums. It gi ves pri o rity to a
subject or theme rather than the exhibits
t h e m s e l ve s , which are considered as
evidence from the past and not as the
centre of at t e n t i o n . I n t e rp r e t ation means
s t i m u l ating and surp rising people, a n d
c h a l l e n ging accepted ideas,without turn i n g
the museum into a classroom.Visitors are
encouraged to refer to their ow n
e x p e ri e n c e s , not just straight scientific
knowledge,and to relate on equal terms to
the heritage they are learning about.
In addition to national parks,h u n d r e d s
of historic spots around the world have
chosen this interp r e t at i ve approach.A m o n g
them are Canada’s Louisbourg Fo rt r e s s
a n d , in the United Stat e s , the town of
Salem and the bat t l e fields of the War of
I n d e p e n d e n c e . Since the late 1970s, t h i s
trend has involved new ways of presenting
things based on the experience of the visit
i t s e l f. V i s i t o rs explore the ambience of a
place steeped in history and see what they
can learn from it and what ideas it gi ve s
t h e m .I n t e rp r e t ation confronts people with
q u e s t i o n s ,t h e o ries and new perceptions of
history. The settlement of the West in the
United Stat e s , the slave trade and
c o l o n i a l i s m , for example, are put in
p e rs p e c t i ve .A rmed with this kind of cri t i c a l
approach,visitors come up with their own
i n t e rp r e t ations of the things they are
presented with.
In Quebec, museums which take an
i n t e rp r e t at i ve approach have experi m e n t e d
a lot with the role of interpreter and critic
and offer their visitors quite ori ginal places
and experiences. The Châteauguay Battle
Centre (commemorating Canada’s defeat
of an A m e rican invasion in 1812) has
chosen to question the part played by
heroes in our societies. The museum at
Trois-Pistoles encourages discussion about
the intensive whaling carried out by the
Basques in the estuary of the St.Lawrence
river in the 16th century.
A green 
revolution
In the 1970s, the populari z ation of
museums was taken further with the
d e velopment of the ecomuseum concept
by Georges Henri Rivière, an imaginative
French museologist who took a new look at
the three basic components of a museum—
the bu i l d i n g, the collections housed in it
and the people who come to see them.He
favoured replacing buildings as the site of
museums with a wider setting in which
t y p o l o gically classified collections wo u l d
* Consultant for museums and heritage development
A p i o n e e r i n g
UN E S C O p e r i o d i c a l
When the UNESCO periodical Museum was
launched in 1948, it was the first
international magazine devoted to museums.
To d a y,under the title Museum International, it is
still the only one. Published quarterly in 5
l a n g u a g e s, it provides information and analysis
about museology and has followed step by step
the developments that have transformed the
museum world.In the last half century it has done
much to further recognition of the importance of
the cultural heritage by the international
community. In recent decades, UNESCO has
contributed to the design, construction or
m o d i fication of museums in over 50 countries.
■
For subscriptions to the English edition,contact:
Blackwell Publishers (United Kingdom). Fax:+44
(0) 18 65 381 381
French and Spanish editions:Jean De Lannoy,
Brussels. Fax:+32 2 538 08 41.Internet:
jean.de.lannoy@infoboard.be
Russian edition: Tatiana Telegina (Moscow). Fax: 7
095 247 17 94
Arabic edition: Fawzy Abd El-Zaher (Cairo). Fax:20
2 39 22 566
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F T H E T I M E S
January 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 41
be replaced by examples of the natural and
cultural heritage which could be observed
in their normal env i r o n m e n t . The people
who visited such museums, he thought,
should be people who lived locally and we r e
both users and preserve rs of the heri t a g e
that was on display.
In Europe and North A m e ri c a , t h e r e
has been extensive experi m e n t ation with
R i v i è r e ’s concept of
d e c o m p a rt m e n t a l i z at i o n . E x a m p l e s
include the cultural park in Molinos
( A r a g o n ) , S p a i n , the Proud World House
( s h owing labour conditions) in Montreal
(Canada) and, in France, the ecomuseums
of Margeride (rural life) in the A u ve r g n e
and on the isle of Ouessant (the mari n e
environment).
Militant 
museums
The ecomuseum movement is mainly
a rural one, but urban va riants of
ecomuseums sprang up as needy distri c t s
in big A m e rican cities awoke in the 1970s
and 1980s. Neighbourhood museums
were opened in poor areas of New Yo r k ,
Washington D. C . , C h i c a g o, Tucson and
other cities. They were often in form e r
public places, o r d i n a ry houses or sheds,
and illustrated local eve ry d ay cultures,
from an ethnic, working-class or crafts
The Science Centre Museum at Monterrey (Mexico).
s t a n d p o i n t .
These new kinds of museums often
s p u rred existing ones to reconsider their
place in the city and in society at large.
S e veral conventional museums, such as the
C h i l d r e n ’s Museum in Indianapolis and
the New York City Museum, b e g a n
“ o u t r e a c h ”a c t i v i t i e s ,s t a ging exhibitions in
streets,suburbs and poor neighbourhoods
on themes including dru g s , violence and
sexually-transmitted diseases.
In the same area as the closely-linked
ye l l ow and blue cat e g o ries are two other
trends which have developed in seve r a l
p a rts of the wo r l d . The firs t , w h i c h
appeared in the mid-1980s, might be
called a “ m i l i t a n t ” t r e n d , where the
museum becomes an instrument of
community development by spreading
and sharing its resources. S e ve r a l
museums in the Sahel countries of Niger,
Burkina Faso and Mali have chosen this
approach involving exhibits from animist
c u l t u r e .Their aims and actions are similar
to those of European ecomuseums,
M e x i c o ’s community museums and the
neighbourhood museums of the United
S t ates and South A f ri c a .
The second trend,knowledge-sharing,
is found particularly in natural science and
science and technology museums which
seek to stimulate interest in science and to
point young people towards scientific
c a r e e rs. There are now many technology
museums and hundreds of science centres
all over the wo r l d , not only in We s t e rn
c o u n t ries but also in India and the Far East,
notably China, Japan and Indonesia.
Blockbuster 
exhibitions
The last two decades have been marked by
profound economic changes and
u p h e ava l s. In a number of countri e s ,
budgets for culture and museums have
been cut back.To cope with this situation,
some museums have adopted presentat i o n
and marketing techniques to raise money
The last two decades have been marked by
profound economic changes and upheavals.
In a number of countries, budgets for
culture and museums have been cut back
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
New Yo r k ’s Chinatown m u s e u m
S I G N S  O F T H E T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
30 sites added to
World Heritage
L i s t
UNESCO’s World Heritage Committee, which
met in Kyoto from 30 November to 2
December 1998, added 30 new sites (three
“natural” sites and 14 “cultural”sites) to the
World Heritage List, bringing the number of
listed sites of “exceptional universal value”to
582 in 114 countries, including two newcomers,
Belgium and the Solomon Islands.
The committee’s choice confirms its intention
to preserve items of the relatively recent
h e r i t a g e.After Völklingen ironworks (Germany,
added in 1994) and Verla groundwood and
board mill (Fi n l a n d ,1 9 9 6 ) , three new industrial
sites were chosen:A u s t r i a ’s Semmering railwa y ;
the four hydraulic lifts on Belgium’s Canal du
C e n t r e ; and the D. F. Wouda Steam Pumping
Station in the Netherlands.
The other new sites, with their countries, are
as follows: B e l g i u m : Flemish Béguinages; L a
G r a n d - P l a c e, B r u s s e l s. B o l i v i a : the Fort of
S a m a i p a t a . C h i n a : the Summer Pa l a c e, a n
imperial garden in Beijing; the Temple of
Heaven,an imperial sacrificial altar in Beijing.
C y p r u s : C h o i r o ko i t i a . Czech Republic:
Holasovice historical village reserva t i o n ;
gardens and castle at Kromeríz. France:routes
of Santiago de Compostela; historic site of Ly o n .
G e r m a n y : classical We i m a r. I t a l y : Cilento and
Vallo di Diano National Park with the
archaeological sites of Paestum and Velia,and
the Charterhouse of Pa d u l a ; the Historic Centre
of Urbino; the archaeological area and the
patriarchal basilica of Aquileia. Japan:historic
monuments of ancient Nara. L e b a n o n :O u a d i
Qadisha (the Holy Valley) and the forest of the
Cedars of God (Horsh Arz el-Rab). M e x i c o :
historic monuments zone of T l a c o t a l p a n ,t h e
archaeological zone of Pa q u i m é , C a s a s
G r a n d e s. The sub-Antarctic islands of New
Zealand. Portugal: prehistoric rock-art sites in
the Côa Valley. Russian Federation:the Golden
Mountains of A l t a i . Solomon Islands: E a s t
Rennell.Spain:university and historic precinct
of Alcalá de Henares; the historic centre of
Oviedo (extension of the churches of the
kingdom of the A s t u r i a s ) ; rock art of the
Mediterranean Basin on the Iberian peninsula.
S w e d e n : the naval port of Karlskrona. Tu r ke y :
the archaeological site of Tr o y. U k r a i n e : t h e
historic centre of Lviv. ■
■ New Yo r k ’s Chinat own History
Museum looks at the contribution of
Chinese and other people, i n c l u d i n g
tourists, to the growth of this Manhattan
n e i g h b o u r h o o d . It is a place of
remembrance and dialogue.
The museum, which opened in 1990, i s
a kind of laboratory where exhibitions and
activities are focused entirely on dialogue
b e t ween communities. Those who run it
keep their fin g e rs on the pulse of
neighbourhood problems and discuss with
the public—Chinese, New Yo r k e rs or
t o u ri s t s — h ow they might be solve d .
Interactive exhibitions are held to improve
the lives of temporary or permanent local
r e s i d e n t s. The museum’s contents raise
many questions on subjects ranging from
housing and demographic issues to the
p rinciples of respect and gr at i t u d e , a n d
Chinese culture.
The museum, which is split into seve r a l
l o c at i o n s ,uses unort h o d ox methods. It acts
as a kind of forum,stimulating discussion,
helping visitors in their dealings with the
a u t h o ri t i e s , highlighting little-know n
historical facts and demolishing, with help
from the visitors , prejudices and myths that
die hard,e.g.that Chinese are illegal aliens
only qualified to work in restaurants and
laundries, and that they lead secretive and
therefore shady live s. The museum also
t ries to act as an interm e d i a ry betwe e n
citizens and officialdom with the aim of
defending the poorest people.
The Chinat own Museum keeps links
with the past alive , but it is mainly
c o n c e rned with the neighbourhood as it
is today and with its future. T h r o u g h
d i s c u s s i o n , it reckons it has carved out a
role for itself that had hitherto been
n e g l e c t e d . By its openness, it invites all
New Yo r k e rs and visitors to unders t a n d
and love a living neighbourhood which is
still gr ow i n g .
■
for running costs and expansion by stagi n g
major events and adopting the profit -
o riented approach of the 1980s and 1990s.
A rt museums have led the fie l d ,
through large exhibitions billed as
e x c l u s i ves or “ firs t - e ve rs ” .The trend began
with the Tutankhamen exhibition in the
early 1970s. All the resources of adve rt i s i n g
and public relations are used to promote
p r e s e n t ations of an art i s t ’s new wo r k s , o f
rarely-seen pri vate or museum collections,
unique treasures or exotic or extraordinary
o b j e c t s. These blockbuster shows cost a
f o rtune to organize. Their purpose is to
raise large amounts of cash to enable
museums to repay their debts and put on
new exhibitions. N owa d ays museum
curators are often hired for their ability to
raise money or to stage shows of this kind,
hopefully to turn a profit.
This trend is growing as public grants
for museums and cultural bodies diminish.
The appearance of museum boutiques to
boost takings is also part of this bu s i n e s s
strategy.
Mourning 
and remembrance
A museum can also be an instru m e n t
whereby society can mourn a lost golden
age and at the same time look directly at
the present and the future. Through the
p rism of collected and exhibited objects,
h i s t o rical events and trends can be seen
in a pers p e c t i ve uncluttered with morbid
n o s t a l gi a .
The Scandinavians have long used
museums for this purpose.A century ago,
the Swedes opened the first open-air
museum ( s k a n s e n ) in Stockholm to
remember their traditional fa rming culture.
They and the Norwe gians are now opening
labour museums and industri a l
ecomuseums to solemnly bu ry their
g l o rious working-class and trade union
h i s t o ry, to mark the decline or death of their
major heavy industries and promote the
development of modern technology.
Over the past 15 years, new museums
of this kind have sprung up in many places
to commemorate atrocities and major
d i s a s t e rs that are engr aved in the collective
m e m o ry. Numerous institutions have
opened in North A m e ri c a , Europe and
I s r a e l , for example, to mark the Holocaust,
the Viet Nam war and other relat i ve l y
recent human tragedies.
In France, m a ny recently opened
m u s e u m s , such as the Memorial museums
at Caen and Péronne and a number of
Resistance museums, attempt to come to
t e rms with the terrible memories of two
world wa rs. The same kind of thing is
happening in Britain and the rest of
Europe. Other museums have been set up
to commemorate natural disasters , such as
gr e at flo o d s , volcanic eruptions and
e a rt h q u a k e s. These funerary monuments
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
■
Of all the at t r a c t i o n s , possibilities and
u n c e rtainties of the Intern e t , one of
those raising the most speculat i o n
centres on its impact on the production,
d i s t ri bution and consumption of inform at i o n
and news. In a recent report on the future of
the printed press in a digital wo r l d , D u t c h
media analyst Monique van Dusseldorp notes
t h at “ N e w s p a p e rs as carri e rs of content have
had to yield va rious functions in the past
c e n t u ry to radio and television serv i c e s ,a n d
n ow there are other cat e g o ries of inform at i o n
t h at might migr at e , this time to the net. . . .
Unexpected competitors such as search
e n gines and free homepage serv i c e s , as well as
the online services of television stat i o n s ,n ow
fight in the same arena for the user’s at t e n t i o n
and the limited adve rtising money ava i l a b l e .”
The fact is that the media cannot ignore
the fast and furious pace with which use of
the Internet is gr ow i n g . At a conference on
the electronic press held in Lyo n ,F r a n c e ,i n
October 1998, Randy Bennet, of the
Newspaper A s s o c i ation of A m e rica (NAA),
said that “The Internet market is expected
to increase from around 150 million users
worldwide today to almost 300 million by
the year 2001.” Surveys conducted by the
A m e rican company Fo rrester Research
forecast that worldwide online expenditure
on adve rtising will rise from almost $2
billion today to about $15 billion in 2003.
“The numbers tell us that the Internet will
continue to develop as a mass medium,
t h at adve rt i s e rs will increasingly shift dollars
to this medium and that traditional media
will have to figure out their role in this new
s p a c e ,” Bennet said. Miguel A n g e l
B a s t a n i e r , director of intern ational relat i o n s
with the Spanish daily El País, pointed out
t h at “ e ve ry newspaper will have to be on the
Internet as a service to its public and as a
means of self-promotion. It cannot run the
risk of seeing its readers obtain this serv i c e
from its competitors.”
In fa c t , the written press has turned to the
I n t e rnet in order to stay competitive with the
other online media. A m e rican Jo u rn a l i s m
magazine stated recently that there are 3,622
d i gital newspapers wo r l d w i d e . A year ago,
there were only some 900 outside the United
S t at e s , as against 1,563 in 1998, largely as a
result of the increasing number in Canada, t h e
United Kingdom, N o r way, Brazil and
G e rm a ny. Ye t , in spite of all the effort and
i nve s t m e n t , not a single online newspaper
can be considered profit a b l e .
The Wall Street Journal:
an eloquent exception
One of the main dilemmas editors are
t rying to resolve lies in switching from
n e w s p rint to the computer screen and in
making money without replacing the ori gi n a l
m e d i u m , in other words without readers
giving up the traditional form at and changi n g
over permanently to the electronic ve rs i o n .
“The important thing is not so much
going on the Internet as staying on it
without losing money on the pri n t e d
version,” says André Jaunin, founder and
manager of Edicom, the Internet site of
the Swiss group Edipresse, which publishes
a number of newspapers and magazines
including Le Mat i n, Tri bune de Genève, B i l a n
and Optima. “The idea is not to display all
the contents of the printed ve rs i o n ,” h e
says. “We consider that it is absurd to offer
the newspaper we are selling on the streets
free of charge on the Web. Our electronic
p u b l i c ation is different from the pri n t e d
ve rs i o n .The news items it contains are bri e f
and are updated eve ry ten minutes.They are
designed to be expanded in the following
d ay ’s printed edition.” H owe ve r , h a r d
i n f o rm ation is not enough. The new
t e c h n o l o gies have to be used to keep
I n t e rnet readers interested. Some of the
approaches which the electronic press can
offer to please the public and advertisers
include personalized services, free e-mail,
i n t e r a c t i ve articles and opportunities to
swap ideas via chat forums.
In Bennet’s view, “the key to success
with any new medium is a commonsense
approach to serving the needs of consumers
and advertisers, aided by technology, but
not driven by it.”
Simon Wa l d m a n , the Internet editor of the
English daily newspaper The Guardian,
d e s c ribed his efforts to create new products
of interest to its readers.“ We have designed a
space on our  Web page which presents cri c k e t
m atches in real time, for example,” he said,
“and this has been extremely successful.” E l
País Digi t a l, the leading light of the Spanish
electronic press with 50,000 hits a day in
October 1998, had a similar success with its
direct transmission of chess mat c h e s ,w h i c h
are particularly popular with Spaniards.
In terms of profit a b i l i t y, although there is
no unive rsal model or magic form u l a , t h e
n e w s p a p e rs which have gone onto the Net try
to surv i ve pri m a rily through subscri p t i o n s ,
More and more newspapers and periodicals 
are going online. How is electronic technology affecting the production 
and consumption of the printed word?
Can papers
n e t a profit ?
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
C O N N E X I O N S
financial pressure to succeed in this hard-
fought market may, out of the desire to be
firs t , fall into the temptation of transmitting
unchecked inform at i o n , neglecting the
a c c u r a cy they have traditionally attached to
information-gathering.
The virtually limitless amassing of
i n f o rm ation from a wide range of sources on
the Internet may also gi ve rise to a welter of
c o n f u s i o n . This makes the traditional
n e w s p a p e rs ’ task of rigorous selection and
objectivity even more va l u a b l e .Randy Bennet
b e l i e ves that consumer behaviour may change
as new choices and capabilities emerge, bu t
t h at the need to ensure that inform ation is
a c c u r at e , to gi ve an ove rview of events and to
p r ovide ready access will remain unaffected.
It is for this reason that newspapers will focus
on the individual and translate online the
t rust they have acquired over the ye a rs.
Will newsprint sink in the digital sea?
Some of the predictions made are out of
touch with reality. Bastenier forecasts that
most newspapers will eventually disappear
and that “the only surv i vo rs will be
heavyweights with a sense of perspective,
such as Le Monde or El País, or very small
provincial papers which are close to their
r e a d e rship and largely provide inform at i o n
about and for a particular community.
H owe ve r , I would not let the computer
screen be a substitute for the pleasure I get
from reading news on paper, where I can go
through the pages as I please, leaving part
of the paper for later on.”Although the last
word has not yet been written on the
s u b j e c t , it is quite clear that nothing will eve r
be the same in the world of inform at i o n
since the coming of the Internet. ■
Jany Lesseur
Website of the month
http://www.unu.edu
It is a university but has no student body, faculty or campus in the traditional sense.The “faculty”of
the United Nations University (UNU) is its worldwide network of scholars and its “students” are
mainly young researchers and other professionals from developing countries who receive postgraduate
training.
In 1969, following a proposal by the then Secretary-General U Th a n t , the United Nations
recommended that a new type of academic institution was needed to promote scholarly international
and scientific co-operation to help solve urgent global problems. Six years later UNU opened its doors.
UNU’s academic work is currently carried out at its Tokyo centre and by five research and training
centres and three programmes located in various parts of the world.Current priority areas of concern
are development economics research,new technologies, natural resources management, b i o t e c h n o l o g y
and the environment. A leadership academy opened in 1995 seeks to enhance the skills of young
future leaders. Soon to start is an internship programme for postgraduate students and working people
seeking jobs in the international public or private sector.
The homepage provides extensive information on all of UNU’s activities, its ongoing research,
conferences and seminars around the world.The UNU also produces its own academic publications and
co-operates in the production of five professional journals. ■
a d ve rtising and electronic trading.H owe ve r ,
most of them agree that surfers , who are
nomadic by nature and are constantly
s e a r c h i n g, are not prepared to pay a prov i d e r
to obtain their inform at i o n , unless it is vital
and can only be found on the Intern e t ,w h i c h
is seldom the case. Perhaps one of the most
eloquent exceptions is the authori t at i ve
financial newspaper T h e Wall Street Jo u rn a l,
which has more than 250,000 subscri b e rs ,
t wo-thirds of whom pay to receive only the
d i gital ve rsion of the publication which
n e ve rtheless does not turn a profit . A large
number of the electronic newspapers and
news bulletins in the United States which
had adopted the subscription method know
all about this.They are backtracking and are
t rying to attract as many visitors as possible in
order to sell adve rtising space.The free digi t a l
ve rsion of El Pa í s obtains its income basically
from adve rt i s i n g, from which it hopes to
make some $700,000 in 1998.M a riló Ruiz de
E l v i r a , who is in charge of the electronic
e d i t i o n , explains that plans are being made for
new strat e gies involving electronic trading,
c o n s u l t ation of archives and other paid
products and serv i c e s.André Jaunin points out
t h at , in addition to adve rt i s i n g, the main
sources of income from Edipresse’s Intern e t
site are electronic sales of travel bookings,
w i n e , books and music.
Although the Internet clearly offers
n e w s p a p e rs the opportunity to achieve
i m m e d i ate global reach and to compete
with a wide range of sources, it also obliges
them to keep on updating their content,
thus leaving very little time for checking.
This poses another dilemma: should they be
the first or the most reliable purve yor of the
news? Digital newspapers exposed to
Mobile
psychology
It’s easy to spot brand new owners of mobile
phones from a distance. Walking down the
street they grin like children who have just
unwrapped the toy of their dreams. And they
practically shout into the receiver, as if they
have trouble imagining that their voices can be
heard over such a tiny device. They are
experiencing a thrilling sense of freedom. In the
wink of an eye they can be in touch with anyone
whenever and wherever they please.
It took a century for the fixed telephone to
become a commonplace feature of everyday
life in Western societies; it took a decade for
the mobile phone to spread throughout the
countries of both North and South.According to
forecasts, the number of subscribers to one or
another of the world’s radiotelephony services
is expected to climb from today’s 275 million
or so to 530 million by 2003. Right now the
Scandinavian countries are in the lead. Th e
subscription rate is 53 per cent in Fi n l a n d ,47 per
cent in Sweden and 44.15 per cent in Norway,
followed by Japan (34.5 per cent),Italy (30 per
cent) and the United States (24 per cent).
L i ke eyeglasses and wristwa t c h e s, the mobile
phone “has joined the small circle of items that,
with astonishing speed, have become an
extension of the human body,” w r o t e
sociologist Jean-Claude Kaufmann in France’s
Le Monde n e w s p a p e r. The mobile
simultaneously reflects the changes of our times
and speeds them up. It allows users to mix the
professional,personal and social areas of their
lives at any moment. It responds to the
p e r vasive sense of urgency in modern societies,
bestows the gift of ubiquity and, s a y
sociologists and psychiatrists, reduces the
anxiety caused by absence and loneliness.
But the portable phone is also having an
impact on social behaviour.The sound of its ring
is increasingly perceived as an annoyance in
public places such as restaurants, c i n e m a s,
museums and trains,which are widely regarded
as havens of relaxation where people can enjoy
a brief respite from the fast and furious rhythm of
modern life. And they create new dilemmas for
u s e r s : when should they leave the phone on or
off and to whom should they give their number?
Do they really want their boss,m o t h e r,b o y f r i e n d
or girlfriend to be able to reach them anywhere,
anytime? The opening pages of the handbook of
mobile psychology are only now starting to be
w r i t t e n . ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
better known as “ Ta s i n i Vs The New Yo rk
Ti m e s” , attracted widespread attention as
this was the first new media copyright case
of its sort in the United States. In 1997, a
l ower court ruled in favour of the
p u b l i s h e rs ,s aying the existing US copyri g h t
l aw allowed the publishers to reuse
c o n t ri butions “in any revision of that
c o l l e c t i o n .”The case has now moved to the
appeals court.
“The present US copyright law does
not state explicitly anything about
electronic ri g h t s. C o u rts have just begun to
consider wri t e rs ’ claims and there are
demands to include electronic rights in the
existing law,” says Carlinsky.
On the other side of the A t l a n t i c,
though there are no specific regulations as
yet gove rning the use of journ a l i s t i c
m at e rial in the electronic media, j o u rn a l i s t s
and authors in many We s t e rn European
and Scandinavian countries have reached
partial or full agreements with publishers
over copyrights and the Internet.
Copyright law 
that benefits authors
“The existing European authors ’ ri g h t s
law is sufficient to handle the pay dispute
b e t ween wri t e rs and publishers in
electronic publishing. H owe ve r , the system
is different in Anglo-Saxon law,” s ay s
R e n ate Schroeder, of the Bru s s e l s - b a s e d
European Federation of Journalists.
The copyright law generally followed in
S c a n d i n avian countri e s , as well as in France
and Germany, benefits the authors. When
m at e rial is used again in electronic
p u b l i s h i n g, a u t h o rs have the right to be
consulted as to where and how it is used
and to receive extra pay m e n t . For example,
■
With Internet spreading like wildfire,
authors around the world have been
c l a m o u ring for protection of their
c o p y ri g h t s. H owe ve r , this has resulted in
an increasingly tough battle with publishers
who want writers to sign a contract giving
away all rights,including electronic.
Until a few ye a rs ago, a u t h o rs and
journalists may not have bothered to scan
through their work contracts with regard
to copyrights. In fact,many magazines did
not even send contracts to authors. N ow
both sides are careful about the mention of
“ c o p y ri g h t s ” in the contract for reuse of
a rticles and other creat i ve work in Intern e t
and electronic database systems.
A u t h o rs argue that print publishing is a
one-time event bri n ging in one set of
r e ve n u e s , including adve rt i s e m e n t s.On the
other hand, m at e rials in electronic
publications can be used repeatedly, each
time potentially generating new
a d ve rtisement reve n u e s.“So we tell authors
that it’s a big mistake to grant permanent
rights for a one-time fee,” s ays Dan
Carlinsky, vice president of the American
Society of Jo u rnalists and A u t h o rs (ASJA),
New York.
While some publishers are ready to pay,
o t h e rs maintain that once authors cede
their rights they cannot claim additional
payments for reuse of their material. In a
case filed in 1993, a group of freelancers in
New York challenged publishers and
electronic reusers of published wo r k ,
claiming copyright infri n g e m e n t .The case,
Writers bloc to defend
their rights
the leading French daily Le Monde e n t e r e d
into a two-year agreement with its staff in
1996 on electronic rights. From its annual
e a rnings through electronic publicat i o n s ,
it pays a percentage of its revenue from
online editions and CD-ROM to all its staff
m e m b e rs , whether or not their work has
been used.“This agreement is the first of its
kind in France and it is working well,” says
Michel Colonna d’Istri a , chief of L e
Monde’s multi-media services.
On the other hand, in the A n g l o - S a x o n
c o p y right model used in the US and the
UK and adapted also by the Netherlands,
publishers can and do use their economic
p ower to gain the right to reuse articles and
other creat i ve mat e rials after making a one-
off pay m e n t . A u t h o rs in these three
c o u n t ries claim that the present law denies
the right to compensation for the reuse of
their mat e ri a l s. In 1997, h owe ve r , t h r e e
Dutch journalists for the first time won a
c o u rt case against the newspaper d e
Vo l k s k ra n t over republication of their
articles without permission on CD-ROM
and the World-Wide Web.
The UK-based Ja n e ’s Inform at i o n
G r o u p, publisher of Ja n e ’s defence
m a g a z i n e s , demands all rights from authors
around the world for both print and
electronic editions. The magazine gr o u p
maintains that its one-off fee includes all
f o rms of delive ry. “So far no one has
complained,” says a Jane’s spokesperson.
Mike Holderness, who is active in the
campaign for electronic rights in the UK
for the National Union of Jo u rn a l i s t s
( N U J ) , s ays that the A n g l o - A m e ri c a n
c o p y right system gi ves economic adva n t a g e
to publishers and denies benefit to authors.
“There is an obvious need to harm o n i z e
c o p y right laws within the European
Union,” he says. ■
Print journalists are calling–usually in vain–for
additional payment when their articles are
reused in the electronic media
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Yo r d an R a d i c h ko v :
46 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
You like to say that life is a beautiful
sentence full of spelling mistakes.
Human lives are sentences written with lots
of love and inspiration but plenty of
m i s t a k e s , and mine is no exception.
However old and wise they are,people still
make mistakes.
You have said that people are the ro u g h
d raft of God. Would you compare God to
a writer who crosses a lot of things out?
I would be wa ry of comparing God to
a nyo n e , especially a wri t e r. God doesn’t
make mistakes,and I can’t imagine myself
p l aying the fool who would try and fin d
them. I don’t know whether God exists. If
he does, so much the better. If he doesn’t,
it’s not a tragedy.
As for people. . . . The other day, as I
was drinking my coffee and listening to the
r a d i o, I looked through my window and saw
a magpie looking after her babies in her
nest. And I said to myself, people are like
i n s e c t s. They are capable of looking in
different directions at the same time,
keeping one eye on the outside, the other
on the inside.
How do you see the world?
I’m convinced that disorder is the world’s
natural state.We’re the ones who make the
mistake of trying to set things straight.
People want to organize the universe while
they have enough trouble putting order into
their own lives.
Do you take the world seriously?
The world already takes itself seri o u s l y
enough without my putting my oar in.
E ve rything is extremely serious dow n
here—the committees, f o u n d at i o n s ,
i n t e rn ational organizat i o n s , p o l i t i c a l
r e gimes—not to mention the people who
gi ve themselves airs and believe in their
own gr e at n e s s. But when they ride on their
high horse we a ring a bowler hat , they forget
t h at all it takes is a gust of wind to blow the
h at away and all their gr e atness with it. I
hate anything that is deadly serious.
You have a marked taste for the absurd and
for paradox, which are the basis of your
approach to literature.
That is the only sensible approach in this
b o ring wo r l d .At the risk of shocking yo u , I
am convinced that humanity is bored.It is
ready to be entertained at the drop of a hat .
The mechanism is quite simple: just look at
the Monica Lewinsky affair in the United
S t ates! People all over the world feel
c o n c e rn e d , h ave got invo l ve d , h ave had a
good laugh. I tell myself that my readers
are bored and need to be entertained.So I
write for them what interests and amuses
m e . D o n ’t wo rry, my interests go beyo n d
Lewinsky and other affa i rs. I am fa s c i n at e d
by the peasant wisdom hidden behind the
apparent naivety of simple folk. I t ’s an
undercurrent in all my stories.
What do you think about current events?
News is like the fresh water that ri ve rs pour
endlessly into the ocean. It doesn’t make
the sea any less salty.
I have a strong feeling that the wo r l d
t o d ay is heading towards a prov i n c i a l i z at i o n
of mentalities,which are not developing at
the same pace as technology. I would even
s ay that things are moving backwa r d s.Ta k e
the A m e ricans again. They went to the
moon,much to their credit. But they have
made such a fuss over their president’s high
jinks that you can’t help wo n d e ring whether
the United Stat e s , despite all its modern
technology, is not somehow becoming one
of the world’s remote provinces.
The remote province is one of your 
favourite settings. Cherkaski, for example,
is a half-real, half-imaginary 
The ‘Kafka of Sofia’ uses
the grotesque to expose
the world’s absurdity in
short stories and plays
steeped in peasant
wisdom
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
the improbable
Bulgarian
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G  T O …
Bulgarian village in the middle 
of nowhere. Where did you get 
the idea for your series of books set 
in this village?
T h at was in the sixties. B u l g a ria was going
through a complex peri o d , to say the least.
I ’ ve always had a penchant for the
gr o t e s q u e .The Cherkaski that appears in
my stories is the result of this combinat i o n
of the complex and the gr o t e s q u e . But the
village really does exist. I t ’s near my
b i rt h p l a c e . I know it we l l . M a ny of my
c l a s s m ates came from there. They are
incredible people.They have n ’t changed.
In 1968 the local authorities arrested me
when I went back to Cherkaski to make a
m ovie based on my short story “ T h e
C a p t i ve Balloon”.
Why were you arrested?
Because I was doing something that didn’t
fit in with communist party ideals. M y
s h o rt story was banned almost as soon as it
was published, and the mov i e , which we
managed to finish after all sorts of trials and
t ri bu l at i o n s , was banned after the firs t
screening.The censors deemed my work a
s e rious attack on the dignity of the
B u l g a rian people. At the time literat u r e
either glori fied the system or it wa s
censored. My work had to be “heroic” in
order to be recognized.
It’s not easy to find “irreproachable
heroes” in the middle of Bulgaria—or
anywhere else, for that matter.
In Bulgaria, it’s not easy to survive unless
yo u ’re a hero. D i d n ’t you know that all
B u l g a rians are heroes? Didn’t you know
t h at we ’re the best? We ’ ve left all the vices to
our neighbours and kept all the virtues for
ourselves.We’re very proud of that. But to
tell the truth, I’ve noticed the same thing
just about everywhere in the world.
You’ve been criticized for creating
characters impervious to ideology.
At the time the authorities were incapable
of such subtle analysis. One of my
politically committed short stories is about
a man named Gotsa Geraskov, who makes
an imagi n a ry trip to Pa ris and arri ves there
on a public holiday. Disappointed to fin d
a city completely asleep, he turns around
and heads back home almost immediat e l y.
The censors noticed neither the political
dimension nor the criticism of the regi m e
t h at could be read between the lines. H a d
I written the same short story with
M o s c ow as the setting, there would have
been a harsh reaction. Fo rt u n at e l y, t h e
c e n s o rs took my work literally.
Your work is steeped in the
supernatural.Is that because it was
necessary to use coded 
language under the Zhivkov regime 
or was it a form of aesthetic
experimentation? Would you 
have written the same way in a
democracy?
I don’t like to express myself directly.
G r a n t e d , I have worked a bit like Aesop or
La Fo n t a i n e , but I would have written the
same thing in the same way under any
political system. Some critics have said
t h at I have drawn a gr e at deal of
i n s p i r ation from Bulgarian folklore. I t ’s
t rue that all my writing bears the impri n t
of the region where I was born . But it’s
also true that in the past what I wrote
wa s n ’t always understood in Bulgari a .
Sometimes the critics were hard on me.
My work didn’t meet with full acceptance
until Gabriel García Márquez’s books
were translat e d .
Your work has often been compared 
with his. Are you flattered or annoyed 
by that?
I’m not the least bit bothered by it.Critics
often compare wri t e rs when they don’t
know what else to say.
But García Márquez’s fiction is not 
peopled with the same kind of supernatural
beings as the tenets and verbludes that
appear in your work.
Did you invent these creatures or did you
borrow them from Bulgarian folklore?
The ve r b l u d e came straight out of my
i m a gi n at i o n , but the t e n e t s is a creature that
appears in Bulgarian folk tales.The name
m ay deri ve from the Russian word t e m,
which means shadow. An old belief has it
that if a cat hops over a corpse, the soul of
the deceased will never go to heave n . It will
remain earthbound and become a kind of
va m p i r e . But vampires are a Romanian
s p e c i a l i t y. Our t e n e t s are much nicer. N o t
only do they not drink blood, but they can
actually make themselves quite useful.T h e y
p l ay a positive role. One t e n e t s is said to have
finished weaving the rug of a woman who
had fallen ill.Another typed a short story
on my typewriter.
Maybe you don’t believe in them, but
the people who live in my region do. One
d ay, in the village where my mother wa s
b o rn , I asked an old woman if she had seen
a t e n e t s l at e l y. She answe r e d , “Oh no, we
haven’t seen any around here for ages, but
People are like insects. They are capable of looking in
different directions at the same time, keeping one eye on
the outside, the other on the inside.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
Bulgaria
Historical landmarks
14th-19th centuries: Ottoman
occupation.
1878: Bulgaria becomes independent
after the Russo-Turkish war.
1 9 1 2 : D u ring the first Balkan wa r ,
B u l g a ria fights with Greece, Serbia and
M o n t e n e gro against the Ottoman empire.
1913: Unhappy about the post-war
settlement, Bulgaria turns against its
former allies but is defeated.
1914-1918: Bulgaria joins the Central
Powers (Germany, Austria-Hungary), i.e.
the defeated side.
1941-1944: Bulgaria fights on the side of
the Reich and occupies part of Greece
and Yugoslavia.
September 1944:The communists
assume power.
1954-1989: Rule of Todor Zhivkov.
10 November 1989: Todor Zhivkov is
removed from power after a palace
revolution supported by Moscow.
November 1991:The Union of
Democratic Forces (UDF) comes to
power.
January 1995:The neo-communists,
under the name of the Bulgarian
Socialist Party, return to power.
February 1997:The UDF again replaces
the socialists.
Economic data
Bulgaria was essentially rural before
1944. During the communist period it
specialized in the mechanical, electronic,
chemical and food industries. After the
fall of communism, more than half the
population fell below the poverty line. It
was not until 1997 that signs of
improvement began to appear.
GNP: $1,140 per capita (1997), almost
half the 1990 figure. ■
the other day they were talking about them
on the radio.” In fa c t , she was referring to a
broadcast of one of my stories!
The inhabitants of Cherkaski 
a re totally cut off from the outside 
w o r l d . For them, nothing 
is more exotic than Romania, on the
opposite bank of the Danube,
w h e re they have never been. Have 
their lives changed since the fall of 
the Berlin Wa l l ?
Ve ry much so.Television has arri ved in the
remotest corn e rs of the prov i n c e . It has
broadened hori z o n s ,s t i rred new interests
and kindled new desires. A while ago I
visited my cousins in a small town near
C h e r k a s k i . Their house was empty. A s
u s u a l , n e i g h b o u rs appeared to tell me they
we r e n ’t there. “ W h e r e ’ ve they gone?” I
a s k e d . I was surp rised because my cousins
are getting on in ye a rs and usually at least
one old grandma was always home.“ T h e y
all went off to the municipal reading
r o o m ,” was the answe r , “to see a stri p
s h ow.”
You couldn’t say the change has not
been drastic! But that ’s not all. M o d e rn i t y
has totally transformed my village. I t ’s
been swa l l owed up and wiped off the map
by a dam! It’s as if it was intended to gi ve
me ideas for my stori e s. The march
We s t ward continues, as you might
i m a gi n e : the names of towns were changed
almost as soon as Zhivkov fell because, a s
e ve ryone know s , changes of that kind are
e s s e n t i a l . For example, the regi o n a l
c a p i t a l , M i h a ï l ov gr a d , has become
M o n t a n a , just like the A m e rican stat e .T h e
t ow n ’s name has been changed so often
no one knows what to call it any more.
Once it was called Ku t l ov i t s a .You have to
a d m i t , the name has a “ b a r b a ri a n ” ring to
i t . One day at the turn of the century, a
bearded man drove through the town in a
c a r.The rumour immediately spread that
he was King Ferdinand of Bulgaria in
p e rs o n . The village wo rthies called a
meeting and wrote a petition requesting
the National Assembly to change the
name of the village to “ Fe r d i n a n d ’s
Ku t l ov i t s a ” . It sounded much more
s t y l i s h !
How has Bulgaria changed? Where do you
think the country is heading?
For a ve ry long time I saw Bulgaria as a
white bear floating on an iceberg, all alone
in the middle of the ocean.We have n ’t come
down off the iceberg in the past few years,
but at least we pass other bears and wave to
each other. Soon we wo n ’t be alone any
m o r e . I think we ’re on the right track.We ’r e
no longer cut off and the world looks at us
in a different way. I have high hopes for the
future.
But Bulgaria still has problems, especially
“Didn’t you know that all Bulgarians are heroes?”
Area : 111,000 km2
Population : 8,726,000
Sofia
ROMANIA
TURKEY
GREECE
SERBIA
MACEDONIA
Plovdiv
VarnaCherkasti
Kalimantsi
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
January 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 49
T A L K I N G  T O …
new literary trends in Bulgaria?
Ye s , especially with young authors. B u t
again, permit me to voice some doubts on
the quality of the results. I’m not against
i n fluences that could be fruitful bu t , a s
Maupassant said,the best belly-dancing is
done in the Ori e n t . I don’t like pseudo-
i n n ovat i o n s. Call me old-fa s h i o n e d , but I
miss the days when 80,000 copies of a nove l
by Victor Hugo were published in Bulgari a
and all of them sold out! T h at ’s saying a lot
for a country with a population of eight
m i l l i o n . There was a tradition of reading
which is dying out nowa d ay s. As I said,
B u l g a ri a ’s famous reading rooms, w h i c h
h ave been around since the nineteenth
century, are being turned into nightclubs.
Many young Bulgarians have emigrated or
are thinking of doing so because of the
country’s severe economic and moral crisis.
Do you have a message for them?
I would be tempted to advise them to stay
at home.There’s no place like home.But I
am wa ry of persuading or dissuading
anyone.I can only speak for myself. In my
v i e w, people must draw water from their
own we l l s.The French have their we l l s ,t h e
G e rmans have theirs ,e ven if they draw beer
from them. . . .And I think eve ryone should
do the same. Look at wild animals.
W h e r e ver they roam, they always go back to
their lairs. Salmon swim to the Sargasso
Sea to die. Birds return home no mat t e r
how far they may have migrated. Can you
imagine that a little bird can be wiser than
a human being?
In view of the tragedies afflicting the
Balkans, do you think Balkan writers have a
special role to play?
W ri t e rs can decide to defend a cause
through their wo r k , or they can do the
o p p o s i t e .I t ’s a personal choice. I don’t have
a ny advice to gi ve on that because, as we
s ay back home, “if you want to do
somebody harm , then gi ve them advice.”
In the end, e ve rything depends on the
context of space and time.There might be
places in the world where writers may not
feel the need to become invo l ve d . I think
t h at ’s impossible in the Balkans. I n
B u l g a ri a , w ri t e rs have always been
a s s o c i ated with eve ry social, p o l i t i c a l ,
r e l i gious and, of cours e , c u l t u r a l
movement.
Is it possible to imagine Balkan writers
getting together to re-establish the long-
severed links between their countries?
economic ones. What is life like there?
I’m going to paraphrase a line from a short
s t o ry by Maupassant which goes something
like this, “ H ow lucky we are to die
surrounded by doctors in white coats!”
Your political commitment 
came late and seems paradoxical.
You were invited to the “dissidents’
breakfast” with French President François
Mitterrand in 1989, but were elected to the
National Assembly as a socialist deputy
during the first free elections two years
later.
At that time Ceausescu had just been killed
and Bulgaria was on the same track as
Romania. It looked as if it might drown in
a bloodbat h . I belonged to a group of
intellectuals who thought that if we rallied
around the socialist part y, we might be able
to channel the tension rising in the streets.
The French socialists had something to do
with that decision. I don’t regret the
experience, but I do consider it a mistake.
T h at said, I never set foot in parliament and
resigned.
Have these historic changes influenced your
work?
N o, but they have certainly influ e n c e d
l i t e r ature in general. F i rst of all they ri d
B u l g a rian literature of the burden of
“ g l o ri fic at i o n ” I mentioned earlier.A u t h o rs
can express themselves more freely. Has the
quality of literature improved? I’m not sure.
Has opening up to the world given rise to
Pain is the same for everyone and doesn’t
discriminate between races and peoples.
It makes everyone equal
“I am convinced that humanity is bored.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50 The UNESCO Courier - January 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
A prolific writer
Yordan Radichkov was born in 1929 at Kalimanitsi, a village in northeastern Bulgaria
which is today submerged beneath the waters behind a dam.
He has been a provincial newspaper correspondent, a scriptwriter with the national
cinema studios and a staff writer on several literary magazines.
In 1989 he was invited to a “ d i s s i d e n t s ’ b r e a k fa s t ” by French President François
Mitterrand, but two years later was elected as a member of the Bulgarian parliament on
a socialist ticket (see box p. 4 8 ) . Disenchanted by his experience of politics, he soon
resigned and once again became a full-time writer.
His literary career began in 1959 with the publication of a collection of short stories
and since then he has written some 40 books. In 1971 he won the Dimitrov Prize for
L i t e r at u r e , one of Bulgari a ’s leading literary awa r d s. He has also received many prizes from
other countries, including, in 1984, the prestigious Grinzane Cavour Prize for the best
foreign book published in Italy.
He has a notable following in the Scandinavian countries and in Italy,and has published
over a hundred titles in foreign languages. ■
W ri t e rs in the Balkans are divided by
t r a d i t i o n . The peoples of the region have
more or less conflictual relat i o n s h i p s. E a c h
w riter stays in his or her camp.T h at doesn’t
mean there isn’t a certain intellectual
s o l i d a ri t y. For example, one of my play s
banned in Bulgaria was first performed in
the Republic of Macedonia in 1988.With
few exceptions,writers have done nothing
to aggr avate conflicts but they have n ’t done
a nything to alleviate them either.
Macedonian and Greek intellectuals have
d r awn closer together in the past few
ye a rs—which to me seems like the most
sensible thing to do—but I don’t know of
a ny other similar initiat i ve s. I have taken
p a rt in a grand total of two meetings
b e t ween Balkan wri t e rs , and I don’t
remember them as being part i c u l a r l y
cordial.
In a way, t h at reflects the situation in
E u r o p e . I understand A m e ricans who
wonder how so many different peoples and
languages can exist in such a small space.
The fragmentation of Europe is even more
marked in the Balkans.
But the trend in Europe is toward s
u n i fic a t i o n . . . . The Portuguese writer
Miguel To rga said, “ U n i v e rsality is locality
without walls.” What do you think of
t h a t ?
I would say the same thing my s e l f.You see,
S o fia is located on the London-Calcutta
axis. Once, it was on the Silk Route.This
g e o graphic location has gi ven the city a
sense of openness, e ven though Bulgari a
has often been isolated since the fifteenth
c e n t u ry.Another route that crosses Sofia —
and to me it’s just as important as routes
taken by people—is the route taken by
migrating birds. It’s known as “the grand
route of A ri s t o t l e ” . The unive rsal core of
Bulgaria is to be found at the crossroads of
these two routes.
If you had to define universality in one
word, what would you say?
I would say: pain. As a writer, I am very
sensitive to human pain. It makes people
equal. Pain is the same for everyone and
doesn’t discriminate between races and
peoples. It makes everyone equal. The
English have a highly developed sense of
h u m o u r ,but that doesn’t mean they feel less
pain than anyone else when they have their
teeth extracted. ■
Language: English French Spanish
Rates (postage included):
Industrialized countries: Developing countries or students 
1 year: 211French francs instead of 264FF* (11 issues including 1 double issue) (Please send copy of your card):
2 years:396 French francs instead of 528FF* (22 issues including 2 double issues) 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder: 72French francs (for 11 issues including 1 double issue) 2 years:211 French francs
I enclose payment: (in French francs only) by
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque) Visa Mastercard Eurocard
N° ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: Date and signature:
Name First name
Address
Postal code City
Optional:Age Profession
(*) Total cover price
I WISH TO SUBSCRIBE TO the UNESCO Courier
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to:
the UNESCO Courier Subscription Services, 31,rue François Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are opposite this order form.
✂
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
L I S T  O F S A L E S A N D S U B S C R I P T I O N A G E N T S
Subs cr ipt ions can be paid to the subscript ion agent in  y our c ou ntr y who wil l  supply rates i n local  cur renc y on re q u e s t
A R G E N T I N A : Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UN E S C O,
Tucumán 1685, 1050 Buenos A i r e s. Fa x :3 7 1 - 8 1 9 4 .
AU S T R A L I A : Hunter Publicat i o n s , 58A Gipps Street,
C o l l i n g wood VIC 3066. Fa x : 419 7154. ISA A u s t r a l i a ,
PO Box 709,To owong QLD 4066. Fa x : 371 5566.
United Nations A s s o c. of A u s t r a l i a / V i c t o rian Div. ,
179 St George's Road,
N. F i t z r oy VIC 3068. Fa x : 481 7693.
AU S T R I A : Gerold & Co, I m p o rt & Export ,
Z e i t s c h ri f t e n / Pe ri o d i c a l s , Graben 31, A-1011 V i e n n a .
Fa x : 512 47 31 29
B E L G I U M : Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Bru s s e l s.
Fa x : 538 08 41.
B R A Z I L : Fundaco Getulio Va r g a s , Editora Divisão de Ve n d a s ,
Caixa Postal 62.591, 22257-970 Rio de Janeiro RJ.
Fa x :5 5 1 - 0 9 4 8 .
C A N A DA : Renouf Publishinq Company Ltd, C e n t r a l
D i s t ri bution Centre, 1294 Algoma Road, O t t awa , Ont K1B
3 W 8 . Fa x : 741 5439.
P é riodica Inc, 1155 Av Ducharm e ,O u t r e m o n t , PQ H2V 1E2.
Fa x : 274 0201.
C H I L E : U n i ve rs i t a ria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10220,
S a n t i a g o. Fa x : 681 9091.
C H I N A : China National Publicat i o n s ,I m p o rt & Export
C o rp. , PO Box 88, 16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 100020.
Fa x : 010 65063101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: A rt i a , Ve Smeckach 30,
111 27 Prague 1.
D E N M A R K : M u n k s g a a r d ,N o rre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148,
DK-1016 Kobenhavn K. Fa x : 12 93 87.
F I N L A N D : S t o c k m a n n / A k ateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23,
SF-00371 Helsinki. Fa x : +358 9 121 4450.
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF-01641 Va n t a a .
Fa x : 852 7990.
G E R M A N Y: G e rman Commission for UN E S C O, C o l m a n t s t r.
1 5 , D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 63 69 12.
Uno Ve r l a g, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55,
D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 21 74 92.
G R E E C E : L i b r a i rie Kauffmann SA, M a u v r o k o r d atou 9,
GR-106 78 A t h e n s. Fa x : 38 33 967.
G UAT E M A L A : Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con
la UN E S C O, 3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1,A p a rtado Postal 2630,
G u atemala City.
HONG KO N G : Hong Kong Gove rnment Inform ation Svcs.
D e p t . , 1 Bat t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
H U N G A RY: Librotrade K F T, Pe riodical Import / K ,P O B
1 2 6 , H-1656 Budapest. Fa x :2 5 6 - 8 7 - 2 7 .
I N D I A : O rient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions A c c o u n t ) ,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estat e ,B o m b ay 400 038.
Fa x : 26 91 278.
Oxford Book & Stat i o n e ry Co, Code No D 8208052, S c i n d i a
H o u s e , New Delhi 110 001. Fa x : 33 22 639.
I S R A E L : L i t e r a ry Transactions Inc. , C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., P O
B ox 1444, Bnei Brak 51114. Fa x : 52 81 187.
I TA LY: L i c o s a / L i b r e ria Comm. Sansoni SPA ,Via Duca di
C a l a b ria 1/1, I-50125 Florence. Fa x :6 4 - 1 2 - 5 7 .
J A PA N : E a s t e rn Book Service Inc. , Pe riodicals A c c o u n t , 3 13
Hongo 3 Chome, B u n k yo Ku ,To k yo 113. Fa x :8 1 8 - 0 8 6 4 .
KO R E A : Korean National Commission for UN E S C O, C P O
B ox 64, Seoul 100-600. Fa x : 568 7454.
L U X E M B U R G : M e s s a g e ries Paul Kraus, BP 2022, L - 1 0 2 0
L u xe m b o u r g . Fa x : 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA : Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic
S t r e e t ,Valletta CMR 01. Fa x : 24 61 82.
M AU R I T I U S : Nalanda Co. L t d . , 30 Bourbon Street, Po rt
L o u i s. Fa x : 212 1313.
M O RO C C O : UN E S C O, 35 avenue du 16 novembre Agdal-
Rabat. Fax:212-767 03 75,Tél.:212-767 03 74/72.
M E X I C O : Librería El Correo de la UN E S C O S A , Col Roma,
G u a n a j u ato 72, Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF.
Fa x :2 6 4 - 0 9 - 1 9 .
N E T H E R L A N D S : S wets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2 1 6 0
SZ Lisse. Fa x :2 5 2 4 - 1 5 8 8 8 .
T i j d s c h riftcentrale Wijck B V, I n t .S u b s. S e rv i c e ,W
G r a c h t s t r a at 1C, 6221 CT Maastri c h t . Fa x : 32 50 103.
NEW ZEALAND: GP Legi s l ation Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 12418,T h o rn d o n , We l l i n g t o n . Fa x : 496 56 98.
NORVEGE : S wets Norge A S ,Ø s t e n s j ø vein 18-0606 Oslo, PO
Box 6512,Etterstad. Fax:47 22 97 45 45.
P O RT U G A L : L i v r a ria Po rtugal (Dias & Andrade Lda),
Rua do Carmo 70 74, 1200 Lisboa. Fa x : 34 70 264.
R U S S I A : Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39,
M o s c ow 113095.
SOUTH A F R I C A : I n t e rn ational Subscription Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 41095, Craighall 2024. Fa x : 880 6248.
Mast Publicat i o n s , PO Box 901, Parklands 2121.
Fa x : 886 4512.
S PA I N : Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37,
28001 Madri d . Fa x :5 7 5 - 3 9 - 9 8 .
L i b r e ria Al A n d a l ú s , Roldana 3 y 4, 41004 Sevilla.
Fa x :4 2 2 - 5 3 - 3 8 .
Los Amigos de la UN E S C O, Alda Urquijo 62, 2 Izd.,
48011 Bilbao. Fa x :4 2 7 - 5 1 - 5 9 / 6 9
SRI LANKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam,
Gardiner Mawat h a , Colombo 2. Fa x : 44 78 48.
S W E D E N : We n n e r gren Williams A B , PO Box 1305,
S-171 25 Solna. Fa x : 27 00 71.
S W I T Z E R L A N D : Dynapresse Marketing SA, ( e x - N av i l l e
S A ) , 38 av V i b e rt , CH-1227 Carouge. Fa x : 308 08 59.
E d i group SA, Case Postale 393, CH-1225 Chêne-Bourg.
Fa x : 348 44 82.
Europa Ve r l a g, Ramistrasse 5, CH-8024 Züri c h .
Fa x : 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG ,W i s s e n s c h a f t l .B u c h h a n d l u n g,
Pe t e rs graben 31, CH-4009 Basel. Fa x : 306 12 34.
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E C O, Chemin du
L a c u e z , CH-1807 Blonay. Fa x : 943 36 05.
T H A I L A N D : Suksapan Pa n i t , Mansion 9, R a j a d a m n e rn
Ave n u e , Bangkok 2. Fa x : 28 11 639.
T U N I S I A : Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de
l ’UN E S C O, 2 2 , rue de l’Angleterr e , 1000RP Tu n i s.
Fa x : 33 10 14
UNITED KINGDOM: The Stat i o n e ry Office Publicat i o n s
C t r e . , 51 Nine Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR.
Fa x : 873 84 63.
UNITED STAT E S : B e rnan A s s o c i at e s , 4611-F A s s e m b l y
D ri ve , Lanham MD 20706-4391. Fa x :4 5 9 - 0 0 5 6 .
U R U G UAY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
Maldonado 1090, M o n t e v i d e o. Fa x : 90 59 83.
V E N E Z U E L A : UN E S C O/ C R E S A L C ,E d i f. A s ov i n c a r ,
Av Los Chorr o s ,C ruce C/C A c u e d u c t o, Altos de Sebu c a n ,
C a r a c a s. Fa x : 286 03 26.
NEW from 
UNESCO Publishing
UNESC O PUBLISHIN G
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publications
E-mail:publishing.promotion@unesco.org
◗ A wide range of
opinions on the current
state and future
development of the
very complex issue of
cultural rights –
particularly pertinent in
view of the precarious
situation of many
minorities and
indigenous peoples 
in today’s world.
150 FF
◗ Nonviolent political strategy
and change are most vividly
associated with Mahatma
Gandhi and Martin Luther
King Jr. Their wisdom has been
employed successfully by
recent popular movements and
a number of peoples, including
the Poles, East Germans,
Czechs and Slovaks, the
Burmese and the Thais.
◗ This book provides 
a detailed look at how
nonviolent strategy actually
works by chronicling its
theorists, their strategies and
their struggles, and by
comparing the words and
ideas of Gandhi and King.
295 FF
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Do s s i e r:
Water: what price for a rare resource?
■ Limited supplies, growing demand  
■ The privatization debate  
■ Agriculture’s great thirst  
■ An international water market–an aid to conflict resolution?  
■ Water and human rights
Features:
■  B i h a r ’s landless villagers  
■  Making good use of waste  
■  Working a way back into society  
■  A d o p t i o n : for love or money?  
■  C h i l d r e n ’s literature turns over a new leaf  
■  Street newspapers  
■  Interview with Nobel prizewinning economist James Tobin 
]]>
</page>
</document>
