<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="114969eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
theC o u rie r
February 1999
Wh a t p r i c e
water?
A d o p t i o n :
for love or m o n e y? 
C h i l d re n ’s b o o k s
come of age 
James To b i n :
reining 
in the m a r k e t s
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 Bihar’s lawless ways Tiane Doan de Champassak,Arvind N. Das
EDITORIAL
9 Daring, caring and sharing Federico Mayor
PLANET
10 The zero option for waste France Bequette
13 Farms in the city France Bequette
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Europe’s welfare-to-work business Simon Wilson and Thierry Jeantet
15 Spanish youth outside in Cecilia Ballesteros
DOSSIER
17 What price
water?
ETHICS
37 Adoption: for love or money? Martine Jacot
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 Children’s books come of age Lucía  Iglesias Kuntz
CONNEXIONS
43 The press takes to the street Sophie Boukhari
45 Munich’s street magazine Kathrin Sander
TALKING TO…
46 James Tobin: reining in the markets
52nd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief: Jasmina Sopova
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat
Photoengraving:Eric Frogé
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,A l c i n o
Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian:Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher copies
are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
a u t h o r ’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
r e q u e s t . Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UN E S C O o r
those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the UN E S C O Courier staff. Th e
boundaries on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the United
N a t i o n s. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform
( m i c r o film and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de
Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,A n n
A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition,
Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ;( 4 )
Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road, Wo o s t e r, O h i o
4 4 6 9 1 , U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - FEBRUARY 1999
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Paris by
UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e. Periodicals postage paid at Champlain
NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’ UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N°2-1999-OPI 99-579 A
C o n t e n t s
February 1999
C o v e r : © Jamie Drummond/Christian Aid/Still Pictures, L o n d o n
18 A rare and precious resource Houria Tazi Sadeq
21 A thirsty planet
22 Who pays the piper? Who calls the tune? Colin Green,John Briscoe,
Bernard Barraqué
25 Hungary:under new management Gabor Szabo
26 South Africa:water for everyone Ferial Haffajee
27 Mexico:the sweet smell of success Juan Carlos Núñez
28 India:Calcutta plugs its deficit Tirthankar Bandyopadhyay
29 Now you see it, now you don’t
Two views on ‘virtual water’ J. A. Allan,Amy Otchet
33 Custom-built solutions for international disputes J. W. D e l l a p e n n a
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
B i h a r’s lawless wa y s
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
The house of this Dalit
(“untouchable”) family was
burned down by a private
army working for a rich
landlord.
A Dalit village.
Photos by
Tiane Doan de Champassak
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Above, Dalits fish in a flooded
field.
Left,harvesting and
processing rice.
Right,a monument built in
memory of 62 Dalits
massacred in Jehenabad
district on 1 December 1997.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Dire poverty and oppression are the grim facts 
of life for the Dalits (‘untouchables’) 
of India’s most backward state
Arvind N. Das*
n
Tr avelling in the eastern Indian stat e
of Bihar is never easy: the trains are
ove r c r owded and the buses are
r a m s h a c k l e . In the south-central plains, 1 0 0
kilometres east and west of Pat n a , the stat e
capital situated on the south bank of the
G a n g e s , bad road conditions make it hard to
m ove around.As well as having to surm o u n t
these obstacles, t r ave l l e rs in this region may
e ven need passes from pri vate part i e s.T h o s e
who issue the passes could be Maoist gr o u p s
but most often they belong to va rious s e n a s—
l a n d l o r d s ’ caste- or class-based pri vat e
a rm i e s.The law enforcement authorities are
v i rtually absent from this regi o n .
The village of Danwar Bihta lies in this
remote area. It is 40 kilometres from the
d i s t rict headquart e rs , A r a , but the terri b l e
road conditions make it almost inaccessible.
The unbridged Sone ri ver which flows near
the village can be crossed by boat but few dare
to make the crossing because of the pri vat e
a rmies which hold sway on both its banks.
The state is very far away in Danwar
B i h t a ; the laws enacted by the legi s l ature are
hardly even heard of and life for the poor is
n a s t y, b rutish and short .D a n war Bihta and
P
* Indian sociologist and author of several studies on
Bihar State
its surrounding area have witnessed many
brutal massacres in the last three decades,
claiming over 1,000 live s , mostly of landless
“ u n t o u c h a b l e s ” or Dalits. The miserable
state of Danwar Bihta reflects the general
lawlessness that pervades Bihar today.
Take Ku s u m l a l , a landless labourer who
barely surv i ved the massacre that the
landlords of Danwar Bihta carried out on
election day in 1989.More than 20 Dalits
were gunned down when they tried to
e xercise their franchise in the parliamentary
e l e c t i o n . Like other Dalits who surv i ve d
the massacre, Kusumlal and his family had
to move away from the village; their lives
were clearly insecure in their traditional
abode.They now live in tiny huts,built on
the roadside near a pri m a ry school in a
village five kilometres from Danwar Bihta.
The cluster of huts, the fact that everyone
belongs to the same caste, the phy s i c a l
distance from the landlords and the
proximity to the school provide a certain
degree of security.
The situation is wo rse for Ku s u m l a l ’s
w i f e , D h a n p at i a , and their eight-ye a r - o l d
d a u g h t e r , P u n a m i a . E ve ry day they have to
t rudge to the Sone ri ve r ,t wo kilometres from
their hut, to fetch water in earthen pots. It is
not that there is any lack of water in the
nearby ponds and we l l s. Ku s u m l a l ’s fa m i l y
and others like them are “ u n t o u c h a b l e s ”a n d
are not allowed by rest of the villagers to take
water from the public pond near their huts.
Armed struggle
Kusumlal and his 11-year-old son Manjhi
cannot find work in the nearby village.T h e
landlords there will not employ them;nor will
people like Kusumlal dare to return to a
group of people who have left the scar of a
bullet injury on his right shoulder.They have
to trudge long distances in search of wo r k ,
sometimes up to ten kilometres each way, t o
e a rn a meagre 30 rupees (70 cents) per day.
E ven this kind of work is only available for
four months a ye a r ,l e aving them in hunger
and misery for the rest of the time.
Ku s u m l a l ’s son goes to the village
p ri m a ry school on the days when he cannot
find wo r k , but this does not necessarily mean
t h at he will actually get any education there.
The school may be shut: the teacher, a
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
landholder from a neighbouring village, is often
a b se n t , s u p e rvising work on his land rat h e r
than teaching the Dalit children in the pri m a ry
s c h o o l . There is, of cours e , no question of
Ku s u m l a l ’s daughter even going to school and
l e a rning about the gr e at wide world since a
girl child is expected from an early age to bu s y
herself with household work instead.
Kusumlal himself does not know much
about the world beyond his wretched existence.
He never went to school. All his life he has
lived in or near Danwar Bihta.He went to Ara
s e veral times when the case regarding the
D a n war Bihta firing was going on, but his visit
was confined to the court buildings where he
and others like him were summoned to give
evidence.
Kusumlal has not gi ven up hope. He is
aware that he is not alone. Living conditions are
similar for the nearly 1.5 million landless Dalit
l a b o u r e rs in Bihar who are now getting together
here and there to form peasant and labourers’
o r g a n i z ations in a bid to improve their
s i t u at i o n . Unable to overcome the ru t h l e s s
repression by peaceful means, some Dalits
like Kusumlal support militant Naxalite
groups such as the Pe o p l e ’s War Group
(PWG) and the Maoist Communist Centre
(MCC) who believe in armed struggle to
end upper-caste domination. Many more
join the Communist Pa rty of India
( M a r x i s t - L e n i n i s t ) , k n own locally as
“ M a a l e y ” , which seeks to combine
p a r l i a m e n t a ry politics with militant peasant
struggles.Together they have formed their
own “armies”to fight for their rights.
Kusumlal doesn’t want money. H e
wants to be treated with dignity. He wants
the landlords to stop sexually exploiting
and raping Dalit wo m e n . He wants the
l a n d l o r d s ’p ri vate army, the Ranbir Sena, t o
halt its massacres. Kusumlal doesn’t know
when these things will happen but he firm l y
believes they will come about one day. n
Opposite page top left and
above: the laborious task of
brick-making is reserved for
Dalits.
Opposite page (middle photo):
Dalit children drying a sari in a
wheat field.
Left: many Dalit children in
rural Bihar only have access to
improvised outdoor classes.
Opposite page far left (below):
a rich landlord who owns 500
h e c t a res of farmland and has
12 bodyguard s.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Bihar: a place of inequalities and tensions
8 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
B ihar is India’s second most populous state  after
Uttar Pra d e s h . Half the size of Germany, it has a
larger population than Germany and A u s t r i a
c o m b i n e d . B i h a r, whose name is derived from the
sanskrit word v i h a r a ( m o n a s t e r y ) , is studded with
Buddhist monuments and historical sites, one of the
most important being Bodh Gaya where Lord Buddha
attained enlightenment 2,500 years ago.
In stark contrast to its glorious past,Bihar today
is in the throes of economic chaos and
unprecedented social tension. It has the dubious
distinction of being one of India’s most crime-ridden
states, with 14 murders a day and one kidnapping
every four hours.As in other Indian states, people in
Bihar are divided on the age-old caste system in
which the Dalits or untouchables are at the bottom
of the ladder. Dalits constitute around 15 per cent of
the state’s population but they hold less than two per
cent of the cultivated land. The social tensions are
largely due to agrarian inequality, and often result in
clashes between landed gentry and landless Dalit
labourers. Active Dalit resistance in Bihar started in
the 1960s, when landless labourers aligned
themselves with Maoist Naxalite groups. Th e
landlords and other upper-caste people formed their
own private armies to assert their supremacy.
Wo m e n , children and old people are often the
victims of these caste-based massacres. The state
a d m i n i s t ra t i o n , irrespective of which party is in
power, is powerless to control these clashes which
have been going on for the last three decades.
Bihar is India’s most backward state, with the
lowest literacy rate and per capita income. On the
other hand,it is the richest state in terms of mineral
r e s o u r c e s, accounting for 40 per cent of India’s total
production.Rabri Devi is the present chief minister,
heading a centrist Rashtriya Janata Dal (National
People’s Party) government. n
Total area: 173,877 sq.km
Population:90 million
Literacy rate:38 per cent
State capital: Patna
n PATNA
Bihar
Nepal
West Bengal
Orissa
Madhya
Pradesh
Uttar
Pradesh
Ara l
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E D I TO R I A L
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 9
n
The threat of fresh water scarcity is a major ri s k . On the one hand, resources are not
u n l i m i t e d ; they are finite and fragi l e .On the other, total world demand for water has ri s e n
s e venfold in the course of this century, while world population has increased threefold
over the same peri o d . Increased demand goes hand in hand with rising living standards
resulting from socio-economic deve l o p m e n t . This is bad news insofar as demand will
continue to escalate as living standards hopefully improve .But it is good news insofar as this
l e vel of development increases our capacity to make more economical use of wat e r.
This collective resource is becoming rarer because it is being overexploited by a
c o n s u m e rist and pollution-generating humanity. The wa rning signs are clear: fa l l i n g
water tables, s h rinking ri ve rs and lakes, widespread pollution, creeping desert i fic at i o n .Wat e r
s h o rtage is exacting a gr owing human toll in terms of malnutri t i o n ,d i s e a s e ,a b a n d o n m e n t
of rural areas, and swollen urban settlements. Prophets of doom predict that water,even
more than oil or land, may soon foment bitter conflicts.
But if the outlook is gloomy, crisis is not yet inevitable,on condition that we do three
t h i n g s : put technology back in its place; recognize both the possibilities and the limitat i o n s
of the market; and above all give priority to a new “water ethic”.
Technology can only provide part of the answer. The water crisis is not an isolated
p h e n o m e n o n . It is an important but specific aspect of the general crisis of a deve l o p m e n t
model based on a concept of gr owth which is obsessed with macro-economics and
technology and neglects social, human and environmental fa c t o rs. We should firm l y
oppose so-called miracle solutions. In any case, where in today ’s economic climate are we
going to find the means to build dams, pipe systems, channels and reservo i rs , or to
finance the “ e c o j o b s ” needed for scientific management of agriculture and the env i r o n m e n t ?
There is also growing pressure to recognize that water should become a commodity
like any other. In this pers p e c t i ve the market could be used to regulate water demand, b o t h
to reduce overall consumption and to arbitrate between users , within countries and
internationally. This approach certainly has a role to play in enhancing the value of an
increasingly precious resource and thereby reducing wa s t e . But if market mechanisms we r e
to rule unchecked, what would happen to the role of the public authorities? How could
they exercise their responsibility for social justice, especially towards all those who still have
no access to drinking water?
Technology and the market can be precious allies in getting to grips with the looming
water cri s i s , but ultimately the response to it must rest on ethical and cultural foundat i o n s.
There should be three imperat i ve s :d a ri n g, c a ring and shari n g .D a ri n g, because postponing
urgent decisions on the grounds that all the data are not available would be tantamount
to letting demand gr ow until it reaches its natural and economic limit. C a ri n g,because ove r
a billion people still have no access to drinking wat e r. S h a ring because the only altern at i ve
to wo rsening conflict rests on determ i n ation to show a sense of equity and community.T h i s
is not a utopian ideal: in human history, water has been a greater force for unity than for
division. n
D a r i n g , c a r i n g
a nd s h a r i n g
Federico Mayor
This collective resource is
becoming rarer because it is
being overexploited by a
consumerist and pollution-
generating humanity. The
warning signs are clear:
falling water tables,
shrinking rivers and lakes,
widespread pollution,
creeping desertification.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
P L A N E T
The z e ro option for  
The world may be producing too much waste. It is also spawning plenty
of imaginative ideas about how to handle it
n
The world is groaning under the
weight of the rubbish people produce
and things are getting wo rs e . N o b o d y
k n ows exactly how much waste there is in
the Third Wo r l d , but the Organization for
Economic Cooperation and Deve l o p m e n t
(OECD) has produced figures for its 29
m e m b e r - s t at e s , which are mostly ri c h
c o u n t ri e s.
B e t ween 1980 and 1995, it say s , t h e
total amount of municipal waste increased
from 347 to 484 million tonnes—238
million in the United States and 153
million in the 15 countries of the European
U n i o n .
I n d u s t ries alone in the OECD
countries produced 1.5 billion tonnes of
waste in 1995. The French—top of the
agricultural and forest waste league with
377 million tonnes compared with the
Greeks’ 90 million—throw out 17 billion
plastic bags every year. They junk 1.7
million vehicles and discard 20 million
t y r e s. The Germans throw away 4.42
million tons of packaging—a tri f l e
compared with the Americans’ 64 million
t o n n e s. The US is also top where
computers are concerned, scrapping 10
million every year.
Fo rty million tonnes of recy c l a b l e
waste were exported by OECD countries
in 1990.“To reduce flows of materials,we
need a revolution in how we think about
them—a transition as profound as the
movement from the Stone Age to the
Bronze Age,” says John Young, a senior
researcher at the Worldwatch Institute in
Washington. “This revolution, however,
will centre not on a new material, but on
how to use existing materials far more
efficiently.”
What is waste?
There are several definitions.
B e l gi u m , for example, calls it “ a ny
substance or object which the holder
discards or intends or is required to
discard”. As a result the official quantity
of waste in Belgium is high—645,636
tonnes exported in 1991, compared with
only 21,126 exported by France and
108,466 tonnes by the US.
Mexico’s definition of waste is very
complicated: “Any material . . . whose
quality does not permit its use again in
the same process that generated it”. In
Switzerland, “wastes are movable things
which the owner discards or whose
disposal is in the public interest”. In
South Korea, waste means “any matter . .
. which becomes unnecessary for human
living or business activities”.
The OECD notes an extra problem to
do with differentiating between the word
“discard” in the definitions—meaning to
get rid of, scrap or abandon—and
“ d i s p o s a l ” , which means destru c t i o n ,
removal, emptying or dumping.These are
quite varied solutions.
The amount of waste exported does
not necessarily match the amount
imported, since the definition of such
material can change when it crosses a
national border. If used tyres are exported
as waste to a country with laxer rules,
they become an ordinary commercial
item when imported there.
So tracking the intern at i o n a l
m ovement of waste is a nightmare.
Especially as the cost of recycling and
dumping varies from country to country.
The cheapest disposal method, if you
manage to dodge customs, is still to
smuggle 
i n , s ay, used tyres and dump them 
on waste ground without regard to the
environment.
“The culture of consumption that has
spread since mid-century from Nort h
America to Western Europe, Japan and a
wealthy few in developing countries has
brought with it an unprecedented
appetite for physical goods—and the
materials from which they are made,” says
Young.“In the United States, the average
person accounts for the use of some 540
tonnes of construction mat e ri a l s , 1 8
tonnes of paper, 23 of wood, 16 of metals
and 32 tonnes of organic chemicals in the
course of a lifetime.”
So it is vital to reduce consumption 
of raw mat e rials and minimize waste 
production.
The three Rs—reduce,
re-use, recycle
Most industrialized countries have
passed laws about waste based on the
three Rs—reduce, re-use and recycle.The
‘The culture of consumption that has spread since mid-
century from North America to Western Europe, Japan and
a wealthy few in developing countries has brought with it
an unprecedented appetite for physical goods and the
materials from which they are made’A re f o restation and resin extraction project 
in Colombia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
  wa s t e
P
laws cover several sectors: industry and
packaging, household and organic waste,
paper, vehicle batteries, tyres and oil and
other lubricants. The goal is to cut the
amount at source, especially where
hazardous substances are concern e d ,
such as chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)
which attack the ozone layer. The latter
are hard to collect and are gradually being
taken off the market.
Tyres can be re-used to make anti-
noise barriers. Paper can be recycled. But
some waste cannot be dealt with by the
three Rs and has to be incinerated—
which is criticized as polluting the air with
high levels of dioxin gas near the
i n c i n e r at o rs—or dumped, which is
t o l e r ated less and less because of
pollution discharges and the
accompanying bad smells.
To tackle this wo rrying situat i o n
which is very hard to remedy, Belgian
economist Gunter Pauli in 1994 launched
the Zero Emissions Research Initiative
(ZERI) which in effect means “ z e r o
waste”. The scheme is backed by the
Tokyo-based UN University—a network
of unive rsities particularly concern e d
about the environment—and invo l ve s
trying to save everything in industry and
a gri c u l t u r e , t r e ating all waste as raw
material and avoiding pollution at the
same time as making profits and creating
jobs. Quite a few projects were presented
at ZERI’s fourth congress in Windhoek,
Namibia, in October 1998, attended by
250 delegates from five continents. Here
are three of them.
Composting 
a pesky plant
Originally from South America, the
water hyacinth (Eichhornia crassipes) was
introduced elsewhere either accidentally
or deliberately because of its beauty and
has now made itself at home all over the
tropics.
In Africa, it was first spotted in the
Nile Delta, then in the South African
province of Natal, and then in 1937 in
Southern Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe). It
began spreading across the continent in
earnest in the 1950s, jumping from lakes
to rivers,from dams to marshes,and from
ponds to irri g ation canals. But the
beautiful stranger is a killer.
It suffocates native plants, fish and
amphibious creatures by draining oxygen
from the wat e r. It hampers ri ve r
transport—and so trade and tourism—
and especially fishing when it gets tangled
M These earthworms produce enzymes 
that can be used in soap manufacture.
Mushrooms grown on agro-industrial 
waste can create jobs.P
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
P L A N E T
1998,
hottest year
of the century
According to the World Meteorological
Organization (WMO),1998 will go down in
history as the hottest year of the twentieth
century.The earth’s average surface temperature
increased by 0.58°C between 1961 and 1990.
Te m p e ratures have been rising steadily since
1 8 6 0 , the year records began to be ke p t , a n d
today they are 0.7°C higher than they were at
the end of the nineteenth century. Last year edged
out 1997 as the hottest year on record with an
a v e rage temperature 0.43°C higher than those
recorded for the period 1961-1990.
Peter Scholefield, head of W M O ’s Wo r l d
Climate Data and Monitoring Progra m m e, s a y s
1999 has little chance of topping 1998.“It will
not be as hot because the heat records observed
in 1998 were largely due to El Niño,” he says.Th e
cyclical El Niño phenomenon, in which the surface
t e m p e rature of the Pa c i fic Ocean rises, was over by
the middle of 1998 and is not likely to reappear
for at least two years. The 1998 El Niño wa s
particularly intense and caused many disasters
around the world.Drought sparked huge fires in
Indonesia and floods devastated Ecuador, Pe r u
and Ke n ya at the beginning of the year. Th e
torrential rains that fell on China between June
and August were due to El Niño’s last gasps.
According to W M O, northern Eurasia was the
only part of the world spared by the heat in 1998.
In Florida, in the southeastern United States, t h e
period between April and June was the driest on
record in 104 years.France and the United Kingdom
had the warmest February of the century. Q a t a r
posted its hottest summer in history, and a record-
breaking heat-wave caused the deaths of over 100
people in Russia in June. Drought ra vaged severa l
parts of Bra z i l ,where fires broke out spontaneously.
Chile had the least rain in a century. Drought also
affected New Zealand and the Fiji Islands. n
in boat propellers and destroys nets with
its we i g h t . It threatens hy d r o - e l e c t ri c
power production by clogging up the
channels which feed the dams. Farming
suffers too because the fast-growing plant
blocks irrigation canals.
When all efforts to control it had
failed, ZERI decided to treat it as a
friend, as people do in Viet Nam where it
is cultivat e d , d ried and made into
compost which is excellent for growing
edible mushrooms. A kilo of such
compost can produce 112 kg of fresh
tropical oyster mushrooms (Pleurotus sajur
caju) in five weeks.
In Ethiopia, D awit A b at e , a
mycologist in the biology department at
Addis Ababa University, is training street
children to gr ow this simple and
profitable crop. In Zimbabwe, Margaret
Taguira, of the University of Africa at
Mutare, produces up to 100 kg a day.
Spore banks can now be set up, after the
Chinese example, to foster the scheme
which has turned a plague into a weapon
against poverty.
A worm that washes 
whiter
The colour white evokes thoughts of
purity and clean-smelling linen. But it
gets that way through treatment with
chlorine, which eats away at ozone. The
phosphates in detergents are also blamed
for killing off life in lakes and rivers and
causing green tides in the sea by setting
off excessive growth of plants, which then
decompose and empty the water of the
oxygen necessary for other things to grow.
Z.M. Nyiira, of Uganda’s National
Council for Science and Technology, in
Kampala, explains that some insects such
as termites produce enzymes that
“digest” cellulose and the blood and flesh
of living creatures; others include the
larvae of the bluebottle, the tsetse fly, the
mosquito and the earthworm. So why not
extract from some of the 1,800 known
varieties of earthworm, such as Eisenia
foetida, the enzymes they produce which
can easily remove blood, wine and earth
stains?
Such enzymes are already used to
p u rify medicines and va c c i n e s. N ow they
can be extracted from a wo rm with a
s y ringe without killing it; the only diffic u l t y
is distinguishing between the head and the
t a i l . Small soap firms in Colombia and
S l ovakia have started using this method.
The miracle of Las Gaviotas
The Las Gaviotas Env i r o n m e n t a l
Research Centre was set up in 1966 by
Paolo Lugari at V i c h a d a , in eastern
Colombia near the Venezuelan border.
Funded by the central mortgage bank, it has
built an intern ational reputation on its large-
scale use of renewable energy—equipping
40,000 units of low-cost housing in Bogota
with solar wat e r - h e at e rs and refri g e r at o rs ,
setting up semi-industrial kitchens fuelled
with cottonseed oil heated to 180°C in
vacuum tubes, so avoiding the use of
polluting fuels.
At Vichada,the hospital founded by Las
Gaviotas produces its own energy, distils its
own water, provides naturally-purified air,
cooks its own biologi c a l l y - gr ow n
vegetables and grows medicinal plants.
Colombia is losing 650,000 hectares of
trees each year, and Lugari has decided to
launch a huge reforestation programme.
Despite drought and extreme soil acidity,
about 1,000 hectares have been reforested
at the rate of one Caribbean pine planted
every few seconds around the clock for
three months. Resin extracted from the
pine is drained into boxes made of recycled
cardboard ingenious enough to have won a
national prize for innovation in packaging.
The return of the forest has meant
water has come back too. Filtered and
purified by the layer of humus, it is bottled
and sold cheaply as part of a treatment for
the digestive ailments which affect the
population. The fifth world congress of
ZERI will be held at Vichada this October.
A brewery for breeding fish
At Tsumeb, in northern Namibia, the
national brewery company makes sorghum
beer without leaving any waste. Inspired by
a pilot project in Fiji, the brewers also
breed fish and gr ow mushrooms. T h e
sorghum waste is put in concrete
containers where it ferments and gives off
methane gas. Eighty per cent of Tsumeb’s
inhabitants cook with this gas, t h u s
avoiding the use of wood fuel.
Namibia is one of the driest countries
in the world, and it takes five litres of water
to make a litre of beer. Instead of going to
waste, the water from the brewery is used
to fill big ponds. Seven tonnes of grain are
needed to produce a tonne of butcher’s
meat, but only 1.8 tonnes are needed to
produce a tonne of fish.So George Chan, a
M a u ritian expert who has wo r k e d
e x t e n s i vely in China, got the idea of
breeding fish near breweries and has had
excellent results. Grain also makes a very
good bedding in which to gr ow
mushrooms. Similar experiments are being
c a rried out in North A m e ri c a , Ja p a n ,
G e rm a ny, B r a z i l , Colombia and the
Seychelles. n
France Bequette
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
n
In both rich and poor countri e s —
especially the latter—people are flo c k i n g
from rural areas to the cities.The United
N ations Development Programme (UN D P)
s ays the population of the wo r l d ’s cities will
nearly double between 1990 and 2025, ri s i n g
from 2.4 billion to 5.5 billion.
Urban gardens, long neglected and eve n
disdained because they were carelessly
cultivated or insalubrious, are becoming a
source of food and income for newcomers
from the countryside.The UNDP sees them
as a resource that should be exploited. I t
began looking into urban agriculture in 1991
and presented a report on it to the United
N ations Conference on Human Settlements
(Habitat II) in 1996.
The UN D P uses the term “ a gri c u l t u r e ”i n
a broad sense—it ranges from raising animals
to recycling wa s t e , while the term “ u r b a n ”i s
used to cover “the area of a city’s sphere of
s o c i a l ,e c o l o gical and economic influ e n c e ” .
It describes urban agriculture as “ a n
i n d u s t ry that produces, processes and
markets food and fuel, largely in response to
the daily demand of consumers within a
town,city or metropolis,on land and water
dispersed throughout the urban and peri-
urban area, applying intensive production
m e t h o d s , using and re-using nat u r a l
resources and urban wa s t e s , to yield a
diversity of crops and livestock.”
Green-fingered
urban gardeners
C i t y - d we l l e rs eve rywhere display enorm o u s
ingenuity when it comes to growing things.
They make use of small gardens (apart from
f o rmal allotments), gaps between bu i l d i n g s ,
waste gr o u n d , r o a d s i d e s , r a i lway
e m b a n k m e n t s ,t e rr a c e s , balconies and eve n
s t a i r we l l s. On spaces just a few metres
s q u a r e , you can find vegetable plots,
hydroponic crops (grown with nutrients in
sand or water but without soil), fruit trees,
fis h t a n k s , flowe rs and small animals such
as rabbits, h a m s t e rs and poultry in cages
hanging on walls.
These urban “ fa rm e rs ” are mostly
wo m e n , who produce vegetables and animals
for their own consumption and to make a
little pocket money. For example, a young
mother in Nairobi noticed at the roadside
near her house a spot where for ye a rs people
had dumped and bu rned garbage. S h e
realized how fertile it would be and planted
beans and maize there. Since then, she has
been able to feed her fa m i l y, d rying the
beans to eat during the off-season and
selling roasted corn cobs to passers - b y.
Another woman gr ows manioc and spinach
near a leaky pipe.Access to water is a seri o u s
p r o b l e m — i t ’s either too far away or too
expensive.
You don’t have to own land to gr ow
ve g e t a b l e s. A nything will do—boxe s ,
g u t t e ri n g, old tyres, plastic bags. In Mexico
C i t y, people gr ow potatoes in discarded
t ruck tyres. In the Chilean capital, S a n t i a g o,
the Centre for Education and Technology
has a model 20 m 2 urban garden to show
h ow things can be done. To save space,
c o n t a i n e rs are stacked up in a pyramid
shaded from the sun by a vine. C u c u m b e rs ,
Farms in the city
marrows and melons grow vertically along
the walls.
In Po rt - a u - P ri n c e , H a i t i , an A m e ri c a n
food aid organization is encouraging people
to gr ow crops on the flat roofs of houses.To
make sure that the garden isn’t too heavy for
the roof to support , it advises using not eart h ,
but a 5- to 10-cm thick layer of either compost
made from garbage,or else cut gr a s s ,b a g a s s e
(sugar-cane wa s t e ) , rice husks or maize leave s.
In St. Pe t e rs bu r g, in Russia, people use sacks
of peat to gr ow things in, with the sack serv i n g
as a container. Analyses made in New Yo r k
s h ow that such intensive l y - gr own crops
contain a tenth the amount of pollution found
in fie l d - gr own crops.
But if not practised properly, u r b a n
a griculture can cause pollution and disease.
Fe rtilizing plants with untreated sewa g e ,
for example,can cause cholera epidemics.
Lead and cadmium from petrol gets
c o n c e n t r ated in leaf ve g e t a b l e s. To avo i d
these ri s k s , communities must be educat e d
about them,urban agriculture included in
local gove rnment policy and health
regulations enforced. Community groups
must also be encouraged so as to boost the
gr owth of a food source which has become
vital in overcrowded cities. n
F. B.
Harvesting vegetables grown on the roof of a slum house in Bangladesh.
On terraces, balconies and even in stairwells, city-dwellers are growing more
and more food—in the North for pleasure, in the South for survival
These urban ‘farmers’ are
mostly women, who
produce vegetables and
animals for their own
consumption and to make a
little pocket money
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
21.2 % European Union 10.8 %
21.3 % Belgium 9.0 %
8.1 % Denmark 5.4 %
10.7 % Germany 9.9 %
31.0 % Greece 9.6 %
39.2 % Spain 20.9 %
29.0 % France 12.6 %
15.9 % Ireland 10.2 %
33.6 % Italy 12.4 %
7.3 % Luxembourg 2.5 %
9.7 % Netherlands 5.5 %
7.6 % Austria 5.1 %
14.1 % Portugal 6.6 %
35.4 % Finland 15.0 %
21.9 % Sweden 10.4 %
13.6 % United Kingdom 7.1 %
14 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
Europe’s welfare- to
In Europe, thousands of ‘companies for jobs’ are trying to teach marginalized
young people and the long-term unemployed how to work
n
In the 15 member-states of the
European Union, the ave r a g e
unemployment rate is nearly 11 per
c e n t , with big va ri ations betwe e n
countries. But there is plenty of work,
especially in the area of the “ s o c i a l
economy”.
This sector, which accounts for 6 per
cent of all jobs in Europe, includes firms
and organizations whose aim is not just to
maximize their profits. They are keen to
increase the quality and accessibility of
their products in addition to the well-
being of their members and employees,
especially by raising their level of
education and training.
Many of them aim more specifically to
help the most marginalized people to bu i l d
up skills and work experience before they
get a regular job. This invo l ves two main
groups: young people who may never have
worked and older long-term unemploye d
p e o p l e . Most of the latter are men, m a ny of
whom worked in traditional industries and
who find the skills that gave them status are
no longer in demand.
They often have multiple problems,
ranging from educational failure to family
and housing problems and alcohol or
drug abuse. Many dropped out halfway
through their secondary schooling and
have difficulty reading and writing. But
they all have their own abilities and skills.
They should not be treated as victims but
as people who can take responsibility for
their own future given proper support.
A stepping-stone 
to the job market
All over Europe, the we l fa r e - t o - wo r k
schemes through training and wo r k
experience which sprang up in the 1970s
have blossomed in the 1990s.They aim to
help people move out of joblessness and
into a form of supported employment
with training.
A study of six countries published by
the European Union and the French
Committee of We l fa r e - t o - work Companies
(CNEI) reported last year that there were
tens of thousands of schemes of this kind in
existence1.They accounted for more than
280,000 jobs, a drop in the ocean
compared with the number needed.They
were also temporary jobs—short - t e rm
contracts ranging from a few months to a
couple of ye a rs. They are not ends in
t h e m s e l ve s. We l fa r e - t o - work schemes are
not meant to create jobs but to be a
stepping stone to the job market. T h e y
could be called “companies for jobs”.
Their name, role and method of
funding va ry from country to country.T h e y
usually get some support from local,
r e gional and national gove rnments and
some of them work in part n e rship with
private firms and trade unions. They take
the form of co-operat i ve s , mutual societies,
associations,foundations and charities.
In Scotland, for example, the W i s e
Group provides jobs in the interm e d i at e
labour market—jobs that range from
r e n ovation of ru n - d own estates to home
i n s u l ation and forestry. Pa rticipants receive
a wage and have to learn the discipline of
work—keeping regular hours and making a
commitment.
In Germ a ny, a new kind of employ m e n t
and professional qualification company
(“Beschaeftigungs und
Q u a l i f i z i e rungsgesellschaft”—BQG) has
emerged since reunification,mainly in the
f o rmer East Germ a ny as a result of the
mass sackings that came with pri vat i z at i o n .
In France, the government provides
incentives for about 800 welfare-to-work
companies (“entreprises d’insert i o n ” )
which have the difficult task of balancing
their books and winning orders in
An operative recycles telephone equipment as part of a French welfare-to-work scheme.
Unemployment rates in the
15 European Union countries 
Unemployment rate (15-
to 24-year-olds)
Total
unemployment
* Simon Wilson is a British policy analyst and consultant.
Thierry Jeantet is a French expert in social economics and
author of l’Economia Sociale in Europa (Ed.Liocorno,
Italy, 1999).
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - TheUNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
e- to-work business
Spanish youth outside in
P
competition with “normal” firms at the
same time as hiring jobless people at the
end of the road and marginalized young
people. “Intermediary associations” and
“neighbourhood committees”, m a i n l y
concerned with community activity in
poor suburbs and with providing local
services, are also growing.
In Italy, l aws are encouraging the
development of some 2,500 “social co-
o p e r at i ve s ” . In Spain, about 1,000
welfare-to-work schemes are operating,
along with 500 “special job workshops.”
All these enterprises work mainly in
the building trade and the services sector,
but also in improving the environment,
recycling, vehicle repair and restaurants.
Some are even breaking into innovative
s e c t o rs such as communications and
biotechnology.
Gaining vocational skills is important.
The jobs of the future will be highly
skilled jobs with a strong technology
component and will involve contact with
p e o p l e . But “companies for jobs” d o
much more than teach their employees
how to paint houses, plant trees, repair
computers or look after old people.They
offer experience of the world of work.
Job insecurity
Thierry Delavaux,who runs a welfare-
to-work firm in a Paris suburb, says:“You
have to focus both on know-how and on
h ow to behave .A young person can learn to
hammer nails in perfectly, but that wo n ’t be
any good if he turns up for job interviews
with a walkman on his head.”
E m p l oye rs need people who are “ j o b
r e a d y ” , people they don’t have to teach
how to read, write and count, how to be
m o t i vated and to communicate with fellow
workers.The first things these job-seekers
have to learn are getting to work on time,
meeting deadlines and working in a team.
Sometimes they have to be encouraged to
buy an alarm clock, helped to plan the route
to their workplace by public transport ,a n d
even need to be accompanied to work for
the first few days.
In a world where professional careers are
constantly changing, they also have to be
taught how to adapt to new and fle x i b l e
working conditions—repeated short-term
contracts, working from home and wider
use of inform ation and communicat i o n
technologies.
This is especially important because
those who find employment after a we l fa r e -
t o - work scheme (less than half of the total)
often move into insecure jobs with low
wages and poor prospects. n
n
“We can’t go to the police,or borrow
money from the bank or anything.All
I ’ ve got is my name. . .” This stat e m e n t
by a character in My Name is Jo e, a new fil m
by British director Ken Loach, d e s c ribes in
a nutshell the plight of those who find
themselves on the margin of society.
It is no easy matter to bring yo u n g
people in this situation back into society, t o
break the vicious circle of marginalization
and give them the chance to find a steady
job and,more importantly, to learn a skill.
Semilla is one of many organizations in
Spain that are trying to do just this.
“ We try to prepare them for long-term
j o b s , but even if they find work for only a
few months, it enables them to build up
their CV,” s ays Luis Oscar Reye s , who ru n s
S e m i l l a ’s youth inform ation centre and jobs
c l u b. “They often have a range of skills
which unfort u n ately don’t come across ve ry
well in an official document.” S e m i l l a ,
which was founded nearly 25 ye a rs ago, i s
based in the Madrid dorm i t o ry suburb of
V i l l ave r d e , which has a high school dropout
r ate (60 per cent), and is plagued by
a l c o h o l i s m , u n e m p l oy m e n t , d ru g
a d d i c t i o n , broken families and youth gangs.
Breaking
the vicious circle
“I think I’ll be able to get a job after this,”
s ays 19-year-old Cri s t i n a , who heard about
Semilla when she was at school.After studying
cutting and dressmaking in a design and
fashion house for two ye a rs , she now works in
M e t a s , a boutique which also belongs to
S e m i l l a .There she has learned all about selling
d e c o r ated fa b rics and household linen,
r a n ging from accounting to customer
r e l at i o n s , and making window blinds and
q u i l t s.
“They take turns doing different jobs,
l e a rning how a business works and above all
h ow to accept responsibilities,” s ays Pa l o m a ,
who runs the shop and supervises its staff of
five (three teachers and two professional
couturiers) as well as the students.
Simon Wilson and Thierry Jeantet*
Over a thousand Spanish organizations,
many based in tough neighbourhoods,
are running schemes to bring young
outsiders back into society
1. Des pratiques différentes, une volonté commune. Les
“entreprises sociales”et la lutte contre l’exclusion dans
six pays de l’Union Européenne (“Different
practices,a common will.‘Social firms’and the
fight against exclusion in six EU countries”).The
study, published in 1997, covers Germany,
Austria,Belgium, Spain,France and Italy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Fighting truancy
with made-to-
measure
education
A group of Uruguayan teachers is battling
i l l i t e racy in a poor area of the capital,
M o n t e v i d e o, by giving children who skip school—
and their mothers—individual help.
The teachers say youngsters drop out mainly
because they do not have enough contact with the
written word at home, where the main influence is
o ral communication, mostly with the mother. So a
child who sells sweets and becomes very good at
mental arithmetic can fail maths at school through
being unable to cope with abstractions and tra n s f e r
familiar everyday mental calculations into
mathematical symbols.
The mothers—mostly uneducated or
functionally illiterate—play a key part in their
c h i l d r e n ’s ability to learn and handle symbols and
can encourage them to think in abstract terms.
To bring mothers into this learning process, the
teachers meet them and their children at home for
an hour twice a week.
The progra m m e, known as El Abrojo ( t h e
thistle), has so far involved 1,168 people and is
b a c ked by the Uruguayan education ministry and
Terre des Hommes, a French non-governmental
organization.It does not aim to take the place of
the school but simply to build bridges so children
can return to the classroom.
The scheme has been a great success. Every one
of the children from 88 families who took part went
back to school and got much better results.R e a d i n g
became a new family pastime. Some children and
their mothers even began keeping diaries which,
says project coordinator Adriana Briozzo of the
U r u g u a yan Institute of Popular Education, h e l p s
“to boost the self-confidence of the children and
their mothers and to channel the aggressivity of
the mothers.”
Reading sessions have been held in the street
and a travelling library has been set up. Th e
teachers hope to extend El Abrojo, which won
UN E S C O’s Noma Prize for Literacy last year, to many
more families. n
E-mail for El A b ro j o :a b ro j o @ c h a s q u e. a p c. o rg
16 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
A worldwide movement
community initiat i ves have long been
launched by volunteers.Those which have
s u rv i ved have brought together part n e rs
from associations and local authori t i e s ,
without depending too heavily on support
from the public purse.
In A f rica and Latin A m e ri c a , t h e
number of micro-credit co-operat i ve s ,
grassroots groups and other neighbourhood
a s s o c i ations invo l ved in vo c ational training
and job creation, is growing all the time.
This kind of informal sector is sometimes
bigger than the formal labour market. n
n Europe has no monopoly on
organizations working at the crossroads
b e t ween economics and social wo r k . I n
Japan, mutual companies in the insurance
sector and consumer co-operatives are an
established part of the scene. Recently new
service co-ops have been created, many of
them built up by women.
For more than a decade, the progr a m m e
to fight unemployment in Quebec has
s u p p o rted the creation of co-operat i ves and
associations which aim to get people back
to work. In the United States, many local
Hundreds of young people like Cri s t i n a
h ave been prepared by Semilla,which is funded
by public and pri vate Spanish and European
bodies and currently has 270 students.
The young people go to Semilla on their
own initiat i ve , or on the advice of relat i ve s ,
f riends or social wo r k e rs. Those under 16
(the legal school-leaving age) start by going to
a day centre and the ones who have not been
to school for at least four months receive
special instru c t i o n .E vening classes also help
the youths overcome their educat i o n a l
p r o b l e m s.
Three workshops gi ve the oldest among
them a two- or three-year training in
c o m p u t e rs , fashion and design, or the hotel
business. The last stage of the course is a
spell in the world of work, at first within
Semilla itself, which apart from its shop
and workshop has a catering service.
“We also have agreements with firms
like Campofrio (one of Spain’s leading food
companies) and Auchan (a French
s u p e rmarket chain) so young people can do
unpaid work training for up to three
months,” says Reyes. “We’ve also have 40
people in a supervised professional back-to-
work progr a m m e , which invo l ve s
subsidizing firms to the tune of 30,000
pesetas ($215) a month for eve ry yo u n g
p e rson they take on for at least six months.”
Semilla also acts as a labour exchange,
serving as a clearing house for job offers,
helping people compile CVs and prepari n g
them for courses run by the Spanish state
e m p l oyment agency, I N E M . It reckons that
80 per cent of those who have received the
training it provides manage to find jobs,
mostly in small neighbourhood shops.
S e m i l l a ’s experience is not unique.
There are thought to be more than a
thousand similar organizations in Spain.
The biggest cat e g o ry among them includes
w h at are known as social co-operat i ve s ,
back-to-work firms which exist mainly in
C atalonia (more than 200), A n d a l u s i a
( 1 5 0 ) ,M a d rid (100), the two Castiles (60),
the Basque Country (50), Valencia (50)
and Galicia (50). Their methods and
o r g a n i z ation systems differ, but they are all
guided by one basic pri n c i p l e — t h at
prevention is the first step in the struggle
against exclusion. n
Cecilia Ballesteros in Madrid
A young woman at work in a boutique run by the Spanish workfare association Semilla.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 17
Wh a t
price
w a t e r ?
A water crisis looms closer, it seems, every day. In just a couple of
g e n e ra t i o n s, the earth’s population will reach an estimated
nine billion people, as against some six billion today. How will this
g rowing population be fed? Tw o - t h i rds of water consumption
a l ready goes to irrigation, and agricultural needs are incre a s i n g.
M e a w h i l e, industrialization is also taking a heavy toll on our fra g i l e
water supplies, c reating both new demands and risks of pollution.
H y d rologists and civil engineers used to have a standard
response to water scarc i t y : build more dams, desalinization plants
and even pipelines to bring water from humid to dry are a s. Not only
have these technological options failed to keep up with rising
d e m a n d , but they are also too expensive, in ecological as well as
economic terms.
To d a y, our hydrological landscape is being re-designed as
conservationists and economists form an unusual alliance. Instead of
a s k i n g, “how can we provide new supplies?”, they now insist the
main question is, “how can we cut demand?” Their concerns point
to a major para d o x : we waste a re s o u rce without which we cannot
l i v e. The key to more rational management appears to be simple:
c h a rge consumers for the water they use. At the same time, o t h e r
m a r ket mechanisms are seen as a solution to allocating water
re s o u rces effic i e n t l y. For example, laws in the US state of California
e n c o u rage farmers to sell their water rights to cities instead of
g rowing crops during a dro u g h t .T h e re is even talk of setting up an
international water market so that water-poor countries can buy
supplies from the water- r i c h . But what are the political and social
costs of this approach? Can we afford to treat this vital re s o u rc e
l i ke any ordinary commodity? In short, what price water? n
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
A ra re and p re c i o u s
n
Water is a bond between human beings and
n at u r e . It is ever-present in our daily lives and in
our imagi n at i o n s. Since the beginning of time, i t
has shaped extraordinary social institutions, a n d
access to it has provoked many confli c t s.
But most of the wo r l d ’s people, who have neve r
gone short of wat e r , take its availability for gr a n t e d .
I n d u s t ri a l i s t s , fa rm e rs and ordinary consumers
blithely go on wasting it.These day s ,t h o u g h ,s u p p l i e s
are diminishing while demand is soari n g .E ve ryo n e
k n ows that the time has come for attitudes to change.
Few people are aware of the true extent of fresh
water scarcity. M a ny are fooled by the huge
expanses of blue that feature on maps of the wo r l d .
They do not know that 97.5 per cent of the planet’s
water is salty—and that most of the wo r l d ’s fresh
water—the remaining 2.5 per cent—is unusable: 7 0
per cent of it is frozen in the icecaps of A n t a r c t i c a
and Greenland and almost all the rest exists in the
f o rm of soil humidity or in water tables which are
too deep to be tapped. In all, barely one per cent of
fresh water—0.007 per cent of all the water in the
wo r l d , is easily accessible.
O ver the past century, p o p u l ation gr owth and
human activity have caused this precious resource to
d w i n d l e .B e t ween 1900 and 1995, world demand for
water increased more than sixfold—compared with
a threefold increase in world populat i o n .The rat i o
b e t ween the stock of fresh water and world populat i o n
seems to show that in overall terms there is enough
water to go round.But in the most vulnerable regi o n s ,
an estimated 460 million people (8 per cent of the
wo r l d ’s population) are short of wat e r , and another
q u a rter of the planet’s inhabitants are heading for the
same fat e . E x p e rts say that if nothing is done, t wo -
thirds of humanity will suffer from a moderate to
s e vere lack of water by the year 2025.
Inequalities in the availability of wat e r —
sometimes even within a single country — a r e
r e flected in huge differences in consumption leve l s.
A person living in rural Madagascar uses 10 litres
a day, the minimum for surv i va l , while a French
p e rson uses 150 litres and an A m e rican as many as
4 2 5 .
Scarcity is just one part of the problem. Wat e r
quality is also declining alarm i n g l y. In some areas,
c o n t a m i n ation levels are so high that water can
no longer be used even for industrial purp o s e s.
There are many reasons for this—untreated sewa g e ,
chemical wa s t e , fuel leakages, dumped garbage,
c o n t a m i n ation of soil by chemicals used by fa rm e rs.
The worldwide extent of such pollution is hard to
assess because data are lacking for several countri e s.
But some figures gi ve an idea of the problem. It is
thought for example that 90 per cent of wa s t e
water in developing countries is released without
Fresh water is a scarce commodity. Since it’s impossible to increase supply,
demand and waste must be reduced. But how?
0
1
2
3
4
Global water withdrawals (1900-2000)
in thousands of km3 per year
⌧ ⌧ ⌧ ⌧ ⌧ ⌧
1900 1920 1940 1960 1980 2000
Total Agriculture Industry Municipality
n n n n
Sharper vision
D esalinization,state of the art irrigation systems, techniques to harvest fog—technological
solutions like these are widely hailed as the answer to water scarcity. But in searching for the
“miracle”solution,hydrologists and policy-makers often lose sight of the question:how can we
use and safeguard this vital resource? UN E S C O’s International Hydrological Programme (IHP) take s
an interdisciplinary approach to this question. On the one hand, IHP brings together scientists from
150 countries to develop global and regional assessments of water supplies and,for example,
inventories of groundwater contamination. At the same time, the programme focuses on the
c u l t u ral and socio-economic factors involved in effective policy-making. For example, g r o u n d wa t e r
supplies in Gaza (Palestinian Authority) are coming under serious strain,partly because of new
business investment in the area. IHP has a two-pronged approach. F i r s t ,t rain and help local
hydrologists accurately assess the supplies. Second,work with government officials to set up a
licensing system for pumping groundwater.
By joining forces with the World Water Council,an international think-tank on hydrological
issues, IHP is now hosting one of the most ambitious projects in the field: World Water Vision.
Hundreds of thousands of hydrologists, policy-makers, farmers, business leaders and ordinary
citizens will take part in public consultations to develop regional scenarios as to how key issues
like contamination will evolve in the next 25 years. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 19
What price water?
P
re s o u rc e Houria Tazi Sadeq*
a ny kind of treat m e n t .
Things are especially bad in cities, where wat e r
demand is exploding. For the first time in human
h i s t o ry, there will soon be more people living in cities
than in the countryside and so water consumption
will continue to increase. S o a ring urbanization will
sharpen the rivalry between the different kinds of
water users.
Curbing the explosion
in demand
Today, farming uses 69 per cent of the water
consumed in the world, industry 23 per cent and
households 8 per cent. In developing countri e s ,
a griculture uses as much as 80 per cent.The needs
of city-dwe l l e rs ,i n d u s t ry and tourists are expected
to increase rapidly, at least as much as the need to
produce more fa rm products to feed the planet.T h e
problem of increasing water supply has long been
seen as a technical one, calling for technical solutions
such as building more dams and desalination plants.
Wild ideas like towing chunks of icebergs from the
poles have even been mooted.
But today, technical solutions are reaching
their limits. Economic and socio-ecologi c a l
arguments are levelled against building new dams,
for example: dams are costing more and more
because the best sites have already been used, and
they take millions of people out of their env i r o n m e n t
and upset ecosystems. As a result, twice as many
dams were built on average between 1951 and 1977
than during the past decade, according to the US
e nvironmental research body Wo r l d watch Institute.
Hydrologists and engineers have less and less
room for manoeuvre, but a new consensus with
new actors is taking shape. Since supply can no
longer be expanded—or only at prohibitive cost
for many countries—the explosion in demand must
be curbed along with wasteful practices. A n
e s t i m ated 60 per cent of the water used in irri g at i o n
The water from the
fo u n t a i n
g l i d e s, flows and
d re a m s
a s, almost dumb, i t
l i ck s
the mossy stone.
Antonio Machado
(1875-1939),Spain
* Moroccan jurist,president of the
Maghreb-Machrek Water Union,
vice-president of the International
Water Secretariat
Drawing water from a well 
in Burkina Faso.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
Lack of access to safe water
and basic sanitation, by region,
1990-1996 (percent)
Region People without People without
access to access to
safe water basic sanitation
Arab States 21 30
Sub-Saharan Africa 48 55
South-East Asia and the Pacific 35 45
Latin America and the Caribbean 23 29
East Asia 32 73
East Asia (excluding China) 13 —
South Asia 18 64
Developing countries 29 58
Least developed countries 43 64
Periods of complete renewal
of the earth’s water resources
Kinds of water Period of renewal
Biological water several hours
Atmospheric water 8 days
Water in river channels 16 days
Soil moisture 1 year
Water in swamps 5 years
Water storages in lakes 17 years
Groundwater 1 400 years
Mountain glaciers 1 600 years
World ocean 2 500 years
Polar ice floes 9 700 years
Source: Human Development Report 1998, New York, UNDP
Source: World Water Balance and Water Resources of the Earth , Gidrometeoizdat,Leningrad,1974 (in
Russian)
is lost through inefficient systems,for example.
Economists have plunged into the debate on
water and made quite a few wave s.To obtain “ r at i o n a l
u s e ” of wat e r , i . e . avoiding waste and maintaining
q u a l i t y, they say consumers must be made to pay for
i t . Out of the question, reply those in favour of free
wat e r , which some cultures regard as “a gift from
h e ave n ” .And what about the poor, ask the champions
of human rights and the right to water? Other
i m p o rtant and prickly questions being asked by
d e c i s i o n - m a k e rs are how to calculate the “real pri c e ”
of water and who should organize its sale.
The state
as mediator
The principle of free water is being challenged.
For many people,water has become a commodity
to be bought and sold. But management of this
shared resource cannot be left exclusively to market
f o r c e s. M a ny elements of civil society—NGOs,
r e s e a r c h e rs , community groups—are campaigning
for the cultural and social aspects of wat e r
management to be taken into account.
E ven the World Bank, the main advo c ate of
water pri vat i z at i o n , is cautious on this point. I t
recognizes the value of the part n e rships between the
public and pri vate sectors which have sprung up in
recent ye a rs. Only the state seems to be in a position
to ensure that practices are fair and to mediat e
between the parties involved—consumer groups,
private firms and public bodies. At any rate, water
r e g u l ation and management systems need to be
based on other than purely financial cri t e ri a . If they
aren’t,hundreds of millions of people will have no
access to it. n
+ …
l A person can survive for about a month without food, but only about a week
without water.
l About 70 per cent of human skin consists of water.
l Women and children in most developing regions travel an average of 10 to 15
kilometres each day to get water.
l Some 34,000 people die a day from water-related diseases like diarrhoea and
parasitic worms. This is the equivalent to casualties from 100 jumbo jets
crashing every day!
l A person needs five litres of water a day for drinking and cooking and another
25 litres for personal hygiene.
l The average Canadian family uses 350 litres of water a day. In Africa, the
average is 20 litres and in Europe, 165 litres.
l A dairy cow needs to drink about four litres of water a day to produce one litre
of milk.
l A tomato is about 95 per cent water.
l About 9,400 litres of water are used to make four car tires.
l About 1.4 billion litres of water are needed to produce a day’s supply of the
world’s newsprint.
Sources:International Development Initiative of McGill University, Canada;Saint Paul Water Utility, Minnesota,USA
Irrigating an apple orchard in Provence (France).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO COurier 21
What price water?
We now have less than half the amount of water
available per capita than we did 50 years ago. In
1950,world reserves, (after accounting for agricultural,
industrial and domestic uses) amounted to 16.8 thousand
cubic metres per person. Today, global reserves have
dropped to 7.3 thousand cubic metres and are expected to
fall to 4.8 thousand in just 25 years.
Scientists have developed many ways of measuring
supplies and evaluating water scarcity. In the maps at right,
“catastrophic”levels mean that reserves are unlikely to
sustain a population in the event of a crisis like drought.
Low supplies refer to levels which put in danger industrial
development or ability to feed a population.
Just 50 years ago, not a country in the world faced
catastrophic water supply levels. Today, about 35 per cent
of the population lives under these conditions. By 2025,
about two-thirds will have to cope with low if not
catastrophic reserves. In contrast,“water rich”regions and
countries—such as northern Europe, Canada,almost
everywhere in South America,Central Africa,the Far East
and Oceania—will continue to enjoy ample reserves.
The sharp declines reflect the soaring water demands of
growing populations, agricultural needs and
industrialization.In addition, nature has been far from even-
handed.More than 40 per cent of the water in rivers,
reservoirs and lakes is concentrated in just six countries:
Brazil,Russia,Canada,the United States, China and India.
Meanwhile just two per cent of river, reservoir and lake
water is found in about 40 per cent of the world’s land
mass.
As a result,in 2025 Europe and the United States will
have half the per capita reserves they did in 1950, while
Asia and Latin America will have just a quarter of what they
previously enjoyed. But the real drama is likely to hit Africa
and the Middle East, where available supplies by 2025 may
be only an eighth of what they were in 1950. n
A thirsty planet 1 9 5 0
1 9 9 5
2 0 2 5
Water availability of the world regions (1 000m3/year per capita)
1.0 = catastrophically low
1.1 - 2 = very low
2.1 - 5 = low
5.1 - 10 = middle
10.1 - 20 = high
20 = very high
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
n
Colin Green:“Water as an economic 
resource” is generating tremendous
controversy and discussion.
What does this mean in practical terms?
John Briscoe: Two things. F i rs t , there is a cost
a s s o c i ated with providing services like water supply
or irri g at i o n .As with other serv i c e s ,u s e rs should pay
for the cost of those services to ensure among other
things accountability to users and financial
sustainability. In developing countries, it is often
claimed that services must be subsidized to protect
the poor.Yet in virtually every case, the influential
or powerful people benefit from the subsidy, while
the poor don’t receive formal services and end up
p aying water ve n d o rs about ten times more than the
cost of the serv i c e .There is broad agreement on this.
The second point is more subtle and
c o n t e s t e d — w h at economists call the “ o p p o rt u n i t y
cost of water”.Imagine a basin where all the water
is already used.By using one cubic metre of water
(even if it is free),I impose a cost on everyone else
who is denied the opportunity to use that wat e r. I n
technical term s , the highest value of the use denied
is called “the opportunity cost”.The controversy
stems from how to deal with this cost.In the past,
the general solution has been that “ g ove rn m e n t
will allocate wat e r.” But it has become painfully
clear that gove rnments are not ve ry good at this task.
There are several altern at i ve s : one is to charge users
a price and thus ration a scarce resource.This is
strongly resisted by current users , with good reason,
since it is really an abrogation of an existing form a l
or informal property ri g h t .A more creat i ve approach
has been to assign property rights to users and then
allow them to trade those rights.This is not a “free
m a r k e t ” . I n d e e d , it requires a gr e at deal of
r e g u l at i o n . I n f o rmal markets have long existed
w h e r e ver there has been water scarcity. But in recent
d e c a d e s , there has been enormous progress in
establishing formal markets in places like Californ i a
in the United States,Chile,Australia and Mexico.
Bernard Barraqué:Water is first a natural resource,
and in some cases it becomes both a social and
economic good. In Europe, we tend to think that a
price should not be attached to water in its natural
e nv i r o n m e n t . C o nve rs e l y, the cost of installing
technology to make this water useful should be at
least partly covered by users.
Under European water laws, people can take
small amounts of water directly from the source for
free.The general trend in the public water system
is for consumers to pay a small flat fee for the
connection or for a basic allowance of wat e r.B e yo n d
that,they pay for what they use.
In the case of non-domestic users fully or ove r -
exploiting a basin, I think that there should be
abstraction levies, p a rticularly for irri g at i o n .A ve ry
small levy on irri g at o rs can liberate a lot of water for
other users. H owe ve r , it is important to unders t a n d
that these economic incentives (levies) are more
e f ficient when they are set up by “ u s e rs ’b o a r d s ”t h a n
by central regulators.
Colin Gre e n : Is the water crisis really a food crisis? Is
the problem the availability of water for irrigation?
John Briscoe offers a similar response to that of
Bernard Barraqué: I rri g ation is the wo r l d ’s biggest
user (of water) because water is not only abstracted
but also evaporates, meaning it does not return to
A water vendor in Jodhpur
(India).
By putting a price tag on water, we may be able to save this vital re s o u rce fro m
w a s t e. But can privatization schemes ensure that everyone is served? Jo h n
Briscoe of the World Bank argues for a greater role for the marke t . But Fre n c h
academic Bernard Barraqué sees danger in treating water like private pro p e r t y.
Colin Gre e n , self-described iconoclast and economist, asks the questions.
Who pays the piper?
Who calls the tune?
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO COurier 23
What price water?
P
The water flow s
in rivulets and
s t re a m s, to the grid on
the street corn e r,
it stag n ates and 
s we l l s. . . . Then it
h i d e s, d i s a p p e a rs,
becomes as one with
the air we bre at h e. I t
dims the light. I t
lengthens the hours fo r
l ove rs, p ro l o n g s
s o l i t u d e, d e e p e n s
m i s fo r t u n e.
Jaime Sabines 
(1926-),Mexico
the river basin.The problem is not making water
available for irri g at i o n , but ensuring that it is
efficiently used. H owe ve r , the crisis is ve ry
c o m p l i c at e d . There is, for example, the gr ow i n g
problem of pollution.
Colin Green: Economists have developed a variety
of ways to assess the value of natural resources.
But for some people, a resource like wetland has an
intrinsic value which cannot be measured in dollars.
How do we include these moral concerns in
economic analyses?
John Briscoe: I would not call a wetland a “ m o r a l
c o n c e rn ” . It is something people value or wa n t
because it provides a va riety of ve ry import a n t
services,including aesthetic ones and even just so
t h at it will exist. The logical approach is to fin d
ways of getting stake-holders to manage
c o m p r e h e n s i vely the wetland and the entire aquat i c
ecosystem.
Bernard Barraqué: Some suggest that by pricing
the “services” flowing from that wetland, we can
ensure that people value and respect that resource.
I don’t agree with this. Economists have not yet
found a way of truly eva l u ating all of the assets of a
resource like a wetland.
Colin Green: Many economists believe that all uses
of water should be charged at the price equal to
the costs of making that water available. Are prices
really effective in reducing the use and waste of
water?
John Briscoe: Water pricing and metering are
c e rtainly effective in reducing demand. It isn’t hard
to see why this should be the case, since it is true for
everything else we consume.
Bernard Barraqué: Water supply systems are cheap
to run but expensive to bu i l d . This is basically why
d e veloping countries installing a water supply scheme
must rely on heavy subsidies and cheap loans, just as
d e veloped countries did in the past. Once the initial
systems have been completed, then it becomes possible
to raise the prices to cover long-term maintenance of
the systems, as is the case in nort h e rn Europe.
Water meters don’t necessarily lead to reduced
c o n s u m p t i o n . Most European studies have show n
t h at consumption of water for indoor purp o s e s —
d ri n k i n g, c o o k i n g, and bathing—does not va ry
according to the price charged. C o nve rs e l y, o u t d o o r
uses—like filling swimming pools, washing cars and
wat e ring gardens—are more sensitive to pri c e s.So we
h ave to be careful about making blanket stat e m e n t s
c o n c e rning meteri n g . There is another point to be
m a d e . While there is a lot of talk about domestic
m e t e ri n g, little attention has gone to the savings that
could result from metering large irri g ation schemes.
Colin Green: Some economists argue that rights to
abstract water should be made tradable. This
requires that individuals have a legal right to
abstract water, which implies a sense of ownership.
Should existing laws be changed to create that
right?
John Briscoe: Where there is wat e r , there are
implicit rights to that water and conflicts over those
ri g h t s. By formally defining these ri g h t s , we can
establish clearer and more efficient ways of dealing
with a problem that is intrinsic to human existence.
The “trading system”in question has proven to be
a success in places like Californ i a , where laws we r e
passed authorizing fa rm e rs to sell their water ri g h t s
to cities during a drought.The economic and social
benefits of this system are clear.
Bernard Barraqué: In Europe,“ p ri vat e ” wat e rs are
declining in import a n c e , but this does not mean that
they have become “ g ove rn m e n t - ow n e d ” .E u r o p e a n s
generally consider water to be a common propert y,
which can be used but not ow n e d . In most cases, t h e
s t ate does not assume the role of direct manager of
the resources but acts as a kind of guarantor that
different kinds of users share the resources according
to equity, equality and ethical pri n c i p l e s. T h i s
balanced system allows more flexibility than
p ri vat i z ation of resources, and what ’s more it can be
accompanied by monetary compensat i o n .
Colin Green: Is the argument for privatization a
practical one or is it essentially ideological?
Inspecting a water main
in Hamburg (Germany).
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
John Briscoe: B o t h . This is a big subject, w i t h
many red herrings! No one has truly “privatized”
water services except England and Wa l e s.We more
commonly find what French colleagues call
“ d e l e g ated management”, in which ow n e rs h i p
remains public while pri vate operat o rs are
responsible for a va riety of tasks which they do
better than public operat o rs. There is no magi c
r e g u l at o ry solution to the monopoly problem in
which water is either a public or a private domain.
I strongly believe that a mixed system in which
public operat o rs look over their shoulders at pri vat e
c o m p e t i t o rs , and vice-ve rs a ,o f f e rs the best hope for
getting people good services at a reasonable cost.
Bernard Barraqué: I agree with John that mixed
systems are in fact superi o r.There is a wide arr ay of
p a rtial pri vat i z ation schemes across We s t e rn Europe.
In practice, “ p ri vat i z at i o n ”o c c u rs when the public
system fa i l s. There is a general feeling that
p ri vat i z ation is the only choice. But there are
a l t e rn at i ve s. For example, some countries might
find it advantageous to tie together different kinds
of services like gas, electricity and water in a more
efficient system of financing and billing.
Colin Green: Public participation is considered a
critical ingredient to sustainable development. How
can we combine increased public participation with
privatization?
John Briscoe: Astute observers have argued that
the gr e atest benefit of getting the pri vate sector
involved is precisely that it brings greater public
Valencia: a thousand years
of calm waters
The farmers of Va l e n c i a , on the river Turia on Spain’s east coast, t a ke their rights to water very
s e r i o u s l y. For over a thousand years, they have relied on their city’s Water Tribunal to guara n t e e
that water drawn from the Turia is distributed fairly.Although they are not lawyers and do not ke e p
a written record of the verdicts they reach, and although there is no prison for offenders, e i g h t
S í n d i c o s or magistrates meet under the Porch of the Apostles of the Cathedral of Valencia and settle
verbally the disputes arising between farmers over the right to use water from the channels
irrigating the 17,000 hectares of what is known as the “Orchard of Va l e n c i a ” .
This scene, which has been re-enacted every Thursday at midday since the middle of the
tenth century, when A b d - a r-Rahman III was the caliph of Córdoba, m a kes the “ Tribunal de las
Aguas de la Vega de Va l e n c i a ” the oldest law court in Europe.
The eight magistrates, who are dressed in black and are accompanied by a bailiff bearing
the tribunal’s emblem, represent each of the “mother channels”which are used for irrigation
and for distribution of the water from the Tu r i a .The roughly 1,500 farmers from each of these
channel systems elect their own magistra t e, who is required to be someone who actually
farms the land and is not simply a landowner.The task of these “ p e o p l e ’s judges” is to ensure
that all the farmers of Valencia are supplied with the water they need through application of
the provisions of a decree promulgated by King James I of A ragon in 1238,which is still in force
and provides that “Everybody shall be entitled to a share of the water in proportion to the
amount of land owned”.
The most common complaints with which the Court has to deal are concerned with the
squandering or theft of water at times of drought, the disruption of channels, damage to
crops as a result of water overflowing onto adjoining land,and failure to comply with irrigation
schedules and to keep the channels clean so that the water can flow along them freely. n
scrutiny, openness and accountability. In England
and Wales (considered by some to be a model of
water pri vat i z at i o n , but a model I am personally not
a fan of), the local community, p r e s s , and public at
large are much more invo l ved than they were before
privatization.
When people are faced with unresponsive and
unaccountable bureaucracies, they tend to resign
t h e m s e l ves to inefficient serv i c e s.They don’t vo i c e
their demands.With pri vat i z at i o n , people are pay i n g
for a service,have a clear view of the obligations of
the provider and will not accept poor services. In
m a ny countries which have experi e n c e d
p ri vat i z at i o n , we find people beginning to make
the same demands of publicly provided services.
This may prove to be the gr e atest benefit associat e d
with private water management.
Bernard Barraqué: I disagree with John concern i n g
public part i c i p ation in England and Wa l e s.
P ri vat i z ation led to an adve rs a rial form of
p a rt i c i p at i o n . In France also, people tend to have less
c o n fidence in pri vate management.This might be a
good reason to keep some role for local gove rn m e n t .
P ri vat i z ation is ideologically based on
“consumerizing” a service. In the process, people
assume the role of a customer, not a citizen. As a
c i t i z e n , an individual might feel a civic responsibility
to cut down on water use especially during a
d r o u g h t .A customer, on the other hand, expects the
service paid for,no matter what.
It takes a lot of information about how water is
u s e d , for example, to run an efficient system. P u b l i c
p a rt i c i p ation offers this inform ation and so
u l t i m ately lowe rs the system’s running costs. A t
the same time, a more informed consumer may
also be a more demanding citizen. For example, i n
France people complain about high water prices.
They insist on having individual meters even when
those meters aren’t really effic i e n t .S u r e , the meters
will tell them how much water they used. But those
people still aren’t going to see that their water bills
are covering costs to clean up industrial pollution
connected to public sewe rs , for example, or to clean
up nitrates from agri c u l t u r e .With more inform at i o n ,
those same people might start demanding a more
sustainable water policy. n
A community project to build
underground sewerage and
drinking-water installations 
in Guatemala City.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 25
What price water?
n
It looks the same. Tastes the same. It eve n
smells the same, with that familiar foul whiff
of chlori n e . But the seemingly ordinary glass
of water is becoming more and more precious for
the two million inhabitants of Budapest. B e t we e n
1991 and 1999, water prices increased threefold.
Across Hungary, people have seen their water bills
gr ow as much as five times as state budgets dry up,
l e aving public utilities to either cut services or
charge higher rat e s.
After 40 years of socialist mismanagement,
Hungarians have developed an allergy to anything
centrally-run.As a result, the water utilities, which
used to be run mostly by state bodies, were
t r a n s f o rmed into share-holding companies
belonging to the municipal governments between
1991 and 1994. H owe ve r , m a ny of the local
governments are finding the responsibilities of the
companies to be more than they bargained for.
To begin with, municipal authorities had to
raise the water bills of the people who elected
them. Second, the inherited infrastructure is in
need of major investment.While the supply system
ensures that almost everyone has water, very little
of the water used is treated. In Budapest, for
example, about 70 per cent of all waste water is
dumped into the Danube each year (about 193
million cubic metres in 1998), to the growing
chagrin of downstream neighbours. Under the
Sophia Convention of 1994, Hungary has agreed
to curb this pollution but the infrastru c t u r e
required will cost about three billion dollars.
In their search for reve n u e , m u n i c i p a l
g ove rnments are increasingly turning to
p ri vat i z at i o n . B e t ween 1994 and 1997, they sold
25 to 50 per cent of the shares of six of the more
than 200 municipal water companies. These six
companies supply water to about a quarter of the
p o p u l ation nat i o n - w i d e .
But judging by initial results, it will take some
time before that investment translates into
i m p r oved supply and treatment systems. I n
B u d a p e s t , for example, new revenues from the
p ri vatized system are supposed to cover not just
o p e r ating costs but also repairs , n o t a b l y,
r e c o n s t ruction of 10 per cent of the capital’s 4,400
kilometres of pipeline each ye a r. Yet only 30
kilometres of pipeline were fixed last ye a r.
However, there is still a popular conviction that
private managers are bound to do better than civil
s e rva n t s. I n d e e d , economic efficiency has
improved in the capital over the last couple of
years, since some of the water assets were bought
by a Franco-German consortium for $91 million.
The consortium manages the system, while the
municipality retains control over key issues like
water pricing.
Last year, the consortium managed to trim
about $12 million from operating costs, essentially
by restructuring and cutting jobs. The investors
r e c e i ved 75 per cent of these sav i n g s. T h e
remaining 25 per cent were used to keep prices as
low as possible. Even so, last year’s rates still rose
more than 20 per cent against a consumer price
index increase of 13 to 14 per cent. For this year,
private investors originally proposed a 25 per cent
increase which the local government rejected.Only
after protracted negotiations did the two sides
agree to a compromise of 13 per cent,slightly more
than the predicted inflation rate.
The bottom line is clear: no one is satisfied.
Private investors are faced with companies that
continue to lose money, while municipal
authorities fear the political costs from rising water
prices. Meanwhile, ordinary citizens hold their
noses over glasses of water that cost more each
year. n
Gabor Szabo in Budapest
H2O, a formula for good health
Water consists of two atoms of hydrogen and one of oxygen. It also contains potassium, iron,
sodium, calcium, magnesium and carbonates . . . and sometimes bubbles. The world market
for bottled water, which is dominated by the multinational companies Nestlé and Danone, is a fast-
growing sector, with an annual consumption of 80,000 million litres.
The definition of mineral water accepted by FAO’s Codex Alimentarius , which is used as an
international yardstick,says that natural mineral water is water directly extracted from the earth and
bottled close to its source, with a stable composition and subject to as little processing as possible.
This rules out water which is mineralized after extraction, water for medicinal purposes (which is
often sold in chemists’ shops) and water from the mains that is simply bottled.
The market for mineral water, which is synonymous with health and high quality of living, is
also growing. According to figures provided by the specialized consultant Euromonitor, sales
worldwide increased by some 25.5 per cent between 1993 and 1997,rising from 46,430 to 58,290
million litres.
In terms of consumption,the Italians and the French appear to be the peoples who are keenest
on mineral water, since they consume more than 100 litres per person per year, twice the amount
drunk by the Spanish (55 litres) and 20 times more than the Japanese (5 litres).
M i n e ral water is also trendy. It is used in the manufacture of cosmetics, and in some countries
there are bars where only different kinds of mineral water are sold, as well as professional wa t e r-
tasters whose job it is to appraise its qualities. By contra s t , in many developing countries bottled wa t e r
(often sold in large flagons) is a must, because of the poor quality of the mains wa t e r. The United
Nations Development Progra m m e ’s latest Human Development Report notes that if all the world’s
population had access to clean drinking wa t e r, two million lives a year would be saved. n
H u n g a r y : under new m a n a g e m e n t
Hungary is diving into the whirlpool of privatization but the country’s new
water companies have failed to make a splash
May Osiris intro d u c e
you to fresh wat e r.
Inscription on an Egyptian
funerary monument.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
A progressive new water management policy designed to provide
all South Africans with guaranteed access to water
South Africa: water for everyone
n
Among the many stories of depri vation told by
o r d i n a ry South A f ricans during three months of
n ation-wide pove rty hearings last ye a r , one eve n t
still stands out. In a village in nort h e rn Kwa z u l u -
N at a l , crocodiles had reportedly killed a handful of
women who went to a ri ver to collect water for their
basic needs.
As that event graphically testifie s ,water pove rty is
literally a life and death matter in South A f ri c a ,w h e r e
about a third of the country ’s 36 million people lacks
access to adequate supplies of potable wat e r , a n d
almost two-thirds lack basic sanitat i o n .The domino
effects are seve r e .The pove rty heari n g s , organized by
n o n - g ove rnmental organizations and churches, we r e
filled with accounts of children missing school because
of wat e r - r e l ated illness, and women kept out of the
p r o d u c t i ve labour force to take care of them.There is
also the ecological damage caused by lack of sanitat i o n
fa c i l i t i e s , which leaves ri ve rs flowing with disease.
But change is underway as South Africa enacts
w h at many consider one of the wo r l d ’s most
progressive water management policies.
Learning to share
The first part of this new policy invo l ves installat i o n
of collective pumps to ensure that by 2004 eve ry
South A f rican has ready access to at least 25 litres of
clean water a day within 200 metres of home. I n
a d d i t i o n ,e f f o rts are being made to install more pri vat e
taps and to improve sanitation—an undert a k i n g
which is proving difficult as many communities have
trouble paying for these new serv i c e s.
The second part is more ambitious: to dismantle
an apartheid-era system that reserves the precious
resource for a rich minori t y.Black townships are a sorry
sight of people lugging buckets or pushing ri c k e t y
w h e e l b a rr ows filled with water containers.Yet the
n e i g h b o u ring suburbs are a lush haven where an
average home has at least two bathrooms and a kitchen,
while garden-hoses are left on for hours to keep the
grass green in a city like Sowe t o.
In the country s i d e , women in Kwa z u l u - N atal are
killed by crocodiles while fa rm e rs in the same area
i rri g ate their crops almost for free. Not only do the
l atter have ri p a rian rights to water on,under or adjacent
to their propert y,but also they tap into sources locat e d
f u rther away thanks to infrastructure subsidized by the
s t at e .I n d u s t ries like forestry and mining also benefit
from these subsidies. These sectors “ h ave the lion’s
share of water allocation at the moment,” s ays Mike
M u l l e r , Director General of the Water A f fa i rs
d e p a rt m e n t .“There will have to be some shari n g .”
The right to collect water 
for subsistence
This is where the new National Water Act comes
i n .A p p r oved by parliament in 1998,it is now becoming
l aw.The old ri p a rian rights will be replaced by licenses
granted for water uses that bring social benefit s ,s u c h
as job creation and economic empowe rm e n t .L i c e n s i n g
preference will go to new actors ,p a rticularly emergi n g
black fa rm e rs , while a review board will hear appeals
from those who lose out as a result of the act.
The act entrenches the individual’s right to collect
water at the source for subsistence.“In many senses
this is about liberating water from the tyranny of the
l a n d ow n e r ,” s ays the Water A f fa i rs Minister, K a d e r
A s m a l .
Under the current system,rich and poor families in
S owe t o,for example,both pay about 60 cents per cubic
metre regardless of whether they use that water to fill a
swimming pool or cook a meal.Under the new system,
different rates will apply for different uses.The poorest
people relying on collective pumps will pay about 80
cents per month—a fraction of the true costs—per
cubic metre.When it comes to pri vate taps,e ve ryone will
r e c e i ve a basic supply of water at a minimum,s u b s i d i z e d
p ri c e .For supplies above basic needs,about $1.60 pe r
cubic metre will be charged,with an even higher rate for
l u x u ry uses like filling pools.Steep rates will also be fixe d
for large landow n e rs and industri a l i s t s.
The mere idea of wat e r - p ricing has set off a
political explosion. Pa rties representing the poor
and black constituency, the A f rican Nat i o n a l
C o n gress and the Inkatha Freedom Pa rt y, s u p p o rt the
a c t .Yet opposition is virulent from the ri g h t - w i n g
Freedom Front representing white fa rm e rs , t h e
D e m o c r atic Pa rty favo u ring business interests and the
more broadly-based white Nationalist Pa rt y. n
Ferial Haffajee in Johannesburg
Fetching water from a
communal tap in a South
African township.
In its yo u t h f u l
l i m p i d i t y, water is an
i n verted sky in wh i ch
the stars take a new
l i fe.
Gaston Bachelard
(1864-1962),France
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 27
What price water?
M e x i c o : t h e s w e e t s m e l l o f s u c c e s s
n
The smell of bu rning sugar and the lengths of cut
cane strewn along the dirt road point the way to
the San Francisco Ameca sugar mill in Mexico’s
Jalisco stat e , the home of tequila, 73 kilometres from
the city of Guadalajara. To the naked eye , the mill
seems just like any other, with its tall chimneys, the
sound of escaping steam and the comings and goings
of its wo r k e rs.Yet this fa c t o ry stands apart . Until four
ye a rs ago, the mill needed 15 litres of water to
produce one kilogram of sugar. N ow it uses only
three litres.
Besides reducing production costs, this “ m i r a c l e ”
is of direct benefit to the ri ver A m e c a , the mill’s main
source of supply and one of Jalisco’s three largest
rivers.
“ We have made all these changes at the mill
because we are convinced of the need to show concern
for the water supply problem and also because wat e r
is becoming an increasingly expensive item,” s ay s
chemist Matilde Osorio Cru z , head of the mill’s
m a n u fa c t u ring laborat o ry. In the space of five ye a rs ,
the price of wat e r , a basic ingredient in sugar
production,has risen fifteenfold.
An image of St. Francis is displayed near to the
g ates of the fa c t o ry, which was founded in 1903.
From that time until barely four ye a rs ago, s u g a r
production required enormous amounts of wat e r ,
which was drawn from the ri ver A m e c a . At the end of
the process,most of the waste water was discharged
back into the ri ver and contaminated it. Unlike metals
or other types of toxic chemical wa s t e , the by-products
of sugar, consisting chiefly of molasses, are eve n t u a l l y
absorbed by the river but consume a considerable
amount of oxygen, thereby depriving fish and plant
life of sustenance.
According to Osori o, as a result of the measures
taken this problem has been completely resolve d .
“The first thing we did was to set up a water treat m e n t
p l a n t ,” she say s.“Then we started to use closed circuits
in which the water circulates continuously through the
different parts of the process without any of it being
l o s t , as used to be the case.” In practical term s , t h e
system devised is somewhat similar to that of the
b l o o d s t r e a m , in which the fluid circulates and is
processed without having to be renewe d .
Closed circuits
to prevent waste
Among the innovations introduced, O s o rio cites
the creation of a cooling tank to bring down the
t e m p e r ature of the wat e r , which is ve ry hot when it
emerges from one part of the process, before using it
a g a i n . The tank looks like an enormous fountain,
since the system consists of a set of perforated pipes
through which the water gushes before cooling in
contact with the air.Thanks to the system, the wat e r
t e m p e r ature is reduced from 45° to 38°C. Once the
water has cooled, it is fed back into the system.
The project was made possible through support
p r ovided by the United Nations Industri a l
D e velopment Organization (UN I D O) , with the
p a rt i c i p ation of Mexico’s National Chamber of the
Sugar and Alcohol Industry, the Group of Sugar-
E x p o rting Countries of Latin A m e rica and the
C a ribbean (GE P L AC E A) and the National A u t o n o m o u s
U n i ve rsity of Mexico (UN A M) . Similar systems are
being used at the Motzorongo and El Potrero mills in
the Mexican state of Ve r a c ru z .
The San Francisco mill is the pilot plant of the
Beta San Miguel group, which owns a further four
mills in Mexico, to which it plans to extend the
water-conservation experience gained at Ameca.
According to inform ation provided by UN I D O,
its $493,000 loan to the mill could be recouped in two
ye a rs as a result of cost sav i n g s. S e r gio Miranda Cru z ,
the UN I D O official behind the technical studies
c u l m i n ating in this experi m e n t , c o n s i d e rs that “ t h e
results have been so positive that the project could
d e velop into a full-scale progr a m m e . But quite frankly
we have not yet reached that point.”
The sugar-cane harvest started in November 1998
and will go on until May 1999.The machinery wo r k s
night and day.The mill will produce some 100,000
tonnes of sugar and will consume 3,156 cubic metres
of water per tonne produced.For the mill’s technical
staff and wo r k e rs , optimizing water consumption and
i m p r oving sugar quality present a difficult bu t
r e warding challenge. n
Juan Carlos Núñez in Guadalajara,Mexico
In Mexico’s Jalisco State, a sugar mill has reduced its water consumption 
by four-fifths and cut its costs
Mending an antiquated
installation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
d o m i n ated city gove rnment last month. The tax
has been introduced under World Bank pressure in
r e t u rn for loans to help refurbish the city’s
hydrological infrastructure.
The new tax will be applied to all bu i l d i n g s
four or more storeys high—the kind of residential
buildings popular amongst the middle class. It will
in effect cover an extra 10 per cent of city residents
and will hopefully raise $5 million a ye a r , helping to
plug the municipal government’s $17.5 million a
year water systems budget deficit. Currently, only
f i ve per cent of domestic users pay water tax.
Commercial users account for 95 per cent of the
annual $2.4 million now raised from the water tax.
A cutback
on public taps
M e a n w h i l e , to cut down on waste due to leakage
through antiquated pipes, the gove rnment will close
600 of the 12,000 public water taps. For Calcutta’s
1.2 million poor, these public taps are the only
form of access to water. The cutback on taps has
raised serious concern among slum and pavement
dwellers. “Today I have to wait for hours to get a
bucket of water. If they close the tap in my slum
where shall I go?” asks Mohammed Saleem, who
lives in Entally slum in east Calcutta.
The gove rnment reckons that the public’s
c riticism of the water tax is the price it has to pay for
the water system to be improve d . In return for its
tough tax reform s , the gove rnment hopes to get
World Bank help to revamp the city’s entire water and
s e werage system. C u rrently the World Bank is
u n d e rtaking a $ 2.5 million feasibility study for a wat e r
systems overhaul which could cost $200 million.
H o p e f u l l y, the new tax revenues will help the city
i m p r ove water quality as well as quantity. “It is
unsafe to drink water directly from the pipes in
Calcutta,” says Arindam Ghosh, a scientist at the
N ational Environmental Engi n e e ring Research
Institute. According to Ghosh, the existing water
t r e atment plants in the city cannot remove
hazardous chemicals dissolved in the water, taken
directly from the heavily polluted Ganges. As a
result, water-borne diseases are common. n
Tirthankar Bandyopadhyay 
in Calcutta
n
Standing in a long, winding queue, R atan Das
eagerly awaits his turn to get a bucket of wat e r
from the public tap in Topsia slum in southern
C a l c u t t a , capital of India’s West Bengal stat e . D a s ,
like the 200 other people who live in the slum and
are dependent on the tap, is anxious to reach it
before the water stops flow i n g . If he misses out
n ow, he will have to wait another four hours ,
sometimes even more, to get his fil l .
Not far from To p s i a , Meenakshi Mukherjee, a
middle-class housewife living in a one-room flat ,
has an arr ay of vessels under the single water tap in
her house. She needs to store as much water as
possible before the pipe stops pumping out wat e r
and instead coughs out air.
Will the poor
foot the bill?
The travails of Das and Mukherjee in their daily
s t ruggle for water are typical for Calcutta and its
five million people.The city’s antiquated distri bu t i o n
n e t wo r k , built mostly during British rule in India,h a s
long since been unable to cope with the strains of
p o p u l ation gr ow t h . M e a n w h i l e , the impove ri s h e d
s t ate gove rnment has lacked the money needed to
overhaul the crumbling water system.As a result, t h e
leftist state and municipal gove rnments are now
extending their water taxes to the middle classes.
Poor people fear they might be next in line to pay tax
on wat e r.
The decision to extend the water tax—which
h i t h e rto has been paid only by the rich and by
commercial users — was taken by Calcutta’s Marxist-
Short of money to overhaul an antiquated water system, the Indian city may
have opened a pandora’s box by extending the coverage of its water tax
Wat e r, like a skin that
no one can wo u n d .
Paul Eluard
(1895-1952),France
India: Calcutta plugs its deficit
Ablutions in a Calcutta street.
I have to wait for hours to get
a bucket of water.
If they close the tap in my slum
w h e re shall I go?
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 29
What price water?
n
Wa rs will be fought for wat e r. The dire
prediction persists years after it was voiced by
such leading figures as Jordan’s King Hussein
and Boutros Boutros Ghali of Egypt. I n d e e d ,
according to this gloomy scenari o, the Middle East
and North Africa appear to be doomed.This area,
k n own as the MENA regi o n , was the first in history
to run out of water in the 1970s, in the sense that it
became unable to meet all of its needs. But before
panicking over the pessimists’ p r e d i c t i o n s ,c o n s i d e r
a critical fa c t o r.The regi o n ’s leaders have managed
to tap into a major source of water hy d r o l o gi s t s
neglect to mention:virtual water,not actual water
but that embedded in commodities like wheat.
A convenient s o l u t i o n
J.A. Allan*
T h i rsty countries in the
Middle East are
compensating for dwindling
water supplies by importing
‘virtual water’ in the form of
wheat and other farm cro p s.
B e l o w, P rof J. A . A l l a n , a water
specialist at London
U n i v e rs i t y ’s School of Oriental
and African Studies, o u t l i n e s
the issues surrounding a
c o n t ro v e rsial policy and
concept whose wisdom is
widely questioned (see article
page 31).
It would require an inhuman level of courage for
a political leader of a country that has enjoye d
water security for 5,000 ye a rs to announce that
supplies are no longer adequate. Instead, leaders
insist that supplies are “ s u f f i c i e n t ” . But this is
deceptive. Supplies are “sufficient” for the small
amounts needed for dri n k i n g : one cubic metre per
year per pers o n . They may also cover curr e n t
domestic and industrial needs, although both of
these are on the rise. But there isn’t enough fresh
water to cover these demands in addition to the
tremendous amounts needed for food production.
It takes at least 1,000 cubic metres of low quality
water to raise the amount of food an individual
* Professor, Water Issues Group,
School of Oriental & African
Studies, University of London
N o w you see it,
now you don’t...
Watering nursery plants in the Syrian oasis of Palmyra
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
W h at joy
to cross the summer
ri ve r,
sandals in hand!
Buson 
(1715-1850), Japan
needs in a year.
Instead of paying the political costs of publicly
recognizing this defic i t ,l e a d e rs rely on the conve n i e n t
solution of “ v i rtual wat e r ” .To raise a tonne of wheat ,
you need 1,000 tonnes of wat e r. I m p o rting a million
tonnes of wheat is the equivalent to importing a billion
tonnes (cubic metres) of wat e r. Since the end of the
1 9 8 0 s , the MENA region has been importing 40
million tonnes of cereals and flour annually. M o r e
v i rtual water “ flow s ” into the region each year than
flows down the Nile into Egypt for agri c u l t u r e .
Piping desalinated water 
to desert farms
Not only is this virtual water readily ava i l a b l e ,i t
is extraordinarily cheap. W h e at prices have been
falling for the past century. On the curr e n t
a gricultural market which is dominated by the
United States and the European Union, wheat is
traded at about half the production cost.
Accounts of water needed
to produce food items
in the MENA region 
Product Unit Equivalent water
in 1 000m3 per unit
Bovine, cattle Head 4
Sheep and goats Head 0.5
Cereals Metric ton 1.5
Meat bovine fresh Metric ton 20
Meat poultry fresh Metric ton 6
Meet sheep fresh Metric ton 10
Citrus fruits Metric ton 1
Palm oil Metric ton 2
Pulses Metric ton 1
Roots and tubers Metric ton 1
Source: FAO, 1999
So it seems that the MENA region is simply
making the most of the situat i o n ,i m p o rting a highly
subsidized product containing a precious resource.
Yet depending on intern ational trade for such a
vital resource is not socially acceptable in these
c o u n t ries nor is it a strat e gically secure policy.T h i s
p a rtially explains why in the United Arab Emirat e s
d e s a l i n ated water is either piped kilometres to reach
fa rms in the desert or soil is actually moved from one
area to another to build new fa rms for gr e ater food
self-sufficiency. Up until 1991,Saudi Arabia used
significant amounts of fossil water—which is
extraordinarily pure but non-renewable—to grow
c o rn . “The Great Man-Made River Project” i s
L i b ya ’s solution to achieving gr e ater food self-
sufficiency. The plan is to pump water from deep
wells in the north of the country and then send it
through underground pipes to irri g ate about
200,000 hectares along the Mediterranean coast at
an estimated capital cost of $25 billion.These are
Sprinklers irrigate Israeli
tomato fields.
Harvesting wheat in Syria.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 31
What price water?
P
n
I t ’s like trying to get water out of a stone.
Across the Middle East, government officials
refuse to discuss the issue of virtual wat e r
publicly. Even academics are reluctant to express
their views on the topic.W hy such silence? After all,
p u b l i c l y - available statistics clearly indicate the
r e gi o n ’s wheat imports are ri s i n g, and there is
reason to believe that this trade will continue as
countries seek seemingly inexpensive and readily
available sources to compensate for dwindling wat e r
supplies.Technological solutions seem unlikely to
tackle the scarcity problem.With falling oil prices
d e va s t ating gove rnment reve n u e s , e ven we a l t hy
c o u n t ries like Saudi Arabia are finding desalinizat i o n
increasingly unaffordable.
In part , the silence stems from the political
climate.“There are a lot of negotiations going on
right now on va rious security issues, i n c l u d i n g
wat e r - s h a ring agr e e m e n t s. A ny inform ation linked
to water scarcity is sensitive,” explains Mamdouh
S h a h i n , a Netherlands-based Egyptian professor
of civil engi n e e ring widely respected in the Middle
East for his hy d r o l o gical assessments of the regi o n .
Virtual water also has a dirty name among the
r e gi o n ’s hy d r o l o gists and policy - m a k e rs who balk at
the notion that governments should import food
crops instead of growing them. Yes, the region is
faced with a water cri s i s.Ye s ,i m p o rting wheat is an
effective means for dealing with the problem. But
does this mean that countries should abandon their
An economic mirage?
Estimates of
the ‘virtual’ water
contained in the MENA region’s
food imports (1994)
Country Water equivalent in 1 000m3
of net imports (1994)
Algeria 12 397
Bahrain 680
Egypt 18 171
Iran, Islamic Republic of 11 519
Iraq 2 180
Jordan 3 467
Kuweit 2 784
Libyan Arab Jamahiriya 3 237
Mauritania -2*
Morocco 2 419
Saudi Arabia 13 863
Syria 1 014
Turkey -3 468*
United Arab Emirates 3 362
Yemen 3 375
* Negative figures indicate that export exceeds import, e.g.Mauritania,a net
exporter of animals, and Turkey, a net exporter of cereals and animals. Source: FAO,
1999
extreme examples. But consider the case of Egypt,
where about 90 per cent of the national wat e r
budget goes to agriculture and yet another 7.5
million tonnes of grain, equivalent to 7.5 billion
cubic metres of virtual wat e r , were still imported last
year to feed the population of about 63 million.
By downplaying the role of virtual water,there
is a risk that countries will undervalue their own
resources and put off innovat i ve and painful policies.
I rri g ation water is almost free in Egypt, w h i c h
makes for a very expensive policy.The same water
could bring a hundred times more in returns in
the industrial or service sectors. H owe ve r , t h e r e
are major political costs invo l ved in such a transition.
Almost 40 per cent of the labour force works in
agriculture, while most farmers have less than two
hectares each. These people cannot suddenly be
expected to pay for water or abandon their live l i h o o d s.
Time is required to change people’s perceptions of
water and to develop a diverse economy capable of
creating new jobs in other sectors.
Israel is an interesting case in point. This was a
c o u n t ry committed to making the desert bloom. I t s
fa rm e rs have the means to employ the most effic i e n t
i rri g ation systems.And ye t ,d u ring the past ten ye a rs ,t h e
g ove rnment has shown that it is possible to reduce wat e r
a l l o c ations to agri c u l t u r e . It is one of the few countri e s
in the world to charge a high proportion of the delive ry
cost (40 per cent) for irri g ation wat e r. But the curr e n t
p rices would have to double or even treble for the real cost
of water to be recove r e d .
Other MENA countries,like Jordan,Tunisia and
M o r o c c o, are starting to take the same approach.
The trade in virtual water could offer more time and
ease the political tensions in making this difficult
transition. Or it could be used to avoid dealing with
a very real problem. n
Egyptian fellaheen 
have little choice but to use
traditional irrigation
methods.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
H ow wide the wo rl d
wa s, h ow close the
t rees to heave n ,
and how clear in the
water the nearn e s s
of the moon!
Meng Hao-jan
(689?-740), China
agricultural sectors, or make their farmers pay prices
reflecting the real costs of irrigation?
“I disagree with the suggestion that we should totally
depend on virtual water to feed our people,” s ays Shahin.
“ V i rtual water is one solution. But we need a basket of
solutions—by conserving and developing conve n t i o n a l
and non-conventional water sources like harvesting fog
r e s i d u e or re-using drainage wat e rs from irri g ation and
urban uses.”
Don’t overcharge the farmers
Complete agricultural self-suffic i e n cy may well be
impossible in the regi o n .But for Shahin, this does not mean
t h at gove rnments should abandon the goal of improv i n g
h a rvest yields.“ Food imports are even more strat e gi c a l l y
s e n s i t i ve than energy import s.You can live without oil,bu t
not without food,” s ays Shahin. He notes that one danger
of virtual water is that importing nations would be
vulnerable in the event that grain producing countries cut
subsidies to their fa rm e rs ,potentially leading to signific a n t l y
higher pri c e s.
“ Water for irri g ation will remain a free commodity as
long as people remain so poor.This is in the interest of the
people and the administrat i o n ,” s ays Shahin.
C u rrently many irri g ation systems are wa s t e f u l ,
and gi ven the low price of wat e r , there is little incentive
to introduce technology that would improve effic i e n cy
and cut down waste. But, Shahin says, the solution
d o e s n ’t lie in pushing fa rm e rs from their livelihoods by
c h a r ging them for the water they use. I n s t e a d , h e
proposes investing in more efficient irri g ation systems,
like drip irrigation in which perforated pipes installed
just below the soil surface release small amounts of
water directly to the crops’ roots—a system which
reduces eva p o r ation and seepage.The challenge lies in
finding capital to finance technological improve m e n t s.
Shahin also points out that there are strong religi o u s
objections to charging for wat e r. “According to the
K o r a n , if you find someone who needs water but is
unable to reward or compensate you in any way, yo u
must gi ve them some for the sake of God’s blessing
and mercy,” he say s.“So in countries like Egypt and
S y ri a , ri ve rs are considered a gift of God.And since
the people are too poor to compensate the
government for the price of delivering that water,
there is no charge.”
Virtual imports vs. virtual exports
The concept of virtual water also comes under
attack from an economic pers p e c t i ve ,s ays Jad Isaac,
director-general of the Applied Research Institute of
Je ru s a l e m , a non-profit organization for sustainable
d e velopment in Palestinian terri t o ri e s.“If we are going
to talk about virtual import s ,”he say s ,“ we should also
consider our virtual exports (of fruits and ve g e t a b l e s )
to Europe and the United Stat e s.” For Isaac, t h e
question is not whether countries should abandon their
a gricultural sectors , but rat h e r , which types of
a griculture should be gi ven pri o ri t y : w h e at for food
s e c u ri t y, or high value cash crops like vegetables and
f ruits? “ I t ’s all about economics and following market
f o r c e s ,” Isaacs say s. “With globalizat i o n , there is not
a country in the world that can declare itself self-
s u f fic i e n t .”
“Whether we like it or not,” s ays Isaac,“ water is a
finite resource. It would be totally wrong to use it
u n e c o n o m i c a l l y.”According to Isaac,g ove rnment has
the responsibility to provide free water for domestic
n e e d s. But agriculture is an economic activity and so
fa rm e rs should pay for irri g at i o n .“It has to happen,bu t
s l owly because such a large part of the labour force
depends on agri c u l t u r e .You cannot suddenly transform
d e veloping countries into industrialized ones,”he say s.
E ven highly developed nations like Israel, w h i c h
receives tremendous financial and other forms of
assistance from the United States and other We s t e rn
g ove rn m e n t s ,h ave failed to adopt an economically
e f ficient agricultural policy.“ M a ny think there has
been a change in Israeli policy, but the gove rn m e n t
is still subsidizing water,” says Isaac. He notes that
Israel has one of the regi o n ’s highest percentages of
i rri g ated agriculture—about 50 per cent of its arable
l a n d — but that agriculture contri butes less than
two per cent to the economy. On the other hand,
Isaac notes that the Palestinian agricultural sector
represents about 20 per cent of the economy, even
though only six per cent of its arable land is irri g at e d .
“The Israeli policy doesn’t make sense,” s ay s
I s a a c.They should gi ve the water they took by force
back to the Palestinians who can do more in their
d e velopment with it.”With a gross national product
(GNP) of about $17,000 per capita, Isaac maintains
t h at Israel can afford to orient its economy towa r d s
high-technology sectors and depend less on fa rm i n g .
In contrast, Palestinian per capita GNP is about
$1,000 and dependent on agri c u l t u r e , s ays Isaac.
T h at is why Palestinians should continue to deve l o p
fa rming in the short term , while gradually building an
i n d u s t rial base. S ays Isaac: “ I t ’s like a baby. F i rst he
c r aw l s , then he walks and then he learns to ru n .” n
Amy Otchet
Food imports are even more
strategically sensitive than energy
imports. You can live without oil,
but not without food
Making every drop count
with drip irrigation on a
farm near Amman (Jordan).
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
C u s t o m - b u i l t
solutions f o r
international disputes
Joseph W. Dellapenna*
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 33
What price water?
An engineer working
on the King Talal dam,
which supplies water to
Jordan valley farms.
n
Is it any wonder that the English word “ ri va l ”
d e ri ves from the Latin “ ri va l i s ” ,meaning people
who live on opposite banks of a ri ver? All of the
214 largest ri ver basins in the world—home to about
40 per cent of the globe’s total population—are used
by more than one nat i o n .E ven the most cordial and
c o - o p e r at i ve of neighbouring nations have found it
d i f ficult to achieve acceptable arrangements for their
t r a n s b o u n d a ry surface wat e rs.
As the world gropes for solutions to disputes ove r
water resources, many who are concerned about
water issues are increasingly attracted to the idea of
setting up free market trading systems for water.
H owe ve r , market solutions to establishing
s overeignty over and control of water resources are
fraught with danger. Rather, we should look to the
body of international law that countries have been
s l owly developing by drawing on ancient pri n c i p l e s
of sharing dating back centuries.
It must be noted at the outset that countries have
recognized that water is too vital a resource for
nations to go to war. Throughout the many wars
fought in the twentieth century, water facilities have
by and large escaped unscat h e d . In the three major
wa rs between Pakistan and India, for example,
water could have been used as a formidable we a p o n
by both sides. Not only did they both refuse this
deadly option, they implemented water shari n g
agreements even as bullets were flying. Low-level
violence punctuated by full-fledged war has been
s i m m e ring in the Jordan Valley since the 1920s
b e t ween Israel and the neighbouring Arab nat i o n s.
Yet you can count on one hand the number of
times water supplies have been specifically targeted.
H owe ve r , the absence of “ water wa rs ” does not
mean that there aren’t serious disputes brewing,
p a rticularly in arid regions like the Middle East
Customary law provides a
sounder basis than market
forces for water sharing in
international river basins
* Professor of International Law, Villanova University,
Pa.,USA P
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
You are wro n g : in 
the Ti gris the thirs t y
find no path to wat e r,
nor any provision in
its fo a m . . . .
And you are bent like a
bu l rush on the wild
b a n k , p ropped on yo u r
h a n d .
And the only
sustenance is to bite
the palm of yo u r
h a n d s, the only wat e r,
your scat t e red tears.
Ibn Babik 
(d.1020),Baghdad
where already scarce water supplies are in
unprecedented demand as populations gr ow and
lifestyles change with gr e ater industri a l i z at i o n .T h e s e
disputes are generally in the form of diplomat i c
c o n t r ove rs i e s , although sometimes more dramat i c
c o n f r o n t ations ari s e .E ve ry transborder water resource
is coveted by the countries that share the resource.
They carefully monitor the amounts used by
n e i g h b o u rs.
Markets are now much in vogue as ideal
institutions for resolving disputes over control of
water resources and for managing the use of those
resources effic i e n t l y. B a s i c a l l y, the aim is to set up a
trading system by which wat e r - rich countries sell
supplies to those in need. T h e o r e t i c a l l y, m a r k e t s
ensure effic i e n cy and peace. C o u n t ries don’t dare
waste a resource for which they have paid dearly. A t
the same time, the market supposedly helps resolve
water disputes: if one country infringes on the
“ p r o p e rt y ” of another, c o m p e n s ation can be sought
in a court .
A resource with no respect
for borders
Twenty ye a rs ago, few experts or policy - m a k e rs
would have considered such a proposal seri o u s l y.
To d ay, the concept is gaining ground thanks to the
a c t i ve promotion of major lending institutions like the
World Bank and other multinational organizat i o n s.
Pa rt of the enthusiasm deri ves from the triumph of
We s t e rn-style free markets and the assumption that
there are no credible altern at i ves for efficiently
m a n a ging resources. But the market support e rs
overlook a critical fa c t : wat e r , unlike eve ry other
n atural resource except the air we breat h e , is ambient.
It move s. It doesn’t respect borders and so cannot be
controlled by any single entity.Yet for a market to
wo r k , clear ow n e rship rights have to be recognized
before any good can be traded. But how can yo u
d e t e rmine who owns a resource which ebbs and
swells as it moves from one country to the next?
True water markets have rarely existed in the
p a s t , and there is little reason to believe they will in
the future.A curs o ry look at the case of the Nile Va l l e y
highlights the limitations of market-approaches.
The Blue Nile flows from Ethiopia to Sudan and
on to Egypt. As is commonly the case, countries
lower down the basin tend to be richer and more
developed than those further up. This is because
small rivers and streams feed into the river as it
flows, bringing water and nutrients that leave the
lower basin more fertile. Furthermore, the lower
basin generally is relat i vely flat , while the upper
basin generally is mountainous, making agri c u l t u r a l
d e velopment easier in the lower basin. I n d e e d ,
Egypt,with a per capita gross domestic product of
$ 6 3 0 / ye a r , is wealthier than Sudan (GDP
$ 5 4 0 / ye a r ) , and both countries are far more afflu e n t
than upstream Ethiopia (GDP $120/year).
Nevertheless,Ethiopia does get the water first.
One might think, t h e r e f o r e , t h at the Ethiopian
government is in a position of strength and can do
what it wants with the Blue Nile. It could build a
Four international rivers
The Jordan
The river: The 93-km-long Jordan drains part of the
territories of Israel,Jordan,Lebanon and Syria,four of the
states most involved in regional hostilities in the last half
century. It rises in four tributaries, the Yarmouk in Syria,the
Banias in the Israeli-occupied Golan Heights, the Hasbani in
I s raeli-occupied southern Lebanon, and the Dan in Isra e l .B y
virtue of the 1967 war and the “security zone”created in
south Lebanon in the early 1980s, I s rael is the upstream
riparian on the upper Jordan system;Syria is upstream on
the Yarmouk.
P roblems and pro s p e c t s : Jordan and the Pa l e s t i n i a n s,
as downstream riparians of Israel and Syria, are in the worst
position in the basin. J o r d a n ’s dependence on the river
system is particularly great, since apart from a few w a d i s—
watercourses that are dry except in the rainy season—it
has no other important sources of fresh wa t e r. Th r e e
attempts have been made to establish an international
water management regime (in 1953-55, 1 9 7 6 - 8 1 , a n d
1987-90) but each came to a halt because of an inability
to include all riparian states in the proposed arra n g e m e n t .
A water resources working group was set up as part of the
Middle East peace process in 1995 and 1996, but wa t e r
politics specialist Miriam R. Lowi of the Center of
International Studies at Princeton University notes that
“the implementation of a water agreement will not be
effected until the political conflict has reached closure.”
Four international rivers
The Nile
The river:The Nile is 6,700 km long from its most distant
source to its mouth in the Mediterranean,and drains one-
tenth of the African continent.The river system is composed
of two major tributaries, the White Nile and the Blue Nile,
which rise in Lake Victoria (Ke n ya , R wa n d a , Ta n z a n i a ,
Uganda) and Lake Tana (Ethiopia), r e s p e c t i v e l y. The nine
nations of the Nile basin are Rwa n d a , B u r u n d i , t h e
D e m o c ratic Republic of the Congo, Ta n z a n i a , Ke n ya ,
Uganda,Ethiopia,Sudan and Egypt.
P roblems and pro s p e c t s : The vast majority of the river’s
flo w, estimated at 84 billion m3 a n n u a l l y, is used by Egypt,
by virtue of a 1959 treaty between Egypt and Sudan which
allocates to the two countries an amount of Nile wa t e r
that adds up to nearly 90% of the river’s annual flow.
Upstream nations such as Ethiopia want to harness the
N i l e ’s waters to provide economic prosperity for their
growing population and are challenging Egyptian and
Sudanese claims.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 35
What price water?
dam, for example, or develop irrigation systems.
Ethiopia, however, is too poor to pay for this kind
of infrastructure on its ow n .E g y p t , which fears any
interference that might interfere with the flows of
water down the Blue Nile,has succeeded in using
its political clout within multilateral lending
o r g a n i z ations like the World Bank to block Ethiopia’s
applications for financial assistance to exploit the
ri ve r. (The situation may be changi n g, h owe ve r ,a s
the Egyptian gove rnment recently let pass an
Ethiopian loan application with the World Bank
for a small-scale irrigation project.)
Who owns what?
U l t i m at e l y, Egypt claims an absolute right to the
integrity of the river. According to this principle,
Ethiopia should do nothing that might affect the
quantity and quality of water currently flowing to
Egypt. But such a claim deprives Ethiopia of any
means of developing its agriculture and condemns
the country to continued dependence on
international food aid to stave off mass starvation.
Imagine that Egypt and Ethiopia decide to set
up a water market. How would they resolve their
differences? Ethiopia in theory could buy the right
to develop the ri ver from Egypt, although in practice
the price of such a right is likely to be much higher
than it could afford. Or Egypt could compensate
Ethiopia for foregoing the Blue Nile’s
development—another unlikely scenario because
Egypt considers that it already “ ow n s ” the wat e rs it
uses.
The major flaw in any market “solution”is the
failure to determine clearly who owns what.There
are groups of water experts and policy-makers in
Israel and Jo r d a n , for example, who would like to set
up a water trade in the regi o n . On the one hand, t h e
Israelis,who control the source of the vital Jordan
River,say that Palestinians should buy water from
t h e m .And on the other, Palestinians insist that the
Israelis stole the water from them and should now
pay for it.
L e t ’s imagine that two countries did manage to
c l a rify any ow n e rship disputes and began trading in
wat e r.W h at about third parties further dow n s t r e a m ?
Water isn’t like mineral resources. Russia can mine
coal and sell it around the world and neighbouri n g
c o u n t ries barely notice. But try selling part of a
ri ver from one region to the next without
downstream neighbours causing an uproar.
For years, the Turks have discussed a proposal
to sell water from the Euphrates to Israel. About 98
per cent of that river’s flow comes from rain and
s n ow on Tu r k e y, which has built one of A s i a ’s largest
dams to capture and control these wat e rs. H owe ve r ,
the Turkish gove rnment doesn’t have the money to
build all the infrastructure needed to use the wat e r
for ir rigation in Turkey. The Turks could sell the
water to Israel or various Arab nations by building
a pipeline across Syria to the Jordan Valley or the
Arabian peninsula. Perhaps a more realistic option
would be to pipe the water to Tu r k e y ’s
Mediterranean coast and then ship it by tanker.
Claims
and counterclaims
Such a deal would have serious repercussions for
Iraq and Syria, Turkey’s downstream neighbours,
who depend on the Euphrat e s. I m a gine that Tu r k e y
did use the dam’s reservoir for irri g at i o n .
D ownstream nations would still reap benefits
because much of the water used would still reach
t h e m . Run-off from irri g ated fields would feed back
into the river, and the water that evaporates in the
r e s e rvoir and the fields would eventually return
through the water cy c l e . But by shipping Euphrat e s
water outside the va l l e y, the Turks cut off these
b e n e fit s.The only option available to Iraq and Syri a
would be to buy the water to which they feel a
natural right. In my opinion, the solution to
water scarcity lies not in building water markets bu t
in consolidating the rules for sharing found in
customary international law.To better understand
the concept of customary law, consider an analogy.
Suppose there is a field between two villages.
G r a d u a l l y, most people going from one village to the
other come to follow a particular line across the fie l d ,
perhaps the shortest or easiest route.Their numbers
wear a path into the landscape which becomes a
r o a d .E ve n t u a l l y, all agree that this road is the only P
The solution to water scarcity lies not 
in building water markets but in consolidating 
the rules for sharing found in customary
international law
Aerial view of Turkey’s Ataturk
dam on the Euphrates.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
On a carpet of
flowe rs on the bank
of the Nile we
s t a ye d ; the wa ve s
t ra n s fo rmed it into
a face full of
w ri n k l e s.
Baha al-Din Zuhayr 
(d.1258),Egypt
right way between the villages even though no one
can say precisely when this notion took hold.At that
point, people consider those who take a different
p ath as trespassers.And so we find a legal norm and
not merely a factual description of a path.
To d ay there is a well developed body of
c u s t o m a ry intern ational law that gove rns the ri g h t s
of nations in intern ationally shared sources of fresh
wat e r.T h at body of law develops through a process
of claim and counterclaim, with the nations making
the claims appealing to legal rules to establish their
ri g h t s. All nations agree that only ri p a rian nat i o n s —
n ations across which, or along which, a ri ver flow s —
h ave any legal ri g h t ,a p a rt from an agr e e m e n t , to use
the water of a ri ve r. B e yond that ,h owe ve r , there are
t wo types of intern ational claim.The upper-ri p a ri a n
n ations initially base their claims on a b s o l u t e
t e rri t o rial sove r e i g n t y, typically claiming the right to
do whatever they choose with the water regardless
of its effect on other ri p a rian nat i o n s. D ow n s t r e a m
n at i o n s , on the other hand, generally make a claim
to the absolute integrity of the ri ve r, insisting that
upper-riparian nations can do nothing that affects
the quantity or quality of water flowing.
Equitable utilization
The usual solution to these contradictory claims
is found in a concept known as equitable utilizat i o n :
each ri p a rian nation recognizes the right of the
others to use water from a common source.At the
same time, there is an obligation to ensure that the
way in which one ri p a rian nation uses water does not
unreasonably interfere with similar uses of other
nations further downstream.Under this principle,
c o u n t ries usually decide on how much water is
a l l o c ated to one state or another by looking for
some more or less objective standard such as histori c
p at t e rns of use or the amount of land that could be
i rri g ated in each nat i o n .They also take into account
“ o b j e c t i ve ” fa c t o rs , like the need for more water for
growing populations.
C u s t o m a ry law does something that the market
c a n n o t : it recognizes the unique nature of wat e r. I n s t e a d
of trying to determine who “ ow n s ”w h at proportion of
a river, it lays down a set of rules for sharing.
Of cours e , there are at least two problems with this
kind of informal law.To begin with, the principle is too
vague to determine a nat i o n ’s “ fa i r ” s h a r e . S e c o n d ,
there is no neutral way of enforcing the ru l e s. So when
a violation occurs,the only recourse often available is
the law of the vendetta.
But these problems are just part of the nat u r a l
course of developing any form of customary law. At
some point, rules have to be set down on paper and
c o d i fie d .I n d e e d ,n ations have hammered out hundreds
of agreements in the attempt to define what constitutes
fair sharing of a particular wat e r way.The intern at i o n a l
community took a major leap forward about a ye a r
and a half ago by approving the United Nat i o n s
C o nvention on the Non-Nav i g ational Uses of
I n t e rn ational Wat e r c o u rses by a vote of 104 to three. I t
will unquestionably be the leading law gove rn i n g
i n t e rn ationally shared fresh wat e rs once it is rat i fied by
35 nations—a process that could take a decade or
more.The convention provides a set of standards in
codifying the rule of equitable utilization based on a long
list of dive rse fa c t o rs—from geographic and ecologi c a l
considerations to the economic value of existing and
potential uses of the wat e r way. The aim is to help
arbitrators and judges determine “equitable”sharing,
which should not be confused with equal shares.
The convention is a legal document, not a magic
f o rm u l a . Disputes will continue. But instead of resort i n g
to the law of the vendetta, nations can now seek legal
r e s o l u t i o n .The rule of equitable utilization can also serve
to channel the negotiations between ri p a rian neighbours
should they prefer to resolve the matter by treaty rat h e r
than by arbitration or litigation.
The convention reflects not only logi c, but need and
power—which amounts to a far more balanced and
s o p h i s t i c ated approach to managing water than simply
relying on a free market. n
Four international rivers
The Mekong
The river: From its source in the Himalayan peaks of Ti b e t , the Mekong flows for 4,200 km
through China’s Yunnan province (population 38 million) and through Myanmar, Laos,Thailand,
Cambodia and Viet Nam, countries populated by around 190 million people, many of them poor.
P roblems and pro s p e c t s : The river flows through an area which has been at war for much of
the century. Regional institutions including the Mekong River Commission (Cambodia, Vi e t
N a m , Laos and Thailand) are working to turn the Mekong into a “channel of commerce and
p r o s p e r i t y — A s i a ’s Danube”, by exploiting possibilities for mutual benefit and opening up a va s t
new market in this region where cross-border links are often rudimentary. Finance is proving to
be a major challenge, h o w e v e r. Some dam schemes to generate hydropower alarm
environmentalists who warn of problems ranging from the intrusion of salt water into the delta
to loss of rare species.China is building a dam in Yunnan from which electricity may be sent across
Laos to Th a i l a n d . It claims that the project will help river flow and benefit downstream nations,
but there are anxieties among low-lying countries because of the upstream dam’s capacity to
radically alter the river’s flo w, which would disrupt ecological balances.
Four international rivers
The Danube
The river: The Danube is Europe’s second largest river,
with a watershed area of 817,000 km3 in seventeen
c o u n t r i e s. The main channel of the river flows through
Germany, Austria,Slovakia, Croatia,Hungary, Yugoslavia,
Bulgaria,Romania.
P roblems and pro s p e c t s : Pollution by nitrogen and
phosphorus from agriculture, and toxic substances from
industries and cities. Hungary and Slovakia are still divided
by a long-running dispute over the Gabcikovo-Nagymaros
dam project that was referred to the International Court of
Justice in The Hague. In 1997 the court ruled that both
countries were at fault—Hungary when it cancelled work
on the project in 1989 and withdrew unilaterally from a
1977 bilateral agreement, S l o vakia by diverting the Danube
onto its territory without attempting to work out the
disagreement with Hungary.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
R a c ke t e e rs are trying to make a pro fit out of couples in rich countries who want 
to adopt orphan children from the developing world. Tw e n t y - five nations have
now agreed to follow a code of conduct governing international adoption
n
T h e y ’re in love .They live comfort a b l y
somewhere in the “ first wo r l d ” . O n e
d ay, they decide to have children. But the
months and ye a rs go by without any “ h a p p y
e ve n t ” . In the end, they go to a fert i l i t y
e x p e rt .But fertility treatment doesn’t alway s
work and eventually becomes ve ry distressing
for the couple, who feel wounded because
they can’t fulfil their reproductive instincts.
As they become more and more deeply
involved in medical treatment, the idea of
adopting a child takes root.Why not open
their lives to an unloved baby or youngster
who has been abandoned and dumped in an
orphanage? After all,the couple has lots of
love to give and the means to bring up a
family.
Since contraception became common
and abortion tolerated in the world’s rich
c o u n t ri e s , abandoned children, young or
o l d e r ,h ave become few and far betwe e n .A t
the same time, m a ny more people, b o t h
couples and single persons, are seeking to
a d o p t . As a result, adoption of children
from poor countries by couples from the
N o rth has soared over the past 20 ye a rs
(see box).
Long and tricky
negotiations
With few exceptions, the process of
adopting a foreign baby is a long and
complex one, i nvolving talks with social
wo r k e rs ,d o c t o rs and psychiat ri s t s. A lot of
p a p e r work has to be done before consent is
given. In most cases, the process is just as
c o m p l i c ated in the child’s country of ori gi n ,
and the rules vary widely from country to
c o u n t ry. “ I t ’s like an obstacle race,” s ay
parents who have been through it.
Yet scandals regularly come to light,
mainly because dubious go-betweens in
some poor countries take advantage of the
rising demand for adopted children to relieve
we a l t hy couples, tired of waiting for offspri n g
of their ow n , of huge sums, sometimes as
much as $60,000. Wo rst of all, t h e s e
r a c k e t e e rs manage to trick needy mothers
into parting with their biological children.
The case of young Pablo in Guatemala
helped to raise international concern. He
spent the first year of his life in an orp h a n a g e
while his fate provoked a legal battle. His
n atural mother, 3 0 - year-old Elvira Ramirez
C a ñ o, had gi ven her written consent for
his adoption by a Spanish couple. But she
claimed she had signed some kind of
document in a moment of distress eve n
before the child was born , because her
husband had left her when he found out she
was pregnant.
The Spanish couple’s lawyer paid her
m o ne y. But Guatemalan law allows a mother
to renege on such an agr e e m e n t , and with the
backing of a charitable assoc i at i o n , C a z a
Alianza,Elvira managed to get baby Pablo P
A d o p t i o n :
for love or m o n e y?
Heart and home
n
In the United Stat e s , 13,621 foreign
children were adopted by A m e ri c a n
parents in 1997, twice as many as 20 ye a rs
e a r l i e r , according to official figures. T h e
children were mostly born in Russia (3,816),
China (3,597), South Korea (1,654),
G u atemala (788) and Romania (621).
France comes second after the United
States among the so-called host countries.
A total of 3,528 children from 70 countri e s
were adopted by French parents in 1997,
compared with 971 from 10 countries in
1979.Nearly half the children adopted by
French parents come from Viet Nam,
f o l l owed by Colombia,M a d a g a s c a r ,R u s s i a ,
B r a z i l ,G u at e m a l a ,R o m a n i a ,B u l g a ria and
Ethiopia.
The geogr a p hy of intern ational adoption
va ries considerably, sometimes from one
year to the next. South Korea, for example
(which provided 66 per cent of foreign
adoptions in France in 1979), s h a rp l y
r e s t ricted foreign adoptions after the Seoul
Olympic Games in 1988. As in India and
China,prospective parents now have to go
through a recognized organization.
In China, where intercountry adoption
only began in 1991, the rules were eased last
year to gi ve relief to orp h a n a g e s
overcrowded with little girls—the Chinese
are only allowed to have one child if they live
in a city and two if they live in the
c o u n t ry s i d e . In Romania, a large number of
o rphans were adopted after the fall of
Ceausescu in 1989, but ve ry strict ru l e s
h ave now been introduced. In most Muslim
s t at e s , adoption is impossible, either for
local citizens or foreigners. n
The Pablo affair shows the
kind of pressures and
manoeuvres that are typical
of lawyers and people paid
to find babies for adoption.
They always go for mothers
who are poor and illiterate.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
E T H I C S
back in August 1998, not long after his firs t
b i rt h d ay. This was the first time a
G u atemalan court had ever returned a child
to its natural mother after a dubious
adoption.
“The Pablo affair shows the kind of
pressures and manoeuvres that are typical
of law ye rs and people paid to find babies for
a d o p t i o n .They always go for mothers who
are poor and illiterat e ,” s ay officials of Caza
A l i a n z a , whose law ye rs are handling the
cases of 17 other such mothers. T h e
a s s o c i ation reckons that about 440 children
h ave been fraudulently adopted in
G u atemala since 1996, a year which saw the
end of a 36-year civil war in which more
than 100,000 people died.
Guatemala,
a crackdown on racketeers
Not many countries have such simple
adoption procedures as this poor Central
A m e rican stat e . A notary obtains the
consent of one or other of the child’s
b i o l o gical parents, and then law ye rs acting
for the adoptive parents present this
document and a social report to a juvenile
c o u rt judge who decides whether or not
the adoption can go ahead. In the case of
o rphans and abandoned children, the judge
has to certify first that their parents have
vanished or are unknown. In each case, a
lawyer is necessary.
So Guatemala has become a favourite
d e s t i n ation of  We s t e rn couples looking 
for a foreign child to adopt.The number 
of requests received rose from 900 in 
1996 to 2,304 in 1997,most of them from
A m e ri c a n s ,French and Canadians. O f fic i a l s
in all three countries have stepped up their
wa rnings about the risks of adopting
Guatemalan children.
“Lawyers seem to be in collusion with
d o c t o rs , n u rses and social wo r k e rs who
pressure mothers to let go of their children.
They are then placed with foster mothers
k n own to the law ye rs in ‘ c l a n d e s t i n e
o rp h a n a g e s ’ ,” s ays the Intern at i o n a l
Adoption Mission, France’s official body
responsible for monitoring the arri val of
adopted children in France.
Compulsory
DNA tests
The Canadian consulate in Guat e m a l a
City has uncovered another racket, e ve n
wo rs e .S e veral mothers who gave adoption
consent to a judge were found not to be
“ t h e i r ” c h i l d ’s natural mother after
undergoing DNA tests. The babies had
been taken from their real mothers at birt h
in the countryside by women who we r e
paid to say it was they who had given birth
to them.
Canada now requires DNA tests to be
Open arms for a child with 
an uncertain future.
Lawyers seem to be in
collusion with doctors,
nurses and social workers
who pressure mothers to let
go of their children. They
are then placed with foster
mothers known to the
lawyers in ‘clandestine
orphanages’
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
carried out by accredited doctors on the
m o t h e rs of all adopted babies from
G u atemala before the children are allowe d
into the country. The United Stat e s
announced in October 1998 that it would
do the same.The Guatemalan authorities
h ave called on local judges to be more
v i gilant until stricter legi s l ation is passed by
parliament.
In Brazil, where rules for foreigners
adopting children are very strict on paper,
94 women demonstrate regularly in the
t own of Jundiai, near São Pa u l o.A p a rt from
the fact that they are all poor,they have all
had their children taken away from them by
a judge who sent them to a centre which
works hand in glove with an Italian adoption
o r g a n i z at i o n . An enquiry is going on. I n
Viet Nam, t a x i - d ri ve rs , hotel managers and
travel agents openly offer, illegally and for
m o n e y, “ g u i d a n c e ” for We s t e rn parents
seeking to adopt.
Scandals like these, and others that
came to light in Eastern Europe, A f ri c a
and A s i a , helped to convince the
international community of the need for a
legal instrument to establish principles for
i n t e r c o u n t ry adoption.The Convention on
the Protection of Children and Co-
o p e r ation in Respect of Intercountry
Adoption was signed in The Hague in 1993
and came into effect two years later.
Respect 
for the child’s origins
The Convention bans any “ i m p r o p e r
financial or other gain” and “the abduction,
the sale of, or traffic in children” and obliges
each signat o ry state to establish maximum
safeguards to prevent it. So fa r , 21 countri e s
h ave ratified the Conve n t i o n ,1 i n c l u d i n g
Colombia, France and Australia in 1998,
and four others have acceded to it.
In practice,anyone wanting to adopt a
child must make a formal applicat i o n ,e i t h e r
directly or through an NGO of their choice,
to the “central authori t y ” of their ow n
c o u n t ry, which will send the request to the
central authority of the country in which the
applicants wish to adopt a child. T h i s
measure has already reduced the number of
clandestine adoptions between contracting
countries. Before the request is sent to the
foreign country, the adopting country is
Ukrainian
educators win
UNESCO peace
education award
The UNESCO prize for peace education, which
was created in 1980 thanks to a gift from the
Japan Shipbuilding Industry Fo u n d a t i o n , i s
a warded each year in recognition of efforts to
mobilize public support for peace. Educators for
Peace and Mutual Understanding, a Ukra i n i a n
non-governmental organization, won the 1998
p r i z e, comprising a statuette symbolizing peace by
the Spanish sculptor Fenosa and a cheque for
$ 2 5 , 0 0 0 . The award ceremony was held at
UN E S C O’s Paris Headquarters on 15 December
1998.
Educators for Peace and Mutual Understanding
t rains teachers at all levels to spread the ideals of
peace, human rights and the rights of the child.
Founded in Kiev in 1990, this voluntary
association independent of religious or political
affiliations brings together 170 educational
institutions (clubs, centres and other public
bodies) dedicated to helping people live in
harmony with nature, with others and with
themselves.
The NGO organizes conferences, s e m i n a r s,
workshops, publications, ecological expeditions,
visits and exchanges of teachers and pupils.
Hundreds of educators have taken courses at its
university of peace studies and tra i n i n g . One of its
latest international projects,Youth Collabora t i o n ,
organized with the city of Munich, helps young
people deal with problems of social adaptation in
the urban environment.An e-mail scheme twins
schools in Ukraine, the UK and Florida.
Three other non-governmental organizations
received honourable mentions: the Fr i d t j o f
Nansen Academy (Norway),which is promoting
peace education in Ko s o v o ; the World Court
Project in New Zealand,which has launched an
international campaign against nuclear
a r m a m e n t ; and an Israeli language school, U l p a n
A k i va Netanya , which is helping to promote
mutual understanding by its work in teaching
Hebrew and Arabic. n
required to check whether the prospective
parents are “eligible and suited to adopt”
according to the laws and procedures of
both countries involved.
The convention also forbids any
“contact between the prospective adoptive
parents and the child’s parents” until all
the requirements have been met. T h e
authorities of the child’s country of origin
must ensure that the consent of the
b i o l o gical mother (and father if he is
identified) has been “freely given”and has
“not been induced by payment or
compensation of any kind.”
The convention also stipulat e s — l i k e
the 1989 United Nations Convention on the
Rights of the Child—that foreigners can
only adopt a child if foster parents have
not been found in its own country and if
it is “in the best interests of the child”,
whose origins must be respected as far as
possible.
In the same spiri t , s e veral countri e s
require foreign prospective parents, or the
social services of the adopting country, to
make regular reports on the child’s progr e s s
to its country of ori gi n . This “ f o l l ow - u p
p e ri o d ” is 10 ye a rs in the case of Sri Lanka,
four for Pe ru , three for Pa r a g u ay and two for
Romania.
The gr owth of intercountry adoption
has often led to more child adoptions within
the country of ori gi n . In Pe ru , t h e
a u t h o rities have mounted local media
campaigns to ensure that abandoned
children are “ o f f e r e d ” for adoption to
Peruvian couples as a first choice. “Many
mothers come to us because they want to
gi ve up a child they can no longer afford to
b ring up,” s ays a Pe ruvian adoption offic i a l
who asked not to be named.“We do all we
can to dissuade them and help them. But
h e r e , as eve rywhere else, the first thing to do
is to stem the tide of poverty.” n
Martine Jacot
‘Many mothers come to us because they want 
to give up a child they can no longer afford to bring up.
We do all we can to dissuade them and help them.
But here, as everywhere else, the first thing to do 
is to stem the tide of poverty’
1.The Convention so far includes 15 countries
where children are sought for adoption (Burkina
Faso, Cyprus, Colombia,Costa Rica, Ecuador,
Lithuania, Mexico, Moldova, Paraguay, Peru, the
Philippines, Poland,Romania, Sri Lanka and
Venezuela) and 10 countries whose nationals
adopt them (Andorra,Australia,Canada,
Denmark, Spain,France, Finland,Norway, the
Netherlands and Sweden).
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
Children are being told the facts of life 
by a new wave of authors, but there’s still plenty of room
for Prince Charming, fairies and witches.
C h i l d re n ’s books 
n
For ye a rs children’s literature wa s
the Cinderella of literat u r e ,
languishing in the shadow of a
cantankerous stepmother. To d ay the
maiden is ready to go to the ball.
Didacticism and and moralizing are
fading away into the past and writing for
children is becoming an art - f o rm in its
own ri g h t , a genre whose borders now
stretch far beyond the classroom, t h e
l i b r a ry or the nurs e ry. Book production
for young people has also become an
i n d u s t ry which is attracting more and
more attention in the shape of
c o n f e r e n c e s , p ri z e s , book fa i rs and
u n i ve rsity theses all over the wo r l d .
“A children’s book isn’t a schoolbook
a ny longer,” s ays Leena Maissen, head of the
Swiss-based Intern ational Board on Books
for Young People (IBBY), whose offices 
in 60 countries are trying to make more
literature and art available to the world’s
children.
“Books for children are cert a i n l y
valuable teaching aids, and they’re especially
useful for giving children a taste for reading.
But new trends are coming in. Taboos are
being broken, children are being taken
s e riously and being treated like real people,
and long-avoided subjects are being
tackled.”
Fa i ry stories still have a place, of cours e .
Children still dream about witches, bears,
p rincesses and elve s , but in a different way.
Colombian writer Gloria Cecilia Díaz say s
t h at in children’s books these day s , “ t h e
world isn’t always seen through rose-
coloured spectacles. For many people,
talking to children meant using diminutive s ,
talking about little houses and little gi r l s ,a n d
avoiding subjects like disease, violence and
death.”
Manuel Peña Muñoz, a Chilean author
of children’s books, a gr e e s. “Some teachers
think they’ve covered children’s literature
once they’ve told the story of Snow White
and the Seven Dwarfs,” she says. “What’s
m o r e , some authors simply tell stories about
princesses and gnomes,add a bit of moral
icing to the cake, and that ’s it. But that ’s not
enough,these days.”
The illustrator’s
magic wand
A number of recent books have
r e worked subjects, f o rms and narr at i ve
t e c h n i q u e s. To d ay ’s children read stori e s
about divorce, death, drugs, air pollution,
political extremism, violence and racism.
And all kinds of books are being published
which rely on the magic wand of the
illustrator or cartoonist.
Before they know how to read, babies
can play with books made of fa b ric or books
made to take in the bat h .L ater on, they are
given picture books that may be cubical or
triangular, outsized or miniature, possibly
b i l i n g u a l .They also like work-books which
come with wat e r c o l o u rs and paintbru s h e s ,
and comic books crammed with detail
where they have to spot a figure hidden
among thousands of others.
Not that the traditional children’s book
is being sidelined.There are still story b o o k s
where the pages pop up when they are
o p e n e d , to make a forest or a castle.A m o n g
the latest ideas are interactive 
s t o ries where readers choose the plot or
ending they wa n t , and books on CD-Rom,
which are ve ry popular in rich industri a l i z e d
c o u n t ri e s.
The public has enthusiastically gr e e t e d
the wealth of ingenuity displayed by
p u b l i s h e rs. “ P r e v i o u s l y, giving a child a
book was almost seen as an insult,” s ay s
To l e ra n c e told to children
Every two years UNESCO awards a Prize for
C h i l d r e n ’s and Young Pe o p l e ’s Literature in
the Service of To l e ra n c e. The 1999 laureates,
selected by an international jury, are the Ghanaian
writer Meshack Asare and American author A n n e
R.Blakeslee, who died recently.
B l a ke s l e e ’s novel A Different Kind of Hero,
which came top in the category of books for
young people aged 13 to 18,is the story of a
boy who teaches his father to show tolera n c e
t o wards “ f o r e i g n e r s ” who arrive in a
C o l o rado mining camp in the 1880s.
Meshack A s a r e ’s Sosu’s Call, which is
i l l u s t rated by the author, tells how a
disabled boy wins the respect of everyone
in his village by saving it from flooding.
The prizewinning works, which were
chosen from more than 300 books by authors
from 42 countries will receive the award (a
diploma and $8,000 donated by the Fundación
Santa María/Ediciones S. M . of Spain) at a
ceremony which will be held in April during the
Bologna Children’s Book Fair (Italy). n
Sosu’s Call, written and illustrated by Meshack
Asare, is published in Ghana by Sub-Saharan
Publishers.
A Different Kind of Hero , by Anne R.Blakeslee, is
published in the United States by Marshall Cavendish.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 41
come of age
Canadian author Marie-France Hébert .
Her books, published by the French-
language Quebec publisher La Court e
Échelle, sell like hot cakes, in hundreds of
thousands of copies.“ T h e r e ’s a real appetite
for reading these days and I try to get across
to children the passion for reading which is
food for the mind and the heart , like a
medicine or a vitamin.”
Updating
traditional tales
Robert hates maths—he can’t make
head or tail of it. But one night he dreams
of meeting a sharp-tongued little goblin
who promises to teach him all about it.Of
course, he thinks it’s just another bad
dream. But actually he’s being taken on
an exciting journey into the world of
m aths by The Number Devil, a book
published in 1997 by the German poet
and essayist Hans Magnus Enzensberger,
one of a growing band of authors who are
writing these days for children as well as
adults.
Morocco’s Tahar Ben Jelloun (Racism
Explained to My Daughter) , Spanish wri t e rs
Fe rnando Savater (A Father Addresses his
Son on Questions of Ethics) and Carm e n
M a rtín Gaite (“Little Red Riding Hood in
M a n h at t a n ” ) , Chilean Luis Sepúlve d a
(“The Story of the Seagull and the Cat
who Taught him to Fly”) and A u s t ri a ’s
Pat rick Suskind have all updated traditional
s t o ries or tackled topics like racism and
ecology.
The Cuban writer Joel Franz Rosell
s ays this renewal of children’s literature is
p a rtly because school programmes have
been revamped to include modern wo r k s.
“ P u b l i s h e rs see an enormous market here
and are ve ry keen to profit from it,” h e
s ay s. “The thing about the market for
c h i l d r e n ’s books is that children don’t bu y
the books themselve s , someone else does—
p a r e n t s , t e a c h e rs or librari a n s. The child
d o e s n ’t know or care whether there’s an
a u t h o r. Some researchers have eve n
d e s c ribed children’s literature as texts
without authors. But parents are amazed by
the fact that their children can read authors
t h at they like too.”
Some authors say they don’t sw i t c h
styles when they write for children. O t h e rs ,
such as Jasmine Dubé, from Quebec, say
they write in a totally different way.“ W h e n
I write for adults,” she says,“I feel like I’ve
got less spirit, that it’s more cerebral, that
I’m censoring myself more. I don’t gi ve
such a free rein to my imagi n ation and I’m
less direct. I think other wri t e rs do it much
better than me. But when I write for
c h i l d r e n , all my passion and urgency
return.”
C h i l d r e n ’s literature is not deve l o p i n g
at the same speed eve rywhere in the wo r l d .
“In some places, like India, books are still
w ritten for children in a ve ry traditional
way and change is ve ry slow in coming,”
s ays Maissen. Yet from India sprang the
f i rs t - e ver children’s book more than 2,000
ye a rs ago—a collection of tales called the
Pa n c h at ra n t a. The country, which has 18
official languages and more than 1,600
d i a l e c t s , publishes books for children which
mostly draw on tales, legends and heroic
past eras.
The most daring publishers and authors
are in We s t e rn Europe. In Eastern Europe,
the new market economy leaves little room
for quality books. “The Czechs, S l ova k s
and Russians used to be top of the league for
children’s books,” says Maissen.“But the
economic crisis has pushed their highly
c r e at i ve people into illustrating books
published in the West.”
Between books 
and television
Books for children and teenagers have
a healthy share of the market. F i g u r e s
available at the 1998 Frankfurt Book Fa i r
s h owed that 7.5 per cent of the 78,000
books published in Germ a ny in 1997 we r e
for children, a percentage which has
remained steady over the past few ye a rs. I n
F r a n c e , c h i l d r e n ’s books have held up
better than other titles in the publishing
c risis which began in the early 1990s, a n d
in 1997 represented 8.3 per cent of all
s a l e s. In Brazil, 31 per cent of books
published in 1997 (including some
schoolbooks) were written for children.
But such figures should not hide the
fact that reading is competing with
t e l e v i s i o n , films and electronic media,w h o s e
audience is gr owing faster than book
r e a d e rs h i p. A UN E S C O-sponsored surve y
carried out in 1995 by Utrecht University,
in The Netherlands, s h owed that in regi o n s
where there was electricity, 93 per cent of P
‘Some teachers think they’ve covered children’s literature
once they’ve told the story of Snow White and the Seven
Dwarfs. What’s more, some authors simply tell stories
about princesses and gnomes, add a bit of moral icing to
the cake, and that’s it. But that’s not enough, these days.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Fa i rs and prizes g a l o r e
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
Rock art:
a call
for co-opera t i o n
In co-operation with UN E S C O’s International
Council for Philosophy and Humanistic
S t u d i e s, the Camuno centre of historical studies
at Valcamonica (Italy) has launched a three-
year project to list the world’s most important
sites of rock art.
The World Archives of Rock Art (WA R A )
project,which has a $60,000 budget,involves
updating and monitoring data from some 70
c o u n t r i e s. A CD-Rom and a world atlas
containing a selection of 150 sites are also
planned.
Chosen for their aesthetic value and historical
or ethnological interest, the sites are spread out
over eight geographical areas: A s i a , the Near
E a s t , northern A f r i c a , southern A f r i c a , E u r o p e,
North A m e r i c a ,C e n t ral and South A m e r i c a ,a n d
O c e a n i a . Each site will be presented by a
description (including location, t y p e, f e a t u r e s,
d a t e, state of preservation and the state of
r e s e a r c h ) , p h o t o g ra p h s, d rawings and a
b i b l i o g ra p h y.
WARA follows up on an earlier world report
on rock art, the first of its kind, which wa s
submitted to UN E S C O in 1982. The project is
open to specialists and institutions from any
country wishing to participate.
The Valacamonica centre is also offering
three-month internships on prehistoric and
tribal art at which students and scholars can
acquire hands-on experience in research, the
management of cultural property, p u b l i c
relations, the organization of exhibitions and
symposia,translation and publishing. n
For further information contact:
Centro camuno di studi preistorici,
25044 Capo di Ponte
(BS) Italia.
Tel: 39-364 42 091.
Fax: 39-364 42 572.
n Just like books for adults,c h i l d r e n ’s books
h ave their own pri z e s , fa i rs and cri t i c s.T h e
most important specialized body in this fie l d
is the Intern ational Board on Books for Yo u n g
People (IBBY), which was founded in 1953.
It promotes children’s books, publishes a
q u a rterly review B o o k b i r d,d r aws up a biennial
List of Honour of the wo r l d ’s best children’s
b o o k s , and eve ry two ye a rs awards Hans
C h ristian A n d e rsen Prizes to an author and
an illustrat o r.The pri z e s , which carry so much
prestige in the world of children’s literat u r e
t h at they have been called “little Nobel
P ri z e s ” , h ave been won by such authors as
A s t rid Lindgren (Swe d e n , 1958) and Gianni
R o d a ri (Italy,1 9 9 6 ) .The 1998 winners we r e
A m e rican writer Kat h e rine Pat e rson and
French illustrator Tomi Ungerer.
A u t h o rs and publishers of children’s
books also get together at major
i n t e rn ational gat h e ri n g s.The Bologna (Italy)
I n t e rn ational Fair is to children’s literat u r e
w h at the Frankfurt Book Fair (held annually
in October) is to books for adults. T h i s
year’s Bologna Fair,to be held from 1 to 8
A p ri l , is expected to attract 1,400 exhibitors
from 80 countries and some 20,000 visitors.
In addition to the Bologna Fair, there are
specialized fa i rs at Montreuil, on the
outskirts of Paris, and at Mexico City and
Nairobi.
In Spain, the Salamanca-based
Fundación Germán Sánchez Ruipérez is
an Intern ational Centre for Children’s and
Young Pe o p l e ’s Books which sponsors
seminars and studies. At California State
U n i ve rsity San Marcos Professor Isabel
Schon runs a centre for the study of books
in Spanish for children and adolescents.
The Book Bank in Ve n e z u e l a ,
Fundalectura in Colombia, B r a z i l ’s Nat i o n a l
Fo u n d ation for Children’s and Yo u n g
People’s Books in Rio de Janeiro, and the
Centre de Promotion du Livre de Je u n e s s e
at Saint-Denis (France) are among other
o r g a n i z ations that are trying to help children
and books to become firm friends. n
schoolchildren spent an average of three
h o u rs a day in front of a television. G i ven a
choice between a book and T V, most of
them chose TV.
Building a youthful 
following
Publishers have risen to the challenge by
b ri n ging out written adaptations of the
l atest Disney film and telling the story of the
sinking of the Ti t a n i c from all kinds of
a n g l e s. Of course such products don’t have
a ve ry long shelf-life, lasting only as long as
it takes for the big transnational film
companies to come up with another money-
s p i n n e r. To surv i ve such fa d s , p u b l i s h e rs
h ave to build up a loyal following among the
reading public.“ I t ’s important to publish for
different age gr o u p s , to respond to feedback
from readers and keep them when they
become adults,” s ays Norma Sturn i o l o,
editor of the Espacio Abierto series at the
Spanish publisher Anaya.
The major children’s classics, which are
a lways being republished, seem to last
f o r e ve r. At the latest publishers ’ b a l l ,
Cinderella continues to whirl around with
Jules Ve rn e , Lewis Carr o l l , Mark Twain and
Saint-Exupéry. Will she one day lose her
glass slipper? Will she continue to enchant
her readers whatever their age?
G l o ria Cecilia Díaz voices what many of
her colleagues think in pri vat e ,t h at “one of
the nicest things is that gr own-ups read my
books as well.” n
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
+ …
l IBBY: http://www.ibby.org
l Fundación Germán Sánchez Ruipérez
(Salamanca,Spain). Tel: 34 932 26 96 62
l Fundación para el Fomento de la Lectura
(Bogotá,Colombia):
email: fundalec@impsat.net.co
l Fundação Nacional do Livro Infantil e Juvenil:
Rua da Imprensa 16,salas 1212 a 1215,
Rio de Janeiro - RJ - 20030-120 Brazil.
Tel:55 21 2620130
l Centre de Promotion du Livre de Jeunesse
Seine Saint-Denis: 3 rue François Debergue
93100,Montreuil,France
l Banco del Libro (Caracas, Venezuela):
email:blibro@reacciun.ve
l Center for the Study of Books in Spanish for 
Children and Adolescents:
California State University, San Marcos
San Marcos, California 92096-0001
Tel:1 760 750 40 70
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
n
“It was either that or I was fin i s h e d ,”
s ays Chantal.“ T h at ”means selling street
n e w s p a p e rs. Chantal is 41 and has “a lot
to get off her chest”.Her story is that of a stri c t
French upbri n gi n g, dropping out of school
and plans thwa rted by her parents. “I wa s
crazy about wild animals and hors e s ,” s h e
s ay s. “I always wanted to train animals. A n d
n ow look at me. . . .”
Chantal had a breakdown in 1996 after
failing an exam to become a nursing assistant.
“I wanted to kill my s e l f,” she say s. “But one
d ay I met an old friend and poured my heart
out to her. She brought me to my senses and
advised me to sell street newspapers.”
Since then, Chantal has been selling
L’ I t i n é ra n t to trave l l e rs on the Pa ri s
underground. She buys her copies for the
e q u i valent of 50 US cents each and re-sells
them for three times that , making betwe e n
$350 and $700 a month.This supplements
the minimum assistance benefit of about
$430 that she gets from the state.
In Stockholm, a 120-strong sales
force
Thousands of marginalized people like
Chantal live from selling street newspapers in
the big cities of rich countri e s. But unlike
C h a n t a l , who rents a small room, most of
them are homeless.
There are about three million homeless
people in the countries of the European
U n i o n , and three million more in the United
S t at e s. M a ny drink or take dru g s. I n
S t o c k h o l m , 40 per cent of them are affli c t e d
with paranoia, s c h i z o p h r e n i a ,or phobias, s ay s
Malin Speace,who runs Swe d e n ’s only street
p a p e r , the monthly S i t u ation Sthlm, w h i c h
s t a rted publication in 1995.The paper pri n t s
15,000 copies and employs 120 of the city’s
5,000 or so homeless.
“Selling the paper keeps them occupied
d u ring the day,” s ays Speace. “ We actually
steal their time, to keep their minds off dru g s.”
The paper is also a halfway house betwe e n
“ e x c l u s i o n ” and belonging to society. Two
e x p e rts help the ve n d o rs through the maze of
social serv i c e s , which include projects ru n
by non-gove rnmental organizat i o n s ,s t ate aid
and detox progr a m m e s.
The social usefulness of S i t u ation Sthlm
seems undeniable.At the ve ry least, it helps the
homeless and the unemployed to be less cut
o f f. At best, it helps them to find somewhere
to live , some training or a job.
For the past decade, street newspapers
and magazines have gone from strength to
s t r e n g t h .The first one, Street News, s u r fa c e d
in New York in 1989, recalls Tim Harri s ,
president of the National A s s o c i ation of Nort h
A m e rican Street Newspapers. The paper,
which depended heavily on corp o r at e
d o n at i o n s , was founded by rock musician
Hutchinson Pe rs o n s , and had “ s o m e w h at
right-wing libert a rian politics,” s ays Harri s.
The movement then spread across Nort h
A m e rica and to Europe, and is now gr ow i n g
e ve rywhere except in France, where street
p a p e rs have faded after getting off to a bri s k
s t a rt in 1993.
E l s e w h e r e , there are over 150 in a score of
c o u n t ri e s , mostly focusing on social issues
and funded by a mix of pri vate donat i o n s ,
a d ve rtising reve n u e , income from sales and
public subsidies. Canada has a dozen and
the United States more than 40.The biggest
ones in the US—S t r e e t W i s e ( C h i c a g o ) ,S p a r e
C h a n ge (Boston) and Real Change ( S e at t l e ) —
sell between 20,000 and 120,000 copies a
m o n t h . But most are run on a shoestri n g,
p rint about 20,000 copies each and barely
manage to  break eve n .
Tessa Swithinbank, i n t e rn ational editor
of the British street paper The Big Issue,
counted 70 titles in Europe in 1997, half of
them in Germ a ny. As in North A m e ri c a ,
they va ry from papers which print 3,000
copies a month to the nearly 300,000 sold
each week by The Big Issue, which is now the
third favo u rite paper of young Bri t o n s
b e t ween the age of 15 and 24. It was founded
in London in 1991 by a wo r k i n g - c l a s s
I rishman and former Tr o t s k y i t e , John Bird,
with $50,000 from the natural cosmetic
chain The Body Shop.To d ay, with an annual
There are discordant voices in the new international movement to produce
street newspapers in aid of the homeless
P
The press take s
to the s t re e t
Clive Harold,a boyhood friend of Prince Charles, sells The Big Issue in the streets of London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
C O N N E X I O N S
The Big Issue was created to be “ a
prosperous publication with considerable
resources that would offer substantial resources
to the less fort u n at e ,” s ays the Montreal street
paper L’ I t i n é ra i r e.M a ny North A m e rican street
p a p e rs are much more cri t i c a l . Most of them
are run and edited by the homeless themselve s
and fight for the existence of this kind of media
voice in a country where it is rare.
They criticize the eye - c at c h i n g
p r e s e n t at i o n , the management style and the
“ c o m m e r c i a l ” content of the British paper and
accuse it of trying to set itself up as the norm .
The arri val of The Big Issue in Los Angeles last
A p ril has fuelled the debat e , especially as it
t h r e atens to kill off the street paper M a k i n g
C h a n ge, based in nearby Santa Monica.
“ We ’re ve ry vulnerable,” s ays Je n n i f e r
Wa g g o n n e r , who runs Making Change. “ We
only have 20 ve n d o rs and our receipts barely
c over printing costs.”But Wa g g o n n e r ,h e rs e l f
a homeless pers o n , has a business sense to
m atch the competition and is negotiat i n g
with the ri val paper for technical help and for
e x c l u s i ve rights to sell the two papers in the
we s t e rn Los Angeles area.
H a rris is careful not to take sides in this
turf war and in ideological disputes. “It all
depends on your pri o ri t i e s ,”he say s.“If they’r e
p o l i t i c a l , you include the poor in the process
of producing the paper and gi ve them a vo i c e .
If you think money’s more import a n t , yo u
t u rn over of more than $20 million, it has
four regional editions in Britain and three
abroad—in A u s t r a l i a , South A f rica and the
United Stat e s.
Speace says street papers are eve n
s t a rting to spread to countries of the South.
N O S was launched in Brasilia at the end of
last ye a r. Homeless young people in Gambia
sell tourists a paper called C o n c e rn. Plans for
street newspapers are afoot in India and
Japan.Wo r l d w i d e , “about 30 million copies
of street newspapers are probably sold eve ry
year and the number is gr owing all the time,”
s ays Mel  Yo u n g,who runs the Scottish edition
of The Big Issue. B u t , he say s , “there is some
d i s a greement within the move m e n t .”
Ethically correct
The main point of discord is over the
p u rpose of street newspapers. Should they be
the mouthpiece of militant community
o r g a n i z ations or should they be profit a b l e
social enterp rises? The Big Issue has chosen the
second option.Bird thinks it is possible to be
both profitable and “ethically corr e c t ” .I n d e e d ,
putting out a quality publicat i o n , p r o d u c e d
entirely by professionals, is essential for social
e f f e c t i ve n e s s ,he say s.The paper highlights the
t wo or three thousand homeless people who
l i ve by selling it and points up the services it
o f f e rs , such as help with finding somewhere
to live and getting training.
Montreal’s netizen news-vendors
The Quebec newspaper L ’ I t i n é r a i r e offers homeless
people an e-mail address in a former hairdressing
salon which has been turned into a cybercafé. I t ’s an
annexe of the Café sur la Rue (The Café on the Street),
which has been open for the homeless and other needy
people for more than a year.The vendors of the monthly
L ’ I t i n é r a i r e— C a n a d a ’s first newspaper for street people,
which was launched in 1994 and focuses on social
issues—go there for a cheap bowl of soup and to pick
up their copies.The “ c a m e l o t s,” as they are called, b u y
them for 65 cents each and sell them to the public for
double that.
The Café sur la Rue opened its Internet annexe last
October—a kind of high-tech office with a dozen
computers. A few homeless people are quietly busy
there but most of the customers are people from the
neighbourhood or hard-up students. One is typing out
his CV, others are playing games, replying to e-mail,
taking part in an online discussion or looking for a job
on the Web.
The place is nicely decora t e d . On its sandy-coloured
walls are literary quotes such as “Greed starts where
poverty ends”by the French writer Honoré de Balzac,a n d
coloured drawings including a long blue wave breaking
at eye-level.
“ Th a t ’s so you can surf the Net better,” j o kes Sébastien
L a n g l a i s,who runs the project,which was set up entirely
with donations—of time by decorators from Radio
C a n a d a , of computers by hardware firms and of free
services such as an Internet link and setting up a website
( h t t p : / / i t i n e ra i r e. e d u c . i n finit.net) by the cable distributor
Vi d e o t r o n .
F i f t y - f o u r- y e a r-old Lise has been on welfare for
the past 25 years. “It does me good to come here,”
she says. “ The day goes by more quickly.” Th e
computers scared her at first, but now she loves
them.So much so that she comes every day to clean
the place up and greet new customers. When her
“volunteer job”allows her the time, she sends an e-
mail to a friend or reconstructs the “puzzle”she has
created in the computer around a photo of her
daughter and granddaughter.
An Internet course for beginners
“ The hardest people to attract in here are the
h o m e l e s s,” says Langlais. New technology frightens
t h e m , even when free training is offered to the least
educated among them.“Street people are not necessarily
uneducated and uncultured,” he says. “Despite their
personal problems,t h e y ’re interested in lots of things.Th e y
want to know what’s going on, in politics or sport, f o r
e x a m p l e.”
t u rn out a commercial product and reinve s t
the profits to help the homeless.”
Watchdogs for the homeless
Like Harri s ,m a ny of those who run street
n e w s p a p e rs have chosen a middle way. In St.
Pe t e rs bu r g, for example, the fortnightly N a
D nye (in Russian, The Lower Depths, f r o m
the title of Maxim Gorky’s play) tries to
combine professionalism and political
s t ru g g l e .“ To attract young readers and boost
s a l e s ,which fell after the rouble was deva l u e d ,
we carry news about trendy clubs, music and
a rt ,” s ays its founder,Va l e ry Sokolov.
The paper has a page for articles wri t t e n
by homeless people, and two-thirds of its
space is taken up with social issues. “ L a s t
N ove m b e r ,we exposed the fact that the police
were expelling homeless people from the
c i t y,” he say s.“ E ve ry  Tu e s d ay and  T h u rs d ay,
they took groups of 20 or 30 about 40 km out
of town and dumped them in the forest where
the temperature was minus 18°C. We have
asked for an inquiry into this.” B e t ween 2,000
and 4,000 of St.Pe t e rs bu r g ’s 50,000 homeless
people die eve ry ye a r.
“With such dreadful things going on,
our differences seem trivial,” says Young.
“ We have to act in concert to attack abu s e s
and set up a worldwide watchdog to defend
the rights of the homeless.” n
Sophie Boukhari
At the Bonneau Reception Center,which serves hot
m e a l s,“they gave an Internet course for beginners,”h e
s a y s. “Since then, a Romanian guy has stopped by
regularly to get news about his country from the Net.
Another homeless person, who wasn’t interested in
a n y t h i n g , developed a passion for online newspapers.”
The cybercafé’s goal is the same as that of the
newspaper, which gets some financial help from the
g o v e r n m e n t . It aims to demarginalize the poorest
p e o p l e, m a ke them feel wa n t e d , give them some
training and some experience of voluntary or paid
work,in the hope it will lead them back into society.
Some American psychologists say access to new
technology can be a kind of do-it-yourself therapy for
people who are depressed and can help them to
regain their self-confid e n c e.The cybercafé also helps
to build in street people and the unemployed a “ s e n s e
of belonging” to the “big family” of L ’ I t i n é r a i r e, s a y s
the paper’s editor,Alain Demers.
But the river that divides this sheltered environment
from the job market is still hard to cross. Only rarely
does anyone really manage to cross the divide. n
Anne Pélouas
in Montreal
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
Films
beamed
from the sky
Shall we soon be able to go to cinemas where
reels of film won’t be needed? Computer
technology is advancing so rapidly that the day
when films can be projected by satellite to the
remotest corner of the planet is fast approaching.
This prospect is creating a panic in the
laboratories which turn out copies of films, and
most of all among the big international
distributing companies. But it delights film fans
in isolated areas and in small towns where the
local cinema has closed down.
The idea is simple.The film is scanned,and then
compressed and encrypted with its sound tra c k
before being transmitted by satellite or digital
phone line.At the other end,a “satellite modem”,
a decoder and a special projector are needed and
the film can be shown anywhere—in a barn, s a y,
or a village square. No more lugging around reels
or damaging film in transit.
The new technique was first publicly tested in
1996 by a Hollywood firm before it was really
r e a d y. Since then, there have been many try-outs.
The most successful results seem to have been
obtained at the Babelsberg studios in Germany,
supervised by the famous film-maker Vo l ke r
S c h l ö n d o r f f. The European Union is supporting his
p r o j e c t , C y b e r C i n e m a , in a bid to recapture a
public which has lost interest in films with the
closure of local cinemas and to counter A m e r i c a n
domination of international film distribution.
At the end of last year, CyberCinema stepped
up its demonstrations of the new technique by
showing films for children in Dublin,Wa r s a w, S a n
Remo, Liverpool,Hanover and Ivalo (in Lapland).
The promoters reckon they need 500 projection
sites in order to make a profit.By the year 2000,
they hope to have 200.
Two problems will have to be sorted out before
t h e n . The quality of the digital image is not yet
quite as good as that of a standard 35 mm film,
and a digital projector alone costs $200,000.So
maybe the good old reel of film still has a few
years of life in it yet. n
nHeinz Bonni (above) is a bit of a
l o u d m o u t h . “I don’t suffer fools gladly,”
he declares,“and I always say what I think.”
Sometimes he goes even further and uses his
fis t s.A few months ago, he was up in court
for assault. He got a two-year suspended
p rison sentence and a $240 fine. T h at ’s
when he realized he could “count on B i s s” —
the paper paid his fine.
B i s s is short for “Burger in sozialen
S c h w i e ri g k e i t e n ”(“Citizens in Diffic u l t y ” ) .I t ’s
also the name of Munich’s monthly street
m a g a z i n e .The first publication of its kind in
G e rm a ny, B i s s was launched in 1993 by a
group of radical journalists and militant
e va n g e l i c a l s.To d ay, 460 homeless or once-
homeless people have permits to sell the
p a p e r , which cove rs the social crisis and the
problems of marginalized people. They can
sell up to 600 papers a month without losing
their social security pay m e n t s.
Bonni, aged 60, is one of 110 vendors
considered “ r e g u l a rs ” . After a string of
mishaps and occupational diffic u l t i e s , h e
lost his apartment, his job and finally his
emotional stability. He is not your ideal
homeless pers o n , carefully saving money
so as to get back into society. He smells of
d rink as he complains about the other
vendors. But he’s proud to be working for
an “established” magazine, as he calls it.
“Everyone’s heard of Biss,” he says.
It wa s n ’t easy for B i s s to get this fa r. A t
firs t , the team of vo l u n t e e rs was ove r w h e l m e d .
S ome people had their hand in the till,
which was pretty empty any way. T h e
magazine was sinking when 50-ye a r - o l d
Hildegard Denninger, an accountant by
t r a i n i n g, took over in May 1994,
reorganizing it and making better use of
the sales revenue. Now Biss prints 40,000
copies of each issue, has about $150,000 in
the kitty and gets subsidies from the city
council and donations from elsewhere.
Things are going well—a bit too we l l ,
according to some people, who think social
action should not get mixed up with
c o m m e r c e . The magazine, which is put
together by professional journ a l i s t s , is also
c riticized for not giving enough space to what
homeless people themselves think. If they
want to express their views, the homeless can
join a weekly “ w riting wo r k s h o p ”and publish
a rticles in a special section of the magazine.
“It would be naive to think that our
ve n d o rs can turn out we l l - w ritten and
researched articles when most of the
‘ n o rm a l ’p o p u l ation can’t ,” s ays Denninger,
who thinks there’s no altern at i ve to bri n gi n g
out a quality product.
Loyal readers
“I get blamed for being only interested in
m o n e y,” she say s. But how to surv i ve without
it? The homeless earn the equivalent of 80 US
cents for each copy they sell and B i s s h e l p s
t h e m , among other things, to pay off any
debts they have . It also gi ves them a bonus
when they manage to get an apartment and
s u p p o rts them when they tangle with the law.
The magazine has also been able to form a l l y
hire its six best ve n d o rs—those who sell more
than 1,200 copies a month.
Some readers and even some vendors
complain that the magazine devotes too
much space to foreigners in difficulty when
there are so many “ r e a l ”G e rman homeless.
But the readership is pretty loya l . T h e
magazine became well known partly thanks
to a big publicity campaign in 1996 donat e d
by a leading Munich advertising agency. It
i nvo l ved showing top footballer Jürgen
Klinsmann and the city’s mayo r ,C h ri s t i a n
Ude, both disguised as homeless vendors.
E ve ryone seems to get something out of it.
B u t , as Denninger admits, the magazine only
enables a tiny minority of the homeless to fin d
a job and really get a foothold in society. n
Kathrin Sander in Munich
G e r m a n y ’s leading stre e t
monthly has become an
established  institution
Munich’s street
magazine
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
James To b i n :
reining
in the markets
46 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
You once said that the study of economics
offers hope, and that improved
understanding of our economies can better
the lot of humanity. Do you feel economists
have been able to improve the situation of
all humanity, or have they helped some
people more than others?
I think some economists have helped some
p e rsons more than others. T h at ’s quite
l i k e l y. But ye s , I think on the whole
economists have improved the lot of
h u m a n i t y, though we have n ’t done it as
well as I might have hoped.
I began studying economics during the
Great Depression.There was 25 per cent
u n e m p l oyment in the United Stat e s , i n
France probably 15 to 20 per cent, a n d
complete disorder. The intern at i o n a l
political scene was certainly affected by the
failure of the world economy. The rise of
Hitler was directly related to the Great
Depression in Germany.
Anybody who went to college who had
his eyes open and read the newspapers in
the 1930s had the right to be concerned
about the economic situat i o n , and the ri g h t
to believe that failure of the world economy
had a lot to do with the many threats to the
peace of the world, to fascism, nazism and
c o m m u n i s m .To the extent that we learn e d
in the Great Depression  how to keep from
having great depressions anymore we have
reduced the likelihood that things like that
would happen again. We figured out why
there was a depression,and we figured out
w h at kind of monetary and fiscal policies we
could use as a remedy.
It seems that economists have genera l l y
c o n c e n t rated on the production of wealth,
and less on its distribution.
A c c o rding to international org a n i z a t i o n s
l i ke the United Nations Development
P ro g ramme (UNDP), inequality is incre a s i n g
within countries and between countries.
T h a t ’s why one might argue that
economists have concentrated on the
p roduction of wealth, and less on
d i s t r i b u t i o n .
I don’t think that ’s a fair charge against my
p r o f e s s i o n . A c t u a l l y, consider the whole
welfare state that you have in France and
throughout Europe—economists have had
a lot to do with bri n ging it about and
organizing it. We didn’t have those things
when I was younger. Social security didn’t
b e gin in the United States until 1936 duri n g
the depression. We didn’t have publicly
s u p p o rted health care until after the wa r.A
lot of those things have come with the help
and the advocacy of economists.
Why does inequality keep increasing at the
national and international levels?
T h at ’s a really complicated question. I don’t
h ave any single answe r. We ought to be
spending a lot of our energy, our emotion,
and our intelligence to find ways of reducing
inequality both within countries and
between countries.
It hasn’t been ignored by economists.
The World Bank, for example, was founded
in 1945 for that purpose.The reduction of
inequality requires that people who have
e a rned higher incomes in markets be taxe d
in order to improve the standards of living
of the people who have been less fort u n at e ,
who earned less in markets. Among the
major preoccupations of economic policy,
social policy and politics is the level of
t a x ation and the degree to which
g ove rnments transfer your earnings into
the hands of people who are less fort u n at e .
Ta x ation and transfer programmes are a
big political issue.
You ask: w hy don’t democracies succeed
in making more transfers of income and
wealth from the fort u n ate people who earn
a lot to the less fortunate people who earn
much less? And then the same thing is tru e
on a bigger scale between nat i o n s ,b e t we e n
people in one part of the world and people
in another. I suppose if  you really wanted
to reduce inequality across the whole wo r l d
you would try to get rid of all immigration
b a rri e rs , so that people could move
w h e r e ver they want to, to get jobs and higher
wa g e s.T h at would certainly be an immense
political problem.
In an age of globalized markets and deregulation an
American Nobel prize-winning economist champions a
tax on short-term financial transactions to head off
international crises and help poor countries
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
P
Since 1971 you have been saying that
states need to have at least a minimum
amount of control over their national
monetary policy. With globalization, have
states lost control over monetary policy?
It is true that the globalization of financial
markets has diminished the control that
s t ates have over their own monetary policies.
There always has been a constraint on
m o n e t a ry policy ever since we started hav i n g
some liberalization of monetary regulat i o n s
back in the Bretton Woods system begi n n i n g
in 1945. But that has gone on much more
rapidly in the last few ye a rs , and it does
limit particularly the power of small
c o u n t ries like those in East Asia to run their
own monetary policies.
Given financial globalization, how can
states preserve their monetary autonomy?
Well, they have to have some ways to slow
d own the inflow and outflow of foreign
currency and to make the convertibility of
their own currencies into foreign currency
less damaging to the country as a whole.
Consider for example what happened in
East Asian countri e s , where some of the
banks—the banks in Korea for example—
b o rr owed from New Yo r k , To k yo and
London banks.They borr owed ve ry short -
term, one week or two weeks, so that the
l e n d e rs , the big banks in New York or To k yo
or London could decide eve ry week or two
whether to renew the loan.The commercial
bank in Korea, for example, has to pay back
the New York bank in dollars. H ow is it
going to get the dollars? It is going to take
some Korean wo n , the local curr e n cy, to the
Korean central bank and say “ you promised
to gi ve us so many dollars per wo n . Here is
my won and I want what e ver you have
promised to gi ve for wo n .” So the hard
c u rr e n cy reserves of the country in the
hands of the central bank then eva p o r ate as
the banks pay back their loans.T h at ’s where
the reserves go, and if reserves vanish like
t h at then the curr e n cy will have to be
devalued.That’s what happened in 1998.
If, for example, Korea had had a law
which said banks are not allowed to have
s h o rt - t e rm hard curr e n cy debts that are
u n c overed by corresponding short - t e rm
a s s e t s , then the central bank would be
protecting itself. If they were to have
i n t e r f e r e d , to that degr e e , with complete
g l o b a l i z ation of the Korean banking system
and the Korean money market, it wo u l d
have been a very good thing.
There are a number of ways in which
those countries can protect themselves. A
transaction tax is one method.
That brings us to the so-called Tobin tax.
Could you briefly explain to us what it is
and how it would work?
There are 1.3 trillion dollars a day in foreign
exchange transactions.Those transactions
would be taxe d , at a ve ry low rat e ,
something like one tenth of one per cent per
dollar per transaction.The taxes would be
levied by each country on transactions that
o ri gi n ate in the country, and collected by the
usual tax authority of that country.
If people are invo l ved in making a lot of
transactions eve ry day, e ve ry we e k , t h e y
would have to pay the tax a lot of times.S o
they are discouraged from doing that just by
the existence of the tax.
Would the world look different today if
your tax had been in place since the 1970s?
Would Asia have had the tremendous
growth that we saw, which was partly
fuelled by investments and capital flows?
Would we also have had 
an Asian financial crisis, if the tax had been
in place earlier?
Of the 1.3 trillion dollars in transactions per
d ay, ve ry few have to deal with the move m e n t
of productive capital from the savings of one
c o u n t ry into the investment of another
c o u n t ry. D e veloped countries nowa d ay s
m ove about 200 billion dollars a year into
i nvestment in developing countri e s. So mos t
of the transactions that occur are not relat e d
directly to desirable movements of
p r o d u c t i ve capital from developed to
underdeveloped countries.
China doesn’t have full convertibility,
except of Chinese curr e n cy earned by
f o r e i g n e rs in trade. You cannot conve rt
Chinese currency into dollars or francs or
yen just to move funds around.They have
strict financial control very much like the
controls that France had in 1945-46 right
after the wa r. In fa c t , France had exchange
controls of some kind until the middle of the
1 9 8 0 s. China receives a lot of direct
investments from overseas without having
c o nve rtibility of capital funds from one
c u rr e n cy to another. I t ’s not essential to
have that.
Most of the investment from deve l o p e d
into underdeveloped countries wo u l d n ’t
have been influenced significantly by the
Tobin tax, by the exchange transaction tax.
In fa c t , the advantage of that device is  that
it doesn’t tax long-range inve s t m e n t s
appreciably at all. If you take a 20-ye a r
round trip by putting equity capital into
an underdeveloped country, s ay from
France into Viet Nam, and you don’t take
the money out for 20 ye a rs , you pay a tenth
of a percent the first time and a tenth of a
per cent coming back. T h at wo u l d n ’t
influence your calculation about whether
you want to make the investment.It’s only
the ve ry short - t e rm movements of
c u rrencies that would have been
discouraged.
So would the so-called Tobin tax  have
actually prevented an Asian crisis?
C e rtainly you need other things as we l l .
You need reforms in your own banking
system and stock markets. The other big
m i s t a k e , perhaps a bigger mistake than
some of the things we have been discussing,
is the practice of having a fixed exchange
rate.You wouldn’t have the currency crisis
if you didn’t have a fixed exchange rate. A
f i xed exchange rate is a promise by the
central bank of the country to pay a fixed
amount of dollars , ye n , euros or a basket of
s e veral curr e n c i e s. If the central bank
doesn’t have a reserve of hard currency, it
has to default on this promise. It’s like the
failure of an ordinary bank. If depositors
come and ask for cash for their deposits
and the bank doesn’t have them, then the
We ought to be spending a lot of our energy,
our emotion, and our intelligence 
to find ways of reducing inequality both within countries
and between countries
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 47
James Tobin
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
Economic liberalism with a human face
bank has to close and there is a crisis.
In the light of the Asian crisis,
many of the countries in Asia feel that 
they have lost their power, that there has
been a shift in the balance 
of power between the state and the free
market. Do you think that view has any
substance?
I think that they are right about that to a
considerable degr e e .The financial markets
being completely liberalized and in my view
p r e m aturely liberalized, l e aves gove rn m e n t s
without the control or restrictions which
they need to limit the speed and volume of
m ovements of funds in and out of their
currencies.
Do you think we will continue to have big
financial crises. Are we learning from our
mistakes?
Financial crises are not inevitable. I think we
will probably learn from  mistakes and we
wo n ’t go back—at least in the case of these
countries—to trying to defend a fixed rate
of exchange, against dollars or ye n , a n d
t h at will certainly make crises less frequent.
The whole of history is peppered with
i n t e rn ational financial cri s e s. I am not sure
it’s right that they are more frequent now.
There are more people in adva n c e d
c o u n t ries who have put money into
c o u n t ries where crises occurr e d . I n
p a rt i c u l a r ,c o u n t ries in Asia had gr own ve ry
r a p i d l y, almost miraculously, for two or
three decades and had promoted themselve s
to higher echelons and higher places in the
pecking order of countries and economies.
They have a lot of the trappings of the
m o d e rn European or A m e rican economy —
stock markets, bond markets, m o n e y
m a r k e t s , all these things—and gr ow i n g
l e vels of wealth and income. They have
much closer ties to financial enterp ri s e s
ove rseas in major countri e s. So there was a
bigger shock when they couldn’t maintain
their promises to pay dollars to banks in
America and Japan.
Do you think is there any chance of the
Tobin tax being implemented one day. In
France there is a movement to promote it.
Political fig u res agree with this tax when
they are in opposition. But when they are in
power they don’t talk about the Tobin tax.
I am not optimistic about that . I don’t think
the financial community, i n c l u d i n g
m i n i s t e rs of finance in major countries and
the central banks of those countries, have
a ny use for those taxe s.They don’t want it.
Even if somebody else in the government
may say good things about it as François
M i t t e rrand did, it wo n ’t go through the
Tee-shirts captioned “former rich”have sold like hot cakes in Thailand.
n
Nobel economics prize-winner Ja m e s
Tobin may be 80 ye a rs old but he is still
hard at wo r k . At Yale Unive rs i t y, where he
taught from 1950 to 1988, this tireless
researcher and gifted popularizer has an offic e
where he gi ves interviews and writes—so fa r
he has published 16 books and more than 400
a rt i c l e s.
In the autobiographical note he wrote
for the Nobel Foundation in 1981, he said
that he studied economics and made it his
career because it “was and is intellectually
fa s c i n ating and challengi n g, p a rticularly to
someone with taste and talent for theoretical
reasoning and quantitat i ve analysis.” It also
offered the hope of bettering the lot of
h u m a n k i n d . His family backgr o u n d — h i s
mother was a social worker and his father an
independent-minded journ a l i s t — a l s o
helped a lot to shape the direction of 
his life.
B o rn in Illinois, he lived through the
Great Depression and what he called the
“miserable failures of capitalist economies”
which caused worldwide political and social
d i s a s t e r.The depression also “spelled cri s i s
for economic orthodoxy”and “triggered a
f e rtile period of scientific ferment and
r e volution in economic theory.” It wa s
d u ring this time of ferment that To b i n ,t h e n
an undergraduate at Harvard, discovered
the theories of John Maynard Keynes in
1936.
As a supporter of economic liberalism
with a human fa c e ,Tobin has ever since then
defended the stat e ’s role in the economy and
fiscal and bu d g e t a ry adjustments. In the 1950s
and 1960s,he led the resistance to the cru s a d e
for monetarism headed by another Nobel
p rize-winner for economics, M i l t o n
F ri e d m a n . Tobin firmly backed the
D e m o c r atic Pa rty and was an adviser to
President John F. Kennedy in 1961-62.
Twenty ye a rs lat e r , he spoke out once more,
this time against President Ronald Reagan’s
p o l i c i e s , which were largely inspired by
F ri e d m a n ’s ideas.
Since the early 1970s, he has wa rn e d
against the development of pri vat e
s p e c u l ation in money markets, which is
u n d e rmining the independence of nat i o n a l
m o n e t a ry policies. To discourage these
s p e c u l at o rs , he proposed in 1972 an
i n t e rn ational tax on spot curr e n cy
t r a n s a c t i o n s.The Tobin tax, as it was dubbed,
found enthusiastic support e rs on the left,
especially in Europe.
Tobin was awarded the Nobel prize in
1981 for his work on money supply and
his mat h e m atically form u l ated theory of
the allocation by firms and households of
their portfolios among different assets.
Tobin’s theories have influenced a whole
g e n e r ation of researchers and stimulat e d
analysis of the balance of payments and
economic growth. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
attempt to regulate capital flows so as to
help prevent the kind of crisis we have
seen in A s i a ?
I don’t think there is going to be any
i n t e rn ationally co-ordinated policy. I do think
t h at there is going to be more tolerance by the
IMF and by the gove rnments in Nort h
A m e rica and Europe of developing countri e s.
In some of those cases I think there’s probably
not a big disagr e e m e n t . For example, t h e
banking systems of those countries were not
ready to be part of intern ational fin a n c i a l
m a r k e t s. They we r e n ’t ready because they
d i d n ’t have the institutional and legal
f r a m e works that we take for granted in our
s y s t e m s. A l s o, consider securities markets.
In the United States we have had a federal
a g e n cy, the Securities and Exchange
Commission (SEC) since the 1930s. Yo u
c a n ’t sell stocks and bonds on the open
market without regi s t e ring complete
i n f o rm ation about it with the SEC.Yet many
of our pri vate financial firms helped set up
exchanges in underdeveloped countries which
February 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 49
T A L K I N G  T O …
finance ministry.They are not going to go
for it, the Intern ational Monetary Fund
(IMF) is not going to go for it.
People do not like to be taxe d .They think
it is an interference with the free market.
Hasn’t there been a little bit of a shift in
the way people think?
A little bit of a shift, r e a l i z at i o n , s o m e
recognition at the last big meetings of the
IMF and the World Bank. Some recognition
t h at maybe globalizat i o n , l i b e r a l i z at i o n
i n t e rn ationally has gone too fa s t , too fa r. B u t
there’s been no actual proposal as to how
that would be remedied.At least they did
express a little more openness to consideri n g
ways in which flows of funds now in
different currencies could be moderated. I
n e ver heard them mention the tax. I did see
only one mention, in which Mr Michel
C a m d e s s u s , head of the IMF, said he saw no
support for international taxation.
Do you see there being some sort of
A Thai woman sells her jewelry to raise some ready cash.
The financial markets being completely liberalized 
and in my view prematurely liberalized, leaves
governments without the control or restrictions which
they need to limit the speed and volume of movements 
of funds in and out of their currencies
A controversial
tax
In order to avoid tumultuous financial and
economic floods and droughts caused by
increasingly mighty international capital flows for
speculative purposes and to protect national
policies from dictatorship by the market,in 1972
James Tobin proposed a worldwide foreign
exchange transactions tax.In brief the idea is to
levy a 0.1% to 0.5% on money exchanged from
one currency to another.
Such a tax, the Nobel Prize-winner has insisted,
would be punitive for short-term financial plays
and would thus slow down speculative capital
movements such as those that led to the surge
and then collapse of Asian financial markets over
the past decade. On the other hand, the “Tobin
tax”,according to its author, would not be high
enough to deter commodity trade or long-term
investments in productive enterprises.
Some analysts, h o w e v e r, feel that the Tobin tax
would be impossible to administer because all
countries would have to agree to it and such
worldwide fiscal harmonization would be
unprecedented. n
P
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50 The UNESCO Courier - February 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
Language:⌧ English ⌧ French ⌧ Spanish
Rates (postage included):
Industrialized countries: Developing countries or students 
⌧ 1 year: 211French francs (32,15 euros) instead of 264FF* (11 issues including 1 double issue) (Please send copy of your card):
⌧ 2 years: 396 French francs (60,35 euros) instead of 528FF* (22 issues including 2 double issues) ⌧ 1 year: 132 French francs (20,10 euros)
⌧ Binder: 72French francs (11 euros) (for 11 issues including 1 double issue) ⌧ 2 years: 211 French francs (32,15 euros)
I enclose payment: (in French francs only) by
⌧ Bank cheque (except Eurocheque) ⌧ Visa ⌧ Mastercard ⌧ Eurocard
N° _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ Expiry date: Date and signature:
Name First name
Address
Postal code City
Optional:Age Profession
(*) Total cover price
I WISH TO SUBSCRIBE TO the UNESCO Courier
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to:
the UNESCO Courier Subscription Services, 31,rue François Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are opposite this order form.
"
In fact, it was the original idea behind
the IMF. All the countries had in the
b e ginning rather generous drawing rights in
the IMF which they could use  without
question. Now they are certainly not big
enough  because the total size of the quotas
of all the countries together in the IMF is
about 150 billion dollars,which is nothing
for a worldwide institution that ’s supposed
to do what they are supposed to do.
I think the World Bank is different. I
am afraid in the last couple of years, the
IMF has started taking over what was the
World Bank responsibility. The IMF
p r e s c riptions for the countries in East A s i a ,
whom they were presumably helping,
included prescriptions for fundamental
changes in institutions in the interest of
reforming the long-run structure of those
e c o n o m i e s. But that was supposedly the
mission of the World Bank,not of IMF.
Economists have made great strides over
the last decades. But they were unable to
predict something as great as the financial
crisis in Asia. Why is that? Why, despite all
these advances in economics, are
economists unable to foresee or forecast
these kinds of crises?
You can’t predict financial markets. If you
could predict them, then the process of
acting on your prediction to get money, to
get profit s ,r e m oves the possibility of making
money in them. They are mat t e rs of
e x p e c t ations and emotions, and they are
not predictable really.
As for the general question of why can’t
economists predict things: t h at strikes me as
really unfa i r. M e t e o r o l o gists know a lot
about we ather but their predictions are not
always accurate.Doctors know a lot about
human disease but they are often surp ri s e d ,
often incapable of doing anything about it.
So we are not alone in our failures.
Do you think that there has been generally
a shift towards market mechanisms in
education,science and culture. If so, has it
been a good thing or not?
I think it’s hard to make generalizat i o n s
about that. I think it’s true that there has
been a movement against gove rn m e n t
r e g u l ation around the wo r l d . For example,
p ri vat i z ation of gove rn m e n t - ow n e d
e n t e rp ri s e s. In many countri e s , a lot of that
was not necessary, wa s n ’t part i c u l a r l y
desirable.I think we have in this country a
lot of people, including one of our political
p a rt i e s , who are opposed to using
g ove rnment money for culture, who wo u l d
like to transfer gove rnment money from
public education into subsidizing pri vat e
education,private schools.There has been
a trend in that direction.
Do you think it’s a good trend?
I think the spirit of it is not a good trend. I n
general it’s selfish and short-sighted. n
Interview by Sophie Boukhari,
d i d n ’t have these kinds of essential safeguards.
It would be ve ry reasonable for a
country like Thailand or Korea to regulate
the amount of foreign currency debt held
not only by the banks in their countri e s
but also by the corp o r ations in their
countries.What you really want to do is to
encourage your companies to attract equity
investments,because they are not going to
cause you to have a currency crisis.
In the context of financial crises, what is
the role of institutions like the IMF and
World Bank? What is your ideal of how they
should operate? Are they adequate, alone,
to address some of the issues like
development and amelioration of situations
where there is a financial crisis? Do we
need other financial institutions, such as a
World Central Bank?
I think the IMF could move in the direction
of being a world central bank—which is more
like what it was meant to be. T h at means
t h at it would be prepared to prov i d e
i n t e rn ational liquidity to countries getting
into trouble without pretending that they are
guilty of crimes and have to be punished as a
p rice of the assistance. A central bank in a
c o u n t ry which serves as a lender of last resort
for banks in that country lends to them when
they have liquidity problems without acting as
though they committed a cri m e .They expect
to be paid back short l y.We should see more
of that spirit on the part of the IMF.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
L I S T  O F S A L E S A N D S U B S C R I P T I O N A G E N T S
Subscr ipt ions can be paid to the subsc ript ion agent in y our cou ntry who wil l  supply rat es i n local  currenc y on re q u e s t
A R G E N T I N A : Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UN E S C O,
Tucumán 1685, 1050 Buenos A i r e s. Fa x :3 7 1 - 8 1 9 4 .
AU S T R A L I A : Hunter Publicat i o n s , 58A Gipps Street,
C o l l i n g wood VIC 3066. Fa x : 419 7154. ISA A u s t r a l i a ,
PO Box 709,To owong QLD 4066. Fa x : 371 5566.
United Nations A s s o c. of A u s t r a l i a / V i c t o rian Div. ,
179 St George's Road,
N. F i t z r oy VIC 3068. Fa x : 481 7693.
AU S T R I A : Gerold & Co, I m p o rt & Export ,
Z e i t s c h ri f t e n / Pe ri o d i c a l s , Graben 31, A-1011 V i e n n a .
Fa x : 512 47 31 29
B E L G I U M : Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Bru s s e l s.
Fa x : 538 08 41.
B R A Z I L : Fundaco Getulio Va r g a s , Editora Divisão de Ve n d a s ,
Caixa Postal 62.591, 22257-970 Rio de Janeiro RJ.
Fa x :5 5 1 - 0 9 4 8 .
C A N A DA : Renouf Publishinq Company Ltd, C e n t r a l
D i s t ri bution Centre, 1294 Algoma Road, O t t awa , Ont K1B
3 W 8 . Fa x : 741 5439.
P é riodica Inc, 1155 Av Ducharm e ,O u t r e m o n t , PQ H2V 1E2.
Fa x : 274 0201.
C H I L E : U n i ve rs i t a ria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10220,
S a n t i a g o. Fa x : 681 9091.
C H I N A : China National Publicat i o n s ,I m p o rt & Export
C o rp. , PO Box 88, 16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 100020.
Fa x : 010 65063101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: A rt i a ,Ve Smeckach 30,
111 27 Prague 1.
D E N M A R K : M u n k s g a a r d ,N o rre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148,
DK-1016 Kobenhavn K. Fa x : 12 93 87.
F I N L A N D : S t o c k m a n n / A k ateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23,
SF-00371 Helsinki. Fa x : +358 9 121 4450.
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF-01641 Va n t a a .
Fa x : 852 7990.
G E R M A N Y: G e rman Commission for UN E S C O, C o l m a n t s t r.
1 5 , D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 63 69 12.
Uno Ve r l a g, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55,
D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 21 74 92.
G R E E C E : L i b r a i rie Kauffmann SA, M a u v r o k o r d atou 9,
GR-106 78 A t h e n s. Fa x : 38 33 967.
G UAT E M A L A : Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con
la UN E S C O, 3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1,A p a rtado Postal 2630,
G u atemala City.
HONG KO N G : Hong Kong Gove rnment Inform ation Svcs.
D e p t . , 1 Bat t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
H U N G A RY: Librotrade K F T, Pe riodical Import / K ,P O B
1 2 6 , H-1656 Budapest. Fa x :2 5 6 - 8 7 - 2 7 .
I N D I A : O rient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions A c c o u n t ) ,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estat e ,B o m b ay 400 038.
Fa x : 26 91 278.
Oxford Book & Stat i o n e ry Co, Code No D 8208052, S c i n d i a
H o u s e , New Delhi 110 001. Fa x : 33 22 639.
I S R A E L : L i t e r a ry Transactions Inc. , C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., P O
B ox 1444, Bnei Brak 51114. Fa x : 52 81 187.
I TA LY: L i c o s a / L i b r e ria Comm. Sansoni SPA ,Via Duca di
C a l a b ria 1/1, I-50125 Florence. Fa x :6 4 - 1 2 - 5 7 .
J A PA N : E a s t e rn Book Service Inc. , Pe riodicals A c c o u n t , 3 13
Hongo 3 Chome, B u n k yo Ku ,To k yo 113. Fa x :8 1 8 - 0 8 6 4 .
KO R E A : Korean National Commission for UN E S C O, C P O
B ox 64, Seoul 100-600. Fa x : 568 7454.
L U X E M B U R G : M e s s a g e ries Paul Kraus, BP 2022, L - 1 0 2 0
L u xe m b o u r g . Fa x : 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA : Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic
S t r e e t ,Valletta CMR 01. Fa x : 24 61 82.
M AU R I T I U S : Nalanda Co. L t d . , 30 Bourbon Street, Po rt
L o u i s. Fa x : 212 1313.
M O RO C C O : UN E S C O, 35 avenue du 16 novembre Agdal-
Rabat. Fax:212-767 03 75,Tél.:212-767 03 74/72.
M E X I C O : Librería El Correo de la UN E S C O S A , Col Roma,
G u a n a j u ato 72, Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF.
Fa x :2 6 4 - 0 9 - 1 9 .
N E T H E R L A N D S : S wets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2 1 6 0
SZ Lisse. Fa x :2 5 2 4 - 1 5 8 8 8 .
T i j d s c h riftcentrale Wijck B V, I n t .S u b s. S e rv i c e ,W
G r a c h t s t r a at 1C, 6221 CT Maastri c h t . Fa x : 32 50 103.
NEW ZEALAND: GP Legi s l ation Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 12418,T h o rn d o n ,We l l i n g t o n . Fa x : 496 56 98.
NORVEGE : S wets Norge A S ,Ø s t e n s j ø vein 18-0606 Oslo, PO
Box 6512,Etterstad. Fax:47 22 97 45 45.
P O RT U G A L : L i v r a ria Po rtugal (Dias & Andrade Lda),
Rua do Carmo 70 74, 1200 Lisboa. Fa x : 34 70 264.
R U S S I A : Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39,
M o s c ow 113095.
SOUTH A F R I C A : I n t e rn ational Subscription Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 41095, Craighall 2024. Fa x : 880 6248.
Mast Publicat i o n s , PO Box 901, Parklands 2121.
Fa x : 886 4512.
S PA I N : Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37,
28001 Madri d . Fa x :5 7 5 - 3 9 - 9 8 .
L i b r e ria Al A n d a l ú s , Roldana 3 y 4, 41004 Sevilla.
Fa x :4 2 2 - 5 3 - 3 8 .
Los Amigos de la UN E S C O, Alda Urquijo 62, 2 Izd.,
48011 Bilbao. Fa x :4 2 7 - 5 1 - 5 9 / 6 9
SRI LANKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam,
Gardiner Mawat h a , Colombo 2. Fa x : 44 78 48.
S W E D E N : We n n e r gren Williams A B , PO Box 1305,
S-171 25 Solna. Fa x : 27 00 71.
S W I T Z E R L A N D : Dynapresse Marketing SA, ( e x - N av i l l e
S A ) , 38 av V i b e rt , CH-1227 Carouge. Fa x : 308 08 59.
E d i group SA, Case Postale 393, CH-1225 Chêne-Bourg.
Fa x : 348 44 82.
Europa Ve r l a g, Ramistrasse 5, CH-8024 Züri c h .
Fa x : 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG ,W i s s e n s c h a f t l .B u c h h a n d l u n g,
Pe t e rs graben 31, CH-4009 Basel. Fa x : 306 12 34.
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E C O, Chemin du
L a c u e z , CH-1807 Blonay. Fa x : 943 36 05.
T H A I L A N D : Suksapan Pa n i t , Mansion 9, R a j a d a m n e rn
Ave n u e , Bangkok 2. Fa x : 28 11 639.
T U N I S I A : Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de
l ’UN E S C O, 2 2 , rue de l’Angleterr e , 1000RP Tu n i s.
Fa x : 33 10 14
UNITED KINGDOM: The Stat i o n e ry Office Publicat i o n s
C t r e . , 51 Nine Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR.
Fa x : 873 84 63.
UNITED STAT E S : B e rnan A s s o c i at e s , 4611-F A s s e m b l y
D ri ve , Lanham MD 20706-4391. Fa x :4 5 9 - 0 0 5 6 .
U R U G UAY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
Maldonado 1090, M o n t e v i d e o. Fa x : 90 59 83.
V E N E Z U E L A : UN E S C O/ C R E S A L C ,E d i f. A s ov i n c a r ,
Av Los Chorr o s ,C ruce C/C A c u e d u c t o, Altos de Sebu c a n ,
C a r a c a s. Fa x : 286 03 26.
NEW from 
UNESCO Publishing
UNESCO PUBLISHING
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publications
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
Biotechnologies 
in developing
countries: 
present and future
by Albert Sasson
Human diseases, food
production: biotechnologies 
can improve the lives of
millions of people in developing
countries.
An authoritative series, a 
comprehensive international 
reference for researchers, 
policy planners and international 
co-operation organizations.
Volume 1:
Regional and national
survey
A comprehensive overview 
of the status of biotechnolo-
gy research and development 
in the developing world.
Volume 2:
International 
co-operation
The means to reduce dispari-
ties and to spread present
and foreseen benefits of bio-
technologies.
Volume 1:
764 pp., 24 x 15.5 cm, 280 FF
Volume 2:
808 pp., 24 x 15.5 cm, 280 FF
Special offer 
for both volumes: 500 FF
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Do s s i e r:
A new deal for the poor
n Millions plunged into poverty
n The new international consensus
n Strengths and limits of market forces
n The State: interventionism or laissez faire?
n The resources of the poor
Features:
n  Communities pull together in the USA
n  What to do with obsolete nuclear plants?
n  American Chicanos learn by painting
n  Biological research: some terrifying prospects
n  Finding a way home for looted artworks
n  Singapore: when the Web weds TV
n  Interview with Ivorian writer Ahmadou Kourouma
]]>
</page>
</document>
