<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="115117eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
theC o u rie r
March 1999
A new deal
for the poor
Nuclear decommissioning:
a p roblem that won’t go away
Tracking down
looted art
Ahmadou 
Ko u ro u m a :
an A f r i c a n
n o v e l i s t ’s inside
s t o r y
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
52nd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat
Photoengraving:Eric Frogé
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian:Gianluca Formichi,Sira Miori (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e : Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UN E S C O or those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. P h o t o
captions and headlines are written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r
s t a f f. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O o r
the United Nations. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7
Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfil m s
( X e r o x ) , Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C . R .
Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d , Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - MARCH 1999
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Pa r i s
by UN E S C O. Printed in Fr a n c e. Periodicals postage paid at
Champlain NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N°3-1999-OPI 99-580 A
C o n t e n t s
M a rch 1999
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 United States: Rallying to a new beat Photos by Stephen Shames
EDITORIAL
9 Myths and illusions Federico Mayor
PLANET
10 Nuclear decommissioning:
a problem that won’t go away Nicholas Lenssen
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Chicanos paint their way back Annick Tréguer
DOSSIER
17 A new deal
for the poor
John Ko h u t , Mirel Bran,
Andreas Harsono, Christian Lionet,
Valentin Simeon Zinga
18 ‘Human development’ (world map)
20 The final and optimal crisis of the century Rubens Ricupero
1. The markets
23 A fickle friend Andreas Harsono
25 Mali:growth without development Sophie Boukhari
26 Chile’s two-track therapy Eduardo Olivares
2. The state
27 USA:the self-help gospel Vicky Elliott
28 Twilight in Tunisia Sophie Boukhari
30 In the former Eastern bloc,a hazardous transition Omar Noman
3 . The people
32 Culture—the wild card Ramesh Singh
34 ATD’s streetwise librarians Martine Jacot
35 Madagascar:a waning tradition Soahangy Mamisoa Rangers
36 Another lost decade? Thierry Lemaresquier and Mümtaz Keklik
ETHICS
3 7 Genetic weapons: a 21st-century nightmare ? Ethirajan Anbarasan
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 Tracking down looted art Lucía  Iglesias Kuntz
CONNEXIONS
43 ONE intelligent island Malini Rajendran
Talking to…
46 Ahmadou Kourouma, an African novelist’s inside story
C o v e r : © Hans-Jürgen Burkard/Bilderberg/Studio X, Pa r i s
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
n
The 1960s and 1970s marked the
b e ginning of profound changes in
family structures in the United Stat e s.
As the population became more mobile,
many parents raised children without sup-
p o rt from the extended fa m i l y. D i vo r c e
rates rose,and so did the numbers of chil-
dren raised in single-parent households
and/or by parents working outside the
home.In the 1970s few mothers of infants
worked outside the home; now more than
half do.
Today a quarter of American families
with children under age three live in pove rt y.
Most of them are headed by one parent,
usually the mother, and many live in unsafe
neighbourhoods with poor access to quality
child care and health serv i c e s.To help ease
PARADING FOR HOPE. Focus: Hope, a
movement created in Detroit in the
aftermath of the city’s 1967 race riots,
holds an annual eight-mile walk for
justice which brings people together on
the birthday of deceased black rights
leader Martin Luther King Jr to
demonstrate their commitment to
interracial harmony. The movement is
working to rebuild the manufacturing
base of inner-city Detroit, and runs a
Center for Advanced Technologies (CAT)
in partnership with six universities and
industrial partners including Ford and
General Motors.
the plight of these fa m i l i e s , hundreds of
grassroots family support programmes have
sprouted across the United States over the
last 25 ye a rs , coalescing into a movement of
growing size and complexity.
The activities of a handful of these com-
munity-based schemes are illustrated on
these pages. All of them are locally ru n ,
with the participation of volunteers. They
encourage education and the work ethic,
promote economic development, rehabili-
t ate housing and fight cri m e .M a ny of them
work closely with local religious institu-
tions, and most are involved with the local
school—backing up teachers in the class-
room,providing after-school care, organi-
zing summer progr a m m e s , and making sure
students get to school safely.
United States R a l l y i n g
to a new b e a t
Photos by Stephen Shames
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
PREPARING FOR LIFT-OFF. These elementary
school students in Denver, Colorado, are
members of a Rocket Club sponsored by
the US National Society of Black
Engineers, a college and university
student organization.Their school is one
of several Family Resource Schools in
Denver which are open after school
hours and on weekends as community
centres offering adult basic education,
parenting education and family 
support services.
* Pursuing the Dream:What Helps Children and
Their Families Succeed, by Stephen Shames
(photographer) and Kathy Goetz Wolf, Family
Resource Coalition of America, 1997.
The photos are a small selection of
m a ny taken over a three-year period by
p h o t o j o u rnalist Stephen Shames, who tra-
velled through 15 States and the District of
Columbia meeting disadvantaged families
and reporting on how they are being helped
to triumph over terrible odds to stay toge-
ther and become self-reliant. In 1997 they
were published in a book by the Fa m i l y
Resource Coalition of America*. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
AMERICAN GRAFFITI. Roy Panton paints over graffiti on Third Street,
Los Angeles. He is a member of Bresee Youth Center, an after-
school centre for youths aged 11-18, which has a contract with the
city to paint out graffiti in an area with the highest gang-related
crime rate in Los Angeles and few parks or recreational facilities.
One thousand kids from central LA participate, two-thirds of them
boys. Fifty-five per cent are African-American, 42 per cent are
Latino. The Center employs former graffiti artists in a computer
design and desktop publishing business, and other children work
distributing flyers, in the computer lab, or at the Center’s store. At
a homework lab, volunteer mentors and peer tutors help students
with reading, writing and math skills.
+ …
l 14% of the US population was living below
the poverty line* in 1994
l More than 20% of the aged are income-poor
l 59% of children in income-poor households
were in one-parent families (1989-92)
l 4% of the population not expected to survive
to age 40 (1990)
l 11% of secondary-school-age children not
enrolled in school (1993-95)
l Real per capita GDP of poorest 20% of
population (1980-94): $5,800
l Real per capita GDP of richest 20% of
population (1980-94): $51,705
* $14.40 (1985 purchasing power parity) 
a day per person Source:UNDP
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
FRIENDS IN NEED. Friends of the Children
searches out abused, neglected and
violent youth in Portland, Oregon, and
gives them committed, full-time mentor
“aunts” and “uncles” from their own
community. Each child spends at least
five hours a week with his or her Friend,
going to the park or the mall, getting
help with homework, learning about
personal hygiene. A Friend is a constant
in the child’s life, which otherwise may
be full of upheaval.Above, during
basketball practice,
T.R. hangs on to Friends of the Children
volunteer Zach Harris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
WHEN PARENTS BECOME PUPILS. At Linapuni Elementary School in
Honolulu, Hawaii, parents Taeotafe Melei and Anna Tauala watch
their first-grade children show them how to work on computers
in their school’s computer lab. They are involved in the Parents
and Children Together (PACT) youth centre located at a housing
project that was notorious for gang activity and drugs until PACT
and community residents, with the help of police and the housing
authority, got together to do something about it.They set up a
Parent-Child Center to teach parenting skills, loaned money to
and trained residents to start businesses and set up a
neighbourhood patrol and the youth centre to keep teens and
pre-teens out of trouble.
POP CULTURE. Luz Martinez disciplines his
son, Carlos (left and opposite page).
They have been counselled by Avance, a
parenting programme working in public
housing projects and schools all over
Texas. Avance, which was started in
1970 by teacher Gloria Rodriguez,
encourages parents to use consistent
discipline by communicating with their
children rather than blowing up in
anger and hitting them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
STRONG, SMART, AND BOLD. Girls, Inc. is a national organization dedicated to helping girls
aged 9 to 18 to avoid early sexual activity and pregnancy and become “strong,
smart, and bold”. Its programme teaches assertiveness (how to say “no” and remain
popular) through role playing. Above, in an after-school talk group for middle school
girls in Orange County, California, 13-year-old Kristine receives support from other
girls after revealing some things that are troubling her. This supportive
environment, in a neighbourhood where gang members regularly accost and grope
girls on their way to school, is run by a professionally trained adult. More than half
the girls served through Girls, Inc.’s 750 national affiliates are from single-parent,
low-income families.
A TIMELY HAND. In Brooklyn, New York, the
Bedford Stuyvesant Volunteer
Ambulance Corps has cut response time
to three minutes and trained over 100
people as paramedics. Here, an
ambulanceman helps a man who was hit
on the head with a chair during a street
fight.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E D I TO R I A L
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 9
n
In 1989, the fall of the Berlin Wall was rightly welcomed because it marked the
collapse of a system that provided a degree of equality but rejected freedom.Today
there is a strong possibility that the system gradually spreading all over the world—
a kind of neo-liberal fundamentalism—may also collapse.In its obsession with freedom,
vital though freedom is, this fundamentalism disregards equality, a term which should
not be regarded here in purely static and statistical terms, but as something dynamic
and ethical. Equality can only be truly practised in a context of social solidarity or—to
borrow from the vocabulary of the French Revolution—of fraternity.
On the one hand, we have a world that is immensely rich in resources, p o s s i b i l i t i e s ,k n ow-
ledge and experi e n c e ; its constituent societies are freer and more dynamic than eve r.T h e r e
is an extraordinary potential for everyone to live a better life. But at the same time,new
and ever higher walls are being built both between peoples and between social groups within
individual countries.We are experiencing a travesty of development, which is creating a
world bipolarized into extremes of wealth and poverty.
The most common reactions to this disastrous situation are ve ry often the result of two
misapprehensions.The first can only be described as ideological or doctrinaire since it is
not based on the facts as they can be observed.It says that since the dominant system of
values and things is by definition more than sat i s fa c t o ry, the persistence of impove ri s h m e n t
is merely a temporary blip. Enough time has elapsed,h owe ve r , for us to see that this is not
the case, including in countries where this system has been part of the established order
for more than a century. One statistic is particularly eloquent. In just over 30 ye a rs ,
world production has approx i m ately doubled, but the gap has more than doubled betwe e n
the income of the 20 per cent of the world’s people living in the richest countries and the
income of the wo r l d ’s poorest 20 per cent, according to the United Nations Deve l o p m e n t
Programme.
The second misapprehension stems from another form of blindness and illusion,
namely the belief that poverty can be regarded exclusively as a moral issue,as if it had no
other kind of implications for those who are not poor.G l o b a l i z ation is, h owe ve r , a two - way
process. It enables the countries of the North to export their values and their paradigms
as well as their goods and capital to the countries of the South, but it also makes them much
more vulnerable to the backlash of crises that afflict these countries. Even in the North,
the cult of competitiveness is undermining situations once considered extremely stable.
The tide of precarity is rising steadily, so that people who have never been poor no longer
regard poverty as a distant prospect but as one so close that it could engulf them at any
moment.
Because of inadequate socio-economic deve l o p m e n t , the extraordinary upsurge of demo-
c r a cy over the past 30 ye a rs remains a ve ry fragile process, and there is a risk that the trend
m ay be reve rs e d .When hunger, disease and ignorance preva i l ,c i t i z e n s ’p a rt i c i p ation in deci-
sion-making becomes either non-existent or a mere charade.D e m o c r atic institutions become
empty shells, r e p r e s e n t ational bodies existing in form only and devoid of real signific a n c e .
Social divisions caused by economic distortions exacerbate the failures of democracy
which in turn pose serious threats to civil order within countries and to peace between
nations. It is high time to face these obvious facts. n
Myths and
i l l u s i o n s
Federico Mayor
The tide of precarity is
rising steadily, so that
people who have never
been poor no longer regard
poverty as a distant
prospect but as one so
close that it could engulf
them at any moment
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
P L A N E T
Nuclear  
a p roblem that   
Critics of current waste disposal and power plant dismantling schemes
believe that the legacy of nuclear power generation may impoverish and
endanger future generations for millennia to come
n
I m a gine traveling a thousand ye a rs
hence in a landscape with ri s i n g
concrete domes, shrouded with mys-
t e ry, f o r b i d d e n n e s s , and slowly decay i n g
defences of barbed wire and other barri e rs.
The ruins are guarded by a priesthood that
wards off all those who may feel inclined to
t r e s p a s s , wa rning people of the dangers
that lurk within the centre of their shrine.
Such may be the future fate of the more
than 500 civilian nuclear power reactors
built in the second half of the twe n t i e t h
century.
In nearly all industries, the disposal of
a n t i q u ated plants and equipment is a
s t r a i g h t f o r ward and relat i vely low-cost ope-
r at i o n . But the high levels of radiation pre-
sent in retired facilities make it extremely
complex and costly for nuclear powe r.U p o n
final closure, a nuclear power plant is
c o nve rted from an asset generating elec-
t ricity that can be sold to energy users , to a
concrete and steel mass of radioactive wa s t e
Dismantling: the nuts and bolts
The basic “deconstruction” of a nuclear plant takes place in a three-step process, the guidelines of
which have been established by the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA). These phases consist
of removing the fuel and auxiliary structures;ensuring safe confinement of remaining radioactive struc-
tures and components;and finally taking the plant apart and removing it from the site.
The first job is to empty the reactor core of its fuel and to remove it from the site. In the second phase,
all remaining radioactive materials are confined and sealed; the result is sometimes referred to as “ s a f e -
s t o r e ” . If left in place for 30 to 100 years, slightly contaminated materials such as metals and concrete will
lose much of their ra d i o a c t i v i t y. The third phase involves removing all elements from the site and making
it usable for other purposes.
Because appropriate national infrastructures do not yet exist in many countries, operators have
often opted to postpone final dismantling until approved solutions for waste disposal are available.
Another reason to opt for deferred dismantling is the cost-benefit (see article). In the case of Britain’s
Magnox Electric,for example, which has adopted a 135-year safe-storage strategy, the fact that decom-
missioning costs are discounted over 135 years lightens the company’s books today. n
awaiting eventual dismantling and isola-
tion from humans and the biosphere.
Although it is unlikely that a scenario such
as that envisioned above will occur, the fa c t
remains that human societies have yet to
d e t e rmine just what will happen with retired
nuclear power plants.
François Chenevier, the director of the
French nuclear waste agency, admonished in
1990 that “it would be irresponsible for us to
b e n e fit from nuclear power and leave it to
l ater generations to deal with the wa s t e .”Ye t
t h at situation had already occurr e d , and will
likely continue into the next three or so
d e c a d e s. Although nuclear reactors are
expected to operate for between 30 and 40
ye a rs , their radioactive legacy — i n c l u d i n g
the physical structure of retired reactors — w i l l
remain for thousands of ye a rs.
The problem of what to do with shut-
tered reactors is gr owing steadily.As of the
b e ginning of 1999, 94 nuclear reactors had
been retired. At the same time, only 429
r e a c t o rs were in operat i o n , meaning that one
out of eve ry 5.5 reactors that has ever been
built has already been permanently closed.
Yet only a handful of these have actually
been taken apart.
This lack of progress in decommissio-
ning reactors is partly planned. Some coun-
t ri e s , such as Japan and the United Stat e s ,h ave
announced policies that would have them
dismantle closed reactors within a decade or
t wo of closure. Other countri e s , such as
Canada and France, intend to wait seve r a l
d e c a d e s.At the extreme, the United Kingdom
has decided to wait more than 100 ye a rs
before finally tearing down any reactors at all.
T h u s , old reactors could become a near per-
manent fixture in some countri e s.
The irony in tearing down nuclear
p ower plants is that the longer they ru n ,t h e
more radioactive their interi o rs get from
neutron bombardment. And the higher the
r a d i o a c t i v i t y, the more diffic u l t ,d a n g e r o u s ,
and expensive it is to dismantle the plants,
and store or bury the residual radioactive
wa s t e .T h u s , waiting decades or longer bet-
ween closing reactors and actually tearing
them down makes the task that much easier
and safer to undertake.
‘It would be irresponsible for us to benefit
from nuclear power and leave it to later generations 
to deal with the waste’
* Energy specialist and former Senior Researcher at
Worldwatch Institute, Washington, D.C.-based policy
research unit. Portions of this article are drawn from
work done by Worldwatch.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
d e c o m m i s s i o n i n g :
   won’t go awa y Nicholas Lenssen*
Gundremmingen nuclear power plant in Bavaria,
Germany, during dismantling.
S t i l l , the radioactivity of the actual bu i l-
d i n g s — p a rticularly the reactor’s core ve s s e l
in which the nuclear reaction takes place—
will last for hundreds of thousands of ye a rs.
The radioactive substance nickel 59, f o r
example, is found in the reactor’s core, an
area that has experienced the heavy bom-
bardment of neutrons from fission’s chain
reactions. Nickel 59 has a radioactive half-
life of 80,000 years, meaning that it takes
roughly a million ye a rs before it is safe.
Current plans are to bury the waste,isola-
ting it from humans and the biosphere until
it becomes harm l e s s. H owe ve r , no country
has yet taken political action on just where
it will bury these materials.
Some scientists assure the public that
the problem of radioactive waste can be
s o l ved through such bu ri a l , although others
debate whether it can be “solved” in the
n o rmal fashion at all.Waste cannot be des-
troyed, nor can scientists prove that it will
s t ay out of the biosphere if bu ri e d . Proof of
a hy p o t h e s i s , via the scientific method,
requires demonstrat i o n .Yet with radioactive
waste,such proof would require hundreds
of human generations and entail extensive
ri s k s. C ri t i c s , from abori ginal people to
scientists, have often noted the presump-
tuousness of our civilizat i o n ’s willingness to
reach forward in time,borrowing from the
future that which we can never repay. To
leave a legacy that does not merely impo-
verish future life but may endanger it for
millennia to come, constitutes an act of
unprecedented irresponsibility.
Ignoring
early warnings
Politicians traditionally have been reluc-
tant to tackle an issue that will not come to
the forefront until after their political careers
have ended.Indeed,both government and
i n d u s t ry have long ignored wa rnings about
r a d i o a c t i ve wa s t e s , including the problem of
decommissioning nuclear power facilities.
In 1951, H a rvard Unive rsity president
James B. C o n a n t , f o rmer administrator of
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
P L A N E T
A technician wearing protective clothing slices through 
a wall with a cutting torch.
n Commercial nuclear power has appa-
rently reached its zenith—at least for
the current generat i o n .G l o b a l l y, capacity of
nuclear power has increased less than five
per cent since 1990, and in 1998 the wo r l d ’s
capacity actually declined slightly. E ve n
though global capacity is likely to rise in the
next year or two, it will almost cert a i n l y
decline precipitously in the ye a rs follow i n g
as the construction pipeline dries up, and
the closure of older, u n e c o n o m i c, and poli-
tically unpopular reactors accelerates.
By the end of 1998, 429 reactors were
operating, one less than five years before.
C o n s t ruction is taking place at 33 new reac-
t o rs. Of these, s e ven are likely to be
connected to the grid by the year 2001,
though another fourteen may never be com-
pleted.
Western Europe accounts for 150 ope-
rating reactors, though only one new one
remains under construction. In fact, West
European gove rnments have started addres-
Nuclear power today
sing the closure of existing reactors , as indi-
c ated by the German and Swedish gove rn-
m e n t s ’e f f o rts to begin phasing out nuclear
e n e r g y. E l s e w h e r e , g ove rn m e n t s — i n c l u-
ding the French—have started debat i n g
reducing their countri e s ’ dependence on
the atom.
In Central and Eastern Europe, as well as
Russia and Ukraine, some 68 reactors are
o p e r at i o n a l ,with four being actively wo r k e d
o n .Although many of these countries plan to
expand their nuclear industri e s , they fa c e
financial limitat i o n s , and public opposition
in the face of the 1986 Chernobyl accident.
The A m e ricas account for 123 reac-
t o rs , though only two—one each in A r g e n-
tina and Brazil—are under constru c t i o n .
In Canada and the United Stat e s , t h e
nuclear industry is under extraordinary
economic pressure as reactors are unable to
compete economically with other means
of providing electricity services.
Asia remains the last stronghold for the
nuclear power industry, with 88 reactors
o p e r ating and 26 under constru c t i o n ,t h o u g h
e ven here a slow d own is evident. Japan only
has two reactors under constru c t i o n , a n d
South Korea has scaled back its intent due to
the twin blows of political changes and eco-
nomic cri s i s.Ta i wan is building what is reco-
gnized by all as the country ’s final two reac-
t o rs , and efforts to create commercial nuclear
p ower industries in countries such as Indo-
n e s i a ,T h a i l a n d , and Viet Nam have all fa i l e d
in recent ye a rs.
China currently has the world’s most
ambitious programme, with a plan to go
from the three reactors it operates today to
more than 50 by the year 2020. It is pro-
b a b l e ,t h o u g h ,t h at China’s ambitious plans
will fail as they have in eve ry other country
when economics, s a f e t y, and decommis-
sioning and radioactive waste issues become
debated by the public. n
the wa rtime Manhattan Project to deve l o p
a nuclear bomb, spoke publicly of wastes that
would last for generat i o n s. In 1957, a U. S .
N ational A c a d e my of Sciences panel cau-
tioned that “unlike the disposal of any other
type of wa s t e , the hazard related to radio-
a c t i ve wastes is so gr e at that no element of
doubt should be allowed to exist regarding
s a f e t y.” In 1960, another A c a d e my com-
mittee urged that the waste issue be resolve d
before licensing new nuclear fa c i l i t i e s.
Such recommendations fell on deaf
e a rs , and one country after another plunged
ahead with building nuclear power plants.
G ove rnment bu r e a u c r ats and industry spo-
kespeople assured the public that decom-
missioning and nuclear waste could be dealt
with, yet few resources were dedicated to
these issues.Working with radioactive wa s t e
was “not glamorous . . . nobody got brow n i e
points for caring about nuclear wa s t e ,”
according to Carroll Wilson, first general
manager of the U.S.Atomic Energy Com-
mission. So the issue was figuratively, and
almost literally, swept under the rug until the
late 1970s when safety problems and acci-
d e n t s , questions about health effects, s o a ri n g
c o s t s , and eroding public confidence slowe d
reactor construction.
Still, most people probably believe to
this day that the problem of dismantling
retired reactors and disposing of their wa s t e s
is not an issue to be concerned with.That
may be true, but even if an engineering or
social solution, such as a nuclear pri e s thood
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
Island nations
threatened as
global warming
kills coral reefs
Global warming is killing coral reefs and posing
a threat to many of the world’s island nations,
especially in the Pacific and the Indian Ocean. A
recent study by the U.S-based Global Coral Reef
Alliance (GCRA) says that last year’s rise in global
t e m p e rature destroyed most of the coral reefs
surrounding the Seychelles archipelago in the
Indian Ocean.The colourful reefs, which are part
animal and part plant, protect coastlands from ero-
s i o n ,provide a home for many marine fish species
and attract tourism.As havens of biodiversity they
have been called the rainforests of the ocean.
“ There is no replacement for dead cora l s,” says Dr
Thomas Goreau, President of the GCRA, w h o
headed the study.
C o ral reefs may also be destroyed by events like
pollution and hurricanes but such damage is
minimal compared to that of global warming.
Scientists say additional heat in the atmos-
p h e r e, due to an increase in greenhouse gases such
as carbon diox i d e, is going into the oceans.W h e n
the water temperature goes beyond a certain
p o i n t , the corals respond by bleaching themselves,
expelling the algae that give them colour and
provide nutrition. If the warm condition persists for
too long, it weakens the cora l , sometimes fatally.
Wide-scale bleaching began to be observed in
the 1980s but dramatically increased last year, t h e
hottest year of the century. Researchers say abnor-
mally warm conditions persisted in sea water for
more than five months in 1998, causing extensive
damage to corals around island nations inclu-
ding Seychelles,M a u r i t i u s,Maldives and Sri Lanka.
“Ninety per cent of corals in Seychelles and in
some islands of Indonesia are already dead.We will
witness the consequences in the next ten years,”
says Goreau.The dead coral barriers have not disin-
t e g rated so far, but if and when they do low-lying
islands in the Indian Ocean region would witness
severe beach erosion, besides experiencing huge
losses in fis h e r i e s. n
With the aid of a claw arm,a worker stores nuclear waste containers behind a protective wall
made of lead and concrete.
t h at will protect the biosphere, is found,
there remains a huge, unpaid bill for achie-
ving it.
Despite some early real experience with
the cost of decommissioning plants, it still
remains uncertain just what those costs will
be—and who will pay. E s t i m ates of the dis-
mantling cost have ranged from 10 per cent
of the initial capital investment to 40 per
c e n t , and even 100 per cent. This trans-
l ates into costs ranging from $50 million to
more than $3 billion for a large reactor.
Who’s going to pay,
and how much?
In fact, one smaller reactor, the 167-
megawatt Yankee Rowe of Massachusetts,
which cost $186 million (1993$) to build in
1960 ended up having a dismantling bill of
more than $350 million three decades lat e r.
Indeed, if governments and utilities have
had a difficult time justifying the cost of
building and operating reactors , c l o s i n g
them could be an even harder sell.
In the United Kingdom, the gove rn-
m e n t - owned utility insisted for ye a rs that the
cost of tearing down redundant plants
would be relatively small. Then, in 1989,
when the gove rnment was in the process of
a failed attempt to privatize the country’s
nuclear industry, the utility admitted that
the decommissioning cost was roughly four
times that it had previously stated.
S i m i l a r l y, though most countries require
their operat o rs to collect funds for decom-
missioning during a reactor’s operat i o n ,
most of these funds consist of only “book-
k e e p i n g ”f u n d s.T h at is, the utility credits a
decommissioning fund with money, bu t
the actual cash is spent on other activities.
Thus, there is no guarantee that when the
utility actually needs the money for decom-
m i s s i o n i n g, it will have it.Yet even with sys-
tems that require actual cash reserves to be
c r e ated shortages can easily mount, if reac-
t o rs are shut down before the end of their ori-
ginal expected lifespan,as has been more the
rule than the exception with the nearly 100
r e a c t o rs now permanently closed.
In fa c t , the early retirement costs of reac-
t o rs in the United Stat e s ’e l e c t ricity markets
could run to more than $15 billion. In recent
ye a rs , S we d e n ’s gove rnment raised the
amount of money utilities need to collect for
d e c o m m i s s i o n i n g .No one can say for sure just
h ow much it will cost to handle the wa s t e
l e g a cy from nuclear powe r , though so far the
e s t i m ates continue to climb upwa r d .
In other countri e s , including France
and most developing countri e s , g ove rn-
ments intend to provide public funds to
dismantle reactors when the time comes,
ensuring that the current generation that
uses the power from nuclear plants will
pass on to future generations the cost of dis-
posing of them.
In the end, decommissioning could
become the largest remaining expense fa c i n g
the nuclear industry and the gove rn m e n t s
who have supported it, p a rticularly if effort s
to confine radioactive waste fa i l . E ven if no
more nuclear waste is creat e d , dealing with
existing waste will require attention and
i nvestments for a period that defies our usual
notion of time.The challenge before human
societies is to keep nuclear waste including the
actual remnants of shuttered plants in isola-
tion for the many millennia that make up
the hazardous life of these mat e ri a l s. In this
l i g h t , no matter what becomes of nuclear
p owe r , the nuclear age will continue for a
ve ry long time. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
C h i c a n o s
paint t h e i r
way back
Jobless young ethnics in several cities 
of the southwest US are finding a purpose in life
when they get together and paint murals
n
In the Arizona city of Tucson,100 km
from the Mexican border,1995 was a
record year for crime. Ninety-four of
its 667,000 inhabitants (29 per cent of
whom are Hispanic, 3.8 per cent blacks and
3.5 per cent Indian) were murdered.Most
of the victims were members of these mino-
rities.
One of them was Pete Va l e n z u e l a , a n
u n a g gr e s s i ve 15-year-old who didn’t belong
to a gang. He was gunned down in broad
d aylight while walking in the no-man’s - l a n d
b e t ween two ri val “ t e rri t o ri e s ” ,B a rrio A n i t a
and Barrio Sova c o. After his funeral,
h atreds intensified and Pe t e ’s friends swo r e
to avenge his death.
A Chicano mural painter named Julio
B e rn a l , and Martín Hern á n d e z , a commu-
nity organizer, realized it was urgent to
channel these dangerous emotions. T h e y
suggested painting a mural to commemo-
r ate the dead teenager and called it Por  V i d a
(In Favour of Life).The project attracted
about 40 young people aged between nine
and 17, who worked on it together for nine
months.To raise money to buy materials,
they washed car windows in the evenings
and at weekends.
“ Pete was like a brother,” s ays Gino
Molina.“I nearly went crazy after he died.
But mulling over our culture together,dis-
cussing what people feel about the family or
religion and trying to express all that on a
wall helped me a lot. I didn’t know any-
thing about art, but I just got on with it.If
I hadn’t, I would have gone on drinking. I
used to live in fear and I carried a gun.”
Today, 19-year-old Gino is f ather of a
baby and has just finished another mural
in memory of Pete which he painted by
himself on the wall of the local supermar-
k e t . There are now more than 130 such
murals in and around Tucson.
In Arizona,Texas, California and New
M e x i c o, Chicanos (Mexican immigr a n t s
and/or their descendants) are sizeable
m i n o rities which are still gr owing as a result
of immigration.It is hard for them to get a
foothold in American society and many of
them live in b a rri o s (Spanish for neighbou-
rhoods),either in the centre of big cities or
on their outskirts, away from areas where
there are jobs.These communities tend to
be self-contained and generate self-des-
tructive tensions and conflicts.Young Chi-
canos face many problems—dropping out
of school, violent gang rivalry, alcoholism,
d rug dealing and illegal gun possession—all
of which can lead to serious gang warfare
stirred up by agents of organized crime.
Defusing tensions
Walls in the b a rri o s are often daubed
with slogans and vicious gr a f fiti refle c t i n g
this violent wo r l d . But more and more
m a g n i ficent frescoes are appearing in this
urban landscape, reflecting a ve ry old
Mexican tradition of murals depicting
scenes from the past or aspects of modern
l i f e .After Mexico’s 1910 revo l u t i o n ,p a i n-
t e rs such as Diego Rive r a , José Clemente
Orozco and David A l faro Siqueiros
r e n e wed this form of expression and used
it to record the gr e at social struggles of
their time. In the 1970s, other artists took
over where they left off. In the United
S t at e s , a rt i s t s , s c u l p t o rs , p a i n t e rs and art
t e a c h e rs harnessed their ideals, skills and
talents to helping young members of their
ethnic group who had gone astray to find a
‘We sprayed graffiti on walls, smashed windows 
and raised hell at night, just for the fun of it. We all did.
In the end, I got into trouble with the police because
there are drugs everywhere here’
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
For some young descendants of the Yaqui Indians chased out of Mexico at the turn of the century,
painting is a way of rediscovering their roots and expressing their identity.
place in A m e rican society through art and
highlighting their shared roots.
Pedro Flores, who is descended from the
Yaqui Indians who were chased out of
Mexico at the beginning of the century,got a
bad start in life. “I hung out on the streets
with a gang of friends for ye a rs ,”he say s.“ We
s p r ayed gr a f fiti on wa l l s , smashed window s
and raised hell at night, just for the fun of it.
We all did. In the end, I got into trouble with
the police because there are drugs eve ry w-
here here.” He did his first paintings duri n g
community events organized by two mural
a rt i s t s , Miguel Flores, also of Yaqui stock,
and A n t onio Pa z o s , a Mexican who has been
living in Tucson for more than 20 ye a rs.
“Their paintings, inspired by our culture,
reminded me who I was and where I came
f r o m .They helped me get a grip on my s e l f.
N ow I couldn’t imagine life without pain-
t i n g .”Pedro resumed his studies and fin i s h e d
high school. At 18, he is a counsellor in the
r e c r e ation department of the Yaqui tri b e ’s
Pascua Reservation (more than 5,000 Ya q u i s
l i ve in the Tucson area).He is organizing seve-
ral painting and mosaic projects for yo u n g
p e o p l e . On walls and movable panels, t h e y
h ave together depicted major aspects of their
c u l t u r e , such as the traditional “dance of the
d e e r ” ,which takes place at night and goes on
until sunri s e . Pedro in turn tries to help tee-
n a g e rs break the vicious circle of violence and
m a r gi n a l i z ation they are trapped in.
“Most families in our neighbourhood are
alcoholic,” says John Escalante, another
Ya q u i . “The fat h e rs and mothers drink and
the cousins and uncles sell dru g s.We aren’t
taught about our culture in school. I t ’s denied
and bu ried by white society. If I hadn’t done
the murals with the other Ya q u i s , I wo u l d
n e ver have made it, because my fat h e r ,d r ow-
ned in his booze, c o u l d n ’t care less.”
In 1996,Pa z o s ,who is assistant director of
Tu c s o n ’s El Rio Neighborhood Centre,d e c i-
ded to take up a major challenge: m a k i n g
peace between two wa rring groups of jobless
C h i c a n o s , one Hispanic, the other Ya q u i .H e
also wanted to gi ve them a taste for wo r k .H e
decided on repainting the dirty gr a f fit i - c ove-
red wall of a power station which marked the
frontier between a Yaqui neighbourhood (Bar-
rio Libre) and a Hispanic neighbourhood
(South Tu c s o n ) .The electricity company gave
its permission and even funded the project.
One day, Pazos began painting on the
wall.A boy soon appeared and asked what
he was doing. “This is our wall,” he said.
Pazos replied sharp l y :“Then it’s about time
you all got down here. I t ’s your wall and
there’s a lot of work to do.”Young people
poured in from the two neighbourhoods,
and Pa z o s , p l aying up his Mexican roots
and Yaqui blood, organized them into a
team to paint pictures of their culture and
its highlights.Things got dangerously tense
at one point, t h o u g h , because the yo u n g
Hispanic Chicanos did not want the cultu-
ral roots of the Yaqui Chicanos depicted on
the part of the wall nearest the Hispanic
Chicano neighbourhood.
With the help of neighbours , Pazos tra-
ced the history of the pre-Columbian civi-
l i z at i o n s.“I wanted to show them that we ’r e
all of mixed blood, t h at half of all Mexicans
have both Spanish and Indian blood.They
realized they were mixed too and that this
should be shown in the mural.So the first
b rightly-coloured communal wall painting
was born and the ri val gangs learned to get
to know and talk to one another instead of
killing each other.
Leaving gangs behind
The U.S.-Mexican border city of El Pa s o
and its 606,000 mostly Hispanic citizens have
one of the highest jobless rates of any U. S .
city—nearly 12 per cent compared with the
n ational average of 5.4 per cent. One we l l -
k n own mural painter,Carlos Callejo,and an
a rt education teacher at Del Valle High
S c h o o l , María Almeida Nat i v i d a d , j o i n e d
forces to ferret out new talent, gi ve yo u n g
people from poor families a sense of self-
esteem and train them in a skill to help them
find a job.
“I wanted to involve my students in
group-produced wall paintings to help them
d i s c over the history of the region and their
own history,” says Almeida. That chance
came last year with the 400th annive rs a ry of
the arrival in El Paso of its first Spanish
c o n q u i s t a d o r , Juan de Oñat e .Doing a mural
around this theme in the high school gr o u n d s
“changed the live s ” of several pupils.
“It opened up my mind and helped me
get beyond my problems and leave behind
the gangs in my neighbourhood,” s ays Misael
A rm e n d á ri z . “I feel prouder of my Mexican
‘I wanted to involve my
students in gro u p - p ro d u c e d
wall paintings to help them
discover the history of the
region and their own history’
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
Boys in school
still outnumber
girls
“The most urgent priority is to ensure access
to education for girls and women,” says
article 3 of the World Declaration on Education for
All adopted by 155 countries in 1990.But a recent
UNICEF report, The State of the World’s Children
1999, reveals that only the industrial countries
have achieved parity between girls and boys in pri-
mary school enrolment.
The disparity in favour of boys still exists in
most developing countries. Of the 130 million
children aged 6 to 11 who are out of school in the
developing world, 73 million are girls. G e n d e r
inequality is most blatant in South Asia, where
there is a 12-point gap between boys’ and girls’
school enrolment. Next come North Africa and the
Middle East (nine points) followed by Sub-Sahara n
Africa (four points). Situations can vary widely
within the same region.Afghanistan bans girls
from going to school, whereas Bangladesh has
achieved parity and some A rab countries—Jordan,
Libya and Tunisia—are not far off. Latin America
and the Caribbean are an exception to the rule:
more girls than boys are enrolled in school. I n
Trinidad and To b a g o, UN I C E F s a y s, boys think wor-
king hard in school is not macho enough.
The advantages of educating girls are obvious.
An educated woman’s children are healthier and
she is more likely to see that they go to school. S h e
has more control over her fertility, plays a greater
part in economic life, and stands up more for her
rights at home and in the community.
UNICEF says that adopting a series of key mea-
sures would help reduce the disparity in favour of
b o y s. They include recruiting more female tea-
c h e r s ; rooting out gender bias from teaching
materials;making schools safe for girls, who are
sometimes victims of sexual hara s s m e n t ; l o c a-
ting schools closer to children’s homes in countries
where it is dangerous for them to walk the roads;
offering free education to eliminate, among other
things, the favouritism that benefits boys. n
Walls that speak volumes
This mural was painted by a group of Tucson teenagers in memory of a 15-year-old
who died a violent death.
roots and I express that in what I paint.”
Misael has already won several small pain-
ting commissions from the city authori t i e s
and will soon go to unive rsity to study art .
As a result of what he has learned while
organizing the painting, H e rnández has
rethought the stereotypes he has in his ow n
head and those of his community. “ We
decided to include in the mural people who
suffered at the hands of Oñat e — I n d i a n s
with hands and feet chopped off. History
sometimes gives its heroes shiny but false
images. A mural painter has a very big res-
p o n s i b i l i t y : o r d i n a ry folk don’t go to
museums but they do walk past outdoor
murals. So we have to paint the truth.”
M a ny other experiments are under way
in El Pa s o, where more than 150 wall pain-
tings now brighten up the city. Jesús Alva-
r a d o, a social worker in El Segundo, t h e
c i t y ’s poorest neighbourhood, runs city-
sponsored graphic art wo r k s h o p s.The most
recent murals show the struggle of the
Indians in Mexico’s Chiapas state.
These people,along with many others,
e x p e rience a kind of collective therapy
through the murals—intensive work which
a l l ows children and teenagers to find fulfil-
ment within their own culture as dignified
and respected human beings. n
Annick Tréguer
in Tucson and El Paso.
their need to be heard and recognized. N o t
long before, they had been giving vent to
their fru s t r ations with what they saw as sick
urban society—dirty streets in a city where
garbage was no longer being collected,
j o b l e s s n e s s , d rug addiction, p r o s t i t u t i o n
and so on—by hurling rocks and insults. B u t
now peaceful groups of children and tee-
nagers were expressing their values, fears
and hopes in imaginative paintings. They
also showed their sense of responsibility by
pitching in to help clean up the city.
To paint vivid murals you don’t need any
f o rmal educat i o n . Although 80 per cent of
Haitians can neither read nor wri t e , t h e y
h ave a tradition of painting magnificent gr a f-
fiti art in the street, on roadside hoardings and
on just about any surface they can fin d —
when the gove rnment allows them to.Pe r h a p s
the gr e y, dingy walls in all the wo r l d ’s cities are
just waiting for an opportunity to speak. n
n “ M a ny of the people who have done the
wall paintings aren’t professional artists
or decorators. They are children and tee-
n a g e rs who have started using colour. A
lot of these unemployed kids had lat e n t
talents that suddenly gave a voice to the
walls and the asphalt. It was a kind of pop
a rt . Professional painters and decorat o rs
only joined in much lat e r.” T h at is how
S e n e g a l ’s S u d - H e b d o magazine summed up
a remarkable movement called Set setal
(“clean and make clean” in the Wolof lan-
guage) that spread among the young people
of Dakar,the country’s capital.
Children and teenagers in some of the
c i t y ’s poorest neighbourhoods started cove-
ring walls with magnificent, c o l o u r f u l
murals,often with slogans scrawled across
t h e m .K i d s ’ stuff? Not exactly. Like gr a f fit i
a rtists in the United Stat e s , these yo u n g
people were using wall painting to express
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 17
A new d e a l for 
the poor
Collapsing national economies, natural disasters and political storms have
dragged millions of people below the poverty line in the 1990s. Meanwhile, in
many parts of the world, vast proportions of the population have been living
in misery for years without any solutions yet in sight. Against such a
backdrop, a new approach is emerging on ways to fight poverty. No longer
are open markets, government or the poor seen separately as the key to
eradicating poverty. Instead, a dominant view these days is that all three
need to be brought together in a concerted attack. In short, a new deal is
being offered to help the world’s poor. But is it enough? 
Our dossier looks at the prospects and problems in the three-pronged battle
against poverty.
n
In a west Bucharest public housing estate that
has seen better days, Liliana tries to prepare a
casserole for dinner.“But without meat.Meat
would be a luxury,” s ays the 41-year-old high school
t e a c h e r , who was once middle class but now counts
h e rself amongst Romania’s “new poor”, p a rt of the
fallout from the collapse of the state in the former
Eastern bloc.
Half way around the wo r l d , in Ja k a rt a , w h e r e
l u x u ry cars , designer labels and sky-high aspira-
tions once symbolized an economic boom, a recent
financial crisis has ove rnight deflated the economy
and plunged huge swaths of Indonesian society into
p ove rt y. In the middle-class Bumi Serpong Damai
housing complex, for example, children scave n g e
through the garbage looking for used bottles and old
n e w s p a p e rs , while adults often take to more extreme
m e a n s. “They are easily tempted to steal,” s ays a
s e c u rity guard at the complex.
M e a n w h i l e , in the fishing village of Cabique
on the shores of the Caribbean in southeastern
H a i t i , an entire community is sinking steadily deeper
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier- March 1999
into poverty as a result of environmental misma-
n a g e m e n t .D e f o r e s t ation means that the pounding
tropical rainstorms break up the earth and sweep
into the sea tonnes of sole which choke the coral
where the fish feed. As a result, the fish that once
supplied a livelihood for this village have moved on.
“It’s been 10 years now that I’ve done absolutely
nothing because there’s nothing to do here,” says
V i c t o r , 3 5 , a former soldier and a father of two
children,who picks up spare cash working in local
harvests.
E l s e w h e r e ,m a ny are locked in a vicious circle of
poverty that has existed for generations and seems
likely to pers i s t . In the village of Mimetala, 30 kms
from Yaounde, capital of Cameroon, 80-year-old
M a rie Biloa has been unable to work since a car acci-
dent 15 ye a rs ago. There is no state aid for the
u n e m p l oye d , but she did receive a payout from a pri-
vate insurance company.When her son-in-law stole
t h at money and ran off, she was left without a
means of support . To d ay Biloa dreams of going
back into her former business of selling snacks at a
street stall, but she lacks the $18 needed as a start-
up investment. Neither can the rest of her family
help. Biloa’s daughter has been abandoned by her
h u s b a n d .B i l o a ’s 20-year-old grandson is ill, with a
sickness that has not yet been diagnosed because the
family cannot afford to take him to hospital for
tests. And so Biloa is forced to exist on handouts
from villagers while a local charity gi ves her medical
help free of charge.
Like a disease that has gone into remission bu t
l ater strikes back with a ve n g e a n c e ,p ove rty has ove r
recent ye a rs resurged in places that once seemed to
be on the mend. As the Romanian, Indonesian and
Haitian vignettes illustrat e , the root causes range
from a political vacuum left in the wake of form e r l y
a u t h o ri t a rian regi m e s , to the collapse of fin a n c i a l
markets that once seemed to be the surest remedy for
p ove rt y, to natural disaster and environmental mis-
m a n a g e m e n t .The impact of these fa c t o rs has been
b r e at h t a k i n g : in the last two ye a rs alone, tens of mil-
lions of persons have been added to the lists of the
wo r l d ’s poor in Southeast A s i a . In the Fo rmer Sov i e t
Union and Eastern Europe, the number of poor has
swelled by some 170 million during this decade.
Meanwhile,as in the case of Biloa, among vast
stretches of humanity poverty lingers as it has for
decades without any immediate hope of a cure.
But how can pove rty be alleviated? In the 1980s,
the so-called “ Washington consensus”—an approach
built around the tri c k l e - d own economics of multi-
l ateral lending institutions headquartered in the U. S .
c a p i t a l — s aw the market as the saviour of the poor.B y
e n s u ring the efficient functioning of markets, e c o-
nomies would flo u rish and eventually wealth wo u l d
make its way down to the impove ri s h e d .T h at at
least was the theory. H owe ve r , markets have prove n
to be fickle fri e n d s.
In our special focus on poverty, Rubens Recu-
p e r o, S e c r e t a ry-General of the UN Conference on
Trade and Development, looks in greater detail at
an emerging new consensus on tackling pove rt y
(page 20). No one pretends to have all the ans-
we rs , but there does seem to be general agr e e m e n t
t h at a multi-faceted approach is vital: m a r k e t s ,
governments and poor people themselves need to
work in concert to find solutions to poverty.
Our section on the market shows that trade
and capital flows are still seen as vital ingredients in
the fight against pove rty but are not panaceas.
Poverty is like a disease that has
gone into remission but later
s t r i kes back with a vengeance
The human
development index
Traditional economic indicators
such as per capita gross national
product, give an incomplete idea
of the real socio-economic
conditions in a country, and to
provide a fuller picture the United
Nations Development Programme
(UNDP) created the human
development index (HDI) in 1990.
The HDI takes into account three
types of data:life expectancy;
educational attainment (adult
literacy and combined primary,
secondary and tertiary
enrolment); and standard of living
measured by real purchasing
power.
The index is a scale between
1 (the highest) and 0 (the
lowest).High human
development is regarded as
comprising HDI values of 0.8 and
above;medium comprising values
of 0.5 to 0.799;and low
comprising values below 0.5
Some 1.3 billion people
l i ve on less than $1 a
day and almost 3
billion on less than $2
a day.Almost 11% of
the inhabitants of the
i n d u s t ri a l i zed countri e s
l i ve on less than $11.4
d o l l a rs a day.*
* These figures and others
accompanying articles in this
dossier are taken from UNDP
reports published in 1998
‘Human  
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 19
A new deal for the poor
I n d e e d , the financial crisis in Southeast Asia (pages
23 and 24) has demonstrated that faith in eco-
nomic growth as a way out of poverty has led to
neglect of safety net-building to help the poor
during times of trouble.
Pa rt two of this dossier demonstrat e s , by looking
at the United States, the former Soviet bloc and
Tunisia (pages 24 to 31), under what circumstances
the state can play a constru c t i ve role in the fight on
p ove rt y, and why in some cases the state has prove n
i n e f f e c t i ve in finding solutions.The theme ru n n i n g
through this section is that the state must play a vital
part in the war on poverty, knowing when to inter-
vene and when to stand aside.
F i n a l l y, in recent ye a rs analysts, politicians and
n o n - g ove rnment aid organizations have increa-
singly discovered that poor people may themselve s
possess analytic and other abilities that can be ins-
trumental in grappling with poverty (pages 32 to
3 6 ) . Making use of the skills and cultural at t ri bu t e s
of the poor is proving to be much more important
than was imagined a decade ago. But  local cultures
can also be an impediment to improvement. n
John Kohut 
with contributions from journalists
Mirel Bran in Bucharest,Andreas Harsono 
in Jakarta,Christian Lionet in Port-au Prince,
and Valentin Simeon Zinga in Yaounde 
  development’ worldwide
Human development index
Source:Ozer Babakol,Human Development Report Office, UNDP, New York 1999
0.185-0.378 0.378-0.633 0.633-0.767 0.767-0.887 0.887-0.96 No data
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The final and optimal c r i s i s
of the century
20 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
Global financial crises have shaken faith
in the market as panacea. To d a y, the world is grappling for a new 
consensus to meet the challenges of globalization, development and poverty.
* Secretary-General of the United
Nations Conference on Trade and
Development (UNCTAD)
n
It may sound paradoxical to join two such
apparently contradictory words as “optimal”
and “ c ri s i s ” . I heard the expression for the firs t
time from the Director of the Institute for Interna-
tional Economics, C . Fred Bergsten, in Wa s h i n g t o n ,
D.C. He explained that it was be-coming increa-
singly common there, in the sense of the crisis being
gr ave enough to force the mighty to finally do some-
thing without being so serious as to render the
action useless and too late.
We may be approaching an optimal point.For eve n
the most enthusiastic prophets of the brave new wo r l d
of globalization (for instance,p a rticipants in the Wo r l d
Economic Fo rum at Davos) are beginning to question
the wisdom of their blind beliefs, and to look for a
human and social dimension to add to their world view.
One of the advantages of crises is that they can
p l ay a catalyzing role in changing our perception of
t h i n g s. And so, it seems, in the face of crisis we are
n ow witnessing gr owing signs of a new turning point.
This new current addresses humanity’s future in
t e rms of globalizat i o n ,d e velopment and pove rt y,a n d
asks a fundamental question: w h at is the nature and
sense of the economy? Is it an autonomous and largely
s e l f - r e g u l ating mechanism like the galaxies or the pla-
n e t a ry system, or is it a product of culture and society,
the result of societal choices based on va l u e s ?
Once more the impulse for change is coming not
so much from academic debate but from reality itself,
from the huge gaps between the rich and the poor.To
cite just one example:basic education for all would cost
$6 billion a ye a r.By compari s o n , $8 billion are spent
annually on cosmetics in the United States alone.
Such gr o t e s q u e , e ven obscene, contrasts show
d r a m atically that the twin problems of deve l o p m e n t
and pove rty are still ve ry much with us more than a
decade after the Washington Consensus claimed to
h ave reached “ u n i ve rsal conve r g e n c e ” around “ t h e
common core of wisdom embraced by all seri o u s
e c o n o m i s t s ” . In broad term s , this approach recom-
mended that gove rnments should: (i) pursue eco-
nomic stability in the sense of balancing the budget and
R u b e n s
R i c u p e r o *
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 21
A new deal for the poor
A homeless youth 
in London.
e l i m i n ating balance-of-payments defic i t s ; (ii) open
their economies to the rest of the world through trade
and financial liberalizat i o n ; and (iii) promote free
market capitalism through pri vat i z at i o n , d e r e g u l a-
t i o n , and other measures of liberalizat i o n .P r o p a g at e d
through the Intern ational Monetary Fund (IMF)
and the World Bank, the Washington Consensus has
been the dominant paradigm for development from
the early 1980s until the mid-1990s. Its introduction
entailed a total shift from earlier thinking, u s u a l l y
seen as a shift from state-led d i ri gi s m e to market-
o riented policies.
O ver the last few ye a rs ,t wo important challenges
to the Washington Consensus have emerged: firs t l y,
the UN D P’s sustainable human development approach
a n d ,s e c o n d l y, an emerging “ S o u t h e rn Consensus”,
founded on analyses made from the pers p e c t i ve of
c o u n t ries undertaking late industri a l i z ation and see-
king to catch up with rich countries in the global
e c o n o my.This Southern Consensus has not yet been
s u f ficiently elaborated to incorp o r ate predominantly
a gricultural economies of A f rica and the least deve-
loped countri e s. But it can be deduced from the
increasing convergence between the Latin A m e ri c a n
e x p e rience and East Asian development models.
The overselling of globalization
The sustainable human development approach
espouses a set of values different from those under-
pinning the Washington Consensus. Whereas the
Washington Consensus focuses on the promotion
of gross domestic product gr owth and has been
implemented through a top-dow n , d o n o r - c o n d i-
tionality-driven and outside-expert-led approach,
the sustainable human development approach
argues that development should improve the nat u r e
of people’s lives, and that it should be founded on
p a rt i c i p ation and a more equal part n e rship bet-
ween developing countries and aid donors.
M o r e ove r , the Washington Consensus has cracked
in the practical sense that real differences of opinion
h ave emerged in Wa s h i n g t o n ,b e t ween the IMF and the
World Bank,on the causes of the Asian crisis and how
best to handle it.The Chief Economist of the Bank,
Joseph Stiglitz, has argued that there is a need for a
“ p o s t - Washington Consensus” to achieve broader
o b j e c t i ves—higher living standards and equitable, s u s-
tainable and democratic development—using a wider
range of instruments to correct market fa i l u r e , to foster
c o m p e t i t i o n , and to control short - t e rm capital flow s.
It may be too early yet to announce the final
demise of the Washington Consensus despite Sti-
glitz’s critique,UNCTAD’s work in favour of a Sou-
t h e rn Pe rs p e c t i ve or the renewed emphasis on
p ove rty eradication resulting from the 1995 Copen-
hagen Summit for Social Development.
The emerging new consensus will be dri ven by the
main “ wo r k a b l e ” a l t e rn at i ve , East Asian models,
strengthened through their convergence with Lat i n
A m e rica experi e n c e , and adapted to A f rica and the
least developed countri e s.There are still serious obs-
tacles facing efforts to develop a more comprehensive
consensus that would finally be able to ove r c o m e
and reconcile the old ideological antinomies:m a r k e t
ve rsus stat e , p rice stability ve rsus economic gr ow t h ,
capital accumulation ve rsus income distri bu t i o n ,
competition and open integr ation into the world eco-
n o my ve rsus national industri a l i z ation and consoli-
d ation of a strong local productive capacity.
There will be a special difficulty in devising
strategies for long-term development in a world of
globalized money where speculat i ve attacks and
financial vo l atility can unravel and destroy in a
matter of weeks the economic growth and poverty
reduction achieved in 30 ye a rs , as happened recently
in Indonesia. In other wo r d s , here is where the pro-
blems of development and pove rty coincide with the
challenge of globalization.
After the fall of the Berlin Wall almost 10 years
a g o,g l o b a l i z ation was ove rsold to the public as a sure
way of bri n ging more accelerated gr owth and pros-
p e rity for all. But the record of economic gr owth in
the 1990s has been a dismal one, not only much
inferior to the exceptional rates of the 30 Glorious
Ye a rs of the post-war period but disappointing eve n
in comparison with the troubled 1970s. Still wo rs e ,
we are approaching the year 2000 without a solution
to the aggravation of the two most serious failures
of the twentieth century : mass unemployment and
growing inequality inside and among nations.
One of the problems with the conve n t i o n a l
approach to globalization is that it is too narrow. It
usually reduces and impoverishes a complex phe-
nomenon to just one of its components, t h e
Available food supplies
ought to be enough to
provide each of the
planet’s inhabitants
with at least 2,700
calories per day. But
more than 800 million
people go hungry.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier- March 1999
Meeting the basic
needs of the
p o p u l ations of
d eveloping countri e s
( fo o d , d rinking 
wat e r, s a n i t at i o n ,
health care and
e d u c ation) would 
cost roughly $40
billion a ye a r,
or 4% of the
combined wealth of
the 225 ri chest people
in the wo rl d .
Yardsticks of poverty
Arecent trend has been to regard poverty as a process of denial of basic opportunities and choices
for human development, rather than just a shortage of income. The United Nations Deve-
lopment Programme (UN D P) ’s Human Development Report 1997, which was exclusively devoted
to poverty era d i c a t i o n , stressed the multidimensional nature of poverty and introduced a human
poverty index (HPI) containing three va r i a b l e s : the percentages of people expected to die before
age 40,of illiterate adults, and of people without access to health services and safe water and
of underweight children under five.
The dollar-a-day poverty line is one of the most widely used measures of impoverishment. I t
defines the poor as those whose income is less than a dollar a day per person,an amount cal-
culated at purchasing power parity (PPP) to be enough to buy a bundle of goods necessary for
s u r v i va l . PPP adjusts for differences in local costs in different countries.The standard for the dollar-
a-day definition is based on 1985 dollars and prices.
In 1998, UN D P published a report entitled Overcoming Human Poverty, which contained the
following definitions:
Human poverty:The lack of essential human capabilities, such as being literate or adequately nou-
r i s h e d .
Income poverty: The lack of minimally adequate income or expenditures.
E x t reme poverty: Indigence or destitution, usually specified as the inability to satisfy minimum
food needs.
O v e rall poverty: A less severe level of poverty, usually defined as the inability to satisfy essential
nonfood as well as food needs.The definition of essential nonfood needs can vary significantly across
c o u n t r i e s.
Relative poverty: Poverty defined by standards that can change across countries or over time.
An example is a poverty line set at one-half of mean per capita income—implying that the line
can rise with along with income.
Absolute poverty: Poverty defined by a fixed standard, one example being the international dollar-
a-day poverty line.Another example is a poverty line whose real value stays the same over time
so as to determine changes in poverty in one country.
The UN D P says that out of 130 countries,90 have developed operational definitions of extreme
poverty and 86 have definitions of overall poverty, only a minority of which are solely income-based.
Almost all the rest combine income with measures of people’s living conditions and quality of life.
“ This represents an important shift.A decade ago, only a minority of countries had official defin i-
tions of poverty and most of these were based exclusively on income.” n
e conomic unific ation of commercial markets, i nve s t-
ment opportunities and financial markets on a pla-
n e t a ry scale. In that reductionist way, we miss the ri c h
d i ve rsity of what actually is an historic process with
a ve ry strong cultural element. A rising out of the
breakthroughs in electronics and telecommunica-
tions which constitute the first scientific revolution to
change our perceptions of time and space, unlike the
previous ones that dealt basically with energy and
m at t e r , g l o b a l i z ation represents the unific ation of
the planet for human interaction and mutual know-
l e d g e .But scientific and technological breakthroughs
are no guarantees in themselves that the new tech-
niques will be used not to dominate but to liberat e
and promote human beings. In the past, it was pre-
cisely the scientific revolution of Galileo and Newton
which gave the West the technological superi o rity that
made colonialism and imperialism possible.
The situation now is certainly more decisive in
t e rms both of promise and threat s. I n d e e d , n e ve r
before has knowledge become so crucial as to consti-
tute the ve ry condition for deve l o p m e n t .As we move
away from a type of economy where success wa s
d e t e rmined by capital, cheap labour or abundance of
resources towards one that is know l e d g e - i n t e n s i ve ,t h e
monopoly of inform ation and technology may easily
become a frightening weapon for domination and
o p p r e s s i o n , the roots of inequality.
We are beginning to understand the first prin-
ciples of a new branch of economics, information
economics. The old presumption was that infor-
m ation had a zero or negligible cost.We now know
t h at inform ation has a cost and that this cost of tran-
saction may be the difference between economic
success or failure.Without access to information
there will be no access to markets.The market solu-
tion will not always be the optimal solution because
markets are systems to process and convey infor-
m ation and they are never perfect in performing this
t a s k .F i rms and economic actors , people and gove rn-
m e n t s , h ave to deal with inform ation and some
will prove more able at it than others.Those who are
well educated and who have good access to infor-
m ation and knowledge will prevail in a highly com-
p e t i t i ve wo r l d .W h at will happen then to the legi o n s
of losers in the global competition, unskilled wor-
k e rs in rich countries or marginalized countri e s
and continents like A f rica? To take care of them, we
will have to redefine the concept of competition as
a game that not only needs clear rules and an impar-
tial arbiter, as in the World Trade Organizat i o n , bu t
also, like all games, requires training, preparation
and educat i o n . In the same way as one has to learn
how to play a game, nations need to learn how to
produce, how to trade, how to compete. Govern-
ments and international organizations must strive
to make inform ation and knowledge available to all
in an equal way.
The return of Adam Smith
E ven if we find how to share inform ation and
k n owledge in such a way as to allow widespread eco-
nomic development of all or most countri e s , this will
not guarantee per se a fair and balanced distri bution of
the results among all cat e g o ries of citizens.A c c e l e r at e d
economic gr owth is certainly a necessary condition for
rapid pove rty reduction, as was demonstrated in
China and Asian countries in general. It is not,
h owe ve r , a sufficient condition, as we have learn e d
from some Latin A m e rican examples of extreme
c o n c e n t r ation of wealth and income and from what is
n ow happening in many industrialized societies.
We still do not know enough about how to
balance growth and distribution, or reward initia-
t i ve with relat i ve equality. D e ve l o p m e n t ,p ove rty and
globalization are problems that will only be solved
if we go back to the ori ginal approach to economics
as “political economy ” , as part of what Adam Smith
t a u g h t : moral philosophy, t h at is, the economy as a
product of the “ p o l i s ” , the city of human beings. N o t
as the planetary system whose laws we cannot
change, but something that is the result of societal
choices based on shared values. And the first of all
values is that the economy was created for man
and not man for the economy.This is the only way
to promote genuine hope, and faith that the future
will be better than the past. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 23
A new deal for the poor
1. The m a r k e t s
Looting in the ethnic Chinese
district of Jakarta,Indonesia,
in May 1998.
n
Hadijah sits cross-legged on the floor inside her
t i ny, dimly-lit tin-roofed cabin in the Cilenggang
area in the southwe s t e rn belt of Ja k a rta and tri e s
to hide her embarrassment as she describes her
attempts to find work.
“They say I’m too old,” the 43-year-old widow
m u t t e rs ,r e f e rring to a South Korean fa c t o ry and a
German business centre not far from her house.
Managers at both companies have rejected her job
application.
Hadijah’s fruitless effort began in October last
year after she lost her job of 24 ye a rs as a tea lady at
a Jakarta car spare parts manufacturer, which was
badly hit by a sudden fall-off in demand in the
wake of the Asian financial crisis that began its
sweep across the region two years ago.
M e a n w h i l e , rampant inflation has meant
Hadijah spends far more money than before the
crisis to buy food and to keep her only daughter in
school. Prices of basic commodities such as rice,
sugar, cooking oil and kerosene have increased,in
local currency terms, three to five times what they
were before the crisis hit.
Against a backdrop of awesome economic
growth in the 1970s, 1980s and early this decade,
the common wisdom across Southeast Asia used to
be that the market was the key to eradicat i n g
poverty.To a large extent that indeed was the case.
However, the financial crisis has shaken that faith
and exposed the weakness of the economic tri c k l e -
down approach to poverty alleviation.
“The ‘ m a gic of the market’ m ay work for those
who have ready access to capital, i n f o rm ation and
s k i l l s ,” I n d o n e s i a ’s education and culture minister
J u wono Sudarsono last August told an intern at i o n a l
seminar on Indonesian reform s ,“ but not for those who
lack educat i o n , skills and well-placed connections.”
According to Indonesia’s Central Bureau of
Statistics, the number of people living below the
p ove rty line—those who consume a minimum
2,100 calories a day—had soared to 95.8 million or
about 48 per cent of Indonesia’s total population of
202 million by the end of 1998.
It is indeed a huge setback. In 1976 Indonesia had
54.2 million poor people or 40.1 per cent of the whole
p o p u l at i o n . But by 1996, after two decades of rapid
economic gr ow t h , the wo r l d ’s fourth most populous
c o u n t ry had reduced the number of the poor down to
22.5 million or 11.3 per cent of the populat i o n .
Economic recove ry is vital if the trend is to be
r e ve rs e d .H owe ve r , as a World Bank report points out,
the rapid economic gr owth of previous ye a rs had
papered over long-standing problems with regard
to pove rty alleviat i o n .Among these are persistent poc-
kets of pove rty and rising inequality, weaknesses in
labour rights and need for social security nets.
“A rapid return to macroeconomic stability and
gr owth through distri butionally favourable adjust-
ment policies is the only way to begin to put a flo o r
In A s i a , financial crisis has thrust millions back into
impoverishment and shattered faith in the ability of marke t s
alone to address the problems of the poor. But can the re g i o n
capitalize on the lessons learned from the cra s h ?
A fickle friend
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
Official development
assistance in steep decline
In 1970 the world’s rich countries proclaimed their intention of devoting a minimum of 0.7 per
cent of their gross national product (GNP) to official development assistance (ODA) to the world’s
most disadvantaged countries.Within the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development
(OECD) and at the General Assembly of the United Nations, they committed themselves to
considerably increasing grants and concessional loans to help beneficiary countries to speed up
their economic and social development.
Almost 30 years later this target was only achieved by Denmark,Norway, Sweden and the
Netherlands, which devoted between 0.7 per cent and 1 per cent of their GNP to ODA.What’s
m o r e, o v e rall ODA has so far declined that in 1997 it was running at its lowest level for 50 years,
since the Marshall Plan of 1947.According to a World Bank report entitled Assessing Aid—What
Works, What Doesn’t, and Why, published in November 1998,official development assistance
flows declined by one-third in real terms between 1991 and 1997. In 1997 ODA totalled no more
than 0.22% of the GNP of all donor countries, and only 0.08% of the GNP of the United States,
which held the wooden spoon. Only Canada and Japan increased their ODA in real terms in 1997.
Aid now only constitutes one quarter of financial flows to developing countries, and there are
big disparities in sources and volumes of development finance in each region.According to OECD,
in 1997 sub-Saharan Africa received an average of some $27 per capita of aid and $3 per capita
of foreign direct investment.By contra s t , Latin America and the Caribbean received $13 per capita
of aid and $62 of foreign direct investment.
The World Bank recommends states to target their ODA to countries that have made big efforts
to achieve “ s o u n d ” management (non-corrupt institutions, respect for the rule of law and economic
f r e e d o m s, open marke t s, e t c . ) . It estimates that if $10 billion of aid were directed towards these coun-
tries which are unjustly penalized by the overall decline of ODA, 25 million persons would be rescued
from poverty. n
under falling incomes of the poor,” says the World
Bank report.
In Indonesia, as in many other parts of A s i a ,h o u-
seholds by and large have few formal mechanisms to
protect them from pove rty resulting from job losses,
disability or agi n g .I n s t e a d ,most rely pri m a rily on per-
sonal savings and informal family and community
l i n k s. But the financial crisis has cut so deeply that
those bu f f e rs against pove rty are proving to be too thin
for comfort .
H a d i j a h , for example, spent 1.5 million rupiah of
her separation pay to build a small food ve n d i n g
stand in front of her house last December. A niece
c o n t ri buted 0.5 million rupiah to buy basic com-
m o d i t i e s.At the end of the month they are able to take
home a paltry 150,000 ru p i a h , under $20 at recent
exchange rat e s.
But not eve ryone has even that frail surv i va l
mechanism and the result has been the wo rst social
tension and violence seen in decades.
Crime triggered by hunger
Amid mounting ethnic and religious tension, ri o t s
and looting have taken place in Indonesian tow n s
and villages as demoralized soldiers do nothing bu t
look on. One of the wo rst riots took place in Ja k a rt a
on 14-16 May 1998 when thousands of looters ran
amok attacking properties owned by ethnic Chinese,
whose economic prominence in this country has
made them a target. More than 1,200 people we r e
k i l l e d , mostly in bu rned superm a r k e t s , and many
Indonesian women of Chinese descent were sexually
h a r a s s e d .E ven outside of ri o t s , looting has become a
major problem, with highwaymen along an import a n t
road linking Ja k a rta with Surabaya ,I n d o n e s i a ’s second
most populous city, simply stopping the dri ve rs and
taking over the trucks loaded with food
I r o n i c a l l y, the deva l u ation of Indonesia’s curr e n cy
since the crisis broke,along with rising food pri c e s ,h a s
caused a huge shift in the internal terms of trade in
favour of fa rm e rs ,while palm-oil and cocoa producers
h ave benefited from soaring world prices for their
p r o d u c e . The World Bank says rural consumption
has increased 10 per cent over the past ye a r.
“The driving force behind this crime is hunger.
The hungry and angry people provide a good place
for the devil,” said rural sociologist Loekman Soe-
t risno of Gajah Mada Unive rs i t y.
In response to the cri s i s , the gove rnment has
sold cheaply or even gi ven away basic commodities
like ri c e , sugar and cooking oil. C h a rity organizat i o n s
h ave organized cheap lunch boxes for poor wo r k e rs
and unemployed people.
But many analysts say that the effort is not
e n o u g h .
As recommended by the Intern ational Mone-
t a ry Fund, the World Bank and the Asian Deve l o p-
ment Bank—key sources of finance to prop up Indo-
nesia during the crisis—the gove rnment in Ja k a rta has
set aside about $2.4 billion in funds to carry out a
social safety net programme for the 1998/1999 fis c a l
ye a r.The programme consists of food subsidies for
the poor, health services and subsidized medicine,
financial help for schools and funds for social work to
boost employ m e n t .
H owe ve r , implementing the progr a m m e , i n t r o d u c e d
early last ye a r , is diffic u l t .According to Marie Muhammad,
who chairs a programme monitoring team, only about 30
per cent of funds had been disbu rsed by the beginning of
this year due to overcautiousness of gove rnment officials in
parceling out the aid for fear of any graft or other irr e g u-
l a ri t i e s.
L i k e w i s e ,T h a i l a n d , also hard hit by the financial cri s i s ,
is trying to improve its social security system. S e verance pay,
the key net for the unemploye d , last year was extended to
10 months from six months. The gove rnment has also
launched a program to provide free health care for laid-off
wo r k e rs and their fa m i l i e s.Aid from multilateral fin a n c i a l
institutions is being channeled increasingly into training and
other programmes to help the unemploye d .
E ven so, such efforts appear to be far from adequat e .
Southeast Asian countries have been so enfeebled by the
c risis that now, when social security is most needed, is also
the most difficult time for gove rnments to raise funds for
social welfare. So far, safety net programmes have been
set up as largely short-term measures to deal with the
effects of the crisis rather than as steps forward to restru c-
t u ring socio-economic systems over the long term with a
view to protecting the poor.
H owe ve r , Southeast Asia may at least have made a
s t a rt towards more aggr e s s i ve attempts to buffer the poor
against future crises in that there is now at least recognition
t h at the market alone is not enough to alleviate pove rt y.
n
Andreas Harsono in Jakarta,Indonesia
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 25
A new deal for the poor
Whose fault is it that economic growth has been accompanied by increasing
poverty in one of the world’s poorest countries?
M a l i : g rowth w i t h o u t
d e v e l o p m e n t
Most of the poor 
scrape a living in the informal
economy.
The wo rl d ’s thre e
ri chest people have
assets that exceed the
combined gro s s
domestic product of
the 48 least deve l o p e d
c o u n t ri e s.
n
In the last few ye a rs ,M a l i ’s economic gr owth rat e
has picked up,but most Malians have n ’t noticed the
b e n e fit s.“ I t ’s gr owth without jobs,d e velopment or
f r e e d o m ,”s ays A m i n ata D.Tr a o r é , a psychosociologi s t ,
bu s i n e s swoman and decorat i ve artist who is Mali’s
minister of culture and touri s m .“Macroeconomic per-
f o rmance is being achieved at the cost of the basic and
urgent needs of most of the populat i o n ,” she say s.
M a l i ’s gross domestic product (GDP) grew on ave-
rage by five per cent a year between 1994 and 1996,
and pove rty by two per cent a ye a r , according to a
r e p o rt by the country ’s Observat o ry for Sustainable
Human Development and the Struggle against Pove rt y
(ODHD) published in July 1998. The new poor,
Traoré say s , “are people who’ve lost their jobs and
those who’ve never had a job”—people who’ve been
laid off from state bodies regarded as ove rs t a f f e d ,a n d
young people without a job.Most of them gr av i t ate to
the informal economy, where taxes are not paid and
figures are unava i l a b l e .“Without this sector the situa-
tion would be explosive ,” according to Tr a o r é .
To d ay, 72 per cent of of Mali’s 9.2 million popu-
l ation live below the pove rty line, i . e . on barely $180
a year (less than 50 cents a day ) , according to ODHD.
The indicat o rs present a grim picture. One third of
Malians cannot expect to live to the age of 40;a l m o s t
f o u r - fifths are illiterat e ; over half lack clean wat e r
s u p p l i e s ; and two-thirds have no access to health ser-
v i c e s.Half the children under five suffer from chronic
m a l n u t ri t i o n , as against 35 per cent in 1988. T h e
only bright spot is a slow d own in the rate at which
p ove rty is spreading. B e t ween 1989 and 1994, t h e
number of people living below the pove rty line rose
by 11 per cent a ye a r , as against two per cent since.
Traoré believes that the World Bank and the Inter-
n ational Monetary Fund bear considerable responsi-
bility for deteri o r ating living conditions. In a recently
published book, L’ E t a u (Actes Sud publishers , Pa ri s ,
1 9 9 9 ) , she claims for her country the right to shape its
own destiny. For several ye a rs , “decisions have been
taken without the Malians, and for most of the time
without their even being aware of the fa c t , and this is
bound to jeopardize chances of consolidating the
d e m o c r at i z ation process,”she laments.“The needy are
hardest hit by measures imposed on A f ri c a ’s ove ri n-
debted countri e s. These measures also discredit the
s t at e ,which is called on to withdraw from such vital sec-
t o rs as educat i o n ,h e a l t h , water supply and sanitat i o n .
In short , social we l fare has to be pri vatized so that the
s t ate can meet its commitments to its creditors.”
Bad management
She believes that these reforms aim to consoli-
d ate the power of the wo r l d ’s ruling elite.“Their pur-
pose is to create more opportunities for the powe r f u l
and they extend control of our minds as well as our
r aw mat e rials by the rich countri e s.” She also
b e l i e ves that they undermine state efforts to improve
the situation of the depri ve d .At the end of 1994, t h e
Malian gove rnment decided to focus on sustai-
nable development and the struggle against pove rt y,
drawing up a “national strategy”in 1997. But this
“laudable option” will fail if the Intern ational Mone-
t a ry Fund and the World Bank continue to follow the
same approach, Traoré believe s. “Under adjust-
ment policies the state has ve ry little room for
m a n o e u v r e . Each dossier—employ m e n t , yo u t h ,
wo m e n , h e a l t h , e d u c at i o n , the env i r o n m e n t —
requires money that is not locally ava i l a b l e . To
obtain finance from funding bodies means sub-
mitting to conditions that are supposed to improve
management and productivity. These conditions
are actually counter-productive: low wages are a
d i s i n c e n t i ve to wo r k e rs ,p e rp e t u ate bad management
and spawn unrest and political instability.”
Traoré does not deny the responsibility of
A f rican states in the bankru p t cy of their econo-
mies. “I don’t say there isn’t corruption. . . . But I
plead for the sharing of responsibility. Most of the
decisions that have been taken in Africa have been
the result of advice, guidance, and in some cases
constraint. Now we must be lucid, rigorous, and
demanding both on ourselves and on those who
claim to help us.” n
Sophie Boukhari
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
Chile’s two-track therapy
Ultra-liberal economic measures strongly backed up by state intervention
have reduced poverty, but there are still glaring inequalities
n
Chile is the only country in Latin A m e ri c a
where pove rty has substantially diminished
over the past decade.The United Nations Eco-
nomic Commission for Latin A m e ri c a , based in
Santiago de Chile, says the trend began in 1987
under the Pinochet dictat o rs h i p, t wo ye a rs before the
return of democracy.
In that ye a r , 39 per cent of Chileans lived below
the poverty line. By 1996, the figure had almost
halved, to 20 per cent. Chile’s president, Eduardo
Frei,says two million of his country’s 14.5 million
people have emerged from pove rty since 1990 and
that the incidence of poverty has fallen by half.
There seem to be three major reasons for this:
sustained economic gr ow t h , increased social spen-
ding and the launching of several job-creation pro-
grammes. All the politicians claim credit for it, of
course.The right wing, pointing out that poverty
began to decline towards the end of military rule,
claims it was largely the result of ultra-liberal eco-
nomic policies applied since 1978.
General Augusto Pinochet brought in econo-
mists from Milton Fri e d m a n ’s “Chicago school”
of monetarists and Chile became the first Lat i n
A m e rican country to rigorously deregulate and pri-
vatize its economy, open up markets and cut taxes.
I n f l ation was tamed, gr owth began again and
foreign inve s t o rs flocked to Chile, which became
k n own as “the jaguar of the South” in the lat e
1980s.
The “Chicago Boy s ” had promised exceptional
p r o s p e rity and an automatic decline in pove rt y.
But the ranks of the poor shrank only slowly. And
as street protests grew with the approach of the
1988 and 1989 elections, the regime came up with
a raft of social measures.
President Pat ricio Ay lw i n , elected in 1989, a n d
his successor, Eduardo Frei, who has been in powe r
since 1994, took deliberate steps to reduce pove rty and
counter the negat i ve effects of ultra-liberal policies,
which had tolerated a high rate of pove rt y.At the same
t i m e , gr owth remained strong—an average of 7 per cent
a year between 1991 and 1997 until it slowed down last
year from the effects of the Asian financial cri s i s.
In 1996, 71 per cent of all government expen-
diture went to the social sector and minimum wa g e s
rose 55 per cent in real terms between 1989 and
1996, which was faster than labour productivity.
Business was called upon to share the cost of this
dramatic switch and did not object overmuch to
paying taxes on their increased profits. However, a
supertax on the rich would have set off a storm of
protest,so was out of the question.
Along with this effort to redistribute wealth as
p a rt of President Ay lw i n ’s “ fair deve l o p m e n t ”p r o-
gramme, steps were taken to encourage new busi-
n e s s e s. Utilities like electri c i t y, t e l e p h o n e s , d ri n-
king water and adult education were subsidized.
Other programmes sent young professionals off to
the country ’s poorest regions to stimulate deve-
lopment there using local labour.
The Solidarity and Social Investment Fund
(FOSIS) has also played a big part and today
finances more than 18,000 production projects put
together by rural fa m i l i e s , fis h e rm e n ,r e p r e s e n t at i ve s
of Indian peoples and small bu s i n e s s e s.The seve n -
year-old fund also has a budget to train people for
these projects.
But there is still a “social debt” which Chile
has not yet been able to wipe out:the gap between
the ve ry rich and the ve ry poor. A recent Wo r l d
Bank report shows that Chile is one of the world’s
ten countries where inequalities are most pro-
nounced.The richest 10 per cent of its population
have incomes 30 times bigger than the poorest 10
per cent.This huge gap is Chile’s challenge for the
future, despite the great progress made so far in
reducing poverty. n
Eduardo Olivares 
in Santiago
The “Chicago Boys” had
promised prosperity and an
automatic decline in poverty.
But the ranks of the poor 
shrank slowly
A soup kitchen in Santiago,
Chile.
E a ch ye a r, almost 
12 million ch i l d ren die
b e fo re their fif t h
b i r t h d a y.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 27
A new deal for the poor
n
It is not easy, in the glassy canyons of San Fran-
c i s c o ’s financial distri c t , to walk a block amid the
early morning commuters without passing a
huddled heap—a person without a home—stret-
ched out on a bed of cardboard. B e g g a rs sitting by
garbage cans hold out frying pans for change from
manicured ladies. In the subu r b s , a new underclass
of scave n g e rs wheel stolen shopping carts miles
through the streets, heaped with the bottles and cans
they trade in for a pittance at the recycling centre.
Rudolph Giuliani, the mayor of New Yo r k ,m ay
have chased the vagrants off the streets of Man-
h at t a n , but the reality of pove rty for most ordinary
Americans is all too plain to see.How is it that the
richest nation in the industrialized world main-
tains a pove rty level that has hovered around 13 per
cent for a good two decades (and 16.5 per cent in
1997)?
Welfare is for those
who fall by the wayside
Wealth in the United States accumulates at
wa rp speed, but it concentrat e s.The richest 20 per
cent of A m e ri c a n s , according to UN Deve l o p m e n t
P r o gramme fig u r e s ,e a rned 8.9 times more than the
poorest 20 per cent.Yet the majority of the A m e ri c a n
e l e c t o r at e , as far as one can ascert a i n , is not uncom-
f o rtable with this equat i o n .Witness President Clin-
ton’s last State of the Union address, in which he
boasted of cutting the welfare rolls in half, offered
little or nothing that might materially improve the
existence of the poor—and rapidly earned himself
approval ratings of 76 per cent in the polls.
One thing is clear.The United States does not
have a social contract.This “new” nation of hete-
rogeneous states has never acquired the respect for
an all-providing, munificent central authority that
the European nation states inherited from the
m o n a r c h i e s. A m e ricans are deeply suspicious of
g ove rn m e n t , and reluctant to pay for anything that
might expand its operat i o n s.Their rates of taxat i o n
remain the lowest of the industrialized nat i o n s.T h e
p rinciples of utilitari a n i s m ,s t riving for the gr e at e s t
b e n e fit for the gr e atest number, h ave never found a
s y m p athetic hearing in a society that prides itself on
its worship of the individual.
M e a n w h i l e , the Protestant work ethic perva d e s
political discours e .We l fare in A m e ri c a , in the shape
of Aid to Families With Dependent Children, was
o ri ginally intended to benefit widows or wo m e n
with children born out of wedlock—reserved for
those families that could not depend upon the ear-
nings of a male householder. S o m e h ow, there is an
indelible association in the American psyche that
makes it immoral to live off the state.Where Euro-
pean national insurance plans espouse unive rs a l
e n t i t l e m e n t , we l fare is for those who fall by the
wayside.To be poor in America carries in a certain
measure the stigma of sin—a failure to realize the full
potential of being A m e ri c a n , which means the
potential to better one’s condition.
The fact remains that the American working
class has only sporadically played a determinative
role in politics, under the influence of radicals
i m p o rted from Eastern Europe or south of the
border, or among the relatively settled workforces
o f, for example, the auto industry. Most A m e ri-
cans identify themselves as middle-class, whether
they own an ancient Ford or a yacht and, always
hopeful of improving their lot, prefer not to identify
with those on the lowest rungs of the social ladder.
One can trace the weakness of A m e rican labour
back to the influence of Southern slave-owners on
the A m e rican polity, pressing for the extension of sla-
very as new states joined the Union and militating
against the political organization of labour in the
i n d u s t rialized nort h .And while solidarity in Europe
was built upon the shared values of a cohesive com-
munity at the beginning of this century, in the
United States,the constant pressure of new immi-
grant groups eager to join the workforce in the land
of opportunity has kept wages down and workers
acquiescent.
The result has been to keep those in power res-
2. The state
Individualism, an ethic of self-improvement,
and suspicions of big government help explain a situation in which a rich
nation tolerates high poverty levels
USA: the self-help gospel
To be poor in America carries 
the stigma of sin—a failure
to realize the full potential 
of being American
M o re than 100 million
people in industri a l
c o u n t ries live below
the poverty line and
m o re than five million
a re homeless.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
The homeless “surface 
as unsightly symptoms 
of urban blight”.
ponsive first and foremost to the interests of those
who help pay for their campaigns.The first order of
business for any American president is to pave the
way for the proverbial “healthy business climate”,
with his Tr e a s u ry Secretary close by his side. C a p i t a l ,
a lways holding in reserve the threat of a capital
s t ri k e , in the form of a slow - d own in wa g e s , o r
r e t r e at and relocat i o n , has managed to limit its
contribution to social expenditure.
A healthy
business climate
The interests of the disenfranchised count for
ve ry little in this context except insofar as they sur-
face as unsightly symptoms of urban blight, sus-
ceptible to grand invocations of the great spirit of
A m e rican vo l u n t a ri s m , as in President George
Bush’s “thousand points of light”.
And, indeed, there is a powerful strain of civic
responsibility at work in A m e rican communities, firs t
commented on in the 19th century by the French
historian Alexis de Tocqueville, which has made it
possible for gove rnment to spin off many of the
functions it performs in Europe to nonprofit or
r e l i gious organizat i o n s , whether in the shape of
hospitals, soup kitchens or shelters—in a form of
m i xed part n e rs h i p.This safety net, h owe ve r ,s h ow s
e ve ry sign of being shredded under the recent we l-
fare reform, as the two-year limit on drawing wel-
fare benefits comes up and ever more children fa c e
the prospect of going hungry.
Few politicians of national stature have made a
career as advo c ates for the poor. One is Je rry Brow n ,
former governor of California and twice presiden-
tial candidat e , who has spent much of the past
decade deconstructing the unquestioned assump-
tions of the American political agenda,such as the
need to cut we l fare and provide jobs. “ We need
more we l fare and fewer jobs,” he argued relent-
lessly on his radio programme “We the People”,
making the point that automation is inexorably
e ating up jobs and that A m e rica needs an “ i n c o m e -
maintenance system” guaranteeing the basic ri g h t s
of food,lodging, education and medical care to all
its citizens.
B r own now finds himself back in office as newly
elected mayor of Oakland,a battered municipality
across the bay from San Francisco with a large
black population that the cy b e r - wealth pouring out
of Silicon Valley has somehow managed to pass by.
This is a town so depressed that the supermarkets
h ave fled and where many people, too poor to ow n
c a rs , are forced to make a two-hour bus trip simply
to buy the most basic household necessities.
But Brown, in the first days of his tenure, has
turned his attention not to social programmes but
to police patrols in the desolate downtown area,
hoping to attract new tenants to the offices in the
empty skyscrapers. His order of the day: making
Oakland safe—for business. n
Vicky Elliott in San Francisco
The UNDP has called Tunisia’s fight against poverty a model 
for the rest of the Arab world. The government certainly does a great deal—
perhaps a bit too much
Twilight in Tunisia
the name by which the fund is commonly known to
Tunisians.
A few months after the work has been done, t h e
poor man receives the first bills. He is illiterat e ,
and throws them away. In due course an electri c i t y
c o m p a ny employee shows up on his doors t e p :
“ Yo u ’re ungr ateful! W hy don’t you pay ? ”The poor
man answe rs , “ W h at with? I’m no richer than
n
Once upon a time there was a poor man adri f t
in the solitude of what the Tunisian gove rn m e n t
calls a “twilight zone”—an isolated, poverty-
stricken area. One day President Ben Ali visits the
poor man,promising that soon he will have water,
light and a decent home thanks to “26-26”.This
figure is the postal account number of the Nat i o n a l
S o l i d a rity Fund (FSN) set up at the end of 1992 and
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Over 800,000 people have access to medical assis-
t a n c e ; nearly half a million pri m a ry-school stu-
dents receive an allowance eve ry year when they go
back to school after the summer va c at i o n ; and in six
ye a rs the FSN has spent some $350 million on
d e veloping 928 “twilight zones”. There are also
housing and rural and urban development pro-
gr a m m e s.This range of measures was rounded out
in late 1997 by the creation of the Tunisian Solida-
rity Bank (BTS). In 1998 the bank granted low-
interest loans (5 per cent) to 7,300 small bu s i-
nesses. “Now the priority is to stimulate the spirit
of enterp ri s e ,” s ays bank chairman and CEO A b d e l-
latif Saddem.
The gove rnment is doing a gr e at deal.A little too
m u c h , some people say, and not always for the best.
In 1996, a study by the Tunisian research firm
D i r a s s at reported that the vagueness of public assis-
tance allocation guidelines has encouraged cro-
ny i s m .O n e - fifth of the PNAFN’s benefic i a ries live
above the poverty line while the poorest families
swell the waiting lists.According to several accounts,
civil servants in the ministry of the interior and the
cells of the ruling party interfere with the selection
process.
The war on pove rty focuses on the rural areas,bu t
t wo-thirds of Tu n i s i a ’s poor live in the cities. In the sub-
urbs of Tunis for example, H ay Ettadhamen, the lar-
gest of the country ’s 800 squatter settlements, is not
c l a s s i fied as a “twilight zone” e ven though 30 per
cent of the population of the former Islamic funda-
mentalist stronghold lives below the pove rty line.
An opportunity to team up
with civil society
E x p e rts point out a third problem: g ove rn m e n t
p r o grammes could do a better job targeting the
poorest people and urban yo u t h . For example, o n l y
4.8 per cent of the BTS’s debtors are illiterat e — e ve n
though one in three Tunisians can neither read nor
w ri t e . “ Policies to support micro-businesses and
the informal sector in general will be even more
necessary in the future,” says Mahjoub. Especially
since Tunisia has launched a campaign to upgrade
its industrial fa b ric in preparation for implementing
a free-trade accord with the European Union, w h i c h
m ay lead to higher unemployment and lower wa g e s.
Urban youth left out of the educational system
h ave ve ry few means to improve their lot.Yo u n g
people are deserting the gove rn m e n t ’s “ n e i g h b o u-
rhood houses”, where they find the supervision too
s t ri c t .D e l i n q u e n cy is still a taboo subject, and there-
fore not dealt with, while illicit alcohol sales, h a s h i s h
d e a l i n g, p r o s t i t u t i o n , illegal immigr ation ri n g s ,t h e f t
and other petty crime known as b e z n e s s is on the ri s e .
To d ay the gove rnment seems to realize that it can
no longer fight pove rty alone on eve ry front.To help
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 29
A new deal for the poor
Wo rld consumption
ex p e n d i t u res on go o d s
and services re a ch e d
$24 trillion in 1998,
twice the level of 1975
and six times that of
1 9 5 0 . But 20% of the
wo rl d ’s people account
for 86% of this total. I n
70 countries with
n e a rly a billion people,
consumption is lowe r
than it was 20 ye a rs
ago.
The leather workshop in a
children’s rehabilitation centre
in Tunisia.
The war on poverty focuses on
the rural areas, but two-thirds of
Tunisia’s poor live in the cities
b e f o r e .And besides, I thought 27-27 would take care
of the bills.”
This joke, which is making the rounds in Tu n i s ,
sums up the situation we l l .O f ficials are doing more
and more to help society’s most disadva n t a g e d
members. But much remains to be done to bring
them into economic life and break with seve r a l
decades of paternalism and assistance.
If there is a country where the term “ we l fare stat e ”
means something it is Tu n i s i a .The gove rnment has
a lways pursued a vigorous social policy since inde-
pendence in 1956. At first it was part of President
Habib Bourguiba’s socialist approach. To d ay it is a
pillar of President Zine El Abidine Ben A l i ’s law - a n d -
order policy, which was bolstered after fundamenta-
list Muslims made headway in the late 1980s.“ S o c i a l
stability is a matter of securi t y,” s ays secretary of stat e
Kamel Haj Sassi,who manages the FSN.As a result,
economic liberalization has been accompanied by an
i n t e n s i fied anti-pove rty campaign.
“From 1987 to 1993, in the middle of the adjust-
ment peri o d ,” the World Bank report s , “the gove rn-
m e n t ’s per capita social spending increased by 14 per
cent in real term s.” The results are plain to see.
“Despite the shock of liberalization and ri s i n g
unemployment,” says Tunisian economist Azzam
M a h j o u b ,“the pove rty rate has declined quite signi-
ficantly since 1970, although the drop began slow i n g
down in 1985,especially in the cities.”The United
Nations Development Programme (UNDP) says
t h at the percentage of people living below the
p ove rty line (approx i m ately a dollar per person per
d ay in cities and half a dollar in the countryside) fell
from 22 per cent in 1975 to 6.2 per cent in 1995.
But the International Labour Organisation (ILO)
also reports that some nine million Tunisians are still
“ v u l n e r a b l e ” . So fa r , social transfers — e q u i valent to
$150 per person per month, according to Mongi
Layeb of the ministry of economic development—
seem to have protected them from the worst.
Tu n i s i a ’s neediest people benefit from an ars e n a l
of measures. Some 112,000 households receive a
d o l l a r - a - d ay allowance from the National Pro-
gramme of Assistance to Needy Families (PNAFN).
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
with funding, it is appealing to the generosity of Tu n i-
sians via communication campaigns and collections
in companies and gove rnment offic e s. G ove rn m e n t
r e p r e s e n t at i ves say they also want to invo l ve other
s k i l l s , including those of non-gove rnmental organi-
z at i o n s.But development associations are few and fa r
b e t we e n .“They are unprofessional and don’t alway s
get enough encouragement from the authori t i e s ,”
s ays specialist Henda Gafsi.M a ny officials want to keep
control over the population and believe that civil
society initiat i ves are targeted against the stat e .
In Hay Ettadhamen, the independent NGO
Enda Interarabe proves them wrong. The gr o u p
runs a bustling centre called Espace 21, which offers
small loans and a wide range of errands and serv i c e s.
In three ye a rs the centre has financed over 1,000 mic r o -
bu s i n e s s e s , most of them small shops. Despite easy credit
t e rm s , the gove rnment has a hard time recove ring its loans,
but Enda,which lends at 17 per cent,has a 98 per cent reim-
bu rsement rat e .Espace 21 is also a recreational and training
centre for disadvantaged yo u t h . “ M a ny turn down the
training programmes we find for them because they prefer
b e z n e s s and easy money,” s ays director Essma Ben Hamida.
“But after a few months here,” she explains, “ at least they
l e a rn how to live in society by the ru l e s.”
The work of Enda and other organizations show s
that the state “could do better by teaming up with civil
s o c i e t y,” concludes Mahjoub—in other wo r d s , by demo-
cratizing public life. n
Sophie Boukhari
In the former Eastern bloc,
a h a z a rdous t ra n s i t i o n Omar Noman*
What should the state do in a region where poverty is making a horrific comeback?
In 1960, the 20% of
wo rld populat i o n
living in the ri ch e s t
c o u n t ries had 30 times
the income of the
p o o rest 20%—by 1995
their income was 
82 times as much .
* Senior Project Manager, UNDP
n
In the former Eastern bloc, strong central
g ove rnment virtually wiped out pove rt y
through wealth redistri bution mechanisms.
But as the region undergoes political transition,
the state is no longer up to the task,and poverty is
making a horrific comeback. E ven the form e r
middle classes now rank among the impove ri s h e d .
In the va s t , ethnically dive rse Fo rmer Soviet Union
(FSU) and Eastern Europe, the breakdown of central
planning and in many cases, the absence of effective
s t ate institutions to cushion the jolt, h ave led to the
most acute pove rty and we l fare reve rsals in the wo r l d .
Based on a daily four dollar benchmark—consi-
dered the minimum required to surv i ve — t h e
number of poor increased by over 150 million in
s e ven ye a rs , a figure gr e ater than the total com-
bined population of France, the United Kingdom,
the Netherlands and Scandinavia. Since the 1998
financial crisis in Russia, the ranks of the poor are
estimated to have swelled by a further 20 million.
W h at ’s more, in this decade dollar-a-day pove rty has
made a comeback: in Romania and Bulgari a ,five per
cent of the population lives below that level.
E a s t e rn bloc transition countries were the only
ones in the world to have recorded a decline in
n ational incomes from the start of the curr e n t
decade up to the present.The declines have been as
gr e at as 60 per cent in some cases. A region that had
v i rtually no inflation under the previous system
suddenly experienced the most acute price instability
in the wo r l d , with prices rising in excess of 500 per
cent per year between 1990 and 1995.
It is also the only region in the world to have wit-
nessed a decline in men’s life expectancy, which in the
Russian Fe d e r ation fell from 64.2 to 57.6 ye a rs from
1989 to 1994, l ower than in Egypt, India and Bolivia.
Morbidity from syphilis, tuberculosis and AIDS has
increased dramat i c a l l y.And a system that once pri d e d
itself on having achieved near-unive rsal literacy has suf-
fered serious reve rs a l s. In Central Asian countri e s ,t h e
p ove rty of families has become a major impediment
to school at t e n d a n c e ,and research in several countri e s
suggests that there is a continued threat of illiteracy
e m e r ging amongst certain gr o u p s.
There have been many losers in the transition
process.
Wavering between gradualism 
and shock therapy
Children for one, with a massive erosion of
child allowa n c e s. In the Russian Fe d e r at i o n ,p ove rt y
rates among the under-15 group stood at 46 per
c e n t , compared to 35 per cent for adults between 31
and 60 and 22 per cent for pensioners. With the
decreasing number of child-care fa c i l i t i e s , m a ny
women have been forced to abandon work.
But what gives poverty in this region a qualita-
t i vely different profile from that of most deve l o-
ping nations is the slide into precarity of those who
once made up the professional middle class under
s o c i a l i s m . Large numbers of once prestigious scien-
t i s t s ,e n gi n e e rs and other highly educated specialists
e m p l oyed by public institutions have joined the
ranks of the poor, with little apparent chance of
transferring their skills to the market system and
becoming part of the entrepreneurial class. Once
s u p p o rt e rs of a democratic opening, this fru s t r at e d ,
m a r ginalized class is now more likely to be the firs t
to stand behind an authoritarian regime.
This general picture merits temperi n g . C e n t r a l
European countries (Czech Republic, H u n g a ry and
Po l a n d ) , which were independent at the time of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 31
A new deal for the poor
breakup of the Fo rmer Soviet Union but had extensive
trade links with it—moved swiftly toward a market-
b a s e d , p ri vate-sector dominated economy, with rea-
sonably competent state institutions.These countri e s
still have the lowest levels of inequality in the wo r l d .
Social transfers in the form of pensions,u n e m p l oy m e n t
b e n e fits and child allowances increased relat i ve to
gross domestic product (GDP) or remained constant.
The economies of the Baltic Stat e s , initially disru p t e d
by the loss of energy subsidies from the USSR, r e g a i n e d
momentum after a relat i vely short period of hy p e ri n-
flation and declining output. A g a i n , p a rtly because
they came into the Soviet fold at a later dat e , their stat e
institutions remained competent and credible.
This has not been the case in the former Sov i e t
R e p u b l i c s. Most of these were unable to reach
consensus on the course of transition and wavered bet-
ween gradualism and shock therapy. In the Russian
Fe d e r ation and Ukraine, r e f o rm has been paralyzed
over such issues as property rights in agri c u l t u r e .
Public institutions, namely the law and order machi-
n e ry and the tax revenue serv i c e s ,h ave collapsed,v i r-
tually destroying the gove rn m e n t ’s ability to redistri-
bute resources.
The pendulum has swung too far
In Russia, taking advantage of a political va c u u m ,
the exe c u t i ve rushed through with a series of reform s
t h at further undermined credibility in state institu-
t i o n s , by providing generous underhand deals in the
p ri vat i z ation process and creating the conditions for
the mafia ’s gr ow t h , not unlike the situation in Italy in
the 19th century. In 1996, the richest 5 per cent of the
p o p u l ation controlled a share of income equal to
t h at of the bottom 60 per cent—and in many coun-
t ri e s , inequality has surpassed the troubling leve l s
found in Latin A m e ri c a .
From the all-intrusive state, the pendulum has
swung too far in the opposite direction. Often,the
i d e o l o gical inheritance dictated a rush to dismantle
the stat e .And ye t , as countries of Central Europe go
to show, the state has a key role to play in the tran-
sition process. E x c e s s i ve liberalization leads to
p ri vate monopolies, capital fli g h t ,u n p a l atable leve l s
of inequality and lack of trust in the market due to
financial fraud. Strong public institutions are
required that regulate financial markets and transfer
resources effectively to vulnerable gr o u p s. Last bu t
not least,reviving growth is the critical issue.
Many countries of the FSU were poised for a
t u rnaround when the 1998 Russian crisis set them
b a c k . S t i l l , the outlook is not comprehensive l y
b l e a k .M a ny countries have defined their economic
c o u rs e ,h ave we l l - e d u c ated populat i o n s , are inve s-
ting in retraining manpower and moving ahead
with we l fare reforms and institution-bu i l d i n g .N o t
including countries of Central Europe and the
Baltic Republics, there are some exceptional cases.
Azerbaijan will be an important test: thanks to an
easily exportable oil surp l u s , the country is likely to
b e n e fit from a boost in revenue (even with world oil
p rices as low as they are). But will it share the we a l t h ?
M a ny fear that wealth will stay concentrated in the
hands of a small oligarchy, a nightmarish scenari o.
A second group of countries (Uzbekistan,K a z a-
k h s t a n , Tu r k m e n i s t a n , B u l g a ria and Romania) is
b e ginning to post gr owth and take a more pro-active
stance towards the future.M a ny are making strenuous
e f f o rts to form trade and technology links other than
with Russia. But for a third group of countri e s —
Ta j i k s t a n ,G e o r gia (embroiled in an endless confli c t ) ,
A rm e n i a , the Kyrgyz Republic and Russia—the most
highly populated country of the FSU—the pros-
pects seem bleak. In Russia, it is conceivable that a
fairly coherent former Communist party gr o u p i n g
acting like a reformist state in China could shore up
public institutions without losing the momentum
of reform . In the wo rst case scenari o, the country will
simply print money, r e t u rn to hy p e ri n flat i o n , f u e l
social discontent and heighten political confli c t .
Clearly the Russians are aware of the leverage
they hold on the intern ational stage. They have
essentially defaulted on debt. Chaos in the region
is too great a threat to global security to be taken
m i l d l y, making it highly unlikely that We s t e rn powe rs
will pull back. On the contrary : the situation is
likely to engage the United States in the regi o n
more than it had ever expected to be.
I n t e rn ational agencies have an important role to
p l ay in strengthening public institutions in many
new areas and some traditional ones, such as health,
e d u c ation and the financial sector.Recognizing that
the transition process is a much more painful and sys-
temic process than initially conceive d , the Nordic
c o u n t ries are reviewing their aid policies towa r d s
the FSU, while the European Union is set to increase
its commitment in the months ahead. n
Since the onset of the
economic crisis, the shop
Natasha Tushnova runs in the
Russian village of Novo has
been nearly empty.
+ …
l For a comprehensive
analysis of development in
this region, see the UNDP
Report Poverty in Transition?
1998 (224pp.,
ISBN:92-1-126100-7)
h t t p : / w w w. u n d p. o rg / u n d p / r b e c
Excessive liberalization leads to
private monopolies, capital
flight, unpalatable levels of
inequality and lack of trust in the
market due to financial fraud
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
u n d e rstanding and respect for local culture. H owe ve r ,
this respect should not dive rt us from the ultimat e
g o a l : to reduce pove rt y. In my experi e n c e , l o c a l
culture is more often than not the cause of pove rt y.
From The Gambia to Nepal, it is not hard to iden-
tify cultural practices that limit the potential of
wo m e n , children or ethnic gr o u p s. The dominant
culture is structured to keep certain individuals or
groups in the service of others. It perp e t u ates their
p ove rt y.
I am not suggesting that the role of the outsider
is to arrive in a community with a list of “needed
changes”.Every community, no matter how poor,
has individuals with ve ry lucid understandings of the
cultural dynamics at play.These people have plans
and ideas on how to improve their condition. It is
the job of the outsider to understand the local
culture well enough to find these people and offer
support.
Gaining access into a community means gaining
p e o p l e ’s trust—a formidable challenge, p a rt i c u-
larly when it comes to the very poor.These people
are “ i nv i s i b l e ” . They are never the ones to gr e e t
you at the village gates but that doesn’t mean they
a r e n ’t wat c h i n g .The challenge of gaining their tru s t
becomes twice as difficult if you are seen staying with
the relat i vely we a l t hy or powerful villagers. T h e
poor will never trust you if you frequent the homes
of those considered responsible for their poverty.
A lot of time
and a little trust
Ironically, one of the most telling signs of the
ve ry poor is their silence. Organize a public meeting
to discuss the needs of the community and yo u
can be certain that those who speak the most need
your help the least.The ve ry poor are either shocked
by the idea that someone is asking them to make
demands or completely fatalistic about the chances
of their lives changing.
A lot of time and a little trust can overcome some
of this fatalism. I remember working in Sindhu-
p a l c h owk district of Nepal, where after six months
of meetings, a man finally felt comfortable to recount
32 The UNESCO Courier- March 1999
3. The people
In sub-Saharan A f ri c a ,
the number of
u n d e rn o u rished people
m o re than doubl e d
b e t ween 1970 and
1 9 9 0 , rising from 103
million to 215 million.
n
In the hills of we s t e rn Nepal, a poor dairy
farmer may have little more to offer his kids
than milk to dri n k .Cut-off from the markets of
Kathmandu, these farmers must barter and trade
with middle-men to earn a mere pittance.About two
years ago, a group of local and international non-
g ove rnmental organizations decided to try and
widen the fa rm e rs ’ financial hori z o n s. To g e t h e r ,
they set up a string of collection points along the
h i g h way leading to the capital so that fa rm e rs could
drop off their milk daily, with the state dairy cor-
p o r ation looking after the supplies’ d e l i ve ry and
s a l e . Before long, they ran up against a major road-
b l o c k : the people manning the collection points
refused to accept the milk of the Dalits—the untou-
chable caste which is forbidden to handle the wat e r
or food of upper castes. By not recognizing this
d i c t ate of the local culture, they had unwittingly set
up a pove rt y - e r a d i c ation project which rejected the
poorest people.
W h at were the altern at i ves? Accept the local
culture and try to set up an alternative market for
the Dalits? Or try to break past the cultural barri e rs ?
In the end,they broke through with the support of
human rights activists who streamed in from the
capital to put pressure on the local authorities.
I tell this story to highlight a dilemma often
ignored in discussions concerning poverty-eradi-
cation: how can we respect local culture without
accepting the status quo? Local culture has become
something of a sacred cow for “ i n t e rn ational deve-
lopment experts” in the last ten years or so. This
reaction is understandable gi ven all the wa s t e d
resources and harm resulting from attempts to
“ i m p o rt ”d e velopment projects from one situat i o n
to another. In short , just because a project “ wo r k s ”
in one country or region of a country, it will not
n e c e s s a rily reap the same success in another. S o m e
of the failed plans now appear as pure folly:telling
A f rican women to stop breast-feeding their babies,
neglecting to teach children to write in their mother
tongues and trying to convince fa rm e rs to gr ow
crops their communities didn’t want to eat.
A successful project clearly requires a solid
Culture—the wild card
Ramesh Singh*
Anti-poverty projects in developing countries cannot hope to succeed 
unless they find leverage in local cultures
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 33
A new deal for the poor
* Director of the British NGO Action-Aid in Viet Nam
Senegalese village women discuss setting up a
cereal bank. The cultural key
to empowerment
Culture, defined in its broadest sense as the totality of a society’s distinctive ideas, beliefs,
values and knowledge, can play an important role in overcoming poverty.
James Sengendo, a Ugandan sociologist who teaches at Makerere University in Kampala,
goes even further. “To the extent that people are the ultimate objective of all development
efforts,” he says, “a people’s culture is not only an instrument of development, but also the
social basis of human development.” In fact, the collective activities that communities have
always practised in order to survive are based on their own systems of cultural values (see
article page 35). Since the beginning of the 1990s, development specialists have been insis-
ting on the need for active participation by the most disadvantaged in projects concerning
them.According to Robert Chambers of the University of Sussex,UK, many development pro-
jects have failed because they have tried to impose in widely different local contexts standard
programmes designed by outsiders. There are plenty of examples of programmes implemented
in places where they turned out to be unnecessary and of projects that were not adapted to
local needs.
The United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) report on Overcoming Human
Poverty stresses that the only real solution is “to empower the poor”and that this will requi-
re “increased organization and participation of all people in decision-making,and the mobili-
zing of social energy.”
“The one who rides the donkey does not know the ground is hot,” says an African pro-
verb. Sometimes it is necessary to get one’s feet burned. n
a bit of his past.This very poor farm labourer was
once relat i vely we a l t hy. He traced his problems
back to the year his father died.According to local
custom of the Tamang ethnic group, a family must
spend a tremendous amount on a funeral,with a vil-
lage feast lasting several days and gifts of clothing
given to neighbours.This man and his wife sold a
few animals to cover the costs. The next year, his
mother died and they sold eve rything but their
house to pay for the funeral.
This man had a plan.With just one female bu f-
falo, he could earn money by breeding the animal
and selling its milk to buy back his wife’s gold jewe l-
lery which was sold to pay for the last funeral. By
building on these assets, his son would then be
able to pay for his parents’ funerals without going
into debt. In short , his solution to a better life lay in
preparing for death.
Seeing through
a cultural cloud
This man clearly understood the cause of his
p ove rt y.He had a sound financial plan for improv i n g
his condition. But cultural conceptions wo u l d
continue to reinforce his fa m i l y ’s pove rt y. My role wa s
clearly not to tell him to change his religious beliefs.
But discussions continued and broadened to include
other villagers and community gr o u p s , and before
long they decided to work with the Lamas, the reli-
gious leaders , to curtail the influence of local customs.
This “ p a rt i c i p at o ry approach” is not just a way
of changing a community’s foundations but of bu i l-
ding on its “social capital” or solidari t y. From A f ri c a
to Asia, the poorest communities have set up their
own systems of mutual assistance. Basically, each
household contributes money or material to a col-
l e c t i ve fund. The group then meets regularly to
give that money to the family most in need. The
challenge lies in building on this solidari t y : to move
from a safety-net to a means of improving the com-
m u n i t y ’s live l i h o o d . The same co-operation can
build a collective forestry project, a literacy pro-
gramme or a new irrigation system.
For some expert s , this solidarity is engrained in
the “culture of the poor”. I would like to think that
poor people are somehow more caring and
concerned for others’ well-being. But I don’t.The
s o l i d a rity seems to have stronger links to live l i h o o d
needs than culture.This may sound like academic
quibbling over wo r d s , but there is a tendency to let
the wa rm glow of culture cloud our vision of the tru e
causes of pove rt y. For example, I remember my
initial contact with a Dalit community in western
N e p a l . I was taken by the strong and intri c ate bonds
between these people. But there was no mystery
i nvo l ve d .G e n e r ations of collective margi n a l i z at i o n
forced the community to turn inwards. The chal-
lenge lay in developing this solidarity so that the
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
+ …
l ATD Fourth World
1 0 7 , avenue du Généra l
L e c l e rc
95480 Pierrelaye, France
Tel:(33 1) 30 37 11 11.
Fax: (33 1) 34 30 07 33.
Children in a Guatemala City
shantytown read books lent by
ATD Fourth World volunteers.
ATD’s streetwise
librarians
An NGO that uses culture as a weapon against poverty and exclusion but
doesn’t always get a friendly welcome from the hungry
n
When Hurricane Mitch hit Tegucigalpa, the
capital of Honduras, in the evening of 28
October 1998, the first thing Carlos, M a u ri c i o
and Jaime did was to persuade families in the Nueva
S u yapa neighbourhood to quit their corru g at e d
iron and brick shacks.
As the rain fell in torrents they took the stri c k e n
s l u m - d we l l e rs to improvised shelters in schools and
c h u r c h e s.Then the three volunteer wo r k e rs with AT D
Fo u rth Wo r l d , a non-gove rnmental humanitari a n
o r g a n i z at i o n , went back to rescue their street library.
They collected the children’s books,c r ayo n s , sheets of
p a p e r , s c i s s o rs and modeling clay displayed on the
green plastic sheet that for some ye a rs they had regu-
larly been taking to the city’s poorest distri c t s , a n d
r e t u rned with their precious cargo to the refugee shel-
t e rs. Along with some 160,000 other ATD Fo u rt h
World vo l u n t e e rs and 300 paid staff members in 30
c o u n t ri e s , they have been wa ging a “ war on pove rt y
through culture”—at the risk of shocking the ve ry
poor whose other needs are much more glari n g .
Not by bread
alone
Reinforcements soon reached them from neigh-
b o u ring Guatemala and from France, where AT D
Fo u rth World is based.The newcomers brought pup-
pets with them as well as shovels to clear the ru b b l e .I n
the end the shovels were hardly used,but the puppets
worked ove rt i m e .While rescue wo r k e rs gave emergency
a s s i s t a n c e , ATD Fo u rth Wo r l d ’s “cultural activists”
helped the hurricane victims keep their spirits up by len-
ding them books and performing sketches.
“ E ve ry b o d y,especially society’s poorest members ,
needs culture as much as bread. Not before or after
b r e a d , but at the same time.”T h at is the basic tenet of
ATD (Aid in Total Distress), which was founded in
1957 in a camp for homeless families in the Pa ri s
s u burb of Noisy-le-Grand by Father Joseph W r e s i n s k i .
F i rst the priest invited actors to perform Sophocles’
A n t i go n e in the muddy, ramshackle settlement.T h e n
he laid on an exhibition of ori ginal works by Picasso,
B r a q u e , Miro and Léger. “Culture is a fundamental
ri g h t ,” said Father W r e s i n s k i ,“ but the shame the poo-
rest people have to endure cuts them off from that
ri g h t .” He wanted culture “to cease to be a pri v i l e g e ”
and to help people outside mainstream society “ b e l i e ve
in their own culture and in their intelligence.”
ATD Fo u rth World began working in Central
A m e rica in 1979. On the edge of Te g u c i g a l p a ’s huge
city dump,needy people of all ages jostle for position
w h e n e ver a garbage truck arri ve s. They eke out a
m e a gre living by scave n ging through the ru b b i s h .
ATD Fo u rth World volunteer Régis De Muylder has
not always been gi ven a wa rm welcome when he has
t u rned up with his green plastic sheet. “ We don’t
want your books,” he was often told. “Here we have
to fight to eat . Our children are dying of hunger.”B u t
De Muylder refused to gi ve up,and today adults and
children stop work when he and other vo l u n t e e rs
a rri ve . “ L e ave them alone,” s ays veteran garbage
picker Don A n t o n i o.“ T h e y ’re here to help us, not to
judge us.” Don Antonio has himself learned h ow to
w rite in order to describe “ w h at he has gone through”
to his children.He finds it too hard to tell them about
such grim experi e n c e s.
Street libraries have been set up in 25 countries in
the North and the South.Their main aim is to encou-
rage children of school age to enrol in school,or if they
h ave dropped out to go back to the classroom. AT D
Fo u rth World says that unless people learn how to
read or write they cannot hope to escape from pove rt y.
Vo l u n t e e rs fa m i l i a rize the most disadvantaged yo u n g
people with a va riety of teaching mat e rials in order to
p e rsuade them that ignorance is not inevitable and that
they can go to school without feeling ashamed.Pa r e n t s
are patiently handled so as to get them used to the idea
of sending their children to school.
Another objective is to bring children, t e e n a g e rs
and adults together  and encourage them to respect
each other and get on together.“ We ’re not trying to
e n t e rtain the poorest people or organize neigh-
bourhood eve n t s ,” s ays Je a n - M a rie A n g l a d e , a one-
time chemical engineer who is now an ATD Fo u rt h
World staff member. “Our goal is to build self-
confidence in people who are outside the mains-
tream and to help them see their strengths,” so that
they can recover their human dignity, make their
voices heard and assert their rights. n
Martine Jacot
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 35
A new deal for the poor
Madagascar has a long
tradition of village solidarity.
In the uplands of northern Madagascar, the villagers
of Ambingivato shaped their community’s future with their own hands.
But this kind of collective action is fading fast
Madagascar: a waning tradition
n
A m b i n gi vat o,a village with a hundred or so inha-
b i t a n t s , is five hours ’ walk from A m b a r a r at a ,t h e
nearest town accessible by ve h i c l e . For the past
20 ye a rs it has had a hospital and a school which serve
four neighbouring villages.This sounds a bit gr a n d ,a s
the hospital is just a couple of big whitewashed rooms,
one of them a mat e rnity ward and the other for recei-
ving pat i e n t s.The school consists of two huts built of
t a n i m a n ga ( c l ay ) ,each with four rooms in which chil-
dren of different ages and educational levels mix.
But makeshift though it is, the hospital has meant
t h at mothers-to-be no longer have to suffer the ordeal
of bumping along all the way to A m b a r a r ata in a cart
d r awn by two oxe n .The school is equally modest bu t
it provides an education for the local children.
Both were built by local fa rm e rs themselves follo-
wing a decision by the fo k o n o l o n a,a kind of community
assembly and a political institution dating from pre-colo-
nial times. A ny project initiated by the fo k o n o l o n a
becomes a public facility and is respected as such.
To the Malagasy, the term conjures up a picture
of solemn meetings at which the community gat h e rs
to decide its future. One of its regular functions, f o r
e x a m p l e , is clearing roads after the heavy December
and Ja n u a ry rains. Each year at this season, A m b i n-
givato is cut off from the other villages by godram-
potaka, the very thick grey mud that is typical of
Madagascar’s rural areas, and its people are pre-
vented from exporting rice and coffee via A m b a r a-
rata to Befandriana Avaratra.The menfolk set to
work with shovels to clear the blocked roads.
U n aware of new concepts of “community deve-
l o p m e n t ” and “local part i c i p at i o n ” and well before
We s t e rn NGOs arri ved in Madagascar,A m b i n gi vat o ’s
fo k o n o l o n a was thinking about how to improve local
conditions without calling on any outside help. To
build their school and hospital,the villagers divided up
the work among themselve s.The children went dow n
to the Anjingo River to gather rocks, the men broke
them into small pieces to use as foundation mat e rial and
men and women together hauled earth which wa s
m i xed with rice straw to make big bricks for the wa l l s.
To raise funds in an economy where cash is
little used, the fokonolona held fairs and organized
h o t e l y—small inns where women served ri c e , ox
meat and poultry to the people from surrounding
villages, who would buy tickets for the occasion in
a d va n c e . At the fa i rs , where 1970s music was playe d
on old gramophone records, the young and not-so-
young came to eat ,h ave a good time and spend a bit
of money.The cash raised went to buy things like the
h o s p i t a l ’s expensive corru g ated iron roof and to
build one of the school’s two huts.
The other part of the school still has a that-
ched roof. N ow, after many ye a rs , it is time to
replace it with corrugated iron and mend the mud
walls weatherbeaten by gale-force winds sweeping
in from the Indian Ocean every year.
But the A m b i n gi vato fo k o n o l o n a is no longer so
energetic and is less enthusiastic about the school
than it once wa s.The fall in coffee prices in the last 20
ye a rs , the death of elders who handed down cus-
t o m s , the exodus of young people and the lack of local
prospects may help to explain why all the A m b i n gi vat o
fo k o n o l o n a does these days is clear the roads.T i m e s
h ave changed. In recent ye a rs , m a ny non-gove rn-
mental organizations have been busy in Madagascar.
They bypass the fo k o n o l o n a, and do eve rything from
p r oviding water supplies to refurbishing schools.T h e
projects are useful and local people take part in them.
But the initiat i ve comes from the outside. Instead of
taking their own decisions and doing the job them-
s e l ve s , people are now content to wait for others to do
it for them. n
Soahangy Mamisoa Rangers,
Paris-based Malagasy journalist
At the fairs, w h e re 1970s music
was played on old gra m o p h o n e
re c o rd s, the young and not-so-
young came to eat, have a good
time and spend a bit of money
S even million people
die each year of
c u rable diseases and
800 million have no
access to health care.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
tely make possible a genuine redistri bution of
i n c o m e .
The fight against human poverty needs more
time than the fight against income poverty alone.
This disparity is probably even greater in coun-
tries particularly subject to economic instability
(East Asia), or where the socio-economic system
has suffered a major shock (the former Soviet
Union), or where the human development poten-
tial is still a long way from being fully achieved
(sub-Saharan Africa).
The extraordinary way in which apparently
entrenched situations can be reversed in the
struggle against poverty throws sharply into ques-
tion the “sustainability” of the policies followed
so far and also of those which are going to have to
be adopted to tackle the long-term human conse-
quences of crises which can be solved relatively
quickly in narrowly economic terms. A new chal-
lenge for the start of the 21st century is how to set
up mechanisms to guarantee human security in
the face of the multifarious risks inherent in a glo-
balized economy. n
36 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
The economic crises of the late 1990s hit harder than 
those of ten years ago. How can the world’s poor be sheltered
from the uncertainties of a globalized economy?
Another lost decade?
Thierry Lemaresquier and Mümtaz Keklik*
n
At the end of the 1980s, when East and
Southeast Asia were starting to set the pace
not only for economic performance but also
for reducing income poverty, a weakened sub-
Saharan Africa and Latin America were painfully
emerging from a lost decade.
A string of disasters in the 1990s—economic
c ri s i s , debt and political paralysis—wiped out the
a d vances these continents had made over the pre-
ceding 20 ye a rs and plunged new sectors of their
p o p u l ation into pove rt y. The same kind of stri k i n g
contrasts can be seen in a survey of the 1990s—new
c atastrophes afflicting entire regions and dashing
hopes of a substantial world-wide reduction of
p ove rty at the dawn of the third millennium.
The crisis that has gripped East Asia since
1997 has jeopardized at breathtaking speed the
hard-won economic achievements of the last 30
years. In the former socialist countries of Eastern
Europe and the former Soviet Union, what is
politely called a “transition” has, for want of the
economic, legal and political infrastructure nee-
ded for the switch to a market economy, led to a
collapse in real wages and a dizzying rise in inco-
me disparities. In sub-Saharan Africa, the hopes
raised by the recent resumption of growth in
some countries have been cancelled out by the
AIDS epidemic.
Do the 1990s already represent a lost decade?
As we emerged from the 1980s, despite all the
economic disru p t i o n s , i m p r ovements in such
fields as adult literacy, life expectancy and infant
mortality helped to limit the negative impact of
loss of income by many people.Unfortunately the
same cannot really be said of the crises which
East A s i a , the “ t r a n s i t i o n ” s t ates of Eastern
Europe and the countries of sub-Saharan Africa
are facing today.Why?
The short - t e rm effects of a recession can be
cushioned by va rious macro and micro-econo-
mic measures, including maintenance of social
spending and extending society’s safety nets. B u t
when the crisis is so violent that it sweeps away
most of the progress made in the field of human
d e ve l o p m e n t , the situation is quite different.T h e
solutions then call for the use of not just the stan-
dard economic measures but also for a long-term
commitment to making social policy more effec-
t i ve and reforming the institutions which ultima-
The short-term effects of a
recession can be cushioned by
various macro and 
micro-economic measures,
including maintenance of social
spending and extending society’s
safety nets
* Thierry Lemaresquier and Mümtaz Keklik 
are respectively director and consultant in the Social Development
and Poverty Elimination Division of UNDP’s Bureau of Development
Policy.
Of the 4.4 billion
people in deve l o p i n g
c o u n t ri e s, n e a rly thre e -
fifths lack basic
s a n i t at i o n .Almost a
t h i rd have no access to
clean wat e r. A quarter
do not have adequat e
h o u s i n g.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
The spectre of new biological weapons made possible by the mapping of 
the human genome makes it more urgent than ever to prevent biotechnology
research from being hijacked for evil purposes
Genetic w e a p o n s:
a 21st-century
nightmare?
n
It sounds like science fic t i o n , but like
m a ny another prediction that was once
dismissed as far-fetched it may become
a reality.
Scientists have wa rned that recent
a d vances in biological research could eve n-
tually lead to the creation of a new type of
b i o l o gical arsenal capable of targeting a
specific group of human beings with
common genetic characteri s t i c s , as may be
the case with certain ethnic groups.
“It will unfort u n ately be possible to
design biological weapons of this type when
more information on genome research is
ava i l a b l e ,” s ays Dr Vivienne Nat h a n s o n ,
head of science and health policy at the
B ritish Medical A s s o c i ation (BMA), t h e
body which represents the medical profes-
sion in the United Kingdom.
This terrifying prospect may be an unwe l-
come piece of spin-off from research being
c a rried out under the Human Genome Pro-
ject (see box ) , an intern ational scientific effort
to map and sequence the genes in the human
body and find out more about human DNA
( d e ox y ribonucleic acid), the molecule which
p r ovides the biological instructions to make
a human being.
Repairing defective genes
L ate last ye a r ,genome research achieve d
a breakthrough when scientists for the firs t
time deciphered the full genetic progr a m-
ming of an animal.The creature was a micro-
scopic roundwo rm known as C a e n o r h a b d i t i s
e l e ga n s, but because wo rms and humans have
t u rned out to share many genes in common,
the wo rm genome is regarded by biologists as
an essential basis for understanding how the
human genome wo r k s.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
a gree that the technology to produce ethnic
weapons is not a reality now,some feel there
is a real chance that it may be deve l o p e d
within the next ten ye a rs.“No need to wait till
the project is completed. E f f o rts to regulat e
genetic research should begin now,” s ay s
D a n d o.
P r o f. Dando says the world community is
already struggling to eliminate existing bio-
l o gical we a p o n s.These we a p o n s ,which carry
agents spreading deadly diseases like anthrax
and other lethal tox i n s , can deva s t ate human
beings without causing damage to bu i l d i n g s
or infrastru c t u r e .E x p e rts say that a few hun-
dred kilograms of a “ we a p o n i z e d ” b a c t e ri a l
p r e p a r ation has the potential to wipe out up
to three million inhabitants concentrated in a
city like New Yo r k .
The apartheid regime in South A f rica is
widely believed to have developed forms of
b i o l o gical we a p o n ry for use against the black
p o p u l at i o n . In the past, h owe ve r , c o u n t ri e s
h ave rarely used such biological weapons in
wa r fa r e ,p a rtly because of their fear of elimi-
n ating friendly populations and killing their
own combat a n t s.The new developments in
genetic research described by Professor
Dando would remove these limitat i o n s.
38 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
E T H I C S
nThe Human Genome Project (HGP),
which began in 1990, is an intern at i o n a l
1 5 - year $3-billion initiat i ve to trace and iden-
tify all the 60,000 to 80,000 genes (the human
g e n o m e ) .I n t e rn ational in scope, it has been
d e s c ribed as the largest scientific research
e f f o rt ever undertaken in the biologi c a l
s c i e n c e s. It is also seeking to determine the
complete sequence of 3 billion sub-units of
human DNA (deox ribonucleic acid), t h e
molecule which codes genetic inform at i o n
and provides the biological instructions to
make a human being. At least 18 countri e s
h ave established genome research projects,
and about 1,000 individuals from 50 coun-
t ries are members of the Human Genome
O r g a n i z ation (HUGO), which helps to co-
o r d i n ate intern ational collaborat i o n .
About 17 per cent of the genes had
been sequenced by late 1998,and the pro-
ject is expected to be finished by 2003,the
Genome research: hopes and d i l e m m a s
‘The social and ethical
s a f e g u a rds which may
p revent ethnic conflict and
weapons development need
to be discussed urg e n t l y ’
Scientists say a detailed understanding of
genetic mechanisms of human beings will
help them to find out the causes of many
d i s e a s e s. For example, k n owledge of an indi-
v i d u a l ’s genetic make-up will enable doc-
t o rs to predict whether or not a specific dru g
will work on a particular pat i e n t ,a l l owing the-
rapies to be more accurately targeted. S i m i-
l a r l y, genetic testing for predisposition to a
range of illnesses could become feasible,a n d
by using what is known as gene therapy doc-
t o rs would be able to replace deficient genes
or repair defective ones.
H owe ve r , genome research may turn
out to have a grim downside.
It has proved that biologically there are
more similarities between human beings
than differences, f u rther dissolving tradi-
tional prejudices of race and ethnicity.
H owe ve r , differences do exist, and if inve s-
t i g ations provide sufficient data about ethnic
genetic differences between populat i o n
gr o u p s , it may one day be possible to target
the groups with dangerous micro-organisms.
One specialist who takes this eve n t u a l i t y
very seriously is Malcom R. Dando, Pro-
fessor of Peace Studies at Bradford Uni-
versity, England. In Biotechnology,Weapons
and Humanity, a newly published report
which he wrote for the BMA,he examines
the whole question of how the revolution in
biotechnology might be used to attack the
genetic constitution of an ethnic group.
“The social and ethical safeguards which
m ay prevent ethnic conflict and we a p o n s
d e velopment need to be discussed urgently,”
he said in an interv i e w. Although scientists
Genetic inform ation is already being used
in some countries to “ i m p r ove ” b i o l o gi c a l
we a p o n s ,e . g . by equipping them with agents
to provide increased antibiotic resistance—
and it is likely that this trend will accelerate as
the knowledge and understanding of its appli-
c ations become more widely know n .
In the hands of
terrorists or cult groups
The problem of the proliferation of bio-
l o gical weapon research has been aggr avat e d
by fall-out from the collapse of the form e r
S oviet Union. Most of the nearly 30,000
scientists who were invo l ved in biologi c a l
research in the USSR during the 1980s are
n ow out of a job because of the country ’s eco-
nomic diffic u l t i e s. Last ye a r , some of them
disclosed that they had been approached by
c e rtain countries which have shown part i-
cular interest in learning about microbes
t h at can be used in war to destroy or protect
c r o p s , as well as genetic engi n e e ring tech-
niques that could be used to make deadly
g e rms for which there may be no antidotes.
Dando argues that scientists in countri e s
t h at belonged to the former Soviet Union
should be dive rted from invo l vement in pro-
grammes with sinister motives by schemes
such as scientist-to-scientist exchanges, j o i n t
research projects and the conve rsion to civi-
lian use of laborat o ries and institutes once
a s s o c i ated with the Soviet military effort .
One prospect that alarms arms control
experts is that biological weapons will fall
into the hands of terrorist or cult groups.
Twe l ve people were killed and 5,000 injured
year that marks the 50th annive rs a ry of the
d i s c ove ry of the structure of DNA by Ja m e s
Watson and Francis Crick.
D e t e rmining the sequence of the DNA
bases in the entire human DNA will eve n-
tually determine where genes are located and
w h at instructions are carried in a part i c u l a r
section of DNA. This inform ation will be
used by researchers to understand the func-
tion of genes and how they cause disease.
Genome research has already helped scien-
tists to identify genes associated with dia-
b e t e s ,breast cancer and A l z h e i m e r ’s disease.
The project also opens up an arr ay of ethical
dilemmas relating to such questions as genetic
testing for predisposition to hereditary diseases
and the possible use of genetic inform at i o n
about individuals for commercial purp o s e s
( e . g . insurance) and the sharing of know l e d g e
b e t ween rich and poor countri e s.Another key
issue is that of the intellectual property of
+ …
Useful websites
l http://www.gene.ucl.ac.uk/hugo (The Human
Genome Organization)
l http://www.nhgri.nih.gov (The National Human
Genome Research Institute)
l http://www.ornl.gov/hgmis (Human Genome
Project Information)
l http://www.tigr.org (The Institute for Genomic
Research)
r e s e a r c h e rs , especially since pri vate compa-
nies have entered the gene-mapping race.
UN E S C O has adopted a Unive rsal Decla-
r ation on the Human Genome and Human
Rights which was endorsed by the United
N ations on 9 December 1998.Among its sti-
p u l ations is the follow i n g : “No one shall be
subjected to discri m i n ation based on genetic
c h a r a c t e ristics that is intended to infringe or
has the effect of infri n ging human ri g h t s ,f u n-
damental freedoms and human dignity.” n
E . A .
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
Cleaning up 
the net
A s the world wires up, police are grappling for
a solution to a growing problem: the Internet
is unleashing a frightening wave of child porno-
graphy.
Circulation of child porn is growing exponen-
t i a l l y, according to experts at a recent UN E S C O
meeting on the issue. A few years ago, Interpol
raids on suspected paedophiles turned up a small
number of videos and magazines, according to
Agnes Fournier de Saint Maur of Interpol’s Spe-
cialized Crime Unit. Last year,O p e ration Cathedra l ,
a major international police crackdown on
cybersmut,led to the arrests of 96 people in 12
c o u n t r i e s, with a half-million images stockpiled in
U.S. computers alone.
Experts say the feeling of anonymity in down-
loading images helps netizens weave intricate
networks to exchange pornographic materials.
This appears to fuel both demand and supply of
child porno.
To aid police crackdowns on these networks,
governments are tightening legal loopholes.
H o w e v e r, differences in national laws are pro-
ving to be an obstacle. In the UK, for example,
police cannot effectively attack the source of the
materials because about 95 per cent of them
comes from abroad.The largest concentration of
child porn websites is found in Japan,where it is
not an offence to possess and distribute child
porn.
Police are also running into a technological
b a r r i e r : computer encryption codes used to circu-
late materials secretly. Pressure is building on
software companies to reveal these codes, while
Internet service providers are coming under fire for
not closing dubious websites. Fournier de Saint
Maur says that if the computer industry doesn’t act
fast to clamp down on child porn,“then it may well
be that the judicial system will do it for them.”
Threats like this are rattling human rights
groups. Do we want police setting up guidelines
to censor the Internet? Human rights groups note
encryption is not just used by pornogra p h e r s, b u t
also by political dissidents trying to exercise a
basic right:freedom of expression. n
in the Tokyo subway in 1995 in an attack
launched by the Aum Shinry k yo cult using
s a ri n , a lethal nerve gas that produces
asphyxia.Investigations later revealed that
the cult group had had no problem in
recruiting scientists to work on biological
weapons but could not employ the we a-
pons due to lack of a proper delive ry system.
As a first step in coping with the problem
of potential new biological we a p o n s , a rm s
control experts are calling for the bolsteri n g
of the Biological and Toxin Weapons Conve n-
tion (BTWC),an intern ational treaty signed
in 1972.The convention prohibits its signa-
t o ries from deve l o p i n g, p r o d u c i n g, s t o c k p i l i n g
and acquiring biological we a p o n s.
Dando points to the fact that though
142 nations have signed the convention so
fa r , this has not deterred countries from
d e veloping or obtaining knowledge on bio-
logical weapons. “This is mainly because
there is no verification system attached to
the convention,” he says.
Monitoring  the uses
of genome mapping
“The threat of new genetic weapons is
clearly going to be an ongoing problem for
the intern ational community,” s ays Michael
M o o d i e , President of the U.S.-based Che-
mical and Biological A rms Control Insti-
t u t e . “Such weapons are covered by the cur-
rent treat y,but this needs to be strengthened
by an effective ve ri fic ation protocol and fully
implemented so we can be sure states comply
with their obligat i o n s. A va riety of tools
should be used, including arms control,
e x p o rt controls and enhanced intelligence
capability to monitor countries of concern .”
The BMA report cited earlier says pro-
fessional scientists and physicians should
shoulder their ethical responsibilities and
take no part in biological and genetic we a p o n
p r o j e c t s. It calls for close monitoring of deve-
lopments in biotechnology worldwide and
open debat e ,p a rticularly in relation to the use
of genome mapping. H owe ve r ,“These mea-
sures can minimize the threats but not eli-
m i n ate them,” s ays Nat h a n s o n .
There is also gr owing concern about the
misuse of genetic inform ation available on
I n t e rn e t . Scientists worldwide share infor-
m ation on new findings in biological research
through Internet which could be manipu-
l ated by pri vate gr o u p s. N athanson say s
I n t e rnet service prov i d e rs have an ethical
o b l i g ation to ensure inform ation on biologi c a l
weapons is not available on their we b s i t e s.
One big problem in monitoring is how
to distinguish between research carried out
for good and evil ends. The fact is that
genetic research which develops specific
therapeutic agents is scientifically indistin-
guishable from research to develop a lethal
or disabling agent targeted at specific clus-
t e rs of genes in an ethnic gr o u p.This makes
it all the more necessary to make sure that
information is used for positive purposes.
According to Dando, one avenue to be
explored is to ensure that developing coun-
t ries are gi ven the opportunity to share the
benefits of the modern revolution in bio-
t e c h n o l o gies which can be used for disease
control and economic deve l o p m e n t . I n
return they would be required to promise
that malign research would not be carried
out in their laboratories. “This is currently
being negotiated by countries which are
party to the BTWC,” he says. n
Ethirajan Anbarasan
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
Drawing up accurate inventories of art treasures is an essential first step in
the fight against massive international trafficking
Bas-reliefs from the temple of Banteay Chmar (Cambodia) before and after looting.
Three terra-cotta heads stolen in Nigeria in 1994.
They were seized by the French police and
restored to Nigeria in 1996.
n
In economic term s , illicit trafficking in
cultural property ranks alongside inter-
national illicit trading in arms, drugs
and tobacco. To d ay, i n t e rn ational effort s
to stop it rely not only on legi s l at i o n , but also
on an approach which is by no means uni-
versally applied—thorough cataloguing.
Imagine that your car has been stolen
and that when you go to report the theft yo u
c a n ’t remember what model it is.You can’t
s ay in what year it was manufactured or
w h at its regi s t r ation number is, and yo u
certainly haven’t got a photo of it. Even if
the police find it within 24 hours , t h e y
won’t know whose it is, and what’s more
you’ll have a hard time proving that it was
yours in the first place.
This is often the case with works of art
which have been stolen from museums or
religious buildings or have been looted or
traded in questionable circumstances in
wartime. One day they may be seized by
customs officials or turn up on the art
market without their legi t i m ate ow n e rs
being able to prove their case.
The many organizations that are
engaged in combating the illicit trade in
cultural propert y, including national police
f o r c e s ,I n t e rpol (the Intern ational Cri m i n a l
Police Organizat i o n ) , the Intern at i o n a l
Council of Museums (ICOM),the Interna-
tional Institute for the Unific ation of Pri vat e
L aw (UN I D RO I T) and UN E S C O, are now
m oving beyond their traditional concern
with the theft aspect of the problem and
emphasizing prevention rather than cure.
They encourage personal and electronic
s u rveillance of works of art in places where
they are exhibited, but this solution is not
a lways affordable.They also say that taking
p h o t o graphs and making detailed inve n t o-
ries and keeping them in a safe place can be
a more effective way of tackling the problem
of theft than might appear at first sight.
The Getty Inform ation Institute, w h i c h
is part of the Los Angeles-based Getty
Foundation in the United States,has been
working for some ye a rs on a project to
d e velop a new intern ational standard, c a l l e d
Object ID, intended to simplify and ratio-
nalize the description of works of art and
a n t i q u e s.The project, which has UN E S C O’s
backing, does not exclude any of the exis-
ting methods. One gr e at advantage is its
simplicity—a record is made of each art
wo r k , giving its measurements (size and
weight),the material it is made of (such as
b r o n z e , wo o d , o i l , e t c. ) , the subject, t h e
date,the author and other data.
I n t e rpol regularly publishes details of the
most wanted works of art . It is currently put-
ting the finishing touches to a CD-ROM
and testing an electronic system which will
enable any of its offices to know within
minutes whether an object appears on any
of the lists of stolen art.It will be as simple
as sending an e-mail to the database at
Interpol headquarters in Lyons (France)
and getting back a coded message, which
may even include a picture of the object
concerned.
No country 
is safe
M e a n w h i l e , the Intern ational Council of
Museums published a “Red List” of A f ri c a n
art works at the end of 1997, highlighting
objects that are particularly likely to come
from illegal or clandestine excavat i o n s. Fo r
ICOM’s Valérie Jullien, “This is something
like a list of endangered animal species. It
c o n c e rns objects from sites in the Niger
Valley, Chad or Cameroon that are syste-
m atically looted, resulting in the destru c t i o n
of archaeological sites month after month,
thereby removing any possibility of recons-
t ructing the history of the objects, of the civi-
lizations from which they came and of the
people who made them.”The list is intended
to be open-ended and could therefore be
applied to endangered objects in other areas
of the world,adds Jullien.
All the organizations invo l ved agree that
illicit trafficking is a scourge from which
no country is immune. In A f ri c a , there have
Tracking down  
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Making honesty the b e s t p o l i c y
been thefts from the national museums of
A l g e ri a , A n g o l a , B o t swa n a , E g y p t , C ô t e
d ’ I vo i r e , L i b ya , N i g e ria and the form e r
Z a i r e , to mention only a few. In Latin A m e-
rica, indigenous communities such as the
Coroma of Bolivia are fighting to recover
ceremonial fabrics (q’ipis), and any obser-
vant visitor to Mexico City’s Nat i o n a l
A n t h r o p o l o gical Museum cannot help noti-
cing the gaps left in some of its display
cases where objects have disappeared in
mysterious circumstances.
Europe and North A m e rica have not
been spared. Camille Corot’s painting Le
Chemin de Sèvres (1885) vanished from the
Louvre museum in Pa ris one Sunday in
M ay 1998, d u ring peak visiting hours.
According to Interpol data,in 1997 alone,
2,476 art works were stolen in Germany,
2,944 in Russia, 2,244 in the Czech Repu-
blic and 5,569 in France. In Italy, the police
reported that over 30,000 art objects were
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 41
n Apart from domestic legislation,states,
o r g a n i z ations and individuals can make
use of a whole arsenal of ethical and legal
remedies to defend their rights in cases of
illicit trade in cultural property. The most
recent of these instruments is an interna-
tional Code of Ethics for Dealers in Cultural
P r o p e rt y, which UN E S C O recommended its
Member States to adopt in January 1999.
The novelty of this Code, a kind of hand-
book of good conduct, resides in the fact that
it was prepared with the help of the dealers
themselves, who are urged to check scru-
pulously the ori gin of all the works of art in
which they trade.
The 1954 Hague Convention on the
Protection of Cultural Property in the Case
of A rmed Conflict was followed in 1970 by
the UNESCO Convention on the Means of
Prohibiting and Preventing the Illicit Import ,
Export and Transfer of Ownership of Cul-
tural Propert y.This non-retroactive Conve n-
tion has been ratified by 89 countries.
The UN I D RO I T ( I n t e rn ational Institute
for the Unific ation of Pri vate Law) Conve n-
tion on Stolen or Illegally Exported Cultural
Objects (1995) is complementary to the
UN E S C O C o nve n t i o n , in the sense that it
g ove rns mat t e rs chiefly related to public law,
while the latter concentrates on pri vate law.S o
far it is binding on seven countries (Lithuania,
Pa r a g u ay, R o m a n i a , Pe ru ,H u n g a ry, C h i n a
and Ecuador).The most significant clause in
the UN I D RO I T C o nvention is the pri n c i p l e
whereby anyone in possession of a stolen
object is always bound to return it, e ve n
though the object was acquired in good fa i t h .
L a s t l y, looting of the historic remains of
shipwrecks throughout the world has led
UN E S C O to undertake the drafting of a
C o nvention on the underwater heri t a g e , a
p a rticularly sensitive issue in the Scandi-
n avian countri e s , Australia and the Cari b-
b e a n . n
stolen in 1996, which is equivalent to the
stock of an average-sized museum.
Besides the economic value represented
by these objects on the intern ational market,
the damage caused by the loss of cultural
h e ritage sometimes borders on the irr e p a-
r a b l e .
This was the case with over 100 Khmer
sculptures discovered by the Thai authori-
ties on trucks in January 1999.The pieces
had been taken from the temple of Banteay
C h m a r , built at the end of the 12th century
in north-western Cambodia by King Jaya-
varman VII. The bas-reliefs adorning the
wall around the temple were ripped out in
s e veral places, l e aving a gap over 11 metres
l o n g . According to Professor Claude
Ja c q u e s , who directed an on-site inve s t i g a-
t i o n , this is a particularly serious case
because the wall contained palaeographic
inscriptions which are rarely found in sur-
viving written documents. In other words,
this particular theft amounts to the des-
t ruction of archives “ t h at end up decorat i n g
the drawing rooms and gardens of people
    looted         a r t
These statues from Burkina Faso (above) and
Nigeria (above right) feature on the “Red List”of
the International Council of Museums (ICOM).
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
Saving
Bosnia’s
heritage
How do you look after national heritage in a
divided country? Since the November 1995
Dayton Accords on peace in Bosnia and Herze-
g o v i n a , the former Yugoslav republic has been
divided into two parts—the Croat-Muslim fede-
ration and the Serb republic. But the country’s
historical monuments and sites are spread over the
two and are a common heritage.
A Bosnia-Herzegovina state body, the Bosnian
Institute for Heritage Protection, has the job of loo-
king after this heritage, but with scant means at
its disposal.A country exhausted by war can pro-
vide very little funding. Internal problems and
lack of dialogue between the different ethnic
communities have also held up passage of a law
governing national heritage by the institutions
of Bosnia and Herzegovina.Lack of such legisla-
tion has badly handicapped the Institute in doing
its job and in appealing for funds from abroad.
International organizations can do nothing in
such a situation.M e a n w h i l e,heritage sites ra n g i n g
from the prehistoric to those of the Austro-Hun-
garian and Ottoman empires are steadily crum-
bling away.
But there are a few glimmers of hope in this
bleak picture. In November 1998, a UN E S C O- s p o n-
sored international team began the job of rebuil-
ding Mostar’s Old Bridge, which had been des-
troyed in the fighting.The 16th-century bridge, a
symbol of links between ethnic communities,
should be restored to its former glory by the year
2001.By then, it may have also have become a
UNESCO World Heritage site.The Institute recently
proposed that it be placed on the World Heritage
List,along with part of Sarajevo’s city centre.
Right now, there are no World Heritage sites in
Bosnia and Herzegovina. But UN E S C O’s help would
be invaluable in the task of saving what remains
of the country’s historic wealth of culture. n
An ongoing campaign
nWill the British Museum of London
return to Greece the Parthenon sculp-
tures widely known as the Elgin Marbles?
This question has caused ri ve rs of ink to ru n
ever since 1982, when Melina Mercouri,
then minister of culture of Greece, t o o k
the floor at a UN E S C O conference in Mexico
City and said: “I believe the time has come
for these marbles to return home to the
blue skies of Attica,to their rightful place,
where they form a structural and functional
part of a unique entity”.
A t h e n s , which will host the Olympic
Games in 2004, has renewed its political
and diplomatic efforts to take adva n t a g e
of this event to repat ri ate the sculptures
that Phidias carved to adorn the temple of
Athena on the Acropolis in the fifth century
AD.The United Kingdom argues that the
sculptures were legally purchased in 1816
from Lord Elgin,who 14 years earlier had
r e m oved them from Athens with the special
p e rmission of the Ottoman sultan by whom
Greece was ruled at the time.
The publication in July 1998 of a revised
edition of a book by the British expert
William St. Clair (Lord Elgin and the Marbles,
Oxford Unive rsity Press, first edition 1967)
set the ball rolling again, since its author
claims to have proof that in 1937 Bri t i s h
Museum curat o rs caused irreparable damage
to the surface of the marbles, by scru b b i n g
and scraping them in order to return them to
w h at they believed to be their ori ginal colour,
namely white, r e m oving forever the honey-
coloured patina that had adorned them since
A n t i q u i t y.
Greek archaeologist Yannis T z e d a k i s ,
who has supported the cause of the return
of the marbles for 40 years,adds that:“We
are not sure whether the chemical sub-
stances used in the cleaning remain active ” .
He calls for Greek specialists to be given
access to the Museum’s archives and to the
actual sculptures.
M e a n w h i l e , the British Museum is orga-
nizing a conference of experts later this
year to assess the state of what it regards as
its propert y : 56 of the 97 panels of the Pa r-
thenon fri e z e , 15 of its 64 metopes plus
other sculptures, which together account for
half the surviving pieces of the Greek
t e m p l e .The British Museum argues that it
o f f e rs free access to the public, t h at it opens
s e ven days a week and that it receives some
six and a half million visitors each year. n
who cannot even decipher them.”
Recalling that the Angkor site, w h i c h
contains some 1,200 temples spread over an
area of 300 km2, is part of the heritage of
h u m a n i t y, Cambodian Prince Norodom
Suhamomi expresses his Gove rn m e n t ’s
concern on the issue in these terms: “We
h ave a heritage that is disappeari n g . In some
places in Cambodia, ten times more sculp-
tures have been lost in three decades than
b e t ween the eighth century and the 1970s,
and we now need the help of our colleagues.
E ven though the Cambodian authori t i e s
are doing all they can to combat this ini-
quitous situat i o n , their efforts will neve r
be sufficient because the demand in Europe
and the United States is simply enorm o u s.”
Making up
for the damage
Another question that arises for profes-
sionals is what to do when a stolen work of art
r e a p p e a rs in an auction or in the back room
of a none too scrupulous trader. For Va l é ri e
J u l l i e n , there is no easy answe r: “Buying it
would be unethical, since it would signify
e n c o u r a ging this type of traffic k i n g .” A p a rt
from the costs of the purchase itself, t h e r e
could be other related expenses, such as the
legal costs incurred by gove rnments or indi-
viduals for court actions to recover their pro-
p e rt y, or the considerable costs of paying for
the transfer of art works between places as fa r
a p a rt as Italy and Ethiopia. In some cases,
l aw ye rs ’ o f fices may provide free services or
p ri vate companies may sponsor returns in
exchange for publicity, but such contri bu-
tions are marginal and certainly not enough
to cover all the expenses.
UN E S C O’s Intergove rnmental Com-
mittee for Promoting the Return of Cultural
Property to its Countries of Origin or its
Restitution in Case of Illicit A p p r o p ri at i o n
is considering setting up a fund based on
vo l u n t a ry contri bu t i o n s , and this might go
some way towards solving the problem.
Differences may of course be settled
with the goodwill of the parties. For ins-
tance, as a result of a court judgment fol-
l owed by a friendly agr e e m e n t , almost 200
objects of pre-Columbian art curr e n t l y
exhibited at the Museum of Non-Euro-
pean Cultures in Rimini (Italy) alongside
their names and ori gins carry the follow i n g
m e n t i o n : “ P r o p e rty of the State of
Ecuador”. n
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
n
They have been a familiar sight across
Singapore recently: bronzed Indian
workmen clad in fluorescent orange SCV
(Singapore Cable Vision) jackets labouri n g
under the scorching sun to lay cable for the
island stat e ’s suburban neighbourhoods.T h e
rush to cable up the island is the result of an
i n i t i at i ve by the gove rnment to transform the
entire population into netizens, hooked up
by cable modem to a nationwide broadband
n e t wo r k , at a speed 100 times faster than cur-
rent ISDN Internet access.
While the idea would seem ridiculous in
a country as large as, s ay the U. S . , Brazil or
China, wiring Singapore is hardly a daun-
ting task, given a total land mass of barely
647.5 square kilometres. Dubbed Singa-
pore ONE, the national network aims to
d e l i ver a new level of interactive , m u l t i-
media applications and services to homes,
businesses and schools. The authori t i e s
claim that this effort is the first in the wo r l d
O N E i n t e l l i g e n t
i s l a n d S i n g a p o re is bidding to create a ‘ w i red’ economy
w h e re services converge on the Internet at an
u n p a ralleled pace to transform the island’s chief
re s o u rce—a well educated population—into a new
b reed of netizens
to go “live” and deliver such services to a
mass user base.
“Singapore ONE is more than just a
communication network. It will empower
Singaporeans to work efficiently in a ‘ s m a rt ’
e nv i r o n m e n t , to fa c i l i t ate the use and access
of information to enhance their business,
personal and family lives,” Prime Minister
Goh Chok Tong has stated.
The gove rnment considers it crucial for
a resource-scarce country like Singapore
to equip itself for the inform ation age. S i n-
gapore’s push to carve out a place in the
global digital marketplace is especially signi-
ficant in the light of the Asian financial
c ri s i s. While some Asian countries have
been tightening controls on their markets,
Singapore is trying to open up the eco-
n o my further through a va riety of initia-
t i ve s , including ONE. Other Asian countri e s
are looking on to see whether Singapore
ONE may hold important lessons for them
in their efforts to make the most of the
information age.
With a per capita gross domestic product
of $24,600, Singapore ranks among the
wo r l d ’s top 20 richest economies. S i n g a p o r e
ONE is therefore not just a social serv i c e
from a gove rnment to its people but rather a
c rucial investment in the country ’s only
r e s o u r c e : its people.The gove rnment decision
to commit $240 million for ONE infra-
s t ructure development reflects a commit-
ment to upgrade the skills and knowledge of
its we l l - e d u c ated populat i o n .
S e rvices on offer range from banking,
s h o p p i n g, t h e atre ticket booking, and pro-
p e rty viewing to distance learn i n g . T h e
va rious virtual colleges and scholastic pro-
grammes offer eve rything from engi n e e ri n g
c o u rses to interactive multimedia cours e s
for school-kids. E n t e rt a i n m e n t , like a favo u-
rite TV programme or video, is provided on
d e m a n d . A chat on the phone with a fri e n d
is replaced by a virtual video conference.
Instead of wo rrying about what the kids are
doing at home, parents can keep an eye on
them thanks to video-conferencing, with a
web-camera sending images from home to
the personal office computer.
40,000 users
U s e rs of cable modems are charged a
subsidized flat rate of about $21 a month and
u s e rs of SingTe l ’s ADSL lines enjoy a similar
r at e . The network began a one-year pilot
phase in June 1997 and was commercially
launched the following ye a r. Only about
15,000 households have bought the pac-
k a g e .H owe ve r , the low subscription rates are
offset by the gr owing number of users ,a c c o r-
ding to officials at the National Computer
Board (NCB), the main gove rnment body
behind the project. “If you include users at
s c h o o l s , t e rt i a ry institutions, c o m m u n i t y
centres and librari e s , we have a conservat i ve
e s t i m ate of at least 40,000 users ,” said Ng
Kin Ye e , assistant director for progr a m m e
management and new media.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
C O N N E X I O N S
Ng says it is normal for new infrastru c-
ture products to experience a modest initial
u p t a k e . “Singapore ONE is not just about
i n f r a s t ru c t u r e ,i t ’s all about building the skills,
the people awareness among senior citizens,
children and their parents who might have
had a phobia for computers ,” he say s.
The gove rnment began laying the gr o u n d-
work to create an IT- l i t e r ate population for
Singapore ONE in the 1980s. To d ay more
than 40 per cent of Singapore households
own a computer and more than 350,000 out
of a population of 3 million subscribe to the
I n t e rn e t . In fa c t , Singapore has been reco-
gnized as the second most IT- l i t e r ate country
in the world after the United Stat e s by the
World Competitiveness Report , which is
published annually by the Institute for Mana-
gement Development (IMD) in Switzerland.
E-commerce on ONE
S i n g a p o r e ’s electronic-commerce—or
e-commerce, short for buying and selling
over the Intern e t — i n f r a s t ructure is equally
a d va n c e d . Online purchases can be paid
through cashcards or security credit card
p ayment systems and banks use digital cer-
t i f i c ates and smart cards to offer secure
online banking. C o m p r e h e n s i ve legi s l at i o n
is also being considered to provide an elec-
tronic transaction legal framework to encou-
rage more online commerce.
“ E - business is not just about E-com-
m e r c e ,” said Howie Lau, manager for e-bu s i-
ness solutions at Hewlett Packard Singapore.
“ E - business opens up tremendous opport u-
nities for companies to further relat i o n s h i p s
with customers , p a rt n e rs and employees by
linking internal business processes to the
I n t e rn e t .Singapore ONE could potentially be
valuable for scenarios where large amounts of
i n f o rm ation or speed of transmission are fa c-
t o rs such as the exchange of business docu-
ments with part n e rs ; s h a ring of common
i n f o rm ation within a community (e.g. r e a l
e s t ate agents sharing a common database of
p r o p e rt y ) ; realtime synchronization of multi-
m e d i a ; mobile employees gaining access to
c o rp o r ate file serve rs ,d at a b a s e s.The scena-
rios are pretty well endless.”
A l r e a d y,S i n g Tel has launched a separat e
ATM network specifically targeted at bu s i-
n e s s - t o - business transactions to complement
Singapore ONE. The focus of Singapore
O N E ’s network is to connect consumers to
businesses and gove rn m e n t .M e a n w h i l e ,S i n g-
Te l ’s ATM network connects bu s i n e s s e s ,a c a-
demic institutions and gove rn m e n t . S i n g-
Te l ’s ATM network will have connexions to
Singapore ONE and will provide it with high
speed intern ational links. Since its launch in
June last ye a r , S i n g Te l ’s ATM network has
established links to A u s t r a l i a , Hong Kong,
Japan and the U. S .There are plans for SingTe l
to be extended to Europe and other major
Asia Pa c i fic destinations this ye a r.
While some analysts anticipate that bu s i-
n e s s - t o - business transactions will take ove r
from the ori ginal consumer-based plan for
Singapore ONE,NCB’s Ng says that both
sectors can grow in tandem. “One sector
need not necessarily exclude the other,” h e
i n s i s t s. C u rr e n t l y, the 200 service prov i-
d e rs to Singapore ONE include major
s u p e rm a r k e t s , fashion and retail outlets,
b a n k s , insurance companies and books-
tores.
Retailers thinking globally
“Interactive multimedia offers infinite
possibilities for retail,” says Bernard Yang,
manager of Nanyang Optical, one of Sin-
gapore’s major optical chains which has a
site on Singapore One.“Imagine a person
watching a TCS (Television Corp o r ation of
Singapore) drama. The viewer likes the
frame wo rn by Zoe Tay (popular Singapore
a c t r e s s ) , with a click of a bu t t o n , up pops the
Focal Point (Nanyang Optical on Singa-
pore ONE) and he or she can buy and have
the same pair delivered to their doorstep.”
“Selling via the Net also means I do
not have to put up with exorbitant rentals
and expensive manpower. All I need is a
good web designer and a system adminis-
t r ator plus leased line charges. If I can make
the same sales on the Net that I do in my
shops,then I’d be a really happy guy!”
Most retailers , like Nanya n g, h ave a pre-
sence on the Internet as well as on Singapore
O N E . P r e d i c t a b l y, sales are higher on the
I n t e rnet than on ONE, simply because of
higher user rat e s.Ya n g, h owe ve r , sees it as
vital to establish a name for himself on ONE,
which he anticipates will be the main plat f o rm
Website of the month
http://www.unicef.org/bhutan
Bh u t a n , the little-known kingdom of 630,000 people nestled in the folds of the eastern Himalaya n
M o u n t a i n s, has taken another step out of self-imposed isolation: the country now appears on the
Web.Through a site recently created by the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF),one quickly discovers
that Bhutan is not a fossilized and romanticized Shangri-La.In fact,the development experience of Bhu-
tan is unusual because, since it started opening up to the ouside world in 1961, it embarked upon what the
World Bank, for one, calls a far-reaching development stra t e g y, and has made substantial progress in
improving living standards.
The government’s growth objectives, however, are tempered by an earnest desire to preserve the coun-
t r y ’s distinctive cultural heritage and its rich natural resources base. Bhutan has been well ahead of the rest
of the world in its commitment to environmental protection:for example, forest cover has increased from
60 to over 70 per cent in the past twenty years.
Bhutan joined the U.N. in 1971 and UNICEF’s involvement began three years later when it started its first
water supply programme. Since then, UNICEF has been involved in health,education, water and sanitation
p r o j e c t s.The website,animated with photogra p h s,music and videos, provides us with a glimpse of the coun-
try and its people in their everyday village lives:a health worke r, a teacher, a Buddhist monk,and many others.
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
The Web lifestyle
n Leading the “ web lifestyle” of billionaire
Bill Gates should be a reality for the ave-
rage Singaporean in four or five ye a rs accor-
ding to the Microsoft founder.Visiting the
island in 1998, G ates predicted that this
would become a reality in Singapore even
faster than in the U.S., thanks to the Sin-
gapore ONE initiative.
A l r e a d y, d r e a m e rs at the National Com-
puter Board have created a mock cy b e r-
flat.Picture this: Hassan,the eldest son, is
lounging on his bed enjoying a romantic
video-conference chat with his gi r l f ri e n d
in A u s t r a l i a . He suddenly remembers he
has forgotten her birt h d ay ; a few clicks of the
mouse and he has ordered flowe rs to be
d e l i vered to her within the hour. M e a n w h i l e
Mum is in the kitchen simultaneously
cooking dinner and attending a corporate
planning video conference meeting with
her boss and colleagues in the US.
H a l f way through the meeting, s h e
remembers a few ingredients she’s forgot-
ten to buy. She clicks a couple of times on
a mouse (while listening with apparent
c o n c e n t r ation to her colleague’s bu s i n e s s
plan) and the gr o c e ries will be at her doors-
tep in a couple of hours. Meanwhile,baby
is visible, sleeping peacefully on the “live”
baby monitor screen and toddlers Noraini
and Nordin are shown on yet another
screen watching Discovery Channel inter-
actively, downloading everything they ever
wanted to know about elephants. Dad is in
the living room folding the laundry while
buying and selling shares via the Net.A split
screen enables him to communicate with
his office staff at the same time. Dream it
might be for now, but the cyberflat inhabi-
ted by super-efficient netizens may well be,
according to Gat e s , a reality in the near
future. n
for e-shopping in Singapore in the future.
Consultants say that Singapore retai-
lers on the Net should already be thinking
globally. “Some of the most successful e-
commerce websites, like Amazon.com,do
business with the whole wo r l d . So if
someone has a good idea that can be sold to
a nyone in the wo r l d , Singapore may be just
as good as any other place to start ,” said IT
consultant Jeroen Domensino. “ T h e r e
a p p e a rs to be too much concern here ri g h t
n ow over technicalities such as securi t y
i s s u e s.The truth is that elsewhere people are
already making big money via the Net,
regardless whether security issues (credit
card fraud, for example) are completely
r e s o l ve d . In the end, I think that consu-
mers all over the world are changing their
attitude towards what’s safe.”
Choosing between
the virtual and the real
Along with the gr owth in e-commerce,
multimedia software companies are expe-
riencing exponential demand.“Think of it as
H o l l y wo o d . If Hollywood made movies only
for the U. S . , it would be a limited market.We
want to be the Hollywood of multimedia,”
said Michael Ya p, N C B ’s assistant chief exe-
c u t i ve . S o f t ware deve l o p e rs hope that via
i n t e rn ational links, they will gain publicity
and future markets for their wo r k . “But we
will have to move fa s t ,” s ays Ng. “ I t ’s a fa s t
gr ow i n g, fast changing env i r o n m e n t .”
And in a small way, even local TV pro-
d u c e rs are anticipating demand in other
markets for Singapore progr a m m e s.“ T h e r e
is much potential to export our culture to
other countri e s ,” s ays James Leong of T C S
Multimedia. “We would definitely like to
push our content over the Internet as TCS
has done for television (Singapore-pro-
duced TV series have been broadcast in
Australia and Ta i wa n . ) ” C u rrently about
half of Singapore ONE subscri b e rs sub-
s c ribe to T C S ’ 1-on-One service which
o f f e rs made-in-Singapore TV sitcoms,
dramas,news and documentaries.
While software whizzkids and plucky
e n t r e p r e n e u rs in this little city state gear up
to make their name in cy b e rs p a c e , t h e r e
remains a fair amount of scepticism as to
whether ONE will ever be a real hit at home.
A video conference chat either with the
bosses or with good friends is unlikely to
gain popularity over coffee or kopi-O (locally
b r e wed black coffee) at the neighbourhood
outdoor food-stall.
Likewise video-on-demand viewed from
a 14-inch desktop monitor is likely to be a
much less at t r a c t i ve option to the ave r a g e
Singaporean compared with watching the
l atest laser discs or Video CDs on the fa m i-
l y ’s 31-inch stereo TV (the pride and joy of
most Singapore households). And in this
metropolis ove r built with malls, real shopping
as opposed to virt u a l , will likely remain the
most popular pastime, regardless of how
i n t e r a c t i ve and alluring a web-mall might be.
There will definitely be choices and
options for consumers and entrepreneurs.
Some will choose the virtual and some will
choose the real.The authorities only hope
t h at they will have equipped the populat i o n
with the IT literacy to at least exercise that
option in the next millennium. n
With distributed
c o m p u t i n g , t h e r e ’s
s t rength i n
n u m b e r s
Suppose you have to crack a really hefty com-
puter problem—in technical jargon,say you
want to decode a computer message written in the
“56-bit encryption” common these days. In theory
i t ’s very simple: you try all possible solutions until
you find the right one. But there’s a problem:the
total number of possible solutions is two multiplied
56 times by itself—a number which would fil l
almost a whole line of this column.
There are two ways to deal with this. Either you
happen to have the great privilege of using one of
the world’s super- c o m p u t e r s, in which case the pro-
blem will be solved very quickly, or else you resort
to the old idea that strength lies in numbers.
S e v e ral websites are tackling it the second wa y,
among them http://www.distributed.net,by dra-
wing on the dormant capacity of the perfectly
ordinary computers of some 22,000 voluntary
p a r t i c i p a n t s. L i ke all computer buffs, these volun-
teers do not use their machines at full capacity or
all the time. Any programme they use—e. g . a
word-processing programme—occupies only part
of the machine’s capacity.And like all enthusiasts,
they sometimes feel like phoning a friend or stop-
ping for a cup of coffee. Some of them even leave
their computers switched on when they’re not
using them.
What these volunteers do is install in their
machine a small free programme which, w h e n
they connect to a central “server”by a modem,
tells the server how much capacity is available in
the machine.The machine then downloads the ele-
ments needed to process a tiny part of the gigantic
calculating operation.
“Distributed.net”,which at first took 40 days
to crack the code, managed it in less than a day by
this method. Others, including the University of
California at Berke l e y, the radio-telescope at A r e-
c i b o, in Puerto Rico, and an American UFO club are
planning to call on 110,000 computer enthu-
siasts around the world to help analyse ra d i o
signals received from outer space in the hope of
detecting signs of extra-terrestrial life. But this
method of “distributed computing” can also per-
form more urgent tasks. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
A h m a d o uKo u r o u m a
anAfrican novelist’s
inside story 
Ahmadou Kourouma is a writer from Côte d’Ivoire whose relatively slender
but highly original output—three novels published over 28 years—draws up
an eloquent indictment of the injustices imposed on black Africa
Your first novel, The Suns of Independence,
published in 1970, has won acclaim as a
masterpiece and has sold 100,000 copies.
But you had a hard time finding a publisher
for it. Why?
The book was rejected for two reasons.
F i rs t , my style had a certain ori gi n a l i t y
stemming from the particular way in which
I used the French language. Some readers
found this disconcert i n g . S e c o n d , m a ny
people disliked the conception of the
n ove l . I had structured it in the kind of way
used by the A m e rican writer John Dos
Passos earlier this century. I ended the fic-
tional part of the book with a section I
would describe as documentary. After tel-
ling the story of the protagonist, Fa m a , I
d e s c ribed situations and events that took
place in Côte d’Ivoire at the time of the
Cold Wa r. I talked about things that might
be called sensitive . Some A f rican publi-
s h e rs even sent the manuscript back to me
with scat h i n g, almost insulting comments.
How did you come to master what was for
you a foreign language—French?
I had no choice in the matter. I didn’t
know how to express myself in any other
language. My English was poor, and I
have never learned Arabic. In school I was
only taught French and, like everyone
who went to school before decoloniza-
tion,I wasn’t allowed to speak our mother
tongue, Malinke1. So I had to use French
to describe Malinke people and tell sto-
ries of Malinke life.Some people have cri-
ticized me for “bashing” the French lan-
guage and giving it a Malinke twist.
It has even been said that you have “cuc-
kolded” French.
Whatever people might say, I am not
trying to change French.What I’m inter-
ested in is reproducing to the fullest pos-
sible extent the way my characters live
and think. My characters are Malinke.
And when the Malinke speak, they follow
their own logic, their own way of looking
at the world. That approach doesn’t go
into French. The sequence of words and
ideas in Malinke is different from what it
is in French. There is a big gap between
what I describe and the form in which I
express myself, a gap much bigger than
the gap when an Italian speaks French,
for example. I repeat, my objective is not
formal or linguistic. What I’m interested
in is reality. My characters must be cre-
dible and to be credible they must speak
in the novel as they speak in their own
language.
How would you describe the Malinke lan-
guage?
Some people may disagree, but it seems
to me that African languages are on the
whole far richer than European lan-
guages. They have a wide range of words
to denote one and the same thing and a
multitude of expressions to describe one
and the same feeling, as well as many
mechanisms for creating neologi s m s.
Malinke alone has around ten of these.
African languages are rich in proverbs
and sayings which people constantly refer
to. So it’s not surprising that sometimes
we get bogged down when we use French
to describe our lives and our psychologi-
cal universe.The French language, on the
other hand, is the product of a Catholic,
r ationalist civilizat i o n . T h at ’s obvious
from its structure, its way of analysing
and describing reality. Our language is
influenced by fetishist spirituality and is
closer to nature.
Western authors often speak 
of writing as a physical,vital,
organic need. For you, it is more a way 
of getting a hearing.
For us African writers, writing is also a
matter of survival.When I wrote The Suns
of Independence, I wanted to campaign
against abuses of social and economic
power. That was a vital and absolute
necessity! All contemporary French and
other European wri t e rs have devo t e d
some of their work to the four years of
o c c u p ation and oppression that their
c o u n t ries endured during the second
world war. But in Africa we had 100 years
1 . The Malinke are the largest of the gr o u p s
composing the Mande ethnic gr o u p. Most of them
l i ve in Guinea, M a l i , Senegal and Côte d’Ivo i r e ,
where they make up 11 per cent of the populat i o n .
C o nve rted to Islam in the 11th century, t h e
Malinke have ruled powerful empires which they
d o m i n ated by force of numbers ,a rms and
economic powe r.They are reputed to have a good
head for bu s i n e s s , and are also known as Dioulas, a
word meaning “ m e r c h a n t s ” in Malinke.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 47
Hard facts
“We African writers work in gruelling condi-
t i o n s,” says Ahmadou Ko u r o u m a .“ W r i-
ters are seldom rich anywhere in the world, but for
us things are even tougher. We have fewer
r e s o u r c e s, fewer readers and fewer publishers.”Th e
only available statistics, which are not recent but
are probably still valid, reveal that sub-Saharan
Africa publishes three times fewer titles than the
average for developing countries and 25 times
fewer than that for the developed countries.
“ There are two ways of writing in A f r i c a ,” Ko u-
rouma says.“ The first is to write about Africa and
Africans. Writers denounce situations they know
relatively well,and run risks by shouting out the
t r u t h .They can’t expect big sales. They write for rea-
ders in developing countries, where people either
can’t read or can’t afford to buy books.The second
is to write for a wider public by tackling topics that
are of interest to non-Africans as well as A f r i-
c a n s. There are African authors living in Fra n c e, f o r
example, who write for an exclusively European
r e a d e r s h i p. They are European writers even if they
were born in A f r i c a . Others manage to publish best
sellers in France and are read in Africa as well, b u t
that is more unusual.
“I think that we should try and write for eve-
ryone by presenting our problems as universal
human problems.We should follow the example
set by the best Latin American litera t u r e. But A f r i-
cans are changing.The first African authors took
up the pen to show that they too could express
themselves as writers, that they too were human
b e i n g s. At the time, some people had doubts
about that. . . . My generation has gone further
than that. We have often chosen literature as a
campaigning medium.” n
of occupation, and it’s vitally important
for us to talk about this and analyse its
consequences and effects. We had as
many massacres as Europeans did during
the last war and under authori t a ri a n
Stalinist regimes. In my second novel,
Monnew, which was published in 1990, I
wanted to get across the message that we
too have endured great suffering. That
suffering is also the subject of the novel I
recently finished.Its title is En attendant le
vote des bêtes sauvages (“Waiting for the
wild animals to vote”), and it’s based on
the tragedy of the Cold War in Africa.
The sufferings you describe are intense and
extreme. But in this novel you express gra-
titude to a dictator for his “courage” in tel-
ling his compatriots that they were “thie-
ving, lazy savages.”
That remark does not refer to the people
“down below”,as we say, but to those “on
top”, the dictators’ buddies. Resignation
was the only option for the people down
below, whom I describe as “coarsened by
their beliefs and their poverty, patient and
dumb”.The Cold War prevented African
countries from finding a way out of their
predicament. It kept a millstone around
their necks. Foreign powe rs gave the
orders and pulled the strings, picked the
dictators that suited them and sent in
their military whenever there was any
resistance.
But it was the most brutal, ignorant leaders
who won the internal power struggles in
African countries.
Yes, and they also had to be cynical.The
foreign powers needed them. Apart from
a few exceptions, they didn’t want bright
p e o p l e . Those who wanted to defend
Africa, who wanted to strike a balance
between the two sides by playing cat-and-
mouse with them, were immediately eli-
minated.
But when opposition movements came on
the scene at the beginning of the democra-
tization process after the Cold War, they
turned out even worse than the dictators.
T h at ’s a fa c t .The earliest opposition leaders
t u rned out to be dru n k e n , d ru g - a d d i c t e d
l o o t e rs without principles or scru p l e s. A n d
the opposition leaders who returned after a
long exile we r e , as I have described them,
“ p e rsons alien to their country ’s people and
For us African writers, writing is also a matter of survival.
When I wrote The Suns of Independence, I wanted to
campaign against abuses of social and economic power.
That was a vital and absolute necessity!
© Ulf Andersen/Editions du Seuil, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
way of life” and therefore incapable of gr a s-
ping what was really going on. I t ’s true that
both wanted first and foremost to take
r e venge and to get ri c h .W hy? Because they
all still believed in the mirage that power is
all that mat t e rs.
People had given up and let their lea-
ders behave as village chiefs did in tradi-
tional Africa. The dictators thought they
could go it alone,taking decisions without
e ven listening to their advisers.
Government money was their money. All
those who got rich were pawns of the
government.The dictator’s power was so
absolute that all kinds of things were
expected of him. To gi ve you one
example, in my country even today, when
a fairly well-known person dies, the fami-
ly still expects the head of state to pay
10,000 or 20,000 French francs ($1,800
or $3,500) for the funeral!
Since that’s how things were, it’s not
surprising that democratization got off to
a very bad start.The old power structure
and all its works had to be destroyed,
because eve rything revo l ved around
t h e m . It was impossible for any t h i n g
constructive to be built on the existing
foundations, not only by the corrupt dic-
tators and their cronies, but also by the
opposition leaders who came back from
exile abroad and hadn’t a clue about what
was really going on. People always behave
in the same way. As the Malinke proverb
says,“The dog won’t give up its awkward
way of sitting.”
One criticism that has been made of your
most recent novel is that in Africa reality
and magic seem to be inseparable. Your
anti-hero, the dictator Koyaga, defeats all
his adversaries largely because of the
strength of his magical powers.
I don’t believe in magi c. And when
Africans ask me why I don’t, I say that if
magic really existed, we wouldn’t have
allowed the abduction of 100 million
people, of whom perhaps 40 million rea-
ched the Americas and 60 million died on
the way. If magic really worked, the slaves
would have turned into birds, say, and
would have flown back home. I don’t
In West Africa, hunters belong 
to a brotherhood which is at the top 
of the traditional social hierarchy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
March 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 49
T A L K I N G  T O …
A singular voice
A B I D JA N
C Ô T E  D ’ I V O I R E
Liberia
Burkina Faso
Mali
Yamoussoukro
Boundiali
+ …
l Po p u l a t i o n : 14.7 million
l D e n s i t y : 42 pers o n s / k m2
l Illiteracy rate: 57%
l GDP/per capita/year:$690
l UNDP ranks Côte d’Ivoire among the countries
with low human development,in 21st position
among the countries of sub-Saharan Africa.
n “A week ago Koné Ibrahima had fini-
shed in the capital,” runs the opening
sentence of The Suns of Independence, mea-
ning that Koné Ibrahima had died the pre-
vious week. It set the tone for a novel in
which Ahmadou Kourouma transposed
into French the speech-rhythms and images
of Malinke,his mother tongue.This was a
new departure in the world of French-lan-
guage A f rican literat u r e , which had hithert o
tended towards academicism. K o u r o u m a ’s
fiction may owe much of the originality of
its form and content to its author’s eve n t f u l
life story.
Ahmadou Kourouma was born in 1927
in the little town of Boundiali, t o d ay a local
administrative centre in Côte d’Ivoire.His
father was a nurs e , and as such belonged to
the colonized elite. He was called “ d o c t o r ”
and his rank gave him the right to use the
s e rvices of A f ricans subjected to forced
labour. But Kourouma was brought up by
an uncle who was on the other side of the
fence. He was a master-hunter, a leading
member of the brotherhood that stood at
the top of the traditional social scale because
of the power it enjoyed by virtue of its we a-
pons and the magic it acquired from bon-
ding with nature.
believe in magic because when I was a
boy, I saw forced labour. If magic existed,
the victims of forced labour would have
been able to escape. But in a novel you
have to describe your characters’ mentali-
ty and ideas. Power and magic are insepa-
rable in the minds of most Africans. The
dictator not only has power and money,
he also has the best fetishists and sorce-
rers. Because they are the best, the dicta-
tor is invulnerable and his power is limit-
less. For the dictator’s entourage and for
the people at large, power and magic are
one.
So how can Africa be successful 
in a world where science and technology
are increasingly important?
Rationality will gain ground at the same
time as democracy, which is still far off
but is slowly coming in. It won’t solve
every problem, but we already have its
f o u n d ation stone—the spoken wo r d .
Everywhere, we say what we want, and
that’s quite an achievement. And one
important thing we can say—and see—is
that the chief’s almighty power is on the
way out. The press can now expose
corruption and abuses of power; a leader
has to campaign against his opponents in
elections; it’s possible to get rich without
being a stooge of the government. The
leader is no longer a superman. He no
longer has everything going for him. He
has to shoulder duties and responsibili-
ties. He is becoming like everyone else.
And consequently the magical part of his
power is disappearing.
And yet at the end of your latest 
novel the dictator is forced to hold elec-
tions, but “if people refuse 
to vote for him, the animals will 
come out of the bush, get hold of ballot
papers and elect him with a landslide majo-
rity.”
Odd as it may seem, many people think
that kind of thing is possible.They’re even
sure presidents get elected that way. But
we ’re making some headway. B e f o r e ,
either there weren’t any elections at all, or
if an election was held, the dictator only
had to ask for 99 per cent of the vote for
his wish to be granted. Now he is forced
to cheat. Votes from wild animals are the
last refuge of dictators in distress. n
Interview by
René Lefort and Mauro Rosi.
As a student Kourouma took part in
protests at the Bamako Technical High
School in Mali.Then he was drafted into the
French army and ordered to Côte d’Ivoire
to part i c i p ate in a crackdown on the emer-
ging liberation movement, the Rassemble-
ment Démocratique A f ri c a i n.When he refused
to do this, he was drafted into the French
colonial army in Indochina, a posting he
only accepted because Bernard Dadier,
then Côte d’Ivoire’s most famous writer,
p e rsuaded him that military experi e n c e
would prepare him for the anti-colonial
war which he believed to be inevitable.
The next stage of Kourouma’s life came
when he travelled to France to study
science—a field spurned by most children of
the A f rican elite.He returned to Côte d’Ivo i r e
just after independence and worked as an
insurance exe c u t i ve , but did not stay long.“ I
was impervious to the magic of the single
p a rt y, which claimed to be the only form of
a u t h o rity capable of developing the country,”
he say s. Kourouma was jailed for a few
months and eventually went into exile.
His second homecoming, in 1970, wa s
almost as bri e f.When his play Le diseur de
v é rité (“The Truth Te l l e r ” ) , was published in
1 9 7 4 , it was deemed “ r e vo l u t i o n a ry ” . So he
left the country and lived in Cameroon and
Togo until 1993, continuing his career in
p ri vate insurance companies.
At 72, he thinks that his “ g e n e r at i o n
first got things wrong and then wa s n ’t up to
the job.”This was the generation that came
after the birth of the concept of Negritude
d e veloped by Léopold Sedar Senghor,“ w h o
had recognized the Negro’s qualities as a
man, but an incomplete man. We naively
believed that only colonization prevented
A f ricans from becoming fully rounded
people like any other. If A f ricans thieve d ,f o r
example, it was because of colonialism. If
colonialism ended, they would all get dow n
to wo r k .E ve ryone was going to make sacri-
fices for Africa.But we didn’t take the rea-
lity and psychology of Africa into account.
TheSuns of Independence was the first book
of its kind to emphasize that A f rica wa s
partly to blame for its own plight.The lure
of wealth and power had got the better of
Africans. And, like everyone else, intellec-
tuals thought only of lining their pockets.”
As he says this, K o u r o u m a , who is a fri e n d l y
giant of a man, bursts into a hearty laugh.
“If I didn’t yield to temptation,” he says,
“maybe it’s only because I didn’t have the
opportunity!” n
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
L E T T E R S  T O  T H E  E D I T O R
50 The UNESCO Courier - March 1999
Language: English French Spanish
Rates (postage included):
Industrialized countries: Developing countries or students 
1 year: 211French francs (€32,15) instead of 264FF* (11 issues including 1 double issue) (Please send copy of your card):
2 years:396 French francs (€60,35) instead of 528FF* (22 issues including 2 double issues) 1 year: 132 French francs (€20,10)
Binder: 72French francs (€11) (for 11 issues including 1 double issue) 2 years: 211 French francs (€32,15)
I enclose payment: (in French francs only) by
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque) Visa Mastercard Eurocard
N° ⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧ Expiry date: Date and signature:
Name First name
Address
Postal code City
Optional:Age Profession
(*) Total cover price
I WISH TO SUBSCRIBE TO the UNESCO Courier
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to:
the UNESCO Courier Subscription Services, 31,rue François Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are opposite this order form.
"
2 A working tool
For me, as a teacher, the Courier is a very
useful working tool.The subjects you
cover, with all their human aspects,
interest my pupils and give me ideas for
many of my personal projects.
Congratulations on your “new format”,
with its short and clearly written 
articles which I find far more accessible
to young readers.
Ylen Orrego
Valence, France
2 The granny boom
My name is Sasithorn. I enjoy reading
the UNESCO Courier. After reading about
old people in your December 1998 issue,
I looked at my grandmother. I think I
will take care of her and love her as
much as myself.
Sasithorn,
a student from Thailand
2 The Courier on Internet
I am delighted to see that the Courier is
now on Internet. Congratulations!
Valery Lysenko
Chernobyl,Ukraine
2 Glowing pictures
The photos illustrating each article are
impressive and striking. Each issue of
UNESCO Courier is a feast for the mind,
the eyes and the imagination.
Prof. Capasso, Rector,
Otto Krauze Technical School No. 1,
Buenos Aires, Argentina
2 Sobriety and realism
We want to congratulate you on the new
presentation of the UNESCO Courier. Its
remarkable sobriety is a positive feature,
enabling readers to get an immediate
grasp of the topic being covered. I found
particularly memorable the poignant
beauty and tragic realism of the photos
of Russian miners that appeared in the
November 1998 issue.The article that
accompanied the photos depicted a
world of total wretchedness, whose
existence I had hitherto unsuspected.
Julie Corseaux,
Villejuif, France
2 The green light
You take a constructive approach to
social and environmental problems.
When will people learn the reflex that
whenever a tree is felled another should
be planted? When will there be a “decade
for trees”? When will taxes on industry
be paid directly to the ministry of the
environment? When will we learn?
Jaime and Dauphine Giraldo
Lain,France
2 The vanishing heritage 
We commend the conscientious courage
you show in publishing articles
highlighting offences against human
dignity and against the natural
environment on which we all depend.
But we miss two features which seem to
have disappeared: Greenwatch and
Heritage.
Michael and Elizabeth Rochester
St. John’s, Newfoundland, Canada
The environment and the heritage still
receive regular coverage, but in somewhat
different form.The environment is covered in
the “Planet” feature, and “Signs of the
Times”regularly presents heritage-related
topics. Editor
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
L I S T  O F S A L E S A N D S U B S C R I P T I O N A G E N T S
Subs cr ipt ions can be paid to the subsc ript ion agent in  y our cou ntr y who wil l  supply rat es i n local  currenc y on re q u e s t
A R G E N T I N A : Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UN E S C O,
Tucumán 1685, 1050 Buenos A i r e s. Fa x :3 7 1 - 8 1 9 4 .
AU S T R A L I A : Hunter Publicat i o n s , 58A Gipps Street,
C o l l i n g wood VIC 3066. Fa x : 419 7154. ISA A u s t r a l i a ,
PO Box 709,To owong QLD 4066. Fa x : 371 5566.
United Nations A s s o c. of A u s t r a l i a / V i c t o rian Div. ,
179 St George's Road,
N. F i t z r oy VIC 3068. Fa x : 481 7693.
AU S T R I A : Gerold & Co, I m p o rt & Export ,
Z e i t s c h ri f t e n / Pe ri o d i c a l s , Graben 31, A-1011 V i e n n a .
Fa x : 512 47 31 29
B E L G I U M : Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Bru s s e l s.
Fa x : 538 08 41.
B R A Z I L : Fundaco Getulio Va r g a s , Editora Divisão de Ve n d a s ,
Caixa Postal 62.591, 22257-970 Rio de Janeiro RJ.
Fa x :5 5 1 - 0 9 4 8 .
C A N A DA : Renouf Publishinq Company Ltd, C e n t r a l
D i s t ri bution Centre, 1294 Algoma Road, O t t awa , Ont K1B
3 W 8 . Fa x : 741 5439.
P é riodica Inc, 1155 Av Ducharm e ,O u t r e m o n t , PQ H2V 1E2.
Fa x : 274 0201.
C H I L E : U n i ve rs i t a ria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10220,
S a n t i a g o. Fa x : 681 9091.
C H I N A : China National Publicat i o n s ,I m p o rt & Export
C o rp. , PO Box 88, 16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 100020.
Fa x : 010 65063101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: A rt i a , Ve Smeckach 30,
111 27 Prague 1.
D E N M A R K : M u n k s g a a r d ,N o rre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148,
DK-1016 Kobenhavn K. Fa x : 12 93 87.
F I N L A N D : S t o c k m a n n / A k ateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23,
SF-00371 Helsinki. Fa x : +358 9 121 4450.
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF-01641 Va n t a a .
Fa x : 852 7990.
G E R M A N Y: G e rman Commission for UN E S C O, C o l m a n t s t r.
1 5 , D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 63 69 12.
Uno Ve r l a g, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55,
D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 21 74 92.
G R E E C E : L i b r a i rie Kauffmann SA, M a u v r o k o r d atou 9,
GR-106 78 A t h e n s. Fa x : 38 33 967.
G UAT E M A L A : Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con
la UN E S C O, 3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1,A p a rtado Postal 2630,
G u atemala City.
HONG KO N G : Hong Kong Gove rnment Inform ation Svcs.
D e p t . , 1 Bat t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
H U N G A RY: Librotrade K F T, Pe riodical Import / K ,P O B
1 2 6 , H-1656 Budapest. Fa x :2 5 6 - 8 7 - 2 7 .
I N D I A : O rient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions A c c o u n t ) ,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estat e ,B o m b ay 400 038.
Fa x : 26 91 278.
Oxford Book & Stat i o n e ry Co, Code No D 8208052, S c i n d i a
H o u s e , New Delhi 110 001. Fa x : 33 22 639.
I S R A E L : L i t e r a ry Transactions Inc. , C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., P O
B ox 1444, Bnei Brak 51114. Fa x : 52 81 187.
I TA LY: L i c o s a / L i b r e ria Comm. Sansoni SPA ,Via Duca di
C a l a b ria 1/1, I-50125 Florence. Fa x :6 4 - 1 2 - 5 7 .
J A PA N : E a s t e rn Book Service Inc. , Pe riodicals A c c o u n t , 3 13
Hongo 3 Chome, B u n k yo Ku ,To k yo 113. Fa x :8 1 8 - 0 8 6 4 .
KO R E A : Korean National Commission for UN E S C O, C P O
B ox 64, Seoul 100-600. Fa x : 568 7454.
L U X E M B U R G : M e s s a g e ries Paul Kraus, BP 2022, L - 1 0 2 0
L u xe m b o u r g . Fa x : 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA : Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic
S t r e e t ,Valletta CMR 01. Fa x : 24 61 82.
M AU R I T I U S : Nalanda Co. L t d . , 30 Bourbon Street, Po rt
L o u i s. Fa x : 212 1313.
M O RO C C O : UN E S C O, 35 avenue du 16 novembre Agdal-
Rabat. Fax:212-767 03 75,Tél.:212-767 03 74/72.
M E X I C O : Librería El Correo de la UN E S C O S A , Col Roma,
G u a n a j u ato 72, Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF.
Fa x :2 6 4 - 0 9 - 1 9 .
N E T H E R L A N D S : S wets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2 1 6 0
SZ Lisse. Fa x :2 5 2 4 - 1 5 8 8 8 .
T i j d s c h riftcentrale Wijck B V, I n t .S u b s. S e rv i c e ,W
G r a c h t s t r a at 1C, 6221 CT Maastri c h t . Fa x : 32 50 103.
NEW ZEALAND: GP Legi s l ation Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 12418,T h o rn d o n , We l l i n g t o n . Fa x : 496 56 98.
NORVEGE : S wets Norge A S ,Ø s t e n s j ø vein 18-0606 Oslo, PO
Box 6512,Etterstad. Fax:47 22 97 45 45.
P O RT U G A L : L i v r a ria Po rtugal (Dias & Andrade Lda),
Rua do Carmo 70 74, 1200 Lisboa. Fa x : 34 70 264.
R U S S I A : Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39,
M o s c ow 113095.
SOUTH A F R I C A : I n t e rn ational Subscription Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 41095, Craighall 2024. Fa x : 880 6248.
Mast Publicat i o n s , PO Box 901, Parklands 2121.
Fa x : 886 4512.
S PA I N : Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37,
28001 Madri d . Fa x :5 7 5 - 3 9 - 9 8 .
L i b r e ria Al A n d a l ú s , Roldana 3 y 4, 41004 Sevilla.
Fa x :4 2 2 - 5 3 - 3 8 .
Los Amigos de la UN E S C O, Alda Urquijo 62, 2 Izd.,
48011 Bilbao. Fa x :4 2 7 - 5 1 - 5 9 / 6 9
SRI LANKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam,
Gardiner Mawat h a , Colombo 2. Fa x : 44 78 48.
S W E D E N : We n n e r gren Williams A B , PO Box 1305,
S-171 25 Solna. Fa x : 27 00 71.
S W I T Z E R L A N D : Dynapresse Marketing SA, ( e x - N av i l l e
S A ) , 38 av V i b e rt , CH-1227 Carouge. Fa x : 308 08 59.
E d i group SA, Case Postale 393, CH-1225 Chêne-Bourg.
Fa x : 348 44 82.
Europa Ve r l a g, Ramistrasse 5, CH-8024 Züri c h .
Fa x : 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG ,W i s s e n s c h a f t l .B u c h h a n d l u n g,
Pe t e rs graben 31, CH-4009 Basel. Fa x : 306 12 34.
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E C O, Chemin du
L a c u e z , CH-1807 Blonay. Fa x : 943 36 05.
T H A I L A N D : Suksapan Pa n i t , Mansion 9, R a j a d a m n e rn
Ave n u e , Bangkok 2. Fa x : 28 11 639.
T U N I S I A : Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de
l ’UN E S C O, 2 2 , rue de l’Angleterr e , 1000RP Tu n i s.
Fa x : 33 10 14
UNITED KINGDOM: The Stat i o n e ry Office Publicat i o n s
C t r e . , 51 Nine Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR.
Fa x : 873 84 63.
UNITED STAT E S : B e rnan A s s o c i at e s , 4611-F A s s e m b l y
D ri ve , Lanham MD 20706-4391. Fa x :4 5 9 - 0 0 5 6 .
U R U G UAY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
Maldonado 1090, M o n t e v i d e o. Fa x : 90 59 83.
V E N E Z U E L A : UN E S C O/ C R E S A L C ,E d i f. A s ov i n c a r ,
Av Los Chorr o s ,C ruce C/C A c u e d u c t o, Altos de Sebu c a n ,
C a r a c a s. Fa x : 286 03 26.
UNESCO Publishing pro p o s e s
UNESCO PUBLISHING
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publications
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
Poverty: 
A Global Review
Handbook on International
Poverty Research
Report on poverty and poverty
research. Ideas and reflections.
A major contribution to setting up
the agenda for poverty research.
620 pp., 300 FF
UNESCO Publishing / Scandinavian
University Press
Poverty and 
Participation in 
Civil Society
Yogesh Atal and Else Øyen
Poverty is on the rise in many parts
of the world and calls for a drastic
rethinking of development policies.
The increase of the participation of
the poor in society involves a
fundamental change in the attitudes
and perceptions of the ‘non-poor’.
152 pp., 50 FF
UNESCO Publishing / Abhinav Publications
The Protection of Cultural
Property in the Event 
of Armed Conflict
Commentary on the Hague
Convention of 14 May 1954
An in-depth commentary on this
cornerstone convention and guidelines 
on legal and practical means to ensure
adequate protection.
450 pp., 220 FF
UNESCO Publishing / Dartmouth Publishing
Trade in Antiquities:
Reducing Destruction 
and Theft
Patrick O’Keefe
Instruments for reducing theft and
suggestions on ways to change 
the antiquities market.
119 pp., 128 FF
UNESCO Publishing / Archetype Books
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Do s s i e r:
A passion for sport
n Turning the tables
For women, the disabled, ethnic minorities 
and the poor—can sport offer an escape route 
from discrimination?
n Constructing an identity
Sport as an outlet and a crucible for national,
religious and intercommunity conflicts;
Supporters: What fires the fans?
Features include:
n Ayacucho (Peru): the path to recovery
n Indigenous peoples defend their ancestral lands
n Learning through play
n The arms race: ready for the next round?
n The Library of Alexandria reborn
n Community radio: neighbours taking the mike
n Interview with Palestinian envoy Leïla Shahid
]]>
</page>
</document>
