<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="115591eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Indigenous people
t a ke on
big business
No fare w e l l
to arms
Leila Shahid:
the re s o l v e
of a Pa l e s t i n i a n
e n v o y
The s p e l l of s p o r t
theC o u rie r
April 1999
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
52nd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat
Photoengraving:Eric Frogé
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian:Gianluca Formichi,Sira Miori (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e : Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UN E S C O or those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. P h o t o
captions and headlines are written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r
s t a f f. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O o r
the United Nations. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7
Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfil m s
( X e r o x ) , Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C . R .
Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d , Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - APRIL 1999
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Pa r i s
by UN E S C O. Printed in Fr a n c e. Periodicals postage paid at
Champlain NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N°4-1999-OPI 99-581 A
C o n t e n t s
April 1999
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 Ay a c u c h o : an uneasy calm Francisco Díez-Canseco T á va r a ,
Photos by Alejandro Balaguer
EDITORIAL
9 Peace without victory Federico Mayor
PLANET
10 Indigenous people
take on big business Sophie Boukhari
11 The oil flows and the forest bleeds Carlos Viteri Gualinga
12 The Kakadu controversy Dennis Schulz
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Pretending for real Asbel López
DOSSIER
17 The spell of sport
18 1. What’s in a game?
by René Lefort and Jean Harvey
20 Iranian women put on their running shoes Siavosh Ghazi
22 Training for life Ole Kristian Bjellaanes
23 Going for glory Glenn Manarin with Myung-soo Kim Taejon
24 A star that never rose K. K. Man Jusu
25 Basketball at midnight Gary A. Sailes
26 Hidden hurdles of colour Amy Otchet
28 2. The agony and the ecstasy Philippe Liotard
30 Batting for the nation Ramachandra Guha
32 A Cuban mix of muscle and ideology Marcos Bustillo
33 New players, same game Lincoln Allison
34 All together! Sergio Leite Lopes
35 Till death do us part Eduardo Arias
36 May the betting man win. . . . Robert Horn and Thaskina Khaikaew
ETHICS
3 7 No farewell to arms Vincenç Fisas
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 Alexandria: from papyrus to the Internet Michel Arseneault
CONNEXIONS
43 Latin America’s endangered frequencies Rafael Roncagliolo
TALKING TO…
46 Leila Shahid:The resolve of a Palestinian envoy
C o v e r : Mexican soccer fans in full cry during the 1998 World Cup.
© S. R u e t / Te m p s p o r t s / S y g m a , Pa r i s
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Ay a c u c h o:
an uneasy calm
n
Aya c u c h o, capital of the Pe ru v i a n
d e p a rtment of the same name, s t i l l
lives on edge nearly 20 years after the
Sendero Luminoso (Shining Path) guer-
rillas first went into action there. Relief ove r
the guerri l l a s ’d e f e at is matched by the ten-
sion of an “ a rmed peace” maintained by the
continued presence of underground ele-
ments of this terr o rist organization in nearby
districts and provinces.
Also known as Huamanga, the name
gi ven to the city by the Spaniards when they
founded it on 29 Ja n u a ry 1539, Aya c u c h o
sits 2,752 metres up in a lush valley in the
we s t e rn cordillera of the A n d e s. Its 100,000
inhabitants share a double heri t a g e ,s p e a k i n g
the Quechua language and living in accor-
dance with Indian traditions, i rr e s p e c t i ve
of social class.The local elite has managed
to preserve this tradition of cultural duality,
avoiding the social discri m i n ation which
has marred it elsewhere in Pe ru .
Ayacucho is the cradle of the Wa ri
culture which produced a remarkable pre-
Festive traditions are reviving in the Peruvian highlands where the Shining Pa t h
guerrillas once held sway. But 20 years of civil war have left lasting wounds
Francisco Díez-Canseco Távara*
Photos by
Alejandro Balaguer
*President of the Peruvian Peace Council
Marketing in Quinua,near Ayacucho.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Inca empire and displays its mixed heri-
tage with a rich musical tradition blending
the sounds of Andean h u ay n o dance music
with a distinct romantic element of Spanish
origin.At no time is the city more vibrant
than during Holy We e k , when Chri s t i a n
and Indian religious devotion reaches its
apogee in Aya c u c h o ’s 37 churches, ( o f fic i a l l y
there are 33, to match the age of Christ at
his death).
The festival was cancelled for seve r a l
years for fear of bombs and ambushes and
because the curfew ruled out after-dark
processions, but it bounced back in 1993,
after the capture of the Shining Pat h ’s
leader, Carlos Abimaël Guzmán, on Sep-
tember 12, 1992.
Major historical landmarks are dotted
around the city, and include the Pampa de
Q u i n u a , site of the Battle of Ayacucho which
clinched Latin A m e ri c a ’s independence
from Spain.The battlefield is now shaking
off its military associations to stress cul-
tural activities, including the Encuentro de
Teatro, which hosts theatre groups from all
over the world.
Above, arid hilltops around Ayacucho,
almost 3,000 metres above sea level.
Children at school
in the village of Huanta.
Opposite page,
high-altitude health care.
Women gather to have 
their children weighed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
But the restored festive spirit and the
r e t u rn to an almost normal daily life cannot
hide the wounds left by years of terror and
v i o l e n c e . New social problems have cropped
up as some of the city’s youth have joined
the dozen of gangs which at t a c k , rob 
and kill.They’re mostly made up of young
men who have had close brushes with the
g u e rri l l a s , to whom in many cases they have
lost a family member.
There is also the problem of the desti-
tute refugees from guerrilla violence who
h ave invaded the city, where they now prefer
to stay rather than risk returning to the
u n c e rtainty of their rural homes. T h e
d e p a rtment of Ayacucho was by far the
Above, the festival of crosses 
at Luricocha.A hundred crosses, some
over 5 metres high,are blessed in the
village church.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
wo rst hit by the Shining Pat h ’s terr o r. M o r e
than 10,000 of its inhabitants were killed,
3,000 more disappeared and 170,000 we r e
forced from their homes—in all, a third of
the total population.
The cradle of many cultures and a city of
c o n t r a s t s , with colonial churches, n a rr ow
old streets, sunlit morn i n g s , cloudy after-
noons and nights of reve l ry and h u ay n o d a n-
c i n g,Ayacucho is gradually recove ri n g .B u t
it needs time to rebuild a social fa b ric rooted
in solidari t y, a traditional feature of A n d e a n
c o m m u n i t i e s.
Although the ye a rs of curfew—when
nobody ventured out after eight at night
and shops and restaurants tightly bolted
Lima
Ecuador Colombia
Pacific
Ocean 
Brazil
P E R U
Ayacucho
Above, on All Souls Day 
dancers in Ayacucho pay tribute 
to the dead.
Ayacucho’s theatre festival, held 
in the last week of May,
hosts 400 performers from 
all over the world.The event 
was created in 1978.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
The cost of 
the “dirty war”
Carlos Abimaël Guzman was a philosophy
professor at the University of A y a c u c h o
when he founded the Shining Path breakaway
faction of the Peruvian communist party and
launched his “enduring people’s wa r ” . He began
it in May 1980 with a symbolic act—a com-
mando burned ballot boxes in Chuschi, a remote
village in the area, two days before elections
were to be held.
The country had just emerged from 12 years
of army rule, poverty was spiralling out of control
and anarchy reigned.At first the well-organized
guerrillas were welcomed by the population,
especially as they handed out plots of land. B u t
things started going wrong when the rebels
began executing “ t r a i t o r ” peasants and lea-
ders of community groups and installed a ruth-
less and bloody tyranny based on fuzzy futurist
reasoning.
The guerrillas and their “ e n e m i e s ” , the Tu p a c
Amaru Revolutionary Movement, a rebel group
founded in 1983 and destroyed by its 1996 sei-
zure of hostages at the Japanese embassy in
Lima,were both defeated in the “dirty war”.
But the toll was enormous—more than
26,000 dead,4,000 missing and 50,000 children
orphaned. The government has put its cost at
more than $25 billion—the equivalent of Pe r u ’s
foreign debt, on which interest charges alone
absorb a third of the foreign exchange earned
by exports of fish,copper, zinc and silver.
President Alberto Fujimori, elected in 1990
and re-elected five years later, began an exten-
sive structural adjustment and priva t i z a t i o n
programme. He also curbed civil liberties after
what the rest of the world calls his 1992 “civi-
lian coup d’etat”, when he dissolved parlia-
m e n t , suspended constitutional rights and
sacked more than 500 magistrates.
Hyperinflation was beaten—falling from
2,700 per cent in 1989 to just 7 per cent last
year—and economic growth set a Latin Ame-
rican record in 1994 with a figure of 13 per
cent.Growth slowed last year to two per cent,
mainly because of torrential rains set off by the
El Niño weather phenomenon and the effects of
the Asian economic crisis. According to the
World Bank, 54 per cent of Peru’s 25 million
people live below the poverty line and under-
employment affects half the active population.
n
their doors—are a thing of the past, there is
still a state of emergency in Huamanga pro-
vince and in four of the 11 other prov i n c e s
which make up the depart m e n t .This means
some constitutional rights are suspended
and the army has free rein to search public
buildings and private houses.
Strolling through the quiet streets of Aya-
cucho under a cloudless sky, you would think
nothing could prevent the return of peace.B u t
until the inhabitants can once again exe r c i s e
their basic rights and steps are taken to reduce
p ove rty and margi n a l i z at i o n , there will be no
t rue and lasting peace. n
A Holy Week procession in Ayacucho.
Latin America’s oldest church stands
in the city.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E D I TO R I A L
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 9
n
UNESCO’s approach to sport is summed up in its 1978 International Charter of Phy-
sical Education and Sport .These activities, the Charter say s ,“should seek to promote
closer communion between peoples and between individuals,together with disinte-
rested emulat i o n ,s o l i d a rity and frat e rn i t y, mutual respect and unders t a n d i n g, and full res-
pect for the integrity and dignity of human beings.”
The promotion of ethical values—especially to combat margi n a l i z ation and vio-
lence—is central to this approach. It stresses the necessity for sport to be open to eve ryo n e ,
starting with young people who are all too often sidelined because they are physically or
mentally disabled, because they live in problem areas or just because they are female.
UN E S C O’s focus is on promoting sport for all. It believes that in a society in which people
need to be equipped for lifelong learning, sport can make a vital contribution to educa-
t i o n . For education invo l ves much more than spoon-feeding inform at i o n . Its ultimate pur-
pose is to stimulate people’s capacity to think,create and interact with others and to use
this capacity in order to be self-reliant, while also helping others to improve their we l l - b e i n g
and quality of life.Sport is an incomparable way of achieving these aims.
We live in a world where the gap between rich and poor keeps on gr ow i n g . On the sport s
fie l d , or failing that , in streets, c o u rt ya r d s , or fie l d s , such differences disappear like magi c.
People compete against each other, but they also get together in teams, using weapons that
are for once entirely peaceful: s p e e d ,s t r e n g t h ,s k i l l , endurance and intelligence—qualities
that have nothing to do with social status.
We live in a violent world.In cities, where two-thirds of humanity will soon be living,
e ven young children go out onto the sports field bu rsting with the aggression they have accu-
m u l ated in their daily live s. And here too, a kind of miracle takes place and the aggr e s s i o n
is transformed.Its negative and destructive charge is transmuted into a positive desire to
beat one’s opponent—not to achieve victory at all costs and by any means, but fairly, in
a contest governed by rules that both sides observe.In these conditions sport becomes a
school where people can give vent to their aggressive instincts and at the same time learn
tolerance and respect for others.Those who practice sport become aware of forces which,
if they are not curbed,might blindly take over their lives.
We live in a world of wo rsening nat i o n a l , ethnic and religious antagonisms.The capa-
city of sport to unite people—almost to weld them together—is obvious these day s. It cul-
m i n ates in the Olympic Games and the soccer World Cup, which have gi ven the world so
m a ny ennobling images of comradeship. Our pleasure is all the gr e ater because it is
shared on an unprecedented scale. No other modern social event makes people feel so
strongly that they belong to a global village.
But unfort u n ately there is more to sport than this.S p o rt is not monolithic: it takes many
f o rm s , and is ri ven by differences and disagr e e m e n t s.When sport hits the headlines it does
not always glorify the heroes who have won our admiration by their performances on the
field.Behind the scenes, but increasingly in the spotlight,is a world of wheeling and dea-
l i n g, d ru g - t a k i n g, and athletes who are subject to premature specialization and intolerable
s t r e s s. B a r b a ric chauvinism takes over when public opinion and the enthusiasm of support e rs
are fired up to fever pitch.
In poor countries, four out five young people still have no access to adequate sports
facilities and training.The stakes are so high in big sporting events that only the results count:
the purpose of sport goes by the board.The designation of winners and losers is more impor-
tant than bri n ging together athletes to compete under a set of ru l e s.This is a far cry from
the “ h a p p i n e s s ” e voked by the French poet Paul Verlaine—the happiness of “ p e a c e
without victory”. n
Federico Mayor
We live in a world where
the gap between rich and
poor keeps on growing. On
the sports field, or failing
that, in streets, courtyards,
or fields, such differences
disappear like magic.
Peace w i t h o u t
v i c t o r y
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
P L A N E T
n
“ I t ’s hard to explain what ’s happened to
u s. All we have left is our name:
A m u n g m e .The mountains, the ri ve rs ,
the forests—everything—belongs to Free-
p o rt and the gove rnment now. We have
nothing left.”
These words of an old man in Irian Jaya
( I n d o n e s i a n - ruled West Pa p u a ) ,r e p o rted by
members of Survival International,a non-
g ove rnmental organizat i o n , sum up the loss
and injustice felt by millions of indigenous
peoples around the wo r l d . For more than 30
ye a rs , according to many NGOs, the United
N at i o n s , European Members of Pa r l i a m e n t
and U. S .S e n at o rs , these “ o ri gi n a l ”i n h a b i-
tants of our planet have watched their land
being polluted,their holy places destroyed
and their families wasting away or dying in
the name of a “development” they are the
last to benefit from.
In Indonesia, the U.S. firm Freeport-
McMoRan, in association with the British
company Rio Tinto and local authorities
including ex-President Suhart o, a c c o r d i n g
to Survival, has rights to an area as big as
B e l gium in the wo r l d ’s largest gold reserve ,
which is also ve ry rich in copper. Mining has
polluted the ri ve rs , d e s t r oyed one of the
wo r l d ’s best-preserved virgin forests and
d e s e c r ated religious sites. M a ny NGOs have
denounced the army for using violence
against people protesting this damage.
In Colombia,5,000 Uwa A m e rindians are
resisting the use of their sacred lands by Occi-
dental Pe t r o l e u m . After threatening mass
s u i c i d e , they have attracted so many suppor-
t e rs that Shell has said it will pull out of its
p a rt n e rship with Occidental in the area.
With Shell, it’s a case of once bitten,
twice shy. In Nigeri a , the company is fa c i n g
stiff opposition from the Ogoni and Ijaw
people, who are demanding that it should
l e ave unless they obtain rights to the rich oil
deposits on their lands. In conjunction with
the gove rn m e n t , Shell began drilling in
Ogoniland in 1958 and has since extracted
an estimated $30 billion worth of oil.
In 1995, aWorld Council of Churches
fa c t - finding mission reported that the local
people had no electri c i t y, telephones or
basic health facilities and that the environ-
ment was seriously damaged.The Ogonis
s ay Shell had close links to the army, w h i c h
crushed any protests. The crisis came to a
head in November 1995, when nine Ogoni
l e a d e rs , including the writer Ken Saro-
Wiwa, were executed by hanging.
Activism
has paid dividends
M a ny cases could be cited in which the
activities of transnational companies wo r-
king hand in glove with local authori t i e s
b ring destru c t i o n , c o rru p t i o n , division and
d e ath to the lands of indigenous peoples.
This unacceptable situation has bolstered
the determ i n ation of the wo r l d ’s indigenous
Indigenous 
on big 
Transnational companies which mine and harvest raw materials on the rich
lands of indigenous peoples no longer ‘have it all their own way’
Sombre legacy:oil-polluted marshes in
Ogoniland, Nigeria.
Sophie Boukhari*
*UNESCO Courier journalist
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
p e o p l e , who number around 300 million
wo r l d w i d e .D u ring the 1980s, they began to
organize themselves and in 1982 a special
UN working group helped strengthen their
n e t works and brought them to intern at i o n a l
at t e n t i o n .
Their position was summed up in the
1992 Declaration of Kari-Oca, in Brazil,
whose preamble states that “We, the Indi-
genous Pe o p l e s , maintain our inherent
rights to self-determ i n ation and to our lands
and terri t o ri e s.”Their aim is to win decision-
making power over company projects, the
right to oppose them and, if they approve
them, the right to share the profits. Their
well-publicized battle has been highlighted
by many human rights and pro-env i r o n-
ment organizat i o n s , including A m n e s t y
I n t e rn at i o n a l , Human Rights Wat c h ,M i n e-
Watch,Survival International and Friends
of the Earth.
A foreign company can no longer start
operations on indigenous lands without a
mass of websites reporting on its eve ry
m ove m e n t . The public in rich countri e s
takes other action as well,often occupying
a company’s headquarters and boycotting
its products.
Such widespread activism has brought
results. Indigenous people have long been
considered by their states as obstacles to
d e ve l o p m e n t , as groups which have to be at
best assimilated and at worst eliminated.
They are now recognized in several coun-
t ri e s , including Denmark, the United Stat e s ,
Canada and Australia, as full citizens with
rights to their lands. In the Philippines,
they are negotiating to monitor mining pro-
jects. In Latin America, several countries
have amended their national constitutions
to give them some protection.
In the hope of further progr e s s , t h e y
are waiting with great anticipation for the
UN declaration on their rights which is
due to be adopted before the end of the
United Nations Decade for Indigenous
Peoples (1995-2004).
They can boast of some small victories
over the transnationals. They have forced
s e veral big firm s , such as Mobil Oil in Pe ru ,
to drop projects. They have managed to
get others to negotiate and to help restore
the environment.They have also called for
compensation for past injustices. But only
rarely do they win a real share of profit s ,a s
some Inuits or North A m e rican Indians
have managed to do.
Windfalls that revive
ethnic tensions
“The transnationals can’t have it all
their own way any more,” s ays Julian Burger,
of the UN High Commission for Human
Rights.The companies are losing an enor-
mous amount of money because of sabotage
and local resistance (Shell was forced to
suspend operations in the Niger Delta in
1993) and perhaps even more by discredi-
ting themselves in the eyes of consumers in
rich countries.
On its we b s i t e ,S h e l l - N i g e ria admits its
“responsibility” to indigenous peoples. It
s ays it spent $32 million in Nigeria in 1997,
mainly to build schools and hospitals,and
pledges that “until the end of the century,
at least a fifth of its budget”will go to res-
toring the environment. In the same year,
F r e e p o rt invested one per cent of its profit s
in Indonesia in development projects in
Irian Jaya.
After adding environmental preservat i o n
to their codes of conduct and investing in
“cleaner” infrastructures, more and more
t r a n s n ational firms are saying they will push
human rights issues. But on the spot, t h i n g s
are ve ry tough, they point out.They are up
against local tribal and military leaders
more interested in making money for them-
selves than helping the local community.
F r e e p o rt says the first big payments it
doled out in Indonesia to set up a deve l o p-
ment fund were stolen by a local gove rn-
ment offic i a l .The sharing out of this wind-
fall has revived old ethnic tensions and wa s
a factor in setting off tribal wa r fa r e . A n d
sometimes the anger of local people whose
l i ves have been ravaged over several decades
is too strong to be placated by a foreign
c o m p a ny ’s change of policy.
When attacked by human rights cam-
p a i g n e rs who accuse them of not opposing
repression, and even taking part in it, the
t r a n s n ationals take refuge behind the pri n-
ciple of national sove r e i g n t y, s aying only
governments have the right to make deci -
sions about their people. It is also ve ry hard
for them to refuse deals on grounds of pri n-
ciple or give up a large part of their profits
in a competitive world where shareholders
want maximum profits.
Ineffectual monitoring systems
As a result, m a ny people wants to see a
body of laws and intern ational rules to regu-
l ate the operations of transnational firm s.B u t
attempts to do this have so far failed or had
little effect.The UN centre set up in 1974 to
draft a list of rights and responsibilities of
transnationals was disbanded in 1993 and
guidelines on the subject worked out by
the Organization for Economic Co-opera-
tion and Development (OECD) and the
International Labour Organisation (ILO)
are not mandatory.
The most recent attempt in this direc-
tion was a European parliament resolution
in January this year calling for monitoring
of the operations of European transnatio-
n a l s , notably by holding we l l - a d ve rt i s e d
public hearings starting this June, w h e r e
N G O s , trade unions and firms will be able
to voice their grievances.
“ M a ny existing codes of conduct aren’t
wo rth the paper they’re written on because
they aren’t implemented,” says Euro-MP
Richard How i t t , who drafted the resolu-
tion.“We want European companies to be
monitored to see how far they comply with
i n t e rn ational law in the field of env i r o n-
ment, human rights and labour rights, in
particular as far as indigenous peoples are
concerned. Many indigenous groups face
extinction and tragically European com-
panies have been part of the threat to these
communities.” n
peoples take
business
‘Many existing codes of
conduct aren’t worth the
paper they’re written on
because they aren’t
implemented’
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
P L A N E T
n
One and a half billion dollars—that’s
h ow much compensation 75 Cofa n ,
Secoya and Quechua Indians living in
E c u a d o r ’s Amazon region want from
Texaco. They accuse the U.S. oil giant of
perpetrating “ecocide” during 26 years of
o p e r ations in Ecuador and maintain that the
damage is continuing because the firm is
using old equipment.
The Indians have not sued in the court s
of their own country but before a court in
New Yo r k . B e t ween 1964 and 1990, a
consortium of a Texaco subsidiary and the
E c u a d o rian state oil company Pe t r o e c u a d o r
drilled 339 wells,including 232 which are
still producing in the eastern part of the
c o u n t ry and have been operated exclusive l y
by Petroecuador since 1992.
The Indians quote studies done by env i-
ronmental organizations such as the U.S.
National Resources Defense Council and
the Center for Economic and Social Rights,
both based in New Yo r k , and on research by
scientists from the Harvard School of Public
H e a l t h . The Indians say Texaco has pol-
luted about a million hectares of land and
that some 30,000 people have contracted
skin and intestinal diseases, had my s t e ri o u s
miscarriages and in some cases developed
cancer.
* Ecuadorian anthropologist
Texaco is also accused of having released
more than 75 million cubic metres of tox i c
liquid waste into ri ve rs and mars h l a n d s ,
accidentally spilled more than 60,000 cubic
metres of oil and left uncovered more than
600 dumps containing toxic mat e ri a l . I n
addition,it is said to have caused conside-
rable deforestation along with soil erosion
and reduced biodiversity.
Texaco has admitted that “oil spills some-
times do occur”, but it cites inve s t i g at i o n s
by two firm s ,A gra Earth and Env i r o n m e n t a l
and Fugro McClelland, which say the Te x a c o
s u b s i d i a ry “acted responsibly” without cau-
sing “a lasting or significant impact” on the
e nv i r o n m e n t .Texaco adds that between 1995
and last ye a r , under an agreement with the
E c u a d o rian authori t i e s , it carried out a $40
million “ r e m e d i a l ”p r o gr a m m e .
The subsidiary, it say s , “ c o n s i s t e n t l y
complied with the laws of Ecuador and
international petroleum industry environ-
mental standards” and that all its operat i o n s
“took place under the control and superv i-
sion of Ecuador’s gove rn m e n t ” . It adds
that the matter should go before an Ecua-
dorian court because “U.S. courts should
not gove rn the activities of a sove r e i g n
foreign nat i o n , just as foreign courts should
not govern the activities of the U.S.”
These are the issues U. S .D i s t rict Judge
Jed Rakoff is due to decide in A p ril 1999 at
the end of a tortuous legal battle which has
lasted more than five ye a rs. If he decides the
case can be heard in the United Stat e s , it will
set a ve ry important precedent, o p e n i n g
the way for other non-U.S. citizens to sue
U.S. firms in the United States itself.
The four gove rnments Ecuador has had
over the past six ye a rs have opposed such
m ove s. For reasons of national sove r e i g n t y,
they have said, the matter should be dealt
with in Ecuador. But if that happened, u n l i k e
in the U. S . where “class actions” (joint suits)
are allowe d ,e ve ry one of the 30,000 people
affected would have to sue individually. O n
top of that , s ays their law ye r , C ri s t o b a l
B o n i fa z , the plaintiffs do not believe they
will get justice in Ecuador because Ecua-
d o rian judges lack experience of such cases
and most of all because oil interests are too
p owerful there.
T h i rteen million hectares—almost half
the country — h ave been leased for explora-
t i o n , mainly to intern ational oil companies.
Oil provides half of all Ecuador’s export s
and 40 per cent of its national income. It is
considered the key to the country ’s progr e s s ,
enabling some to argue that ecologi c a l
damage is a price that has to be paid.
But this is nonsense. E c u a d o r ’s foreign
debt has risen from $217 million before
the oil boom to nearly $15 billion today, a n d
70 per cent of Ecuadorians live below the
p ove rty line. And oddly enough, the oil-
fields are in the poorest parts of the country,
where working conditions are tough and
the pay bad.
The oil flo w s, and the forest b l e e d s
Carlos Viteri Gualinga*
A group of Ecuadorian Indians are suing the oil company Texaco 
for ‘ecocide’ in the U.S. courts
‘U.S. courts should not govern the activities 
of a sovereign foreign nation, just as foreign courts should
not govern the activities of the U.S.’
In Quito, Indian women demonstrate outside
the headquarters of the Tripetrol company.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
A protest breakfast at the Jabiluka site.
Eccentric Pluto
is still a planet
It’s official:Pluto is a planet,and a major one
at that, says the International Astronomical
Union (IAU ) . H o w e v e r, Johannes A n d e r s e n ,
Secretary-General of the IAU, says he’s willing to
bet that had Pluto been discovered today instead
of in 1930,it might not have been classified as
the ninth planet in the solar system.
As planets go, Pluto is rather unusual. To
begin with, it is made of ice while the other eight
“major planets” are either rocky or gaseous. S i z e
is another strike against Pluto, which is even
smaller than our moon. Finally, Pluto’s orbit is
e c c e n t r i c , making it the only planet to cross the
path of another (that of Neptune).
Many scientists consider Pluto the leader of
a new pack of bodies called trans-Neptunian
objects (TNOs). But astronomers are still trying
to decide how to classify the 100 TNOs disco-
vered since 1992. Should they form a separate
category or slip it in with the 10,000 “minor pla-
n e t s,” i . e. a s t e r o i d s ?
To resolve the issue of Pluto’s classification,
the IAU asked astronomers around the world to
cast their votes via email. News of the balloting
caused a such a public outcry in favour of main-
taining the status quo that the ballot was quickly
cancelled.
Critics in the scientific community insisted
that the proposed changes would do nothing
more than confuse the general public. The emo-
tional response came “largely because kno-
wing all planets is something you learn in ele-
mentary school,” says Mike A’ H e a r n , a n
astronomer at the University of Maryland. Pe o p l e
tend “to think of this as the way the universe is,”
he adds.
It may take years before we get a really close-
up view of Pluto.The U.S. National Aeronautics
and Space Administration (NASA) plans to
launch the Pluto-Kuiper Express, an unmanned
space probe in 2004. It will take another six
years for the spacecraft to reach the planet.
M e a n w h i l e, says A n d e r s e n , astronomers will
keep a careful eye on TNOs and their unofficial
leader:Planet Pluto. n
n
Indigenous peoples and env i r o n m e n t a l
groups have often been at loggerheads.
But in A u s t r a l i a , one group of A b o ri-
gines has teamed up with env i r o n m e n t a l i s t s
in a dispute over a uranium mine.
In 1996 the Australian gove rnment gave
p e rmission for the mining company Energy
Resources of Australia (ERA) to begi n
work at the Jabiluka mining site, with ura-
nium reserves estimated to be worth more
than $8 billion.
The decision touched off a national and
i n t e rn ational controve rsy over Ja b i l u k a ,
which lies in the middle of the Kakadu
N ational Pa r k , listed as a World Heri t a g e
Site by UNESCO.
In  a report last December, UN E S C O c a l-
led on the Australian government to put a
stop to the mining project, saying Jabiluka
t h r e atened the environment of Kakadu and
the cultural heritage of the A b o ri gi n e s. A
UN E S C O committee will decide this July
whether to put Kakadu—habitat for hun-
The Kakadu
controversy Dennis Schulz*
The oil companies are notorious for per-
suading local authorities to turn a blind eye to
e nvironmental damage and even for buying up
polluted fa rmland so as to avoid demands for
c o m p e n s ation or rehabilitat i o n . The Nort h
A m e rican firm A R C O, which says it nego-
t i ates with the Indians, e ven got official per-
mission to build security fences around its ins-
t a l l at i o n s , along with pri vate paramilitary
g u a r d s , at a cost of nearly $2 million a month.
To end these three decades of harmful
dreds of species of wildlife and Australia’s
oldest sites of human occupation dating as
far back as 60,000 years ago—on its list of
World Heritage Sites in Danger.
The Australian gove rnment says the
UN E S C O r e p o rt contains err o rs of fa c t ,l aw,
science and logi c. ERA says the report ’s
recommendations do not make “environ-
mental,social or legal sense.”
Lobbying and demonstrations by a coa-
lition of 3,500 environmentalists and the
M i rrar A b o ri gi n e s , the traditional ow n e rs of
the site, was  a contri buting factor in
prompting UN E S C O to inve s t i g ate the
impact of mining on them and their envi-
ronment.
Kakadu Aborigines remain split on the
mining issue. There are only 28 Mirr a r
among the 500 A b o ri gines at Kakadu.
Many Aborigines hope for Jabiluka’s com-
mencement on economic grounds.
At present the Jabiluka project is conti-
nuing. n
p r a c t i c e s , the laws concerning oil opera-
tions should be thoroughly ove r h a u l e d ,a n d
this is bound to involve co-operation bet-
ween the state and civil society. Signs that
things might be changing include talks bet-
ween the gove rnment and indigenous
peoples about oil and about setting up two
protected areas in the Amazon region.
M e a n w h i l e , graffiti on the walls of
several towns proclaim that “the oil flows
and the forest bleeds.” n
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
Pretending for  
Simulation games are gaining popularity as educational tools in fields ra n g i n g
f rom humanitarian action to business management and accident pre v e n t i o n
n
The policeman checks Sonia’s passport
and then directs her to the prison door
with the barrel of his gun. She doesn’t
m ove . “Get in there quick,” he shouts, p o i n-
ting the weapon at her fa c e . S u rp ri s e d , s h e
e n t e rs the cell where other detainees are
crammed together in the semi-darkness.O u t-
s i d e , s h o u t s , s i r e n s , and explosions can be
h e a r d . After a while, the policeman comes
b a c k : “ You want your passport? Then get
d own on your knees and pick it up.” S h e
h e s i t ates a few seconds before obeying.“If yo u
come back here, you know what ’s wa i t i n g
for you? A bu l l e t .”
Sonia is starting to understand why a
foreigner might want to seek asylum. She is
not a refugee herself, but an 18-year-old
French student who has come to the Parc
de la Villette in Paris to visit an exhibition
entitled “A different kind of journey—the
p aths of exile”. She is taking part in a simu-
lation exercise for which she has assumed
the identity of Sybel, a 21-year-old Tu r k i s h
girl whose photo appears at the entrance to
the exhibition, along with photos of 11
other refugees of different nat i o n a l i t i e s ,
among them Luis, L e i l a ,Ve s n a ,K a n a , Pave l ,
and Tarik.The stories of how they came to
be exiles are acted out in detail by 27 pro-
fessional actors who play the roles of
officials, customs and police officers in a
room as big as a gymnasium where airport
customs offices and police headquart e rs
have been reconstituted.There are even a
minefield and a clandestine workshop.
In the three months after it opened in
N ovember 1998, the exhibition at La V i l l e t t e
attracted over 10,000 visitors. Its educa-
tional interest lies not so much in the wo r d s
the actors use as in their behaviour as they
make visitors experience the humiliations
and contempt with which refugees are often
t r e at e d . “I felt a profound sense of injustice,”
Sonia explained. “It takes a great deal of
courage to do what Sybel did. I didn’t know
h ow much a person might have to go
through simply to live like everyone else.”
E m p at hy, the imagi n at i ve power to enter
into the feelings of others and to identify
with them, is a mechanism that is widely
used nowa d ays to create an awa r e n e s s
among young people and adults in deve-
loped countries of the situation faced by
refugees who seek asylum there. But this is
just one of many applications of simula-
tion games, which are, for example, used to
fa m i l i a rize children with the pollution
hazards in Mexico City or A u s t r a l i a n
firemen with procedures for controlling
forest fir e s.To d ay, u n i ve rsities and compa-
nies all over the world are using these games
because they have proved to be a low-cost
and effective method of preparing people for
the world of work.
Role-playing in simulation games pro-
vides flashes of insight which improve the
quality of our perception of others and of
gi ven situat i o n s. It changes the way we look
at others. “I now think of the refugee pro-
blem in terms of individuals and not of
figures,” said Mark Madoga on leaving La
Villette. “When I see a refugee on the TV
news,I see above all a human being.”
When bombs rain down
A similar result is obtained by “ Pa s s a g e s ” ,
a simulation game created in 1995 by the
O f fice of theUnited Nations High Commis-
sioner for Refugees (UNHCR),working with
t wo psychologists and a game specialist. L i k e
the La Villette exhibition, it seeks to make a
broad audience aware of the situation confron-
ting refugees, but it consists simply of a 30-
page handbook and is much less costly and
simpler to put into effect because only four lea-
d e rs are needed for 50 part i c i p a n t s. In four
ye a rs , over 5,000 persons in Switzerland,
S we d e n , the Netherlands, Tu n i s i a , A u s t ri a
and Chile have taken part in the game—
mostly scouts in the 12-to-18 age gr o u p, a s
well as students, t e a c h e rs and NGO members.
One of the most intense experiences of
“ Pa s s a g e s ” is when participants listen blind-
fold to a simulated bombing at t a c k .There is
complete pandemonium, and in the general
p a n i c, families split up. Parents and chil-
dren start to call out for one another. C l a i r e ,
a 34-year-old volunteer with an NGO based
Employees of a French automobile factory learn new skills via games.
‘I now think of the refugee problem in terms 
of individuals and not of figures. When I see a refugee on
the TV news, I see above all a human being’
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
real Asbel López*
in Geneva , admits that even after seve r a l
ye a rs ’ work with asylum seekers , she still did
not understand why refugees were so insis-
tent on keeping their families together—so
much so that this was liable to become their
only concern . “And then I too experi e n c e d
the terrible sense of families being separat e d
d u ring the bombardment,” she said.“ For me
the only thing that counted from then on in
the game was family unity.”
Role playing in action
Many companies now use simulation
games to train their staff—from manual
workers and technicians to executives—in
such areas as marketing, production mana-
gement and human resources. In France, a
c o n s u l t a n cy, P r o c o n s e i l , decided to tap the
rapid expansion of this market by creating
a subsidiary dedicated solely to the deve-
lopment of adult training games: C I P E
( I n t e rn ational Centre for Educational Pe d a-
gogics). In the last ten years,the company
has designed 25 games in 10 languages and
trained more than 10,000 pers o n s. Its thou-
sand or so customers in 18 countries include
the French companies A é r o s p atiale and
Y ves Saint Laurent, as well as the unive rs i-
ties of the Sorbonne in France and Nuova
Magini in Italy, a university technological
institute in Spain and Harris Semiconduc-
tors in the United States.
The use of simulation games began to
spread after the Second World Wa r , notably to
teach business management. The most
popular of the early games, “ Top Manage-
ment Decision Simulat i o n ” , was designed in
1956 by the A m e rican Management A s s o-
c i at i o n . In the 1970s,m a ny courses giving an
introduction to economics were deve l o p e d ,
including the “Island Game” i nvented by
p s y c h o - s o c i o l o gist Claude Zerbib, and Prof.
Je a n - M a rie A l b e rt i n i ’s “The Company in
A c t i o n ” , a role game in which each part i c i p a n t
p l ays in turn an offic i a l , an entrepreneur and
a head of fa m i l y.
In the field of air accident prevention,
s i m u l ation exercises have become highly
sophisticated. John Rolfe,an expert in this
field, not only uses conventional high-tech
flight simulat o rs , but also includes such
s i t u ations as hijacking and the sudden illness
of a pilot. In co-operation with the Royal A i r
Force and British commercial airlines,R o l f e
reconstructed the circumstances in which
accidents occurred and created emergency
s i t u ations which crews must learn to handle
by following established procedures without
being led astray by snap judgments.
The development of information tech-
nology and the Internet has encouraged
the creation of simulation games designed
among other things to develop commer-
cial and electoral strat e gi e s ,d e fine the most
convenient transport timetables and make
p o p u l ation and climatic forecasts based on
different scenarios.
D a n ny Saunders , who publishes T h e
I n t e rn ational Simulation and Gaming Ye a r b o o k
which first appeared in London in 1991,
says the number of simulation games has
doubled in recent ye a rs.The United Stat e s ,
the United Kingdom and Finland are
In Tunisia,over 700 people from 18 Arab countries and France took part in UNHCR’s “Passages”game in 1996.
* UNESCO Courier journalist
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO’s virtual
university
“John is teaching people how to operate a
screw-making machine.” Soon,the fami-
liar image this sentence conjures of someone
demonstrating a huge machine in front of a
group of students will require a visual update.
John will be sitting alone in front of his computer
s c r e e n , his students will be scattered all over the
world and the machine will, p h y s i c a l l y,not exist.
Welcome to the age of online, t h r e e - d i m e n-
sional training.
John will be able to teach his class from any
place he likes because he and his students will
be linked up through the Internet (see the UN E S C O
C o u r i e r, O c t o b e r 1 9 9 8 ) . There won’t be any
more need for an actual machine, which will be
replaced by a “virtual”one—that is, a picture
which includes the illusion of “ d e p t h ” — t h e
third dimension—and displays the machine
from various angles. The advantages for stu-
dents are obvious. They’ll have the benefit of
three-dimensional viewing and be linked in a
network.
Such is the goal of UN E S C O’s “ Virtual Univer-
s i t y ” p r o j e c t . It involves “employing three-
dimensional images until now used in com-
puter game programmes, so as to create virtual
environments in which people can learn,” s a y s
Philippe Quéau, head of UN E S C O’s Information
and Informatics Division.
The first step is to bring together two different
w o r l d s — o f ficial French educational institutions
such as the University Institute for Teacher Tr a i-
ning (IUFM), the National Centre for Distance
Learning (CNED), and a private firm (Cryo) which
creates virtual images and will contribute its
three-dimensional simulation technology.
After bridging this gap, UN E S C O hopes to fin d
partners interested in helping to introduce the
project to poor countries.The programme would
sponsor the setting up of virtual educational
communities and improve distance learning in
science and technology.But for now, says Quéau,
“the main thing is to obtain more funding to
continue developing educational programmes
using computers.” n
16 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
among the most active countri e s. I n
English-speaking business schools, s i m u l a-
tion games are coming to be used as an
assessment technique. “At the end of the
c o u rs e ,” D a n ny Saunders say s , “a gr o u p
of students are asked to propose at least
t wo creat i ve ways of leading a company out
of a crisis situation based on an authentic
case.”
In Spain, the use of training games has
also gr own in recent ye a rs , according to Jo s é
Luis Menes Soler,Training Director at the
Zaragoza Intern ational Business School
(CESTE) whose curriculum has offered
c o u rses including corp o r ate simulat i o n
games for the past six ye a rs. According to
Menes Soler, “it is a reve l ation for students
to see how the consequences of their deci-
sions in a particular area such as marketing
or finance can affect a company ’s ove r a l l
r e s u l t s , because all the areas of the bu s i n e s s
are inter-relat e d .” It might have cost their
companies a gr e at deal of time and money
had recent gr a d u ates been obliged to learn
these consequences in a real work situat i o n .
Training South African
entrepreneurs
Among the steps taken to correct the
inequalities created during the apartheid era
in South A f ri c a , an Equality Act today
requires companies to offer positions of res-
ponsibility to blacks, m a r ginalized for so
long that they often lack adequate expe-
ri e n c e . To remedy this shortcoming many
South A f rican companies use training games
such as “ Team Business”, c r e ated by Busi-
ness Education Design. The parti c i p a n t s
are divided into five groups, each of which
is responsible for creating a company to
m a n u facture and sell cardboard boxe s.T h e
players must find raw material suppliers,
negotiate loans with banks,buy the neces-
s a ry equipment and design their products.
According to Esmo Ndzimande, an exe-
cutive with South Africa’s ESKOM power
c o m p a ny, this game is a valuable introduc-
tion to the general principles of manage-
ment and prepares employees to react to
rapid change. “ W h at ’s more,” he say s ,
“observing the corporate process through
simulation helps us to detect faults in our
production system because it provides us
with a model showing how things should
really function.”
According to a study by South Africa’s
N ational Productivity Institute (NPI),
managers in some 50 companies in South
Africa which have adopted this kind of trai-
ning programme reported “ i m p r oved team-
work and willingness to share tasks, as well as
increased productivity, i m p r oved unders-
tanding and appreciation of the role of mana-
gement, a reduction in conflict in the work
s i t u at i o n , i n n ovat i ve ideas and efforts to
implement cost savings.”
Suitcases that didn’t suit
M i riam Garza, an industrial engi n e e r
who teaches organization and production
management courses at the Unive rsity of
San Luis Potosi in Mexico, uses CIPE’s “ K i t
C a s h ” game to explain how companies func-
tion.
Her students are divided into three
groups.They are asked to set up companies
which are contending for the suitcase market.
Each team starts out with the same amount
of cash, and has to manage its budget,plan
manufacturing, accounts and cash flow. As
the game progr e s s e s , va rious difficulties ari s e ,
such as production delays caused by break-
d owns and sudden changes in customer
tastes.
One of the students, G i l b e rto Cru z ,
r e m e m b e rs that his team’s first excurs i o n
into the market was disastrous.“Our suitcases
were far more expensive than those made by
the competition,” he says.“We realized that
we had not invested enough in machinery.”
Forced to cut their production costs in
order to compete, the young people had to
reappraise the ideas they had studied in the
classroom because they had not learned how
to apply them in practice. “Until we realized
t h at the market was not interested in our
s u i t c a s e s ,” C ruz adds, “ we didn’t unders-
tand the importance of good planning and
sound market research. Seeing the other
teams make a profit while we were crippled
with debts was far more effective than any
amount of classroom theory.”
Training games are increasingly used. B u t
h ow effective are they? Their advo c ates believe
they are a marvellous way of capturing part i-
c i p a n t s ’ at t e n t i o n .They illustrate complex pro-
cesses in a simple manner and are a useful
tool for making the public aware of all kinds of
p r o b l e m s. But objective assessment methods
are essential: in what sense and in which situa-
tions is simulation better than other teaching
methods and why? According to Danny Saun-
d e rs “ t h at is the gr e at challenge of the learn i n g
g a m e ” . n
‘Observing the corporate process through simulation helps us
to detect faults in our production system because it pro v i d e s
us with a model showing how things should really function’
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 17
The spell of sport
A harsh wind is blowing through big-time sport these days, highlighting corruption and
drug scandals, enormous salaries, stock exchange raids on top teams and the exploitation
of child worke rs who stitch balls or sports shoes.
Yet nothing checks the soaring popularity of sport. Millions of players and competitors
strive for stardom and millions of fans cheer their heroes on. Egged on by the media, b y
politicians and by the make rs of sports equipment, m o re and more people are falling under
the spell of great sporting events which have become quasi-religious rituals.
Our survey looks at the ways in which these passions are fired and at the joys and
successes they can bring. But it also examines the downside of a situation in which the
myths attached to sport are manipulated by powerful forc e s.
Sport leads neither to perdition nor para d i s e. It should not be seen as the latest example
of the opium of the people or as a pretext for violence. Nor is it a miracle solution which
can neutralize dangerous tensions, p romote greater freedom and improve human re l a t i o n s.
Most likely it is a mixture of all these factors. C e r t a i n l y, as French sports historian
B e r n a rd Jeu has put it, it is an important way for societies “to confront themselves.”
Nifty footwork.A Zambian
child’s home-made football.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
n
Basketballer Michael Jo r d a n ’s announcement
on Ja n u a ry 13 that he was retiring made head-
lines all around the wo r l d . He was up there with
Pelé, they said.The American superstar’s skill has
dazzled eve ryone who has watched him dashing
around a basketball court; as he leaps to dunk the
ball in the net he seems to be momentarily sus-
pended in the air.They call him “Air Jordan.”
But Jo r d a n , the Chicago Bulls star whose income
as a player last season was estimated at $30 million,
is also at the head of a business empire. His impact
on the U. S .e c o n o my is reckoned by Fo rt u n e m a g a-
zine at $10 billion. His link with the sporting goods
firm Nike is believed to have generated about $5.2
billion in sales of shoes and clothing.
Idol of the wo r l d ’s youth he may be, but people
argue about the role in society that he has—or
hasn’t—played.The basketball shoes carrying his
name have been stitched by child wo r k e rs in swe at-
shops, say U.S. trade unions. He has never spoken
up for Black causes,say leaders of the Black Ame-
rican community. Has he not set up thousands of
young people for a big fall because he is such a
symbol of social advancement and success? Try as
they might to emulate him, their chances of suc-
ceeding are close to nil.
In fa c t , has he not been a huge publicity machine
which has strengthened social inequalities in the
U.S. and other countries and helped big transna-
tional companies to conquer a world market?
In August 1998, notes Siavosh Ghazi in his art i c l e
on page 20 of this issue, 40 Iranian women footbal-
l e rs were gi ven permission to train in a stadium in
Teheran for the first time in 20 ye a rs. In a sense, t h e y
are the heirs of the pioneers , led by Frenchwo m a n
Alice Millat , who founded the Intern ational Wo m e n ’s
S p o rts Fe d e r ation and then, in 1922, launched the
first wo m e n ’s Olympic games.Women athletes are still
in a minority in the Olympics, after making their debu t
in tennis and golf. Only a little more than a third of the
c o m p e t i t o rs at the last summer Olympics were wo m e n .
E ven today women are still battling for complete equa-
lity and fair treatment in sport.
People with physical disabilities have removed one
b a rrier that discri m i n ated against them in sport .M o r e
and more disabled athletes,using special facilities,are
t o d ay playing the same sports as the non-disabled.
They have their own sports meetings, and since 1960
they have had their own Olympic games. H owe ve r ,
the presence of the disabled in mainstream clubs is
still rare and the example of the Norwegian swimmer
described on page 22 is an exception.
So is sport an instrument manipulated by the
p owerful? Or is it a lifeline for those who are
marginalized and excluded by society? Can it be an
Note:Since 1994,there has been a two-year gap 
between the winter and summer Olympics . For the 2002/2004 and
2006/2008 games, fees are still being negotiated.
Source: International Olympic Committee
Olympic Games broadcasting fees 
(millions of dollars )
1984 390
1988 728
1992 928
1994/1996 1,248
1998/2000 1,831
2002/2004 2,230
2006/2008 2,529
“ I t ’s just a job. G ra s s
grow s, b i rds fly,
wa ves pound the
s a n d . I beat people
u p.”
Muhammad Ali,
U.S. boxerChildren in a Nicaragua shantytown 
go for the ball.
* Respectively UNESCO Courier
journalist and professor at the
School of Human Kinetics,
University of Ottawa, Canada
1. W h a t ’s in a g a m e?
Does sport create harmony or foment division? Or both at once?
René Lefort and Jean Harvey *
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 19
The spell of sport
outlet for social discontent? The examples cited above
p r ovide no straightforward answer to these ques-
tions. In some cases sport serves the establishment;
in others it can be a seedbed for social activism.At one
and the same time it plays a host of contradictory
social roles at local, n ational and intern ational leve l .
S p o rt does not speak with a single vo i c e . It is
not monolithic. It holds different meanings for dif-
ferent social groups,partly depending on what they
want to get out of it. For the we l l - h e e l e d ,s p o rt can be
a way of adve rtising their social stat u s. P l aying at
e x c l u s i ve golf, tennis or cricket clubs can be an
opportunity to display membership of a privileged
gr o u p.A m ateur sport was controlled for a long time
by such people.
At the other end of the spectru m , s p o rt prac-
tised with the most rudimentary facilities can be a
gr e at form of self-expression for disadvantaged yo u n g
people the world ove r , and may—in exceptional
cases—offer them a way out of pove rty and depri va-
tion. Here the myth of sport as a ticket to upward
mobility can be seen in its quintessential form.The
profiles of a young Korean tennis prodigy (page 23)
and a footballer from Côte d’Ivoire who finds him-
self out on the street after once being hailed as the Pe l é
of his neighbourhood (page 24) illustrate the force and
fragility of this myth.
The kaleidoscope of sport also includes the big-
time spectacular events which have become first and
foremost a commodity whose economic import a n c e
and presence in the media are gr owing non-stop
(see boxes below). And finally there’s sport as it is
e n j oyed by so many people around the wo r l d — a
pastime that helps to keep them fit and brings them
together in a convivial setting. But here too the com-
petition can be intense, and the atmosphere may
t u rn sour. I t ’s among amateur sportsmen and sport s-
women that dru g - a buse is rife and where on-the-
field clashes can be the most violent.
S p o rt is something more than a mirror of the
societies in which it is playe d . It is not a carbon copy
of their inequalities and problems. It is a world in its
own ri g h t , with its own life and its own contradictions.
Through the medium of sport , countless vo l u n t e e rs ,f o r
e x a m p l e , organize activities and events that make a posi-
tive contribution to their communities (see article on
Midnight Basketball in the U. S . on page 25).T h r o u g h
s p o rt , a strong feeling of comradeship develops among
athletes at all leve l s. In short , major social issues
i n fluence sport , just as sport can play a big part in hel-
ping to solve them.
In a world in which all gifted young athletes were
talent-spotted and gi ven equal opportunities to deve l o p
their skills, s p o rting encounters really would take place
on a level playing field. But we do not live in an ideal
wo r l d . The gr e at myth surrounding sport is that it
abolishes social divisions, or at least that its symbolic
force gi ves it a gr e ater capacity to do so than any other
social activity. But the fact remains that the essence of
sport is competition,and competition means making
c o m p a ri s o n s , setting up hierarchies and separat i n g
winners from losers. n
+ …The economics of sport (estimates)
l *Overall annual turnover:over $400 billion
l *U.S. annual turnover:nearly $200 billion
l *Soccer annual turnover:over $200 billion
l Annual growth:between 6% and 10%
l Share of GDP in rich countries:between 1% and 1.5%
l Share of world trade: 2.5%
l Sponsorship worldwide:nearly $7 billion
l Stock exchange value of the English football club Manchester United: m o re than $1 billion
l Ferrari’s annual budget:nearly $150 million
l Michael Jordan’s earnings in 1997: nearly $80 million
* These totals include equipment,construction of facilities, broadcasting fees, sponsorship and players’
and competitors’ earnings.
S o u r c e : L’Économie du sport, by Jean-François Bourg, to be published in the Encyclopedia Universalis.
A young couple play 
football on the banks 
of Lake Titicaca (Bolivia),
the world’s highest lake.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
women were there that day simply because they
l oved football,” Mahnaz Amir Shaghaghi, w h o
coached the training session, s ays with a hint of
p ri d e .
Female enthusiasm for football really took off in
N ovember 1997 during the qualifying matches for
the 1998 World Cup.When the Iranian team unex-
pectedly scored a narrow victory over the Austra-
l i a n s , who were playing at home and were in tip-top
f o rm , the whole country exploded with joy, from the
capital to the smallest villages. Millions of men and
women poured into the streets.
A welcome for the returning heroes was set for
a week later at the Azadi Stadium, south of Te h e r a n .
The authorities made it clear on radio and television
t h at women would not be allowed into the sta-
d i u m , but to no ava i l .F i ve thousand women forced
their way in past astonished police, an event unseen
since women were banned in 1992 from attending
all-male sporting events and vice versa.
The same delirium seized the country when
the Iranians beat the U.S. team 2-1 in the French
city of Lyons during the World Cup on June 21.It
led to many appeals for women to be officially
a l l owed to play football.The popular young Iranian
actress Shifteh Farahani said she “ p r e f e rred play i n g
football to watching films.” Faezeh Hashemi, a
member of parliament (and daughter of form e r
Iranian President Ali Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani),
who has done much to promote women’s sport,
finally persuaded the authorities to give in, to the
delight of female football fans. “Women had been
allowed to play basketball, but not football,” says
Shaghaghi. “But whether you touch the ball with
hand or foot,it’s the same.”
Before the Revo l u t i o n , all sports were open to
women but they only featured at national and
i n t e rn ational level in four of them—vo l l e y b a l l ,b a s-
k e t b a l l , athletics and sw i m m i n g . S p o rt swo m e n
recall how they were never encouraged. “ B e f o r e
n
The day—22 August 1998—is engr aved in
Iranian history as a victory for wo m e n . Fo rt y
of them took part in an amateur football trai-
ning session at Te h e r a n ’s Hejab Stadium. Since the
s t a rt of the country ’s Islamic Revolution in
Fe b ru a ry 1979, women had been forbidden to
p l ay football. “ S c h o o l gi r l s , students and older
Sportswomen are slowly making headway in Iran even if men aren’t allowed 
to watch them perform and vice versa
Iranian women put on 
their running shoes Siavosh Ghazi*
* Journalist in Teheran,Iran
Ladies join Lord’s
Last September, when London’s all-male Marylebone Cricket Club (MCC) voted to admit
women to full membership some rejoiced that a bastion of male privilege had decided to
join the 20th century just before the next one began.
“I am delighted and excited by the decision,” said club president Colin Ingleby-Macke n z i e.
“ Women are a very fine species.” Not everyone was so rapturous, h o w e v e r.“ This means the
end of life as we know it,” one middle-aged member was heard to say.
C r i c ke t , an 11-a-side game with bat and ball that was invented in England over 200 years
a g o, has been played for years by women, as well as men, at national and international level.
So why should there be so much fuss about one club’s insistence on keeping its maverick sexist
status? The answer is that MCC wrote the rules of cricket,ran the game until 1969,and still
has a powerful if largely symbolic voice as guardian of the sport’s heritage.
MCC’s ground,Lord’s, is for example the headquarters of international cricket’s gover-
ning body, the International Cricket Council,which groups 9 countries or areas qualified to
play top-level international test matches, as well as a list of 42 associate and affiliate mem-
bers ranging from Argentina to Zimbabwe.
Last September’s poll,in which nearly 80 per cent of MCC’s 17,500 members (average
age 57) took part, was the club’s third vote on women’s membership. On the first occasion
in 1991, the pro-women lobby got a drubbing. Second time round, in February 1998, they won
56 per cent of votes. In September the two-thirds majority required to change the club’s mem-
bership rules was just achieved.
Some observers wondered whether the result was prompted by a sense of surviva l
rather than a real change of heart. MCC was worried that it might fall foul of possible UK legis-
lation requiring private clubs with any kind of public role to admit both sexes.An MCC appli-
cation for National Lottery funding had been turned down partly because of the sexist
admissions policy. Perhaps some “yes”voters thought that since there was an 18-year wai-
ting list for membership they would not have to live with the consequences anyway.
In March it was announced that ten honorary  women members had joined the club. By
virtue of a specially drawn up dress code, they will be allowed to rub shoulders with men in
the club pavilion—but only as long as their shoulders are covered.There is even talk of sel-
ling MCC silk nighties in the club shop. “ Women are going to be looked after in every
c o n c e i vable capacity when they become members,” I n g l e b y - M a c kenzie was reported as
saying. n
‘Women had been allowed 
to play basketball, but not
football. But whether 
you touch the ball with hand 
or foot, it’s the same’
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 21
The spell of sport
1 9 7 9 , you had to choose between sport and the
ve i l ,” s ays Hashemi.
From the start of the Revolution, the govern-
ment tried to curb wo m e n ’s sport s. “The hard-
liners had a reactionary reading of religion,” says a
j o u rn a l i s t .“It all boils down to the way you interp r e t
the scri p t u r e s.” But even the moderates were against
women we a ring sports gear in front of men.This wa s
only allowed amongst other women.
These days there are women active in 25 sport s ,
including skiing, vo l l e y b a l l , b a s k e t b a l l , s h o o t i n g,
r ow i n g, k a r at e , judo and gymnastics. The stri c t
s e gr e g ation of men and women has had some posi-
t i ve effects. “ M a ny women have been trained in
recent ye a rs as referees and coaches—about 16,000
of them, in all sport s ,” s ays Shaghaghi. Iran now has
56 intern at i o n a l - l e vel women trainers for vo l l e y b a l l
and six for fencing, for example. And in recent
months, women have been taking part in motor-
racing. “Theoretical and practical courses began
three months ago and have been a great success,”
says a reporter on the daily newspaper Zan (which
means “woman” in Persian).
“The separation of the sexes has encouraged
many traditional Iranian families to allow their
daughters to play sports,which they hadn’t up till
then,” says Jilla Amiri, who played football during
the time of the Shah. Sport is also more open to
young women from the middle or lower classes.
But equipment and facilities are very meagre.
“Most sports centres are reserved for men,” says
Amiri.“We don’t have a tenth of the facilities they
h ave . Radio and television never report on wo m e n ’s
s p o rt s , not even championship mat c h e s. Pictures of
such events cannot be shown and this is a serious
block to the development of women’s sport.”
The wo m e n ’s daily Z a n is an exception. I t
reports on women’s sports and encourages its rea-
d e rs to play up to professional leve l .The paper is ru n
in fact by Faezeh Hashemi, who managed to get a
cycle path built in a park south of the capital where
boys and girls could ride their bikes together.
E ven more signific a n t l y, she has pushed the
idea of an Islamic Wo m e n ’s Games, of which two
h ave since been held in Iran. In 1993, 11 coun-
t ries took part , with a total of 345 women in
eight sport s , including shooting, table tennis,
handball and basketball. In 1997, nearly 1,000
women from 21 countries came to Teheran t o
compete in 13 sport s , including tennis, c h e s s ,g y m-
n a s t i c s , k a r at e , swimming and equestri a n i s m .
C o u n t ries invo l ved included Syri a , B a n g l a d e s h ,
Tu r k m e n i s t a n , A z e r b a i j a n , K a z a k h s t a n , In d o n e s i a
and Ku wa i t . The events were shown on televi-
s i o n , but were filmed from a distance. E ven these
broadcasts were cancelled after objections from
c o n s e rvat i ve s.
Such occasions gi ve Iranian women a chance to
compete against foreign teams, even if they them-
s e l ves are not so skilled. For higher profile intern a-
tional eve n t s , the ban on showing themselves in
s p o rts gear, especially short s , in front of men remains
a sizeable obstacle. But a woman was in the nat i o n a l
shooting team at the last Olympic Games and an Ira-
nian woman skier won a bronze medal at the A s i a n
Games at the end of last ye a r.These are two sport s
that may well attract growing numbers of Iranian
women in times ahead. n
The 2nd Islamic Women’s Games, held in Teheran
in December 1997.
‘The separation of the sexes 
has encouraged many 
traditional Iranian families 
to allow their daughters
to play sports, which they hadn’t
up till then’
“ I t ’s impossible 
to have close friends 
in tennis, b e c a u s e
sooner or later 
yo u ’ll be playing
against them.”
Arantxa Sánchez Vicario,
former top seed 
woman tennis player.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
Around $700,000 are being invested eve ry year in
p r o grammes to bring disabled and non-disabled at h-
letes together in the same clubs. Stig Morten is him-
self now a member of an ordinary sports club. S p o rt s
clubs are also receiving money to improve access for
disabled people to arenas which were ori ginally bu i l t
only for the non-disabled.
In some sports such as shooting, disabled and
non-disabled athletes can perform on equal terms if
suitable arrangements are made. In many cases,
according to the association for handicapped at h l e t e s ,
it is only social barriers that keep handicapped and
non-handicapped apart.
“This is going to change, and it is ve ry import a n t
that it should.But I think it may take 10 or 15 years
before all the barri e rs come dow n ,” Stig Mort e n
says.
Another thing that helps to bring barri e rs dow n
and develop gr e ater tolerance, Stig Morten thinks,
is the fact that he trains in the pool with non-disa-
bled children and adults.
Stig Morten Sandvik has achieved success in the
swimming pool, and hopes to continue as a top-leve l
swimmer for a few more ye a rs.But he feels that his gr e a-
test achievement—one that can not be valued in gold,s i l-
ver or bronze—has already been wo n : s e l f - c o n fid e n c e
and the belief that he can do things that people who
d o n ’t have to use a wheelchair take for gr a n t e d . n
Disabled Norwegian student Stig Morten Sandvik has won medals as a swimmer.
But sport has above all helped him achieve confidence and self-re s p e c t
Training for life
Ole Kristian Bjellaanes*
n
“ I t ’s thanks to sport that I’m so independent in
life. Sport has meant everything to me,” says
Stig Morten Sandvik, a 28-year-old Norwe-
gian political science student who trains for 12
hours every week to become a better swimmer.
Stig Morten, who lives at Bodoe, in Nordland
c o u n t y, was born with A rt h r o gryposis multiplex
congenita (AMC), a disease which affects the
muscles. This makes him dependent on a wheel-
c h a i r , although he can also move around using
crutches.
He was six when his mother first took him to the
swimming pool. He took to the water and soon
came to feel that swimming would play a big part in
his life.The gold medals he has won in World Cham-
pionships and the bronze medals he took in the
Paralympics in 1992 and 1996 prove just how
important it became.
But for Stig Mort e n , as for many other disabled
p e rs o n s ,s p o rt has far more to do with managing his
life than with winning pri z e s.“My sporting activity
made me a normal Norwe gian boy. I was able to do
something as well as all my fri e n d s ,” he say s. It also
made him very independent in his daily life.When
he was 16 and about to gr a d u ate from high school,
he chose to live alone. N ow he is moving in with his
girlfriend.
Bringing the barriers down
He is sufficiently independent to be able to
clean his apartment by himself. He cooks and goes
shopping on his own.“The only thing I can’t do is
change light bulbs,” he says.
In Norway most disabled people have their ow n
houses or apart m e n t s , and look after themselve s ,
sometimes with support from personal care assistants.
Ve ry few of them live in special institutions. S t i g
M o rten feels totally integr at e d , and few people eve n
comment that he has a gi r l f riend without a han-
d i c a p. He is also convinced that his sport gi ves him
a self-respect and self-confidence that disabled people
who don’t practice such an activity may lack.
Some 22,000 physically and mentally handi-
capped people are members of Norway ’s associat i o n
for disabled at h l e t e s. In 1996 the Norwe gian sport s
movement decided to make an effort to integrate
sport for disabled people and sport for “normal”
p e o p l e . This is in line with developments in the
rest of a society where disabled people are pro-
vided with facilities such as transport and pers o n a l
assistance to help their social integration.
“If we don’t do
something quick l y,
the United States wo n ’t
be winning any more
medals for spri n t i n g.
L e t ’s stop subsidizing
our opponents,”
i . e . by letting foreigners
p r o fit from the
A m e rican training
s y s t e m .
Carl Lewis,
holder of 9 Olympic 
Gold Medals.
*Journalist in Oslo, Norway
Stig Morten Sandvik.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 23
The spell of sport
A promising 12-year-old Korean tennis-player who seems to be relishing 
the pressure as he quests for athletic perfection and international acclaim
Going for glory
Glenn Manarin with additional reporting by Myung-soo Kim Taejon*
* Journalists in Taejon,
South Korea n
Under the mid-morning sun at Chungnam
N ational Unive rsity in Ta e j o n , South Korea, 1 2 -
year-old Dong-whee Choi is hitting baseline
forehands weighted with topspin and punchy two-
handed backhands to a player twice his age from the
u n i ve rsity team.With the snow-capped mountains
of Kyerong-san in the distance, Choi is hard at
t r a i n i n g, filling the days of winter va c ation on sand
courts.
Like many other children his age, Choi has
dreams of athletic wo n d e r. But unlike the vast majo-
ri t y, he is on the path to realizing his dreams, a l o n g
with those of his fa m i l y, coach and, perhaps one day,
those of his country.
Choi is going to Bradenton, F l o ri d a ,a c c o m p a-
nied by his coach and his 10-year-old sister Ha-ya n g,
thanks to a five-year scholarship from the interna-
tionally renowned Nick Bollettieri ’s Tennis A c a-
d e my.At Bollettieri ’s , which boasts alumni including
many of Choi’s heroes—such as tennis greats Pete
Sampras and André Agassi—Choi will find the
competition and training facilities he needs to meet
his soaring aspirations. He will also face unprece-
dented pressure at what is often described as a
“boot camp” where nothing less than winning is
accepted—an approach which he seems to relish.
Six hours a day on the court
“My first goal is to win the U. S . Open and I wa n t
to be at least one of the top-five ranked playe rs in the
world,” says the winsome youth, his demureness
m o m e n t a rily dissipated by his fervour for the sport .
“ I ’ ve never considered how long it’s going to take to
happen.I never think about my age.”
Children like Choi, so strangely determ i n e d ,
e voke admiration but also a nagging concern that
they have been pressured to succeed by aggr e s s i ve
p a r e n t s. Some might also question the wisdom of let-
ting such a young child invest so much towa r d s
such a distant goal.Yet as Choi’s experience high-
l i g h t s , it could be even more difficult for a parent to
tell a child:“ G i ve up your dreams of glory.”
Choi was first introduced to tennis at the age of
three when his fat h e r , In-chul Choi, a lieutenant-
colonel in the South Korean military and a keen
tennis playe r , bought him a toy racket.At six, he gr a-
d u ated to a real racket, p l aying regularly with his
fat h e r.While his parents say they initially intended
for Choi to enjoy the sport recreat i o n a l l y, they lat e r
sought to develop the boy ’s apparent potential by
h i ring 45-year-old Choong-sup Song as coach in
1 9 9 4 . “He wa s n ’t so gr e at at firs t ,” s ays Song. “ B u t
he was so hard-working and he has such a strong will
for someone his age. H e , his parents and myself all
h ave the same goal now.”
T h at goal has made Choi’s life anything bu t
o r d i n a ry. In Korea’s Confucian-influenced society,
where academic endeavour and success is a ve ri t a b l e
litmus test of social worth,most youngsters spend
hours a day studying in private educational insti-
t u t e s , supplementing their regular studies.Yet Choi
spends the bulk of his time on the court—about six
hours a day, seven days a week.“Sometimes I find
it diffic u l t ,” he say s , “especially when I can’t hit
the ball well, but aside from that that I just enjoy it
and have fun.”
National heroes
C h o i ’s work ethic earned him an inv i t ation to the
1998 Orange Bow l , an intern ational tournament in
M i a m i ,F l o ri d a . He took first prize from a field of 128
of the wo r l d ’s top 12-ye a r - o l d s.While in Flori d a ,h e
also aced Bollettieri ’s tennis school eva l u ation test for
the scholarship before signing a contract with IMG
( I n t e rn ational Management Group),which manages
the careers of many of the wo r l d ’s top at h l e t e s.
When the news in Florida reached Korea, the
young player and his family were deluged by inter-
view requests from the media. The reaction to
C h o i ’s early success, which would go largely unno-
ticed in many other countri e s , comes as little surp ri s e
in Korea,where athletes who excel on the interna-
tional stage are a source of intense admiration and
pride. Los Angeles Dodger pitching ace Chan-ho
Park and golfer Se-ri Pak, the 1998 Ladies’ Pro-
fessional Gold Association (LPGA) Rookie of the
Ye a r , are nothing less than national heroes in
K o r e a — e xe m p l a rs of excellence, p a rticularly in
these morale-hungry times of economic crisis.
While the future looks rosy for Choi, w h at of the
chances of him breaking his wrist or caving in to the
mounting psychological pressure? W h at then? T h e s e
questions aren’t recognized by Choi and his parents.
I n s t e a d , they voice their trust in Choi’s coach,
S o n g, who refuses to consider anything except posi-
tive outcomes.
“I’m doing what I really want to do,” s ays Choi.
“My coach says it’s better if I can play we l l , but that
I shouldn’t have pressure on me,and my parents just
tell me to do my best. . . . Since I was a little kid, I ’ ve
never had any other dreams except being a tennis
player and now I am so happy.” n
Dong-whee Choi in action.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
Heading for stardom?
n
“They used to tell me sport was just for hooligans.
They deceived me.” Who did? “ E ve ryo n e .” Je a n -
Jacques Diodan, from Côte d’Ivo i r e , is bitter. A ny
little thing reopens the wo u n d , like the TV progr a m m e
a few months ago which showed the opening of a school
for street children sponsored by his compat riot Basile
B o l i . Boli was the defence pillar of Olympique Mar-
s e i l l e s , a team which, in its glory day s ,g ave France its firs t -
e ver European Champions Cup. His was a real success
s t o ry.
He and Je a n - Jacques started out in exactly the same
way. A few years apart, they played in the local teams
t h at were all the rage in Abidjan in the 1970s and
1980s. Boli was a great hulk,while Jean-Jacques was a
slight figure who became a magician when he had the
ball at his feet.
Je a n - Jacques became the darling of A b i d j a n ’s poor
s u burb of  Tr e i c h v i l l e , with his cunning dri b b l e s ,fierce vo l-
leys and brilliant opport u n i s m . All the neighbourhood
a s s o c i ations begged him to join their teams. To entice
h i m , they offered him sweets or cakes,a few hundred CFA
f r a n c s , an a b o k i (coffee with cream) or a ga r b a (a dish of
f ried fish and manioc flo u r ) .
The talent scouts of the big Abidjan clubs were also
s n i f fing around for future champions.T h at was how Boli
was discove r e d , along with others like Gadji Celi and
Youssouf Fo fa n a , the future star of Monaco.These lads
were not obsessed with turning professional.They playe d
because they liked to,because they loved being cheered by
the Sunday crowds and sometimes being carried aloft as
h e r o e s.
But it became so enjoyable in the end that they sacri-
ficed eve rything for it, s t a rting with their schoolwo r k .
Je a n - Ja c q u e s , a bright youth who had entered secondary
school when he was 11,s t a rted playing truant and skipping
c l a s s e s ,b e ginning with maths and English.His report
card summed it all up—playing hookey, bad marks and
lack of concentrat i o n .
His fat h e r , a customs officer so proud of his son
t h at he nicknamed him “the Pelé of Tr e i c h v i l l e ” , wa s
d u m b s t ru c k . He and the rest of the family knew that
only the best school leaving cert i fic at e , not a football
pitch, would ensure the boy’s future.
There were row s , punishments and beat i n g s ,
but to no avail. Jean-Jacques didn’t make a clear
choice and so ended up losing on both counts.
Sport is like a jealous woman who refuses to share
her man.If Jean-Jacques refused to devote himself
d ay and night to football, then he wo u l d n ’t become
a star and wo u l d n ’t go off to Europe to earn millions.
If he returned to school,he would just limp along.
In the end, to eve ryo n e ’s surp ri s e , he got his
leaving certificate but his marks were too poor for
him to continue in public high school.The altern a-
t i ve was pri vate schooling. But his angry fat h e r
refused to pay for that. “If you want to become a
Pelé,then go and be one,” he said sarcastically.
E ve n t u a l l y, a sympathetic elder sister who was a
journalist agreed to come up with the money. So
Je a n - Jacques continued his studies, managed to
pass his baccalaureate and even went on to earn a
degree in sociology.
But this meant nothing in a labour market ove r-
loaded with gr a d u at e s. Jo b l e s s , he lived off his fa m i l y.
His wife, with whom he had a baby, left him because
he wa s n ’t earning any money. He dreamed of emi-
gr ating to the United Stat e s — t h at he would be chosen
from thousands of others as an eligible immigr a n t
and then, in an immigr ation lottery, win the right to
actually go there. He turned once more to his sister, t o
p ay for him to learn a trade.
The fame of the Pelé of Treichville never we n t
b e yond his neighbourhood, though he is convinced he
had the talent to go furt h e r. He didn’t manage either
to get a literature doctorate which, he is equally sure,
would have opened the door to a fine career.
Meanwhile Basile Boli is a millionaire and, at 30,
Jean-Jacques Diodan is unemployed. n
A star that never ro s e
K. K. Man Jusu*
Sporting stardom beckons 
to talented young athletes 
all over the world, but only
very few reach the top.
Je a n - Jacques Diodan’s story is
one of many
* Journalist in Abidjan,
Côte d’Ivoire
‘If you want to become a Pelé,
then go and be one’
“By 2005 no A f ri c a n
n ational soccer teams
will be left. E u ro p e a n
clubs are importing
yo u n ger and yo u n ge r
A f rican playe rs, a n d
taking away their
n ationality by
p i cking them fo r
E u ropean nat i o n a l
t e a m s.”
A coach with Milan AC
football club.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 25
The spell of sport
Midnight Basketball is giving thousands
of young males in poor
neighbourhoods of U. S. cities an
opportunity to play the game and ke e p
out of tro u b l e
B a s ketball at m i d n i g h t Gary A. Sailes*
n
Anthony Carter, a 22-year-old African-Ame-
ri c a n , is a star player in the Unive rsity of Hawa i i
Basketball team.He has already had lucrative
offers from prestigious clubs in the National Bas-
ketball Association (NBA) league.
Not long ago, C a rter was one of many poor
young males looking for opportunities in A t l a n t a ’s
Jonesboro south subu r b , k n own for its high cri m e
r at e . His life took a different turn after he joined the
local “Midnight Basketball” (MBL) league where he
spent three ye a rs.As a result, he is now in unive rs i t y
and looking ahead to a bright future in the NBA
l e a g u e . M B L , which organizes basketball playe d
b e t ween 10:00 p. m . and 2:00 a.m, has changed the
l i ves of many young males like Carter who live in the
poor neighbourhoods of Atlanta and might otherwise
h ave drifted into cri m e . (See box . )
The only difference between Midnight Basket-
ball and normal basketball is that it is played at
hours when young inner city males are most vul-
nerable to the drug culture,crime and other nega-
t i ve activity. In a nutshell, MBL takes the playe rs off
the street at night and places them in a play gr o u n d
area under organized and structured conditions.
Emmanuel Hunt, Jr, President of Atlanta MBL,
quoting police records, s ays that the programme has
helped to bring down the crime rate in the inner city,
which fell by 40 per cent in the last five years.
Chapters
in fifty cities
The first Midnight Basketball League was start e d
in 1986 in Glenarden, M a ry l a n d , and since then
the idea has spread to major cities like Los A n g e l e s ,
A t l a n t a ,M i a m i ,C l e veland and Detroit. Like NBA,
MBL has its own organized stru c t u r e .To d ay, it has
50 chapters nationwide and about 10,000 yo u n g s t e rs
p l ay in MBL games across the country.The Com-
m i s s i o n e r ’s office is located in Chicago and there are
r e gional offices which organize tournaments bet-
ween local teams and between cities. Last ye a r ,
according to National A s s o c i ation of MBL offic i a l s ,
about 200,000 spectat o rs watched the matches per
night nationwide and the television viewe rs h i p
crossed the 3.5 million mark.
MBL playe rs , selected normally on open tryo u t s
in each city, are in the 17-25 age group and on
average spend three to four ye a rs in the progr a m m e .
They are distri buted among different teams which
p l ay in a local league. Most participants in the
MBL are A f ri c a n - A m e ri c a n s ,m e m b e rs of the gr o u p
that outnumbers other ethnic groups in the poor
neighbourhoods of many U. S . c i t i e s. “ Pa rt i c i p a-
tion in the league is open to all young males.We do
not discri m i n ate on racial or ethnic grounds in
selecting the players,” says Tony Adams,an official
at the Fountain City MBL of Columbus,Georgia.
What makes an MBL match different from a
n o rmal basketball game? Before each eve n t , t h e
players have to attend a one-hour workshop which
focuses on topics like job interview skills, financial
m a n a g e m e n t , AIDS/HIV awa r e n e s s , d rug and
alcohol abuse prevention, conflict resolution and
*Associate professor 
of Sport Sociology at Indiana
University and author of African-
Americans in Sport: Contemporary
themes
A programme 
to combat crime
The Sentencing Project, a U. S. Criminology Think Ta n k ,
reported in 1998 that the leading cause of death
among African-American male youth between the ages
of 17 and 25 is homicide and that one in six A f r i c a n - A m e-
rican males will be arrested before they reach the age of
1 9 . It is estimated that one in 22 African-American males
will be killed by a violent crime before reaching the age
of 44.Moreover, as many as 42 per cent of incarcerated
men in the United States are black males. It is estimated
that by the year 2000,approximately 50 per cent of black
males between the ages of 17 and 30 will be either
incarcerated or under penal supervision.Law enforcement
officials and criminologists have established that the
increased drug use, drug trafficking and disenchantment
with the American educational and employment oppor-
tunity structure has led to the increased arrests among col-
lege age African-American males.
In an effort to address rising crime and related pro-
blems among youths in Glenarden,Maryland,the town
m a n a g e r, G.Van Standifer, established the Midnight Bas-
ketball League in 1986.His aim was to provide an alter-
native to youngsters who wander around their neigh-
bourhood during the night and end up committing crimes.
With the support of businesses, law enforcement offic i a l s,
and political and community leaders, the first Midnight
B a s ketball League programme was organized in the
same year.The MBL says that programme was successful
in reducing the incidence of reported crimes by almost 60
per cent in Glenarden. Standifer later created the format
for other communities to develop MBL leagues in their
area. Today, MBL chapters have been developed in over
50 cities in the U.S. and in Puerto Rico. Each chapter is a
non-profit,community-based organization that adheres
to formal training, rules and regulations based on the ori-
ginal successful programme. n
“Sport can fire
the highest 
and the lowe s t
p a s s i o n s.
It can deve l o p
d i s i n t e restedness 
and a sense of honour
as well as love 
of pro fit .
It can be ch i va l rous 
or corru p t , manly 
or bestial. Nobility 
of fe e l i n g, the cult 
of disinterest 
and honour, the spiri t
of ch i va l ry, m a n l i n e s s
and peace are 
the prime needs 
of modern
d e m o c ra c i e s.”
Pierre de Coubertin 
(1863-1937),
French educator,
first president 
of the International 
Olympic Committee
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
n
Monkey-hoots and banana peels fire down on the
black British footballer who commits the sin of
missing a goal.Reprehensibly racist behav i o u r ,s ay
the pundits,but these are the isolated occurrences of
a few rotten apples.A look past these extremists sup-
posedly reveals an arena in UK society—the world of
s p o rt—where eve ryone has an equal opportunity to
s u c c e e d .B a rri e rs of colour and class cannot possibly
be found on the track, it is argued, where the stop-
watch is the ultimate judge.According to UK A t h l e-
t i c s , the gove rnment body promoting track and fie l d
s p o rt s , 24 per cent of top at h l e t e s , meaning those
who receive grants on the basis of perform a n c e , are of
A f rican or Caribbean ori gi n ,e ven though they com-
pose just two per cent of the UK populat i o n .I n d e e d ,
blacks represent 48 per cent of these top at h l e t e s
who are focusing on their training and not simulta-
neously pursuing academics.
As Robin Phillips of UK Athletics say s , this high
r e p r e s e n t ation would  generally be seen as a sign of
social progr e s s.Yet the rosy picture darkens with the
q u e s t i o n : w hy are so many blacks running? Pe r h a p s
because they don’t have the same chances of succee-
ding in other areas, s ays Ben Carri n g t o n , a sociologi s t
at the Unive rsity of Bri g h t o n , widely respected in
B ritish academic circles for his research on racism in
s p o rt and who is now editing a book on the subject.
This is not to suggest that blacks are genetically gi f t e d
for sport—a proposition Carrington vehemently rejects
Black sprinters
are dominating
the sport in the
UK but
troubling
questions belie
what some see
as 
a triumph
against racism
Hidden hurdles of   
e n t r e p r e n e u rs h i p. A nyone who does not at t e n d
these classes is not allowed on the basketball court .
“Instructors encourage the participants to take up
jobs and sometimes the local association helps them
to find one,” says Hunt.
There are eight to ten teams in each chapter with
10-12 playe rs in each team,and each team plays on an
average three to four games per week during a summer
s e a s o n . MBL playe rs can stay in the league till they
reach 25 ye a rs of age and some of those who retire
come back to the system as instru c t o rs , coaches and
vo l u n t e e rs.
“The stress is on discipline, punctuality and beha-
v i o u r. M e m b e rs are not allowed to enter the court if
they come late for the class and if they misbehave
d u ring a game they are immediately sent out,” s ay s
Mark Gallagher, assistant sports supervisor at the
R e c r e ation and A rts Center in Wat e r l o o, I owa .
Respecting the rules
MBL playe rs are not paid for their part i c i p at i o n .
The only incentive comes in the form of balls, s h o e s
and T-shirts, making the event a totally non-com-
mercial activity. Local gove rn m e n t , n o n g ove rn-
mental organizations and pri vate companies sponsor
these events.
W h at makes these yo u n g s t e rs follow strict ru l e s
and regulations inside the basketball court when they
h ave difficulty in following the rules of the society? In
his book The Violent Social Wo rld of Black Men, s o c i o-
l o gist William Oliver argues that black males often
break rules as a form of resistance to discri m i n at i o n
and disrespect in a white-dominated society. T h e y
channel themselves into the areas where they per-
c e i ve opportunities exist, and sport , especially bas-
k e t b a l l , is one of them.1
For A f ri c a n - A m e rican youth basketball has
become a subculture in its own ri g h t .Talented high
school playe rs are recruited by top colleges and
are offered scholarships to study and also to play in
the college team.The best college playe rs then go on
to play professional basketball in the NBA or in ove r-
seas leagues.
For these youngsters in poor neighbourhoods,
MBL not only provides an opportunity to play the
game but also contri butes to their self-identity and
s e l f - a s s e rt i o n . Fo l l owing the rules of the game
enables them to gain respect from their peers ,p o p u-
l a rity and a reputation as fierce competitors. A
player in an MBL league can lose his reputation in
his locality if he is kicked out of the programme on
d i s c i p l i n a ry gr o u n d s. The message of MBL is
s i m p l e . If you want an opportunity to play the
game, you have to respect the rules. n
1 . According to 1998 U. S . Census Bureau figures 34 million
blacks live in the United Stat e s , representing 12 per cent of
the populat i o n .H owe ve r , according to sport sociologi s t
Richard Lapchik at the Center for the Study of Sport in
Society at Nort h e a s t e rn Unive rsity in Boston, they compri s e
85 per cent of the National Basketball A s s o c i ation (NBA)
t e a m s , 67 per cent of National Collegi ate A t h l e t i c
A s s o c i ation (NCAA) division I basketball teams and are
represented in 95 per cent of all college basketball teams.
“ W h at ever games 
a re played with us,
we must play no ga m e s
w ith ours e l ve s.”
Ralph Waldo Emerson,
U.S. poet
* Amy Otchet
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 27
The spell of sport
as being both racist and scientifically unfounded. I n s-
tead he points to the ways in which stereotypes seep
into the lives of young blacks and reinforce the socio-
economic reasons leading them to pursue at h l e t i c s.
At the age of 24, Julian Golding is one of Br i-
t a i n ’s hopefuls, becoming the Commonwealth 200-
metre champion last year. From an early age on,
Golding knew he was fast but didn’t dream of beco-
ming a champion. He was raised to focus on edu-
cation, not sport, as “the way out” of the working
class life of his parents, Jamaican immigrants who
arrived in the 1960s.
Missing idols
So Golding studied hard at school, filling his free
time with tennis, track and trampoline activities. B u t
at 16, his  school director took him aside for a chat .
“Why not pursue running as a career? You’ve got
talent.” The same encouragement came from his
p hysical education (PE) teacher. There was no
mention of his academic opportunities.
Golding began weighing his options. “I was a
better tennis player than a spri n t e r ,” he say s , “ bu t
there was no-one to look up to. No black tennis
i d o l s. So I thought about trying to be the firs t ”u n t i l
his first visit to the local tennis club.“The courts we r e
packed but there wa s n ’t one black pers o n . I didn’t feel
c o m f o rt a b l e . I started asking about the subscri p t i o n
and coaching fees,” s ays Golding, c a l c u l ating the
expense for his parents who had five kids to support .
“I thought, ‘No way ! ’ And walked out.”
He started training at a local track, focusing on
black idols, like Linford Chri s t i e , the 1992 Olympic
colour
100-metre champion.“You’ve got to have a vision
of success. Linford made it and he’s from the same
neck of the woods in west London as me.”
G o l d i n g ’s experience is typical, s ays Carri n g t o n .
Money, status and glamour “pull”kids into sport.
However,black kids,in particular,also experience
the “ p u s h ” of PE teachers , who may have good
intentions but inadve rtently reinforce  stereotypes.
“The (PE) teachers think that certain types of kids,
namely black kids, are going to be better off in an
athletics career,” s ays Carri n g t o n , “because they’r e
never going to make it in the world of finance or
medicine.”
Carrington points to a full body of research in
this area. One of the most recent surve y s ,c o n d u c t e d
by Sid Hayes and John Sugden of the Unive rsity of
B ri g h t o n ,i nvo l ved about 35 PE teachers in an eth-
nically mixed region of the Midlands. Over 80 per
cent of the teachers reported the “feeling that black
pupils tend to be advantaged in sport ” , which most
identified as at h l e t i c s. Almost 75 per cent at t ri-
buted their black students’ sport success to “phy-
siological reasons”.
Science and stereotypes
Golding is not shocked by the teachers ’r e s p o n s e .
On the contrary,he has learned to accept as truth the
same stereotypes of “black braw n ” . As a teenager,
Golding was falsely “taught that it is a ‘ s c i e n t i fic
fa c t ’t h at black people in general are able to move their
muscles faster than white people” because they have
special muscle fib r e s.“ S t atistics seem to prove it,” h e
s ay s.“When was the last time we saw a white spri n t e r
compete in the finals of an Olympic game? Back in
1980—almost 20 ye a rs ago.”
Yet Golding is not fully convinced by this “ m u s c l e
t h e o ry ” and welcomes Carri n g t o n ’s assertion that it
b e a rs no scientific gr o u n d i n g . When asked of any
other biological explanations for black athletic suc-
c e s s , Golding quietly mentions the “Black Body, a
t e rm that I hat e ”which refers to the stereotype of the
black muscular muscular torso of men like Linford
C h ri s t i e .The emotional edge to his voice suggests that
Golding is torn by a personal quandary. He has been
taught that blacks are gifted in athletics—a stereotype
reinforced by media images of black muscular men.
Yet he also knows that “black braw n ” is loaded with
racist ove rtones suggesting “white intelligence”.
So it is with visible relief that Golding listens as
C a rrington debunks these erroneous “b i o l o gi c a l
e x p l a n at i o n s.” The sociologist traces their roots to
the Eugenics movement of the 1920s and 30s,
which ori gi n ated in North A m e rica and later spread
throughout Europe. The aim was to produce a
genetically superior population,which is linked to
the notion of a hierarchy of separate races in which
blacks were placed on the bottom, s ays Carri n g t o n .
To reinforce this ranking, anthropologists tried to
define the model white and black male by measu-
ring and comparing their va rious body part s — e a r-
l o b e s ,n o s e s , limb lengths and so on.“These studies
were inherently racist and had very little scientific
validation behind them,” says Carrington.* UN E S C O C o u r i e r j o u r n a l i s t
Above, Britain’s Julian Golding
on his way to victory in the
semi-final of the 200 metres,
during the European athletics
championships in Budapest
(Hungary) in 1998.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
The build-up for an international sporting
event can create a tremendous sense 
of national unity. But there’s always a danger
of such powerful emotions turning sour
*Sports Faculty
University of Montpellier, France
The Eugenics movement disappeared after the
Holocaust in World War II. H owe ve r , C a rri n g t o n
finds some of the same “ b i o l o gical arguments” a n d
i d e o l o gical conceptions emerging today with genetic
r e s e a r c h .There is, for example, a misconception in
some sectors of the public that scientists will prove
racial differences. “ To d ay we know that there are
about 100,000 genes in the human body and yet less
than ten of them are related to skin colour,”s ays Car-
ri n g t o n . “Obviously there are va ri ations betwe e n
gr o u p s ,” but these differences are linked to geo-
gr a p hy. In short , as groups migr ated around the
wo r l d , people adapted to their physical surr o u n-
dings and passed those changes on to their descen-
d a n t s.
A gene for playing darts or snooker
Still the idea persists that scientists will one day
d i s c over a gene which makes blacks run fa s t .“ T h e n
there must be a gene among white working-class Bri-
tish males for throwing darts or playing snooker,”
jokes Carrington. “It’s comic. No one would ever
suggest that Canadians are somehow genetically
inclined to playing ice hockey...Yet whenever you
have black success, there is a genetic argument.”
These arguments often serve to deny or reduce
the dedication and intelligence of successful black
at h l e t e s ,s ays Carri n g t o n ,p a rticularly in the media.
He does not suggest that sport commentators are
inherently racist. But Carrington does see a ten-
dency to treat black and white athletes differently.
Commentators often focus on the black athlete’s
n atural ability, he say s , while white athletes are also
praised for their intelligent strat e gies and dedicat i o n .
Golding points to a related dimension: t h e
impact on young white at h l e t e s. “If I was a 16-
year-old white student,I wouldn’t dream of going
into athletics,” he says.With the media zooming in
on black powerhouses like Linford Christie, “I’d
think that I didn’t have a hope to win.”
“With blacks dominating the sport,” Golding
senses a public “yearning for a new Roger Black”,
the English (white) 400-metre runner who won a
s i l ver medal at the 1996 Olympics.This desire is not
manifested in any overt forms of racism,says Gol -
ding, but rather through “hidden agendas.”
The “ ye a rning for the Great White Hope”
cannot be proven.But for Carrington, it is impor-
tant to note the impact of the perception that it
e x i s t s. He refers to a scenario which, he say s , i s
taken ve ry seriously by many black at h l e t e s. I m a gi n e
the following: four athletes—three black and one
white—compete for three places on a team.The firs t
t wo clock ve ry fast times and take their places.T h e
other two are close, but the white athlete is slightly
slower.Who makes the team? 
“ You have to be above and beyond eve ryone else,
so that there isn’t any argument not to pick you,”
s ays Carri n g t o n . “But that kind of skews the picture
of black athletic success. People don’t see the ave-
rage black athletes because they don’t make the
teams.This in turn leads people to say, ‘See,there
must be something special about them.’” n
2 . The a g o n y
Philippe Liotard*
n
A sudden roar surged from the throats of the
thousands of spectat o rs packed in the stadium
and from hundreds of millions more all around
the globe.French soccer star Emmanuel Petit had
just sent the ball into the back of the Brazilian net
a few minutes before the end of the 1998 Wo r l d
Cup final.
As the great roar erupted, so did the bodies
from which it came. Arms were stretched trium-
phantly aloft and then reached out exultantly to
embrace other bodies. In the midst of the din,
people hugged each other—on the pitch, in the
stands, before giant screens set up in Paris, Saint
Étienne and thousands of other French towns
and villages, and in front of TV sets in bars, cafés
and homes.
The rejoicing went on late into the night, a s
c r owds all over the country took part in the biggest
e ruption of popular joy in France since the Libera-
tion at the end of the Second World War.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 29
The spell of sport
As the goal was scored, other equally violent
c ries were uttered. But they were shorter and ended
in sobs. Cries of pain, rage, frustration and humi-
liation, they soon gave way to silence.Amazement
and disbelief were written on grim, tortured faces.
The shouting, the tears and the body language
were triggered by a whirlwind of emotions. On one
s i d e , the ecstasy of the French; on the other the
grief of the Brazilians, whose team had been beat e n
3 - 0 . The final was watched around the world by
t wo billion passionate fans of all ages and eve ry
imaginable social,cultural,ethnic, national,politi-
c a l ,i d e o l o gical and religious affil i at i o n .All the sym-
bolic might of sport was on display—the ability to
transcend divisive issues and generate intense,
spontaneous and widely-shared emotion. H ow is
it possible that a mere football match can creat e
such high drama?
Passion of this kind no longer surp rises anyo n e .
Yet huge intern ational sports gat h e rings are only
recent eve n t s. The first modern Olympic Games
were held in 1896 and the first football World Cup
in 1930.At the end of the 19th century, sport was
a pastime reserved for the upper classes of ri c h
c o u n t ri e s ,but between 1920 and 1940 the situat i o n
changed drastically. S p o rt was gi ven more and more
press and radio cove r a g e , became ve ry popular and
was skilfully exploited by the authorities for politi-
cal purposes.
Fascist Italy and then Nazi Germany were the
first to make use of it. Exploited by the Nazis for
propaganda purp o s e s , the 1936 Olympic Games
in Berlin marked the start of the modern era of
sport as a spectacle.The Berlin games are still stu-
died as an example of the way in which crowds can
be lured and fa s c i n ated by spectacular eve n t s.T h e y
launched the tradition of grandiose and finely
o r c h e s t r ated sporting events which bring prestige to
the organizing country.
Hyping up
the supporters
But dictat o rships have not been the only
r e gimes to use sport to promote nat i o n a l i s m .S i n c e
the end of the Second World War, sporting events
h ave helped countries win intern ational promi-
nence and build up national identity. E ve ry new
state creates its own national sports teams. During
the annual sporting calendar,patriotic feelings are
Dismay in Copacabana,in Rio de Janeiro, after Brazil’s defeat by France 
in the final of the soccer World Cup, 1998.
regularly called on to support a team or a cham-
p i o n . Political and economic interests and the
media can use the powerful symbol of sport to rally
c i t i z e n s ,c u s t o m e rs and spectat o rs around a sense of
national belonging.
Sporting events help people that they belong
to a community.To take part, you join one of the
groups of spectators behind each of the two com-
peting teams, and share the emotions of your fel-
low supporter s. During the match, your sense of
identity is mobilized on behalf of your national,
village or neighbourhood team, whichever the
case may be.This passionate feeling of together-
ness and partisan commitment is the core of
spectator sports.
These big events bring together (tele)viewe rs
who sometimes have only one thing in common—
the desire to see a clash between two sides which will
produce a single winner. Such is the hierarchical
n ature of sport . Getting together to see a sport i n g
e vent always brings with it the hope that we w i l l
b e at t h e m. The sense of community is based on
rivalry and opposition to others.The main thing is
that everyone is united against the other side.
The us-against-them attitude is built up in all
the talk and media hype that precede the event and
at t ri bute meanings to it.This build-up is the cru c i a l
element in the process of bri n ging people together.
I t ’s also the most unconscious one.The meaning of
the event is defined by what is said before it takes
place.A feeling of solidarity mounts as the big day
approaches.
The World Cup in France was built up in this
way over two ye a rs. O f t - r e p e ated slogans conv i n c e d
people that this was “a chance for France”, w i t h o u t
explaining why. E x h o rt ations to back the nat i o n a l
team found their way into all kinds of fields—in
and the e c s t a s y
An us-against-them attitude is
built up in all the talk and media
hype that precede the event and
attribute meanings to it. This
build-up is the crucial element in
the process of bringing people
together. It’s also the most
unconscious one.
The success 
of the A t l a n t a
Olympics (1996) 
“will have an
e n o rm o u s, p o s i t i ve
impact on wh at
A m e ricans all over 
this country will
b e l i eve we can do.
And goodness know s
we need it.”
President Bill Clinton
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
n
The British novelist Alan Sillitoe once wrote
t h at “ s p o rt is a means of keeping the nat i o n a l
s p i rit alive during a time of so-called peace. I t
prepares the national spirit for the eventuality of
wa r ” .
Some have argued otherwise, maintaining that
s p o rt can be invaluable in bri d ging gaps of intern at i o n a l
u n d e rs t a n d i n g . C e rtainly there can be little doubt
t h at sport tends to bring together athletes of otherwise
hostile nations or communities. D u ring the Cold Wa r ,
ice hockey playe rs of the Soviet Union and the United
S t ates had a sincere affection for each other, d e s p i t e
their fierce ri va l ry on the ri n k .But does sport also bri n g
together the communities to which the sport s m e n
belong or does it rather reinforce longstanding hosti-
lities and ri va l ri e s ?
W h e n e ver there is a cricket mat c h* b e t ween India
and Pa k i s t a n , for example, the fans on both sides fin d
it difficult to separate national pride from an aesthetic
a p p r e c i ation of the game. For these two postcolonial
cousins have fought three wa rs in the fifty ye a rs since
they became free and neighbouring nat i o n s.At the pre-
sent time they fight a shadow war over Kashmir,a ter-
ri t o ry claimed by both. H ow fa r , if at all, do these
deep political hostilities spill over into the cricket fie l d ?
C ri c k e t , a game of British ori gi n , has a passionat e
f o l l owing in both countri e s.With the possible excep-
tion of the cinema, c ricket reaches out to more
people than any other form of entertainment in
the subcontinent. E ve ry match played by the
n ational team is followed by hundreds of millions of
fa n s , and the playe rs themselves have iconic stat u s.
O ver the past half-century, India and Pa k i s t a n
30 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
Batting for the   n
How far has
p o l i t i c a l
a c r i m o n y
between India
and Pa k i s t a n
spilled over
onto the cricke t
fie l d ?
* Indian sociologist,historian and
columnist based in Bangalore
(India).Author of several books
on social history and on cricket.
p o l i t i c s ,s p o rt , the media, a d ve rtising and even lite-
r at u r e . The foundations of victory were laid as a
sense of national awareness was creat e d , gr a d u a l l y
uniting in support of this particular cause French
people who were in other respects divided.“ S p o n-
t a n e o u s ”o u t bu rsts of collective joy were prepared
months before the competition began. The end-
less hype created the event just as much as the
e vent had created the hy p e .
We are
the champions!
The scenes of popular jubilation showed how
people identified themselves with the winners. By
defeating Brazil, the French players beat the team
considered the best in the world. By a mysterious
alchemy, all the French and their supporters also
became “the best”. “We are the champions . . . of
the world,” they chanted.They had proved them-
selves better than the best,i.e.the losers,who were
only mentioned during the long night of celebrat i o n
in terms of the humiliation inflicted on them.A g a i n
and again people raised one, t wo and then three
fingers as they savoured the 3-0 score.The delight
of one side was a counterpoint to the other’s grief.
“ We ” were triumphant and all-powe r f u l . “ T h e y ”
no longer existed,except as a foil.
By pulling off such an historic feat,the French
football team were able to rally behind them an all-
inclusive France of “Blacks,Whites and Beurs”1.
But this was a transient phenomenon which faded
as the excitement died away. Other  sporting eve n t s
would bring people together in the same way.
W h at ’s more, this kind of seemingly inoffensive
j u b i l ation actually harbours tensions which become
more acute when competition in sport provides a
pretext for them. S p o rting events can spark vio-
lence which homes in on the “enemy”of a threate-
ned or humiliated “us”.“They”become the focus
of collective hatred because of their commitment to
the opposing side.
The competition invo l ved in sport generat e s
and channels passions on the basis of winners and
l o s e rs. For their own support e rs , the playe rs are the
personification of all kinds of talents and qualities,
including viri l i t y.The opposing team and their sup-
p o rt e rs are characterized as practitioners of all kinds
of vices and taunted as “the weaker sex”.
So the result of a sporting encounter goes hand
in hand with a fantasy of male dominat i o n , a n d
s p e c t ator sport symbolizes the endless struggle bet-
ween groups of human beings, r ather than their
alleged fraternal instincts. It doesn’t take much for
jubilation to degenerate into violence where “any-
thing goes”. n
Ramachandra Guha*
1. Beurs: second generation North African immigrants.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 31
The spell of sport
h ave played each other at cricket much less frequently
than they have other countri e s. B e t ween 1961 and
1978 they did not play any matches at all. B e t we e n
1978 and 1989 there were regular exchanges of cri c k e t
t e a m s ,with India and Pakistan each touring the other
c o u n t ry three times. Since 1989 they have chosen to
p l ay against one another only on “ n e u t r a l ”t e rri t o ry —
the Gulf emirate of Sharjah,A u s t r a l i a ,e ven Canada.
F i n a l l y, early this year a tour of India was planned by
the Pakistan cricket team.
The visit was bitterly opposed by the extremist
right-wing politician Bal T h a c k e r ay, whose Shiv Sena
p a rty rules the city of Mumbai,generally considered
the home of Indian cri c k e t .T h a c k e r ay claimed it
would be “ u n p at ri o t i c ” to allow Pakistan to play
c ricket on Indian soil while that country was spon-
s o ring “ t e rr o ri s m ” in Kashmir.The Shiv Sena dug up
the pitch at Delhi, where a Test match was to be
p l aye d , and issued threats that they would phy s i-
cally attack the Pakistani cri c k e t e rs if they came.
Despite this opposition, the tour went ahead.Te s t
matches were played at Chennai in southern India
and in Delhi, with tight security and massive crow d s
in attendance, and without any incident. Pakistan
won in Chennai and India in Delhi.T h e n ,h owe ve r ,
the two teams moved on to Calcutta to play the firs t
m atch of an Asian Test Championship (in which the
third part i c i p ating team is Sri Lanka). In a closely-
fought contest, Pakistan wo n , but only after a
c o n t r ove rsial decision by the umpire had ru l e d
against the brilliant Indian cricketer, Sachin Ten-
d u l k a r.This led to an outpouring of protest from the
c r ow d , the throwing of bottles onto the field and the
suspension of play. The last stages of the mat c h
were played before an empty stadium.
Great expectations
On the field and off it, the cri c k e t e rs of Pa k i s t a n
and India are brought together by a shared lan-
guage (Hindustani) and a shared regional culture.
When they play for a World XI, the Indian and
Pakistani cri c k e t e rs room together.Among the fa n s ,
t o o, the genuine cricket lover appreciates fine bow-
ling or batsmanship by the other side. W h e n e ve r
Pakistan play England,or any other third country,
Indian cricket love rs tend to support Pa k i s t a n .T h u s
when India were knocked out early in the 1992
World Cup, and Pakistan went on to win, m o s t
Indians felt “at least the Cup came to Asia”.
All the same, there is little doubt that when the two
c o u n t ries play against each other, s p o rt is made to carry
the baggage of pat ri o t i s m .P r o fic i e n cy at sport ,e s p e-
cially cri c k e t , is made to stand in for failure in other
s p h e r e s. India and Pakistan are both poor countri e s ,
but victory on the sporting field can, in the minds of
the insecure pat ri o t , make up for that . In the light of
present trends, India and Pakistan have little hope of
joining the league of the wo r l d ’s prosperous nat i o n s.
But they might again be world champions in cri c k e t ,
as India was in 1983 and Pakistan was in 1992.At the
individual level too, each country has produced some
of the wo r l d ’s finest cri c k e t e rs.
In both India and Pa k i s t a n , the cri c k e t e rs themselve s
are made to bear the brunt of an intensified nat i o n a l i s m .
When India won against Pakistan in the quarter fin a l s
of the 1996 World Cup, the defeated team went back
home in fear.The home of their captain,Wasim A k r a m ,
was attacked by angry fa n s.Questions were asked in the
Pakistani Parliament alleging that the loss was delibe-
r at e ,t h at the playe rs had been bribed to lose.The cri c-
k e t e rs had of course tried their best,but on the day the
other team played better.
These feelings are replicated amongst émigr é
communities too. For more than a decade now the
Gulf emirate of Sharjah has hosted a cricket tour-
nament in which both India and Pakistan part i c i p at e .
For the last three years the two countries have also
annually played a series of five matches in Toronto.
It has been well documented that patriotic feelings
are often exaggerated among diasporic communities,
who yearn for their homeland as they do not com-
pletely assimilate in their country of residence. C e r-
tainly the cricket fans in Sharjah and Toronto bear
ample testimony to this.
Sequel of Partition
W h at are the roots of this nationalism? Hindu and
Islamic chauvinists on either side, as well as some
We s t e rn commentat o rs , tend to represent the confli c t
in religious term s. I would stress that its roots are
p ri m a rily terri t o rial rather than religi o u s. A l t h o u g h
Pakistan is an Islamic stat e , India also has a substan-
tial Muslim populat i o n .I n d e e d , some of India’s fin e s t
c ri c k e t e rs have been Muslims, including the present
captain of the national team, Mohammed A z h a-
ru d d i n .The genesis of confli c t , on the cricket field or
e l s e w h e r e , must be explained otherwise.
On the Pakistan side, it is the fact that India is seen
as the huge and sometimes ove r b e a ring Big Bro-
ther of the region, a country that throws its weight
around. On the Indian side, it is the memory that
Pakistan ori gi n ated in a movement for secession,
t h at in the ori ginal vision of Indian nationalism both
lands were to be part of one nat i o n . Independence in
August 1947 also meant Pa rt i t i o n .Through cri c k e t ,
t h e r e f o r e , the smaller nation of Pakistan can hope to
challenge the political weight of India. Indian nat i o-
nalists, for their part, have never completely recon-
ciled themselves to the existence of Pakistan as a sepa-
r ate political entity.They thus tend to see in cri c k e t i n g
v i c t o ry an affirm ation of the illegi t i m a cy of the
demand for breaking up India.
So should there be further cricketing contacts bet-
ween India and Pakistan? Is cricket a means of taming
n ational tensions,or is it rather a way of stoking the fir e s
of aggr e s s i ve nationalism? One cannot,a l a s ,a n swer this
question unambiguously either way.For sport unites bu t
it also divides, and in this case cricket is made to carry
the burden of national expectat i o n . I n e v i t a b l y, t h i s
becomes more intense when Pakistan and India play
one another.A section of the fans cannot forget the poli-
tical animosities, and take a mere game far more
s e riously than they should. n
e   nation
* C ricket is a game played by
t wo teams of 11 playe rs on a
field with a wicket at either
end of a 22-yard pitch.T h e
object is for one team to score
runs by hitting a ball while the
other tries to dismiss them by
b ow l i n g, c atching or ru n n i n g
them out. E d i t o r
“ S e rious sport 
has nothing to do 
with fair play.
It is bound up with
h at re d ,j e a l o u s y,
b o a s t f u l n e s s,
d i s re ga rd of all ru l e s
and sadistic pleasure 
in witnessing 
v i o l e n c e : in other
wo rds it is war minus
the shooting.”
George Orwell
February 1995:Indian police order spectators
out of Calcutta’s Eden Gardens ground after disruptions
during a match between India and Pakistan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
A Cuban mix of muscle
and ideology Marcos Bustillo*
n
“ We owe 38 ye a rs of sporting achievement to the
unconditional backing Cuban sport has receive d
from the revo l u t i o n a ry Gove rnment and especially
from our commander-in-chief Fidel Castro,”s ays Hum-
b e rto Rodríguez, President of the National Institute
for Sport ,P hysical Education and Recreation of Cuba
( I N D E R ) , founded in 1961.The results speak for them-
s e l ve s. With only 11 million inhabitants and despite
s e vere economic cri s i s ,Cuba came fifth in the Olympic
medal rankings at Barcelona in 1992, and eighth at
Atlanta in 1996. At the Pa n - A m e rican leve l , it ranks
s e c o n d , after the United Stat e s.
“Mass invo l vement in sport and highly effic i e n t
s t ructures have made it possible for big stars to emerge,”
s ays Norge Marr e r o,n ational commissioner for row i n g .
Cuba has 31,700 physical education instru c t o rs , one for
e ve ry 458 inhabitants, compared with one teacher for
e ve ry 42 pers o n s , and one doctor for eve ry 170. Fo r
1 9 9 9 , the budget for sport is 125 million Cuban pesos
(the same figure in U. S . d o l l a rs at the official rat e ,
although the semi-official rate is 20 to the dollar), w h i c h
is equivalent to the budget for culture and science.
“ S p o rt is part of the people’s culture,” M a rrero adds,
“because people have learned that sport means quality
of life and health.”
H i g h e r ,s t r o n g e r , faster . . . and more revo l u t i o n a ry.
Outside the sports arena, a Cuban athlete may be
t r e ated as a prince or a villain, depending on an ima-
gi n a ry borderline traced by his own loyalty to the
s t at e .The boxer Te ó filo Steve n s o n , Olympic champion
in 1972, 1976 and 1980, was admitted to the “revo-
lutionary hall of fame” because he rejected lucrative
professional contracts abroad. A different fate has
awaited other eminent sportsmen and wo m e n ,
mostly baseball players, who, having opted for the
t e m p t ations of professional status and for exile,
have had their names struck off the official roster.
Desertions are a thorn in the revolution’s side.
But according to Rodríguez,Cuban sport “ c a n n o t
ignore a century marked by globalization and neo-libe-
r a l i s m ” . The champion of amat e u ri s m , it has been
forced willy-nilly to wade into a sea of professionalism
and excessive commercializat i o n .After the collapse of
its main partner and backer, the Soviet Union, C u b a
has begun a process of cautious transform at i o n ,o p e-
ning the door to certain aspects of the market economy.
As a consequence of the hard ye a rs of crisis (1989-
1 9 9 3 ) , when gross domestic product (GDP) fell pre-
cipitously by some 37 per cent, most of the island’s
11,000 sports facilities suffered serious deteri o r at i o n
and even the nutritional system in its training centres
was affected. In order to find a way out, Cuba has
devised a complex system that enables it to obtain eco-
nomic resources through Cubadeport e s , an enter-
p rise set up in 1991 under the authority of INDER.
Drumming up funds
The chief function of Cubadeportes is to seek
funding for Cuban sport .At present its main source
of income, the amount of which is not publicly dis-
closed, is provided by some 600 trainers who are
spread over four continents. It has also introduced
a new scheme whereby leading Cuban sports fig u r e s
are prepared to take up temporary contracts in vo l-
leyball clubs in Italy, basketball clubs in Argentina
and handball clubs in France and Hungary.
F i rst-class athletes are considered privileged com-
pared with the run of the populat i o n .They can win
p rizes in dollars or in kind (cars and apartments) in
exchange for a contri bution to the state for its support
in terms of training, board and lodgi n g .There are no
o f ficial figures for the income of sportsmen and
wo m e n , but it is reckoned that a member of a nat i o n a l
team is paid about 500 Cuban pesos a month ($25 at
the semi-official rat e ) , while the average monthly
wage of a Cuban worker is about $11.
J u d ging by the results achieved in intern at i o n a l
c o m p e t i t i o n s , Cuban muscle serves the ideals of the
r e vo l u t i o n .S p o rt is a jewel that is proudly shown to
the outside world and acts as an incentive within the
c o u n t ry. In the words of Rodríguez, its challenge is
“to enhance the role of the individual, by prov i d i n g
a better grasp of patriotic values and of national
identity”. n
* Journalist in Havana,Cuba
Working out:sport is part of
young Cubans’ daily routine.
Sport, a mainstay of Cuba’s socialist Government,
seeks to affirm ‘patriotic values and national identity’
© Sarah Caron/Gamma, Paris
“Do you know 
wh at my fa vo u rite 
part of the game is? 
The opportunity 
to play.”
American footballer
Mike Singletary
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 33
The spell of sport
The USSR used its mighty, gold medal-winning sports machine 
to help build patriotism. Now, the new republics of the former Soviet empire
are trying the same trick. So far, to no avail
New players, same game
Lincoln Allison*
n
The former Soviet Union today is a land of
ove r gr own pitches, broken goal posts and bent
basketball hoops.The widespread decrepitude
is a dismal reminder that Soviet sport was an arti-
ficial construction shaped to state purposes.
Abandoning Soviet disdain for “ b o u r g e o i s ”
s p o rt , in the 1940s Stalin invested massively in a pro-
gramme to develop athletic excellence.The overt
r e a s o n , as with the space progr a m m e , was to
demonstrate the capacities of the Soviet system to
the rest of the world. In fact, the more important
effect was probably in the “near abroad” of the
fourteen non-Russian Soviet republics, where the
regime encouraged people to be patriotic towards
both their particular national culture and towards
the much larger “Soviet Motherland”.
In short,gold medals were used to bring cohe-
sion to a disparate empire marked by ethnic and
inter-regional tensions.
Premier Olympic power
The policy wo r k e d .S oviet sporting success in the
Olympic Games was massive : the USSR headed the
medals table in the summer games on seven out of
eight occasions between 1952 and 1980. It is true
that this success did not extend much beyond the
O l y m p i c s : when it came to sports that existed pro-
fessionally in the West the USSR either underper-
formed (as in soccer) or failed to develop at all (as
in golf). But the Olympics were able to sell them-
s e l ves as the wo r l d ’s premier sporting event and the
S oviet Union was able to sell itself as the wo r l d ’s pre-
mier Olympic power.
When the political edifice collapsed so did its
sports system.
Now the new republics are once again flirting
with the idea of investing in sport as a means of bu i l-
ding a national identity. People in the Republic of
Georgia, for example, have often been shocked to
d i s c over that We s t e rn e rs know almost nothing about
them. In their own minds their nation has been a
cradle of European and Christian civilization, the
place where wine,cultivated wheat and alphabetic
w riting all ori gi n at e d .T h at most people in the We s t
a s s o c i ate “ G e o r gi a ” with Atlanta rather than T b i l i s i
is deeply depressing to Georgians.
Eduard Shevardnadze, President of the Repu-
blic of Georgi a , once remarked that a single football
m atch could highlight the existence of the Georgi a n
nation as nothing else could.
In this context, the qualifying competition for the
1998 World Cup, in which Georgia was in the same
group as England and Italy, was an import a n t
opportunity to put the country on the mental map
of many people in the West.Visiting Tbilisi for the
g a m e , I was impressed by the sense that Georgi a n s
had few aspirations to win or qualify, but were des-
perate to put on a good show.
But it seems the decline of sports in the form e r
S oviet Union will be virtually impossible to reve rs e ,
and sports will not prove to be a tool for political
purposes in the new republics. The reason is that
identification with national teams cuts no ice in a
context of economic collapse and ethnic hatred.
When interviewing people recently in the Repu-
blic of Georgi a , I found that there was no gr a s s r o o t s
sporting culture capable of keeping things going.
F u rt h e rm o r e , the vo l u n t a ry principle which sustains
sport at grassroots level in the West was a concept
that people did not even understand.
The exceptions will be in highly commercial
sports where there are still good coaches and large
sums of money to be made in the new global labour
market for successful playe rs : football and tennis are,
p e r h a p s , the prime examples. There is, by local
standards,enormous money to be made from the
sale of local players to the West and by competing
in European competitions.
For now, in Georgia at least, it seems that the
only real hope is that outsiders will come to the
rescue. “We will have great athletes and coaches
a g a i n ,” I was repeatedly told in my Georgian trave l s ,
“when the capitalists come and invest money in
our sports facilities and training programmes.” n
* Director, the Warwick Centre for
the Study of Sport,UK
Young Georgian footballers
training outside the national
stadium.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
n
It’s a modern phenomenon, which only deve-
loped at the end of the 1930s, when football,
hitherto the reserve of a select group, became
a mass sport . The game spread and grew in the
1960s and 1970s and its fans got yo u n g e r. T h e
average football supporter today is aged between 15
and 25.And for some time now, it hasn’t just been
a specifically British phenomenon. Fa n atical devo-
tion to a team, and sometimes to a sporting hero, h a s
steadily taken hold on all five continents. Suppor-
ters’mania is now universal,with pretty much the
same motives and forms eve ry w h e r e , but it still
springs from local roots.
Different styles of football derive from distinc-
tive body movements established in different cul-
t u r e s. The names gi ven to support e rs va ry from
place to place and sum up the way they behave .T h e
word “ s u p p o rt e r ” , used by the English and then the
F r e n c h , c o nveys the idea of force and backing
behind a team.The Brazilian t o r c e d o r screws up his
face in wo rry as a match proceeds.The Italian t i fo s i
s u f f e rs from t i fo, an illness marked by fever and
twitchiness.
Initiation into this brotherhood can come very
e a r l y, from the moment a fat h e r , an uncle, a brother
or a godfather gi ves a newborn child the jersey of a
favourite team.It can also happen later on,while a
child is growing up. With neighbours and school-
m at e s , he plays football in the street or with a team,
listens to or watches match reports, discusses the
game with friends and finally goes to the stadium
himself.
Once there, he—and more and more she—and
an older relative will go and join the group of sup-
p o rt e rs who back the same team as they do.The ri va l
fans face each other in the stands behind one  of the
g o a l m o u t h s. The energy they generat e , t h r o u g h
new collective emotions and forms of expression,
produces new identities of class, neighbourhood,
region,religion and country.
Until not so long ago, the layout of the stadiums
h e l ped all this along. S p e c t at o rs packed into big open
areas on the edge of the pitch, and terraces without
numbered seats. Modern stadiums have become
more comfortable, and security measures tend to
put a damper on collective emotions. But although
violence still persists,it is orchestrated,as the fans
sing, chant slogans and shout witticisms or insults
at the other side’s playe rs and the referee. A spot of
c r e at i ve stage management and choreogr a p hy turn s
it into a sort of carnival.
The spectacle of the match enables the sup-
p o rt e rs to experience a moment when a society
becomes aware of itself, when a coherent gr o u p
expresses its identity through non-religious ri t u a l s.
The fans are drawn to stadiums because both the
match and the spectacle that goes with it have the-
rapeutic and cathartic functions,which are vital in
modern urban industrial society, where people are
obliged to exercise great self-discipline and always
hide their feelings. A sporting event provides an
outlet because it teaches a person to develop a
controlled expression of emotions which have to be
curbed in other circumstances.
“A society which doesn’t gi ve its members ,
especially young people, sufficient opportunity to
e n j oy the excitement of a contest which can, but not
n e c e s s a ri l y, i nvo l ve physical strength and bodily
s k i l l s , is in danger of making their lives overly dull,”
wrote the German sociologist Norbert Elias. “ S u c h
a society will not provide the appropri ate sat i s f y i n g
c o m p e n s ation for the humdrum tensions generat e d
by normal daily life.” n
All together!
Sergio Leite Lopes*
A Brazilian soccer 
fan in France to support 
his team,beaten in the 1998
World Cup final.
* Federal University of 
Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
Being in a football stadium means you can
sing, shout, jeer, swear and leap around—
working off feelings you repress elsewhere.
Even better, you’re in a crowd
‘Such a society will not provide
the appropriate satisfying
compensation for the humdrum
tensions generated by normal
daily life’
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 35
The spell of sport
n
The best account of what it means to be a foot-
ball fan has been written by English wri t e r
Nick Hornby, who describes in his book Fever
Pitch his relationship with Arsenal, the long-esta-
blished London football club that plays in Englan-
d ’s Premier League. I t ’s like being marri e d .But not
like today’s marriages, which don’t last as long as
c o u rt s h i p. N o, this is a stri c t , s p a rt a n ,V i c t o ri a n ,
t i l l - d e at h - d o - u s - p a rt kind of marri a g e .“A holy mar-
ri a g e ,” s ays the Dominican singer Juan Luis Guerr a
in his song “Like a bee in the honeycomb”.
I t ’s also a marriage in which there’s no place for
i n fid e l i t y. In Colombia, a fan of Bogotá’s Santa Fe
team is never going to have a two - week affair with
M i l l o n a ri o s , the city’s other big team.At the outside
he might have a furt i ve and fleeting platonic rela-
tionship with teams from other cities, such as Depor-
t i vo Cali, Unión Magdalena or Júnior de Barr a n-
q u i l l a . But such innocent betrayals end abruptly on
the day when these teams play Santa Fe .
The fan behaves like an exe m p l a ry husband.
He is tender and tru e . He accepts his team’s defects
just as a husband accepts that his wife is not as slim
as she was the day he fell in love with her, or that she
snores, has dark circles under her eyes, or pulls a
long face for 18 hours of the day. There may be
short-lived outbursts of fury when the team plays
b a d l y. (Santa Fe have gone twenty ye a rs without
winning a title.) Except for his angry comments on
p l aye rs who are slow on the turn or incapable of
defending the team’s colours.The fan always ends
up in the stadium, a lways accompanies his team
through thick and thin and always cheers them on
with the refrain: “Olé oléolá/I love you more and
more each day.”
Spine-tingling
sensations
And just as the husband pays all the household
bills without flinching even though he may think
t h e y ’re outrageously high, the fan squanders his
wealth on the team. And how! In the past he just
had to pay for tickets. Not any more. Now he also
has to put his hand in his pocket to buy his team’s
T-shirt (its design and manufacturer change every
six months or so but he has to have the latest one),
its scarf, banner, the official record of the suppor-
ters’songs.
And what does he get in return? A lot of intan-
gibles that only the true fan can really appreciat e .A
sense of tribal belonging that’s like no other expe-
rience in the wo r l d , whether it’s an electoral vic-
t o ry, a rock concert with a 100,000-strong audience
or a military victory.T h at tingling in the spine whe-
n e ver your team scores a goal or wins a mat c h
against its time-honoured enemy gi ves way to an
i n d e s c ribable sensation that can last for day s , if not
ye a rs. In 1992 Santa Fe beat Millonarios 7 : 3 .E ve n
t o d ay it’s an unforgettable memory for the suppor-
t e rs of the reds and they rub it in whenever they
meet fans of the blues.
It’s a reason for clinging on to life:I can’t ima-
gine dying without knowing which team is going
to win this ye a r ’s championship or how many goals
we ’re going to beat Millonarios by the next time
we play them. It doesn’t matter whether yo u ’ ve cho-
sen the right team (Atletico de Bilbao or Real Socie-
d a d , Boca Juniors or River Plat e , Inter or AC Milan,
A rsenal or Tottenham Hotspur), your football team
is neither more nor less than the love of your life.
n
The trials and tribulations 
of a Colombian soccer fan
T i l l d e a t h do us part
Eduardo Arias *
World Cup 1998:
Colombian supporters
cheer on their team 
against Romania.
* Journalist and supporter of Deportivo Independiente Santa Fe
Football Club, Bogotá,Colombia
‘Olé oléolá/I love you more
and more each day’
In 1994 the Pre s i d e n t
of Brazil ord e red thre e
days of nat i o n a l
m o u rning after 
the death of ra c i n g
d ri ver Ayrton Senna.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
Thai boxing fans 
are hooked on gambling 
as much as the niceties of
their favourite sport
n
For the past 20 ye a rs , Sialek Chanarak,a 53-ye a r -
old shop-ow n e r , has spent nearly eve ry Fri d ay
night at Bangkok’s Lumpini Stadium, one of
T h a i l a n d ’s two top arenas for Muay T h a i , or T h a i
k i c k b ox i n g .“I don’t like box i n g,” Sialek insists as he
leafs through a wad of baht,T h a i l a n d ’s curr e n cy. “ I
come to gamble. If there was no gambling here, I
would never come.”Sialek is not alone. Of the 10,000
people who jam into the ramshackle stadium,n e a r l y
all are betting on the battles in the ri n g .“Only the tou-
rists don’t bet,” Sialek say s , pointing to the ri n g s i d e
s e ats occupied by Japanese and European visitors.
M a ny of the foreign women are cri n ging as the
b oxe rs pummel each other, d i g ging knees into their
opponents groins and launching rapid-fire kicks
cracking against skin and bone.
M u ay  Thai is T h a i l a n d ’s national sport .A mart i a l
competition developed from the hand-to-hand combat
techniques of ancient Siamese soldiers , it seems similar
at first to intern ational box i n g .F i g h t e rs wear gloves for
three-minute rounds held in boxing ri n g s.After that ,
the similarities end. K i c k i n g, kneeing and elbow i n g
your opponent are all legal, as is pushing and throw i n g
him to the canva s.Then there is the music: a three-
piece band comprised of dru m s , cymbals and the
j ava pipe plays frenetic, ancient Thai battle music to
urge the fig h t e rs on.
A fatal
attraction
M u ay Thai has been deemed so integral a part of
Thai character that the National Culture Commis-
sion ove rsees its promotion. The Ministry of Edu-
c ation runs a Muay Thai Institute to teach the intri-
cacies of the sport . And the army runs Lumpini
Stadium and the World Muay Thai Council, t h e
s p o rt ’s gove rning body. But Muay Thai pales in
p o p u l a rity beside another national pastime: g a m-
b l i n g . Simply put,Thais love to bet. Police have esti-
m ated that billions of baht are wagered by T h a i s
each week on English Premier League Fo o t b a l l
a l o n e .U n d e r ground casinos operate with impunity
in Bangkok.And the country ’s most famous Buddhist
monk attracts thousands of devotees who believe
t h at if he whacks them on the head with a rolled up
n e w s p a p e r , they might win the national lottery.
S t i l l , millions of Thai boys and young men have
a passion for MuayThai.Like boxing anywhere,it
provides a flickering hope they can fight their way
out of pove rt y.A major match at Lumpini can earn
100,000 baht, or about $2,500, with boxe rs fig h t i n g
May the betting man win...
Robert Horn and Thaskina Khaikaew*
on average once a month. A purse that size is a
f o rtune to the young fa rm e rs and fa c t o ry hands
dreaming of kicking their way out of hardscrabble
fields or the squalor of Bangkok’s slums. But it’s
nothing compared to the money changing hands in
the stands at Lumpini and other stadiums.
“ I ’ ve won as much as 800,000 baht (over $20,000)
on one fig h t .But I also once lost a million ($27,000),”
s ays Chat ri Kanchanamanoon, the 50-year-old ow n e r
of a gold shop. But Chat ri ’s losses are relat i vely mild
compared to that of his best fri e n d .“He bet a huge sum
of money and he got too excited,”s ays Chat ri .“He wa s
c h e e ring his fighter and suddenly fell on the flo o r.H e
had a heart attack and died.”
Most bets these day s ,h owe ve r ,a r e n ’t as heart - s t o p-
pingly large since the country ’s economy crashed in
July 1997.And the gambling fatalities are not all from
n atural causes. C h at ri says that some gamblers who
c o u l d n ’t pay their debts have been killed.
As the fighters knee and elbow each other,
screaming fans stand atop wooden benches or surge
against the green chain link fences that separate the
different ticket sections. I t ’s in between rounds,
though, that the action really heats up. While the
boxers catch their breath, the gamblers wave their
a rms and wiggle their fin g e rs in an intri c ate system
of signals that lets the bookies know how much
they want to bet on which fighter at what odds.
There is a slim minority of fans like Paisan Phak-
d e e s u n t h o rn , who abstain from betting.“I like Muay
T h a i ,” s ays the 32-year-old civil serva n t , adding that
he used to fight as a teenager.“I don’t have money to
wa s t e ,” he say s , on the “bad habit” of betting. Pa i s a n
c h e e rs on the boxe rs , but like so many other fa n s ,h e
d o e s n ’t have a favo u rite fig h t e r. Paisan seems too
wrapped up in the sport to focus solely on the career
of a single boxe r.G a m b l e rs like Sialek agr e e .“ You can’t
h ave a favo u ri t e . . . .T h at would only interfere,”he say s.
“ You have to bet with your head, not your heart .” n
* Journalists in Bangkok,
Thailand
For Thai boys, learning 
the basics of Muay Thai 
is part of growing up.
“ T h e re are people wh o
think that wrestling is
an ignoble sport.
W restling is not sport,
it is a spectacl e, and it
is no more ignoble to
attend a wre s t l e d
p e r fo rmance of
s u f fe ring than a
p e r fo rmance of the
s o rrows of A rnolphe or
A n d ro m a q u e.”
Roland Barthes,
French literary critic 
and semiologist
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
m i l i t a ry spending by 19 per cent and 12
per cent respective l y. Notable examples in
the low-income group include South A s i a n
c o u n t ri e s , China and some A f rican coun-
t ri e s , and in the middle-income gr o u p
such Mediterranean countries as A l g e ri a ,
L e b a n o n ,S y ria and Tu r k e y. G r owing mili-
t a ry budgets not only eat into spending on
human deve l o p m e n t , but also heighten the
risk that arms will be used to deal with
political cri s e s.
Asia is the continent where the gr owth in
m i l i t a ry expenditure has been strongest.
I n d i a , Pa k i s t a n , S ri Lanka, C h i n a , I n d o-
n e s i a , Ja p a n , M a l ay s i a , M ya n m a r , S i n g a-
p o r e , Ta i wa n ,T hailand and South Korea
h ave all increased their budgets signific a n t l y
in recent ye a rs , although as a rule by a
No farewell Vincenç Fi s a s *
to arms
n
Judging purely by the figures, the
“ d i s a rmament race” which began
after the fall of the Berlin Wall in
1989 appears to have yielded some tan-
gible results. Political détente between the
major powers led not only to the conclu-
sion of agreements for the withdrawal and
destruction of weapons, but also to a
reduction of military expenditure in many
countries.
H owe ve r , careful scru t i ny of the
figures reveals a more complex and para-
doxical picture. It shows that a decade
after the “disarmament” process began
there are conflicting trends, some of
which provide few grounds for optimism.
The reduction effort has not been the
same everywhere.What is more alarming,
many countries and entire regions have
begun to rearm.
World military expenditure has fallen
by about one-third since 1988. In 1997 it
was running at $740 billion (equivalent to
roughly $2 billion a day, or 2.6 per cent of
global GDP, compared with $3 billion a
day at the end of the 1980s).
Contrasting 
trends
The first point to note, however, is
that this reduction is due basically to cuts
made in Europe and in the United States.
And while Europe heads the list with a
drop of over 50 per cent in the last deca-
de (see table), this spectacular decrease is
chiefly due to the reduction which began
in Russia in 1992. In Western Europe, the
reduction in military spending has been
far more modest, around 14 per cent.
The second point is that while the
high-income countries have reduced the
size of their military systems and the cor-
responding expenditure, the low- and
middle-income countries have increased
The great powers might have cut down on military expenditure, but low- and
middle-income countries have boosted their spending. In Asian countries
alone, arms purchases have doubled in four years.
*Holder of the UNESCO Chair of Peace 
and Human Rights at the Autonomous University of
Barcelona,Spain
Tanks ready for the scrapyard at Rockensussra,Germany.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38 The Unesco Courier - April 1999
E T H I C S
An international code of conduct
n
There seems little doubt that the coun-
t ries producing and selling arms have
not resisted the temptation to offset the fa l l
in demand for military equipment from
the industrialized countries with export s
to the Third World, which is nowadays the
scene of most confli c t s. In 1997, i m p o rts of
c o nventional weapons by developing coun-
tries came to almost $19 billion.And bet-
ween 1993 and 1997 the five permanent
member states of the United Nations Secu-
rity Council together accounted for more
than 80 per cent of arms transfers, accor-
ding to SIPRI (Stockholm Intern at i o n a l
Peace Research Institute).
In 1997, in an effort to reve rse this
trend, a Committee of Nobel Peace Prize
Winners, on the initiative of Oscar Arias,
f o rmer President of Costa Rica and winner
of the 1987 Nobel Peace Prize,drafted an
International Code of Conduct on Arms
Tr a n s f e rs , which it will submit to the United
N ations General Assembly in the hope that
it will be adopted as a binding intern at i o n a l
t r e at y. “Our children urgently need schools
and health centres, not machine guns and
fighter planes,” the Committee declared. I n
fa c t , the figure for arms imports by deve l o p i n g
c o u n t ries in 1997 was three times more than
the extra investment needed to provide basic
e d u c ation for all those countri e s ’ c h i l d r e n ,
and one and half times more than what it
would have cost to provide the whole popu-
l ation with basic health services and ade-
q u ate food.C o n s i d e ring that more than half
the countries spend more on defence than on
h e a l t h ,A rticle 10 of the Intern ational Code
s t i p u l ates that “ A rms transfers may be
conducted only if the recipient stat e ’s expen-
ditures on health and education combined
exceed its military expenditures”.
The states usually justify high military
spending on the ground of its deterr e n t
e f f e c t , and hence as a means of guaran-
teeing the security of their citizens. Accor-
ding to the United Nations Development
P r o gramme (UNDP), h owe ve r , the pro-
bability in developing countries of dying
from social neglect is 33 times gr e ater than
that of being killed in a war resulting from
external aggression.
The International Code stipulates that
any country that wishes to acquire arma-
ments must meet certain requirements,
including the promotion of democracy, t h e
protection of human rights and the trans-
p a r e n cy of military expenditure.A c c o r d i n g
to the Committee, i n t e rn ational arms trans-
fers “foster political instability and human
rights violations,prolong violent conflicts,
and weaken diplomatic efforts to resolve
differences peacefully”.
Similar codes of conduct either already
exist or have been proposed within the Orga-
n i z ation for Security and Co-operation in
E u r o p e , the European Union, the United
S t ates and South A f ri c a .These mechanisms
urgently need to be applied at intern at i o n a l
l e ve l , c o n s i d e ring that conventional we a-
p o n s , and light weapons in part i c u l a r ,
continue to cause 90 per cent of the casual-
ties in today ’s armed confli c t s. n
lesser percentage than the rise in their GDP.
A substantial part of the increase has gone
into buying new weapons—expenditure on
a rms purchases doubled between 1994 and
1997.This trend may be expected to slow
d own in the next few ye a rs ,h owe ve r , for two
reasons—the financial crisis that has affected
many of the region’s economies and pres-
sure from the Intern ational Monetary Fund
for these countries to reduce government
expenditure,including military spending.
L atin A m e rica has not escaped the
temptation to rearm.Military expenditure
in South America rose by 14 per cent over
the last decade, notably in Brazil, C h i l e
and Pa r a g u ay. In the last few ye a rs purcha-
sing of new we a p o n s , some extremely
e x p e n s i ve , has also increased. Central A m e-
ri c a , which for decades was one of the
regions worst ravaged by armed conflicts,
constitutes an exception. In the last decade,
it has actually reduced its military expen-
diture by almost 40 per cent following the
conclusion of peace agreements.
In the Middle East, a traditionally lucra-
t i ve market for arms export e rs , m i l i t a ry
spending has also followed an upward trend,
especially in Iran, Saudi Arabia and Syria.
In Africa, on the other hand, only Algeria
and Uganda have increased their military
bu d g e t s , and sub-Saharan A f rica as a whole
has reduced military expenditure by no less
than 46 per cent. But the civil wa rs and
cruel massacres that have occurred throu-
ghout the decade prove once again that the
b rutality of conflicts and the numbers of vic-
tims they claim are not necessarily linked to
the acquisition of sophisticat e d , costly we a-
ponry. The proliferation of light weapons,
easily acquired and inexpensive (500 million
units worldwide) is not sufficiently refle c t e d
in the statistics of military expenditure. It is
enough to point out that 200,000 assault
rifles can be had at discount prices for the
cost of a single fighter plane.
Smaller armies,
new equipment
Variations in military expenditure can
be explained by two major parameters:
the size of armies and the type and quan-
tity of armaments they acquire. Among
the major powers a third factor comes
into play, namely the cost of research and
development in the military sector.
According to the U.S. Arms Control
and Disarmament Agency (ACDA), the
n u m b e rs of military personnel in the
world’s armies fell by some six million
between 1988 and 1995 (to 22.8 million
in 1995),a drop of 20 per cent.This helps
to explain the aggregate reduction in mili-
tary expenditure. There are major diffe-
rences between regi o n s , h owe ve r. T h e
World military
expenditures
(Billions of dollars, constant 1995 prices)
1988 1997 % variation
Africa 12.6 8.8 -30
North 2.2 3.2 +45
Sub-Saharan 10.4 5.6 -46
Americas 410.0 290.0 -29
North 390.0 268.0 -31
Central 0.8 0.5 -39
South 19.2 21.9 +14
Asia 95.0 120.0 +26
East 83.8 106.0 +27
South 11.2 13.6 +22
Europe 500.0 234.0 -53
Middle East 39.6 43.3 +9
Oceania 8.9 8.8 -1
Total 1066.0 704.0 -34
Source: SIPRI (Stockholm International Peace Research Institute),
SIPRI Yearbook 1998, p. 192
d e veloped countries cut their arm e d
forces by more than 35 per cent,the deve-
loping countries by only 10 per cent on
ave r a g e . The percentage reductions in
n u m b e rs in Central A m e rica (60 per
c e n t ) , E a s t e rn Europe (44 per cent),
North America (25 per cent) and Western
Europe (17 per cent) bear a clear relation
to cuts in military budgets.This is not the
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
case, however, in regions such as the
Middle East, which have offset decreased
numbers with the modernization of their
a rmies and purchases of equipment.
Numbers of military personnel increased
slightly in Latin America and South Asia.
Since 1990, military expenditure on
defence equipment has fallen by a quar-
ter. In the countries of the North Atlantic
Treaty Organization (NATO), expenditu-
re on equipment fell by one-third between
1988 and 1997, when it amounted to $95
b i l l i o n . These figures stand in contrast to
the sales of the hundred leading arm s - p r o-
ducing companies which, according to
SIPRI (Stockholm Intern ational Pe a c e
Research Institute) dat a , reached the sub-
s t a n t i a l figure of $156 billion in 1996.
Thirty-nine of the companies, half of
them American, clocked up annual mili-
tary sales in excess of one billion dollars.
SIPRI estimates research and deve-
lopment expenditure at $58 billion in
1995, of which $48 billion were accoun-
ted for by NATO countries ($37 billion
by the United States alone). Since 1989,
this type of expenditure has fallen in most
countries. Three noteworthy exceptions
are Japan, India and South Korea, all
three of which have increased their overall
military spending, in absolute terms, in
the last decade.
Expenditure on research, which chiefly
concerns the nuclear powers, accounts for
14 per cent of total military spending in
the United Stat e s , 11 per cent in France, 9 . 5
per cent in the United Kingdom, 5 per cent
in Russia and around 4 per cent in China.
It accounts for 10 per cent of Swe d e n ’s
military expenditure and more than 5 per
cent of that of India, Germany and South
Africa.All these countries,plus Spain and
A legal weapon
against firearms
The growing number of lawsuits being
brought by Americans seeking damages
from commercial firms has become an effective
way to promote causes on which members of
Congress may be reluctant to legislate, b e c a u s e
they are often dependent on these companies
for election campaign funds.
A New York federal court jury recently set a
precedent by ordering gun manufacturers to
pay $4 million to someone accidentally wounded
in a 1995 shooting incident.The decision, on 11
February 1999,marked the first time that Colt,
Beretta and other arms makers were deemed
guilty of “negligence”for having flooded New
York shops with “dangerous products”. Th e
firms have appealed but many other suits
against them are under wa y, some by city
governments.
The gun manufacturers, b a c ked by the
powerful National Rifle A s s o c i a t i o n , a pressure
group of firearm owners that claims three mil-
lion members, have fiercely opposed all legal
efforts to restrict the ownership and sale of
g u n s. Yet crime figures remain spectacularly
high in the United States.The number of mur-
ders fell from 24,700 in 1991 to 18,200 in
1 9 9 7 , but it is still by far the highest of all the
industrial countries.
The only anti-gun law of recent years was
passed after an epic congressional battle. I t
requires anyone buying a gun to wait five wor-
king days so the seller can check if the buyer has
a criminal record.
Suing for damages has already proved an
effective weapon in the U.S. Consumer groups
have used it successfully as have victims of
asbestosis and the harmful effects of tobacco.
The method is spreading to other countries.
G u a t e m a l a , Nicaragua and Panama recently
brought civil suits against big U. S. tobacco com-
panies in the hope of getting compensation for
the money they have spent to treat people suf-
fering from smoking-related illnesses. n
Ja p a n , account for more than 90 per cent of
world expenditure on armaments research.
What happened 
to the peace dividend?
When the process of reducing military
expenditure began, the idea was for disar-
mament to serve development and for a
“peace dividend” to be created with the
savings that would accrue. What was the
outcome of that commendable initiative?
According to a United Nations Develop-
ment Programme (UNDP) report , the total
“peace dividend” worldwide exceeded $900
billion by the mid-1990s, but “Most of the
savings appear to have been committed to
budget deficit reductions and non-deve-
lopment expenditures”.
The figures presented above also indi-
cate that the “peace dividend” is far from
being a universal phenomenon. Unfortu-
nately it is the countries most in need of
resources for their development that spend
most on military activities, often more than
they spend on health or education (see
box).
It is significant that the latest indicator
used by the Bonn International Center
for Conversion (BICC) to measure the
disarmament effort of a list of 157 coun-
tries shows up negative for 69 of them.
This gives a clear idea of the enormous
effort that is still required. n
Sources: SIPRI  Yearbook 1998;World Military
Expenditures and Arms Transfers 1996 (ACDA,
United States, 1997); Conversion Survey 1998
(BICC, 1998)
Dismantling a nuclear weapon at Amarillo, Texas (USA).
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The Unesco Courier - April 1999
n
In the centre of A l e x a n d ri a , b e t we e n
the eastern port and the unive rs i t y, a
thousand labourers are working night
and day on a huge construction site with
four big cranes. The cylindrical 11-storey
building being built there in the middle of
a lake has been designed by a firm of Nor-
we gian architects, S n ø h e t t a , which won an
i n t e rn ational competition in 1989 that
drew 1,400 entries from 77 countries. Its
circular shape is meant to conjure up,
against the backcloth of the Mediterr a n e a n ,
the image of  “a lighthouse of know l e d g e
re-emerging in a perpetual sunrise”,in the
words of the project’s director-general,
Prof. Mohsen Zahran.
The bu i l d i n g, which should be fin i s h e d
by autumn 1999, will revive the legendary
Bibliotheca Alexandrina (BA).Its promo-
t e rs hope that , with the help of the best
m o d e rn technology, it will spread the intel-
lectual influence of A l e x a n d ria throughout
the Arab world and beyond much more
e f f e c t i vely than its predecessor did at the
time of Caesar and Cleopatra.
The 36,770-square-metre library will
s e at 2,000 people and have up to eight mil-
lion books, p e ri o d i c a l s ,m a n u s c ri p t s ,m i c r o-
films and CD-RO M s. Its computeri z e d
c at a l o g u e , which France is helping to bu i l d ,
will be one of the most advanced in the
world and available in A r a b i c, English and
F r e n c h . Its planetari u m , its Intern at i o n a l
School of Inform ation Studies and its
museums of archaeology, c a l l i gr a p hy and
science are expected to attract students,
s c h o l a rs and visitors from all over the wo r l d .
Books
for a wide public
The idea of reviving the library wa s
born in 1974, when Cambridge-educated
M o s t a fa el-Abbadi, a history professor and
author of a study on the  “Life and Fate of
the Ancient Library of A l e x a n d ri a ” d r e a-
med of resuscitating the “temple of lear-
n i n g ” he had spent so many ye a rs studying.
The president of A l e x a n d ria Unive rs i t y, D r
Lutfi Dow i d a r , backed him and together
they won the support of the Egyptian
government and UNESCO, which funded a
feasibility study and an Internet we b s i t e
(www.bibalex.gov.eg).
El-Abbadi is fairly happy with the way
things have turned out, though he wo u l d
prefer the BA to be just a place for scholars.
It will open its doors to a far wider public,
h owe ve r. “ We don’t want books without
r e a d e rs ,” s ays the writer Gamal el-Ghat a n i ,
editor of Akhbar al-Adab, the weekly lite-
r a ry supplement of the big Cairo daily
newspaper A l - A k h b a r. “Unlike my son, I
d o n ’t know how to use a computer,” h e
c o n f e s s e s.“The A l e x a n d ria Library is being
built for his generation, not mine, but the
public will enjoy it as much as I enjoye d
going to the old national library.”
At the entrance to the building site
stands a slab of A swan granite bearing an
Egyptian hieroglyph, a Chinese ideogr a m ,
an Arabic letter and a Greek “ e ” .The mes-
sage of the granite blocks which make up
the outer walls of the building is clear: t h e
l i b r a ry aims to be a crossroads of alphabets,
words and languages, like the city where it is
l o c at e d . A r c h a e o l o gical digs at the site—a
f o rmer unive rsity car park where work began
in May 1995, s e ven ye a rs after Egyptian Pre-
sident Hosni Mubarak and UN E S C O Di r e c-
t o r -General Fe d e rico Mayor laid the foun-
d ation stone—have shown that it used to be
p a rt of the royal neighbourhood.But no one
k n ows exactly where the old library stood or
w h at it looked like.
A l e x a n d r i a , from  
The Library of Alexandria was A n t i q u i t y ’s most prestigious centre of learning.
Its rebirth may bring a new beacon of knowledge to the A rab world
A project costing over $170 million.
Michel
Arseneault*
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 41
The rebirth of the BA has been enthu-
siastically welcomed abroad. G e rm a ny is
supplying equipment to move documents
and Italy a laborat o ry to restore manus-
c ri p t s. N o r way will provide furniture and
Japan audiovisual equipment. France will
d o n ate a copy of the archives of the old
Suez Canal Company, Turkey will gi ve
10,000 books and Australia will prov i d e
some works of art . About 300,000 books
have been collected so far, a third of them
donated.
A catapult
for development
Fo rmer UN E S C O D i r e c t o r - G e n e r a l
Amadou-Mahtar M’Bow launched a
world-wide appeal in 1987 for the library ’s
revival, saying it would transform the cul-
tural scene in the Middle East and the
c o u n t ries of the Maghreb.The UN E S C O f e a-
sibility study stressed this key role it could
play in the Mediterranean area.
This mission will probably be accompli-
s h e d , reckons project director Prof.Z a h r a n ,
who is a U.S.-trained Egyptian architect.T h e
BA could become “a catapult for the eco-
nomic and social development of Egypt,”h e
s ay s. “A country can have gr e at we a l t h , bu t
if it has no culture, it soon falls apart .” H e
predicts that the BA will become “a bridge of
u n d e rstanding and interaction between East
and We s t . Its revival will benefit humanity.
But we mustn’t think that the child will be a
prodigy from the moment of its birt h .We ’ l l
h ave to wait several decades before we can
see its real influ e n c e .”
E l - G h atani also hopes it will be a bri d g e
b e t ween Egypt and Europe, a continent he
sees as close because it shares the culture
and especially the religions of the Mediter-
ranean basin. “The roots of Europe’s
r e l i gions are right here,” he say s. T h e
A l e x a n d rian writer Edwar al-Kharr at
would like to see Alexandria become “the
capital of collective memory and a have n
for literary figures and scientists.”
More concretely, the BA will enable
E g y p t ’s young people—half the country ’s
p o p u l ation is under 20—to step up the pace
of their studies.According to Zahran, E g y p-
tian students sometimes take four years to
finish a doctorate—twice as long as stu-
dents in the West—because research mat e-
rial is hard to come by.
The first benefic i a ries of the BA will be
the 80,000 or so students at A l e x a n d ri a
U n i ve rs i t y, whose library only has 250,000
works (Egypt’s national library has 1.5 mil-
l i o n ) .S c h o l a rs from all over the Arab wo r l d
could come to A l e x a n d ria instead of or
before going to the United States or Bri-
t a i n . If the BA continues to attract the
attention of foreigners in this way, it will
play an important role.
By bri n ging back documents that we r e
s c attered through We s t e rn countries in the
19th century, the library will enable scho-
  papyrus to the In t e r n e t
A mysterious disappearance
n Alexandria, founded by Alexander the
Great, had a lighthouse that was one of
the seven wo n d e rs of the wo r l d . It was also
the site, from about the third century BC,
of the most famous library of ancient times.
Greek thinkers such as Euclid, P t o l e my
and Dionysius T h r a x , r e s p e c t i vely the
“ i nve n t o rs ” of geometry, map-making and
gr a m m a r , worked there.There too 72 rabbis
t r a n s l ated from Hebrew into Greek the wri-
tings that would come to be know n , at least
by Christians,as the Old Testament.
The library also arranged for passing
ships to be hijacked and relieved of any
m a n u s c ripts they happened to be carry i n g .
Its avowed aim was to own all the books in
the wo r l d . It kept the ori ginals and gave
copies of them back to their owners. The
l i b r a ry ended up with between 500,000
and 700,000 manuscripts, mainly rolls of
p a p y ru s ,t h at were stored in attics after the
most valuable of them had been rolled up in
linen or leather. For about 600 years, they
were kept in a “museum” (in its original
meaning of “temple of the muses”) in the
royal neighbourhood which was the home
of the seve n t h , last and most famous of the
Cleopatras.
It was long thought that this Cleopat r a ’s
first husband,Julius Caesar, whose troops
bu rned down part of A l e x a n d ria in about 48
B C , was responsible for the library ’s demise.
But historians today have other theori e s.T h e
library may have disappeared in the third
c e n t u ry AD during fighting betwe e n
Zenobia,queen of Palmyra,and the forces
of Emperor A u r e l i a n . Or perhaps in the
f o u rth century, when Christians destroye d
“ p a g a n ”w ri t i n g s. Or maybe in the seve n t h
c e n t u ry, when an Arab general occupied
the city and ordered documents to be
burned to heat up the public baths. n
* Canadian journalist in Alexandria,Egypt
l a rs to compare the manuscripts in Egypt
with the copies that are being donated by
foreign benefa c t o rs. An example is the
m a n u s c ripts in the Escurial Palace in
S p a i n , which are a crucial part of Arab heri-
tage and copies of which have been made
for the new library. The BA could also
acquire more recent works which have been
taken out of the Arab wo r l d . The superb
l i t h o graphed books published in Fe z , i n
Morocco, in the 1920s can up to now only
be consulted at Harvard University, in the
U.S.,for example.
Support from
international donors
The BA is due to be officially opened at
the end of this year by President Mubarak,
who will be running for a fourth term of
o f fice in October.Will his opponents cri t i-
cize him for spending so much money on a
fa n cy library when half the country ’s adult
p o p u l ation cannot read or write? Egypt is
E G Y P T
Cairo
Suez Canal
Alexandria
Alexandria will become ‘the capital of collective memory
and a haven for literary figures and scientists’
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
The world’s great
libraries 
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The Unesco Courier - April 1999
African films
in search
of an audience
W hat can be done to ensure that African-
made films are seen by A f r i c a n s ?
Attempts to tackle this problem were made at
workshops organized at this year’s Panafrican
Film and Television Festival (Fespaco) held in
Ouagadougou (Burkina Faso) from 27 Fe b r u a r y
to 6 March.
A solution is needed urgently, for Africa is
rapidly becoming a dustbin for cheap A m e r i c a n
movies, kung fu films, Hindu melodramas and
Latin American soap operas.About 90 per cent
of the films shown at the festival will never be
seen in Africa because “there’s no real distri-
bution network, just importers,” according to
Dominique Wa l l o n ,who has written a report on
the problem for the European Union.
Almost all the market in Fr e n c h - s p e a k i n g
Africa is controlled by African American Films
(AFRAM),which is a subsidiary of MPEAAM, a
powerful Hollywood bridgehead.To get cinema-
owners to take its films, AFRAM gives awa y
copies in exchange for 30-40 per cent of box-
o f fice takings. In contrast, African films have
to be rented at set prices. So it’s Sylvester Stal-
lone and Arnold Schwarzenegger who swa g g e r
across African cinema screens. Small impoveri-
shed neighbourhood cinemas often show just
pirated videos.
But there are pockets of resistance. Came-
roonian producer Bassek Ba Kobhio has been
running a scheme for the past four years called
Écrans Noirs, which distributes African films in
C a m e r o o n ,G a b o n ,C o n g o - B r a z z a v i l l e, the Cen-
tral African Republic and soon Chad,using the
region’s network of French cultural centres.
But cinema managers say the distribution of
African films will have to be subsidized because
they rarely draw big crowds. Nour-Eddine Saïl,
of Canal Plus Horizons, a French company, s a y s
the big television networks should be legally
obliged to fund African film-making. Wa l l o n
thinks governments should build cinemas and
allow the private sector to run them. It remains
to be seen if African governments will take up
these suggestions. n
n L i b r a ries are usually compared on the
basis of how many printed volumes they
c o n t a i n . But this can be deceptive because
c o u n t ries have their own definitions of what
a volume is. M o s c ow ’s state library, f o r
e x a m p l e , counts as a “ vo l u m e ”a ny publica-
tion longer than two pages, including maga-
zines—which produces a total of 30 million
“ vo l u m e s ” , the same number as in the St
Pe t e rs burg library. On the other hand, i n
France a “ vo l u m e ” must contain more than
50 pages and may not be a peri o d i c a l .
The U. S .L i b r a ry of Congr e s s ,f o u n d e d
in Washington in 1800, is considered the
biggest in the wo r l d , with 29 million
vo l u m e s. C h i n a ’s national library in Bei-
jing claims 16 million.These two are fol-
lowed by a group of five, with stocks esti-
m ated at between 10 and 13 million
volumes each. Among them are Harvard
University Library, in the U.S., the New
York Public Library, and the library in
F r a n k f u rt ,G e rm a ny, which opened in 1994.
The British Library in London has
nearly 12 million vo l u m e s. This is about
the same number as the French Stat e
L i b r a ry, which opened in Pa ris in 1996,
includes the contents of the old Biblio-
thèque Nationale (National Library ) , and is
also known as the “ Très Grande Biblio-
thèque”(the “Very Big Library”).
The library in A l e x a n d ri a ,E g y p t ,e ve n-
tually scheduled to contain eight million
wo r k s , will then rank after France’s stat e
l i b r a ry and be in the same group as the libra-
ries in Berlin, Berkeley (California) and the
Romanian A c a d e my in Bucharest. n
f orking out almost two-thirds of the $172
million cost of the building itself. P r o c e e d s
from an intern ational funding appeal, t o
which Arab countries have already generously
c o n t ri bu t e d ,will foot the rest of the bill.
Paradoxes
of the Arab world
“Of course it’s expensive ,” s ays El Gha-
tani,“but a library isn’t some kind of festi-
val that ends after three day s. It would have
cost even more if we’d waited another 30
years to build it.” Its worth should be seen
in terms of culture, not cash, and this, he
b e l i e ve s ,d r aws attention to one of the para-
d oxes of the Arab wo r l d . “The ri c h e s t
culture is in the poorest countri e s — I ’ m
thinking of Yemen—and the richest states
have the least interesting cultural material.
The ru l e rs of the rich states have bu i l t
palaces in Lausanne and Geneva instead
of libraries. But the age of the oil dollar is
coming to an end. We have to return to
more basic values,” he says.
Might the BA encourage democracy —
a concept that ori gi n ated in Greece—in
Egypt and the rest of the region? “ To bu i l d
a democratic stat e ,” s ays archaeologi s t
Ahmed Ahdel Fat t a h , director-general of
the Greco-Roman museum in A l e x a n d ri a ,
“ we need the tools of democracy, a n d
k n owledge is one of them. D e m o c r a cy isn’t
in such bad shape in Egypt, compared with
some of its neighbours. This of cours e
d o e s n ’t stop us saying that we don’t have
e n o u g h .Thank God I was born in Egypt. I
c o u l d n ’t publish my writings in a lot of
other Arab countri e s. n
The new library is set to open its doors before the year 2000.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
Latin A m e r i c a ’s
e n d a n g e r e d
f re q u e n c i e s
A champion of
community ra d i o
stations warns of thre a t s
to their existence in
Latin A m e r i c a
n
Alongside state-run radio and large-
scale private broadcasting networks
there is another world of community
radio stations, owned, run and editorially
controlled by the public they serve.These
“alternative” radio stations may not have
a range beyond the slum, village or island
from which they broadcast. Many of them
are shoestring operations staffed by local
volunteers.
Unlike commercial radio, which makes
money from adve rt i s i n g, community radio
s t ations are not profit - o ri e n t e d — t h o u g h
sometimes they accept a little adve rt i s i n g
in order to surv i ve .They are there to serve
the local populat i o n . Because of their
c o n t ri bution to a culture of peace and the
gr owth of democracy, they are making
h e a d way on eve ry continent.
With the development of democrat i c
m ovements and the emergence of new
pri vate and public pressure gr o u p s , c o m-
munity radio has taken root all over the
wo r l d , though on different scales and with
d i f f e ring effects. This is largely due to new
and better technical equipment, c h e a p e r
FM transmitters and the gradual disappea-
rance of public broadcasting monopolies.
When recognized by the gove rn m e n t
and protected by law—as in the United
S t at e s ,Australia and Canada, for example—
they coexist uncontentiously with com-
mercial stat i o n s. A number of European
c o u n t ries have followed the example of
F r a n c e , where the law was changed in 1982
to legalize “ p i r at e ” or “ f r e e ” radio stat i o n s.
In Africa and Asia, the growth of local
radio has been spectacular.The most stri-
king case is South Africa where, accor-
ding to the Media Institute of South
Africa (MISA), community broadcasting
has great potential. On these continents
community radio is helping to roll back
illiteracy, promote education and provide
information about health, the environ-
ment, farming, democracy and hot issues
like landmines. But in one part of the
world, Latin America, it is under attack.
Fewer voices
Community radio stations involved in
e d u c ational broadcasting or speaking out
for trade unions, u n i ve rsities or indigenous
peoples have been operating in Latin A m e-
rica for more than half a century. “They’ve
been used to announce all kinds of things,
from prices down at the local market to
s o m e o n e ’s horse that has gone astray,” s ay s
José Ignacio López Vigil,the Latin Ameri-
can and Caribbean representat i ve of the
World A s s o c i ation of Community Radio
B r o a d c a s t e rs (AMARC). “ T h e y ’ ve also
taught thousands of people to read and
thousands more how to figure out where
their employe rs have cheated them of their
wa g e s. T h e y ’ ve helped to make sure that
children were va c c i n ated and they’ve
encouraged ordinary people to speak up.”
There are probably more than 2,000
community radio stations broadcasting in
Latin America; 400 of them are affiliated
to AMARC, twice as many as three years
* Peruvian sociologist, journalist and university teacher.
Former president of the World Association of Community
Radio Broadcasters (AMARC).
An announcer in the studio of a Dar es-Salaam
(Tanzania) Catholic radio station.
Rafael Roncagliolo*
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The Unesco Courier - April 1999
C O N N E X I O N S
ago. But while their number keeps on
growing, the stations are having problems
obtaining legal recognition.
Until recently, Latin America’s local
radio stations coexisted with commercial
stations without too much trouble. But
the concentration of the media over the
past few years has tended to push non-
profit radio and smaller stations in gene-
ral out of the picture.This has inevitably
led to fewer voices being heard on the air.
Most of Latin A m e ri c a ’s community radio
s t ations are waiting to be assigned a fixe d
f r e q u e n cy or else official permission to broad-
c a s t . H owe ver they are not defined by their
legal status but by their goals.Whether regi s-
tered as public or pri vate companies (linked
to unive rs i t i e s ,r e gions or tow n s ) , their defin i n g
f e ature is that they are non-profit organizat i o n s
without any political axe to gri n d .
Strong programmes,
weak transmitters
The fact that they are linked to the local
community does not necessarily mean they
are small or ill equipped. In fact existing sta-
tions are trying to upgrade their technical
r e s o u r c e s , and new ones, such as Radio Tri-
nidad FM in Pa r a g u ay, t ry to start up with the
best possible fa c i l i t i e s. M a ny stations have
weak transmitters but make up for it by
h aving computers in the newsroom. S o m e
e ven broadcast via the Intern e t .
Nor does their community spirit mean
that they put out boring programmes with
poor-quality sound.The kind of intermi-
nable discussions and across-the-block
denunciations that characterized commu-
nity radio in its early days has given way
to more open-minded and witty pro-
grammes which cover all aspects of life.
In Europe a distinction has always been
made between profit - o riented commercial
radio and public-service broadcasting desi-
gned to play a socio-cultural role.In Latin
A m e ri c a ,h owe ve r , this distinction has been
b l u rred because stat e - owned radio and tele-
vision stations have been largely used as
political tools and have had little or no
social or cultural value.
In El Salvador, a recent telecommuni-
cations law gave clear advantage to profi-
table private firms and established regula-
tions which favour big capital, to the extent
t h at even the country ’s second biggest tele-
vision stat i o n , which is pri vat e , was in
danger of closing down.In Uruguay, radio
operating licences have to be approved by
the defence ministry, and broadcasters
without a licence risk a prison sentence. I n
Chile,the power of a transmitter is limited
to one watt. In Brazil and Argentina, new
l e gi s l ation is looming which would concen-
t r ate radio ow n e rship even further and thus
narrow the public’s choice.
In Pe ru , one of the few countries in
L atin A m e rica where community radio sta-
tions can operate without too many legal
p r o b l e m s , a new law passed in March 1998
banned non-profit stations from accepting
even the very small amount of advertising
which could ensure their surv i va l . S i n c e
they receive no state subsidy or support,
they are doomed to close, and this means
that several sources of criticism of the pre-
sent government will fall silent.
Closing doors
Their staff have appealed in vain to
the national ombudsman (D e fensor del
Pueblo), and press freedom officials of the
O r g a n i z ation of A m e rican States have
approached the government without suc-
cess. If the law is applied, dozens of sta-
tions may have to shut down.
One of them is Radio Cutivalú, which
has about 400,000 listeners in the north
of the country and is the region’s main
medium-wave station.The station, which
is named after a pre-Inca Indian leader,
won a United Nations prize last year for
its “successful efforts to fight poverty”.
A live broadcast from Bolivia’s Radio Esperanza.
Alternative radio
n
Community, free, pirate, local, indige-
n o u s ,e d u c at i o n a l ,i n s u rr e c t i o n a l — t h e s e
are just some of the labels used to descri b e
“ a l t e rn at i ve ” radio stat i o n s. A recently-
published book* has identified about 20
types all over the wo r l d ,o p e r ating alongside
“established” stations.
Most of them belong to either the Wo r l d
Association of Community Radio Broad-
c a s t e rs (AMARC) or the Intern at i o n a l
A s s o c i ation of Broadcasting (AIR).
AMARC,founded in August 1983 during
the UN-sponsored World Communicat i o n s
Year, defends, co-ordinates and promotes
radio stations around the world that are
c o m m u n i t y - owned or broadcast socially-
o riented progr a m m e s.With headquart e rs in
M o n t r e a l , it has more than 2,000 mem-
bers on five continents.
A I R , which started in Mexico in 1946 as
the Inter-American Association of Broad-
c a s t i n g, is based in Montevideo (Uru g u ay )
and switched to its present name in 1985.
It defends broadcasting which conform s
to intern ational technical and legal stan-
dards and is a longstanding critic of com-
munity radio stations on the grounds that
some of them cause interference problems
through not having an official frequency. B u t
AIR also defends free expression of ideas
and encourages co-operation between radio
s t ations and organizat i o n s , both nat i o n a l
and intern ational and publicly and pri vat e l y -
owned. n
* Las Otras Radios, by Alfredo Bouissa,Eduardo
Curuchet and Oscar Orcajo (Editorial Nordan-
Comunidad, Uruguay, 1998).
+ …
l AMARC: http://www.amarc.org
Phone:(514) 9820351
l AIR: http://www.distrinet.com.uy/air—iab/
Phone:(59) 824088121
Most of Latin America’s
community radio stations
are waiting to be assigned
a fixed frequency or
official permission to
broadcast
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
Brain waves
to help
the disabled
Totally-paralysed people may soon be able to
write on computer screens by using electrical
signals from their brain.
Two research teams, one in the United States,
the other in Germany, have come up with a
device which,with the help of two small elec-
trodes attached to the top of the skull, “ r e a d s ”
the waves given off by the brain.Three people
with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, a degenera-
tive motor neurone disease, used the method to
write a short sentence over half an hour.
“ These patients couldn’t communicate at
all,” says Edward Taub of the University of Ala-
bama in an article in the January 1999 issue of
New Scientist m a g a z i n e. He and Niels Birbaumer,
of the University of Tübingen,record electrical
signals coming from the cortex of the brain.
The patients, by developing their ability to give
positive or negative signals, control the upwa r d
or downward movement of a cursor which
chooses from among 32 letters and punctuation
marks on the screen.
The two teams are writing a computer pro-
gramme which could speed things up by anti-
cipating words from the first few letters, d e p e n-
ding on the context of the sentence and the
frequency with which words are used in the
language.
Several other researchers around the world
are trying to harness the potential of brain
signals to relieve the ordeal of paralysed people.
Last year an Australian team managed to get
patients to operate a switch from signals regis-
tered on a brain scan.A team in Atlanta,in the
U.S.,implanted electrodes in the brains of two
people, enabling them to write messages on a
computer screen.But a dangerous brain ope-
ration is needed.The team is hoping one day to
come up with a device that can use brain signals
to stimulate muscles and restore partial use of
some limbs. n
It is also the only station attached to
Propuesta Regi o n a l, a “ d e velopment foru m ”
whose participants include professional,
university and religious associations inde-
pendent of the gove rn m e n t . It played a key
role in helping the population survive the
rains and flooding brought by the El Niño
weather phenomenon.
L i s t e n e rs say their favo u rite pro-
grammes are the station’s competitions to
encourage writing inspired by local tales
and legends, which have attracted more
than 1,300 amateur writers from towns
all over northern Peru. Equally popular
are regional song festivals sponsored by
Panasonic and other firms, which give
dozens of self-taught authors and compo-
sers a hearing they would never have
enjoyed on commercial stations.
Cutivalú is not the only Peruvian radio
station whose future hangs in the balance.
The same goes for Radio Marañón, which
broadcasts from Ja é n , in the A m a z o n
region.At the other end of the country, in
Puno, near the Bolivian border, Radio
Onda Azul is in danger of losing its net-
work of rural correspondents because it
can no longer afford to pay them.
All these laws violate constitutional
rights and go against current internatio-
nal guarantees of freedom of expression.
Community radio stations, which are by
definition poor, have taken all kinds of
legal steps to defend themselve s. I n
Argentina and Paraguay, they have mana-
ged to survive because they have won
their case. In Ecuador, they successfully
challenged a law before the country’s
constitutional court. Ombudsmen in El
Salvador and Peru have made strong sta-
tements defending the stations’ rights.
Fair shares
on the air
What is at stake in Latin America is
very clear. Will the airwaves, which are
part of overall human heritage, be mono-
polized by commercial firms, or will be
they also be available, as they are everyw-
here else in the world, to communities,
educational groups and non-profit orga-
nizations, in other words to the full spec-
trum of civil society exercising its right to
free expression?
What lies ahead for community radio
stations? They defend the right to free
speech, help to create the diversity of opi-
nion which is an essential feature of
democracy, and encourage local develop-
ment,a culture of peace, the protection of
the environment and other civic causes
which cannot be measured in terms of
financial gain.
The history of the right to speak on
the air began at the beginning of the cen-
tury. Its defenders around the world have
had to wage many struggles and make
many sacrifices. Today it is more impor-
tant than ever to ensure there is room for
everyone on the airwaves. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Leila Shahid
46 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
As Pa l e s t i n e ’s re p resentative in France and a
s p o ke s p e rson for the Palestinian A u t h o r i t y,
y o u ’ re often in the media spotlight. But you
only have a very brief entry in the latest
edition of Who’s Who in the Arab World . . .
Perhaps it’s better that way. I’m not an
ambassador in the usual sense because
Palestine isn’t a state ye t . As representa-
t i ve of a people who for the past half-century
h ave been trying to win recognition, I have
to fight a battle on two fronts. One—more
behind-the-scenes—is to maintain close
ties with France and the European Union
so as to defend the political rights of the
Palestinian people.The other is public, a n d
i nvo l ves correcting a number of widely-
accepted “facts” through the media.The
Palestinian question is perhaps the most
consistently and massively distorted inter-
national political issue.
Not so long ago it was said that the Pa l e s-
tinian people didn’t exist. Palestine was consi-
dered a country without inhabitants—a
d e s e rt—for a people without a land, the Je w s.
Its name was removed from maps and history
books the day Israel was creat e d .
I t ’s been an existential bat t l e . Fo r
decades,Israelis thought they would cease
to exist if they recognized the Palestinian
p e o p l e . And Europeans thought that reco-
gnizing the Palestinians would be tanta-
mount to betraying the Israelis, a people
t owards whom they had strong guilt feelings
because of the Holocaust.So we’ve had to
fight to set things straight and show that
recognition could happen on an equal basis.
Most Israelis today, especially the new gene-
r ation of histori a n s , a gree that Pa l e s t i n e
wasn’t a desert in 1948.
The other main historical distortion has
been the dismissal of the Palestinian people
as a bunch of armed fig h t e rs and terr o ri s t s.
The i n t i fa d a, which lasted from 1987 to
1 9 9 3 , did a lot to show there was a society
t h e r e , just like any other, with all its compo-
n e n t s , including women and children. B u t
t h e r e ’s still prejudice. Palestinians are still tar-
gets of stereotypes regarding Arabs and Mus-
lims in general.They spring from eve ry d ay
racism and the legacy of colonial times.
You’re a “foreign” Palestinian—one from
the outside. How did your family come to
leave Palestine and what was it like to live
in exile?
My mother’s family has always been very
involved in the Palestinian national move-
ment born at the turn of the century after
the fall of the Ottoman Empire and the
b e ginning of the British Mandate in Pa l e s-
tine which was supposed to pave the way for
independence.From then on, Palestinians
began to demand the right to found a stat e .
But it very soon became clear that, unlike
S y ria and Lebanon, Palestine would not
succeed in that goal, because it had to make
way for the Jewish national home which
the British had promised to the Zionists.
When the Palestinian national move-
ment saw that political and diplomat i c
means were not enough to reve rse what
was happening, it resorted to arm s. T h e
f i rst big Palestinian uprising against the
British, the first intifada, was in 1936. My
gr a n d father and gr e at uncle took part in it.
In 1939, my grandfather was arrested and
sent off to a military camp in the Seychelles.
Like all the leaders of the move m e n t , he wa s
detained until 1945, d u ring which time
women and children were deported to areas
under the French mandat e . So my mother,
who came from Je ru s a l e m , found herself in
L e b a n o n . It was there that she met my
fat h e r , who had come as a student from
A c r e , in Pa l e s t i n e .They got married and my
t wo sisters and I grew up outside Pa l e s-
tine,like two-thirds of all Palestinians.
Where does your political awareness stem
from?
My fa m i l y. I was ve ry affected by the 1967
Arab-Israeli wa r , which broke out the day I
was due to take my high school gr a d u at i o n
e x a m ,on June 5.The exam was cancelled.We
were sure that we ’d win the wa r , but when we
realized after six days that Israel had beat e n
all the Arab armies—of Syri a , Egypt and
Jo r d a n — we were shat t e r e d . June 1967 was a
ve ry deep shock for Arab intellectuals. We
thought that the intern ational community
would be sympathetic to the injustice and
exile Palestinians were forced to endure.We
Since her high-school days she has embraced the Palestinian cause. Now,
as the Palestinian Authority’s representative in France, Leila Shahid is
continuing the fight for the creation of a Palestinian state, for women’s rights
and peaceful coexistence at the heart of Mediterranean civilization
The re s o l v e
of a Palestinian envoy
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
thought that it would support us. But it
applauded the Israeli victory instead.
I decided to get invo l ved in political
activism and I began learning how to handle
we a p o n s. It was a symbolic way of restori n g
a sense of dignity. But I soon realized I
wa s n ’t cut out for the military and opted for
political and social work in the Palestinian
refugee camps. In my first year of unive rs i t y,
I took part in activities to prepare for the
i n t i fa d a. In 1969, the refugees rose up to win
the right to organize politically and manage
their own affa i rs. From then on, the va ri o u s
groups which made up the Palestine Libe-
r ation Organization (PLO) took part in
running the camps, which were adminis-
tered by the United Nations via UNWRA
(the United Nations Relief and Wo r k s
Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near
E a s t ) .This was a ve ry intense period for me.
I felt like I had returned to Palestine and
r e d i s c overed my history and culture. A f t e r
t h at , I went off to study anthropology in
F r a n c e , where I met my husband, who is
M o r o c c a n , and we went to live in his country.
In 1989,President A r a fat asked me to repre-
sent the PLO in Ireland. From there I wa s
sent to the Netherlands and finally to France.
Has being a woman ever been a handicap
for you?
I come from a family of three gi r l s , so I
never had to defend myself against a boy
who might have wanted to get the upper
hand. My f ather, who was a professor of
medicine,believed strongly in the equality
of the sexes, and both my parents always
backed me in what e ver I wanted to do. M y
husband has the same attitude.
How has the Arab-Israeli conflict affected
Palestinian women?
M a ny women found themselves in foreign
c o u n t ri e s , away from their traditional vil-
lage surr o u n d i n g s , side by side with men
who were traumatized and jobless. T h e s e
men were so humiliated by the loss of their
lands that they had no strength to react. S o
the women had to take charge of things and
organize day - t o - d ay life with ve ry few means.
If they hadn’t been uprooted like this, i t
would have taken decades to break with tra-
d i t i o n .A l s o, U N W R A , which was in charge
of education and health in the refugee camps,
inside and outside Pa l e s t i n e , set up a system
of compulsory education for all, both boy s
and gi r l s.This partly explains why Pa l e s t i-
nians have one of the highest literacy rates in
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 47
the Arab wo r l d .But Palestinian women have
a lways been aware that their role in the resis-
tance would not be enough to guarantee
them equal rights with men. So they have
t ried to organize themselve s , not just as mili-
tant nationalists but also as wo m e n .
To do what?
There are a number of wo m e n ’s organiza-
t i o n s.M a ny are working on a code to defin e
the status of women and a constitutional
guarantee of equality.There is a good start i n g
point since the 1988 declaration underlines
t h at the Palestinian state will have a parlia-
m e n t a ry system which guarantees equal
rights for men and wo m e n . But it’s hard to
put into practice, because we can’t cut our-
s e l ves off completely from the rest of the
r e gi o n ,where individual rights are based on
Islamic law, the s h a ri a.T h e r e ’s a debate bet-
ween lay people and religious officials in
society and in parliamentary bodies. B e yo n d
the judicial fie l d , wo m e n ’s groups have pro-
grammes which encourage women to take
paid jobs. O t h e rs are doing research. B i r
Life spills over on to an abandoned railway line in a Gaza refugee camp.
Many women found themselves in foreign countries, away
from their traditional village surroundings, side by side
with men who were traumatized and jobless. These men
were so humiliated by the loss of their lands that they had
no strength to react
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
Zeit Unive rsity has the regi o n ’s only centre
for wo m e n ’s studies.
Yet there are very few women in the
Palestinian Authority. Isn’t there a risk of
finding the Algerian syndrome in which
women are sent back to the kitchen as
soon as the struggle is over?
The fight isn’t ove r , either against the occu-
pation or for women’s rights. And the two
are linked. For wo m e n ,e ve rything depends
on the balance of power in the society.T h e
future of the progr e s s i ve , s e c u l a rist ten-
dency led by President Arafat depends on
the peace process. If that collapses, the fun-
damentalist position will get stronger and
a u t o m atically harm the position of wo m e n .
Are schools co-ed in Palestine?
There are two kinds of schools—the
UNWRA ones in the camps and those in
the autonomous areas run by the Pa l e s t i n i a n
Authority since 1994. Both are co-educa-
tional, except for a few in the Gaza Strip
which are pri vate schools serving the more
conservative elements of society.
What laws govern the status of Palestinian
women today?
It depends where they live .M a ny legal sys-
tems coexist in Pa l e s t i n e — O t t o m a n ,E n g l i s h ,
Egyptian (in the Gaza Stri p ) , Jordanian (the
West Bank) and Israeli (civil and military, i n
East Je ru s a l e m ) .I t ’s a unique situat i o n — s o
m a ny legal systems applying to so few people.
We ’re trying to come up with a body of law s
t h at will be truly Pa l e s t i n i a n .
You emphasize that a solution to the
Israeli-Palestinian conflict is crucial for the
whole Mediterranean region. Why?
After the creation of the state of Israel, t h e
c o n flict spread to Egypt, which was the firs t
c o u n t ry to sign a peace treat y, to southern
L e b a n o n , which has been occupied for 20
ye a rs , the Golan Heights (Syri a ) ,occupied for
30 ye a rs , and to Jo r d a n ,which recently signed
a peace treat y. A resolution of the confli c t
will show whether the peoples of the Medi-
t e rranean can live together in mutual res-
p e c t . If Palestinians and Israelis can manage
to do this, their example can encourage
o t h e rs — B e r b e rs and A r a b s ,Turks and Ku r d s ,
for example. Palestine isn’t like other coun-
t ri e s. I t ’s the heart of Mediterranean civiliza-
t i o n , the only place which brings together
EGYPT
JORDAN
1947
SYRIA
LEBANON Damascus
Amman
Jerusalem
Tel Aviv
Gaza
Partition plan proposed
by the UN
Jewish state
Arab state
International zone
Arab countries
An eclectic
education 
Education is considered a major priority for
Pa l e s t i n i a n s,an observation difficult to quan-
tify given the scope of the diaspora. H o w e v e r, t h e
political upheaval surrounding the i n t i f a d a h a s
taken a toll on education in the territories:lite-
racy rates have declined, while the dearth of
trained professionals in science and techno-
logy hampers the economic development.
The Palestinian Ministry of Education, o f fi-
cially set up in 1994,has the major task of conso-
lidating the eclectic system of public and priva t e
schools inherited after 27 years of occupation. I n
the West Bank, for example, schoolchildren follow
nine years of courses based on Jordanian curri-
c u l a ,while in Gaza, they take ten years of classes
following the Egyptian model.This system dates
back to 1948 when UN R W A (the United Nations
Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees
in the Near East) began setting up schools in
the refugee camps to reflect the curricula of the
host nations. To d a y, the challenge lies in inte-
grating these different schools as well as the
public schools set up by the ministry and a small
percentage of private schools established by
Muslim and Christian organizations.O v e r a l l ,t h e
gender ratio in enrolment at the primary level is
e q u a l , although girls tend to have higher drop-out
rates as they move on to secondary levels and
higher education.All of the territories’ eight uni-
versities and over half of the some 20 community
colleges are priva t e.
The ministry is working closely with UNESCO,
a long-standing educational partner, to inte-
grate the various schools and find the funding
to enlarge the system as Palestinian families
return from the diaspora.A major priority also
lies in developing a standard curriculum and in
particular courses in Palestinian history—a for-
bidden subject throughout 27 years of occu-
pation. n
November 1917: The Balfour Declaration in which
the British Foreign Secretary promises support for
the creation of a Jewish national home in Pa l e s t i n e.
May 14,1948: Declaration of the state of Israel.
1 9 4 8 - 1 9 4 9:War in Pa l e s t i n e, prompting a massive
exodus of Palestinians and ending with a victory for
Israel and armistices signed with Arab neighbours.
Jordan annexes the West Bank, while Egypt rules
the Gaza Strip.
May 29, 1 9 6 4: Creation of the Palestine Liberation
Organization (PLO).
June 5,1967: Six-Day War in which Israel defeats
the combined forces of Egypt, Syria and Jordan
and occupies the Sinai,Golan Heights, West Bank,
Gaza and East Jerusalem.
February 1-4, 1969: Yasser Arafat becomes pre-
sident of the PLO Executive Committee.
September 1970: Jordan expels the PLO which
moves its headquarters to Lebanon.Within a few
m o n t h s, a low level war of attrition takes place
along the southern Lebanese border between PLO
and Israeli forces.
October 6, 1973: Start of the October War, also
known as the Yom Kippur War, in which Egyptian
and Syrian forces attack Israel to try to recover
occupied territories.
September 17, 1 9 7 8: Camp David Accords signed
by Egypt and Israel lead to Israeli withdrawal from
the Sinai and a peace treaty.
June 6, 1 9 8 2: Israel invades Lebanon to defeat PLO
and Syrian forces. Hundreds of Palestinians are
later massacred at the Sabra and Chatila refugee
c a m p s. Arafat then moves PLO headquarters to
Tunis.
December 1987: I n t i f a d a (uprising) begins in
Israeli-occupied territories.
November 12-15, 1 9 8 8: PLO declares the creation
of a democratic state while denouncing terrorism
and recognizes the state of Israel in December.
September 13, 1 9 9 3: Signature in Washington of
I s r a e l i - Palestinian accords secretly negotiated in
Oslo and sealed by the famous handshake between
Yitzhak Rabin and Yasser A r a f a t .
July 1, 1 9 9 4:Arafat returns to Gaza to establish the
Palestinian Authority.
November 4, 1 9 9 5: Rabin assassinated by an
Israeli extremist.
May 29, 1 9 9 6: Benjamin Netanyahu elected prime
minister of Israel.
October 23, 1998: Wye Plantation Accords bet-
ween Israel and PLO mark an attempt to reinvigo-
rate the peace process.
May 4,1999: End of the five-year interim period
included under the terms of the Oslo Accords.
A brief chronology
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
April 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 49
T A L K I N G  T O …
the three major monotheistic religions and
their cultures. Their peaceful coexistence
would have an impact beyond the regi o n —
e ve rywhere that different cultures are try i n g
to reject and exclude one another.
The Arab world currently seems to consist
of groups trying to dominate one another.
The Arab world hasn’t always been like this.
I t ’s a ve ry recent phenomenon.D o n ’t forget
t h at in A n d a l u s i a , Europeans and Arabs live d
together in extremely fruitful harm o ny until
the time of the Inquisition, when Chri s t i a n s
excluded Jews and Muslims from society.
The lack of tolerance we see in the A r a b -
Muslim world today is part of a contemporary
political crisis which began with the founding
of nat i o n - s t at e s. It isn’t an inherent part of
Arab culture. I t ’s to do with the failure of poli-
tical systems which have managed to defeat
colonialism but have n ’t found the path to
d e m o c r a cy or gi ven people a chance to aspire
in political, economic and cultural term s.S o
t h e y ’ ve fa i l e d , which is why people set such
i m p o rtance on their own identity or seek an
a l t e rn at i ve political ideology in religi o n .
The interim period for the application of
the Oslo Accords ends on May 4. What’s the
outcome of this process?
I t ’s disappointing. The peace process has
been at a standstill ever since Mr Netanya h u
came to power three ye a rs ago. So we ’re fa r
behind the agreed timetable.The Israeli army
should have withdrawn from all the occu-
pied terri t o ri e s. But so far we only control
three per cent of the West Bank and 60 per
cent of the Gaza Stri p.We should have been
able to hold both parliamentary and local
e l e c t i o n s , but the latter have n ’t been pos-
s i b l e .We should have completed most of the
toughest negotiations over the status of Je ru-
s a l e m , r e f u g e e s , s e t t l e m e n t s , b o r d e rs and
wat e r , but we have n ’t even started ye t . S o
does that mean nothing has been achieve d ?
N o, some gains are irr e ve rs i b l e . The most
i m p o rtant is the mutual recognition betwe e n
Israeli and Palestinian gove rnments and socie-
t i e s. It is now accepted that the Pa l e s t i n i a n
people exist and have national ri g h t s. T h e
second gain has been the right of return to the
homeland—the e l - ow d a of the Pa l e s t i n i a n
n ational movement which developed in
exile—has been recognized. It was marked by
the return of President A r a fat to build a stat e .
What has been done to create new
infrastructures?
Roads,industries and farms in the territo-
ries recovered by the Palestinian A u t h o ri t y
were mostly destroyed during the 30 years
of the occupat i o n . So fa r , not much progr e s s
has been made here, mainly because the ter-
ritories have been sealed off by the Israeli
a rmy.The economy can’t take off if the cir-
culation of goods and people is blocked.
EGYPT
JORDAN
1948
SYRIA
LEBANON
Amman
Jerusalem
Tel Aviv
Gaza
The WestBank 
was annexed by Jordan in
1950
Israel according 
to the 1947
partition plan
Territories conquered by
Israel in 1948
Arab countries
EGYPT
JORDAN
1967
SYRIA
LEBANON
Amman
Jerusalem
Tel Aviv
Gaza
EGYPT
JORDAN
1996
SYRIA
LEBANON
Amman
Jerusalem
Tel Aviv
Gaza
Israel before
the Six-Day War
Territories occupied in
1967
Territories returned in
1974 (Quneitra),or
1982 (Sinai)
Arab countries
Israel (internationally recognized
f r o n t i e r s )
Territories annexed by Israel
Israeli-controlled South Lebanon
Palestinian autonomous areas
Other occupied territories
Arab countries
An early start: Palestinian children at play school in Rafah,Gaza.
‘Don’t forget that in A n d a l u s i a , E u ropeans and A rabs lived
together in extremely fruitful harmony until the time of the
I n q u i s i t i o n , when Christians excluded Jews and Muslims
f rom society. The lack of tolerance we see in the A ra b -
Muslim world today is part of a contemporary political
crisis which began with the founding of nation-states’
Damascus Damascus Damascus
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50 The UNESCO Courier - April 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
I WISH TO SUBSCRIBE TO the UNESCO Courier
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to:
the UNESCO Courier Subscription Services, 31,rue François Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
For payments in other currencies , please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are opposite this order form.
"
This obstacle is smaller in social matters.
G r e at progress has been made in educat i o n
with the help of the European Union and
UNESCO. Palestinians invest a tremendous
amount in educating their children. I don’t
know of any other people, except perhaps
the Jews, who have compensated so much
for the loss of terri t o ry by acquiring know-
l e d g e . But there’s still a lot to be done,
especially creating a modern curri c u l u m
tailored to Palestinians and not copied from
courses in Egypt, Jordan or Israel.
Has the international community kept its
promises?
Ye s , a b s o l u t e l y. Donor countries can be
commended for guaranteeing the educat i o n
and health of a people wracked by eco-
nomic crisis. Over 60 per cent of the wor-
king population in the Gaza Strip is unem-
ployed, and over 47 per cent in the West
B a n k . But this aid wo n ’t have any really
p o s i t i ve effect unless the pri vate sector
seriously invests,and for that we need sta-
bility and normalized political conditions.
There’s been a lot of talk in the press about
irregularities and corruption inside the
Palestinian Authority. What has been done
to tackle this?
I t ’s the kind of problem that threatens all
s o c i e t i e s , including the most advanced ones
in Europe.So imagine the difficulty in Pa l e s-
t i n e ,where there aren’t laws or a legal system
in place ye t . There wo n ’t be transparency
or genuine pluralism until there’s a state of
l aw, and we don’t have a state ye t .
How is the Palestinian Authority preparing
for the May 4 deadline?
The Israeli gove rnment has decided to hold
elections on May 17 to effectively cancel the
M ay 4 deadline set in the Oslo A c c o r d s.
After May 4 there will be a legal no-man’s -
l a n d . The big question is who will fill the
void? We can’t live forever on a temporary
b a s i s. Are we going to let the Israeli gove rn-
ment take away our rights? Can the Pa l e s t i-
nians decide unilaterally to set up a state in
the West Bank, Gaza and East Je rusalem? W i l l
the intern ational community shoulder its
responsibilities after having recognized Pa l e s-
t i n i a n s ’ right to self-determ i n ation? All these
questions will arise on May 4.
Will you live in Palestine one day?
As one of the four million refugees living
outside Pa l e s t i n e , my status isn’t yet defin e d .
It will be part of the final negotiations. My
greatest dream is to live in Palestine.
Where?
In Jerusalem,I hope. n
Interview by 
Sophie Boukhari and Amy Otchet
Women on their way to the polls in the 1996 legislative elections.
Language: English French Spanish
Rates (postage included):
Industrialized countries: Developing countries or students 
1 year: 211French francs (€32,15) instead of 264FF* (11 issues including 1 double issue) (Please send copy of your card):
2 years:396 French francs (€60,35) instead of 528FF* (22 issues including 2 double issues) 1 year: 132 French francs (€20,10)
Binder: 72French francs (€11) (for 11 issues including 1 double issue) 2 years: 211 French francs (€32,15)
I enclose payment: (in French francs only) by
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque) Visa Mastercard Eurocard
N° ⌧—⌧—x—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧ Expiry date: Date and signature:
Name First name
Address
Postal code City
Optional:Age Profession
(*) Total cover price
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
L I S T  O F S A L E S A N D S U B S C R I P T I O N A G E N T S
Subscr ipt ions can be paid to the subscr ipt ion agent  in you r c ountry who wil l  su ppl y rates in local  currenc y on re q u e s t
A R G E N T I N A : Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UN E S C O,
Tucumán 1685, 1050 Buenos A i r e s. Fa x :3 7 1 - 8 1 9 4 .
AU S T R A L I A : Hunter Publicat i o n s , 58A Gipps Street,
C o l l i n g wood VIC 3066. Fa x : 419 7154. ISA A u s t r a l i a ,
PO Box 709,To owong QLD 4066. Fa x : 371 5566.
United Nations A s s o c. of A u s t r a l i a / V i c t o rian Div. ,
179 St George's Road,
N. F i t z r oy VIC 3068. Fa x : 481 7693.
AU S T R I A : Gerold & Co, I m p o rt & Export ,
Z e i t s c h ri f t e n / Pe ri o d i c a l s , Graben 31, A-1011 V i e n n a .
Fa x : 512 47 31 29
B E L G I U M : Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Bru s s e l s.
Fa x : 538 08 41.
B R A Z I L : Fundaco Getulio Va r g a s , Editora Divisão de Ve n d a s ,
Caixa Postal 62.591, 22257-970 Rio de Janeiro RJ.
Fa x :5 5 1 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA : Renouf Publishing Company Ltd,
5369 ch.Canotek Road,Unit 1,Ottawa,Ont K1J 9J3.
Fax:(1-613) 745 7660. Faxon Canada,POBox 2382,London,
Ont.N6A 5A7. Fax:(1-519) 472 1072.
C H I L E : U n i ve rs i t a ria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10220,
S a n t i a g o. Fa x : 681 9091.
C H I N A : China National Publicat i o n s ,I m p o rt & Export
C o rp. , PO Box 88, 16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 100020.
Fa x : 010 65063101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30,111 27
Prague 1.
D E N M A R K : M u n k s g a a r d ,N o rre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148,
DK-1016 Kobenhavn K. Fa x : 12 93 87.
F I N L A N D : S t o c k m a n n / A k ateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23,
SF-00371 Helsinki. Fa x : +358 9 121 4450.
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF-01641 Va n t a a .
Fa x : 852 7990.
G E R M A N Y: G e rman Commission for UN E S C O, C o l m a n t s t r.
1 5 , D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 63 69 12.
Uno Ve r l a g, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55,
D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 21 74 92.
G R E E C E : L i b r a i rie Kauffmann SA, M a u v r o k o r d atou 9,
GR-106 78 A t h e n s. Fa x : 38 33 967.
G UAT E M A L A : Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con
la UN E S C O, 3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1,A p a rtado Postal 2630,
G u atemala City.
HONG KO N G : Hong Kong Gove rnment Inform ation Svcs.
D e p t . , 1 Bat t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
H U N G A RY: Librotrade K F T, Pe riodical Import / K ,
POB 126, H-1656 Budapest. Fa x :2 5 6 - 8 7 - 2 7 .
I N D I A : O rient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions A c c o u n t ) ,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estat e ,B o m b ay 400 038.
Fa x : 26 91 278.
Oxford Book & Stat i o n e ry Co, Code No D 8208052,
Scindia House, New Delhi 110 001. Fa x : 33 22 639.
I S R A E L : L i t e r a ry Transactions Inc. , C/0 Steimatsky Ltd.,
PO Box 1444, Bnei Brak 51114. Fa x : 52 81 187.
I TA LY: L i c o s a / L i b r e ria Comm. Sansoni SPA ,
Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-50125 Florence. Fa x :6 4 - 1 2 - 5 7 .
J A PA N : E a s t e rn Book Service Inc. , Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
3 13 Hongo 3 Chome, B u n k yo Ku ,To k yo 113. Fa x :8 1 8 - 0 8 6 4 .
KO R E A : Korean National Commission for UN E S C O,
CPO Box 64, Seoul 100-600. Fa x : 568 7454.
L U X E M B U R G : M e s s a g e ries Paul Kraus, BP 2022,
L-1020 Luxe m b o u r g . Fa x : 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA : Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36,
26 Republic Street,Valletta CMR 01. Fa x : 24 61 82.
M AU R I T I U S : Nalanda Co. L t d . , 30 Bourbon Street,
Po rt Louis. Fa x : 212 1313.
M O RO C C O : UN E S C O, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat
Fax:212-767 03 75, Tel.:212-767 03 74/72.
M E X I C O : Librería El Correo de la UN E S C O S A , Col Roma,
G u a n a j u ato 72, Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF.
Fa x :2 6 4 - 0 9 - 1 9 .
N E T H E R L A N D S : S wets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830,
2160 SZ Lisse. Fa x :2 5 2 4 - 1 5 8 8 8 .
T i j d s c h riftcentrale Wijck B V, I n t .S u b s. S e rv i c e ,W
G r a c h t s t r a at 1C, 6221 CT Maastri c h t . Fa x : 32 50 103.
NEW ZEALAND: GP Legi s l ation Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 12418,T h o rn d o n , We l l i n g t o n .
Fa x : 496 56 98.
NORWAY : S wets Norge A S ,Ø s t e n s j ø vein 18-0606 Oslo,
PO Box 6512,Etterstad. Fax:47 22 97 45 45.
P O RT U G A L : L i v r a ria Po rtugal (Dias & Andrade Lda),
Rua do Carmo 70 74, 1200 Lisboa. Fa x : 34 70 264.
R U S S I A : Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39,
M o s c ow 113095.
SOUTH A F R I C A : I n t e rn ational Subscription Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 41095, Craighall 2024. Fa x : 880 6248.
Mast Publicat i o n s , PO Box 901, Parklands 2121.
Fa x : 886 4512.
S PA I N : Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37,
28001 Madri d . Fa x :5 7 5 - 3 9 - 9 8 .
L i b r e ria Al A n d a l ú s , Roldana 3 y 4, 41004 Sevilla.
Fa x :4 2 2 - 5 3 - 3 8 .
Los Amigos de la UN E S C O, Alda Urquijo 62, 2 Izd.,
48011 Bilbao. Fa x :4 2 7 - 5 1 - 5 9 / 6 9
SRI LANKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam,
Gardiner Mawat h a , Colombo 2. Fa x : 44 78 48.
S W E D E N : We n n e r gren Williams A B , PO Box 1305,
S-171 25 Solna. Fa x : 27 00 71.
S W I T Z E R L A N D : Dynapresse Marketing SA, ( e x - N av i l l e
S A ) , 38 av V i b e rt , CH-1227 Carouge. Fa x : 308 08 59.
E d i group SA, Case Postale 393, CH-1225 Chêne-Bourg.
Fa x : 348 44 82.
Europa Ve r l a g, Ramistrasse 5, CH-8024 Züri c h .
Fa x : 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG ,W i s s e n s c h a f t l .B u c h h a n d l u n g,
Pe t e rs graben 31, CH-4009 Basel. Fa x : 306 12 34.
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E C O,
Chemin du Lacuez, CH-1807 Blonay. Fa x : 943 36 05.
T H A I L A N D : Suksapan Pa n i t , Mansion 9, R a j a d a m n e rn
Ave n u e , Bangkok 2. Fa x : 28 11 639.
T U N I S I A : Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de
l ’UN E S C O, 2 2 , rue de l’Angleterr e , 1000RP Tu n i s.
Fa x : 33 10 14
UNITED KINGDOM: The Stat i o n e ry Office Publicat i o n s
C t r e . , 51 Nine Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR.
Fa x : 873 84 63.
UNITED STAT E S : B e rnan A s s o c i at e s , 4611-F A s s e m b l y
D ri ve , Lanham MD 20706-4391. Fa x :4 5 9 - 0 0 5 6 .
U R U G UAY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
Maldonado 1090, M o n t e v i d e o. Fa x : 90 59 83.
V E N E Z U E L A : UN E S C O/ C R E S A L C ,E d i f. A s ov i n c a r ,
Av Los Chorr o s ,C ruce C/C A c u e d u c t o, Altos de Sebu c a n ,
C a r a c a s. Fa x : 286 03 26.
Tools for understanding 
reality globally
U N E S C O
world reports World Information Report
1997/98
Written by leading experts from around 
the world, provides a global and topical picture
of archive, library and information services 
on the five continents and addresses the most
challenging issues that they face at the dawn 
of the twenty-first century.
(1997, 450 pp., 275 FF)
World Culture Report 1998
Culture, Creativity and Markets
Hard and comparative data in the hybrid field 
of culture and development to understand issues
such as the room left for different approaches 
to development in the face of globalization and 
the conditions of indigenous cultures.
The reputed specialists contributing to this 
first World Culture Report maintain that many
local cultures and art forms are stimulated by
intercultural contact and global markets, rather
than crushed by them.
(1998, 488 pp., 260 FF)
World Education Report
1998
Teachers and Teaching in a Changing
World
A global review of the status and working
conditions of teachers (the largest profession in
the world) and of trends in teaching and learning
based on recent developments in educational
systems and policies. Also reviews the impact of
new technologies on teaching and their potential
to take learning beyond the classroom.
(1998, 178 pp., 150 FF)
U N E S C O P u b l i s h i n g
7, place de Fontenoy, 75732 Paris 07 SP
Fax : 01 45 68 57 41
Internet : http://www.unesco.org/publications
World Communication
Report
The media and the challenge 
of the new technologies
This worldwide picture describes the impact of
the new information technologies on the
workplace, the media, culture and intellectual
property. It also examines the relationships
between power, information and democracy.
(1998, 280 pp., 250 FF)
World Science Report 1998
Describes the organization and conduct of
science and technology around the world, and
trends in science higher education and in
research and development. Examines major
problems encountered by each region and the
role played by science in resolving major issues
facing human society – food security and water
resources.
(1998, 288 pp., 344 FF
UNESCO Publishing/Elsevier)
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Do s s i e r:
Science and technology:
public service or private enterprise?
n How the private sector is shaking up research
n Globalization: redrawing the R and D map
n Winners and losers: are social needs being met?
n Towards a new contract between scientists and society
Features include:
n Impressions of Istanbul
n Antarctic pollution: a threatened no-man’s-land
n The environment in the classroom
n Child labour: discordant voices
n Direct democracy in Mali: building on tradition
n Activist humour: interview with British comedian Mark Thomas
]]>
</page>
</document>
