<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="116241eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Fe a t u res include:
n M a d a g a s c a r ’s u n d a u n t e d
s t reet children 
n A virtual library on the We b
n G u rdev Singh Khush,
masterminding a new rice re v o l u t i o n
Focus   the South:
the big city or bust
theC o u rie r
June 1999
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
52nd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat
Photoengraving:Eric Frogé
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian:Gianluca Formichi,Sira Miori (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e : Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UN E S C O or those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. P h o t o
captions and headlines are written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r
s t a f f. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O o r
the United Nations. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7
Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfil m s
( X e r o x ) , Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C . R .
Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d , Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - JUNE 1999
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Pa r i s
by UN E S C O. Printed in Fr a n c e. Periodicals postage paid at
Champlain NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N°6-1999-OPI 99-583 A
C o n t e n t s
June 1999
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 M a d a g a s c a r ’s undaunted street childre n
Photos by Rip Hopkins, text by Adelson Razafy
EDITORIAL
9 C i t i e s, cititizens and civilization Federico Mayor
PLANET
10 Space law lifts off for a new odyssey Amy Otchet
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Colombia exports its ‘new school’ blueprint Asbel López
16 G u a t e m a l a :m o t i vation and multispeed learning Mirja Va l d é s
ETHICS
3 7 Dead-end seeds yield a harvest of re v o l t Ethirajan Anbarasan
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 C racking the code of art’s allure Anthony Freeman
CONNEXIONS
43 A virtual library on the We b Sophie Boukhari
45 2,000 world classics online Sam T. We l l e r
TALKING TO…
46 G u rdev Singh Khush, masterminding a new rice re v o l u t i o n
C o v e r : A slum in Johannesburg (South A f r i c a ) . Most of the people who live there are immigrants
from Mozambique. © James Nachtwey/Magnum, Paris
17 FOCUS
The South:
the big city
or bust
Unprecedented numbers of people 
are pouring into the towns and cities 
of the developing countries.
How are they coping with life 
in mega-cities that are already 
bursting at the seams? 
Some answers emerge from 
reports on Lagos, Jakarta, Brasilia 
and Shanghai.
For detailed table of contents see page 17.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
n
A lat e - e vening downpour drenches
A n t a n a n a ri vo, the capital of Mada-
g a s c a r ,k n own as Tana for short .H u g e
drops thud on the outside of a cardboard box
which once contained a fridge but is now
propped up against a grey wa l l .I n s i d e ,s n u g l y
wrapped in jute sacks, Rado and Toky cling
to each other and try to get some sleep.
But the floor of their “ c a b i n ” is soaked.
Groping their way in the darkness,the two
M a d a g a s c a r ’s
u n d a u n t e d
street children
A n t a n a n a r i v o ’s boay kely sleep rough and live hard , but they
a re still childre n , with childre n ’s fears, laughter and high spirits
Adelson Razafy
Journalist in Antananarivo, Madagascar.
Above, blackened by exhaust fumes, the tunnel under
Tana’s city centre serves as a dormitory for children,
especially during the rainy season.
Below, running after cars can be fun.
Photos by Rip Hopkins
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
b oys get up and sit on makeshift stools,
which are in fact big stones that stop their
abode from blowing away on days when
the wind is strong. With his feet on the
waterlogged ground and head dow n ,e i g h t -
year-old Toky tells his story.
“This reminds me of my first night in
Ta n a . We ’d just arri ve d — my father and
mother, my three brothers and sisters and
me—when it started pouring.We slept on
the gr o u n d , under a shopfront awning with
other poor people.The next morning, my
little sister complained that people had
been groping her all night. Since then, my
family has preferred to live in a cabin like
ours, near the route-taxi station where my
father sells maize pancakes.
“But I stay here because it’s close to the
m a r k e t . Before we came to Ta n a , we live d
near A n j o z o r o b e , in the nort h , where my
father worked in the paddy fie l d s. He gave
half of the harvest to the ow n e r ,e ven though
he was the one who paid for the seedlings,f e r-
tilizer and pesticides. One day, the ow n e r
asked for two-thirds instead of half. T h at ’s
when my father decided to leave for Ta n a .”
The other boy,R a d o,has never lived in the
Hygiene goes by the board when scraps are the
only form of sustenance. Top, children rummage
through fishmongers’ waste.
Above and left, in Antanarivo’s Analakely market,
street children set up stands for traders or carry
shopping for the well-to-do.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
c o u n t ry s i d e .“When I was little,we lived in one
room with electri c i t y,”he said.“But my fat h e r
drank and didn’t pay the rent. One day, we
were thrown out onto the street.”
When dawn breaks, the two boys craw l
out of the now-shapeless box .They will have
to find somewhere else to sleep before night
falls again. But this isn’t the time to be loo-
k i n g .The market is starting up and the firs t
t rucks are arriving with goods to sell. T h e
b oys have to rush off and set up stalls for five
t r a d e rs who employ them.With the pittance
they earn doing that , they can buy a meagr e
b r e a k fast at a corner stand—some tea (in
fa c t , hot water with sugar in it) and two ri c e
p a n c a k e s.When business is good, they treat
t h e m s e l ves to a cup of coffee with milk.
After that , Rado and Toky make for the
main entrance of the market, where they
mingle with a crowd of other children, a l l
waiting for the arri val of well-off ladies in
c a rs whose purchases they will offer to carry
for a small fee. Rado knows the tricks of the
t r a d e .You have to avoid the talkat i ve ones,w h o
spend hours nat t e ring to the shopkeepers ,
and the tight-fisted ones, who are always hag-
gling about the price of what they bu y.
In waste dumps, children scavenge whatever
they can find,including chunks of unused coal.
Right, the dump adjoining Anosibé market in
Antananarivo. Below, a smoking garbage dump
on the city’s outskirts, where Raoulatsh and his
friends struggle to survive. Young scavengers are
looked down upon as unclean by those who have
managed to land a menial job.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A lost g e n e r a t i o n
If there is one country where the term “ l o s t
g e n e r a t i o n ” means something, i t ’s Madagascar.
The 45% of its 14 million inhabitants who are
under 15 will confirm that. Since the time they
were born, the economy of their island, in the
Indian Ocean off the coast of Mozambique, has
steadily deteriorated.
Between 1980 and 1995, per capita income
shrank by an average 3% every year,according to
UN fig u r e s. Daily calorie intake per person has
fallen by 22% since 1970 and 34% of children
under five are malnourished. A recent study by
the country’s national statistics institute, I n s t a t ,
showed that nearly half the infants below the age
of three suffer from retarded growth—the highest
proportion in Africa—and that one child in six
dies before reaching the age of fiv e.
Education figures for the island—which,at
592,000 sq km, is the fourth largest in the world—
are just as gloomy.School attendance between the
ages of 6 and 23 nearly halved, from 60% to
3 3 % , between 1970 and 1995, and nearly three-
quarters of all schoolchildren fail to complete
primary school.
To d a y, 72% of the Malagasy live on less than
a dollar a day, despite the fact that their land
has abundant agricultural and mineral resources.
The island also has tremendous tourist poten-
tial.In 1997,the country’s foreign debt reached
$4.4 billion—120% of gross domestic product
(GDP). This disastrous economic situation is the
result of several decades of political turmoil and
administrative disorder.
A n t a n a n a r i v o
A n t s i r a b e
Fi a n a r a n t s o a
To l i a r a
M a h a j a n g a
To a m a s i n a
A n j o z o r o b e
A n t s i r a n a n a
Mozambique Channel
Indian Ocean
Rado used to look after cars parked near
the market, which was less tiring and better
p a i d . But older children have seized control
of that and chase off any younger ones who
t ry to edge their way in. Rado also know s
there are two things he will never do again—
ru m m a ging in garbage cans and beggi n g .
“The garbage boy s ” are looked down on as
idle and dirty by the other b o ay kely, a s
M a d a g a s c a r ’s street children are called. R a d o
is 12 ye a rs old and because he is in good
h e a l t h , no one takes pity on him any more.
Like all the capital’s boay kely—which
the NGO Médecins sans Frontières ( D o c-
t o rs Without Borders) estimated in 1997 to
number 3,500 out of the city’s one million
i n h a b i t a n t s — R a d o ’s wo rst fear is of crack-
downs by city officials. The last one dates
back to the summer of 1997, when there
was a clean-up before the Jeux de la Fran-
cophonie, an international sporting event
b ri n ging together countries that use French
as a common language. Shacks were torn
d own and the street children were taken
off and dumped in a reception centre 50 km
outside the city. But they all ran away
because the rules and the staff were too
s t ri c t . The children walked back to the
capital, living off petty thieving along the
way. After the Games ended, they we r e
back at the market again.
Disease is another threat to street chil-
d r e n . The oldest ones remember typhus.
But not Rado. He surv i ved the bu b o n i c
plague epidemic which occurred in 1997-
9 8 .The disease first broke out in a slum just
b e l ow the market and then gradually spread
among the street children. Some of them
watched as the fatal swellings twisted their
arms.The health authorities responded by
knocking down all the shacks and dousing
the area with clouds of chemicals. M a ny of
the children died. Rado was shocked by
w h at surv i vo rs told him when they return e d
from hospital—that the nurses and wo m e n
attendants had balked at treating the sick
c h i l d r e n , who were dirty and smelly and not
in a position to give them a tip.
Are the boay kely condemned to spend
all their lives on the streets? Probably.The
Things have been a shade better since 1997,
when the economic growth rate (3.7%) topped
population growth (2.8%) for the first time in many
y e a r s. The upturn was maintained last year. M a n y
credit the improvement to the rapid switch to a
m a r ket economy and a democratic system after a
long period of “true socialism”.But in Madagascar,
as elsewhere in sub-Saharan A f r i c a , the remedy of
liberalism may not be enough to roll back poverty.
n
Above, begging at car windows. Children 
with a handicap or carrying a baby are more
likely to get attention.
For the youngest children,left,begging is the
only means of survival.
Far left below, teenagers on the street have their
own children who are left to fend for themselves
during the day, when their parents go to work.
Below, playing a game of hide and seek in a skip.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
girls often end up as prostitutes and the
b oys doing odd jobs. The port e rs , c a r
wa s h e rs , illegal ve n d o rs , b a rr ow haulers ,
water carri e rs and pickpockets were all once
street children. D o - g o o d e rs like Lazari s t
priests or NGOs which campaign against
child labour try to change their lives by
sending them to school. But the children
often rebel. H ow can they do “ h o m e wo r k ”
when they have no home, no table, no light?
W h at ’s the point of “doing nothing” i n
school all day when there’s nothing to eat at
the end of it?
Rado knows he will never escape his
present condition. He envies the few boay
k e l y who have been adopted by foreign
fa m i l i e s. Sometimes photos get passed
around among the boys at the market—
pictures of well-fed yo u n g s t e rs posing with
a grin in front of some place like the Eiffel
Tower. Rado has no chance of that happe-
ning because he’s older than eight, t h e
maximum age for adoption.
But he can still laugh and have fun. Pa s-
sers-by are always surprised that the boay
k e l y are cheerful.They live from day to day
and don’t wo rry too much about the future.
For them, a good day is one when they eat .
And as this good fortune is often enjoyed
inside the likes of an empty refri g e r at o r
b ox , they laugh as much—if not more—
than in a fancy villa. n
Top, during the week,Dominique and Emma live
in the street. On Sundays, they visit Emma’s
parents, in a slum on Tana’s outskirts.
Above, a detention centre in Ambouimangakely.
This institution finances itself by raising chickens,
which are tended by the detained teenagers.
Below, children swing on the gates at the
entrance of Antananarivo’s central park as they
wait for passersby.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E D I TO R I A L
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 9
n
In 1995, UNESCO created a Cities for Peace Prize to pay tribute to city governments
which have succeeded in “strengthening social solidari t y, i m p r oving living conditions
in troubled neighbourhoods and developing genuine urban harm o ny ” .E ve ry two ye a rs ,
five cities,each from a different world region, are thus recognized.
The gove rnance of cities has become a vital issue of our time and UN E S C O’s Management
of Social Tr a n s f o rm ation (MOST) progr a m m e , launched in 1994, includes studies of change
in urban settings which are reported back to city offic i a l s. UN E S C O b e l i e ves that cities, a n d
especially mega-cities,are the laboratory of a new age where the future of humanity will
be decided.
Most of the world’s population will be concentrated in cities by the beginning of the
next century, and the percentage of people living in urban areas will have just about 
doubled between 1950 and 2015. The numbers of city-dwe l l e rs will have increased 
fivefold over the same period,and the number of people living in cities of over a million
will have gr own more than eightfold.This dizzying rate of urbanizat i o n , which is going on
as headlong as ever in most poor countri e s , upsets the natural equilibrium and the checks
and balances which have always operated up until now.
Cities consume enormous amounts of energy, exhaust water supplies, and devour food
and materials. In exchange,they pour out sewage and pollution.Their physical environ-
ment is wo rn out because it can no longer provide the input or absorb the output.And city
g ove rnments are exhausted by trying—when they see fit and when they are able—to respond
to the basic needs of citizens by providing such things as housing, running wat e r ,s e we rs ,
lighting and proper roads.They often prove just as powerless—or indifferent—to use for
the benefit of the whole community the surplus energy and problem-solving ingenuity which
citizens have .Yet this tremendous vitality is the basis of the dynamic development of so many
cities today.
Between pressure from below and paralysis at the top, the city has become a micro-
cosm of the future of our civilizat i o n . It is in cities where lies the gr e atest danger of a shat-
tered society where people think only of themselve s. Unless we create links between all its
i n h a b i t a n t s , the unity of a city bu rsts apart . It breaks up into countless groups which deve l o p
along the lines of class, race,culture and religion.Such ghettos cannot come together to
f o rm a genuine whole. On the contrary, the way they close off from each other, s o m e t i m e s
i nvolving physically defending themselves against other parts of the city, c r e ates a kind of
urban apartheid.
The words city, citizens and civilization have the same root.A citizen was originally a
p e rson who had the right to live in a city and who, by exercising rights and fulfilling duties
like every other citizen, helped build a civilization.This means that the humanization of
cities is crucial for the future of all of us. And it is not an impossible dream.There are plenty
of examples,in the North, South,East and West,where it has taken shape.
But the price is the creation of a city administration in which people can play a full part
and which is based on a revival of true citizenship. Only in this way will the city serve its
inhabitants by using the creat i ve capacities of eve ryone—men and wo m e n , young and old,
rich and poor. n
Federico Mayor
The words city, citizens and civilization have the same ro o t .A citizen was 
originally a person who had the right to live in a city and who, by exercising 
rights and fulfilling duties like every other citizen, helped build a civilization.
C i t i e s, c i t i z e n s,
and c i v i l i z a t i o n
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
P L A N E T
s p a c e , d e b ri s , the commercialization of
space,and intellectual property.
“ E nvironmental protection”has a special
meaning in space. A bolt or a nail trave l l i n g
faster than a bullet at 75,000 kilometres an
hour can seriously damage an expensive tele-
c o m m u n i c ations sat e l l i t e .An estimated two
million kilos of junk are already in orbit, w i t h
about 110,000 objects between one and 10
centimetres and another 8,500 fragments
e ven bigger.And these numbers are expected
to gr ow exponentially. In 10 ye a rs ’ time 1,000
s atellites will be orbiting the eart h , up from
600 circulating today.
An orbiting junkyard
Yet the space debris problem may prove
r e l at i vely easy to resolve because it directly
c o n c e rns major powe rs with the biggest
i nvestments in  space hardware like the
U. S . , Russia and France. “ We ’ ve already
had at least one major accident, when a
piece of debris hit the French sat e l l i t e ,
C e ri s e ,” s ays Dr. K a i - U we Schrogl, a law ye r
with the German Aerospace Centre.The
accident didn’t cause too much of a legal
ruckus, though, because the “guilty” frag-
ment was ori ginally from a French launcher.
“But just imagine if that debris had come
from a Russian or Chinese launcher.”
While there is some mention of env i r o n-
mental protection in two of the three UN
c o nventions gove rning space activities (see
b ox page 13),there are no binding rules desi-
gned to limit debri s. “The United Stat e s
d o e s n ’t want anything resembling intern a-
tional regulat i o n s ,” s ays Schrogl, but many
other countries are pushing for a UN agr e e-
ment on the issue. I r o n i c a l l y, the U. S . is the
only country with national regulations concer-
ning space junk and, s ays Shrogl, the U. S .
g ove rnment is now in the process of streng-
thening these laws which are expensive to
i m p l e m e n t . It costs much more to build a
s atellite that doesn’t shed its spent rocket
b o o s t e rs than one that does.“When cheaper,
more polluting launchers developed by other
c o u n t ries begin to reduce A m e ri c a ’s com-
p e t i t i ve edge,we will find a U. S .a d m i n i s t r a-
tion favourable to intern ational ru l e s ,”S c h r o g l
As commercial interests and international partnerships dovetail in space exploration and use,
space law will have to be rewritten to cut a way through an increasingly dense legal thicke t
n
Send up a sat e l l i t e , haul an asteroid onto
it and ship it to the earth . . . .This may
sound like science fic t i o n , but it’s on the
agenda of an A m e rican industrialist bent on
being the wo r l d ’s first proud owner of a celes-
tial body.W h at ’s to stop him,a p a rt from the
cost? How do things stand legally, f o r
example? According to intern ational space
l aw, no one can lay claim to a celestial body.
But if he manages to get his asteroid down to
e a rt h , it will have ceased to be a heave n l y
body and space law wo n ’t apply.
As technological development opens up
commercial possibilities in space, a Pa n d o-
r a ’s box of legal questions is ready to bu rs t
o p e n .There is, for example, no legal defin i-
tion of where airspace ends and outer space
Space law lifts off
for a new o d y s s e y
Amy Otchet
UNESCO Courier journalist
b e gi n s. So while an aircraft registered in one
c o u n t ry needs permission to fly through
another country ’s airs p a c e , the situat i o n
would be less clear for a microwave - p owe r e d
reconnaissance device which is being deve-
loped to fly about 30 kilometres overhead and
is neither a satellite nor an aircraft.
Issues like this will take centre stage at
the upcoming Third United Nations Confe-
rence on the Exploration and Peaceful Uses
of Outer Space (UNISPAC E ) , which will be
held in Vienna,Austria, in July. Represen-
tatives from 185 states as well as industrial
l e a d e rs in the field will be attending the
c o n f e r e n c e , the most important intern a-
tional meeting on space affa i rs held this
decade.The decisions arising from UNIS-
PACE will shape the way we envision and
use outer space.Three major issues in par-
ticular will dominate the legal discussions:
A spacewalking astronaut floats in an
environment increasingly polluted with debris
from rockets and satellites.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
s ay s.“The United States would prefer to see
r e g u l ations set in a non-gove rnmental foru m
where they can do what they like. But they’ll
e ventually be forced to go to the United
N at i o n s.”
The issue of liability is highlighting a
major gap in existing international space
law. All the major agreements in this field
were negotiated during the Cold Wa r ,w h e n
states were the sole actors in space.Today,
p ri vate companies are increasingly invo l ve d
in the constru c t i o n , launch and operation of
space objects.Yet there is no formal licen-
sing system.As Shrogl describes the situa-
t i o n ,i t ’s as if countries have failed to set up
a driving licence system for space traffic, t h e-
reby setting the stage for intern ational col-
lisions.
Consider the case of the new Sea Launch
C o m p a ny which is launching satellites from
the high seas beyond the bounds of nat i o n a l
j u risdiction and therefore beyond the control
of gove rn m e n t s.The consortium is regi s t e r e d
in the Cayman Islands and consists of four
p a rt n e rs : N o r we gi a n s , R u s s i a n s , U k r a i-
nians—each owning about 20 per cent—
and the A m e rican company Boeing, w h i c h
owns 40 per cent. C o m p l i c ating mat t e rs
f u rt h e r , the ship and plat f o rm used for the
launches are registered in Liberi a .W h at if a
failed launch accidentally drops a rocket on
a fifth country? Which gove rnment will be
held responsible for ensuring that the com-
p a ny pays the damages?
A condominium in space
In the case of Sea Launch, the United
S t ates unilaterally decided to assume res-
ponsibility for political and economic rea-
s o n s , s ays Dr. Frans von der Dunk, c o -
director of the Intern ational Institute of A i r
and Space Law at the Unive rsity of Leiden,
in the Netherlands.“If Boeing was allowe d
to circumvent U. S . j u ri s d i c t i o n , it could
offer launches to China and other coun-
t ri e s ,” s ays von der Dunk, who explains that
a substantial amount of technical know-
ledge is passed on in the process of fitting a
s atellite into a launcher—a sensitive point for
the U. S .While a solution was found for Sea
L a u n c h , the bottom line remains, s ays vo n
der Dunk: “the law has to come to gri p s
with the complexities of the bu s i n e s s.”P r e s-
sure is beginning to build up within the
United Nations Committee on the Pe a c e f u l
Uses of Outer Space (UNCOPUOS) to
d e velop an intern ational agreement or at
least a set of guidelines to resolve questions
of responsibility and liability.
Intellectual property is also likely to
attract a lot of attention at UNISPAC E ,
especially in light of preparations to launch
the Intern ational Space Station (ISS). A
project involving 16 countries, the station
will be the largest and most complex stru c-
December 1998: construction of the International
Space Station begins as a U.S. node is joined to a
Russian module by the crew of a Space Shuttle
mission.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
P L A N E T
ture ever placed in orbit. A rr ays of solar
panels with a total surface of half an acre will
be connected up to a column the length of
a football field comprising a series of round
modules where a crew of seven will live
and conduct scientific experi m e n t s. O ver 40
space flights will be needed to deliver and
assemble the components of the stat i o n ,
which will weigh about 460 tons.The ISS is
scheduled for completion in the year 2004.
“ I t ’s essentially a marriage of conve-
n i e n c e ,” s ays Dr. Ram Jakhu of the Institute
of Air and Space Law at McGill Unive rs i t y
in Canada.The partner states are setting up
a kind of condominium, s h a ring the
expenses of communal services but retai-
ning control of their individual modules.
The stat i o n ’s law ye rs have had almost as dif-
ficult a time as the engineers.They’ve had
to iron out everything from visas and pos-
sible death cert i f i c ates for astronauts to
customs duties.Topping the list of techni-
calities has been intellectual property ri g h t s.
The ISS will provide an environment of
m i c r o gr av i t y, sometimes described as
“ we i g h t l e s s n e s s ” , giving researchers a
unique opportunity to study solids, l i q u i d s
and gases and the forces that affect them.
This may turn out to be a goldmine, since
scientists expect to make some phenomenal
breakthroughs in biotechnology, research on
c o m bustible and renewable fuels, p h a rm a-
ceuticals and the development of metal
a l l oys of unprecedented strength. P h a rm a-
ceutical companies are also whetting their
appetites. They have plans to grow in the
ISS ve ry pure and precisely ordered protein
c rystals which could be used to design new
strains of very effective drugs. Imagine the
s c e n a ri o, s ays Ja k h u , in which an Indian
scientist is allowed to conduct experi m e n t s
in Russia’s research module where he or she
discovers a cure for cancer.Who owns the
intellectual property rights? Now chances
are the two countries would broker some
kind of agreement ahead of time.But that
d o e s n ’t mean the Ja p a n e s e , for example,
c o u l d n ’t copy the experiment in their
module. Space is a free zone beyond the
bounds of terr e s t rial copyright laws and
bodies like the World Trade Organization.
“Should we try to apply traditional ru l e s ,
which are ve ry protective and nat i o n a l i s t i c,
or should we change the approach when the
i nvention contains a benefit for the whole of
mankind?” asks Prof . Maureen Williams,
space law expert at the Unive rsity of Buenos
A i r e s. “Obviously countries and compa-
nies investing astronomical sums should
be rewarded for their inve n t i o n s. But should
a formula with unive rsal benefits, like a
cure for flu, be licensed strictly on a com-
mercial basis or should there be prov i s i o n s
to make it accessible?” Here Williams is
e voking a major principle of space law
embodied in the Outer Space Convention
of 1967:“the exploration and use of outer
space . . . shall be carried out for the benefit
and in the interest of all countries, irrespective
of their degree of economic or scientific deve-
lopment. . . .”
The question of intellectual property ri g h t s
a rises in a particularly acute form in the case of
remote sensing, which has a wide range of appli-
cations, from monitoring deforestation to pre-
dicting mud-slides and improving agricultural
irrigation. It is also a somewhat elegant way of
r e f e rring to observation by sat e l l i t e .D u ring the
Cold War, most countries tacitly accepted the
fact that they were being watched or “sensed”
but this “ g e n t l e m a n ’s agr e e m e n t ” is coming
under increasing strain for two reasons.To begi n
w i t h , the technology has dramatically improve d .
The old remote sensing systems only had a
resolution of 30 metres or larger—referring to
the amount of detail, or land area, t h at could be
seen.The latest systems offer resolution of just
one metre. Until a few ye a rs ago, these adva n c e d
systems were basically in the hands of national
intelligence communities in the U. S . , R u s s i a
and a handful of other countri e s.The technology
‘Obviously countries and companies investing astro n o m i c a l
sums should be re w a rded for their inventions. But should a
formula with universal benefit s, l i ke a cure for flu , be licensed
strictly on a commercial basis or should there be provisions to
m a ke it accessible?’
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
is now making its way into the commercial
s e c t o r , and companies are selling the infor-
mation they acquire to the highest bidder.
“There is particular concern that terrorist
groups will be able to get their hands on
detailed inform ation about potential tar-
gets that they never had access to before,”
says Stephen Doyle,a former deputy head
of intern ational affa i rs with the U. S .
N ational Aeronautical and Space A d m i-
nistration (NASA).“The groups could go
through third parties to buy the data and
no-one would be able to trace them.”
For 10 ye a rs , d e veloping countries have
been calling for rules to regulate remote sen-
sing which they see as an infringement of
their national sove r e i g n t y.With high-resolu-
tion images,a company like Shell can explore
a developing country ’s oil resources without
e ven setting foot on its terri t o ry.As things stand,
a company can take pictures of a country ’s
n atural resources without the country ’s consent
and is under no obligation to share that infor-
m at i o n .The company “ ow n s ”t h at data and is
therefore free to sell it at any pri c e .The most the
c o u n t ry of ori gin can hope to do is buy the
rights to the dat a . If not, t h at country may we l l
find itself in a situation in which another com-
p a ny or gove rnment that did buy the data has
a better understanding of their resources than
they do.
“This is a highly sensitive and political
issue,” says Williams. Although the UN has
adopted a series of principles to ensure fair
access to remote sensing dat a , the fact remains
that countries being sensed have no right to
p rior consent, nor do they have a preferential
right to access the data.
Uses and abuses
of remote sensing
“We haven’t got a very good deal, to say
the least,” s ays Dr. José Monserr at Filho,
vice-president of the Brazilian Society of
Aerospace Law. “We [developing countries]
need a legally binding agreement to regulat e
remote sensing. O b v i o u s l y, g ove rnments and
e n t e rp rises from industrialized countri e s
d o n ’t see the need for a new agr e e m e n t .T h e y
prefer customary law ” and vo l u n t a ry codes or
p rinciples which, s ays Filho,“just maintain the
status quo.”
“ You must be practical,” wa rns He Qizhi,
legal adviser on space affairs to the Chinese
Ministry of Foreign Affairs. “If you set too
high a goal, you achieve nothing.” Instead of
pushing for a legally binding conve n t i o n ,H e
is hoping to see “softer instru m e n t s ” l i k e
d e c l a r ations and resolutions designed not
only to limit abuses of remote sensing but to
extend its benefits. “This could be a ve ry
p owerful tool for improving the env i r o n m e n t
and saving lives, particularly in developing
countries. . . .The principles for this co-ope-
r ation and fair access are in the existing
c o nventions but they’re just not clear or
c o n s p i c u o u s.” He is hoping that UNISPAC E
will spotlight the need for co-operat i o n
through declarations or principles which may
l ater pave the way for regional or bilat e r a l
agreements.
As one positive step, Shrogl points to a
new European Union policy providing scien-
tists with access to remote sensing data while
still permitting its commercial sale. “We’re
going to see national and regional legi s l at i o n
n e g o t i ated on an ad hoc basis,” he say s ,“ bu t
we ’re not going to see something like the
Law of the Sea. . . . The question is how to
organize intern ational co-operat i o n , not force
it.” n
UN heavyweights in
space law
l Treaty on Principles Governing the A c t i-
vities of States in the Exploration and Use of
Outer Space, Including the Moon and other
Celestial Bodies (1967):The most important of
all space law agreements;assures the free explo-
ration and use of space, including the moon and
celestial bodies provided that these activities
are for the benefit and in the interest of all coun-
t r i e s. States are responsible for all activities
conducted by their nationals. No-one can appro-
priate outer space.There is no explicit notion of
national sovereignty recognized in space, u n l i ke
a e r o s p a c e. 95 states have ratified the treaty.
l A g reement on the Rescue of A s t ro n a u t s,
the Return of A s t ronauts and the Return of
Objects Launched into Outer Space (1968):
The first humanitarian law for astronauts, this
agreement obliges all states to come to the
rescue of those in danger. 85 states have ratifie d
the agreement.
l Convention on Liability for Damage
Caused by Space Objects (1972):With space
debris a long foreseen problem, the conven-
tion essentially holds states liable for damages
resulting from their space objects on earth and
in space.While considered a milestone in sett-
ling disputes, it requires a substantial amount of
precision especially in light of growing invol-
vement of private companies in commercial
space activities. 80 states have ratified the
convention.
l Convention on Registration of Objects
Launched into Outer Space (1975): S t a t e s
are required to register every space object laun-
c h e d , including the object’s basic orbital para-
meters and general function. 40 states have rati-
fied the convention and registered about 4,900
o b j e c t s, including space debris and non-operating
s a t e l l i t e s.The registry is generally seen as a weak
i n s t r u m e n t . Not all of the states operating in
space have ratified it and even those that have fail
to register every object launched.
l Agreement Governing the Activities of
States on the Moon and Other Celestial
Bodies (1979): Designed to assure the orderly
and safe development of the moon’s natural
resources on an equitable basis, the agreement
has failed in political terms with only 9 states
ratifying it. Neither the U. S. nor Russia will sign
because of an article stating that the moon and
other celestial bodies are part of the “ c o m m o n
heritage of mankind”, a provision which also
formed the basis of the Law of the Sea. Th e
common heritage principle is criticized for being
too va g u e, yet states, particularly the United
S t a t e s,firmly oppose any attempts to specify its
provisions. n
In this false-colour satellite image of Tokyo’s
metropolitan area, red stands for vegetation 
and blue for buildings. Remote sensing systems
can now capture details with a resolution 
of one metre.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
n
At La Niña school, the teacher doesn’t
stand in front of the class dishing out
k n ow l e d g e . Instead he sits amid a
group of pupils having a discussion with
t h e m .The children, of different ages, wo r k
not at individual desks but around hexa-
gonal tables.The teacher doesn’t deliver a
lecture or give orders. Each child goes and
fetches a self-instructional guide and then
settles down to study.The teacher doesn’t
demand silence in class, because the school
not only allows but strongly encourages
discussion and group-work.
La Niña, in Colombia’s coffee-gr ow i n g
Andean province of Caldas, is a rural school
run according to the principles of the New
School (Escuela Nueva) move m e n t ,w h i c h
was devised by Colombian education expert s
who have managed to turn the disadva n t a g e s
of rural schools—lack of equipment, o n e -
room establishments and one or at most two
t e a c h e rs for children of different ages and
abilities—into assets, p r oviding a positive
e x p e rience which instils self-reliance,
responsibility and teamwo r k .
“The thing you notice most when you
visit a ‘new school’ is how hard the pupils are
concentrating,” says Ernesto Schiefelbein,
a former Chilean education minister and
n ow rector of Santiago de Chile’s Santo
Tomás Unive rs i t y, who visited the first “ n e w
s c h o o l ” in Colombia in 1985. “ S o m e t i m e s
when the bell rings for play t i m e ,m a ny chil-
dren are so absorbed they just continue
wo r k i n g . So learning comes easily.You also
notice that they’re always asking questions,
which is a ve ry good way to judge how
effectively they’re learning.”
Self-instruction
The wat c h word of the “new school”
method is self-instruction based on spe-
c i a l l y - w ritten guides (g u i a s) cove ring mat h s ,
natural and social sciences and languages.
These guides are something more than text-
b o o k s ; they suggest activities and exe r c i s e s
t h at can be done both in and out of school,
along with detailed instructions that enable
the child to go at his or her own speed.
So pupils make progress according to
their ability and the time they have ava i-
l a b l e , focusing on the subjects that interest
them most or which they find most diffi-
c u l t . At harvest time, they are allowed to
go off and help their fa m i l i e s , a f t e r wa r d s
resuming their lessons where they left off.
This has helped to reduce the amount of
special coaching needed and also dropout
n u m b e rs , which are considerable in
C o l o m b i a ’s small rural communities,
where between half and three-quart e rs of
all children do not go to school or else
drop out after a couple of ye a rs.
The guides have been criticized for being
too structured and for curbing teachers ’
c r e at i v i t y, but they are ve ry useful, i n e x p e n-
s i ve teaching mat e rials that can enable a
single teacher to run a one-class school.
They gi ve the teacher time to both help the
youngest children to read and attend to those
who have problems learn i n g .
The critics also forget that teachers in
developing countries are usually not very
well trained.In Latin America,says Schie-
felbein, there is “the myth of the dynamic
teacher who can work wonders with kids”
when the evidence is that “after six ye a rs of
p ri m a ry school, half the continent’s children
c a n ’t understand a simple article on the
front page of a newspaper.”The big adva n-
tage of the guides is that they can be easily
f o l l owed by poorly-trained teachers and
also give pupils a lot of independence.
Teacher training is a key element of the
system. Teachers have to learn to use new
educational tools which encourage both the
pupils and the community to get involved.
They also have to drop the teacher’s tradi-
tional authoritarian role as a transmitter of
knowledge. Each year teachers attend three
o n e - week wo r k s h o p s , and visit a demons-
t r ation school to “ l e a rn by doing” and see the
a d vantages of the new method with their
own eyes.
As well as using guides, the teacher and
pupils organize “learning areas”where they
collect inform ation and objects related to
c l a s swork and other aspects of daily life. Fo r
e x a m p l e , a natural science topic may invo l ve
having an area with sand where local plants
and insects are kept.
Another novelty of the New School move-
ment is the “school council”, p r oviding prac-
tical introduction to civic and democrat i c
life.It is made up of committees which look
after the school garden, health matters, the
l i b r a ry, discipline and sport s , and encou-
rages co-operation and leadership based on
the interests and daily lives of the children.
The La Niña school has a farming com-
mittee which organizes crop gr owing and
animal breeding. “What we want is to feel
To make up for the failings of traditional rural schools, C o l o m b i a ’s Escuela Nueva m o v e m e n t
o f f e rs flexible and efficient solutions which are being taken up in other countries
Colombia exports its ‘new  
Children at an Escuela Nueva in Colombia elect their school council.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
proud of being country people and to learn
how to use the land in a more productive
way,” s ays 13-year-old committee chairm a n
David Cabal.
Other principles of the New School
m ovement are that teaching must be
adapted to local conditions and lifestyles.
Parents and other members of the com-
munity regularly take part in school activi-
ties, improving buildings and equipment,
d o n ating teaching mat e rials and helping
teachers during lessons. In addition, they
encourage the children to be interested in
their own history and traditions.The guides
suggest collecting prove r b s , my t h s ,l e g e n d s
and accounts of how people used to live .I n
this way, the school becomes a living source
of knowledge about the community.
“The New School movement is perhaps
the most successful educational reform that
I ’ ve seen in more than 30 ye a rs ’e x p e ri e n c e
in almost 20 countri e s ,” wrote Richard J.
K r a f t , of the Unive rsity of Colorado, in a
1997 report for the World Bank and the U. S .
A g e n cy for Intern ational Deve l o p m e n t
( U S A I D ) . “The boosting of teachers ’s k i l l s
has brought radical changes in the
c u rri c u l u m , in community deve l o p m e n t ,i n
d e m o c r atic behaviour and in improve d
s c h o o l i n g .”
In 1989, the World Bank singled out
the Escuela Nueva movement as one of the
three pri m a ry school experiments in the
world which had succeeded in making edu-
c ational innovat i o n s , and recommended
t h at “the lessons of this experience be widely
d i s s e m i n ated among policy - m a k e rs in deve-
loping countri e s.” Since then, the model
has been successfully used in Guatemala,
where it has been adopted in its entirety (see
box page 16). Other countries, including
Chile, Argentina and recently Nicaragua,
have borrowed parts of it.
The Philippines is the first country out-
side Latin A m e rica to use the model to
improve teaching at all levels in its multi-
grade rural schools, which have a poor repu-
t at i o n . The Multigrade Demonstrat i o n
Schools Project (MGDSP) has set up 24
schools in 12 provinces. It all began with a
visit by Filipino officials to “new schools” i n
Colombia in 1993. Persy So, a UNICEF
staffer in Manila, recalls that the visitors
were impressed by the pupils, who we r e
self-reliant and responsible, and freely
expressed their thoughts and opinions
without fear of their elders.
The children in the Filipino country s i d e
who have been part of the programme have
gained self-confidence and show gr e at e r
interest in their lessons. Some parents now
prefer their children to attend these schools
r ather than traditional schools where there
is one teacher for each age group.“It’s like
being in a pri vate school,” s ays 13-ye a r - o l d
Adonis Corasay, who likes the fact that the
village school in Begageng, in Benguet
p r ov i n c e , n o rth of Manila, n ow cat e rs for
fifth and sixth-gr a d e rs , meaning that he will
be able to complete his pri m a ry schooling
there.
In Colombia, the New School move-
ment has survived difficulties at local and
n ational leve l .A study produced in 1998 by
U N E S C O ’s Regional Education Office for
L atin A m e rica and the Cari b b e a n , based in
Santiago de Chile, s h owed that of 11 Lat i n
A m e rican countries surve ye d , C o l o m b i a
was the only one where third-grade pupils
in rural schools got better marks than city
children in language and maths,in spite of
h aving fewer mat e rials and despite the pro-
blems of ill-educated parents, g e o gr a p h i c a l
distance and isolation.
Teacher training
Rural schools in Chile and Argentina,
which were also surve yed and have adopted
some of the ideas of the “new schools”, d i d
not show such good results as the Colom-
bian ones. Schiefelbein thinks this is because
they have n ’t systematically adopted the new
p r o gr a m m e .“Chile has only taken on board
a few suggestions made on five pages of a
m a n u a l , and Argentina is still trying out
the programme in just a handful of schools,”
he says.
The programme in Colombia has its
c ri t i c s , h owe ve r. Noel F. M c G i n n , P r o-
fessor of Education at Harvard Unive rs i t y,
notes that in its early stages, the Escuela
N u e va programme “ was closely monitored
and nurtured by persons who were highly
committed and highly talented”. But as
the programme expanded, it “became the
responsibility of people who had only
r e c e i ved brief training [and] may not have
been fully convinced about the concept.”
Some teachers may have needed trai-
n i n g, while others , e ven though they
grasp the new methods, are not willing to
include them in their daily teaching acti-
vity. An Ecuadorian teacher, Rosa M.
Torres, observed during a visit to several
“new schools” in Colombia in 1992 that
  school’ blueprint Asbel López
Unesco Courier Journalist
‘ What we want is to feel proud of being country people and to
learn how to use the land in a more productive way’
Working in groups and encouraging self-instruction are the hallmarks
of the Colombian method.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
G u a t e m a l a :motivation 
and multispeed learning
Mirja Va l d é s
Journalist in Guatemala City
n At firs t , some parents didn’t like the new
system at the “Queen of Holland” s c h o o l ,
138 km north of Guatemala City, b e c a u s e
their children didn’t bring homework back
with them.They thought their offspring must
be learning less. But their doubts soon
disappeared when they saw the progress their
sons and daughters were making. N ow they
u n d e rstand that the “ h o m e wo r k ” has to do
with the ongoing life of the community.
Ipólito A l va r e z , who is 11, helps his
craftsman fat h e r , but he is still learning eve n
though his hands may be caked with mud,
“ my homework is to ask my parents about
the village and its history,” he say s.
The school, in the village of Santa
Marta,near San Jerónimo, in the province
of Baja Verapaz, is one of the 2,084 rural
schools which are part of the N u e va Escuela
U n i t a ria (New Unitary School) project.
The programme, run by the Guatemalan
e d u c ation ministry and based on the
Colombian model, began in 1991 and now
i nvo l ves 3,500 teachers and about 113,000
children.
T h i rt y - f o u r - year-old Oscar Guerrero has
taught for 12 ye a rs in unitary schools, six of
them under the new system. “ B e f o r e , t h e
children were passive , timid and didn’t
p a rt i c i p ate much,” he say s.“ I ’d gi ve my daily
lesson in front of the class and they just
l i s t e n e d .When I asked them if they had any
q u e s t i o n s , no one raised their hands although
I knew they hadn’t unders t o o d .”
N ow things are quite different.The same
children will pipe up with a question. Fo r
e x a m p l e , after following the instructions in
their guide and observing a plant, I p ó l i t o
will come and ask about photosynthesis.
M e a n w h i l e , the other children are
discussing among themselves what they
have seen.
The shelves in the library carry about 15
b o o k s , with three copies of each.The pages
are all dog-eared from being constantly used
by the children year after ye a r. As in
C o l o m b i a , the school’s 32 pupils have
organized their own student gove rn m e n t ,
which is chosen using the same system as the
one used in national elections, with vo t e r
r e gi s t r at i o n , electoral cards and a campaign.
The school has two classrooms, e a c h
measuring six metres by eight and divided
into sections according to subject and age-
gr o u p. On one wall is a map of the
community drawn by the children on the
back of an adve rtising poster.To save paper,
before they start using notebooks,the first
and second grade pupils learn how to draw
shapes and marks in the sand.
The children are allowed to learn at their
own speed, so their education does not clash
with the harvest season when they have to go
with their parents to the coast. If the school
year ends and they have n ’t reached the
required leve l , the teacher just marks their
school report with the words “in process of
l e a rn i n g ” . n
+ …
l Ernesto Schiefelbein, R e d e fining basic education
for Latin America: lessons to be learned from the
Colombian Escuela Nueva, UN E S C O, I I E P, 1 9 9 2 .
l Noel F. M c G i n n , “Resistance to good ideas: E s c u e l a
Nueva in Colombia”, in Education reform in the
South in the 1990s, edited by Lene Buchert, UN E S C O,
1 9 9 8 .
many teachers were still attached to old
ways. “The ideal of progressive education
coexists with conservative and outdated
practices,” she said.
It is hard to say how many genuine “ n e w
s c h o o l s ” there are in Colombia. Twenty ye a rs
after they first appeared, m a ny of them are
“ n e w ” only in name. The “ Vo l vamos a la
G e n t e ” Fo u n d at i o n , in Bogota, reckons there
are about 12,500 schools operating accor-
ding to the ori ginal pri n c i p l e s.The number of
t e a c h e rs who have had some training and
still apply what they learned is thought to be
around 10,000, a big jump when you think
there were only 150 at the end of the 1960s
and just 500 in 1975.
The programme survives, despite the
ups and downs of Colombian government
funding, because of the tactics of the New
School move m e n t ’s organizers. O ver the
last couple of decades, e ve ry new educat i o n
minister has been taken to see a “ n e w ”
rural school and a traditional one.Official
support for the new model has usually fol-
l owed (even though it costs 10 per cent
more than the traditional one) because it has
the clear merits of improving the quality of
teaching and reducing the numbers of tea-
chers needed.
But to introduce a new way of educat i n g
c h i l d r e n , “which aims not to mirror society
but to change it,” according to Schiefelbein,
means top officials and individual teachers all
h ave to be persuaded of its va l u e .This is an
e n o rmous task, but a ve ry vital one. n
In rural regions of the Philippines, 24 pilot
m u l t i g rade schools have started putting Escuela
Nueva methods into pra c t i c e. In some cases, t h e
schools were built by the communities themselves.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 17
FOCUS
The b i g city or bust
Surviving the South’s urban revolution
18 Living with Leviathan
Martine Jacot
19 Mexico City—those confounded 
demographers
20 The urban explosion (map)
22 Lagos: the survival of the determined
Amy Otchet
25 Fear and loathing in Ikosi
26 Jakarta’s dispossessed
Andreas Harsono
28 Dismembered communities
29 A Brasilian’s home is a castle
Licia Valladares and Martine Jacot
32 Shanghai’s migrant millions
James Irwin
36 Urbanization and globalization
Jorge Wilheim
The number of people living in cities has doubled since 1975 and will
double again between now and the year 2015.This unprecedented urban
revolution, which mainly affects the Third World, is not just a question of
numbers. The appearance, organization and even the function of cities
have been revolutionized. Traditionally, cities have been places of meeting
and exchange, but now they are splitting up into enclaves divided by walls
built by the well-off and by social and ethnic barriers. In this situation, city
authorities are often powerless or acquiescent (see pages 18 to 21).
In Lagos (Nigeria), ingenuity and determination are the key to survival
(pages 22 to 25). Millions of inhabitants of Jakarta (Indonesia) have had to
rebuild their lives after being evicted from their homes because of pro p e r t y
speculation (pages 26 to 28). On the other hand, the authorities in Shanghai
seem to be coping with an influx of four million “ t e m p o ra r y ” re s i d e n t s, w h o
a re however only accepted on sufferance (pages 32 to 35). B rasilia (Bra z i l )
bristles with iron railings that protect people’s privacy, as Brazilian sociologist
Licia Va l l a d a res explains (pages 29 to 31).
Jorge Wilheim, one of the organizers of the United Nations Habitat II
conference (Istanbul, 1996) puts these issues in a broader context of place
and time. Cities, and thus our civilization, he predicts, will be shaped by
the ongoing phenomenon of globalization (page 36).
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
Humanity is about to set a new record.Nearly
two-thirds of the planet’s population will be
living in cities by 2025, UN population
experts say. Until now, rural people have out-
numbered city-dwellers.
World population, according to the same pro-
jections, will top eight billion in 25 years’ time,
including five billion in cities.The increase will be
particularly spectacular in the cities of the develo-
ping world, whose total population will double to
four billion. We are going to see an unpreceden-
ted exodus of people from rural areas.
The demographers’ predictions are only ten-
tative of course (see box on opposite page). But
the flow of people into megacities in developing
countries is well under way. Several sociological
changes are behind it.
Cities used to need muscle-power for the jobs
they provided, the experts point out. But today
they no longer attract people just because of their
economic potential. “There’s plenty of evidence
that they can go on steadily attracting people even
Living with L e v i a t h a n
In the year 2015, t h e re will be 30 mega-cities with more than 8 million inhabitants—
22 of them in A s i a . How will they cope?
when the job-generating sectors are in bad shape
or disappeari n g,” s ays Philippe Haeri n g e r , a
research supervisor at the French Scientific
Institute for Development in Co-operat i o n
(ORSTOM).
People no longer move to urban centres
because they are fairly sure to find work.They do
so because they want to leave the countryside
where there are too many people tilling the land
and because they hope to leave poverty behind.
Rightly or wrongly, the city seems to offer pro-
gress and freedom, a vision of opportunity, an
irresistible lure.
The result is that both inside and outside
c i t i e s , there are more and more squat t e rs and poor
h o u s i n g .U r b a n i z ation in the developing world dif-
f e rs from that in the industrialized countri e s , s ay s
Canadian town planner Richard Stern , head of
the Urban Communities Centre at the Unive rs i t y
of To r o n t o, in “the speed of the process, the gr ow-
th of pove rt y, the extent of urban sprawl and the
expansion of the informal economy.”
Martine Ja c o t
UN E S C O Courier J o u r n a l i s t
Fortress-type housing
complexes are becoming
increasingly common in all the
world’s large cities. Here, a
high-security dwelling in
Cruzeiro, one of Brasilia’s
satellite cities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 19
The South’s urban re v o l u t i o n
Mexico City – those confounded demographers
Medium or long-term predictions about population sometimes turn out wrong.One of the most flagrant examples
is that of Mexico City. In the 1980s, demographers warned that it would have between 22 and 30 million people
by the year 2000,making it the world’s biggest urban area,ahead of Tokyo.
But the Mexican capital today has “ o n l y ” 17 million inhabitants.According to recent reports by the College of Mexico
and Mexico’s National Population Council, the city’s average annual population growth rate fell from 5.06% in the 1970s
to 2.59% in the 1980s and 2% since 1990.What happened?
Fi r s t , the experts overestimated the city’s population at the time of the 1980 census and underestimated the drop in
fertility, which fell from 45 births per 1,000 women of childbearing age in 1965 to 28 per 1,000 in 1992.Mexicans were
also discouraged from emigrating to the capital by other factors, including the 1985 earthquake which killed more than
30,000 people there, and worsening air pollution.Thousands of firms were induced by grants to move from the capital
to smaller cities.They took their jobs with them.
So the flow of people was reversed. Mexico City grew in the 1980s at the rate of about 1,500 people a day, but from
1992 on there was a net loss of population.In that year, 661,000 people left the capital and fewer than 171,000 came
to live there.
Mexico City stands on the site of the former Aztec city of Te n o c h t i t l a n , whose 60,000 inhabitants made it the
world’s biggest urban centre at the time of the Spanish Conquest in the 16th century.Today’s estimates suggest it has
lost this title forever. It is expected to stay below the 20-million mark until 2015, when it will be only the world’s seventh
largest urban area.This is a great relief to the authorities, which were facing a crisis of excessive and chaotic growth.Th e
city’s population has increased tenfold since 1940,when it was only 1.7million,and its area has grown from 500 sq km
in 1940 to today’s 4,500 sq km. n
How are the authorities in the developing
world’s urban areas responding to such “inva-
sions”? In today’s deregulated world, the trend is
to question the very idea of providing the general
population with basic urban services, most obser-
vers note. For want of resources, cities in develo-
ping countries are increasingly abandoning their
public service function.
China is still an exception to this in seve r a l
way s. O f ficials there, in a context of ri gid plan-
ning—though this has eased in recent ye a rs — a r e
t rying to prevent the influx of more rural migr a n t s
than the city economies can cope with, as the
example of Shanghai show s. Can such a policy,
which works fairly well for the moment, s u rv i ve the
political and economic changes under way ?
At the other end of the scale is Lagos
(Nigeria), whose expansion is chaotic. About 200
slums have sprung up in this African city. Every
now and then, one of them is bulldozed without
notice and without heed for its inhabitants. But
Lagos survives thanks to the vibrant ingenuity of
its millions of citizens. Another revealing city is
Jakarta,where the authorities themselves have joi-
ned in frantic property speculation. As a result of
this speculation, more than 4.5 million people
have been evicted from their homes in the last 30
years, with little compensation, to make possible
the construction of high-rise blocks, which some-
times stand empty.
How do the original inhabitants of a city react
to the massive influx of people from outside? In
more and more cities, you see smart neighbou-
rhoods protected by guards—what Brazilian
researcher Teresa Caldeira calls “fortress-cities”.
In these fortified enclaves, built partly in respon-
se to real or imagined lack of security, the roads,
sewage system,schools and other community ser-
vices are private. Outside them, public areas have
been abandoned to the least fortunate members
of the society and the infrastructure there is
crumbling or inadequate.The middle and poorer
classes also defend themselves in their own neigh-
bourhoods. One surprising case can be found in
the satellite cities just outside Brasilia, where iron
railings protect the houses, from fancy villas to
the humblest shack.
Will the mega-cities of the 21st century be
made up of islands of “social tribes”—“anti-
cities”of walled enclaves,whose wealthy residents
refuse to pay taxes to provide facilities for the
city’s less fortunate inhabitants? Will cities still
integrate their inhabitants?
“The existence of a slum means the authori-
ties have failed,” says Anthony Pellegrini, an
urban development expert at the World Bank.
The bank encourages projects where the state and
the private sector join hands to help the less for-
tunate buy plots of land in areas with an infra-
structure. Other experts say the “anti-social”
aspects of globalization should be blamed. They
would like to see the big cities of the next centu-
ry return to their original function as a crossroads
and a meeting-place. n
T h e re are hardly 
a ny open spaces left 
on the globe. . . .T h e
planet has turned into
a boundless wo rld city.
Yakov Okunev,
Russian writer
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
Mexico City 
New York 
Buenos Aires
Los Angeles
São Paolo
Lima
Bogota
Rio de Janeiro
São Paolo (Brazil) 20.3
Mexico City (Mexico) 19.2
New York (USA) 17.6
Los Angeles (USA) 14.2
Buenos Aires (Argentina) 13.9
Rio de Janeiro (Brazil) 11.9
Lima (Peru) 9.4
Bogota (Colombia) 8.4
Number of mega-cities 
( m o re than 8 million inhabitants)
1975 1995 2015
World 11 23 36
More developed regions 6 6 6
Less developed regions 5 17 30
Africa 0 1 2
Arab countries 0 1 1
Asia 4 13 22
Europe 2 2 3
Latin America and the Caribbean 3 4 6
North America 2 2 2
Source: World Urbanization Prospects, UN, New York,1998
The urban e x p l o s i o n
The increasing number of mega-cities of more
than eight million inhabitants illustrates in
itself the major demographic and geogr a p h i c a l
trends of the past century. In 1950, only two cities,
London and New Yo r k , were that size. In 1900 they
were the world’s most populous cities,followed by
Pa ri s. In 1975, there were 11 mega-cities, i n c l u d i n g
six in the industrialized countries. In 1995, there
were 23, most of them (17) in the developing coun-
t ri e s. In 2015, the projected number of mega-cities
is 36, 30 of them in the developing world and most
(22) in Asia.
U r b a n i z ation is taking place at different speeds
on different continents. In North A m e ri c a , t h e
number of city-dwellers overtook the rural popu-
l ation before the Second World Wa r. In Europe,
this happened after the war and in Latin A m e rica at
the beginning of the 1960s.To d ay, these three conti-
nents are almost equally urbanized (75% of Euro-
peans and Latin Americans are city-dwellers and
77% of North Americans, according to UN esti-
mates for the year 2000).
A similar process is occurring in A f rica and
A s i a , which are still mainly ru r a l .Their proport i o n
of city-dwellers rose from 25% in 1975,to 35% in
1995 and a little more than 37% today.The turn i n g
p o i n t , when the figure will top 50%, is predicted for
around 2025.
In terms of numbers, the world’s city-dwellers
in 2025 should total 307 million in North A m e ri c a ,
566 million in Latin A m e ri c a ,572 million in Europe,
752 million in A f rica and 2,507 million (2.5 billion)
in Asia. In 2015, the world’s six biggest cities are
expected to be Tokyo, Bombay, Lagos, São Paulo,
Dhaka and Karachi.
E x p e rts say the rate of population gr owth will
e ventually decline eve ry w h e r e , but once again at
ve ry different speeds. B e t ween 2005 and 2010,
annual population gr owth rates are predicted to be
3.82% in A f ri c a , 2.59% in A s i a , 1.68% in Lat i n
A m e ri c a , 1.06% in North A m e rica and 0.24% in
E u r o p e . n
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 21
Bombay (India) 26.3
Dhaka (Bangladesh) 19.5
Karachi (Pakistan) 19.4
Calcutta (India) 17.3
Delhi (India) 16.9
Hyderabad (India) 10.5
Teheran (Iran) 10.3
Lahore (Pakistan) 10
Madras (India) 9.1
Bangalore (India) 8
Tokyo
Changchun
Harbin
Osaka
Seoul
Bombay
Bangalore
Hyderabad
Madras Bangkok
Teheran
Lagos
K i n s h a s h a
Beijing
Shanghai 
Dhaka
Metro Manila
Jakarta
Calcutta
Delhi
Lahore
Karachi
Istanbul
Moscow
Cairo
Paris
Hangzhou
Tianjin
Lagos (Nigeria) 24.6
Cairo (Egypt) 14.4
K i n s h a s h a (D e m .
R e p. of the Congo) 9.4
Istanbul (Turkey) 12.3
Paris (France) 9.7
Moscow (Russia) 9.3
Tokyo (Japan) 28.9
Shanghai (China) 18
Beijing (China) 15.6
Metro Manila (Philippines) 14.7
Jakarta (Indonesia) 13.9
Tianjin (China) 13.5
Seoul (Korea) 13
Hangzou (China) 11.4
Osaka (Japan) 10.6
Bangkok (Thailand) 9.8
Changchun (China) 8.9
Harbin (China) 8.1
1975  1995  2015  1975  1995  2015  1975  1995  2015  1975  1995 1975  1995  2015  1975  1995  2015  1975  1995  2015  1975  1995
n
World
n
More developed
regions
n
Less developed
regions
n
Least developed
regions
Population living in urban areas (perc e n t a g e ) Population living in urban areas (millions)
38
70
27
14
23
34
38
49
75
80
45
54
1 543
733
877 971
809
50 132
326
1
2 991
2 574
3 962
The South’s urban re v o l u t i o n
The 36 cities expected to have more than 8 million inhabitants in 2015
a c c o rding to UN pro j e c t i o n s, and their projected population (in millions).
Source: World Urbanization Prospects, UN, New York,1998
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
L a g o s: the survival 
of the determined
22 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
It’s rush-hour near the stadium in Lagos where
N i g e ria has just lost a football mat c h . Streams of
young men run through the street to let off steam
as crowds dive into the tangle of battered yellow
minibuses. A dozen passengers pack into one bus,
and the dri ver grinds into gear, lurching at full
throttle to gain a six-inch lead over his competitor.
The side-view mirror has to be pulled in for the bu s
to squeeze through.Girls balancing bags of water on
their heads edge their way through the traffic to ve n d
their wares.Toilet brushes,cutting shears,smoked
fish, hankies,inflatable globes and even a steering
wheel are sold by boys as the coil of traffic becomes
ever more ensnared.But the action never stops for
a moment.That’s Lagos—a city that moves, mira-
culously, against the odds.
A mighty 
magnet
I t ’s difficult to find the centre, let alone the
l o gi c, of this city reputed to be the most dangerous
in A f ri c a .Three bridges connect about 3,500 square
kilometres of lagoon, i s l a n d s , swamp and the main-
l a n d , where unlit highways run past canyons of
s m o u l d e ring garbage before giving way to dirt
streets we aving through 200 slums, their sewe rs
running with raw waste. So much of the city is a
my s t e ry. No one even knows for sure the size of the
p o p u l at i o n — o f ficially it’s 6 million, but most expert s
estimate it at 10 million (see box)—let alone the
number of murders each ye a r , the rate of HIV
infection or the quantities of drugs that pass through
the port of A p a p a . C o rruption is endemic at all
levels. A bus driver doesn’t even slow down to slip
a few bills into a policeman’s open palm to avoid
being pulled ove r.The rich barricade themselves on
two fortress islands, removed from the mainland,
where two-thirds of the population live below the
poverty line.
But to look upon Lagos simply as the archetypal
urban nightmare is to miss the point. L a g o s , as the
e c o n o m i c, cultural and, until 1991, political powe-
rhouse of mighty Nigeri a ,i s , for all its fa u l t s , also a
magnet pulling some 300,000 people eve ry ye a r.T h e
streets aren’t all paved with concrete, let alone gold,
but Lagos appears as an El Dorado in the pove rt y -
s t ricken countryside where work can be found and
dreams of the good life can come true. In reality,
most find it a daily struggle to make ends meet, ye t
an iron-clad conviction that those dreams will mat e-
rialize one day gives Lagos a vibrant beat.
If you ask Lagosins about the glue that holds
their city together they speak of endurance. Fo r
s o m e , it is a capacity to withstand sufferi n g .T h i s
helps to explain the much talked-about boom in
e va n g e l i s m .“ People are seeking spiritual solutions
to their economic problems,” s ays Pastor Ebenezer
B a b a j i d e , who opened his Jesus Generation Gospel
Church last year in the annex of a nurs e ry school.
But there is a dri ve that goes beyond simply the will
to survive.
Amy Otchet
UNESCO Courier journalist
Lagos is a city where near anarchy prevails rather than government. Lagosins respond 
to the chaos by relying on their own ingenuity to get by
On the Apapa-Oshodi
Expressway, a typical traffic
jam—locally known 
as a “go-slow”.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 23
The South’s urban re v o l u t i o n
“In Nigeri a , there is a spirit to aggr e s s i vely pur-
sue the good life,which you wo n ’t find elsewhere on
the continent,” s ays Felix Morka, e xe c u t i ve director
of the non-gove rnmental Social and Economic
Rights Action Centre.The oil boom beginning in
the 1970s raised expectations for a better life which
people managed to hang on to, even after the eco-
nomy took a nose-dive in the 1980s and the World
B a n k ’s structural adjustment policies made life
more diffic u l t . “ I t ’s as if people are struggling to
r e ve rse the economic dow n t u rn as individuals,”
says Morka.“Everyone wants capital to start their
own bu s i n e s s. This industriousness is ve ry Nige-
rian but the struggle is even more fierce and stark in
Lagos where there is such a concentration of pres-
sures,resources and population.”
Wheelbarrows
rented out as beds
Instead of exploding under pressure, L a g o s i n s
h ave pumped that much more out of the inform a l
s t ru c t u r e , which Morka calls “an incredible renewa b l e
resource that has been the military gove rn m e n t ’s
gr e atest ally.”This underground economy enables at
least half the city’s people to make ends meet. B y
taking the edge off economic hardship, the inform a l
sector cuts down the potential for political upheava l .
Typical of the informal sector is the professor
who earns 5,000 naira, equivalent to about $55 a
month, and takes on a second or even a third job.
Perhaps he opens a small food store to pay for his
daughter’s tuition fees of $85 per semester. In this
vast black market, vegetables and fruit flow across
the border from neighbouring Benin, their entry
eased by bribing customs officials who earn about
$55 a month.When the government cuts domes-
tic fuel supplies to meet export demands, the
informal sector fills the tanks of taxis and buses to
keep Lagos moving. Behind this informal sector
lies a powerful if not desperate spirit of initiati-
ve—wheelbarrows are rolled out of a construction
site at night to serve as rented beds at 20 cents a
shot for homeless seeking shelter under an ove-
rhang.When rain makes a market run with mud,
kids wait with buckets of water to wash shoppers’
feet for a few naira.
The informal sector is where a man pushes a
c a rt from one home to the next, making $65 per
month for hauling away garbage and then earn i n g
another $55 by salva ging the reusable junk.A tanker
pulls up to fill a 100-gallon water tank for $6 to the
owner who then sells a bucketful for five cents. I t ’s the
b a rter that takes place when a baker has too many
l o aves left over at the end of the day or the flu rry of
m o t o r cycles gathered at the street corner where
buses don’t stop.And it’s at the heart of a basic code
ruling Lagos, from the thriving fruit market to the
quiet fishing community: Do It Yo u rs e l f.
A maze of planks stretch into the lagoon of
E bute Metta, where about 400 wooden shacks sit on
stilts over the wat e r ,r e m oved from the surr o u n d i n g
soot and speed of Lagos. Naked kids swing from the
p l a n k s , while women bathe and prepare the eve n i n g
meal.“We built this place on our own,” says Chief
Johnson Aibe, by trading fish for wood from mills
nearby to build homes and canoes.There are no offi-
cial deeds or titles in this community. A council of
elders decides who can build a new home at what
p ri c e . H a rsh experience has taught these people
that the less interface with officialdom, the better.
They used to live on the other side of the lagoon bu t
in 1985 the government decided to demolish their
homes to build housing estates that these people
couldn’t afford.Many lost everything, never recei-
ving a naira in compensation.Their options lay in
r e bu i l d i n g, by their own means, on their own term s.
In some way s ,E bute Metta reflects a lost Lagos
of the 1950s and 60s, when people flocking from the
c o u n t ryside basically built small communities within
the city along ethnic and geographic lines.Today’s
cosmopolitan Lagos has moved past this tradition.
“Eko gbole o gbole,” an expression in Yoruba,one of
the country ’s 250 local languages, has a double
Fa c t fil e
The State of Lagos spans 3,577 km2 which includes the metropolitan area of about 1,183
k m2, of which only 728 km2 is dry land.A new governor and legislator were scheduled to take
control from the military administration on May 29,1999. The area is divided into 20 local
government districts (whose leaders will also be elected) which have suffered from severe
underfunding.
Population 
The most recent census (1991) reported a population of 5.6 million. H o w e v e r, it is widely dis-
credited because many of the city’s inhabitants returned to their villages of origin during the
c e n s u s.Experts generally estimate that the population ranges between 10 and 13 million, c o m-
posed largely of the country’s three main ethnic groups:Yo r u b a , Ibo and Hausa.According to
UN projections population will reach 20 million by 2010.
History
Lagos was known as Eko before the Portuguese arrived in the 15th century. Declared a Bri-
tish colony in 1861, the town of about 250,000 was divided into separate quarters for expa-
t r i a t e s, the indigenous population and migrants. In 1960, Lagos became the political and eco-
nomic capital of the newly independent Nigeria. By 1963, more than one million people lived
in Lagos.
In 1966,the military took control of the country and a civil war broke out the following
y e a r, unleashing another wave of migration to Lagos.The oil boom of the early 1970s, in which
the price for a barrel of crude rose from 30 cents to $13,unleashed a wave of irrational and
corrupt infrastructure spending on, for example, a series of major highways which divide the
city but fail to relieve the infamous traffic jams.The demographic and transport pressures conti-
nued to mount as the city experienced phenomenal economic growth: by 1978, L a g o s
accounted for 40% of Nigeria’s external trade and 40% of the national skilled population.Th e
world recession of 1981 sent Lagos reeling into the debt and runaway inflation which
continue today.The ongoing electrical blacko u t s, housing shortages, sanitation problems and
telecommunications logjams all stem from this period. In 1991,Abuja was officially declared
the political capital of Nigeria.
Economic data
According to government sources, 62% of Nigeria’s GNP is concentrated in Lagos, along with
about 40% of currency in circulation and 45% of the industrial labour force.Yet it is estimated
that about two-thirds of the city’s population live below the poverty line, while 60 to 70%
depend on the informal sector. Only about 30% have access to running water.About 6,000
tons of garbage are generated each day and only 0.09% of solid waste is treated. n
A town is like an
a n i m a l .A town has a
n e rvous system and a
head and shoulders
and fe e t . A town is a
thing separate from all
other tow n s, so that
t h e re are no two tow n s
a l i k e.And a town has
a whole emotion.
John Steinbeck,
American writer (1902-1968)
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
m e a n i n g : “Lagos is a melting pot”or “ A nything goes
in Lagos.” The bonds of the extended family still
we ave this city together. Spare rooms, for example,
are virtually non-existent as there is always a brother
or a cousin needing a place to stay. Church groups
also play a key role in celebrations and tragedies,
p r oviding a safety net of support for their members.
At the same time, Lagos is like any other major
c i t y, where personal contacts are the key to fin d i n g
a decent apartment or a new job. Yet in this city,
connections are also essential for finding basic ser-
vices like electri c i t y, s e c u rity and wat e r. For example,
p ower outages lasting eight hours are a routine part
of the day. Only the rich can afford a generat o r , bu t
the crafty will work together to lay cables and pirat e
electricity from a government building nearby.
Tapping into
water pipes
Break-ins are a major concern for rich and poor
communities alike. So each household in the neigh-
bourhood will chip in about $25 a month to hire
local patrols which go so far as to close local roads
late at night.
“Do not vandalize!” reads a public announce-
ment painted on a water main lining a highway.
“Stop the thieves who depri ve you of wat e r.” But in
a city where only an estimated 30 per cent of fa m i-
lies have running wat e r , tapping into a pipe is not a
crime but a chance for home improvement.
While complacency doesn’t gain much gr o u n d
in Lagos, the driving initiative has yet to spark an
organized demand or movement for socio-eco-
nomic ri g h t s. While the reasons behind this are
c o m p l e x , there is one obvious fa c t o r: over 30 ye a rs
of military control and human rights abuse with the
likes of the infamous General A b a c h a , who died last
A corpse lies among rotting vegetables in the
street of Ikosi, the largest fruit and ve g e t a b l e
market in Lagos.The killing took place the
day before,on April 15,when bulldozers were sent
in by the local gove rnment to level the market.
Barefoot, wearing shorts and a T-shirt emblazoned
with the name of A m e rican basketball playe r
Michael Jo r d a n , the dead man remains anony m o u s ,
probably just another migrant worker at the market
where 12,000 people scratched a living. Black cloth
c ove rs his face—the sole act of kindness his co-wo r-
k e rs can bestow. Only the local gove rnment can
r e m ove a cadaver but officials don’t dare enter Ikosi.
Normally, the market would buzz with lorries
dropping pineapples, plantain and yams beside
the labyrinth of ramshackle shops, stalls and
tables. Now a putrid mix of rotting fruit, tear gas
and tension hangs in the air a day after the local
government chairman, Mrs. Thorpe, ordered a
private contractor to demolish Ikosi, which she
An attempt to destroy a fruit market highlights 
the mutual suspicion between government and
people who have no choice but to take matters 
into their own hands
Fear and loathing in I ko s i
considered a fire-trap and a magnet for crime.
She maintains that she had the full support of
Ikosi’s trade union representatives.
Sevi Taiwo is one of those leaders. “We built
this place by ourselves,” says Mrs Taiwo, who has
worked at Ikosi for 30 years. Mrs. Taiwo claims
that she met with the local government several
times to discuss ways of improving the market’s
sanitary conditions. She feared that plans to raze
and rebuild Ikosi would result in rental fees
beyond the reach of the current occupants. Her
voice went unheard.
On the morning of April 15, police ordered
people to leave as the bulldozer headed for the
first shop. The owner pleaded with them to stop
but the police kicked and shot his 24-year-old
assistant,Bob. As the bulldozer moved on,crowds
threw stones and police fired tear gas and bullets.
But the marketers kept coming and the police
fled. Emboldened by the retreat, the crowd set
fire to the bulldozer.
Within an hour,the police returned with rein-
forcements. “People weren’t even fighting, just
running as the police fired at them,” says Mutia
Akintae, a student passing by. “As I ran, I felt my
clothes burning.” Acid had been thrown on his
chest and face, giving rise to speculation that
Source:Marc-Antoine de Montclos,
Development Research Institute, France.
Atlantic Ocean
Lagoon
Maroko
Ebute Metta
Original colonial settlement
Richest neighbourhoods
Relatively rich neighbourhoods
Relatively poor neighbourhoods
Poorest neighbourhoods 
Expressways
NB. Classification of neighbourhoods into
the 4 categories above is based on the
number of occupants per dwelling,
residential density, rent levels and income.
0 2 km
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 25
The South’s urban re v o l u t i o n
“area boys”, bands of unemployed men, had been
brought in to intensify the havoc.
In the immediate afterm at h , the marketers estimat e
t h at up to several dozens of people were killed and a quart e r
of the shops destroye d .The trade union officials are in
h i d i n g, widely suspected of colluding with the gove rn m e n t .
Women clear the debri s , while men patrol for looters.
M e a n w h i l e , the elders seek the support of the o b a , t h e
a r e a ’s traditional king.
The 97-year-old oba is indisposed. Besides,says his
secretary, Prince Jede Rokosu, the king’s authority
extends only over spiritual matters. “I have heard
of people being killed at Ikosi,” says Rokosu,“but
I have not seen anything.”Would the prince or the
king come to see Ikosi and to consult the elders?
“That would not be appropriate.” If the people
came to the king, could he present their concerns
to the government? “Events have overtaken that
possibility,” says the prince.
Two mornings after the confrontat i o n , a
human rights activist is brought to Ikosi for
consultation. Under an overhang, women sweep
the ground and arrange benches as a crowd
gathers. A prayer for peace is offered by Chief
Bamiro, an unofficial leader, before discussions
turn to Nwaogbe’s offer to file a court injunction.
Gradually, a new dynamic takes hold in Ikosi.
When the bulldozers first arrived, the marketers
were prepared to die rather than see their liveli-
hoods destroyed. But in the aftermath, there is a
clear consensus that bravery alone won’t prevent
another attack.The next step in survival requires
organization. So after consulting their people, the
elders decide to propose to the government that if
the authorities provide specific guidelines for a
new Ikosi, the people will build it on their own.
Despite the new resolve, tension is still high
with fears of another police attack.Tires smoulder
at the front of the market but deeper inside
bunches of plantain and bags of millet are on dis-
play as children hawk water and music blares
from a barber shop. The dead man still lies in the
street but Ikosi takes a deep breath. A. O. n
The Ikosi market,still bustling with life several days after the bulldozers went in.
year. How do you demand the right to water from
a regime which openly rejects the rule of law?
A new elected government is now taking the
reins and offers some sense of optimism. But “ e l e c-
tions are just the tip of the iceberg,” s ays Prof.A k i n
M a b o g u n j e , N i g e ri a ’s most famous geogr a p h e r.
“ To bring some sanity to a city like Lagos, yo u ’ ve got
to bring gove rnment down to the people by getting
them involved in decisions concerning their own
n e i g h b o u r h o o d s ,” he say s.“This is the only way they
can be expected to not just contribute to public
works but monitor the ways in which people’s repre-
sentatives spend their money.”
Concrete bunkers for the lucky
M . O.A j ay i , an urban planner, s ays that instead of
receiving gove rnment help in response to gr a s s r o o t s
p r o b l e m s , Lagos has been subject to orders , i s s u e d
from the top down and often causing more harm than
good (see article below ) . The district of Maroko,
which was razed in 1990, is the most obvious case in
p o i n t . About 300,000 people used to live in this
beach-front slum.Sitting below sea-leve l , Maroko wa s
regularly flo o d e d , with tides of wat e r , mud and raw
waste making it an unhealthy place to live and an eye-
sore for the neighbouring community of V i c t o ri a
I s l a n d , a fortress for the ri c h .
“The police just came with bu l l d o z e rs and told
us to leave ,” s ays Helen Omame, 5 0 ,r e m e m b e ri n g
the day 9 years ago when her home was destroyed.
“ People were killed in the demolition, children left
s t r a n d e d .”To d ay, she and her husband live with their
8 children a few kilometres down the coast at “ n e w
M a r o k o ” , almost a carbon copy of the ori gi n a l ,
where the lucky live in concrete bu n k e rs built by the
s t at e . Like many other fa m i l i e s , the Omame fa m i l y
were never compensated for their losses. At night,
the family splits up to sleep in the wooden shacks of
the market.“The kids are really feeding the fa m i l y,”
s ays Helen.“ I t ’s easier for them to find odd jobs, l i k e
collecting garbage and carrying sacks of sand at
construction sites.”
Ironically, this may be the up and coming area
of Lagos. “Everyone is moving out here fast,” says
a smiling Ellen Kole inside her new ice-cream
shop. While luxury homes with domed roofs and
sweeping balconies sprout on the horizon, more
modest families like hers flock to three-roomed
bungalows, lacking water, electricity and a drain
for raw waste. “The new government is going to
invest here,” Ellen announces. In the meanwhile,
her family and neighbours will make do on their
own as they push the city’s limits. Lagos moves
on, without a straight course or a plan, but with a
singular will. n
The city is not an
asphalt jungle. It is a
human zo o.
Desmond Morris,
British zoologist (1928-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
O n a humid tropical evening in mid-Apri l ,
H e n ry Muhamad Ali stood under a tall
billboard in southern Ja k a rt a .“ L o o k ! ” h e
said bitterly, pointing up to the sign above his head.
“It says eve rybody should apply for a building perm i t
when constructing their houses.”
Ali had good reason to be bitter.The billboard
had been set up at an intersection near the campus
of the Unive rsity of Indonesia, on a grassy spot where,
exactly a decade ago, he had been living in a house
legally built on a 2,000-square-metre plot of land.
Then came the day when he and his family we r e
forcibly evicted.
“Hundreds of police and army officers , s o m e
a rmed with machine guns,forced my wife and children
to leave our home,”he cri e d , adding that tractors had
been used to flatten his house.
All over the Ja k a rta agglomerat i o n ,m a ny middle-
and lower-class Ja k a rtans could tell similar stori e s.
They were the legal ow n e rs of houses w h o s e
c o n s t ruction had been authori z e d .Then they we r e
d ri ven out to make room for the skyscrapers ,r e a l
estate complexes and highrise condominiums that
have transformed central Jakarta.
Land speculation in Ja k a rta—and in Indonesia
in general—has been more intensive than elsewhere
in A s i a .There are several reasons for this. One is
t h at Indonesia has no progr e s s i ve tax system to
discourage people from accumulating land holdings.
(A progr e s s i ve tax system is one in which we a l t hy
people pay relat i vely more tax than the less we a l t hy. )
S e c o n d l y, Indonesian people traditionally like to
i nvest their money in land, which is considered a
yardstick of their social status as well as a source of
we a l t h . G ove rnment officials as well as pri vat e
d e ve l o p e rs jostle to accumulate land: the higher an
o f fic i a l ’s rank, the more land he is likely to possess.
T h i r d l y, Indonesian banks traditionally regard land
as good collateral for loans, and in the 1980s and
1990s competed with each other to provide credit
for land speculat i o n . They did not realize that
Indonesia’s economic structure was fragile.
B e t ween October 1993, when the gove rn m e n t
issued a package of deregulation measures which
included the liberalization of land ow n e rs h i p, a n d
June 1998, I n d o n e s i a ’s National Land A g e n cy issued
“ a p p r o p ri ation perm i t s ” to scores of deve l o p e rs
over a total area of almost 250,000 hectares.
An appropri ation permit allows deve l o p m e n t
companies to approach residents in a target area to
n e g o t i ate and sell their land. In practice, d e ve l o p e rs
often used strong-arm methods to force small land-
owners to sell up.
According to an estimate by the Ministry of
Public Housing, by 1999 enough land had been
“ r e l e a s e d ” by its ow n e rs to satisfy Indonesia’s
demand for new houses for a hundred ye a rs. In other
wo r d s , the speculat i ve bubble bu rs t , and one reason
Ja k a r t a’s
d i s p o s s e s s e d
Andreas Harsono
Journalist in Jakarta (Indonesia)
Victimized by speculative
development projects and arbitra r y
planning pro c e d u re s, millions of
Jakartans have had to start their
lives afre s h
City limits
(administrative)
Bekassi*
Depok*
0 5km
Tangerang*
Java Sea
Major roads
Urban highways
Railways
First colonial city
Second colonial city,
administrative district
The Golden Triangle
and its extensions
Fashionable areas
Most densely populated
areas
Residential area
Commercial area
Axes of urban growth
Port or industrial
areas
New towns *
A slum in central Jakarta.
Source:Jérôme Tadié.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 27
The South’s urban re v o l u t i o n
w hy the Indonesian banking sector is enmeshed in
economic crisis today is because of its non-
performing property loans.
In this “land ru s h ” the gove rnment ignored tow n
planning blueprints it had helped to prepare. H e n c e
the story of people like Ali.
At the height of the forced eva c u at i o n s , in the
l ate 1970s and in the 1980s, Indonesian newspapers
were full of stories about deve l o p e rs using arm e d
thugs to harass small land-ow n e rs and soldiers
strong-arming citizens opposed to what was going
o n . Human rights law ye rs tried desperately to
n e g o t i ate but in some cases they too were prosecuted
and even jailed.
Not all threatened home-ow n e rs took things lying
d ow n . Some organized resistance, and in one case
s o l d i e rs on an eviction mission were attacked with
s h a rpened bamboo spears. “ M a ny of these people
were actually killed,” s ays Pa n a n gian Simanungkalit
of the Center for Indonesia Property Studies, w h o
e s t i m ates that 4.5 million people were eva c u ated from
their homes in Ja k a rta during the authori t a rian ru l e
of President Suharto between 1968 and 1998.
When officials
override planning blueprints
For 55-year-old Ali this was not the first time he
had been evicted from his home. In 1959, w h e n
Indonesia was preparing to host the Asian Games,
his house was one of hundreds in the Senaya n
d i s t rict of central Ja k a rta that were bulldozed to
make room for the Senayan Sports Complex, t h e
largest in southeast Asia.
On that occasion he received a small amount of
c o m p e n s at i o n , and used it to buy a plot of land
about two kilometres away. T h e n , in 1979, h e
decided to sell up for a profit and buy the 2,000-
square-metre plot of land in Srengseng Sawah where
he would later experience eviction for a second time.
Before he made the purchase, h owe ve r , he took
certain precautions. He went along to the office of
the Gove rnor of Ja k a rta and to the mayoralty of
s o u t h e rn Ja k a rta (see box) and consulted the Master
Plan the authorities had drawn up to deal with
problems of Ja k a rt a ’s rapid urban gr ow t h . He wa s
reassured when officials told him that the Srengseng
S awah area was intended to be a housing zone. L at e r
he was issued with a building perm i t .T h e n , in 1989,
officials simply said that they had changed the
Master Plan. When Ali protested the Ja k a rt a
authorities ordered the soldiers to go in.
W h at happens to Ali and the millions like him
who have been expelled? Where do they go and how
do they set about rebuilding their lives?
A lot depends on their means.The authori t i e s
p r ovide compensation for evicted people, but this
is usually ve ry low. On average it amounts to one-
t wentieth of the market price of their propert y
according to Panangian.
The gove rnment tried to introduce low - c o s t
housing in certain areas, but its efforts were a drop
in the ocean and were soon dwarfed beneath the
forest of high-rise condos and skyscrapers.
Officials usually encourage displaced small
l a n d ow n e rs to move to the suburbs or to join a
g ove rnment-sponsored transmigr ation progr a m m e
designed to relocate people from ove rp o p u l at e d
islands such as Java , Madura and Bali to more
s p a rsely settled islands such as Irian Jaya ,
Kalimantan or Sumatra.
Those who can afford to do so move out to the
s u bu r b s. M a ny have settled in Bekasi, to the east,
and Tangerang to the we s t , which have become the
Fa c t fil e
Population
The UN estimated that the population of the Jakarta urban agglomeration,Indonesia’s
capital and largest city,was 8.6 million in 1995, having risen from 1.452 million in 1950.A c c o r-
ding to UN projections, it will be almost 14 million in 2015. Jakartans are drawn from many
ethnic groups. Sundanese from West Ja va and Ja vanese dominate, but Sumatran,M i n a n g k a b a u ,
Balinese and others are well represented.There is also a significant Chinese population which
was victimized during massive rioting in May 1998.Most Jakartans are Muslims, but Buddhism,
Hinduism,and a variety of Christian confessions are also represented.
Political situation
In 1966 the government declared Jakarta (total area 661 sq km) a special metropolitan
district with a status and administration similar to that of a province.The city has a governor
and five mayoralties: Central Jakarta,South Jakarta,North Jakarta, West Jakarta and East
Ja k a r t a . Central and West are the main business areas. Most government offices and embas-
sies are located in Central.A mayoralty comprises several districts (k e c a m a t a n) , and a district
consists of between a dozen and two dozen sub-districts (k e l u r a h a n) . Mayors are appointed
by the governor.
Economic data
Jakarta developed as a centre of trade under the Europeans and still plays an important
role in international and domestic commerce. Ja k a r t a ’s share of gross domestic product
represents 9% of the national total: 14% of transportation and communication, 15% of manu-
facturing,25% of trade and services and 65% of banking.Manufactured goods include tex-
tiles, footwear, clothing,foodstuffs, chemicals, plastics and electronic devices. But manufac-
turing is much less important than in other Asian cities at comparable levels of development.
History
In the late 16th century the Dutch East India Company built a walled city, Batavia,as a
trading centre.The Dutch built drainage canals and later an extensive urban railway system.
By 1930 Jakarta had 530,000 inhabitants, and included a Chinatown and a modern European
quarter surrounded by rural villages (k a m p u n g s) . In 1945 Indonesian freedom fighters
declared Indonesia’s independence and renamed the city Jakarta.n
High-rise blocks in central
Jakarta.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
D i s m e m b e red c o m m u n i t i e s
28 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
Ali may have been unlucky, but things turned
out much better for him than for millions of
other Jakartans.
Nearly half the population of the Indonesian
capital now lives below the poverty line, w h i c h
means a monthly income of less than $20 per family.
Property speculation has particularly affected the
slums where most of the poor live.
Ms Wardah Hafid z , who runs a Ja k a r t a - b a s e d
N G O, the Urban Poor Consortium, cites as a routine
example the case of the people of Kampung Sawa h ,
in western Ja k a r t a . In 1994, a government offic e
claimed the land. Initially the residents refused to
l e a v e, but finally had to give in after accepting a pit-
tance in compensation—between $30 and $70—
despite having lived there for more than 20 years.
When President Suharto fell in 1998, they filed a
lawsuit against the government.
Payment of compensation, however small, is by
no means a universal practice. Evicted people are
not in a strong position. The agents of the
promoters first utter a mixture of threats and
promises to each family. If the victims decide to
r e s i s t , they usually meet and choose leaders to
represent them.
This is taking a great risk, says Hafid z ,b e c a u s e
they are then marked out for a campaign of terror
by the henchmen of the promoters, or by the
m i l i t a r y. The evicted people are also more
vulnerable because they are usually squatters.
Some of them use their meagre compensation
to resettle in a distant suburb, but most spend the
money at once and have to look for another illegal
roof in one of the slums that line the railway tracks
and the river banks. “Hardly anyone becomes richer
as a result of being evicted,” says Ms Hafidz.
Property speculation is one of the main causes of
i m p o v e r i s h m e n t .
Such evictions also tear apart the social
fabric. Jakarta gradually grew up as kampungs
(“villages”) developed around the old colonial
centre. The social ties there were very strong
because most people came from the same rural
area. They even won some political and admi-
nistrative recognition,and each kampung would
choose a “chief” who represented them before
the authorities.
The evictions are destroying this community
spirit because people are being scattered all
over the city and its surrounding area. Hafidz
says the the problem of violence in Jakarta,
including increased conflict between neigh-
bours, has worsened with the recent economic
crisis. But the violence is also caused, she says,
by weakened solidarity as a result of the des-
truction of traditional social ties. n
main concentrations for the gr owth of
m a n u fa c t u ring employment and population on the
outer edge of the Ja k a rta agglomerat i o n . For the
poor it wa s , and is, a ve ry different story (see below ) .
Compared to many,Ali was lucky.When he wa s
e v i c t e d , he filed a lawsuit against the authori t i e s. A t
f i rst he got free legal aid, but did not work while
waiting for his case to come up and spent a lot of
time attending court sessions. After a protracted
legal battle his case was dismissed on appeal in 1996,
but he was awarded compensation of around 50
million rupiah ($19,230 at the then exchange rat e ) .
This was just enough to buy the 150 square-metre
plot of land where he and his family live today, a
kilometre away from the site from which they we r e
expelled in 1989.
When he lost his house, Ali also lost his
workplace—he used to be a we l d e r. Like other
displaced households, the family has become much
p o o r e r. If Ali had been allowed to keep the house
he owned in Senayan in the 1960s and 1970s he
would now be a ve ry rich man indeed since land
p rices in this desirable area of Ja k a rta have
skyrocketed.
Ali is now out of wo r k .His wife,Umroh A i n i ,t ri e s
to support the family and has opened a small kiosk at
a bus stop, selling soft drinks and peanuts. T h e i r
c h i l d r e n , aged between nine and 30, share the small
house with their parents.The three oldest sons dropped
out of school and found work as bus dri ve rs.
Displaced people like Ali lose their confidence as
well as their homes.They feel they have failed in life.
They also leave behind them the tightly knit social
s u p p o rt network of neighbours and relat i ves which
is a strong feature of Indonesian life. People who live
in Ja k a rt a ’s new suburban areas usually come from
a pat c h work of ethnic and religious backgr o u n d s.
M a ny people do not know their neighbours.
Those who live in the suburb areas face many
p r o b l e m s , r a n ging from longer commuting hours
to bad sanitat i o n , i n a d e q u ate telephone lines and
low water quality.
Clean water 
for 5% of the population
Water supply is an ever-present problem in cities
of the South and Ja k a rta is no exception. PAM Jaya ,
the water supply operat o r , is perhaps Ja k a rt a ’s wo rs t -
run state-owned company. In spite of 170 per cent
gr owth between 1987 and 1997, it can only supply
clean water to around 5 per cent of the populat i o n .
Displaced families have to rely on their we l l .T h e
water from A l i ’s well is still dri n k a b l e , but many
other fa m i l i e s , especially in central and nort h e rn
Jakarta,have to buy their drinking water every day
from itinerant vendors.
PT Te l k o m , I n d o n e s i a ’s telecoms utility, h a s
t u rned in a better perform a n c e .B e t ween 1992 and
1997 it increased the number of telephone lines in
Ja k a rta from 560,000 to 1.7 million, a 200 per cent
i n c r e a s e . But supply is still far below the demand
of Jakarta’s nearly 10 million people.
The trouble is,Ali couldn’t possibly afford to be
hooked up.When asked his telephone number, h e
smiled and shook his head, “These shoes I am
we a ring are the only ones that I saved from the
wreckage in 1989,” he said. “If I can’t afford to bu y
new shoes, h ow can you expect me to have a
telephone?”
L ater on that A p ril eve n i n g, when Ali was about
to leave to meet his wife, he described how he had
joined thousands of students occupying Indonesia’s
parliament building in May 1998. He shared their
objective: to kick out Suharto.
“ S u h a rt o ’s daughter built this inters e c t i o n ,”A l i
said as he left the site where his home and his dream
were taken away from him a decade ago. One thing
he didn’t lose on that fateful day was his pri d e . n
The idea of a global
v i l l age is ab s u rd ;i t ’s in
cities that tribes have
been re b o rn .
Stephen Frears,
British film director (1941-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Brasilia is two places. One of them is Brazil’s
f u t u ristic capital, built between 1957 and
1 9 6 0 . This monumental city, dreamed up by
t own planner Lucio Costa and architect Oscar
N i e m e yer and known as the central zone (plano pilo-
t o; see draw i n g, page 31), has about 300,000 inha-
bitants (as ori ginally intended), mainly the staff of
g ove rnment ministries and foreign embassies.
Much less known to the world is the other
Brasilia,the suburbs where middle-class and poor
Brazilians live. In the original plan, these areas
were not supposed to have more residents than
the central zone. But today there are 16 satellite
cities, forming a huge urban expanse containing
1.3 million people. And one thing always stri k e s
v i s i t o rs to this metropolitan jigsaw puzzle: t h e
number of dwellings—whether elegant villas,
humble wooden shacks or residential complexe s —
t h at are surrounded by metal railings.
In front of smart houses in Núcleo Bandeirante,
the oldest satellite city 15 km south of the central
z o n e , and in the nearby towns of Ta g u at i n g a ,G u a r a
and Cru z e i r o, iron railings often rise from the pave-
ment as high as the first flo o r , giving the impression
that people are living in cages.
In the poorest and newest suburbs, like Santa
Maria (which sprang up in 1994), Recanto das
Emas and Samambaia, many people even put up
iron railings round their wooden shacks before
they’ve been completed.The same goes for new
migrants, who continue to settle, though at a slo-
wer rate than before (see factfile), on the “edge of
June 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 29
The South’s urban re v o l u t i o n
A B ra s i l i a n ’s home is a castle
In the suburbs of the Brazilian capital, even poor families barricade
themselves behind iron ra i l i n g s. To guard against thieves, but also 
to proclaim that they have conquered a fiefdom in the city
Licia Valladares and
Martine Ja c o t
Licia Valladares is a sociologist at
the University Research Institute
in Rio de Janeiro (IUPERJ) and
visiting professor at the French
Institute of Town Planning (IUP,
Paris XII)
Martine Jacot is a UNESCO Courier
journalist
the edge” of the city, in country areas and even in
the neighbouring state of Goias.
The first explanation you hear for these railings
is the frequency of cri m e .“Until eight or nine ye a rs
ago, the satellite cities were safe places,” says Jesse
de Souza, a 35-year-old army officer. “But since
then,crime has shot up. Burglars don’t bother any
more with the m a n s o e s, the we a l t hy villas by the
lake in the central zone, because they’re too fa r
away and the security there is too sophisticat e d .
The buildings in the central zone are guarded
round the clock.
“But in the satellite cities, it’s much easier for
thieves. Everything gets stolen—bicycles, cars,car
radios, CD players, television sets from inside
houses.They tried to break into our house. It was
the railings that saved us.” De Souza was born in
Bahia state and lives in Ceilandia, a satellite city
of 360,000 people founded in the 1970s to rehou-
se migrants from the slums.
The private surveillance
business
M a ria de Jesus Pe r e i r a , a 40-year-old house-
wife, insisted that her husband put up iron bars
before they could be bu r g l e d . M a ny people are
unemployed in Santa Maria and theft is common.
“And now my four children can play safely,” she
s ay s , “I can even leave them outside the house,
behind the railings,while I run a few errands.”
Since the early 1980s, violence and securi t y
have been a major issue in Brasilia and even more
so in other big Brazilian cities and elsewhere in
L atin A m e ri c a . A whole industry has gr own up
around the demand for pri vate security and sales of
s e c u rity equipment—from intercoms to camera
surveillance systems—are booming.
The most extreme examples of this trend are the
condominios fe c h a d o s, p ri vate estates (houses, a p a rt-
ment blocks, shops and services) hidden behind
walls and which you can only get into by showing
an ID to watchmen at a guardpost. P r o m o t e rs have
successfully sold the idea of “peace and securi t y ”t o
h o u s e - bu ye rs. In the centre of cities and in the sub-
u r b s , such closed communities and other protected
areas are multiplying.They are, as Teresa Caldeira
describes it1, fortified enclaves for the upper and
middle classes. Their existence helps to increase
urban segr e g at i o n , with poorer people relegated to
areas which are still public but poorly equipped
with infrastructures or even derelict.
“Smile, you’re on camera,” reads a sign at the entrance to a bakery in Ceilandia.
The warning continues on the right:“Dear customers:we apologize for the inconvenience 
of these security measures. Please wait.The doors open automatically.”
1. See her article “Building up walls: the new pattern of
spatial segregation in São Paulo”in UNESCO’s International
Social Science Journal, No. 147, March 1996.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
In Brasilia, the central zone is itself a kind of for-
t r e s s , whose walls are inv i s i b l e . The only border
b e t ween the capital and the satellite cities, which are
situated at a safe distance, is a belt of green coun-
tryside.The guarded communities have grown up
on the edge of this green belt. But surp rising though
it may seem,the satellite cities beyond bristle with
iron railings.
Town planner Marilia Steinberg, of the Uni-
ve rsity of Brasilia, thinks the constant concern
about security masks more subtle reasons for these
measures. “Migrating to Brasilia was for all of us a
g a m b l e , an adve n t u r e ,” she say s. “I don’t know
anyone who’s stayed in the new capital or nearby
who hasn’t now got a better life.The railings protect
you but they also let you show off how quickly
yo u ’ ve gone up in the wo r l d ,m at e rially and socially.”
A wall hides everything but you can look through
railings and see the house and even what is going on
inside it.You can also see the car or cars—a sign of
success—parked in the yard.
Other observe rs agree that such reassuri n g,
effective and probably even essential defences also
play a symbolic role.The inhabitants of this other
Brasilia came to the capital to begin a life or make
a new start, dreaming of success.Yet such dreams
h ave almost been outlawe d . The building of the
central zone, from 1957 to 1960, called for the
h i ring of more than 100,000 labourers ( c a n d a n go s ),
mostly from nort h e a s t e rn Brazil. These wo r k e rs
lived in wooden shacks on the edge of the central
z o n e .After Brasilia was officially opened on A p ril 21,
1960, their makeshift houses were dubbed “illegal
s l u m s ” . But most of the wo r k e rs , proud of their pio-
n e e ring efforts to build a new capital, refused to leave
the new El Dorado. Other migrants eve n t u a l l y
arrived from all over the country and settled on
vacant land outside the central zone.
Faced with the influ x , the federal district autho-
rities decided in 1970 to improve conditions rat h e r
than trying to evict eve ryo n e . They built up the
i n f r a s t ructure of the satellite cities so as to head off
any haphazard “invasion” of the central zone.
The prevailing impression is that each migr a n t
family somehow wants to show by means of railings
t h at it has carved out a fie f d o m ,h owe ver small, a n d
t h at its dream has come true here in the federal distri c t ,
at the gates of what is known as “ o f ficial Brazil”.
The story of Cleiton Pereira Santos, a 23-ye a r -
old geogr a p h e r ,i l l u s t r ates this social ascension and
Playing safe behind bars in Cruzeiro.
Uninviting:high railings rise up around a private housing estate at Sobradinho, one of Brasilia’s satellite-cities.
To d a y, some people
c ri t i c i ze Brasilia as
c o l d , i m p e rs o n a l ,
i n h u m a n , e m p t y. It is
not our fault [that of
Lúcio Costa and Oscar
N i e m eyer] if Bra s i l i a
has fallen victim to the
injustices of capitalist
s o c i e t y.
Oscar Niemeyer,
Brazilian architect (1907-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 31
The South’s urban re v o l u t i o n
values ve ry we l l . “My fat h e r , who was from a small
t own in the nort h e a s t e rn state of Piaui, came to Bra-
silia to work as a mason in the early 1960s,” h e
s ay s. “At first he stayed with a relat i ve , and then we n t
back to fetch my mother.The two of them rented a
small apartment in the central zone. But they wa n t e d
their ‘own’ home, so they built their first house,
which was quite modest,in Taguatinga.Later they
sold it and built a detached house with railings in
C e i l a n d i a . My fat h e r , who has built up a small
bu s i n e s s ,n ow wants to sell that , buy some more land
and build a guarded house on it.”
Status
symbols
Brazilians of all classes want to own their own
h o m e s. Official figures show 72 per cent of all
houses are pri vately ow n e d , and gove rnment bodies
like the National Housing Bank have always encou-
raged home ow n e rship rather than paying rent,
even in the area of public housing.
But in Brasilia and in the rest of the country,
buying your own house is also a way to protect
yourself against another kind of insecurity—eco-
nomic uncertainty. Continual crises have driven
home a blunt message: that you can easily lose
your job but it’s much harder to lose your house
if you own it in a country where a government
social safety-net hardly exists. All the more rea-
son, then, to see that your house is secure and
that it keeps its value.A house is worth more with
iron bars around it than without.All houses in the
“other Brasilia” fetch a good price, even wooden
shacks.
The railings are part of this world of symbols and
va l u e s.They are also to some extent a counterpoint to
Costa and Niemeye r ’s central zone, with its ava n t -
garde concrete buildings and monuments.The inha-
bitants of the other Brasilia only go into the capital, t h e
city of the ruling class, to work there or to catch a bu s
h o m e . The railings are perhaps the response of the
poor to the social and geographical segr e g at i o n
imposed on them by a fort r e s s - c a p i t a l , a symbol of suc-
cess outside a citadel without wa l l s. n
+ …
The iron railings of Brasilia have not yet been written
about by specialists, but the following works describe
their context:
l The Modernist City: Architecture, Politics and Society in
Brasilia, James Holston (Yale University 1986).
l Brasília: a construção do cotidiano , by Brasilmar F.
Nunes (Editora Paralelo 15,Brasilia,1997).
l Brasília, Ideologia e Realidade: espaço urbano em
questão d’Aldo Paviani (Editora Projeto/CNPQ, São
Paulo, 1985).
l Brasília: moradia e exclusão, by Aldo Paviani (Editora
UNB, Brasilia,1996).
Fa c t fil e
The federal district of Brasilia covers 5,788 sq km and includes the central zone of Bra-
silia itself, 16 “satellite towns”and a rural area.
Population (official census figures)
The number of people living in the federal district rose from 546,000 in 1970 to 1,176,800
in 1980 and 1,822,000 in 1996.The population growth rate is slowing down,as in Brazil’s other
major cities. In Brasilia,it fell from 8.1% between 1970 and 1980 to 2.84% between 1980
and 1991.Internal migration in Brazil over the past 10 years has been mainly to the states
of Mato Grosso and Rondonia,which has relieved pressure on cities like São Paulo and Rio
de Janeiro.
Political situation
After the 1964 military coup, Brazil had 21 years of army rule. Civilian government
returned with elections in 1985.
According to the terms of the new national constitution of 1988, the federal district is run
by a popularly-elected governor (he had been appointed by the central government since 1960)
and his deputy. Joaquim Roriz became the first elected governor in 1990.Defeated in a re-
election bid in 1994, he was succeeded by Cristovam Buarque, but returned to office in 1998.
The governor, deputy governor and the administrators of all the federal district’s constituencies
m a ke up the district’s executive body. Legislative power is in the hands of 24 deputies
elected every four years at the same time as the governor.
Economic data
Twenty-two per cent of the federal district’s workforce are civil serva n t s, 14% work in busi-
ness and 53% in other service activities. Economic life is dominated by small businesses or
very small operations set up by the inhabitants of the satellite towns. Unemployment is put
at 22% of the workforce, however, according to an official body, CODEPAN (central plateau
development commission).
Official figures show that a third of all those living in the federal district own a car and
92% have television.Basic utilities are available to nearly everyone—93% have access to drin-
king water and 84% are connected to a sewage system. n
Town planner Lucio Costa’s 1957 blueprint for Brasilia,known as the central zone (plano
piloto) was based on what he called “two axes which intersect at right angles to make a
cross”or what looks more like a large bird.Along the main axis are the city’s chief centres of
activity—with at one end the huge Square of the Three Powers (executive, legislative and
judiciary) and the Ministries’ Esplanade. On each side of the arms of the cross (or wings of
the bird) are residential areas divided into superquadras (groups of housing blocks).The idea
was to build a city without road junctions, where “the car is no longer the implacable enemy
of people”.Inside the central road intersection complex is a huge bus station called
Plataforma, which more than 400,000 people pass through every day, coming in from the
satellite cities. Brazilia is on UNESCO’s World Heritage List.
SOUTHERN AXIS
(residential)
NORTHERN AXIS
(residential)
Bus
station
Square of
the Three
Powers
PARLIAMENT
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
Among the well-dressed unive rsity students
mingling just outside the gates of Shanghai’s
p r e s t i gious Fudan Unive rs i t y, three men stand
o u t . Dressed in surplus army uniform s , they  perch
on the curb behind small cardboard signs stuck in
p avement cracks.The crude signs adve rtising their
labour for odd jobs or construction work can be has-
tily snatched up and hidden should the police make
a sudden appearance.
The men, m i grants in their 20s and 30s from the
nearby city of Suzhou, n e ver know when they might
h ave to make a quick get-away. U n e m p l oyed for the
past month and flat broke, they have n ’t paid the tem-
p o r a ry residence permit fee, which makes them
subject to possible eviction from Shanghai.
“ We don’t have much money for any t h i n g, i n c l u-
ding the 15 RMB1 (US$1.75) for the monthly per-
m i t s , so it’s better if we stay clear of the police,” s ay s
the eldest of the three.
A steady
stream of manpower
Te m p o r a ry residents, the so-called “ f l o at i n g ”
p o p u l at i o n , are eve rywhere in China’s richest city.O n
b i cycle and afoot they stream through the city, ri n gi n g
bells and shouting out offers to sharpen knive s , s e l l
f ruit and vegetables from their carts or haul away old
junk and garbage. Like the three men from Suzhou,
they are ready to do almost any t h i n g, p r ovided it will
keep them in China’s city of opport u n i t y.
Such is the allure of Shanghai that an estimat e d
3.3 million of its 13.6 million population are migr a n t s.
Thanks to a thriving economy propelled not only by
economic reform but also an ambitious national policy
to transform Shanghai into a major Asian fin a n c i a l
c e n t r e , the city has turned into a huge constru c t i o n
s i t e .M i grants have filled the need for sheer manpowe r.
But for the most populous city in the wo r l d ’s most
populous country, the massive migrant populat i o n
b rings new problems, from huge strains on
i n f r a s t ructure to an exacerbation of a widening social
chasm between the haves and the have - n o t s.
China is going through “ u r b a n i z ation of a scale
n e ver seen before in its history,” s ays Wu We i p i n g, a
n at i ve of Shanghai who teaches Urban Studies and
Planning at the V i r ginia Commonwealth Unive rs i t y
in the United Stat e s.Already some 30 per cent of the
c o u n t ry ’s 1.3 billion people live in the cities.T h at
p r o p o rtion is likely to reach 50 per cent in the not-
too-distant future, according to Wu .
In a wo r d , the challenge is of truly epic
p r o p o rt i o n s. But so far Shanghai does at least seem
to be ave rting many of the wo rst problems of urban
swell common in other developing countri e s.T h e n
a g a i n , not eve ry city in the world has at its disposal
the tool that has been a  key to Shanghai’s qualifie d
s u c c e s s : a set of controls perhaps only possible under
a system of authoritarian government.
“China is one of the few places where there is a
d e l i b e r ate gove rnment policy that addresses
u r b a n i z at i o n ,” s ays Wu . One solution has been to
encourage the gr owth of small and medium-sized
cities around the country to take some of the
d e m o graphic pressure off the largest city.The other
pillar of the urbanization policy is to control migr a n t
p o p u l ations once they have reached a city. It is in
this latter area that Shanghai has shown its skill.
M i grants started making their mark on cities
soon after they were first allowed to move there in
1 9 7 8 , the beginning of China’s economic reform
p r o gr a m m e . Control on mobility was effected
through the hukou, or place-of-origin system.One
had to remain in one’s place of ori gin unless gr a n t e d
p e rmission to move . A p a rt from being illegal,
m i gr ation without official approval made life quite
literally unliva b l e : without the appropri ate h u k o u
card one was denied access to essentials such as
ration tickets for rice,meat and cotton cloth.
But the former constraints on migr ation we r e
a r b i t r a ry, imposed from the top dow n , and we r e
c e rtainly not compatible with the market economy
t h at was to develop after the Cultural Revo l u t i o n .
As the economy exploded, jobs opened up for
unskilled labourers ,p a rticularly in coastal areas
where most of the foreign and domestic inve s t m e n t
has poured in. In response, the authorities have
encouraged migr ation to bring in cheap labour.
M e a n w h i l e , higher crop yields and rising populat i o n
on a dwindling arable land mass have left the
c o u n t ryside with at least 100 million surp l u s1.The Chinese currency is called Renminbi (RMB).
‘China is one of the few places where there is a delibera t e
government policy that addresses urbanization’
As it learns to manage the massive influx of ‘ t e m p o rary residents’ 
that provide muscle for its explosive economic gro w t h ,
C h i n a ’s city of opportunity is treading a delicate balance between 
c o n t rol and gra s s roots involvement
S h a n g h a i’s migra n t
m i l l i o n s James Irwin
Shanghai-based Canadian journalist
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 33
The South’s urban re v o l u t i o n
labourers.
The hukou card system is still in place, but cities
like Shanghai today also issue temporary perm i t s
to accommodate migr a n t s.The temporary perm i t
system gi ves the gove rnment the best of both wo r l d s :
flexibility and a relatively strong level of control.
M i grants must first get permission from their
local gove rnment back home to work away from
their area of ori gi n . Upon arri va l , the fort u n ate stay
with family or friends from back home, while others
sleep rough as the authorities provide no
accommodation for transients.
Should they want to stay more than three days,
m i grants are required to get a three-month residence
r e gi s t r at i o n , which can then be extended for a two -
year permit issued by an enterp rise or local police
s t at i o n . Pe rmits are granted only upon proof of legal
a c c o m m o d ation in the city and of employ m e n t .O n
top of this, m i grants need to apply for an urban
e m p l oyment perm i t , r e n e wable yearly for a fee
e q u i valent to $8.40. Unlike blue- or white-collar
e m p l oye e s , street ve n d o rs and small retailers apply
for business licences instead of employment perm i t s.
Only after they have managed to make it through
all these bu r e a u c r atic check points are migr a n t s
legally allowed to remain in the city.
The temporary permit system means that in times
of economic dow n t u rn—such as that which has left
the three Suzhou men jobless for about three-quart e rs
of the past year—the authorities have some leve r a g e
to force migrants to go back to their homes. A n
e s t i m ated one in four of Shanghai’s float i n g
p o p u l ation doesn’t bother to register with the
a u t h o ri t i e s.
I g n o ring the law seems to be much easier than it
wa s ,c e rtainly in the pre-economic reform era. S o
much of the economy is now pri vate that one is not
n e c e s s a rily forced into contact with the stat e .At the
same time, the success of economic liberalizat i o n
means that food and other basic goods are so abu n d a n t
t h at ration coupons are no longer needed—again,
reducing reliance on state organs.A l s o, the numbers of
m i grants are so huge that it is impossible for the police
and other authorities to keep tabs on them all.
It is possible for migrants to achieve long-term
r e s i d e n cy, but the hurdles are substantial and ensure
t h at most will never make the gr a d e .For example, t o
make the leap, m i grants must purchase an
a p a rtment or house, which requires considerable
c a s h ; get corp o r ate sponsors h i p, which is usually
granted only to the well educat e d ; or marry a local,
which requires overcoming the considerable
Building up the modern city:migrants are ready to take on all kinds of heavy work 
in order to stay in Shanghai.
City planning has had
its day.The age of
c u l t u re is begi n n i n g.
Oriol Bohigas
Guardiola, Spanish architect
(1925-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
prejudice of the snobbish Shanghainese who showe r
disdain upon the floating population.
But while the state keeps close watch on migr a n t s ,i t
also intervenes to make sure they have at least the basics
of surv i va l .T h at help is motivated not only by a sense
of charity or social duty: the last thing the state wa n t s
is for social problems to fester and explode into mass
m ovements potentially challenging the political order.
Life for migr a n t s , while in many ways difficult, i s
n e ve rtheless not impossible. For example, on the city’s
n o rt h e a s t e rn outskirts at the long-abandoned Jiangwa n
a i rp o rt , sits a temporary residents’ camp sanctioned by
the municpal gove rnment three ye a rs ago. T h e
community is anything but fa n cy, and life here pales in
c o m p a rison with that of the middle classes and
especially the small, but visible class of new rich who
have made it to the top through a mixture of contacts,
s avvy and privileged position. N e ve rtheless Jiangwa n
is relat i vely clean and orderly—a far cry from squat t e rs ’
communities found in the wo rst slums of other
developing countries.
The site, home to 500 fa m i l i e s , includes a
ru d i m e n t a ry health dispensary, a few wo r k s h o p s , t i ny
fa c t o ri e s , small stores, a clutch of hairdressers ,
ramshackle places to eat , market gardens and a host of
other small bu s i n e s s e s.Young children proudly lead the
way to a school which, while ru d i m e n t a ry, does have a
t e l e v i s i o n , a stereo and wall maps of the wo r l d , and is
probably no different from thousands of other
e l e m e n t a ry schools in poorer parts of the country.T h e
t e a c h e rs , mainly in their early 20s, come from the same
p r ovinces as the migrants and thus share a common
d i a l e c t .The children themselves seem cheerful and
o u t g o i n g, and are all properly shod and healthy
looking—apparently enjoying the same sort of
parental attention that China’s one-child fa m i l y
planning policy has inadve rtently ensured for today ’s
youth.
The majority of the adults, who come from
nearby provinces such as Jiangsu as well as poorer,
hinterland provinces including Henan, A n h u i ,S z e-
chuan, leave the camp to work each day in nearby
Shanghai and its environs.To do so they must pass
through the gates of the compound under the occa-
sionally watchful eye of the gat e k e e p e rs , most of
whom are laid off wo r k e rs from state enterp ri s e s
and all of whom are bona fide Shanghai residents.
Second-class
citizens
Like other such camps, Jiangwan is under the
j u risdiction of the local district committee, which is
responsible for ensuring the residents are regi s-
tered, taxes and temporary residency permits are
paid,and security is maintained.
Each family pays approx i m ately $70 to the pri vat e
landlords who built and own the rows of houses
where it and its neighbours live . In a country where
the state has traditionally pr ovided housing for
nominal amounts of money, these rents are very
e x p e n s i ve .L i k e w i s e , the half-yearly tuition of about
$50 is fairly onerous. Yet migrants don’t seem to
complain much, perhaps because overall life in the
city is better or more promising than that back at
home.
A p a rt from the temporary permit system, t h e r e
are a number of factors which help the municipa-
lity manage the floating population issue, not the
least of which is the city’s policy of grassroots mana-
g e m e n t . In a pyramid-shaped organizational stru c-
ture with the city at the apex, the district just below,
the street next and the neighbourhood forming the
wide base, the city has found a way of keeping local
involvement high.
Through this last level of gove rn m e n t , the neigh-
bourhood committee,the authorities oversee day-
t o - d ay contact with the transient populat i o n .O n c e
k n own for being composed of busybodies who
interfered at every opportunity in people’s lives—
denouncing and ensuring punishment of eve ry-
thing from extramarital affairs to even mild forms
of political or even social dissent—the committees
have been professionalized in recent years.Where
once they were usually composed of retired people,
n ow they are manned by paid staff, usually dis-
placed state employees who have been specially
trained,notes Wu. Instead of being seen largely as
an instrument of interference in people’s private
l i ve s , the committees nowa d ays concern themselve s
with practical,everyday affairs.
Wu believes this approach is miles from central
planning-type d i k t at ,a remarkably efficient form of
maintaining control while answe ring genuine needs
for social serv i c e . As the population under any one
Fa c t fil e
Population
The Shanghai agglomeration is the most densely-populated part of China. Some 13.6 mil-
lion people live there, in an area of 6,340 sq km.This includes the city itself (375 sq km), s e v e n
industrial satellite cities and some small outlying towns.There were just over five million people
in 1950,so the population has more than doubled in less than 50 years. It is expected to top
18 million by 2015, according to the latest UN projections (see World Urbanization Prospects,
New York,1998).
Political situation
The self-governing municipality of Shanghai answers directly to the central government.
China’s current president,Jiang Zemin,as well as his prime minister, Zhu Rongji,were both
once mayors of the city. The present mayor, Xu Kuangdi,studied in England and then taught
engineering at Shanghai University.
Economic data
Shanghai is China’s biggest port.It has a long trading and industrial history and was the
port of entry during the Empire, from 1842,when the Treaty of Nanking was signed.More
recently, the opening-up of the city launched in the 1970s with the approval of the central
government has boosted its development. The main features of this are heavy industry
(metallurgical and steel plants, petrochemicals, building ships and planes) and textile, elec-
tronic and computer industries. In 1990, the government announced it was setting up a spe-
cial new economic zone called Pudong which would be China’s new financial centre.
The economy of the Shanghai area grew by an annual 14% between 1992 and 1996, w h i l e
direct foreign investment reached $10 billion a year. In 1997, this investment rate fell by half,
pulling the growth rate down to 12.7%. It fell further last year, to about 9%, according to offi-
cial estimates. Fallout from the Asian financial crisis and recent industrial restructuring has
increased unemployment, which is officially 8% but is unofficially estimated to be double that.
Annual per capita income remains way ahead of the rest of China however at $3,000, c o m p a r e d
with only $860 for the country as a whole.
New sectors have recently been earmarked as priority areas, including telecommunications, n e w
technologies and the pharmaceutical and biotechnology industries. n
People like each
other so much that
when they escape
f rom the city they
still look for crow d s,
in other wo rds they
re c o n s t ruct the city
in the country s i d e.
Charles Baudelaire
(1821-1867)
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 35
The South’s urban re v o l u t i o n
resident committee rarely exceeds 2,000 people, t h e
organization is characterized by a strong sense of
familiarity.
Another tool for managing migrants is urgi n g
e m p l oye rs to provide housing for their staff.Wu esti-
m ates that 36 per cent of migrants in Shanghai live at
or close to their place of work and that nearly half of
all rural labour migrants live in housing provided by
urban enterp ri s e s.Two-thirds of those listing constru c-
tion as their occupation live at construction sites.
But while migrants may fare better here than in
other parts of the developing world, there is little
doubt that they in effect do not enjoy the same
status as Shanghainese.Migrants are second-class
citizens, grudgingly accepted for their labour but
mistrusted because of the stresses they add to the
c i t y ’s infrastru c t u r e . Other residents of Shanghai are
often subsidized for the cost of their children’s e-
d u c ation by their employe rs or the gove rn m e n t .
The same goes for medical serv i c e s. Not so the
t e m p o r a ry residents, who must pay the full cost
should medical treatment be necessary. And their
children,many of whom are born in Shanghai, are
destined to be forever locked on the outside looking
i n . M i grant children are unlikely to mingle with
their Shanghainese peers. A Shanghainese parent
would be distraught if his child married a migr a n t —
which is not all that likely any way as the two wo r l d s
a r e , for all the physical prox i m i t y, culturally leagues
a p a rt , difference of dialect being just one of the
many factors. Besides, there is a big price to pay:
when a Shanghainese man marries a migr a n t
woman,their child inherits her place of orgin.
Pa rt of the disdain comes from the sheer lack of
s o p h i s t i c ation of the migrants in terms of dialect and
d e m e a n o u r , and their misplaced expectat i o n s. Fo r
example, male economic migrants typically buy a
suit before hitting the big city in hopes of landing a
desk job.They often end up we a ring the suits—the
labels still stitched to the sleeves—not in fa n cy
o f fice blocks, but on construction sites. A n o t h e r
cause for animosity is that problems such as rising
crime are attributed to migrants.
One does not have to look very far for signs of
contempt or discri m i n at i o n . Outside a high school
in downtown Shanghai—gleaming with new buil-
dings and proud of its new sports stadiums, e x p r e s s-
ways and a metro system, all built by migrants—a
policeman on a motorcycle is checking the papers
of a migrant worker who has been selling brightly
coloured shoelaces to the students. Not even dei-
gning to get off his bike, the policeman speaks
sharply to the middle-aged woman.
Distraught and crying she pleads her case to
the uniformed figure of  authority who snaps closed
his notepad and speeds off down the street.
Still weeping , the woman gathers her meagre
goods and begins walking away, watched by a small
c r owd of Shanghai residents. Where she’ll go is
anyone’s guess. n
Shanghai’s train station serves as  a dormitory for many
migrant workers. District of former
international
concessions
Former French
concession
Old Chinese city
Huang Pu
river
Pudong
business
district
The Bund 
Source: G. Abadia,
IAURIF, France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
How we handle globalization will determine whether our cities and our
civilization will be divided and violent or user-friendly and peaceful
Urbanization and g l o b a l i z a t i o n
Jorge W i l h e i m
Architect and town planner in São Paulo, author of plans for a number of towns and
cities, including Curitiba,in Brazil.He was also deputy secretary-general of the UN
Habitat II conference (Istanbul, 1996).
We cannot get a clear picture of urban life in
the 21st century, especially in the poor
c o u n t ries of the South, unless we take into
account the phenomenon of globalizat i o n , w h i c h
has already brought dramatic changes. C i t i e s ,a n d
especially mega-cities, are where those changes make
their first appearance. So it is there too that the gr e at
upheavals of the next century will take place.
G l o b a l i z ation gi ves shape to the “global village”
predicted by the Canadian Marshall McLuhan.T h e
“ i n f o rm ation era” t h at it ushers in compresses time
and we are now living in a world speeded up as neve r
b e f o r e .World-wide urbanization is proceeding at a
similar rate and its pace in the poor countries of the
South seems terri f y i n g . By 2025, t wo-thirds of
humanity will be living in cities and tow n s , w h e r e
the best opportunities in life tend to be.
G l o b a l i z ation also accentuates a “new urban
g e o gr a p hy ” in both North and South. Islands of ri c h
c o n s u m e rs are spri n ging up in cities amid an ocean
of depri ved people. More and more unemploye d
p e o p l e , i m m i gr a n t s , m i n o rities and the homeless,
are pushed into cities by pressure from “ m a r k e t
e c o n o m i e s ” . As a result, all urban areas—not just
those in the poor countries of the South—will have
to deal with gr owing internal tensions. In New Yo r k ,
for example, the poorest 20 per cent of the
p o p u l ation earns 15 times less than the richest 20
per cent.
Cities have always had their smart
neighbourhoods and their dangerous areas—the
old cities of Europe even more so than those of the
A m e ri c a s , where there is more geographical and
social mobility. But such social and geogr a p h i c a l
s e gr e g ation has changed in pace and scale because
of the gr owth in the urban populat i o n , the increase
in “illegal”migrants and rising uncertainty.
In fa c t , we have entered a period of histori c a l
t r a n s i t i o n , where discontinuities prevail ove r
a d j u s t m e n t . Radical changes in the nature of
production and jobs and the incredible
c o n c e n t r ation of capital in the hands of the fin a n c i a l
sector and speculat o rs weigh much heavier in our
l i ves these days than the stat e ’s efforts to adjust and
i m p r ove the market economy. S e gr e g ation in cities
has been gi ven a new lease of life whose
consequences we do not know. It has reached
unprecedented dimensions because of the explosive
growth of urban areas.
A c c o rding to one scenario, things will go badly.
The gr owing pace of globalization will increase
u n c e rtainty about the future. Fear and defence
mechanisms will gr ow among people and institutions,
fuelling intolerance, xenophobia and mistrust of
e ve rything new or foreign. Urban tensions will manifest
t h e m s e l ves with increasing violence, and segr e g at i o n
will sharp e n . Public areas will be abandoned and
become dangerous no-man’s - l a n d s , the wretched abode
of society’s rejects. Cities will lose their ori ginal function
of being a crossroads for meeting and exchange.
If globalization also continues to go hand in hand
with deregulation of financial markets and an
unchanged level of indebtedness of poor countri e s ,t h e
l atter will not be able to maintain their urban
i n f r a s t ru c t u r e s.And if on top of this there is corru p t i o n
and lack of political will,challenges to the system will
increase and violence will gr ow. C a s h - s t r a p p e d
a u t h o rities will respond with undemocratic measures
and will even ally themselves with financial mafias which
provide them with funds.
A c c o rding to a second scenario, everything will be all
r i g h t. In line with the principle that “ e ve rything the stat e
does is public, but the state doesn’t control eve ry t h i n g
t h at is public,” a new social contract will be drawn up
b e t ween the stat e , the market, the working populat i o n
and civil society, including NGOs. Cities will develop a
new quality of life by providing citizens with a foru m
for exchange. Jobs will be created in the social sector,
in the fields of the env i r o n m e n t , e d u c at i o n ,r e s e a r c h ,
culture and leisure, opening up possibilities for yo u n g
p e o p l e .
In the countries of the South, l o n g - t e rm deve l o p m e n t
s t r at e gies will be drafted and urban planning practised,
taking advantage of the opportunities provided by
g l o b a l i z ation but without falling into its traps.Tow n
planning will become part of the political process, a n d
the state will work with the pri vate sector, monitored by
institutions of civil society.A d e q u ate housing will be bu i l t
with the help of micro-credit and controls on the pri c e
of building mat e ri a l s. I m p r oved infrastructures will enable
m a r ginal areas to become part of the civilized part of the
c i t y. D e m o c r a cy will come up with new ways of gove rn i n g
with the help of networks of invo l ved citizens.
In a transitional scenario, action strat e gies should
fall somewhere between these two extremes.T h e y
should include social goals so that in big urban areas a
society emerges which is founded on part i c i p at o ry
democracy and on “capitalism with a human face”or
“market socialism”.
But the outlook is less clear than ever. Let us hope
the present transition will lead rapidly to a new reviva l
of humanism, whose first signs we are already seeing.
This would open up the road to a development which
is fair,humane and peaceful. n
This is the era of
a rch i t e c t u re.T h e re
can be no new
a rch i t e c t u re without
a new fo rm of tow n
p l a n n i n g. O ver time,
n ew cities have
a l ways re p l a c e d
older ones. B u t
t o d a y, the ra d i a n t ,
happy city of
m o d e rn times is
ready to be born .
Le Corbusier,
Swiss architect and town
planner (1887-1965)
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
Dead-end seeds
yield a harvest of revolt 
n
It was a dream come true for seed
c o m p a n i e s. S p u rred by the ongoing
biotechnology revo l u t i o n , scientists have
d e veloped an innovat i ve technique enabling
companies to produce genetically altered seeds
t h at do not germ i n ate once fully gr ow n .T h e
r e s u l t : fa rm e rs who opt for these seeds will
h ave to buy them each time they plant a new
c r o p, opening a potential gold mine for the
seed companies.
The technique,k n own as the “ Te c h n o l o g y
Protection System” ( T P S ) , was jointly
p atented by the Delta and Pine Land (DPL)
seed company and the U. S .D e p a rtment of
A griculture (USDA) in March 1998. S e e d s
i n c o rp o r ating this technique are expected to
be commercialized by 2005. While the
i n n ovation is welcomed by seed
m a n u fa c t u r e rs , fa rm e rs in many deve l o p i n g
c o u n t ries have been conducting campaigns
Fa r m e rs in developing countries are up in arms against a new technique
to produce sterile seeds. S c i e n t i s t s, h o w e v e r, warn that blind opposition
to biotech re s e a rch will do more harm than good
Ethirajan A n b a r a s a n
UNESCO Courier journalist
and staging protests—sometimes turning to
violence—against the T P S ,f e a ring the new
technique could be detrimental to their
i n t e r e s t s.
At present, except for some hy b rid crops
like cotton and canola, fa rm e rs do not usually
buy seeds for self-pollinating plants like wheat
and ri c e . Fa rm e rs in the developing wo r l d
consider it their “ ri g h t ” to save or exchange
s e e d s , a practice that has been followed for
more than 10,000 ye a rs.
According to the UN, more than 1.4
billion people, mainly resource-poor fa rm e rs ,
depend on fa rm - s aved seeds and seeds
exchanged with their neighbours as their
p ri m a ry seed source. C ritics say that steri l e
seeds are a serious threat to this group of
fa rm e rs ,a s s e rting that the innovation will
f u rther impove rish them.
“The introduction of any technology that
p r e vents fa rm e rs from keeping their own seeds
is not desirable.Fa rm e rs ’ rights include ‘ p l a n t
b a c k ’ ri g h t s.The TPS will certainly preve n t
this ri g h t ,” s ays Dr M. S . S wa m i n at h a n ,a n
eminent scientist who played a leading role
in India’s Green Revo l u t i o n .
In India, where 90 per cent of the 100
million fa rm e rs depend on saved seeds, fa rm
lobby groups are vehemently opposed to this
new technology entering local seed markets.
In the southern Indian state of Karn at a k a ,
e x p e rimental plots of genetically engi n e e r e d
crops belonging to Monsanto, one of the
wo r l d ’s leading seed companies, we r e
ransacked by a group of fa rm e rs last year in
the mistaken belief that they contained the new
s t e rile seed technology.A c t u a l l y, the test site
was for a pest-resistant hy b rid cotton seed
which had nothing to do with T P S .The public
o u t c ry forced the gove rnment to declare that it
In Burma (above) and many other developing
countries, seeds are saved and resown year after
year. “Terminator” technology will put a stop to
this traditional practice.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999Le Courrier de l’UNESCO - Mai 1 99
E T H I C S
would not allow the technology to enter India.
Opposition to TPS has been gaining pace
in other parts of the developing world where
seed saving is an age-old custom. In a
s t atement to a conference held by the Fo o d
and A gricultural Organization (FAO) in 1998,
d e l e g ates from 20 A f rican countries said the
new technique poses a serious threat to food
s e c u ri t y,a f firming “it will destroy the dive rs i t y,
the local knowledge and the sustainable
a gricultural systems of A f rican fa rm e rs.”
S c i e n t i f i c a l l y, the TPS is considered a
milestone in biotechnology research.The new
method produces plants that bear sterile seeds
through an interp l ay between three
transplanted genes, one of which produces a
t oxin that kills seeds in their final stages of
d e ve l o p m e n t .C ritics howe ver refer to it as
“ t e rm i n ator technology” because of the
t e c h n i q u e ’s ability to neutralize a plant’s
g e rm i n ating capacity—a characteri s t i c
introduced for purely commercial reasons.
“The new technique is to protect U. S .
technology and seed pat e n t s ,”explains Melvin
O l i ve r , one of the USDA scientists who
i nvented the technology.The TPS is now being
tested on tobacco and cotton seeds which are
expected to enter the market by 2005.
When news of the term i n ator pat e n t
b r o k e , it sparked a multi-media debat e ,
especially on the Intern e t ,c o n c e rning the
ethics and social relevance of introducing the
TPS in developing countri e s.The USDA
r e c e i ved hundreds of e-mail letters from
around the world questioning the validity of
the new method.
Taken aback by the anti-sterile technology
c a m p a i g n ,Monsanto seed corp o r at i o n ,w h i c h
is in the process of acquiring DPL,a n n o u n c e d
in A p ril this year that it will not commercialize
the TPS until an independent intern at i o n a l
review of its env i r o n m e n t a l , economic and
social effects is completed.
In defending the T P S , seed companies
underline that it costs them between $30 and
$100 million to develop a high-yielding
genetically engineered seed va ri e t y. T h e
present system of seed sav i n g, which is
p r e valent in most developing countri e s ,m a k e s
it difficult for them to gain sufficient returns on
their inve s t m e n t . Losses have even forced
some companies to suspend crop
d e velopment progr a m m e s.
The threat to biodiversity
But a number of farming experts and
o r g a n i z ations reject this logi c. “I do not
consider that the cost spent by seed com-
panies can be recovered only by term i n at o r
t e c h n o l o g y. In fa c t , most successful seed
companies are those whose seeds have a
r e p u t ation for quality and affordable pri c e ,”
says Swaminathan.
C ritics of term i n ator technology also
argue that poor fa rm e rs in the tropics not
only produce 15 to 20 per cent of the wo r l d ’s
food supply, they also maintain crop va ri e t i e s
t h at are a source of genetic dive rsity for the
wo r l d ’s plant breeders and genetic engi n e e rs.
For example, the Manila-based Intern at i o n a l
Rice Research Institute (IRRI) relies on tra-
ditional rice va rieties collected from fa rm e rs
in many parts of the world to develop new
high-yielding seeds (see pages 46 to 50).
“If fa rm e rs eat or abandon their tradi-
tional seeds in the process of adopting ter-
m i n ator seeds,c e n t u ries of crop genetic dive r-
sity could be lost foreve r ,” s ays Pat Mooney,
E xe c u t i ve Director of the Canada-based
Rural A d vancement Fo u n d ation Intern a-
tional (RAFI), a non-gove rnmental organi-
z ation which is spearheading an intern at i o n a l
campaign against term i n ator technology.
Pointing to another wo rse-case scenari o,
some scientists fear that the TPS trait could
spread to other crops if pollen carrying a ter-
m i n ator gene lands on plants in neighbouri n g
fie l d s.“Plants in the neighbouring crop wo u l d
then produce seeds that would not germ i-
n at e ,” s ays Rob Marchant,a research associat e
at Nottingham Unive rsity (United Kingdom).
If this happens, there is a danger that fa r-
m e rs who opt for normal seeds may end up
h aving sterile ones because of crops with the
t e rm i n ator trait in adjacent fie l d s.
To safeguard fa rm e rs in deve l o p i n g
c o u n t ri e s ,S wa m i n athan would like to press
UNESCO’s Bioethics committee to draft a
U n i ve rsal Declaration on the Plant Genome
and Fa rm e rs ’R i g h t s , similar in spirit to the
one adopted by UN E S C O in 1997 on the
A protest against genetically modified organisms 
is held during an international meeting of experts in Cartagena (Colombia) in February 1999.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
Human Genome and Human Rights.This
D e c l a r ation expresses rights and pri n c i p l e s
that should govern research on the human
g e n o m e , emphasizing the pre-eminence of
human dignity.
A backlash against
biotechnology
While the debate over the TPS is heat i n g
u p, scientists are concerned that the contro-
ve rsy is leading to gr owing anti-biotechno-
logy feelings in many developing countri e s.
Some environmental groups in South A s i a
have even called for a total ban on geneti-
cally engineered seeds, fearing they could
cause harm to human beings.
“There are gr owing misconceptions
about genetic research.The myths have to be
d i s p e l l e d .The fact is that biotechnology is the
only solution if we want to increase wo r l d
food production to meet future demands,”
a s s e rts Dr A rie A l t m a n , professor of hort i-
culture at the Hebrew Unive rsity of Je ru-
s a l e m . Pointing to declining food production
in some Asian countri e s , he says that the
process of the Green Revo l u t i o n , w h i c h
helped many nations in the region boost
food output in the 1960s and 70s, has clearly
reached sat u r ation leve l .“So genetically engi-
neered crops are the only solution to increase
y i e l d ,” claims A l t m a n .
But who will take the initiat i ve of deve-
loping new seed va rieties? Gove rn m e n t
spending worldwide has been minimal in
a gricultural biotechnology, while the pri vat e
sector has been pumping millions of dollars
into research and development in this fie l d .
Now, they are not willing to invest more in
s e l f - p o l l i n ating crops like wheat and ri c e
unless returns are ensured, and perceive
the TPS as one way of achieving this.
DPL officials claim that pest-resistant
w h e at and rice seeds can be developed in the
next six to seven ye a rs ,s i g n i ficantly boosting
global food production. But they contend
t h at once such high-yielding va rieties enter the
m a r k e t , it will be difficult to monitor the
p atenting rights because they are mass-culti-
vated crops.At present, some seed companies
oblige fa rm e rs to sign a contract affirming that
they will not re-use the seeds purchased.To
enforce this, companies send inspectors to
monitor fa rm e rs ’ a c t i v i t i e s. While such a
system is already difficult to implement in
the U. S . , where ri gid patent rights exist, it is
next to impossible in the developing wo r l d .
“The TPS is essential to safeguard the pat e n t s
of new va ri e t i e s ,” s ays Olive r.
TPS proponents also argue that seeds
i n c o rp o r ating a term i n ator trait will not be
forced on fa rm e rs.“If they do not want them,
they can always continue with other seed
va ri e t i e s ,” s ays Harry Collins, vice president
of technology transfer at the Mississippi-
based DPL. H owe ve r , if the best seeds ava i-
lable on the market all carry a term i n at o r
t r a i t , fa rm e rs who refuse to buy them will
be left with ones of inferior quality.
The trend towards concentration on
the seed market is also likely to limit choice.
RAFI maintains that the top 10 seed cor-
p o r ations control 30 per cent of the $23 bil-
lion seed market wo r l d w i d e . In the last few
ye a rs Monsanto has become one of the
wo r l d ’s largest seed companies, and is the-
refore in a position to make direct use of ter-
minator technology across the globe.
Realizing that this technology could be
a money-spinner, other seed companies
have jumped into the fray. “After the ter-
m i n ator pat e n t , 29 patents along similar
lines  have been obtained by 12 European
and U. S . seed companies seeking to exploit
new engi n e e ring techniques for profit
motives,” says Mooney.
RAFI is not is the only outfit lobbying
against the T P S .The Consultat i ve Group for
I n t e rn ational A gricultural Research (CGIAR),
the wo r l d ’s largest organization in this fie l d ,i s
opposed to introducing the technology in
d e veloping countries and has banned its use
in its 16 agricultural research institutes.
In Ja n u a ry 1999, more than 50 non-
g ove rnmental organizations and fa rm - l o b b y
groups from South A m e rican nations assem-
bled in Ecuador to form a coalition against ter-
m i n ator technology entering the continent.
“ Poor fa rm e rs will get nothing out of it.We
are not only against term i n ator but against all
transgenic seed va ri e t i e s. It doesn’t gi ve poor
fa rm e rs any adva n t a g e s ,” s ays Silvia Ribeiro,
‘After the terminator patent, 29 patents along similar lines have
been obtained by 12 European and U. S. seed companies seeking
to exploit new engineering techniques for pro fit motives’
who works with a coalition of fa rm e rs ’o r g a-
n i z ations and NGOs in southern Brazil.T h e
n e t work has scheduled a series of public mee-
tings and demonstrations throughout Brazil
in the coming months to create awa r e n e s s
among fa rm e rs about the T P S . Some local
g ove rnments in Brazil have already banned the
e n t ry of term i n ator seeds once they become
available in five to six ye a rs.
Biotech proponents argue that the nega-
tive reaction to terminator seeds is prema-
t u r e . “If the new seeds are going to increase
the yield by 15-20 per cent, fa rm e rs will not
mind paying for the seeds,” says C.S.Pra-
k a s h , Director of Plant Biotechnology
Research at Tuskegee Unive rsity in the U. S . ,
and consultant for Monsanto.
Farmers in the U.S. are already expe-
riencing the benefits of insect-resistant and
herbicide-resistant crops through higher
yields and profit s.Transgenic insect-resistant
maize saved U. S . fa rm e rs  an estimat e d
$190 million in 1997 and substantially
reduced insecticide use.
Not all developing countries oppose agri-
cultural biotechnology. Fa rm e rs in China
and A r g e n t i n a , for example, h ave responded
favourably to genetically engineered seeds.
Chinese fa rm e rs have been successful in cul-
t i vating hy b rid cotton seeds and buy them
e ve ry year from the companies.“ Fa rm e rs are
the best judges. They know what is econo-
mically beneficial for them.If they find that the
t e rm i n ator trait is unv i a b l e , they themselve s
will reject it,” s ays Prakash. n
+ …
Some useful Websites:
l http://www.rafi.org
l http://www.mssrf.org
l http://www.ars.usda.gov/misc/fact.htm
l http://www.monsato.com
l http://www.oneworld.org/panos
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Cracking the code
o f a r t’s allure
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - Juin 1999
n
‘If a Martian ethologist were to land on
earth and watch us humans,he would
be puzzled by many aspects of human
nature, but surely art—our propensity to
c r e ate and enjoy paintings and sculpture—
would be among the most puzzling.What
biological function could this mysterious
behaviour possibly serve?
“Cultural fa c t o rs undoubtedly influ e n c e
what kind of art a person enjoys. But,even
if beauty is largely in the eye of the beholder,
might there be some sort of universal rule
or ‘deep structure’, underlying all artistic
experience?”
V i l ayanur S. R a m a c h a n d r a n ,Director of
the Center for Brain and Cognition at the
U n i ve rsity of California at San Diego, h a s
made a bold and controve rsial attempt to
a n swer these intriguing questions by
proposing a new scientific theory of art .T h e
t h e o ry explains many familiar experi e n c e s ,
such as why a cartoon squiggle can evoke a
we l l - k n own face more quickly than a full
colour photogr a p h , and why many men fin d
the hour-glass figure of Marilyn Monroe sexy.
Professor Ramachandran’s theory
addresses three questions: (a) W h at are the
“ rules of art ”t h at make something pretty? (b)
W hy did these rules evo l ve and have the form
t h at they do? (c) W h at is the brain circuitry
i nvo l ved? Previous theories of art have looked
at one or two of these questions,but this is the
first time all three have been tackled together.
With his colleague William Hirs t e i n ,
Ramachandran proposes a list of “Eight law s
of artistic experience . . . t h at artists either
consciously or unconsciously deploy to opti-
mally titillate the visual areas of the brain,” i n
p a rticular that part of the brain known as the
limbic system. Of the eight (see box page
4 2 ) , three seem to be especially signific a n t : a
p s y c h o l o gical phenomenon called the “ p e a k
shift effect”; the principle of “ gr o u p i n g ” ;a n d
the benefit of focusing on a single visual cue.1
The ‘peak shift effect’
The “peak shift effect” is a we l l - k n ow n
p rinciple in animal discri m i n ation learn i n g .
For example, if a rat is taught to discri m i n at e
a square from a rectangle and rewarded for the
r e c t a n g l e , it will soon learn to respond more
frequently to the rectangle. M o r e ove r , if the
r at is trained with a prototype rectangle of, s ay,
aspect ratio 3:2, it will respond even more
p o s i t i vely to a longer and skinnier fig u r e — s ay,
of aspect ratio 4:1.This curious result implies
t h at what the rat is learning to value is not a
p a rticular rectangle but a ru l e : rectangles are
better than squares. So the gr e ater the rat i o
b e t ween the long and the short sides, i . e .t h e
less square-like it is, the “ b e t t e r ” the rectangle
is in the rat ’s eye s. This is the “peak shift
e f f e c t ” .Ramachandran argues that this pri n-
ciple holds the key for understanding the
e vo c at i veness of much of visual art .
H ow does the peak shift effect relate to
human pat t e rn recognition and aesthetic pre-
ference? Consider the way in which a skilled
c a rtoonist produces a cari c ature of a fa m o u s
fa c e , s ay the late U. S . President Richard
N i x o n ’s. W h at a cartoonist does (uncons-
ciously) is to take the ave ra ge of all fa c e s ,s u b-
tract it from Nixon’s face (to get the difference
b e t ween Nixon’s face and all others) and
then a m p l i f y the differences to produce a cari-
c at u r e .The final result, of cours e , is a draw i n g
t h at is even more Nixon-like than the ori-
gi n a l .The artist has amplified the differences
t h at characterize Nixon’s face in the same
way that an even skinnier rectangle is an
a m p l i fied ve rsion of the ori ginal prototype
t h at the rat is exposed to.Hence Ramachan-
d r a n ’s aphorism that “All art is cari c at u r e ” .
(This is not literally tru e , as he admits, but it
applies surp risingly often.) In other wo r d s ,
w h at the artist tries to do is not only capture
the essence of something but amplify it in
order to activate neural mechanisms more
p owerfully than the ori ginal object.
Look at the Chola bronze—the accen-
t u ated hips and bust of the Goddess Pa rvat i
( F i g . 1) and you will see at once that this is
essentially a caricature of the female form.
Here the artist has chosen to amplify the
“very essence” (called the rasa by Hindu
artists) of being feminine, by moving the
image abnormally far toward the feminine
end of the female/male spectru m . T h e
a rtistic amplific ation produces a “super sti-
mulus” to which, Ramachandran conjec-
t u r e s ,c e rtain brain circuits respond.A rt i s t s
may also try to evoke a strong direct emo-
tional response by exploiting the peak shift
effect along dimensions other than form.
For instance,a Boucher, aVan Gogh, or a
Monet may be thought of as a cari c ature in
“colour space”.
Perceptual grouping
and binding
A second basic principle suggested by
Ramachandran is “ gr o u p i n g ” (or binding).
The way this works can be illustrated by the
D a l m atian dog picture shown in Fig. 2 .T h i s
is seen initially as a random jumble of
s p l o t c h e s. The number of potential gr o u-
pings of these splotches is infin i t e , but once
the dog is seen,your visual system links only
a subset of these splotches together and it is
impossible n o t to “hold on” to this group of
linked splotches. I n d e e d , the discove ry of
A bold new theory to identify the 
common denominator of all visual art
1. V.S. Ramachandran and William Hirstein are
publishing a fuller exposition of this subject later
this year in the Journal of Consciousness Studies
under the title “The Science of Art, A
Neurological Theory of Aesthetic Experience”.
Anthony Fr e e m a n
Managing editor,
Journal of Consciousness Studies
F i g u re 1. The accentuated features of a bro n z e
statue of the Indian goddess Parvati 
( c i rca 11th century A . D. ) , amplify the essence of
the feminine to produce a “peak shift effect”.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 41
the dog and the linking of the dog-releva n t
splotches generates a pleasant “ a h a ”s e n s a-
t i o n . In “colour space” the equivalent of this
would be we a ring a blue scarf with red flo-
we rs if you are we a ring a red skirt ; the per-
ceptual grouping of the red flowe rs and yo u r
red skirt is aesthetically pleasing. A rt i s t s
u n d e rstand the pleasure gi ven by such effects.
The evo l u t i o n a ry value of such gr o u p i n g
of stimuli to pick out objects is obvious: it
makes the detection of both prey and pre-
dators much easier. But how is such grou-
ping achieved? The key idea is as follows.
G i ven the brain’s limited at t e n t i o n a l
resources and shortage of neural space for
competing representat i o n s , e ve ry stage in the
processing of visual information offers an
opportunity to generate a signal that says,
“Look, here is a clue to something poten-
tially object-like!” Pa rtial solutions or
conjectures to perceptual problems are fed
back from every level in the hierarchy to
e ve ry earlier module to impose a small bias
in processing, allowing the final percept to
emerge from such progressive “bootstrap-
ping”.
C o n s i s t e n cy between partial high-leve l
“ hy p o t h e s e s ” and earlier low - l e vel ensembles
g e n e r ates a pleasant sensat i o n — e . g . t h e
D a l m atian dog “ hy p o t h e s i s ” encourages the
binding of corresponding splotches which,
in turn ,f u rther consolidate the “ d o g - l i k e ”
n ature of the final percept and we feel good
when it all finally clicks in place.And what
the artist tries to do is to tease the system with
as many of these “potential object” clues as
possible—an idea that would help explain
w hy grouping and “perceptual problem-
s o l v i n g ” are both frequently exploited by
a rtists and fashion designers.
Isolating a visual signal
The third principle (in addition to peak
shift and binding) emphasized by
Ramachandran is the need to i s o l at e a single
visual modality before you amplify the signal
in that modality.The brain’s ability to do this
explains why an outline drawing or sketch is
more effective as “ a rt ” than a full colour
p h o t o gr a p h .Consider a full-colour illustrat i o n
of Nixon, with depth, s h a d i n g, skin tones and
b l e m i s h e s ,e t c.W h at is unique about Nixon
is the form of his face (as amplified by the
c a ri c at u r e ) , but the skin tone—even though
it makes the picture more human-like—
d o e s n ’t contri bute to making him “ N i x o n -
l i k e ” and therefore actually detracts from the
e f fic a cy of the form cues.This explains why
one not only “gets away ” with just using
outlines—they are actually more effective than
a full-colour half-tone photo, despite its hav i n g
more inform at i o n . Hence the aphori s m
“more is less” in A rt .
Additional evidence for this view comes
from the “ s avant syndrome”—autistic chil-
dren who are “ r e t a r d e d ” and yet produce
beautiful draw i n g s.The animal drawings of the
e i g h t - year-old artist Nadia, for instance, a r e
almost as aesthetically pleasing as those of
Leonardo da Vinci (Fig. 4 ) . R a m a c h a n d r a n
argues that this is because the fundamental
disorder in autism is a distortion of the
“salience landscape”; s avants shut out many
i m p o rtant sensory channels, thereby allo-
wing them to deploy all their at t e n t i o n a l
resources on a single channel.
‘Lie detector’ testing
Ramachandran believes that the “peak
shift principle” can be tested directly. The
method would employ skin conductance
response (SCR), the technology used in
“lie detectors”. The size of the SCR is a
direct measure of the amount of limbic
(emotional) activation produced by an
i m a g e . It is a better measure, as it turn s
o u t , than simply asking someone how much
emotion they feel about what they are loo-
Figure 3.A caricature of Richard Nixon by the
French cartoonist Mulatier.
Figure 2.Grouping:the Dalmatian emerges from
a random jumble of splotches, producing a
pleasing sensation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
The eight laws
of artistic experience
1
The ‘peak shift principle’ makes exaggerated
elements attractive
2
Isolating a single cue helps to focus
attention
3
Perceptual grouping makes objects stand out
from background
4
Contrast is reinforcing
5
Perceptual ‘problem solving’ is also
reinforcing
6
Unique vantage points are suspect
7
Visual ‘puns’ or metaphors enhance art
8
Symmetry is attractive
of the term “ p r e t t y ” . If used at all by seri o u s
a rt cri t i c s , the word damns with faint praise.
Prettiness is not seen as a synonym for
b e a u t y, but as a shallow impostor.Yet Rama-
chandran uses it without irony as a positive
at t ri bu t e .This one piece of unfort u n ate ter-
minology might be forgi ve n , but other ele-
ments in his work are all of a piece with it.
First, there is the heavy reliance on the
female form and upon the erotic in his
e x a m p l e s. Then he seems to equat e
“ a r o u s a l ” (as measured by SCR) with a
p o s i t i ve aesthetic response—an assump-
tion felt by critics to presuppose the reduc-
tionist case he is trying to prove . Ta k e n
together,these points seem to some critics
to confuse pornography with high art.
The “science of art ” has also been
attacked from the scientific side, on the
grounds that its proponents have not ye t
conducted any serious empirical tests of their
i d e a s. At best they have offered a manifesto
for a research programme and made some
suggestions for possible lines of inve s t i g at i o n .
E ven then, it has been pointed out that the
n a rr ow range of examples used hardly justifie s
the lofty claims to be dealing with the whole of
a rt , let alone to have uncovered the “ l aws of
aesthetic experi e n c e ” . Nor has hitching his
b a n d wagon to the Buddhist train, b y
a s s o c i ating his “eightfold law s ” with the
B u d d h a ’s eightfold noble path wo n
Ramachandran any fri e n d s , though to be fa i r ,
he admits himself that this is a slightly
whimsical associat i o n .
C riticism has centred on the lack of
p r o p o rtion between the narr ow approach to
art taken by Ramachandran and the gran-
diloquent claims he makes for his theory —
a l t h o u g h , as he admits, he initially pro-
posed it “in a playful spirit”. But the very
audacity with which its author propounds
it guarantees that we shall be hearing a lot
more of it in the coming months. n
king at , because the verbal response is
fil t e r e d , e d i t e d , and sometimes censored
by the conscious mind. M e a s u ring SCR
a l l ows direct access to “ u n c o n s c i o u s ”
mental processes.
The experiment would compare a sub-
j e c t ’s SCR to a c a ri c at u r e o f, s ay, Einstein or
N i x o n , to his SCR to a p h o t o of the same indi-
v i d u a l s. I n t u i t i ve l y, one would expect the
photo to produce a large SCR because it is
rich in cues and therefore excites more
m o d u l e s. If one found, p a r a d ox i c a l l y, t h at the
c a ri c ature actually elicited a larger SCR, t h i s
would provide evidence for the operation of
the peak shift effect—the artist would have
unconsciously produced a super stimulus.
Critical responses
Ramachandran says that one could also
compare the magnitude of an SCR to cari-
catures of women (or indeed, to a Chola
bronze nude or a Picasso nude) with the
SCR to a photo of a nude wo m a n . It is
c o n c e i vable that the subject might claim
to find the photo more at t r a c t i ve at a
conscious leve l , while regi s t e ring a large
“unconscious aesthetic response”—in the
f o rm of a larger SCR—to the artistic repre-
sentation.That art taps into the “subcons-
c i o u s ” is not a new idea, but our SCR mea-
surements may be the first attempt to test
such a notion experimentally.
Not surp ri s i n g l y, R a m a c h a n d r a n ’s
attempt to reduce aesthetic experience to a
set of physical or neurobiological laws has
already met with stout cri t i c i s m .A symptom
of trouble to come has been seen in his use
Figure 4.The savant syndrome:
horses drawn by Leonardo 
da Vinci (right) and by 
an eight-year old autistic child.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
n
Publisher Eric Eldred belongs to a
breed of diehards who see the World
Wide Web as a way to fulfill ideals rat h e r
than make money. “ Ve ry much like
UN E S C O, we feel a responsibility to our
public—all human beings on the eart h — t o
preserve our culture of books and art and
make it available to as many as we can,” h e
s ay s. “ We are now blessed with a gr e at deal
of free computer power and we would like
to turn this to good use.”
Since 1995, E l d r e d , the A m e ri c a n
founder of Eldritch Press, has published
on the Web gr e at classics of literature whose
copyright has expired and which have the-
refore fallen into the public domain. H e
wants to build up a virtual library for uni-
versity literature students and high-school
pupils like his triplet daughters.
From Victor Hugo
to the Kama Sutra
Eldred is not the only person fighting to
make culture more accessible and wides-
pread in cy b e rspace than in the “ r e a l ” wo r l d .
In the industrialized countries,such as the
United Stat e s , plenty of moves are afoot
to freshen up the tired old image of the
public library. In recent years, millions of
pages of the works of the greatest writers,
h i s t o ri a n s , poets and philosophers have
been scanned1 onto the Internet or, in some
cases, simply re-typed and put online.
So fa r , such digitalized mat e rial consists
mainly of Anglo-Saxon classics or products
of  We s t e rn culture translated into English.
For example, you can download from the
Web into your computer the writings of
A ri s t o t l e , Oscar W i l d e ,To l s t oy,Victor Hugo,
and a handful of A r a b , Pe rsian and Chinese
a u t h o rs , plus the Kama Sutra. You don’t
need to go hunting for a book that you can,
in this way,k e e p, p rint out, a n n o t ate and use
as you wish or forward to your friends.
These freely-available virtual libraries
h ave been set up by determined indivi-
d u a l s , N G O s , u n i ve rs i t i e s , g ove rn m e n t s
and intern ational organizat i o n s.The Guten-
berg Project and The Oxford Text Archive
(OTA) are the pioneers (see page 45). On
a bigger scale, n ational libraries have begun
the monumental task of digitalizing all the
hundreds of thousands of documents and
pictures they possess.
The first to take the plunge are the
French National Library (BNF) and the
U.S. Library of Congress, says Sonia Zill-
hardt of the BNF. “ O t h e rs have begun wo r-
king on the project in the past three years
but some are still at an experimental stage.
Most don’t have enough money to do it.”
Scanning a page costs between one and
four dollars , so millions are needed to pro-
cess whole collections. But the hardest part
is overcoming the conservatism of some
cultural officials who have to be dragged into
cyberspace.
“ E ve ry country should provide easy
access to documents in the public domain,”
s ays Zillhardt. “The policies of different
states must converge in the new environ-
ment of the world inform ation society.”
This is the aim of the Bibliotheca Univer-
salis (BU) project which was launched in
1995 by the G7 group of the world’s seven
richest countri e s , joined last year by Russia,
and now links 13 countries in all. “They
Untold riches await anyone who can tap into the public libraries now available
on the Internet. But stiffening copyright law could rein in the tre n d
A virtual l i b ra r y
on the Web 
1.“Photographing” a page by computer and
transferring its contents to a computer’s memor y.
Sophie Boukhari
UNESCO Courier journalist
Classics of world literature are now available for free on the Internet.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
C O N N E X I O N S
h ave to work out between them who is digi-
talizing what , as well as establish shared
communication norms,” says Zillhardt.
But there’s many a slip twixt cup and lip.
Each national programme goes at its ow n
s p e e d ,with its own pri o rities (such as U. S .h i s-
t o ry in Washington or mat e rial about the
gr e at Po rtuguese explorers in Lisbon) and its
own technical norm s. On top of that ,c u rr e n t
computer programmes do not allow people
to switch from a document in Japanese or
Arabic to one in the Latin alphabet.
By the end of the ye a r ,e ve ryone invo l ve d
in the BU project should have pledged to
put together an initial shared collection of
works on the theme of exchanges between
different peoples. But how many years will
it be before Japanese researchers can make
a request in their own language and come
up with documents from all the associated
libraries? And how much longer than that
will it be before a student in Burkina Faso
can make use of such a tool?
At first sight,virtual libraries seem like
a godsend for people in poor countri e s ,
giving them access to the wo r l d ’s collec-
tive memory, which is concentrated in the
rich countries.They just need a computer,
an Internet connection and some money.
“Web access is still very much a dream in
many developing countries and the cost of
i n t e rn ational phone connections there is
p r o h i b i t i ve ,” s ays Philippe Quéau, UN E S C O’s
director of inform ation and computing.
“Fetching material off the Web takes time
and is expensive — s e veral dollars an hour in
Africa,for example.”
Does this mean online culture is beyo n d
the reach of poor countries? No, but they
h ave to develop two kinds of serv i c e s. F i rs t ,
the local creation of “ m i rr o r ”s i t e s2 of online
l i b r a ri e s , which are accessible for the cost of
a local phone call.And then encouraging the
distribution of works in the form of CD-
R o m s , which cost less than a dollar to copy.
UNESCO has launched a collection called
Publica and will soon put out a CD-Rom of
the great Arabic classics. But it is having a
hard job bri n ging out a similar one on
French-language literature.
“ For two ye a rs I’ve been up against the
i n e rtia of French officialdom which doesn’t
want to get into a fight with the publishers ,
e ven though the works I want to put on
CD-Rom have come into the public
d o m a i n ,” s ays Quéau, who deplores the
rampant pri vat i z ation of the public domain
for profit,“either by extending the life of a
c o p y right or by making use of technology.”
Privatization of the public domain
Both these types of privatization are in
the works. Microsoft’s new Windows 2000
p r o gramme will make it easier to read texts
on the screen, a sign that “e-books” could
soon be on sale in the bookstores.We could
download and read hundreds of works on
such small book-sized computers. B u t
would they, as Eldred fears,become “anti-
b o o k s ” which couldn’t be freely exchanged?
To keep its monopoly, the computer
i n d u s t ry would just need to impose a tech-
nical norm to enable e-books to be read.
Works in the public domain would then
h ave to be electronically edited and so
would once more fall under a copyright.
Intellectual property laws are also get-
ting tougher. A European Union directive
in October 1993 extended the copyri g h t
on an author’s works from 50 to 70 years
after his or her deat h . “It seems reasonable
to us to cover two generations of the author’s
d e s c e n d a n t s , as intern ational law stipulat e s
and in view of today’s greater life expec-
tancy,” says Anne Bergman, an adviser to
the Federation of European Publishers.
The trend is the same in the United
We b s i t e of the month
h t t p : / / w w w. u n . o rg / p u b s / C y b e r S c h o o l B u s / h u m a n r i g h t s /
Everyone everywhere has human rights, but not everyone everywhere respects them.What are they
and how are they protected? Teachers and students around the world are always looking for mate-
rials to help them understand this complex issue.
The UN Human Rights in Action project is an answer—presented in plain language, in English, Fr e n c h
and Spanish.The project aims not just to teach,but to encourage students to act. It collects stories of classes
or schools defending and promoting human rights in their communities which will, in turn, become part
of a global compendium published online. n
+ …
l Eldritch Press:eldred.ne.mediaone.net/
l Berkman Center for Internet and Society,
Harvard:cyber.law.harvard.edu
l Bibliotheca Universalis:www.konbib.nl/gabriel
l UNESCO: www.unesco.org/webworld/public
domain/public inf.html
l The Internet Classics Archive/MIT:
Internet:www.literature.org/works/
2.A local copy of an original site based in another
country.
S t at e s , where the life of a copyright has
gr own from 28 ye a rs at the beginning of the
c e n t u ry to 75 ye a rs last ye a r. The U. S .
C o n gress extended this by a further 20
ye a rs last October when it passed the Sonny
Bono Copyright Te rm Extension A c t .S o m e
people are even campaigning for unlimited
copyright,or one for eternity minus a day.
The “minus one day ” is to avoid charges of
unconstitutionality, since U.S. federal law
forbids unlimited copyright.
The aim is also to encourage authors’
c r e at i v i t y, not to provide their heirs and
c o p y right holders with an endless source of
i n c o m e , s ays Eldred. He claims the new
law is unconstitutional and filed a suit in
January 1999 to get it struck down.A first
decision will be made in July 1999 and the
m atter should go all the way to the Supreme
Court, says legal expert and Harvard pro-
fessor Lawrence Lessig, who backs Eldred.
Congress has no right,he says,to limit the
public domain as a whole and extend the
monopoly of a few pri vate gr o u p s , l i k e
Disney and the film industry, which lobbied
very hard to get the Bono Law passed.
“In five ye a rs ’t i m e , Mickey Mouse wa s
to enter the public domain and Disney
would have lost the ability to control dupli-
c ation of Mickey Mouse fil m s ,” s ays Les-
s i g . “The same with the film industry.Te d
Tu rner is another big winner. H e ’s just
purchased the Metro Goldwyn Maye r
a r c h i ve , which now has a 20-year additio-
nal life for him.”
“The public domain is the we l l s p ring of
our culture,” says Eldred. “Think of how
much Disney has taken from works that
are no longer under copyri g h t . Think of
how silly it would be if you had to pay 7.5
cents to an author each time your child
sang ‘Happy Birthday’in public!” n
‘In five years’ time, M i c key Mouse was to enter the public
domain and Disney would have lost the ability to contro l
duplication of Mickey Mouse fil m s.The same with the fil m
i n d u s t r y.Ted Turner is another big winner. H e ’s just purc h a s e d
the Metro Goldwyn Mayer arc h i v e, which now has a 20-year
additional life for him.’
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
Relying on the sole efforts of volunteers, P roject Gutenberg has been
launching the world’s literary heritage into cyberspace for nearly 
30 years while conducting a crusade against copyright re s t r i c t i o n s
2,000 world classics on line
n
When Michael Hart , a student at the
U n i ve rsity of Illinois, was gi ven a free
I n t e rnet account, he spent an hour
p o n d e ring the potential of the gi f t , then typed
in the A m e rican Declaration of
Independence and sent it to eve ryone on the
n e t wo r k s. Project Gutenberg had just been
b o rn .
T h at was back in 1971, when only 23
c o m p u t e rs in the U. S . were online and
computer memories were small. B e l i e v i n g
t h at the gr e atest value created by computers
would be the storage and retri e val of library
m at e ri a l s ,H a rt continued his project with the
U. S .C o n s t i t u t i o n , the books of the Bible and
S h a k e s p e a r e ’s play s. As computer powe r
i n c r e a s e d , he launched into book-length
m a n u s c ri p t s ,b e ginning with a popular classic,
Alice in Wo n d e rl a n d. To d ay, there are 160
million Internet accounts globally and
Michael Hart ’s free cy b e r - l i b r a ry just posted
its 2,000th title: C e rva n t e s ’ Don Quixote, i n
S p a n i s h.While the majority of titles are in
E n g l i s h , the library also comprises a handful
in French, Italian and Lat i n .
Idealistic and utilitarian
Although he claims he’s never read a
computer manual, H a rt , the son of a
professor specializing in Shakespeare and a
m at h e m at i c i a n , is a child of the inform at i o n
a g e , a recluse who prefers to communicat e
via e-mail from his home in Urbana, I l l i n o i s.
“I started the project because I am idealistic
and utilitari a n ,” s ays Hart , a self-descri b e d
blue-collar rebel.
“Michael Hart should be as famous as Bill
G at e s ,” a s s e rts C h i c a go Tri bu n e c o m p u t e r
columnist Jim Coat e s. But Hart has neve r
t ruly reaped the mat e rial reward from being
the first to post texts on the net. P r o j e c t
Gutenberg is a non-profit enterp ri s e ,e n t i r e l y
funded through donat i o n s. Its first grant came
from A p p l e , and others followed from such
outfits as Hewlett Pa c k a r d , IBM and
M i c r o s o f t , whether in the form of super
s c a n n e rs or dollars.
“ We don’t have a budget of any kind,”
a s s e rts Hart flat l y. The project, w h i c h
averages 36 new books a ye a r , relies on some
1,000 vo l u n t e e rs. Nor is there an editori a l
c o m m i t t e e .Vo l u n t e e rs are encouraged to
choose books they’d like to add to the library,
as long as they fall into the public domain,
which restricts the selection to pre-1923
wo r k s.They scan and proof the books before
sending them to Hart , who puts them on-
line in Plain Vanilla A S C I I , the most
widespread code for inform ation interchange.
H a rt ’s technique has its cri t i c s. I n
E n g l a n d , the Oxford Text A r c h i ve compri s e s
over 2,500 online titles specifically geared to
the academic community. Hence the
i m p o rtance of enriching the raw text with
footnotes and choosing the most widely
respected edition of a wo r k . Such details are
far from Hart ’s chief concern . In his wish to
make classics available to the masses, h i s
gr e atest crusade is against copyright law.S i n c e
the launching of Project Gutenberg, the time
p e riod of copyright in the U. S . has been
extended twice, which according to Hart ,
“ e l i m i n ated two million books from lists we
could be using.”H a rt has been threatened by
dozens of law s u i t s ,r e p o rtedly for digi t a l i z i n g
editions of books that are still covered by
c o p y ri g h t .
M a ny publishers claim that the Gutenberg
project is no threat to bu s i n e s s.N o rt h we s t e rn
U n i ve rsity Press, for example, r e c e n t l y
Sam T. We l l e r
Chicago-based journalist.Correspondent
for Publishers Weekly.
published the complete works of Herm a n
M e l v i l l e ,which are also available free of charge
from Project Gutenberg. “This is public
domain mat e ri a l ,” s ays Nicholas We i r -
W i l l i a m s ,director of Nort h we s t e rn Unive rs i t y
P r e s s. “The Melville mat e rial on the we b
d o e s n ’t damage our sales.” “ You could put
full texts of eve ry book you publish on the
n e t ,” adds Walter Lippincott, director of
P rinceton Unive rsity Press,“and it wo u l d n ’t
h u rt sales. I don’t think anybody wants to read
ve ry much online.And who wants to sit there
and print out hundreds of pages?”
On the contrary, H a rt predicts a bri g h t
future for e-texts, if only for ve ry simple
r e a s o n s.“Most people don’t have 2,000 books
in their entire home,”he say s.“ You can now fit
t h at many books on one disk, for free.” B u t
p e e ring into his crystal ball, he also foresees
public domain copyright laws extending on.
“If this is, i n d e e d , the inform ation age, I ask:
‘the inform ation age . . . for whom’?” n
+ …
l Project Gutenberg:www.gutenberg.net.
l The Oxford Text A rc h i v e :o t a . o x . a c. u k / i n d e x 2 . h t m l
Project Gutenberg’s founder Michael Hart,
a self-described “blue-collar rebel”.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
reas food production is gr owing at a rate of
1.5 per cent per year. Investment in irriga-
tion has virtually ceased and good land is
being lost to industri a l i z at i o n . If present
trends continue, it will not be possible to
meet future demand for food.
To what extent can new technologies help
to boost yields? Where is rice research
heading?
We now have rice va rieties which have a
yield potential of about 10 tonnes per hec-
tare.However,the present average yield of
i rri g ated rice in Asia is around 5 tonnes
per hectare under best management. To
increase the average output to 8 tonnes,
we have to fine-tune the production system
and invest more in irri g ation and in educa-
ting fa rm e rs about new technologi e s.We are
c o n fident that by early in the next century,
new seed varieties with a yield potential of
12 to 12.5 tonnes per hectare will be avai-
lable.
The future of rice research will be
o riented more towards eco-friendly agri-
culture. Rice breeders worldwide are now
d e veloping new rice plants which are
drought-resistant and pest-resistant, a n d
h ave the inbuilt capacity to outgr ow we e d s.
In the next 30 to 50 ye a rs ,t e m p e r at u r e - s e n-
sitive rice plants will also be needed with
tolerance to higher temperatures because of
global warming.
What is the next step for the International
Rice Research Institute (IRRI)?
At the IRRI, our next aim is to bring
46 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
Experts have warned of a possible food
crisis in Asia in the coming decades due to
population growth combined with lowered
rates of food production. Is there a
possibility of famine surfacing again in
some Asian countries?
The Asian region will definitely fa c e
food shortage some time in the future if
present trends continue. In most A s i a n
c o u n t ri e s , where the staple food is ri c e ,
p o p u l ation gr owth has not yet stabilized
and the demand for food is increasing.
According to UN estimates, by 2020 the
world population will have swollen to
around 8 billion people, 5 billion of whom
will be rice consumers. We estimate that
the wo r l d ’s rice harvest must increase from
the present 560 million tonnes to 840 mil-
lion tonnes per year to meet the demand.A l l
this has to come from existing agricultural
land, as no more cropland is available in
m a ny countri e s.While increasing food pro-
d u c t i o n , the Asian countries should also
think about active population control pro-
grammes.
How fast is food growth increasing to meet
the demand?
Unfortunately food production is not
keeping pace with population gr ow t h .B e t-
ween 1960 and 1990,global food produc-
tion was increasing at a rate of 2.8 per cent
per year while population grew at a rate of
b e t ween 2.1 and 2.2 per cent. So there wa s
not much of a problem. H owe ve r , the situa-
tion changed in the 1990s. N ow populat i o n
is increasing at the rate of 1.8 per cent whe-
about a “Green Green Revo l u t i o n ” to pro-
duce more rice from less land and water,
and without chemical pesticides or herbi-
c i d e s. For this we have developed a new
plant type, called “Super Rice”, which is in
the experimental stages.This new plant, a
product of conventional breeding methods,
will have an entirely different architecture
from that of our earlier seed varieties.
In IR8, the first high-yielding ri c e
va ri e t y, half of the plant’s weight is grain and
half is straw, whereas the new Super Rice
plant is 60 per cent grain and 40 per cent
straw.This new variety will have increased
photosynthetic capacity, directing more
energy into grain production and less into
f o l i a g e .An early prototype of this new plant
was developed a few ye a rs ago and now we
are working to improve the grain quality and
to incorp o r ate genes that will gi ve the seed
variety disease and pest resistance so that
fa rm e rs wo n ’t have to use pesticides. For the
f i rst time, we have “ b o rr owe d ” the gene
t h at gi ves maize its stem strength and intro-
duced it into the new plant.This will enable
the plant to carry more gr a i n s , increasing the
yield by at least 25 per cent compared to
existing varieties. We hope to release it to
Asian farmers by early next century.
When you started your career at the IRRI 32
years ago, the primary aim was to develop
Gurdev Singh Khush:
An architect of the Gre e n
Revolution* is now trying to
bring about a “ G reen Gre e n
R e v o l u t i o n ” to avert a food
crisis in the coming decades
* Gurdev S. Khush is Principal Plant Breeder 
and Head of the Division of Plant Breeding,Genetics
and Biochemistry at the International Rice Research
Institute (IRRI) based at Manila (the Philippines).
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G  T O …
high-yielding rice varieties to prevent a
food crisis. That led 
to the Green Revolution.Then came eco-
friendly agriculture and now efforts are
being made to develop genetically
modified seeds. How would you describe
this transition?
Asia witnessed acute food shortages in
the 1960s and it was urgent to step up food
production.This was achieved by develo-
ping high-yielding rice varieties like IR-8,
IR-36 and IR-64 at the IRRI which mat u r e d
in 110 days compared to the 180 day s
required for traditional va ri e t i e s.This trans-
f o rm at i o n , better known as the Green Revo-
l u t i o n , helped to double rice production in
Asia between 1967 and 1992, ave rt i n g
famine in many countri e s. In some countri e s
like Indonesia, rice production trebled.
H owe ve r , it was realized during the process
t h at indiscri m i n ate use of pesticides and
f e rt i l i z e rs caused environmental damage. S o
the emphasis shifted towards sustainable
agriculture. Farmers were encouraged to
use organic manure, compost and bio-fer-
t i l i z e rs. Subsequently new seed va ri e t i e s ,
genetically resistant to certain insect pests,
were also deve l o p e d , minimizing the use
of hazardous pesticides.
On the social side, we realized that the
new seed varieties were more successful in
irrigated areas with good water resources.
The impact of new technology was minimal
in uplands and rain-fed areas, where most
of the poor farmers lived. Our next chal-
lenge is to develop drought-resistant rice
va rieties to help those fa rm e rs living in
unfavourable environments.
masterminding a
new rice re v o l u t i o n
As a prominent actor in the Green
Revolution how would you react to
criticism that excessive use of fertilizers
and pesticides resulted in soil degradation?
I think most of this criticism is unjusti-
fied. We were about to witness famine in
Asia in the 1960s and the priority was to
increase food production. So mineral fert i-
l i z e rs and pesticides were used to boost
p r o d u c t i v i t y. But there is no evidence or
d ata to show that soil degr a d ation occurr e d
because of the Green Revolution process. I t
could have happened because of improper
use of agricultural lands. Excessive use of
f e rt i l i z e rs and pesticides and no proper
drainage systems in fields during heav y
rains or floods also contri buted to soil degr a-
d at i o n .N ow we actively promote Integr at e d
Pest Management, e n c o u r a ging fa rm e rs to
Farming on the edge of the city in Yunnan Province (China), below. In many Asian countries, urbanization and industrialization 
are steadily encroaching on cropland.China has introduced laws to stop agricultural land from being converted to use by industry and housing.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
rationalize pesticide use.
There are a lot of misconceptions about
the use of mineral fert i l i z e rs. Our research
findings have proved that rice plants defin i t e l y
need balanced nutrients to produce more
gr a i n .Whether these nutrients come from
mineral fert i l i z e rs or organic manure does not
m at t e r. Look at the fa rm e rs in the U. S .a n d
other developed countries who continue to
use fert i l i z e rs and harvest higher yields.If there
were problems in using mineral fert i l i z e rs ,
they would be the first ones to raise the alarm .
If fertilizers are not harmful why are some
farmers opting for organic farming?
Some farmers go for organic farming,
without using mineral fertilizers or pesti-
cides, because it is lucrative and there is a
demand for organic food in Western coun-
tries. But their production level is half of
what they used to harvest before by using
f e rt i l i z e rs. I am sure that if all fa rm e rs sw i t-
ched over to organic fa rm i n g, c u rrent food
production would be reduced by half, t ri g-
g e ring a food cri s i s. In my view, o r g a n i c
fa rming is not a viable altern at i ve but a
recipe for disaster.
Some say that many traditional rice
varieties have disappeared as a result of
48 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
The man b e h i n d the miracle
the introduction of IRRI’s new varieties,
resulting in loss of genetic diversity. What
is your response to this view?
It is natural for fa rm e rs to switch over to
new varieties providing higher yields. As a
c o n s e q u e n c e , the number of va rieties in
farmers’ fields goes down. In the U.S., for
e x a m p l e , fa rm e rs were gr owing over 50
va rieties of soya bean 30 ye a rs ago but now
they cultivate only five or six new high-yiel-
ding varieties. How can you stop farmers
from using a new variety which gives them
higher yields? It is not true that traditional
seed va rieties have been lost foreve r. We
collect those va rieties and save them in our
g e rmplasm bank at the IRRI. So fa r ,a b o u t
85,000 traditional rice varieties have been
collected from many parts of Asia, which
were grown before the Green Revolution.
Similarly countries like Indonesia, I n d i a
and China also have their own seed col-
lection centres.These will be used for gene-
rations to come when we want to develop
new seed varieties.
I disagree with the view that the genetic
potential of those traditional va rieties is
lost completely.When a new va riety is deve-
l o p e d , rice breeders incorp o r ate genes from
30 to 40 different traditional varieties and
incorporate them into the new seed.Take
the case of IR-64, a very popular variety
among Asian farmers. It has genes taken
from at least 44 different parents.We cannot
d e velop modern va rieties without tradi-
tional varieties.
According to a UN report, global fresh
water supplies are barely half of what 
they were 20 years ago and the shortage 
is likely to increase in the coming years.
How can farmers cope with the water
shortage?
This is going to be another major pro-
blem in future. Rice is a high wat e r - c o n s u-
ming crop but we find fa rm e rs using more
water than is actually required. On ave r a g e ,
fa rm e rs use 5,000 litres of water to produce
one kilogram of ri c e . It is not essential to use
so much wat e r. N ow there are technologi e s
available to produce one kilo of rice with as
little as 1,500 to 2,000 litres of wat e r.U n f o r-
t u n ately many fa rm e rs are not aware of these
new trends and do not have access to the new
t e c h n o l o gi e s. There is a misconception
among fa rm e rs that they need to maintain a
few inches of water above ground level in ri c e
fields throughout the gr owing peri o d . We
h ave shown that it is enough to keep the soil
s at u r ated with wat e r.A new initiat i ve needs
to be launched by rice-producing countri e s
to educate rice fa rm e rs about water mana-
g e m e n t .
There is a strong demand to produce more
rice to solve the food problem.However,
some environmental groups complain that
methane gas, which emerges out of rice
fields, contributes to the greenhouse effect.
How can this problem be solved?
It is true that methane emission occurs in
rice fields but the problem has been exag-
g e r at e d .S t atistics show that only 15 per cent
of global methane emission ori gi n ates from
paddy fields. The remaining 85 per cent
comes from industrial activities wo r l d w i d e .
So we should first try to reduce methane
emissions from industry by introducing alter-
n at i ve eco-friendly technologi e s. But yo u
cannot stop rice production. Rice will
Dr Gurdev Singh Khush may not be a house-
hold name. But his rice varieties are. In the
last 32 years, he and his team at the Interna-
tional Rice Research Institute (IRRI) in Manila,
have introduced over 300 new grain va r i e t i e s,
including IR8, I R 3 6 , IR64 and IR72,which triggered
the Green Revolution in Asia in the 1960s. To d a y,
IRRI rice varieties and their progenies are planted
in over 70 per cent of the world’s rice-fields.
“Farmers were initially sceptical about our
new grain va r i e t i e s,which took less time to mature
than traditional varieties. But our perseverance
paid dividends,” recalls Dr Khush. During the fir s t
25 years of Dr Khush’s programme, world rice
production doubled from 256 million tonnes in
1966 to 518 million tonnes in 1990,enabling an
additional 700 million people to obtain adequate
nutrition.
In 1976,Dr Khush introduced IR36, called “ t h e
miracle rice” that has since become one of the
w o r l d ’s most widely grown food crop va r i e t i e s.
According to IRRI estimates, IR36 has added about
five million tonnes of rice annually to A s i a ’s food
supply and accounts for an additional $1 billion
yearly income to Asian farmers.
What prompted Khush to take up a career in
agricultural research? “I come from Punjab, in nor-
thern India. There was a lot of poverty and not
enough food. My father was a farmer, and he
strongly encouraged me to do something for the
agricultural community,” says the 64-year- o l d
scientist. His pioneering research has won him
many awards, the most notable being the World
Food Prize in 1996,which he won for his contri-
bution to “ a d vancing human development by
improving the quality, quantity or availability of
the world’s food supply.” The prize, w i d e l y
regarded as the equivalent of a Nobel Prize for
agriculture, is awarded by the World Food Prize
Foundation based at Des Moines (USA).
Khush is now working on new grain va r i e t i e s
designed to increase yields by another 25 per
c e n t .“ The mission of my life is to continue to work
towards the improvement of rice, and to be able
to feed more and more people,” says Dr Khush
who now lives in Los Banos, near Manila in the
Philippines, with his wife, Dr Harwant K.Khush.
n E.A.
+ …
l IRRI Website
http://www.cgiar.org/irri
I am sure that if all farmers switched over to organic farming,
c u r rent food production would be reduced by half, triggering a
food crisis. In my view, o rganic farming is not a viable
alternative but a recipe for disaster
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
June 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 49
T A L K I N G  T O …
The world’s top ten rice-producing countries (thousands of tonnes)
continue to be gr own because it is the food
of humanity.At the IRRI we are also wo r k i n g
on ways to minimize or eliminate methane
emissions from rice fie l d s.
Many Asian countries talk about land re f o r m
designed to even out the distribution of
farmland among farmers and laboure rs.
U n f o r t u n a t e l y, in many countries land re f o r m
has not become a reality for socio-political
re a s o n s. Do you believe that the pre s e n t
unequal distribution of land has any
relevance to food production? 
Equal land distri bution among fa rm e rs
is highly relevant because it not only refle c t s
on food production but also on socio-eco-
nomic conditions. Look at the Indian expe-
ri e n c e . In states like West Bengal and Punjab,
land reforms were carried out in the 1960s
and 1970s and food production in those
r e gions has increased as a result. On the
c o n t r a ry, in the eastern state of Bihar most of
the land is owned by a handful of landlords.
This unequal land distri bution is the main
reason for the clashes between landow n e rs
and labourers there for the last 50 ye a rs.
B i h a r ’s average food production is also ve ry
l ow compared to other stat e s. In the Philip-
p i n e s , land reforms were introduced in the
early 1970s and since then rice lands have
been owned by rice producers , not by land-
l o r d s. Japan also undertook land reform s
after the Second World War and food pro-
duction has increased steadily since then.
Reports have shown that cultivable areas in
Asia are decreasing gradually due to rapid
urbanization and industrialization. What
repercussions will this have in the next 25
years?
In many Asian countri e s , p r o d u c t i ve
agricultural land is situated close to cities
and towns. When the cities expand these
lands become the first victims. In China, f o r
example,agricultural land is disappearing
rapidly to meet the demands of industrial
and housing projects. In the 1970s, the area
under rice cultivation in China was ove r
35 million hectares. By 1990 the figure had
dropped to 31 million hectares. C h i n a
doesn’t have additional land which can be
c o nve rted to agricultural purp o s e s. T h e
Chinese government is aware of this pro-
blem and has introduced strict laws to pre-
vent agricultural land from being conve rt e d
to industrial and housing purposes.
In Indonesia, p a rticularly in Java ,6 0 , 0 0 0
hectares of rice land are lost eve ry ye a r
n Rice-producing countries
Source: FAO Rice Information
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50 The UNESCO Courier - June 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
I WISH TO SUBSCRIBE TO the UNESCO Courier
Language: English French Spanish
Rates (postage included):
Industrialized countries: Developing countries or students 
1 year: 211French francs (€32,15) instead of 264FF* (11 issues including 1 double issue) (Please send copy of your card):
2 years:396 French francs (€60,35) instead of 528FF* (22 issues including 2 double issues) 1 year: 132 French francs (€20,10)
Binder: 72French francs (€11) (for 11 issues including 1 double issue) 2 years: 211 French francs (€32,15)
I enclose payment: (in French francs only) by
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque) Visa Mastercard Eurocard
N° — —— — — — — ——— — — — — — — — —— Expiry date: Date and signature:
Name First name
Address
Postal code City
Optional
Age: Occupation: Teachers and students
Special field: Level:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering the optional questions above.
(*) Total cover price
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to:
the UNESCO Courier Subscription Services, 31,rue François Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are opposite this order form.
"
because of increasing demand for houses
and fa c t o ri e s , and in the Philippines,they lose
around 10,000 hectares of rice fields for the
same reasons.We should remember that ri c e
fields being consumed by urban gr ow t h
cannot simply be replaced by clearing more
f o r e s t s. C o u n t ries such as the Philippines
d o n ’t have much forest left.To partly com-
p e n s at e ,Asian countries should try to bri n g
more areas under irri g at i o n . Again that
requires a lot of inve s t m e n t .
Scientists say that the arrival of monsoon
rains has been either delayed or advanced
due to global climate change, affecting
farming communities in many Asian
countries. What could the consequences be
if the pattern continues?
It will be ve ry destru c t i ve for agri c u l t u r e
if this change in the we ather pat t e rn ,k n ow n
as the La Niña effect, s t rikes again this ye a r.
In Southeast Asia last year, the monsoon
was delayed by four months whereas it
rained heavily during the harvest season so
that rice crops were destroyed.As a result,
rice fa rm e rs have suffered heavy losses in the
last two years. Rice production in the Phi-
lippines and Indonesia has gone into sharp
decline following the La Niña effect. I hope
this continues to be a rare phenomenon,
which occurs once eve ry 10 ye a rs or more.
If it happens every year then it will have a
devastating effect on rice cultivation.
Has the Asian financial crisis had an impact
on rice production?
The Asian financial crisis pri m a ri l y
affected South Korea,T h a i l a n d , I n d o n e s i a
and Malay s i a . In South Korea and Malay s i a ,
the agricultural sector was unaffected, a n d
rice production in those countries has been
n o rmal for the last two ye a rs. T h a i l a n d
managed to withstand the crisis mainly
because of its strength in rice cultivat i o n .
M a ny Thais who were working in fa c t o ri e s
m oved back to rice fields following the eco-
nomic cri s i s.As a result, the area under ri c e
c u l t i vation increased and Thailand was able
to produce more rice than in the previous
ye a rs.The Thai gove rnment has realized that
rice cultivation is the country ’s backbone, a n d
is paying more attention to agriculture now.
In Indonesia, the economic crisis has
had an adve rse impact. In the afterm ath of
the cri s i s , the cash-strapped Indonesian
g ove rnment stopped giving subsidies for fer-
t i l i z e rs and fertilizer prices shot up.M a ny ri c e
fa rm e rs had to abandon their crops because
they simply could not afford to buy fert i l i z e rs
at the new rat e s. Economic cri s i s , along with
La Niña, hit rice output in Indonesia last
ye a r , reducing rice stocks to their lowe s t
l e vel in the last decade. Indonesia was a ri c e
e x p o rter until a few ye a rs ago but now
i m p o rts three million tonnes a ye a r.
What about China?
M a ny experts have predicted that China
is likely to face a major food shortage in the
next century.The population is still increa-
sing at the rate of 1.1 per cent. It is estimat e d
t h at the population gr owth rate will stabilize
only after touching the 1.6 billion mark
compared to the present 1.2 billion.That
means another 400 million to 500 million
more people to feed. Only 11 per cent of the
total land area in China is suited to agri-
c u l t u r e .The rest consists of mountains and
deserts. So China will become the largest
i m p o rter of food grains 30 ye a rs from now.
n
Interview by Ethirajan Anbarasan
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
L I S T  O F S A L E S A N D S U B S C R I P T I O N A G E N T S
Subscr ipt ion s can be paid to t he subsc ript ion agent in you r cou ntry who wil l  su pply rates in  local  currency on re q u e s t
A R G E N T I N A : Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UN E S C O,
Tucumán 1685, 1050 Buenos A i r e s. Fa x :3 7 1 - 8 1 9 4 .
AU S T R A L I A : Hunter Publicat i o n s , 58A Gipps Street,
C o l l i n g wood VIC 3066. Fa x : 419 7154. ISA A u s t r a l i a ,
PO Box 709,To owong QLD 4066. Fa x : 371 5566.
United Nations A s s o c. of A u s t r a l i a / V i c t o rian Div. ,
179 St George's Road,
N. F i t z r oy VIC 3068. Fa x : 481 7693.
AU S T R I A : Gerold & Co, I m p o rt & Export ,
Z e i t s c h ri f t e n / Pe ri o d i c a l s , Graben 31, A-1011 V i e n n a .
Fa x : 512 47 31 29
B E L G I U M : Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Bru s s e l s.
Fa x : 538 08 41.
B R A Z I L : Fundaco Getulio Va r g a s , Editora Divisão de Ve n d a s ,
Caixa Postal 62.591, 22257-970 Rio de Janeiro RJ.
Fa x :5 5 1 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA : Renouf Publishing Company Ltd,
5369 ch.Canotek Road,Unit 1,Ottawa,Ont K1J 9J3.
Fax:(1-613) 745 7660. Faxon Canada,POBox 2382,London,
Ont.N6A 5A7. Fax:(1-519) 472 1072.
C H I L E : U n i ve rs i t a ria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10220,
S a n t i a g o. Fa x : 681 9091.
C H I N A : China National Publicat i o n s ,I m p o rt & Export
C o rp. , PO Box 88, 16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 100020.
Fa x : 010 65063101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30,111 27
Prague 1.
D E N M A R K : M u n k s g a a r d ,N o rre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148,
DK-1016 Kobenhavn K. Fa x : 12 93 87.
F I N L A N D : S t o c k m a n n / A k ateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23,
SF-00371 Helsinki. Fa x : +358 9 121 4450.
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF-01641 Va n t a a .
Fa x : 852 7990.
G E R M A N Y: G e rman Commission for UN E S C O, C o l m a n t s t r.
1 5 , D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 63 69 12.
Uno Ve r l a g, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55,
D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 21 74 92.
G R E E C E : L i b r a i rie Kauffmann SA, M a u v r o k o r d atou 9,
GR-106 78 A t h e n s. Fa x : 38 33 967.
G UAT E M A L A : Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con
la UN E S C O, 3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1,A p a rtado Postal 2630,
G u atemala City.
HONG KO N G : Hong Kong Gove rnment Inform ation Svcs.
D e p t . , 1 Bat t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
H U N G A RY: Librotrade K F T, Pe riodical Import / K ,
POB 126, H-1656 Budapest. Fa x :2 5 6 - 8 7 - 2 7 .
I N D I A : O rient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions A c c o u n t ) ,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estat e ,B o m b ay 400 038.
Fa x : 26 91 278.
Oxford Book & Stat i o n e ry Co, Code No D 8208052,
Scindia House, New Delhi 110 001. Fa x : 33 22 639.
I S R A E L : L i t e r a ry Transactions Inc. , C/0 Steimatsky Ltd.,
PO Box 1444, Bnei Brak 51114. Fa x : 52 81 187.
I TA LY: L i c o s a / L i b r e ria Comm. Sansoni SPA ,
Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-50125 Florence. Fa x :6 4 - 1 2 - 5 7 .
J A PA N : E a s t e rn Book Service Inc. , Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
3 13 Hongo 3 Chome, B u n k yo Ku ,To k yo 113. Fa x :8 1 8 - 0 8 6 4 .
KO R E A : Korean National Commission for UN E S C O,
CPO Box 64, Seoul 100-600. Fa x : 568 7454.
L U X E M B U R G : M e s s a g e ries Paul Kraus, BP 2022,
L-1020 Luxe m b o u r g . Fa x : 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA : Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36,
26 Republic Street,Valletta CMR 01. Fa x : 24 61 82.
M AU R I T I U S : Nalanda Co. L t d . , 30 Bourbon Street,
Po rt Louis. Fa x : 212 1313.
M O RO C C O : UN E S C O, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat
Fax:212-767 03 75, Tel.:212-767 03 74/72.
M E X I C O : Librería El Correo de la UN E S C O S A , Col Roma,
G u a n a j u ato 72, Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF.
Fa x :2 6 4 - 0 9 - 1 9 .
N E T H E R L A N D S : S wets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830,
2160 SZ Lisse. Fa x :2 5 2 4 - 1 5 8 8 8 .
T i j d s c h riftcentrale Wijck B V, I n t .S u b s. S e rv i c e ,W
G r a c h t s t r a at 1C, 6221 CT Maastri c h t . Fa x : 32 50 103.
NEW ZEALAND: GP Legi s l ation Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 12418,T h o rn d o n ,We l l i n g t o n .
Fa x : 496 56 98.
NORWAY : S wets Norge A S ,Ø s t e n s j ø vein 18-0606 Oslo,
PO Box 6512,Etterstad. Fax:47 22 97 45 45.
P O RT U G A L : L i v r a ria Po rtugal (Dias & Andrade Lda),
Rua do Carmo 70 74, 1200 Lisboa. Fa x : 34 70 264.
R U S S I A : Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39,
M o s c ow 113095.
SOUTH A F R I C A : I n t e rn ational Subscription Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 41095, Craighall 2024. Fa x : 880 6248.
Mast Publicat i o n s , PO Box 901, Parklands 2121.
Fa x : 886 4512.
S PA I N : Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37,
28001 Madri d . Fa x :9 1 5 7 5 - 3 9 - 9 8 .
L i b r e ria Al A n d a l ú s , Roldana 3 y 4, 410091 Sevilla.
Fa x :9 5 4 2 2 - 5 3 - 3 8 .
Los Amigos de la UN E S C O, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd.,
48011 Bilbao. Fa x :9 4 4 2 7 - 5 1 - 5 9 / 6 9
SRI LANKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam,
Gardiner Mawat h a , Colombo 2. Fa x : 44 78 48.
S W E D E N : We n n e r gren Williams A B , PO Box 1305,
S-171 25 Solna. Fa x : 27 00 71.
S W I T Z E R L A N D : Dynapresse Marketing SA, ( e x - N av i l l e
S A ) , 38 av V i b e rt , CH-1227 Carouge. Fa x : 308 08 59.
E d i group SA, Case Postale 393, CH-1225 Chêne-Bourg.
Fa x : 348 44 82.
Europa Ve r l a g, Ramistrasse 5, CH-8024 Züri c h .
Fa x : 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG ,W i s s e n s c h a f t l .B u c h h a n d l u n g,
Pe t e rs graben 31, CH-4009 Basel. Fa x : 306 12 34.
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E C O,
Chemin du Lacuez, CH-1807 Blonay. Fa x : 943 36 05.
T H A I L A N D : Suksapan Pa n i t , Mansion 9, R a j a d a m n e rn
Ave n u e , Bangkok 2. Fa x : 28 11 639.
T U N I S I A : Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de
l ’UN E S C O, 2 2 , rue de l’Angleterr e , 1000RP Tu n i s.
Fa x : 33 10 14
UNITED KINGDOM: The Stat i o n e ry Office Publicat i o n s
C t r e . , 51 Nine Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR.
Fa x : 873 84 63.
UNITED STAT E S : B e rnan A s s o c i at e s , 4611-F A s s e m b l y
D ri ve , Lanham MD 20706-4391. Fa x :4 5 9 - 0 0 5 6 .
U R U G UAY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
Maldonado 1090, M o n t e v i d e o. Fa x : 90 59 83.
V E N E Z U E L A : UN E S C O/ C R E S A L C ,E d i f. A s ov i n c a r ,
Av Los Chorr o s ,C ruce C/C A c u e d u c t o, Altos de Sebu c a n ,
C a r a c a s. Fa x : 286 03 26.
UNESCO PUBLISHING
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publications
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
World
Social
Science
Report
1 9 9 9
The first volume 
of a new biennial report
The social sciences 
as tools for understanding
today’s world
UNESCO Publishing/Elsevier
352 pp.,29.7 x 21 cm,
figures, charts,statistics
ISBN:92-3-103602-5
Price: 295 FF per copy
plus 30FF postage per order
Written by a truly
international team of
highly regarded authors,
the World Social
Science Report is a
unique source of facts,
figures and assessments
of the role of the social
sciences in the world
today.
Both specialists and 
the general public will
find chapters addressing
their concerns, written
in a language that is
accessible without loss
of rigour.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Fo c u s :
Tourism and culture:
Rethinking the relationship
n The ethical stakes of cultural tourism
n Indigenous hosts and tourist guests: Venezuela, Australia,
the Himalayas, the Canadian Far North . . .
n The dilemmas of the heritage business: Petra, Luang Prabang,
Venice. . .
n Packaging the heritage: Central Europe, southern Morocco,
Santiago de Compostela
n A guidebook guru speaks out
n Club Med’s Gilbert Trigano: empires in the sand
Features include:
n The island-hoppers of Bangladesh
n The war toll on biodiversity
n Overruling sovereignty: the case for humanitarian intervention
n Comic strips for peace
n Life after death for the Morse code?
n Interview with Albanian intellectual Jusuf Vrioni:
the roots of Balkan crises
]]>
</page>
</document>
