<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="117043eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
B I O E T H I C S
The lure of the perfect child
September 1999
PEOPLE AND PLACES
Forever young
in Cuba
PLANET
Millennium bugs
with
a deadly bite
CONNEXIONS
Internet
and
paedophilia
IN T ERV IEW
Sunila Abeysekera,
peace campaigner
in Sri Lanka
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
52nd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Film duplication:Annick Coueffé
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian:Gianluca Formichi,Sira Miori (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e : Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UN E S C O or those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. P h o t o
captions and headlines are written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r
s t a f f. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O o r
the United Nations. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7
Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfil m s
( X e r o x ) , Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C . R .
Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d , Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - SEPEMBER 1999
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Pa r i s
by UN E S C O. Printed in Fr a n c e. Periodicals postage paid at
Champlain NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 N°9-1999-OPI 99-585 A
C o n t e n t s
September 1999
C o v e r, page 2: illustration by André Fr a n ç o i s. Focus drawings by Hervé Pinel, Paris
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 Fo rever young in Cuba
Photos by Grégoire Ko r g a n o w,text by Antonio José Po n t e
EDITORIAL
9 A crucial encounter Federico Mayor
PLANET
10 Millennium bugs with a deadly bite Robert Matthews
13 The ten plagues of Egypt triggered by ecological disaster?
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Schooling in times of strife Mark Richmond
16 Lessons and challenges of  Kosovo M . R .
FOCUS
ETHICS
3 7 Is copyright on the wrong tra c k ? Mireille Buydens
38 The counterfeiting industry
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 C a r t h a g e ’s long-awaited re s c u e Sophie Bessis
42 Tug of war in Beirut and Cairo Sophie Boukhari
CONNEXIONS
43 Pa e d o p h i l i a : the darker side of the Net Cynthia Guttman
TALKING TO…
46 Sunila A b e y s e k e ra :peace campaigner on a war-torn island
CUS
1 7 B i o t h e t i c s : the lure of the perfect child
With a new “genetic age” on the horizon,
future parents may seek to create a made-
to-order “dream child”. This prospect leads 
to a thicket of thorny bioethical questions.
Will genetics spawn new forms of eugenics? 
Will societal pressures exert a coercive force on
procreative decisions and influence our conception of a
life worth living?
Detailed table of contents on page 17.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
w Photos on pages 3-8 are taken from Avoir 20 ans à
La Havane, by Grégoire Korganow and Jean Springer,
published by Editions Alternatives, Paris, 1998. Antonio
José Ponte is a Cuban writer and poet (see page 6).
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
n
Spend an evening in Havana or some
other Cuban town such as Matanzas
or Pinar del Río and you get the fee-
ling time is at a standstill. The past slips
away, and the future is a long time
coming, so you are left stuck in the pre-
sent. To be 20 years old in Cuba is to be
20 years old for ever. It is either a won-
derful gift or a refined form of torment.
The choice is yours.
Twenty is an age when you most feel
F OREV ER TW EN TY
IN CUBA 
wPhotos by Grégoire Korganow
Text by Antonio José Ponte
Cuba’s young men and women in a hurry face up to a frustrating situation
where time seems to stand still
A bride at her parents’ home, just before a Havana wedding. The divorce rate in Cuba is high, and it is not uncommon 
for Cubans to marry three or four times.
the immensity of time.Young people have
m a ny hopes, but they are quickly
betrayed. After three or four dreams have
come to nothing, those that are left seem
vain. Impatience makes you see every-
thing that happens in the same way. You
h ave n ’t yet learned the adult art of
concealing boredom.
Asking young Cubans about the futu-
re, or—to put it more bluntly—about
their destiny, is like asking them for a false
address.They’ll say they’ve never heard of
it, that it doesn’t exist.The shrewdest of
them will say that the future is elsewhere,
not here.
When yo u ’re 20, you want to be
somewhere else, far away. Perhaps most
20-year-olds feel like that, all over the
world. They certainly do in Cuba. The
capital and provincial towns and villages
are full—crowded and empty at the same
time—of things that signify nothing.
You’re at the ideal age to enter a new
world, but you find the world around you
has already been taken over by others who
got there before you.
It isn’t possible to create anything new
in a country at the end of its history.
Revolutions come to power to make sure
t h at gove rnments stand still, on the
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
‘ T HE MOST BE A U T IFUL LA ND ’
4 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Atlantic Ocean
Caribbean Sea
grounds that there have already been
enough changes in the country’s history.
When you are young, you tend to look
for things that have not been fouled up by
earlier generations, things that they did
not know about and so are untainted by
their approval.
Fed up with provincial life, people can
set their sights on moving to Havana,
while people tired of Havana will want to
leave the country. Afterwards, often when
it’s impossible to return, they will want to
be back in Havana, or in some provincial
town or village.The reason for such wan-
derings is partly biological, partly politi-
cal. Or rather totally biological and total-
ly political, if we accept that in cities
human biology has become political.
A thirst for adventure
The Cuban government has often mana-
ged to turn this desire to escape to its own
advantage.Taking part in other countries’
wars, compulsory military service, schoo-
ling organized in the fields,and the mobi-
lization of teenagers all exploit this need
to leave home and slake a thirst for adven-
t u r e . These are children’s cru s a d e s ,
exceptional intervals in the preva i l i n g
stagnation.
Many are set on leaving—the youth
When Christopher Columbus landed on the
island of Cuba in 1492, he wrote in his tra v e l
d i a ry that he had come across “the most beautiful
land ever seen by human eyes”. Today the 110 , 8 6 0 -
sq.km island, the biggest in the Caribbean, has a
population of about 11 million, more than half of
them of mixed blood. One fifth of the population live
in the capital, Havana.
HAVANA
Mexico
United States of America
Bahamas
Haiti
Jamaica
Pinar del Río
Nueva Gerona
La Juventud
Cienfuegos
Sancti-Spiritus
Victoria de las Tunas
Santiago de Cuba
Holguin
Guantanamo
Bayaamo
Matanzas
Santa Clara
Ciego de Avila
Camagüey
who builds a raft and sneaks out of the
country on it, those who try their luck in
the U.S. immigration lottery, or sell their
bodies to foreigners in the hope of getting
help to leave the country. For people who
live in the unending present, the best ploy
is to saturate each moment with activity,
until it gives way to the next. You can call
that joie de vivre or a horror of the void—
take your pick. Young people in Cuba are
full of both.
A social experiment like the 1959
revolution,which has spent so many years
defying the basic laws of economics,
which imposes austerity as a way of thin-
king and poverty as a daily routine, is
A sugarcane processing plant near Cienfuegos in central Cuba. Before its collapse, the USSR bought on
preferential terms almost half Cuba’s sugar harvest, which then amounted to some 7 million tons a year. The
yield fell to 3.2 million tons in 1998.
Since the 19 59 revolution, Cuba has been a com-
munist state headed by Fidel Castro who, as well as
being president is chairman of the Council of State
and the Council of Ministers, first secretary of the
Cuban Communist Party (the only permitted party)
and commander-in-chief of the armed forces.
Education and health care for all have been two
of the pillars of the revolution for the past 40 years.
As a result, Cubans have a level of litera cy only sur-
passed in Latin America by Argentina and Uru-
guay, and the region’s highest life expectancy (76 .1
years). 
Several hundred Cuban doctors are presently
working outside the country. The tradition of sen-
ding doctors abroad started soon after the revolu-
tion began and peaked between 1975 and 1989.
In the early 1990s, the collapse of the commu-
nist bloc plunged Cuba into a serious economic
crisis. According to the Cuban government, the
island’s gross national product (GNP) fell by 35%
b e tween 1989 and 1993, and then rose by 2.5% in
1995, 7.8% in 1996 and 2.5% in 19 97. According to
United Nations statistics, Cuba’s per capita GNP was
$ 1,983 in 1995. Castro has cautiously opened up the
country to foreign capital, allowed the free circu-
lation of the U.S. dollar, and encouraged the deve-
lopment of tourism. These changes have led to
the reappearance of social problems such as pros-
titution and petty crime which had been era d i-
cated or had become insignificant.
In the political sphere, the one-party system
continues to exist, the independent media cannot
develop, and international human rights organi-
zations deplore the way dissidents are treated. 
An estimated one million Cubans are thought to live
in exile.  n
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Tobacco is dried after being harvested near Pinar del Rio (in the west of the island). Cuba produced more than 160 million Havana cigars in 1998 and exported them to
around 100 countries. The USA, Cuba’s main customer before the revolution, still maintains a trade embargo on Cuban goods, including the famous cigars.
Sugarcane cutters near Santiago in southern Cuba. Sugar is white, brown and black—like Cuba’s population since the time of the slave trade, 
say the poets.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
CUBA’S NEW WAV E
OF WRI T ERS AND POET S
The poet and short story writer Antonio José
Ponte was born in 1964 in Matanzas, about
100km east of Havana, and in 1980 moved to the
Cuban capital where he studied hydraulics. After
qualifying he worked as a hydraulic engineer for
five years.
He has won Cuba’s National Critics’ Prize
twice—in 1991 for Poesia 1982-1989 (“Poetry
19 8 2 - 1989”, published by Le t ras Cubanas,
Havana) and in 1995 for his book Un seguidor de
M o n t a i gne mira La Habana ( “A disciple of
Montaigne looks at Havana”, published by Vigia,
Matanzas). In 1995, he was awarded a writer’s
scholarship by the Alejo Carpentier Foundation
in Havana. His first book, Trece poemas
(“Thirteen Poems”) was published in 1988 by the
Cuban ministry of culture and won him the
young poet’s prize in the same year.
In 1997, he published Asiento en las ruinas (“A
Seat in the Ruins”, Le t ras Cubanas publishers) and
a short story, C o razón de Skitalietz (“Heart of 
S k i t a l i e tz”). His latest book, Las comidas pro f u n d a s
(“Profound sustenance”), was published in
Spanish in 1997 by the French publisher Deleatur,
in Angers. This elegant and scholarly work, which
is hard to categorize (it is neither a short story, nor
an essay nor a novel) deals with the history of food
and the relationship between human beings and
what they eat.
The International Writers’ Parliament in Stras-
bourg recently awarded Ponte a one-year scholar-
ship to live in Porto, Portugal, and write a novel.
While in Portugal he will continue to contribute to
the Cuban magazines La Gaceta de Cuba, Union
(the magazine of the Cuban Writers’ and Artists’
Union, UNEAC), Casas de las Americas and Le t ra s
Cubanas.
At 34, Ponte is one of the new wave of young
Cuban poets and writers, including Le o n a r d o
Pa d u ra, Abilio Estevez, Ronaldo Menendez Pla-
sencia, Daniel Diaz Mantilla, Ismael González, Ales-
sandra Molina and many others. n
bound to produce young people with an
outsized acquisitive instinct. To be 20 in
Cuba is to be obsessed with money. A
country where wages are paid in the
national currency but where you can only
live if you have foreign currency, incites
people to flee, to go to the place where
that currency comes from.
One might object that education will
e ventually change the situation of Cuban
yo u n g s t e rs. But teachers ’ lessons do not deal
with the real wo r l d .This is inevitable.Like all
e d u c at i o n , Cuban education teaches people
to aspire, to want certain things, to achieve
g o a l s. But these are verbs that cannot be
c o n j u g ated when time stands still, w h e n
there is a vo i d . If the yo u n g s t e rs happen to
get good training, it will simply equip them
to live far away, a b r o a d .
The equation boils down to shortages
on the one hand, and money and beauty
on the other. This is a discovery made at
20 which stays with you until the day you
sink into oblivion and death.
In Cuba, at 20, you discover another
r e a l i t y : the inability to run your own life, o r
to try to balance the two sides of the equa-
t i o n . But long before you reach 20,you dis-
cover that what’s lacking is freedom. n
After work in a rural school (escuela del campo) near Pinar del Rio in western Cuba. Secondary school pupils over the age of 12 attend such schools for two months
each year as a “social service in agriculture”.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
Sunday on the beach, Santiago de Cuba.
The University of Havana. In 1995, 12.7% of young Cubans entered university, as against 20.1% in 1985. All children receive primary education and 94% reach the fifth
year of schooling. Three-quarters of young people from 12 to 17 are in school. Adult illiteracy is low.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A young couple and their child.
A Cuban rock singer rehearses in Havana. Young Cubans, like their elders, love music and dance. Fiesta time means salsa, timba, guaracha, mambo, rumba, rock,
techno, son, guajira, trova, danzón, bolero, and cha-cha-cha.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E D I T O R I A L
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 9
n
If a scientific discovery can form the basis of a technology, then it is highly pro-
bable that the technology will eventually be applied. Today this lesson of his-
tory is causing anxiety among politicians,scientists and public opinion concer-
ned about the current far-reaching developments in biotechnologies.
It is now possible to penetrate to the very essence of living things as a result of
spectacular scientific advances that are gradually revealing the innermost mecha-
nisms of life.The technologies based on this field of knowledge offer humanity for
the first time astonishing powers to revolutionize the process of creating and deve-
loping human beings and, ultimately, the human species. Technically speaking,
these breakthroughs could lead to the revival,in even more effective guises,of euge-
nic practices we hoped had been buried forever. Fortunately, this nightmare sce-
nario seems highly unlikely.
But history also shows that new technologies are rarely applied without a fra-
mework of rules and procedures designed to ensure that they are beneficially used.
Human progress has always been driven by the winds of freedom, including free-
dom of enquiry and initiative, but human beings have always tried to head in the
right direction and to respect certain limits. The biologists have done their work:
they have sown the seeds of vast possibilities. Now it is up to society to make sure
that only the benefits are harvested.The biotechnology revolution beckons huma-
nity to a crucial encounter between science and ethics.
Where human reproduction is concerned, as with technology in general, we
must be guided by respect for three basic and interdependent principles—dignity,
freedom and solidarity.
For human dignity to be respected, each person must be regarded as unique.
This position has far-reaching consequences for human procreat i o n . F i rst of all, i t
rules out cloning as a means of reproduction because this technique, which is
almost upon us, i nvo l ves genetically “ d u p l i c at i n g ” an existing pers o n . More gene-
r a l l y, p r e d e t e rmining the basic characteristics of a future pers o n , notably trying to
enhance their future physical or mental capacities, v i o l ates the ve ry essence of
human individuality. This kind of engi n e e ring would end up by depriving indivi-
duals of that which is theirs alone—the my s t e rious processes whereby their unique
genetic heritage emerges and interacts in its own unique way with their env i r o n-
m e n t .
Advances in prenatal scanning and testing techniques may confront parents
with grave new decisions. The danger is that various kinds of pressures or even
regulations will develop which only allow “genetically correct” people to be born.
This would be totally unacceptable. No authority—be it political, social or econo-
mic—should be able to enact such a “genetic order”, still less impose it.
So increasing emphasis must be laid on solidarity. Genetic tests and treatments
must not be allowed to create new forms of discrimination—between those who,
for whatever reason, can or want to take advantage of them,and those who cannot,
mostly for lack of money.
The risk of uncontrolled, unmonitored genetic engineering increasingly looms
over us. But we are starting to see the emergence of a new “responsible” form of
genetic engineering in which the power of science is subjected to the power of
ethics—an ethics that benefits everyone, not just a few, and looks towards future
generations, not just short-term interests. n
Federico Mayor
Genetic tests
and treatments
must not be
a l l o w e d
to create new
forms of
d i s c r i m i n a t i o n —
b e tween those
who, for whatever
reason, can or
want to ta ke
a d v a n tage of them,
and those who
cannot, mostly for
lack of money
A CRUCIAL ENCOUN T ER
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
P L A N E T
n
At firs t , the men seemed to be sufferi n g
from nothing more than a case of
i n flu e n z a : a bad headache,aching joints,
a feve r. But it quickly became clear that
dozens of Durba’s gold miners in the
D e m o c r atic Republic of the Congo were in
the grip of something far wo rs e .S o m e h ow,
late last year, they had come into contact
with a terrifying infectious agent that was
attacking all their internal organs, causing
them to bleed uncontrollably.
O ver the following months, over 60
m i n e rs died from the my s t e ry disease, t h e i r
limp bodies covered with blotches and
oozing blood even after deat h .Local doctors
had never seen anything like it. At firs t ,n o t
e ven seasoned experts from the Wo r l d
Health Organization (WHO) could say for
sure what was causing such appalling
deaths.
But many harboured the same suspi-
cion: that the miners had become infected
by a so-called emerging viru s : a tiny packet
of genes that had lain undisturbed in its
natural lair for years, perhaps millennia—
until humankind blundered into it.
The suspicion was that the my s t e ry
disease was caused by a so-called fil ov i ru s ,
a thread-like virus whose deva s t ating effect
on the human body had first been disco-
vered 30 years ago.
In 1967, dozens of people working in
l a b o r at o ries in Germ a ny and Yu g o s l avia fell
ill with eerily similar symptoms. S e ven died,
and many of the survivors suffered long-
t e rm effects ranging from impotence to
i n s a n i t y. The source of the infection wa s
traced to a batch of ve rvet monkeys
i m p o rted from Uganda, m a ny of which had
died during transportation.
The monkeys were found to be car-
rying a filov i ru s , which was duly named
after one of the German towns where the
first cases emerged: M a r bu r g .To this day, n o
cure has been found. If the victim’s immune
system cannot fight it, i t ’s over—a fate that
awaits over 50 per cent of those who become
infected.
Deadly pathogens—
do not disturb
In May, WHO confirmed eve ryo n e ’s
f e a rs : tests on blood samples taken from the
miners showed that they had indeed been
infected with Marburg virus. Soon reports
began to emerge of an outbreak of the same
disease among soldiers in Zimbabwe .T h o u-
sands of troops had been crossing into DRC
to support President Laurent Désiré Kabila
as he tried to put down a rebel uprising.
Fo rt u n at e l y, blood tests on three soldiers
suspected of carrying Marburg turned out
to be negat i ve , and by early summer the out-
break in Durba was ove r. The virus had
vanished again, back into its jungle haunts—
but precisely where, no one know s. S o m e w-
here out there, a creature—a species of bat ,
p e r h a p s , or a rodent—is unwittingly acting
as a refuge for Marburg.
W h at is clear is that the more incur-
sions into virgin terri t o ry humankind
m a k e s , the gr e ater the risk of another
encounter with Marburg—or perhaps some-
thing wo rs e . After decades of insouciant
use and abuse of the wo r l d ’s nat u r a l
r e s o u r c e s , from the primordial forests of
e q u at o rial A f rica to the oceans, the threat of
disturbing new and deadly pathogens now
has to be taken seriously.
The wa rning signs have long been clear.
As long ago as 1485,reports emerged of a
disease known as the Swe ating Sickness,
in which victims progressed from sudden
swe ating to prostration and death in just 24
h o u rs. It struck four more times before
vanishing again in 1551. But the country
affected was not some isolated jungle com-
munity in the tropics.The Sweating Sick-
ness wreaked its havoc in England, u l t i m a-
tely claiming the lives of around 20,000
p e o p l e — over 0.5 per cent of the total 
population.
Recent research has linked the emer-
gence of Sweating Sickness to a strikingly
MIL L ENNIUM BUGS 
WITH A DE A DLY BI T E
w Robert Matthews
Through an arrogant or ignorant disregard for ecological complexities, ceaseless human
encroachment on nature can unleash a terrible new threat of killer diseases carried by
microbes that have long lain undisturbed 
w Science Correspondent of the Sunday Telegraph,
London
Deforestation in Madagascar. The emergence of several lethal viruses has been linked to the destruction of
woodland.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
modern phenomenon: deforestation.The
timing and spread of the outbreak ties in
with the mass destruction of woodland in
S h r o p s h i r e , on the we s t e rn borders of
England.The suspicion is that forest wor-
k e rs somehow allowed the virus respon-
sible for the disease to spread beyond the
c r e ature that had acted as its host for count-
less generat i o n s , b ri n ging it into contact
with populations big enough to sustain an
epidemic.
This is a scenario that has been played
out again and again in our own times. In
Argentina after the Second World Wa r , va s t
areas of the Pampas were cleared with her-
bicide to make way for new crops. In the
p r o c e s s , the natural balance between a spe-
cies of field mouse and its predat o rs was dis-
t u r b e d , and the numbers of the form e r
soared—as did those of itinerant fa rm - wo r-
k e rs. By the early 1950s, people began to fa l l
prey to feve rs , vomiting and headache.
Some went on to suffer massive haemor-
r h a gi n g, and died hideous deat h s.The cause
was eventually traced to a previously unk-
n own viru s ,J u n i n ,c a rried by the field mice.
The same story was repeated in Bolivia,
where farmers keen to grow maize hacked
d own stretches of jungle near the Machupo
R i ve r. Sure enough, the reports of strange,
h o rrible deaths among fa rm - wo r k e rs start e d
to roll in, and their cause was traced to
another haemorrhagic virus, duly named
Machupo, again carried by field mice.
And early in 1999, evidence emerged to
link campaigns of deforestation to the rise
of the most notorious emergent disease of
them all: A i d s. In Fe b ru a ry, an intern a-
tional team of researchers published a paper
in the journal N at u r e t h at points to the
chimpanzee Pan troglodytes trog l o d y t e s as the
natural host of HIV-1, the lethal virus that
now infects over 30 million people world-
wide.
Killed for their meat by hunters hired by
timber companies, these apes are bu t c h e r e d
in their thousands each year in conditions
t h at are ripe for the transmission of viru s e s.
Finding its way into cities via infected meat
for restaurants and via the hunters them-
s e l ve s , H I V-1 went on to be sexually 
transmitted throughout the world, accor-
ding to this latest research.To dat e , over 12
million people have died from A i d s , 80 per
cent of them in sub-Saharan Africa.
The dangers of an arrogant disregard for
the complexities of ecosystems may take
other forms than the destruction of virgin
territory. It was, for example, attempts at
r e f o r e s t ation in nort h - e a s t e rn A m e ri c a
d u ring the 19th century that led to the
recent emergence of Lyme Disease, a poten-
tially fatal bacterial infection affecting the
j o i n t s ,h e a rt and brain, passed to humans via
ticks carried by deer.
The deer came into contact with
humans following moves to rectify the
impact of deforestation caused by inten-
s i ve fa rm i n g . Local gove rnments launched
p r e s e rvation and reforestation progr a m m e s ,
and created a landscape attractive to both
h u m a n s , deer—and Ixodes scapulari s, a deer-
b o rne tick which carries B o rrelia 
A microbiologist carries out culture tests at South Africa’s National Institute for Virology in Johannesburg in May 1999. Results showed that the Marburg virus was
responsible for the death of over 60 people in Durba (Democratic Republic of the Congo).
In Fe b r u a ry, an international
team of researchers published
a paper in the journal N a t u r e
that points to the chimpanzee
Pan troglodytes troglodyt e s a s
the natural host of HI V - 1, the
lethal virus that now infects
over 30 million people
w o r l d w i d e .
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
P L A N E T
burgdorferi, the bacterium responsible for
Lyme Disease.
With few natural predat o rs in the newly-
f o rmed ecosystem, the deer flo u ri s h e d ,a n d
increasingly came into contact with humans,
who were also flocking to the area,
entranced by its apparently “ n at u r a l ”
beauty. By the mid-1970s the first cases of
the tick-borne disease were being noted
among the inhabitants of Old Lyme,
Connecticut.
The same story has since been played
out in Europe, Asia and Australasia, and
tens of thousands of cases of Lyme Disease
are reported worldwide each year.
The return of TB, diphtheria,
cholera and malaria
The return of a number of old killer
diseases once thought vanquished also
s e rves to wa rn of the dangers of hubris and
complacency. Tuberculosis, all but elimi-
nated in the West following the advent of
decent housing and powerful dru g s , h a s
been on the rise again since the mid-1980s
with over three million killed each ye a r
wo r l d w i d e .M a ny experts blame sloppy use
of antibiotics by We s t e rn doctors , w h i c h
has allowed mutant TB bacteria to survive
and create resistant strains. In developing
c o u n t ri e s , the Aids epidemic—which has left
tens of millions with no disease-fighting
immune system—caused the number of
TB cases to triple by the early 1990s.
Outbreaks of diphtheria, another bac-
t e rial disease of the lungs that especially
targets young children, were virtually unk-
nown in the last days of the former Soviet
U n i o n .Around 40,000 cases were report e d
in 1998, p ri m a rily among the poor and
homeless who flocked to major cities follo-
wing the collapse of the union, w h o s e
health-care systems had collapsed with it.
In the early 1990s,cholera returned to
haunt the A m e ricas after a century of
absence. Experts suspect this deadly bac-
t e rial gut disease was imported from Asia in
water flushed from the ballast tanks of
ships. At the turn of the century, virtually
no cases were known in the A m e ri c a s ;
t o d ay, around 60,000 cases are being repor-
ted each year. Globalization of commerce
h a s , it seems, gi ven us all too ready access to
rather more than just exotic produce from
faraway lands.
Yet of all the resurgent diseases, it is
m a l a ria that provides the most poignant
example of where ecological effects have
shattered the dream of complete eradica-
t i o n .The ori ginal optimism stemmed from
the introduction of DDT into developing
n at i o n s , to kill off the mosquitoes that carry
the parasite responsible for malaria.
Within ten ye a rs of its introduction after
the Second World War,DDT had saved an
e s t i m ated 5 million live s. In many countri e s ,
the impact was truly astonishing. In 1948
S ri Lanka had 2.8 million cases of malari a ;
by 1963, f o l l owing the introduction of
DDT, the number had fallen to just 17.
But by the late 1950s, evidence had
emerged suggesting that DDT’s pers i s t e n c e
in the soil and ability to creep up the food
chain was having a deadly effect on some
forms of wildlife.
Although some experts are beginning to
dispute the evidence—and especially its
relevance to the Third World—DDT now
faces a worldwide ban. The mosquitoes
h ave , h owe ve r , gone from strength to
s t r e n g t h . In Sri Lanka, the number of
m a l a ria cases rose from 17 back to 2.5 mil-
lion within just five ye a rs of abandoning
D D T.Wo r l d w i d e , a staggering 400 million
cases are being reported each year, along
with almost two million deaths—90 per
cent of which take place in Africa.
In March 1999, Dr Gro Harlem
B ru n d t l a n d , the Director-General of  W H O,
singled out malaria as an example of a
pandemic killer likely to benefit from ano-
ther environmental threat : global wa rm i n g,
caused by man-made pollution trapping
more of the sun’s heat in the atmosphere.
Dr Brundtland pointed out that malari a
is now being reported in locations at higher
altitudes than in previous ye a rs , such as
the mountain plateaus of Kenya . W h i l e
admitting that there are likely to be va ri o u s
e x p l a n ations for the change, Dr Bru n d t-
land believes that one possibility is global
warming.
Rising sea-levels, caused largely by the
t h e rmal expansion of water dri ven by global
wa rm i n g, pose another threat , according to
Dr Brundtland.“If coastal protection sys-
tems are not strengthened, a 50-centimetre
rise in sea-level by 2100 would place 80
million people in danger of being flooded
more than once a ye a r , compared to 46 mil-
lion people under present climate and sea-
level conditions,” she says. “The displace-
ment of so many people to already
d e n s e l y - p o p u l ated delta areas and on popu-
lous island states would be bound to result
in outbreaks of diseases like diphtheria and
d i a rr h o e a , just to mention the most obvious
o n e s.The rising water table along the coast
could also encourage the release of patho-
A cholera epidemic struck Peru in 1991. Above, family members at the graveside of a victim in Chimbote,
north of Lima.
‘If coastal protection systems
are not strengthened, 
a 50-centimetre rise in sea-
level by 2100 would place
80 million people in danger
of being flooded more than
once a year, compared to
46 million people under
present conditions.
The displacement of so many
people to already densely-
populated delta areas and on
populous island states would
be bound to result in
outbreaks of diseases like
diphtheria and diarrhoea’
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
gens into septic systems and waterways.”
But while the effects of global wa rm i n g
on sea levels have yet to make themselves
c l e a r ,f e a rs are already gr owing that the sea
m ay pose a more immediate—and insi-
dious—threat to health.
It stems from humankind’s insouciant
use of the wo r l d ’s oceans as gigantic sewe rs.
A 1993 World Bank report estimated that
around 30 per cent of humans have no
other waste disposal system than streams,
rivers—and the sea.
For years a case of “out of sight, out of
mind”, the dumping of so much waste in
coastal waters is now starting to have an
impact on health. V i ruses from human
diseases like polio and hepatitis have start e d
to be found in shellfish, while toxic algal
b l o o m s — vast colonies of simple, p at h o g e n -
packed organisms that thri ve on wa s t e -
d e ri ved nutrient—are becoming increa-
singly frequent along coastlines.
It is now becoming clear that the sea
is acting like a gigantic cold-store for
potentially deadly microbes like rotavirus,
responsible for severe diarr h o e a , and polio-
v i rus—and sometimes they emerge to cause
h avoc on the mainland. In December 1992,
thousands of people in Bangladesh fell
victim to cholera, f o l l owing an upwelling of
b a c t e ria-laden ocean water off the southern
W ERE THE TEN PLAGUES OF EG Y P T
T RIGGERED BY AN ECOLOGICAL DISAS T ER ?
While concern mounts over the risk of new
diseases emerging from the seas and rivers,
one leading expert believes that they may hold the
key to an ancient catastrophe: the Ten Plagues that
struck Egypt almost 3,300 years ago.
According to the Book of Exodus in the Old
Testament, Egypt was punished by God with a
series of terrible plagues after refusing to release
Moses and his followers from slavery. Sceptics
have long rejected this ancient story as a myth,
but according to Dr John Marr, former chief epi-
demiologist for New York City, the story may well
be based on fact. His research suggests that the
biblical plagues may have been the result of an
ecological disaster triggered by algal blooms,
whose disease-spreading effect is now causing
growing concern among scientists. 
The first of the Ten Plagues, in which the Nile
reportedly turned blood-red and undrinkable, is
strikingly reminiscent of the toxic “red tides” still
caused by algae known as dinoflagellates in
some parts of the world today.
The resulting ecological imbalance caused by
the death of fish could, says Dr Marr, have led to
the second and fourth Plagues, of toads and their
prey, flies. He also argues that a specific type of fly
could explain the third and fifth plagues, of lice
and livestock sickness: the midge-like creature
Culicoides creates a louse-like irritation and tra n s-
mits deadly viruses that kill animals in hours.
Dr Marr says that another insect—the stable
fly, which causes the bacterial disease glanders—
is a good candidate for the sixth plague, of boils
on man and beast.
While the seventh and eighth plagues—hail
storms and locusts—need little explanation, the
ninth plague, in which darkness fell for three days,
may have been due to an outbreak of Rift Va l l e y
Fever, known to cause tempora ry blindness.
But Dr Marr’s most ingenious explanation
concerns the final and most dramatic of all the
Plagues: the Death of the First Born. He suggests it
is a direct result of the Egyptians’ attempts to deal
with the previous disasters. Hastily gathering what
little crops had survived the hail and locusts, they
may have stored the damp grain in silos. Under
such conditions, the grain would go mouldy, and
become coated with deadly mycotoxins. By bibli-
cal tradition, the eldest child would have received
double rations of contaminated grain—leading to
widespread deaths among the fir s t - b o r n .
If Dr Marr is correct—and other experts say
the chain of events is plausible—the legend of the
Plagues of Egypt may be a timely warning of how
an ecological disaster can trigger devastating
diseases that threaten civilization. n
The female Anopheles mosquito carries the malaria parasite and injects it into the human bloodstream.
coast.
From deforestation to overpopulation,
mass migr ations to global transport , at m o s-
p h e ric to oceanic pollution: the reasons for
which new and resurgent diseases can and
do rise up to threaten humanity are legi o n .
But lessons are being learn e d . Some are
very basic and relatively simple to imple-
m e n t , such as the one-time-only use of
hy p o d e rmic needles. O t h e rs are equally
obvious but far harder to achieve, such as
making safe sex advice effective among
those at risk from sexually-transmitted
diseases like Aids.
Early detection
and rapid control measures
As with any threat ,e t e rnal vigilance for
new disease outbreaks is now being seen as
c ru c i a l . In its report on the outbreak of
plague in India in August 1994, the A l l -
India Institute of Medical Sciences wa rn e d
t h at such re-emerging infectious diseases are
a gr owing threat wo r l d - w i d e .“Early detec-
tion and rapid implementation of effective
control measures are essential,” the report ’s
a u t h o rs said, and duly called for the setting
up of national surveillance centres to act as
early-warning systems.
But the key message now emergi n g
from many of the recent outbreaks is a
blunt one: we must become far more
thoughtful in our dealings with the env i-
ronment and its delicate ecosystems. L o n g
dismissed by some as just a pious desidera-
tum, the cost of ignoring this simple mes-
sage could be nothing less than the needless
death of millions. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
n
When people are robbed of their
h o m e s , land and possessions by violent
c o n f l i c t , time and time again they ask
for educat i o n . O ver the past decade, f r o m
S o m a l i a , Sudan and Rwanda to Bosnia and
K o s ovo, the United Nations has been
confronted in all-too-close succession by
w h at are commonly referred to as complex
political emergencies.These crises invo l-
ving violent internal conflicts based on
n at i o n a l i s t , l o c a l , ethnic and religious fa c-
t o rs , lead to huge internal and extern a l
population displacements,the looting and
destruction of infrastructure,the targeting
of civilian populations and the collapse of
essential basic serv i c e s.Their spread, p a r-
ticularly in A f ri c a , owes much to the break-
d own of the post-colonial settlements of the
1950s and 1960s held in place somewhat
a rtificially by superp ower ri va l ries duri n g
the Cold War and associated ideological and
geopolitical alignments.
Warlords and bandits
At the root of many such emergencies
are escalating economic problems that have
s t i m u l ated fierce inter-group struggles ove r
access to and control over resources. I n
some cases, such as Somalia, violent intern a l
conflicts have led to the collapse of the
s t at e ,l e aving ordinary citizens at the mercy
of warlords and bandits.
Assuring survival is of course the first
task of any humanitarian operation.This
means providing basic services such as food,
wat e r ,s e c u ri t y, health care and shelter. B u t
along with this,there is a steadily growing
recognition of the need to introduce edu-
cation in the early stages of humanitarian
a s s i s t a n c e , whether it be for refugees, i n t e r-
nally displaced persons or wa r - a f f e c t e d
p o p u l at i o n s.This notion, of relat i vely recent
o ri gi n , d r aws upon several justificat i o n s.
One is the right to education itself, a right
which is not forfeited because of war or
d i s p l a c e m e n t .This right is enshrined in the
C o nvention on the Rights of the Child
(1989) and was at the heart of the Jomtien
Conference (1990) on Education for All.
These developments have helped to gene-
r ate an intern ational policy context condu-
cive to the recognition not only of everyo-
n e ’s right to education but also of the
o b l i g ation of all social actors — a g e n c i e s ,
donors and NGOs—to translate that right
into practice.
At a practical leve l , e d u c at o rs and psy-
c h o l o gists emphasize the importance for
c h i l d r e n ’s development of minimizing the
p e riod during which learning is disru p t e d .
Organized recreational and educational acti-
vities bring routine back into children’s live s
w Chief of educational services co-ordination
for the United Nations Interim Administration Mission
in Kosovo. Former head of UNESCO’s Programme
for Education for Emergencies and Reconstruction
in Nairobi.
SCHOOL ING IN TIMES
OF STRIFE
w Mark Richmond
From ‘school-in-a-box’ packages to counselling for children traumatized by fear and
bereavement, education is playing a pivotal role in emergency relief operations
Schoolchildren in Kibondo, a resettlement village in the Kigali region (Rwanda). Some 230,000 Rwandan 
children do not have places in school.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
and help them to maintain a connection to
their own socio-cultural env i r o n m e n t .W h e-
ther formal or non-form a l , schooling can
re-establish a sense of norm a l cy in an
a b n o rmal situat i o n , and offer alienated yo u t h
an altern at i ve to militias, c ri m e ,d e l i n q u e n cy
or dru g s. In emergency situat i o n s , s c h o o l s
can be one of the most valuable channels for
c o m m u n i c ating messages about the env i-
r o n m e n t , n u t ri t i o n , mine awa r e n e s s , c h o-
lera and Aids preve n t i o n .They are also places
where themes such as human ri g h t s ,p e a c e
and reconciliation can be broached. S u c h
values constitute the underpinning of any
subsequent programme of national recons-
t ru c t i o n .M o r e ove r , schools can often serve
as centres for relief and rehabilitation pro-
grammes for the community at large. E d u-
c ation can offer opportunities for paid
e m p l oyment and provide adults with a
chance to play a role in their new, a l b e i t
t e m p o r a ry, s u rr o u n d i n g s.Last but not least,
e d u c ation symbolizes a commitment to the
f u t u r e , something more valuable than ever in
the afterm ath of violent confli c t .
While each crisis calls for a specific type
of rapid educational response, the trage-
dies of the past decade have given interna-
tional agencies sufficient experience to draw
up guidelines for conducting operat i o n s.
Because it is impossible to get a schooling
system into gear ove rn i g h t , a phased
approach enabling education to be intro-
duced in the early stages of humanitarian
assistance has become standard practice in
emergency situations.
After the collection of relevant educa-
tional data (number of children, ava i l a b i l i t y
of teachers, etc.), a first phase brings chil-
dren together for recreation activities—
games,songs,listening to stories,and per-
haps some simple lessons. D u ring a second
p h a s e ,n o n - f o rmal schooling is established
on a systematic basis, often using a Te a-
cher Emergency Package (TEP), w h i c h
was first conceived by UNESCO for use in
Somalia and has now been translated into
s e veral languages and culturally adapted
to suit different populations.
Although the concept is evolving, this
“ s c h o o l - i n - a - b ox ” or “mobile classroom” i s
designed for approx i m ately 80 refugee chil-
dren of pri m a ry school age and aims to
teach functional literacy and numeracy,
r ather than a formal graded curri c u l u m
with exams. A box typically includes slat e s ,
chalk, exercise books and pencils for stu-
dents and a teacher’s bag containing cloth
charts (alphabet, number and multiplica-
tion),a guide outlining teaching methods,
an attendance book and scrabble sets of
small wooden blocks so that teachers can
create language and number games. Desi-
gned for a six-month learning span,TEPs
act as a bridge between no schooling at all
and a return to some form of regular schoo-
ling.
After this interim peri o d , the third phase
of near-normal schooling generally begi n s ,
based on curricula and textbooks (when
available) from the country of ori gi n .A n o t h e r
i m p o rtant aspect of emergency educat i o n
p r o grammes is the training of teachers to
recognize symptoms of trauma in children
who all too often arri ve in their new makeshift
schools after witnessing appalling levels of
h o rror and violence. Psycho-social support
p r o grammes include counselling to help
children come to terms with loss, b e r e ave-
m e n t , displacement and fear.
This entire strategy is geared towards
e d u c ation for repat ri at i o n . The concept,
f i rst clearly art i c u l ated during the expe-
rience of providing schooling to Mozam-
bican refugees in Malawi in the 1980s,has
gained growing acceptance in the 1990s,
p a rtly because host countri e s , which are
generally too poor to absorb a large foreign
E d u cation symbolizes
a commitment to the future,
something more valuable
than ever in the aftermath
of violent confli c t
Wooden boards carved with Koranic verses are the only teaching materials available in Bardera camp for refugees and displaced persons (Somalia).
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
The scene in Neprostino camp near Skopje (Macedonia) on April 15 1999, the third day at school 
for some 500 children who had fled from Kosovo.
influx, need to be reassured that refugees
will not settle there on a permanent basis.
Hence the importance of using the mother
tongue as the language of instru c t i o n , of tea-
ching the curriculum of the country of
o ri gin (provided it has not been a source of
oppression to the displaced populat i o n ) ,
and relying largely or wholly upon refugee
teachers to staff the schools.
The notion that education is geared
t owards repat ri ation adds a long-term
dimension to the concept of emergency. It
implies that planners think along a relief-to-
d e velopment continuum that fits in with
the development policy being designed for
a country or sub-regi o n . U n f o rt u n at e l y,
this is not a linear process: c o u n t ries such as
Angola and Sudan have slipped in and out
of war over recent decades, h a m p e ri n g
efforts at national reconstruction.
Community initiatives
Broadly speaking, emergencies can be
c o n c e i ved as opportunities for educat i o n a l
t r a n s f o rm at i o n .This is why the planning of
e m e r g e n cy educat i o n , especially when the
task of rebuilding educational systems begi n s ,
must integr ate an approach that combines
t o p - d own technical planning,which tends to
c h a r a c t e rize most postwar systems, w i t h
bottom-up community-oriented deve l o p-
ment initiat i ve s. In emergency situat i o n s ,
p a r e n t s ,e l d e rs and professionals often play
an important role in the setting-up and ru n-
ning of schools, often developing a sense of
ow n e rship towards them.
They should continue to have a voice in
the planning of education after resettling in
their country of ori gi n . But traditional ave-
nues through which financial support is
channelled for reconstruction tend to
exclude civil society. D o n o rs go through
the central state—often a highly weakened
state with poor administrative and mana-
gement capacity—to deliver funds, a
method that tends to undermine more par-
t i c i p at o ry approaches to educational plan-
n i n g . The intern ational community also
needs to take stock of recent interventions
and assess them in more thorough and cri-
tical way s. The turn over of crises in the
past decade has been such that sufficient
time has not been devoted to actually lear-
ning from the past. R ather than jump onto
the next emergency, key practitioners
i nvo l ved in large-scale operations should
be given the opportunity to take stock so
that institutional knowledge can be accu-
m u l ated and lessons learnt can inform
future practices. Such reflection could also
s e rve to put education higher up on the
agenda when defining budgets and priori-
ties for complex emergencies. n
EMERGENCY EDUCAT ION: THE LESSONS
A ND CH A L L ENGES OF KOSOVO 
The Kosovo crisis will be a major source of expe-
rience and reflection regarding emergency edu-
cation. The refugee situation in Albania and Mace-
donia witnessed the application of many lessons and
p ractices derived from other emergencies: for
example, the inclusion of education within the early
stages of refugee assistance operations, the attempt
to provide demarcated spaces within camps for
recreational and educational activities, the priority
focus on primary schooling, the provision of educa-
tional kits, the attention given to psycho-social needs,
the explicit adoption of a phased approach, and the
use of refugee teachers in the camps (see article).
Although international agencies and NGOs
clicked into action when the crisis broke out, the
provision of education was not without problems.
In Macedonia, there was rapid turnover in the
camps, with people often being transferred to other
countries, making it very difficult to plan or to have
a stable school population. Also, many Kosovar
refugees were living with families in predominantly
ethnic Albanian communities. This naturally placed
a heavy burden on local school systems and
required both the governmental authorities and
external agencies to divide their attention betw e e n
camp-based and community-based programmes.
The burden of accommodating the influx of
refugees, particularly as it placed heavy pressures
on each country’s educational infrastructure, faci-
lities and resources, led both Albania and Mace-
donia to request substantial amounts of interna-
tional assistance for their own educational systems.
The limited and rapidly depleted capacity of the
ministries of education contrasted sharply with the
c o m p a ratively well-resourced situation of many
external agencies and NGOs, a situation found in
many humanitarian operations. Little attention is
given to the collateral damage caused to resource-
starved educational systems in host countries.
With the war over and the refugees returning
home comes the task of rebuilding the whole edu-
cational system in Kosovo, the next logical phase of
the emergency operation. According to a prelimi-
n a ry UNI CEF survey of 394 schools, 43 per cent of
them were completely destroyed or severely
damaged. But the task is an acutely sensitive one.
Prior to the attack on the ethnic Albanian popula-
tion in March 1999, the official educational system
had been run by Serbs while a parallel system for
ethnic Albanian children had operated clandestinely
for 10 years. Kosovar Albanians boycotted the
formal system because they could no longer accept
the ethno-ideological bias they detected within the
curriculum.
Technically, the United Nations Interim Admi-
n i s t ration Mission in Kosovo (UNMIK) has control
over these matters and it is determined to pursue
an even-handed approach which respects the inter-
ests of both Serbs and ethnic Albanians in Kosovo.
But establishing and maintaining a unified system
will be far from easy. The UN peacekeeping force
(KFOR) will be put to the test in protecting Serb chil-
dren in integrated schools. As of August 1999, the
question of who will pay teachers had not been
resolved. Schools need to be repaired and equipped
with furniture and toilets, children have to be pro-
vided with textbooks and other basic materials and
psychosocial services have to be made available.
The certification of children’s learning in the para l l e l
system has to be agreed upon. In the longer run, the
greatest challenge will be to restore quality to the
system: for example, formal teacher training and
regular professional development for Kosovar Alba-
nian teachers was virtually impossible in the 19 9 0 s .
The situation that exists today is a golden oppor-
tunity for Kosovar education to broaden its vision
and modernize its teaching and learning pra c t i c e s .
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 17
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
FOCUS
B i o e t h i c s : the l u re
of the perfect child
Anew age unfolds as scientists put the
final touches on a map of the human
g e n o m e : our some 100,000 genes.
Among the wealth of potential benefit s,
f u t u re parents will not only be able to scre e n
foetuses for “ d e f e c t s ” , but also may one day
be able to correct a predisposition for diseases
l i ke breast cancer or even “ e n h a n c e ”c e r t a i n
b e h a v i o u ral or physical traits deemed
d e s i ra b l e.
Why shouldn’t parents make the most of
technology to create the “child of their
d re a m s ” , beaming with health and potential?
D a n g e rous fantasy lurks in this sunny hope,
warn voices from bioethical and scientific
c o m m u n i t i e s, feminists and disabled rights
g ro u p s. Will genetics spawn new forms of
eugenics? An emotionally charged word laden
with historical connotations, eugenics defie s
easy defin i t i o n .Yet the word ’s very forc e
demands re flection on the dark side of
attempts to genetically “ i m p ro v e ” the human
s p e c i e s.
The articles in this section illustrate the
ways in which societal pre s s u res can exert
a coercive force on re p roductive decision-
m a k i n g. In the United States, for example,
we see commercial interests driving pare n t s ’
conceptions of their childre n . Po p u l a t i o n
p re s s u res in China fire debate over a
c o n t ro v e rsial law to limit the birth of
handicapped people, while cultura l
discrimination against girls drives parents in
India to extremes to produce sons.
The apprehensions surrounding human
cloning are clearly seen in Dolly’s birthplace,
the United Kingdom. Meanwhile the shadow
of the past leads Germany to tread softly in
the field of biotechnology. F i n a l l y, we take a
b road look at the ethical issues raised by
c u r rent disparities in international access to
the fruits of genetic re s e a rc h .
Contents
18 Uncharted terrain on tomorro w ’s
genetic map
Sophie Boukhari and Amy Otchet
20 Genetics in three easy lessons
22 Screening awakens spectres
of the past
Hilary Rose
24 Religion, genetics and the embryo
Sophie Boukhari
25 Israel: Matchmaking with DNA
Rae HB FishMan
26 U. S. :D ream child or nightmare scenario?
• Medicine’s last frontier
Lee M.Silver
27 • The dangers of laissez faire
Amy Otchet
29 In India, sex selection gets easier
R.Ramachandran
30 Is China’s law eugenic?
• ‘A concern for collective good’
Qiu Renzong
31 • ‘The legislation imposes decisions’
Frank Dikötter
32 United Kingdom: human cloning is
Dolly’s debatable legacy
David Dickson
34 Germany: the dark shadow of the past
Hartmut Wewetzer
35 Genes of inequality
Mohamed Larbi Bouguerra
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
w UNESCO Courier journalists
Uncharted terra i n
on tomorro w ’s genetic map
w Sophie Boukhari and Amy Otchet
In the post-genomic age, medical science’s good intentions could lead us
to the frontier of new forms of eugenics
In about three ye a rs , we should have the keys
to decode our biological “ e g o ” .Through the
Human Genome Project, thousands of resear-
c h e rs from about 50 countries are putting the fin a l
touches to a map identifying all of our roughly
100,000 genes.This inform ation will open the way
to developing a large number of innovat i ve treat-
ments and techniques to cure and prevent disea-
s e .
At the beginning of this “genetic age”, we can
expect an extensive bat t e ry of DNA tests which
p r o s p e c t i ve parents will use to gain an extraordi-
n a ry picture of their embryo ’s genetic make-up.
These tests may be used in utero to reassure parents
as to the health of their child-to-be. On the other
h a n d , signs of disease or handicap might also lead
to the decision to abort .This same bat t e ry of DNA
tests will also be used for preimplantation diagnosis,
in which prospective parents sift through and then
select in vitro (“test tube”) a fertilized egg (or eggs)
before implantation in a wo m a n ’s wo m b. Both of
these screening approaches are part of “ g e n e t i c
c o u n s e l l i n g ” , a term used to describe a ve ry sen-
s i t i ve process in which people basically decide what
kinds of individuals are born .We already see this
selection process at work with health policies in
some countries encouraging women to take pre-
n atal tests for Dow n ’s Syndrome.
In the next phase of genetic research, g e n e t i-
cists will develop a range of treatments for genetic
d i s o r d e rs , including gene therapy,n ow just in their
ve ry early stages.This research is raising wild hopes,
from the ability to cure certain cancers to comba-
ting the 4,000 to 5,000 genetic illnesses identifie d
so fa r. Some geneticists are already dreaming of
g e rm-line therapy in which genetic changes are
passed along to future generat i o n s. Indeed scien-
tists like A m e rican Lee Silver foresee the rise of a
new discipline:“ r e p r o g e n e t i c s ” which will com-
bine cloning and genetic engi n e e ring techniques
to one day “ e n h a n c e ” in vitro embryos (pp. 2 7 -
2 8 ) . Enhancement could take a va riety of form s :
from improving resistance to disease to modifying
b e h avioural or physical traits with a view to pro-
ducing the “child of parents’ d r e a m s ” .
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 19
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
For now, these scenarios are not only techni-
cally impossible but legally prohibited: r e p r o d u c-
t i ve cloning of humans (pp.32-33) and germ - l i n e
therapy are forbidden.But they are wa rning signs
for those who fear that medicine will be used as a
way of selecting and controlling “ g o o d ”and “ b a d ”
g e n e s.“ We are on the verge of a new eugenic age,”
wa rn the serried ranks of philosophers ,p ri e s t s ,
human rights campaigners and anti-abort i o n
gr o u p s.Their cry has sparked a major bioethical
d e b ate on two fronts.The first revo l ves around the
ve ry definition of eugenics (see glossary ) , an emo-
tionally charged word closely associated with the
h o rr o rs of Nazism (pp. 2 2 - 2 3 ) . S e c o n d l y, w i l l
a d vances in genetics gi ve rise to new forms of euge-
n i c s ?
Asian countries (pp.30-31) and Arab Gulf stat e s
already have laws denying the disabled the right to
be born .According to Noëlle Lenoir, f o rmer pre-
sident of UNESCO’s Intern ational Bioethics Com-
mittee (IBC),“in societies already plagued by  dis-
c ri m i n at i o n , genetics could become another
i n s t rument of exclusion.” Can any society claim
t h at it is untainted by this social ill? Certainly not
those which deem girls inferior (p. 2 9 ) .
What is normality? 
The debate over eugenics reminds us that there
is no such thing as a “ p e r f e c t ”b a b y.The human
gene pool cannot be “ c l e a n e d ” up  because, a s
scientists point out, new genetic anomalies deve-
lop with each generat i o n . B e s i d e s , genetic engi-
n e e ring is an inherently risky endeavour because
it is impossible to predict which genes our des-
cendants may need in the future.
A host of fundamental ethical questions also
a ri s e .Tests to detect late onset diseases raise the
problem of defining a life wo rth living. A genetic
disease like “ H u n t i n g t o n ’s chorea usually deve-
lops between the ages of 38 and 45,” s ays French
geneticist and bioethicist A xel Kahn.“ Yet think of
all the gr e at artists and musicians who died befo-
re reaching 40.We see here the difficulty in say i n g
t h at a life isn’t wo rth living if it ends or suddenly
d e t e ri o r ates at a certain age.”
Another thorny question lies in defining “ n o r-
m a l i t y ” . I m a gine the discri m i n ation directed
t owards handicapped people in a society accusto-
med to the idea of eliminating genetic “ d e f e c t s ” ?
M a ny bioethicists such as IBC president Ryuichi
Ida also see gr ave dangers potentially arising from
the “genetic enhancement” of embryo s.To begi n
w i t h , new inequalities would develop between those
who could afford such “ t r e at m e n t ” and those lac-
king access to it (pp. 2 7 - 2 8 ) .
We must also ask whether parents have the ri g h t
to “ d e s i g n ” the child of their dreams? “A child is
a separate and complete individual who cannot be
reduced to the expectations of his or her parents,”
s ays Kahn.“Being a parent is supposed to be about
l oving a child as he or she is.Parenting is not about
r e q u i ring a child to be as you would like him or her
to be. In this respect, children are in danger.”
G l o s s a r y
DNA: deoxyribonucleic acid,the carrier of genetic information (pages 20-21).
ES cells: embryonic stem cells, mostly t o t i p o t e n t, i . e. capable of providing the genetic pro-
gramme required to direct the development of an entire individual.
Germ cell: reproductive cell (sperm or egg cells), changes in which are passed down through
generations.
Somatic cell: non-germ cell,known as an “adult”cell.
Chromosome: rod-like structure made of DNA,visible when a cell is divided
(see pages 20-21).
Clones: genetically identical living things, obtained by asexual reproduction.
E u g e n i c s : a term invented by the British scientist Francis Galton from the Greek words “ e u ”
(good) and “genos”(birth,race).The study of how to improve human genetic heritage (see
pages 22-23).
G e n e: a segment of DNA which, alone or in combination with others, determines creation of
a trait.An organism’s total genetic material is its genome (see pages 20-21).
Recessive gene: one which does not produce the character to which it is linked unless it exists
on both the male and female chromosomes in the pair.A dominant gene, on the other hand,
produces its characters by dominating the different gene carried by the other chromosome
in the pair.
Genetic disease:several thousands of these have been identified.Some are mono-genic,
i.e. a single gene is responsible for the disease. Others are multi-genic, with several genes
involved.
Gene thera p y : treatment of genetic diseases by introducing genetic material into the
patient’s genes (see pages 20-21). n
Yet brandishing the spectre of eugenics is sim-
plistic and dangerous, insist many scientists, b i o-
technology exe c u t i ve s ,b i o e t h i c i s t s , and feminists.
F u rt h e rm o r e ,a n t i - a b o rtion groups might mani-
p u l ate the debate to curtail women's hard-wo n
rights to control their own fertility (pp. 2 2 - 2 3 ) .
There may also be a positive side to “ l a i s s e z
fa i r e ” or “ u t o p i a n ”e u g e n i c s — t e rms which are
sparking a flu rry of discussion in affluent We s t e rn
c o u n t ri e s. M a ny bioethicists and scientists main-
tain that these new forms of eugenics simply des-
c ribe the choices individuals—not the state or the
community—will be able to make about the kind
of children they want to bring into the wo r l d .B u t
h ow will commercial pressures and interests dri ve
these decisions? “With sufficient adve rt i s i n g, t h e
biotechnology market will make parents feel guil-
ty if they don't consume” all the genetic tests and
s e rvices ava i l a b l e ,s ays Lori A n d r e w s , an A m e ri-
can legal expert in the field (pp. 2 8 - 2 9 ) .
As geneticists point out, science and medicine
h ave always advanced by violating social taboos.
Scientists should not be penalized for the ways in
which society uses their discove ri e s.The ethical
p ath lies in giving people time to reflect on the
consequences of scientific progr e s s.
“Individuals eve rywhere are faced with more
and more ethical dilemmas,” s ays Lenoir.“In some
way s ,i t ’s easier when you live in an authori t a ri a n
or religious society.The rules are laid out before
you (pp. 2 4 -2 6 ) . But in culturally dive rse and secu-
lar societies, where people have access to info rm at i o n
and can stand up for their ri g h t s,i t ’s much harder to set
g u i d e l i n e s.This is wh at gave birth to bioethics.” n
Give me the strength
and the will to broaden
my knowledge. S t e e r
me from the idea that
all is within my reach.
M a i m o n i d e s,
Rabbi and doctor (1135-1204)
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
F rom DNA to Dolly
Genetics in three easy lessons
Ewe A
Ewe B
Ewe C
Dolly, clone of ewe A
Take a donor cell
from the animal
to be cloned Only keep
the nucleus Introduce the
nucleus into the
egg cell
The embryo is implanted into
surrogate mother
for gestation
Remove
the nucleus
Take an
unfertilized
egg cell
1. What is a gene?
The nucleus DNA
When the cell divides,
fragments of DNA join into
23 pairs of chromosomesDNA
G C T A
C G A T
G C T A
C G A T
G
C
The cell
A gene
2. The making of Dolly
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 21
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
1 Our bodies are made up of cells, each contai-
ning a nucleus of DNA (Deox y ri b o n u c l e i c
a c i d ) .This huge molecule resembles a sort of spi-
ral ladder,a double helix whose parts twist and ove r-
l a p. It is divided between 23 pairs of complemen-
t a ry chromosomes—one inherited from the fat h e r
and one from the mother in each pair.
This DNA “ s p i r a l ” contains about three billion
“bar codes”, which consist of four different bases—
adenine (A in red), t hymine (T in blue),cytosine (C
in green) and guanine (G in ye l l ow)—which are
a lways linked with each other in the same way as base
p a i rs (A with T and C with G).
About 95 per cent of the DNA in the nucleus has
no known function, while the remaining 5 per cent
contains some 100,000 genes. Pieces of DNA, w h i c h
are so minute that they cannot be seen by a micro-
s c o p e , are composed of several thousands of “ b a r
c o d e s ” .The way the four base-pairs are strung toge-
ther is a sort of coded message: by interpreting this
c o d e , and switching particular genes on and off, t h e
cells manufacture the proteins which make us what
we are.
2 There are several methods of cloning. B u t
until the birth of the cloned sheep, D o l l y, i n
July 1996, it was necessary to use test-tube embryo s
d e ri ved from an encounter between an egg and a
s p e rm at o z o i d .The embryos were divided in two
and each half implanted inside a surrogate mother
to obtain two clones.The creation of Dolly was revo-
l u t i o n a ry because it did not require using a “ n o r-
m a l ” e m b ryo (one made by an egg and a sperm ) .
The famous sheep of the 1990s was born from the
“ m a rri a g e ” of an egg cell from which the nucleus
had been removed and an adult cell taken from the
sheep to be cloned.
3 More than 4,000 genetic diseases are res-
ponsible for a third of all infant deaths in the
d e veloped countri e s.When “ d e f e c t i ve ” genes are
s p o t t e d , an attempt to “ r e p a i r ” them can be made
using genetic engi n e e ri n g . Still in its infa n cy, t h i s
technique invo l ves injecting “ h e a l t hy ” genes into
diseased cells. But because of the minute size of cells
and genes, it is impossible to do this “by hand” l i k e
in a normal surgical operat i o n . So scientists use ve c-
tors—deactivated viruses or retroviruses (a special
kind of viru s ) .These carri e rs of “ g o o d ” genes can
p e n e t r ate the targeted cells of the patient by them-
s e l ve s. But howe ver promising these techniques may
be for the future, none is effective in treating disease
at present.
3. Correcting a genetic anomaly
“Defective”gene Therapeutic gene
Therapeutic gene
Therapeutic gene
Gene of the retrovirus
Cell
DNA of the cell
Vector
DNA of the cell
Nucleus
Implant the therapeutic gene in a vector
(retrovirus, virus or liposome)
Introduce the vector into the “defective”cell
a.If the vector is a retrovirus
The DNA of the defective cell
recombines with the DNA of the virus
carrying the therapeutic gene
b. If the vector is a virus or a
liposome
The therapeutic gene neutralizes the
sick gene from a distance
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
For almost half a century eugenics—literally the
science of “ i m p r ov i n g ” the gene pool—has
been equated with the horr o rs of Nazism.
While German geneticists such as Benno Müller
Hill have sought to confront the scientific commu-
n i t y ’s complicity with the Nazis, s y s t e m atic scru t i ny
of eugenic policies in other countries has long been
neglected.
H i s t o rians have recently filled the gap to offer a
c l e a r , if depressing, picture of cultural and poli-
tical support for eugenics in North A m e rica and in
m a ny European countries from the start of the
20th century to the 1970s. Industrial barons and
political elites had predictably little sympat hy for the
socially disadvantaged who were the targets of
eugenic policies. S u rp ri s i n g l y, eugenics also at t r a c t e d
considerable interest among we l fare reform e rs ,
Marxist and socialist intellectuals as well as feminists
c o nvinced that science should help the state in fos-
t e ring a genetically “ fit ”p o p u l at i o n . Some favo u r e d
negative eugenics, seeking to limit the production
of the “ u n fit ” ;o t h e rs opted for positive eugenics to
encourage the “fit”to have more children.
Once the horr o rs of Nazism were widely know n ,
m a ny countries were careful to avoid using the
word eugenics even though they continued to prac-
tice it.These “ p o p u l ation policies” mostly took the
f o rm of the compulsory steri l i z ation of “ f e e b l e
minded” women. Racism led to African American
women being grossly over-represented among the
60,000 people forcibly sterilized in several A m e ri c a n
s t ates from 1907 to 1960. In Scandinav i a ,p o l i t i c a l
leaders and geneticists adopted state policies for
c o m p u l s o ry steri l i z ation out of concern that the
e m e r ging we l fare state would encourage the “ u n fit ”
to reproduce and so reduce the quality of the
n ational stock. In Sweden alone, 63,000 people, 9 0
per cent of them women, were sterilized between
1934 and 1975.Norway, a much smaller country,
sterilized 48,000 in the same period. By contrast,
British and Dutch geneticists and policy-makers
adopted voluntary sterilization together with the
mass institutionalization and segr e g ation of the
“feeble-minded”.
The silence surrounding these painful chapters in
h i s t o ry is not surp ri s i n g . It takes a dour courage to
u n e a rth the horr o rs of any nat i o n ’s past. In Swe d e n ,
for example,the press first sparked public outrage ove r
S c reening awake n s
s p e c t res of the past
w Hilary Rose
C o n f ronting the eugenic pasts of North America and Europe is a painful 
but crucial experience for shedding light on today’s debate.
w Professor of Physic (medical
ethics) at Gresham College,
L o n d o n . Author of Love, Power and
Knowledge: Towards a Feminist
T r a n s f o r m a t i o n
of the Sciences
(Cambridge Po l i t y, 1 9 9 4 )
eugenics in the 1970s.Yet it wa s n ’t until 1996 that the
g ove rnment agreed to compensate the women who
s u f f e r e d .To d ay ’s renewed interest in the past stems
from founders of the Human Genome Project
( H G P ) . From the project’s conception in 1985, l e a-
ding scientists like James Wat s o n ,c o - d i s c overer of the
s t ructure of DNA, s aw the need publicly to confront
this sinister past to prevent the shadow of the old stat e -
controlled eugenics from impeding the progress of the
H G P.As a result, they set aside part of the three-bil-
lion-dollar research budget to study not just the past
but the social, legal and ethical implications of cur-
rent research. M a ny scientists are acutely aware that
new forms of eugenics risk arising with new deve-
lopments in the field of genetics.
Fears of growing stigmas
Today geneticists are generally very careful to
avoid any links to state-controlled eugenics by adop-
ting a new approach with a Janus-like posture.
Facing the patient—the would-be parent—they
p r ovide informed choice about DNA testing. Fa c i n g
the stat e , they promise that fewer disabled chil-
dren will be born. However, as more foetuses are
screened for a growing range of conditions, many
voices within the disability movements argue that
“ t e s t i n g ” amounts to searching for the “ a b n o rm a l ” .
This “ s e a r c h ” steadily reduces our notions of what
it is to be “ n o rm a l ” , and this, activists say, w i l l
intensify the stigmatization of all disabled people.
Some activists have come close to an absolutist
opposition to all DNA testing to prevent women
from aborting so-called “abnormal”foetuses.This
position has predictably raised serious concern in the
I have an intense desire
to return
to the womb.
A n y b o d y ’s.
Woody A l l e n ,
American fil m - m a ker (1935-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 23
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
T i m e l i n e
1 8 4 0 - 1 8 5 0: The start of modern embryology.The Estonian Karl Ernst von Baer describes the
first stages of the formation of an embryo.
1 8 6 6:A Czech monk, Gregor Mendel, develops laws of heredity after experiments with peas.
1875-1883: A German anatomist, Walther Flemming, counts the number of human chro-
mosomes. He finds 24 pairs, a figure amended to 23 by the Indonesian scientist Joe-Hin Tjio
in 1956.
1 9 0 5:“ M e n d e l i s m ” , the study of heredity, is renamed “ g e n e t i c s ” (from the Greek word g e n e -
tikos, meaning generate) by the British biologist William Bateson.
1 9 5 3: Biologists James Watson (U. S.) and Francis Crick (UK) discover the “double helix” s t r u c-
ture of DNA.This marks the real beginning of molecular genetics,which expresses genetic infor-
mation in physico-chemical terms.
1973: The first experiments in human cloning by dividing an embryo. Also the first transge-
n e s i s, the artificial transfer of genetic material from one species to another.
The age of genetic engineering begins.
1978: The birth in Britain of Louise Brown,the first test-tube baby, conceived by in vitro fer-
tilization.
1 9 9 0: The Human Genome Project is launched to locate and identify all the genes of human
DNA before the year 2003.
1 9 9 5: Mark Hughes makes the first clones of human embryos by transferring the nucleus, d e s-
troying them after a few weeks.
1 9 9 7: British embryologist Ian Wilmut announces he has cloned a sheep, which he calls Dolly,
from an “adult”cell (see pages 20-21). n
global movement of women struggling to control
their own fert i l i t y. I n d e e d , the disability move m e n t
can look like an ally of pro-life gr o u p s.Yet it is pos-
sible, as disabled feminist groups have shown, to
share the disability movement’s concerns and still
defend women’s reproductive rights.
The “genetically approved”
To begin with, it is crucial to recognize that
despite the proliferation of DNA tests—each
patented and profit-yielding—genetics has so far
failed to fulfill its vaunted promises of gene therapy.
D o c t o rs are screening for conditions and disorders
which they cannot treat. So abortion is often pre-
sented as treat m e n t . Meanwhile a good mother-to-
be is expected to accept every test she can either
afford or the state provides. For many bioethicists,
feminists and disabled rights activists,this prolife-
ration of DNA tests opens the way to “consumer
e u g e n i c s ” which in the guise of offering gr e at e r
r e p r o d u c t i ve choices in practice applies pressure to
select the “genetically approved”.
To assure truly free reproductive decision-
making, it is crucial to ask: who benefits from the
tests—individuals or companies selling them? For
most women—not all—a DNA test which can accu-
r ately indicate a terrible genetic disorder in the
foetus enhances, even if sadly, her ethical choices.
But what about the possible proliferation of DNA
tests for relat i vely minor genetic disorders , l i k e
deafness or restricted stature? 
Another major ethical issue lurks in the proli-
f e r ation of DNA testing: by focusing on genetic
we a k n e s s e s , we may neglect environmental fa c t o rs ,
like pove rt y. A m e rican sociologist Tr oy Duster
points out that the most effective way—in both
medical and economic terms—to promote the birt h
of healthy newborns lies in helping poor women eat
properly during pregnancy. In the state of Cali-
f o rn i a , more infants suffer from the serious and
often fatal health problems caused by low birt h
weight than by genetic disease. For Duster, t h e
state decision to invest in DNA testing instead of
anti-poverty programmes opens the “backdoor to
eugenics” with painful implications in view of the
fact that A f rican A m e ricans are massively ove r -
represented among the poor.
How can we better manage this powerful bio-
technology? We can begin by stimulating an
informed debate about the possibilities and limits
of DNA testing.The public needs a solid informa-
tion base to take an active part in developing sen-
sitive and effective regulatory systems. Screaming
headlines announcing “designer babies” in which
fantasy parents choose the height, i n t e l l i g e n c e ,
looks and behaviour of their future offspring will do
little to help us resolve thorny ethical questions
a ri s i n g .I n s t e a d , we might begin by learning from the
t wo countries where the public trusts its gove rn m e n t
most when it comes to biotechnology, Denmark and
the Netherlands. It is not by chance that they have
done the most to manage these technologies demo-
cratically. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
issue is still at the core of the questions raised
about genetic engi n e e ri n g, either by tradition,
culture or duty.”
Should a person have recourse to prenat a l
screening and consider having an abortion if a
s e rious genetic defect is discovered? Should
research on embryo s , gene therapy and cloning
be allowed?
All the “religions of the Book”(Christianity,
Judaism and Islam) believe that the answe rs to
these questions largely depend on the status of
the embryo.The frontier between “ g o o d ” a n d
“ b a d ” genetic engi n e e ring depends on whether
or not the embryo is considered to be “ a n i m at e ” .
An “opposition front”
“If the embryo has a soul,then it is endowed
with a human as well as a biological life and any
attack on its integrity is seen as a cri m e ,” s ay s
French geneticist René Frydman.“If it is inani-
m at e , the prohibition remains—God-gi ven life
should be respected—but the offence is less
serious.”
The Catholic Church is in many respects a
special case. For a start , it has a single “ m a gi s-
t e ri u m ”or teaching authori t y,whereas other reli-
gions have a more familiar approach, such as dis-
cussions with a rabbi (Je w s ) , p riest (Ort h o d ox
C h ristians) or master (Buddhists). Other reli-
gions also have various branches (reformed and
o rt h o d ox Je w s ,m a ny broad streams of Buddhism)
or schools of jurisprudence (Malikite,Hanafite,
Shafi’ite and Hanbalite among Sunni Muslims,
for example). Most important of all, while all the
major religions generally believe human life and
dignity should be respected, the Church of Rome
is the only religion that considers the embryo “ a s
a human being from the moment of conception”,
and it sticks firmly to this doctrine.
Pope John Paul II has repeated it several times,
notably in the encyclicals Ve ri t atis Splendor ( 1 9 9 3 )
and E va n gelium V i t a e ( 1 9 9 5 ) .These have resul-
ted in a number of prohibitions: “ n o ” to prena-
tal screening if it it is done with the thought of a
possible abortion and “ n o ” to most research and
therapy on embryo s.The Vatican is also against
both reproductive and therapeutic cloning on the
grounds that it violates the “unified totality” o f
O nce upon a time Christian theologi a n s
argued about the sex of angels. N owa d ay s
they argue about the soul of the human
e m b ryo in a debate that concerns creatures of
flesh and blood and spills way beyond Chri s-
tianity.
“Although religious practice may be decli-
n i n g,” s ays French geneticist and Member of Pa r-
liament Jean-François Mat t e i , “the metaphy s i c a l
R e l i g i o n , genetics and
the embryo
w Sophie Boukhari
C a t h o l i c s, P ro t e s t a n t s, B u d d h i s t s, Muslims and Jews bring an array of re s p o n s e s
to the bioethical questions posed by genetic technologies.
w UNESCO Courier journalist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
I S R A E L : DNA MAT C H M A K E R S
w Rae HB Fi s h M a n
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 25
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
the human person and the sacred link betwe e n
sexuality and procreation.
The positions of Ort h o d ox Christians are ve ry
close to those of the Vat i c a n . But the “ o p p o s i t i o n
front”to genetic technologies is limited to these
t wo gr o u p s. For Islam and Judaism, the impor-
tant principles are the moment when the embryo
acquires a life of its own and respect for descen-
d a n c e .The Koran says in Surat 23: “And cer-
tainly We created man of an extract of clay,T h e n
We made him a small seed in a firm resting-place,
Then we made the seed a clot, then we made the
clot a lump of fle s h , then We made (in) the lump
of flesh bones, then We clothed the bones with
fle s h , then We caused it to gr ow into another crea-
tion.”
But some Muslims believe it is 40 days befo-
re the soul (ru h) enters the embryo, while others
b e l i e ve it is 120. At the same time, while prena-
tal screening is accepted,there is argument over
a b o rt i o n . H’mida Ennaifer, of the Higher Insti-
tute of Theology in Tu n i s ,s ays “Islamic jurists all
condemn abortion after the foetus has receive d
the breath of life. Some Malekites condemn it
e ven when the child is less than 40 days old while
other schools of thought allow it during the first
four months of pregnancy.”
Islam also allows gene therapy on the human
b o d y, but in general it proscribes the modifica-
tion of germ-cells and bans anything which denies
the notion of divine creat i o n , s t a rting with clo-
n i n g . H owe ve r , a minority of jurists regard clo-
ning as sometimes preferable to “genetic adulte-
ry ” because it respects the line of descent by
avoiding a situation where a sterile couple uses
s p e rm or eggs from a donor in art i ficial insemi-
nation.
Jews cite the Bible and the Ta l m u d .When the
Talmud reports that during the miraculous cros-
sing of the Red Sea by the Israelites (Exodus,
chapter 15), e ven the unborn children in their
mothers’ wombs praised God,it comments that
“if they could praise the glory of God, it means
they have a soul and a conscience.”This comes
about after the 40th day, the Talmud says. Until
then,the embryo is “only water”.So to obey the
halakha ( Jewish Law ) , it is preferable to carry out
p r e n atal screening before the 40th day.After that ,
a b o rtion is not allowed unless the mother’s life is
in danger. In practice, it all depends on what the
rabbis say.Some hold that if the mother has a ner-
vous breakdown when she learns she is carrying
a child with an incurable condition, a b o rtion is
p e rm i s s i b l e , e ven after the 40-day limit. O t h e r
rabbis are a lot stricter.
Jews allow experiments with embryo s , e s p e-
cially if they have no chance of surv i v i n g .J u d a i s m
also does not rule out cloning, s ays French theo-
Love is made in heaven,but for many people,
marriages are arranged on Earth. For ultra-
orthodox Jews, marriages are made between
families as much as between individuals, on the
basis of mutual interests.“Intelligence and scho-
larship are highly va l u e d , n a t u r a l l y, but back-
g r o u n d , social position,wealth and health are also
i m p o r t a n t ,” says Israeli rabbi Yigal Bezalel Sha-
fran.
Families known to be genetic carriers of fatal
diseases are stigmatized,because in this strictly
o b s e r vant community abortion is generally for-
bidden unless the mother’s life is endangered.Ye t
A s h kenazi Jews (of Eastern European origin) have
the highest risk of Ta y - S a c h s, a genetic disease
causing dementia and death in childhood.The risk
of carrying the disease can run as high as four per
cent for the A s h kenazi (one in 25) compared to
0.2 per cent for non-Jews and Sephardic Jews (of
Mediterranean origin).
In 1983 a rabbi and a doctor in New York crea-
ted Dor Ye s h o r i m , a non-profit organization which
provides A s h kenazi with pre-marital genetic tests
to avoid the betrothal of two carriers of a fatal or
severely debilitating genetic disorder. A b o u t
70,000 people in New York,Israel and the United
Kingdom have been tested for Tay-Sachs and
other genetic diseases like cystic fib r o s i s. The pro-
gramme started in Israel in 1986,and since then
not a single Tay-Sachs child has been born in the
ultra-orthodox A s h kenazi community. It works
because both the spiritual leaders and the com-
munity agree with its principles, practices and
results.
Yet some medical geneticists oppose the pro-
gramme on the grounds that it snubs We s t e r n
m e d i c i n e ’s standard of privacy and the individual’s
“right to know” because the test results are retur-
ned to the “more objective and less emotionally
i n v o l v e d ” Dor Yeshorim rabbi,and not to the indi-
viduals tested.The prospective couple is informed
only if both members are carriers, in which case
they usually seek other partners. If just one of the
pair is a carrier, no one is told and the marriage
plans proceed.
There may be a lesson here for other cultures
and even for Western science. As genetic scree-
ning tests are increasingly ava i l a b l e, mostly for
diseases with no cure, people may have to bear
what Rabbi Shafran calls “an emotional burden of
knowledge that can only cause distress”.This bur-
den might be eased if the right to knowledge is
vested in their social group, in other words, if indi-
viduals choose the “right not to know”. n
w Israeli-based scientific journalist
Man has been
truly termed a
“ m i c r o c o s m ” ,
or little world in
h i m s e l f, a n d
the structure of
his body should be
studied not only by
those who wish to
become doctors,
but by those who wish
to attain to
a more intimate
knowledge of God.
A l - G h a z â l i ,
Muslim theologian 
( 1 0 5 8 - 1 1 1 1 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
l o gian and jurist Raphaël Braï. “If cloning is done
for therapeutic reasons, the matter has to be dis-
cussed with other people. S e veral religious notions
clash at this point. For example, the oneness of
the human person and the duty to heal oneself.”
But cloning for reproductive reasons is not allo-
wed,with few exceptions.
Protestant Christians are generally even more
open to advances in genetics.They stress free will
and regard each case on its meri t s ,l e aving a deci-
sion to the couple involved.“Some allow prena-
tal screening followed by an abortion if the wo m a n
so decides,” s ays Carlos de Sola, head of the bioe-
thics unit of the Council of Europe, which has
a rranged discussions between religious autho-
ri t i e s. “Some people even endorse choosing the
sex of a future child through sperm selection,
so as to create a family containing both boys and
gi r l s.” Protestants approve of research using
embryos as long as it is strictly supervised.They
do not rule out cloning either, though they reject
cloning for profit or for eugenic reasons.
Buddhists are even less dogmatic because they
b e l i e ve all truth is relat i ve . A French expert in
B u d d h i s m , Raphaël Liogi e r , notes that “the only
w Professor at Princeton
University in the Departments of
Molecular Biology, Ecology and
Evolutionary Biology and in the
Woodrow Wilson School of Public
and International Affairs. Prof.
Silver is the author of Remaking
Eden: Cloning and Beyond in a
Brave New World, Avon Books,
New York,1998.
Boston, USA: June 1, 2010
Barbara is nursing her new-born baby, Max. “My
husband and I chose him from the embryos we made,”
she tells a friend. “We also made sure that Max
wouldn’t turn out to be fat like my brother Tom or
addicted to alcohol like my husband’s sister.”
Seattle: March 15, 2050
Melissa is in the early stages of labour in a maternity
ward.To take her mind off the contractions, she looks
at computer-generated pictures of a five-year-old gir l
with blond hair and green eyes and others of the same
girl as a teenager. This is Melissa’s yet-to-be-born
child.What cannot be seen is that she has a package
of genes to provide her with lifelong resistance to HIV
infection.
Washington, DC: May 15, 2350
The country is divided into two classes:the GenRich,wh o s e
families invested heavily in the genetic design of their off-
s p ri n g,and the Nat u ra l s,whose families couldn’t afford to
do so.The GenRich make up 10 per cent of the populat i o n ,
and dominate the upper echelons of society,while the Nat u-
rals wo rk as low-paid service prov i d e rs.GenRich parents
pressure their children not to dilute their expensive ge n e t i c
e n d owment by marrying Nat u ra l s.
This is not an exercise in Hollywood screen-
writing.These scenarios emerge from our current
base of scientific and technological knowledge.
Since the 1980s, genetic engi n e e ring has been suc-
cessfully practised with mice, c ow s , sheep and pigs. I t
h a s n ’t yet been applied to human beings simply because
ethical limit is sufferi n g, for Buddha is pri m a rily a
h e a l e r.”The Dalai Lama, leader of T i b e t ’s Buddhists,
s ays what mainly has to be taken into account are
“the good effects and bad effects of genetic engi-
neering.” He agrees that it can be used to “improve
the human body—the brain,for example.”
“The body is only a vehicle for karma [the ethi-
cal consequences of a pers o n ’s actions that deter-
mine their destiny in their next incarn at i o n ] ,” s ay s
Liogier. “If the body has been genetically altered or
c l o n e d ,i t ’s really not ve ry import a n t .A b o rtion howe-
ver is frowned on because it damages karma.”
But again, e ve rything is relat i ve and the main
c o n c e rn is to avoid pain.The Dalai Lama says “ a b o r-
tion is allowed when a pregnant woman might die
if she gave birth or bear a severely handicapped child.”
The range of answe rs religions gi ve to bioethi-
cal questions is ve ry va ried and constantly changi n g,
except for the ri gid doctrine of the Vatican and the
i n flexibility of fundamentalists in all religi o n s. Fa c e d
with problems which go to the ori gin and meaning
of life itself, s ays Fry d m a n ,“ r e l i gious opinions are
probably a big help because they recall humanity’s
root values without trying to impose them and are a
forum for discussion,not a body of dogma.” n
U. S. :D ream child or
n i g h t m a re s c e n a r i o?
New technology making it possible to produce children immune to chronic genetic disease 
also paves the way for ‘designer babies’ for parents who can afford them.
This prospect is opening a Pa n d o ra ’s box of ethical, social and legal dilemmas—nowhere more
than in the United States.
1 . M e d i c i n e ’s last f ro n t i e r
w Lee M. S i l v e r
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 27
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
w UNESCO Courier journalist
the most basic technique for adding genes to embryo s
has a success rate of only 50 per cent at best.And for
the even more complicated task of altering genes to
cure dis e a s e , the odds are about a million to one.
But with cloning, the entire equation changes.
You can now take a cell from a fertilized egg of just a
few days and then clone it to make millions of copies
which could then be engineered by, for example,
injecting foreign DNA through a microscopic
n e e d l e .Thanks to the “Wilmut technique” (see page
2 1 ) , the scientist can then take a properly engi n e e-
red cell’s nucleus and insert it into a fresh egg which
is placed in the mother’s wo m b.
This is just one of many approaches now being
d e veloped in laborat o ri e s. By using one or a combi-
n ation of them,genetic engi n e e ring of human embryo s
will be safe and efficient by the middle of the 21st cen-
t u ry.We will face the ultimate frontier in medicine and
p h i l o s o p hy—the power to change the nature of the
human species.
Genetic engi n e e ring will begin in a thoroughly
acceptable manner, by treating severe childhood
diseases like cystic fib r o s i s. S e rvices will then steadily
expand in two distinct phases. In the firs t , parents will
gi ve their children genes that others naturally have . Fo r
e x a m p l e , they will incorp o r ate within their embryos the
genes which make some people naturally resistant to
c e rtain forms of cancer or HIV infection (about one
per cent of the A m e rican male population has a gene
making them immune to HIV infection).At the same
t i m e , they may reve rse predisposition to conditions like
obesity or alcoholism and diseases like diabetes.
Geneticists will then focus on the mind and senses.
To begin with,d o c t o rs will replace or alter genes linked
to mental diseases and antisocial behaviour like
extreme aggr e s s i o n . As technology improves and
s p r e a d s , parents will have the choice of enhancing
a rtistic potential, for example, by heightening visual
or auditory acuity.With better understanding of the
human brain, we will enhance cognitive abilities by,
for example, strengthening the gene responsible for
c o nve rting short term memory into long term
m e m o ry.This is now being done in mice.
All of these services invo l ve altering or adding genes
which already exist in the human genome.H owe ve r ,
in the second phase of genetic engi n e e ri n g, we will
actually introduce new genes into the genome.
Humans might develop night vision by gene-transfers
from bats or entirely new traits like the ability to deci-
pher radio wave s.O b v i o u s l y, this kind of engi n e e ri n g
will take a gr e at deal of time to develop because of the
complexity and risks invo l ve d .We cannot introduce a
gene into the human genome without being cert a i n
t h at it wo n ’t cause any harm .
One way or another,we will see an exponential ri s e
in the number and va riety of possible genetic exten-
sions—like the additions to computer operating sys-
tems that occurred during the 1980s and 1990s.
Extensions that were once unimaginable will become
indispensable . . . to those parents who can afford
them. n
“W ith QualGene serv i c e s ,you too can have
the highest quality embryo money can
bu y.Our scientists are dedicated to yo u r
h e ri t a g e — d o n ’t leave your precious children to chan-
c e ! ”
I t ’s just a matter of time before such an ad tanta-
lizes prospective parents of the United Stat e s ,s ays Dr.
Jeffrey Botkin, a bioethicist and pediat ric geneticist.
A m e ricans have a heart-felt fetish for doing eve ry t h i n g
possible to help their children succeed. So why not
gi ve them the ultimate headstart by selecting the “ b e s t ”
from a batch of fertilized eggs or by one day geneti-
cally enhancing a child-to-be?
Welcome to the world of laissez faire eugenics,
s ays A rthur Caplan, one of the most influential A m e-
rican bioethicists.“This simply means that people are
free to choose how they want to design their children,
with the constraints that they don’t kill,h a rm or make
them wo rse off,” s ays Caplan, of the Unive rsity of
Pe n n s y l va n i a .“If yo u ’re not taking any [health] ri s k s ,
2 .The dangers of laissez faire
w Amy Otchet
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
then it’s hard to criticize the goal of trying to biolo-
gically make your child better.”
Not so for the philosopher who first coined the
t e rm laissez faire eugenics, Philip Kitcher of Colum-
bia Unive rs i t y.“ We ’re putting the rat race into the
wo m b ,”he say s.“I used to be more optimistic,” t h i n-
king that education and support for the disabled wo u l d
lead to a genetic utopia free of discri m i n at i o n .“ B u t
n ow I see the root of the problem goes deep into capi-
talist society with the pressure to compete,”s ays Kit-
c h e r. “ Parents with the resources will feel pressured
to make sure that their children have ‘the right gene-
tic stuff.’ ”
Picking and choosing
‘ d e s i rable’ tra i t s
As geneticists develop new DNA tests and tech-
niques to screen and perhaps one day enhance
e m b ryo s ,“parents will be torn between the desire to
do the best they can for their child and their percep-
tion of the prejudices and inequalities surr o u n d i n g
t h e m ,”s ays Kitcher.I m a gine a couple sorting through
a batch of in-vitro fertilized eggs. Perhaps scientists
will find that there are certain genes which corr e l at e
with same sex preference.“Then we can expect some
parents to say, ‘ we ’re not prejudiced bu t i t ’s aw f u l l y
hard for a lesbian daughter to make it in our society.
. . .”Genetic testing, s ays Kitcher,will be used to we e d
out “ u n d e s i r a b l e s ” the way amniocentesis is now used
in China and India for sex-selection.This laissez fa i r e
eugenics will creep up on society as people increa-
singly look to genetics to relieve—not resolve — p r o-
blems caused by social situat i o n s. Skin colour could
be considered a social handicap,in which case an A f r o -
A m e rican couple might seek to produce a white baby.
While doctors might refuse the request, it begs the
question as to whether or not the gove rnment has a
role in regulating the selection and,p e r h a p s , one day,
the enhancement of embryo s.
Legal regulation “is not likely to happen and I’m
not sure that it should,” s ays Caplan. In the United
S t at e s ,“ p e rsonal choice is believed to be the best ans-
wer to questions of conception and reproduction,”h e
s ay s , explaining that this commitment to pri va cy has
kept abortion legal. If gove rnment began regulat i n g
the conditions in which children are born ,a n t i - a b o r-
tion groups might find a way of curtailing wo m e n ’s
rights to control their fert i l i t y. B e s i d e s ,s ays Caplan,
h ow can gove rnment begin limiting what parents bio-
l o gically offer their children when they have virt u a l-
ly free rein in environmental mat t e rs such as reli-
gion and education? Caplan also points out that
genetically enhancing an embryo will not be the same
as “ p r o gr a m m i n g ” a child. A strict religious upbri n-
ging may mould a child far more than enhanced at h-
letic ability, for example. B e s i d e s , is there any t h i n g
wrong with giving a child improved memory? 
The problem,s ays Kitcher, lies in the cumulat i ve
effects of individuals’d e c i s i o n s.A more homogeneous
society will emerge as parents select some traits ove r
o t h e rs.This wo n ’t lead to a Hollywoodesque scena-
rio of a nation dominated by chubby blond cheru b s
with blue eye s. I n s t e a d , Kitcher wa rns that the focus
on picking and choosing “ d e s i r a b l e ” traits may reduce
respect for dive rs i t y, reinforce racism and widen the gap
b e t ween those who can and those who cannot afford the
l atest genetic serv i c e s.
Ethically this would be wrong,s ays Caplan,but “ t h e r e
is no escaping it.” R e s t ricting individual liberty for the
common good is not the “ A m e rican way ” .“ We rely on
the wisdom of individual choice to get to the gr e ater bene-
fit—not some notion of an agreed upon collective bene-
fit ,” s ays Caplan.
Yet there may be some legi s l at i ve room for manoeuvre,
s ays Lori A n d r e w s , director of the Institute of Science,
L aw and Technology in Chicago.Constitutional protec-
tions prevent the gove rnment from interfering in a cou-
p l e ’s decision to have or not have a baby, s ays A n d r e w s.
This does not guarantee absolute freedom in deciding
w h at kind of child to have or under what conditions.
A major stumbling block to regulation lies in the ragi n g
c o n flict between anti-abortion groups and the scientific
community over embryo research.Extreme positions on
both sides have led to a “ l e gi s l at i ve va c u u m ” ,s ays A n d r e w s ,
l e aving the pri vate sector to pursue the research beyo n d
the scru t i ny of federal review boards.As it stands now,t h e
Food and Drug A d m i n i s t r ation (FDA) is supposed to
decide which genetic tests and treatments are available to
c o n s u m e rs.The problem,s ays A n d r e w s , is that FDA deci-
sions are based on safety and effic a cy—ethical conside-
r ations and public debate are not part of the equat i o n .
M a r keting campaigns
The legi s l at i ve vacuum leaves a lot of responsibility
on the doorstep of the medical community. E n o rm o u s
p r o fits stand to be made in the emerging field of repro-
d u c t i ve genetic serv i c e s.Marketing campaigns will focus
on the “perfect baby” to convince parents that their chil-
dren-to-be require “the best money can offer” in prena-
tal diagnoses and enhancement.With these commercial
p r e s s u r e s , parents will need medical and ethical guidan-
ce to eva l u ate the products.
Yet “the medical profession has gotten little beyo n d
identifying the problems,” s ays Dr. Botkin of the Uni-
ve rsity of Utah.D o c t o rs are trying to adopt a “ n o n - d i r e c-
t i ve ”approach when revealing the results of prenatal tests.
But as Botkin points out, r e p r o d u c t i ve decision-making
b e gins with the choice of tests taken. Professional stan-
dards traditionally reflect the minimum a doctor should
do in particular circumstances.As genetics deve l o p s ,d o c-
t o rs will need to consider the maximum.Yet they alone
cannot set the limits which, Botkin say s , require a broad
social dialogue.
The need for public debate is perhaps the one point
on which eve ryone agr e e s.While bioethicists like Caplan
focus on “good parenting”, Kitcher goes a step furt h e r.
“When we begin talking about how to groom human
beings from the womb on, something has gone aw f u l l y
wrong in our society,”he say s.“ Pa rt of the solution lies in
l e gi s l ation but part lies in modifying the culture of the
a f fluent society.We are living in a time of the self-profes-
sed triumph of capitalism.As a philosopher, I am incli-
ned to ask: is this competition good for us and our chil-
d r e n ? ” n
While the law
[of competition]
may be sometimes
hard for
the individual,
it is best for the
race because it
insures the surviva l
of the fittest in
every department.
A n d rew Carnegie,
American industrialist
( 1 8 3 5 - 1 9 1 9 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
In I n d i a, sex selection
gets easier
w R . R a m a c h a n d r a n
New sex pre-determination techniques 
a re likely to re i n f o rce anti-female pre j u d i c e.
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 29
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
w Delhi-based Indian science
journalist
A single word on a sign advertises a thriving busi-
ness in India: u l t r a s o u n d . Using sound waves to
produce images of foetuses,this diagnostic tool
is a common part of prenatal care. But in India, a d ve r-
tisements for ultrasound carry a hidden message: d o c-
t o rs will use the tool to reveal the sex of the unborn ,o p e-
ning the way to abort “negative” results, meaning in
effect females.
Clinics have resorted to this disguised adve rt i s i n g
since a law enacted in 1996 banned the use of prenatal tes-
ting for sex selection.D o c t o rs are only allowed to test foe-
tuses for genetic and congenital abnormalities or disease.
In pri n c i p l e , they can be prosecuted for giving the fa i n t e s t
hint as to the sex of a foetus.
Yet the law looks better on paper than in practice,
admits S.C. Srivastava, Policy Director of the central
g ove rnment Health Ministry. R e gi s t r ation of clinics
has been slow and there has not been a single prose-
cution despite official acknowledgment of widespread
a bu s e . One reason is that abortion up to the 20th we e k
of pregnancy is legal,even though sex selection is not.
It is hard to prove an abortion is done for sex selection.
Female foeticide
Sex determ i n ation has been rampant in India since the
1970s when doctors began misusing amniocentesis (ana-
lysis of uterine flu i d ) . A 1985 survey in Bombay, f o r
e x a m p l e , r e vealed that 90 per cent of amniocentesis
centres were invo l ved in sex determ i n at i o n ,with nearly 96
per cent of female foetuses abort e d .To d ay, ultrasound is
the preferred method, with some 1,500 clinics operat i n g
in Punjab alone,a nort h e rn state of over 20 million people
where India’s first sex determ i n ation clinic was set up.T h e
only thing the law seems to have done is to raise doctors ’
fees from about $10 to $30 a session to compensate for the
risk of criminal prosecution.The situation will even get
wo rse with a new wave of ultrasound units, s ays Dr. S h a-
rada Ja i n , a we l l - k n own Delhi gynecologi s t . A m n i o c e n-
tesis is effective in sex determ i n ation in the 16th to 18th
weeks of a pregnancy.To d ay,abdominal ultrasound ima-
ging can tell the sex of a foetus with 90 per cent accuracy
at 14 we e k s. More advanced trans-va ginal ultrasound—
widely-used in Delhi and spreading elsewhere—has eve n
gr e ater accuracy at 12 we e k s. Thus female fœticide is
n ow possible in the first trimester when abortion is less
c o m p l i c ated and there is less suspicion of sex selection,s ay s
D r. Ja i n .
The heart of the problem is traditional at t i-
tudes towards females, insists Dr. Mira Shiva of the
Vo l u n t a ry Health A s s o c i ation of India in New
D e l h i .D a u g h t e rs are seen as an expense part i c u l a r l y
because of the dow ries families pay to marry them
o f f. Under such circumstances, the law banning sex
selection is a “non-starter,” says Dr. Shiva.
G i ven this value system, h ow would people
respond to new genetic technologies to pre-select
the sex of embryos? An A m e rican fertility institute
recently caused a stir with a new technique, M i c r o-
Sort, which separates sperm bearing X-chromo-
somes (producing females) from those with Y- c h r o-
mosomes (producing males).Doctors report a 93
per cent success rate for producing girls and 73 per
cent for boy s.The current $5,000 cost of such a pro-
cedure is expected to fall and doctors believe it is
only a matter of time before the new sex pre-deter-
mination technique hits India.
“I can easily provide the service within months,”
s ays Dr. Anoop Kumar Gupta of Delhi IVF and
Fe rtility Clinic. “If I do, I will have hundreds of
clients queuing outside.” Some doctors in India,
like Dr. T. C . Kumar of Hope Infertility Clinic in
B a n g a l o r e ,b e l i e ve the pre-determ i n ation technique
would stem female fœticide.“The ethical choice lies
b e t ween the preve n t i o n , and the perp e t u ation of fœti-
c i d e ,i n fanticide and homicide of females,” s ays Dr.
Ku m a r. “Social change is a long, d r awn-out pro-
c e s s. Can we afford to wait until these changes
o c c u r ? ”
But according to Dr. S h i va , sex pre-selection
would only feed the “ p at h o l o gical condition of 
our society which discri m i n ates and denigr at e s
wo m e n .” n
The best of either
sex should be
united with the best
as often as possible,
and the inferior with
the inferior as
seldom as possible.
P l a t o, G reek philosopher
(428-348 BC)
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
Is C h i n a ’s law eugenic?
C h i n a ’s approach to family planning has been attacked in the West as authoritarian
and an infringement on individual rights. B e l o w, Chinese Academician Qiu Renzong re j e c t s
claims that his country’s Law on Maternal and Infant Health is eugenic. O v e r l e a f, a German
Sinologist challenges Qiu Renzong’s position.
Ch i n a ’s Law on Mat e rnal and Infant Health (see
b ox opposite page) has attracted considerable
c riticism in the We s t e rn media and scientific
c i r c l e s. Some of the criticism is valid but some is
based on misunderstandings caused by linguistic or
cultural barri e rs. Much of the confusion revo l ve s
around the word yo u s h e n g, which repeatedly occurs
in the legal text.A tricky word with dual meanings,
it is commonly used to mean “ h e a l t hy birt h s ” in asso-
c i ation with child-reari n g . H owe ve r , yo u s h e n g c a n
also be used to describe eugenic programmes such
as that practised by the Nazis.U n f o rt u n at e l y,E n g l i-
sh translations of the law tend to reflect this lat t e r
m e a n i n g .
Is the Mat e rnal and Infant Health Law eugenic?
I would argue that for a policy to be eugenic it must
first reject individual consent and second, be based
on racism. Neither of these conditions applies to
C h i n a ’s law.While doctors may advise two indivi-
duals at risk of passing on hereditary disease to refrain
from marrying or to undergo steri l i z at i o n , the ulti-
m ate decision is left to these adults.When prenat a l
testing reveals genetic disease, a doctor will offer
advice—not a directive — c o n c e rning abort i o n .
The way to a higher domain
It is also crucial to recognize that the law is not
m o t i vated by racism but by a desire to reduce birt h
d e f e c t s. I n d e e d , there is no racist tradition in China.
The Chinese have been the victims of We s t e rn impe-
rialism and Japanese militari s m .They may have
made gr ave mistakes, but they have never claimed
superiority over another people,and their military
actions have never been motivated by racism. N o r
is racism part of China’s internal policies.The Han,
C h i n a ’s dominant ethnic gr o u p, do not claim super-
iority over China’s minorities.
We s t e rn e rs are often shocked by Chinese at t i-
tudes to defective foetuses because they do not
u n d e rstand the cultural and economic fa c t o rs invo l-
ve d .The gr e at Confucianist Xun Zi (300-237 BC)
s a i d :“ B i rth is the beginning of a human being, a n d
d e ath is the end of a human being. A human being
who has a good beginning and a good end fulfills the
Tao [the Way to a higher spiritual domain].”Two
major fa c t o rs shaping genetic policy in China emer-
ge from this Confucian view. F i rs t ,a b o rtion is moral-
ly and socially acceptable because life begins with
b i rt h . A foetus is not considered a human being.
S e c o n d , congenital disease and deformity are consi-
dered a sign of sin committed by the parents or ances-
t o rs in their previous life. G i ven that a defective new-
b o rn child is traditionally called a “monster foetus”,
it is not surp rising to find little in the way of fa m i l i a l
or social support . One of the parents of a deform e d
baby will usually have to stop wo r k i n g, and the costs
of caring for such a child can amount to a third of an
average wo r k e r ’s salary.
Poverty
C h a n ging these negat i ve attitudes will take a
gr e at deal of time.There are now more than 50 mil-
lion handicapped people, mostly living in poverty,
and it is unreasonable to expect any major impro-
vements in the treatment of handicapped children
and their mothers in the near future. In this context,
m a ny feel that these children and their mothers
would be better off if the handicapped had neve r
been born . In fa c t , the Chinese A s s o c i ation of the
Handicapped formally urged the gove rnment in
1989 to speed up legi s l ation to prevent the birt h
of deformed babies, gi ven their suffering and the
burden they represent for society.
The concern for the collective good has at times
led geneticists and others in China to infringe upon
individual autonomy.They have confused what is
t e c h n o l o gically possible (genetic testing) with what
is ethically perm i s s i b l e .H owe ve r , I feel that the law
is a positive step towards guaranteeing eve ryo n e
access to genetic counselling and to prohibiting sex-
s e l e c t i o n . Chinese geneticists and bioethicists have
c riticized some articles of the law.Their suggestions
include more explicit recognition of the pri n c i p l e
of informed consent. Last ye a r , the authori t i e s
consulted leading Chinese bioethicists and gene-
ticists and will make the needed changes at  an
appropriate time.Meanwhile,I would ask Western
colleagues to directly consult officials, g e n e t i c i s t s
and citizens instead of trying to sanction China,
which may do more harm than good. n
w Bioethics programme director,
Chinese Academy of Social
Sciences, Beijing
1. ‘A concern for c o l l e c t i v e g o o d ’
w Qiu Renzong
If the twentieth part of
the cost and pains
were spent in measures
for the improvement of
the human race that is
spent on the
improvement of the
breed of horses and
c a t t l e, what a galaxy of
genius might we not
c r e a t e.
F rancis Galton,
British scientist, initiator of the
study of eugenics (1822-1911)
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 31
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
Su p p o rt e rs of China’s Mat e rnal and Infant Heal-
th Law often argue that the word yousheng i s
mistranslated as “eugenics”,instead of “heal-
t hy birt h ” . Besides the simple observation that a
t e rm has no gi ven meaning outside the context in
which it is used, it might be noted that in European
languages the word “ e u g e n i c s ” also etymologi c a l l y
r e f e rs to “ h e a l t hy birt h ” (Greek root meaning “ g o o d
in birth”).
The term yo u s h e n g appeared in China duri n g
the 1920s when many publications on eugenics we r e
t r a n s l ated or written in Chinese.The intern at i o-
nal eugenics move m e n t , spanning from Swe d e n
to Ja p a n , was embraced by many intellectuals in
C h i n a . Some openly praised Nazi racial policies,
while others adopted a softer approach aimed at
p r e venting “ u n f i t ” individuals from reproducing.
While eugenics became taboo after the communist
t a k e - over in 1949—as it did elsewhere in the wo r l d
gi ven its association with Nazism—it reappeared as
an intrinsic component of the one-child policy of
1978.
Today, large numbers of popular and scientific
p u b l i c ations still hail the British scientist Francis
Galton (1822-1911; Charles Darwin’s cousin, t h e
founder of eugenics) as the father of yousheng w h i c h
they clearly define as the science by which the stat e
can improve the physical and mental features of
its population by selective breeding.
The law ’s support e rs strongly emphasize its reco-
gnition of “individual consent”:but what real effect
can “individual consent” h ave in a one-party stat e
such as China, where political dissent is so often
punished? These support e rs tend not to mention the
half a dozen provincial laws passed since 1988 which
n e ver mention individual wishes: in Gansu prov i n-
c e , for instance, “ i d i o t s ” ,“ c r e t i n s ” and “ i m b e c i l e s ”
(not defined in medical terms) are not allowed to
m a rry unless they have been steri l i z e d .
It is crucial to understand that racism is not a
n e c e s s a ry component of eugenics.Thousands of
individuals judged to be mentally impaired we r e
forcibly sterilized in Scandinavian countries until
the 1960s without being defined as “ r a c i a l l y ”d i f f e-
r e n t .To defend China’s law by arguing that the Han
do not think of themselves as superior to “minori-
t i e s ” is seriously misleading.W hy not ask ethnic
Tibetans what they think about this? 
An inalienable right
Eugenic laws in China fall largely on two gr o u p s :
peasants (about 70 per cent of the population) and
ethnic minori t i e s , (55 groups comprising about eight
per cent of the populat i o n ) . In specialist and popu-
lar publicat i o n s , Chinese geneticists claim to find
higher rates of mental and physical handicap among
the peasantry than the urban populat i o n .They also
claim that there are higher rates among at least some
ethnic minorities in comparison to the majority Han.
These geneticists maintain that the economic back-
wardness of these groups is reinforced by inbree-
d i n g . I would argue that this is no more than a scien-
tized ve rsion of Han prejudice against minori t y
endogamic practices.
“Confucian va l u e s ” are also evoked to justify the
1995 law. China is not frozen in time.To invoke Xun
Zi in the 1990s is as useful as referring to the Spar-
tans to explain Nazi policies. R e p r o d u c t i ve freedom
is not the prerogat i ve of a few privileged cultures, bu t
an inalienable part of individual ri g h t s. C o e r c i ve
methods of controlling population gr owth cannot be
defended on cultural gr o u n d s.The steri l i z ation pro-
grammes used in India during the “ e m e r g e n cy per-
i o d ” in the 1970s, for example, were ove r w h e l m i n-
gly rejected once general elections were held.B e s i d e s ,
research shows that in China and elsewhere indivi-
duals have ve ry different views on the treatment of
handicapped people. In surveys by Chinese resear-
c h e rs in the late 1980s, up to 25 per cent of those
questioned considered life to be sacred in all cir-
c u m s t a n c e s. S e rious birth defects are one of the most
painful challenges any family can fa c e , and all pos-
sible ethical considerations and medical options
should be carefully considered and openly debat e d .
The present eugenic legi s l ation does not reflect this
consensus-making process; it imposes decisions.
E ven in democratic countri e s , m a r gi n a l i z e d
people may be treated in a discri m i n at o ry way, a s
social prejudice and economic interest affect the
n ature of genetic inform ation made available to
fa m i l i e s , e m p l oye rs , insurance companies or we l-
fare stat e s. In a one-party state like China, e u g e-
nic laws have been used to suppress rather than assist
vulnerable people. n
w Director, Contemporary China
Institute, School of Oriental and
African Studies, University of
London
2. ‘The legislation i m p o s e s d e c i s i o n s ’
w Frank Dikötter
POINTS OF LAW
The following are key excerpts from the official translation of China’s Maternal and Infant Health
Care Law, which came into effect in 1995.
Article 8: The pre-marital physical check-up shall include the examination of the following
diseases:(i) genetic diseases of a serious nature;(ii) target infectious diseases;and (iii) rele-
vant mental disease.
Article 10: Physicians shall, after performing the pre-marital physical check-up, e x p l a i n
and give medical advice to both the male and the female who have been diagnosed with cer-
tain genetic disease of a serious nature which is considered to be inappropriate for child-bea-
ring from a medical point of view;the two may be married only if both sides agree to take
long-term contraceptive measures or to take ligation operation for sterility.
Article 16: If a physician detects or suspects that a married couple in their child-bearing age
suffer from genetic disease of a serious nature, the physician shall give medical advice to the
c o u p l e, and the couple in their child-bearing age shall take measures in accordance with the
physician’s medical advice.
Article 18:The physician shall explain to the married couple and give them medical advice for
a termination of pregnancy if one of the following cases is detected in the prenatal diagnosis:
(i) the foetus is suffering from genetic disease of a serious nature; (ii) the foetus is with defect
of a serious nature; and (iii) continued pregnancy may threaten the life and safety of the pre-
gnant woman or seriously impair her health. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
Human cloning is D o l l y ’s
d e b a t a b l e o f f s p r i n g
w David Dickson
The dawning possibilities of human cloning raise unprecedented ethical and political
d i l e m m a s. N o w h e re is the debate more intensive than in Britain, w h e re the cloned sheep Dolly
was created using a revolutionary technique.
w News editor of the
international science journal
Nature, and author of The New
Politics of Science (University of
Chicago Press, 1988)
In Fe b ru a ry 1997, when British scientist Ian W i l-
mut and his colleagues at the Roslin Institute out-
side Edinburgh announced that they had suc-
cessfully cloned a sheep, D o l l y, the news set off a
global wave of concern about the possibilities of
human cloning. In contrast, the reaction of gove rn-
ment officials in Britain was one of sat i s fa c t i o n — b o r-
d e ring perhaps on complacency — t h at adequate pre-
p a r ations had already been made to address the full
i m p l i c ations of cloning research.
As political leaders across the world spoke stern-
ly of the need for an immediate global morat o ri u m
on such research, B ritain was able to point out that
human cloning—the creation of humans copied from
other humans—was already banned under the
Human Fe rt i l i z ation and Embryology A c t , passed in
1 9 9 0 .
The 1990 Act does, h owe ve r , a l l ow research on
human embryos up to 14 days old and in pri n c i p l e
appeared to open the way for “therapeutic cloning”—
the use of cloning techniques to develop a potential
range of medical treatments such as organ and tissue
replacement and repair.
But the mood changed in June this ye a r , w h e n
the gove rnment refused to endorse a proposal from
the respected regulat o ry body established by the act—
the Human Fe rt i l i z ation and Embryology A u t h o ri-
ty—to allow amendments to the legi s l ation which
would formally allow research into therapeutic clo-
n i n g .The gove rnment said it needed more time to
study the ethical implications of such amendments.
For Bri t a i n , the political dilemma is part i c u l a r l y
a c u t e .On the one hand, the cloning techniques deve-
loped by Wilmut and his colleagues have been hailed
as a major scientific breakthrough whose broad poten-
tial medical applications promise to provide a major
boost to the British economy, for example through
licensing to companies across the wo r l d .
But with trust in gove rnment scientists already
deeply scarred by the experience of bovine spongi-
f o rm encephalopat hy (BSE, i n f o rmally known as
Mad Cow Disease), and further dented by concern
over the potential health and environmental dangers
of genetically modified crops, the gove rnment appea-
red reluctant to take further risks to its credibility by
giving rapid approval to another “ r e vo l u t i o n a ry ”a n d
c o n t r ove rsial technology.
Copies of pop stars
There are few who would endorse the use of clo-
ning technology to produce replica human beings to
o r d e r. It is therapeutic cloning, with its enorm o u s
potential medical applications to humans, t h at is at
the centre of most current controve rs y.
One possible application of therapeutic cloning
could be the treatment of women whose mitochon-
d rial DNA—the genetic mat e rial that provides ener-
gy to the cell—is damaged, and therefore risks pas-
sing this defect on to their children. Another is the
ability to gr ow and graft skin in this way,which wo u l d
replace the need for the current practice of using skin
taken from another part of a pat i e n t ’s body.The same
technique could be used to replace damaged bone
or liver cells.
The problem, of cours e , is that the word cloning
remains highly emotive ,c r e at i n g, as it does, v i s i o n s
of rich pop stars or autocratic dictat o rs ordering up
multiple copies of themselve s. C ritics argue that clo-
ning represents the ultimate “ i n s t ru m e n t a l i z at i o n ”
of a human being: t r e ating one individual pri m a ri l y
as the means to gr atify another, not as an end in him-
self or hers e l f.They also argue that any attempt to
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 33
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
distinguish between “ r e p r o d u c t i ve cloning”and “ t h e-
rapeutic cloning” is largely semantic, and that gi v i n g
the green light to the second will inevitably lead to
the firs t .
But the distinction is seen as critical for those keen
to realize the full medical potential of the cloning
t e c h n i q u e s.Among them is Wilmut himself, who has
spent much of the past two and a half ye a rs talking
about both the threats and the promises that his wo r k
has opened up, and now works as chief scientific offi-
cer for Geron Bio-Med,a company set up earlier this
year jointly by the Roslin Institute and a U. S .b i o-
technology company, G e r o n , to exploit the potential
of his wo r k .
For W i l m u t , like many others , the ethical threat s
of human cloning invo l ve sensitive issues of human
identity and social relat i o n s h i p s ,p a rticularly within
the fa m i l y.“ We can all imagine the type of issues that
would arise if a cloned child were born into our ow n
fa m i l y,” he say s.“Just think, for example, of the dif-
ficulties for a child who fails to meet the expectat i o n s
of its parents, which is quite likely gi ven that pers o-
nality is only partly the result of our genetic inheri-
t a n c e .” But he also insists that the promises of clo-
ning techniques, if responsibly used, r e m a i n
e n o rm o u s.“There is a large potential here for prov i-
ding more effective treatment for a range of diseases,
such as Pa r k i n s o n ’s Disease, t h at are associated with
damaged cells that do not have the ability to repro-
duce themselve s.” He acknowledges that the ethi-
cal dilemmas are diffic u l t ,a d d i n g :“ We are keen to
take part in any discussion that addresses them.”
But attempts to win acceptance for therapeutic
cloning research in the political arena have prove d
fraught with obstacles,p ri m a rily stemming from the
political strength of anti-abortion gr o u p s ,who remain
deeply opposed to all forms of cloning.
T h i s , for example, has already been the fate of
attempts by the Clinton administration to introduce
l e gi s l ation in the United States that would simulta-
neously outlaw reproductive cloning while allow i n g
e m b ryo cloning for therapeutic purp o s e s.
Sensitivities in the U. S .are high.Earlier this ye a r ,
the National Institutes of Health announced that ,
despite being subject to a congressional ban on the
use of federal funds for research on embryo s , it had
decided to sponsor work on stem cells obtained from
e m b ryos provided by the pri vate sector, e . g . , left ove r
from fertility treat m e n t s. (Stem cells are undifferen-
t i ated cells from which specialized cells such as blood
cells deve l o p.) But congress is now moving to close
this loophole.
The pers p e c t i ve of U. S . c ritics is close to that
which has dominated legi s l at i ve debates in mainland
Europe—in particular in France and Germ a ny — w i t h
its heavy emphasis on potential threats to human
“ d i g n i t y ” . Indeed it is this approach, combined with
the view that human life begins at conception, t h at
has led most European countries to ban not only
attempts at human cloning, but all forms of embryo
r e s e a r c h .
‘A moral black hole’
In contrast, the official British (and A m e ri c a n )
approach has,up to now,been more pragmat i c, s e e i n g
the potential dangers of human cloning pri m a ri l y
in terms of the possible medical ri s k s , such as uncer-
tainty over long-term complicat i o n s. But the UK
g ove rn m e n t ’s new announcement appears to refle c t
an increased willingness to accept that other more
explicitly “ e t h i c a l ” fa c t o rs need to be taken into
a c c o u n t .
This acknowledgment was immediately we l c o-
med by religious lobby groups such as Chri s t i a n
Action Research and Educat i o n , whose director,
Charles Colchester,was quoted in the London Ti m e s
as urging the gove rnment to ensure that a new review
body set up by the gove rnment to inve s t i g ate human
cloning techniques should consider what he descri-
bed as the “gaping moral black hole” in such scien-
t i fic research.
But this suggestion was widely criticized by resear-
c h e rs in the fie l d .R o b e rt W i n s t o n , for example,p r o-
fessor of fertility studies at the Royal Po s t gr a d u at e
Medical School in London,wa rned that many of Bri-
t a i n ’s “best scientists” m ay be tempted to leave the
c o u n t ry to carry on their work if the gove rnment does
not back dow n .“By confusing the cloning argument,
the gove rnment is in danger of impeding one of the
most significant medical advances of the decade,”h e
s a i d .
There was also criticism from those keen to see
cloning techniques developed as a commercial acti-
v i t y. “ B ritish science is currently at the forefront
of this emerging field,” s ays John Sime, the chief
e xe c u t i ve of the Bioindustry A s s o c i at i o n , the pro-
fessional organization for the UK biotechnology
i n d u s t ry.“But it is a competitive one in which much
is at stake,both for patients and the economy.”
Some remain optimistic that research will recei-
ve the green light. “If the promises that have been
made for these new techniques, in terms of the
potential for treating degenerat i ve diseases,are eve n
half tru e , it would be immoral not to go ahead with
the research,” s ays Juliet Tizzard of the Progr e s s
E d u c ational Tru s t , a group that lobbies in favour of
research on reproductive technologies.
But this conclusion is far from assured, and the
debate is far from over.The prospect of being able
to produce identical copies of adult humans conti-
nues to hold enough fascination for some—and to
be sufficiently distasteful for others—to ensure that ,
w h at e ver the potential medical benefits from
the less dramatic aspects of cloning research,
its support e rs face a difficult task in getting
permission to proceed. n
‘ We can all imagine the type of issues that would
arise if a cloned child were born into our own family.
Just think, for example, of the difficulties for a child
who fails to meet the expectations of its pare n t s,
which is quite likely given that personality is only
partly the result of our genetic inheritance.’
Because of heredity, o u r
lives are actually as full
of cabbalistic signs and
spells as
if sorcery really did
e x i s t .
M a rcel Pro u s t ,
F rench writer (1871-1922)
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
w Journalist in Berlin (Germany)
G e r m a n y : the d a r k
shadow of the past
w Hartmut We w e t z e r
Memories of the Nazis’ eugenics ideology provide a sombre 
backcloth to German debate on applications of human 
genome re s e a rc h
Germans tread very delicately in the field of
b i o e t h i c s. When the birth a cloned sheep
called Dolly was announced in 1997, it set off
wild speculation in the media.The idea of cloning
humans was immediately dubbed immoral and set
off a barrage of condemnation from many politi-
cians, scientists, church officials and environmen-
talists. It had already been formally banned by a
1990 German law protecting embryos.
Why is there such near-unanimous agreement
about this and why are people so touchy when it
comes to discussing biology, medicine and ethics?
Why is Germany so far behind in what bioethicist
Ludger Honnefelder calls its “ability to think and
judge” in these matters?
We have to remember the horr o rs perp e t r ated by
the Nazis in the name of eugenics.These pseudo-
s c i e n t i fic theories developed in the 1930s, and from
1939 on they were used to justify, among other
t h i n g s , the exterm i n ation of Je w s , h a n d i c a p p e d
people (100,000 of whom were subjected to “ e u t h a-
nasia”in the space of five years) and gypsies.
In the name of science and “the master race”,d o c-
t o rs and geneticists performed horri fic experi m e n t s
on human guinea pigs.“The whole subject was taboo
among German scientists until the early 1980s,” s ay s
Benno Müller-Hill,a geneticist at Cologne Unive rs i t y
who published a book in 1984 called “ M o rtal Science”.
“We can’t walk past this ocean of blood and
continue on our way as if nothing had happened,”
he says. Especially as modern genetics may spawn
new kinds of “scientific racism”. It could lead, he
s p e c u l at e s , to a link being made between genes
g ove rning certain character traits, such as aggr e s s i o n ,
and membership of an ethnic group, which would
encourage discrimination.
Germany’s National-Socialist past also weighs
on the Council of Europe’s Convention on Human
Rights and Biomedicine, which Germ a ny refuses to
s i g n .M a ny politicians, r e l i gious believe rs ,e nv i r o n-
mentalists and associations of handicapped people
s ay it isn’t tough enough. They agree with the
Catholic Social Democrat Robert Antretter, who
f e a rs “a resurgence of disregard for human life as it
was applied during the Nazi era.”
They oppose parts of the convention which
a l l ow research to be done, in certain circumstances,
on human subjects who cannot gi ve reasoned
consent (mainly children and the handicapped).
They also deplore the fact that it does not ban
experiments on embryos,as in Germany. Opposi-
tion to the convention is gr owing in the German par-
liament.
‘We enjoy
disaster scenarios’
Only prenatal examinations seem to escape the
general cri t i c i s m . The churches do not strongly
oppose this practice.Wolf-Michael Catenhusen, a
Social Democrat and Secretary of State for research
in the present gove rn m e n t ,s ays it is important that
the people involved should be able to decide whe-
ther or not to bring a handicapped child into the
world. “We musn’t forget,” he says,“that in more
than 90 per cent of cases such examinations prove
parents’fears to be groundless.”
The “ h i s t o ri c ”suspicion of genetics does not seem
to have lessened since the coalition gove rnment of
Social Democrats and Greens took office in 1998.T h e
Greens are critical of modern medicine and science.
“ P r o gress in biomedicine calls into question our
concept of what it means to be human,”s ays Monika
K n o c h e , the Greens’ health expert .
G e rman scientists and industrialists stress that the
c o u n t ry must not get left behind by its foreign com-
p e t i t o rs in the field of the new technologi e s.“ We enjoy
disaster scenari o s ,” f o rmer President Roman Herzog
once said.“Nearly all discove ries raise many questions
about the risks and dangers invo l ve d , but few about
the opportunities they prov i d e .” n
The life of science is
that superficial life.
It pursues success with
skill and thoroughness,
and takes no account
of the higher nature of
m a n .
R a b i n d ranath Ta g o re,
Indian poet (1861-1941)
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 35
B i o e t h i c s : the lure of the perfect child
Genes of i n e q u a l i t y
wMohamed Larbi Bouguerra
New drugs and treatments based on genetic re s e a rch are set to widen existing disparities 
in access to medical tre a t m e n t
w Former director of Tunisia’s
National Institute for Scientific
and Technical Research and
author of La Recherche contre le
tiers monde (“Research against
the Third World”;PUF, Paris, 1993)
and La Pollution invisible
(“Invisible Pollution”;PUF, Paris,
1997)
Medicine in the 21st century is likely to be based
on genetics.The decipherment of DNA being
done as part of the intern ational Human
Genome Project will probably unleash a flood of
a p p l i c ations which will make it possible to improve
the physical condition of human beings at a time when
m a ny experts are saying the limits of “ c o nve n t i o n a l ”
medical care have been reached.
O ver the next two decades, gene therapy, i m m u-
nology and cell culture enabling production of total-
ly uncontaminated blood (for people with leukemia,
for example) are expected to make gr e at stri d e s.T h e
availability of a range of prenatal tests designed to
spot genetic anomalies in embryo s
will boost the development of genetic counselling
s e rv i c e s.
But who will benefit from all this? Right from the
s t a rt of the Human Genome Project in 1990, Ja m e s
D.Wat s o n , one of the discove r e rs of DNA’s double
helix structure, has campaigned for this great pro-
ject to stay in the public domain. “The wo r l d ’s
n at i o n s ,” he has said, “must realize that the human
genome belongs to eve rybody on the planet and not
to individual countries.”
Most discove ries and new treatments have come
out of laborat o ries in the rich countri e s , but people
from countries of the South have also contributed
their brain power and hard work. It was an Indo-
n e s i a n , Joe-Hin T j i o, who prove d , in 1956 in
S we d e n ,t h at human beings have 46 chromosomes.
In 1968,in the United States,Indian Nobel Prize-
winner Har Gobind Khorana became the firs t
person to synthesize a human gene.
Lack of resources
and political will
Analysis of the DNA of some indigenous peoples
has yielded valuable genetic data for scientists who
h ave subsequently declared discove ries made on the
basis of it to be their own intellectual propert y.
One such population study, for example, i d e n t i-
fied the genes of a man of the Hagahai tribe (Pa p u a
New Guinea) which provide immunity to the leu-
kemia virus HTLV.
But owing to lack of resources and political
w i l l , m a ny poor countries have trouble putting
together a serious policy on science which would
reduce their total dependence on rich countri e s
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
and enable them to work out research priorities.
Some of these countries howe ver have human exper-
tise and facilities which allow them to contri bute to
work on DNA sequencing.
India, for example, has six laboratories where
this can be done, all of them linked to the Hydera-
bad Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology.
Some Indian specialists would have preferred to
sequence the DNA of pat h o l o gical organisms
(microbes, mosquitoes, contaminants,etc.) which
are common in India, r ather than that of human
beings chosen at random. In this way, it would have
been easier, they say, to develop applications that
would be immediately useful to people in India.
This is an ongoing debate because nobody can gua-
rantee that analysis of the human genome will lead
to medical treatment for people in the countries of
the South, where there are fewer profits to be made
than in the North.
Light-years away
from medecine’s new horizons
The other big question is that of access to the new
f o rms of treat m e n t . E ven in rich countri e s , w h e r e
public spending on health is being cut, these thera-
pies will be ve ry expensive — at least to begin with—
and are likely to trace a new frontier between the we l l -
off and the rest of the population (see page 26). S o
it is not ve ry likely that treatment of this kind will really
reach the people of the third wo r l d .The countries of
the South are also light-ye a rs away from the new
h o rizons of medicine because they lack basic health
facilities and trained health wo r k e rs.
Should some countri e s , or even whole regions like
A f rica south of the Sahara, not be part of today ’s
d e b ate about bioethics just because they might be
excluded from the benefits of tomorr ow ’s medicine?
The answer is no. F i rs t , because their inhabitants are
sometimes directly invo l ve d . The eliminat i o n , f o r
e x a m p l e , of some “ h a rm f u l ” genes through germ - l i n e
therapy—if it were ever applied on a wo r l d - w i d e
scale—could be ve ry harmful to them. In accor-
dance with the phenomenon known as pleotropy, a
single gene can control several characteri s t i c s.T h u s
the recessive gene of cystic fibrosis may play a part in
fighting cholera.
Sickle-cell anaemia (an abnormal form of the
red pigment of the blood, haemoglobin) affords
some protection against the deadly form of the
malaria parasite, Plasmodium falciparum. If the
gene that triggers this condition is eliminated, do
we risk seeing even more cases of malaria? This is
a very gloomy prospect in a world where malaria
is already killing two million people a year and
when none of the big pharmaceutical companies
have invested money to look for a vaccine. More
generally, the whole planet is concerned by the
risk of reducing the genetic reserves available to
future generations by altering or eliminating cer-
tain genes. Is it not presumptuous and dangerous
to anticipate their needs when nobody yet knows
what kind of environment they will be living in?
No one on the planet should be excluded from
discussions about mat t e rs affecting human exis-
tence, which are of course of universal concern.
Bioethics is about the absolute, intrinsic worth of
every individual—the very essence of human life.
The lines it draws between what is possible and what
is acceptable should be worked out with the invol-
vement of all the world’s cultures,even if they are
minority or dominated cultures.
What’s more, bioethics again poses the urgent
question of solidarity among human beings in the
face of illness.When genetic medicine no longer just
s e rves the rich but also enhances their lifestyle,
prolongs their lives or enables them to produce
children with specific characteristics, can we deny
the people of poor countries the benefits of know-
ledge which would free them from the scourge of
d e b i l i t ating parasitical diseases, of Aids and of here-
ditary afflictions? How long could such “medical
apartheid” fail to affect the consciences of those
living in the countries of the North? n
A T R E ATY ON THE GENOME?
‘In the framework of international co-operation, States should seek to encourage measures
enabling: . . . the capacity of developing countries to carry out research on human bio-
logy and genetics, taking into consideration their specific problems, to be developed and streng-
thened . . . ; developing countries to benefit from the achievements of scientific and tech-
nological research so that their use in favour of economic and social progress can be to the
b e n e fit of all.”Article 19 of the Universal Declaration on the Human Genome and Human Rights
gives a new focus to “the rights of solidarity”. The declaration,which is not legally binding,
was adopted by the international community in 1997 after long negotiations within UN E S C O’s
International Bioethics Committee (IBC).
The declaration also enshrines two major principles, explain Noëlle Lenoir, who chaired
the IBC during the negotiations. Fi r s t , rejection of biological determinism: human beings are
not animals programmed by their genes. Second,a refusal to accept that genetics can pro-
vide justification for socially discriminatory or racist practices.“Human dignity” is the key expres-
sion in the text, which condemns reproductive cloning.This declaration adopted under UN E S-
CO’s auspices is today the only text of universal scope which specifically concerns bioethical
issues. “But,” Lenoir adds, “I feel that in the present context of globalization we should be
moving towards a treaty,” that signatory states would be bound to respect.Wa r n i n g :t u r b u l e n c e
ahead. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
IS COP Y RIGHT ON THE 
W RONG TRACK ?
w Mireille Buydens
Efforts to strengthen intellectual property rights are posing a challenge 
to their original purpose—striking a balance between the protection 
of individual property and the public interest
n
W h at is the purpose of intellectual pro-
p e rty rights? Ori ginally they were based
on the principle that creat o rs should be
granted exclusive rights to exploit their
wo r k s , in order to ensure they were properly
r e m u n e r ated and, in addition, to encourage
c r e at i ve activity. But in the interest of the
community and of future artists and inve n-
t o rs , those exclusive rights were limited in
time:when the term of protection ran out,
the works fell into the public domain, a
c o p y right-free space that encourages crea-
tion and competition.They could then be
used as raw mat e rial and a kind of “ s u g g e s-
tion box ” by fresh generations of creat o rs.
A balance between the protection of indi-
vidual property and the general interest wa s
guaranteed.
To d ay that balance has been destroye d .
The founding principles of intellectual pro-
p e rty seem to be threatened by an ill-consi-
dered increase in the number of pri vat e l y
held exclusive rights at the expense of the
public domain.
Counterfeit software
and designer clothes
The main factor hastening these deve-
lopments is a change in the economy, w h i c h
focuses increasingly on products with “ i n t e l-
lectual added va l u e ” , such as new softwa r e ,
the selection and presentation of informa-
t i o n , specialized computer serv i c e s , c u l-
tural and entertainment products,biotech
p r o d u c t s , and other applications of cut-
ting-edge technologi e s. Control of ideas,
f o rm s , images and brands is a cru c i a l
element in this so-called “immaterial eco-
nomy”.
While it is difficult to steal a consign-
ment of steel gi r d e rs or a cargo of bananas,
it is child’s play to copy software or manu-
facture counterfeit designer clothes. It is
easy for intellectual added value to be illicitly
w Professor at the Catholic University of Louvain
and a lawyer in Brussels, BelgiumN ew Delhi, in a get-tough demonstration organized by software companies, an elephant tramples on pirated CDs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
E T H I C S
a p p r o p ri at e d : it cannot be “put under lock
and key”.Those who want to exploit it for
their own profit simply need to be able to
reproduce it. P i r ates in this field can market
copied products at a lower price than the
originals,since they do not have to pay the
cost of creating or adve rtising the product.
By doing this, they distort competition.
International negotiations
To protect their industries against piracy
and counterfeiting (see box), the member
c o u n t ries of GATT (General A gr e e m e n t
on Ta riffs and Tr a d e , which gove rned inter-
national trade from 1947 to 1994) set out
to strengthen intellectual property ri g h t s
within the GATT framewo r k .G AT T ’s main
c o n c e rn was to protect companies from
u n a u t h o rized copying and unfair competi-
t i o n , thus ensuring they would get a return
on their investment.
When GATT concluded its first agr e e-
ments, intellectual property was not very
high on the agenda. In the immediat e
postwar years,products put on the market
still consisted of atoms of mat t e r , not bytes.
It was not until the Uru g u ay Round of talks
s t a rted in 1986 that the issue came to be dis-
cussed at the intern ational leve l .T h at round
of talks resulted in the signing, on April 15
1994, of the Agreement on Trade-Related
Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights
( T R I P S ) . Like the multilateral agr e e m e n t s
on trade in goods, the text was included in
an appendix to the Marrakesh framework
agreement that set up GATT’s successor,
the World Trade Organization (WTO).
TRIPS,which has a global application
(most countries in the world have now sub-
s c ribed to it), c o n f i rmed the economic
importance of intellectual property rights.
It requires member states to protect all
f o rms of creat i o n :l i t e r a ry and artistic wo r k s
in the broadest sense (including maps and
press photos), computer progr a m s , d at a
b a s e s , sound recordings, radio and television
b r o a d c a s t s , d r awings and models, i nve n-
tions of products and processes in eve ry
technological field, the lay-out designs of
integrated circuits,and so on.
The agreement was a milestone in the
h i s t o ry of intellectual propert y. F i rs t , i t s
scope of application is unprecedentedly
w i d e :a nything created in the fields of tech-
nology, software, news or culture can and
must be protected by an intellectual pro-
p e rty ri g h t , in such a way that it exclusive l y
benefits rights holders, who alone decide
h ow it should be reproduced and distri-
buted. Secondly, for the first time TRIPS
requires contracting states to organize pro-
cedures and sanctions that enable ri g h t s
holders to ensure that their rights are res-
p e c t e d .Those states are for example obliged
to allow persons or companies whose ri g h t s
h ave been infringed upon to go to court
and obtain damages. Such duties are chiefly
incumbent upon the developing countri e s.
Most of these countries do not possess the
human or financial resources that wo u l d
enable them to develop their own produc-
tion, and they have tended to become the
p r e f e rred locations of the copying industri e s.
In this general move towards compre-
hensive protection of products with intel-
lectual added value, the European Union
has not lagged behind. In the course of the
past 10 ye a rs , it has been ve ry active in
introducing new legislation.According to
the directive of May 14, 1991, computer
p r o grams are protected by copyright at
European Union level. Similarly, the defi-
nition of copyright content has been tigh-
t e n e d ,p a rticularly as regards the copyri g h t
of works put on the Intern e t . In this connec-
tion, a proposed directive on “the harmo-
n i z ation of certain aspects of copyright and
n e i g h b o u ring rights in the inform at i o n
s o c i e t y ” was examined by the European
Parliament on February 10, 1999, with a
view to its adoption.The directive contains
p r ovisions for authors or their rights holders
to control the distri bution of their works on
the Net or to forbid it. Any copy of their
sound or visual works available online will
entitle them to financial compensat i o n ,
even if the copy is made solely for strictly
private use.
A new right to protect investment
The protection of data bases by copy-
right has also been confirm e d . For the firs t
time in the European Union, it was even
extended to their contents by a directive of
March 11 1996. Until then, it had been
accepted that a compilation of data pos-
sessing the characteristics of an ori gi n a l
creation could be protected by copyright.
But this protection covered only the selec-
tion and arrangement of the data, in other
words the structure or container of the
base,not its content.The raw data, on the
other hand,were not covered by copyright
and could therefore be used by anyo n e .O n
this occasion, the European legi s l at o r
stressed that data collection could, irres-
pective of the creation of the data base’s
a r c h i t e c t u r e , represent a substantial inve s t-
m e n t . He concluded that the content of
the data base should also be protected.
Clearly departing from the traditional ru l e s
g ove rning intellectual propert y, which in
t h e o ry concern creat i ve contri butions alone
(products with intellectual added va l u e ) ,
he established a new right designed to pro-
tect financial inve s t m e n t .Those who make
a “ s u b s t a n t i a l ” i nvestment are prov i d e d ,
de fa c t o, with an exclusive right to the bene-
T HE COUN T ERFEI T ING INDUS T R Y
A ccording to Peter Lowe of the Counterfeiting Intelligence Bureau (CIB), a London-based organiza-
tion that reports to the International Chamber of Commerce, counterfeiting is a “multi-billion-dollar
industry”. The CIB puts its global turnover at $250 billion. “It is estimated that it accounts for 5-8 per cent
of world trade,” says Lowe. The most commonly counterfeited products are software programs, CDs, CD-
Roms, videocassettes, watches and designer clothes.
In the United States, the copyright industries alone (essentially the cinema, television, publishing, record
companies, and manufacturers of software and video games) lost $12.4 billion as a result of pira cy in 19 9 8 ,
according to the International Intellectual Property Alliance (IIPA). This group of commercial bodies that
are campaigning for stronger protection of intellectual property includes 1, 350 American companies. Accor-
ding to its president, Eric Smith, “copyright industries are growing very fast worldwide”. In the United States,
they account for about 3.65 per cent of GNP. In 1996, they became the country’s main export, ahead o f
automobiles, agri-foodstuffs and aerospace. n
P i rates can marke t
copied products
at far lower prices
than the originals,
since they don’t have
to pay the cost
of creating or advertising
the product.
By doing this,
they distort competition
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
fits of their inve s t m e n t , e ven if there has
been no intellectual creation.
Financial interests again have now
prompted the European legi s l ator to
consider the adoption of a directive on the
protection of biotechnological inventions.
The move was motivated by two factors:
f i rs t , “the protection of biotechnologi c a l
inventions will certainly be of key impor-
tance for the Community’s industrial deve-
l o p m e n t ” ; s e c o n d l y, “research and deve-
l o p m e n t , notably in the field of genetic
e n gi n e e ri n g, require a considerable degr e e
of high-risk investment which cannot be
profitable unless there is adequate legal
protection”.
Financial terminology—talk of profit a-
bility and an attractive “return on invest-
ment”—is invading the sphere of intellectual
p r o p e rt y. The notion of intellectual pro-
perty used to be a way of protecting intel-
lectual added value; it has now become an
instrument for turning invested capital to
good account. Is this a necessity or is it
r e grettable? The question is wo rth deba-
ting.
It is true that in the field of biotechno-
logy, for example, creation requires consi-
derable investment.This is something that
i n d u s t rial companies cannot accept unless
they are sure of being able to make it at least
p a rtially profit a b l e . On the other hand, o n e
m ay reasonably wonder whether there is
any point in creating a new monopoly on
i n f o rm ation contained in data bases, e ven if
a great deal of time and money has gone
into creating them.The idea here is not to
r e ward an intellectual creat i o n , h owe ve r
s l i g h t , but merely to repay an investment in
time and money.This trend could well jeo-
pardize the sharing of know l e d g e . T h e
notion of intellectual property here seems to
h ave departed from its basic purp o s e ,w h i c h
was to ensure a balance between pri vat e
and public interests.
This change of direction is one of the
f i rst perve rse effects of the exponential
increase in the amount of space occupied by
intellectual propert y. More fundamentally,
it has been engineered by a society that
tends to make legal and mat e rial protection
the keystone of its ethos: all property and
a nything else of value needs to be protected
against ri s k . Accident preve n t i o n ,s e c u ri t y,
insurance and protection have become man-
tras in developed Western societies. It has
reached the point where those societies
sometimes seem to have forgotten that ri s k
is an inherent aspect of life and freedom.
The second perve rse effect of the boom
in intellectual property—the broadening
of its scope as well as of its duration—is
equally wo rry i n g . In 1993, for example,
the duration of copyright in the European
Union was increased from 50 to 70 years
after the author’s death.
On many occasions over the last ten
ye a rs , l e gi s l at o rs and courts have also
a greed to an unlimited extension of the
scope of copyright protection. O ri gi n a l l y
designed to protect works of art , c o p y ri g h t
has been extended to cover eve ry sphere of
human creat i o n , from the design of car
b o d y work or ties, m e t e o r o l o gical photo-
graphs and the instruction manuals of
e l e c t rical household appliances to dat a
bases and recipes. Since eve ry t h i n g
belongs to someone, an authori z ation from
the owner is required for eve ry t h i n g . I n
practice it has become extremely diffic u l t
to create a multimedia wo r k , to shoot a
fil m , to compose a piece of music, or to
publish an illustrated book without in
some way having to use elements that are
protected by copyri g h t , and therefore
h aving to request a detailed authori z at i o n
from copyright holders and to pay them
financial compensat i o n .
In the short term , this increase in the
number of exclusive rights will be a threat
to economic activity itself. C o m p e t i t i o n ,
after all, boils down to offering the same
product as someone else. N ow if that 
product and all its va ri a n t s , ve rsions and
components are protected by intellectual
c o p y ri g h t , copying—in other wo r d s ,
making a competing offer—becomes an
extremely hazardous exe r c i s e . If limited
e x c l u s i ve ri g h t s , which used to form part of
the ori ginal spirit of intellectual propert y,
protect companies against illicit copying,
d i s p r o p o rt i o n ate exclusive rights quite
simply wipe out competition altogether.
As for the extension of the duration of
c o p y ri g h t , it means that the community’s
right to make free use of a work after it has
fallen into the public domain will be a
theoretical possibility rather than a fa c t .
The present duration of copyright protec-
tion often exceeds the period during which
the created work is in fact usable. After 70
ye a rs or more, an old computer program is
of no use to anyo n e .
S i m i l a r l y, the European directive on
d ata bases theoretically restricts their pro-
tection period to 15 ye a rs. But it stipulat e s
t h at if a data base is modifie d , notably by a
large number of additions, deletions or
changes which show there has been sub-
stantial further inve s t m e n t , the durat i o n
can be extended by 15 ye a rs.T h u s , a regu-
larly updated data base can be protected
for ever and will therefore never fall out of
c o p y ri g h t .T h at contravenes the most fun-
damental principles that underlay the
notion of intellectual property ri g h t s. n
Los Angeles, 1996: a police raid on a T-shirt store selling counterfeit clothing.
R e s e a r c h
and development,
n o tably in genetic
engineering, require a
c o n s i d e ra b l e
amount of high-risk
investment which
ca n n o t
be profita b l e
unless there is adequate
legal protection
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
n
Imagine an urban area whose popula-
tion has increased from 300,000 to
nearly two million in 40 years. It
sprawls out in every direction and its
growth seems unstoppable. This is the
case of Tunis, which has even started
filling in some of the salt lakes on its per-
iphery and building modern neighbou-
rhoods on the reclaimed land.
As you go north of the capital,past the
big port of La Goulette and the old sub-
urb of Kram, you suddenly come upon a
vast expanse of meadowland, green in
winter and yellow in summer, that is dot-
ted with the remains of walls, heaps of
stones and the stumps of still-gleaming
marble columns. These are the outskirts
of Carthage, in Antiquity the prosperous
capital of the Roman province of Africa.
Towards the sea, the landscape is
again dominated by buildings, forming an
immense garden city interspersed with
the splendid ruins of the ancient city. Its
suburbs stretch further north as far as
ancient Megara, overlooked from a height
by the village of Sidi Bou Saïd, whose
white domes have for centuries stood out
between the sea and the sky.
Unexcavated 
remains
C a rt h a g e , a city both mythical and
r e a l , was founded in the 9th century B. C .
by the legendary Queen Dido (also
k n own as Elissa), who hailed from
Phoenicia. It became the Mediterranean’s
most fo rmidable maritime trading powe r
until the rise of the Roman Empire,
which destroyed it in 146 B. C . Its for-
tunes then revived under the Romans.
Only ruins are left of the Phoenician city,
but the remains of Roman and Byzantine
C a rthage are more abundant and gi ve a
good idea of what one of the biggest
cities of ancient times was like. But a
large part of the old city is still bu ri e d
a n d , if steps are not taken, m ay stay hid-
den foreve r.
To get an idea of the threats that hang
over ancient Cart h a g e , you have to climb
atop the hill of Byrs a , which was the site
of a Phoenician fortress and then the
Roman foru m . To d ay the hill is occupied
by the St Louis basilica, which was bu i l t
in early colonial times, and the form e r
a r c h b i s h o p ’s palace, n ow a museum.
From here, you can see over the entire
plain of Tu n i s. Nearly all the narr ow
coastal strip between the lake and the sea
is built up. Teeming slums fill the sou-
t h e rn end of the stri p. F u rther nort h ,b e t-
ween Carthage and the seaside resort of
M a rs a , are chic residential suburbs where
e ve ry rich or politically powerful Tu n i s i a n
dreams of living.
C a rt h a g e , which was supplanted by
Tunis more than a thousand ye a rs ago,
seems to have become once more a sym-
bolic place of power since Habib
B o u r g u i b a , independent Tu n i s i a ’s firs t
p r e s i d e n t , established the presidential
palace there. The urban pressure seems
i n e x o r a b l e , whether from the poorer
areas or from the zone of luxurious villas
which look on to them. Tunis has no
more room to expand and is gr e e d i l y
e yeing a 500-hectare area which has been
set aside as a future archaeological park.
The site of Carthage has been protected
for the past 30 years, and new building
has been virtually halted. Urbanization
began at the end of the last century, with
the construction of the railway from Tunis
to La Goulette and Marsa. Under the
French protectorate, villas and housing
estates began encroaching on the area.
After independence in 1956, this creeping
expansion accelerated dramatically. The
city grew in size because of population
growth and an exodus from rural areas. A
new gove rnment-fostered middle class
sharpened appetites for land and proper-
ty speculation. Concrete spread like a lava
flow.
A rescue 
operation
In the early 1970s, awareness began to
spread, both in Tunisia and abroad, that
the remains of Carthage were in danger of
disappearing forever. On May 19, 1972,
UNESCO Director-General René Maheu
launched an international campaign to
save the site, which was put on UNESCO’s
World Heritage List in 1979. Rescue ope-
rations soon began. As a dozen teams of
archaeologists from several countries got
to work, the Tunisian government took
CA RT H AGE’S 
LONG - AWA I T ED RESCUE
w Sophie Bessis
Despite 30 years of protection, the site of the great city of Antiquity is still being eroded by urban
pressures. A major conservation project now in the works should pave the way for new exca v a t i o n s
w Freelance journalist
Carthage
Port of Tunis
1 1.5 3 km
Tunis
Bardo Museum
Medina
Ariana
Lake Tunis
La Marsa
La Goulette
Sidi Bou Saïd
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
September 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 41
steps which led in 1985 to the declaration
of a 600-hectare zone of Carthage and
Sidi Bou Saïd as a protected area where
new construction was mostly banned.
Heritage campaigners breathed a sigh
of relief. But if the worst has been avoided
over the past 15 years, threats still loom.
The fight to save Carthage has been
conducted at various levels. It aims to halt
the spread of poor housing as well as to
curb the appetite of the wealthy who are
determined to put up buildings and of
businessmen who want to promote hou-
sing development in a zone where land
values are the highest in the country.
There is little sympathy for the morato-
rium on such development. Why, people
ask, should a building project, which is
either necessary or profitable, be banned
just to preserve past history which only
interests an educated minority of
Tunisians? 
Over the years, six orders have cut
back the area of the future archaeological
park planned in 1985. Two zones were
reclassified as part of the urban area and
were quickly built on, while luxury villas
h ave sprouted around the fa m o u s
Phoenician ports. Some land has been
gi ven to the Polytechnic Institute to
expand its campus. Squatting by poor
people in the Ellil district on the edge of
Carthage has also been allowed.
These encroachments on the protec-
ted zone are worrying but not alarming,
according to one expert, and so far the
core of the site has been preserved. But
the pressures are so strong today that tou-
gher laws are now needed as well as the
creation of the long-awaited Carthage-
Sidi Bou Saïd archaeological park, whose
physical existence would finally put an
end to such pressures.
Things are moving along slowly. Since
1991, a cabinet committee chaired by
President Zine El Abidine Ben Ali has
overseen the Carthage project, for which
the president has always expressed strong
support. Officials are working on a pre-
servation and development plan for the
park which is expected to be much more
detailed and restrictive than the 1985 pre-
servation order. It will authorize public
expropriation of any part of the site,
enabling the government to buy the land,
most of it still privately-owned. It will ban
division of plots of land and the building
of housing estates and, with the 1994
Heritage Code, will complete the coun-
try’s set of preservation laws.
UNESCO dispatched a team of experts
to Tunis in March 1999 to take a look at
the plan.They reported that it was “use-
ful and coherent”, though it “risked set-
ting off conflicts, mainly with landowners
. . . but also for other reasons, including
financial ones.” The stat e , they said,
“should make a substantial investment to
gain control of the land by buying it.”
So all the obstacles have not yet been
overcome, but if the determination of the
politicians holds, the preservation plan
should come into effect before the year
2000. To mark the occasion and also
launch a new series of excavations, the
Tunisian authorities want to stage an
international conference on Carthage in
January 2000.
By making the establishment of the
park irreversible, Tunisia will be the only
Mediterranean country to have protected
600 hectares of land in the centre of its
biggest urban area. Tunis will be the only
Mediterranean city with a park of such
size and with such a rich history. For the
past 30 ye a rs , f riends and admirers
of Carthage have been fighting to make
this great dream come true. So far the
battle has not been lost—but it has yet to
be won. n
After independence
in 19 56, urban expansion
a c c e l e rated dra m a t i ca l l y.
The population increased,
and a new middle class
sharpened its appetite
for land and property.
Concrete spread like 
a lava flo w
An upmarket residential area around the port of Phoenician Carthage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
w UNESCO Courier journalist
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
n
The efforts to safeguard Carthage and the
nearby village of Sidi Bou Said (see page
40) are particularly notewo rt hy because
ancient remains in two other Arab capitals have
not always enjoyed the same good fort u n e .
In Cairo, the pyramids have had a narr ow
e s c a p e .“I don’t think anything can harm them
n ow,” s ays Zahi Haw wa s , the energetic head
of the Giza archaeological zone.In 1995,h owe-
ve r , this UN E S C O World Heritage site, w h i c h
contains the last of the Seven Wo n d e rs of the
World that can still be seen, was nearly cut in
t wo by the gr e ater Cairo ring road being bu i l t
to decongest the city of 15 million or so inha-
b i t a n t s.After a campaign led by UN E S C O a n d
helped by the media,Egyptian President Hosni
Mubarak came down on the side of heri t a g e .
As a result,the eight-lane ring road has not
been paved for the four kilometres that we r e
supposed to cross the Giza Plat e a u , but the
rubble is still there and the route has been
handy for truck dri ve rs who use it as a short
c u t .“I ordered this traffic to stop at the begi n-
ning of June,”s ays an annoyed Haw wa s ,w h o
wants the gove rnment to build a detour that
avoids the site.
“ We asked for the road foundations to be
d e s t r oyed but that wa s n ’t done, so I fear the
plan to use the route isn’t completely dead,”
s ays Said Zulfic a r , a former UN E S C O o f fic i a l
who fought against the ring road and is now
s e c r e t a ry-general of the French NGO Pat ri-
T UG -OF - WA R
IN BEIRUT AND CA IRO
w Sophie Boukhari
The defence of archaeological treasures in the Lebanese 
and Egyptian capitals has triggered epic battles and led 
to mixed results
moine sans Frontières (Heritage Without Bor-
d e rs ) .
He deplores the fact that another part of
C a i r o, the protected site of Fustat , the first city
founded by the Muslim conquerors in the 7th
c e n t u ry, is being harmed by “rampant urban
e x p a n s i o n ” .The authori t i e s , he say s ,“ h ave
built social housing and an amusement park
right in the middle of the town when it hasn’t
e ven been excavated by archaeologi s t s.
“In Egypt, there are laws and officials bu t
there are also people more powerful than the
l aw s , along with a lot of speculat o rs ,” s ays Zul-
fic a r , hinting at the weakness of the stat e ’s
Higher Council for Antiquities in the face of
big construction firms headed by people in the
inner circles of powe r.
This is something the inhabitants of Bei-
rut know all about.After the recent civil wa r ,
Lebanese archaeologists had an unexpected
chance to explore and display the precious
b owels of the city centre which had been expo-
sed by bombing. But the area “ was cleared by
bu l l d o z e rs and dynamite as part of a huge
urban renewal project,” s ays Lebanese archi-
tect and town planner Jade Ta b e t .The main
shareholder of Solidere, the company doing
the clearance wo r k ,was we a l t hy former pri m e
minister (1993-1998) Rafik Hari ri ,who is now
in disgr a c e .
This meant that a blueprint making the
city into a kind of Manhattan on the Mediter-
ranean was forced on the centre of the Leba-
nese capital “ e ven before archaeologists could
s t a rt diggi n g,”s ays Leila Badre, the respected
c u r ator of the Museum of the A m e rican Uni-
ve rsity of Beiru t .“From that point on, the die
was cast—badly—and we realized that the
i m p o rtance of the archaeological remains wa s
going to be played dow n .”
E x c avations sponsored by UN E S C O b e t-
ween 1993 and 1995 uncovered some ve ry
valuable remains,notably the ancient “ t e l l ”o r
mound which was evidence of the city’s Phoe-
nician ori gi n s. In 1996, the gove rnment eve n
ordered three sites to be preserve d , but the
order was never carried out.“If we don’t take
action quickly,the remains will be damaged,”
wa rns Badre.
Who can do this? Solidere or the Directo-
r ate General of Antiquities? Solidere is going
through a bad pat c h , and in A p ril 1999 the
head of the Directorate General and half of his
aides were thrown in prison for embezzlement.
“ I t ’s a mess,”s ays Ta b e t .“ We should have
based the plan for the new centre of the city
on sites that could have become centres of
at t r a c t i o n .But just try persuading someone
who only thinks in cash-flow terms that
archaeology can create added value! All the
d e ve l o p e rs see are square metres of space to
be built on as fast as possible.So some remains
h ave been dumped in the sea,o t h e rs are cru m-
bling into dust and Solidere’s ‘ d a z z l i n g ’p r o-
ject is 
in the doldru m s. I t ’s dreadful to see the 
3 , 0 0 0 - year history of a city sold down 
the ri ve r.” n
Greater Cairo’s tentacular growth reaches out to the pyramids.
Development and rebuilding in central Beirut
have given short shrift to archaeological remains.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
n
The most cunning criminals have alway s
sought to outsmart police, and cy b e rs-
pace is no exception.The virt u a l ,b o r-
derless unive rse frequented by some 130 mil-
lion netizens provides the detective wri t e r
with eve ry ingredient for a labyrinthine thri l-
l e r: an anonymous interfa c e ,c h a r a c t e rs miles
a p a rt adopting nicknames and fake addresses,
sometimes disguising their identities to enti-
ce a victim into a real-life meeting, or sen-
ding encrypted mat e rials that are just about
impossible for outsiders to decode.
It could be a thri l l e r , except when the
m at e rial being traded is child porn o gr a p hy
and the people enticed are under-age.
Images range from innocent photogr a p h s
of young children with neutral or smiling
expressions to extreme cases: in 1996, m e m-
b e rs of the Orchid Club chat room (see glos-
sary) used a digital camera connected to a
computer to photograph a 10-year-old child
posing in a sexually explicit manner.T h e
pictures were transmitted to other online
ring members who made requests for the
girl to pose in other positions.The ring wa s
an intern ational one,and its members we r e
arrested in several countries.
Innocence in danger
As the online population gr ow s , c o u n-
t ries and organizations are stepping up
efforts to curtail child pornography on the
Internet.By the medium’s very nature,the
venture is intern at i o n a l . In A p ril 1999 UN E S-
CO launched its Innocence in Danger move-
ment that aims to sensitize public opinion
to child porn o gr a p hy on the Internet and
mobilize resources to make the Net safer for
c h i l d r e n . In May, a victory was scored when
Ja p a n , one of the largest producers of child
p o rn mat e ri a l , passed a law banning its pro-
duction and distri bu t i o n . In September, t o p
European and American judicial and poli-
ce offic i a l s , along with industry representa-
tives and NGOs, are meeting in Austria to
discuss strat e gies for reinforcing co-opera-
tion in the field.
w UNESCO Courier journalist
T HE DA RK ER SIDE 
OF THE NET
w Cynthia Guttman
To combat child pornography on the Net, there is a strong consensus that governments, 
law enforcement, industry and users each have a role to play
Just how perva s i ve is child porn o gr a p hy
on the Net? In researching her fort h c o m i n g
b o o k , A Pa r e n t s ’Guide to Protecting Children
in Cybers p a c e, Pa rry A f t a b , an A m e ri c a n
cy b e rspace law yer and former director of
Cyberangels, the largest U.S.online safety
and education programme,compiled a list
of 30,000 sites relating to child abuse or pae-
d o p h i l i a , out of an estimated total of 4.3
million sites. Looking more closely at news-
groups (see glossary ) , Rachel O’Connell, a
p s y c h o l o gist from the Unive rsity of Cork
(Ireland) who is co-ordinating a European
research project (COPINE) on the issue,
found that child porn o gr a p hy amounted to
0.07 per cent of around 40,000 newsgr o u p s
wo r l d w i d e . According to Ruth Dixon,
manager of a British hotline run by the
I n t e rnet Watch Fo u n d at i o n , the wo rst mat e-
rial is concentrated in some 20 newsgr o u p s.
Trading child porn o gr a p hy, h owe ve r , is just
one face of the coin, the other is the danger
of children entering online chat groups with
the intention of making friends or shari n g
i n t e r e s t s , and ending up fa c e - t o - face with
a person who turns out to be much older
than claimed and seeking a sexual encoun-
ter.
One of the greatest concerns is that the
I n t e rnet has made child porn o gr a p hy more
visible and accessible, giving paedophiles
the sense of being connected to a commu-
nity of like-minded individuals. According
to O’Connell, “one of the most signific a n t
fa c t o rs influencing the gr owth of child por-
nography on the Internet is the ease of dis-
s e m i n ation and collection.A n o nymity and
c o nvenience have revealed an extraordi-
n a ry level of sexual interest in children. P r e-
s u m a b l y, this interest was either dorm a n t
or latent on this scale in the past.”As Mar-
tine Brousse,head of the French NGO Vo i x
de l’Enfa n t , puts it, “the person who might
not have gone through the process of bu y i n g
In Chicago, DeNashatae Horton shows her mother and sister some of the tools developed on its web site
by the Ameritech company to help parents and children surf the Internet safely.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
C O N N E X I O N S
a particular magazine to nurture his fa n-
tasies can now just go on the Net, i t ’s not
d i f f i c u l t .” In newsgroups devoted to child
p o rn ,u s e rs typically recount claimed expe-
riences and fantasies to each other and
exchange pictures, sometimes by the hun-
dreds. O’Connell has found that they tend
to be a fairly cohesive and we l l - s t ru c t u r e d
c o m m u n i t y, and provide advice to each
other on how to avoid detection. M o n e y
rarely comes into the equation.
Legal loopholes
There is nothing illegal about exchan-
ging fa n t a s i e s.W h at is illegal in most coun-
t ri e s — but not in all—is the production and
d i s t ri bution of child porn o gr a p hy.This can
make it difficult for authorities to take action
at the source, where mat e rials are being
u p l o a d e d . Nor is the possession of child por-
n o gr a p hy a criminal offence eve ry w h e r e .T h e
d e finition of a child’s legal age va ries from
one country to another,and so does the defi-
nition of indecency. And while the majori t y
of users are based in developed countri e s ,
NGOs such as Casa Alianza and ECPAT
(End Child Prostitution,Child Po rn o gr a p hy
and Tr a f ficking of Children for Sexual Pur-
p o s e s ) , express concern that child sex tou-
rism is being promoted via Intern e t ,p u t t i n g
children at further risk of not only being abu-
sed but having their photographs taken and
transmitted online from countries where ru l e s
r e l ating to child porn o gr a p hy are lax or non-
e x i s t e n t .Faced with these loopholes,p o l i c e ,
N G O s , judicial authorities and law enforce-
ment are pressing for national legi s l ations to
be better harm o n i z e d .
Since the mid-1990s,police forces in a
number of countries have set up units spe-
cialized in tracking down online child por-
n o gr a p hy. In Bri t a i n , Scotland Ya r d ’s pae-
dophilia unit started to take the Net
s e riously when inve s t i g ations led to the sei-
zure of computer hard dri ves containing
child pornography images.The U.S. Fede-
ral Bureau of Inve s t i g ation (FBI) launched
an undercover operation dubbed I n n o c e n t
I m a ge s in 1994 to target people trading in
child porn or expressing an interest in tra-
velling inter-state with the intention of
h aving sex with minors. “ We pretty much
h ave this down to a fine tuned science,”
explains veteran FBI agent Peter Gulotta.
“ Ty p i c a l l y, most of our work invo l ves going
into chat rooms that we have reason to belie-
ve are invo l ved in child porn o gr a p hy.We
pose as adults willing to trade in child porn
or as a young boy or a young girl.In a very
s h o rt period of time, a predator will enga-
ge us in a conve rs ation about our sexual acti-
v i t y. Some will ve ry quickly express a willin-
gness to actually travel to meet us.”T h i s
technique has led, since 1995, to 357 arr e s t s ,
with a 99 per cent conviction rate.
Not all countries have the resources,
skills and legal right to intervene in this way.
An intern ational convention on cy b e rs p a-
ce crime is currently in the wo r k s , with a
p a rticular focus on procedural problems
such as collecting evidence in a crossborder
electronic env i r o n m e n t .“ I n t e rn e t , i n s o fa r
as crimes against children go, calls into ques-
tion the entire way in which police forces
wo r k ,” s ays Agnès Fo u rnier de Saint Maur,
chief of specialized crime at Interp o l .“ We
h ave to envisage legi s l at i ve changes that take
this into account, because without law s ,p o l i-
ce can do absolutely nothing.We also need
additional resources to equip police forces
with the right tools.” Jim Reynolds,former
chief inspector of Scotland Ya r d ’s paedo-
philia unit, r e grets that not all countries have
specialized units or identified points of
contact to whom intelligence on paedophiles
can be passed on.There are complaints of
r e p o rts being sent from one country to ano-
ther and not being acted upon for months.
W h at is far from clear is the relat i o n s h i p
b e t ween viewing child porn o gr a p hy and
sexually abusing a child, e ven though an
image is already the reflection of an abu s e .
“Child porn o gr a p hy is a far more seri o u s
issue that merely talking about photogr a p h s ,
it is the actual visual depiction of the sexual
assault of a child,” stresses Reynolds. “ T h e
c i r c u l ation of these photographs revictimizes
the child.”According to French psychiat ri s t
B e rnard Cordier, the Internet can reinfor-
ce a paedophile’s tendencies and increase the
risks of committing an offence should a par-
ticular set of circumstances allow it.W h at
c o n c e rns Gulotta is that most people arr e s-
ted have no prior records,but inve s t i g at i o n s ,
which include examining mat e rials on com-
puter software and disks,h ave on some occa-
sions revealed previous sexual encounters
with children.When pictures are seized, t h e
first pri o rity of law enforcement is to deter-
mine how recent they are in order to reach
children who might be at risk now. I n
conjunction with police forces in seve r a l
c o u n t ri e s , the COPINE project has constru c-
ted a database of seized child porn o gr a p h i c
videos and pictures traded via the Intern e t .
These images lend themselves to crime scene
a n a l y s i s ,p r oviding clues as to the picture’s
o ri gins and fa c i l i t ating co-operat i o n ,s i n c e
the same pictures may be reported to poli-
ce in different countri e s.
Partly in response to demand from the
police and the public, industry has started
to come forwa r d . “Pressure on them has
been extremely strong,” s ays Saint Maur.
“From the ve ry begi n n i n g, e ve ryo n e ,i n c l u-
ding the police, put the blame on them. B u t
just as you can’t blame the postal service for
shipping porn videos, i t ’s rather difficult to
really point the finger at Internet Serv i c e
P r ov i d e rs (ISPs, see glossary ) .N o n e t h e l e s s ,
this pressure has led ISPs to co-operate with
p o l i c e . For them, i t ’s out of the question that
they should do the policing.”The bottom
line is that without the technical expert i s e
of industry and its willingess to pass on
information to the police,the fight against
illegal content will be ineffective . Police raids
on ISPs in Germany have led to an uneasy
r e l ationship between industry and law
enforcement bodies. “Law enforcement in
and of itself is not a solution, it has to be
p a rt of a broader framework that includes
the taking of responsibility by the industry
i t s e l f,” s ays Jens Wa l t e rmann of the Ber-
telsmann Fo u n d at i o n , which designs and
s u p p o rts projects in a wide number of fie l d s.
At its Internet Content Summit being held
On October 20, 1996, more than 300,000 people
took part in a “white march” in Brussels (Belgium)
to demonstrate solidarity with the victims of
paedophiles.
‘Internet, insofar as crimes
against children go,
calls into question
the entire way
in which police forces work.
We have to envisage legislative
changes that ta ke
this into account,
b e cause without laws, 
police can do absolutely
n o t h i n g ’
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
on September 9-11, the foundation will pre-
sent “practical recommendations for gove rn-
m e n t ,i n d u s t ry and users to work together
in developing a new culture of responsibi-
lity on the Internet.”These involve impro-
ving mechanisms to deal with harmful and
illegal content, namely hotlines as a feed-
back mechanism for users , vo l u n t a ry codes
of conduct among ISPs and software for
rating and filtering purposes.
Rising public awareness
For now, hotlines are the main mecha-
nism through which potentially illegal
content is report e d . Such hotlines exist in
less than ten countries and are funded by
g ove rn m e n t , i n d u s t ry, NGOs or a combi-
n at i o n . Links with law enforcement are not
a lways strong enough.The question of a pri-
vately funded line informing police about
activities regarding a third party can, in some
c o u n t ri e s ,be viewed as a breach of pri va cy.
Saint Maur and French cyberspace lawyer
Daniel Kahn both stress that governments
should be the ones setting up hotlines, w i t h
direct transmission of the information to a
c e n t r a l , specialized police unit.The Bri t i-
sh-based NGO ChildNet Intern ational is
heading an initiat i ve that aims to harm o n i-
ze and improve co-operation among hot-
lines while encouraging new ones. T h e
European Parliament is expected to adopt
a policy by the end of the year that wo u l d
encourage member states to set up specia-
lized round-the-clock units to liaise with
ISPs and law enforcement when alleged ille-
gal material is reported.
The fact that reports to all hotlines are
increasing points to rising public awa r e n e s s
of the issue.While industry is working on a
number of rating and fil t e ring initiat i ve s ,t h e s e
are not deemed sophisticated enough to deal
with child porn o gr a p hy. Aftab recently tes-
ted all the fil t e ring mat e rials on the market
and found that none blocked out the list of
illegal child porn o gr a p hy sites that she had
c o m p i l e d .Cyberangels now licences this list
out to fil t e ring software companies, but so
far only one, Net Nanny,has acquired it. B u t
fil t e ri n g, e ven if it wo r k s ,might protect chil-
dren online but certainly not those whose
images are being traded.
N G O s ,i n d u s t ry and police stress the role
of educat i o n ,both for parents and children,
in raising awareness and reporting illegal
m at e ri a l .Aftab believes that children under
13 should not be taking part in unmonito-
red chat rooms, which software can block
A foreign sex tourist in a ‘girly bar’ in Pattaya (Thailand).
+ …
l www.unesco.org/webworld/innocence
l www.casa-alianza.org
l www.childnet-int.org
l www.cyberangels.org
l www.ecpat.net
l www.fbi.gov/library/pguide
l www.info.fundp.ac.be/~mapi/plan.html The Belgian
Movement Against Paedophilia on Internet has published
a comprehensive report on the issue.
l www.iwf.org.uk The British Internet Watch Foundation
is considered one of the most effective attempts at self-
regulation.
l www.stiftung.bertelsmann.de
Glossary
l Internet Service Providers (ISP): Services offering
direct, full access to the Internet at a flat, monthly rate.
l Chat rooms: Maintained by online providers or systems
such as Internet Relay Chat (IRC), they allow for real-time
text conversation between users.
l Usenet (Newsgroups): Like a giant bulletin board
where users post messages and information.
o u t . Awareness programmes also emphasi-
ze that schools should not be building we b
sites feat u ring pictures of children and divul-
ging personal inform ation about them. A s
head of the U. S .N ational Action Commitee
for the Innocence in Dange r i n i t i at i ve ,A f t a b
has eve ry intention of multiplying awa r e n e s s
i n i t i at i ve s , and already has giants like Micro-
soft and AOL on her side. Only a public
gr o u n d swell can prompt gove rnments to allo-
c ate more resources towards what is funda-
mentally a child protection issue.“Right now,
i t ’s possible to have a finger on the pulse,”
s ays O’Connell, cautioning against sensa-
tionalizing the problem. “If the threat
becomes too large, these individuals will go
f u rther undergr o u n d , to laye rs of the Inter-
net where you wo n ’t be able to find them.I t ’s
only a matter of time before that actually hap-
p e n s.” n
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
According to a recent United Nations study, 
Sri Lanka is the country with the second highest
number of disappeared people in the world.1
And yet there seems to be hardly any debate
within the country about human rights viola-
tions. Why is this?
One of the biggest tragedies of Sri Lanka
t o d ay is the existence of a culture of fear
in both the majority Sinhala and the mino-
rity Tamil societies. Ethnic conflict (see time-
line) and the war against Tamil militants
h ave heavily militarized the society. In the
last three decades,people in the north and
east of the island have lived under the Sri
Lankan army, the Indian Pe a c e k e e p i n g
Force (IPKF) and different Tamil militant
gr o u p s. Both inside and outside the confli c t
z o n e s , civilians are used to living under dif-
ficult conditions, with official and unoffi-
cial curfews, house-to-house search opera-
t i o n s ,a rr e s t s ,t o rture and detention as part
of their eve ry d ay experi e n c e . Some civilians
who openly spoke out against the violence
and terror have been killed publicly by the
a rmy or by the militants. So there has been
no way civilians could talk about human
rights violations.
In the south, the situation is not much
d i f f e r e n t .Thousands of Sinhala youths died
when the government tried to suppress an
i n s u r g e n cy launched to oppose the Indo-
Lanka peace accord of 1987. In the ye a rs
b e t ween 1987 and 1990, piles of bodies bu r-
ning along the roadside became a common
s i g h t . Both the army and the insurgents we r e
responsible for those massacres and disap-
pearances.
In the context of such experi e n c e s ,
civilians in Sri Lanka fear that if you raise
your voice against injustice, the punishment
will be nothing less than deat h . Not intimi-
d at i o n , assault or impri s o n m e n t , but a ve ry
brutal death.Even today, people are being
a b d u c t e d , detained and tortured by the
s e c u rity forces and by para-military and
militant gr o u p s.The culture of fear has gi ve n
rise to a culture of silence. People are still
afraid to talk about what happened betwe e n
1987 and 1990, or about what is going on
t o d ay. Under existing conditions we cannot
expect civilians to come forward to talk
about the human rights abuses of the past
and present.The challenge facing civil socie-
ty in Sri Lanka now is how to break this
culture of silence.
Although there has been extensive loss of 
life in the conflict in Sri Lanka, the international
community has not taken a particularly 
strong line on this issue. What do you feel
about this?
According to our estimates more than
SUNILA ABEY SEK ERA :
PE ACE CA MPA IGNER
ON A WA R -TORN ISLA ND
100,000 people have been killed in Sri
Lanka in the last two decades. It is a pity
that our successive governments as well as
the Tamil militant groups have not made
sincere efforts to find a peaceful solution. I f
the intern ational community had shown a
little more interest and put pressure on the
S ri Lankan gove rnment and the Ta m i l
r e b e l s , I think there could have been a nego-
tiated settlement by this time.
A l t hough Sri Lanka is in a state of wa r ,
the country continues to receive We s t e rn
d e velopment aid.This money is supposed to
be used for relief, r e c o n s t ruction and reha-
b i l i t at i o n . But how is it possible to undert a-
ke development work in the midst of a wa r ?
P r o b a b l y,We st e rn countries consider the Sri
Lankan situation as a manageable confli c t .
If the situation becomes unmanageable,
as in Kosovo or Rwa n d a , then I think there
may be some kind of initiative.
In my view, there is also an element of
racism and neo-colonialism invo l ved in the
We s t ’s lack of interest in the Sri Lankan 
Defying threats to her life, a UN award-winning Sri Lankan human rights activist has brought
abuses in Sri Lanka to the attention of the international community (see box opposite page)
1.The United Nations Working Group on
Enforced or Involuntary Disappearances says that
over 12,000 Sri Lankans have gone missing since
1980 after being detained by security forces. Only
Iraq, with 16,384 missing persons, had more
cases of disappearances.The Sri Lankan
government estimates the number of disappeared
persons at around 17,000,while Sri Lankan
human rights groups say more than 42,000
people have disappeared in the last two decades.
Sunila Abeysekera, flanked by UN High Commissioner for Human Rights Mary Robinson, receives a
UN Human Rights award from Secretary-General Kofi Annan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G  T O …
s i t u at i o n . If one white person had been
abducted or killed in Sri Lanka, then the
Western countries would have reacted dif-
f e r e n t l y. These are brown people killing
b r own people in a fa r away country.W hy
should the West bother?
A few years ago, the Sri Lankan 
government formed commissions of inquiry
to look into the disappearance of civilians 
and human rights violations. What have these
led to?
In the 1990s, human rights groups in
S ri Lanka and abroad launched a huge
public campaign demanding an inquiry into
the reported disappearance of over 42,000
p e o p l e .As a result, the gove rnment form e d
a Presidential Commission of Inquiry (PCI)
in 1992 to inve s t i g ate the complaints. S i n c e
then there have been several other com-
missions on disappearances.
Thousands of families of the disappea-
red testified before the PCIs, which in turn
submitted reports to the president. But the
commissions lacked powe rs to initiate legal
action against those found guilty. None of
the reports has been made public so fa r.A l l
the reports are lying with the presidential
s e c r e t a ri at .Only the president has the autho-
rity to submit them to parliament.
In 1998, because of considerable pres-
sure from the United Nations Human
Rights Commission, civil society, the media
and the intern ational community, t h e
g ove rnment said it had initiated action
against about 100 policemen who we r e
i m p l i c ated by the disappearances commis-
sion for the Central Province of Sri Lanka.
This resulted from a list of over 1,000 com-
p l a i n t s. Only one of the accused was a senior
officer.The rest were junior officials.
Human rights groups have been calling
for the commission to inve s t i g ate furt h e r
and expose those higher officials and poli-
ticians who actually gave orders for these
abductions and killings. In the context of
the on-going wa r , one has to understand the
dependence of the political structures on
the security machinery. From the stat e ’s
point of view (not from mine), you can per-
haps even justify formal impunity, but there
cannot be a total denial of the reality of what
has happened in Sri Lanka. If found guilty,
politicians should be barred from holding
public office and from contesting elections.
This demand is not unprecedented.There
are many examples, including A r g e n t i n a ,
C h i l e ,G u at e m a l a , and El Salva d o r , of coun-
t ries where va rious commissions named
political bosses for human rights abuses.
Human rights groups were also success-
ful in forcing the Sri Lankan gove rn m e n t
to allow a visit by Amnesty Intern ational and
A VICTORIOUS STRUGGL E
AG A INST IN T IMIDAT ION
Intimidation is nothing new to 46-year-old Sunila Abeysekera, the Executive Director of INFORM, a lea-
ding Sri Lankan human rights organization set up in 1989. In 1988, when she was several months pre-
gnant, death threats forced her to flee the country and seek refuge for a brief period in the Netherlands.
Her “crime” was to persistently demand accountability for human rights abuses and action against per-
p e t rators of human rights abuse, regardless of their rank or position. She was on the hit list of the Janata Vimukti
Pe ramuna (JVP), a militant leftist movement, in the mid-1970s, soon after her expulsion from the group. Her
bold criticism of the movement’s activities and a call for democra cy and justice within the group had
aroused the wrath of some senior members. But she weathered the storm and continued to work on her ow n
for civil rights. “When everyone is criticizing you, then you are doing the right thing,” Abeysekera says.
She was among the few members of the majority Sinhala community who established direct contact
with Tamil women in the north and east of Sri Lanka after the outbreak of ethnic conflict in 1983. Wo r k i n g
closely with her father, Charles Abeysekera, she highlighted human rights violations perpetrated by
s e c u r i ty forces under the guise of the Prevention of Terrorism Act and emergency rule in the country’s Ta m i l -
dominated north and east.
The Sri Lankan human rights situation attracted international attention after human rights NGOs in Sri
Lanka, including INF O RM, began to participate in the annual sessions of the UN Human Rights Commission
in Geneva from 1992 onwards. Abeysekera’s consistent presence at international human rights fora and
the international focus she has brought to the human rights situation in Sri Lanka have helped to bring
about some improvements. At the parliamentary elections in 1994 Sri Lankan political parties were
forced to pledge that they would give top priority to improving the human rights situation if elected to offic e .
“Though the promise has yet to be fulfilled, at least they recognized that there is a problem,” she says.
Abeysekera, a mother of two, now lives in Colombo, working with INFORM and many other human
rights and women’s rights groups seeking peaceful and democratic change in Sri Lanka.
UN HUMAN RIGHTS AWARDS
On December  10, 1998, Sunila Abeysekera was honoured by the United Nations for her outstanding
contribution to the struggle for human rights. With Angelina Acheg Atyam of Uganda, Jimmy Carter
of the United States, Jose Gregori of Brazil, and Anna Sabatova of the Czech Republic, she received a UN
Human Rights Prize at one of a series of events held at UN Headquarters in New York to mark the 50th
anniversary of the adoption of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
H o n o ra ry in nature, the Human Rights Prizes were instituted by the General Assembly in 1966 and awarded
for the first time in 1968 on the occasion of the commemoration of the 20th anniversary of the Universal Decla-
ration of Human Rights. Since then, the prizes have been awarded in 1973, 1978, 1988 and 1993. Previous
awardees include Nelson Mandela, Eleanor Roosevelt, U Thant and Dr Martin Luther King, Jr. n
then by the United Nations working gr o u p
on disappearances in 1991.T h at was the firs t
time that the gove rnment recognized that
there had been disappearances. It was a major
breakthrough for the human rights move-
ment in the country.
Sri Lanka has been witnessing violence for the
last three decades. What impact has this had on
women and how have they responded?
Women and children are the first vic-
tims of any kind of conflict. In Sri Lanka
thousands of families have been displaced
The war has left scars in northern and eastern Sri Lanka.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
tive and a positive impact.
At the same time, we also find wo m e n ’s
groups playing an active role in fighting for
peace and human ri g h t s. In 1986, the arr e s t
of around 600 Tamil boys led to the creat i o n
of the “ M o t h e rs ’F r o n t ” ,which organized pro-
tests in the streets of the nort h e rn town of Ja f f-
n a .They broke the barri e rs of a silence of many
ye a rs , and paved the way for a renewed acti-
vism for human ri g h t s.Since then,women of
all communities have come together in orga-
n i z ations seeking justice for disappearances
and working for peace and reconciliation in a
ve ry critical way.
Conservative groups argue that by claiming
equal rights for women, feminist groups are
destroying ancient culture and tradition. Do
you agree?
In South Asia we have this burden of an
ancient past.All our political and nat i o n a l i s t
m ovements have focused on the fact that we
are people with a gr e at heritage and a gr e at
c i v i l i z at i o n .There is no doubt that we have
i n h e rited from the past certain noble va l u e s
which need to be protected.But how can yo u
use religion and culture to justify discri m i n a-
tion against people on the basis of gender,r e l i-
gion and caste?
The conservat i ve s ’ hold over society rests
on their ability to wield control over wo m e n .
More than ever before in history wo m e n
h ave become the markers of the culture and
traditions of a community.The easiest way
to measure this is by looking at how a com-
munity imposes a dress code on wo m e n .We
find stricter dress codes for women now than
in the past. I think we are living in a socie-
from the north and east due to the violen-
c e . Men either join the army or the militant
gr o u p s.The third option for them is to leave
the country. It has been up to the women to
keep families together and to take care of
the children.There are about a million dis-
placed people within Sri Lanka and most
of them are women and children.
M a ny of these displaced women live in
pitiful conditions in gove rn m e n t - run camps.
Because there is a shortage of food, c l o t h i n g,
medicine etc. , they are forced to take up
small-time jobs elsewhere. But they are not
safe in their wo r k p l a c e s.The women are sub-
jected to a lot of sexual harassment.As a result
of the heavy militari z ation of the society, t h e
incidence of violence in the north and south,
p a rticularly sexual violence against wo m e n ,
has increased alarm i n g l y.
Communities are deeply divided by the
c o n fli c t , and men respond by imposing more
r e s t rictions on wo m e n .This applies to Sin-
h a l a ,Tamil and Muslim wo m e n . On the one
h a n d , the conflict pushes women to become
wage earn e rs and to assume responsibility
for the surv i val of their fa m i l i e s.On the other
h a n d , they are expected to conform to tra-
ditional values and safeguard the “ i m a g e ”
and “ i d e n t i t y ” of the community.
A l s o, both the army and the militants
r e c ruit women for their forces. Some of
them are even used as suicide bombers.T h i s
also has an impact on attitudes towa r d s
women in a society as traditional as ours. I n
a South Asian society, the fact that women
r e c e i ve military training and handle arm s
challenges existing attitudes towards wo m e n
and images of them.This has both a nega-
T IMEL INE
w 1948
Sri Lanka gains independence from Britain.
w 1978
An amendment to the constitution changes
the parliamentary form of government to a
French-style presidential system. The
popularly elected president is head of state,
chief executive, and commander in chief of
the armed forces. 
w 1983
The Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE),
an armed guerrilla movement fighting for a
separate homeland for Tamils, ambushes an
army convoy killing 13 soldiers and triggering
anti-Tamil riots all over the country in which
more than 2,500 people are killed. In the
ensuing ethnic crisis half a million Tamils leave
the country to seek refuge in India and
elsewhere.
w 1987
India and Sri Lanka sign an accord to bring an
end to the conflict. An Indian Peacekeeping
Force (IPKF) is sent to the island to end the
hostilities and supervise surrender of arms by
the Tamil militants.
w 1989
After a year-long battle with the LTTE, the IPKF
returns to India. Soon after, the second
“Eelam war” breaks out between government
forces and the LTTE.
w 1991-92
The Sri Lankan government allows a visit by
the United Nations Working Group on
Enforced or Involuntary Disappearances.
w 1993
President Ranasinghe Premadasa is
assassinated by a suicide bomber. Prime
Minister D.B. Wijetunge is elected president.
w 1994
The People’s Alliance (PA), a coalition of
parties headed by the Sri Lanka Freedom
Party (SLFP), wins the parliamentary elections
and forms a goverment. The leader of the PA,
Chandrika Bandaranaike Kumaratunga, is
sworn in as president after winning elections
in November.
w 1995
Failure of peace talks between Tamil rebels
and the government. The LTTE launches major
attacks against armed forces triggering the
third Eelam war.
w 1997
Sri Lanka ratifies the Optional Protocol to the
International Covenant on Civil and Political
Rights and establishes a permanent national
Human Rights Commission (HRC) with a
mandate to investigate human rights
violations, including “disappearances”. 
On May 18, 1999, demonstrators outside the office of Sri Lankan President Chandrika Kumaratunga demand
the release of all prisoners of war and the opening of peace talks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
September 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 49
T A L K I N G  T O …
ty that ’s becoming increasingly fundamen-
talist and puritanical.
C o n s e rvat i ves quote religion as an excu-
se to retain their control over wo m e n . I
strongly believe that religious practices in
South Asia have nothing to do with the phi-
losophical framework offered by different
r e l i gi o n s , including Islam, Hinduism and
Buddhism.They have to do with male reli-
gious leaders who interpret religious texts
to suit their convenience.
The increased part i c i p ation of wo m e n
in the economic and political life of society
is a challenge to existing cultural and tradi-
tional barri e rs. For example, the concept of
the family is slowly being eroded as a result
of economic and social changes that are
b e yond the control of any individual.
Women are becoming independent, a n d
m e n ’s role and the male hold over the fa m i-
ly and society are being challenged by the
processes of globalizat i o n . Hence there is
c riticism of wo m e n ’s claims for equal ri g h t s
and equal treatment.
What role have peace movements and human
rights groups played in Sri Lanka?
Human rights and peace move m e n t s
h ave been trying to create a small space
within a heavily militarized society.T h e y
work closely with the media,academics and
cultural wo r k e rs to spread the ideas of peace
and civil ri g h t s.We hope that as an influ e n-
tial community within society they will have
the courage to speak out.
In 1998 we saw the emergence of two
alliances of non-gove rnmental organizat i o n s
working for peace and a negotiated solution
Source: Le Monde, August 6, 1998
Jaffna
India
Indian
Ocean
100 km
Kilinochchi
Vavuniya
Trincomalee
Batticaloa
COLOMBO
Tamils: 95%
Tamils: 1/3, Muslims: 1/3, 
Sinhalese: 1/3
COUN T R Y
INF ORM AT ION
Name: Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka
Area: 65,610 sq.km
Capital: Colombo
Population: 18.2 million (Sinhalese 74%, Tamil 18%,
Muslim 7%)
Languages: Sinhala, Tamil, English
Religions: Buddhism, Hinduism, Islam, Christianit y
Currency: Sri Lanka rupee 
($1 = 70 Sri Lanka rupees)
Literacy rate: 90%
GDP: $716 per capita
President: Chandrika Kumaratunga
to the ethnic conflict. One is the Nat i o n a l
Alliance for Peace (NAP), consisting of repre-
s e n t at i ves from Ta m i l , Muslim and Sinhala
c o m m u n i t i e s , and the other is the Interr e l i-
gious A l l i a n c e , which includes Catholic and
Anglican bishops and Buddhist monks.To g e-
ther they visited several areas of the nort h
and the central provinces in 1998 and also
held talks with the Tamil militants.
A big rally was organized in Colombo in
Fe b ru a ry this year by the two gr o u p s. For the
first time we had Hindu,C h ristian and Bud-
dhist clergy on the same plat f o rm and all of
them spoke of the need for peace.This is a
ve ry positive deve l o p m e n t .There is a gr o-
wing realization that you have to negotiat e
with the Liberation T i g e rs of Tamil Eelam
(see timeline,opposite page) in order to move
t owards any kind of democratic and peace-
ful settlement of the ethnic conflict in Sri
L a n k a .This kind of intervention is small bu t
c ritical at a moment when ordinary citizens
are afraid to talk.
It can’t be easy to be a human rights activist in a
heavily militarized society. . . 
You are ri g h t .When I started working on
human rights two decades ago it was not easy.
One is regarded as a trouble-maker, s o m e-
times as a traitor. Questioning the role of the
g ove rnment and of the different political
a c t o rs in destroying democratic stru c t u r e s
and creating a militaristic environment led
to attacks from all sides.
In general, human rights activists in Sri
Lanka are working under extreme pressu-
r e . Human rights abuses are committed by
many actors,and we must be critical of all
In June 1999, women in Chemmani village carry pictures of their missing loved ones as excavations begin at a
common grave nearby.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
I WISH TO SUBSCRIBE TO the UNESCO Courier
50 The UNESCO Courier - September 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to:
the UNESCO Courier Subscription Services, 31,rue François Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
For payments in other currencies , please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are opposite this order form.
"
of them. Training people to document
human rights abu s e s , b ri n ging cases befo-
re the law, p r oviding support for victims, a l l
this is a part of our wo r k . M o n i t o ring and
i n t e rvening in human rights abuses in the
north and east is especially difficult.We do
not easily acquire permission to visit areas
under the control of the militants. If there
are reports of human rights abuses in those
a r e a s , we go at the risk of our live s.We are
b a rred from having direct contacts with the
Tamil militants because of the Preve n t i o n
of Te rr o rism Act (PTA ) , which makes our
work even more difficult.
O ver the ye a rs , we have built up a good
n e t work of groups all over the country — p e a c e
c o m m i t t e e s , r e l i gious gr o u p s ,c o m m u n i t y
o r g a n i z ations and wo m e n ’s gr o u p s — w h o
send us inform ation and provide support .
Some individuals living in the troubled
areas pass on inform ation to us. If necessa-
ry, they travel to neighbouring areas on fa c t -
finding missions, sometimes risking their
lives.
Apart from attracting international attention 
to disappearances, what are your achievements
in human rights work?
I consider my consistent invo l vement in
va rious campaigns over the last 20 ye a rs and
acceptance by different networks of gr a s s-
roots organizations and move m e n t s ,b o t h
Sinhala and Ta m i l , as itself a major achie-
vement.The UN award,I feel,is a symbo-
lic vindication of the work I have done all
these years.
Our gr o u p, I N F O R M ,c o - o r d i n ates with
m a ny other groups and organizations in
launching human rights campaigns. I n
1 9 9 7 , we were part of a campaign calling
for action against soldiers who raped and
killed a Tamil schoolgirl,Krishanti Kuma-
r a swa my, while she was in custody. H e r
m o t h e r , brother and a neighbour who we n t
looking for her were also murdered.T h e
p e rsistent demands finally forced the
g ove rnment to initiate legal proceedings
against the suspects. Six of the accused we r e
sentenced to death in 1998.T h at was a land-
mark verdict and was the first time there
had been some kind of prosecution against
a rmy pers o n n e l . I think the credit should
go to all the human rights groups.
What are the chances of reconciliation after 
20 years of ethnic conflict?
T h at ’s a difficult question. As a human
rights activist I can say that it is possible for
all communities in Sri Lanka to live together
with dignity and respect.To achieve that ,l e a-
d e rs of all communities should come forwa r d
to make a new beginning through the pro-
cesses of forgi veness and reconciliat i o n .
There should be an acceptance that all
sides have committed horrendous cri m e s.
Then we have to move beyond that . I f
people are going to dwell on the past,then
there can be no solution.We have come out
of a particularly bad and horrifying period
in our history.The older generation from all
the communities still remember how they
l i ved together happily in the past. It is the
younger generation which has witnessed
wa r ,s e p a r ation and sufferi n g . If the situa-
tion is allowed to dri f t , then there is no chan-
ce for peace in Sri Lanka.
We all know that even if the war comes
to an end tomorr ow, peace will not return
unless the people from all communities are
willing to accept the past, f o r gi ve each other
and go back to living together. For this we
need a new democratic political stru c t u r e
and legal safeguards for the rights of all com-
munities. n
Interview by Ethirajan Anbarasan
UNESCO Courier journalist
Language: English French Spanish
Rates (postage included):
Industrialized countries: Developing countries or students 
1 year: 211French francs (€32,15) instead of 264FF* (11 issues including 1 double issue) (Please send copy of your card):
2 years:396 French francs (€60,35) instead of 528FF* (22 issues including 2 double issues) 1 year: 132 French francs (€20,10)
Binder: 72French francs (€11) (for 11 issues including 1 double issue) 2 years: 211 French francs (€32,15)
I enclose payment: (in French francs only) by
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque) Visa Mastercard Eurocard
N° — — — — — — — — — — — — — — — — — — — Expiry date: Date and signature:
Name First name
Address
Postal code City
Optional
Age: Occupation: Teachers and students
Special field: Level:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering the optional questions above.
(*) Total cover price
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
L I S T  O F S A L E S A N D S U B S C R I P T I O N A G E N T S
Subscr ipt ion s can be paid to the s ubsc ript ion agent in you r c ountry who wil l  su ppl y rates in  local  currency on re q u e s t
A R G E N T I N A : Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UN E S C O,
Tucumán 1685, 1050 Buenos A i r e s. Fa x :3 7 1 - 8 1 9 4 .
AU S T R A L I A : Hunter Publicat i o n s , 58A Gipps Street,
C o l l i n g wood VIC 3066. Fa x : 419 7154. ISA A u s t r a l i a ,
PO Box 709,To owong QLD 4066. Fa x : 371 5566.
United Nations A s s o c. of A u s t r a l i a / V i c t o rian Div. ,
179 St George's Road,
N. F i t z r oy VIC 3068. Fa x : 481 7693.
AU S T R I A : Gerold & Co, I m p o rt & Export ,
Z e i t s c h ri f t e n / Pe ri o d i c a l s , Graben 31, A-1011 V i e n n a .
Fa x : 512 47 31 29
B E L G I U M : Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Bru s s e l s.
Fa x : 538 08 41.
B R A Z I L : Fundaco Getulio Va r g a s , Editora Divisão de Ve n d a s ,
Caixa Postal 62.591, 22257-970 Rio de Janeiro RJ.
Fa x :5 5 1 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA : Renouf Publishing Company Ltd,
5369 ch.Canotek Road,Unit 1,Ottawa,Ont K1J 9J3.
Fax:(1-613) 745 7660. Faxon Canada,POBox 2382,London,
Ont.N6A 5A7. Fax:(1-519) 472 1072.
C H I L E : U n i ve rs i t a ria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10220,
S a n t i a g o. Fa x : 681 9091.
C H I N A : China National Publicat i o n s ,I m p o rt & Export
C o rp. , PO Box 88, 16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 100020.
Fa x : 010 65063101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30,111 27
Prague 1.
D E N M A R K : M u n k s g a a r d ,N o rre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148,
DK-1016 Kobenhavn K. Fa x : 12 93 87.
F I N L A N D : S t o c k m a n n / A k ateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23,
SF-00371 Helsinki. Fa x : +358 9 121 4450.
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF-01641 Va n t a a .
Fa x : 852 7990.
G E R M A N Y: G e rman Commission for UN E S C O, C o l m a n t s t r.
1 5 , D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 63 69 12.
Uno Ve r l a g, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55,
D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 21 74 92.
G R E E C E : L i b r a i rie Kauffmann SA, M a u v r o k o r d atou 9,
GR-106 78 A t h e n s. Fa x : 38 33 967.
G UAT E M A L A : Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con
la UN E S C O, 3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1,A p a rtado Postal 2630,
G u atemala City.
HONG KO N G : Hong Kong Gove rnment Inform ation Svcs.
D e p t . , 1 Bat t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
H U N G A RY: Librotrade K F T, Pe riodical Import / K ,
POB 126, H-1656 Budapest. Fa x :2 5 6 - 8 7 - 2 7 .
I N D I A : O rient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions A c c o u n t ) ,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estat e ,B o m b ay 400 038.
Fa x : 26 91 278.
Oxford Book & Stat i o n e ry Co, Code No D 8208052,
Scindia House, New Delhi 110 001. Fa x : 33 22 639.
I S R A E L : L i t e r a ry Transactions Inc. , C/0 Steimatsky Ltd.,
PO Box 1444, Bnei Brak 51114. Fa x : 52 81 187.
I TA LY: L i c o s a / L i b r e ria Comm. Sansoni SPA ,
Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-50125 Florence. Fa x :6 4 - 1 2 - 5 7 .
J A PA N : E a s t e rn Book Service Inc. , Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
3 13 Hongo 3 Chome, B u n k yo Ku ,To k yo 113. Fa x :8 1 8 - 0 8 6 4 .
KO R E A : Korean National Commission for UN E S C O,
CPO Box 64, Seoul 100-600. Fa x : 568 7454.
L U X E M B U R G : M e s s a g e ries Paul Kraus, BP 2022,
L-1020 Luxe m b o u r g . Fa x : 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA : Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36,
26 Republic Street,Valletta CMR 01. Fa x : 24 61 82.
M AU R I T I U S : Nalanda Co. L t d . , 30 Bourbon Street,
Po rt Louis. Fa x : 212 1313.
M O RO C C O : UN E S C O, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat
Fax:212-767 03 75, Tel.:212-767 03 74/72.
M E X I C O : Librería El Correo de la UN E S C O S A , Col Roma,
G u a n a j u ato 72, Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF.
Fa x :2 6 4 - 0 9 - 1 9 .
N E T H E R L A N D S : S wets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830,
2160 SZ Lisse. Fa x :2 5 2 4 - 1 5 8 8 8 .
T i j d s c h riftcentrale Wijck B V, I n t .S u b s. S e rv i c e ,W
G r a c h t s t r a at 1C, 6221 CT Maastri c h t . Fa x : 32 50 103.
NEW ZEALAND: GP Legi s l ation Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 12418,T h o rn d o n , We l l i n g t o n .
Fa x : 496 56 98.
NORWAY : S wets Norge A S ,Ø s t e n s j ø vein 18-0606 Oslo,
PO Box 6512,Etterstad. Fax:47 22 97 45 45.
P O RT U G A L : L i v r a ria Po rtugal (Dias & Andrade Lda),
Rua do Carmo 70 74, 1200 Lisboa. Fa x : 34 70 264.
R U S S I A : Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39,
M o s c ow 113095.
SOUTH A F R I C A : I n t e rn ational Subscription Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 41095, Craighall 2024. Fa x : 880 6248.
Mast Publicat i o n s , PO Box 901, Parklands 2121.
Fa x : 886 4512.
S PA I N : Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37,
28001 Madri d . Fa x :9 1 5 7 5 - 3 9 - 9 8 .
L i b r e ria Al A n d a l ú s , Roldana 3 y 4, 410091 Sevilla.
Fa x :9 5 4 2 2 - 5 3 - 3 8 .
Los Amigos de la UN E S C O, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd.,
48011 Bilbao. Fa x :9 4 4 2 7 - 5 1 - 5 9 / 6 9
SRI LANKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam,
Gardiner Mawat h a , Colombo 2. Fa x : 44 78 48.
S W E D E N : We n n e r gren Williams A B , PO Box 1305,
S-171 25 Solna. Fa x : 27 00 71.
S W I T Z E R L A N D : Dynapresse Marketing SA, ( e x - N av i l l e
S A ) , 38 av V i b e rt , CH-1227 Carouge. Fa x : 308 08 59.
E d i group SA, Case Postale 393, CH-1225 Chêne-Bourg.
Fa x : 348 44 82.
Europa Ve r l a g, Ramistrasse 5, CH-8024 Züri c h .
Fa x : 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG ,W i s s e n s c h a f t l .B u c h h a n d l u n g,
Pe t e rs graben 31, CH-4009 Basel. Fa x : 306 12 34.
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E C O,
Chemin du Lacuez, CH-1807 Blonay. Fa x : 943 36 05.
T H A I L A N D : Suksapan Pa n i t , Mansion 9, R a j a d a m n e rn
Ave n u e , Bangkok 2. Fa x : 28 11 639.
T U N I S I A : Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de
l ’UN E S C O, 2 2 , rue de l’Angleterr e , 1000RP Tu n i s.
Fa x : 33 10 14
UNITED KINGDOM: The Stat i o n e ry Office Publicat i o n s
C t r e . , 51 Nine Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR.
Fa x : 873 84 63.
UNITED STAT E S : B e rnan A s s o c i at e s , 4611-F A s s e m b l y
D ri ve , Lanham MD 20706-4391. Fa x :4 5 9 - 0 0 5 6 .
U R U G UAY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
Maldonado 1090, M o n t e v i d e o. Fa x : 90 59 83.
V E N E Z U E L A : UN E S C O/ C R E S A L C ,E d i f. A s ov i n c a r ,
Av Los Chorr o s ,C ruce C/C A c u e d u c t o, Altos de Sebu c a n ,
C a r a c a s. Fa x : 286 03 26.
UNESCO 2000
Agenda del Patrimonio Mundial
Con bellas fotografías y comentarios sobre diversos bienes culturales o
naturales del patrimonio mundial,la Agenda 2000 le permitirá organizar su
tiempo diario y semanal y contribuir al mismo tiempo a la protección de la
memoria universal, única y diversa.
Trilingüe español, inglés y francés  | Mapa de husos horarios 
Indicativos telefónicos internacionales  | 58 fotografías en color
Éditions UNESCO
Ediciones UNESCO
UNESCO Publishing
É D I T I O N S  U N E S C O
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax : +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet : www.unesco.org/publications
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
UNESCO 2000
Agenda du patrimoine mondial
Les sites du patrimoine mondial au fil de vos semaines.
Sites historiques chargés de mémoire,merveilles de l’art du monde, témoignages 
du progrès technique, prouesses spectaculaires de la nature et faunes exceptionnelles :
à travers les photos et les courts textes synthétiques,une vision d’un monde qu’il 
nous appartient de protéger.
Trilingue : anglais/français/espagnol
Cartes des fuseaux horaires
Indicatifs téléphoniques internationaux
58 photos en couleurs
UNESCO 2000
World Heritage Desk Diary
Unique colour photographs and short legends
describing World Heritage sites that illustrate your
weekly organizer and remind us all that
protection of our common cultural and natural
diversity is paramount.
Trilingual: English/French/Spanish
Daily and weekly organizer
Time zones; telephone codes
58 colour photographs
ISBN : 92-3-003607-2
UNESCO Publishing/San Marcos
140 pp., 19 x 26 cm
120 FF / 18,29 €
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Fo c u s :
Youth and Aids: the pressure to educate
n Interview with UNAIDS director Peter Piot
n Sub-Saharan Africa in the eye of the storm
n Traditional healers  join the fight
n Southeast  Asia’s response 
n Schools and prevention: homework in store
n How discrimination slows down the effort
Features include:
n A Sunday in Berlin
n Revising the ABC of women’s literacy
n World Heritage: a concept under fire at Kakadu (Australia)
n The death penalty: abolition gains ground
n Farewell to the golden age of photojournalism
n Modern dance: inspiration without frontiers
n Interview with Spanish sociologist Manuel Castells:
citizens vs the network society
]]>
</page>
</document>
