<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="117419eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
G e t t i n g
y o u t h
t h rough the Aids crisis
BE L G I Q U E: 160 FB. C A N A DA : 5,75 $. E S PA Ñ A : 550 PTA S. F R A N C E : 22 FF NEDERLAND: 8 F L .P O RT U G A L : 700 ESC. S U I S S E : 5,50 FS. UNITED KINGDOM: £ 2 . 3 0
October 1999
PLANET
The Kakadu affair
shakes the
heritage world
CONNEXIONS
Photojournalism:
the last lap?
IN T ERV IEW
Manuel Castells:
the citizen versus
the machine
PEOPLE AND PLACES
Berlin, the island 
that was
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
52nd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian:Gianluca Formichi,Sira Miori (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e : Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UN E S C O or those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. P h o t o
captions and headlines are written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r
s t a f f. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O o r
the United Nations. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7
Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfil m s
( X e r o x ) , Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C . R .
Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d , Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - OCTOBER1999
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Pa r i s
by UN E S C O. Printed in Fr a n c e. Periodicals postage paid at
Champlain NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 10-1999-OPI 99-586 A
C o n t e n t s
October 1999
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 B e r l i n , the island that was Photos by Ute Mahler, text by Thierry Bruehl
EDITORIAL
9 Four challenges for a new world Federico Mayor
PLANET
10 The Kakadu affair shakes the heritage world Sophie Boukhari
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Questioning the ABCs of women’s litera c y Anna Robinson-Pa n t
ETHICS
37 The death penalty:abolition gains gro u n d Martine Ja c o t
39 The American exception Vicky Elliott
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 The melting pot of modern dance Jean-Marc Adolphe and Martine Ja c o t
CONNEXIONS
43 P h o t o j o u r n a l i s m :the last lap? Edgar Roskis
TALKING TO…
46 Manuel Castells: the citizen versus the machine
C o v e r : © UNESCO/Tellem
1 7 Focus Getting y o u t h
t h rough the Aids crisis
The HIV/Aids epidemic is raging in the countries of the
South—above all in sub-Saharan A f r i c a . Around half the
newly infected are aged between 15 and 24. The only
solution is to step up preventive action of all kinds. A number
of new approaches are proving their worth. Their widespread
application calls for support from the authorities at every
l e v e l .
Detailed table of contents on page 17.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 3
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
BERL IN , T HE ISLA ND
T H AT WAS w Photos by Ute Mahler, Text by Thierry Bruehl
w Mr. Mahler is a German photographer with the
Ostkreuz Agency, Berlin.Mr. Bruehl is a 31-year-old
German theatre director.
n
Berlin was once an island. I move d
from Cologne to West Berlin in 1988,
when the Wall was still standing. To
reach the city you had to travel through
the German Democratic Republic (GDR),
a country that the average West Germ a n
b o rn after the war knew less about than
France,Spain or Belgium.
Reaching West Berlin was like dri v i n g
through a tunnel.The city was  already the
largest in the Federal Republic, but so ve ry
distinct from it.This melting pot of “ c o l d -
war wa rri o rs ” , ageing activists of the 1968
r e vo l t s , politically active students and disillu-
sioned artists made a somewhat archaic
impression on the outsider.The highly-sub-
sidized showcase of the We s t e rn wo r l d ,We s t
Berlin had a pa rticularly leisurely existence.
The city landscape was dominated by bu s y
cafés serving breakfast till 6 p. m .C o m p a-
Gone are the days of We s t
Berlin’s insular tra n q u i l l i ty and
East Berlin’s state-coerced ca l m .
Today, a metropolis is rising up
on the ruins of the Wa l l
A family relaxes on the roof of its cabin in the “garden city” area of Berlin’s Ostkreuze district.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A tea-dance in the Prater fairground in former East Berlin.
City limits
Mitte
Tiergarten
Green
spaces
Lakes and
rivers
Former
Wall
BERL IN: BIRT H
A ND REBIRT H
By European standards, Berlin is a relatively young
c i ty, with its first records dating from 1234. Lo ca t e d
at the crossroads of a medieval trading route, the city
rapidly prospered and became the residence of the
p owerful Hohenzollern dynasty that reigned for over
500 years. The sprawling capital, which Chancellor
Gerhard Schroeder referred to as the “Berlin Republic”
upon taking up office there on August 23, stretches
over 800 sq. km and is located 80 km from the Po l i s h
b o r d e r. The move of the century took place over the
summer, with the transfer of parliament, ministries
and 12,000 employees from Bonn (involving no less
than 120,000 pieces of furniture, 38,000 metres of fil e s ,
carried for the most part by rail, with special road
convoys for confidential defence files and art works).
Powerful symbols of the past remain: the fin a n c e
m i n i s t ry will move into the building from which Luft-
waffe chief Herman Goering commanded the air
war, while the Ministry of Labour will be housed in the
former headquarters of Nazi propaganda chief Joseph
G o e b b e l s .
Berlin
Germany
The biggest beakfast. Each year a TV channel organizes a mammoth breakfast party outside the Olympic
Stadium, lasting from 10 a.m. until 2 the next morning. The meal costs around 10 Deutschmarks ($5).
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 5
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
A Turkish family enjoys a picnic in the park of the Schloss Bellevue, a palace which has been the official
residence of the President of the Federal Republic of Germany since 1994.
0 4 km
Tiergarten
Reichstag *
Brandenburg
Gate
Kongresshalle
Postdamer
Platz
Reclaiming its former status marks a rebirth for
Berlin, a city at the heart of the German enlighten-
ment in the 18th century when it was capital of the
kingdom of Prussia, before being proclaimed ca p i t a l
of the German Empire in 1871. During the 19 20 s ,
Berlin was one of Europe’s foremost cultural and
s c i e n t i fic centres, associated with such names as
Bertolt Brecht, Walter Gropius and Albert Einstein. But
the 19 20s were also marked by rising unemployment
and merciless inflation, facilitating Hitler’s rise to
p ow e r. In 1945, the devastated city was divided into
four zones of occupation, then partitioned into East
and West Berlin in 1949. The wall was built in August
19 61. When the city celebrated its 750th anniver-
s a ry in 19 87 on separate sides, few could have pre-
dicted that the country—and Berlin—would be reu-
n i fied two years later. In 19 91, the Bundestag chose
Berlin as capital by a narrow 18-vote majority. The city
is now one of superlatives, with three opera houses,
160 museums and an ultra-modern cinema complex
that will be ready for the next Berlin Film Festival in
Fe b r u a ry 2000. The capital is placing hope in its
n ew status to shore up its economy and become a
major transportation hub, with Europe’s largest
railway station under construction. n
A decorated stretch of the former Berlin Wall forms a multicoloured background for a swinging accordionist.
* The renovated Reichstag 
is the new seat 
of Germany’s Parliament. 
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
red to a metropolis like London or Pa ri s ,
Berlin was laid-back, q u i e t , almost sleepy
like a country village.
Bird’s eye view
of a burgeoning city
It was only by heading east in the city
t h at you started to feel uneasy—the contrast
c o u l d n ’t have been gr e at e r. After passing
the rigorous border checks and changi n g
the obligat o ry amount of curr e n cy, you step-
ped through the Iron Curt a i n — yet suppo-
sedly you were still in the same city.T h e
people all seemed so similar, with closed
expressions on their fa c e s.The pubs we r e
usually empty and you had the impression,
especially after 11 at night when the theat r e s
c l o s e d ,t h at the capital of the GDR had rol-
led up its sidewalks—but  as it turned out,
this was only on the surface.
So much for the past.I t ’s now been almost
ten ye a rs since the Wall was pulled dow n .G e r-
m a ny is reunited and so is Berlin, which is
n ow the country ’s capital with the Bundestag
(parliament) and gove rnment having move d
from Bonn this summer. I t ’s been seven ye a rs
since I moved to the Mitte District on the bor-
der of Prenzlauer Berg in East Berlin.At firs t ,
c u riosity drew me here, the wish to discove r
this “ o t h e r ” city inside my ow n .We were lucky
enough to get hold of  a wasteland whose
ow n e rs had not been clearly identifie d .Yo u n g
people transformed empty halls, fa c t o ries and
ballrooms into art associat i o n s ,t h e atre wo r k-
shops and “ i n ”p u b s. As these new ve n u e s
became more established, the arts scene shif-
ted from West to East. Just a casual stroll will
lead you to marvel at an arr ay of conve rt e d
buildings and spaces that I doubt you wo u l d
find in any other city.
Right in the centre, just about 500 metres
n o rth of the Reichstag, t e e n a g e rs have car-
ted sand up to the demolished We l t j u g e n d
( “ World Youth”) stadium on Chaussestrasse
and set up a “beach vo l l e y b a l l ”p i t c h .R i g h t
A visitor takes to the air during the annual big breakfast event outside the Olympic Stadium.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 7
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
next to the pitch—remember this is bang slap
in the city centre, s u rrounded by office blocks
and shopping malls—there’s a huge golf trai-
ning course for sports students and other
a m at e u rs.These initiat i ves aren’t motivat e d
by profit but by the simple desire to play vo l-
leyball or golf right dow n t ow n . But has
a nyone on the city council considered that
this area is going to be one of the most inve s t-
m e n t - at t r a c t i ve construction sites in the city
once the gove rn m e n t , the Bundestag and
their administrations have moved in?
Potsdamer Plat z , about 500 metres south
of the Reichstag, tells a completely different
s t o ry. Just after reunificat i o n , the Berlin
Senate thoughtlessly sold it off to Daimler
Benz and Sony. In the last few ye a rs , t h e
a r e a , which was the largest construction site
in Europe, has turned into an art i ficial com-
mercial district with new residential streets.
There used to be an insular tranquillity in
West Berlin, while a state-coerced calm pre-
vailed over East Berlin.To d ay both have fa l-
len between the cracks of the contrasting
d e velopments of volley ball courts and com-
mercial zones.
B e t ween these two areas, there is one
place from which one can pause to contem-
p l ate Berlin: the new terrace and dome of
the renovated Reichstag building provide a
b i r d ’s - e ye view, from a good distance, of this
city in full transform at i o n . If you look
t owards the west across the city centre’s
large park, the T i e r g a rt e n , little seems to
h ave changed. Early into a summer’s eve ,
you can see curls of smoke rising from
countless Berlin barbecues, most often
b e l o n ging to large Turkish families making
up for the absence of a  garden. A midday
stroll through the garden reveals another
Berlin peculiari t y : naked sunbat h e rs ri g h t
in the city centre!
N ow look east to find the view domina-
ted by a forest of cranes in action. Old bu i l-
Hard-hatted tourists take a guided visit to the Sony company’s building site on Potsdamer Platz, whose
concentration of cranes and construction works symbolizes the new Berlin.
The Oberbaumbrücke, Berlin’s longest bridge, frames a boat-load of tourists on the river Spree. A terminus
for road traffic and an underground railway line before reunification, it was reopened in 1994.
If you look towards the west
across the city centre’s large
park, the Tiergarten, little
seems to have changed…
Now look east to find the view
dominated by a forest of
c ranes in action. Old buildings
dating from the GDR era which
are not protected as historica l
monuments are being
demolished to make way for
n ew construction. 
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
An outdoor theatre session in a courtyard of the Acud building, an alternative culture centre in the Mitte (“centre”) district which once again merits its name. 
Before the Wall came down, most of the district was in East Germany.
dings dating from the GDR era which are
not protected as historical monuments —
from hotels built in the 1960s to the Fo r e i g n
O f fice—are being demolished to make way
for new constru c t i o n .The redistri bution of
f o rmer GDR propert i e s , which usually hap-
pens by selling off land and buildings to pri-
vate inve s t o rs , has provoked a ve ritable reno-
vation hy s t e ri a .You can only guess at the
façades of homes hidden behind the scaf-
folding lining nearly eve ry street in East Ber-
l i n .Where I live , houses are being renova-
ted one after the other, the facades painted
in pastel hues, with balconies added, a p a rt-
ments built into the roofs—and steadily
rising rents.
G i ven all the buzz and activity of the
c o n s t ru c t i o n , you look forward to an eve-
n i n g ’s refuge in one of the “ a l t e rn at i ve ”
e n c l aves I mentioned earlier.“ A c u d ” , for ins-
t a n c e , has such a special feel.The bu i l d i n g,
which used to house squat t e rs , is set back
from a busy street in the Mitte Distri c t ,j u s t
around the corner from my place.Acud is a
world of its ow n .B a n n e rs draping the seve r a l
s t o ries of the building announce a smorgas-
bord of cultural eve n t s. In the at t i c, you can
sit back in old car seats and discarded row s
of cinema seats to enjoy films rarely scree-
ned elsewhere. One floor down you will fin d
a small gallery, b e n e ath that a concert hall
and an A f rican restaurant.The court yard has
been taken over by fringe theatre gr o u p s
w h o ’ ve created a performance space with an
i m p r ovised nature reminiscent of the “ G l o b e
T h e at r e ” . Daily life unwinds in places like
A c u d ,which reflects the events and the meta-
m o rphosis of the New City.These are islands
in a sprawling city which only ten ye a rs ago
was an island itself. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E D I T O R I A L
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 9
n
“We can’t predict the future, but we can prepare it,” chemistry Nobel laureate Ilya
P ri g o gine once observe d . For the most part , the future will be what we make of it, e ve n
if by definition and through circumstance its fabric consists of uncertainty, change
and unpredictable creation.
Two major upheavals have profoundly changed our vision of the wo r l d .F i rs t , the scien-
tific revolution has taken us from an age of certainty and dogmatism and plunged us in
an ocean of uncertainty and doubt. We believed in the predictability of phenomena
governed by the imperious certainties of science:now the paradigms of determinism are
yielding to a concept of nature and history whose hallmark is uncertainty. Secondly, the
third industrial revo l u t i o n , based on the inform ation age and the rapid introduction of new
technology into all facets of human life, is changing the world into a global one.
Pa r a d ox i c a l l y, this globalizat i o n , far from creating a homogeneous global society,
whether desired or deplored, is subjecting societies to a logic of disintegr at i o n . It is a logi c
of selective pairi n g s , of exclusive gr o u p i n g s , of separat i o n , rifts and disaffil i at i o n .The highly
a s y m m e t ric economic success of a system which is based on the concept of liberty but has
forgotten equality and solidarity is a virtual political failure: it is coupled with an ethical
vacuum and with a complete lack of purp o s e .The power of globalization is devoid of mea-
ning.
In the face of these fractures and this va c u u m , four challenges must be fa c e d .The firs t
is that of peace, which is the precondition for successfully tackling all the others. Since the
end of the Cold Wa r , a fourth cat e g o ry of countries has appeared on the intern ational stage,
in addition to the industrialized and developing countries and those in transition. I t
comprises countries at war or emerging from conflict in which the state has often foun-
dered in genocide and intercommunal massacres.
The second challenge: will the coming century witness the onset of a new kind of pove rt y
whose victims will live side by side with unprecedented wealth? According to the United
N ations Development Progr a m m e , in 1960 the 20 per cent of the wo r l d ’s people who live
in the richest countries had 30 times the income of the poorest 20 per cent—by 1995 they
had 82 times as much income.
Sustainable development and the wise management of the global environment pose
the third gr e at challenge. E ve rywhere humanity is draining the resources which could have
fed tomorr ow ’s generat i o n .We have to find our way towards another type of deve l o p m e n t ,
one that is more economic, more intelligent, more cari n g . Because humanity has acquired
the technical capacity to commit collective suicide, it has to learn to assume the “ m a s t e ry
of mastery”,in the words of French philosopher Michel Serres.
The fourth challenge is that of the “erratic boat”syndrome.As a result of globaliza-
t i o n ,m a ny states appear to have mislaid their maps, compasses and direction-finding ins-
t ru m e n t s ,e ven the will to set a cours e .They are tossed about by the wave s , as though his-
t o ry had fallen into the hands of “ a n o nymous masters ” who can no longer be
controlled—financial markets,raw materials markets, statistics of all kinds.
But awareness of these problems has sharpened and solutions exist:hope remains. If
only we can find a way to give millions and millions of silent people a real opportunity to
use their freedom of thought and of speech, we would see the decisions of the mighty bow
to the only power that counts: that of the people.
G l o b a l i z ation must never remain confined to only the netwo r k s , t e l e c o m m u n i c a-
tions, computers, the media world or markets. It will have to be based on the consolida-
tion of a public democratic space worldwide.It is only on this condition that we will suc-
ceed in rendering globalization humane, making it a project with truly unive rsal promise,
and giving it a meaning.
This is the course we must plot for the twenty-first century. n
F OUR CH A L L ENGES 
F OR A NEW WORL D
Federico Mayor
The issues and proposals
outlined in this editorial are
developed by  Federico Mayor
in his  recently published book
Un Monde Nouveau.1
Federico Mayor has served
as Director-General of UNESCO
for twelve years. His second
mandate at the head of the
Organization comes to an end
in November 1999. 
The nomination of his
successor is a key item on the
agenda of UNESCO’s forthcoming
G e n e ral Conference 
(October 26-November 17).
Each member state has a vote
within this sovereign body 
of UNESCO.
1. Un Monde nouveau by Federico
Mayor, in collaboration with Jérôme
Bindé of UNESCO’s Analysis and
Forecasting Office (Editions Odile
Jacob, Paris). The English version, 
“The World Ahead: our Future in the
Making” is forthcoming.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Once their work was done, t h e
Aborigines say, these supernatural crea-
tures—which still have influence over the
inhabitants and the fertility of the land—
spread out over the countryside, pausing
to fight or to rest, and established a num-
ber of sacred places: the so-called places
and trails of “Dreamtime”.
But the dream stops right there.
Today, the Kakadu region is seen as the
site of one of the world’s richest deposits
of uranium. The park, the biggest in
Australia and the size of Belgi u m ,
contains an explosive mix—the familiar
t u g - o f - war between conservation and
economic development, the tricky pro-
blem of radioactive waste and the asser-
tion of indigenous peoples’ rights.
Three mining enclaves (Ranger,
Jabiluka and Koongarra) were mapped
out in the early 1970s, before the park
was created in 1979, Australian officials
point out.The Ranger mine has been ope-
rating since 1981. The Northern Land
Council (NLC), which officially repre-
sents the 16 local Aborigine tribes in the
running of the park, gave the go-ahead in
1982 for the Jabiluka mine.
A year later, things changed. A new
government was elected which curbed
uranium production and put the Jabiluka
project on hold. But “with the agreement
of the NLC and consent of the Aboriginal
traditional owners,” according to an April
1999 Australian government report, the
Jabiluka lease was transferred in August
1991 to the firm Energy Resources of
10 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
P L A N E T
T HE KA KA DU A FFA IR SH A K ES
T HE HERI TAGE WORLD 
w Sophie Boukhari
The opening of a mine in Australia’s Kakadu Park has revived international debate about the
protection of the world heritage
w UNESCO Courier journalist
‘ We are telling the truth. 
Non-Aborigine people often
doubt the sincerity 
of our cultures. But this sacred
site belongs to the Mirra r s . ’
n
How far should world heritage be
protected and who should judge?
Nearly 30 years after UNESCO adop-
ted its 1972 Convention on protecting
natural and cultural heritage sites “of
outstanding universal value”, the ques-
tion is still stirring passions. The much-
publicized row over Kakadu, which was
put on the World Heritage List in 1981, is
the most recent example.
Supporters and opponents of extrac-
ting uranium from the Jabiluka mine,
which is an enclave in the park but not
officially part of it, have been fighting it
out for the past few years. Battles between
experts, flights of rhetoric, clashes bet-
ween police and militants, press campai-
gns, special meetings of UNESCO units
and diplomatic horse-trading have all
been part of this stormy episode of world
heritage.
Kakadu is in A u s t r a l i a ’s Nort h e rn
Territory and includes a wide range of
wetland and woodland ecosystems. The
area contains many rare species and
numerous places where ancient rock dra-
wings can be seen. Cultural traditions
there go back more than 50,000 years,
making it the continent’s oldest known
human settlement. This long history
makes its “cultural landscape” a unique
s h owcase of the relationship betwe e n
humans and their environment.
Dreamtime
The scenery, plants and animals of the
region feature strongly in the religion and
traditions of the 550 or so Aborigines who
live in Kakadu.They keep a close spiritual
link to their lands, of which they are “tra-
ditional owners” under Australian law.
They believe they were put there by “spi-
rit beings” such as the rainbow serpent,
which they say appeared at the time of the
world’s creation to give the planet its
shape and existence.
Australia (ERA), although the deposit
was still not being mined.
There was another U-turn in March
1996, when the Liberal Party won natio-
nal elections and said it favoured opening
new uranium mines, including the one at
Jabiluka.After environmental surveys, the
government gave a green light to ERA,
which started digging in early 1998. It
reckons the project, which will create
jobs, could earn up to $2.5 billion in
export earnings and produce $140 mil-
lion in royalties for the Aborigines. But
the 27 members of the Mirrar tribe are
dead against the project.
A “dangerous” site
The Mirr a rs are the traditional
owners of the Jabiluka enclave.They say
the mine is dangerous for them and they
no longer feel bound by the agreement
the NLC signed in 1982.Their new lea-
der,Yvonne Margarula, has proved very
tough. They say the Aborigine leaders,
including her late father, were pushed
into the agreement by the mining compa-
nies at a time when Aborigine rights were
still little enforced and their leaders unu-
sed to “modern” negotiations.
The Mirrars also consider the expe-
rience of the Ranger mine inconclusive.
Although the Aborigines have received
r oya l t i e s , “the social situation in the
region has not improved since the 1980s,”
according to a 1997 survey commissioned
by several of the parties involved in run-
ning Kakadu, including ERA. U n l i k e
other Aborigine tribes who favour the
mining, the Mirrars say it will turn their
lives upside down and threaten their tra-
ditional subsistence economy based on
hunting and gathering. They also stress
that the site of the mine is a very sacred
spot, one of the “Dreaming” places that
are “dangerous” because disturbing them
will have terrible consequences. “We are
telling the truth,” says Margarula. “Non-
Aborigine people often doubt the sinceri-
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
It was also concerned about the mine’s
“visual impact” on the site and the dama-
ge it might cause to the daily culture and
religion of the Mirrars.
The Intern ational Council of
Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS) and
the International Centre for the Study of
the Preservation and Restoration of
Cultural Property (ICCRO M ) — t wo
advisory bodies of the World Heritage
Committee—emphasized the fragility of
the intangible heritage of the Aborigines.
“We respect Mecca and Jerusalem, so we
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 11
P L A N E T
Taken in October 1998, this aerial shot clearly shows the advanced state of construction of the Jabiluka mine by the company Energy Resources of Australia. 
The Mirrars, an Aboriginal group, maintain that the mine would seriously harm their most sacred sites.
‘ We respect Mecca 
and Jerusalem, so we should
respect these holy places too.
The problem is that nobody
has ever defined their exact
area. That’s just known to 
a few sages. They’re supposed
to keep this secret but now
they’re ready to reveal it 
to defend themselves.’
ty of our cultures. But this sacred site
belongs to the Mirrars.”
The tribe teamed up with ecology
activists to form the Jabiluka Blockade in
1996 to halt the project, and militants
have clashed with police at the site several
times. Almost two-thirds of Australians
say they are against opening the mine. An
a g gr e s s i ve intern ational campaign has
been launched and has spread around the
world.
The dispute soon landed on the desk
of UNESCO’s World Heritage Committee,
on which sit representatives of 21 coun-
tries each elected for six years. They have
been inundated by hundreds of letters
denouncing the mine’s threat to the envi-
ronment and the cultural rights of the
Mirrars. The World Conservation Union,
one of the Committee’s three advisory
bodies, confirms that the danger is real.
The Committee decided to send
experts to Kakadu in June 1998.The mis-
sion reported that there were “ s e ve r e
ascertained and potential dangers to the
cultural and natural values”of the park.It
noted the scientific uncertainty about the
impact of the mining on water supplies
and aquatic wildlife and about the long-
term effect of stored radioactive tailings.
should respect these holy places too,” says
Henry Cleere of ICOMOS. “The pro-
blem is that nobody has ever defined their
exact area. That’s just known to a few
s a g e s. T h e y ’re supposed to keep this
secret but now they’re ready to reveal it to
defend themselves.”
C l e e r e , along with the Mirr a rs and
m a ny expert s , s ays the Jabiluka enclave
cannot be dissociated from the park’s huge
n e t work of “ D r e a m i n g ” trails and places
e ven if legally it is not part of the heri t a g e
s i t e .To disturb the enclave , they say, wo u l d
t h r e aten the whole sacred netwo r k .
Cultural rights
The mission criticized the fact that the
building of the mine was presented to the
World Heritage Committee as a “fait
accompli” when the Committee should
h ave been told about it before wo r k
began, according to the terms of the 1972
Convention. It called on the Australian
government to revise the 1982 and 1991
agreements so as to protect the Mirrars’
cultural rights.
In December 1998, the Committee,
meeting in Kyoto (Ja p a n ) , urged the
Australian government to stop building
the mine and scheduled a special session
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
P L A N E T
for July 1999 to decide whether to classi-
fy Kakadu as an endangered heritage site.
The NGOs were very pleased and the
Australian government launched a coun-
ter-attack.
The Kakadu dispute has many
domestic political implications and has
set off fierce arguments with the opposi-
tion Labor Party and the Greens, who
challenge the government’s environmen-
tal policies and accuse it of jeopardizing
the process of reconciliation with the
Aborigines, which was stepped up in the
early 1990s.
The environment minister, S e n .
Robert Hill, led a strong delegation to
Paris to stress several points. First, that
Australia had no lessons to learn from
anyone.It had been among the first coun-
tries to sign the Convention in 1974 and
had changed its laws accordingly. The
mission said Australia had the biggest
expanse of world heritage sites of all the
signatory countries and that it spent $30
million a year on maintaining them.
Alcohol and Western food
Hill emphasized that the mining
enclaves were already there when the site
was put on the World Heritage List and
that Australia had said at the time it reser-
ved the right to start operations at
Jabiluka. The Ranger mine had not cau-
sed any environmental damage, t h e
Australian delegates said, pointing to
their country’s long experience in mining
and very strict regulation of it on ecologi-
cal and health grounds. Citing a number
of experts, they said environmental risk
was small and the way the radioactive tai-
lings were stored was very safe.The mine
was also hidden by hills and hardly visible
from the park. It could only really be seen
from the air and only 10 per cent of visi-
tors to Kakadu flew over the park.
Recalling that the Aborigines had ini-
tially agreed to mining at Jabiluka, the
officials said the mine did not directly
threaten the sacred sites, which were pro-
tected under Australian law.They in effect
accused the Mirrars of using their religion
as an argument to derail the project.The
April 1999 government report said it was
not until 1997 that there was a call to
extend Boyweg, one of the sacred sites,
possibly to cover the whole mining valley.
“These revisions upgraded the site from
‘sacred’ to ‘sacred and dangerous’,” it
said, adding that the new call was “not
consistent with anthropological records
or previous statements.”
The delegation also said the govern-
ment was not responsible for the slow
social and economic development of the
Aborigines and the breaking down of
their culture. “We can’t stop them using
r oyalties to buy alcohol and We s t e rn
food,” one delegation member told the
C o m m i t t e e . The Australians promised
however to revise ERA’s mining plans and
resume talks with the Mirrars to establish
their cultural rights more clearly.
Then, on July 12, 1999, Hill sprung a
surprise: the Jabiluka mine would start
operations in 2001 but just slowly, only
reaching full capacity when the Ranger
mine had virtually closed in about 10
years’ time. The government would ear-
mark $1.8 million to beef up the park’s
infrastructure and would step up efforts
to improve housing, water supply, educa-
tion, health and the job situation for the
Aborigines.
“There will be an enquiry in coming
months to assess the danger to the cultu-
ral property of the Aborigines,” he said.
“We intend to appoint a mediator bet-
ween the traditional owners and ERA.
We’re going to take a break. We recognize
the problems of mining in this environ-
ment, even if the mine is not strictly part
of the park.”
The World Heritage Committee deci-
ded not to classify Kakadu as an endan-
gered heritage site. But the Committee
said it was still “gravely concerned”by the
mine’s impact on the living cultures of
Kakadu and by the lack of dialogue and
progress in jointly managing the Mirrar
people’s cultural heritage. It said it had
s i g n i ficant reservations concerning the
“scientific uncertainties” relating to the
project and asked the Australian govern-
ment to present new reports before April
15, 2000.
The many NGO representatives who
came to UNESCO headquarters at the
same time as the delegation strongly pro-
tested.The Wilderness Society called the
Committee’s decision “a dramatic capitu-
l ation to intense pressure from the
Australian gove rn m e n t .” It and other
NGOs said the decision damaged the
The Jabiluka, Ranger and Koongarra enclaves are
not themselves classified as “world heritage” though
they are within the Kakadu park (20,000 km2).
Jabiluka
Ranger
Koongarra
0                          50 km
Kakadu park has many prehistoric rock art sites portraying mythological heroes, animals 
and objects familiar to the Aborigines.
Northern
Territory
A U S T R A L I A
Kakadu 
National 
Park
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
1972 Convention’s credibility and was the
outcome of a “dirty tricks campaign” by
Australia to win over the countries repre-
sented on the Committee.
The government had announced in
early 1999 a $600,000 lobbying campaign
to prevent Kakadu being classified as an
endangered site. It also said in June 1999
it would back the candidacy of Australia’s
former foreign minister Gareth Evans to
succeed Fe d e rico Mayor as Director-
General of UN E S C O. The W i l d e rn e s s
Society said it hoped such backing was
not simply “a way of pressuring” the cur-
rent chair of the World Heri t a g e
Committee, Japan’s Koichiro Matsuura,
who is also a candidate to replace Mayor.
A p a rt from its many political dimen-
s i o n s , the Kakadu affair has shown how
vulnerable world heritage is. H ow far must
p r e s e rvation go, when exceptional land-
scapes and monuments are increasingly
under threat , as evidenced by the lengthe-
ning list of endangered sites, which now
total 23? Can mining or other economic
projects be blocked when they endanger
sites but when the need for jobs and deve-
lopment is more and more urgent? A n d
who should decide the importance of a site
and how it should be preserve d ?
“In the begi n n i n g, world heritage wa s
d e fined in the light of We s t e rn artistic cul-
tural traditions,” s ays Cleere. “But that ’s
c h a n g e d . N ow we recognize cultures
which aren’t monuments but where the
landscape has a ve ry gr e at cultural va l u e ,
especially in A f rica and Oceania. T h e y
h ave to be protected in the name of huma-
n i t y.”
But what should be done when their
importance is not fully appreciated, inclu-
ding in their own country? How far can
the international community go to pro-
tect them? The jury is still out. Under the
1972 Convention,countries which ask for
sites to be put on the World Heritage List
must recognize them as “a world heritage
for whose protection it is the duty of the
international community to co-operate”.
But they can also interpret it as meaning
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 13
P L A N E T
‘Now we recognize cultures
which aren’t monuments 
but where the landscape 
has a very great cultural value,
especially in Africa 
and Oceania. They have 
to be protected in the name 
of humanity. ’
their sovereignty will be “totally respec-
ted”.
With Kakadu, the Australian govern-
ment has stuck to a very narrow interpre-
tation of the Convention regarding inter-
national co-operation,as embodied by the
Committee. It has refused to recognize
the Committee’s right to list the site as
endangered without its prior agreement.
Sen. Hill has also challenged the way the
Committee works by questioning the legi-
timacy of its advisory bodies, saying “the
role of so-called independent experts and
advisers is up for scrutiny in the future.”
Eco-imperialism
He has thereby given comfort to those
who oppose joint management of world
h e ri t a g e . Fo rty members of the U. S .
C o n gress have backed Australia ove r
Kakadu, denouncing UNESCO’s supposed
“eco-imperialism”.
In a petition to President Bill Clinton
on July 1, 1 9 9 9 , they said any dispute ove r
an Australian mine should be settled by
Australians “ working with their elected
l e a d e rs , not at some obscure Wo r l d
H e ritage Committee.”They urged Clinton
to ensure that the Committee did not
“ m e d d l e ” in the Jabiluka issue. The pres-
sure group also wants world heritage sites
in the United States to be controlled by the
U. S . C o n gr e s s. It said this demand was “ a
response to the Committee’s meddling in a
dispute regarding a proposed gold mine
l o c ated on pri vate property outside the
b o u n d a ry of Ye l l owstone National Pa r k ” .
The U. S . g ove rnment forced the abandon-
ment of the mining project there in 1996,
after Ye l l owstone was declared an endange-
red world heritage site.
These and many other examples show
that joint management of world heritage
is neve rtheless gaining gr o u n d . T h e
Jabiluka affair was not part of this trend,
but it has illustrated the astonishing orga-
nizational power of supporters of world
g ove rn a n c e . N G O s , politicians (the
European Parliament voted against the
mine in January 1999) and ordinary citi-
zens all over the world were inspired to
campaign to “save Kakadu”.
“We’ve never seen anything like this,”
says Sarah Titchen, who is in charge of
the case at UN E S C O’s World Heri t a g e
Centre.“Now everyone around the world
involved in world heritage knows about
Kakadu.”
Meanwhile the saga continues. T h e
M i rr a rs are now opposing, quite legally,
the building of a 15-km road through their
t e rri t o ry. The road would allow ERA to
take uranium mined at Jabiluka to be trea-
ted at the Ranger mining complex, w h i c h
would be less environmentally harmful bu t
most of all, much cheaper. ERA has eve n
hinted it will leave the Kakadu region by
2006 if the Mirr a rs do not gi ve way. I t
s h o u l d n ’t count on the rainbow serpent to
advise them to do so. n
At the White House in April 1999, Hillary Clinton welcomes Yvonne Margarula, one of the 27 Mirrar
“traditional owners” of the Jabiluka enclave who had recently received the Goldman Environmental Prize
along with Jacqui Katona, (in background) for the campaign against the uranium mine.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
healthier and better educated children, a n d
are more “ p r o d u c t i ve ” .H owe ve r , I had also
begun to realize over the ye a rs that wo m e n
attending and running literacy classes don’t
a lways share these views.The aid agencies
intent on finding linkages between wo m e n ’s
l i t e r a cy rates and development indicat o rs
such as child mort a l i t y, f e rtility and nutri t i o n
tended to use the words “ e d u c at i o n ”a n d
“ l i t e r a cy ”i n t e r c h a n g e a b l y. On a micro leve l ,
they often eva l u ated literacy progr a m m e s
through calculating the percentage of wo m e n
who went on to join savings and credit gr o u p s
or the number of families who built lat ri n e s.
My own impression was that these wo m e n
attending classes (as well as their teachers )
were less convinced about the deve l o p m e n t
outcomes associated with literacy and made
more distinction between “ l i t e r a cy”and “ e d u-
c at i o n ” . Whereas the latter took place in
schools and enabled their children to gain
good jobs and stat u s , the women regarded
14 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
n
As we slipped along the muddy pat h s,L a x m i
took her sandals off and said she was such a
green cucumber she should not be going to all
this trouble —I blame my parents, she said.1
Laxmi was on her way to an adult literacy class,
held at night in A ru t a r , her village in We s t e rn
N e p a l . Like almost all the local middle-aged
wo m e n , she had not been allowed to at t e n d
school as a youngster—though her brothers
h a d — but she now saw a chance to catch up
on reading and wri t i n g . By calling hers e l f
“ green cucumber”, she referred to the com-
mon Nepalese say i n g,“ W hy eat green cucum-
ber at the time of dying?”Becoming literat e —
like eating cucumber in this area—is both a
l u x u ry and a challenge at this late stage of life.
I had been chatting to Laxmi as a fri e n d , bu t
also as part of my research into the links bet-
ween literacy and deve l o p m e n t . For eight
m o n t h s , I lived in A rutar to try to find out why
women like Laxmi go to such trouble to learn
to read and wri t e , and what they feel they have
gained from the classes.This period was ve ry
much a two - way learning process,since Laxmi
and her friends were equally intrigued as to
w hy a We s t e rn woman with her four-ye a r - o l d
son should want to live in a village eight hours ’
walk from a road!  
Rejecting the functional approach
In many developing countri e s ,i n c l u d i n g
N e p a l , where only 14 per cent of adult
women are literat e ,l i t e r a cy is often heralded
as the entry point for involving women in
i n c o m e - g e n e r ating activities and improv i n g
their health practices. P l a n n e rs and policy -
m a k e rs in aid agencies repeatedly underline
t h at better educated mothers have fewe r ,
w The author, a British scholar from the University of
Sussex, was awarded the 1999 UNESCO International
Award for Literacy Research
QUES T IONING 
T HE ABCs OF WOMEN ’ S
L I T ERACY
w Anna Robinson-Pant
By sharing the day-to-day village life of Nepalese women who made the move to attend
literacy classes, an inquisitive researcher takes a critical look at what is being taught, and why
In the Nepalese village of Arutar, Alina holds a literacy class for mothers accompanied 
by their children.
“the adult class”as a poor substitute. I heard
them say that the cert i fic ate gi ven at the end of
the course was no use in getting a job—“it’s
just for ours e l ve s ” .O b s e rving classes, I wa s
aware of this tension between what the wo m e n
wanted and the progr a m m e ’s contents.O f t e n
this resulted in many dropping out but it wa s
also clear that some were directly challengi n g
w h at the aid agencies had on offer. In part i-
c u l a r , they rejected the “functional literacy ”
approach to convey messages and skills
directly relevant to development activities.To
m e , the picture was ve ry different from the
p a s s i ve stereotype often presented of the poor
third world woman gr ateful to learn to read
i n f o rm ation about improving her family life.
These women already knew about fa m i l y
planning and nutrition and if they did not use
this know l e g e , it was because either they had
no physical access to health facilities or they
d i s a greed with the new ideas.They had not
joined the literacy class to discuss health,f o r e s-
1) Italicized in the text are extracts from the
author’s field notes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
t ry or credit fa c i l i t i e s ,but to learn to read and
w rite—sometimes for practical purposes such
as account keeping or writing letters ,but often
just to feel educated like their husbands and
c h i l d r e n .
Ironic joking
It was the desire to reflect these wo m e n ’s
p e rs p e c t i ves that led me to conduct more
in-depth research. I chose to focus on two
contrasting programmes in differing areas
of Nepal. The classes in We s t e rn Nepal
( A rutar) were run by an intern ational aid
a g e n cy which used the literacy class as a way
of forming wo m e n ’s micro-credit gr o u p s.
The programme near Kathmandu (in Lalit-
pur district) was organized by a small local
NGO which developed its own lesson sheets
linking literacy skills to health awareness.
In both cours e s , which were run by local
s t a f f, the lessons were designed to gi ve
health messages through stories about vil-
lage women who did or did not follow
recommended practices. S e veral of the older
women challenged the messages and ironi-
cally countered the images of ignorant vil-
lage women port r ayed in the stori e s : N a n i
[ l i t e ra cy trainer] was explaining that a cert a i n
type of wo rm was on “ s a g ”(a kind of spinach)
and that if one eats it raw,one gets infe c t e d .T h e
women laughed “ W h at can you do if yo u ’re in
the fields all day cutting paddy and you see some
nice sag gr ow i n g. No time to cook it—just eat
it and get wo rm ” .Then Nani talked about hook
wo rms and said you catch this wo rm if you go to
the toilet with no shoes on.The woman laughed
and joked,“ We don’t have to wo rry about that
o n e — we don’t have any toilets to go to any-
way! We just go in the stream.” The group of
older women cackled away and then the joker
turned her attention to me:“What can I do—
e at or study? How can I cut paddy, d ry it all
d ay and then come to study? My arms are
aching, I’m tired out.”
As Nani was an older experienced fa c i-
l i t at o r , she could handle the wo m e n ’s sar-
c a s m ,s y m p athizing with those who were too
tired to study. But the younger girls who ran
classes found the discussion style daunting
and resorted to chanting of alphabet letters
i n s t e a d .A further issue was around language:
the course was written in Nepali, p a rtly in
response to the younger women who saw
flu e n cy in the latter as opening more doors
to them than their local tongue, N e wa ri .
H owe ver the older women insisted that the
up the hill for the big meeting of six wo m e n ’s gr o u p s
will you? They explained that each group had to
appoint a leader and that person had to attend a
meeting of all the local wo m e n ’s gr o u p s. . . . S a n-
s a ra wanted to send her daughter in her place as
she could read and wri t e ,but this was not allo-
we d . I later discovered that Sansara had a good
mental record of all the loans taken by gr o u p
m e m b e rs ,r e p ayment schedules and interest
owe d , but that these details were not wri t t e n
d ow n .The group members preferred their
traditional oral practices or to rely on yo u n-
ger family members , but the agency was keen
t h at they should adopt new practices of wri t-
ten account keeping and agenda setting,e ve n
if in reality these were less accurat e .
In both, the A rutar and Lalitpur classes,
the women encouraged the teachers to spend
time on chanting the texts in unison and
copying out wo r d s ,r ather than the more crea-
t i ve discussion approach in which they had
been trained.Though the women disputed
fa c i l i t at o rs conduct the class in Newa ri ,s o
in practice there was a mixture of both.
Hierarchical relationships
In A ru t a r , the literacy course was a direct
e n t ry point into wo m e n ’s group activities
around sav i n g s , credit and income genera-
t i o n .The women were expected to use the
l i t e r a cy skills to keep accounts, minutes of
meetings and write report s. Although the
women recognized that the deve l o p m e n t
a g e n cy presented a rare opportunity for secu-
ring a loan, they disputed many of its ideas
i n d i r e c t l y — e ven the assumed link betwe e n
l i t e r a cy and income generat i o n .When I inter-
v i e wed Sansara, the treasurer of the A ru t a r
wo m e n ’s group (also mother of seve n ) ,s h e
explained that her role was to look after the
record books: I asked her wh at was in them and
she said she had no idea.Other people write in it
and she just has to carry them to the meetings.
Her daughter said,you wo n ’t have to carry them
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 15
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
‘What can I do—eat or study?
How can I cut paddy, dry it all
day and then come to study?’
In Arutar, low-caste women who learn to read and write are often more strongly motivated by a desire 
to improve self-esteem than the need to keep accounts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
Sansara, the treasurer of the Arutar women’s group,
with two of her 7 children.
A LO W -CASTE LIFE
the teacher’s authority in relation to the deve-
lopment ideas, they welcomed a more hie-
rarchical relationship where they called the
teacher “ M i s s ” ,a n swered the register and imi-
t ated the kind of education they had seen in
local schools. A l i n a , the A rutar fa c i l i t at o r ,
responded by treating the women (who we r e
much older than she) as school children,e ve n
though she knew well the constraints wo m e n
faced as they were her neighbours :
A l i n a : Did you understand it? I said so
much myself I don’t know if you unders t o o d .
To m o rr ow don’t bring any children.And study
at home.
All the women laugh—no time.
A l i n a : If you can’t study,h ow can I teach?
Go home and study in any free moment yo u
have,here and there.
So what did women gain from literacy
c l a s s e s ? Although many women challenged
the teaching methods, language of instru c-
tion or course content, their ve ry presence at
the classes suggested that they still saw some-
thing to be gained from literacy.As time we n t
o n , I realized that what they valued in the
e x p e rience was less tangible than the skills of
keeping written accounts or reading about
wo rm s. When I talked to Sansara, t h e
wo m e n ’s group treasurer, she was keen to
s h ow me the part of the records book where
the women had signed their names. I noticed
on another page that there were only thumb
p rints—these were the marks of their hus-
bands who had attended in their place one
d ay.The fact that a wife could sign in place of
a thumb pri n t , when her husband could not,
i n d i c ated some important changes taking
p l a c e .S u rp ri s i n g l y,most men did not see this
as a threat to their authori t y, as they regarded
w riting as just one skill which one member of
the family needed. For the women howe ve r ,
signing their name constituted a new identity
as a “ l i t e r at e ” wo m a n .When I attended the
annual parents’ meeting at A rutar school, I
d i s c overed that the few women who came did
so partly to assert their identity in a public
arena through signing the regi s t e r.
A private space
An incident that I observed at the A ru t a r
l i t e r a cy class made me realize that some
women were beginning to use literacy for their
own purp o s e s : I sat next to Misra and glanced
at her book—she had written something about
h e rs e l f.She covered it with her hand when she saw
me looking.Alina [teacher] asked her wh at she
had written—something that was in my mind,
she answe r e d .But still she refused to show it.I wa s
i n t rigued to think that Misra—the husband
who refused to let her come to the literacy class
r e g u l a r l y — was now perhaps expressing her-
self through wri t i n g . It seemed that wri t i n g
(and reading) might provide a pri vate space
for women to reflect on their experi e n c e s.F u r-
ther proof of this are some of the articles and
s t o ries written by women published as a fol-
l ow-up to the literacy course (see box ) .
So whose agenda should determine the
kind of programmes on offer? The link being
made between literacy and inform ation on
h e a l t h ,n u t rition or income generating through
the “ f u n c t i o n a l ” approach seemed to result
p ri m a rily from the aid agencies’ need to pro-
duce quantifiable results from literacy pro-
gr a m m e s. My experiences in Nepal show that
we , the “ d e ve l o p e rs ” ,h ave not taken time to
u n d e rstand where women are starting from,
and more import a n t l y,where they want to go.
They may already have knowledge about
n u t rition and skills in chicken-rearing and
In the following story from Sangalo, a collec-
tion published by Save the Children (USA) for
n e o - l i t e rates, Sushila Uparkoti from Arutar
explains her position as a low-caste woman. 
“Nepal’s thirty-six castes are like one com-
mon flower garden.”1 Low castes are oppressed.
Women  are not allowed to go to places like
water holes, inns, temples. Our fathers and
mothers used to say that our caste was not to
study. What’s the point of studying? Can’t get a
proper job, they used to say. When they wanted
to write letters they had to go the upper castes.
They had to work all morning for others in order
to have one letter written. Seeing our own condi-
tion, we feel very worried. Even at the adult class
we had to sit apart from upper caste friends. But
after studying, we realized that one of the rea-
sons for being backward was our lack of educa-
tion. Nowadays after studying in the adult class,
we can say and write some of the things in our
minds. Nowadays, mother and father are very
pleased that we can read and write letters. They
have started sending younger brothers and sis-
ters to school. The number of low castes at
school has increased. It seems for lack of educa-
tion we were dominated and suppressed. n
1. This saying is attributed to King Prithvi Narayan Shah,
who unified Nepal in the 18th century.
they may not want to learn to write agendas
for meetings or accounts. Is the desire to wri t e
about your feelings as a low-caste woman or to
read religious books as justifiable as the more
concrete development aims? If women want to
i m i t ate a style of education provided in tradi-
tional village schools, should the aid agencies
be supporting this? 
Gains in self-confidence
The illustrations from Nepalese classrooms
d e m o n s t r ate that if women are not getting the
kind of literacy that they wa n t , they either drop
out or put pressure on class fa c i l i t at o rs to focus
on what they enjoy. Aid agencies need to
respond to this challenge and gi ve wo m e n
more direct control over what they learn and
h ow.This can be done by conducting initial
research into wo m e n ’s specific needs and inter-
e s t s : not eve ryone wants to write about their
l i ve s , just as some women may prefer to learn
h ow to write accounts.
L i t e r a cy programmes can be based on
wo m e n ’s own interests and an unders t a n d i n g
of the local context,r ather than a unive rsal ste-
reotype of an “ i l l i t e r at e ” wo m a n .E d u c at i o n
around issues such as family planning can
b e gin from a more critical approach that
encourages women to analyse their problems
and find ways to address them.L i t e r a cy - f o c u-
sed programmes are only beginning to draw
on such part i c i p at o ry planning approaches in
an attempt to provide support for wo m e n ’s
existing (rather than imagined or projected)
l i t e r a cy needs.The development outcomes of
such programmes might be more difficult to
e va l u ate than the numbers of savings gr o u p s
f o rmed or scores on a health knowledge test.
But the gains in wo m e n ’s self-confidence and
changes in social relationships should be long
lasting and eventually improve their quality of
l i f e . n
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 17
The industrialized world stands out as an excep-
tion on the global Aids map: it has managed to
stabilize the rate of new infections and to shar-
ply reduce the number of Aids deaths through new
combinations of anti-HIV drugs.But everywhere else,
the pandemic is spre a d i n g, while the sick are tre a-
ted poorly if at all. This is notably the case in South
and East A s i a ,a n d , most dra m a t i c a l l y, s u b - S a h a ra n
Africa where the epidemic rages out of control in
s e v e ral countries. Six million people were infected
with HIV in 1998. Four million of them live in sub-
S a h a ran A f r i c a . Of the two and a half million people
who died last year of A i d s, two million were A f r i c a n
( p p. 2 0 - 2 1 ) .
T h e re is no vaccine to prevent the disease, a n d
new combinations of drug therapies are too costly
for the South.The only available weapon is pre v e n-
t i o n ,which is becoming ever more vital since about
half of new HIV infections are in young people.Yo u t h
also tend to be more open than adults to learning
about safer sexual behaviour.
But for preventive education to be effective, i t
must be a priority for everyone.“ We’ve pre f e r red to
keep our eyes shut,” states Peter Piot, e x e c u t i v e
d i rector of UNAIDS (pp. 1 8 - 1 9 ) .Aids bears a heavy
symbolic burden which helps to explain why it is all
too often treated as a taboo,especially in sub-Saha-
ran Africa (pp. 2 2 - 2 4 ) . Schools are only just begin-
ning to focus on Aids education (pp. 3 0 - 2 1 ) ,which is
further complicated by the stigma surro u n d i n g
people living with the disease (pp. 3 5 - 3 6 ) .
N o n e t h e l e s s, new approaches can bear fruit.T h e
results are seen clearly in Southeast Asia (pp.2 7 - 2 8 ) ,
s p e c i fically in Thailand with the “100 per cent Condom
C a m p a i g n ”( p.2 9 ) ,as well as in sub-Saharan Africa by
way of films (p. 2 5 ) , t raditional healers 
( p.2 6 ) , Ko ranic schools (p.33) and school teachers (p.
3 2 ) . South America also offers positive signs, as seen
with a pro g ramme tailored for street children in Mexico
( p.3 4 ) .Most importantly, s t resses Piot,politicians no
longer need to be convinced of the value and neces-
sity of pre v e n t i o n .
FOCUS
Getting youth
t h rough the A i d s c r i s i s
C o n t e n t s
1 8 Seizing every opportunity
Interview with Peter Piot
2 0 F rontline Aids victims: girls in the South
1 | The African epicentre
2 2 A slow march forward
Damien Rwegera
2 5 A condom tree in Burkina Fa s o
2 6 H e a l e rs to the re s c u e
Alassane Cissé
2 | Southeast A s i a
2 7 Slowly getting bolder
Pa wana Wienrawee and Carol Livingstone
2 9 Stemming the tide in T h a i l a n d
Wanphen Sreshthaputra
3 | The classroom and
b e y o n d
3 0 P revention at school: an arduous cours e
Monique Fo u i l l o u x
3 2 A crash course for Rwandan teachers
Yvon Moren
3 3 U g a n d a : a jihad against A i d s
Maggie Keenan W h e e l e r
34 Reaching street kids on their own turf
Guillermina Nava r r o
35 The stigma of A i d s
Jean Dussault
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
Around half of all new cases of HIV infection 
in the world involve young people between 
15 and 24. Why?
Because that’s the age when you begin experi-
menting with sex and change partners most
often, which multiplies the risk of infection. Our
studies in Kenya and Zambia show 15, even 23
per cent of girls between 15 and 19 are HIV-posi-
tive, compared with only three to four per cent of
boys. Girls are more vulnerable for both biologi-
cal reasons (the female genitals are more suscep-
tible to infection than those of males and are par-
ticularly vulnerable in the case of girls because
they have not yet developed) as well as socio-cul-
tural ones (whether they are won over by gifts or
are the victims of force, they often have as part-
ners adult men who because of their age are more
likely to be HIV-positive than boys).
The roots of the problem lie mainly in pover-
ty and male chauvinism.Hence the importance of
educating boys, who have to be taught that their
worth doesn’t depend on the number of women
they’ve seduced. We have to change the whole
“sexual culture” as it were. But we have to be
humble: we’re not going to change the world in
the space of a few years.
What’s the impact of preventive education on
young people’s sexual behaviour?
Youth are more receptive to prevention mes-
sages and go on to adopt a more responsible atti-
tude to sexuality than adults. In countries where
there’s been a good response to prevention cam-
paigns, we’ve seen a very marked drop in the rate
of infection among the 15 to 24-year-olds. In the
past eight years, the rate in Ugandan urban areas
has fallen 40 per cent. In Zambia, it has dropped
most markedly among schoolchildren.
All this shows that education has an impor-
tant role to play. Even though it’s true that many
children in developing countries don’t go to
school, the majority nevertheless pass through
school. The opportunity must be seized to give
them an education about Aids adapted to their
age-group, right from the start of primary school.
Some people still fear this will encourage children
to have sexual relationships, but has anyone ever
waited for lessons before starting their sexual life?
It’s been statistically proven that preventive edu-
cation makes people much more sexually respon-
sible, namely by having sexual relationships later
and using protection.
Is Aids education given the attention it deserves in
schools?
Quite honestly, no, and not even in industria-
lized countries. But extraordinary work is being
done in some places. Brazil, for example, has a
very good programme, which begins in primary
schools and is backed by UNESCO. Zimbabwe too,
where UNICEF is helping. Ugandan schools have
introduced a new curriculum subject called
“straight talk” in which pupils comment on daily
newspaper sections written specifically for young
people. The experiment is spreading in Kenya
and a few other countries, but there’s a long way
to go before it becomes general practice.
I myself plan to strengthen my contacts with
education officials, government ministries and
teachers’ unions. Curricula which include the
Aids question have been designed, tested and
then not applied, like many good intentions. It’s
no longer a question of developing teaching mate-
rials, but of making use of them.
The United Nations General Assembly recently
declared its goal to cut the rate of new infection
among young people by a quarter in the countries
hardest hit by the epidemic. Isn’t this overly
ambitious?
Ambitious yes, but not unrealistic. Experience
has shown it can be done if you get all sectors of
society involved, starting with youth. UNAIDS
works a lot with young people. We design aware-
ness campaigns not just with young staff mem-
bers in their early 20s but also after consulting
teenagers whose ideas are always, I must say,
quite refreshing.
Since 1997, we’ve had an annual World Aids
Campaign which targets young people.This year,
the young Brazilian footballer Ronaldo has
agreed to be involved. His words carry much
more weight than mine among the youth of poor
communities like those where he grew up. The
popular Ugandan singer Philly Lutaaya also wor-
ked with us before he died of Aids. If all the
famous people who are HIV-positive admitted the
Seizing every o p p o r t u n i t y
Fighting Aids involves no less than changing our whole sexual culture. Peter Piot, E x e c u t i v e
D i rector of UN A I D S, s t resses the impact of preventive education on young people’s behaviour
Has anyone ever waited for
lessons before starting their
sexual life? It’s been statistically
p roven that preventive education
m a kes people much more
sexually re s p o n s i b l e, namely by
having sexual relationships later
and using pro t e c t i o n
If scientists fail to cure
A i d s, the epidemic will
become a soft nuclear
bomb on human life.
Kenneth Kaunda,
former president of Zambia
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 19
Getting youth through the Aids crisis
fact, as Lutaaya did,it would have a great impact.
But they often keep quiet and I understand their
fear of being rejected if they admit it. Aids is
Janus-faced, and each side is just as terrifying as
the other—one is the virus that kills and the other
is the society, which also kills.
How can the stigma be fought?
That’s my latest priority, in fact. To be prag-
matic, we send volunteers who are open about
having HIV to work in schools, hospitals, govern-
ment ministries and other key places. T h i s
“public” approach to Aids has a much greater
effect than any speech about respecting the indi-
vidual. These volunteers are already working in
Malawi, Zambia, Thailand, South Africa and
Burundi and soon in Burkina Faso. I’d like to
spread this strategy all over the world, but we
don’t have the resources and it’s very hard to find
people willing to take on such a mission.
Why do you think Aids is still largely cloaked in
silence 20 years after it appeared?
The taboo surrounding Aids is a universal
phenomenon. In most societies, talking about
sexuality isn’t easy, even between two partners.
Also, the impact of Aids on societies wasn’t felt as
strongly 15 years ago as today. People also go into
denial, which is an instinctive reaction to danger.
Read The Plague by Albert Camus again.Another
natural reaction is to say that it’s only something
that happens to others. So for 20 years,we’ve pre-
ferred to keep our eyes shut. Uganda, Senegal
and Thailand are among the very few countries
whose political leaders have reacted in a timely
manner. It isn’t just a matter of poor countries
either: U.S. President Ronald Reagan never pro-
nounced the word “Aids” in public.
But this year,the dialogue has started going in
the other direction. Until now, I had to convince
political leaders that the situation was serious in
their countries. Now it’s they who are taking the
initiative.That’s a big step forward.
How do you explain this turn-around?
First,the impact of Aids on societies has beco-
me so great it can’t be ignored any longer, despi-
te the tremendous human capacity for denial.
Then, without boasting, I have to say that the
concerted action of the United Nations has hel-
ped a lot. We’re seizing every opportunity to
spread the message about Aids by going all out to
increase the number of sectors we work with—
groups like boy scouts,women’s movements,pea-
sants and others. I myself meet heads of state,
mayors of big cities, ministers of finance, business
leaders, army generals, musicians, footballers,
bishops and imams—anyone who can influence
members of a society. Religious leaders can be a
big obstacle to a prevention campaign but I most-
ly consider them to be allies.
Are they really allies?
I’ve noticed that those religious leaders in
close contact with the population—the parish
priest, the village imam—are the most receptive
to prevention campaigns, including encouraging
the use of condoms, which is the most delicate
aspect.The further you go up the hierarchy, the
harder dialogue becomes. Nevertheless, a Vatican
envoy attended our March 1999 conference in
Buenos Aires about involving priests in the fight
against Aids. The message of the conference was
clear: sex education at school is vital. Only a few
years ago, this was inconceivable. n
Interview by Jasmina Sopova,
UNESCO Courier journalist
U N A I D S :
w o r k i n g
t o g e t h e r
The Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS
(UNAIDS),launched in January 1996,is an innovative
partnership that brings together the efforts and resources
of seven UN organizations, namely the United Nations
Development Programme (UN D P) , the United Nations
Population Fund (UNFPA),the United Nations Children’s
Fund (UNICEF),the World Health Organization (WHO),the
United Nations Educational, S c i e n t i fic and Cultural Orga-
nization (UN E S C O) , the United Nations International Drug
Control Programme (UN D C P) and the World Bank. Th e
first programme of its kind in the UN system,it aims to
help mount and support an expanded response engaging
the efforts of many sectors and partners from government
and civil society. n
Internet:http://www.unaids.org
A World Aids Day march in San Salvador.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
Facts about A i d s
Aids—acquired immunodeficiency syndrome—is
caused by the human immunodeficiency virus
( H I V ) , which weakens the body’s immune system.
Once they have an established HIV infection, i n d i v i-
duals are infected for life and will probably succumb to
serious opportunistic infections caused by the weake-
ning of their immune system. Treatment with antiretro-
viral drugs can slow the progression of HIV infection
but these expensive medications are not available to
most people in the developing world, who often lack
access even to drugs that combat opportunistic infec-
t i o n s. In individuals who do not get antiretroviral the-
r a p y, the time between infection with HIV and the
development of the serious illnesses that define Aids is
around eight years, and most patients do not survive
much more than two years after their onset.
HIV spreads through unprotected sex (intercourse
without a condom), transfusions of unscreened blood,
contaminated needles (most frequently for injecting drug
u s e ) , and from an infected woman to her child during pre-
gnancy, childbirth or breastfeeding.
HIV is a slow-acting virus.The majority of infected indi-
viduals look healthy and feel well for many years after
i n f e c t i o n ; they may not even suspect they harbour the
virus, though they can transmit it to others. Conservative
UNAIDS estimates are that 90% of all HIV-infected people
worldwide do not know they have the virus. A laboratory
blood or saliva test is the only certain way to determine
whether an individual is HIV-positive. n
Source:UNAIDS
Global estimates of the HIV/Aids epidemic, D e c e m b e r
1 9 9 8
People newly infected with HIV in 1998
Total 5 800 000
Adults 5 200 000
Women 2 100 000
Children under 15 590 000
Number of people living with HIV/Aids
Total 33 400 000
Adults 32 200 000
Women 13 800 000
Children under 15 1 200 000
Aids deaths in 1998
Total 2 500 000
Adults 2 000 000
Women 900 000
Children under 15 510 000
Total number of Aids deaths since the beginning 
of the epidemic
Total 13 900 000
Adults 10 700 000
Women 4 700 000
Children under 15 3 200 000
Source:UNAIDS
Some two decades after the virus started to
s p r e a d , HIV/Aids is a gr owing crisis dispro-
p o rt i o n ately weighing on youth and on the
d e veloping wo r l d .About a third of the 33.4 million
people world-wide living with HIV are aged 15-24,
and half of all new HIV infections occur among this
gr o u p. F i ve young people are infected eve ry minute.
F u rt h e rm o r e , studies in A f rica show girls have four
or more times the infection rate of boys.
The developing world accounted for 95%,and
Sub-Saharan A f rica alone for 70% of new HIV
infections in 1998.Aids is now the biggest killer in
A f ri c a . Nine out of ten HIV infections among chil-
dren under 15 last year occurred in A f ri c a .I n fa n t
m o rtality in some A f rican countries rose as much
as 150% in 1998 alone. Life expectancy is fa l l i n g
by as much as 20 ye a rs as a result of A i d s.The cri s i s
is also having an impact on economic deve l o p m e n t ,
with many A f rican companies saying Aids illness
and death costs sometimes total more than corpo-
r ate profits. Elsewhere too the crisis is gaining
gr o u n d . In A s i a , of the 7.2 million people living with
Aids,a fifth were infected last year.
W h at is perhaps most startling is that HIV is
expected to gather force as a killer. In 1990 it
accounted for 8.6% of adult deaths from infectious
diseases in the developing wo r l d .By 2020, t h at fig u r e
is expected to rise to 37.1%. n
F rontline Aids victims:
girls in the S o u t h
Yo u t h , in particular girls, and developing countries bear the brunt of Aids’ virulent spre a d
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 21
Getting youth through the Aids crisis
Regional estimates of the number of people living with H I V/ A i d s
Regional estimates of the number of people living with H I V/ A i d s
Adults (15-49 years % of Epidemic Main modes
of age) living with HIV positive started of transmission*
HIV/Aids (% of total adults who are for adults living
population) women with HIV/Aids
Sub-Saharan Africa 8 50 late ’70s – early ’80s Hetero
North Africa and the Middle East 0.13 20 late ’80s IDU, hetero
South and East Asia 0.69 25 late ’80s Hetero
East Asia and the Pacific 0.068 15 late ’80s IDU, hetero, MSM
Latin America 0.57 20 late ’70s – early ’80s MSM, IDU, hetero
Caribbean 1.96 35 late ’70s – early ’80s Hetero, MSM
Eastern Europe and Central Asia 0.14 20 early ’90s IDU, MSM
Western Europe 0.25 20 late ’70s – early ’80s MSM, IDU
North America 0.56 20 late ’70s – early ’80s MSM, IDU, hetero
Australia and New Zealand 0.1 5 late ’70s – early ’80s MSM, IDU
Total 1.1 43
Source:UNAIDS, Geneva.
* MSM(sexual transmission among men who have sex with men),IDU (transmission through injecting drug use),Hetero (heterosexual transmission).
= 50 000 persons
= 50 000 persons 
infected in 1998
Sub-Saharan AfricaLatin America
North America Western Europe
North Africa and
the Middle East
Eastern Europe
and Central Asia
Caribbean
East Asia and the Pacific
Australia
and New Zealand
South and East Asia
n Aids deaths n Number of people living with HIV/Aids
1980 1985 1990        1995       1998 1980 1985 1990              1995 1998
1 688 136 259 2 662 566
9 745 177
23 429 905
33 401 199
87 694
554 251
1 646 877
2 470 234
22 500 000
4 000 000
1 400 000
160 000
330 000
45 000
890 000
44 000
500 000
30 000
270 000
80 000
210 000
19 000 6 700 000
1 200 000
560 000
200 000
12 000
600
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
1 The African epicentre
A slow march f o r w a rd
w Damien Rwegera
In the eye of the global Aids epidemic,Africa has no choice but to
o rganize a massive, m u l t i - p ronged prevention campaign which mobilizes
the broadest range of players
The Aids epidemic raging in sub-Saharan A f ri c a
is one of the wo rst plagues of recent centuri e s.
The region has only a tenth of the wo r l d ’s
p o p u l at i o n , but is home to two-thirds of the total
number of people with HIV/Aids.Two-thirds of
those infected in 1998 live in the region and the
s i t u ation is “out of control” in some countri e s ,a c c o r-
ding to UNAIDS.
Sub-Saharan A f rica is the poorest region of the
p l a n e t , a fact which deepens the cri s i s. In this
c o n t e x t ,p r e vention is the only way out and to dat e ,
it has been glaringly inadequat e .H owe ve r , the qua-
l i fied success of preve n t i ve measures in some A f ri c a n
c o u n t ries demonstrates that actions can be as effec-
tive in stemming the crisis there as anywhere else.
The main problem lies in cultural attitudes to
i l l n e s s , pain and deat h . A f ricans tend to regard
disease not as something phy s i o l o gical but as the
result of social or religious fa c t o rs , such as a curs e ,
poisoning or divine punishment.
More than any other disease, Aids is associa-
ted with death and sex. With sperm and vaginal
fluids. It is passed on by blood and a mother’s
milk. All this gives it powerful symbolism while
making it a veritable taboo leading people to go
so far as to deny its existence. Out of derision,
some young people in francophone countries say
that Sida, the French acronym for the disease,
stands for Syndrome Invented to Discourage
Lovers (in French). They are not convinced by
scientific explanations of the disease especially
after the bogus reasons trumpeted at the begin-
ning of the epidemic: namely that A f ricans we r e
responsible for spreading the disease because they
“had sex with green monkeys”. A f ricans responded
in kind, claiming that “Aids comes from white
p e o p l e , especially white women who kiss their dogs
and sleep in the same bed with them”.
The main goal of preventive education is to
fight such ignorance and fantasies. The second
goal—to explain how to protect against it—runs
up against a similar problem of perception:
condoms are a “white people’s thing”. Moreover,
they are so expensive that sometimes a person has
to choose between buying something to eat or
having safe sex. For an African earning about $50
a month,paying nearly 20 cents for four condoms
is out of the question.
The effectiveness of preve n t i ve education has
to take into account these cultural perceptions and
m i s u n d e rstandings and respect social stru c t u r e s. I n
A f ri c a , e ven in cities, adolescents just cannot talk
to their parents about sex. Such discussion is limited
to people of their own age and sex.So Aids educa-
tion must follow suit: wo m e n , men and teenagers
each have to be approached in different ways.
Adults have to drastically change acquired
h a b i t s.Te e n a g e rs have to be persuaded to adopt safe
sexual habits, a much easier task.Yet this is a long-
t e rm job operating on three leve l s — awa r e n e s s ,i n f o r-
mation and education.
Despite meagre resources, A f rican countri e s
h ave made gr e at efforts to raise awareness and
spread inform at i o n . Po s t e rs and radio are the favo u-
red methods. Pe r f o rming arts presentations and
advertising are also often used. Experience shows
t h at condom sales increase in the ten days follow i n g
an awareness campaign. But these campaigns must
happen more frequently to be effective because repe-
tition is the key.
Reaching young people
in hierarchical societies
E d u c ating young people is still the main chal-
lenge because they are the chief victims of A i d s.
Around half of the newly-infected people wo r l d w i d e
are between the ages of 15 and 24. In 1998, 90 per
cent of the wo r l d ’s infected people under 15 lived in
sub-Saharan A f rica where there is a tendency to
engage in sexual relations at a relat i vely young age.
These relations are often forced, with 12 and 13-
year-old girls often the victims of sexual abu s e .
w Rwandan anthropologist.
Member of Pan-African Aids
Organization (Paris, France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 23
B i o é t h i q u e : la tentation de l’enfant parfaitGetting youth hr ugh the Aids crisis
The world spends $1.5
billion each year on
Aids prevention.
Pa r a d o x i c a l l y, o n l y
$200 million a year are
spent in sub-Saharan
A f r i c a , which has the
highest concentration
of HIV carriers. A f r i c a n
states provide 10 per
cent of this amount.
This is a mark of their
p o v e r t y, but also a
mark of their
i n s u f fic i e n t
commitment to a
prevention policy
D r. F rançois Chièze,
Managing director of 
the Pan-African A i d s
O rg a n i z a t i o n
Schools would seem to be the ideal place to
reach youth and most countries have at last inclu-
ded preve n t i ve education in the school curri c u l u m
(see pp. 3 0 - 3 1 ) . But in sub-Saharan A f ri c a ,a b o u t
t wo-thirds of all pri m a ry school-age children and
80 per cent of secondary school-age children do not
go to school.So while schools must be part of pre-
ve n t i o n , it will take some time before they have a
real impact. In A f ri c a , more than any other regi o n ,
the only way to attack the epidemic is to mobilize
all the major actors in society at eve ry leve l — t h e
g ove rn m e n t , civil society, local communities and
foreign aid sources.The higher placed they are, t h e
gr e ater impact they will have gi ven the fact that A f ri-
can societies are so hierarchical.
At the top are those with political powe r.T h e y
bear considerable responsibility for the spread of
the pandemic.Their only excuse for inaction is that
the continent is beset with terrible problems. I n
c o u n t ries at wa r ,Aids is hardly a pri o ri t y.And when
t h e r e ’s no wa r ,p ove rty is people’s main concern —
not A i d s. After all, the disease has never come up
as an issue at election time.
The self-criticism of the continent’s heav y-
we i g h t , South A f ri c a , has had quite an impact. P r e-
sident Thabo Mbeki publicly admitted when he
launched the Partnership Against Aids project on
October 9, 1998,that “for too long we have closed
our eyes as a nation, hoping that it was not really
true”, while “every day another 1,500 South Afri-
cans were infected in South A f ri c a .” He appealed to
young people and to the population at large to use
condoms.
A campaign will obviously not work unless the
b attle against Aids is a top pri o rity for gove rn m e n t s
and gi ven ongoing at t e n t i o n .This has happened
in Uganda which has been the most successful A f ri-
can country in terms of Aids prevention.The ini-
t i at i ve for the all-out battle came from President
Yowe ri Musewe n i , who understood the extent of
the disease from the day he came to power in 1986:
out of about 60 army officers sent for military trai-
ning in Cuba,where Aids tests are compulsory, 20
were HIV- p o s i t i ve .Without further ado, he ear-
marked funds for a large-scale national prevention
c a m p a i g n . Uganda has since made considerable
g a i n s. For example, b e t ween 1989 and 1995, t h e
p r o p o rtion of teenage girls (between 15 and 19)
who remained virgins increased from 26 per cent
to 46 per cent.They had the courage to refuse sexual
relations.
In Senegal, p r e vention has also been boosted by
HIV/Aids in sub-Saharan A f r i c a
A poster from Burundi.
The five hardest hit countries . . .
Z i m b a b w e: out of a population of 11.7 million, 1.5 million
people live with HIV/Aids. The HIV-infection rate among
adults* stands at 24.84%.
Botswana: out of a population of 1.5 million, 190,000
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 25.1%.
N a m i b i a: out of a population of 1.6 million, 1 5 0 , 0 0 0
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 19.94%.
Z a m b i a: out of a population of 8.5 million,770,000 people
live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 19.07%.
S w a z i l a n d: out of a population of 900,000, 84,000 people
live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 18.05%.
* The term “adults”refers to the 15-49 age group
. . . and the five least hit
Madagascar: out of a population of 15.8 million,8,600
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 0.12%.
M a u r i t a n i a: out of a population of 2.4 million, 6 , 1 0 0
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 0.52%.
Equatorial Guinea: out of a population of 420,000, 2 , 4 0 0
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 1.21%.
N i g e r: out of a population of 9.8 million, 65,000 people live
with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 1.45%.
M a l i: out of a population of 11.7 million, 89,000 people live
with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 1.67%.
Source: UNAIDS, 1998.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
I t ’s an object of our
t i m e s. . .
An indispensable
auxiliary of amorous
e n c o u n t e r s. A
c u m b e r s o m e
companion of passing
p l e a s u r e s. Banal and
n e c e s s a r y : the condom.
F rom Sortons couverts!
(“Go Out Pro t e c t e d ” ) ,
L i b r i o / S i d a c t i o n , Pa r i s, 1 9 9 9
t o p - l e vel political decisions, with clear results. I n
1998, the government of Côte d’Ivoire earmarked
$1.6 million for a prevention campaign and recently
the president set up a nationwide fund,containing
an equal sum for taking care of the ill.This repre-
sents a huge amount of money in Africa.
B i l ateral and multilateral aid agencies are more
likely to help countries which make their own fin a n-
cial commitments to preve n t i o n .B e yond that ,i n t e r-
n ational organizations like UNAIDS,WHO and
UNESCO can and must convince African leaders of
the extent of the problem. In 1996, the countries of
A f rica as a whole, except for Botswa n a , K e nya ,
M a l awi and Uganda, spent less than $1 million each
on Aids prevention.
S p i ritual leaders and traditional chiefs, w i d e l y
respected and obeyed across the continent, r e p r e-
sent another key set of actors. Since the epidemic
s t a rt e d , r e l i gion has hindered rather than helped
the fight against A i d s. A devout Catholic will not
use a condom if he is told it is a sin,any more than
a Muslim will if the imam does not even deign to
talk to him about Aids.
The lessons learned from a conference on
Aids held in Dakar (Senegal) in 1997 are revea-
ling. About 300 participants from Africa, Europe
and the Middle East, represented the two main
r e l i gions of those regions—Islam and
Christianity. Just getting people together to talk
about such a delicate topic was an achievement.
After some stormy discussions, everyone agreed
that Aids was a disease and had to be viewed in
strictly medical terms. If it did not remove all the
obstacles to prevention campaigns, the conferen-
ce at least managed to persuade participants to
stop opposing the mere idea of them. Across the
continent, religious leaders are now starting to
join the fight against Aids—for example, Caritas
International, one of the world’s biggest networks
of NGOs, as well as the group Christians and
Aids and Uganda’s Islamic Medical Association
(see p. 33) have become involved.
With doctors powerless to cure or effectively
treat the disease, people are turning to the sym-
bolic authority of the ancestors, embodied by tra-
ditional chiefs. They are directly concerned by
preventive education because some customs run
the risk of spreading Aids—such as marrying the
sister of one’s late wife or the brother of one’s
dead husband and taking part in certain ceremo-
nies which involve washing the dead.There is an
alternative to every custom, as long as the head of
the family accepts it. If the traditional chiefs were
to decide to do more to help prevention, they
could speed up the process of changing certain
practices.
Risky customs
Equally formidable are the traditional healers
and practitioners , who have a leading part to play
since most A f ricans consult them. N i g e ria has
700,000 such healers but only 20,000 doctors for
120 million inhabitants. I nvolving the healers in the
fight against Aids not only draws on their prestige
but also lessens the harm they can do: namely by
admitting the disease exists and claiming they can
heal it.Va rious projects have targeted healers by pro-
viding them with training and instilling them with
a gr e ater sense of responsibility. For example, i n
1995-96 the Aids Fo u n d ation of South A f rica was in
contact with about half a million healers and 650
a s s o c i at i o n s , all of which admitted that even if they
could sometimes treat the symptoms, they could
not cure the disease. Before that , 75 per cent of
them said the opposite.
The Zimbabwe National Traditional Healers
Association, with 50,000 members, has over the
past decade run about 500 workshops which deal
with all social groups (teenagers, polygamous
families, healers, traditional chiefs) as well as
members of parliament. The aim is to make
people aware of the dangers involved in traditio-
nal rites such as circumcision, female excision
and cures involving incision.
P r e ve n t i ve education in A f rica remains the
only way of combating A i d s , but prevention must
not exclude medical treat m e n t .A f ricans cannot be
told forever that “medicine is for others bu t
condoms are for yo u ” . There is no underestima-
ting the importance of a French initiat i ve in May
1 9 9 8 , which was favourably received by the G8
(Group of Eight Industrialized Nat i o n s ) , and led
to the creation of the Intern ational T h e r a p e u t i c
S o l i d a rity Fund. S u p p o rted by rich countri e s , t h e
fund aims to make anti-Aids drug treat m e n t s
more available in developing countri e s. B e t t e r
access to treatment will not only help save pat i e n t s
but reinforce prevention effort s. E x p e rience has
s h own that infected people with no hope of treat-
ment are more likely to have unprotected sex than
those with medical support . n
A Kenyan poster.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 25
Getting youth through the Aids crisis
A fter she heard from a cousin in Ouagadougou
(Burkina Faso) about the dangers of cat c h i n g
A i d s , one of Konat é ’s two wives asked him to
wear a condom. The dismayed Konaté told his
f riends about the request and they made fun of him.
His pride was so wounded that he became impotent
and even his mistress couldn’t solve the problem.
E ventually the village witch-doctor interve n e d
and told Konaté his only hope was to say a prayer at
the foot of the tree on which the “ t h i n g ” ( t h e
condom) supposedly gr e w. So Konaté went off to
look for the tree.
The film K o n at é ’s T h i n g, which came out this
ye a r , tackles Aids prevention in a light-hearted way,
by laughing at male sexual pride and odd customs.
Fanta Regina Nacro, the fil m ’s 36-ye a r - o l d
Burkinabé director,explains her approach:
Why did you use humour to handle such a
distressing topic?
Being alarmist about Aids wo u l d n ’t have helped
m u c h . People run away from painful images. B u t
we all like recalling funny episodes.
As an A f rican wo m a n , I’m particularly concer-
ned about A i d s. I wanted to use the wonderful means
of communication I had—film—to help prevent the
d i s e a s e . I know how my people think and it wo u l d n ’t
h ave worked to say to them in a moving or peremp-
t o ry way “ Wear a condom!”The whole weight of tra-
dition would have come down on me.So I took ano-
A condom tre e
in Burkina Fa s o
Fighting prejudice with laughter, film director Fanta Regina Nacro 
gets a strong message acro s s
ther tack.Through laughter, you can fight prejudice
more easily.
You raise a number of questions yet you don’t deal
directly with young people even though they have
been hit the hardest by the epidemic.
I’m the first to admit this.But try and tell that to the
N ational Centre for Aids Preve n t i o n . I was told that
it would be “ d r a g ging them down into debauchery.”
They were so insistent that I gave up.The issue reeks
of hy p o c ri s y. Health offic i a l s , community organiza-
t i o n s ,e ve ryone invo l ved in the fight against A i d s ,t h e y
all avoid talking about and to young people. Fo rt u n a-
tely children are present during awareness campaigns
in the villages and no one chases them away. So they
l e a rn how to use condoms, just as they can if they see
my fil m .
We don’t have the right to leave children in the
dark about A i d s. Right now, I’m trying to get the
film more widely distri buted so most young people
in Burkina Faso can see it. I t ’s been shown on nat i o-
nal television but not eve ryo n e ’s got a TV set.A tra-
velling cinema is in the wo r k s , along with public pre-
sentations and discussions to be held in provincial
towns and villages.
How do you gauge your success?
In A f rican countri e s , where there aren’t any ve n-
ding machines for contraceptive s ,p e o p l e — e s p e c i a l l y
young people—don’t dare to go and buy them.We
d e c i d e d , as part of a promotion campaign, to either
hand out a free box of contraceptives or the equiva-
lent of one dollar.When a fa rm - worker was handed a
b ox of condoms, he was visibly delighted.When he
was gi ven money, he was gr ateful but nothing more.
With a dollar,he could buy five boxes but he wo u l d n ’t
dare do so.
Since the film has been shown in Burkina Fa s o,
kids have been asking in the market simply for
“ K o n at é ’s thing” and that ’s what they get. T h i s
a c h i e vement is much more important to me than
any prize the film has won.
Interview by Jasmina Sopova n
HIV/Aids in
Burkina Fa s o
Out of a population of
11 million, 370,000
live with HIV/Aids. Among
adults in the 15-49 age
group, 7.17% are HIV-
infected,along with
22,000 children under the
age of 15. The epidemic
has so far claimed a total
of 250,000 lives.
Source: UNAIDS, 1998.
In Ethiopia a puppet theatre is used as part of an Aids prevention campaign.
In African countries where there
a ren’t any vending machines for
c o n t ra c e p t i v e s, p e o p l e —
especially young people—don’t
d a re to buy them
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
“You could see the bones sticking out under
my skin and I was almost blind,” s ay s
Amadou Sow. “I’d had Aids for 12 years
when I decided to see the m a l a n go h e a l e rs. M a l a n go
means ‘ w h at is needed and is suitable.’ I came back
feeling better. Since then, I have recovered my sight
and gained we i g h t .”While Sow is a “ m i r a c u l o u s ”5 0
years or so old,he knows that he is not completely
cured of Aids.
In Senegal’s Fatick region, 150 kilometres
from the capital,Dakar,the Malango Association,
founded in 1983, has 450 members who are tra-
ditional healers (a fifth of them women) and work
in 264 villages. Starting from the belief that natu-
re has a cure for every ailment, they use mainly
powders, potions and plant extracts. But invoking
the spirits is also part of traditional therapy. In the
animist view of the world,humans are considered
a link in the cosmic chain who summon the lower
orders (minerals, plants and animals) to join the
higher ones (spirits, ancestors and gods). All of
them must be called on in the hope of finding
cures.
Unlike many of their counterp a rts in other
countries, the association’s healers don’t promise
their patients they will be cured of Aids.They suc-
cessfully treat some of the symptoms (diarr h o e a ,
vomiting and leukaemia) and ease sufferi n g .W h e n
the treatment is ineffective , they steer their pat i e n t s
towards health practitioners who work with them.
So far they have treated more than 10,000 people
from A f rica (including Senegal), Europe and the
United States.
The first stop
on the road
Three quarters of all Senegalese go to traditio-
nal healers. “In some areas, there’s one doctor for
e ve ry 100,000 people and one traditional healer
for eve ry 1,000,” s ays Dr. E rick Gbodoussou, h e a d
of the Malango Association’s experimental centre.
Gbodoussou trained in We s t e rn medical schools
but is convinced traditional healers can not only
effectively fight some diseases, but can also play a
useful role in prevention.“When I treat someone
with Aids,I discourage them from having sex with
their part n e rs ,” s ays one of the associat i o n ’s healers ,
a man in his 70s. “I tell them they can infect their
partners if they don’t do what I say.”
w Journalist with Sud
Quotidien,Dakar (Senegal)
In Dakar’s Tilène market, traditional healers
have been interested in helping to raise awareness
about the disease.“Aids exists and we have to dis-
cuss it with young people who are sexually acti-
ve,” says Ibra Niokhobaye Diouf. Do the ill
people dare talk about their sex lives? “Ten out of
the average 15 patients I see each day raise the
subject openly,” he says. “I use each occasion to
make them understand they have to protect
themselves from this disease that everyone talks
about so much.” With more healers like Diouf,
the message about Aids reaches the whole popu-
lation by word of mouth.
In the village of Sambé, in the Diourbel
region,healers attended seminars on Aids in 1998
organized by the NGOs Enda Tiers-Monde and
Ndef Leng (“act together”).The seminars featu-
red information workshops, debates and docu-
mentary films which convinced them of the pre-
vention campaign’s worth. Unfortunately, there
were only 35 healers present.“Healers aren’t very
e f ficiently used in awareness campaigns, ye t
they’re our first stop on the road,” says Dr.
Moustapha Guèye, of Enda Tiers-Monde. In our
talks, African traditional structures always have
pride of place. It’s time to make use of them.”
The intern ational conference on traditional
medicine and HIV/Aids, held in Dakar in March
1 9 9 9 , c o n firmed the key role of the healers. T h e
c o n f e r e n c e , organized by Prometra (a Senegalese
NGO which promotes traditional medicine) and
sponsored by a dozen intern ational organizat i o n s ,
attracted about 200 healers and 250 doctors and
s c i e n t i s t s , as well as political decision-makers ,j o u r-
nalists and people living with HIV and Aids from
about 30 countries around the globe. At the end of
the discussions, the traditional healers were inv i t e d
to take part in UNAIDS programmes and at t e n d
the next world conference on A i d s , in Durban
(South A f rica) in July 2000. n
H e a l e rs
to the re s c u e
w Alassane Cissé
Vastly outnumbering standard doctors, t raditional healers are destined to play a key role 
in the fight against Aids in A f r i c a . Senegal shows the way forward
HIV/Aids 
in Senegal
Out of a population of
8.7 million,75,000
live with HIV/Aids. Among
adults in the 15-to-49 age
group, 1.77% are HIV-
infected,along with 3,800
children under the age of
15. The number who have
died of Aids since the
epidemic began is not
known.
Source: UNAIDS, 1998.
‘In some are a s,
t h e re ’s one doctor 
for every 100,000 people 
and one traditional healer 
for every 1,000’
We don’t need to come
up with some
s u p e r t e c h n o l o g i c a l
secret weapon. Th e
answers are already in
A f r i c a .
Peter Piot,
Executive Director of UNAIDS
( 1 9 4 9 - )
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 27
Getting youth through the Aids crisis
w Respectively technical
adviser for PATH (Programme for
Appropriate Technology in Health)
and Bangkok-based journalist.
Slowly getting bolder
w Pa wana Wienrawee and Carol Livingstone
While the region increasingly taps the media’s potential to spread the message on
Aids pre v e n t i o n , t raditional taboos continue to hamper the educational pro g ra m m e s
2 Southeast A s i a
MTV Asia is currently broadcasting an excel-
lent HIV- p r e vention campaign. S avvy and
m o d e rn ,M T V ’s commercial efforts reach
a f fluent youth in major cities.The music love rs who
see MTV’s HIV education spots have the means to
afford condoms and protect themselve s.These yo u n g
people include many of the future leaders of A s i a ’s
next generat i o n .
But the majority of youth in the Mekong regi o n
— young agricultural wo r k e rs in rural areas,newly arri-
ved fa c t o ry wo r k e rs in big cities, d ay labourers on
c o n s t ruction sites and others — d o n ’t have access to
M T V ’s message. Much of the HIV and Aids educa-
tion aimed at youth takes place in schools,but it usually
only begins after the sixth gr a d e . A large number of
young people have already left school by this age. I n
C a m b o d i a , for instance, only 40 per cent of children
continue their education after their sixth ye a r.
Throughout the regi o n , traditions still act as a
sizeable obstacle to effective HIV/Aids prevention pro-
gr a m m e s. Sexual education is not considered a part
of the natural process of gr owing up.Parents still gr e at l y
i n fluence their children’s choice of marriage part n e rs.
In countries like Cambodia and Mya n m a r ,a rr a n g e d
m a rriage is often practiced. P r e - m a rital sex for “ g o o d ”
women is considered scandalous. Couples often do
not dat e , and thus, sexual negotiation doesn’t begi n
until well into the marital relat i o n s h i p, if eve r.
Scare tactics
As in many countri e s ,t e a c h e rs and students in the
r e gion often have trouble discussing sexual issues in
the classroom.Teacher trainers , who help teachers
l e a rn to discuss sex with their students, often find that
these adults have never touched a condom before and
are frequently embarrassed while giving the lessons.
Most grew up in an environment in which sex wa s
n e ver discussed. O f t e n , the task of conducting sessions
on condom education is left up to NGOs. Pa rt l y
because of the traditional difficulty of talking openly
about sexual issues, m a ny of the education pro-
grammes have focused on scare tactics: if you have sex
or inject drugs you will get Aids and die.Youth can
often list what is considered appropri ate and inap-
p r o p ri ate behav i o u r ,but this knowledge doesn’t alway s
change how they act.Traditional taboos have fil t e r e d
into the formal and non-formal health education sys-
t e m s , and affect how gove rnments and societies at
large perceive sexuality and HIV. For instance,
condoms were illegal in Myanmar until 1992. In some
c o u n t ri e s , a woman carrying one would be conside-
red a prostitute by many members of her community,
including the police.
E f f e c t i ve youth education programmes need to
equip young people with the skills and know l e d g e
to effectively negotiate their sexual behav i o u r. S u c h
programmes must start out by listening to the stu-
d e n t s , finding out about the reality of their sexual
l i ve s , and helping them to deal with these situat i o n s.
The reality is that throughout Southeast Asia there
h ave been fairly profound changes in sexual morals
and social behav i o u r: for instance, young couples
are now more likely to hold hands than 20 ye a rs ago.
Pa rtner selection in countries such as Thailand is
A Vietnamese poster.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
HIV/Aids in South and East A s i a
28 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
You have to start from
the ground [children
and youth] with
e d u c a t i o n , so that
youth will grow
fruitfully and be
protected from A i d s. I f
not the tree will die.
Youth delegate to the fourth
International Congress on A i d s
in Asia and the Pa c i fic, M a n i l a
( P h i l i p p i n e s ) , October 1997.
now often left to the young themselves. Advertise-
ments show a life in which an acknowledgment of
sexuality is the social norm.
S t i l l ,m a ny traditional attitudes towards sexuality
p r e vail and some have a particularly high cost. B e c a u s e
female virginity is highly prized in some countri e s ,i t
is considered acceptable for young men to visit pros-
t i t u t e s.The sex trade has been a major cause of the
spread of Aids in the regi o n . In T h a i l a n d , there are
n ow more men infected with HIV than wo m e n , bu t
the ratio is expected to be even by 2005. Fo rt y - f o u r
per cent of the prostitutes in the nort h e rn region of
Thailand are thought to be HIV- p o s i t i ve . In Cambo-
d i a ,t h at figure is over 60 per cent in some areas.
Dealing with prostitution
In Cambodia, they start at 13, or even yo u n g e r.
M a ny sex customers delude themselves by thinking
t h at they are less likely to contract HIV from the yo u n g .
By UN standards, 80 per cent of the sex wo r k e rs in
Cambodia are yo u t h . In other countri e s ,m a ny yo u n g
hill tribe women have ended up in the sex industry.
And this trade continues to gr ow.
M a ny gove rnments have tried to deal realisti-
cally with the prostitution issue. For example, C a m-
bodia and Thailand have supplied condoms in bro-
t h e l s. This is an important measure, when yo u
consider that the yo u n g, less well-off men who drop
out of school before being taught about HIV- p r e-
vention and reproductive health, are among those
who may feel they can’t afford a condom. But not
all condoms are free. Pove rt y, especially among
yo u t h ,p l ays a major role in the spread of the viru s.
W h at appears to be a cheap price for a condom to an
office worker in Bangkok, m ay be prohibitive l y
e x p e n s i ve to a bicycle tire repairman in a village.A s
m a ny A f rican programmes have show n , money for
e d u c ation and prevention in all form s , from all sec-
t o rs , is a key factor in fighting the spread of the viru s.
Because so many young people in Southeast A s i a
are beyond the reach of traditional HIV/Aids educa-
tion progr a m m e s ,m a ny of the most successful ones
h ave invo l ved peer group talks.These might take place
in the wo r k p l a c e ,i n f o rmally at someone’s home,
d u ring youth festiva l s , vo c ational training pro-
grammes or via other community activities. Pe e r - t o -
peer education invo l ves not just discussing Aids and
the peer pressures involving sex, but includes talking
about eve ry t h i n g, helping young people gain life skills
to negotiate all the issues in their live s.
The local media that may reach the majority of
the less-educated population make an import a n t
contribution to forming people’s attitudes to HIV.
Soap operas have been a successful medium for
spreading the HIV message in Viet Nam. A non-
g ove rnmental organization in Cambodia sponso-
red a boat tour along the Mekong to produce a video
about an HIV- p o s i t i ve Cambodian soldier retur-
ning home. Because it was well-made and captured
the audience’s interest, the video was an extremely
e f f e c t i ve education tool and was seen by ove r
100,000 in the space of three months.
To counter gi ven the many negat i ve represen-
t ations of Aids victims in T h a i l a n d , a group of NGOs
has commissioned a series of portraits of yo u n g
people with HIV. Professional photogr a p h e rs ,m a ny
of whom have worked with fashion magazines, h ave
d o n ated their services to help young people see that
these individuals are as beautiful, and as full of life,
as everyone else.
The epidemic, which disproport i o n ately affects
young people, must be seen as a socio-economic
and a development problem by gove rnments and
society at large. Unless there is a rapid and effective
r e s p o n s e , it is foreseeable that Aids will curb the
economic gr owth of the region in the ye a rs to come.
It is imperat i ve that development plans incorp o r at e
an HIV/Aids pers p e c t i ve , and all the more so when
dealing specifically with programmes targeting the
region’s youth. n
The five hardest hit countries . . .
Cambodia: out of a population of 10.5 million,130,000
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults* stands at 2.4.%.
T h a i l a n d: out of a population of 59 million, 780,000 people
live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 2.23.%.
M y a n m a r: out of a population of 47 million, 4 4 0 , 0 0 0
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 1.79.%.
I n d i a: out of a population of 960 million, 4.1million people
live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 0.82.%.
Nepal: out of a population of 22.6 million,26,000 people
live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 0.24.%.
*adults refers to the 15-49 age group
. . . and the five least hit
Bangladesh: out of a population of 122 million,21,000
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 0.03.%.
Lao Pe o p l e ’s Democratic Republic: out of a population
of 5.2 million, 1,100 people live with HIV/Aids.The HIV- i n f e c-
tion rate among adults stands at 0.04.%.
Indonesia: out of a population of 203.5 million, 52,000
people million live with HIV/Aids. The HIV-infection rate
among adults stands at 0.05.%.
Philippines: out of a population of 70.7 million,24,000
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 0.06.%.
Sri Lanka: out of a population of 18.3 million, 6 , 9 0 0
people live with HIV/Aids.
The HIV-infection rate among adults stands at 0.07.%.
Source: UNAIDS, 1998.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Stemming the t i d e
in T h a i l a n d
wWanphen Sreshthaputra
T h rough a sustained national campaign, Thailand has brought its rate of HIV infection under
c o n t ro l , but the economic crisis is casting a shadow over the pro g re s s
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 29
Getting youth through the Aids crisis
w Bangkok Post journalist
(Thailand)
“Condom Night” in Bangkok.
A survey conducted in Thailand for the British
c o n t r a c e p t i ve firm Durex, published in
December 1998, showed that 60 per cent of
those questioned used condoms. Polls taken by
UNAIDS among 21-year-old Thai men found that use
of condoms in brothels in northern Thailand rose
from 61 per cent to 93 per cent between 1991 and
1995, while the number of customers fell by half.
Such changes in sexual behaviour are two solid
results of  T h a i l a n d ’s large-scale effort to fight A i d s.
Even before the first case was detected in Thailand in
1 9 8 4 , Mechai V i r ava i d ya (“Mr. C o n d o m ” ) , a fa m i l y
planning pioneer and founder of the Population and
Community Development A s s o c i at i o n , was publicly
s i n ging the praises of condoms. At first he was accused
of tarnishing the country ’s image, but then he wa s
c o n gr at u l ated for his major contri bution to halting the
spread of sexually-transmitted diseases (STDs) and
Aids.
Non-governmental organizations were the first to
support his work but were quickly overwhelmed.The
rapid spread of such diseases spurred the government
to launch a broad mobilization campaign. In 1992, it
announced a three-year plan to monitor and fight A i d s.
By 1996,the plan’s budget had risen to $82.3 million,
an initiative unmatched in any other country.
Coordinated by the ministry of health, preventive
e d u c ation was gradually taken over by civil society as a
w h o l e . By 1990, e ven before the plan was launched,
television had become the chief source of inform at i o n ,
with the broadcasting of expensive advertising spots.
Rural communities set up solidarity funds and Bud-
dhist monks opened their temples to ill people
rejected by their families.The religious association
Sangha Metta, based at the Buddhist Unive rsity of
M a h a m a k u t , at Chiang Mai, has so far trained more
than 500 monks and nuns to work in preve n t i o n
and treatment.
In most towns, people with Aids or HIV took
a c t i o n . The New Life Friends associat i o n , set up
in 1993, has several hundred members and is doing
an impressive job of raising awa r e n e s s , e s p e c i a l l y
in schools. M a ny members are now teaching classes
about the disease.
Complacency 
and budget cuts
From the early 1990s, clinics specializing in
t r e ating STDs, whose patients were mostly wo r-
king in the sex industry, generously handed out free
condoms and pushed brothel ow n e rs to encourage
their use.This programme,launched on a national
scale in 1991 and known as the “100 per cent
Condom Campaign” is the key to Thailand’s suc-
c e s s , according to W i wat Rochapichaya k h o n , t h e
UNAIDS director for the Asia-Pacific region.
But prevention has flagged for the past two
years for several reasons. Rochapichayakhon says
people have taken for granted the progress and
h ave become complacent. The head of the
European Union’s Aids programme in Thailand,
Alessio Panza, blames a new policy of targeting
specific groups rather than conducting a mass
campaign. The chief of the Aids department in
the Thai health ministry, Chaiyos Kunanusont,
claims that the economic and financial crisis that
erupted in 1997 is responsible. The budget to
prevent the disease has been cut by a quarter, he
complains.
The effect of the economic crisis on the epide-
mic is unclear.Will the newly-unemployed end up
working in the brothels of Patpong and Pat t aya? Or
will the falling standard of living mean fewer cus-
tomers and so less demand for new sex workers?
One thing is cert a i n : the thousands of people retur-
ning to the countryside after losing their jobs in the
t owns are already causing sexual health problems in
the north and northeast of Thailand. n
HIV/Aids 
in T h a i l a n d
Out of a population
of 59 million,
780,000 people live
with HIV/Aids. Among
adults in the 15-to-49
age group, 2.23% are
HIV-infected,as are
14,000 children under
the age of 15. The
epidemic has so far
claimed a total of
230,000 lives.
Source: UNAIDS, 1998.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
P re v e n t i o n at school:
an arduous cours e
wMonique Fo u i l l o u x
School is an ideal place to make young people aware of the danger of A i d s. But the
topic is delicate and all the harder to handle with precious few re s o u rc e s
w Education coordinator for
Education International,with
additional contributions from
Nathalie Barboza (UNESCO Dakar);
Babakar Fall,coordinator of the
Group for Research and
Development on Population and
Education, Dakar (Senegal);
Asa Andersson-Singh,
formerly a programme specialist
with the UNESCO office in New
Delhi (India).
Ed u c ating schoolchildren about Aids is some-
thing ve ry recent in developing countri e s —
when it happens at all. M a ny politicians, s c h o o l
p rincipals and teachers are trapped by sexual taboos
and believe Aids education encourages young people
to have sex. Only in 1997 did a report by UN A I D S
(entitled E f fects of sex education on young people’s
sexual behav i o u r) come out showing there was no
such danger at all.
The situation is finally beginning to change.
M a ny developing countries have now taken the
plunge and Aids education is part of their school
c u rri c u l a .S o m e t i m e s , subterfuges have to be used.
I n d o n e s i a , a Muslim country, has chosen to talk
about “reproductive health education” instead of
sex education.Many countries have followed suit.
Senegal’s pioneering 
programmes
In West and Central Africa,the subject is tack-
led in “family life and population education” pro-
grammes which offer a multi-disciplinary mix of
b i o l o g y, home economics and health, civic and
moral educat i o n .H owe ve r ,d i f ficulties lie not just in
devising programmes but also in teaching them
e f f e c t i ve l y. In most countri e s , the programmes have
not yet been endorsed by the government.
Senegal is a pioneer in the field and family educa-
tion is even taught in pri m a ry schools there. S i n c e
1 9 9 4 , a Senegalese NGO, Group for Research and
D e velopment on Po p u l ation and Education (GE E P)
has set up 140 family education clubs, i nvolving 52
per cent of the country ’s secondary schools. In 1997,
three such clubs were started at Dakar Unive rs i t y.
So far more than 2,000 pupils, a third of them
gi r l s , h ave completed training as group leaders.
Their job is to make their fellow students, as well as
young people not in school, aware of Aids through
cultural day s , fa i rs and holiday camp activities.Te a-
c h e rs help them by looking after administrat i ve
m at t e rs. D u ring the 1997-98 school ye a r , their wo r k
involved about 45,000 young people,representing
32 per cent of all secondary school students.
In A s i a , the situation va ries widely from coun-
t ry to country.T h a i l a n d ,C a m b o d i a ,L a o s ,Viet Nam
and Sri Lanka have well-established prevention pro-
grammes which are part of formal educat i o n ,w h i l e
Nepal, Pakistan,Bangladesh and the Maldives are
only just getting start e d . In India, an Aids awa r e-
ness campaign is supposed to be part of phy s i c a l
e d u c ation and courses in “social useful productive
wo r k ” . But often teachers do not even know such
p r o grammes exist, so they have to make do by them-
s e l ve s. In the most remote parts of India and elsew-
h e r e , t e a c h e rs with little knowledge of Aids are
expected to initiate an open discussion about sexua-
lity with classes of 50 to 80 pupils without the help
of books on the subject.This is asking too much.
Teachers: overcoming
their own inhibitions
“One of my students asked me a question about
Aids which I just didn’t know how to answe r , so I said
it wa s n ’t the subject we were dealing with,” a d m i t t e d
a history teacher in A f rica during a seminar in Lomé
( Togo) in A p ril 1999. “But I had the feeling it wa s
the first time the child had dared to ask the question
and I fear he wo n ’t dare ask it again.”
The teachers , t h e m s e l ves inhibited, do not
k n ow how to tackle the subject. In West A f ri c a ,o n l y
Guinea has arranged for Aids education at the
N ational Te a c h e rs ’C o l l e g e , while Burkina Faso and
3 The classro o m
and beyond
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 31
Getting youth through the Aids crisis
Togo are focusing on secondary school teachers.
The other countries have made little headway.
Te a c h e rs also need to have access to interactive
teaching methods so they can create an at m o s p h e r e
of confidence to encourage young people to voice their
c o n c e rns and learn to protect themselve s. But tea-
ching mat e rials are seriously lacking.At the begi n n i n g
of the 1990s, UN E S C O and the World Health Organi-
z ation (WHO) published some manuals for school
c u rriculum planners suggesting activities for pupils
and how teachers might approach the subject (see
b ox ) .S e veral thousand of these well-produced guides
were pri n t e d , but there are 55 million teachers in the
wo r l d . More recently,Togo put out a brochure for
s c h o o l c h i l d r e n , but it was distri buted only pri vat e l y.
Reach children 
when they’re young
Even when appropriate tools are available,tea-
chers do not always make use of them.Experience
shows that young teachers,who adapt much more
easily to new approaches, are the ones to rely on.
As a ru l e , nobody is really prepared to talk to yo u n g
people about sex.Parents do not feel up to the job
and pass it on to the teachers who in turn pass it
back to the family or the church.This is especially
so in majori t y - C atholic countri e s , mainly in Lat i n
A m e ri c a , where condoms are still sometimes regar-
ded as “an instrument of the devil.” S u rveys by
UNAIDS show that when young people are we l l -
i n f o rmed about the disease, they protect themselve s
more effectively than adults. In Chile, Brazil and
Mexico, boys between 15 and 18 are the most fre-
quent users of condoms.
But education authorities still balk at preve n t i o n
p r o grammes and do not like to recognize that yo u n g
people are sexually active .E ven though premari t a l
sex is frowned upon, it is common among teenagers ,
who change part n e rs more often than adults.This is
w hy about half the new cases of infection are found
among people between 15 and 24. So they must be
wa rned about Aids as early as possible.
The ideal age to start preve n t i ve education is
about seve n , according to expert s. Children of that
age do not have inhibitions, express themselve s
openly at school and freely pass on what they learn
to the rest of their family and are thus excellent
agents of communicat i o n . It is too late to begi n
introducing this education in secondary school
because between a quarter and a half of all school-
children in developing countries drop out of school
after five ye a rs. P r o grammes outside school are the-
refore vital to combat A i d s. There are some, bu t
not enough progr a m m e s , which mainly reach chil-
dren in big towns.
So there is a great deal of work to be done.But
people are clearly becoming aware of the problem.
After two decades of silence, the issue of Aids has
finally reached the horizon of the classroom. n
UN E S C O
and Aids education
S et up in 1987, UNESCO’s Section for Preventive Edu-
cation aims to develop responsible attitudes and
behaviour at individual and community levels using edu-
cational strategies.The goal is to enhance national capa-
cities to implement effective educational programmes.Th i s
can mean implementing pilot projects, providing exper-
t i s e, and organizing conferences and teacher training
w o r k s h o p s. It assists in launching international cam-
paigns aimed at youth in collaboration with civil society,
promoting peer education,creative teaching and publi-
shing guides for teachers and educational materials.
The Unit of Cultural Research and Management’s
project originated in the UNAIDS Coordinated Appeal for
1998-1999.Its basic concern is to understand and take
into account people’s cultures in the broadest sense
when developing preventive actions against HIV/Aids.
The World Foundation for Aids Research and Preven-
tion was established in 1993 by UN E S C O D i r e c t o r- G e n e r a l
Federico Mayor and Professor Luc Montagnier, c o - d i s c o-
verer of the HIV virus. The goal of the foundation is to
mobilize all kinds of private initiatives, to create new
partnerships and find novel forms of co-operation, e s p e-
cially in research and prevention, in order to support and
continue actions against Aids taken by public authorities.
n
+ …
l http://www.unesco.org/education
Every time a child dies
of A i d s, human rights
are violated.
Children and Aids: 
An Imminent Calamity, U N I C E F
In Senegal children find out about Aids from primary
school textbooks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
At the school in Mujina, a couple of hours by
road from the Rwandan capital of Kigali, t h e
t e a c h e rs have gathered for a day of instru c-
tion about Aids organized by the NGO E n fants réfu-
giés du monde.They all admit to being confused:
w h at can we do? they ask.Their pupils start hav i n g
sex quite early on—around 16 for boy s , but much
e a r l i e r , from about 12 and up for gi r l s , who are often
pestered and harassed by adults.The teachers all
a gree that the school is ideally situated to reach
young people in efforts to prevent the spread of the
d i s e a s e . But how exactly can they get the message
across to their pupils? 
The curriculum officially includes lessons about
Aids and sexually transmitted diseases (STDs), bu t
t e a c h e rs have not been taught how to tackle these sub-
j e c t s.They don’t have books or other written mat e-
ri a l , their own knowledge is limited and mainly obtai-
ned from the radio. Their mother tongue lacks
euphemisms for sexual mat t e rs.And even the most
energetic teachers shy away from the subject for fear
of being accused by parents of corrupting the minds of
their children.
An ‘internal army’
“As a result,”s ays a pri m a ry school inspector,“ m o s t
of them just don’t teach the classes they’re supposed
t o.”According to one female teacher,“ i t ’s impossible in
R wanda to talk about sex with children under 12.”
A team from the Rwandan Child to Child pro-
gramme gi ves a one-day crash course on a teaching
method by which children learn to be more concer-
ned about their own health and that of others.T h e
training aims to equip the teachers with inform at i o n
about Aids and techniques for tackling the subject.
Right from the start,the team reminds partici-
pants that A i d s , unlike any other sexually transmit-
ted disease, is a blood disease, not one directly affec-
ting sexual organs. From this angle, t e a c h e rs can
handle the matter more calmly, like any other infec-
t i o n .The problem is that many teachers are unclear
about the va rious functions of blood.With malari a
widespread in the regi o n , they know that red blood
cells carry ox y g e n , but they are less familiar with
white ones or with problems of the immune system.
Basic inform ation about blood is conve yed with
the help of games and ve ry brief talks.The immune
s y s t e m , for example, is presented as a professionally
organized “ i n t e rnal army ”which attracts their at t e n-
t i o n .They overcome their shyness and join in acting
A c ra s h c o u rse for teachers
w D r. Yvon Moren
During a day of role-playing and discussion, Rwandan teachers learn to broach the subject 
of Aids in the classroom without shyness or fear
w Member of the “Child to Child”programme, Institute of
Health and Development, Université Paris VI (France)
out how the virus attacks the body and how the va ri o u s
p a rts of the immune system fight back. A “ M r. H I V ”
and a “ M r. M a l a ri a ” gi ve talks about the virus and
h ow it spreads.
Before looking at how the virus enters the human
b o d y, the teachers are asked to draw the male and
female genitals.Ve ry few are comfortable doing so.
But making a life-size model of the female genitals,
using what e ver is at hand (an avocado pear for the
u t e ru s , for example) is met with enthusiasm. A pre-
s e n t ation about the different stages of Aids gi ves the
t e a c h e rs a chance to talk at length about the disease,
which is so present in their eve ry d ay life and ye t
remains inv i s i b l e .
After several further scientific points have been
m a d e , the question of prevention is tackled. T h e
Fleet of Hope, a book written by Bernard Jo i n e t , a
C atholic missionary and professor of psychology at
Ta n z a n i a ’s Unive rsity of Dar es Salaam, is used.
Aids is presented as a kind of Biblical flood and the
class “ e m b a r k s ” on one of three “ a r k s ” — a b s t i n e n c e ,
fidelity or condom—to escape drowning.
An eva l u ation of the training shows that teachers
feel it is vital to improve their scientific know l e d g e .
But this isn’t enough for them. Students in higher
grades are asking them all sorts of questions about
s e x u a l i t y, which they are at a loss to answe r. n
In my country,
B o t s wa n a , there is a
serious problem of
c o m m u n i c a t i o n
between parents and
their children. This is a
cry from our hearts:
p a r e n t s, talk to us.
W i t h o u t
c o m m u n i c a t i o n ,
guidance and dialogue
on your part, we are a
lost generation. C o m e
to our aid.
1 4 - y e a r-old girl addressing the
International Conference on
STD/Aids in A f r i c a ,K a m p a l a
( U g a n d a ) ,1 9 9 5
Cover of a book produced by Dr. Yvon Moren 
and Rwanda’s Child to Child programme 
(Edicef publishers, Paris, 1996).
HIV/Aids 
in Rwanda
Out of a population of
5.8 million,370,000
live with HIV/Aids. Among
adults in the 15-49 age
group, 12.75% are HIV-
infected,along with
22,000 children under the
age of 15. The epidemic
has so far claimed 170,000
lives.
Source: UNAIDS, 1998.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 33
Getting youth through the Aids crisis
U g a n d a : a j i h a d against A i d s
w Maggie Keenan W h e e l e r
In informal schools tied to mosques, Muslim religious leaders have taken on a pivotal role in
teaching youth the basics of pre v e n t i o n
Mohammed Mubiru admits that Aids is a
topic he has never discussed with his
p a r e n t s.“They would think I was being dis-
r e s p e c t f u l ,” he say s. So where did Mubiru , a teena-
ger, learn about the disease? 
In an innovat i ve project launched by the Isla-
mic Medical A s s o c i ation of Uganda (IMAU ) , yo u t h
in Mpigi (50 km southwest of Kampala) and Kamuli
D i s t ricts (140 km northeast of the capital) are lear-
ning about Aids at Madarasa schools associated with
the mosques in their villages.These schools are open
on weekends to teach Muslim children the A r a b i c
language and principles of Islamic culture and beha-
v i o u r. Muslims account for about 16 per cent of
U g a n d a ’s 20 million people. In 1989, the country ’s
highest Muslim authority declared a jihad (holy
war) on A i d s ,p aving the way for the Madarasa A i d s
Education and Prevention project.
In a 36-lesson curriculum developed by the
Ugandan Ministry of Health and the United
N ations Children’s Fund (UNICEF), youth in the
Madarasa schools learn about HIV/Aids transmis-
s i o n ,p r e vention and control during 40-minute ses-
s i o n s.The curriculum was recently enriched with a
life skills component to equip youth with some of
the tools they need for building self-esteem and
coping with va rious challenges of gr owing up.To p i c s
include resisting peer pressure,c o m m u n i c ation skills
and being assert i ve : “If a girl is asked by a man to
h ave sex, she needs to know how to say no and mean
n o,” insists Neema Nakya n j o, I M AU ’s project offi-
c e r. He helps to train county sheikhs, imams and
their assistants to use the curri c u l u m .These trai-
n e e s , i n - t u rn , s u p e rvise the training of vo l u n t e e r
Madarasa teachers at mosques in their area. Since its
launch in 1995, the programme has reached more
than 36,000 children in 350 schools.
“It is challenging to introduce the topic of A i d s ,
but children need to know,” s ays Imam Hassan
Magola from Bukulube Mosque.The project under-
lines that certain traditional Muslim practices 
can increase the risk of exposure to the HIV 
v i ru s , namely male circumcision with unsteri l e
i n s t ruments and ablution of the dead without pro-
t e c t i ve glove s. Introducing the topic of condoms
h owe ver proved to be the single gr e atest hurdle. I n
the first ye a r , the issue was removed from the cur-
riculum after some religious leaders argued that
recommending use of condoms would promote sex
outside marri a g e . O ver a ye a r , I M AU held a dia-
logue with Islamic leaders to work through their
c o n c e rn s , stressing that the condom was only being
promoted as protection after the failure of the first
t wo lines of defence: abstaining from sex and hav i n g
sex only within marri a g e . As IMAU argued, gi r l s
do become pregnant before marriage and there are
m a ny cases of sexually transmitted disease among
the unmarri e d . Islamic leaders eventually agr e e d
t h at education on the responsible use of condoms
was acceptable and the topic was reinserted in the
curriculum in the second year.
N ow, the project’s main struggle is with funding.
UNICEF has contri buted $35,000 to the project
since its launch while parents are encouraged to gi ve
the Madarasa teacher 100 Ugandan shillings per
session (less than 10 cents) and have repeat e d l y
expressed their support for the project. G r ow i n g
n u m b e rs of non-Muslim parents are seeking to enrol
their children in the Madarasa Aids classes.W h at ’s
clear is that students feel able to talk more openly
about the subject.“When I see someone with A i d s ,
I know what they are going through and I sympa-
t h i z e ,” s ays one student. “I have learned that A i d s
is a reality and I live in fear of it.” n
HIV/Aids 
in Uganda
Out of a population of
20.7 million, 9 3 0 , 0 0 0
live with HIV/Aids. A m o n g
adults in the 15-49 age
g r o u p, 9.51% are HIV-
i n f e c t e d , along with 67,000
children under the age of
1 5 . The epidemic has so far
claimed 1.8 million lives.
Source: UNAIDS, 1998.
w An American freelance writer who recently spent several
years in Uganda,where she prepared two Best Practice Case
Studies for UNAIDS, including one on the project cited in this
article
At this Ugandan school associated with the village mosque,
pupils learn to fear God . . . and Aids.
‘She needs to know
how to say no and mean no’
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
w Journalist based in Mexico City
R e a c h i n g s t reet kids on their
own turf
w Guillermina Nava r r o
Born in Mexico City, Latin A m e r i c a ’s only Aids 
p revention pro g ramme for street children is ready to 
s h a re its expertise with other countries in the re g i o n
The street is their home. For several thousand
young Mexicans, it is the place where they play,
e at , sleep and when they can, wo r k . For many,
the sex trade is the only way of earning a few pesos.
It is also the most likely way that they will become
infected with HIV.In a few ye a rs time, m a ny of them
will succumb to Aids.
Finding suitable ways to prevent Aids is no
simple task, and even less so when street children
are concern e d . “They are anxious, unstable and
sometimes aggr e s s i ve ,” s ays psychologist Gualbert o
G at i c a . To help tackle the problem, the NGO Casa
A l i a n z a , which has been working in Mexico since
1 9 8 6 , launched its Luna (“Moon”) programme two
ye a rs ago. It is the only Aids prevention campaign
in Latin America designed especially for homeless
children.
Distorted 
knowledge
Luna, a name the infected children conjured
up to evoke light amid darkness, is currently
monitoring 6,180 children and teenagers. Besides
being present on the preventive front, the pro-
gramme also keeps a close check on HIV-positive
children, provides medical treatment for youth
with Aids and psychological counselling for their
friends.
“Since 1997, the number of infected children
has ri s e n , so we ’re focusing on preve n t i o n ,”
explains Nicasio Garcia Lopez, the programme’s
coordinator. “Street children usually know about
sex and Aids, but it’s often distorted knowledge.
Hence the importance of effective prevention.”
Vo l u n t e e rs and teachers from Casa A l i a n z a
comb the capital’s neighbourhoods eve ry day to
p e rsuade boys and girls to go to the organizat i o n ’s
“ s h e l t e r ” where they can attend an hour-long
workshop twice a week called “ H I V / A i d s — W h at
is it?”.With the help of simple, colourful teaching
m at e ri a l s , they learn how the disease spreads and
h ow to protect themselves against it. M a ny chil-
dren are also reached directly on their home
ground—the street.When they go around the city,
Casa A l i a n z a ’s teachers carry games with them
t h at can be set up any w h e r e , all based on ques-
tions and answe rs. A game of darts for example.
Depending on where the children land the dart s
on the board, they must answer different ques-
t i o n s. A n o t h e r , called Marat h o n , is based on an
athletics race. The most popular game, L u n o c a ,i s
like snakes and ladders and provides inform at i o n
about HIV, the immune system and ways to pre-
vent A i d s. Such teaching mat e rial is easy to use
and entirely based on linking ideas and pictures.
A 1996 joint survey by  the United Nations
Children’s Fund (UNICEF) and Mexico City
officials found that 13,373 young people under
18 lived and/or worked in the streets of the capi-
tal. Their number grew by 20 per cent between
1992 and 1995—more than 6 per cent a year.
Casa Alianza is also present in the United
S t at e s , C a n a d a , G u at e m a l a , H o n d u r a s , C o s t a
Rica and Nicaragua and is setting up a Luna net-
work in Latin America, based on the methods,
equipment and learning games used in Mexico.
“The idea is to copy the material and come up
with a manual which can be used all over Latin
America to assess the results,” says the program-
me coordinator.
The Mexican headquarters of Casa Alianza
also plans to devise new materials and games,
such as colouring books, picture slides and
puzzles which contain information about HIV.
The organization also responds to frequent
requests to give talks to schools, parishes and
Mexican institutions which care for disadvanta-
ged children. This is perhaps the best evidence
that the Luna programme is shining brightly. n
+ …
l http://www.casa-alianza.org
A young workshop organizer in a Mexico City refuge run
by the NGO Casa Alianza.
SILENCE= DEAT H
Slogan of ACT UP,
an Aids activist gro u p
HIV/Aids 
in Mexico
Out of a population of
94.2 million,180,000
people live with HIV/Aids.
Among adults in the 15-49
age group, 0.35% are HIV-
infected,along with 1,700
children under the age of
15. The number of people
who have died of Aids
since the epidemic began
is unknown.
Source: UNAIDS, 1998.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 35
B i o é t h i q u e : la tentation de l’enfant parfaitGetting youth hr ugh the Aids crisis
The s t i g m a of A i d s
w Jean Dussault
Discrimination against people with A i d s
is a major obstacle to fighting the epidemic.
The solution lies in education
w Member of the the Canadian
HIV/Aids Legal Network 
In her village in Kwa z u l u - N at a l , the South A f ri c a n
p r ovince hardest hit by the Aids epidemic, G u g u
Dlamini died because of the disease. But it wa s n ’t
the virus per se that killed her.She was accused by fel-
l ow - v i l l a g e rs of having brought shame on the com-
munity by talking publicly about being HIV- p o s i t i ve .
When she was beaten by a neighbour who advised her
to keep quiet, she went to the police but they did
nothing to protect her.The next night, v i l l a g e rs at t a c-
ked her house before stoning her and beating her to
d e at h .
While this story has gone round the wo r l d ,t h e r e
are other less bloody but just as revealing tales that
receive no attention.HIV-positive children are the
targets of other children’s angry parents who do
their utmost to have them expelled from the nur-
s e ry or school or excluded from sports activities.
Some doctors and dentists refuse to treat people
with A i d s. Community help projects regularly come
up against the refusal of local inhabitants to have
such “ p l a g u e - s t ri c k e n ” people living in their neigh-
b o u r h o o d .E ven dead, these people continue to ins-
til fear, with some funeral parlours refusing to accept
their remains.
Victims of such discri m i n ation are often poor
and isolated.They do not dare complain about how
they are treated for fear of making things wo rs e .T h e
few statistics about them hardly reflect the extent
of the phenomenon.The number of known cases is
just the tip of the iceberg.
Marginalized groups
As well as being frequently ostracized by ordi-
n a ry folk, H I V- p o s i t i ve people are sometimes also
hit by discri m i n at o ry law s. Using prevention as a
pretext,governments adopt laws which violate the
U n i ve rsal Declaration of Human Rights. O f fic i a l
public health programmes are sometimes the source
of violations.There are plenty of examples.
Blood tests have been made compulsory for cer-
tain “target populat i o n s ” such as newborn babies
in New York stat e ,p rison inmates in at least 18 U. S .
states and foreigners wishing to stay more than 30
d ays in such countries as Egypt, B u l g a ria and Geor-
gi a . In some U. S .s t at e s ,d o c t o rs are obliged to pass
on to the authorities the names of patients who have
tested positive for HIV. As a ru l e , H I V- p o s i t i ve
people are refused entry to the United States.
In a collection of essays entitled “Ethics and Law
in the Study of A I D S ” (published in 1992 by the
Pa n a m e rican Health Organizat i o n ) ,K at a rina To m a-
s e v s k i , an intern ational human rights expert ,p o i n t s
out that “if one were to read the Unive rsal Decla-
r ation of Human Rights with the aim of finding out
which human rights have been affected by various
responses to A i d s , one would see that most, if not
a l l , basic human rights and freedoms, laid down as
the common standard of achievement for humanity
more than 40 ye a rs ago, h ave been challenged, v i o-
l at e d , or denied in the context of HIV/Aids.” E x p e rt s
have pointed out in vain that no medical or public
health reason justifies measures restricting the ri g h t s
of HIV- p o s i t i ve people.These measures are usually
i n e f f e c t i ve and even counterp r o d u c t i ve . And ye t ,
discrimination continues.
Most ill people evoke compassion but Aids tri g-
g e rs the opposite reaction.The stigma of HIV is tied
to powerful social symbols, sources of prejudice and
intolerance towards groups which may va ry from
one country to the next but all share a common trait:
they are people who were marginalized even before
the emergence of A i d s.They include immigr a n t s ,
r e f u g e e s , people in pri s o n , male and female prosti-
t u t e s ,n at i ve peoples, d rug addicts and homosexuals.
It is sometimes enough just to belong to one of these
so-called “ ri s k ” groups to be considered a “ t h r e at ”
and thus presumed guilty of spreading the epide-
m i c. People who help them are often regarded as
their “accomplices”.
The world appears to be divided in two. On one
side are people with Aids and those who help them
I make love, I eat, I get
d r e s s e d , I do the same
things as everyone else.
Is there a difference
between me and them?
Is there something on
me which shows that
I’m sick? I’m not a
danger to anyone.
A rsène Ta o,
Côte d’Ivoire,
in La Revue Noire, Pa r i s )
“Solidarity in Grief” is the title of this manual produced
for teenagers in the Dominican Republic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
and on the other, those who imagine they are safe
from the disease and do not feel concern e d . Some in
the first group avoid health and social serv i c e s
because of the stigma to which they are subjected
and their fear of discri m i n at i o n .Those who most
need help, i n f o rm ation and education are thus for-
ced underground which makes them even more vul-
n e r a b l e . Some people refuse to be tested for A i d s ,
p r e f e rring not to know. O t h e rs keep their infection
secret or else deny it.
People in the second group may be sticking their
head in the sand like ostri c h e s , but they are not for
t h at matter spared by the epidemic.Their self-defence
mechanisms feed their ignorance and create illusions
t h at gi ve them a false sense of securi t y.They think HIV
only strikes at “ ri s k ” groups—sealed communities
with which they have no contact. Believing that HIV
respects social frontiers makes them vulnerable in
t u rn .At an institutional leve l , such a belief slows dow n
awareness programmes and helps to reduce the fun-
ding they at t r a c t . So the stigma and discri m i n at i o n
t h at accompany Aids are not only consequences of
the epidemic but also contri bute to its spread.
The late Jo n athan Mann, who was head of the
World Health Organizat i o n ’s Special Progr a m m e
on Aids and of Harvard Unive rs i t y ’s François-Xav i e r
Bagnoud Center, insisted that human rights feat u r e
prominently in the campaign against HIV. A r g u i n g
t h at such protection of ill or HIV-infected people
was vital for ethical, judicial and practical reasons, h e
stressed that a community could not deal effecti-
vely with the disease if it failed to respect the basic
right of people to have a say in decisions concern i n g
their own future.
Protecting the victims
Although the stigma of HIV/Aids is tied to igno-
r a n c e ,i n f o rming people about the virus and the ri s k
of catching it is not enough to eradicate it.Preven-
t i ve education has to be accompanied by seri o u s
e d u c ation about discri m i n at i o n , but this is still at
an embryonic stage.
At the intern ational leve l ,h e a l t h , legal and ethics
e x p e rt s ,r e p r e s e n t at i ves of communities affected by
the disease and study groups have been insisting for
several years on the need to ensure that policies to
reduce the spread of Aids and care for its victims
respect their rights and their dignity, whether they
h ave the disease or are just at ri s k . But the appeals of
the experts will remain a dead letter without broad
public understanding and sufficient will, e s p e c i a l l y
on the part of political decision-makers.
The UN High Commission for Human Rights
and UNAIDS in 1998 published 12 guidelines for
s t ates on the rights of individuals concern i n g
H I V / A i d s. One of them recommended laws to pro-
tect victims of discri m i n ation in pri vate and public
sectors while guaranteeing respect for privacy and
c o n f i d e n t i a l i t y. Another focused on one of the
sources of discri m i n ation and called on states to
“promote the wide and ongoing distri bution of crea-
t i ve educat i o n , training and media progr a m m e s
explicitly designed to change attitudes of discri m i-
n ation and stigmat i z ation associated with HIV/Aids
to understanding and acceptance.”
The current gap between the quantity of recom-
m e n d ations and a sluggish bu r e a u c r a cy is glari n g .
In Aids prevention campaigns, the issue of discri-
m i n ation often falls by the wayside and is rarely dis-
cussed in schools.The odd educational film at t a c k s
the stigma but no-one can boast of a broad aware-
ness campaign that has an important impact on
society.
The main features of education against discri-
m i n ation must be worked out in each country accor-
ding to the social context and the evolution of the
d i s e a s e . After the targets and participants have been
c h o s e n , steps must be taken to create a fri e n d l i e r
atmosphere for people who have Aids and who fa c e
rejection and indifference.This must also be done
for their families and friends as well as all those invo l-
ved in the fight against the epidemic.We must not
forget that the disease is the enemy, not the people
who have it. n
+ …
l http://www.aidslaw.ca
This young Zambian belongs to a nationwide network 
of anti-Aids clubs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 37
E T H I C S
T HE DE ATH PEN A LTY :
A BOL I T ION GAINS GROUND
w Martine Jacot
Countries that have abolished capital punishment now outnumber those applying it. 
But four countries still account for 80 per cent of all executions.
n
In the teeming jumble of daily news,
one important human rights event
passed almost unnoticed recently: on
June 2, 1999, Russian President Boris
Yeltsin commuted the death sentences of
716 people to life imprisonment. The
death penalty was thereby effectively abo-
lished in Russia, in line with its commit-
ment upon joining the Council of
Europe1 in 1996. In that year, Russia exe-
cuted 40 death row pri s o n e rs , s a d l y
almost a dark world record.
Russian Justice Minister Pave l
K r a s h e n i n n i k ov said the presidential
decree was “a historic day” for his coun-
try. The decision may encourage the for-
mer Soviet bloc countries wishing to
become members of the Council of
Europe to follow suit or risk being barred
in the future.
Tipping
the balance
The Council was the first body to sign
(in 1983) an intern ational agr e e m e n t
obliging the signatories to abolish the
death penalty in peacetime. The treaty
(Protocol 6 of the European Convention
on Human Rights) came into effect in
1985. Since the Berlin Wall came down,
22 former or new European countries
have dropped capital punishment, at least
for “ordinary” crimes. The most recent
were this ye a r: L at v i a , C y p rus and
Northern Ireland. In 1998, Azerbaijan,
Bulgaria, Estonia and Lithuania took the
same step for all categories of offences
and Kyrgyzstan and Turkmenistan decla-
red moratoriums on executions.
Europe is not the only continent
w UNESCO Courier journalist A drawing by French artist Roland Topor (1938-1997) published by Amnesty International in 1982.
1 Set up in 1949, the Council of Europe, based in
Strasbourg (France), aims to strengthen
democracy, human rights and rule of law in its
member-states, which have grown from 23 before
the fall of the Berlin Wall in 1989 to 40 today.
where the abolitionist cause has made
h e a d way. Amnesty Intern ational notes
that the number of countries that have
totally abolished the death penalty has tri-
pled over the past 20 years—from 19 in
1979 to 68 by April 1999. To this list can
be added 14 more countries that impose
the death penalty in wartime only and 23
others where it is considered to have been
abolished “in effect” because they have
not executed anyone for at least ten years.
This total of 105 states compares with
the 90 countries or territories that have
executed at least one of their death row
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
1,067 people were executed and 1,657
death sentences imposed. Tax evasion has
been a capital offence in China since
1997, which brought to about 60 the
crimes punishable by death there.
About a hundred people were execu-
ted in the Democratic Republic of the
Congo in 1998 according to Amnesty,
and 66 in Iran. In the United States (see
p. 39), 68 prisoners were executed, most
by lethal injection.Three of the U.S. pri-
soners were under 17 when they commit-
ted their crimes. Since 1990, only six
c o u n t ries—the United Stat e s , I r a n ,
N i g e ri a , Pa k i s t a n , Saudi Arabia and
Yemen—have continued imposing death
sentences on people who were minors at
the time of their offence. But in Yemen, a
presidential decree has just put an end to
this practice.The UN Convention on the
Rights of the Child forbids the death sen-
tence in the case of minors and has been
ratified by all UN member-states except
for Somalia and the United States.
A contagious effect
on neighbouring nations
Is the United States—regarded, like
France, as a “cradle of human rights”—
having a contagious effect on some of its
38 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
E T H I C S
prisoners over the past 20 years. Today
countries opposing the death penalty out-
number those applying it. The “balance”
tipped only recently, between 1997 and
1998. When you look at the picture over
the whole century, progress is even more
impressive: in 1899 only Venezuela, Costa
Rica and the tiny republic of San Marino,
in Italy, had decided to abolish the death
penalty.
Such progress is clearly linked with
the gr owth of local and intern at i o n a l
human rights move m e n t s. The deat h
penalty is increasingly thought of as a
cruel and inhuman punishment. Its irre-
ve rsibility always touches people’s
consciences in cases where it turns out
that innocent people have been victims of
a r b i t r a ry or unfair tri a l s , cases which
receive more and more publicity these
d ay s. I n t e rn ational pressure has also
increased. 1999 saw the tenth anniversary
of the UN General Assembly’s adoption
of its first protocol calling for the aboli-
tion of the death penalty.
Many countries decided to abolish
capital punishment as a way of turning
over a new leaf following long periods of
political repression. This is what happe-
ned not only in the former communist
countries of Eastern Europe but also in
South Africa (1997) and before that in
L atin A m e rica—in A r g e n t i n a , B r a z i l ,
Peru, Nicaragua and El Salvador.
A cradle
of human rights
Elsewhere, action by courageous poli-
tical leaders has been needed to overcome
local public opinion that has remained
mostly in favour of the death penalty.The
French socialist government,for example,
abolished the death penalty in 1981 soon
after taking office. But opinion polls sho-
wed it was not until 18 years later, in
1999, that a majority of the public polled
finally turned against the death penalty,
despite France’s reputation as the “cradle
of human rights”. In other countries, the
process has sometimes been a very long
one. Belgium and Greece repealed the
death penalty in 1996 and 1993 respecti-
vely, more than 20 years after carrying out
their last executions.
Despite this progr e s s , A m n e s t y
International reminds us that at least
1,625 prisoners were executed in 1998 in
37 countries, four of which—China, the
Democratic Republic of the Congo, the
United States and Iran—accounted for
80 per cent of the total.
In China, for want of official figures,
Amnesty estimates that in 1998 at least
+ …
l Amnesty International, International
Secretariat, 
1 Easton Street, WC1XOW London, 
Phone: (44 171) 413 55 00, 
Fax: (44 171) 956 11 57.
Website: http//www.amnesty.org
l Death Penalty Information Center:
http//www.essential.org/dpic
l News about the death penalty:
http://iep.univ-lyon2.fr/PdM
EX ECU T IONS
IN 37 COUN T RIES
A m n e s ty International reports that death
penalties were carried out in 37 countries
and territories in 1998: 
Afghanistan, the Bahamas, Belarus, China,
Congo, Cuba, Egypt, Ethiopia, Guatemala, Iraq,
I ran, Japan, Jordan, Kyrgyzstan, Kuwait, Le b a n o n ,
Nigeria, Oman, the Palestinian Authority, Pa k i s t a n ,
Russia, Rwanda, St Kitts-Nevis, Saudi Ara b i a ,
Sierra Leone, Singapore, Somalia, Sudan, Syria,
Taiwan, Thailand, the United Arab Emirates, the
United States, Uzbekistan, Viet Nam, Yemen and
Zimbabwe. n
neighbours? In the Caribbean, rampant
c rime has fired support for capital
punishment among gove rnments and
public opinion. Nine prisoners were exe-
cuted by hanging in early June 1999 in
Port-of-Spain, capital of the Caribbean
state of Trinidad and Tobago, five years
after the last execution took place there.
The Bahamas used the gallows again
twice in 1998, after a two-year pause.
While the last execution by hanging in
Jamaica took place in 1988, there’s a high
risk that the practice could be resumed:
there are 40 people on death row there,
several of whom have almost exhausted
all legal recourse.
The myth
of deterrence
Rampant crime was also used by the
authorities in the Philippines to justify
restoring the death penalty in December
1993, with the first execution being car-
ried out in February 1999.Yet this coun-
try was the first in Asia to abolish capital
punishment, in 1987, after the fall of
President Ferdinand Marcos.The current
head of state, Joseph Estrada,has stressed
his determination to attack poverty—the
“compost-heap of crime”—but without
abolishing the death penalty. Recent opi-
nion polls show about 80 per cent of
Filipinos are in favour of it. Over the past
six years,914 people have been sentenced
to death in the Philippines.
But so far no study has shown clearly
that capital punishment is a deterrent.On
the contrary, the murder rate has fallen in
several countries that have abolished it,
such as Canada, a neighbour of the
United States. Amnesty International and
other human rights organizations hope
the U.S., among others, will at least abo-
lish the death penalty for people who were
minors when they committed their crime,
as well as for the mentally ill and the
elderly. n
Progress is clearly linked 
with the growth of local 
and international human rights
movements. The death penalty
is increasingly thought of 
as a cruel and inhuman
p u n i s h m e n t .
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 39
E T H I C S
n
In a nation where the death penalty is in
force in 38 out of 51 stat e s , r o u g h l y
3,500 pri s o n e rs are waiting on deat h
r ow, 47 per cent of them white and 42 per
cent black.* Executions are on the ri s e ,w i t h
68 carried out in 1998. In addition to impo-
sing the death penalty for crimes committed
by juve n i l e s , the U. S . is also unusual in
making no exceptions for the mentally retar-
d e d .
W h at explains the endorsement of the
d e ath penalty by four out of eve ry five A m e-
ricans? In the civil rights period of the1960s,
the percentage of those in its favour bri e fly
dipped as low as 42 per cent.But since the
Supreme Court reinstated it in 1976,after
a morat o rium of about a decade, s u p p o rt
has been little short of monolithic. It is tru e
t h at the figures drop (to about 60 per cent)
if those surve yed are presented the altern a-
t i ve of keeping serious offenders in jail
without possibility of parole.
The ‘death belt’
H owe ve r , fear of crime persists and a puni-
t i ve climate remains. L aw m a k e rs are conti-
nually introducing bills to expand the list of
“ a g gr avating fa c t o rs ” presented to the jury in
m a ny states in the sentencing phase of a capi-
tal case.
The so-called “ D e ath Belt” of the Sou-
t h e rn stat e s , with their history of lynch law,
accounts for a hefty percentage of death row
i n m at e s , and half of the executions in 1997
were carried out in Texas alone. But Cali-
fornia,which pays out more for its prisons
than its unive rs i t i e s , n ow has the largest
number of inmates on death row. New Yo r k ,
whose Gove rnor Mario Cuomo was one of
the few American politicians in recent his-
t o ry willing to risk a public stand for aboli-
t i o n , has brought the death penalty back.
And in A ri z o n a ,o f ficials intend to accele-
rate the pace of executions.
Built on Puritanical foundat i o n s ,h u m a n
relations in this gun-toting culture are still
v i e wed in Manichean term s , va l i d ating the
f r o n t i e rs m a n ’s call for the bad guy to be
s t rung up. In a climate heavily influ e n c e d
by the religious ri g h t , a public stand against
capital punishment is regarded as nothing
s h o rt of political suicide. E xe c u t i ve cle-
mency, which was used to commute many
d e ath sentences to life imprisonment duri n g
the heyday of the gangsters in the 1930s and
1 9 4 0 s , is rarely exe r c i s e d .Witness Gove r-
nor Bill Clinton,who approved the execu-
tion of a mentally retarded convict in A r k a n-
sas just after winning the presidential
elections in 1992,and California’s Demo-
c r atic Gove rnor Gray Dav i s , who has pas-
sed up the possibility of staying two exe c u-
tions this year.
M o r e ove r , the criminal justice system is
i n e x t ricably intertwined with electoral poli-
t i c s. D i s t rict at t o rn e y s , who make the deci-
sion whether to seek the death penalty in a
gi ven case, are elected. S t ate judges, o n c e
a p p o i n t e d , face a retention vote at the next
general elections.While federal judges are
appointed for life, they face a grueling congr e s-
sional confirm ation bat t l e .Public perception
is that capital cases, which can cost a state in
the region of $1.2 million to prosecute, a r e
subject to unduly lengthy scru t i ny. In fa c t ,
l e gi s l atures around the country have made it
increasingly difficult to bring appeals.
M e a n w h i l e , despite a 1984 Supreme
C o u rt ruling intended to correct racial bias
in jury selection, the operation of the deat h
penalty remains racially skewe d .Of the 1,838
D i s t rict At t o rneys in death penalty states as
of May this ye a r , only 22 were Hispanic and
22 black.Although roughly equal numbers
of blacks and whites are homicide victims, o f
the 500 people put to death between 1977
and 1998, 81.8 per cent were convicted of
killing a white pers o n . Setting aside cases
i nvolving particularly egr e gious crimes such as
s e rial killings, the death penalty falls dispro-
p o rt i o n at e l y, for crimes of equal seve ri t y,u p o n
poor blacks who cannot afford adequate legal
r e p r e s e n t at i o n .
There are some signs of movement in
public opinion. A cluster of miscarriages of
justice on death row and the reve rsal of seve-
ral convictions have helped to rally support
both for a new morat o rium on executions and
for a plan to dive rt spending on death penalty
cases into a fund for the families of homicide
v i c t i m s. It is also conceivable that if a Demo-
c r at comes to power at the next elections and
appoints two new justices of a less than
extreme conservat i ve pers u a s i o n , the Supreme
C o u rt might turn the situation around.
B e t ween now and then, p ri s o n e rs wa i t
on death row. In the words of one juve n i l e
offender in Oklahoma,“ To condemn me to
d e ath . . . is to say my life has no positive
va l u e , I’m beyond correction or rehabilita-
t i o n .” It is strange that a nation that puts such
store in the perfectibility of the individual is
willing to discard so many live s. n
T HE AMERICAN EXCEP T ION
w Vicky Elliott
In a climate influenced by the religious right, a public stand against the death penalty
is regarded as nothing short of political suicide
w Journalist, San Francisco Chronicle
In Texas, the cross marking the grave of an executed prisoner bears his number, not his name.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
n
The scene is set in Sowe t o, one of Jo h a n-
n e s bu r g ’s notoriously poor tow n s h i p s ,
soon after Nelson Mandela’s election in
A p ril 1994 as president of South A f ri c a .I t
was here in Sowe t o,d u ring riots in 1976, t h at
the apartheid gove rn m e n t ’s police shot dead
more than 500 young people.
Jean-François Duroure, a white French
dancer trained in A n g e rs (France) and at
the schools of German choreographer Pina
Bausch and A m e ricans Merce Cunningham
and Viola Fa b e r , is trying to explain his pro-
ject to a group of young street dancers. He
speaks in broken English which his listeners
do not fully understand.The look on their
faces seems to say : ‘Just what does this white
man want of us and why is he here?’
Duroure talks about his gr e at curi o s i t y, h i s
wish to exchange experiences and to cho-
r e o graph them. No reaction from the
a u d i e n c e . His words don’t seem to get
t h r o u g h . S u d d e n l y, Duroure gets up and
s t a rts to dance.The youths join in one by
one and the impromptu performance lasts
five hours.
Communicating
without words
“This is how we finally started to com-
m u n i c ate—without any wo r d s ,” D u r o u r e
s ay s.“This is how I learned to find my phy-
sical spontaneity with them, people without
f o rmal training as dancers but who had dan-
ced since birt h .This is how I brought them
w h at I could and how we established mutual
c o n fidence and respect which enabled us
to create together.”
The result was W h at A r eYou Doing Here,
a “ c h o r e o graphed report ” of sketches blen-
ding dance, music and song with street
scenes and township ceremonies. F r e n c h
and South A f rican cultural officials we r e
sceptical at first about this project by a white
dancer but the final result was wa rmly recei-
ved by the public in South A f rica and
Europe in 1997 and 1998.The choreogra-
pher is currently repeating the experi e n c e
in the city of Durban in Kwazulu-Natal.
Unlike Duroure, who dances mainly to
“inspire encounters and complicity”, E a
Sola seeks through her work to delve into
u n k n own dimensions of the inner self. “ I t ’s
something from ve ry deep down inside
which you then have to pass on to others,”
she say s. Sola is Vietnamese and when she
was barely a teenager, she was forced into
exile in the West,and felt at a loss.
She returned to Viet Nam to delve into
her country’s rich culture,mainly through
the nort h e rn Vietnamese traditional art form
k n own as h at chéo which dates back to the
13th century and combines song, d r a m a ,
dance and percussion.With 15 V i e t n a m e s e
T HE MELT ING POT 
OF MODERN DA NCE
w Jean-Marc Adolphe and Martine Jacot
More than ever before, modern dance is synonymous with buzzing cultural exchange—from
North to South, East to West, and vice-versa
w Jean-Marc Adolphe is editor of the French arts
magazine Mouvement and artistic adviser for dance at
the Bastille Theatre in Paris.Martine Jacot is a UNESCO
Courier journalist.
Hi no hashira (“The dance of summer”) by the American choreographer Susan Buirge.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 41
p e a s a n t s , she produced a modern wo r k ,
which breaks through communication bar-
ri e rs , about remembering pain. Sécheresse et
p l u i e (“Drought and rain”) was a lean, s t ri p-
p e d - d own performance in which the pea-
sants at one point waved pictures of dead
r e l at i ve s.The work was followed by Il a été
une fois (“Once upon a time”) and Vo i l à
vo i l à, which was performed at the Lincoln
Center in New Yo r k .Tr avelling through Ger-
m a ny, F r a n c e ,D e n m a r k ,S we d e n ,B e l gi u m ,
B ritain and Po rtugal with her V i e t n a m e s e
d a n c e rs and musicians, Sola noticed “ w i t h
the same surp ri s e ”t h at at each destinat i o n
the “ p ri vate language of the body” c o nve ye d
feelings beyond wo r d s. So there was no need
for any translations.
A nomadic art
José Navas is from Ve n e z u e l a , w i t h
Indian and Spanish blood from his mother
and Italian and A f rican blood through his
fat h e r. He has been based for the last few
years in Montreal (Canada) after studying
in New Yo r k , and dances and choreogr a p h s
regularly in both Europe and North A m e-
ri c a . By “talking about his Ve n e z u e l a n
c u l t u r e ” through his body, he has found a
way of breaking down language barriers.
M o d e rn dance has clearly become a
major vehicle for cultural exchange around
the wo r l d . It does more than simply
transcend spoken wo r d s : it seems to repre-
sent a common experience of humanity.“ We
are all human beings—a link that comes
before national or ethnic ties,” s ays Duroure.
“A child who cries conveys the same mes-
sage eve ry w h e r e .” Dance also invo l ves a dif-
ferent view of things, appealing to the ima-
gi n at i o n , just like music, and often with
m u s i c.
All these fa c t o rs partly explain the
upsurge of modern dance,a worldwide phe-
n o m e n o n . In 1998, 442 choreogr a p h e rs from
52 countries attended the prestigious Inter-
n ational Choreogr a p hy Fe s t i val in Seine
Saint-Denis (a suburb of Pa ri s ,F r a n c e ) . Fo r
the past decade, more and more festiva l s
giving pride of place to modern dance have
been held all over the world—in Prague
( Tanec Praha, e ve ry June), Brazil (Fe s t i va l
I n t e rnacional de Dança, in Belo Hori z o n t e
in Nove m b e r ) ,To k yo (the Yokohama Fe s t i-
va l ) , Stockholm (Dansen Hus), V i l n i u s
(Lithuania) and Adelaide (Australia).Fe s t i-
vals are also spreading across the Mediter-
ranean regi o n . A modern dance gat h e ri n g
was held in Tunis in early 1999, with dan-
c e rs from Egypt, L e b a n o n , A l g e ri a ,
M o r o c c o, Jordan and Syri a .O t h e rs will soon
take place in Casablanca and Beirut.
Dance often accompanies openings and
gr owth in other domains. In 1995, the firs t
Luanda Fe s t i val in Angola symbolized
attempts to revive the country after 20 ye a rs
of civil war.The second one,held in 1998,
claimed the title of the Fe s t i val of A f ri c a n
C h o r e o graphic Creation and showcased the
blossoming of modern dance across the
c o n t i n e n t . Some of the pri z e w i n n i n g
troupes—from Côte d’Ivo i r e , Burkina Fa s o,
K e nya , South A f ri c a ,N i g e ri a ,M a d a g a s c a r ,
Ghana and Mozambique—went to the Fe s-
t i val of New Dance in Montreal (Canada) in
September 1999.
Dance—the art of move m e n t — h a s
a lways been, in essence, nomadic in cha-
racter (see box ) .Yet the past few ye a rs have
seen a tremendous mingling of different tra-
d i t i o n s , with artists who are increasingly
mobile in time and space.Two French cho-
The Rite of Spring , by the French choreographer Maurice Béjart.
‘I was trained in African 
s tyles by the older men 
in the village but I never
imagined I could make 
a career of it or that I could
dance in silence, without
music. Abroad, I discovered 
the music inside me.’
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
r e o gr a p h e rs , Jean-Claude Gallotta and
H e rvé Robbe, went to set up a troupe in
Ja p a n , where the A m e rican Susan Buirge
joined with a Shinto priest and an expert in
ga ga k u music to create a four-part produc-
tion based on the agricultural seasons. C l a r a
A n d e rm att from Lisbon works with Cape
Verdean dancers , and Susane Linke from
G e rm a ny is putting together a show with
Senegalese dancers.There is no shortage of
other examples.
Miniature multinationals
Dance companies are miniature multi-
n at i o n a l s. The Ta n z t h e ater of Wu p p e rt a l
( G e rm a ny) run by Pina Bausch includes
people from ten countries, whose national
traits find pride of place in her productions.
The Tanztheater creates pieces all over the
world these days. Two Burkinabé dancers
joined the Choreography Centre in Mont-
pellier (southern France) while retaining
links with their country. One of them, S a l i a
Sanou,had just completed his law studies
and passed the exam to become a police
inspector when he was invited to
France.“In 1991, you couldn’t make a
living from dance in Ouagadougou,” h e
said of Burkina Faso’s capital. “I was trai-
ned in A f rican styles by the older men in
the village but I never imagined I could
make a career of it or that I could dance in
silence, without music. Abroad, I discove-
red the music inside me.”
In Burkina Fa s o, Sanou and his col-
league Seydou Boro created a piece called
S i g n i n t o, which won a prize at the 1998
Luanda Fe s t i va l . Both dream of opening
together a choreogr a p hy centre in Ouaga-
d o u g o u , where studios but not dancers are
lacking.
“The challenge for me is how to bring
my culture and my experiences to other
people so they resonate even more with
their cultures without making modern
dance too cerebral,” says Deroure in Dur-
ban.He would like to move towards a kind
of language encompassing these different
cultures.
“Everywhere,especially in Latin Ame-
ri c a , our generation is more and more of
m i xed background and the next will be eve n
more so,” s ays Navas in Montreal. “ We ’r e
opening up to the world and exchangi n g
things more than ever before.”
Yet does this mixing process risk homo-
genizing or wat e ring down creativity? “ A b s o-
lutely not,”s ays Sola.“ Tradition without crea-
tion is steri l e . In dance as in other art i s t i c
fie l d s , transplanting one country ’s traditions
to another doesn’t wo r k , except for a few eth-
nology enthusiasts. M o d e rn dance can only
be creation and innovat i o n .” n
SHEDDING STRA I TJACK ET S
Dance, like other art-forms, has been alive since
time immemorial, never ceasing to gain new
ground. At the temple of Palaiokastro, in Crete,
dance was offered to Zeus to make the vines and
farm animals fertile. Ceremonies like this were to
be found from India to pre-Columbia America. Is it
possible to draw the line at which dance evolved
from a communal rite to a form of self-expres-
sion? What about the period in India, for example,
when dance forms originally derived from martial
arts became “performances” in their own right? 
With a touch of humour, the anthropologist
Johann Kealiinohomoku refers to classical ballet as
“a kind of ethnic dance”. Ballet became popular in
France under Louis XIV, who set up the first royal
dance academy in the West. Indeed the king him-
self danced in public until 1670. The matrix of
artistic dance, ballet also opened a new vista for cul-
tural exchange, with Italian opera troupes visiting
France in the 17th century. But it was not until the
start of the 20th century, with the break ushered in
by the birth of modern dance, that this art form
espoused influences from much farther afield.
An insatiable curiosity for universal and spiritual
forms of expression inspired the work of America n
c h o r e o g rapher and dancer Ruth Saint-Denis whose
passion for Oriental dance was first sparked by a
cigarette poster of an Egyptian goddess. Her famous
E gypt, Greece and India which she performed
across the United States in 1916 was a mix of pyr-
rhic dances, scenes from the banks of the Nile and
the Ganges and evocations of nirvana. Another of
her famous compatriots, Isadora Duncan, the high
priestess of “barefoot dance”, sought to liberate the
body from the straitjackets of the past by conjuring
up an imaginary version of ancient Greece.
This search for “truth” of the body continued
to grow throughout the 20th century, with constant
exchanges between “here” and “e l s ewhere” in a
dialogue first between the United States and
Europe and then with the Orient. In London in
1916, the Japanese dancer Michio Ito created a
modern version of a traditional Japanese n ô
d ra m a , At the Hawk’s We l l , with the Irish poet
W. B . Yeats. Another Japanese dancer, Ta k a y a
Eguchi, came to Germany to learn from the legen-
d a ry Mary Wigman and then returned to his
homeland to add a new dimension to modern
expressive dance.
In Paris, colonial exhibitions introduced the
public to Javanese, Kurdish, Persian and Armenian
dancers. After World War II, this cultural exchange
and intermingling resumed with a new dynamic.
From the late 1970s, the spectacular rise of modern
dance owed much to the seeds sown by German,
A m e r i can and Japanese dancers and teachers. 
France was a meeting point. Some of the lea-
ding figures in the French dance world were
foreign—among them Americans Susan Buirge
and Mark Tompkins, Hideyuki Yano of Japan,
Hungarian Joseph Nadj, the Afro-American Elsa
Wolliaston and Angelin Preljocaj of Albanian
origin. The impact of the movement was felt to
v a rying degrees all over Europe.
Today Europe and North America have lost
their choreography monopoly as enthusiastic
young audiences around the world throng to see
n ew forms of artistic expression. Dance is increa-
singly nomadic in chara c t e r. The dancer travels yet
works within his or her own space, while some
c h o r e o g raphers go so far as to see the stage as a
“ f ragment of mental space”. J-M. A. n
Il a été une fois , by the Vietnamese choreographer Ea Sola.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 43
C O N N E X I O N S
n
The famous picture of the distraught
woman in A l gi e rs being comforted by
a friend (left) may well be the last
still photograph to have been printed on
front pages all over the wo r l d . On the
d ay it was taken, September 23, 1 9 9 7 ,t h e
Agence France Presse photogr a p h e r
Hocine was the only photographer or
cameraman on the scene.Another equally
c e l e b r ated and fairly recent agency photo
(below) shows a young man singlehan-
dedly blocking an advancing column of
tanks in Beijing on June 4, 1989 during
the Chinese student movement. It was
taken in quite different circumstances.
The top photo, taken by a press photo-
grapher working for an agency, is unique.
The Chinese protester, on the other hand,
was photographed in virtually identical
shots taken by three photogr a p h e rs wo r k i n g
for three leading agencies (Associated Press,
Magnum and Sipa-Presse) as well as by a
cameraman from Bri t a i n ’s Independent
Television News (ITN).
Hawked around
to the highest bidder
W hy is this difference import a n t , yo u
m ay ask, since the impact of both photos is
strong? The answer is that an exclusive
p h o t o,w h at journalists call “a scoop”,can be
h awked around to the highest bidder wo r l d-
wide and earn many thousands of dollars.
This can’t happen when similar photos have
been taken by several photogr a p h e rs. If the
man who took the A l gi e rs photo had not
been a salaried employee of an agency which
charges its customers by subscription rat h e r
than on a picture-by-picture basis (see box
page 44), both he and the agency could
h ave sold the photo for a fort u n e .
Are any gr e at exclusive photos being
taken these days—the kind of scoops whose
i m p a c t , fa m e , composition and ability to
w Senior lecturer in the Information and
Communication department of the University of Paris-X,
Nanterre (France)
An Algiers suburb, September 23, 1997: a distraught woman who has lost several family members in a
massacre is comforted by a relative. The photo appeared on front pages all over the world.
A young man halts a column of tanks on June 4, 1989, 
during the student movement in Beijing.
PHOTOJOURN A L ISM :
T HE LAST LA P ?
w Edgar Roskis
Supply of photo reports outstrips demand, competition from television is intense. 
Can photojournalism survive?
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
C O N N E X I O N S
capture a moment have encapsulated infor-
m ation and symbolism in a single aesthetic
object? Perhaps not. In 1967, F r e n c h m a n
R aymond Depardon and British photo-
grapher Don McCullin were the only mem-
b e rs of their profession cove ring the war in
B i a f r a .1 In 1994, s e veral hundred photo-
gr a p h e rs descended on Rwanda in aircraft
c h a rtered for military - h u m a n i t a rian pur-
p o s e s. G o o d - b ye to the exclusive photo.
W h at ’s more, these photogr a p h e rs arri ve d
three months after the genocide began on
A p ril 6 and could only send back depres-
singly similar pictures of the afterm ath of the
tragedy—the exodus and the epidemics,
not the event that sparked them off.
Exponential growth
P h o t o gr a p hy is widely considered to
h ave been invented in 1839.Since then the
number of photographic images has gr ow n
e x p o n e n t i a l l y. It is increasingly hard, d e s-
pite photogr a p h e rs ’s k i l l s , to come up with
a picture that doesn’t echo an earlier one.
Because of the laws of supply and demand
this has led to the situation in which increa-
sing output of news pictures goes hand in
hand with a decrease in the price they fetch.
Does a photo—a silent image, with a
b rief caption or no caption at all—have
a ny intrinsic meaning? Imagine a shot of a
h o rseman who is caught by the camera
whipping his hors e . Is he a coward fle e i n g
the enemy or is he charging bravely forwa r d ?
It all depends,of cours e ,on the caption that
goes with the picture and its credibility.
Take the example of the photos that
were long thought to show the “ Ve l ’d ’ H i v ”
stadium in Pa ris at the time when French
Jews were held there for deport ation in July
1 9 4 2 .2 N ow we know that they show a mee-
ting held two ye a rs lat e r.And what should
we make of the photo analysed by French
philosopher Régis Debray in his book L’ O e i l
naïf (“The Naive Eye”) showing a group of
Pa risian strollers looking nonchalantly at a
bus with an open rear plat f o rm? The scene
a p p e a rs banal, except when we know that
the packed bus was taking Jews to the inter-
nment camp at Drancy, outside Pa ri s.
Herein lies one of the ove rriding we a k-
nesses of photojournalism and of photo-
gr a p hy in general, d e s c ribed by the Ger-
m a ny philosopher Walter Benjamin as
“The image in an age when it can be tech-
nically reproduced”. “I’m just an image,
nothing more,” is all it says to us.
Despite this draw b a c k ,a number of pho-
tos have had a decisive effect on public opi-
nion and changed the course of history.O n e
notable example is the photo of the naked
girl running away from the Vietnamese vil-
lage of Trang Bang which had just been
bombed by mistake with napalm by South
Vietnamese aircraft on June 8, 1 9 7 2 . It wa s
taken by a Vietnamese AP photogr a p h e r ,
Nick Ut.A n o t h e r ,d ating from four ye a rs
earlier and showing Saigon police chief
N g u yen Loan shooting dead a “ s u s p e c t ” at
point-blank range, was taken by Eddie
A d a m s , an A m e rican working for A P.3 A
third shows the naked body of an A m e ri-
can soldier being dragged through the
streets of Mogadishu.It humiliated the Uni-
ted States and turned U. S . public opinion
against the presence of A m e rican troops in
S o m a l i a .
The strength and the weakness of pho-
t o j o u rnalism stem from its capacity to
t rigger a sudden earthquake in public
o p i n i o n — p r ovided that the wo r l d ’s maga-
zines and daily newspapers get hold of the
photo and circulate it. But this key role
has now been taken over by television.
E ven if screened images are often less
s h a rp than many famous still photos,
television gives them added weight and
viewer interest via sound, commentary
and in some cases on-the-spot report i n g .
‘Telepresence’
From an aesthetic viewpoint, p h o t o-
gr a p hy is eve ry bit as good as television
r e p o rt i n g .A photograph can be looked at
again and again, whereas the televised
image fades from the screen. H owe ve r , a
good television report has a didactic adva n-
t a g e : it can explain and teach us about
e ve n t s. Since the 1960s, television sets
h ave become a common household item,
and TV reports reach vast audiences.
M e a n w h i l e , the ingredients of photogr a p hy
PHOTOJOURN A L ISM: HOW IT WORK S
There are three kinds of photojournalism. The
first and oldest kind relies on individual free-
lance photographers who come up with ideas,
shoot a feature and then offer it to various media,
mostly magazines and sometimes daily papers,
for publication. In some cases the media will com-
mission them to produce a report in line with their
special interest or skills.
The second kind comprises groups of photo-
g raphers working in an agency. The oldest and most
prestigious agency is Magnum, which was founded
in 1945 and is the only agency run as a photogra-
phers’ co-operative. Gamma, set up in 19 67 by Ray-
mond Depardon and his associates, is another
famous agency. Sygma and Sipa-Presse were
founded later. All these agencies are based in Pa r i s .
Their way of paying photographers and hence their
working methods are ra d i cally changing. The agency
and the photographer consult with the editors of a
client publication before a job, and usually split the
cost of the assignment as well as the potential pro-
fits originating from publications which negotiate
reproduction fees on a ca s e - b y - case basis. They
keep the copyright to all their photos. This 50 - 50
agreement has revolutionized major assignments.
The third kind of photojournalism is done by the
big news agencies—Associated Press (American),
Reuters (British) and Agence France Presse (Fr e n c h )
—which are often known as wire services. The
media pay subscriptions to the agencies for unli-
mited use of agency photos and news.
News agency photographers are on a regular
s a l a ry, and like most agency journalists their names
are not widely known. They are paid at a fixed ra t e
irrespective of the sales of their photos. Recently,
international photofeature agencies such as
Gamma, Sygma and Sipa-Presse have also put
some of their photographers on fixed salaries. The
turnover of each of these three international agen-
cies is nearly $20 million a year. n
W EBSI T E
OF THE MON T H
h t t p : / / w w w. u n f p a . o r g
On October 12, world population is estimated
to reach 6 billion. This benchmark is just one
of the themes covered by the website of the United
Nations Population Fund (UNFPA), the leading
international agency which helps developing coun-
tries deal with demographic issues. Family planning,
access to healthcare and equality for women are
just some of the missions of UNFPA, which was
created 30 years ago. The agency warns that the
next decade will be crucial: world population could
reach between 8 to 12 billion depending upon the
social programmes and political decisions made in
the next few years. n
2. More than 12,000 French Jews were rounded
up on July 16 and 17, 1942,and taken to the
Vélodrome d’Hiver stadium (the Vel’ d’Hiv’) in
Paris. From there,most of them were taken to a
transit camp in the suburb of Drancy, and then
sent to German concentration camps.
3.Both these photos won a Pulitzer Prize, the
most famous award in U.S.journalism.
1 . A conflict lasting from 1967 to 1969 when the
Biafra region of Nigeria attempted to break away
from the central gove rn m e n t .
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 45
C O N N E X I O N S
A 10-year-old Vietnamese girl, Kim Phuc, running down a country road had ripped her flaming clothes from her body after being burned by napalm. 
This 1972 photo brought home to Americans the horror of the Viet Nam war.
are fine craftsmanship, the courage of the
p h o t o grapher and the high level of skill
required to capture a unique moment, n o t
a second too late or too early.
W h at French writer Jean-Louis We i s s-
berg calls “ t e l e p r e s e n c e ”has swept away the
era of printed magazines. E ven the most
p r e s t i gious magazines no longer shape
public opinion, except on ve ry rare occa-
s i o n s.W h at Debray calls the “ v i d e o s p h e r e ”
has taken over “hot news”, l e aving photo-
j o u rnalism to a few independent photo-
gr a p h e rs who have a hard time getting their
work published.
So is photojournalism on its last legs?
Perhaps not, but to use a metaphor from
athletics maybe it’s on the last lap.The big
photo agencies such as Gamma, Sygma
and Sipa-Presse (see box on facing page)
h ave been forced to turn to areas out-
side journ a l i s m , like illustrating books,
d i c t i o n a ries and ency c l o p a e d i a s , wo r k i n g
for the communications departments of
public and semi-public institutions, p h o-
t o graphing the tempestuous lives of cele-
b ri t i e s , or even doing plain laborat o ry
wo r k .C e l e b rity photos accounted for 60
per cent of Sygma’s turn over before it
was taken over two ye a rs ago, while news
photos earned less than 10 per cent.
These agencies are now so economi-
cally weakened that they are easy prey for
outside inve s t o rs.A major investment gr o u p
looking to break into the field can buy out
a famous photo agency and gain far more
than a network of photogr a p h e rs and a
stock of photos. It can also acquire a pres-
t i gious name which is wo rth far more than
the financial costs of the takeove r.
Banks took a sizeable stake in Gamma
in 1997. More import a n t l y,m e g a - c o m p a-
nies such as Bill Gat e s ’ Microsoft and its
d atabank Corbis have been especially active
in trying to get their hands on major photo
a r c h i ve s. In June 1999, Corbis bought
S y g m a ,whose photos by its salaried staff are
all free of copyri g h t .These photos can be
reproduced ad infin i t u m ,without bri n gi n g
a ny royalties to the photogr a p h e rs who took
t h e m .These companies can draw freely on
such huge archives to obtain low-cost illus-
t r ations for their multimedia activities or else
re-sell these pictures far more cheaply than
o t h e rs on the market,e ven if they are dat e d .
Wire services
“It’s hard to tell the difference these
days between a fresh news picture taken
at gr e at expense and a much cheaper
photo that has come from an archive,”
says Roger Thérond,former head of the
French weekly magazine Pa ri s - M at c h. I n
fact too much photojournalism is killing
photojournalism, just as too many taxes
kill taxation.The fact remains,however,
t h at the death of the written press has
been predicted for the past twenty years
yet it is still alive—and abundantly illus-
trated.So how do things really stand?
Perhaps the past has caught up with us.
The gat e k e e p e rs of photojournalism did
not emerge ove rn i g h t . In 1903, F r e n c h
e n gineer Édouard Belin invented a machine
which could transmit photos by telephone
from one place to another, like sending a
fax today.The machine enabled all the wo r l-
d ’s daily newspapers to receive pictures in
“real time” for publication the next day.
“Wire serv i c e s ” such as A s s o c i ated Press,
R e u t e rs and Agence France Presse were set
up to serve as communications netwo r k s
and feed the media pictures via this pro-
c e s s.
These agencies, n ow virtually the sole
p l aye rs in news photogr a p hy, continue to
c over world events alongside the big tele-
vision netwo r k s.The hundreds of wo r k e rs
on their staff would claim to be simply
“doing a job”. Most newspapers are sat i s-
fied with what they produce. M e a n w h i l e ,
p h o t o j o u rnalism in the strict sense—tel-
ling a story with still photos—is now the pre-
s e rve of a handful of talented art i s t s. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
The most recent meeting of the G8 group 
(the world’s eight leading industrial powers)
decided for the first time that globalization
needed to be “humanized”. Does that mean
it’s inhuman right now?
It’s very human and very creative in
the eyes of the strong and very inhuman
for the weak. It creates unprecedented
polarization.
A third of the world’s population has
substantially raised its standard of living
and expanded its cultural and technologi-
cal resources.The other side of the coin is
that the latest UNDP Human Development
Report showed a massive growth in both
inequality and poverty as well as social
exclusion and marginalization all over the
world,with a few big exceptions including
India, China and Chile.
Forty per cent of the planet’s popula-
tion lives in misery on less than two dol-
lars a day. Within this category, a growing
number live in extreme poverty, especial-
ly cultural poverty. No one in this plight
can make any use of the emerging infor-
mation society. So “humanizing” globali-
zation means harnessing all the enormous
creative might of the new technologies, of
new economic productivities and of
worldwide communication through the
Internet so that it benefits people outside
the most advanced, educated and sophis-
ticated sectors of the most powerful coun-
tries. But for the moment, this is just a
pipe dream. We’re told we have to do
things differently, but the effects of such
discrimination are still not being correc-
ted. In fact quite the opposite is happe-
ning.
Does this discrimination match the divide
between so-called “generic labour” and “self-
programmable labour”?
Not entirely. S e l f - p r o gr a m m a b l e
labour has enough information, educa-
tion and culture to adapt to constantly
changing technological and professional
conditions. But in a system which has
become purely based on the individual,
without any social safety net or solidarity,
belonging to this category doesn’t mean
you’re invulnerable: if a major incident
occurs, such as a physical or psychologi-
cal illness or a family crisis, you find your-
self on the other side of the fence. Many
middle-class children, for example, start
taking drugs between the age of 18 and
20 and end up in prison, thus heading
right down the path to social exclusion.
Generic labour refers to workers who,
because they don’t have a specific qualifi-
cation and an adequate level of education
and culture, cannot fit into the predomi-
nant system of production—machines
can or could replace them. Within this
category, there are two groups. There are
those who are still relatively protected,
who keep their jobs because they work in
institutions or live in countries that help
and protect them, and guarantee a decent
standard of living. There are also those
who live either in run-down city suburbs
in rich countries or in poverty-stricken
M A NUEL CAS T EL L S :
T HE CI T IZ EN VERSUS
T HE MACHINE
As the technological revolution revolutionizes economic life and communications and shakes 
industrial society to its foundations, a noted Spanish sociologist asks where the citizen stands 
in the emerging ‘information society’
regions and nations without the infra-
structure or companies that make pos-
sible and guarantee a transition towards
the information society. Such people are
totally excluded. That social exclusion
comes from lack of work.
Why do you say capitalism is much more
brutal today than it was in the past?
Because it’s broken the social
contract.These days, networks mean you
can connect everything that carries value
for this dominant system, thus making
those connected to it extremely dynamic.
But this structure also means that any-
thing for which it has little regard—indi-
viduals, regions, sectors and companies—
d o n ’t get connected and are thereby
condemned.And since it manages to take
control of anything which could be of
value to it, capitalism can afford to be
extremely choosy and to impose its own
rules.This is helped by the fact that states
and institutions, political or para-politi-
c a l , which acted as a counterwe i g h t
during the Industrial Revolution, have
very little influence over worldwide com-
munications, capital movements, techno-
l o gical development and production.
Might is right, a purely Darwinian logic .
Is anyone exempt from this logic?
In a way, it takes root independently of
a company ’s will and those who resist are
c rushed by competition because the net-
works consist only of the strong. And it
takes root inside the firms themselve s ,
independent of managers or outside share-
h o l d e rs. Look at advanced capitalism in
Silicon Valley which, i n c i d e n t a l l y, e m b o-
dies in a sense the 1960s Marxist ideal of
wo r k e rs ’ m a n a g e m e n t . The people who
work in Silicon Valley are paid to a large
extent in shares rather than a regular sala-
The people who work in
Silicon Valley are paid to a
large extent in shares ra t h e r
than a regular salary. So it’s in
their interest to push their way
upward in the firm, even if it
means kicking a colleague out
of a job on the grounds that he
or she isn’t productive enough.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G  T O …
ry. So it’s in their interest to push their way
up in the firm , e ven if it means kicking a
colleague out of a job on the grounds that
he or she isn’t productive enough.
Does this illustrate a trend which you
emphasize, namely the extraordinary
individualization of people’s destinies?
Setting aside current myths about the
impact of the new techno-economic sys-
tem on jobs, usually measured in terms of
falling unemployment, the fundamental
change lies in the greater flexibility of
labour relations.The way companies ope-
r ate in networks—both internal and
external—is destroying the notion of a
stable, reliable job which dates from the
Industrial Revolution.
In Bri t a i n , the birthplace of that revo-
l u t i o n , 55 per cent of the workforce is
i nvo l ved in va rious kinds of temporary,
p a rt-time or freelance wo r k . The traditio-
nal model of organized labour is no longer
the ru l e . The same thing is happening in
cities in poor countri e s , which are beco-
ming more and more urbanized.There the
so-called informal economy holds sway
and labour relations revo l ve round the
l o n g - t e rm lack of stable and regular wo r k .
Economic activity in such countries can be
quite pri m i t i ve but some of it is ve ry
a d va n c e d .
Whether we like it or not, job fle x i b i l i-
CAS T ELLS ON THE
UNI T ED NAT IONS
I think international organizations like UNESCO
have a really important part to play. They can
be a link between governments which are still,
after all, political instruments, and demands based
on people’s ideals, especially in the fields of deve-
lopment and peace.
So they must be meeting-places but, increa-
singly, also forums which give rise to pra c t i ca l
projects. For example, everyone agrees educa t i o n
is the key to reducing inequality and exclusion. But
what exactly does education mean? What must be
done on a world scale so the kind of education
needed reaches the two-thirds of humanity who
currently have no access to it? The response must
indeed come from governments. But UNESCO is
the very kind of organization within which a world
education strategy can be drawn up.
Bodies like the International Monetary Fund,
the World Bank or the G8 group of countries are
managing systems of worldwide exchanges but
they concentrate on technological innovation,
economic productivity and growth of informa-
tion. Their power must be balanced by interna-
tional organizations like UNES CO , the World Health
Organization and the International Labour Orga-
nisation, which could draw up a new world social
and cultural contract, as the other bodies did for
economics and technology. But they will only
succeed in this if they acquire similar legitimacy
and authority by using the might of the netw o r k s .
n
ty is so much more efficient than previous
a rrangements that firms which still opera-
te with a mainly salaried workforce and
stable and established working methods
are doomed to failure by the laws of com-
p e t i t i o n . F i rms are also relying more and
more on a core of skilled wo r k e rs they
want to keep (and to whom they gi ve
stable jobs) and on a huge mass of tempo-
r a ry and sub-contracted wo r k e rs.W h at we
h ave is an individualization of the relat i o n-
ship between salaried wo r k e rs and firm s
on one side and among self-employed wo r-
k e rs on the other. E ve rybody sub-
contracts with eve rybody else.
But this trend introduces a totally unequal
balance of power between workers and
companies. . . .
Yes, but also between workers them-
selves. The strongest have real bargaining
power in the market, depending on what
they can contribute to their own or any
other firm.The unskilled don’t have such
power or any real power of collective bar-
gaining through trade unions. In the now-
dominant pri vate sector, unions these
days have only a meagre role and union
membership is steadily falling.This is why
we must resist shrinking the social securi-
ty safety-net and support a transition
from protecting individuals who wo r k
(the situation in most countries) to pro-
tecting people whether they work or not.
You paint a very gloomy picture. . . .
Saying that these changes only lead to
social exclusion isn’t the whole story.
They are extremely useful for very many
people—the worldwide image- and opi-
nion-makers. This is not a small elite or
oligarchy, since between 30 and 40 per
cent of the population in countries like
the United States and France belong to it.
They’ve gained huge opportunities not
The way companies operate in
n e tworks—both internal and
external—is destroying the
notion of a stable, reliable job
which dates from the Industrial
R e v o l u t i o n
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
identity which it called citizenship. And it
protected its citizens. But globalization
means the state can no longer guarantee
such protection or provide the meaning
necessary to foster citizenship.
Two reactions are possible to the buil-
ding of an inform ation society which
gives pride of place to competition. For
the strongest, those with money and
power, competition can give purpose to
their lives if they develop a totally indivi-
dualistic, even narcissistic and consume-
rist identity, becoming big earners and big
spenders. All networked societies are basi-
cally individualistic. It’s the liberal and
libertarian ideology of the dominant tech-
nical and economic elite.
But all around them, a whole mass of
people either lack the resources to
connect to this individualism or else reject
it. They give meaning to their lives by
building community identities. T h e y
build them on cultural practices which
express simple, sturdy values, such as
God, country, ethnic identity, land and
family. This makes them feel protected in
some way against the worldwide changes
over which they have lost all control.
But these identities are ambivalent. . . .
They can be open because they’re
engaged in dialogue with people who have
other identities. But they can be dogmatic
when expressed in a rigid, inward-looking
way which shuts out all other identities.
That’s the crux of the problem: everybo-
dy can’t be Argentine or Serb, Catholic or
Muslim, female or homosexual, so the
strong affirmation of a unique identity as
only for economic but also social, intel-
lectual and cultural creativity. As well as
generating social exclusion, the technolo-
gical revolution has creative and libera-
ting aspects that we should not ignore.
Such as?
The Internet has reduced the power
of governments and the big media mono-
polies to control people. One result is
more openness, especially where political
corruption is concerned. The powerful
are used to spying on ordinary citizens,
but now citizens can spy on the powerful.
Work can be more independent and pro-
fessional advancement more varied. We
don’t have to stay stuck for life in the
same bu r e a u c r a cy and only adva n c e
through seniority.The educational level of
women is rising to an extraordinary
extent (most university graduates in the
U.S. are now women, for example).Their
professional advance is continuing.
D i s c ri m i n ation is still there, but it’s
dwindling. It’s better than being shut
away at home.
One of the main points of your work 
is that the information society seems 
to harbour the seeds of opposition to itself. 
How is that?
The process is very complex. The
modern state—whether liberal, socialist
or Marxist—has been built on a denial of
basic and historical identities. The state
made the nat i o n , not the other way
round. But it also managed to fuse these
original identities into a new abstract
A MONUMEN TA L W ORK
The publication of Manuel Castells’ monumental
trilogy about information technology and the
global economy, The Information Age: Economy,
So c i e ty and Culture ,1 a t t racted wide attention and
superlatives from reviewers impressed by the eru-
dition and breadth of this “encyclopaedic work”.
Castells’ aims might indeed seem grandiose. He
says he wants to “understand our world”—all of it—to
t ry to “give meaning to what appears to us today as
terrible chaos.” In the last quarter of a century, he says,
“a technological revolution—information technology —
has transformed our ways of thinking, consuming,
buying and selling, running businesses, communi-
cating, living, dying, making war and making love.”
He explains why and how these processes have
come about in three volumes of over 300 pages
each, the result of 12 years’ interdisciplinary
research which took him all over the world. He
says the structure of industrial society—its econo-
mies, political units, industrial complexes and cul-
t u ral identities—always revolved round centra l
points but that these are now disappearing. In
what he calls the “informational society,” a system
of networks develops in every sector. “The power
of flows overwhelms the flows of power,” he says.
Such iconoclasm is the product of an unusual
intellectual journey. In 1962, the 20-year-old Cas-
tells, “a shade Marxist but not Leninist” and to a far
greater extent “anarchist and libertarian”, left his
native Spain to study in France. He was expelled
from France in May 1968 but returned two years
later.
By chance, he gravitated towards urban socio-
l o gy and became one of its leading exponents. His
La Question urbaine ( 1972) was translated into 10
languages, and The City and the Gra s s ro o t s won the
C. Wright Mills Prize in 1983 for the best social
science book published in the United States. To d a y
he is professor of sociology and city and regional
planning at the Center for Western European Stu-
dies at the University of California at Berkeley.
A friendly and persuasive man, with an impish
sense of irony, Castells refuses to act the guru and
points out that his work has limits. “Every time an
intellectual has tried to answer the question ‘what
should we do?’ it’s led to disaster,” he says. n
1. The 3 volumes, published by Blackwell, Oxford, UK,
are: The Rise of the Network Society (1996), The Power of
Identity (1997) and End of Millennium (1998).
This photo and photo on facing page feature in a report by Swedish photographer Lars Tunbjork 
on the dehumanization of the office environment.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
October 1999 -The UNESCO Courier 49
T A L K I N G  T O …
the only way to give meaning to one’s life
leads to fragmentation into tribes, to a
sort of collective atomization.
The only answer to this major threat is
to build bridges between these very diffe-
rent identities.The main challenge for the
state is to establish not only a political
contract between citizens but a cultural
contract so that all these cultural codes
and multiple identities can communicate
with each other. Only with such a
contract can a state guarantee the coexis-
tence of these identities while recognizing
their individual expression. But in view of
the state’s historical mode of construc-
tion, it is ill equipped to do this.
In view of this dual threat of exclusion and
fragmentation, how can a shared awareness
develop and lead to global political action?
This is the key question and I don’t
have an answer. I’ve based my work on
observation, which isn’t forecasting.What
I see is a lot of resistance to the grip of the
network system. Some of these networks
no longer obey any human logic whatsoe-
ver: they have become what I would des-
cribe as automata.
The best example is the world finan-
cial market. It controls everything and no
one controls it, not even governments.
First, it pools together money from all
kinds of ori gi n s , not just fin a n c i e rs ’
money but everyone’s, including our own
(in the form of savings or pension funds).
Computer programmes and electrical cir-
cuits then keep it constantly mov i n g
around. Finally, and above all, it obeys
rules which are only partly economic,
because what I call information turbulen-
ce plays a crucial part. Various players,
including political players, send messages
and create images which lead a multitude
of other players to react in the financial
market. But they don’t act in concert and
no one can say for sure how the market
will react. M a ny playe rs , some more
powerful than others, can thus influence
the world in which these financial tran-
sactions take place.They can follow stra-
tegies, but nobody can control the process
or the outcome of the game. An automa-
ton has been created.
So what happens to politics?
Today politics are not defined by the
media but within media space, which is
occupied by the countless and ever more
varied television stations and, increasin-
gly, the Internet.So what comes into poli-
tical existence—in other words what
forms into a political opinion in people’s
minds—depends solely on what appears
in the media. Traditional political stake-
holders are adapting to this new media
context. But they don’t play leading roles
in it at all.They’ve been joined by a mass
of lobbies, interest groups and professio-
nal organizations which specialize in crea-
ting and manipulating messages and
images.These groups create new inform a-
tion turbu l e n c e , which stems from their
d e t e rmined strat e gies and how indepen-
All netw o r ked societies 
are basically individualistic. 
It’s the liberal and liberta r i a n
i d e o l o gy of the dominant
t e c h n i cal and economic elite.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50 The UNESCO Courier - October 1999
T A L K I N G  T O …
I WISH TO SUBSCRIBE TO the UNESCO Courier
Language: English French Spanish
Rates (postage included):
Industrialized countries: Developing countries or students 
1 year: 211French francs (€32,15) instead of 264FF* (11 issues including 1 double issue) (Please send copy of your card):
2 years:396 French francs (€60,35) instead of 528FF* (22 issues including 2 double issues) 1 year: 132 French francs (€20,10)
Binder: 72French francs (€11) (for 11 issues including 1 double issue) 2 years: 211 French francs (€32,15)
I enclose payment: (in French francs only) by
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque) Visa Mastercard Eurocard
N° Expiry date: Date and signature:
Name First name
Address
Postal code City
Optional
Age: Occupation: Teachers and students
Special field: Level:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering the optional questions above.
(*) Total cover price
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to:
the UNESCO Courier Subscription Services, 31,rue François Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are opposite this order form.
"
dent the media are. But the final political
result—the impact on decisions citizens
take—has no relation to the wishes of each
of the playe rs. I t ’s the “ a u t o m at i c ” result of
interactions that nobody can control.
How do people react to this “automatism”?
I’ve noticed they do two things. First,
they vote to express their opposition.The
main changes brought about by elec-
tions—caused by shifts of mood among
only 5-10 per cent of voters—are the
result of opposition to a past event or
decision, not of support for a future poli-
cy. Such protest votes show that citizens
feel on the defensive towards the political
system. Secondly, they rate the system’s
players right at the bottom of the league
table of what they respect in society.They
think they’re corrupt, expensive and inef-
ficient.As a result, more and more people
are ceasing to see politics as a way of
changing their lives.
What about those who do want to change
things? 
Our generation has been conv i n c e d
t h at the state is the main instrument for
applying a political programme which
meets the expectations and needs of civil
s o c i e t y. But what can the state do today
faced with the financial machine and the
media machine? It has extremely limited
room for manoeuvre. People who want to
change things or do more in life than just
e a rn money are developing a new way of
conducting politics, this time without any
m e d i ation from the stat e . They have come
to act politically by taking pragmatic ethi-
cal action, working to bring about real
change in a small geographical area, at a
s p e c i fic time or in a limited fie l d . Of cour-
se such an approach only brings about ve ry
small changes in comparison with all the
changes that are necessary, but at least it’s
e f f e c t i ve . I t ’s a practical policy designed to
b ring immediate results. S u c c e s s f u l
examples of this approach include NGOs
like Doctors of the World and the Jubilee
2000 move m e n t , which has achieved sub-
stantial results in its campaign to alleviat e
the debt burden on the poorest countri e s.
Can such a piecemeal policy make a dent in
this big issue?
My bet is that all these piecemeal and
isolated activities,which involve hundreds
of thousands of people, will gradually
come together to form networks. I hope
the growth of networks will eventually
include those which want to fight the
harmful effects of other networks. That
alongside the networks of money, techno-
logy and information, alternative but just
as powerful (and so just as efficient) net-
works will develop and convey alternative
values that will steadily build new global
political strategies.
But some fundamental trends are
emerging even before we reach this final
stage. Look at the women’s movement. It
managed to set off the biggest cultural
r e volution in human history without
using traditional political means.
However, the changes in cultural prac-
tices and codes, first inside wo m e n ’s
minds, were so far-reaching that they’ve
now been incorporated into political sys-
tems, at least where those systems are
dynamic and democratic. n
Interview by René Lefort
Director of the UNESCO Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
L I S T  O F S A L E S A N D S U B S C R I P T I O N A G E N T S
Subscr ipt ions can be pai d to the subscr ipt ion agent  in  your  c ountry who wil l  su ppl y rates in local  currenc y on re q u e s t
A R G E N T I N A : Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UN E S C O,
Tucumán 1685, 1050 Buenos A i r e s. Fa x :3 7 1 - 8 1 9 4 .
AU S T R A L I A : Hunter Publicat i o n s , 58A Gipps Street,
C o l l i n g wood VIC 3066. Fa x : 419 7154. ISA A u s t r a l i a ,
PO Box 709,To owong QLD 4066. Fa x : 371 5566.
United Nations A s s o c. of A u s t r a l i a / V i c t o rian Div. ,
179 St George's Road,
N. F i t z r oy VIC 3068. Fa x : 481 7693.
AU S T R I A : Gerold & Co, I m p o rt & Export ,
Z e i t s c h ri f t e n / Pe ri o d i c a l s , Graben 31, A-1011 V i e n n a .
Fa x : 512 47 31 29
B E L G I U M : Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Bru s s e l s.
Fa x : 538 08 41.
B R A Z I L : Fundaco Getulio Va r g a s , Editora Divisão de Ve n d a s ,
Caixa Postal 62.591, 22257-970 Rio de Janeiro RJ.
Fa x :5 5 1 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA : Renouf Publishing Company Ltd,
5369 ch.Canotek Road,Unit 1,Ottawa,Ont K1J 9J3.
Fax:(1-613) 745 7660. Faxon Canada,POBox 2382,London,
Ont.N6A 5A7. Fax:(1-519) 472 1072.
C H I L E : U n i ve rs i t a ria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10220,
S a n t i a g o. Fa x : 681 9091.
C H I N A : China National Publicat i o n s ,I m p o rt & Export
C o rp. , PO Box 88, 16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 100020.
Fa x : 010 65063101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30,111 27
Prague 1.
D E N M A R K : M u n k s g a a r d ,N o rre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148,
DK-1016 Kobenhavn K. Fa x : 12 93 87.
F I N L A N D : S t o c k m a n n / A k ateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23,
SF-00371 Helsinki. Fa x : +358 9 121 4450.
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF-01641 Va n t a a .
Fa x : 852 7990.
G E R M A N Y: G e rman Commission for UN E S C O, C o l m a n t s t r.
1 5 , D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 63 69 12.
Uno Ve r l a g, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55,
D-53115 Bonn. Fa x : 21 74 92.
G R E E C E : L i b r a i rie Kauffmann SA, M a u v r o k o r d atou 9,
GR-106 78 A t h e n s. Fa x : 38 33 967.
G UAT E M A L A : Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con
la UN E S C O, 3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1,A p a rtado Postal 2630,
G u atemala City.
HONG KO N G : Hong Kong Gove rnment Inform ation Svcs.
D e p t . , 1 Bat t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
H U N G A RY: Librotrade K F T, Pe riodical Import / K ,
POB 126, H-1656 Budapest. Fa x :2 5 6 - 8 7 - 2 7 .
I N D I A : O rient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions A c c o u n t ) ,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estat e ,B o m b ay 400 038.
Fa x : 26 91 278.
Oxford Book & Stat i o n e ry Co, Code No D 8208052,
Scindia House, New Delhi 110 001. Fa x : 33 22 639.
I S R A E L : L i t e r a ry Transactions Inc. , C/0 Steimatsky Ltd.,
PO Box 1444, Bnei Brak 51114. Fa x : 52 81 187.
I TA LY: L i c o s a / L i b r e ria Comm. Sansoni SPA ,
Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-50125 Florence. Fa x :6 4 - 1 2 - 5 7 .
J A PA N : E a s t e rn Book Service Inc. , Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
3 13 Hongo 3 Chome, B u n k yo Ku ,To k yo 113. Fa x :8 1 8 - 0 8 6 4 .
KO R E A : Korean National Commission for UN E S C O,
CPO Box 64, Seoul 100-600. Fa x : 568 7454.
L U X E M B U R G : M e s s a g e ries Paul Kraus, BP 2022,
L-1020 Luxe m b o u r g . Fa x : 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA : Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36,
26 Republic Street,Valletta CMR 01. Fa x : 24 61 82.
M AU R I T I U S : Nalanda Co. L t d . , 30 Bourbon Street,
Po rt Louis. Fa x : 212 1313.
M O RO C C O : UN E S C O, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat
Fax:212-767 03 75, Tel.:212-767 03 74/72.
M E X I C O : Librería El Correo de la UN E S C O S A , Col Roma,
G u a n a j u ato 72, Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF.
Fa x :2 6 4 - 0 9 - 1 9 .
N E T H E R L A N D S : S wets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830,
2160 SZ Lisse. Fa x :2 5 2 4 - 1 5 8 8 8 .
T i j d s c h riftcentrale Wijck B V, I n t .S u b s. S e rv i c e ,W
G r a c h t s t r a at 1C, 6221 CT Maastri c h t . Fa x : 32 50 103.
NEW ZEALAND: GP Legi s l ation Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 12418,T h o rn d o n , We l l i n g t o n .
Fa x : 496 56 98.
NORWAY : S wets Norge A S ,Ø s t e n s j ø vein 18-0606 Oslo,
PO Box 6512,Etterstad. Fax:47 22 97 45 45.
P O RT U G A L : L i v r a ria Po rtugal (Dias & Andrade Lda),
Rua do Carmo 70 74, 1200 Lisboa. Fa x : 34 70 264.
R U S S I A : Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39,
M o s c ow 113095.
SOUTH A F R I C A : I n t e rn ational Subscription Serv i c e s ,
PO Box 41095, Craighall 2024. Fa x : 880 6248.
Mast Publicat i o n s , PO Box 901, Parklands 2121.
Fa x : 886 4512.
S PA I N : Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37,
28001 Madri d . Fa x :9 1 5 7 5 - 3 9 - 9 8 .
L i b r e ria Al A n d a l ú s , Roldana 3 y 4, 410091 Sevilla.
Fa x :9 5 4 2 2 - 5 3 - 3 8 .
Los Amigos de la UN E S C O, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd.,
48011 Bilbao. Fa x :9 4 4 2 7 - 5 1 - 5 9 / 6 9
SRI LANKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam,
Gardiner Mawat h a , Colombo 2. Fa x : 44 78 48.
S W E D E N : We n n e r gren Williams A B , PO Box 1305,
S-171 25 Solna. Fa x : 27 00 71.
S W I T Z E R L A N D : Dynapresse Marketing SA, ( e x - N av i l l e
S A ) , 38 av V i b e rt , CH-1227 Carouge. Fa x : 308 08 59.
E d i group SA, Case Postale 393, CH-1225 Chêne-Bourg.
Fa x : 348 44 82.
Europa Ve r l a g, Ramistrasse 5, CH-8024 Züri c h .
Fa x : 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG ,W i s s e n s c h a f t l .B u c h h a n d l u n g,
Pe t e rs graben 31, CH-4009 Basel. Fa x : 306 12 34.
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E C O,
Chemin du Lacuez, CH-1807 Blonay. Fa x : 943 36 05.
T H A I L A N D : Suksapan Pa n i t , Mansion 9, R a j a d a m n e rn
Ave n u e , Bangkok 2. Fa x : 28 11 639.
T U N I S I A : Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de
l ’UN E S C O, 2 2 , rue de l’Angleterr e , 1000RP Tu n i s.
Fa x : 33 10 14
UNITED KINGDOM: The Stat i o n e ry Office Publicat i o n s
C t r e . , 51 Nine Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR.
Fa x : 873 84 63.
UNITED STAT E S : B e rnan A s s o c i at e s , 4611-F A s s e m b l y
D ri ve , Lanham MD 20706-4391. Fa x :4 5 9 - 0 0 5 6 .
U R U G UAY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe riodicals A c c o u n t ,
Maldonado 1090, M o n t e v i d e o. Fa x : 90 59 83.
V E N E Z U E L A : UN E S C O/ C R E S A L C ,E d i f. A s ov i n c a r ,
Av Los Chorr o s ,C ruce C/C A c u e d u c t o, Altos de Sebu c a n ,
C a r a c a s. Fa x : 286 03 26.
UNESCO 2000
Agenda del Patrimonio Mundial
Con bellas fotografías y comentarios sobre diversos bienes culturales o naturales
del patrimonio mundial, la Agenda 2000 le permitirá organizar su tiempo 
diario y semanal y contribuir al mismo tiempo a la protección de la memoria
universal, única y diversa. 
Trilingüe español, inglés y francés  | Mapa de husos horarios 
Indicativos telefónicos internacionales  | 58 fotografías en color
Édit ions  UNESCO
Edic iones UNESCO
UNESCO Publishing
É D I T I O N S  U N E S C O
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax : +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet : www.unesco.org/publications
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
UNESCO 2000
Agenda du patrimoine mondial
Les sites du patrimoine mondial au fil de vos semaines.
Sites historiques chargés de mémoire, merveilles de l’art du monde, témoignages 
du progrès technique, prouesses spectaculaires de la nature et faunes exceptionnelles :
à travers les photos et les courts textes synthétiques, une vision d’un monde qu’il 
nous appartient de protéger.
Trilingue: anglais/français/espagnol
Cartes des fuseaux horaires
Indicatifs téléphoniques internationaux
58 photos en couleurs
UNESCO 2000
World Heritage Desk Diary
Unique colour photographs and short legends
describing World Heritage sites that illustrate your
weekly organizer and remind us all that 
protection of our common cultural and natural
diversity is paramount. 
Trilingual: English/French/Spanish
Daily and weekly organizer
Time zones; telephone codes
58 colour photographs
ISBN : 92-3-003607-2
UNESCO Publishing/San Marcos
140 pp., 19 x 26 cm
120 FF / 18,29 E
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Fo c u s :
Transition countries build the rule of law
n A decade of Western advice: what’s the verdict? 
n Ukraine: the legacy of the Soviet system
n Kyrgyzstan: starting from scratch
n Caught between old and new
n South Africa: finding a place for customary law
n Benin: a model system, but still on the horizon 
n Winners and losers of legal reform
Fe a t u res include
n Japan’s 20-year-olds: a pen-portrait with pictures
n Climate changes that make the world flip
n Codes of conduct for consumers and workers
n Internet and television get together
n A committed doubter: interview with Italian writer 
Antonio Tabucchi
]]>
</page>
</document>
