<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="117896eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
PLANET
Climatic changes
that make 
the world flip
CONNEXIONS
Wedding bells 
for Web and TV?
IN T ERV IEW
Antonio Tabucchi:
a committed
doubter
PEOPLE AND PLACES
Johannesburg: 
the sheltering
screen
BE L G I Q U E: 160 FB. C A N A DA : 5,75 $. E S PA Ñ A : 550 PTA S. F R A N C E : 22 FF NEDERLAND: 8 F L .P O RT U G A L : 700 ESC. S U I S S E : 5,50 FS. UNITED KINGDOM: £ 2 . 3 0
Making the leap
to a rule of law
November 1999
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
52nd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director:René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief:John Kohut
English edition:Roy Malkin
Spanish edition:Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition:Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit:Georges Servat
Illustrations:Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation:José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian:Gianluca Formichi,Sira Miori (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e : Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the
authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UN E S C O or those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. P h o t o
captions and headlines are written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r
s t a f f. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O o r
the United Nations. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7
Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfil m s
( X e r o x ) , Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C . R .
Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d , Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - NOVEMBER1999
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Pa r i s
by UN E S C O. Printed in Fr a n c e. Periodicals postage paid at
Champlain NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition et photogravure:
Le Courrier de l’UNESCO.
Impression:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 11-1999-OPI 99-587 A
C o n t e n t s
November 1999
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 The sheltering scre e n Photos by Thys Dullaart, text by Tomas Dashuber
EDITORIAL
9 All human rights for all Federico Mayor
PLANET
10 Climatic changes that make the world fli p Robert Matthews
WORLD OF LEARNING
14 When the press plugs the schoolbook gap
Asbel López and Lucía Iglesias Ku n t z
ETHICS
37 Taking the sweat out of sweatshops Ruth Mayne
39 ‘Work,yes—but with dignity’ Roberto Fo n s e c a
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
40 Move over Milan, Manila is taking the catwalk Allen T. C h e n g
CONNEXIONS
43 Wedding bells for Web and T V ? Francis Balle and Sophie Boukhari
TALKING TO…
46 Antonio Ta b u c c h i : a committed doubter
1 7 Focus Making the leap 
to a rule of l a w
Efforts to establish a rule of law are high on the agenda and
making headway in many countries. But effective application
of rights for all is often encumbered by obstacles including the
legacy of the past, neglect of customary law, w h o l e s a l e
transplantation rather than adaptation of foreign models, t h e
primacy accorded to the market rather than public welfare, a n d
lack of resources for enforcement.
Detailed table of contents on page 17.
C o v e r : © Michal Batory, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
These children could not afford the price of a ticket and had to plead with the doorman, who later let them in.
Before being admitted to the cinema, street kids are frisked for drugs.
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 3
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
T HE SHELT ERING SCREEN
w Photos by Thys Dullaart, Text by Tomas Dashuber
An all-night cinema offers a haven for Johannesburg’s street children and other homeless people
n
The lights go out and the curtain ri s e s.
Images scored with scratches and rich in
dust particles flicker over the blotchy
s c r e e n . A crackling noise issues from the
l o u d s p e a k e rs as the strip of brittle celluloid
is pulled through the projector.
The art of survival
We are in the Thari Cinema in down-
town Johannesburg.All around are blocks
of tenements and empty office buildings.
Howard, the projectionist, is focusing the
projector before inviting the audience to
enter a world of action and beauty, not to
mention ideals that can probably never be
lived up to.
Around this time it is quiet in central
w Thys Dullaart is a South African photographer 
(see box page 7). Tomas Dashuber is a Belgian-born
photojournalist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Howard, the projectionist, keeps one eye on the projector and the other, through a hole in the wall, on the screen.
Years ago, Miklos Zenasi escaped communist rule in Hungary. Now a homeless 66-year-old, he spends most
nights in front of the screen.
Jo h a n n e s bu r g . B e t ween about six and
eight o’clock in the evening, employees
quit their offices in the formerly flouri-
shing “City of Gold”. Many head for the
outlying townships. Others drive back to
the carefully-guarded luxury subu r b s
north of Johannesburg. The commuters’
destination depends on the colour of their
skin.
The affluent night owls who, in the
heyday of apartheid, drove downtown in
the evening to have a drink in the Carlton
Tower are seldom seen. The city centre
has become a kind of “grey zone”, where
organized crime, prostitution, drug abuse
and rough justice prevail.
Those who remain behind in the city
centre have nowhere to go.They are street
children or incorri gible adve n t u r e rs who
get a kick out of what has been stigmat i z e d
as the “most dangerous town in the wo r l d ” .
All the street children are black boys
most of whom have run away from poor
homes to escape abuse of one kind or
another. On the streets they learn the art
of survival. This means finding a suitable
clan and carving out a place for yourself
in a hierarchy that dictates who wears the
jersey on cold nights. Even if you are free-
zing, the worst enemy is not being cold
but being alone.
A warm place to go
They might have spent the day sca-
venging, begging and stealing.Many sniff
glue. Official shelters for street children,
some run by the churches, provide bunks
and a soup kitchen. On some nights
Samaritans hand out food. But while
almost all the children have spent time at
one of these shelters, they never stay there
too long. Some of them, once their basic
needs have been catered for, head off for
the Thari cinema in Market Street.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 5
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Howard rewinds a reel of film.
V I TAL STAT IS T ICS
While South Africa (population 41 million,
area 1.2 million km2) has a per ca p i t a
income ($3,210) which places it among the
middle-income countries, its income disparities
are among the most extreme in the world.
One-third of the population has a “first world”
standard of living, but over half live in “third
world” conditions. In the latter group, almost all
of whose members are black, only half have pri-
m a ry education, only one quarter of households
have access to electricity and running water, and
one third of the children suffer from chronic mal-
nutrition. Unemployment levels are among the
highest in the world. n
Source: World Bank
Cape Town
Johannesburg
Pretoria
Durban
Indian Ocean
Atlantic
Ocean
Namibia Botswana
Zimbabwe
Although it is in dire need of renova-
tion, this movie-house has become a kind
of haven, a secure, warm place where
homeless people can find shelter. As well
as street kids, it attracts other underprivi-
leged people who have slipped through
the very loose “net” of the South African
social security system.
The proprietor of the cinema has no
objection to his auditorium being used by
the waifs as a kind of dormitory.The only
condition he insists on is that they do not
consume alcohol or use dru g s. E ve ry
night, between 20 and 30 kids make
themselves as comfortable as possible on
the cinema’s threadbare carpet.
‘It’s like belonging
to a big family’
One regular guest remarks,“It’s pretty
hard to get accepted here, but once yo u
are it’s like belonging to a big family.” He
talks about the hard reality of life in the
m i l l i o n - p o p u l ation city outside. I n s i d e , yo u
can find a place among the rows of dilapi-
d ated seats and see second-rate films packed
with action. Once, when he was spending
the night outside in the street, somebody
stole his shoes while he was asleep.That is
just one more reason to pay two rand (50
cents) for a place to doze between Te rm i n at o r
and Air Force One.
Another regular is 66-year-old Miklos
Zenasi, who comes in about the same
time each evening and looks for his favou-
rite place in the front row. Here he dis-
creetly settles down for the night. Miklos,
who is known to everyone as “The old
man”, openly admits that he is no longer
the wild bull he was once reputed to be.
He deserted from the Hungarian army,
fled the communist regime, and by roun-
dabout routes eventually found his way to
South Africa. Now, he says, he is too old
for that kind of excitement.What’s more,
he adds, pointing to different parts of his
body, he’s a mass of aches and pains. For
a while he lapses into silence before final-
ly revealing that he has spent more nights
in recent years beneath the screen than
anywhere else.
Around six o’clock in the morning,
when A rnold Schwarzenegger has got
even with his last enemy, the city outside
begins to throb with life again. It is time
for the Thari to expel its children for ano-
ther day. It may well see them again in the
evening just as Howard is checking the
focus of the lens for a further round of
dreams. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
A star looks down. From a poster of the film Desperado, Antonio Banderas keeps watch over a man sleeping
in the foyer.
A young boy dozes on the floor beneath the projector’s dazzling beam.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 7
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Ramshackle seats are used as mattresses.
A group of boys with eyes glued to the screen . . . until sleep overtakes them.
AN UNOBT RUSI V E
EY E
Thys Dullaart, a 31-year-old South African pho-
t o g rapher on the staff of the Johannesburg
S t a r n ew s p a p e r , won the 1999 World Press Photo
Award (“Daily Life” ca t e g o ry), with the picture
s t o ry on Johannesburg street children from which
photos published in this feature have been selected.
Dullaart worked as unobtrusively as possible using
a small Le i ca ca m e ra. He quotes with approval the
great French photographer Henri Cartier Bresson
who once said “Anyone who wants to catch fis h
should not disturb the water.” In other words, if you
want to take pictures in a cinema, it’s a good idea
not to disturb the performance.
“Living and working in Johannesburg has
taught me many things about street children,” he
says. “Eager to see their response to the Thari
cinema photos, I arranged for some of the boys fea-
tured in them to meet me at the annual World Press
Photo Exhibition. I was amazed when they com-
mented instead on a story about street children in
Romania. ‘But they are white,’ was their initial
reaction, followed by a discussion which gave me
the impression that it was themselves they saw in
those photos from Romania.” T. D. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Another action drama comes to an end in front of a sleepy audience.
Some of the ushers were once homeless themselves.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
E D I T O R I A L
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 9
n
The end of the millennium has seen some remarkable advances in political demo-
cracy. Oppressed peoples everywhere are at last, or once again, tasting freedom.
They owe these victories largely to themselves, to the intelligence, determination,
and even the genius of their citizens.
But this freedom will be fragile as long as it is cast in a single mold, the vehicle of a
uniform globalization which speaks with a single voice, primarily that of commerce.
Principles may be universal; the mechanisms that infuse life into them are shaped by a
host of features that are specific to each society.
No vision of democracy—which transcends politics and includes economic, social
and cultural life—can really take root if it is a sterile copy that fails to take account of
the history and myths, the values and traditions of each people.While these roots are
necessary, however, they provide no justification for citing “cultural relativism” as an
excuse for violating the basic principles on which the rights of human beings are foun-
ded. Respect for “cultural identity” cannot legitimize anti-democratic practices.
A second danger arises from the fact that the field in which these rights are elabo-
rated and exercised is all too often limited.The recent commemoration of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights was a reminder that human rights comprise not only
political and civil rights but also, on exactly the same basis, economic and social rights,
such as the right to a job, housing, health and education.
One and a half billion people live in dire poverty.Their most fundamental right, the
right to life, the bedrock of all other rights, is constantly threatened. So the still unfini-
shed struggle to extend and strengthen human rights includes the duty to promote
development.
This duty is not only a matter of legal formalism or an ethical imperat i ve .
Fundamental freedoms will remain ve ry fragile as long as pove rt y, exclusion and inequa-
lities pers i s t . The forces of globalization encourage the  establishment of the rule of law,
but a ve rsion of law biased in favour of rules needed for successful business activity.T h e y
also do more to sharpen economic and social tensions rather than to reduce them.
The momentum created by efforts to establish the rule of law in a growing number
of countries is coming up against a major obstacle.The principles and rules that govern
international relations are increasing their influence on the lives of nations, but they are
very far indeed from being democratic.The strongest still hold sway.
This is true where individual states are concerned.They feel their wings have been
clipped, and see their legitimate prerogatives being eroded by the rise of a kind of pri-
vate-sector absolutism,which tends to limit the functions of government to security and
mediation,paralyzing its role as the guarantor of the general interest and depriving it of
the necessary means to apply the rule of law.
It is also true of the community of states because there is still no world structure
which is accepted as the embodiment of the force of law. The United Nations is a
unique international democratic forum, but its authority has been weakened first by
nearly half a century of the Cold War and then by unilateral actions taken by the major
powers, in defiance of the very principles they profess to defend.
The rule of law is indivisible; it must encompass freedom and welfare, individual
countries and the world at large. n
ALL HUMAN RIGH T S
F OR ALL
Federico Mayor
As this issue goes to press,
UNESCO is in process of electing
a new Director-General.
In accordance with UNESCO’s
Constitution, UNESCO’s
Executive Board, comprising
representatives of 58 Member
States, recommends a single
candidate to the UNESCO
General Conference. The
Conference, in which each of
UNESCO’s 187 Member States
has one vote, is the
Organization’s sovereign
governing body. It will take a
decision on the Board’s
proposal on November 12, and
the new Director-General will
assume his functions a few
days later.
Further details about the
election will appear in the
next issue of the Courier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
P L A N E T
n
The once-green land of Ireland tur-
ned into a frozen wildern e s s. H a rp
seals swimming among ice-floes off
the coast of France. Polar bears prowling
the streets of A m s t e r d a m . These are the
images conjured up by the latest research
into global warming.
Ye s , you read that corr e c t l y : global wa r-
ming—the rise in the world’s average tem-
p e r ature caused by the trapping of the sun’s
heat by pollution in the atmosphere.
If you are baffled by that, then prepare
to be shocked.For the same research is now
suggesting that such dramatic changes in
the climate of northern Europe could take
place in as few as 10 years.
Again, this figure is not a misprint: no
zero has gone missing. Scientists have
recently uncovered compelling evidence
t h at global wa rming can have a deva s t at i n g
impact on timescales far shorter than
a nyone believed possible. Not centuri e s ,
not even decades, but ye a rs , in what are
being called “ c l i m atic fli p s ” . One leading
e x p e rt has recently gone on record to wa rn
t h at some north Atlantic countries could
find themselves plunged into Arctic condi-
tions over the space of just 10 years.
Risk of
sudden upheaval
In geological term s ,t h at is as fast as the
blink of an eye.But even in human terms,
such a rate of climatic change is incredi-
bly—and quite probably intolerably—
rapid. It is far from clear whether any eco-
n o my or agricultural system could cope
with such sudden upheaval.
Yet evidence is now mounting that such
“ c l i m atic fli p s ” not only can happen, bu t
h ave happened in the past. It is evidence
that adds new urgency to the global war-
ming debat e , which has lost much of its
momentum in recent ye a rs. It also high-
lights the frightening complexity of the task
facing scientists trying to predict the eart h ’s
response to human activity.
Arguments about climatic change typi-
cally focus on how increasing levels of so-
called greenhouse gases—principally car-
bon dioxide from burning fossil fuels—in
the eart h ’s atmosphere trap ever more of
the sun’s heat.
Huge efforts have been put into predic-
ting the likely global temperature rise cau-
sed by the extra greenhouse gases, and cur-
rent best estimates point to a rise of 1.5
d e grees Celsius or so over the next century.
But while scientists wa rn that even so
apparently small a rise in temperature could
cause upheaval in eve rything from agri c u l-
tural practices to the spread of disease, t h e
rat e of change hardly seems terri f y i n g .S u r e l y
we can cope and have coped with events that
change over several generat i o n s ?
Such arguments are buttressed by ano-
t h e r , apparently compelling, a r g u m e n t
against rapid climate change. The eart h ’s
oceans have colossal thermal inert i a , a n d
would surely iron out any sudden upheava l :
weight for weight, it takes ten times more
energy to heat water than it does solid iron.
Small wo n d e r ,t h e n ,t h at scientists we r e
u n s u rp rised when they failed to find any
signs of rapid climatic changes when they
first studied ancient ocean sediments, the
isotope levels of which retain a record of
past temperatures.
The end of the Ice Age: 
a puzzling discovery
But this apparently comfort i n g
c o n fluence of theory and data is now
known to contain two huge loopholes.The
first reared its head in the early 1980s, w h e n
a joint U.S.-European team of scientists
working in Greenland made a puzzling dis-
c ove ry.They had extracted an ice-core from
a site in the southern part of the country,
CL IM AT IC CH A NGES 
T H AT M A K E T HE W ORL D FL IP
w Robert Matthews
Global warming’s impact on the environment is not necessarily a  drawn-out affair. Recent
evidence shows that dramatic changes or ‘climatic flips’ could happen virtually overnight.
w Science correspondent of the London Sunday
Telegraph
By analysing icy sediments (ice-cores) extracted from deep beneath the earth’s surface scientists can plot the
course of climate change thousands of years ago. Below, a sample taken at Lake Annecy (France) in winter.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 11
P L A N E T
and had measured isotope levels in the gas
trapped at different depths in an at t e m p t
to gauge the temperature in the region ove r
thousands of years.
Because the ice builds up relat i ve l y
r a p i d l y, the ice-core was expected to gi ve
the researchers the most fine-detailed pic-
ture yet of temperature changes in the
r e gi o n . Plotting out the corresponding tem-
p e r at u r e s , the researchers discovered some-
thing puzzling—and disturbing.
As expected, the core showed the rise in
t e m p e r ature corresponding to the end of
the last Ice Age around 11,000 years ago.
But it also showed that the bulk of that
wa rm-up had taken place in the space of
just 40 years.
At the time, no one knew what to make
of the result, which flew in the face of eve-
rything scientists then knew about climate
change—or thought they knew. In the ye a rs
t h at followe d , h owe ve r , f u rther ice-cores
were extracted, and they revealed an even
more dramatic story : a 5- to 10-degr e e
increase in temperature and doubling of
p r e c i p i t ation over Greenland in the space of
just 20 years.
Nothing in the earlier ocean sediment
core data had prepared scientists for such a
finding—nor could it. For this was the first
loophole in the argument against sudden
c l i m atic fli p s : the absence of evidence from
the ori ginal ocean sediment cores simply
r e flected the ve ry broad-brush picture they
g ave of temperature change. They lacked
the detail offered by ice-cores.
Prompted by the Greenland fin d i n g s ,
scientists have since tracked down locat i o n s
where ocean sediment builds up fa s t
enough to gi ve a record of temperat u r e
comparable in detail to that from the ice-
c o r e s. A n d , sure enough, they reveal the
same story of rapid climatic change in loca-
tions as far apart as California and India.
The history of science shows that fin-
ding evidence for some astonishing pheno-
menon is often only part of the story. To
c o nvince the scientific community at large,
the evidence has to be backed up by a more
comprehensive explanation.And for many
years the standard explanation for why Ice
Ages begin and end provided yet more rea-
sons for thinking all climatic change must
be slow and graceful.
T h at explanation rests on work by a Ser-
bian scientist named Milutin Milankov i t c h ,
who in 1920 linked Ice Ages to changes in the
shape of the eart h ’s orbit.Caused by the push
and pull of the other planets, these orbital
changes altered the concentration of sunlight
reaching the planet. Such changes would
n aturally take place ve ry gr a d u a l l y, on times-
cales of many thousands of ye a rs—a recipe
for climatic change that is anything but
a b ru p t .
A global heat
transporter
Yet, once again, there is a loophole in
this comforting argument—as Wa l l a c e
Broecker of Columbia University, New
York Stat e , realized around the time
climate experts were puzzling over the
ice-core data.
This loophole centres on a ve ry specific
feature of the earth’s oceans:their circula-
tion pat t e rn s. Ocean currents transport
heat around the globe like a vast conveyor
b e l t . In the A t l a n t i c, for example, wa rm
water travels northwards from the Gulf of
Mexico, passing its heat to the air by eva-
poration as it goes.This makes the current
p r o gr e s s i vely cooler, saltier and denser until
e ve n t u a l l y, near Iceland, the water is so
heavy that it sinks, and begins a long jour-
ney southward,along the ocean floor.
Broecker realized that this complex,
subtle process—which he called “ T h e
Conveyor”—could be the Achilles heel of
the eart h ’s climat e ,a l l owing subtle changes
to be turned into dramatic upheava l . Fo r
instead of having to alter the whole body
of the oceans, just a small change in tem-
p e r ature might be enough to alter the beha-
The history of science shows
that finding evidence for some
astonishing phenomenon is
often only part of the story. 
To convince the scientific
c o m m u n i ty at large, the
evidence has to be backed up
by a more comprehensive
e x p l a n a t i o n
Ocean currents continually transport heat around the globe like a liquid conveyor belt. Above, simplified chart of the circulation process.
Warm Shallow
Current
Cold and Salty
Deep Current
Sea-to-Air
Heat Transfer
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
P L A N E T
viour of the Conve yor—and trigger radical
and rapid climatic change over a large area.
For example,gradually melting ice from
the Arctic could dilute the saltiness of the
Conveyor to a critical density where it no
longer sinks and begins its journey south-
ward to pick up more heat.The Conveyor
would, in effect, be switched off, isolating
the north Atlantic from the wa rming wat e rs
of the tropics.The result would then be dis-
tinctly paradox i c a l , with a slight wa rming of
the Arctic causing temperatures of nort h
Atlantic countries to plunge.
B r o e c k e r ’s explanation is now widely
believed to lie at the heart of rapid climate
change in the past. Wo rry i n g l y, h owe ve r ,
global warming is predicted to have preci-
sely the type of warming effect on the Arc-
tic ice that threatens the existence of the
C o nve yo r. Computer projections of the
effect of pollution on global temperatures
predict an inflow of cold, fresh water into
the nort h e rn A t l a n t i c — water that could
dilute the Conve yor enough to switch it off.
The Achilles heel 
of the earth’s climate
If that happened, s ays Broecker, w i n t e r
temperatures in the north Atlantic region
would fall by 10 or more degrees Celsius
within 10 years, giving places like Dublin
the climate of Spitsbergen, 400 km north of
the Arctic Circle.“The consequences could
be devastating,” he says.
It is a scenario that gains credibility from
ice-core dat a , according to climate expert
K e n d rick Taylor of the Desert Research Ins-
titute in Reno, N e va d a . He says that many
cores suggest that around 8,000 ye a rs ago
there was a sudden plunge back to a “mini Ice
A g e ” which lasted around 400 ye a rs. T h e
most likely cause, s ays Tay l o r ,was the release
of melted ice-water from lakes in Canada into
the A t l a n t i c, which switched off the heat -
t r a n s p o rting Conve yo r.
“The change in freshwater flux to the
oceans was large, but not that much diffe-
rent from what gr e e n h o u s e - i n d u c e d
changes may produce in the future,” he said
in a recent paper in A m e rican Scientist. “It is
ironic that greenhouse warming may lead
to rapid cooling in eastern NorthernAme-
rica,Europe and Scandinavia.”
So just how close is the Conve yor to
switching off once again? The short answe r
is: no one knows. Computer models have
still to identify the critical density of sea-
water at which the Conve yor will switch off,
or the greenhouse gas concentrations nee-
ded to release the requisite amount of melt-
water.
Cutting pollution 
buys time
W h at computer models have show n ,
s ays Tay l o r , is that reducing pollution emis-
sions buys time—both by slowing the rate
of global warming, and also by driving the
c l i m ate more gently, which seems to
increase its stability against rapid change.
But while scientists struggle to capture
the full complexity of the climate on their
s u p e r c o m p u t e rs , evidence of other causes
of dramatic climate change is beginning to
e m e r g e .
Last July, Professor Martin Claussen and
his colleagues at the Potsdam Institute for
C l i m ate Science, G e rm a ny, r e p o rted evi-
dence that today ’s Sahara desert was creat e d
Photographed through a polarized light microscope, a cross-section of a 100,000-year-old ice-core 
from the Antarctic.
A MUDDY MYSTER Y
The effects that scientists now believe can shape
the earth’s climate are astonishingly subtle, and
one of the most bizarre centres on the connection
between Ice Ages, earthquakes, and mud.
Last year a team from the Southampton Ocea-
nography Centre in Britain announced in the jour-
nal N a t u re the discovery of a 450 - b i l l i o n - c u b i c -
metre deposit on the sea-floor off the coast of
Sardinia—the aftermath of a truly enormous slide of
mud: enough to engulf the whole of France to a
depth of a metre.
Carbon dating of the plankton above and below
the mud bed suggest that the slide took place
around 20,000 years ago—at the height of the last
Ice Age. This was a time when so much water had
been turned to ice that sea-levels were 120 metres
l ower than they are today—a fact that the team
suspects is crucial to the cause of the colossal
mud-slide.
Formed out of thousands of years of river depo-
sits, the mud would have been rich in organic mat-
ter—material that rots to produce huge amounts
of methane gas. Normally this gas would have
been locked into the mud by the huge pressure of
sea-water lying over the submerged sediments.
But as the Ice Age deepened and sea-levels fell,
the mud deposits would find themselves exposed,
and thus able to release their pent-up methane
gas.
This gas is a very potent source of global war-
ming, and the sudden release of huge amounts of
it might have helped push the earth back out of
the Ice Age.
Certainly the timing of the Sardinian mud-
slide—at the height of the last Ice Age—is intriguing,
says team member Professor Euan Nisbet of Lon-
don’s Royal Holloway College: “It is possible that a
big slide could have released enough methane to
act as a warming trigger.”
It is an idea that has gained strength from a
recent discovery by researchers at Duke Univer-
sity in North Carolina. In a paper also published in
Nature last year, they argue that the sheer weight
of ice pressing down on the earth’s crust may have
triggered huge earthquakes during the Ice Age.
Could these have triggered massive submarine
mudslides, releasing methane that led to the end of
Ice Age? As yet, no one knows. But it points to yet
another astonishingly subtle link between the envi-
ronment, climate—and us. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 13
P L A N E T
in a sudden climatic “ fli p ” t h at took place
just 5,500 ye a rs ago, t u rning vast areas of
lush grassland into an arid wilderness and
d e va s t ating ancient civilizat i o n s.
Using a sophisticated computer model
of the land, sea and atmosphere, the team
has discovered just how subtle are some of
the effects that can turn Milankov i t c h - s t y l e
changes in the earth’s orbit into major cli-
mate upheaval.
The Sahara’s quick-change act
They found that over the last 9,000
ye a rs the gr av i t ational pull of the planets
has altered the tilt of the eart h ’s axis by
about half a degr e e , and changed the timing
of eart h ’s closest approach to the sun by
around five months.
By themselves, such subtle changes
should not cause major climatic effects.
But when Claussen and his colleagues
included the effect of vegetation in their
computer model, they found that it cau-
sed rainfall levels to plummet over the
Sahara region.
They traced the cause to “ f e e d b a c k ”
effects,in which a slight drop in vegetation
l e vel makes the eart h ’s surface slightly bet-
ter at reflecting sunlight, which causes rain-
fall levels to drop—prompting more vege-
tation loss,and so on.
According to Claussen, these feedback
effects turned the va s t , o n c e - green Sahara
into a brown wasteland within just 300 ye a rs.
“It was the largest change in land cove r
d u ring the last 6,000 ye a rs ,” he say s.“It wa s
ve ry seve r e , ruining ancient civilizat i o n s.”
The discove ry is likely to force histo-
rians to rethink their explanations of eve n t s
in the regi o n . For according to Claussen, i t
contradicts the long-held belief that the col-
lapse of agriculture in the region was cau-
sed by ancient farmers exhausting the soil:
“Although humans lived in the Sahara and
used the land to some extent, we think that
ancient land use played only a negligi b l y
small role.”
The findings are also being seen as ano-
ther wa rning of just how unstable eve n
t o d ay ’s climate may be. “It is capable of
c h a n ging ve ry abru p t l y,” s ays climat e
expert Andrew Goudie of Oxford Univer-
s i t y. “ We ’ ve known that the extent of the
Sahara has yo-yoed back and forwards for
millions of ye a rs , and that about 8,000
ye a rs ago it was much wetter than today,
with big rivers feeding into the Nile. But I
h a d n ’t realized just how rapid the chan-
geover had been.It is salutary.”
Temperature 
nose-dives
Also in July, a team of researchers from
the unive rsities of Illinois and Minnesota
reported the discovery of another climatic
“flip” in the northern hemisphere around
9,000 ye a rs ago, which temporarily plunged
the region back into an Ice Age.
Using lake sediments from Minnesota,
the team confirmed the existence of the
This prehistoric rock painting from Tassili N’Ajjer in southern Algeria is a reminder that the Sahara was once
a fertile region with abundant plant and animal life.
‘The change in freshwater 
flux to the oceans was large,
but not that much different
from what greenhouse-induced
changes may produce 
in the future. It is ironic that
greenhouse warming may lead
to rapid cooling in eastern
Northern America, Europe and
S ca n d i n a v i a ’
cold snap around 8,200 ye a rs ago, as reve a-
led by the ice core dat a . But they also found
evidence for another dive in temperatures
around 8,300 to 8,900 ye a rs ago.The team
thinks this older cold snap was linked to
the release of melted ice from lakes into the
Atlantic—which may have switched off the
C o nve yo r. But the researchers now think
t h at the more recent flip most likely had
another—and as yet unknown—origin.
W h at is clear is that until we know
much more about the complexity of climat e
change, all bets about how much time we
have to take action are definitely off.What
evidence we do have increasingly points to
the stark possibility that we may have fa r
less time than we thought.
“I used to believe that change in climat e
happened slowly and would never affect
me,” admits Taylor. “Now I know that our
c l i m ate could change significantly in my
lifetime.” n
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
children who have mostly never owned
schoolbooks or at best have had to learn
from borrowed ones, acquire a sense of
ownership which is an important aspect
of the media’s current educat i o n a l
projects.
Aralynn McMane, director of the
World A s s o c i ation of Newspapers (WA N ) ,
a Pa ris-based body which awards an
annual World Young Reader Prize (see box
page 16), s ays “in recent ye a rs we have
seen supplements for young people, i n
L atin A m e rica and elsewhere, become a lot
s m a rt e r. They sound less like gr ow n - u p s
l e c t u ring or pandering to children and
more like a trusted friend or mentor with
something useful and relevant to say.”
George Kelly, one of the founders of
the WAN and adviser on educational pro-
jects to several Latin American newspa-
pers, says the best supplements are pro-
duced in Brazil and Argentina. Folha and
O Estado, two major dailies in São Paulo,
Brazil’s economic capital, put out two
c h i l d r e n ’s we e k l i e s , Fo l h i n h a a n d
E s t a d i n h o. Brazilian journalist Marcelo
Soares thinks they are valuable because
they carry articles which interest children
“without treating them like slaves of
Xuxa,” a famous Brazilian former model
who presents children’s programmes on
14 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
n
A few weeks ago, several children
wrote to the editors of Zurquí, the
educational supplement of the Costa
Rican daily newspaper La Nación. They
complained that their parents wouldn’t
let them cut out and paste figures from
the paper as the instructions indicated.
Defending themselves, the parents argued
they did not want to spoil their precious
family collections of Zurquí issues. In the
following week’s supplement, the editors
came up with a suggestion: photocopy the
figures, so that children could cut them
out and parents could keep their newspa-
per intact.
This is just one sign of the growing
interest generated by the educational sup-
plements published by many Lat i n
American papers. A distressed 11-year-
old schoolgirl in Bogotá, the capital of
Colombia, phoned the country’s largest
daily, El Tiempo, to beg for a back issue
because she had lost her own copy. What
she really wanted was Mi Tiempo, an edu-
cational supplement the paper distributes
free to pupils at 80 public and private
schools in the city. “The girl was upset
because she lost the paper before she’d
finished doing all the activities in it,” says
Ofelia Corradine, the managing editor of
the monthly, which prints 31,000 copies.
For most of the school pupils in
B o g o t á ’s poorest neighbourhoods—30
per cent of which are taking part in the
project—Mi Tiempo is not only the closest
to a schoolbook that pupils have ever
come across but also something they can
take home to colour, draw in, and write
down what they think. One of the issues
in the first half of 1999, for example, ran
articles about tolerance and getting along
with others, with plenty of space where
the children could express their opinions.
“Each child gets a copy, so they deve-
lop a close personal relationship with the
s u p p l e m e n t ,” s ays Corr a d i n e . T h e s e
w UNESCO Courier journalists
W HEN THE PRESS PLUGS
T HE SCHOOL BOOK GAP
w Asbel López and Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Educational supplements for young readers are flourishing 
in the Latin American press
television. These supplements also try to
explain in simple terms current events
like the war in Kosovo or the recent
Turkish earthquake. Estadinho also carries
regular columns on language and science.
‘A fun way to read’
Other smaller papers are hot on their
h e e l s. In the Argentine city of Bahía
Blanca, La Nueva Provincia sends a fort-
nightly supplement called El Diario de los
Chicos to 3,000 subscribers aged between
5 and 14. One of its writers, known as
“Santiago”, is a 12-year-old film critic
with a collection of 700 film reviews from
newspapers all over the world. In the city
of Paysandú, Uruguay’s most widely read
provincial paper, El Telégrafo, publishes
Gurises (which comes from a Guaraní
Indian word meaning “ c h i l d r e n ” ) , a n
eight-page tabloid whose motto is “A fun
way to read”. Ever Thursday, the day it
a p p e a rs , “ t h e r e ’s plenty of fun in
Pay s a n d ú ’s schools,” s ays Enri q u e
Sánchez, a journalist on El Telégrafo.
Gurises publishes material for class-
room use and gives news about school
events, competitions and other children’s
activities. It also provides an outlet for
imaginative work by printing unpublished
stories and, with backing from the World
Wildlife Fund (WWF), tries to get across
to its readers the importance of protec-
ting nature,with a section of photographs
on environmental issues. In 1996, the
g ove rnment of this nort h e a s t e rn
Uruguayan province declared Gurises to
be “of value” to the province because it
encouraged children to read.
The newspapers are usually not just
concerned with attracting young readers,
but also with getting their parents into the
habit of reading the paper every day.
Latin American newspapers depend more
heavily for survival on news-stand sales
than on income from advertising.This is
because most Latin American countries
do not have independent bodies to verify
‘In recent years we have seen
supplements for young people,
in Latin America and
e l s ewhere, become a lot
s m a r t e r. They sound less like
grown-ups lecturing or
pandering to children and
more like a trusted friend or
mentor with something useful
and relevant to say. ’
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
circulation: advertising agencies have to
make do with circulation figures provided
by the newspapers themselve s. T h i s
c r e ates lack of confidence and limits
advertising sales.
The result is a flurry of promotional
activities to boost circulation, with initia-
tives such as subscribers’ clubs—started
by El Tiempo in Bogota—and competi-
tions with fla s hy prizes and gifts of
atlases, encyclopaedias, health booklets,
football posters, CDs and cookbooks.
Education sells papers
E d u c ation has become a weapon in the
b attle for new readers. The day Z u r q u í
comes out in Costa Rica, sales of its parent
p a p e r , La Nación, go up by 25 per cent. O n
Tu e s d ays in Pa r a g u ay, when ABC Escolar
hits the streets, the circulation of A B C, o n e
of the country ’s main papers , rises betwe e n
20 and 40 per cent without any other pro-
m o t i o n , s ays Natalia Laport a , the supple-
m e n t ’s editor. Last July and A u g u s t ,
A p r e n d o, the children’s supplement of L a
Prensa de Pa n a m a had a pull-out section of
h i s t o rical photos of the Panama Canal,
which will return to Panamanian ow n e r-
ship this December. “When we printed the
cut-out features on Sunday s , sales of the
main paper went up by 17 per cent, a
record for us,” s ays Wendy Tri b a l d o s , w h o
is in charge of the supplement.
most recent political changes around the
wo r l d . “If you went to a school, the atlas in
the library would still probably show the
S oviet Union as a single country,” he say s.
Some of the supplements follow the sylla-
bus prescribed by their country ’s educa-
tion ministry. Z u r q u í ’s e d i t o r , Pat ri c i a
B r e n e s , s ays “the fact that the supplement
is connected with Costa Rica’s official syl-
l a bus is an additional at t r a c t i o n . T h at ’s
w hy it’s used so much by parents and espe-
cially teachers.”
Following such programmes involves
tackling the same subjects every year, but
the editors try to vary their approach each
time around. To teach about resistance to
the invasion of Nicaragua by the U.S. fili-
buster William Walker in 1856, Zurquí
used a play and included a script and ins-
tructions about how to make costumes.
The following year, it printed cut-outs to
put in a history corner in the classroom.
Later the children were encouraged to
produce a newspaper which featured the
main historical events and a description
of daily life in those days.
Low-cost reading
The great advantage of the supple-
ments is that they are much cheaper than
schoolbooks and books in general. The
edition of La Nación which contains
Zurquí costs only $0.39,while school text-
The supplements can increase the
circulation of their parent papers largely
because education continues to be regar-
ded in Latin America as a means of social
advancement.1 But they also have defini-
te advantages over other teaching
methods and resources.
One is their considerable capacity to
r e l ate knowledge to the present. P r o d u c i n g
a schoolbook, from the moment someone
thinks of writing it until the time it lands on
a pupil’s desk, takes at least two ye a rs. I n
c o u n t ries with few resources to update their
school pri m e rs regularly, this period can be
much longer. But newspapers record
e vents which happened only a few days ago.
Kelly remembers a Latin A m e ri c a n
g e o gr a p hy supplement which showed the
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 15
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
Every Sunday, the Panamanian children’s supplement Aprendo prints sports news (at left) and children’s opinions on the week’s special topic (right).
1. According to figures from the United Nations
Development Programme (UNDP), 23 per cent
of children who attend school in Latin America
and the Caribbean do not reach the fifth year.
‘The fact that the supplement
is connected with Costa Rica’s
official syllabus is an
additional attraction. 
That’s why it’s used so much
by parents and especially
teachers’
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
MY FIRST 
S TOR Y- BOOK
The first story-book many South African school-
children come across is the Johannesburg
Sunday Times’s 4 - p a g ee d u cational supplement
R e a d R i gh t, which in the last 8 months has printed
12 stories which can be pulled out and saved. Lisa
B l a k eway, editorial director of the project, which
was launched in January 1999, says these illus-
trated stories have been the supplement’s most
popular feature.
ReadRight has a print run of 485,000 copies
which are inserted into the Sunday Times, as
well as 36 , 500 more which, with help from foun-
dations, companies and individuals, are handed
out free in 900 rural and township schools, most
of which do not have a library.
The supplement is aimed at teachers, parents
and pupils and can include reading and com-
prehension exercises, mapwork, life-skills acti-
vities, essay competitions, book reviews by chil-
dren, stories to discuss in class and a course
about how the government is organized.
The Sunday Times’s commitment to educa t i o n
goes back further than R e a d R i gh t. The South
African government’s inability to supply school-
children with textbooks they need to follow the
c o u n t ry’s new educational curriculum inspired the
paper to publish all the courses in it over a 6-week
period. ReadRight, which is an extension of this
initiative, boosted the parent paper’s circulation
by 7 per cent. Now, there are plans to set up
quarterly workshops for teachers. 
This ambitious project won this year’s World
Young Reader Prize awarded by the World As s o-
ciation of Newspapers. n
+ …
l http://www.suntimes.co.za/edu/
books cost $5.
I c a ri t o, which is put out by the Chilean
daily paper La Te r c e ra, has 100,000 rea-
d e rs. It has two sections, one for pri m a ry
school children and another for those of
high-school age. It featured English as a
subject this year and has been on the We b
since 1997. “The I c a ri t o D i gi t a l site is visi-
ted by 5,500 people eve ry day, w h i c h
makes it one of Latin A m e ri c a ’s most
popular we b s i t e s ,” s ays Nuria Cot, a tea-
cher who edits the supplement.
Chile’s education minister, José Pablo
Arellano, pointed out at the end of 1998
t h at Icarito “ r e p o rted on curri c u l u m
changes being considered in the country’s
educational reform programme and also
on new teaching methods.” This meant,
he said, that the supplement was “an
extremely valuable reference tool for both
pupils and teachers.”
The teachers and children recognize
the value of the supplements. M a r í a
V i r ginia López Jo r d á n , a secondary
school teacher in Jujuy (Argentina), says
“ t h e y ’ ve provided me with up-to-dat e
material which you can’t get in school
textbooks. I’ve worked with teachers in
other subjects like history, g e o gr a p hy,
ethics and civics.The pupils can weigh up
the various sources, which stimulates dis-
cussion and helps them form opinions.”
Other advantages the teachers usually
mention are the interest the supplements
generate in the classroom, the valuable
extra source of information they provide
and the way they illustrate abstract ideas
with concrete examples.
Learning without tears
Despite all this, the supplements are
sometimes criticized for being over-aca-
demic.The press ought to be encouraging
interesting and enjoyable extra-curricular
activities, but instead it is becoming a
kind of school in itself.
Kelly says that despite attractive desi-
gn and bright colours, the content is
sometimes too seri o u s , especially in
Colombia and Argentina. Supplements
try to talk in an adult way about complex
political and social topics. “A British child
would quickly switch off,” he says. Still,
he underlines that one of the best ways to
judge the quality of the supplements is to
see how schools make use of them. “If
they do—and this is happening—it means
the supplements must be providing some-
thing that the country needs.”
Kelly thinks the press projects in
schools should first of all entertain chil-
dren and encourage them to express
t h e m s e l ve s. “There is nothing which
assures that being serious will make
people learn better.The opposite tends to
be true.When you make something exci-
ting and interesting, that’s when young
people open up and understand what you
are doing,” he says.
Tribaldos, the editor of Aprendo, says:
“We’re writing for the child of today.
We’re producing a supplement which is
entertaining and instructive at the same
time.” This credo has to survive. At least
those who associate education with plea-
sure hope it will. n
+ …
l http://www.wan-press.org
Costa Rican children’s supplement Zurquí uses catchy illustrations and simple language to explain 
the basics of plant photosynthesis to its readers (left). 
At right, the Argentine supplement El Diario de los Chicos hails peace in Northern Ireland, commenting 
that “when people or peoples accept the ideas of others, peace is possible.”
‘There is nothing which 
assures that being serious 
will make people learn better. 
The opposite tends to be true.
When you make something
exciting and interesting, 
that’s when young people
open up and understand 
what you are doing’
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 17
FOCUS
Making the leap 
to a rule of l a w
C o n t e n t s
1 8 A world in tra n s i t i o n
Yash Gai and John Ko h u t
1 | Former Soviet bloc
1 9 No quick fix
Stephen Holmes
2 1 Ky rg y z s t a n :b reaking out of the old shell
Cynthia Guttman
2 4 U k ra i n e : legal eagles with clipped wings
Serhiy Holova t y
2 6 A world’s eye view of the law
2 | Pro g ress in the South
2 8 In traditional societies, the jury is out 
on legal re f o r m
Yash Ghai
3 1 B e n i n : justice on the horizon
René Lefort
3 3 South A f r i c a : blending tradition 
and change
Ferial Haffajee
3 4 Chinese courts get a hearing
Katherine A r m s
3 6 Law and social justice
Kerry Rittich
Across the world, wherever
authoritarian regimes have been
toppled and free market economic
systems have been introduced, the
establishment of the “rule of law” has
vaulted to the top of the agenda. Good
laws effectively applied respond to a
growing aspiration for the full exercise of
human rights to be guaranteed. Legal
reform is also part and parcel of the
process of integration into globalized
markets. This process is bound to be a
long one.
In the former Eastern bloc, attempts to
simply import laws from the West have
largely failed (pp. 19-20). The heritage of
the recent and remote past is a heavy
burden, as a former Ukraine Justice
Minister (pp. 24-25) describes from first-
hand experience. But, as recent changes in
Kyrgyzstan suggest (pp. 21-23), it is not
necessarily an insuperable obstacle.
Tradition also cuts different ways in
Third World countries where disregard of
customary law may create new forms of
injustice (pp. 28-30). Post-apartheid South
Africa is trying to find a new role for
customary law (pp. 33-34). Benin, via the
independence of its new constitutional
court, is reviving its tradition as “a
pioneer of democracy”. A report (pp. 34-
35) citing examples in the fields of labour
and business law shows how Chinese
citizens are increasingly turning to the
courts to find redress for grievances. The
legal omnipotence of the political
authorities is being eroded.
But in a world where legal systems are
so different (pp. 26-27), lack of resources
means that the transition process is going
to be an uphill job. This “enforcement
gap” helps to explain why there are
winners and losers in the globalization of
the rule of law.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
A world 
in t ra n s i t i o n
w Yash Ghai and John Ko h u t
In a number of countries emerging from authoritarian rule, a new quest for the rule of law is
being encouraged by popular pre s s u re and globalization
w Respectively Professor of
Law at Hong Kong University, and
Editor-in-chief of the UNESCO
Courier
On the steppes of Central Asia in countries
not so long ago under Stalinist rule, youths
are being taught something unimaginable a
decade ago: to defend their legal rights in the
event of being stopped by police.After 17 years of
dictatorship, Benin has a new constitutional court
to which even the humblest citizen can appeal.
Almost one third of its decisions so far have
concerned human rights violations.
The passion for the principle,if not always the
practice, of the rule of law is not coincidental.
Much of the world has changed radically in
recent years, moving from one-party authorita-
rian rule and command economics to multi-party
politics or to free markets,and often both.Rule of
law—a system in which,in theory and in practice,
the law is binding on all persons as well as the
government, a system which treats all equally—is
seen as instrumental to the success of such trans-
formation.
The present wave of transition started 20
years ago in Latin America with the dismantling
of military rule and the establishment of demo-
cracy. This was followed by the collapse of com-
munist regimes in the Soviet bloc, and the shift
towards  more democratic political systems and
free market-oriented reform. Meanwhile, a num-
ber of states and territories in Africa and Asia, as
a result of mass movements (Benin,Indonesia) or
political evolution (Taiwan), are changing autho-
ritarian or dictatorial regimes to more participa-
tory and accountable systems.
Momentum for legal reform has come from
growing popular pressure at national level, as well
as from globalization,the catch-word not only for
increasing trade and economic integration, but
also for standards of civil conduct affecting ordi-
nary people’s basic rights. Membership in econo-
mic and political groupings and federations often
brings international pressure for countries to pro-
tect basic rights through a rule of law.
While a set of laws in itself doesn’t guarantee
individuals rights—Nazi Germany and Stalinist
Soviet Union had legal codes—a legal system
equitably and tenaciously implemented is a cor-
n e rstone of democracy. “I can’t conceive of
democracy without a rule of law,” says Meir
Leker, Secretary General of the International
Association of Legal Science.
The force of tradition
If there is consensus on the need for a rule of
law, the dynamics involved in success or failure in
getting to such a goal are varied. First of all there
is tradition. For instance, one legal scholar traces
the absence of the rule of law in Russia back to
the influence of Russian Orthodoxy on the legal
consciousness and a tradition of absolutism unin-
terrupted for nearly half a millennium. On the
other hand, a strong traditional sense of freedom
can give impetus to the establishment of the rule
of law after a period of dictatorship. Secondly,
socio-economic factors play a part: in free mar-
kets, workers, business owners and investors all
demand protection. Then there is the Weberian
analysis that as political leaderships move away
from chari s m atic legi t i m a cy based on gr e at
deeds—such as leading a revolution—they seek
l e gi t i m a cy elsewhere, including in effective
government through the law.
In the 1960s and 1970s, USAID (the U. S .
A g e n cy for Intern ational Development) and the
Ford Fo u n d ation sponsored law reform pro-
grammes in the South directed more at economic
and social development than political deve l o p m e n t .
By and large they fa i l e d . G ove rnments which pas-
sed the laws had little commitment to them.
S u f ficient resources were seldom provided for the
i m p l e m e n t ation of the law s. Most projects ove r e s t i-
m ated the capacity of states to absorb new policies
and institutions; for example there were not
e n o u g h , or not enough well trained, l aw ye rs ,j u d g e s ,
a d m i n i s t r at o rs , who understood or were able to
o p e r ate the new law s. Most projects underestimat e d
the persistence of custom and customary practices.
Many similar issues arise in current efforts to
build a rule of law. Here we assess the dynamics
at play in those attempts. n
If there is consensus 
on the need for a rule of law,
the dynamics involved 
in success or failure in getting 
to such a goal are varied
Nobody has a more
sacred obligation 
to obey the law 
than those who make
the law.
S o p h o c l e s,
G reek poet (496-406 B. C. )
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 19
Making the leap to a rule of l a w
1 Former Soviet bloc
No quick fix
w Stephen Holmes
Fo re i g n e rs have swamped the former Soviet bloc with legal advice,
but the results have fallen far short of expectations
Over the past half-dozen ye a rs , a flock of
foreign development agencies and pri vat e
foundations have organized a multimillion-
dollar effort to promote “the rule of law ” in the for-
mer Soviet bloc.Aimed at fostering stability in the
r e gi o n , these multilateral and bilateral effort s ,o f t e n
ove r l a p p i n g, were not entirely eleemosynary.W h i l e
political stability would reduce the security bu r d e n
on the West,economic stability would presumably
p r ovide a new market for We s t e rn goods and a
favourable business climate for We s t e rn inve s t m e n t .
Embedded in these legal assistance progr a m m e s
are a handful of basic assumptions, the most impor-
tant of which is that the free market is creat e d , s u s-
t a i n e d , and constantly re-attuned by legi s l at i ve and
a d j u d i c at i ve decisions that must be reliably enfor-
c e d .E s s e n t i a l l y, l aw is seen as a springboard to eco-
nomic deve l o p m e n t . In line with this idea, the lion’s
share of foreign aid for legal reform in Eastern
Europe and Russia has been devoted to improv i n g
the security of acquisitions and transactions.
But considerable resources have also been
aimed at promoting, for instance, voting rights and
due-process rights for criminal suspects. Unfortu-
nately, in these areas too, more attention has been
paid to on-paper legi s l at i ve advances than to solving
pervasive problems of compliance and implemen-
t at i o n .S t rictly on-paper reform efforts flowed nat u-
rally from the weakness of enforcement capacities in
Eastern Europe after 1989 and Russia after 1991,
and to some extent from a long tradition of legal
r e g u l ations which appeared “on the books” bu t
were not followed or enforced in practice.
W h at have we learned from these imperfect
efforts?
Lesson one:
the magnitude of the problem
The first steps of legal reform , such as the draf-
ting and ratification of a bill of rights,may be rela-
tively easy. But subsequent steps,such as creating
an honest civil service,are much harder.
I m p r oving the quality of public institutions
requires a broad and deep social consensus and
capacity for co-operat i o n . L aw is a public good,
and politically disorganized societies, by defin i t i o n ,
have a hard time creating public goods.The unde-
renforcement of basic rights in,say, Russia is often
a product of fiscal insolve n cy. The miserably low
s a l a ries and benefits of Russian judges, which have
engendered a crisis of unders t a f fing and low - q u a l i t y
personnel, constitute a major obstacle to the deli-
very of justice in the Russian Federation.
One must thus recognize that legal reform is a
branch of state-building. Legal development pro-
jects have scored only modest successes in the
r e gion because, among other reasons, the post-
communist state remains incapable of repressing
force and fraud.
But the post-communist state must not only
become stronger; it must simultaneously become
more accountable. Accountable gove rn m e n t , i n
t u rn , presupposes a society well-organized enough
to discipline office-holders.
w Professor of Politics and Law
at Princeton University and New
York University School of Law, and
director (1995-97) of the Soros
Foundation’s legal reform
programme in Eastern Europe and
Russia
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
Human-rights projects in the region have ten-
ded to channel resources toward private actors in
civil society and to neglect gove rnment as a part n e r.
Commercial-law projects, by contrast, have chan-
neled resources, including We s t e rn expert i s e , t o
g ove rnmental agencies, neglecting “civil society”
or private-sector actors as potential partners. The
first lesson of a half-decade of abortive or stalled
legal reform is therefore the need to compensat e
for these symmetrical short c o m i n g s. Legal deve-
lopment projects must aim at increasing the res-
ponsiveness of government to social interests and
opinions.
Lesson two:
the illusions of reform 
by decree
The rule of law implies that the legi s l at u r e
wields serious powers and bears serious responsi-
b i l i t i e s. It is therefore next to impossible to conduct
a successful legal reform programme without a
r e f o rm majority in the lawmaking body. If the legi s-
l ature and the exe c u t i ve branches are unable to co-
operate, as they are in Russia,many of the laws in
force will be anti-reform or, at the ve ry least, i n c o m-
petently or shoddily drafted.
The designers of foreign technical assistance
p r o grammes should not, t h e r e f o r e , ove r e s t i m at e
the effectiveness of rule of decree, that is, by one-
sided exe c u t i ve-branch decisions, t h at do not repre-
sent a wide social consensus and have not been
hammered out in a process of consultation with
social forces outside a small clique in the Kremlin.
Foreign-funded projects should target technical
assistance to areas of legal reform where exe c u t i ve -
legislative co-operation is possible.
Lesson three:
the inadequacy 
of mirror-imaging
Much of We s t e rn legal-development aid has
aimed at replicating We s t e rn institutions abroad.
In the early 1990s, e s p e c i a l l y,We s t e rn-trained legal-
d e velopment professionals often strove to trans-
f o rm the legal systems of Eastern Europe and Rus-
sia to make them resemble the legal systems they
knew at home. But law is not a kitchen appliance
t h at we can unplug in the United States or Ger-
m a ny and simply plug in again in Bucharest or
Sofia. Recipient input in (even a veto over) model
selection and import is essential.
Lesson four:
lack of trained development
professionals
Lawyers are trained to solve routine problems
within routine procedures.They are not trained to
r e flect creat i vely on the emergence and stabiliza-
tion of the complex institutions which law ye ri n g
silently presupposes. Ordinary legal training, the-
r e f o r e , is not adequate to the extraordinary pro-
blems faced by the manager of a legal deve l o p m e n t
project in Eastern Europe or Russia.Legal reform
cannot succeed without attention to social context,
local infrastru c t u r e , professional skills, l o gi s t i c
capacities,and political support.
The much-lamented lack of donor co-ordina-
tion is rooted in the weak theoretical framewo r k
underlying the foreign funding of legal reform .T h e
European Union and the U. S . should jointly creat e
and fund a “Legal Reform Strat e gies Centre” t o
p r ovide a “ d ri ve r ’s manual” for legal reform ,b a s e d
on empirical studies.
Lesson five:
project selection,
governmental support
For the sake of sustainability, project selection
must give greater weight to recipient interest and
commitment than to donor interest and commit-
ment.Law is an aspect of sovereignty. As a conse-
quence,many foreign-funded rule-of-law projects
will inevitably operate under joint supervision of
the foreign donor and the local government.This
doubling of oversight and reporting requirements
m ay in some cases paralyze the operation of the
p r o gramme or destroy its coherence. This is rea-
son enough for development agencies to continue
to work as closely as possible with “ c l i e n t s ” or part-
ners within the government.That necessity, howe-
ver,imposes certain limits on project selection.
The “ rule of law ” s l o g a n , r e m e m b e r , is redo-
lent of the Cold War, when it was used to express
the We s t ’s sense of moral superi o rity over the Sov i e t
b l o c.To d ay, it is essential that We s t e rn - financed law
p r o grammes avoid all appearance of tri u m p h a l i s m
or imperi a l i s m . Since anti-piracy laws aim at
making Russians pay more for We s t e rn videos,
C D s , and softwa r e , over-emphasis on such laws can
leave the impression that the West is seeking “tri-
bute”after its “victory”in the Cold War.
Lesson six:
project selection: social support 
Given the limited resources at the disposal of
foreign legal assistance progr a m m e s , it makes sense
to choose projects strat e gi c a l l y. Projects with some
potential for producing interim successes—and the-
refore able to sustain donor interest and commit-
ment—should be favoured over projects that will
have no visible benefits for 20 or 50 years.
In general, foreign support should be given to
l aw reform efforts which combine top-down and
bottom-up features,working both with the regula-
tors and the regulated.Stated differently, the crea-
tion of a functioning ru l e - o f - l aw system depends
on negotiated ru l e - m a k i n g . Foreign-funded legal
development projects should aim at strengthening
c o n s u l t at i ve and co-operat i ve relations betwe e n
s t ate and society.The relat i ve strength of such rela-
tions in Poland and Hungary helps explain the
modest but important advances they have achie-
ved in the area of legal reform . It is the weakness of
s t ate-society relations elsewhere in the form e r
S oviet bloc that explains the weakness of the rule of
law in many post-communist states today. n
It is better to do 
your own duty, h o w e v e r
i m p e r f e c t l y, than to
assume 
the duties of another
p e r s o n , h o w e v e r
s u c c e s s f u l l y.
B h a g a v a d - G i t a
( S a c red Book of India)
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
November 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 21
Making the leap to a rule of l a w
At the Judicial Training Centre in Bishkek, a
staff member slips a C D-Rom into a compu-
ter,calls up all the legislation passed in Kyr-
gyzstan since last August and scrolls down several
screens of amendments and law s. Such readily ava i-
lable inform ation and technology are rare in this
cash-strapped nation of 4.7 million inhabitants that
has built its reputation since independence in 1991
on the boldness of its democratic reforms, to such
an extent that it can be hard for the judicial profes-
sion to keep up.
In a district court of the capital, there are no
such modern installat i o n s. The walls here are in
dire need of repainting, a bare lightbulb hangs ove r
an uncluttered desk staffed by two clerks, a manual
t y p e w riter sits atop a large locker, and a hard bench
is propped in a corridor leading to the judge’s offic e .
I n s i d e , there is no sign of being in a state body—no
official portrait, no flag, no emblem or uniformed
officials.
The case underway involves a private bank,the
n ational securities commission and a newspaper,
none of which has a lawyer.The bank is suing the
securities commission for defamation after the lat-
ter accused it of providing false inform ation and
publicized the affair in the press. Into the fif t h
h e a ri n g, the case, one of the more complex ones
heard by this judge, e xe m p l i fies an all too common
problem.“The main difficulty is applying the new
l aw s ,” she say s.“Sometimes there are many contra-
dictions within the law, which makes our task very
difficult, especially given the number of new laws
adopted in the last two years.”
Her struggle echoes that of many of the coun-
try’s 300-odd judges trying to come to grips with
new laws and codes (including a civil, tax code and
c riminal code) gove rning entirely novel fields of
e x p e rt i s e : leasing and selling bu i l d i n g s ,f r a n c h i s i n g,
p r o p e rty ri g h t s ,p ri vate bu s i n e s s ,b a n k ru p t cy, b a n-
k i n g, customs and organized cri m e . And there is
more to come:the family code is being revised and
the final touches have just been put on a new elec-
toral code, which will be put to the test this fa l l .
This intense activity is a far cry from the days when
new laws were passed down from Moscow and the
judicial system was under the helm of the commu-
nist part y. N ow judges and law ye rs are not only
expected to understand the new legislation along
with intern ational instru m e n t s , but to help conceive
new laws and amend former ones.
Economic integration
Since independence,Kyrgyzstan has often hai-
led itself as “the Switzerland of Central Asia”—a
multiethnic country that has gone further than any
of its neighbours in constructing an open society.
S u rrounded by gas-rich Uzbekistan and oil-ri c h
K a z a k h s t a n , not to mention China—some argue
t h at the resource-poor country had no other option
than to invest in democratic reforms as a way to
attract intern ational attention and integr ate into
the world market. Along with efforts to fight cor-
ruption, make the state administration more effi-
cient and institutions more credible, P r e s i d e n t
Asker Akaev has repeatedly stressed the import a n c e
of strengthening economic integr at i o n . L a s t
N ove m b e r , Kyrgyzstan became the first country in
the region to join the World Trade Organization.
“This is all out of our own domestic nat i o n a l
i n t e r e s t s ,” s ays Ednan Karabaev of the Ky r g y z - R u s-
sian Slavic Unive rs i t y. “ We started by reforming the
s t at e , while Uzbekistan began with the economic
s t ru c t u r e . In our case, the previous gove rning stru c-
ture would not have allowed the reforms to succeed,
whereas in Uzbekistan, there would have been aw UNESCO Courier journalist
Ky rg y z s t a n : b reaking out 
of the old shell
w Cynthia Guttman
In Ky rg y z s t a n , widely re g a rded as the most democratic country in Central A s i a , legal reform 
is running up against old attitudes and dire economic conditions
Fourth year law students at Ky rgyz National State Univers i t y :e n rollment in this field has surg e d
over the past decade, but students complain about the lack of recent reading materials.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
social explosion had it started off by changing the
political stru c t u r e .” Although recognizing that they
h ave little tradition of self-gove rn a n c e , the Ky r g y z
are fond of claiming that democratic principles are
deeply embedded in their nomadic traditions. L aw
professor Galina Mukambaeva is delving into
M a n a s, the revered national epic, in an attempt to
p r ove that her nation of nomadic tribes had its ow n
s t ructure and ideology over 2,000 ye a rs ago. In the
c a p i t a l , a fie ry equestrian statue of the legend’s hero
is just as present as a giant one of Lenin, which stands
next to the shrine where the Kyrgyz flag is guarded,
a proud symbol of newfound nat i o n h o o d .
A hybrid system
The turning point in this democratization pro-
cess came in May 1993,when Kyrgyzstan adopted
a new constitution that established a secular demo-
c r atic society “based on the fundamentals of rule of
l aw ” . The country counts a fledgling opposition
press (see box ) , legalized trade unions (albeit we a k ) ,
some 20 political part i e s , and over 1,000 non-
g ove rnmental organizat i o n s. It recently became the
first country in the former Soviet Union to autho-
rize private land ownership. Most observers would
agree that the country has a solid legal framework
but the context remains very fragile for putting it
into practice. Extreme pove rty is on the ri s e ,p ri vat e
business lacks the wherewithal to kickstart the eco-
nomy, and many, especially in rural areas, long for
the times when the state provided a cushioned secu-
ri t y. In the south, a hostage crisis and border war are
d r a g ging on. They have already claimed over a
dozen lives and displaced several thousand people.
The separation of three branches of power is
one of the cornerstones of the Constitution,which
represents a radical break from the omnipotence
of the stat e . “There were situations at the begi n-
ning of independence when the gove rnment tried to
use the judges and court s ,” s ays Mr Ty l e b a l i e v,
chairman of the Supreme Court.“But now things
h ave changed, and the court system is indepen-
dent.” Not everyone would agree that such a long
road has been travelled,however,starting with the
judges themselves. Seventy per cent of them prac-
ticed during the Soviet period. Now they have to
learn to function in a hybrid system mingling ele-
ments from the  European and A n g l o - A m e ri c a n
m o d e l s , with many laws from Soviet times still pre-
vailing in amended form.
“We’re moving from an inquisitorial model to
an adversarial model. Under the previous system,
the prosecutors would bring the case, the judges
were very passive,” explains Lamar Cravens,of the
A m e rican Bar A s s o c i at i o n ’s Central and East Euro-
pean Law Initiative.“Without a habit of initiative,
i t ’s ve ry hard to enforce the new procedural ru l e s.”
Lawyers are also faced with the task of sharpening
their advo c a cy skills and understanding all the
defence mechanisms available to them in protecting
their clients. N atalia A b l ova , director of the Bureau
on Human Rights and Rule of Law, regrets that all
too many law ye rs fail to apply intern ational human
rights instruments in arguing their cases.
Herding sheep
to make ends meet
But even with the strongest commitment,
judges can seldom devote themselves heart and
mind to their task.“ S a l a ry is one of the most impor-
tant elements necessary for judges to keep their
i n d e p e n d e n c e . I know of judges who keep sheep
and cattle to surv i ve ,” s ays Anarkul To k s o b a e va ,
Vital statistics
Po p u l a t i o n: 4.7 million, of which an estimated 61.2% live in rural areas.
Principal ethnic groups (1989 census):Ky r g y z :5 2 % ,R u s s i a n :2 1 . 5 % ;
Uzbek:12.9%
GNP: $1.7 billion;GNP per capita:$350
Human Development Index ranking: 97
Poverty (% of population below national poverty line): 51%
Literacy (% of population age 15+): 97
Life expectancy at birth (years): 67
External debt as % of GDP: 54.4%
Source: World Bank,Human Development Report 1999
note: figures vary by up to  20% according to the source used
A new sense of re s p o n s i b i l i t y
There is no more poignant illustration of extreme poverty in Kyrgyzstan than the sight of elderly
women erring the streets,hawking a few newspapers that passersby might not have picked up
at one of the city’s kiosks. Freedom of expression is a constitutional right and was further bolstered
by a referendum in 1998 forbidding the adoption of laws limiting press freedom.A fledgling oppo-
sition press exists, and yet, over the years, it has lived through a steady tug of war with government.
An emblematic figure of the opposition press is Zamira Sydyko va ,e d i t o r-in-chief of Res Publica, v i e-
wed by many as the veteran opposition newspaper. S y d y ko va spent two and a half months in pri-
son over a series criticizing the chairman of the Kyrgyz gold mining company.Another journalist spent
four months in prison over an article on the appalling conditions of workers living in factory dormi-
t o r i e s. Last year, an edition of the paper was banned in a region where a toxic spill by a foreign com-
pany occurred. S y d y ko va puts her problems down to money and the high risk involved in criticizing
sacred cows:“Such cases come up every time you touch someone in a high position, and the state
is always the winner.”More recently, the editor of the opposition daily Vechernii Bishkek ran into pro-
blems with law enforcement, allegedly over tax issues.Talgat A s y ra n k u l o v,president of I n d e p e n d e n t
B i s h kek T V, one of four independent channels,believes he has avoided problems by sticking to fir m
p r i n c i p l e s :“we broadcast information that has been checked three times and presents several dif-
ferent viewpoints.We show no violence, no drugs and make no political declara t i o n s.” The OSCE
monitors press freedom and tries to serve as a clearing house for complaints,but Jerzy Wieclaw urges
caution in the matter. “Newspapers sometimes run into problems because they don’t check their
i n f o r m a t i o n . There should be an element of responsibility, and this is still something new here.” n
K Y R G Y Z S T A N
Bishkek
Kazakhstan
Tajikistan
Uzbekistan
China
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 23
The quest for r u l e of lawMaking t  leap to a    
director of the Judicial Training Centre, which orga-
nizes seminars for judges on analysing new legisla-
t i o n .A judge earns approx i m ately $40 per month—
more than a teacher ($15 to $20 a month) or a
g ove rnment clerk ($10 a month) but far short of the
minimum required to survive. Such a context can
undermine the ideal of judicial independence. “If
you don’t come under pressure from a member of
p a r l i a m e n t , you come under the pressure of the
shadow economy,” notes Toksobaeva.
The selection process is also a point of debate:
judges are appointed for a set term by the presi-
dent upon the recommendation of an at t e s t at i o n
committee, a process that parliament is seeking to
m o d i f y.“ C r e ating an independent judiciary is really
the major problem of this country:to have elected
j u d g e s , at least at some leve l , to improve their stat u s ,
if not in a radical mat e rial way, at least to gi ve them
the feeling of independence,” s ays Jerzy W i e c l aw,
head of the Organization for Security and Co-ope-
ration in Europe (OSCE) in Kyrgyzstan.
Instilling confidence in the court system is a
lengthy task, rendered all the more difficult if the
judiciary’s image is tainted.Before lodging a com-
p l a i n t , people have to prove they have paid their
state tax.Many cannot afford a lawyer. Law enfor-
cement agencies are judged weak and often unk-
nowledgeable about their own law and internatio-
nal obligations. “People’s rights are frequently vio-
lated, whether by a state body or another person,
but they have no custom of turning to the courts,”
s ays Mirgul Smanalieva , head of the A t t o rn e y s
Association of Kyrgyzstan.“One of our goals is to
organize TV programmes to explain to people how
they should behave and who they should turn to
when their rights are violated.If each citizen knew
their rights and could fight for them, m aybe our
system would work more effectively.”
Such an investment in civil society is considered
one of the keys to entrenching rule of law.“ I t ’s a little
better than before but people still don’t know their
ri g h t s , they don’t know what the constitution means,
h ow their taxes are spent or how to lobby for their
i n t e r e s t s ,” s ays A s i ya Sasykbaeva , head of the Inter-
belim center, an umbrella organization providing ser-
vices to improve NGO capacity.The Soros foundat i o n
is earmarking 8 per cent of its budget towards law
p r o grammes (against 2.5 per cent at present) to sup-
p o rt law and human rights projects,open up legal aid
centres and improve the competence of administrat i ve
o f ficials in the regi o n s.Schools are also a target.“ T h e
goal is to make eve ry student feel they are a citizen of
this country and to understand they have human
ri g h t s ,”s ays Atyrkul A l i s h e va of the Institute for Regi o-
nal Studies, explaining the aim of her textbook on
l aw, constitution and human ri g h t s , which is being
used for the first time this year in high schools.
Soul-searching
At the university level,where law is a subject in
growing demand, new disciplines are being intro-
duced, especially in the field of international law.
Some faculties are trying to encourage more ana-
lysis and less rote learning, more practice and less
theory. Although new books are being written by
p r o f e s s o rs , m a ny of those still in use date from
S oviet times, l i b r a ries are poor, there is a lack of
published legal commentaries and a number of law
faculties are short of qualified teaching staff. The
multiplication in the number of universities since
independence (from 9 to 23) has also led to wide
gaps in quality.The ABA is urging the government
to set up a national competency standards exam
for all students wishing to practice law.
In a country still soul searching after the col-
lapse of the USSR, youth are likely in the best posi-
tion for shaping a new ideology. According to the
O S C E ’s Jerzy W i e c l aw, “ e d u c ated youth want to
think and behave like Europeans, this is their point
of reference.” Although jobs in the legal field are
hard to come by at present, S m a n a l i e va has no
doubts about the commitment of the yo u n g .
“There is a big difference between the young gene-
r ation and ours.We had a complex about expressing
our minds openly, and this interferes with our abi-
lity to be creat i ve .The young speak openly and bra-
vely and can convince.They are the ones who will
really bring in reforms.” n
Checking the headlines at a kiosk in Bishkek,the capital.The country boasts a small
opposition press and several independent television channels.
You must remember that
some things 
that are l e g a l l y right are
not m o r a l l y r i g h t .
A b raham Lincoln,
U. S. statesman (1809-1865)
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
Vital statistics
Surface area: 604,000 sq km
Population: 50.3 million;life expectancy:67 years
Poverty: 32% of population below national poverty line
GNP: $42.7 billion;GNP annual growth - 2.4%
GNP per capita: $850 (1998 estimate), a fall of more than 60% since
i n d e p e n d e n c e. ( O f ficial figures overstate fall in output because of
expansion of the informal economy beyond the reach of government
regulations. Estimates of the informal economy range as high as 60%
of GDP).
S o u r c e : World Bank
U k ra i n e : legal e a g l e s
with clipped wings 
w Serhiy Holova t y
U k raine embarked on a far- reaching legal reform pro g ra m m e, but found that old habits die
h a rd in an entrenched n o m e n k l a t u r a. B e l o w, the viewpoint of a former Minister of Ju s t i c e
Shedding 350 ye a rs of colonial serv i t u d e
when it became a state eight years ago,
Ukraine has confronted enormous difficul-
ties in establishing the institutions of democracy,
including a rule of law.
In 1995 Ukraine became a member of the
Council of Europe, voluntarily taking upon itself
to fulfil obligations concerning the adoption of a
new democratic constitution, the drafting of new
civil and criminal codes, the reform of the judi-
ciary and the harmonizing of its legislation with
European norms and standards of human rights
and freedoms. In June 1996, the passage of a
constitution expressing Ukraine’s desire to build
a rule of law was hailed by the Council of Europe.
Yet on the whole there is less democracy in
Ukraine today than there was four ye a rs ago.
Ukraine is in default of its obligations under the
t e rms of its accession to the Council of Europe, t h e
j u d i c i a ry generally remains corrupt and ineffic i e n t ,
e xe c u t i ve and legi s l at i ve intransigence have left ini-
t i at i ves with respect to Ukraine’s commitments
suspended in a legi s l at i ve purgat o ry, and corru p-
tion is rampant in Ukraine’s public administrat i o n .
As a result, Ukrainian society’s view of the law is
marked by cynicism and scepticism.
Soviet legacy
The genesis of the problem lies in the legacy of
S oviet rule and the monopoly of state power in
Ukrainian society. S oviet era elites retained powe r
after independence and now continue to wield tre-
mendous administrat i ve control over the lives of
c i t i z e n s.To d ay they ove rsee the unbridled distri bu-
tion of state propert y, and exercise control ove r
most economic activity, resulting in widespread
institutional corru p t i o n .They have expanded their
p ower by establishing new administrat i ve bodies to
r e g u l ate the pri vate sector and citizens’ p ri vate acti-
vities through the imposition of licences, q u o t a s
and other controls. With institutions of civil socie-
ty too weak to hold them to account, the gove rn i n g
n o m e n k l at u ra has no incentive to promote signifi-
cant democrat i c, especially legal, r ef o rms so long as
its members continue to be the principal benefic i a-
ries of the existing system.
In 1995, I as Minister of Justice designed a
reform programme in line with the principles of
the Council of Europe and the provisions of
Ukraine’s constitution.Our key objectives were to
have the ministry of justice take the leading role
in the administration of justice in the country, to
promote and secure individual human rights and
freedoms, to create a market-oriented legal infra-
structure, and generally to incorporate transpa-
rency and openness in the legal system.
A comprehensive legal reform programme
was undertaken, involving everything from the
rights of the accused upon detention and arrest,
to the principle of an accused’s innocence until
guilt is proven.
‘Clean hands’
to wipe out corruption
But weak governance has allowed corruption
to flourish.It has resulted in the emergence of the
present machinery of government where respon-
sibilities overlap and accountabilities are diffuse,
in ministerial ownership of commercial activities
and associated conflicts of interest, in the low pay
and poor supervision of civil servants and in the
lack of a public service ethos in the civil service.
Changing the prevailing mentality from a com-
mand approach to public administration to an
w A member of parliament and
former Ukrainian Minister of
Justice, Serhiy Holovaty is president
of the Ukrainian Legal Foundation,
which was founded in 1992 to
work towards the establishment of
the rule of law in Ukraine.
U K R A I N E
Kiev
Romania
Poland
Belarus
Black Sea
Sea 
of Azov
Russia
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 25
Making the leap to a rule of l a w
approach based on a transparent, accountable
public service is a daunting task.
The ministry of justice undertook concrete
measures to bring the issues of transparency and
accountability in government to public attention.
In April 1997, the President of Ukraine adopted
a “National Programme against Corruption”,
popularly referred to as the “Clean Hands” cam-
paign, developed by the ministry. This program-
me proposed a systemic approach to the problem
of corru p t i o n , including legi s l at i ve initiat i ve s ,
deregulation of the economy, and the reform of
public administration to make it more accoun-
table and transparent.
Judges under threat
The ministry ’s reform efforts were ve h e m e n t l y
resisted by the entrenched n o m e n k l at u ra in gove rn-
ment and the judiciary, largely by implementing
the programme to the minimum necessary extent,
then claiming that it had been carried out.
The problem of building an independent judi-
ciary proved particularly acute. Today’s judges
still carry the burden of Soviet traditions, when
the judiciary often acted in tandem with prosecu-
tors and communist party officials to suppress the
rights of individuals. They are under-trained and
so poorly paid that they are largely at the mercy
of threats and bribes from the political and admi-
nistrative authorities over which they should be
exercising control. It is common for judges to
receive threats from local authorities to cut off
electricity, gas and heat if “appropriate” decisions
are not rendered. Both the public and the judicia-
ry remain ignorant of the citizens’ constitutional
rights to be protected from official interference in
the judicial process. Efforts to establish a legal
basis for a market economy have not met with
greater success.
Indeed, most citizens of Ukraine are alarmin-
gly resigned to the status quo, and do not yet
appreciate, let alone insist upon, the enforcement
of the rights they now possess. Thus, reform of
the legal system is hampered by a collective
memory of the use of the law by state authorities
as an instrument of oppression, and not as the
handmaiden of individual liberty.
This situation is compounded by the state of
the legal profession. Numerous attempts have fai-
led over the past few years to establish a profes-
sional, self-governing law society which would
ensure the protection of the rights of citizens and
the provision of quality legal services. The prima-
ry impediment to the realization of this goal is
that Ukraine today still possesses a legal culture
where lawyers are seen, and see themselves, as
servants of the state. Most law school graduates
still seek employment in law enforcement bodies
or in government agencies.
Stalinist forces
on the prowl
The prokuratura—established by Stalin as a
completely autonomous law enforcement body
with extensive powers of supervision over all
levels of government and administration, and
powers to initiate actions in criminal matters—
continues to perform many of its Soviet-era func-
tions, including supervision over judicial deci-
sions. Even though under Council of Europe
obligations that are incorporated in the constitu-
tion, the prokuratura was to have shed its Stalinist
responsibilities, its investigative powers have been
expanded. After a brief attempt at reform, the
State Security Service, the SBU, is once again
performing many of the functions of its predeces-
sor, the KGB. With some exceptions, the legal
profession has largely been silent and ineffective
in safeguarding citizens against these and other
abuses of their rights.
To turn this situation around requires the emer-
gence of a new legal culture based on the pri n c i p l e s
of the rule of law set out in the constitution.T h e s e
p r ovide for a new relationship between the indivi-
dual and the stat e , whereby the state undertakes to
f o s t e r , p r e s e rve and protect the human rights and
freedoms of the individual. R e a l i z ation of these
o b j e c t i ves requires an understanding of what the
constitutional rights of the Ukrainian citizen mean
and how they should be applied.
This is fundamentally the responsibility of
Ukraine’s law schools. And here they are failing
miserably. They remain fundamentally conserva-
tive. Educators continue to teach that the law is
an instrument of sanction by the government,
and not an instrument to protect the rights of citi-
zens against the excesses of the stat e . T h e
Ukrainian Legal Foundation has made a start
towards the creation of a new law school along
the European model by founding the Ukrainian
Centre for Legal Studies, which teaches human
rights and market-oriented commercial law. n
A July 1997 demonstration of Kiev tradespeople demanding tax reductions and measures
against bureaucratic corruption.
It is easier to change
laws than it is to change
mentalities and inertia.
F rancisco Fernández Ord ó ñ e z
Spanish lawyer and
politician (1930-1992)
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
Civil law: Inspired by Roman law. L e gi s l ation is the
primary source of law. Civil codes are the centre-
piece of the legal framework and the foundation of
all other laws which complement or make excep-
tions to it.The codes are mainly characterized by a
high level of abstraction which enables the judge
to interpret and analyse situations either by
applying the legislation or by extrapolatiing from
the overall framewo r k . France is a prototypical civil
l aw nat i o n . O ver 60% of the world population is
influenced by this tradition.
Common law: D e ri ved from English unwritten law
t h at evo l ved from the 12th century onwa r d .K n ow n
as “judge-made law ” . J u ri s p rudence is the pri m a ry
source of law. D e veloped through an inductive
a p p r o a c h , legal concepts emerge and progress ove r
t i m e ,c o n s t ructed by an amalgamation of numerous
cases that bring together the legal scope of these
c o n c e p t s. Common law prevails in the United King-
d o m , the U. S . A . and most Commonwealth coun-
t ri e s ,i n fluencing over 30% of the world populat i o n .
Islamic law: C o n t r o l l e d , ruled and regulated by the
Islamic religion and followed by over 20% of the
world populat i o n . Its main source is the holy book,
the Koran, complemented by the Sunna—limited
i n t e rp r e t ation of the Koran by the prophet.This legal
methodology is known as Shariah (the way to fol-
l ow ) .The sacred law purp o rts to regulate all aspects
of society and its citizens. One unique characteri s t i c
of Islamic law is the precedence of collective ri g h t s
over individual ri g h t s. Individual rights and freedoms
are restricted by the religi o n ’s moral and divine impe-
r at i ve s. Recent developments have favoured an
e x t e n s i ve interp r e t ation of the moral rules to adapt to
the new reality of the 21st century.
Mixed systems. They include two or more legal
methods used concurrently or interactively in a
multi-cultural or multi-religious society. The legal
systems of many North A f rican and Middle Eastern
c o u n t ries are strongly influenced by the civil law tra-
d i t i o n ,but in some areas, especially those relating to
p e rsonal stat u s , family mat t e rs and property law,
these countries tend to follow Islamic tradition.
Customary law: Body of usage and customs that
h ave , through time, acquired force of law.There are
many expressions of customary law, which can be
developed notably through religion, race or cultu-
ral identity. It plays an important role in a relat i ve l y
large number of mixed law countries and, over time,
m a ny of these nations tend to implement their “ c u s-
A world’s eye view  of the l a w
A variety of different legal systems and traditions grew up over many centuries.
Some were exported far and wide. Now there are signs that they are starting to converg e.
Major legal systems
Civil law
Common law
Customary law
Mixed systems
Islamic law
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
November 1999 - The UNESCO Courier 27
Making the leap to a rule of l a w
n 2350 BC:Urukagina’s Code
This code has never been discovered but it is mentioned in other
documents as a consolidation of “ o r d i n a n c e s ” or laws laid
down by Mesopotamian kings.
n 2050 BC:Ur-Nammu’s Code
Earliest known written legal code. Evidence shows it was sup-
ported by a legal system including specialized judges, the giving
of testimony under oath, and the power of judges to order
damages to be paid to a victim by the guilty party.
n 1700 BC:Hammurabi’s Code
This Babylonian king came to power in 1750 BC. Under his rule,
a code of laws was developed and carved on a huge rock column.
The expression “an eye for an eye” has come to symbolize the
c o d e ’s underlying principle.
n 1300 BC:The Ten Commandments
The Prophet Moses received a list of ten laws directly from God.
Known as the Ten Commandments, they later became part of
the Bible.
n 1280 BC to 880 BC:The Laws of Manu
A written compilation of legal rules which had been passed on
from generation to genera t i o n . It formed the basis of the caste
system in India,where people were classified by their social stan-
d i n g . Punishment only used as a last resort. Members of higher
castes punished more severely than those of lower castes.
n 621 BC:Draco’s Law
Draco, a Greek citizen, was chosen to write a code of law for
A t h e n s. The code was so severe that the word “ d ra c o n i a n ”h a s
come to mean unreasonably harsh.
n 450 BC:The Twelve Tables
These laws written to govern Romans are considered to form
the foundation of much modern public and private law. Pro-
moted the organization of public prosecution of crimes and ins-
tituted a system whereby injured parties could seek compen-
sation from their aggressors.A basic principle is that the law must
be written.Justice should not be left to judges alone to inter-
pret.
n 350 BC:The Chinese Code of Li K’vei
The first Chinese imperial code of laws dealt with theft, r o b b e r y,
p r i s o n , arrest and general rules. It served as a model for the T ’ a n g
Code.
n 529: Justinian’s Code
The Byzantine emperor Justinian is remembered for his codific a-
tion of Roman law known as the Corpus Juris Civilis. Many legal
maxims still in use today are derived from the code, which inspi-
red the modern concept of justice.
n 604:The 17-Article Constitution of Japan
Written by a Japanese prince regent,the Constitution shaped mora-
lity and law in Ja p a n .One of its clauses said that “peace and har-
mony should be respected because they are very important for inter-
group relations”.Shows emphasis of “Oriental law” which seeks
to prevent disputes, whereas “ Western law” seeks to resolve
d i s p u t e s.
n 653:T’ang Code
Listed crimes and their punishment in 501 articles, r e v i s i n g
earlier Chinese codes and standardized procedures.
n 1100:First Law School
Started by Italian jurist Irnerius in Bologna.By 1150, it had over
10,000 students and contributed to the revival of the Corpus
Juris and the spread of Roman law throughout Europe.
n 1215:Magna Carta
King John of England signed Magna Carta (the “great charter”),
conceding a number of legal rights to his barons and to the
p e o p l e.The first time a king allowed that he could be compelled
to observe a law or that the barons could question him.Has been
called the “blueprint of English common law”.
n 1776:The American Declaration of Independence
For the first time a government rebuked the medieval theory that
certain people possessed by right the power to rule others.
n 1804:Napoleonic Code
A comprehensive code of law enshrining many victories obtained
during the French Revolution,e. g . individual liberty, equality before
the law and the lay character of the state. Inspired similar civil codes
in the Canadian Province of Quebec (1865), Germany (1900)
and Switzerland (1907).
n 1864:The Geneva Convention
Agreement designed to provide for minimal human rights in time
of wa r, e. g . for protection of military medical personnel and for
humane treatment of the wounded.
n 1945-46:The Nuremberg War Crimes Trial
A panel of eight judges tried Nazi officials for crimes against
peace, crimes against humanity and war crimes, showing that
even in time of war basic moral standards apply.
n 1 9 4 8 :The Universal Declaration of Human Rights
Proclaimed by the United Nations. Enshrines civil,political,
economic,social and cultural rights. n
S o u r c e : The World Wide Legal Information Association (More information can be
found on http://www. w w l i a . o r g / h i s t . h t m )
Landmarks in legal history
tomary laws”in a code.Justice can be delivered in
many ways adapted to local traditions.
Legal systems in former Soviet Union and Eastern
Europe.The vast majority of these countries were
part of the civilist legal tradition prior to the 1917
r e volution or postwar changes. Fo l l owing those
e ve n t s , p a rts of their codes were inva l i d ated to
accommodate communist ideology, and their civil
codes were never fully abrogated between 1917-
1 9 9 1 . Since 1991, Russia and other East European
c o u n t ries have been undergoing important reform s
to adapt to globalization, while remaining true to
their civilist roots.
Impact of globalization: Legal systems have become,
in certain areas, b a rri e rs to the development of
world trade.Hence,in the last 50 years,the rise of
international institutions which promote the har-
monization of laws and try to minimize the effects
of “transystemic legal barri e rs ” .I n t e rn ational trade
is the driving force in the development of a jus com-
mune that will transcend and coexist with traditio-
nal legal systems. n
Prepared with the assistance of the Faculty of Law,
University of Ottawa, and David J. Shaw, attorney at law,
Utah (USA)
If you like laws 
and sausages,
you should never wa t c h
either 
being made.
Otto von Bismarc k ,
German statesman 
( 1 8 1 5 - 1 8 9 8 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
w Sir Y.K. Pao Professor of Law,
Hong Kong University
2 P ro g ress in the South
In traditional societies,
the jury is o u t
on legal re f o r m
w Yash Ghai
Customary laws do not always easily fit into human rights development
t h e o r i e s. But they can play an indispensable  role in ensuring justice
Numerous countries in the South recently
have embraced the idea of the rule of law in
the conviction that legal reform helps nur-
ture nascent democracy and market-ori e n t e d
economic reforms.
Despite ve ry important advantages in establi-
shing a rule of law regi m e , it is neve rtheless a long-
t e rm enterp ri s e . Meanwhile there are certain costs
and problems—so often ignored by legal refor-
m e rs—with the shift to law as a pri m a ry mode of
o r g a n i z ation and framework for policy.
In many societies it is foolish to think of new
legal institutions as a panacea. We cannot assume
that reliance on legal reform will necessarily suc-
c e e d , or that it is appropri ate in all cases.
P s y c h o l o gical attitudes and social conditions
necessary for the rule of law may be absent in cer-
tain societies. The rule of law is not easily establi-
shed in societies where the notion of power is per-
sonalized, rather than located in an office. Nor is
the concept of the limitation of power readily assi-
milated in societies dominated by monarchs or
chiefs or other kinds of hierarchy. States which
are largely agrarian, based on the peasantry and
under the influence of traditional ideologies, are
less likely than largely urban societies to demand
the accountability from their rulers that is essen-
tial for the rule of law. Thus constitutional
reforms in imperial Ethiopia did little to limit or
regulate the government.As a result,introduction
of a rule of law in a Western sense may not only
fail, but also, it could backfire: that is to say, some
of the consequences of reliance on law as a
method of social regulation may be negative.
Contemporary discussions of the strategy of
law tend to overlook the reality of countries that
are largely “pre-modern”. Modernity is associa-
ted with a concept of “rationality” based on a
belief in the scientific method, and confidence
that society can be changed and reformed by
conscious design. Law itself is a deliberate crea-
tion, aimed at clear objectives and regulation. In
that sense the role of state law in modern societies
which have been integrated on the basis of the
economy, particularly the market economy, and
which are closely connected to the apparatus of
the state, can be different from that in societies
which are still dominated by customary values,
institutions and practices.
Cultural factors
and local loyalties
P r e - m o d e rn societies in most Asian and
African states have their own systems of gover-
nance and dispute settlement. Cultural factors
are more, or at least as, important as the econo-
mic. Local loyalties transcend loyalty to the state.
Community pressures are more powerful than
state sanctions in influencing social behaviour.
Justice according to local expectations and by
local institutions is more highly valued than that
of state law and tribunals.
C u s t o m a ry laws and methods do not alway s
easily fit into the human rights development theo-
ries which now dominate the redesign of stat e
s t ru c t u r e s , such as the separation of powe rs or pro-
f e s s i o n a l i z ation of justice. There are undoubtedly
problems with traditional or informal justice. But it
is an important resource and we should attempt to
i m p r ove its effic a cy rather than to eliminate it.
Traditional justice can form the basis of inexpensi-
ve , p a rt i c i p at o ry and accessible forms of justice.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 29
Making the leap to a rule of l a w
A particularly apt illustration of the role of
customary law comes from the persistence of
belief in witchcraft in a large number of societies.
Many aspects of the community, such as recipro-
city, arrogance or private accumulation of wealth
may be more effectively managed through fear of
punishment for transgressions by witchcraft than
by state regulation. National criminal law may
command little allegiance in a community which
does not identify with the state, and which has its
own moral standards. The weakening of traditio-
nal structures by modern laws may undermine
communal mechanisms which help to maintain
social cohesion.
Thus the emphasis on the law at the expense
of customary systems can have quite unexpected
consequences. It can weaken traditional institu-
tions, for example of dispute resolution, before
the institutions of a rule of law can be fully set up
across a country. It is well known that the tradi-
tional function of dispute settlement was to main-
tain balance and harmony in the community and
therefore it aimed at reconciliat i o n . M o d e rn
methods focus more on retribution and thus may
fail to remove the underlying causes of conflict.
There is widespread feeling in Papua New
Guinea that its problems of crime and violence
are associated with the decline of traditional sanc-
tions.The operation of the institutions of modern
law can put access to justice beyond the means of
the large majority of people, particularly in the
rural areas. Courts or other tribunals may not be
available locally. The apparatus of justice, and
those required to mobilize it, tend to concentrate
in urban centres (in Mozambique, for example, a
recent survey found that only 5 per cent of
lawyers are located outside Maputo, the capital).
Access to justice
Moreover,the financial cost of justice through
a formal legal system is much greater than in tra-
ditional systems (as Western states are discove-
ring). Costs include high salaries and other perks
for judges; the fees of prosecutors and defence
lawyers; construction of buildings, libraries and
remand centres. Rules of fair trial require the pro-
vision of legal aid, at least in trials for serious
offences. Few developing states have adequate
resources for these tasks, at least not without
Customary laws and methods 
do not always easily fit 
into the human rights
development theories 
which now dominate 
the redesign of state 
s t r u c t u re s, such as 
the separation of powers or
p rofessionalization of justice
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
societies.The assumption behind the present stra-
tegy of law, reflected in foreign assistance for
democratization or conditions for other forms of
assistance, is that there is a unity of purpose bet-
ween democracy and markets, and that similar
institutions and laws serve them both. However,
the law for the market may have a different struc-
ture and dynamics from that for democracy. Law
for democracy is about the empowerment and
protection of all people,particularly the weak; but
law for the market is about conferring power on
the rich and the well organized. Property, a prin-
cipal legal instrument for the market, reduces the
scope for commons, i.e., property owned collecti-
vely, and transforms it into a private entity.
This results in the impoverishment of many
and the enrichment of a few. Property, combined
with another legal instrument for the market,
contract, has become the major means whereby
capitalists own, and exercise control over, the
labour, and other resources, of the poor.
Laws made
by private interests
These developments have at least two adverse
effects on democracy. First, more and more poli-
cies and laws are made at the behest of foreign
states and capital, reducing the scope of national
democratic decision making. Increasingly these
laws are made by private interests, either in inter-
national economic institutions, or more directly
by commercial corporations through joint ven-
tures and arbitration regimes. For example, many
countries have been pressed to bring in legislation
on intellectual property rights, particularly in
genetic engineering, which has opened natural
resources to foreign ownership. In India such
legislation was opposed widely by farmers and
other interest groups, but the government was
under gr e at pressure from the World Tr a d e
Organization (WTO) and the U.S. government to
enact it. Finally, mention can be made of laws or
regulations which have eaten away at workers’
rights,or welfare provisions for education or heal-
th, despite considerable public opposition.
Secondly, there is a distinct shift of domestic
political power to wealthy domestic classes, in
alliance with foreign capital.A large part of these
developments are brought about by and encapsu-
lated in the l aw, which is often imposed, as the
a b ove examples show, and as is illustrated by the
conditions imposed on Korea, Thailand and
Indonesia by the World Bank and the Intern at i o n a l
M o n e t a ry Fund for assistance to them during the
recent financial cri s e s.
I realize that there is no easy answer to the
problems of change.There is undoubtedly a dan-
ger of romanticizing traditional systems, forget-
ting the oppression that takes place within its
interstices. It is sufficient here to warn against the
opposite tendency, the romanticizing of formal
legalized systems,and to urge caution in the stra-
tegy of law. n
diverting them from the more material needs of
the people.
The grafting of a modern legal system on to a
customary one may reduce real access to justice
for some social groups. One reason is that lawyers
are able to use their power to oust from the legal
sector those without full legal qualifications and
to secure monopolies of legal serv i c e s. I n
Cambodia and Mozambique, for example, an
increasingly organized legal profession has exclu-
ded from the system paralegal defenders who pre-
viously rendered important legal services after a
period of six-12 months training, compared with
several years training for lawyers.This has increa-
sed the cost of legal services and has reduced
access to legal representation.
A fair trial
Furthermore, formal systems of justice are
marked by lengthy delays. These are the results
not only of procedural rules, but also of the shor-
tage of lawyers and judges (and sometimes of the
lack of transport to take remand prisoners to
courts). Police are seldom trained or able to cope
with the formal legal system. They lack forensic
and investigative skills, and this leads to long per-
iods of  detention or remand of suspects, or the
use of pressure, sometimes amounting to torture,
to extract confessions. The notion of a fair trial
involves at least one appeal. There is a serious
backlog of cases, and consequently a denial of
justice. At the same time, traditional institutions
which not only would deal expeditiously and
effectively with these cases, but also provide sta-
bility in social relations, are marginalized or abo-
lished. Unencumbered by complex rules of pro-
cedure and restrictions on admissibility of
evidence, traditional leaders were able to settle
disputes speedily.
Formalization of the legal system and the legal
profession may decrease the capacity of the
government itself to make use of the legal system.
This is the consequence of the high salaries that
lawyers can command in the private sector. The
problem is, once again, illustrated by Cambodia
and Mozambique. Top lawyers in both these
countries have gravitated to the private sector,
p a rticularly to service large corp o r at i o n s. A s
governments cannot hire lawyers of equal compe-
tence due to official salary scales, the government
is at considerable disadvantage during negotia-
tions with a corporation or investors as a group.
In both these states, considerable legislative draf-
ting is done by private firms of lawyers; in fact
they, and not the government end by making poli-
cy in crucial public matters. The difficulties for
the government are aggravated as these develop-
ments lead to greater integration of the national
economy into the global system, increasing the
reliance on lawyers with international and com-
parative expertise.
This brings us to a fundamental problem
underlying legal reform in many pre-modern
It goes without saying
that a law 
to be valid must be clear
enough to make its
c o m m a n d s.
Hugo L. B l a c k ,
U. S. Senator and Supreme Court
Justice 
( 1 8 8 6 - 1 9 7 1 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 31
Making the leap to a rule of l a w
B e n i n : j u s t i c e on the horizon
w René Lefort
The law is paramount in Benin, but the courts and the police are still not 
e n f o rcing it effectively
‘Twe n t y - five thieves bu rned alive in Benin by
v i gilante gr o u p s ,” read the headline on a
recent news agency story. After a spate of
r o b b e ries and rapes, the thieve s , mostly immigr a n t s ,
were publicly burned to death in the southeastern
p r ovince of Couffo in A u g u s t . The gove rn m e n t
sent troops to beef up the local police, but lynch law
is spreading and replacing police work and the judi-
cial process.
Yet the U. S . S t ate Department and human
rights organizations both within and outside Benin
s ay the country has become “a constitutional demo-
cracy” and “is now living under the rule of law”.
Benin is held up as an example in sub-Saharan
A f ri c a , where “the wind of democracy ”t h at blew in
the early 1990s is otherwise dying down.
Benin is ahead of the pack,says Maurice Glele
Ahanhanzo, a member of the country’s constitu-
tional court, because legal principles are now so
deeply rooted in the population that “they have
become the main instrument for regulating life in
s o c i e t y ” .H owe ve r , the Beninese can see that these
principles are still very far from being effectively
applied, even by the courts. They draw their own
c o n c l u s i o n s , all too often by taking the law into
their own hands.
Benin’s “democratic revival”is home-grown—
it hasn’t been copied from elsewhere. Unlike the
situation in many other French-speaking African
states,it does not stem from the loss of a powerful
ally after the Berlin Wall came down. Nor is it the
result of pressure following France’s decision,
announced by President François Mitterrand in a
speech to francophone A f rican leaders in June
1 9 9 0 , to make aid to A f rican countries conditional
upon their progress towards democracy. If there has
been any outside influence, it has come from the
foreign aid agencies whose intervention became
indispensable because of Benin’s ru n d own eco-
nomy.
The “democratic revival”is above all the result
of a dynamic process within Beninese society that
was triggered by the rejection of 17 ye a rs of
“Marxist-Leninist” dictatorship.The old regime’s
death knell was sounded in February 1990 by a
c o n f e r e n c e , the first of its kind in A f ri c a ,t h at brought
together the “dynamic forces of the nat i o n ” . A
constitution adopted a few months later was “in its
entirety devised, sought for and drafted by the
people of Benin,” s ays A h a n h a n z o. It started by
“ a f firming the deep-rooted opposition” of the Beni-
nese people to the previous regi m e ’s legal viola-
tions and other failings.
A counterweight
to the authorities
Another factor lies in the prestigious history of
B e n i n , previously known as Dahomey, and the nos-
t a l gia it gi ves rise to. The educational system wa s
much better than elsewhere.The country was a seed-
plot of intellectuals and earned the nickname “ t h e
L atin Quarter of A f ri c a ” after the famous Pa ris stu-
dent distri c t . Its “ gr a d u at e s ” staffed colonial admi-
n i s t r at i ve services all over West A f ri c a .The remarkable
“ d e m o c r atic reviva l ” fits into a long history that
Beninese are ve ry proud of. The preamble to the
constitution states that Beninese want to “once more
be the pioneers of democracy and the defenders of
human rights that we were until quite recently.”
The constitution devotes 33 articles to a detailed
exposition of all basic rights, as if its authors had
wanted to cover all the authoritarian practices the
c o u n t ry had experi e n c e d . The articles set fort h
p o l i t i c a l ,c i v i l , economic and social ri g h t s ,i n c l u d i n g
a “ right to deve l o p m e n t ” in all its form s. A b ove
a l l , the document makes the constitutional court the
keystone of the new rule of law.The court is empo-
wered to gi ve an opinion, when requested to do so,
on any prospective laws or regulations which might
i n f ringe human ri g h t s. E ven more import a n t , i t
can also, on its own initiat i ve , pass judgment on such
laws or regulations after they have been adopted.
What’s more, any citizen can bring a suit of thisw Director of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r
Mathieu Kérékou,democratically elected president of Benin in 1996.He was required 
by the country’s constitutional court to retake the oath of office after leaving out several
words during the first ceremony.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
nature before the court without paying a fee.
This fa c i l i t y, which does not exist in the wo r l d ’s
old,most entrenched democracies,is widely used.
Around a third of the court ’s 468 decisions up to the
end of 1998 concerned human rights violations.
Some other decisions have been widely tru m p e t e d .
The court ’s seven judges annulled the election of the
wife of the country ’s first democrat i c a l l y - e l e c t e d
p r e s i d e n t , Nicéphore Soglo, as a parliamentary
d e p u t y.They also forced his successor, f o rmer dic-
tator Mathieu Kérékou, who was democratically
elected in March 1996, to re-take his oath of offic e
because he had “omitted” several words the first
time round.
The court has become the main counterwe i g h t
to the authorities because of its wide powe rs and the
extremely independent way it has used them. Its
i n t e grity is unquestioned. According to a recent
survey1 it is the country’s best-known institution
and, for 94 per cent of those polled, the one they
trust most.
Totally different opinions were expressed about
the police and the other courts,however. All those
polled felt that “a policeman can wield complete
p ower over you at the drop of a hat ” . A r b i t r a ry
a rr e s t s ,u n a u t h o rized searches, b rutal detention in
custody for longer than the maximum legal period
are common, and prison conditions are inhuman.
Ninety-two per cent of those who took part in the
s u rvey said they had no confidence in the legal
system because it was corrupt and too slow.
“ T h e r e ’s a two-speed approach to civil libert i e s ,”
s ays Julien To g b a d j a , head of Benin’s Human Rights
L e a g u e . “At the top yo u ’ ve got tremendous freedom;
at the bottom, m a s s i ve violat i o n s.” Ninety-four per
cent of those polled said “powerful people often
intervene to halt or pervert the course of justice.”
The judges have some solid arguments on their
side,starting with their extremely inadequate faci-
lities and pay. The first computers , for example,
h ave only just arri ved—as a gi f t . Justice gets a
n o rmal share of the national budget (1.6 per cent in
1999) but the country has only 144 judges (one for
every 8,000 citizens),a fifth of the figure in indus-
t rialized countri e s. G i ven their meagre salaries ran-
ging from $200 to $600 a month gr o s s , h e r o i c
efforts are needed to resist bribery.
For ordinary citizens, justice is remote. T h e
only court of appeal sits in the capital and 90 per
cent of the population neither speak nor read French,
the only language used in law books and tri a l s. In pri n-
c i p l e , legal fees don’t exist, but the courts are increa-
singly asking those involved to contribute to their
c o s t s.A l s o, for cultural reasons, l awsuits create hat r e d
and bitterness which endure for generations. As a
r e s u l t , Beninese go in for extra-legal “ a rr a n g e m e n t s ”
and at worst resort to lynching.
Democratic revival
But they still want the law to be more widely
a p p l i e d . “Civil society is ve ry active in the face of the
authorities’ many attempts to curb freedoms,” says
Togbadja.The impetus for this mobilization comes
from the independent media (about 10 newspapers ,
a dozen radio stations and four television channels),
human rights NGOs (no less than 100 of them), t h e
churches and, says Togbadja, “a handful” of politi-
c i a n s. This is because “the political class grew up
under the old totalitarian regi m e ,” s ays V i r gile A k p ovo
of the Human Rights Institute.
The democratic revival is going strong, chorus
Benin’s human rights campaigners.They are parti-
cularly happy about the start of a programme to
m o d e rnize the legal system and improve pri s o n
c o n d i t i o n s , as well as to apply a constitutional clause
t h at says human rights must be taught in schools and
even in the armed forces.
But the activists also firmly agree that the move-
ment is fragile and that the main threat comes not
from people’s attitudes or from laws or institutions,
but from underdevelopment. Social and economic
rights are virtually a dead letter because of widespread
corruption and impoverishment.
In addition, s ays A h a n h a n z o,“there can be no ru l e
of law without a stat e .” He criticizes liberalization and
structural adjustment policies, and asks “how can
anyone think of downsizing a state which is already
in poor shape?” As Senegalese President A b d o u
Diouf likes to point out, “hunger is incompat i b l e
with democracy,” because it means people “ c a n ’t
play their part as citizens.” n
B e n i n :
Area: 113,000 km2 in the
form of a 700-km-long strip
of land;51 people per km2.
Population: 6 million,
annual growth rate 2.9%;
infant mortality 88 per
thousand live births;life
expectancy 53 years.
Illiteracy: 52% (men),79%
(women).
GNP per capita: $380 a
year;annual economic
growth rate:5.6%
S o u r c e : World Bank
B E N I N
Cotonou
Nigeria
Gulf of Benin
Togo
Niger
Burkina Faso
1.The survey was carried out for a conference on “the
critical assessment of respect for individual human rights
and democratic practice in Benin” (Cotonou,September
17-18, 1998) organized by Benin’s Institute for Human
Rights and the Promotion of Democracy.
‘ T h e re ’s a two-speed
a p p roach to civil liberties.
At the top you’ve got
t remendous fre e d o m ; at the
b o t t o m ,
Laws change less
rapidly than
c u s t o m s ; they are
dangerous when
they lag behind
customs and even
more so when they
claim to precede
t h e m .
M a rguerite Yo u rc e n a r
F rench novelist and
essayist (1903-1987)
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 33
Making the leap to a rule of l a w
South A f r i c a : blending 
t radition and change 
w Ferial Haffajee
In South A f r i c a ’s Herculean task of law re f o r m , w o m e n ’s groups are in the vanguard 
of the movement to adapt traditional law to post-apartheid society
When former President Nelson Mandela
m a rried Graça Machel last ye a r , their We s-
tern ceremony was simple and secret. But
their customary marriage in the verdant hills of
Xunu in the Transkei was treated like an occasion
of stat e . Machel was welcomed in traditional dress
by the elders of the Te m bu clan in a ceremony
beamed around the world. And Mandela’s elders
negotiated her bride price or lobola with Machel’s
Mozambican kin.
The event was significant for many reasons, ye t
above all, it moved traditional customs and laws
from the fringes to the centre of South A f ri c a n
s o c i e t y. It signaled a shift in power for customary law
which the apartheid state treated as common law ’s
“poor cousin”.
A gr o u n d swell of innovation is underway to
instill new authority, resources and dignity to cus-
t o m a ry law. Not only is the aim to correct histori c a l
i n j u s t i c e , but to rebuild trust in the criminal justice
system and respect for the rule of law.The challenge
lies in building a legal system which integr at e s
common and customary law in line with the new
c o n s t i t u t i o n , e n s h rining such fundamental pri n-
ciples as gender equality. “The old, unequal rela-
tionship between common law as the big brother
and customary law as the poor cousin is gone,”
says Professor Thandabantu Nhlapo of the South
A f rican Law Commission.“Both have to be judged
in terms of the constitution.”This harmonization
process marks a major step in South Africa’s Her-
culean task of legal reform . The first step lay in
repealing apartheid laws. Next came the need to
reconstitute the Law Commission, which was domi-
n ated by racist judges of the old regi m e .N ow it must
shape new laws to govern a new social order.
C u s t o m a ry law in South A f rica has suffered
similar travails to those of other African countries
with a colonial past.A f rikaner gove rnments inheri t e d
a dual legal system of common and customary law
from British colonizers. They codified this mixed
system into the Nat i ve A d m i n i s t r ation Act which in
1986 became the Black A d m i n i s t r ation A c t —
sculpted as a tool to divide, by fine-tuning the sepa-
r ate system of administration for blacks. Under the
A c t ,c u s t o m a ry law was tolerated so long as it wa s n ’t
deemed “ r e p u g n a n t ” to common law, in which case
it was nullified.
Swift, cheap justice
Yet customary law is probably the only form of
justice known to many South A f ri c a n s.About half the
p o p u l ation lives in the countryside where traditional
c o u rts  administer customary law in over 80 per
cent of villages.The court s , which are also found in
some urban tow n s h i p s , deal with eve ry d ay disputes
like petty theft,p r o p e rty disagreements and domestic
a f fa i rs—from marriage to divorce and succession.
(The courts cannot impose fines of more than $6 and
s e rious crimes are tried by formal court s. )
Justice is swift and cheap as the courts are run
with minimal formalities and charge less than a
dollar for a hearing.The judges use everyday lan-
guage, and the rules of evidence allow the com-
munity to interject and question testimonies.T h e s e
courts are close to the people who don’t have the
money or time to travel to towns for formal court s.
Yet the system is not without its cri t i c s — n a m e l y
wo m e n , who are barred from serving as judges and
often discri m i n ated against as litigants.Pa r a d ox i c a l l y,
wo m e n ’s gr o u p s , under the umbrella of the Rural
Wo m e n ’s Move m e n t , h ave been in the vanguard of
e f f o rts to recognize customary law and adapt it to post-
a p a rtheid society.Discussions about ways of elevat i n g
c u s t o m a ry law are intertwined with debates on making
w Senior Editor, Johannesburg
Financial Times
In January 1999,Thabo Mbeki is blessed by village elders before successfully running for the
South African presidency after the retirement of Nelson Mandela.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
w Beijing-based writer
Chinese courts get a hearing
w Katherine A r m s
In an increasingly confli c t - p rone society, o rdinary Chinese are shunning g u a n x i— p e rs o n a l
connections—and granny patro l s, and calling their lawyers instead
The sort of skulduggery to which the 80 wo m e n
l a b o u r e rs fell victim is now so common that
the case might well have escaped public notice.
Four years ago the women,from a poor area of
inland Hebei prov i n c e , came to the country ’s capi-
tal to work at the Huayi Clothing Mill,a fully Chi-
n e s e - owned bu s i n e s s. G i ven a slow d own in the eco-
nomy, the women considered themselves lucky to
h ave jobs. U n f o rt u n at e l y, h owe ve r , the clothing mill
didn’t pay its workers for more than a year.
The women complained to local authori t i e s ,
but to no avail.Finally, as a last resort they applied
to the Centre for Women’s Law Studies and Legal
Services in Beijing for help.
Recently, they won their lawsuit and have been
awaiting a decision on damages.Their lawyer esti-
m ates that a total of between $120,000 and
$230,000 will be awarded to the 80 wo m e n .
Amounting to between $1,500 and $2,900 per per-
son,that may not sound like much, but compared
to the average per capita income in China it repre-
sents a small fortune.
What is perhaps most amazing about this story
is that the women bothered to turn to the courts at
all given that the judicial system has such shallow
roots in both pre- and post-revolution China.
Though the legal system is in its infa n cy and, a c c o r-
ding to human rights activists, is subject to gove rn-
ment interference in the case of sensitive political
i s s u e s , it is neve rtheless being taken increasingly
seriously.
In imperial times up until the beginning of this
c e n t u ry, China didn’t even have law ye rs. R at h e r ,
it had scri b e s , commonly known as “ l i t i g at i o n
it gender-neutral.Three issues top the agenda: t r a d i-
tional marri a g e s ,i n h e ritance rights and the status of
traditional court s.
Under apartheid, traditional or customary law
m a rriages were not legally recognized and only
regarded as “unions”.If a couple couldn’t afford a
common law marri a g e , the woman was considered
a “ m i n o r ” who wa s n ’t even allowed to open a credit
account with a local gr o c e r. Most rural wo m e n
raise their children alone as their husbands are
migrant workers in mines and industrial centres.
“The women couldn’t buy anything.They had to
wait for their husbands to return from the city in
order to sell propert y,” s ays Likhapa Mbatha of
the Centre for Applied Legal Studies (CALS), a
legal think-tank.Thus, the Recognition of Custo-
m a ry Marriages Act was passed last year after close
c o l l a b o r ation between the SA Law Commission
and the women’s movement. For Mbatha, “It’s a
recognition that South Africa is in Africa.”
Reforming and recognizing
traditional courts
This first victory was about righting an apart h e i d
w r o n g : disrespect for customary law.The next step
lies in making it gender-neutral.According to cus-
tomary law, only males can inherit property and
we a l t h .N h l a p o ’s sub-committee has proposed bri n-
ging this law into line with the non-discriminatory
common law. Indeed, the proposal may not be as
radical as it appears. In a research project, CALS
found that many villages have informal ways of
ensuring inheritance to widows and daughters. A
p a r l i a m e n t a ry decision on the proposed changes is
anxiously awaited.
The third priority lies in reforming and reco-
gnizing traditional courts. South Africa’s common
law criminal justice system is buckling under the
weight of shrinking budgets and poor management,
according to the National Director of Prosecu-
t i o n s. Nhlapo sees a partial remedy in expanding the
o p e r ations of the traditional courts which have the
respect of the people—an essential ingredient in
reinforcing the rule of law. “ You must empowe r
traditional courts to dispense justice in a way and in
a language that people understand,” says Nhlapo,
“by bri n ging traditional courts in line with the
constitution and financially investing in them.”To
begin breaking down the gender barricades to jus-
tice, the South African Law Commission recom-
mends having elected councillors preside with tra-
ditional chiefs in their court s. H owe ve r , the wo m e n ’s
lobby does not fully trust the chiefs and headmen.
So instead of formally recognizing these courts or
expanding their powe rs , the lobby would simply like
to see them treated as local arbitration tri bu n a l s. N o t
surprisingly, the proposition has ignited an open
b attle with the traditional leaders , who want to
strengthen their courts.
The jury is still out on the traditional courts
s y s t e m .W h at e ver the outcome, it will be a milestone
in South Africa’s history and quest for justice. n
Wherever Law ends,
Ty ranny begins.
John Locke,
English philosopher 
( 1 6 3 2 - 1 7 0 4 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 35
The quest for r u l e of lawMaking t leap to a    
t ri c k s t e rs ” ,w ho might launch appeals on behalf of
people who felt they had been wronged. E n g a ging in
this practice was potentially dangerous. “ H a b i t u a l
l i t i g ation tri c k s t e rs ” could be exiled to the “ m a l a-
rial regions”of the south.
After the 1949 communist revo l u t i o n , the pri o-
rity of the judicial system was to serve socialism, a
p rinciple which often worked against protection of
i n d i v i d u a l s ’ ri g h t s. Things got wo rs e . D u ring the
Cultural Revolution of 1966-76, Mao Zedong
wiped out legal institutions in favour of “ r e vo l u t i o-
nary justice”.
Coping with
a judicial vacuum
In this vacuum, ordinary Chinese people have
had to depend on informal neighbourhood com-
mittees, commonly run by elderly, retired women
wo r k e rs forming a sort of gr a n ny pat r o l , or on part y
or gove rnment leaders to intervene in disputes.
I nva ri a b l y, the politically well-positioned have used
g u a n x i , the Chinese term for personal connections,
to sway arbitrat o rs. M e a n w h i l e , those without good
g u a n x i h ave often had no choice but to suffer in
s i l e n c e , or make a desperate journey to Beijing
where they camp outside the State Council’s peti-
tion office for days or weeks hoping that some
g ove rnment official might gi ve them a sympat h e t i c
ear.
Since the end of the Cultural Revolution and the
b e ginning of economic reform in the late 1970s, t h e
Chinese leadership has gradually been rebuilding a
legal system.This ye a r , for the first time, the gove rn-
ment amended the national constitution to declare
China a country gove rned “according to the law ” .
This may seem banal,but legal experts say the
clause is import a n t .Although reference to a “ rule of
l aw ” is not made as such,“ b a s i c a l l y, the spirit is the
s a m e ,” s ays Wang Chenguang,a s s o c i ate professor of
law at Hong Kong’s City University.
One underlying reason for the switch to reliance on
l aw is that the old party and community stru c t u r e s
can no longer cope. In big cities, where high rises now
house significant swathes of society, m a ny of them
recently arri ve d , n e i g h b o u rs no longer know each
other as they did,say, two decades ago when govern-
ment restrictions on movement made it virt u a l l y
impossible to switch abodes. Local committee elders
are reluctant to interfere in the lives of people they
d o n ’t know, and residents are unwilling to counte-
nance interference, s ays Wa n g, a former member of
Beijing University’s law faculty and practicing lawyer
in Beijing.
Corruption and regionalism
At a practical leve l , Beijing now sees the legal sys-
tem as a possible solution to two of its biggest hea-
daches:corruption,which President Jiang Zemin has
called the single biggest threat to the future of the
Communist Pa rt y ; and regi o n a l i s m , in which local
o f ficials gi ve preference to local companies, o f fic i a l
bodies and other entities,a trend which many central
g ove rnment officials believe undermines nat i o n a l
unity.
M e a n w h i l e , s ay other expert s , society is simply
becoming increasingly confli c t - ridden as the rapid
change to a free-market economy presents all sorts of
new opportunities for disputes. For example, s i n c e
China abandoned co-operat i ve fa rming and turn e d
towards free enterprise, more and more people have
flocked to cities and towns to find wo r k .The poor and
u n e d u c ated are frequently victimized by greedy or
abusive bosses.
There are now in China some 140,000 law ye rs ,
still a small number in a country of 1.2 billion people.
But with free enterp rise gr owing law is increasingly
popular amongst students as a lucrat i ve vo c at i o n .
Since the Centre for Wo m e n ’s Law Studies opened
in 1995, six staff law ye rs have assisted more than 7,000
people, according to Guo Jianmei, a lawyer and the
centre’s director. She says they have tried more than
400 cases and have won more than half. Guo credits
the UN Fourth World Conference on Women held in
Beijing in 1995 with giving the centre a big push.
“Many people from foreign countries came here
and they asked us, ‘Do you have legal aid?’ and we
told them we didn’t.It started the whole discussion,”
she says.
Spreading the word about basic legal rights is a
fundamental necessity. In 1993, Xie Lihua founded
R u ral Women Knowing A l l, the first publication for
m i grant wo m e n . She was interested in the plight of
rural women in big cities without money and exploi-
ted by employers.There are an estimated one million
migrant women in Beijing alone,many of whom have
no idea they have ri g h t s , s ays Xie, whose magazine
has a circulation of 220,000 and an estimated reader-
ship of 14 million.
“It used to be:‘I order you to do this’without any
q u e s t i o n ,” s ays Xie. N ow “ we are moving from a plan-
ned economy to a market economy and with this move
our laws have to change as well.” n
Some 30 investors outside the Beijing municipal government office in April 1998 call 
for the justice system to enforce contracts they had signed.
Let the welfare of the
people be the supreme
l a w.
C i c e ro,
Roman statesman and writer
(106 B. C.-43 A . D. )
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
Law and social j u s t i c e
w Kerry Rittich
Law reform in the service of democracy must find ways 
of protecting the vulnerable 
Legal reform and “good gove rn a n c e ”h ave va u l t e d
to the top of the development agenda. I n t e rn a-
tional financial institutions and influ e n t i a l
d o n o rs continually stress the importance of the ru l e
of law, a healthy regulat o ry environment and strong
and consistent enforcement of rights to successful
economic deve l o p m e n t . In the new world order, t h e
s t at e ’s role is to fa c i l i t ate pri vate activity rather than
guarantee the we l fare of its citizens.
But there is gr owing concern that market reform s
and globalization are connected to gr e ater social stra-
t i fic ation and economic inequality. W h at is often
overlooked is that legal reform may enhance rat h e r
than alleviate this strat i fic ation and inequality.
It is important to see legal reform as a key part
of a broader set of policy, legislative and institutio-
nal reforms which are designed to create not simply
rule- and norm-based societies but particular types
of market economies.There are no “free”markets;
functioning markets depend upon a legal infra-
s t ructure and a commitment to the rule of law.T h e
gr owing interest in legal reform indicates nothing if
not the widespread recognition of this fact.
Tradeoffs between
efficiency and equity
Respecting the rule of law and protecting ri g h t s
h owe ver does not mean that there is any one best set
of law s ,e ven in a market economy.Yet legal reform
projects in developing and transitional countries have
become inseparably associated with the idea of a
s i n g l e , optimal path or model. C u rrent projects
emphasize strong protection for property ri g h t s ,t h e
consistent enforcement of contracts and, i n c r e a s i n-
g l y, financial sector regulation as the foundation of an
i nve s t o r - f riendly legal infrastru c t u r e . At the same
t i m e , s t ates in transition to markets have been dis-
couraged from adopting or retaining “ e x c e s s i ve ”
r e g u l at i o n s , including protective labour market poli-
cies that might impede gr owth and effic i e n cy.
M a r k e t - o riented legal reforms can affect the for-
tunes of different groups in at least three different
way s.The first is through the types of reforms that are
i m p l e m e n t e d . Because legal reforms allocate ri g h t s
and entitlements, different rule structures may we l l
b e n e fit different groups in different way s. In some
i n s t a n c e s , there may be tradeoffs between effic i e n cy
and equity. Strong  property rights will protect
ow n e rs and entrepreneurs but may contri bute to the
d i s a d vantage of renters and wo r k e rs ; e nv i r o n m e n-
tal and consumer protection laws protect the public
at large but impose costs on bu s i n e s s e s.
S e c o n d , people can be affected by the absence of
p a rticular law s.Labour standards and laws authori-
zing collective bargaining, for example, h ave been
c rucial in industrialized societies. If they are weak or
missing as they are in many developing countri e s ,o r
if they are indefinitely postponed because pri o rity is
gi ven to implementing laws and regulations which
fa c i l i t ate economic transactions, vast numbers of
people can find themselves wo rse off than they need
be in the market for labour. Pa rticular groups may
also be harm e d .Women with caregiving obligat i o n s
are likely to be systematically disadvantaged and shut
out of better work opportunities without market
r e g u l ations which ensure that part of these costs are
b o rne by others.This is especially likely where social
p r o grammes and subsidies are reduced or eliminat e d
at the same time, as has occurred in many parts of
Central and Eastern Europe.
Open debate
Finally, where legal reforms follow a “standard
f o rm ” or are designed by experts from afa r , a com-
mon experience in transitional stat e s , the risk is
that local history and priorities will be ignored or
displaced and democratic control over decisions
about basic social organization is weakened.
To avoid aggravating inequality and worsening
the position of those who are frequently already
vulnerable in the reform process, three conditions
need to be met.
F i rs t , c o n flicts of interests—between wo r k e rs
and entrepreneurs , for example—as well as the
necessary tradeoffs that legal reforms often entail
should be acknowledged openly, r ather than hidden
behind the veil of efficiency. This will allow coun-
t ries to debate more openly the political and distri-
butive choices that legal reforms involve.
S e c o n d , donor countries and intern at i o n a l
financial institutions need to rethink the position
t h at state “ i n t e rve n t i o n ” is usually or necessari l y
the enemy of economic development.
T h i r d , d e veloping states need much more
space, indeed they should be actively encouraged,
to accommodate distri bu t i ve , equity and social
concerns not only through social programmes and
t r a n s f e rs but through the processes of legal and
r e g u l at o ry reform as we l l .This would allow gr e at e r
attention to labour market concerns and environ-
mental protection as well as to poverty alleviation
and gender,racial and ethnic equity. nw Assistant professor, Faculty of Law, University of Toronto
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 37
E T H I C S
TA K ING THE SWEAT
OUT OF SWEAT SHOPS
w Ruth Mayne
Thanks to an alliance between northern consumers and workers in the South hundreds 
of companies have adopted codes of conduct designed to improve labour conditions
n
From London to Nicaragua, c o n s u-
m e rs and wo r k e rs are uniting to at t a c k
an age-old scourge: swe at s h o p s. M a j o r
consumer campaigns are gaining gr o u n d
across We s t e rn Europe and North A m e ri c a
by joining forces with non-gove rn m e n t a l
o r g a n i z ations (NGOs) and trade unions in
the South to demand respect for workers’
basic rights.
The roots of the campaigns go back to the
l ate 1980s, when NGOs and trade unions
began working together to mobilize and chan-
nel gr owing public awareness and outrage
over exploitat i ve labour practices as countri e s ,
p a rticularly in the South,competed for foreign
i nvestment by denying wo r k e rs ’f u n d a m e n-
tal rights (like joining a trade union) and large
companies relocated fa c t o ries from country
to country in search of cheap labour.
The campaigns have basically taken two
a p p r o a c h e s.The firs t , dubbed fair trade ini-
t i at i ve s , seeks to help small producers in
d e veloping countries receive a fair price for
their wo r k . NGOs help them by promoting
niche markets for their products—ranging
from handwoven rugs to coffee beans.
Eventually, the producers also gain access
to mainstream markets,with special labels
indicating their “fair trade” products.
In the second spate of campaigns, r e f e r-
red to as ethical trade initiat i ve s ,N G O s ,t r a d e
unions and consumers pressure (via petitions
and demonstrations) large multinat i o n a l
companies to adopt codes of conduct res-
pecting minimum labour standards for their
fa c t o ries and those of their suppliers.W h i l e
both kinds of campaign can complement one
a n o t h e r , they have different aims. Labels aim
at helping individual producers in deve l o p i n g
c o u n t ri e s , whereas codes seek to improve
labour conditions in mainstream industri e s
such as retailing and manufa c t u ring textiles,
c l o t h i n g,f o o t wear and toys in both the Nort h
and South.
One high profile operation took aim at
mighty Nike, the athletic shoes manufa c t u-
w Policy adviser, Oxfam
San Francisco garment workers take part in a march on the National Day of Conscience 
against Sweatshops, April 4, 1997.
r e r , which agreed to a code of conduct after
a heated consumer campaign in North A m e-
rica and Europe backed up by media exposés
of labour abuse in Indonesia, China and
Thailand. Clothing companies like Levi
S t r a u s s , Liz Clairborne and The Gap have
also adopted codes to protect their brand
n a m e s.While there is no precise data concer-
ning the number of companies adopting
c o d e s , the Intern ational Labour Organisa-
tion (ILO) counted and reviewed more than
200 codes in a 1998 report .O ver 80 per cent
of the codes had been adopted by multina-
tional enterp ri s e s , mostly based in the Nort h .
A new departure
The code campaigns can be seen as a
response to the stark failure of gove rn m e n t s
and multilateral institutions to help ensure
a fair distribution of trade benefits to wor-
k e rs and small producers. With gove rn-
ments and business increasingly hostile to
s t at u t o ry regulation and trade unions since
the late 1980s, the campaigning gr o u p s
h ave focused on market-based mechanisms
to achieve social and environmental goals.
The code campaigns have made it
easier to build consensus between nort h e rn
and southern NGOs than previous
attempts at reforming the world trading
system.Trade union proposals in the mid-
1990s for a wo r k e rs ’ rights clause at the
World Trade Organizat i o n1, for example,
were viewed with great suspicion by many
d e veloping country gove rn m e n t s.They saw
such clauses as a new form of nort h e rn pro-
tectionism aimed at keeping cheaper sou-
t h e rn goods out of their markets.They we r e
also mindful of past campaigns gone awry:
consumer boycotts backfired as companies
simply changed suppliers or relocated their
fa c t o ri e s.The result: lost jobs, not improve d
working conditions.The codes mark a new
d e p a rture by stressing the need for co-ope-
r at i o n : companies are encouraged to adopt
1 The International Confederation of Free Trade
Unions (ICFTU) has suggested a social or
workers’ rights clause that would make WTO
privileges conditional on compliance with a set of
internationally agreed fundamental workers’
rights. The ILO would retain the role of
monitoring and judging infringements.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
tions must play a central role in deve l o p i n g
and implementing codes. In the Dominican
R e p u b l i c, for example, the non-gove rn-
mental organization CIPAF (Research
Centre for Action on Women) is joining
forces with Oxfam to develop a code for
wo r k e rs in the free trade zones.The Domi-
nican campaign is linked to a wider netwo r k
of wo m e n ’s associations trying to improve
labour conditions across Central A m e ri c a
under the banner, “ Wo r k , ye s — but with
d i g n i t y ! ” (See article next page.)
E ven though the Dominican constitu-
tion and labour code enshrine the right to
freedom of association and collective bar-
g a i n i n g, m a ny companies in the free trade
zones prevent unionization by intimidat i n g
and black-listing organizers , while massive l y
h i ring temporary wo r k e rs.According to local
N G O s ,c o n f r o n t ation was the traditional res-
p o n s e , with wo r k e rs ’o r g a n i z ations denoun-
cing company violations and employe rs dis-
puting the allegat i o n s , while threatening to
m ove their operations to other countri e s.
The gove rnment was left paralyzed, f e a r f u l
of losing jobs. H owe ve r , these dynamics are
n ow changing in the Dominican Republic.
G i ven the campaign’s intern ational expo-
s u r e , companies are now beginning to nego-
t i ate with wo r k e rs and gove rnment to pro-
duce a joint code of conduct for all free trade
zones in the country.
Practice lags
behind rhetoric
While the campaigns mark a major step
forward, they have limits. Codes can com-
plement but not replace government regu-
l at i o n . G ove rnments are ultimately res-
ponsible for enforcing human rights and
the rule of law. However imperfectly they
perform this role in practice, they are the
38 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
E T H I C S
a strategy of long-term engagement with
s u p p l i e rs to improve working conditions
over time, r ather than taking the simpler
but potentially more damaging route of
w i t h d r awing their business when labour
a buses are found and highlighted by consu-
mer campaigns.
For codes to be effective , they must meet
a few basic conditions. F i rs t , all releva n t
a c t o rs—especially wo r k e rs — h ave to be invo l-
ved in their design and implementat i o n .N o t
only must they include the seven core ILO
c o nventions (assuring respect for human
rights at the wo r k p l a c e , including freedom of
a s s o c i ation and collective bargaining) bu t
they must address local concern s , l i k e
m i grant labour.The codes should also apply
to “ fle x i b l e ” and informal sector wo r k e rs
where possible and promote long-term enga-
gement to improving conditions. I n d e p e n-
dent ve ri fic ation is indispensable.
Boosting morale 
and productivity
In the UK, for example, the top five retai-
l e rs , including Marks & Spencer and C&A,
h ave agreed to adopt ethical codes of conduct
after three ye a rs of consumer lobbying gal-
vanized by the Clothes Code Campaign laun-
ched by Oxfa m ,an intern ational non-gove rn-
mental aid organizat i o n . Thousands of
c o n s u m e rs petitioned the companies, w h i l e
O x fam staff made the case for ethical trade
with senior corp o r ate managers who soon
s aw the commercial advantages of the codes.
A code can do more than just safeguard a
c o m p a ny ’s public image.By improving wo r-
king conditions, a code can boost staff morale
and productivity—both essential for making
a company more competitive .
H owe ve r , consumer support is only one
p a rt of the equat i o n : local labour associa-
+ …
l Clean Clothes Campaign: 
www.cleanclothes.org
l Clothes Code Campaign:
www.oxfam.org/uk
l Ethical Trade Initiatives:
www.eti.org.uk
l International Labour Organisation:
www.ilo.org.
l Stop Sweatshops:
www.uniteunion.org
body best suited to mediate between the
different interest groups in society when
setting and enforcing labour standards.
Another key concern is that corporate
practice often lags behind the rhetoric of
support for ethical trade.In a 1998 review
of 215 codes of conduct, the ILO found
that only 15 per cent included freedom of
a s s o c i ation and collective bargaining. O n l y
25 per cent of the codes had provisions to
p r e vent forced labour—or the refusal to
contract with companies using forced
l a b o u r.And ve ry few had monitoring requi-
rements.
The ILO also points out the arbitrary
n ature of consumer pressure campaigns
which mainly single out companies with a
brand name to protect.They also tend to
focus on exporting companies and so do
not necessarily cover wo r k e rs in the domes-
tic sector.
Fear of
bureaucracy
But these are arguments for improving
the initiat i ves rather than abandoning them
altogether. Some of the problems could be
in part rectified by a shift to home-grown
i n d u s t ry or sector-wide codes of conduct
which would promote greater involvement
by developing country suppliers and
governments.The ILO might also help to
d e velop an intern ationally agreed model
code of conduct—although this might
spark resistance.
Some NGOs are concerned that ILO
i nvo l vement would ove r l y - bu r e a u c r at i z e
the campaigns. Some developing country
governments are also wary of ILO support
for these schemes out of fear of northern
protectionism.
The campaigns are now at a crossroads.
Hundreds of codes have been adopted by
c o m p a n i e s , the next step lies in applying
them.One thing is certain:the impetus for
vo l u n t a ry initiat i ves will not go away as long
as the wo r k e rs fail to receive a fair distri-
bution of the wealth they help to create. n
A textile factory in a Nicaragua free zone in 1990, before the adoption of an ethical code.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 39
E T H I C S
n
After more than a decade of war and
i n t e rnal confli c t , peace officially retur-
ned to Nicaragua in May 1990.T h o u-
sands of members of the so-called “ C o n t r a
a rmy ” laid down their weapons and tens of
thousands of reservists and soldiers were reti-
r e d .M a ny of them automatically swelled the
a rmy of the unemploye d .
“When the war ended, we didn’t know
w h at to do, we felt exposed. I got a job in a
fa c t o ry at the Las Mercedes industrial free
trade zone, picking up garbage and cleaning
m a c h i n e ry,” s ays Eugenia. Her experience is
echoed by many women working in the
c o u n t ry ’s m a q u i l a1 assembly industri e s.E u g e-
nia never thinks of leaving her job. “ T h e r e
a r e n ’t any other fa c t o ri e s ” she say s ,“and I’m
40 ye a rs old, so I have to stay where I am and
put up with things without complaining.”
Violence
The Las Mercedes free zone curr e n t l y
has more than 20 textile assembly plants,
most of them A s i a n - owned and directly pro-
viding over 18,000 jobs, 80 per cent of them
held by wo m e n .These fa c t o ries export e d
more than $135 million wo rth of goods in
1 9 9 7 , compared with the slightly more than
$200 million earned by the country ’s main
e x p o rt , c o f f e e . For many ye a rs , the local
media attacked the violation of labour law s
by the fa c t o ri e s.Women in particular we r e
the victims of persistent phy s i c a l ,p s y c h o l o-
gical and verbal abu s e .They were also fir e d
simply because they became pregnant.
“There was a really violent aspect to life
in the free zone,” s ays Sandra Ramos, l e a d e r
of the María Elena Cuadra Movement of
Working and Unemployed Wo m e n .“ To try
to end the abu s e s , we forced a code of
conduct on the assembly plants.”
The 10-article code deals with mat t e rs
like mat e rnity leave , working hours , ove rt i m e
wa g e s , regular medical checkups and job secu-
ri t y. It is the first of its kind to be negotiat e d
and put into effect in Central A m e ri c a ,w h e r e
there are about 1,100 such fa c t o ri e s
e m p l oying more than 300,000 wo r k e rs.
Under the banner, “ Wo r k , ye s — but with
d i g n i t y ! ” (the slogan of a coalition of wo m e n ’s
labour groups lobbying for codes of conduct
across Central A m e ri c a ) , the Nicaraguan ini-
t i at i ve owes its success to wo r k e rs ’d e t e rm i-
n ation and strong public support which took
the shape of a 30,000-signature petition.
The ministry of labour made the code a
m i n i s t e rial edict on Ja n u a ry 23,1 9 9 8 .W i t h i n
about a we e k , all of the fa c t o ry ow n e rs of Las
Mercedes accepted the code in an open letter
to the labour minister:“ We have decided of
our own accord to comply with the ministe-
rial edict because we think it will improve and
h a rmonize relations between employe rs and
e m p l oye e s.”
Working conditions slowly began to get
b e t t e r.A survey carried out in Ja n u a ry 1999
by the María Elena Cuadro Movement sho-
wed that since the code was adopted most
wo r k e rs (95 per cent of the 2,562 wo m e n
polled) had not been victims of the kind of
m i s t r e atment common up until then.T h e
s u rvey also found that fa c t o ries began ope-
ning creches and food areas where wo r k e rs
could eat meals brought from home or
bought from ve n d o rs. But the wo r k e rs also
said there was a long way to go before they
had social securi t y, decent wages and good
fa c t o ry hy gi e n e .The average monthly wa g e
was less than $100, far below the estimat e d
cost of a fa m i l y ’s basic needs of around $150
a month.
“ R e g u l ation of foreign investment in
Nicaragua is inadequat e ,” s ays Ramos. B a c-
ked by women MPs, her movement is now
pushing for parliament to reform the law s
governing the free trade zone.“The code of
conduct was a first step,” she say s ,“ but it’s
only a means to an end.”
The whole matter is a tricky one, h owe-
ve r , and demands caution. Ramos says inter-
n ational consumer campaigns to press for
codes of ethics can be ri s k y. Pressure applied
the wrong way could lead to closure of the
factories and the loss of local jobs.
‘Clean’ clothes
“At intern ational leve l , some people are
campaigning with good will, but others are see-
king to advance their own national interests
through these campaigns.”The Nicaraguan acti-
vists are against,for example,b oycotting Central
A m e ri c a ’s free trade zones.They are also oppo-
sed to the idea that consumers in rich countri e s
should only buy locally-made goods.Tr a d e
unions in the United States in particular have
promoted this approach, which Ramos rejects
as nat i o n a l i s t i c. On the other hand,“ We think
the campaign in Europe for ‘ c l e a n ’ clothing pro-
d u c t s , which doesn’t talk about a boycott bu t
about improving working conditions, is more
e f f e c t i ve ,” she says of campaigns like that of
O x fam (see article page 37).
“ W h at we ask campaigners in rich coun-
t ries to do is negotiate directly with the big
textile firms there so they respect wo r k e rs ’
rights in their fa c t o ries in poor countries and
l ater to organize an independent inspection to
check whether the fa c t o ry ow n e rs are kee-
ping their word.
“ A ny way,” s ays Ramos, “the code of
conduct isn’t something invented in the Nort h .
It was thought up by women of the South.We
h ave n ’t copied any foreign model.” n
1 . Fo r e i g n - financed textile fa c t o ries set up in free
trade zones, where they are exempt from taxes and
produce for foreign markets. Most of the women are
manual wo r k e rs who assemble garm e n t s.
‘ W ORK, YES — BU T
WITH DIGNI TY ! ’
w Roberto Fonseca
Nicaraguan workers have prevailed on foreign employers to adopt a code of ethics enshrining
respect for their rights and better working conditions
w Editor-in-chief, La Prensa, Managua (Nicaragua)
N I C A R A G U A
Honduras
Costa Rica
Managua
Pacific Ocean
Caribbean Sea
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F T H E T I M E S
40 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
n
Until the late 1980s Patis Tesoro was a
housewife and part-time fashion desi-
gner who enjoyed an upper-middle class
life in the exclusive neighbourhoods of San
J u a n , a town on the outskirts of Manila.
O c c a s i o n a l l y, she would tailor-make an out-
fit for people in her rich circle of fri e n d s ,a n d
it would bring enough money to buy the
e x p e n s i ve ornaments with which she deco-
r ates her spacious home.
But in the afterm ath of nat i o n - bu i l d i n g
t h at followed the 1986 ove rt h r ow of Presi-
dent Ferdinand Marcos, Tesoro found her
t rue calling as a social activist, e n t r e p r e n e u r ,
and leader in development economics. S e e i n g
t h at ethnic wear was a part of Philippine
identity that was dying out as the result of an
i nvasion of polyester and cotton goods based
on We s t e rn design, Tesoro set out to save
one humble piece of heri t a g e :p i ñ a , a hand-
woven fibre deri ved from the pineapple leaf,
the mainstay of the traditional ethnic dress
called the b a r o n g. (See box on facing page).
Turning over a new leaf
More than a decade lat e r , her designs are
de rigueur for Philippine high society.A l o n g
the way to success,Tesoro almost single-han-
dedly helped create thousands of jobs for
peasants and we ave rs throughout the Philip-
p i n e s. In a country whose per capita GDP is
roughly $880 a ye a r , piña we ave rs can now
e a rn as much as $200 or $300 a month.S u c h
an income makes it much more likely that
women will stay in the villages and we ave
piña rather than go abroad to be domestic
s e rva n t s ,who earn salaries ranging from $300
to $400 a month.Though Tesoro had a lot of
help from others , she used no capital except
her own pocket money and grants totalling no
more than a few million pesos1. Her story is
t h at of raw determ i n at i o n ,s t r at e gic lobbying
of the right gove rnment offic i a l s , and smart
marketing at home and abroad.It is also a tale
of how the developing world can transform
tradition into business that creates we a l t h
and shores up cultural identity.
For developing nat i o n s , the potential
economic rewards alone of building fa s h i o n
design and retailing capabilities are enor-
m o u s. C u rrently the South is the hub of tex-
tile and clothes manufa c t u ri n g,Asia being the
biggest producer (garments account for 45
MO V E O V ER MILA N , M A NILA
IS TA K ING T HE CATWA L K
w Allen T. Cheng
Reviving a piece of fashion heritage, a Filipino housewife creates an alternative 
sense of style
w Hong Kong-based journalist
Filippino women at Banga in Aklan province (Visayas islands) extract fibre from pineapple (piña) leaves.
1.1US$ = around 40 pesos.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F T H E T I M E S
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 41
per cent of Hong Kong’s exports) with Lat i n
A m e rica now emerging as a playe r.
But these are largely “low-end” opera-
tions where the gross profit margins are
fairly small—perhaps only 10 per cent.T h e
big margi n s , as much as 200 per cent, go to
d e s i g n e rs and retailers , predominantly We s-
t e rn . Ironically in recent ye a rs many We s t e rn
fashion houses have turned to ethnic themes
from A f ri c a , L atin A m e rica and Asia for
creative inspiration. In the middle of this
supply chain, trading houses that source
from manufa c t u r e rs and sell to retailers
enjoy margins of 20-30 per cent.
If the developing world has thus far been
r e l e g ated to a swe atshop role, things may be
c h a n ging in Asia as the regi o n ’s economies get
back on track following the 1997 fin a n c i a l
c ri s i s , and as indigenous designers discove r
their abilities.
“We (in Asia) have a wealth of talent
e m e r gi n g, as good as anywhere in the
wo r l d ,” s ays Professor Edward Newton,
c h a i rman of Hong Kong’s Institute of Te x-
tiles and Clothing, A s i a ’s biggest such
research centre and think tank.
But to realize potential a lot of art i s t i c
c r e ativity is needed, as well as a sense of
w h at sells,g u m p t i o n , risk-taking and a vision.
“I always felt that we Filipinos were loo-
king for an identity,” s ays Tesoro at a coffee
shop she’s built adjacent to her museum-like
s t u d i o,which is filled with rolls of traditional
fa b rics and tropical spices.“ W h at we needed
to do was to get back to our roots.We we r e
losing our identity. We were being ove r w-
helmed by We s t e rn civilizat i o n .”
Ethnic roots
Tesoro’s story begins in the late 1980s.
In the euphoria after the dow n fall of the
Marcos regi m e ,Tesoro and her close fri e n d s
began a process of soul searching. M a ny
wanted to do something to contri bute to
the new republic and decided to look at their
ethnic roots: a complex history of ethnic tri-
bal traditions, f l avoured by Spanish and
American colonialism.
Along with two other we l l - c o n n e c t e d
A piña weaver prepares her loom.
T HE SECOND LIFE
OF A 400-Y E A R -
OLD TRA DI T ION
B rought by the Spanish galleons to the Phi-
lippines in the 1580s, the pineapple soon
b e came a major crop in the isles. The variety that
prospered then bore a fibrous fruit with leaves
that grew up to two metres, three times longer
than the leaves of today’s edible variety.
Natives took those leaves and stripped them
down to fibres, which they spun into threads to
make a shimmering, soft fabric, softer than the
softest hemp, yet with more texture than silk. By
the 1600s, piña and abaca—a fabric made from
the fibres of a plant related to the banana—
b e came the major exports of the Philippines.
Natives traded piña and abaca with merchants
from the Middle East, Malaysia, China and India.
“It was what everyone wore—piña and abaca,”
says Patis Tesoro. It wasn’t until the 1700s that
locals began importing cotton from England.
The piña plant couldn’t compete with impor-
ted cotton or silk, both of which were mass pro-
duced in Europe and in China. Despite that, piña
and abaca were what many rural Filipinos conti-
nued to wear well into this century. The process
of weaving these fibres was far more cumber-
some than cotton or silk, both of which can be
spun into very long threads by  machines. The
piña fabric had to be hand-woven because its
fibres were  never more than two metres in
length and were hard to attach to each other.
As a result, piña fabric was far more expen-
sive to weave than either cotton or silk. Because
of its higher price, piña became the fabric of
choice of Filipino noblemen. “It used to be that if
you wore a piña barong, you’d really made it,”
says Tesoro. n
we a l t hy fri e n d s , Te s o r o, n ow 48 and a
mother of four, opened the Padrones de
Casa Manila, a museum that celebrat e s
more than 300 years of Philippine history.
It was then that Tesoro came to realize that
m a ny traditional industries were dead or
dying during ye a rs of neglect under Marcos.
Among them was what once was the pri d e
and joy of the Philippines: n atural fib r e s.
Tesoro was particularly intrigued by piña
c l o t h , which by that time was nearly impos-
sible to fin d .
When Tesoro went in 1986 to the
V i s aya s , a set of islands where piña still gr e w
w i l d , she found only a handful of part - t i m e
we ave rs—most of them women in their lat e
70s or 80s. Clearly piña was going to die
with these wo m e n ,s ays Te s o r o, who began
lobbying local officials to set up courses to
train the next generation of we ave rs. It took
Tesoro nearly two ye a rs of lobbying offic i a l s
before they took any action.
It was finally only by contacting V i c t o r
O r d o ñ e z ,Under Secretary of Educat i o n ,a n d
Carlos Dominguez,S e c r e t a ry of A gri c u l t u r e ,
t h at Tesoro was able to convince the gove rn-
ment to take action. In 1988, Tesoro and
the Aklan State College of A griculture in
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F T H E T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
the V i s ayas began a series of courses on piña
we av i n g . It took another year of lobbying
g ove rnment officials for Tesoro to conv i n c e
the gove rnment to put up more funding to
train local fa rm e rs to begin cultivating piña
a g a i n . “It was not easy,” s ays Te s o r o.
Re-establishing the piña trade was eve n
more diffic u l t .She recalls the first meeting she
held with former gr owe rs , we ave rs , leaf stri p-
p e rs and traders.She asked why they stopped
selling piña.“There was a shouting mat c h ,”
s ays Te s o r o. “ People blamed each other and
the middlemen.W h at it came down to was the
p rice of piña was just too low.There wa s n ’t
nearly enough a profit margin for the industry.
People would rather go ove rseas to be
domestic helpers than be we ave rs.”
Status symbol
By now, the gove rn m e n t ’s Fiber
I n d u s t ry and Development A s s o c i ation wa s
on her side.Together they began setting up
a distri bution channel for the piña. In turn ,
she promised the gr owe rs and we ave rs that
she would buy their supply and also help
promote their fa b rics nationally by inte-
grating them into her fashion designs. In
fa c t , it was Tesoro who continually wa s
willing to pay a higher price for piña at the
b e gi n n i n g . By marketing her piña b a r o n g s t o
her rich fri e n d s ,Tesoro was able to influ e n c e
how the elites of Manila dressed.
Tesoro’s clients list today reads like a
W h o ’s Who of the Philippines: C o ry A q u i n o
and her daughters,former President Fidel
Ramos and his wife, President Estrada and
his wife, and almost every major business
tycoon in the country. “It is now a status
symbol again,” claims Te s o r o, whose outfit s
sell for as much as $1,000 each.
In fa c t , it was by enlisting the help of
f o rmer first lady Amelita Ramos that Te s o r o
FASHION TIPS
FROM THE
PHIL IPPINES
For those wishing to launch a fashion busi-
ness, using their own funds or other sources
of investment, Tesoro has this advice:
1. Identify partners in government and local com-
munities who can be won over to your cause.
2. Learn about the community you will rely on.
3. Make all partners see that the project will ra i s e
living standards and benefit the country and its
c u l t u r e .
4. Selling to big fashion houses isn’t that diffic u l t
because they are always looking for new ideas,
innovative products and materials. But ensuring
adequate supplies is a challenge. n
was not only able to get more funding gr a n t s
to train both gr owe rs and we ave rs but also
spread the gospel about the importance of
piña as a fa b ric among Philippine elites.To g e-
t h e r ,Te s o r o, the former first lady, and a few
o t h e rs , founded the Katutubong Pilipino
Fo u n d at i o n ,which is dedicated to the reviva l
of traditional Philippine art s ,crafts and culture.
To d ay, Tesoro is no longer the only
bu yer of piña. M a ny younger Filipino desi-
g n e rs are turning to it. In fa c t , the piña
industry today employs more than 2,500
people in the state of Aklan alone, which
produced 80,000 metres of piña fabric in
1998, up from a mere 3,000 metres a year
back in 1986. Aklan is the centre of the
piña industry in the Philippines. H e r e ,m o r e
than 80 per cent of the country’s piña pro-
ducts are produced.The industry’s annual
turnover is roughly US$1 million a year.
Much of the Philippine’s piña export s
+ …
l The Art of Philippine Embellishment ,
by Patis Tesoro (Anvil Publishing Inc., 
Manila, 1994) traces the history
of Philippine apparel from its native 
roots to modern times.
began after the Pa ris Fair of May 1997,w h e n
Tesoro and then first lady Ramos put on a
major show to promote traditional Philip-
pine fibres to the wo r l d ’s top fashion houses.
T h at show was the re-introduction of piña to
the wo r l d . New York-based Filipino-Ame-
rican designer Josie Nat o ri is now experi-
menting with piña, for instance.More may be
on the way. The Japanese textile gr o u p,
K a n e b o, for instance, is experimenting for
the first time with the mass manufa c t u ring of
piña by mixing its fibres with others.
Newton shares the view that many deve-
loping nations will explode on to the wo r l d
fashion scene. He is particularly optimistic
about India and China,which have the market
gi rth to produce influential fashion culture
and may some day ri val the We s t . B e s i d e s
To k yo,he sees the emergence of Hong Kong
and Shanghai as possible ri vals to Milan,
Pa ris and London in the next decade or two.
Hong Kong already plays the pivo t a l
role as the sourcing centre for the entire gar-
ment industry and is also beginning to pro-
duce some top fashion design talent. S h a n-
ghai will ri s e , s u p p o rted by its gr ow i n g
middle class, which demands not just We s-
t e rn brands but Chinese ones as we l l .
I n d e e d , in China today Jeans West is already
a leading domestically-produced blue jean.
Unique products
“Some day, ‘Made in China or Hong
Kong’ will become a status symbol,” says
Newton.
Smaller countries such as the Philippines
will have fewer chances of producing name
brands because the home markets in most ins-
tances are just too small to gi ve them global
p r e s e n c e . T h e r e , s ays Newton, d e s i g n e rs
should focus on niche design and products.“ I f
you don’t have uniqueness, then you have to
be competitive in making cheap garm e n t s
like any other developing country in the
wo r l d ,” he say s.
Finding the right designs however is a
huge challenge. Newton believes talented
young designers would do well to study
fashion in the West, as did Japan’s Kenzo
(Paris) and Josie Natori (New York).
H owe ve r , Te s o r o ’s example suggests
breakthroughs are possible by looking inwa r d .
She now hopes to professionalize the Philip-
p i n e s ’ n atural fibre industry so that future
d e s i g n e rs will have more ingredients to use in
their ethnic designs. n
Samples of piña material.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 43
C O N N E X I O N S
W EDDING
BEL L S
F OR WEB AND TV ?
w Francis Balle and Sophie Boukhari
The divide between the Internet and television is fading fast. How will television survive 
this whirlwind of convergence? 
w Francis Balle, a French university lecturer, 
author of Dictionnaire des médias (1998) and Médias 
et sociétés (9th edition, 1999) and Sophie Boukhari,
UNESCO Courier journalist
n
Does the future of television lie in the
Internet, as many people in the global
a u d i ovisual industry believe ?
Television has ruled the media roost
during the second half of this century. But
is the familiar TV set, watched passively
from a distance by lolling couch potatoes,
now destined to be dethroned by the
interactive computer, operated by users
working inches from the screen? Or will
TV and computer combine to spawn a
new generation of hybrid products and
audiovisual services, resembling neither
the TV set nor the computer as we know
them?
Imagine for example a screen full of
images you could activate any time you
l i k e d . If you were watching the fil m
Titanic, you would use an infra-red remo-
te control to click, like a computer mouse,
on the face of Leonard DiCaprio to fetch
a biography of him from the Web or send
him an e-mail. You would click on his
shoes to buy a pair of the same kind or
even click on the wreck of the famous
ship to download,for a price,other videos
about it.
Conglomerates 
locked in battle
We’re not there yet. Indeed, any pre-
dictions must be offered with a grain of
salt. After all, is anyone clever enough to
predict exactly what the tumultuous affair
between the Internet and television will
give birth to? However, crystal balls aren’t
needed to see the increasingly fuzzy line
b e t ween television and the computer.
After sizing each other up as rivals, the
worlds of computers and the audiovisual
media have realized they need each other
and can gain from technological “conver-
gence”. With the digital revolution, any
text, drawing, sound or picture can be
turned into standard computer format
and used either on the Internet or on tele-
vision (as it goes digital).
This has set off major shifts in a new
industry arising at the crossroads between
audiovisual services, computers and tele-
communications. A major battle is raging
between two giant conglomerates. On one
side is the world’s biggest Internet service
provider, America Online (AOL), which
has joined forces with Philips and
DirecTV, the leading U.S. satellite digital
television operator, in a bid to win the
race to capture the next century’s custo-
mers. On the other side, AT&T, the worl-
d’s biggest telecommunications firm and
the main U.S. cable operator (which also
provides high-speed Internet access) has
teamed up with Microsoft,which is trying
to impose its software on the Internet net-
works and in the new decoders used by
digital TV sets.
Many factors are pushing the two
worlds of the Internet and television
towards each other. The Net is drawing
away more and more viewers from TV
and threatening its revenue from adverti-
sing. Recent surveys in the U.S. show
television viewing (which averages four
h o u rs a day compared with three in
Europe) has dropped since the under-30s
have plugged in to the Web. The trend is
expected to accelerate as more young
Americans get high-speed Web access,
which is currently only available in
700,000 homes.
The big guns of the Web—those who
provide services and software—want to
turn TV viewers into Netizens so they can
expand their markets. The number of
Internet users is tiny compared with the
Digital technology makes it possible to transmit a video via the Internet.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
C O N N E X I O N S
W EBSI T E
OF THE MON T H
h t t p : / / w w w. u n e s c o . o r g / n e ta i d
A n ew UNES CO site has been launched in
conjunction with NetAid, the foundation
which uses Internet technology to help in poverty
reduction. Created by the United Nations Deve-
lopment Programme (UND P), with the aid of Cisco
Systems, a private company, NetAid has the
ca p a c i ty to handle 60 million hits per hour. It uses
the powers of the Internet to bring together
people from all over the world to exchange ideas
and aspirations, to volunteer goods and serv i c e s ,
or simply to learn about the causes of poverty
and solutions to it. UNES CO promotes informal
and community-based approaches ca p i t a l i z i n g
on the skills and capacities of the poor them-
selves and encouraging them to devise their ow n
strategies to rise out of poverty. n
The Net prov i d e rs are also using this
same method to offer TV viewe rs an endless
range of online serv i c e s — i n f o rm at i o n ,t r a i-
ning and entert a i n m e n t . Far from killing off
TV in ye a rs to come, I n t e rnet will actually
gi ve it a second wind by drawing it furt h e r
(than cable or satellite) into the age of dive r-
sity and abu n d a n c e .
At the same time as the Net goes on
television, television will stake new terri-
tory on the Net by offering access to exis-
ting TV channels and new “webchannels”
set up specially for it.
TV programmes
live on the Net
This expected boom in TV on the
I n t e rnet is a bit surp rising in view of the
ve ry poor quality of the images. At present,
putting a video film online is a bit like
t rying to get a camel through the eye of a
n e e d l e . The feed down a telephone line is
far too slow and irr e g u l a r. Reception qua-
lity va ries according to the bandwidth and
the number of people connected. T h e
images come through at the rate of four or
five a second (five times slower than a nor-
mal television transmission), the size of the
picture is no more than 25 cm2, and line
congestion causes frequent sudden breaks
in transmission. But TV channels, from the
going online for the first time will be acces-
sing the Net via television. There is a good
chance this will happen in developing coun-
t ries too. In India, the Sat yam Infoway ser-
vice provider has just brought out a box
which allows TV viewe rs to access the Net.
In Bri t a i n , the majority of the population is
expected to take up digital television within
a matter of ye a rs. C h ris Smith, the Culture
S e c r e t a ry, said last September he wa n t e d
the new technology to bring the Intern e t
into eve ry home.
With Internet heading into the home,
electronic commerce is set to take off—
which just happens to be one of the aims of
the technological conve r g e n c e .The viewe r ,
for example, will see an adve rtising banner
at the top of the screen announcing a bar-
gain price for, s ay, a pair of jeans. It will take
just a click of the remote-control to get to
the maker’s website and order a pair.
number of people who watch television.
In rich countries,95 per cent of the popu-
lation watch television, but only 20-35 per
cent of families have computers, which
still scare a lot of people because they are
complicated to use and are still associated
mostly with the workplace.
Cyberspace
in the salon
So at the dawn of the 21st century,
sound, video images and television pro-
grammes are proliferating on the Web.
Meanwhile, as television becomes digital,
it is starting to offer interactive facilities
and access to the Internet.
Since WebTV was launched in the
United States in 1996 and purchased by
Microsoft the following ye a r , the race has
been on to provide television viewe rs with
access to the Net via their TV screens.T h i s
facility is currently being offered through
b oxes linking the TV set to a telephone
l i n e . As digital TV spreads, s u p e r - d e c o d e rs
will gi ve future viewe rs access—through
c a b l e , s atellite or radio—to a profusion of
channels (many of them paying) as well as
to the Web and other interactive digi t a l l y -
p r ovided serv i c e s , such as pers o n a l i z e d
we ather forecasts and news serv i c e s , d at a-
banks which can provide in-depth mat e ri a l
about TV progr a m m e s , shopping centres
and home banking. Recent surveys suggest
t h at there will be 61 million decoders ope-
r ating in the world by 2003.
There seems to be a gr owing consensus
t h at the Net will not become a really wides-
pread medium until it reaches people’s
homes through the TV set. A recent surve y
in Britain showed that 70 per cent of people
Internet technology encourages active participation by users hunting 
for information on the Web.
There seems to be a growing
consensus that the Net will
not become a really
widespread medium until 
it reaches people’s homes
through the TV set
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 45
C O N N E X I O N S
How much longer can the couch potato survive?
smallest to the major netwo r k s , k n ow that
over the next decade big innovations will
t r a n s f o rm the scene, with gr e ater speed,
3D images, full-screen pictures and other
i m p r ove m e n t s.
According to the managers of
Comfm, a French Web portal (gateway
site) which provides access to radio and
TV stations around the world, in mid-
1999 over 100 TV stations were transmit-
ting their programmes round the clock
live on the Net. Hundreds of other gene-
ral and specialist channels offer audiovi-
sual archives, either free or paying.
By broadcasting television on the Net,
you can reach a global audience much more
cheaply than by cable or sat e l l i t e .A l s o, in an
increasingly competitive environment due
to the skyrocketing supply of programmes
on offer,TV stations plan on using the We b
to make themselves more at t r a c t i ve . Fo r
example a “webviewer”, during a football
m at c h , can look up biographies of the
players or the history of the teams by clic-
king on a banner which runs across the
s c r e e n . A viewer can also plunge deeper
into a subject while the TV news is on by
delving into the Web to get extra informa-
tion and video mat e rial which is available on
demand. It remains to be seen, however,
whether this mass of material will overw-
helm the average viewer.
Online TV stations, despite their cur-
rent hesitations, also dream of becoming
successful Web portals. The programmes
would draw in consumers and then steer
them towards virtual shopping centres.
They would sell not just videocassettes,
games and CDs but all kinds of other
items, from clothes to cheese.
S e veral of the big networks are also
hoping to win back on the Web some of the
v i e we rs they are losing to new stations and
to the Net. The major networks are bu s y
setting up websites which complement
their television programmes without com-
peting with them.The giant U. S . n e t wo r k ,
A B C , has launched the firs t - e ver live inter-
a c t i ve “ we b - o n l y ” news progr a m m e . I t
goes out on the Web in the middle of the
d ay, at 12.30, to target a new audience of
o f fic e - wo r k e rs during their lunch-break.
Special-interest
TV channels
An entirely new kind of TV, the web-
channel, is also emerging in the shape of
countless small stations operated by com-
panies, political organizations and spe-
cial-interest groups (medicine and
cooking, for example). One big advantage
they have is that production and broad-
casting costs are negligible. Many of the
people setting up such webchannels think
mass television has a limited future.They
are betting that audiences will become
more and more fragmented just as they
did with the growth in cable-and-satellite
d e l i vered progr a m m e s. With digi t a l i z a-
tion, this fragmentation is expected to
increase and give rise to television com-
munities,with viewers tuning into thema-
tic programming.While watching highly-
specialized channels, webviewers can look
up material about the topic being presen-
ted or chat with other people connected
to the site.
More than 40 million people—about
a quarter of all those online—already have
software to access these sites and down-
load sound and video from them onto
their computers. The wo r l d ’s leading
a u d i ovisual port a l , B r o a d c a s t . c o m
(recently taken over by Yahoo!), gets half a
million visitors every day.
W h at about the future? As television
and the Web conve r g e , will the familiar old
TV set disappear? It seems unlikely, since
the two means of communication are dis-
tinct—the Internet meets the needs of the
i n d i v i d u a l , and television addresses a mass
a u d i e n c e .They also have different publics—
the active Net-user and the passive T V
v i e we r. So we can be fairly sure TV will
s t ay T V, w h at e ver kind of screen we shall use
to watch it. There will always be people
who want to lap up the programmes offered
on their favourite channel. Mass TV will
always have a role in broadcasting major
events which bring a mass audience toge-
ther,such as the funeral of Princess Diana
or the World Cup football final. n
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
T A L K I N G T O …
The central figure in your best-known novel,
Pereira Declares, A Testimony, is an 
ageing and lonely widower who is in charge 
of the cultural pages of a newspaper.
Why did you choose an anti-hero as your
main character?
I’ve always been drawn to tormented
people full of contradictions. The more
doubts they have the better. People with
lots of doubts sometimes find life more
oppressive and exhausting than others,
but they’re more energetic—they aren’t
robots. I prefer insomnia to anaesthesia. I
don’t go for people who lead full and
satisfying lives. In my books, I’m not on
the side of the authorities. I’m with those
who’ve suffered. My first novel, Piazza
d’Italia, was an attempt to write history
that hasn’t been written, history as writ-
ten by the losing side, in this case the
Tuscan anarchists. My books are about
losers, about people who’ve lost their way
and are engaged in a search.
What are they looking for?
T h e y ’re looking for themselves through
o t h e rs , because I think that ’s the best way
to look for oneself.The main character in
Indian Nocturn e, who retraces the steps of
a friend who’s disappeared in India, is invo l-
ved in such a quest. And so is Spino, t h e
character in The Edge of the Hori zo n w h o
t ries to find out the identity of an unknow n
corpse.I don’t know whether these people
are going to find themselve s , but as they live
their lives they have no choice but to fa c e
up to the image others have of them.T h e y ’r e
forced to look at themselves in a mirr o r ,a n d
they often manage to glimpse something of
themselves.
After the success of Pereira Declares with the
Italian public, there was some talk of your
running for election to the Italian Senate. Do
you regret ruling out that opportunity?
No, I’m happy to go on living the life
I’ve chosen. I’m a university teacher and I
like my job. Literature is my life of cour-
se, but from an ontological point of view.
From an existential point of view, I like
being a teacher. Literature for me isn’t a
wo r k a d ay job, but something which
involves desires, dreams and fantasy. I
don’t want to promote my own image
either. I don’t like going on television or
mixing in literary circles. I live quietly at
home among my family and fri e n d s.
Besides, there are politicians who do the
job far better than I ever could. I think it’s
more interesting to keep a sharp eye on
politics. My job is to look at what politics
is doing, not be a politician myself.
Your latest novel, “The Lost Head of
Damasceno Monteiro” (1997), is based on the
story of a man who was murdered in a
Republican National Guard police station on
the outskirts of Lisbon and whose headless
body was found in a park. Why did you use
this real-life event?
I was in Portugal when this shocking
act occurred. I was deeply revolted.When
a crime offends human nature, it offends
us personally.You feel both horrified and
guilty. My emotions, sensitivity and ima-
gination as a writer were moved by this
event. Look, I have here the documents
drawn up by human rights investigators
from the Council of Europe in Strasbourg
who monitor conditions of detention in
European countries. They talk about the
relations between the police and citizens
in police stations—places of detention to
which you or I would be taken today if we
broke some law or other in the street.
A N TONIO TA BUCCHI: 
A COMMI TT ED DOUBT ER
An Italian novelist jolts the forces of complacency in the world of fact as well as fiction 
If a politician’s job is to 
soothe people, to show that
all’s well because of his or 
her presence, mine is to
disturb people, to sow the
seeds of doubt. The ca p a c i ty 
to doubt is very important for
human beings. For heaven’s
s a ke, if we don’t have any
doubts, we’re fin i s h e d !
1. Ludwig Wittgenstein,Austrian-born British
philosopher (Vienna 1889-Cambridge 1951), was
one of the founders of modern analytic
philosophy. “The limits of my language constitute
the limits of my mind,” he wrote in his Tractatus
Logico-Philosophicus. In “Plato’s Gastritis”,
Tabucchi criticizes this logic, which he describes
as “very sensible but very limited”because “it
only allows us to talk of what is known”.
Did you use these documents when you were
writing the novel?
Ye s , I wanted to know about the situat i o n
in Po rt u g a l , which is rather concern i n g .R e a-
ding other reports made me realize things are
the same nearly eve rywhere else in Europe,
including in countries which seem more
d e m o c r at i c. But democracy isn’t a state of
p e r f e c t i o n . It has to be improve d , and that
means constant vigi l a n c e . I thought I had to go
b e yond the actual event and talk about it
through a novel—to gi ve fictional treat m e n t
to this violent occurr e n c e . In a nove l ,my fee-
lings and sense of outrage can find a broader
means of expression which would be more
symbolic and applicable to many European
c o u n t ri e s.
What was the Portuguese public’s reaction 
to the book?
I didn’t get many requests for interv i e w s.
People generally don’t go in for self-cri t i c i s m ,
so I’m not surp rised when a foreign writer is
attacked for looking too closely at this kind of
i n c i d e n t .But when Sergeant José dos Santos,
the killer, finally confessed to his crime and
was sentenced to 17 ye a rs in jail, the Po rt u-
guese press asked me how I’d been able to pre-
dict the outcome of the trial in my nove l , as if
I was a fort u n e - t e l l e r. I was in Istanbul at the
t i m e ,and when I got back to my hotel I found
n e w s p a p e rs had fa xed me lists of questions.
But I don’t think I have any particular talent
for prediction, because when you have three
or four elements in hand,you don’t have to be
a genius to reach certain conclusions.Fa n t a s y
and imagi n ation are also a kind of intuitive
k n owledge which doesn’t have much to do
with Wittgensteinian logi c,1 as I said in my
book “ P l at o ’s Gastri t i s ” . But they are a form
of know l e d g e , one involving suspicion and
d o u b t .
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - November 1999 47
T A L K I N G  T O …
K EEPING HIS OP T IONS OPEN
Antonio Tabucchi is used to writing his novels on
hot, empty July afternoons in Lisbon, where he
lives for six months of the year. But this summer, he
had other things on his mind. None of his colleagues
in the International Parliament of Writers was able
to go to East Timor to write about the referendum
there in late August, a historic step in the Timorese
people’s fight for independence from Indonesia. He
hesitated to go to this island 700 kilometres from
A u s t ralia because he was afraid he wouldn’t be able
to get back in time to give key evidence in favour of
a gypsy family in a court case in Florence.
This is a ty p i cal situation in the 56-year-old wri-
ter’s life. Tabucchi waits for things to happen and
keeps all his options open. He knows that an encoun-
ter with a book, a picture or a person can give a new
twist to a person’s life. His own changed after he read
on a train journey a poem called Ta b a c a r i a ( “ T h e
Tobacconist’s”), by the Portuguese poet Fe r n a n d o
Pessoa (18 8 8 - 19 35). He went to study in Lisbon and
developed a passion for the country which, he says,
is now part of his “genetic baggage”.
With María José de Lancastre, he has tra n s l a t e d
much of Pessoa’s work into Italian and written a book
of essays and a play about him. In 1992, he wrote a
novel in Portuguese, Requiem: A Hallucination, which
a friend later translated into Italian for him. Ta b u c-
chi is married to a native of Lisbon and has a daugh-
ter “who is more Portuguese than Italian and a son
who is more Italian than Po r t u g u e s e ” .
He was born in Vecchiano, a village not far from
Pisa, in Tuscany. Nearby is the University of Siena,
where he teaches literature six months of the year.
The subject of his next course will be the Brazilian
poet Carlos Drummond de Andrade (19 0 2 - 87 ) ,
whom he got to know in Rio de Janeiro.
Tabucchi writes a column for the Italian new s-
paper C o r r i e re della Se ra and for Spain’s El País.
Among his various awards are France’s Medicis
Prize for the best foreign novel in 19 87, Europe’s
Jean Monnet Prize in 1994 and the Nossack Prize
from the Leibniz Academy in 1999.
In the 1995 Italian parliamentary election ca m-
paign, the hero of his novel P e re i ra Declare s
b e came the symbol of left-wing opposition to com-
m u n i cations magnate Silvio Berlusconi. Many
people identified with the Portuguese journalist
who, in 19 38 during the Salazar dictatorship, com-
mitted a bold act of rebellion. Today Tabucchi is
k n own first and foremost as “the author of P e re i ra” .
This book continues your debate with the
Italian semiologist and writer Umberto Eco.
What’s the root of your disagreement with
him?
Eco sees the intellectual as an organizer
of culture, someone who can run a maga-
zine or a museum. An administrat o r , i n
fa c t . I think this is a melancholy situat i o n
for an intellectual. I claim the right to take
a stand once in a while. When something
strange happens in the world or in yo u r
h o m e , you have to look into it to see if yo u
can pin it dow n , work it out, talk about it
and sound the alarm : “Look out! This is
happening in my home, in my tow n , in the
wo r l d , which is also my home.” On the
other hand, an intellectual would be totally
witless if he said: “Something terrible is
happening in my home but I can’t get
interested in it because I’m putting toge-
ther a catalogue for an exhibition of pain-
tings in my local museum.”
So what do you think an intellectual should be
doing?
If a politician’s job is to soothe people,
to show that all’s well because of his or
her presence, mine is to disturb people,to
sow the seeds of doubt. The capacity to
doubt is ve ry important for human
beings. For heaven’s sake,if we don’t have
any doubts, we’re finished! An intellectual
is going to have doubts, for example,
about a fundamentalist religious doctrine
that admits no doubt, about an imposed
political system that allows no doubt,
about a perfect aesthetic that has no room
for doubt. Doubts are like stains on a
shirt. I like shirts with stains, because
when I’m given a shirt that’s too clean,
one that’s completely white, I immediate-
ly start having doubts. It’s the job of intel-
lectuals and writers to cast doubt on per-
f e c t i o n . Perfection spawns doctri n e s ,
dictators and totalitarian ideas.
Are you absolutely certain about this?
There are some fundamental values
i t ’s impossible to be wrong about.
Nobody can disagree with the saying “do
not do unto others what you would not
have done unto yourself”. That’s some-
thing basic, that’s part of human nature. I
don’t have any doubts either about the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
Perhaps some more should be added to
the list, but I don’t have the slightest
doubt about human rights.
Doubts begin when political action is taken.
For example, was it right or wrong to underta-
ke military intervention in Kosovo to stop
human rights violations?
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The UNESCO Courier - November 1999
T A L K I N G T O …
article entitled “Florence, the capital, but
the capital of gypsies”—note the use of
the word “but”. In it, a columnist sneered
at seminars on gypsy culture that had
been organized by the Michelucci
Foundation, of Fiesole, near Florence.
Fifty years after half a million gypsies
were exterminated in the Second World
War—thousands of them in Auschwitz—
we’re again preparing the mass killing of
this minority.
Why are gypsies so often the target of this
kind of violence?
Xenophobia manifests itself especially
against civilizations and cultures that are
weak because they lack economic
r e s o u r c e s , means of subsistence or land. S o
nomadic people are the first targets of this
kind of aggr e s s i o n . Sometimes it isn’t phy-
sical violence but violence in the form of
i n t o l e r a b l e , subhuman living conditions
like those the gypsies on the outskirts of
Florence have to put up with. I ’ ve cri t i c i-
zed this situation in a report that wa s
recently published in Italy2. M a ny gypsies
h ave fled their own countries and are
nomads by necessity after escaping from
the war in Yu g o s l av i a . A society which
c o n s i d e rs itself civilized can’t treat people
like that . I t ’s contrary to the notion of
culture and hospitality, to the ve ry spirit of
our civilizat i o n , which ori gi n ates in
Ancient Greece and European humanism.
What did you mean when you titled one of
your articles “I am an Albanian”?
The salt of any interesting civilization
is mixture.A civilization that’s closed and
i n ward-looking is steri l e . C i v i l i z at i o n s
that are worthy of attention have mana-
ged to incorporate a variety of ingredients
and elements. As a writer, I’ve always
been interested in others. The most
important basis of any novel is wanting to
be someone else, and this means creating
a character. We all want to be someone
else but without ceasing to be ourselves. I
think it’s very important to defend this
“The salt of any interesting civilization is mixture.” Above, Berlin police gesture Romanian 
gypsies to move on.
BIBL IOGRA PH Y
Tabucchi’s works translated into English
and published by New Directions include
P e re i ra Declares: A Te s t i m o ny ( 19 9 6 ) ,
Requiem: A Hallucination (1994), The Edge
of the Horizon ( 1990), Indian Nocturne
(1989), Letter from Casablanca (1986), and
Little Misunderstandings of No Importance
( 19 87). His Fernando Pessoa, written w i t h
Maria José Lancastre, was published by
Pocket Archives in 1997. n
Xenophobic violence 
is the most serious conflict 
in Europe today, one which 
I think it’s imperative 
for intellectuals and writers 
to oppose in word and deed
article published by one writer was com-
pletely different from and contradictory
to that published by another the day befo-
re. I think this is very important.
But politicians also have to make decisions.
There comes a moment when doubts have to
be left behind.
Ye s , but I still prefer politicians who lis-
ten to the doubts of others and start hav i n g
a few doubts themselve s. I t ’s ve ry useful
when politicians have doubts because there
are so many choices to be made in the
wo r l d . U n f o rt u n ately politicians in Europe
these days are more concerned with fig u r e s
and accounts than with pri n c i p l e s.T h e y ’r e
like Eco’s intellectuals: political adminis-
t r at o rs and bu r e a u c r at s.
One of the most worrying kinds of violence in
Europe nowadays is rooted in xenophobia.
What do you think about that?
Xenophobic violence is the most
s e rious conflict in Europe today, o n e
which I think it’s imperative for intellec-
tuals and writers to oppose in word and
deed. It has broken out in many coun-
tries, for economic and social reasons like
u n e m p l oyment and clandestine migr a-
tion. But we have to make a distinction
between skinheads, for example, who are
simply the embodiment of brute force,
and people whose speeches and writings
p r ovide theoretical backing for racial
hatred and attacks on minorities. This is
being done openly, with virtual impunity.
In June 1999, Italy’s third-biggest news-
paper, Giornale della Toscana, printed an
2. Gli Zingari e il Rinascimento, Librerie Feltrinelli,
April 1999.
Yes of course. But remember that
during the Kosovo war, writers could
express themselves freely, which I think
was a very good thing. Many members of
the International Parliament of Writers
(IPW) did so because we set up a network
of newspapers , including L i b é rat i o n
(France), El País (Spain) and Corriere
della Sera (Italy). Every day, a writer
spoke up. There were many conflicting
viewpoints, but I think writers’ opinions
were expressed with great freedom during
the war. Who were the only people who
d i d n ’t have any doubts at the time?
Politicians and the military. But writers
expressed one doubt after another. An
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O …
“Xenophobic violence is the most serious conflict in Europe today.” 
Above, skinheads on the outskirts of Paris.
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER"
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15€) instead of 264FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35€) instead of 528FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11€) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10€)
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15 €) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No.⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—
⌧—⌧—⌧ Expiry date: ⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧—⌧
Name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:                  Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
idea in real life too.
What has had the greatest influence on your
political life?
It’s hard to say. Perhaps the story of
my country, my childhood, my grandfa-
ther, the First World War. My interest in
human rights originates in anti-war fee-
lings that go back to my childhood. I was
born in the Second World War during the
Nazi invasion of my country. I vividly
remember the stories my grandfather told
me about the carnage of the First World
War, which people tend to forget was one
of the worst massacres in human history.
So this antipathy to violence goes back to
my childhood, to my grandfather and to
the anarcho-libert a rian and republican
tradition of my native Tuscany.
You’re one of the founders of the International
Parliament of Writers. How did it get started?
Three hundred intellectuals from
around the wo r l d , including To n i
M o rri s o n , Günter Grass and Octavio Pa z ,
founded it in 1993 after the murder of the
A l g e rian writer and poet Tahar Djaout.
The idea was to set up an organization to
p r o t e c t , almost phy s i c a l l y, w ri t e rs and
intellectuals threatened with deat h , p e rs e-
cuted or imprisoned in their countri e s. A
year lat e r , we set up a council of about 50
m e m b e rs. Its first president was Salman
R u s h d i e , who was unfort u n ately not just a
symbol but a living target of such pers e c u-
t i o n . Our current president is the Nigeri a n
w riter Wole Soy i n k a .We have a network of
about 30 “ r e f u g e ” cities which offer wri t e rs
and their families a decent place to live and
enough money to subsist and take part in
the city’s cultural activities—its librari e s ,
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G T O …
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George's Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Brussels. 
Fax: 538 08 41.
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
Oxford Book & Stationery Co, Code No D 820 8 0 52, Scindia House, New
Delhi 110 001. Fax: 33 22 639 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Nalanda Co. Ltd., 30 Bourbon Street, Port Louis. 
Fax: 212 1313 .
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
Los Amigos de la UNES CO, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 94427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG, Wissenschaftl. Buchhandlung, Pe t e r s g raben 31, 
CH-4009 Basel. Fax: 306 12 34 .
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce
C/C Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: 286 03 26 .
+ …
l International Parliament of Writers (IPW): 
ipwpie@compuserve.com
(Website under construction)
East Timorese lining up to cast ballots in the August 30, 1999 referendum 
on independence or autonomy.
schools and associat i o n s.
Are any of these cities outside Europe?
Yes, they exist in Brazil and Australia.
Mexico City recently became a refuge-
city, in line with a tradition going back to
the 1920s and 1930s, when the Mexican
capital took in many persecuted intellec-
tuals from Europe. I went to Mexico City
in March 1999 with the secretary-general
of the IPW, the French writer Christian
Salmon, to sign an agreement whereby
the Mexican authorities provided a refuge
for two writers,Vladimir Arsenijevic from
Serbia and the Kosovar-Albanian writer
Xhevdet Bajraj. Both of them now live in
Casa Citlapletel, a house run by the
Friends of the IPW association.
Has any IPW action given you particular
satisfaction?
Everything it’s done has been useful.
Our notion of a writer is a very broad one.
It includes Shakespeare and a journalist
working on a newspaper in a remote villa-
ge in Afghanistan. But I’m very happy
that Italy, whose only refuge-city so far is
Venice, will soon have three more such
towns in Tuscany—Grosseto, Pontedera
and Certaldo. I’m very fond of Certaldo
because it was the birthplace of
B o c c a c c i o, the gr e at medieval Italian
novelist. They’re all quite small towns
where writers can get together more easi-
ly than in a big city.
The IPW organized support for the August
1999 self-determination referendum in East
Timor. Why?
When you have a foreign invasion—in
this case by the Indonesian army—wri-
ters, intellectuals, newspapers and maga-
zines are the first targets of repression.
Xanana Gusmão, the Timorese leader, is
a poet and a journalist. In 1994, the IPW
voiced support for the self-determination
of the Timorese people in the name of
fundamental principles of justice and civi-
lization. More recently, we asked for the
referendum to be held without fraud and
without violence by the anti-independen-
ce militias which are conniving with the
Indonesian regime. I think the internatio-
nal community, the United Nations, will
have to insist and bring pressure to bear
so a military power like Indonesia doesn’t
crush the people of this little island. So I
agree with Nobel Peace Prize winner José
Ramos Horta when he says that if you call
for troops to get out of Kosovo, you must
also demand the withdrawal of
Indonesian troops from East Timor, even
though the public seems to think that a
European country is more important than
a tiny island in the Indian Ocean. People
have a right to live, even on an island
which seems insignificant to most people.
n
Interview by Asbel Lopez
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO PUBLISHING
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
World Social
Science Report
1999
The social sciences 
as tools for 
understanding today’s
world
UNESCO Publishing/Elsevier
352 pp., 29.7 x 21 cm, 
ISBN: 92-3-103602-5
295 FF / €44.97
Written by a truly
international team of
highly regarded authors,
the World Social Science
Report is a unique source
of facts, figures and
assessments of the role of
the social sciences in the
world today.
Both specialists and 
the general public will
find chapters addressing
their concerns, written in
a language that is
accessible without loss of
rigour.
World
Communication
and Information
Report
1999-2000
An overview of 
the wild development 
of information 
and communication
technologies
300 pp., 1999, 29.7 x 21 cm
ISBN 92-3-103611-4
250 FF / €38.11
Beyond mere technical
analysis, a study of the
countless challenges
facing societies all over
the world
A key subject for
UNESCO, whose
Constitution outlines the
mission to promote
understanding between
peoples through
education, science,
culture and
communication
U N E S C O  P u b l i s h i n g
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In the next issue
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
Fo c u s :
Memory: confronting the past
to shape the future
n Can bygones be bygones?
n Rosalina Tuyuc (Guatemala): forgive but not forget
n South Africa: the price of national reconciliation
n Rwanda’s collective amnesia
n Chile: looking back in anger?
n Cambodia: exit from fear
n International courts as servants of memory
Fe a t u res include
n The colourful world of the circus
n Forests and climate: the big tradeoff
n Training the police against racism
n The year 2000: who’ll be at the party?
n International radio: conquering new audiences
n Interview with Kenyan environmental activist 
Wangari Muta Maathai
]]>
</page>
</document>
