<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="119966eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
PEOPLE AND PLACES
Chiapas: the magic
of the mirror
PLANET
The “miracle” 
of the Rhine
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
Diving 
for dollars
CONNEXIONS
Internet to the rescue 
of democracy?
Wo m e n ’s long
m a rch to power
June 2000
P u b l i s h e d
in 27
l a n g u a g e s
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
PEOPLE AND PLACES
3 The magic of the mirro r Photos by Alex We b b, text by Fabrizio Mejía Madrid
PLANET
9 The “ m i ra c l e ” of the Rhine Urs We b e r
WORLD OF LEARNING
13 Doing it their own way: home schooling in the U. S. Jeff A r c h e r
15 E u ropean disunity Cynthia Guttman
ETHICS
38 G y p s i e s :t rapped on the fringes of Euro p e Alain Reyniers
40 A Roma ghetto in Flore n c e Nicola Solimano and Tiziana Mori
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
41 Diving for dollars Vincent Noce
CONNEXIONS
44 Internet to the rescue of democra c y ? René Lefort
46 A f r i c a : cell phones for citizenship Interview with Ibrahima N’Diaye
INTERVIEW
47 M a rgarita Salas:knowledge to dispel fear
1 6 Focus Wo m e n ’s long march to p o w e r
“Women’s rights are human rights.” This landmark slogan of
the Beijing Conference on Women held exactly five years ago is
more than ever brandished by women the world over. Already
influential forces in their own communities, women are now
demanding greater access to decision-making powers. But why
does their quest to break into the male political bastion remain
such an obstacle course?
Detailed table of contents on page 16.
C o n t e n t s
June 2000 53rd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Roy Malkin
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
French edition: Martine Jacot
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Sophie Boukhari
Cynthia Guttman
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Georges Servat,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck 
(Tel:(33) (0) 1 45.68.45.86)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,A l c i n o
Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salal El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the
UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three voucher copies
are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
a u t h o r ’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
r e q u e s t . Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UN E S C O o r
those of the editors of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the UN E S C O Courier staff. Th e
boundaries on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the United
N a t i o n s. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform
( m i c r o film and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de
Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,A n n
A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition,
Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ;( 4 )
Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,Wo o s t e r, O h i o
4 4 6 9 1 , U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - JUNE2000
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Paris by
UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e. Periodicals postage paid at Champlain
NY and additional mailing offices.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 6-2000-OPI 99-592 AC o v e r : © Alain Buu/Gamma, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 3
T HE MAGIC OF THE MIRROR
◗ Photos by Alex Webb, text by Fabrizio Mejía Madrid
The uprising in Chiapas has forced Mexican society to look at the Indians straight on, 
perhaps for the first time, and to start weaving with them a truly common future
◗ Alex Webb is an American photographer with 
the Magnum agency.
Fabrizio Mejía Madrid is director of culture at the
municipality of Mexico City. A contributor to the daily 
La Jornada, he is the author of three books, including
“Small Acts of Civil Disobedience”, published in Spanish
in 1996.
■
I seemed to notice a movement from
beneath her shawl, a kind of sudden
v i b r at i o n . I looked down at the
wo m a n ’s feet and was start l e d : her cal-
loused heels bore all the dust and dirt of
ye a rs walking barefoot. I placed a coin in the
woman’s permanently open palm,and ran
into the Museum of Anthropology. I was
seven or eight years old. I asked my father
about the woman to whom I had just been
told to gi ve some money. “ S h e ’s an Indian,”
he replied. “But something was mov i n g
inside under her clothes,” I insisted. “ I t
must have been her child,” my fat h e r
c o n c l u d e d , and we walked on into the
M ayan room of the museum without say i n g
a word.
The image of that Indian woman in
Mexico City has haunted me every year
since. It is not really an image, more like
fragments of a body—an outstretched
hand, the soles of her feet, the coppery
colour of her arm—and the suggestion of
another being moving beneath her
clothes. When you come across them in
the cities, you don’t look at them directly.
They, the Indians, lower their eyes as if to
acknowledge that the colour of their skin,
their “defective” Spanish and their rural
Children in front of a mural featuring Emiliano Zapata in Polhó, a village located in the Chenalhó municipality, in the heart of Chiapas.
garments have made them invaders in this
land of mestizo nationalism. They have
never had looks or expressions. Nobody
can remember their faces.
In contrast, the term “ i n d i g e n o u s
people” — as opposed to “Indians” — is
part and parcel of Mexican history. Like
millions of other Mexican children, I
grew up seeing murals by Diego Rivera,
where the Aztecs came to represent sym-
bols and values, but not people. From as
far back as I recall, “indigenous” has
meant that under the earth on which we
walk there are vestiges of women and men
who erected pyramids to worship the sun,
dreamt about the number zero, sacrificed
virgins and predicted eclipses. But bet-
ween the “Indian” and the “indigenous”
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
identification, a form of magic and a mir-
ror that creates a third party: neither one-
self nor the other, but that which makes
us similar, that in which we both recogni-
ze ourselves. This reflection of the other
which is also my own self in another per-
son’s gaze was exactly what was denied to
me by the country to which I belong. For
500 years the Indians were not men and
women who had to be wiped out, but
simple non-humans who survived thanks
to a national evasion: not looking at them
head-on, in the eyes. Looking in the eyes
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
4 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
there has never been any connection
beyond the fact that neither had a face.
For centuries the Indians submissively
joined the growing mass of invisible spec-
tators of a distant country, of an ethereal
land which changes without the need to
involve those who are watching it. The
image of the “Indians” was one of pea-
sants always waiting for land,justice, edu-
cation and health. We knew they existed
because there were millions of them,
though we stayed deaf to what they were
t rying to tell us. Taken into account
because of their sheer number, t h e
“Indians” ended up being tackled as a
“problem” in the 1970s: that of migration
to the cities. The so-called “Marias”—
“Indians” who asked for charity dressed
in highly coloured clothes—were the fai-
thful reflection of the failure of our shared
life and of the only offer that we made to
help them belong to Mexico: stop being
Indians.
When on January 1, 1994, the Indians
in Chiapas rebelled once more against
contempt, they did so covering the whole
face apart from the eyes. They made the
country look at them. They knew that
morality started by looking at someone in
the eyes. It is the source of empathy, of
Revolutionary images on a wall in Polhó express some of the inhabitants’ aspirations.
of the Indians made us capture in their
reflection the very part of ourselves that
exists in the other,the foreign in each and
every one of us.
Four years on, the women from an
Indian community displaced by a “low-
intensity war” were the architects of ano-
ther major change. After the massacre of
women and children in Acteal on
December 22, 1 9 9 7 , the women of
X’oyep decided to rise up against the
army’s presence. Already forced out of
their homes, they were not ready to be
drawn into hostilities once again. They
pushed the soldiers with their bare hands
right to the village’s boundaries, while
one of them carried in her hands X’oyep’s
last hen. Riled by indignation, she defen-
ded the bird and together with the other
women, triumphed over a professional
army. The moral strength of the Tzeltal
Indians of X’oyep rested in January 1998
on their physical weakness and on their
small number, but also on their opposi-
tion to war.They are the poor people who
refuse to be helped by a country which
allowed the Acteal massacre to take place.
In their resistance there is a moral stance
that connects me to them: neither would
I resign myself to a great “national plan”
The image of the “Indians”
was one of peasants always
waiting for land, justice,
e d u cation and health. 
We knew they existed 
b e cause there were millions 
of them, though we sta y e d
deaf to what they were try i n g
to tell us.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
June 2000 -The UNESCO Courier 5
Standing guard at the entrance to Polhó.
A rope marks off Zapatista territory, barring its access to foreigners.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
6 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
A memorial to villagers killed in Acteal in 1997.
MEX ICO’S 
P OOREST STAT E
Along with neighbouring Yucatan and Oax a ca ,
Chiapas, a state in southern Mexico, has the
c o u n t ry’s highest proportion of indigenous
people: 42.5 per cent of its three million or so
inhabitants are Mayans. Nationally, there are
approximately 10.6 million indigenous people
out of a population of 92 million, 80 per cent of
whom are mixed-race.
Mostly rural, Chiapas breaks Mexico’s
p o v e r ty records. In 1995, it was estimated that
59 per cent of the population were living on less
than the minimum income necessary for surv i v a l
(then put at $150 a month). That situation is
partly explained by the fact that Chiapas, so far
from Mexico City, is the state where land reform
was the most weakly implemented. When the
reform ended in 1992, half the land in Chiapas
was still in the hands of large landowners.
That is the context in which the “Zapatista
Army of National Liberation” (EZLN) led by “sub-
commandante” Marcos burst upon the scene on
J a n u a ry 1, 1994, a symbolic date because it mar-
ked the entry into force of the NAFTA free-trade
agreement with the United States and Canada.
EZLN rebels overran seven Chiapas municipali-
ties, including the city of San Cristobal de las
Casas, demanding “d e m o c ra cy, freedom and jus-
tice for all Mexicans.” A ceasefire was declared
after two weeks of fighting with the army in
which, according to official sources, 159 people
were killed, though human rights groups put the
death toll at over 400. On February 21, 1994, the
EZLN and Mexico’s federal government began
talks for the first time, mediated by the bishop of
San Cristobal, Mgr Samuel Ruiz. Signed on
Fe b r u a ry 16, 1996, the San Andres accords on
the rights of indigenous peoples were rejected by
the authorities, on the basis that national sove-
reignty had to be protected.  
The cost of breaking off the negotiations has
been high. For example, 45 alleged EZLN sym-
pathizers were killed in the village of Acteal on
December 22, 1997.
In March 1999, 2.5 million Mexicans took
part in a consulation organized by the EZLN on
i n t e g rating indigenous law into the Constitution.
The strategy of the guerrillas, whose objective is
not to seize power, consists of gathering support
from national and international civil society for a
democratisation of Mexican society. ■
that I have not chosen.Their actions have
made them famous because they entailed
a nationalism without patriots: they did
not want any happiness that would des-
troy them for their own good. In the
hands that pushed out the army, I saw the
“Marias” of my childhood disappearing.
The distance between looking
and listening
Although we have become more
willing to tolerate difference, we are still
no more ready to listen to and understand
the voices of difference.The idea of diver-
sity in Mexican society brings to mind
divided ghettoes where contact between
one tradition and another inevitably wea-
kens one of them.Moving from the ethnic
to the ethical does not mean we should
strive to preserve that diversity, but rather
absorb what it is trying to tell us. It is the
gap between looking and listening, bet-
ween accepting that the Other exists and
experiencing its fragility as one’s own,
between opening windows and building
bridges. It is this gap that we have to nar-
row: to go from living alongside each
other to experimenting with living toge-
ther. I know that with the X’oyep women
we will travel that road. ■
Mexico
Tuxtla Gutiérrez
Chiapas
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 7
A refugee family in X’oyep, to the northeast of Tuxtla Gutiérrez.
Musicians performing in Polhó.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E  A N D  P L A C E S
8 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
Refugee children in X’oyep.
A government military post in Chenalhó.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
P L A N E T
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 9
T HE “ MIRACL E ”OF T HE RHINE
◗ Urs Weber
Fish are once again swimming in the Rhine River but it took an ecological catastrophe 
for the countries it flows through to clean up their act
◗ Editor of the regional supplement of the Swiss daily
newspaper Basler Zeitung, in Basel
■
For decades, the Rhine was one of
E u r o p e ’s most repelling waste dumps.
To d ay, c o n c e rted efforts by all the
c o u n t ries along its banks have restored the
ri ve r ’s health.The symbol of that recove ry
is the mighty salmon, which swims once
more in its wat e rs : over 200 have been
caught since 1996. But the road to success
was long and hard.
Europe’s busiest waterway, the Rhine
is navigable over a distance of 883 kilo-
meters stretching from its source near
Basel to its mouth in the Netherlands. For
centuries, many cities and major indus-
trial areas, such as the Ruhr Valley, have
occupied its banks. One of the world’s
densest road and railway networks follows
its course.The river also irrigates areas of
intensive agriculture and vineyards pro-
ducing highly-prized wines.
Other crops, such as maize, tobacco,
sugar beet and market garden produce
(often in greenhouses), which consume
high amounts of fertiliser, are greater
threats to the environment. Run-off from
dairy and pork farms also cause damage.
Thousands of people drink water drawn
from the river, while urban waste flows
into it. A glance at the Rhine’s geography
(see map and box) shows that civilisation
puts huge strains on the river, which flows
through five countries, making it a proto-
type of co-operation in intern at i o n a l
waters.
A subject of treaties
An 1816 treat y, one of Europe’s
oldest, established the Rhine as a navi-
gable waterway. The accord was updated
in Mainz in 1831 and replaced in 1868 by
the Mannheim Act, which set up the
Strasbourg-based Central Commission of
the Rhine, whose purpose was to guaran-
tee freedom of movement on the “inter-
n ational wat e r way.” Dikes were bu i l t
along its branches and marshland was
dredged to make it navigable for vessels
with draughts of up to 3,000 tonnes.
In 1885, five countries along the river
signed an agreement of quite another
sort,the Salmon Treaty.The International
Salmon Commission was set up to pro-
tect the fish, which were vanishing from
the river as a result of pollution and dams
t h at prevented them from migr at i n g .
Salmon swim out to sea when they are
about 18 months old and return to the
place where they were born to spawn at
the age of four or five years.The countries
along the Rhine decided to encourage the
introduction of young salmon into the
river.
But during the nineteenth century,
major civil engineering projects were built
in and around the river without any prior
b i l ateral agr e e m e n t s. Decisions we r e
taken and work done which threatened
neighbouring countries or towns further
downstream. In 1807, the Grand Duchy
of Baden (stretching from Basel to
Mannheim and later absorbed into
Wu rt e m burg) unilaterally decided to
canalise part of the river. The German
hydraulic engineer in charge, Jo h a n n
Tulla, straightened out its course, increa-
sing the water flow. Those “ i m p r ove-
ments” had a disastrous impact on the
water table of the upper Rhine plain,
whose level fell. The softwood forests
were no longer regularly flooded, a featu-
re of the river’s plain, and dried out.
Joining forces
against pollution
The Grand Canal of Alsace, which
France began in 1920, was also built
without consulting neighbouring coun-
tries. The decision was made by the vic-
tors of World War I as part of the Treaty of
Versailles. The canal enabled France to
build 10 hydroelectric plants and dams
between Basel and Strasbourg, not to
mention others on tributary rivers, which
blocked the movement of migratory fish.
The waterway, which was widened in
1950, lowered the level of the Rhine.
The river did not become Europe’s
cesspit until the mid-twentieth century.
Huge amounts of liquid waste, mostly
from towns, farms and expanding indus-
tries, were dumped into the river with
impunity. The level of phosphates from
fertilisers and household products such as
detergents reached alarming levels. The
fish population dwindled and in 1935 sal-
mon vanished entirely. It was also increa-
singly difficult to draw drinkable water
from the river, and it often smelt like car-
bolic acid and tasted salty.
After World War II, most European
states refused to negotiate with Germany.
But, unlike what happened in 1919, the
idea of a joint effort to ensure the future
of the Rhine gained ground. In 1946, the
Netherlands asked Switzerland to take
part in a discussion on pollution in the
river.
The participants settled for a new
international conference on salmon in
Basel in 1948, when it was noted that the
great fish really had disappeared from the
A COMMISSION 
F OR THE DA NUBE
The 2,857-kilometer Danube, Europe’s
second-longest river after the Volga, starts
in Germany and irrigates Austria, Slovakia,
H u n g a ry, Croatia, the Fe d e ral Republic of
Yugoslavia, Romania, Bulgaria, Moldova and
Ukraine before flowing into the Black Sea.
After several unsuccessful attempts, a
Danube Commission based on the Rhine
model was set up in Vienna in 1992.  An inter-
national convention on cross-border pollution
and environmental preservation was signed in
Sofia (Bulgaria) in 1994 and entered into force
four years later.
The Danube’s hydrogra p h i cal basin
stretches out over 817,000 square kilometers
and drains parts of a dozen countries.  Some of
them—Switzerland, Italy, Poland, Albania and
Macedonia—do not feel directly concerned and
have not joined the Commission.
At the present time, the Danube is less pol-
luted than the Rhine was in the 1970s. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
LE RHIN N’EST PAS
UN LONG FL EUVE TRA NQUIL L E
The Rhine flows down from two Alpine springs in
S w i tzerland’s Grisons region. One of them feeds
the anterior Rhine (Vorderrhein), the other the pos-
terior Rhine (Hinterrhein). They converge at the Swiss
village of Reichenau to become the Alpine Rhine,
which forms the border between Switzerland and
Austria before crossing Lake Constance. After the
famous 25-metre-high Schaffhouse Falls, the river
becomes the High Rhine (Hochrhein) and flows west,
where it demarcates the border between Germany
and Switz e r l a n d .
Downstream from Basel, the river turns north
and becomes the Upper Rhine (Oberrhein) for
the next 300 kilometers or so. Then it briefly
forms the border between Switzerland and
France and, for the next 180 kilometers, between
France and Germany and, finally, between seve-
ral German states (Länder). At Mainz, the river
turns west again, then north at Bingen. This is the
Middle Rhine (Mittelrhein), which crosses the
Rhine mountains for 100 kilometers. 
At Bonn, the river becomes the Lower Rhine
(Niederrhein), which, upon reaching the Dutch
border near Emmerich, turns west once more
and splits up into several waterways to form the
Rhine Delta, into which the Meuse also flows. 
From Reichenau to the North Sea, the Rhine is
1,320 kilometers long. The river’s hydrographical
basin stretches out over approximately 250,000
square kilometers that are home to 51 million
people and cover parts of Switzerland, Austria,
Germany, France, Luxembourg and the
Netherlands. The Rhine’s many branches include
the Aare in Switzerland, the Ill in France, and the
Kinzig, Neckar, Main, Lahn, Mosel, Ruhr, Lippe
and smaller tributaries in Germany. ■
P L A N E T
10 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
Rhine. The need to set up a permanent
intergovernmental body to handle general
pollution issues then became clear and
the Intern ational Commission for the
Protection of the Rhine (ICPR) was esta-
blished on June 11, 1950 at a meeting of
representatives from the countries along
the river (plus Luxembourg) that agreed
to fund it.
The results were slow in coming.
Water pollution steadily wo rsened for
over 20 years. But at least countries had
decided to take regular samples of the
Rhine’s water, which led to a system to
monitor water quality along the river’s
entire length.
The persistence
of hard metals
In 1963, the first draft agreement to
clean up the Rhine was signed in Berne.
The same year, the ICPR was given a per-
manent headquart e rs , first in Lux-
embourg and from 1964 in Koblenz.
Since then, a secretariat has collected and
distributed valuable data on the river’s
condition and drafted progress reports on
various ecological problems.
The Commission operates in a rather
innovative way, which experience has pro-
ved to be useful. Environment ministers
and officials from each member state
gather at ICPR meetings on a regular
basis. Decisions are taken jointly and each
country, Land or regional government
adopts the ensuing measures. But neither
the ICPR nor its secretariat has any exe-
cutive or coercive power to speak of, such
as the authority to order the construction
of new fa c i l i t i e s. S i m i l a r l y, t h e
Commission draws up env i r o n m e n t a l
projects for the Rhine, but if adopted they
are funded and implemented by each
member country. The secretariat simply
m o n i t o rs their application along the
river’s entire length.
In 1976, the European Community
(later the European Union) joined the
ICPR, lending it more authority, and sub-
sequent measures began to show results.
Between 1970 and 1974, the river’s oxy-
gen content was still between only two
and four milligrams per litre—too low to
support the growth of any organism.
But between 1970 and 1990, t h e
countries along the river spent $38.5 bil-
lion on building a string of purification
plants. The oxygen level steadily rose and
some of the river’s biodiversity returned.
However, experts noted that the purifica-
tion plants did their work after the pollu-
tion had occurred, limiting the effects
without tackling the causes. Furthermore,
S W I TZ ERLA ND
0 100 km
V IL LAGE - NEUF
SELTZ
KO BL ENZ / M O SEL KO BL ENZ / RHEIN
BIMMEN / LO BI T H
KA MPEN
V UREN
H AGES T E IN
REK IN GER
FRA NCE
A US T RI A
GERM A N Y
LUX EMBOURG
NET HERLA NDS
Le k
Wa a l
N e d e r - R i j n
L i p p e
I j s s e l
R u h r
Wu p p e r
S i e g
La h n
M a i nN a h e
N e c ka r
Aa re
Vo rd e r r h e i n
B o d e n s e e
H i n t e r
r h e i n
S a r re
S a u e r
S a a r
I l l
R h i n e
R h i n e
M o s e l l e
M o s e l
A h r
E rf t
AN IN T ERN AT IONAL WAT ERWAY
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
P L A N E T
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 11
the plants could only eliminate a small
amount of the heavy metals in the water.
“The river has some ability to clean
itself, but this has been over-estimated,”
says Anne Schulte-Wülwer-Leidig, a bio-
l o gist in Koblenz. So the Rhine still
contained high amounts of heavy metals,
such as mercury, cadmium and zinc, and
harmful substances, including polychlo-
robiphenyls (PCBs),benzene and atrasine
(from pesticides).
In 1976, the ICPR member-countries
signed a convention on chemicals that
ranked some as dangerous and put them
on a “black” or a “grey list.” Maximum
levels were set for cadmium, mercury and
other particularly harmful substances.
Those steps were taken at a time when
manufacturers were able to acquire tech-
nology to eliminate or separate out dan-
gerous toxins during the production
stage. Previously, they could only be filte-
red out at the end.
That same year, the countries along
the river signed an agreement on chlo-
rides to reduce the Rhine’s salt content
from 500 to 200 milligrams per litre along
the German-Dutch border. The high
level, which spoiled drinking water, was
mainly due to waste from potash mines in
Alsace (slated for closing in 2004) and in
Lorraine flushing into the Rhine and the
Moselle,as well as to chemical waste from
plants along the river Main.The salt level
in the river Weser, polluted by potash
discharges from the Werra, sometimes
reached 3,000 mg/litre.
People living along the Rhine were in
for a terrible shock in November 1986
when a fire broke out at the Sandoz che-
mical plant at Schweizerhalle, near Basel.
The water that firefighters used to put out
the blaze flushed huge amounts of insecti-
cides and pesticides into the ri ve r ,s p a r k i n g
an ecological cat a s t r o p h e . E nv i r o n m e n t a l
awareness rose and the affected populat i o n
and their representat i ves demanded that
m a n u fa c t u r e rs take much tougher action
against pollution.
“The Basel disaster enabled the ICPR
to set higher goals in its 1987 Rhine
Action Programme for Ecologi c a l
Rehabilitation,” says Koos Wieriks, of the
ICPR secretari at . Commitments we r e
made to cut the amounts of the most
hazardous pollutants in half by 1995.
Many experts thought this target could
never be reached, but ICPR samples sho-
wed that from 1985 to 1992, mercury in
the river at the German town of Bimmen-
Lobith, near the Dutch border, fell from
six to 3.2 tonnes, cadmium from nine to
5.9 tonnes, zinc from 3,600 to 1,900
tonnes, atrasine from 10 to 3.7 tonnes
and PCBs from 390 to 90 kilograms.
Special chemical purification plants
were built up- and downstream from
Schweizerhalle. “The 1987 programme
won credence for the idea that the Rhine
was a total ecological system,” s ay s
Schulte-Wülwer-Leidig. Under the pro-
gramme, the Rhine was to become a place
where salmon, p i k e , p e r c h , trout and
other fish could thrive once more. But to
achieve that goal, the water quality had to
be further improved,an objective that was
reached before the 2000 target dat e .
Industrial development once transformed the Rhine into a veritable wasteland.
‘The Basel disaster 
enabled the IC PR to set 
higher goals 
in its 19 87 Rhine Action
P r o g ramme for Ecologica l
R e h a b i l i ta t i o n ’ .
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
P L A N E T
12 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
Agricultural fertilisers are one of the river’s main pollution sources.
Since 1991, more than a million young
fish have been released into the Rhine and
its branches.
But the troubles of the migrating fish
were not over. In 1996, the first salmon
caught in the river for many years was
hooked just before the Iffezheim dam,
near Baden-Baden. The fish came from
the North Sea but because of the dam
could not reach the branch where it was
born. Salmon only spawn in the places
where they started life.
With the help of ecology movements,
the reluctance of power station owners to
build costly bridges or complex networks
of passageways for the salmon is gradual-
ly breaking dow n . Such facilities are
already under construction at Iffezheim,
at the confluence with the river Ill (which
has no dams on it), at a cost of about $6
million, and at Gambsheim, in Alsace.
Basel residents are being consulted about
planned changes in the landscape that
would help the salmon migrate. Egon
Oberacker, a professional fisherman in
the Swiss town of Nordbaden, is pleased
that fish will be more plentiful now. But,
he says, “we still can’t live off fishing
alone, as we once did.”
The idea of an integr ated ecosystem
t h at will enable a rich va riety of animal and
plant life to thri ve in the Rhine and its
branches once more has come a long way.
In 1998, the ministers of the Commission
set targets to restore natural areas as part
of a global ecosystem stretching from the
mouth of the Rhine to the Jura, the A l p s ,
the Rhine mountain range, the old soft-
wood forests of the flo o d p l a i n s , a n d
streams of the Rhineland-Pa l at i n at e , t h e
Black Forest and the Vo s g e s.
M e a n w h i l e , not all the pollution pro-
blems have been solve d . One of the most
s e rious is in the Rhine delta’s huge basin in
the Netherlands, where tox i n - filled mud
dredged from the port of Rotterdam has
been dumped since the 1970s. C o n t a m i n a-
tion levels are falling now, but several of the
old toxins in the ri ve r ’s sediment are only
ve ry slowly being eliminat e d . And all along
the Rhine, the main source of pollution is
still fa rm fert i l i s e rs , which seep into the ri ve r
e ve ry time it rains. ■
T HE TENNESSEE
PRECEDEN T
One of the oldest interstate bodies set up
around a river is the Tennessee Valley
Authority (TVA) in the United States.  It was
created on May 18, 1933 by the government of
President Franklin D. Roosevelt as part of the
New Deal’s far-reaching public works program-
me.  Since then, many federal and local bodies
have delegated authority to the TVA.  The
hydrological basin of the 1,600-kilometer-long
Tennessee River, a branch of the Ohio, drains
sections of Virginia, North Carolina, Georgia,
Alabama, Tennessee and Kentucky.
Those states and the federal government
set various priorities when the TVA was set up,
including bringing the river’s erratic water
levels under control to prevent flooding, buil-
ding a series of hydroelectric plants and brin-
ging electricity to remote areas.  Twenty-one
dams and six reservoirs were built.  The entire
system enabled the growth and modernisation
of farming and the reforestation of some areas.
Today, the TVA is considered an outstan-
ding example of regional planning. ■
In 1996, the first salmon
caught in the river 
for many years was hooked 
just before the Iffezheim dam,
near Baden-Baden
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 13
Stress-free learning? By some estimates, at least one million American children are home schooled.
■
Twenty ye a rs ago, C h ristopher and
Eileen Herman would have technically
been breaking the law. Opting against
c o nventional schooling, the parents are tea-
ching their two children at their home in
Washington stat e ,where until 1985, the only
legal way to home school was to hold a stat e
teaching license—something they both lack.
But today, the Hermans not only can
teach their children at home without fear of
p r o s e c u t i o n , they also have an extensive arr ay
of resources and supports at their disposal.
They belong to three local organizations of
parents who educate their children at home,
attend state-wide home schoolers ’ c o nve n-
t i o n s , and regularly cull advice from similar
families on the Intern e t .“Just about eve ry b o d y
k n ows someone who’s home schooling,”M rs.
H e rman say s.“ People may still think it’s kind
of odd, but there isn’t as much suspicion or
hostility any m o r e .”
Legal recognition
I n d e e d , the Hermans are part of one of the
fastest gr owing educational trends in the Uni-
ted Stat e s.By some estimat e s , the number of
home schooled children in the country has
gr own from roughly 50,000 in the mid-1980s
to at least one million today. ( O t h e rs peg the
p o p u l ation as high as 1.8 million).While that
still represents at most only three percent of
the total number of the country ’s school-aged
c h i l d r e n , the rapid rise in the popularity of
home schooling deserves notice.It has quickly
become the second most popular form of non-
g ove rnment sponsored education in the U. S . ,
n ow outranked only by the schools affil i at e d
with the Roman Catholic church.
“One big accomplishment of the move-
ment is that they’ve made home schooling a
viable educational option,” s ays Mitchell Ste-
ve n s , a sociologist at Hamilton College in
C l i n t o n , N. Y.and the author of an upcoming
book on home schooling.“It now has a small
place in the menu of educational choices in
this country.”
The forces behind the movement are com-
p l e x , and the bigger it gets, the harder it
becomes to describe a “ t y p i c a l ”home schoo-
l e r. Most experts see two ve ry different
l i n e a g e s.One was born in the late 1960s from
the altern at i ve school move m e n t , whose fol-
l owe rs believe children learn best when libe-
r ated from the ri gid structures of form a l
schooling and allowed to pursue their ow n
i n t e r e s t s.The other was largely fueled by the
c o n c e rns of some conservat i ve Protestant
families who—at about the same time—began
to wo rry that the public schools could no lon-
ger ensure the proper form ation of their chil-
d r e n ’s character.“Both are skeptical of the
bu r e a u c r atic organization of educat i o n ,”S t e-
vens say s. “ I t ’s a matter of, ‘I don’t wa n t
someone else taking care of my children.’ ”
Until the 1980s, home schooling in the
United States was still largely an undergr o u n d
a c t i v i t y,without legal recognition. But as the
number of practitioners gr e w, judges and
p r o s e c u t o rs became more willing to accept
t h at home schooling was permitted under
legal provisions allowing children who we r e n ’t
in school to be ‘otherwise instru c t e d .’ In 1983,
a d vo c ates formed the Home School Legal
Defense A s s o c i ation to push the issue in stat e
l e gi s l atures and to provide legal representat i o n
to individual home schooling fa m i l i e s.
To d ay, the practice is recognized as legal
in all 50 stat e s , although its regulation va ri e s
gr e at l y. I d a h o, for example,places ve ry few res-
t rictions on home schooling parents,not eve n
asking that they inform any state or local offi-
cials of their intentions. O r e g o n ,m e a n w h i l e ,
m a n d ates that such families periodically have
a ‘ q u a l i fied neutral pers o n ’ test their chil-
d r e n . N owhere in the U. S . are parents now
required—as they once were in Wa s h i n g t o n
s t ate—to be licensed teachers.A few states call
for parents to either have some college edu-
c ation or follow a home schooling ‘ q u a l i fie r ’
c o u rse at a community college.
S t ate laws often stipulate the number of
d ays of instruction and the general content
areas to be covered by fa m i l i e s. But while
these provisions usually call on parents to
keep records of their children’s progr e s s ,t h e y
are generally not required to turn these ove r
DOING IT 
T HEIR OWN WAY
◗ Jeff A r c h e r
Whether for religious reasons or out of a strong desire to do things differently, a growing
number of parents in the United States are choosing to educate their children at home
◗ Staff Writer at Education Week (U.S.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
14 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
to a gove rnment body. “ E ven the most ri g o-
rously regulated states in A m e rica have some
flexibility—a recognition that your child may
be learning at a different pace,” s ays Pat ri c k
Fa r e n g a , president of Holt A s s o c i at e s , a Cam-
b ridge (Massachusetts)-based publisher of
home schooling mat e ri a l s. S t ate and local
school districts va ry in how they accommo-
d ate home-schooled children. In some cases,
they are allowed to part i c i p ate in field trips or
sign up for certain classes while in others ,
school officials do not let them join any extra-
c u rricular activities.
Although conservat i ve Protestants appear
to make up the largest single bloc of home
s c h o o l e rs , the movement is dive rs i f y i n g .I n
recent ye a rs ,C at h o l i c, M u s l i m , and Je w i s h
home schoolers have formed their own orga-
n i z at i o n s ,and the practice continues to at t r a c t
a substantial number of more secular-min-
ded fa m i l i e s. S u rveys by the National Home
E d u c ation Research Institute in Salem (Ore-
gon) suggest that religion still is the most com-
mon reason for home schooling, but the
research centre also has identified five other
strong motivat i o n s :c o n c e rn about the aca-
demic quality of local conventional schools;
a belief that the best education also is the most
i n d i v i d u a l i z e d ; the desire to enhance rela-
tionships among family members ; an at t e m p t
to mitigate the negat i ve influences of peer
p r e s s u r e ; and wo rries that schools are beco-
ming increasingly unsafe. O f t e n , these rea-
Perhaps one of the best indications of
success is home schooling’s gr owing reco-
gnition by A m e rican colleges and unive rs i-
t i e s.The Home School Legal Defense A s s o-
c i ation recently surve yed more than 500
institutions of higher learning and found
t h at all but two had admissions policies for
e va l u ating home schooled students who lack
traditional high school records. M a ny col-
leges now accept evidence of student pro-
gress prepared by parents, p o rtfolios of their
wo r k , and standardized tests in place of
transcripts.
Despite its gr owing acceptance, p a r e n t s
still are sometimes brought before judges in
d i s a greements over whether they’ve corr e c t l y
f o l l owed state regulat i o n s. In a highly-publi-
cized case last ye a r , a Ve rmont home schoo-
ler was jailed for two weeks for refusing to let
s t ate examiners eva l u ate her 15-year-old son.
S t ate officials argued that they needed to make
sure the boy—reputed by local school offi-
cials to have learning defic i e n c i e s — was being
a d e q u ately served at home.
While public approval of home schoo-
ling has spread, it isn’t unive rs a l . A 1997
survey co-sponsored by the Gallup polling
organization and the international educa-
tion organization Phi Delta Kappa showed
that 57 per cent of Americans think home
schooling is a ‘bad thing’—though this wa s
d own from the 73 per cent reported 12
ye a rs earlier.The National Education A s s o-
sons ove r l a p.
Home schooling techniques va ry as much
as the motivations for doing it. In a country
with no national curri c u l u m ,s t ates are res-
ponsible for setting educational standards,
which are generally only loosely applied to
home schoolers. Parents generally put toge-
ther their instructional plan themselve s.H u n-
dreds of publishers now produce mat e ri a l s
geared toward home schoolers , their wa r e s
sold through the World Wide We b , in specia-
lized magazines and conve n t i o n s.They refle c t
a wide arr ay of educational approaches and
p h i l o s o p h i e s , from non-denominational cor-
respondence courses to mat e rials “ built upon
the firm foundation of scriptural tru t h ”a n d
not the “ p s e u d o - s c i e n t i fic jargon of the secu-
lar educat i o n i s t s.”
Trust in public schools
The few large-scale research projects that
h ave been carried out in the United Stat e s
suggest that the home schooled children
whose families part i c i p ated in the studies tend
to perform well above the national average on
standardized tests. But many researchers are
hesitant to make too much of such fin d i n g s ,
because of the obvious self-selection problem.
F u rt h e r ,m a ny agree that a substantial num-
ber of home schoolers remain undergr o u n d ,
refusing to be counted by state or local autho-
ri t i e s , and making it difficult to reach conclu-
s i o n s.
Keeping in tune: taking part in extra-curricular activities outside the home is just one way of interacting with other children.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
W O R L D  O F  L E A R N I N G
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 15
■
The continent that has adopted a
single curr e n cy is a long way from
unity on home educat i o n . A l t h o u g h
d ata remains scarce, s u p p o rt groups in seve-
ral countries claim that they are receiving
increasing numbers of requests from parents
looking for altern at i ves to formal school sys-
t e m s , a movement being matched by legi s-
l at i ve attempts to curtail its practice.
According to Amanda Petrie, one of a
handful of European researchers on the
subject,there is an underlying thread run-
ning through recent legi s l at i ve changes sug-
gesting that “if you are not in school, you
are not learn i n g .” In Ireland, an Educat i o n
( We l fare) Bill put forward for discussion in
1999 treats home education as a school
attendance problem,rather than as a right
guaranteed by the Constitution, w h i c h
declares that the pri m a ry educator of the
child is the fa m i l y. With the expressed
intention of cracking down on sects, t h e
French parliament voted a new law in
December 1998 obliging parents to follow
the national curriculum more closely and
i n s p e c t o rs to visit their children once a ye a r
in the home.The law was passed by a hand-
ful of deputies without consulting with
r e p r e s e n t at i ves of the home education com-
m u n i t y. For Elyane Delmarès of the French
support group Les Enfants d’Abord, “it’s a
bogus argument. The state already has a
whole arsenal of weapons to fight sects.
This is really about the state having a stron-
ger hold on education.”
S u p p o rt groups say these controls cast
home education in a negat i ve light and
r e flect misconceptions about how learn i n g
takes place outside school. For Pe t ri e ,i m p o-
sing a national curriculum and allowing ins-
p e c t o rs into the home are two examples.T h e
first assumes that “the state knows what edu-
c ation is, takes a certain form u l a , and if yo u
apply this form u l a , your child is going to be
fin e .” The second discri m i n ates against
people who are “not upper middle classes
with reams of bookcases in the home.”
The value of
informal learning
But even in countries where the prac-
tice is tightly restri c t e d , ambiguity often
p r e va i l s. In Spain, where schooling is com-
puslory up to 16 years of age—special cir-
cumstances aside—a court ruled in 1999
in favour of parents from Almeria who are
e d u c ating their seve n - year-old child. I n
G e rm a ny, where home education is illegal,
s e veral families have gone to court and paid
fines but they have been allowed to conti-
nue the practice. After returning from a
posting in Micronesia, Dorothee Becker
and her husband found that their two chil-
dren were unable to adapt to the German
school system. “It didn’t offer the va ri e t y
we had hoped for, especially in languages
and science,” s ays Becker, who has been to
c o u rt once. In the Netherlands, a u t h o ri t i e s
h ave refused 90 per cent of homeschooling
r e q u e s t s , acccording to Syne Fo n k , head of
the support group Syntax. In response, a
growing number of parents are starting up
their own private schools.
Increasing research on home educat i o n
would be a first step to breaking through
some of the misconceptions surrounding the
fie l d , still widely shunned by the academic
c o m m u n i t y. Studies are most advanced in
the UK,which has Europe’s strongest home
education community, with an estimated
10,000 children.There can be one hundred
different reasons for making the commit-
m e n t ,r a n ging from a simple question of phi-
l o s o p hy, to concern about bullying and beha-
vioural problems at school to religious
c o nv i c t i o n s. Alan T h o m a s , a visiting fellow
at the Unive rsity of London Institute of Edu-
c at i o n ,c a rried out in depth-research on 100
families in Britain and Australia to prov i d e
one of the first detailed accounts of how
parents go about the task of teaching their
children at home.Besides shorter lessons and
extra individual at t e n t i o n ,Thomas noted the
far-reaching impact of informal and shared
l e a rning and the importance of conve rs at i o n
that is all too often lacking in school. He
found that children had “high confidence in
their ability to learn ,high self-esteem and are
socially mature in a way many who have been
to school are not. T h e y ’ ve not experi e n c e d
fa i l u r e . If you don’t understand something,
you deal with it there and then.”
Pe t rie takes the debate one step furt h e r ,
emphasizing that the right to home educa-
tion should be a principle of democracy. “ I
think it comes down to a question of how
much confidence the state has in the parent’s
ability to know what is right for their ow n
c h i l d r e n .The debate hinges on that .” ■
EUROPEAN DISUNI TY
◗ Cynthia Guttman
Parents throughout Europe are becoming bolder about educating their children at home, 
even if it means defending their rights in court
◗ UNESCO Courier journalist
+ …
Educating Children at Home, Alan Thomas,
Cassell, London, 1999
www.worldzone.net/lifestyles/homeducation: 
a site drawn up by Amanda Petrie that
provides information on legal aspects of
home education in Europe
www.rama.1901.org/vens for information on the
French home education movement
Les Enfants d’Abord is organizing a home
education conference from Aug. 26 to Sept. 2,
2000. For information: 33-4-70 59 81 23
c i at i o n , the country ’s largest teachers ’
u n i o n , also maintains a policy stat e m e n t
arguing that , “home schooling progr a m s
cannot provide the student with a compre-
h e n s i ve education experi e n c e .”The Nat i o-
nal A s s o c i ation of Elementary School Pri n-
cipals has issued a similar warning, adding
that government authorties should “make
c e rtain that those who exercise these
options are held strictly accountable for the
academic achievement and social/emotio-
nal gr owth of children.” A major part of
their concern is that home schooled stu-
dents may not learn enough about relating
to children from other backgrounds.
Home schoolers themselves disagr e e
about how big the movement will gr ow.
Some predict a straight-line gr owth for
many more years, while others see it soon
reaching a point of diminishing return s.
Polls suggest that most Americans remain
s at i s fied with their local public schools,
which educate about 90 per cent of the
c o u n t ry ’s students. But most observe rs
agree that, however large, home schooling
has established itself as a lasting feature in
the landscape of A m e rican educat i o n . A s
parent and publisher Patrick Farenga puts
it, “the concept of education is no longer
held to the schools like monks in a monas-
tery.” ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Acentury of feminism has failed to overturn several millennia of
p a t r i a r c h y : proof is the fate of women in many parts of the world today
( p. 1 7 ) . But from unrelenting battles to fragile victories (pp. 1 8 - 2 0 ) ,b y
the end of the twentieth century women had learned to defend their welfare
and their interests. The two sexes, they say, are different but have equal
rights and responsibilities.
Little by little,women have undermined the old order that sealed their inequi-
table fate.By standing in the forefront of struggles against apartheid and male
d o m i n a t i o n , South African women are considered as role models: the power
they have won has enabled them to impose laws sanctioning the violence to
which they are subjected (pp. 2 0 - 2 1 ) .I ranian women have not yet reached that
p o i n t ,but they are seizing every opportunity, from education to the ballot box ,
to strengthen their rights (pp.22-23 ). The struggle for equality in the work-
place (pp. 23-24) and reproductive rights (pp. 24-25) are other aspects of
w o m e n ’s emancipation that are still high on the agenda, five years after the
Beijing women’s conference.
Despite their massive and henceforth world-wide mobilisation, women still
encounter obstacles to political participation, where they remain a tiny mino-
rity (pp.28-29 and 30-31).Kept back by mentalities and societies that are moving
ahead at a snail’s pace, in the private sphere they are negotiating a new sha-
ring of time with men (pp.2 6 - 2 7 ) .Following a path opened up in northern Europe,
women in countries such as India (pp. 32-33) have obtained quotas that
ensure more democratic representation.
In South Korea and elsewhere, they have created political breeding grounds
to motivate and train the leaders of tomorrow
( p p. 3 4 - 3 5 ) .
A genuine renewal of political leadership
seems to be under wa y. It promises to be one of
the more important breakthroughs of the century
that has just begun (pp. 35-36 and 37).
■
Fo c u s Wo m e n ’s long 
m a rch to 
p o w e r
C o n t e n t s
O p i n i o n
1 7 No pro g ress without a secular society
Taslima Nasreen
1 | Fo rceful voices
1 8 One battle after another
Sophie Bessis
2 0 South A f r i c a : a strategic ascent
Shireen Hassim
2 2 Emancipation under the veils
Siavosh Ghazi
2 3 S w e d e n : court battles for equal pay
Elisabet Ornerborg
2 4 Pe r u :s kewed planning
Natalia Ta r n a w i e c k i
2 | The political are n a
2 6 For a fair sharing of time
Rosiska Darcy de Oliveira
2 8 U n finished democracy 
3 0 A woman in the lion’s den
Hinde Ta a r j i
3 2 I n d i a ’s nurseries of politics
Mrinal Pa n d e
3 4 South Ko re a ’s campaign schools
Glenn Manarin
3 5 Betty Friedan: debunking 
the mystique of politics
Judy Mann
3 7 Closing ra n k s
Yvette Roudy
16 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 17
Eve ry day, women continue to be victims of rape,
t r a f fic k i n g, a c i d - t h r ow i n g, d ow ry deaths and
other kinds of tort u r e . At the opening of this
new century, women are still not considered as equal
human beings in many parts of the wo r l d .R e l i gion and
patriarchy continue to have an all-encroaching hold
on their live s , maintaining and justifying their age-old
oppression.In some South Asian societies,this hold
is even increasing.
I do not believe that there can be real equality in
a society dominated by religion. Western countries
speak repeatedly about the necessity of economic
d e velopment to alleviate pove rt y. But this is not
enough.Societies such as Saudi Arabia may be eco-
nomically developed, but women are deprived of all
ri g h t s. The supremacy of religion is incompat i b l e
with freedom of expression, wo m e n ’s rights and
d e m o c r a cy. This is why I see religion as the main
enemy of women’s development.
We have to act on several fronts at once. F i rst of all,
i m p r oving access to educat i o n . In a society like Ban-
g l a d e s h ,80 per cent of women are illiterat e . For centu-
ries women have been taught they are the slaves of men.
It is ve ry hard to change their minds,to make them awa r e
of their oppression, to gi ve them a sense of their inde-
p e n d e n c e . This educational effort has to go hand in
hand with a secular feminist movement in society. S u c h
m ovements have to start within the country and they
cannot take hold when people are uneducated and una-
ware of their oppression. I’m not sure you can accom-
plish much from the outside, except to expose in the
media the atrocities women in all too many countries fa c e
in their day to day live s.
In Muslim countri e s , this movement is emergi n g,
but ve ry timidly, and it has a slim margin of maneuve r.
It has the uphill task of fighting for the repeal of religi o u s
l aws and the introduction of a uniform civil code. So fa r ,
it  tends to be constituted by a few individual feminists
who are forced to be diplomat i c, to compromise with
f u n d a m e n t a l i s t s , be they men or wo m e n . But they are
t rying to change the system,step by step, and it will take
a ve ry long time. People are not yet ready to do away
with religious laws that impact upon eve ry aspect of
s o c i e t y, from education and health to the workplace and
the home.
For wo m e n ’s status to change, we also need enligh-
tened leaders who believe in equality. In countries such
as mine, women with a strong voice do not have the
s u p p o rt of political leaders , whether they be men or
wo m e n .Look at the countries in which women are in
p o l i t i c s , or even heads of stat e . Does it follow that
women in those countries are emancipated? Because
of long-standing vested interests, such leaders continue
to back measures that oppress wo m e n .They are not
i d e o l o gically committed to changing these condi-
t i o n s. In South A s i a ,most of the women who become
heads of state are religi o u s , and like men, they adhere
to the religious objectives of the Establishment. I am
the victim of a country where the prime minister is a
wo m a n . Because I went one step too far in denoun-
cing religion and the oppression that it keeps wo m e n
u n d e r , I had to leave my country.
I have seen women oppose me when I talked
about women’s rights. They said straight out that
God did not believe that women should have so
m a ny ri g h t s.And I have met men in my country who
are against what is said in the religious scriptures and
b e l i e ve in equality between men and wo m e n . I t
does not depend on gender. It depends on one’s
c o n s c i e n c e . Muslim women who are we a ring the ve i l
and glorifying their subservience are obviously not
going to better the lives of the oppressed.
Until a society is not based on religion and wo m e n
are considered equal to men before the law, I do not
think that politics will advance the cause of wo m e n .I n
We s t e rn countri e s , women are educat e d , they are
t r e ated equally, they have access to jobs. In these
c o n d i t i o n s , their part i c i p ation in politics has a meaning.
E d u c at i o n , a secular feminist move m e n t , a n d
l e a d e rs—both men and women—committed to equa-
lity and justice.This is what it will take to change the
dire conditions which too many women still fa c e
t o d ay. It will take a ve ry long time, but we are here to
work towards that end. ■
O p i n i o n
◗ Taslima Nasreen
No pro g re s s
without 
a s e c u l a r
s o c i e t y
◗ Born in Bangladesh,
Ms. Nasreen has led a twin
career as a doctor and writer.
She is the author of six novels,
several collections of poetry
and essays, and an
autobiography. Her works have
been translated into over a
dozen languages. Two of her
novels, Shame and My
Girlhood, were banned in her
country, where Islamic
fundamentalists issued a fatwa
against her. Accused by her
government of blasphemy, Ms.
Nasreen has been living in exile
since 1994.She has received
numerous international awards,
including India’s Ananda
Award,the European
Parliament’s Sakharov Prize and
the International Humanist
Award from the United States.
The one whose wife
dies is lucky. But not
so the man whose
cow dies.
Bengali pro v e r b
Until a society is not based 
on religion and women 
a re considered equal to men
b e f o re the law, I do not think 
that politics will advance 
the cause of women
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
We often hear that this will be the century
of women, in light of the tremendous
strides that have been made in the past
thirty years or so. Although it is far too soon to
confirm this prediction, it can safely be asserted
that the twentieth century was marked by their
struggle to leave the home,where they were confi-
ned by the ancestral division of roles along gender
lines. Around the world,women have campaigned
to win the rights they have been denied and to
build, side-by-side with men, the future of the
planet.
True, such struggles had already been waged
in the past, although they were deliberately shun-
ned in official historical accounts. But the brief
revolts of this special “minority”, which accounts
for over half of humanity, did not change the
place of women in their societies. They may have
ruled the roost, sometimes enjoying undeniable
respect, but nevertheless they were still born to
serve men and bring their husbands’ descendants
into the world.
Education:
their first struggle
Yet, at the start of the twentieth century, the
traditional distribution of roles, seemingly legiti-
mised by every religion and frozen in a “natural”
order, began to crumble under the two-pronged
assault of modernisation and women’s struggle
for their collective emancipation. They waged
many battles to gradually obtain, despite set-
backs, a change in their status—which is still far
from achieved.
The first struggle of the twentieth century was
for education. In 1861, a young woman gradua-
ted in France with a baccalaureate, a highschool
leaving exam, for the first time. In 1900, the first
female university was founded in Japan.The same
year, girls won the right to secondary education in
Egypt and the first girls’school opened in Tunisia.
Young women who could made the most of these
new educational opportunities, not only to beco-
me better household managers and good educa-
18 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
◗ Freelance journalist 
based in Paris
tors for their children, as the main discourse of
the period suggests, but also to do something
unprecedented: to enter the forbidden spheres of
public life, to exercise citizenship and to partici-
pate in politics.
Throughout the twentieth century, women
waged a battle on two fronts: by fighting for their
own rights and taking part in the major social and
political emancipation movements. In 1917, the
Russian Bolshevik Alexandra Kollontaï became
the world’s first woman cabinet minister. African
American Rosa Parks triggered the civil rights
movement by refusing to give up her seat to a
white man on an Alabama bus in 1955. Djamila
Boupacha was a heroine of Algeria’s war for inde-
pendence.Women were entirely committed to the
goals of these movements but seldom received
anything in return for participating in them.Once
their countries’ new masters took power, they
often found themselves sent back to the kitchen.
But they continued fighting for their own rights,
and it is on this front that they achieved their
greatest victories.
The earliest feminist movements, which first
appeared in the West in the late nineteenth centu-
ry, focused on workplace and civil rights issues.
I n d u s t ry needed wo m e n ’s labour, which wa s
underpaid in comparison with that of their male
counterparts. ‘Equal pay for equal work!’ deman-
ded American and European women, who began
setting up their own trade unions and organizing
strikes. They made unquestionable strides, but
after more than one century of struggle, most
women around the world still earn less pay for
equal work.
The right to vote
The second objective of the twentieth centu-
ry’s pioneers was participation in public life,
which hinged first and foremost on having the
right to vote. The struggle was long and some-
times violent, as shown by the British “suffra-
g e t t e s ” who demonstrated in the streets or
Chinese women who made their demands heard
One battle after another
◗ Sophie Bessis
Women fought for their rights throughout the twentieth century. In the past severa l
d e c a d e s, their struggle has truly become global, but all is far from won
1 Fo rceful voices
For a long time I have
hesitated to write 
a book on women. Th e
subject 
is irritating, especially to
w o m e n ; and it is not
n e w.
Simone de Beauvoir,
F rench writer (1908-1986)
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 19
by invading their country’s new parliament in
1912. Everywhere, the fierce resistance of the
political world progressively yielded to determi-
ned women’s movements.
Scandinavia is where women first won the
right to vote and to run for election, with Finland
leading the way in 1906. The First World War
t h rust them into the forefront, with most
European women winning the right to vote in
1918 and 1919, although French and Italian
women had to wait until after the Second World
War to at last be recognized as citizens. Outside
the West, women also organized to demand their
rights. Groups were founded in Turkey, Egypt and
India. In 1930, the first congress of women from
the Near and Middle East gathered in Damascus
to demand equality. Throughout this peri o d ,
women eve rywhere declared that , outside of
motherhood, they had the right to be just like
men, and that men could not deny them this
right.
Control over their
own bodies
For a while, women’s rights movements took a
back seat to the Second World War and liberation
struggles in the European colonies. The fight
against fascism and, after 1945, c o l o n i a l i s m ,
mobilized all their energy. Women distinguished
themselves in these struggles,but that did not suf-
fice to establish their rights as a gender. However,
the world continued to change.With independen-
ce, many women in the South won access to
schooling, salaried employment and, in a few
exceptional cases, the closed world of politics. In
Western countries, the post-war period saw them
enter the work force on a massive scale.The gap
between social reality and the discriminatory laws
defended by exclusively male power structures
grew wider.
In the West,the second generation of feminists
emerged in the wake of the libertarian move-
ments of 1968. Picking up where their elders left
off, they broadened the scope of their demands,
for late-twentieth century feminists no longer
aspired to the right to be “just like men”.
Challenging the claim of the “white male” to
represent universality, their goal was to achieve
equality while remaining distinct as women.The
women’s liberation movement that first emerged
in the American middle-class claimed the right to
control one’s own body. Feminists fought for
contraception and abortion rights in many coun-
tries where one or both were against the law, and
for autonomy and equality within the couple.
“The personal is political,” proclaimed women
inspired by Marxism and psychoanalysis.
“Workers of the world, who washes your socks?”
chanted demonstrators in the streets of Paris in
the 1970s. In France, the Veil law legalizing abor-
tion unleashed emotional debate in 1974.
Many Third World women could not identify
with the struggles being waged in the West and
insisted on leading their own battles at their own
pace. However, these Western feminist move-
ments breathed new life into the cause.
Recognizing the changes and proclaiming their
intention to accelerate them, the United Nations
declared 1975 “International Women’s Year”
and organized the first international women’s
conference in Mexico City.
Already proclaimed in the Unive rs a l
Declaration of Human Rights in 1948, sexual
equality was reasserted in 1979 by the
Convention on the Abolition of All Forms of
Discrimination Against Women, which became a
precious emancipation tool in the North as well
as the South. At UN conferences in Copenhagen
in 1980, Nairobi in 1985 and Beijing in 1995,
women from both hemispheres found common
ground, demanding the right to “have a child if I
want it, when I want it,” rejecting Malthusian
principles and claiming their place in political
In Munich, Germany, a poster printed for Women’s Day on March 8,1914 demands the right
to vote for women.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
South A f r i c a :
a s t rategic a s c e n t
◗ Shireen Hassim
Since the advent of their country’s first democratic government, women have imposed far-
reaching pieces of legislation. Making them effective remains an uphill battle
◗ Lecturer in Political Studies at the
University of Witwatersrand,and
member of the Gender and
Elections Reference Group
coordinated by the Electoral
Institute of South Africa.Also on
the advisory board of Womensnet
(www.womensnet.org) 
bodies that until then had decided the world’s
future without them, struggling against religious
fundamentalism that jeopardizes their modest
gains.
Misogyny of the
political class
Of course, the struggle of Kuwaiti women
against those who have denied them the right to
vote or Indian women against the forced abortion
of female fœtuses is not the same as American
women’s battle against their own fundamentalists
or French women’s campaign against the misogy-
ny of the political class.Women’s movements take
different approaches depending on the continent
and do not necessarily have the same priorities,
but the struggle has nonetheless become global
d u ring the past several decades. In the last
t we n t y - five ye a rs , women have gradually in-
creased their presence in public life, although it
can hardly be said that the doors are wide open
for them. From Africa to Asia, women’s organiza-
tions have multiplied and acquired experience.
But their victories remain incomplete and the
future is uncert a i n . From the nightmare of
Afghan women to the ways in which equality is
resisted in the so-called most advanced countries,
the obstacles show that there is still a long way to
go. Will women see the end of the struggle in this
century that has just begun, the one which sup-
posedly belongs to them? ■
Beijing Plus Five
Five years after a historic women’s conference in Beijing
that gathered some 30,000 participants from 189 coun-
tries, the United Nations General Assembly will be holding
a special session in New York from June 5-9,2 0 0 0 . The goal
of the meeting, entitled “Women 2000:Gender Equality,
Development and Peace for the Twenty-First Century,” is to
take stock of progress made in implementing the Platform
for Action adopted in 1995. Divided into 12 areas of critical
c o n c e r n , this set of commitments calls for economic oppor-
tunity and security for women, quality education and health
care, full political and economic participation and the pro-
motion of human rights, among others. M e a n w h i l e, w o m e n
are on the march to demand an end to poverty and violence.
Launched on March 8 by the Fédération des femmes du
Québec,the World March of Women gathers some 4,000
groups from 153 countries. The initiative culminates at the
United Nations in New York on October 17, 2 0 0 0 , t h e
World Day for the Eradication of Poverty. ■
+ …
www.un.org/womenwatch/daw
www.ffq.qc.ca
Changing the World Step by Step. Mosaic 
in Tribute to Women’s Struggles Worldwide.
A collection of empowering experiences publi-
shed by The World March of Women
Right after South A f ri c a ’s second democratic elec-
tions in June 1999, the newly elected President
Thabo Mbeki appointed eight women to minis-
t e rial positions,double the number in the first gove rn-
m e n t . The country ranks seventh in the world in
t e rms of women parliamentary representat i ves (25 per
c e n t ) , while the South A f rican constitution and the
A f rican National Congress (ANC) gove rnment have
entrenched gender equality as a key political va l u e ,
s i g n i ficant achievements on a continent where wo m e n
are all too often regarded as secondary citizens.
The moral support of leaders such as Oliver Ta m b o
and Nelson Mandela notwithstanding,wo m e n ’s gains
result from a we l l - a rt i c u l ated strategy that took shape
within the ANC well before its 1994 electoral victory.
With a transition to democracy in progress in the early
1 9 9 0 s , this strategy focused sharply on representat i o n
i s s u e s. In 1991, women within the ANC demanded a
quota of seats on the National Exe c u t i ve Committee.
They fa i l e d , but in 1994, the ANC was the only part y
to adopt a 30 per cent quota of women on its electoral
l i s t s.When the ANC started drafting the Reconstru c-
tion and Development Progr a m m e , the backbone of
its electoral manifesto,wo m e n ’s groups within the part y
lobbied hard for it to address their concerns regarding
e m p l oy m e n t ,health and land ow n e rs h i p.This lobbying
was bolstered by a powerful grassroots movement that
shared the aim of making South A f rica a non-racial,
but also a non-sexist democracy.Women from all wa l k s
of life formed a National Coalition in 1992, which tur-
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
ned gender representation into a multiparty concern .
A c c o m p a nying the dri ve to get women into power wa s
an emphasis on getting them out to vote through tar-
geted campaigns.
Opposition from traditional leaders
Once in government, women were influential
in drafting the constitution, adopted in 1996.The
task was not always easy. Even though the coun-
try touted itself as a non-sexist democracy, in
pushing for the insertion of an equality clause,
women ran into strong opposition from several
traditional leaders, including some within the
political fold of the ANC, who argued that it
conflicted with the protection of custom and tra-
dition.Strong political lobbying efforts by women
MPs such as Mavivi Manzini, Baleka Mbete and
Thenjiwe Mtintso undercut the arguments of the
traditional leaders.Women MPs were also instru-
mental in getting clauses included on reproducti-
ve rights as well as socio-economic rights.
Most women who entered Parliament in 1994
were committed to advancing the rights of South
A f rican women—an inevitable source of tension
when their positions came into conflit with those of
their respective part i e s. S t i l l , a number of routes
were pursued to break through this ‘ l oya l t y ’d i l e m m a .
By far the most successful structure for adva n c i n g
wo m e n ’s rights has been the Joint Committee on the
I m p r ovement of Quality of Life and Status of Wo m e n .
Grouping women from across party lines, this par-
l i a m e n t a ry committee consults with wo m e n ’s orga-
n i z ations in civil society and has played a cri t i c a l
role in proposing and fast tracking legi s l ation so that
it is put on the roll for debat e .Had it not been for this
c o m m i t t e e , it is more than likely that several fa r -
reaching pieces of legi s l ation directly concern i n g
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 21
Women’s long march to power
1.AZT has been shown to reduce transmission of HIV
from pregnant mothers to their babies.
women would not have been passed. In part i c u l a r ,t h e
Te rm i n ation of Pregnancy Act provides women with
access to abortion under significantly broader and
more favourable conditions than in the past. T h e
Maintenance Act of 1998 substantially improves the
position of mothers dependent on child support
from their former part n e rs.Free health services have
been provided for pregnant women and children
under the age of six.The 1998 Domestic Violence A c t
was important in sensitizing the judiciary to the fa c t
t h at violence within families was a public mat t e r.
The committee has also stood behind a budget ini-
t i at i ve which analyzes how different ministries allo-
c ate resources specifically to benefit wo m e n .
These gains are laudable. But despite the
significant number of women in cabinet—many
of whom come from an activist background —
they have been unable to oppose cutbacks in
social service spending or increases in arm s
expenditure (the deputy minister of defense is a
Quaker and head of the ANC’s women’s parlia-
mentary caucus). And although health minister
Dr Manto Tshabalala is a woman and longtime
gender activist, she has not supported women’s
organizations’ demand for the HIV/Aids drug
AZT to be offered to pregnant women and rape
survivors.1 The government has argued that the
option is unaffordable, a position not necessarily
held by women within the ANC, nor, for that
matter, by the opposition.
Securing leadership positions
in political parties
In the 1999 election campaign, no party ques-
tioned the principle of gender representation.
Instead, the focus shifted to specific policy issues
such as violence against women, unemployment,
housing and health care, with national television
and radio allotting air time to debate the positions
held by the competing parties. Women activists
pointed out that despite the formal commitments
to gender equality, political parties failed to outli-
ne policy positions on key gender issues. For
example, not one party had a policy with regard
to dealing with violence against women despite
the fact that South Africa has one of the highest
incidence of rape in the world.
These interventions during elections highlighted
the need for women to become significantly more
organized within political parties and to hold lea-
d e rship positions within them.This will gi ve wo m e n
MPs the support they need to become even more
e f f e c t i ve within the legi s l at i ve arena, but also ensure
that internal party mechanisms exist to hold them
accountable to women members and not just part y
leadership. Joyce Piliso-Seroke,chairperson of the
Commission on Gender Equality, has commented
t h at a long climb remains. The gove rn m e n t , s h e
s a i d ,“talks the talk of gender equality, without wa l-
king the walk.The Domestic Violence and Main-
tenance Acts will remain just so many words unless
i n f r a s t ructure and human resources are provided to
make them effective.” ■
An ANC gathering on the eve of the country’s first democratic elections in April 1994.
The women were
c o u ra g e o u s, p e r s i s t e n t ,
e n t h u s i a s t i c ,
i n d e f a t i g a b l e, and their
protest against the pass
system set 
a standard for anti-
government protests
that was never equalled.
Nelson Mandela, former South
African president (1918- )
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
‘I’ll go to parliament dressed as I was during my
c a m p a i g n , in an ove r c o at and a head-scarf. N o
way will I put on the chador.” Elaheh Koulaï, a
u n i ve rsity professor elected to parliament as a repre-
s e n t at i ve of Tehran in the Fe b ru a ry 18, 2000 legi s l a-
t i ve elections, unleashed a political storm when she
made this quasi-revo l u t i o n a ry proclamat i o n . S i n c e
the advent of the Islamic Republic in 1979,all wo m e n
holding official positions have wo rn the chador, t h e
l o n g,black fa b ric cove ring that conceals the entire body
from head to toe.
Marzieh Dabagh, an outgoing member of parlia-
ment who was not re-elected, reacted to Koulaï’s sta-
tements by threatening to “ b ox the ears ”of any wo m a n
who would dare come to the M a j l i s (the Iranian par-
liament) without the traditional chador.The brother
of the Guide of the Islamic Republic, Hadi Kha-
m e n e i , a leading member of the reformist camp,h a d
to step in and cool tempers dow n , s aying that all
f o rms of ve i l s , from the simple head-scarf to the
c h a d o r , are acceptable.
This debate may seem tri t e , but it reveals the
a s s e rt i veness of women in Iranian society, i n c l u d i n g
outside Te h r a n , where they are seldom seen without
the chador. Fatemeh Khatami (no relation to the pre-
sident) was elected to parliament in Mashhad,not fa r
from the Afghan border, e ven though she does not
wear the chador, an unprecedented event in the pro-
v i n c e s.
An educated generation
A symbol of the Islamic order,the obligation to we a r
the veil has never prevented women from standing
up for their ri g h t s.At the beginning of the revo l u t i o n ,
the gove rnment tried to send them back into the
h o m e , p ri m a rily with offers of early retirement and
i n c e n t i ves to work less.But officials soon gave up in the
face of resistance (women were accustomed to gentler
t r e atment under the Shah, especially if they belonged
to the elite) and the needs of the country, then at wa r
with Iraq.To d ay,women account for 12 per cent of the
work force.Although the figure is the same as in 1979,
it is likely to rise as new generations of better-educat e d
women enter the labour market.
For women have taken full advantage of the literacy
for all campaign launched after the revo l u t i o n ,e s p e-
cially in the country s i d e , which had remained back-
ward under the Shah.To d ay the percentage of girls in
school is almost the same as that of boys (nearly 80 per
c e n t ) .Young women account for 40 per cent of uni-
ve rsity students and, t wo ye a rs ago, for the first time
more girls than boys were admitted to the competitive
n ational entrance examinat i o n s.This ye a r , they eve n
make up 58 per cent of the accepted candidat e s.
“Almost all leisure activities are closed to gi r l s ,”
explains law yer and wo m e n ’s rights advo c ate Meh-
ranguiz Kar. “So they focus on their studies.”
Women are still overwhelmingly underr e p r e s e n t e d
in political decision-making bodies, but they play a
d e c i s i ve role as vo t e rs.“Their turn-out has been outs-
tanding since the May 1997 legi s l at i ve ballot, w h i c h
helped elect President Khat a m i ,” continues Kar.“ T h e
wo m e n ’s vote is a conscious vo t e . They carefully
choose candidates who are in favour of their ri g h t s.”
In Fe b ru a ry 1999,they made use of their power to vo t e
some 300 women into municipal councils during the
first local elections since 1979. In the rather traditional
E m a n c i p a t i o n under the veils
◗ Siavosh Ghazi
Despite the Islamic re v o l u t i o n , women have never stopped standing up for their rights.
In head-scarves or chadors, they are at the heart of the struggle to modernize society
◗ Freelance journalist based in
Tehran
Young Iranian women at the ballot box in the first round of the February 18,2000 
legislative elections.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 23
p r ovincial cities and tow n s , these results reflect a
“ r e volution of mentalities”, s ays Fatemeh Ja l a ï p o u r , a
Tehran municipal council member responsible for
wo m e n ’s issues.
The wo m e n ’s vote also helped reform e rs win the
l e gi s l at i ve elections. Some interior ministry officials say
t h at women outnumbered men vo t e rs : 55 per cent
compared with 45 per cent. B u t , as journalist Saïd
Leylaz points out,“this time they didn’t vote specific a l l y
for women candidat e s ,” e ven though their number
increased by 70 per cent compared with the last legi s-
l at i ve elections. Like the outgoing M a j l i s, the new par-
liament has only fifteen women deputies (out of 290),
but they are moderates rather than conservat i ve s.
A voice in the press
Women must still settle for a backseat in politics,bu t
they hold a gr owing number of senior civil serv i c e
p o s i t i o n s. Since taking office in 1997, P r e s i d e n t
Mohammad Khatami has asked his ministers to appoint
women to head up the va rious ministerial depart-
m e n t s.And his brother, Mohammad Reza Khat a m i ,
who leads the Islamic Iran Pa rt i c i p ation Front,said after
t h at movement won the last elections, “ We are in
favour of women entering the gove rn m e n t .”
The rise of Iranian women is partly due to their
own mobilization effort s. After the Iran-Iraq wa r ,
m a ny of them organized all kinds of activities within
r e l i gious organizat i o n s , often spurred on by the
g ove rn m e n t . Since 1997, they have rushed into the
l i b e r a l i z ation process begun by Mohammad Kha-
tami to set up more independent non-gove rn m e n t a l
o r g a n i z at i o n s , despite resistance from conservat i ve s ,
who until now have controlled the committee in
charge of issuing perm i t s.To d ay, the social fa b ric is
p a rtly based on wo m e n .“In Te h r a n ,s e veral hundred
grassroots mutual aid, e nvironmental protection and
other groups are headed by wo m e n ,” s ays Ja l a ï p o u r.
L i k e w i s e , the number of young women on student
councils is steadily on the ri s e .A n d ,s ays Kar, wo m e n
head over 40 publishing companies, most of which
p rint books on wo m e n ’s issues or by women authors.
The press has also played a key role. As early as
1 9 9 0 , women Muslim intellectuals founded the
monthly Z a n a n (Wo m e n, in Fa rs i ) , where they cam-
paign for a revision of their legal status and a more
m o d e rn form of Islam.They are demanding the same
rights as men with regard to inheritance (under shari a ,
they are entitled to only half as much as men),d i vo r c e
(they can be repudiated for no apparent reason) and
child custody (which is denied them if their daughter
is over seven and their son over two ) . Only a few
minor touch-ups have been made in the past seve r a l
ye a rs to correct these inequalities. For example, a
woman may now request that her right to ask for a
d i vorce be recognized in the marriage contr a c t .
Widely read by young wo m e n ,Z a n a n boasts a cir-
c u l ation of 30,000,one of the highest runs of any Ira-
nian monthly. H owe ve r , there as elsewhere, t h e
d e b ate over the interp r e t ation of Islamic rules still
d o m i n ates the issue of gender equality, which limits
the scope of the feminist move m e n t .“ A d vo c ates of
s e c u l a rism still cannot organize as such,” s ays Kar.
They have voiced their concerns on several occasions
within non-gove rnmental groups such as the Orga-
n i z ation of Women Jo u rnalists and through the
wo m e n ’s press, in Z a n a n and the daily Z a n, before it
was shut down less than one year ago.
“ We ’re going to have new laws passed in favo u r
of gender equality,” said Elaheh Koulaï after she
won the election. The deputy’s determ i n ation is
likely to put her on a collision course with irat e
c o n s e rvat i ve s , who view the “loosening of moral
s t a n d a r d s ” as a sign of their political defeat . ■
S w e d e n : court battles 
for e q u a l p a y
◗ Elisabet Ornerborg
Even in the country with the world’s highest number of female cabinet ministers,
the gender gap is not closed in the workplace 
Despite an Equal Opportunities Act  passed in
1 9 7 9 , S wedish women earn 15 to 20 per cent
less than men. F i ve ye a rs ago, an economist
won her case, p r oving that she took home less than
her male counterp a rts in the same borough,
although her responsibilities and education we r e
i d e n t i c a l . But when it comes to comparing different
jobs deemed of equal value, the task is much more
complex.
In 1995, almost 400 Stockholm area nurses lod-
ged a wage discri m i n ation complaint with their
Equal Opportunities Ombu d s m a n . Because cases
are dealt with on an individual basis, three different
proceedings were filed in the Labour Court . A fourt h
was filed separately in 1996 by two midwives from
Orebro county council,in southern Sweden.
F i ve ye a rs down the line, none of these cases has
been resolve d .The nurses and midwives claim that
their work is of equal value to that of male medical
t e c h n i c i a n s ,but that their wages are about 15 per cent
◗ Swedish journalist,
with Lag&Atval, a magazine
specialized in labour issues
It is not possible 
to develop a country
without first adva n c i n g
the status of women.
Habib Bourg u i b a ,
first president of Tunisia 
( 1 9 0 1 - 2 0 0 0 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
◗ Journalist based in Lima (Peru)
1.These 243 complaints, which included 30 deaths,are
collected and detailed in the report Nada personal. Reporte
de derechos humanos sobre la aplicación de la anticoncepción
quirúrgica en el Perú (“Nothing personal.A human rights
report on the implementation of surgical sterilisation in
Peru”),released in mid-1999.The author,lawyer Giulia
Tamayo, was awarded Amnesty International’s Ginetta
Saga prize for her work on behalf of women’s rights.
Pe r u : s kewed p l a n n i n g
◗ Natalia Ta r n a w i e c k i
Two Peruvian organizations working on behalf of women’s rights have waged a successful
campaign to re v e rse coercive family planning policies
The first rays of morning sun appear through the
w i n d ow.The water boils, the dry clothes must be
brought in, the children woken up. In the humble
house where Damiana Barrientos lives in one of
L i m a ’s southern subu r b s , a new day is begi n n i n g .
But for Damiana, this is no ordinary daw n :t o d ay she
must go to court .
In Fe b ru a ry 2000,Damiana won the right to free
medical care from the Pe ruvian health ministry until
she makes a full recove ry from an operation per-
f o rmed against her will. “ E ve rything began in the
m at e rnity ward of a Lima hospital in 1998 when I gave
b i rth to my baby,who died a few days after I had a cae-
s a r e a n ,” s ays Damiana.“There they cut my fa l l o p i a n
tubes and forged my signature on a paper saying I had
c o n s e n t e d .But complications emerged afterwa r d s ,a n d
n ow I’m suffering from a dropped uteru s.”She we n t
to the court s , but though the state acknowledged that
there were “ d e ficiencies in the quality of care,”her case
was closed.Thanks to law ye rs from the Committee for
the defence of wo m e n ’s rights in Latin A m e rica and
the Caribbean (CLADEM-Pe ru) and to the Mov i-
miento Amplio de Mujeres group (MAM), D a m i a n a ’s
case was taken to the Inter-American Commission on
Human Rights, where it is now awaiting sentence.To
d at e , CLADEM has filed legal complaints over 243
cases of forced steri l i s at i o n .1
Since 1996, when the first evidence emerged of
s e rious violations of human rights through the imple-
m e n t ation of vo l u n t a ry surgical steri l i s at i o n ,MAM and
CLADEM have sought to reform the family planning
p o l i cy embraced by the Pe ruvian gove rnment in 1995,
and aimed at reducing the birth rate in rural areas from
5.6 children for each woman to an average of 2.5
children by the year 2000.“Our goal was to ensure that
women could freely opt for one of the va rious methods
of family planning and get the gove rnment to prov i d e
i n f o rm ation on all the altern at i ves rather than impose
vo l u n t a ry steri l i s ation as the only possible method,”
s ays CLADEM’s Giulia Ta m ayo.
“Health festivals”
According to CLADEM,the family planning pro-
gramme heralded by President A l b e rto Fujimori as a
way to make health services more democratic and
t r a n s f o rm women into “ m a s t e rs of their destiny ”h a s
been conve rted since 1996 into a policy of forced
s t e ri l i s ation devoted to meeting national quotas,w i t h
s u r gical steri l i s ation as the only option.To make the
l atter more popular,“health festiva l s ” were organized
in which women were goaded into agreeing to undergo
the operat i o n . “ We decided to have only two chil-
d r e n .T h at ’s why we chose to have our tubes cut, a n d
we are happy!”Messages like this featured prominently
on the colourful banners hoisted in villages to
announce the health festiva l s , which would last bet-
ween one and three days and include sporting activi-
ties and public concert s.
D u ring the festiva l s , va c c i n ation campaigns,
tests for breast and uterus cancer and dental check-
ups were promised, but not all of these serv i c e s
were provided.No official information is available
on the number of festivals held between 1996 and
l owe r.The former look after hospital apparatus and
require less educat i o n .
The case has revo l ved around job eva l u at i o n s.T h e
m i d w i ve s ’e m p l oye rs maintain that there is no salary
gap between the two work cat e g o ries since they receive
c o m p e n s ation for night shifts and work four hours
l e s s.The medical technicians work days only.T h e
O m budsman has argued that basic monthly wa g e s
should be compared, not those taking compensat i o n
for shift work into account.The Labour Court turn e d
to the European Court of Justice in Luxe m b o u r g,
which ruled in A p ril that basic salaries should be com-
p a r e d , taking the case back to the Swedish court .
“The most significant thing about these cases
is that they are all focusing on the difference in pay
b e t ween different professions, one dominated by
women,one by men.How do you prove that work
is of equal value? There is no precedent in our court
about this,” explains Raija Lounava a r a , of the Equal
Opportunities office.
If the nurses and midwives win their respective
c a s e s , their employe rs will be held liable for damages.
It does not follow that the 400 nurses who filed com-
plaints in 1995 will benefit .“But rulings stating that
these persons have been discri m i n ated against will
send a ve ry important message to trade unions and
e m p l oye rs ,” said Lounava a r a . N e ve rt h e l e s s , t h e
n u rs e s ’ union does not support the court cases which
break with the Swedish tradition of collective agr e e-
m e n t s. It argues that wages are best set through nego-
t i ation and by relying on market forces, gi ven the
s h o rtage of nurs e s. Since 1995, the union has streng-
thened this negotiating process and obtained the
s h a rpest wage hikes on the labour market. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 25
1 9 9 8 , though according to the health ministry,
there were 463 “ c a m p a i g n s ” in the first half of
1996, which were attended by 120,000 people in
remote rural areas.
“These massive campaigns were preceded by
home visits carried out by medical wo r k e rs with the
aim of winning over fertile women with more than four
c h i l d r e n .People lived in a state of permanent anxiety,”
declares Ta m ayo. R e p o rts collected by Ta m ayo indi-
c ate that couples were explained the benefits of the sur-
g e ry, which was presented as the only option, b e f o r e
being forced to sign a document.Those who under-
went the operation were then presented with 15 kilo-
grammes of food, while the health worker who suc-
cessfully persuaded the woman in question wa s
awarded a bonus.
CLADEM gathered together a large number of
complaints proving that the poor sanitary conditions
in which the steri l i s ations were carried out had caused
s e rious complicat i o n s , sometimes leading to deat h ,
and that these after-effects were not just limited to iso-
l ated cases as the gove rnment had claimed, but we r e
p a rt and parcel of a vast systematic practice. In the
absence of any official answe rs to its questions,
CLADEM called on the press at the end of 1997 to
make the complaints public and put direct pressure
on the gove rn m e n t .
“Not all of the family planning programme is
w r o n g .We don’t oppose it, but we want to point out
the traumatic results of the coercive implementat i o n
of vo l u n t a ry steri l i s at i o n ,” o b s e rves MAM’s María
Esther Mogollón. In 1998, her organization decided
to check out reports that had emerged from Lima and
the country ’s interi o r.“Fifty vo l u n t e e rs visited hospitals
in 19 out of the 25 districts where the programme had
been applied to talk with those affected and with doc-
t o rs ,” s ays Mogollón. “The two most serious pro-
blems we saw were medical negligence and a lack of
i n f o rm ation for wo m e n ,” she adds. MAM has since
decided to distri bute pamphlets listing the rights of
health service users , and urging them to contact an
e m e r g e n cy advice hotline in the event of any abu s e s
of those ri g h t s.
O f ficial statistics report that 800,000 couples we r e
attended by state family planning services in 1998,bu t
t h at only 3.5 per cent chose vo l u n t a ry steri l i s at i o n ,a n d
t h at so far the total number of sterilised men and
women in Pe ru stands at 300,000 —in a proport i o n
of 10 women to each man. U n o f ficial fig u r e s , i n
c o n t r a s t , suggest that almost 500,000 people have
undergone the surgery.
Fo l l owing the campaigns mounted by
CLADEM and MAM, the health ministry has been
forced to change its methods, and now incorp o r at e s
the MAM pamphlet in the inform ation it distri bu t e s ,
as well as offering two advice sessions to would-be
patients: one on contraceptive methods, and the
other on the contraceptive method chosen, i n c l u d i n g
(if necessary) a briefing on the possible complica-
tions and irr e ve rsible nature of surgical steri l i s at i o n .
A 72 hour-period between signing the consent form
and the operation has also been granted to allow for
any second thoughts.
A year after the introduction of these reform s ,
Pe ru ’s family planning programme now maintains a
much lower profil e . No health festivals have been
staged this ye a r ,while according to authori t i e s ,d e m a n d
for vo l u n t a ry steri l i s ation has dropped by 30 per cent.
The main goal of the wo m e n ’s rights groups has been
to condemn the deva s t ating effects and psycholo-
gical damage that have followed the operat i o n s , bu t
their campaigns have helped ensure that poor ru r a l
people can plan their family freely, and learn the way s
of responsible parenting. ■
Nela Julcarine leaving a healthcare centre on the outskirts of Lima.She is one of several social workers who denounced
the ways in which state medical officers pushed women into undergoing surgical sterilisation.
The male is by nature
s u p e r i o r, and the female
i n f e r i o r ;
and the one rules, a n d
the other 
is ruled.
A r i s t o t l e,
G reek philosopher 
(384-322 B. C. )
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
At the dawn of the 21st century, states and
the international community can no longer
refute the fact that humanity is made up of
two sexes, not just one.This discovery, a precious
legacy of the century that just closed, has brought
women’s existence into the limelight. One of the
great democratic challenges for societies over the
next century will be to mature so that both sexes
are able to live their lives on an equal footing,
with all their differences, contrasting history and
culture, but also with equal rights and responsibi-
lities.
Women’s rise to power and their participation
in politics are the vital signs of a healthy demo-
cracy. If only this vision that emerged from the
1995 Beijing Women’s Conference could spread
worldwide! I would call it a radicalisation of
democracy. When women take part in the public
arena, contributing to the ongoing, shared effor t
to shape better ways of living together, a qualita-
tive leap occurs. Their participation fills a gap
which has until now prevented the emergence of
a truly democratic culture.
Archaic attitudes
Equal sharing of decision-making by men and
women is a pre-requiste for democracy. In Brazil,
women hold half the civil service jobs (they are
more qualified than men), but only 13 per cent of
s u p e rv i s o ry positions. The ultra-modern bu i l-
dings in the federal capital, Brasilia, stand in
sharp contrast with the persistence of intellectual
and emotional outlooks which hark back to the
19th century and hinder women’s empowerment.
But attitudes are not the only obstacle to
women’s ambitions. The structure of society and
the way men and women run their daily lives are
other stumbling blocks.
The Inter-American Development Bank has
had the good idea of giving the Institute for
Cultural Action, an NGO in Rio de Janeiro, the
task of setting up a pilot programme to train
Brazilian women for positions of political and
social power, an experiment which is to be exten-
ded to the rest of Latin America. Participants
include trade union and NGO leaders,key figures
from the black and indigenous communities,
company executives, civil servants and policyma-
kers.
These women of different ages, educational
backgrounds and ethnic origins are all aware of
one fact: they are paying a very high price for a
social contract that was negotiated when women
were in a position of weakness,and agree that this
has to change.
Re-mapping the division between
public and private life
Women account for 46 per cent of Brazil’s
working population and hold 51 per cent of the
university degrees, but still perform almost all
tasks at home, in the private sphere. A study of
300 women in positions of responsibility by the
Centre for Women’s Leadership (CELIM) in Rio
de Janeiro revealed the difficulty they had in
making choices, their temptation to give up and
the risk of pulling back in the face of increasing
obstacles. Their difficulties show that there is an
urgent need to re-organize the use of time,to stri-
ke a new balance between responsibilities and to
re-map the division between public and private
life. Household tasks must be recognised as time-
consuming, socially and economically vital and a
serious check on women’s ambitions.
Women in positions of power must constantly
prove that they can behave like men. They keep
For a fair sharing 
of t i m e
◗ Rosiska Darcy de Oliveira
Women may have entered public life on a massive scale, but they are still 
on their own when it comes to running the household. A new balance must 
be struck if there is to be genuine democra c y
◗ President of the Centre for
Women’s Leadership (CELIM),Rio
de Janeiro, Brazil
2 The political are n a
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 27
quiet about having to look after children, run a
household and care for elderly parents. Bringing
those issues out into the open would mean admit-
ting “flaws” that men do not have, for the simple
reason that they delegate such work to their
wives.
By drawing a veil of silence over their home
life as if it were something illicit, women are allo-
wing a basic fact to be hidden: the world of work
relies on a domestic zone run by them. Women
have changed, but the world of work has not and
they are reaching the point of exhaustion. Filled
with a deep sense of injustice, they are asking
themselves: “Where did I go wrong?”
Understanding that humanity is composed of
two different but equal sexes has several implica-
tions. Society must redefine itself because women
are turning up in public carrying children in their
arms and breast-feeding them, and because they
have their own awareness and language that come
from life experiences which are different from
those of men.
An untenable
double burden
Articulating issues affecting public and private
life is complicated, but that does not mean the
equation is impossible or that the problems they
raise should be brushed aside—especially since
the two worlds of public and private life are inter-
twined and mutually supportive.The balance bet-
ween the two has now been upset. Women have
entered public life on a massive scale, but the
organization of home life—how time is used and
who is responsible for what tasks—is still the
same, as if nothing had changed. And yet such a
world, where women are expected to soldier 
on just as before, “simply” adding to their lives
experiences hitherto reserved to men, is called
egalitarian.
That misunderstanding is fueled by an age-old
tradition of dismissing the world of women, even
by women themselves. Because society does not
consider what they do in the home as having any
major social significance, it fails to add this part
of their lives to the other side of the equation.
This is why the massive migration of women
from the home to the public arena is occurring
without societies having to think seriously about
how and by whom domestic work will be done in
the future (and which women still do, but at what
cost!).The double burden, resulting from an out-
dated social contract, is putting women under
mounting pressure by speeding up their lives to
an untenable pace.We are facing a social problem
that society as a whole must solve and not, as
many think, a problem that women must settle by
working even harder.
As new areas of power open up to women,
both sexes must take a fresh look at how they use
time. Re-arranging it is a challenge to society’s
imagination. But has this necessity sunk into the
minds of decision-makers? I do not think so. This
poses a major problem because it is a missing
building block in the construction of our demo-
cracies.
The everyday work of CELIM is proof of this.
Women must put these issues on the political and
economic agenda, thereby contributing to a more
radical definition of democracy. Feminism’s new
demand for a different sharing of time also opens
a debate that goes beyond the interests of women
a l o n e . In the final analysis, time and its
constraints define the limits of our own lives and
the range of choices we make, in accordance with
the meaning we give to our own existence.
The equality equation is increasingly complex.
It is not enough to wipe out the last traces of dis-
crimination in public life. A new definition of
equality will emerge when both sexes start sharing
responsibility in the private realm. Otherwise, the
issue will be distorted and women will lose all
chance of succeeding in public life. ■
Being there: A woman nursing her child during a political rally in Tokoza, 
South Africa.
If you say,
“I’m for equal pay,”
t h a t ’s a reform.
But if you say,
“I’m a feminist,”
that’s a
transformation 
of s o c i e t y.
Gloria Steinem,
American writer and
feminist (1934-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
U n finished d e m o c ra c y
Women in politics:
still “the s e c o n d s e x ”
% 0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100
15.3  Americas
15.3  Asia
14.1  Europe, excluding Nordic countries
38.8  Nordic countries
13.5  Pacific
11.7  Sub-Saharan Africa
3.6  Arab States
13.8  World
Source:Inter-Parliamentary Union,April 2000
% 0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100
42.7  Sweden
37.4  Denmark
36.5  Finland
36.4  Norway
36.0  Netherlands
34.9  Iceland
30.9  Germany
30.0  Mozambique
29.8  South Africa
29.2  New Zealand
28.6 Bosnia and Herzegovina,
Venezuela
27.6  Cuba
28.3  Spain
26.8  Austria
26.7  Grenada
26.5  Argentina
26.0  Turkmenistan, Viet Nam
25.0  Namibia
Source:Inter-Parliamentary Union,April 2000
The 20 countries 
where women hold at least 
25% of parliamentary seats
Women in national parliaments
(in percentage, by region,
both houses combined)
Nearly eve ry w h e r e , with the notable exception of
c o u n t ries like Ku wa i t , l aws entitle women to
vote and be elected. But in reality, the propor-
tion of women in legi s l at i ve bodies falls far short of
representing their percentage in the general popula-
t i o n .The Inter-Pa r l i a m e n t a ry Union (IPU),a Geneva -
based organization comprising 139 parliaments, s ay s
t h at men still account for 86 per cent of the wo r l d ’s par-
l i a m e n t a rians and that no country—not even in nor-
t h e rn Europe—has achieved total pari t y. In the form e r
communist countri e s ,which once boasted some of the
wo r l d ’s highest rates of female representation in poli-
t i c s , the percentages have fallen sharply since 1989.
L i k e w i s e , the IPU say s , “there has been no signi-
ficant increase in the number of women heads of
g ove rnment and, a b ove all,m i n i s t e rs throughout the
wo r l d .” The average number of women heads of
g ove rnment is around 12 per cent.A n d , they seldom
obtain strat e gic portfolios such as fin a n c e , the interi o r
or defence but are more likely to be gi ven the minis-
t ries of social affa i rs , the fa m i l y, health and the env i-
r o n m e n t ,which have lower funding and less political
c l o u t . ■
Regardless of their political affil i at i o n , in all
c o u n t ries women must overcome a host of
stumbling blocks that limit their political
careers. “Most obstacles to progress consist. . . of
deficiencies of various kinds,” the IPU says, inclu-
ding lack of time,training, information,self-confi-
dence, money, support, motivation, women’s net-
works and solidarity between women.
In every culture, prejudice and stereotypes die
hard. The belief still holds sway that women
belong in the kitchen and with the children,not at
election rallies or in the Speaker’s chair. The
media often reinforce traditional images of
women, who, upon entering politics, also often
bear the brunt of verbal and physical attacks.
In impoverished countries racked by civil stri-
The 1980s has seen 
a powerful
c o u n t e rassault on
w o m e n ’s rights,
a backlash,
an attempt to retract the
handful of small and
hard-won victories that
the feminist movement
did manage to win for
w o m e n . Th i s
c o u n t e rassault is largely
i n s i d i o u s : (...) it stands
the truth firmly on its
head and proclaims that
the very steps that
e l e vated women’s
position have actually
led to their downfall.
Susan Fa l u d i ,
journalist and American author
( 1 9 5 9 - )
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Heads of State 7 3 . 7 %
( B e r m u d a ,F i n l a n d ,I r e l a n d ,L a t v i a , Pa n a m a , San Marino, Sri Lanka)
Heads of Government 3 1 . 6 %
( B a n g l a d e s h , New Zealand and Sri Lanka)
Number of countries whose government includes a woman 1 4 5 7 6 . 3 %
Minister of Defence and Ve t e ran A f f a i r s 4 2 . 1 %
Minister of A g r i c u l t u r e 7 3 . 7 %
Minister of Finance/Budget 9 4 . 7 %
Minister of Science, Technology and Research 9 4 . 7 %
Minister of the Economy/Development 1 4 7 . 4 %
Minister of Foreign A f f a i r s 1 5 7 . 9 %
Minister of Justice 2 3 1 2 . 1 %
Minister of Education 2 3 1 2 . 1 %
Minister of Labour/Employment/Vocational Tra i n i n g 2 5 1 3 . 2 %
Minister of Fa m i l y / C h i l d r e n / Yo u t h 2 6 1 3 . 7 %
Minister of the Environment 2 8 1 4 . 7 %
Minister of Health 3 0 1 5 . 8 %
Minister of Culture 3 2 1 6 . 8 %
Minister of Social A f f a i r s 4 4 2 3 . 2 %
Minister of Wo m e n ’s Affairs/Gender Equality 4 7 2 4 . 7 %
Source:Inter-Parliamentary Union,1999
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 29
S t rategies of c h a n g e
How can women—a “minority” that makes
up 52 per cent of the world’s population—
take their rightful place in the management
of the world’s affairs? The controversy surroun-
ding various measures intended to encourage
them will continue for a long time to come.As the
fierce debate over France’s recent parity law sho-
wed,the two camps are divided into the advocates
of practical efficiency and the defenders of a theo-
retical universalism.
“Some feminists view the demand for parity in
decision-making forums as a step towards the
r e building of a dividing wall between the sexe s , a
d e velopment conducive to hierarchy - building and
d i s c ri m i n at i o n ,” s ays the IPU. “ O t h e rs , on the
c o n t r a ry, view it as a means to eliminate barri e rs
and as an altern at i ve to strat e gies that h ave failed to
wo r k : e n t ry into parties (in which women regularly
fa i l ) ,p a rtial redistri bution by means of quotas. . . o r
pious hopes for a change in mentalities.”
In northern Europe, where the feminist move-
fe and deteriorating economic and social condi-
tions, women are strapped by the tasks of mana-
ging everyday life and looking after their families.
The IPU stresses the general lack of child-care
facilities—often reserved for a privileged few—
the reluctance of political parties to change the
times and running of meetings and the weak bac-
king women receive from their own families.That
support, which is moral as well as financial, is all
the more vital because women have internalised
negative images of themselves since the dawn of
time and often suffer from low self-confidence.
Another obstacle is the lack of fin a n c i a l
resources, especially as election campaigns beco-
me increasingly expensive . To make mat t e rs
wo rs e , women encounter more or less ove rt
machismo in the form of closed political circles
barring entry to the “second sex”. Lastly, they
deplore the lack of solidarity between women,
exacerbated by the fact that the number of avai-
lable positions is limited. ■
ment is very strong, parties set up quotas in the
1970s and have been raising them periodically to
the point of achieving near-parity. That policy is
starting to spread to the rest of Europe, especial-
ly left-wing parties. But in some countries, such
as Portugal, bills in favour of such measures have
recently failed to pass (February 2000).
The situation in developing countries is more
varied but seems to be changing. Many parties
and governments—especially in Angola, Burkina
Fa s o, Cape Ve r d e , C h i l e , G u at e m a l a , I n d i a ,
Namibia, the Philippines, South Africa and Sri
Lanka—have taken steps in favour of quotas or
announced their intention to do so. ■
Women in the Executive
+ …
● w w w. i p u . o rg
● Politics: Women’s Insight. The views of some 200
women politicians in 65 countries—from why they
run to how they feel their involvement in politics
m a kes a differe n c e.
Series Reports and Documents No 36,
I n t e r- Parliamentary Union, 2000 
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
a handful were activists like her.They were fussed
over by the men in the organizat i o n , who wanted to
show they were modern-minded and strongly in
favour of wo m e n ’s emancipat i o n .The UNEM exe-
c u t i ve committee welcomed Skalli and she took
on her first political responsibilities.
King Hassan II, who came to the throne in
1961,soon called a halt to these “antics.” In 1965,
a high-school student rebellion grew into a popular
u p rising and a state of emergency was declared.T h e
UNEM was decapitated when all its leaders were
drafted into the army. Except for Skalli, t h at is,
who gr e atly resented being treated differently
because of her sex. “I had dreams about an army
t ruck that would pick me up and take me away
with my comrades.”
Skalli acquired her yen for politics during these
ye a rs of activism. But the state of emergency drove
the UNFP, of which she was a member, u n d e r-
gr o u n d . Morocco entered a period of political
repression. Women party members busied them-
s e l ves with looking after political pri s o n e rs ’ fa m i l i e s.
Badia Skalli had the good fortune to be born at
a time when the world made sense, and eve-
rything was linked to some kind of cause.
F i rst came the struggle for independence, then the
big push to build a new and freer country. Cold rea-
lity eventually dashed these hopes, but from the
outset,there had been that dream.
Skalli was born in 1944 in El Ja d i d a , about 100
kilometers south of Casablanca.At 10 she had her
first taste of political activism.A pro-independence
d e m o n s t r ation passed her house, and suddenly she
was marching in step with the protesters. T h i s
earned her a good hiding when she got home,but
the seed had been sown.
When Skalli enrolled at the Unive rsity of Casa-
blanca in 1962 to study law, the National Union of
Moroccan Students (UNEM) was at its height and
spearheading the left-wing opposition part y, t h e
N ational Union of Popular Forces (UNFP).
“You just had to join in,” she remembers.“You
just felt it so strongly.The students were the elite.”
Women students were few and far betwe e n ,and only
A woman in the l i o n ’s den
◗ Hinde Ta a r j i
For years, M o roccan member of parliament Badia Skalli has put her long-standing loyalty 
to the Socialist Party before her feminist beliefs. Now she is at the centre of a tough battle
◗ Freelance journalist based in
Casablanca
In Casablanca, thousands of Islamic conservatives took to the streets on March 12,2000 to protest a proposed reform 
of the family legal code, which governs the status of women.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 31
The young Skalli married, but her husband was
killed in a road accident three ye a rs lat e r. It took her
several years to recover.
The call of politics was too compelling. W h e n
the UNFP split in 1975, she sided with the part y ’s
“ d e m o c r at i c ”wing to help found the Socialist Union
of Popular Forces (USFP),which meant giving up the
tempting dream of revo l u t i o n .The battle was now to
be fought within the institutional bounds defined by
the law. Skalli was one of the part y ’s few female can-
d i d ates in the 1976 local elections, the first to be
held under the state of emergency.
She campaigned in a poor, p r e d o m i n a n t l y
Berber-speaking area, where she found women cut
off from the world because they were illiterate and
did not understand Arabic. She had put her finger
on the plight of Moroccan wo m e n .The young can-
d i d ate also found that vo t e rs had no preconceptions
about women in politics and judged her by what she
s a i d . But the party asked her not to mention the fa c t
that she was a widow—a woman without a hus-
band—in her nomination papers.
S k a l l i ’s election bid fa i l e d , and she took it badly
because the party had lost a seat . The issue of
wo m e n ’s part i c i p ation in politics sparked little
public interest. But she was leader of the USFP’s
wo m e n ’s organizat i o n , founded in 1975 duri n g
I n t e rn ational Wo m e n ’s Ye a r. Awareness was ri s i n g,
but female party activists still put wo m e n ’s issues on
the back burner.
“Next to the historic figures who had fought for
independence or spent time in pri s o n , we felt small
and tended to fade into the backgr o u n d ,” she say s.
Though a key figure in the USFP, it was a long time
before Skalli gained enough self-confidence to assert
her rightful place in the party.
After another defeat at the polls, this time in a
p a r l i a m e n t a ry election, she won a municipal council
s e at in 1983. Two women Socialist Pa rty candi-
dates were elected in the same town and the party
planned to make Skalli the council president.The
proposal triggered an uproar. Despite being socia-
lists, some “comrades” were dead-set against the
i d e a . “A people who entrust their business to a
woman are heading for ru i n at i o n ,” the prophet
Mohammed is supposed to have said.The party lea-
d e rship backed down and the job went to a yo u n g e r
and less qualified man. Skalli had to settle for being
the council vice-president.
The practical experience of sharing power with
men was highly instructive. “Everything happens
behind the scenes, in the framework of a male com-
plicity that shuts out women,” she says. Women’s
issues rarely interest men, she notes, and because
female politicians are so few, they are “like clay
pots against iron ones.”
N ow that she had entered the fight for political
power as an equal,Skalli saw repressed machismo
coming to the surface again.The USFP’s decision
to put her up as a parliamentary candidate sparked
rebellion in the ranks and she encountered her firs t
sexist at t a c k s , such as “she smokes. . . s h e ’s a widow.”
But she was pleased to note once more how little her
gender mattered to the vo t e rs. In fa c t ,m a ny people
b e l i e ved she was more tru s t wo rt hy than men
because of her sex.
S k a l l i ’s political career continued to prosper
and she remained a staunch party stalwa rt . S h e
campaigned for wo m e n ’s ri g h t s , but “the party still
came firs t .” Until the 1993 parliamentary elec-
tions, the USFP wanted her to be its only female
candidate. At that point, she protested and threa-
tened to withdraw if other women were not allowe d
to stand.The party gave in.
Two woman entered parliament that ye a r , a
milestone for Morocco—Skalli and Lat i fa Bennani
Smires of the Istiqlal (Nationalist) Party. Just two
women among 300 men.After the 1997 elections,
there were still only two. But the political scene
c h a n g e d . The left-wing opposition, kept out of
power for nearly 40 years, took over the reins of
government and USFP secretary-general Abder-
rahmane Youssoufi became prime minister. In his
inaugural speech,Yo u s s o u fi said he wanted to pro-
mote wo m e n ’s ri g h t s. The secretary of state for
protection of the family and children got to work on
the matter with the help of women’s NGOs.
Bitter attacks over proposed code
A year lat e r , a draft programme to “make wo m e n
p a rt of the development process” was presented
to the prime minister. It included a reform of the
mudawana, the family legal code based on sharia
(Islamic law), which governs the status of women.
The planned reforms include abolishing polygamy,
raising the marriage age for girls from 15 to 18
a n d , in eve ry case, replacing repudiation with court -
a p p r oved divo r c e . “It was too good to be tru e ,”
s ays Skalli. “But we believed in it.We didn’t expect
such a fuss.”
The first attack on the project came from a
member of the government itself, religious affairs
minister Abdelkebir Alaoui M’d a g h ri .A broad range
of conservat i ves led by Islamic fundamentalists
took up the cry.They put on a show of force, b i t t e r l y
attacking the reform’s supporters as bad Muslims
and even atheists. Bogged down by internal divi-
s i o n s , the gove rnment is playing for time. T h e
reform is a burning issue,and the government has
no intention of getting burned.
The gove rn m e n t ,s ays Skalli, b e a rs an import a n t
responsibility and has clearly displayed a lack of cou-
rage on the issue of women. She recognizes that
much is at stake, for women in particular and
Moroccan society in general, and finds the situat i o n
distressing. But what can you do when you are “a
clay pot”? ■
Now that she had entered 
the fight for political power 
as an equal, Skalli saw 
re p ressed machismo coming
to the surface again.
It is better to be a man
than a woman because
even the most misera b l e
of men has a wife to
order around.
Isabel A l l e n d e,
Chilean writer (1942-)
Badia Skalli
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
Nothing short of a  small revolution occurr e d
d u ring President Bill Clinton’s visit to India last
M a r c h . In the rural heartland of  Rajasthan, a
dozen village women sat around on plush blue sofa s ,
in resplendent dress, to discuss issues of democracy
and power with the U. S .p r e s i d e n t . F i rst they intro-
duced themselve s : all are elected representat i ves of their
village councils (p a n c h ayat s) . Together they run a
wo m e n ’s dairy cooperat i ve and have initiated seve r a l
small credit and loan schemes for poor, l a n d l e s s
women in their communities. They had discarded
the age-old custom of hiding their veiled faces behind
home wa l l s.N ow, they explained, they had to go to the
bank to draw and desposit money, and to their distri c t
h e a d q u a rt e rs to attend monthly meetings.
E ven as they spoke in their nat i ve tongue, t h e
women freely used English words such as ‘ l o a n ’ ,
‘ c r e d i t’ ,‘ I n t e rn e t ’ ,‘ p u b l i c ’ and ‘no confid e n c e ’ .T h e y
complained about the lack of jobs for their educat e d
s o n s , spoke about the need to open a school close by
for their adolescent daughters , and their ongoing fig h t
for drinking wat e r , better roads, seeds and fa rm i n g
tools for their villages.
A lingering debate
Some might like to dismiss this meeting as a cleve r
act of ‘ f e e l - g o o d ’ politics on the part of the President
or as a showcased stunt on the part of the Indian
g ove rn m e n t .But the meeting was really about wo m e n
e n t e ring politics and staying on. Along with some
million others across the country, these women are the
d a u g h t e rs of the 73rd and 74th amendments of the
Indian Constitution.Passed in 1993, these two amend-
ments oblige all states to reserve one third of seats in
the three-tiered system of local gove rnment (village,
block and district leve l s ) — k n own as p a n c h ayati ra j—
to wo m e n .Elected directly by and from among the vil-
l a g e rs , the p a n c h ayat s can make decisions concern i n g
a wide range of fie l d s , from agriculture to health,
e m p l oyment and pri m a ry educat i o n .
In a short time, women have shown their potential
to wield power effectively at the village level and chal-
lenge feudal traditions.According to some observe rs ,
this is one of the reasons why the passage of the
Wo m e n ’s Reservations Bill, which seeks to reserve
33 per cent of all seats in the national parliament and
s t ate assemblies to wo m e n , has been repeat e d l y
blocked in the parliament.F i rst put forward in 1996,
the bill was reintroduced in 1998 but lapsed follow i n g
the gove rn m e n t ’s fall the same ye a r. It was resur-
rected in December 1999 but has continued to creat e
h avoc in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of the par-
l i a m e n t .There are only 43 women MPs in the curr e n t
Lok Sabha,out of a total figure of 543,and the majo-
rity are from the elite.
Opponents of the bill,which include the Rashtri ya
Ja n ata Dal and the Samajwadi Pa rty (both centre-left),
along with some constituents of the ruling coalition,
led by the Hindu nationalist Bharat i ya Ja n ata Pa rt y
( B J P ) , claim that the bill should include a sub-quota
for Other Backward Classes1 and Muslim wo m e n .
Otherwise they argue,the quotas will only promote the
interests of the elite.The debate has been characteri z e d
by an ugly display of male muscle and lung powe r: i n
one instance, the Speaker had to adjourn the House,
in another,opposing law m a k e rs grabbed the bill off  his
d e s k .M e a n w h i l e ,C o n gress (I) president Sonia Gandhi
staged a walkout with her party members protesting
against the delay in the bill’s passage.
As the debate lingers ,a number of organizations are
intent on highlighting the success of women in the p a n-
c h ayat s.They are also working hard to build up lea-
d e rship among the most marginalized gr o u p s ,n a m e l y
Dalit and Tribal communities, and to gi ve women a
better understanding of their powe rs and rights at
the local leve l .The Society for Pa rt i c i p at o ry Research
in Asia (PRIA) for example, helps to groom wo m e n
c a n d i d ates for elections through education and trai-
ning and gi ves p a n c h ayat r e p r e s e n t at i ves the oppor-
tunity to meet with their counterp a rts from other
s t at e s.At another leve l , these organizations are seeking
to mobilise women to vo t e , and if need be, stand up
against election malpractices, such as giving bribes or
d i s t ri buting liquor to win vo t e s.
A recent study prepared by the Multiple A c t i o n
Research Group (MARG), a Delhi-based NGO,
concluded that the constitutional amendments have
indeed acted as a catalyst for gr e ater part i c i p ation by
women in gove rn a n c e , but the legi s l ation now needs
to be fin e - t u n e d : women should be gi ven more than
a single term in a reserved constituency to make a real
d i f f e r e n c e ,and eve ry effort should be made to prov i d e
I n d i a ’s n u rseries of politics
◗ Mrinal Pa n d e
Over a million women hold the reins of power at the village level but a law to boost 
their presence in parliament has been deadlocked for several years
◗ News anchor for the state
television network Doordershan,
former editor with the Hindustan
Times Group, founder of the Indian
Women’s Press Corps, author of
several works of fiction and plays,
all published in Hindi
1 . Other Backward Classes account for 52 per cent of India’s
p o p u l at i o n .They belong to kinship groups that are entitled to
c e rtain benefits because they are considered disadva n t a g e d ,
although less so than ‘scheduled castes’ (previously referred to
as untouchables) and ‘scheduled tri b e s ’ .
In a short time, women 
have shown their potential 
to wield power effectively 
at the village level and challenge
feudal tra d i t i o n s
Woman is born free and
her rights are the same
as those of a man ( . . . )
All citizens, be they men
or women, being equal
in the state’s eyes, m u s t
be equally eligible for all
public offic e s, p o s i t i o n s
and jobs, according to
their capacity and
without any other
criteria than those 
of their virtues and
t a l e n t s.
Olympe de Gouges,
F rench writer and re v o l u t i o n a r y
( 1 7 4 8 - 1 7 9 3 )
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 33
them with literacy training.A separate study conducted
in three states on the gove rn m e n t ’s behalf by the
Centre for Wo m e n ’s Development Studies also high-
lighted the fact that the reservations had benefit e d
women from the Other Backward Classes.
Despite this, the barri e rs to part i c i p ation remain
s i z e a b l e . Rural areas are plagued by illiteracy and
p ove rt y, and pat ri a r c hy remains deeply entrenched.
Practices such as wife beating and dow ry deaths are still
p r e va l e n t .F u rt h e rm o r e ,as Ela Bhat t , the founder of the
S e l f - E m p l oyed Wo m e n ’s A s s o c i ation (SEWA) points
o u t , rural women do not represent a unified gr o u p.
C a s t e , clan and family considerations still ove rs h a d ow
political and gender-based pri o rities for large numbers
of women in rural areas. As such she say s , wo m e n
p a n c h ayat m e m b e rs are easily manipulat e d ,coerced and
coopted by their male counterp a rt s.A l s o, d r e s s ,e l e c-
tion campaign meetings and strat e gies for women are
still often decided by male members of the fa m i l y.
Reaching a critical mass
Feminist economist Devki Jain feels that political
e m p owe rment through affirm at i ve action is essen-
tial for women to ‘break this hard-rock of pat ri a r c hy.’
There has been much debate in the country about
whether illiterate rural women have the skills to stand
for elections and take offic e .The late Gita Mukherjee,
a Communist Pa rty of India member and six-time MP
from West Bengal, who headed the special parlia-
m e n t a ry committee on the Reservations Bill, r e p e a-
tedly asserted that the first step was to allow wo m e n
to break into politics; their awareness would auto-
m atically ri s e .The p a n c h ayati ra j i n s t i t u t i o n s , she said,
are to be valued as the real nurs e ries of political lea-
d e rship  for wo m e n .Pove rty and violence, she stressed,
can only be fought against effectively if women form
a critical mass in all decision-making bodies, from vil-
lage p a n c h ayat s to the parliament.
It may seem ironic that Madhu Kishwa r ,an activist
and editor of the Delhi-based feminist journal M a n u s h i,
is one of the bill’s cri t i c s.She argues that party leaders
will merely flood the reserved constituencies with the
“Bibi (wife) Beti (daughter) bri g a d e .” With the Fo ru m
for Democratic Reform , an umbrella organization of
wo m e n ’s gr o u p s , she has proposed an altern at i ve bill
t h at would make it legally binding for political part i e s
to present women as one third of their total candidat e s
and to gi ve proport i o n ate tickets to those from Dalit and
B a c k ward Classes. H owe ve r , M u k h e r j e e ’s long time
a s s o c i ate Bidya Munshi has criticized the proposal,c l a i-
ming that women are likely to be relegated to seat s
where political parties are unlikely to win.
S t i l l , despite entrenched pat ri a r c hy, there are
obvious signs of change,e ven if they seem anecdotal.
The chief minister of Madhya Pradesh, D i g v i j ay
S i n g h , recently organized a meeting with women in
B h o p a l .C h a i rs were laid out for the ministers and high
o f ficials and mats on the floor for elected wo m e n
r e p r e s e n t at i ve s. As the meeting began, R e m m e b a i , a
t ribal woman stood up and questioned the chief
m i n i s t e r: “ You keep talking about wo m e n ’s equality
and reservations for wo m e n .We are in politics now, t h e
people have elected us. Is there a shortage of chairs in
your city?”A hundred ye a rs ago Remmebai and her
family would have been hung from trees for their
a u d a c i t y. But the chief minister thanked her humbly
for raising the issue and the next day all of them sat on
similar chairs. ■
Raising awareness: a panchayat gathering in the village of Haryana, in northern India.
I became a feminist as
an alternative 
to becoming 
a masochist.
Sally Ke m p t o n ,
American journalist (1943-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
In the industrial city of Ulsan, Lim Myung-sook
represents a rare coup in Korean society, a
woman in a position of public powe r. In this tra-
ditionally male-dominated nat i o n , the 45-ye a r - o l d
local assemblywoman is one of the success stories
of the non-profit Center for Korean Women and
Politics (CKWP).
H i s t o ri c a l l y, the public visage of Korea has been a
male one,while a wo m a n ’s role has been confined lar-
gely to the pri vate world of the home, a fact rein-
forced by the still strongly persistent values of Confu-
cianism and a male-run corp o r ate wo r l d .“Korea is not
really feminized at all,” s ays Sohn Bong-Scuk,a poli-
tical scientist and the founder of the CKWP. “ T h e
value system has prohibited women from getting
i nvo l ved in politics,”s ays Sohn,pointing to the fact that
municipalities and the National Assembly have seen
just a handful of female representat i ve s.
Sohn established the CKWP in 1990 to help
b ridge the gap between the ideal of equal representa-
tion and reality. Funded largely by foundation gr a n t s ,
the center employs a staff of eight and operates on an
annual budget of $180,000. For Sohn, there are three
major obstacles to gr e ater female representat i o n :t h e
p owerful male-oriented political culture, a deep-
rooted old-boys network and economics.
“Korean political parties are ve ry much pri vat e ,
person-centered parties with many medium-level
b o s s e s. If you want to be an important person in the
p a rty you must belong to someone else in the fa m i l y
South Ko re a ’s 
campaign school 
◗ Glenn Manarin
P rejudice and cronyism traditionally bar Ko rean women from politics but a non-pro fit tra i n i n g
c e n t re offers keys to success – from fashion tips to campaign stra t e g i e s
◗ Journalist based 
in South Korea
tree,so it’s not easy for a woman to enter that kind
of informal inner-circle,” says Sohn.
Most women also don’t have the large sums of
money needed to run for offic e . By law, n at i o n a l
assembly candidates must have a minimum of
$210,000 for their campaigns. H owe ver Sohn say s
some candidates will spend up to two million dollars.
Backing with strings attached
F u rt h e rm o r e ,c o rp o r ations have proved unwilling
to back female candidat e s.“When business or indus-
t rial sectors support a candidat e , there is a kind of
s t ring at t a c h e d . In the case of a woman candidat e ,
they don’t feel they’ll get anything back,” s ays Sohn.
“As a minority in politics, women are ve ry cautious
and tend to be less invo l ved in any dirty bu s i n e s s.
They are also usually firs t - year congr e s swomen so
they are not in positions of power yet to help them.”
Lim Myung-sook struggled to raise the $9,000
minimum to run for office in her local assembly. B u t
with the financial support of the CKWP and another
local non-profit gr o u p, she managed to raise the mini-
mum but far less than most candidat e s. H owe ve r ,
more than money and the expected prejudices stood
b e t ween her and offic e : Lim was sorely lacking in poli-
tical experi e n c e .In 1994, she was working as an env i-
ronmental campaign activist when friends suggested
she run in the upcoming local assembly election.W h i l e
p r e p a ring her bid, she received a call from Sohn who
i nvited her to attend the center’s “Campaign School.”
Lim Myung-sook (at left) participating in a protest against a school closure.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 35
Betty Friedan: debunking 
the mystique of politics
◗ Judy Mann
Women account for just 13 per cent of the U. S. C o n g ress and 10 per cent of the Senate.
But a pioneer of the contemporary feminist movement keeps the faith 
◗ Columnist for The Washington
Post, author of The Difference:
Discovering the Hidden Ways We
Silence Girls – Finding alternatives
that can give them a voice (Warner
Books, 1996)
Betty Friedan burst onto the American scene
in 1963 with The Feminine Mystique, a book
that transformed the way women thought of
themselves not only in the U.S. but also around
the world. She gave voice to the silent malaise
gripping housewives as they tended chores and
wondered silently, ‘Is this all?’. Friedan called it
the problem that had no name, but one society
had to face.
Since then,Friedan,often called the mother of
the U.S. women’s movement, has published a
series of seminal works. Her most recent book is
a memoir, Life So Far, published this spring by
Simon & Schuster. I interviewed her just before
the start of her book tour. At the beginning of the
interview, she quipped:“The trouble is when you
write a memoir, you finish it, and now you think
‘I’m dead.’”
Given the historical strength of the U.S. women’s
movement, why are there still so few women in
politics?
It takes so much money to run for office in the
U.S. Women don’t make that much money and
Lim attended a three-day session with about 40
other wo m e n , five of whom were also candidat e s
in other local assembly races. At the theoretical
l e ve l , the women learned to see female political par-
ticipation as a means to the ultimate goals of equa-
lity and true democratic representat i o n .At the prac-
tical leve l , they focused on speech-making skills,
political and campaign strategy as well as making
voter contact. In Korean election campaigns, i m a g e
is all-import a n t . So the women were advised on
fashion and hair styles, while those who used regi o-
nal dialects were coached in standard Korean.
Finally, participants were assigned roles as candi-
d at e s , electoral offic e rs and campaign managers
and a model election was held.
Different policy
preferences
Lim was among three women from her session
who went on to electoral success. In 1995, s h e
became the first woman to be elected to the Ulsan
Local A s s e m b l y, and she was re-elected in 1998.
Since then, another two women have attained offic e
in Ulsan.
Last A p ri l , CKWP also had reason to celebrat e .A
c a n d i d ate who they had trained in Seoul and also
sent abroad to Germ a ny and the United States for fur-
ther preparation was elected to the national assembly.
In most cases though, the center focuses on the gr a s s-
r o o t s ,u r ging housewives to run for local rather than
n ational offic e , whose candidates tend to already be
s avvy politicians.
In addition to the campaign school, the center
holds annual training sessions for women interested
in political issues. For three day s ,u n i ve rsity students,
h o u s e w i ves and established bu s i n e s swomen gat h e r
to discuss a chosen theme,such as sexual harassment
or affirm at i ve action.After seminars and discussion on
the topic, they are assigned roles, such as minister of
labour or minister of foreign affa i rs , and they are
divided into two camps: pro-feminist and anti-femi-
n i s t .They then hold a mock congress to hone their
d e b ating skills and get a taste for politics.“I like to gi ve
them motivation from a young age to be a leader in the
f u t u r e ,” s ays Sohn.
Another major activity is research on political
gender issues like female voting and gove rning pat-
t e rn s. Perhaps most import a n t l y, the CKWP has
found that “ women have different policy preferences
than men,” s ays Sohn. “They are more concern e d
about minori t i e s , the margi n a l , the aged and children.”
For example, in the blue-collar city of Ulsan, a s s e m-
b l y woman Lim has concentrated on fa c t o ry pollution
and recy c l i n g, social we l fare issues, the rights and
needs of the disabled, and wo m e n ’s ri g h t s.
Despite the progr e s s ,Korea is still far from the day
when politicians like Lim will comprise a healthy chunk
of the political base. In the previous national assem-
bly there were 11 women among 299 representat i ve s.
Recent elections in A p ril placed a record 16 wo m e n
into office (11 of whom were elected through affir-
m at i ve action legi s l ation implemented in 1995 after
e x t e n s i ve lobbying by CKWP and other gr o u p s ) .P r o-
gress indeed, but in its 273-seat national assembly,
Korean society is still represented overwhelmingly by
m e n . Sohn says the slow rate of change has been dis-
c o u r a ging but feels the CKWP has contri buted to an
i m p o rtant shift in thinking.“The political conscious-
ness has been raised,” s ays Sohn.“ N ow even men can
accept the wo r d s ,women and politics.” ■
As a woman, I have no
c o u n t r y.
As a woman, I want no
c o u n t r y.
As a woman,
my country is 
the whole world.
Vi rginia Wo o l f,
British writer (1882-1941)
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
à temps qu’il faut, dans
l’intérêt 
de l’humanité tout
entière, réserver sur la
Terre des zones où
l’expansion de l’homme
cède le pas à la
conservation des autres
espèces.
Julian Huxley,
biologiste britannique, p re m i e r
d i recteur général de l’UN E S C O
( 1 8 8 7 - 1 9 7 5 )
Networking on the Web 
A number of organizations in the U.S. are gearing up for the 2000 election. Many have
experience in supporting women candidates and training campaign staff, others are focu-
sing on informing women and encouraging them to vote. Here are some of the players.
Emily’s List (www.emilyslist.org) is a major source of early funding for pro-choice,
Democratic women.
The Women’s Campaign Fund (www.wcfonline.org),the National Women’s Political
Caucus (www.nwpc.org) and the National Organization for Women (www.now.org) all
provide support to pro-choice, feminist candidates.
The Wish List (www.thewishlist.org) supports pro-choice Republican women candidates.
Village.com, one of the largest Internet sites geared to women, offers on-line registra-
tion,interviews with candidates and chat rooms to exchange information with them.
The White House Project (www.thewhitehouseproject.org) is working to change the
political climate so that women can be elected to the presidency and other key positions.
League of Women Voters (www.leagueofwomenvoters.org) runs voter registration
campaigns to encourage women to vote.
Lifetime Television (www.lifetimetv.com), has formed a partnership with the National
Council of Women’s Organizations, (made up of 110 national women’s groups), for a biparti-
san campaign to educate women about issues that affect them and to underscore the impor-
tance of their vote. ■
they don’t have as easy access to it as men do. I
wouldn’t mind running for the Senate but I cer-
tainly would not want to have to raise the money.
In addition to the issue of money, women also
h ave the main responsibility for [raising their] kids.
T h at takes some ye a rs off most wo m e n ’s career life.
How has your work facilitated women’s entry into
politics? 
The things I wrote helped women break
through certain barriers in their own psyche—the
way they looked upon themselves and their possi-
bilities. The feminine mystique, that miasma of
influences, would keep women modest, shy, silent
and invisible. I told them to shout—don’t whis-
per. I organized women to break through the
feminine mystique, to run for office, to get wea-
pons against sex discrimination enforced.
You’ve worked hard for equal rights and affirmative
action. How effective do you think they’ve been
and how could they be strengthened?
Women today in the U.S. are getting the same
number of professional degrees as men.The dis-
c r e p a n cy lies in the childbearing ye a rs and
women never catch up.We are the only industria-
lized nation without a national programme of
childcare. It’s outrageous.
Tu rning to equal pay for equal wo r k , the pri n-
ciple is right but there are a lot of ways of sidelining
i t .Too many women are segr e g ated in jobs that may
be even more valuable than jobs men do, bu t
because women do them they are paid less. So we
began to say equal pay for work of equal va l u e .W hy
should janitors get more than a schoolteacher? Or
where would doctors be without nurs e s ?
Do you think women’s issues like economic equality
and reproductive rights are considered marginal
and difficult to construct a campaign on?
These issues affect 52 per cent of the popula-
t i o n . Women in this country have far more powe r
than they are using.They vote in higher proport i o n
than men do. The real question is why aren’t we
using our power to make the issues that are impor-
tant to us a higher pri o rity and get more wo m e n
elected to offic e . These issues are not as margi n a l
as they might once have been considered. I doubt
a nybody running for office in any metropolitan
area would dare to have as their slogan, “ Wo m e n
Go Back Home.” Although you never know what
would happen if there were an economic dow n-
t u rn .
What more could the women’s movement do to
support female candidates? 
It will be interesting to see what happens with
H i l l a ry (Rodham Clinton) in New Yo r k . Will there
be a big upsurge of support for her from wo m e n
crossing party lines? One thing didn’t really please
m e : when Hillary became visibly vulnerable to her
Monica [Lewinsky] problems, her ratings went
up. It was as if women couldn’t identify with her
superi o ri t y. They were more able to identify with
her when it became clear that eve rything wa s n ’t
easy than when she was so in control. I want to see
women really identifying with their own empowe r-
ment and getting out of the ‘ v i c t i m ’ s t at e .
What are some strategies that would facilitate
women’s entry into politics?
There are more and more women mayors—
women who are going through the ranks on their
way up. It used to be the only women you saw in
Congress were widows sitting in their husbands’
seats. That’s not the way it is anymore. Maybe for
me or for you the progress isn’t fast enough but
it’s fair and it will get better as more women study
political science and head student governments in
colleges and go to law schools. Up to now, law has
been the way into politics. More than 40 per cent
of law students are women. So in another genera-
tion, the talent pool will be nearly equal.
Any parting thoughts you’d like to share with
readers?
Women are not defined any longer as mothers
or housewives. To the degree I’ve had a hand in
making that happen, I feel very pleased and very
proud. I’m impatient for the next step. Now
women make up only 12 per cent of government.
What would it be like if they were 50 per cent? I
think politics would be different. Some research
done a few years ago found that by adding two
women to a state legislature the agenda changes.
And not just in the direction of women’s rights,
but in all directions having to do with life—chil-
dren, sickness, old people, health,quality of life—
and not just highways. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Women’s long march to power
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 37
The long march of women towards an equal
share of political,social and religious power is
far from over,whatever the country or system
of government.
France has just passed a parity law to break dow n
the resistance that has stymied the advancement of
women in politics for the past half-century. F r o m
n ow on, political parties must run an equal number
of women and men candidates in local elections and,
more broadly, in elections based on the proport i o n a l
s y s t e m , although the law is flawed with regard to
l e gi s l at i ve contests. In any eve n t , of course resort i n g
to legi s l ation is an admission of those part i e s ’r e s o u n-
ding failure to meet wo m e n ’s expectat i o n s , e ve n
though they are shared by the public at large. In the
belief that a seat for a woman means one less seat for
a man, F r a n c e ’s highly conservat i ve political leader-
ship does all it can to stop progress in its tracks.
I call these fa i n t - h e a rted advances a “ p i e c e-
meal”policy. Things look different and machismo
is less fierce, but at the end of the day there are still
not enough women to make their voices heard. We
know from the Scandinavian experience that they
need to hold at least a third of the seats in parlia-
ment to form a critical mass.
Women look at politics in their own way. M u c h
less attracted to the exhilarating feeling that power
can bring, they view it mainly as a way to change
t h i n g s. As mayor of a town with 25,000 inhabi-
t a n t s , I tend to consider parks more important than
parking lots. Housing lay-out can set off lively dis-
cussions about how to design kitchens, which for
me are friendly places that should open up onto
living rooms. I have noticed that male politicians
tend to talk much while we women are much better
at organizing our time.
I am tempted to say that women and men have
different attitudes about how to organize space and
time. Our participation leads to the emergence of a
certain, unknown reality which escapes the focus of
political action because it remains hidden in a corn e r.
It is there, but it cannot be seen. For example, is it
n o rmal for a wo m a n ’s career to be penalised by a
function—motherhood—that only she can fulfill?
The landscape of women’s rights is one of stark
contrasts. In Western countries, the march towards
equality has achieved uneven results. In others, it is
fraught with alarming setbacks,the cruelest example
being Afghanistan,where women are deprived of the
most basic ri g h t s. The women of Kosovo whom I
met recently still lack access to health programmes at
a time when mother and child mortality rates there
have reached alarmingly high levels.
Major United Nations conferences from Mexico
City to Beijing have helped women emerge from the
shadows.They need laws to defend their rights,and
institutions to gi ve those laws teeth. L aws may be
n e c e s s a ry sometimes, but they are not enough. T h e y
must be accompanied by a social movement led by
women.Nothing can ever be taken for granted when
wo m e n ’s rights are concern e d , and eve ry victory femi-
nists win is a fragile one because feminism,though it
fits the textbook definition of a movement for social
change,is not yet recognised as a political fact.
Everything depends on women’s will when their
rights are won: the right to education, work, control
their bodies, m ove about freely, own propert y, and so
o n .And the women who have come the furthest must
not forget to stretch their hands out to those who have
been left by the way s i d e . In A l g e ri a , women have suc-
ceeded in pushing back all forms of fundamentalism.
Women can indeed breathe new life into politics
and make it more accessible,more human and non-
violent as soon as they realise the power that comes
from working together. ■◗ Former French minister of women’s affairs, mayor 
of Lisieux, a deputy in the French parliament and chair 
of the Council of Europe’s committee on equal opportunity for men
and women
Closing ra n k s
Every victory feminists win is a fragile one, says former cabinet 
minister Yvette Roudy.◗ To defend their rights, women have to be 
at the helm of a strong social movement
Women can indeed 
b reathe new life into politics 
and make it more accessible,
m o re human and non-violent 
as soon as they realise 
the power that comes fro m
working together.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
E T H I C S
38 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
but wherever they went, presented them-
selves as craftspeople, artists and traders.
They were independent workers,commit-
ted to being masters of their own time,
intent on making an earning from odd,
on-the-spot jobs and with enough skills to
meet the requests and needs of a disper-
sed clientele.
Many Europeans no doubt frowned
upon the Gypsies’ working habits: how
they sought out jobs each day, their trust
in luck, their spontaneous way of approa-
ching strangers and their persistence. It
set them apart from farming communities
who worked for the long term, in tune
with the changing seasons. Despite this
and the inevitable friction between people
from different backgrounds, nomads and
farmers needed each other. The nomads
provided 
tools, baskets, veterinary care, music or
temporary manpower to the farmers, who
g ave them food and other goods in
exchange.
For a long time, the Roma managed
to make a living in this way, mainly as iti-
nerants but also by staying in one place
when there were opport u n i t i e s. T h e r e
were plenty of such cases in the Ottoman
Empire and in central Europe, where the
Roma served in the armies of invaders.
They were also active in the Iberi a n
peninsula, where they took over from the
Moors and Jews expelled towards the end
of the 15th century, at the time of the
Reconquista, until they too were forced
out.
These few examples go to show that
Gypsies were not excluded because of a
deep-rooted failure to adjust to local 
economic conditions, as it is too often
suggested. Rather, it seems clear that
governments and officials—first in wes-
tern Europe,especially Spain, and then in
central and eastern Europe—have, over
the centuries, gone to great lengths to
portray the Roma as a foreign and anti-
social people without a culture of their
own.
■
The figures are shocking. B e t ween 60
and 80 per cent of Hungary ’s wo r k i n g -
age Roma are estimated to be unem-
p l oye d . More than 60 per cent of Romania’s
Gypsies are said to live below the pove rt y
line and 80 per cent have no formal quali-
fic at i o n s. In Bulgari a , the same percentage
of Gypsies living in cities are jobless.T h e
figures are believed to be much higher in
the countryside.
In some villages of southern and eas-
tern Slovakia, all Roma of adult age are
destitute. In Britain, an estimated 10 to
20 per cent of the “travellers,” as they are
called, live in absolute poverty. In some
French cities, between 70 and 80 per cent
of the Gypsy population are on welfare
payments paid out to the most destitute.
Their housing conditions are appal-
ling, while their bill of health is another
cause for concern: most Roma have a life
expectancy of under 50.
Valued skills and masters 
of their own time
A glaring gap separates Europe’s
peoples from the continent’s largest
minority. Why, despite repeated attempts
to assimilate or exclude the Gypsies over
the past 600 years, have they remained
cut off from other peoples and for the
most part, pushed to the fringes of socie-
ty? After all, not every group of people
who came to live in Europe has been sys-
tematically ostracised. The Hungarians
were a nomadic people of Asian origin
but they managed to become a nation.
And there are others.
Probably not all the Roma—who first
came from India—were nomads when
they arrived in the Byzantine Empire in
the 12th or 13th century. But as far as we
can tell from various writings, they had
talents that enabled them to participate in
the economies of the regions they cros-
sed. They had no ambitions to conquer,
G Y PSIES: TRA PPED ON
T HE FRINGES OF EUROPE
◗ Alain Reyniers
Across Europe, Gypsies live in dire poverty and are frequently the target of violence 
and racism. But some governments are finally taking notice of the continent’s largest minority
◗ Ethnologist, lecturer at the Catholic University of
Louvain and editor of the magazine Études Tsiganes.
A Gypsy camp in Trent, in northern Italy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
E T H I C S
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 39
The contrived image of the Gypsies as
an idle, roaming and dangerous people
was one of the devices—along with vio-
lence, coercion and ideology—that was
used to help forge the national identity of
peoples belonging to specific territories
with well-guarded borders. In the 19th
c e n t u ry, when these peoples rose up
against foreign ru l e rs , the nat i o n a l i s t
struggle was always on behalf of a single
majority people, whose sturdy peasant
values were often played up, to the detri-
ment of all other elements in society,
including the Roma.
The influence of this past on forging a
common identity as an excluded people
cannot be underestimated. The nomads
of the A u s t r o - H u n g a rian Empire, f o r
example, settled in the 18th century as
“new peasants,” but were not given any
land. It contributed to a culture of mis-
trust and resistance towards gadjes (non-
Gypsies).
Even though the Gypsies had been the
long-time economic and cultural partners
of European peoples, they were always
kept out of political decision-making,
though it can be questioned whether they
were interested in becoming involved at
this level. At best they were regarded as
juniors to be dominated, at worst trouble-
makers to be pushed aside. Some closed
off from the world and scratched a living
on the edge of gadjo society, while others
took another path, making contact with
non-Gypsies as best they could.
In the process,some collective traits of
the Roma—wariness of the outside world,
the tendency to mix with one’s own and a
fatalistic attitude towards events—beca-
me accentuated and encouraged their
separation from other peoples.
Mutual distrust
Children were understandably taught
to be weary of the gadjes. Their education
was geared at following in their parent’s
footsteps and focused on the practical,
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
E T H I C S
40 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
with their environment serving as the
starting point for learning.
The tendency to exclude Gypsies
grew steadily throughout the 20th centu-
ry. Police in we s t e rn Europe cracked
down on them with increasing harshness.
These days, Gypsies are confined to a
limited number of parking plots and cam-
ping grounds that are often ill-equipped
for the needs of travelling families.
The gr owth of market forces and
changes in consumer tastes, along with
n e we r , more sophisticated production
m e t h o d s , h ave helped to dri ve some
Gypsy communities deeper into poverty.
Their trading practices are restricted by
laws against selling door-to-door, against
street activities and against recuperating
objects from dumps. Such legi s l at i o n
takes absolutely no account of their skills,
nor of the stakes at hand for Roma in this
domain. If they had no access to social
assistance or credit (although the public
image of Roma is hardly conducive to res-
pect),many would find themselves in des-
perate situations.
Targets of violence 
in eastern Europe
Under communism in central and
eastern Europe, Roma were first seen as a
social aberration, a relic of the “bour-
geois” world that would eventually disap-
pear. The Gypsies were shipped en masse
to work in menial jobs on collective farms
and in state enterprises. The lack of poli-
tical attention to the Roma’s culture—
their ancestral language, their education
geared to sharing and their economic
flexibility stressing income from odd
jobs—and the crying indifference to the
xenophobia that developed towards them,
did not facilitate the assimilation of young
Gypsies into the socialist societies.
The collapse of communism in eas-
tern Europe brought great suffering and
violence to the Roma, whose neighbou-
rhoods have been repeatedly attacked by
skinheads and others. In Bosnia and more
recently in Kosovo, Gypsy communities
were even destroye d . U n e m p l oy m e n t
among them has further increased.
In a sense, this new marginalisation,
which has produced emigration move-
ments towards a utopian El Dorado
(namely western Europe), is simply ano-
ther consequence of the political and
nationalist attitudes that have harmed the
Gypsies time and time again in the past.
Gypsies often have little lifeline outside
their communities, which are refused any
territorial rights by the host societies.
They are often prevented from settling in
a region that seems more hospitable
because they are ill-equipped to cope with
the demands of today’s economy and lack
a decent level of education.
Recognizing
national minorities
The Roma have nonetheless made a
few significant strides in recent years.
Several international bodies and many
NGOs have taken up their cause and have
pushed programmes to foster their inte-
gration—both economically and socially.
Governments are finally recognizing them
as national minorities or are taking mea-
sures to encourage their development in
the longer term.
Not all Roma have had their spirit
broken by centuries of being shunned.
Some have adapted, occasionally by assi-
milating but more often by highlighting
their traditional know-how and showing a
willingness to become involved in the host
society.
The future of the Roma probably does
not depend on a single solution. Given
the problems and obstacles they face, it is
more than ever linked to a collective
determination to build a humane and
democratic society where individuals and
groups can blossom and flourish. ■
A ROMA GHETTO IN FLORENCE
◗ Nicola Solimano and Tiziana Mori
Florence, a cosmopolitan city where the world’s
greatest art and architecture attest to a blen-
ding of cultures, has for ten years been debating
the fate of some 200 Roma families—approximately
1,000 people—living within its boundaries. Like
other major Italian cities where Roma have spon-
taneously settled, Tuscany’s capital has opted for
the solution of “nomad campgrounds”: in essence,
reserves where newcomers are herded together.
Most of the Roma in Florence are from Mace-
donia and Kosovo. They came during the past fif-
teen years, driven from their homes by the econo-
mic crisis and wars that have racked the region,
where they had almost completely given up their
wandering ways and settled down in certain neigh-
bourhoods of large cities.
At first, the Roma of Florence and the surroun-
ding area constantly moved around in small family
groups, driven from one place to the next by pro-
testing neighbours or by real estate projects laun-
ched in new, expanding suburbs. In the early 90s,
the municipality decided to concentrate them in
two “nomad campgrounds”. One is on the site of a
former rubbish dump located in a flood-prone area
near the river Arno. The other is a strip of land wed-
ged between the railroad tracks and the highway.
These unusable spaces were of interest to no one.
In Florence and elsewhere, the areas chosen for
“nomad campgrounds” revealed a widespread atti-
tude: Gypsies must be kept apart from the genera l
population, and the general population would do
best to keep their distance from them.
The city’s government considered these camp-
grounds a tempora ry solution. In fact, they were the
first in a series of other “tempora ry solutions” and
have never been called into question. All the classic
earmarks of ghetto pathology have appeared there;
the risk of fire is especially high. On several occa-
◗ Members of the Michelucci Foundation, Florence
sions, children have died in blazes when their
parents were unable to rescue them. Sanitary faci-
lities are collective. Each is used by several families,
with obvious consequences on health, mainte-
nance costs and relations between families.
The deterioration of facilities, living conditions
and social relations was inevitable. Scourges such
as drug abuse, partly due to contact with disad-
vantaged members of the local community, have
led to increased control by the authorities. The
campgrounds are closed spaces; their entra n c e s
are under surveillance; the comings and goings of
Roma and non-Roma alike are recorded. All the
features making up a ghetto are in place.
In the past few years, Roma organizations and
volunteers supported by a few rare but well-know n
intellectuals, such as the writer Antonio Tabucchi,
have pressured the municipality into finding alter-
native solutions. Under a regional law based on a
Michelucci Foundation project, the authorities have
built a small sub-division of six housing units assi-
gned to Roma from Macedonia. The project was
so successful that some 30 other families have
been re-accommodated in city - owned units. These
experiments show that, when they are taken out of
the degrading living conditions and exclusion in
which they had been living for years, Roma families
seize the opportunity to integrate themselves
socially and economically.
H owever, the building of the sub-division met
with fierce criticism in Florence, exploited by right-
wing parties, which dissuaded the municipality from
undertaking similar projects. Not enough families
have been relocated to permanently close the
“nomad campgrounds”, where Roma refugees fle e i n g
the war in Kosovo have arrived in the meantime.
Florence continues presenting the face of a city
of art and culture to the world, while at the same
time it is incapable of striking a dialogue with a
small minority from a different background. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 41
■
The wo r l d ’s biggest museum lies
under the sea. Over the centuries
h u n d r e d s , perhaps thousands of
ships—nobody has even a remote idea
how many—have sunk in storms or the
heat of battle, bringing Roman amphorae,
gold bars, cannons and crates of Chinese
porcelain with them.
Maritime trade began booming in the
sixteenth century : the ships of the Dutch
East India Company made 8,000 round-
t rip voyages to China in a 200-year peri o d .
But until the mid-twentieth century, there
was no way reach this underwater museum,
and the world’s oceans were like a gigantic
safe containing civilisation’s treasures.
Two of the oldest ships found recently
came to a grim end just over 2,700 ye a rs
a g o, when they were probably on their way
from Tyre to the Pharaohs’ Egypt laden
with wine-filled amphorae. A m e ri c a n
u n d e r water archaeologists Robert Ballard,
who discovered the wreck of the Ti t a n i c,
and Lawrence Stager, of Harva r d
U n i ve rs i t y, found the two Phoenician ve s-
s e l s , each less than 20 metres long, off the
Israeli coast in June 1999.
They had been asked to locate an
Israeli submarine, the Dakar, which sank
in 1969, taking its 69 crew members
d own with it. Two small underwat e r
robots, Jason and Medea, descended to
300 and 900 metres to film and inspect
the Phoenician vessels, which led to the
discovery that they were still in an excel-
lent state of preservation.
The deeper the water the less oxygen,
so wrecks there are much better preserved
than those closer to the surface, according
to Ballard. “The great depths, the absen-
ce of sunlight and the great pressures
seem to preserve history far more than we
thought,” he says. A 3,300-year-old ship
was found off Turkey in more shallow
waters, and two more Phoenician vessels,
dating from the seventh century BC, were
located near Murcia, Spain, but all were
in much worse condition.
The discovery of the two wrecks off
the coast of southern Israel came as a sur-
prise because historians were unaware
t h at the Phoenicians conducted trade◗ Journalist with the French daily newspaper Libération
DI V ING 
F OR DOL LA RS
◗ Vincent Noce
New technology means shipwrecks swallowed up by the deepest waters can now be reached.
But who owns the precious finds? Some countries allow a free-for-all of plundering
Underwater treasures: exploring the wreck of a 16th-century galleon that sank off the Philippine coast.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
42 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
the divers realized they had been excava-
ting two wrecks that had sunk one on top
of the other.
At that time, no laws or official bodies
r e g u l ated underwater archaeologi c a l
exploration in France or anywhere else.In
1966 President Charles de Gaulle’s
minister of culture, André Malraux, set
up an underwater archaeological explora-
tion division and made it compulsory to
declare finds in French territorial waters.
In 1989, two years after a similar law
had been passed in the United States,
France adopted legi s l ation that gave 
the state sole ownership rights to all sun-
ken treasures found in its terri t o ri a l
waters. Until then, it had been possible to
share them. As a result, the number of
declarations plummeted from about 250
a year to under 50. Seven years later, the
g ove rnment tried to counter the 
drop by announcing rewards of up to
200,000 French francs (approx i m at e l y
$30,000) for discovering such treasures,
depending on its scientific value. But
those rewards are rarely paid: explorers
risk breaking the law since a single
amphora can fetch up to 10,000 French
francs ($1,500) on the market.
U n aware amateur dive rs think
amphorae do not “talk.”That is a big mis-
take, because they do. They can tell us
along that route. A wine decanter (sho-
wing that wine was decanted in those
days), stone anchors, food crockery and a
censer were found among Ty rr h e n i a n
amphorae typical of the period, which
allowed researchers to roughly determine
the date the ships went down as well as
where they sailed from.
“More important discoveries should
come in the near future that could signifi-
cantly alter our understanding of ancient
maritime trade,” predicts Ballard. The
discovery off Sicily of Roman ships dating
from between 100 BC and 400 AD has
already confirmed a long-disputed theory
according to which the Romans were
quite capable of sailing in deep water a
long way from the coast.
A question
of ownership
Yet until only half a century ago, when
the autonomous deep-sea diving suit was
invented, it was still impossible to go
anywhere near deep-sea wrecks. In 1952
Jacques Cousteau led the first underwater
archaeological expedition off Marseilles,
which was a very busy Mediterranean
port in Roman times. His team brought
up Greek and Roman amphorae, which
puzzled specialists at first because they
were at least a century apart in age.Then
when the wreck occurred, the nationality
of the crew and how the cargo was ship-
ped. And the discovery of amphorae is
what usually indicates that an ancient
wreck is nearby, concealed in the sand.
For the 14 centuries between 700 BC
and 700 AD, these large jars were used to
t r a n s p o rt wine, o i l , pickled products,
spices, tea and other goods. After that,
hundreds of years went by before vessels
once again began carrying items—can-
nons and porcelain this time—that future
archaeologists and treasure-hunters could
use as clues to detect the locations of
shipwrecks. The years in between are a
blank, either because wrecks disintegrated
or remain invisible, or because maritime
trade collapsed.
Site leasing
to private investors
For example, a barn a c l e - e n c ru s t e d
cannon tipped archaeologists off to the
presence of a wrecked French fleet off
Ve n e z u e l a ’s Las Aves islands. King 
Louis XIV had dispatched the warships to
drive the Dutch out of the Caribbean.
Commanded by Count Jean d’Estrées,
the French looted Tobago before heading
to Curaçao, where they would have defea-
ted the Dutch had not half the 13 war-
ships and 17 privateers sunk in a storm on
May 11, 1678. Five hundred of the 5,000
crewmen were drowned and 1,000 died
of starvation or disease after being stran-
ded on desert islands.The disaster put an
end to France’s dream of ruling unchal-
lenged in the Caribbean, which quickly
became a haven for pirates.
Though they no longer fly the skull
and crossbones, p i r ates are still there
today. About 15 years ago, a Venezuelan,
Charles Brewer-Carias, and an American,
Barry Clifford, one of the world’s best-
k n own shipwreck hunters , found the
French flagship Le Terrible, which had 70
cannon and a crew of 500, amid other
wrecks at the site.
Clifford says he was shocked by the
lease of the site to a private investor. “The
Venezuelan people will someday look
back in horror at what is being permitted
to happen to Las Ave s ,” he say s.
Venezuela, which does not have a public
archaeological body that could explore
the site,gave a construction company cal-
led Mespa exclusive permission to exca-
vate and sell whatever they could find.
“We had an archaeologist on board the
research ve s s e l ,” s ays the firm , w h i c h
admits it wants to make a profit by setting
up a discovery “industry”.
“In every single case where countries
Drawing up an inventory of Ming dynasty porcelain found in a 16th-century shipwreck.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
S I G N S  O F  T H E  T I M E S
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 43
have issued permits for treasure hunting,
they have always ended up the losers,”
says Florida archaeologist John de Bry.
“Piracy is alive and well.” Mespa thinks it
can find Count d’Estrées’ and his officers’
p e rsonal va l u a b l e s , but archaeologi s t s
doubt a war fleet would have been car-
rying much “treasure.” However, they
fear the historical and archaeologi c a l
value of items will be lost, as well as the
wreck’s position.
The wrecks also cast light on how
ships were designed and built in the days
French minister Colbert was creating a
royal navy and an entire industry around
it. Recording the exact position of the
various items on the sea’s floor before
bringing them up to the surface is an
extremely delicat e , costly and time-
consuming task. All underwater explora-
tion is very expensive and comes without
any guarantee of success.
Since profit is the treasure-hunters’
only motive, and every day of exploration
costs a small fortune, they are in a hurry
to bring up whatever can be sold, even if
it means destroying everything in their
way. Some even use explosives to reach
what they want.
They have no interest in items that
cannot be sold but which may be of ines-
timable value to historians, such as a pot-
tery shard bearing an inscription that may
provide clues about a ship’s route, a piece
of shoe that can tell much about how the
s a i l o rs dressed or a skeleton show i n g
wounds or nutritional deficiencies. The
hull of the Maurithuis, which sank off
Guinea on its way back from China in
1609, was still lined with nearly 20,000
plates of almost pure zinc, showing that
Chinese metallurgists were very far ahead
of their European counterparts.
The problem of granting exploration
permits is much greater in Portugal’s
Azores island chain, which has one of the
world’s biggest concentrations of wrecks
because it was a necessary stopover for
ships crossing the A t l a n t i c. Po rt u g a l ’s
museum of archaeology has listed 850
sunken Spanish and Po rtuguese ships
there, many loaded with gold.
Eighty-eight of them lie in the Bay of
Hangra de Heroismo, where the British
treasure-hunter John Grittan showed up
in 1972, eventually spending two months
in jail and being banned from exploring.
Nearly a quarter of a century later he
returned—after the law changed to allow
private firms to explore—as manager of
Arqueonauticas, chaired by Rear Admiral
Isaias Gomes Texeira, one of the first
companies to obtain an exploration and
excavation permit.
One of the most famous treasure-hun-
ters, Florida-based Bob Marx, joined the
undertaking, lured by a deal giving him
half of whatever was discovered at a depth
of up to 50 metres and 70 per cent of
what was found further down. “This law
has sacrificed our history to money,” says
Francisco Alves of the national archaeolo-
gy museum. Meanwhile, the Spanish are
frantically poring over legal documents to
see if they have a right to save galleons
that are their own heritage.
FINDERS KEEPERS 
A ND MIL I TARY EXCEP T IONS
P atrick O’Keefe, an Australian lawyer and cul-
tural heritage specialist, says the discovery of
the Titanic was a turning point. Exploration teams
now have the technology to go anywhere and to
e x cavate at once-unthinkable depths. “Interna-
tional regulations are urgently needed because no
wreck is safe anymore,” he says. 
But the international community is lagging far
behind the technology. Some countries have more or
less successfully established rules on underw a t e r
a r c h a e o l o gy within their territorial waters (usually 12
miles, or 22 km., from their coasts). However, few are
developing the resources to ca r ry out their ow n
undersea explorations. In international waters, any-
thing goes. Individuals are entitled to keep what they
find, and every ship that is “saved” belongs to who-
mever discovered it, in keeping with the maritime tra-
dition of “salvage on the high seas.”
But UNESCO’s Lyndel Prott says, “the wrecks
aren’t saved when they’re found by a treasure-
hunter. On the contrary, they’re the ones who
endanger them.” The 1982 Convention on the
Law of the Sea barely touched on the issue of
underwater treasure.
UNESCO has drawn up a planned convention
that would ban all commercial use of underwater
wrecks. Unfortunately, the world’s major mariti-
me and technological powers—the United States,
Britain, France and Japan—want to keep their
hands free and look askance at any attempt to
take away their freedom of action. 
Their navies cite the tradition that warships
forever belong to the country that launched them
to keep others from touching their wrecks, even
when they are four centuries old. The United
States used this argument to win its right to the
wreck of the Alabama, a Confederate privateer
sunk by the Union navy off the French port of
Cherbourg towards the end of the American Civil
War. And what about a Spanish galleon wrecked
in the Portuguese Azores? When is a wreck dee-
med to have been abandoned by its country or
its owner?
Two meetings of specialists—a third has been
set for July 2000—have so far failed to sort out the
mess, or to obtain a firm political commitment
from the international community to lay down
the law in Davy Jones’s locker. ■
Sometimes treasure-hunters hit the
j a c k p o t . One of them, the impetuous
Michael Hatcher, netted about $15 mil-
lion from the piecemeal sale of Chinese
porcelain he found in the wreck of the
Dutch ship Geldermalsen, which sank in
the China Sea in 1752. Christie’s, the
world’s biggest auction house, sold the
pieces off for a while but then quietly
stopped, probably because of the contro-
versy and legal problems raised.
H atcher claims he found the wreck in
i n t e rn ational wat e rs , but researchers say it
was lying within Indonesia’s terri t o rial limits.
Ja k a rta opened an inve s t i g at i o n , and one of
the inve s t i g at o rs drowned in a diving acci-
dent at the site, adding to the detective nove l
aspect of the case. E ventually the Indone-
sians dropped the enquiry, but ru m o u rs tied
t h at move to the corruption of the Suhart o
family then ruling the country.
“All this money going around just
makes matters worse because it is recy-
cled to pay for new explorations,” says
Lyndel Prott,a legal expert on world heri-
tage matters with UNESCO. “Countries
allow the kind of pillage of their underwa-
ter treasures that they would never tolera-
te on land.” ■
Since profit is the treasure-
hunters’ only motive, 
and every day of explora t i o n
costs a small fortune, they are
in a hurry to bring up
whatever can be sold, even 
if it means destroying
e v e rything in their way.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
C O N N E X I O N S
44 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
The court threw out the case. Yet the
system’s technical shortcomings, inclu-
ding the inability to prove a voter’s identi-
ty and to ensure the secrecy of the ballot,
were deemed unimport a n t . N e a r l y
86,000 Democrats cast ballots, 40,000 of
them through the Internet. Three-quar-
ters of the e-voters were between 18 and
35, an age group that is usually less inter-
ested in voting than their elders. Only
slightly over 12,000 people bothered to
turn out for the previous such primary
four years earlier.
Was the experiment conclusive? A
local paper, the Tucson Citizen, said many
voters were drawn more by the method’s
novelty than by the candidates. More
generally, Stephen Hess, of the Brookings
Institute, thinks that “procedural ques-
tions are not what prevents people from
voting.” But Santini believes that e-voting
is “an amazing opportunity for our
exhausted democratic system.”
The American firm Election.com has
announced it will provide such voting ser-
vices for next November’s U.S. presiden-
tial election. And Steve Case, of the huge
Internet service provider (ISP) America
Online (AOL), thinks experiments like
the one in Arizona are further proof that
the Internet is “transforming the way
people interact with their local and natio-
nal governments.”
Political parties, new citizens’ move-
ments and public authorities are increa-
singly quick to grasp that fact, at least in
c o u n t ries we a l t hy enough to have 
widespread Internet access. Until everyo-
ne has interactive digital television, the
Net seems to be the quickest, cheapest
and only truly interactive way for citizens
to exchange information and opinions
between themselves as well as with their
elected representatives.
Most political parties now have their
own websites to present their platforms.
Numerous public services use them to
explain their structure, operations and
aims and to answer people’s questions by
e-mail. And many municipalities provide
information and consult citizens by e-
mail before taking any major decision.
A chance
to voice views
New citizens groups that believe in a
different kind of globalisation also make
intensive use of the Internet. In South
Korea,where nearly half the population is
on line, 600 community organizations
recently posted a “black list” on the Web
of 90 parliamentary candidates with
murky pasts, including some who had
been convicted of corruption. Fifty-eight
of them were defeated in the subsequent
election, some by virtual unknowns.
Askwith suggests going one step fur-
ther. He sharply criticised the way a typi-
cal British Royal Commission set up to
study a controversial issue operated. In
practice, only the views of the panel’s
members and the “experts” who appea-
red before it carried any weight, he said.
The citizens who attended the hearing
were few and unrepresentative.They were
“mostly the retired and unemploye d ,
since the ill-publicised event took place
on a Thursday afternoon.” They did not
really understand the issue at hand and
were asked to speak only at the end of the
hearing, and even then only briefly and
for appearance’s sake.
■
A “dumb rage of impotence” is how
Richard A s k w i t h , a senior editori a l
writer for the British newspaper The
Independent on Sunday d e s c ribed his fee-
lings in a recent art i c l e . “ E ve rything our
government does it does in my name, yet
what say have I ever had? One vote in five
ye a rs , for a choice of scarcely distingui-
shable bands of disingenuous careeri s t s.
What kind of choice is that?”
Askwith is implacable:“Parliamentary
d e m o c r a cy, i nvented in the days of the
h o rse and cart and perfected during the
steam age,” has had its day. “ I t ’s time
g ove rnments found a new way to let the
people decide.”1
The solution? The Internet.
“ E - d e m o c r a cy will wake politics up,” s ay s
French MP André Santini,m ayor of the Pa ri s
s u burb of Issy-les-Moulineaux, which he has
made into a model Internet-connected tow n .
“I’m sure it can cure people’s disaffection
with politics, just as the Internet economy is
b e ating unemploy m e n t .”2
The Arizona
experiment
The clearest sign of this political apa-
thy is low voter turnout, to the point that
“these days universal suffrage is now only
universal in name,” says Santini.The first
I n t e rnet voting experiment was the
Democratic Party primary election in the
U.S. state of Arizona that took place from
March 7 to 11, 2000. Opponents of e-
voting went to court, arguing that it dis-
criminated against poor people without
Internet access (the “digital divide”).
IN T ERNET 
TO THE RESCUE 
OF DEMOCRACY ?
◗ René Lefort
Advocates of e-democracy profess that the Internet is the only way to bridge the gap 
between disaffected citizens and politicians. “Nonsense” say others
◗ Director of the UNESCO Courier
1. The Independent, September 4, 1999.
2.The French daily Libération, April 21,2000.
E-voting is “an amazing
o p p o r t u n i ty for our exhausted
d e m o c ratic system.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
C O N N E X I O N S
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 45
In contrast, he says, stand the poten-
tial advantages of the Internet, which is
already used by campaigners who, though
scattered across the world, are all on-line
at the same time, sometimes several hun-
dred of them for days on end, delving
deeply into an issue and expressing infor-
med and considered opinions. T h e s e
groups are known as amphinets. It all
costs very little compared with a face-to-
face meeting of all the participants.
Askwith asks, why not use this method
and open it up to ordinary citizens chosen
at random? Their views, r e p r e s e n t i n g
public opinion, would reach the “repre-
sentatives of the people,” who would no
longer just vaguely hear them but be for-
ced to take their views seriously.
Other e-democracy advocates go even
f u rt h e r. R ather than settling for using elec-
tronic means merely to improve the flawe d
representativeness of elected officials, why
not do without them altogether? Marc
Strassman, executive director of the Cam-
paign for Digital Democracy,3 suggests an
electronic system good enough to eliminat e
any possibility of fraud.Voters would use it
to voice their views on every possible and
imaginable issue, from whether a country
should undertake a military operation to
deciding on the content of a proposed law.
The system would be advanced enough
to immediately and electronically analyse
the full range of opinions. Strassman says it
would correct the “large and gr owing imba-
lance in political influence between com-
mon people and the professional political
class and its clients who increasingly domi-
nate the initiative process.”
The time has gone when parliamentary
decisions were taken after “ c o n s u l t i n g
dozens of people whose opinions and views
are highly privileged at the expense of mil-
lions who are disadvantaged by this
c o n c e n t r ation of powe r ,” Strassman say s.
We should switch to “direct electronic
d e m o c r a cy ” where “millions of e-mail vo t e s
d e t e rmine the direction of the republic.” I n
s h o rt , he argues, “the Net becomes so
p owe r f u l , so ubiquitous and so easy to use”
that it can “let us govern ourselves.”
Santini thinks this will be the key to “a
shift from an occasional democracy to a
continuous one.” It would be akin to revi-
New ways: casting votes via the Internet during the Democratic Party’s primary in Arizona in March 2000.
ving the agora in ancient A t h e n s , the cradle
of democracy where the city’s 20,000 citi-
zens who were entitled to met and debat e d .
The Net would make such a forum per-
m a n e n t , instantaneous and, when eve ry
p e rson on the planet is on line, wo r l d w i d e .
Over-reliance
on technology
“Nonsense,” says Frenchman Jacques
A t t a l i , the founder of Planetfin a n c e ,4 an elec-
tronic microcredit netwo r k . F i rs t , the agora
would not be a democratic ideal: nobody has
thought of reviving it where that would be
p o s s i b l e , such as a village of a few hundred
i n h a b i t a n t s. W hy? Because the representa-
t i ve system would remain indispensable.
There is no doubt the system is in
crisis, says Patrick Viveret, who writes for
the French magazine Transversales Science
Culture. He notes a tendency in represen-
tative systems towards delegating authori-
ty that could go as far as confiscating it
altogether. So citizen participation would
be absolutely vital to genuine
r e p r e s e n t at i o n , and the Net wo u l d
3. www.digitaldemocracy.org 4. www.planetfinance.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
C O N N E X I O N S
46 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
read nor write?  Of course we must teach
them how, which is a long-term underta-
king. We can also make use of technology.
N owa d ay s , vo i c e - a c t i vated computers and
Braille gi ve blind people access to the
I n t e rn e t . I t ’s easy to imagine similar devices
for illiterate people. The energy situation is
just as bad. Fe wer than 10 per cent of
Malians have access to electricity or tele-
phones. What can be done?  In the short
t e rm we must settle for equipment that
runs on batteries,for example.
Which medium encourages the broadest
possible participation in the democratic
process in Mali today?
T h e r e ’s no question it’s radio, w h i c h
overcomes the dual problems of illiteracy
and communication in the va rious nat i o n a l
l a n g u a g e s.Transistor radios are small, c h e a p
and battery-powered. What the transistor
radio is today, the mobile phone will be
t o m o rr ow. Soon the Internet will be acces-
sible by mobile phone, and I’m sure that will
help us take a big leap forward.
Mobile phones with Internet access will be
tremendously expensive.
True, but radios were also very expen-
s i ve when they first appeared. It might
seem illusory to picture the spread of mobile
phones in A f ri c a , but technology is deve l o-
ping ve ry quickly, which brings prices dow n
just as fa s t . Political determ i n ation and
the commitment of companies will be cru-
cial to the future of such technology in
Africa.
If the Internet was widespread in Mali today,
how would it affect democracy?
It would encourage more citizens to
take part in the democratic process. It
would probably be more effective than
radio in helping them to learn things and
to voice their opinions. At election time,
computerised voting would solve major
problems, such as the participation of
Malians living abroad (20-25 per cent of
the population) and of villagers who must
sometimes travel 20-30 kilometers to
reach the nearing polling station. But,
technical problems aside, Malians are not
exactly flocking to the voting booth. They
seem to have lost faith in the country’s
political leaders, and we mustn’t rely on
the Internet to make up for their lack of
motivation. ■
Interview by Jasmina Sopova, 
UNESCO Courier journalist
■
Do democra cy and the Internet go together i n
Africa?
They don’t, because the Internet has
only just started appearing on the continent.
To become a tool of democracy, the Intern e t
must become democratic itself!  The Web
has penetrated every country in the world,
but only two per cent of the globe’s popu-
lation have access to it. In most African
countries, the Internet is used only by an
elite living mostly in big cities. To make it
more widespread, we need support from the
wealthy countries.
What do you expect from them?
That they help us develop an infra-
structure as cheaply as possible while
taking local conditions into account.
We’re not asking for hand-outs. If they
decide to invest, they have everything to
gain, especially in economies of scale.
Ninety-eight per cent of the wo r l d ’s
population is not on line yet—that’s bil-
lions of people. However poor they are,
they represent an incredible market. The
countries of the South will gain too,
because new technology helps to spread
information, which is a tremendous asset
in promoting the growth of democracy.
Then there’s the issue of solidari t y. R i c h
countries invest a lot to foster democracy
around the wo r l d . If the Internet is a means
of helping to achieve that end, we ’d be baf-
fled if they didn’t help us overcome the
obstacles in our way.
What are those obstacles?
The first major stumbling block is illi-
t e r a cy, which concerns about half of Mali’s
population. What’s the point of giving all
citizens Internet access if they can neither
A FRICA: CELL PHONES 
F OR CI T IZ ENSHIP
Ibrahima N’Diaye, the mayor of Mali’s capital Bamako, is banking on the Internet to boost
democracy in Africa via specially-outfitted cell phones
p r ovide “substantial opport u n i t i e s ” i n
that regard.
But making e-democracy a “global alter-
n at i ve ” would mean giving too much powe r
to the “ t e c h n i c i s m ” which is taking over the
m o d e rn economy, the idea that “ p r o b l e m s
can be solved by technology, i n d e p e n d e n t l y
of the playe rs invo l ve d ,” wa rns V i ve r e t .
D e m o c r a cy requires “ c o l l e c t i ve intelli-
g e n c e ” , which is much more than merely the
sum of different opinions, as they are ins-
tantly served up by opinion polls today and
will be by the Internet tomorr ow (the
“ d e m o c r a cy of opinions”).There needs to
be “time for careful refle c t i o n ,n u rtured by
opinions and counter-opinions bri n gi n g
together mediat o rs who say what they think
in the public arena,” he say s.
Also needed, says Attali, is the “time
for political initiat i ves to prove their
worth.” That might entail a period of
unpopularity before they eventually gain
widespread support. The alternative, he
says, is an “Internet world” that would
lead to “excessively reversible and contra-
dictory decisions”, and consequently to a
“dictatorship of the here and now.” ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
I N T E R V I E W
June 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 47
Do you think research to decode the human
genome should be placed in the public
domain?
We cannot patent basic knowledge of
the sequence.What we possess in our own
organisms, biologically speaking, cannot
be patented even by law. But applications
derived from knowledge of our genes can
be. The U.S. company Celera Genomics
seems to be leading the race to decode the
entire human genome sequence.
According to press reports, the firm has
already decoded the entire sequence—
some 50 million “bits” of DNA—though
they still have to fit the pieces together,
rather like a jigsaw puzzle. On the other
side is the public consortium, made up of
teams from a number of countries wor-
king through their national public health
i n s t i t u t e s , which are proceeding more
slowly and hope to finish the sequencing
in two years’ time. But they are progres-
sing in a more orderly fashion. So that
when they do finish the sequences, they
will know exactly where each part goes.At
first the private company tried to patent
the sequences, and there were many
public fig u r e s , including some ve ry
renowned scientists such as the presidents
of the American Academy of Science and
of the British Royal Society, who opposed
the “patentability” of gene sequences. Bill
Clinton and Tony Blair also protested.
The company seems to have backed down
and will make its results public. However,
what can be patented are the possible
uses of those sequences in methods to
cure specific illnesses.
Are we witnessing the excessive
commercialisation of science?
Pa rt l y, ye s. There might be excessive
c o m m e r c i a l i s ation if the proper limits are
not imposed.There is an interesting case in
connection with cloning: scientists from a
research institute at the Unive rsity of
Wisconsin succeeded in 1998 in deri v i n g
M A RG A RI TA SA LAS :
K NO W L EDGE 
TO DISPEL FE A R
Margarita Salas, a Spanish pioneer in molecular biology, dismisses alarmist reactions to recent
scientific advances and stays thoroughly optimistic on all fronts
and culturing human embryonic stem cells
—cells that are the parent cells of all tissues
in the body.The achievement has profound
i m p l i c ations for transplant medicine. O n l y
p ri vate firms currently fund this wo r k ,
because in the United States there is a law
banning the public funding of research
based on human embryo s. It is ve ry dange-
rous to let this sort of work remain solely in
p ri vate hands. These firms will be able to
p atent their findings and make people fork
out presumably large sums of money when
they have to undergo transplant operat i o n s.
If the funding came from public sources,
this monopoly wo u l d n ’t exist.
But are governments investing enough in basic
research?
I t ’s impossible to make generalisat i o n s.
The percentage of gross domestic product
e a rmarked for research in places like the
United States or in some of the most deve-
loped European countries hove rs around
t wo to 2.5 per cent, sometimes even more.
Spain has one of the lowest levels of resear-
ch funding in Europe, standing at 0.9 per
c e n t , one point below the European Union
ave r a g e , so there’s a long way for us to go.
The interesting thing about pri vate fun-
ding is that it comes not just from bu s i-
n e s s e s , but also from foundations and eve n
from individuals. In the United Stat e s , f o r
e x a m p l e , people who contri bute to resear-
ch funding are entitled to deduct it from
their taxe s , which is not the case in coun-
t ries like Spain. I t ’s vital to promote fis c a l
policies that encourage people to fund
r e s e a r c h .
What are the potential risks of privately
funded research?
It’s dangerous if the results are witheld
and patented in such a way that licenses
are required to use the data.
Scientific research is a highly competitive field.
Is there room for cooperation?
In the first place, scientists do not
work alone. This is no longer the era of
Ramón y Cajal.1 Whether or not they
share affinities, scientists must work in
1. Santiago Ramón y Cajal. Spanish neurologist
(1852-1934). Nobel prize for physiology and
medicine in 1906.
A life’s vocation: Margarita Salas in her lab at Madrid’s Universidad Autónoma.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
I N T E R V I E W
48 The UNESCO Courier - June 2000
teams for the simple reason that it’s
impossible for an isolated individual to
g ather enough knowledge to have an
international impact. In the European
Union, for instance, we are seeing increa-
sing cooperation, because support and
funding are granted to teams formed by
groups from different countries. But in
the private sector, groups working at the
cutting edge of science strive to get there
before their competitors because of the
huge economic stakes involved.
Are scientists doing anything 
to narrow the research gap between 
North and South?
Researchers from the South take part
in some collaborative projects and attend
major intern ational congr e s s e s , but in
general this cooperation has more to do
with institutional reasons than with any
political will to narrow the gap.
Why does cloning frighten people?
Because they think of human cloning
and that scientists will run amok with it.
That’s ridiculous. First, the technology
we have at the moment falls far short of
enabling us to produce cloned humans,
though it’s clear that it will improve until
that becomes possible. But then, what is
the point of making individuals who are
all alike? Over 20 years ago, when the
issue of in vitro fertilisation arose, people
said it was horrific, that it wasn’t natural.
They wondered what sort of children
would be born from this technology.
Would they turn out like monsters? All
sorts of things were said. The first girl
born via this technique is now 23 or 24
years old. She’s perfectly normal and in
vitro fertilisation has solved many fertility
problems. So has it been good or bad for
humanity?
So do you defend cloning?
Once again, we have to make a few dis-
t i n c t i o n s. I think human cloning to produ-
ce individual human beings is repellent,
and in some countries there are law s
against it. But we can envisage cloning a
few stem cells to produce useful organ tis-
sues towards therapeutic ends, or animal
cloning for the same purpose or to make
d ru g s. For example, a gi ven gene can be
implanted in a sheep. These genetically-
m o d i fied animals can then be cloned to
produce large quantities of factor IX, w h i c h
is necessary for blood coagulation and is
used in the treatment of haemophilia.
Should limits be placed on scientific research
to prevent abuse?
Scientists themselves have demanded
that their discoveries not be used against
humanity. Furthermore, bioethics com-
mittees involving scientists have spread all
over the world in the past ten years and
are working with the same aims.The main
purpose of cloning is to obtain useful tis-
sues which can, for example, mitigate the
problem of the body rejecting organ
transplants. There was a proposal to keep
cells from the umbilical cords of new-
borns so that in the future stem cells
could be obtained in order to make tis-
sues. That way, if someone needed an
organ transplant, his or her own cells
would be readily available, and doctors
would be able to culture new tissue from
them. That would circumvent the pro-
blem of rejection and therefore be a very
positive step forward.
Another scientific advance which has sparked
an uproar is genetically modified organisms.
What is your opinion?
Those fears are entirely based on a lack of
k n ow l e d g e . N ature changes slowly all the
time so that it can adapt. In the laborat o ry,
those changes are simply accelerat e d .
Green deputies protesting against cloning at the European Parliament in Strasbourg.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
I N T E R V I E W
crops to arid soil. Though from the
United States, he lived for a long time in
Mexico, and is totally in favour of geneti-
cally modified plants. He thinks the
movement against them is ridiculous in
light of all his work to enable plants to
grow in dry soil.
You seem to have perfect trust in the intrinsic
goodness of scientists.
Science in general is moving in the
right direction, towards helping humani-
ty, not perverting it. New cloning and tis-
sue transplant technology is developed for
the good of human beings. There is no
reason to be afraid, on the contrary.
What can scientists do to put that message
across?
I believe there are more scientists
interested in humanism than the other
way around,because humanists think that
science is too difficult to understand.That
is exactly why the Instituto de España,
A LIFE FOR SCIENCE
Since 19 01, when the Swedish Academy set
up Nobel prizes for achievements in various
s c i e n t i fic disciplines, only 11 women, compared
with 435 men, have received one of the awards.
But with the help of programmes to support
women’s involvement in scientific research
sponsored by UNES CO and the European
Commission, the careers and commitment of
s e v e ral female pioneers have proved that scien-
ce is no longer an all-male domain. Margarita
Salas has faith that “in the not too distant futu-
re women will achieve a rate of participation in
the professional world and in society high
enough for them to believe that they matter at
all levels and in every situation. And not beca u-
se there are quotas: I’m totally against quotas
for women. It’s up to us to conquer the space
that we deserve.” She has done just that by
devoting herself entirely to her profession: “I
like other things too, like music or art… I go to
concerts and exhibitions, but research is the
purpose of my life,” she says. 
Born in Canero in Spain’s Asturias in 1938,
Salas was 16 when the “yearning for discove-
ry” took her to Madrid to study chemistry. At
19 she met Severo Ochoa, who won the Nobel
Prize for Medicine the following year. Ochoa
encouraged her to write a doctoral thesis in
Madrid and, later, to work with him in his New
York laboratory. Today, this molecular biolo-
gist’s résumé is 24 pages long and includes—
besides two honoris causa degrees and over
200 studies and articles in scientific journals—
UNESCO’s Carlos J. Finley prize (1991) and the
Jaime I research prize (1994), among others.
Since 1995, she has headed the Instituto de
España. On January 10, 2000, UNESCO Director-
General Koïchiro Matsuura presented her in
Paris with the UNESCO-L’Oréal prize for the best
European scientist of 1999, an honour for
which 34 candidates were competing. Four
other scientists, one for each continent, were
awarded the same prize. ■
+ …
http://www.forwomeninscience.com
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498 FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:                  Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
Fa rm e rs have traditionally modified plants
through genetic crossbreeding which gene-
r ates seeds that can gr ow in ari d , saline or
other soils. This was possible after a lot of
time and wo r k , and nobody thought it wa s
w r o n g,e ven though it came down to geneti-
cally modifying the seeds.A skin graft is also
a genetic modific at i o n ,though people are not
afraid of it. And genetically modified plants
are no different. Among the 50,000 or
100,000 genes that a plant contains,only one
or two different ones are added to make them
resistant to insects, to a viru s ,or to saline soil.
This is done through ve ry simple experi m e n t s
t h at can last days or we e k s.W hy are people
afraid? Because they don’t know what ’s invo l-
ve d . On the other hand, e ve ry genetically
m o d i fied plant has been tested before it is put
on the market. I do think that food which
comes from genetically modified plants
should be properly labelled so the consumer
can decide. But eating products that come
from genetically modified plants does not
entail any sort of ri s k : I myself would have no
objections to eating them.
What is the exact motive behind creating
genetically modified organisms?
Genetically modified plants can have
nothing but benefits for the human spe-
cies.The other day I read about a kind of
genetically modified rice which produces
a 35 per cent greater crop yield. The
importance for countries suffering from
famines is obvious. It’s true that those
seeds are patented, but over time the
patents will fall into the public domain
and the seeds will be cheaper. Not long
ago we received a visit from Norman
Borlaug, an agronomist who won the
1970 Nobel Prize for his work in adapting
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
I N T E R V I E W
It’s a virus which infects the Bacillus
s u b t i l i s, a non-pathogenic bacteri u m
which is widely used in biotechnology.
When the virus infects this bacterium it
destroys it, but causes no damage to other
organisms. Phi-29 is simple and easy to
handle; it has only 20 genes, in compari-
son to the 100,000 which the human
genome contains. N e ve rt h e l e s s , t h e
control mechanism of this virus is pretty
sophisticated, which makes it something
of a model system. As a result, what we
are studying in the virus can be extrapola-
ted to other virus systems in more com-
plex animals and organisms. The protein
that we have studied in this virus also
exists in a similar form in other viruses
which are not innocuous, or “bad” shall
we say, because they cause diseases like
poliomyelitis, hepatitis B or hepatitis C.
What professional achievement are you most
proud of?
A c t u a l l y, there are two. One is ve ry per-
s o n a l . When I was working in the Seve r o
Ochoa laborat o ry, I found two previously
u n k n own proteins necessary to start syn-
thesising proteins. It was a ve ry import a n t
breakthrough and ve ry satisfying for me,
especially since I was just starting out and
working alone. My second major achieve-
ment was in Spain. I was part of a team that
d i s c overed another protein which is closely
linked to the nucleic acid of the virus on
which we are wo r k i n g .We proved that it wa s
n e c e s s a ry for the replication of viral DNA.
And your greatest disappointment?
A scientist cannot expect success
e ve ry day. There are disappointments
throughout a scientist’s life. There are
times when experiments don’t work, or
when you get stuck in a dead-end and
have to change direction, but they are
minor setbacks and never too serious. I
don’t think I’ve ever had a major disap-
pointment. Besides, I’m an optimist.
Would you say that there is a feminine and a
masculine way of conducting research?
In over 20 years of teaching I’ve had
male and female doctoral and post-docto-
ral students,and I don’t think there is any
single feature that really sets them apart.
Having said that, women have perhaps
been less aggressive and more patient,
while men have tried to be the first to
come up with results. Nowadays, women
are beginning to acquire a level of educa-
tion that is making them bolder about not
always staying one step behind men and
always being more patient than they are.
Apart from that nuance, I don’t see any
differences.
What would you say to a female student who
wants to dedicate her life to scientific
research?
My advice would be the same for a
woman or a man, which is that if they real-
ly enjoy scientific research, they must
u n d e rstand that they will have to dedicat e
t h e m s e l ves 100 per cent to it.There are no
half measures.You either gi ve your life to it,
or you don’t . If you are really prepared to
d e vote all your time to research, then go
a h e a d . And then I tell them it’s for life. ■
Interview by Lucía Iglesias Kuntz, 
UNESCO Courier journalist
which I head and which includes the eight
n ational academies, o f f e rs a series of
conferences that give scientists the chan-
ce to discuss and popularise phy s i c s ,
mathematics and genetics in a rigorous
but simple way, using language the public
can understand. We must work towards
popularising science more widely. That
means extra effort by scientists, but it
ought to be a duty.
What do you think the most important areas
of research will be in this century?
I think one of the most important is the
b r a i n . It is the essential key yet to be disco-
ve r e d : w hy we think, w hy we speak, w h at
the molecular mechanisms are behind our
thought processes. M a ny people are wo r-
king in that area. B e s i d e s , as John Maddox ,
who was editor of N at u r e magazine for
m a ny ye a rs has said, the human being’s
intellectual capacity is so gr e at that at some
point in the future there will be nothing left
to discove r.
Will that lead to boredom?
We l l , neither you nor I will be around to
see it. Take the example we just discussed
c o n c e rning sequencing the human genome,
which is known as “the beginning of the
e n d .” I t ’s one thing to have the sequence
and quite another to know what it is wo rt h
and to understand the function of each one
of our 100,000 genes. By current estimat e s ,
t h at will take another 100 ye a rs , so I don’t
think we’ll have time to get bored.
You’ve spent the last 30 years working with
the phagocytic cell Phi-29. Could you explain
what this is?
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George's Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Jean de Lannoy, 202 av du Roi, B-1060 Brussels. 
Fax: 538 08 41.
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
Oxford Book & Stationery Co, Code No D 820 8 0 52, Scindia House, New
Delhi 110 001. Fax: 33 22 639 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Nalanda Co. Ltd., 30 Bourbon Street, Port Louis. 
Fax: 212 1313 .
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. F ax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
Los Amigos de la UNES CO, Avenida Urquijo 62, 2 Izd., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 94427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Karger Libri AG, Wissenschaftl. Buchhandlung, Pe t e r s g raben 31, 
CH-4009 Basel. Fax: 306 12 34 .
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce
C/C Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: 286 03 26 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
192 pp., 29.7 x 21 cm
175 FF/ 26.68
UNESCO Publishing/IBE
U N E S C O  P u b l i s h i n g
178 pp.
29.7 x 21 cm
150 FF
22.87 
World
Education
report
2000
World Data 
on Education
A Guide to the 
Structure of National
Education Systems
Edited by Massimo Amadio
| An overview of all the actions,
treaties and programmes 
that have taken place over the 
past half-century in favour of
education throughout the world.
| An analysis of the progress
that has actually been made.
| Concise description
of 144 education
systems with statistical
data on primary
education.
The right to education for all
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
m a n y v o i c e s o n e w o r l d
P u b l i s h e d
in 27
l a n g u a g e s
In the next issue:
Fo c u s :
Youth culture s :
the global tracks of music
■ The voice of a genera t i o n : h i p - h o p
■ A Maori warrior goes against the flo w
■ South A f r i c a : l i b e ration musicians meet 
young kwaito upstarts
■ A l g e r i a : passing the crown from rai to ra p
■ Techno appeal: the return of the mass dance 
m o v e m e n t
■ Raving in the A u s t ralian bush:
ecologists and party-goers unite
■ M o ral panic in Goa
Fe a t u res include
■ Through the lens of the Dogon
■ Trade in endangered species: the debate 
over banning
■ Teenage pregnancy: what education can change
■ The embargo on Ira q : a right or a crime?
■ Taj Mahal and Lima: heritage before business
■ Vital connections: the South goes mobile
■ Interview with A r g e n t i n a ’s Quino,
father of the Mafalda comic strip
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
www.unesco.org/courier
]]>
</page>
</document>
