<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="120752eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
PLANET
Chernobyl:
the political fall-
out continues
ETHICS
U.S. death penalty:
a debate 
without morals?
SIGNS OF  THE TIMES
Moving Africa
with a 
dance rhythm
Canada:$3.95 Cdn,United Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
THE RAGE FOR 
ASIAN CINEMA
October  2000
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
World Heritage 
R e v i e w
S u b s c r i p t i o n s :
Ediciones San Marcos, Maldonado 65,
28006, Madrid, Spain
tel. : +34 91 309 20 80      fax : +34 91 444 80 51
e-mail: sanmarcos@flashnet.es
The timeless trea-
sures of our natural
and cultural heritage
and the efforts
underway 
to safeguard them
for future genera-
tions
Subscription rates
6 issues: 
190 FF (4,750 ptas, 28.97)
single issue: 
35 FF (900 ptas, 5.34)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
C O N T E N T S
OCTOBER 2000
53rd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Octavi Marti
French edition: Sophie Boukhari
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: The Mouveur,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (moderator), Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corral,Alcino Da
C o s t a , Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh(Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” ,p l u s
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. S i g n e d
articles reprinted must bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be
supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Th e
UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfic h e )
b y : (1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfil m s
( X e r o x ) , Ann A r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C . R . Microcard Edition,
Indian Head Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and
Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road, Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - OCTOBER2000
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Paris by
UN E S C O. Printed in Fr a n c e. Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and
additional mailing offic e s.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 9-2000-OPI 00-592 A
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UNESCO Courier staff. The boundaries on maps do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the
United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 Shooting the Breeze
Photos by the Balalaika Workshop, text by Sophie Boukhari
PLANET
10 Chernobyl: the political fall-out continues
Fred Pearce
1 4 B e l a r u s : facing the disaster alone
Interview with Vasily Nesterenko
WORLD OF LEARNING
15 The bias behind nomadic education
Saverio Kratli
1 7 S c h o o l , the Tuaregs’ new weapon
Yves Bergeret
ETHICS
40 U.S. death penalty: victims seize the high ground
Ivan Briscoe
SIGNS OF THE TIMES
43 Moving Africa with a dance rhythm
Interview with Alphonse Tiérou
4 5 Tell me how you dance and I’ll tell you who you are
Alphonse Tiérou
CONNEXIONS
46 Digital disappeara n c e s
Sara Gould and Marie-Thérèse Varlamoff
INTERVIEW
48 Tuenjai Deetes: a bridge to the hill tribes
Corrections
The painting presented on the cover of the September issue and on page 36 is the work of American artist John
Martin/SIS, Paris. The image was erroneously accredited to French artist Michel Granger.
In the September issue, an article on p. 42 mistakenly referred to the Mostar Bridge as a World Heritage site.
© East Film,Seoul
The rage for 
Asian cinema
The year 2000 looks particularly auspicious for
Asian cinema. Iran, Japan, South Korea and
China have been stealing the limelight from the
West at the most prestigious film festivals. Each
of these new waves has followed its own course.
Building on the momentum, a few South
American directors are also leaving their mark
on the other side of the world.Will new techno-
logies push the movement even further?
Fo c u s
Detailed table of contents on page 18
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Shooting  
4 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
The fly-past
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
 the Bre e z e
“ I take pictures of everything— 
of my family and especially my friends.
It’s pure pleasure.”
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 5
You gotta be niii-ce to the reporter!”says 19-year-old Romain,who likes to
make his friends laugh.And he knows all about what behind a good image.
He and all the enthused amateur photographers at the Balalaika workshop
in the suburb of Bourtzwiller,outside Mulhouse (see box p.8 ) , are ready, e v e n
eager to answer “the reporter’s ”q u e s t i o n s.They seem happy to talk, to be lis-
tened to,to show off their work.Th e y ’re pleased to be known and appreciated.
About 40 per cent of this suburb’s 15,000 inhabitants vote for the extreme
right-wing National Front and these youngsters,mostly of North African origin,
voice in words the very things they strive to show in their pictures.
“They have a quiet attitude to life,” says Eric Vazzoler, the photogra-
pher who runs the workshop.“They rarely take pictures of burnt-out cars.”
The youths insist photography hasn’t “ s a v e d ”them from a so-called “ s o r d i d
u n i v e r s e,” as some articles have claimed.But everyone has found something
in it to match their needs. It has given them pleasure and self-confid e n c e,a n d
they have stopped being afraid of what other people think. It has also
opened up a new social and cultural horizon,a new world of imagination.
Like many youths, those in Mulhouse are anxious to meet people and
have new experiences.But they are also hesitant, torn between family ties and
the call of the outside world,between love of photography, which requires
devotion and time, and love itself, which takes them elsewhere. Here is a
sample of their thoughts.
Samir, 16,training in car maintenance:
“ I ’ve been taking photos for two years now. I take pictures of every-
thing—of my family and especially my friends. I t ’s pure pleasure.Once you’v e
done photography yourself, you don’t see other people’s photos in the same
way any more.You look at them more carefully and search for a message.”
Cub photographers from immigrant backgrounds 
take an unusually candid look at their troubled
neighbourhood on the outskirts of the French city 
of Mulhouse
PHOTOS BY THE BALALAIKA WORKSHOP,
TEXT BY SOPHIE BOUKHARI
PHOTOS BY JAMEL BÉRIBÈCHE, MORAD BOUKHEMERRA, SAMIA CHIBOUT,
JOËL DIORFLAR, MESTÛRE GÜLER, NADYA KREITE.
SOPHIE BOUKHARI IS A Unesco Courier JOURNALIST.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Shooting the Bre e z e
Who minds anyway?
6 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
“You don’t need to be saved just because you
live in a poor neighbourhood.”
After prayers during the Eid festival
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 7
Samia, 22,studying management:
“ With Eric,we do printing and developing.Yo u ’ve got to be serious and
learn how to do it. We’ve seen how we can do it all ourselves and on top of
that our work’s getting recognized.
The articles they’ve written about us say that ‘thanks to photography,
t h e y ’ve got themselves out of a rut.’ Th a t ’s not true.Anyone can come to the
workshop but not everybody does.You don’t need to be saved just because
you live in a poor neighbourhood.One paper said burnt-out cars were part
of our daily lives,but that’s not true either.They’re interested in us because
we live in a place like this. People say:‘Look at where they come from and
yet they still manage to take photos.’ Or else it’s:‘That’s how those neigh-
bourhoods are!’ So they’re either trying to see through our eyes or else they
think we’ve been saved.
Through taking photos I’ve made new friends. Before, I would never
have gone to an exhibition.Nowadays, I walk in, look and talk with people
from different social backgrounds.
Once a photographer rang me from Germany to buy one of my pictures.
I was proud. My parents were too and told everyone about it. Eventually I’d
like to have my own photo lab if I have the money. But I don’t want to be a
professional photographer. It’s too hard.”
Nagi, 26,works with a maintenance company:
“I came here from Tunisia four years ago and I didn’t have any friends.
I ’d already done a little photography in Tu n i s i a ,and I kept it up.I t ’s helped me
to find out how people live here and to meet people. I like the atmosphere of
the photo lab even though there are some tricky moments with Eric.S o m e t i m e s
I don’t like what he says.But it’s taught me I have my faults,that I’m stubborn.”
Rap group La Baze in concert
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Shooting the Bre e z e
8 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
B a l a l a i k a ’s Photogra p h e rs
One day, art photographer Eric Vazzoler decided that he’d had enough traipsing
around Paris trying to sell his work, mainly about the former Soviet Union. So he
agreed to take charge of a “neighbourhood cultural project”in the northern suburb
of Mulhouse, in eastern France, and not surprisingly, gave his workshop a Russian
name. Projects like these were started by the Ministry of Culture in 1996 to try to
“reduce social divisions.”
“I was going to stay seven months, but I’ve been here nearly four years now,”says Eric,
3 7 .H e ’s about to move on, but his project has lasted longer than all the others and
been much praised.There have been exhibitions in France and other countries,g e n e r o u s
press coverage and a book soon to be published.
The youngsters credit Eric with its success.“He isn’t easy and he’s demanding to work
with,but what a pro!”they say. “We can always knock on his door at 11 o’clock at
night to get a roll of film.”
E r i c ,who lives in the neighbourhood, is more modest.“When I arrived here, there wa s
n o t h i n g . I filled a gap,and I have the cream of the crop.The really disturbed kids can’t
take the studious atmosphere of the lab.” And in his gruff but kindly way, he adds:
“Their pictures are very nicely composed.They’ve got a distinct style. They’re refre-
shing and generous. At their age I was busy copying the great masters. These kids
aren’t influenced by anyone.” Except by Eric,of course. ■
Kamel, 19,training to service machinery and computers:
“I’ve loved everything to do with pictures since I was little, when I
dreamt of being a film producer.The photo workshop has been a godsend.
Especially when I found out it only cost $5 a year to join.
P h o t o g r a p h y ’s classy.When you do it, you meet different people, f r o m
other social classes. The lab is also fun. We have a really good time there.
B e f o r e, when I looked at a photo, it didn’t mean anything to me. Now I know
how to criticize my own photos and other people’s. I ’ve learned how to
defend my perspective and my work.We don’t get much chance to exhibit
what we do, but we can help to change the image of young people.
When I tell people I take pictures, e v e r y o n e ’s amazed. Hip-hop is
seen as normal,but photography surprises people.They think this must be
a good guy and they’re less afraid of me.
Once, I was stopped going into a nightclub. My face must not be the
right shade of colour. I got out my camera and as soon as they saw I’d come
to take pictures for free, they opened the door. Another time, I worked for
someone who did body-painting. I was paid for it and I felt recognized.
As soon as there’s a project, I’m interested. I can see myself doing it for
a living but not as a photo-journalist or a portrait photographer. I’d like to
be an artistic photographer.Yo u ’re freer. My goal is to develop my own style
and make a name for myself.”
Sandrine, 18,training in commercial management:
“At last I have a passion.B e f o r e, I wasn’t doing much of anything. I was
pretty self-absorbed. Now I have friends.The hardest part is to accept the
criticism of Eric and the others, because I’m personally attached to the
photos I take. For a while, I even stopped taking them.Then I started again.
I got a bit of self-confidence.”
Jamel, 24,studying at the Mulhouse art school:
“I’m the one who does all the graffiti art in the neighbourhood. I go by
the name ‘Serio’ because S, E and R are the letters I draw best and also
because they remind me of the word ‘ s e r i o u s.’ I started out wanting to study
music but the equipment’s expensive. So I got into painting. I’ll need pho-
tography at least until the end of my time at art school. I’m interested in
images. I think about them all the time.” ■
Neighbourhood games  
Three colours
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 9
My brother reads the Koran
Taking a shower
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
A
10 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
sigh of relief ripples across Europe as
engineers prepare to shut down Cher-
n o b y l , the world’s most feared nuclear
power plant, on December 15th. Politi-
cians have finally brokered a deal in
which Western donors foot the bill of
about two billion dollars to close and
fully entomb the Ukrainian reactors.Ye t
for many ordinary citizens, the nightmare
continues.
Just a few months ago, on April 26th,
thousands marched solemnly through the
towns of Belarus, Ukraine and eastern
Russia to commemorate the dead from
the nuclear disaster 14 years before. At
1:26 am bells tolled to mark the moment
when a Chernobyl reactor blew and a
deadly radioactive fall-out began to
blanket their fields and towns.
But as well as mourning, there was
f e a r. Fear of the continuing radiation,
which could claim thousands more.And
fear of speaking out of turn. That night,
Yuri Bandazhevsky, rector of the Gomel
Medical Institute in Belarus until his
arrest last year, was in forced internal
exile in the capital of Minsk. He is one of
many researchers who say their work has
been suppressed or ignored by govern-
ments anxious to play down the radia-
tion risks their citizens still face.
Estimates of the death toll to date
range from the 32 offered by U N n u c l e a r
scientists to the 15,000 suggested by some
Ukrainian researchers. In Ju n e, s c i e n t i s t s
at the U N’s Scientific Committee on the
Effects of Atomic Radiation (U N S C E A R)
reported that “there is no evidence of a
major public health impact attributable to
r a d i a t i o n , apart from a high level of thy-
roid cancer in children [from which] few
should die.” Yet the previous day the U N
S e c r e t a r y - G e n e r a l ,Ko fiA n n a n ,a p p e a r e d
to disagree when he said:“ The catastrophe
is far from over. It continues to have a
devastating effect not only on the health
of the people, but on every aspect of
s o c i e t y.”So what is the truth? And how do
these disparities arise?
The accident at the Chernobyl nuclear
P L A N E T
Just how bad was the world’s
worst nuclear disaster? The
answer lies hidden within a
web of politics and scientific
uncertainty enmeshing the UN
and eastern European
governments
FRED PEARCE
ENVIRONMENTALJOURNALIST AND
CONSULTANT FORTHE BRITISHWEEKLY MAGAZINE, The New
Scientist
After the ex p l o s i o n , 50,000 “ l i q u i d a t o rs ”w e re sent onto the roof of the reactor to “clean up”
C h e r n o b y l :
the political fall-out
continues 
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 11
power plant reduced the Number Four
reactor to an inferno spewing out a radio-
active cloud for ten days. It released a
hundred times more radioactivity than
the atomic bombs at Hiroshima and
Nagasaki combined. For several days
there was total silence, before the panic
evacuation of some 116,000 people from
an exclusion zone that stretched up to
30 kilometres from the plant.
Only years after the accident did the
public learn that a larger zone some 150
kilometres away near the Belarus town of
Gomel and extending into Russia suf-
fered heavy fall-out in rain shortly after
the accident. It emerged in 1989 that a
fifth of Belarus had been signific a n t l y
c o n t a m i n a t e d . Some 400,000 people were
r e s e t t l e d .And today around four million
people still live in areas with some ack-
nowledged contamination.
O f ficial secrecy inside the Soviet Union
and its successor governments about the
extent of the contamination continues to
bedevil the task of keeping people safe,
says Greenpeace’s Chernobyl specialist
Tobias Muenchmeyer.Researchers inside
the affected countries agree.“A regime of
s e c r e cy was accepted in our country from
the very first second the catastrophe hap-
p e n e d ,”says Vladimir Chernousenko, t h e
Ukrainian scientist who co-ordinated the
post-accident clean-up.
A partial information blackout by
g o v e r n m e n t s, combined with scientific
c a u t i o n , has helped lead U N agencies into
seriously underestimating the death toll,
Muenchmeyer believes. Critics of the
nuclear industry such as Rosalie Bertell,
president of the International Institute
of Concern for Public Health in To r o n t o,
say there is another political reason.Th e y
point to a 1959 agreement between the
International Atomic Energy A g e n cy and
the World Health Organization, w h i c h
said that “the I A E A had the primary res-
ponsibility for encouraging,assisting and
co-ordinating research on, and the deve-
lopment and practical application of
atomic energy.”According to Bertell,“ t h e
I A E A has since considered itself to be the
watchdog over information about radia-
tion health effects which is distributed to
the public.” Bertell and other organiza-
tions this year called for the W H O t o
amend the agreement.
The most important radioactive iso-
topes released at Chernobyl were iodine
and caesium. Iodine-131 has a half-life
(the time it takes for half the atoms of a
radioactive isotope to decay) of eight
days. It was mostly inhaled and eaten in
contaminated food. Caesium-137 has a
half-life of some 30 years. It is still present
in soils and vegetation and continues to
contaminate people through foodstuff.
Some lesser isotopes have half-lives of
hundreds or even thousands of years.
C o n t ro v e rsy over 
the casualty list
Who suffered? In the front line were
the “liquidators”—the estimated 600,000
to 800,000 soldiers and public employees
drafted in to make the reactor safe and
bury contaminated waste. Some 50,000 of
them worked on top of the reactor.“ Th e y
were supposed to stay on the roof to fig h t
the fire for only 90 seconds, then be
r e p l a c e d . One can easily guess this did
not happen,” says Jean-Pierre Revel,
senior health official at the International
Federation of the Red Cross.As a result,
237 liquidators were hospitalized;32 died.
But since then, the Soviet Union and
its successors have been unable or
unwilling to keep track of this most-at-
risk group. According to Leonid Ilyin, a
former Russian member of the Interna-
tional Commission on Radiological Pro-
t e c t i o n ,“none of these men was registered
by name. None was checked [for subse-
quent health] on a regular basis.They all
went back to their homes.”This failure is
probably the largest organizational cause
of the disputes over Chernobyl’s death
t o l l .Last A p r i l ,Viacheslav Grishin,p r e s i-
dent of the Chernobyl League—a Kiev-
based organization that claims to represent
the liquidators—said 15,000 liquidators
had died and 50,000 were handicapped.
His source was a controversial estimate by
C h e r n o u s e n k o, based on likely cancer
rates from radiation doses that he believes
the liquidators received.
Cancers have been the biggest long-
term medical fear. By 1991, doctors were
reporting many cases of thyroid cancer
among children under four at the time of
the disaster. In 1992,a group of Western
researchers, including Keith Baverstock
of the WHO, agreed that Chernobyl was
the likely cause. Yet it was only in 1995,
after some 800 cases had emerged, that
the UN system formally accepted the fin-
the surface.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
d i n g.This delay had serious implications
in finding and treating the disease, w h i c h
is not fatal if caught early enough.
Playing politics and
crushing dissent
The conclusion had been initially
controversial partly because the evidence
from Hiroshima and Nagasaki suggested
that there should be far fewer cases. B u t
politics also entered the equation. Th e
E c o n o m i s t magazine speculated that “ i f
the health risks have been underestimated
or understated, the American govern-
ment could face new lawsuits on every-
thing from the Nevada [nuclear] tests to
the Three Mile Island nuclear accident in
1 9 7 9 .”
At any rate, there are now some 1,800
recorded cases of thyroid cancer attri-
buted to Chernobyl. In the most conta-
minated districts, such as Gomel, c h i l d-
hood rates are 200 times those in western
E u r o p e. Estimates of the total number of
cases expected to arise in the future range
from a “few thousand,” suggested by the
I A E A, to the 66,000 predicted for a single
group—Belarusian children under four
at the time of the disaster—by W H O s c i e n-
tist Elisabeth Cardis, who stressed that
“the risk estimates are very uncertain.”
What about other cancers which take
longer to develop? Offic i a l l y, the W H O
stands by its assessment of 1996 that while
“there have been some reports of
increases in the incidence of specific mali-
gnancies in some populations living in
contaminated territories and in liquida-
t o r s, these reports are not consistent and
could reflect differences in the follow-up
of exposed populations.” But some of its
scientists are sceptical.They ask not what
can be proved,but what can be expected
on the basis of known science.
Based on Hiroshima and Nagasaki,
Baverstock expects an “ e x c e s s ” of some
6,600 fatal cancers, including 470 leu-
kaemia cases. But a team of Belarusian
doctors claims to have found leukaemia
rates four times the national average
among heavily exposed liquidators.A n d
there are fears that,as with thyroid cancer,
rates could be far higher than expected.
But scientific uncertainty should not
detract from the fact that there are poli-
tical reasons why the truth about the
disaster may remain hidden, s a y s
Muenchmeyer of Greenpeace. National
g o v e r n m e n t s, who act as gatekeepers for
most of the statistics reaching U N a g e n c i e s,
have a political agenda, he says. Th e
Ukraine is running 14 nuclear reactors
with another four under construction,
according to the IAEA. “So the Ukraine
d o e s n ’t want to ruin the image of nuclear
power by stressing the harm done by
C h e r n o b y l ,” says Muenchmeyer, “ b u t
they also want aid for health programmes.
So then they are interested in showing the
b u r d e n .Often they contradict themselves
within a few days.”
The Belarus government has consis-
tently downplayed the disaster, e v e n
though the country received an estimated
70 per cent of the fall-out.“ They decided
that the territory and the number of
people affected are so great, and the
government so poor, that they cannot
solve the problem.They decided to shut
down dissent,” says Muenchmeyer. This
has hampered research and apparently
prevented findings by local scientists from
reaching UN agencies.
Two years ago, Rosa Goncharova of
the Institute of Genetics and Cytology
in Minsk reported evidence that conge-
nital abnormalities were turning up in
the children of those irradiated by Cher-
nobyl. She told a conference that since
1985, cases of cleft palate, Down’s syn-
drome and other deformities had
increased by 
83 per cent in the areas most heavily
c o n t a m i n a t e d , 30 per cent in moderately 
contaminated areas and 24 per cent in
“clean”areas.
But two years later, when contacted
for this article, Cardis of the WHO said
she had “not received copies of the
p a p e r ” by Goncharova. Nor had she
received copies of work by the director of
the independent Belarusian Institute of
Radiation Safety (Belrad),Vasily Neste-
r e n k o. He had found that in the most
contaminated areas, the incidence of
diseases of the circulatory system had
risen fourfold and deaths among children
from respiratory diseases were up 14-
fold (see interview).
The dangers of the
twilight zone
And consider the fate of Yuri Ban-
d a z h e v s k y, whose case has been taken
up by Amnesty International.As rector of
the Gomel Medical Institute, he carried
out autopsies at the city’s forensic
m o r g u e, on bodies whose deaths were
not considered connected to Chernobyl.
He examined their internal organs and
compared them to the organs of rats that
he had fed grain containing radioactive
c a e s i u m .He was shocked by his fin d i n g s :
“ The pathological modifications of the
kidneys, heart,liver and lungs was iden-
tical to those among the experimental
r a t s.” From this he concluded,“that accu-
mulation of radiocaesium in the organs
played a major role in the triggering of
pathological responses.” In other words,
it made them ill and even killed them.
His paper went ignored. His subse-
quent criticism of the post-Chernobyl
research conducted by the Ministry of
Health brought him more enemies.And
last summer he was arrested on unspeci-
fied bribery charges, and locked up for six
m o n t h s. His computer and all his fil e s
were confiscated and he remains confin e d
Lethally close to Chernobyl, the abandoned city of Pripiat in Ukraine.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 13
to Minsk “under investigation.”
People are still being exposed to
radiation from Chernobyl. In large areas
of Belarus in particular the environment
is still heavily contaminated. The W H O
says “some foods produced by private
farmers do exceed [WHO limits].” But it
points out that most large farms mini-
mize take-up of radioactivity in soils by
deep ploughing and applying fertilizers.
“No food produced by collective farms
now exceeds the limits.”
But thousands of people rely on pri-
vate farms, according to Belrad’s Neste-
r e n k o, who maintains that a quarter of
the food grown inside the contaminated
zone supersedes official radioactivity
l i m i t s. More than 500 villages are drin-
king contaminated milk.M o r e o v e r,m a n y
people rely on “ w i l d ” produce such as
m u s h r o o m s, berries and hunted meat—
the most risky food of all says the WHO’s
B a v e r s t o c k .
A n d , of course, there are the people
who return to live a twilight life inside
the exclusion zone, replanting their
contaminated gardens, gathering food
from the forests and raiding abandoned
food stores. Most are old women, w h o
judged that the radioactivity could do
them little harm at their age.But there are
recent unconfirmed reports of a baby
being born there. The tragedy, as Ko fi
Annan said, goes on. ■
P L A N E T
In the weeks after the accident, coniferous trees and mammals that ate
ground vegetation received the highest doses of radiation.Trees died and
were buried by the liquidators. Cows grazing heavily contaminated grass
near the reactor died. So too did most of the mice in the exclusion zone.
Most intriguingly for scientists, the survivors were almost all female. O n l y
after four generations did male numbers begin to recover.
Mona Dreicer, a U. S. researcher who collated material for a major inter-
national conference held on the Chernobyl aftermath in 1996 (Vi e n n a ) ,
says that levels of radioactivity in surface soils had fallen by a factor of
a hundred by the autumn of 1986, and “by 1989 the natural environment
had begun to recover.” B a d l y
damaged conifers were making
cones again and the rodent
population was growing fast.
To d a y, the roll call of wildlife
includes wild boar, e l k , d e e r,
foxes and some 200 wolves.The
list of animals failing to return is
relatively short: pigeons and rats,
which rely on human leftovers to
flo u r i s h , as well as swa l l o w s,
which have apparently fallen
prey to genetic disorders.
But the region remains heavily
contaminated,particularly soils,
v e g e t a t i o n , the tree wood and
leaf litter on the forest floors that
cover roughly a third of the
exclusion zone.The zone has become, in effect,the world’s first radioac-
tive nature reserve. It is a fantastic laboratory to analyze the impact of
radioactive fall-out.Yet says the head of the reserve, Nikolai Voronetsky,
most researchers have avoided travelling there, fearing for their own per-
sonal safety. It is not surprising, p e r h a p s. Three out of a team of ten bota-
nists who visited in 1986 are now dead,he says.
Vo r o n e t s k y ’s own researchers have shown that the internal organs of the
wolves and most other creatures remain radioactive.The wolves are particu-
larly worrisome as they stray outside of the reserve, hunting for sheep and
h o r s e s.The boar tallied the highest geiger-counter readings,says Vo r o n t e s k y,
because they dig into contaminated soil in search of food.
Rosa Goncharova of the Institute of Genetics and Cytology in Minsk says
that she has observed increased “genetic anomalies” in rodents and fis h
in the contaminated zone. Dreicer downplays such reports.“ The frequency
of these reported defects was shown to be similar in highly contaminated
and non-contaminated regions. . . Leading to the conclusion that they
were not due to increased radiation dose,” she says. But critics see this
as UN “ s p i n .” For one thing, you would not expect a close correlation bet-
ween defects and crude fall-out levels because, as Dreicer herself has
pointed out,the vagaries of local soils can lead to grazing animals recei-
ving high doses even in areas that had low fall-out.
There are many ways that radioactivity can “leak into the wider environ-
m e n t .” Earlier this year there were fears that fires raging across peat
bogs in the contaminated zones could unleash radioactive clouds of
smoke.The U.S. embassy sent a team to check for fall-out,but reportedly
none was found. Wa t e r, h o w e v e r, has proven to be a serious conduit for
c o n t a m i n a t i o n .
During spring flo o d i n g ,c o n c e n-
trations of radioactive materials
in local rivers increases by up to
four times. In fact, the contami-
nated zone had been flo o d e d
six times since the accident,
each time washing radioactive
material down river, e s p e c i a l l y
along the banks of the Pripyat,
which drains into the Dneiper
and ultimately the Black Sea.
With nine million Ukrainians
drinking water from reservoirs
on the Dneiper and many more
eating food irrigated by the river
wa t e r s, a European Commission
report has concluded that radio-
active water is the most important environmental threat still posed by the
a c c i d e n t .
Fourteen years after the disaster,radioactive materials are remaining mobile
within soils and ecosystems much more than scientists had expected. J i m
Smith of the British government’s Centre for Ecology and Hydrology repor-
ted in May this year that “the environment is not cleaning itself of the pol-
lution at the rate we previously thought.” In places, he said caesium wa s
being “re-released into the ecosystem” as the Chernobyl legacy begins a
new cycle. ■
F.P.
The world’s first radioactive re s e r v e
Testing the levels of soil contamination in the exclusion zone.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
You maintain that the effects of the Cher-
nobyl disaster have been played down not
just by your own country’s leaders but also
by international organizations...
The U N Scientific Committee on the
Effects of Atomic Radiation (U N S C E A R)
relies on the figures of the International
Atomic Energy A g e n cy (I A E A) , w h i c h
represents the nuclear lobby. In evalua-
ting the disaster, the I A E A has compared
Chernobyl to Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
But in Ja p a n , the thermo-nuclear reac-
tions took place entirely in the air and the
soil was not contaminated. After the
Chernobyl fir e, neighbouring countries
were bombarded by hundreds of tonnes
of radionuclides (or particles).The soil of
Belarus alone absorbed two-thirds of the
fall-out and some of the nuclides, such as
c a e s i u m - 1 3 7 , stay radioactive for more
than 30 years. Food accounts for 80 per
cent of the long-term contamination of
the population. Since the disaster, m y
institute has been systematically moni-
toring children with special spectrome-
t e r s. My colleague, P r o f. Yuri Bandaz-
h e v s k y, was the first to link the
accumulation of radioactivity in people’s
bodies to their illnesses. The contami-
nation has caused many diseases not
recognized by international organiza-
t i o n s.
What are these ailments?
After doing thousands of autopsies, B a n-
dazhevsky and his team showed that cae-
sium-137 had accumulated in muscle tissue,
beginning with the heart.Two-thirds of the
2,000 children monitored in the highly-
contaminated area of Gomel have heart
p r o b l e m s. The concentration of caesium in
the kidneys has also caused serious mal-
functions from an early age. Caesium in
the eye muscles leads to cataracts. Fo r
e x a m p l e, a 1997 study in Svetlovisy, n e a r
G o m e l , found that a quarter of children
between 13 and 15 had cataracts.
During pregnancy, the placenta in
mothers-to-be stores caesium which irra-
diates the foetus and after the birth,the
mother breastfeeds the baby with conta-
minated milk. This leads to several
d i s e a s e s, such as “Chernobyl A I D S,”
which is an immunity disorder.The radio-
active particles also combine with lead
(which was used in 1986 to put out the fir e
and was then absorbed into the ground)
to cause mental retardation and stomach
a i l m e n t s. We are heading towards a
national disaster.
What does your country need most?
Two million people, a quarter of them
c h i l d r e n ,are living in contaminated areas.
We have to set up mobile units to monitor
these people and what they eat. My ins-
titute doesn’t have many resources, s o
can only do very little monitoring. It’s
also threatened with closure because the
government doesn’t want the “ d i s t u r-
b i n g ”news to spread. The contaminated
children need to be sent for a month’s
stay in clean areas at least twice a year
and be given pectin-based pills,which are
e f f e c t i v e, very cheap and made in
U k r a i n e, though not here. We have to set
up centres for young mothers in areas
where they can eat uncontaminated food
while pregnant and breast-feeding.
Why hasn’t your government raised the
alarm about all this?
Belarus is facing alone a disaster it’s not
responsible for. Neither Russia nor
U k r a i n e,where Chernobyl is located,h a s
helped us. Our national budget only
allows a small amount of money to be
spent on the victims and our government
o f ficials believe they know best. But they
h a v e n ’t properly evaluated the situation.
Th e y ’ve lied to tens of thousands of Rus-
sians who have come from “hot spots” o r
crisis areas in the former Soviet Union to
live in the contaminated region.1 Th e y ’r e
still lying to their own people. They have
a head-in-the-sand attitude. Only massive
international aid and strong logistical
support by the government will ensure
the survival of my people in the long run.■
1 After the collapse of the Soviet Union, 25 million
Russians found themselves living outside the new
b o rders of Russia, mainly in Central Asia and the
Caucasus where there was and still is war. T h e
Belarusian government encouraged them to settle in
the contaminated areas by giving them housing,
jobs and resident status.
P L A N E T
C h e r n o b y l : the political fall-out continues
B E L A R U S :
FACING THE DISASTER A L O N E
INTERVIEW BY GALIA ACKERMAN
OF RADIO FRANCE INTERNATIONALE
The Chernobyl nuclear disaster
continues to threaten the
survival of the Belarusian
people, says Vasily Nesterenko,
a local physicist*
On April 26,2000, crowds marched in downtown Minsk to mark the anniversary of the disaster.
* Vasily Nesterenko is former director
of the Nuclear Energy Institute of the
National Academy of Sciences of Belarus
and currently head of the independent
Institute of Radiation Safety (Belrad)
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 15
L
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
All too often, education has been touted as the key to transforming nomadic identity,
which goes a long way towards explaining its patchy record
SAVERIO KRATLI
RESEARCHER AT THE INSTITUTE OF DEVELOPMENT STUDIES
(SUSSEX)
ife in the dry lands is harsh. There is no
sheltering shade, the sun cracks the soil
and watering the animals is a daunting
task in the dry season.But the pastoralists
know how to survive. They know that
nobody can go without eating and drin-
king for as long as they can,except per-
haps the other group of pastoralists on the
other side of the escarpment. When the
rainy season finally comes, if indeed it
ever does, the pasture is glorious and the
herd fattens quickly.They know their ani-
mals one by one, their colour and beha-
viour, their “parents”and so forth,going
back several generations.To the pastora-
lists, these animals are more than beau-
tiful;they have individuality.
A clash of cultures
When addressing the education of
pastoralists, it is all too often forgotten
that to be a  “pastoralist” means being
Turkana (Kenya),Rabari (India),Qash-
qa’i (Iran), or from some other commu-
n i t y. It is an identity these people take
pride in,a complex and sophisticated way
of life which,with all its harshness, they
profoundly love.E d u c a t i o n ,h o w e v e r, h a s
mainly been intended as an instrument to
transform the pastoralists into something
else. The history of mass education pro-
grammes for nomads has been that of an
encounter between people seeking new
ways of adapting to an evolving context—
monetarization of the economy, c o m m o-
dification of labour and privatization of
land—and a broad set of actors, f r o m
p o l i cy-makers and project officers to tea-
chers and local officials, who widely
believe that nomads have to be “saved”
from their way of life. It is upon this cul-
tural clash that the “problem”of delive-
ring mass education to nomads has been
framed and policy solutions devised.
The bias behind
nomadic education
After years of war in Somalia, schools have re-opened despite poor conditions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
Nomadic herders number several tens
of millions of people, mainly in African
dry lands, the Middle East, and south-
w e s t , south and central A s i a .They include
some of the most vulnerable of all sou-
thern populations. They often make a
significant contribution to national food
p r o d u c t i o n . M o b i l i t y, harsh environ-
mental conditions and remoteness have
always stood as barriers to the provision
of formal education, and millions of
nomadic pastoral children remain out-
side the system.
Political motives
underpin initiatives
M o n g o l i a , a country where the majo-
rity of the population is nomadic, stands
as a case apart. Compulsory state edu-
cation for children between eight and 18
began in 1940.The system relied on hun-
dreds of schools with dormitory facilities
built in all rural settlements. Education
was free,accounting for more than15 per
cent of GDP. Schools were well staffed,
with highly motivated and comparatively
well-paid teachers, most of whom came
from a nomadic background.Within the
following 20 years, Mongolia passed from
around two to more than 90 per cent lite-
r a cy and by 1990,before liberalization, t h e
country had almost reached a rate of 100
per cent. This unprecedented fig u r e —
unmatched ever since with a nomadic
population—can hardly be explained in
terms of innovative programme content.
The standard curriculum was highly aca-
demic and teacher-centred in nature. I n s-
tead, the crucial factor had more to do
with a sympathetic human environment
and the absence of a rift between the cul-
ture of the school and that of the nomads.
But Mongolia is a chiefly nomadic
c o u n t r y.Although scarce documentation
and widely differing contexts make it dif-
ficult to paint a general history of nomadic
e d u c a t i o n , political motives always
underpin initiatives. In Somalia,a short-
lived rural development campaign laun-
ched in 1974 took a bold approach: the
government simply closed down all
secondary schools for one year and sent
20,000 students and teachers to the coun-
tryside to teach literacy to the largely
nomadic population.They used methods
learnt in Koranic schools, writing letters
on a blackboard, reading them aloud and
asking pupils to repeat. This was, at least
in intention, a two-way campaign, as one
of the slogans underlined: “ What you
k n o w, t e a c h ; what you do not know,
l e a r n .” Hindered by the 1974 drought,
the campaign was nevertheless a surpri-
sing success: in only seven months,9 1 0 , 0 0 0
of the 1.2 million students registered sat
the final test and 800,000 passed.
A more common reason for provi-
ding education to nomadic pastoralists
emerged when a number of newly inde-
pendent African states realized that some
of the dry lands and the livestock were
valuable “ n a t i o n a l ” r e s o u r c e s. As such,
pastoralists had to become more closely
integrated into the economy, notably by
increasing production. The task of
“ m o d e r n i z i n g ” the nomads was left to
e d u c a t i o n . The Kenyan case is instruc-
t i v e. In 1970, the Parliament amended
the Anglo-Maasai agreement,which kept
the reserves closed to non-Maasai, and
launched a programme aimed at impro-
ving enrolment by setting up low-cost
boarding schools. But the new educa-
tional facilities were flooded by pupils
from non-pastoral ethnic groups and were
disregarded by the Maasai. In the late
1 9 7 0 s, when an evaluation found that the
boarding schools were operating below
c a p a c i t y, the government decided to tem-
porarily cut funds to the programme.
Some analysts argued that carrying out
education in the absence of economic
development and related social services
had been a mistake.The 1984-1988 Deve-
lopment Plan concentrated on improving
livestock resources, marketing facilities
and banking services, assuming that
demand for education would stem from
increased monetary resources. R a t h e r
than look at the programme’s shortco-
m i n g s, the blame was put on pastoralists’
“backward” way of life. All that policy-
makers had to do was reverse the equa-
tion: from education as a path towards
development, to development as a path
towards education.
Mainstream explanations for the fai-
lure of education provision in pastoral
areas usually blame the recipients. It is
assumed that the problem stems from the
nomads’ obsolete way of life and cultural
c o n s e r v a t i s m , rather than from the inca-
pacity of a national system to respond to
the living conditions of a signific a n t
number of its citizens.Research is practi-
cally inexistent on the impact of educa-
t i o n .Figures on enrolment and attendance
rely on local records that are often incom-
plete and inaccurate,yet these figures are
usually the main yardstick used to mea-
sure the outcomes of education pro-
g r a m m e s. The most profound impact of
these programmes remains an untold
s t o r y. Social norms, networks and rela-
tionships of authority play a critical role in
pastoral livelihood systems, which edu-
cation often tends to undermine.A divide
often sets in between educated and non-
educated members of communities.
Recent research underlines how projects
of directed change are embedded into
education programmes for nomads, t e n-
ding to antagonize local learning and
socialization patterns. Although govern-
ments may no longer be trying to trans-
form pastoralists into settled farmers, t h e y
are still trying to transform them into
“something else,” such as “ m o d e r n ”l i v e-
stock producers, as in Nigeria.
Hooking nomads 
to the system
With the push for decentralization
and cost-sharing in education over the
past ten years, some governments are tur-
ning to innovative partnerships with inter-
national development agencies rather
than investing in mass education pro-
g r a m m e s. Pastoral areas are particularly
t a r g e t e d , given that they have the lowest
l i t e r a cy rates. A few non-formal educa-
tion programmes are now focusing on
providing a service directly related to life
in pastoral societies.By moving away from
the emphasis on productivity, there is
room to address crucial livelihood issues
such as resource access, c o n flict manage-
ment and local advocacy. In Senegal, t r a i-
ning modules have been developed in
local languages for pastoralists. In Ke n y a ,
an out-of-school programme launched in
1992 has set up learning centres offering
non-formal primary education to nomad
c h i l d r e n , with strong community invol-
v e m e n t .
But these alternative approaches do
not address the structural inadequacy of
education systems.They are often about
getting beneficiaries “ h o o k e d ” to “ fit the
s y s t e m ,” and are but a parallel second-
class education. Unless the power issue
behind the formal/non-formal divide is
a d d r e s s e d , even the best education pro-
grammes may only result into channel-
ling out-of-school children into persis-
tently unresponsive systems. ■
Although governments 
may no longer 
be trying to transform 
pastoralists into 
settled farmers, they are
still trying to 
transform them into 
“something else,”
such as “modern”
livestock producers
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 17
“For the past few years,people in all the
settlements have supported and
valued schooling,” says a representative
of local school parents.“ Things are chan-
ging and our nomadic culture seems to be
e v o l v i n g.”
The pupils at the little schoolhouse at
I m b a s s a s s o u t è n e, south of Ti m b u k t u ,
include Peul and Tuareg nomad children.
Its six classes offer both primary and secon-
dary education, catering to students from
six to 18. In the evening, l i t e r a cy classes
are held there for adults.
Not all schools in the region boast such a
r e c o r d .The school at Djebok,40 kms east
of Gao, counts 254 children enrolled in
four primary classes,but only 25 in its fiv e
secondary grades. Mohamed ag Hama-
d i d a , the headmaster, says about 15 per
cent of the children drop out each year.Th e
r e a s o n s : some settlements are far from the
s c h o o l , while tradition stipulates that loo-
king after cattle is more noble and wor-
thwhile than attending what is known as
“the French school.”
The children are taught by the “ c o n v e r-
g e n t ”m e t h o d , which mainly relies on using
Ta m a z i g h t , the Tuareg mother tongue,
when they start school.The first year,t h r e e
quarters of the lessons are in Ta m a z i g h t .
Fr e n c h , M a l i ’s official language, takes on
increasing importance to become the only
one used by the time the children reach
their sixth year.
Education in its “ m o d e r n ” form was intro-
duced during the French colonial era and
coldly welcomed by the Tu a r e g s.The tribal
chiefs refused to let their sons go to school,
sending children taken from serf families
i n s t e a d . After independence, d i s t r u s t
remained towards an institution that was
foreign to the traditional culture and threa-
tened to force nomads into adopting a
sedentary lifestyle.
But recent events have revolutionized the
lives of the Tu a r e g s. Major droughts in
1973 and 1984 and then armed rebellion in
the early 1990s1 and subsequent repres-
sion caused large migrations. The peace
agreements in Mali (1992) and Niger
(1995) allowed the displaced people to
return with the help of the UN High Com-
mission for Refugees, but not until 1996.
Many parents then changed their attitude
and concluded that going to school could
help their offspring find jobs away from the
world of nomadic cattle-herding.E d u c a t i o n
had also proved useful during the peace
negotiations and later to help Tu a r e g s
secure government jobs.
Many partners are involved in the educa-
tion of Tuareg children, including the Wo r l d
B a n k , the Organization of Petroleum-
Exporting Countries (O P E P) , U S A I D, t h e
Islamic Development Bank, the Fr e n c h
group Volunteers for Progress and Dutch
and French government aid bodies.
The host countries contribute too.E m m a-
nuel Sagara, director of basic education
for the Gao region, held a seminar in the
Chadian capital, N d j a m e n a , in Ja n u a r y
2 0 0 0 , that brought together education
experts and officials from Burkina Fa s o,
M a u r i t a n i a , N i g e r, Chad and Mali. Po l i-
cies vary widely from country to country.
Chad has travelling schools, whose tea-
chers move with the nomads. Niger has
opted for a mixed system, with children
spending six months in a school and the rest
of the year tending animals. Mali has
chosen to set up a series of “ s i t e s ” w h i c h
include a school and a nearby well to attract
and accommodate the nomads.
Sagara says school attendance by 6-12-
y e a r-olds is 36 per cent in the Gao
region,with girls accounting for 18 per cent
of the total. But there are no figures on
how many nomad children are among
them because language and ethnic origin
are not seen as relevant.
Souleymane ag Mehdi,who runs T é l o u é t ,
an NGO specialized on economic deve-
lopment in northern Mali, also notes a
change of attitude among the Tuaregs that
he attributes to a post-rebellion re-eva-
l u a t i o n . Despite the risk of educated young
Tuaregs becoming assimilated,he stresses
the role that the most enlightened of them
could play in avoiding this outcome. Th e
key is to support Tuareg culture, n a m e l y
through publishing,n e w s p a p e r s,m u s e u m s
and research and documentation centres.
So far, none of the above exist. ■
1. Fo l l owing an armed rebellion and ethnic strife in
northern Mali between 1990 and 1994,over 150,000
Malians fled the country. By mid-1995, due to the
implementation of a peace agreement, and efforts
by the Malian authorities to secure national recon-
c i l i a t i o n , stability has been re-established in nor-
thern Mali.
S C H O O L ,
THE T UAREGS’ NEW W E A P O N
YVES BERGERET
FRENCH WRITERAND TEACHER, FOUNDER OFTHE LANGUAGE
AND SPACEASSOCIATION SPECIALIZEDIN NORTH-SOUTH
ARTISTIC PROJECTS
The Tuaregs have shed their
longtime reticence towards
schooling but questions remain
over how the system chooses
to deal with their nomadic
lifestyle. Countries in sub-
Saharan Africa have come up
with different solutions
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
The bias behind nomadic education
Mohamed ag Hamadida teaches the Tuareg language to a child from Djebok in northern Mali.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
C o n t e n t s
1 . F rom West to East
2 0 A s i a ’s magic lantern
Alain Ja l l a d e a u
2 2 B reathless We s t , brilliant East
Joan Dupont
2 4 Film score c a rd s
2 . New waves
2 6 After the re v o l u t i o n :
the cinema will carry us
Mamad Haghighat
2 8 Shooting on a shoestring
Brice Pe d r o l e t t i
3 1 South Ko re a :f reedom or love?
I  Myung-hee
3 3 The Chinese conundrum
Jacob Wo n g
3 4 Don’t blink now, i t ’s Kazakhstan
Cloé Drieu
3 4 A rg e n t i n a ’s gritty re s u rg e n c e
David Oubiña
36 B ra z i l : revival at risk
Pedro Butcher
3 7 D i re c t o rs in exile
Interviews by Sophie Boukhari
3 9 Te c h n o l o g y, the artist’s ally
Yousri Nasrallah
THE RA
A s i a n
he year 2000 is looking particularly auspicious for Asian cinema.
From Iran, Ja p a n , South Korea or China, fil m m a kers in the East
are raking in awards at the most prestigious festivals, such as
those in Cannes,Venice and Locarno (pp.2 0 - 2 1 ) .The same crea-
tive muscle is hard to find in the We s t , where the industry is now
dominated by the laws of entertainment and profit (pp. 2 2 - 2 3 ) .
While neo-realism seems to be a major influ e n c e, each of these
new waves has marked its own path. I r o n i c a l l y,as Iranian cinema
grabs the international limelight, it is losing the official acceptance
it won after the revolution of 1979 (pp.2 6 - 2 8 ) . In the dying days of Ja p a n ’s major studios,
young fil m m a kers are finding limited budgets alongside new-found freedom to focus on
a disillusioned generation (pp. 2 8 - 3 0 ) .The advent of democracy in South Korea and efforts
to defend local production have spawned a new generation of directors who are winning
plaudits at home and abroad.At the same time, C h i n a ’s “sixth generation” of directors is
flourishing despite public indifference
and the struggle against censorship
( p. 3 3 ) .
On the other side of the world, s o m e
South American directors are making
their own wa v e s. The seventh art is
proving to be particularly fertile in
A r g e n t i n a ,where directors  are turning
a poetic eye to life on the street (pp. 3 4 -
3 6 ) . While fil m m a kers in exile add to
the ranks of this movement (pp. 3 7 - 3 8 ) ,
the advent of new technologies (p.
39) may carry it to new creative
g r o u n d s.
Dossier concept and coordination by
Sophie Boukhari and James Burnet,
respectively journalist and editor in
chief of the UNESCO Courier.
F O C U S
T
18 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
When you make films and are lucky
enough to get one shown at a festival, y o u
can then set off round the world taking
your movie from one festival to another.
I t ’s a big opportunity,not just for making
your name–vital for those of us outside
mainstream cinema–but also because you
discover other independent films and
come to realize you’re not alone.
I have followed this fil m m a k e r ’s pil-
g r i m a g e, and have met fellow directors
in Ta i w a n ,South Ko r e a , Japan and Iran. I n
B e r l i n , N a n t e s, Rotterdam and at Sun-
d a n c e, I have also witnessed a powerful
new wave of films coming from Asia that
has coincided with a revival of fil m m a-
king in Latin A m e r i c a .There is no single
theme or style. Each film is different, b u t
all are intent on depicting real life and all
are made with paltry resources.
I shot one of my fil m s,R a p a d o ( C l o s e
C u t ) , with a grant from the Rotterdam
festival to write a script outline.What pays
for a synopsis in Europe can fund a whole
feature film in A r g e n t i n a . Having no
money isn’t a virtue,but it does focus your
mind and forces you to look for narra-
tive solutions that fit your budget. Ja p a-
nese filmmakers agree with us South
Americans that film schools should be
used as a nursery for directors and tech-
n i c i a n s, and as a way into the profession.
Buenos Aires now has more than 15 fil m
s c h o o l s, a profusion that can only inspire
people to make fil m s.
Has Western cinema lost its way?
M a y b e,but there are still some great direc-
t o r s. Films made in developed countries
these days tend to suffocate you with the
same tired old plots and easy images
drawn from ubiquitous television. In Iran,
you can still tackle a subject in a fresh
and innocent way and film something with
the feeling that you are showing it on
screen for the first time. Iranian film is
rife with this “ fir s t - t i m e ”e l e m e n t , and it’s
what gives it special strength.Fi l m m a k e r s
in Taiwan work under different condi-
t i o n s, but they too have managed to get
down to basics by delving into their coun-
t r y ’s past and casting light on a society
that sometimes doubts its very existence.
You can’t say the same for the Ja p a-
nese film industry, which has a long history
and is now rivalled by a fast-growing
audio-visual world of TV channels and
video games. Th e r e ’s no room for inno-
cence here, only crafty, intelligent and
subversive use of current formats. D i r e c-
tors from Japan and Hong Kong borrow
a d v e r t i s i n g, video and other well-worn
techniques to tell other stories and spark
a different set of emotions.
This upsurge of “new waves” may be
related to the general decline or disap-
pearance of government subsidies for
fil m m a k i n g.Apart from the United States,
where such help isn’t needed because of
the captive domestic market,g o v e r n m e n t
aid to local film industries has dried up in
most countries.The subsidies that remain
have in any case stagnated, with money
nearly always going to the same places. I t
would be tremendous if governments
were to back something that has now
begun to flower naturally in so many parts
of the world.
A lack of state support has perhaps
given rise to another trend. This is the
rise of new producers, individuals and
institutions working without any national
anchoring. It’s another form of globali-
z a t i o n , aimed at specific film projects
satisfying particular desires and needs,
bringing together people who share a
love for a special kind of cinema and a
wish to see something different to the
deathless fare served up by giant distri-
bution chains. ■
THE WONDERFUL W O R L D
OF FILMMAKING
BY MARTÍN REJTMAN
ARGENTINE FILMMAKER, DIRECTOR OF Silvia Prieto (1999)
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 19
O P I N I O N
AGE FOR 
c i n e m a
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ALAIN JALLADEAU
REPRESENTATIVE OFTHE FRENCH FILM LIBRARY IN NANTESANDFOUNDER AND DIRECTOR OFTHE THREE CONTINENTS FESTIVAL
A s i a ’s 
magic lantern
Astonishing and moving films from Asia
and Iran are giving cinema a fresh impetus
and countering American attempts to
dominate the world’s film industry
Cinema is alive and
w e l l , and fil m m a k e r s
are still surprising
and enthusing us.
More often than not,
the most promising come from
A s i a , the continent at the head
of a new cinematic move-
m e n t . The quality of films
being made in this vast
region is improving all the
time, and new talents are cropping
up to compete with American and
European directors.
The 2000 Cannes Film Festival
underscored this extraordinary vita-
l i t y. I r a n ’s Samira Makhmalbaf and
her wandering teachers in B l a ck-
b o a rd s pushed out some highly
sophisticated competitors, such as
the American Coen brothers’
ironic O Brother Where A r t
Thou? Danish director Lars von
Trier may have won the Golden
Palm for his very nordic D a n c e r
in the Dark, but China’s Jiang
Wen took the Grand Prix,Tony
Leung from Hong Kong the Best
Male Performance prize and Ta i-
w a n ’s Edward Yang the prize
for Best Director. The Locarno Film Fe s t i v a l
confirmed the trend in August by awarding its
Golden Leopard prize to Chinese director Wang
S h u o ’s B a b a and the Silver Leopard to Hong Ko n g ’s
Fruit Chan for Little Cheung.Asian films also fig u r e d
prominently at the Venice Film Festival in Sep-
tember, with The Circle by Iranian director Jafar
Panahi reaping the Golden Lion.
Such surges of new talent are nothing new in
cinema. In the early 1960s, the “new wave” in the
French film industry provided the paradigmatic
example of how this could be done. Since then,
there have seen many such creative rebellions—in
Poland (Roman Po l a n s k i , Jerzy Skolimowski),C z e-
choslovakia (Milos Fo r m a n , Ivan Passer), Ja p a n
(Nagisa Oshima, Shohei Imamura) and Brazil
(Glauber Rocha,Ruy Guerra).
Wherever they arise, these new waves—since the
term has become part of our basic vocabulary—
share common traits. They reflect a protest against
traditional concepts of fil m m a k i n g, led by artists
calling for greater freedom of expression as a way
of escaping from the straightjacket imposed by the
film industry of that time.A few strong personalities
carry others with them,a movement takes shape and
then blossoms.
But today one factor has changed in the equa-
t i o n : the American movie business has since streng-
thened its grip and taken over nearly all the cinemas
around the world. Its commercial strength remains
unrivalled, even though the quest for domination
has badly eroded the creativity of American fil m .I t
would be hard to find the modern equivalent of a
John Cassavetes,whose emblematic S h a d ow s ( 1 9 6 0 )
inspired a whole generation of filmmakers.
1 .FROM WEST 
Chinese director Jiang
Wen wins the Cannes 2000 
Film Festival’s Grand Prix.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 21
In the face of this U. S. j u g g e r n a u t , how have
t o d a y ’s new waves managed to take hold the world
over?  First of all, they have been recognized by
international critics,who have always done the spa-
dework when it comes to spotting new talents. O n e
need only remember the pivotal role played by
Henri Langlois, head of Fr a n c e ’s National Fi l m
Library, critics like André Bazin,directors such as
Jean-Luc Godard and François Truffaut and a whole
team of “Young Turks” at the French Cahiers du
C i n é m a magazine in bringing to light a pack of
directors from the U.S., Japan,India,the ex-Soviet
Union,Scandinavia and elsewhere.
Freshness and simplicity:
the keys to Iranian success
Film festivals, such as Cannes, Venice, Berlin,
London and Nantes, sought out new high-quality
work to enhance their programmes, helping impor-
tant filmmakers get established.O b v i o u s l y, n e i t h e r
critics nor festivals can create new cinematic move-
ments. But they can give them the chance to break
through and enable directors to continue making
fil m s,while sometimes even attracting support from
authorities in their home countries.
Taiwan’s case is instructive. The Three Conti-
nents Festival in Nantes (France) gave prizes in
1984 and 1985 to two films by Taiwanese director
Hou Hsiao-hsien, who went on to win international
a c c l a i m . The Taiwanese authorities then decided
to back the most promising directors and help spur
the growth of a new film industry.U n f o r t u n a t e l y, t h i s
policy was soon abandoned. Hou, Yang and Tsai
Ming-liang have enough of a reputation to raise
backing abroad,but for younger fil m m a k e r s, t h i n g s
are much tougher (see page 33).
Although American hegemony has had devas-
tating effects in some Asian countries (in Indo-
n e s i a , for example, American companies control
99 per cent of distribution and have stifled local
fil m - m a k i n g ) , the continent’s overall scene is one of
buzzing creativity.
Iran provides the finest example of dynamic
c i n e m a . Modern Iranian films are enrapturing, w i t h
an element of surprise and a human sensitivity that
is hard to find in American movies.A sense of fre-
shness and simplicity explain the appeal of these
films. The country was producing such films long
before the ayatollahs took power in 1979 (see page
2 6 ) . In the 1970s, Abbas Kiarostami had already
made such remarkable films as Tr a v e l l e r (1974) and
The Report ( 1 9 7 7 ) . But it was not until the 1988
Three Continents Festival that a Kiarostami fil m ,i n
this case Where is the Friend’s Home (1987), was
shown outside Iran.The new government had done
nothing to help the industry sell its films abroad,a n d
few festivals were able to show the works of Iranian
directors. It took many years for people to realize
how creative their films were, and how filmmakers
had managed to overcome censorship with a strong,
personal and original style.Elsewhere in A s i a , Ja p a n
stands out as a leader in the creative arts. B e g i n n i n g
with a Hollywood-style big studio system, its golden
a g e, in my opinion,has never won the recognition it
truly deserved. In the 1950s, Japan was producing
about 650 films a year—more than the United
States—and could boast great directors like Kenji
M i s o g u s h i , Yasujiro Ozu, M i k i o
N a r u s e, Akira Ku r o s a w a , w h o s e
talents were sometimes slow to be
r e c o g n i z e d . As the big studios
declined and these directors disap-
p e a r e d , another generation arose,
including names such as Nagisa
Oshima and Shohei Imamura, who
expressed themselves with greater
freedom by tackling subjects that
were more social and violent.Today
the country is turning out a new wave of provoca-
tive directors like Kiyoshi Ku r o s a w a ,Shinji A o y a m a ,
and Shinya Tsukamoto (see page 28).
These new film movements—and there are
many more, such as in South Korea (page 31) and
Argentina (page 35)—guarantee cinema’s survival.
Critics and festivals have not invented them.They
are simply helping such work reach audiences eager
to support quality films. So long as this continues,
there is reason to remain optimistic. ■
THE THREE CONTINENTS FESTIVA L
Created in 1979 in Nantes (France) by brothers Philippe and Alain Jalladeau,who
were both inspired by a love for cinema and travel,the Three Continents Festival
became the very first in the world devoted to A s i a n ,African and Latin American cinema,
and has so far showcased over 1,000 films. By including premieres of feature films,
retrospectives of noted directors, tributes to an actor or actress and programmes of
films from just one country, the festival has provided a host of different ways to gauge
the movements of world cinema.This year’s event will take place from November 21-
28.
The selection panel chooses films that reflect the social,historical and cultural conditions
of the three continents. From Uzbekistan to Iran, Palestine to Egypt, Mali to Niger, I n d i a
to China, passing on the way through Ko r e a , Brazil and Bolivia, the festival never fails
to present radically different cinematic points of view. By discovering the first films of
a number of directors, the festival has also helped win recognition for some of cinema’s
most distinctive new auteurs: M a l i ’s Souleymane Cissé, C h i n a ’s Chen Kiage, I r a n ’s
Abbas Kiarostami, Ta i wa n ’s Hou Hsiao-hsien and Tsaï Ming-liang and Kazakhstan’s
Darezhan Omirbayev.The festival has also contributed to the renown of Indian directors
l i ke Satyajit Ray,Ritwick Ghatak and Guru Dutt, Japanese director Shohei Imamura,a n d
Brazilian Pereira dos Santos. ■
FO RM O R EI N F O R M AT I O N :
h t t p : / / w w w. 3 c o n t i n e n t s. c o m
h t t p : / / w w w. c i n e m a . d i p l o m a t i e. f r
Cinema is, of course,
the most
international art.
Sergei Eisenstein,
Soviet film director
(1898-1948)
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
 TO EAST
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
B reathless We s t ,
brilliant East
Economic value dominates everything in the West, and cinema is no exception. Made for
profit, moulded by television, most movies have become pure entertainment. The results
are a big turn-off
PARIS-BASED
CINEMA CRITIC FOR
THE International
Herald Tribune Every film-buff in Europe knows the name
of Paulo Branco,a renowned Po r t u g u e s e
producer who has worked with Manoel de
O l i v e r a , Raul Ruiz and Chantal
A c k e r m a n ,directors whose idiosyncratic
styles have helped keep independent cinema aflo a t .
B r a n c o ’s views of current American and European
cinema have become clouded with pessimism:We s-
tern cinema, he says, “has slipped into a kind of
comfort level,while filmmakers from China,Hong
Kong,Taiwan,and Korea have had to struggle and
use their imagination,which gives their films edge
and audacity.”
The dominance of economic values and the
search for prosperity in the West appears to have
deprived the region’s filmmakers of creative muscle.
In contrast, A s i a ’s political, economic and social
upheavals have bred a cultural tension reflected in
its flo u r i s h i n g,dynamic cinema.“ The culture is chan-
ging enormously,and telling stories is a way of dea-
ling with the changes,” declares Piers Handling,
director of the Toronto Fe s t i v a l .“Look at post 1917
R u s s i a ,p o s t - World War I Germany,p o s t - World Wa r
II Italy,post-1959 Cuba,post-colonial France in the
late 50s—all started producing dynamic fil m s. Th i s
energy tends to be dispersed when things are going
w e l l .H o l l y w o o d ’s Golden Age in the 30s and 40s was
largely due to a flood of talent from Europe,p e o p l e
running away from communism or fascism and fin-
ding themselves in a country full of immigrants.”
New York critic Dave Ke h r, who sits on the
selection committee of the Lincoln Center’s New
York Film Fe s t i v a l , feels the same.In his opinion, t h e
vitality of Eastern cinema may have something to do
with these countries’ resistance to post-modernist
irony and self reference.“ They take their stories and
JOAN DUPONT
22 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
1 . FROM WEST TO EAST
Three-dimensional cinema: today’s film-goers are plied with images and deprived of passion.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 23
PETITS MÉDIAS : N O U V E L L E S VO I X
their genres seriously, whereas the West has lost
belief in the old formulas without finding anything
viable to replace them.”
But Gilles Jacob, president of the Cannes fes-
tival—which this year awarded its Golden Palm to
Danish director Lars Von Trier’s deeply northern
Dancer in the Dark and prizes to three Chinese
films and young Iranian director Samira Makh-
malbaf—remains to be convinced of such a cate-
gorical difference.“Iranian cinema is poetic, fresh.
The consecration of Asian cinema is happening
n o w,but the movement has been growing for years;
Kiarostami is almost 60.The jury’s choice, h o w e v e r,
d o e s n ’t diminish the value of other cinemas.Fr e n c h
cinema is also on the rise.”
After years of failing to recognize filmmakers
from the East,the West now seems only too ready
to welcome them with open arms.“ For years we pre-
tended we could ignore anything that wasn’t A m e-
r i c a n , E u r o p e a n , and sometimes Ja p a n e s e,” s a y s
Marco Muller, who recently left his post as director
of the Locarno festival and co-produced Makh-
m a l b a f’s B l a ck b o a rd s and Zhang Yu a n ’s S e v e n t e e n
Ye a r s. “ We all have a debt towards U. S. c i n e m a
because it’s the first syntax we were exposed to,
but now, we’re being exposed to others from Asia,
Africa and Latin A m e r i c a .The Cannes and To r o n t o
festivals established credibility for these films. It’s
not just story telling, but a different film universe
that has been shaping up in the past two decades.
Western reality desperately needed an injection of
something new and that has come from those who
have been shut out by the industry.”
In the United States, m e a n w h i l e,business values
and the power of the studios have only served to
squeeze diversity out of film production. “ I n
E u r o p e,” says Paulo Branco, “ w e ’re all indepen-
d e n t ; in A m e r i c a , even Martin Scorcese,who started
out independent,knows how to handle being recu-
perated by the system.”
Foreign films: the desperate
search for distributors
And America does not really have auteurs,Fr e n c h
producer Francesca Feder learnt in New Yo r k ’s Spa-
nish Harlem,where she made Raphael Nadjari’s T h e
S h a d e. “In A m e r i c a , you have kilos of film school
movies shown at Sundance,a festival that is like a mar-
keting machine.They look like studio movies made
with less money. Miramax buys a couple, and the
fledgling director graduates to the studio.”
Annette Insdorf, in charge of cinema studies at
Columbia University,d i s a g r e e s, remarking that des-
pite the appetite for Asian cinema, U.S. indepen-
dents flourish while films from other countries like
Poland, Hungary, Brazil, Italy and Germany that
dominated festivals in previous decades are much
less visible.“Independent films in the U. S.are being
produced in larger quantities,thanks partly to digital
video and new venues like Showtime on TV. But
foreign language films are having a harder time in
the U. S.partly because independent American fil m s
are flooding the market.”
Her view is echoed by Jacques Bidou, a Paris-
based producer who worked with Haitian Raoul
Peck on L u m u m b a and Cambodian Rithy Panh
on Un soir apres la guerre (One evening after the
w a r ) . Bidou acknowledges that independent A m e-
rican films still have the advantages of language and
a larger scope:“ The volume of American films that
invade theatres and television in Europe prevents
distribution of those made by other nations,” h e
s a y s.“ The problem is not creativity, i t ’s distribution.
We see movements in China,Ta i w a n , Japanese and
Ko r e a , countries in which national films have an
a u d i e n c e. But when the market is so small, the fil m
needs foreign distribution. Television doesn’t buy
foreign language fil m s, and distributors won’t take
the risk.”
The most visually
overwhelmed generation
Television’s strong-arm in production has cer-
tainly cut into filmmaking ambition, dictating the
nature of movies even down to the casting. Piers
Handling (director of the Toronto festival) feels
that Western cinema is now almost
totally oriented towards the market-
place and the notion of providing
entertainment. “Western audiences
have been devastated by the impact
of television—they are the most
visually overwhelmed generation in
history, so their idea of what consti-
tutes the moving image experience is
a dumbed-down version of life. To
get them to pay attention you cannot
give them small, intimate stories about real people—
too boring and underwhelming—you have to give
them sensation.”As a result,H a n d l i n g ’s Toronto fes-
t i v a l ,which is non-competitive,has picked up on new
trends in world cinema and drawn films from cul-
tures that he argues “are not yet media-saturated,
that still have a literary or verbal culture, such as Iran
and China, and are making the best films in the
world.”
Yet hope remains for the Western film industry,
argues Gilles Ja c o b, insisting that there is still
money to make more challenging movies.“ C i n e m a
is always in the red, globally speaking,” he says,
“ We have to put fresh money into the system and
we need new people, like Francis Bouygues, w h o
launched Ciby 2000.” Over the past few years, C i b y
2000—a French production company—has co-pro-
duced films by David Ly n c h , Quentin Ta r a n t i n o
and Pedro A l m o d o v a r.The international trend for
French producers has developed even further:
Humbert Balsan produces Egyptian Youssef Cha-
hine and Yousri Nasrallah, as well as Sandrine
Ve y s s e t ; Marin Karmitz produces American inde-
pendent Johnathan Nossiter and Austrian Michael
H a n e k e ; while Michel Propper produced Israeli
Amos Gitai and Peter Brook of Britain. Wi t h
several critical and commercial successes under
its belt, c i n e m a ’s alternative globalization appears
well underway. ■
Photography is truth.
And cinema is truth
24 times a second.
Jean-Luc Godard,
French film director
(1930-)
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
A giant among 
On the whole, the film market has taken a nosedive as cinema
admissions have fallen to a fifth of what they were ten years ago.
There is one exception: the American film industry is making huge
gains in the U.S. and worldwide
The U.S. alone invests more in the film industry than any
other country for which statistics are available.
The second in line is the European Union,with a total
investment of $2,559 million in 1999.
Top ten leaders in film production, 1999 U . S . share of local box-office, 1999% Comparison with 1990
Source: Screen Digest (contact: David.Hancock@screendigest.com)
Source: Screen Digest (contact: David.Hancock@screendigest.com)
IN V E S T M E N T
Among the world’s top ten producers, India and the U.S. are neck-to-neck.
The European Union ranks third with 706 feature-length films produced in
1999, however it has captured only three per cent of 
the U.S. market.American films compose roughly half the market 
in nine out of the ten leading movie-producing countries and territories
in the world.
PR O D U C T I O N
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 25
Cinema screens in the world’s regions per million
population in 1998 
The number of cinema screens in each country per million
population in 1998
% Comparison 
with  1988
Source: Screen Digest (contact: David.Hancock@screendigest.com)
Sources: Screen Digest (contact: David.Hancock@screendigest.com); UNESCO Institute for Statistics.
Admissions (per million population) have followed the same
pattern as the number of screens (see below). The only
regions to witness an increase are North America and the
A u s t ralia/New Zealand/Pa c i fic Islands re g i o n . Between 1988
and 1998, the annual number of movie-goers fell to less than
a seventh of what it used to be in Central and South A s i a ,
l a rgely because of an explosion in the production of pira t e
v i d e o s. In Central and Eastern Euro p e, the situation is even
w o rs e : admissions have fallen by more than 33 times
following the disentegration of state-run film industries.
AD M I S S I O N S
In North America and the region of Australia/New Zealand/Pacific Islands,
the number of screens per million population is on the rise. A steady
decline, however, has been recorded in Central and South Asia (the
world’s most populous region) as well as in Central America/the
Caribbean. Meanwhile the number of screens operating in Central and
Eastern Europe has plummeted.The situation elsewhere remains stable.
SC R E E N S
 dwa r v e s
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
After the re v o l u t i o n :
the cinema will carry us
Cinema was authorized by the Islamic Republic for propaganda purposes, but a new
generation of directors is offering the world a very different image of Iran
2.NEW WAV E S
In Iran,cinema did not become legitimate (in
the eyes of believers) until the revolution of
February 1979. Before that political upheaval,
which stemmed from widespread dissatisfac-
tion with the Shah’s regime and resulted in an
“Islamic Republic” headed by Ayatollah Ruhollah
Khomeini, the seventh art had drawn thundering
condemnation from the clergy.
Movies first appeared in Iran at the start of the
twentieth century, and Muslim clerics voiced their
opposition to the new art form as soon as the first
theatres opened in Tehran in 1904.Several cinemas
were burned down, with sometimes tragic conse-
quences:in August 1978,400 people lost their lives
at the Rex in the city of Abadan.Mullahs believed
the movie theatre to be a symbol of the godless
West and a competitor to the mosque, thus making
it a direct threat to their power.F u r t h e r m o r e,m o v i e s
were considered blasphemous because they fea-
tured images of women without veils and, l a t e r,
scenes of dancing accompanied by music.
Fanatical believers could not tolerate the icono-
graphical portrayal of humans: God alone is the
“ C r e a t o r ” and the “ C r a f t s m a n ” of living beings.
Mosque decorations, especially in Iran, contain no
figurative representations, and for centuries the
power of words dominated Iranian society.Wi t h o u t
any tradition of visual artistic expression (with the
exception of miniatures in the 14th and 15th centu-
r i e s ) , “ i m a g i n a t i v e ” representation became the
domain of writers and, above all, p o e t s.
Between 1930 and 1979, approximately 1,100
feature films were shown in 420 theatres,but not one
of them met with the ayatollahs’ approval. R i g i d l y
MAMAD HAGHIGHAT
IRANIAN FILM CRITICAND HISTORIAN, AUTHOR OF Histoire du cinéma iranien,
(“A HISTORY OF IRANIAN CINEMA”), PUBLISHEDBYTHE GEORGE POMPIDOU CENTRE IN 1999
Iranian director Moshen Makhmalbaf with his youngest daughter. A former supporter of the Islamic regime, his views have been transformed by cinema.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 27
Muslim parents even beat their children for going to
the movies. But when Khomeini took power, a
strange reversal occurred. O v e r n i g h t , the cinema
became of interest to everybody, including the cle-
r i c s.As in other areas, the new regime took control
of everything.It confiscated images and made its own
visual style omnipresent on television,in newspapers,
on walls and in movie theatres. The blessed and
p u r i fied seventh art had won its legitimacy, t h o u g h
foreign cinema, which flies in the face of Islamic
v a l u e s, was banned. As a result, the national fil m
industry had no competitors on Iranian soil.
During his exile in Fr a n c e,Ayatollah Khomeini
had become aware of the image’s role as an effec-
tive political propaganda tool. Back in Tehran, he
saw Dariush Mehrjui’s film The Cow (1969) on
television. The film, with a style close to realism,
focuses on the troubled lives of impoverished far-
mers in a remote village,where one character iden-
t i fies with his dead cow, the only property he owns.
This movie inspired the religious leader to make a
speech on the educational role of film.
Setting the wheels 
of dissent in motion
As early as the first year of the revolution,all parts
of the state worked hard to create an “ I s l a m i c
c i n e m a ”that would move in “the right direction.”A t
the very same time, a rival style of cinema, d r a w i n g
on the tradition of high-quality filmmaking from
before 1979, was also born. A few fil m m a k e r s
managed to create a language that skirted around the
relentless censorship,drawing inspiration from eve-
ryday life (through a fusion between documentary
and fiction) and from Persian poetry.The freshness
and innocence of their films struck a chord with the
p u b l i c. The film directors also learned to play one
state body against another,especially as the various
appoined officials changed position frequently.
The new cinema’s leading representative,A b b a s
Kiarostami, who also co-founded the filmmaking
department at the Institute for the Intellectual
Development of Children and Young Adults in
1 9 6 9 , uses his camera to challenge Khomeini’s cine-
matic precepts. As Iran and Iraq braced for a par-
ticularly murderous war (1980-1988), the new
regime, after just a few months of nascent demo-
c r a cy, took a much harder line. In this grim context,
Abbas Kiarostami made at the end of 1979 Alter-
native 1,Alternative 2, an indictment of informers
that lays bare the ineptitude of various social classes,
including the clergy. The movie was banned and
never approved for release. But Kiarostami, who
says that he is a secular director,had set the wheels
in motion of a form of filmmaking that would prove
a formidable adversary to the regime.
K i a r o s t a m i ’s films criticized the mullahs’ hold
over society. In H o m e w o r k ( 1 9 9 0 ) , he attacked the
brainwashing of children.Th e n ,with Taste of Cherry
( 1 9 9 7 ) ,he focused on suicide,which is against Islamic
l a w, and whose causes must be sought in people’s
despair over Iran’s rigid social structures. A n o t h e r
barrier fell with The Wind Will Carry Us ( 1 9 9 9 ) ,
which casts doubt on the existence of an after- l i f e.
Kiarostami is not the only director to have chal-
lenged Iranian society. In B a s h u ,The Little Stranger
( 1 9 8 7 ) ,Bahram Beyzaï condemned the terrible conse-
quences of the holy war against Iraq.So did Mohsen
Makhmalbaf in Marriage of the Blessed ( 1 9 8 9 ) .A m i r
Naderi focused on the authorities’ attitude towards
soldiers missing-in-action at the beginning of the war,
which he gave an alternative account of in the as yet
unreleased S e a r ch 2.With The Runner ( 1 9 8 5 ) ,N a d e r i
became the first director since the revolution to give
leading parts to children, who went on to become
some of Iran’s most popular movie “ a c t o r s ” .
This is noteworthy because
Iran is undergoing a demographic
b o o m .The population has nearly
doubled in the past 20 years, a n d
almost half of all Iranians are
under 20. Film directors noticed
that the authorities were failing
to take these figures seriously,
and—drawing on the saying that
words of truth come from the
mouths of babes—they cast chil-
dren to explore facets of everyday
l i f e.
From a whimsical cinematic
style partly based on Egyptian
and Indian B-movies, Iranian fil m s
made the transition to something
between “Italian neo-realism” a n d
“ French new wave,” s h a t t e r i n g
taboos and washing Iran’s dirty
laundry in public. Worst of all in
the mullahs’ eyes, this new cinema
captured the imagination and the
talent of the regime’s apologists.
The most stunning example of this
is Mohsen Makhmalbaf. A pure
product of the protests that
marked the end of the Shah’s rule,
he spent four years in jail before
being released in 1979. He was
fully committed to the new regime
and directed the Islamic A r t i s t i c
Theatre Centre, a propaganda
o r g a n i z a t i o n , before gradually moving towards
c i n e m a .With the complete trust of the authorities,h e
then directed The Pe d d l e r ( 1 9 8 7 ) , which caused a
sensation by openly criticizing the regime and
denouncing the “lies of the mosque.”When journa-
lists asked him, “ M a k h m a l b a f, what have you
become? Are you stepping out of line?” he replied,
“ I ’ve discovered cinema,and it has changed the way
I look at the world.”
On a trip to Europe, Makhmalbaf was so deeply
moved by Wim Wenders’ Wings of Desire that he
made blasphemous remarks on his return to Iran.“ I f
God must send a new prophet, his name will be
Wim Wenders,” he declared. He then made a film
WORLD PRODUCTION RANK
1999: 13
LOCAL FILMS’ SHARE OF 
DOMESTIC BOX-OFFICE
1998: 95%
NUMBER OF FILMS PRODUCED
POPULATION (millions)
1988: 51.9
1998: 65.8
NUMBER OF SCREENS
1988: 279
1998: 285
Data for cinema admissions and total
film production investment are not
available.
Sources: Screen Digest (contact: 
David Hancock@screendigest.com) and
UNESCO Institute for Statistics.
TO KNOW MORE
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Shooting on a shoestring
Young Japanese producers are stretching tight budgets to produce a wave of often dark
films while the big studios, fattened by prosperity, are falling on hard times
FRENCH JOURNALIST BASED IN TOKYO
BRICE PEDROLETTI
challenging the dogma of Islamic society, Time of
L ov e ( 1 9 9 0 ) , about an affair between a married
woman and her lover. Contrary to all expectations,
the movie was shown at the Tehran film festival
the same year, where it drew huge crowds in just a
few screenings (though it was not cleared for general
release). That event, in part, cost Makhmalbaf his
position at the Ministry of Culture, which at the
time was headed by none other than the current pre-
sident,Mohammad Khatami.
The 1990s marked a turning point.The West was
surprised to discover a different Iran at film festivals,
with Iranian movies addressing themes such as friend-
s h i p, tolerance and togetherness.A time of honours
and awards had begun. “ O n c e, Iran exported oil,
rugs and pistachios.Now it can add movies to the list.
Iran exports its culture, which is a good thing,” s a i d
K i a r o s t a m i , who won the 1997 Golden Palm at
Cannes for Taste of Cherry. In 2000, three Iranian
filmmakers won prizes at Cannes, including Makh-
m a l b a f’s 20-year-old daughter,S a m i r a , the youngest
award-winner in the festival’s history, for B l a ck-
b o a rd s. Bahman Ghobadi, m e a n w h i l e, won the
Golden Camera award for A Time for Drunken
H o r s e s and Hassan Yektapanah for D j o m e h.
Iran is a veritable breeding ground for fresh
cinematic talent.To d a y, around 20 gifted directors,
including Kiarostami,M a k h m a l b a f, Ja l i l i ,M e h r j u i ,
B e y z a ï , Fo r o z e s h , Naderi and Panahi, make 15 per
cent of the 60 films that the country produces each
y e a r.The limits of this cinema, which is shattering
the last taboos, are still unknown.
For the first time,a feature fil m ,The Circle,w h i c h
reaped the Golden Lion at the 2000 Venice Film Fe s-
t i v a l , deals with prostitution, a topic that had pre-
viously been totally off-limits in the Islamic republic.
Fo r t y - y e a r-old Jafar Panahi, who had already won
the Golden Camera award at Cannes in 1995 for T h e
White Balloon, made this outstanding film without
even submitting the script to Iran’s censorship com-
m i t t e e.A willingness to test the regime’s limits can also
be witnessed among writers and journalists, some of
whom were killed or imprisoned in 1999. A r r e s t s
have continued since the beginning of the year.
Female directors have encountered even more
h u r d l e s, but they too have found a place behind
the camera in making films about the condition of
w o m e n . For example, Rakhshan Banni-Etemad,
Tahminé Milani and a dozen or so others are making
names for themselves in Iran’s “ m a c h o - I s l a m i c ”
s o c i e t y. Young Iranian exiles who studied in the
West are also going back home,bringing a different
vision of Iran with them. For example Babak
P a y a m i , who directed the remarkable A Day More,
a film about love, lived in Canada.
Iran has adopted the modern imagery coined by
films. Whether in documentary or fiction, Iranian
cinema has liberated itself and become part of peo-
ple’s day-to-day lives. All Iranians are now spell-
bound by images,“whether it is a just image or just
an image,” to borrow the expression of Fr e n c h
director Jean-Luc Godard. ■
2 . NEW WAV E S
28 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
The tiny bar in To k y o ’s Shinjuku district has
barely changed over the past 50 years. I t s
owner keeps a careful eye on the rows of
whisky bottles that line the ancient dive’s
w a l l s, each bottle bearing the name of a
filmmaker from somewhere across the world.E v e r y
time one of these illustrious guests passes through
To k y o, they find their private bottle waiting, i n t a c t .
For Masaki Ta m u r a , a famous director of photo-
graphy who worked with the big names in documen-
tary and fiction films in the 1970s and 1980s, the bar is
a favourite hangout when taking a break between
two shoots.One day in the early 1990s,h o w e v e r, in the
middle of a shoot with a famous director, Ta m u r a ’s
patience with movie-making finally broke.“I was sick
of the old methods. The approach was too conven-
t i o n a l . I wanted to give up film and I didn’t work for
the next three years. I thought it was all over for me.”
That is until he met Shinji Aoyama and did
camera work for his first fil m , H e l p l e s s. “During the
s h o o t , everybody knew how to do everyone else’s
j o b,” he says.“ You had to because the budget was so
s m a l l . It was a miracle how we managed to make a
three-hour film in cinemascope with so little money.”
At 61,with a moustache,shock of grey hair, s e n s i-
tive face and calm voice of a character from a Ya s u j i r o
Ozu fil m ,Tomura describes his new career as a conver-
s i o n . “At fir s t , I didn’t understand the film language
these young people used. The way they worked was
new to me. Ideas come from all sides. Everyone has
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 29
something to say and we discuss everything together.
But I got used to it and now I speak that language.”Fo r
the past five years,Tamura has been working exclusi-
vely with this young generation,whose creative energy
has given new life to Ja p a n ’s battered film industry.
These filmmakers are all between 20 and 40 years
o l d , and produce their films with extremely limited
resources in the world’s most expensive city. Some of
them have worked in television, advertising or car-
t o o n s, and hold down several jobs to make ends
m e e t . They tend to focus on social and psycholo-
gical themes, like delinquency and mindless crime,
which mirror the confusion and malaise of a gene-
ration that has rejected the old ambitions of getting
r i c h , blind loyalty to one’s employer and social har-
m o n y.
Without access to major distribution networks,
they make do in a ghetto of art cinemas where com-
petition is fie r c e : this new genre can never earn much
m o n e y. Financing the productions is also a night-
m a r e,with budgets ranging from $100,000 to a million
d o l l a r s.Most do not even have an inter-negative ver-
sion (from which copies can be made without dama-
ging the master)—a common sacrifice made by
makers of short films elsewhere.
“I often have to go into debt to get the fil m
s t a r t e d ,”says Shinya T s u k a m o t o.“ You start shooting
with the crew working for nothing and hoping to
get paid later.Then I show the rushes to video editors
to try to get them to invest in the fil m .” Making fan-
tasy films in the tradition of the Frenchman Georges
M é l i è s, Tsukamoto is a director, c a m e r a m a n , s e t -
d e s i g n e r, actor and producer all rolled into one.
At 40, he has made six films independently and
another two for the big studios. It took eight months
to make Bullet Ballet, his seventh and second-to-last
fil m , whose street scenes were largely shot clandes-
t i n e l y. Like his first fil m s, Te t s u o and To kyo First,
Bullet Ballet conveys the vibrant energy of its director,
who depicts the fragile equilibrium of young people
living on the brink of disaster, in a culture of violence
from which there is no return.
Just as in the 1970s, when major studios such as
Nikkatsu switched to B movies and the soft porn
works on which many filmmakers cut their teeth,
t o d a y ’s producers have made erotic films (p i n k u
e i g a) and gangster films on budgets even smaller
than their elders.These video or 16mm productions
are targetted directly at the video market.
Kiyoshi Kurosawa continues to make film noir
on 16mm for video,though he infuses his creations with
a surprisingly philosophical dimension.The two major
works of the Revenge II s e r i e s,Eyes of the Spider a n d
Serpent Pa t h ( 1 9 9 8 ) ,were shot one after the other,e a c h
in two weeks, with the same crew and
the same actors. The same plot of
r e v e n g e,h o w e v e r, is handled very dif-
ferently in the two cases.“I don’t mind
shooting like this,” he says.“In fact it’s
a luxury to be able to make two ver-
sions of the same story.”Takashi Miike,
king of gangster gore fil m s,a g r e e s.
Takeshi Kitano,big brother to this
new generation of fil m m a k e r s, s t a r t e d
out in a similar fashion.It was too hard
being an actor and producer at the same
t i m e, so he went behind the camera.
Today his company Office Kitano turns out a steady
stream of independent fil m s,though he makes most of
his money by selling to television.
Never before has a “new wave” in Ja p a n e s e
cinema made such a virtue out of necessity.The cur-
rent generation has set up its own makeshift net-
work with a freedom unprecedented in the history of
the nation’s film industry.The French “new wave”o f
the 1960s had little choice but to depend heavily on
big studio money. So long as the films drew the
c r o w d s, independent filmmakers and the studio
There is no such
thing as national
cinema, only
i n d i v i d u a l
fil m m a k e r s .
Youssef Chahine,
Egyptian fil m
Shinya Tsukamoto’s Bullet Ballet: a tough look at Japanese youth.
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
bosses always found a way of wor-
king together.
But falling attendance rates
combined with an economic down-
turn has dealt a sharp blow to the
Japanese industry. The major dis-
t r i b u t o r s — To h o, Toei and Sho-
chiko—have brushed aside the
newcomers and made money by
filling their cinemas with foreign
films (70 per cent of total revenue),
animation (about 20 such films were
made in 1999) or their own pro-
d u c t i o n s.
As a result, the “new wave” o f
the 1990s had to set up shop,p h y s i-
cally and fig u r a t i v e l y, in a country
where training had long been the
preserve of big studios. New fil m
and video schools are springing up
like Eiga Bi Gakko, which was
founded two years ago by pro-
ducer Kenzo Horikoshi. C l a s s e s
are often taught by young direc-
tors, who submit film proposals as
part of the school programme to
produce two films each year.Aki-
hiko Shiota made a couple of
erotic films before his remarkable
Moonlight W h i s p e r s in 1999,w h i c h
follows three children growing up
in a city suburb and cost less than
$200,000.
“ The films are made without any thought of the
big studio network,” says Hirokazu Ko r e - E d a ,w h o
directed Wonderful Life. Because they owe favours
to no-one, the young directors are totally free to
e x p e r i m e n t .For Wonderful Life,Ko r e - E d a ,who was
trained in documentary production,sent his assistants
out on a five-month mission to capture on video
“the best memories” of about 500 elderly people.
He looked at the rushes, did the casting and then
contacted those he had chosen to appear in the fil m .
Nobuhiro Suwa,director of M / O t h e r, d e v e l o p e d
in three feature-length films a very personal style
based on improvisation and lengthy shots, some of
which last over five minutes.H story,his third fil m ,i s
the story of the filming of an imaginary re-make of
Hiroshima Mon A m o u r, in which Béatrice Dalle
plays the original star, Emmanuelle Riva.
As for A o y a m a , his feature film E u r e k a d e a l s
with a recurrent theme in 1990s Japanese cinema—
that of a new life, a transition to an alternative state
of existence following a traumatic experience. I t
shows three people, a man and two children, w h o
have escaped from a bloody hostage-taking episode
and struggle throughout the film to find their way out
of a maze of misfortune.
New outfits upstage 
the big studios
The technical, stylistic and narrative maturity of
E u r e k a,made in black and white cinemascope,s t a n d s
out among other independent films which,despite all
their energy,sometimes seem laborious productions
overly concerned with navel-gazing and experi-
m e n t a t i o n . It is perhaps no accident that the fil m
was one of the first produced by Suncent Cinema
Wo r k s, the new company of Takenori Sentoh.The 38-
y e a r-old producer is seen by many as a pioneer of new
Japanese cinema. In 1992, he joined the pay-TV
channel Wowow and gave several beginners their
first break, including Aoyama for H e l p l e s s. S i n c e
t h e n , Sentoh has produced more than 35 films for
Wowow and others companies, including some fes-
tival favourites of recent years. In 1999, he set up
his own production company, S u n c e n t .
Distribution is still very difficult in Ja p a n , b u t
S e n t o h ’s success abroad and Kitano’s commercial
breakthrough have encouraged other centres of
independent film production, i n c l u d i n g, i r o n i c a l l y,
the former major distributors Daiei and Nikkatsu.
Some previously occasional partners of the new
Japanese cinema (video editors, advertising agen-
cies and radio and television stations) are now more
involved in co-production, while countless multi-
media firms (Little More, Uplink and Gaga, f o r
example) are encouraging alternative productions.
Meanwhile the disintegration of the big-studio
system is gathering pace.An almost-bankrupt Sho-
chiku has sold its studios at Ofuna, near To k y o.
“ This reminds me of the g e k o k u j o,”says the head of
a film school, referring to 15th and 16th century
feudal Japan when the serfs took the place of the
g e n t r y.Sentoh for his part has started hiring banking
executives and others totally alien to the film
industry on the condition that they are true fil m
f a n a t i c s.He has always wondered,he says,“if anyone
in the mainstream Japanese movie industry even
likes cinema.” ■
30 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
WORLD PRODUCTION RANK
1999: 3
LOCAL FILMS’ SHARE 
OF DOMESTIC BOX-OFFICE
1998: 32%
NUMBER OF FILMS PRODUCED
TOTAL POPULATION (millions)
1988: 122.6
1998: 126.3
NUMBER OF SCREENS
1988: 2005
1998: 1993
CINEMA ADMISSIONS (millions)
1988: 144.80
1998: 153.10
TOTAL FILM PRODUCTION 
INVESTMENT (US$m)
1999: 1053.16
Sources: Screen Digest (contact: 
David Hancock@screendigest.com) and
UNESCO Institute for Statistics.
TO KNOW MORE
2 . NEW WAV E S
Shinji Aoyama’s Eureka, an emblem for Japan’s new directors.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
South Ko re a :
freedom or love?
The advent of democracy in South Korea and efforts to defend local film production against
U.S. competition have spawned a new generation of filmmakers who are winning plaudits at
home and abroad
SOUTH KOREAN JOURNALIST BASED IN PARIS
AND CONSULTANT FOR SEVERAL FILMFESTIVALS
South Ko r e a ’s filmmakers are in a recalci-
trant mood. They are battling the Ame-
rican juggernaut in its effort to lift a local
quota on importing foreign fil m s,but these
militants don’t have their backs to the
w a l l : the general public shares the country’s new cul-
tural exuberance,and is backing its young directors.
“Our young filmmakers are to be congratulated on
the breadth of their imagination and their box-
office successes,” says 58-year-old Lee Doo-yong,
who has made more than 50 fil m s. “ They know
what they want to say.Th a t ’s something new round
here.”
The South Korean film industry is doing extre-
mely well. It conquered 37 per cent of the domestic
market in 1999 (up from 25 per cent the previous
year and 18 per cent in 1997),a total boosted by a
record 6.5 million people who went to see the film
S h i r i ( Titanic only managed a local audience of 4.3
million).
With this windfall,the man who made the film,
Kang Je - g y u , decided to join forces with young fil m-
m a k e r s, revamp the distribution network and lay the
groundwork for cooperation between Asian coun-
tries. New film companies (Sidus, Cinema Service,
Myung Fi l m ,East Fi l m ,Bom) are also zeroing in on
young directors just starting out. Serious money
from the likes of Mirae Esset, U n i k o r e a , CJ Enter-
tainment and National Technology Finance is fil l i n g
the gap left by the big industrial conglomerates,
the chaebol, which pulled out of film fin a n c i n g
during the 1997-98 Asian financial crisis.
It was in the midst of the economic downturn
that the United States chose to attack the system of
quotas in place since 1985. The main feature of
t h e s e,one which ensured the industry’s prosperity,
stipulated that Korean films should be shown in
cinemas for between 100 and 146 days a year. But
the reaction from South Korean professionals,
backed by France, stopped the U.S. campaign in its
tracks.
Despite a drop in the number of productions
caused by the economic crisis, 18 films by fir s t - t i m e
directors (out of a total of 43 new films) were made
in 1999 and seven of the year’s 10 most popular
films were debuts. In 1999,22 such first films and 10
second features by new directors were made out of
a total of 53 releases,at an average cost of about $1.5
million each.
The rise of this new cinema dates back to the late
1980s, at the end of years of authoritarian political
rule that began in 1961 with the long dictatorships
of Park Chung-hee and then Chun Doo-hwan. In
the period leading to 1971,the South Korean film
industry had also prospered,turning out some 200
films a year despite the military regime and the dis-
torting effects of the Cold War, which partly para-
lyzed cultural life. Society was by then moderni-
zing at lightning speed, and films mirrored the social
and political ferment that resulted.
Ha Kil-jong’s 1975 film Parade of Fo o l s, a favou-
rite of the new wave, came to symbolize this period.
I MYUNG-HEE
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 31
Seom by Ki-duk,one of the leading lights of this new generation.
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
With a final scene that is still tremendously moving,
the film has become an icon for young directors, i n s-
piring the landmark film of the Korean new wave,
Lee Ja n g - h o ’s Declaration of Fo o l s ( 1 9 8 3 ) . K i l -
j o n g ’s film depicts a nation’s youth that is innocent
and full of dreams but shaken by
the political situation, a youth lon-
ging for freedom and democracy.
“ The entire South Korean film
industry suffered from crippling
c e n s o r s h i p,” Lee Doo-yong says.
“In 1980,in front of my very eyes,
a minor official clipped out half an
h o u r ’s worth of negatives from my
film The Last Eyewitness, which I
was particularly fond of. What an
incredible waste of creative work!
I even considered giving up fil m
altogether.”
After filmmaking restrictions
were lifted in 1985 and script cen-
sorship abolished in 1987,a fresh
new cinema appeared around
1 9 8 8 . Park Kwang-su’s A S i n g l e
Spark (1996) and Jang Sun-woo’s
A Petal (1996), films made by two
veterans of this new wave,m a r k e d
a peak of public interest in libe-
rated political cinema. The two
films dealt with a couple of key
events which had long been taboo:
the banning of the trade union
movement and the massacre at
Kwang-ju in 1980, when 2,000
people died according to witnesses
but only 200 according to the Chun
Doo-hwan regime. Public support
for the films was proof of the new
cinema’s vigour.
The impact of the jointly-made
The Night Before the Strike (1990)
was just as significant for the then
bold and militant independent
c i n e m a .To watch this aesthetically
unimpressive film in the only place
it could be seen, a university
c a m p u s, it was best to wear trai-
ning shoes and know how to run.
On one occasion 1,700 police plus
a helicopter turned up to seize a
copy of the film.In all,a million young people saw
it even though it was officially banned.
The film’s producers and directors, like several
others—such as Lee Eun, Lee Yo n g - b a e, C h a n g
Dong-hong and Jang Yu n - h y u n ,along with the critic
Lee Yong-kwan—advocated links between the fil m
world and the working class.To d a y, they hold impor-
tant posts in bodies such as the KOFIC, set up to
encourage film creativity on the model of France’s
National Film Centre, the CNC.
Sopyonje set off another revolution in 1993 by
drawing many more people to the cinema.Th r o u g h
a melancholy paean to the disappearing art of tra-
ditional singing, veteran director Im Kwon-taek,
who already has 90 films under his belt, took a new
look at the nation’s painful course since the Ja p a n e s e
occupation. This journey through cultural history
sent a shockwave through audiences. More than a
million people went to see it,beating all records and
overshadowing local box office interest in Steven
Spielberg’s Jurassic Park.
The enthusiasm for Korean-made films has
c o n t i n u e d . Cinema audiences keep on growing and
films by first-time directors often draw more than a
million people.But public interest has shifted, w i t h
young people between 17 and 25—who make up the
majority of cinema-goers—becoming the key to
commercial success.
A landmark 
for Korean culture
Yet the film industry’s new vitality,along with the
growing role of big investors, has not helped all
d i r e c t o r s.C h u n h y a n g, Im Kwon-taek’s latest work,
which in 2000 became the first Korean film to be offi-
cially presented at the Cannes festival,was a box-
office flop. The generation of directors aged over
50—Lee Doo-yong, who made L’ A m o u r ( 1 9 9 9 ) ,
and Bae Chang-ho, director of The Heart (1998)—
is having big problems making small-budget inde-
pendent fil m s.Even the granddaddy of the industry,
75-year-old Sin Sang-ok, cannot complete his film
The Vi s i t, the tale of a father who discovers his
daughter working as a bar hostess in Seoul, illus-
trating the conflict between tradition and the thrus-
ting materialism of today.
The times clearly favour young filmmakers ins-
pired by Hollywood formulas and video-game
s c r i p t s, but independent cinema has not given up yet.
Since the arrival of democracy, it has simply changed
its slogans. Instead of “Freedom or death!”it now
p r o c l a i m s, as if in reference to the French surrealist
poet Robert Desnos,“Freedom or love!”
Films made by this school, such as Spring in My
Hometown (1998) by Lee Kwang-mo, Peppermint
C a n d y (1999) by Lee Chang-dong, Christmas in
August (1998) by Huh Jing-ho and The Spy (1999)
by Jang Jin, have spread abroad. The best-known
director among them, Hong Sang-su, who made
The Day the Pig Fell Into the Well in 1996, is opti-
mistic.“I think Korean cinema will stay very inter-
esting for another decade at least,” he says, p o i n t i n g
out that cinema courses in universities draw talented
s t u d e n t s, that many short films are getting shown and
that movie websites are proliferating.“ The cinema
is going to become the main landmark for Korean
culture in all its diversity,” he says.“And that’s exci-
ting.” The release in September of young director
Park Chan-ook’s new film Joint Security A r e a,w i t h
ticket sales of a million in its first three days, shows
that the issue of reconciliation with North Korea has
generated even more powerful subject matter. ■
2 . NEW WAV E S
32 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
WORLD PRODUCTION RANK
1999: 14
LOCAL FILMS’ SHARE 
OF DOMESTIC BOX-OFFICE
1998: 25%
NUMBER OF FILMS PRODUCED
TOTAL POPULATION (millions)
1988: 42
1998: 46.1
NUMBER OF SCREENS
1988: 696
1999: 528
CINEMA ADMISSIONS (millions)
1988: 52.20
1998: 45.76
TOTAL FILM PRODUCTION 
INVESTMENT (US$m)
1999: 111.73
Sources: Screen Digest (contact: 
David Hancock@screendigest.com)
TO KNOW MORE
Neo-realism is a
moral perspective on
the world.
Roberto Rossellini,
Italian film director
(1906-1977)
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
T h e
Chinese 
c o n u n d r u m
Chinese-language 
films and directors
have flourished 
in recent years even 
as they struggle 
at home against 
censorship and 
public indifference
HEAD OF ASIANCINEMA PROGRAMMINGFORTHE HONG KONG INTERNATIONAL FILM FESTIVALFROM 1997 TO 2000
If garnering awards at major film festivals like
Cannes is a sign of good health, then Chinese
fil m s, or more accurately Chinese-language
films, are doing splendidly. Mainland China,
Taiwan and Hong Kong each had a film that
picked up honours at the last Cannes festival—
Jiang We n ’s Devils on the Doorstep,Edward Ya n g ’s
Yi Yi and Wong Kai-wai’s In the Mood of Lov e r e s-
pectively—while Ang Lee’s out-of-competition
Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon was a hit among
festival-goers.
Unlike the more mainstream C r o u ching Ti g e r,
h o w e v e r,the other three films have not been released
on home ground. Devils on the Doorstep, w h i c h
invited the wrath of China’s Film Bureau by travel-
ling overseas without going through the proper chan-
n e l s,probably needs to clear a few hurdles before it
can see the light of day. In the cases of Yi Yi and In the
Mood of Lov e, the reasons are commercial: n e i t h e r
film is expected to do well at the box-offic e,and dis-
tributors are moving cautiously. S t r a n g e l y, the soils
that produce these films do not seem particularly
congenial to serious cinema.Scrutiny of these movies’
financing in fact reveals that apart from D e v i l s,all are
international co-productions.
The People’s Republic to this day keeps a tight
rein over filmmaking and parrots the dogma
“cinema must serve the people.” But this constraint
has been perversely undermined by modern China’s
obsession with its historical destiny.“ Fifth Genera-
tion” filmmakers such as Chen Kaige and Zhang
Yimou portray China’s past, and are faithful to the
dictums of 1930s “progressive”Chinese cinema in
using history to dissect the failings of the present.
But “Sixth Generation” fil m m a k e r s, who arrived
on the scene in the aftermath of the 1989 Ti a n a n m e n
uprising, trumpet a very different sense of aesthe-
tics. Working without official approval, early films
like Zhang Yuan’s Mama (1991) and He Jianjun’s
Red Beads (1993) seethe with inwardly directed
r a g e, capturing the fatalism of post-1989 society.
Allegories based on madness,dysfunctional families
and above all alienation are major themes. Fo r
these independents, the biggest headache is seeing
their films scoop up awards on the festival circuit
while remaining largely unseen in China itself.
The two currents—historical
and contemporary—look set to
join in Jia Zhangke’s new fil m
P l a t f o r m.A richly layered work, i t
observes the lives of young people
in a provincial music troupe as
they fall in love and are hurtled
into the vast unknown of China’s
m o d e r n i z a t i o n . Over three hours
long but with less than a hundred
s h o t s, the film is unprecedented
in mainland Chinese cinema.
Taiwanese fil m s, m e a n w h i l e,
have won international recogni-
tion even though the island’s fil m
industry has been in  decline, w i t h
annual output dwindling to 20
films and funding coming from
the government or abroad. Ye t
Taiwan still manages to produce
some of the world’s best filmma-
kers, including Hou Hsiao-hsien,
Edward Ya n g, Tsai Ming-liang
and Ang Lee—a film-maker with
stronger mass appeal than his
peers and a track record in light
comedy (Eat Drink Man Wo m a n) ,
adaptations of classic novels
(Sense and Sensibility) and, with
C r o u ching Ti g e r, o l d - s c h o o l
swordplay.
Similar financial concerns
abound in Hong Ko n g, home to
headline-grabbing art-house
BY JACOB WONG
October 2000 -The Unesco Courier 33
WORLD PRODUCTION RANK (CHINA)
1999: 10
LOCAL FILMS’ SHARE 
OF DOMESTIC BOX-OFFICE
1998: n.a.
NUMBER OF FILMS PRODUCED
TOTAL POPULATION (millions)
1988: 1,121.9
NUMBER OF SCREENS
1988: 161,777
1998: 65,000
CINEMA ADMISSIONS (millions)
1988: 18,730
1998: 121
TOTAL FILM PRODUCTION 
INVESTMENT (US$m)
1999: 34.7 
Sources: Screen Digest (contact: 
David Hancock@screendigest.com) and
UNESCO Institute for Statistics.
TO KNOW MORE
Yi Yi, by Taiwanese director Edward Yang, reveals the gulf between the old and the new.
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The Kazakh film industry was a ship in the night.It raised a few hopes,
but now it’s vanishing.
At the end of the 1980s, cinema was the first cultural activity in Kazakhs-
tan to feel the currents of freedom that Mikhail Gorbachev’s policy of per-
estroika had unleashed.A dozen young filmmakers who had trained at
Moscow’s prestigious VGIK film school returned home in 1987,including
Serik A p r i m o v, Darezhan Omirbayev,Amir Karakulov,Talgat Te m e n o v,all of
whom would soon be winning prizes in major film festivals.
The story of the country’s film industry began with Rashid Nugmanov’s
1988 film The Needle, which was a big hit all over the then Soviet Union and
one of the first films to break the taboo of talking about drug addiction.N e x t
came A p r i m o v ’s T e r m i n u s, a  film depicting the absurdity of daily life in a
Kazakh village.
These films set a realist tone, and the works that followed—many of them
autobiographical—claim to follow in the tracks of Fr a n c e ’s “new wa v e.”
With their almost documentary styles and ingenuous touches, these fil m s
gave directors the freedom to say exactly what they felt.
The period after perestroika and then independence in 1991 proved quite
a good time for artists. Government continued to subsidize the film indus-
try and more than 30 private studios sprang up. But most of these have
since disappeared due to a lack of cash.In 1994,Kazakhstan (with its 16
million inhabitants) turned out about a dozen films. By 2000 this had fal-
len to only a handful.
Working conditions are tough, with no laws to encourage private film pro-
d u c t i o n ,old-fashioned studio equipment,virtually non-existent distribution
networks and a public with little money to spend on going to the cinema.
Fi l m m a kers have also lost their prestige.The unity of style and subject of the
early days has gradually faded, and local films were quickly eclipsed by
American imports.
Everyone has adjusted to the new situation in their own way.The luckiest
filmmakers, such as Omirbayev and Aprimov, have found foreign produc-
tion partners—in France and Japan—while others are making advertise-
ments or mortgaging their apartments. ■
CLOÉ DRIEU
RESEARCHERAND ASSISTANT TO DAREZHAN OMIRBAYEV
DON’T BLINK NOW, IT’S KAZAKHSTA N
directors like Fruit Chan and Stanley Kwan. Th e
interdependence of mainstream and non-mains-
tream cinema is perhaps most prominent here:
Chan and Kwan came through the ranks of com-
mercial cinema during the mid-and late-1980s,
when the industry was enjoying a golden age.
N o w, h o w e v e r, these directors have to seek fin a n-
cing elsewhere.
With the People’s Republic unlikely to relax
its control, and Hong Kong unlikely to support
commercially unviable projects, C h i n e s e - l a n-
guage cinema looks set to follow the Ta i w a n e s e
model of international funding. How this pro-
cess will impact on “Chinese national cinema” o r
even the idea of national cinema per se will prove
fascinating to watch. ■
A rg e n t i n a ’s gritty resurgence
A constellation of young directors is touching the “rawness of things in the street” with a
bare narrative and a poetic eye
UNIVERSITY PROFESSORAND
AUTHOR OF SEVERALWORKS ON
CINEMA The present is an absurd legacy of the past,”
says young Argentine filmmaker Pablo
Trapero.“It’s crazy that a guy of 50 has to
start from scratch like a kid.That kind of
absurdity creates a tension I used to tell the
story of Rulo.”
R u l o, the hero of Mundo Grúa (Crane Wo r l d,
1 9 9 9 ) ,Tr a p e r o ’s first feature fil m , is a worker fig h t i n g
to survive. O n c e, long ago, he had his 15 minutes of
fame as a member of a rock band, but he is not too
nostalgic and meekly accepts his daily lot. He quali-
fies as a crane operator,but is rejected for the job he
wants after failing a medical.Then a job in the pro-
vinces comes up, involving driving an excavator at a
site hundreds of kilometres from Buenos A i r e s, f a r
from friends and family. Rulo puts up with this until
DAVID OUBIÑA
34 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
he gets bored,then returns to Buenos Aires to face an
uncertain future.There is something noble about this
man who manages to keep going by clinging to what
little he has—loyal and unshakeable friendships.
The 28-year-old Trapero studied film at univer-
s i t y, and had only made short films before directing
Crane World. Shooting stretched out over a year
since it could only be done when there was enough
money for equipment and crew, though the gaps
allowed him to put together sequences and rewrite
the script as he went along.
“I wanted a film that was like a hidden camera
filming snatches of reality,” he says.The film,made
in semi-documentary style, gives a dramatized view
of daily life stripped of all pretence.“ The crane is for
all of us a symbol of building the future,” says Tra-
2 . NEW WAV E S
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 35
pero.“Rulo wants to have a future but he can’t get
o n e.” Everyday life, familiar characters, a bare nar-
rative and independent production—all are hall-
marks of other recent Argentine films that have
borrowed from the John Cassavetes tradition of
neo-realism and the “new waves”of the 1960s.
The nearest thing Argentina has previously had
to this kind of cinema came from the so-called 60s
Generation group of fil m m a k e r s, who trained in art
cinema and short movies.They called for a break with
t r a d i t i o n , with the big-studio star system and even
with “ e n t e r t a i n m e n t ,” just as their young descen-
dants in the 1990s have been fighting against the
hackneyed style of television and other media.Th e
critical and public acclaim received by Crane Wo r l d
along with its festival successes have shown how
potent this new genre of films can be.
Glossing over a troubled
past
The enthusiastic revival of Argentine cinema
in the 1960s was fleeting, but it gave birth to two
major fil m m a k e r s : Leonardo Favio and Hugo San-
t i a g o.Several years had to pass, h o w e v e r,before this
legacy could be built upon. First,the 1976 military
coup put an end to any chance of making fil m s.
Then, after democracy was restored in 1983, most
new films chose to flatter people’s good consciences.
This soothing, opportunistic genre was epitomized
by Luis Puenzo’s The Official Ve r s i o n ( 1 9 8 4 ) ,w h i c h
won an Oscar for Best Foreign Film and tells how
a woman begins to suspect that her adopted
daughter is one of the children of people killed by
the military.The story is not about the girl or her tor-
tured and murdered parents or about her grand-
mother who searches for her, but about a woman
filled with doubts about herself.Some films,never-
theless confronted the grisly events of the military
regime. They included Alejandro Agresti’s Secret
We d d i n g (1988) and Hugo Santiago’s
The Pavements of Saturn (1985).
The latest batch of films has received
scant encouragement.A new film industry
law (1994) was immediately applied in
the wrong way.Two new taxes—on video-
cassettes and films broadcast on televi-
sion—on top of the existing ones (a per-
centage on every cinema seat sold) were
meant to help subsidize Argentine fil m s,
but an economic recession cut proceeds to
a third of the envisaged amount.Fi n a n c i a l
aid to films on general release,m e a n w h i l e,
was disbursed according to box-offic e
r e c e i p t s. As a result, the animated fil m
M a n u e l i t a (1999) about a female turtle,
seen by two million cinema-goers,
received a much larger subsidy than either
Crane Wo r l d or Silvia Prieto,with 68,000
and 14,000 box-office sales respectively.
But Trapero is not alone in leading a
cinematic charge. Martín Rejtman,
Esteban Sapir and A d r i á n
Caetano/Bruno Stagnaro are also part of
a movement going by the name of “ N e w
Argentine Cinema,”which has produced
the country’s most exciting films in recent
years.“Films should be about everyday
t h i n g s,” says Sapir. “ You should
shoot in a different way and touch
the rawness of life in the street.We
have to change cinema by making
real life into a poem.”
It all began in 1995 with the
commercial screening of H i s t o-
rias Breves, a collection of short
films that had won prizes from the
National Institute of Film and
Audiovisual A r t s.The formula was
r e p e a t e d , and gave impetus to
several young directors—Raúl de
la To r r e,Eliseo Subiela, Juan Jo s é
Ju s i d , Daniel Barone and Beda
Docampo Feijoo—whose enthu-
siasm had managed to break
through a suffocating academic
milieu.
Argentina is now turning out
between 20 and 30 films a year.
But local showings are not enough
to recuperate the one to two mil-
lion dollars each film costs to
make, a budget that directors are
unwilling to trim. Rejtman attacks
this way of thinking, saying it is
“important for filmmakers to stop
thinking about sales strategies and
start thinking about film strate-
g i e s. I’m not saying there’s no
commercial cinema but we have
to stop thinking just about that.”
New films like P i z z a , Beer and
C i g a r e t t e s,Crane Wo r l dand Mala Epoca (Bad Ti m e s ) ,
which cost four or five times less to make than other
m o v i e s,had well-balanced investment/return ratios.
“ We should make films over the next five years that
d o n ’t cost more than $400,000 each,” says Caetano.
WORLD PRODUCTION RANK
1999: 19th
LOCAL FILMS’ SHARE OF 
DOMESTIC BOX-OFFICE
1998: 13%
NUMBER OF FILMS PRODUCED
TOTAL POPULATION (millions)
1988: 31.6
1998: 36.1
NUMBER OF SCREENS
1988: 647
1998: 810
CINEMA ADMISSIONS (millions)
1988: 28.4
1998: 32.4
TOTAL FILM PRODUCTION 
INVESTMENT (US$m)
1999: 133.3
Sources: Screen Digest (contact: 
David Hancock@screendigest.com) 
TO KNOW MORE
Marco Bechis’ Garage Olimpo: the Argentine military dictatorship revisited.
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
“ Th a t ’s still a huge amount of money for a country
without any.”Young filmmakers have learnt to save
money by forming co-operatives, not shooting at
w e e k e n d s, using natural backdrops and employing
non-professional actors and technicians who are fil m
s t u d e n t s.
Stagnaro and Caetano, two of the participants in
the Historias Breves, co-directed P i z z a , Beer and
C i g a r e t t e s in 1997 by respecting these conditions.
Its enthusiastic reception highlighted a slowly-deve-
loping trend that had evolved from films such as
Fine Powder (1996) by Esteban Sapir, which com-
bined the experimental style of Godard with novel-
ties from video-art;Garage Olimpo (1999) by Marco
B e c h i s, a lucid and painful look at detention centres
during the military dictatorship; and Mala Epoca
(1998) by Mariano de Rosa, Nicolás Saad, R o d r i g o
Moreno and Salvador Roseli, which linked a
number of stories set in a hostile urban context,
where everyone appears misplaced and unsettled.
“ We film things we’d like to see ourselves as
fil m - g o e r s,” says new director Andrés Ta m b o r n i n o.
Lucrecia Martel, also shooting her first fil m , says that
what annoys her about the “ d i n o s a u r s ” (the previous
generation of filmmakers) is that they became
“indifferent and timid,and so ended up using false
metaphors instead of getting out into the street
and depicting things as they are.”
The new wave of films cannot be called a move-
m e n t .They do not fit a defined set of values and are
not aesthetically uniform.Their vitality comes from
their diversity and their different approaches; t h e y
share what a country suffered, they share the spirit
of a generation, the methods of production, t h e
personal imprint of the author, the shunning of rhe-
toric and the concern for identity.They give a blunt
but impassioned account of Argentina following
the military dictatorship, in the era of Presidents
Raúl Alfonsín and Carlos Menem.
A film like Crane Wo r l d was a hit because it is a
sombre portrait of people who refuse to abandon
their hopes. It is this combination of melancholy and
resistance that connects Rulo with his audience. ■
36 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
2 . NEW WAV E S
By the time Itamar Franco was elected president of Brazil in 1992,the
country’s film industry had virtually disappeared.A year later, a new
broadcasting and cinema law lent fil m m a kers a lifeline: firms that decided
to invest in film production were given tax rebates of up to three per cent,
and investments could be recouped at the box office.
The Brazilian film industry at once leapt to life. Only two commercial films
were made in Brazil in 1992.In 1999,there were 33.Subjects have also
become more varied,and locations diversified.New talent has sprung up
not just in Rio de Janeiro, but also São Paolo, the northeast and the south
of the country.
A number of new films, such as Tata Amaral’s A Starry Sky, Beto Brant’s
B e l l y U p, Bruno Barreto’s Four Days in September, Sergio Rezende’s
Lamarca and Carla Camurati’s Carlota Joaquina,have addressed violence
and the country’s military dictatorships,while the sertão,or semi-arid nor-
theast of Brazil—which won renown in the classic Brazilian cinema of the
1960s through movies such as Nelson Pereira dos Santos’ Barren Lives
and Glauber Rocha’s Black God, White Devil—has been revived as a back-
drop.
“You can see in these new films the link between the new wave and tele-
vision melodrama, which grew in the 1970s and 1980s during a huge
surge in production,”says critic José Carlos A v e l l a r.Walter Salles’ film C e n -
tral Station, which won the Golden Bear prize at the 1998 Berlin Film Fes-
t i va l , illustrates precisely this connection through the story of a boy looking
for his father in the sertão with the help of a female teacher.
But economic crisis threatens this surge of creativity.“My new film didn’t get
a cent under the 1993 law,”says Salles, currently shooting in the sertão a Bra-
zilian version of Albanian writer Ismail Kadare’s novel Broken April.
“The 1993 law has shown itself to be shaky and inadequate,” says Paulo
C a l d a s, who has just made a documentary about city life, The Little Prince’s
Rap against the Wicked Souls. Over its first five years, $184 million went on
film production via the law and only $12.5 million on distribution and
marketing—a tiny sum in a market dominated by American films. ■
PEDRO BUTCHER
JOURNALIST AT THE Jornal Do Brasil
B R A Z I L : R E V I VAL AT RISK 
A statement of intent for Argentine cinema: Pablo Trapero’s Mundo Grua.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
D i re c t o rs 
in exile
Rithy Panh  (Cambodia), Alejandra
Rojo (Argentina) 
and Abderrahmane Sissako
(Mauritania) have all 
settled in France, but the 
pull of their home 
country permeates their 
artistic lives
How did you get into film?-----------------
Rithy Pa n h: It wasn’t something I chose.
Film came to me when I went into exile
after what I went through in Cambodia.
If I’d stayed there, I probably would
never have become a fil m m a k e r. It isn’t a reco-
gnized profession there.But  I’ve always been aware
of the power of images. In Cambodia,I lived next
door to a film studio, so I used to peak in on the
shoots.
The Khmer Rouge genocide is a genocide with
no recorded images except for photos. As such,
everything is  photographed in people’s memories.
What you’ve seen and lived through is always run-
ning through your mind. It was this—the process of
remembering things—that drew me into film. My
desire to make them was born here in Fr a n c e.Wh e n
I arrived in 1979, I knew my work would have to
relate to what had happened in Cambodia.After a
w a r, either you keep quiet or you try to piece toge-
ther what’s been shattered.I dabbled in painting and
w r i t i n g, and then, one day, someone lent me a
camera for a party at a vocational college where I
was taking a carpentry course. Some people made
cakes for the occasion, I made a little film.I knew
then, at 20, where my vocation stood. I attended
classes at IDHEC [a prestigious French film school]
and made my first documentary, Site Number Two,
about a Cambodian refugee camp.
Alejandra Rojo: When I was a kid, I wanted to
be a painter. But I was living in a very political envi-
r o n m e n t ,not an artistic one.My father was a lawyer
and my mother a psychoanalyst.When I was about
1 5 , I lost interest in painting, graduated from high
school and began studying science. But two years
l a t e r, I dropped all that and decided that I wanted to
make fil m s.So I followed classes and took the plunge.
Abderrahmane Sissako: I was brought up in
Mali and returned to Mauritania to finish high
s c h o o l . Right after that, I went off to the Soviet
U n i o n , like thousands of other African students. I t
was easier to go there than to Fr a n c e. I had a scho-
larship to study film and I started making my own.
How did you come to France?
Pa n h: Because of the Khmer
R o u g e. I was 17 years old. M a n y
members of my family were killed
and the rest of them fled to France.
R o j o: I came here when I was 12,
as an exile. My father defended poli-
tical prisoners.The whole family had
to leave A r g e n t i n a . It was the time of
the death squads—22,000 people
d i s a p p e a r e d . We were apparently on
the target list.
Sissako: I came in 1993 because
my film October had been chosen for
the Cannes Film Fe s t i v a l . I was
invited to stay here and continue fil m m a k i n g. I
spent 12 years in Russia and now I’m in Fr a n c e. Fo r
how long, I don’t know.
What are the pros and cons of living outside yo u r
own country? Does it affect the way you make fil m s ?
Pa n h: When you’re an exile, you don’t really
have an identity any more.Whether in Cambodia or
France, I’m kind of at home everywhere and now-
INTERVIEWS BY SOPHIE BOUKHARI
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 37
Abderrahmane Sissako (right) in Life on Earth.
Alejandra Rojo of Argentina
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
The films are a
roadmap through
emotional and
intellectual terrain
that provides a
solution on how to
save pain.
John Cassavetes,
American film
director (1929-1989)
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
here. Far and close from everything. I’m interested in
this distance. It allows you to stand back and to see fur-
t h e r, to grasp the shape of things.The lesser evil for an
exile is managing to make use of this. I go back to
Cambodia and then I leave it again. I t ’s a natural cy c l e.
Coming back to a Paris film studio is somewhat like
going on a retreat.I recharge my batteries. Cambodia
is a cultural desert.
R o j o:Exile changes your whole destiny. No matter
w h a t ,i t ’s always uprooting. But half my family wasn’t
killed or put in concentration camps.
I had a two-week sea voyage and
then understood what a drop in
status meant. You were someone
back home and  suddenly you
became nobody. In the end, t h a t ’s
not such a bad thing. You’re less at
the mercy of your social background.
You see things from a more personal
standpoint. Having to work in ano-
ther language creates a style simply
because you’re not fully in tune with
what’s being said.I’m always aware
of the gap, that what’s one way here would be different
there. Many immigrants share this feeling of living a
double life.But as an artist, I manage to go beyond this
stage.A film,a painting, a piece of music are all coun-
tries in themselves.You don’t need a country once you
have that.Exile is a moderately interesting life expe-
r i e n c e, but it’s fascinating from a cinematographic
standpoint.It’s a source of new ideas and stories. Our
age makes me think of some science fiction stories
about inter-galactic peoples who move about and
migrate on a mass scale. When I sit down to write, I
don’t tell myself that I’m going to write stories about
exiled people.They just come to me, from deep down
in my sub-conscious. You don’t make the films you
want.You make the films that have to be made.
Sissako: Exile is always a handicap. But distance
allows you to look at your own country, its past, i t s
history from a slightly foreign viewpoint. When we
talk about home, we tend to hesitate, to go by feel.It’s
a delicate process that you can lose a grip on at any
m o m e n t . Maybe we have more sensitivity. S o m e t i m e s
you choose to be silent and allow people to interpret.
What ties do you have with your native country?
Pa n h: I ’ve just made my first film in Fr a n c e,a docu-
mentary about the Cambodian community here. I ’ve also
shot one film in Mali. I ’ve made all the others in Cam-
b o d i a . I’m interested in living with the people there.
The film nearly becomes secondary.H e r e,I feel tired and
s t r e s s e d .Th e r e, the people who have to fight to survive
give me strength. Survivors always feel guilty.To escape
from this strange feeling, I need to be with other people.
The camera lets me do that—lets me say I have words,
dreams and thoughts to express, that I really belong to
the world. Film has helped me restore my own dignity.
In Cambodia, I’m also helping to train filmmakers and
t e c h n i c i a n s,with assistance from the Ministry of Culture.
Over the past 10 years,w e ’ve put together a good team.
Rojo: I don’t go back to Argentina very often.The
last time, I felt I was living in an American colony.
Here in France, you don’t realize how fast globali-
zation is racing ahead.The countries of the South are
becoming colonies,holiday camps or military camps
of the great American empire. There’s a film to be
made about that. I ’d go back to Argentina to work,
but that’s all. I t ’s to do with my family being
r e j e c t e d . I don’t see anything too exciting about
being Argentinian and it’s very hard to feel a cultural
identity there. I t ’s a sort of recent patchwork of
which I’m a good example.My maternal grandmo-
ther was Lithuanian and her husband was an Egyp-
tian who spoke Yiddish.My paternal grandfather,
who was a Spanish Catholic, married a Russian-
German Protestant.
S i s s a ko: I often go to Mali and Mauritania—
usually about twice a year, often to check film loca-
t i o n s. I go back and forth. Each trip enriches and
alters the story and each casting changes the film in
some way.
Do you have any urge to live in your native country?
Pa n h:D e fin i t e l y.But there’s no movie business
in Cambodia. I t ’s easier to find the money in Fr a n c e.
I raise money here but I keep to small Cambodian-
scale budgets.
R o j o: I think there’s something in Latin A m e r i c a
t h a t ’s worth really looking into,but I haven’t found
it yet.
S i s s a ko: I know I’ll go home one day. I’m in
France for financial reasons. I’m starting to be
known and I’m getting some interesting proposals
from producers and television. I t ’s very hard to
work in our countries.Filmmakers are on their own.
There’s no money to be had,no local film industry,
no film schools. Africa’s always had this dearth of
production and things are just getting worse. No
more than 10 films a year are made on the whole
c o n t i n e n t . You can’t have a ski champion in a
country where there’s no snow.
What are your plans?
Pa n h: Apart from fiction and documentaries, t h e
project closest to my heart is the gathering of a fil m
archive on the Cambodian genocide.Over the next
20 years, the witnesses will either die or their memo-
ries will become distorted.We live in a society domi-
nated by images. If we don’t make our own images,
we won’t exist any more.The countries of the South
are going to die of that too, after already being eco-
nomically pillaged.
Rojo: I’m working on a story about a woman
with a split personality.About a robot that replaces
a woman.
Sissako: My next film will be about exile. I’m
going to try to tell the story of people who apply to
emigrate,who are waiting to leave. I’d like to show
that exile begins before the voyage itself. My films
are often linked to my own life.At the same time, I ’l l
try to tell how I got into film. ■
2 . NEW WAV E S
38 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
I made films so my
mother, who didn’t
go to school, could
read the pictures.
Safi Faye,
Senegalese film
director (1943-)
Cambodian Rithy Panh
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Te c h n o l o g y,
the artist’s ally
All filmmakers can profit from new technology, says Egyptian director Yousri Nasrallah. The
only trouble is that it may turn distribution networks upside down
EGYPTIAN FILMMAKER, WHOSE LASTFILM
El Medina WAS SHOWN AT THE LOCARNO FESTIVAL (SWITZERLAND) IN
1999
I
made my fourth and latest feature fil m , E l
M e d i n a, in digital video on the streets of Cairo
and in Paris. I was the first Egyptian director to
make a fiction film using this new technique.
After the talkies, colour and the advent of
t e l e v i s i o n , many people see digital video as the
fourth revolution in the history of cinema.
It already has talented aficionados such as Lars
von Trier and the other Danish directors who support
his Dogma statement of film principles.Their watch-
w o r d s : shoot with a camera on your shoulder,use no
a r t i ficial lighting to be as true to life as possible. S u c h
a doctrine could only come from a rich country,w h e r e
creative people need self-imposed restrictions to
flo w e r.We on the other hand have to cope with autho-
ritarian regimes and the dead hand of censorship.
I ’ve given up 35mm cameras not out of principle,b u t
for practical reasons. My budgets won’t allow me to
do otherwise.
No easy images
Pragmatism means first of all not going on about
the film you might have made. Just do it,with every
resource you can lay your hands on. I have only one
r u l e : I must keep my independence. For my fir s t
f e a t u r e,Vols d’Été (Summer Flights),made in 1988,
I wanted a star from the Egyptian big-studio system
to play the wife of a landowner living in the 1950s
who hated [former Egyptian president, G a m a l
Abdel] Nasser. But she just wouldn’t accept the
p a r t . Her fans wouldn’t understand, she said. C h a n-
ging the script would be to lose my independence.
So I shot the film with non-professionals—an archi-
tect,a tourist guide and a journalist.
Whether it’s amateur actors or digital video,
once I’ve accepted the limitations that I haven’t
chosen,I have to sort out the problems they bring.
And that’s what I like.Th a t ’s where creation starts.
Technique is never an artist’s enemy.A painter
will try goache, oil or wash drawing techniques.
You and the cinematographer on a film simply want
the most out of the camera. Unlike 35mm fil m ,
video doesn’t have depth of field:right close up or
very far off, you get the same sharp image.To give
the shots depth,we tried to add as much colour as
p o s s i b l e, using painted walls and brightly-coloured
clothing.And we established the film’s visual style
to suit the story of these people who watch each
other from their balconies.
When a new technology appears, we often start
by asking the wrong questions. Digital video is
c h e a p e r,so will it lower artistic standards? Not at all.
The invention of the pencil didn’t lead to standar-
dized literature. Young directors have to unders-
tand that there are no such things as easy images,
only a less costly way to tackle problems. But the fear
that new techniques will make things uniform is
u n d e r s t a n d a b l e. Digital video has given rise to a
fashion that says because the cameras are light, y o u
ought to run all over the place.But do you remember
Julien Duvivier’s film The Great Wa l t z? The camera
was big as a wardrobe, but it spun round with the
greatest of ease because the film required it to.L i k e-
w i s e, a video film sometimes requires fixed shots.
Doubts about new technology tend to centre on
distribution,because there is talk of cinemas sho-
wing films beamed in by satellite. For big fil m s,
shown in thousands of cinemas, this method is jus-
t i fie d .But the telecommunications giants are trying
to secure a monopoly. So what will happen then to
all the “little” films produced in poor countries?
The power of technology, h o w e v e r, a l w a y s
reaches a limit. For many years, we were cut off
from each other by television and its production
methods. All of us: viewers, producers and script -
w r i t e r s.But look at the credits of Fe l l i n i ’s or Yo u s s e f
Chahine’s films from the 1950s. There were many
authors—people who wanted to meet each other
and talk about life and fil m s. It was wonderful.
Today young filmmakers are rubbing shoulders,
working together and fighting against such isolation.
The same desire is there.And that goes for me too.
Every film I make, I want to get as many people
together as I can. ■
BY YOUSRI NASRALLAH
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 39
A scene from Dancer in the Dark ( L a rs von Tr i e r ) , a film shot with about 100 digital camera s .
THE RAGE FOR A S I A N C I N E M A
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
T
40 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
E T H I C S
On the eve of the U.S. presidential elections, the death penalty—repudiated by almost all democratic
nations—is notable only for its absence from debate. Abolitionists are changing their tactics to ‘win
over’ a majority
BY IVAN BRISCOE
UNESCO Courier JOURNALIST
hough the legal battle was arduous, G a r y
Gilmore eventually got what he had
longed for on January 17, 1977. Tied by
nylon rope to an office chair,with a white
target disc pinned to his chest, the petty
thief and lovesick murderer stared down
the barrels of five state rifle s.After ten idle
y e a r s, the firing squad in a Utah jailhouse
sent a signal around the world: e x e c u-
tions in the United States were back.
Since Gilmore’s landmark demise—
hastened by his own preference for death
in place of jail—a further 663 people have
f o l l o w e d , killed by lethal injections,e l e c-
tric currents or poison gas administered on
judicial orders. What started in the late
1970s as a dribble of ill-fated convicts had,
by the turn of the century, become a
regular feature of the nation’s public life,
played out to a peculiar combination of
silence from U. S.politicians and last-ditch
pleas for clemency from the European
U n i o n ,Amnesty International and other
moral bulwarks of the We s t .
The contrast with the rest of the demo-
cratic world—of which the United States
considers itself the leader—is more
marked on the issue of the death penalty
than possibly any other aspect of domestic
p o l i cy. While U. S. foreign policy bears
down on “rogue states,” its executioners
keep good rhythm with the likes of Iran
and Iraq (though remain way behind
U. S. death penalty:
victims seize 
the high gro u n d
Supporters of the death penalty celebrate an execution at the prison in Huntsville, Texas.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 41
group leader, C h i n a ) . When a proposed
worldwide moratorium on the penalty
came up for debate in the UN Human
Right Commission in April 1999, the U. S.
predictably voted against, along with
C u b a , C h i n a , Sudan and nine other
n a t i o n s.Some 108 countries,on the other
h a n d , have in law or in practice abolished
the punishment, with Turkmenistan and
Ukraine among the most recent to enlist.
The appeal of 
tough justice
For the average high-level U. S. p o l i t i-
c i a n ,h o w e v e r, the death penalty has only
minor administrative defects, if any at all.
Of the four presidential and vice-presi-
dential candidates lining up in elections
on November 7, all support the punish-
ment—from Democrat candidate Al Gore
to Republican George W Bush, who has
ratcheted up its use in his last five years as
Texas governor,granting only one reprieve
and rubber-stamping 144 executions.P u b l i c
support for the penalty, in spite of a major
new abolitionist offensive that has helped
cut approval ratings from a high of 80 per
c e n t , still hovers over 60 per cent.
“I call it the silver bullet, in reference
to the Lone Ranger [a U. S. t e l e v i s i o n
series set in the Wild We s t ] ,” e x p l a i n s
Robert Bohm,a professor in criminology
and death penalty expert from the Uni-
versity of Central Florida.“A lot of people
in this country who are very fearful of
c r i m e, whether rationally or not, are loo-
king for a silver bullet to deal with it—and
the death penalty is a very attractive
b u l l e t .”
A host of arguments, used previously
by philosophers as venerable as Thomas
Aquinas and Je a n - Jacques Rousseau,
have helped make the penalty an emblem
of tough justice. Despite a lack of agreed
data,defenders of capital punishment in
the U.S. argue that the system is cheap,
acts as a deterrent and prevents suppo-
sedly “ l i b e r a l ”parole boards from relea-
sing jailed murderers into an unsuspecting
world—a practice that Dudley Sharp,
from the Justice For All project,says has
led to 10,000 killings since 1971.Above all
else, the penalty is vaunted as the only
true outlet for a society outraged by hei-
nous crimes; as Rousseau wrote, “ i n
killing the criminal, we destroy not so
much a citizen as an enemy.”
In response, a new generation of abo-
litionists has quietly shed its moral indi-
g n a t i o n . No longer are the lives of serial
killers and sociopaths held to be inhe-
rently worth preserving. I n s t e a d ,p r e s s -
friendly groups like the Death Penalty
Information Centre stress the injustices
of its application, from the racial inequi-
ties that it breeds to the risk that inno-
cents might be slaughtered.
For the Centre’s director, R i c h a r d
D i e t e r, this strategy aims to conquer
A m e r i c a ’s famed middle ground, t h a t
majority of people who seem to support
the penalty without great conviction or
p a s s i o n . “ The death penalty seems to
have all this baggage, all these problems
—innocent people, international oppo-
s i t i o n , u n f a i r n e s s, racial problems,” h e
a r g u e s. “ Th a t ’s a lot of baggage, and it
may not be worth it.” In January, to Die-
t e r ’s delight, Illinois’ Republican governor
shelved the penalty over concerns that
innocent people might be executed.The
g o v e r n o r, fit t i n g l y, had been a lifelong
supporter of capital punishment.
Miguel Angel Martinez is one of
around 3,600 inmates whose life is at
stake. In 1992, a Texan court found the
prospective Air Force cadet guilty of mur-
dering three men in a gang knife assault—
an attack in which his new lawyer insists
he was a “bit player.” He was sentenced
to death at the age of 17, four years before
he was legally entitled to drink beer.
Writing from what he terms the “ m a n -
made hell”of Terrell Unit in Texas, Mar-
tinez says he harbours hopes for the new
abolition campaign. But death row has
razed all his faiths. Religion he sees as a
“hollow vessel,” while society is a place of
hate: “you know, there is still an actual
conditioning in people to accept punish-
ment even when other options exist . . .We
are all sadists and masochists to a degree.”
For many outside the United States, i t
is precisely this unnecessary cruelty that
taints the death penalty, even though the
same countries that now scorn the punish-
ment enjoyed their own illustrious
moments with the noose, guillotine and
hatchet man. British law—which heavily
i n fluenced practice in its colonies—was
bent on execution. By the 18th century,
for instance,222 crimes were punishable by
death in Britain, including robbing a rabbit
warren and cutting down a tree.The public,
in turn,liked nothing better than a picnic at
the gallows.When one notorious murderer
was hanged in 1807 in London, 4 0 , 0 0 0
people turned up, though an ensuing mass
frenzy killed a hundred of them.
Following World War II and the
spread of codified human rights, m a n y
nations reconsidered,then scrapped the
p e n a l t y. But the United States proved an
exception to the rule: even in the ten-
year hiatus from 1967 to Gilmore’s exe-
c u t i o n , courts and states,acting on a tem-
porary plunge in the penalty’s popularity,
shunned what one Supreme Court justice
termed the “machinery of death” i n s t e a d
of dismantling it outright. Indeed when
the Supreme Court issued its Furman vs
G e o r g i a rulings in 1972, declaring the
penalty to be “cruel and unusual,” f u r i o u s
southern state legislators busied them-
selves with redrafting their statutes to
accommodate the Court’s objections.A s
violent crime climbed steeply upwards
in the recession-hit 1970s, a new-look
death penalty was ready and waiting in
several state law books. Some 38 states
now feature the sentence in their penal
c o d e s, while around three per cent of the
n a t i o n ’s convicted murderers are dispat-
ched to death row.
Victims’ rights and the
d raw of opinion polls
Underlying this penchant for capital
punishment—particularly marked in
eight southern states, home to 90 per cent
of recent executions—appears a deep-
rooted sense of what justice means.Wh e n
Alan Wo l f e, a Boston University politics
professor, went to Texas to research opi-
nions towards the 1998 execution of Karla
Faye Tu c k e r, he was astonished by the
r e s p o n s e : rather than feel pity for the
cheery 38-year-old inmate who had
repented and “found God,” most people
believed death to be perfect retribution
for her pickaxe slaying of an ex-lover.
“I think it touched on a very basic,
fundamental view of society that people
h a v e, that is pre-political and pre-religious,
that has to do with an inherent sense of
what justice means,”says Wo l f e.“ I t ’s about
paying for your sins and creating some
sort of equilibrium: a life is taken,and the-
refore another life should be taken.”
Retribution and scant pity for the
murderer dominate the thinking of those
who fervently back the penalty—espe-
cially the victims’ relatives.The first rela-
tive allowed under a new Texan law in
1996 to witness the execution of the mur-
derer recalled how “I would like to have
seen him humiliated a bit. I think he
should have been brought in and strapped
down in front of us.” In radio talks shows
across the land,callers demand that killers
be “fried”so they can “meet Hitler.”
The irony is that this atavistic sense of
justice is so out of synch with other trends
in U.S. culture. Most Christian teachings
“It’s about paying for your 
sins and creating 
some sort of equilibrium:
a life is taken,
and therefore another 
life should be taken”
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
innocent lives may have been shed.Die-
t e r ’s centre lists 87 people exonerated
from death row since the penalty’s reins-
t a t e m e n t , while several DNA tests are
currently underway in an effort to dis-
cover the first scientific confirmation of an
executed innocent.
Racial bias in imposition of the death
penalty has provided yet further ammu-
nition for the punishment’s opponents.
Although black murderers are propor-
tionately under-represented on death
r o w, there is undeniable statistical evi-
dence showing that death penalties are
imposed almost entirely (over 80 per-
cent) when victims are white. In Georgia,
meanwhile, Mears reports that only one
out of 159 district attorneys is black. For
many campaigners, says criminology pro-
fessor Robert Bohm,the penalty is simply
“a new form of social control that
replaced slavery.”
Calls for a moratorium
In the case of Martinez, prejudice (he
is Mexican-American),poverty, and the
fact that an accomplice’s father was a
local judge appeared to have vitiated all
chance of leniency. Indeed his legal saga
reads like a litany of the death penalty’s
i n i q u i t i e s : his trial lasted five days, t h e
alleged accomplices are free, and a large
part of the local district attorney’s office
has since been sacked for taking bribes.
“It is like two people playing chess, one
who is very good at it and another who is
just learning how the pieces move,” he
recalls of his trial.
His case and others have led campai-
gners to hope a moratorium may be
called as the “silver bullet” is sullied by
procedural failure, and maybe buried by
a richer variety of crime policies.S c e p t i c s
for their part warn that the machinery of
death could just be reinvented in a
s l e e k e r, “ f a i r e r ” g u i s e. But one thing
seems clear: if the penalty goes, it will not
go at the behest of an ethical revolution.
As Wolfe argues, “if you leave out the
morality entirely, I think A m e r i c a n s
would be very sympathetic to halting or
at least slowing capital punishment.” ■
42 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
point to the importance of forgiveness,
and most Americans are practising Chris-
tians. Daytime television has made the-
r a p y, and its motifs of confessing past sins
and reinvention,central to people’s lives.
But murder and punishment,above all in
the south, still follow the dictates of an
“eye for an eye.”And while violent crimes
soared over the past two decades, c l a i-
ming the lives of 500,000 Americans (with
around 17,000 murders a year at present)
and drawing gruesome media coverage,
adherence to this philosophy of uncom-
plicated vengeance grew inexorably.Th e
victim—and concepts of victimhood—
now stand at the heart of the modern
U. S. death penalty, whether in the sen-
tencing phase of the murder trial,when
bereaved relatives take the stand, or in
state politicians’ rhetoric.“If the debate
is just over the penalty or not the death
p e n a l t y,” sighs Dieter, “ i t ’s like asking
whether you’re for criminals or victims.”
Public opinion in countries like Bri-
tain or France, however, was hardly very
different.In almost all cases, clear majo-
rities supported the penalty, though poli-
tical leaders resolved to push through
with abolition all the same. Politicians in
the United States, on the other hand,
have been unwilling or unable to emulate
these feats. The generation that was so
closely linked to the civil rights era—the
Ke n n e d y s, Martin Luther King—may
have been equipped to do so,but its fig u-
reheads were fated to die early. M e a-
ningful debate has been further impeded
by the penalty’s deployment at state level,
often boxing the issue into a local crime
perspective, and by the absence of other
proposals such as gun control or poverty
programmes, ruled out by costs and lob-
b i e s.But more than any other factor, it is
what observers see as the frenetic nature
of U. S.d e m o c r a cy, with its comparatively
weak political parties, incessant elections
and hyper-sensitivity to opinion polls,
that has exposed candidates to constant
courting of voters’ hunches.
The price of opposing the penalty
became evident in the mishaps of Michael
D u k a k i s, Democratic presidential candi-
date in 1988, who turgidly repeated his
opposition to the penalty when asked
what he would do if his wife and children
were slain and thus was branded “ w e a k ”
on crime. All politicians swiftly learnt
that support for the penalty, though it
may not have mattered to them much as
an issue, was a vote-securing synonym
for “ t o u g h n e s s ” on crime. For elected dis-
trict attorneys (local prosecutors), who
often later become judges,exploitation of
the issue became rife.“ I t ’s a quick way to
get on television and get your name in the
p a p e r,” says Michael Mears, from the
Georgia Indigent Defense Council.“It’s
a placebo for the public, like giving the
patient a sugar-coated tablet.”
With victims occupying the moral
high ground and politicians unable to
draw themselves away from the glitter
of a poll booster, the practical tack taken
by the new abolitionists seems sensible.
Already they appear to have convinced
the majority of the American public that
● www.prodeathpenalty.com
supporting the death penalty
● www.deathpenaltyinfo.org
Death Penalty Information Centre
● www.miguelangelmartinez.com
website of Miguel Angel Martinez
● www.knoware.nl/users/annegr/
deadman/talking.htm 
articles by death row inmate Dean Carter
TO KNOW MORE
Protestors rally against the execution of Gary Graham in Texas (June 2000).
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 43
Y
S I G N S O F T H E T I M E S
Everyone dances in Africa: from this simple truth, Alphonse Tiérou, a choreographer and researcher
from Côte d’Ivoire, fashions his faith in dance’s power to push society onwards
INTERVIEW BY JASMINA SOPOVA
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
our last work is entitled “If Dance Moves,
Africa Will Move”. What do you mean by
t h a t ?
A country’s economic and social
development does not depend only on
its capital and labour, as economists and
the free-market tradition suggest. C u l-
ture is just as important.In La société de
c o n fia n c e ( “ The Society of Tr u s t ” ) ,p u b l i-
shed in 1995,the French academic Alain
P e y r e fitte correctly explained that the
main theories placing economic resources
such as raw materials, c a p i t a l ,l a b o u r,p r o-
duction,investment,and growth rates at
the heart of development were out of
date. He said that cultural factors, which
have been relegated to the rank of “by-
standers,” should be regarded as a basic
driving force of progress. In truth, t h e
intangible, immaterial aspects of culture
help to shape people’s mentalities.Th a t ’s
why they are the real locomotive of any
society. If they are neglected,if they are
not put at the core of thinking about
d e v e l o p m e n t , there is a chance they may
turn into insurmountable obstacles.
What cultural factors impede development
in Africa?
Ta b o o s, s u p e r s t i t i o n , polygamy and
tribalism are some of them. How can a
woman lead a fulfilling life when she is
constantly struggling against her rivals
to keep her husband’s affection? How
can you bring up your children the way
you want to when you must submit to
your elders’ authority? How can you
think and reflect with a calm,level head
when 10 or 20 of you are living under the
same roof? In my opinion,this custom is
an abuse of the traditional values of bro-
therhood and generosity because it stands
in the way of personal self-fulfil l m e n t .
You can’t save money or achieve per-
sonal goals because you must obey the
g r o u p ’s demands. In this “ g r e g a r i o u s ”
s o c i e t y, whose roots lie in traditional cul-
t u r e, it is inconceivable for the individual
to have an existence outside his or her
c o m m u n i t y. But individuality is precisely
where the source of progress lies.
Of all these problems, the most
serious is probably an inferiority com-
p l e x , which has a tremendous hold in
Africa. It generates a culture of depen-
dence to the detriment of a culture of
r e s p o n s i b i l i t y, paralyzes and suffocates
the whole continent,destroys the basis of
social cohesiveness. I’m convinced that
the main cause of under-development in
Africa is a lack of self-confidence.
What do you mean by that?
Africans do not trust A f r i c a n s.Wh i t e s
enjoy more consideration and are given
more resources than blacks. Take a per-
sonal example. In 1987,during a lecture
tour in black A f r i c a , I was arrested in one
country and brought before the ministry
of youth, s p o r t s, culture and scientific
r e s e a r c h , which considered my speech
on African culture suspicious.At the end
of a prolonged interrogation,a white man
Moving Africa with
a dance rhythm
A pioneering theorist of A f r i c a n
c h o re o g raphy 
The choreographer and independent researcher Alphonse Tiérou,43,comes from a long line
of great “families”that are heirs to the wisdom masks of West Africa.Brought up among
great chiefs and prominent dignitaries, he studied at the National Arts Institute in A b i d j a n ,t h e n
capital of his native Côte d’Ivoire, after a traditional education in African dialectic and rhetoric.
Ti é r o u ’s first book, Le Nom africain ou langage des traditions ( “ The African Name or the Language
of Tr a d i t i o n s ” ) , published in 1977, is about oral civilization.His work on African masks,Vérité pre -
mière du second visage africain ( “ The First Truth of the Second African Fa c e ” ) , came out one year
l a t e r. In 1983, he published La Danse africaine c’est la vie ( “African Dance is Life”), followed by
his main work on traditional choreography, Dooplé: The Eternal Law of African Dance (his only
work translated into English by Harwood Academic Publishers, 1 9 9 2 ) , which has gone through
three editions in French since 1989. His first novel, S é g o u l é d é, came out in 1992. His next book,
which will be published by the same Paris-based company, Maisonneuve et Larose, is entitled S i
la danse bouge, l’Afrique bougera (“If Dance Moves,Africa Will Move”).
Alphonse Tiérou also devised the touring exhibition that came to the Musée de l’Homme in Pa r i s
in June 2000 under the title “From dance to sculpture:a different view of African aesthetics. ”
He is currently the director of the Dooplé resource, teaching and research centre for African crea-
tion in Paris. For more information,call (33 1) 44 73 42 01.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44 The UNESCO Courier - October 2000
walked into the office. He spoke out on
my behalf. The minister immediately
changed his tone.After a few phone calls,
he opened doors for me to all the media
while the most beautiful conference hall
in the city, the place used by the country’s
sole political party, was placed at my dis-
p o s a l . Similar things happen every day
in our countries.
This inferiority complex can also be
seen in the relationship with traditional
d a n c e. S o m e t i m e s, African artists who
have acquired a veneer of training in
Western dance hurriedly denigrate their
r o o t s. L i k e w i s e, instead of developing
their own analyses,African intellectuals
just repeat everything that some foreign
pseudo-specialists say and write about
their culture.The problem is that the dis-
course of these specialists often locks
African dance in a ghetto and denies the
continent the right to evolve and moder-
nize.They see Africa as a living museum
of past traditions.
Can dance change that mentality?
I’m convinced it can.The creative act
is fundamental to the emancipation of
the individual.Everyone knows that. B u t
it is even more fundamental in the
African context, where individuality, t h e
source of progress, is often stifled by
group pressure and conformity.
That is where dance can be a factor of
d e v e l o p m e n t . It can tear up the old
s t u m p s, destroy the causes of evil that are
deeply rooted in the human sub-conscious,
give individuals the possibility of belon-
g i n g, of finding and fulfilling themselves.
That is how it can make society move.
Because only a society made up of free
and self-confident individuals can find the
right solutions to its problems.
D a n c e, a major component of A f r i c a n
c u l t u r e,mobilizes a vast amount of energy
that should be more effectively channelled.
Everybody dances in A f r i c a : p h a r a o h s,
queens and kings, s a i n t s, the masks of
w i s d o m ,pregnant women,b a b i e s,old folks,
j u d g e s,g e n e r a l s,heads of state—remember
Mandela? Governments in Africa should
take more account of the emancipatory
qualities of dance,and also give artists and
researchers the means to pursue their
work more effectively.They mustn’t forget
that the very fact of researching our
d a n c e s, which condition our entire lives,
means agreeing to accepting ourselves as
we are, freeing us from our complexes,
making us feel good about who we are
and what we think, proving that we have
c o n fidence in ourselves, in all Africans and
in the rest of the world.
How can African dance help to establish a
relationship with the rest of the world?
Choreography is an “ e x p o r t a b l e ”c u l-
tural product. On a large scale, it could
become an asset for modern A f r i c a .S i n c e
African dance has spread worldwide, i t
has done more to bring young people from
the North and South closer together than
any other policy,no matter how good and
w e l l - i n t e n t i o n e d .Dance is still the shortest
route linking one individual to another. I t
is about passion and seduction. D u r i n g
the period of colonization, We s t e r n e r s
understood this perfectly well and made it
illegal to dance with A f r i c a n s.
In the past few decades, thanks to the
African diaspora and to the many dance
courses held in the North as well as the
S o u t h , the trend has started moving in
the opposite direction. Real exchanges
have taken place, sincere and deep friend-
ships have been woven in a spirit of
mutual trust, dignity and respect. Th e
rising interest in African dance calls for an
adequate response on the part of A f r i c a n s
themselves, so that supply grows at the
same pace as demand.Because, to para-
phrase the French philosopher A l b e r t
Ja c q u a r d , on the dance floor “the only
worthy goal is not to be better than o t h e r s,
but to be better because of others.” ■
Dance can tear up 
the old stumps,
destroy the causes of 
evil that are
deeply rooted in the human 
sub-conscious,
give individuals the 
possibility of belonging,
of finding and 
fulfilling themselves
Nelson Mandela dances with a choir of compatriots at the 8th  Assembly of the World Council of Churches (December 1999).
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 45
The great poet and president of Senegal,
Léopold Sédar Senghor, said that by
using the word “ s t e p,”the Europeans had
turned dance into an abstract game “to
take man off the earth and project him
into the sky.”Africans prefer the expres-
sion “basic movement,” because it implies
a connection between the dancer and the
earth.A famous verse by the same poet
perfectly expresses this symbiotic rela-
tionship between human beings and the
earth beneath them: “ We are dancing
people whose feet are revitalized by
stamping them on the hard ground.”
The first of the ten basic movements,
which I have observed in all the regions
and among all the peoples of A f r i c a , is the
d o o p l é. This is a composite term bor-
rowed from Oueoulou, the secret lan-
guage of the glaé, a community of mask
bearers belonging to the Wêon people,
who live in western Côte d’Ivoire. G l a
(the singular of glaé) means mask in the
African sense of the term, in other words
the costume, the accessories and those
who wear them. I have chosen the lan-
guage of this community of wisdom
masks (in Africa,the mask is considered
a living entity) because it is sacred,spiri-
t u a l , divine and, as a result, belongs to
no single group of people. Furthermore,
the Wêon (also known as the Guéré) are
the guardians of the only g l a é p r a y e r,
whose content clearly expresses the com-
bined spiritual, technical and structural
aspects of dance.
In Oueoulou, d o o means mortar and p l é,
p e s t l e. These are cooking utensils
common to every part of Africa and
occupy a central place in everyday life.
The movement of a person using a pestle
is the basis of African dance. On the one
h a n d , the pestle pounding the mortar
produces sounds, percussion, a beat—in
short,music. On the other hand,the up-
and-down movement of the plé beating
against the doo makes it shake, tremble,
move—in other words,d a n c e.So the d o o
becomes a musical instrument, the plé a
dancing object and the person doing the
pounding, a composer.
Dance conveys our vision of the world
and conditions our entire existence. I t s
basic movements are all symbolically
c h a r g e d . They express a person’s rela-
tionship to the Earth, to God, to the com-
munity of the living and that of the dead.
Each movement also has a specific mea-
n i n g : dancing in a bent-over position with
arms folded over the chest is a symbol of
i n i t i a t i o n ; stamping feet on the ground
is a show of extreme joy; tapping fore-
heads against each other is an act of com-
munion.Dance is thus a coded language
that creates a dialogue between dancers
and spectators familiar with its under-
lying symbolism, signifying that it cannot
be measured against Western standards
despite frequent attempts to do exactly
that.In African dance, for example, sho-
wing two open hands is a sign of honesty,
clear conscience and hospitality. I n
contemporary dance, the same g e s t u r e
symbolizes the density of the air that the
artist embraces or pushes away. Jo i n i n g
the palms of two hands together is a gesture
of prayer in the Christian world.For A f r i-
c a n s,h o w e v e r, it is a way of concentrating
all the body’s energy,the right hand having
a negative polarity and the left, a posi-
tive polarity. The symbolism of these
movements is rooted in an ethical, aes-
thetic and social context that cannot be
ignored if one wants to grasp the full
meaning of African dance.And even less
so if one wants to judge it. ■
S I G N S O F T H E T I M E S
Moving Africa with a dance rhythm
ALPHONSE TIÉROU
DIRECTOR OFTHE DOOPLÉRESOURCE ,
TEACHINGAND RESEARCH CENTRE FOR AFRICAN CREATION IN
PARIS
In Africa, dance and the
economy are intrinsically
connected: the origins of the
dooplé, the first of ten basic
movements in African dance, lie
in the motion of using 
the pestle
Dance is a coded
language that creates
a dialogue between
dancers and spectators
familiar with its
underlying symbolism
TELL ME HOW YOU DANCE A N D
I’LL TELL YOU WHO YOU A R E
Doing the dooplé: with a straight back,knees
bent and each foot planted firmly on the
ground,rise and bend as if pounding a mortar
and pestle to the beat of the music.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
D i g i t a l
d i s a p p e a ra n c e s
T
46 The UNESCOCourier - October 2000
C O N N E X I O N S
Obsolete machines and the ephemeral nature of web-based materials are just some of the hurdles
confronting archivists as they struggle to preserve the world’s digital heritage
SARA GOULD AND 
MARIE-THÉRÈSE VARLAMOFF
SARA GOULD IS PROGRAMME OFFICER FORTHE UNIVERSAL
AVAILABILITY OF PUBLICATIONS AT IFLA (INTERNATIONAL
FEDERATION OF LIBRARY ASSOCIATIONSAND INSTITUTIONS).
MARIE-THÉRÈSE VARLAMOFF IS CHIEF CURATOR
AT THE FRENCH NATIONAL LIBRARY AND
DIRECTOR OFTHE PRESERVATIONAND CONSERVATION
PROGRAMME AT IFLA.
he wobble of Neil A r m s t r o n g ’s legen-
dary leaps on the moon are engraved in
the memory of at least a generation.Yet
30 years later, much of the actual data
from that mission has been lost. Appa-
rently, NASA lacked the foresight to save
the equipment and software required to
read it. If the scourge of technological
obsolescence can cause such a loss for
the world’s leading space agency, i m a-
gine the challenge awaiting national libra-
ries in their task to preserve the world’s
digital heritage.
Just a few years ago, digital technolo-
gies emerged as a godsend for archivists.
As e-mail and the Internet spread, p u n d i t s
began taking bets on how long it would
take for paper to disappear. L i b r a r i e s
with the financial means began digitizing
their collections. Instead of submitting
their precious collections to page-fraying,
spine-breaking habits of scholars in a
merciless search for key passages, libra-
rians handed them a slim pair of C D-RO Ms,
digital copies of the great works, which
could be scanned in minutes.With a flip of
a switch, libraries could signficantly
expand access to their collections.
Yet in the frenzy to digitize, precious
resources may have been wasted.Wi t h o u t
a co-ordinated strategy, some sister orga-
nizations have made digital copies of
similar sections of their collections.Wi t h
a bit more foresight, they might have
worked together to offer a more diverse
s e l e c t i o n . Converted to the cult of the
new technologies, others have been a bit
too zealous in cleaning up—throwing
out—their ageing documents like old
n e w s p a p e r s.And fin a l l y, some of the more
prestigious institutions have fallen upon
a double-edged sword after proudly dis-
playing the gems of their collections on
the Internet.The digital versions whetted
the general public’s appetite to see the
“real thing”which means that crowning
documents like the Magna Carta risk
becoming veritable attractions.
I r o n i c a l l y, the supposed saviour, d i g i-
t i z a t i o n , may be an enemy in the battle to
build and preserve perpetual archives.
To begin with, t h e
technology is so new
that we cannot be cer-
tain of the longevity
o f, for example, C D-
ROMs. A more imme-
diate threat lies in the
extraordinary speed
of technological pro-
g r e s s. “ The great
creator becomes the
great eraser,” warns an American futurist,
Stewart Brand.We can read a thousand-
y e a r-old manuscript,yet archivists cannot
decipher some materials that are less than
20 years old.
Remember the old floppy discs of the
not-so-distant past? If by some miracle a
library finds some of those clunky
m a c h i n e s, the chances of acquiring spare
parts, the right software required and a
trained technician are just about nil.
To d a y, “backward compatible” s o f t-
ware—that designed to read old ver-
sions—generally only covers one or two
generations of changes,which offers little
relief when the average life cycle of hard-
ware and software is a mere 18 months.
I n d e e d , the U. S.based Research Libraries
Group found in a 1998 survey that nearly
half (15 of 36) of its member institutions
reported losing access to part of their
digital holdings because of obsolescence.
Awaiting a long-term solution, a r c h i-
vists continue to rely on a veritable relic:
m i c r o film for crumbling paper collec-
tions. But the old stand-by does little to
resolve the latest thorn in their side:the
new wave of “ b o r n - d i g i t a l s,” w o r k s
created on computer-like websites and
electronic journals.
Consider the case of continually up-
dated documents on the We b. Should we
preserve all the various drafts of the docu-
ment or only the final version? The drafts
of great works of literature are treasure
troves for scholars. For instance, Victor
H u g o ’s splendid
handwriting and the
powerful drawings he
used to fill in the mar-
gins of the pale blue
paper he favoured are
rich in historical signi-
f i c a n c e. In the near
f u t u r e, those who
study literary history
will be at a loss if all
they have is a diskette containing the
final “ c l e a n ” version with no draft, n o
h e s i t a t i o n , no notes, no drawings nor
doodles.
The same is true of e-mail.A century
a g o, famous writers may have recorded
their movements, discoveries and emo-
tions to friends or family in letters which
have often been preserved as part of our
cultural heritage, helping to set literary
works in the context of the writer’s life and
t h o u g h t . E-mail storage is increasingly
seen as a burden on a computer system.
Will the memory of today’s literary giants
lose out to that of the computer? 
And what about all the links an elec-
tronic publication might have to other
websites? The exhilaration that grips us
when we surf the Net quickly turns to
vertigo with the thought of preserving
that sea of information.
In the near future, those 
who study literary 
history will be at a loss 
if all they have is 
a diskette containing the 
final “clean” version
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCOCourier - October 2000 47
National libraries are testing two dif-
ferent approaches. Given the extraordi-
nary volume of web-based materials,
Australian archivists are becoming “ g a t e-
k e e p e r s,” sifting through and selecting
the most important materials for a
national electronic repository.To be part
of the depot, an item must either be
about the country or particularly rele-
vant to its interests. A l t e r n a t i v e l y, it can
be the work of an Au s t r a l i a n ,r e c o g n i z e d
as an authority on an issue of interna-
tional signific a n c e. While this approach
appears to be the most practical, there is
a danger in becoming overly selective.
After Napoleon ransacked the Va t i c a n
archives and sent them back to Paris in
1 8 1 0 , the French only saved the docu-
ments of immediate and apparent
i n t e r e s t .
Alternatively, archivists might try to
save the entire electronic domain of a
country. Sweden has embarked on such
an ambitious project, in collaboration
with other Nordic states.Thanks in large
part to a robot that takes regular “snap-
shots” of the Internet, the Swedes have
already amassed more than 58,000
items—from online publications to confe-
rence proceedings—in building a central
electronic repository.
Both of these routes lead to two major
o b s t a c l e s : copyright conflicts and costs.
In some countries, publishers must
deposit copies of every new publication in
national libraries.These laws, h o w e v e r,d o
not always apply in the electronic domain.
While some publishers voluntarily deposit
copies of “ h a n d h e l d ”w o r k s, like C D-RO Ms,
ephemeral works like electronic journals
are practically untouchable for legal rea-
s o n s. By subscribing to those journals,
libraries or individuals aren’t actually
buying a “ c o p y,” just a license to access the
material.
Taking a digital
refresher
Do they have the right to offer that
access to the public? And what if a library
stops a subscription? Then they don’t
necessarily have the right to display or
offer public access to back issues for
which they paid.
Enormous financial pressure is buil-
ding on national libraries and publishers
alike to iron out new business arrange-
ments and partnerships. Publishers are
leery of the responsibility for preserva-
t i o n , yet at the same time cannot afford to
see their collections become obsolete.
M e a n w h i l e, the archivists are finding it far
more expensive to acquire an electronic
publication than a traditional one. Th e
National Library of Au s t r a l i a , for example,
estimates that it takes one person a full
working day to acquire the first version of
an online publication—a task five times
more labour intensive than adding a print
i t e m . A study by the British Library sug-
gested that the cost of managing and pre-
serving a digital publication over a 25-year-
period is about 20 times greater than it is for
p r i n t .
A hefty chunk of the costs go to “ r e f r e-
s h i n g ” digital documents. Every five or
ten years, electronic collections are sup-
posed to embark on a “ m i g r a t i o n ,” i n
archival lingo, to an updated computer
c o n fig u r a t i o n .U n f o r t u n a t e l y, the journey
is not without its casualties. Formats and
presentations may change and some sec-
tions risk disappearing altogether.Does it
matter if the look and “ f e e l ” of a website
c h a n g e s, so long as the contents remain? 
For some archivists, migration is just a
standby for “ e m u l a t i o n ,” which would
involve a combination of software and
hardware capable of mimicking the beha-
viour of obsolete platforms and operating
s y s t e m s. In short, the aim is to develop a
kind of mini-archive to “ r e m i n d ”c o m p u-
ters of their past. But the technological
wizards can only forge part of the key to
preserving our digital documents. U l t i-
m a t e l y, we must reconfigure relations bet-
ween libraries and publishers. ■
National libraries with the financial means have been steadily digitizing their collections.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Tu e n j a i
D e e t e s :
a bridge to the hill tribes
48 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
T A L K I N G T O . . .
t a time when many T h a i
people viewed the hill
t r i b e s1 in the north of the
country as a security risk,
you started working with
t h e m .Wh y ?
In the early 70s, I was a
university student in
Bangkok where I heard
all kinds of stories about
the hill tribes,many of whom had fled from
ethnic conflicts and hardships in neigh-
bouring Burma, L a o s, China and Cam-
b o d i a . The hill tribes were accused 
of drug traffic k i n g, prostitution and de-
stroying forests with their slash and burn
cultivation methods. I decided to see for
myself through a student volunteer pro-
gramme to teach the Thai language in the
h i l l s.It didn’t take long to see that there was
very little truth in those allegations.
I first went to stay with the Lizu
people in Chiang Rai province.Here was
this city-girl, born in Bangkok, who had
never before climbed mountains, s t u m-
bling along trails for four hours. I ’ll never
forget how refreshing it was to find the
village and its tidy winding paths shel-
tered by an enormous forest. Despite all
of the negative things that I heard, to my
great surprise, I found the hill tribes living
in a pure environment leading a simple
traditional life. I couldn’t understand
their language yet I could feel the
With an iron will and a calm
spirit, the activist continues her
25-year struggle with the hill
tribes of Thailand for cultural
and environmental
preservation
A
Tuenjai Deetes,left, in a hill tribe village in northern Thailand.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier 49
Individuals and groups with vested
interests exploited the geographic advan-
tage of the region for opium production.
But the blame fell on the hill tribes, lea-
ding the United Nations and the Th a i
government to massively introduce the
cultivation of cash crops like fruits and
v e g e t a b l e s.These projects have had little
success in improving the life and dignity
of the hill tribes and have taken a heavy
toll on the environment.
The Hmong tribe, for example,
have been among the worst affected.To
grow vegetables, they diverted more and
more water from the rivers and began
using fertilizers to increase their yields.
By reducing and polluting rivers, t h e y
came into conflict with the Thai farmers
living in the lowlands.
Wasn’t this also linked to the problem of
d e f o restation? We ren’t the hill tribes
accused of causing great damage by clea-
ring forest for farming and then burning
the fields after a harvest to re j u v e n a t e
the soil?
Tr a d i t i o n a l l y, the hill tribes used
slash and burn tactics in a limited way—
just to produce food for their families.
But in trying to produce cash crops and
satisfy the demands of the market, t h e
tribes surpassed the natural capacities of
the land,degraded by deforestation and
e r o s i o n . The Akha tribes, for example,
began cultivating rice in steep areas,
which caused soil erosion.They are now
trying alternative methods.
H o w e v e r, I do not think that slash
and burn cultivation alone caused the
deforestation in the northern region.
Timber companies and other commercial
groups from the south should be held
responsible for the large-scale problem.
I do not deny that a country like Th a i l a n d
needs more timber and other natural
resources for its economic development.
But at what cost? To d a y,no one appears
willing to publicly discuss this problem.
You  started out as a ‘ s p o ke s p e rson’ for the
hill tribes. How has your role changed?
By studying their language, h i s t o r y
and kinship system, I gained their confi-
d e n c e.This enabled me to introduce some
basic education projects which later led to
the creation of the Hill Area Development
Foundation (HADF,see box).Since then,
with the help of donor agencies, and the
Thai government we were able to esta-
blish schools for children as well adults in
the hill regions.
The general aim is to offer access to
the formal education system. H o w e v e r,
we also try to instil the children with a
deep sense of pride in their history and cul-
t u r e, so that they won’t blindly assimilate
the ways of mainstream society but change
in a positive way, based on their culture.
For example,we very carefully developed
a new syllabus integrating the knowledge
of the ethnic tribes with that of the Th a i
curriculum for the HADF-run schools.
We also concentrate on offering
training in sustainable agricultural
methods so that hill tribe farmers can
people—they were so pure in heart.Th e i r
spirit inspired me. I wanted to understand
their philosophy, their way of life in har-
mony with nature. I was enchanted by
the songs and folklore through which the
elders passed on their knowledge and
wisdom to the young.
The headman of the first village I
visited was like a father to me. He invited
me to stay, and even offered to build me
a hut, in exchange for teaching the chil-
dren and adults the Thai language. E v e n
though the Lizu and many other groups
have lived in Thai territory for genera-
t i o n s,very few spoke the language.Th e y
were so far removed,geographically and
c u l t u r a l l y, from the mainstream.We made
an agreement.Until they could speak for
t h e m s e l v e s, I would serve as an interme-
d i a r y, a bridge between the hill tribes,
the Thai government and wider society.
What kind of problems were the hill tribes
f a c i n g ?
At that time, nearly half of the hill
tribes didn’t even have Thai citizenship.
As a result, they didn’t have any legal
rights to the land they had been cultiva-
ting for years. The increasing demand
for forestland was pitting them against
Thai authorities who were declaring a
growing number of forest regions as
nature reserves in order to protect the
environment.
There were no roads, s c h o o l s, h o s-
pitals or public services in the hill regions.
The illiteracy rate was about 90 per cent
and the birth rate in the highlands was
almost three times higher than that of
the lowlands. Infant mortality was almost
d o u b l e. In short, they were the most
disadvantaged among the disadvantaged
in the country.And yet,even though they
were deprived of basic amenities, the hill
tribes never thought that they were under-
privileged because nature provided for
all their needs, including medicine.
We ren’t there accusations that the hill
tribes were involved in opium cultivation?
For generations, tribes like the Lizu,
the Hmong and others grew opium as
part of their cultural tradition. E l d e r s
would sometimes smoke during family or
community gatherings. It was also used
for a variety of traditional medicines.
These people rely on their own resources.
But I can assure you that a hill tribe never
got rich by growing opium for outsiders.
H o w e v e r, the situation changed
when increasing Western demand for
opium (to produce heroin) triggered
illegal trafficking of the drug from the 
so-called Golden Tr i a n g l e, the area bor-
dering Thailand,Burma and Laos.
Near the Myanmar frontier, Akhas slash and burn the land before planting crops.
1 . A c c o rding to the Hill Area Development Fo u n-
d a t i o n ,a p p r oximately one million hill tribe people
live in T h a i l a n d ’s mountainous northern and wes-
tern border regions. About 65 per cent of the hill
population belong to two major ethnic groups–the
Karen and Hmong tribes. Other tribes like the
L a h u ,A k h a ,M i e n ,H ’t i n ,L i z u ,Lawa and Khamu
make up the rest of the population.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50 The Unesco Courier - October 2000
“ a life in the hills ”
abandon slash and burn tactics.The new
t e c h n i q u e s, apart from preventing soil
e r o s i o n , revitalizes the land.
The environmental groups were
right to highlight the problem of defo-
r e s t a t i o n . H o w e v e r, instead of offering
a l t e r n a t i v e s, the government just began
evicting the tribes from forest areas.
Our aim isn’t simply to introduce new or 
foreign techniques but to adapt and 
revitalize traditional agricultural prac-
t i c e s. For example, the Karen tribes
continue to follow an age-old rotation
s y s t e m . Instead of clearing land entirely,
they simply cut the branches from the
bottom of trees. They then rotate bet-
ween swathes of land to grow a single
c r o p,which gives the soil a chance to reju-
v e n a t e.
This kind of training project seems to be
part of a larger struggle to strike a balance
between various groups depending on the
same limited re s o u rc e s. Can you describe
the ongoing conflict between the hill tribes
living in the re g i o n ’s watershed area and
those in the lowlands? 
In tropical countries like Th a i l a n d ,
we depend on a delicate natural process
whereby forests absorb rainwater and
release it into the rivers.If you reduce the
f o r e s t ,the rain just runs off the land and is
wasted instead of flowing into the rivers.S o
we must take immediate steps to preserve
the remaining forestland in the watershed
a r e a .Apart from being the main sources
of water, the watershed area is also very
supportive of many ecosystems.
U n f o r t u n a t e l y, only the hill tribes
living in the watershed region are
expected to preserve the forest while
those living downstream in the lowlands
and cities are not showing any signs of
changing their ways. In fact, they use
more water than people living in the ups-
tream areas. It is totally unfair on the part
of the authorities to impose restrictions
on the hill tribes and force them to relo-
cate far away from their region in an
effort to save forests.
How can we expect the hill tribes
alone to make all the sacrifices? Preser-
ving the environment is the duty of eve-
ryone and if we do not want the hill tribes
to use the forest,we have to provide them
with alternatives.Th a t ’s why I insist on a
harmonious relationship between the
two sides.
In recent years, the Thai government has
been investing in development projects
for the northern re g i o n . What are the
results so far?
There are more roads, e l e c t r i c i t y
and other basic infrastructure in the hills
n o w. But far less has been invested in
education or environmental projects
because politicians derive few benefit s
from them. When companies bid for a
contract to build a new road, for example,
a commission is usually given to the poli-
tician involved.
As a result of the construction pro-
j e c t s, there is increasing contact between
the hill tribes and lowland Thais which
has led to a new set of problems. Th e
insular life of the hills made it easier to
create a shared vision of life in harmony
with nature. Now the hill tribes must
deal with the symbols of materialism.I n
a way, they face the same problems as
many developing countries.
Greater exposure to advertising
creates more greed.Young people in par-
ticular want to wear blue jeans, drive a
m o t o r cycle or a car, just like city people.
They no longer want to work the land but
simply make money.So many are migra-
ting to big cities, which creates a lot of
social tension. In the cities, they often
get involved in prostitution, for example,
and then return to the hills carrying
diseases like A I D S.
Little by little, cultural identity is
eroded by materialism.If this continues,
I am afraid that the culture of the hill
tribes could be lost forever. So we—the
hill tribes,NGOs and government—must
find ways of improving living conditions
and assuring the people similar rights to
lowlanders while retaining their specific
cultural identity.
You mention the need for land rights, y e t
many of these people don’t even have a
Thai passport. Why is citizenship such a
p ro b l e m ?
Due to political and economic rea-
sons many hill tribes from neighbouring
countries have been migrating to Th a i-
land for centuries.You must understand
that indigenous people in general don’t
feel bound by national borders.To begin
w i t h , they are often forced to move
because of political conflicts and envi-
ronmental needs.
Up until 1992,it was relatively easy
to obtain some kind of identity papers 
if you were born in Th a i l a n d . But the
government changed the laws, after 
large-scale migration into the area for
both political and economic reasons.
According to new rules,applicants should
prove that they and their parents were
born in Th a i l a n d .But  few of these people
possess birth certific a t e s. We must also
consider the plight of those not born in
the country. How can we send people
back to Burma where there is no justice? 
It is very complicated. The Th a i
government cannot grant citizenship to
everyone and is doing its best under the
present circumstances. The cross-border
migration also brings friction within the
tribal communities.For example,H m o n g
ethnic tribes in Thailand are finding it dif-
ficult to secure enough forest for their
own families. So when ethnic confli c t
began driving Hmong tribes from Laos
across the border, the Thai Hmong asso-
ciation told them that they should go back
to their country once the situation stabilizes.
The hill tribes of Thailand are a major tourist
a t t ra c t i o n . Have they pro fited from this?
Eco-tourism and cultural tourism
should improve understanding between
people from different parts of the world.O n
the contrary,the travel industry is exploiting
the hill tribes in Thailand without even rea-
lizing it. While the government earns
revenue by promoting tourism in the north,
hardly any of the money is invested back in
the region. Only the tour operators and a
few middlemen profit .
The tourists tend to treat the 
indigenous people as some kind of exotic
s p e c i m e n . Instead of coming to the hills to
take photos, they should learn to respect
the local people and their culture. In nor-
thern Th a i l a n d , boats carrying foreign
tourists often stop at Lahu and Karen vil-
lages along the Mekong River.Wh e n e v e r
a boat arrives, children start running in
China
BANGKOK
CHIANG RAÏ
Thaïland
Cambodia
Laos
Myanmar
(Burma) GOLDEN
TRIANGLE
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G T O . . .
October 2000 - The Unesco Courier E51
Action Network. From Malaysia to the
Philippines and even Nigeria, t h e
struggle is in many ways the same.P e o p l e
need the rights to their lands and
resources—the right to earn a living with
nature. They need protection from the
multinationals, which plunder areas for
resources like timber, oil and minerals.
In the name of research, c o m p a n i e s
make millions by patenting the traditional
knowledge and medicines of indigenous
p e o p l e s. Now the tribes themselves are
being used for genetic research. In return,
the tribes get nothing. In Th a i l a n d , w e
have had some well-known cases of
exploitation of tribal medicines by We s t e r n
c o m p a n i e s.But due to legal complications
we could not do anything about the abuse.
We must also question government
policies for managing resources. Fo r
e x a m p l e, countries often declare forest
regions as protected areas, ignoring the
rights of indigenous peoples who have
been living there for hundreds of years.U p
until recently, the major environmental
campaigns and treaties did not look into
the problems of the indigenous people.
In the early 1990s, the United Nations
declared the International Decade for the
Wo r l d ’s Indigenous Peoples (1995-2004),
yet so far, it has not been successful.O n l y
a few countries have taken concrete steps
to recognize their rights.
The positive side, however, is that
groups internationally are co-ordinating
their efforts and learning from others’
e x p e r i e n c e. But the time has come to sit
down with bodies like the World Trade
Organization and the World Bank to
frankly discuss the world’s future. ■
I N T E RVIEW BY ETHIRAJA N
A N BA R A S A N
UNESCO CO U R I E R J O U R N A L I S T
A LIFE IN THE HILLS
In 1973, university students in Thailand sta-
ged mass demonstrations calling for demo-
cracy and an end to the country’s military dic-
t a t o r s h i p. In response, authorities closely
monitored all student activities inside the
c o u n t r y. Tuenjai Deetes’ work as a student
volunteer teacher in the hill village of Baan
Pangsa in northern Thailand was no excep-
t i o n . Undeterred by intimidation and sur-
v e i l l a n c e, Deetes pursued her mission with
determination.
In 1976 Deetes found herself in a similar
situation following a left-wing inspired stu-
dent revolt in the country, which was brutally
repressed after the military staged a coup in
October of that year. When authorities came
knocking on her door, she recalls telling them:
‘‘I believe in peace and non-violence and wish
to continue with my work for the hill tribes.’’
Though initially dubious,o f ficials allowed her
to pursue her work and Deetes went on to
win government support for her projects
soon after. On the other hand, she was alwa y s
cautious not to take sides in ethnic conflicts
or to confront directly the drug lords in the
sensitive border region.“We had to operate
with extreme care and tact without offen-
ding anyone.”
Deetes founded the Hill Area Development
Foundation (HADF) in 1986 to assist hill tribes
in dealing with problems ranging from envi-
ronmental management to social develop-
m e n t .To d a y, the HADF works in 27 hill villages
in the watershed area of the Mae Chan and
Mae Salong rivers on the Thai-Burmese border.
Slightly built,the 48-year-old Deetes travels
indefatigably from one hill village to another.
It requires extraordinary courage and convic-
tion for a Bangkok-born-and-raised girl to
give up the comforts of the big city for the
remote hill regions. Over the years, D e e t e s
has won enormous respect and admiration
from her peers, who recently elected her as a
senator after she stood as an independent
candidate in Chiang Rai, the capital of the
mountainous province in northern Thailand
where she works.
Deetes’ dedicated and selfless service has won
her many laurels, including the 1994 Goldman
Environmental Prize, given annually to grass-
roots environmental activists. During the 25th
anniversary of the United Nations Environ-
ment Programme in 1997, she was named as
one of “25 Women Leaders in A c t i o n ” for her
role in protecting the planet.
Despite her achievements, Deetes remains
modest and down to earth. In the coming
years she wants to train more volunteers to
work with the hill tribes and create a network
of organizations in the region. ‘‘I cannot
change the governments of the world on my
o w n . With small groups, we can change the
world and steer it in a positive direction,’’ says
the soft-spoken Deetes.Married with two chil-
d r e n , she now lives in Chiang Rai. ■
chocolates or money. Some foreigners
also come to the hills looking for sex tou-
r i s m .The international community should
take serious steps to ban this.
What is it like to work in Thailand for an
NGO championing the cause of indige-
nous peoples? What contacts do you have
with other NGOs abroad and what are the
issues involved?
Many people are questioning non-
governmental organizations in general.
They are often regarded as being in per-
petual opposition to the government.
Some groups and newspapers in Th a i l a n d
accuse the NGOs of selling the country’s
misery abroad in order to get foreign fun-
d i n g.In a country like Th a i l a n d ,I think the
main role of the NGO should be to offer
a voice to the disadvantaged.By offering
a different viewpoint, we can offer alter-
native perspectives on our society. I am
certain that most NGO workers realize
that they alone cannot achieve the mission.
They need co-operation from other parts
of the society.
I have learned a lot from working
with indigenous groups internationally,
particularly through the Rainforest
An Akha woman shops in Chiang Rai.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Focus:
■ Schools and business: historical echoes
■ U.S. parents claim value for money
■ South Africa’s government clamps
down on e-learning
■ Universities: strategic alliances 
to conquer new markets
■ New Zealand:A cautionary tale
■ Educating for jobs or citizenship?
■ Global learning and local identities
■ Balancing interests: the state’s response
Features include:
■ Shopping malls: a new pastime?
■ Brazil: public opinion shifts
over the Amazon
■ A new mission for schools in East Timor 
■ Soccer: racism’s enduring stronghold
■ Fixed prices for books: a boon for reading?
■ What makes reality TV tick?
■ Maryse Condé and Elizabeth Nunez:
A Caribbean exchange
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
November 2000:
Education:
the last 
frontier for
profit
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 27 languages
22 - 26 November 2000, Paris (Porte de Versailles) France
E v e rything you want to know about EDUCATEC 2000 and EDUC'MAT 2000
as exhibitor, visitor, or auditor to the confere n c e s . . .
Educatec and Educ'mat are
the two exhibitions open
only to professionals at  the
w o r l d ’s largest trade educa -
tional fair, "le Salon de l’édu -
cation". Last year’s event
gatheed over 1,800 exhibi -
tors  and 440,000  visitors
from 62 countries. Among
this year’s many highlights,
the education ministers of
the 15 European Commu -
nity countries will present
their national strategies and
practices concerning new
t e c h n o l o g i e s .
EDUCATEC 2000 and EDUC'MAT 2000 are organised by EDIT EXPO INTERNATIONAL / TARSUS Group  12, rue Vauvenargues  75018 Paris (France) 
Tel. 33 (0)1 42 23 13 56 - Fax 33 (0)1 42 23 13 07 - Email : editexpo@tradefairs.worldnet.fr - http://www.educatec.com
18th Professional 
exhibition of educational and 
vocational training equipment, 
systems and services.
2nd Pre-elementary 
and primary schools 
exhibition+
]]>
</page>
</document>
