<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="121198eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Brazil turns its
back on the 
Amazon trade
The hooligan
within: football’s
racist faces
TV: all eyes
on the reality
game
EDUCATION:THE LAST
FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
November  2000
Canada:$3.95 Cdn,United Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
◗ PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 Shopping heaven
Photos by Marcos Pesaresi, Text by Vicente Verdú
◗ PLANET
10 Brazil turns its back on the Amazon trade
Diana Alves
1 3 Where the riches lie 
Diana Alves
◗ WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Teaching free Timor
Gabriel Dvoskin
◗ ETHICS
38 Garlic, knives and banners:
football’s racist faces
Tim Crabbe
4 0 A tricolour triumph?
Tim Crabbe
◗ SIGNS OF THE TIMES
41 The price of a good read
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
◗ CONNEXIONS
43 All eyes on the reality game
Ivan Briscoe
4 5 Inside the emotion machine
Interview with Peter Lunt
◗ INTERVIEW
46 Maryse Condé: grand dame of Caribbean literature
C O N T E N T S
NOVEMBER 2000
53rd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Octavi Marti
French edition: Sophie Boukhari
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: The Mouveur,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l , Alcino Da
C o s t a , Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted provi-
ding the credit line reads “Reprinted from the UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of
i s s u e, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprin-
ted must bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
r e q u e s t . Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by
an international reply coupon covering postage. The UN E S C O Courier is pro-
duced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de
Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) , Ann A r b o r,
Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d , Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - NOVEMBRE2000
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Paris by UN E S C O.
Printed in Fra n c e. Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and additional
mailing offic e s.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 11-2000-OPI 00-592 A
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UNESCO Courier staff. The boundaries on maps do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the
United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
© Cover by Alain Le Quernec, France
E d u c a t i o n :
the last frontier for pro-
fit
Representing a two trillion dollar budget worldwi-
de, education is one of the last domains to remain
largely in public hands. Riding on a neo-liberal tide,
mounting 
discontent with public schools and the Internet’s
spread, the corporate world 
is putting its stamp on education.
The United States is at the helm of this wave of
privatization, now spreading across 
the globe. But is everyone profiting from this
Fo c u s
Detailed table of contents on page 16
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
S h o p p i n g he
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Menswear in Bloomington,Minnesota (United States).
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
PHOTOS BY MARCO PESARESI,TEXT BY VICENTE VERDÚ
MARCO PESARESI ISAN ITALIAN PHOTOGRAPHER.
VICENTE VERDU IS A SPANISHJOURNALISTANDWRITER , ANDWINNER
OFTHE ANAGRAMA ESSAY PRIZE IN 1996
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 5
ea v e n
The shopping mall acts as an oasis
where the world of holidays 
is in incessant rebirth and regeneration
Like a cosmos where the light never dims, shopping malls play multiple
roles in modern-day culture: that of a Godless paradise,of a timeless space,
of an absolute getaway without landmarks.The shopping mall is an enter-
tainment venue, and its greatest achievement lies in cultivating the fantasy
that one has stopped existing in some way without ever really dying.Wi t h
its background music, controlled climate and round-the-clock operations,
the polished halls of a mall stand as a metaphor for a happy trip to nowhere
in particular—a perfect holiday.
In contrast to the places where people work,the shopping mall acts as an
oasis where the world of holidays is in incessant rebirth and regeneration,as an
enclosed space where time never acquires a restrictive dimension,where sen-
sations obey the calls of seduction, a v a i l a b i l i t y, flattery and reward instead of
duty and penance.Streets in shopping malls are circuits turned towards providing
entertainment or pleasure, just as holidays,at least in their intent.The world’s
largest mall—Canada’s West Edmonton in the western province of A l b e r t a —
covers a space equivalent to 100 football pitches, and according to Je r e m y
R i f k i n , author of The Age of A c c e s s,contains the largest indoor amusement park
in the world, the largest indoor waterpark,a golf course, 800 shops,11 depart-
ment stores,110 restaurants, an ice-skating rink,13 nightclubs and 20 cinemas.
The plans for the planet’s very first mall were drawn up in 1924 by 
J. C. Nichols in Kansas City, and the centre that resulted, with its Mediter-
ranean architecture, tiled fountains and cast-iron balconies, became the pro-
totype for those built after World War II. All shopping malls currently
boast similar fountains, w a t e r f a l l s, tropical plants, ocean blue patios, m a r b l e
They are the ultimate entertainment destinations: walled
kingdoms outside space and time 
where the weary can give free rein to the pleasure principle
and consume in a holiday spirit
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Shopping heaven
sightlines and the latest pop tunes.This host of links between the
holiday and the shopping centre helps alleviate the distress
caused by regimented time.
There are no clocks in shopping centres, and no impa-
tience over wasting valuable time. In contrast to nature’s bound-
less space, the mall offers an illuminated cavern that has neither
beginning nor end, but is shaped like a Moebius strip.Within it,
time is shattered,and what is left in place is space made fun.
The average American,according to sociologist William
Kowinski,author of the The Malling of America, visits a shop-
ping mall every ten days, and spends over an hour and a quarter
there on each occasion; the most frequently given reason for this
pilgrimage is a desire for “ e n t e r t a i n m e n t .” Indeed the shop-
ping malls of the future have been billed as entertainment
centres in which people will be able to shed the burden of their
own selves.M i n n e s o t a ’s Mall of A m e r i c a ,w h i c h
until just recently was the largest in the world, i s
visited by over 45 million people each year,
among them package tourists from Australia.
The place has become a kind of sacred site of the
sort discussed by the late Romanian philoso-
pher Mircea Eliade. It has the same power of
attraction as Mecca or the Vatican, where one
has to go at least once in a lifetime.
Working is the mundane side of life, b u t
being a consumer is potentially its most poetic or
symbolic pay-off. While the average worker is
asked to be realistic and pragmatic, c o n s u m p-
tion can stimulate every possible dream, e v e n
the dream of salvation in the form of liberation
from the constraints of space and time.
Nothing seems to threaten this walled
kingdom protected by security guards and wat-
ched over by increasing numbers of closed cir-
cuit cameras. Sociologist Peter Hemingway has
argued that the mission of mall architects and
designers consists in providing a sugared dream,
where one can buy,play and experience without
ever having to go outside—where one can
change experience like one switches television
c h a n n e l s,using the credit card as the all-powerful
Open Sesame.
L o u d s p e a k e r s,closed circuit cameras,v i d e o
recorders and monitors are integral parts of a
system that is aimed at the production of a totally
autonomous universe. Inside the mall’s walls, i t
can be spring even if snow is falling on the streets
o u t s i d e,or autumn though it is baking hot under
the summer sun.Weather has no real meaning,
Working is the mundane side of life, 
but being a consumer is potentially its
most poetic or symbolic pay-off
Gadgets.Bloomington,Minnesota.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 7
and is only a pretext for a change in fashion. Different segments
of the mall can resemble Th a i l a n d , the Ty r o l , China or Canada,
since its inner space has been transformed into a dolled-up uni-
v e r s e, just like paradise. In Scottsdale,A r i z o n a , the Borgata repro-
duces the Tuscan village of San Gimignano in the middle of the
d e s e r t ,while Olde Mistic Village in Connecticut is a carbon copy
of the main street in a New England town from around the start
of the 17th century. The vogue for copying, a key trait of global
s o c i e t y,has forged an alliance with the shopping mall in its bid to
make places and dates vanish. In the inaugural ceremony for
West Edmonton,one of the centre’s creators,Nader Ghermezion,
declared that people would no longer have to “go to New Yo r k ,
P a r i s, Disneyland or Hawaii.We can offer you all that here!”
Assembled under one roof, built to copy the best of all
w o r l d s, with a selection of the best the globe can offer.Wh e r e a s
any given shop in a city has had to choose its urban location in
accordance with historical and geographical dictates, the shop-
ping mall is free from any such demographic tradition—indeed
it is free from history entirely.The main criterion for a mall’s loca-
tion is simple:how fast people can get there. Father and son. Bloomington, Minnesota.
Big or small? A shopper ponders in the Gum, Moscow (Russia).
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Shopping heaven
8 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
The mall is constantly changing its 
appearance, anchoring itself to an evolving 
present in a magical process
Sweet and sour. Taipei (Taiwan).
A quiet moment in the Forum des Halles, Paris (France).
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 9
The mall is constantly changing its appearance, a n c h o r i n g
itself to an evolving present in a magical process that eludes all
threat of death. Freed from the pull of gravity, the mall is now
s o c i e t y ’s most revered safety valve, with such importance as a
social and political symbol that terrorists intent on disrupting
normal life choose it as a prime target. By planting a bomb in
a mall, they attack the contemporary vision of dreamland. In this
“ s p a c e s h i p,” the city’s most benevolent and leisurely impulses
are now distilled. The world of work, illness and repression
has been extracted; all that remains is soft-flowing leisure and
purchasing power.
Independent, beyond the pull of gravity, open all hours,
without prisons, sweet-smelling, tropical and radiant,the shop-
ping mall is a parody of utopia. Mornings are the same as after-
n o o n s,Sundays as Mondays,China as A r g e n t i n a , Rome as New
York; potential purchases are in abundance, changing only to
match the spiral of constant progress and advertising them-
selves as the best items going. Faced with this spectacle, t h e
visitor is invited to partake of the profusion as if he or she were
on holiday and about to dive into the sea.Buying becomes like
dipping in the ocean—disappearing, forgetting oneself and eve-
rything else. All becomes one in the newest passion of the day.
■
All the fun of the fair. The Gum,Moscow.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
B
◗ P L A N E T
BY DIANA ALVES
BRAZILIAN JOURNALIST SPECIALIZING
INTHE ENVIRONMENT
B razil turns its back on
the Amazon tra d e
For the first time, the Brazilian public has joined the ecological campaign 
to save the rainforest
r a z i l ’s ecologists and rural landowners
will remember 2000 as the year of
c o n f r o n t a t i o n . Both wanted to decide the
future of the world’s biggest biological
r e s e r v e.A mass petition, protest demons-
trations and a torrent of 20,000 e-mail
messages supported the country’s non-
governmental organizations (NGOs) 
and blocked an amendment to the
national forestry regulations that would
have increased by a
quarter the number
of trees that could 
be legally felled in 
the Amazon region,
which lost an esti-
mated 532,000 sq km
of forest between
1978 and 1997.
At the height of
the confrontation last
M a y,a public opinion
poll showed that 88
percent of the elec-
torate would vote
against parliamen-
tary candidates w h o
backed the amend-
m e n t . N i n e t y - t h r e e
percent of those 
questioned said pro-
tecting the environ-
ment did not hinder
the country’s deve-
l o p m e n t ,while 90 per-
cent believed that cut-
ting down more trees would not help
reduce hunger.Even more important was
the finding that in a country where few
people read newspapers, 63 percent said
they had closely followed the debate,
mostly through radio and television reports.
The financial press was firmly against
the amendment too.“ There is not a single
argument that can justify this disastrous
m e a s u r e,” said the influential newspaper
Gazeta Mercantil. “Brazil has plenty of
fertile land.There are more than 100 mil-
lion hectares of unused land alone in the
s e r t ã o,” the scrubland that covers a
quarter of the country.Amazonia has lost
60 percent of its original vegetation
through the spread of soybean farming
and especially pasture land for cattle.
Another major Brazilian newspaper,
O Estado de São Paulo, summed up the
worries about the future with a headline
that asked:“ What kind of air are we going
to breathe?” The popularity of the eco-
logists’ campaign could be seen through
the fact that characters in the cartoon
strip M ó n i c a, which appears in dozens of
n e w s p a p e r s, were dressed in mourning
clothes as a sign of protest.
“ For the first time
Brazilian society is
r e a c t i n g, o r g a n i z i n g
itself and getting
results through a
major campaign that
started inside the
c o u n t r y,”says Eduardo
M a r t i n s,until last year
head of the federal
environment agency,
I BA M A . “In A m a-
z o n i a , the proposed
amendment was de-
nounced by sectors
that have never stirred
b e f o r e, such as the
middle class and the
local media,” d e c l a r e s
biologist A d a l b e r t o
Ve r í s s i m o,a researcher
with the Institute of
People and the Envi-
ronment in A m a z o n i a ,
I M A Z O N, one of the
r e g i o n ’s most respected
N G O s.“Everyone understood that a public
resource was about to be destroyed without
generating any kind of development.”
Brazilian public opinion,which is now
in tune with what many international
bodies and organizations have been advo-
cating for years,has switched as a result of
the economic disaster of unregulated log-
g i n g. Most of the destroyed forest areas
have become pasture land or soybean,
p a l m ,coffee and black pepper plantations.
These foreign crops,which are ill-suited to
poor soil and heavy rains,have had a hard
time growing over two-thirds of the defo-
rested area.Half the 20 million hectares of
pasture are also in a miserable state.
Low yields made farmers look for new
l a n d , causing deforestation to increase
year after year—always in vain,h o w e v e r,
because 78 percent of the soil was too
acidic and had little natural fertility.A l o n g
with this vicious circle, there were trans-
port problems. It takes several days by
river to get from the ranches deep in the
jungle to a port from where crops can be
sent out to domestic and foreign markets.
So although 14 percent of A m a z o-
n i a ’s virgin forest has been destroyed, it is
still a poor area and its 20 million inha-
bitants—three-quarters of whom live in
towns—only produce seven percent of
the country’s GDP. Per capita income
there is below the national average,w h i l e
the region’s main export, Brazil nuts, is
only worth about $3 million, far behind
the $230 million earned from the urban
production of syrups for soft drinks.
The waste of sawmills and 
the defiance of loggers
A recent survey carried out by
IMAZON for the World Bank showed
why farming in the region is so diffic u l t .I t
noted that 18 percent of the Brazilian part
of the Amazon was given over to cattle-rai-
s i n g. That area, in the far south of the
A m a z o n , is the most deforested part and
has a low annual rainfall of 1,800 mm.To
the north is a mixed zone that has a little
more rain and where farming is still fea-
s i b l e, despite a host of insects and plant
d i s e a s e s. In the remaining 45 percent of
Brazilian A m a z o n i a , where heavy rain
falls each day, the only viable large-scale
economic activity is forestry. “Here and
in the mixed zone, logging is as profit a b l e
as agriculture,”says Ve r í s s i m o,one of the
experts involved in the survey.“ That shows
forestry is the best thing for A m a z o n i a .”
But the timber industry has not
managed to make use of this natural
resource without destroying it. N e a r l y
three years ago a European Commission
report blamed the industry for 72 per-
cent of deforestation,and said its activities
10 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
Brazilian public 
opinion, which 
is now in tune with 
what many 
international bodies 
and organizations 
have been 
advocating for
years,
has switched as 
a result of the 
economic disaster 
of unregulated 
logging
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 11
A bird’s-eye view of deforestation in Amazonia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
were much more harmful to the forests
than felling by farmers or ranchers. Th e
sawmills also waste an enormous amount
of timber, sometimes as much as two-
thirds of the trees felled.Even worse,m o s t
timber firms do not obey the law. “ Th e
strategic affairs ministry says about 80
percent of the timber is illegally chopped
down in the region and forest manage-
ment schemes are mostly ignored,” says a
survey put together by Greenpeace.
What are these schemes? Fi r s t , there is
the battle to keep current forestry regula-
tions on the books and strictly enforce
t h e m . During the 1960s, each landowner
was required to preserve 50 percent of the
forests on his land.As deforestation sped
u p,parliament decreed in 1996 that 80 per-
cent must be preserved. President Fe r-
nando Henrique Cardoso sided with the
e c o l o g i s t s,saying that “forestry regulations
are needed to ensure the survival of A m a-
z o n i a ,which belongs to Brazilians but also
to humanity as a whole.”
A haven for biodiversity is the
last farming frontier
Brazil contains the planet’s richest
biodiversity and the widest range of plant
s p e c i e s. A sixth of all the world’s birds
live there, an eighth of all amphibians,
one in every 11 mammals and a 15th of
the world’s reptiles. Five thousand diffe-
rent kinds of trees grow in the Amazon,
against North America’s 650.
Another scheme currently on the
books is the Pilot Programme to Pre-
serve Tropical Forests, funded by the G7
countries, the European Union and the
Brazilian government,which have toge-
ther contributed $280 million to support
sustainable use of the forests. The pro-
gramme is the biggest multilateral invest-
ment in the environment ever made in a
single country.
As well as these schemes, there is the
Amazon Region Protected Areas Pro-
g r a m m e, backed by Brazil, the Wo r l d
Bank and other international bodies, s u c h
as the World Wildlife Fund and the Wo r l d
Bank Forest Alliance Programme.It aims
to convert 10 percent of Amazonia into
protected areas.Twelve million hectares
are already protected,and the goal is to
increase that to 37 million hectares—an
area the size of Germany.
All these conservation measures are
opposed in varying degrees by A m a z o-
nian landowners, who see the region’s 5.1
million sq kms as the last agricultural fron-
t i e r,with unlimited possibilities for growth.
They say society owes them something for
having stopped felling on part of their lands
to help safeguard the environment, a n d
are demanding monetary compensation.
An all-party parlia-
mentary commission,
headed by the pro-
government centre-right
deputy Mosir Miche-
letto, tabled a draft law
at the end of 1999 to
allow a very flexible
interpretation of the
forestry regulations.
M i c h e l e t t o ’s bill stipu-
lated that half of Ama-
z o n i a ’s ranchland should
remain uncleared, b u t
that Amazonian state
governments would be
able to grant 
special logging conces-
sions on a case by  case
b a s i s.Estates of less than
25 hectares, meanwhile,
would be exempted
from all conservation
regulations.
During a
demonstration in favour of the new pro-
posal last February, 600 members of the
National Agricultural Federation made a
nationalistic protest against what they
called “the harmful interference of
national and foreign ecological organi-
zations in drafting punitive laws which
hinder national development.”
Environment Minister José Sarney
Fi l h o, the National Environment Council
(CONAMA) and the NGOs responded
by pointing out the need to continue pre-
serving 80 percent of the A m a z o n i a n
f o r e s t . For six months, they organized
public debates all over Brazil.
Battles among the region’s
shareholders
The ecologists overwhelmingly sup-
port the government’s stand.Their main
criticism is that the scrubland areas 
of the Amazon must also be safeguarded,
since—contrary to most people’s
beliefs—jungle is not the only native
vegetation in the A m a z o n . E n v i r o n-
mental NGOs say it is not enough to
leave only 35 percent of the ranchland in
this ecosystem untouched, as CONA M A
p r o p o s e s, let alone descend to the 20 per-
cent threshold in the Micheletto pro-
posal.Either way, it would seem hard to
ignore Brazilian public opinion, w h i c h
now broadly agrees with arguments that
until recently were dismissed as unpa-
triotic and slavish to foreign interests. ■
12 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
The nine states making up the Amazon, which spans 5.5 million km2.
Reducing the rainforest to ashes to make way for cattle ranchers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
P L A N E T ◗
BY DIANA ALVES
BRAZILIAN JOURNALIST SPECIALIZING
INTHE ENVIRONMENT
WHERE THE RICHES LIE
The preservation of forest areas can only be funded through regulated and sustainable 
use of the rest of the Amazonian jungle
At stake are not just the millions of
square kilometres of jungle or the
14,000 million cubic metres of timber gro-
wing in the region, or even the fact that it
is a biological reserve that contains a third
of the world’s plant and animal species.
Behind the dispute that has set off so
many debates in parliament over much of
the past year are advocates of two very dif-
ferent models of development.
Rural landowners naturally want to
continue chopping down trees to clear
land for cattle or agriculture. E n v i r o n-
mental organizations want to protect spe-
c i fic areas of tropical forest as agents of cli-
mate regulation, a source of future
m e d i c i n e s, a place for scientific research
and home to many indigenous tribes,w h i l e
leaving the logging industry to use the
rest of the jungle in a sustainable fashion.
The economic feasibility of the lan-
downers’ stance has already been chal-
lenged by the facts, while the ecologists’
plans are only feasible if accompanied
by a myriad of other measures. Ecotou-
rism is one possible source of revenue, a s
is use of the jungle’s pharmaceutical or
biotechnological re-
sources.
But the region’s main
income would still come
from logging. There has
been significant progress
in this activity, such as the
planting of a million hec-
tares of trees for timber
in the past seven years.
A score of A m a z o n i a n
sawmills have pledged to
rotate their use of forest
areas and allow the
forests to regenerate.
One such company, Mil
M a d e i r e i r a s, w a s
awarded a quality certifi-
cate by the Forest Ste-
wardship Council (FSC),
the chief monitor of sus-
tainable forestry deve-
l o p m e n t , after dividing
55,000 hectares into 30
lots with a rotation
system to ensure that each lot was only
touched every 30 years.The firm also has
a 25,000 hectare reserve which it pre-
serves permanently.Another 17 compa-
nies are willing to follow the example of
Mil Madeireiras and hope to get certifi-
cates from the FSC.Among them is Cikel,
the region’s biggest sawmill.
But “ c e r t i fie d ”companies such as these
are still rare among hundreds of semi-legal
c o m p e t i t o r s. Most of the 1,600 sawmills 
in the Brazilian Amazonia are small or
medium-sized outfits that account for 70
percent of total production. “Illegal 
timber will always be cheaper,”says A d a l-
berto Ve r í s s i m o,a biologist with the Insti-
tute of People and the Environment in
A m a z o n i a . He is
counting on two
government measures
to speed up regulation
of logging.
The first is the
National Forestry Pro-
gramme being drawn
up by the Environ-
ment Ministry to
encourage new tree
plantations and pro-
tect existing ones.Th e
other is to make com-
panies bid for logging
p e r m i t s. Ve r í s s i m o
says the government
will have more
control over felling if
it is done on publicly
owned land.
Apart from logging, the possibility of
planting new areas that will act as carbon
sinks (in an effort to limit climate change
in accordance with the Kyoto Protocol),
has sparked the interest of several of the
r e g i o n ’s landowners. A pilot project is
under way on the island of Bananal, in the
far south of the region, sponsored by a
foundation linked to the U.S. electricity
multinational American Electric System.
This aims to preserve 200,000 hectares, a s
well as plant 240,000 saplings and recover
800 hectares each year.
Biotechnology is the region’s third big
investment opportunity.In the coming year,
a centre for research into the A m a z o n
r e g i o n ’s resources will open in Manaus.Th i s
is urgently needed because foreign labora-
tories are already developing thousands of
drugs based on the traditional knowledge of
Amazonian tribes.One of the best examples
is a cure for high blood pressure,C a p o t e n ,
made by scientists (at the pharmaceutical
company Bristol-Meyers Squibb) from the
venom of the j a r a r a c á s n a k e.
A couple of years ago the government
asked a group of scientists to focus their
work on A m a z o n i a . One of the group’s
main conclusions was that the region
could support all kinds of activity, f r o m
agriculture and logging to extracting
natural resources. Even the much-criti-
cized pasture lands were said to be tole-
r a b l e. According to Roberto K i s h i n a m i ,
head of Greenpeace-Brazil, “the best
thing would be to designate commercial
and ecological areas
and see which ones
should be protected
and at what cost.”
Two of Brazil’s A m a-
zonian states, R o n-
donia and To c a n t i n s,
are moving in exactly
this direction.
Early next year,
when the Brazilian
parliament takes up
the amendments to
the forestry regula-
tions again, t h e
country might clearly
identify what kind of
activities should be
allowed in A m a z o n i a .
The parliamentary
debates will coincide
with publication of the annual defores-
tation figures by the National Institute
for Space Research,INPE—figures that
will tell whether ecologists or rural lan-
downers have won the war of percen-
tages.
But another problem will remain:h o w
to make the transition from a world of
symbolic victories and defeats, of laws
which are not obeyed,to one where the
government manages to convert symbols
into reality. ■
S o u r c e s : Ministry of Development,Tr a d e
and Industry;National Institute of Ama-
zonian Research and the Bank of Ama-
zonia;Greenpeace.
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 13
B razil turns its back on the Amazon tra d e
“The best thing 
would be 
to designate 
commercial 
and ecological 
areas and see 
which ones 
should be 
protected and 
at what cost.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A
◗ W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G
GABRIEL DVOSKIN
ARGENTINE JOURNALIST
Teaching free Ti m o r
Money may be tight, but East Timor’s school year began recently with plenty of enthusiasm. One of the
people in charge discusses what lies in store
14 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
school year without teachers, schools or
universities—just pupils. This is the chal-
lenge facing Armeido Maya, the former
rector of the University of Timor who is
now running the country’s higher educa-
tion system. “If we could manage while
occupied by Indonesia, just think what we
can do now that we’re free,” he declares.
M a y a , 4 2 , was born in East Ti m o r
under Portuguese rule. In 1975,only two
weeks after gaining independence from
Po r t u g a l , the country was occupied by
Indonesia.“I had to give up my plans to
enter the Jesuit school in Dili [the
c a p i t a l ] ,”he says.“I was 18 and very keen
to learn, but for two and a half years I
chose to live in the jungle and the bush
with my mother and two brothers as a
member of the underground resistance.”
When he left the Fr e t i l í n g u e r r i l l a s
and came back to Dili,he was tortured by
the occupation forces. After agonizing
about what to do with his life,he gave up
the idea of becoming a priest though not
his faith in East Ti m o r ’s independence.
To d a y, the problems are different.
“ N i n e t y - five percent of school buildings
were destroyed by the Indonesians a little
over a year ago after the referendum that
c o n firmed our wish for independence,”
he says. Rebuilding a poor country is
t o u g h .“ The help of the Catholic church
has been very important,”says Maya,w h o
spent five years at the Catholic University
in Java reading history and geography.
The East Timorese are 90 percent Catholic,
and identify closely with a church that was
on their side during the bloody 24-year
Indonesian occupation, in which 300,000
people were killed. As a result, the 1996
Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to A r c h-
bishop Carlos Ximenes Belo and the poli-
tical leader José Ramos Horta.
Starting from scratch:
from language to history
“ The education system needs fir s t
a i d ,” says Maya.“ To begin with, we want
to teach computing,human rights,E n g l i s h
and Po r t u g u e s e.This is what we need for
training and informal education.” Th e
language problem in East Timor is espe-
cially serious since almost everyone
speaks the Bahasa of the Indonesian inva-
d e r s, while the local Tetun language has a
surprising number of dialects.“Bahasa is
going to be replaced by Tetun and Por-
tuguese in primary and secondary schools,
and by Portuguese and English in higher
education,” he says.
Language classes, however, are jeo-
pardized by some very basic flaws. “We
could only begin the school year when
classrooms had roofs and enough books
and other materials,”says Maya,who also
points to a lack of good teachers.“Half of
East Timorese children study in a roofless school destroyed by anti-independence militia in Dili.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
those who say they can teach primary
and secondary courses would fail profes-
sional tests.”
Things are not much better in the uni-
v e r s i t y.“ We have 5,000 people wanting to
take courses in agronomy, e d u c a t i o n ,e c o-
nomics or political science, which are our
four faculties, but we only have 1,000
places because 3,000 are already reserved
for those whose studies were interrupted
last year. Furthermore, we only have 90
teachers for the four faculties.”
The curriculum has also caused a
number of headaches.“ We have to teach
children the history of our country,but we
need to do it with a book that is impartial
and based on democratic values,” h e
observes.“We’re working on a textbook
with help from foreign teachers, w h i c h
will have to be ready
within a year.” Th e n
it will be read under
tin roofs, in class-
rooms with dirt flo o r s,
in buildings nobody
ever thought would
become places of
l e a r n i n g. The Je s u i t
Jacob Filomeno, who
runs the refugee
o f f i c e, simply notes
that “every day we
have 2,000 children
gathered outside wanting to take classes.”
UNICEF sent $490,000 worth of
school supplies to East Timor, mainly in
the form of $300 kits designed by
UNESCO “that were a success in Somalia
and Rwanda” according to Pilar A g u i l a r,
the UNICEF representative in East
Timor.“Each kit contains enough mate-
rials for 80 pupils and a teacher in a class
that can be held outdoors.”
Coping with a desperate situation does
not faze Maya, whose only complaint is
that he does not have time to play chess
and to read. Outside his offic e, the alleys
and streets are full of pigs, chickens and
oxen while helicopters skim through the
sky to anxious glances from people below.
“Between 1993 and 1997,after retur-
ning from further studies in sociology
and economics in New Zealand,I was in
charge of the University of Dili again
and the situation was worse,” r e c a l l s
M a y a .“I don’t mean in terms of poverty,
but in terms of freedom. The tyres of my
car were slashed several times,I got death
threats by phone. I had to go into exile in
the United States, to Minnesota.There I
w a s,a man from the tropics,used to tem-
peratures of more than 30° C, passing the
time in some place where I remember
being frightened by snow!”Maya had to
go into exile several times due to political
fluctuations in East Timor, but his firm
intention was always to return.
But going home after the fall of
former Indonesian dictator Suharto was
no easy matter.“After the independence
referendum on August 30th of last year,
we had to hide in the mountains again,”
he says.“I didn’t even have time to enjoy
my honeymoon. But now I’m back,and
this time for good.” Maya hopes many
other students and ex-students share his
desire to return.“Most who went to New
Zealand and Australia to study will come
back. I’m sure of that. We need them to
build the country. Their skills are vital
for our people and the thousands of chil-
dren who have to go to school.”
For the moment,
life is still confused
and unstable.Wi t n e s s
the jumbled state of
East Ti m o r ’s small
s o c i e t y : in market-
p l a c e s, several lan-
guages are mirrored
by three currencies—
the U.S. dollar, which
has been adopted 
as the official cur-
r e n cy, the Indonesian
rupiah and the Au s-
tralian dollar, both local currencies  from
neighbouring states.“Over the next year,
w e ’ll have elections and a local Ti m o r e s e
government will take over from the coun-
t r y ’s Brazilian administrator, Sergio Vi e i r a
de Mello,” says Maya.
The present administration is a coali-
tion that includes members of the
National Council of Timorese Resistance
( C N RT ) , such as Maya, who also works in
the education ministry,and officials from
the United Nations Transitional A d m i-
nistration in East Timor (UNTA E T ) .
“We’re working against the clock,” says
M a y a .“As well as the help from UNICEF,
w e ’ve also had $13 million from the Wo r l d
Bank that we’ve used for the most urgent
repair work and to provide some trai-
ning for teachers and pay their wages.”
“Wages,” it should be said, is some-
thing of a euphemism. Maya is ready to
tackle all the problems that come his way,
including hunger. He prefers not to talk
about it, but UNICEF is also taking care
of the most urgent food needs of pupils
and teachers, some of whom are going
to school on empty stomachs and are so
tired that they cannot concentrate for
long. “But at least we’re free now,” says
Maya with a smile. ■
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 15
Key dates
1520:
Portuguese invasion of East Ti m o r.
April 25, 1974:
Triumph of Po r t u g a l ’s Revolution 
of the Carnations opens the way to decoloni-
z a t i o n .
1975:
Civil war concludes with the 
d e c l a ration of independence 
by Fretilin (the Revolutionary Front 
for the Independence of East Ti m o r ) .
July 17, 1976:
Indonesian President Suharto orders the
annexation of East Ti m o r, which becomes an
Indonesian province. Nicolau Lobato leads
resistance to 
the occupying forces.
December 1978:
Lobato dies in combat.
Xanana Gusmao succeeds him.
November 12, 1991:
Indonesian troops kill 271 people 
in the Santa Cruz cemetery, D i l i ,
during the funeral of an independence acti-
v i s t . The West condemns 
the massacre.
November 20, 1992:
Gusmao is arrested in Dili.
His initial sentence of life 
imprisonment is commuted 
to 20 years.
October 1996:
Dili Archbishop Carlos Ximenes Belo and José
Ramos Horta, international spokesman for
the resistance, are awarded the Nobel Pe a c e
P r i z e. The campaign for independence res-
t a r t s.
May 1998:
Suharto resigns, and is succeeded 
by Yusuf Habibie. The East Timorese guerrillas
intensify their activities, and are met with a
brutal crackdown by Indonesian troops.
January 27, 1999:
Indonesia announces an about-face 
in its policy towards East Ti m o r.
The province will be offered autonomy; i f
r e j e c t e d , the path to full independence will be
o p e n .
August 30, 1999:
The East Timorese vote in 
the landmark referendum organized by the
U N, with 78.5 percent rejecting 
plans for provincial autonomy.
The army and pro-Indonesian militias reacted
by attacking civilians and destroying local
i n f ra s t r u c t u r e.
“We have to teach 
children the history 
of our country,
but we need to do it 
with a book that 
is impartial”
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
C o n t e n t s
1 . C o rp o rate ambitions
1 8 Education Inc. ?
Cynthia Guttman
1 9 Echoes of corporate influ e n c e
Dorothy Shipps
2 . Catering to demand
2 3 O b j e t i v o :b rand-name schooling 
Luciana Zenti
2 4 Private education: the poor’s 
best chance?
James To o l e y
2 6 South A f r i c a : the race for 
portable qualific a t i o n s
Karen MacGregor
2 8 When parents want out
Pedro A .N o g u e ra
3 0 E d i s o n ’s third way
Mark Wa l s h
3 1 Wiring up the ivory towers
Robin Mason
3 . Notes of caution
33 New Zealand: the price of the 
m a r ket model
E d ward B. F i s ke and Helen F. L a d d
3 5 O f f s h o re thre a t s
Interview with Gajaraj Dhanara j a n
3 6 Money over merit
Interview with Samik Lahiri
3 7 Beyond economics
Yin Cheong Cheng
E D UC
the last fro
wo trillion dollars or one-twentieth of global gross domestic pro-
d u c t : this is what the world spends on education according to the
most measured assessments. The private sector, which accounts
for roughly a fifth of the amount, is determined to capture a
larger share of this giant market (p.18). Riding on a neo-liberal
wa v e, vaunting greater effic i e n c y, i n n o vation and knowledge of the
job marke t , the corporate world is gaining unprecedented influ e n c e
in running education and shaping its goals  (pp. 19-22). In the
United States, there is a groundswell of support for privatization
and companies are starting to run public schools (pp.28-30). In Brazil,the Objetivo chain
a t t racts close to 500,000 students, mostly from privileged backgrounds, while in India,p r i-
vate schools are winning marks for catering to the poor (pp. 2 3 - 2 6 ) . Higher education is at
the vanguard of the commercial drive, with online learning spurring multiple alliances to attra c t
students able to pay for a prestigious offshore degree (pp.2 6 - 2 7 ,3 1 - 3 2 ) . But there are already
lessons to be learnt from excessive
trust in market principles. The less
a d vantaged are seldom the winners,
as New Zealand’s bold experiment
goes to show (pp. 33-34),quality is
often dangerously compromised
while national identities  run the risk
of erosion (pp. 3 5 - 3 6 ) . To d a y ’s
supreme economic focus needs to
be urgently balanced by a more
holistic approach, and in this, t h e
s t a t e ’s role is pivotal (pp. 17 and
37).
Dossier concept and coordination by
Cynthia Guttman, UN E S C O C o u r i e r
journalist
F O C U S
T
16 The Unesco Courier - November 2000
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The process of globalization is moving
ahead so fast that it has reached hereto-
fore public sector areas, such as education.
Tr u e, the relationship between schools
and the private sector goes back a long
way. Learning institutions have adapted
some of the private sector’s operating
m e t h o d s, and the public service has dele-
gated teaching missions to private com-
p a n i e s, but a further step has been taken.
The explosion of new technologies,w h i c h
speeds up the production and spread of
“educational goods” and the globalization
of markets, spurs on their commerciali-
zation worldwide and eventually, i r r e s i s-
tibly attracts entrepreneurs, always on
the lookout for new markets.Today edu-
cation is a sector weighing two trillion
dollars and companies are continually
expanding their choice of “ e d u c a t i o n a l
m e r c h a n d i s e.”At the same time, the real
or supposed shortcomings of public edu-
cation are turning parents and students
away from it,and fuelling their growing
demand for quality services, which they
are ready to seek elsewhere.
Everyone who believes that educa-
tion is a basic right thinks that commer-
cialization carries acute risks.They argue
that education must not only train wor-
k e r s, but also citizens and responsible
i n d i v i d u a l s. Therefore they question not
only the effects liberalization will have,
which would lead to discrimination against
the most disadvantaged countries, g r o u p s
and individuals,but also the impact a com-
mercial approach will have on the spread
of “common values” or respect for the
indispensable diversity of learning content
and methods,which take into account the
l a n g u a g e, culture and teaching traditions
of the people for whom they are intended.
Proponents of liberalization criticize
the public school system’s ability to offer
equal access to education for all. Th e y
stress that it’s time to increase and  diver-
sify offer in order to meet demand that the
traditional systems can no longer meet, a l l
the less so because of budget cuts. Th e y
emphasize the necessity to introduce ideas
of productivity and responsibility, the lack
of which, they argue, is the public sector’s
main shortcoming.
It is the opinion of UN E S C O,and of its
member states, that neither a wholly
public nor an entirely commercial edu-
cation system can overcome the educa-
tion crisis, which is tangible. The organi-
zation is convinced that public and private
education sectors each have something
valuable to contribute, and that by com-
bining their efforts and forging partner-
s h i p s, they can boost the educational sys-
t e m ’s overall effectiveness—under one
c o n d i t i o n :primary responsibility for tea-
ching must remain in the hands of public
a u t h o r i t i e s, because they alone are the
guardians of the common interest.A b o v e
all, education must be a means to train
responsible citizens. It goes without saying
that the deregulation of educational ins-
titutions cannot be accompanied by the
decline of the basic rules which underpin
the educational mission, and by a lack of
serious monitoring to ensure that those
rules are observed.
This is just as valid on a worldwide
s c a l e.The commercialization of education
requires regional or international co-ope-
r a t i o n ,especially to ensure that the acqui-
sition of universal values remains the pri-
mary objective of any educational system.
The World Trade Organization has started
taking an interest in this issue. But we
would be  straying from our mission by
envisaging the impact of globalization only
from a business perspective, and there-
fore ignoring its effects on—and potential
for—human freedom and self-fulfil l m e n t
through education, science and culture. ■
G UARDING 
THE COMMON INTEREST
JACQUES HALLAK
UNESCO ASSISTANT DIRECTOR-GENERAL FOR EDUCATION
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 17
O P I N I O N
AT I O N :
ontier for pro fit
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
CYNTHIA GUTTMAN
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
E d u c a t i o n I n c . ?
Buoyed by mounting criticism of public education,
the business world is investing in this new field with 
a managerial mindset and enterprising spirit
1 . C O R P O R ATE A M B I T I O N S
As the winds of liberalization blow
onwards, a new vocabulary is running
through education  plucked straight
from the corporate universe.P r i n c i p a l s
step into the shoes of managers, p a r e n t s
become choosey customers while schools compete
and innovate, striving to offer an efficient,quality
service, which at the end of the day yields a  profit
and turns out graduates fit for the job market.
Tacitly supported by governments,the movement
is gaining legitimacy worldwide, fuelled by the grass-
roots and corporate interests,both of which have taken
aim at public education’s tarnished report card.
In the mid-1990s, the European Round
Table of Industrialists,which gathers
prominent CEOs, pointed its
finger at “an ever- w i d e n i n g
gap between the education
that people need for
t o d a y ’s complex world
and the education
they receive.” Th e
Merrill Lynch bro-
kerage fir m
laments that
“ t w e l f t h - g r a d e r s
in the U. S. in the
most recent inter-
national compari-
sons finished dead
last and next to last
in math and science
r e s p e c t i v e l y.”P a r t i c i-
pants at the Wo r l d
Education Forum in
Dakar in April 2000
deemed it “unacceptable that
more than 113 million children
have no access to primary education
… and that the quality of learning and
the acquisition of human values and skills fall
far short of the … needs of societies.”
As Motoyo Kamiya from the OECD’s Centre
for Education Research and Innovation notes, e d u-
c a t i o n ,which typically represents 25 to 30 percent of
public spending,“is becoming more politicized and
controversial both at the national level and locally,
because of decentralization.”Accounting for roughly
20 percent of total education spending, the private
sector has always provided services, textbooks or
schooling via missions, NGOs or other channels.
But now, following the dismantling of state mono-
p o l i e s,the whole public sector is deemed ripe for libe-
r a l i z a t i o n .For advocates of  this process, h e a l t h c a r e,
along with education—a market worth two trillion
dollars—are the last bastions to be overrun.
Critics attack public education’s ineffic i e n cy and
b u r e a u c r a t i c, often overly-centralized, outmoded 
s t r u c t u r e s. Pointing to the principles that have made
many a business prosper, they argue that schools need
market incentives and competitive pressures to
improve and innovate, and that these can be created
through various forms of  privatization.As the Euro-
pean Round Table of Industrialists puts it,“the whole
situation could be turned around if school education
underwent the same transformation as the workplace.”
Struck by funding cuts,higher education is at the
vanguard of more commercial reforms,from weaving
closer ties with industry to tapping the online learning
m a r k e t .But despite the latter’s bullish forecasts, t h e
burgeoning of the private sector cannot be pinned to
technology alone. As Kamiya notes, a broad public
sector reform movement is underway, in which
market-oriented approaches are the backdrop. I n
the U. K .and the U. S. , the publication of league tables,
test scores and rankings,accompanied by hefty media
p u b l i c i t y, is “putting schools under pressure to attract
students and hence funding.” In many countries,
rules are being loosened up over the right to set up
s c h o o l s, while the running of public schools is being
entrusted to private outfit s.
Answering the pressure from below
Taking this process one step further, schools are
becoming business enterprises in their own right. I n
western A f r i c a , retired teachers are opening their
o w n , while elsewhere in the developing world full-
fledged private school chains are attracting growing
n u m b e r s. Under pressure to cut spending, g o v e r n-
ments are loosening regulations and providing incen-
tives to the private sector. In Côte d’Ivoire, 60 per-
cent of secondary schools are now in private hands.
The trend seems set to stay.“ Wh a t ’s really pushing
the for- p r o fit sector is parental demand for better
and different education,”says the World Bank’s Harry
P a t r i n o s.“ N o w,in relatively poor countries,people are
demanding English, t e c h n o l o g y.They know it’s out
there and that some countries are benefiting greatly
from it. They see that the private sector is able to
gear its product to those demands.” ■
After bread,
education 
is the primary
need of the
people.
Georges Jacques Danton,
French 
revolutionary leader (1759-94)
S
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 19
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
DOROTHY SHIPPS
ASSISTANTPROFESSOR OF EDUCATION AT TEACHERS COLLEGE, COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY (U.S.). SHE IS CO-EDITOR, WITH LARRY CUBAN, OF Reconstructing the
Common Good in Education (STANFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS, 2000)
Echoes of corporate influ e n c e
Although business leaders in the United States influenced 
school policy in the past, today their clout is largely unrivalled
1 . C O R P O R ATE A M B I T I O N S
L ooking to business is nothing new in edu-
c a t i o n . A century ago, schools adopted
reforms based on their reputed economic
benefits to individuals and the newly
industrializing urban society.The current
era has at its core a resurrected and strengthened
version of this notion. In both eras, reformers have
agreed that whatever public schools do to improve
individual students’ job opportunities has direct
economic consequences for the nation as a whole,
and for cities in particular.
The difference today is that corporate refor-
mers have gained the upper hand, tilting a tension-
filled compromise that had prevailed over the past
100 years. Corporate leaders have assumed the
unrivalled moral authority to define the purposes
and methods of public schooling in response to the
new technology-driven global economy. Hailed as
victorious generals in the battle between capita-
lism and socialism,many espouse a millennial vision
that links education to global free markets.Schoo-
l i n g, they tell us, hedges our national bets in the
global competition for market share and predicts
which students become good employees.But history
also cautions us that the long-term consequences of
t o d a y ’s experiments are probably less well unders-
tood than their advocates imagine.
The transfer of management methods from busi-
ness to schools began with a critique of school failure.
Between 1880 and 1920, different proponents had
their own economic justifications for reform. C o r-
porate leaders criticized urban schools for failing to
respond to a newly industrialized, c e n t r a l i z e d , a n d
increasingly integrated world economy.They sought
Honing job skills: Parisian school pupils perfect their enamel work in the early twentieth century.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
Facts and fig u r e s
Public expenditure on education has remained stable despite the steady
rise in enrolment. The private sector, which has long been involved in
education, has reinforced its position in the market and staked new
territory in software and computer tools for learning.
In general terms, the poorer the region,the smaller the
budget for public education.At all levels, public
expenditure per student has generally remained the same
in relation to the gross national product.
Yet it is widely believed that greater investment is
required to educate all students properly, including those
from disadvantaged backgrounds.
Trends in public expenditure on education as a proportion of GNP
Source: UNESCO World Education Report 2000
Source: UNESCO World Education Report 2000
PU B L I C E X P E N D I T U R E R E M A I N S T H E S A M E D E S P I T E G R O W I N G D E M A N D
During the past 50 years, total enrolment (at all levels) has
grown twice as fast as the world population.The most
dramatic increase has been in developing countries:
primary and secondary enrolment has risen eight-fold,
while the number of higher education students has
increased by a factor of 14.
RI S I N G T I D E O F S T U D E N T S
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 21
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
Private education expenditure as a percentage of total spending on education in 
selected OECD countries (1997)
Percentage of private school enrolment 
(primary and secondary) in selected countries (1997)
Changes in private education spending as a percentage 
of total education expenditure in selected OECD countries
Global higher education 
online market 1(US$ millions)
The number of academic CD-ROMs
available worldwide 3
Educational software market 
for schools and private consumers2
(US$ millions)
1-Source: Jupiter Communicatons; Moe, Michael T., Market Overview and Trends, World Bank/EdInvest, 2000.
2-Source: IDC Financial Times; Heyneman, Stephen P., Educational Qualifications: The Economic and Trade Issues, 2000.
3-Source: Waterlow New Media Information
Source: Education at a Glance 2000, Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD)
Data concerning private education is generally sparse,
incomplete and not always coherent. It is estimated that
the private sector accounts for about 20% of total
spending on education and is generally on the rise.
This proportion, however, can vary widely between
countries and often within a single country depending
upon the level of education.
PR I VAT E E D U C AT I O N G A I N S N E W G R O U N D
TH E E X P L O S I O N I N T H E N E W T E C H N O L O G I E S M A R K E T F O R E D U C AT I O N
Source: Education at a Glance 2000, OECD.                                                                                                                Source: OECD Education Database
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
1 . C O R P O R ATE A M B I T I O N S
centralization and effic i e n cy,frequently invoking the
powerful metaphor of scientific management or
“ Ta y l o r i s m ,” using the stopwatch and management
to discover the “one best way.”These principles had
been instrumental, industrialists of the time believed,
in creating the American industrial revolution and the
wealth of powerful international companies. Th e
quest for effic i e n cy of those decades led to the pro-
blems we must now repair, notably the rigid and
bureaucratic structure of our school systems.
To d a y, public schools continue to adapt new
business efficiency techniques in what seems to be
a constant recycling process. S c i e n t i fic manage-
ment,it turns out,was only the precursor to a host
of ever newer management theories aimed at encou-
raging greater worker productivity, and hence
greater national wealth.
When schools become levers
to attract business investment
These trends have echoes in the management
reforms prescribed for and adopted by schools.S o m e
seek increased effic i e n cy through decentralized school
governance while others imagine that outsourcing
(or contracting) the management and operation of
schools will lift educators’ performance because
incentives are lacking in secure government jobs.
All this is happening against the backdrop of eco-
nomic globalization, which inevitably creates poli-
tical tensions by pitting governments against one
another in competition for transnational corporate
jobs and global capital. Our current era mimics the
turn of the century to the extent that international
capital flows and transnational production processes
i n fluence both corporations and governments.To d a y,
technologically induced speed,growth among inves-
t o r s, concentration of wealth, and interconnected-
ness have increased the effects of this global specu-
lation and decreased the capacity of governments to
regulate business and markets. Not surprisingly, t h i s
global market ideology has been broadly recognized
as a force in national education policy.
Reforming local schools becomes one of the
ways that cities engage in the global competition to
provide production resources to corporations.Wh e n
formal schooling is seen as a key element of pro-
ductive capacity,a view reinforced by the decline of
manufacturing and the rise of information-based
technologies in the U. S. , the quality of the local
public school system takes on renewed importance
for business leaders and local politicians alike.
Today’s corporate leaders have uncommon access
to elected political officials and government agency
h e a d s, the wealth of large corporations to draw
u p o n ,and the ability to affect local and regional eco-
nomies simply by making business decisions.
Schools are treated as engines of economic
development to lure businesses to a particular city
or state, so corporate and local political leaders
cooperate in their governance and redesign. I n
short,school policy becomes labour policy.
This powerful combination of corporate,n a t i o n a l
and state executives is happening  at the expense of
education professionals. In contrast to the turn of the
c e n t u r y, when educators played a pivotal role in
debates by emphasizing the role of schools in deve-
loping citizenship, today they have been largely dis-
c r e d i t e d . Selecting school leaders from outside the
field has become both symptom and spur to this
decrease in the educator’s status.A small but influ e n-
tial group of school districts is choosing leaders from
among the ranks of businessmen, politicians and
the military, rather than educators.
All this is taking place with little evidence that
recent management solutions will turn around poor
schools, nor that improvements in school perfor-
mance protect against declines in productivity or the
business cycle. Yet there are more troubling pro-
blems with reform strategies that pit the market
against government in education.One is that edu-
cation is reduced to its narrowest economic pur-
poses.According to a 1992 survey, corporate exe-
cutives most want schools to emphasize “a basic
understanding of math and science” and “ s o u n d
work habits such as self-discipline, timeliness and
dedication to work.” These are laudable goals, but
r e flect a narrow set of traits that employers predict
their workers will need in an information economy.
The corporate model of reform pays little heed
to other expectations of public schools: b u i l d i n g
just and tolerant communities, reducing distrust of
one another and our shared institutions, safeguar-
ding democratic ethics and introducing children to
the cultural wisdom of the world. We are also wit-
nessing the abandonment of many kinds of equality.
Neither markets nor business ethics routinely put
equality or fairness above profits.Whole groups of
people will not fit the prevailing model of what it
takes to be competitive in an educational market-
place in which competition is the guiding principle
of improvement. Another disturbing trend is the
anaemic citizenship that economic justifications for
schooling envision. Increasing the emphasis on indi-
vidualism is likely to exacerbate a pattern of civic
disengagement many already find disturbing in its
scale and scope.
A balancing act to re a c h
a healthy equilibrium
We need a contemporary counter-movement to
restore a healthy equilibrium of goals for our public
s c h o o l s. This movement would be grounded in a
very different educational critique that rejects the
metaphor of market (or management) failure, a n d
instead tackles the problems in our schools as symp-
toms of a widespread civic breakdown.The solutions
to school failure would then hinge on common
c o n c e r n s,rather than rigorous individual competition
and accountability. In addition to academic criteria,
parents and reformers would craft student perfor-
mance measures that reward active citizenship, t o l e-
rant and respectful behaviour, and cultural know-
ledge in the arts,history and languages.This reform
m o v e m e n t , seeking equity and tolerance, w o u l d
revitalize democratic institutions, and not merely
aim for more efficient production. ■
All education
springs 
from some image
of the future. 
If the image of
the future 
held by a society
is grossly
inaccurate, its
education 
system will
betray its 
youth. 
Alvin Toffler, 
American futurologist (1928-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
???????????? : ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 23
Th i r t y - five years after it was founded,O b j e-
tivo has grown into one of the most thri-
ving educational enterprises in Brazil,w i t h
over 400 schools located all around the
country and a university.Wh a t ’s the secret?
Objetivo’s aim is to see that students get through,
and in this the company succeeds. Fewer than one
percent of pupils at the primary and secondary
level repeat a year, far below the national average,
which stands at 21.3 percent in primary school and
40.1 percent at the secondary level, according to
Education Ministry figures.
While the share of students in the private sector
is declining  (10.5 percent in 1996 to 8.2 percent in
2 0 0 0 ) , Objetivo reaches close to 500,000 pupils from
kindergarten to university level. Besides its own
schools (13 in São Paulo alone, where its head-
quarters are located), the company has franchises in
places as far apart as Brasilia, G o i a n i a , M a n a u s,
Campinas and Bauru.
O b j e t i v o ’s pedagogical coordinator,Alfredo Fe r-
n a n d e s,attributes the company’s success to the sound
reputation it has built over the years.“ Th e r e ’s a posi-
tive atmosphere in our schools,w e ’re always open to
a dialogue with students and society at large,”he says.
What has become a national network began in
1965 as a preparatory course for the entrance exam
required by Brazilian universities.This notched up
a pass rate of almost 90 percent and its fame quickly
g r e w. In 1970, spurred by the good state of its
finances, Objetivo founded a regular school,since
university entrance coaching was not part of the
national education system. “ We wanted to offer
quality education so we came up with our own acti-
vities and methods,” says Fernandes.
Objetivo grew rapidly. In 1972, its first faculties
were inaugurated,and sixteen years later, it was offi-
cially recognized as a full-fledged university (UNIP),
which today counts 53,000 students. In 1975 Objetivo
set up its first kindergarten and primary schools.
The schools accept both good pupils and those
with learning diffic u l t i e s.“After much discussion,w e
decided to go for an open school with no strea-
m i n g, where everyone had a chance to express
themselves,” says Fernandes.“This openness is the
main difference between us and other private
schools.”
Ironically, Objetivo is criticized because it has
no entrance exam.“Because we made it easy for
children to get into our schools and stay there, we
LUCIANA ZENTI
JOURNALIST FOR NOVA ESCOLA,
A BRAZILIAN EDUCATION MAGAZINE
O b j e t i v o : b rand-name schooling
A Brazilian chain of for-profit schools prides itself on a national network,
a pioneering use of technology and a high pass rate
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
Children explore the possibilities of paint in one of Objetivo’s schools.
2 . C ATERING TO DEMAND
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Total population 
(millions, 1999): 168
Adult literacy 
rate (1998): 84.5%
Gross enrolment 
ratio* (1997):
- Primary education: 125%
- Secondary education: 62%
- Tertiary education: 15%
Students enrolled in 
private primary and 
secondary schools 
(1997): 12.2%
* Enrolment as a percentage of 
the population of official school age for each
level
Sources: World Bank, UNDP, OECD.
KEY FIGURES, BRAZIL
24
2 . C ATERING TO DEMAND
Acommon assumption about the private
sector in education is that it caters only
to the élite,and that its promotion only
serves to exacerbate inequality. On the
contrary, recent research points in the
opposite direction.If we want to help some of the
most disadvantaged groups in society, then encou-
raging deeper private sector involvement is likely to
be the best way forward.
Several developments are underway  in India, a l l
of which involve the private education sector meeting
the needs of the poor in distinct ways. But India is not
unique in this respect—similar phenomena are hap-
pening all over the developing world.
As a point of departure, how do government
schools serve the poor? Usefully, the government-
sponsored Public Report on Basic Education in
India (PROBE) from 1999 paints a very bleak pic-
ture of the “ m a l f u n c t i o n i n g ”of government schools
for the poor.When researchers called unannounced
on their random sample of schools,only 53 percent
had any “teaching activity” going on. In  33 percent,
the headteacher was absent.Alarmingly, the team
noted that the deterioration of teaching standards
was not to do with disempowered teachers, but ins-
tead could be ascribed to “plain negligence.” They
Private education:
the poor’s best chance?
Across the developing world, private schools and education companies 
are not only flourishing, but reaching the poor. India is a case in point
JAMES TOOLEY
PROFESSOR OF EDUCATION POLICY, UNIVERSITY OF NEWCASTLE (UNITED KINGDOM)
were accused of having purely commercial inten-
t i o n s,” he says. In a country with widespread poverty,
Objetivo’s fees (between $215 and $355 a month
depending on the level) are certainly a sizeable
obstacle for many parents.
The high cost of tuition and the fact that the
project was started by people from outside the edu-
cation world made many experts suspicious of the
s c h o o l s. “I’m very much against commercializing
e d u c a t i o n ,” says Dermeval Saviani, professor of phi-
losophy and education history at the State Univer-
sity of Campinas.“Education is a social need that is
by nature incompatible with the private sector.”
Objetivo is a good example of this, he argues.
“ With the profits it makes from higher education, i t
has the money to  provide low-cost schooling.But this
is not happening. Because maintaining all its infra-
structure calls for major investment,Objetivo ignores
the poorest people.” He says this is a common failing
of all profit-making private schools, which are only
accessible to middle and upper-class children.
With an annual turnover of approximately $400
million,the company has a long tradition of inves-
ting in technology. It had the first school in Brazil to
use interactive video for teaching, and was the fir s t
to introduce computers in the classroom. N e a r l y
all its schools have computer rooms, libraries and
sports fie l d s, and offer extra-curricular activities
such as judo, music and visual arts.
“ This means we can escape from the routine
and learn more,” says 14-year-old Bianca Sgai
Fr a n c o. As well as having it own teaching mate-
r i a l s—t e x t b o o k s, computer software and CD-
R o m s—some schools are carrying out pioneer pro-
j e c t s.Two of them are linked to the environment:t h e
Sea School at Angra dos Reis, near Rio de Janeiro,
was founded in 1988 and offers courses in marine life
to pupils and teachers,while the Nature School,d e e p
in the Amazonian jungle, is run on similar lines.
Another attraction is the Talent Encourage-
ment Programme for children with exceptional
s k i l l s.A parent or teacher can ask for a gifted child
to be tested in order to take special classes in both
the social and natural sciences. “I enrolled my 11-
y e a r-old daughter in an Objetivo school because of
this programme,” says Maria Cecilia Novaes
Au g u s t o. “Now she’s doing robotics, t e c h n o l o g y
and art.It’s a very good programme.”
Tereza Cristina Matteis pays about 1,200 reales
($650) a month for the schooling of her three sons.“ I t ’s
a forward-looking educational system that keeps very
close contact with the children’s families,”she says. S i l-
vana Da Costa,who attended an Objetivo school and
now has three of her children there, says “ i t ’s very
open to the parents.” Given that her husband’s job has
meant living in eight of Brazil’s states, O b j e t i v o ’s
nationwide network has proved an invaluable asset.
Fe r n a n d e s, the chain’s pedagogical coordinator,
says the key difference between the schools and
the state system is the level of teacher training.“ I t ’s
a very serious problem in Brazil,” he says.Which is
why Objetivo offers all its teachers regular refresher
c o u r s e s.“Each year we organize at least five regional
meetings with teachers from other states,” s a y s
Deborah Cristina Catarinacho,who has taught Po r-
tuguese for the past 12 years. Quality control is also
s t r i c t ,with teachers around the country required to
use the course materials in exactly the same way.
“Objetivo draws you in,” says Adriana Ve n t u r i ,
a preschool teacher. “ We ’re a family where eve-
ryone encourages each other to go forward.” ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 25
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
noted “several cases of irrespon-
sible teachers keeping a school
closed ... for months at a time,”
many cases of drunk teachers, a n d
headteachers who asked children
to do domestic chores. S i g n i f i-
c a n t l y, the low level of teaching
activity occurred even in those
schools with relatively good infra-
s t r u c t u r e, teaching aids and pupil-
teacher ratios.
But is there any alternative to
these schools? Surely no-one else
can do better than government
given the resources available? A s
it happens, the PROBE report
pointed to private schools that
were serving the poor and
c o n c e d e d—rather reluctantly—
that such problems were not found
in these schools. In the great majo-
rity of private schools—a g a i n
visited unannounced and at
r a n d o m—there “was feverish
classroom activity.”Most parents
would prefer to send their chil-
dren to private schools if they could afford them.P r i-
vate schools, they said,were successful because they
were more accountable: “the teachers are accoun-
table to the manager (who can fire them), a n d ,
through him or her, to the parents (who can with-
draw their children).” Such accountability was not
present in the government schools,and “this contrast
is perceived with crystal clarity by the vast majority
of parents.”
The way forward: loosen regulations
and set up voucher schemes
To many readers, the existence of these private
schools for the poor will come as a surprise. It was
to me too, until I had the privilege of conducting
fieldwork for the International Finance Corporation
(the private finance arm of the World Bank) on a
group of such schools operating under the banner
of the Federation of Private Schools’ Management
based in Hyderabad.The federation has 500 private
schools (from kindergarten to grade ten) serving
poor communities in slums and villages. I was
impressed by both the entrepreneurial spirit within
these schools —they were run on commercial prin-
c i p l e s, not dependent on hand-outs from state or phi-
l a n t h r o p y— but also by the spirit of dedication
within the schools for the poor communities served:
not for nothing were the leaders of the schools
known as “social workers.” But these schools suffer
under restrictive and inappropriate regulations.
One example will suffic e : to be recognized, a school
must deposit up to  50,000 rupees(about $1,200) in
a stipulated bank account, of which neither the
capital nor the interest can be touched.Given that
the fees charged in these schools ranged from 25 (60
cents) to Rs 150  per month (about $3.50), w i t h
most of the schools grouped near the lower end of
the range, such sums are completely prohibitive.
Fees of around $10 per year are not affordable
by everyone,but they are to a large number of poor
f a m i l i e s. F u r t h e r m o r e, the great majority of the
schools offer a significant number of free places —
up to 20 percent— for the poorest students,a l l o c a t e d
on the basis of claims of need checked informally in
the community.
All of this suggests that if one is interested in
serving the needs of the poor in India, then trying to
reform the totally inadequate, cumbersome and
unaccountable government system is unlikely to be
the best way. I n s t e a d , reform the regulatory envi-
ronment to make it suitable for the flourishing of pri-
vate schools for the poor,help build private fin a n c i n g
schemes using overseas and indigenous philanthropy,
and encourage public voucher schemes, so that
parents can use their allowance of funding where they
see the schools are performing well, rather than was-
ting them in unresponsive state schools.
Private education in developing countries isn’t
just about the poor, of course, and there are many
exciting examples of big education businesses. B u t
these too have implications for the ways in which the
private sector can reach the least advantaged. O n e
Indian company which embodies much of the exci-
tement and innovation in the education industry is the
National Institute for Information Te c h n o l o g y
( N I I T ) . With its competitor, A p t e c h , it shares just
over 70 percent of the information technology edu-
cation and training market in India, estimated at
roughly Rs. 1.1 billion ($24 million). NIIT has 40
wholly owned centres in the metropolitan areas,a n d
about 1,000 franchised centres across India. It also
has a global reach, with centres in the U. S. ,A s i a -
P a c i fic,E u r o p e,Ja p a n ,Central Asia and A f r i c a . A key
aspect of NIIT’s educational philosophy is that there
is a need to harness research to improve the effi-
c i e n cy of learning and to raise educational standards.
Because of its success in developing innovative
and cost-effective IT education and training,NIIT has
In large states
public education
will always 
be mediocre, for
the same reason
that in large
kitchens 
the cooking is
usually bad. 
Friedrich Nietzsche, German
philosopher (1844-1900)
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
attracted the attention of several state governments.
First off the mark was Tamil Nadu,which wanted to
bring a computer curriculum to all of its high schools.
S i g n i fic a n t l y, although allocating about $22 million
over five years to this endeavour, it didn’t hand the
funds over to government schools,perhaps in light of
the PROBE report’s lessons. I n s t e a d , it developed a
model to contract out the service to private compa-
n i e s,which provide the software and hardware,w h i l e
the government supplies electricity and the class-
r o o m . For the first round of the Tamil Nadu process,
43 contracts were awarded for 666 schools,with NIIT
allotted 371 schools. Many of the classrooms have
become NIIT centres, open to school children and
teachers in daytime, then used by the franchise holder
in the evenings. The contracting out of curriculum
areas such as this represents an important step for-
ward in relationships between the public and pri-
vate sectors,and provides an interesting model worth
watching and emulating.
Most recently, NIIT has focused on reaching
largely illiterate and unschooled children through the
I n t e r n e t . Within weeks of having set up an “ I n t e r n e t
k i o s k ” in a slum area, the institute’s researchers
found that without any instruction, children could
achieve a remarkable level of computer literacy.
NIIT is exploring ways to roll out the idea com-
m e r c i a l l y,harnessing the power of the private sector
to reach the poorest through modern technology.
These initiatives all find echoes in other deve-
loping countries. In each case, the private, not the
public sector, is most responsive to the needs of
the poor, and is bringing innovation, e f fic i e n cy and
educational quality to the lives of the most disad-
v a n t a g e d .The private sector has the potential to pro-
mote greater equity and to influence education
policy, provided it is encouraged and viewed as a
p a r t n e r, not a threat to governments,whether in the
developing or the developed world. ■
South A f r i c a : the race 
for portable qualifications 
The government is trying to put some order into the burgeoning private higher education
sector and clamp down on dodgy foreign outfits
26
KAREN MACGREGOR
SOUTH AFRICAN JOURNALISTAND
CORRESPONDENT
FOR THE TIMES HIGHER EDUCATION
SUPPLEMENT
L ebo Sekoto is an upwardly mobile young
w o m a n , a 28-year-old senior human
resources consultant at a large mining
corporation in Pretoria. She is now inter-
nationally mobile too, she says, t h a n k s
to the arrival of Britain’s De Montfort University.
It is one of hundreds of further and higher educa-
tion institutions—local and foreign—that have set
up shop in South A f r i c a .
Now nearing the end of a part-time MBA ,L e b o
offers good reasons for choosing De Montfort.“I
want to expand my horizons and work for a multi-
national corporation and gain experience in the
United Kingdom.So I thought it fitting to obtain a
globally portable U.K.qualification.” In fact Lebo,
born in the sprawling black township of Soweto,h a s
been studying most of her life.
After leaving school she obtained a business
diploma at a polytechnic. Then came a part-time
degree in industrial psychology and business mana-
gement through the distance University of South
A f r i c a ,and now the MBA ,which combines part-time
and on-line study. “Companies see you as a young
black female fir s t ,”she says,“irrespective of your qua-
l i fic a t i o n s. If I want to move up the ladder to become
a chief executive, I have to be three times more qua-
l i fied and experienced than male colleagues.”
De Montfort (450 students in South Africa of
whom 65 percent are black) is one of several foreign
institutions now operating in South A f r i c a ’s private
s e c t o r. It is unusual in being non-profit and aiming to
build management skills in this developing country:
most others, local and foreign,are straight businesses.
It was also the first private institution to be registered
in South Africa under new laws aimed at regulating
the growth and quality of private higher education,
which is burgeoning here as it is in many other coun-
tries—to the point of threatening the viability of
many public institutions.
“Our public sector is immature, so we are imple-
menting new policies to develop it,” says Professor
Nasima Badsha, the government’s deputy director-
general in charge of higher education.“Much of the
private sector is for- p r o fit and market-driven, a n d
does not share our commitment to access, e q u i t y,
quality and human resource development. S u c h
concerns are shared by a number of countries in the
s o u t h .” Fees for private institutions tend to be 30 to
50 percent higher than those for state institutions.
After the dismantling of apartheid,
the foreign influx begins 
It is not known exactly how many private tertiary
institutions are currently operating. In higher edu-
c a t i o n , 100 of more than 200 institutions that applied
for accreditation have been or are well on the way to
being registered.The private higher education insti-
tutions have more than 20,000 full-time students in
South A f r i c a , which last year had 564,000 students in
the public sector.Hundreds of thousands are enrolled
in private part-time higher education courses and a
vast number of further education courses ranging
The teacher 
is to students
what the rain 
is to the field.
Zaira Alexandra Rodriguez
Guijamo, Mexican pupil
(1985-)
● The Probe Team,
Public Report 
on Basic Education in
India, Oxford,Oxford
University Press, 1999
● Tooley, James, The
Global Education Indus -
try, London,IEA/IFC,
1999,and Reclaiming
Education, London,
Continuum/Cassel,
2000
TO KNOW MORE
2 . C ATERING TO DEMAND
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
ning quality,disruption and lack of safety in the state
s e c t o r.
With an unemployment rate near 30 percent
and the formal economy absorbing only 56 percent
of students from top universities—and 25 percent
from less respected ones—students seek “ m a r k e-
t a b l e ”q u a l i fications that vocationally oriented poly-
technics and private institutions are seen to offer.
Many people see foreign degrees as more prestigious
and portable than local ones, while others view them
as an emigration ticket to a richer country.
Most of the private institutions are genuine, b u t
fly-by-night operators are a problem. The 1997
Higher Education Act is supposed to weed them out
by requiring that all private institutions seek course
accreditation from the South African Qualific a-
tions Au t h o r i t y. They must also register with the
education department, which has two criteria for
acceptance: financial viability and quality.
“ Foreign institutions posed a particular threat
to public universities,” says Professor Badsha.“ Th e y
mostly operate in a narrow range of areas,e s p e c i a l l y
I T, business and commerce,‘cherry picking’ fin a n-
wealthy can afford, resulting in a new form of apar-
theid, says Badsha.“We are trying to move away
from race and class to create truly South African ins-
titutions.”
As a result, the government is amending the
act to make it more difficult for foreign institutions
to set up in South A f r i c a . For example,before gran-
ting permits, the registrar will judge whether the
applicant is useful to the public system and broadens
the scope of courses offered. Even though South
A f r i c a ’s constitution prohibits discrimination against
foreign institutions, some of them have threatened
to take the issue to the World Trade Organization.
Indeed many foreign institutions have already left.
Education Minister Kader Asmel strongly
rejects claims that the clampdown is motivated by
“narrow protectionist agendas or national chauvi-
n i s m .” The goal, he says, is simply to assure the
accountable and efficient use of public resources.
“ We do not wish to turn a blind eye to supra-
national developments, or build new walls around
ourselves. But we cannot stand by and watch the
erosion of our system.” ■
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
from literacy to art, computing and business.
The influx of foreign institutions began after the
n a t i o n ’s first democratic elections in 1994.With the dis-
mantling of apartheid, black students shifted away
from poorly resourced “ b l a c k ” institutions to well-
endowed formerly “ w h i t e ”o n e s, while many mostly
middle-class white students moved to private institu-
t i o n s, due to perceptions—hotly denied—of decli-
cially lucrative courses without the obligation of offering the
full range of disciplines. Public universities found themselves
losing income-earning courses they use to cross-subsidize
expensive disciplines such as music and art, medicine and
e n g i n e e r i n g,which are critical to South A f r i c a ’s cultural, s o c i a l
and economic development.”
Foreign institutions also attract good staff from public uni-
versities by paying higher salaries,and charge fees that only the
A computer course for adults at the Lawaaicamp settlement in the Western Cape, South Africa.
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 27
Total population 
(millions, 1999): 42
Adult literacy 
rate (1998): 84.6%
Gross enrolment 
ratio (1997):
- Primary education: 133%
- Secondary education: 95%
- Tertiary education: 17%
Students enrolled in 
private primary and 
secondary schools 
(1996): 3.3%
Sources: World Bank, UNDP.
KEY FIGURES, SOUTH AFRICA
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Total population 
(millions, 1999): 273
Adult literacy 
rate (1998) 99%
Gross enrolment 
ratio (1997):
- Primary education: 102%
- Secondary education: 97%
- Tertiary education: 81%
Private share of 
expenditure on 
educational institutions,
all levels (1997): 25%
Sources: World Bank, UNDP, OECD.
KEYFIGURES, UNITED STATES
The industrialized world’s first public edu-
cation system is under siege, with fierce
attacks pitched from all sides in the U.S.
political arena. First the administrative
leadership of large urban school districts
is reeling from accusations of being ineffic i e n t ,
overly bureaucratic and more preoccupied with
rules and regulations than with providing quality
education to students. M e a n w h i l e, t e a c h e r s, s t u-
dents and parents,especially those from low-income
areas, are the targets of blame for what has been
characterized as the “rising tide of mediocrity that
threatens our very  future as a nation and a people.”
Never before has education received such atten-
tion in a presidential campaign. The nation tuned
into televised debate where Al Gore and George
Bush clearly marked out the battle lines.The Demo-
crat pledged to pump $115 billion more into a school
system in need of  greater accountability and inno-
v a t i o n ,while the Republican vowed to dismantle the
system and replace it by privately managed schools
that operate on marketplace principles.
At the centre of the debate lies the highly
controversial voucher plan: instead of paying taxes
to support their local public school, parents can
opt to use that money to send their child to a private
school.In 1998 Florida became the first to adopt a
statewide plan,while California and Michigan will
vote on similar initiatives in November 2000.Cali-
f o r n i a ’s is notably supported by Tim Draper, a
Silicon Valley venture capitalist. The proposed
p o l i cy : to provide state-funded scholarships of $4,000
(compared to the $5,627 per student the state now
spends) to any parents who want to send their chil-
dren to private or parochial schools.
Despite their power, teacher unions have been
left to the margins of the debate. Often castigated
as stubborn defenders of the status quo, u n i o n s
have been forced into a defensive posture, a t t e m p-
ting to fight off the most radical reform measures
while working to raise the salaries and benefits of
their members, which are widely recognized as
inadequate.Although the American Federation of
Teachers and the National Education Association
continue to play a major role in statewide elec-
t i o n s, their influence in the debate over educational
reform has been minimal.
Support for the privatization camp is drawn lar-
gely from certain corporations which perceive public
education as hopelessly unfix a b l e, religious conser-
vatives who want to exercise greater control over
what their children are taught, and a growing
number of middle-class parents whose children
already attend private schools and who resent being
taxed to support a system they do not patronize. I n
most states, this coalition has been unable to muster
the support needed to implement privatization pro-
posals beyond a small number of isolated cases.
But this appears to be changing.
Other constituencies who once were viewed as
reliable supporters of public education now appear
willing to back efforts to radically transform the
system and replace it with new models, many of
which remain undefined and untested. A recent
study conducted by the Joint Center for Po l i t i c a l
and Economic Studies found that 88 percent of
African Americans were in favour of education
choice plans, with the highest support (95 percent)
coming from families earning less than $15,000 a
y e a r. For parents whose children have long consti-
tuted a “captured market” and been forced to attend
the most inferior schools, the various privatization
proposals hold out the promise of providing access
to quality education.
The white middle class takes flight
How do we explain this groundswell of interest?
The answer is far from straightforward.Though the
right to education is not guaranteed by the U. S.
c o n s t i t u t i o n , access to education has effectively
become a universal entitlement. Moreover, many
s i g n i ficant advancements in civil rights for racial
minorities, the disabled, language minorities, and
more recently gays and lesbians, have first been
achieved in public education before spreading to
other sectors of society. Schools in the U. S. a r e
governed locally, and throughout the country com-
munities increasingly look to their public schools for
solutions to a growing list of social problems.
Yet so many schools are in such a lamentable
state that the entire system is now under attack.
Severe funding cuts in the 1980s forced many school
districts to eliminate academic programmes (such as
a r t , music and athletics), increase the number of stu-
dents per classroom,and reduce access to services such
as counselling. Fractious labour relations, d e c a y i n g
buildings and an array of social problems, many of
which are related to impoverishment of the children
they serve,have overwhelmed school personnel.
Such conditions have compelled many middle-
class families to flee urban school districts and trans-
formed many schools into institutions of last resort.
African American and Latino students are grossly
o v e r-represented in these failing schools.So it may
be only natural to find their parents increasingly
open to voucher proposals.
28
PEDRO A. NOGUERA
URBAN SOCIOLOGIST, PROFESSOR AT HARVARD UNIVERSITY’S GRADUATE SCHOOL
OF EDUCATION
When parents want out
In the U.S., parents are claiming the right to spend their tax money as
they see fit and are rallying in growing numbers behind voucher plans. A
critical look at the school choice controversy
2 . C ATERING TO DEMAND
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 29
Fe a r, racial prejudice toward mino-
r i t i e s, and the arrival of new immigrants
have also contributed to the flight of the
white middle class. States such as Cali-
f o r n i a , Florida and New York have
experienced substantial increases in
public school enrolment due to the
immigration of large numbers of A s i a n s
and Latin A m e r i c a n s.As the demogra-
phics of the student population has
c h a n g e d , registered voters, t y p i c a l l y
older and disproportionately white,h a v e
been less willing to cover the costs of
public education through tax increases.
The airline model and the
future of schools left behind
Despite their many weaknesses,
public schools continue to offer one
of the only sources of mobility and
social support to poor and working-
class families. Under voucher schemes,
elite schools may become even more
selective as an  increase in the demand
for admission allows them to raise the
cost of tuition and moves them even
further beyond the reach of low-
income families.And what will happen
to those schools and students left
behind?  Funding is based largely on
e n r o l m e n t , so it seems unlikely that
the undesirable schools will receive
the resources needed to improve.Th e
State of California’s legislative analyst
projects a major cut in public school
funding if the children already in pri-
vate schools receive vouchers and if
five percent of those in the public
system use vouchers to leave.
Shifting the burden
of responsibility 
The essential difference between
the present situation and what is likely
to occur after privatization is that indi-
viduals rather than government will
bear responsibility for ensuring access to
quality education. Advocates point  to
the example of the new airlines that
were established shortly after the indus-
t r y ’s deregulation in the 1980s. M o s t
of the new airlines no longer exist,
h o w e v e r, and those that do are widely
seen as offering inferior quality albeit at a lower
p r i c e.But the advocates still argue that  new schools
c o u l d n ’t possibly be worse than the public ones now
operating in certain districts. But unlike public
s c h o o l s, which are required to  meet legally establi-
shed educational standards (mainly teaching cre-
dentials and  accessibility for students), there is no
guarantee that private schools will be held to similar
r e q u i r e m e n t s.
The advocates seem to be gaining the political
a d v a n t a g e. In such a climate,defence of public edu-
cation must be based upon more than its potential to
i m p r o v e, but on evidence that this can in fact be
d o n e.Public education is in desperate need of reform,
and those who value and appreciate its role in society
must be at the forefront of efforts to hasten the pace
of change, otherwise A m e r i c a ’s “one best system”
could very well be terminated. ■
Children and parents rally in Dayton,Ohio, for the freedom to pick their schools.
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
MARK WALSH
ASSOCIATE EDITOR OF EDUCATION WEEK (U.S.)
E d i s o n ’s third wa y
In a less than a decade, a New York-based company has established a
reputation for managing troubled public schools, but the venture is still
struggling to make a profit
Benno C. Schmidt Jr. stunned many when
he quit one of the most prestigious posi-
tions in academia in 1992 to help lead a
controversial educational venture that
had no guarantee it would ever open its
first school.
Schmidt was lured from the presidency of Ya l e
University by media entrepreneur Christopher
Whittle to bring some educational prestige to what was
then known as the Edison Project,a venture launched
in 1991.The goal:to try new approaches in elementary
and secondary education that Whittle believed would
be as revolutionary as Thomas Edison’s replacement
of the candle with the electric light bulb.
Nine years later, Edison Schools Inc. is viewed
as the leading company in the movement towards
private management of public education in the U. S.
It now manages 108 public schools serving some
57,000 students, up from 25 schools in 1997-98.
Many are so-called charter schools, namely public
schools that are largely independent of the tradi-
tional school districts and operate free of many
state bureaucratic rules.They receive funding from
the state government on a per-pupil basis and
parents pay no tuition. But Edison also contracts
with school authorities to manage traditional public
schools using its educational model.
“Most people thought of this as a kind of expe-
riment on the edge of the possible,” says Schmidt,
“and a lot of people are distrustful of how a private
firm would operate public schools. But we’ve seen
a broader and broader acceptance by public edu-
cational institutions that good,high-quality private
firms have a lot to offer.”
In many districts, authorities have turned over
some of the worst performing schools to Edison.
While the company has a well-oiled marketing
machine, a number of school administrators have
been attracted by Edison’s all-encompassing exper-
tise and bold approach.The company offers a com-
plete package,which cost $40 million to develop. I t s
curriculum is regarded as rigorous,exceeding requi-
rements of most states. School days are longer than
n o r m a l , students take Spanish in kindergarten and
can study for the International Baccalaureate.The
schools have at least three computers per class-
r o o m ,and students can take home a personal com-
puter to work on projects and surf the Internet as
well as to link parents and teachers.
The company has a touchy relationship with
the country’s two teachers’ unions,which have been
generally critical of private management. Th e
unions’ chief concerns are that the company uses
relatively inexperienced teachers, and that the tea-
cher turnover rate is high.The American Fe d e r a t i o n
of Teachers (AFT) has paid particularly close atten-
tion to test scores and argues that the achievement
record is not as rosy as the company paints it.“ S o m e
of their schools have improved and some have
really struggled.Th e r e ’s no magic in being private,”
says Celia Lose, an AFT spokeswoman.
Despite criticism, Edison Inc. is confid e n t .E n r o l-
ment has increased eightfold since 1996, r e v e n u e
stands at  $225 million, financial losses are shrin-
king ($37 million) and its stock has inched upward
since the company went public in November 1999.
While the company’s priority is to get a firmer foo-
ting in the U. S. —it has to manage several hundred
schools before realizing economies of scale— it will
seek to expand internationally. “Edison genuinely
represents what people in the U. K . , especially To n y
B l a i r, call a third way,” says Schmidt.“ I t ’s not fully
p r i v a t e,and not fully public.” He notes that to many
in Europe,privatization of public services has been
an “all or nothing” p r o p o s i t i o n . It has meant taking
a state enterprise “and converting it completely to
private management,” he says.“Edison offers more
of a partnership with government.” ■
An investment 
in knowledge
pays the best
return.
Benjamin Franklin, American
statesman 
and scientist 
(1706-1790)
Team work and technology: a sampling of activities in an Edison school.
2 . C ATERING TO DEMAND
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 31
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
BY ROBIN MASON
DIRECTOR OFTHE OPEN UNIVERSITY’S MASTERS PROGRAMMEIN OPENAND
DISTANCE EDUCATION (U.K.)
Wiring up the ivory towers
Prestigious universities are forging alliances to conquer a share of the 
e-learning market and stand up to virtual competitors
Just like airline companies, u n i v e r s i t i e s
around the world are forming partnerships
and consortia in response to the pressures of
g l o b a l i z a t i o n .The World Education Market
held in Vancouver last May was a timely
s i g n : t h e
fair, expressly organized to foster relations bet-
ween universities, training providers, software com-
panies and representatives from nations with large
education needs,attracted participants from over 60
countries.
This race to “partner up” is fuelled by a number
of factors. In most industrialized countries, g o v e r n-
ment funding for higher education has decreased,
forcing institutions to look for new markets either
to subsidize campus programmes or just to remain
v i a b l e.There is a  growing need for lifelong learning
as “jobs for life” vanish and the information society
drastically reduces the shelf-life of almost any edu-
cational qualific a t i o n .Technological developments,
increasingly necessary for learners in all fields to
master, offer ever more innovative tools for sup-
porting e-learning.
For business,online learning is “ t h e ”new market
o p p o r t u n i t y, with the need for re-training and pro-
fessional updating predicted to create an $11.5 billion
industry by 2003. Business is better able to develop
and maintain the technological infrastructure neces-
sary to run large online systems and everyone, i n c l u-
ding the universities, recognizes that it takes robust
telecommunications technology to deliver educa-
tion and training on the scale demanded.
A host of companies has sprung up to help uni-
versities shape and package courses for online pre-
s e n t a t i o n , while network providers are jockeying for
position to deliver online education.
The United States is the undisputed leader in the
field, prompting governments in the U.K.,Canada
and Australia to commission hefty studies on the
danger of national universities being eroded by
U. S.ventures turned global.Canada and the U. K .a r e
● Robin Mason, Globa -
lising Education: Trends
and Applications, Rout-
ledge, 1998
TO KNOW MORE
First-class diplomas are just a mouse click away.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
in the early stages of setting up their own virtual uni-
v e r s i t i e s. But what has become clear is that the conser-
vative and labyrinthine decision-making processes
which characterize most university procedures are
being jolted by a race to get a share of the lifelong
learning market.
So far, the most common approach for universities
to break into the e-learning universe has been to develop
courses specifically for a corporate partner or to form
alliances among themselves.Universitas 21, a company
incorporated in the U. K . , is a network of 18 leading
universities in ten countries.Earlier this year, it formed
a joint venture with Rupert Murdoch’s News Corpora-
tion to provide premium higher education programmes
using new information technologies and learning
m e t h o d s.In October 2000, S t a n f o r d ,P r i n c e t o n ,Yale and
Oxford formed “ The Big Four A l l i a n c e,” aimed at offe-
ring courses in the arts and sciences
to 500,000 alumni.
Very often,prestigious universi-
ties have stayed clear of going fully
o n l i n e, seeing a danger to their
brand name.Many are limiting their
offerings to continuing education
programmes and/or non-degree
c o u r s e s, and more often than not,
they are aiming at the corporate
m a r k e t . One company,U N e x t . c o m ,
has partnered with first-class insti-
tutions such as the University of
Columbia (U. S.) and the London
School of Economics to create
online courses marketed under the
name Cardean University. Th e i r
t a r g e t : the Fortune 500 companies as
well as individual adults. Th e y ’v e
managed to attract Nobel laureates to design courses and
the universities receive royalties for their content. O t h e r
universities have formed spin-off for- p r o fit companies
s p e c i fically to develop online programmes.This facilitates
the commercialization of software and other products,
and is a way to take a commercial approach to conti-
nuing and professional studies without compromising
the University’s academic standing.
Then there are the freestanding for- p r o fit virtual uni-
v e r s i t i e s, which are arousing the ire of institutions that
have prided themselves on a long history of  public
s e r v i c e.The most quoted examplar is Phoenix Univer-
s i t y, the largest private outfit in the U. S. Now owned by
the Apollo Group, it operates the country’s largest
online programme with 12,200 students.The university
tracks students’ progress and contacts those who don’t
submit assignments on time or fail to enrol in subse-
quent courses.Many critics question Phoenix’s blatant
c o m m e r c i a l i z a t i o n , but few doubt the university’s
impact on continuing professional development pro-
vision.
Although e-learning is in its infancy, its impact can
already by gauged.New providers are coming on the
market all the time and the trend is accelerating to the
point of upsetting universities’ virtual monopoly in
educational accreditation.An Information Te c h n o l o g y
training course offered or accredited by Microsoft has
undoubtedly become more valuable than a Bachelor
of Science from a renowned university.
The more consumerist the approach of the edu-
cation provider,the more what is taught is influ e n c e d
by demand. M BAs dominate e-learning provision
and IT courses are a close second. While the new
consumer/learner demands fle x i b i l i t y,choice and just-
in-time learning opportunities,suppliers will inevitably
arise who are focused on meeting the demand at the
expense of quality and value. And is the consumer
really the best judge of what course material to
choose? Education is a more complex “ p r o d u c t ”t h a n
toothpaste or washing powder.A totally consumer-
driven education market is unlikely to be in society’s
best interests in the long term.
The commercialization of education usually
goes hand-in-hand with desegregation: c o u r s e
d e s i g n ,d e l i v e r y, t u t o r i n g, a s s e s s-
ment and accreditation may be
carried out by different organi-
z a t i o n s. Students might study
courses or modules from diffe-
rent universities or providers
and then put themselves for-
ward for examination and
accreditation by yet another ins-
titution. While most academics
loathe marking assignments,
they regard this scenario with
horror, and blame commercia-
lization for the demise of the
“community of scholars”
concept of a university. Th e
death of the “course” has also
been predicted, with learners—
especially corporate and on-the-
job learners—demanding short study modules.
What then happens to the ability to get an overview
of a field when learning consists of the student
selecting a whole series of unconnected learning
“bites”? Learners will be “ z a p p i n g ” between short
sequences or presentations much as they do bet-
ween television channels.
But while some faculty view e-learning with
a l a r m , technology-based learning is where most of the
pedagogical innovation is taking place in universities.
Multimedia learning resources and interactive simu-
lations are being developed for the web.C o l l a b o r a-
tive learning activities, new forms of online assess-
ment and small group teaching technologies are
making online courses more stimulating, i n t e r a c t i v e
and attractive than many face-to-face taught courses.
Despite “doom and gloom scenarios,”most mode-
rate observers of the scene see a continued future for
the campus university, especially at the undergra-
duate level, while e-learning will above all cater to
a d u l t , professional and independent learners. S o m e
commercialization of education is good  if it fosters
i n n o v a t i o n ,concern for quality and responsiveness to
consumer demands.But if some is good, more is not
necessarily better! Not in education at least. ■
If the
government
would make
up its mind to
require for
every child a
good
education, it
might save
itself the
trouble of
providing one.
It might leave
to parents to
obtain the
education
where and
how they
pleased, and
content itself
with helping
to pay the
school fees of
2 . C ATERING TO DEMAND
The most common 
approach for 
universities to break
into the e-learning 
universe has 
been to develop 
courses specifically 
for a 
corporate partner
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
???????????? : ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 33
The case for bringing the ideas and values of
the private sector to primary and secon-
dary education sounds fine on paper. G i v e
local schools operational autonomy.Th e n
abolish geographical enrolment zones and
allow parents to choose which school their child
will attend so that schools have to compete to attract
s t u d e n t s. In the resulting educational “ m a r k e t p l a c e,”
schools will improve their teaching and student
achievement records.
Such was the thinking that New Zealand applied
to the running of its state education system in the
1990s under a series of legislative changes known as
Tomorrow’s Schools reforms.The reform plan was
the boldest experiment with market-based educa-
tion ever carried out by a developed country.
Overnight, the system goes local
and parents take charge
What were the results? The answer is at best
m i x e d . It was good for some schools and some stu-
d e n t s, but disastrous for other schools, many of
which served disproportionate shares of disadvan-
taged students.As New Zealand policymakers now
busily retreat from the reforms, their experience
offers some warnings for other countries thinking
about moving down the same road.
The application of market principles to the deli-
very of public education was a natural step for New
Z e a l a n d .This island nation of 3.8 million people had
gone through a serious economic crisis in the early
1980s that had left the country close to bankruptcy.
In 1984 a new Labour government was elected that
decided to break with tradition and restructure the
c o u n t r y ’s economy around neo-liberal themes.By the
end of the decade, the government extended the
restructuring effort to the social sectors of the eco-
n o m y. First came the national health system, t h e n
housing and welfare. Education was next.
EDWARD B. FISKE AND HELEN F. LADD
EDWARD B. FISKE, FORMER EDUCATION EDITOR
OF THE NEW YORK TIMES, AND HELEN F. LADD, PROFESSOR
OF PUBLIC POLICY STUDIESAND ECONOMICS
AT DUKE UNIVERSITY (U.S.). CO-AUTHORSOF A BOOK ON
NEW ZEALAND’S SCHOOL REFORMS, WHEN SCHOOLS COMPETE: A CAUTIONARY
TALE (BROOKINGS, 2000).
New Zealand: the price of 
the market model
The country with the most 
free-market public education 
system in the West is now 
trying to rescue schools 
caught in a downward spiral
3 . N OTES OF CAU T I O N
Maori language classes at a primary school in Te Koha, New Zealand.
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Total population 
(millions, 1999): 4
Adult literacy 
rate (1998): 99%
Gross enrolment 
ratio (1997):
- Primary education: 101%
- Secondary 
education : 113%
- Tertiary education: 63%
Private share of 
expenditure in educational 
institutions : n.a.
Sources: World Bank, UNDP.
KEY FIGURES, NEW ZEALAND
34
3 . N OTES OF CAU T I O N
In 1989, Parliament abolished the national
Department of Education and turned control of
primary and secondary schools over to locally
elected boards of trustees, dominated by parents.
Virtually overnight, one of the world’s most tightly
controlled public education systems became one
of the most decentralized.The central government
continued to fund the education system,negotiate
teacher contracts and enforce accountability
through an inspectorate system.
Innovation versus the downward
spiral of low-performing schools
Two years later a new government controlled by
the conservative National Party ratcheted the stakes
up another notch. Parliament abolished neighbou-
rhood enrolment zones and gave parents the right to
choose which school their child would attend. P r i-
mary and secondary schools found themselves com-
peting for students in an educational agora. P u b l i c
relations and marketing skills became as integral
to the job description of principals as knowledge of
curriculum and the ability to manage a faculty.
Many schools prospered under the new arran-
g e m e n t s, especially those serving middle and upper-
middle class students. Such schools had the social
capital among their parent bodies to elect boards of
trustees with the governance, financial, legal and
other skills needed to run an educational institution,
and some  principals with entrepreneurial instincts
took full advantage of their new-found autonomy to
offer innovative educational programmes.
The Gladstone Primary School in Au c k l a n d ,f o r
e x a m p l e, began offering a programme organized
around the theory of “multiple intelligences” a r t i-
culated by Harvard University psychologist Howard
G a r d n e r.“No one is restricting us,”said Colin Dale,
the principal.“ The potential is now there to do wha-
tever you want. I t ’s all about meeting needs and per-
f o r m i n g. If you get it right,people will flock to you.”
Self-governance did have its price.The workload
of principals and teachers increased substantially and
many schools serving large numbers of disadvan-
taged students found it difficult to muster boards of
trustees with the requisite governance skills.
For their part, New Zealand parents enthusias-
tically embraced their new right to choose where
their child would go to school. Substantial num-
bers of students began venturing outside their local
neighbourhoods to attend classes. Their numbers
included many Maori and Pacific Island students
from low-income families who saw an opportunity
to flee low-performing urban schools.
From the point of view of parents,moving up the
scale in choice of school is understandable and even
r a t i o n a l .But in New Zealand,parents judge the qua-
lity of schools by the ethnic and socioeconomic mix of
their students.Schools with a preponderance of Euro-
pean students are seen as superior to those with large
numbers of Maori and Pacific Islanders. In the new
educational marketplace, schools serving predomi-
nantly white students have grown in size during the
1 9 9 0 s, while those serving large numbers of minority
students saw their rolls decrease.They could not com-
pete for either high quality teachers or motivated stu-
d e n t s.The cost of transportation and optional school
fees have also limited minority access to the most
desirable schools.
Although other countries might design a compe-
titive system somewhat differently from New Zealand,
the forces unleashed by parental choice are under
any circumstances likely to push systems towards
greater polarization.By defin i t i o n , in any competitive
environment some participants will be successful and
others will fail. Th a t ’s the way markets work. We
observed situations in New Zealand where schools
operating on a level playing field were engaged in
vigorous competition for students that probably
redounded to the benefit of both.The problem is that
the playing field is not always level. Enrolment data
show lower income and minority students are dis-
proportionately represented among schools that are
unable to compete. There has been an enhanced
concentration in schools at the bottom of diffic u l t -
to-teach students—those from poverty-stricken homes,
those whose English is weak,those with learning dif-
ficulties and those who are suspended from other
schools for disciplinary reasons.
New Zealanders describe the loser schools as “ s p i-
r a l l i n g ”d o w n w a r d .Once they begin to fall behind in the
educational marketplace,downward spiralling schools
find their problems compounding and feeding on each
o t h e r.Lower student rolls means fewer teachers,w h i c h
means a less attractive academic programme, w h i c h
means even fewer students.Schools become losers;s o
do the students and families served by them.
The return of the state and the 
need for policy safeguards
By the mid-1990s public pressure began buil-
ding on the Ministry of Education,a policy - o r i e n t e d
successor to the abolished department, to assist
these spiralling schools. The ministry began offe-
ring managerial assistance,then moved toward more
direct intervention. By 1998 top ministry offic i a l s
were conceding that the educational marketplace
would never work for as many as a quarter of
s c h o o l s.
One may ask whether it is defensible, on moral,
practical or other grounds, to organize the delivery of
public education so that you know from the outset
that a properly working system will seriously exa-
cerbate the problems of some schools.The creation
of losers might be justified if competition led to an
overall improvement of the system as a whole and the
losers would still be winners in absolute terms. Or it
might be justified if the Ministry of Education,a w a r e
that competition leads inevitably to unsuccessful
s c h o o l s,stood ready with a safety net.Neither condi-
t i o n ,h o w e v e r, was present in New Zealand.
The country’s decade-long experience with
market-based reform demonstrates there are no
panaceas in school reform. The trick is to adopt
reform strategies that will protect the positive values
of self-governance and competition while minimi-
zing their negative consequences through appro-
priate policy safeguards. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 35
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
O f f s h o re
t h r e a t s
The impending flood of offshore
courses may do more than lure
students away from the public
system. It may shake a pillar of
national cohesion, says Gajaraj
Dhanarajan, head of the
Commonwealth of Learning* 
A re online degrees offered by fore i g n
u n i versities eroding the position of
national institutions?
The impact has not been significantly felt yet,
because a large part of the population in developing
countries cannot afford  to pay for courses travelling
via the Internet from offshore sources. Even when
such courses are heavily subsidized, as is the case
with the African Virtual University, the cost is pro-
hibitive.An AVU course from Canada,the U.K.or
the U.S. is said to be around $200-300 per credit.
Th a t ’s probably the monthly salary of an academic
in one of the countries with an AVU site.
What about in the longer term?
Academic environments run the risk of being des-
tabilized in countries where offshore courses are
d o w n l o a d e d . Students who can afford these courses
are the ones who have already enjoyed previous pri-
v i l e g e s, notably a much better secondary educa-
t i o n . Offshore degrees provide yet another privilege:
they’re an attractive proposition for those wishing
to get jobs abroad besides being prized by local
employers. So two types of  student communities
might evolve: an underprivileged class that attends
a local university and a privileged class that can
use a brand-name “ f o r e i g n ”e d u c a t i o n .This is likely
to create resentment. The local academic commu-
nity could also become demoralized if it sees itself
serving only the second best.
So there is a threat to national cohesion?
Ye s. In many developing countries,higher education
is seen as a key component of nation-building. I
fear this is in danger of being damaged for a number
of reasons including a mismatch between offshore
curricula and local hopes of building national cohe-
sion,maintaining cultural integrity and addressing
local resource needs.What we are seeing with off-
shore courses is the dumping, at an international
l e v e l , of products created for domestic consumption.
H ow much leverage do governments have in
this context?
There is very little they can do without running into
INTERVIEW BY CYNTHIA GUTTMAN
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
a string of criticism including accusations of erecting
barriers to the free flow of information. Local legis-
lation concerning quality and curriculum can be
applied to foreign institutions in real space, but is
much more difficult to do in cy b e r s p a c e. G o v e r n-
ments could  tax those delivering the product, b u t
ultimately the customer pays.Taxing the user is also
d i f ficult to justify because students could argue that
t h e y ’re already paying for a quality they can’t get
l o c a l l y. Governments could take a stronger moral
l i n e, saying yes to a free market but stipulating that
a significant part of the curriculum must address
local human capital development needs.They have
to be persuasive in presenting those arguments in
global fora like the World Trade Organization.
H ow can local institutions improve their stan-
d i n g ?
Local capacities have to be developed, and these
include making education accessible to those who
cannot study within campus walls. Online education
is not the only solution.There are open universities
in the developing world that do a very good job of
taking knowledge to learners through a variety of
methods but which are supported at the village level
by mentors who can help students. These capaci-
ties ought to be developed. Universities in develo-
ping countries should become dual-mode institu-
tions to cater to the off-campus population. If those
capacities include e-learning, w o n d e r f u l . But our
aim should be to improve access to learning and to
internationalize education. This does not mean
making education a trade.The issue is too important.
Commodifying education does not augur well for the
cause of internationalizing edu-
c a t i o n .
■
*The Commonwealth
of Learning is an
international organi-
zation to encourage
the development
and sharing of open
learning and distance
education knowledge,
resources and technolo-
gies. For more informa-
tion,see www.col.org
Education is 
the art of making
man ethical. 
Georg Friedrich Hegel, German
philosopher, (1770-1831)
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
When did the commercialization of edu-
cation became a concern for the SFI?
SFI has been strongly protesting moves
to privatize education since the early
1990s when the process of economic
liberalization started in India.Since then education has
come under severe threat due to the policies of suc-
cessive governments bent upon following the Wo r l d
B a n k ’s privatization agenda.While the share of higher
education in the government’s total education budget
has gradually declined over the years,private investors
have gained more and more access to the market.
Despite rules to monitor private institutions,
there is in reality no government control over most
of the private medical,engineering and other colleges
mushrooming all over the country. Most of them
have no infrastructure,offer poor quality education
and charge very high fees that can’t be afforded by
even the middle class, let alone the poor.
What are the implications for students?
Fi r s t , private investors are setting up large edu-
36
INTERVIEW BY UTPAL BORPUJAR
JOURNALIST BASED IN NEW DELHI
Money 
over merit?
Samik Lahiri, g e n e ral secretary of the
Students’ Fe d e ration of India (SFI),
one of the world’s largest such
o rg a n i z a t i o n s, raises the alarm 
over advancing commerc i a l i z a t i o n
3 . N OTES OF CAU T I O N
cational institutions where entry is based more on
the capacity to pay or donate large sums of money
than on merit. In recent years we have also seen the
emergence of small time fly-by-night operators.
They claim to charge lower fees and set up illegal
institutions that are sometimes housed in one-room
s t r u c t u r e s, like a dental college we came across
near Agra,in the northern state of Uttar Pradesh.
Many private institutions in  states like Bihar do not
even have the minimum number of teaching faculty
required by government rules.Whenever there is an
o f ficial inspection, they simply hire extra profes-
sors who disappear afterwards.
In clear violation of a Supreme Court order
passed in the mid-1990s, some private institutions
allocate places beyond stipulated limits to those who
have money instead of giving opportunities to meri-
torious students.There were reports that during the
most recent admissions to a private medical college
in the southern Indian city of Manipal, the highest
bidder paid Rs 26 lakhs ($58,000) for a place.
Even in government institutions, fees are being
hiked to such an extent that meritorious students
from poorer families are finding it harder to pursue
their studies. Universities are now expected to raise
25 percent of their recurring expenditure through
fees and other methods. We found that due to a
c a s h - c r u n c h , many government-run institutes were
unable to upgrade their laboratories and syllabi.
Has commercialization improved the quality of
education?
N o.The overall quality of private educational
institutions is abysmal, though there may be a
few exceptions like the Pai group of educational
centres operating in southern India. Our own stu-
dies found that some promoters of private edu-
cational institutes openly violate the laws of the
l a n d , primarily through the fact that they run their
institutions in the name of trusts, meaning without
Total population 
(millions, 1999): 998
Adult literacy 
rate (1998): 55.7%
Gross enrolment 
ratio (1997):
- Primary education: 100%
- Secondary education: 49%
- Tertiary education: 7%
Students enrolled in 
private primary and 
secondary schools 
(1997): 26.1%
Sources: World Bank, UNDP, OECD.
KEY FIGURES, INDIA
Against commercial education:students protest in New Delhi earlier this year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 37
YIN CHEONG CHENG
CENTRE FOR RESEARCHAND INTERNATIONAL COLLABORATION, HONG KONG INSTITUTE OF EDUCATION
Beyond e c o n o m i c s
Unless policymakers take a more all-round view of education,
they risk sending their countries down the wrong path
Over the past decade,educational change
in most countries has been driven by
one imperative:survival in the global
economy.This process has been parti-
cularly salient in the A s i a - P a c i fic region
following the drastic shock of the 1997 economic
d o w n t u r n . But in the current reform process,
marked by speeding commercialization and eco-
nomic preoccupations, other educational missions
are being ignored,and countries risk paying a high
price for their shortsightedness.
There’s no denying that economic considera-
tions are critical in today’s world.Students have to
acquire the knowledge and skills to survive and
compete in the global economy, especially one
which more than ever before prizes human capital.
A high-quality labour force gives nations a cutting
edge in global competition.Understandably, stres-
sing economic returns in the current educational
debate attracts private resources. But education
has other functions that are the indispensable corol-
lary of more balanced,equitable development.Th e y
deserve to be briefly explained.
The first is a social function: education has a
role to play in facilitating social mobility and brin-
ging about integration in often very diverse consti-
tuencies. It is at school that children learn how to
form a broader set of relationships, to live toge-
ther and become aware of belonging to a commu-
n i t y. Linked to this is education’s  political function:
schools are there to teach us civic attitudes, to make
us aware of our rights and responsibilities —in
e s s e n c e, to become responsible citizens.The task is
fundamental in light of democracy’s advance in so
many countries over the past decade or so. Then
there is education’s cultural function.Developing
creativity and aesthetic awareness, accepting other
traditions and belief systems while valuing our own
are all part of the path towards fulfillment. Finally,
education is a goal in and of itself. Schools help
children learn how to learn and play a pivotal role
in transferring knowledge from one generation to
E D U C AT I O N : THE LAST FRONTIER FOR PROFIT
the next. I believe that all these facets of learning are
critical for the long-term prosperity of our societies.
In our globalized, interdependent world, these func-
tions take on a more international character. Eve-
r y w h e r e, education has a role to play in eliminating
racial and gender biases, promoting global common
interests, movements for peace, and greater inter-
national understanding.
Rising above short-term pressures
to strike a harmonious balance
While education is widely recognized as the
spine of the learning society, the complexity lies in
striking a balance between these various functions.
The commercialization of education that we are
witnessing the world over inevitably pushes schools,
e d u c a t o r s,parents and policymakers to pursue short-
t e r m , market-driven outcomes. L a w y e r s, b a n k e r s
and businessmen have an increasingly high profile in
educational debates. Following Southeast A s i a ’s
downturn in 1997, they were influential in changing
the academic mindset. In little time, emphasis has
shifted from academic achievement to developing
communication skills, c r e a t i v i t y, a d a p t a b i l i t y. In and
of itself, this is not necessarily regrettable.The pro-
blem is that these skills are all perceived to be at the
service of a supreme economic value.
Sounder research will be required to analyze
and assess where the current trends are leading us.
It is increasingly recognized, h o w e v e r, that unless
economic growth is accompanied by good gover-
n a n c e, a fair sharing of benefit s, better social and
environmental protection and attention to culture,
it will, sooner or later, lead to unrest. It is through
education that this broad spectrum of concerns can
be nurtured. Po l i cymakers who have taken stock
of this holistic mission unfortunately represent a
minority in today’s educational debates and reforms.
Their foremost challenge is to manage commercia-
l i z a t i o n , to rise above short-term pressures and  to
take a more ethical stance towards education, a
long-term strategic view. ■
a profit motive. Despite making huge profits
through students fees, these private institutions
submit records showing that they are not making
any and claim that they’re re-investing the money
to set up more institutions.
What kind of public response has there been?
People are upset,but they don’t have a forum to
p r o t e s t .Apart from the left,even mainstream political
parties are not bothered about this.A large section of
the media has failed to take up the issue and
concerned students are not allowed to raise their
v o i c e. In fact, the government did not give permission
to the SFI to hold a rally on the issue in New Delhi
last September, but we organized demonstrations
in most state capitals. In November,we plan to mobi-
lize 100,000 students in Delhi to protest against the
commercialization of education. ■
UNESCO is being
looked upon 
as the forum
through which 
to promote 
and uphold the
primary and 
overriding
responsibility 
of the State, 
to ensure the
right to quality
education for all. 
Koichiro Matsuura,  Director-
General of UNESCO (1937-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
T
◗ E T H I C S
BY TIM CRABBE
PRINCIPLE LECTURER IN SPORT SOCIOLOGY AT BRITAIN’S
SHEFFIELD HALLAM UNIVERSITY
G a r l i c , knives and
b a n n e rs : f o o t b a l l ’s 
racist faces
The terraces of some of Europe’s biggest football clubs have become stomping grounds 
for racist abuse, though the problem stems far beyond match day
hree days into England’s new football
season and Patrick Vi e i r a , Fr a n c e ’s Wo r l d
Cup and Euro 2000 winning midfield
p l a y e r, is dismissed while playing for
Arsenal against Liverpool, earning his
second red card in as many matches.Th e
British press is quick to speculate that
he will quit the English game, invoking
the player’s own accusations that he has
been subject to “ r a c i s t ” intimidation from
players and officials alike. According to
Vieira, he is being singled out for abuse
not because he is black, but because he is
French—a complaint previously made
by expat footballers like Eric Cantona,
Frank Leboeuf and Emmanuel Petit.
Only months before, a defender playing
for West Ham faced disciplinary charges
after allegedly calling Vieira a “ Fr e n c h
p r a t ”and joking that “he could smell the
garlic”when the midfielder spat at him.
“What a load of nonsense,” commented
West Ham manager Harry Redknapp at
the time. “There is no way he should be
p u n i s h e d .What for? For having a joke?”
The true colours of fans
dancing with a swastika flag
In England, the cradle of football hoo-
l i g a n i s m , the debate over racism in foot-
ball has evolved.Overt racism among sup-
porters and abuse directed at black
p l a y e r s, both of which flourished in the
1970s and 1980s, have declined steeply in
recent years in the face of vociferous
public campaigning, though residual pre-
judices against foreign players have evi-
dently been unaffected. E l s e w h e r e, i n
c o n t r a s t ,much less trivial manifestations
of racism plague the game. Th r o u g h o u t
much of Europe, football grounds have
become hosts to deplorable displays of
supporters’ bigotry, providing outlets
through sporting rivalry to attitudes that
are either dormant or concealed in society
at large.
The recent conviction of Ricardo
Guerra for the murder of Aitor Zabaleta,a
Real Sociedad fan from Spain’s Basque
r e g i o n , is a case in point. Z a b a l e t a ’s death
came in the aftermath of the stoning of an
Atletico Madrid supporters’ bus after a cup
tie played in San Sebastian, during which
A t l e t i c o ’s notorious Bastion group of hoo-
l i g a n s,of which Guerra was a member,h a d
chanted “ F u e r a , fuera maricones, n e g r o s,
Va s c o s,C a t a l a n e s,f u e r a ,f u e r a ”(Get out,g e t
o u t ,q u e e r s,n i g g e r s,Basques and Catalans)
to the tune of the Spanish national anthem.
While the official line is that Zabaleta was
killed only because he followed a different
football team, the public perception of the
B a s t i o n ’s political sympathies was re-
enforced during the return game when they
were captured on film bouncing up and
down with a swastika fla g.
Several commentators have suggested
this racial hatred can be explained by the
i n fluence of neo-Nazi and neo-fascist
groups inside football grounds. A l o n g
with A t l e t i c o, extreme racism has
resurged among fans of Real Madrid and
Espanyol in Spain,Lazio and AC Milan in
38 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
English hooligans make themselves felt in Lille, France, during the 1998 World Cup.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Italy, Paris Saint-Germain in France and
Red Star Belgrade in Yu g o s l a v i a . In Italy,
U d i n e s e ’s attempts to sign the Je w i s h
player Ronnie Rosenthal were aban-
doned after anti-Semitic slogans were
daubed on the club’s office walls, while
Lazio fans unfurled a banner reading
“Auschwitz is your country, c r e m a t o r i a
your home” along with swastikas prior to
a game with local rival Roma.
The labelling of particular clubs or
fans as prototype fascists or racists,
h o w e v e r, is in fact deceptive.While Ger-
Cup Finals held in Italy in 1990, w h e n
Napoli fans abandoned the Italian
national team to support their local
Argentine hero Diego Maradona,“ u l t r a s ”
from northern Italy demonstrated their
hostility towards Maradona, Napoli and
the southern region by supporting any
team playing against A r g e n t i n a . As a
r e s u l t , the “ r a c i s t ”elements amongst nor-
thern fans had no problem cheering in
passionate support of the black A f r i c a n
team from Cameroon when they played
Argentina—the then embodiment of all
that the northerners detested.
Race as a weapon in the
arsenal of ritualized abuse
In short,the racism on display in Euro-
pean football matches is more often than
not dependent on the traditions and his-
toric rivalries within white fans’ cultures.
Here the concept of an “effective insult”
proves useful: fans will tend to use the
abuse that is most effective and pertinent,
in an effort to cause the most harm and
p r o v o c a t i o n . Supporters of English clubs
who have rivalries with clubs from Liver-
pool regularly sing “ I ’d rather be a Paki
than a scouse (Liverpudlian)” for the same
reasons Italian fans throughout the north
often refer to fans and players of southern
clubs such as Napoli as “ b l a c k s.” In each of
these cases, the effective insult is chosen on
the basis of racial outcasts despised by
both groups of fans, with the obvious aim
of making the insult as hurtful as possible.
To state a preference for the racial cate-
gory “ P a k i ” over the white identity of the
“ s c o u s e r ” might be seen to add venom to
the insult, while the association of sou-
thern Italians with “ b l a c k n e s s ” plays with
internal insecurities relating to the region’s
proximity to A f r i c a .
These insults only work because of the
stigma that these racial groups still suffer
in the minds of large swathes of white
European society. As such, race often
stands on the sidelines, ready to be mobi-
lized in circumstances where it is deemed
appropriate within the ritualized abuse of
a football game rather than forming the
political core of fans’ identities. The fact
that many of the Italian ultras’ chants are
adapted from traditional communist and
fascist songs is, in itself, no more evidence
of political sympathies than the extensive
use of hymn tunes among British fans is
evidence of ecclesiastical affil i a t i o n .
Comparisons between the insults
levelled in football grounds across the
world only goes to prove that racism
emerges against a backdrop of shared
prejudices among supporters. In Brazil,
for instance, where many fans are from
ethnic groups who are themselves mar-
ginalized and discriminated against, r a c i s t
abuse is rare (and is substituted by sexist
d e r i s i o n ) . In England, the success of black
players has shifted prejudice to the kind
of race-fuelled denigration mentioned
above or to the xenophobic “ h u m o u r ”
endured by Vi e i r a . In Eastern Europe,
and to some extent in Germany and Italy,
a comparative lack of black players has
left racist insults of these footballers as a
potent weapon in supporters’ armoury
of abuse.
The spectre of racism in the football
ground certainly is appalling,but its roots
lie neither in far-right factions nor in the
particular characteristics of fans. Vi o l e n t
footballing antagonism is the circumstance,
but European society is the cause. ■
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 39
Ducking the issue
FIFA’s Executive Committee responded to
the incidents in Spain and Italy by decla-
ring that it “vigorously condemns these
public demonstrations of racism. This type
of behaviour, whether visible on the pitch,
the terraces or outside the stadium,is unac-
ceptable.” While this may be a laudable
development, such statements do not dis-
guise the lack of action against football
administrators such as the president of the
Turkish team Tra b z o n s p o o r, Mehmet A l i
Yilmaz,who called the black English striker
Kevin Campbell a “cannibal” and “disco-
loured,” forcing him to go on strike before
he was transferred to the English team
Everton. ■
Trouble in
S t ra s b o u rg
For the manager and directors of
S t ra s b o u r g ’s Racing Club, the season
could not have started in a worse fashion.
Following a string of bad results, an estima-
ted 50 fans of the club in Fra n c e ’s A l s a c e -
L o r raine region barra c ked manager Claude le
Roy and grunted like monkeys at two of the
c l u b ’s African players. Days later, a wall of the
c l u b ’s stadium was adorned with a swa s t i k a
and the words “Le Roy, dirty Jew.” Th e
Racing directors immediately filed a com-
plaint for inciting racial hatred against the
suspected culprits, sparking an investigation
by local prosecutors. ■
many has one of the worst reputations
for far-right influence amongst its fans,
many claim that this image, fostered by the
German media,does not accurately refle c t
r e a l i t y. Professor Volker Rittner of the
Sports Sociology Institute in Cologne for
e x a m p l e,argues that “Nazi symbols have
a provocative role; they break down
t a b o o s.But the point is not political—it is
to get noticed and mentioned in Mon-
d a y ’s newspapers.” Even where there is
evidence of politically motivated racist
behaviour amongst fans, it is often uns-
t a b l e, contradictory and secondary to foot-
ball-related enmities. During the Wo r l d
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
◗ E T H I C S
BY TIM CRABBE
PRINCIPLE LECTURER IN SPORT SOCIOLOGY AT BRITAIN’S
SHEFFIELD HALLAM UNIVERSITY
A TRICOLOUR T R I U M P H ?
France’s recent footballing successes have been hailed as victories over racism,
but discrimination lingers on
Writing in the liberal English national
newspaper The Guard i a n after the
French World Cup victory in 1998, N i c k
Fraser suggested that “no man or woman
really believed in a multicultural Fr a n c e …
French people probably merely wanted
foreigners to be more like themselves.”
His remark seemed to fly in the face of
Fr a n c e ’s cup-winning exuberance.Just as
major sporting tournaments offer some of
the last spaces in which notions of identity
and nation can be ritually expressed and
c e l e b r a t e d , victory can also seem to
b r e a c h ,or even dissolve, racial differences
within a country.And the French national
t e a m ’s achievements in winning the Wo r l d
Cup and Euro 2000 were widely credited
as such a triumph over traditional, c u l t u-
rally homogenous nationalism.
The French national team which
achieved these feats displays an incredible
d i v e r s i t y,with many of its stars born outside
of metropolitan Fr a n c e, including Marcel
D e s a i l l y,Patrick Vieira and Lilian Th u r a m .
Others like Youri Djorkaeff,Thierry Henry,
the talismanic Zinedine Zidane and the
Championship Final scorers Sylvain Wi l-
tord and David Tr e z e g u e t ,would qualify as
what Fr a n c e ’s Jean Marie Le Pen,leader of
the extremist National Front party,w o u l d
call “ Français de souche récente,” m e a-
ning that such players are not “ r e a l ”
Frenchmen because their parents were
recent migrants.
French Sports Minister Marie
Georges Buffet stated in the aftermath of
the Euro 2000 victory that the multi-
ethnic side proved France had created a
harmonious society “that could do great
things together.”The prominent presence
of Arab and black citizens among the
celebrating crowds in the capital
appeared to back Buffet’s point, e s p e-
cially given that the French had pre-
viously suburbanized urban poverty and
largely confined its immigrant popula-
tions to the desolate b a n l i e u e ring sur-
rounding Paris.
Notions of diversity, h o w e v e r, can still
be seen as little more than a style of natio-
nalism that assimilates (rather than
excludes) newcomers and insists on one
universal sovereign identity.What mattered
in the victory party was that Arabs and
black 
citizens were cheering for a France whose
identity had already been secured in their
a b s e n c e. Deeper patterns of discrimina-
t i o n had certainly not been resolved.
Paris’ racially stratified geography was
once again apparent the morning after,a s
the same Arab and black citizens lauded as
symbols of a new united France returned
to their homes on the outskirts of the city.
M e a n w h i l e, the multicultural band of
players who won the Euro 2000 trophy
have now returned to luxury homes in
I t a l y, England and Germany where they
play their club football—managed by
white coaches,paid by white directors and
watched by white spectators.
The enduring stereotype
of brain versus brawn
The pretext for these sporting hierar-
chies may well be the culture of Europe’s
former colonial powers, in which white
settlers ruled indigenous “ c o l o u r e d ”p o p u-
lations on the basis of the supposedly
greater rationality of white people as
against the sensuality, lack of emotional
restraint or intelligence of the “ n a t i v e.”
The continuing power and resonance of
such notions were reflected in the inter-
pretation of the outcome of Euro 2000
by the left-wing French daily, L i b é r a t i o n,
which claimed that “ Fr a n c e ’s victory, i t s
s e c r e t , is without doubt based on the win-
ning combination of two styles—physical
and technical.” S a d l y, the metaphor ‘ p h y-
sical = black, technical = white’ is o n l y
thinly disguised within such analyses,
which do little to move beyond the racial
differences implicit within the concept of
40 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
G a r l i c , knives and banners :
Victory euphoria in France at the end of the 1998 World Cup.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
T
S I G N S O F T H E T I M E S ◗
LUCÍA IGLESIAS KUNTZ
UNESCO Courier JOURNALIST
The price of a good re a d
The price of books in recent years has pitted small independent bookshops against 
the big chains, supermarkets and the Internet. But what is in the customer’s best interest?
he end-of-year holidays are nearing. I m a-
gine you have decided to give books as
presents to all your friends and relatives,
who are interested in just about every-
t h i n g. The decision is made, but where
should you buy them? The standard
choice is your local bookshop.There you
will probably find a professional book-
seller who will be able to recommend the
most interesting books for each of your
f r i e n d s, tell the difference between a
paperback and a pocket edition, a n d
order from the publisher or distributor
any book he or she does not have in stock.
If you live in Fr a n c e, S p a i n ,G e r m a n y
or any of the other six European Union
countries that have a single-price policy
for books, it will cost you exactly the same
whatever bookshop or department store
you go into looking for the cheapest price.
And if you are a good customer, t h e
bookseller may give you a five percent
discount,which is usually the maximum
allowed under the fixed-price laws.
This system is founded on two basic
p r i n c i p l e s : that the same book should
cost the same wherever it is bought,w h e-
ther in the centre of Berlin or the only
shop in a tiny Bavarian village, and that
unlike shoes and clothes, the price will
stay the same all year round because sea-
sonal discounts are not allowed. Under
this arrangement, the publisher usually
sets the price of the book, giving the book-
seller a profit margin of about 30 percent.
But if you live in Belgium, S w e d e n
or the United Kingdom (where book
prices were deregulated in 1995),you will
find big differences from shop to shop
because the booksellers themselves can
set the prices.Although this seems at fir s t
sight to benefit the reading customer, t h e
book trade is divided over it. In a world of
disappearing national borders, transna-
tional authorities such as the European
Union are therefore seeking a degree of
standardization which, while obeying the
laws of competition,is fair to everyone.
The advocates of the fixed-price
system hold up Germany as an example.
With its 7,000 or so bookshops and more
than 1,200 publishers, it is one of the
driving forces in the print word.Or Fr a n c e
where, unlike the film industry’s depen-
dence on government aid, publishing is
s e l f - s u f fic i e n t . In both countries, all those
involved in the book trade—authors,
p u b l i s h e r s,distributors and booksellers—
ardently defend the fixed-price system.
Similar attitudes can be found in Spain,
where the government has deregulated
discounts on textbooks for the current
school year, unleashing noisy protests
from writers,publishers and booksellers.
The French publishers’ magazine L i v r e s
H e b d o reports that in the United Kingdom,
where both systems have operated over the
past decade,five years of deregulation have
seen the price of books rise 16 percent, f a r
more than the nine per-
cent rise in the cost-of-
l i v i n g. One result of this,
the magazine says, h a s
been increased book sales
in bookshop chains and
department stores, w h e r e
the person who sells you
a book one day may be
switched to the cosmetics
counter the next.
Under a free-pricing
s y s t e m , the law of supply
and demand will imme-
diately affect prices, s i n c e
publishers mark up their
best-sellers to compen-
sate for losses from the
discounts handed out by
s u p e r m a r k e t s.The temp-
tation becomes strong
just to publish things that
will sell easily and
q u i c k l y, with a resulting
loss of diversity. F u r t h e r-
m o r e,for every 200 books
published there is rarely
more than one best-seller,
and it is not unusual for
these to keep on turning
up in the catalogues of
the same handful of
p u b l i s h e r s — n a m e l y
those who can afford to
pay huge advances to the
most famous authors and
buy the most expensive
foreign rights.
“A system where
there is competition over
prices only works for the best-selling
b o o k s : the rest are seen as ‘bad quality’,”
says Markus Gerlach, a German expert
on book prices. “This argument is quite
unacceptable when it comes to a book
of poetry or an essay.”
Of course books are not the only pro-
ducts with fixed prices. In virtually every
c o u n t r y, c i g a r e t t e s,medicine and newspa-
pers are as well.“Books are a cultural pro-
duct and as such they deserve every pro-
tection we can give them, especially as
they are now threatened by things such as
pirating and illegal copying,”says J.R y b a ,
who runs a bookshop in Israel.
But let’s continue our book-buying
expedition.If you have a credit card and
an Internet connection, you can order
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 41
Horizons widen with a book on a Parisian rooftop.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
N
your books from one of the many online
bookshops, which will send the books to
your home. You will probably have to
pay the  shipping charges and trust the
e f fic i e n cy of the postal system, but the
advantages are clear:
you can buy the
books without leaving
your home or offic e
from businesses that
are open round the
clock every day of the
week.And in theory,
as in Jorge Luis
Borges’ Library of
Babel, all the world’s
books are just a
mouse-click away.
And what about
the prices? H a r r y
Potter and the Philoso-
p h e r’s Stone, the fir s t
book in British author
J. K . R o w l i n g ’s series
which is enchanting
the young and not-so-young on every conti-
n e n t , costs 5.79 euros in France (roughly
$ 4 . 8 0 ) , 9.71 in Spain (for the Spanish edi-
tion—it costs 10.28 in Catalan) and 14.31 in
G e r m a n y, according to data compiled at
the end of October 2000 from various
online bookshops.All these countries have
a fixed-price system,which does not neces-
sarily lead to cheap books. On the other
h a n d , a book can cost
less in Marseilles,
where prices are fix e d ,
than in Brussels,w h e r e
they are not.
Alongside super-
m a r k e t s, actual and
virtual bookshops,
there is a third way to
buy a book. If you
belong to a book club,
such as France Loisirs
in Fr a n c e, the Círculo
de Lectores in Spain
or Bertelsmann Buch-
club in Germany (all
of which, i n c i d e n t a l l y,
are owned by Bertels-
m a n n ) , you can get
quite cheap hardback
books to give as gifts.But you will have to
forget about the new Harry Potter book,
the last winner of the Goncourt Prize or a
new revised translation of Don Quixote,
since such clubs have to wait at least nine
months before they can offer the latest
books for sale. Their catalogues are slim
t o o, because publishers are unwilling to
take the risk of releasing a book unless
sales are pretty much guaranteed. S u c h
clubs may sell carefully chosen books quite
c h e a p l y,but they can prove an annoyance
after a while because you have to buy a
minimum number over periods of up to
two years.
L a s t l y, the other factor that can make
your holiday purchases cheaper or dearer
is tax. If you live in Sweden or Denmark,
book prices may not be very expensive,
but you will have to add a 25 percent sales
t a x , something that does not exist in the
United Kingdom, Ireland and Norway.
So what is the best way to buy your
books? There is no single answer.Do you
want to give best-sellers, books about
current affairs, reference books, original
works or translations? Do you want prose
or poetry? Full or abridged versions?
Complete works or anthologies? Hard-
back or paperback?
Whatever price you pay, dear reader,
the future of books is in your hands.
Enjoy them. ■
42 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
Barely a whisper in Guilin,China.
“Books are a 
cultural
product and 
as such 
they deserve 
every 
protection 
we can 
give them”
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
C O N N E X I O N S ◗
BY IVAN BRISCOE
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
All eyes on the re a l i t y
g a m e
A new television genre has won
huge audiences across 
the world. Despised by some,
adored by others, reality shows
play upon the paradoxes of
modern society—but at what cost?
ine people are travelling across Spain in
a bus.Ten Poles will be locked in a house
in Wa r s a w.Germans have been invited to
slim and earn their lost weight in gold.A
seemingly mundane set of events, w a t-
ched over by cameras and transformed
into primetime television by the fact that
everyone must work together though
only one can win.
Reality may have perplexed philoso-
phers and scientists for centuries, but in
the jargon of modern-day television it
has become a surefire way to entice the
restless viewer.Across Eastern and We s-
tern Europe, North and South America,
programmes devised on the basis that a
“ r e a l ” set of events involving “ o r d i n a r y ”
people is unfolding—with cash prizes—
have defied the industry’s rules of thumb.
Place ten unknown men and women in a
locked villa in Spain under the gaze of 29
c a m e r a s, and the result is unexpected: 1 2
million people,a third of the nation’s popu-
l a t i o n , tuned in to watch.
Everywhere the small-screen formula
of constant surveillance, m o n e y - d r i v e n
competition and confinement has tra-
v e l l e d , it has triumphed. In the United
S t a t e s,S u r v i v o r—featuring 16 contestants
marooned on a sweltering Malaysian
island and forced to eat grubs—simply
overwhelmed all other summer pro-
g r a m m i n g,picking up 50 million viewers.
A sister show in Brazil did likewise. S o m e
15 countries, m e a n w h i l e, have adapted
the Dutch programme Big Brother, l a u n-
ched in 1999, in which ten people inhabit
a house, c o n v e r s e, c o m p l o t , and with the
help of viewers’ votes thin down over
several months to a final winner.An esti-
mated 300 million people have now seen
the show; those veterans of the Spanish
villa are already stars, contributing their
particular mystique to the market of cele-
brity tie-ins through a video-game and
auction of their favourite blankets.
“ We created a new genre where we
proved that ordinary people can be very
interesting as characters, and where next-
door people can do much more than eve-
ryone expected they could,”declares Jo h n
De Mol, the Dutch head of Endemol
Entertainment and inventor of Big Brother.
For muttering critics and offended
b i s h o p s, h o w e v e r, this new genre was a
case of television sinking to a misanthropic
l o w.While some agreed with De Mol that
his show was consensual, competitive fun
and excellent fodder for what A m e r i c a n
producers term the water cooler—the place
in the office where staff gossip—opponents
found only voyeurism and degradation.I n
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 43
The Red Room in the U.S. Big Brother house, where contestants communicate 
via camera with the programme’s producers.
N
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
G e r m a n y,government ministers suggested
the programme could be declared uncons-
t i t u t i o n a l . Bernard Crick, biographer of
the author George Orwell, despaired at a
f u l filled prophecy.People “are simply depo-
liticized by cultural debasement, d u m b e d
d o w n , kept from even thinking of deman-
ding fair shares,”he wrote of Orwell’s satire
in 1 9 8 4, the novel that invented Big Brother.
The show, he suggested, offered the same
glitzy “ p r o l e f e e d .”
Intimate troubles under 
the glare of spotlights
So many viewers and such attacks
would suggest that cameras and humans
have been striking up a new relationship.
“ Viewers come from all social classes,e v e n
culturally very high ones,” argues Ignacio
B e l , a professor in information rights in
M a d r i d . “It comes down to a morbid fas-
c i n a t i o n , to an unhealthy curiosity.”Wh e n
the American channel Court TV briefly
ran a show in which criminals confessed
their murders on camera, the concerns
seemed fully justifie d .Watch Big Brother,
h o w e v e r, and privacy fears may be
a l l a y e d . For a start, the participants w a n t
to be there: their fear is not exposure but
a n o n y m i t y, a kind of individual fade-out.
And though much of the appeal centres
on the promise of spying a saucy
moment—sex is always being talked
a b o u t , though rarely had—the truth is
that the viewer’s diet is less salacious. I n
the British version, contestants overslept,
tended chickens, photocopied their ana-
t o m y, and decried the utter tedium of
living on television without watching tele-
v i s i o n . Rather than intrusive, the antics
were just excruciatingly banal.
But look again, and the
same lack of action can take
on a different meaning.
Nothing much happens, n o -
one emits an even remotely
interesting opinion, but the
tell-tale reality TV gesture,t h e
quick eye-fli c k , registers the
nearest camera.Each conver-
s a t i o n , vacuous as it may be,
treads a perilous line between
s e l f - e x p r e s s i o n , i m p r e s s i n g
housemates (who nominate
each other for eviction), a n d
currying favour with millions
of sofa-bound viewers. Th e
effect is akin to a public rela-
tions assault course. “ I t
appealed to the psychologist
in me,” says 39-year-old Nidi
Etim from Manchester,
E n g l a n d .“ Watching how they
all interacted, who were the natural lea-
d e r s, how they coped with the nomina-
t i o n s.”
At the heart of reality shows’ popu-
larity are exactly these interpersonal
c o n flicts—the same force which animates
traditional drama, soap-operas and talk-
s h o w s. Indeed talk-shows are among the
closest relatives of reality T V, a l l o w i n g
“ o r d i n a r y ” people to thrash out their
most intimate troubles under the glare of
studio lights. But the new genre has a
different focus. Cameras are mounted
on an island or in a house, and a mini-
society is invited in. Viewers pry on
e v e n t s, monitor reactions, assess beha-
v i o u r. Instead of an individual’s tale, or a
daily life, the show is about the society’s
e v o l u t i o n , the disintegration of an artifi-
cial assembly via a period of co-operation
towards a final prize-winner.
“ The best mixture of fiction and reality
that has existed until now,”insists Elizabeth
L o p e z , producer of Gran Hermano f o r
S p a i n ’s Te l e 5 .The shows may be contrived
(the producers of the U. S.Big Brother t r i e d
to bribe dull contestants $50,000 into
making way for a “ s e x y ”n e w c o m e r ) ,but as
Lopez says, the participants “write their
own scripts.”For many viewers,the struggle
is all too recognizable. It is the balance
between staying on the show,getting others
off the show, and preserving at least a
façade of solidarity. It is a “ s c r i p t ” that the
modern workplace and family are founded
upon—battling to be first but staying
p o p u l a r.In Internet chat forums,the debate
centres on who is sincere, who is “ p l a y i n g
Miss Cool,” who is the villain: in short,
how each person responds to the chal-
l e n g e. Add cameras and excessive stage 
m a n a g e m e n t ,says social psychologist Peter
Lunt (see interview opposite), and the
stakes get even higher. Contestants are
not just playing with each other, but with
the very nature of living in a world domi-
nated by the emotions, language and
images coined by the mass media.
With it has come a new kind of cele-
brity. Graduates from the school of 24-
hour surveillance such as Holland’s Bart
Spring and U.S. Survivor victor Richard
H a t c h , a gay corporate trainer, h a v e
soared into fame’s dizzy heights—Spring
has even launched his own logoed clo-
thing range. Rather than offer perfect
teeth,the new stars glitter with ordinari-
n e s s : they are people one could know
before fame won them the services of
bodyguards and image consultants. N o n -
stop availability of many shows on the
Internet,gossip sites, public voting, even
the chance to e-mail participants, r e i n-
forces this democratic attraction. R e a-
lity TV appears to be under viewers’
control even as it trumpets media power.
The cynical appeal 
of a staged life
Following its early successes, the mix
of ceaseless documentary and game-show
is spawning in a frenzy, c o n fining volun-
teers in buses (De Mol’s new show T h e
B u s) , locking them to possible mates
(Chains of Lov e,De Mol again) or chasing
them round cities (the extremely bizarre
game at www. r e a l i t y r u n . c o m ) .“Any given
success is overproduced like mad by imi-
t a t o r s,”says Todd Gitlin,a leading thinker
on the media from New York University.
All harmless, say the show’s produ-
c e r s.No blood is spilt, and no-one ends up
poorer. Yet the loops connecting televi-
sion and society are difficult to untangle.
It may be fun to watch men and women
stumble through the hardships with a fat
lens over their shoulder, but is this not a
case of television spreading its empire?
And in so doing, is television imposing its
own shorthand on the “real” world—its
t y p o l o g i e s,quick characterizations,g a m e -
show dynamics and ad breaks?
“I suspect that the greatest fla v o r i n g
of life that comes from these shows is a
kind of knowing cy n i c i s m ,” says Gitlin,
“an embrace of the idea that everything
is staged, that feelings are shallow, t h a t
the difference between life and simula-
tion is insignific a n t .” Not a voyeuristic
hell then, but a televised format to daily
l i f e : that may be reality T V ’s main mes-
s a g e. O r, as one man said of his Big Bro-
t h e r h o u s e m a t e s :“ w e ’re so close . . . w e l l ,
I feel we are.” ■
44 The UNESCO Courier - November 2000
Big Brother fans in Cologne, Germany, welcome their
favourite contestants back to “real”life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
C O N N E X I O N S ◗
INSIDE THE EMOTION MAC H I N E
Peter Lunt, a social psychologist at University College London and expert on the impact 
of television, pins the vogue for “reality” on changes in public emotional life
Do you see reality shows as a new tele-
vision genre, or something that has
evolved from previous programmes?
Reality television seems to have two dif-
ferent origins.One of them is the changing
form of the talk-show, which from a very
gentle format based on celebrities’ public
relations evolved via presenters like Phil
Donahue and Oprah Winfrey in the
United States into something that shifted
interest from the everyday life of a cele-
brity to celebrating everyday lives.
Take the programma Queen for a Day
as an example. This was a gameshow in
the U. S. in the 1960s for middle-class hou-
s e w i v e s,who would file in the studios and
be selected on the basis of their hard-
s h i p s : the people who had the most heart-
rending and difficult stories got to tell
them to the audience, there was a vote,
and the most worthy person was crowned
Queen for a Day, and given all sorts of
presents. It was a momentary reversal of
social status, like putting the ordinary in
the position of the king, which was done
in medieval fairs and tournaments.
But to understand reality television, y o u
also have to look at another genre, w h i c h
is fly-on-the-wall documentary. In the
1960s, especially in Britain, this formed
part of a cultural trend towards repre-
senting ordinary lives in cinema and tele-
v i s i o n .And what you see there is a move-
ment from celebration to something
closer to scrutiny or surveillance.
But in contrast to fly-on-the-wall docu-
m e n t a r y, the presence of cameras in these
new shows is absolutely crucial.
That is very important. Compared to pre-
vious shows, the new programmes have a
much more managed feel.Jerry Springer [ a
U. S. talk-show] is a good example of this
f o r m a t .A first person comes on and is given
lots of time to discuss an intimate problem—
everything is quite calm.Then there’s a gra-
dual build-up of tension as other people
are levered into the process.Then the people
who come much later get much less time,
leading much more intensely to an emo-
tional eruption.The idea is that we’ve lost
the ability to express ourselves,and that it’s
only in these carefully structured and
managed public spaces that we can do this.
You can see similar structuring elements in
other reality shows.There is the inevitability
of voting, an underlying push in the pro-
cess that is highly ritualized.
A re you saying it is increasingly difficult to
e x p ress emotions without some kind of
intervention?
I’m not making radical arguments that
w e ’re completely transformed in our
emotional life, though some thinkers have
argued just that.The most I’d want to say
is that this new mode of public expression
and scrutiny of emotions is of central
importance to how we think about our-
selves and experience our emotions.Th e
appeal of these programmes is very much
based on that.
How do you explain the success of these
shows in so many different countries?
I am inclined to link this to the globalization
of culture.The new kinds of global social
relations are precisely formulated through
m e d i a t i o n , through business, t h r o u g h
t r a v e l , and are not grounded in the tradi-
tional collective social forms. The same
goes for work,which is no longer a life-long
career but requires fle x i b i l i t y,a d a p t a b i l i t y
and the construction of teamwork within
o r g a n i z a t i o n s.What we now know is that
we all live in these sorts of artific i a l l y
constructed relations—which are not arti-
ficial anymore,but have become our reality.
How do you interpret the connection bet-
ween these pro g rammes and new tech-
nologies, many of which seem to under-
mine people’s privacy?
There’s been a lot of vague talk recently
around issues of privacy. In the case of e-
c o m m e r c e, for instance,everyone knows
that companies have a lot more informa-
tion about them. So there’s something
being worked through here about this
extraordinary explosion of information
about individuals, and what this implies
for how they can live and be private,
expressive individuals.The programmes
stand I think as a metaphor for that—
and no more. The shows work because
they push these buttons, though they defi-
nitely don’t provide any interesting ana-
lysis of the question. ■
November 2000 - The UNESCO Courier 45
All eyes on the reality game
In Germany, Jana and Juergen go to their bedroom for the first time in the Big Brother house.
INTERVIEW BY I. B.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The Unesco Courier - November 2000
◗ T A L K I N G T O . . .
“When you write, you give your version of reality.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 47
M aryse
C o n d é :
g rand dame of
Caribbean litera t u re
w h i t e.Then when I went to France I dis-
covered that the colour of my skin
meant something. It was not an acci-
dent that I was black.There was a deep
difference between me and the people
whose skin was white. I had to go to
Africa to discover the meaning and
importance of that difference.
EN:And what did you discover?
M C : At the beginning I thought the dif-
ference was that black people had a
common culture that was different from
the culture of French people. I believed
that all black people were united by a
common origin, a common history. We
were basically one people divided by the
evils of slavery. I , who was born in Gua-
d e l o u p e, was separated from the people
in Guinea, where I was in A f r i c a ,s i m p l y
because of the slave trade.
EN:Do you think differently now?
M C : I made an important discovery in
A f r i c a : I did not share the same lan-
guage as the people in Guinea. We did
not eat the same food—this may seem
trivial to you,but it is important.We did
not dress the same way,we did not enjoy
the same type of music, we did not share
the same religion. In a few months, I
found myself terribly isolated. I could
not even communicate with my Gui-
nean husband. So I made a second dis-
c o v e r y :r a c e, in fact, is not the essential
f a c t o r.What is important is culture.As I
did not share the culture of the Gui-
nean people, of the African people, I
left A f r i c a ,a n d , as a result, my marriage
e n d e d .
E N :Then would it be fair to say that cultu-
rally there are now more similarities bet-
ween you and your husband, R i c h a rd
P h i l c o x , though he is white and British,
than there were between you and your firs t
h u s b a n d , though he was black and African? 
MC: When I met Richard twenty years
ago, I was in my period of political acti-
vism and I could not see myself with a
white man.My children,also, were very
nationalistic and so they were shocked
and disturbed that I would be involved
with a white man.But eventually I came
to understand that the colour of one’s
skin does not matter. I found that a white
man was closer to me than my first hus-
N:I was very moved by a talk
you gave two years ago about
g rowing up in Guadeloupe
and thinking of yourself as no
d i f f e rent from a Fre n c h
person. Could you talk about
why it was important for you
to go to Africa?
M C : E l i z a b e t h , I remember when I took
you to a restaurant in Guadeloupe how
surprised and shocked you were to see
that all the cooks and waiters were
w h i t e,French people.So imagine what it
was like growing up in Guadeloupe
some years back. The teachers in the
schools were Fr e n c h . The priests, w h e n
we went to Mass with our families, w e r e
w h i t e. We lived in a completely white,
French environment. It seemed normal
to me. I did not ask any questions. O f
c o u r s e, when I looked at my face in the
mirror I could see that it was black, b u t
for me, colour was totally unimportant.
I felt I was exactly like the people
around me, that is to say, French and
The celebrated author speaks
openly of her new book, passion
and politics with Elizabeth
Nunez, a leading literary light
from Trinidad
E
Elizabeth Nunez.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The Unesco Courier - November 2000
Maryse Condé: g rand dame
of Caribbean litera t u re
b a n d ,even closer to me than the majority
of the people I knew. It is a matter of
u n d e r s t a n d i n g : in a word, l o v e. M a r r i a g e
should not be viewed as part of a political
a g e n d a . It concerns the feelings and per-
sonal choices of two people.
EN: To return to the time when you left
A f r i c a , did you go back to Guadeloupe or
to France?
MC: One has to make a living, so I went
to Fr a n c e, though it was difficult there for
me to find a job. But in France I
immersed myself in the Guadeloupean
and Martiniquan society living as a
person in exile. Five years later, I went
back to Guadeloupe.
E N : So what are your thoughts now about
Africa? Do you sometimes feel ashamed of
Africa when you hear stories of the cor-
ruption there? I often think that a cruel
j o ke is being played on us today. Just as we
a re beginning to re s t o re our pride in our
rich African heritage, we are being bom-
b a rded with media reports about the cor-
ruption that seems to be rampant in A f r i c a .
MC: I lived for twelve years in Africa.I
must confess they were the most diffic u l t
years of my life. I was in Guinea and
G h a n a . One cannot deny the corruption
of the régimes there.The people in those
regions are suffering from the evils of
their rulers. They are dying of hunger
and disease.We have to face the fact that
there is a lot of evil and hardship in
A f r i c a . But it should not lead us to
conclude that Africa is inferior. It took
years for European countries to arrive at
d e m o c r a cy. Even now many of them
have not achieved it.Fr a n c e, for example,
is constantly being ripped apart by strikes
and riots. So why should we be ashamed
of the problems of Africa? They are
aggravated by neocolonialism, by the
lack of education for the people. Th i s
situation is the consequence of many
years of colonialism, of independence
that happened under the worst possible
conditions. So I am not ashamed at all.
Africa is trying hard to find solutions. I
believe that one day it will.
E N : In your novel The Last of the African
K i n g s you seem to satirize those middle-
class African Americans who speak only in
glowing terms about the African people
and are critical of those who focus on
the corruption that exists there.You wro t e
about a fictitious “ p restigious black col-
lege in Atlanta where duty towards one’s
race was taught as devoutly as science
and litera t u re.”
M C : Those African Americans who think
this way are simply trying to find a way
to hide their deep inferiority complex.
They are ashamed of Africa as it is today,
and they prefer to lie about the corrup-
tion and evil there. Let’s face it:Africa
has been robbed of its grandeur, of its
p o w e r, of its magnific e n c e. If we keep
having the kind of discourse that
conceals these painful facts, we will have
an incomplete view of Africa.It is time
we realize that we have a duty towards
the suffering of our people. I am not
interested in fighting for reparation for
slavery or for financial aid. I am fig h t i n g
Leaving the church in Sainte-Luce, Martinique. Taken at the start of 20th century.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 49Octo
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
M C :N o,not really. It would be too easy to
say that I am writing to educate my
p e o p l e.For the early generation of writers,
like Aimé Césaire, that was their goal—
t e a c h i n g, writing for their people. Fo r
m y s e l f, for my generation, we are much
more modest.We are writing to make the
world understandable to us first of all,
and if it is understandable to us, p e r h a p s
others will understand the world better.
E N : Is this why you do not write your
books in Creole? A c c o rding to some intel-
lectuals like Patrick Chamoiseau in Mar-
tinique, as Caribbean writers we should
write our stories in Creole, the language
of the majority of the people in the Carib-
bean.
M C : I refuse to accept that kind of dicho-
tomy between French and Creole. As I
like to say,Maryse Condé does not write
in French or Creole.Maryse Condé writes
in Maryse Condé.Each of us has to find a
v o i c e, a way of expressing the emotions,
the inner impressions that we have,and to
do that we should use all the languages
that are at our disposal. In my last novel,
Célanire cou-coupé, there is a glossary at
the end of the book. In it you will fin d
words in African languages, in Creole lan-
g u a g e s, in Spanish. In order to express
the story I wanted to tell, in the manner I
w a n t e d , I had to use many resources.Th a t
kind of narrow choice between Fr e n c h
and Creole is a political choice. In politics
it is necessary to speak in the language
that can be best understood by our
p e o p l e, that is closest to our people, b u t
when we write, we should be totally free
to choose the medium that is best suited
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:         Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
NUNEZ IN 
FULL BLOOM
“Still waters run deep.”The worn expres-
sion takes on a polished gleam with Eli-
zabeth Nunez, who sends readers reeling
with her latest book, Bruised Hibiscus, i n
which she reveals the pain and vengeance
of two women who dare to defy the political
and cultural taboos of colonial Trinidad in the
1 9 5 0 s.The dizzying force of the novel seems
at odds with the author’s privileged upbrin-
ging in Trinidad and now tenured position as
English professor and director of the Black
Writers’ Institute at Medgar Evers College in
New Yo r k .At the age of 56,Nunez appears to
use her own security as a springboard–ra t h e r
than refuge–to explore life’s passions.
In addition to her three novels and scholarly
publications, Nunez also contributes to the
l i t e rary world as director of the National
Black Writers’ Conference, which aims to
improve opportunities for authors of colour,
especially those from her beloved Carib-
bean. ■
● When Rocks Dance
(Ballantine, 1988)
● Beyond the Limbo Silence
(Seal,1998)
● Bruised Hibiscus
(Seal,2000) 
to find a solution that I can give to the
people of Africa who are in despair, w h o
need to find a way to restore faith in
t h e m s e l v e s. To quote [Jamaican black
nationalist] Marcus Garvey, “I would
like to teach the black man to find beauty
in himself.” The problem for me is not
fighting white people who are bad and
e v i l , but fighting our own people who
are bad and evil.
E N : Yet you write a lot about slavery,
which I find unusual for a Caribbean writer.
Caribbean people seem to sweep such
stories under the rug.We seem to want to
think well of the “mother country,” of the
Europeans. Recently, a British expatriate
reviewer in Trinidad, bristling under the
criticism of colonialism in my latest novel
Bruised Hibiscus, implied that I had bitten
the hand that had fed me. I was shocked
by the silence that followed her review,
even from my family. No one stood up to
say the obvious—that it was I who had fed
the British through slavery and colonia-
lism. What do you hope to achieve with
the stories you tell about slavery?
MC: People often ask me for whom am
I writing.The answer is I am writing for
myself. I write about slavery,Africa,the
condition of black people throughout
the world because I want to order my
t h o u g h t s, to understand the world,and to
be at peace with myself. I write to try to
find answers to the questions I ask
myself. Writing for me is a type of the-
rapy, a way to be safe and sound.
E N : So you don’t have an instructive goal
in mind?
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Maryse Condé: g rand dame
of Caribbean litera t u re
to our desires and aspirations.
E N :And for you, is that language Fre n c h ?
M C :My Fr e n c h , my own brand of Fr e n c h .
It is not the language you hear in Fr a n c e.
It is a combination of the language of a
person born in Guadeloupe,who listens to
the many different sounds of language,
and my own personal language.
E N : So what makes someone an authentic
Caribbean writer?
MC: I hate the word authentic. Here, I
a m ,Maryse Condé, born in Guadeloupe,
having lived in Africa and Paris,and now
living and working in New York. Here
you are, Elizabeth Nunez, born in Tri-
n i d a d , working and living for most of
your life in New Yo r k . We are both
authentic Caribbean writers. It is a ques-
tion of a personal choice, how we relate
to our mother country in the Caribbean,
how we see our place in the world,how
we see ourselves and who we are.
EN: Yet I sometimes think that because I
live outside of the Caribbean, people there
think either I have lost the right to write
about the Caribbean or that I have been
away too long to be able to write authen-
tically about it.Do you ever experience a
similar anxiety?
M C : What does it mean to write authen-
tically about the Caribbean? When you
w r i t e, you give your version of reality. I
am never anxious to justify myself to the
p u b l i c. If they believe that I am not a
true Caribbean writer, t h a t ’s fair enough,
but I do believe that I have all the right to
speak about Guadeloupe and that I am a
t o t a l , genuine Guadeloupean writer.
E N : But do you think there is a distinctive
Caribbean literature?
M C : Ye s, but it is difficult to define.
Edwidge Danticat [a young Haitian
author living in New York] is writing an
aspect of Caribbean literature.Yo u ,E l i-
zabeth, are writing an aspect of Carib-
bean literature. I am writing an aspect of
Caribbean literature and the people who
are writing at home, who never leave
home—Patrick Chamoiseau for
example—they are writing an aspect of
Caribbean literature. The totality of all
these different voices compose a sym-
phony which is Caribbean literature. I am
not going to define it because it is too
c o m p l e x , too plural, too changing to have
only one narrow definition.
E N : Some people label me a feminist
writer because of the strong female cha-
racters in my novels. But the truth is that
I don’t deliberately try to create strong
women.My characters are patterned after
the women who have influenced my life:
those who refused to see themselves as
victims and took charge of their lives.T h e re
are also very strong female characters in
your novels.Would you say you are a femi-
nist writer? 
M C : My answer is similar to yours. I was
educated by a strong mother and a strong
g r a n d m o t h e r. My sisters are strong. A l l
the women I knew in Guadeloupe were
s t r o n g. They triumphed over the condi-
tions that limited them. My books are a
r e flection of what I see in life. I don’t think
I am a feminist. I write about what I know.
EN:I loved your novel, Windward Heights.
It was liberating to see Emily Bro n t ë ’s classic
work through the eyes of a black cast of cha-
ra c t e rs. You effectively dismantled ra c i s t
theories that would dispute our common
h u m a n i t y. Was this your intention or did
you have more personal reasons for wri-
ting your novel?
M C : Somebody gave me Emily Brontë’s
Wuthering Heights when I was about 15 and
was still living in Guadeloupe. I was a very
sombre child,a very lonely child.My mother
died when I was very young and for years I
tried to reconnect with her. I looked for her
e v e r y w h e r e, in nature,e v e r y w h e r e.When I
read Wuthering Heights, I felt it was written
for me. I ident i fied completely with Heath-
c l i f f’s pass i o n
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George’s Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
Gordon & Gotch Australia Pty. Ltd., Private Bag 290, Burwood VIC 3125 .
Fax: 03 9888 8561
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Partner Press, 11 rue Charles Parenté, B-1070 Brussels.
Fax: (32 2) 556 41 46/Tel.: (32 2) 556 41 40/partner press@ampnet.be
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: UNES CO O f fice, 8 Po o rvi Marg, Vasant Vihar, New Delhi 110 0 57
Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg, Ballard
Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Editions Le Printemps Ltée., 4 Route du Club, Va c o a s .
Fax: 686 7302. 
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
UNES CO Etxea, Alda Urquijo 60, Ppal. Dcha., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: Distriplumes, Apartado 49232, Colinas Bello Monte, 10 4 2
A Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 979 8 36 0
UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce C/C
Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 28 6 0 326 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
November 2000 - The Unesco Courier 51
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
the subject but you recently established
the book prize, Prix Des Amériques Insu-
l a i res et de la Guyane, for the best litera r y
work written in any of the languages of
the Caribbean.
M C : Some people criticize me for accep-
ting money from Amédée Huyghues Des-
pointes who funded the prize.They say he
is a b é k é [a white Creole from the planto-
c r a cy ] , but the man loves Guadeloupe as
I love Guadeloupe.He is concerned about
the country’s future. We are in the year
2 0 0 0 . We should be finished with these
divisions between black and white and
move towards unity.
EN: You have a new book, Célanire cou-
coupé.
M C : I t ’s a departure from my other
n o v e l s. My daughters have been com-
plaining that all my novels are sad and
p a i n f u l , so I wrote a comical novel, a fan-
tastic novel. It is based on a story I read
in a newspaper in Guadeloupe, in 1995,
about a baby girl who was found dead,
her throat slashed, in a heap of rubbish.
E N :That doesn’t sound like a happy novel,
Maryse.
M C : Listen and tell me what you think.
Everyone wanted to know why the baby
was killed that way. I mean,a woman who
wants to get rid of her baby doesn’t usually
slash the baby’s t h r o a t .Th e r e is a special
cruelty and malice in doing such a thing.S o
people in Guadeloupe began to specu-
late that the baby was used as a human
s a c r i fic e. In my novel, I imagined she was
brought back to life by a doctor who
repaired her throat.The girl then goes in
search of those who murdered her.
EN:That is a very sad story.
MC:Wait. The girl begins to attack eve-
rything that we think of as sacred. For
e x a m p l e, she goes to Africa at the begin-
ning of colonization.When she sees that
colonization is failing because there is no
communication between Africans and
Europeans, she decides that the way to
improve the situation is to have a bor-
dello where African women could make
love to white men.A h , you are laughing.
EN:That is funny.
MC:So, you see, I was not wrong to say
the novel is comical.
EN: Farcical.
MC:Yes, that is the word.
E N : How do you manage to do all that
you do, Maryse? You are a magnific e n t
w r i t e r, you have a brilliant career as a
professor, scholar, administrator, literary
activist, mentor to fledging writers, and
yet you have a very active family life.
M C : H o n e s t l y, I do not have an answer.
I do not make an effort to be one or the
o t h e r. I am everything at the same time. ■
to find Cathy after her death. I wrote my
novel to prove that in spite of differences
in time, c o n d i t i o n s, or ideology, w o m e n
could communicate with each other
because we share common desires and
e x p e r i e n c e s. Emily Brontë could speak
to Maryse Condé more than a century
later because her story was similar to my
personal history. I was compelled to
rewrite Brontë’s story, not to show the
differences between Caribbean women
and English women, b u t ,r a t h e r, to show
what we had in common.
EN: I notice that you begin the book by
saying you hope Emily Brontë will appro v e
of your interpretation of her masterpiece.
Did that wish for her approval limit you in
any way?
MC: I must confess that I totally forgot
Emily Brontë, the author, when I was
writing my novel.What I concentrated on
was the passion between Cathy and Hea-
t h c l i f f, the excessive love that fused these
two characters. But I read Brontë’s novel
often, and I kept it on my desk open to
the page where Cathy says, “I am Hea-
thcliff.” That is a beautiful line. It tells
about the intensity of passion possible
between two people. When I was fin i-
shed writing my novel, I wondered what
Brontë would think of it, but it was not a
serious question I asked myself. I never
tried to compete with Brontë. She posed
no problem for me.
E N : Can you talk a little about your work at
Columbia University?  I know you cre a t e d
the Department of Francophone Studies
t h e re. In fact, you are the chairpers o n .
MC: In New York there is a lot of space
devoted to the English- and Spanish-
speaking Caribbean people,but there is
hardly any space for Fr e n c h - s p e a k i n g
Caribbean people. It seems as if we don’t
e x i s t .When I tell people I am from Gua-
d e l o u p e, they are puzzled. They have
never heard of Guadeloupe.When I was
invited to teach Caribbean literature at
Columbia University, I felt I had a duty
to use my position to create a depart-
ment to attract people from the French
Caribbean so that they would have a
space to talk about themselves and about
their work and so make their presence
k n o w n . I won’t say I changed the face of
New York—that would be arrogant—
but at Columbia, at least, people now
know that Aimé Césaire is not the only
Francophone writer from the Caribbean.
E N : You are far too modest, M a r y s e. I
know you are also an advocate for all
Caribbean litera t u re. Not only have you
o rganized some major conferences on
CONDÉ AT THE HELM
St o r y t e l l e r, a c t i v i s t , teacher and critic—but perhaps one title best applies to Maryse Condé:n a v i-
gator. For the grande dame of Caribbean literature incites us to explore ever-shifting terrain,
from the cruelty of the slave trade and the self-hate caused by racism to the spiral of lovers’ pas-
s i o n . In threading through the web of relations between A f r i c a , the Caribbean and Europe,C o n d é
calls on her personal experience. Born in 1937 in Guadeloupe, she left her comfortable family at
the age of 16 to study in Paris, where the spirit of decolonization and the Négritude movement
led her to criss-cross Western Africa,first with her Guinean husband and then as a single mother
of four children. Returning to Paris in 1973, she completed a doctorate in Caribbean literature from
the Sorbonne while launching her literary career. Her first great success was her S e g u s e r i e s
( 1 9 8 4 ) , renowned for its historically accurate and engaging portra yal of the impact of Islam on ani-
mist West Africa and the brutality of the slave trade.
In 1985,Condé won a Fulbright scholarship to teach in the U.S. and went on to set up the Cen-
ter for French and Francophone Studies at Columbia University where she continues to teach.H e r
11 works of fiction (translated in several languages) have earned her numerous prizes, including
the prestigious French awards, Le Grand Prix Litteraire de la Femme (1986) and the Prix Yource-
nar (1999).Perhaps more importantly, Condé is one of the few “foreign”authors to be accepted
by Africans as one of their own.She and her husband,Richard Philcox,divide their time between
New York and Guadeloupe. ■
● Selected titles: Windward Heights (Soho Press, 1 9 9 9 ) ; D e s i r a d a (Distribooks International,
1 9 9 8 ) ; The Last of the African Kings (University of Nebra s k a , 1 9 9 7 ) ;
I, Tituba, Black Witch of Salem (Ballantine, 1994).
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Focus:
■ The widening horizons of world heritage –
Charles Carrère
■ Rice-paddies in the Philippines:
a causeway to the sky —Alfred A. Yuson
■ The sandy treasures of Mauritania 
– Moussa Ould Ebnou
■ Suzhou’s soulful gardens – Lu Wenfu
■ Guanajuato: a mine of silver and 
Mexican history– Rafael Segovia
■ The thousand and one nights of 
Marrakesh’s Jemâa-el-Fna square – 
Juan Goytisolo
Features include:
■ A ride on the Trans-Siberian Express
■ Spain’s new water fight
■ Cleaning corruption out of Asia
■ Jerusalem: source of sound and fury
■ Ian Tattersall: the lost human species
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
December 2000:
Seven 
writers,
seven 
wonders
of the world
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 27 languages
w w w. l d j . t m . f r
]]>
</page>
</document>
