<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="121326eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WORLD HERITAGE
SEVEN WRITERS IN A
WORLD OF WONDERS
Jerusalem:
source 
of sound 
and fury
Corruption 
crackdown
in Korea 
and Thailand
Ian Tattersall:
a fresh 
eye on human 
evolution
December  2000
Canada:$3.95 Cdn,United Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
World Heritage 
R e v i e w
S u b s c r i p t i o n s :
Ediciones San Marcos, Maldonado 65, 28006, Madrid, Spain
tel. : +34 91 309 20 80      fax : +34 91 444 80 51      e-mail: sanmarcos@flashnet.es
The timeless treasures of our
natural and cultural heritage
and the efforts underway 
to safeguard them for future
generations
Subscription rates
6 issues: 190 FF ($40, 4,750 ptas, 28.97)
single issue: 35 FF ($6.95, 900 ptas, 5.34)
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
UNESCO Publ ishing
n How to influence the emergence of the social and
ethical dimensions of globalization? Culture might be the
answer.
n Experts, statisticians and artists provide information 
and analysis and propose new concepts, insights and policy
recommendations.
Attached to the book is the cd-rom Guide to Cultural Resources 
on the Web, including museums, cultural management sites and other
Internet addresses.
29.7 x 21 cm
414 pp.
260 FF/ 39.64
World Culture Report 2000
Cultural diversity, conflict and pluralism
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
C O N T E N T S
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 3
DECEMBER 2000
53rd year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Octavi Marti
French edition: Sophie Boukhari
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: The Mouveur,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l , Alcino Da
C o s t a , Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Shri Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads “Reprinted from the UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” ,p l u s
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author’s name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. The UN E S C O Courier is
produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UN E S C O, 7 Place
de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) , Ann A r b o r,
Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfie l d
R o a d , Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL: C1 - DECEMBER2000
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly in Paris by UN E S C O.
Printed in Fra n c e. Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and additional
mailing offic e s.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 12-2000-OPI 00-592 A
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily re p resent the opinions of UN E S C O or those of the
e d i t o rs of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r s t a f f. The boundaries on maps do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the
United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
◗ PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 The Trans-Siberian’s
grand bazaar
Photos by Frédéric Hermann, 
text by Michel Jan
◗ PLANET
10 When the rain in Spain is not enough
Octavi Marti
12 Free or foreign: the water battle in Bolivia
Jorge Cuba
◗ WORLD OF LEARNING
14 Hands on: in this museum, touching is the rule
Jorge Wagensberg
◗ ETHICS
37 Corruption: striking where it hurts in Korea
Glenn Manarin
38 A Thai crusade for clean politics
Laurence W. Sreshthaputra
◗ CULTURE
40 Jerusalem: source of sound and fury
René Lefort
◗ MEDIA
44 When computers chip away 
at our memories
Ivan Briscoe
◗ TALKING TO…
46 Ian Tattersall: the humans we left behind
Detailed table of contents on page 16.© Bertrand Gardel/
Hémisphères, Paris
Fo c u s Seven writers in 
a world of wonders
Maori sculptures in New Zealand
As the third millennium begins, the notion 
of world heritage continues to break new
ground. Influenced by Western tradition,
UNESCO’s World Heritage List long gave pride 
of place to monuments. Gradually, natural sites
have gained their rightful place, along with
those described as “mixed” (both cultural and
natural). Finally, sites singled out for the
exceptional vitality of their traditions are now
attracting recognition. In this dossier, seven
writers share their vision of a small selection
of these global wonders.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
T h e Tra n s - S i b e r ian ’
“I can tell any train by the noise of the wheels
European trains beat four four time, 
in Asia it’s three five or three seven”
Blaise Cendrars, Prosody of the Transsiberian and of Little Jeanne of France, 1913
(translated by John Dos Passos)
4 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Hawking goods on the platform of a station  near Novosibirsk.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
n ’s grand bazaar
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 5
It takes more than five days to get from Beijing to Moscow through
Mongolia—no trip for the impatient.But I have always loved this journey.
At one time the departure was a solemn occasion, with deserted carriages
pulling out of the station before a row of Red Guards waving Mao’s little red
book to the strains of The East is Red. Nowadays, it is a hectic affair, with a
myriad of goods overflowing in jam-packed corridors.
As the train pulls out of the station it seems to lurch in front of the
corner tower rising on the Tartar city’s southeastern edge, a rare vestige of
the old ramparts, as if hesitating for a last time. Some travellers let their eyes
linger on the outlying neighbourhoods of China’s capital, while others begin
their adjustment to the small, slow-moving cell they will call home for the next
five days. During the journey’s first few hours, the train clatters through the
hilly northern Chinese countryside, where the Great Wall—at first well-
restored,later reduced to a state of pitiful ruin—once marked the limits of
the civilized world. Working through the landscape of loess, ochre and
gorges dotted by scrawny willow trees, the train slowly chugs up to the
Mongolian plateau.Depending on the season, the landscape rolling by is worn
down by summer rain or frozen like a rock in the dead of winter.
The train’s steady beat and the spectacle of this epic land,as fascinating
as a receding shoreline, inspires a mood of contemplation—that is until the
passengers are overcome by drowsiness caused by neither boredom nor
w e a r i n e s s,but a combination of daydreaming, r e a d i n g, c o n v e r s a t i o n ,w h i s p e r e d
secrets and treasured moments liberated from time, which seems forgotten
or at least less pressing.After Datong, further north in Mongol country, t h e
steppe stretches out monotonously to the horizon.A horseman keeping a herd
of camels and a yurt are signs of humanity in the endless space, s p a r s e l y
covered with grass in midsummer, a moonscape from November to spring.
As evening falls, darkness creeps through the train.The lights in the cars
have wiped out the outside world. In the heart of a desert that the passengers
have forgotten, a strange coziness fills the compartments. The outdated
decor in first class—worn-out velvet the colour of crushed raspberries, p i n k
ribboned shades on table-lamps next to the windows, bevelled mirrors,
imitation mahogany veneer and faded green curtains—keeps up the illusion
of past luxury.A closed world, carried by the clickety-clack of steel on steel,
advances into the night.The sleeping-car bunks are stacked three high.A weak
light shines on languid bodies dappled in shadow. Skillfully tied-up and
stacked luggage fills the rest of the space.
Ulan Bator, the Selenga valley and the shores of Lake Baikal, I r k u t s k ,
Tomsk, Novosibirsk,Sverlovsk (renamed Ekaterinenburg), the Urals. The
days go by ticking off a litany of names that turn like the train’s wheels.
From Moscow to Beijing, travellers have five days 
to indulge their nostalgia in a legendary 
journey alongside adventurers and the odd bit of illegal
trade
PHOTOS BY FRÉDÉRIC HERMANN,TEXT BY MICHEL JAN
FRÉDÉRIC HERMANN IS A FRENCH PHOTOGRAPHER. MICHEL JAN IS A FRENCHWRITER
SPECIALIZING IN CHINA WHO RECENTLY PUBLISHED
LE RÉVEIL DES TARTARES, EN MONGOLIE SURLES TRACES DE GUILLAUME DE RUBROUCK (PAYOT, 1998) AND LA
GRANDE MURAILLE DE CHINE
(IMPRIMERIE NATIONALE EDITIONS, 2000).
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
The Tra n s - S i b e r i a n ’s grand bazaar
“If I was a painter I’d splash a great deal of red, 
a great deal of yellow on the end of this journey
Because we must all of us have been more or less cracked
And an enormous delirium brought the blood 
out on the drawn faces of my traveling companions.
As we drew nearer Mongolia
That roared like a burning building”
Blaise Cendrars, Prosody of the Transsiberian and of Little Jeanne of France, 1913
6 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
The train’s measured pace opens the way to contemplation: here, a Russian woman from Siberia gazes out.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 7
Changes are slow and the passengers have settled into their
h a b i t s.They return from the samovar at the end of the corridor
with faltering steps, following their daydreams, leaning their
elbows against the window; or weary of a journey that seems
endless, they play cards and chess.
The dining car changes with each country.The food’s quality
is uneven and offers a crude gastronomic tour first of China,
then Mongolia and finally Russia. But canteen or greasy-spoon,
it is part of the trip, attracting a steady flow of passengers and
adding its own touch of the exotic.The powerful smell of garlic,
the steam of boiled mutton and the bitter aroma of s o l y a n k a
In the Trans-Siberian’s
regular cars,
the bunks are stacked
three high.
The “national”wagons
stop at every 
border and are
replaced by others.
Russian cars
only run in Russia,
Mongolian ones 
in Mongolia 
and Chinese ones 
in China.
Along the way,
the traveller crosses a
whole cast of
characters: soldiers
(below),traders,
traffickers,thieves and
other adventurers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
The Tra n s - S i b e r i a n ’s grand bazaar
(cabbage soup)
juxtapose the swaying
and creaking axles.A t
opening time it’s the
liveliest place on the
t r a i n , with a varied
c l i e n t e l e. A few
We s t e r n e r s, c u r i o u s
about the smallest
d e t a i l , try to strike up
conversations with the
natives in a common
l a n g u a g e, C h i n e s e
warily check out their
neighbours and,
further away,R u s s i a n s
hunch over their
b o r s c h t ,disoriented by
the throng of
f o r e i g n e r s.
Only a few
diplomats from east
Asia used to take the
Trans-Siberian back 
to the USSR. But in
the past few years,
the weekly train
between Beijing and
M o s c o w,which travels
by way of Mongolia or Manchuria, has been frequented by
passengers travelling for a host of different reasons. The most
common is trade,a product of shortages on the opposite side of a
b o r d e r,the resourcefulness of merchants and the flurry of peoples
who have now rediscovered bartering after years cut out of market
a c t i v i t y. There are also the “ s p e c i a l i s t s ” drawn to international
express trains, on the lookout for shady opportunities or even
ready to commit a crime. Female adventurers looking lost and
would-be immigrants who withhold their names and dream of an
elysian Europe still roam the wagons.
The further the train reaches into Siberia, the livelier the
corridors become. Train employees and passengers, all of them
C h i n e s e, unwrap cargoes including sacks of rice, bundles of
clothes and plastic utensils.The stops are few and far between,b u t
when they do come, the platform suddenly turns into one giant
b a z a a r. Rows of Russian women offer the most unexpected
i t e m s :berries from the neighbouring forests,hot potatoes, t a w d r y
l a m p s, shoes designed for discomfort. Men and women walk
across the tracks,wending their way between the cars as they carry
sacks bulging with who-knows-what. A teenager flees after
snatching a pair of trousers offered for sale by a Chinese man
leaning out of a train window. S u d d e n l y, the locomotive’s siren
puts an end to the buying and selling,and the passengers rush back
on the train, already thinking about the next stop.
And so on—until the Trans-Siberian reaches the area just
outside Moscow, rolling through villages dotted with white or
gold church towers resembling the birch trees that blanket the
Russian countryside in autumn.
The journey is a source of adventure and a muse. Isn’t
Blaise Cendrars’ Prosody of the Transsiberian one of modern
poetry’s most beautiful verses? Travelling across Asia to reach
Europe still captures the imagination. It is as if the people
roaming from one continent to another, frozen in our memories,
alone represent what is unchanging in human destiny. ■
“After Irkutsk the journey became 
very much slower
Much too slow,
We were in the first train 
that went around Lake Baikal”
Blaise Cendrars, Prosody of the Transsiberian and 
of Little Jeanne of France, 1913
Some don’t travel light.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 -The Unesco Courier 9
A moment of elation before the expanse of Mongolia’s steppe.
R U S S I A
M O N G O L I A
K A Z A K H S T A N
C H I N A
MOSCOW
VLADIVOSTOK
BEIJING
Perm
Omsk
Novosibirsk
Krasnoyarsk
Irkutsk
ULAN BATOR
Ulan Ude
ChitaLake
Baikal
Harbin
THE WILL OF THE CZARS
The “real” Trans-Siberian travels
9,198 kilometres from Moscow to
Vladivostok.The train only runs
on Russian territory, on a line
that was finished in 1916.It was
built to double a line completed
in 1904 that the Russians
considered too unsafe after the
Russo-Japanese war of 1904-1905
because it crossed Manchuria.
Today, two lines link Moscow and
Beijing. At first,they follow 
the Trans-Siberian route before
forking southward, one through
Manchuria,the other through
Mongolia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
“What we call ‘the water problem’ in Spain
is going to become ‘the water war,’ ”
predicted Spanish ecologist José Manuel
Naredo in 1997. Three years later, t h e
400,000 people who marched through the
streets of Zaragoza (a town of 650,000
inhabitants) on October 8 appeared to
prove him right. Their target was the
National Water Plan (NWP), unveiled by
the government on September 5.
The plan’s centrepiece is the diversion
of a billion cubic metres of water each
year from the River Ebro to occasionally
or permanently arid regions on the
c o u n t r y ’s Mediterranean coast. Fo r
inhabitants of the province of A r a g ó n ,
the 700,000 million pesetas (more than
$3.5 billion) that the government intends
to spend on building 529 kilometres of
new waterways and several dams are
simply 700,000 drops of water in a cup
that is already spilling over.
Aragón feels robbed. The 400,000
demonstrators may have been
exaggerating a little when they shouted
that the waters of “our Ebro” would be
used to keep golf courses green, f i l l
swimming pools for tourists and supply
amusement parks while others die of
thirst and neglect. But as Naredo
o b s e r v e s, “people no longer accept the
mainstay of Spanish water policy for the
last century, of taking water where you
find it and transferring it to where it’s
needed.”
The opponents of the NWP have
stepped up their attacks. They say water
supplies can no longer be managed on
technical criteria alone. The planned
diversions are dangerous, they argue,
because the Ebro basin has not had a
water surplus for the past quarter of a
10 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
OCTAVI MARTI 
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
When the rain in Spain 
is not enough
Spain uses vast quantities of water. To meet its country’s needs, the government 
has resorted to technical solutions such as diverting the Ebro river
—a project that many people have condemned for squandering a precious resource
Irrigation in the Ebro delta: are farmers abusing cheap water?
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 11
c e n t u r y.
But their main criticism is that the
diversion of the river is completely
u n n e c e s s a r y. Economic history teacher
Enric Tello believes the answer to Spain’s
water problems lies in “reorganizing the
s u p p l y.” He argues that the country is
suffering from “water schizophrenia” a n d
that “sooner or later taxpayers will wonder
why they are still subsidizing the irrigation
of crops that are already being subsidized
and are often produced in excessive
q u a n t i t i e s.”
This “schizophrenia” arises, he says,
from the huge gap between the price of
water for irrigation, which is almost free,
and the much higher cost of water used in
cities and industries. So why not try to
narrow that gap? The answer could lie
in a small detail that both Tello and
Naredo point to: Environment Minister
Jaume Matas launched the NWP at the
headquarters of the Public Wo r k s
Employers’ Federation.
The ministry offers a quite different
s p i n .O f ficials say demand for water will
keep on growing and requires the building
of costly aqueducts. They agree that the
irrigated area of around 3.5 million
hectares should not be increased, b u t
defend the river diversion plan and talk of
building more than 70 new dams at a cost
of three thousand billion pesetas (about
$15.5 billion) over eight years.All of which
clashes with a European Union directive
d e fining every water catchment area as a
distinct management unit and ruling out
water transfers from one area to another.
But the ministry insists it is no longer
possible to “ g o
b a c k w a r d s,”
declaring that the
NWP “will solve the
water problem for
g o o d .” S p a i n ’s 1,070
big dams already
make it the world’s
leading country in
terms of proportion
of dam-created lakes
to total land mass.
The fact is, h o w e v e r,
that many serve no
p u r p o s e, since for months on end they
are filled to only five or 10 percent
c a p a c i t y.
Spain began its first major river
diversion scheme in the 1960s by linking
the Tagus in the west and centre-west to
the Segura in the southeast—a transfer of
600 million cubic metres of water a year.
But in 1999, the province of Castilla,
which the Tagus flows through, refused to
supply a drop more than 40 million cubic
m e t r e s, less than 10 percent of the amount
originally planned.
What had happened? Maize growing,
which requires a lot of water,expanded in
the regions along the Tagus (the Mancha
and the Meseta). To irrigate today’s
150,000 hectares of maize, you need to
draw heavily on underground water and
also pump more from the Ta g u s. I n
Murcia (watered by the Segura), which
benefits from the diversion scheme,
irrigated areas have grown enormously.
Biologist José Luis Benito notes that
“absurd though it might seem, t h e
diversion of the Tagus has turned a
hitherto occasional and irregular drought
into a systematic and permanent one.”
Forty million hectares of Spain have
a Mediterranean climate. Because the
rainy season and warm weather do not
c o i n c i d e, there is little vegetation. P l a n t i n g
m a i z e,a l f a l f a , potatoes and beans in such
a climate is not a particularly sound idea
because these crops depend upon a lot of
w a t e r. In the Mancha, for instance, it takes
a tonne of water to produce a kilo of
m a i z e. If water was not subsidized, a s
Pedro Arrojo has noted in his study of the
irrigated regions of A r a g ó n ,90 percent of
this land could not be profitably farmed.
This has led the historian Tello into
calling for a new agricultural policy based
around sustainable development which
would preserve subsidies for “ m a i n t a i n i n g
balanced land use and other social and
environmental reasons,”but hand out the
aid directly to farms rather than using it to
bring down the price
of water, fuel and
chemical fertilizers.
If water for
irrigation were not
100 times cheaper
than water for
i n d u s t r y, c r o p s
unsuited to Spain’s
climate would be
a b a n d o n e d .But Te l l o
has proposed a
solution already
adopted in the United
States through the California Water Bank.
This “ m a r k e t ” allows farmers, at certain
times of the year, to re-sell some of their
water stocks to cities that need it.B e c a u s e
they make money from this, they can then
grow crops that need less water, even if
they are less profit a b l e. So the cities get
the water they need,the farmers do not lose
money and water resources are not over-
u s e d .
Of the one billion cubic metres of
water that will be diverted under the
NWP, 300 million will go to the Valencia
region, 430 million to Murcia, 90 to the
Andalusian province of Almería and 180
to Catalonia.But the latter has no water
shortage, and is unlikely to have one for
at least another 25 years judging by its
P L A N E T ◗
Water for 
irrigation 
is 100 times 
cheaper than 
water for 
industry
Atlantic Ocean
Méditerranean
Sea
F R A N C E
S P A I N
MOROCCO A L G E R I A
MADRID
Barcelona
Zaragoza
Valencia
Murcia
Almería
C A S T I L L A
L A  M A N C H A
A N D A L U S I A
E b r o
J ú c a r
S e g u r a
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
A bill to privatize Bolivia’s
government-owned water network
recently sparked off a “water war” that
grew into one of the Andean country’s
most serious social crises of the past few
years.
The conflict erupted in January 2000
when the price of drinking water was
tripled in the central Bolivian city of
C o c h a b a m b a , and peasants in the
surrounding arid region suddenly found
that the water they had been drawing
freely for generations no longer belonged
to them. City-dwellers accustomed to
subsidized water supplies were
confronted by the true market price,w h i l e
the peasants—mostly Quechua Indians
who had owned the water for centuries—
involuntarily found themselves customers
of Aguas del Tunari, a subsidiary of the
British firm International Water.
No clean water for 
one third of the people
These changes were the result of Law
2 0 2 9 ,a bill passed at the end of 1999 which
privatized state drinking water and sewage
d i s p o s a l . “ The law’s big mistake was to
privatize the sources of the water as well
since franchises are usually only applied to
administration of the service,” s a y s
Bolivian hydrologist Carlos Fe r n á n d e z
Ja u r e g u i , a UNESCO water expert.
F u r t h e r m o r e, the law was pushed through
without any kind of public hearings and
under pressure from the French fir m
Lyonnaise des Eaux,which is in charge of
the water supply in the capital, La Paz,
through a local company called Aguas de
I l l i m a n i .
In South A m e r i c a ’s poorest country,
where a third of the population has no
access to clean water and 70 percent of
people live below the poverty line, there are
plenty of reasons for social unrest. O n c e
b e g u n , the water conflict escalated into a
much wider rebellion lasting 10 chaotic
months and causing huge economic losses,
an 11-day state of siege and a dozen deaths.
The unrest was serious enough to
make the government cave in.In April,
Aguas del Tunari pulled out of the
contract they had signed with the state to
build a dam at Misicuni aimed at boosting
current population growth. Naredo adds
that after Barcelona’s preparations for
the 1992 Olympic Games,which involved
shutting down old industrial plants that
consumed a lot of water,“the city’s water
table rose to the point that it had to pump
water out to avoid flooding the subway
and underground parking lots.”
Tello has looked into the potential
b e n e fits of “a system that would penalize
waste and encourage saving and recy c l i n g
w a t e r.” Whenever industry has realized
water can cost it 10 times less through
careful planning, it has changed its
patterns of use.Tello has also shown that
investing 100,000 pesetas (about $500) to
equip every household in Catalonia with
electrical and water appliances that can
save and re-use water would be cheaper
than a projected scheme to channel water
from the River Rhône, in southern Fr a n c e,
to Barcelona, at a cost of around 200
billion pesetas (more than $1 billion).
Taxing water in a more consistent way
would solve another big problem: that of
outdated piping.Pedro Arrojo has noted
that the water network in Zaragoza was
so leaky that no difference was registered
between daytime and nighttime
c o n s u m p t i o n . In the market gardening
area around Valencia, the price farmers
pay for water is fixed by the amount of
land they need to irrigate, meaning that
losses caused by faulty piping are
generally ignored. Another example is
the Jucar imperial canal, which is built
directly in the earth and results in massive
leakage.
The second largest ecological
reserve under threat
Spain gets 346 billion cubic metres of
rainfall each year, of which 109 billion
remains after evaporation. This should
be enough to meet an annual demand of
35 billion cubic metres,80 per cent of it for
agriculture, which usually pays one peso
per cubic metre.
In areas where the price of water for
irrigation is higher (30 pesetas a cubic
metre) because it comes from
desalination plants or from underground,
farming is very sophisticated. A l m e r í a ,
which 20 years ago was Spain’s poorest
p r o v i n c e, is today the country’s fastest
growing one and relies upon the most
foreign labour (which is neither
welcomed nor assimilated). B e c a u s e
yields are very high, the province has
13,000 hectares of land that are illegally
irrigated.
The diversion of the Ebro is an
ineffective response to Spain’s cultural,
social,political and economic problems.
Opponents of the scheme say it even
creates new difficulties:the defenders of
the environment are especially worried
that the Ebro delta, the country’s second
biggest ecological reserve, m i g h t
disappear.
Since the end of the 19th century,
sediment in the river has dropped by 95
p e r c e n t .As a result, the government has to
invest about 20 billion pesetas ($100
million) to add sand to some beaches.O n e
thing is nevertheless certain: i f
d e s e r t i fication continues to advance in
S p a i n , the country will not be needing extra
s a n d . ■
12 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
BY JORGE CUBA
BOLIVIAN JOURNALIST
FREE OR FOREIGN:
THE WATER BATTLE IN BOLIVIA
Should water be supplied by local authorities or private companies? 
A violent conflict in Bolivia has recently shown that both 
can work, but only if the wishes of consumers are taken into account
Water wars
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
the Cochabamba region’s water supply.
But in spite of the citizens’ victory in the
“water war,”C o c h a b a m b a ’s basic problems
have not been solved.The city has no more
than five hours of water a day,and only 40
percent of farmers in the surrounding area
have access to clean water.“ The only way
to end Cochabamba’s water shortage is to
build the dam,” says Fernández Ja u r e g u i .
“ The other solutions are just sticking
p l a s t e r s.” Other plans, such as one to tap
into underground rivers,have so far made
little headway, while efforts to form a
cooperative or limited company with the
involvement of local people have come to
n o t h i n g.
Aside from the dam, the Misicuni plan
includes building a tunnel, w a t e r
p u r i fication plants and sewage farms to
the tune of $300 million. The generous
terms the privatization law
gave to contractors were
j u s t i fied in terms of the need to
attract enough investment to
pay for the multi-million-dollar
project on top of the money
provided by Bolivian
t a x p a y e r s. In the end,h o w e v e r,
the project backfired on
President Hugo Banzer’s
g o v e r n m e n t :Aguas del Tu n a r i
is demanding heavy
compensation for having to
withdraw from the project,
stoking fears that if the state
does not pay up, B o l i v i a ’s
reputation with foreign
investors will be harmed.
Taking culture and
customs into account
But the departure of these
foreign firms is not necessarily
the best solution, not even for
the poor. Due to their
international experience,
multinationals are usually
better value for money than
local public utilities, they use
the water more effectively and
pay better salaries to their
t e c h n i c i a n s. G o v e r n m e n t s, f o r
their part, must shield citizens
from the natural commercial
appetites of these giant water
c o m p a n i e s.
In Fernández Ja u r e g u i ’s
o p i n i o n , B o l i v i a ’s water
problems stem from
administrative failures, a n d
Bolivians are paying for their
inexperience in water
l e g i s l a t i o n .“ There aren’t any
laws or institutions and there
i s n ’t enough suitable
infrastructure to cope with the
water problem,” he says.
Other Latin A m e r i c a n
c o u n t r i e s, in contrast, h a v e
acquired useful experience in
solving the thorny confli c t s
caused by water.C o m m u n i t i e s
are very attached to the free
supply of water enjoyed by
previous generations, b u t
through frank and open
dialogue they can also come to understand
that it is a scarce resource which must now
be paid for. “ There were obviously other
ways to tackle the water problem in
B o l i v i a ,”says Fernández Ja u r e g u i .“ Wa t e r
legislation has to be based on consulting
local people, as other laws are. If local
c u l t u r e,customs and ways of life had been
taken into account, all these problems
could have been avoided.” ■
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 13
“What is ours is ours and cannot be taken away”: m a rching against the hike in water rates in
P L A N E T ◗
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
S
JORGE WAGENSBERG
SPANISHPHYSICISTAND DIRECTOR OFTHE
LA CAIXA FOUNDATION SCIENCE MUSEUM IN BARCELONA
ome time ago I got into the habit of
leaving my office to eavesdrop on visitors
in every nook and cranny of the La Caixa
Foundation Science Museum that I run in
B a r c e l o n a .A lot of what they say proves
very interesting, and excellent food for
thought about what a modern science
museum should aim to be.
O n c e,I was hot on the heels of a young
father and his son of about seven. Th e y
paused in front of a mimosa pudica p l a n t
whose leaves recoil when you touch them.
Father:Did you see that?
Boy:What? What’s happening? Hey!
But is it real or not?
Father:It’s real.Don’t you see?
I lingered behind them as they
approached a model of the Amazon that
compresses a day’s life in the rainforest
into the space of 10 minutes, i n c l u d i n g
an electrically-generated storm, t o r r e n t i a l
rain and a rainbow. In the middle of the
s h o w, the entranced boy looked up to his
father and asked once again:“ D a d , is this
real or not?”To which his father replied:
“It isn’t real. . . Watch carefully!”
A few minutes later,at an underwater
archaeology exhibit with a giant aquarium
featuring a sunken ship and huge moray
fish swimming between the furniture in
the captain’s cabin, I heard another
exchange:
Boy:They’re real,aren’t they?
Father:Of course.You can see that.
Boy:And the furniture?
Fa t h e r : H m m . I don’t know. I think
some of it is.
The boy’s metaphysical obsession—
about whether things are real or not,
about the difference between experience
and theory, between a replica and “the
actual thing”—was much stronger than
his father’s.U n w i t t i n g l y, this young visitor
reopened a critical debate in our museum
over when to use a real-life object,when
14 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
Hands on: in this museum,
touching is the rule
Jorge Wagensberg eavesdrops on visitors to the science museum he runs 
in Barcelona. The conversations he overhears enable him to imagine 
A tactile exploration of our planet in a room devoted to understanding the thriving of life on earth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 15
to use a replica and whether the two can
be combined.
In any case it’s clear what a museum
must not do:namely boil down its exhibits
to excerpts from a book whose crammed
pages can be read by the long-suffering
visitors as they walk down a hallway into
rooms full of  scale models for
demonstrations and videos and
computers that look like shopfronts of
electrical stores. One of the most
elementary mistakes made by today’s
museums is to forget that the absolute
priority is to be real.
Just as classes, conferences and
seminars are based mainly on the spoken
word, cinema and television on images
and books and magazines on the written
word, museums and exhibitions should
focus on the real object or event.For it is
the prospect of encountering reality that
draws people to museums.
In recent years, science museums have
been at the vanguard in terms of changing
their collections, methods and
engagement with the public. Our slogan
these days is “please touch.” The old
concept of the display case has been
replaced by that of experience, and the
academic label has changed into a more
literary one. Above all, the former
highbrow attitude has been overtaken
by an effort to involve all five human
senses.
A careful mixture of
touch, feelings and thought
Another thing I’ve learnt on my
strolls around the museum is that we still
have a long way to go before youngsters
feel comfortable there. I recently came
across a little girl,no more than six years
old, throwing large stones at a wooden
open-air kiosk used in summertime as
an ice-cream shop. It was winter and the
kiosk was closed. I reached her just as
she was about to throw another stone.
As soon as she saw me,she dropped it and
looked down shamefacedly. I stood there
silently for a moment before she looked
u p, gazed at the kiosk, then turned to me
and asked:“Is that yours?”
To get our young visitors to treat
things in the museum with care, they have
to feel they have a stake in them.Th o u g h
it is not easy,one way is to try to stimulate
their senses. In a science museum, t h e
most effective stimuli are a careful
mixture of touch,feelings and thought.
L e t ’s take a few examples. Once I
quietly shadowed a boy of about 10 into
the museum’s big vivarium, which had
an exhibit called “Invisible Stillness.”At
first he saw nothing. But behind the glass
and amid dry leaves, earth and roots, l i v e d
three dozen stick-insects (E x t e t o s o m a
t i a r a t u m) . The boy was puzzled and
looked around,clearly annoyed.He must
have thought it was a joke or that the
exhibit was being repaired.
Then he spotted a notice saying:“ Th e r e
are 30 big insects in here.” With an
incredulous look, he seemed to be
wondering how so many insects could be
invisible in such a small space. Then he
saw them—one. . .t w o. . .t h r e e.“ H e y,now I
get it! There they are,” I heard him say as I
watched his face light up. His eyes had
been looking at the insects, but his brain
h a d n ’t seen them. That is emotional
i n t e r a c t i o n . The boy, like many other
v i s i t o r s, was enthralled by everything he
saw after that.
Next to the vivarium is a window in
which you can see a mass of scattered
dots with no discernible pattern. If the
visitor touches a lever, some of the dots
arrange themselves into the shape of an
a n i m a l . This is an example of genuine
manual interactivity:move the lever and
the animal appears; release it and the
creature disappears before your eyes.
It is a small trick that arouses the
imagination and makes the point that
many hunted animals stay absolutely still
when a predator is terrifyingly close to
t h e m . Applied in daily life (why do we
wave to attract the attention of a waiter
who pretends not to see us?), it explains
what mental interactivity means, a n d
allows the visitor to make comparisons
and even reinterpret previous experiences.
The main job of a modern museum
should be to go beyond preserving
h e r i t a g e, i n f o r m i n g, training and even
t e a c h i n g, and to generate this kind of
excitement through objects and real
p h e n o m e n a . People can then physically
experience the feelings of the scientist,
who is not seeking either good or evil but
simply trying, like anyone else, to come up
with as much knowledge as he or she can
about the world in an effort to make
h u m a n i t y ’s cosmic solitude bearable.
Th a t ’s why scientists do experiments—
they are endeavouring to converse with
n a t u r e.A museum should strive to make
visitors plunge like divers into the
s c i e n t i s t ’s quest.
For the best ideas,
tune into the young
Based on my experience as a museum
director and eavesdropper, I think we
should pay close attention to what
children say, because we might learn
something from youngsters who are
learning themselves. Our museum is for
people of all ages or education. But the
youngest visitors have what turn out to be
certain very good ideas.So we must tune
into their thoughts, like those of two boys
and their mother as they were coming
out of our large weather exhibition. O n e
boy was about 10 and the other about
five and had to run to keep up. The 10-
year-old seemed annoyed.
B oy, 1 0 : Mum! Mum! W h a t ’s in the
Amazon?
M o t h e r : O K , we’ll go and see. B u t
maybe you’ll be disappointed.
And then from somewhere behind me,
a little voice.
Boy, 5:Mum?
Mother: Yes dear?
Boy, 5:What’s disappointed? ■
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
B a rc e l o n a ’s 
Science Museum
Opened in 1981, the La Caixa Foundation
Science Museum is the first of its kind in
Spain. Its main aim is to spread scientific
and technical knowledge among the
general public, especially students. To do
t h i s, it encourages contact between
s c i e n t i s t s, teachers and scientific
institutions. It covers an area of 7,000
square metres and another 30,000 are
currently being added on.
To know more:
www.fundacio.lacaixa.es
Budding scientists at the helm.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
C o n t e n t s
1 8 The past is not just made of stone
Léon Pressouyre
2 0 The soul of Suzhou’s gard e n s
Lu We n f u
2 3 Irrigating time with the Kinderdijk 
w i n d m i l l s
Serge van Duijnhoven
2 6 The tre a s u res in Mauritania’s dunes
Moussa Ould Ebnou
2 9 G u a n a j u a t o : fortunes made of silver
Rafael Segovia
3 1 Dancing anew on the stairways to 
h e a v e n
Alfred A . Yu s o n
3 4 Jemâa-el Fna’s thousand and
one nights
Juan Goytisolo
SEVEN 
in a Worl 
his voyage is a personal one:seven writers share their vision of a small
selection of wonders chosen from the 630 cultural and natural sites on
U N E S C O ’s World Heritage List.The Senegalese poet Charles Carrère sets
forth his approach to heritage, as both an inheritance and a gift to be
passed on, a fruit of many meetings and exchanges, an expression of
memory and hope (p. 17).As Professor Léon Pressouyre explains, the
criteria for selecting world heritage sites have considerably evolved
since the adoption in 1972 of an international convention to protect these
treasures of humanity, now spread across 118 countries (pp. 18-19).
Our journey begins with the wanderings of Chinese writer Lu Wenfu in the gardens of  Suzhou (pp.
2 0 - 2 2 ) . Serge van Duijnhoven recalls his childhood near the Kinderdijk windmills, forever threatened
by the sea (pp. 2 3 - 2 5 ) . Mauritanian writer Moussa Ould Ebnou describes how his country’s 12th and
13th century cities are inexorably being reclaimed by the desert sands (pp. 26-28).Rafael Segovia
of Mexico testifies to the unwavering tenacity of Guanajuato, a town that surged from the belly of
the mountain in the 15th century with the discovery of silver and gold mines (pp. 29-30). In the
Philippines, Alfred A. Yuson admires the rare
complicity  forged between nature and the
indigenous tribes who have patiently sculpted
the rice terraces of Luzon Island over the past
2,000 years (pp. 3 1 - 3 3 ) . And finally, J u a n
Goytisolo brings life to the notion of ora l
heritage by inviting us to Morocco to hear the
legendary storytellers of Jemâa-el-Fna square,
in Marrakesh.
Dossier concept and coordination by 
Jasmina Sopova, UNESCO Courier journalist
F O C U S
T
16 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
The World Heritage 
emblem symbolizes 
the interdependence 
of the world’s natural
and cultural diversity.
While the central
square represents
the results of human
skill and inspiration,
the circle celebrates
the gifts of nature.
The emblem is round,
like the world, a symbol
of global protection for
the heritage of humankind.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Heritage is a timely theme in a world
shaken by an intense and violent crisis,o n e
which calls into question an entire system
of values while eroding the relationship
between people and the environment.Th e
effects of industrial and technological
evolution testify to this: the sacred pact
between people, nature and the universe
has been severed.The planet is poisoned.
And life seems threatened in all its different
f o r m s.
This crisis not only beckons us to
rethink our approaches to development
but the very notion itself. For too long,
development has solely been seen
through the materialist lens of production
and consumption. To d a y, i n t e l l e c t u a l s,
artists and writers are increasingly
convinced that this concept, w h i c h
s a c r i fices culture to economic growth,
the qualitative to the quantitative, c a n
only bear catastrophic consequences.
To d a y,we renew our longstanding call
to place culture ahead of all else.The great
landmarks in humanity’s history have
always been in the domain of culture. It is
not a question of creating cultural,e t h n i c
and geographical ghettoes. On the
c o n t r a r y. Putting culture first means
appreciating the specificity and richness of
our respective identities, building on the
heritage of the past and enriching that
which we bequeath to future generations.
It is a heritage to which all peoples,
n a t i o n s, c o n t i n e n t s, in short, all civilizations
could contribute their own irreplaceable
v a l u e s.
This would lead us towards a
humanism of “giving and receiving” t h a t
the Martinique poet Aimé Césaire has
so fervently called for. This humanism
offers a new way of conceiving the terms
of exchange.The outcome is a symbiosis
of cultures so that they don’t become
alike or fuse, but are enriched through
encounters with each other.This “ c u l t u r e
of the universal,” cherished by the
Senegalese poet Léopold Sédar Senghor,
is not a universal culture but a meeting of
civilizations.
It is in this meeting that humanity’s
world heritage lies. Human beings
distinguish themselves from animals by
their creative spirit, with which they
transcend the horizons of the visible. Fi r e,
once mastered, is transformed into
rustlings of life, colours and shapes. The
first staff our ancestors leaned upon,the
first stones they chose to rest upon, the
first cave in which they sought shelter,
were all tinged with the colours of light.
Human beings were born in beauty from
the outset: for the beautiful they were
born.
Created by stardust, peoples crossed
the world, sprinkling it with stones as
g u i d e p o s t s, just as in the tale of Hansel and
G r e t e l . As time passed, they built
monuments carrying the stamp of their
genius and the permanence of their
s p e c i e s.
For coherent action, we need an
image of the past and a vision of the
f u t u r e. For if science cannot answer
questions regarding their earliest origins,
nor those of the afterlife, human beings
will climb many mountains to proclaim
their faith in life.Their spirit of resistance
and their hope springs from this faith.It
is a faith that is proclaimed, like a vital
need,on the front of their buildings.
From the cabins of their childhood
to the columns of temples,on each stone,
behind every door, this hope will be
forever engraved. ■
H E R I TAG E , A LESSON 
IN GIVING AND RECEIVING
CHARLES CARRÈRE
SENEGALESEPOET AND PAINTER, VICE PRESIDENT OFTHE INTERNATIONAL POETRY HOUSE IN BRUSSELS (BELGIUM).
ONE OFHIS MOST RECENTWORKS IS HIVERNAGE PUBLISHED BY L’HARMATTAN (PARIS, 1999).
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 17
O P I N I O N
 WRITERS 
 d of Wo n d e rs
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A professor at the Université Paris
I,Léon Pressouyre is president of
the Commission for the
conservation of Bosnia-
Herzegovina’s national
monuments, within UNESCO. He
was the ICOMOScoordinator 
(International Council on
Monuments and Sites) 
for the World Heritage 
Convention between 1980 and
1990 and represented France on
the World Heritage Committee
from 1990 to 1997.He is the
author of 
The World Heritage Convention,
Twenty Years Later (UNESCO,
1993).
LÉON PRESSOUYRE
18
LÉON PRESSOUYRE
FRENCH UNIVERSITYPROFESSOR
W hat is the common thread running
through the U N E S C O Wo r l d
Heritage sites featured in this issue,
which have inspired a constellation
of writers and artists fascinated by
their unique and irreplaceable nature? The sites
may not be stars on the tourist circuit,nor are they
formally connected with each other, but they are
telling examples of some recent changes in our
attitudes towards heritage.
One is the steadily vanishing division between
cultural and natural heritage.The other is a growing
awareness of the value of intangible heritage,w h i c h
is being undermined and too often brushed aside by
the unstinting advance of globalization.
The World Heritage Convention,adopted by the
U N E S C O General Conference in 1972, fashioned a
v i t a l ,ground-breaking idea into an international legal
s t a t u t e. But it defined humanity’s heritage very
conservatively under two headings: the cultural and
the natural. This marked the culmination of a long
tradition and of a more recent intellectual effort to
match the splendours of art with the wonders of
n a t u r e.
H u m a n i t y ’s admiration for its own creations
was displayed as far back as the second century
B.C. in the famous list of the seven wonders of the
world—a world narrowly confined to the eastern
Mediterranean.
Tides, phoenixes and volcanoes:
proof of divine power in nature
Few people are aware that the wonders of nature
were in fact listed well before the modern era and
the birth of environmental awareness.A 12t h- c e n t u r y
Latin manuscript held in the French National
L i b r a r y, for instance,contrasts the seven destructible
man-made wonders with seven wonders of nature
which,the author says, are proof of divine power.
On the list are tides,plant germination, the phoenix
(the mythical bird that rises from its own ashes), a
volcano (Mount Etna in Sicily), a hot spring near
Grenoble (Fr a n c e ) , as well as the sun and the moon.
These were wonders unaffected by age or accident,t h e
author maintains, and their demise could only come
with the end of the world, whereas the man-made
wonders were destined to disappear well before then.
The 1972 Convention reflects this dual European
t r a d i t i o n . It was not the product of a debate among
p h i l o s o p h e r s, historians and sociologists about the
concept of heritage, but simply the convergence of
two schools of thought. One came directly from the
1931 League of Nations conference in A t h e n s, a n d
concerned preserving cultural heritage as defin e d
in terms of classical notions of a “ m a s t e r p i e c e ” o r
“wonder of the world.” The other stemmed from
the first international conference on protecting
n a t u r e, in Bern in 1913, which was followed up by the
Brunnen conference in 1947 and the foundation the
following year of the World Conservation Union,
whose aim was to pass on to future generations
“ u n s p o i l e d ” natural sites untouched by humans.
Vineyards and rice terraces
find their way onto the List
This division between cultural treasures (thought
of as monuments created by human beings) and
natural ones (which owed nothing to human
involvement) long dominated the application of
the 1972 Convention.In 1994,nearly half the sites
on the World Heritage List were cultural ones within
E u r o p e.Nothing could have been further removed
from the spirit of the Convention.
When in June 1994 the World Heritage
Committee adopted the recommendations of
experts who had looked into how representative the
List was, it absorbed the very different conception
of culture espoused by anthropologists and
e t h n o l o g i s t s, one that encompasses a complex
mixture of social organizations,ways of life, b e l i e f s,
know-how and expressions of past and present
cultures.
The accession to the List of cultural landscapes,
such as the rice terraces of the Philippine Cordilleras
and Fr a n c e ’s Saint-Emilion vineyards, is one of the
The Convention Concerning the Protection of the Wo r l d
C u l t u ral and Natural Heritage, adopted in 1972 by the
UNESCO General Conference, e n c o u rages states to choose
exceptional sites for preserva t i o n .To date, the Convention has
been ra t i fied by 161 countries. In November 2000, the Wo r l d
Heritage List consisted of 630 sites in 118 countries—480 of
them cultura l , 128 natural and 22 described as mixed. ■
To know more:
www.unesco.org/whc
World Heritage Review, published quarterly by UNESCO
Publishing www.worldheritagereview.org
The past is not just made 
of stone
The world’s heritage is about more than monuments and natural
wonders—the intangible ideas and beliefs 
that make up our collective memory also have their rightful place
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 -The Unesco Courier 19
The heritage of 
a country is
essentially its
cultural identity,
and whether 
big or small,
majestic or
simple, physical
or non-physical, it
must be
maintained and
have a meaning
for every new
generation. 
I.M. Pei,
American architect 
(1917-)
positive outcomes of the 1994 change in guidelines.
A few years earlier, even though public interest in
historical gardens (such as those of Shalimar, i n
L a h o r e, Pakistan) was fully recognized, s t e r i l e
debates would probably have prevented them
gaining a place on the List.
The same goes for industrial heritage. Before
they began being put “ o p e n l y ”on the List, i n d u s t r i a l
sites were admitted in disguise: the salt mines at
Wi e l i c z k a , in Po l a n d , and the royal salt works in the
French town of Arc-et-Senans, for example, were
accepted in 1978 and 1988 on the basis of their
architectural merit. M e a n w h i l e, the prestige of
monuments declined as interest grew in roads,
railway networks, rivers and canals—all of them
long neglected by the List,perhaps because of legal
problems involved in preserving them.
Moving away from classical
definitions of a masterpiece
Such choices reflect a significant change in our
concept of heritage. By finally questioning the idea
inherited from ancient times and firmly rooted in
European culture of what a masterpiece is, t h e
World Heritage Committee opened the way to a
more balanced picture of humanity’s heritage. A
shared and indivisible heritage, where the
interaction of people and nature is fully recognized,
is gradually winning converts from the incomplete
vision of heritage that the 1972 Convention
perpetuated despite its best intentions.
No longer is the sacred Maori mountain in New
Z e a l a n d ’s Tongariro National Park seen as very
different from Mount A t h o s, in Greece,even though
the forests and volcanic craters of the first are
monuments steeped in sacred meaning while the
second houses the world’s largest collection of
Byzantine art.
Legends, beliefs and traditions:
safeguards to our collective memory
So intangible heritage—the amorphous body
of beliefs, l e g e n d s,written and oral traditions along
with forms of behaviour that make up our
diversity—has made a vigorous comeback onto the
World Heritage List. The 1972 Convention made
only passing mention of intangible heritage and
tied it to the existence of material evidence.But after
long neglect it now seems that intangible heritage is
the key safeguard to humanity’s collective memory,
precisely because of its very vulnerability.
What would happen to Marrakesh—whose city
w a l l s, mosques and palaces are preserved like
museum pieces—if the Jemâa-el-Fna Square was no
longer a vibrant and colourful meeting place of
c u l t u r e s, filled with music and hubbub and the
aromas of several worlds that we are lucky to know?
What would the Sri Lankan city of Kandy be like
without its annual pilgrimage that draws thousands
of the faithful to venerate the remarkable relic that
is the Buddha’s tooth? And what would become of
the World Heritage site of Sukur, in Nigeria,if the
highly structured society living there suddenly lost
all its centuries-old traditions? ■
Pomp and circumstance in Kandy, Sri Lanka,during an annual pilgrimage to venerate the Buddha’s tooth.
S E V E N  W R I T E R S  I N  A  W O R L D  O F  WO N D E R S
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
The soul of S u z h o u ’s gardens
The Suzhou gardens in southern China recreate nature in miniature to celebrate the
harmony between heaven and Earth. An initiate guides us along their winding paths,
decoding a host of refined symbols
LU WENFU
CHINESEWRITER
In the 13th century, the Ve n e t i a n
merchant and adventurer Marco
Polo was the first Westerner to
introduce Suzhou to Europe. Fo r
h i m , this paradise on Earth was
above all a flourishing silk-production
c e n t r e. L a t e r,other Europeans fascinated
by the city,which is criss-crossed by canals,
called it “the Venice of the Orient.” I n
the 1980s, I helped to spread Suzhou’s
fame by presenting it as a paradise for
gourmets in my novel,The Gourmet.A n d
w h e n , in 1997, UN E S C O inscribed Suzhou
on the World Heritage List because of
its classical gardens, the town’s reputation
acquired yet another dimension.
Cruel as they may be, human beings are children
of nature and cannot live without mountains,w a t e r,
g r a s s, t r e e s, sunshine and air. If we are far away
from those elements, we feel stifle d , ill at ease,
t r a p p e d .As soon as we can,we go on vacation. B u t
rather than travel,which can be a tiring, expensive
and even dangerous exercise, why not make a
replica of nature in miniature,“an artificial nature”
intended for daily use?
In Europe, for example,parks are huge.I m m e n s e
forests crossed by abundant rivers stretch as far as
the eye can see without any obstacles to mar nature’s
s p e c t a c l e.These parks are actually large stretches of
nature that have been “fenced off” and touched up
a bit by adding a building here and there on the
banks of a river or at the edge of the woods.
Chinese landscaped gardens,on the other hand,
put more emphasis on the idea of harmony between
heaven and Earth, a salient feature of Chinese
philosophy. The gardens of Suzhou are actually a
man-made landscape. Its designers have replicated
all of nature’s basic features in miniature on flat
ground.Since it is impossible to move mountains,
they built rock gardens. Since the courses of rivers
cannot be changed, they dug canals into the earth
and made water flow through them.And the ground
beneath Suzhou is so gorged with water that all it
takes is a hole three metres deep to create a pond.
The people who live there, without a false sense of
s h a m e, acknowledge that they have “ f a l s i f i e d ”
mountains and rivers. But that “falsification” is a
work of art in the fullest sense of the term and,
consequently, fundamentally truthful.
Rock gardens are the soul of Suzhou.The stones
of which they are made—the soul’s receptacle—
NORTH
KOREA
SOUTH
KOREA JAPAN
BEIJING
Suzhou Shanghai
Yellow Sea
Sea of
Japan
East China Sea
Rocks are the soul of the gardens and trees their most precious good.Here, in the  “Garden of the Master of Nets.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Born in 1928 in the Chinese
province of Jiangsu,Lu Wenfu has
lived in Suzhou since 1945.A
journalist,he  went on to become
a novelist and has won several
national literary prizes. Vice
President 
of the Association of Chinese
Writers, he is the founder 
and editor of the Suzhou
Magazine, published monthly. His
books translated into English
include
The Gourmet and Other Stories of
Modern China (Readers
International,1987).
LU WENFU
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 21
S E V E N  W R I T E R S  I N  A  W O R L D  O F  WO N D E R S
come from Lake Ta i , which is located near Suzhou.
Worn down by erosion, these delightful, steep rocks
were so famous that even the emperors of the distant
north sent their builders to bring them back to
decorate their gardens. The most famous and
precious among them are called “rock peaks.”Th e
assessment of their quality is based on three criteria.
They must be “ s l e n d e r ” rather than “ b u l k y,” t h e y
must contain horizontal as well as vertical “ t u n n e l s ” ;
and their surface must be wrinkled rather than
s m o o t h .
But there is more to creating a work of art than
piling up beautiful rocks. The first rock garden
m a s t e r s,highly skilled and very cultured craftsmen,
appeared at Suzhou under the Tang (618-907) and
Song (907-1271) dynasties, a period when gardens
were flourishing everywhere in China. Th e
successors of these first landscape designers were so
numerous and talented that under the Ming dynasty
( 1 3 6 8 - 1 6 4 4 ) , the town and its surrounding area was
dotted with between 200 and 300 gardens.To d a y, 7 7
are left,of which 27 have been designated national
l a n d m a r k s. But many of them are actually just large
courtyards containing small gardens decorated with
flo w e r s, p l a n t s, bamboo and rocks, like the ones
that were once found in most of Suzhou’s houses.
Changing the landscape with every
step: a rule of garden design
Qing Gu Yliang was an undisputed master under
the Qing dynasty (1644-1840). He created the
limestone “Mountain of the Villa of Embracing
B e a u t y ”1 (H u a n x i u) . Gu Yliang went blind towards
the end of his life, but his followers completed the
work under his supervision. And therein lies the
secret of the mountain’s beauty:it was built by the
master’s soul,rather than his hands. It is the exact
r e p l i c a , in miniature,of the real mountain that lived
in his heart. Its dimensions are modest—it covers
less than 500 square metres and its peaks are no
more than seven metres high. But the moment you
go inside,you feel as though you are walking into the
entrails of a huge, wild mountain located on the
edge of a winding gorge. And you think of these
words by Chen Congzhou,a current-day specialist
on Chinese gardens:“the mountain that looks like
a rock garden is strange; the rock garden that looks
like a mountain is a thing of wonder.”
H o w e v e r, it takes more than a mountain to
make a landscape.Water is another of the gardens’
crucial features. But to bring water to the gardens,
it is necessary to either make use of an already-
existing pond or stream,or dig into the ground.In
any case, the builders must know how to open
trenches and make water flow through them, t o
create and then re-unite the branches of a river. In
short,they must know how to imitate the bends of
a river in order to obtain what we call “ s i n u o u s
c u r r e n t s.” The masters of Suzhou excelled in this art.
Rivers mean bridges.The gardens of Suzhou are
dotted with all manner of miniature stone and wooden
s p a n s. For example, the “Garden of the Master of
N e t s ”1(Wa n g s h i y u a n) has a very pretty little bridge
that can be crossed in two or three strides.
Suzhou has mountains, r i v e r s,bridges—but what
about trees? A landscape with neither plants nor
flowers is a desert.Old trees are the most precious
feature of classical Chinese gardens because
anything is possible, including laying out a Suzhou
garden in the United States, except making an old
tree. In the  “Lingering Garden” 1(Liuyuan) there
is a thousand-year-old ginkgo tree.The shade of its
fan-shaped foliage is where the master decided to
build the rock garden.
Visitors to Suzhou must not be impatient.U n l i k e
Ve r s a i l l e s, where the splendid vista of palace and
park can be taken in with a single, sweeping glance,
the gardens of Suzhou are hidden behind narrow
streets like demoiselles in a boudoir.When you walk
into a garden, you might even feel a bit disappointed:
the first thing you see is a long, zig-zagging gallery.
This is the “winding path leading to serene beauty,”
a basic feature of the garden’s architecture.At fir s t
s i g h t , it may not look very interesting.But before you
know it, a patch of garden behind a wall will wink at
you through the latticework of a sculpted window.
Trees and pavilions can be made out in the distance.
After a few steps on a winding path, a magnific e n t
garden appears before your eyes.
“Changing the landscape with every step” i s
the second rule that must be observed in classical
Chinese garden design.The scene shifts as you walk
along. To avoid the impression of monotony and
r e p e t i t i o n , the designers erected walls pierced with
sculpted windows that divide the gardens into
The gardens are dotted with miniature stone and wooden spans.
1.Site inscribed on UNESCO’s World Heritage List.
2 . Two sentences of which certain words set up
relationships between them with corresponding
meanings and sounds. U s u a l l y, these “ m a t ch i n g ”
words occupy the same position in both sentences.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
several sections without obstructing a view of the
entire complex. Your eyes are never at rest in a
garden of Suzhou.At every turn, the sight of a rock,
a stand of bamboo or a banana tree takes the visitor
by surprise. Each plot of land has been designed to
resemble a splendid painting. A dead angle here
would be like a failed brushstroke.
This method of dividing up space with doors,
w i n d o w s, g a l l e r i e s, rock gardens and streams creates
the impression of contemplating a scale-model of
n a t u r e. It provides what we call “a glimpse of
grandeur through the miniature.”
Gardens inspired by poets,
painters and calligraphers
To d a y, landscape architects design projects
before building a park or playground.The masters
of the gardens of Suzhou had no plans. They took
their ideas from poetry. They also drew plenty of
inspiration from Chinese painters, who often
returned the compliment by exalting the beauty of
their works. Th u s, many painters, poets and
calligraphers helped to create the gardens of
Suzhou.
The gardens were never really fin i s h e d .As time
went by, they were enlarged, enhanced and
p e r f e c t e d .Once a rock garden,a stream or a pavilion
was completed, the masters had the custom of
inviting their lettered friends to savour famous
liqueurs and give free reign to their fertile
i m a g i n a t i o n s. The guests inscribed calligraphy on
the door lintels and parallel sentences on the
u p r i g h t s2.They also gave advice on where to build a
new bridge or pavilion. L a t e r, the masters
embellished the garden heeding the advice they had
received and invited their friends back to have a
drink and write poetry.
Had it been any other way, the gardens of
Suzhou probably would not have the refinement
that has made them so famous. ■
One must choose
pebbles the 
size of a goose
egg so that 
the paving
resembles the
brocade of the
Shu region.
Ji Cheng,
Chinese landscape artist
(1582-circa 1634)
Latticed windows sculpt space in the 
“Garden of Harmony.”
Classical Chinese garden design,which seeks to recreate
n a t u ral landscapes in  miniature, is nowhere better
i l l u s t rated than in the four gardens in the historic city of
Suzhou.Universally recognized as masterpieces of the genre,
they were inscribed on the World Heritage List in 1997. The
gardens reflect not only the profound importance of natural
beauty in Chinese culture, but also the political, economic and
cultural changes that took place in classical China.
Created between the 16th and 18th centuries, when classical
Chinese landscape design was at its height, the gardens of
Suzhou were designed to deeply satisfy both the minds and the
souls of the city’s inhabitants.To d a y, these microcosms, w h i c h
enclose all the basic features of nature and culture – water,
s t o n e, p l a n t s, b u i l d i n g s, poetry and painting – contribute to the
study of China’s architecture, human sciences, a e s t h e t i c s,
p h i l o s o p h y, b o t a n y, h y d raulic engineering, e n v i r o n m e n t a l
sciences and folk culture.
The  “Humble A d m i n i s t ra t o r ’s Garden” is the largest of the
four gardens (52,000 square metres). It contains a lake, w h i c h
covers one-fifth of its surface area, and a wide array of plant
s p e c i e s, including lotus,w i s t e r i a ,f o r s y t h i a s, trees and flo w e r i n g
s h r u b s. Its central part is a reproduction in miniature of the
lower Ya n g - T s e u - K i a n g , the world’s third-longest river after
the Amazon and the Nile.
The “Lingering Garden,” which stretches out over more than
23,000 square metres, contains the famous “cloud-shrouded
p e a k ” (a 6.5-metre-tall limestone formation) and the gardens’
most beautiful collection of engraved stele. It was designed by
Xu Taishi and dates back to the late 16th century.
The much smaller “Garden of the Master of Nets” ( 5 , 4 0 0
square metres) was built in the 18th century. Its most
distinguishing feature is a magnificent house with four
successive courtyards built in strict observance of feudal rules.
The smallest of the four gardens (less than 2,200 square
m e t r e s ) , and probably the oldest, is the “Garden of the
Mountain of the Villa of Embracing Beauty”, which belonged to
the royal academician Shen Shixing and housed the famous
“ m o u n t a i n ” designed by Qing Gu Yliang (see article). I t s
a r t i ficial glens, t ra i l s, g r o t t o s, g o r g e s, c l i f f s, crests and cliffs vie
with nature. ■
REFLECTIONS OF CHANGE IN CLASSICAL CHINA
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
A s a child, I thought of windmills as
helicopters flying over the landscape of
my imagination. Their astonishing
shapes looked both archaic and
futuristic to me. They were strange,
timeless machines sailing on the elements: earth,
water and wind.
Sometimes my father, a hydraulic engineer in
northern Brabant, took me on a polder (land
recovered from the sea),where a humpbacked mill-
keeper taught me the “ l a n g u a g e ” of windmills: “ a
windmill with its sails puffed out walks ‘on its head,’ ”
the gentleman told me. “During a storm, it walks
‘ b a r e - l e g g e d .’ ”Windmills could be either “ h a p p y ”o r
“in mourning,”they could work alone in the solitude
of a polder or in couples on the banks of a b o e ze m
(the basin of a polder near a river and above its
water level). Each visit was an adventurous
expedition to a land of make-believe,a world made
up of still, dark water covered with white foam, o f
musty reservoirs, rustling wind and strong scents.
When I went to Kinderdijk-Elshout, l o c a t e d
northwest of the Alblasserwaard (“land on the
w a t e r ’s edge”), I joyfully discovered that it smelled
like the pumping stations of my childhood.A smell
of fresh water, cool stones, diesel fuel,
grease and tools. C u r i o u s, the first thing I
did was walk over to the plant. I wandered
around the big machines,and ended up in
the repair shop. The sight from the bay
windows took my breath away. Th e
p o l d e r, the dikes along two canals, t h e
broad bed of the Lek river, the waving
reeds in the two upper basins, the 19
windmills stretching out as far as the
h o r i z o n , proudly holding up a dark and
threatening sky, looked as if they had
been painted by Ruysbroeck,R e m b r a n d t ,
Mesdag or some other brush-wielding
m a g i c i a n . Only a distant grey building and an odd-
looking apartment complex shaped like a ferryboat
reminded me that I was in the present.
The A l b l a s s e r w a a r d , which lies close by the sea
and at the mouth of several swollen rivers, h a s
always been threatened by water. It has been
flooded at least 30 times. The last deadly tide
swamped the area in 1953, killing 1,800 people. B u t
the saddest,and most famous flood is still the one
S E V E N  W R I T E R S  I N  A  W O R L D  O F  WO N D E R S
SERGE VAN DUIJNHOVEN
DUTCHWRITER
Irrigating time with 
the Kinderdijk windmills
It’s impossible to picture the Netherlands without windmills,
but they have done far more than inspire the great 
Flemish painters. Without them, half the country wouldn’t exist
When winter arrives,out come the skates:a feast on ice in Kinderdijk.
The Hague
Rotterdam
Amsterdam
B E L G I U M
North Sea
Kinderdijk
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
A writer and historian,Serge van
Duijnhoven is 
an all-round artist.Born in 1970
in Oss (Netherlands),he lives
and works in Brussels (Belgium)
where he created the group De
Spooksprekers, with 
the rapper Def P. and the
saxophone player and 
poet Olaf Zwetsloot.In 
collaboration with a theatre
troupe, he also founded 
the MillenniuM review.
His works include Obiit in 
orbit, a CD of poems and music
(Bezige Bij/Djax Records, 1998),
as well 
as poetry collections and fiction.
SERGE VAN DUIJNHOVEN
24
that occurred on the night of November 18 to 19,
1 4 2 1 ,when the water swallowed up some 60 villages.
Legend has it that a cat managed to keep a baby
rocking in its cradle in the middle of the roiling
w a v e s. The dike that the cradle landed on was
named Kinderdijk,“the child’s dike.”
Ready to serve if modern
equipment breaks down
Dutch history owes much to the windmills.Tr u e,
the western Netherlands could not have been built
without the dikes, but the windmills are what keep
the diked land habitable. Without them, half of
present-day Holland would not exist. The Dutch
would have ended up leaving the land,worn down
by their futile struggle against water.
“God created the world, but the Dutch created
H o l l a n d ,” said René Descartes. The Fr e n c h
philosopher was very familiar with the country for
having lived there a while, but he wasn’t entirely
r i g h t . More than 5,000 years ago, many places that
had been wrenched from the sea were already
i n h a b i t e d . The remains of a canoe and a female
skeleton (named Trijntje) were discovered during
work on the Betuwlijn, a new, highly controversial
railroad line.
The A l b l a s s e r w a a r d ’s earliest long drainage
canals were built in the 11th century. A hundred
years later, a dike already surrounded almost the
entire area and the basins of the two rivers that
flow across the Alblasserwaard,the Alblas and the
G i e s s e n , were developed.They became the districts
of the Nederwaard (“the low land”) and the
Overwaard (“the high land”). In 1277, Count Floris
V of Holland set up the district’s Water and Po l d e r
Administration,an organization in charge of dike
upkeep. But these efforts would not suffice. In the
aftermath of a major flood in 1726, it became
obvious that drainage mills were indispensable.
A first row of eight round,stone mills was built
in the Nederwaard in 1738. Two years later, t h e
same number of mills was erected in the Overwaard,
parallel to the first row, but this time they were
constructed of wood and had eight sides with
thatched roofs. As the years went by, this complex
grew with the addition of new mills, locks and
pumping stations. This innovative hydraulic
irrigation system acquired a reputation and became
known as “drainage by stages.” Fi r s t , the mills
drained water in the lower basins and polders.Th e n ,
they channeled it to raised reservoirs. Lastly, the
excess water passed through half a dozen locks
before draining into the river.
To d a y, the mills are kept in working order,r e a d y
to serve in the event modern equipment breaks
d o w n . And all of them are inhabited. A swing in a
little yard, vegetables in a garden, a fis h e r m a n ’s
rowboat moored between reeds provide a glimpse
into the occupants’ everyday lives. Just one mill is
open to the public during the summer. I n s i d e, you can
see not only the impressively-sized cogwheel,but also
picture the frugal life of a mill-keeper and his family.
Inside the mill itself, you feel as if you’re on a boat
in the middle of the sea.As it turns,all the ribs in the
woodwork creak. In the entrance, a dead muskrat
hangs in a cage.At the beginning of the last century,
the muskrats were imported for their fur from
America and the present-day Czech Republic, b u t
they soon became a veritable scourge for the
i n h a b i t a n t s ; their digging and scratching caused
major damage to the dikes. Even today, they are
hunted on a massive scale, cooked in wine sauce
and eaten under the more appetizing name of “ w a t e r
r a b b i t s.”
“I wouldn’t live in one of those windmills for
UNESCO inscribed the Kinderdijk-Elshout network of
windmills on the World Heritage List in 1997. Th e
network attests to the ingenuity and bravery of the Dutch
p e o p l e, who developed a highly intelligent hydraulic system
to stabilize and cultivate a large stretch of peat bog in the
Netherlands.
Located on the northwest edge of the A l b l a s s e r waard (“land
on the water’s edge”),the complex helped drain the inner
districts of the Overwaard (“the high land”) and the
N e d e r waard (“the low land”) until 1950, when the mills
were closed. The 19 remaining mills are still in opera t i n g
condition.
The site and its upstream and downstream polders, e q u i p p e d
with natural drainage systems, rivers and streams, w i n d m i l l s,
pumping stations and spillwa y s, have remained virtually
unchanged since the 18th century.Today this typically Dutch
landscape is officially protected as a cultural monument and
a natural reserve. ■
Hear the creaking ribs of the woodwork.
AN INGENIOUS SYS T E M
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 25
anything in the world,”says Henk Bronkhorst, w h o
manages them for the polder authority.“ Th e y ’re too
humid, too cramped and too inconvenient!” And
yet,he feels passionate about the mills and is glad
to see them on UN E S C O’s World Heritage List.“ Th a t
recognition will probably help us save them from
being torn down”,he says.
Wine and poetry for the
new windmill inspectors
I n d e e d ,Dutch windmills have suffered a terrible
f a t e. There were nearly 10,000 of them in 1860.
To d a y, just 900 remain. I n d e e d , it is nothing short of
a miracle that so many mills at Kinderdijk have
been preserved. In 1950, the Polder A d m i n i s t r a t i o n
was preparing to tear down all the mills that were
“out of service.” Replaced by diesel-powered
hydraulic pumps that could evacuate water much
f a s t e r, they were perceived as useless and too
expensive to maintain.But the worldwide renown
they have acquired will help to assure their future,
and Bronkhorst hopes it will be easier for him to
raise money for their restoration.“We really need
it.The stone of the round mills has become porous
over the years and a fifth mill is collapsing,” he says.
Managing the windmill area is no easy task. Th e
local communities,f a r m e r s,Calvinist ministers,b u s i n e s s
people and officials regularly quarrel over their upkeep,
the building of access roads and parking lots and the
cost of restoration projects.The site’s inscription on the
World Heritage List has spurred the creation of an
organization in charge of managing the interests of
all the windmills within the designated area.
At the entrance to Kinderdijk,west of the locks,
stands the Gemeenlandshuis, the community house.
This is where officials gather to assess the danger in
d i f ficult times and decide on
which measures to take.
During senior-level meetings,
they share a large meal in a
room adorned with paintings
by 17th-century masters.Th e
Overwaard inspection
authority used to welcome
its new high-level members
by serving them wine in cups
that could contain up to one
l i t r e.Each new member was
asked to drink it all in one
g u l p, before writing a poem
in the community house
b o o k .One of them goes like
t h i s : “the cup was offered to
my lips/with these words:
drink up, c o m r a d e / b e c a u s e
you took the risk/here we
push away water, not wine.”
The inspectors used every
means at their disposal in
their war against water—
even the muses!
I t ’s easy to reach the
Overwaard windmills from
the community house. The
closer you get to the central
dike, the further back you go in time.Automobiles
give way to peacefully grazing cows and sheep.Th e
only sounds you hear are the chattering of aquatic
birds such as bitterns,purple herons and sea martins,
the crowing of a rooster and reeds rustling in the
w i n d .You can smell the fragrance of ripe apples that
have fallen from the trees. I remain silent at the
sight of five moss-green umbrellas sheltering the
patience of a few old men fishing.The wings of the
mills turn stubbornly as gales can reach force six on
the Beaufort scale.
But what are the windmills draining? What are
they transporting from one place to another?
The Kinderdijk landscape symbolizes an
endangered species, the typical Dutch windmill.
But for the people of the Netherlands, it also
symbolizes their never-ending struggle to keep their
l a n d . “ The land is still sinking,” says Henk
B r o n k h o r s t ,“and the water level has risen in the past
few decades. We had to add another reservoir, a
sort of funnel, to the upper basin to be able to
collect more water, as well as an extra pump for the
locks.”
Weapons to push back the 
sea’s never-ending advance
Galloping on his nag Rocinante, Don Quixote
tried to attack the windmills. With windmills as
their only weapons, the Dutch are trying to push
back the sea’s never-ending advance.According to
some forecasts, in a few hundred years the
Netherlands will no longer exist because of global
warming. Water will take back from people what
they have taken from her.Time will tell if they will
have been as bold as the lord of La Mancha, Don
Quixote.
The farms and
cottages lie quiet
and dejected in
the barren land
and the only
things alive are
the windmills . . .
whose strong
sails catch the
force of wind
thrashed with 
the rains.
Henri Polak, Dutch politician
and writer (1868-1943)
S E V E N  W R I T E R S  I N  A  W O R L D  O F  WO N D E R S
Being inside a windmill is not unlike stepping onto a boat rocked by the seas.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The tre a s u res 
in Mauritania’s
d u n e s
Once, Mauritania’s ksours were thriving
centres of trade and learning. Today, the
country is struggling to save them from
sand, wind and oblivion 
26
MOUSSA OULD EBNOU
MAURITANIAN WRITER
Waves of white, beige and red sand
incessantly blow from the north and
s o u t h , crashing against the purplish
mass of the A d r a r,a mountain range
that crosses Mauritania between the
Majabat El Koubra and Aouker deserts.The dunes
conceal four jewels:Ouadane and Chinguetti in the
n o r t h ,Tichitt and Oualata in the southeast.These old,
stone-built cities date back to the 12th and 13th
centuries and were once very prosperous,but today
they only barely survive in such a hostile
e n v i r o n m e n t . O u a d a n e, C h i n g u e t t i ,
Tichitt and Oualata may be drawing their
last breath, but they are essential to
understanding the history of this area,
whose fate was closely linked to the water
table and the trade routes that span the
M a g h r e b, the Sahel and black A f r i c a .
These cities, known as k s o u r s— o f
which Chinguetti was probably the most
famous—were located on major caravan
r o u t e s, and over the centuries turned
into metropolises of trans-Saharan trade,
especially in gold and salt. Th e
Chanaguita [inhabitants of Chinguetti]
were skilled merchants who established regular
contacts with the Maghreb, Egypt and Arabia to the
n o r t h , and Guinea, Côte d’Ivoire and Nigeria to
the south,playing an important part in the spread of
both Arabic and Islamic culture. Trade caravans
from Chinguetti sometimes employed over 30,000
camels carrying salt, w o o l ,g u n p o w d e r,d a t e s,m i l l e t ,
wheat and barley. They returned from the south
with gold powder, slaves, ivory, animal hides and
ostrich feathers. These goods were subsequently
resold in Cairo, S i j i l m a s s a , Fez and above all
T l e m c e n , where Venetians and Genoese traders
stocked up in the two f o n d o u k s that were specially
set aside for them.
According to some sources, the origins of
O u a l a t a , which means “shady place” in Berber,
probably date back to a period preceding Islam. B y
the 13th and 14th centuries, Oualata had become
such an important trading centre that its name
appeared on European maps. A great Muslim
f a m i l y, the Maqqaris,had built a warehouse there for
gathering goods from the south and storing
merchandise from the north before they were
resold.Oualata was also where pilgrims from west
Africa assembled before travelling on to Chinguetti,
a departure point for the annual caravan to Mecca.
This pilgrimage had made the city so famous that for
a long time Mauritania was known as Bilad
Chinguel—the land of Chinguetti.
Libraries and schools
guard priceless manuscripts
A major trade route connected Oualata with
O u a d a n e,which was a very prosperous city,e s p e c i a l l y
between the 14th and 18th centuries.But trade was not
its sole source of wealth. Learning has always been
extremely important to Mauritanians. S u n n i t e
Muslims of the Malikite rite, they turned their k s o u r s
into renowned intellectual centres that attracted
many foreign students.To this day, their libraries and
m a d r a s a s [ Koranic schools] have jealously preserved
some 40,000 priceless manuscripts.At one time up to
M O R O C C O
S E N E G A L
A L G E R I A
NOUAKCHOTT
Chinguetti Ouadane
Oualata
Tichitt
M A U R I T A N I A
Atlantic Ocean
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
40 scholars lived on the same street in Ouadane,or at
least that’s what people say.And if the etymology of
the city’s name is any indication,that was most likely
t r u e, since it means “the city of the two wadis”: t h e
wadi of the palm trees and the wadi of knowledge.
Benefiting from its location on the route
between Oualata and Ouadane,Tichitt grew into a
m a g n i ficent city.The town’s multi-storied houses—
with blind walls on the ground flo o r, a door for
only opening to the outside and façades built of
coloured stones—are fragile remnants of typical
Mauritanian architecture.
The buildings’ subdued polychrome stands in
sharp contrast to the exuberant façades in Oualata,
where the doors, porches, vents and windows are
trimmed with white drawings against a reddish-
brown undercoat. The rosettes around the lustral
stones are especially beautiful. People living here
brush their fingers over them before performing
ritual ablutions with water that has often been in
short supply in a town whose narrow streets are
stifled by sand and dust.
But Oualata’s most famous paintings adorn the
walls of inner courtyards. Composed of simple,
endlessly repeated designs, these arabesques show
the stairs, d o o r s, w i n d o w s, alcoves and openings off
to their best advantage. They are usually painted
with a substance made of brown ochre, c h a r c o a l ,
gum and cow pat.
Children’s laughter replaced by
the stubborn whistling of the wind
These decorations are typical of Oualata. I n
O u a d a n e, on the other hand, the houses were built
of pink or grey sandstone and a mortar made of
clay and straw.All the walls in the city were covered
with clay to protect them from the scarce rain,g i v i n g
them an extremely sober,r e fined appearance.To d a y,
this coating only remains in places, testimony to the
decrepit state that the entire city has fallen into.
The laughter of children running through the narrow,
astonishingly angular streets and up cramped stairs
between two blocks of houses has faded away.Th e
teeming throngs have vanished forever. A single
sound now breaks this realm of silence: the whistling
of the wind as it stubbornly blows against ghostly
f a ç a d e s. O u a d a n e ’s families have moved to a small
part of the “upper town,” deserting all the other
S E V E N  W R I T E R S  I N  A  W O R L D  O F  WO N D E R S
The arabesques on
Oualata’s walls
still inspire the
drawings traced
on women’s hands
(see photo p. 26).
Deserts stir our
emotions because
they represent
Nature as it was
before human
beings came on
the scene. They
also show us
what it may be
like after we
have
disappeared.
Théodore Monod,
French naturalist 
(1902-)
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 27
Defying time: the entrance to a mosque in Chinguetti.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
s a n d . Legend has it that seven towns have been
superimposed on this site, and the one that has
come down to us today is irretrievably sinking
beneath the dunes. Only the upper stories of a few
houses are visible—the rest has been swallowed
by the sand.As recently as a century ago, this oasis
was farmland that produced enough food to feed a
population of several thousand inhabitants.To d a y,
the few wind-battered palm trees are dying, half-
buried in sand.The final blow came last year, w h e n
torrential rains destroyed 80 percent of the town.
L u c k i l y,the splendid mosque and its square minaret,
the most beautiful building of all,survived.
Musicians still sing the glory
of life in the ksours
Although Mauritania’s old towns have lost
ground to the Sahara in the north and the Sahel in the
s o u t h , along with suffering a devastating, d e c a d e s -
long drought,they refuse to go quietly into the night.
The creative genius of ancient civilizations is still
the driving force behind Mauritanian culture. Th e
designs on Oualata’s walls are the same as those still
drawn on the hands and feet of Mauritanian women.
They can also be found in jewelry, leatherwork and
w o o d w o r k , the embroidery on men’s garments, t h e
dye of women’s veils,the weave of traditional carpets
and even the bills of the nation’s currency, t h e
o u g u i y a. The melodies of Va l a , a famous musician
from Chinguetti who has become an emblematic
figure of Mauritanian music, are still played on the
t i d i n i t, the Moorish lute. Other traditional
c o m p o s i t i o n s, such as the a w d i d , which was once
performed as the Tichitt caravans were being loaded,
immortalize the various aspects of life in the k s o u r s
when they were at the height of their glory.
Thus tradition is passed down from one
generation to the next, like the beams that still
pump water from old wells in the small farm plots
and nonchalantly bow up and down across the
centuries. ■
In 1996, the old Mauritanian k s o u r s of Ouadane, C h i n g u e t t i ,
Tichitt and Oualata were included on the World Heritage List
as the last vestiges of traditional desert life. Each of these towns
is typical of the settlement pattern of nomad populations. E a c h
has a few main streets that served as the cara vans’ access
roads or led directly to the palm groves and cemeteries. A l l
were surrounded by defensive wa l l s, today reduced to a few
f ra g m e n t s, which marked the limits between the old k s o u r a n d
newer neighbourhoods.Their architecture also developed to meet
the requirements of nomad life: houses were used to store
goods most of the year, while the inhabitable rooms fulfil l e d
various functions depending on the season or time of day.
These four medieval towns are the last existing ksours. They
were trade and religious centres as well as focal points of
Islamic culture that housed tens of thousands of ancient
m a n u s c r i p t s. Despite local and regional confli c t s, d r o u g h t ,
f a m i n e s, epidemics and the end of the cara van tra d e, they have
survived to this day. I s o l a t i o n ,new administrative and economic
centres in other parts of Mauritania and the constant outflo w
of their inhabitants have nevertheless further jeopardized
their existence.
At the request of Mauritania’s government, UNESCO launched
an international campaign in 1978 aimed at preserving these
cities and funded restoration and conservation work, e s p e c i a l l y
to save the mosques.Two years later, the Mauritanian Scientific
Research Institute set up a photographic and documentary
archive. In 1993, the Mauritanian government created the
National Foundation for the Preservation of Ancient Towns,
whose purpose is to help the towns overcome the causes of
their decline and revitalize them with integrated preserva t i o n
and development progra m m e s. A project to preserve and
renew Mauritania’s cultural heritage funded by the Wo r l d
Bank also includes the old towns in its remit. ■
The author is one of Mauritania’s
greatest Frenchlanguage novelists.
He currently serves as cultural
advisor to his country’s president.
Moussa Ould Ebnou has written
two novels, L’amour impossible
and Le Barzakh, published by
L’Harmattan in Paris in 1990 and
1994 respectively.
MOUSSA OULD EBNOU
Intricate designs adorn the interior of a house in Oualata.
n e i g h b o u r h o o d s. And if a few buildings are still
standing in the rest of the city, it is thanks to the
foresight of their builders,who provided them with
ledges to protect them from rain and wind erosion.
In Chinguetti too the sand has slowly invaded
the courtyards of abandoned houses, to the point
that the floors of formerly inhabited rooms lying
under collapsed stone walls are now more than one
metre below street level. But this city remains “ t h e
soul of the country,” and population loss has been
less severe than in Ouadane, Tichitt and Oualata.
The square minaret of its famous mosque, which was
the national symbol of Bilad Chinguel for a long
time, is still afoot and defying time.
By contrast, Ti c h i t t , located in a basin at the
foot of the Adrar, is much less protected from the
T R A D E , RELIGION AND CULT U R E
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
RAFAEL SEGOVIA
MEXICANWRITER
Nestled in a narrow gorge of the Sierra
Madre in the heart of Mexico,
Guanajuato is one of those post-
Columbian towns hewn out of rock that
seem to spring straight from the
m o u n t a i n s. Contrasting with the arid landscape of
Cuanaxhuata (“the hill of the frogs”), this elegant
4 5 0 - y e a r-old dame of the Spanish Era continues to
protect herself behind fortifications from the region’s
fierce winds, just as she did for three centuries against
repeated attacks by the nomadic Chichemeca
p e o p l e, sworn enemies of the Spanish conquerors.
The town lies above a network of subterranean
s t r e e t s. Its majestic old mansions, baroque and neo-
classical churches, palaces, convents and hospitals
have all the charm of a bygone era.
Narrow winding streets that faithfully espouse
the uneven terrain echo with the footsteps of times
past and the crystalline tinkle of fountains splashing
onto stone slabs.And a touch of forbidden romance
still hovers on the Callejón del Beso (“Street of
the Kiss”), which is so narrow that a Romeo and
Juliet who once lived opposite each other stole
furtive embraces leaning from their balconies.Th e i r
story ended sadly: she was shut away in a convent
and he was forced to flee into exile.
The tale of a zealous explorer
who dug for hidden treasure
The spirit of Guanajuato, guarded by its stone
w a l l s, is impregnated by a rich memory which
d o e s n ’t trap the town in a sleepy past.Once upon a
time, it had just a single street that wound its way
through the rocks to reach a vast esplanade,now the
Plaza de los Pastitos. Today, modern highways cut
through the mountains, giving better access to this
tourist and university town, which is also an
economic and cultural centre.
The little provincial burg of 50,000 inhabitants
has been stirred from its slumber by the thousands
of tourists crowding its outdoor cafés, b y
businessmen drawn to its prosperity, by miners who,
like their forebears, still dig gold and silver out of the
g r o u n d ,and by students who liven up a multitude of
small squares with their youthful enthusiasm.
Not to mention the din that has engulfed the
town every October for the past 20 years or so when
the Cervantino dramatic arts festival draws leading
international performers along with hordes of
onlookers—and not always the most educated sort.
Their noisy revelling drove the townspeople to ask
the federal government to
abolish the prestigious
cultural event.
As I make my way
through this crowd, I cannot
help wondering what life
would have been like had
this town followed a more
tranquil course than its
turbulent history.At times a
bustling metropolis, a t
others a sleepy village,
Guanajuato has evolved
with the flow of political events and the ups and
downs of the mining industry.This chequered course
seems to have left its stamp on the local mentality.
Aware of their precarious existence,living off chance
d i s c o v e r i e s, forever waiting for riches while fearing
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 29
G u a n a j u a t o : fortunes made of silver
Once home to the world’s largest silver mine, this Mexican town has bred many zealous
and fiercely devout souls. Today, flocks of tourists, university students and a prestigious
theatre festival kindle its spirit
S E V E N  W R I T E R S  I N  A  W O R L D  O F  WO N D E R S
BELIZE
U N I T E D S T A T E S
GUATEMALA
MEXICO
Guanajuato
M E X I C O
Gulf of Mexico
Pacific Ocean
The town’s 50,000 inhabitants are aware of their fragile existence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
To say the least,this Mexican
writer, born in 1951,feels at
home in all the arts, from
photography and filmmaking to
the theatre, television and video. A
literature professor and prolific
author of literary essays, Rafael
Segovia has co-ordinated a string
of cultural events. He notably
staged a performance presented
at the 1986 Cervantino festival of
dramatic arts, The Poets’
Altarpiece, or Love and Death in
the Golden Age.A collection of his
numerous literary essays is
forthcoming.
RAFAEL SEGOVIA
30
p o v e r t y, the inhabitants of Guanajuato are cautious,
stubborn and fiercely devout.
To prove the point, take the zeal of one A n t o n i o
de Ordoñez, who convinced himself that he would
unearth a hidden treasure. When the Va l e n c i a n a
m i n e,five kilometres from the town,was abandoned
in 1760, he refused to believe its resources were
exhausted and began a long and arduous prospection
of the area.The adventure took him to the brink of
death and despair but his belief was not to be shaken.
After four years, his companions nearly gave up
on him, but he used his gifts as a preacher,
alternating sermons and prayers, to persuade them
to continue with their quest. Four more years of
ordeals and suffering passed. And then the longed-
for miracle occurred. Antonio de Ordoñez
discovered the Veta Madre, the Valenciana mother
lode, one of the richest in the world.
A 525-metre descent into 
the bowels of the earth
Ordoñez became wealthy and Guanajuato
turned into the world’s biggest silver mine. L i k e
many other mines in the region, it is still in
operation.Its main shaft is 525 metres deep and it
has almost 40 kilometres of galleries. In the
beginning, the workers went down slanting steps
more than 700 metres into the bowels of the earth.
Each miner had to climb them 14 times a day
carrying 75 kilos of ore every time.This gives an idea
of the wealth the Spanish Empire amassed over
three centuries.
To thank God for rewarding his efforts, O r d o ñ e z
decided to offer part of the riches he had drawn
from the earth, so he built a magnificent church, o n e
of the most impressive in the whole country. The
altarpiece covered with gold leaf, the rich decoration
and still largely intact paintings and artifacts make
La Valenciana church a unique example of
Churrigueresque art, the Mexican baroque that
smoothly combines Indian and Spanish styles.
Once the bastion of the 
strictest Catholic morality
A quick tour of Guanajuato suffices to
understand the predominant role played by the
Catholic church. In the 17th and 18th centuries
a l o n e, more than 15 convents, t e m p l e s, c h u r c h e s
and chapels were built in an area of less than two
square kilometres,which is today the old city centre.
Such religious zeal is also reflected in the street
n a m e s.Calle del Campanero (“Bellringer Street”),
for example, commemorates Luis A n t o n i o
S o l o r z a n o, the Santa Fé parish bellringer who ruled
the townspeople’s lives at the beginning of the 20th
c e n t u r y, letting them know when it was time for
m a s s, when wakes for the dead were being held
a n d , if necessary,when the curfew hour had arrived.
For many years Guanajuato was a bastion of the
strictest Catholic morality. The inhabitants, l o c k e d
inside the town as if in one huge house,all knew each
other and anyone who broke the rules of decency was
singled out for reproach. It was fertile ground for all
kinds of outlandish passions, which Jo r g e
Ibagüengoitia wove into thoughtful and humorous
s t o r i e s. The work of this warm-hearted, t a l e n t e d
Guanajuato native, who died young in 1983, s t i l l
inspires Mexican playwrights and new wave
fil m m a k e r s, immortalizing the surreal and
conservative mood of this little town slowly being
eclipsed by modern life. ■
Founded by the Spanish at the beginning of the 16th
c e n t u r y, the town of Guanajuato, capital of the state of the
same name, became the world’s leading centre of silver
e x t raction in the 18th century. Located in the centre of Mexico,
Guanajuato has always had a symbiotic relationship with its
m i n e s. Everything in the town testifies to this: its picturesque
“ s u b t e r ranean streets,” its sumptuous churches like La
Compañía and La Valenciana which are considered to be
among the finest examples of baroque architecture in Centra l
and South A m e r i c a , the construction of numerous dams and
h y d raulic installations, not to mention the mines themselves.
The deepest shaft, the Boca del Infierno (“Mouth of Hell”)
plunges down a breathtaking 600 metres. The historic town
of Guanajuato and its adjacent mines were added to the Wo r l d
Heritage List in 1988. ■
Narrow lanes echo tales of forbidden romance.
MARRIED TO THE MINE
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 31
S E V E N  W R I T E R S  I N  A  W O R L D  O F  WO N D E R S
ALFRED A.YUSON
FILIPINOWRITER
Filipinos often refer to the Banaue rice
terraces as the eighth wonder of the world,
and understandably so.Of all the exquisitely
sculpted rice terraces which climb the slopes
of the Cordillera in Luzon, the largest island
in the Philippine archipelago, those of Banaue are the
finest expression of the genius of local tribes.With the
terraces of Mayoyao,Kiangan and Hungduan, t h e y
represent a “ t r a d e m a r k ” of Ifugao culture. As the
Filipino architect and conservationist Au g u s t o
Villalon has written, “the terraces are the only
Philippine monument constructed without any
foreign influence or intervention, and without
enforced labour of any kind.” They endow the
province of Ifugao with a unique landscape,born of
a harmonious complicity between human beings
and their environment.
For the past two millennia, rice has
been planted under the harshest conditions,
at an altitude of over 1,000 metres. To
construct their terraces, farmers first have
to identify concave areas, place stone
markers there and fill the cracks in the
slope with gravel to avoid slippage.As each
layer of walling is added,the level of soil is
r a i s e d ,with some walls reaching six metres
in height. Without animals and only
rudimentary tools, these farmers have patiently
recarved the steep mountain slopes, respecting their
natural curves.Sometimes no larger than three metres,
the terraces are irrigated by an ingenious system.
Bamboo conduits of different diameters deliver just
the right amount of water to the young rice shoots. A
complex  system allows the water run-off to flo w
downhill and flood the terrace next in line.
The best rice is cultivated by the poorest farmers on the highest,most inaccessible terraces.
Dancing anew on 
the stairways to heaven
Safeguarding the spectacular rice terraces of the Philippines begins with
preserving the culture of those who created them.
In August, after nearly 50 years of silence, the drums of Ifugao
priests once again resounded across the mountains of Luzon
Island, marking a revival of ancestral customs
MALAYSIA
MANILA
Bontoc
Sulu 
Sea
South 
China 
Sea
Banaue
Philippine 
Sea
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Author of poetry collections,
novels, essays and children’s
stories, Alfred A.Yuson is vice
chairman of the Writers’ Union of
the Philippines.A documentary
filmmaker and scriptwriter, he
teaches literature at Ateneo de
Manila University. He has received
several literary distinctions,
including the Centennial Literary
Prize (marking the independence
of the Philippines) for his novel
Voyeurs & Savages (Anvil
Publishing Inc.,1998).His most
recent work is an essay entitled 
The Word on Paradise (Office of
Research & Publications,Ateneo
de Manila University, 2000).
ALFRED A.YUSON
32
Here, men and women repeat the gestures and
practices of their ancestors.Like 2000 years ago, t h e y
use only organic fertilizers and pesticides of plant
o r i g i n , harvested in the neighbouring forests.Th o s e
who own the lower, larger terraces are the wealthy
e l i t e, while the peasants till the upper, n a r r o w e r
s p a c e s. The Ifugao people prize their t i n a w o n, a
fragrant homegrown upland rice,preferring it to the
commercial lowland variety. Other staples such as
sweet potatoes are also grown in forest clearings,b u t
only rice is prepared during celebratory feasts—
along with chicken and pork.
After Ferdinand Magellan reached the
Philippines in 1521, the Spanish easily occupied the
lowlands. But they encountered stiff opposition in
the mountains from what they called “restless and
warlike tribes.” Headhunting by certain tribes
particularly appalled and infuriated the Spanish,
who mounted punitive expeditions with such
regularity that today the episodes read like a game
of tag carried on between two cultures over  three
centuries.
But the Spanish never pacified the mountain
p e o p l e s. It was not until the American occupation that
began in 1898 and the opening of the highlands by
army engineers that the tribes were finally subdued.
American Episcopalian missions then met with more
success than the Spanish attempts at Christianization.
Selling the gods for
large sums of money
Despite a strong missionary presence that lasted
a full century, the Ifugao continued to cling to their
animistic beliefs.The b u l - o l or rice god is a particularly
revered figure in their pantheon. A pair of b u l - o l
figures carved from hardwood stands watch over
each family’s granary. During ceremonial rituals,
Ifugao elders slaughter chickens, recite divine
incantations and pour the sacrificial blood over the
head of the b u l - o l s for a good harvest.Even though
the tradition of honouring the b u l - o l remains strong,
it has become difficult to find a finely carved,a n t i q u e
rice god strapped to the wall of an Ifugao house.
Families have long since learned to part with their
heirlooms in return for large sums from itinerant
c o l l e c t o r s.
There have been other changes:fewer of these
families can now claim to live solely off the terraces.
They require extensive repairs, and the irrigation
system must be dredged periodically.With a growing
p o p u l a t i o n , each child inherits a smaller plot of
land.And sadly, most of the younger generation—
attracted to the lures of city life—are reluctant to
undertake the laborious chore of rice farming.Th e
highlands account for seven percent of the total
land area of the Philippines, but are home to less
than two percent of the country’s population.
Aware that the rice terraces are at risk, t h e
Filipinos have made them a national affair. Th e
government declared them “national treasures”in
1 9 7 3 ,and a little over a decade ago, established the
autonomous Cordillera Administrative Region
(CA R) to encompass all the land-locked provinces
of the Cordillera mountains.
But while several programmes have focused on
the physical preservation of the terraces, using a
scientific and technological approach, few efforts
have been taken to preserve the indigenous cultures
that created them.And it is widely believed that if
this culture dies, the farming practices will go as
well.
In mid-August 2000,the National Commission
for Culture and the Arts (N C CA) spearheaded the
revival of a farming ritual called Pa t i p a t w h i c h
m u m b a k i (Ifugao holy men) had celebrated for the
last time in 1944. So after many years of silence, t h e
tagtags once again resounded in the village of
A m d u n t o g. Beating rhythmically on these wooden
s h i e l d s, menfolk dance through the rice fields to
drive away evil spirits and rats, which eat crops and
dig burrows, causing seepage and erosion.
“After chanting invocations and offering animal
s a c r i fic e, the mumbaki joined several males from the
village in the beating of the tagtag,” observed the
Filipino writer Dexter Osorio. “All were dressed
in the traditional red loincloths of the Ifugao and
adorned with the crimson leaves of the Ti plant or
d o n g l a, which are used for special rituals. Th e
percussive sounds resulted in a complex rhythm of
interlocking beats, to which the line of performers
h a l f - a r c h e d , half-danced as they made their way
around the village. Leading the line was a spear-
Filipinos are intent on
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 33
wielding m u n g g i h i g i, who punctuated the beat with
spear thrusts and an occasional whoop echoed by the
other participants.At the edge of the rice terraces, the
group was met by another parade of dancers from the
neighbouring village of Nalnay, half of whom were
children who beat their shields with an enthusiasm
that rivalled those of their elder counterparts.The two
lines of paraders merged in a controlled orgy of sound,
colour and motion,and proceeded to make their way
down through the terraces toward the river,where the
rats and bad spirits were meant to drown.A member of
the Nalnay contingent confessed that their older men
did not want to join the ritual, so it was the children who
did.”
Like Dexter Osorio,we might well wonder whether
Ifugao culture itself isn’t suffering from erosion.“ E v e r
since standardized Western education and Christianity
was introduced to the Cordilleras,” he writes,“age-old
rituals have been set aside and traditional beliefs
forgotten, resulting in apathy and an eroded sense of
identity.”
Still the enthusiastic participation of children in the
ritual is a promising sign. Cultural erosion may not be
i r r e v e r s i b l e. H o p e f u l l y, it isn’t too late to keep alive the
genius of our ancestors, who shaped these magnific e n t
stairways to bring us closer to heaven. ■
Located in the northern Philippines, Luzon is the largest of 7,000 islands dotting the
Philippine archipelago.Rice terraces blanket steep mountain slopes, spreading across an
area of 20,000 km2. Inscribed on the World Heritage List in 1995, the four clusters of terra c e s
found in the municipalities of Banaue, M a y o ya o, Kiangan and Hungduan are all located in
Ifugao province.
The terraces evoke a harmony that has been preserved between the inhabitants and their
e n v i r o n m e n t . Each cluster is surrounded by a buffer ring of private forests (m u y o n g) ,m a n a g e d
according to tribal pra c t i c e s. Covered by steeply pitched thatched pyramidal roofs,the villages’
one-room dwellings are raised above the ground on four posts and reached by a ladder which
is pulled up at night.
A centrally located ritual rice field is the first parcel to be planted or harvested. Near the
dwellings is the ritual hill,usually marked by a grove of sacred betel trees where the holy men
(m u m b a k i) carry out traditional rites.
For the past 2,000 years,knowledge of these rituals and farming practices has been passed
o ra l l y.These methods are the expression of the Ifugao’s mastery of watershed ecology and
t e r race engineering. In the past decades, many terraces have been abandoned and
deforestation has caused serious damage.As farming of the terraces is intricately connected
with religious,c u l t u ral and social tra d i t i o n s,a whole system of values has to be preserved.Th e
absence of a broad vision having led to sporadic attempts at preserva t i o n , the Ifugao Te r ra c e s
C o m m i s s i o n , created in February 1994, developed a six-year master that takes a holistic
a p p r o a c h . ■
S E V E N
To this day, the
terraces endure,
but more
importantly, 
they continue 
to function. 
Fidel Ramos, former Philippine
president (1928-)
THE ENDURING ROLE OF RITUA L
© McCurry/Magnum, Paris
 on preserving their rice terraces,which were declared “national treasures”in 1973.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
JUAN GOYTISOLO
SPANISHWRITER
Je m â a - e l - F n a ’s thousand and o n e
My first contact with oral tradition on
Marrakesh’s Jemâa-el-Fna square
led me to start thinking about the
s p e c i fic nature of written literature,
and the differences between these
two modes of expression.In oral communication,
the speaker can refer to the context at any time:in
other words, to a specific situation with which the
listeners are familiar. In written literature, the author
and reader have nothing in common aside from
the text written by the former and membership (by
birth or learning) in the same linguistic community.
Oral literature establishes a line of communication
between a speaker and a listener, both of whom
experience the world in a similar or even identical
w a y. Reading a novel,on the other hand, e s t a b l i s h e s
communication between a narrator and a reader; t h e
former is unable to verify whether the latter
p o s s e s s e s, at the time of reading, s u f f i c i e n t
knowledge of the context to understand the text.
That is why the reader, distant from the text in
space and/or time, needs an intermediary to recreate
the context and fill in the gaps. Hence the presence
in translated novels of the editor’s or translator’s
explanatory notes.
In the h a l c a, the circle of listeners and spectators
that forms around the storyteller, none of that is
necessary. The storyteller addresses these people
d i r e c t l y ; they are his accomplices.The text he recites
or improvises functions like a score, leaving the
performer a wide margin of freedom. In the oral
tradition,changes in voice and oratorical rhythm,
expressions and gestures, play a fundamental role:
even a seemingly sacred text can be parodied and
Born in 1931 in Barcelona,Juan
Goytisolo lives 
in Paris and Marrakesh.
His numerous essays, short
stories and novels—including in
English Marks of Identity, Count
Julian, 
The Marx Family Saga, Space in
Motion, Quarantine: a Novel
and Juan the Landless—have
won him international renown.
His most recent works published
in English are Marrakesh Tales
(Serpents Tail), Landscapes of
War (City Lights Books) and
Inferno and Paradiso (Actar
Editorial).
JUAN GOYTISOLO
The oral traditions of Marrakesh’s famous square are unique in the world
for their richness and variety. They are also the roots of a new concept:
humanity’s oral and intangible heritage
There is no other square like this in the world.Every day, musicians,storytellers,dancers,jugglers and bar
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 35
S E V E N  W R I T E R S  I N  A  W O R L D  O F  W O N D E R S
lowered to a scatological level. In children’s stories
and chansons de geste, the frequent use of para-
linguistic devices and cynegetic sketches (which
evoke hunting), stresses the magic, power or
dramatic aspects of the episodes being told.
As my knowledge of d a r i x a ( M o r o c c o ’s A r a b i c
dialect) improved, I was able to appreciate the
richness and variety of the oral traditions preserved
within Marrakesh’s Jemâa-el-Fna square. I attended
performances of classical works like The T h o u s a n d
and One Nights a n d A n t a r i a, legends based on X e h a,
A i ch a and K a n d i x a—to mention just three popular
folk heroes—comic improvisations,and a number of
sexual pantomimes by highly talented h a l a i q u i s
( s t o r y t e l l e r s ) , of whom Saruh and Bakchich, b o t h
now dead, merit a special mention.They expressed
themselves effortlessly in the spectators’ dialect,
using euphemisms which only those sly folk with long
experience of the h a l c a could decipher.
Jemâa-el-Fna is a great melting pot of folk
cultures where the Berber and g n a w i t r a d i t i o n s
c o n v e r g e.The Berber tradition is characterized by
songs and recitals in Ta m a z i g h t , the language of the
majority of Berbers, or in Soussi, the language of
Berbers from the Agadir region.Performances range
from love poems to elegies to works of moral and social
c r i t i c i s m . G n a w i are the descendents of slaves who
belonged to a popular confraternity.Their vast repertory
includes invocations and prayers that are part of ritual
trance ceremonies. Professor Hamid Hogadem has
recently assembled recordings he has made of present-
day h a l a i q u i s from the three traditions in a single volume,
which will be soon be published with the support of
UN E S C O.
Everything belonging just to the
present is doomed to perish with it
As the years go by, my thoughts on the specificity of
literature have extended to the relationship between
oral and written traditions. In the European and A r a b
cultures I am familiar with,their interdependence shows
that a codified and listed oral tradition has nurtured the
development of written literature, which returned the
favour by seeping into the circuits of oral story-telling.
Many lyrical and narrative medieval texts have been
written for public performance,and can only be properly
understood when their acoustic and para-linguistic
dimensions are taken into account. It is highly signific a n t
that the 20th century’s most innovative and sensitive
narrative authors, including James Jo y c e,L o u i s - Fe r d i n a n d
C é l i n e,Arno Schmidt,Carlo Emilio Gadda,G u i a m a r a e s
Rosa and Guillermo Cabrera Infante, combined writing
with basic features of the oral tradition.Their novels—
featuring a whole range of competing voices—sound as
if they were meant to be read aloud,enabling readers to
appreciate the true value of the underlying literary
e x p l o i t s. For my part, I would point to how much the
s q u a r e ’s oral cross-winds inspired me in writing my novel
M a k b a r a.My work would probably have been different
without them. The act of listening—in other words, t h e
simultaneous presence of the author or storyteller and an
attentive audience—gives a new dimension to poetic
and narrative texts, as it did in the time of Chaucer,
B o c c a c i o, Juan Ruiz, Ibn Zayid, and Al Hariri.A buried
thread links the Middle Ages to the literary avant-garde
of the twentieth century. As the great Russian theorist
Mikhail Bakhtin subtly showed,a work cannot survive the
centuries to come unless it has been
nurtured by the centuries that have gone
b e f o r e. Everything belonging just to the
present is doomed to perish with it.
For many reasons, the fragility and
precariousness of Jemâa-el-Fna causes
me ongoing concern. The spectacle
offered by the square is the product of a
fortunate combination of circumstances
(some documents indicate that it existed
as far back as the mid-16th century), b u t
it may vanish,swept away by the assault of
unbridled modernity that jeopardizes our
lives and our works. Considered until recently as a vestige
of the Third World by a large part of Morocco’s
Europeanized elite (causing the square to be temporarily
closed after independence before popular pressure
compelled the authorities to re-open it), it is paradoxically
appreciated for its very anachronism.Urban planners and
technologically-advanced societies from “ d e v e l o p e d
c o u n t r i e s ” even consider it a desirable model, w o r t h
emulating as a site where people from all walks of life
come to meet and talk with each other,as well as eat,s h o p
and stroll, enjoying the richness and variety of a place that
A L G E R I A
M A L I
RABAT
Marrakesh
M A U R I T A N I A
Atlantic 
Ocean
ne nights
bards stage new shows to teeming crowds.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
is continuously in motion.As I wrote in these pages
years ago, the square may be destroyed by decree,b u t
not created by one. Becoming aware of that will
probably help to save it.
E v e r-increasing traffic, e n v i r o n m e n t a l
deterioration and,above all, certain building projects
that flagrantly violate a law passed in 1922—projects
which, if they are actually built, will disfigure the
environs of Jemâa-el-Fna forever—are serious
enough to merit a worldwide campaign to save the
square’s endangered oral and intangible heritage.
Since the meeting of experts from many different
and sometimes very distant regions organized by
UN E S C O in Marrakesh in June 19771,we have been
acutely aware that this is the only place on the
planet where musicians, s t o r y t e l l e r s,d a n c e r s, j u g g l e r s
36
and bards put on a new show before large crowds
every day of the year. The square offers us an
ongoing spectacle in which the distinction between
actors and spectators fades: everyone can be one or
the other if he or she desires. We live in a world
where the information technology juggernaut is
homogenizing and impoverishing our lives by
bottling them up in the remote-controlled darkness
of privacy. Jemâa-el-Fna offers the exact opposite:
a public space that fosters social life through a
mixture of humour, tolerance and diversity created
by its poets and storytellers.
In 1997, UN E S C O’s general conference adopted
the concept of humanity’s oral and immaterial
heritage, giving vital backing to plans to protect a
vast number of oral and musical traditions,crafts and
k n o w l e d g e, not to mention the “living human
treasures”who possess them.2
Today, it is no longer possible to deny that all
cultural richness, which sowed the seeds of what we
call “high culture,” will be swept away if we do not
rush to its rescue. ■
1. During this international consultation of experts
focusing on the preservation of places where folk
culture thrives, a new concept of cultural
a n t h r o p o l o g y, the oral heritage of humanity, w a s
defined.
2. The individuals who embody the skills and
t e chniques necessary for carrying out certain aspects
of a people's cultural life and ensuring the long-
term survival of its tangible cultural heritage.
La n g u a g e s, o ral litera t u r e, m u s i c ,d a n c e, g a m e s, m y t h o l o g y,
rites, customs and craftsmanship are among the “ cultural
e x p r e s s i o n s ” that UN E S C O has been committed to protecting
since 1997.
At of the source of this innovative undertaking was the Jemâa-
el-Fna square and the commitment of one man,Spanish writer
Juan Goytisolo, who spends part of each year in Marra ke s h .“ I t
all started a few years ago, when I wrote an article against the
plan to build a 15-story glass tower on the square,” he says.
“I fought the project,because I’m convinced that any change
in the layout of Jemâa-el-Fna would endanger the mira c l e
that has taken place there every day for five centuries [see
a r t i c l e ] . I think the authorities were receptive to my argument,
especially when I told them,‘What would happen if they cut
60 metres off the Eiffel Tower? Such a decision involves not
just the Paris city government,but humanity as  whole!’ The
project was abandoned.”
Not much later, another project was born: creating a list of
h u m a n i t y ’s masterpieces in the fields of oral and intangible
h e r i t a g e. O ral traditions and other forms of expression of folk
c u l t u r e, as well as the places where they flo u r i s h , could soon
boast that new title. UN E S C O D i r e c t o r- G e n e ral Ko ï c h i r o
M a t s u u ra has named a nine-member jury that will be renewed
every four years. The earliest applications can be filed by
December 31, 2 0 0 0 , and the first gems on the list of humanity’s
o ral and intangible heritage will be named in June 2001. N e w
works will be added every two years.
“UN E S C O’s backing,” says Juan Goytisolo, “can be used to
change the minds of the authorities and opinion-leaders and
to encourage many people to take a fresh look at certain
c u l t u ral phenomena. It is important to understand that the
loss of a single halaiqui (storyteller) is much more serious for
humanity than the death of 200 best-selling authors. Unesco
cannot save the halaiquis a l o n e, but it can help. We have
recorded their voices and their tales are going to be published,
but even that is not enough.We must avoid turning something
which is living into a museum piece, but help to keep it alive.
We must see to it that storytellers do not end up begging on
the streets at the end of their lives. It is not hard to imagine, f o r
e x a m p l e, schools taking their student to listen to the h a l a i q u i s,
introducing them to their own culture and teaching them that
not all tales belong to Walt Disney.” ■
U N E S C O TO T H E R E S C U E O F THE H A L A I Q U I S
A public space that invites conviviality.
Marrakesh was
the city where
black and white
legends crossed,
languages
mingled and
religions clashed
with the
immutable
silence of the
dancing sands.
Fatima Mernissi,
Moroccan sociologist 
and writer 
(1940-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
T
E T H I C S ◗
GLENN MANARIN
SEOUL-BASEDJOURNALIST
Striking where it hurts
Civic groups in Korea led an unprecedented campaign to blacklist corrupt politicians in recent elections,
but the old guard is blocking the will to reform
here is an old saying in South Korea that
if a man rose to high political offic e, h i s
family would be financially set for three
g e n e r a t i o n s.But in their young democracy,
Koreans are discovering that they have the
power to topple corrupt politicians and
band together to battle political vice.
The National Assembly elections last
April will go down as a landmark for civic
e m p o w e r m e n t . On January 10, t h e
Citizens’ Coalition for Economic Ju s t i c e
( C C E J ) , a non-governmental
o r g a n i z a t i o n , released a list of 167 “ u n fit ”
c a n d i d a t e s. Past involvement in
corruption scandals, violations of the
nation’s Election Law, and resistance to
democratic and anti-corruption reforms
were among the criteria for being
blacklisted.
In the following days, a temporary
alliance of 470 civic groups formed the
C i t i z e n ’s Alliance for the 2000 General
Elections (CAGE) in an effort to build
both unity and power in numbers.CAG E
came up with an additional 47 names,
threatening that if the nation’s parties
d i d n ’t nominate different candidates,t h e y
would launch full-scale rejection campaigns
against the allegedly unethical politicians.
To no one’s surprise, parties accused
CAGE of “political terrorism” and drew
attention to electoral laws preventing non-
political groups other than labour unions
from engaging in political campaigning.
But with the public steering the agenda—
opinion polls showed that 80 percent
would not vote for blacklisted
candidates—President Kim Dae-jung and
the Assembly amended the Election Law,
permitting CAG E ’s existence.Groups also
successfully lobbied the government for
the mandatory release of candidates’ past
c r i m i n a l , tax and military service records.
The new legislation was a deadly blow
for corrupt politicians. Fearing rejection
c a m p a i g n s, parties screened candidates
more carefully and nominated many
younger hopefuls.S i m u l t a n e o u s l y, m a n y
party heads nominated blacklisted
politicians in spite of CAG E ’s pledge.
The coalition responded with a “ r e j e c t i o n -
list”of 86 candidates and highlighted 22
main targets, most of whom were long-
time political heavyweights.
In with the young and
out with the string-pullers
CAGE held street rallies, p e t i t i o n
drives, phone and e-mail campaigns and
set up websites aimed at the youth vote in
particular. The sites, which featured the
endorsements of popular fil m ,t e l e v i s i o n
and music stars, received almost one
million hits during the run-up to the
election.
On April 14,Koreans awoke to a new,
much younger polity.Voters had rejected
70 percent of the blacklisted candidates.
Of the 22 special targets, only seven were
e l e c t e d . First and second-term lawmakers,
many in their 30s or 40s, made up 80
percent of the new assembly.The election
was heralded as a turning point in Ko r e a n
p o l i t i c s : a new force had emerged, t h e
civil society sector,determined to rid the
country of crooked politics.
The rise of this broad coalition can be
traced to Ko r e a ’s powerful democracy
movement that peaked in 1987, w h e n
middle-class workers and labourers
joined students to demand fair and
democratic elections, forcing President
Chun Doo-hwan to accede. “ The anti-
corruption movement succeeds the
democratic movements of the past
d e c a d e s,” says Kim Geo-sung of the A n t i -
Corruption Network in Korea (ACNK).
“This wasn’t possible before because we
[civil society] didn’t have enough power
for these kinds of activities.”
But mobilizing a citizenry accustomed
to reading about influence-peddling and
payoffs in headlines would not have gained
December 2000 -The Unesco Courier 37
Demanding the right to engage in political campaigning.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
LAURENCE W. SRESHTHAPUTRA
BANGKOK POST JOURNALIST
A THAI CRUSADE FOR CLEAN POLITICS
New watchdogs now have the teeth to fight corruption but old-style politics aren’t going to disappear
overnight. Some say this will take no less than a revolution in political culture 
Not a day goes by in Thailand without
some new tale of corruption being
aired in the press. Some see a revolution
underway while others question the use
of attacking such a long-accepted disease.
So what chances do the anti-corruption
crusaders have?
If events this year are anything to go by,
they might well be gaining the upper hand.
The first senatorial elections by popular
vote held in March turned into a veritable
soap opera with the newly established
Election Commission ordering more than
half the races to be run again because of
irregularities or vote-buying. In the end, i t
took five rounds of voting to fill all the
s e a t s.
Later in the month, S a n a n
K a c h o r n p r a s a r t , the all-powerful interior
minister and secretary-general of the
ruling Democrat Party, was forced to
resign after the National Counter-
Corruption Commission (NCCC)
accused him of falsifying documents
concerning a $1.2 million loan.Another
key event was the rioting in the southern
province of Nakhon Si Thammarat set
off in early September by police
corruption.
The crash that killed 
tolerance for bribes
The list of scandals gets longer each
day in a country where corruption drains
away 10 to 20 percent of the national
budget—about 2.25 to 4.5 billion dollars.
“There’s clearly a knock-on effect,”
says Pasuk Phongpaichit, an economics
professor at Bangkok’s Chulalongkorn
University and author of several books on
corruption.According to the drafters of
the NCCC programme, “there is broad
consensus in favour of a national crusade
against corruption aimed at reforming
the whole society.”A recent poll showed
that Thais saw government corruption as
the country’s third most serious problem,
behind the economic crisis and the rising
cost of living, and just ahead of drugs.
This great urge for change is the
culmination of a long process that began in
the late 1970s when the army agreed to a
p o w e r-sharing deal. Since then, Th a i l a n d
has seen civil society grow and become a
38 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
Striking where it hurts
such momentum without the shock of the
1997 financial crisis,which brought on the
most economically painful recession since
1 9 5 3 . Policies that nurtured collusion
between the government, the ch a e b o l s
(industrial conglomerates) and banks were
widely believed to have precipitated the
c r i s i s.“ The crisis was the responsibility of
the politicians who were pulling the strings
of the economic system,”says Kim Yo u n g -
r a e,a political scientist at Ajou University
in Suwon. In July 2000, a report by the
Korea Economic Research Institute stated
that corruption had eroded national
economic growth by 1.5 percent.
“ We took the opportunity of elections
this year to end the irrational cycle of re-
electing people who had been connected
with corrupt dealings,” says Woo Pil-ho a
co-ordinator of the People’s Solidarity
for Participatory Democracy (PSPD).
Following the election,problems within
the civic sector itself threatened to derail
the nascent movement.Several prominent
civic leaders were involved in scandals,
including accusations of accepting money
from influence-buying corporations. O n e
CAGE official was arrested for accepting
a large bribe from an election candidate.
M e a n w h i l e, in the National A s s e m b l y,
junior lawmakers keen to push further anti-
corruption reform vowed to cross party
l i n e s,an act once unfathomable in Ko r e a n
p o l i t i c s. They met fierce opposition,
h o w e v e r, from the old guard who
demanded party unity. And although
President Kim has pledged his support for
the election reform bill, the splintered
A s s e m b l y, in which no party holds an
outright majority,has been deadlocked for
most of the year. In November, a f t e r
another bribery scandal erupted, t h e
president reaffirmed his government’s
determination “to mobilize prosecutors,
police and financial watchdogs to eradicate
corruption with a resolve that this be the
last battle.”
Organizations like ACNK know that
their mission involves wholesale societal
c h a n g e. “ We need to change the system
and public consciousness,” says AC N K ’s
K i m , drawing attention to the emphasis
put on the group over individual initiative.
“ We have a kind of system for preserving
c o r r u p t i o n . Anyone could be a whistle-
b l o w e r,but if he is,h e ’ll become an outcast.”
But CAG E ’s success encouraged the
n a t i o n ’s top civic groups to form the
Korean Civic Social Solidarity Alliance.
This permanent coalition is seeking
legislation requiring politicians to account
for all funds and guarantee democratic
party structures,particularly with respect
to nominations, as well as greater public
participation in monitoring and
evaluating elected officials.
As one of A s i a ’s most developed
countries and a young democracy, Ko r e a
is being watched closely by the rest of
the continent. “Serving as a model can
be one of the best practices of Ko r e a n
N G O s,” says Kim. “ We believe other
countries can adopt such activities, b u t
the situation depends on the power of
their civil society.” ■
“ We took the
o p p o r t u n i t y
of elections
this year to end the
irrational cycle
of re-electing people
who had been
connected with corrupt
dealings.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 3939 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
player on the political scene, notably by
taking a strong stand against an attempted
military coup in May 1992. What was
tolerated 30 years ago is no longer
a c c e p t a b l e.
Several political leaders have stood
out in this period of transformation. In
November 1985, Chamlong Srimuang,
an austere former army commander,
became the most popular mayor
Bangkok has ever had.A few years later,
police lieutenant Prathin Santiprapop,
known as “Mr Clean,” ran an effic i e n t
operation to stamp out a profitable
nationwide timber-smuggling scheme.
Then, in 1997, came two events that
hastened the course of Thai history:the
Asian financial crash and the enactment
of a new constitution.“People tolerated
the waste of money in bribes when things
were going well,but much less at a time of
economic crisis,” says Phongpaichit.
In July 1997,a 40 percent devaluation
of the national currency led to a slump
that immediately threw millions of people
out of work.But the crash also opened the
way to reform and restructuring,
especially in the financial sector, where
secrecy encouraged corruption.
People knew economic recovery could
only come through political reforms.Th e
drafting of a new constitution, the 16th in
the country’s history, switched into higher
g e a r. It introduced new checks and
b a l a n c e s, such as a constitutional court, t h e
N C C C, a national election commission
and a human rights commission.
Parliament followed up with a law
giving everyone access to administrative
d o c u m e n t s. “ The new constitution
provides the legal means to investigate
government officials after complaints
from citizens and organizations,” s a y s
Phongpaichit.The NCCC can prosecute
and punish deputies, senators and cabinet
ministers and has various legal weapons.
The most feared is the obligation to
disclose financial assets,which has already
caused a few heads to roll, and the so-
called “50,000 signatures law,” which can
force authorities to investigate someone
suspected of corruption.
But these weapons can be difficult to
handle. “Someone who wants to start a
petition first has to appear before the
Senate and then prove that the minimum
50,000 signatures collected are genuine,”
says Deunden Nikomborirak,of the Th a i
Research and Development Fo u n d a t i o n .
Beyond these practical considerations
is a sense that corruption is profoundly
rooted and all-pervasive—even among
doctors, teachers and monks. The latter
have been involved in many recent
s c a n d a l s, even though the law still forbids
looking into the assets of their temples.
“ I t ’s very hard to make people realize
that what they’ve done all their lives is in
fact illegal and can land them in court,”
says Abhisit Vejjajiva,head of the prime
m i n i s t e r ’s office. “ You really have to
change the political culture and that’s
not going to be easy.”
A daunting task awaits
corruption investigators
Many aspects of Thai culture and social
values—such as respect for hierarchies, a
distaste for confrontation and the belief
that wealth and a powerful job go hand in
hand—tend to encourage corruption.
The task ahead might seem daunting:
“ We haven’t done very much so far,”
admits Krirkiat Phipatseritham, a former
rector of Thammasat University and a
member of the NCCC, who reels off
figures to prove his point.Seventy percent
of cabinet ministers, 60 percent of
parliamentary deputies and 30 to 40
percent of senators are involved in
corruption,he asserts.“We have to keep
an eye on about 5,000 people,” he says.
“ We ’ve inherited 3,300 case fil e s,of which
only 700 have been dealt with so far.”
C l e a r l y, the anti-corruption crusaders are
not about to claim victory but the big
clean-up has well and truly begun. ■
A giant hand advertises the Democrat Party’s campaign for “Politics with Clean Hands.”
E T H I C S ◗
The obligation
to disclose
financial assets
has already
caused a few
heads to roll
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
◗ E T H I Q U E S
L
40 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
E T H I Q U E S ◗
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 40
I
C U L T U R
RENÉ LEFORT
DIRECTOR OFTHE UNESCO COURIER
Je r u s a l e m :
s o u rce of sound and fury
In a small precinct of Jerusalem’s Old City, 4,000 years of history have generated 
a religious, symbolic and mythical intensity unmatched anywhere in the world
sraelis and Palestinians do agree upon at
least one point: their most recent
negotiations at Camp David stumbled
over the future status of Jerusalem,and
especially a tiny 15-hectare area—a
precinct perhaps more holy, sacred and
exalted in the eyes of several religions
than any other in the world.
The heart of the problem—a quasi-
rectangular area measuring just under
500 metres by 300, carved out of the rock
at its northern end and elevated on the
east and west sides where the land
slopes—is about a fifth of Je r u s a l e m ’s
Old City, forming its southeast corner.
Temple Mount to the Jews and the
Haram al-Sharif (The Noble Sanctuary)
to Muslims forms a platform that seems
suspended in the air: its walls, s o m e t i m e s
rising up 40 metres, tower above the
entire Old City and far beyond.
The approaching tourist, pilgrim or
worshipper is confronted by these colossal
walls of hewn stone blocks up to 10 metres
l o n g. They were built under Herod the
G r e a t .Recognized by the Romans as king
of the Je w s,he rebuilt the top of the Je w i s h
temple from 19 B. C. and completed most
of the reconstruction by around 9 A . D.
Detailed descriptions have survived
which talk of the temple’s size and
splendour—50 metres long,wide and high,
This article is based on the work of
Oleg Grabar, an Islamic art expert who is
professor emeritus at the Institute for
Advanced Studies at Princeton University
( U. S. ) , and of Ernest-Marie Laperrousaz,
honorary professor in the religious studies
department of the École Pratique des
Hautes Études in Paris and author of a
1999 book about the temples of Je r u s a l e m .
Inside the Dome of the Rock.
The Kotel,also known as the Western Wall or the Wailing Wall.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S I G N E S D E S T E M P S ◗
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 41
◗ S I G N E S D E S T E M P S
41 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
on an esplanade bordered by hundreds
of white marble columns,some of them 30
metres high. Giant doors and stairways
led out onto the square itself. But after a
fire started by the legions of the Roman
emperor Titus in 70 A . D. ,what remains of
this building besides religious beliefs,m y t h s
and even ideology, all of them stronger
and more powerful than before? No trace
of the Temple has been found. Fr o m
H e r o d ’s building, only a few large
gateways and most of the walls have
s u r v i v e d .
One part of the walls, on the west
s i d e, was called the Wailing Wall by
Christians in the Middle Ages. The Jews
simply refer to it as the Western Wall (the
Ko t e l ) , the place where they came to pray
and mourn. For centuries they have
considered it the holiest place of Ju d a i s m .
Some say it was built on the foundations
of the wall around the first Jewish Te m p l e.
Archaeologists, however, think the only
remains of this earlier wall are actually
part of the present eastern wall.
“And behold, I propose to build a
house for the name of the Lord my God,
as the Lord spoke to my father David,
saying ‘ Your son, whom I will set on your
throne in your place, he shall build the
house for My name.’”
Thus spoke Solomon, son of King
David,who united the 12 tribes of Israel
into a kingdom with Jerusalem as the
c a p i t a l . Solomon bought a hill called
Mount Moriah and it was there, m o r e
than 3,000 years ago, that he built the
first Jewish temple, between 960 and 953
B. C. Its dimensions might have been
modest—only about 30 metres by 10 wide
and 15 metres high—but literary sources
praise the splendour of its interior
decorations made of gold,silver, bronze
and Lebanese cedarwood.
An eternal Covenant
and rules to respect
Above all else, it housed at its centre
the Ark of the Covenant, placed inside
the Holy of Holies whose sole entrance
was a door that from the 6th century B. C.
only the high priest could pass through. I t
was the home of the Eternal.
The Ark enclosed the two blocks of
stone—the Tablets of the Law—which
Moses received from God on Mount
S i n a i .These sealed the Covenant between
a “chosen people”and the single God of
the Israelites, whom they later proclaimed
the sole God of all humanity.M o n o t h e i s m
was born.
The Covenant was a contract. G o d
ordered the faithful:“You shall have no
other gods before me” and “you shall not
make graven images,” and laid down the
main moral and liturgical rules. If they
respected God’s law, the faithful would
not only become “a great nation”living in
happiness and prosperity,but God would
also give them a land of their own.
Because the Covenant was eternal,
they would own the land for eternity. I f
they carried out their divine obligations,
they could live there. If they did not,G o d
who gave the land could take it back and
relinquish his people to the miseries of
e x i l e.But an eventual return was promised:
“if you return to Me, and keep My
commandments and do them, t h o u g h
some of you were cast out to the farthest
part of the heavens,yet I will gather them
from there, and bring them to the place
which I have chosen as a dwelling for My
n a m e.”
Exiles there were. Israelites from the
northern kingdom of Samaria were exiled
in Assyria seven centuries before Christ.
Jews from Judea were exiled in Babylon
after the destruction of the First Temple
by Nebuchadnezzar in 587 B. C.And after
the destruction of the Second Temple by
Aerial view of Temple
Mount/Haram al-Sharif
from the southwest. Inside the Al-Aqsa mosque.
Reconstruction of the Second Herodian Te m p l e, by Israeli archaeologist Leen Ritmeyer, 1 9 7 7 .L
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
◗ S I G N E S D E S T E M P S
42 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
S I G N E S D E S T E M P S ◗
December 2000 -The Unesco Courier 42
the Romans in 70 A . D. , Jews were exiled
for nearly 2,000 years. During all this
t i m e, religious Jews implored God, t h r e e
times a day, 365 days a year, to restore the
Temple and thus the Covenant between
G o d , them and their land,at the centre of
which was Temple Mount.
“If I forget you, O Je r u s a l e m , Let my
right hand forget its skill! If I do not
remember you,Let my tongue cling to the
roof of my mouth” (Psalm 137). Th e s e
words are recited at every Jewish marriage.
Where exactly was the First Te m p l e ?
Historians and archaeologists generally
agree it was on Mount Moriah.The A l t a r
of Holocausts was probably at the very
t o p, in line with the rules of the time
about choosing the site of a shrine and
erecting it.There is a rock on the Mount
that the Torah—the first five books of
the Bible—says was the rock where
Abraham proved, 1,000 years before it
was written,that he worshipped God to
the point of being ready to sacrifice his
son Isaac. The first Covenant was made.
Abraham—or Ibrahim in the Ko r a n —
is usually considered the ancestor of both
Jews and A r a b s. More than 2,000 years
l a t e r, it was from this same rock,a c c o r d i n g
to Muslim tradition, that the Prophet
M o h a m e d , arriving from Mecca after a
mystical night journey, ascended to
h e a v e n .The faithful can see the supposed
venerated footprint of the Prophet.
In 638, Caliph Umar conquered
Je r u s a l e m . The esplanade the A r a b s
discovered was by now a wasteground
littered with ruins and had not been used for
religious purposes for centuries, as if to
signify that the city had lost its Je w i s h
c h a r a c t e r. Written sources say that the
esplanade was even used as a rubbish dump
after serving as the site of a Roman temple.
Later writings described how Umar
cleaned up the esplanade and the rock.
Since then, because more remains have
been found, speculation has given way to
c e r t a i n t y.Construction work and what one
would call today restoration were done to
make the esplanade a religious and social
centre for the new Muslim community. I t
was enlarged over several centuries.
The Haram takes its
present-day shape
The southern and eastern walls were
partly rebuilt. The two present-day
platforms on the esplanade were laid out.
It was probably on the southernmost of
the two that the first mosque—in fact just
a shelter to keep the sun off worshippers—
was built, the Al-Aqsa mosque (“the
furthest mosque” in A r a b i c ) . On the other
higher platform, the Dome of the Rock
was built soon afterwards, around the turn
of the 7th and 8th centuries. Ever since
t h e n , its dome,atop an octagonal building
which Suleyman the Magnificent later
adorned with coloured tiles that are still
t h e r e, has towered over the Haram and
nearly all of the city and its suburbs.The A l -
Aqsa mosque was then rebuilt several
t i m e s.
U
NESCO has regularly been asked since 1967, c h i e fly by A ra b
c o u n t r i e s, to help “preserve the cultural heritage of East
J e r u s a l e m ,” which includes the Old City and the Temple Mount,
the Hara m .At UNESCO’s general conference in fall 1999, they reitera t e d
a request that “no measure and no action likely to modify the religious,
cultural,historical and demographic character of the city or the overall
balance of the site be taken.”
This appeal was mainly based on the fact that the United Nations
considers Jerusalem to be “an occupied city.”Those seeking UNESCO’s
help cite the 1954 Hague Convention for the Protection of Cultura l
Property in the Event of Armed Conflict and the 1972 Convention for
the Protection of the World Cultural and Natural Heritage. J e r u s a l e m
has been a UNESCO World Heritage site since 1981 and on the List of
World Heritage in Danger since 1982. The 1972 Convention requires
the country responsible for a site to ensure it is not damaged or altered.
The A rab countries are mainly concerned about the measures taken by the
I s raeli authorities in the Old City, especially those involving population
changes and archaeological digs.“In the Middle East confli c t , each side
establishes its legitimacy by digging into the ground,” wrote Ja c q u e s
Ta r n e r o,of the Paris-based Interdisciplinary Research Centre on Jews and
D i a s p o ra s.“Symbolic and archaeological strata signal the precedence of
one side over the other.”
The Israelis want excavations to help reconstruct the history of their holy
p l a c e s. In principle, they cannot undertake them because a 1956 New
Delhi recommendation by UNESCO forbids an occupying power from
doing this kind of work.The Muslim authorities fear Israeli excavations will
undermine the foundations of the esplanade and cause the mosques to
c o l l a p s e.
I s rael rejects these criticisms, and says they have more to do with politics
than preserving heritage. The current Israeli ambassador to UNESCO
says that in current negotiations on the matter, “any move… by an
outside body, especially an international organization like UNESCO,
would create ill feeling and be considered an unwelcome interference.”
UNESCO decisions on the issue are based on the opinions of experts.
The next such mission to Isra e l , to be led by Professor Oleg Gra b a r, i s
a waiting the green light from Israeli 
a u t h o r i t i e s. ■
Abraham, or 
Ibrahim in the Koran,
is usually 
considered the 
ancestor of both 
Jews and Arabs
UNESCO AND JERUSALEM’S OLD CITY
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
S I G N E S D E S T E M P S ◗
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 43
◗ S I G N E S D E S T E M P S
43 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
C U L T U R E
The Crusaders (1099-1187) took over
the entire esplanade but did not
permanently alter it. When Saladin
recaptured Jerusalem from them, h e
removed all trace of their presence and
restored the buildings to their previous
s t a t e. It was his dynasty, the Ay y u b i d s, a n d
then above all the Mamluks, rulers from
the 13th century to the beginning of the
1 6 t h , who transformed the Haram into
what it is today.
They increased the number of places
for prayer and built religious schools
(m a d r a s a s) , along with libraries,
retirement homes and hostels for pilgrims.
The Haram now had both religious and
secular buildings, which jutted out over
the edge of the walls.
The Koran makes no clear reference
to Jerusalem as a holy place.At the outset,
Muslims were to face towards the city
when they begin to pray. But right from
the start, the mosque the Koran calls “ t h e
furthest sanctuary,” where it says the
Prophet went after his celestial journey
from Mecca,was associated with the holy
places that were developing in Je r u s a l e m .
Th e n , probably from the 8th century,
the stories of the mystical journey and
of Mohamed’s ascent merged and a very
powerful emotional, i n t e l l e c t u a l ,r e l i g i o u s
and personal link grew between al-Quds
(“the holy”),which is the Arabic name for
Jerusalem,and the Muslims.
3,000 years of demolition,
rebuilding and restoration
It became the third holiest city of
Islam,after Mecca and Medina in Saudi
A r a b i a , and a very important place of
p i l g r i m a g e. Some Muslims believe that
the Kaaba, the construction that stands in
the centre of the mosque in Mecca and
which contains the Black Stone attributed
to Ibrahim,will be transported at the end
of time to stand near the Dome of the
R o c k .Th e r e,all Muslims will face God on
Judgment Day.
The Haram, the Temple Mount, has
seen never-ending construction,
d e m o l i t i o n , rebuilding and restoration
for nearly 3,000 years now. The same
stones have perhaps been used in the
same places to build temples both to
pagan gods and to the one God of the
world’s three monotheistic religions.
Over the centuries, the various
masters of the city, because they were
always both religious and secular, e r a s e d
all trace of their conquered predecessors
and used new monumental buildings to
flaunt their power on the esplanade
overlooking the entire city.
This Je r u s a l e m , around which exiled
Jews built their identity,was a celestial one.
“Somewhere between heaven and earth,
often closer to heaven than earth, Zion [a
hill near Temple Mount] beckoned and
gave meaning to the lives” of these exiles,
say Jean-Christophe Attias and Esther
B e n b a s s a , authors of a recent article in
the French magazine Notre Histoire.
From the end of the 19th century, t h e
Zionist movement, although mostly
composed of secular Je w s, “made the
ancient myths relevant to the present
d a y ” and “took possession of the holiness
of the land,” according to Attias and
Benbassa. Jerusalem was seen as both a
physical and a celestial place, as a
promised land and a national territory.
Compromise vs coexistence:
resolving religious conflict
In 1980, the Israeli parliament decreed
that “all of reunified Jerusalem is the
capital of Israel.” At the same time,
nationalism was rising among the
P a l e s t i n i a n s, partly in response to the
Israeli move, and one of their principal
goals became the proclamation of
Jerusalem as the capital of a future
Palestinian state. The Umma, t h e
worldwide Muslim community, i n s i s t e d
that the Haram was inalienable.
Temple Mount or the Haram: today
this site is doubly sacred to the faithful
and to many non-religious people, a n d
sometimes exploited by two nationalist
c u r r e n t s.Will there be a conclusion where
one side wins all and the other agrees to
lose everything? Can the two sides share
these strata of historically interwoven
masonry steeped in such passionate
emotion? Shimon Peres, who as Israeli
foreign minister was one of the architects
of the Oslo Accords, is fond of pointing
out that political conflicts can be solved by
compromise, but religious ones can only
be settled through coexistence. ■
L a n d m a r k s
■ circa 2000 B.C.: according to the Bible,
A b raham leaves on God’s orders to the
Promised Land chosen for him,which stretches
between the Dead Sea and the Mediterranean.
This same biblical source states that Abraham
was ready to sacrifice his son Isaac to God
from the rock at the summit of what will
become known as Temple Mount or Haram al-
Sharif.
■ circa 1200 B.C.: Moses receives the Tablets
of the Law from God on Mount Sinai.
■ circa 953 B.C.: the construction of the First
Temple is completed under the reign of King
Solomon.
■ circa 587 B.C:destruction of the First Temple
by Nebuchadnezzar.
■ 515 B.C.: the construction of the Second
Temple is completed.
■ from 19 B.C. to A.D. 64: reconstruction of
the Second Temple under King Herod the
Great. The size of the working site led some to
believe that he had in fact built a Third Temple.
■ 70:destruction of the Second Temple.
■ 132-134:theories point to the construction
of a new Temple, which would have been the
fourth one.
■ 6 3 2 : death of the Prophet Mohamed.
According to Muslim belief, he rose to the sky
from the rock on the esplanade following a
mystical night journey from Mecca.
■ 638: Caliph Umar seizes Jerusalem and
builds a first mosque there.
■ 691-92: construction of the Dome of the
Rock.
■ 1 0 9 9 - 1 1 8 7 : the Crusaders occupy
Jerusalem.
■ 1187-beginning of the 16th century: the
Ayyubid dynasty and to a greater extent the
Mamluks (from 1250) give the Esplanade, in
particular the Al-Aqsa Mosque, its current
features.
■ 1917:beginning of the British mandate over
Jerusalem.
■ 1948: following the first Arab-Israeli war,
West Jerusalem is annexed by Israel and East
Jerusalem, which is home to the Old City,
comes under Jordanian administration.
■ 1967: Israel seizes East Jerusalem.
■ According to the Jewish religion, the Third
Temple will be constructed once the Messiah
arrives.
Can the two sides 
share these strata 
of historically
interwoven masonry 
steeped in 
such passionate 
emotion?
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
◗ E T H I Q U E S
44 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
E T H I Q U E S ◗
December 2000 -The Unesco Courier 44
I
M E D I A
IVAN BRISCOE 
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
When computers chip
away at our memories
Galloping advances in information technology promise to give us instant access to all the world’s
knowledge. But how will human memory fare against the rise of the super-machine?
f the architects of technology’s next great
leap forward are to be believed, a l l
knowledge may soon be shrunk to
vanishing point. N a n o t e c h n o l o g y, o r
computing carried out at the scale of
a t o m s, is their byword for the future.Wi t h
its awesome potential,scientists at IBM
have recently argued,around 11 million
400-page volumes—the entire contents,
s a y,of Fr a n c e ’s National Library—could
be stored and primed for instant viewing
on a device the size of a human palm.
The ink may still be fresh on these
b l u e p r i n t s, but the elixir of portable
omniscience no longer seems so far away.
Seemingly cast-iron laws of ever
increasing computer power, along with
the rise of powerful new technologies,
appear to point to a horizon where all
that can be known and remembered can
be transferred to machines with which
human beings then interact at will.And it
is a future that for some is already spelling
big trouble for the brain.
Surveys point to yawning gaps
in general knowledge
“Computers not only distract us from
contemplation of deeper values; t h e y
discourage us from contemplation itself,”
declares Stephen Bertman, a classics
professor at Canada’s University of
Wi n d s o r, and author of the recent book
Cultural A m n e s i a. In his opinion, s o c i e t y ’s
love affair with fast and far- r e a c h i n g
machines—online computers, p a l m - t o p s
and mobile phones, all just for starters—
leads inexorably to memory loss rather
than gain.
As surveys repeatedly show,k n o w l e d g e
of history, l i t e r a t u r e, geography and even
current affairs seem to be on a steep
d e c l i n e : 60 percent of adult A m e r i c a n s
cannot recall the name of the president
who ordered the dropping of the fir s t
atomic bomb, just as 77 percent of young
Britons are perplexed by the words Magna
C a r t a .The day of the nano-shrunk library
could soon come,but will any of its users be
able to remember a single line of poetry?
The connection between these
yawning gaps in general knowledge and
information technology is by no means
e s t a b l i s h e d , but a host of thinkers in
different fields are sure the issue is one
that will shortly become all too pertinent.
“External support for our memory has a
direct effect on our memory,”argues Je a n -
Gabriel Ganascia, a leading neuro-
scientist based in Paris’ Pierre et Marie
Curie University.“At the same time as it
helps us and extends our physical
c a p a b i l i t i e s, it diminishes our individual
f a c u l t i e s.This is a vital question,one which
has been around for a long time. E v e n
Plato speaks in the P h a e d r u s of writing
being both a good and an evil for our
m e m o r y.”
Good or evil,writing has nevertheless
formed one of the main tools in the
evolution of human memory. Indeed it
is civilization’s unrelenting hunger for
placing memory in external stores—cave-
p a i n t i n g s, then manuscripts, l i b r a r i e s,
printed works and finally computers—
that has supported the entire march of the
s p e c i e s. As the Canadian
neuropsychologist Merlin Donald has
o b s e r v e d , each of these new technologies
has helped humans “ o f f - l o a d ” t h e i r
m e m o r i e s. Pre-literate societies, f o r
instance, depended on oral tradition for
their expertise—a practice undermined
by the flaws of overworked brains, t h o u g h
fertile ground for epic poetry.Through the
written word,memories were freed from
the head:knowledge could be stored for
retrieval in books,and then recrafted into
the sort of novel and complex codes on
which modern society is founded:
“examples might include the servicing
manuals for a rocket engine, t h e
equations proving the Pythagorean
t h e o r e m , a corporate income tax
handbook, or the libretto and score for
Eugene Onegin,” states Donald.
Becoming good
memory managers
The benefits of storing memory
outside the brain are unquestionable,b u t
the invention of printing over 500 years
ago followed by the post-war onset of
computing have added a new note to the
process:that of thundering acceleration.
One simple equation has come to
embody this. Known as Moore’s Law
after its inventor Gordon Moore, the co-
founder of Intel, it stipulates that
computing power—defined in terms of
capacity and speed per unit cost—doubles
every two years.The trend has held for the
last 40 years. Should it continue as
expected to around 2020, a personal
computer by that year will have exactly
the same processing power as a single
human brain.Add the promised marvels
of nanotechnology, optical and quantum
c o m p u t i n g, and machines might reach
utterly daunting proportions. “ O n e
penny’s worth of computing circa 2099
will have a billion times greater
computing capacity than all humans on
E a r t h ,”breezily announces Ray Ku r z w e i l ,
an American supremo of artificial
i n t e l l i g e n c e, in his book The Age of
Spiritual Machines.
Kurweil may well be too confident in
his predictions,but the quandary remains:
if computers become so quick, so mighty,
According to 
Moore’s Law,
computing power 
doubles every 
two years.
By around 2020,
a personal computer 
will have exactly 
the same processing 
power as a single 
human brain
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 4545 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
so cheap, then where will the relatively
impoverished human mind fit in? Three
years ago, I B M ’s Deep Blue computer
beat the world’s finest fle s h - a n d - b l o o d
chess player , Garry Kasparov, over the
course of six games. If human functions
ultimately resemble moves of chess, t h e n
must the brain and its stores submit to the
superior wisdom of the microchip?
For many cognitive scientists, r e l a t i o n s
between mind and machine are already
undergoing drastic reconfiguration.
“Distributed intelligence” is the new
m a x i m , encapsulating all systems in which
individuals and computers mesh to carry
out a collective task,whether it be landing
an aircraft or tracking share prices. The
Internet is so far the crowning glory—a
system that in principle might combine
individual users into a potent “ g r o u p
m i n d .” For Norman Johnson from the
Symbiotic Intelligence Project at the Los
Alamos Laboratory, New Mexico, t h e
collective power unleashed by such a
system could solve problems far beyond
any individual’s capacity.
All of this may sound abstract,but the
effects on memory are being felt now.
Facts and figures no longer take pride of
place in school curricula. Within the past
two years, South Ko r e a , Singapore and
Hong Kong—havens of rote learning—
have debated plans to axe huge swathes of
standard classroom study. Experts in
education stress that students must learn
to be adaptable, skilled in manipulating
s y m b o l s, able to respond to new situations;
in short, ready to deal with the new
e c o n o m y, a realm where the computer is
k i n g.
“ We will need a lot of new skills,”
declares the neuro-psychologist Donald.
“ We have to become good memory
m a n a g e r s — w e ’ve moved away from
managing a lot in our heads to managing
memory devices.We have to devote more
space to this executive control and less to
rote memory storage.”
Nurturing imaginative 
thinking at school
As he acknowledges, the result is an
inevitable reduction in “ i n d i v i d u a l
presence.” It is a form of mental life that
has unsurprisingly earned bitter
r e c r i m i n a t i o n s. Earlier this year the
Alliance for Childhood joined the fray by
publishing a report entitled Fool’s Gold
attacking the numbing effects of
computers at school, above all primary
s c h o o l : “A heavy diet of ready-made
computer images and programmed toys
appears to stunt imaginative thinking.
Teachers report that children in our
electronic society are becoming
alarmingly deficient in generating their
own ideas and images.”
While proponents of the electronic
future insist on the liberating, e l e v a t i n g
potential of machines—Kurzweil even
suggests that we could “ p o r t ” our minds
onto super-powered computers for an
intellectually and sensually richer life—
suspicion continues to fester.As Ganascia
o b s e r v e s, human memory is much more
than simple information processing.Th e r e
a r e, for instance, at least five systems of
human memory, making up an
inordinately rich web of self-refle x i v e,
interweaving recollection that no
computer has even come close to imitating.
But if memory is increasingly stored in
machines that we then manage for our
l e a r n i n g, work and leisure, then how will
these systems in the brain fare? And how
will imagination, intelligence and
understanding—all of which depend on
an efficiently functioning memory—be
affected? The simple answer is:we still do
not know.
Yet one image stalks the debate. It is
not the old science fiction fear of a
malevolent computer (the HAL of 2 0 0 1 :
A Space Odyssey p e r h a p s ) ,but of a citizen
without a personal memory to speak of.
B e r t m a n , for one, is convinced that
Virtual competition:Garry Kasparov on his way to losing against Deep Blue, IBM’s chess playing computer .
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
◗ T A L K I N G T O . . .
A model of Lucy (left) and her mate. With 40 percent of her skeleton remaining,Lucy gives us a glimpse of one of our 
oldest upright ancestors, A. afarensis, dating back over three million years.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
December 2000 - The Unesco Courier 47
Ian Ta t t e rs a l l :
the humans
we left behind
We have a history of diversity and
competition among human species which
began some five million years ago and
came to an end with the emergence of
modern humans.Two million years ago,
for example, there were at least four
human species on the same landscape.
Maybe they got along by basically
ignoring each other or even having
peaceful interactions.We don’t know.
In any event,we are now the sole
surviving twig on a big branching bush
produced by this process of evolutionary
e x p e r i m e n t a t i o n .We ’re n o t the pinnacle
of a ladder that our ancestors laboriously
climbed.
How do your views on human evolution
differ from traditional Darwinian notions? 
According to Darwin, you have
legions of organisms that over time
evolve themselves into a new species.
It’s like a fine-tuning process, guided by
natural selection, in which the individuals
best-adapted to their environment
reproduce and pass on their “ f a v o u r a b l e ”
characteristics, so that each generation
improves upon its predecessor.
So we tend to think of evolution in
terms of characteristics, rather than
s p e c i e s. For example, we speak of the
“evolution of upright walking” or the
“evolution of the hand,” often without
realizing that legs and hands can only
be part of the story. The reality is that
natural selection is a blind mechanism
which can vote up or down only on entire
o r g a n i s m s, warts and all. I n d i v i d u a l
organisms are mindboggingly complex
and integrated mechanisms: they succeed
or fail as the sum of their parts, n o t
because of a particular characteristic.
I t ’s the same with populations and
s p e c i e s.Species are out there competing
with others in a real world of limited
r e s o u r c e s.Wh a t ’s more, the ecologies of
which they form a part have an alarming
t e n d e n cy to change abruptly. If your
habitat is covered by an ice sheet, i t ’s
pretty irrelevant how well you are
adapted to the meadows and forests now
buried beneath the ice.
Finally in the Darwinian notion you
have a slow accumulation of changes over
generations leading to the creation of a
new species [when individuals of the same
lineage can no longer reproduce].
However a population will change
morphologically [biologically] with time
i ke most people, I was taught
to think of human evolution
as a linear chain, with a
“missing link” connecting apes
and a series of pro t o t y p e
humans in a process of
perfection reaching the pinnacle that we
occupy today. This is the traditional view
of paleoanthro p o l o g i s t s, veritable human
fossil hunters who try to piece together our
h i s t o r y. But the field is now incre a s i n g l y
divided and you are seen as the leader of
a new and growing camp. Please explain.
This notion of human evolution as
being a linear trudge from primitivism to
perfection is totally wrong. I came to
paleoanthropology from the study of
lemurs [monkey-like primates] in
Madagascar where you have a huge
diversity of animals. You cannot help
a s k i n g,“How did these creatures become
so diverse?” Yet this question is not
asked in paleoanthropology because
there is only one species of humans
today. Somehow we believe it is normal
and natural for us to be alone in the
w o r l d .Yet in fact, if you look at the fossil
r e c o r d , you find that this is totally
unusual—this may be the first time that
we have ever had just one species of
humans in the world.
A world renown
paleoanthropologist cuts down
old notions of our family tree to
reveal a host of unknown
ancestors: extinct human
species
L
Tattersall’s sketch of our family bush.
Millions
of years
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48 The Unesco Courier - December 2000
Neanderthals have been known for 
150 years now. What can we possibly
find that nobody has noticed before ?
but this doesn’t necessarily lead to the
creation of a new species.For meaningful
genetic changes to take hold, t h e
population must be small. [ The larger the
p o p u l a t i o n , the more difficult it is for
major genetic changes to spread.]
So why haven’t we seen this diversity in
the fossil re c o rd? A c c o rding to tra d i t i o n a l
re a d i n g s, t h e re are about six or seven
species of humans. Yet you argue that
there are at least 17 and probably more.
Paleoanthropologists have basically
not paid enough attention to morphology
when comparing fossils and tend to
overlook differences in the shape of the
s k u l l , for example, the jaw or the spine.
They seem to think that once they have
measured the age and the brain size of the
f o s s i l , they can shoehorn it into a
particular species. It is very clear that over
the long haul, the brain size of hominids
has increased.H o w e v e r, this “ t r e n d ”h a s
distracted attention away from diversity
and led scientists to focus on continuity,
thereby reinforcing the notion that our
evolutionary history has been one of a
s l o w, single-minded progress from
primitiveness to perfection.
In addition,paleoanthropology has
been practiced largely by people who
come from a human anatomical
background.So many don’t know what
the rest of the living world is like.
You’ve spent the past seven years tra v e l l i n g
a round the world with a colleague, Je f f re y
S c h w a r t z ,to study every major human fossil
ever found.Why? 
We started out looking at the
N e a n d e r t h a l s, thinking “My God, t h e
Neanderthals have been known for 150
years now. What can we possibly fin d
that nobody has noticed before?”And
the very first one we picked up we saw
some structures inside the nasal cavity
that had never been noticed before. By
extracting more information out of the
record, we hope to get a better idea of
the diversity that exists out there.
I don’t think anyone has ever seen the
e n t i re fossil re c o rd . How did you get past
the politics in the field to gain access? 
It is very diffic u l t , especially for
more recently discovered fossils.They are
often very personal discoveries and there
is a tendency to say,“How can y o u m a k e
comments about a fossil I f o u n d ? ”A l s o,
most human fossils are found in the Th i r d
World and are sometimes seen as
bargaining chips for extracting money
from We s t e r n e r s. There can be a
tremendous amount of commissions,
bureaux and administrative hoops to jump
through before you can get access to the
f o s s i l s. But I have been very impressed
by the ways in which our colleagues have
helped us.The whole process could have
been a lot more gruesome and a lot more
e x p e n s i v e.
T h e re ’s a pile on your desk of about 2,000
pages describing the fossils which, a l o n g
with photos, will be published in a thre e -
volume set beginning this Marc h . T h e
photos alone will mark a major step in the
field because most PhD students never
even see the fossils they study.Why is it so
important just to describe, let alone
a n a l y z e, fossils that have been known for
over a century? 
One of the big problems has been
that everyone describes fossils
d i f f e r e n t l y. They use different
terminologies that are all based on
Homo sapiens and are not necessarily
appropriate for other kinds of fossil
hominids. By using Homo sapiens as a
kind of reference point or template, the
existing body of literature tends to distort
the fossil record. We ’re describing
everything the same way so that even if
you haven’t seen the original fossils, y o u
can consult and compare these
descriptions and come to your own
c o n c l u s i o n s. For the first time, h u n d r e d s
of fossils will be compatibly described.
By studying lemurs, you may have
developed the critical eye needed to
recognize diversity in human fossils. But
can you hold up the skull of one of our
ancestors, say a Neanderthal, and really
maintain the same detachment as when
looking at a monkey’s skull? 
I don’t think that you should look
at a human fossil with a different eye
than you would use for any other fossil.
They are both documents of species that
have now vanished.They are part of the
w o r l d ’s history of diversity. Besides if
you study hundreds of fossils, you don’t
have time to ponder the existential
aspects of being human.
Some might argue that this detachment is
your weakness. By focusing solely on
biological differences between fossils, y o u
pigeonhole them into narrow categories
that ignore other factors, namely culture.
I don’t think that we’re excluding
a n y t h i n g. But if you don’t start with
m o r p h o l o g y, y o u ’re going to be misled all
the way down the line. Once you have a
systematic structure into which to place
your species, then you can mix in
everything else—like the tools that they
used or their settlement patterns.
Do you ever find it surreal to try to piece
together such a vast history with such
m e a g re clues—bits of jaw here, some bra i n
case fragments there? It must take a solid
Mystery hangs over the top skull:
scientists are not sure if it is Neanderthal,
as below, or from a related species.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:         Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
molecules have and we should always
believe molecules above morphology.”
But I don’t think that is true.There are no
magic bullets.We can widen the field with
genetic and isotope studies but we will
learn the most by persuading people to
look more closely at the existing fossils.
A battle is raging between sociobiologists
and cultural anthro p o l o g i s t s. B a s i c a l l y,
sociobiologists believe that humans all
s h a re some kind of essential nature
shaped by evolution. C u l t u ra l
anthropologists, in contrast,vehemently
reject universal statements about human
n a t u re and focus on local context in
explaining our behaviour. Where do you
stand?
I’m not certain about what the
cultural anthropologists stand for.But the
general feeling is that history is driven in
some way by cultural factors.Yet I see a lot
of randomness and contingency in history.
On the other hand, t h e s e
evolutionary psychologists [sociobiology
applied to our species] are completely
m i s l e d . For example, say they want to
explain something like violence.They will
treat it as a separate category and then
develop just-so stories as to why that
particular characteristic emerged in
e v o l u t i o n ,all the while forgetting that any
characteristic is embedded in a very
complex organism.
You’ve raised the issue of violence.Why do
you think we have a tendency toward s
a g g ression? Why can’t one genera t i o n
learn from the next and avoid conflict? 
We are psychologically so
Specimen:
Ian Ta t t e r s a l l
Species:
Homo sapiens
Age: 5 5
O r i g i n : Born in
England, raised in
East A f r i c a
S t a t u s : Curator of Anthropology at the
American Museum of Natural History, N e w
York City 
Pe rsonal evolution: Followed in the
footsteps of his illustrious predecessor Charles
Darwin by studying at Cambridge University’s
Christ’s College of  where he majored in
anthropology and archaeology. H o w e v e r, h e
s t rayed from the path of human evolution as
a PhD student by leaping to the study of
p r i m a t e s, notably lemurs (small monke y - l i ke
creatures) in Madagascar as well as monke y s
in Mauritius.
Distinguishing feature s : Two unusual
t raits resulted from time spent in the jungle
with our primate cousins:fir s t ,a critical eye to
recognize the diversity of our human
a n c e s t o r s ;s e c o n d , a deep respect for nature
which has led to the conclusion that his own
species is a monster,whose ravenous appetite
and irrational behaviour imperils the world.
Historical significance: Leader of the
camp to knock our species off the pedestal
of human evolution. ■
ego to come to a firm conclusion.
N o, because you’re not creating
a n y t h i n g. Yo u ’re doing your best to
reconstruct evolutionary history and you
know that science in general is a system
of provisional knowledge—it’s not an
authoritarian system of belief where you
make “ a ” discovery and that stays
definitive for the rest of time. All that
scientists know is that what we believe
today is probably not going to be what
we believe tomorrow. Science is
grounded in doubt.
But some people are more willing to
accept this provisional nature than others.
You probably have colleagues fuming with
your ongoing list of human species.
I t ’s just because they’re not used
to it. I t ’s hard to convince people to
reconsider fossils they thought they have
known for over 30 years. But they are
more flexible with new fossils because
they don’t have any received wisdom
about species no one knew existed before.
This seems to be the heyday of geneticists.
There is a strong feeling that if they can
just manage to extract the DNA fro m
human fossils, we will finally get to the
bottom of our evolutionary history. D o
you think genetic re s e a rch will tra n s f o r m
the field of paleoanthropology? 
My feeling is that the two sets of
data are still pointing in the same general
direction of multiple human species.A n d
that is comforting. But there are paleo-
anthropologists out there feeling
depressed and saying, “Oh God! Our
data don’t have the resolution that
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
If you really want to understand human
n a t u re, don’t look to the past,
look to how people are in the pre s e n t
complex—or perhaps screwed up—at least
partly because of the way in which our
brains were built up over the ages,
structure on structure.While the old notion
of an inherent conflict between older and
newer brain structures and functions seems
o v e r s i m p l i fie d , it is self-evident that it is in
our controlling organ, the brain, that we
must search for the keys to the
contradictions that we all exhibit, e v e r y
d a y.
Hold on. I thought you just rejected the
evolutionary biologists’ penchant for
looking to biology to explain our  behaviour.
In my book Becoming Human, I
write that it may seem odd to devote
hundreds and hundreds of pages to ways
of looking at the fossil record and then
conclude that you cannot learn much
from it about how people behave today.
If you really want to understand what
humans are, don’t look to the past,look
to how people are in the present.
Not only do we look to the past to
u n d e rstand the present but we pro j e c t
the present on interpretations of the past.
For example, the Neanderthals are
veritable icons, yet they were just one
actor on a huge stage. How do you explain
this emotional attachment? 
Neanderthals were very happy
living in Europe for 200,000 years and
suddenly modern Homo sapiens s h o w
up and BOOM! Th e y ’re gone. So to
make it more palatable, some people
have been suggesting,“ We l l , maybe they
were just genetically swamped by hordes
of invading modern humans.” I don’t
think that can possibly have been the
case. Neanderthals and modern Homo
s a p i e n s are just too different to have
interbred successfully. But if it makes
people feel better about poor old
Neanderthal being genetically swamped
than physically annihilated, then so be it.
One thing truly sets us apart from every
other species: c o n s c i o u s n e s s. H u m a n
consciousness has been described as a
kind of inner eye, which allows the brain to
observe itself at work and there f o re
permits us to have the complex
i n t e r p e rsonal relationships that far exceed
those of any other animal. Modern human
anatomy goes back over 100,000 years
but it wasn’t until maybe 40,000 years
ago that modern cognition suddenly burs t
on the scene, as evidenced by the cave
art of the Cro - M a g n o n , for example, i n
E u ro p e. What triggered this cognitive
explosion? 
It is impossible to be sure what
this innovation might have been,but the
best current bet is that it was the
invention of language. For language is
not simply the medium by which we
express our ideas and experiences to
each other. Rather it is fundamental to
the thought process itself. It involves
categorizing and naming objects and
sensations in the outer and inner worlds
and making associations between
resulting mental symbols. It is impossible
for us to conceive of thought (as we
know it) in the absence of language,a n d
it is the ability to form mental symbols
that is the fount of our creativity, f o r
only once we create such symbols can we
recombine them and ask questions like
“What if…?”
Why haven’t other species developed
spoken language?
Many species have very complex
v o c a l ,gestural and scent-based systems of
communication but even in the great
a p e s, vocalizations seem limited to
expressing emotional states. We have
managed to separate vocal sounds from
e m o t i o n , and instead to attach them to
symbols that we form in our minds.As far
as we know, this is a unique ability that
was only relatively recently acquired. I n
f a c t , if we were to set the evolutionary
clock back only a few hundred thousand
years and run the whole process all over
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George’s Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
Gordon & Gotch Australia Pty. Ltd., Private Bag 290, Burwood VIC 3125 .
Fax: 03 9888 8561
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Partner Press, 11 rue Charles Parenté, B-1070 Brussels.
Fax: (32 2) 556 41 46/Tel.: (32 2) 556 41 40/partner press@ampnet.be
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: UNES CO O f fice, 8 Po o rvi Marg, Vasant Vihar, New Delhi 110 0 57
Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg, Ballard
Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Editions Le Printemps Ltée., 4 Route du Club, Va c o a s .
Fax: 686 7302. 
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
UNES CO Etxea, Alda Urquijo 60, Ppal. Dcha., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: Distriplumes, Apartado 49232, Colinas Bello Monte, 10 4 2
A Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 979 8 36 0
UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce C/C
Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 28 6 0 326 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
T A L K I N G  T O … ◗
of us are in states of disgrace and always
shall be.
S e c o n d , ethics are all products of
the human mind. We cannot derive any
concepts of morality or of natural law
from contemplating nature. The reason
why is that nature is indifferent to
individual suffering or success and to call
such indifference amoral would be to
a n t h r o m o r p h i z e.
Human evolution has come to a standstill,
you say. We haven’t really changed since
acquiring cognition and we cannot expect
any major innovations in the future.Wh a t
is holding us back? 
Yo u ’ve got to have small
populations in order to get meaningful
genetic innovations. The population is
getting larger all the time, individuals are
i n finitely more mobile now and the
prospect of isolation of populations is
lower than it ever has been. We can
imagine some sci-fi scenarios of isolated
space colonies but they would inevitably
be sustained by a lifeline from Earth. O r
we can imagine genetic engineering.
H o w e v e r, a r t i ficially produced genotypes
could only be sustained by sequestering
“ e n g i n e e r e d ” individuals which I doubt
and hope would never be deemed
p e r m i s s i b l e. But if it was, these genetic
innovations would remain only among
these small “ l a b o r a t o r y ”p o p u l a t i o n s.
So to hope that a bit more
evolutionary fine-tuning will solve our
problems is foolish optimism.We have to
cope with ourselves as we currently cope
with the world and the problems that we
cause in it.We have reached a pinnacle in
the sense that Homo sapiens is truly
something unique.Whether you think it
is superior or not is up to you. I suspect
that if other species were capable of
contemplating this question, they would
not conclude that we represent a
p i n n a c l e.
In the world’s richest, most industrialized
c o u n t r y, the United States, a debate ra g e s
over the teaching of human evolution in
h i g h s c h o o l s.The “ c re a t i o n i s t ”m o v e m e n t
wants to impose Biblical scriptures in the
c l a s s ro o m . Has this movement hampere d
your work? The Internet has a long list of
sites in which creationists not only attack
your work but also pray for your soul.
I t ’s absolutely appalling.This is the
only country where this is happening.I t ’s
due to a certain group of fundamentalist
Protestants who seem to feel that human
beings need the word of God in order to
behave properly. Th e y ’re threatened,
insecure and looking for a scapegoat.
I get an occasional letter from
creationists who are very concerned
about my soul and insist that I follow the
“true path.” But I’ve never received any
threats or felt any restrictions in my work.
For a man who studies dead people, you
seem to go out on a limb politically. You
cannot avoid the ire of the creationists but
you have gone a step further by writing
that attempts to limit women’s
re p roductive rights are “the ultimate
example of human hubris” at a time when
global human population growth is
causing ecological havoc.Why go so far?
I just draw conclusions on the basis
of what I see around me in the world as
a human being, not as a
p a l e o a n t h r o p o l o g i s t . I’m concerned
about this emphasis on the quantity of life
because it’s ultimately going to have a
deleterious effect on its quality. Th e r e
are three times as many people in the
world as there were when I was born.
But it cannot go on indefin i t e l y … ■
INTERVIEW BY AMY OTCHET
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST.
Décembre 2000 - Le Courrier de l’UNESCO 51
I ’ve never had a more profound or
powerful experience. It is such
extraordinary art in such an
extraordinary environment—the age is
only a secondary part of that experience.
This symbolic activity appeared so
s u d d e n l y : art and carving, e n g r a v i n g,
notation music, people decorating their
bodies and burying each other in
elaborate styles and so on.
You’ve maintained that this kind of
symbolic activity was for the most part
reserved to Euro p e. Perhaps it was
occurring elsewhere in Africa or Asia but
just slipped through the cracks of a spars e
fossil re c o rd? You could be accused of
Eurocentrism.
We have some early hints in A f r i c a
of humans transporting exotic materials
over long distances, some traces of fli n t
mining and 50,000-year-old ostrich
eggshell beads and so on. People may
have even been navigating to Au s t r a l i a
60,000 years ago.These are all things that
probably required the same kind of
cognitive apparatus that produced
L a s c a u x . But the record is tantalizingly
p o o r.
This isn’t to suggest that any of this
cognition and creativity originated in
E u r o p e.Apparently the first Cro-Magnon
brought these capacities with them but
from where we don’t know. It may well
have begun in A f r i c a . But right now, t h e
best record that we have is in Europe.
And that’s why it attracts so much
a t t e n t i o n . H o p e f u l l y, w e ’ll be learning
more from other parts of the world as
we make more discoveries.
You’ve suggested that the art at Lascaux
reflected a body of mythology, a view of
the world and humanity’s place in it. Do
you think this thirst or quest to unders t a n d
our origins is a distinctly human trait? 
Oh yes.This intense curiosity about
our origins, this intense need to know
“ w h y ” is a profound part of us.I think the
bottom line is that the ability and desire
to ask these questions are deeply
embedded in the human psyche.We are
trying to satisfy this curiosity when we
study human evolution. Indeed we may
not be learning nearly as much about
ourselves as we think we are.
For many people, the ultimate question is
whether primitive man was more noble or
“better off” than civilized man. In your
o p i n i o n , did a state of gra c e, so to speak,
exist before or after the advent of
civilization as we know it? 
(Burst of laughter) Fi r s t , a state of
grace is a concept which humans devise
while knowing that it doesn’t exist.M o s t
En haut, un crâne d’Homo sapiens
t rouvé en Afrique du Sud et vieux d’environ 
100 000 ans. En bas, un crâne 
daté d’environ un million d’années 
et qui reste à classifie r.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Focus:
■ Is globalization stifling rural life?
■ Diary of an Egyptian fellah
■ The landless arise in Brazil 
■ Chinese agriculture: down on taxes and the WTO
■ Farmers and consumers join forces in France
■ The death of a dream: the sequel to South Asia’s Green
Revolution 
■ Filipino farmers take on the GM industry
■ Indian bio-villages: a model for sustainable 
development
Features include:
■ A river journey through Senegal
■ How Bangladesh fell victim to arsenic
■ Palm Beach and beyond: options for 
electoral reform in the United States
■ A tale of two Russian schools
■ The rise and fall of online racism
■ Yul Choi: the figurehead of South Korea’s
anti-nuclear movement
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
January 2000:
Free trade 
and Frankenstein
food: the new
peasants’ revolt
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 27 languages
]]>
</page>
</document>
