<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="121920eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
P ro fil de
l ’ i n t e r n a u t e
en rupture
de To i l e
Le nucléaire,
p a ra d e
à l’effet
de serre ?
I t s u k u s h i m a
et son temple:
le temps
re t ro u v é
Afrique CFA:1000 F.CFA,Antilles:18 FF, Belgique:160 FB, Canada:3,95$Can,
Espagne:550 Ptas, USA:4,25 $US, Luxembourg:154 F.Lux, Portugal:700 Esc ,
Suisse:6,20 FS , United Kingdom:2,5£,Maroc:20 DH.
WHEN THE STATE FAILS
A SURVIVAL GUIDE
Cy b e r n a u t s
flee the
d ot . c o m
e ra
Ca  nuclear
ower beat
g  o b a l
w a r m i ng ?
S hi n t o
and shoguns:
a return to
I t s u k s h i m a
February 2001
Canada:$3.95 Cdn,Uni ed Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
7, place de Fontenoy
75352 Paris 07 SP
France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
U N E S C O  P u b l i s h i n g
Human Rights: Concepts
and Standards
Edited by Janusz Symonides
2000, 390 pp., 
234 x 156 cm
ISBN 92-3-103589-4
170 FF/E25.92
n A detailed analysis 
of civil, political,
social and cultural
rights, as well as 
the rights of people
belonging to vulne-
rable groups such as
women, children,
indigenous people,
migrant workers and
minorities.
Human Rights in Perspective Series
Other titles in the series
• Biomedical Technology and 
Human Rights
• Cultural Rights and Wrongs
• Education for Human Rights: 
An International Perspective
• Human Rights: New Dimensions 
and Challenges
• Human Rights: 
Questions and Answers
• Privacy and Human Rights
• Taking Action for Human Rights 
in the Twenty-first Century
• The Universal Declaration 
of Human Rights
• World Directory of Human 
Rights Research and Training
Institutions
n Reflections on his-
torical perspectives
and philosophical
foundations of
human rights.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
◗ PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 My mother, my mirror
The mother-daughter dialogue in A r g e n t i n a .
Photos by Adriana Lestido,
text by Luisa Futoransky
◗ HUMAN RIGHTS
10 Where drug firms fear to tread
For the world’s pharmaceutical giants, the gaping needs of developing countries do not
necessarily rhyme with good business. Ivan Briscoe
◗ EDUCATION
13 Staying power: a Russian tale
The daily battle to make school a place of learning and life. Nick Holdsworth
◗ PLANET
37 Beating global warming with nuclear power?
The nuclear industry claims it holds the keys to reducing greenhouse gases. Ecologists are
fighting back. Christine Laurent
◗ CULTURE
41 Shinto and shoguns:
a return to Itsukushima
A novelist returns to the cherished site of a venerated Shinto shrine,
on an island near Hiroshima. Hiroko Ta k e n i s h i
◗ MEDIA
44 Fleeing the dot.com era
Rebelling against the Internet’s commercial era , disillusioned cybernauts
are switching off in droves. Sally Wy a t t
◗ INTERVIEW
47 Choi Yul
and the greening of Korea
The man with “nerves of steel” r e c o u n t s
his crusade for environmental protection.
C O N T E N T S
February 2001 - The Unesco Courier 3
FEBRUARY 2001
Detailed table of contents on page 16.
© Thony Belizaire/AFP, Paris
Fo c u s When the state fails
A survival guide
Armed groups and mafias usually manage to impose
their law on areas no longer controlled by the state,
l i ke in Colombia. But when the state is non-existent
or stripped of power, autonomous gra s s ro o t s
o rganizations also flo u r i s h . In Mogadishu,
t h e Congolese city of Bumba (ex-Zaire ) , the A f g h a n
countryside and the slums of Guatemala City and
Po r t - a u - P r i n c e, self-governing communities are
devising innovative ways to provide basic services.
Some are giving new vigour to citizenship. C o u l d
these gra s s roots powers be the base ingre d i e n t
for rebuilding ailing states?In a slum of Port-au-Prince.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily re p resent the opinions of UN E S C O or those of the
e d i t o rs of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r s t a f f. The boundaries on maps do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the
United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
I N T H I S I S S U E
◗ Resistance
When the state fails or takes all, men
and women strike back by creating
their own networks, not just to
survive, but to uphold their dignity
(pp. 19-36). This same spirit of
resistance drives Russian teachers to
pursue their educational mission
despite meagre resources (pp. 13-15).
Passive resistance also has its
followers:take the case of cybernauts
who are turning their back on an
increasingly commercial World Wide
Web (pp. 44-46).And finally, the spirit
of revolt is personified in Choi Yul, a
South Korean activist whose battle
against dictatorship and the damaging
effects of economic development
stands as a fervent defence of
democracy and the environment
(pp. 47-51).
◗ Debate
Is nuclear energy the solution to
reducing the greenhouse gas
emissions which are wreaking climate
havoc? Ecologists reject the
proposition and insist that the key lies
in improving energy efficiency and
“clean”alternatives like wind and
solar energy (pp.37-39).Drug giants,
for their part,may have arguments for
staying clear of developing countries,
but the question remains:how can
deadly epidemics, starting with AIDS,
be assuaged in these lands (pp.10-12)?
◗ Memory
The sombre past of Argentina marks
the relations between three mothers
and their daughters in a web of love
and rebellion captured by
photographer Adriana Lestido and
the writer Luisa Futoransky (pp. 4-9).
In a nostalgic return to the isle of
Itsukushima, Japanese author Hiroko
Takenshi traces her childhood around
a legendary Shinto temple (pp. 41-43).
DECEMBER 2000 CORRECTION
Reference was made in the p. 36 box to a “a 15-floor glass
tower.” It should have read “15-metre.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
My mother,
my mirro r
4 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Eugenia,age 32, lives alone with her three-year-old daughter Violeta.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
I“Once upon a time,” or so fairy tales begin. “ M a - m a ! ” is but a mere syllable,
r e p e a t e d .And rooted in my memory is the first sentence of my school textbook:
“My mama loves me.”Th a t ’s how you learned to read when I was a child.We were
brought up to believe that a mother’s love was special, different from other
k i n d s.That it can’t err,d o e s n ’t hesitate, is never ambivalent or contradictory like
other loves. But that’s just an illusion, like most strongly held beliefs.
The subject, long silenced, is starting to crop up at conferences and to appear
in articles, films and anthologies. I remember how I felt at an exhibition a few years
ago where 80 women photographers from all over the world had been invited to
show pictures of mothers as they saw them.It was a parade of complex and multi-
dimensional portraits of mothers: combative or emotional, young or ageing,
enticing or gentle.
But distress about resemblance—that “my mother = myself”—was a recurrent
t h e m e.The phrase proclaims it and psychoanalysis pretty much confirms it: l i k e
m o t h e r, like daughter.The myths of the perfect mother and the “good daughter”
collapse to reveal what they truly are: a house of cards blown down by a mere
b r e e z e.
It so happens that the captions of the exhibition’s photos carried no date,n o r
do those in this reportage by the Argentine photographer Adriana Lestido.A r e
they trying to tell us that ties between mothers and daughters are timeless?
Ties created by a whole kaleidoscope of distorting mirrors, r e flections and
boomerang-type occurrences.What about the physical gestures and mannerisms
of speech we repress deep within ourselves just because they’re copied from her,
she who is watching us from the other side of the mirror? Love and rebellion seem
inseparable from this primal, fundamental relationship always so marked by
intensity and guilt.And such anguish as well.
I’m tempted to think mother-daughter relationships in Argentina can’t be
all that different from what they are in Belgium,Transylvania or Canada.Yet
they probably are. My country was unified by the Spanish language, which we
Through a kaleidoscope of memories and
feelings, the author probes one of our most
intense and primal relationships—that
between mothers and daughters—and the
dimensions it has taken in Argentina’s recent
traumatic history
PHOTOS BY ADRIANA LESTIDO, TEXT BY LUISA FUTORANSKY
ADRIANA LESTIDO IS A PHOTOGRAPHER. LUISA FUTORANSKY IS A WRITERAND POET.
HERTRANSLATEDWORK INCLUDES A POETRY SELECTION, THE DURATION OF THE VOYAGE (JUNCTION PRESS,
1998). BOTH ARE FROM ARGENTINA.
Marta,32,a single mother, with her 11-year-old daughter Nana.
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
s u r v i v o r s, so they had to use all their skill to deal with the here and
n o w.They had no keys to enter the New World so they picked the
lock with skeleton keys, or failing that, h a i r p i n s, all fashioned into
tools of their future. This is how they filled their lives with new
words and gestures.It was easier for the men to make the transition.
Military service, farm work and trading helped them adapt much
more quickly to the ways, the feel and the customs of the country.
I belong to a generation of children of Jews who came to
A r g e n t i n a , disappearing off the map as they fled in boats from
repeated wars and pogroms. Just like A l b a n i a n s, Cubans and
Haitians do today, and before them Vietnamese and Ko r e a n s — t h e
latest of history’s never-ending castaways. People with one hand
outstretched and the other reaching behind—but grateful
t h e y h a v e hands at all. E x i l e, long before Babel, was and still
i s p u n i s h m e n t .
I’m the product of a world which had only just discovered
e l e c t r i c i t y, a world without television, with dirt roads and
impenetrable barriers, where you were invariably told:“ We don’t
talk about such things, young lady.” And what a range of “ s u c h
t h i n g s ” there were, including all forms of love and, n a t u r a l l y, a
taboo on sexuality.
Where women gathered in my childhood, serials on the radio
reigned amid the whirr of Singer sewing machines. During the
excessively long periods of mourning, they drank bitter maté tea and
My mother, my mirro r
called Castilian when I was growing up, and its people are mainly
immigrants.
From generation to generation, away from their country of
b i r t h ,women have steadily handed down the extraordinary strength
of their culture of origin and through it, the not-always-silent presence
of an absent language. You can detect it in the uneven, e n e r g e t i c
cradlesongs whose words and rhymes are unintelligible but can still
lay nightmares to rest.The uprooted, the immigrant arrives with very
few fixed images; the scarf she sometimes wears on her head perhaps
sums them all up.She clutches her bundle of belongings, the trunk of
the castaways.The treasure she brings is buried deep in her memory,
but the locks have been broken or the keys lost amid a primeval pain.
At the next level, the most powerful one, lies a whole collection
of feelings, memories and melodies. For example, I can see my own
mother nearly a teenager scattering corn to feed the chickens,
combing her hair or untangling my long braids. “My poor darling
m o t h e r,” went the chorus of the most popular song of the time, s u n g
by Alfredo Castillo. Then there was the almost-daily ritual of
meticulously ironing —with a fire-heated iron—the pleats of my
white starched smock. The stricter she got, the more rebellious I
b e c a m e.And her victory was more emphatic each time, because she
never dies, that mother we knew when we were children.
The women I’m talking about—mothers, g r a n d m o t h e r s, g r e a t -
g r a n d m o t h e r s — d i d n ’t fit a preset image of urban dwellers.They were
From the youngest age, Violeta has been protective of her mother.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
6 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 7
◗ D ’ I C I E T D ’ A I L L E U R S
dyed their clothes black all year round, dipping them in big zinc tubs,
so as to strictly observe the rituals.You had to wear black for three
long years before you could dress in the range of greys of the semi-
mourning period. My fellow Argentine women, unable to bear so
many deaths in one lifetime, hid a deep melancholy and rage under
a facade of moral strength.
A quarter of a century after the tragedy that convulsed the
whole of Argentine society, the wounds of the descendants have not
yet healed. The 1976-83 military dictatorship and its dreadful cull
of tens of thousands of dead or disappeared sent a whole generation
of traumatised and terrified young people fleeing back to Europe,
the land of their ancestors.
This dagger still cuts as sharp as ever in the memories of the
victims of this calamity. Its cruel traces continue to befoul our air,
as in Europe do the ugly wounds left by the ravages of World Wa r
II and, more recently, in A s i a , by the Cambodian genocide, and in
A f r i c a , by the Rwandan one.
Latin America is brimming with tragedies that can’t be erased.
The model behaviour of the Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo is a
source of consolation.Their dignity,anger and courage is an example
of how the ferocity of dictatorships can be confronted with justice
and love—weapons that are considered ineffective.
As for our own mothers, they who have set up shop forever
within us and outside us, I think we have to take a step back
from them to see their true value.There is nothing more diffic u l t
than drawing what is closest to us, the lines of our own hand. For
them as for us, it is difficult to break these blood ties made of so
much likeness and difference. But nobody ever promised us that
reaching true independence in our lives would be a path strewn
with roses. ■
After several break-ups, Maura,22, returned to live with her mother.
THE MOTHERS OF THE PLAZA
DE MAYO : TRUTH AND JUSTICE
In April 1977, 14 Argentine women
gathered in the Plaza de Mayo in Buenos
A i r e s, in front of Casa Rosada, t h e
presidential palace, demanding from the
military dictatorship news of their
disappeared sons and daughters. When the
police tried to disperse them,they responded
by marching around the square. This march
was repeated every Thursday at 3:30 p.m.for
23 years. Demanding “truth and justice” at
the height of the repression,the Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo, dressed
in their trademark triangular white shawls, achieved more with the sheer
strength of their blood ties than judges, trade union organizations and
diplomacy put together. Enduring symbols of the fight against the
impunity of a military dictatorship under which over 30,000 people
remain accounted for, they set a model that has since been followed by
mothers in Lebanon,Israel and Algeria.
They became known for their slogan: “You took them alive, we want
them returned alive.” ■
For more information:
www.madres.org
www.madres-lineafundadora.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
My mother, my mirro r
Maria, 54,had her daughter Stella when she was 18.Their relationship is marked by dependence.
Maura finds peace alongside her mother Alma (standing).Marta and Nana:close, even in sleep.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
8 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Marta and her daughter Nana strolling on the beach.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
T
BY IVAN BRISCOE
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
W h e re drug fir m s
fear to tre a d
Access to medicines in poor countries has become a critical issue with the spread
of AIDS and re-emergence of illnesses once thought to have been beaten. Can
the profit-driven pharmaceutical industry offer any kind of response?
here is a little, forgotten disease afoot,
and a third of Faustino To r r i c o ’s
neighbours are infected. As a medical
professor in the local university of
C o c h a b a m b a ,B o l i v i a ,he would like to do
more to help the affli c t e d , but the vicious
blood-sucking bug that hosts Chagas
disease has one insuperable defence
against the world’s health industry.
Trypanosoma cruzi likes its insect carriers
to live in mud walls and roofs—it likes to
feed on the poor.
As Torrico knows only too well, the
numbers do not add up. He knows of
some pills that could help the
450,000 infected people in his region—
many of whom will see their hearts and
guts irreparably perforated by the
parasite—but they cost a dollar a go.
That makes $90 million to treat Cocha-
bamba alone, about 84 million more than
his entire country’s six-year budget for
treating Chagas disease.
The portents of such immense
shortfalls are well known to the
developing world’s health profession.
For the 23 million AIDS victims in sub-
Saharan A f r i c a , they point to absent
t r e a t m e n t ,semi-legal scrambles for cheap
pills and almost inevitable death.S i m i l a r
tales can be told of malaria and
t u b e r c u l o s i s.Yet these are the “big three”
d i s e a s e s : major world scourges, all of
which (now including malaria) have at
least a foothold in the rich nations and a
claim on global attention.For Chagas in
B o l i v i a , yellow fever in Guinea and
sleeping sickness in Uganda, the pockets
of exotically named illnesses are
ringfenced by silence.
As for drugs,what there is tends to be
e x p e n s i v e, ineffective or both.One recent
study for the World Health Organization
(WHO) revealed that between 1975 and
1 9 9 7 ,1 , 2 3 3 new chemical treatments were
put on the market.Only 11 were for what
are known as “tropical diseases.” O v e r
half of those were initially designed for
animals.
“If you look over the last 20 y e a r, t h e
share of developing countries in the
w o r l d ’s pharmaceutical consumption has
actually dropped from a quarter to
2 0 p e r c e n t . So in essence we have
7 5 percent of the world’s population
consuming only about 20 percent of the
w o r l d ’s drugs in terms of value,” e x p l a i n s
Jonathan Quick, head of the W H O ’s
essential medicines division.
The frantic search
for market winners
Bridging this fracture between
medical need and medical supply has
become an urgent issue, pushed to the
forefront of politicians’ minds by the
ravages of AIDS on the A f r i c a n
subcontinent and discussed at the G-8
table in Okinawa last July. Quite simply,
the market-driven behaviour of the
pharmaceutical industry seems to afford
little space for the health needs of those
too poor to buy pricey new drugs. Th e
scale of the challenge is to bring profit and
poverty together.
It is a task made that much harder by
the fragmented nature of modern health.
For previous generations, the most
devastating infectious diseases—
t u b e r c u l o s i s, s m a l l p o x , syphilis and
polio—spanned the globe, paying little
heed to geography or wealth. N o w,
h o w e v e r, rich and poor illnesses are
clearly divisible. What kills in the west
are chronic ailments such as heart disease,
cancer and strokes. Poverty and poor
healthcare, in contrast,have proved just
the right environment for the emergence
of new resistant strains in old pestilence.
Over 70 percent of malaria sufferers in
Sierra Leone, to take just one of many
c a s e s, enjoy no benefit from the old
chloroquine prescription. Fo r
pharmaceutical companies, it is a sad fact
that does little to interfere with market
strategy.
From modest beginnings in the
penicillin trade that followed the end of
World War II, the industry has changed
beyond recognition.Annual research and
development in the sector now stands at
$40 billion, overshadowing the work of
In Burkina Faso, a young boy leads
◗ E T H I C S
10 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
public laboratories which in turn jostle to
match the industry’s priorities. Impelled
by a string of mergers and acquisitions, a
pack of multi-billion dollar corporations
currently dominates, all of them
frantically searching to please
s h a r e h o l d e r s, avoid takeover and find the
holy grail—the drug that can net a billion
dollars in sales a year until its 20-year
patent expires.
Given the scale of their investments
(an estimated $500 million per new drug),
potential sales are clearly the key to
choosing a field for research.According to
Herman Mucke, a Vi e n n a - b a s e d
independent analyst of the industry, the
craze of the moment is the central
nervous system—the weak link in old
p e o p l e ’s bodies,and thus a market winner
in ageing Europe.“ L i f e s t y l e ” drugs have
also boomed since Pfizer unleashed
Vi a g r a .The sinking of considerable funds
and talent has produced alluring new
treatments for weight loss, face wrinkles
and separation anxiety in pet animals.
Tired of depending on stubborn health
authorities and doctors’ prescriptions,
the firms are even aiming straight at
consumer desire in the style of a chain
store. For the first ever time, a television
advertisement was shown in Britain in
1999 “ r e c o m m e n d i n g ” a visit to the doctor
for sufferers of incontinence.Why? Heard
of Pharmacia & Upjohn’s new drug?
“ Th e r e ’s no disputing that one old,
f a t , b a l d , fungus-ridden rich man who
can’t get it up counts for more than half
a billion people who are vulnerable to
m a l a r i a ,” intoned an article on the
industry in the left-wing U.S. magazine
The Nation.
Yet as the pharmaceutical industry is
careful to argue, such criticisms mistake
moral fury for fair assessment. Th e
i n d u s t r y, after all, is in the private sector—
from where it must attract consumers and
recoup investment. For shareholders, t h e r e
is no more reason for it to serve pills to the
poor than for banks to hand out cash to the
destitute or supermarkets to disburse food
to the hungry.“Some individuals in various
firms might be far-looking enough, b u t
you know how these companies work:
they have thousands of shareholders who
tell the director that the only thing to
worry about are profits and dividends.
When those two drop, they are pensioned
off and that’s it,” says Mucke.
In spite of such pressure, s e v e r a l
companies have still co-operated in major
public health ventures. The U. S. f i r m
Merck, for instance, donated 65 million
doses of the drug ivermectin over a
decade, a vital part in largely successful
efforts to eradicate river blindness disease
in A f r i c a . Several firms have also pledged
to continue production of drugs to
counter sleeping sickness.
But few health activists have any
illusions about the firms’ warmth of heart.
“ The logic of the pharmaceutical industry
is not the logic of social action,” s t a t e s
Jean-Marie Kindermans from Médecins
Sans Fr o n t i è r e s. In response, his globally
respected organization has begun to fig h t
for immediate measures to get existing
drugs into the hands of those too poor to
afford them.
Charitable agreements
and generic drugs
A prime target are the people infected
with HIV and AIDS in A f r i c a . P e t e r
L a n g i , a leading health official from
Uganda (820,000 infected out of a
population of 21 m i l l i o n ) , admits that
“access to HIV drugs is minimal and they
are very expensive.The medicine is only
available from a few hospitals in the
capital.”All five leading pharmaceutical
firms agreed last May to cut the prices on
AIDS drugs for Africa by 80 p e r c e n t .
Langi explains that in Uganda’s case a
deal has just been struck to bring the
price of the triple therapy antiretrovirals
down to $140 a month. The only snag is
that his government’s health budget
stands at $12 per person per year.
For Médecins Sans Fr o n t i è r e s, t h e
message is clear: gentlemanly deals with
the pharmaceutical firms are not enough.
In the opinion of many public health
a c t i v i s t s, the firms are acting for the same
strategic reasons that motivated their $20-
million donation to the U. S. p r e s i d e n t i a l
election campaigns. Cut prices and
g i v e a w a y s, most recently seen in Pfiz e r ’s
pledge to hand South Africa free
fluconazole (a cure for cryptococcal
m e n i n g i t i s, the frequent result of A I D S
i n f e c t i o n ) , certainly look good on press
r e l e a s e s. But generic versions of these
the way for his grandfather, who lost his sight because of river blindness disease.
February 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
same drugs are currently being
manufactured by upstart firms in Brazil,
I n d i a ,Thailand and A r g e n t i n a ,s o m e t i m e s
at less than a fortieth of the big fir m s ’
p r i c e s.Could it be that the giants’ charity
is just a ploy to win plaudits, q u a s h
c o m p e t i t i o n , and preserve their rights to
worldwide patent protection (see box)?
“ The solution for AIDS is not to have
five big donors reducing their prices—
we need pressure for a political
a g r e e m e n t ,not a charitable one,”d e c l a r e s
K i n d e r m a n s. Encouragement of cheap
g e n e r i c s, relaxation of patent restrictions
and differential pricing of medicines in
poor and rich countries have all been
pinpointed as critical steps. The goal is
to bring the pharmaceutical industry to
heel—to remind it that health, t h e
condition for human life, can never be
just another market.
Incentives to boost
invention
B u t , as the WHO hastens to add,
confrontation is not a solution. In the case
of AIDS and patented drugs, says Quick,
“we need change on all sides,” i n c l u d i n g
b u s i n e s s, politics and also consumers in
rich countries, who may have to shoulder
higher prices even though their pills are
being transformed into just one more
c o m m o d i t y. As for tuberculosis, m a l a r i a
and those forgotten tropical diseases,
grindingly slow research partnerships
between public and private sectors still
seem the only option. One major global
malaria initiative,for example, envisages a
new drug rolling off the production line in
five years at a mere $150 m i l l i o n ;i n d u s t r y
has promised assistance “in kind.” A n d
though several drugs to combat sleeping
sickness are now being donated, one of
the most promising patents, that for
e flo r n i t h i n e, is stuck like a limpet to the
W H O ’s hands: no firm has yet agreed to
risk the combustible production process.
The giant pharmaceuticals,
meanwhile, are digging in.At the centre
of their concern is the patent system—the
axle of the entire industry. Scrap that or
tinker with it, as more radical health
activists demand, and firms risk terminal
demise.
I n s t e a d , a defence has been mounted:
developing countries are hampered more
by bad healthcare than lack of pills.And if
flourishing drugs firms are needed in poor
c o u n t r i e s, says Viren Mehta, head of the
New York-based pharmaceutical analysts
Mehta Partners, then strong patents and a
dose of public funds are essential. “ Th e
pharmaceutical industry is at an infle c t i o n
p o i n t . The new tool of biotechnology
makes the future very exciting: it allows us
to move beyond trial and error, start with
a clean slate and begin to do fundamental
research into the mechanisms of nature,”
he argues. “If we look at it over two
g e n e r a t i o n s, what is needed are solutions
that can be distributed in a cost-effective
w a y. What we need from this science is a
pill that can cure malaria in a safe, e f f e c t i v e
m a n n e r, a pill that can clean water, a pill
that can make crops grow.
“If the results are protected for a short
time in the private sector, it is a
s u f ficiently attractive carrot which allows
them to be widely available a generation
l a t e r. But human nature being as it is, it is
somehow not able to muster the power,
energy and creativity when there is no
r e t u r n ,” adds Mehta.The industry agrees:
the way to beat market failure is through
more markets. With the new patent
r e g i m e, they say, a genuine research
industry has taken root in Mexico and
B r a z i l . Even some of India’s 28,000
copycat firms have turned to invention.
In terms of the incentives to
i n v e n t i o n ,Mehta is almost certainly right.
But so long as the good works of the
pharmaceutical industry are an
afterthought of revenue, the incentives to
clear the parasites from Cochabamba’s
roofs may well stay off sick. ■
Patents and the W TO
For the major pharmaceutical firms, it is the formal ratification of their global rights. For public
health activists, it risks becoming a byword for corporate control and moral indifference.
Approved in 1995 at the creation of the World Trade Organization, the Trade and Related
Intellectual Property Rights agreement—TRIPS for short—is sure to be at the heart of future
debate over access to essential medicine.
The irony is that TRIPS is itself ambiguous over exactly how strong patents should become. By
2006, all 137 countries in the WTO must have implemented strong intellectual property rights
guaranteeing 20-year monopolies on novel drugs. Several articles in the text, however, allow for
loopholes like licensing a local version of a patented drug or importing from the cheapest foreign
supplier in the event of a health emergency.
What this might all mean is as yet uncertain. So far, U.S. trade officials have interpreted the
agreement as a leash on countries like Thailand and Argentina with flourishing generic
pharmaceutical firms (cases against both Argentina and Brazil are pending before the WTO’s
dispute settlement board). Former U.S. President Bill Clinton,however, seemed to veer towards the
lenient interpretation in May 2000 by signing an executive order allowing African nations to flout
pharmaceutical patent rights. The battle for TRIPS has just begun. ■
In Cambodia,tuberculosis victims receive care at the hospital in Sotnikum.
12 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
E D U C A T I O N ◗
NICK HOLDSWORTH
REGULAR CONTRIBUTOR ON EASTERN EUROPE TO THE TIMES HIGHER EDUCATION SUPPLEMENT AND SEVERAL BRITISH DAILY NEWSPAPERS.
AUTHOROF MOSCOW, THE BEAUTIFUL AND THE DAMNED. LIFE IN RUSSIA IN TRANSITION (ANDRE DEUTSCH, LONDON, 2000)
Staying power:
a Russian tale
In a town of 40,000 souls, a school has managed to keep up standards on a shoe
string, while in Moscow, a trailblazing principal ploughs along with his
alternative approach to learning, attracting both criticism and curiosity
glasnost (freedom) and perestroika
(rebuilding) hastened the collapse of
communism in 1991 and a new flush of
educational freedom swept through Russia.
But the chaos of Boris Ye l t s i n ’s liberal
experiment brought poverty, u n c e r t a i n t y
and a collapse of central authority that
eroded many of the new liberties offered.
Tatiana Sergeyevna saw her standard of
living plummet along with the real value of
her wages when they were paid on time
and a host of problems arise she could
never have foreseen back in the Soviet
U n i o n ’s twilight years of the mid-1980s.
Vladimir Putin’s surprise ascendancy to
the Kremlin a year ago has changed
n o t h i n g, she says.
To d a y,Tatiana Sergeyevna,her director
Vyatcheslav Sashenkov and the other
3 8 members of staff, do the best they can
with the bare minimum of resources to
maintain educational standards at a school
considered one of the best in the town of
40,000 people.
Per capita funding for the school’s
6 9 0 pupils is a paltry two roubles a day,
about $50 a day for the entire school.H e r
monthly salary is 1,500 roubles ($56), t h e
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 13
TTatiana Sergeyevna Korobovtseva works
hard to keep her spirits up despite the
constant and chronic challenges of teaching
in the small railway-junction town of
Rtishchevo in the region of Saratov,
6 5 0 kilometres away from Moscow.
At 40, she is the deputy director of
Secondary School No. 2 and looks back
over a career that spans the entire recent
epoch of upheaval and change in Russia.
Mikhail Gorbachev had only just come to
power when she started teaching and the
Communist Party line still dictated much of
the curriculum. G o r b a c h e v ’s policies of
Role-playing:at Moscow’s School for Self Determination, students and their teacher bring Antiquity to life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
school director’s a dollar more. Many of the
children come from families with lower
incomes or with only one parent. A paid-
for canteen service helps ensure most
children get a hot meal at lunchtime for
three roubles (about 10 U. S. cents) a
s e r v i n g. A board of trustees made up of
p a r e n t s, heads of local enterprises and
teachers raises money to help the school
and the poorest students, but the lack of up-
to-date teaching materials, textbooks and
computers remains sorely felt.
Many have left teaching in the last
decade to go into business or to work as
“shuttle traders” living off the slender
p r o fits to be had from buying cheap goods
in Turkey or Poland and selling them at a
small mark-up in Russia. Those who
remain tend to be the dedicated ones or
those with nowhere else to go.When asked
why she stays on, Tatiana Sergeyevna’s
answer is both typical and revealing. “ I
love my job and could not conceive of life
without teaching. It is a quality of all
Russians that we are used to fighting for
our survival and using laughter and
humour to get through,” she says.
Humour is especially essential for
Tatiana Sergeyevna, a math and computer
s p e c i a l i s t . She has never had the
opportunity to use the Internet and can
only teach programming in theory because
the school’s 13-year-old Soviet-made
computers have been declared a health
hazard due to their high level of electro-
magnetic radiation emissions.“I try not to
talk about the Internet very much with
the children and instead set them tasks to
be solved using algorithms. They write
programmes in their exercise books. I have
to make do with this,” she says.
Her director Vyatcheslav Sashenkov
laughs hollowly when told the Fe d e r a l
Education Ministry plans to train hundreds
of thousands of teachers in using the
Internet and to provide every school in
the country with at least one worldwide
web-connected computer within the next
d e c a d e.“In the entire school there is only
one student who has her own personal
computer and the nearest Internet provider
is in Saratov, 200 kilometres away. Th e
regional governor Dmitri Ay a t s k o v
provides money for computers whenever
a new school is built, but that still leaves
existing ones without the means to provide
proper computing facilities.”
But it would be wrong to picture life at
School No. 2 as all doom and gloom. Th e
academic freedoms ushered in after 1991
have given new scope and vigour to the
c u r r i c u l u m . National guidelines for core
subjects such as Russian language, h i s t o r y
and math leave much choice in other areas.
Teachers are free to devise their own
l e s s o n plans and optional subjects for after-
hours tutoring with a liberty unknown in
Soviet times.
When parents need ex t ra
hands to help out
During the first flush of freedom in the
early 1990s the school offered a wide range
of “fashionable options”as Sashenkov puts
i t : extra English courses, d a n c i n g, c h e s s,
computing (using the then not-quite-so
ancient computers now ruled out of
b o u n d s ) , cultural studies.The teaching day
stretched up to eight hours across six-day
w e e k s. But financial difficulties and, m o r e
recently health concerns, have curtailed
this enthusiastic activity.The regional State
Epidemic Centre ruled that children
cannot attend more than six hours of
classes a day and the school week has been
curbed to five days.
Extra tuition, particularly for those
about to take university entrance exams,
are provided on a paid-for basis—one way
teachers can add a little to their poor
s a l a r i e s.A partnership between the school
and two universities—the technical and
agrarian—in the regional capital Saratov,
means brighter students can study in
lyceum (upper secondary) classes to
prepare for college entrance.
The school has its problems: truancy,
often supported by parents who need extra
hands to help out on the market stall,for
e x a m p l e, is a growing challenge. B u t
despite the financial diffic u l t i e s, which are
common to all schools in the state sector,
particularly those far from Moscow,
Tatiana Sergeyevna does not bemoan her
lot in life. “In defence of a provincial
s c h o o l ,we think that the process of decay
is less pernicious here than in more urban
areas. We have fewer unruly parents and
pupils and hardly any cases of alcoholism
or drug use among our students.”
In Moscow, Alexander Tu b e l s k y ’s
School for Self-Determination might as
well be on another planet, despite the fact
that is also state-funded.This experimental
school has frequently found itself at odds
with educational orthodoxy, both under
communism and the post-Soviet order. N o
stranger to the financial constraints
encountered in the provinces, Tu b e l s k y ’s
battles have been more about intellectual
and pedagogical independence.
The educational philosophy at the
school in the Izmailovo district of north-
eastern Moscow rests as much on a rich
domestic vein of alternative approaches to
teaching and learning as it does on examples
from overseas, notably Britain’s Summerhill
and the free school movement of A . S. N e i l l .
Children and their unique abilities,a p t i t u d e s
and needs are at the centre of the school’s
p h i l o s o p h y. Freedom of choice in subjects,
14 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
A growing divide
Do they see a future? According to a report published by the UNICEF Innocenti Research Centre in
Florence, the number of 15 to 18-year-olds opting out of school in Eastern Europe and the
Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS) rose by three million between 1989 and 1998,from six to
nine million,more than one third of that age group.
Countries with lower enrolment rates are those lagging behind economic recovery and reform. On
average, school graduation rates have dropped by –13% in the CIS, ranging from –6% in Russia to
–13% in Kyrgyzstan and –26% in war-torn Tajikistan.
Evidence also suggests that a greater divide is emerging when it comes to educational access. According
to a cited OECD review, “As Russian society becomes increasingly stratified in terms of wealth, Russian
education is increasingly stratified in terms of opportunity.” The report, “Young People in Changing
Societies,” which includes interviews with youth in the region’s 27 countries, calls for more “youth-
friendly”schools in terms of teaching methods, curricula and the school environment.It draws attention
to a health threat to youth,notably an impending HIV/AIDS crisis in a region which was one of the least
affected parts of the world a few years ago. ■
www.unicef-icdc.org
R U S S I A
MOSCOW
Saratov
Rtishchevo
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
E D U C A T I O N ◗
lesson plans and, y e s, attendance are all
guaranteed under an impressive school
c o n s t i t u t i o n . “ I t ’s a myth that a child needs
to learn a certain set range of subjects in
order to complete his education and be a
successful member of society,” s a y s
Tu b e l s k y, an expressive man with a thick
mop of white hair, who has just turned 60.
“But if a child has spent his school life
learning to find information and to use it for
his clearly set goals; if he has learnt to
communicate and cooperate with others
and to understand the nature of what he is
r e a d i n g, then in the process he has acquired
and developed abilities that may be applied
to whatever he subsequently needs in life.”
With no legally established standards to
meet other than minimum time
requirements for certain core subjects, t h e
school is able to offer its 1,000 pupils and
2 0 0 kindergarten children an academic
freedom theoretically available to any in
R u s s i a .
Staunch opposition
to testing and ra n k i n g
The activities of nearly 80 sixth
graders—children aged 11 and 12 on a
wintry Saturday afternoon—offer a
glimpse into how Tu b e l s k y ’s school, n o w
in its 13th year of innovation, w o r k s.Th e
children are studying ancient civilizations,
as their art-work and displays from fie l d
trips to archaeological sites in the Crimea
in the corridors attest. In the school’s
t h e a t r e, all are clustered around tables
dressed in sandals and togas.Some of the
boys are resplendent in Romano-Greek
helmets and body armour. The teachers
too are dressed in togas and despite the
usual flights of balls of paper from one
table to the other and an occasional
s n i g g e r, the atmosphere is positively
b u s i n e s s l i k e.
Working math, science and computing
into a topic that encompasses role playing
from the cave-dwellers onwards may sound
faintly ridiculous to some, but Tu b e l s k y
quietly assures that his approach results in
between 60 and 70 percent of school leavers
going on to higher education and all
becoming self-reliant, responsible and
balanced adults.“I cannot describe a typical
g r a d u a t e : the whole idea of the school is not
to categorize people, but the main feature
I observe is that if they fail in something,
they never blame someone else.They refle c t
on the reasons for their failure and try to
use that experience to move on.”
Yulia To u r c h a n i n o v a , a professor of
education and former head of the Russian
in-service teacher training organization, a
close associate of Tu b e l s k y,puts it like this:
“It is freedom that generates and brings
up responsibility.
Slaves are the most
irresponsible people:
i t ’s not their work, n o t
their results and they
d o n ’t care. Only a free
person is a
responsible person.”
I t ’s this inner
freedom that the
school aims to foster
in students and is one
of the reasons it
attracts a steady
stream of visitors.
Vehemently opposed
to the international conventional wisdom
of standards, testing, ranking tables and
academic streaming, the school does not
work with specially selected pupils: 8 0
percent are drawn from the local district,
a suburban area characterized by high
unemployment, poverty and criminality.
The rest are accepted from families
throughout the city anxious to take
advantage of the rare opportunities for
self-development offered.
Finances and behavioural problems
common to all Russian schools are no
s t r a n g e r s. The school’s monthly budget of
$15,000 may be ten times as much as
R t i s h c h e v o ’s School No. 2 , but is still low by
western European standards. D o n a t i o n s
from parents and sponsors totalled $9,000
during 2000. Most teachers earn around
1,800 roubles ($64) and many moonlight
as private tutors.Disciplinary problems are
resolved through a school court,
emphasizing the philosophy that all
individuals must be held accountable for
their actions.
I t ’s a tough act for any school principal
to maintain, more so in Russia where
examples of corruption and lack of
responsibility abound.A casual comment
by some students when challenged by a
group of visiting teachers from Vo l g o g r a d
over their “ u n w o r k m a n l i k e ”dress  sums up
its success. “ Why should we dress
d i f f e r e n t l y ? ” they asked. “ We don’t work
h e r e ; we live here.” ■
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 15
Tatiana Sergeyevna displays the school’s computer, declared a health hazard.
Lunchtime at Rtishchevo’s School No. 2.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
F O C U S
16 The Unesco Courier - February 2001
C o n t e n t s
1 8 Bottom-up for the state
René Lefort
1 8 C o l o m b i a : “a culture built on
illegality and forc e ”
Interview with Libardo Sarmiento
2 1 Money rules in Mogadishu
Hassan Barise
2 4 B u m b a : the city where
cyclists are hero e s
Colette Bra e c k m a n
2 7 H a i t i : alone on the hill
Gotson Pierre
3 0 Going the co-operative way
in Guatemala City
Claudia Mojica
3 3 A f g h a n i s t a n :
in the valley of dro u g h t
Alain Boinet
3 5 Troubled lands where
criminals are king
Interview with Alex Schmid
WHEN THE
a surv
he map of the world is dotted with growing “grey areas”—
places where might is right and poverty is extreme. In these areas
the state imposes its will,fleeces its subjects or simply ceases to
e x i s t . A lack of political will and dire economic hardship help
explain its absence. In many cases, the state is such a recent
phenomenon that its construction is unfin i s h e d . Fierce conflict in
Colombia over what the state should do, for instance, has stunted
its growth (pp.18-20).
This power failure gives free rein to organized crime (pp. 36-37).
But these grey areas are not always disaster- s t r i c ke n . By tapping their sole remaining
assets—their know-how, t ra d i t i o n s, age-old power structures and above all their
determination—these neglected peoples have learnt to pull together.They have brought basic
order to their surroundings and created simple services. Over time they have seized authority
from distant governments. If these two players could pool their strengths, a strong and law-
governed state might rapidly emerge
(p. 18).
We turn the spotlight on these self-
governing organizations, placing them
in their historical and social contexts.
The journey takes us to Somalia,w h e r e
a cornucopia of such groups could
bode a national renaissance (pp. 21-
2 3 ) , to Congo (ex-Zaire), where the
breakdown of the state is coupled
with civil war (pp. 2 4-2 6 ) , to the slums
of Po r t-au-Prince (Haiti) and
Guatemala City (pp. 27-29 and pp.
30-32), and finally, to the valleys of
Afghanistan.
Dossier concept and
coordination by René Lefort,
director of the UNESCO Courier
T
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
On paper, the world is governed by
sovereign states, each exercising exclusive
control within its own territory. In reality,
millions of people live in a political vacuum
in which the state exercises little or no
meaningful authority. This “sans État”
condition includes ungoverned urban slums,
forgotten rural communities, a n d , m o s t
d r a m a t i c a l l y, the growing zones of state
c o l l a p s e.
Observers rightfully point to this trend
with alarm.They cite the spread of “ c h a o s ”
as a global security threat—a breeding
ground for lawlessness, organized crime,
w a r l o r d i s m , humanitarian crises, a n d
unchecked disease. I n d e e d , this crisis of
governance is an underlying source of much
of the misery of underdevelopment and
violent crime that many of the world’s
poorest people endure.
Fo r t u n a t e l y, the communities living in
these zones of state retrenchment are not
p a s s i v e. Their towns and neighbourhoods
are usually far from anarchic. From rural
Somalia to the urban slums of Haiti, t h e s e
stateless communities are devising
innovative ways to organize themselves to
provide a variety of basic services.The most
ambitious of these spontaneous forms of
self-governance even conduct quasi-
diplomatic relations with the external world.
International development agencies know
this well—local polities have become
important partners at the grassroots level
where the state is unable or unwilling to
exercise authority.
This trend poses a broader historical
q u e s t i o n . Is the retrenchment and even
collapse of some states a temporary
phenomenon related to the end of the Cold
Wa r, or is it the beginning of the end of the
era of state-centric global politics itself? It
has often been argued that sovereign states
were an inappropriate, western imposition
on the colonized world. What we are now
w i t n e s s i n g, these critics add, are local
communities shrugging off this failing
colonial legacy, remaking polities and
indigenous systems of governance which
better match local realities and meet local
n e e d s. Others add that the forces of
globalization are also accelerating the
erosion of state authority and sovereignty.
Does this imply that the state is actually
being replaced by these institutions of self-
governance? Here one must proceed with
c a u t i o n . In most cases, they are very limited
and fragile institutions, located in slums and
war zones.S e c o n d ,despite its irrelevance as
a functional polity in some parts of the
w o r l d , the state is likely to remain with us for
a very long time.It remains the cornerstone
of the current international political system;
international organizations and law are
s t a t e - c e n t e r e d , and personal travel
documents are state-based. The world at
large is simply not equipped formally to
interact with and recognize alternative
p o l i t i e s.The irony, t h e n , is that for some of
the world’s people, the state is
simultaneously irrelevant and indispensable.
I n s t e a d , we are witnessing a trend
toward a two-tiered system of political life
in parts of the Third Wo r l d . On one level,
there will be “paper states”—thin, f o r m a l ,
and weak juridical structures—which will
continue to lay claim to a sovereignty they
cannot actually exercise, but which the
international community requires and will
continue to recognize.Beneath the surface
of the paper state, a second tier of political
life—a messy, flu i d , i n n o v a t i v e, o f t e n
informal mosaic of local polities—will
continue to evolve, and will provide at least
some of the public goods which
communities desire.They will include local
non-governmental organizations, r e l i g i o u s
m o v e m e n t s, neighbourhood groups,
business associations, clans and mafia ,a n d
will often draw extensively on international
r e s o u r c e s. The challenge to the external
world will be learning to work constructively
with this increasingly complex political
development in some Third World settings.
■
B E N E ATH THE SURFACE OF PAPER STAT E S
KEN MENKHAUS
PROFESSOR OF POLITICAL SCIENCE AT DAVIDSON COLLEGE (U.S.)
O P I N I O N
E STATE FAILS
ival guide
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW BY ASBEL LÓPEZ
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
C o l o m b i a : “a culture built on
illegality and forc e”
In the absence of a legitimate state, guerrillas, paramilitary forces and
organized crime have each managed to lay down their law, says
Colombian economist and philosopher Libardo Sarmiento 
RENÉ LEFORT
DIRECTOR OF THE UNESCO COURIER
The state: rising from below?
Grassroots organizations might be filling in for failed states, but for 
the rule of law to take effect, government and communities have to
work hand-in-hand
Violence in Colombia claimed 38,000 lives
last year and created 10 times that number
of refugees. What is the Colombian state
doing about this?
Colombia does not have a classic state where
rule of law prevails, as is known in We s t e r n
democracies. Neither is there any agreement over
what kind of state is needed to get out of the present
c r i s i s.What exists is a skeletal state, run by an elite,
and a few state projects. We’re a country adrift in
the wind.
A
t the beginning of the 20th century,
l e s s than a tenth of the world’s
population lived in countries that were
i n d e p e n d e n t .To d a y,the United Nations
counts 189 member states and nearly all
human beings live under the rule of a sovereign state
recognized by the international community. B u t
d o e s this make these states legitimate in the eyes
o f their citizens and do they fulfill what is expected
of them?
In 46 of the 144 countries and territories covered
in the latest Amnesty International annual report,
armed groups are killing civilians,torturing people and
seizing hostages. The state is not fulfilling its main
r e s p o n s i b i l i t y, namely keeping a monopoly on the
use of legitimate force.
Human rights violations, crime and purely
predatory behaviour prevail: many states are
instruments with which a minority robs the people,
instead of returning tax money in the form of services.
C l e a r l y, in these cases, the state is a thief —nothing
m o r e, nothing less. In others, rule of law might exist,
but it goes unenforced because states lack the means
to carry out their most basic mission.
Faced with such a vacuum or coercive context,
citizens can respond by falling back on their “ s o c i a l
capital”—namely their desire to pull out of the
situation by setting up grassroots organizations. A
group of people starts a process of material
i m p r o v e m e n t , focused on combating poverty. Th e y
also spark a revival of identity, since they take charge
of their lives in accordance with their traditions and
k n o w l e d g e.L a s t , they set in motion a political process
through the flourishing of local participatory
d e m o c r a cy.
So is this gradual expansion of local power and
autonomy the real way to build —this time from the
bottom-up—a new kind of state in tune with people’s
needs and expectations? One that is inevitably
different from the model “ i m p o r t e d ” from rich
c o u n t r i e s ?
Community self-government has two obstacles
that only the intervention of the state,however absent
or unsympathetic it is, can overcome. Fi r s t , a
neighbourhood must be developed in accordance
with the infrastructure and regulations controlled by
public authorities so that it fits in with what is
happening in adjoining areas. S e c o n d , i n e v i t a b l e
c o n flicts between the various local parties involved can
be democratically resolved only within broader
institutions that  the state can provide.
To build strong and legitimate states where none
e x i s t , two approaches must work together:one from
the “bottom-up”—making use of social capital that
often lies untapped—and the other from the “ t o p
d o w n ,” in the form of a state that fulfils its
r e s p o n s i b i l i t i e s. ■
18 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Is that because eve r yone is working at cross-
purposes?
In the last few years, the country has been
arguing over two opposing models. One is a classic
state that could implement a set of neo-liberal
policies—in other words, a small, e f ficient state
aimed at strengthening private capital. A p p l y i n g
this model over the past decade has caused a deep
crisis in agriculture and industry as well as a
progressive decline in living standards.
On the other side are those who want to build a
state which would entrench the social rights
established in the 1991 constitution and feature a
degree of decentralization and citizen participation.
It would be a more interventionist state, one that
would guarantee not just civil and political rights but
s o c i a l ,economic and cultural ones. It would be more
environmentally conscious, and would lead the way
to a genuine participatory democracy, not just one
where power is delegated.
The clash between these two visions has
generated huge polarization right in the middle of
a civil war that has sharply escalated since 1995. S o
far, neither model has managed to come up with
institutions that would usher in a law-governed
state. As a result, the state has become very weak
and now has precious little legitimacy.
What are the implications?
In the absence of the state—or rather because
of the perverse way the state behaves—parallel
authorities have sprung up with the aim of
controlling political,social,economic and military
life over great swathes of the country, t h u s
“ b a l k a n i z i n g ” the national territory. Th e s e
authorities or groups settle disputes and impose
their own binding rules. All this, of course, l i e s
outside the country’s legal institutions. P a r a m i l i t a r y
forces and left-wing guerrilla groups control vast
areas of land, while organized crime holds sway
over parts of the big cities. In some places these
groups set up a real “state within a state,” with all
that the notion implies: they make and enforce
l a w s, collect taxes from business people, i n d u s t r i a l i s t s
and landowners, and even regulate people’s daily
l i v e s.The result is a completely fragmented country
with no connection between state and nation.
You have argued that “the Colombian state
does not enforce any binding rules.” What do you
mean by this?
Each citizen follows his or her own code of
conduct and rejects those held by other people.
Someone who is honest but has no links with
powerful people cannot survive. This happens at
all levels, even when you queue up to sort out a
simple piece of paperwork.So in Colombia’s case,
I think the problem is not just drug smuggling but
also institutions and a culture built on illegality and
f o r c e, sometimes armed force.Today the issues are
trafficking drugs or people and embezzling public
funds, but tomorrow it could be any other illegal
activity that leads to easy money.
C O L O M B I A
BOGOTA
P A N A M A
E C U A D O R
P E R U
B R A Z I L
V E N E Z U E L A
“Carrobomba”by Colombian artist Fernando Botero depicts an all-too familiar occurrence.
However bad
a government
may be,there is
something
worse—
the removal
of government
.
Hippolyte Taine,
French historian
and philosopher
(1828-1893)
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 19
WHEN THE STATE FA I L S : A  SURV I VAL GUIDE
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
So Colombia is not a nation-state either?
No, and I don’t think it can be under present
circumstances because of the high level of
fragmentation and lack of state legitimacy.
According to the classical concept of a nation-state,
the state must serve the national interest. But in
Colombia the state has always served the ruling
class, except for a brief period in the middle of the
19th century. There’s no shared political sense of
n a t i o n h o o d . Because of the history of the
provinces—notably the constant clash between the
interests of local and central governments and the
weakness of institutions—a nation-state built
democratically from below, from the local and
regional level,has not emerged.
E ven in the most advanced democracies, t h e
state is expected to play a mediating role between
p owerful pre s s u re groups. Does it do this in
Colombia?
In our country,government policies are closely
linked to corporate and private interests. Th e
powerful groups—economic, political, military or
even some trade unions, such as that representing
civil servants—use the state for their own purposes.
As a result,p o l i c i e s, laws and public spending do not
cover the entire range of Colombians’ interests. I t ’s
not a state with a broad democratic or collective
interest in the common good.
Although that might seem very theoretical, it
n evertheless has serious effects on Colombians’
daily lives.
I n d e e d . People find it extremely hard to get any
kind of business or work going because they cannot
rely on the social capital of trust. A citizen also
starts from the assumption that he or she cannot
count on any real support from the state and knows
it will not defend any constitutional rights.
Can you give us some examples?
Th e r e ’s no security for opposition political parties.
In the last 15 years,more than 3,000 members of the
left-wing Patriotic Union party have been murdered.
About 90 percent of all crimes go unpunished.Th e
judicial system is also profoundly class-biased:m o r e
than 50,000 poor Colombians are languishing in
p r i s o n ,while powerful people involved in corruption
cases are simply put under house arrest. All the
politicians mixed up in the scandal surrounding the
election of President Ernesto Samper (1994-98),
whose campaign was funded by drug barons, c l e a r l y
p r o fited from this elitist system of justice.
What has kept the country together despite all
this?
It might seem odd, but the one thing that has
acted as a lifeline for national institutions amid
these conflicts is the use of the state budget as a kind
of cake to be sliced up, as spoils of war to be handed
out to regional politicians.
So it will be a big job for Colombians to estab l i s h
a social democratic state...
We have the same pressing needs as any modern
globalized society though we have not managed to
build either a state or a nation. Nor have we carried
out major democratic reforms to entrench basic
freedoms and civil, p o l i t i c a l , s o c i a l , e c o n o m i c,
c u l t u r a l , environmental and indigenous people’s
rights.The society has many conflicting groups but
no centre or shared agenda.
Human rights and peace with social justice must
underpin any such shared agenda. P a r t i c i p a t o r y
d e m o c r a cy and local and regional autonomy are
indispensable for the reconstruction of a Colombian
state and nation fit to cope with the new demands
of a globalized society. The other big challenge is
education—building institutions dedicated to the
common good, bringing about a culture of
democracy and modern citizenship. ■
T I M E L I N E
1 9 4 8 - 1 9 5 7: After a civil war that claimed 300,000 lives,
C o n s e r vatives and Liberals agree to a power-sharing deal that lasts
until 1 9 7 8.All other political parties are suppressed, leading to the
growth of guerrilla groups including the Movimiento 19 de Abril (M-
1 9 ) , the pro-Soviet Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia (FA R C )
and the National Liberation Army (ELN).
1 9 8 0 s: The rise of the drug lords threatens to undermine the
authority of the  government.
1 9 8 4: A state of siege is declared in response to the escalation of
political and drugs-related violence.
1 9 8 6: The Patriotic Union (PU), FA R C ’s political arm, wins seats in
g e n e ral elections. Pa ramilitary squads start assassination campaigns
against PU politicans. Drug tra f fic kers invest their illicit wealth in
land and form their own private armies to fight the guerrillas.
1 9 8 9: M-19 announces an agreement with government and forms
a political party.
1 9 9 4: Ernesto Samper rises to power amidst allegations of
campaign contributions from the Cali cartel, unleashing a prolonged
political crisis and rising tensions with the U. S.
1 9 9 6:The legislature votes not to impeach President Samper.
1 9 9 8 - 1 9 9 9: C o n s e r vative Andres Pa s t rana elected president and
proposes ambitious peace plan. An area the size of Switzerland is
ceded to FARC control. Pa ramilitary death squads declare
Colombian human rights advocates as military targets.
2 0 0 0: The U. S. approves a $1.3 billion military and civilian aid
package as part of Plan Colombia, a drugs-fighting scheme. FA R C
suspends peace talks and warns that it will step up military action.
2 0 0 1: Negotiations underway to cede land to ELN. ■
20 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
Population:
41.5million (1999)
GNP per capita:
$2,250 (1999)
GNP per capita
annual growth rate:
1.5% (1990-98)
Life expectancy
at birth:
70years (1998)
Adult illiteracy rate:
8.8% (1998)
Sources: World Bank, UNDP.
KEY FIGURES
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
F
lash back ten years,when dictator Siad Barre
fled the Somali capital hidden in a tank: l e f t
at the mercy of rival factions, Mogadishu fell
into violence and anarchy.Until the return of
a shaky transitional national government in
early 2001, it has endured without the shadow of a
r e g i m e, and yet…
It may be a ransacked, ravaged and divided city
where few public buildings still stand, but Mogadishu
does not live severed from the rest of the world. Fo u r
airline companies run by local entrepreneurs mainly
service Arab countries. More than 15 small Cessna
airplanes fly in daily from Ke n y a , carrying khat, t h e
narcotic leaves widely chewed in Somalia.
The natural port of El-Ma’an,about 30 kilometres
northeast of Mogadishu, employs more than 4,000
p e o p l e, while the telecommunications sector has
created some 3,000 jobs. G o a t s, sheep and camels are
shipped to Arabian countries, bringing in the hard
c u r r e n cy needed to import rice, s u g a r, cooking oil
and clothes.
I r o n i c a l l y, Bekara market in the city’s business
centre is one of the best stocked in East A f r i c a .
Children hawk over 20 newspapers, including half a
dozen poorly printed dailies rarely running more than
six pages. Crowds can be seen exchanging currencies,
both international and local.And money seems blind
to factional wars: north and south Mogadishu have
their own currencies,as does the breakaway Somaliland
R e p u b l i c, but all can be exchanged and converted.
Transactions are made orally and exchange rates set
according to the imports and exports of the day: w h e n
thousands of heads of livestock are exported against
d o l l a r s, the green note’s value automatically drops.
Once a thriving Indian Ocean port,Mogadishu has
renewed its former vocation to become a business
kingdom unrestrained by any government or
r e g u l a t i o n , commanding a top-notch communications
network and a one-million-strong diaspora that has
proven a lifeline for a country where a succession of
HASSAN BARISE
SOMALI JOURNALIST BASEDIN MOGADISHU
Money rules in M o g a d i s h u
How does a country live without a government for ten years? In the Somali capital,
self-made businessmen with the help of unsparing Islamic courts are trying to prove
that they have more might than the warlords
Shops offer the cheapest phone rates in Africa and airlines compete, a parodox of this stateless nation.
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 21
WHEN THE STATE FA I L S : A  SURV I VAL  GUIDE
MOGADISHU
E T H I O P I A
Indian
Ocean
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
foreign-brokered negotiations has floundered more
than a dozen times in the past decade.
At the height of the civil war in the early 1990s,
when armed militia blocked travel while looting,
killing and raping, necessity proved once again to be
the mother of invention.Very high frequency (VHF)
radios left behind by the fleeing regime were seized by
enterprising youngsters, who helped inhabitants
contact their relatives elsewhere in the country.
From gunmen to battle wagons:
the price of security
As famine spread across this nation of pastoralists,
they set up the “ h a l a w a d ” remittance system,
permitting money to be transferred at six percent
interest from countries such as Ke n y a , E t h i o p i a ,
D j i b o u t i , Yemen and the United Arab Emirates. I n
1 9 9 5 , the doomed UN Restore Hope operation in
Somalia left behind state-of-the-art communication
f a c i l i t i e s. Since then, several telecommunication
companies have cropped up in the city,offering dollar-
a-minute phone calls—the cheapest rates in A f r i c a —
to just about anywhere in the world, along with fax and
e-mail facilities.
While insecurity and regular deadly skirmishes
have forced most investors to fle e, local businessmen
are doing their best to prove that they can call the
s h o t s. In the early days of the civil war, they hired
gunmen from their own clans for protection, t h e n
boosted their forces by creating large militias whom
they pay and feed.To travel across the city’s different
z o n e s, each under the control of rival factions, t h e y
jumped over clan barriers by pooling some of their
m o n e y.They equipped themselves
with battle wagons to carry their
commodities from the seaports to
the city centre. And they are just
about the only ones who created
j o b s, reducing the ranks of the
unemployed so readily recruited
by roving armed gangs.At the helm
of the city’s three FM radio stations,
they also have a hold over
i n f o r m a t i o n . Each station has its
own political agenda, but all have
proven valuable allies to NGOs,
who regularly use airtime to
broadcast messages on health and
other matters of daily survival.
More recently, this new business
elite has turned to another force
that has filled the law and order
vacuum over the past years:I s l a m i c
clerics and courts.According to one
of the capital’s leading
b u s i n e s s m e n , the cost of
maintaining security had become
such that “we had to change our
m e t h o d s.”Militiamen in the service
of Islamic courts have undoubtedly made the capital
a safer place, closing down dozens of checkpoints set
up by warring factions, cleaning the roads of garbage
and earning the trust of people traumatized by years
of violence. Each family contributes money—and if
they cannot afford to, a son—towards their
n e i g h b o u r h o o d ’s security.Businessmen have worked
on uniting the Islamic courts to create one giant
T I M E L I N E
1960: The independent Somali Republic comes into being.
1969: General Mohammed Siad Barre takes power in a coup,
suspends the Constitution and forms a Supreme Revolutionary
Council to administer the country along Marxist lines.
July 1977: Somalia declares war on Ethiopia in the disputed
Ogaden region. The Somali government announces the withdra wa l
of its forces from the region in 1978.
1 9 9 1: Barre flees Mogadishu in the face of armed opposition. C i v i l
war breaks out between rival warlords.
May 1991: Self-styled Somaliland Republic in the north of the
country declares independence.
December 1992-March 1995: A UN force led by the U.S. tries to
establish peace and ensure the supply of aid to victims of drought
and war. This intervention fails and UN troops pull out in 1995.
July 1 9 9 8: Autonomy is declared for the north-eastern province of
Puntland.
March 2000: Reconciliation talks begin in Arta,Djibouti. For the
first time, a wide range of civil society groups are represented.In
August,a transitional national assembly is elected based on clan
representation. ■
The Indian Ocean seaport keeps thousands of people employed.
22 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
security organization for the capital.As such, S h a r i a
l a w, with its merciless treatment of crime, r o b b e r y
and adultery (sentences range from executions to
stoning and chopping of hands and legs), has been
introduced with little opposition. Only the warlords
who feel their influence undermined have lashed out
at the clerics, accusing them of bringing Islamic
fundamentalism into the land.
Security aside,Islamic groups have filled a political
and social void, from food distribution to healthcare.
Local organizations funded with money from Islamic
countries such as Saudi Arabia and Kuwait have
reopened some 30 schools in the capital following
the same syllabus as in the donor country. The 22
NGOs operating in the city—several of which are
run by women—have also become influential players.
These organizations played a critical role in
campaigning for the Djibouti-backed peace talks in
2000 (see box) that led to the election of a president
and 245 MPs, including 25 women,a record number in
the country’s political history, at a time when Islamic
law holds sway over growing numbers.
It is one of the many ironies in this city of 1.5
million where business, Islamic chiefs and NGOs
jostle to maintain an extremely fragile order. Wi l l
these groups continue to put their weight behind
reconciliation? Will the arrival of the new president
Abdiquassim Salad Hassam, a member of  the Hawiye,
M o g a d i s h u ’s dominant clan, lay arms to rest? All is far
from won. Riots over fake currency notes, f u e l
shortages and spiralling price hikes recently rocked the
business district. Several new government
representatives have been assassinated. R e f u g e e s
who have fled drought and war in other parts of the
country are crowded into makeshift huts and shell-
pocked government buildings.Electricity comes from
small generators, water from household tanks or
donkey-drawn carts.Although criticized for pillaging
the country’s natural resources and paying little heed
to the needy, the business community is anxious to take
a stand. It has already offered to bankroll the
demobilization of some 20,000 militia members—a
move that is, of course, good for business. ■
Somalia is the archetypal  “failed state”in UN speak.Not without reason:
it’s the only country in the world where there has been no national state,
even on paper, since 1991.No national government,no civil servants, central
bank or public services—starting with a police force and a judiciary. Not even
nationality in the legal sense, since a Somali passport,which anyone can buy
for $30,isn’t recognized anywhere in the world.
W h a t ’s more, the country is divided into three areas—Somaliland in the
northwest,Puntland in the northeast,and the southern zone, which is still at
wa r. In Mogadishu, or rather in the part of the city it controls—the new
t ransitional national government operates from a few hotel rooms paid for by
local businessmen. Born in August 2000 at a peace conference in Arta, in
neighbouring Djibouti, the government isn’t recognized by any We s t e r n
powers, even though many of them have given it “encouragement.” It’s also
opposed by the rulers of Somaliland and Puntland and resisted by those who
have plunged the country into chaos—the warlords and their militias.
Armed battles take a daily toll of victims. Despite recent improvements in the
s i t u a t i o n , 400,000 Somalis don’t have enough to eat.About 150,000 have been
forced from their homes by floods and a cholera epidemic has broken out.
Yet relative peace and stability have reigned for several years in Somaliland and
P u n t l a n d . Mogadishu is also returning to normal. A nation seems to be
rebuilding itself and a new kind of state emerging through a unique process:
i n d i g e n o u s, s e l f - s u f fic i e n t , from the bottom up, from the local to the national.
A dozen attempts by the A rab League, Egypt and Ethiopia failed to bring
reconciliation and reunification to Somalia because they sought to reimpose
a classic state [from top down] and to reach an agreement between the
warlords.
The building blocks of Somali society are clans, divided up into a multitude of
s u b - c l a n s. The key institution is the s h i r, a meeting of clan chiefs, w h o
sometimes have to confer for months before reaching agreement. It was a series
of s h i r s, g radually extended to include clan families, that produced an
independent authority in Somaliland,with its own police, army, courts, civil
servants, currency and free press.
The economy functions there, with minimal foreign aid, and is buoyed by a new
generation of businessmen that the tiny state relies upon to provide public
services. The shirs managed to neutralize, indeed eliminate the warlords by
playing “ c i v i l i a n s ” off against “ m i l i t a r y ” p e o p l e. Most importantly, t h e
government authorities have won acceptance because their laws are based on
common law, and increasingly on Ko ranic law. They also never imposed
themselves on the clans. I n s t e a d , the government stems from them and strictly
respects their power balance.
This approach has been followed elsewhere, notably in Puntland. It was a driving
force at the recent Arta conference, which unlike most international gatherings
on the issue resembled a modernized version of a giant traditional s h i r. It lasted
more than six months. For the first time, intellectuals, NGO officials and even
women—a first in Somali history—turned up to speak for the “ m o d e r n ”
sector of civil society. Then the elders, the businessmen, religious leaders,
traditional chiefs and finally the warlords joined in.The whole driving force of
the conference—which brought together about 2,800 people—and the
elections held during it rested upon balancing the clans.
Does this first attempt at giving Somalia a national government based on the
country’s social structures and,in a broad sense, its culture, have a chance?
Haven’t its sponsors – mainly Djibouti – tried to go too fast, turning their backs
on a more gradual approach that would have involved slowly bringing together
or federating self-governed areas until the whole country was covered, in a type
of building-block process?
It is safe to conclude that the Arta talks will stand as a decisive turning point,
because representatives from across Somali society had a say in the process.
The post-Arta era has begun,and it lies in their hands. ■
*Anthropologist at the Paris-based Institute for Development Research (IRD).
MOHAMED A B D I * : “A UNIQUE INDIGENOUS PROCESS IS AT W O R K ”
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 23
WHEN THE STATE FA I L S : A  SURV I VAL  GUIDE
Population:
9.4million (1999)
GNPper capita:
n.a.(1999)
GNP per capita
annual growth rate:
n.a.(1990-98)
Life expectancy
at birth:
48years (1998)
Adult illiteracy rate:
76% (1998)
Sources: World Bank, UNDP.
KEYFIGURES
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
T I M E L I N E
COLETTE BRAECKMAN
BELGIAN JOURNALIST, AUTHOR OF L’ENJEU CONGOLAIS
(THE STAKESIN CONGO), PUBLISHEDBY FAYARD,1999
B u m b a : the city
where cyclists are hero e s
Once supplied by the Congo River, this city controlled by rebel groups has
lost its vocation as one of the country’s bread baskets. Instead, cycling
shopkeepers travel perilously to bring back prized goods from afar, while
the Internet offers a reprieve from isolation
A
little Cessna from Aviation without
Borders loaded with crates of drugs
for the hospital makes big circles in
the sky before touching down in
B u m b a . Seen from above, t h e
runway looks like a strip of sand in the middle of
v e g e t a t i o n .The sound of the purring engine stirs
Bumba out of its lethargy. Men in uniform rush
towards the runway, blocking it with a wreck of
a truck, which a Ugandan offic e r
soon orders them to move.
Civilians hurry over on bicy c l e s,
and a European priest waves his
arms.
As soon as the plane arrives,
local taxis called “ t o l e k a s ” —
ancient bicycles with rear seats
padded with wool—pick up the
p a s s e n g e r s. Gently crunching in
the sand, the bikes have become
slumbering Bumba’s sole means
of transportation,except for a few
sputtering motorcycles owned by
diamond-hunters who display their
luck until they run out of fuel: a
barrel of oil costs $300.
The immense, majestic Congo River, the main
artery of this country, which is as large as Europe, i s
now impracticable.The whaling ships have stayed in
K i n s h a s a , the capital, the ferry boats are motionless,
the dug-out canoes lie carefully hidden in the tall
grass of the banks for fear that soldiers will
requisition them.
Bumba was once the centre of a fertile farming
area that kept Kinshasa supplied in manioc, rice and
palm oil. N o w a d a y s, the sleepy city lies in territory
controlled by one of the rebel groups sharing what
remains of the Democratic Republic of the Congo,
the former Zaire: the Movement for the Liberation
of the Congo,headed by Jean-Pierre Bemba, s t r o n g l y
supported and flanked by Ugandan troops.
Since the outbreak of the war, the shopkeepers
who once were supplied by the river have no other
choice but bicy c l e s.The local population hails them
as veritable heroes.The bravest travel all the way
to Kisangani, capital of Eastern province, o r
Butembo, on the Ugandan border, to bring back
two highly-prized treasures:bales of second-hand
clothes and blocks of salt.They reach astronomical
prices because the cyclists risk life and limb
pedalling across a thousand kilometres of forest in
w a r-torn areas where armed gangs survive by
looting and kidnapping civilians for ransom.Th e s e
m e n , who weigh an average of 60 kilos, carry loads
that sometimes exceed 100, and each trip takes
over two weeks.
Throughout the city, which has no potable water
Bumba
KINSHASA
D E M O C R A T I C
R E P U B L I C
OF THE CONGO
CENTRAL AFR ICAN REPUBLIC
A N G O L A
S U D A N
Z A M B I A
1 9 6 0:The Republic of the Congo gains independence from Belgium.
Civil war breaks out,exacerbated by foreign intervention.
1961:Assassination of the first head of state, Patrice Lumumba.
1 9 6 5: G e n e ral Joseph-Désiré Mobutu seizes power in a military
c o u p. B a c ked by western powers, he embarks upon unifying and
pacifying the country, renamed Zaire.
1 9 7 0 : Mobutu establishes his Popular Revolutionary Movement
(MPR) as the sole legal party.
1 9 8 6 - 1 9 9 0: The country draws mounting foreign criticism for its
human rights abuses. Mobutu announces the advent of a multi-
party system,which never comes into effect.
1 9 9 4: Following the Rwandan genocide,some 1.3 million ethnic Hutus,
including many who actively took part in the genocide, flee the country
and settle in camps in eastern Zaire.
1 9 9 6 - 1 9 9 7: Rebel party leader Laurent-Désiré Kabila forms the
Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of the Congo. He
launches an expedition in the east of the country. Supported by
R wanda and Uganda, he attacks Hutu camps in Zaire, some of  which
served  as bases for guerrillas attempting to destabilize the new
regime in Kigali.Mobutu flees into exile and dies four months later.
Kabila’s troops enter Kinshasa.Kabila declares himself president of
the Democratic Republic of the Congo.
1998: Kabila turns against his former allies, Uganda and Rwanda,
with support from Angola and Zimbabwe.The country descends into
civil war and is split in two.
1 9 9 9: A ceasefire accord reached in Lusaka never comes into effect.
January 17, 2 0 0 1: Kabila shot and killed in an attempted coup
d’état. ■
24 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Population:
49.8million (1999)
GNP per capita:
$110 (1999)
GNP per capita
annual growth rate:
–8.3% (1990-98)
Life expectancy
at birth:
51years (1998)
Adult illiteracy rate:
41.1% (1998)
Sources: World Bank, UNDP.
KEY FIGURES
or electricity,palm oil burns in small lamps ironically
named “Bemba lights” after the local warlord.
E l s e w h e r e, they are called “Kabila lights” after the
recently shot chief of state. Palm oil also turned
Father Carlos, a Belgian priest who has been living
in Equator province for 30 years, into a hero. I t
powers a generator he patched up to run an ancient
wireless telegraph, B u m b a ’s only means of
communication with the outside world.
But it would be wrong to think that this forlorn
place lives in a vacuum without order and
a u t h o r i t y. Fi r s t , rebel leaders, like the central
government elsewhere, maintain structures that
keep a close watch on the population and have the
means to transmit information without delay.
S e c o n d , the Congolese have formed thousands
of grassroots groups that oversee and organize
day-to-day activities,perform the function of social
c o n t r o l , distribute meagre resources, and even
mete out expeditious justice. And a foreigner
cannot walk around the market stalls without
paying a prior visit to the “president.” Elected by
the shopkeepers, he is responsible for keeping
order. He chooses stall locations, sets prices and
settles disputes.
Like in the poor neighbourhoods of Kinshasa
and other towns, crime is relatively low in Bumba,
not because people are more virtuous but because
“vigilance committees,” which were formed a long
time ago to try and prevent atrocities by the
m i l i t a r y, use every means at their disposal.When a
thief is caught in the act, he has the living daylights
beaten out of him and, in some cases, finds himself
with a flaming tyre around his neck. But human
rights organizations have also spread throughout
the country. They make observations, take notes,
publicize atrocities (and there are many) and write
reports.
Standing in the middle of Bumba, the hospital is
i m p e c c a b l e.The staff is dressed in white; the rooms
are swept clean;a young pharmacist proudly shows
off her rows of neat shelves. It takes visitors a few
moments to figure out why they feel uneasy. The
only healthcare facility in this city of 100,000 people
is practically empty.At the end of a long, deserted
c o r r i d o r,nuns have thrown a sheet over a motionless
shape on the flo o r, leaving only the army boots
sticking out.It is the body of a government soldier
taken prisoner who died of hunger because no one
could afford to feed him and he had no relatives in
the area. A physician on duty summed up the
s i t u a t i o n : people have no money.Not even enough
to pay for a doctor’s visit, which costs the equivalent
of two French francs, or the barest minimum of
d r u g s, much less sterile gloves, thread and bandages
for operations.
“Deaths outnumber births,” says Father Carlos,
“and there are more patients than pupils. M y
parishioners stay away from Sunday mass because
t h e y ’re ashamed of being seen wearing rags, o r
nothing at all!”
The schoolhouse doors have been stripped off,
the benches and blackboards taken away by people
who used them to make coffins. But they remain
remarkably organized.The student population has
dropped because families can afford to spend the
tiny sum required to pay school fees on only one of
their children.The government has not paid teachers
for ages, but every three months, parents contribute
the equivalent of one dollar, and the teachers eke
out a living on small incomes.
The classrooms at the Institut Notre Dame, a
private school run by nuns, offers a surprising
spectacle: the pupils have no textbooks. Instead,
We shall either
find a way
or make one.
Hannibal,
Carthaginian general
(c.247-183 B.C.)
Better than nothing:archaic devices keep Bumba supplied with a few precious goods.
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 25
WHEN THE STATE FA I L S : A SURV I VAL GUIDE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
t h e y work with a few overcrowded note-
b o o k s. Neat rows of arithmetic problems are
written out next to English and Latin grammar
lessons on the blackboard, and the pupils, who
speak polished
Fr e n c h , e a g e r l y
greet foreign
v i s i t o r s, a s k i n g
them,for example,
whether the
election of a new
president in the
United States will
change anything in
a devastating war
that nobody wants.
Civil servants
nostalgically recall
the one time they
have been paid in
the past three years: a few months after Kabila’s
seizure of power, they received $180 in wages and
back pay. Since then,they only go to work to keep
their spirits up and preserve their social standing,
carefully recording each visitor’s name and position.
Bumba may have few means of
c o m m u n i c a t i o n , but one of them is virtual: t h e
Internet has breathed new life into grassroots
o r g a n i z a t i o n s. When Father Carlos’ generator
w o r k s, volunteer groups use his satellite phone.
Perhaps the Internet has also enabled the
Congolese, who are living in a divided, occupied
c o u n t r y, to keep in touch with each other,c i r c u l a t e
information and, when necessary, contest the
authorities in place. The self-organization of civil
society has offset the vacuum of government and
preserved what, in the eyes of the Congolese,
represents the basics: the identity and unity of
their nation. ■
Although the famous “article 15”does not appear in a
single law, it is the golden rule for survival in the former
Z a i r e.“Article 15” stands for four little words: “ Yo u ’re on your
own!”
In what was once the personal property of King Leopold II
a n d , from 1908, a Belgian possession, economic exploitation
was imposed on the “ n a t i v e s ” with a harshness unpara l l e l e d
in any other African colony. The relationship between the
indigenous population and the colonial power was based
on fear and reprisals.
After the Second World Wa r, half-hearted efforts to make up
for lost time fell short of offsetting the accumulated social
and administrative backwa r d n e s s. In 1960, the year of
i n d e p e n d e n c e, the country counted just one university
graduate. The lack of qualified personnel to manage the
s t a t e, combined with the Cold War and Belgium’s
manipulations of ethnic conflicts, were in large part
responsible for the Congo’s plummeting into chaos.
The first social services, which mainly appeared in education
and training,followed Mobutu’s seizure of power in 1965
and the country’s pacification.But the use of the state to
satisfy personal interests to the detriment of the common
interest emptied the government of its substance and threw
the country into a bottomless pit. Because of the lack of
s e p a ration between the single party and the state, t h e
nationalization of the economy and,especially, the spread
of corruption, government structures were moribund when
Laurent Kabila seized power in 1997.
Faced with a disintegrating state that nonetheless remained
a predator, the population gradually developed mechanisms
of self-regulation and self-defence to survive.They could be
seen everywhere. In the economy, everybody—especially
women—plied a petty trade or owned a small business off
the books. In the legal sphere, informal mechanisms steeped
in traditional practices made up for the vacuum left by the
s t a t e.They were also visible in the social arena—schools and
hospitals—even though the traditional domination of the
churches in this sector is on the wane. Lastly, in politics, a
myriad of farmers’, n e i g h b o u r h o o d , professional and
confessional (religious or secular) organizations has cropped
up since the late 1980s to promote common interests and
stand up for people’s rights against the appetites of what
remains of the state, or even against other groups. Their
leaders are members of the educated but financially bankrupt
middle-class, traditional chiefs or simply strong figures.
But self-organization also has its limits.At best, the informal
economy enables people to survive. Might makes right is
often the rule.Poor management, scheming of every kind and
cronyism are widespread. There is a blatant shortage of
financial and material resources; the only available aid,
which is difficult to obtain, comes from the west. L a s t l y, t h e
war that has been raging since 1998 has cut the country into
two more or less equal parts, one of which is occupied by
rebel factions under the control of Rwanda and Uganda.Th e
conflict has shattered the mechanisms of family solidarity,
which used to play a primordial role. ■
* Congolese researcher, author of “The Catholic Church
and Political Power in Congo-Zaire: the Democratic Quest”
(1997) and “From Mobutu to Kabila : the Avatars of an
Unexpected Handover” (1999), published in French by
L’Harmattan, Paris.
WAMU OYATA M B W E * : “ YOU’RE ON YOUR OWN!”
Scooters:the best way to carry a heavy load.
26 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
T
hings are going from bad to worse in
M a r t i s s a n t . I t ’s the same all over the
Haitian capital of Po r t - a u - P r i n c e, but the
situation is even more acute in this
sprawling slum that stretches up the side of
a hill south of the city. At the last count, in 1996,
about 25,000 people lived here. And the number is
growing all the time because of the high birth rate and
the exodus of people from the countryside. Th e r e ’s
filth everywhere—puddles of dirty water in potholed
s t r e e t s, gutters choked with garbage,buildings erected
without any planning.The inhabitants,who lack even
the most basic public services,call themselves  “ p e o p l e
on the outside.”
But they have laboured, since the fall of the
Duvalier dictatorship in 1986,to build up alternative
services enabling the community to live, or rather,
to survive. To d a y, jobless youngsters just out of
s c h o o l , others who have learned a trade,
unemployed people and women are all involved
in running a variety of community groups dedicated
to different goals.
É d o u a r d , a father of three, is an active leader of
the Youth Association of Saint Bernadette and
Malet Streets (AJSM). “Our first concern is the
garbage,” he says. AJSM members, most of whom
have no job,pick up the rubbish and take it down the
hill to the main road.The garbage trucks don’t pass
through the teeming streets of Martissant.
The group has submitted a $900 project proposal
to the Port-au-Prince city authorities to buy gloves,
w h e e l b a r r o w s, picks and shovels, and even
megaphones to keep people informed. So far, t h e r e
has been no response. “We’ve been shunted from
one office to another,” says Malherbe, an A J S M
m e m b e r. “If this goes on, w e ’ll call everyone
together and stage a demonstration.”
Garbage disposal and other sensitive problems
sometimes set off bloody disputes between
people who live higher up the hill and those lower
down who suffer as a result of the rubbish dumped
t h e r e. Calling the police doesn’t help: they refuse to
get involved and advise people to deal with it
themselves.
When neighbourhood quarrels erupt, p e o p l e
turn to the older and wiser
inhabitants of the town—often
natives of Martissant or
homeowners—to mediate and
restore peace. When this
h a p p e n s, two or three elders put
their heads together to find a
satisfactory solution rooted in
common law. Recourse to the
state legal system is rare. “ I t ’s a
waste of time,” says one man.
“ Justice can be bought here, l i k e
GOTSON PIERRE
HAITIAN JOURNALIST
H a i t i :
a l o n e
on the hill
The inhabitants of
the Port-au-Prince slum
of Martissant have created
a mosaic of community
groups to fill in as best
they can for a crying absence
of public services
H A I T I
PORT-AU-PRINCE
Atlantic
Ocean
C U B A
D O M I N I C A N
R E P U B L I C P U E R T O
R I C O
Caribbean Sea
Lining up in Port-au-Prince for drinking water provided by a local charitable group.
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 27
WHEN THE STATE FA I L S : A SURV I VAL  GUIDE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
Population:
7.9million (1999)
GNP per capita:
$460 (1999)
GNP per capita
annual growth rate:
–3.2% (1990-98)
Life expectancy
at birth:
54years (1998)
Adult illiteracy rate:
52.2% (1998)
Sources: World Bank, UNDP.
KEY FIGURES
rice and peas at the m a r k e t .”
Demanding that a neighbour be taken to court
could also be risky. Would the bailiff dare come
face to face with the ch i m è r e s, the gangs of
j o b l e s s youths in the pay of the ruling party?
C o n fident of their unbridled power, these youths
use intimidation to control access to the slums
they hold sway over.
The young people of Martissant have also
formed “vigilance brigades” of 10 to 15 people to
defend themselves against robbers and prevent
crime after dark. Not a full-time force, they are
mainly active after an upsurge of crime.
“We look out for trouble from the rooftops,”
says Charles, who belongs to one of these groups.
“As soon as we see a ze n g l e n d o [Haitian Creole
for a thug], we alert everyone by blowing into a
l a m b i [a giant sea shell].” The inhabitants
immediately spring into action, catch the ze n g l e n d o
and take him to the police,who often let the culprits
go free.“So sometimes he gets lynched by an angry
crowd,” says Charles.
During the day, Martissant hums with activity.
Vendors wander the streets hawking their goods
while others set up shop along the main road
b y the seashore, often spreading their wares out
i n the middle of the street. Sometimes the
authorities send out men to force them back on
to the p a v e m e n t s.
Most of the women in Martissant work outside
the formal economy. They have no ready access to
credit, so they turn to money-lenders who “stab”
them with exorbitant interest rates that can reach
30 percent a month.Lenders resort to any means,
including armed force and violence, to make debtors
repay their loans. But there is no protection to be
f o u n d :victims have little faith in the state’s capacity
to address their grievances.
“We’ve set up an informal community bank,”
says Marie-Eramite,of the Martissant Organization
of Valiant Women (OFVM).About 50 people pay
one gourde (four U. S. cents) each day. After a
m o n t h , the kitty is handed over as credit to two
members of the group. This works better, she says,
than the more traditional system in which monthly
deposits are made.
“ The state should do its job and build us a
market here,” says Guerda,a single mother with fiv e
c h i l d r e n . Like many heads of families, her main
worry is paying the rent for her “house,” a single
room for which she pays between $200 and $300
a year.
Bribes to go
to high school
“ The rent was due yesterday and I’m busy lying
low,” she says. Guerda earns less than 36 gourdes
($1.40),which is the official daily minimum wage.
She knows her landlord wants to raise the rent by
about $80 a year, even though she can barely
manage the current amount.Guerda also points out
that landlords in Martissant “ d o n ’t pay any taxes on
the rent they collect.”
Only a tiny number of houses or shacks are
connected to the electricity grid.
Many people tap into the supply
i l l e g a l l y, using special wiring. A n d
some sell the stolen electricity to
their neighbours for about $2 a
month.
When there’s a fir e,“ i t ’s up to all
of us to put it out,” says Marie-
Eramite. “Last summer, we had to
form a k o n b i t [a Creole word
designating a group of people
working together] to extinguish the
fla m e s. The whole neighbourhood
helped fetch water in whatever was
at hand. The children helped by
throwing stones at the blaze.By the
time the firemen arrived, the fir e
had been extinguished.At fir s t ,t h e y
refused to help, saying the streets
were too narrow for them to enter.”
Parents in Martissant dream of
being able to send their children to
secondary school.But this is hard to
do, says Guerda,“because they ask
us for bribes of about $40 per pupil.”
The cost of schooling rises every
year and the c o l l è g e s [high schools]
28
Many children never even set foot in the slum’s poorly equipped school.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
hardly deserve the name. “When my kids go off to
school each morning to Hermann Hereaux,one of
the oldest state schools around here, I worry about
the walls collapsing onto them,” says Yo l e t t e.Th e r e
are no toilets or drinking water at the school. The
neighbourhood sometimes goes without water for
three months at a stretch.The parents have decided
to get together to buy the materials to build new
wooden benches for the children to sit on. “ Th e
carpenters are going to make them for free,” she
says.
Valiant as the efforts of civil society may be, t h e y
soon come up against the obstacles of enormous
needs and meagre resources.Take for example the
Haitian Women’s Solidarity Organization, which
opened a clinic in Martissant in 1996, the slum’s fir s t
medical facility. “ We look after women and
children,” says Marie-Yolenne, who works there.
The clinic is open three days a week and has a
female gynaecologist who also acts as a general
p r a c t i t i o n e r. She sees about 3 0 patients a day, w h o
pay 15 gourdes ($0.60) for an appointment.B u t ,s h e
says,“they struggle to pay for the medicine.”
Like the inhabitants of other slums, the people
of Martissant believed change would come with
the December 1990 presidential elections, w h i c h
brought the left-wing priest Jean-Bertrand A r i s t i d e
to power. But they were disappointed. Far fewer
went out to vote last November 26 when he ran for
re-election.
“ We still hope things will change,” says Guerda
stoically.“Because we just can’t go on like this.” ■
An armed revolt led by emancipated slaves won independence for Haiti in
1 8 0 4 , at a time when it was considered the world’s richest colony. Half the
country’s 400,000 slaves had been born in Africa,so they had to fashion an
entirely new country, building a nation and a state structure at the same time.
H a i t i ’s history since then has, u n d e r s t a n d a b l y, been neither easy nor conventional.
The former slaves quickly fled the old plantations and in time became owners
of small plots of land.The rural population dispersed as far as they could go,
into remote mountain areas, forming a very small number of villages. Most towns
were established along the coast and continued to be trading posts, as in colonial
t i m e s. Only now, they were dominated by the new local ruling class, which quickly
took the place of the departed slave-owners by restoring colonial institutions
and practices.
Th u s, from the outset, the new state locked itself into the role of a violent and
a r b i t rary predator. The rural population chose to ignore it or find ways to
circumvent its authority. The state seemed to offer the people nothing of
value, and it was shunned to the largest extent possible.
But as dictatorships and strong-arm regimes succeeded one another throughout
the 19th and 20th centuries, Haitians tried to find waysto provide themselves
the basic community services that thestate failed to deliver.A local grassroots
autonomy was born,and it functioned and coexisted alongside authoritarian
r e g i m e s. Th e state in fact saw this as a convenient escape from their
responsibilities, including funding for education,health and infrastructure.
The strength of this phenomenon was illustrated in 1986 when the Duvalier
dictatorship was overthrown, revealing the existence of an impressive number
of spontaneous social networks. Hitherto very informal, the structures comprised
about 30,000 community groups and grassroots organizations of all kinds. O n l y
a few of these groups were openly political.Nearly all of them were set up to
take charge of the most basic aspects of urban and rural life by trying to meet
the needs of the community, albeit with scant resources.
But history still weighs heavily on Haiti.The old fear of state power, h e i g h t e n e d
by the military coup in 1991, remains very strong. Local structures remain semi-
clandestine in order to protect their participants when necessary. A l s o, t h e
historic fragmentation of Haitian society, which is reflected in its  physical
d i s p e r s i o n , has left a dearth of bodies able to bridge the gap between the
people and the state.
It is still very hard today to bring together the multitude of groups that have
sprung up in Haiti to defend people against the state or compensate for its
failings. And thus it is hard to lay the foundations of a modern, democratic
dialogue between the government and the people. ■
* Author of several books on Haitian society, including the recent Créoles-
Bossales:le conflit haïtien, (Ibis Rouge, 2000, Paris).
GÉRARD BA R T H É L E M Y * : “A PROFOUND MISTRUST OF THE STAT E ”
T I M E L I N E
1804: Haiti becomes the first independent country of former
slaves in the world.
1957: François “Papa Doc” Duvalier elected president, a title
extended for life in 1 9 6 4. He rules with an iron fist until his death
in 1971, killing thousands.
1971-86: Jean-Claude “Baby Doc”Duvalier succeeds his father
as “ p r e s i d e n t - f o r- l i f e ” .A general revolt forces him to flee to Fra n c e
in 1 9 8 6. The army takes over and promises constitutional
government.
1986-December 1990: A succession of mostly military regimes,
until the landslide election victory of Jean-Bertrand A r i s t i d e, a left-
wing Catholic priest.
September 1991: The army overthrows Aristide. International
sanctions are imposed on Haiti.
1993: The UN orders an oil and arms embargo. The army agrees
to allow Aristide to take power again, but prevents his return from
exile.
1 9 9 4 : On September 19, U. S. troops peacefully occupy the
country and restore Aristide to power on October 15.
1995: A UN peacekeeping force takes over from US troops. An
Aristide protégé, René Préva l , is elected president virtually
unopposed.
1996-98: Violence and killings increase and the ruling Lavalas
party splits. An electoral dispute leads to the resignation of the
prime minister in 1997, but parliament refuses to approve any
successor.
1 9 9 9 : P r é val appoints a new government independently of
parliament.
2 0 0 0 : Parliamentary elections in May are won by A r i s t i d e ' s
Fanmi Lavalas party, but disputed results draw international
criticism and an opposition boycott of presidential elections in
November, which Aristide wins (92%) against minor candidates.
■
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 29
WHEN THE STATE FA I L S : A SURV I VAL  GUIDE
We need
government 
to do for 
the people 
what they 
cannot do for
themselves.
Abraham Lincoln, 16th
U.S. president (1809-
1865)
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
CLAUDIA MOJICA
FREELANCE JOURNALIST BASED IN GUATEMALA
Going the cooperative way
The El Mezquital slum may still be a target for gangs, but its inhabitants
have devised some of Guatemala City’s best-run community projects,
giving access to clean water, health centres and schools
“G
angsters kill three youths in El
M e z q u i t a l ” ran the headline in
one of Guatemala City’s evening
papers in its first edition of the
new year. Few readers were
s u r p r i s e d , since the name of El Mezquital has, l i k e
other poor areas of Central A m e r i c a ’s biggest city,
become intimately associated with extreme poverty,
crime and violence.
More than 120,000 people are thought to live in
the six districts or shantytowns of El Mezquital on the
southern edge of Guatemala’s capital. Some work for
the government or in the private sector and a few
have professions, but the vast majority are either
unemployed or, like 43 percent of the country’s
labour force, work in the informal economy.
In the centre of El Mezquital the roads are paved,
there is public transport and small businesses operate.
But the shantytowns are mostly run-down areas
where wood and tin shacks are often built on the
edge of ravines.
Because they were built on illegally occupied
l a n d , the shantytowns at first had no public services
of any kind. This encouraged the growth of
community efforts that have turned out to be the
best run in the whole city. Determined not to rely on
what little government help was available, t h e
inhabitants decided to set up groups aimed at spurring
community development, either by providing vital
support to some government institutions or by taking
direct charge of supplying and administering basic
s e r v i c e s.
Pitching in: inhabitants of El Mezquital digging a trench to install water pipes.
30 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
Population:
11.1million (1999)
GNPper capita:
$1,660 (1999)
GNP per capita
annual growth rate:
1.7% (1990-98)
Life expectancy
at birth:
64years (1998)
Adult illiteracy rate:
32.7% (1998)
Sources: World Bank, UNDP.
KEY FIGURES
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
“ When the co-operative was founded in 1990,
there were just 35 of us. Today we have over 1,600
m e m b e r s,” says Juana de Jesús Padilla, a housewife
who is spokeswoman of the “Effort and Hope”
United Housing Co-op (CO I V I E E S) , which was set
up to obtain legal titles to squatted land and raise
money to build houses.
“Back then we didn’t have any water supply,”
she says, “so we did our laundry in the river and
drank water we bought from the water trucks that
came round. As a result, many children contracted
stomach illnesses.” Several NG Os and government
bodies gave money to help the community come up
with its own project to supply drinking water,and the
recently founded CO I V I E E S agreed to get the plans
going and run them.
With the initial funding, three wells were sunk,
pipes laid and plants built to treat drinking water and
purify contaminated water.Although experts did the
technical work, many volunteers from the
neighbourhood helped out for free. The head of the
p r o j e c t , María Elizabeth Mijangos, reports that the
wells produce about 57,000 cubic metres of water a
month for 2,600 families. “ We charge one quetzal
($0.13) per cubic metre, while the city authorities
charge other neighbourhoods three quetzals,” s h e
s a y s.
Garbage collection is also managed by CO I V I E E S
via a truck that passes through twice a week. Th e
service charge is 15 quetzals ($1.95),about five times
cheaper than what the city charges.
The Neighbourhood Association for the
Betterment of El Mezquital (AV E P RO C O M E Z) was
founded in 1989. Its current secretary, civil servant
David Luna,recalls how six years ago the El Mezquital
health centre announced it would have to close down
because it could not meet the minimum standards of
cleanliness and security required to operate.The area
around the centre, protected by a simple fence of
wire netting, was also a constant target for gangs.
“ We held raffles and went door to door asking for
d o n a t i o n s,” says Héctor Gutiérrez, the engineer who
heads AV E P RO C O M E Z. “ We wanted to build a
perimeter wall to protect the centre, but we soon
realized we needed more than that. So we thought of
investing the initial funds in something that would
The key to El Mezquital’s success stems from its inhabitants’ clear
understanding that they were living in unbearable conditions. Many had
come from rural areas—or at least their parents had—and their determination
to adapt to city life made this awareness all the more acute.Their representatives
asserted that they wanted to make the slum into a proper town by changing
it physically and by setting up basic urban services. Such a strong will comes
as no surprise: throughout their history, Guatemalans have repeatedly shown
their appetite for change, and yet every time, they have been crushed in their
efforts.
The government, absorbed by a civil war and unable to respond to such a
desire either institutionally or materially, stamped out every grassroots initiative.
Such schemes, it thought,could only be the work of its enemies. This absence
of the state only sharpened the thirst for change among the people of El
Mezquital because it gave them a free hand.And, paradoxically, the general
breakdown of Guatemalan society encouraged the emergence of self-governing
structures.
Foreign aid organizations—mainly UNICEF and Médecins sans Frontières in
1986—did not come with ready-made solutions to impose but aimed to
inspire and encourage a movement that had already begun.The people of El
Mezquital had created institutions and democratically elected their own
representatives independently of the state’s electoral system.
The leaders of these grassroots organizations cannot be easily categorized. S o m e
are natural leaders, some have political or trade union experience, w h i l e
others are very ordinary,almost self-effacing people.Their dedication to the cause
is not without a few predictable fla w s. Personal agendas, power struggles and
even embezzlement are inevitable, as in any group endeavour, though a bit less
here than elsewhere.
The limits to the kind of grassroots self-government that has developed in El
Mezquital is tied to the shifting relationship between state officials and local
o r g a n i z a t i o n s. The state acknowledges that local leaders relieve them of
some duties and control rebellious neighbourhoods, so much so that city
authorities officially delegate power into their hands. Links with foreign aid
organizations also offer a guarantee of their good behaviour. But no authority—
city or government—wants to see self-governing groups turning into alternative
power centres:attempts are thus made to control and impede them.
This kind of independent self-development comes at great cost. The World Bank,
which arrived on the scene later, calculated that investment between 1994 and
1997 was about $1,300 per family. Foreign aid organizations must persevere
and be very diplomatic in their behaviour and goals.They also have to accept
that what they experience in El Mezquital is life itself, with all its ups and dow
■
* Worked for 10 years with grassroots organizations in El Mezquital;
currently responsible for water hygiene with Médecins sans Frontières.
FRANCISCO DIAZ*: “A HISTORICAL THIRST FOR CHANGE”
Groups also seek to protect children,the prime targets of poverty.
ELSALVADOR
HONDURAS
MEXICO
Guatemala City
G U A T E M A L A
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 31
WHEN THE STATE FA I L S : A SURV I VAL  GUIDE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
generate enough profit to ensure the centre’s future.”
A car park next to the health centre was thus
b o r n . “ The area was full of rubbish,” says Ja c i n t o
G o n z á l e z , the association’s vice-president.“It took us
six months to clean the place up, get rid of the weeds
and level the ground.”The car park, which holds up
to 35 vehicles, charges 90 quetzals ($11.70) a month
or 5 quetzals ($0.65) a day, and the profits go to
maintain the centre and pay for a security guard.
Amid El Mezquital’s traffic and pollution the
renovated health centre is a little oasis,with lawn grass,
t r e e s, rosebushes and birds. “ We see about 2,400
patients each month and give them free consultations
and medicine,” says Walter Méndez, one of three
doctors working there.Although the clinic belongs to
the health ministry,“most of what you see here is the
result of AV E R P RO C O M E Z,” he says. “I think it’s the
best-equipped clinic in
the whole city.”
Money from the car
park has also been used
to buy desks and other
furniture for the new
g o v e r n m e n t - o w n e d
Institute of Basic
E d u c a t i o n , w h o s e
premises were handed
over completely empty
to the teachers appointed
by the education ministry
to run it. P r i m a r y
education in the
neighbourhood is mainly
provided by two state-
run and two Catholic schools that are virtually free,
though there are also a few private schools
Street crime, h o w e v e r, remains El Mezquital’s
greatest unsolved problem.“ We all risk being attacked
in the street or in our homes and the police do nothing
about it,”complains José Luis Guitiérrez,who lives on
10th Street, one of the most dangerous in the whole
n e i g h b o u r h o o d .The threat posed by gangs of youths,
known as m a r a s, is not confined to El Mezquital. A
survey published in the local press showed that about
90 such gangs operate in the capital. In 1999 alone
more than 4,000 gang members,most of them children
from slum areas, were arrested and charged with
using and dealing drugs, possessing illegal fir e a r m s,
m u r d e r, sexual abuse and blackmail.
Brother Demsey Luarca,who runs the Dios Con
Nosotros parish, shares the concerns. “ The kids at
our school are an easy target for the m a r a s, who lie in
wait for them as they come and go and rob them of
their small amount of lunch money, their schoolbooks,
even their clothes and shoes.”
After many fruitless attempts to get the police to
a c t ,Brother Demsey tried to set up a neighbourhood
watch system similar to one in an adjoining
c o m m u n i t y, where residents raise the alarm with
whistles when they suspect criminals are prowling
a r o u n d . But the idea did not work, he says, b e c a u s e
people feared reprisals from the gangs.
Although El Mezquital has a police sub-station
with six permanent offic e r s, inhabitants seem to have
little trust in them.The story has been the same at the
national level following the 1997 peace agreement
between the government and guerrilla forces which
created a young police force that is still inexperienced
and lacks the equipment needed to maintain law and
o r d e r.
M e a n w h i l e, the people of El Mezquital have fix e d
their hopes for a better future on their own efforts.A t
the end of a day’s work as a small merchant, Ja c i n t o
González often joins a few neighbours to do
community tasks such as cleaning and painting the
Institute building.“Some people manage to contribute
m o n e y,” he says, “but it’s more valuable to give an
hour of one’s time.”
Despite some inevitable internal problems and
occasional power struggles, the community groups are
attracting people in growing numbers.There is talk of
opening a second health centre, another car park
and a playground, as well as expanding the water
supply system and launching a reforestation
c a m p a i g n .
“I’m 67,” says Juana de Jesús Padilla, “but I feel
more like 15.As long as I have the strength I’ll spend
all my free time working for the co-op.”No-one could
doubt her determination. ■
T I M E L I N E
1 9 5 4: A CIA-supported coup topples the reformist government of
Jacobo Arbenz Guzmán.
1 9 6 2: The first guerrilla movements are formed.
1 9 6 6 - 1 9 8 4: C o u n t e r-insurgency wa r. The four guerrilla movements
unite to form the Guatemalan National Revolutionary Union (URNG).
1 9 8 6: President Vinicio Cerezo is elected, marking a return to civilian
r u l e.Violence continues amidst frequent reports of torture and killings
by right-wing “ d e a t h - s q u a d s.”
1 9 9 3: President Serrano imposes martial law but is forced into exile.
A gradual return to constitutional rule and the first genuine efforts to
investigate past human rights violations.
1 9 9 4: The UN establishes the Human Rights Ve r i fication Mission in
Guatemala (MINUGUA ) .
1 9 9 6: Under UN auspices, signing of a peace treaty between the
government and URNG guerrillas on Dec. 2 9 .
1 9 9 9:The UN-sponsored Historical Clarification Commission publishes
its report in which it estimates that more than 200,000 people
disappeared or were killed between 1 9 6 2 and 1 9 9 6. It documented
600 large-scale massacres and attributed 93% of the violations to the
armed forces.
2 0 0 0: Un Secretary-General Ko fi Annan recommends extending
M I N U G UA’s mission until December 2 0 0 1. The government accepts
state responsibility for a very limited number of massacres, i n d i v i d u a l
executions and disappearances which occurred during the country’s
civil conflict and agrees to compensate the relatives of some victims of
human rights abuses. ■
Maria del Carmen, an energetic co-operative member.
32 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
I
t ’s five in the morning. The day dawns in the
Jalrez Va l l e y.Along the base of rocky mountains
topped by snow-capped peaks, a band of
vegetation stretches for 50 kilometres.We pass
groups of women in brightly-coloured clothing
and children herding sheep.Bomb craters still scar the
ground while flags flutter in the wind,
commemorating the s h a h i d s—the martyrs of the
war against the Soviet Union. Soon we come to the
village of Doabi, with its 560 inhabitants and 80
f a m i l i e s.
“Asalam-aleikum!”Hadji Amin,the khan—the
equivalent of mayor—gives us the traditionally warm
Afghan reception.We talk about the major problem
of the moment,the drought.More than a score of the
valley’s 180 villages have been badly hit and 10,000
people out of the local population of 50,000 may be
forced to leave the area.After 20 years of war, t h e r e
remains no government institution able to mount
any relief operation.That now depends entirely on the
villages themselves and on the links they have forged
with humanitarian organizations such as Solidarités
and agronomists working in the region.
The drought has affected non-irrigated crops
across the whole country.Amin has heard that more
and more people are fleeing abroad, and that
hundreds of families are arriving each day in the
refugee camps on the border with Pakistan or in the
western town of Herat. Some of them have been
through this grim experience before.At the height
of the war,as many as six million people are thought
to have fled the country. Today, 2.6 million are still
refugees in Pakistan and Iran.
Despite the gravity of this new crisis, p e o p l e
are forging a response. This is probably the only
constant in the country’s recent history. The war
took the lives of a million A f g h a n s.To d a y,ten million
mines are still strewn throughout the land and
tremendous hardship endures, but the villages are
mitigating some of the damage through their solid
traditional structures.
In Doabi, daily life is based on almost total self-
s u f fic i e n cy. Wh e a t , potatoes and fruit are grown,
while chickens, sheep and goats are raised along with
a few cows and beehives. In this broad-based rural
e c o n o m y,people trade with each other,put together
community work teams and help families in need.
Sipping tea until
consensus is reached
At the end of the summer, in the yards where the
grain is threshed,everyone hands over a share of his
harvest to the mullah, another to the mirab—the
“water overlord” who looks after the irrigation
canals—and one to the shepherd. The rest is then
divided up. The farmers are proud that Pakistani
merchants come all the way here to buy apples,
production of which has been expanded in
recent years.
Whenever a dispute surfaces in the village or
with a neighbouring one, or when some kind of
wider threat arises, such as drought, the village
assembly meets. This is the d j i r g a (in the Pashtu
l a n g u a g e, or s h u r a in Dari),which gathers together
the elders, the q a z i (religious judge), the mullah, t h e
t e a c h e r, a few farmers—some of them former
resistance chiefs—and of course the khan. All the
men wear a turban, s h i r t ,
baggy trousers and a p a t u, a
thin wool shawl.Over tea,
everyone listens and has
their say. Decisions arise
once consensus is reached.
It would be wrong to
see the d j i r g a as a simple
stopgap making up for the
lack of other systems of
a d m i n i s t r a t i o n . B y
t r a d i t i o n , explains A m i n ,
similar village assemblies
ALAIN BOINET
DIRECTOR OFTHE FRENCH NGO SOLIDARITÉS,
HASWORKEDIN AFGHANISTAN OVERTHE PAST 20 YEARS
A f g h a n i s t a n:
in the valley of
d r o u g h t
T h roughout this nation shattere d
by years of war, t raditional village
assemblies have continued
to gather, p roving their deep
commitment to bettering
everyday life
The place where disputes are settled and decisions made.
A F G H A N I S T A N
KABUL
P A K I S T A N     
T U R K M E N I S T A N
I R A N
U Z B K T N .
T A J I K I S T A N
Bamiyan
Jalrez
Government
must be born
from country.
José Martí,
Cuban patriot and
writer
(1853-1895)
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 33
WHEN THE STATE FA I L S : A SURV I VAL  GUIDE
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
have often been summoned at the regional and
even national level.By keeping up the local d j i r g a s,
the traditional system which has helped to define the
common good for the whole country is being
m a i n t a i n e d . Even if this seems a pipe-dream today,
Amin adds that everyone is convinced it is the best
way forward.
Afghanistan is a patchwork of ethnic groups
and the Jalrez Valley hosts a rare combination.Its
people are mainly Pashtuns,but there are also Ta j i k s
and Hazaras—reputedly descendants of Genghis
Khan’s soldier-workers—who make up the Shiite
minority in a country that is 85 percent Sunni
Muslim.Other ethnic groups in the valley include
Turkmens, Uzbeks and Nuristanis.
We stop in front of the mosque in Qala Ali, a
village high in the mountains hard hit by the
d r o u g h t , where about 40 Hazara families live.A s i d e
from hosting the shura, the mosque also welcomes
travellers and serves as a school,where the mullah
teaches the Koran,writing and basic arithmetic to
the village children.
Mullah A h m a d , who is clearly in charge, s p e a k s
for the village, which has managed to retain its
quasi-autonomy despite the wars. Tr a d i t i o n a l l y,
some of the menfolk go off to Kabul or Iran to
earn more money for their families; this year the
exodus is larger than normal.
There has been no rain for two years.The wheat
harvest has shrunk by 80 percent and the potatoes
are not growing any more.The villagers have sold a
few of their animals and everyone has gone into debt
while awaiting better days. Education is Ahmad’s
other big concern. For several years the village
assembly has wanted to hire a m o a l e m ( t e a c h e r ) ,b u t
money is shorter than ever.
In 1974, A f g h a n i s t a n , one of the world’s
1 0 poorest countries, had 500,000 school pupils,
1 5 , 0 0 0 teachers (2,000 of them women), 350 schools
for girls and 2,500 for boys. The national system
was certainly patchy, but it provided education up
to university level.To d a y, education depends entirely
on the meagre resources of the villages and teacher-
training has vanished.
The new masters of Kabul
On the drive back to Kabul, we pass men on
horses and large trucks brightly painted with lions
and flowers going up to the pass. Over the past few
years, this route has changed.There is more traffic
n o w, you do not see any armed men and the
checkpoints manned by this or that faction at almost
every kilometre have gone.
Our driver explains how the Taliban took control
of the valley soon after they entered Kabul in
September 1996. First they sent several men to call
for a ceasefire, threatened those who resisted with
dire punishment and bought off any hesitant
f a c t i o n s.Only after that did they install their military
and civilian governors.
Public services are non-existent. But thanks to a
balance of power very much in their favour, t h e
Taliban have ended the interminable faction wars.
The country still has no legitimate government,
fighting continues in the northeast, stronghold of
General Ahmed Shah Massoud, and violence
occasionally flares up elsewhere.The new masters of
Kabul have nevertheless managed to obtain a
monopoly of force, one of the state’s primordial
roles.
One day, perhaps, a great national djirga will
define the common good and the duties of a new
national state. M e a n w h i l e, the inhabitants of the
v a l l e y, exhausted by 20 years of fighting, h a v e
decided to lay down their arms for peace and
security, two things they lost sight of long ago. ■
TO KNOW MORE
www.solidarites.org
T I M E L I N E
1973: A military coup abolishes the monarchy and ushers in a
republic presided by Mohammed Daoud, a cousin of the king.
1979: Following a Communist coup in 1978, the Soviet Union
invades Afghanistan in December. Babrak Karmal becomes head of
state. Resistence mounts from Muslim rebels  with whom troops
wage a protracted guerrilla war.
1 9 8 6: Sayid Mohammed Najibullah becomes president amid
continuing civil war against rebel Muslim forces.
1988: Following a UN-mediated agreement, Soviet troops begin
their withdrawal, which is completed in 1989. Fighting between
various rebel factions and government forces ensues.
1992: President Najibullah steps down on April 16 as mujahideen
insurgents close in on Kabul.An interim council takes over. Fa c t i o n a l
fighting between troops of the Minister of Defence Ahmed Shah
Massoud and the Hezb-I-Islami, led by Gulbuddin Hekmatya r,
continues until the signing of a peace agreement.
1 9 9 4 - 1 9 9 6: A newly formed militant Islamic movement, t h e
Taliban (i.e. : “students of religion”) gains ground with Pakistani
support.
1996: Taliban forces capture Kabul. Former President Najibullah is
hanged, and Afghanistan declareds an Islamic state under Sharia
law. By the end of 1996, the Taliban control 90% of the country.
1999: Following the collapse of peace talks between the Taliban
and the opposition Northern A l l i a n c e, the U. S. imposes financial and
economic sanctions on the Taliban regime.
2 0 0 0: New UN sanctions intended to press the Taliban to surrender
Osama bin Laden, the Saudi-born suspected terrorist. UN aid
workers say displaced Afghans now make up the world's largest
body of refugees. ■
34 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
Population:
25.9million (1999)
GNP per capita:
n.a.(1999)
GNP per capita
annual growth rate:
n.a.(1990-98)
Life expectancy
at birth:
46years (1998)
Adult illiteracy rate:
65% (1998)
Sources: World Bank, UNDP.
KEY FIGURES
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
W
hen the state we a ke n s, d o e s n ’t
organized crime often takes its
place?
The emergence of organized crime
is symptomatic of a malaise in all of
s o c i e t y, which is not necessarily an expression of the
s t a t e ’s weakness. There are strong states in weak
societies and vice versa.The words “ s t a t e,” “ s o c i e t y,”
“ s t r o n g ” and “ w e a k ” can be used in any combination.
Most countries have beautiful constitutions,but in
themselves they do not guarantee the rule of law,
which is instead based on a vibrant civil society, a
strong and independent press, and a real separation of
powers between the executive, legislative and judicial
branches of government. And above all, you need a
culture of lawfulness to prevent the emergence of
organized crime.A strong state,as such, is completely
compatible with the existence of criminal
o r g a n i z a t i o n s. I n d e e d , the state is sometimes the
instrument of criminal systems.
Would you say that the situation is ripe for
organized crime when the social contract linking
society to the state is disrupted?
Ye s.A case in point is what happens after a war.
Look at Kosovo today: the United Nations’ presence
there has not proved sufficient to control organized
c r i m e. Generally speaking, when the relationship
between the state and society deteriorates,all kinds
of shadow or parallel societies, which lie at least
partly outside the scope of the law, increase their
i n flu e n c e. These shadow societies can assume a
political expression, for example, as liberation
m o v e m e n t s ; a religious expression, as millenarian
s e c t s ; or a criminal form, as in the mafia or triads.
There are currently dozens of countries in the midst
of a transition period which will hopefully lead to
stronger democracies.But during this stage, they are
susceptible to higher levels of organized crime.Th e y
are nevertheless better off than countries ruled by
military “ k l e p t o c r a c i e s.”
H ow does organized crime establish its influ e n c e ?
To start with, the use of similar methods enables
organized crime to co-exist with the state.Some secret
services use the same clandestine practices as criminal
o r g a n i z a t i o n s, such as safe houses, c o r r u p t i o n ,
blackmail and wet jobs [murder]. R e s i s t a n c e
movements may also do the same in wartime. E v e n
when they are victorious, not everybody gains power.
Some less fortunate members turn to crime.We know
of many cases where organized crime and entire
sectors of the state maintain secret partnerships that
b e n e fit each other. In return for at least a modest
level of impunity, organized crime provides a supply
of voters and funds election campaigns.Often a regime
has to collapse before the full measure of white collar
or khaki crime becomes apparent. An example is
N i g e r i a .Under the late dictator Sani A b a c h a ,abuse of
public office became a multi-billion dollar business.
A re white-collar criminals a serious thre a t ?
They come from the highest echelons of the state
and know how to maintain a semblance of legitimacy
while manipulating laws and institutions. O r g a n i z e d
crime rings cannot do that. Old apparatchiks and new
robber barons have plundered on a grand scale many
states created in the aftermath of the Soviet Union’s
c o l l a p s e. Secret service agents have used their know-
how to set up crime networks. To d a y, the Russian
m a fia is reportedly active in over 50 countries.
INTERVIEW BY MICHEL BESSIÈRES
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Troubled lands w h e r e
criminals are king
Organized crime can take root in all kinds of states but finds a ripe
breeding ground in crisis-ridden countries, says Alex Schmid from
the United Nations’ Terrorism Prevention Branch
Waiting for the judge after a mafia strike in a Sicilian village.
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 35
WHEN THE STATE FA I L S : A SURV I VAL GUIDE
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Organized crime’s grip on society often seems
i r reve r s i b l e. Is your cause a hopeless one?
N o.There is a very wide variety of examples.S o m e
criminal organizations rise and fall, others keep on
going for generations. M a fias—namely secret societies
with a code of silence and hierarchical command
structure—are just one face of organized crime.To d a y
there are much more amorphous networks formed on
a project basis which change countries and members
with ease. Criminal groups also arise in immigrant
c o m m u n i t i e s,where people are struggling for survival.
Depending on the situation, the second generation
children either become law-abiding citizens or take
over the criminal business of their fathers. S o m e t i m e s
new groups eliminate their predecessors. In We s t e r n
E u r o p e, the Albanian mafia has made considerable
inroads on the Turkish mafia ’s control of heroin
distribution from the Balkans.
It is often easier for the police to combat foreign
organized crime groups.When the police is infil t r a t e d ,
and corrupt elements start eliminating “good cops,”t h e
fight becomes more diffic u l t . Then the priority is to
clean up the police either by creating a new police
corps or by resorting to the intelligence service.
Is democracy an effective we apon against
organized crime?
It is wrong to assume that organized crime does
not exist in democratic countries. Open societies offer
excellent opportunities for mafia groups.D e m o c r a c i e s
must therefore wipe out police corruption, set up
effective intelligence services and win broad public
support for their fight against crime. In addition,
measures such as reducing the size of the black market,
controlling immigration in a fair and liberal way and
cutting unemployment can all help. Elected offic i a l s
and senior civil servants must be made accountable,
while corruption and money laundering must be
fought vigorously. If those who hold power in the
state set a good example of integrity and demonstrate
genuine care for the well being of people, it is possible
to fight organized crime effectively. P r e s e n t - d a y
Palermo is an example of how the tide can be turned
even in the heart of what was traditional mafia
t e r r i t o r y.
Has the reduction of government intervention in
the economy created a breeding ground for organized
c r i m e ?
Privatizations and deregulation offer organized
crime great possibilities. The deregulation of
international financial markets since the 1970s have
made money-laundering possible on a global scale.I n
many countries, private security companies have
more personnel than the police force, without having
the authority and legal basis of the latter. Given that
private security firms in some countries have a well
deserved bad reputation, this is an alarming trend.
Open societies with open borders are vulnerable
to transnational criminal activities. Modern criminals
can use information technology to plan theft or fraud
in one place, before syphoning off the profits into
off-shore bank accounts at the other end of the w o r l d .
But the international community is trying to meet
the challenge. In December 2000,124 countries met in
Palermo to sign the new Convention against
Transnational Organized Crime,a powerful instrument
for international law enforcement cooperation. O t h e r
instruments of this kind are needed to combat cy b e r-
c r i m e, for which the European Union is already
working on a regional convention. A convention
against corruption is under consideration.
The police and justice systems must harmonize
their responses to organized transnational crime and
increase their effectiveness. States and societies must
acquire the means to fight it.And the United Nations
must serve as a forum to co-ordinate their efforts. ■
T H E  W E I G H T  O F  O R G A N I Z E D  C R I M E
These highlights are extracted from a recently released U. S.
Government report.
Money laundering:According to a recent estimate, worldwide
money-laundering activity is roughly $1 trillion per year, of which
$300-500 billion represents laundering related to drug trafficking.
A former managing director of the International Monetary Fund has
estimated worldwide money laundering at 2 to 5% of the world’s
GNP, equivalent to a total ranging from $800 billion to $2 trillion.
Drugs: in 1999, Americans spent $63 billion on illegal drugs.
Trafficking of humans: In 1997, some 45,000 to 50,000
women and children were trafficked to the U.S.,representing 6 to
7% the world total.An estimated 225,000 women and children
from Southeast Asia were trafficked across international borders in
1997, accounting for nearly one-third of the world total. The UN
estimates that migrant smuggling worldwide involves 4 million
people and $7 billion annually.
N a t u ral re s o u rc e s: The stealing and illicit trade of natura l
resources generates an annual $5 to $8 billion for criminal
organizations.
Nearly 75% of the world’s rough diamonds, valued at about $5.2
billion on the open market,are mined in Africa.Of the total 1998
diamond production in A f r i c a , 13% was mined informally, mostly by
insurgent groups.
Russian crime groups illegally extract and sell 300 metric tons of
amber worth an estimated $1 billion each year, according to press
reports.
Cars: The annual global contraband trade in stolen vehicles is
estimated at $10-15 billion.
P i ra c y: According to U. S. Coast Guard data, financial losses
incurred as a result of high-seas piracy are estimated at about $450
million per year. ■
The greatest
of all evils
is a weak
government.
Benjamin Disraeli,
former British
prime minister
(1804-1881)
36 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
F
CHRISTINE LAURENT
FRENCH JOURNALIST
SPECIALIZING INENVIRONMENTAL ISSUES
Beating global warming
with nuclear power?
The nuclear power industry claims it holds the keys to reducing the greenhouse gases
responsible for global warming. Opponents are striking back with their own arsenal of
facts and figures
or several years, the nuclear energy
industry has attempted to cloak itself in
different ecological robes. Its credo:
nuclear energy is a formidable asset in
the battle against global warming
because it emits very small amounts of
greenhouse gases. This stance, f i r s t
presented in the late 1980s when the
extent of the phenomenon was still the
subject of controversy, is now at the heart
of policy debates over how to avoid
droughts, downpours and floods.
To d a y, few would deny the existence
of global warming and the fact that we
have to do something about it.The latest
report by the Intergovernmental Panel
on Climate Change (IPCC),released in
November 2000, revised its own
predictions upwards, forecasting that
temperatures will rise between 1.5 and
4.5°C by the end of the century.
Human activity obviously shares part
of the blame for global warming,s t a r t i n g
in wealthy countries where industrial
development began in the mid-19t h
c e n t u r y. It is estimated that in these
c o u n t r i e s, carbon dioxide (CO2) and
methane emissions increased by 70
percent and 145 percent respectively in
150 years. Gathered in Kyoto (Japan) in
1 9 9 7 , representatives of 38 industrialized
countries signed a protocol under which
they agreed to cut their overall CO2
emissions by 5.2 percent of the 1990 level
by 2012. The European Union is to
account for 8 percent of the cuts, t h e
United States 7 percent, Japan and
Canada 6 p e r c e n t . Russia was let off the
hook because its economy collapsed
after 1990. The effort should not be
scorned.Studies show that if the trends
of the past decade continue, t h e s e
countries will emit 20 percent more CO2
instead of 5.2 percent less by 2012.
But what’s the best way of reaching
these goals? The solutions range from
using more nuclear power, d e v e l o p i n g
renewable energy sources, encouraging
m a s s - t r a n s i t , implementing stricter
energy-saving measures and planting
f o r e s t s. “ There are all kinds of ways to cut
C O2 e m i s s i o n s,” says Antoine Bonduelle,
founder of the Climate Action Network,
which includes 320 non-governmental
organizations worldwide. “ Th e
negotiations become extremely complex
if all of these options are discussed at
o n c e.” So much so that during a
An energy-saving lamp reveals the most promising scenario: reduce consumption and cut pollution.
P L A N E T ◗
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
conference in The Hague in November
2000,the 180 countries failed to reach a
consensus on how to apply the Ky o t o
protocol.
Improve living standards
without suffocating the planet
The main focus in the battle to cut
greenhouse gas emissions is to reduce
energy consumption, which accounts for
approximately 80 percent of the
d i s c h a r g e s.The primary culprits are coal
and oil burned by electrical power plants,
heating installations and cars.The battle
is all the fiercer because in the
developing countries—which emit an
average of 0.4 tonnes of carbon per
inhabitant per year compared with three
tonnes in the OECD—growth
requirements will lead to a rapid increase
in emissions.A recent report by Georges
C h a r p a k , winner of the 1992 Nobel prize
for physics,warns that “if China pursues
its current rate of industrial growth, by
2050  it will emit eight times more carbon
dioxide than the entire industrialized
world does today.”
Seeking to avoid a situation where
badly needed improvements in living
standards go hand-in-hand with rising
greenhouse gas emissions, rich countries
agreed at the Kyoto summit  to transfer
more environmentally friendly and
efficient technology (see box).
In this context,nuclear power seems
like a simple, e f ficient solution that is
all the more attractive because it does
not call into question our societies’
energy intensive development patterns.
The world’s seven richest countries,
which include the nations with the
highest number of nuclear power plants,
advocated this solution way back in 1989
at a G7 summit. “ We recognize that
nuclear energy plays an important role
in cutting greenhouse gases,” t h e y
proclaimed.
After the Kyoto summit, t h e
European Union published in 1999 a
study called “ D i l e m m a ” , a title that
speaks for itself. European experts
sketched three different scenarios on
C O2 r e d u c t i o n , with nuclear power
accounting for varying shares of total
energy output.They concluded that the
EU has no chance of delivering on its
promise unless Europe boosts its nuclear
power capacity by the equivalent of 80
percent of its current capacity. Th e
European Atomic Fo r u m , a nuclear
industry trade group, claims that “in a
single year, nuclear power has helped to
avoid emitting 1.8 billion tonnes of CO2
in the world, w h i c h , for Europe, i s
equivalent to the emissions of 200
million cars.” Meanwhile, the OECD’s
Nuclear Energy A g e n cy published a
report in 1999 based on the hypothesis
of tripling nuclear capacity by 2050. If
that were to happen, C O2 e m i s s i o n s
would drop by6.3 billion tonnes a year
according to its calculations.
At first sight, the figure sounds
convincing enough to sweep aside any
protest from the anti-nuclear camp.
North-South nuclear solidarity
The defenders and detractors of nuclear power are now arguing about
sustainable development on a planetary level. Among the different
alternatives currently being discussed to help the rich countries meet
Kyoto's objectives, the clean development mechanism is the only one that
involves north-south cooperation.It aims to cut pollution in the poorest
countries by encouraging the transfer of clean technologies that
discharge low amounts of greenhouse gases. A developing country could
receive investment aid,while a developed country could deduct some of
the gains achieved from the amount of CO2 it is allowed to emit. For
instance, if the Chinese government asked a consortium of European
companies to build a nuclear plant instead of a coal plant, the  resultant
cut in CO2 emissions could benefit the consortium’s various members and
enter into the national reduction objectives.
Nuclear power could  contribute to the fight against the greenhouse
effect, but is it appropriate for sustainable development? At The Hague,
non-governmental organizations proposed drawing up a list of
technologies acceptable to all the parties. Nuclear power was omitted
because it was too controversial.
The  president of the conference, Jan Pronk, took up the NGOs’
suggestion to exclude nuclear energy as a solution for  developing
countries but,paradoxically, agreed that investments in nuclear power in
Eastern Europe could help  bargaining over reducing CO2 emissions. ■
Workers enter the dome of the Angra 2 nuclear reactor in Brazil.
◗ P L A N E T
38 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
But emissions from human sources are
increasing by 22 billion tonnes a year
and despite planned restrictions in
developed countries, they are projected
to rise by 60 percent globally between
now and 2020! This would bring them
to 35 billion tonnes. While an annual
reduction of 6.3 billion tonnes 30 years
down the road should not be shunned,
i t ’s not enough to convince anti-
nuclear advocates that this source of
energy is the miracle solution to global
w a r m i n g.
Beyond expert circles, s c e n a r i o s
giving nuclear energy a new lease on
life are running into mounting
opposition from society at large, s h a k e n
by the 1986 Chernobyl catastrophe and
growing concern over how to manage
nuclear waste. Almost all developed
countries have put their nuclear
programmes on hold. In 2000, not a
single reactor was under construction,
on order or planned in North America
or Western Europe. To d a y, t h e
staunchest advocates of nuclear power
are in A s i a — Ja p a n , Korea and, to a
lesser extent,China and India—and in
Eastern Europe. At the end of 1999,
the Vienna-based International A t o m i c
Energy Agency counted 38 reactors in
the planning or construction stages in 14
c o u n t r i e s. Many of them are unlikely
to be commissioned because of the
economic slump in the countries that
have ordered them.
Anti-nuclear advocates also argue
that the abundance of energy allowed
by nuclear power plants discourages
energy-saving measures. F u r t h e r m o r e,
investing important sums in nuclear
energy means earmarking less for
exploring alternative energy sources.
A report by the World Wi l d l i f e
Foundation notes that nuclear energy
does not necessarily lead to a
V I E W P O I N T S
“Replacing the plague with cholera ”
CORINNE VEITHEN, GLOBAL 2000
PH.D IN BIOLOGY; HEAD OFTHECLIMATE CHANGECAMPAIGNFOR THE GLOBAL 2000 ASSOCIATION (FRIENDS OFTHE EARTH,
AUSTRIA).
The anti-nuclear movement has spawned many environmental organizations. The hazards of
radioactive waste, passed down to future generations, and the risks of proliferation or accidents,
fuel our opposition. The greenhouse effect does not after our position. Solving the problem of
climate change with nuclear energy is like replacing the plague with cholera.
In the framework of the Kyoto protocol, the discussions do not focus on nuclear power as such,
but on how appropriate it is to include it in the flexibility mechanisms intended for Eastern Europe
or the developing countries. Is a wealthy country that invests in nuclear energy in another nation
entitled to CO2 “credits”that could count towards its reduction objectives or be sold on the open
market? Our answer is no, because nuclear power is not a sustainable energy source and therefore
cannot be encouraged by the Kyoto protocol. Countries that have agreed to cut CO2 emissions
plan to combine “internal” efforts [in their own countries] with external ones [in developing
countries or eastern Europe]. They could store up CO2 credits by building a few reactors in the
poorest countries, to the detriment of renewable energy sources, which are harder to put in place.
In Eastern Europe, all they would have to do in order to acquire CO2 credits is patch up an already-
operating nuclear power plant and keep it functioning for ten years.We believe that nuclear power
has received enough subsidies over the past 40 years. Now a chance must be given to other
energy sources, such as wind and solar power. Flexibility mechanisms must encourage the growth
of energy sources that everyone considers sustainable. ■
“Small re a c t o rs are a solution”
CHRISTIAN STOFFAËS
DIRECTOR OF INTERNATIONAL PROSPECTING AT ELECTRICITÉ DE FRANCE.
Nuclear power is coal’s only real alternative to make massive cuts in CO2 emissions, but the
environmental movement is turning a deaf ear to this reality. Several countries in Europe,
including Germany, Sweden, Italy, Switzerland and Spain, have signed a moratorium on new
plants. In those countries, the need for new reactors will not be felt for another 20 years. On the
other hand,there is a major potential in the emerging countries, where the demand for electricity
is rising 3 to 6 percent a year. In the fight against the greenhouse effect, sustainable energy
sources have a role to play in rural areas. But it is impossible to imagine them powering
megalopolises of 20 million people in China,India and Southeast Asia.In those places, the choice
is between coal, gas and nuclear power. We want to promote a different kind of nuclear power,
with international safety monitoring managed by an inter-governmental agency and the
development of smaller, safer, 100 to200-megawatt reactors between [compared with an average
capacity of 1,000 megawatts today]. It is also necessary to set up an international system to
monitor nuclear materials and to outlaw plutonium, which is a byproduct of recycling military
waste. Today, the UN must consider inscribing nuclear power in flexibility mechanisms. ■
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 39
Investing important
sums in nuclear energy
means earmarking
less for exploring
alternative
energy sources
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
reduction in CO2 e m i s s i o n s. “ Th e
United States accounts for 5 percent of
the world’s population, over 25 percent
of CO2 emissions and 29.4 percent of
n u c l e a r-generated electricity.
C o n v e r s e l y, China accounts for 21.5,
13.5 and 0.6 percent, r e s p e c t i v e l y. A
closer look at the trends between 1980
and 1997 reveals that the penetration
of non-fossil power sources [especially
hydraulic] in China during this p e r i o d
allowed that country to cut back on
only 10 million tonnes of carbon,
compared with 430 million tonnes had
Beijing adopted energy-efficiency
m e a s u r e s.”
The World Energy Council also
argues that the best way to reduce
consumption is to improve energy
e f fic i e n cy.The potential is tremendous.
Estimates suggest that savings could
reach 30 to 50 percent in Europe, and 30
to 70 percent in the United States.This
t h i n k i n g, advocated by non-
governmental organizations for a long
t i m e, is gradually winning support from
political leaders, including in Fr a n c e
(which obtains 75 percent of its
electricity from nuclear plants),where
the government has just adopted a
national plan to improve energy
efficiency.
“ For three years,w e ’ve been working
on translating the political commitments
made at Kyoto into specific measures,”
said French Environment Minister
Dominique Voynet after The Hague
c o n f e r e n c e,where she led the European
d e l e g a t i o n . “ To achieve that goal,
consumer patterns in the rich countries
will have to change and more efficient
power sources will have to be offered to
developing countries. But it will be
difficult.”
Co-generation is a new technology
being  adopted in the United States and
E u r o p e, and could show the way.A  coal-
or oil-fired electric power plant is made
Armenians set up shop at the doorstep of a local nuclear plant.
to produce heat and electricity at the
same time,recuperating up to 90 percent
of the energy produced instead of an
average 45 percent with conventional
p l a n t s. C o m b i n e d - cycle technology (a
gas turbine combined with a steam
turbine) has made tremendous strides
and offers an energy efficiency rate of
6 0p e r c e n t , while remaining cheaper than
a classic fuel-burning plant.
Individual consumers can also make
a difference. Lighting manufacturers
have calculated that the use of low-
consumption bulbs each year saves
electricity equivalent to the output of
several nuclear reactors. In the same
v e i n , household appliance and
electronics manufacturers are designing
products that guzzle less energy. A few
tenths of a kilowatt-hour of savings on a
refrigerator represents, on a worldwide
s c a l e, the output of several dozen nuclear
power plants.
L a s t l y, in addition to energy-saving
a p p l i a n c e s, research suggests that
renewable energy sources such as
h y d r o g e n , solar and wind power are
bound to acquire a new dimension in
the 21st century. To d a y, G e r m a n y ’s
windmills generate as much electricity as
four nuclear power plants. A c c o r d i n g
to the Danish  BTM-Consult, w i n d m i l l s
could soon supply over 10 percent of
the world’s electricity—half the current
nuclear output. The debate is far from
c o o l i n g.
Fi n a l l y, the anti-nuclear camp has
taken another feather out of its cap.
Mycle Schneider, head of the Wo r l d
Information Service on Energy (WISE),
points out that the nuclear sector’s CO2
emissions are far from negligible when
the whole production chain is looked
a t , not just the plants themselves. Th i s
includes  construction, e x t r a c t i o n ,
t r e a t m e n t ,c o n v e r s i o n , transport and the
stocking of waste. Taking this into
a c c o u n t , WISE calculates that for
Fr a n c e, the nuclear chain’s share of total
emissions ranges from 1.6 to 9.1 percent.
More importantly, Schneider stresses
that nuclear plants only produce
e l e c t r i c i t y, whereas our societies also
have significant heating needs.
Emissions by plants that produce both
electricity and heat would be higher
than those obtained with more effic i e n t
gas plants… The nuclear industry’s
response is being anxiously awaited. ■
A few tenths
of a kilowatt-hour
of savings
on a refrigerator
represents,
on a worldwide scale,
the output of
several dozen nuclear
power plants
◗ P L A N E T
40 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
HIROKO TAKENISHI
Shinto and shoguns:
a return to Itsukushima
At first sight, Itsukushima appears to be one island among many dotting Japan’s
Seto Inland Sea. Yet a novelist returns to the cherished site of a venerated shrine
where Shinto rituals set the skies and waters ablaze with music and the echo of
bygone rulers
sea becomes an ink wash drawing with
infinite contrasts of light and shade. On
evenings when the skies are at their
c l e a r e s t , the reflections of sun rays sparkle
gold upon the sea, transforming the
landscape into a dazzling oil painting.
In this ocean landscape, I t s u k u s h i m a
is just one island among many. With a
circumference of about thirty kilometres,
it stands at the southwest end of the bay
of Hiroshima,in the district of Saeki.Its
culminating point is Mount Misen, r i s i n g
530 metres, and harbouring ancient
forests which belong to a protected
natural site. The island is also known as
Miyajima (the Sanctuary Island), b e c a u s e
several Shinto deities are worshipped
here.According to tradition,no one was
allowed to live on the island at one time,
for its entire surface was considered an
object of worship that could only be
venerated from afar. But Itsukushima is
also distinguished by its main shrine,b u i l t
on a sandbar at the foot of a small
m o u n t a i n , and its vermillion Otorii
gateway, standing directly in the sea.
This grand gate marks the entrance to
Itsukushima’s main shrine, designated a
national treasure in Japan and added to
the World Heritage List in December
1 9 9 6 . Pine trees and stone lanterns
Graceful roofed corridors link the shrine buildings,set between mountain and sea.
The silhouettes of a multitude of islands
follow one another in close succession
on the peaceful waves of this inland sea,
bordered by the coasts of Honshu,
Shikoku and Ky u s h u . From Honshu, t h e i r
jagged outlines could be mistaken for an
extension of the mainland. The horizon
line is barely perceptible. Fishing boats
and ocean vessels ply back and forth in an
incessant ballet. From an aircraft window,
the diversity of the islands’ shapes, s o
clearly cut upon the ocean’s surface, i s
even more startling.At times they appear
like a flock of animals lying on their
bellies with outstretched legs, at others,
like giant ink strokes etched by the
forceful hand of some bold calligrapher.
The colours of the sky, the shapes and
movements of the clouds, the shade of
the hills rising upon the islands: h e r e,
nothing remains the same for a single
moment,not least the tides of the inland
sea. The harmony of the sky, islands and
sea—forever shifting over the course of
the four seasons with the moods of dawn
and dusk,of night and day—creates vistas
which seemingly reflect the very mystery
of nature.On days of soft rain, the distant
About the author
Born in Hiroshima in 1929, the novelist
and sociologist Hiroko Takenishi has
published close to 70 books. She gained
recognition with her short story entitled
Gishiki (“The Rite”) in 1969. As a literary
c r i t i c , she is noted for her essays on
classical Japanese literature and her
studies of the country’s medieval women
p o e t s. Her selected works (T a k e n i s h i
Hiroko chosakushu ) were published in six
volumes in 1995 by Sinchosha (Tokyo).Her
short stories are included in Fire from the
Ashes, a prestigious anthology edited by
the Nobel laureate Kenzaburo Oe, as well
as in Western Literature in a World
Context, edited by Paul Davis et al (New
York,St. Martin’s Press, 1995). ■
C U L T U R E ◗
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 41
According to tradition,
no one was allowed
to live on the island
at one time
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
alternate on both sides of the path leading
to the sanctuary. The island’s deer can
also be sighted on this walkway. Th e
temples, with their graceful roofs made
with several layers of cypress bark, s t a n d
out elegantly against the dark green of the
h i l l s.They are linked by vermillion roofed
corridors.When the tide rises, they look
like the pavillions of some lavish edifice
floating upon the sea.As it ebbs, they are
left to rest on the white sands.
The spectacle of tiny fish coming in
with the tide to frolic under the pathways
always warms the heart. The sun’s rays
streaming into crystal water fall upon the
e y e s, spines or viscera of these fish darting
in the waters, tracing straight lines and
c i r c l e s.And during the short ferry crossing
to Itsukushima, the shadows of
passengers are reflected on the white
sands of the shoals.
I was born in 1929 in Hiroshima,
where I lived until 1949.I cannot count
the number of times I boarded the ferry
to Itsukushima over the course of these
twenty years. The emotion I felt as we
approached the island which seemed to
greet me, the sadness that filled me when
we departed, varied with my age and
physical condition of the moment.But it
w a s n ’t until I became an adult and left my
birthplace that I realized on many
occasions that these feelings were far
from trivial.This experience of my youth
bore the seed of the exaltation or
despondence that would sometimes seize
me in adulthood. Still today, the whistle of
the day’s last ferry vibrates in the air and
the glow of lanterns suspended on the
roofed corridors quiver on the water’s
s u r f a c e. But thoughts of the island
awaken more than nostalgia.
In the summer of 1945, the atomic
bomb changed Hiroshima forever.
B e f o r e,elementary school teachers would
take their classes on outings to the ruins
of the city’s castle or to the island of
I t s u k u s h i m a . What I remember best is
the springtime beauty of the cherry
blossoms above the castle’s stone walls.
The cherry trees of Itsukushima also
come back to me, but less so than its
m a g n i ficent autumn leaves. Seen from
the sea, the island’s unique landscape
stands out with unparalleled majesty and
g r a c e. When you set foot there, t h e
delicate refinement of the trees’ shapes
and colours is equally moving.
The fiery glow of autumn leaves,
which is particularly striking at
Momijidani Park (Maple Va l l e y ) , is a
feast for the eyes across the island. The
colours are at once soft and vivid. Th e
play of light and shade, i n c e s s a n t l y
changing with the sun’s  strength and
p o s i t i o n , the rustling of wind in the pines,
the scent of the tide, the crows’ cry and the
wandering deer endow the island with a
charm found nowhere else. To prevent
the deer from nibbling on fresh shoots, a
growing number of trees are protected by
metallic hoops. It would be difficult to
forget the light green buds dotting the
branches of maple trees like the pearls of
the morning dew before the first heat of
s u m m e r. Even when the foliage thickens,
this fresh green loses none of its intensity.
The sun casts its light upon the veins of
the young leaves, giving them the sudden
appearance of a delicious summer treat.
A shogun’s fervent quest
for divine protection
There are a number of ways to reach
the top of Mount Misen, including a cable
car which offers a frightening glimpse at
the depths of the forests.Such a feeling of
fear is impossible to imagine from the
shore. I will always remember the thrill
with which I gazed at the tips of the young
maples when I was a child.Their beauty
is unmatched by all those I have since
seen throughout Japan.
Ituskushima Shrine is part of the city
of Miyajima. Six buildings form the
s h r i n e, all designated as national
t r e a s u r e s : the main sanctuary, the four
buildings of the adjoining Marôdo Shrine
(Sanctuary of the Visitor) as well as the
East and West stages.The main shrine is
dedicated to Ichikishima Hime-no-
M a k o t o, Tagori Hime-no-Makoto, a n d
Tagitsu Hime-no-Makoto, three female
deities who protect seamen and their
ships. According to temple records, the
main sanctuary was constructed in
5 9 3A D,but it was under the influence of
Taira-no-Kiyomori (1118-1181) that the
shrine underwent extensive renovation to
acquire its present dimensions and style.
Kiyomori was a shogun [military
leader] at the end of the Heian era. In
1 1 4 6 ,when he was appointed governor of
Aki province (the west of the current
department of Hiroshima), his faith in
the deities of Itsukushima gained
astonishing fervour. Seeking their
protection to give his clan lasting peace
and prosperity, he multiplied offerings to
the island’s sanctuary, going as far as
A beloved icon:the grand gateway marks the entrance to the shrine.
42 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
ordering the making of the Heike Sutra,
thirty-three ornamental scrolls.
Designated as national treasures, these
scrolls reflect the quality of artefacts kept
in the Itsukushima sanctuary. Due to
K i y o m o r i ’s influ e n c e, Itsukushima Shrine
became known to the Imperial Court.
After the emperor himself visited
I t s u k u s h i m a ,pilgrimages started to thrive
t h e r e. H o w e v e r, despite Kiyomori’s
w i s h e s, the glory of the Heike household
was short-lived and the clan’s line
extinguished.
The temple’s records make mention
of repeated fires and occasional repairs
after Kiyomori’s death. The last large-
scale works mentioned date back to 1571,
with the reconstruction of the main
sanctuary in the S h i n d e n z u k u r i
architectural style characterizing
aristocratic palaces of the Heian period
(794-1185).
Ancient music and Shinto priests
to accompany a ritual at sea
I mentioned earlier that I have
boarded the the ferry many times to
I t s u k u s h i m a . Not only because the island
is close to the city of Hiroshima,but also
because my family owned a small house
on the island where we regularly spent the
summer. Consequently, I have probably
seen the day rise and night fall upon the
island more often than most passersby.
The year is marked by several festivals:
the Seven Bay Temple Festival (Nana
Ura Jinja) in which a ritual is held
dedicated to crows, the Tamatori Fe s t i v a l
during which young men fight in high
tide to snatch a disc cut from a camphor
t r e e,or the Chinkasai Festival to prevent
fir e s. But I would like to evoke one of
the island’s most popular festivals, t h e
Kangensai (“the festival of wind and
string instruments”).
This ritual takes place at sea, once a
y e a r, beginning on the 17th day of the
lunar calendar’s sixth month and running
late into the night. How the festival
unfolds is closely tied to the moon’s rise
and the timing of the tides. The holiest
object from the Itsukushima shrine is
placed in an imperial palanquin which is
carried by boat to all the nearby shrines.
A Shinto priest accompanies this cortège.
The boat, decked with streamers and
d r a p e r y, is towed by another in which
athletic young men work the paddles and
o a r s.The priests charged with conducting
the ceremonies in each temple often take
on the role of performers at sea when
they interpret b u g a k u p i e c e s, a n c i e n t
music of the Imperial court.
Shrouded in smoke and a blinding
h a l o, the light of the torches sends
crackling sparkles raining into the waves
like the branches of a weeping willow on
f i r e. The sounds of the b u g a k u
instruments travel with the wind, l e a v i n g
a trail of bewitching echoes.This festival
is an uncanny blend of boldness and
g r a c e,nonchalance and rigour.At its heart
stands the image of a shogun at the height
of his power, faced with a fading destiny
and the yearning to perpetuate the golden
age of the Heian.
When the barge has finished its
rounds, it passes a last time through the
grand Otorii gateway at the cove’s
entrance to proceed towards the main
shrine of Itsukushima. In the background,
the moon is already high in the sky,a b o v e
Mount Misen. Long after I left my
birthplace, in 1978, I published a novel
called K a n g e n s a i. Once again, I
contemplated this island, its hills, t i d e s
and currents with trepidation,as if I had
been suddenly awakened from a deep
sleep. I gazed at the water, the fire, the
deceased.I lived through a moment that
I could not have envisioned in the days
when I still resided in Hiroshima. ■
Bringing out the shrine’s holiest object during the Kangensai festival.
Located in the western part
of the Seto Inland Sea,
the island of Itsukushima is home
to a magnificent 12th-century shrine,
although its existence
is thought to date back to 593 AD.
Poised between sea and mountain,
the architectural ensemble
of this Shinto sanctuary
is unique in Japan.
A reflection of the deeply rooted
spiritual culture of the Japanese
people, it is a perfect illustration
of the country’s concept
of scenic beauty.
Hiroshima
TOKYOITSUKUSHIMA
C U L T U R E ◗
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 43
This festival
is an uncanny blend
of boldness
and grace,
nonchalance
and rigour
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
T
SALLY WYATT
LECTURER IN COMMUNICATIONS STUDIES AT THE UNIVERSITY OF AMSTERDAMAND MEMBEROF THE BRITISH “VIRTUAL SOCIETY?”
PROGRAMME ANDAN EDITOR OF “TECHNOLOGY AND IN/EQUALITY, QUESTIONING THE INFORMATION SOCIETY” (ROUTLEDGE, 2000)
Fleeing the dot.com era
The Internet has been proclaimed as the supreme network, the place where one
day all human beings will communicate. So who are these strange people
switching off in droves?
wo years ago,one of the scientists behind
the original computer language that
gave birth to the Internet announced a
daring new plan. Work would begin,
Vinton Cerf declared, to spread the
network beyond the boundaries of Earth:
the InterPlaNet, as it has been baptized,
would bring online computing to outer
space.
Outlandish as it may at first seem, t h e
plan is consistent with the hype and breezy
forecasting all too often surrounding
discussion of the Internet.Even though
mounting evidence points to a stubborn
“digital divide”separating not just poor
and rich countries but also groups within
n a t i o n s, p o l i cy m a k e r s, business and
computer scientists downplay the fig u r e s
as brief blips in the unstoppable onward
advance of the network.
“A figure of a hundred computers per
human is not entirely unreasonable,
leading to a thousand billion computers
in the Internet in 2020,”argued Christian
H u i t e m a , a scientist involved in the
creation of the latest Internet protocol,
IPv6.“Some have observed that such a
target was a bit narrow.”
This technological optimism has come
under increasing scrutiny over the past
y e a r. The “Digital Divide,” a UN
Development Programme report from
1 9 9 9 , revealed that less than 15 percent of
the world’s population accounted for
more than 88 percent of the Internet’s
u s e r s. The financial failure of multiple
dot.com firms and a sense that the
technology is still too slow and unreliable
have dented some grander hopes for an
An uprising against the digital age? No, a protest in Munich to promote the recycling of old PCs.
◗ M E D I A
44 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
“information superhighway.” Yet it is a
little known and barely noticed trend that
may perhaps prove the most troubling: f o r
the first time, evidence has emerged of a
widespread tendency to abandon the
Internet.
No forecasting has yet taken account
of this. A cast-iron premise in all
extrapolations of the Internet’s future is
that once the network is available,
prolonged use necessarily follows.
Recent empirical work has suggested
otherwise. Cyber Dialogue, an Internet
research consultancy based in the U.S.,
has uncovered evidence of a slowdown in
Internet growth based on interviews with
1,000 users and 1,000 non-users. Th e y
argue that the rate of growth is
decelerating overall, and that an absolute
decline in the number of users aged 18 to
29 is underway. An interesting claim is
that approximately one third of U. S.
adults simply do not believe they need the
Internet and what it offers.
The first signs of a rebellion
against commercialization?
Similarly, a 2000 survey in the U.K.
found that 40 percent of the adult
population had no intention of going
o n l i n e, while most of them put their
reluctance down either to cost or to the
belief that the Internet was irrelevant to
their lives.Only a third of those who had
stopped using the Internet expected to
reconnect in the future. In early 1997,
Cyber Dialogue estimated there were
9.4 million former users in the U. S. , a
figure that had jumped to 27.7 m i l l i o n
by September 1999.
According to U. S. researchers Ja m e s
Katz and Philip Apsden,the number of
ex-users jumped in the 1990s, albeit by a
smaller margin. Their national,random
telephone surveys sketch some features
of this apparent anomaly. People who
stop using the Internet, they argue, are
poorer and less well-educated. Th o s e
who are introduced to it via family and
friends are more likely to drop out than
those who are self-taught or receive
formal training. Most surprisingly,
teenagers are more likely to give up than
people over 20.
These results must be treated with
considerable caution,since former users
can easily become active ones at a later
date. But the sheer existence of Internet
malcontents—and in such numbers if
Cyber Dialogue is to believed—raises
critical challenges to the entire online
i n d u s t r y. Why the decision to abandon
use just at the time of giant Internet
expansion prompted by the introduction
of the World Wide Web?
Possibly the most salient feature in
the trend is how it has coincided with a
revolution in the network’s character.
Though there is as yet no concrete
evidence of a link between the two, the
suspicion is that the Internet’s first users
have been alienated by the rampant
commercialization of the network over
the past five years. Perhaps these figures
point to the first signs of rebellion against
the transformation of a computer- l i n k e d
community into a marketplace.
During its first 20 years, the network
was the preserve of computer science
p r o f e s s i o n a l s, students and academics
resourceful enough to negotiate its
complicated protocols (see box). But in
1 9 9 1 , the U. S. National Science
Foundation decided to allow commercial
t r a f fic, heralding the Internet’s switch
from academic forum to virtual bazaar.
The foundation’s decision was followed
by the creation of the Commercial
Internet Exchange, designed to regulate
the exchange of traffic between newly
emerging and profit-oriented Internet
service providers (ISPs).
From four computers connected in
1969, the number grew to 188 by 1979,
159,000 by 1989, and over 56 million
worldwide by mid-1999.But the decisions
of the early 1990s and the emergence of
the Web—allowing user- f r i e n d l y
multimedia features and full integration
of the Internet’s previously dispersed
elements (e-mail, file transfer and
information access)—also marked a
change in style. The temptations of
advertising on and profiting from this
unique interface soon proved
o v e r w h e l m i n g.The proportion of Internet
computer addresses ending with .com or
.net, and thus in the private sector, has
risen steeply as a result. By 1999, these
addresses formed 79 percent of the
Internet, up from 47 percent four years
earlier.Over the same period,the public
sector share, represented by addresses
ending with .edu, .mil, .gov and .int, fell
from 48 to 17 p e r c e n t . N o n - p r o f i t
organizations also dropped in their share,
from five to two percent.From their very
low base at the end of the 1980s, b u s i n e s s
shot to a position of dominance within a
decade.
There is no doubting that the Internet
remains an incredibly diverse collection
of resources. Much of the original public
sector ethos has also remained:most sites
are free, and a slew of databases or
archives held by companies (particularly
the press) are open to whoever wishes
to access them.
But it does seem highly probable, if
a s yet empirically unproven, that the
Internet’s mutation has driven away its
first zealots. Back in the 1980s, there was
The ages of the Internet
The Internet has only come into being as a mass communications technology over the course
of the last decade. According to Lorcan Dempsey, a British expert on the subject,the network
has passed through four different stages.
First,there was the Internet as a testbed or scientists’ playground, where the technical problems
of creating a wide era computer network were being solved. This occurred mainly in the 1970s,
and primarily in the United States.
Second came the emergence of the Internet as a community, consisting mostly of computer
science professionals and students. This era, dating from the end of the 1970s to around 1987,
was marked by the creation of new services and forms of communication such as Usenet groups.
Again, this was concentrated in the United States, though other industrialized countries became
increasingly involved.
Third,the broadening of the Internet into a general academic resource, when the information and
services on the Internet became more important than the addresses of the connected computers.
This stage lasted from about 1987 to 1993, predominantly in industrialized countries.
Last, the transformation of the Internet into a commercial information infrastructure, a
phenomenon that began once the World Wide Web became available in 1993. A g a i n ,
concentration in industrialized countries remains high. ■
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
relatively little distinction between the
producers of what was on offer on the
network and the consumers. If you had
the skills and resources needed to access
the Internet,it was more than likely that
you would be able to produce content
and even services for it. The ethos was
“give some, take some.”
A string of mergers
in the scramble
for supremacy
In the first few years of the web, this
interactive culture continued, a l l o w i n g
anyone with a small amount of technical
knowledge to become an “ I n t e r n e t
p u b l i s h e r.” The change since then has
been profound. Increased emphasis on
scripting languages,multimedia and links
from the web to databases held by
organizations has handed power to
skilled,professional programmers. Now,
the medium that was initially conceived as
an opportunity for smaller organizations
and individuals to create and prosper on
a “level playing fie l d ” has bifurcated into
an industry of producers and a mass of
consumers.
This trend was reinforced by the
spread of search engines such as Yahoo!
and A l t a Vi s t a , both of which aimed to
help the user navigate through the surfeit
of Internet resources. C o m m e r c i a l
extension of this concept has given rise to
the “portal”—one of most important
elements in the current web industry.
While offering traditional search features,
these portals also try to maximize revenue
by “click-through”advertising and deals
with electronic commerce firms. Th e
result of the scramble for portal
supremacy has been a string of mergers
and takeovers aimed at securing a top
spot in Internet rankings, with leading
contenders like AO L , Yahoo! and
Microsoft acquiring other fir m s,b o o s t i n g
c o n t e n t , and linking up to media
companies such as Disney and A B C
network.As the era of digital television
d a w n s, this convergence of access and
content is certain to accelerate.
There are definitely many users who
would not object.Even in its mid-1990s
i n c a r n a t i o n , use of the Internet was
plagued by problems of connection, s l o w
movement of data, excesses of
information and the off-loading of “ j u n k
mail.” It seems likely that some of those
who abandoned the Internet did so out of
disappointment with the sluggish and
haphazard service they received once
they had signed up for the promised
information revolution.
Such former users could well be
tempted back by the latest Internet
d e v e l o p m e n t s.A stress on “ p u s h i n g ”p r e -
defined content through portals,
sophisticated encryption schemes, secure
payment systems and faster connections all
promise to make the network easier to
use and navigate, while simultaneously
reducing variety. Add to this the
fragmentation of the Internet through its
introduction in mobile phones, i n t e r a c t i v e
television and palmtops, and it is clear that
the marriage between access and
content—between the device that leads
the user into the network and what the
user sees—may well become much tighter.
The result could be absolute
commercialization.
The symbolic value of joining
the information highway
This goes to show that the
requirements of different groups of users,
and particularly groups of former users,
are not necessarily the same. The more
commercial the network becomes, t h e
more it strays from its free and interactive
origins, the more likely certain users will
be turned off.A different group of users,
on the other hand, might switch off were
it to remain chaotic and technical.
Certain trends may help to bridge this
g a p.The number and breadth of Internet
resources is still growing,as is the quantity
of local content made outside the United
S t a t e s.Simple text message services sent
via low-speed telecoms—the so-called
“information dirt track”—could also
speed the take-up of the Internet
throughout the developing world,e v a d i n g
the costly trap of commercial,h i g h - s p e e d
service providers.
But a whole set of premises about the
exponential increase in use of the Internet
and the loyalty of Internet users are under
threat.At present,the symbolic value of
having Internet access is mainly perceived
as a sign of inclusion in an unspecified,
high-technology future. Its rejection can
be seen to imply a refusal of the
i n t i m i d a t i n g, exhausting pace of
technological and social innovation.The
Internet may travel to space,but it still has
convincing to do on Earth. ■
Internet users in the world (millions), 1990-2000
1990 1991 1992 1993 1994 1995 1996 1997 1998 1999 2000
2.6 4.4 6.9 9.4 16 34
56
92
145
257
385
Some may be switching off, but the Internet is attracting steadily growing numbers.
◗ M E D I A
46 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
Connected travelling:a cyber-tram in Amsterdam.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Choi Yu l
the gre e n i n g
of Ko re a
zones. Our major water reservoirs have
become acidified,making them unfit for
human consumption. The government
has been taking measures1 to control
industrial pollution but automobile
emissions have become another major
source of contamination. For example,
in the capital Seoul, 60 percent of air
pollutants come from motor vehicle
emissions.
Then there is the issue of nuclear
power: to meet the industry’s growing
energy demands, the government plans
to build more nuclear power plants in
the coming years.This is a major concern
because we already have 16 nuclear
reactors generating over 40 percent of
the country’s electricity, and some of
them have a very poor safety record.
Any mishap could spell a disaster not
only for South Korea but for the whole
region.
In July 2000,a choreographed campaign to save the wetlands.
Choi Yul spent his prison
years strengthening his
grasp of environmental
problems. Today, the
country’s leading green
activist is rallying the
South Korean people
against polluting
industries. Together, they
have scored victories
against both national
and foreign
governments
outh Ko rea has
witnessed im-
p ressive industrial
and economic
g rowth in the last
two decades. What
impact has this
h a d on the envi-
ronment? 
There is no doubt that the economic
boom turned South Korea into one of
A s i a ’s fastest-growing economies,
bringing people prosperity. But little
attention was paid to the damaging
effects of rapid industrialization on the
environment because people were
desperate to fill their stomachs. Today,
the country is paying a heavy price for
this.
Harmful emissions from industries
have created high air pollution levels,
resulting in acid rain in our industrial
S A re Ko reans ready for a more
environmentally friendly lifestyle?
There has definitely been a shift.
Twenty years ago,people were not aware
of environmental problems.Raising the
subject of pollution in public was
considered as an anti-government, a n t i -
development attitude. The military
regime of the time suppressed all forms
of civil society activities.H o w e v e r, a f t e r
the success of the 1987 June democracy
s t r u g g l e, the influence of environmental
groups has increased significantly.
We should be clear about what kind
of prosperity we want—a healthy lifestyle
with modest resources or polluted
surroundings with more wealth. O u r
current way of life is influenced by
western culture with its wasteful habits. I
am confident that if people realize the
damages they are causing to their
e n v i r o n m e n t , they will be willing to
T A L K I N G  T O  . . . ◗
February 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
“If the present trend continues, the goverment
will be forced to pump in billions of dollars
to clean up the environmental mess”
change their attitude and the government
will follow
suit.
Also, if South Korea does not meet
global environmental regulations, it will
lose its economic competitiveness.
Foreign investors will shy away if the
country gets increasingly polluted. If the
present trend continues, the government
will be forced to pump in billions of
dollars to clean up the environmental
mess. Korea has gone beyond the stage
when it could achieve growth only by
sacrificing environmental quality.
Protecting the environment is the most
economically efficient way of achieving
social well-being, far more than building
more polluting industries to generate
wealth.
How did you get involved in
e n v i ronmental activism and what kinds of
difficulties have you run into?
In the 1970s, we were living under a
repressive military government and I
was organizing democratic movements
with other students in my university. I
was imprisoned in 1975 for my activism
and spent a total of six years in prison
(see box).While in solitary confin e m e n t ,
I asked Amnesty International and other
civic groups to send me environmental
books from overseas because such texts
were not viewed as “ p o l i t i c a l ” by prison
a u t h o r i t i e s. I ended up reading more
than 250 books on global environmental
issues and I realized that South Ko r e a ’s
rapid industrialization process would
soon lead the country towards an
ecological disaster.
After my release, with support from
several youth and pro-democracy
a c t i v i s t s, I founded the country’s fir s t
environmental NGO, the Ko r e a n
Research Institute of Environmental
P r o b l e m s, in 1982. The government
regarded it as an illegal entity and
demanded that the association be
disbanded. But I was not deterred. We
fought against the government’s
attempts to construct nuclear waste
storage sites, the dust contamination
from coal briquette plants, the spoiling
of mountains to make golf courses, and
the reclamation of coastal tidal-flats.
One of our first campaigns was to
highlight environmental hazards in the
Onsan industrial complex, known for
its non-ferrous metals industry, in 1984.
Our investigations revealed that levels of
heavy metals like copper, zinc and
cadmium in water and other living
beings were between 10 and 100 times
higher than in other areas. Nearly 10
percent of the local people had severe
pollution-related health problems like
sore limbs, sore eyes and serious skin
d i s e a s e s. But when we launched the
campaign,it was very hard to convince
people about the problems while local
doctors and biochemists rejected my
requests to scientifically prove them. I
then invited the Japanese doctor Harada
Masazumi—who had previously
i d e n t i fied industrial pollution as the
cause of Minamata disease2—to visit
Onsan.He described the disease in the
region as a complicated pollution-
related illness far worse than Minamata.
His findings were given wide media
coverage in South Ko r e a , turning the
subject into a major social issue. Th e
government belatedly organized an
investigation team and implemented
m e a s u r e s, including moving residents
of the area to safer regions.
The Ko rean Fe d e ration for Enviro n m e n t a l
M o v e m e n t , which you lead, a l s o
campaigns against nuclear power plants.
Why?
When nuclear power plants started
spreading in the 1950s, the nuclear
industry argued that they were safe and
clean. I also believed this propaganda.
After looking at the disastrous accidents
in Chernobyl,it is clear that there is no
remedy for nuclear radiation. S c i e n t i s t s
say people will continue to be affected
for generations.
Then there is the problem of safe
disposal of nuclear waste for which
South Ko r e a , like other countries, i s
struggling to find a solution. There is
currently no plan for long-term storage
or reprocessing of the spent nuclear fuel.
Also, the risk of a nuclear fallout is
Widespread protests led to the cancellation of a dam project on the Dong River in
48 The UNESCO Courier - February 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
greater in a country where there is a
repressive or authoritarian government
in power. If you look at global trends,
more and more nuclear reactors are
cropping up in developing countries
with authoritarian regimes. I am worried
that the possibility of a catastrophe is
greater in these nations.
In South Ko r e a , we are more
concerned about nuclear- r e l a t e d
problems because all our neighbours—
C h i n a ,North Ko r e a ,Taiwan and Ja p a n —
operate nuclear power plants. If an
accident happens in any of these
c o u n t r i e s, all of them will face the
c o n s e q u e n c e s. F u r t h e r m o r e, Russia has
been using its Far Eastern coast to dump
its radioactive material. So the threat of
a nuclear mishap is much higher in the
Far East than in other regions.The 1999
nuclear accident in the Tokaimura plant
in Ja p a n , which killed two workers and
exposed hundreds of local residents, is a
stark reminder that even rich countries
cannot vouch for the safety of their
nuclear reactors.
What is the situation of nuclear power
plants in South Korea?
The safety system is not satisfactory.
Though there are no reports of major
a c c i d e n t s, almost all 16 of them have
faced technical problems leading to
radioactive leakage, which the nuclear
industry tried to cover up. Some of the
power stations operate the old model
CANDU reactors. In October 1999,
there was a heavy water leakage in the
Wolsong nuclear plant:it was reported
that 22 workers were exposed to
radiation when 12 gallons of radioactive
water leaked from a reactor. Some of the
workers involved in salvage operations
were also exposed to radiation.
KFEM organized a team to
investigate this affair.When we entered
the nuclear plant, officials gave us
protective clothing before going near
the accident site. When we came out of
the area, detection equipment showed
that we had received radiation.Th o u g h
it was not life-threatening, the fact is
that even an outside inspection team
was given faulty protective gear. Th i s
allows you to imagine the condition of
workers inside the plant.
While developed countries show a
trend towards reduced dependence on
nuclear energy, South Korea is taking
the opposite course. The government
plans to increase the number of nuclear
plants to 35 by the year 2030.It has no
major plans to develop renewable
e n e r g y, which accounts for less than one
CHOI Y U L : N E RVES OF STEEL
His colleagues call him “a man of steel,” an apt description for a 51-year-old activist who has
gone through many a battle for his ideals. During his university days, Choi Yul strongly opposed
the military regime and was eventually thrown into prison,where he suffered repeated torture and
beatings. Even after his release, he was kept under house arrest and all his activities were closely
monitored. “In fact, the government did not allow me to travel abroad to participate in any
environmental conference until 1987,” recalls Yul.
Yul’s talent lies in convincing his countrymen to join the struggle against pollution. In 1993 his
movement merged with seven other similar organizations from different parts of the country to form
the Korean Federation for Environmental Movement (KFEM), which has grown into one of Asia’s
largest environmental organizations, with 47 regional branches and 85,000 individual
memberships. Yul is one of the most decorated environmentalists in the region. He was the 1994
laureate of UNEP’s Global Environmental Award and of the prestigious Goldman Environmental
Award the following year. Despite his many breakthroughs, Yul’s mission is far from accomplished.
“Since Koreans have been addicted to economic prosperity for years, creating an environmental
consciousness still remains a major challenge for activists,” says Yul,described by the Korean media
as one of the country’s most influential opinion-makers. If this is the case, then a change of mind
may well be in the making. ■
T A L K I N G  T O  . . . ◗
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 2) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 72FF ( 11 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211FF ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:         Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
“M o re and more nuclear re a c t o rs are cropping up
in developing countries with authoritarian
re g i m e s”
percent of energy produced in the
country.
South Korea cannot shut down all its
nuclear reactors immediately.But KFEM
is firmly against building new reactors
and we insist on stringent safety measures
for the existing stations.At the same time,
the key to phasing out nuclear power
plants is to change our industrial structure
towards less energy consuming industries.
It also means making people aware that
alternatives exist. K F E M , for example,
recently showed off a housing model
using solar and wind energy, and received
positive public feedback. I am confid e n t
that once people become convinced of
the potential of alternative energy
s o u r c e s, they will agree to the idea of
closing down nuclear power plants.
K F E M ’s successful campaigns against
p roposals to build a nuclear waste dump
on Gulup Island in South Ko rea and
Ta i w a n ’s plans to transport nuclear waste
to North Ko rea hit international headlines
a few years ago.
The campaign against the
construction of a nuclear waste dump on
Gulup Island began in 1994,after it was
disclosed that the government had
secretly started work on it. During the
demonstrations, one resident died and
many activists were arrested.Once the
campaign grew into a national protest
and the geological instability of the area
became widely publicized, t h e
government cancelled the construction
p l a n .This campaign is remembered as a
landmark in Ko r e a ’s anti-nuclear
movement.
Regarding Taiwan, plans to export
nuclear waste to North Korea were
made public in January 1997. We were
determined to stop this because we were
sure that ultimately, the North Korean
people would suffer,as the regime there
would never disclose the details of this
contract to its citizens. Secondly, North
Korea does not have the resources or the
technology to safely store this nuclear
waste forever. KFEM organized for a
team of  activists and congress members
to visit the nuclear depository site in
Taiwan. We told the authorities that if
North Korea is starving,you should send
food,not nuclear waste.
We received support from
environmental NGOs around the world,
sent petitions to the UN and worked
closely with dozens of other civic groups.
The project was finally cancelled in
December 1997. It was a great morale
booster for environmental movements in
South Korea and throughout the region.
In a historic meeting last year, l e a d e rs
f rom the two Ko reas revived hopes of
re u n i f i c a t i o n . What role could the
environment play in this process?
Without a doubt,environment could
be a cornerstone for beginning
negotiations between the two Ko r e a s.
Protecting the environment and
biodiversity is a prerequisite for
sustainable development. Though we
have no first hand knowledge of existing
environmental conditions in North
Ko r e a , some residents there have told us
that industrial pollution across the
border is not as bad as in the South.But
the country faces problems of famine as
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George’s Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
Gordon & Gotch Australia Pty. Ltd., Private Bag 290, Burwood VIC 3125 .
Fax: 03 9888 8561
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Partner Press, 11 rue Charles Parenté, B-1070 Brussels.
Fax: (32 2) 556 41 46/Tel.: (32 2) 556 41 40/partner press@ampnet.be
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: UNES CO O f fice, 8 Po o rvi Marg, Vasant Vihar, New Delhi 110 0 57
Orient Longman Ltd (Subscriptions Account), Kamani Marg, Ballard
Estate, Bombay 400 038. Fax: 26 91 278 .
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Editions Le Printemps Ltée., 4 Route du Club, Va c o a s .
Fax: 686 7302. 
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
UNES CO Etxea, Alda Urquijo 60, Ppal. Dcha., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: Distriplumes, Apartado 49232, Colinas Bello Monte, 10 4 2
A Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 979 8 36 0
UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce C/C
Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 28 6 0 326 .
Environment could be
a cornerstone
for beginning
negotiations between
the two Koreas
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
well as flooding and soil erosion.
President Kim Dae-Jung made a good
start by discussing environmental
problems in the Korean peninsula during
the summit meeting in June 2000. I hope
the momentum continues in future talks.
Since North Ko r e a ’s energy
consumption is lower than the South’s,
launching an alternative energy
programme would be easier and perhaps
more effective there. R e f o r e s t a t i o n
programmes in the North could be
another joint project. Both sides could
also explore the possibility of co-
management of water resources, e c o-
systems and wildlife preservation in the
sensitive demilitarized zone at the border
between the two countries.We learnt that
North Koreans are also favourable to the
idea of keeping this zone. Since South
Korea has a stronger economy, it should
fin a n c i a l l y support North Korea in solving
its environmental problems. But we have
to be cautious not to allow an onslaught
by polluting industries from the South in
the name of economic co-operation and
assistance.
As a pioneering enviro n m e n t a l
m o v e m e n t , what kind of co-operation do
you have with other groups and what
are some of your plans for the future?
KFEM was accredited to the United
Nations Economic and Social Council
with Special Consultative status in Ju n e
1 9 9 8 .This recognition allows us to carry
out environmental protection activities
through various UN programmes.
Though we can highlight environmental
problems within South Korea,we need
support from like-minded groups to take
these issues onto the global stage. We
have also developed various
programmes to share the experience of
Korean environmental movements with
other Asian nations.
Among other activities, we started
an Environmental Education Centre  in
1999 to develop programmes for
s t u d e n t s, leaders and field activists, and to
encourage citizens to participate in
environmental campaigns. We can no
longer work effectively by just raising
awareness. We need to bring people to
the sites where the damage is being done.
KFEM is also involved in the Ko r e a n
Eco-centre in Seoul, which will be an
education space for citizens and a home
for the environmental movement. The
government and other donor agencies
are helping with this project.We are also
working with 60 experts from various
fields to prepare a blueprint for an
environmentally friendly society, p a r t l y
subsidized by the government and donor
a g e n c i e s.We will be working out how to
build a society that is geared toward
using less energy and water, f e w e r
a u t o m o b i l e s, and generating greater tax
dividends for the environment. ■
INTERVIEW BY
ETHIRAJAN ANBARASAN
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
1. South Korea is not a party to the Ky o t o
Protocol on climate ch a n g e, w h i ch sets
limits on greenhouse gas emissions.
Since 1990, however, the government
has passed several environmental
regulations to limit harmful emissions
by industries. Also, in February 2000,
environment ministers from Ja p a n ,
China and South Korea agreed to
conduct a joint study on acid rain and
air pollution, and to establish an
environmental data centre to promote
regional co-operation in tack l i n g
pollution issues.
2. A neurological disorder caused by
water contaminated with industrial
waste.
Totem poles to protect coastal tidal flats.
T A L K I N G  T O  . . . ◗
February 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 51
54th year
Published monthly in 27 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
French edition: Sophie Boukhari
Ethirajan Anbarasan
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Shiraz Sidhva
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Gérard Prosper,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
Russian:Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Samay Singh (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing the
credit line reads “Reprinted from the UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author’s
n a m e. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by:
(1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,
A n nA r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,
Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - FEBRUARY 2001
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly
in Paris by UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e.
Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and additional mailing offic e s.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 02-2001-OPI 00-592 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Focus:
n From mobile phones to credit cards:
keys to tracking your every move
n The geopolitics of international surveillance
n The legislative battle between the U.S.
and Europe over personal data in e-commerce
n British comedian Mark Thomas takes aim at police
cameras in the UK
n The making of an international privacy movement
Features include:
n A day in the life of women in Kuwait
n SOS for coral reefs
n Internet in school: revolution or gadget?
n The teenagers who toppled Milosevic
n The black market of bestsellers
n War correspondents caught in ethical conflicts 
n Interview with Spôjmaï Zariâb, an Afghan writer
in her own class
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
February 2001:
New technologies
and surveillance:
how to protect
your privacy
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 28 languages
]]>
</page>
</document>
