<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="122747eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
P ro fil de
l ’ i n t e r n a u t e
en rupture
de To i l e
Le nucléaire,
p a ra d e
à l’effet
de serre ?
I t s u k u s h i m a
et son temple:
le temps
re t ro u v é
Afrique CFA:1000 F.CFA,Antilles:18 FF, Belgique:160 FB, Canada:3,95$Can,
Espagne:550 Ptas, USA:4,25 $US, Luxembourg:154 F.Lux, Portugal:700 Esc ,
Suisse:6,20 FS , United Kingdom:2,5£,Maroc:20 DH.Global warming:
i g n o rance is 
not bliss 
Child tra f fic k i n g :
when crimes
go unpunished
Chinua A c h e b e :
founding father
of African litera t u re
June 2001
Canada:$3.95 Cdn,Uni ed Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
Vo l u n t e e rs :
the power of kindness
20 01 - IN T ERN AT IONAL YEAR OF VOLUN T EERS
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
U N E S C O  P u b l i s h i n g
• To find a referen-
ce 
• To buy a book, 
a cd-rom, a
video... 
• To download a
digital version 
• and pay online in 
a secure environ-
ment 
With just one click
www.unesco.org/publishing 
New Website
Quick 
Easy 
Secure 
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
◗ PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 Sydney:the beauty and the vice
Forget the blue skies of tourist brochures and discover Sydney
in a darker mood. Photos by Trente Parke, text by David Marr
◗ PLANET
10 Global warming: ignorance is not bliss
Will politicians pay heed to scientists’ forecasts at the next international
climate conference? Michel Bessières
◗ WORLD OF LEARNING
13 With Bolivar we go
Ve n e z u e l a ’s ambitious reform to get all children into school comes
under fire for its ideological content. Fabrice Losego
◗ ETHICS
38 Children in chains
The trafficking of children spares no country, not even in the North, but so far, efforts at
striking back have been half-hearted. Louise Corradini
40 NGOs: gladiators of freedom
◗ CULTURE
41 A local train named desire
A train line featured on the World Heritage List winds through A u s t r i a ’s
Semmering Pa s s, evoking memories of a va n i s h e d , melancholy world.
Sylvia Treudel
◗ MEDIA
44 None so blind as those who will not see
Why India’s press prefers to cover beauty contests rather than report
on starvation and poverty. P. Sainath
◗ TALKING TO…
47 Chinua Achebe:no longer at ease in exile
C o n fined to a wheelchair in the United States, the founding father of A f r i c a n
literature in English stays as close as ever to his native land.
JUNE 2001
Detailed table of contents on page 16
Fo c u s Vo l u n t e e r s :
the power of kindness
Teenagers in Ljubljana, retired Britons, d i s a b l e d
Fi l i p i n o s, South African students…. Around the
w o r l d , millions of volunteers are waging a bat-
tle to help their peers marginalized by econom-
ic hardship and violence. Along the wa y, t h e y
are generating a social capital that might still
b e i n v i s i b l e, but is destined to play a role as
pivotal as the state and the market in years to
c o m e.
A volunteer in India.
C O N T E N T S
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not neces-
sarily represent the opinions of UN E S C O or those of the editors of t h e
UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and headlines are written by t h e
UN E S C O C o u r i e r s t a f f. The boundaries on maps do not imply offic i a l
endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the United Nations of the
countries and territories concerned.
I N T H I S I S S U E
◗ Distress
In a long interview (pp. 47-51),
Nigerian writer Chinua Achebe, one
of the founding fathers of African
literature, regrets that the term
slavery is applied to extreme forms
of exploitation,because it downplays
the Trans-Atlantic slave trade. Yet,
in many countries, including those
industrialized,millions of children
lead an existence that is tantamount
to economic and sexual slavery.
Working on the ground and through
international awareness campaigns,
NGOs are trying to change the tide
(p. 38-40).A tide that does not seem
to be shifting in India, where public
opinion is poorly informed of the
immense distress reigning in the
country. This time, it is the press that
is accused of giving the better part of
its space to the mirages of the
consumer society (pp. 44-46).
◗ Solidarity
The year 2001 celebrates volunteers,
the millions of women and men who
tirelessly strive to stitch together
social networks torn apart by
economic crisis and violence.
Alongside the state and the market,
this third sector produces an invisible
wealth (pp. 16-37). The fight against
exclusion is also at the heart
of Venezuela’s ambitious education
reform to reach the million or so
children who don’t go to school.But
opponents denounce the move as an
attempt at indoctrination (pp 13-15).
A sense of solidarity should also
guide states in tackling global
warming. At the next climate
conference in Bonn this July, it is to
be feared that the self-interest of
some countries will stand in the way
of any significant action,despite
scientists’ alarming forecasts 
(pp. 10-12).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 5
What happens when you live in a city that’s a travel agent’s dream? You start seeing yourself through
tourist eyes, unless you open your umbrella and follow one of the locals around. Then, the mood shifts,
but the city loses none of its magnetic power
PHOTOS BY TRENT PARKE;TEXT BY DAVID MARR
TRENT PARKE ISAN AUSTRALIAN PHOTOGRAPHERWHOSPENT FIVEYEARS DOCUMENTING SYDNEY STREET LIFE, WHICHRESULTED INHIS BOOK “DREAM LIFE.” DAVID MARR IS A JOURNALISTWITH THE
SYDNEY MORNING HERALD AND AUTHOR OF A BIOGRAPHY OFTHE AUSTRALIANWRITER PATRICK WHITE.
S y d n e y : the beauty
and the vice
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S ◗
Sydney is not the city of sunshine the world imagines it to be.I t ’s a dark town.
A port town.A damp city of heavy downpours and morning fog.Whole sum-
mers can be lost under wet grey skies.Winters are brief but uncomfortable.
Everything travel brochures say about blazing skies and summer heat
is true, of course, but like an aunt with a nasty temper, S y d n e y ’s character
is marked by grim shifts of mood. Winter westerlies cut like a knife. The
sun isn’t seen for days. Rain buckets down.
Stepping into a quasi-divine light upon leaving the Opera House.
Shadows advancing on Eddy Avenue.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
Then the umbrellas appear. Even more than London,
Sydney is an umbrella town because it’s all we need against the
w e a t h e r. Overcoats would be wonderful in those few cold
weeks, but in Sydney a good coat is a luxury. Even raincoats
aren’t strictly necessary. You can live and die without one. In
the city we shelter under that most Australian urban detail:
shop awnings. But we all have umbrellas.
Those who have grown up here are not surprised by the
dark, contradictory moods of the place. But something has
changed since the tourists arrived.At first we wondered what
they had come to see. Now, more and more, we see ourselves
through their commercial eyes. Downpours are a breach of
promise. Cold is a civic embarrassment.Poverty and corrup-
tion must be hidden from the outside world here on a few
days’visit.
Sydney has been a corrupt town since the 1790s when sol-
diers guarding the convicts brought rum ships down from
C a l c u t t a . Booze was the currency of the first years of the
c o l o n y.Human failings have been a source of corruption ever
s i n c e :d r i n k ,g a m b l i n g, d r u g s, p r o s t i t u t i o n . . . .Vice has fuelled
both the commerce and religions of the town.
One of the strangest contradictions of this almost-Eden is
the power of preachers and their talk of damnation and the
a p o c a l y p s e.They fear the beauty of the place will corrupt our
souls. Odd prophets appear out of the dark with messages of
fear and hope.They paint their slogans on the walls. Heaven
and hell are just around the corner.S y d n e y ’s light collaborates
in this Old Testament mood: the sun blazing under storm
c l o u d s, or laying gold over asphalt in the early evenings. C o n-
gregations aren’t dwindling here.
Beauty can corrupt. Nothing is more characteristic of
Sydney than the endless commercial pressure to have a slice of
the harbour: a commercial wharf, a beach or a million-dollar
view of the water. From the earliest days of white settlement,
governments have been selling off the harbour. Sydney has per-
fected every way known of turning beauty into cash.
For the citizens of this town, the Bridge and Opera House
have a special meaning.They are known all over the world:
S y d n e y : the beauty and the vice
6 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
Unfazed,bowlers huddle under their umbrella.
Founded in 1788 when 11 convict-bearing ships of Britain’s first fleet
arrived from England to establish the colony of New South Wa l e s,
Sydney officially became a city in 1842. To d a y, it is a vibrant, m u l t i c u l t u r a l
metropolis, which is home to four million people and over 200 national-
i t i e s. More than a quarter of its residential population was born overseas—
about 28% hail from Asia, 16.5% from Britain and Ireland,16% from
southern Europe and 8.5% from the Middle East, while a further 20% are
children of migrants.
During the 2000 Olympics, held from September 15 to October1,Sydney
and its iconic Harbour seized the world stage, attracting nearly four mil-
lion visitors and 11,000 athletes.A further 3.5 billion television viewers fol-
lowed the Games, dubbed the “best ever”by the president of the Inter-
national Olympic Committee. ■
O LYMPIC CITY
Everything travel brochures
say about blazing skies and
summer heat is true, of
course, but like an aunt with
a nasty temper, Sydney’s
character is marked by grim
shifts of mood.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 7
The silhouette of an ocean liner echoes the profile of the Opera House, whose roof was designed to evoke a ship at full sail.
A solitary couple dwarfed by the Harbour Bridge, an early 1930s construction.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
a British steel bridge from the 1930s and a Scandinavian fantasy
conceived in the early 1950s that have become the symbols of
a South Pacific city. But for Sydney people these two are spec-
t a c u l a r, reassuring exceptions to the rule that almost everything
built on the harbour is shabby, done for the worst motives,a n d
fails to live up to what might be the most beautiful port in the
world.
Not that we spend our lives gawping at them.Just as Parisians
live with the Louvre and Cape Towners with Table Mountain,
we live with the Bridge and the Opera House with easy pride.
We put our heads under umbrellas and slosh past in the rain,
aware but not giving them a thought. We ’re happy—even
proud—to leave gawping to the tourists. But then on a winter
day of strong sun we drive across the Bridge, or we arrive at the
Opera House on an autumn evening when the moon is coming
up over the water, and the beauty of the place seems brand new.
But trust Sydney:the mood will change. Thank God. Who
would want to live in the city of travel agents’ dreams? But the
real Sydney is irresistible:dark,shabby and contradictory, full
of strange sights and strange voices. As I write these notes
onan early winter morning, the rain is pouring down.It’s time
to leave for work. I ’ve left my umbrella somewhere—who
knows where? I’m going to get soaked. ■
S y d n e y : the beauty and the vice
8 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
When summer storms hit,up go the ubiquitous umbrellas.
A U S T R A L I A
Darwin
Perth
Hobart
Melbourne
Sydney
Brisbane
Adelaide CANBERRA
I N D O N E S I A
P A P U A  N E W  G U I N E A
Coral Sea
Indian
Ocean
Great Australian Bight
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
June 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 9
Learning to manoeuvre on slippery ground.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
S
MICHEL BESSIÈRES
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Global wa r m i n g :
ignorance is not bliss
At the seventh international climate conference that opens in Bonn, Germany on July 16, scientists
will confirm their alarming forecasts while political leaders are likely to give them the cold shoulder.
Why?
ince the 1992 Earth Summit in Rio, n i n e
years of negotiations on global warming
have led virtually nowhere. Yet some-
thing has changed: the scientific com-
munity has gained extensive knowledge
about the scope and causes of global
warming, putting them in a more legiti-
mate position than ever to alert gov-
e r n m e n t s. M e a n w h i l e, public opinion is
paying increasing attention to the
p r o b l e m . B u t , as Benjamin Dessus, a
French expert and member of the Inter-
governmental Panel on Climate Change
( I P C C ) ,w r i t e s :“ w e ’re standing before a
real paradox: public will is still falling
s h o r t , as though knowledge cripples
action instead of prompting it.”
Global warming is no longer a
matter of controversy.The 20th century
recorded the highest temperatures in
1,000 years, with an average increase of
0 . 6 ° C. The last two decades were the
hottest of the 1900s.
A series of phenomena accompa-
nies rising temperatures. For example,
almost all the world’s glaciers have
s h r u n k , while the thickness of the polar
ice cap has decreased by 40 percent
(from 3.1 to 1.8 metres) in 50 years.
Scientists have yet to establish clear
links between global warming and the
increase in natural disasters such as
droughts, storms and floods. But as the
French physicist Hervé Le Treut says,
these episodes “illustrate what might
happen if global warming continues.”
Is the current warming part of the
cyclical phases that the planet has always
e x p e r i e n c e d , or have greenhouse gas
Nepalese police check what’s coming out of the exhaust in Katmandu,one of Asia’s most polluted cities.
◗ P L A N E T
10 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
emissions resulting from human activi-
ties created new conditions? Almost all
experts now defend the second hypoth-
e s i s. Atmospheric levels of the main
greenhouse gas, carbon dioxide (CO2),
are steadily on the rise, increasing from
280 parts per million (ppm) at the dawn
of the industrial revolution to over 360
ppm today. Forecasters say the fig u r e
will climb to between 540 and 970 ppm
by the late 21st century.
Drought
and disease
The scientific community has been
sounding the alarm for a long time.Th e
first world climate conference took place
in Geneva in 1979.Nine years later, the
World Meteorological Organization and
the United Nations set up the IPCC, a n
international network of over 3,000
researchers and experts that published
reports in 1990, 1995 and 2001, e a c h
more alarming than the last. When the
latest one came out in early 2001, K l a u s
To e p f e r,director of the United Nations
Environment Programme, said that “ t h e
scientific consensus now sounds the
alarm in all the world’s capitals.”
The new report upwardly revised
previous forecasts, predicting that tem-
peratures will climb between 1.4 and
5.8°C by 2100—an increase that has been
“unprecedented for 10,000 years”—and
that ocean levels will rise between 10
and 90 centimetres.The report’s second
section focuses on global warming’s eco-
nomic and social consequences. A r e a s
where cholera and malaria are endemic
will spread, harvests will decrease in
tropical and sub-tropical regions and
drought will strike arid and semi-arid
zones more frequently.
Global warming will worsen the
imbalance between north and south
because it will have a greater impact on
poor countries, and because “those with
the least resources have the lowest
ability to adapt.” By 2050,according to
e s t i m a t e s, the world’s population will
have grown by three billion people to
reach nine billion inhabitants, and elec-
tricity consumption will be 1.5 to 2.7
times higher than it is now. The fossil
fuels responsible for the greenhouse
effect will still account for 75 to 80 per-
cent of total energy consumption,
nuclear power four to seven percent
and renewable sources (wind, sun and
water) 20 percent at best.
A number of climate-related changes
are expected (models do not exist for
these phenomena at the present time).
The most alarming one involves ocean
c u r r e n t s, which are responsible for tem-
perature exchanges between the planet’s
cold and hot regions. Two Swiss
r e s e a r c h e r s, Thomas Stocker and
Andreas Schmittner, say that the Gulf
Stream—the circulation of current in
the North Atlantic—could be inter-
rupted when atmospheric CO2 l e v e l s
reach 750 ppm. That is precisely the
figure that forecasters say will be
reached during the course of the 21st
century.
Specialists suggest combining tech-
nological solutions to stabilize green-
house gas emissions. They range from
using more efficient devices (low-voltage
l a m p s, for example) to developing cogen-
eration (the combined production of
heat and electricity) and using renewable
energy sources such as solar and wind
p o w e r. Industry has already cut its emis-
sions worldwide (they still account for 19
percent of the total), but transportation
has increased them by 75 percent.
Dessus says that the future depends
less on technological breakthroughs
than on priorities when choosing infra-
structures. Put simply, will the Chinese
and Indians choose the automobile or
the train civilization? A n d , he adds,
debate over transportation infrastruc-
tures must apply to energy and telecom-
munications networks as well. It is better
to invest in small fossil energy deposits
(coal or oil) intended for local con-
s u m p t i o n , which would be more energy-
e f ficient than setting up heavy infra-
s t r u c t u r e s, even if they are used for
transporting cleaner energy.
Symbolic targets
Of course,scientists realize that their
role is not to make political decisions.A t
the 1992 Rio summit, the participating
countries signed the United Nations
Framework Convention on Climate
C h a n g e.This document is based on two
p r i n c i p l e s : economic development in
southern countries must not be ham-
pered, and gas concentrations must be
stabilized at levels that will not danger-
ously disrupt the climate. I n d u s t r i a l i z e d
countries were asked to make an effort.
The 156 nations that ratified the con-
v e n t i o n , including the United States
despite its recent shift into reverse, are
still bound by their signature.
Since then, six conferences on the
climate have tried to make headway.
The only specific commitment dates
back to the 1997 Kyoto Conference,
when the industrialized countries gave
themselves until 2012 to cut their green-
house gas emissions by 5.2 percent.Th e
convention will not enter into force until
it is ratified by at least 55 countries
A study of the Antarctic ice cap of Vostok shows a close correlation,over 400,000years, between levels of
atmospheric gases and surface temperatures.
Carbon dioxide (ppmv)
Gap with current temperatures (°C)
Methane (ppbv)
– 400000 – 300000 – 200000 – 100000 0
Age (year before present)
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
accounting for 55 percent of emissions.
So far only 33 nations, all from the devel-
oping world, have ratified the protocol.
France is the only industrialized nation
preparing to follow suit. M o r e o v e r, n o
major polluter has met its target.France,
for example, was supposed to stabilize its
emissions, but they have already risen by
two percent.
These targets, which have only a sym-
bolic meaning for the environ-
m e n t , were supposed to usher in a
new period of political commit-
m e n t .They will not be met.The six
international climate conferences
that have taken place over the
past nine years can be considered
f a i l u r e s.As observers have stated,
each country has put its national
interests fir s t ,buckling under pres-
sure from corporate lobbies. P r e s-
ident George W. Bush’s decision
to renounce the Kyoto Protocol is
a telling example. C o m m e n t a t o r s
have pointed out that his polit-
ical career, like that of vice-pres-
ident Dick Cheney, has long been
linked to the U.S. oil industry.
Thinking in millennia
In Fr a n c e, the government
coalition of socialists, greens and
communists has withdrawn its
planned ecotax on industry con-
sumption of fossil fuels one year
before the June 2002 legislative
elections, showing that the brisk
pace of democratic politics is out
of step with the slow rate of plan-
etary changes.The oft-mentioned
precautionary principle is still
given lip service. “Every serious
attempt to tackle the greenhouse
effect will have immediate costs, w h e r e a s
the benefits won’t be apparent for a long
t i m e,” writes John W.A n d e r s o n , an A m e r-
ican environmental journalist with
Resources for the Future. “To the extent
that these potential benefits boil down to
a catastrophe that might not occur, their
impact will never be obvious. The costs,
however, are.”
Only negotiations on nuclear weapons
can compare with the scope and gravity of
the current climate talks. With the fir s t ,
h o w e v e r, there was a sense of urgency.
When it comes to global warming, i t ’s as if
solutions to curtail the problem can be
put off until later. In the meantime, g r e e n-
house gases are accumulating in the air.
Even if emissions were reduced,it would
take years (between 50 and 50,000
depending on the type of gas) for them
to disappear from the atmosphere. As
IPCC president Robert Watson has
stated,“the time it takes to check envi-
ronmental damage can’t be measured in
years or decades, but in centuries and
m i l l e n n i a .” This inertia—combined
with the accumulation of greenhouse
gases in the atmosphere—should be
taken as a motivation for immediate
action.But the opposite has happened.
Negotiators wrongly interpret it as an
additional respite.
The discussions that began in Ky o t o
on trading “polluting credits”is a good
illustration of that viewpoint. Th e
“umbrella group” (the United States,
Au s t r a l i a , New Zealand, Japan and
Russia) has imposed the idea of market
transactions by creating the right to
purchase pollution credits from coun-
tries falling short of their quota,and to
borrow against their future quotas.
Behind this approach lies the idea that
technological innovation and the
m a r k e t ’s creative capacity will provide
solutions in time. Seen from that angle,
countries see no point in imposing
heavy legal constraints on themselves.
As President Clinton said,“the Amer-
ican way of life is not negotiable.”
A plea for equity
The industrialized countries have
the tacit conviction that market-driven
technological progress will provide the
a n s w e r s.That is why they tend to reason
in terms of tons of CO2 per
share of GDP.
For example, the Chinese
release 3.93 tons of CO2 into
the atmosphere per $100 of
GNP produced, A m e r i c a n s
and Germans 4.6 and 7.7
times less, respectively. Seen
from the developed coun-
tries’ point of view, t h e i r
model of energy efficiency is
the best. Why should it be
changed? 
On the other hand,devel-
oping countries and many
non-governmental organiza-
tions argue that international
negotiations make no sense
unless they are grounded in
e q u i t y.That is why they would
rather base calculations of
C O2 emissions on the number
of inhabitants. Anil Agarwal,
of the Centre for Science and
Environment in Delhi (India),
has figured that a single A m e r-
ican releases as much green-
house gas as 25 Indians, 3 3
P a k i s t a n i s, 85 Sri Lankans, 1 2 5
Bangladeshis and 500
N e p a l e s e. He suggests allo-
cating the same emissions
quota to every human being.
This is where the public debate
comes up against humanity’s oldest
moral dilemma. Should a tree be judged
by its fruit, as implied by the U. S.
p o s i t i o n , which emphasizes energy
efficiency? Or on the contrary, should
the same rights be granted to all,
a s Agarwal argues? It is doubtful
t h e i s s u e will be settled at the Bonn
conference. ■
A lake near Bhopal (India),dried up by the current heat wave.
◗ P L A N E T
12 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
T
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
FABRICE LOSEGO, WITH ADDITIONAL REPORTING BY THE UNESCO COURIER
FREELANCE JOURNALIST
With Bolivar we go
Taking aim at corruption and vested interests, Venezuela’s government has launched
a far-reaching education reform. Some see Cuba at the doorstep, while others applaud
the will to shore up an ailing system
he Venezuelan revolution is on the march,
bearing education as its torch. S i n c e
sweeping to power as president in Fe b-
ruary 1999, Hugo Chavez, a former lieu-
tenant-colonel who led a foiled coup seven
years earlier, has launched an education
reform unprecedented in the country’s
200-year history.
Why education? “ I t ’s probably the
most important battlefield in the process of
c h a n g e,” said education minister Hector
Navarro recently. “ You can reform the
e c o n o m y,but for change to be irreversible,
you first have to change the citizen.”
Throughout his campaign, Chavez tapped
into public disaffection with the political
system that has been dominated by the
same two parties for 40 years. After being
voted in, a new constitution was drafted.
The country was renamed Bolivarian
Republic of Ve n e z u e l a , in homage to
Simon Bolivar, the 19th-century father of
Venezuelan independence and one of
C h a v e z ’s foremost intellectual mentors.
Then the government launched a radical
shake-up of the education system, c l a i m i n g
it was plagued by corrupt practices and
growing inequity. One of its prime targets
is an “ o l i g a r c h y ” made up of privileged
classes and the Church, whom the presi-
dent accuses of robbing the poor of an
education.
There’s reason for concern. The mar-
ginalized formed the bedrock of Chavez’s
electoral base, and they’re no minority.
Twenty years ago,Venezuela boasted some
of the highest quality of life indicators in
Latin America.Today, it is estimated that
two-thirds (14.6 million) of the population
lives below the poverty line, while a further
7.5 million people (31percent) are classifie d
as indigent.1
Education has suffered from the crisis.
Spending fell from 7.4 percent of GDP in
1983 to 3.8 percent in 1998. The primary
school completion rate stands at 84 per-
cent,lagging behind the 94 percent Latin
American average. “In the last 20 years,
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 13
A mural depicting Cuban hero Jose Marti and Venezuela’s Simon Bolivar graces a newly opened school aimed at poor children.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Venezuela has gone through a transition
from an ’education of castes to an educa-
tion of masses,’ considerably increasing
coverage and widening opportunities,”
states an evaluation prepared for
UNESCO. It notes, however, that “there
has been a deterioration in indicators like
repetition and dropout as well as in the
quality and pertinence of the cur-
riculum…Private education has been pro-
moted as the ’channel of excellence.’ ”
According to Abraham Zalzaman,one of
the report’s authors,“the whole education
system is in need of deep change. Q u a l i t a-
tively, it’s very weak.”
Patriotic revival
Against this backdrop, Chavez abol-
ished registration fees in public schools,
sent the armed forces into local commu-
nities to repair and build schools and hos-
p i t a l s, and launched a pilot programme
aimed at underprivileged children.
According to conservative estimates, the
initiatives have already allowed 350,000
children to enroll (roughly 4.2 million chil-
dren make up the basic school popula-
tion),a figure the president has vowed to
boost by the end of the year. During a visit
to Venezuela in January 2001, U N E S C O ’s
D i r e c t o r-General Koichiro Matsuura com-
mended Venezuela’ “serious efforts” t o
promote basic education, reflected in an
increase in education spending to 6 percent
of GDP,well above the 3.9 percent average
in developing countries.
So far, out of the 20,000 primary and
secondary schools in the country, n e a r l y
2,000 have been renamed Bolivarian.Th e i r
strong points: they offer eight hours of
classes per day (most schools only go half
d a y s ) , free meals, medical care and sports.
Patriotic symbols have acquired cult status
in many of them. Classrooms have their
“Bolivarian corners,” where the flag, the
national anthem and a portrait of the inde-
pendence leader are displayed.The flag is
raised every morning and children are
briefed in the classroom on  “Bolivarian
principles,” as mandated by the new Con-
stitution.
These pilot schools give a taste of a
profound attempt to reform the system,
framed in the National Education Project.
One of project’s chief architects is Carlos
L a n z , a sociologist and former guerrilla
who spent eight years in prison for taking
part in the kidnapping of an A m e r i c a n
businessman in the 1970s. Lanz does not
shrug off his subversive past, but affirms
that “there is no relationship between the
armed struggle of those times and the pro-
posals for educational reform put forward
by the current government.”
The project’s ideological slant, h o w-
e v e r, is fairly blunt.The “new revolutionary
education model”views globalization as a
“colonialist threat … with serious impli-
cations for collective memory and national
i d e n t i t y.”The project laments that television
and computers have “imposed values”in a
“subtle form of domination and coloniza-
t i o n .”To confront this onslaught, the project
advocates a school that will be “a space of
cultural resistance and counter- h e g e m o n y,
a place to reconquer the country’s heritage
and Indo-Afro-American roots.”A c c o r d i n g
to Carlos Casanova, a philosophy professor
from Simon Bolivar University in Caracas,
this turn represents “a loss of the western
structure in Venezuelan society, and a nega-
tion of its Hispanic past.”
With the aim of making the country
more efficient and “building an army of
patriotic Venezuelans,” secondary school
students are required to follow pre-military
instruction.A manual geared at 14-year-
olds warns against “irrational immigra-
t i o n ,” notably from neighbouring
Colombia. There are other bones of con-
tention.In its will to “democratize educa-
tion,” the project advocates the establish-
ment of “educational communities” t o
govern schools. These would extend the
present system, composed of parents,
teachers and the school principal, to the
community at large, from local sports clubs
to neighbourhood associations.The goal is
for “schools to contribute to the forma-
tion of a participatory culture.”
Private schools’ associations, t h e
Church and teachers’ unions have seen
red.In January 2001,some 5,000 parents
and teachers marched through the streets
of Caracas, the capital city, c h a n t i n g
“Chavez,don’t mess with my children,”
and accusing the regime of indoctrinating
youth in Cuban style. “ The new regime is
trying to ’infiltrate’ schools to get its ide-
ological message across,” says  Leonardo
Carvajal,a professor from Andres Bello
Catholic University, who also derides the
idea of educational communities. “Each
one will have its president, elected by
whoever from the neighbourhood, be it
the butcher, the carpenter or groups close
to the regime.” Carvajal spearheaded a
c o u n t e r-proposal for a new education
law that was presented to the National
A s s e m b l y. Intellectuals are railing against
attempts to rewrite history books to
14 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
Handing out free meals at a new Bolivarian school in a Caracas military camp.
“The project’s  anti-
western thesis on the
ends of education 
goes against the 
notion of transmitting
universal values.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
r e flect the president’s views. “ C h a v e z
wants to erase everything that happened
between Bolivar and himself,” s a y s
Guillermo Moron, a renowned historian
and educator.
The signature of an “integrated coop-
eration accord” between Venezuela and
Cuba in the field of education has hardly
cleared the air. In exchange for 53,000 bar-
rels of cheap oil per day, the country that
scores best in international education tests
in Latin America is committed to sup-
plying Venezuela with teacher training
consultants and other services. A team of
27 Cuban “ e x p e r t s ” was invited to con-
duct a “Bolivarian Literacy Campaign”
throughout Ve n e z u e l a , while 1,600
Venezuelan teachers have already gone
to the island to study the Cuban educa-
tional model. A foundation affiliated to
the Ministry of Education recently spon-
sored a nationwide essay contest on “Che
Guevara,Example for Youth.”
Teachers’ unions are fuming over
Decree 1011, which would create a new
echelon of senior school inspectors, a r m e d
with wide powers to recommend dis-
missals. The government argues they are
required because entrenched supervisors
turn their back on corrupt practices, w h i l e
opposition politicians are concerned the
decree will be used to fire teachers who
“resist teaching Chavez’s anti-imperialist,
anti-elitist and anti-corruption ideology.”
Modernization or
revolution?
Some longtime educational experts
insist on cutting through the rhetoric .
“ We ’re a very long way from a second
C u b a ,” says Abraham Zalzaman,p r e s i d e n t
of the Institute for Studies in Education
Technology and Training and co-author of
the UNESCO evaluation. “ We ’ve signed
accords with Cuba as we have with Europe
and the U. S. on other matters.”O p p o s i t i o n
to Decree 1011 is hardly surprising. “ I t ’s
the first time that we’re talking about cor-
r u p t i o n ,” says Zalzaman.“Private education
has become more of a business than a ser-
v i c e. . . If there was a supervision system in
place worthy of the name, a lot of schools
would be closed,”he said,referring to bribes
sometimes paid to officials to get around
stringent rules governing the opening of
new privately run schools.
Some regret that for now, the project
has not focused on the nuts and bolts of
l e a r n i n g.“ I t ’s a partisan political project,”
says Mariano Herrera,coordinator of the
Centre for Cultural and Educational Inves-
t i g a t i o n s.“Our children need to learn how
to read and write before anything else.
Also, the project’s anti-western thesis on
the ends of education goes against the
notion of transmitting universal values and
respecting other cultures.”
Carlos Lanz defends the government’s
position in the face of poverty and global-
i z a t i o n .“ Their mistake [referring to those
opposed to the project] is neutrality.They
speak like us about forming citizens, but
without recognizing the confli c t s, i n t e r e s t s
and power relationships inherent in society.
For those people, there is neither weak
nor strong,while we openly take the side of
the underprivileged, the oppressed. We
have to place ourselves in the context of
Ve n e z u e l a ’s revolution, which is about
anti-oligarchy and anti-imperialism.Edu-
cation has to reflect these traits.”
“ The discourse is very aggressive,”
concedes Zalzaman.“A lot of the proposed
changes have been poorly presented.But
t h e r e ’s nothing revolutionary about the
r e f o r m .I t ’s a push towards modernization.
For the first time in 40 years, w e ’re starting
to have a real political debate.Th e r e ’s a dis-
course that’s going to revitalize the country
and give a voice to those 84 percent who
live in poverty. Of course, the middle class
feels threatened.” ■
1 . S o u r c e : Venezuela Country Profile by
The Economist Intelligence Unit,2000.
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 15
Mariano Herrera*: “ Teachers at a loss”
What is the state of education in Venezuela?
Very poor. For instance, 40 percent of youth between 15 and 24
dropped out of school even before reaching high school.There are two
million young people between 10 and 24 years old who don’t go to
school or have a job. But it’s not only the fault of the education sys-
tem. Extreme poverty, which affects more than half the Venezuelan
population, is an important factor of exclusion from school. It’s a
vicious circle that has to be broken.
Many observers claim that teachers are poorly trained.
They’re not trained enough to teach the basics, namely reading and
writing.In 1980, there was teacher-training reform. From a two-year
course centred on practical problems such as working with a class of
young children,we’ve shifted to a five-year university training which
is much more theoretical. University mainly trains English, biology or
literature teachers and plenty of civil servants specialized in planning,
statistics and the economics of education. But when it comes to
teaching children how to read and write, young teachers are at a loss.
And students only study 900 hours a year…
That’s the way it is in most Latin American countries. There are not
enough schools for everyone. With the return to democracy in 1961,
there was a sense of urgency and a “massive literacy plan” was
launched.“Temporary”schools were built because we were lagging so
far behind and had to move fast. The problem is that the provisional
slowly became permanent, and now we have schools with zinc roofs
in 60°C heat that are falling into ruin. To make up for the lack of
schools, we invented the double-shift,whereby each school welcomes
two different sets of students every day. Teachers are obliged to run
from one school to another, sometimes up to three in a day, just to
make a half-decent living.
Why didn’t Venezuela invest more in education at the time of the oil
boom?
Many underdeveloped countries did the same, especially in South
America. Oil suddenly made Venezuela a rich country in terms of per
capita income but it stayed underdeveloped in terms of the money
allocated to education.An elitist system was set up that favoured the
development of universities to the detriment of primary and secondary
schools. Today, the country’s universities absorb nearly half the total
education budget.
* General coordinator of the Centre for Cultural and Educational
Investigations (Caracas).
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
lfredo Olivera, a young Argentine psychiatrist, launched a radio station
to give patients in a Buenos Aires psychiatric hospital the chance to
express themselves and get in touch with the outside world (pp. 1 8 - 1 9 ) .
Oliveira is not driven by a quest for adventure or an attraction for the
m a r g i n a l .L i ke millions of volunteers around the world, he is striving to
stitch together social networks torn apart by exclusion and violence. A s
the promoters of the International Year of Volunteers 2001 highlight,
giving one’s time is a source of enrichment, though the efforts are
often invisible and yield benefits far beyond mere economic value (pp.
2 0 - 2 1 ) .Throughout the 20th century, such voluntary initiatives have steadily expanded (pp. 2 2 - 2 3 ) .
Volunteers don’t perceive their work as a gift,but an exchange (p. 26). Young Slovenians have
started up a hotline to help their peers in trouble (p. 2 7 ) . In Brazil, company employees are mobi-
lizing in reaction to their ailing state (pp. 2 8 - 2 9 ) . Carmen Reyes Zubiaga of the Philippines is set-
ting an example, showing disabled people like herself that they can live in dignity (pp. 30-31).
In India,women who have been victims of domestic violence are helping others fend for them-
selves (pp. 3 1 - 3 2 ) , while in South A f r i c a , students are spending their holidays working in the most
underprivileged communities (pp. 3 3 -
3 4 ) . Volunteering has no age limit: i n
B r i t a i n , pensioners are recycling tools
sorely lacking in the Third World (pp. 3 4 -
3 5 ) . So alongside the state and the
m a r ke t , the non-profit sector—also
known as the third sector—is flo u r-
ishing. But its potential should not be
o v e r e s t i m a t e d : collaboration with the
other sectors rather than separate action
is the best hope for achieving mean-
ingful social progress (pp. 36-37).
Dossier concept and co-ordination by
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz, UN E S C O C o u r i e r j o u r -
nalist.
AC o n t e n t s
1 / A Global Force 
1 8 When patients take the mike
Soledad Va l l e j o s
2 0 Vo l u n t e e r i n g : a global force
for change?
Justin Davis Smith
2 2 From work camps to virtual aid
Arthur Gillette
2 4 Roll up your sleeves
2 / New Bonds
2 6 Self-interest or goodwill?
Interview with Fernando Chacon Fuentes
2 7 S l o v e n i a : teens talking to teens
Ingrig Mager
2 8 B r a z i l : taking up the social slack
Jayme Brener
3 0 A tornado on wheels
Carlo M. Ta d i a r
3 1 I n d i a : starting over at the ashram
Sudha Ramachandra n
3 3 South A f r i c a : mixing sweat with earth
Rehana Rossouw
3 4 The mending hands of youthful elders
Glyn Roberts
3 6 An “ a s s o c i a t i o n a l ”r e v o l u t i o n
Lester M. S a l a m o n
VO L U N T E E R S
the power 
F O C U S  
16 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The current International Year of Vol-
unteers has one overarching aim: to bring
about widespread recognition of the mil-
lions of people around the globe who,
through voluntary acts, play a signific a n t
role in fostering social cohesion within com-
m u n i t i e s.They are bringing light into a trou-
bled world.The problem is that this light has
been hidden under a bushel for far too long.
Governments are encouraged to endorse
pro-volunteer policies and see volunteerism
for what it is worth—an important chunk of
what we now refer to as “social capital.”
There are strong arguments for taking
a closer look at the impact of volunteer
w o r k . In recent decades, we have witnessed
how war and civil strife in scores of coun-
tries have driven families from their homes.
Displaced people and refugees have lost
their bearings and must start anew with
neighbours who may or may not share their
cultural tradition and values. Vo l u n t a r y
efforts by the victims of confli c t , often sup-
ported by volunteers outside the affected
c o m m u n i t i e s, are a critical factor in helping
to reinvent social cohesion in new settle-
ments. Conflict is not the only cause for a
breakdown in social cohesion. M i g r a n t
groups flooding urban areas in many
developing countries have a similar effect.
In every case, we need to tap into the vol-
unteer potential and extend our effective-
ness in fostering social cohesion.
Over the years, we have shifted from
seeing volunteerism uniquely as a one-way,
North-South street.We are learning to com-
bine the strengths of domestic and interna-
tional volunteers of all nationalities, s h a r i n g
skills for the betterment of communities.
Volunteers work in service functions within
o r g a n i z a t i o n s,but also informally and spon-
t a n e o u s l y. For far too long, we have
neglected the contributions of mutual aid
groups looking out for the interests of neigh-
b o u r s. Their efforts are recorded in invis-
ible ink. Through survey research at the
national level, we can gain a better appreci-
ation of their achievements and suggest how
g o v e r n m e n t s, the UN system and other
external actors can promote a positive envi-
ronment for volunteerism to flourish at the
local level.
Another broadening avenue is corporate
v o l u n t e e r i n g. Employees are given time off
to volunteer in their communities,or to take
off a few weeks to assist people in another
part of the world and, at the same time,
broaden their own experience. Although it
is starting to pick up speed, the private sector
can take corporate volunteering much fur-
ther. It is more than good PR—it builds a
s t r o n g e r, more enlightened and cohesive
work force. We are also encouraged to see
the new waves of volunteers—working from
home or office computers—who donate time
to organizations worldwide through the
U N V-powered online volunteer service
( h t t p : / / a p p. n e t a i d . o r g / OV ) . These gifted
h o m e m a k e r s, s t u d e n t s, professors and
employees make the most of their time, for
the benefit of others.
A word of caution: as volunteers of
good will, we must counter negative
impulses in our societies and shed light on
the activities of racists and extremists,w h o,
in the name of cohesion,wage violent hate
campaigns.
Now is our time to build networks globally
to facilitate and promote volunteer action.Th i s
is what IYV 2001 is all about, and close to
15,000 individual volunteers and organizations
have already registered their support for this
o c c a s i o n .We are talking about an expanding
c o n s t i t u e n cy of volunteers. They want to be
h e a r d ,to be understood for what they accom-
p l i s h ,and taken seriously for the tremendous
contributions they make to society. ■
E F F O RTS IN INVISIBLE INK
BY SHARON CAPELING-ALAKIJA
EXECUTIVE COORDINATOR OFTHE BONN-BASED UNITED NATIONS VOLUNTEERSPROGRAMME
June 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 17
E R S :
 of kindness
O P I N I O N
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
SOLEDAD VALLEJOS
JOURNALISTWITHTHE ARGENTINE DAILY PAGINA/12
When patients take the mike
How the dogged efforts of a young psychologist are keeping patients in a Buenos
Aires mental hospital in touch with the outside world
1 . A GLOBAL FORCE
“I
miss you,D a d ,I miss you, I know.Will you
be all right in Rosario?”
“He’s called Rosario,” explains Perrota
into his microphone. One of over
9 0 0 patients in Buenos Aires’ José T.
Borda Psychiatric Hospital, Perrota helps host
Radio La Colifata (Radio Crazy), a station that
transmits what patients have to say for five hours
every Saturday.The recording studio is a table set up
in the hospital gardens,while a blackboard attached
to a tree lists the afternoon’s programmes:“ Vi s i t s,”
“ R o c k ,” “ Teenage problems,” “Sports news” a n d
“Dead Mute.”
Around 30 people—patients who are not taking
part,visitors and other station staff—are listening
intently to “A Romantic Moment.” Perrota tells
his life story:how he came to the hospital,how a girl-
friend had helped him as much as she could, how
hard it can be to get a job and return to the outside
world after you are discharged.“I just want to get
o u t ,” he says. “ This is just temporary for me, f o r
everyone.We all dream of getting out of here.”
A curly-haired young man operating the sound
equipment picks up the microphone to tell Perrota
that in two months’ time, CDs of the radio broad-
casts will be available, and that with his experience
as a salesman and role in helping build up the sta-
tion,he will once again be given a job.
The announcement comforts Perrota. It also
shows the progress made by a project that began
10 years ago when Alfredo Olivera,the very same
curly-haired man operating the equipment, was a
psychology student who wanted to help out where
he could. In those days, the hospital had weekly art
and craft workshops “attended by patients who
were wandering around,” Olivera recalls. “I spent
nine months going from workshop to workshop,
but I could see that what was being done started and
ended right there.”
Olivera wanted to do something different, to
“work with the outside world,with the wider com-
munity.”
It is no shock to learn that aside from getting an
appalling press, neuropsychiatrists in many insti-
tutions actually live up to their reputation. Even
today, the Borda Hospital is intimately linked in
both public image and physical reality to all that is
unwanted and dreaded. Located about 30 blocks
from A r g e n t i n a ’s political and economic centre, it is
a place where time has stopped.Some of the patients
will never walk the streets again,others will never
Gathering in the station’s outdoor recording studio, in the hospital’s gardens.
International Year
of Volunteers
18 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
see their families again. Some have spent more
than half their lives inside. Hundreds of people live
in vast, forgotten wards. As is customary in the
Argentine public health system, doctors are few
and those specialized in treating mental patients
fewer. All this went through Olivera’s mind as he
thought about how to renew the patients’ contact
with the outside world.
“I knew someone who had a programme on an
FM community radio station, SOS in San Andrés,
and he asked me to talk about what it was like
inside Borda as part of a programme on insanity.
Instead I suggested that the patients themselves
talk about their problems.”
The next Saturday,Olivera told the patients of his
i d e a , and took a tape-recorder to the workshops,
stressing that “what they said would go on the air and
was a way of getting back in contact with society.
“One of the patients then said ’I want to talk
about why women are strange.’ Another said ’I
want to tell jokes.’ Another said he wanted to draw,
and so on.They began to speak. It was wonderful.”
Olivera was delighted with
the first recording, and other
meetings followed until finally
the radio station called him. H e
took along a small sample
(roughly edited with a twin cas-
sette machine) of some of the
conversations about madness
and mental hospitals, and “we
began to encourage listeners to
call the station and ask the patients questions.”
The Borda patients’ show soon became a weekly
fixture on the San Andrés community radio.
According to the dictionary of l u n f a rd o—a Buenos
Aires dialect— c o l i f a t o means someone who is
“ o d d , half-crazy or disturbed.” It was the name
taken from a list drawn up by the patients and voted
for by listeners.
Gradually, while dividing his time between the
faculty and his steady job, Olivera managed to get
other stations to broadcast snippets about what
was happening in Borda until eventually the
patients’ own radio station was born. Thanks to
these efforts, and without any financial or technical
help from any institution,La Colifata is now retrans-
mitted by about 50 stations. It was invited to the
World Communication Congress that the Buenos
Aires Press Workers’ Union (UTPBA) hosted last
y e a r, and for the second year running had a stand at
the Buenos Aires International Book Fair.
With the help of a short-wave radio enthusiast
who regularly tuned in,the programmes have even
been relayed to Miami and the Antarctic. And,just
like any other station, its reporters have regular seats
in the press box at Boca Júniors’ football stadium.
But the station’s boss, a psychologist who was
overwhelmed by requests for advice and has already
lost count of the talks he has given about the station,
still lives on what he earns as a researcher.He fla t l y
refuses, however, to see his work as that of a saint.
He began as a volunteer and remains one. La Coli-
fata has kept on broadcasting because he and nine
other people work for free, and because solidarity
still counts for something.
“Some listeners found out from a magazine
article that we lugged all the equipment each week
by train and bus from my house to Borda and back,”
he says,“so they called us up and gave us a second-
hand Citroen.” Soon afterwards, when the patients
launched a campaign to collect money for street chil-
dren,the car became a sort of taxi service. “When
someone couldn’t manage to bring their donation
to the hospital,I went with two patients in the car
and knocked at their door. The patients were no
longer just deprived urchins, but had their medium,
the radio, and used it to help other people.”
Another listener,this time in Bariloche,1 , 5 0 0k m s
southwest of Buenos A i r e s, even offered holidays for
some patients,who were thus given the opportunity to
leave the hospital for the fir s t
time in years.“ They did a broad-
cast from the civic centre there
before 300 p e o p l e. The experi-
ence changed them, it was won-
d e r f u l . And then there was
another trip to the coast. O n e
patient from Bolivia had never
seen the sea before.”It was also
thanks to listeners’ gifts that the
station received new recording equipment.
Since all the patients taking part have their own
particular psychological disorders, working with
them on the radio has also taught Olivera a lot
about his profession.Each time he goes on air, he
has a therapeutic objective and knows why he says
what to whom.Currently, and for a token fee, he is
looking after one patient who managed to get a
discharge from the hospital.
But he scoffs at those who like to call him a
h e r o.“People commonly put two or three ordinary
people on a pedestal and say how wonderful they
a r e.We ’re trying to get beyond this because the pro-
ject works and is flo u r i s h i n g.We ’re hoping that in 30
y e a r s, this will be seen as an example of how people
can work with those who are rejected because of psy-
chological problems.”
For this to come true, the next step is proper
training for volunteers. In places like A r g e n t i n a ,
this is probably the challenge such work faces for it
to survive and not be canonized in the void. ■
“ We’re hoping this
will be an example
of how to work with
people rejected because
of psychological problems.”
+ …
colifata@elsitio.net
History
depends solely
on the will
of man.
Jorge Guillén,
Spanish poet 
(1893-1984)
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 19
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
International Year
of Volunteers
JUSTIN DAVIS SMITH
DIRECTOR OFTHE LONDON-BASED
INSTITUTE FOR VOLUNTEERING RESEARCH
(WWW.IVR.ORG.UK)
Vo l u n t e e r i n g ,
capital of the f u t u r e?
Governments are waking up to the economic and social benefits
of volunteering, but should not rely on it as a stopgap for solving society’s ills
1 . A GLOBAL FORCE
full circle to economics again) higher levels of eco-
nomic growth.
While this capital has a role to play in building
strong and active communities, it can only be
maximized in certain conditions.Volunteering works
best in the context of a healthy and well-resourced
public sector. It is not a substitute for government
services but rather an essential complement—adding
value to the services provided by paid professionals.
As an essential ingredient of a healthy, democratic
s o c i e t y, governments have a vested interest in its
p r o m o t i o n , even when volunteers are involved in
campaigning activities and speak out against public
policies.
The benefits to the volunteers themselves should
not be underestimated.It used to be said that vol-
unteering was based on the idea of a gift relation-
s h i p.N o w, most people see it as an exchange, w h e r e
both giver and receiver benefit in equal measure.
Volunteers are quick to cite a rich list of benefits,
I
n a telling recognition of volunteering’s place in
s o c i e t y, the United Nations General A s s e m b l y
will meet this December to debate how gov-
ernments can do a better job of supporting those
who contribute to their communities without
any financial return. It is an apt culmination to the
International Year of Volunteers that has mobilized
people in 130 countries.
It is hardly surprising that governments around
the world are waking up to volunteering’s eco-
nomic and social benefit s. In the United Kingdom,
for example, volunteering contributes an esti-
mated £40 billion ($64 billion) to the economy,
whilst in Canada its economic value has been put
at $16 billion. A recent comparative study in
2 2 countries estimated that volunteers put in hours
equivalent to the work of 10.5 million full-time
employees! 
But there are dangers in solely drawing attention
to these economic justifications, even though they
can raise the status of volunteering, in much the
same way as the women’s movement has long
argued in relation to household work.
Governments might be tempted to replace paid
workers with volunteers to save money. For one,
this overlooks the fact that volunteering requires
investment and training to yield a return: a
r e c e n t study in Europe estimated that every
d o l l a r invested in volunteering brought eight in
return.
From gift
to exchange
More importantly, growing evidence supports
what volunteers throughout the world have long
k n o w n ,namely that it is good for society.A c a d e m i c s
have developed the notion of social capital to
describe the links and connections made by indi-
viduals through volunteering. Some studies have
suggested that a society rich in social capital will tend
to have lower rates of crime, lower levels of school
absenteeism and inter-racial conflict,and (coming
20 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
A volunteer doctor from the NGOCasa Al
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
June 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 21
from meeting friends to learning new skills and
gaining a different perspective on life.
Those suffering from social exclusion are
particularly likely to benefit . Disabled people taking
part in volunteering can aid social integration and
challenge the negative stereotypes of themselves
aspassive recipients of care. For the young, volun-
teering offers opportunities for self-development
and risk-taking,and provides a valuable grounding
in citizenship.
For senior citizens, it could help the process of
’active ageing’—some research has even suggested
that volunteering is good for health! In short,vol-
unteering provides a classic win/win situation, b e n-
efiting both the volunteer and society.
Removing barriers
Still, barriers to participation remain: in some
countries there is no freedom of association,while
in others, legislation may work against involving
certain groups, such as the unemployed. O r g a n i z a-
tions may be unable to pay travel expenses for vol-
u n t e e r s, thus penalising those with the lowest
incomes. There may also be attitudinal barriers —
some people may reject volunteering as old-fash-
ioned and outmoded — or institutional ones: o r g a-
nizations may be reluctant to develop opportunities
for volunteers to get involved.
Governments have a role to play in removing
these barriers, by creating an environment — legal,
fiscal and institutional — in which people are able
to volunteer.The Dutch government, for example,
has decided to scrutinize or “proof” all new legis-
lation to maximise its impact on volunteering.
Employees on 
the go in Japan
Governments also have a key role to play in
funding the organization or information technology
infrastructure at the national and local levels, t o
enable volunteering to flo u r i s h .As major employers,
they can encourage staff to play an active role in
their local communities.Taking on board emerging
evidence of the benefits of volunteering on staff
morale, team-building and business profile, more
and more employers—in the public and private
sectors—are encouraging their staff to get involved
in volunteer activity.
Ja p a n ’s Osaka Gas Company, for example,
launched a scheme called “Chiisa na To m o s h i b i ”o r
“ Tiny Lamplight” in 1981. By 1994, a staggering
13,500 staff were involved in the volunteer scheme,
which entailed employees participating in a range
of community services. The company promoted
volunteerism by allowing staff to take leave ranging
from 10 days to 12 months. Retired staff and the
families of employees were also encouraged to par-
ticipate in social welfare activities.
Though governments have their role to play in
endorsing pro-volunteer policies, they must also
recognize their limitations.The volunteering move-
ment rightly cherishes its independence, and any
attempt by the state to control its agenda must be
fiercely resisted. ■
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
Ask a group of people what volunteering means and you’re likely to get a whole range of
a n s w e r s. For some, it conjures up images of people helping the less fortunate– providing assis-
tance to children, the ill, the elderly or the blind. For others, it means campaigning for
change—getting involved with a local environmental pressure group or supporting a global
drive to abolish landmines. For yet others, it is about the struggle for survival—working with
friends and neighbours to garner the essentials of everyday life.
Whatever form it take s, voluntary activity stands apart from paid work or leisure in three wa y s.
Firstly, it is not carried out primarily for monetary gain. Secondly, it is carried out freely and
without coercion. Th i r d l y, volunteering must benefit the community, although it can be
rewarding for the volunteer, often in intangible ways.
While some societies are richer in volunteering than others, we need to be careful about
adopting a league-table approach to measuring this activity. Given the variety of forms it take s,
we run the risk of overstating the divisions between industrialized countries—which are per-
haps richer in formal volunteering—and developing ones, where the informal tradition of
volunteering is often more pronounced. ■
W H AT IS VO L U N T E E R I N G ?
Alianza treating a street child in Guatemala.
Societies need
to recognize
and promote
volunteerism 
as a valuable
activity. And
they must
encourage
volunteer
action at home
and abroad.
Kofi Annan, UN Secretary
General (1938-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
International Year
of Volunteers
22 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
ARTHUR GILLETTE
FORMER SECRETARY GENERAL OFTHE COORDINATING COMMITTEE FOR
INTERNATIONAL VOLUNTARY SERVICE,
ENDED HIS CAREER AT UNESCO AS DIRECTOR
OFTHE DIVISIONOF YOUTHAND SPORTS ACTIVITIES;
AUTHOR OF SEVERAL BOOKS ON VOLUNTEERING
From work camps
to virtual aid
Once closely tied in with community traditions, volunteering’s expansion has
been driven by an internationalist spirit. Today, it attracts a wide array of
enthusiasts, including those on the sidelines 
1 . A GLOBAL FORCE
S
orin Hurdubae, 3 8 , lives in Paris and works
several hours a week at Echanges-Solidarités-
Te r r i t o i r e s. Known by its French play-on-
words acronym EST (“East”), this NGO
focuses on cooperation with the countries in
transition of Eastern Europe—including Sorin’s native
R o m a n i a .
Sorin is but one of several part-time volunteers
of different nationalities without whom EST could
not survive, much less prosper. His desire to “lend a
helping hand” is echoed by millions of people around
the world, making volunteering a centrepiece of
today’s social landscape.
Historically, not “to lend a helping hand”would
have been an aberration.Virtually all pre-industrial
societies had more or less formal communal mutual
assistance institutions. Some survived well into the
20th century, others still exist, chiefly in the coun-
t r y s i d e. In Mali for example, a practice known as
t o n obligated youth to take part in community tasks
as part of their rite of passage into adolescence. In
Ecuador, the Quichua people continue to organize
mingas, whereby each household in a com-
munity donates labour for a specific local
p r o j e c t . In India, the notion of s h r a m d a n—
offering voluntary labour—continues to
mobilize people for rural projects, f r o m
road building to literacy training. More gen-
e r a l l y, almost all the world’s religions include
a dimension of social responsibility towards
those in need, a responsibility often intri-
cately linked to salvation or other forms of
spiritual advancement.
Friendship after war
In European societies however, g o o d
will lost some of its pre-eminence with the
industrial revolution, the rise of modern
states and the onslaught of money as the
main medium of exchange. At the same
t i m e, international movements began to
e m e r g e, notably the World Alliance of
Y M CA s, the first international youth NGO,
formed in the 1860s. In the U.S.,its volun-
teers proved instrumental in helping immi-
grant populations from Europe to settle.
After the devastation caused by World
War I,coming to the aid of the less fortunate found
renewed expression. Volunteering became a more
structured endeavour, often seen as a means of
building friendship among young people from dif-
ferent European countries. In 1920, the first inter-
national voluntary work camp was organized in
Esnes, a village near Verdun (France),an area rav-
aged by the horrible battle that took some one mil-
lion lives during the war. An initiative of the Inter-
national Fellowship of Reconciliation, the camp
helped rebuild farms and other physical infrastruc-
t u r e, a n d ,s i g n i fic a n t l y, included volunteers who had
been enemy soldiers in the Great War. It also led to
the launching of a still active and creative NGO,
Service Civil International (SCI—International Vo l-
untary Service).
P r e figuring North-to-South programmes such
a s the British Voluntary Service Overseas, t h e
U. S. Peace Corps and the German Deutsche
In 1945,International Voluntary Service workers rebuilding the French village of Ecurcey.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 23
Entwicklungsdienst by a quarter of a century, SCI
sent the first recorded team of long-term volunteers
from what were not yet called “ i n d u s t r i a l i z e d ” t o
“ d e v e l o p i n g ” countries—Europe to India—in 1934.
M e a n w h i l e,as economic depression spread,s t a t e - r u n
work camp organizations often sprung up in countries
as far apart as the U.S. and Bulgaria to give the job-
less a chance to learn a skill by volunteering for con-
servation and physical infrastructure projects.
In the immediate aftermath of World War II,
national and international teams of volunteers once
again contributed much to rebuilding Europe. To
cite just one example, many of the stones and bricks
that create the charm of today’s Old Warsaw were
lovingly laid by volunteers from several countries.
But a new world was also in the making, in which
volunteering was to play its part.The United Nations
was born, with its commitment to promote peace,
social progress and understanding between peoples
—ideals close in spirit to much volunteering in the
inter-war years. In 1948, UNESCO took the lead in
involving itself with volunteering by convening the
First Conference of Organisers
of International Vo l u n t a r y
Wo r k c a m p s.The gathering cre-
ated the NGO now known as
the Coordinating Committee
for International Voluntary Ser-
v i c e, which helped to consoli-
date and expand volunteering
worldwide.
The emancipation from
colonial rule of many countries
in Africa and Asia led to the birth of a myriad of local
voluntary service organizations.From Togo to Ke n y a ,
from Nigeria to India, countries set up volunteeer
work camps chiefly devoted to such tasks as b u i l d i n g
s c h o o l s, d i s p e n s a r i e s, r o a d s, e t c.The emerging nations
of the Third World also began to host qualified long-
term volunteers from industrialized countries.Th e s e
schemes were mostly bilateral at the outset, but their
success led to the creation three decades ago of the
UN Volunteer Programme. UNV is now a multi-
lateral effort with a high proportion of South-South
v o l u n t e e r i n g. Soon after it gained independence
from Portugal in the late 1970s, for example, G u i n e a -
Bissau hosted a number of Latin American UNV
teachers.
Rusting the Iron Curtain
Some observers are quick to note that volun-
teering can be kidnapped or abused to serve political
agendas—the Hitlerjugend Arbeitsdienst labour
brigades in Germany and similar schemes in other
totalitarian countries provide some unfortunate
illustrations. There have been many other instances,
however, when the opposite has been the case. The
East-West work camps set up during the Cold War
are perhaps the most telling example. These camps
(organized by NGOs in the West and party-approved
“social organizations” in the East) aimed to promote
c o n t a c t , concrete cooperation and mutual understanding
between youth from both sides, with Third World vol-
unteers often present as neutral leavening. Even though
small in scale, these initial efforts to rust the Iron Curtain
did not,to put it mildly, please all authorities of the con-
flicting superpowers and their allies, hence their lasting
symbolic importance.
Help online
With the advance of globalization, volunteering is
entering another age.While work camps set up for spe-
c i fic conservation or physical infrastructure projects still
mobilize people, social volunteering (e.g. philanthropic
assistance to the homeless) and its cousins, h u m a n i-
tarian volunteering (for example to assist refugees) and
a d v o c a cy volunteering (for such causes as human rights
and fair trade) have come into the spotlight.
A growing trend is that, within and between soci-
e t i e s, volunteering is empowering the excluded: d i s a b l e d
p e o p l e, i m m i g r a n t s, and more generally, those on the
margins of society are helping their
own.In some instances, it is paving
the path to recreating a sense of cit-
i z e n s h i p : in the U. S.state of Georgia,
for example, some 2,000 prison
inmates willingly served as volun-
teer firemen during the year 2000,
following training. Online volun-
t e e r i n g, sometimes criticized as
dehumanizing, offers the potential
to involve people who might other-
wise be considered unfit to help others.And many recent
initiatives show that there is almost no age limit to
becoming a volunteer: in Israel, 10 to 13 y e a r-old students
are training retired people in computer literacy, while
retiree volunteering is also an encouraging trend. The
Association of Senior European Counsellors reports,
for instance, a network of 15 member bodies in 11 Euro-
pean Union countries, totalling over 9,000 volunteer
consultants.
Such retiree volunteering is a personal concern. I
ended my UN E S C O career in April 1998.S i n c e, I ’ve under-
taken a number of volunteer assignments for the UNV
and various NGOs, notably in A z e r b a i j a n , H u n g a r y,
Palestine and Romania. With due modesty, I hope I
have contributed to a variety of projects there, f r o m
r e cycling of household trash in Greater Budapest to
job creation for the young unemployed in Brasov. All
have brought me invigorating experiences, unexpected
l e a r n i n g, even delight.Although unpaid, volunteering can
offer unique non-material remuneration. That is one
reason why I expect that, when he retires in about
another quarter century, Sorin Hurdubae will continue
to “lend a helping hand.” ■
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
What
volunteers
bring is the
human touch,
the
individual,
caring
approach that
no
government
programme,
however
well-meaning
and well-
executed, can
deliver.
Edward James Olmos,
American actor (1947-)
The emancipation
from colonial rule
of many countries
led to the birth
of a myriad of local
voluntary organizations.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The online wa y
Surfing the United Nations web site one
n i g h t , Nigeria Adedoyin Onasanya ’s
attention was drawn to the slogan of
N e t a i d . o r g : online action against
absolute poverty. “There was a list of projects in
which interested people could work, and with-
out ever having to leave home!,” he recalls.
After enrolling and answering some basic ques-
tions about his skills, experience and areas of
interest, Onasanya became an online volunteer.
Among his most noteworthy achievements has
been the creation of an e-discussion group for
Nigerian development practitioners. He has also
worked for the Horizon Communication project,
which investigates, documents and catalogues
succesful initiatives aimed at combating poverty
and under-development.
Netaid.org was born two years ago through
the joint effort of the United Nations Develop-
ment Programme (UNDP) and Cisco Systems, a
world leader in Internet technology. Its novelty
rests in the way it has exploited information
technology by tailoring it to the limitations as
much as to the wishes of all those people who
want to join in “voluntary work that is not phys-
ical, but online,” as the Filipino Chere Castane-
da puts it. Though financial donations are will-
ingly accepted in a click of the mouse, the most
novel feature of the organization is the way it
joins together people willing to offer their time
and talents with those who need specific help in
developing a project. And it doesn’t matter
where in the world the sides are living.
To take one example, Joanne K. Morse—a
professor at the University of Hampton, Virginia,
and author of science fiction novels—wrote a
bilingual dictionary for children in rural areas of
Ghana. Designing web pages is another activity:
Jade O’Hanlon, from Britain, created a pro-
gramme to assist children in Sri Lanka called
Help for the Children, while Ana Carvalho from
Portugal did the same for an urban project in the
Philippines, the Rejoice Urban Development Pro-
ject. Peter van der Zee from Holland, meanwhile,
helped translate documents from English into
German.
Most volunteers will never meet face-to-face
the people with whom they exchange e-mails,
but some enthusiasts have planned trips to do
just that. Working from Arizona,Terry Rosenlund
has collaborated with an AIDS prevention pro-
ject in Kenya, the Kenyan AIDS Intervention Pre-
vention Project Group (KAIPPG). His work
involves securing resources in the United States
for the treatment of AIDS victims and orphaned
children. This year he’s planning to travel to
Africa to “get to know the KAIPGG family.” Lau-
rie Moy, another online volunteer from the
States, will soon visit the Ugandan handicapped
people’s project with which she has worked
from Dallas. Judyth Sassoon,a British scientist at
the University of Bern, also plans to visit that
country to get a better idea of what help is
required in the field of child health. She is
already working with the Uganda Children’s
Fund in an effort to create a mobile health unit
for children in remote rural areas.
Netaid.org is based on the principle that
there are many initiatives, small or large, which
can bring about major changes in the fight
against poverty. All that is needed are a screen,
a keyboard, and the will to help. ■
A.L.
+ …
More information:
www.netaid.org
ROLL UP YOU
24 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Would you like to be an international volun-
teer?
The Co-ordinating Committee for International
Voluntary Service (CCIVS), created in 1948 and
o p e rating under the auspices of UNESCO, c u r-
rently works with 140 NGOs in 100 countries,
which take on unspecialized volunteers to work in
development projects alongside the local popu-
l a t i o n . Its role is to put potential volunteers in
contact with organizations that can decide what
they should do.
The service encourages volunteering as a means
to work for peace, international understanding,
s o l i d a r i t y, c o o p e ration and reconciliation between
the different peoples of the world. CCIVS’ main
fields of action are informal education,preserva-
tion of cultural heritage and the environment,
and emergency aid and reconstruction.
Are you involved in volunteering research?
CCIVS is currently co-ordinating a joint campaign
for the International Year of Volunteers that will
end in 2002 with a four-day conference whose
main areas of debate are:access to volunteering
for under-privileged people, volunteering and
peace work, i n t e r-regional exchange, and the
legal rights and mobility of volunteers.
To find out more, contact:
The Co-ordinating Committee for International
Voluntary Service
UNESCO
1 rue Miollis
75732 Paris Cedex 15
France
Tel:(00 33) 1 45 68 49 36
e-mail:ccivs@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/cciv
What are the aims of the International Year of
Volunteers 2001?
The aims are increasing volunteering’s profil e,
promoting it as activity, making it easier to
become a volunteer and improving the exchange
of knowledge and experience between volunteers
from around the world. The year also offers a
unique opportunity to pay homage to the millions
of volunteers who each day provide essential help
to those who most need it.
For more information,see www.iyv.org
A few tips
U N I T E D  N A T I O N S  V O L U N T E E R S
The United Nations Volunteers Programme (UNV) was cre-
ated by the General Assembly of the United Nations in
1970 to serve as a partner in development cooperation.
Every year, close to 5,000 professions from over 150
nations work in a range of technical,economic and social
fie l d s, from community-based initiatives to peace-build-
ing processes. They listen and discuss; teach and tra i n ;
e n c o u rage and facilitate. Seven out of ten UNV volunteers
come from developing countries.
More information:http://www.unv.org
On the rise:
total number ofUNV volunteers worldwide
Year Number
1971 35
1975 376
1980 1,052
1985 1,493
1990 2,637
1995 3,263
2000 4,780
Source:www.unv.org
OUR SLEEVES
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 25
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Self-interest or goodwill?
From improving a CV to meeting kindred spirits, volunteers are driven by a
myriad of motives. For many, giving a hand is simply a moral obligation, says
Spanish social psychologist Fernando Chacón Fuentes*
INTERVIEW BY
LUCÍA IGLESIAS KUNTZ
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Why do people feel the need to volunteer?
It isn’t easy to figure out because the desire to
volunteer stems from many inner motives that are
very hard to discern.The only source of information
we have is the actual volunteer. But all the studies
that have been done—especially those by two
American professors,Allen M.Omoto (University
of Kansas) and Mark Snyder (University of Min-
nesota)—come up with two broad reasons. Th e
main one is a feeling of moral or religious obligation
to help solve a problem. These are the altruists. I
prefer to call them “ h e t e r o - c e n t r e d ,” or focused on
o t h e r s.The second group of volunteers are the ego-
tists or “ s e l f - c e n t r e d .”Th e y ’re out to get some ben-
efit for themselves.
But these motives aren’t exclusive of each other, are they?
N o. There aren’t any “ p u r e ”v o l u n t e e r s. N e a r l y
all of them are driven by a combination of motives,
though one will dominate the others.
Volunteers who hold out the longest in organi-
zations are those who are altruistic, but at the same
time recognize that they are benefiting from their
work.
What are these motives?
Omoto and Snyder have identified fiv e.The fir s t
is belief in a set of values. By volunteering, people
express their own personal principles.So if someone
thinks of him or herself as a humanitarian kind of
person and acts accordingly, they’ll feel at ease.
The second, quite broad motive is a quest for
k n o w l e d g e.Some people go to developing countries
to gain a different perspective on life, while others
merely do so to add to their CV.
The third reason is more utilitarian: v o l u n t e e r i n g
is a means to an end, often driven by the wish to
meet others, especially kindred spirits.
The fourth group of motives is what we call
i d e n t i fication with the community. This is when
someone identifies with a specific group or problem
and makes a commitment to it by becoming actively
i n v o l v e d . These are the volunteers you’ll find in
causes such as the mentally ill, cancer or A I D S.
Some people clearly join the fight against AIDS as
a way of acknowledging rights and above all iden-
tifying with those groups which are hardest hit by the
epidemic.
The last group of motives,much rarer and harder
to explain,is what psychologists call self-defence.
When someone is very afraid or anxious, they some-
times become a volunteer as a way of confronting
their fear. An example is the homosexual who gets
involved in the battle against AIDS. It can also be
a way to cope with more general fears and anxieties,
and some of my colleagues encourage their patients
to get involved in voluntary activity to take their
mind off their own problems. But I don’t really
approve of that.
Why not?
Because I think voluntary projects should help
the people targeted by such programmes. Th e y
aren’t there to help the volunteers themselves.
Who volunteers most,women or men?
Neither differ much in their reasons for volun-
teering, though more women volunteer than men,
especially in social work and health.Yo u ’ll also fin d
more men in civil protection organizations.Wh e t h e r
we like it or not, this has a lot to do with traditional
roles—women tend to be the carers while men put
out fires and deal with disasters.
Are volunteers different from place to place?
I don’t know of any transcultural study about
t h a t , but national surveys suggest a few differences.
In Eastern societies, such as Ja p a n , people work
more for groups and for the community. They talk
more about the interests of a group and having a
sense of duty. In Western societies,especially A n g l o -
Saxon ones, people act in more individualistic ways.
Societies have always had their own mecha-
nisms for dealing with social needs unmet by the
s t a t e. B e f o r e, families took care of their elders.
These natural networks are breaking down and
creating exclusion.In this sense, volunteering will
always have an important role to play.
* Professor of Social Psychology at Madrid’s A l c a l á
de Henares University and president of the Official
College of Psychologists in Madrid.
International Year
of Volunteers
2 . NEW BONDS
26 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Te e n s
talking to t e e n s
By starting a hotline, some 50 Slovenian teenagers have become pros at
listening, conversing and gently settling everyday hassles
T
he phone rings, startling two high school
s t u d e n t s, Tina and Ja n a .“ I ’ll get it!” s a y s
Ja n a .“ This is ’Teens Talking to Te e n s ’ . . .”
We ’re in Ljubljana,the capital of Slovenia,
at the Youth Counselling Centre, w h i c h
began a hotline for troubled teens in 1993.Wh a t ’s so
original about this self-financing project? The people
answering the phones aren’t experts but 14 to 18
y e a r- o l d s.Pairs of them are on duty every day from
three to five in the afternoon, except weekends and
v a c a t i o n s. At fir s t , they were teenagers from the
n e i g h b o u r h o o d .Then their schoolmates and friends
of friends started pitching in.
To d a y, they number about 50.
“Everybody knows our
phone number,” says Nina.
“ I t ’s posted in the schools.
Most callers are high school
students. Some of them think
w e ’ll do their math home-
w o r k .”But that’s not what the
hotline is there for. “Mothers
call us too,” says Daniel,“ w h e n
they have reasons to think
their children are taking drugs.We ’ve got a good fil e
of special institutions we can refer them to. And
when the situation looks serious, we transfer the
call to the professional staff.”The volunteers have
been duly advised that drugs are a matter for
experts.
Ales says the best thing about the hotline is that
it gives teenagers a chance to speak freely about
school,parents and sex.“It’s different from going
to shrinks,which can be awkward and boring some-
times.”
A d u l t s, including centre director Ljubo
R a i c e v i c, psychologist Natasa Fabjan and edu-
cator Lili Raicevic,keep a low profil e.Their role is
limited to training and supervising the volunteers.
Answering the questions is not always easy.“ S o m e-
times you feel powerless,” says A n d r e j a . “If some-
body calls several times, you eventually figure out
w h a t ’s really bothering them. But most people
call just once,and you wonder whether you said the
right thing.” Nejc adds, “ The best ideas always
occur to you after hanging up! So, we tell our-
selves that the main thing is to talk,if only to take
the caller’s mind off his or her dark thoughts.”
Why do these young people spend hours on the
phone with strangers? Maja, who is still a minor,
has already been listening and counselling for
three years. “The high school sent me here,” she
s a y s.“ They told me I was too talkative,and thought
that talking on the phone would do me good.I’ve
met lots of nice people here. We train together
and go out together.We’ve all become friends.”
The young volunteers are devoted to helping
o t h e r s, but they also get something out of the expe-
rience. For some, the hotline is a means to keep
loneliness at bay. Others satisfy their need for
freedom and self-assertion. “ Th e y ’re emerging
from childhood and want to take on responsibili-
ties, but people often tell them they’re too young.
Here, they’re taken seriously.
Volunteering gives them a
chance to make the transition
between playing and work-
i n g,” says the centre’s director,
an educator and psycho-
therapist by training .
The volunteers say that
since they’ve started “talking
to teens,” they have become
aware of other people’s woes
and can settle their own more
easily. For example, Stela, who joined the group
when she was 13,eventually shared her problems
—a serious conflict with her parents—with her
new friends.
The professional staff members have also had
to work on themselves and mature at the same
time as the teens. “ The idea came from them,”
says  Raicevic.“At fir s t , we were reluctant because
they were stepping into an area traditionally
reserved for professionals and adults. But we told
ourselves that without young people, their influ e n c e
and ideas, we could never succeed. Why not let
them take part in making decisions and get
involved?” The 8,000 or so phone calls received
since the hotline opened in 1993 proves they can.
■
INGRIG MAGER
JOURNALIST AT THE SLOVENIAN DAILY DNEVNIK
+ …
Slovenian Youth Counselling Centre: w w w. z - m i s s s. s i
“They’re emerging
from  childhood
and want to take
on responsibilities,
but people often tell them
they’re too young.”
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 27
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
B ra z i l : taking up the social slack
The crisis of the state and the limits of the free market have fuelled a boom in
voluntary work, in which business is taking a lead
JAYME BRENER
BRAZILIAN JOURNALIST
Reaching out to street children in Brazil.
2 . NEW BONDS
International Year
of Volunteers
28 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
because our institutions are going through a serious
c r i s i s,” says the president of the São Paulo city council,
José Eduardo Cardozo, who was elected last year
with strong support from civic awareness groups.
Leilah Landim,a researcher from ISER, a r g u e s
that the growing number of volunteers in Brazil is
changing the nature of social work, which for the
first three centuries of European colonization was
the almost exclusive domain of the Catholic Church.
Social networks
instead of crime
But the triumph of free-market economics, the
decline of trade unions, the state’s faltering ability
to invest and the dizzying growth of problems such
as urban violence, drug trafficking, AIDS and
teenage pregnancies, have paved the way for the
construction of new social networks based on vol-
untary work and goodwill initiatives by business.
“Millions of people,many of them wealthy, h a v e
realized that poverty can lead to drug dealing that
could threaten their own children,” says Gilson
S c h w a r t z , of the University of São Paulo’s Insti-
tute of Advanced Studies. “Many business people
“D
o your bit” is the slogan of a major
radio campaign by the Brazilian
Organizing Committee for the
International Year of Vo l u n t e e r s
2 0 0 1 .The simple and blunt slogan
is emblematic of a trend that has been changing
Brazilian society in recent years—the boom in vol-
untary work.
A nationwide survey in 1998 by the Institute for
Studies in Religion (ISER) in Rio de Ja n e i r o
showed that 22.6 percent of Brazil’s adult popula-
tion—or 13.9 million people—did some kind of
unpaid social work,and that 13.9 percent of them
belonged to a community association. These fig-
ures are far behind the 49 percent of U.S. citizens
who do voluntary work,but they reflect a remark-
able development in Brazilian society, which has tra-
ditionally been polarized between the state and
the private sector, with little room in between for
community involvement.
“ The growth of voluntary activity is largely
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
When a man
is willing and
passionate,
the gods are
with him.
Aeschylus, 
Greek dramatist
(525-426 B.C.)
now understand that supporting professional
training programmes is the way to get children off
the street,where they might otherwise fall into a life
of crime that could threaten their businesses.”
One of the features of this boom in voluntary
work in Brazil is the attempt to go beyond simple
h a n d o u t s.Ruth Cardoso, the anthropologist wife of
President Fernando Henrique Cardoso, is the dri-
ving force behind the Community Solidarity Pro-
g r a m m e.She launched the Volunteers’ Project at the
end of 1997 with the stated aim of improving on tra-
ditional populist schemes. The project’s charter
declares that it is urgent to “establish a modern
culture of voluntary work based on trained volun-
teers and making services work.”
Bankers on
the literacy trail
The charter also says,with a touch of irony, t h a t
“the new vision of voluntary work has nothing to do
with charity or providing bored people with things
to do.”
In the last five years, voluntary work has enabled
Community Solidarity to give vocational training to
87,000 young people between 16 and 21 reckoned
to be “at risk of social exclusion.”
But perhaps the most original feature of this
growth in voluntary work is occurring inside com-
p a n i e s.A recent survey among 100 of the 380 fir m s
a f filiated to the Ethos Institute, which promotes
business ethics, showed that 94 percent of them
had their own voluntary projects.
The state-owned Bank of Brazil’s “ R e a d ,W r i t e
and Liberate” p r o g r a m m e, for example, i n v o l v e s
more than 2,100 of its employees in voluntary efforts
to promote literacy and encourage people all over
the country to read. The programme has already
taught more than 31,000 people to read and write,
and one of its most recent successes was to teach
these skills to 220 inhabitants of a small A m a z o n i a n
village, Belém do Alto Solimões.
M e a n w h i l e, the Dutch multinational clothing
firm C & A says 20 percent of its Brazilian
employees—equivalent to 1,400 people—are doing
voluntary work. The cosmetics group Natura has
assembled a group of storytellers who go around the
country entertaining thousands of people in schools,
hospitals and other social institutions.Through the
“Children Are Life” p r o g r a m m e, 84 volunteers
from the Schering-Plough laboratory have taught
basic principles of health and hygiene to more than
25,000 children since 1998.
Non-toxic glue
At the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing
plant at Sumaré, about 120 kilometres from São
P a u l o, 80 percent of the 2,600 employees take part in
voluntary work.Staff from the Brazilian subsidiary
of the U.S. security firm Chubb set aside one day a
year to teach children from poor areas about what
they do.The 95 branches of the local subsidiary of the
U. S. shoe firm Heel Sew Quick (HSQ) are helping to
fund a school for young shoemakers in São Paulo,a n d
have also developed a non-toxic glue that will be
used by HSQ in all its overseas factories. S h o e-
makers’ glue is widely used as a drug by street chil-
dren in Brazil’s major cities.
“The social awareness of Brazilians has clearly
grown,” says Dr Walmir Frare, who runs Bit Com-
p a n y, one of the country’s biggest networks of com-
puter training schools.“The idea that private firms
should help to reduce social inequalities has really
caught on,and a big part of that is supporting vol-
untary work by their employees.” Bit Company is
involved in training teachers and students,and has
an experimental project to teach elderly people
how to use computers.
Many voluntary programmes start out as fairly
personal or informal schemes. Human resources
expert Gilmar Bernardi, who works for the Fr e n c h
telecommunications giant Alcatel in São Paulo,
decided 10 years ago to fund the creation of a
nursery for working mothers in a church on the
edge of the city.Today there are three, one of them
in a favela, or slum area.
Powerful alliances
While social work spreads throughout Brazilian
civil society, it must still be stressed that religious
organizations continue to play a major part in vol-
untary action,particularly among the very poor.
Lastly, the rapid expansion of the Internet in
Brazil is giving a powerful boost to voluntary
a c t i v i t y. At fir s t , charities found it an excellent way
to raise money and disseminate their ideas. Nowa-
d a y s, its main contribution to voluntary social work
is perhaps through education. Many projects use it
to enable students and teachers to help deprived stu-
dents throughout the country.
Perhaps the most ambitious programme is the
City of Knowledge, run by São Paulo University’s
Institute for Advanced Studies and the Education
Faculty Fo u n d a t i o n , backed by the media (the news-
papers Gazeta Mercantil, Folha de São Paulo and
O Estado de São Pa u l o) , big companies such as
IBM,Banco Santander and Boston Bank,and the
publishing houses Moderna and Pangea.The project
involves permanent voluntary in-firm training of
instructors, teachers and students. ■
+ …
Volunteers Portal (www.portaldovoluntario.org.br) describes
examples of social work and suggests ways businesses can
get involved. The site has had more than a million and a
half visitors in its first four months online.
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 29
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
International Year
of Volunteers
30 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
A t o r n a d o on wheels
Neither poverty nor polio can slow down Carmen Reyes Zubiaga, who has
thrown herself into the cause of the disabled from the Philippines to Cambodia
CARLO M. TADIAR
MANILA-BASED JOURNALIST
2 . NEW BONDS
P
aralyzed by polio at the age of a year- a n d - a -
half in exceedingly poor circumstances,
Carmen Reyes Zubiaga has spent a lifetime
battling the odds.To d a y, she is the chief of sev-
eral organizations and the leading light in her
country for the movement seeking to uplift the plight
of those who, like her, have been shorn of a normal
physical life.
Born the sixth of nine children of a carpenter and
laundry woman,Carmen has lived most of her life in
Ta y t a y, R i z a l , a municipality at the edge of the
sprawling national capital of the Philippines, Metro
M a n i l a . Navigating the winding, narrow streets of
Taytay requires great dexterity while dodging a torrent
of traffic and people. But Carmen is a
master of this labyrinth.On the day of
our meeting, she beat me to the place
of assignation by an embarrassing 20
minutes, despite my two fully opera-
tional legs and four automobile
wheels. Carmen arrived via tricycle,
the motorized pedicab that is a pop-
ular mode of public transport.
Campus activist
I miss her the first time I survey
the restaurant, because I fail to see
the wheelchair and the woman who
turns out to be Carmen Reyes
Zubiaga seems far too young for
someone so accomplished. She has
set up three organizations and a foun-
dation—all dedicated to supporting
the disabled through micro-credit pro-
g r a m m e s, s c h o l a r s h i p s, and other forms of assistance.
Not only did she create these groups, but she also
devotes virtually all of her time to them without fin a n-
cial compensation.
This remarkably pretty and gentle person con-
trasts with the steely and authoritarian persona she
exudes by voice over the telephone. A strong vocal
command is clearly essential to impose her will in a
society that customarily downplays individual volition.
“My mother said I was very hard-headed as a child,”
she laughs. “I didn’t even know what a wheelchair
looked like,” she says, recalling her childhood and
early adolescence spent crawling on the floor because
her family couldn’t afford a wheelchair.At the age of
14, she took the initiative to write to a ladies’ club
asking for support,which they readily supplied.Wh i l e
her parents were unable to offer much materially,
they were generous in their support. “ They never
treated me as a special person,” she says, which meant,
“in my family, I never experienced any discrimination.”
Poverty also forced her to stop temporarily her
education after elementary school. But ten years later,
Carmen resumed her studies through the assistance of
a Belgian missionary, Sister Valeriana Baerts, and the
institute she founded, Tahanang Walang Hagdanan
(House Without Stairs), which is now the country’s
foremost agency advancing the plight of the disabled.
Though many scoffed at her for daring to enter col-
lege, Carmen rose to the top of her class while con-
tributing to comic books to help pay for her studies.
Struck by the number of wheelchair-bound students
(around 10),she launched her first volunteer project
to raise funds to construct ramps for wheelchair access
around campus.
Tahanang proved to be Carmen’s well-spring—not
only did she work as a volunteer throughout her stu-
dent days, but after graduating, she took up the roles
of public relations executive and project developer for
nine years. This experience enabled her to hone her
skills in organizing, marketing, fund-raising and net-
w o r k i n g. It was also at Tahanang that she met her
husband,who is not disabled.
After Tahanang, she offered her services to the
United Nations Development Program,which sent her
to Cambodia to launch the first government
Carmen Reyes Zubiaga: promoting economic independence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
I
t all began with one woman’s dream to help those
in the same situation as herself:p o o r, u n e d u c a t e d
and in urgent need of a safe haven.
In 1975,Susheelamma found herself with two
children to support and a broken marriage. The
daughter of a weaver, her education was cut short
because her family couldn’t afford secondary school
fees. Today, she is at the head of the Sumangali Seva
Ashram in Bangalore, staffed by a dedicated team of
450 full-time volunteers. Day after day, the ashram
offers destitute women who come knocking at its
door a roof over their heads and a chance to get a new
start in life by learning a skill. Once they can stand on
their own feet, the women are free to look for jobs out-
side the ashram,or to work with its myriad projects for
a small stipend and two square meals a day. Many of
them have never forgotten the hope it provided,and
continue to contribute to the ashram’s smooth running
in some form or other.
It is a gaping vacuum in social services that
prompted Susheelamma and a group of friends to
found the ashram in 1975.At the time, they managed
to convince the state government to allot them a plot
of land to build a small shelter and a school to educate
destitute women. But the land had a deep open pit on
i t ,and filling it was beyond their financial reach. S l o w l y
but surely, Susheelamma and her friends convinced
people to donate to their cause, and eventually a
school shed was built.
“ We did not have the money to buy books for
children or to feed the women who had arrived at the
ashram to stay,” says Susheelamma,a petite and frail
65 year-old who continues to preside tirelessly over the
a s h r a m ’s activities.She and the other volunteers would
work all night to make little trinkets, which they sold
to raise meagre sums of money.When she started the
ashram,she was earning a mere 170 rupees a month
(around $4) from her work as a warden and a nursery
SUDHA RAMACHANDRAN
ASSISTANT EDITOR, DECCAN HERALD, BANGALORE
Starting over at the ashra m
In southern India, women who once fled their homes with nothing in hand are
now helping others to earn a living and playing a role in health and education
programmes
2 . NEW BONDS
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 31
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
endeavour—a semi-autonomous agency—to deal
with its teeming numbers of disabled,a legacy of the
bitter civil war.
Even though conditions are worse there than they
are in the Philippines, she says, the centre managed to
set up employment opportunities for the disabled.
But her greatest fulfilment lay in setting an example
for Cambodians with disability, w h o, she says, f o r-
merly had a single destiny—begging.
Business from home
“When I would go to the market in Cambodia,
I’d be regarded differently,” she says,“because I was
b u y i n g, not begging. So for Cambodian people, I
painted a different picture of the disabled.”
The disabled in Cambodia had previously been
reduced to the most abject status, robbed of any hope
of happiness, l o v e, m a r r i a g e, and children. S h e, on the
other hand,had crossed an ocean to go to Cambodia
and  had brought along her husband and two children.
When she returned to the Philippines after three
y e a r s, a third child was added to her brood, a girl
entrusted to her parentage by a very poor Cambodian
couple.
Back home in the Philippines, she set up three
organizations and a foundation to help people with
handicaps pursue an education,learn new skills and
start their own businesses. The organizations clearly
reject the charity of the missionaries. I n s t e a d , t h e y
promote self-assurance and economic independence.
“You have to create wealth before it can be distrib-
uted,” says Carmen.So for example, to fund educa-
tional scholarships, her foundation is running a coop-
erative grocery aimed at becoming a chain.
Employment is very difficult to come by for the
disabled.Not only are they the last to be considered
for any position,but commuting between work and
home is also extremely arduous. “That’s why we’re
promoting micro-entrepreneurship and giving out
l o a n s, so the disabled can set up their own businesses
in their own homes,” she says.
The organizations also stress a principle close to
C a r m e n ’s heart: the virtue of volunteer work.“I am the
beneficiary of other people’s goodwill,” she under -
scores.“If not for a volunteer who brought me to the
National Orthopaedic Hospital, I would not have met
Sister Valeriana Baerts….No matter who you are, if
you don’t know how to share, you’ll get nowhere.” ■
Susheelamma,
the founder.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
school teacher. Of this, she used Rs100 to maintain her
f a m i l y, and the rest to launch the ashram’s pro-
g r a m m e s.“Some volunteers, like Parvatamma [who is
a member of the ashram’s core committee, and more
f o r t u n a t e ] , would hand over their entire monthly
salary cheques to us,” recalls Susheelamma.
The ashram’s first income-generation scheme
involved cutting and twisting wires into a U-shape to be
sold as metal poultry feeders. One kilogram of these
would fetch 40 paise (less than a cent),but drop by drop,
they had enough to make ends meet. Then they made
garlands of silk cocoons.Volunteers would carry sacks
of them on their backs in the overcrowded state trans-
port buses to deliver them to stores across the city.
Lifelong loyalty
Today, the ashram receives grants from the gov-
ernment as well as financial and material assistance
from international aid agencies,along with individual
d o n a t i o n s. Its real asset, h o w e v e r, are the volunteers:
from the outset, the ashram was based on the principle
of recruiting those who once benefited from its ser-
vices. Committed to improving the lives of their less
fortunate sisters, the volunteers run education and
training programmes, provide counselling to women
in distress (who may not need shelter) and conduct
regular adult literacy programmes, health check-ups
and immunization campaigns. The ashram also runs
two primary schools, 130 a n g a n w a d i (or childcare)
c e n t r e s, which provide supplementary nutrition to
c h i l d r e n , pregnant women and breastfeeding mothers
in slums,2 5c r è c h e s, and 19 non-formal schools, also in
slums.
People like Shantamma make this whole
endeavour possible. One of the pillars of the ashram,
she trains volunteers and is a source of strength and
guidance to all those around her. The unassuming
lady vividly recalls the day, 25 years ago, when she and
her two infant children came here,seeking shelter. H e r
eyes still moisten as she recounts how uncertain the
future seemed after walking away from an alcoholic
husband who beat her in front of the children and
brought another woman to live with them. Unedu-
cated and unemployed, she had no idea how she
would fend for herself and the children.Then someone
told her about the ashram,which willingly accepted
h e r. I n i t i a l l y, Shantamma worked only in the kitchen;
then she took care of the children in the ashram’s
c r è c h e. M e a n w h i l e, she followed a literacy course
offered by the ashram.Then she was trained by other
volunteers to become a health worker, a d v i s i n g
women in villages on nutrition and immunisation.
Adopting a shanty town
To d a y, Shantamma lives in her own house but
comes to the ashram every day to help in the kitchen
and train other women to participate in income-
generation projects.“I lived in the ashram for seven
y e a r s,” Shantamma says.“It gave me a s h r e y a ( s h e l t e r )
when nobody else wanted me. I can never forget
that.… I will help others who come here as long as
I can.”
The atmosphere at the ashram is tranquil, if busi-
ness-like. Residents rise before dawn and after med-
itation and a spartan breakfast,they set out to work.
Although they are not obliged to, just about all of
them, including those with mental and physical dis-
abilities, volunteer to help. This willingness has been
the mainstay of the ashram from the outset.
In addition to full-time volunteers, many others
from the community at large give some of their time.
S h a k u n t a l a , an engineer in a government department,
spends a few hours each weekend helping with odd
j o b s, a f firming that it makes her feel more worthwhile.
Some contribute through active service, others through
financial donations.Philanthropy is well-entrenched in
Indian philosophy; volunteers are convinced that they
must help others in order to enjoy prosperity and
peace of mind.
Many of the ashram’s women now volunteer in the
nearby Kuprajbande slum, which was so run-down
that the ashram decided to “ a d o p t ” it and improve the
lives of its inhabitants. Fifty-six shanty dwellings were
rebuilt by volunteers, and awareness campaigns
launched on health sanitation and against alcoholism.
To d a y, the slum has been renamed Shaktinagar—the
City of Strength.Volunteers claim their drive against
alcoholism has been so effective that almost 80 percent
of the men (the women rarely drink) have become tee-
totallers.
Susheelamma’s story is proof of how individuals
with no means, but plenty of courage and determina-
t i o n , can bring about lasting change.“ Th e r e ’s still a lot
to be achieved,”she muses.“ What we have done is but
a drop in a vast ocean of need.” ■
An ashram volunteer advising a woman about health issues in Shaktinagar.
International Year
of Volunteers
32 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 33
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
I
t may not be everyone’s idea of a perfect holiday,
but France Montwedi had the adventure of his
l i f e.From South A f r i c a , the student of natural sci-
ences took a bus to Maputo, capital of Mozam-
b i q u e.With 11 other volunteers,he was then led
to a nearby village, deserted since last year’s flo o d s,
and given his tasks: mixing mortar, l e a r n i n g
Po r t u g u e s e, swatting mosquitoes and reconstructing
the community’s school building.
Set up in 1993 under the auspices of the Centre
for Human Rights at the University of Pretoria, t h e
Southern African Student Volunteers Organization
( SA S VO) has become a pioneering body for com-
munity action across the region.Working in poverty-
stricken areas, the organization has sent out groups
of students to spend part of their vacations on pro-
jects and fill some of the gaps left by under- r e s o u r c e d
governments.
But the organization is not just about good
w o r k s, as Montwedi’s experience goes to prove.“ We
get a lot of students participating—mainly black
students who’d otherwise have to stay at home over
the summer because they are not so wealthy. For
them it’s an enormously beneficial experience to
go and work in rural areas of southern A f r i c a ,”
explains Jan Bezuidenhout,SA S VO’s deputy co-ordi-
nator.
For Christoff Heyns, a founding member and
director of the Centre for Human Rights, the ini-
tiative is a crucial step towards reaffirming young
p e o p l e ’s African identity and sense of belonging.“ I
believe that if you mix sweat with earth, you get
ownership of that land.And if you mix sweat with the
sweat of others, you get joint ownership.”
His hope is that SA S VO may one day lay the
groundwork for a pan-continental volunteering
body. “If there is a problem in Rwanda or Mozam-
bique, the first people to arrive to offer assistance
should be Africans,” he says.
From building
to counselling
So far, however, SASVO is the only indigenous
South African organization promoting voluntary
action among university students and young
p e o p l e in rural and disadvantaged communities.
To date, more than 6,000 student volunteers from
4 0 academic institutions in 10 African countries
have undertaken participatory community
development projects in South Africa, Swaziland,
M o z a m b i q u e, B o t s w a n a , Ta n z a n i a , Uganda and
Namibia.
Although South African youth have a proud his-
tory of activism—
they were at the fore-
front of the struggle
against apartheid—
Heyns says voluntary
action is a different
c h a l l e n g e. “A c t i v i s m
is primarily focused
on political issues.
While voluntarism
d o e s n ’t exclude this, i t
includes non-political
activities like working
in a hospice or e d u-
cating people about
issues like AIDS.”
Since 1996, t h e
o r g a n i z a t i o n ’s pri-
mary focus has been
on  schools: t h e y
have renovated over
4 0 , built some
214 classrooms, and
painted more than
800 others as well as
four children’s hos-
pital wards. But stu-
dent volunteers have
also built houses,
community centres
and sports fie l d s, a n d
planted vegetable
gardens and trees.
They have done dis-
aster relief work, r u n
human rights educa-
tion workshops,
assisted with the
general elections in
South Africa and taken statements for the Tr u t h
and Reconciliation Commission. Future projects
are expected to focus more on HIV/AIDS aware-
ness, counselling and agricultural projects
In the opinion of its organizers,SA S VO’s greatest
accomplishment has been to instil in volunteers and
REHANA ROSSOUW
JOURNALIST AT THE MAIL AND GUARDIAN, JOHANNESBURG
Mixing s w e a t with e a r t h
South African university students are flocking to the country’s main volunteering
organization with the promise of fun, manual labour
and a radical change in African politics
2 . NEW BONDS
SASVO volunteers repair a school in Mozambique damaged by floods.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
International Year
of Volunteers
34 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
about human rights issues or about gender issues. I t
creates links between illiterate and semi-literate
p e o p l e, and university students who might them-
selves have grown up in such villages.”
In 1997, SASVO made its first move towards col-
laborative ventures and piloted its Operation Zenzele
(“Do it yourself”) Project.This focused more specif-
ically on upgrading, renovation and repair of the
socio-economic infrastructure (particularly of schools)
in disadvantaged communities in conjunction with
township youth and secondary school learners.A d v i c e
on which communities to target within South Africa
often comes from the government,whose ministries
work closely with the organization.
In addition, SASVO offers longer-term opportu-
nities for graduates to work in development projects
where they can gain experience and practical skills
in their field of study or interest. Volunteers also
have the option of working for NGOs and interna-
tional agencies.More than 19 long-term placements
have been made.
With branches at seven universities in southern
Africa, there is no shortage of students waiting to
enrol.“We have so many people applying for our
projects that we do not see the necessity of building
a large infrastructure,” says SASVO project coordi-
nator Belinda Mogashwa.“We would prefer not to
spend money on management and offic e s ; instead we
want to plough in money and resources where they
are needed most:in destitute communities.” ■
community members alike ideals of self-reliance,
s e l f - h e l p, voluntarism and love of Africa through
projects that help to secure access to education and
services for all—access that would otherwise be
impossible to guarantee.As Bezuidenhout sees it, t h e
volunteers’ experiences may as a result prove critical
in beginning to bridge the divide that has tradition-
ally separated A f r i c a ’s political elite from those who
are ruled.
“The problem in Africa had always been that
once people get to power, they loose contact with
those they were meant to serve.But volunteers will
always remember their time working in a rural com-
munity,” he explains.
Bridging the
class divide
Projects have indeed been marked by stronger
links between the organizers and the communities
they are seeking to serve. “At fir s t , our volunteers
would arrive in communities and commence with
the work that needed doing. Nowadays, by the time
our volunteers arrive, the community already has
the materials and the plans.They have ownership of
their projects and we provide the sweat,” Heyns says.
Meanwhile, adds Bezuidenhout,village people
and volunteers—some of whom are likely to become
political and business leaders in the decades to
come—have time and the opportunity during their
work to debate issues of pressing concern.“ They talk
GLYN ROBERTS
FOUNDER OF TOOLS FOR SELF-RELIANCE, HAMPSHIRE, UK (WWW.TFSR.ORG)
The mending hands
of youthful elders
In Great Britain, thousands of retired men gain a new lease on life
by refurbishing rusted tools and dispatching them to craftsmen
in Africa.A personal account of this ongoing adventure
2 . NEW BONDS
W
e started Tools for Self-Reliance in
1979 with a handful of volunteers,
based on the simple idea of collecting
and sending refurbished tools to vil-
lage workshops in A f r i c a .My interest
in tools grew alongside a rising disenchantment with big
technical projects overseas. I ’d seen foreign compa-
nies in West Africa make huge profits in the name of
d e v e l o p m e n t . Expatriate staff who were supposed to
make a difference enjoyed huge salaries, servants and
extravagant perks, all adding to Third World debt.
Much of this assistance seemed to inhibit the ordinary
working people from taking initiatives to better their
l i v e s.
In Ethiopia,I ’d observed costly Caterpillar diggers
brought in by aid agencies rusting away, because it was
impossible to find diesel or spare parts for them.
M e a n w h i l e, thousands of Ethiopians went unem-
ployed and hungry. Surely there was a way to do
things differently.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 35
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
Then,one day, hearing an aid worker in Uganda
complain that young people were stealing the tools
from his visual aid display, it struck me that tools
could empower these poor people and give them a
l i v e l i h o o d . Visits to local craftsmen showed their
equipment was almost worn out, chisels sharpened
t o the last centimetre, hammers mere stumps of iron.
I was sure there was scope for an organization which
could assist them while avoiding traditional
debt traps.
The first steps
Back home, the idea crystallized further. M y
mother pointed out that in our street alone, t h e r e
lived dozens of people with tools from a lifetime
stacked in their sheds.What did this mean, in terms of
the unused hammers, s a w s, and sewing machines that
could be collected all over Britain? 
We got to work with a bunch of dedicated student
volunteers from the Polytechnic in 1979, using an
abandoned church hall in Portsmouth as our first tool
shed. There was no heating, no water, no gas, no fur-
n i t u r e, but we were jubilant. We had found some-
where to clean the first batch of 240 tools collected
from houses in the Kingston prison area.
To d a y, tools worth more than £500,000 ($800,000)
each year are shipped to partner organizations in
Tanzania, Zimbabwe, Uganda, Mozambique, Sierra
Leone and Ghana.Working closely with these groups,
TFSR is able to deliver targeted aid to groups of
craftsmen in poor communities. We also promote
local tool production by supporting blacksmith
training programmes in Ta n z a n i a , Z i m b a b w e, a n d
Sierra Leone. Rural blacksmiths use our heavy-duty
equipment to make and mend tools locally,p r o d u c i n g
far more than we could ever ship out.
Without its large core of dedicated volunteers,
TSFR would not exist. When we started out,we had
never considered what secondary benefits this scheme
might bring,especially for retired men, who are often
reluctant to get out and socialize—often to the despair
of their wives. Thousands of them have got a new
lease on life by volunteering with us—today, o l d e r
men make up about half the membership of our 70
groups. Once a week,up and down the country, they
get together to de-rust, m e n d ,s h a r p e n , oil and fin a l l y
pack the tools, as good as new (and sometimes better
because steel in old tools is often of superb quality) for
dispatch to Africa.
Talking tools
in Tanzania
Some of these volunteers once earned their living
as mechanics, engineers or builders, and they take
great pride in teaching their skills to younger members.
“What they have in common,” says Tony Care, coor-
dinator of T S F R , Wa l e s, “is their high standard of
w o r k m a n s h i p. They are methodical and thorough.
They enjoy taking on a complicated job and refuse to
be beaten by it.They’re a mine of useful information
and a constant source of funny stories from the past.”
It can be a time for
nostalgia too. N o w
and then, a volunteer
will pick up a rusting
instrument and
e x c l a i m , “I haven’t
seen one of these
since World War II!”
H o w e v e r, i t ’s not
just the practical
aspect of the job that
attracts our volun-
t e e r s. Most come
because they appre-
ciate the underlying
spirit of the organi-
z a t i o n , and sharing
experiences with
o t h e r s. “TSFR is
infinitely worth-
w h i l e,”declares Jo h n
Watley, our 84 year-
old sewing-machine
guru who was once
the town clerk in
A n d o v e r, H a m p-
s h i r e. “ I t ’s the most
original and in the
best sense, ’r e v o-
lutionary’ relief
workI’ve ever come
a c r o s s.” In Don-
c a s t e r,Derek Ta y l o r,
72,shares his reason
for volunteering.
“Our son was killed
in a road accident,” he explains.“My wife and I started
to think of our own lives. Before, our family was the
only thing that mattered. N o w, we are outward-
l o o k i n g ;everyone is our family.Some of our v o l u n t e e r s
illustrate how it’s never too late to make a difference.
Kevin Petrie, 8 5 , spent his working life as a book-
keeper and teacher, and only started collecting and
refurbishing tools at 70. Over the last 15 years, he has
refurbished 11,500 beautiful tools, mainly for car-
pentry. A member of the TSFR board of trustees, he
visited Ta n z a n i a , at his own expense, to see the equip-
ment in use.The country’s former president, Julius K.
Nyerere, who was a TSFR patron,invited him home
to discuss the role of tools and artisans in development.
Later, as Kevin travelled around villages to broaden
his education,his enthusiasm was so evident that he
was christened Mzee kijana, or youthful elder.
When I asked Ke v i n ’s wife, R u t h , how she felt
about the thousands of hours he had spent closeted in
the garage, she smiled.“ H e ’s been happy doing those
t o o l s,” she mused.“I see it as our small contribution to
help the world along.” ■
Kevin Petrie on the job in his garage workshop.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
LESTER M. SALAMON
DIRECTOR OFTHE CENTERFOR CIVIL SOCIETY STUDIES AT JOHNS HOPKINS
UNIVERSITY, UNITED STATES
An “a s s o c i a t i o n a l” r e v o l u t i o n
The powers of free markets and states are often said to have spelt the end for
civil society. Not so, argues the author: the non-profit sector is booming,
alongside voluntary action
T
he new spectre which is haunting the devel-
oped world is not that of the proletariat,
which Karl Marx called to our attention some
150 years ago.R a t h e r, it is the lonely bowler,
as described by Robert D. Putnam in his
book B owling alone:The collapse and revival of A m e r-
ican community—the alienated individual cut off from
his or her social roots, lacking bonds of trust and rec-
i p r o c i t y, and forced to function in a universe of all
against all without those “habits of the heart,”as A l e x i s
de Tocqueville called them, which make human exis-
tence tolerable.
Accusing the welfare state
This situation has been traced in some accounts to
the rise of the state and the more formal parts of the
voluntary sector, which have supposedly crowded out
informal voluntary activity and left it without a clear
social function.A struggle is said to be raging between
two epic foes: on one side the organized structures of
social existence, c h i e fly the state and formal social
organizations;and on the other the self-organization
of individuals, with the former emerging victorious in
the world’s more developed regions, while true citizen
self-organization holds its own,mainly in less devel-
oped regions.
In reality, we seem to be in the midst of a “global
associational revolution”—a massive upsurge of orga-
nized private voluntary activity, of structured citizen
action outside the boundaries of the market and the
s t a t e. It may well prove to be as momentous a feature
of the late 20th century as the rise of the nation-state
was in the late 19th century.
Why is it happening now? The answer lies in four
crises and two revolutions.
The first of these impulses is the perceived crisis
of the modern welfare state, the growing sense that in
Western Europe and North America,it has become
o v e r l o a d e d , and expectations have outrun the
capacity of state-delivered welfare to deliver. Fa r
from simply protecting individuals against unrea-
sonable risk,the welfare state stands accused of sti-
fling initiative, absolving people of personal respon-
sibility and encouraging dependence.
A crisis of development has arisen alongside this.
The oil shocks of the 1970s and the recession of the
early 1980s dramatically changed the outlook for
developing countries.In sub-Saharan A f r i c a ,We s t e r n
Asia and parts of Latin America,average per capita
incomes began to fall. One result has been a growing
consensus about the limitations of the state as an
agent of development, and a new-found interest in
“assisted self-reliance” or “participatory develop-
m e n t ,” an aid strategy that stresses the engagement of
grassroots energies through NGOs.
A worsening global environmental crisis—fuelled
partly by the continuing poverty of developing coun-
t r i e s, and partly by the wasteful practices of the
wealthy—has also stimulated citizens into taking
action on their own.
Fi n a l l y, the collapse of the socialist experiments in
Central and Eastern Europe has deepened scepticism
about the abilities of government to satisfy the full
range of human needs.While the promise of socialism
had long been suspect, the economic regression of the
mid-1970s helped destroy what limited legitimacy
the communist system had retained.This failure ush-
ered in a search for new ways to satisfy unmet needs,
leading not only to the formation of market-oriented
cooperative enterprises, but also experimentation
with a host of NGOs.
International Year
of Volunteers
In Lucknow, India,embroiderers belonging to the Self-
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 37
Beyond these four crises, two further develop-
ments also explain the recent surge of third-sector
organizations.
The first is the dramatic revolution in communi-
cations that took place during the 1970s and 1980s.Th e
widespread dissemination of the computer, fib r e -
optic cable, fax,television and satellites opened the
world’s most remote areas to the communications
links required for mass organization and concerted
action.This development was accompanied by a sig-
nificant increase in education and literacy. Between
1970 and 1985,adult literacy rates in the developing
world rose from 43 to 60 percent.
Awakening the global bourgeoisie
The combined expansion of literacy and com-
munications has made it far easier for people to orga-
nize and mobilize. Authoritarian regimes that had
successfully controlled their own communications
networks have grown powerless to stop the flow of
information through satellite dishes and faxes. I s o l a t e d
activists can more easily strengthen their resolve,
exchange experiences, and maintain links with sym-
pathetic colleagues at home or abroad.
Fi n a l l y, the economic expansion of the 1960s and
early 1970s produced a new global bourgeoisie which
has helped promote third-sector growth. During this
period the world economy grew five percent per year,
with all regions sharing in the expansion—in fact the
growth rate of the USSR, East European and devel-
oping countries exceeded that of industrial market
economies. In Latin America,Asia and Africa, this
growth helped create a sizeable urban middle class
frustrated by the lack of real economic opportunity
and often, real political participation. When eco-
nomic conditions deteriorated after the 1970s oil
shock,these new elites turned to NGOs in response,
providing much of the leadership that has fuelled
third-sector growth.
A wish-list
for the non-profit sector
The result has been the emergence of an orga-
n i z e d ,p r i v a t e, n o n - p r o fit sector that has quietly taken
its place as a major economic, social and political
force in nations around the world. Work done in 22
countries for the Johns Hopkins Comparative Non-
p r o fit Sector Project has revealed that non-profit
organizations accounted for five percent of the work-
f o r c e, not including the involvement of an estimated
11 million full-time unpaid volunteers.It also revealed
t h a t , as a general rule, the larger the non-profit sector,
the more extensive the level of volunteering, under-
lining the fact that voluntarism is in some sense a
social and not just an individual act.
What all of this suggests is the need for a new
approach to address public problems.Two paradigms
have dominated our thinking up to now. The fir s t
stresses sole reliance on the market,and the other sole
reliance on the state. But the market model, though it
has recently staged a remarkable recovery,e s s e n t i a l l y
collapsed in the Great Depression of 1929.The public
sector model fell with the Berlin Wa l l .The temptation
will be strong among third sector activists to advance
the “non-profit sector” as the panacea, and to urge
complete reliance upon it.
Without denying the vital contribution that non-
p r o fit institutions can make, we should be wary of
claiming more for the sector than it can deliver. We
have learned over the past 100 years that today’s
problems are too complex for any one sector to handle.
What this suggests is that the appropriate para-
digm for the 21st century is one of partnership and a
politics of collaboration—i.e. a “new governance”
that emphasizes collaboration, not separate action, b y
the different sectors as the best hope for achieving
meaningful progress.This is the true meaning of the
“civil society” about which we hear so much today—
not a sector, but a relationship among sectors, and
between them and citizens, in which all are actively
engaged in addressing public problems.
Voluntarism has an important part to play in
achieving such civic engagement.It can propel insti-
tutions into engaging in such collaborative efforts
and can serve as the social grease to lubricate the
resulting cooperation. Given the suspicions that often
exist on all sides, this will not be an easy future to
achieve or to manage. But it is the one that seems to
me to offer the greatest prospects. ■
T H E  P O W E R  O F  K I N D N E S S
Employed Women’s Association enhance their skills.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
I
LOUISE CORRADINI 
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Children in chains
At the start of the new millennium, the trafficking and exploitation of children is one of the world’s
greatest scandals, enslaving around 100 million youngsters. Getting the upper hand on it means
attacking the root causes of poverty and boosting law enforcement
n 1997,police in New York discovered
a network of 55 deaf-mute children
selling key-rings in the city’s subway
s y s t e m . The Jackson Heights Deaf-
M u t e s, as the press called them, h a d
been brought from Mexico by a gang
specializing in selling defenceless chil-
dren into slavery. At the end of an 18-
hour day, they were expected to bring
their bosses $100. Paid nothing, t h e y
were subjected to violent physical
abuse.
This episode revealed that child
slavery was indeed taking place in the
heart of Western civilization.A c c o r d i n g
to U. S. government estimates, b e t w e e n
700,000 and two million women and
children are sucked into this illegal trade
every year worldwide.
When the youngsters arrive in a for-
eign country, far away from their fami-
l i e s, they are at the mercy of their
e m p l o y e r s. I s o l a t e d , they are put to
work in plantations, f a c t o r i e s, c o n-
struction sites or domestic service. Or
else they are forced to beg or become
child prostitutes.Often confined in their
w o r k p l a c e s, they toil in hazardous con-
d i t i o n s. In short, they are treated as
slaves.
The stories of Charles Dickens,
Victor Hugo, Emile Zola and Edmundo
d’Amicis about exploitation of children
in the 19th century are comparable to
what child slaves have to endure at the
dawn of the new millennium.
The phenomenon cannot be sepa-
rated from the much broader reality of
child labour.The International Labour
Organization (ILO) reckoned in 1995
that 73 million children under the age of
10 were “economically active” world-
w i d e. On this ground, new forms of
exploitation have developed. Due to
the illegal nature of child slavery and
trafficking, it is extremely difficult to
collect data on its extent,but several
recent studies give some idea of the
sheer magnitude of the problem.
Staggering
figures
• Every year, around 200,000
women and children are victims of the
trade in Southeast Asia,according to
the International Organization for
Migration (IOM).Tr a f ficked children
are being forced into sweatshops,
brothels and begging on the streets.
• Between 100,000 and 150,000
Nepalese women and girls were sent in
1995 to India,where they were sexually
exploited, reports the Committee on
the Rights of the Child. The Bangla-
desh National Women Lawyers’ A s s o-
ciation reports that more than 13,000
children were trafficked out of
Bangladesh in the last five years.
• UNICEF estimates that there
are 200,000 child slaves in West and
Central Africa.
• In June 2000, Human Rights
Watch denounced the practice of
employing children in slave-like con-
ditions on U. S. f a r m s. About 50,000
women and children enter the United
States each year to be used as slaves,
the U.S. Central Intelligence Agency
admitted in April 2000.
• In Brazil, 40,000 children are sold
every year to work on farms and as
domestic servants.The traffickers lure
girls with promises of jobs in restau-
rants in remote parts of the Amazon.
Once there, they are forced to work in
nightclubs and moved from one
mining community to another.
• Girls from Guatemala, H o n d u r a s
and El Salvador are taken to Mexico
and sold to brothels for $100 or $200
e a c h , according to Casa A l i a n z a , a
human rights NGO that defends chil-
dren in danger in the region (see page
40). In Nicaragua, an average of one
child disappears every three days.
From Nepal to Nigeria or Brazil,
the methods are the same.Traffickers
Symbols of exploitation:the hands of a young boy employed in a Colombian brick-making factory.
◗ E T H I C S
38 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
win the confidence of the parents with
a small amount of money or clothes
and the children are then entrusted to
t h e m . The recruiters promise to look
after the children and find them a job
that will help raise the standard of living
of the whole family.
Trafficking in children arises from
p o v e r t y, the decline of the extended
f a m i l y, lack of education for the chil-
dren and of other sources of income
for the family. But the illicit trade is
also a result of how some societies
regard children.The parents themselves
are often reponsible for the enslave-
ment of their offspring, seeing them as
an investment and hoping they will be
able to make some contribution to the
family income, either in cash or in kind.
This view creates fertile ground for child
labour and trafficking to develop.
Offences that
go unpunished
In strongly patriarchal societies,
women and children have little or no
freedom, which explains the extensive
discrimination against girls, w h o s e
exploitation for sexual purposes or as
domestic servants is seen to a certain
extent as “normal.”
The absence of national legislation
aimed at punishing such trafficking
makes things easier for the go-betweens
and the employers. There is no agreed
definition of the crime nor a common
standard for penalties.In some countries
charges can be pressed in court, but this
is very rare.I n e f ficiencies in law enforce-
m e n t , including lack of political will and
corruption,perpetuate the problem.
Lasting scars
The ILO’s International Programme
on the Elimination of Child Labour
(IPEC) is striving to find solutions to the
p r o b l e m . Based on past experience,
IPEC has started several projects to
help governments combat traffic k i n g
of children in A f r i c a , Asia and Latin
A m e r i c a .These aim to raise awareness
of the issue and free children from
exploitative work by tackling the root
causes of poverty, i g n o r a n c e, i n a d e q u a t e
educational systems and law enforce-
m e n t , as well as the lack of remunerative
employment for adults.
The dreadful conditions which traf-
ficked children work in and their contact
with dangerous machinery and mate-
r i a l s, as well as the harsh discipline
meted out to them, do not simply harm
their health. It also subjects them to
severe psychological trauma. S e p a r a-
tion from their families, the coercion
involved in all trafficking, made worse
by sexual abuse of child domestics,
street children and prostitutes, makes
them prone to depression. For many of
these victims, this torment paves the
way to a life of crime or drug addic-
tion. ■
Convention C182, known as “the Worst Forms of Child Labour Convention,” was adopted in
1999 by the ILO. This applies to “all forms of slavery or practices similar to slavery, such as
the sale and trafficking of children, debt bondage and serfdom and forced or compulsory labour,
including forced or compulsory recruitment of children for use in armed conflict.”
The “Protocol to Prevent,Suppress and Punish Trafficking in Persons, especially Women and Chil-
dren, supplementing the United Nations Convention against Transnational Organized Crime”
defines trafficking in persons as “the recruitment, transportation, transfer, harbouring or receipt
of persons, by means of the threat or use of force or other forms of coercion, of abduction, of
fraud, of deception, of the abuse of power or of a position of vulnerability or of the giving or
receiving of payments or benefits to achieve the consent of a person having control over anoth-
er person, for the purpose of exploitation. Exploitation shall include. . . the exploitation of the
prostitution of others or other forms of sexual exploitation, forced labour or services, slavery or
practices similar to slavery, servitude or the removal of organs.”
Both documents define a child as a person under 18. ■
LEGAL INSTRUMENTS
The price of exploitation
In the Camerounian town of Bamenda, you can see notices in the street asking for child work-
ers between six and 14. These are posted by clandestine middlemen who recruit the youngsters
for cocoa or cotton plantations, where they will be paid just $14 a month.
In Abidjan (Côte d’Ivoire), employment agencies contract children to work in mines for $10 a
month. They also find girls to send to Europe or the United States to work as maids for $25 a
month, many of whom end up in child prostitution rackets.
With their miserable wages, these children are a pool of virtually free labour. The story is pretty
much the same all over West and Central Africa. Trafficking in children for use as cheap labour in
conditions of near-slavery has increased there in recent years, as an ILO investigation team found
when it visited nine countries in the region.
The IPEC studies have traced trafficking routes and identified some countries as mainly suppliers
(Burkina Faso, Ghana, Mali and Togo), while some (Côte d’Ivoire and Gabon) tend to be mainly
receivers. Others (Benin and Nigeria) are both.Nigeria seems to be particularly affected by the
phenomenon: 1,178 women and children are reported to have been trafficked between March
1999 and December 2000.
Most of the children are sold by their parents for between $14 and $40 each.Some of the agents
say they manage to find work for as many as 150 children a year.
One Nigerian network makes between $10,000 and $12,000 for smuggling a child into New York,
U.S. immigration officials say.
The system is the same in Asia and Latin America,two other continents described by internation-
al human rights organizations as “major suppliers”of child slaves. The total value of this world-
wide trade in children is hard to estimate. But experts say it is one of the most profitable forms
of organized transnational crime after drugs, illegal gambling and prostitution. ■
June 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
A
L. CORRADINI AND ASBEL LÓPEZ
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALISTS
N G O s : gladiators of freedom
Working on the ground and in international campaigns, NGOs have managed to shed a glimmer of
hope on the lives of hundreds of thousands of child slaves
CHILDREN IN CHAINS
t five in the morning, well before most
children get up to go to school,12-year-
old Abula sets out on a six-kilometre
barefoot trek along a road made of mud
and stone to work on a coffee plantation
in Bouafle, Côte d’Ivoire.
When he gets there, wet and tired,
the foreman tells him where he is to plant
that day.“ You have to work fast because
they threaten to punish and starve us if we
d o n ’t do the set amount of work,” he says.
“If we can’t work because we’re ill, we
risk being physi-
cally tortured.O n e
day I saw them tor-
ture two friends of
mine who wanted
to escape. Both of
them ended up
dead.”
Abu la wa s
rescued by A n t i -
Slavery Interna-
t i o n a l , which was
founded in Lon-
don in 1839 and
proclaims itself
t h e w o r l d ’s oldest
NGO.
Alo ng  w i th
other international
o r g a n i z a t i o n s, s u c h
a s t h e I L O ,
UNICEF and the
European Union, NGOs have grown
much more effective in their fight against
child slavery and gone beyond simply
trying to make governments and inter-
national bodies aware of its most extreme
e x p r e s s i o n .Their most valuable work lies
in rescuing and rehabilitating dozens of
children suffering the cruellest forms of
exploitation.
These NGOs work though close coor-
dination between North and South.Th o s e
in the South gather evidence and testi-
m o n i e s,while those in the North publicize
the issue and help organize international
c a m p a i g n s, the most striking of which
was the Global March Against Child
Labour in 1998,when groups set out from
A s i a , Latin America and Africa to
assemble outside the ILO’s headquar-
ters in Geneva and denounce all exploita-
tion of the world’s children.
Anti-Slavery International is now
pressing governments and political
leaders to make the fight against child
workers part of their political pro-
g r a m m e s. It maintains permanent con-
tact with NGOs in the South and funds
projects there to investigate the situation
of child workers.
One such NGO is the Bangkok-
based Child Workers in Asia (CWA ) ,
which recently highlighted the case of a
child who was being atrociously
e x p l o i t e d . Like Abula in A f r i c a ,1 4 - y e a r-
old Devi Lina Sari also rose before dawn
to go to her job on a sugar plantation in
Medan, Indonesia. “I set out at 6 a.m.
every day except Sunday,” she says. “I
start work at seven and finish at four in
the afternoon, with an hour’s break at
midday.”
Like all children of her age, s h e ’d like
to play with her friends,but after cutting
s u g a r-cane for eight hours she is too
exhausted to do anything but rest.“If I
cut myself with the machete, the boss
pays for medicine but I have to reim-
burse him. If I’m ill and can’t work, I
don’t get paid.”
When CWA identifies a child worker
being exploited,one of its officials goes
with a policeman and a social worker to
rescue the child and return him or her to
the parents (if the child has been taken
away by force),or else hand him or her
over to a rehabilitation centre or volun-
teer family if the youth has been sold as
a slave.Children who have had the trau-
matic experience of slavery are rehabil-
itated over a period of three to six
months.
The worst kind of child exploitation is
s e x u a l . M a r i a , a
1 2-y e a r-old Hon-
duran girl, w a s
kidnapped in her
c o u n t r y, sold in
Guatemala and
taken from there
to Mexico, w h e r e
she was bought by
the owner of a bar
who forced her to
become a prosti-
t u t e, servicing 20
men a day.
This tragic case
was discovered
b y Casa A l i a n z a ,
founded in Gua-
temala in 1981 and
now the Latin
American branch
of Covenant House,
a New York-based NGO. Casa Alianza
started out by rehabilitating street chil-
dren in Central A m e r i c a , but for the past
four years it has focused on exposing the
sexual and commercial trafficking and
exploitation of children,which includes
p o r n o g r a p h y, sexual tourism and child
prostitution.
This is a massive task, but it has
already proved effective: Costa Rica’s
special judge dealing with sex crimes
acknowledges that two-thirds of the cases
coming before him have been raised by
Casa Alianza. ■
Making chalk in a factory in Mandsaur, India.
◗ E T H I C S
40 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
I
SYLVIA TREUDL
WRITER, PUBLISHERAND POLITICAL
SCIENCERESEARCHER IN VIENNA
(AUSTRIA)
A local train named desire
The railroad that chugs across Austria’s Semmering pass is on the UNESCO World Heritage list. More
than a technological achievement, this local train evokes memories of a vanished, melancholy world
t ’s not a good idea to visit the Semmering
pass if you’re sad, unless you’re feeling
really blue. And if you do make the
j o u r n e y, take the old S e m m e r i n g b a h n
r a i l r o a d , which will offer much more
than a winding trip through the moun-
tains:a list of sentimental or legendary
names will send chills up and down your
s p i n e. Höllental (Hell Va l l e y ) , B ä r e n-
sattel (Bear Saddle), Eselstein (Donkey
R o c k ) , Adlitzgräben (Adlitz Graves),
Kalte Rinne (Cold Furrow). I ’ve always
preferred to cross the Semmering on
this local train rather than on the com-
fortable express.
Once, I looked at the scenery strad-
dling my motorcy c l e.The Höllental valley
was cold and wet,the curves on the way
to the pass scattered with sandy furrows.
But even back then, I was too melan-
cholic to admire the beautiful,strangely
anachronistic scenery. What, lurking in
the verdant forests, makes you cry and
puts joy back in your heart? Perhaps I
always chose the wrong time of year for
a trip to the Semmering. When the fog
brushes up against the rocks with its
shreds of unhappiness and slips into the
green meadows, when the gardens shoot
past the train’s windows, dazzling with a
thousand colours, there is just one thing
I want to do: shine one last time and
learn to die with beauty,before the dead
season comes.This mountain and scenery
fill me with such sadness! Old memories
come flooding back. Not mine, but those
that others have told me, which they in
turn had heard somewhere. Even so, t h e y
stir something in me. And I always con-
jugate the Semmering in the past tense,
like the beginning of a fairy tale:“Once
upon a time…”
Once upon a time, t h e n , a land on
the eve of a revolution had an emperor
who decided to conquer a mountain.In
so doing, he resorted to a modern
strategy whose purpose was to take
people’s minds off the problems of the
day. Confronted with the revolution of
1 8 4 8 , he decided to send construction
workers to the area straddling Lower
Austria and Styria and keep them busy
on a bold project. The clever emperor
killed two birds with one stone. Part of
the impoverished, desperate revolu-
tionary proletariat found itself far from
Vienna, forced to do hard construction
work.And the government took all the
Fall colours:the Semmering railway crossing the viaduct over the Kalte Rinne.
C U L T U R E ◗
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
that looked as though they might col-
lapse beneath the weight of ornate Art
Nouveau architectural ornamentation
rose with the same arrogance as their
counterparts on the Ringstraße,Vi e n n a ’s
most fashionable thoroughfare. Th e y
attracted the late nineteenth century’s
wealthiest people and most famous
celebrities.
Silhouettes of
a vanished world
N o b l e s, b a n k e r s, i n d u s t r i a l i s t s,
p a i n t e r s, writers and philosophers felt
an irresistible attraction to Semmering.
E l e g a n c e, luxury and beauty, m i n g l i n g
with a good dose of decadence and nar-
c i s s i s m ,gradually overran the high moun-
tain pastures. In the event of an emer-
gency, Vienna was not far away, and the
train trip was more enjoyable than trav-
elling by horse and carriage. In summer,
the area vied with the Mediterranean.
In winter, it was the meeting place for a
closed circle of regular visitors.
That world,which is as irretrievably
lost as Atlantis, was strictly off-limits to
people outside the closed circle of
fin a n c e, politics or the interloping sphere
of culture… Shh! Isn’t that the writer
Arthur Schnitzler’s ghost behind the tall
pine tree over there? Isn’t he casually
holding the manuscript of a melodrama
credit for a spectacular, c o u r a g e o u s
undertaking—in Au s t r i a , at any rate:
building a railroad that defied the moun-
t a i n s.Workers filled crevices in the rock,
built viaducts over valleys and ravines.
And the result was majestic. Today, the
almost Gothic arches, which stand out
against the sky and mountains in some
p l a c e s, seem as though they had been
built merely to beautify the scenery,
rather than to hold up the deafening roar
of tons of steel which seemed to signal
nature’s capitulation to industry.
A certain Carlo Ghega, who was born
in Venice and has gone down in archi-
tectural history and Austrian politics
under the name of “Knight Karl von
Ghega,” shepherded this adventure to a
successful conclusion. Tie after tie, r a i l
after rail, he tamed the rebellious land-
scape in heroic solitude. At least
according to the undying legend, which
even inspired an Austrian bank note (it’s
out of circulation today). On the other
h a n d , the labourers who wore themselves
out hewing the rock walls with pickaxes
and spades are seldom mentioned.Th a t ’s
how history is written.
The work was finished in 1854. A t
the time, Semmering station was the
highest point on Earth reached by a rail-
road. The passengers were just as “ele-
v a t e d .” Lavish villas and luxurious hotels
in his pale hands? And down there, on
that carpet of moss, isn’t that Sigmund
Freud,looking a bit under the weather,
lost in his thoughts? A little further away
in the undergrowth, is that a grazing deer
or the poet Peter Altenberg walking for-
ward with an energetic gait? Silhouettes
of a vanished world…. Only the trees
still remember these happy, sad or loving
figures strolling beneath the dense
canopy of foliage and needles. But for
me, their presence haunts the woods, in
the dark shadows of the rock walls.
I do not see any female silhouettes,a s
though women had never existed! Ye t
Wanda must have stayed near here. Or
perhaps she did not have enough money
to spend a summer in Semmering. She
undoubtedly would have felt comfort-
able had she been able to afford a pre-
sentable dress. And who knows, maybe
the course of her life would have changed
if she could have left her unbearable hus-
b a n d , Leopold von Sacher- M a s o c h , a t
h o m e. But those are just assumptions
and guesswork. And I’m surprised at
feeling so down again.
Those ladies who accompanied those
gentlemen to the Semmering took the
waters there and enjoyed the change of
s c e n e. They came to chat and turn on
their charm or,once their beauty wilted,
while away the boredom. All of them
On May 5 1842,an alpine garden party marks the opening of Glöggnitz Station (oil painting by Anton Fisher).
42 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
sank with their century without a trace.
The only things left are faded captions on
old photographs, like “ladies of the
nobility at a charity ball in front of the
champagne kiosk in Reichenau Park,
probably on the 50th anniversary of the
Semmering railroad,in 1904.”
Why does this scenery keep me from
living with my day and age? Why does it
drive me into a state of melancholy, t h r u s t
me into a past that is so at odds with my
d e s i r e s, a kitschy, hopeless past occa-
sionally resuscitated on the fli c k e r i n g
screen of a revival movie house? Th e
emperor hunting big game; the young
empress disguised as Romy Schneider,
unless it’s the other way round; Austria
depicted as a sewing kit,filled to the brim
with aristocrats flanked by their sup-
pliers! Only a handful of zealous laun-
d r y w o m e n , upright hunters and wary-
looking poachers—against a backdrop
of mountains and meadows—answer
back.
A concrete jungle?
What awakens these old stories,
which have so little to do with me? Is it
the landscape or my passion for words?
Or the dark melancholy that the Sem-
mering makes me feel? I never see it in
the full light of day, even when the sun is
shining at its brightest. Though it is
breathtakingly beautiful,this landscape
tells me a tragic tale. No matter how
much I think about the farmers, c o a l
m i n e r s, metal-workers and small
landowners who populate it, I cannot
soften this gloomy impression. M o u n-
tain life is tough.
L e t ’s turn away from the past and
look towards the future. Hikers, moun-
t a i n - c l i m b e r s, t o u r i s t s, sports enthusiasts
and railroad buffs make up most of the
S e m m e r i n g ’s summer population. B e i n g
a railroad buff myself, I am closely fol-
lowing the debate over building a tunnel
under the Semmering—a project that
fills me with dread and mistrust. If the
tunnel does go through (it depends on
political choices),that will be end of my
magnificent,melancholic journeys.
The tunnel would let anonymous
express trains zoom through the belly of
the mountain, saving the 20 minutes that
I so thoroughly enjoy losing in the switch-
backs.The 21st century citizen that I am
could congratulate herself on such effi-
c i e n cy and progress! But I don’t .I n s t e a d
I am outraged at seeing this wild yet at
the same time civilized place usurped,
bruised and turned into a concrete jungle.
Isn’t it the fear of witnessing the disap-
pearance of these unfathomable dreams
that come over me without rhyme or
reason during each of my journeys in the
Semmering? They wander like stray cats,
wending their way through the landscape,
hiding, fearful, free and untamable like
nightmares.
I admire this area, but I wouldn’t
want to live with it.
Only visit the Semmering if you are
prepared to feel sad. Unless you are
really happy. ■
The railroad line in Semmering,Austria, which has been on the UNESCO
World Heritage list since 1998, belongs to the “cultural landscapes”
that first made their appearance on the list in 1994.A leg on the route from
Vienna to Trieste, the line cuts through 41 kilometres of rugged mountain
scenery between Glöggnitz and Mürzzuschlag and resulted in the world’s
first completely artificial tourist resort.
The 57 brick-and-stone guardhouses every 700 metres along the tracks,
and the lavish villas and luxury hotels lining the route, are outstanding
examples of the harmonious integration of architecture into a natural set-
ting. The train crosses the daunting Semmering Pass at an altitude of 895
metres, travels through 14 tunnels (with a total length of 1,477 metres),
over 16 viaducts (with a total length of 1,607 metres),four of which have
two stories, and under more than 100 vaults. The railroad marked the start
of the Alps’ career as a tourist destination.
The route was divided into 14 sections, each given to a different company.
In June 1848, 1,007 male and 414 female labourers started hewing away
at the mountains with pickaxes. It took six years and up to 20,000 people
to finish the job. On July 17,1854,this engineering masterpiece was com-
plete, and the first passengers were able to board.
The rugged terrain,lack of powerful explosives and technical limitations of
the time made the task especially painstaking. Project manager Carlo
Ghega not only had to do a complete survey of the area for lack of reliable
maps, but to develop new surveying instruments as well.
The Semmering railroad was rebuilt many times over the years, especially as
the weight and speed of trains have increased. Its appearance changed the
most between 1957 and 1959,when the line was electrified. These necessary
adjustments, however, have not altered the almost unique harmony between
nature and architecture. ■
IN PERFECT HARMONY WITH THE LANDSCAPE
S E M M E R I N G
G E R M A N Y
Bregenz
A U S T R I A
VIENNA
Eisenstadt
Graz
Klagenfurt
Innsbruck
Linz
Salzburg
I T A L Y
S L O V E N I A C R O A T I A
C Z E C H  R E P U B L I C
C U L T U R E ◗
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
I
P. SAINATH
INDIANJOURNALISTAND AUTHOR
None so blind as those
who will not see
Why don’t stories on starvation and clean drinking water make it onto the front page of South Asian
newspapers? An Indian journalist rails against the growing rift in his country between mass media
and mass reality, a trend driven by increasing corporate control 
t took the Supreme Court of the land to put
hunger back on the front pages of the
Indian press in early May this year.Which
is surprising.Wh o ’d have thought any pub-
lication needs to be told that hunger is still
a story in this country and the rest of South
Asia?
I n d i a , Pakistan and Bangladesh have all
declared food surpluses in the past two or
three years. Between them,the neighbours
have a surplus of 50 million tonnes of
food—but they are home to half the world’s
hungry. Unemployment and hunger have
increased in the same decade that regis-
tered the surpluses.
Yet few in the media thought the
paradox worth pursuing. I n d i a , with 45 mil-
lions tonnes of unsold excess stock of grain,
was bursting with stories waiting to be told.
Most of them are still waiting. From the
m i d - 1 9 9 0 s, evidence of farmers commit-
ting suicide in large numbers began to pour
in from several states, particularly A n d h r a
Pradesh in the south. In 1996-97, f o r
example, over 400 farmers in a handful of
districts in Andhra Pradesh killed them-
selves, mainly because they were too bur-
dened by debt and unable to feed their
f a m i l i e s.A few stray reports acknowledged
t h i s, but no national newspaper actually
put it on the front page. Recent govern-
ment figures show that in Anantapur, just
one district of A n d h r a , 1,826 people, m a i n l y
farmers with very small holdings of two
acres or less, committed suicide between
1997 and 2000.A g a i n , the media has chosen
to look the other way,allowing the author-
ities to manipulate records of what caused
the deaths.
By the end of 2000, it was clear India
was facing its most serious agricultural crisis
in over two decades. Not a single national
newspaper assigned a full-time correspon-
dent to report on this crucial development.
Never mind that hundreds of millions in
India still depend on agriculture for a living.
Fi n a l l y, the Peoples’ Union for Civil
Liberties (PUCL) of Rajasthan state
resorted to a public interest litigation in
the Supreme Court of India on the issue of
h u n g e r, drawing attention to the paradox of
bursting granaries and empty stomachs. I n
early May, the Court served notices to six
state governments, directing them to
explain why things were going so
w r o n g. Th a t , fin a l l y, made it to the front
p a g e s. But nobody wrote about the crisis, o r
went into the field to talk to the poor about
their misery. They concentrated only on
the fact that the court had asked the states
to explain themselves.
Glaring
contradictions
Over the last decade, the Indian press
has been obsessed with the most trivial
topics. Journalists are more interested in
telling the world that India’s burgeoning
new middle class finally has access to
McDonald’s burgers and the latest inter-
national designer labels. Or writing about
the proliferation of weight-loss clinics and
beauty contests. These are the topics that
generate advertising revenue, not un-
pleasant stories about starvation deaths
and the lack of clean drinking water, even
in the heart of large cities. India’s contra-
dictions are well-reflected in the press. On
the one hand, you have overweight urban-
ites paying thousands of rupees to shed
weight at clinics, while on the other, thou-
sands starve to death. The media got the
first story.They missed the second.
Examples of the short-sightedness that
a f flicts much of South Asian journalism
a b o u n d .Dozens of cover stories appeared
on the automobile revolution, as India lib-
eralized the automobile industry in 1991.
More and more rich people bought cars to
add to those they already owned.In 1998,
there were still just five million registered
◗ M E D I A
44 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
Picking the leaves that make beedis for a pittance:does anyone care?
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
vehicles in a nation of one billion.The real
s t o r i e s,on growing pollution and the lack of
mass rapid transit systems which India
direly needs to transport those who will
never be able to afford cars, were rarely
told.And there were no stories about the
fact that bicycle sales, a reliable indicator of
rural well-being, fell sharply.
There are occasional bleeding-heart
stories on the sorrows of the poor, but the
newspapers fail to make the connection
between poverty and the policies driving
it—what I call “market fundamentalism”
and its attendant structural adjustment pro-
grammes.
Why is there such a lack of interest in
crucial issues like poverty? What accounts
for the disconnection between mass media
and mass reality, and why do the largest
sections of the Indian press  fail to cover the
most important stories? 
The grip of press barons
The 1990s have witnessed the decline
of the press as a public forum.This can be
attributed largely to the relentless corpo-
rate takeover of the Indian press and the
concentration of ownership in a few
h a n d s. Around seven major companies
account for the bulk of circulation in the
powerful English language press. In the
giant city of Bombay,with over 14 m i l l i o n
people, The Times of India has a stran-
glehold on the English readership. It also
dominates the Hindi and Marathi lan-
guage press.
The Ti m e s is clear and unequivocal in its
June 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 45
Journalist and author P. Sainath won Amnesty International’s first-ever Global Human Rights
Journalism prize in June 2000. This follows a dozen other prestigious awards, including the
European Commission’s Lorenzo Natali Journalism Award in 1994.
Sainath received international recognition after he spent two and a half years bicycling through
India’s poorest districts, filing reports about a class of people the press seldom deigns to write
about. That work formed the basis of his landmark book, Everybody Loves a Good Drought
(Penguin Books, 1996), a devastating portrait of how the Indian government’s development
policies have gone awry.
The book, which has been translated into three Indian languages as well as Swedish and
Finnish, is now in its eighth printing. It remained the number one non-fiction bestseller by an
Indian author for over two years.
Covering India’s ten poorest districts, Sainath traversed close to a 100,000 kilometres—includ-
ing 5,000 on foot—lugging a heavy typewriter (there was never enough electricity around to
recharge a laptop battery).
Despite their extremely critical content,several stories from his journey have been used as case
studies for trainees in India’s elite administrative service, the IAS. Other project landmarks
include an oral archive of taped interviews with people from the bottom one percent of society
talking about themselves and a unique visual archive of thousands of photographs of the Indi-
an poor at work.
Sainath is currently writing a series of reports on the Dalits, formerly called untouchables, who
remain India’s most marginalized and discriminated-against people.
When not on the road,Sainath teaches at Bombay’s Sophia Polytechnic.He has been a visiting
professor at universities in Australia,Canada and the U.S. ■
ABOUT THE AU T H O R
In the state of Orissa,two men carry their severely injured brother on a bamboo bed to the nearest hospital, 40 kms away.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
priorities. Beauty contests make the front
page. Farmers’ suicides don’t. Sometimes
reality forces changes, but this is the excep-
tion,not the rule. Most other large Indian
newspapers are eagerly following T h e
Ti m e s ’ p h i l o s o p h y, inspired by the press
baron Rupert Murdoch:a newspaper is a
business like any other, not a public forum.
Monopoly ownership has imposed a set of
values entirely at odds with the traditional
role of the Indian press.
An illustrious record
H i s t o r i c a l l y, the press in India has been
very strong at covering the issues it today
tends to ignore. Indian journalism was a
child of the nation’s freedom struggle.
Mahatma Gandhi,Jawaharlal Nehru and a
host of other freedom fighters doubled up
as journalists and publishers, bringing out
their own newspapers. These and many
others plied a radical journalism that con-
stantly put the British Raj on the defensive.
The journalists of the 1920s, 1930s and 1940s
may have been very ill-equipped, and some
would call them pamphleteers. Yet, from
within a very narrow press, they reflected
much wider concerns than journalists do
today.
Now, with rare exceptions, the greatest
Indian papers are run increasingly on cor-
porate lines. Profits and advertising do not
rhyme with socially-relevant news. This is
r e flected in the “ b e a t s ” (or portfolios) of
journalists within newspapers. The Indian
press covers far more than the basic poli-
tics, sports and commerce stories it concen-
trated on a decade ago. We now have full-
time correspondents for fashion, g l a m o u r,
design,even eating out! One non-financial
daily has 11 correspondents covering busi-
ness in a society where less than two percent
of the population have investments of any
kind.Beats related to covering the lives of
ordinary people, h o w e v e r, are vanishing at a
rapid rate. Correspondents covering educa-
tion are often loaded with several other unre-
lated beats because education is not consid-
ered a weighty enough topic.And no paper
has a full-time poverty, unemployment, or
housing correspondent.
Not surprisingly, the media has proved
increasingly inept at covering development
i s s u e s. The more elitist it gets, the less it
will be able to achieve this.The equation is
s i m p l e : the more corporate a newspaper
becomes in its ownership and culture, the
less space there is for public interest in it.
This is explained cogently in Ben
Bagdikian’s book, The Media Monopoly,
which shows the incredible power of media
conglomerates across the globe.A handful
of them, like Rupert Murdoch’s Newscorp
and AO L - Time Warner decide much of
what most nations see, hear or read.
When the media is driven by no higher
cause than maximization of profit, it can
seldom serve the public interest.When cor-
ralled by corporate interest, journalism gets
d e v a s t a t e d . And in the world order of
market fundamentalism, the suggestion
that anything could be fundamentally
wrong with neo-liberal economics, w i t h
globalization or privatization,is heresy. If
Gandhi were alive today, he would be
quickly denounced as a dangerous left-
wing loony.
The 1990s have witnessed a rapid
growth of inequality the world over, as suc-
cessive UN Human Development Reports
have shown us. This may occasionally be
reported in the press. But questioning the
social and economic philosophies and
frameworks that generate this inequality is
just not done.
Signalling society’s weakness
Ye t , even allowing for the limits
imposed by corporatization, the Indian
press can do much more.
Journalists must place people and their
needs at the centre of stories, and accord
better coverage to the rural political
p r o c e s s.They should discuss political action
and class confli c t , not the politicking. Q u i t e
a few good journalists hold back from this
t e r r i t o r y, f e a r i n g, perhaps justifia b l y, b e i n g
branded as “ p o l i t i c a l ” (read leftist). Ye t ,
evading reality (the largest number of
absolute poor live in India) helps no one.A
society that does not know itself cannot
cope.
More stories on the rights and entitle-
ments of the poor could help. The press
can and does make a difference when it
f u n c t i o n s. Governments do react and
respond to the press, if the press tries hard
enough to be heard. Take the example of
the stories on starvation deaths in Kala-
h a n d i ,B i h a r, in the 1980s, which forced two
prime ministers to visit the place.
Decades ago, commenting on the
dismal role of the American press in a mis-
carriage of justice,an attorney in the United
States said they failed “to signal the weak-
ness in society.”That remains a fine defin-
ition of the minimum duty of a decent press:
to signal the weaknesses in society. It is a
duty the Indian press increasingly fails to
p e r f o r m ,but must try to.At least there are
some journalists who believe they should,
and they must push harder to signal these
w e a k n e s s e s. Only then can we hope for
meaningful development. ■
◗ M E D I A
46 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
Press in the world’s largest democracy
Despite its shortcomings, the Indian press reflects the country’s immense diversity, count-
ing some 43,828 publications, including 4,890 dailies. Newspapers are published in 18
principal languages and over 81 small languages and dialects. Hindi, the national language,
accounts for the largest number of papers.
The total circulation of the Indian press reached nearly 127 million in 1998 (most recent fig-
ure available). Daily newspapers had a circulation of three million in 2000, while non-dailies
accounted for just under eight million copies.
The Times of India is by far the largest circulated daily newspaper in the country, with its six
editions attracting a daily circulation of more than 1.3 million copies. The Malayala Manora -
ma, published with eight editions in Malayalam,the language of Kerala state, has a total com-
bined circulation of 1.12 million copies. The Gujarat Samachar, with five editions published in
Gujarati,comes in third position with 859,015 copies.
All these newspapers are privately owned by publishing houses that produce several publica-
tions in different languages. Despite these six-digit figures, only 12.68 percent of India’s one
billion people have access to a printed publication. ■
Source: Press Information Bureau, Government of India and World Association
of Newspapers, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
no longer at ease in exile
n your last book, you recall listening
as a child to the conversations of
your relatives and family friends
who met at the piazza of your
father’s house. You only began to
understand the significance of their
discussions decades later.To d a y, a t
the age of 70,are there any ideas
from those early times that con-
tinue to rattle around in your head?
Yes—the recognition of the impor-
tance of stories.We don’t know one-tenth
of the stories knocking about.But if you
want to understand a people’s experi-
e n c e, life and society, you must turn to
their stories. I am constantly looking for
that moment when an old story suddenly
reveals a new meaning.
It’s a bitter loss not to meet the kind
of people that I encountered in my
father’s house.They were not giants—in
fact they were quite unimpressive in terms
of what they achieved, but when they are
g o n e, you realize that they were more
important than you originally thought.
At the age of 25,you began writing your first
story, Things Fall Apart, which is considered
one of the first African classics to be published
in English (1958).Legend has it that the book
was the result of what you describe as a “ l a n d-
mark rebellion,” when your fellow students
openly challenged the latent racism in Mister
J o h n s o n,written by a British author and revered
by colonial teachers. At the time, did you have
any idea where this rebellion would lead? 
Mister Jo h n s o n did not turn me into a
writer—I was born that way. But it did
open my eyes to the fact that my home
was under attack and that my home was
not merely a house or a town, but an
awakening story in which the first frag-
Chinua A c h e b e :
I
Although confined to a wheelchair far from his native Nigeria, the founding father of African
literature in English is as close to his beloved home as in student days, when revolt awoke the writer
within
June 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
A writer on a constant search for new meanings in African stories.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
“Westerners see a moral message
in art as a weakness”
THE WISE MAN IN THE W O O D S
True art is universal.An old and sometimes pretentious idea until you meet—or read the
work of—Chinua Achebe. No grand theories to build a universal civilization, instead the
Nigerian offers stories steeped in Igbo philosophy, which have inspired the most diverse read-
ers. The same books that helped to sustain Nelson Mandela during his prison years are stud-
ied as classics by students around the globe. Considered the founding father of the African
novel,Achebe has attracted more scholarly papers and media articles than any other African
author. His work—including some 20 books, numerous essays and edited collections of African
short stories—has been translated into 50 languages.
The first novelist to offer an African perspective on colonialism, Achebe has turned the same crit-
ical eye to contemporary ills such as the rampant corruption of Nigeria’s rulers. In his most recent
b o o k , Home and Exile ( O x f o r d , 2 0 0 0 ) , Achebe analyzes the current state of post-colonial litera-
ture based on his personal experience. In particular, he celebrates his good fortune in being part
of a “crossroads generation.” Born in Nigeria in 1930, he recalls village elders infusing his child-
hood with traditional Igbo culture, while a modern education and the heady days of Nigeria’s
independence provided the distance to both respect and criticize his society without passing
j u d g e m e n t .
Today Achebe is faced with a painful story: a car accident in 1990 forced him into a wheelchair.
Unable to receive the medical care he needs in Nigeria,he lives with his wife in a modest house
in the woods north of New York City at Bard College—a small elite liberal arts college, where
both Achebes teach.
“During happier days,” says Achebe, “I always suspected that the virtue of difficulty is enrich-
ing.But I didn’t have any real personal experience to base this on until my accident.I remem-
ber being in the hospital and a well-meaning visitor asked,’Why you?’ And I said,’Why not?’
(A deep laugh) ’Who should it be?’”
Under the soft wisdom lies a bitter irony: the man who has beseeched African artists to stay at
home is exiled from the place closest to his heart and where he is needed most, N i g e r i a . “But the
inner life is a major source and doesn’t entirely depend on where you happen to be. You make
use of what life deals,” says A c h e b e, “which is what a lot of our stories are about.” ■
ments of my own existence began to have
coherence and meaning.
To begin with, it just seemed to me
that everyone was entitled to tell his or
her own story. Some of the first people to
embrace this notion were friends and
classmates who more or less said,“ Well if
Chinua can do it, so can I.”Then came the
ladies. Even the British writers who had
previously tried to represent us began to
step back and leave the telling to the
owners of the story.
This recognition hasn’t stopped
growing. It’s gone to the point where the
seventh edition of the Norton A n t h o l o g y
of English L i t e r a t u r e includes Things Fa l l
A p a r t as a major contribution of the 20t h
century.
Artists are now pushing to not only tell their
own story but to do so in their own language.
You must understand their frustration. Things
Fall Apart has been translated into about 50
languages but not your native Igbo.
Of course it bothers me. However, I
feel very strongly that a novel written
about the Igbo people in English is better
than no novel at all. You can never wait
for the ideal circumstances to take action.
You do what you can right away—not in
50 years or 15—because you cannot be
certain where the current situation will
lead.
For instance, a few months ago I went
home for the first time in 10 years.The real
purpose of the journey was to give a
public lecture in Igbo about the problem
of the language (the continued use of a
standard dialect imposed by colonial mis-
s i o n a r i e s ) . It was one of the most incred-
ible things I have ever done in my life.
Thousands and thousands of people in
an open stadium were dramatically
responding to my words. So the question
of Igbo language is very close to my heart
and I’m working on it all the time. T h i n g s
Fall Apart tells the world about the Igbo
people. Now let us figure out how to tell
our children and ourselves in our own
language the same story and even more.
I t ’s not a matter of choosing this language
or the other, but about accommodating
both possibilities.
Your stories revolve around the weaknesses of
your central characters.As you’ve written,“ i t ’s
not very exciting when monstrous characters
cause trouble. When an ordinary man causes
h a v o c , that is more ominous.” But We s t e r n
critics often seem very uncomfortable with this
irony. They’d rather see a hero come through.
Their criticism seems to reflect an essentialist
view of the good African or the bad.
I think the word essentialism is appro-
priate. I don’t know where this defective
way of looking at art comes from.I sus-
pect it’s more Western than A f r i c a n
because in my case—that of the Igbo—art
is inclusive. It includes ordinary people
and their lives.
We have, for instance, this Mbari cel-
ebration in which ordinary people are
secluded for a few months to work with
professional artists. Everyone and every-
thing is included in the creative process.
Whatever appears on the horizon—be it
a new religion or a missionary’s bicy c l e —
is part of this story.This is a way of domes-
ticating what is new or foreign. B y
bringing a new element into your home,
you bring it under surveillance. It’s both
about hospitality and practicality to
ensure your own safety.
The goddess—called Ani by the Igbo—
who commands the Mbari festival is not
only responsible for art and creativity but
morality as well.So there is always a fron-
tier between good and evil.This is why art
cannot be used to justify destruction or an
essentialist view of people. That doesn’t
48 The UNESCO Courier - June 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
mean that our heroes are angels—they are
human like anyone else.
H o w e v e r, Westerners see a moral
message in art as a weakness. In the We s t ,
a novel that is said to be “ p o l i t i c a l ” is not
very good. Or critics say,“despite its polit-
ical message, it is good,”which is in itself
a very political thing to say. For it means,
“the world is okay; we don’t need to drag
any extraneous or political issues into the
story.”
In searching for a metaphor to reflect post-
colonial literature, you first considered:“Until
the lions produce their own historian, the story
of the hunt will glorify only the hunter.” In the
end, you opted for Salman Rushdie’s saying:
ious forms in which we were being inte-
grated into the empire....“Writing back”
is not violent like the lion. It celebrates
debate and persuasion.
You have been revolting since your early days
against a long line of colonial literature  which
was originally used to justify the slave trade.Th e
current media trend of reporting only on the
misery of Africa stems, in your eyes, from this
same line of thinking.The latest chapter in this
“ s t o r y ” is the call to “ t a ke a hard look at
A f r i c a ”and insist that the continent’s problems
are strictly her own fault. Why this rise in
“zealotry”?
I suspect it’s the guilt of imperialism
and slavery. Slavery is probably the one
thing that the West is still most uncom-
fortable about. I suspect that the “ d i s-
c o v e r y ” of slavery in Africa today gives a
good deal of good feeling to this group of
zealots. Some people, perhaps not real-
izing what’s going on, are playing into
their trap. There is no denying the abuse
of children that can go on in poverty—
when parents, for example, send their
children to work because they are unable
to earn a bare minimum.But then some
well-meaning Westerner stumbles upon
this and cries “ S l a v e r y ! ”The downgrading
of the word “ s l a v e ” to represent any kind
of abuse or ill-treatment doesn’t help the
story about what happened for 300 years
in the Trans-Atlantic slave trade.
For every two steps forwa r d , t a ke one step
backwards—that’s the way you described the
“The empire writes back.” Why? 
The metaphor of the lion was far too
dramatic. The lion was bound to drag in
willy-nilly the question of its strength and
overpowering the enemy. But the “The
empire writes back”reminded me of the
first post office in my village.As a child, I
watched the building go up and followed
the transactions going on there. As I
learned to put pen to paper, I watched
postmasters on bicycles bringing sacks of
letters and taking others away.Then came
the blue-painted lorry emblazoned with
“Royal Mail”. As children, we called it
Ogbuaekwu-ugwo, which means Killer-
t h a t - d o e s n ’t - p a y - b a c k . We saw the var-
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 51) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396 French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 48French francs ( 7. 32 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:     Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
Leaping forward by casting ballots in Nigeria’s 1999 presidential elections.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
“The oldest man is the reference book of the
v i l l a g e. This keeps the mind active”
“experiment known as Nigeria” about 20 years
ago in an interview.What phase is the country
in now? 
Nigeria took a huge step to get out of
military dictatorship. However the mili-
tary had been so powerful for so long
that an ordinary civilian leader taking
them on seemed to require too much luck
to succeed.
So Olusegun Obasanjo [a retired
general elected president in 1997]
seemed to be the ideal person to navigate
this problem. He was the only military
ruler ever to hand power back to civil-
i a n s, in 1987.And fin a l l y, he experienced
the terrorism of the military dictator
Sani Abacha and is lucky to be alive.
He has done fairly well. But the
problem of getting Nigeria back to sanity,
let alone prosperity, is far greater than
anyone imagined.So there doesn’t seem
to be a chance for much dramatic
achievement in this first term. But the
fact that we are still knocking about and
asking how we should proceed is a truly
great measure of success.
The fear I have now comes from
rumours that the next president could be
Ibrahim Babangida, the military dictator
preceding Abacha.If we were to get the
notion that the retired generals from the
terrible past will take their turn to rule—
that would be a signal for the ultimate
suicide.
A central question in your work has been about
finding an appropriate form of political repre-
sentation.Does the question still apply?
Finding the form is not diffic u l t , a t
least on paper. But it is difficult when the
economic poverty of the people is so great
that we cannot trust them to exercise con-
trol over who rules them—a situation in
which they would accept a few dollars
from anybody in exchange for their vote.
The level of poverty is crucial in mea-
suring the success of any kind of repre-
s e n t a t i o n .And the most ruthless and cy n-
ical leaders know this. So they plunder
the state and stash the money to use
whenever there is an election.
Western reports on Nigeria’s transition to
democracy almost always evoke the spectre of
an ethnic explosion.How real is the threat?
The ethnic problem is real but an
explosion is not inevitable.You have dif-
ferences in language, culture and history.
But it is important to realize that none of
these ethnic groups were recently
imported into Nigeria.They have all been
there through the millennia. The level
of contact among groups has increased,
but nobody is an intruder. So if it was
possible in the past for these people to live
as near or distant neighbours, then there
is no reason to expect an inevitable explo-
sion today.
Whenever there is a problem, if you
look closely you will find somebody
manipulating differences between people
to serve a purpose of their own.We saw it
clearly at the beginning of our nation-
alist existence, when the British were
planning their exit from Nigeria. Th e y
helped to set one group against another so
that we would fight amongst ourselves
instead of against them.
Our leaders inherited that ability to
create dissension.You saw it at its worst
during our civil war, the Biafran Wa r.
And we have it today with the imposition
of sharia law in parts of the country.O u r
real problem is one of leadership at all
levels.
You once asked in an interview: “How do we
transmit a national culture to Nigerians if not
through works of imagination?” Aren’t you
putting a lot of responsibility on the shoulders
of the artist?
Yes it is heavy. But a little goes a long
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George’s Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
Gordon & Gotch Australia Pty. Ltd., Private Bag 290, Burwood VIC 3125 .
Fax: 03 9888 8561
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Partner Press, 11 rue Charles Parenté, B-1070 Brussels.
Fax: (32 2) 556 41 46/Tel.: (32 2) 556 41 40/partner press@ampnet.be
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: UNES CO O f fice, 8 Po o rvi Marg, Vasant Vihar, New Delhi 110 0 57.
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Editions Le Printemps Ltée., 4 Route du Club, Va c o a s .
Fax: 686 7302. 
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
UNES CO Etxea, Alda Urquijo 60, Ppal. Dcha., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: Distriplumes, Apartado 49232, Colinas Bello Monte, 10 4 2
A Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 979 8 36 0
UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce C/C
Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 28 6 0 326 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
w a y. It surprised me for instance when
in 1987 a leader of one of the main parties,
which is based in the Muslim north,a s k e d
me to be his deputy. I joined simply to tell
people that it was possible to go from
eastern Nigeria to a party in the north
that is led by a mullah,an honest man of
integrity. That I was a writer rather than
politician made the proposal doubly
remarkable.
So the writer has a leadership role to play.
Ye s, but you must also explain that
nobody can have all the answers. B y
saying that our problem is one of leader-
ship doesn’t mean that the “ f o l l o w e r s h i p ”
has no work.
Everybody wants to be a leader until
you see the responsibilities it entails.Yo u
see this clearly in a society like mine,
where age, for example, is revered. But
not revered for nothing. The oldest man
is the one who knows most about the
past.He is the reference book of the vil-
lage. That kind of responsibility keeps a
man’s mind active.
When will you go home to take on this role? 
Aaah,I really want to go back home.
But there are a number of serious limita-
tions that have increased since I went
into the wheelchair. I have to consider
for instance such things: is there a hospital
within reach? If I need certain antibi-
otics, will they be available? 
What do you miss most?
The atmosphere of real work. Th e
atmosphere of people who are on the
same page with you. For instance, j u s t
before my accident,I became president of
my town council. The other day, the cur-
rent president wrote to me to ask for my
help with a project for a new library.
Nobody in upstate New York comes and
says, “we want to build a library, can you
help?” I miss being where I am needed
most.
INTERVIEW BY AMY OTCHET
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
+ …
Major titles:
Things Fall Apart (over 8 million copies sold
since its publication in 1958 by Heinemann),
No Longer At Ease (1960), Girls at War and
Other Stories (1972), Anthills of the
Savannah (1987), The Voter (Viva Books,
1994)
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
54th year
Published monthly in 28 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Louise Corradini
French edition: Sophie Boukhari,Philippe Demenet
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Shiraz Sidhva
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Gérard Prosper,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Pushplata Taneja (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Sardinian:Diego Corraine (Nuoro)
Russian: Valeri Kharkin (Moscow)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing the
credit line reads “Reprinted from the UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author’s
n a m e. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts can-
not be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by:
(1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,
A n nA r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,
Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL: C1 - JUNE2001
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly
in Paris by UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e.
Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and additional mailing offic e s.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 06-2001-OPI 00-592 A
June 2001 - The Unesco Courier 51
A traditional meeting of masks, minds and spirits in South Ika,Nigeria.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Focus:
■ From tattoos to piercing: tapping ancient rites
■ Clues from the art world
■ Neuroscience and the frontiers between body and soul
■ Economic development: driving the body’s growth? 
■ Argentina: jobless men on the fitness kick
■ Medicine: the price of resculpting a body 
■ The illicit organ trade
■ Hiding away from old age
■ Towards the human robot?
Features include:
■ Angola: a journey into the ruins of Kuito
■ Nurturing tropical forests back to life
■ Quebec: the triumph of multilingualism
■ Southern NGOs dictate their terms
■ Crafts in the grip of global trade
■ Freedom according to Spanish philosopher Fernando Savater
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
July-August 2001:
The body:
new ideals in
the global age
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 28 languages
]]>
</page>
</document>
