<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="123798eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
P ro fil de
l ’ i n t e r n a u t e
en rupture
de To i l e
Le nucléaire,
p a ra d e
à l’effet
de serre ?
I t s u k u s h i m a
et son temple:
le temps
re t ro u v é
Afrique CFA:1000 F.CFA,Antilles:18 FF, Belgique:160 FB, Canada:3,95$Can,
Espagne:550 Ptas, USA:4,25 $US, Luxembourg:154 F.Lux, Portugal:700 Esc ,
Suisse:6,20 FS , United Kingdom:2,5£,Maroc:20 DH.
October 2001
Canada:$4.65 Can,United Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
Striking peace
on troubled
wa erst
SEPTEMBER 11, 2001
MAKING SENSE OF THE ATTACK
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
OCTOBER 2001
C O N T E N T S
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily re p resent the opinions of UN E S C O or those of the
e d i t o rs of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r s t a f f. The boundaries on maps do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the
United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
I N T H I S I S S U E
◗ Shockwaves
After the initial shock of the attacks
on September 11,three words have
been repeated like a mantra:
war, civilization and Islam.Such
reductionism more often than not
prevents considered analysis of
the context in which this abominable
act was committed (p. 3). Several
articles in this issue provide leads
for undertaking such urgently needed
reflection,though they were not
planned as reactions to the atrocities
in New York and Washington.
From Jerusalem,the Palestinian
scholar Sari Nusseibeh dreams
that his city, ravaged by violence,
may fulfil its destiny and bring peace
to nations (pp. 4-9).Pierre Sané, a
senior UNESCO official and former
secretary-general of Amnesty
International,explains why Durban
was a success in the fight against
racial discrimination, which lies at the
source of  many current frustrations
(pp. 10-12).Dirty money is a weapon
of terrorism:the United Nations
is preparing a convention against
corruption,a scourge fed by
globalization (pp. 39-41).“Digital
convergence”unites all means of
communication onto a single medium.
This technical revolution goes hand
in hand with increasing economic
concentration,undermining the
critical importance of pluralism
(pp. 39-41).In an interview, Malian
griot Sotigui Kouyaté,one of Peter
Brook’s longtime actors, shares a deep
commitment to cultural encounters
(pp. 47-51).Such cultural mixing is
hard to come by in contemporary art,
despite its claims to being universal
(pp. 42-43).And while education is a
key to transmitting knowledge and
fostering critical thought,its role
may be increasingly endangered
by the ageing population of teachers
(pp. 13-15).
The dossier also  brings a message
of hope. While many have predicted
that wars this century will be fought
over water, recent and distant history
points to the contrary:this precious
resource nourishes dialogue rather
than conflict (pp. 16-38).
◗ PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 Jerusalem: childhood truths
A Palestinian scholar from one of Jerusalem’s oldest families dreams that his city
might one day outshine human differences.
Photos by a student collective from Al-Quds University, text by Sari Nusseibeh
◗ VIEWPOINT
10 In defence of Durban
The Durban conference against racism was the target of much unfair criticism, argues Pierre
S a n é , who led UN E S C O’s delegation.
◗ EDUCATION
13 A hard sell for teaching
In industrialized countries, teaching is a greying profession.Attracting a new generation starts
with addressing some deep-set grieva n c e s. Cynthia Guttman
15 Chicago’s headhunting drive Julie Blair
◗ ETHICS
39 On the tracks of a global vice
Fed by rapid globalization, the scourge of corruption has become top priority
for the United Nations. Michel Bessières
◗ CULTURE
42 Contemporary art: who calls the shots?
A handful of rich countries dominate the art scene,despite the appearance
of an increasingly internationalized marke t .
Interview with Alain Quémin
◗ MEDIA
44 When the media meet as one
The era of digital convergence promises to be a giant upheaval in the wa y
people communicate, relax and work. John Vince
46 All power to the barons? Interview with Robert McChesney
◗ TALKING TO…
47 Sotigui Kouyaté: the wise man of the stage
His career spans many cultures, but Malian actor Sotigui Kouyaté is fir s t
and foremost committed to sharing A f r i c a ’s living traditions.
Detailed table of contents on page 16
Fo c u s Striking peace
on troubled waters
The one re s o u rce we can’t live without is
becoming ever more scarc e. Will wars be fought
over water, as they have been over oil? 
The thesis is pro v o c a t i v e, but overlooks the fact
that hostile countries have almost always
managed to strike deals on the rivers flo w i n g
a c ross their bord e rs. F rom the Danube to
t h e N i l e, this dossier highlights the ways
i n which water is used to extinguish fires ra t h e r
than ignite them.
Erratum: the photo caption published on page 40 of our previous issue should have read as follows : “Street children,
gathered voluntarily by Russian officers, take part in an informal rehabilitation programme which includes a military
training component.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
E D I T O R I A L ◗
C lose to 7,000 dead, nearly all of them missing.
The world’s sole superpower struck at the heart
of its economic life and defence system,
something that no state at war with the U. S.
had previously managed to achieve. A whole
new scale of destruction, marking the advent of “ h y p e r-
t e r r o r i s m .”Suspects linked to obscure transnational networks
believed to centre around a billionaire wa r l o r d , hidden in a
country that could not be more different from A m e r i c a .N o
admission of responsibility. The September 11 attacks were
u n t h i n k a b l e. For this very reason, the shockwaves that
ensued have been unprecedented.
First thoughts went to the victims, their families and
the nation, in a spirit of unreserved solidarity. Then,once
rescue operations got underway and public security
measures were taken, came disbelief, rage and resolve,
but also, on a more diffuse level, the time for
introspection and doubt.
American military forces are mobilizing and
Operation “ I n finite Justice,” (renamed “ E n d u r i n g
Freedom”) has been launched. But to deliver what kind
of justice, within what legal constraints and against
whom? Doing justice to the victims and  preventing more
violence by dismantling terrorism is a legitimate and
imperative obligation. But the wall of an American
Muslim insitute bears an anonymous warning: “An ‘eye
for an eye’ leaves everyone blind.” Retaliation against
fanatics using force alone succumbs to their logic. The
military and security response can only be fair, and thus
effective, if it is part of a global answer to the key
question: how and why did we come to this?
So far, the words that are repeatedly cited— war,
civilization and Islamism—stand in the way of profound
analysis. The first word is inappropriate, since wars are
fought between nation-states. The second has a painful
history that can be traced back to the Enlightenment,
when humanity was divided into the “civilized” and
“barbarians” in order to legitimize Western conquests.
This war-cry of “civilization”came to paper over colonial
expansion. Today, use of this word in the singular
suggests that the world contains only one civilization,
relegating all others to an inferior or even non-existent
status. The third term, Islamism,describes a political and
religious movement advocating expansion of and respect
for Islam. The term is increasingly confused with its
violent extremes, which are condemned by most
Muslims. To line up this skewed definition with the words
“war” and “civilization” is to adopt exactly the same
way of thinking as that embraced by the alleged culprits.
Actions that stem from such an interpretation inevitably
lead to a dead-end.
Reactions to the attacks as gleaned from the
international press offer a starting point for reflection.
They point to significant fault lines. The attacks were
clearly a trauma for Americans, as well as for many
people, mostly living in developed countries. A very small
number of people openly displayed abominable joy. A
larger group, while empathizing with the victims, looked
upon these attacks as one more instance—albeit a more
dramatic one—of a plague of violence affecting the
entire planet. This time it had hit the U.S., as it had
already struck many other countries. Yet perhaps the
greatest number of people around the world showed no
more than indifference, as if these events were
happening on another planet,or did not break with life’s
daily routine.
More than half a century ago in London, when
German bombs were still raining upon the city, diplomats
and an educated group of men and women gathered to
reflect upon the unthinkable events of their time. Why
and how, in the heart of “Christian Europe,” in the
country with the most educated population, c o u l d
Nazism surge and the Holocaust take place? What new
world order could prevent a return to barbarism? Their
answers are cast in UNESCO’s Constitution. They found
that a denial of reason unleashed a denial of human
dignity. They attributed this to barriers erected between
people, which gave rise to “mutual incomprehension.”
Their answer lay in a voluntary mission that called for the
development of the “free exchange of ideas and
k n o w l e d g e ” for the “purposes of mutual
understanding”—the “United Nations.” They sought to
give meaning to a world that had gone adrift by
restoring “the moral and intellectual solidarity of
mankind.”
True, the historic context was starkly different from
today. True, the world has strayed from the path traced
by these visionaries. One probably explains the other. But
do these differences invalidate the visionaries’
conclusions and render their path impracticable?
THE UNESCO COURIER
September 25, 2001
September 11, 2001
Making sense
of the attack
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A new day begins in the Holy City.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Following André Chouraqui’s vision of Jerusalem in last month’s
Courier, Al-Quds university president Sari Nusseibeh, whose family
holds the keys to the Holy Sepulchre, spins a childhood tale that has
lost none of its profound resonance
PHOTOS BY A STUDENT COLLECTIVE,TEXT BY SARI NUSSEIBEH
THESE PHOTOSARE SELECTED FROM A PROJECTCONDUCTED BY STUDENTS FROM AL-QUDSUNIVERSITY IN JERUSALEM,
OFWHICH SARI NUSSEIBEH ISTHE PRESIDENT
Sometimes when I am asked how my family—a Muslim family
named after “Nussaibah,” a female warrior-companion of the
Prophet from Medina—ever came to hold the keys to one of
Christianity’s holiest sites in Jerusalem, the Holy Sepulchre, I
smile indulgently. Th e n , I begin by saying: “ We l l , there are a
f e w traditions in the family concerning this,but let me begin with
this tale…”.
The story I then spin out is an innocent mixture of fact and
fiction,a mosaic of the subjective and the objective, which has
been imprinted in my sub-conscious ever since my early
c h i l d h o o d .For me, this is the essence of the identity of Je r u s a l e m
—a beautiful mosaic of tales spun out from a misty past, r o o t e d
in events, whether real or presumed,and constituting the fibre
of the hearts and souls of its inhabitants.
One such tale of which I am particularly fond, e n c a p s u l a t i n g
as it does the magical relation between Man and the City, is that
of the Caliph Umar’s entry into Jerusalem in 638 A . D.It is a tale
that seeped deeply into my consciousness during my childhood,
resounding year after year in my ears and mind,but cumulatively
gathering with it and impressing upon me a particular moral; o n e
P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S ◗
Je r u s a l e m :
childhood truths
At rest in the garden of the Dome of the Rock.
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
w h i c h , because of its association with Islam’s origin in the City,
is fundamental to my self-identity as a Muslim Jerusalemite.
The almighty Caliph of Islam, I have been led to believe,
being totally overawed by the prospect of entering this sanctifie d
C i t y,would only deign to arrive at its gates unarmed.Leaving his
fierce and victorious warriors behind,accompanied only by his
aide and one beast of burden,he approaches the City peacefully
and by foot,to be cordially received by its Christian Guardian,
Bishop Sephronious. On his journey towards the City, the story
goes (and I take this also to be a fundamental part of the tale),
the Caliph and his man-servant exchange places to ride their
single camel.
Much of history is made of what happens next.To me, the
Je r u s a l e m : childhood truths
Jerusalem can still outshine human differences
and reign supreme.
Sunlight and shadows over the eternal City. A window display on the Via Dolorosa.
During a course given by French photographer Luc Chéry*, s t u d e n t s
in literature, architecture and archaeology from A l-Quds University
experimented for the first time with another form of “ w r i t i n g ” —
p h o t o g r a p h y. Working on the theme “ J e r u s a l e m , my city,” t h e y
meandered down narrow lanes and into marke t s, equipped with
t h r o wa way cameras, in search of subjective, timeless shots.The result,
a collection of 35 photographs from which the present illustrations are
s e l e c t e d , will go on show in Jerusalem, R a m a l l a h , Gaza and Nablus, a s
well as in several capitals of the region. ■
IN SEARCH OF THE T I M E L E S S
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
6 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
* In partnership with the cultural service of the French General Consulate, the Al-Ma’mal Foundation
for Contemporary Art and the Centre for Studies on Jerusalem.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
A monument to the dead in the Salah Eddin cemetery stands alongside a shopping district.
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
mystery of Jerusalem is already engraved in the above tale.L a i d
out before me, I immediately see the moral contours of a cosmic
d e s i g n ,mapping out and balancing the relation between the Man
and the City, between Earth and Heaven.At one end of the
design stands the Conqueror and First leader of Men.But his
size is diminutive. His submission is total. His humility and
self-denial are complete.At the other end stands the Golden but
“conquered” City. Its size is majestic. Its form is imperial. Its
heavenly walls totally impregnable,
impervious but to the pious, who enter it
submissively and with humility. It is not
another stone-habitation to be submitted
and conquered by force. It is the
penultimate earthly stepping stone in the
journey of the humble and pious towards
their Creator.
I look at this drawing in awe and
wonder. Not here do I find the signs of
pomp and glory of earthly warriors. Nor
here in the drawing do I see the details of
b l o o d , battle and plunder. There is a
peaceful absence of human force and
violence. There is only the City’s divine
s u p r e m a cy, illuminating the path to God.
A jewel box
of moral tales
I take a look back to reevaluate or
understand the approach of the Caliph
and his man-servant. It takes but a second
for me to realize the other signific a n t
m e s s a g e, the other universal value in this
childhood tale: the equality and
brotherhood between men. R e g a r d l e s s
of their respective earthly stations,C a l i p h
and man-servant are equal before God.
A n d , as equals, they naturally come to
share their earthly utilities.
This is certainly no Roman Emperor
riding golden chariots surrounded and
protected by soldiers and servants, nor a
Cleopatra or Pharaoh carried regally on
the shoulders of beautiful Nubians
belonging to a sub-race, in celebration of
M a n ’s mighty conquests: it is, r a t h e r, a
humble servant of God,piously seeking to
be received by Him. Je r u s a l e m — t h e
stones and the inhabitants—is a jewel-
box of such moral tales. The mosaic
intercrosses time and space, stone and
soul, reality and dreams. It is impossible
not to hear the throbs of your heart, not to
pierce through present sounds and smells
to the point of contact with the images and
sounds of the past,as you tread through
the ancient cobbled streets of history.
You may see soldiers and guns parading through the streets
of the present.You may see anguish or pain or suffering. You
may sense bigotry,or bias or misplaced self-righteousness. B u t
somehow, you manage to gaze right through these and other
images of human contortions, from this period or from other
grim periods of Je r u s a l e m ’s history, to see Jerusalem as its
r e a l ,heavenly self, as a City of unity and piety.And as you gaze
at this eternal Jerusalem with the eyes of faith, you manage
Je r u s a l e m : childhood truths
The Souq al Qattanin,or Cotton Merchants’ market.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
8 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Returning from school through the market of the Damascus Gate.
somehow to imbibe differences and imbalances,distilling into
your own identity other peoples’ pains, tales and histories.
For, what is a Jerusalemite if not a complete human being, a
human being stripped of earthly prejudices, of racism and
bigotry, a human being sufficiently purified to be received by
God?
I would like to believe, in spite of the contortions of the
present, that Jerusalem can still outshine human differences
and reign supreme; and that Je w s, Christians and Muslims
can still make Jerusalem fulfill its destiny of bringing peace unto
the nations. I believe the secret to this dream lies in a childhood
t a l e. It is the tale of Umar: that men who would venture
t o s t e p into the earthly Je r u s a l e m , in fulfillment of the
b e c k o n i n g of God, should behave towards each other as
equals, and be prepared to share their earthly means of entry
to the divine world. ■
Jerusalem’s thousand and one spices.
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
S
PIERRE SANÉ
ASSISTANT DIRECTOR-GENERAL FOR SOCIALAND HUMAN SCIENCESOF UNESCOAND FORMER SECRETARY-GENERAL OF AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL
In defence of Durban:
racism is back on the agenda
“Total fiasco,” “a congregation of the converted,” “a lot of hot air”—the media’s verdict on the Durban
conference against racism was a harsh one. It was also unfair, says Pierre Sané, who led UNESCO’s
delegation
ince racial segregation ended in the
United States and apartheid was
abolished in South A f r i c a , m a n y
governments have denied the existence
of racism in the world,and particularly in
their own societies. Despite this, a world
conference against racism, r a c i a l
discrimination,xenophobia and related
intolerance in Durban, South A f r i c a ,
( Au g. 3 1 - S e p t . 7) managed to draw
delegations from 170 c o u n t r i e s. It was
an extraordinary admission by those who
took part that racism exists in all societies.
The job of the conference was to
point to new kinds of racism1 that today
affect immigrant workers, a s y l u m -
s e e k e r s, r e f u g e e s, displaced people, t h o s e
with HIV/AIDS and others. It was also
intended to denounce moves towards
“genetic discrimination,” for example
when a firm asks a future employee for
his or her genetic imprint with the excuse
of looking for possible“abnormalities.”
The Durban conference brought debate
A protest against racism and poverty held in Durban.
◗ V I E W P O I N T
10 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
up to date on all these points.
These kinds of political gatherings
invariably give rise to trials of strength,
and there are failings. The final
documents in Durban do not mention
the biggest group of human beings
affected by discrimination—South
A s i a ’s 260 million d a l i t s, o r
u n t o u c h a b l e s. Neither was there
mention of black people living in Arab
countries, nor of the Palestinians.
Putting faces
on the victims
But many “ i n v i s i b l e ” victims did
show their faces to the world at the
c o n f e r e n c e. Seemingly trivial but really
very telling was a delegation of
“ P y g m i e s,” who came to publicize for
the first time at a world conference the
threats to their society from war in
Central A f r i c a .Afro-Latins—people of
African origin from Colombia and
Venezuela—also spoke of their
suffering.
The presence of delegations of
R o m s, G y p s i e s, Sindis and other
travelling people—all victims of a
racism ignored by the international
c o m m u n i t y—were able through their
links with NGOs to have their say in the
c o n f e r e n c e ’s final declaration and action
plan. Many other victims were clearly
i d e n t i fie d . Now it is up to governments
to do something about them.This was a
s i g n i ficant achievement for the con-
ference.
Some critics have singled out the
“catch-all”nature of the gathering and
claimed that it was submerged by
disputes of “questionable relevance”—
arguments about whether reparations
should be made for slavery, or whether
Israel should be condemned on the
grounds that Zionism is racist.
The task of the conference was to
list the causes of racism, and slavery was
seen in this context.The slave trade and
colonialism were probably legitimized
by racism and in turn encouraged it.
They were denounced in these terms.
And for the first time, the international
community recognized that slavery and
the slave trade were “appalling tragedies
in the history of humanity” and that
they formed a “crime against humanity.”
All this is only a start. UNESCO, for
e x a m p l e,argues that people have a duty
to remember the past and is calling for
scholars to be allowed access to all
records so that the extent and effect of
the slave trade can be conclusively
a s s e s s e d . It is also asking that school
textbooks reflect the importance of this
tragedy and its criminal nature.
Hidden guilt
The conference had no brief to work
out details relating to the controversial
issue of compensation for slavery during
its 10-day session. But it carried out its
job by making a declaration of principle
over the “moral obligation” to pay
financial compensation for wrongs
committed,and for me that is stronger
than a “legal obligation.”
Giving the status of victims to
Africans, who were the objects of this
t r a d e, finally enables their descendants
to lift their heads high, while allowing
the descendants of those who
committed the crime to end their
s i l e n c e. I have always regarded
development aid as the unhealthy
product of a secret feeling of guilt.Wi t h
the crime recognized for what it is, s u c h
aid can be replaced by fair
compensation that will put the parties
involved on an equal footing.
Some people think the Palestinian
issue was intrusive, but it was inevitably
going to come up in Durban at a
conference organized by the UN High
Commissioner for Human Rights. For
delegations from Arab and Muslim
c o u n t r i e s, the issue is one of human
r i g h t s, discrimination (some Israeli laws
discriminate in this way), v i o l e n c e
against a people and violation of the
right to self-determination. It is in the
news and had to be raised,as apartheid
was in its day.
The United States and Israel, who
were against allowing the issue onto the
a g e n d a , withdrew from the conference.
But the agenda was democratically
drawn up by all the working groups. If a
topic appeared relevant to the aim of the
c o n f e r e n c e, they could decide to include
it for discussion. They did so, and the
final conference declaration expressed
“deep concern” over “the increase in
anti-Semitism and Islamophobia in
various parts of the world,” w h i l e
emphatically rejecting any equivalence
between Zionism and racism.
A moral
re-armament
Can we trust the countries that
promised the conference they would
fight racism? The first test will be
whether they come up with national
plans to do so, along with a budget,
identification of perpetrators and
victims, legislation and a timetable for
a c t i o n .They have said they will.To help
t h e m , the conference has drawn up a list
of “best practices,” such as banning all
kinds of discrimination in the workplace
and in housing, devising ways to
measure progress in education  by the
most disadvantaged groups, a n d
assuring that those who file complaints
about racism (especially concerning the
police) are protected.
All this might seem wishful thinking.
But all world conferences—Rio on the
environment and Beijing on women’s
rights—have ended the same way,
namely with a declaration and a plan of
TEN YEARS OF
WORLD CONFERENCES
1992. UN Conference on Environment and
Development (Rio de Janeiro)
1993. World Conference on Human Rights
(Vienna)
1994. International Conference on Po p u l a t i o n
and Development (Cairo)
1995. World Summit for Social Development
(Copenhagen)
1995. Fourth World Conference on Wo m e n
(Beijing)
1996. Second UN Conference on Human
Settlements (Istanbul)
1996. World Food Summit (Rome)
2001. World Conference against Racism, Racial
Discrimination, Xenophobia and Related
Intolerance (Durban) ■
For the first time,
the international
community recognized
that slavery and
the slave trade
formed a
“crime against
humanity”
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
action that is not binding but which is
based on existing conventions and law.
The aim of such gatherings is to get
countries to re-commit themselves—a
kind of moral re-armament—towards
working together to solve a problem
that depends on international
c o o p e r a t i o n . Nobody forces
governments to take part in these events.
But the fact that negotiations over the
final declaration were so tough shows
exactly how important countries thought
it was. By signing that declaration,they
pledged their word and their credibility,
and agreed to make regular reports on
how their promises were being put into
e f f e c t . Everything also depends on how
far civil society—the 1,000 NGOs who
attended the conference—get involved.
When they get back home, they can say
to their government: “ Yo u ’ve signed.
Where’s your action plan?”
Some people accused these NGOs
o f going to extremes in Durban, t o
t h e point of stifling debate. But there
was plenty of impassioned argument
a t the conference. It was only natural
f o r associations supporting murdered
victims to lose patience with the
“ r e a l i s m ” espoused by governments. S o
the debates were very lively, but not
violent.
The conference put the fight against
racism on the agendas of all NGOs.
Governments have made progress too
by joining a democratic debate
ultimately aimed at the shared
management of global society. Durban
was worth it. ■
1. See UN E S C O C o u r i e r, S e p t e m b e r
Durban gave the final proof: the gatherings of NGOs that are now part
and parcel of all major UN conferences are turbulent affairs.To make
matters worse, they are often infiltrated by “false NGOs,” associations
created especially for the event by undemocratic states, political parties
or industrial lobbies. But even so, these assemblies are valuable hothouses
that have facilitated the gradual emergece of a “global civil society” i n t e n t
on talking on equal terms with the powers that be.
D u r b a n , the first major conference of the 21st century, formed the
latest instalment of a series of similar events (see p. 11) over the last
decade, meetings that have heralded the ascent of non-governmental
representatives into the management of international affairs. They may
be accused of squandering funds (budgets vary from two to 10 million
dollars each),but today’s UN conferences are no longer mere stages for
states to lock horns. Aside from revealing the differences between
governments and other parts of society (such as NGOs, cities and
b u s i n e s s e s ) , the summits also vent the disputes within civil society
i t s e l f. The Rio Earth Summit in 1992 was the first occasion in which
N G O s, until then excluded from large global gatherings, played an
significant part in shaping debate—even if their representatives were
shunted several kilometres away from the official conference. But all the
s a m e, they were there in force (over 2,500 of them), denouncing injustice,
blaming market economics for its undesirable effects and proposing
“alternatives.”
S o m e t i m e s, as in the 1993 Vienna conference on human rights,a c t i v i s t s
have been granted a presence on the official podium and a voice in the
final decision-making process. In Beijing,in 1995,they made the front
p a g e, which is more than can be said of the official conference discussions
on women’s rights. For the very first time,Amnesty International’s then
secretary-general,Pierre Sané,held a press conference in China.
As the summits have continued, these NGO forums have grown in
importance and diversity, often with the approval of the UN. Termed the
“gringo forum” at Rio due to the preponderance of groups from the
northern hemisphere, these meetings have since welcomed a much greater
presence of delegates from the developing world, testimony to the upsurge
of southern NGOs. ■
A FORUM OF SOUND AND FURY
A mural in Namibia celebrates unity between people of different colour.
◗ V I E W P O I N T
12 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
L
CYNTHIA GUTTMAN
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
A hard sell for teaching
In the industrialized world, teaching is a greying profession and burnout rates run high.Attracting a
new generation starts with tackling some deep-rooted grievances,
which go well beyond better pay
ike religion,a calling often sets students
on the path to teaching, but today, t h e
fervour of times past is waning, leaving
schools across the developed world
scurrying for teachers.
Countries are scouting far from home
to fill vacancies, turning the profession
into a global marketplace,with recruiting
grounds stretching from Russia to South
Africa and New Zealand. Some have
even relaxed immigration rules to attract
candidates.
Governments have also taken to
investing in television advertising
c a m p a i g n s, with such slogans as
“Everybody remembers a good teacher”
( E n g l a n d ) , “Be a teacher, be a hero”
( U. S.) or the more cryptic “ Te a c h e r.Wh a t
if the future was you?”(France).
Advertising may not suffice for
raising the beleaguered status of teachers.
Once they’ve scratched the surface, m a n y
novices put the key under the door. In the
United States, up to 50 percent of
teachers leave the profession within the
first three to five years, a trend echoed in
several other industrialized countries.A t
the present rate, the gaping hole left by an
ageing population of teachers is unlikely
to be filled naturally. In most OECD
c o u n t r i e s, the majority of primary and
secondary school teachers are above 40.
The U.S. has to renew two-thirds  of its
teaching force in the next decade. I n
Fr a n c e, also faced with a steady
retirement of staff,enrollment on t e a c h e r
training courses is down
20 percent.
Ageing aside, similar patterns prevail
in most countries, with economic growth
fuelling the “brain drain.” S c i e n t i f i c
disciplines are the hardest hit, a s
university graduates are lured to private
business by more attractive salaries. E v e n
in the public sector, the OECD has found
that other professions tend to be better
off than primary school teachers. I n
C a n a d a , the latter earn less than a
draughtsman or social worker.
Rising expectations
While front-page stories about
children being sent home or schools
switching to four-day weeks are common
because of staff shortages, the real issue,
says the OECD’s Paulo Santiago, is about
declining quality. As he underlines,
research shows that teachers are by far
the single most important influence on
student achievement. If this is true, it does
not augur well for many pupils,e s p e c i a l l y
those worst-off.
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 13
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
The single most important influence on learning.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
In the U.S.,up to 60 percent of teach-
ers who work in poor neighbourhoods are
not certifie d .More than half the country’s
physics teachers don’t have a major or
minor degree in the subject; for math
teachers the proportion is 33 percent.
In country after country, a paradox is in
the making.On the one hand,standards are
being raised and new curricula introduced
in the name of the knowledge economy.
“ Things that you used to see in senior high
school now appear in younger classes,
because we’re trying to cram in more and
m o r e,” says the general secretary of the
Canadian Teachers’ Federation.
On the other, teachers continue to be
faced with large classes, m o u n t i n g
expectations and poor professional
training. “We frequently have to update
our knowledge, especially in the sciences,
and this is not taken into account by
i n s t i t u t i o n s,” says a representative of the
French secondary teachers’ union
( S N E S ) . In Britain, the government
lowered national targets in math for 14-
year-olds after schools complained that
the demands were unrealistic.
Demands for a
greater say
What tends to exasperate the
profession is that these targets often
rhyme with stricter checks on teachers. I n
the UK, for example, teachers are
expected to prepare detailed lesson plans
for inspections and monitoring. “ Yo u
have to prove that you’re doing what the
government has set down,” says Je f f
Holman of the British National
Association of Head Teachers. “There is
a sense that someone is always looking
over your shoulder.”
His concern is shared by his peers in
other countries.“Leading politicians say
we should leave schools in the hands of
professionals, then they turn around the
next week and say that students need
more training in history or again in maths
because we’re lagging behind the rest of
E u r o p e,” says Alf Lindberg, of the
Swedish Teachers’ Union. “ Th e r e ’s a
palpable sense,” according to SNES’
Denis Paget, that “governments no longer
look towards teachers as people who are
c r e a t i v e, but as executors of a
programme.”
For the OECD’s Santiago,“the main
problem is that teachers don’t have
enough autonomy and decision-making
p o w e r. They don’t have much of a say
about the curriculum and teaching
m e t h o d s. For any activity, the most
important thing is motivation, and that
comes from incentives.”
I n c e n t i v e s,h o w e v e r, are an explosive
i s s u e. So far, governments have mostly
opted for “soft”ones. Sweden is offering
training for unqualified teachers. B r i t a i n
has introduced bursaries for trainee
teachers and offered to pay off their
student loans over their first ten years on
the job. In certain short-staffed subjects,
potential candidates are lured by “ g o l d e n
h e l l o s,” while affordable housing has also
been promised in the country’s
prosperous southeast.
Incentives become a much thornier
issue when sacrosanct salary structures
are touched. Teachers’ wages are
traditionally based on education level
and years of service.A r g u a b l y, the snail’s
pace of pay rises adds to some of the
p r o f e s s i o n ’s gripes. The alternative of
tying wages to student achievement and
teachers’ performance in the classroom is
political dynamite. Timid experiments
with performance pay are being carried
out in a handful of U.S. school districts,
while in Saxony (Germany) the education
minister stepped down over an attempt to
introduce this system.
For now, there are less politically risky
o p t i o n s. “Strategies are really crucial,”
says Mildred Hudson,head of Recruiting
New Te a c h e r s, a U. S. n o n - p r o f i t
o r g a n i z a t i o n . “ We ’ve known this was
going to be a problem, but we didn’t plan
p r o p e r l y.” Coaching for apprentice
t e a c h e r s, scholarship support, fie l d i n g
students at the high school level and
scouting for talent in community colleges
have all enjoyed modest success. Many in
the profession also admit that it’s high
time to “recognize that adults can go
through two, three or four careers in their
lifetime,” says Hudson “We don’t know
how to bring those adults into the
classroom and there’s definitely a pool
out there.”
Governments might have woken up
late to the crisis, but shortages are now
climbing high up on the political agenda.
Education was a bone of contention in
recent elections in Britain and the U.S.,
while in Sweden, a country heading for
the polls, a recent Gallup survey revealed
that 78 percent of those interviewed put
education ahead of health care and
unemployment as a leading concern. In
France, also gearing up for elections in
2 0 0 2 , schools have so far not been cited as
a hot campaign topic. “Public debate is
very weak,” laments Monique Vuaillat,
the former head of SNES. Then again,
the shadow of an economic slowdown
might lure some talents toward a
profession they’d once have shunned—at
least until the going gets better. ■
14 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
Lined with houses and gardens, the Dutch town of Almere hardly looks like a place where
teacher shortage might be an issue.And yet,it’s more acute here than anywhere else in
the country.“Between last Christmas and the summer, at any given time, three or four schools
were forced to lock their doors for one or two days a week,” says Netty Tiemersma,head
of the local education board.
Almere has arisen in less than 25 years on the outskirts of A m s t e r d a m , growing rapidly into
a middle-class town of 160,000 people, with a majority of young families.Against the backdrop
of a national shortage, teachers have been hard to come by. Instead,Almere has come up
with other solutions, such as team teaching. Primary schools have hired assistants from
different walks of life and bumped up class sizes to 40 or 50 pupils. Teachers divide them
into sub-groups and rely on their assistants for learning activities. In the longer run,
assistants may receive teaching qualific a t i o n s.The strategy,now being tried out in other towns,
is winning support, with retired teachers and part-time bankers knocking on A l m e r e ’s
school doors. The board stands ready to “interview anyone interested in working in
education.” ■
Wybo Algra, journalist for the Dutch daily Trouw
COMMUNITY BUSINESS
“There’s a palpable
sense that
governments
no longer look towards
teachers as people
who are creative,
but as programme
executors”
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
T
JULIE BLAIR
REPORTER AT EDUCATION WEEK (U.S.)
C h i c a g o ’s headhunting drive
The “windy city” has embarked on an aggressive drive to court teachers, often weary of working in a
district where a majority of students live in poverty
hree years ago, administrators in the
Chicago Public Schools did little more than
advertise available teaching positions in
local newspapers in an attempt to recruit
educators.
This academic year, t h e y ’ll spend more
than $2 million on the endeavour, d i s p a t c h
headhunters throughout the nation to
locate talent, and develop a partnership
with the city to provide affordable housing
for those they hire.
“In a seller’s market,we have to go out
there and woo people,” said Carlos Ponce,
chief human resources officer for the school
d i s t r i c t . C r i t i c s, h o w e v e r, warn that
ambitious recruiting efforts must be coupled
with well-funded retention policies. “You
can recruit all you want and have wonderful
i n c e n t i v e s, but if working conditions are
not palatable, teachers are going to leave,”
said Barnett Berry of the National
Commission on Teaching & A m e r i c a ’s
F u t u r e, a panel of educators, public offic i a l s,
business and community leaders charged
with analyzing the national teacher
shortage.
Corporate tactics
Like many urban school districts in the
United States, the Chicago Public Schools
has overhauled its approach to attract and
retain teachers. Of the 26,000 educators
now on the payroll, 17 percent will be
eligible to retire next year, Ponce said.A n d
while the state of Illinois produces more
than enough teachers to meet demand,
only a handful want to take on the
challenges of working in America’s third-
largest school district, where 94 percent of
the 432,000 students enrolled are believed
to live in poverty, a figure based on the
number of free lunches distributed.Many
students are black or belong to Hispanic
and other minority groups, a n d
administrators are desperate for educators
to reflect this diversity, as well as for those
who are bilingual, q u a l i fied to teach special
e d u c a t i o n , m a t h e m a t i c s, s c i e n c e, or are
willing to work in schools located within the
poorest neighbourhoods.
“In the past,we used to just sit back and
wait until teachers came to us,”Ponce said.
“What we did [during the 1998-99 school
year] was to institute a corporate-style
recruiting programme.” That meant
allocating significantly more dollars and
manpower to recruitment efforts and
thinking creatively about meeting the needs
of rookie educators. The recruitment
budget was increased from $500,000 to $2.1
million over the past three years, and 12
recruitment officers now do the work once
assigned to two, Ponce said.This year, t h e y ’l l
travel to 60 colleges and universities around
the country to attend job fairs, a strategy
never before implemented.
F u r t h e r m o r e, the headhunters are
offering competitive packages. Beginning
teachers with bachelor’s degrees can earn
between $35,521 and $39,365 their fir s t
year;those with master’s degrees can pull
in between $37,981 and $41,825.E d u c a t o r s
also have the choice of two types of medical
plans and may be eligible for a college debt
cancellation programme offered by the
federal government, provided they choose
to work in a shortage area.To make the deal
even more attractive, the district has
instituted a pilot programme to provide
up to $5,000 in salary advances to be repaid
over a teacher’s first few years of work.
Future plans include embarking on a
partnership with the city to provide housing
assistance for teachers in a city where the
cost of living is high.
To date, the strategies appear to be
working, Ponce said.“During the 1998-99
school year, we brought in 1,900 teachers,”
he said.“In 1999-2000, we did 2,200. This
year, we’re shooting for 3,000.”
Experts, however, point out that there
is no research available to determine which
strategies are most cost-effective. “We’re
getting a number of takers on these things,
but we don’t know what the long term
impact will be,” said Susan Melnick of
Michigan State University.
Success depends on making lasting
changes within the system, she said, from
higher wages and better training to
effectively manage the difficulties of the
modern-day classroom.That will all come
in good time, Ponce said.“None is happier
than me about the national teacher
shortage because it has allowed us to
A HARD SELL FOR T E AC H I N G
Looking for educators who are ready to work in the poorest neighbourhoods.
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ill wars be fought over wa t e r, as they have been over oil? Th e
fear has been expressed by high-ranking UN officials and state
l e a d e r s. The short answer is that no military force in the
world has ever managed to “capture”a river basin and the
only full-fledged water war dates back over 4,500 years (pp.
18-19).“Water by its very nature is used to extinguish fires,
not to ignite them,” says Jordan’s Munther Haddadin, who
negotiated one of the most historic water agreements ever
signed (p. 22).
In the Middle East, thirsty nations have no choice but to cooperate. Despite the bloodshed
between Israelis and Pa l e s t i n i a n s, the two sides regularly meet to assure water supply in the We s t
Bank,while informal talks continue on a plan to share the region’s resources (pp. 22-25).
From the Danube (pp. 26-27) to the Nile (pp. 3 0 - 3 1 ) , mighty rivers have been used as pawns in the
Cold Wa r. Yet today, as countries like Egypt, Ethiopia or the republics of 
Central Asia shake free from this legacy, they are learning to trust one another by trading in the
economic benefits of wa t e r, l i ke hydroelectricity or irrigation supplies. Just by studying an aquifer
or a river, states like Namibia and
B o t s wana (pp. 3 4 - 3 6 ) , or India and
Bangladesh (pp. 3 2 - 3 3 ) , are shedding
t h e i r  
mutual suspicions. There are no magic
formulas in hydrodiplomacy, but slowly,
a new alliance is forming between
l a w y e r s, technicians and the people
closest to the resource (pp. 3 7 - 3 8 ) .
To g e t h e r, they are devising ways of
sharing the one natural resource that
we cannot replace, or live without.
Dossier concept and coordination by A m y
Otchet, UNESCO Courier journalist
WC o n t e n t s
1 8 S a b re - rattling among thirsty nations
Interview with Aaron Wo l f
2 0 A thirsty world
2 2 A Jo rdanian fire extinguisher
Amy Otchet
2 2 If common sense prevails 
Gershon Baskin and Nader El Khatib
2 6 A tale of two dams
György Moldova
2 8 The tide turns in Central A s i a
René Cagnat
3 0 Taming the Nile’s serpents
Khaled Dawoud
3 2 South A s i a : sharing the giants
Sanjoy Hazarika
3 4 The Kalahari’s underg round secre t s
Amy Otchet
3 7 Negotiating with nature :
the next ro u n d
Michèle Ferenz and Lawrence E. S u s s k i n d
STRIKING  
on trou
F O C U S
16 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
There is no denying the potential violence
surrounding the current water crisis.
About 40 percent of the world’s
population live in river basins shared by
two or more countries. These basins
comprise more then 50 percent of our
planet’s landmass. Only a fool would be
surprised to find competing claims over
w a t e r.Yet this interdependence does not
inevitably lead to war over water.
The “water war”thesis may actually
help create the very conflicts it seeks to
a v o i d . It is usually presented as a growing
number of people vying for less and less
water. However, the current crisis is not
about an absolute limit, but about
d i s t r i b u t i o n . For water to reach people at
the right place and time, a government
must have access to technology,
knowledge and money as well as the
institutional capacity to distribute this
essential resource.
The wealthy North cannot approach
the South by saying, “Conserve water!
D o n ’t develop the resource. D o n ’t use
water-saving technologies to grow food.
And for God’s sake, reduce population!”
This message may be based upon good
intentions but it reinforces a sense of  panic
and the notion of a zero-sum game, i n
which one side must compete against
another for water. It is a message to the
bullies,“You better get yours first!”
By focusing on looming water wars,
we fail to see water as a tool for
preventive diplomacy. For example, a
river basin forces us to rethink notions of
i n t e r -
d e p e n d e n c e. Instead of fearing it as
w e a k n e s s,we use it as a network to better
respond to the tests of nature. B y
exchanging information on events like a
flood or  drought, states can reduce the
potential danger.This flexibility addresses
the basic, almost primordial fear that has
driven humans to become toolmakers
and engineers: fear of uncertainty in a
harsh environment. While often
challenging the engineering mentality,
this same fear inspires environmental
c o n c e r n s. Somehow water forces us to go
d e e p e r, beyond adversarial relationships,
to confront what we really share—an
instinct for life.
Water is one of our enduring human
symbols of life, regeneration,purity and
h o p e. It is one of our potent links with the
s a c r e d , with nature and with our cultural
i n h e r i t a n c e. It offers a medium for a
global project that unifies humanity in a
single cause for peace, stability and
ecological sustainability. The water war
thesis takes us in the opposite direction.
It denies the universal acceptance of
water as a common good.
The water war thesis has raised
consciousness of the resource. But we
are in danger of crying wolf too often.
This thesis plays to human fears—fears of
c h a n g e, fears of deprivation, fears of
l i m i t s, fears of violence and indeed
primordial fears of death. It is time to
move beyond fear to action. L e a d e r s
need to rediscover and harness water’s
capacity to generate wealth, its potential
for multiple uses and reuse, its great
convening power, its ability to provide
the learning ground for building civic
culture.
Perhaps we need to “go back to the
future”and look at how water has been
used in order to redefine the goals of
water leadership. Water holds the
potential for both conflict and
cooperation—the choice is ours. ■
DON’T CRY W O L F
JEROME DELLI PRISCOLI
SENIOR POLICYANALYST AT THE INSTITUTE OF WATER RESOURCES, U.S. ARMY CORP OF ENGINEERS
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 17
 PEAC E
bled waters
O P I N I O N
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
INTERVIEW BY AMY OTCHET
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
S a b re - ra t t l i n g
among thirsty nations
Aaron Wolf*, an American geographer, dispels the scare-mongering
of a looming war over water by sifting through just about every related
conflict and treaty in history
Just about every journalist writing about water
will evoke the spectre of past and impending
w a rs over the re s o u rc e. You have searc h e d
for and analyzed every international water
a g reement signed and “ i n c i d e n t ” re p o r t e d .
W h e n
was the last time two states formally went to war
over water? 
The only recorded incident of an outright war
over water was 4,500 years ago between two
Mesopotamian city-states over the Ti g r i s - E u p h r a t e s
in the region we now call southern Iraq. Since then,
you find water exacerbating relations at the
international scale. But you also regularly fin d
hostile states—such as India and Pakistan or the
Israelis and Palestinians—resolving water confli c t s
even while disputes rage over other issues.
We also analyzed every
reported water incident
between two states that we
could find anywhere in the
w o r l d ’s 261 international river
basins in the past 50 years.Tw o -
thirds of a total of 1,800 e v e n t s
involved cooperation, l i k e
conducting joint scientific
investigations or signing over 150 water treaties.
Turning to the negative events, we found that
8 0 percent consisted of verbal threats and posturing
by state leaders, which was probably aimed at their
own internal constituents. In 1979, E g y p t i a n
president Anwar Sadat said:“The only matter that
could take Egypt to war again is water,” in reference
to the Nile. King Hussein allegedly said the same
thing for Jordan in 1990.
Yet in the last 50 years, there have only been
3 7 events in which people actually shot at each
other over water. Of those, 27 were between Israel
and Syria over the Jordan and Yarmouk rivers.
But critics argue that you cannot look to history to
p redict the future because of unprecedented stress on
increasingly scarce water supplies.
I cannot think of a worse case than the Tigris-
Euphrates or the Jordan River.All of these countries
have run out of water. They have the means to
divert their neighbour’s water and the enmity
between them couldn’t get much worse. Yet they
have all come up with agreements.
States have gone to war over oil,why not water? 
S t r a t e g i c a l l y, water wars don’t make sense.Yo u
cannot increase your water resources by going to
war with a neighbour unless you are willing to
capture the entire watershed, depopulate it and
not expect a tremendous retaliation.
But water has been used as a weapon and target in war.
Th a t ’s a totally different issue,which happens all
the time.During the Gulf Wa r, Iraq destroyed most
of Ku w a i t ’s desalination plants and the A l l i e d
coalition intentionally targeted Baghdad’s water
supply and sanitation system. Serbian engineers
reportedly shut down Pristina’s water system in
Kosovo before NATO arrived in 1999.
Yet you must distinguish between water as a
source of conflict, as a resource and as a weapon.
We’ve gone to war over oil. Yet you wouldn’t put
that event in the same category
as the military use of a flame
thrower or even napalm.
So where does this water- w a r
talk come from? 
A lot came from the post-
Cold War period, when the
Western military asked,“what
do we do now?” That is when this whole
environmental security movement took off. B y
around 1992, a lot of political scientists began writing
that resource scarcity in general was going to lead to
w a r f a r e. I t ’s very tempting to see water as a source of
c o n flict once you begin to understand what it means
to society and ecosystems. But in emphasizing the
value of the resource, these analysts overlooked the
subtleties involved.
You argue that water by its very nature induces co-
o p e ration between states. Can you give an example? 
The Oslo Accord between Israelis and Palestinians
actually came out of backroom talks among water
people from the region who met in Zurich in 1990—
I believe.The water people introduced their political
counterparts to one another and actually hatched out
the process, which led to the accord.
This kind of scenario happens regularly because
* Director of the
T r a n s b o u n d a r y
Freshwater Dispute
Database project
( h t t p : / / t e r r a . g e o. o r s t . e d u )
and associate professor at
Oregon State University
You cannot increase
your water resources
by going to war
with a neighbour
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 19
water naturally flows into other realms. States along
the Nile began by talking about water and are now
working towards an agreement that includes roads,
electricity and other infrastructure (see pp. 30-31).
You maintain that the “red flag” for international
water is not water scarcity but one country’s attempt
to dominate an international river. Most of these
c o n flicts usually revolve around plans to build a
major dam. But this kind of project generally re q u i re s
assistance from organizations like the World Bank,
which evaluate proposals according to enviro n m e n t a l
and ethical criteria. By pulling the purse strings, c a n ’ t
these organizations prevent water conflicts fro m
arising? 
What you’re suggesting has been the case. But
as more private capital takes over investment in
these projects, the ethical and environmental
criteria of the development banks is no longer an
i s s u e. Tu r k e y, for example, is diverting private
a n d public capital to fund one of the most content-
ious projects, known as GAP, which envisages the
construction of 22 dams and 19 power plants on
the Tigris-Euphrates and its tributaries.The same is
true for the Narmada dam in India and China’s
Three Gorges project.
The T i g r i s - E u p h rates is regularly cited as a fla s h p o i n t
for a possible war. How can anyone induce Turkey,
probably the most powerful state in the region,not
to pursue its own interests to the detriment of its
downstream neighbours, Iraq and Syria? 
Everybody keeps talking about the Ti g r i s -
Euphrates as a potential fla s h p o i n t ,but what’s really
interesting is that in 1991, NATO actually asked
Turkey to shut the flow of the Euphrates towards
I r a q . But the government refused and basically
s a i d ,“ You can use our air space and bases to bomb
Iraq,but we won’t cut off their water.”
Since the 1970s, Tu r k e y, Syria and Iraq have
had an implicit agreement,which Turkey continued
to respect even while building the dams.And despite
the rhetoric, Syria and Iraq both recognize that
they benefit from those dams because they even out
the river’s flow and extend their farmers’ growing
s e a s o n . Turkey wants to be seen as a fair, g o o d
neighbour for several reasons, including NATO
pressure as an ally, internal politics and attempts to
join the European Union. The difficulty lies in
making the implicit agreements explicit.
Water professionals maintain that you have to
manage a river basin as a whole. But multilatera l
water treaties must be a nightmare to negotiate.
Which are more effective—multilateral or bilateral
agreements? 
The more people in the room, the more diffic u l t
it is to reach an agreement, especially when you
are dealing with a country’s sovereignty. Take the
Jordan River as an example:Syria and Jordan have
an agreement, Jordan and Israel have an agreement,
Israel and Palestinians have an agreement—several
sets of bilateral agreements for a multilateral basin
which is managed fairly effic i e n t l y, although the
Palestinians will eventually claim and probably get
greater water rights.
A new way of solving water confli c t s, some economists
argue, is to set up an international water market.But
then again, we can look to the recent conflict in which
the U.S. has argued that Canada must sell its water
re s o u rces under the terms of the North American Fre e
Trade A g reement—a proposition that Canada re j e c t s.
What is the value of treating water as an economic
resource when trying to resolve a conflict?
Economists can highlight and quantify the
benefits flowing from water, like hydroelectricity,
and help build what we call a “baskets of benefit s.”
For example, the U. S. and Canada have an
agreement in which the U. S. has flood control dams
within Canadian territory. The U. S. pays Canada
for that benefit . It is generally easier and more
equitable to allocate the benefits than the water
itself.
Economists also remind us of the need to recover
the cost of water delivery, treatment,storage and so
o n .But we’re often pushed to think in terms of water
markets—buying and selling water as a commodity
even though this has never happened internationally
in a practical sense.As someone who is committed to
water emotionally, aesthetically, religiously and for
ecosystems, I am reluctant to think of water as just
another economic good. ■
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
Let not a simple
drop of water
that falls on
the land go
into the sea
without serving
the people.
Parakkama-Bahu I,
King of Sri Lanka
(1153-1186)
A potential flashpoint? Turkey’s GAP dam project.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
A thirsty world
The population is not only growing but using more water, even though
the world’s total supply remains the same. This scarcity could put a major
brake on the world’s development this century
T A K I N G  S T O C K  T O  B E T T E R  M O V E  A H E A D
Nearly ten years have passed since the Rio Earth Summit of
1992 alerted the world to the importance of “water”on the
international development agenda. Since then, assessments of
global water resources indicate that water scarcity will increase
dramatically during the next decades, with a disproportionate
effect on developing countries. Demand is growing,and with it,
competition among different users. Unless we change the way we
think about and manage our water resources, both people and
planet could suffer irreparable damage.A l r e a d y, the lives and well-
being of millions of people are constrained by water.
The World Water Assessment Programme (WWAP)—established
in 2000 and endorsed by 23 United Nations agencies with a stake
in water—is part of the global effort to seek integrated
approaches and sustainable solutions to human development
problems. Hosted at UNESCO, it responds to concerns expressed by
the international community at the World Water Forum in The
Hague (2000), and builds on the challenges  identified in the
Ministerial Declaration that followed.
A key component of the project will include the World Water
Development Report, which will not only assess the state of the
world’s water resources but monitor the progress in meeting its
growing demand. The first edition of the report will be published
in 2003.
Within the WWAP framework, a project has recently been
launched to help dispel the myth that increasing water stress
will inevitably lead to international conflicts or potential
“ fla s h p o i n t s,” namely along the world’s
261 international river basins “ s h a r e d ” by 145 countries.
Although water offers potential for conflict,it also provides a
powerful tool for cooperation. Hence the title of the new PPCP
project: From Potential Conflict to Cooperation Potential. A
series of studies, publications and educational activities will
focus on the social,cultural,scientific and political complexities
involved in transboundary water resources. ■
+ …
http://www.unesco.org/water/wwap
Links to all UN partner agencies are found under “partners”on
the WWAP home page.
A brochure about the Programme and the World Water
Development Report is also available on-line in English, French,
Spanish,Russian,Arabic and Chinese.
Physical scarcity
Economic scarcity
Little or no scarcity
Not estimated Indicates countries that will import more
than 10 percent of their cereal consumption in 2025
If states substantially invest in wa t e r-related infrastructure
and management policies, we can expect the projections
presented below.
Yet despite these efforts, many countries will still face
“physical water scarcity in 2025:” their water needs will
outstrip supplies no matter what measures are take n .O t h e r s
will be faced with “economic water scarcity:”they will lack
the financial and institutional capacity required to increase
their water supplies by 25 percent.
La pénurie d’eau en 2025.Projected water scarcity in 2025.
20 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 21
Evolution de la consommation mondiale d’eau par secteur d’activité,en km3.Dyna ics of water use by secto  in km3.
6,000
5,000
4,000
3,000
2,000
1,000
0
1900 1940 1950 1960 1970 1980 1990 1995 2000 2010 2025
Total Agriculture Industry Municipal
Evolution du volume d’eau douce disponible par habitant et par an, en milliers de m3.Global water availability per person i  million m3.
20
15
10
5
0
1950 1960 1970 1980 1990 1995 2000 2010 2025
Répartition de la population mondiale, en 1995 et en 2025,selon les quantités annuelles
d’eau douce renouvelable, disponibles par habitant,en m3.
Global annual re ewabl  water supply per p rson in 1995
and projection  f r 2025 in m3.
60%
50%
40%
30%
20%
10%
0%
1995 2025
500 m3 500–1,000 m3 1,000–1,700 m3 1,700 m3 Unknown
Since 1900, w o r l d
population has doubled yet the
amount of fresh water used has
increased more than six-fold.
Agriculture is by far the largest
consumer of wa t e r, m o s t l y
because of the spread of
irrigation. Two-thirds of all the
water consumed in the world
goes to farming, a share
expected to shrink only slightly
by 2025. More effic i e n t
irrigation techniques are clearly
the first and crucial step to
reducing water use.
Today, there is about 6,800
m3 of water available per
person on a yearly basis. I f
current trends continue, o n l y
4,800 m3 will be available in
2 0 2 5 . This is an optimistic
calculation because it is based
upon estimates of all the water
flowing in rivers after
e vaporation and infiltration into
the ground. It does not take into
account the minimum required
to maintain river ecosystems,
for example. Nor does it reflect
the difficulty in accessing all of
this water or its extremely
unequal distribution.
When per capita wa t e r
supply is less than 1,700 m3 per
y e a r, an area suffers from
“water stress”and is subject to
frequent water shortages. I n
many of these areas today,
water supply is actually less
than 1,000 m3 per capita which
causes serious problems for
food production and economic
development. Today, 2.3 billion
people live in wa t e r- s t r e s s e d
a r e a s. If current trends continue,
water stress will affect 3.5
billion—or 48 percent of the
world’s projected population—
in 2025.
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
A
s the violence between Israelis and
Palestinians spirals and cooperation is
considered an act of treason, both sides
continue to work together on a single issue:
w a t e r. In Fe b r u a r y, six months after the
intifada erupted, Israel and the Palestinian Au t h o r i t y
( PA) jointly called upon their people to keep water
and wastewater infrastructure out of the cycle of
d e s t r u c t i o n .The reason is simple:both of their systems
are intertwined.
The Israeli-Palestinian Joint Water Committee,
set up under the Oslo A g r e e m e n t s, is probably the
only common framework to survive the past year.
Despite sealed borders and gunfir e, the committee
regularly meets to deliver water in the West Bank,
where many wells and springs have gone dry,e s p e c i a l l y
as the current drought scorches a second year. Talks
and action revolve around practical issues—repairing
pipes or delivering chlorine. Yet plans to construct
new wells, which the Palestinians desperately need
GERSHON BASKIN AND NADER EL KHATIB
RESPECTIVELY CO-DIRECTOR OFTHE ISRAEL/PALESTINE CENTERFOR RESEARCHAND INFORMATIONAND DIRECTOR OFTHE BETHLEHEM-BASEDWATER ENVIRONMENT
DEVELOPMENT ORGANIZATION
If common sense p r e va i l s
Despite sealed borders and gunfire, Israeli and Palestinian experts
continue to meet on the sidelines in an attempt to hammer out
a way of sharing their blue gold
22 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
AMY OTCHET 
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
A Jordanian
fire ex t i n g u i s h e r
An insider’s view on one of the most historic water agreements ever
signed—the deal between Israel and Jordan
B
y parking his purple 1979 Caprice further
upstream he diverted the attention of the
Israeli patrols on the opposite bank of the
Ya r m o u k . Slowly he made his way along the
Jordanian side of the river, until he reached
a large eucalyptus tree where a dozen men waited with
r o p e s, axes and spades. Barely speaking, they lowered
him down the six metres to the water’s edge, b e f o r e
following him, one by one. “Give me that axe,”he told
the crew leader. “In the name of God, the Merciful and
Most compassionate,” he said in a low voice, b e f o r e
striking deep into the enemy—a sandbar over 20 metres
wide which had been diverting part of Jo r d a n ’s water
share to Israel. It was 1984, ten years before the two
states would sign a peace treaty that included one of the
w o r l d ’s most famous water-sharing agreements. Th e
man who played a key role in masterminding it also led
that expedition.
“ Whenever I think back on it, I choke,” s a y s
Munther Haddadin, former water minister of Jo r d a n .
While clearly proud of his axe-wielding adventure,
Haddadin doesn’t recommend it as a standard
negotiating technique. I n s t e a d , the civil engineer with
a penchant for international law offers more subtle,y e t
no less demanding lessons learned from hammering
out the historic water treaty with Israel.
“ The trick is to try to transform the entire show into
a positive sum game, so that both sides view themselves
as winners,” he says. For example,“a major concession
The Jordan River:breaking down defenses.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 23
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
on our part was the recognition of Israel. I had to
make the Israelis feel secure but at the same time use
this weakness as a card in my sleeve.”
Tales of poisoning
As Haddadin explains, all of the states along the
Jordan River had agreed to their rightful share of water
in a plan drawn up with the assistance of an American
diplomat in 1955. H o w e v e r, the technical resolution
w a s n ’t translated into a political accord because it
would entail tacit Arab recognition of the state of
I s r a e l . Once Egypt broke this taboo in 1979, I s r a e l
was anxious to continue the peace process and turned
to Jordan.To some extent,water served as a bridge in
opening discussions between the two states:a drought-
stricken Jordan was losing part of its rightful share of
the Yarmouk River to Syria and Israel.
At fir s t , Haddadin kept contact to a minimum,
only discussing immediate technical problems, l i k e
the famous sandbar, under the auspices of the United
Nations Truce Supervision Organization.With military
escorts looking on, Haddadin and his Israeli
counterpart would meet midstream, standing in two
feet of the river’s water.S l o w l y, they got in the habit of
pulling up sandbags to talk at a makeshift picnic table
along the Yarmouk.But it wasn’t until 1991 that the
formal peace process began and Haddadin began
hammering out major water-sharing proposals.
Whether meeting in a hotel lobby in a foreign
capital or the garden of Jo r d a n ’s Crown Prince,“ a l w a y s
avoid a stand-off,”says Haddadin.When Israelis balked
at his demands for more water, he would “beat around
the bush”on economic grounds. “Let us see who can
afford to increase their supply by pumping or
desalinating water,”he would ask in order to highlight
the gap in per capita income between the two countries.
“Do you think you will live in peace when your
neighbour is starving?”
During the three years it took to forge a deal,
Haddadin earned a reputation as a staunch negotiator
and a hothead capable of exploding unexpectedly,w h i c h
he laughs off as a “ s k i l l ” to destabilize his opponents.B u t
as he notes, you cannot just seal a deal,you have to sell
it. With kid gloves, he informed his fellow officials that
they didn’t own the country’s namesake and would have
to share the water of the Jordan River Basin. Despite
personal attacks (namely false rumours that his
American wife was Je w i s h ) , Haddadin proudly watched
the signing of the peace treaty with its water annex in
1994 and later became minister of water and irrigation.
But Haddadin would pay for this glory in 1998,
when residents of West Amman found cloudy water
running through their taps after a treatment plant
failed to handle high levels of algae.The water didn’t
pose a serious health threat but it did spread a noxious
mix of nationalism and fear,as tales of Israeli poisoning
spread through the media and ordinary grapevines.
“The panic was orchestrated from within Jordan to
bring down the government,” says Haddadin, w h o
decided to resign as minister. Since then,he has gone
on to set the record straight in his new book.* While
highlighting his own role, the real heroes are the
Yarmouk and Jordan Rivers. In the words of Haddadin:
“ Water by its very nature, is used to extinguish fir e s, n o t
to ignite them.” ■
*Diplomacy on the Jo rdan—International Conflict and Pe a c e f u l
Resolution (Kluwer Academic Publishers,O c t .2 0 0 1 )
and were promised in Oslo, have been abandoned.
The violence of the past year has killed the formal
discussions on redistributing water supplies and
recognizing Palestinian sovereign rights over natural
r e s o u r c e s.The Israeli government no longer considers
water to be a technical issue but a matter of national
s e c u r i t y.According to the hawks, I s r a e l ’s very existence
depends upon military and political control of the
Palestinian Te r r i t o r i e s, especially the West Bank which
provides for 25 percent of Israeli water needs.
Talking dollars
and cents
This obsession with security is certainly not new in
I s r a e l . Even before the intifada, environmental issues
were cast as threats, sold to the public as “ w a t e r
s e c u r i t y ” or “food security.” The Western press in
particular has towed this line, peddling stories about
water inevitably killing prospects for peace. Yet the
truth of the matter is that hydrologists and civil
engineers on both sides have been steadily developing
possible long-term agreements. While formal
discussions of these plans are now taboo, technicians
and government experts from across the region are
continuing to meet quietly, beyond the reach of hawks
on all sides. Here is an outline of a plan we have in
mind.
First a bit of background.Palestinians each have
about 85 cubic metres per year for all of their needs—
d o m e s t i c, industry and agriculture.Average use among
Israelis is 447 cubic metres per year. In the West Bank,
about 25 percent of the population doesn’t have
running water, even though this area is relatively rich
in groundwater thanks to the Mountain A q u i f e r, f r o m
which  Israel pumps about 85 percent of its yield. H e r e
lies the heart of the dispute.
The famous Mountain Aquifer actually consists
of three different ones—situated in the east, n o r t h w e s t
and west of the mountain.The media tends to paint the
Eastern Aquifer as a political minefie l d ,yet the path to
resolution is far from tortuous. The Palestinians can
rightfully claim absolute sovereignty over the aquifer
JORDAN
Length: 322 km
Source: Mount Hermon
Mouth: Dead Sea
Countries: Israel,Jordan,
Lebanon, Palestinian
Territories, Syria
YARMOUK
Length: 80 km
Source: Jordan-Syria border
Mouth: Confluence with the
Jordan River
Countries: Israel,Jordan,Syria
RIVER FLOWS
I S R A E L
L E B A N O N
Y a r m o u k
J
J o r
d a n
JERUSALEM AMMAN
DAMASCUS
D E A D  S E A
W E S T
B A N K
M O U N T A I N  A Q U I F E R
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
which lies entirely within their territory. Byinstalling
pumps after 1967,Israel has apparently contravened
international rules concerning military occupation.
The decision to give up this aquifer is not as painful as
it might seem. It is the poorest of the three in terms of
water quantity and quality.
The rest is not so clear- c u t , as seen with the We s t e r n
Aquifer, the largest of the three.About 80 percent of
the recharge basin—the area in which rain and streams
trickle down into the aquifer—lies in Palestine.
H o w e v e r, that water naturally
flows underground into Israel,
where most of it is pumped.
Palestinians claim that they
own the water because it
originates in their territory. A t
the same time,Israelis invoke the
cardinal international right of
historic use—they were the first
to tap into and develop this
source about 80 years ago through an agreement with
the British Mandate (in a concession to a Je w i s h
contractor).
Debates over water rights generally turn in circles.
While there is clearly a need to recognize both sides’
sovereign rights to natural resources, i n t e r n a t i o n a l
law and common sense directs us to find a “ r e a s o n a b l e
and equitable” use of the water.How do you determine
a fair deal? You cannot quantify a right to water, but
you can calculate the need for it.
Everyone—Palestinians and Israelis—should be
entitled to a minimum of 100 metres3 per year for
domestic and industrial use. To do this, Israel would
have to reallocate  100 to 200 more million metres3 o f
water each year to Palestinians. No state leader wants
to give up control over a resource, especially one so
precious and politically explosive as water. But there
is another way of evaluating the trade-off: in dollars and
cents.
Water equals money. Each cubic metre of water in
Israel is worth an estimated $0.20/m3. So the water in
dispute amounts to between $20-40 million a year—or
about 0.05 percent of Israeli GDP. This isn’t worth
fighting over. It is money well spent.
The economic value of water is obviously not new
in the Middle East. For years,
thirsty governments have been
trading in “virtual water”—
economists actually calculate the
water it takes to grow fruit and
v e g e t a b l e s. So by importing
tomatoes and oranges, f o r
e x a m p l e, governments are
actually buying cheap, b i o -
degradable packets of water. I t ’s
a lot easier and cheaper to import a tonne of fruit and
vegetables than the water it takes to grow it.
We want to expand this trade.To begin with, I s r a e l i
farmers can no longer earn a living by feeding their
c o u n t r y, which is accustomed to a costly We s t e r n
l i f e s t y l e. Not so for the Palestinians. Both Israel and the
Palestinian Authority currently allocate about 80
percent of their respective water supplies to
agriculture. In Israel, farmers make up about three
percent of the labour force and contribute three
percent of the GDP. In Gaza and the West Bank, a
third of workers depend upon agriculture, w h i c h
accounts for about a third of the GDP. So it is no
surprise to find that Israel buys the entire surplus
from farms in the West Bank and Gaza, p r o v i d i n g
Can this trade expand? Farmers setting up irrigation for agriculture in Jiftlik Valley, near Nablus.
For years, thirsty 
governments
in the Middle East
have been trading in
“virtual water”
If you listen to
water, learn its
language, then
water will bring
you knowledge
of all beings and
living things.
Yves Thériault, Canadian
writer (1915-1983)
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 25
for one-twelfth of the country’s fresh fruit and
vegetable needs. We suggest that they both use this
trend to their advantage and that of their neighbour,
Jordan.
Over the next 10 to 15 years, all three parties
should agree to increase the supply of irrigation water
in Palestine and Jordan.There are several options for
finding the extra water within the Jordan Va l l e y : a
redistribution of supplies from the Mountain A q u i f e r
and the Jordan River. R a i n - h a r v e s t i n g, t r e a t e d
wastewater and improved infrastructure (40 percent of
water is lost to leaky pipes in some Palestinian
m u n i c i p a l i t i e s ) . New sources further afield might also
open up. For example, Lebanon might sell water from
the Litani River which could be stored in Lake Ti b e r i a s.
The new Unity Dam,under construction by Jordan and
Syria,also holds potential.
Desalination: the saviour?
No one loses in this proposal. Palestinians and
Jordanians see a steady increase in the number of
agricultural jobs at a time of staggering unemployment.
They also gain a guaranteed market for crops and by
cultivating more land, Palestinian farmers lay the seeds
for new settlements. We are not suggesting that
Palestine base its economy on agriculture in the long-
term.No country in the Middle East can afford to do
so financially or environmentally. But after decades of
occupation,Palestinians cannot be expected to leap-
frog economically.
Despite Israel’s cultural attachment “to making the
desert bloom,” the state will have to cut back on
f a r m i n g. By allocating more water to Palestinians and
Jo r d a n , it would not only gain a secure source of cheap
fresh food, but the country’s hi-tech industry would
grow by selling irrigation technologies as well as high-
profit seeds, fertilizers and pesticides.
Fi n a l l y, the international community could
“ r e w a r d ” such a regional plan by setting up an
international fund for research and development in
water desalination. For this is clearly our most likely
option in the very near future.
In the next 20 to 30 years, the Israeli and Palestinian
populations are expected to double as their respective
diasporas immigrate to the region, especially with
formal recognition of a Palestinian state. Every drop
of fresh water will be required to fulfill domestic needs.
Desalination will be the saviour. Today the process
costs about $0.65/m3, which is still far too expensive,
especially for agriculture. (In the Middle East, a cubic
metre used for irrigation brings an economic return of
just $0.50 to $1.00).Yet it is still cheaper than importing
from the region’s hydrological baron,Tu r k e y,which has
proposed constructing a “peace pipeline”to deliver and
sell its blue gold at
$0.95/m3.
This proposal may appear to be a naïve attempt to
deny the escalating violence.Yet from where we stand,
it would be absurd and even criminal to give up on our
work.In the very near future, technicians from both
sides and beyond will be meeting outside the region to
continue to informally discuss and refine this proposal.
Contrary to popular belief,water in the Middle East is
not a source of war, but ingenuity. ■
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
Based upon a new report by B’Tselem—the Israeli Center for Human Rights in
the Occupied Territories—released in July 2001.  
In the West Bank, 218 villages—home to about 200,000 people—are not
connected to a single water network. This is why just about every yard in the
area has a cistern where families store the rain water they have collected from
the rooftops of their homes. However, they can usually only live from supplies
during the rainy season between November and March.
In the summer months and sometimes even the winter, most residents have no
choice but to buy water from vendors who own private tanke r s. Even villages with
running water often rely on this commerce because of the irregular supply
during dry months. The owners of the tankers buy most of the water from
Palestinian municipal water networks and the rest from Israeli settlements and
Palestinian-owned private agricultural wells (which are not subject to any
quality control).
This water market is completely unregulated—“market forces” alone set the
p r i c e s.While a household connected to a water network will pay the equiva l e n t
of about a dollar per metre3 , a vendor will charge between $3.50 and $9.50 for
the same amount.This financial burden is like a noose around the neck of many
f a m i l i e s, who have lost their primary source of income since the intifada.1
According to B’Tselem, some village residents can no longer purchase water from
the tanke r s. In the summer, the women and children of these families cross military
checkpoints and blocked roads to fill bottles and jerrycans with water from nearby
springs.
The West Bank contains 114 springs, most of which are primarily used for
irrigation.The most bountiful springs lie in the Nablus and Jericho districts (52
s p r i n g s ) .The others are generally quite poor, especially given the current drought.
For example, the Auja spring,north of Jericho, has totally dried up over the last
three years. Despite decreasing rainfall, an Israeli well continues to pump the
aquifer that feeds the spring for the benefit of nearby Israeli settlements. The
situation has devastated Palestinian agriculture in Al Auga,whose farmers used
to rely upon the spring for irrigation water.
In general, the springs are not just poor in terms of quantity but also quality.Th e
Palestinian Authority does not control the wa t e r, despite the high risk of pollution
by sewage from nearby towns and villages as well as from Israeli settlements and
industrial zones.The very source of a spring can be at risk as the pesticides and
fertilizers used by local farmers seep into the ground. ■
1. According to the Palestinian Central Bureau of Statistics, in the first quarter
of 2001, the median income of a household in the Occupied Territories fell
by 48 percent, unemployment increased from 11 percent before the intifada
to 38 percent, and the percentage of families living in poverty increased to
64 percent, compared to 21 percent before the intifada.  
THE DEHYDRATED WEST BA N K
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
GYÖRGY MOLDOVA
ONEOF HUNGARY’S BESTSELLING AUTHORS, WHOSE SERIOUSWORKSINCLUDE “THE DANUBE IS BURNING”
A tale of two dams
An author renowned for his sense of humour takes a grim view
of a political row between his native Hungary and Slovakia in which
the Danube is held hostage
W
e may thank rivers for life: b r i n g i n g
water to drink, to nourish our fie l d s
and to carry our boats. There is only
one problem: they are exceptionally
suited to forming borders. Instead of
uniting people bound for a common destiny, s u s p i c i o u s
n a t i o n s, often incited by clashing politics, glare at each
other like wolves from opposing shores. I have seen
such venom flowing along the Danube between Hungary
and Slovakia.
The Danube has always been a tempestuous force,
bringing alternating waves of calamity.Either it was too
a b u n d a n t , forcing entire villages to seek higher
ground,or it was too feeble, leaving fields to wither
and causing a sudden halt to navigation.
The Roman emperors Tiberius and Trajan were
the first to hire civil engineers to devise ways of
protecting their banks from the fickle Danube. Many
would follow their example, but it was not before the
20th century that the technicians would muster the
power and tools to tame the river.
By 1951, serious plans were underway to build a
series of dams along the Danube in Hungary and
C z e c h o s l o v a k i a .The Soviet Union was anxious to alter
the river’s shallow reaches which were hampering the
shipment of its goods in Eastern Europe.At that time,
few questioned the wisdom of “correcting mother
n a t u r e ”and it was considered a scientifically proven fact
that a river the size of the Danube required not just one
dam,but several.Otherwise, sediments would collect
and disrupt navigation and damage embankments,
causing bridges to collapse. It would take another
2 0 years to iron out the technical and financial
arrangements but in September 1977,the Republic of
Hungary and the Czechoslovak Socialist Republic
signed a now infamous treaty to build the Gabcikovo-
Nagymaros dam system.
Grinding the axe
of the opposition
The region was clearly suffering. Au t h o r i t i e s
recorded more than 100 days of shallow waters a year,
which damaged the wild flora and left several hundred
ships stranded along a 250-kilometre stretch of the
r i v e r. While the project was originally intended to
improve navigation, it grew to include hydroelectricity
as the oil shocks of the 1970s intensified.
A large reservoir would be built at Dunakiliti,
which straddled both countries. From there, a 17-km
canal would divert 90 to 95 percent of the Danube’s flo w
to a hydroelectric dam and powerplant in Gabcikovo
in Czechoslovakia. About 100 km downstream in
Hungary at Nagymaros, another power station and
dam would even the river’s flow.
Construction began in 1978 based upon plans drawn
up by world-famous Hungarian,Slovak and Austrian
water experts,against whom accusations of a technical
nature could hardly have been raised—not so against
their political inclinations, as it was later revealed.
By the end of the 1980s, the powers waiting to
relieve the socialist system of Eastern Europe lurked in
the shadows. Yet they could hardly demand the
departure of the occupying Soviet army, or indeed  a
multi-party system. I n s t e a d , they demonstrated on
environmental grounds and found an obvious target in
the ongoing construction of the Gabcikovo-Nagymaros
d a m s. It was like a chink in the system’s wall into which
the opposition could wedge its demolition axe, held at
the ready.
Protestors marched en masse down the streets of
Budapest and along the banks beside Nagymaros.
Anybody who had anything to do with the project was
declared a Stalinist, or worse, a traitor to his country.A s
public pressure intensifie d , the Hungarian government
decided to suspend the half-finished construction.Th e
culmination came in 1990 when the right-wing
government took power and unilaterally cancelled the
treaty.
S L O V A K I A
H U N G A R Y
BUDAPEST
BRATISLAVA
Dunakiliti dam
Gabcikovo barrage
Nagymaros barrage
D a n u b e
DANUBE
Length: 2,850 km
Source: Confluence of the
Breg and Brigach rivers in the
Black Forest
Mouth: Black Sea
Countries: Austria,Bulgaria,
Croatia,Germany, Hungary,
Romania,Slovakia,Ukraine,
Yugoslavia
Population around the river
basin: 85 million
RIVER FLOWS
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
October 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 27
But the Czechoslovak side paid no heed to the
Hungarians and carried on with the work further
u p s t r e a m .The authorities unilaterally decided to divert
a 25-kilometre stretch of the Danube, which served as
part of the border between the two countries, into its
own territory,where another dam was built to replace
the one intended for Hungary.Gabcikovo would not be
as powerful as planned,but it would be operational.
Fish in the mud
Protest marches similar to those in
Hungary had no effect.History was not
on the demonstrators’ side. A s
Czechoslovakia divided into two parts,
Slovakia came to see Gabcikovo as the
symbol of their independent state, born in
1993.
By the end of October 1992, t h e
Danube was diverted and the main
channel stretching across Hungarian
territory suddenly lost 90 to 95 percent of
its water. Signs indicating the river’s water
level were left standing on dry land.
Groundwater levels in surrounding areas
dropped by two or three metres days after
the Danube stopped feeding its streams.
Fish were trapped in the old basin, left to
asphyxiate in the mud.
The Hungarians could not believe
the drama unfolding before them.
Extremist elements spoke of blowing up
the obstructing dam. Fo r t u n a t e l y, t h i s
threat was soon replaced by negotiations
fostered by the European Community,
which was already panicked by
bloodshed in the Balkans. Both sides sat
down to talk, yet the balance of power was skewed in
S l o v a k i a ’s favour.With firm control of the lion’s share
of the river’s water supply and energy output, it took
little notice of Hungarian wishes. In April 1993, t h e
dispute was submitted to the International Court of
Justice in The Hague.
In 1994, the Socialists came back into power in
Hungary but could hardly back out of the court case,
which was hailed as a landmark:for the first time, the
court would rule over an environmental dispute. But
this case was about politics, not water.And so the court
handed down an ambiguous decision in 1997, which
both parties could interpret to their advantage. Th e
1977 treaty was still valid,according to the ruling, but
each side was at fault for acting unilaterally—Hungary
for pulling out and Slovakia for continuing with the
c o n s t r u c t i o n . They were called upon to negotiate in
good faith. Even though the court had no way of
enforcing its ruling, both sides returned to the
negotiating table.Anxious to join the European Union,
the two governments wanted to show their wealthy
Western neighbours that they could resolve their
disputes in a civilized manner.The outline of a mutually
acceptable agreement was drawn up to finally complete
the project and resolve key environmental concerns.
Once again, politics intervened. Hungary’s right-
wing opposition joined forces with the “ s t o r m i n g ”
Greens and together they organized mass
d e m o n s t r a t i o n s.For a second time in less than a decade,
they managed to use the same weapons to force the
government to back down. Yet this time, the Socialist
government was keeling before the final deathblow of
parliamentary elections in 1998.
Weak resolve
In their manifesto, the right-wing elements at the
helm of the new government promised to remedy the
Danube. Yet three and a half years later, not a single
worthy step has been taken. Hungary has however,
been spending millions of dollars to take down the
half-built dam and might be forced to spend millions
more to compensate Slovakia for pulling out of the
d e a l . There is talk of forming more committees or
returning to the International Court of Justice—a sure
sign that both countries are still not committed to
resolving the situation.Their true colours will inevitably
show soon—both will hold parliamentary elections in
2002.
Take a stroll along the two banks of the Danubian
basin today and you will see that the Gabcikovo region
in Slovakia is thriving, while on the Hungarian side, t h e
land which was supposed to store water has been
overrun by weeds. And the Danube? The Danube
carries not water, it carries politics, dirty politics. ■
Hand in hand: protestors around the Gabcikovo dam region.
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
RENÉ CAGNAT
AUTHOR OF LE MILIEU DESEMPIRES (LAFFONT, PARIS, 1981), LA RUMEUR DESSTEPPES (PAYOT, PARIS, 1999)
AND A BOOK OF PHOTOS, VISIONS D’UNFAMILIER DES STEPPES (TRANSBORÉAL, PARIS)
The tide turns
in Central A s i a
Geography, the Soviet legacy and population growth are forcing
the five countries of Central Asia to cooperate closely in a region where
water is still used as a weapon
L
ast winter, as usual, I found myself
without gas in my apartment in Bishkek,
the capital of Kyrgyzstan, and I cursed
neighbouring Uzbekistan for cutting it
off at the worst possible moment. Once
a g a i n , I was going to freeze for weeks on end.
What I didn’t know was that this time, Ky r g y z s t a n
was readying to hit back by using “the weapon of
water”as never before.
The Kirghiz simply opened the flood-gates of
their dam at To k h t o g u l , which supplies water to
both Uzbekistan and Kazakhstan via the Syrdaria
r i v e r.Their excuse was that they had to feed their
hydro-electric power stations to make up for the
gas that had been cut off. But the Kirghiz meant
b u s i n e s s. The flood-waters swept away the
embankments in Uzbekistan’s Ferghana valley,
where people did not expect nearly so much water
in the winter. Further north the river was blocked
with ice, so the surge of water was diverted as it is
every winter towards the Aidarkul Basin.
This has been going on for three decades, w i t h
more water each year. Greater use of hydro-
electricity in winter means the power stations
discharge a lot of waste water downstream.As a
r e s u l t , the basin, which was once a desert, h a s
turned into a huge and useless lake that is
2 0 0 kilometres long and 30 km wide, and which
contains 16 k m3 of water that would otherwise
have flowed into the Aral Sea, where it is badly
n e e d e d .1
Trading off
water and gas
This year’s “ r e v e n g e ” flooding was the biggest
e v e r. It lasted two weeks, yet drew only a few
complaints from the Uzbeks.The Kirghiz replied,
tongue in cheek, that after releasing so much
water they could no longer guarantee a supply in
the summer. The response from Ta s h k e n t , t h e
Uzbek capital, was swift. Five days later, the two
countries sat down to negotiate. Ten days after
t h a t , I had gas in my kitchen again.
The media was pessimistic about the talks.
But on July 12, it was announced that “the water
problem has been solved.” The deputy prime
ministers of Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan and
Uzbekistan signed an agreement for the “ s e n s i b l e
use of water and energy resources.” Even though
this “ u n d e r s t a n d i n g ” was limited to a year’s
duration and was drawn up by purely technocratic
m i n i s t r i e s, it opened the door to multilateral
exchanges instead of the previously annual
bilateral accords. In exchange for electricity and
water from Ky r g y z s t a n , the Kazakhs will provide
400,000 tonnes of coal and the Uzbeks an
undisclosed quantity of gas.
But the big event came a few days later.A law
published in Bishkek on July 29 about “the inter-
governmental use of water resources, dams and
other water-related installations” took the region
into a whole new era. Modelled on the 1992 Dublin
D e c l a r a t i o n , the law stated that “water has an
economic value in all its competing uses and should
In Kazakhstan, a ship stranded on the dying Aral Sea.
28 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
be recognized as an economic good.”
From now on, so long as the Kirghiz can get
their neighbours to respect the agreement, t h e
other countries will have to pay not just for the
water—making it a real commercial product—but
also for maintenance of installations and for the
hydraulic technology. If the region’s economic
powers react intelligently, there will be a
crackdown on wasting water—a major revolution
that could put an end to the sort of Soviet-era
vices that still taint the behaviour of ordinary
p e o p l e.
Absence of meters and
availability of free water for
irrigation has led to enormous
wastage in both town and
c o u n t r y. General inertia and
the abundance of water
produced by giant Soviet
installations have killed off
the art of irrigation learnt
over centuries.When water is
p r o v i d e d , it is done so only in
huge quantities that harm
both vegetation and people.
Parched soil becomes marshland.Thirsty people
are soon plagued by mosquitoes. But nobody
complains or criticizes.
The same apathy mixed with irresponsibility—
rooted in people’s attitudes for decades—has
produced utterly inadequate installations from
one end of the water supply chain to the other.
Water leaks from dams and canals. The much-
vaunted Turkmen canal has no concrete
f o u n d a t i o n , and so loses as much water in the
Karakum Desert it crosses as it provides for local
i r r i g a t i o n . Excess irrigation water is never drained,
so the landscape in Central Asia is dotted with
stretches of waste water or marshland, while at a
lower altitude, the starved Aral Sea is slowly
d y i n g. But the new law could put an end to this
scandalous history of waste.
A historic
w e a p o n
Will the people of Central Asia rally to
support it? Individually yes, collectively only
m a y b e. But their rulers must realize the danger
and take action, or else water will become a
powerful weapon in a region where cities were
once swept away because an enemy—Genghis
Khan—diverted rivers towards them, and oases
were destroyed because an invader—
Tamerlane—smashed irrigation canals.
After a centuries-long war between the
Uzbek emirates of Bukhara and Kokand for
control of the river Zeravshan, the Russians did
not manage to seize Bukhara until 1868, w h e n
they had cut off its water supply. The Soviets
made things worse first by creating small
mountainous states such as Kyrgyzstan and
Tajikistan that had copious amounts of water,
and states that were more powerful or wealthy—
K a z a k h s t a n , Uzbekistan and Tu r k m e n i s t a n —
but which had less water.A series of dams were
then built along the borders between the two
groups of states.
In 1911, about 15 million people lived in
Tu r k e s t a n , a region of central Asia that includes
Tu r k m e n i s t a n , U z b e k i s t a n ,
Ta j i k i s t a n , Ky r g y z s t a n , t h e
southern part of Kazakhstan
and Chinese Xinjiang. To d a y
there are 73 million
i n h a b i t a n t s, and the figure
could top 100 million by 2025,
imposing an even greater
burden on the water supply.
The Aral Sea is s t i l l
disappearing because of bad
w a t e r m a n a g e m e n t . O n e
hopes the same thing will not
happen to several endangered
o a s e s, such as the one at Bukhara.
The solution lies in closer cooperation
between the five Central Asian countries. O n l y
this can produce the mutual sacrifices needed if
the water is to be shared. ■
1 . The Aral Sea was once fed by two rivers, t h e
S y rdaria and the A m u d a r i a , until major
installations built under Soviet rule diverted
them to irrigate cotton plantations.To d ay the sea
is half its original size and contains only a third
of the water it used to.
K A Z A K H S T A N
T A J I K I S T A N
K Y R G Y Z S T A N
ASHKABAD
ASTANA
DUSHANBE
TASHKENT       
BISHKEK
Bukhara
Ferghana
Almaty
Kokand
T U R K M E N I S T A N
A F G H A N I S T A N
I R A N
C H I N A
S y r d a r
i a
A m u d a
r i a
Aral
Sea
X I N J I A N G
Karakum Canal
La ke Ba lk as h
T O K H T O G U L  B A R R AG E
A Ï DA R KO U L
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 29
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
General inertia and
the abundance of water
produced by giant
Soviet installations
have killed off the art
of irrigation learnt
over centuries 
SYRDARIA
Length: 3,078 km
Source: Confluence of the
Naryn and Karadaria rivers in
the Tian Shan Mountains
Mouth: Aral Sea
Countries: Kazakhstan,
Kyrgyzstan,Tajikistan,
Uzbekistan
Population around the basin:
13.4 million
AMUDARIA
Length: 2,620 km
Source: Confluence of the
Vakhsh and Pandj rivers in the
Pamir Mountains
Mouth: Aral Sea
Countries: Afghanistan,
Tajikistan, Turkmenistan,
Uzbekistan
Population around the basin:
15.5 million
RIVER FLOWS
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
KHALED DAWOUD
CORRESPONDENT FOR AL-AHRAM (CAIRO)
Ta m i n g
the Nile’s serp e n t s
Guzzled by Egypt but generated in Ethiopia, the waters of the Blue Nile
have long been a source of sabre-rattling. A new plan might finally put
an end to the spectre of a river war
L
egend has it that at the time of the pharaohs,
the people of Egypt sent gifts up the Nile to
the kingdom of Ethiopia to placate the Gods
that fed the river’s source. Egypt had, a n d
remains to have, good reason to be grateful:
some 86 percent of the water that flows down the Blue
Nile to irrigate the arid North African country emanates
from floodplains on Ethiopian territory.
Yet the one-way river flow between Egypt and
Ethiopia—as might be expected between a country that
craves water and a country that supplies it for free—has
not always resulted in such harmonious exchanges of
g i f t s. In 1979, E g y p t ’s then president Anwar Sadat made
the Nile’s fate into an urgent issue of national security.
“The only matter that could take Egypt to war again is
w a t e r,” he said in reference to Ethiopia’s plans to tap into
its one precious natural asset.
The potential for conflict over the water is
u n d e n i a b l e. Some 95 percent of the Egyptian
population is packed onto the fertile ribbon of land
along the banks of the Nile and its delta, the country’s
only water sources of note. Desperately poor and
underdeveloped Ethiopia, in contrast, has suffered
periodic droughts since the 1970s, causing the loss of
millions of lives.The Blue Nile1, emerging largely from
Lake Tana in the Ethiopian highlands, has long been
eyed as a possible source for irrigation,h y d r o e l e c t r i c i t y
and general economic growth in a country whose
population is set to boom. At present, E t h i o p i a
consumes a mere two percent of the water available to
it.
Water distribution between the two A f r i c a n
neighbours has always had a political edge, but by the
time of Sadat’s sabre-rattling remarks, a different
rivalry was poisoning relations. After flirting for a
decade with the United States, Ethiopia found itself
ruled in the 1970s by Colonel Mengistu Haile-Mariam’s
Marxist regime. Soviet experts invited by the colonel
began studying the feasibility of damming the Nile’s
tributaries and exploiting its water, provoking Egypt
into threatening that any dams built would be
destroyed by military force.
“Although such threats gave rise to the commonly
held notion that future African wars would be over
w a t e r, the fact is that these tensions were a spin-off of
the Cold War,” argues Rushdie Saeed,one of Egypt’s
most prominent experts on water issues.
Since the end of the Cold War, however, the Nile
waters have continued to prompt regular diplomatic
s p a t s. The early 1990s, for example, saw Sudan and
Egypt at loggerheads following alleged efforts by the
Sudanese government to overthrow Egypt’s president,
Hosni Mubarak.Sudan and Ethiopia formed a joint
Blue Nile Valley Organization and pledged to study
several major infrastructure projects with or without
Egypt’s approval. Once again, Mubarak resorted to
threats of military intervention.
Though a marked improvement in relations
between Cairo and Khartoum has since calmed nerves,
diplomats and experts are convinced that only a lasting
settlement will bring peace to the Nile’s coveted waters.
Until now, only one agreement has been signed by
Egypt and its neighbours—the Nile Waters A g r e e m e n t
of 1959 between Sudan and Egypt, itself based on a
deal made by the region’s colonial powers in 1929.
Ethiopia was not even mentioned in the accord.
Yet the case for some more equitable distribution
of the river waters is mounting by the day. B e s i d e s
Lining up for water in Ethiopia,a nation
Water always
flows toward
the areas
of least
resistance.
Moses Isegawa, 
Ugandan writer (1963-)
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 31
E t h i o p i a ’s traumatic droughts and destitution,s t u d i e s
point to a staggering rise in the country’s population:
current data suggest that the population will increase
from 61.4 million at present to 186 million in 2050.
Given that only 1.7 percent of the country’s arable
land is irrigated (compared to 100 percent of Egypt’s ) ,
an exponential rise in demand for water is only to be
expected.
A durable solution might not be too far off. I n
July of this year, and after five years of preliminary
t a l k s, the 10 states of the Nile basin—including Egypt,
the Sudan and Ethiopia—announced that they had
secured World Bank money for a series of programmes
to explore how the river’s waters can best be shared.
The Nile Basin Initiative (NBI) has launched several
such studies, due to be followed by loans worth at
least three billion dollars.
Thrashing out
differences
“ The River Nile still has a great potential which is
not yet exploited and which can be a great benefit to
the people of the Nile basin,” said Egypt’s minister of
public works, Mahmoud Abu Zied, in a recent
interview. “Each country is entitled to an equitable
share from the river without causing appreciable harm
to the other riparian states.”
Underpinning the initiative is the experience of
states surrounding the Mekong River in Southeast
A s i a . Since 1957, Vi e t n a m , L a o s, Cambodia and
Thailand have been members of a commission charged
with economic development of the river basin. D e s p i t e
political differences between the
nations and an absence of formal
t r e a t i e s, the body has helped
convert the Mekong into a source
of regional integration instead of
r i v a l r y : the Nam Ngum
hydropower plant,completed in
Laos in 1971, provided electricity
to the home country and covered
80 percent of Th a i l a n d ’s needs,
even during the violent conflicts
that followed inauguration.
With this precedent in mind,
the World Bank hopes the Nile’s
waters might usher in a similar
spirit of co-operation. Which is
not to say that members of the
programme have been pulling
their punches. “ There are
questions such as how to
calculate future quotas. S h o u l d
it be according to the size of the
territory or the size of the
p o p u l a t i o n , or possibly the
availability of other water
r e s o u r c e s ? ,” wondered one
Egyptian official who took part in
a recent NBI meeting in Geneva.
“We all have different ideas for
answers and this remains to be
resolved.”
Ethiopia has already started
building a series of small dams
to tap the Blue Nile water.
According to officials involved in the projects, these
dams will benefit nations downstream by protecting
Sudan from over-flooding and reducing the silt
accumulation suffered by Lake Nasser dam in Egypt.
But Egypt’s Saeed is unconvinced by their arguments.
He insists that it is in fact more dangerous for the silt
to be stopped than for it to flow with the water: s h o u l d
the former occur,he says, the river might gain in energy
and cause havoc in the northern reaches of the Nile.
Saeed also takes issue with Ethiopia’s claims that
the new dams will enable the government to sell
electricity to neighbouring countries.“ Which countries
Ethiopian officials have had in mind is difficult to
d e t e r m i n e, h o w e v e r,as none of Ethiopia’s neighbours
are industrialized nations or great consumers of
electricity,” he observes.
All parties now admit, h o w e v e r, that their
differences of opinion are better thrashed out at the
negotiating table than left to the generals. Wh a t
promised to be A f r i c a ’s next war might just have
become Africa’s latest remedy. ■
1. The Blue Nile originates in Ethiopia,the White Nile
in Uganda.The confluence of these two rivers is near
K h a r t o u m , in the Sudan.A p p r oximately 86 percent of
the Nile water flowing into Egypt is from the Blue N i l e.
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
hard hit by periodic droughts since the 1970s.
CAIRO
Alexandria
Aswan
Mediterranean
Sea
E G Y P T
S U D A N   
E T H I O P I A
K E N Y A
ASMARA
Lake
Tana
ADDISABEBA
U G A N D A
D E M . R E P .
O F C O N G O
S U E Z  C A N A L
S A U D I
A R A B I A
KHARTOUM
NILE
Length: 6,693 km from its
remotest headstream,the
Luvironza River, Burundi;
5,588km from its major
source, Lake Victoria in East
Africa
Mouth: Mediterranean Sea
Countries: Burundi,
Democratic Republic of the
Congo, Egypt,Eritrea,
Ethiopia, Kenya,Rwanda,
Sudan, Tanzania,Uganda
Population around the basin:
89 million
RIVER FLOWS
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
SANJOY HAZARIKA
SENIOR FELLOW AT THE CENTRE FOR POLICY RESEARCH, AN INDEPENDENTTHINK TANK BASED IN NEW DELHI.
FORMER REPORTERFORTHE NEW YORK TIMES OUT OF SOUTH ASIAAND AUTHOR OF FIVE BOOKS, OFWHICH HIS LATEST,
RITES OF PASSAGE (PENGUIN BOOKS INDIA, 2000)
South A s i a :
sharing the giants
Three of the world’s mightiest rivers flow through countries of the Indian
subcontinent. Despite strife and war, several landmark agreements have
been reached, but fresh disputes are looming
R
egional cooperation appears difficult to
come by in South A s i a . There have been
four conflicts between India and Pakistan
since 1947, clashes on the Indo-Bangladesh
border and accusations about India’s
overwhelming influ e n c e. When the South A s i a n
Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC) was
established in the 1980s to provide a forum for
discussion primarily on trade, contentious topics like
water resource negotiations were totally excluded from
its brief. Ye t ,South Asia has a commendable record in
the realm of water- s h a r i n g, developed through a
combination of civil society presure, political sagacity
and technical co-operation.
Countries had one precedent in the fie l d . Th e
Indus Waters treaty, signed between India and
Pakistan in 1960, is a landmark as far as water- d i s p u t e
resolutions go.The dispute can be traced back to the
Partition of the Indian sub-continent in 1947. Th e
Indus river begins in the Himalayan mountains of
Kashmir on the Indian side, flows through the arid
states of Punjab and Sindh, before converging in
Pakistan and joining the Arabian Sea south of
K a r a c h i . The source rivers of the Indus basin
remained in India, leaving Pakistan concerned by
the prospect of Indian control over the main supply
of water for its farmlands. The newly formed states
could not agree on how to share and manage the
cohesive network of irrigation, which was impossible
to partition.
Brokered by the World Bank, the treaty, which
covers the largest irrigated area (26 million acres) of
any one river system in the world,has survived two
wars and provides an ongoing mechanism for
consultation and conflict resolution through
inspections, exchange of data and visits. The treaty
Farmers in the Tibetan village of Zangri try to salvage their barley crop after the Tsang-po burst its banks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 33
demonstrates how functional cooperation on both
sides is not impossible to achieve, though most other
contentious issues remain deadlocked.
New breakthroughs were made in the 1990s over
w a t e r-sharing in the region. In December 1996,
recently elected governments in both India and
Bangladesh decided to resolve decades of acrimony
over the sharing of the waters from the Ganges, one
of the most culturally and economically significant
rivers on earth.The breakthrough came after years of
political stalemate and bitter rhetoric at the public
l e v e l , alongside quiet work behind the scenes by
water specialists, politicians and scholars on both
sides at the non-governmental level.The result was the
30-year India-Bangladesh water-sharing agreement,
signed in 1996.
Bangladesh, being in the downstream and delta
portion of a huge watershed,has been most vulnerable
to the water quality and quantity that flows from
u p s t r e a m .The way rivers are used in one country can
indeed have far-reaching effects on nations
downstream.
When India built the Farakka Barrage in the
1 9 6 0 s, Bangladesh (then East Pakistan until its
independence in 1971), watched helplessly as it
wreaked havoc.In the dry season, the barrage blocked
the natural flow of water into the country, c a u s i n g
drastic water shortages. And in the rainy season,
sudden water releases caused floods and extensive
d a m a g e, including the loss of property and human
lives.
Early warning
systems
The principal objective of the 30-year treaty is to
determine the amount of water released by India to
Bangladesh at the Farakka Barrage.The water- s h a r i n g
a r r a n g e m e n t s, primarily for the dry season, a r e
specified to the last drop and depend on the river’s
flow. It aims to make “optimum utilization” of the
waters of the region,and relies on the principles of
“ e q u i t y, fair play and no harm to either party,” with a
clause for the sharing arrangements to be reviewed
every five years.
Spurred on by the success of this treaty, I n d i a
resolved yet another riverine dispute, this time with
N e p a l , in 1997. The Mahakali River treaty settles
N e p a l ’s entitlement to water flows and electricity
from the Indian side, improving on a 1992 agreement.
The treaty, h o w e v e r, has run into opposition from
various Nepali groups, who claim it is still unfair to the
c o u n t r y ’s interests.
Although these various agreements point to
steady regional cooperation on water- s h a r i n g,
another dispute may be looming on the horizon.
This time, it centers on the Brahmaputra,the other
great river of this region,which flows through Tibet
( C h i n a ) , India and Bangladesh over a distance of
nearly 3,000 kilometres. Although no dispute has
broken into the open,the issue of information sharing
has strained relations between the three countries.
The problem is that even the most basic data is not
disclosed.
The results have been tragic. In the summer of
2000, a landslide in Tibet caused a dam to collapse,
unleashing a 26-metre wall of water that destroyed
every bridge on the Siang, as the Brahmaputra is
known in the Indian border state of A r u n a c h a l
Pradesh. The water then rushed through the Indian
state of Assam and,within a week,devastated parts
of Bangladesh. Human casualties were light but
damage to property was extensive. An effective
e a r l y-warning flood system is a goal that all three
governments must therefore work towards.
Tapping
the potential
According to Indian offic i a l s, the Chinese had not
shared any information on the build up of water
pressure and the heavy rains in the upstream catchment
area of the river, known as the Tsang-po in Tibet.
Concern is also being voiced about purported
Chinese plans to divert the waters of the Tsang-po
with the help of nuclear tunnelling.This appears to be
a Chinese move to assess international reaction to the
possibility of a dam on the river to tap its huge hydro-
energy potential.
Cooperation on river waters could significantly
improve the lives of millions of people. In the case of
the Brahmaputra, it is not so much a question of
sharing the waters as of tapping the waterway
p r o fitably for mutual benefit , primarily for transport,
commerce and industry.
One example: through cooperation, A s s a m ’s
famed tea could be shipped downstream to
Bangladesh and sent to other parts of the world.
Oil from the Numaligarh refin e r y, also in A s s a m ,c a n
be exported in river barges to meet Bangladesh’s
energy needs. These simple but effective measures
would generate employment and revive the
economies of marginalized communities. ■
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
BRAHMAPUTRA
Length: 2,900 km
Source: Kailas range,
Himalayas
Mouth: Merges with the
Ganges, then into the Bay of
Bengal
Countries: Bangladesh,China,
India
Population around the basin:
300 million (including the
Ganges)
GANGES
Length: 2,510 km
Source: Gangotri glacier,
Himalayas
Mouth: Merges with the
Brahmaputra,then into the
Bay of Bengal
Countries: India,Bangladesh
Population around the basin:
300 million (including the
Brahmaputra)
INDUS
Length: 3,180 km
Source: Kailas range,
Himalayas
Mouth: Arabian Sea
Countries: China,India,
Pakistan
Population around the basin:
150 million
RIVER FLOWS
I N D I A
P A K I S T A N
C H I N A
Calcutta
Karachi
A U T O N O M O U S R E G I O N O F
T I B E T
BHUTHAN
BANGLADESH
J A M M U A N D
K A S H M I R
ISLAMABAD
KABUL
A F G H A N I S T A N
DELHI
DHAKA
KATMANDÚ
B r a h m a p u t r a
B r a h m a p u t r a
I N D I AG a n g e s
I n d u s
Arabian
Sea
Bay of
Bengal
F A R A K K A
B A R R AG E
Lhassa
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
AMY OTCHET
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
The Kalahari’s
u n d e rg round secre t s
Namibia almost came to blows with Botswana over plans to divert
a river, but the answer may lie just beneath the surface of the driest
country south of the Sahara
J
ust nod with a smile and maybe your companion
from the Water Affairs Department won’t notice
the confusion. Driving north into the vast spaces
of Namibia,you keep missing the rivers he spots.
“And this is the Okahanja River,” he says.
Another blank nod.“And here we have the famous
O m a t a k o. It may look small but this river can be very
p o w e r f u l .”Look small? Look where? The patient Greg
Christelis is gushing with tales of flash flo o d s,yet all you
see is a cracked and sandy track in the bush, w h e n
s u d d e n l y, what used to be dry facts and figures about
erratic rainfall and aridity come rushing back—Namibia
d o e s n ’t have any regular or perennial rivers to call its
own.* 
This is a land of ephemeral rivers, which arrive
with near violence and disappear
without warning, flowing for a
few hours, days or even weeks
after a good hard rain before
fading into the red desert sand
or the tall grass of the savannah.
But when they do run, t h e y
represent events in people’s lives.
Men will still swap stories about
a river that hasn’t flowed for 30
years. The old-school Afrikaner
farmer will religiously plot
rainfall levels on a graph, while in black communal
a r e a s, the same information is embedded in lessons that
a father recounts to his children.
A dehydrated capital
In Namibia—the driest country south of the
Sahara—water scarcity and unpredictability form a
constant constraint on national development.Av e r a g e
annual rainfall is 250 mm compared to 1,400 mm in the
Democratic Republic of the Congo, for example. A
corner of the country can receive double the average
rainfall one season and nothing for years after.And the
little that does fall doesn’t stay for long:83 percent is
lost to evaporation, plants soak up and then sweat
another 14 percent back into the atmosphere, l e a v i n g
just two percent to run off those mysteriously
ephemeral rivers and one percent to infiltrate rock
underground.
That single digit, h o w e v e r, may transform the
Namibian landscape. Groundwater is already providing
for about half of the country’s needs and its role will
increase as the population grows and droughts hit
harder and more frequently with predicted climate
c h a n g e.Yet this invisible resource is just breaking the
surface of the country’s national and regional priorities.
“ For the past ten years, w e ’ve focused on
negotiating protocols [agreements] for international
rivers like the Zambezi,which involved eight states.B u t
we ignored groundwater, even through we have
aquifers running across national boundaries,” says Dr.
Serge Puyoo,a French geohydrologist working with the
Southern African Development Community (SADC).
Think of aquifers as a lattice of rock, whose cracks,
crooks and crannies are filled with water. Sometimes
the water is from recent rain which seeped down
through the soil. Other aquifers only contain fossil
w a t e r, rain of bygone geological eras.Depending upon
various factors—from the type of rock to the pull of
gravity—the water can slowly
flow within the aquifer and
b e y o n d . Like rivers,aquifers pay
no heed to national borders.
As Puyoo explains,“not only
has there been a general lack of
knowledge in monitoring and
mapping these aquifers, but a
cultural and historical blockage
to recognizing them. M a n y
countries relegate groundwater
to the geology departments of
government or universities. So politicians and water
managers are unaware of the potential and limits of the
resource, until they are faced with a crisis.”
That is exactly what happened in 1996-97, when
severe drought brought Namibia’s capital,Wi n d h o e k ,
to its knees and the country close to the brink of war
with neighbouring Botswana, according to sensational
media reports. Simmering tensions over disputed
borders added fuel to the fire surrounding Namibia’s
plan to divert part of the Okavango River, w h i c h
originates in Angola before carving the border with
Namibia and then snaking into Botswana to feed the
“jewel of the Kalahari.”In this vast wetland, t r a d i t i o n a l
communities weave around a wealth of biodiversity
and wildlife that tourist operators milk for foreign
currency, amounting to ten percent of the country’s
gross domestic product.
For ecologists in Botswana, the river was sacred.
But in Namibia, those shining waters appeared as a
This is a land
of ephemeral rivers,
which arrive with
near violence
and disappear
without warning.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 35
saviour, prompting civil engineers like Piet Heyns to
update an old scheme to pipe about one or two percent
of the average flow to dehydrated Wi n d h o e k . Th e
capital was in crisis—ordinarily three dams would
store enough water to keep the city running for a few
y e a r s. Two were almost empty and the third was
collecting dust. Officials were digging holes in a
desperate search for more groundwater, w h i l e
municipal authorities set up an electric sign to count
down the days remaining of supply in the dams. By the
time it hit 30,the government prepared to divert the
Okavango. Then,without warning, it rained…
Rolling back
apartheid’s legacy
To d a y, the plans for the pipeline still sit within
reach of Piet Heyns, who is now director of Wa t e r
Affairs and Namibia’s representative to the Permanent
Okavango River Basin Water Commission, which is
supposed to resolve the dispute over the river. Heyns
and his counterpart in Botswana, Balisi Khupe,s p e a k
of glowing plans for joint studies and monitoring.Yet
according to some experts involved, the commission is
mired in bureaucratic gridlock. The delay may prove
b e n e f i c i a l , h o w e v e r, as Namibia moves with the
international current running against building new
dams and their hefty price-tags.
Instead of grabbing for rivers, the government is
looking underground to economize its reserves,n o t a b l y
by building the largest water bank on the continent.Th e
aim is to plug the holes in the three dams, p a r t l y
connected by an open canal running more than
2 5 0 kilometres in the bushy savannah, w h e r e
substantial amounts literally vanish as vapour. In 1997,
for example, the three dams supplied Windhoek with
about 15.7 million cubic metres (Mm3) of water.Yet the
system lost 33.5 Mm3 to evaporation. Instead of letting
that precious river and rain water bake in the sun,
plans are underway to inject it into an aquifer under the
c i t y.The next phase will lie in opening two “ b r a n c h e s ”
of the bank at nearby dams.
Through investment schemes like the bank,
Namibia is removing the vestiges of apartheid’s control
over its natural resources 11 years after independence
from South A f r i c a .“ There was so much money flo w i n g
in from South Africa that we did major infrastructure
projects without proper study,” says Greg Christelis,
chief geohydrologist at Water A f f a i r s. The problem
may not have been the quantity of money flowing in,
but the direction it took: straight to wealthy white
folk in Windhoek and the surrounding cattle country,
where the average livestock farm,fattened by subsidies,
covers at least 5,000 hectares.
Namibia is not alone in trying to roll back the
hydrological legacy of apartheid. South Africa is in
the lead, passing the world’s most progressive water law
to ensure fair and sustainable use of the resource at
home and abroad.With 80 percent of its river (surface)
water originating in Lesotho, the government is keenly
aware of the need for hydro-diplomacy among its
neighbours, notably Namibia and Botswana.“We’re
Just about every country in the world, except for island states, probably shares an aquifer
with a neighbour.Yet these hidden sources of blue gold rarely appear on a map because
so little is known about them. UNESCO is trying to promote a better understanding of these
aquifers from a scientific,legal and management perspective. A new project will not only
highlight important case studies like the Karoo, but develop maps and a database on how
best to manage and monitor transboundary aquifers. The project has several partners,
notably the IAH, the Food and Agriculture Organization and the UN Economic Commission
for Europe. ■
UNMAPPED T R E A S U R E
“Drop by drop,
water sculpts
the rock.”
Theocrites, Greek poet 
(315-250 B.C.)
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
Herding in the communal areas of northern Namibia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
trying to move from the Okavango to something more
positive,” says Christine Colvin of the International
Association of Hydrogeologists in South A f r i c a .
Through SADC,
representatives from the
three countries (and others)
have crafted a set of soon-
to-be legally binding rules
on jointly monitoring and
managing groundwater,
especially transboundary
aquifers. Bear in mind that
this is probably the one
natural resource that has
managed to avoid
international regulation.
Countries spent decades
hammering out a UN
convention on international
r i v e r s, yet they barely
discussed deep aquifers.
Instead of trying to forge
formal agreements,
international organizations
like UNESCO are promoting data exchange and joint
monitoring between countries (see box). N a m i b i a ,
Botswana and South Africa are now mapping an
enormous sequence of aquifers, known as the Karoo,
which spreads across the Kalahari into all three
countries.The initial hope was that the investigations
would uncover phenomenal supplies of water in
Namibia that could serve as an alternative to the
controversial Okavango scheme. On the contrary, t h e
Namibian side appears to be on the decline, a c c o r d i n g
to Jurgen Kirchner, who is helping to coordinate a
major study financed and led by the Japan International
Cooperation A g e n cy that focused on the country’s
most important swathe of Karoo,known as Stampriet
and covering an area of 65,000 kilometres2. The two
ephemeral rivers which most experts used to believe
fed the aquifer seem to dead-end in sand dunes. The
only apparent source of recharge is rainfall collecting
in sinkholes, or indents in the topography, according to
recent satellite images.
Trouble in cattle country
The bad news is more destabilizing within the
country than across the borders. In South Africa,the
aquifer sits beneath a national park, which requires
little water.Demand is also low in Botswana,where few
people are willing to brave the remote Kalahari,
although this may eventually change as traffic increases
along a new highway crossing the desert.
The real conflict is brewing in Stampriet,w h i c h ,s a y s
K i r c h n e r, must reduce its water use by 30 percent.
This prognosis will ricochet like a bullet in this rolling
land,with crests of red sand.This isn’t just any stretch
of cattle country,but a bastion of wealthy white farmers
who believe that they are the backbone of a land they
love but a country they seem to fear and even hate.
Stampriet is the home of a “tough breed,” s a y s
Willie Prinsloo, a legendary driller who dug for water
and minerals across southern Africa before retiring to
his farm,Donnersberg or Thunder Mountain,where he
raises livestock and wildlife for trophy hunting on
7,500 hectares.The one-eyed Willie runs the farm like
a ship, overseeing every watering hole for cattle and
vegetable planted in the plot he shares with his four
l a b o u r e r s, who live in tidy cottages behind his own
h o m e. Banish the thought that he and his brethren
are depleting the aquifer, says Prinsloo. Fault lies with
the government—for it refuses to replace the farmers’
boreholes, the old rusty metal pipes installed decades
ago to bring up the groundwater.To reach the Karoo,
the boreholes must first pass through another aquifer
which tends to have very salty water. Holes in the
pipes enable this saline stuff to sink down and pollute
the clean Karoo.
Communal wisdom
The government, h o w e v e r, has a new policy in
which people pay for the water services and
i n f r a s t r u c t u r e. In the north, nomadic herding
communities are helping to install new pumps and
should one day pay for the water they use. Might the
same apply to Stampriet? 
The question provokes a torrent of what many
would consider racism, as Prinsloo expounds on the
benefits of colonialism.Beneath the old hatred lies a
new fear:government plans to spread the wealth by
land taxes and water metres. Here in the Kalahari,
you can still feel the heat from Robert Mugabe’s
Z i m b a b w e, so few dare to place the word “ l a n d ”b e f o r e
“ r e d i s t r i b u t i o n .” But the government is slowly buying
commercial (generally white) farms from willing sellers
to ease pressure in the northern communal areas,
which are in many ways like a separate country,d i v i d e d
by a three-metre-high fence from the commercial
cattle farms of men like Prinsloo.
According to the Japanese study, about five percent
of Stampriet’s 1,500 farms are now government-owned.
So not only must the Afrikaner brethren cut down on
their water consumption,but they can also prepare for
more and new neighbours. Yet Stampriet’s farmers
are probably the only ones in the country to use half
their expensive groundwater to grow commercial
c r o p s.For economists, this is like throwing gold away—
every cubic metre of water invested in irrigation
brought in just half a Namibian dollar (U. S. $ 0 . 0 6 ) .
For the sake of the  Karoo, Stampriet’s newcomers
hopefully won’t follow the “commercial”ways of the
“tough breed”next door. ■
* Four perennial rivers form part of Namibia’s national
borders.
+ …
For more information, http://unesco.org/water
Atlantic
Ocean 
Indian Ocean
N A M I B I A
A N G O L A
Z A M B I A
Z I M B .
B O T S W A N A
LESOTHOS O U T H
A F R I C A
Okahanja
Cape Town
WINDHOEK
PRETORIA
GABORONE
MASERU
O k a v a n g o
K A L A H A R I
K A R O OS t a m p r i e t
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 37
“I
t seemed absolutely improbable, b o r d e r i n g
on the impossible,” U. S. Interior Secretary
Bruce Babbitt said last January in reference
to a water accord reached among seven of
the southwestern U. S. states after five tough
years of negotiation.The challenge he faced in brokering
this agreement is one shared by many senior
administrators around
t h e w o r l d . As increasing
scarcity exacerbates water
c o n flicts within and among
c o u n t r i e s, water nego-
tiations will inevitably grow
in scope and intensity
almost everywhere.
In a thirsty world,
water can no longer be
regarded primarily as a
“strategic asset” that can
be secured and
safeguarded through the
instruments of
conventional security, l e a s t
of all through the use of
f o r c e.As with atmospheric
pollution leading to ozone
depletion and climate
c h a n g e, or with the
depletion of renewable
resources such as fish
stocks and forests, w a t e r
disputes involve a whole range of political,economic,
social and scientific considerations.The challenge lies in
finding and maintaining a balance between political
and technical priorities.To this end, the United Nations
has developed a framework convention to guide fresh
water negotiations—which 10 states have ratified out of
the 35 required for the treaty to come into force.
National governments are,h o w e v e r, increasingly turning
to an alternative form of negotiation involving neutral
m e d i a t o r s, who work closely with international
o r g a n i z a t i o n s, development banks, and a wide cross
section of groups concerned about the future of water
use.
The Asian Development Bank (ADB), in its 1999
annual report, offered to mediate regional water
disputes as part of a policy to increase access to clean
water in A s i a .And the work of the World Commission
on Dams is cited by many as a remarkable feat of
consensus building between widely divergent interests
around a highly controversial development issue.
From these experiments and other environmental
n e g o t i a t i o n s, we can
highlight some key
principles and “ b e s t
p r a c t i c e s ” in water
negotiations.
Finding a 
unified voice
To begin with,it is not
always obvious who
should be at the
negotiation table. Th e
standard response is for
national governments to
treat water as a foreign
policy matter, and thus to
charge their top-level
diplomats with working
out bi- or multi-lateral
a g r e e m e n t s. It is a mistake,
however, not to include a
host of non-governmental
actors in these
negotiations (farmers,
industry, environmental and women’s groups, etc.),
whose activities directly affect the condition of a
w a t e r s h e d , and whose livelihoods depend on the
r e s o u r c e.These groups,along with local authorities and
indigenous groups, can offer relevant technical and
traditional knowledge necessary to mitigate the
stresses and strains suffered by a water system.
To be effective, these groups must be sufficiently
organized to speak with something approaching a
u n i fied voice. So even before the larger dialogue
b e g i n s, each group must work out its differences
through internal consultations which should continue
throughout the negotiation process. This ongoing
feedback forestalls the tendency of negotiators to
MICHÈLE FERENZ1 AND LAWRENCE E. SUSSKIND2
TOGETHER, THEYARE INVOLVED INTHETRAININGOF BI-NATIONAL MEDIATIONTEAMSFOR THE JOINT ENVIRONMENTAL MEDIATION SERVICE IN JERUSALEM
Negotiating with nature:
the next ro u n d
A step-by-step guide for brokering a deal on the one resource
we cannot live without
S T R I K I N G  P E A C E  O N  T R O U B L E D  W A T E R S
1. Senior Associate at
t h e Consensus Building
Institute and a Doctoral
Fe l l ow at the Program on
Negotiation at Harvard
Law School
2. Director of the Public
Disputes Program at the
H a r v a rd Law Sch o o l ,
and President, of the
n o n-profit Consensus
Building Institute.
“I can tell the way
of celestial bodies,
but can say nothing
of the movement of
a small drop of
water.”
Galileo, Italian astronomer
(1564-1642)
Engineering a mutually reinforcing agreement.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
lock into a position before hearing what others have
to say. Just to be certain that all of the key actors are
i n v o l v e d , an impartial mediator should conduct a
series of confidential interviews with all the key
stakeholders to clarify their concerns and identify
additional players that should be included.
Finding the key people is only one element in
preparing for negotiations. Mediators should also
play a role in “joint fact-fin d i n g ” by helping to identify
experts acceptable to everyone involved and by
framing questions that these scientists should then
be commissioned to investigate. Their findings can
help reduce uncertainties and set priorities that may
differ from country to country so that an overall
“package” of proposals can be
c r a f t e d . They can also help to
establish “red lines” o r
thresholds of resource damage
and depletion that would trigger
more stringent obligations
(known as “ c o n t i n g e n t
agreements”).
Once the key people and
data have been assembled, the
actual negotiations can begin.
After a mediator prepares a
written conflict assessment to create an overview of the
parties’ interests and priorities, face-to-face meetings
can begin. They usually start with the business of
setting an agenda and adopting procedural
groundrules that will allow for constructive
deliberation—or the “creation of value”—in an
atmosphere that emphasizes creative problem-solving.
No party is ever pressured to commit or to
compromise in well-managed mediation. At stage
three it is time to decide—or “distribute value.” The
challenge here is to make sure that the goodwill
previously generated isn’t lost as parties fight for
competing proposals. Once an agreement on the
substance is reached informally, the mediator must
then be certain that it is communicated accurately to
the official decision-makers.
Still waiting
for the “Green Helmets”
In treaty-making, much of the focus is on the
painstaking task of drafting written agreements.Yet,
in the global arena, the resulting provisions are
typically difficult if not impossible to legally enforce.
Calls for an international water court are unlikely to
be heeded in the near future. Nor is deployment of
“Green Helmets”—a kind of environmental
counterpart to the existing blue-helmeted United
Nations peacekeeping forces—feasible. I n t e r n a t i o n a l
relations theorists and lawyers hotly debate the
propensity of states to comply with treaty obligations.
Some subscribe to the Machiavellian notion that
nations flout norms with impunity whenever they
think that the costs of adherence outweigh the benefit s.
Others favour the theory that most nations observe
m o s t international law principles and obligations m o s t
of the time, if only to avoid the “ s h a m i n g ”c a m p a i g n s
orchestrated by non-governmental organizations.B u t
even the optimists readily acknowledge that many
factors other than willful disregard get in the way of
perfect compliance.The vague language of many legal
rules, for examples, is a problem. In addition, some
states simply don’t have the capacity—technically or
financially—to do what they have promised.
These constraints must be kept in mind when
transforming informal understandings into binding
c o n t r a c t s.There are a few important ways of enabling
agreements to adjust over time to
changing circumstances and new
n e e d s. One is to build into the
agreement mutually reinforcing,
s t e p-by-step performance re-
q u i r e m e n t s : the continued
cooperation of one side is tied
to compliance by the others.Th i s
reassures more dedicated or
active states that their initiative
and largesse will not be taken
advantage of by laggards.
Penalties might also be levied in the case of non-
compliance, or rewards might be agreed upon ahead
of time for each step completed as promised.
Fi n a l l y,any effective agreement requires the active
engagement of actors operating on the ground.Wa t e r
negotiations can no longer be left solely to elected
l e a d e r s. The conversation must be broadened. We
also need greater transparency with regard to decision-
making and greater rigour with regard to the scientific
basis underlying the agreements reached.These are the
key lessons learned from the two-decade long
experience with environmental treaty-making and
negotiation efforts. ■
+ …
For more information on environmental negotiation: 
• Lawrence Susskind, Environmental Diplomacy, Oxford
University Press, New York, 1995 
• Lawrence Susskind, Paul Levy and Jennifer Thomas-
Larmer, Negotiating Environmental Agreements, Island
Press, Washington, D.C.,1999 
• Lawrence Susskind, Sarah Mckearnan,and Jennifer
Thomas-Larmer, The Consensus Building Handbook,
Sage Publishers, Thousand Oaks, California,1999
• Lawrence Susskind,William Moomaw, and Kevin
Gallagher, Transboundary Environmental Negotiations:
A New Approach To Global Cooperation, forthcoming
from Jossey-Bass Publishers, San Francisco
Water negotiations
can no longer be left
solely to elected
leaders.
The conversation
must be broadened.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
P
MICHEL BESSIÈRES
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
On the tra c k s
of a global vice
Corruption may be as old as government, but rapid globalization has given it alarming new
dimensions. For the United Nations, the scourge has become a top priority, although so far, the battle
is being waged in thick fog
ublic corruption is a crime as old as
government itself. In the fifth century
B C, Plato talked about it in his L a w s.
Two centuries later, the Indian political
reformer Kautilya1 listed 40 temptations
that civil servants might yield to. But the
state of corruption today is
unprecedented in at least two respects:
scandals are erupting the world over,
and  people are no longer in the mood to
tolerate them.
In less than a year, two sitting
p r e s i d e n t s — Joseph Estrada in the
Philippines and Alberto Fujimori in
Peru—have been forced to resign, w h i l e
a former president—Carlos Menem of
Argentina—has been put under house
a r r e s t . In each case, the main legal
charges and the immediate public outcry
against them involved corruption.
Something that until recently was
seen as just an internal government affair
has become an explicit priority for all
international bodies, from the G-8
nations and the World Bank to the
United Nations, which plans to draft an
anti-corruption convention by 2002.Th i s
surge of activity reflects various concerns,
but has been fed by a single process:
globalization.
The first “ m a n d a t e ” on corruption
received by international bodies has
come from governments themselves.
E T H I C S ◗
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 39
Economic austerity has fuelled the fight against corruption in many countries:here a march in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Twenty years of ever-faster fin a n c i a l
t r a n s a c t i o n s, spurred by deregulation
and the rise of electronic
c o m m u n i c a t i o n s, has turned money
gained from criminal activities into a
source of political and financial
i n s t a b i l i t y. And money embezzled
through corruption has gone hand-in-
hand with the money made by organized
crime.
“These two kinds of crime feed off
each other, hiding and recycling their
p r o fits in the same way,” says Daniel
D o m m e l , president of the French branch
of the NGO Tr a n s p a r e n cy International.
“ To stay out of sight, organized crime
uses corruption, which weakens
institutional safeguards against such
criminals.”
In recent years, several scandals have
revealed the extent of the scourge. I n
the summer of 1998, the International
Monetary Fund (IMF) lent Russia eight
billion dollars to stave off the collapse of
the ruble. Benyamin Sokolov, Russia’s
chief auditor, told a BBC interviewer in
November that year:“We have looked
into what happened to some of the IMF
money and we have to admit that several
billion dollars did not go to the
programmes they were earmarked for.
Some of it was simply stolen.”
The following summer, the biggest
money-laundering scandal in U. S. h i s t o r y
erupted,with the Bank of New York at
its centre. According to the FBI, t h e
Russian mafia used this venerable
financial institution to funnel $10 billion
back into the Russian economy after its
passage through the tiny Pacific island-
state of Nauru, famous for “offshore”
banks that ask few questions of their
customers.
“ Forty years ago, just one place in the
w o r l d , S w i t z e r l a n d , guaranteed secrecy
for its banking clients, but today there
are more than 50 such countries,” s a y s
Yves Mény, head of the Robert
Schumann Centre at the European
University Institute in Florence and
author of Democracy and Corruption in
E u r o p e ( C a s s e l l , L o n d o n , 1 9 9 6 ) .
Monitoring financial movements,
particularly through tax havens, is now
one of the main features of the battle
against corruption.
An annual
blacklist
The Financial Action Task Force on
Money Laundering (FAT F ) , which grew
out of meetings of the G-8 countries and
is based at the Organization for
Economic Cooperation and
Development (OECD), has since 2000
published an annual blacklist of the most
financially suspect countries, sending a
sharp jolt through the genteel world of
international finance.
“ We want to get all banking centres,
including the least willing, to conform
to international standards,” says FATF
executive secretary Patrick Moulette.
“ We ’re exerting constructive pressure
on all of them, whether they’re tax
havens like the Marshall Islands,
Dominica and Nauru,or countries such
as Egypt, I s r a e l , Lebanon and Russia.
Note that we’re removing Russia from
our blacklist of 17 countries because it
passed a law this summer imposing
tighter controls on its banking system.”
Economic interests are also pressing
international organizations to crack
down on corruption. But not for moral
r e a s o n s. Firms operating in the
international arena—from construction
to water supplies—are horrified by the
demands for ever-bigger kickbacks.
The bribing game
“Economic liberalization has sent
the cost of bribes skyrocketing, but few
have noticed,” says Rob Je n k i n s, w h o
teaches political science at Birbeck
College (London).“During public sector
p r i v a t i z a t i o n , prospective buyers fig h t
each other to bribe politicians and civil
s e r v a n t s. And with each new reform,
firms that want to have a say in drafting
the new rules or simply want to know
what the rules will be,are forced to make
pay-offs without getting any guarantees
in return.I ’ve seen that in every country
where I’ve looked at economic reform—
in India,South Africa and Uganda.It is
ironic that in the early 1980s, the IMF
and the World Bank promised that their
liberalization programmes would reduce
the power of bureaucracy and thereby
stamp out the source of corruption.”
To eradicate this kind of crime, the
OECD in 1997 drew up a Convention
on Combating Bribery of Foreign Public
Officials in International Business
Transactions, which has been signed so
far by 33 countries. “Its main point is
s i m p l e,”explains Dommel.“It bans fir m s
in the signatory states from paying
kickbacks to foreign offic i a l s. Until a
few years ago, such “ c o m m i s s i o n s ”w e r e
tolerated in many countries. In France,
for example, they were officially tax-
d e d u c t i b l e. It was compared to going to
40 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
First day in prison for former Filipino president Joseph Estrada,arrested in April 2001.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
confession in church.”
The Convention’s many critics say it
is a step in the right direction, but far
from enough. “It seems absurd to
condemn bribing an official of a
government-owned airline and then shut
your eyes to a kickback paid to an offic i a l
of a private one,” says Stuart Eizenstat,
former U.S. under-secretary of state in
the Clinton administration.
His comments are especially
pertinent at a time when the economic
fashion is to privatize public services.
Benoît Dejemeppe, a state prosecutor
in Brussels and a corruption expert,
notes that the OECD convention is
largely based on the Foreign Corrupt
Practices A c t , which U. S. P r e s i d e n t
Jimmy Carter pushed through Congress
in 1977 in the wake of the Lockheed
bribery scandal that rocked governments
in Europe and Japan.“In over 20 years,
only four major corruption scandals have
led to criminal convictions,”he says,“ s o
I conclude the law isn’t strict enough.”
A third “ m a n d a t e ” a g a i n s t
corruption comes from civil society,
which has shown increasing concern
about the murky relationship between
politics and money. “In the process of
worldwide ‘quasi-democratization’ and
global access to information,what people
want above all else is transparency,”s a y s
Jenkins.
Eluding all
control
Until the end of the Cold War, the
major political movements upheld
widely contrasting ideologies;how they
were financed was seen as less important.
To d a y, in contrast, institutional political
debate boils down to minor differences
over how to apply broadly similar
economic programmes, all requiring big
sacrifices by most of the population.So
it is no accident that anti-corruption
campaigners have emerged at the same
time as economic austerity in Western
E u r o p e,financial crises in Southeast A s i a
and Latin A m e r i c a , and structural
adjustment programmes in many poor
countries.
But the slowness of the anti-
corruption process, the problems
investigators come up against as they
try to trace international networks, the
rarity and lightness of the penalties—
all have helped in fostering a good dose
of  cy n i c i s m . French journalist Denis
Robert has published several books
about corruption scandals. His latest,
(R é v é l a t i o n $) written with Ernest
Baeckes, is about how a Luxembourg-
based clearinghouse called Clearstream
o p e r a t e s. Such institutions are vital to
the business of banking since they
catalogue all transactions and list the
people who make them. Th e y
nevertheless encourage anonymity and
elude all control.
An insult to the poor
“ The very word ‘ c o r r u p t i o n ,’ if it
means a departure from the legal rules,
is no longer appropriate,” says Robert.
“It’s the system that’s corrupt.And the
institutions never react until long
a f t e r w a r d s. As Spanish judge Baltasar
Garzón said, the fight against corruption
is a fight between a mammoth and a
leopard.”
The battle is not only uneven but is
being waged in thick fog according to
five European judges, all anti-corruption
e x p e r t s, who wrote an article in the
French daily Le Monde last May, soon
after Robert’s book came out.“ The main
thing that emerges from this
i n v e s t i g a t i o n ,” they wrote, “is the
deafening silence of those responsible for
the system that is in the dock.… Th e
tactic of hiding one’s head in the sand
might suggest that the book was a
pointless exercise. But we think that it’s
only just started to tell the true story.…
The book should help Europeans
understand what clearinghouses do and
throw new light on the globalization of
finance.”
The effectiveness of different ways to
fight corruption is still being debated.
But everyone at least agrees on what
the enemy is. Even James Wolfensohn,
the Australian president of the Wo r l d
B a n k , raised the then taboo subject
inside the Bank in 1996. He called
corruption a serious “ c a n c e r ” t h a t
“insulted the poorest people by diverting
money to the richest.” ■
1. Author of A r t h a s h a s t r a, a famous
philosophical treatise. He was adviser
T H E  S I Z E  O F  W O R L D  C O R R U P T I O N
Before you can measure corruption, you have to know what it is.The United Nations and the Wo r l d
Bank have adopted the sober definition offered by Transparency International, which calls it “ t h e
misuse of public power for private profit.”
But even its authors recognize the limits of this description since it takes no account of private sector
corruption. To understand this, it’s best to look at how graft works in practice.A bribe, according to
the English dictionary, is “a sum of money or other favour, given to someone in authority so as to
influence their opinions or behaviour.”
Putting a figure on the amount of corruption in the world is very hard but also irresistible. Patrick
M o u l e t t e, executive secretary of FATF (Financial Action Task Force on Money Laundering), s a y s
there is “no financial basis to measure the extent of this illegal activity.All the figures given are fic t i t i o u s
and unscientific.”
FATF documents, however, cite the International Monetary Fund’s estimate of $80 billion a year. In
c o m p a r i s o n , the total of criminally-acquired capital is reckoned at between $500 and $1,500
billion—two to five percent of the gross world production.
Case studies are a much more accurate guide. One in Milan,conducted before and after Operation
Mani Pulite (Clean Hands),showed that the city’s public works budget had been inflated by 30 to
40 percent. The airport extension project, for example, could have been cut from 2,610 billion lire ($1.1
billion) to 1,990 billion ($860 million).
Transparency International has in the past few years published a Corruption Perception Index (CPI),
and more recently, an index of corruption in exporting countries, the Bribe Payers Perceptions Index
(BPI).Both are based on rigorous opinion polls among businessmen, financial analysts, journalists
and sometimes the general public. They are not exhaustive (not every country is represented) and
remain subjective (because they measure corruption as perceived by those aske d ) . But despite
these two drawbacks, they give a meaningful picture of the situation and,in the absence of other
surveys, the indexes have been accepted by public opinion.
In 2001, the CPI index revealed that Fi n l a n d ,Denmark and New Zealand were seen as the least corrupt
countries, while Indonesia,Uganda,Nigeria and Bangladesh came out bottom of the list. ■
E T H I C S ◗
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
H
INTERVIEW BY RENÉ LEFORT
DIRECTOR OFTHE UNESCO COURIER
C o n t e m p o rary art:
who calls the shots?
Despite the international veneer of the art market, research by French sociologist Alain Quémin
shows that a handful of rich countries dominates the scene
ow has contemporary art been affected by
globalization?
Contemporary art lovers and
professionals believe that it’s becoming
increasingly internationalized. A n y
gallery director, art critic, m u s e u m
curator or exhibition commissioner
would more or less agree that it would be
absurd to take nationality or country of
origin into account when judging an
artist’s  work.All that matters, they say,
is whether or not he or she is good. In
other words,an artist’s fame and market
value should have nothing to do with
n a t i o n a l i t y. As proof, those in the art
world point to the fact that exhibitions
and biennales are scattered around the
planet2 (they are even held in Havana,
Taipei and Dakar), and to the rise of
Asian artists after the Eastern European
wave of the early 1990s. In contemporary
a r t , globalization and its corollaries in
the art world—cultural mixing and
relativism—are taken for granted.
But do these claims match what is actually
happening on the art market?
To answer that question, I have
developed or compared several
i n d i c a t o r s, including rankings of
“ r e p u t a t i o n ” by experts (those who
contribute to an artist’s fame or “name
recognition”),the composition of large
private and public collections,
acquisitions by large museums,
participation in major fairs and biennale
e x h i b i t i o n s, sales on the international
m a r k e t , and so on. These indicators
sometimes give different rankings, but
they reveal a very strong geographical
hierarchy (see box). The most famous
artists and those whose works have the
highest market value are from the
United States. Several countries in
Western Europe form the second group,
sometimes equal to or outdoing the
United States, especially at fairs and
biennales.
But the ranking in this group is very
m a r k e d . Germany is far ahead of the
United Kingdom, Fr a n c e, Italy and
S w i t z e r l a n d .After them,the contribution
from other nations, including developed
countries such as Spain, the Nordic
c o u n t r i e s, Japan and South Ko r e a , i s
i n s i g n i fic a n t . The third world is at the
very bottom of the list.
In art as in many other fie l d s, there is
obviously a gulf between a “ c e n t r e,”
made up of only a few countries that are
themselves ranked in a very rigid
hierarchy, and a huge “periphery.”
But artists from the periphery, as you call
i t , have achieved a certain degree of fame
and their works have attained a very high
market value…
That may be true, but the proportion
is very small.And how long will it last?
Artists from Eastern Europe, who were
very fashionable in the early 1990s, h a v e
now fallen into oblivion in the Western
art world.And there’s nothing to indicate
that the Asian or African artists currently
in vogue will not in their turn be as
“disposable as Kleenex”themselves.
In any case, how should they go
about getting known? There are
practically no exceptions to the rule:
they must be exhibited in a country at the
centre or  go there to live in the hope of
finding their place in mainstream
contemporary art.
But hasn’t this inequality always existed?
Without going too far back,didn’t France
occupy this “monopolistic”position from
the late 19th to the mid-20th century?
Ye s,but the big difference is that this
dominant position was recognized and
fully accepted in the name of France’s
contribution to art history.To d a y, on the
c o n t r a r y, contemporary art circles cannot
recognize America’s supremacy in this
field because they simply don’t “see”it.
In the artistic fields where this supremacy
is recognized,it tends to be stigmatized
because the United States is considered
A FEW INDICATO R S
◗ Each year, the German magazine C a p i t a l
publishes a world ranking of living artists called
Kunst Kompass. Highly influential around the
world,it supposedly reflects their aesthetic value
based on the opinions of “ e x p e r t s ” a n d
exhibitions in major museums and shows.
In 2000, the 100 “ b e s t ” artists included 33
A m e r i c a n s, 28 Germans, eight Britons, five Fr e n c h ,
four Italians and three Swiss. Of the 16 other
artists, only five came from the developing world
(South Africa, Cuba, Iran, Mexico, Thailand).
◗ On November 16, 2 0 0 0 , Christies held one of its
two major annual contemporary art auctions in
New York. Of the 48 artists whose works were
s o l d , 26 came from the United States, six from the
United Kingdom, five from Germany, four from
Italy, three from Switzerland,two from Japan and
one each from France and South Africa.
◗ On November 17, 2 0 0 0 ,S o t h e b y ’s held a similar
auction in New York. Of the 63 works sold, 50
were by American artists or artists living in the
United States. Just one was by an artist from a
developing country, where he still lives (Mexico).
■
* Alain Quémin,a researcher and teach e r
at Marne-la-Vallée university (Fr a n c e ) ,
has just published a study commissioned
by the Fr e n ch Foreign Affairs ministry,
entitled “The role of buyer countries on the
market and in the contemporary art
world”
◗ C U L T U R E
42 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
a latecomer on the art scene.
So why is there this contradiction between
image and reality?
I ’ll answer with another question:
why would the contemporary art world
be an exception to the dominant
globalization credo, according to which
e v e r y o n e, wherever they are, has a
chance as long as they have talent? A n d
more specifically, why would it be free
from two contradictory movements that
are part of globalization? On the one
h a n d , you have an endless search for
i n n o v a t i o n , which sometimes goes as
far as including the periphery. On the
o t h e r, the tendency to minimize risk,
especially financial risk, ends up
boosting the value of artists from well-
established art centres, who are
therefore the easiest to promote.
But playing the devil’s advocate, can’t we
say that  “ g o o d ” c o n t e m p o rary artists
simply wouldn’t choose to live in places
w h e re their work cannot be pro p e r l y
exhibited or sold?
To d a y, artists from the periphery
have a growing number of opportunities
to aid them. For example, fine arts
schools are now more open to the
w o r l d . H o w e v e r, these artists rarely
make it on the international scene. Is
that because they might be “naturally”
worse? Let’s take a sporting metaphor.
For decades, people thought you had
to be Scandinavian to be a champion
middle-distance runner.Then they came
from Eastern Europe. N o w, a t h l e t e s
from North and East Africa are winning
all the races.And each time, the success
of these different groups is considered
“ n a t u r a l .” At the very least, t h e
geographical concentration of
contemporary art hampers the
recognition of the artistic potential that
exists outside the United States and in
some European countries. ■
1. Experts sometimes disagree, but they
generally define contemporary art as an
i n n ovative form of creation that
emerged after 1960.The main media
are painting, sculpture, photography,
video, montages and installations.
2. Fairs are events where art works from
galleries chosen by the organizers are
sold. The most famous one is in Basel,
S w i t ze r l a n d . In contrast, biennales are
non-commercial art events (exhibitions)
that display works selected by
c o m m i s s i o n e r s. By defin i t i o n , they are
held every two years.The most recognize d
biennales take place in Venice, Italy and
Kassel,Germany.
Without calling them by their name, Beninese artist Georges Adeagbo, 59,had been doing installations for
over 20 years when Frenchman Jean-Michel Rousset came scouting around the capital Cotonou in search
of new artistic talents for a big collector. By chance, he fell upon Adeagbo’s home and discovered his work
(above picture).That was back in April 1993.A few months later, Adeagbo’s pieces went on show in France
for the first time. At the beginning of this year, works by the Beninese artist were exhibited at the
prestigious P.S.1 museum in New York.
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
T
JOHN VINCE
PROFESSOR OF DIGITAL MEDIA AT BOURNEMOUTH UNIVERSITY (UNITED KINGDOM)
When the media
meet as one
Now the Internet’s star has faded, a new buzzword is circulating in the corridors
of the world’s media. But will “digital convergence” really be able to keep its promise
of communication and information anytime, anywhere, in any shape or form?
he past 40 years have witnessed an
extraordinary evolution. From slow
expensive machines controlled by punched
c a r d s, computers have become low-cost,
powerful units taking up no more space
than a briefcase. S i m u l t a n e o u s l y,our world
has become interlaced with telephone wires,
optic fib r e s, undersea cables, m i c r o w a v e
l i n k s, television channels and satellite
communications.
At the crossing of these two
developments stands the Internet—a direct
result of computer technology intersecting
with communication technology. But for
many in the world of today’s media,this is
merely a first landmark in what promises to
be a giant upheaval in the way people
communicate, relax and work. This is the
era of digital convergence.
According to a recent article in
Scientific A m e r i c a n, convergence is in
principle “the union of audio, video and
data communications into a single source,
received on a single device, delivered by a
single connection.” Digital technology has
already provided a medium for integrating
media that until now required distinct
channels of communication: we can now
send emails using our televisions or text
messages over mobile phones. Real-time
video can be transmitted over radio
c h a n n e l s, while television and radio can be
received on Personal Computers (PCs).
Hyped-up precedents
Full digital convergence promises real-
time access to information anywhere in the
world,and global communication through
t e x t ,g r a p h i c s,video and audio. In fact, t h e r e
seems to be no technological limit to what
might be possible.“ The reality of ‘ a n y w h e r e,
anytime’ access to broadband digital
networks is going to make our lives freer and
f u l l e r,”Gerald Levin,chief executive offic e r
of AOL Time Wa r n e r, has promised. B u t
technology alone cannot bring about such a
w o r l d :as long as consumers and companies
do not embrace it,convergence is likely to go
the way of several hyped-up predecessors.
Over a decade ago, for example, v i r t u a l
reality was the technology of the future,
and many people anticipated a day where
we would be wearing head-mounted
displays and interacting with all manner
of virtual environments. At the time there
was real concern about changes in industrial
practices and social behaviour brought
about by this technology. So what happened
to this vision? We l l , we got it wrong.
Currently, the home computer is the main
interface to the Internet. But relatively few
people in the world have access to PCs, a n d
few would argue that they are ideal for the
purpose—they crash and freeze because
◗ M E D I A
44 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
Watch of the future: a digital audio player on which music can be downloaded to a
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
they were not designed for widespread
Internet use.
In promising to fuse media as diverse as
t e l e v i s i o n , telephone communication,v i d e o
g a m e s, music and data transmission, t h e
era of digital convergence goes one better
than yesterday’s celebrated “information
s u p e r h i g h w a y.”Yet in doing so, it also raises
critical questions: what services are needed,
what is the ideal platform, will it be fully
interactive? Can the old be so easily
combined with the new?
At the root of any digital application
stands a binary coding system: d e s i g n e r s
of early computers found that only when
using such a system could their computers
be relied upon to give consistent results.Th e
binary code enables numbers, letters and
characters to be assigned unique digital
patterns that can be stored on magnetic
t a p e, compact discs, DVD and computer
fil e s.These digital codes can then be readily
transmitted via copper cable, fibre optics or
as radio waves. Once in a digital format,
t e x t ,a u d i o,graphics and video can therefore
all be processed by one common
technology with great accuracy.
Skeptical consumers
Yet achieving this single technology is
far from straightforward. There are
currently three major television broadcast
s t a n d a r d s, and they are all incompatible
with each another. But this is nothing
compared to the many technologies
supporting the Internet, each with a
different bandwidth and physical media.
The problems faced in designing platforms
and communication systems that will be
accepted across the world can appear
insuperable.
One body, the International
Organization for Standardization (ISO), i s
at the heart of efforts to devise world
standards for coding audio-visual
i n f o r m a t i o n . Its Motion Picture Experts’
Group has already notched up several
important benchmarks via standards for
storage media and broadcast, while the
MPEG-4 (now under development) will
establish the means for storage, t r a n s m i s s i o n
and interactive manipulation of video
data—the essence of
what digital
convergence promises
to deliver.
Even once global
standards are assured,
h o w e v e r, a further
obstacle lies in wait.
The Internet is
plagued by long,
erratic response times
because it is a pull-technology, driven by
patterns of user demands. P u s h - t e ch n o l o gy,
on the other hand, reverses the
r e l a t i o n s h i p : servers simply send
information to passive users, as in
television and radio. But if some form of
combination between one-way television
flow and interactive Internet is to be the
basis of our future media,it is hard to see
how it could be operated.Current network
technology could not support a pull-based
approach towards television, while a push-
based approach would simply duplicate
what we have already: n o r m a l ,
uninteractive television or radio.
Yet the problem of fusing Internet with
television is also one of defining the services
o f f e r e d . As Steve Jo b s, chief executive
o f ficer of A p p l e,has observed:“TV is where
you go to turn your brain off; the computer
is where you go to turn it on.” I n f o r m a t i o n ,
entertainment and relaxation appear at
first to be quite different needs. S e r i o u s
doubts remain over whether consumers
will be interested in having to make the
sort of mental effort associated with
computing while also settling down in front
of a sitcom.
“There is a large group of people who
have no interest in the new media and,
contrary to many predictions, that segment
is shrinking slower that the icebergs in
Antarctica,” recently warned Horst Stipp,
director of research at NBC television
network in the United States.
Besides the issue of consumer habits,
infrastructure costs are set to be immense,
and will have to be met by national states or
the private sector before being passed on to
u s e r s. Platforms do not necessarily have to
be expensive. The mobile phone is a good
example of how something that is
technologically sophisticated can almost
be given away, with its cost recovered
through service charges. Users are then
coerced through clever marketing to
upgrade to newer phones with more
features to reinforce their dependence.
The creation and copyright protection
of digital content are other vital issues.We
have already seen that satellite television
provides us with so
many extra channels
that television
programmes have to be
repeated indefinitely to
fill the available space.
But perhaps digital
convergence will solve
this by making it easier
to create totally
synthetic television
programs employing virtual sets and actors.
One might even suggest this has already
started to happen.
Whatever the outcome, it is obvious
that technology will play an increasing part
in our everyday lives. Beyond technology,
digital convergence embraces the services,
industrial practices and social behaviour
that form modern society. We have in our
hands the technology to construct the most
sophisticated machines ever built, but if
they are unusable, simply because of their
operating instructions, then recent lessons
have taught us they will not survive.
Whatever we design must be simple,
reliable and useful. Perhaps this is where
a r t i ficial intelligence will play an important
role. ■
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 45
“TV is where you go
to turn your brain
off; the computer
is where you go
to turn it on.”
o a memory card via the Internet.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
D
◗ M E D I A
INTERVIEW BY IVAN BRISCOE
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
All power to the baro n s ?
Digital technologies may promise a host of new channels and activities,
but the stranglehold of big business is set to tighten, says leading media commentator Robert
McChesney*
o you see digital convergence as a
technological process or as a wider change
in the media?
The notion that there is technological
convergence is undeniable.The transition
to digital format of virtually all media
and forms of communication is on its way
to being completed in the near future.
But the convergence of media ownership
is even more striking, and in many
respects anticipates technological
c o n v e r g e n c e. For most consumers, i t ’s the
convergence of ownership that has
probably had the most direct effect on
their media experience to date. And I
think these changes in ownership will go
a long way towards shaping how the
digital world will eventually look.
How exactly is ownership changing?
The crucial trend is vertical
i n t e g r a t i o n , or more broadly,
conglomeration of media ownership. In
the United States for example—and this
is a pattern that could have been found in
most countries with market economies—
the media industries such as music or
cinema in the 1950s each tended to be
dominated by three or four different
c o m p a n i e s. What has happened in the
U.S. and globally over the last 50 years is
that the largest media companies have
become conglomerates,meaning that the
largest film studio also owns a television
network or a music company, r a d i o
s t a t i o n s, m a g a z i n e s, cable systems, s a t e l l i t e
systems, video rental chains.1 What you
have is a tremendous web of power built
up by the largest firms, which have
become dominant players in several
media sectors. All this predates digital
c o n v e r g e n c e.Digital convergence is really
the cherry on top of the sundae.
But will the new digital technology not
offer greater choice and allow new
companies to enter the market?
There is a paradox with the rise of
the Internet specifically and digital
communications more broadly. Th e
standard belief has been that all of a
sudden,the traditional market power of
these media giants is going to fall because
the barriers to entering media markets
are being radically lowered, if not
e l i m i n a t e d . But the problem with this
theory is that it’s technology driven. I t
makes perfect sense technologically, but
what it misses—and this is the perceived
wisdom on Wall Street—is that new
technologies are not going to spawn a
wave of commercially viable media
entrepreneurs or businesses due to the
market power of existing companies.
Technologies are developed in the market
for the most part, and the ones that are
aggressively pursued and promoted are
the ones most likely to offer a profitable
return for the dominant companies.
What effects does concentration have on
the media we consume?
Firstly, you see the incessant rise of
what I call hyper- c o m m e r c i a l i s m ,
meaning that these companies are quite
rationally trying to make a profit from
every aspect of their media services—
something they can do much more easily
in a non-competitive market. If you don’t
like the fact that in the U.S. the average
commercial radio station has 18 to
20 minutes of advertisements per hour,
you don’t really have any alternative,
they all do the same. The flipside of this
prevalence of commercial values
throughout our media culture is a decline
in public service content. Journalism that
does hard investigation or raises serious
social issues doesn’t make economic sense
for these companies—it costs a lot of
money and the pay-off isn’t high.
F u r t h e r m o r e, the largest media
companies now rank among the largest
firms in the entire economy. Th e s e
companies are not neutral bystanders on
the sidelines of society. Th e y ’re main
players right in the heart of it,with distinct
self-interests on the crucial issues of the
day.
What do you believe should be done?
Our traditional notions of what
proper media ownership is must be re-
e v a l u a t e d . But the sort of public and
political debate on the issues, at least in
the U.S., is the last thing on earth large
media companies want to encourage.As
long as this issue is kept in the smoke-
filled back rooms and lobbyists talk to
p o l i t i c i a n s, the position we have now will
continue. ■
* Professor of Communications at the
University of Illinois
1. The seven largest media conglomerates
in the world are now Disney,AO L - Ti m e
Wa r n e r, S o n y, News Corporation,
46 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
WHEN THE MEDIA MEET AS ONE
Announcing the AOL Time Warner merger.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
ou often say you’re
first and fore m o s t
a storyteller, a
“ g r i o t .” How does
this deep-ro o t e d
identity affect your
a p p roach to
theatre?
I draw my inspiration,my energy,
from meeting people. In my corner of
Africa—my parents were from
G u i n e a , I was born in Mali and I’m
Burkinabé by adoption—such
encounters are important, s i n c e
outsiders are the ones who bring us
what we don’t know.
I didn’t go to any drama school,
unless you count the great school of the
street—the school of life. When I was
y o u n g, a theatre producer friend,
Boubacar Dicko, asked me several
times to play parts for him.But it was
the last thing I dreamed of: at the time,
I was playing for Burkina Fa s o ’s
national football team!
Did you have a bad impression of
theatre?
When I was a kid, I enjoyed k o t e b a
p e r f o r m a n c e s, an old African tradition.
The word means “big snail.”They took
place in our neighbourhood and there
would be three circles—one of
children,another made up of women
and a third one of men. But in those
colonial days, the k o t e b a was dying out
and being replaced by Western-style
t h e a t r e. The French started drama
contests between all their West A f r i c a n
c o l o n i e s, which later became eight
c o u n t r i e s. Consciously or not, the idea
was to instil us with Western culture.
Sotigui Ko u y a t é
The wise man of the stage
Y
Despite years away from home and a career spanning many cultures, Malian actor
and griot Sotigui Kouyaté has not strayed from his foremost mission: to break ignorance
of Africa’s living traditions and spark encounters across continents
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
As Prospero, in Peter Brook’s staging of The Tempest.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Antigone, staged by Sotigui Kouyaté with M
“The best way to kill a tree is to cut
We weren’t allowed to speak our own
language at school. If we did, t h e
teacher would make us wear a piece of
wood or metal around the neck with a
m u l e ’s head on it and deprive us of
lunch. The best way to kill a tree is to
cut it from its roots.This We s t e r n - s t y l e
theatre also helped steer A f r i c a n
intellectuals away from the campaign
for independence.
What made you change heart?
I love dance and in 1966, I finally
agreed to be in a historical play
produced by my friend Boubacar
Dicko which featured a war dance. H e
also asked me to play a part as adviser
to the king. The play won a prize and
went on tour in the region. I became
attached to the show, and then to
a n o t h e r, based on a play written by
my uncle.
Gradually, acting grew on me. But
I wasn’t enamoured by everything—
not the courses run by Fr e n c h
instructors, for example. They told us,
without explaining why,how we should
walk on stage, which seemed far too
affected to me. They would ask us to
imagine a ship,to picture it on the wall,
but I couldn’t see anything. I left,
though by then, I ’d really become
taken with the profession.
I set up my own theatre company in
1966 with a group of 25 people.
Burkinabé radio gave us a place to
work and we mainly did
improvisations. I’d go to work at the
ministry for labour and public
administration in the morning, p l a y
football in the afternoon,and then go
off to theatre rehearsals. At the same
time, I was also writing my first play,
The Crocodile’s Lament. It was about
being sensitive, a gift with which you
can even manage to caress a crocodile,
as it actually happens in several regions
of Burkina Fa s o, where crocodiles are
viewed as sacred.
Sensitivity— is that what actors need
most? 
When I give courses, I do a lot of
work on being open, sensitive and
learning to communicate. Po l i t i c i a n s
always make speeches about
communication and dialogue. But it
all has to do with economic interests,
never human ones. You can’t
communicate if you don’t listen, and
people don’t listen to each other, e v e n
if they live in the same country.
E v e r y o n e ’s absorbed in themselves,
so exclusion grows. People risk their
lives to leave their country, and the
authorities close their eyes on all that.
Finding another way of communicating,
t h rough the efforts of actors fro m
different cultures working together, is
key to the approach of Peter Bro o k ,
who you met in 1983 for the gre a t
Indian epic The Mahabharata.
When I joined the Bouffes du
Nord Theatre in Paris, I had no
intention of staying in Fr a n c e.I ’d taken
a year’s sabbatical from my job at the
m i n i s t r y. The problem—or if you
prefer, the luck in my case—was that
The Mahabharata was a hit. I asked
the ministry to extend my leave, and
they gave me another year unpaid.
But when that was up, the play’s run
still hadn’t ended. I didn’t have an
understudy, and the play lasted nine
hours. I was brought up not to aban-
don something halfway through, I
c o u l d n ’t leave the company. But I’d
been with the civil service for 29 years
and was just a year away from being
able to draw my pension. I lost that,
and four months later, T h e
M a h a b h a r a t a closed and I was left
without a job back home. I didn’t want
to return to my family empty-handed
“A MAN WITH AN EXTRAO R D I N A RY
PRESENCE AND QUA L I T Y ”
When casting The Mahabharata, Peter Brook’s assistant scoured through film 
studios in search of an actor to take on one of the lead roles, Bhisma the sage.
“I saw one shot of a tree and a man as tall and slender as this tree, with an extraordinary
presence and quality. It was Sotigui,” recalls Brook in a recent documentary about the actor. Born
in 1936 in Bamako (Mali), Kouyaté belongs to an illustrious family of griots—masters of words
who are at once genealogists, historians, masters of ceremonies, advisers, mediators, singers and
musicians. He has handed down all these talents, as a composer, dancer, actor and father, to his
own children and a multitude of “spiritual children” dispersed across the world, for whom he is
a precious guide. Filling each of his roles with profound dignity, he has appeared in some 60 films,
most recently in Little Senegal, directed by Rachid Bouchareb. As one of Peter Brook’s longtime
actors, he will tour in several shows over the next year, including The Man Who, based on Oliver
Sacks’ The man who mistook his wife for a hat, and The Suit, adapted from a story by the late
South African writer Can Themba. ■
48 The UNESCO Courier - October 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
because as the oldest son,I was their
p i l l a r.It was very hard.Here in Fr a n c e,
I could struggle, work and continue
to explore my culture and being. Art
has never fed anyone in Africa.
You are said to have slipped into the
part of the wise man Bhisma.
When I joined Peter Brook, I didn’t
feel out of place. I could see everything
B rook has said your imagination was
nourished by a culture where the visible
and invisible worlds are not separa t e. I n
the parts you play, it often seems as if
you’re on an initiation voyage.
I come from a culture where
nature is very important in a person’s
life. Your soul is first incarnated in a
tree, then in an animal and then in a
living human being. Some people are
even named after trees.All this means
everything in the world is alive.
U n f o r t u n a t e l y, humans increasingly
think they’re the only living beings
on earth.
In Fr e n c h , you can point to
someone and say “ t h e r e ’s a person.” I n
several African languages, when you
say “person,” the word is followed by
something that means roughly “ t h e
person of the person.” That is, e a c h
human being comprises many
i d e n t i t i e s, which are in fact other
p e o p l e. Daily life is about discovering
all these beings within. This can only
happen  through  meeting other
people.
“When you meet another, instead of
losing yourself in his eyes, recognize
yourself—and perhaps you’ll see
y o u r s e l f,” the saying goes. Our wise
men tell us that ignorance is the worst
thing that can happen to anyone, w o r s e
than illness or death. And the most
ignorant person of all, they say, i s
someone who has never stepped
was happening inside a circle, just like
in A f r i c a , and on the third day, he took
my hand, looked me in the eye and
said:“Sotigui,from today, you’re part
of the family.” That was a magical
moment for me. He didn’t say:“ Yo u ’r e
part of our group, of our company.”
H e ’d understood the soul of an
A f r i c a n , h e ’d embraced my culture.
Brook is a universal man. For him,
there are no barriers between people,
which is rare in today’s world. Some
people don’t understand my loyalty
to Brook. But how can I not be loyal to
someone who defends such values in
today’s world, where separation and
individualism hold sway?
At his International Centre for
Theatre Research were 22 actors from
18 different countries. In T h e
M a h a b h a r a t a , the five Pandava
brothers were played by a German, a
Fr e n c h m a n , an Iranian, an Italian and
a Senegalese. This bothered no one,
and the play travelled the world for
four years. Only Brook could have
pulled  off such a feat.There aren’t any
races or skin colours in his mind.I’ve
also played Prospero in The Tempest
under him. It was the first time a
European director, a British
Shakespearean to boot, had staged
this play with a black Prospero.
h Malian actors from the Mandeka Theatre.
it f rom its ro o t s”
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 51) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396 French francs ( 6 0 . 35 ) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 48French francs ( 7. 32 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .10 )
2 years: 211French francs ( 32 .15 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:     Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
“Is there any sin so serious
that it can never be forg i v e n?”
outside his or her house.
Your own work as a stage dire c t o r
i s enriched by such contacts and
e n c o u n t e rs. You once pro d u c e d
Antigone with Malian actors.
I t ’s through differences that you
find ways to work together. At the
request of the Jean Moulin Museum
in Paris, I produced a show in 1999 to
mark the centenary of the Fr e n c h
wartime resistance leader’s birth. I
adapted his diary, Le Premier Combat,
and merged it into a novel by the
Cameroonian writer Ferdinand Oyono,
Le Vieux Nègre et la Médaille. Th i s
shocked some of Moulin’s old
c o m r a d e s, but the director of the
museum, a historian, firmly defended
the project.
In recent months, I ’ve been working
on O e d i p u s, which follows naturally
from A n t i g o n e. I ’ve based myself on
several versions of the story, f r o m
Sophocles to Jean A n o u i l h , and even a
thriller on the theme. I ’ve read the
analyses of psychoanalysts from Fr e u d
to Tobie Nathan. All focus on incest.
For me, however, Oedipus is about the
problem of facing up to oneself. I ’ m
not trying to provide an answer, I ’ m
just raising the issue to foster awareness
of the battle that’s inherent in every
destiny, namely not to let ourselves be
overcome by fatalism.Is Oedipus guilty
of killing his father? At first he was
hailed as a hero who rescued a suffering
c o u n t r y. Then he was rejected by his
own sons and stoned to death before
the wall of Thebes by the very people
h e ’d saved. H e ’s a man on the run,
consumed by suffering, by an obsession.
If he’d come to terms with his human
weaknesses, he wouldn’t have gouged
his eyes out. I end my O e d i p u s b y
looking at what I think is the most
serious issue—the refusal to forgive.
The choir exhorts the gods to praise
the hero after his vain ordeal.
It’s an appeal to reason…
Forgiveness doesn’t heal everything
but it can make some things better. Is
there any sin so serious that it can
never be forgiven? Is evil 100 percent
e v i l , or can we find a little crack within
that can draw it closer to good?
You stand for deep-rooted A f r i c a n
v a l u e s, just like the character you played
in Rachid Bouchare b ’s film Little Senegal
(2000). Do you think these values are
under threat?
I’m always afraid of that,but I try
to fight with words and culture. Fo r
example in Bobo Dioulasso, Burkina
Faso’s second city, my children and I
opened a cultural centre a few years
a g o. I set it up in the courtyard
belonging to my father, a very large
s p a c e.Today it’s a place where you can
learn music, percussion and painting, a
meeting place where we invite foreign
painters to teach courses.We also wish
to make it into a computer training
centre. Besides which,we are seeking
to create a university of A f r i c a n
traditions where we could develop
ways to preserve this heritage and
deepen knowledge of our culture.
You also set up the Mandeka T h e a t re in
M a l i , which encourages literary and
artistic creation.
We founded the Mandeka in 1997,
at the same time as France was
deporting charter plane loads of Malian
and Senegalese immigrants every day.
While that was happening, actors in
Bamako were still asking me how they
could come to France, as if they were
blind to how immigrants were being
t r e a t e d . When I advised them not to
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George’s Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
Gordon & Gotch Australia Pty. Ltd., Private Bag 290, Burwood VIC 3125 .
Fax: 03 9888 8561
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Partner Press, 11 rue Charles Parenté, B-1070 Brussels.
Fax: (32 2) 556 41 46/Tel.: (32 2) 556 41 40/partner press@ampnet.be
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: UNES CO O f fice, 8 Po o rvi Marg, Vasant Vihar, New Delhi 110 0 57.
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Editions Le Printemps Ltée., 4 Route du Club, Va c o a s .
Fax: 686 7302. 
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
UNES CO Etxea, Alda Urquijo 60, Ppal. Dcha., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: Distriplumes, Apartado 49232, Colinas Bello Monte, 10 4 2
A Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 979 8 36 0
UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce C/C
Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 28 6 0 326 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
g o, t h e y ’d stare at me as if to say:“ L o o k
at you,you’re doing alright over there,
and so are your sons.” The easiest way
out in the end was to say I couldn’t help
anyone in coming to France. But I was
ready to do what I could by fin d i n g
them jobs, courses or training. This is
what I had in mind when I founded the
Mandeka—stopping young people
from fleeing, helping them to win
respect through having a job and
showing people what they could do.
Antigone was performed in France by
actors from Mandeka.Les Bouffes du
Nord agreed to produce O e d i p u s, i n
which Mandeka’s Malian actors will
perform with French ones.
African theatre and films still have a
very low world profile, unlike African
music.
There is no African cultural policy.
Our filmmakers don’t have the money
to produce and distribute their work.
A few years ago, a lot more films were
given loans against eventual box-offic e
receipts from France because their
s u b j e c t s, often ethnographic, a t t r a c t e d
d o n o r s. But as African directors
became interested in other issues and
left folklore to one side, they secured
less and less money.As for the actors,
for years you could look through the
budgets of African films and not find
any mention of them.
In Mali and Burkina Faso, the film
authorities do what they can, but that
doesn’t go much further than lending
you vehicles and cameras.And it’s even
worse for theatre. The troupes you see
a b r o a d , in Europe,have to live off their
own resources.You can’t even say they
were once better off. When I founded
my own dance troupe in Burkina Faso in
1 9 7 1 , I received no funding. I went into
debt to buy musical instruments and
c o s t u m e s. Several times the government
seized them so they could represent the
country in foreign festivals or greet a
visit by the French president—without
ever giving us anything in return.
Do you feel you’re carrying a message
from Africa?
L e t ’s be modest.Africa is vast, a n d
it would be pretentious to speak in its
n a m e. I’m fighting the battle with
words because I’m a storyteller,a griot.
Rightly or wrongly, they call us masters
of the spoken word. Our duty is to
encourage the West to appreciate
Africa more. It’s also true that many
Africans don’t really know their own
c o n t i n e n t . And if you forget your
culture, you lose sight of yourself. It is
said that “the day you no longer know
where you’re going, just remember
where you came from.” Our strength
lies in our culture. Everything I do as a
s t o r y t e l l e r, a griot, stems from this
rooting and openness. ■
INTERVIEW BY
CYNTHIA GUTTMAN
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Master of ceremonies:a griot performs in Guinea.
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
54th year
Published monthly in 28 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Louise Corradini
French edition: Sophie Boukhari 
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Philippe Demenet
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Shiraz Sidhva
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Gérard Prosper,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Pushplata Taneja (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzir a Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian:Boris Ilyenko (Belgrade)
Sardinian:Diego Corraine (Nuoro)
Russian: Valeri Kharkin (Moscow)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing the
credit line reads “Reprinted from the UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author’s
n a m e. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering
p o s t a g e. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by:
(1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,
A n nA r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,
Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL : C1 - OCTOBER2001
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly
in Paris by UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e.
Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and additional mailing offic e s.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 10-2001-OPI 00-592 A
October 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.org
U N E S C O Publishing
Blue Gold
Interactive Encyclopaedia of Water
■ A mine of interdisciplinary information on water, it
combines a scientific and an attractive approach. 
■ A family and an educational tool.
CD-ROM
PC-MAC
45,58/299 FF
graphics,
22 video clips, 
600 photographs, 
8 slide shows, charts,
diagrams, maps
pc-mac
UNESCO Publishing /
Strass Productions
Also available in French
El Niño
Fact and fiction
By Bruno Voituriez and Guy Jacques
■ The book offers a tour of the Earth’s climate machine
to understand one of its normal but extreme components. 
■ In a straightforward language for non-specialists, a
lively account without sacrificing scientific rigour.
Digital version available at
www.unesco.org/publishing
For young adults
Printed edition:
16,77/110,00 FF
Digital edition: 
8,38/55 FF
140 pages,
15,5 x 24 cm 
Illustrations, photos
Also available
in French 
and Spanish
Focus:
■ When private companies set the research agenda
■ Universities as barometers of free
e x p r e s s i o n : flashpoints around the globe
■ Russian historians vs society’s amnesia
■ A f r i c a ’s battle for academic freedom
■ Medical journals come clean with new guidelines
■ The race to privatize knowledge in
the information age
Features include:
■ A passion for Thai boxing
■ Coastal troubles ten years after Rio
■ Turning the page:when countries rewrite
history textbooks
■ The new fight for economic rights
■ One Koran and four great Islamic schools
■ Exploring our behaviour with French
psychiatrist Boris Cyrulnik
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
November 2001:
Politics, profit and
the university
How free are
scholars?
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 28 languages
]]>
</page>
</document>
