<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="124272eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
P ro fil de
l ’ i n t e r n a u t e
en rupture
de To i l e
Le nucléaire,
p a ra d e
à l’effet
de serre ?
I t s u k u s h i m a
et son temple:
le temps
re t ro u v é
Afrique CFA:1000 F.CFA,Antilles:18 FF, Belgique:160 FB, Canada:3,95$Can,
Espagne:550 Ptas, USA:4,25 $US, Luxembourg:154 F.Lux, Portugal:700 Esc ,
Suisse:6,20 FS , United Kingdom:2,5£,Maroc:20 DH.
A cry of
revolt fro m
A f g h a n
w o m e n
M e d i a :
the No th’s
poorly ver-
sed viewers
Tuning into
t h e “ n e w
c o n s c i e n c e ”
o f Islam 
E c o n o m i c
r i g h t s :
the big
c o m e b a c k
November 2001
Canada:$4.65 Can,United Kingdom:£2.5,USA:$4.25
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
7, place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France
Fax: +33 1 45 68 57 37
Internet: www.unesco.org/publishing
E-mail: publishing.promotion@unesco.orgU N E S C O Publishing
Child Abuse on the Internet
Ending the Silence
n The major works carried out in African countries, in
Albania, Brazil, Guatemala, the Philippines and Sri Lanka.
n The efforts to share information and build networks.
220 pp., 21.5 x 14 cm
23,78/156 FF
Keys to the 21st Century
Edited by Jérôme Bindé
n Over thirty well-known scientists, intellectual 
and creators offer the keys to start the 21st century in full
awareness. 
n Essential issues for the future and concrete paths 
for action.
400 pp., 22.5 x 15 cm
Printed edition: 28.97/190 FF
Education for a culture of peace in a
gender perspective
By Betty Reardon
n The first educational tool for the transformation towards
peace that fully integrates a gender perspective.
n For educators who want to be part of a global movement
towards peace.
n A manual to develop the skills and capacities to build 
and maintain a culture of peace.
200 pp., 24 x 17 cm
Printed edition: 18.29/120 FF
Digital edition: 9.15/60 FF
See the special selection of UNESCO books 
and CD ROMs on Dialogue among civilizations at
www.unesco.org/publishing
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
◗ PEOPLE AND PLACES
4 Afghan women: knowledge and revolt
From the city of Faizabad—home to the only university in Afghanistan open to women—Cheke b a
Hachemi speaks of the suffering of her people.
Photographs by Antoinette de Jong, text by Chekeba Hachemi
◗ PLANET
10 A coastal balancing act
Tourism and sprawling cities are threatening our coastlines. Local groups have a pivotal role
to play in protecting them. Interview by Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
12 Dilemmas in a tropical paradise Gerardo Tena
◗ WORLD OF LEARNING
13 Getting the spin right on history
Profound geopolitical changes have led many countries to revise their history textbooks. Fa l k
Pingel discusses the pitfalls of the exercise. Interview by Shiraz Sidhva
15 Germany: two histories reunited Thomas Schnee
◗ ETHICS
36 Economic rights: the big comeback
Is economic injustice one source of the September 11 attacks? For the past few years,N G O s
have made economic rights a priority. Philippe Demenet
◗ CULTURE
39 Tune into “the new conscience of Islam”
For philosopher Abdou Fi l a l i - A n s a r y, the meshing of religion and politics can only be loosened by
providing more arenas for open debate. Interview by Sophie Boukhari
42 One Islam, a mosaic of believers Slimane Zéghidour
◗ MEDIA
44 An unseen world: how the media portrays the poor
Western viewers tend to be poorly versed on developing countries.The author of a critical study
discusses why and what can be done. Greg Philo
◗ TALKING TO…
47 Boris Cyrulnik: surviving the trauma of life
Violence and broken families are leaving a growing number of young adults traumatized.A
French psychologist offers clues to recovery and “ r e s i l i e n c e.”
Fo c u s Politics and pro fit
S c h o l a rs at risk
The end of the Cold War and the transition to
d e m o c racy in many developing nations were expec-
ted to give a fresh boost to academic fre e d o m . B u t
e v e r y w h e re, s c h o l a rs are running up against mul-
tiple pre s s u re s. In some places, they risk prison or
death if they are too outspoke n . In the rich world,
and even more acutely in the South, cutbacks in
public funding are forcing universities to secure cor-
p o rate funds, a trend that can pro v o ke blatant
c o n flicts of intere s t .
C O N T E N T S
NOVEMBER 2001
Detailed table of contents on page
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily re p resent the opinions of UN E S C O or those of the edi-
t o rs of the UN E S C O C o u r i e r. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the UN E S C O C o u r i e r s t a f f. The boundaries on maps do
not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UN E S C O or the
United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
I N T H I S I S S U E
◗ Freedoms
The international community lagged
in waking up to Afghanistan’s
unrolling tragedy, particularly that
endured by its women.But it also
ignored their fierce resistance against
the oppression of the Taliban
(pp. 4-9). This regime is the most
extreme incarnation of religious
fundamentalism,which also prevails
in other Muslim countries where
religious authorities uphold
an ambiguous relationship with
governments. For Moroccan
philosopher Abdou Filali-Ansary, this
meshing of religion and politics can
only be loosened by providing more
arenas for open debate (pp. 39-43).
The need for open and scientific
discussion is essential for countries
around the world engaged in
rewriting their history textbooks
following the geopolitical upheavals
of the past ten years (pp. 13-15).Open
debate is also the cornerstone of
university life, yet multiple pressures,
both from the economic and political
fronts, are hampering the sacrosanct
concept of academic freedom
(dossier, pp. 16-35).
◗ Divides
Is the deep economic divide running
along the North-South fault line one
of the root causes of the September
11 attacks? For the past few years,
human rights organizations have
made the fight against these
inequalities a foremost priority, but
are they being heard (pp. 36-38)?
Public opinion in rich countries often
seems ill-versed on what’s happening
in the developing world,in part
reflecting the media’s overarching
dependence on audience ratings
(pp. 44-46).Another divide is caused
by the impact of violence and broken
families on many teenagers. But
eclectic psychologist Boris Cyrulnik
says that with the right support,they
have the capacity to pull through,
even in extremely difficult conditions
(pp. 47-51).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
The only university open to Afghan women is located in Faizabad in northern Afghanistan, an area not
under Taliban control.Antoinette de Jong photographed students there
in April 2001. In this first-hand account, NGO director Chekeba Hachemi speaks
of the suffering of her people, but also of their spirit of resistance. She appeals to the world community
not to let Afghanistan become “an inconsolable country.”
PHOTOGRAPHS BY ANTOINETTE DE JONG,TEXT BY CHEKEBA HACHEMI
ANTOINETTE DE JONGIS A DUTCH PHOTOGRAPHER; CHEKEBA HACHEMI IS PRESIDENT OFTHE NGO AFGHANISTAN LIBRE*
Afghan women:
knowledge and
The majority of these students fled Kabul after Taliban forces captured the city and banned education for women.“In the Koran, it is stated that every Muslim
has to acquire as much knowledge as possible. Men and women alike,” says one student.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 5
It took the international community a long time,a very long time,
to grasp what a tremendous danger the Taliban regime in A f g h a-
nistan posed. Dangerous for Afghans—their freedoms, their
hopes for peace and their ancient culture—and for all the
w o r l d ’s peoples.The hallucinating pictures of the September 11
events ended up convincing us that Evil was at work in Kabul.
Ye t , we had been warned.A few months earlier, other pictures
had sparked indignation around the world:women trapped in
fabric dungeons, peering at us from behind narrow bars:A f g h a n s
in chadris. And from behind those bars, inside those moving,
ghostly dungeons, frail, angry voices spoke to us. For Afghan
women are like Afghan men:courageous. Bravery is an ances-
tral virtue in Afghanistan.They spoke to journalists about the
hell in which they were imprisoned, their dark solitude and
the dark future of their people, their children and their betro-
thed.
They resisted. True to their reputation of pride and dignity,
women living in areas under Taliban control set up underground
s c h o o l s, held secret press conferences and organized mutual
assistance networks to defend themselves against ignorance
hunger and terror.Women who had managed to take refuge in
free areas begged Western journalists to tell the whole world that
Kabul had turned into a prison that would some day become a
cemetery.
Why didn’t we pay more attention to these women? We
believed they were the latest in an endless string of misogyny’s
v i c t i m s,one that has plagued so many places for so long. In a way,
we trivialized their agony by likening it to comparable pain
that others have suffered. That was a huge mistake, for the
Taliban regime resembles nothing that we have ever seen,and
the women of Afghanistan have been at the heart of an incom-
parable tragedy.Aw a r e, c o n c e r n e d , empathetic women on the fiv e
continents listened,mobilized and demanded that their govern-
ments do something. But their appeals fell on deaf ears.
Ye s, the officials said,Afghan women are suffering, but it’s not
our fault and besides, what can we do about it? Yet everything
was still possible at the time. Governments could have put pres-
sure on the Taliban and heeded General Massoud,who so feared
the day when they would carry the fires of war to our own coun-
tries.That day is here.We have reacted too late, when violence
We trivialized the agony of
Afghan women by likening 
it to comparable pain that
others have suffered.
That was a huge mistake.
A F G H A N I S T A N
Mazar-i-Sharif
KABUL
P A K I S T A N
T U R K M E N I S T A N UZBTN. T A J I -
K I S T A N
Faizabad
n :
re v o l t
Professor Ali Yussuf Pur, former head of the Kabul medical faculty,
teaching in the university’s only classroom.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
Afghan women:
knowledge and re v o l t
This time, if we fail to hear this
brilliant, exhausted nation’s
appeal, nothing will be left of it.
The Afghans’ legendary laughter
will die out. And tears that no
one sees will flow beneath the
chadris.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 7
Since the Taliban came to power, photographs, television and movie images have been banned. Tapes of Titanic, one of the most
coveted films,circulate underground at great risk.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
Since the Taliban seized power in Kabul, Faizabad’s population has doubled with an influx of refugees from the Afghan capital as well as
from Mazar-i-Charif, where the Taliban systematically slaughtered civilians, according to student accounts.
According to Mari,the deputy director of the Pedagogical Institute, which shares quarters with the medical faculty,
professors earn $1.50 per month, a sum often paid with a three to six month delay.
◗ P E O P L E A N D P L A C E S
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 9
is the only possible response.And we have added a new burden
to the already crushed silhouette of Afghan women.
Now they are wandering through the streets to the sounds of
explosions beneath a sky that is raining bombs. I believe the time
has come to ask Afghan women for forgiveness. Why do I say
“ w e,” when I myself was born in Afghanistan and head a huma-
nitarian organization that has been campaigning for years to free
Afghan women? Because there are two kinds of women:those
condemned to wear the ch a d r i—under pain of death—and
those who are free not to.
I fall into the latter category.And I want to say it again:we
have not done enough.The time has come.Afghanistan is on the
brink of an abyss. This time, if we fail to hear this brilliant,
exhausted nation’s appeal,nothing will be left of it.The A f g h a n s ’
legendary laughter will die out.And tears that no one sees will
flow beneath the chadris. Let’s make our own the destiny of
these people whom blind History seems determined to abolish,
to annihilate. Let’s not turn Afghanistan into an inconsolable
country. ■
Afghan women: knowledge and re v o l t
* Afghanistan Libre (“For a free Afghanistan”) is an organiza-
tion that was created to help Afghans living outside Ta l i b a n -
controlled areas to start rebuilding the country.The group focuses
on education,training and micro-economic projects.
It is currently building a high school for 1,000 girls in the Pa n s h i r
Valley, and has opened a workshop for 300 women,who attend
classes in the morning and work in the afternoon.
+ …
For more information on the plight of Afghan women,please refer to
the UNESCO Courier issues dated October 1998 and March 2001.
Students may wear lipstick,but even in this region,they shroud themselves in their chadris before heading out for the day.
They live in permanent fear of the Taliban arriving in this last bulwark of freedom.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
fishing or fishing with aids like dyna-
mite that damage the ecosystem. It des-
troys basic habitats that are key to the
life-cycle of fish and shellfish. The bio-
diversity of a coral reef is like that of a
tropical forest,so it’s vital to put a stop
to such damage.
What do integrated coastal management
projects involve?
They start from the firm belief that
it’s much wiser to avoid damaging the
environment than trying to restore
w h a t ’s already been lost, though the
T
INTERVIEW BY LUCIA IGLESIAS KUNTZ
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
A coastal
balancing act
The rich biodiversity of coastal regions can be protected without chasing away tourism
and other activities. On one condition: that local people play the lead role in steering conservation
projects, says coastal expert Stephen B. Olsen*
he first time coastal protection appeare d
on the international agenda was at the
1992 Rio Earth Summit. What progress
has been made since then?
Quite a lot. We ’ve gone from tal-
king about general concepts to concrete
a c h i e v e m e n t s, such as the Integrated
Coastal Management (ICM) pro-
g r a m m e s.To be effective, these have to
involve conflicting groups such as the
private sector (industry and tourism),
f i s h e r m e n , villagers and NGOs and
make them realize that they have to
work together. In 2000, there were over
300 such programmes operating in 95
c o u n t r i e s, including many developing
n a t i o n s. We ’ve also had to face the
painful fact that not everything can be
s a v e d .We have to make choices because
unfortunately, in some places, popula-
tion pressure is so high that there’s
nothing left to preserve. If you visit the
main Mediterranean tourist areas in
Italy, Spain or Tunisia, you can see the
high price being paid for ill-conceived
development.
So tourism isn’t compatible with pro-
tecting coastal areas?
Not always.Th a t ’s certainly been the
case in large areas of the Mediterranean
and of the United States. But in many
other countries, such as Cuba and Costa
R i c a , you can see much more thoughtful
tourist development going on. A few
years ago, I worked as a consultant on  a
project in the Sabana and Camagüey
i s l a n d s,off the north coast of Cuba, w h e r e
the government had begun to build huge
hotels almost on the beach.You reached
them by p e d r i p l a n e s, roads which crossed
the lagoon and caused major ecolo-
g i c a l and water-flow problems. U n d e r
the project, sponsored by the Global
Environment Fa c i l i t y,1 the Cubans com-
pletely changed the design, location and
density of the islands’ infrastructure,
resulting in very elegant and environ-
mentally friendly tourist facilities. A t
great expense, the p e d r i p l a n e s w e r e
removed and replaced by structures that
allowed the water to flow freely. Today,
the area attracts tourists and the lagoons
are in better condition.
The second World Climate Confere n c e
will be held in South Africa in 2002.
Wh a t ’s the message to it as far as coastal
protection is concerned?
The big challenge is to help local
people change the way they live and
make authorities more responsive.Th e
problem isn’t a technical one,a question
of know-how or even money. You can
do plenty of good things without much
money, as long as you build local capa-
city and commitment and not just send
in outside experts like me.The problem
is that experts often want to create pros-
perity as quickly as possible without
thinking about the future.
But nearly half the global population
lives in coastal areas and 12 of the
world’s 15 biggest cities are by the sea.
What problems does this create for
coastal areas?
The problems are all to do with
human activity, though they aren’t the
same everywhere. The most common
one is the poor location of roads, docks
and infrastructure along coasts; the des-
truction of major habitats such as coral
r e e f s, marine and wetland food sources;
and pollution of water by sewage dum-
p i n g. The other big problem is over-
Is the grass growi
◗ P L A N E T
10 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
success of the project isn’t always
o b v i o u s. We can apply what we have
learned from working in some very
extensive areas, and  prevent errors and
bad practices from being repeated. I f
we want to move towards sustainable
development and conservation,we have
to improve present forms of gover-
nance. Responsibility for conservation
cannot fall on governments alone—all
interest groups have to be involved.
Then you have to work out what to
develop and what to preserve (see next
p a g e ) .And surprisingly, I ’ve found you
can nearly always reconcile different
interests. But you really have to get a
democratic process going because if
you just allow technicians to work in
isolation,the result is worth very little.
If a project is well thought-out, t h e
people affected by it will understand
and give it their backing, because they
will have been involved from the outset.
Can you give examples of sound coastal
management?
Well, there’s Chesapeake Bay, the
largest and most productive estuary in
the U. S. , the Wadden Sea (shared by
G e r m a n y, Denmark and the Nether-
lands) and the Thames Estuary in
E n g l a n d . Here in Rhode Island, t h e
Coastal Resources Center is trying to
revive an abandoned industrial port
filled with poor quality water.Another
example is the Venice Lagoon in Italy,
which is tremendously complicated but
has enjoyed moderate success.
It seems only rich countries can afford to
rehabilitate their coastal regions.
Not really. Developing countries
have many experimental schemes las-
ting four to six years, but so far few
long-term,large-scale projects, such as
the thriving almost 30-year coastal
management programme in Sri Lanka.
The key to its success has been not tack-
ling all problems at once, but singling
out two urgent ones—coastal erosion
and poorly located infrastructure.
The two main causes of erosion were
human—the mining of river sand
(which eventually builds beaches) and
the destruction of coral reefs to extract
l i m e. Sand was used to make cement
and the lime for plaster and to a lesser
extent farming, because it reduces soil
acidity and increases some crop yields.
Both types of mining created a lot of
jobs and were so profitable that it wasn’t
easy to regulate them in a very poor
country in a state of near civil war. But
there have been some notable achie-
vements. The two activities have been
almost entirely brought under control
and,more importantly, new infrastruc-
ture such as roads and hotels are built
away from beaches and cliffs.
The challenge to poor countries
today is to use this experience and learn
from the many experimental micro-
projects that exist (the Tanzanian island
of Mafia, the Honduran Gulf of Fon-
s e c a , the Philippines and other places),
along with bigger projects over wider
areas. ■
* Head of the Coastal Resources Center
at A m e r i c a ’s Rhode Island University.
1. The Global Environment Fa c i l i t y
(GEF) was set up in 1991 to protect
the environment and promote sustai-
nable development. Its members
include 166 gov e r n m e n t s, the main
development agencies, the scientific
community and a broad range of
NGOs and private sector bodies.
+ …
UN E S C O’s International Oceanographic
Commission will host a conference in Paris
from December 3-7, 2001 called “Oceans and
Coasts at Rio +10.”
(http://ioc.unesco.org/iocweb)
Coastal Resources Center:
www.crc.uri.edu
wing? Researchers measure progress in California’s San Diego Bay.
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Xc a l a k , on the Caribbean coast of
M e x i c o, is no less than a paradise,
blessed with 14,000 hectares of coastal
land and 3,000 more of offshore lagoons.
The area is part of the Meso-American
Barrier Reef, the second largest in the
world and home to a vast array of fish,
turtles, shellfish and manatees. Its ver-
dant expanses of tropical forest contain
spider and howler monkeys, j a g u a r s,
swamp crocodiles and 155 bird species.
Each morning, most of Xcalak’s 400
inhabitants make for the sea to catch
fish,lobster and conch, an activity that
now competes with the first stirrings of
t o u r i s m . Five years ago, the villagers
realized their catches were shrinking
due to the environmental damage
i n flicted by unauthorized fishermen and
tourist guides. In response, the locals
decided to look for ways to protect fis h
stocks and diversify their income
sources.
Helped by experts from Quintana
Roo University and the Rhode Island
University Coastal Resources Center
( C R C, see previous pages), the villa-
gers persuaded the federal government
to designate the area as a national
marine park on June 5, 2 0 0 0 .They were
also named responsible for its upkeep.
To protect the area and satisfy everyo-
n e ’s interests, the land was divided into
six zones. The first was reserved for
fis h i n g, the second for tourism, the third
for game fis h i n g, the fourth for fis h -
breeding, the fifth was closed in winter
and the sixth was set aside for conser-
vation of plant and animal life.
This is all and well, but a greater
danger seems to lie ahead.“ N o w, the vil-
lage is threatened by a government pro-
ject called the Ruta Costa Maya (Mayan
Coast Road), which aims to make
Xcalak part of a major tourist develop-
ment plan,” says biologist Marco Laz-
c a n o, executive director of Amigos de
Sian Ka’an, an NGO involved in several
programmes to protect the region.R u t a
M a y a ’s goal is to include Xcalak in a
massive tourist resort similar to the
sprawling one in Cancún, 300 kilometres
north which receives two million tou-
rists a year.Along with improving access
roads, Ruta Maya plans to build 14,000
hotel rooms.
“It would be unthinkable to stay
outside this development project when
y o u ’re a village whose only access road
has recently been repaired after Hurri-
cane Mitch devastated it in 1998.Wh a t ’s
more, we’re only served by one bus a
d a y,” says Lazcano. Xcalak has no elec-
tricity, but it hopes to be hooked up to
the grid in a couple of months.
The villagers, h o w e v e r, remain wary.
“ They don’t want huge steel and
concrete buildings going up along their
beaches, their wooden houses replaced
or their unsurfaced streets ripped up.
They want to have a say in the Ruta
Maya project to make sure the deve-
lopment is balanced,” Lazcano explains.
“The coastal area is protected, but the
rest of the village on dry land wants to be
part of the development that’s coming to
the whole region. Villagers are trying
to achieve that without giving up their
fishing—the heart of their identity—
and without harming the ecosystem.”
“ Th e y ’re worried about their future
and know that the only chance they
have of preventing a tourist invasion is
by getting together to preserve their
community and not let it be overw-
helmed by developers,” he adds
Xcalak is nevertheless adapting. It
can already boast a couple of small
h o t e l s, with capacity for between 12 and
30 people, and another five are planned
on the outskirts. To prove their good
faith, some villagers have even begun
learning English and taking courses on
customer satisfaction. ■
+ …
Amigos de Sian Ka’an. Apdo. Postal 770.
Cancún, Quintana Roo 77500,Mexico
GERARDO TENA
MEXICAN JOURNALIST
Dilemmas in a tropical para d i s e
“We want tourists, but not too many,” say the 400 inhabitants of Xcalak, a village on Mexico’s
southeast coast. They’ve taken steps to protect the area, but that may not be enough to keep
developers at bay
A COA S TAL BALANCING AC T
A plan of Xcalak shows the marine protected area and other village sites.
◗ P L A N E T
12 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
T
INTERVIEW BY SHIRAZ SIDHVA
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Getting the spin right
on history
Over the past decade, profound historical changes have led many countries to revise how they teach
history in school. Falk Pingel* looks at the pitfalls of the exercise
o what extent do authors who revise school
textbooks tread the fine line between his-
torical truth and distortion for political or
other purposes? 
Careful analysis is required to ensure
that biases do not creep into texts, and
there are several criteria for judging accu-
r a cy. The bottom line is that different
perspectives must be mentioned,other-
wise you’re likely to get a biased presen-
tation of history.This tends to be the case
with how religious issues are treated,or
how the so-called underdeveloped coun-
tries are presented.This can be very dif-
ferent from how the people concerned
actually view their own culture or religion.
We have found biased interpretations of
the two World Wars in European text-
b o o k s,when they dealt with borders, p r o-
blems with minorities or victims of per-
secution,for example.
What guidelines exist for avoiding bias?  
The Institute for International Text-
book Research,with UNESCO, has deve-
loped guidelines for textbook revision.
There are methods on how to do a lin-
guistic analysis of a text to gauge whether
it is biased.The deeper structure of a text
is analyzed to assess whether cultural
diversity is respected, or whether there
are racial and ethnic stereotypes.
What about the choice of authors?
The way textbooks are written varies
across different regions. In We s t e r n
Europe or the U. S. , a team of three or
more scholars is involved in writing a
single text. An open textbook market
exists so that schools have a choice.This
in itself is usually a guarantee that diffe-
rent views are expressed. But in other
regions (including some countries of East
and Southeast Europe, as well as many
African and Asian countries),textbooks
are often written by a single author who
is commissioned by the state to write
according to a narrow set of guidelines.
Is this problem more acute in certain
regions? 
Ye s, in former Soviet countries, b u t
there has been a change for the better in
the last decade. We ’ve organized semi-
nars with textbook authors from Eastern
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 13
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
* Deputy Director of the Georg-Eck e r t
Institute for International Te x t b o o k
Research, Germany, and author of the
UN E S C O Guidebook on Te x t b o o k
R e s e a r ch and Textbook Revision, 1 9 9 9 .
J A P A N : A M B I G U O U S  T E X T B O O K S
The committee charged with revising history textbooks meets in
To k y o ’s unsightly Mombusho building, which houses Ja p a n ’s
Education Ministry. Experts usually update textbooks every two years
to incorporate new information—archaeological discoveries and
decisive revelations—or make changes required by a modifie d
c u r r i c u l u m . This year, the routine task provoked an international
controversy.
The committee revised and approved nine high school history
textbooks.All of them had to be corrected.One, published by Fusosha,
which belongs to the conservative Fuji-Sankei press group, underwent
over 200 modifications.
Despite the requested corrections, the Fusosha textbook, written by a
group of nationalistic professors, continues to ignore the tragic plight
of  “comfort women,” the Imperial army’s former sex slaves, most of
whom were Ko r e a n . And it asserts that there is “no proof” t h e
Japanese slaughtered 300,000 people during a massacre in Nanjing,
China, in 1937.
The eight other books are less questionable but just as ambiguous. All
of them say that, despite its horrors, the Pacific war ended Western
colonialism in A s i a . For now, Japanese students grow up with a truncated
vision of history. N o n e t h e l e s s, the overwhelming majority of public school
teachers has rejected Fusosha’s book, and none of Japan’s prefectures
(each one chooses which books to include in the curriculum) has opted
for it.
But what can be done about revisionist mangas (comic books),which are
breaking sales records? The illustrator and polemicist Yoshinori Ko b a y a s h i
has sold several million copies of Senso Ron (“About the War”),a picture
book that glorifies the heroes of World War II. An organization of
revisionist teachers, Tsukuru Kai, has asked him to illustrate their future
works.
More alarming, polls show that Japanese teenagers, who have been
disoriented by the current economic crisis, say they “enjoy” books
boasting about the code of honour and the Japanese virtues of order and
discipline, without mentioning the atrocities that were committed.
Casting his eye over these various trends, Dr. Aruki Wada,a professor at
Tokyo University, says that “Japan still hasn’t cleaned up its past.” ■
Richard Werly, Tokyo-based journalist
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Europe to teach them new methods of
writing and discussing the different inter-
pretations possible in history.This is par-
ticularly difficult when we are dealing
with the Balkan wars or with the dissolu-
tion of Socialist Yu g o s l a v i a , where memo-
ries of suffering are still fresh.
What do you see as the most serious bias
in history textbooks? 
The tendency to construct a conti-
nuity in time,whether of one culture, o n e
nation and even of nation states, i n v e s t i n g
this culture, people or nation with a
dignity superior to others. Some Euro-
pean countries, for example, say their
nations were born in the 9t h or 10t hc e n-
t u r y, when the nation state has only
existed for 200 years.
How can this be prevented? 
Sometimes discussions are useful to
deconstruct this notion of continuity over
centuries. Of course, most nations trace
back roots to ancient or medieval times,
when social or religious patterns of
dependency were much more important
than ethnic or “national”groupings.The
term “people” or “nation” did not have
the same meaning as today. Often,text-
book authors tend to put their own
people or nation in the centre and dimi-
nish or exclude others believed to have
less “ h i s t o r i c a l ” r i g h t s. Our message is:
d o n ’t dehumanize what is different from
you.
Germany over the last 20 years has deve-
loped an excellent resource for teachers
on the Nazi period. Do textbooks get more
accurate with the passage of time? 
Yes, time does help. It is much harder
to have accurate textbooks for countries
still at war. The latest Palestinian texts
developed by the Palestinian National
Authority don’t deal with the present
dimension of the Israeli-Palestinian confli c t
at all. In contrast, Israel has an open private
textbook market. Different versions are
now available, but none that acknowledge
Palestinian culture or history. ■
14 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
Since coming to power three years ago, I n d i a ’s ruling Bharatiya Ja n a t a
Party (BJP) has actively sought to impose a new history curriculum.Th i s
attempt has nothing to do with new trends or methodology within the dis-
cipline. By restructuring educational institutions, rewriting curricula and
t e x t b o o k s, and making major personnel changes, the government is
attempting to recast the past by giving it a strongly Hindu religious
orientation.
The right-wing party now controls the
Ministry of Human Resource Development
(which includes Education) and the
National Council for Educational Research
and Training (NCERT) which produces most
school texts.Th e s e, along with other public
institutions like the Indian Council for His-
torical Research, are rapidly losing their
academic freedom, as renowned historians
are replaced by bureaucrats and acade-
mics willing to toe the political line.
The current rewriting of Indian history is
part of a larger long-term political plan
aimed at reordering the secular character
that has informed the educational and cul-
tural policies of the country since its inde-
pendence. The BJP seeks to redefine the
character of the nation as Hindu, and to
lend legitimacy to the politics of cultural
n a t i o n a l i s m .To inculcate a sense of national
pride, Indian history is seen through ste-
reotypes rooted in religious identity. N o
aspect of history has been spared, be it
social tensions, political battles or cultural
differences. The achievements of ancient
Indian civilization are identified only with
Hinduism and are grossly exaggerated.
The BJP would have us believe that human-
kind and all scientific discovery, from bronze-casting to printing and
a e r o n a u t i c s, originated in northern India, the original home of the A r y a n s.
The period of the Rig Veda (a religious treatise) has been pushed back to
5000 B.C.against the general scholarly consensus of 1500 B.C.in order to
associate the Aryans with the Indus Valley civilization which flourished in
Harappa and Mohenjodaro, now in Pakistan.
These distortions are not limited to the past. The more recent history of the
national movement has been altered to glorify leaders of staunch Hindu
organizations, even if they were collaborators of colonial rule.
The Hindu view attempts to exclude all those who migrated to India and
their descendants as foreigners or the enemy. In reality, I n d i a ’s demography
r e flects the coming together of a variety of groups—racial, l i n g u i s t i c
and ethnic—during the course of the last
two millennia and raises the question of
who the “outsider”really is.
Fo r t u n a t e l y, there is a strong resistance
from academics and historians against this
trend. They are doing all they can to fight
the gradual introduction of new textbooks
and to uphold the country’s long tradition
of “scientific”history.
Ed. note: The government has defended
its recently introduced National Curricular
Framework for School Education which
suggests that textbooks be revised.D e n y i n g
that “any religious bias” had been intro-
duced into history textbooks, the Human
Resources Development minister, M u r l i
Manohar Joshi, insisted that his govern-
ment was “merely following the changes
recommended by the NCERT. . . We have
prepared the frame in the most democratic
manner,” he said. ■
* Former professor at Jawaharlal Nehru
University in New Delhi. One of several
eminent historians whose two-volume trea -
tise on Modern Indian history, “Towards
Freedom”, was summarily withdrawn by
the Indian Council of Historical Research. 
K . N . PA N I K K A R * : RECASTING THE PAST IN INDIA 
Mohenjodaro, now in Pakistan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
T
THOMAS SCHNEE
JOURNALIST BASED IN BERLIN
G e r m a n y : two histories re u n i t e d
It’s taken several years, but students across the country are now learning a common
version of history that takes stock of everyday life and dissident movements
in the former East Germany
he shock of unification reached class-
rooms in the “ n e w ” Länder (states) of
former East Germany as the 1991 school
year began. Germany was united once
a g a i n . But not its school curriculum.As a
r e s u l t , the West German version was
i m p o s e d . East German history textbooks
were rejected because they faithfully
r e flected the ideology of the fallen regime.
“The publishers quickly brought out
new books,” says Falk Pingel, d e p u t y
director of the Georg-Eckert Institute
for International Textbook Research (see
previous pages).“But they were just new
editions of the ones written in the West in
the 1980s, with an added chapter on reu-
n i fic a t i o n . It wasn’t at all representative of
the idea East Germans had of their own
h i s t o r y.The repressive nature of the Com-
munist regime was emphasized, a l o n g
with East Germany’s membership of the
Soviet bloc.R e u n i fication was presented
as a positive thing, without mentioning
the dashed hopes of those from the East.”
Looking back
without nostalgia
In the space of a year, teachers in the
East had to switch to a very different ver-
sion of history. “Many of them didn’t
know how to explain to their pupils why
y e s t e r d a y ’s truths no longer held today,”
says Andrea Schwärmer, who had taught
history in the eastern state of Th ü r i n g e n .
“ Those teachers lost all credibility and
had to resign themselves to leaving the
profession.”
In the mid-1990s, the education minis-
ters of the Eastern states, who were in
charge of supervising the curriculum
under the federal system, began to push
for change. “Many teachers in the East
requested that we come up with a less
biased textbook and we did in 1995,” s a y s
Walther Funken, head of Volk und
Wi s s e n , the largest textbook publisher in
the Eastern states, based in Berlin.0nce
tied to the Communist regime, the publi-
sher was taken over in 1994 by Cornelsen,
a West German publisher.
“It wasn’t a matter of writing a text-
book for people who were nostalgic for
life in the old East Germany,” s a y s
F u n k e n , “but of presenting in a more
subtle way all the aspects of East German
society through individual portraits. For
example, one chapter compares the dif-
ferent roles of women in East and West
German societies, noting the large
number of them in the East’s workforce
and the political and historical reasons
why women in the West tend to stay
home.”
Last year, the state of Brandenburg
o f ficially revised its history curriculum
for the first time since 1991.More space
is given to daily life in East Germany, t h e
Nazi period and the Holocaust, a com-
parison between Nazism and Stalinism, a s
well as how citizens’ movements helped
bring down the Communist regime.
Sparking debate
“In the East,” says Pingel,“National
Socialism was depicted as a perversion of
the capitalist system. It was obviously not
compared to Stalinism and very little was
said about the concentration camps and
their victims. Dissident movements
weren’t mentioned either.”
The vast majority of German histo-
rians now agree on a common version of
the history of East Germany, says Pingel.
Because the new generations have not
lived the history being taught to them,
“the textbooks discuss the rise of the 1989
citizens’ movements and use a range of
sources and accounts to show how young
East Germans experienced reunific a t i o n .
This open way of teaching doesn’t present
a single truth, but various points of view,”
he says.“It seeks to  encourage debate in
the classroom.” ■
GETTING THE SPIN RIGHT ON HISTO RY
W O R L D O F L E A R N I N G ◗
In the former East Germany, childcare facilities enabled women to work more easily.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ince the first universities were born over eight centuries
ago, intellectuals have negotiated the right to pursue
knowledge without outside pressure, a privilege broadly
known as academic freedom. This sacrosanct notion conti-
nues to be challenged on all fronts. Strapped for funds
because of public sector cutbacks, universities worldwide
are sealing deals with corporations. Although in some
cases these alliances have proved their worth (pp. 21-22),
in many others, they have led to blatant conflicts of inter-
est and run the risk of sidelining basic research and the humanities (pp. 18-20).
In response, medical journals recently took a lead in protecting academic inves-
tigators (p. 23). Meanwhile, hopes that the information revolution would spur
easier access to knowledge are hampered by ever stricter intellectual property
rights (pp. 24-25). Marginalized from the international community, many African
researchers are forced to sell their wares. While they are no longer widely tar-
geted on grounds of subversion,in many other parts of the world, the politics of
ethnic and religious identity have placed intellectuals in the line of fire (pp. 30-
31). Some, such as Afghan professor Abdul Lalzad (p. 29), have managed to flee
with help from the international community, others serve prison sentences (p.
32). The social climate can also
curtail freedoms: in Russia,histo-
rians are running up against a
reluctance to explore the darker
days of the Soviet era (pp. 33-
34). But scholars must seize the
day and play a more prominent
role in addressing pressing glo-
bal problems (p. 35).
Dossier concept and coordina -
tion by Cynthia Guttman, UNESCO
Courier journalist
SC o n t e n t s
1 / The Money Game
1 8 Anatomy of a corporate take o v e r
James L. Tu r k
2 1 Who calls the tune?
Vicky Elliott
2 3 In the name of a fair trial
Jeffrey Dra z e n
2 4 Barbed wire in the re s e a rch fie l d
René Lefort
2 6 Too poor to be fre e
Ebrima Sall
2 / Power Tra p s
2 9 When your university closes down…
Donald Macleod
3 0 In the line of fire
Sam Zia-Zarifi
3 2 No apologies
Steve Negus
3 3 Bound by nostalgia
Nick Holdsworth
3 5 Being on alert
Interview with Brenda Gourley
POLITICS A
S c h o lar
F O C U S
16 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
In the first universities of medieval
E u r o p e,800 years ago, an individual who
questioned official attitudes could find
himself an outlaw.The notion that there
was value in challenging what society
thought permissible through public
debate emerged later, as a result of the
religious and intellectual wars of the
16th and 17th centuries. G r a d u a l l y, a
tacit agreement developed between the
state and universities, whereby freedom
of speech in the public interest was
allowed.
Governments—and to some extent
university administrations themselves—
are losing sight of the reasons for pro-
tecting this community that is allowed,
like the court jester, to ask authorities
awkward questions. Universities are
increasingly seen as training centres
rather than as institutions of higher lear-
n i n g.They are expected to produce skilled
workers instead of critical scholars in
societies where a computer programmer
is deemed more valuable than a philoso-
pher.
Pressure to reduce government spen-
ding coupled with rising student enrol-
m e n t h a s d r i v e n universities world-w i d e
into the arms of commerce.The constant
search for funding is time-consuming and
inefficient. Moreover some “big name”
universities attract private funding more
easily than others because of their pres-
tigious “ b r a n d n a m e s.”When universities
“ c o l l a b o r a t e ” or enter “ p a r t n e r s h i p s ”
with big corporations, the lawyers of the
latter are generally far more astute in
pursuing their clients’ interests than those
negotiating on behalf of universities.Th e
corporation offers a new building, s a l a r i e s
to attract “big leading players,” e q u i p-
ment. In return it may retain control of
the direction of the research and even
impose a new set of staff relationships.
B e f o r e, long-term posts in the uni-
versities gave scientists the opportunity
and security to pursue novel ideas that
arose during their work. But commer-
c i a l l y - financed research aimed at specific
projects does not allow for digression. I t s
prime objective is to produce the goods—
marketable products—leaving funda-
mental science to the sidelines. Th e
sponsor can also control the intellectual
property rights and even the right to
publish the project results. It can prevent
the scientist from sharing research at an
international conference and can even
stop his or her work if the funder doesn’t
like the way it is going.
The old expectation was that scientific
expertise was global in its reach and
e x c h a n g e. Scientists met in international
conferences and gave papers which eve-
ryone could discuss. I n d e p e n d e n t , r e s-
pected voices could be heard to disagree
with the claims of government or corpo-
rate-sponsored research.Today, the cor-
porations are buying up this expertise,
leaving very few voices to challenge what
they are telling the world.
Some international watchdogs are
beginning to take action. Yet even the
American National Academy of Sciences
considers that it is difficult to find indivi-
duals of sufficient seniority and with
visibly clean hands to form a watchdog
body that would call to account those
who manipulate data,appropriate ideas
or bend conclusions. We need a critical
mass of these brave and articulate indi-
viduals who are willing to speak out until
academic freedom is restored and reco-
gnized as a protection of everyone’s free-
doms. ■
L E AVING ROOM FOR DISSENT
GILLIAN EVANS
LECTURERINTHEOLOGY AT CAMBRIDGE UNIVERSITY,
PUBLIC POLICY SECRETARY FORTHE COUNCILFOR ACADEMIC FREEDOMAND ACADEMIC STANDARDS (CAFAS)
November 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 17
AND PROFIT
rs at risk
O P I N I O N
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
JAMES L.TURK
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OFTHE CANADIAN ASSOCIATION OF UNIVERSITY TEACHERS, EDITOR OF THE CORPORATE CAMPUS: COMMERCIALIZATIONAND THE DANGERS
TO CANADA’S COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES, JAMES LORIMER & CO., TORONTO, 1999.
Anatomy of
a c o rp o rate takeover
After scaling the ramparts of academic freedom through secretive
funding deals, corporations are gaining a new foothold in the ivory
towers by exporting a commercial culture of governance
1 . THE MONEY GAME
T
he basic role of the university in democratic
society is at risk.Alone among social institu-
t i o n s, the university’s mission is the unquali-
fied pursuit and public dissemination of truth
and knowledge. The university serves the
broad public interest to the extent it treasures informed
a n a l y s i s, critical inquiry and uncompromising stan-
dards of intellectual integrity.
When those who make up the university, t h r o u g h
their teaching, research and community service,
struggle to push beyond conventional wisdom,they
often threaten those in power with a vested interest
in the status quo.Throughout history, academic staff
who take their mission seriously have sometimes
found themselves at odds with dominant religious
g r o u p s, with governments and the state, and with the
corporate sector.
R e c e n t l y, corporate involvement in the university
has provoked the most concern.Strapped for funds
because of public sector cutbacks, universities have
turned increasingly to the private sector for support,
often considering corporate proposals that would
have been anathema previously. The very concept
of philanthropy has changed. Gone are the times
when donations were made without strings.To d a y, t h e
donor expects something in return.
Universities as autonomous communities of teachers and students are a
creation of the medieval West.The earliest such centres of higher lear-
ning sprang up in Bologna and Paris around 1200.Others soon followed in
O x f o r d , C a m b r i d g e, M o n t p e l l i e r, To u l o u s e, Padua and Salamanca. Th e r e
were over 60 by the late 15th century.The men who formed them,such as
the philosopher Siger de Brabant,the theologian Thomas Aquinas and the
physician Arnaud de Villeneuve, met, often with scant resources, to study
various disciplines, including philosophy, medicine, law and theology. Soon
they were fighting for their autonomy, in other words for the freedom to orga-
nize their courses as they saw fit,teach the students of their choice, confer
diplomas and hire professors.
At a time when law was fragmented into many customs and essentially pro-
tected the local people, u n i v e r s i t i e s, which drew teachers and students
from far and wide, inspired mistrust from the authorities and townsmen.Th e y
needed special protection.
Once acquired, autonomy did not necessarily mean total independence. It had
to be guaranteed by a higher authority who granted written privileges. For
a long time, the Church kept all forms of teaching under its control.It was
the Pope who granted the earliest university privileges, riding roughshod over
those who traditionally supervised schools: b i s h o p s, towns and the prince’s
local representatives, insofar as the secular powers also intervened very early
on.
The expression libertas scolastica appeared in Paris in 1231.To a certain extent,
academic freedoms coincided with what we call freedom of teaching today,
but they still remained under the Church’s tight control. Above all they
involved the right to live and work in peace, and exemption from city taxes,
military service and arrest,trial and imprisonment.
Academic freedoms borrowed much from ecclesiastic liberties: s t u d e n t s
and teachers, whether men of the cloth or not,were in a situation compa-
rable to that of clergymen,who were subject only to ecclesiastical courts,
which had a reputation for being more fair. They could only be tried by
their own institution — professors and the rector, the elected head of the uni-
versity — or by the pope or his representatives.
As such,one of the main aspects of academic freedom was the emergence
of separate university courts that meted out their own justice, setting tea-
chers and students apart from the rest of society.The law was the same throu-
ghout the West for everyone who belonged to those supranational institu-
tions that were, in essence, the first universities.
In the late Middle Ages, the rise of state-like entities meant that academic
freedoms became part of a new political framework, as simple practices
exempt from common law and still subject to revision.A venerable vestige
of the one-time independence and privileges granted by the prince, they now
acquired an ambiguous status. ■
Jacques Verger, professor of medieval history at the Université de Paris-Sor -
bonne, author of “French Universities in the Middle Ages”   (published in
French by Brill, Leiden, 1995).
THE BIRTH OF ACADEMIC FREEDOM
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 19
A good deal of discussion has focused on purely
commercial deals which involve the adornment of
universities with corporate logos and advertising, or
provide suppliers, like soft drink companies, w i t h
exclusive rights on campus.While such deals raise legi-
timate concerns and have provoked student protest,
the bigger danger lies in relationships that threaten
university autonomy and academic freedom. Fo r
e x a m p l e, corporate donations to universities are often
made in utmost secrecy.The details of the deal remain
undisclosed to the university senate or the larger
university community. C a n a d a ’s largest and most
richly endowed university, the University of To r o n t o,
signed secret deals in 1997 with the Joseph Rotman
Foundation ($15 million for the Faculty of Manage-
ment Studies), CEO Peter Munk of Barrick Gold
and Horsham corporations ($6.4 million for the
Centre for International Studies) and Nortel ($8 m i l-
lion for the Nortel Institute for Te l e c o m m u n i c a t i o n s ) .
The deals allow the corporations unprecedented
influence over the academic direction of University
of Toronto programmes.
Mounting unease
For example, the Rotman agreement initially
called for “the unqualified support for and commit-
ment to the principles and values underlying the
[donors’] vision by members of the faculty of
m a n a g e m e n t .” The Munk donation obligated
the Center of International Studies to assure
that this project would “rank with the Uni-
v e r s i t y ’s highest priorities for the alloca-
tion of its other funding, including its own
internal resources.”
In the U.S.,the Massachusetts Institute of Tech-
nology  (MIT) gained considerable notoriety in the
early 1990s, when for a fee of $10,000 to $50,000 per
y e a r, it provided corporations privileged access to
its faculty and to their research reports.The institute
advertised its readiness to place the expertise and
resources of all its schools, departments and labora-
tories at the disposal of industry.
The trend has been gradual,but unease is moun-
ting about overly close relations between corpora-
tions and university-based researchers. Several high-
profile cases have fuelled the debate. In the UK,the
editor of the British Medical Jo u r n a l resigned as a
professor at Nottingham University over its decision
to accept more than five million dollars from British
American Tobacco towards an international centre for
corporate responsibility. In the U.S. and Canada,the
cases of Drs. N a n cy Olivieri (see next page) and David
Ke r n ,among others, stand as blatant illustrations of the
corporate threat to academic freedom and integrity.
While serving as a consultant to a company producing
nylon flock,Kern,the director of occupational medi-
cine at Brown University’s Memorial Hospital (U. S. ) ,
found evidence of a serious new lung disease among
S C H O L A R S  A T  R I S K
the company’s employees.Going against the will of his
university and the company that threatened to sue,
Kern published his findings. His position at the uni-
versity was eliminated.In the same year, the U. S. C e n-
ters for Disease Control officially recognized the new
disease, flock worker’s lung.1
The fact that university administrations did not
side with their faculty in both these cases signals a pro-
found change at work within academic institutions.
Corporate-dominated university boards increasingly
choose top administrators who support a corporate
model of governance. And universities increasingly
operate in market-oriented cultures, in which social
value is measured by short-term market relevance.
There is money for computer science and business
a d m i n i s t r a t i o n , not for philosophy, h i s t o r y, t h e o r e t i c a l
physics or the arts.
The risk, h o w e v e r, is that universities may quickly
run up against the limits of their own game.We know
that public underfunding makes universities more
vulnerable to corporate enticements. But there is no
evidence to suggest that private corporate donations
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
can even begin to replace cuts in public funding. In
Canada alone, over two billion dollars would have to
be earmarked for universities to restore funding to its
level ten years ago. Proof that corporate funding is not
filling the gap is that many countries are dramati-
cally raising tuition fees, which undercuts wider acces-
sibility for students.
But there are powerful pockets of resistance. On
several occasions in recent years, students and faculty
have stood up against blatant commercialism on
campus. In Canada,the alarm was sounded two years
ago when an expert panel published a report recom-
mending that commercialization become the fourth
mission of the university, alongside research,teaching
and community service. It also recommended that
tenure and promotion be more closely tied to engaging
in commercial activities. In opposition, the Canadian
Association of University Teachers drafted a letter to
the prime minister that collected 1,500 prominent
signatures in three days. At stake are concerns about
corporate interests shaping the research agenda.The
issue gained renewed resonance this fall, when a dozen
of the world’s leading medical journal editors took
steps to better protect academic investigators (see
p. 23).
Without academic freedom and autonomy, uni-
versities cannot fulfill their public obligations. Aca-
demic staff have no choice but defend their right to
undertake critical analysis, publish their findings so the
public can decide,and encourage students to question
conventional wisdom. Upon these initiatives, t h e
future of universities depend. ■
1. Eyal Press and Jennifer Wa s h b u r n ,“The Kept Uni-
versity.” Atlantic Monthly, March 2000, p.42.
UNESCO’S ONGOING ENGAG E M E N T
In 1950, UNESCO convened a conference in Nice
(France) at which universities spelt out three prin-
ciples for which every higher learning institution
should stand: “the right to pursue knowledge for its
own sake and to follow wherever the search for truth
may lead;the tolerance of divergent opinion and free-
dom from political interference; the obligation as
social institutions  to promote, through teaching and
research, the principles of freedom and justice, of
human dignity and solidarity…”
Academic freedom became a subject of intense deba-
te in the international community towards the end of
the 1980s, partly linked to the fall of many totalitarian
communist regimes and the spread of democracy.
Since then, a string of declarations has been passed
relating to academic freedom. In 1997, UNESCO’s
General Conference adopted a recommendation
concerning the Status of Higher Education Teaching
Personnel,which states that the principle of academic
freedom should be “scrupulously observed.” Th e
landmark World Conference on Higher Education
(1998) also stressed that academic freedom and uni-
versity autonomy were basic and inalienable condi-
tions required for institutions to carry out their mis-
sion. UNESCO is preparing a world report on the
subject and is heading an initiative to draft an inter-
national instrument to reinforce the principle. In June
2 0 0 1 , UN E S C O also launched the Network for
Education and Academic Rights (see p. 30), which
aims to bring greater international attention to aca-
demic violations. For more information, s e e
www.unesco.org/education/wche ■
If fiction is a gateway to understanding real life, then John Le Carré’s most
recent novel The Constant Gardener is recommended reading.Dr. Nancy
O l i v i e r i , a professor of medicine at the University of To r o n t o, was among the
top-notch scientists he spoke to while researching his murder mystery that
t a kes readers on a dark journey through the pharmaceutical jungle, from A f r i c a
to the rich world.
An expert on thalessemia, a widespread and serious blood disorder, O l i v i e r i
has been at the heart of a swirling controversy since 1996,when she stood
up to A p o t e x , a pharmaceutical company with which she had signed a
c o n t r a c t . During clinical trials in the mid-1990s of potential treatment for the
blood disorder, she discovered that it could have serious side effects in
some patients.
When she approached Apotex with her negative fin d i n g s, they shrugged the
matter off. She turned to the hospital’s Research Ethics Board, w h i c h
reviewed the case and recommended that she draft a revised patient consent
form stating the contra-indications. “Seventy-two hours later, Apotex sent
me a letter saying ‘you’re fir e d . If you say anything, you’re sued.’ Th r e e
days later, they came and swept all the drugs off the hospital’s shelves,” r e c a l l s
Olivieri.
Most disturbing is that neither the university nor its reputed affiliated tea-
ching hospital supported her efforts to disclose, calling the case “a scientific
d e b a t e.” She was stripped of her responsibilities as director of the hospital’s
haemoglobinopathy programme.The conflict of interest turned out to be bla-
tant:the university was expecting a $20 million donation from Apotex.
“Governments have to understand that pharmaceutical companies are
filling a void created by cutbacks in public research money,” says Olivieri,
asserting that scientists have “ z e r o ” margin of manoeuver. “If you blow the
whistle there is nothing to stop the university from firing you.Drug compa-
nies can destroy you.And you can’t legislate integrity.”
The case provoked an international outcry, with the world’s leading thalessemia
experts travelling to Canada in protest. Under pressure, the hospital announced
that it would conduct an external review of its policies. Despite claims by A p o t e x
that Olivieri’s study was flawed,the New England Journal of Medicine publi-
shed her findings.
“This is at heart a public health issue, and I have total confidence that the
facts stand.The story is not over,” says Olivieri. During recent work in Sri Lanka,
she spoke with several patients who had never been told about the drug’s
r i s k s, nor that it was experimental.The drug was licensed in 1999 for specific
use in Europe, where Olivieri has brought a legal challenge to the EU’s
agency charged with approving new drugs. She affirms she’ll never sign ano-
ther contract with a pharmaceutical company although she’ll likely remain
a whistleblower:she’s on a sabbatical in the UK,studying for a masters in
law and medical ethics. ■
NANCY OLIVIERI: “ YOU CAN’T LEGISLATE INTEGRITY”
Restriction on
academic
freedom acts in
such a way as to
hamper the
dissemination of
knowledge
among the
people and
thereby impedes
national
judgement and
action.
Albert Einstein, 
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 21
I
n 1998,the University of California at Berkeley
concluded a $25 million, five-year agreement
with the Swiss company Novartis that has come
to be regarded as a watershed in the relationship
of industry with higher education.
For the first time, the work of an entire univer-
sity department,not just that of its individual mem-
bers contracting independently, was to be under-
written by a multinational company, with  interests
in health care, agribusiness and nutrition.
The corporation, through the Novartis A g r i-
cultural Discovery Institute, newly set up in La
Jolla,California,was to provide roughly one-third
of the budget of the university’s Department of
Plant and Microbial Biology for five years. In return,
the Swiss company won an unprecedented privilege:
the first right to negotiate a license to one-third of
the patentable discoveries made in any of the
department’s laboratories.
Was this a sellout or an inspired coup? Industrial
sponsorship of academic research was nothing new;
by 1998, nine percent of all research at American
universities was sponsored by corporations, a total
of $2 billion as compared with the $13 billion spent
by the federal government that year. But where
faculty members or research teams had made grant
proposals individually for funding to underwrite
their work,this agreement appeared to constitute
the plundering of public resources by a private cor-
poration.
Shopping around for
optimal conditions
The university’s need to reassess its sources of
revenue was recognized in 1993,when Chancellor
Chang-Ling Tien set up a Biotechnology Planning
Board to look into long-term relationships with
industry. The idea was to tap into the universities’
right to license their inventions, first granted by the
Bayh-Dole Act of 1980.
According to Gordon Rausser, an agricultural
economist who was dean of the College of Natural
Resources during the negotiations, the panel,w h i c h
brought members of the university together with
more than a dozen representatives from private
industry, spun its wheels for a few years, failing to
attract sponsors. Since the 1960s, federal funding for
the agricultural sciences remained essentially flat,
while medical and engineering schools have taken
an increasing proportion of the spoils nationally.
“The question we faced was: How do you go
about positioning yourself to advance your inter-
e s t s ? ” Rausser says.Rather than go out begging, t h e
university set out what it considered its optimal
conditions for a partnership. Several companies
expressed interest, some of which wanted to be
able to cherry-pick scientists whose work might be
ripe for commercial application. Only Novartis was
willing to allow the faculty the degree of intellectual
freedom it was looking for, or as the agreement
puts it, “unrestricted funds to support general,n o n -
targeted research.”
In return, the Agricultural Discovery Institute
was granted a 30-day review period to take a first
look at research coming out of the department
before it was published, and a further 90 days to
decide whether to request that the university pursue
a patent protection on it.Brian Wright,a Berkeley
agricultural economist who has worked on intellec-
tual property, points out that the rights to first nego-
tiation under the agreement does not give the com-
pany the right to buy,“only the right to pay enough
so that the university’s willing not to offer it to any-
body else.”This was hardly giving up the store.
S C H O L A R S  A T  R I S K
VICKY ELLIOTT
JOURNALIST BASED IN SAN FRANCISCO
Who calls the tune?
A landmark “strategic alliance” clinched by the University of California
caused an uproar in the academic world, but for a rising generation
of scientists, the deal probably contains what the future will be made of
1 . THE MONEY GAME
Bioengineered crops: a windfall for agricultural faculties?
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
Such distinctions were lost in the furor following
the announcement of the agreement,given the cli-
mate of public resistance to bioengineered crops.
Advocates of ecologically sustainable agriculture in
particular were outraged by what they felt to be an
institutional endorsement of biotechnology.
Pies were thrown at two of the principals and the
Students for Responsible Research coalition
denounced the agreement’s “narrow focus on profit -
oriented and controversial biotechnological
r e s e a r c h .” B e r k e l e y ’s Academic Senate fie r c e l y
debated whether the agreement had been too hur-
riedly pushed through and how it might compromise
academic integrity.
One of the agreement’s features that most
rankled in Berkeley was that two Novartis repre-
sentatives would sit on a five-person committee
that would decide how to allocate the funds for
research every year. But Steven Briggs, who heads
the La Jolla Institute, since renamed the To r r e y
Mesa Research Institute, notes that this provision
was included at the request of the faculty, not the
c o m p a n y.Rausser argues that it
was conceived as a way to gain
industry intelligence into whe-
ther comparable research
might already be under way in
the private sector.
Funding the
unexpected
According to department
chair Andrew Ja c k s o n , the two
Novartis representatives essen-
tially concurred in the first years of the agreement
with decisions reached by the faculty. “I don’t feel
t h e r e ’s any problem with academic freedom at all,”
he says. Paradoxically, the Novartis deal gave the
faculty leeway to pursue imaginative projects in
basic science for which they might not otherwise
have been able to secure fin a n c i n g. Little room
now remains in the allocation of federal revenue for
“funding the unexpected,” as one emeritus pro-
fessor put it. Given the intense competition for
f u n d s,a conservatism prevails on the national review
boards that favours experiments that are not likely
to fail.
The members of the department were at liberty
not to take part in the agreement:of 30,one opted
out and two abstained on principle. Many faculty
members are grateful for the chance to pursue work
that federal agencies might not have funded. “ Th i s
is a godsend,” says Loy Volkman,an insect virolo-
g i s t . “ We have poor funding from the state, a n d
have to find up to 70 percent elsewhere.And usually,
the payer gets to call the tune.”
The agreement allows the university unusual
freedom in negotiating the patents it would retain.
The University of Washington’s arrangement with
M o n s a n t o, by comparison,allows the company both
to file the patent and to see it through to publication,
an abdication of control that Berkeley would never
assent to, according to Carol Mimura,of its Office
of Technology Licensing.
A mousetrap or
sign of the times?
Since the agreement was reached, Syngenta (as
this branch of Novartis was renamed) has optioned
the rights to seven patent applications, of which
four arose from projects funded in part by the La
Jolla Institute, and three were solely funded by it.
A younger generation of scientists, aware that
their working lives will call upon them to operate
both in and out of the ivory tower, appears to have
made peace with the deal.“ I t ’s a sign of the times,”
says Michael Goodin,a post-doctoral student.“ Th i s
is the environment we will be operating in. Th e
only other resource is public funding, and it’s not
there.”
At the annual retreats held by the institute,
both faculty and graduate stu-
dents report that they have
been surprised by how freely
ideas can be exchanged with
outside scientists.N e v e r t h e l e s s,
at hearings in California’s state
capitol last year, D e m o c r a t i c
Senator Tom Hayden charac-
terized the agreement as “ u s u r-
pation of democracy by the bio-
tech industry,” and Senator
Steven Peace, chairman of the
budget committee, raised the issue of accountability,
denouncing the reporting requirements built into
the agreement as “a mousetrap that nobody from a
distance can ever audit.”
An internal university committee was to have
filed a report on the agreement halfway through its
c o u r s e ; it is unlikely to be completed before the
fourth year.
Meanwhile, because Syngenta is in theory free
to revoke its funding at a year’s notice, the faculty
have continued to apply for other funding.The jury
is still out on whether Syngenta is likely to have
gained much more from the agreement than an
observation post from which to keep abreast of the
latest developments in a world-class university.
With the shrinking of the economy and the com-
p a n y ’s investment in transgenic crops now in ques-
tion, it seems unlikely that the agreement will be
renewed.
The hopes of generous financing for universities
from biotech companies that seemed likely a few
years ago now appear misplaced. The Novartis
agreement may itself go down as yet another
inconclusive “ e x p e r i m e n t ” in the university’s 
history. ■
Suppose that
humans want
to be free from
the meddling
of technocrats
and commissars,
bankers and
tycoons...or
anyone else
who tries to wish
freedom and
dignity out
of existence.
Noam Chomsky,
American linguist
(1928-)
Paradoxically,
the deal gave
the faculty
leeway to pursue
imaginative projects
in basic science.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 23
S C H O L A R S  A T  R I S K
C
linical trials are a building block of current
medical practice, carried out to show the
advantages of a new approach to treat-
m e n t . But just doing the trial is not enough:
s c i e n t i fic rigour requires that it undergo
peer review and publication in a medical journal before
changes in clinical practice can occur.
Physicians who had no part in the trial closely exa-
mine it for potential flaws and provide advice to
journal editors. The latter assume that the authors
helped design the study,had full access to the
data and all relevant information before
interpreting the data.Once published,
physicians can make informed deci-
s i o n s, confident that the medical
journal is providing a full and
unbiased appraisal of the treat-
ment.
But recent developments
have put this procedure to
the test. Two decades ago,
trials were done by an
alliance between academic
investigators and commer-
cial sponsors. A c a d e m i c s
were largely responsible for designing trials.
The sponsor provided the money and mate-
rial required to handle the huge volume of
d a t a . Manuscripts reporting trial results were
jointly written by academic and commercial spon-
s o r s ; when they were submitted for publication,
the major authors were often the academic
scientists who had performed key roles
in the trial, giving it enhanced credibi-
lity.
Much of this has changed. Over the past
d e c a d e,many academics have moved to industrial
p o s t s.As a result, sponsors now have substantial exper-
tise in trial design, performance and data interpreta-
t i o n . Scientists working for industry are more likely to
design trials which cast their product in a favourable
l i g h t . Rather than including academic investigators
from the outset, these individuals may be presented
with a trial that has already been designed. Th e
s p o n s o r, who often prepares the manuscript for sub-
mission to a medical journal, h o l d s, and may limit
access to, all the data.The problem is that the sponsor
is not dispassionate about trial results.
There have been a number of well-publicized
cases (see p. 2 0 ) , where sponsors have suppressed
results of clinical trials. What bothered editors the
m o s t , h o w e v e r, were related practices that occur
much more commonly, but in less egregious fashion.
A sponsor may prepare a manuscript in which all
the data of importance are not included or in which
the unwanted side effects of a new approach to the-
rapy are minimized.Putting an interpretational spin
on reported data is not fair to the patients who volun-
teered for the trials or to the broader
community of patients and physi-
c i a n s. We deserve to get a com-
plete and unbiased report of
research results; drug marketing
should not be a consideration
in preparing a report.
In September 2001, the
International Council of
Medical Journal Editors
(ICMJE), an alliance of
the editors of 12 general
medical journals, a d-
opted new rules concer-
ning the ethics of clinical
trial performance and reporting. A c a d e m i c
physicians now need to give assurances that
they have had a meaningful role in trial
design,complete and unlimited access to
the data base, and an uncensored role in
data interpretation and manuscript prepa-
ration. The ICMJE believes these rules will
help everyone. They will provide aca-
demic physicians with needed leverage
as they negotiate research contracts with
sponsors and will empower them to ana-
lyze all the available data fairly.They will aid patients
and physicians by providing additional assurances
that all the information about a new treatment is
p r o v i d e d . They will help commercial sponsors by
levelling the playing field.
Medical treatment has been substantially
advanced by new medical devices and pharmaceuti-
cals.We want this progress to continue, but we want
to be sure that the process of reporting trials is as free
as possible from commercial bias; we believe that
these new rules will help achieve this end. ■
JEFFREY DRAZEN
EDITOR-IN-CHIEF OFTHE NEW ENGLAND JOURNAL OF MEDICINE, PROFESSOR OF MEDICINE AT HARVARD MEDICAL SCHOOL
In the name of a fair trial
Medical journals play a pivotal role in establishing a drug’s safety.
To curb the influence of private firms on reporting results, the most
prestigious journals are tightening publication guidelines 
1 . THE MONEY GAME
The scientist
must be free
to ask any
questions,
to doubt any
assertion,
to seek for
any evidence,
to correct
any errors.
J. Robert Oppenheimer,
American physician
(1904-1967) 
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
RENÉ LEFORT
DIRECTOR OFTHE UNESCO COURIER
Barbed wire
in the research fie l d
As patent claims surge and intellectual property rights are tightened,
researchers are struggling to safeguard the free movement
of information, a key condition for pursuing their work
1 . THE MONEY GAME
W
e ’re said to be living in the know-
ledge society, but does this mean
that knowledge is easier to come by
and moving about more freely?
Has access to knowledge—a basic
academic freedom—improved? Technological strides
undoubtedly make for easier access to information.
But the movement of knowledge is more than a
matter of technology; it is also governed by intellec-
tual property rights, which impose their own limits.
What is the “right balance” between private owner-
ship of knowledge and distributing it to the public free
of charge?
Many scientists, feeling their freedom is under
t h r e a t , have taken action.MIT (Massachusetts Ins-
titute of Te c h n o l o g y ) , one of the leading univer-
sity research centres in the United States, recently
announced that it is putting all its courses and tea-
ching resources on the web free of charge. F u r-
t h e r m o r e,over 22,000 scientists from 161 countries
have launched a boycott of science publication edi-
tors and started campaigning for a “public science
library.”
Legal 
hurdles
“We really don’t see why we should hand our
royalties over to a publisher whose goal is first and
foremost a lucrative one, when we have done all the
w o r k ,” says boycott participant Michael A s h b u r n e r,
a biology professor at Cambridge University in the
U K . “ These publishing houses set such exhorbi-
tant subscription prices that even in rich countries,
it’s sometimes impossible to gain access to some
i n f o r m a t i o n . You can imagine where that leaves
scientists in developing countries.”
In the past few years, technological progress
has prompted the U. S. Congress and the European
Commission to strengthen intellectual property
r i g h t s. These reforms gained a global character
under the aegis of the World Intellectual Property
Rights Organization (WIPO) and the World Tr a d e
Organization (WTO),through the TRIPS accords
( Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property
R i g h t s ) . Since 1995,any state engaging in trade has
had to comply with this new legal order that covers
such sensitive matters as the length of time a text can
be protected by copyright and possible legal
24 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
exceptions to this (known as “fair use”). By and
large, exceptions cover private copy (for personal,
non-commercial use only) and quotation rights for
scientific, educational and academic purposes.
Under cover of international standardization,
the length of time literary or artistic intellectual
property can be protected has just been increased
from 50 to 70 years after the author’s death. C o n c r e-
t e l y, this means that less scientific information is
freely accessible in the public domain.
F u r t h e r m o r e, computer product manufacturers
have developed “technical measures” to fight
“ p i r a cy ” and prevent copying (of software, d a t a-
bases and so on),which keeps users from enjoying
their full rights under the principle of fair use.
Wo r s e, trying to steer around these “technical mea-
sures”could spell legal trouble. Soon,anyone who
tries to exercise legitimate copyrights could be pro-
secuted!
More generally, the scope of information and
knowledge that qualifies for protection is on the rise.
Biotechnology, the human genome and even stem
cells are starting to enter this domain, c r e a t i n g
t i g h t restrictions on genetic
r e s e a r c h . The same goes for
“teaching methods”and data-
b a s e s. For a while now, t h e r e
have even been attempts to
protect ideas and algorithms.
So far, they have been unsuc-
c e s s f u l . Major companies such
as British Telecom have fil e d
for patents on hypertext links,
others have done the same in
the multimedia field.The more patents1 there are,
the more research becomes fragmented and com-
partmentalized.The end result is that researchers’
freedom is restricted.
The risk is that intellectual property rights
become so tight that activities relating to free aca-
demic exchange are legally endangered. Fo r
e x a m p l e, a Princeton University professor has
stopped teaching a course on certain software enco-
ding techniques out of fear that communication
companies will take him to court.And an MIT stu-
dent asked one of his professors to sign a confi-
dentiality agreement before reading his thesis!
Looking at these trends, one can only begin to
question the purpose of intellectual property rights.
The main one is to guarantee the universal spread
of knowledge and inventions, in exchange for pro-
tection from the community for a limited time.Th e
desire to balance out the community’s and inven-
tors’ interests is embodied in the protection time
limits and the principle of fair use.
The debate is raging between those who advo-
cate longer time limits for protecting works and
s c i e n t i fic information, and those who argue that
society needs freer, more universal and less expen-
sive access to knowledge.This debate symbolizes the
quest to achieve social acceptability for what has
become commonly known as “the knowledge
society.”
In an economy of globalized knowledge, t h e
issue is crucial for developing countries, which hold
just three percent of the world’s patents.The 1999
United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)
report stated that “tightened intellectual property
rights keep developing countries out of the know-
ledge sector,” adding that the “relentless march of
intellectual property rights needs to be stopped
and questioned.”
As researchers from the industrialized coun-
tries see the results of their work come under tighter
p r o t e c t i o n , their counterparts in the South have
less and less access to the scientific information
required for developing products geared towards
local needs.For example,dependence of poor coun-
tries on imported medicine, which is expensive and
inaccessible for most of their populations, c o n t i-
nues to grow.
On the other hand, Western researchers have
free access to the scientific information passed down
from one generation to the next
in developing countries. Since
patent laws do not recognize
traditional and indigenous
forms of knowledge, s o m e
scientists have leapt at the
chance to patent them to their
b e n e f i t . In 1995, the UNDP
reports that two researchers
from the University of Missis-
sippi Medical Center were
granted the U.S. patent for using turmeric to heal
wounds, an art that has been practiced in India for
thousands of years.To get the patent repealed,the
claim had to be backed by written evidence—an
ancient Sanskrit text! 
To fund research in the world’s public interest,
some organizations, such as the Consultative Group
for International Agricultural Research, s u g g e s t
taxing patents registered with the W I P O. In 1998,a
tax of $100 per patent would have brought in $350
m i l l i o n , a sum well above MIT’s annual budget
($226 million). More generally, the legal frame-
work of intellectual property should spur access to
all forms of knowledge,because that is clearly in the
general interest.The issue will be on the agenda of
the World Information Society Summit,slated for
2003. ■
+ …
www.unesco.org/webworld/observatory
www.publiclibraryofscience.org
UNDP Human Development Report,1999.
“Tightened intellectual
property rights
keep developing
countries out of
the knowledge sector.”
1. The WIPO says that bet-
ween 1980 and 2000 the
number of patents granted
in the world doubled and
requests for patents in-
creased ninefold.
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 25
S C H O L A R S  A T  R I S K
Academies that
are founded at
public expense
are instituted not
so much to
cultivate men’s
natural abilities
as to restrain
them.
Baruch Spinoza,
Dutch philosopher
(1632-1677)
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
I
n many African countries, academics have
found that the threats to their  freedom have
profoundly changed over the past decade.
Political pressure has steadily given way to
economic constraints.
After independence, academic freedom was
not a priority for the new states and some even
dubbed it a “bourgeois concept.” A university
was supposed to serve the nation and its develop-
ment—by working with the government. Th i s
very quickly led to repression of dissent, a l o n g
with the arrest and imprisonment of many uni-
versity teachers and students and,under the har-
shest regimes, even their murder. U n i v e r s i t i e s,
which had grown from six in the early 1960s to 120
by the late 1990s (excluding South A f r i c a ) ,b e c a m e
a thorn in the side of the dictatorships.
When generals
take the reins
To dampen these hotbeds of subversion,sub-
jects considered dangerous were simply banned.
After 1968 student riots,political science and socio-
logy were forbidden in Rwanda and Senegal.A few
years later, law was banned from universities in
Mozambique. There was censorship everywhere,
especially in Ke n y a , Malawi and South A f r i c a
under the apartheid regime.
More recently, troops occupied the campus of
Lumumbashi University (in the former Zaire in
1 9 9 0 ) , police attacked students in Yopougon (Côte
d’Ivoire in 1991), many dissident Hutu and Tutsi
university teachers were killed during the 1994
Rwandan genocide, intellectuals were murdered in
Algeria and Nigeria’s military rulers liquidated
university administrators and replaced them with
former generals.
But in the last 10 years or so,African academics
have seen their fields of research expand as govern-
ments have embarked on the road to democracy.
Their lives are at risk now in only a few countries,
such as Burundi, and censorship is fading.
Other threats have arisen however.At the end
of the 1990s, one out of three countries in sub-
Saharan Africa was at war. Many universities were
destroyed (see box below on Sierra Leone) or
reduced to virtually nothing.To d a y, the main threat
to academic freedom in Africa is economic. B a d l y
paid university teachers often have several other
jobs and little time for research.Lack of access to
information technology and other means of
BASED ON AN INTERVIEW WITH EBRIMA SALL
A GAMBIAN RESEARCHER AT THE SWEDISH-FUNDED NORDIC AFRICA INSTITUTEAND FORMER HEAD OFAN ACADEMIC FREEDOMPROJECTWITH CODESRIA (THE
COUNCILFOR DEVELOPMENT OF ECONOMICAND SOCIAL RESEARCH IN AFRICA,
BASED IN DAKAR, SENEGAL)
African scholars:
too p o o r to be f re e
The governments of many African countries have eased their pressure on
universities but economic interests are now turning up the heat, as
market value becomes a yardstick for measuring relevance
1 . THE MONEY GAME
A research lab at Kano University, in Nigeria.
No trace
of slavery ought
to mix with
the studies of
the freeborn
man. No study,
pursued under
compulsion,
remains rooted
in memory.
Plato,
Greek philosopher
(428-348 B.C.)
26 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
research and publishing further marginalize
African researchers from the global academic
community.
The universities, which have been “ s a c r i fic e d ”
over the past 20 years on the altar of structural
adjustment programmes, are desperately short of
money. There are more and more strikes—often
brutally suppressed—and some institutions are
trying to work together to meet
the new challenges of globali-
zation. One positive develop-
ment is that in the era of the
knowledge economy, interna-
tional funding agencies, espe-
cially the World Bank, r e c o-
gnize that higher education and
research can no longer be dis-
missed as unnecessary “ l u x u-
ries.”
But universities now have
to come up with “productive”
results. Applied research now
tops the list of budget priorities
and research projects are judged on their “ m a r k e t
value.” Basic research and the humanities have
been sidelined.Universities, traditionally held up
as “ m o d e l s,”have become commercially-oriented.
Makerere University, in Uganda, and others raise
money by selling services. It is true that academics
are paid more in such institutions, their labs have
new equipment and their foreign benefactors
sometimes protect them from local political pres-
sures. But they end up serving the funding agen-
cies—tailoring their research to these agencies’
objectives and even becoming consultants for their
development projects. Sometimes the academics
are just left to implement the projects and are
quickly dropped if they try
to have a say in how they
should be conducted. Th i s
happened to a group of
Sudanese economists after
they protested about an
International Labour Orga-
nization project.
The market has yet to
provide adequate solutions
to Africa’s problems. Tan-
zanian jurist Issa Shivji
neatly summed up the
plight of African intellec-
tuals a few years ago: “ Yo u
know what you can expect from the state and
how to resist,” he said. “But you don’t know
what the market has in store for you. The state
lets you know that it is out to hang you, so you
can put up a fight. The market gives you a long
rope to hang yourself.” ■
After an extremely brutal civil war that began in 1991, Sierra Leone is jug-
gling with a shaky peace process. Chris Squire, a  thermodynamics pro-
fessor at the head of the mechanical engineering faculty at Fourah Bay
College, explains what academic freedom means in a country at the very
bottom of the United Nations Human Development Index.
“I taught in the agriculture faculty at Njala College, 150 kms from the
capital, Freetown,until 1995. When the rebels arrived,life became impos-
s i b l e, so we moved to Fr e e t o w n . But we couldn’t get away from the fig h t i n g
and lawlessness.A shell destroyed the roof of my mechanics workshop and
we were burgled.
“The university—which Fourah Bay and Njala are part of—is now starting
to recover. Njala had 2,000 students last year, up from 900 the year before.
While I don’t know of any teachers who have not been allowed to publish,
I don’t know any who have been able to complete a research project
because there’s simply no money or physical resources to be had.
“I earn $300 a month, paid regularly by the government. But all the teachers
know the university can no longer rely on government funding alone.We have
to explore other paths.
“My department has 300 students and we’re looking for outside funding.We
managed to get some old computers and other equipment from the Food and
Health Organization. More importantly, we’re obliged to run some commercial
activities to make money.We’ve begun making a limited series of doors and
windows in the workshop and we’re thinking of turning out spare parts and
household utensils as well.This small-scale production will also give my stu-
dents practical experience.
“I’m also part of a social science research team looking into ways to restore
peace, funded by Sweden’s Nordic Africa Institute. It might be very remote
from my training but it’s a matter of survival—for me, because I want to
continue my research,and for Sierra Leone, which has to figure out how to
end the fig h t i n g . I don’t receive a regular income from this work and I’ll get
paid when it’s finished.
“I’m also involved with another project, in association with a Nairobi-based
university network with NGO status called Science and Technology Policy
Research. I want to see how local farming, health and education can be
revived at the local level.The vicious circle of violence in Sierra Leone has deep
political,social and institutional roots.
“If we want to really set things right here, we can’t just rely on foreign help.
That applies to agricultural production as much as to the future of our ins-
titutions, which survive precariously with scant resources. The university is
a case in point.” ■
SIERRA LEONE: A RESEARCHER ON ALL FRONTS
Universities have been
sacrificed over
the past
twenty years
on the altar
of structural
adjustment programmes
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 27
S C H O L A R S  A T  R I S K
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
I N D I A : C H E C K S  I N  T H E  S Y S T E M
When India liberalized its economy in 1991, the expertise and
research facilities of the country’s Council of Scientific and
Industrial Research (CSIR) came to be particularly coveted by
multinationals, especially in the drugs and chemicals sector.
Grouping 80 percent of the country’s national laboratories, the
c o u n c i l , which concentrates on industry-oriented research, f o u n d
itself before new dilemmas.
Already in 1986,a government review advised that the council
would have to earn a third of its funding from external and
p r i vate sources.To d a y, nearly 70 percent of the council’s external
earnings (Rs. 2550 million, or $55 million) comes from the
government sector and about 10 percent stems from contractual
research for multinationals. The rest comes from Indian industry.
As government funding becomes tighter, a new balance is
slowly being struck between companies and academic
institutions. “Academics are facing increasing competition from
the fast-growing consultancy research sector, which is less
constrained by traditions of independence and objectivity,”
observes Anil A g a r wa l , chairperson of the independent Centre for
Science and Environment in New Delhi.
But CSIR’s director-general, Dr. Mashelkar, argues that private
research—which only involves two percent of the council’s
scientists and seven labs—does not alter priorities. Critics within
the system, however, say that major changes in the research
culture are evident in the seven labs concerned, which include
the National Chemical Laboratory (NCL) in Pune and the Indian
Institute of Chemical Technology (IICT) in Hyderabad. A single
project for SmithKline Beecham at IICT, worth $100,000,is said
to have engaged eight PhDs, 12 postgraduates and several
technicians for a year. This diversion of high-calibre scientists
from serious research to routine testing and data gathering for
multinationals is a growing source of concern. The pressure to
earn money has led to a decline in new ideas within the
i n s t i t u t e, insiders say. The average earning from a contract
project today is about Rs 1.9 million ($42,000) as against Rs 0.5
million ($11,000) about five years ago. Dr. K. V. Raghavan,
director of IICT, however, believes that contract research has
exposed its researchers to new drug production methods that
could be relevant to India’s future needs.
While Dr. Mashelkar acknowledges the future risk of research
priorities being overturned by foreign contract research,he says
that there are sufficient checks in the system to ensure that it
does not dominate a lab’s agenda.
In a recent statement,Agarwal called upon institutional heads
like Mashelkar to “set up procedures to regulate their public-
funded scientists as they promote greater interactions with
i n d u s t r y.” He points out that a professor at the prestigious Indian
Institute of Technology in Delhi recently released a study, f u n d e d
by the Indian Oil Corporation,claiming that the introduction of
CNG (compressed natural gases) would increase pollution levels
in the city. The Delhi government has imposed use of CNG in
public transport.Agarwal,who has waged a long battle against
pollution in the capital, compares research to an iceberg.“The
public interest could just be the visible tip , with private interest
being the invisible bulk,” he warns. ■
R. Ramachandran, senior correspondent, Frontline magazine,
India
Li ke thousands of other researchers throughout Latin A m e r i c a , G i s e l l a
Orjeda left her native Peru in 1996.After years of effort and frustration,
this distinguished 41-year-old biologist decided exile was the only way to
continue the kind of academic career she wanted.
She graduated from Peru’s National Agricultural University and received a
grant to complete her doctorate at Birmingham University in Britain. O r j e d a
has been working since last year at France’s National Sequencing Centre
(Genoscope),where she is doing research on the rice genome. Research in
Latin A m e r i c a , she says, is “one big mess,” pointing to scant resources,
facilities and coordination.Worse still,it has no real objectives.
“In Pe r u , biologists can’t just decide what field they want to work in after gra-
duating. There aren’t any research institutes, so scientists have only two
choices—working in a university, without resources and sometimes even
without a research programme, or joining the International Potato Centre,
a Lima-based body that funds research in developing countries.As it groups
researchers from around the world,it’s very hard to land a job there. This
means you end up working in whatever project has a vacancy and not in one
that you’ve chosen.”
Orjeda was lucky enough to be accepted by the centre, marking a first step
in her international career.Those who cannot get such a prestigious visiting
card face a grim reality. Pe r u ,l i ke most Latin American countries, e a r m a r ke d
just 0.25 percent of its GDP for research at last count in 1984,according to
UN E S C O. In the United States, the figure is 2.63 percent but this does not include
the huge amount of research funded by the private sector.
“ That makes all the difference,” she says. “ Th e r e ’s no priva t e l y - f u n d e d
research in Pe r u . Big international firms don’t come looking for scientists in
our countries.Why should they? They prefer to hire people in rich countries
who have worked on specific projects and published their work. In Pe r u ,t h e r e
are barely any scientific journals.”
Orjeda can’t accept that science is such a low priority in many developing
c o u n t r i e s.“Putting money into our young minds is the best of all investments,
the only alternative to pull us out of underdevelopment,” she says. S h e
also deplores the fact that what little the government does spend on
research only benefits other countries when the scientists emigrate.
Would she like a big transnational company to pay her to run a research pro-
ject in Lima?  “That would be wonderful,” she says. And if they asked her
to hand over the rights to the results of her research?  “Hardly any scientists
anywhere have control over their results,” she says. “My contract with Geno-
scope states clearly that my research belongs to them.To pretend otherwise
is just wishful thinking.” ■
L ATIN A M E R I C A : CLOSED DOORS
28 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 29
S C H O L A R S  A T  R I S K
DONALD MACLEOD
JOURNALIST FOR THE GUARDIAN NEWSPAPER
When your univers i t y
closes down…
Since the 1930s, an organization in the UK has assisted refugee scholars
in pursuing their academic careers. Abdul Lalzad, a professor from Kabul,
is among those who have managed to continue their research
2 . POWER T R A P S
T
hermal engineering is not usually seen as
politically dangerous and in normal cir-
c u m s t a n c e s, a scientist working on solar
powered desalination would be welcome
in an arid land like A f g h a n i s t a n . But cir-
cumstances have not been normal in that unhappy
country for a long time.
At Kabul University,Professor Abdul Lalzad and
his colleagues struggled with shortages due to the
long civil war and declining numbers of staff and stu-
dents (a majority of them women in the early 1990s),
but they were able to pursue research and teaching.
The holder of a Russian masters degree, Lalzad held
senior positions at the university and had five text-
books and more than 30 published articles to his
credit.Kabul University was badly damaged during
the factional fighting between mujahedin groups
after the fall of the Russian-backed Najibullah govern-
ment, but it was not until the victory of the Taliban
that it was closed completely in 1996.
Uphill struggle
Lalzad’s academic work came to an abrupt halt
and his wife, P a s h t o o n , lost her job as a teacher when
women were forbidden to work. For his children,
especially his four daughters, educational prospects
were bleak.He worked for the Red Cross, in charge
of distributing food to 40,000 widows and disabled
p e o p l e. But he was arrested,beaten with Kalashnikovs
and thrown in prison on suspicion of giving infor-
mation to anti-Taliban forces. Contacts in the Red
Cross got him released, but knowing his life was in
danger he fled to Pakistan, where his wife and children
followed later.
He arrived in Britain in December 1998, where
resuming his academic research proved an uphill
struggle. After a frustrating 18-month wait while his
application for asylum was approved, he eventually
secured a place at South Bank University in London
to pursue his research.He was helped financially by the
Council for Assisting Refugee A c a d e m i c s, a body
founded in 1933 to assist Jewish academics and other
victims of the Nazi purges of universities. CARA also
helped to secure visas for his
f a m i l y, whose last members
arrived a week before the Ame-
rican bombing of A f g h a n i s t a n
s t a r t e d . Speaking at the launch of
the the Network for Education
and Academic Rights last June in
Paris (see p. 3 0 ) , Lalzad warned
that Afghanistan had become a
“roundabout of anti-civilization….
Vying to be the world’s biggest
supplier of opium, a safe-haven
for terrorists and religious extre-
m i s t s, a place with massive des-
truction of human rights, particu-
larly women’s rights,A f g h a n i s t a n
poses threats to regional and inter-
national peace and stability.”
Against this sombre back-
drop, his research into desalination techniques has
been progressing at South Bank, where he is building
an experimental model of a small solar- p o w e r e d
plant. In September, he presented his results to an
international conference and has been approached by
companies to patent his ideas.“If I get the results that
I obtained from mathematical modelling, it will be the
most cost effective and most efficient desalination
technology in the world,” he said.
CARA points out that the payback Britain has
enjoyed from helping refugee academics is out of all
proportion to the tiny investment: since the 1930s,
refugee scholars have included 18 Nobel prizewinners.
While the locations of persecution have changed, t h e
problem remains. CA R A is now helping more than 30
refugee academics, including an Iraqi paediatrician
who helped the Kurdish population,a parasitologist
from Somalia and an Ethiopian pathologist who
arrived in London with five bullets still in his body.
But the thirst for education is powerful.On her
second day in Britain, L a l z a d ’s daughter Shogofa
was enrolling in college: she intends to become a
doctor. ■
+ …
For more information on CARA, see:
www.academic-refugees.org
Professor Lalzad, reunited with his family in London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
A
cademic freedom is a highly sensitive
barometer of respect for human rights
within a society. Respect for academic
freedom indicates acceptance of open
debate and protection of differing ideas
and groups; its absence fosters a climate of ignorance
and intolerance—a perfect breeding ground for extre-
m i s m . Strong evidence for this proposition comes
from A f g h a n i s t a n , where the Ta l i b a n ’s first actions
were to shut down most higher education centres and
ban women and girls from attending school.But in less
extreme forms,governments around the world justify
violations of human rights by casting all critical thought
as an attack on public morality,national security,or cul-
tural purity. N a t u r a l l y,some of the first victims are aca-
demics whose job it is to question all aspects of their
own civilization, from its scientific theories to cultural
c o n s t r u c t s.
Attacks on academic freedom are not limited to
the Taliban or to the Islamic world. For instance,
academics have recently come under official or public
pressure in the United States and Canada for ques-
tioning various aspects of their governments’ past
or projected policies. In the current climate, the right
to speak out is of utmost importance, lest American
universities return to the dark days of anti-Commu-
nist hysteria.
During the Cold War, attacks on academic free-
dom had an apparent ideological rationale. Each side
attacked those thinkers who questioned their socie-
t y ’s reigning dogma: dissidents were subjected to
witch hunts and intellectual (and physical) exile. In
many countries, the response was more violent,
though no less predictable.Activist teachers and stu-
dents were killed, m a i m e d , jailed and silenced in
Latin A m e r i c a ,A f r i c a , and the Middle East, in China
and Korea (North and South), by governments ali-
gning themselves with one of the dominant super-
powers.
Rising
pressure
With the fall of the Berlin Wall,it was expected
that human rights—and academic freedom in parti-
cular—would improve. The belief was that there
would be no need to punish academics in a world see-
mingly focused on economic development, e s p e c i a l l y
where they were instrumental in creating and foste-
ring the newly emerging notions of financial, intel-
lectual and cultural globalization.
But the end of the Cold War and the advent of
easier global communications have placed acade-
mics even more directly in the line of fir e.Their rela-
tively high level of interaction across borders enables
them to judge their societies in comparison with
others, and to point out their governments’ shortco-
mings to their students and the public.With another
international conflict simmering,the pressure to curb
academic freedom is sure to grow.
A variety of new, troubling excuses are now
invoked to justify oppression of educators and their
students.The politics of ethnic and religious identity
In the line of fire
In the name of ethnic purity, religious conviction or even secularism,
scholars and their students are targets of oppression in a large swathe of
countries. Academics are stepping up efforts to marshal public opinion
2 . POWER T R A P S
SAM ZIA-ZARIFI
DIRECTOR OFTHE ACADEMIC FREEDOM PROGRAMME AT HUMAN RIGHTS WATCH
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 31
are chief among them,as governments define them-
selves as protectors of a particular orthodoxy—be it
ethnic purity, religious conviction or even secula-
rism—and persecute those who question it.
Academics in predominantly Muslim countries
have borne the heaviest burden of this new type of
o p p r e s s i o n .From Indonesia and Malaysia to Pakistan,
throughout Central Asia and the Middle East and all
the way to North Africa, scholars and their students
face tremendous pressure. These countries fall under
three broad categories.
First are those countries where religion is an offi-
cial part of the governing ideology. In Afghanistan,
P a k i s t a n , Iran and Saudi A r a b i a , governments justify
attacks against their academic critics on the basis of
ostensibly protecting the faith.In Pakistan this year,
a professor of hygiene was sentenced to die for ques-
tioning whether the Prophet of Islam would have
been able to observe proper religious demands before
his divine ordination.In Iran,where academics and
students have been debating the concordance of their
ancient religion and the modern world, scores of
scholars (including several clerics and theologians)
have been jailed for supposedly insulting religious sen-
s i t i v i t i e s. In these countries, harsh repression is often
excused by the supposed threat posed by foreign
ideas.
S e c o n d , where the govern-
ments have officially embraced a
“secular,” non-religious ideology,
like Turkey and many of the
Central Asian republics,even exhi-
biting piety can lead to official
harassment.Invoking a nebulous
Islamic threat to their orders,
authoritarian governments have
maintained their rule by restric-
ting all scholars who criticize it.
Th i r d , in the majority of predo-
minantly Muslim countries, governments have used
the supposed tension between Islam and the West to
justify years of administrative mismanagement, fiscal
c o r r u p t i o n , and political repression.Tunisia and Egypt,
two countries cast as stalwart allies of the We s t ,t o l e r a t e
neither religious nor liberal criticism of their govern-
m e n t s. I n s t e a d , pious scholars are silenced based on the
supposed threat they pose to the political order; the offi-
cially sanctioned religious establishment is then molli-
fied by government attacks on academics who criti-
cize injustice using the language of liberal democracy.
The politics of ethnic identity have also fuelled
attacks on academics. In Yu g o s l a v i a , social scientists
and historians were called upon to justify the excesses
of ethnic rivalry.When this attempt invariably failed,
the Milosevic government initiated a purge of Serbian
u n i v e r s i t i e s. In Indonesia, academics in areas with
ethnically distinct populations—such as the restive
Aceh province—came under pressure from the
government to squelch any discussion of greater local
a u t o n o m y.In Tu r k m e n i s t a n , the teaching of all foreign
languages has been banned in the name of fostering
Turkmen science.
A troubling new dimension of the limits imposed
on scholarship has been the “ p r i v a t i z a t i o n ”of assaults
on academic freedom. Militant opposition groups
are increasingly willing and able to attack academics
who call for reason.In Spain,academics in favour of
a peaceful resolution of Basque demands suffer inti-
midation at the hands of the separatist movement.
And in Colombia, both pro-government paramili-
tary groups and the guerrillas they fight have taken to
attacking universities in order to silence their critics.
But there is a significant countervailing trend.In
the past few years, academics have been increasingly
willing and able to work on behalf of their oppressed
colleagues. All the characte-
ristics that mark scholars and
students for persecution—
their critical minds, t h e i r
access to information from
inside and outside their own
borders—also allow them to
defend each other.
The response of the aca-
demic community worldwide
to China’s arrest earlier this
year of several scholars on
espionage charges is instruc-
tive. Over 400 China specialists from some 15 coun-
tries signed a petition in support of the scholars, cal-
ling on the Chinese government to substantiate its
charges and to adhere to domestic and international
standards of judicial process.The petition was released
to the media with the cooperation of several promi-
nent academic groups. The U. S. government inter-
ceded with China on behalf of those academics who
were American citizens or residents. Three were
released soon after they had been convicted by tri-
bunals widely described as falling short of proper
judicial standards.While international academic sup-
port played a pivotal role, several scholars—the exact
number is unknown—languish in detention on vague
and unsubstantiated charges.
The international community of scholars can
lobby effectively on behalf of persecuted colleagues,
but this requires cooperation over time—precisely the
support offered by the Human Rights Watch aca-
demic freedom programme, and more broadly, the
Network on Education and Academic Rights. ■
S C H O L A R S  A T  R I S K
Launched in June 2001 with seed money from UNESCO, the Network on Education and
Academic Rights (NEAR) serves as a clearing-house for information regarding attacks on
academic freedom worldwide and also strives to increase contact between groups monitoring
such attacks.The network is developing links with civil society at large to marshal opinion
against violations of academic freedom.Reports of abuses are posted at www.nearinter-
n a t i o n a l . o r g . NEAR will alert those able to take action to protest to governments and
international agencies. ■
A GLOBAL WAT C H D O G
The characteristics
that mark scholars
and students
for persecution also
allow them to defend
each other.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
W
hen sociologist Saadeddin Ibrahim was
sentenced to seven years in prison in
May 2001, a round of shock reverbe-
rated through Egyptian civil society.
The government has always upheld
its right to suppress political Islamists even as they
appease social conservatives by cracking down on the
heterodox fringe. I b r a h i m ,6 3 , did not fit either of these
e x t r e m e s. An internationally respected scholar, h i s
seminal research on the social origins of militant Islamist
groups appears to have had a major impact on the
g o v e r n m e n t ’s strategy for fighting them.In the 1990s,t h e
sociologist was given a prime-time TV spot to address the
nation on confronting extremism. He had close ties to
the first lady,Suzanne Mubarak,and wrote articles in the
state-owned press.
Unlike many state-sponsored scholars, h o w e v e r,
Ibrahim never tempered his views on the regime. H e
openly discussed the problems of Egypt’s Christian
“ m i n o r i t y ”(the very use of that word violates nationalist
taboos because the Egyptian state considers the Copts an
integrated part of the nation) and was critical of the
Arab world’s lack of democracy.One theory attributes his
downfall to his coining of the word “ G o m l u k i y a ”( R e p u-
blarchy) to refer to Arab states where the presidency is
handed from father to son.
In May 2000, I b r a h i m ’s Ibn Khaldoun Centre for
Development Studies was raided. He and 27 of his col-
leagues were arrested and eventually charged with  “ t a r-
nishing the reputation of the state”and “accepting foreign
funding without permission”as well as embezzling money
from his donors and bribing state television offic i a l s.Th e
investigators showed particular interest in a programme
to monitor parliamentary elections scheduled that fall.
Ibrahim was given one final chance. In September
2 0 0 0 ,according to one of his lawyers,he was released on
the understanding that if he kept quiet,the charges would
be dropped.I n s t e a d ,he continued to speak out about his
case and announced that he would continue to monitor
the elections. Four days later formal charges were fil e d
against him.
Uneven support
During the four-month trial that opened in
November 2000, the prosecution denounced Ibrahim in
speeches laced with flowery rhetoric. “Given its role in
the region it is not surprising that Egypt should be the
subject of defamation,” said chief prosecutor Sameh
S e i f,“but what is cause for wonder is that it comes from
w i t h i n , from those who share our lives yet leave only
harm and pain in their wake.”The sociologist was labelled
a “ s w i n d l e r ”and a “genius at deception,”who concocted
false reports about Egypt and sold them abroad. Th e
defense argued,among other points, that any number of
organizations accepted foreign funding and published
reports that could be considered critical of the state.
Ibrahim was convicted on three of four counts (he was
acquitted of the bribery charge) and sentenced to seven
years in prison;six of his co-defendants received two- or
five-year sentences,and the 21 others received one-year
suspended sentences.
Because of Ibrahim’s extensive connections abroad,
and his dual Egyptian-American nationality, the Egyp-
tian regime faced a rash of harsh editorials after the
c o n v i c t i o n . Th e Washington Po s t asked the U. S. t o
remember the verdict when Egypt’s aid package came
up for review.Although some of Ibrahim’s fellow aca-
demics have rallied to his defense,the majority has not.
According to former diplomat and political writer Hus-
sein A m i n ,“this is mostly due to envy. He is considered
t h e foremost Egyptian intellectual by the We s t . H e ’s
made a lot of money and gets invited to many semi-
n a r s.” Throughout the trial, the local press was more
interested in playing up his alleged treason than defen-
ding his freedom of expression.
Some of Ibrahim’s colleagues expect him to be
released this winter.He is reportedly in poor health. Th e
fate of his co-defendants is unsure.For now,I b r a h i m ’s case
stands as a warning to fellow academics.According to a
joint statement by Amnesty International and Human
Rights Wa t c h , the trial  “falls in the context of a number
of blows intended to muzzle civil society in Egypt.” ■
STEVE NEGUS
JOURNALIST BASED IN CAIRO,
FORMER EDITOR OFTHE CAIRO TIMES
No a p o l o g i e s
Since last May, a distinguished Egyptian sociologist has been in prison,
allegedly for tarnishing the state’s reputation. His case stands as
a warning to fellow intellectuals
2 . POWER T R A P S
In the heat of the trial.
There is only
one good,
knowledge, 
and one evil,
ignorance.
Socrates, 
Greek philosopher 
(470-399 B.C.) 
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 33
R
ussian writer Viktor A s t a fiev is no stranger
to controversy.A war veteran, the 77-year-
old Siberian is renowned for his ruthlessly
truthful stories about the Great Patriotic
Wa r, as World War II is known in Russia.
But when his latest book, The Jolly Soldier was
published last year, even a writer of the stature of
Astafiev, regarded as one of Russia’s greatest living
a u t h o r s, was unprepared for the rabid reaction he
met.Astafiev, who lives in the Siberian city of Kras-
n o y a r s k , was pilloried in the press and vilified by
regional politicians for his uncompromising portrayal
of the horrors of the Soviet military. Upsetting some
of the holy cows of Russian wartime myth, notably on
how the nation united to throw off the fascists with
total resolve,A s t a fiev describes how ill-trained boys
were thrown into battle and Red Army soldiers used
as cannon fodder. He also dispels the myth that
peoples of the Soviet Union were unanimously
opposed to the German invaders, instead showing that
the latter were initially welcomed as liberators from
Stalin’s tyranny.
Return to old habits
Members of the city council,many of whom,like
A s t a fiev are a product of Soviet wartime Commu-
n i s m , voted to scrap a small local pension he was paid.
Distressed by the furor,Astafiev, 77,was admitted to
hospital with heart trouble.Now back at home, n e i t h e r
he nor his friends in the city will talk about an episode
that strikes at the core of a new phenomenon in post-
Communist Russia:historical denial.
The A s t a fiev incident is but one acute example of
a growing trend in Russia away from the academic
and intellectual openness that accompanied the fir s t
flush of freedom after the collapse of the Soviet
Union ten years ago.
The upheavals that followed the failed coup by
Politburo hardliners in August 1991 disrupted all the
norms of accepted Soviet-era secrecy. For two years,
researchers, both Russian and foreign,had a heyday
as archivists opened their doors in the heady atmos-
phere of freedom.Following the 1993 stand-off bet-
ween Boris Yeltsin and reactionary political forces, t h e
new power consolidated its position.The process of
forming a new Russian state called for a review of
security structures and secrecy rules.As a result,a new
law on state secrets was adopted, ruling that the
majority of documents must be declassified and made
public after 30 years.
While the Russian Academy of Sciences is wor-
king with history faculties around the country to
develop a new cadre of young historians, r e s e a r-
chers now investigating the grim world of the Soviet
past report an increasing reluctance of many archivists
to allow access to party, secret police and govern-
ment documents despite the 1993 law.
The retreat from the openness of the early post-
Communist years began towards the end of the Ye l t s i n
e r a .The work of the state body responsible for declas-
sifying secret documents ground to a halt two years
ago, and directors of once open and helpful archives
have returned to the old Soviet habit of saying “ n o ”t o
virtually all sensitive requests, academics say.
Nikita Petrov, a reputed scholar and expert on the
NKVD (Stalin’s secret police),who now works with
the Moscow-based human rights organization Memo-
r i a l , claims that “it is much more difficult to gain
access to archives. There is a growth both in the ten-
dency to keep documents secret and to commercia-
lize them—to charge for access.”
S C H O L A R S  A T  R I S K
NICK HOLDSWORTH
CONTRIBUTOR TO THE TIMES HIGHER EDUCATION SUPPLEMENT AND SEVERAL BRITISH NEWSPAPERS; AUTHOR OFTHE BOOK MOSCOW: THE BEAUTIFULAND THE
DAMNED, LIFE IN RUSSIA IN TRANSITION (ANDRE DEUTSCH, LONDON, 2000).
Bound by n o s t a l g i a
In Russia, a new generation of historians is in the making, but society
at large does not seem pressed to question the darker moments
of the Soviet era. For now, nostalgia holds the high ground
2 . POWER T R A P S
A 1993 law gives historians access to archives,a master key to the past.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
Many archivists are from the old guard, and a
nostalgia for the past combined with growing use of
nationalist symbols to rally an economically and
socially troubled country allows them to slip back
into their old habits.
Petrov acknowledges that the 1993 law is remar-
kably democratic and workable, and that  Memorial
has relied upon the threat of using it to force a number
of archives to give access to specific documents.The
challenge to academic freedom is not yet a legal one,
he says, but a social and personal challenge that is
often harder to identify and combat.Th e r e ’s been no
change in the law, but the spirit of Russia has shifted
in the last couple of years, he suggests.
Petrov’s experience is not shared by all.Natalia
Ye g o r o v a , deputy director of the Institute of Uni-
versal History, which is part of the Russian A c a d e m y
of Sciences, scotches all talk of curbs to academic
f r e e d o m ,apart from the recurring and thorny issue of
poverty-level pay.
“Unfortunately it is true that the state commission
for declassifying documents has not been working for
the past two years, but access to archives very much
depends on which archive you go to.There are diffe-
rent rules in different places. Many archives, i n c l u d i n g
much of the higher (Communist) party archives, are
no longer secret.”
Working on Soviet foreign policy and the Cold
Wa r,Yegorova says the main forces limiting her work
are fin a n c i a l . The Academy of Sciences, h o w e v e r,
through its humanities and scientific foundation,
makes grants available to allow for an average $100
monthly top-up to normal salaries.
“ With the exception of a few difficulties acces-
sing  some archives or funding sources,we are working
now as we always have. In fact, at international confe-
rences our American colleagues are surprised at how
fierce and controversial the debates are between Rus-
sian researchers on historical issues,” she says.
A move by the Academy of Sciences earlier this
year to force all researchers to report
contacts with foreigners caused
many to fear the re-introduction of
Soviet-style controls, but nothing
came of it,she said.
Petrov believes the trend to
greater secrecy reflects a desire to
draw a comforting cloth of nostalgia
over current difficulties. “There’s an
inner unwillingness to understand the
criminal past of the country.Te a c h e r s,
doctors and other state workers are
paid little and struggle to make a
living. In these circumstances people
often seek mental comfort in the
past,” he says. The Astafiev case is a
sad illustration of this—someone does
not want the truth to be known.But
we must take courage from the fact
that A s t a fiev wasn’t imprisoned.E v e n
if his oppressors had this desire, t o d a y
they can’t do it.”
Teenage
truths
Others are taking courage from
what a new generation growing up in
Russia is making of the country’s
p a s t . Irina Scherbakov, a professor of
history at the Russian Humanitarian University in
M o s c o w, recently organized a nationwide contest
through Memorial encouraging schoolchildren bet-
ween 14 and 18 years old to send in essays and illus-
trations about Russia in the 20th century. She received
over 3,500 contributions: “ C h i l d r e n ’s entries drew
on interviews with their grandparents, S o v i e t - e r a
documents from archives, family diaries and photo-
g r a p h s.Although the sample is not scientific, their res-
ponses give confidence for a more frank appraisal of
our history,” Scherbakov said.“Many of them treated
the past critically. It really gave us a big dose of opti-
mism.”
It’s a bright beacon in an otherwise bleak land-
s c a p e, Scherbakov concedes:“People do not want to
analyze or argue about the Soviet period; they prefer
n o s t a l g i a . Life today is too hard and many, e s p e c i a l l y
older people, are loathe to face up to their own res-
ponsibilities for the part they played during those
times.” ■
A grim reminder of a Soviet gulag in Siberia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 35
Y ou often lament the gap between the aca-
demic world and pressing social re a l i t i e s.
You certainly feel that in A f r i c a .I ’ m
living at the epicentre of an HIV/AIDS
e p i d e m i c : the province of KwaZulu
Natal has the highest rate of infection in the world.
In this context,AIDS becomes a human rights issue.
I don’t know that universities are engaging enough
in addressing such issues on public platforms at a
time when social justice is so manifestly not part of
our world.Yet it is our social responsibility to do so.
Whether you call it academic freedom or university
a u t o n o m y, academics are a kind of independent
estate which should be providing intellectual lea-
d e r s h i p,all the more so in these very difficult times.
Not doing so can only be regarded as an ethical
f a i l u r e. I also worry, h o w e v e r, about a creeping anti-
intellectualism that undervalues the reflective
impulse in favour of a tough-minded and  often
short-sighted pragmatism.
How can the university go about addressing poverty
and inequality? 
In the late 1980s, we took the bull by the horns
and started a “Strategic Initiatives”dialogue during
which we engaged with many different communities
in the country by asking how the university could
accommodate their concerns and play a role in the
transition from apartheid to democracy.This helped
us to anticipate and to talk with a wide range of
people, some of whom we saw as part of a govern-
ment-in-waiting.
Take the example of our agricultural faculty.
For years it focused on training commercial far-
mers. Today, it has broadened its focus to include
small-scale farming, food security and poverty alle-
v i a t i o n ,and the faculty has lost none of its standing.
There are other issues with which the university
should be intensely e n g a g i n g. Law faculties, f o r
e x a m p l e, should be taking the lead in framing A I D S
as a human rights issue.
Fe a rs are often voiced about academic freedom being
undermined by economic pre s s u re s. Do you expe-
rience this in your daily work?
I have confidence in our ability to draw the line
and to walk away from whatever is going to
compromise our integrity. All over the world the
public purse is being stretched to accommodate rising
numbers of students in higher education.I have spent
a large amount of my time trying to secure funding.
I put funders on the line just as I put academics on the
line. With regard to medical and social research on
H I V / A I D S, a field in which we are very active, I
appeal to the moral conscience of funders. I remind
them we are all living in the midst of one of the grea-
test catastrophes that has befallen humankind.
Does the university have to be organized differe n t l y
to play an effective role in society?
I argue vigorously for universities to actively
try and make their borders more permeable, more
porous.We cannot pretend to know everything, or
to represent all society’s constituents and interests.
Yet they are all important to intellectual life and to
an understanding of what universities can contri-
bute. Partnerships are essential to this understan-
ding.
Not only with the corporate world however.
By no means. We’ve had remarkable partner-
ships with community organizations dating back
to the apartheid era when we housed 84 NGOs on
our campus. This was extremely beneficial for the
u n i v e r s i t y : we were exposed to a wide range of
social issues, notably demand from NGOs for sup-
port in conceiving and managing projects.NGOs are
the fastest growing movement in the world and
universities are not doing enough to create educa-
tion for future leaders in this fie l d .To meet demand,
we recently created a Centre for Civil Society which
focuses on NGO-related study. I ’ve also pushed
very hard to get a compulsory community service
component integrated into our degree programme.
It’s a very powerful learning tool but also a very
effective way of getting things done on the ground
because you can harness so many students to the col-
lective effort.
Do think there is a need for an international instru-
ment on academic freedom,as has been proposed?
Yes. We’ve seen terrible infringements on aca-
demic freedom in Africa and elsewhere. If other aca-
demics don’t speak up about these violations, who
will? None of us can be complacent in any way
about the dangers of such violations. ■
* Professor Gourley is also Vice-Chancellor elect
of the Open University in the United Kingdom.
INTERVIEW BY CYNTHIA GUTTMAN
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
B e i n g on alert
Academics around the world should be engaging much more forcefully in
the search for social justice, says Brenda Gourley, vice-chancellor of the
University of Natal in South Africa* 
S C H O L A R S  A T  R I S K
To a degree,
academic
freedom is a
reality today
because Socrates
practised civil
disobedience.
Martin Luther King, American
pastor
and civil rights leader
(1929-1968)
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
O
PHILIPPE DEMENET
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Economic rights:
the big comeback
Is the economic divide a root cause of the September 11 attacks? For several years, human rights
organizations have made the fight against economic injustice a top priority
ne after the other, the major NGOs cam-
paigning for civil and political rights ral-
lied in the mid-1990s to the banner of
“economic rights.” Marching behind it
was the long-established International
Federation of Human Rights Leagues
(FIDH) and its 105 national affil i a t e s
along with Human Rights Watch and its
supporters in the academic community.
Even more remarkably, the emer-
gency medical aid organization Doctors
Without Borders, which has 2,000 volun-
teers worldwide, launched a campaign in
1996 for access to basic medicines. And
fin a l l y,Amnesty International and its one
million members joined this movement
last August.
“We have to be consistent and rele-
vant,” say these organizations to explain
the move. Governments have to be criti-
cized for their failings in health and edu-
cation policy, transnational companies
for their hypocrisy in doing business in
places mired in poverty,and international
financial institutions for being blind to
the social effects of their programmes.
Beyond the Cold War
Have they been slow in waking up?
Economic rights were legally enshrined
in the International Covenant on Eco-
n o m i c, Social and Cultural Rights.
Adopted by the UN General Assembly
on December 16, 1966 (along with the
International Covenant on Civil and Po l i-
tical Rights), it came into effect 10 years
later and has been signed by 141 coun-
t r i e s. Governments are expected to take
steps to improve the living standards of
their people by ensuring adequate food,
clothing and housing, the right to a job,
training and a “fair” wage, the right to
join a trade union and go on strike, and
the right to health care and education.
For many years, the covenant was
hampered by its ambitious reach and by
the Cold Wa r. Communist countries
hailed its principles, while the We s t
remained primarily interested in civil and
political freedoms. Though they were
dedicated to defending all human rights,
some organizations such as the FIDH in
practice focused only on civil rights.
“You have to remember that in the
1970s and 1980s, many dictatorships—
communist,Latin American,Asian and
African—made defending civil rights an
absolute priority for us,” says FIDH exe-
cutive director Antoine Bernard. Th e
resurgence of economic rights was one
by-product of the collapse of the Berlin
Wall and globalization.With the spread
of the market economy,multi-party poli-
tical systems and technological change,
globalization has meant “growing wealth
for some, but destitution and despair for
many,” says Pierre Sané, former secre-
tary-general of Amnesty International,1
in the organization’s 2001 annual report.
Since the expansion of A m n e s t y ’s
m a n d a t e, its researchers and campaign
directors have felt more at ease. “Until
n o w, we were calling the famine in Sudan
the result of the forcible movement of
people in violation of their civil and poli-
tical rights,” says Amnesty researcher
Bénédicte Goderiaux.“Now we can look
at things in a different way, such as whe-
ther people have access to food.”
Avoiding
platitudes
But as Bernard points out,“ i t ’s easier
to fight for an opposition fig u r e ’s freedom
than for a change in a structural adjust-
ment policy.” Freedom may be the same
indivisible principle the world over, but
one cannot necessarily ask for the same
level of access to health care or employ-
ment in a rich country as in a poor one.
“ We have to be able to set minimum stan-
dards,” says Joanne Csete, an expert on
HIV/AIDS and children’s rights resear-
cher with Human Rights Wa t c h . “ Th a t
way even the poorest countries can start
applying them.”
Some campaigners are already
overwhelmed by the vast range of
economic rights and some enquiry
r e p o r t s read like catalogues of complaint.
Last June, Human Rights Watch publi-
shed a report on Kenyan children affected
by A I D S. After a long section on the
impact of the epidemic in A f r i c a , t h e
report called on the Kenyan government
to ensure that all children of primary
school-age attended school.“ We ’re trying
to suggest some practical steps to govern-
m e n t s,” says Csete,who wrote the report,
“but maybe we’ve been over-optimistic in
this case.”
In an effort to avoid such platitudes,
she says, Human Rights Watch has
decided to focus on “situations where
arbitrary action by governments involves
violation of economic and social rights.”
Amnesty has vowed to maintain its
traditional moral authority by pinpointing
individual rights violations, w i t h o u t
c o m m e n t , then following them up with a
thorough and impartial investigation.
“It won’t be easy.
Figuring out the effect
of an economic
investment on human
rights is much harder
than working out
how it affects
the environment.”
◗ E T H I C S
36 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
“ We ’re going to try to establish if someo-
n e ’s physical and mental integrity has
been violated through a denial of eco-
nomic rights,” says Salil Tr i p a t h i , w h o
runs Amnesty’s economic relations and
human rights campaign.“It won’t be easy.
Figuring out the effect of an economic
investment on human rights is much
harder than working out how it affects the
environment.”
For example, how do you measure
the impact of sealing-off the Palestinian
territories on the economic and social
rights of their inhabitants? The FIDH
has tried to do this. “ We noted the
tonnage of tomatoes exported from
G a z a , before and during the closure,”
says Bernard. “ Then we compared
t h e figures and calculated how much
income the farmers and their families
had lost.”
Another difficulty is that with the
wider field of action, there are far more
potential targets.As well as heads of state,
the usual subjects of reports and peti-
t i o n s, there are now international fin a n c i a l
institutions and multinational companies.
But these fir m s,which are private bodies,
are in no way bound by UN covenants.
“Company bosses are human beings too,”
says Amnesty spokesman Kamal Samari.
“ We can persuade them that making pro-
fits doesn’t have to go hand in hand with
a lack of morality.”
Drawing up voluntary
conduct codes
Long before Amnesty embraced
these extended goals,Sané was a pioneer
of the new approach.For four consecutive
years, he went to the annual meeting of
world economic leaders in Davos (Swit-
zerland) to plead the case for active sup-
port of human rights. He also met the
heads of oil companies and urged them to
draw up voluntary codes of conduct that
would help the firms comply with cer-
tain moral limits.
Leading human rights organizations
have chosen to work with multinational
firms rather than enter into a potentially
costly confrontation.“We don’t draw up
codes of conduct ourselves, but if a firm
asks our opinion, we emphasize two
points,” says Tripathi. “That implemen-
tation of the code should be verified regu-
larly by an independent outsider—an
a c a d e m i c,NGO or firm of auditors—and
that the code is applied at all levels of
the firm and in all its activities, not just at
headquarters.”
Some companies, such as Shell, B P,
Levi Strauss or Reebok, have adopted
codes themselves. But their behaviour
has not always been in line with their
promises, as Amnesty discovered in the
case of the Canadian oil firm Ta l i s m a n
E n e r g y, which was operating in southern
Sudan amid a civil war. In May 2000,an
Amnesty report, The Human Price of
O i l, accused government troops and their
militias of “serious human rights viola-
t i o n s ” in the region of the oilfie l d s, i n c l u-
ding massacres of civilians and forced
displacement of people.The report noted
that government troops were in charge of
protecting Talisman’s installations.
After this report and others, the com-
pany devised a code of conduct,
appointed a full-time human rights offic e r
and said it would examine its “ c o r p o r a t e
In eastern Ecuador:how do you measure the damaging effects of the oil industry on the economic rights of local inhabitants?
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
social responsibility”in a professionally
audited annual report.Amnesty objected
to the company’s 2000 report on grounds
that it “underplayed the serious viola-
tions being perpetrated.”
Seeking
moral approval
Multinational fir m s, eager to win any
kind of good conduct tag,are reaching out
to human rights organizations. “ Th e y
contact us regularly, saying they want our
o p i n i o n ,but they really want to use us to
get a stamp of moral approval,” says Ber-
nard.
The most damning resources human
rights organizations have for now are
“free speech” and exposing an offender to
“public disgrace.”Bernard says these are
just “symbolic weapons, but they can
damage the public reputation of a com-
pany or country.”
One result of the campaign has been
to force the International Monetary Fund
(IMF) into changing its language and
priorities. Since 1999, says the assistant
director of the IMF’s European offic e,
Sergio Pereira Leite, “we’ve been stres-
sing that social expenditure, such as health
and education, should be maintained in
countries whose balance of payments
w e ’re trying to improve. We no longer
talk about ‘structural adjustment’ pro-
grammes but ‘poverty reduction and
growth.’ Now it’s time for us to expand
our relationship with human rights orga-
nizations.”
Some bodies, such as the FIDH,
would like a stronger instrument, s u c h
as an “international economic tribunal”
where victims, represented by human
rights organizations, could lodge com-
plaints against governments and multi-
national firms for violating their eco-
nomic rights. The proposal has aroused
great hostility,but those who believe eco-
nomic rights should be a matter of law
point to the 1961 European Social
Charter adopted by the 41 member- s t a t e s
of the Council of Europe.
A committee of independent experts
who monitor the Charter’s application
hears complaints from recognized NGOs.
In 1998, Portugal was formally asked to
put an end to child labour and in 2001,
Greece was criticized for laws that
implied a version of forced labour.
“The laws of business should not be
considered as being above international
agreements on human rights,”says Sylvia
O s t r y, of Toronto University’s Munk
Center for International Studies. “ Th e
real test is probably going to be about
access to anti-AIDS drugs. South Africa
and Brazil have already rejected inter-
national business rules on intellectual
property in the name of the basic human
right to good health.” ■
1. N ow UNESCO’s assistant director-
general for social  and human
sciences.
César Carrillo*:
“The right to life in Colombia”
What do you think of the new tendency of many NGOs to include
economic rights alongside their demands for civil and political rights?
Many of them hadn’t previously considered us defenders of human rights,
but they’re looking at things differently now. In Colombia, trade unionists
have fought hardest for civil and political rights, as well as for economic
rights. In our country, the priority today is defending the right to life. Our
union has organized activities to expose the abuse many communities suf-
fer and to defend the victims. We also campaign against the government’s
failure to address human rights violations.
Many people have been killed in these campaigns.
Trade unionists in today’s Colombia are heroes. More trade unionists are
murdered here than in any other country on earth. Figures compiled by the
Workers’ Trade Union (USO) show that 10,000 trade union members are
directly under threat.Amnesty International listed the murders of 112 trade
unionists in Colombia last year and 93 more up to August this year. More
than 50 members of the USO alone have been killed in recent years. In my
view, this is because criticism of us has been distorted to link us with the
guerrillas, making us a target for the paramilitary. And the state doesn’t do
enough to protect us against these attacks.
Do you see any difference between violations of economic rights and
human rights?
The most important rights for me are civil and political rights. Mine have
been violated because I’m prevented from carrying out my trade union
work.Having said that,economic rights are basic ones that enable people
to lead a decent life. But, as I say, more important than that is the right
to life itself. ■
Interview by Asbel López, UNESCO Courier journalist
* César Carrillo was head of Colombia’s main oil industry union, the much-per -
secuted Unión Sindical Obrera (Workers’ Trade Union, USO), from 1988 to
1995. He and 15 colleagues were arrested in 1996, and Carrillo spent
18months in prison. At the end of 1998, following the murder of his lawyer,
Eduardo Umaña Mendoza, he was forced into exile after receiving death
threats.
◗ E T H I C S
38 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 39
S
INTERVIEW BY SOPHIE BOUKHARI
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
Tune into the “ n e w
conscience of Islam”
There is a reformist current in Islam, one that takes a critical approach to its origins. For Moroccan
philosopher Abdou Filali-Ansary*, if Muslims had more room to freely debate issues, religion and
politics might no longer be so closely entwined
ince the 19th century, many Muslim thin-
ke rs have sought to “ re f o r m ” I s l a m i c
t h o u g h t . But their efforts have hard l y
led to modern Muslim re g i m e s.Why not?
When there’s a crisis, people tend to
go back to their roots. In the 19th cen-
tury, the reform movement was very
strong because, with the colonial
c o n q u e s t s, modernity suddenly burst
into dar el-islam, the “house of Islam.”
Modernity meant people changing
their relationship with both the world
and themselves. For the first time,
through science, they realized that
many things, such as certain weather
patterns or illnesses, were not a matter
of fate. The social order no longer
seemed impossible to change either.
Revolutions could sweep away des-
pots and people could improve their
living standards.
From India to North A f r i c a , a great
wave of thinkers arose to declare that
Islam, in its earliest form, was in fact
moving towards this powerful moder-
n i t y. But Jamal ad-Din al-Afghani in
I r a n , Mohammed Abduh in Egypt and
others didn’t follow the example of
Christian reformers, who swept away
previous interpretations in order to
look at the scriptures themselves with
a fresh eye.These intellectuals regarded
the history of the first Muslims as a
reference point, on par with the Ko r a n
and the S u n n a h (see glossary p. 4 1 ) .
Their return to the roots of Islam was
d e f e n s i v e. They wanted to reassure
Muslims, to boost their confidence by
telling them that their religion favoured
progress.
The most important event in the
* Editor of the North African book
review journal P r o l o g u e s and author
of a number of books on Islam.
A billboard advertisement in Esfahan for an Iranian movie.
C U L T U R E ◗
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
◗ C U L T U R E
40 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
recent history of Islamic thought came
later, in the 1920s, with a schism in the
reform movement. On one side was
Hassan el-Banna,an Egyptian famous
for founding the Muslim Brotherhood,
and on the other, Ali Abderraziq,also
from Egypt, who was the forerunner
of the critical movement within Islam.
Having translated his work, I can
say he was the first one to go back to the
roots with a critical eye. He empha-
sized that the basic tenets of Islam,
obedience and consultation, are not
r u l e s of political organization but
m o r a l v a l u e s. In return for being
o b e y e d , a person with responsibilities—
f a m i l y, business or political—must
a v o i d making decisions alone like a
tyrant and take into account the views
of those he leads. Abderraziq showed
t h a t while the Islamic political order is
built by Muslims, there is no religious
duty to do so.You can see there’s a big
difference.
But the Prophet Mohammed founded
an Islamic city that has fuelled the ima-
ginary universe of Muslims.Wh a t ’s more,
he was a warrior himself.
What the Prophet founded at
Medina wasn’t a political entity. It was
a religious community. Mohammed was
born in a society where there was no
s t a t e.The tribes were constantly at war
with each other, except for four months
of truce every year. He tried to preach
in this environment for 10 years but
the only followers he drew were the
rejected—the slaves, women and mino-
rity tribes. So he left for Medina in 622
(in the Hegiran calendar), where he
managed to reconcile two enemy tribes
and set up the first Muslim community.
It was a sort of anti-tribe, which ruled
out identifying oneself with a particular
c l a n .You joined it because you wanted
to become a Muslim,by simply taking
an oath (a profession of faith). But this
community was attacked by other tribes
and the Prophet had to defend himself
and become a warrior.
At the time of his death,Arabia had
embraced the new religion and he was
planning an expedition to bring the
new message to Syria. The circum-
stances of history made Medina a
centre of religious proselytism. But the
orders Mohammed left behind were
c l e a r : never use force to convert people.
But there is a very violent verse in the
Koran which says: “So when the sacred
months have passed away, then slay the
i d o l a t e rs wherever you find them, a n d
t a ke them captives and besiege them
and lie in wait for them in every ambush.”
Ye s, that s u r a is very violent indeed.
It was revealed to the Prophet in a war
s i t u a t i o n , when the polytheists were
threatening the very survival of the
M u s l i m s.Alongside this verse,I ’d quote
another of the Prophet’s command-
m e n t s :“ B e w a r e, respect people, do not
rip up trees, burn houses or rape
women.” This is what drew people to
Islam.
After Mohammed died in 632, t h e
Muslim community became a pro p e r
state.
Muslims were immediately divided
over this. Those who defended an
empire (caliphate) led by a chief
“elected” by an assembly, carried the
d a y.The supporters of A l i , who wanted
a state run by the Prophet’s family,
created Shiism. But a third branch is
always forgotten. These were the ear -
liest Muslims, such as Malik ibn
Nuwaira and Abu Dharr, who said:
“We’re a religious community, so why
set up a state?”They were executed or
forced out. Over the centuries, m a n y
thinkers who’ve taken up their ideas
have met the same fate. Their history
has never been written.
Why not?
No authority allowed it. In the 20th
century, the critical movement conti-
nued to be sidelined but it stayed alive.
Ali Abderraziq has had many spiritual
h e i r s, such as Mohammed Mahmud
Taha in Sudan, who was hanged by
Sudanese President Jaafar el-Numeiry
in 1985 and whose writings sell tens of
thousands of copies. Today you have
the Tunisians Mohammed Talbi and
Abdelmajid and Mohammed Charfi,
and in Pakistan Fazlur Rahman and
Abdul Karim Surush in Iran. They all
point out that advocates of the “ s t a t e ”
triumphed for historical reasons and
based themselves on one of many pos-
sible interpretations of the canonical
t e x t s. O b v i o u s l y, these people don’t go
out and kill….
But leaving history aside, t h e re are
sizeable obstacles to criticism of the
Ko ra n , such as its “ u n c re a t e d ,”b a s i c a l l y
divine nature.
This notion developed much later,
three or four centuries after the Pro-
p h e t ’s death. It began as a minority
view but the theologians who argued
for it were so badly persecuted that
they won the support of the masses and
This manuscript,kept in Uzbekistan, is the earliest known written version of the Koran.
It is on UNESCO’s Memory of the World register.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
so managed to impose it. Even more
important is the fact that the famous
concept of sharia, conceived as a law
which is meant to govern every aspect
of a believer’s life, took shape nearly
200 years after the Prophet’s death.
This must be stressed because it marked
an extremely important break with the
p a s t . It was established by Mohammed
Ibn Idriss Shafi’ i , a brilliant young intel-
lectual born 150 years after the Pro-
phet died. Early Islam only talks about
hudud (limits and restraints) imposed
by God, rather like the commandments
not to kill people or seize women.
Islamic jurists draw on it in different
ways to give laws and customs an
ethical basis. But Shafi’i went much fur-
ther and used the h u d u d in the Koran to
come up with rules for every aspect of
human behaviour.
At every stage in Islam’s history, i t ’s
always the hardliners who win.Why?
Because very early on, p o l i t i c s
seized on religion and subsequent reli-
gious debate was always dominated by
political considerations and “ i n s t r u-
mentalized”for partisan ends.
Let’s talk about this modern fundamen-
talist branch of Islam born in the early
20th century, at opposite ends of what
you call the critical movement.Why has
it been so popular?
Fundamentalism is driven by two
major forces that are crushing us like
jaws of steel. I t ’s been supported by
local regimes and by the new world
order dominated by “the We s t .” I t ’s
also been used everywhere to combat
the left and liberation movements. As
C h a r fi pointed out in his book I s l a m
and Fr e e d o m , Arab and Muslim
regimes didn’t just fund movements
but drew up education policies aimed at
teaching the fundamentalist view of
Islam.So the idea of a lasting confron-
tation has been planted in people’s
minds.
The younger generations are cut off
from universal ideas. Philosophy is no
longer taught in Muslim countries or
else in such a minor way as to have
little effect.The other major force dri-
ving fundamentalism has to do with
international politics and economic
relations between North and South.
Since rich countries support despotic
regimes, the mosque is the only place
where the local and world economic
order can be contested. Add to that
what are perceived as attacks from the
outside, such as massive Western sup-
port for Israel and the bombing of Iraq,
Srebrenica (Bosnia) and now Afghan-
i s t a n .The media also carry a heavy res-
ponsibility because they only talk about
Islam when there are attacks and pre-
tend not to know that fundamentalists
are a minority. All this is setting the
scene for a new Hundred Years’ War
and creating an extreme division bet-
ween Islam and the West.
So you agree with Samuel Huntington’s
ideas on the “clash of civilizations.”
No. Huntington depicted this clash
as something almost biological, as if we
were all fundamentally different,as if
culture was a kind of second nature. I n
fact, the clash is a historical construc-
t i o n , a product of specific conditions
and political choices.
So you don’t see Islam as hostile to
democracy and human rights…
D e m o c r a cy and human rights are
recent victories won by humanity. The
values that the fundamentalists and
Huntington say are Western are in fact
u n i v e r s a l . D e m o c r a cy is like fire or
Arabic numerals—the property of
humankind.Islam is neither for it nor
against it.A Muslim can only be against
it if he accepts the historical interpre-
tations of the Koran as “ u n c r e a t e d ”
and the s h a r i a —these fantasies that
came later and claimed religion must
rule everything. Of course,We s t e r n e r s
were the first to achieve democracy,
but they did so in special historical cir-
cumstances and they too had violent
arguments before doing away with part
of their religious heritage.
In Muslim countries, the critical
school of thought might have a chance
if there were minimal conditions of
freedom.Look at the recent history of
Iran. In the 1950s, the country was at
about the same stage of development as
Greece. If the CIA hadn’t overthrown
Mohammed Mossadegh in favour of
t h e S h a h , he would probably have
u s e dt h e c o u n t r y ’s oil to move towards
democracy.
But the Shah suppressed all dissent
and accepted U. S. d o m i n a t i o n . O n c e
a g a i n , Muslims were forced back to the
roots of their identity in Islam. Even
left-wing Iranians eventually supported
Khomeini as a way to fight the Shah’s
d i c t a t o r s h i p.Twenty years later, in 1997,
more than two-thirds of Iranian voters
put their weight behind Mohammed
K h a t a m i , a supporter of this critical
school of thought that I call “the new
conscience of Islam.” ■
+ …
For an extensive database on Islam,see
www.fondation.org.ma
G L O S S A RY
K h a r i d j i s m:A dissident sect founded in 657 and
characterized by its rigorism. Has continued as the
I b a d i t e s e c t , represented in Muscat (Oman),
Zanzibar (Tanzania), Djerba (Tunisia) and in the
Algerian Mzeb.
Koran: from the Arabic “reading,” “recitation.”
The sacred book of Islam was revealed by God to
the Prophet by the angel Gabriel.It is composed
of 114 suras divided into verses.
Sharia: The sacred law of Islam embracing the
entire Islamic way of life.
S h i i s m: A minority branch of Islam dating back to
the first decades of the Islamic era.Its followers
split from the Sunni mainstream to form the party
of Ali,a direct descendant of the Prophet. Today,
Shiites are divided into many sects, including the
Duodecimans, the Ismailites, the Druze, the
Zaydites and the Alawites.
S u n n i s m:The main branch of Islam, which labels
itself as “orthodox.” It emphasizes fidelity to the
s u n n a— the body of customs and practices
based on the Prophet’s words and acts. Sunnism
is divided into four legal schools: the Hanafi
(dominant in Syria,Turkey, Central Asia,India and
China);the Maliki (Maghreb, sub-Saharan Africa
and Western Europe); the S h a fii ( E g y p t ,I r a q ,e a s t
A f r i c a , southern Arabic peninsula, I n d o n e s i a ,
Malaysia) and the H a n b a l i school (Saudi A r a b i a ) .
Wahabism: A strictly orthodox Sunni Muslim
sect, founded by Muhammad ibn Abd al-Wahab
(1703-92),who called for a return to the earliest
doctrines and practices of the religion. Ibn Saud
made it the official doctrine of his kingdom (Saudi
Arabia) founded in 1932 with British support. ■
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
T
SLIMANE ZÉGHIDOUR
JOURNALIST FORTHE FRENCHWEEKLY LA VIE, AUTHOROF
DAILY LIFE IN MECCA, PUBLISHED
IN FRENCH IN 1990 BY HACHETTE
One Islam, a mosaic of believers
Allah is one but Islam is a mosaic. The Muslim world is a linguistic tower of Babel, an ethnic
patchwork, a geographical puzzle and a political kaleidoscope offering a picture of extraordinary
doctrinal diversity
he word Islam derives from the Semitic
root slm, which means both “peace”and
“ p r o s p e r i t y.” Even much earlier than the
Koran, that root could be found in the
name Salem, the Canaan deity who
became the god of Ur-Salem,the City of
S a l e m , Je r u s a l e m . Names such as
S a l o m o n ,S a l o m e, Salmanassar (the king
of A s s y r i a ) , and the word s h a l o m (a gree-
ting that means “peace”in Hebrew and
Aramean) and s a l a m in A r a b i c, also stem
from s l m. For Muslims, “ I s l a m ” m e a n s
“ s u r r e n d e r,” entrusting onself to the will
of God. According to the Prophet
Mohammed, its basic ethic can be sum-
marized by “worshipping God without
associating anything with Him, o b s e r v i n g
the canonic prayer, paying the manda-
tory alms, fasting during the month of
R a m a d a n , offering food to the hungry
and the greeting of peace to neighbours
as well as strangers.”
Today Islam refers to both a religion
and a civilization,but the faithful would
rather use the term u m m a when referring
to the Muslim world (the community of
the faithful), or the expression dar el-
islam (the house of Islam).
That spiritual dwelling stretches from
Indonesia to Morocco,the Arctic Circle to
the Tropic of Cancer. It encompasses 57
states with very different political sys-
tems ranging from the medieval emirate
to the constitutional republic and every-
thing in between: u l t r a - c o n s e r v a t i v e,
I s l a m i c - C h r i s t i a n , modernist and secular
r e g i m e s.These countries are divided into
allies and enemies of the United States,
free-market and socialist economies, r i c h
and poor.
Few people are aware that one in
three Muslims lives in countries domi-
nated by other cultures, including Catho-
licism (France, Belgium), Protestantism
(United Kingdom, United States),
Orthodox Christianity (Russia, M a c e-
d o n i a ) , Judaism (Israel), H i n d u i s m
( I n d i a ) , Buddhism (Sri Lanka) and
Confucianism (China). In all, M o h a m-
med’s disciples—Turks, Kurds, Persians,
A radical change is underway in North Africa and the Middle East:fer-
tility rates may still be just above three children per woman, but they
are falling rapidly. In Lebanon, Tunisia and Iran, the rate has already
dropped below the reproductive level of 2.1 children per woman.A l g e r i a ,
Morocco, Libya and Egypt follow close behind.
A major divide no longer separates both shores of the Mediterranean.In
Tu n i s, the figure stands at 1.55 children per woman, the same as in many
European cities. Muslim culture can no longer be called an obstacle to
modern demographic behaviour. I r a n , under an Islamic regime, w i t n e s s e d
the most dramatic change of all—a drop from 6.4 children per woman in
1986 to 2.06 in 1998.In 12 years, the country travelled the distance the
West took more than a century to cover.
Special circumstances such as civil confli c t , wa r s, embargoes and the
economic crisis have certainly contributed to reducing fertility rates. But
the decline has more to do with irreversible worldwide trends—the
growth of towns and cities, more children (especially girls) in school and
the increase in service sector jobs.
The trend is undermining the patriarchal order that has governed family
structures since time immemorial and left its mark on political allegiances.
It rests on two pillars—obedience of the younger to the older and of women
to men. Lower fertility rates challenge the fir s t : an only child has no
younger sibling to watch over.
The second, still part of legislation based on the s h a r i a l a w, is threatened
by changes in society. Girls have better access to education and are mar-
rying later.Through work, they’re entering a world of men outside their own
f a m i l y.And there are more single women—something hitherto unknown.
The advent of the two-child family does not mean that the days of zero
population growth are here. Birth rates were at their height between
1980 and 1990 and their spectacular fall since then will not be felt on the
labour market until between 2005 and 2015.
But there is cause for optimism. For a very brief moment in history, 2 5 - y e a r-
old adults are in an exceptionally privileged position. They are more
numerous than ever to share the burden of caring for their elders. Given
their low fertility rates, they can count on their savings and investments
going towards improving their living standards, rather than being absorbed
by population growth as in the past.
But to convert this theoretical advantage into something concrete, this
generation must have a chance to put savings aside, which implies having
w o r k . In most countries of the region, tremendous improvements in edu-
cation and an increase in the number of graduates have fuelled ambitions.
But all too often,youth find themselves confronted with unemployment,
or forced to opt for jobs that are below their qualifications. ■
* Senior researcher at the French National Institute for Demographic
Research in Paris, author of a recent work on demography in the Arab
world.
PHILIPPE FARGUES*:THE END OF PAT R I A R C H Y ?
TUNE INTO THE “NEW CONSCIENCE OF ISLAM”
42 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 43
A r a b s, M a l a y s, B e r b e r s, S l a v s, C h i n e s e
and Africans—are spread out over a vast
a r e a , from the Javanese jungle to the
Sahara desert, the Himalayan mountains
to the steppes of Central Asia.
The same diversity can be found on
the level of doctrine.As Mohammed him-
self predicted,Islam has split into 73 dif-
ferent persuasions, currents, denomina-
t i o n s, confraternities and sects, i n c l u d i n g
S u n n i t e s, S h i i t e s, K h a r i j i s, Z a y d i s, A l a-
wites,Ahmadis,Alevites, Ibadis, Bohras,
Qadianis, Bektashis and Druzes. One in
ten believers is Shiite, while the majority
are Sunnite.Although this branch is consi-
dered “orthodox,” it is divided into four
major legal and theological schools
( H a n a fi,S h a fii ,M a l i k i ,H a n b a l i ) , each of
which dominates one swath of dar el-
i s l a m.As a result, the u m m a has as many
faces as Christianity. There is no single,
accepted authority.That accounts for why
it is difficult, if not impossible, for a
consensus to emerge on any point of faith,
dogma or politics.
Islam has no equivalent of the pope
nor of the Vatican,but there are several
intellectual centres. The Shiite world,
which is limited mostly to Iran,has a veri-
table clergy led by an ayatollah, t h e
highest “ r a n k ” in the religious hierarchy.
Sunnite Islam, in contrast, has no hierar-
chical structure. However, El Azhar, the
theological university in Cairo, serves as
an intellectual centre for u l e m a s (the doc-
tors of Islamic law) around the world.
Nevertheless, El Azhar is a state institu-
tion whose rector is appointed by the
Egyptian president. In Te h r a n ,Cairo and
elsewhere, religion remains very closely
linked to political power, when it does
not outrightly contest it. ■
Percentage of Muslim population by country: 0 to 4% 5 to 24% 25 to 49% 50 to 74% 75 to 100%
Muslim Muslim
population population
(millions) (%)
Arab World
Egypt 58.6 90
Algeria 30.5 99
Morocco 28.8 99
Iraq 22,0 97
Saudi Arabia 21.3 97
Africa (not including Arab states)
Nigeria 53,0 43
Sudan 25.6 72
Ethiopia 21.1 33
Tanzania 13.1 37
Mali 9.6 90
The five countries with the largest Muslim population in each of the world’s main regions.
Muslim Muslim
population population
(millions) (%)
Asia (not including Arab states)
Indonesia 182.6 87
Pakistan 134.5 95
Bangladesh 114.1 88
India 121,0 12
Turkey 65,0 90
Americas / Europe*
Russian Federation 14.6 10,0
United States 4.1 1.9
France 3.2 5.5
Albania 2.4 70,0
Germany 1.7 2.1
* According to other sources, the Muslim population in the Russian Federation is between 8.5 and 21 million,in the U.S. between 6 and 7 million,
and 4 to 5 million in France.
C U L T U R E ◗
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
F
GREG PHILO
PROFESSOR OF COMMUNICATIONS AT THE UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOWAND RESEARCH DIRECTOR
OFTHE GLASGOW UNIVERSITY MEDIA GROUP
An unseen world: h o w
the media portrays the
p o o r
Following the attacks on the United States, many commentators have pondered
the Western public’s ignorance of life and issues in the developing world. The author
of a major study discusses why this is so, and what can be done
or over 30 years,numerous academic stu-
dies of how news flows between the deve-
loping and the developed world have rea-
ched the same conclusion: far from being
t w o - w a y, news circulates in a deeply
uneven and distorted manner.“Not only
is there a quantitative imbalance in news
flow, with the Third World receiving far
more material about the First World than
vice versa,” says media theorist A n n a-
belle Sreberny, “but the continual cove-
rage of the global centres of the industrial
world contrasts with the intermittent
images of the south in crisis.”
One frequent criticism has been that
news focuses on disasters and confli c t s
without explaining the complex social
and political histories behind them. The
role of the West also tends to be
ignored—notably when African coun-
tries were deployed as pawns in the Cold
War.
Major news services such as BBC,
ITV,Agence France-Presse and Reuters
have all been accused of offering very
limited accounts of the developing world.
In the U.S., journalist Mort Rosenblum
has attacked the obsession of media
controllers with ratings and their pro-
motion of what they see as entertainment
rather than reliable information.A study
by Steve Askin found that in 1992, the
story of hunger in Africa was only
deemed suitable for U.S. coverage when
it was discovered that elephants were
also dying in the drought.
But are TV audiences really this
shallow? It is a critical question that very
few studies have tackled. One survey in
Scandinavia found that press coverage
of the developing world was dominated
◗ M E D I A
44 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
Not just an “African”issue:a miner in Angola.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
by war and conflict, but that readers
actually said they wanted more on local
culture and “ n o r m a l ” l i f e. In Britain,
meanwhile, a major project was recently
commissioned by the Government’s
Department for International Develop-
ment out of concern over how T V ’s depic-
tions of the developing world could affect
public attitudes.*
A companion study by the Th i r d
World and Environment Broadcasting
Trust (3WE) interviewed 38 senior broad-
casters and programme makers, helping
bring to light the assumptions made about
reports from poor countries. As the
Director of Programmes at Carlton Te l e-
vision in London commented: “I know
from past experience that programmes
about the developing world don’t bring in
the audiences.They’re not about us, and
t h e y ’re not usually about things we can do
anything about.”
A negative diet
of images
It is not hard to see the effects of such
assumptions on coverage. A report for
3WE concluded that the total output of
factual programmes on developing coun-
tries by the four terrestrial channels in
Britain dropped by 50 percent in the 10
years after 1989.Our own study showed
that when the developing world is fea-
tured on British news, a high proportion
of the coverage is related to war, c o n fli c t ,
terrorism and disasters.This is especially
so for the main television channels, with
over a third of coverage on BBC and
Independent Television News (ITN)
devoted to such issues.
Much of the remaining coverage is
given over either to sport or to visits by
w e s t e r n e r s. For example, in our sample
the Bahamas were in the news because
Mick Jagger and Jerry Hall had paid a
visit there, and some countries were fea-
tured simply because the balloon belon-
ging to Vi r g i n ’s boss Richard Branson had
floated over them.
One reason for these changes has
been the greatly increased competition
for audiences following the rise of satellite
and cable channels. Combined with the
onset of a free market from the 1980s and
general television “ d e - r e g u l a t i o n ,” t h i s
has led to a commercial obsession with
grabbing viewers’ attention—a kind of
“watch me and buy something culture.”
Yet this is not necessarily what tele-
vision viewers want. When we actually
interviewed audience groups, we found
that people’s attitudes were rather dif-
ferent from what the broadcasters had
a s s u m e d . Some people w e r e c o m p l e t e l y
“turned off” from the developing world
(about 25 percent of the sample), b u t
the reason was in part the constant nega-
tive diet of images they were given.As
one interviewee put it:“ Well every time
you turn on the TV or pick up a paper,
t h e r e ’s another (war) starting or there is
more poverty or destruction. It is all too
much.”
Nearly all the
people interviewed
recalled negative
images since that was
largely what they had
been exposed to on
t e l e v i s i o n . Levels of
i n t e r e s t , h o w e v e r,
were not nearly so
u n i f o r m . Wh a t
actually bothered a
majority of viewers
was that they simply
did not understand the images they were
being shown. As one put it: “I have a
constant sense of not being properly
informed about background to issues and
things like that.”
A frequent complaint was that jour-
nalists merely took for granted that the
audience knew what the story was about.
In the course of this study, we worked
very closely with journalists and some
c o n firmed what the viewers were saying.
One commented to us that news reporters
were effectively told not to focus on
explanation, but to go for eye-catching
events like fighting, shooting or riots.As
he put it, they had been stopped from
doing “explainers”—now it was “all bang,
bang stuff.”
As a result of this work,we began to
discuss with journalists how TV coverage
might be improved. We agreed that we
would conduct a new pilot study in which
BBC journalists joined a focus group of
“ o r d i n a r y ”TV watchers.The purpose was
to examine what these viewers unders-
tood (or didn’t) from a TV news report,
and then to discuss this with the journa-
lists who had actually
made the news item.
We also wanted to
find out how much
the viewers’ unders-
tanding of the story
affected their level of
interest in it. D a v i d
Shukman from the
BBC was one of the
journalists present,
and we began by
watching two news
reports that he had
presented on the continuing war in
Angola and the terrible effects which
land mines had on the local population.
His report contained very distressing
images and had a strong impact, produ-
cing great sympathy from the viewers.
Yet it also had the normal negative effect
of being interpreted as one more set of
war images from A f r i c a .The viewers’ res-
ponse was that it was sad, but nothing
really to do with them since nothing could
be done.The news report had noted that
the oil and diamond trades financed the
c r i s i s, and that because of corruption
within A n g o l a , people in that country
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 45
The illicit trade in “blood diamonds” has supported wars across Africa.
I asked the group
how they thought
weapons were paid
for... I proceeded
to ask them if
anyone
was wearing
a diamond.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
◗ M E D I A
p r o fited from the war.This fitted the vie-
wers’ notions that it was basically an
“A f r i c a n ”p r o b l e m , because as they saw it,
African people were simply not very good
at governing themselves.
At this point I intervened in the dis-
cussion and introduced some new infor-
m a t i o n . I asked the group where the
mines and munitions had come from.Th e
group reasoned that they came from
industrialized countries,and that Britain,
America and Eastern Europe sold arma-
m e n t s. I then asked how they thought the
weapons were paid for. The answer was
through the sale of diamonds, oil and by
money laundering, all of which had been
mentioned in the news item. I drew their
attention to suggestions that the City of
London was involved in the illicit transfer
of large sums of money from Africa (e.g.
London Evening Standard 2 0 / 1 0 / 0 0 ) . I
proceeded to ask them if anyone was
wearing a diamond.
We eventually did this exercise with
three different groups and in each of
them there was a very surprised reaction
to this question and great shock at the
implication that if they purchased a dia-
mond in Britain, it could be paying for
l a n d m i n e s. I then pointed out to them
the illicit trade in “blood diamonds”and
how this supported wars across A f r i c a .I n
all of the groups, the new information
provoked a very animated discussion and
led the viewers to ask why such back-
ground was not given on television. The
journalists were grilled on this by group
m e m b e r s, who believed that the news
was being censored, though the journalists
denied that this was the case.
Enlightening viewers
The important point to emerge from
this study was that the interest of the vie-
wers in the group increased greatly once
they understood the political and eco-
nomic links underpinning the confli c t s
witnessed on television. Most crucially,
they realized that they were involved
themselves and no longer saw the pro-
blem as just an “African”issue. If people
understand that global political and eco-
nomic relationships are fostering pro-
blems, then they can also see that these
relationships can be changed.The sense
that “nothing can be done” is altered,
and audiences start to see the world quite
differently.
Our research was significant in that it
enabled journalists and academic spe-
cialists to work together to improve the
quality of news and its capacity to explain.
If this collective work is now pursued,it
may be possible to develop new struc-
tures and practices for reporting on the
developing world. ■
* The study was undertaken by the
Glasgow Media Group and examined
both television news content and the
reaction of audience groups A fuller ver-
sion of the results of the Glasgow Media
Group studies is available as “Au d i e n c e
Interest and Understanding of News
P r o g r a m m e s,” w w w. g l a . a c. u k / A c a d /
Sociology/media.html.
46 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
Ithink that coverage of Africa has mostly been aimed at stereotypes, w h e-
reby the Western media go to countries but never take the time to go
deep into stories—they just come out with quick-fix stories that fail to
explore the context of why and how.With enough context,with enough
d e t a i l , people will understand Africa is not just a continent of killers, t h a t
there are causes and there is conflict much as there is in Kosovo and
Chechnya.
When I took the rushes and the script for my film Cry Freetown [about the
brutal rebel invasion of Freetown in 1999] to broadcasters, everybody
l o o ked at the footage and thought it was too shocking for viewers.But my
argument to Channel 4,ITN and CNN was that
this was reality. It happened.And bear one thing
in mind: much as you can say it was graphic,
there were children sitting there as it was hap-
pening and they didn’t have the opportunity
to switch off or look away.
In the images I shot of killing,raping and mai-
ming,I wanted to shock the world. Imagine a
war that had been going on for eight or nine
years, but which nobody in the outside world
had heard about because the media failed to
report it. So I thought: l e t ’s surprise the vie-
wers for a change by explaining the background,
then bringing in the graphic pictures. And I
think it worked.
But I strongly believe the watchword has to be context.When I saw the
news of what happened in the U.S. in September, I never for one minute
saw any of those kinds of graphic images, even though 6,000 people died.
Perhaps Western viewers have matured to such an extent that it’s not
necessary to shock them anymore.They will understand, they will imagine
those scenes. But in the case of A f r i c a ,Western viewers still don’t unders-
t a n d , and the reason why they sometimes think we’re barbaric is that they
see stories and stereotypes told without any context—they think it’s
Africa,another flood,another famine and so on.
The first aim in all my stories is to look at how business and partnership
in the past between Africa and the West have gone wrong.I try to find
something to prick the conscience of Western viewers. In the case of Cry
Freetown, it was easy to point to the diamond trade between Western
mining companies and rebels. My film E x o d u s [about migration from A f r i c a ]
reminded the West that it had been to Africa in the past, it had raped the
land,it had taken without permission.To get the West interested,I try to
get the Western taxpayer to understand that their governments and
money have been used to create confusion and corruption.
I would also like to tell stories that are positive
and work for A f r i c a . My recent documentary
about Uganda was an attempt to look for hope,
but sadly enough the same issues kept coming
back—lack of education,neglect of youth,cor-
r u p t i o n .This is the reality. I t ’s what I’ve got to talk
about.
In Africa, we don’t have the power to use the
media to change attitudes or perceptions. We
have the expertise, we have committed people
who are not in the pockets of politicians, but we
don’t have the money or resources. If we can get
the West to partner us and air those stories, t h a t
would help create this kind of change.” ■
*Born and raised in Sierra Leone, Sorious Samura received a UN I C E F g r a n t
12 years ago to study film-making in Britain. Since then, his documentaries
Cry Fr e e t o w n ,Exodus and Walking on A s h e s have been shown on Channel
4 (London) and CNN.
SORIOUS SAMURA*: CONTEXT IS THE WAT C H W O R D
“I wanted to shock the world.”
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
ou must have been
quite intrigued by the
descriptions of the
September 11 terro-
rists in the media.
These young men had
fairly balanced child-
hoods and were quite
e d u c a t e d .Yet they turned into violent fana-
tics. How do you explain that?
By their total lack of empathy. Ger-
mans became Nazis in exactly the same
w a y,by not being able to imagine someone
e l s e ’s world. For them, you had to be
b l o n d e, dolichocephalic (having a long
head) and not Je w i s h . All other people
were inferior beings.The terrorists in the
U. S. attacks had good upbringing and edu-
cation but they never learned to accept
forms of human existence other than their
own.
Why not?
In some Muslim countries, fanaticism
is manufactured. Just like in Fr a n c e,w h e r e
people were taught to hate Germans after
the 1870 Franco-German war. Te a c h e r s
were actually paid to tell children they
would be glorified if one day they went
off to “smash”the Germans. I’ve seen the
same thing in the Middle East. I’ve seen
books that told little boys that if they died
for religion, t h e y ’d go straight to heaven to
live with Allah. These schools that teach
there is only one truth, are schools of
hatred.
But some of the terrorists were children of
i m m i g rants who adjusted well in Euro p e …
These individuals never made it
through adolescence into adulthood.Th e r e
are more and more young people in
Boris Cyrulnik
Surviving the trauma of life
Y
Trauma and anxiety are the lot of a growing number of young people, as violence holds sway and
traditional notions of the family disintegrate. But there are roads to recovery, says French
globetrotting psychologist, Boris Cyrulnik 
November 2001 - The UNESCO Courier 47
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
“When you don’t know who you are, you
love it when a dictatorship takes charge”
Europe who fail on that score, about a
third of the total,because we don’t know
how to help and support them properly.
They drift and become perfect targets for
sects and extremist movements.When you
d o n ’t know who you are, you love it when
a dictatorship takes charge of you. Th e
moment you submit to a master, to a single
m e s s a g e, you become a fanatic. M a n y
people are also suffering from a growing
sense of anxiety over globalization. They
feel depersonalized and disconnected from
their feelings. Disturbed people feel secure
obeying someone who tells them what to
do. Submission is a good way for them to
get rid of their anxiety.
So you don’t think economic globalization
induces a kind of “collective global sub-
conscious” that helps us to come to grips
with all the ideas and information coming
at us from all sides?
N o.On the contrary, if I want to see the
w o r l d ,I have to accept that I won’t unders-
tand everything. Identity is like speech.
When a baby is born, it has the capacity to
make several thousand different sounds.
But to speak,it has to whittle them down
to between 100 and 300,according to the
l a n g u a g e. The same principle applies to
forging an identity. I must give up a thou-
sand elements or dimensions which cannot
be integrated into the person I want to
b e. To d a y, with globalization, a lot of
people are looking to their roots to
“whittle themselves down” in order to
forge an identity.
So people return to their roots because the
Western “model”is spreading too fast?
Some people are fanatically seeking
refuge in their roots. But this approach
leads to alienation.Since it’s the West that
has the weapons, the money and the tech-
n o l o g y, t h e r e ’s a very good chance We s t e r n
attitudes will become globalized and
spread across the world.Either you unhap-
pily submit to this trend or your hatred
of the West increases, which is what is
happening today. Imaginary identities,
many hundreds or even thousands of years
o l d , will continue to resurface. I t ’s as if the
only choice is between “ d e - i d e n t i fic a t i o n ”
and alienation.
Is there a compromise solution?
Ye s.To avoid feeling alienated, p e o p l e
must recognize that an identity is like a
patchwork of different elements.All iden-
tities are the product of a father’s and
mother’s past and of a religion everyone
interprets according to their cultural sur-
r o u n d i n g s. In Fr a n c e, for example, B r e-
tons are very proud of the painted croc-
kery made in Quimper but not many know
that the style was invented by an Italian
who emigrated to Brittany a century ago.
You’ve talked about the serious problems of
t o d a y ’s teenagers, who are “ d r i f t i n g ”m o re
and more. Yet children have never been
better understood by society than today, s o
why are so many youngsters becoming neu-
ro t i c, committing suicide and taking to
crime?
That isn’t a contradiction. P r o g r e s s
always has a price.The price of freedom is
a n x i e t y.Today children get help to develop
their personalities and become aware of all
kinds of things. They’re more intelligent
and more lively, but also more worried.
We look after them very well when they’r e
young and then we abandon them as soon
as they’re teenagers. Society doesn’t take
over where parents leave off. So a third of
all teenagers fall apart,usually after leaving
high school. To avoid that,we need more
social and cultural structures that will help
them give meaning to their lives by encou-
raging them to be creative, to speak openly,
to reach out to each other. But we don’t do
that.
A teenager’s problem lies in the ques-
tion:“What am I going to do about what
I ’ve been made into?” To answer that,
they must be surrounded by the warmth of
feeling that comes from a group, f r o m
f r i e n d s, from the confidence of being able
to find a job. But the technological revo-
lution has been so massive that schools
now have a monopoly on social selec-
tion—they determine the possibilities
open to an individual. If a boy or girl blos-
soms, they do well in school and learn a
skill. They’ll be among the two-thirds of
teenagers who benefit from the improved
facilities and support available in early
THE UNCLASSIFIABLE CYRULNIK
Boris Cyulnik is, beyond a doubt, resilient.Despite a war-wracked childhood and the deporta-
tion of his parents, he still managed to become a distinguished scholar and well-balanced
individual:happy with his family, respected by his peers and famous for his many books.
Born in Bordeaux, France, in 1937,Cyrulnik only refers to his personal wounds in “third person,”
while writing about children.Clearly, this is a man who has learned to transform weakness into
strength. “I was never put on the ‘conveyor belt’ of life—I’ve always made my own path,” he
says. “I do only what is absolutely required to be considered ‘normal.’”
Instead of distancing himself from people, his personal trauma drove him to try to understand
what it means to be human.After studying medicine, he followed diverse branches of psycholo-
gy, such as neuropsychiatry and psychoanalysis, before breaking the sacrosanct barriers between
academic disciplines. Yet by moving into fields like ethology (which focuses on animal behaviour),
the maverick scholar made considerable enemies in the scientific community.
This anti-specialist,globetrotter and incurably curious academic has never hesitated to question
some of the dogma of psychoanalysis. While Freud holds guilt responsible for neurosis and social
discontent,Cyrulnik feels that there is a “good”kind of guilt,through which “we try to avoid cau-
sing harm because we can empathize with others. This is probably the basis of morality.” ■
48 The UNESCO Courier - November 2001
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
childhood.But the other third don’t like
s c h o o l , feel humiliated and don’t get a
chance to shine elsewhere.They find them-
selves at a loose end on the street, w i t h o u t
a job and often without any family. How
do kids like this recover their self-esteem?
They indulge in “ t o u g h ”a c t i v i t i e s, t e s t i n g
themselves and proving their existence
by adopting primitive social rituals such as
violence, fighting and drugs.
You say,“ t h e re is no family.” But isn’t it just
that the family is changing?
Th e r e ’s no family and it’s changing,a s
expectancy of about 10 days. He’s elimi-
nated if he doesn’t join a gang. D e l i n-
q u e n cy is a way of adapting to a crazy
society.
But what should be done?  Make women
stay at home?
N o, but there has to be someone there,
man or woman.In some cultures that still
have extended families, there’s always a
grown-up at home. E l s e w h e r e, we have to
i n n o v a t e. In Brazil, for example, p e o p l e
construct families that have nothing to do
with blood or biology.An old man says to
an old lady:“I’m sick of going down the
steep slopes in the slums, I’m going to take
care of the house.”And the old lady says:
“Well,I’m going to look after the kids in
the neighbourhood.” And then another,
a bit younger, says:“I’ll chip in with some
money because I’ve got an odd job.”Th e s e
are verbal families, people who’ve made
understandings to protect each other, to be
f r i e n d s, to celebrate and fight together,
like all families. D e l i n q u e n cy vanishes
immediately in these households as soon
as this kind of family develops.
In the We s t , the family has changed dra-
matically, yet laws and attitudes haven’t.
That is because we often make the
mistake of talking about the “traditional
f a m i l y.”Yet this structure only emerged in
the West in the 19th century, at the same
time as the factories.It was a way of adap-
ting to industrial society. A man was an
appendage of a machine and a woman an
it always has. When kids get home, t h e-
re’s no one there. No father, no mother.
Why should they shut themselves up in
an empty house when there are pals out in
the street?  I’ve worked in some Latin
American countries where kids say they
had a row with their mother or stepfather
and just left. Life is physically very hard in
the street but there’s always something
going on—a celebration, a theft, s o m e-
thing to share.You talk and you live.Th e s e
children get used to not having a family by
turning to petty crime. A street boy in
Colombia who isn’t a delinquent has a life
In the Mongolian capital of Ulan Bator, street children in the midst of winter look for
warmth underground,near hot water pipes.
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
Y E S, I wish to subscribe, or take out a subscription for a friend, to the UNESCO COURIER✂
LANGUAGE: English French Spanish
For editions in other languages (see page 51) please contact us
RATES (including postage):
Industrialized countries:
1 year: 211French francs ( 32 .17 ) instead of 24 9 FF* 
( 11 issues including 1 double issue)
2 years: 396 French francs ( 6 0 . 37 ) instead of 498FF* 
( 22 issues including 2 double issues)
Binder: 48French francs ( 7. 32 ) for 11 issues including 1 double issue
* Total cover price
Students, unemployed persons (please send copy of relevant documents), 
developing countries:
1 year: 132French francs ( 20 .12 )
2 years: 211French francs ( 32 .17 ) 
Your first issue will be sent to you as soon as your subscription has been processed.This normally
takes around two weeks.
The list of themes already covered in the UNESCOCOURIER is available on request.
I enclose payment (in French francs only) to UNESCO
Bank cheque (except Eurocheque)
Visa E u r o c a r d M a s t e r c a r d
No. ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘—❘ Expiry date: ❘—❘—❘—❘—❘
Family name:
First name:
Address:
Postal code: City:
Country
Signature:
In order to improve our service to readers, we should appreciate the help you could give us by answering
the optional questions below.
Occupation:
(Teachers and students) Special field:     Level:
Age: Tel.:
Please send this form with your remittance, in French francs only, made payable to THE UNESCO COURIER Subscription Services: 31, rue François-Bonvin 75732 Paris CEDEX 15 (France)
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91, Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45, e-mail: courrier.unesco@unesco.org
For payments in other currencies, please contact one of the subscription agents whose addresses are given on the back of this order form.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
“In most culture s , victims are 
re g a rded as guilty of something”
appendage of a man. There was order in
every facet of life. Individuals—just about
all women and most men—were psycho-
logically crushed.Only a minority, about
two percent of the population, was able to
develop healthily. And so they married
to pass on their property and other goods.
But this version of a traditional family
wasn’t very common at the time because
most workers didn’t get married, s i n c e
they had no property to pass on.
That society has disappeared and there
are fewer and fewer traditional families,
but the model is still in people’s minds.
And the laws are only just starting to
c h a n g e. When there’s just one concept
a r o u n d , it takes a long while for people to
change their attitudes.You have to wage “ a
war of words,” writing and debating, t o
drive things forward. You can invent a
thousand different variations of the family
as long as children still have a place where
they’re protected,where there’s love and
growth and where some things, like incest
are absolutely forbidden,while other rules
can be negotiated.
The idea of resilience you discuss in your
recent books1 is becoming very popular.
Why?
Epidemiological research by the Wo r l d
Health Organization shows that one out of
two people has been or will be seriously
traumatized at some time during their life
(by war, v i o l e n c e, r a p e,c r u e l t y, i n c e s t ,e t c. ) .
One in four will experience at least two
serious traumas.The rest are also bound to
fall on some hard times.Yet the notion of
r e s i l i e n c e, which is a person’s ability to
grow in the face of terrible problems, had
not been scientifically studied until
recently. Today, it’s all the rage in many
c o u n t r i e s. In Latin A m e r i c a , they have
resilience institutes, in Holland and Ger-
many they have resilience universities. In
the United States,you hear the word all the
t i m e.The World Trade Center towers have
even been nicknamed “the twin resilient
t o w e r s ” by those who want to rebuild
them.
So why wasn’t this idea investigated earlier?
Because for a long time people have
despised victims. In most cultures, t h e y ’r e
regarded as guilty of something.A woman
w h o ’s been raped, for example, is often
condemned as much as her attacker
because “she must have provoked him,”i t
is said. Sometimes a victim is punished
even more than an aggressor is. Not so
long ago in Europe, an unmarried woman
who had a baby was thrown out on the
street while the father risked virtually
nothing.
This disdain or hatred has also been
directed against the survivors of war. The
families and villages of these victims are
suspicious and say: “He’s coming home.
That means he must have hidden somew-
here or collaborated with the enemy.”
After the Second World Wa r, the most
deadly in human history, things swung to
the other extreme. The victims became
heroes. By pushing these individuals into
making careers as victims, societies found
a convenient way of downplaying the
crimes of the Nazis. The fact that these
victims survived was used to downplay
the savagery.
At the time, René Spitz and A n n a
Freud2 described children whose parents
had been killed in the wartime bombing of
L o n d o n . They were all profoundly
impaired and shut-off people, suicidal and
unable to relax their bodies. When Spitz
and Freud saw them again a few years
l a t e r, they were amazed at how well they’d
recovered and wrote that these abandoned
children had gone through four stages:
p r o t e s t ,d e s p a i r, indifference—all students
learned about those three—and then reco-
very, which nobody was interested in stu-
L IST OF SA L ES A ND SUBSCRIP T ION AGEN T S
Subscriptions can be paid to the subscription agent in your country who will supply rates in local currency on request
A RGEN T IN A: Edilyr Srl, Librería Correo de la UNES CO, Tucumán 16 8 5 ,
10 50 Buenos Aires. Fax: 371 - 819 4 .
A US T RA L I A: Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collingwood VIC
3066. Fax: 419 7154. 
ISA Australia, PO Box 709, To owong QLD 4066. Fax: 371 556 6 .
United Nations Assoc. of Australia/Victorian Div., 179 St George’s Road,
N. Fitzroy VIC 3068. Fax: 481 76 9 3 .
Gordon & Gotch Australia Pty. Ltd., Private Bag 290, Burwood VIC 3125 .
Fax: 03 9888 8561
A US T RI A: Gerold & Co, Import & Export, Zeitschriften/Pe r i o d i ca l s ,
G raben 31, A-1011 Vienna. Fax: 512 47 31 29
BELGIUM: Partner Press, 11 rue Charles Parenté, B-1070 Brussels.
Fax: (32 2) 556 41 46/Tel.: (32 2) 556 41 40/partner press@ampnet.be
BRAZ IL: Fundaco Getulio Vargas, Editora Divisão de Vendas, Caixa
Postal 62.591, 22257- 970 Rio de Janeiro RJ. Fax: 551 - 0 9 4 8 .
CANADA: Renouf Publishing Company Ltd, 5 369 ch. Canotek Road, Unit
1, Ottawa, Ont K1J 9J3. Fax: (1-613) 745 7660. 
Faxon Canada, PO Box 2382, London, Ont. N6A 5A7. Fax: (1-519) 472 1072 .
CHIL E: Universitaria Textolibro Ltda., Casilla Postal 10 220, Santiago. 
Fax: 681 9091.
CHIN A: China National Publications, Import & Export Corp., PO Box 88,
16 Gongti East Road, Beijing 10 0 0 20. Fax: 010 650 6 3101.
CZECH REPUBLIC: Artia, Ve Smeckach 30, 111 27 Prague 1.
DENM A RK: Munksgaard, Norre Sogade 35, PO Box 2148, DK-1016
Kobenhavn K. Fax: 12 93 87.
FINLA ND: Stockmann/Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, PO Box 23, SF - 0 0 371
Helsinki. Fax: +358 9 121 4450 .
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, PO Box 2, SF - 016 41 Vantaa. 
Fax: 852 79 9 0 .
GERM A N Y: German Commission for UNES CO, Colmantstr. 15, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 63 69 12 .
Uno Verlag, Dag Hammarskjöld Haus, Poppelsdorfer Allee 55, D- 53115
Bonn. Fax: 21 74 92.
GREECE: Librairie Kauffmann SA, Mauvrokordatou 9, GR - 106 78 Athens.
Fax: 38 33 967.
GU AT EM A LA: Comisión Guatemalteca de Cooperación con la UNES CO,
3A Avenida 10 29, Zona 1, Apartado Postal 26 30, Guatemala City.
HONG KONG: Hong Kong Government Information Svcs. Dept., 1
B a t t e ry Path Central, Hong Kong.
HUNG A R Y: Librotrade K F T, Pe r i o d i cal Import/K, POB 126, H-16 56
Budapest. Fax: 256 - 87- 27.
INDI A: UNES CO O f fice, 8 Po o rvi Marg, Vasant Vihar, New Delhi 110 0 57.
ISRA EL: Litera ry Transactions Inc., C/0 Steimatsky Ltd., PO Box 14 4 4 ,
Bnei Brak 51114. Fax: 52 81 187.
I TA LY: Licosa/Libreria Comm. Sansoni SPA, Via Duca di Calabria 1/1, I-
50125 Florence. Fax: 64-12 - 57.
JA PA N: Eastern Book Service Inc., Pe r i o d i cals Account, 3 13 Hongo 3
Chome, Bunkyo Ku, Tokyo 113. Fax: 818 - 0 8 6 4 .
KORE A: Korean National Commission for UNES CO, CPO Box 64, Seoul
100-600. Fax: 568 74 54 .
LUX EMBURG: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 20 22, L-10 20 Luxembourg.
Fax: 99 88 84 44.
M A LTA: Sapienzas & Sons Ltd., PO Box 36, 26 Republic Street, Va l l e t t a
CMR 01. Fax: 24 61 82.
M A URI T IUS: Editions Le Printemps Ltée., 4 Route du Club, Va c o a s .
Fax: 686 7302. 
MOROCCO: UNES CO, B.P. 1777 RP, Rabat. Fax: 212-767 03 75, 
Tel.: 212-767 03 74/72.
MEX ICO: Librería El Correo de la UNES CO SA, Col Roma, Guanajuato 72 ,
Deleg Cuauhtémoc, 06700 Mexico DF. Fax: 26 4 - 0 9 - 19 .
NET HERLA NDS: Swets & Zeitlinger BV, PO Box 830, 2160 SZ Lisse. 
Fax: 2524 - 158 8 8 .
T i j d s c h r i f t c e n t rale Wijck B V, Int. Subs. Service, W Gra c h t s t raat 1C, 6221
CT Maastricht. Fax: 32 50 10 3 .
NEW ZEALA ND: GP Legislation Services, PO Box 12418, Thorndon,
We l l i n gton. Fax: 496 56 98.
NORWAY: Swets Norge AS, Østensjøvein 18-0606 Oslo, PO Box 6512,
Etterstad. Fax: 47 22 97 45 45. 
P ORT UG A L: Livraria Portugal (Dias & Andrade Lda), Rua do Carmo 70
74, 1200 Lisboa. Fax: 34 70 26 4 .
RUSSI A: Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, U1 Dimitrova 39, Moscow 1130 9 5 .
SOUTH AFRICA: International Subscription Services, PO Box 410 9 5 ,
C raighall 20 24. Fax: 880 624 8 .
Mast Publications, PO Box 901, Parklands 2121. Fax: 886 4512 .
SPA IN: Mundi Prensa Libros SA, Castelló 37, 28 0 01 Madrid. 
Fax: 91575 - 39 - 9 8 .
Libreria Al Andalús, Roldana 3 y 4, 410 0 91 Sevilla. Fax: 954 22 - 53 - 38 .
UNES CO Etxea, Alda Urquijo 60, Ppal. Dcha., 48011 Bilbao. 
Fax: 427- 51 - 59 / 6 9
SRI LA NKA: Lake House Bookshop, 100 Chittampalam, Gardiner
Mawatha, Colombo 2. Fax: 44 78 48.
S W EDEN: Wennergren Williams AB, PO Box 1305, S-171 25 Solna. 
Fax: 27 00 71.
S W I TZ ERLA ND: Dynapresse Marketing SA, (ex-Naville SA), 38 av Vibert,
CH - 1227 Carouge. Fax: 308 08 59 .
Edigroup SA, Case Postale 393, CH - 1225 Chêne-Bourg. Fax: 348 44 82.
Europa Verlag, Ramistrasse 5, CH - 8 0 24 Zürich. Fax: 251 60 81
Van Diermen Editions Te c h n i q u e s - A D E CO, Chemin du Lacuez, CH - 18 07
B l o n a y. Fax: 943 36 05.
T H A ILA ND: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajadamnern Avenue, 
Bangkok 2. Fax: 28 11 639 .
T UNISI A: Commission Nationale Tunisienne auprès de l’UNES CO, 22, rue
de l’Angleterre, 10 0 0 RP Tunis. Fax: 33 10 14
UNI T ED KINGDOM: The Stationery Office Publications Ctre., 51 Nine
Elms Lane, London SW8 5DR. Fax: 873 84 63.
UNI T ED STAT ES: Bernan Associates, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham
MD 2070 6 - 4 391. Fax: 459 - 0 0 56 .
URUGU AY: Ediciones Trecho SA, Pe r i o d i cals Account, Maldonado 10 9 0 ,
Montevideo. Fax: 90 59 83.
V ENEZ UELA: Distriplumes, Apartado 49232, Colinas Bello Monte, 10 4 2
A Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 979 8 36 0
UNES CO/ CRES A LC, Edif. As o v i n car, Av Los Chorros, Cruce C/C
Acueducto, Altos de Sebucan, Cara cas. Fax: (58 2) 28 6 0 326 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
dying.
How did resilience become accepted among
psychologists?
The word,which comes from the Latin
“ r e s a l i r e ” (to jump up again), a p p e a r e d
in the English language and passed into
psychological parlance in the 1960s thanks
to an American psychologist, E m m y
We r n e r. She had gone to Hawaii to assess
the development of children who had no
family, didn’t go to school, lived in great
poverty and were exposed to disease and
violence. She followed them for 30 years
and found that in the end, a third had
learned how to read and write, acquired a
skill and started a family. Two-thirds of
them were still in a bad way. But if people
were just machines,all of them would have
failed.
What’s a typical resilient child like, socially
and culturally?
There is no typical profil e. But a trau-
matized child can still be resilient if she or
he has acquired a gut or primitive confi-
dence in the first year of life. Such children
take the attitude that “ I ’ve been loved
therefore I’m worth loving, so I live in
hope of meeting someone who’ll help me
resume my development.”These children
feel a lot of grief  but still relate to other
people, give them gifts of food and look
for an adult they can turn into one of
their  parents.Then they give themselves
a narrative identity – “I’m the one who
was… sent to the camps, r a p e d , forced to
become a child soldier”and so on.
If you give them a chance to make up
for lost time and to express themselves,
nearly all—90 to 95 per cent—become
r e s i l i e n t .They have to be given a chance to
be creative, to test and prove themselves as
k i d s, through things like joining the scouts,
studying for an exam, organizing a trip
and learning to be useful.Problem young-
sters feel humiliated when they’re given
something, especially if there’s a lecture
along with it. But they regain their balance
when asked to give something themselves.
When they grow up, such children are
drawn to selfless professions. They want
others to learn from what they’ve gone
t h r o u g h . They often become teachers,
social workers, psychiatrists or psycholo-
g i s t s. Having been problem children them-
selves helps them to identify with and res-
pect those who have been psychologically
hurt. ■
INTERVIEW BY SOPHIE BOUKHARI
UNESCO COURIER JOURNALIST
1. Boris Cyrulnik is the author of over a
d o zen works. The Dawn of Meaning
was published by McGraw-Hill in 1992.
2. Both are psychoanalysts, one American
(1887-1974) and the other the daughter of
Sigmund Freud (1895-1982).
In a rehabilitation centre for former child soldiers, in Sierra Leone.
T A L K I N G T O . . . ◗
54th year
Published monthly in 28 languages and in Braille 
by the United Nations Educational,Scientific and 
Cultural Organization.
31,rue François Bonvin,75732 Paris Cedex 15 France
Fax:(33) (0) 1.45.68.57.45 - (33) (0) 1.45.68.57.47
e-mail:unesco.courier@unesco.org
Internet:http://www.unesco.org/courier
Director: René Lefort
Secretary, Director’s Office/Braille editions:
Annie Brachet (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.47.15)
Editorial staff (Paris)
Editor in Chief: James Burnet
English edition: Cynthia Guttman
Spanish edition: Louise Corradini
French edition: Sophie Boukhari 
Michel Bessières
Ivan Briscoe
Philippe Demenet
Lucía Iglesias Kuntz
Asbel López
Amy Otchet
Shiraz Sidhva
Translation
Miguel Labarca
Art and production unit: Gérard Prosper,
Photoengraving: Annick Coueffé
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel:33 (0) 1.45.68.46.87)
Editorial Committee
René Lefort (modera t o r ) , Jérome Bindé, Milagros del Corra l ,
Alcino Da Costa, Babacar Fa l l , Sue W i l l i a m s
Non-headquarters editions 
German:Urs Aregger (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
I t a l i a n :G i o vanni Puglisi, Gianluca Formichi (Florence)
Hindi:Pushplata Taneja (Delhi)
Tamil:M.Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Jalil Shahi (Teheran)
Portuguese:Alzir a Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
U r d u : Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan:Jordi Folch (Barcelona)
Malay:Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili:Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
S l o v e n e :A l e k s a n d ra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian:Luba Ranjeva (Sofia)
Greek:Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala:Lal Perera (Colombo)
Basque:Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai:Suchitra Chitranukroh (Bangkok)
Vietnamese:Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Bengali:Kafil uddin Ahmad (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
G a l i c i a n : Xabier Senín Fernández 
(Santiago de Compostela)
Serbian: (Belgrade)
Sardinian:Diego Corraine (Nuoro)
Russian:Valeri Kharkin (Moscow)
Circulation and promotion
Fax:(33) (0) 1 45.68.57.45
Subscriptions and customer service
Michel Ravassard (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.91)
Sales and subscription agents
Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel:(33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Stock management and shipping
Pham Van Dung (Tel:(33) (0) 1.45.68.45.94)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing the
credit line reads “Reprinted from the UN E S C O C o u r i e r ” , plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author’s
n a m e. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts can-
not be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering posta-
g e. The UN E S C O Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by:
(1) UN E S C O, 7 Place de Fo n t e n o y, 75700 Pa r i s ; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox ) ,
A n nA r b o r, Michigan 48100 U. S. A . ; (3) N. C. R . Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New Yo r k , U. S. A . ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield Road,
Wo o s t e r, Ohio 44691, U. S. A .
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
DÉPOT LÉGAL: C1 - NOVEMBER2001
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - 
Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
The UN E S C O Courier (USPS 016686) is published monthly
in Paris by UN E S C O. Printed in Fra n c e.
Periodicals postage paid at Champlain NY and additional mailing offic e s.
Photocomposition and photoengraving:
The UNESCO Courier.
Printing:Maulde & Renou
ISSN 0041-5278 No. 11-2001-OPI 00-592 A
November 2001 -The UNESCO Courier 51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Focus:
■ Taking sides: a world of dialogue or violence
■ “Clash of civilizations” or spectre of a new Cold War?
■ Inter-state dialogue stretched to the limits
■ Religion: a conduit for mutual understanding? 
■ NGOs in North and South: the arduous search
for common ground
■ Latin America: making room for the indigenous way
■ When Indian and Western medicine meet
■ Tourism with meaning
Features include:
■ A passion for Thai boxing
■ Dwindling groundwater: Saudi Arabia’s
dehydrated future 
■ Can schools revive sleeping languages?
■ Refugees: rights and reality
■ Resurrecting the Silk Roads
■ Media: the North through Southern eyes
In the next issue
many voices one world
FOCUS
December 2001
Dialogue
among
civilizations
@ www.unesco.org/courier
The UNESCO Courier is available on the Internet:
Published in 28 languages
]]>
</page>
</document>
