<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="150227eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 11
2007 - number 1
Contents
“Danger is part 
of the Palestinian 
journalist’s daily 
routine” 3
Investigative 
journalism 
in Mongolia 5
Cape Verde
Santo Antão
São Vicente
Branco
Santa Luzia
Raso
São Nicolau
Boa Vista
Sal
Maio
Santiago
Fogo
Secos
Islands
Brava
PRAIA
AT L A N T I C O C E A N
Mindelo
N
Media Revolution 
in Cape Verde 7
Inhabitants 
of the Caribbean 
on the same 
wavelength 8
Timeline 11
The Courier 
looks back 10
Whatever the particular challenges of life in different parts of the 
world, people everywhere need pluralistic and independent media. 
Since its creation, UNESCO has sought to promote the free flow of 
ideas by word and image in the interest of international solidarity, 
democracy, peace and development.
MEDIA MATTERS
This document may be accessed online: www.unesco.org/courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 12
Whatever the particular challenges of 
life in different parts of the world, 
people everywhere need pluralistic and 
independent media. Since its creation, 
UNESCO has sought to promote the free 
flow of ideas by word and image in 
the interest of international solidarity, 
democracy, peace and development. 
The media can provide individuals and commu-
nities with information and ideas, with forums 
on which they can challenge and assess infor-
mation; a resource that can help them gauge 
the efficiency of their politicians and help 
them exercise their democratic rights as 
voters. 
The current edition of the UNESCO Courier 
looks at how UNESCO has been helping people 
around the world acquire the media that will 
meet their specific needs; learn about their 
problems and possible solutions; share experi-
ences and opinions; and celebrate their 
culture. 
© UNESCO
Video training in Hebron, Palestinian Territories
This is why the Organization, through its 
Communication and Information Sector along 
with its International Programme for the Devel-
opment of Communication (IPDC), supports a 
wide range of media projects all over the 
world. 
The Courier in this issue examines some of 
these projects, like the training Palestinian tel-
evision reporter Lana Shaheen received to help 
her contend with the challenges of working in 
a context of political instability, material hard-
ship and gender stereotyping. 
Other programmes help geographically scat-
tered communities, like those of the Caribbean 
islands, pool know-how and resources. While 
some training workshops, for example, assist 
journalists - in this instance in Mongolia - gain 
awareness of important issues of democratic 
governance. Meanwhile, in Cape Verde UNESCO 
has helped the authorities design the legisla-
tive framework that is indispensable for free 
and independent public and private media. ■
THE POWER 
OF THE MEDIA
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 13
Lana Shaheen, was one of the Palestinian 
ten female television reporters who 
received UNESCO-supported training 
at the Aljazeera Centre in Qatar. Since 
her return, she has had to adjust the 
principles and skills she learnt to the 
harsh reality of a tense conflict area.
The caller on the telephone informed me that 
Rafah crossing point - the only gateway for people 
in the Gaza Strip to the outside world - would be 
operating the following day. I was invited to come 
to Jordan by Al Ghad TV, to attend a preparatory 
course leading up to my new job as their Gaza 
Strip reporter. This was very good news – so why 
did I react with worry and fear, instead of pleasure 
and joy? The explanation can perhaps serve to 
illustrate the working conditions of Palestinian 
journalists. 
Of course the idea of the new post was extremely 
encouraging. It meant more work experience to add 
to my CV and another source of income besides my 
main job with Palestine TV and other freelancing. 
But I was upset at the need to leave the Gaza Strip 
as a prerequisite. It wasn’t so much the difficulties 
and humiliation we face at the crossing. More sig-
nificant was the possibility of getting stranded on 
the other side, waiting for weeks or even months 
for a reopening so I could return home. 
I still remember a painful loss due to the irreg-
ular operation of Rafah crossing. I was eagerly 
looking forward to rejoining colleagues in Istanbul 
A special training programme
Ten Palestinian women, all professional television reporters under the age of 27, 
from Gaza and the West Bank, traveled to Qatar in December 2005 for an intense 
two-week training at the Aljazeera Media Training and Development Centre. The 
programme included modules on technical subjects (such as programme editing), 
as well as broader questions, such as media ethics, the role of the journalist in 
society and what is news.
4
“Danger is part of the Palestinian 
journalist’s daily routine”
© Flickr/N. Collett
Today was a busy day because the students attending the 
University in Nablus were voting for student president
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 1
for the follow-up of a course on good 
governance and human rights, but I 
couldn’t go because the crossing was 
closed. Freedom of movement – essen-
tial to a journalist’s pursuit of a story – 
is a right not guaranteed to Palestinian 
media professionals.
The challenge of 
objectivity
It is not the only obstacle we face. 
Endeavoring to apply the valuable pro-
fessional instruction I received in my 
UNESCO-sponsored training course at 
Al-Jazeera Centre, I sometimes feel 
frustrated. Practicing objectivity in 
reporting, for instance, may not be 
harmful to journalists in the west, but 
it can be fatal in underdeveloped coun-
tries ruled by undemocratic regimes if it is seen as 
threatening to dominant interests. As a Palestin-
ian journalist, I have to stress balance and recon-
ciliation in order not to upset this or that party, 
remembering that almost every party has its own 
militia, and every prominent official his own armed 
guards. Insisting on objectivity can lead to being 
fired from one’s job, if not to detention, prison or 
death. 
On another level, I also can’t help noticing, 
when I’m doing a news report in the way I learned 
from my Al-Jazeera trainer, the big difference in 
quality between Al-Jazeera’s editing units or 
transmission equipment and that of Palestine TV. 
Our limited financial resources make it hard to 
upgrade or replace equipment – and we don’t have 
enough in the first place to cover the needs of 
news sections and programs production. The jour-
nalist has no choice but to make concessions on 
quality.
A dangerous profession
The fact that I am an eastern woman living in a 
Moslem community imposes extra restrictions. The 
Palestinian community still finds it improper for a 
woman to stay out late at night, though covering 
urgent news may require it. Modern casual clothes 
like jeans, so much easier for moving freely, can 
be considered as contravening religion, customs 
and traditions. Even within my family, I sometimes 
have difficulty in making my husband – an under-
standing, pragmatic partner, but an oriental 
Moslem man – accept that my work makes special 
demands. He is very sensitive to certain forms of 
conduct imposed by my job, like going out unex-
pectedly or traveling abroad. 
Overall, danger is the most distinguishing char-
acteristic of the Palestinian journalist’s daily rou-
tine. In such a volatile flashpoint as the Gaza 
Strip, most reporting tasks, unfortunately, are 
risky. If a journalist is sufficiently bold and dedi-
cated to cover the almost daily clashes - between 
different militias and armed groups, or attacks by 
Israeli occupation forces - he/she is certainly risk-
ing his/her life . To make the situation worse, no 
protection exists in the way of medical or social 
care for journalists who are injured. ■
Lana Shaheen in Gaza, Palestinian Territories
© Flickr/Arros Alforn
Hawara - check and commuting point south of Nablus, Palestinian 
Territories
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 15
It was interesting. It was challenging. It was dan-
gerous, too. Twenty journalists from popular Mon-
golian media investigated corruption issues for the 
first time and I felt lucky to be part of that intense 
eight-month programme. The team I was working 
with focused on three articles whose titles were: 
Suspicious Facts of Law School, True Face of Two 
Friends and Freedom to Journalists! 
The training and supervision were provided by 
the Mongolian freedom of expression advocacy 
group Globe International in cooperation with 
Press Institute and the initiative was coordinated 
by UNESCO’s office in Beijing. 
We needed to find information, and information 
sources, facts, adequate proof and documentation. 
And we did not have any experiences.
Beginning the 
investigation
In January, we received basic training in 
investigative reporting. We formed four 
teams and we investigated corruption 
cases in the fields of health, economy, 
education and environment. I was in the 
Education team. 
In April, Yvonne Chua from Philippine 
Center for Investigative Journalism came 
to evaluate our investigations and help us 
with the writing of our stories. 
During the workshops we learned that 
corruption is more than bribery; that abuse 
of power comes in many shapes and forms. 
After hours of discussion, my group agreed to 
focus on entrance and graduate exams at the Law 
School of the Mongolian National University, where 
we had a confidential source works. 
With the help of a person who shall remain 
unnamed, we were able to access and copy the 
director’s instructions over the past 10 years. It 
transpired that the Director, S. Narangerel, and his 
Deputy, N. Lundendorj, were the only people in 
charge of the State Examination Commission. 
Interestingly, we found that around ten present 
and former Members of the Parliament received 
degrees from the evening faculty of the Law 
School. Yet we found no trace of their enrollment 
at the school. 4
Investigative journalism in Mongolia
Enkhbaatar G. is a journalist with the Ardyn Erkh daily newspaper. In 2005, 
he participated in the “Media for Transparent Governance” programme. 
Its goal: to raise Mongolian journalists’ awareness of corruption and train them 
in investigative journalism.
© UNESCO
Setting of IPDC’s community radio project
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 1
Documents further showed that Mr. N. Lunden-
dorj has got his bachelor degree and Ph.D from the 
evening faculty and gained Ph.D while he was 
working as deputy director. 
We decided to look into the entrance exams to 
the Law School. One member of our team went 
there and as she was submitting documents for 
admission, a fellow applicant told her that he can 
buy the test of exams for 300,000 Mongolian 
togrogs (approximately US $258). He proposed that 
they share the amount. 
A day before exams, our journalist and the 
applicant were given 42 questions out of the 50 
questions of the entrance exam, enough to pass. 
Both took the exam and both were admitted. The 
questions were given to them by the sister of the 
applicant who had dinner with the director of the 
law school the day before the exam. 
The guy had arranged for the questions to be 
bought demanded his payment. After long discus-
sion, we decided to tell him the truth. He was 
shocked and asked not to publish his name.
The results
Journalists completed their articles in October 
and our material was published with the team 
names. It is sad to say that our team refused to 
publish one of the stories we investigated. 
Instead, we published one titled “Freedom to 
Journalists!” 
The story we did not publish exposed serious 
corruption, but we couldn’t publish it and this is 
very regrettable. Current legislation means that 
following somebody is persecution, collecting 
information is infringement of privacy and may 
violate legislation protection the secrets of 
organizations or the state. Taking pictures can 
be considered an encroachment on the subject’s 
private life and recording their voices without 
consent is illegal. Criticizing someone is tanta-
mount to defamation. And judges require notary 
verification before they will accept the docu-
ments we may produce as valid evidence. The law 
does not provide for freedom of information, nor 
does it recognize our rights to protect our 
sources. 
If investigative reporters must 
work the way detectives do, that is 
not possible in Mongolia. We did do 
it, but we ran the risk of being 
accused in violation of numerous 
provisions of the Criminal Law. 
And we wouldn’t stand much of a 
chance of winning in front of a 
court of law. Even if we enjoyed a 
fair trial, we would lose the case 
because there is no Mongolian law 
to protects us. 
In the end, we learned how to 
look out for and detect corruption. 
But we have also learned to practice 
self-censorship. ■
Enkhbaatar G. in Ulaanbaatar, Mongolia
© Flickr/Harunire
Mongolian University of Science and Technology
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 17
Cape Verde may soon boast six television channels. A 
fact hardly worth mentioning to a television viewer 
from the north, accustomed to choosing from a multi-
tude of channels offering information, entertainment, 
culture, sport, etc., but in Cape Verde, it amounts to 
an upcoming revolution. As was at the time, just 14 
years ago, the creation of Radio Nova, the first pri-
vate radio station in the country. 
Such major change in the media landscape can’t be 
improvised. Regulations are needed to prevent rule by 
the strongest prevailing, and to guarantee the public 
quality and pluralism. Specific texts were therefore 
adopted, criteria established and procedure set in 
motion – a jury reviewed the six applications for Hertz-
ian television licenses received by the Directorate for 
Social Communication (DGCS). The jury took into con-
sideration, for instance, each project’s range of cover-
age, as national coverage represents a significant asset 
for a country like Cape Verde, split into ten islands.
New regulations
Helping to set up regulations that are simultaneously 
fair, appropriate to the context and respectful of 
freedom of expression is part of UNESCO’s work to 
promote free and pluralistic media. The Organization 
therefore contributed legal expertise based on other 
countries’ experience. While there is nothing spec-
tacular about the cooperation UNESCO established, it 
will contribute in the long term to developing a high-
quality communication sector and the participation 
of citizens in managing public affairs. 
Beginning in 2002, UNESCO helped found the Felix 
Monteiro Press Centre, an information facility for 
journalists within the Ildo Lobo Culture Palace pro-
viding periodicals, newspapers and books as well as 
on-line media. Through its International Programme 
for the Development of Communication (IPDC), it 
then contributed to revising certain press laws and 
developing a new Social Communication code. Sev-
eral decrees, recommendations and resolutions have 
already been published. They concern notably the 
creation of private media, the regulation of journal-
ists’ press cards (a press card commission started up 
in July 2006), the rules governing access and activity 
for television operators, the register of companies 
and social communication media, and most recently, 
the rules for the public competition for private tele-
vision broadcasting.
Other projects
UNESCO also participated in the F_rum sobre Comu-
nica__o Social, a social communication symposium 
held in Praia on 8 and 9 December, which brought 
together media professionals, representatives of civil 
society and officials in charge of public policy. On 
this occasion, Sara Lopes, the Prime Minister’s Adjunct 
responsible for Qualification and Employment, men-
tioned other changes, announcing notably that the 
Cape Verdean government intended to concentrate on 
Cape Verde
Santo Antão
São Vicente
Branco
Santa Luzia
Raso
São Nicolau
Boa Vista
Sal
Maio
Santiago
Fogo
Secos
Islands
Brava
PRAIA
AT L A N T I C O C E A N
Mindelo
N
© UNESCO
A country split into ten islands
Media Revolution in Cape Verde
Fourteen years after the birth of the country’s first private radio station, Cape Verde 
is making notable progress in promoting press freedom. Measures have been taken to 
guarantee the public’s access to pluralistic, quality information.
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 18
modernizing the Ag_ncia Cabo-verdiana de Not_cias 
(Inforpress). The national press agency, currently suf-
fering from serious underinvestment, has an impor-
tant role to fulfill serving a population scattered 
among the different islands and a major diaspora. 
At the DGCS, headed by Eugenio Martins, other 
projects are under way that may also involve UNESCO. 
They concern aspects such as training, providing 
equipment for young people to conduct reporting in 
the different islands, and creating digital archives of 
the country’s television and radio. 
The outlook for media in Cape Verde looks even 
brighter thanks to these measures. In 2006, the 
country was ranked 47th out of 167 countries on the 
list assessing press freedom published by the NGO 
Reporters Without Borders. ■
4
Inhabitants of the Caribbean 
on the same wavelength
From Haiti to Jamaica, an active network of local radio stations are able to share their 
experiences and pool resources across marine and linguistic divides on an internet portal.
© Sonia Mills
The Hamalali Garinagu Studio aims to preserve and 
promote the Garifuna language
It’s a good idea whose time has been a long time a-
coming…the idea that if Caribbean people could 
share the challenges and problems and solutions of 
their communities, ‘live and direct’ through a radio 
link, community empowerment and Caribbean iden-
tity could spread like a bushfire. 
UNESCO’s effort to support community broadcast-
ing in developing countries started decades ago, but 
it is in the last ten years that the rapid development 
and penetration of the internet and associated tech-
nology has made collaboration and exchange not 
only possible but evident. In the last three years in 
the Caribbean the spread of internet usage, like cell 
phones, has not been just a phenomenon, it has also 
been a demonstration that poor and rich alike, the 
now generations, want access to technology that will 
allow them to play and to communicate. 
The technology has raced ahead but the hard chal-
lenge to organizations, governmental and non-gov-
ernmental, and to funding agencies, remains the 
same: how to make communication projects sustaina-
ble. In all instances, the challenge is about the sus-
tainability of human as well as technological and 
economic resources.
Increasing Collaboration across 
the Caribbean
UNESCO/International Programme for the Develop-
ment of Communication (IPDC) has led the effort 
and sustained support for intensified collaboration 
and exchange between some pretty far-flung and 4
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 1
remote communities across the Caribbean region. 
Training has been delivered to radio stations in 
Guyana, Suriname, Jamaica, Dominica, Belize, Cuba, 
and Haiti in various aspects of Multi Media Centre 
operation and management. Given the community 
volunteer character of many of these organizations, 
some of the community multimedia centres (CMCs) 
cum radio stations have had mixed fortunes and 
will predictably continue to have their ups and 
downs. 
Delivering training at the actual locations of 
community radio stations on a rotating basis has 
encouraged the sharing of ideas and networking 
among different radio stations and helped to grow 
the feeling of community and comradeship. 
In October 2005, at a meeting in Suriname, the 
decision was taken to develop a regional network 
of CMCs. This decision set the stage for the final 
step towards the creation of the long-dreamed-of 
network. To help the process along, UNESCO has 
provided funding for the creation of an internet 
radio portal which will allow all interested CMCs to 
webcast through the Multimedia for Caribbean Com-
munities (MCCLinks) website. 
According to Alton Grizzle, the UNESCO Officer 
currently responsible for this development: “The cre-
ation of the Caribbean Internet Radio Portal will 
facilitate increased local content development and 
sharing, expand the reach of community media and 
provide a common space for self-expression and 
creativity.” 
In the first stage the three or four stations with 
greatest capacity will stream their broadcasts live. 
Until the other stations can do the same, they will 
provide content by e-mail or by regular mail to ROOTS 
FM, which is responsible for receiving and scheduling 
content. The Regional Radio Project (RRP) is working 
with several Caribbean community stations to 
strengthen their capacity to produce and deliver 
radio programmes. The technical management of the 
portal is provided by the Container Project, a quasi-
CMC located in rural Jamaica which has also bene-
fited from UNESCO/IPDC support.
Results that make a difference
Mervin Jarman, the founding manager of the Con-
tainer Project gives an example of the sort of mate-
rial that community radios can share: “We’ve got 
alot of taped programmes from Dominica – cameos 
about the effect of Hurricane Ivan particularly on 
the lives of young people – I found them totally riv-
eting. There could be devastated young people right 
here in my community. Listening to them, I FELT 
them” 
“I am very grateful to be a part of bringing this 
idea to fruition,” says Rosamond Brown of ROOTS FM. 
“Yes, it’s been a long time coming, and the one dis-
appointing fact is that so many communities are still 
so remote that accessibility will remain a challenge.” 
A challenge that he hopes to overcome with time. 
The Caribbean Internet Radio Portal is a long-
awaited opportunity for people across the Caribbean 
to hear the voices of their brothers and sisters telling 
their own stories and concerns and searching for 
answers together. ■
Sonia Mills in Kingston, Jamaica
© Flickr/Frank Nielsen
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 110
The Courier looks back
From our past issues, a selection of articles on media development:
Radio Ada, the voice of those without a voice, November 2005 
A Ghanaian radio station begins to offer internet connection and training, thus opening new possibilities for its 
small community.  
Community multimedia centres, January 2004 
How this new initiative helps isolated communities in the developing world gain access to information and com-
munication technologies.  
SOS media, October 2002 
Building independent and reliable journalism in post conflict areas is essential for reconciliation and 
reconstruction.  
Nurturing Afghanistan’s fledgling free press, October 2002 
UNESCO helps the war-ravaged nation in the task of rebuilding its media. 
Mexico’s mercenary legacy, July-August 2001 
The country’s press has replaced old docility with hard-nosed opposition and helped to topple a 71-year-old 
system. Will it continue?  
Rise of a new watchdog in Latin America, July-August 2001 
A professor of journalism talks on how advanced technology helps the region’s emboldened media in spreading 
democracy.  
Small media, new voices, February 2000 
A look at some of journalism’s new voices from different regions of the world – and the deeper social impacts of 
this media explosion. 
To learn more: www.unesco.org/courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 111
TIMELINE
The first article of UNESCO’s Constitution, 
adopted in 1946, calls for the advancement of 
mutual knowledge and understanding of peoples 
through all means of mass communication and 
urges the promotion of the free flow of ideas 
by word and image. This defines UNESCO’s twin 
functions regarding the media: support freedom 
of expression as well as media development. Key 
dates since then:
17 – The first survey of technical needs in the press, radio and films is completed. It covers twelve 
countries devastated by the Second World War. 
1 – A dozen countries set up the International Radio University through the joint sponsorship of 
UNESCO and the French Radio Broadcasting Service. 
1 – A weekly 15-minute review is broadcast in 18 languages by the radio stations of 47 countries and 
territories. 
157 – The International Association for Media and Communication Research (IAMCR) is established at 
UNESCO’s initiative. 
157 – The first regional centre for the training of journalism teachers opens at the University of Stras-
bourg (France) with the assistance of UNESCO and the French Government. 
172 – With technical assistance from UNESCO, Mali launches «Kibaru», its first rural newspaper in the 
Bambara language. More than a dozen African papers in several countries follow. 
177 – The Asia-Pacific Institute for Broadcasting Development opens its doors in Kuala Lumpur (Malay-
sia). Initially a UNESCO/UN project, it engages in communication training programmes. 
180 – The International Programme for the Development of Communication (IPDC) is created to help 
develop the media in developing countries. 
180 – An international commission on the study of communication issues, chaired by Sean MacBride of 
Ireland, publishes the report, “Many Voices, One World.” 
183 – The UN proclaims World Communications Year to increase the scope and effectiveness of commu-
nications as a force for economic, social and cultural development. 
185 – The Kheda Project in India is the first recipient of the IPDC-UNESCO Rural Communication Prize. It 
creates audiovisual programmes drawing on traditional cultural expressions. 
© MillyNeT/ Libre de droits
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The UNESCO Courier • 2007 • Number 112
18 – UNESCO adopts a “new communication strategy” replacing the New World Information Order 
launched by the MacBride report. It encourages the free flow of information at all levels while promoting 
improved dissemination of information and strengthening communication capacities in developing 
countries. 
10 - The new strategy takes effect with the organization in February of an unprecedented roundtable 
of media professionals from eastern, central and western Europe, as well North America, just three months 
after the fall of the Berlin Wall. 
11 – The Declaration of Windhoek on independent and pluralist media is adopted during the first of 
five regional seminars. During the next six years, similar initiatives are taken in Almaty (Kazakhstan), 
Santiago (Chile), Sana’a (Yemen) and Sofia (Bulgaria). 
12 – The International Freedom of Expression Exchange (IFEX) network is established with UNESCO’s 
intellectual and financial backing. The network, based in Toronto (Canada), acts as a watchdog on issues 
pertaining to press freedom worldwide. 
13 – The UN General Assembly proclaims 3 May for the yearly observance of World Press Freedom Day. 
1 – The UN designates UNESCO as lead agency for assistance to independent media during the recon-
struction period in the former Yugoslavia. 
17 – An independent international jury awards the first UNESCO/Guillermo Cano World Press Freedom 
Prize to Chinese journalist Gao Yu. 
2001 –UNESCO’s first community multimedia centre is created in Kothmale (Sri Lanka). This new initiative 
combines local radio with a walk-in telecentre for internet and computer training in a rural environment. 
2005 – At the World Summit on the Information Society in Geneva and Tunis (2003 and 2005 respec-
tively), UNESCO mobilizes the commitment of the international community for freedom of expression, 
multilingualism and respect for cultural diversity on the internet. 
4
The UNESCO Courier is published by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization. 
7, place de Fontenoy – 75352 Paris 07 SP, France 
General inquiries by e-mail: courier.unesco@unesco.org 
 Director: Saturnino Muñoz Gómez Editor in Chief: Enzo Fazzino
 French Editor: Agnès Bardon English Editors: Stephen Roberts, Edna Yahil
 Spanish Editor: Lucía Iglesias Kuntz Arabic Editor: Bassam Mansour
 Russian Editors: Vladimir Sergueev, Katerina Markelova Chinese Editor: Weiny Cauhape
 Editorial Assistant: José Banaag Photo Editor: Fiona Ryan
 Web Platform: Fabienne Kouadio, Chakir Piro Layout: Gérard Prosper
Articles and photos credited UNESCO may be reproduced and/or translated providing the credit line reads “Reproduced from the UNESCO Courier”, 
and include date and hyperlink. Photos without UNESCO credit request specific authorization. 
Articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO. 
Boundaries on maps do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations of the countries and territories concerned.
 ISSN 1993-8616 
]]>
</page>
</document>
