<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="184071eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
DOUBLE ISSUE JULY/AUGUST 1993
M 1205- 9308 40,00 F
_
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S DIRECTOR-GENERAL
WINS PRESS FREEDOM AWARD
The Director-General of Unesco, Mr. Federico Mayor, has
been awarded the Golden Pen of Freedom by the International
Federation of Newspaper Publishers (FIEJ), which represents
more than 1 5,000 newspapers worldwide. This is the first time
that the prize has gone to a personality from outside jour¬
nalism. The reforms of Unesco's media policy carried out by
Mr. Mayor since his appointment, says FIEJ, "now enable
Unesco to become a real force for furthering freedom of
expression in the world". Responding to the announcement,
Mr. Mayor said that Unesco was being honoured through him,
adding that "The prize ... is an encouragement and an urgent
invitation to forge ahead. Unesco must take an increasingly
active role in the defence of human rights, of which press
freedom is the cornerstone."
^M
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 INTERVIEW
Oliver Stone ii
Contents
JULY- AUGUST 1993
WHAT IS
MODERN?
11 MAKING IT NEW
13 Modern times, new approaches
by Aya Wassef
15 When less means more
L A "f 1 J fVt. t. I '-
by Ank Levy and Pippo Lionm
16 Micro-Mega Cover: Le spectre du regard
by Yves Beauvois and Alexandra Poulain (1984), by Nissim Merkado, who
describes the elements of the
18 The shy horizon composition as "video, sound, text,
10
by Edmond Petit
GOING TOO FAR
neon and Cécile".
Md. Md.
1 UNESCO IN ACTION <<
NEWSBRIEFS... 11 The devalued image
by Sonia Younan
S3
t UNESCO IN ACTION 17 The apple of my eye
by Nissim Merkado
Greenwatch
WORLD HERITAGE
Santísima Trinidad, memories 18 The more generation
of slavery and sugar by Reginald Fraser Amonoo
by Edouard Bailby 31 The spare parts syndrome
by Bernard Teo
\ REFLECTIONS
Traditions for Tomorrow 41 LIVING WITH CHANGE
by Diego Gradis
******^^^^^^^^^
41 Sound barriers 79
I PORTRAIT
Hahmoud Nokhtar
46
by R. Murray Schäfer
Architects of disorder
#3
(1891-1934) by Fernando and Diego Montes COMMENTARY
by Magdi Youssef 49 The third bank of the river
DH »J
by Roberto Da/Vlatta by Federico Mayor
- BOOKS OF THE WORLD
^ JM
A voyage through European 54 HEARING NEW VOICES
literature
by Edgar Reichmann 55 A world steeped in music
by Isabelle Leymarie
RECENT RECORDS
60 Me and my shadow
by Simon Lane
by Isabelle Leymarie
64 Pieces of music, music of pieces
ï LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
by Leon M'tlo Special consultant
68 Rimbaud's quest for this issue:
by Sami Na'ir Hugues de (eintet
TheLfcjIx Tr Ç1 f*/~\ "The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
|^ Í*- TV A. J "that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
*^»-vt irjip y* "that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
y JI J |\| h.lx unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
j^^^=. intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
46th year Published monthly and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
in 31 languages and in Braille EXTRACT FROM THE. PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER I94S
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
N T E R V I E W
OLIVER STONE
talks to Mahmoud Hussein
and Régis Debray
One of America's leading film-makers, Oliver Stone
has won several Oscars for best film and best
director. He has made many big hits, including
Scarface (1983), Platoon (1986), Wall Street (1987)
and JFK (1992). He follows political and social
developments in the United States closely and
describes them uncompromisingly. Here he talks
about his commitment and the conditions under
which film directors operate.
You have made severalfilms dealing
with very sensitive matters. That is not
easy. In the movie business, it isn't a
question of wanting to do something
then going and doing it, is it?
No, it's never easy, because the stu¬
dios want to make money. That's always
the issue with movies like this: if you
take on a large subject that's contro¬
versial, you're going to upset a certain
group of people. That doesn't generally
help the movie; people think it does,
but many people stay away if there's
controversy.
That wasn't the case with Platoon,
your film about the Viet Nam War,
was it?
Platoon caught the national mood
when it came out. President Reagan
was about to invade Nicaragua, there
was a feeling we were going to be drawn
into another war, and there was a gen¬
uine curiosity, eighteen or twenty years
after the event, about the Viet Nam war.
People were getting tired of Reagan.
The Oliver North trial had just hap¬
pened in 1986, and opinion was begin¬
ning to turn against the militarization of
the country. So I think the timing of
the movie was just right.
Was there an autobiographical ele¬
ment in thefilm?
Platoon is based pretty much on my
own experiences in Viet Nam. I was in
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Oliver Stone (holding script)
with Kevin Costner during the
filming ofJFK ( 1 992).
the 25th Infantry and the 1st Cavalry.
It was not straight autobiography, I
fictionalized the story and ran charac¬
ters together.
You don't see much when you're in
combat, but I felt that every platoon
that I was in was divided into the
people who were more sensitive to the
Vietnamese and the people who were
insensitive to what we were doing in
Viet Nam. There was a moral division
inside each combat unit. I thought the
same about America when I got home.
It was very divided between what they
called the hawks and the doves. Most
people were neutral, but there were
strong opinions on both sides. I fought
with my father, with my family. I felt
very alienated. I tried to deal with those
feelings in a film I made about coming
home, Born on the Fourth ofJuly.
We often hear from the American
film industry that cinema is entertain¬
ment. When Hollywood turns to his¬
tory, accuracy is hardly the main con¬
cern. How do youfeelabout this? Must
entertainment comefirst?
That's two different questions. I
agree that movies are entertainment. A
good movie has to grip you. Most
people don't want to sit for two hours
in the dark watching a documentary, so
you have to introduce the element of
tension, the thriller element. I think
I've been able to deal with relatively
serious subjects in my movies and
make them intriguing, so that people
want to see them. There are a million
films made, in Europe or even in
America, that, let's face it, nobody
wants to see. They don't want to see
life down on the farm if there's nothing
to hook their attention. You know, the
sun comes up, the sun goes down, the
farmer washes his laundry. . . . But if
the farmer has a daughter and aha!
she gets involved with some rich guy,
then the complications start, that's
when the audience gets interested.
Let's look a little further into what
you call the thriller element. Is it always
simply a matter ofgoodguy versus bad
guy, or can it be more complicated than
that?
Good movies play with your idea of
who the villain is. You think some
character is the bad guy but he's not.
The good guy turns out to be the vil¬
lain. So movies are not that simplistic.
In Alfred Hitchcock's films you rarely
know who is going to do what to
whom. In Vertigo, is the woman bad or
good? In Notorious, is Cary Grant bad
or good? We play with identity in
movies.
I have to agree that the film business
has notoriously bungled history. It's
famous for it. We've made heroes of
some very hollow people, no question
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A scene from Salvador
(1986).
about it. We would have made films
about Senator Joe McCarthy if he
hadn't been found out. J. Edgar Hoover
was a hero in my country until recently.
But history is always being changed
and rewritten. Shakespeare made a vil¬
lain out of Richard III and history says
he was essentially a good king. Why
blame Hollywood? Historians them¬
selves should be held to account,
because we are always re-examining
history. A historian like Arthur
Schlesinger reinvents American his¬
tory to his liking, making a hero of
President Andrew Jackson, for
example. George Washington has been
reinterpreted several times. Thomas
Jefferson has been reinterpreted as a
slave-owner, a good guy, a bad guy.
Abe Lincoln's the only one I know
who seems pretty much to have gotten
away with it in American history.
You say that history is reinterpreted
every few years in America, but one
thing that doesn't change is the pre¬
sentation of Mafiosi and gangsters
as heroes in American films. Why is
there thisperversion ofthe idea ofthe
hero?
The glorification of the Mafia in our
country is sick. As great as Coppola's
two Godfather films are, they are, I
believe, historically wrong in
attributing this degree of power to the
Mafiosi when they are really a bunch of
thugs who have done much to corrupt
the country via organized labour, busi¬
ness the liquor business, Las Vegas,
the jukebox business kickbacks for
politicians, and so on. Gangsterism in
our country goes back before the
Italian Mafia, back to Boss Tweed, the
Irish Mafia, the ugly Mafia that existed
in the time of George Washington.
There were all kinds of gangsterism in
American life. To glorify it as we have
done is, as you say, a perversion.
But why do American audiences
respond to these films?
I think it's because we were revolu¬
tionaries, because we were mostly out¬
casts from Europe, because we have a
tough-guy strain. We don't like being
shoved around by authority, which is
not a bad quality in some ways. We
admired Bogart and Cagney, but they
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Television footage used in
JFK, with Martin Luther King
in the centre.
were sentimental gangsters, movie
gangsters.
When you made JFK, for example,
didyou think of it as a militant film?
Yes, in a sense. I didn't give the
Warren Commission's version of events
because it had been defended for years
by the establishment and the media. I
touched a very sensitive nerve in JFK
when I attacked the media, saying that
the cover-up was not only the work of
certain people in government but was
propagated by the media, who accepted
the story without doing any home¬
work and they didn't do any.
The power of the media is, I think,
one of the biggest problems in my
country. The newsrooms of CBS,
NBC, ABC, Newsweek, Time, the
New York Times there are fifteen or
twenty of them and they all think alike,
they plug the same agenda over and
over again. When Clinton came into
office, they forced this young man to
consider the agenda their way. They
force the issue by putting tremendous
pressure on somebody new who may
want to address the situation in a new
way. I think this is a distorting effect of
the First Amendment, whose authors
couldn't have guessed how strong the
media would become in the electronic
era. I don't know the solution. You
have to have freedom of speech, but it's
reached insane proportions when it's
really control of speech, not freedom.
Why is there this consensus among the
twenty or so centres ofpower in the
media?
I can't tell you where it starts, but
there's a decision that certain things will
be on the agenda, that they will make
those things the issue of the day or of
the month. One time it may be home-
lessness or taxes, another time it will
be why the military must be supported
in Iraq or whatever. As I.F. Stone said,
the press are like blackbirds, they all
take off from the telephone wire at the
same time and when one comes back,
they all come back. We're living in an
Alice-in-Wonderland society where
from one month to the next we stagger
from one issue to another. We are told
what is important for that month. I
resent that.
I went to Viet Nam as a result of a
media onslaught that convinced us we
had to prevent it from being the next
domino to fall to communism. The
media messed this country up terribly
with that one. With the Kennedy
murder, they all lined up behind the
idea of the lone gunman firing three
crazy bullets and killing the President,
although there is little factual evidence.
Why exactly didyou make JFK?
I think Kennedy was killed for polit¬
ical reasons, to remove him from power.
First of all because, as of 1963, there
was a significant change in his policies
and the way he viewed the world. He
made a deal with Khrushchev; the two
of them signed the Nuclear Test Ban
Treaty in 1963. He was talking to Castro
behind the establishment's back. He
had signed a memo to pull out of Viet
Nam. This is not speculation: the doc¬
ument exists, he signed it, it's called the
National Security Action Memo¬
randum 263. Only recently Robert
McNamara finally admitted that
Kennedy was going to pull out of Viet
Nam.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
There was a significant accelera¬
tion of intention when Lyndon
Johnson took over. On the very day
Kennedy was buried, as I showed in
the movie, Johnson called an emer¬
gency meeting with General Maxwell
Taylor and the Joint Chiefs of Staff to
push the Viet Nam agenda. There was
a meeting in Honolulu the day that
Kennedy was killed about the subject
of Viet Nam. It's a fascinating story,
what went on the last two or three
days before he was killed.
Didyou have free access to all the
archives?
The archives in America are like they
are in Russia, they're opened but by
the time the public gets to know of
them they've been reviewed and cen¬
sored by the bureaucratic process. A
new legislation was passed, that the film
helped create, opening up the Kennedy
files. Anything that might endanger
national security has to be reviewed by
a special board of people appointed by
the President.
I'm sure that Kennedy, if he had
lived, would have ended the Cold War
with Khrushchev in the late 'sixties, in
his second term. It's interesting that
very shortly after Kennedy was killed,
Khrushchev was ousted. I think there's
a linkage between the fates of the two
men. That's why I think the subject is of
such importance, not just to American
history but to world history in the
twentieth century.
M JFK is a mixture ofstockshots andfic¬
tion. Were some ofthe stockshots infact
staged?
We staged most of it. There are some
genuine stockshots in the beginning,
but not as many as people think. The
autopsy sequence, for example, was all
staged except for one very clear shot
of Kennedy at the end. You'll see that
his face was intact, which is interesting
because if he had been shot from behind
the face would have been blown away.
The docudrama element the inter¬
linking offact and fiction gives the
film its aesthetic impact. But perhaps
that mixture raises a moralproblem too.
I've heard that criticism. My answer
is, it's a war. You ripped off this country,
you told this story no holds barred,
you fought dirty and I'm fighting you
the same way, I steal things left, right
and centre. Yes, I was militant.
Left, Born on the Fourth ofJuly (1989),
starring Tom Cruise. Opposite page,
a scene from Platoon (1 986).
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
What difference did thefilm make?
All films find their way into the
country's subconscious in the end. I
think what it changed was trust in the
government. Around twenty million
Americans saw it. And I don't think
any young kid now will buy the story
that Lee Harvey Oswald was a lone
gunman. The papers don't say that so
much now. They think twice before
saying it.
Would it bepossible to make afilm in
the UnitedStates now about the Amer¬
ican attitude during the GulfWar, with
President Bush as hero or anti-hero ?
That's another Orwellian story. It's
not for me, it's for some other movie¬
maker. Someone said to me that the
Gulf War wasn't a war, it was a TV film.
Nobody got killed on our side and we
didn't even know there were all those
people killed on the other side. There
were six Time magazine cover stories
about the situation before the war
started, and by the end of it Saddam
Hussein looked like Hitler, complete
with the moustache. He was demo-
nized in the American consciousness,
made out to be a monster. We were
ready to go out and kill. It was a hor¬
rible time to live through because again
you saw the way patriotism came out."
You mention patriotism. In the
golden age ofcinema, Americans were
proud ofHollywood. Now foreigners
are buying into Hollywoodand maybe
in a few years they'll have bought
it out. What do you think of this
situation?
The film business is a land without
frontiers. You work for different people
in your lifetime, different producers,
people you never thought you would
team up with. JFK was made with
French, Israeli, German money. The
Italians put up money for The Doors,
the English for Salvador and Platoon.
That's what's good about the film busi¬
ness. All these international players like
to be in on the game.
You approve ofthat?
Of course it's a good thing. How else
would movies get made? They need an
enormous concentration of capital.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
What about creative freedom? Are
you allowed it?
Only if you can get away with it. If
you make a film that makes money,
they like you. I just got by by the skin
of my teeth. Salvador missed out at
the box office, but Platoon was a hit,
and then I got carte blanche for the
next couple of films. They were both
successful, so then I was able to make
Born on the Fourth ofJuly, which also
did well. That gave me a little more
freedom, so then I decided to go for
JFK. They would never have let me
do JFK in the beginning, but they did
at that point of my career, and it
worked.
Why was Salvador not a success?
Politics. When it came out in early
1986, we were still in the grip of Rea-
ganism. The critics were not very kind.
The New York Times said it was a typ¬
ical Costa-Gavras kind of propaganda
effort. Yet most everything of that film
including American complicity has
emerged in the last ten years as a truth.
Do you sometimes feel like a latter-
day knight errant? Knights werepriv¬
ilegedpeople but they also had duties,
they were defending sacred values. Do
you feel both this privilege and this
duty?
That's very true. It's a special situa¬
tion. You must use your power well to
make films that are difficult to get made.
Otherwise you'll lose it.
Right now is a good time for me to
make difficult movies. I just finished
Heaven and Earth in Thailand and Viet
Nam. It's the story of thirtysome years
in the life of a Vietnamese peasant
woman. It was not an easy film to make.
Are you working especially for an
American audience, or do you feel the
world is your audience?
Most of my films have made more
money abroad than in America. JFK
made twice as much abroad. The films
are going well internationally. I feel I
need a world-view to understand my
own life better. I always think film¬
makers tend to underestimate the power
and intelligence of the audience's sub¬
conscious mind.
Not only that, maybe. Perhapspeople
want, at least sometimes, to be stirred by
noble causes?
JFK didn't make any commercial
sense. It was three hours long, it had lots
of dialogue and it was complicated. But
I said I'm going to make this movie, it
will bomb but I have to make it. I never
really thought it would be easily under¬
stood by medium range audiences. But
they did understand it. It was one of the
great experiences of my life. It proves
that people are more intelligent than
they're given credit for. Even if they
don't understand everything at first,
they're willing to sit there and see it a
second time, on video or something, to
fill in the gaps.
How do you explain the world¬
wide fascination with Hollywood
films and with American popular
culture in general?
The world is a satellite world now,
and America is on the cutting edge.
People like the music, they buy it; they
like the look, they buy the clothes; they
like the hamburgers	 Youth wants to
be free from the shackles of the adult
world and old ways of doing things.
It's more fun F-U-N And many Hol¬
lywood movies evoke the concept of
fun. They're light, they're entertaining.
t¡ I think that's the answer.
But not all Hollywood films have
had the same success	
Maybe they didn't have the right
lightness of being.
IO
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
wEE¿e
¿Ofelia BWPJrjja]
WHAT IS MODERN?
What do we mean by "modern"? The concept is elusive, ambiguous, ever-
changing. It is a paradox, constantly disputed, that refuses to be pinned down
by even a tentative definition. That which is modern is that which defies its
own definition, or is defined in negative terms, by what it is not.
There are modern things, not only objects but also functions, qualities
and forms of behaviour. Compact discs are modern and so are organ trans¬
plants and concern for the environment. A taste for superlatives is one fea¬
ture of modernity, whether applied to the prowess of athletes or the soft¬
ness of detergents. Extremity of scale is another, one might think the
minuscule in electronics, the gigantic in architecture.
Perhaps the best way to understand "the modern" is to take a cluster of
modern phenomena and to see what signs, clues and images they reveal.
Acting on this assumption, we asked men and women from different back¬
grounds, cultures and walks of life artists, designers, writers, architects,
musicians, philosophers, doctors, engineers to investigate the concept of
modernity. To help them on their way we suggested a number of ideas, clues
and keywords such as fragmention, the act of seeing, disorder, miniature,
new, audio and invisible.
As it happened, some of these clues did not lead far. However, new
pointers emerged. Where they led to can be seen on the following pages, in
a compilation of images and "signs of the times" that illustrate some of the
innumerable manifestations of modernity.
HUGUES DE COINTET I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
roQKiNr IT NTH
ri n ü tu
The quest for
the new has
become an
obsession, and
novelty an end
in itself. But the
ultimate
modern trend
may lie in
discovering new
meanings in
what already
exists, however
y _ old it may be.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Modern
times,
new
approaches
by Aya Wassef
WE are confronted nowadays with an
endless stream of new products and
ideas new brands of detergent, new
biscuit flavours, the latest issue of the news¬
paper, new economic and social policies, a new
world order and we might be tempted to think
that if something is new then it is by definition
modern, that the very word new is enough to
give the cachet of modernity to anything it is
used to describe. Newness today would thus
seem to be a kind of short cut to modernity,
rather than standing in an obvious or causal
relationship to it.
The widespread use of the word new is
symptomatic of both a state of affairs and a
state of mind. New things have always been
made, but the emphasis on newness as a selling
point has not always existed, still less the craze
for new things. Common sense long decreed
that a new object was one that had not been
tried and tested, that it was not necessarily sound
and might even be dangerous.
THE NEW IS DEAD,
LONG LIVE THE NEWt
Today's perception of newness is very different.
A thing must be new in order to be acknowl¬
edged as modern. Novelty is the price of moder¬
nity whence the paradox of a so-called
"modern" or even "post-modern" society that
still seems, through its frantic quest for nov¬
elty, to be in search of its own modernity.
The European pioneers of Modernism sig¬
nalled that they were breaking with tradition by
ascribing an intrinsic value to newness. This
choice of the new as a symbolic value was an
invitation to take a leap in the dark, to run the
risk of destabilizing generally accepted ideas,
but whereas for these intellectuals and artists
modernity signified a break with the past, within
our modernized society newness has gone its
own way.
Modernity has gone hand in hand with sci¬
entific progress and discovery, industrializa¬
tion, mass production, the consumer society,
the growth of the media and their increasing
influence on culture. With the development of
branches of trade and industry based on new
products, newness has come to be accepted as a
fact of life. It has lost its originality and its rev¬
olutionary connotations as the symbol of a
break with tradition, its sense of being ahead of
its time. It has lost its modernity. The consumer
society demands a rapid turnover of new prod¬
ucts, making sure that what's new today is obso¬
lete tomorrow. The opposite of new is no longer
old, but old-fashioned, yesterday's novelty that
has fallen out of favour. This is an ephemeral
form of newness, greeted with fanfares simply
Above, at a tribal meeting
in Papua New Guinea a
participant sports an outfit
made of tin cans.
Opposite page, M.L
horizontale V (1969), a
collage by the Polish-born
artist Roman Cieslewicz
based on Leonardo da
Vinci's Mona Lisa.
AYA WASSEF,
an Egyptian essayist, is a
consultant with a Paris
communications agency.
tú
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A worker at a factory
producing computer chips
in Silicon Valley, California
(U.S.A.).
because for a fleeting moment it is new. The
new, the supreme triumph of the present over
the past, has become the ultimate expression of
a modernity that has reached fever pitch.
A NEW LOOK
AT THE OLD
Thus emptied of its substance, the new has
become the vector of the dominant values of
our societies. Through constant media expo¬
sure, it has taken over the media. A new product
is more efficient, nouvelle cuisine is healthier, a
new computer is more user-friendly, a new
lifestyle is more environment-friendly, new tele¬
vision is more interactive. Consumer goods are
marketed by associating them with the appeal of
qualities such as efficiency, environmental aware¬
ness, conviviality and comfort. They offer each
individual a slice of modernity and people buy
them in order to claim the values enshrined in
them in other words, to be modern.
A value considered modern in a society here
and now is not, however, necessarily so regarded
elsewhere and at a different time. In a space-time
relationship that has been radically affected by
^*.l iwi II
II* I _ y*Y**' 	 ->-,-'.. ' "tLj ^Tl.
14
faster and ever more sophisticated means of
communication, modernity seems to play tricks
with history and geography. When something
modern originating in the Western industrial
nations the so-called "North" is exported
to the "South" there is a certain time-lag, so
that what is modern in the South is a thing of the
past in the North.
Conversely, what is traditional in the South
is modern in the North. In the "developing"
countries, newness and modernity are often
associated with the acquisition of objects, of
products from the West, which itself went
through this phase some time ago. Modernity in
the industrialized countries, on the other hand,
is often related to a new way of looking at some¬
thing that already exists; paradoxical as it may
seem, "going back to one's roots", rediscov¬
ering in the present the values of the past, is
thus a modern phenomenon.
Significantly, "naturalness" is one of the key
values in a form of modernity that promotes
respect for the natural environment, ecology,
wellbeing, and the health-giving properties of
organically-grown foods and of natural medicine
based on ancient traditions. Naturalness as such
is not new; it is the appeal that it holds for us
today, as a significant new value, that makes it
modern.
THE LOGIC
OF THE NEW
This new approach to what already exists is dis¬
tinctively modern: it is the logic of the new the
process whereby something new is created from
what went before rather than newness in itself,
that is modern.
The artist who synthesizes images out of
images of the real world reduced to digital form
in a computer, the architect who turns a railway
station into a museum, the fashion stylist who
borrows sophisticated materials from the space
industry to create a garment, the designer who
fashions a piece of furniture from recycled mate¬
rial all these are creating something new by a
process of diverting and reshaping, by bor¬
rowing, reassembling and changing meanings.
These are the defining characteristics of an atti¬
tude, today considered modern, in a society
that has broken loose from any kind of histor¬
ical perspective and settled into a continuous
present: new things are wrought from old, dis¬
tant things are brought to our own doorstep, and
everything is seen throught the prism of moder¬
nity this is the logic of the new.
The logic of the new is a logic of retrieving
and reassembling. It scorns the passage of the
years, bringing together in space things that are
far apart in time. The logic of the new is indeed
distinctively modern.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
When less means more
by Arik Levy and Pippo Lionni
Above, a miniature robot
known as "Monsieur"
perches on a leaf.
WHEN people describe their experience of
communications technology and rapid
intercontinental travel, they often say
that we live in a shrinking world. This is an image:
the world is not really shrinking. In a more literal
sense, however, many of the instruments and
appliances we regularly use are, because of tech¬
nological advances, becoming smaller so small
in many cases that it would be no exaggeration to
say that miniaturization is one of the defining
and disconcerting features of life today.
Miniaturization is a process that gives rise to
many questions and very few answers. What is
miniaturization, exactly? At what point is some¬
thing miniaturized? Do we have some notion
that a manufactured object a camera or a tele¬
phone, say can have a "right" or optimum size?
If so, by what standards is this normal size
defined? Now that a pocket-sized electronic
device has the capacity to store the contents of a
pile of documents on an office table, what is hap¬
pening to the rules that have traditionally gov¬
erned our ideas of proportion?
What, furthermore, are the psychological and
physiological implications of miniaturization?
After all, the shape and size of the objects which
surround us inevitably influence the relation¬
ship we have with them. In this dynamic inter¬
action between objects and people, the minia¬
turization of one element in the relationship IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
implies more than just a reduction in size. A tele¬
vision set reduced to the size of a pack of playing
cards is no longer a piece of furniture in the same
proportion to a chair, a table or a cupboard, and
the moving image on its screen is no longer com¬
parable to the static image of a painting hanging
on a wall or a magazine cover. We can pick up a
miniature television and carry it around with us.
It becomes an extension of our bodies. It is easier
to find a place for it in our home. Our reaction to
the relative smallness of objects is important
because it suggests that there may be a limit to the
hitherto seemingly unchecked race towards
miniaturization. As things get smaller and smaller,
the fingers that manipulate them seem to be get¬
ting bigger and bigger. . . .
Miniaturized objects can be seen as "envi¬
ronment friendly" inasmuch as they are designed
to take up the least possible space and consume
the least possible energy and other resources. At
the same time they enable us to free ourselves
from the constraints of place and time: one
response to the hostile subway environment is to
retreat into the auditory isolation of a personal
stereo. Of course there may be limits to the user-
friendliness provided by miniaturization, which,
if taken too far, would literally become a reductio
ad absurdum. It would, for example, be techni¬
cally possible to produce an issue of this magazine
that would be, say, one-twentieth of its present
size, thus saving ink, paper, time, mailing and
transport costs. Unfortunately the magazine
would have become impossible to read with the
naked eye.
Miniaturized consumer products such as
microcomputers and digitally-controlled portable
telephones are becoming familiar features of
everyday life. In Japan a minute robot named
"Monsieur" has been developed using wristwatch
technology. It is driven by an ultra-small, super-
energy-efficient motor with an extremely compact
quartz crystal oscillator that enables the micro-
robot to make precise, shock-resistant movements
over an extended period. "Monsieur" has many
potential applications in industry and medicine.
Imagine a microrobot being injected into your
body and sent crawling around it to carry out a
check-up and if necessary perform repairs.
Not all objects seem destined to be shrunk.
Furniture, clothes and cooking appliances, for
example, will no doubt undergo fundamental
changes in the years to come, but though they
may become minimal, it is doubtful whether
they will become much smaller.
ARIK LEVY,
of Israel, works internationally as a freelance designer. He is
an assistant with a unit of the Ecole Nationale Supérieure
de Création Industrielle in Paris.
PIPPO LIONNI,
of the United States, is co-director of the Paris design
agency "Integral Concept" and a unit director at the Ecole
Nationale Supérieure de Création Industrielle in Paris.
Micro-Mega
by Yves Beauvois and Alexandra Poulain
PARADOXICAL though it may appear, in an
age when the characteristic modern trend
is towards the gigantic, there is also a trend
towards the very small, from Japanese bonsai
trees to computer chips. Are they unconnected,
or are they two different facets of the same mod¬
ernizing impulse?
Those who discuss modernity in the present
tense must necessarily include themselves in the
subject under discussion, for modernity can only
be defined in relation to a given moment in time.
That moment is thereby defined, either implicitly
or explicitly, as a break in the time continuum of
a civilization or culture, and no break can be
more noticeable or indeed spectacular than one
that startles the eye by disproportionately
enlarging familiar features of the beholder's envi¬
ronment. This tendency to make things appear
new by enlarging them finds expression in the
familiar myth of the Tower of Babel, in which the
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
challenge of monumentality translates the desire
to transcend the limits of the human. The urge to
build ever bigger would indeed seem to satisfy
modern man's need to leave some lasting monu¬
ment so as to outlive the vagaries of time.
In the nineteenth century this attitude became
more systematic and widespread than ever before.
The engineering feats of the Industrial Revolution
paved the way for an ever-increasing number of
colossal construction projects: this was the age of
stations built like cathedrals, department stores
resembling temples, and factories disguised as
castles. The context of daily life was radically
altered as urbanization progressed. Cities came to
express the all-conquering power of attraction of
modernity.
Then space began to grow scarce under the
pressure of such overweening ambition. Satura¬
tion-point loomed. To survive, modern man
invented a new, equal and opposite approach, a
steady reduction in the size of objects that were
regarded as taking up too much space. "Small is
beautiful" could be the motto of twentieth-cen¬
tury technology, for miniaturization has been
an overriding concern in the development of
electronics, information technology, office and
household automation and telecommunications.
Gigantism and miniaturization are two coex¬
isting aspects of the same desire to control space
with the aid of increasingly complex technologies.
By using intelligence in this way, modernity
shows itself to be a manifestation ofpower. In the
all-out search for efficiency, the attraction exer¬
cised both by the very large and the very small has
pushed aside concern for harmony and its corol¬
lary, wisdom. Modernity calls for the inordinate.
In some respects this attitude could well be a
new form of hubris, the concept of impious
flouting of the natural order that the ancient
Greeks used to describe the condition of bar¬
barity. Perhaps it is no coincidence that the mas¬
sive and the miniature come together in the
atomic bomb, whose vast destructive power is
matched by its small size.
Our contemporaries may be barbarians, but
they are Titans too, constantly courting danger by
daring to shake established norms to their foun¬
dations.
Left above, the Arche de la
Défense in Paris.
Below, a microchip in the
eye of a needle.
YVES BEAUVOIS
teaches history at the Institut
d'Études Politiques in Paris. He
is the author of a study on
Franco-Polish relations during
the "phoney war", Les Relations
franco-polonaises pendant la
"Drôle de Guerre" (Paris, 1989).
ALEXANDRA POULAIN
teaches English at the
University of Caen (France).
m
hbW> J
*4a^
I
I J
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The sky horizon
by Edmond Petit
18
EDMOND PETIT,
former reconnaissance pilot
and a founder member of
France's National Air and
Space Academy, is the author
of many published works, most
recently a history of aviation
entitled Nouvelle histoire
mondiale de l'aviation (Paris,
1991).
IN the beginning was the bird and the bird
was in the sky, and earthbound humans
sought to imitate it.
In the words of the French poet Saint-John
Perse, "The bird ... by encouraging humans to
fly, alone emboldened them afresh."1
Once people had worked out how birds flew,
they mistakenly believed that they could make
wings for themselves and that they would be
strong enough to work them.
While waiting for wings that worked and
above all for an engine to power them the
people ofAntiquity (which was, after all, modern
in its day) first made imaginary beings fly: gods
and demi-gods, heroes and spirits. To this we
owe the story of Icarus (not forgetting the
inventor Daedalus, his father), a recurrent theme
in the literature and imagery of every age.
We read of magic carpets, feathered capes,
winged horses . . . and of how humankind's first
imagined flights were borne on the pinions of
griffins, eagles or geese. Before aspiring to take
flight unaided, man first acquired experience of
falling: one after another, the would-be birdmen
of old crashed to the ground.
Then one day a visionary came close to
finding the answer. Leonardo da Vinci seems to
have foreseen flying machines, helicopters, para¬
chutes. To judge from his notebooks, he may
even have experimented with such devices.
Some time later, the French philosopher René
Descartes exchanged instructive letters with Père
Mersenne on the question of "whether the art of
flying is possible . . . and if men can fly as high, as
far and as fast as birds	"
The French fantasist Cyrano de Bergerac
devised "six ways of violating the virgin skies".
The Marquis de Bacqueville donned wings to
try to fly across the Seine, and Father Gallien
surmised that "the art of aerial navigation" might
lie in letting oneself be carried along on "air-
rafts" by currents (jet-streams, perhaps?) "at the
altitude where hail forms".
INGENIOUS FLYING MACHINES
Oddly enough, all these precursors of flight came
up with the same prescription: all that was
required was to devise "an ingenious mecha¬
nism". The formula crops up again and again, but
is never accompanied by further details. As early
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Above, an effigy of Icarus
at the Lemon Festival at
Menton on the French
Riviera.
Left, a fleet of spaceships
as imagined by the science-
fiction illustrator Julien
Baum.
Below, an illustration from
a contemporary French
magazine shows America's
pioneer aviators, the
Wright Brothers, taking
flight.
as 1250, the English philosopher Roger Bacon
suggested that "Flying machines could be con¬
structed in which men, seated or suspended in the
centre, could turn cranks that would operate
wings to beat the air."-'
The project was in the air. . . . Everyone was
talking about it except scientists.
In 1782, an influential and respected mathe¬
matician and astronomer by the name of Joseph
Jerome de Lalande, a member of the French
Academy, affirmed that "if men of learning keep
silent, it is not through contempt. Rather it is
demonstrably impossible, in every sense, that a
man could rise into, or even stay up in, the air. . . .
Only an ignoramus would try to do so."
In 1783, Pilâtre de Rozier answered him by
taking off on the first balloon flight, accompanied
by the Marquis d'Arlandes.
Soon Victor Hugo was enthusing:
And Newton 's science flies away
Riding a Pindaric odeP
Writers, scientists and engineers such as
Nadar, Jules Verne, Mouillard, Caylcy, Marey
and Lilienthal made calculations, speculations,
experiments.
In 1 890, Clement Ader became airborne. The
aircraft had taken off at last. In their monoplanes
and biplanes, pilots were no longer floating but
flying. They had been a long time on the drawing
board, these flying machines!
One pioneer aviator, the French engineer
Gabriel Voisin, pointed out that "heavier-than-air
flight does not start with anything as clever as the
wheel. Its inspiration is the wing, rather as if,
instead of relying on wheels for land transport, we
had developed a vehicle with mechanical legs."
Jean Cocteau repeated the remark to me, going on
to add: "Wings arc growing shorter and starting
to disappear altogether. They are turning into
fins. The bird is becoming a fish." There you
have the history of aeronautical engineering in a
nutshell!
After the Wright Brothers, the pioneers gave
way to the sportsmen. Then it was the warrior's
turn. Considerable advances were made in avia¬
tion between 1914 and 1918. With the return of
peace, further progress was made in exploring the
planet. Oceans and mountains were conquered.
Records were broken.
A danger remained. As early as 1759, Samuel
Johnson had written: "If men were all virtuous
... I should with great alacrity teach them all to
fly." A second world war intervened, crueller,
more frightening, more modern than its pre¬
decessor. But aircraft arc not to blame for all the
harm humankind has done with them. Instead,
reflect on Charles Lindbergh's words:
"Hiroshima was as far from the intention of
the pure scientist as the Inquisition was from the
Sermon on the Mount".
Progress continued to be made, to the benefit
of civil aviation, which became safer. With the first
jets, the power of engines increased threefold. It
was time to take another step forward and, as the
French poet Jules Supervielle put it, "to colo¬
nize the stars".
A NEW DIMENSION
Is transient modernity anything more than a
matter of scene-shifting? Time has already lost
much of its importance and distance is a dated
concept. We have conquered a new dimension.
Should we not call it a new freedom? As Jules Roy
has noted, "the speed a spaceship must attain to
escape the Earth's gravity is called escape
velocity."'1
Have we finally escaped, and if so from what?
In continuing down the road that has led from the
prehistoric age of Gagarin to the glorious present
promised for tomorrow, fresh questions arise.
Are there boundaries to space? Is the sky the
limit?
Here on Earth, there is no cause for alarm as
long as speeds can still be measured in relation to
the speed of sound. It will be time to start wor¬
rying when people start talking about the speed
of light. But by then robots may have taken the
place of human beings.
1. Saint-John Perse, L'Ordre des Oiseaux, Gallimard
publishers, Paris, 1972.
2. Roger Bacon, De Opcribus Sccretis Artis et Naturae,
1250.
3. Victor Hugo, La Légende des siècles, 1883.
4. Edmond Petit, Le Ciel et ses poètes, preface by Jules
Roy, Le Cherche Midi publishers, Paris, 1992. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
GOING TOO FRR
/
/
\
!
\
ï
> <fT7\
20
Between Leonardo's time
and the age of the computer, the nature
of the image has profoundly changed.
Strange though it may seem, the
transition to a world overflowing with
electronic images may signal the end of
a culture based on the
act of seeing.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The devalued image
by Sonia Younan
Opposite, a study of
drapery Leonardo da Vinci
made for his painting The
Virgin and Child with St.
Anne.
Below, in an artificial-
reality demonstration, the
operative makes lights
come on in the windows of
skyscrapers by pointing to
them on the screen.
IN times gone by, images were drawn, engraved
or painted on a physical support, in an enclosed
space which took on meaning from the pro¬
jection onto it of the latent physical attributes of
the subject depicted. The way in which this space
was organized had its roots in a physical,
Dionysiac quality which situated it in time and
thereby linked it to music, to what Nietzsche
called that "total dance whose rhythm stirs the
whole body." In The Birth ofTragedy, the German
philosopher described all the plastic arts as aspiring
to the condition of music, which is pure sym¬
bolism and is independent of either image or con¬
cept. The plastic arts are merely the projection of
what he called "sparks of imagery", the draping of
the Apollonian veil of beauty around the subject.
The Dionysiac principle is one of communion
and fusion with the whole universe. The artist
must triumph over subjectivity, find deliverance
from the self, and become the vector of cosmic
energies. It is through this process of "unserving"
that the wisdom of art is attained.
The whole of a picture bears the imprint of the
body and its mystery. In Leonardo's magnifi¬
cent draperies, the body is suggested by inden¬
tations, its very absence enabling it to orchestrate
even more effectively the Apollonian display of
draperies and highlights. What is shown is less
significant than what is left in shadow. The lines
take on meaning only insofar as they condense
the temporal nature of the painter's gesture,
because they exist as music before being pro¬
jected into the spatial dimension. In a corre¬
sponding fashion, the movement of the viewer's
eye as it "browses on the canvas" unlocks many
meanings. In his Theory ofModern Art, the Swiss
painter Paul Klee stresses the idea of the work of
art as genesis and describes the trajectory of cre¬
ation in this way: "The first movement in us,
the active, operative movement, directed towards
the work of art, and then the transmission to
others, to the viewers, of the movement con¬
tained in the picture." A snapshot appears to us
less truthful than a painting precisely because it
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
is cut off from this two-way process that takes
place over a period of time.
THE AESTHETICS
OF BANALITY
What has happened? Apollo has lost touch with
Dionysus. Space has become dissociated from the
body whence meaning could emerge. Machines
have taken over from the eye of the beholder.
Disconnected from the ways in which subjects are
perceived, images are no longer defined in relation
to reality but in relation to one another.
In hyperrealism, painting has found a high-
definition style of its own. In the words of one
hyperrealist painter, "photography is not the last
word in realism" nor is reality itself, one might
add, as the hauntingly accurate detail in this form
of painting confirms. Richard Estes' paintings,
worked up from dozens of different photographs,
recreate urban landscapes caught in the inter¬
play of multiple reflections and frames. They
show us what the human eye could never see,
such as an image reflected in a shop window and
an object inside the window both rendered with
the same degree of definition. Hyperrealism,
with its sharp focus and flattened perspective,
presents a smooth, uniform painted surface that
calls for no effort of the imagination. The frontal,
rectilinear gaze of the camera lens has taken the
place of the eye, with its curving field of vision and
its aura of possibilities. By interposing between
spectator and subject a series of technological
intermediaries, it destroys the original status of the
subject, which becomes the mere adjunct of a
piece of viewing apparatus. Is it fortuitous that the
painter's signature is often reversed, one more
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
A scene from Nick's Movie
(1 979- 1 980), the film Wim
Wenders made with the
American director
Nicholas Ray near the end
of Ray's life.
reflection among others? The painters of the
Renaissance endeavoured to recreate a humane
vision of the world, portrayed in depth, where
light emerged from shade, a vision in which
necessity had its place, a fragile conquest snatched
from the jaws of a universally prevalent contin¬
gency. Driven by an obsessive desire for trans¬
parency, hyperrealism teaches us that there is
nothing below the surface, in short that there is
nothing to sec.
When perception is dissociated from imagi¬
nation, we are left with banality, tautology, liter¬
alism. The psychoanalyst Sami Ali describes
banality as "the end of projection", "the disap¬
pearance of all emotive assocations", the absence
of an inside/outside polarity. "It is a 'reality' that
is both immediate and final," he claims, "cut off
from the historical process of which it is the cul
mination and no longer bearing in itself any trace
of the labour of negation". When temporality is
eclipsed by an absolute positivity, and imagina¬
tion the faculty of saying no is taken away, wc
are left in a situation where everything is
reversible, where copies outrank originals, the vir¬
tual is indistinguishable from the actual, and
reality is no more than a special effect.
A SURFEIT OF IMAGES
An intricate web of relationships has been woven
between the different types of image produced by
painting, photography, the cinema, video and
computer graphics. This rivalry and this mutual
fascination are illustrated in the films of the
German director Wim Wenders, for example in
the relationship between Jonathan and Ripley
in The American Friend. Jonathan, a picture
framer, lives in a workshop filled with the smells
and materials of his craft and in the ambit of the
painterly culture, based on the act of seeing. In
one scene he is the only person at an auction
who spots subtle differences of shades of blue that
reveal some of the works to be fakes. He is the
embodiment of the Apollonian ideal of the Beau¬
tiful, that of the circumscribed, the sober outline,
the frame. With Ripley, the American friend of the
title, we arc taken into the realm of the immate¬
rial, an unchecked flow of symbols, of specula¬
tion. A parallel is suggested between money, the
generalized form of commodities, and images, the
generalized forms of reality. Ripley is defined
only through external symbolism, through the
objects that surround him. At one point he takes
Polaroid photographs of himself lying on a pool
table; eventually the proliferating images cover his
whole body. The death of the original is con¬
summated in the triumph of the copies. Else¬
where we see him taping himself and later playing
back the recording, as though his self-awareness
can only be sustained by means of the fragile
traces recorded by a machine. Ripley, a post¬
modern character, finally draws Jonathan into
his own ambit, that of the sublime reduced to the
level of the quantitative. The turning-point of
the film is marked by a shot ofJonathan smashing
a picture frame in his workshop. The smashing of
the frame symbolizes the relentless onward rush
towards the limitless, the sea, death	
Restoring to images their innocence	 In his
book The Act ofSeeing, Wim Wenders discovers
in seeing the possibility of latent truth that is
"obscured by words, by past events, by opinion."
This return to true perception, unencumbered by
judgements and opinions, is close to the idea,
advocated by phenomenology, of getting back to
things in themselves. It means learning to see
things with the eyes of childhood again. This
possibility tends, however, to disappear as the
number of images we arc exposed to increases.
High-definition systems allow images to be
reproduced ad infinitum without any loss of
clarity and with unlimited possibilities for manip¬
ulation. Digitized and insubstantial, the high-
definition image does not deteriorate like a film 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Grand Luncheonette (1969),
a painting by the American
artist Richard Estes.
24
SONIA YOUNAN
is an Egyptian philosophy
teacher, painter and art critic.
She has published many articles
and has made a short film, Elle
comme Lens (1979).
negative. It makes the concept of "originality"
entirely meaningless, and the special effects to
which it is subjected leave no trace.
Wim Wenders wants to make the cinema a
focal point of resistance to this loss of meaning.
"The cinema," he writes, "must represent, for
each image, a last bastion of this sense of the
image." The transition from a pictorial culture to
the "era of technical reproduction", to repro¬
ductions of works of art, to photography, the
cinema and finally the electronic image, has been
responsible for an increase in the quantity of
images that constitutes "one of the most serious
sicknesses of our civilization".
The cinema has a memory of its own, its own
highly-developed language. To quote Wenders
"cinematographic language is a powerful
medium that leaves its imprint on everything it
produces". Video is easier to handle and more
spontaneous but lacks this "capacity for taking
shape". Its language is basic: instead of con¬
structing a diachronic development it breaks time
down into a succession of instants, and it aban¬
dons the cinematic pan shot in favour of the
close-up. The relationship between film and
video is the same as that between an original and
a copy. The proliferation of video images is indeed
a disease, a malignant tumour that thrives to the
detriment of organic growth. In Nick's Movie,
Wenders shot the cancer-stricken Nicholas Ray
in video because video seemed to him like a
cancer within the film itself. Hence, in order to
check the progress of a disease that the French
sociologist Jean Baudrillard has called "the con¬
tamination of things by the virus of images", and
their "unlimited pullulation", the video image
must be reinserted into the cinematic framework,
marked with its imprint, filled out with the
organic quality, the meaning and the memory
that it presently lacks.
ABSORBED BY THE 'BLOTTING
PAPER' OF THE SCREEN
In his critique of Wagner, Nietzsche poured scorn
on the signs of a modernity that sought to attain
the infinite grandeur of the sublime but only
succeeded in achieving the ultimate in triviality,
that of sound reduced to its component parts,
bereft of all organic linkage. The decline from the
sublime to the quantitative is paralleled by the
way in which the new technology of the image
absorbs us so that image and viewer become one
and actually causes our perception to regress by
eliminating the distance that is an integral part of
our way of seeing.
" Wc used to stand in front of the image, now
we are inside the visual environment." In Vie et
mort de l'image, une histoire du regard en Occi¬
dent, Régis Debray stresses the the importance of
the clement of distance in visual perception.
"Seeing," he writes, "means standing back from
the thing seen, distancing oneself, cutting oneself
off." The perception of sound is more archaic; lis¬
tener and sound become one. In the world of
the audiovisual media, seeing undergoes annex¬
ation by listening, "visual noise" is superimposed
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
upon audio noise. "The visual environment has
virtually become a sound environment." Wc are
caught up in a process of absorption, in what
the French critic Paul Virilio has called the "blot¬
ting paper" effect of the screen.
The omnipresence of images and the speed
with which they are transmitted relieve us of the
necessity to imagine an elsewhere, to project our
thoughts through time and space. Everything is
here and now; everything comes to us without
our having to go anywhere. The cult of live
transmission, immediacy and the close-up con¬
spire to make us believe we are in direct contact
with events; but as Marshall McLuhan has taught
us, the medium is the message, events are indis¬
sociable from the trace they leave, and the only
present is the presence of the image. Removed
from the opaque order of visible culture, the
image has been subjugated by the strategy of
communication and promoted for its own sake,
regardless of any meaningful content.
To prevent the imagination from crumpling
under the impact of high-speed transmission and
to restore to images their lost innocence, we need
to disconnect image from sound which is no
longer recorded on separate tracks as in the cinema.
We must halt the flow of images, and resist the
seductive power of immediacy. If we do, perhaps
we shall witness the return of what Wenders calls
the truth potential. It takes time for meaning to
come across. In Proust's great novel A la recherche
du temps perdu, the taste of a small cake a
madeleine brings back buried memories from the
past, a past relived as the present. Images only
take on meaning again when they arc related to our
own mental images, integrated into our own time¬
frame, vibrating in sympathy with our bodies,
the storehouse of our memories the body, what
Nietzsche called our "great reason".
THE MYSTERY
OF APPEARANCES
In Michelangelo Antonioni's film Blow-up, the
plot revolves around a photograph taken in a
London park. When the photo is developed it
reveals a dead body that Thomas, the photogra¬
pher, had not noticed when he took it. The eye of
the camera captures something that remained
invisible to the naked eye. But Thomas then
decides to blow the image up bigger and bigger,
and again the mystery eludes us. By dint of
zooming in closer and closer we are left with the
meaningless mosaic of the grain of the film, as
meaningless as the grain of Albcrtine's skin is to
the narrator in Proust's novel. The pervasive use
of close-ups and the zoom lens drags us down
into what Baudrillard calls the "blank obscenity"
of a transparent universe. "Where docs this crazy
idea come from," he asks, "the idea of being able
to reveal the secret, to expose the naked sub¬
stance, to touch the ultimate obscenity? The idea
itself is Utopian there is no reality, there never
has been; the power to allure lies in realizing this
and preserving the mystery."
In order to rediscover the allure of appear
ances, to guard against "blank obscenity", the
mystery of the body needs to be reinvented. In
The Draughtsman's Contract, by Peter Green-
away, the English film director and painter, the
architectural drawings of a country house play a
part in the plot, like Leonardo's draperies, giving
depth to the cinematographic image. They cannot
be deciphered as a poster can; they yield up the
memory of past events in minute doses. The
murder clues are revealed through a subtle inter¬
play of appearances and disappearances. The
time-frame of the film and the logic of its plot are
organized around the drawings, and the true
mystery is the one played out in the arrange¬
ment of lines, values and chiaroscuro. Works of
art, as the German philosopher Martin Heidegger
says, always hold themselves "in reserve". The
painter meets his death perhaps because he dis¬
covered the murderer but more certainly because
he was unable to preserve the mystery of appear¬
ances, the innocence of images.
DIGITAL FEVER
In the beginning was the digit; the Word became
software and dwelt among us, to adapt the
French writer René Bergers phrase. Video, com¬
puter graphics, holograms the new visual tech¬
nologies detach themselves from the familiar
forms of our perception and hitch themselves to
Joan of Aragon, by Raphaël
and his studio.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
digits. Computer-generated images usher in the
age of simulation, where virtual reality prevails
over reality itself.
The relationship between art and these tech¬
nologies is a problematical one. Whereas the
artist's approach sidesteps conceptualizations,
digging below the specificities of the real world
to capture the totality of experience, digital
imaging does the opposite, making the specific a
fall-out from the idea of the universal. The artist
becomes a computer operator, and the transcen¬
dency of the work of art implodes somewhere in
the networks. As Michel Jaffrenou has pointed
out, "the proliferation of networks, that spider's
web that is being spun around the whole world,
that fluidity that is seeping into all communica¬
tion, means that works created on screens can be
fed into circuits, circulate through them and
return almost immediately to the sender, trans¬
formed, interpreted and ready to go out again."
Moving and having their being in an intangible
environment, absorbed into the networks, manip¬
ulated in the course of interactive communication,
produced in real time, images arc turning their
backs on human beings and looking at one
another.
26
THE WISDOM OF LOVE VERSUS
THE WISDOM OF THE IMAGE
Other people reveal themselves to us above all
through the expression in their eyes. This does not
add any new significance to the image perceived
by the senses; indeed, it emerges only if and when
that image is destroyed. The endless fascination
of the Mona Lisa reminds us how a gaze can
convey the mystery of another person we are so
captivated by her gaze that we cannot look at her.
The painting itself fades away, disappears, leaving
behind the pure presence of another being. Who
remembers the colour of the Mona Lisa's eyes?
Another person's gaze is unbearable. The
narrator of A la recherche du temps perdu not
only keeps Albertine prisoner but can only tol¬
erate her when she is asleep, because, as he says,
at such times her "personality no longer slipped
away all the time, as it did when we were talking,
through the channels of unacknowledged
thoughts and looks. At such times, she seemed to
have called back all that part of herself that was
outside; she had taken refuge, enclosed and sim¬
plified, within her body." The eyes are the channel
through which the personality escapes and
through which it must return. "Those closed
eyelids," Proust tells us, "laid on her face that per¬
fect continuity unbroken by the eyes."
The proliferation of images is the sign of a civ¬
ilization that has forgotten how to see, that erases
all forms of otherness, a culture "with closed eye¬
lids". Our response to the lure of an act of seeing
that kept a distance between pcrceiver and per¬
ceived, to a love directed towards "the mystery of
the Other", to the transcendency of an art that pre¬
served the aura of original works, is to rush head¬
long into the banal strategies of the image.
m »,:*< -
The apple of my eye
by Nissim Merkado
NISSIM MERKADO
is a French artist and art teacher whose work has been
exhibited in a number of countries, including France,
Belgium and Bulgaria.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
^ÏPPLES, green, yellow and red. Colours	
I have placed the red apple on the ground to
paint it. The ground is ochre, the colour of
scorched earth. There is a contrast. Consistent
and indelible, oils are best for getting close to
nature. Pigments.
The smell of oils is not that of the colour of
the apple. Energy of the senses.
"Energy" is a word that crops up often.
Nothing is certain. I went away for a
moment, and my absence made itself felt in the
silence, a unifying factor: "poly-presence".
Painting, watching colours appear on a flat
surface. A black line weaves around the colours,
which are obstinately pressed up against one
another. Chance.
Everything around gives off vibrations. The
apple is fixed in the retina, but its colour vibrates
somewhere else.
Watching the silhouette of the main object
taking form. The apple is white on a white back¬
ground. Barely visible. . . .
Apples are eaten. Apples rot.
Cézanne proved that there is more to apples
than that: there is beauty in them. The consis¬
tency of the colour builds up the object's
"unique" form a kind of magic whose power
can be transmitted and can be converted from
one material to another.
Physical sensation is consumed, like energy.
A painting, 50.7 x 73.5 centimetres.
Colour has a molecular structure, it reflects
light equally for two bodies whose basic iden¬
tity differs materially. The similarity between the
red skin of the apple and the colour of blood is
artificial. When removed from any convention
relating to form and given its freedom, colour
enters the realm of universal abstract thought.
The tree on which the apple grows is empty.
The sun shrinks in volume. Seen through
an electron microscope, the pips of an apple
contain a sequence of memories that have not
been decoded.
With the aid of X-rays, one can see that the
artist sketched and painted in the pips before
covering them over with green paint. Memory
is something else again.
Photo by Pascal Rieu.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The more generation
by Reginald Fraser Amonoo
THE aims of industry and commerce in
today's world are to create more wealth
and a wealthier population. Improved
means of production have brought about over¬
production and fierce international competi¬
tion. While the mechanization of agriculture,
mass production on factory assembly lines,
robotization and computerization have
increased productivity, they have also saturated
markets with surplus products. Europe, floun¬
dering in its milk lake, has to sell off its goods at
cut price, whilst the United States and Japan
are producing too much steel and turning out
too many cars. Even the computer industry,
following a period of expansion, is marking
time. The social costs of overproduction
reduced profits, business failures, factory clo¬
sures, unemployment, whole sectors of the
»8 M
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Right, an advertising
billboard in Lagos
(Nigeria).
Below, a computer
assembly line in Germany.
economy in disarray, whole regions turned into
disaster areas are considerable. The Third
World too is affected, as overproduction results
in a disastrous fall in world commodity prices.
The need to find buyers for these super¬
abundant goods accounts for one of the major
phenomena of modern times, the power of
advertising, now an industry in its own right,
buttressed by the growth of the mass media
television, film, video and home teletext termi¬
nals as well as press advertisements and bill¬
boards. The media dangle before consumers the
prospect of an escape from prosaic reality, a dif
ferent, compensatory view of life. The stars of
Hollywood and show business, who with their
extravagant life-styles have taken the place of the
kings and conquering heroes of times gone by,
entice an adoring public with glimpses of a
world of dreams and fantasy, where every pas¬
sion can be satisfied. There is also an infatuation
with the extraordinary, which explains the pop¬
ularity of sports champions, whose feats provide
copy for specialized publications and the record-
books and who cash in on their achievements by
featuring in advertisements.
In a context of overproduction, any means, 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
REGINALD FRASER
AMONOO,
of Ghana, ¡s a visiting professor
at the University of Zimbabwe.
A specialist in French 17th-
century theatre and language
problems in Africa, he is the
author of many articles and a
study on Language and
Nationhood: Reflections on
Language Situations, with
particular reference to Ghana
(Ghana Academy of Arts and
Sciences, Accra, 1989).
A young motorcyclist in a
village in Niger.
legal or otherwise, must be used to attract poten¬
tial clients. Anything goes: unfair competition,
industrial fraud, infringement of patents, indus¬
trial espionage or whatever. Advertising goes
all out to whet the consumer's appetite, even
resorting to deceit. Every product is presented
as the best, the most competitively priced, the
most efficient. All kinds of hype are used.
Advertisers will stop at nothing to get their
message across, including the exploitation of
feminine charms. If customers are short of ready
cash, they are offered easy terms, at least to start
with. They may even be offered a car they can
drive away without having to put any money
down, with a free tankful of petrol thrown in.
THE LURE
OF
EASY MONEY
Are the developing countries affected by this
phenomenon? I believe they are. There is, for
example, nothing new about young Africans'
infatuation with imported goods after all, trade
with the early European explorers was based on
Africans' taste for luxury goods from abroad.
The remarkable thing is the way in which this
infatuation has spread to broad sectors of the
African population since the Second World War.
Several factors have been at work here. In
Ghana, for instance, as air travel became more
common in the 1940s and 1950s, the fact of
having visited England, London in particular, or
having studied in Europe conferred special status
30
on the happy few, in the eyes of the vast majority
of their compatriots who had never left the
country. They were known as the been-to, and
with their higher social standing they set the
fashion, especially among the young.
To a certain extent, a desire for higher social
status and material prosperity also motivated the
struggle for political emancipation. What could
once only be gained through education and
this was hard to come by could now be
obtained through success in politics, whatever
one's educational level. A new kind of politician,
brought to power by a succession of coups
d'état, appeared on the scene, replacing one
privileged class by another.
Lastly, the lure of easy money and an affluent
life-style has attracted many young Africans
into occasional dealing in imported luxury
goods. These small traders who travel back¬
wards and forwards between West Africa on
the one hand and Europe and the United States
on the other make no appreciable contribution
to their countries' economies.
A variety of small-scale drug traffickers
follow the same route there is now an under¬
ground market for drugs in Africa. The risks are
enormous but the profits to be made are very
tempting. The consumers are obviously after
bigger kicks than they can get from more
innocuous stimulants; in other words they too
are out for more. Drug abuse is not necessarily
a modern phenomenon, but its spread is some¬
thing new. The incidents that have occurred in
some universities and even some secondary
schools, as well as among some of the soldiers
involved in military coups, show that drug-
taking is starting to spread among the young.
THE HIGH LIFE
In many ways, therefore, a growing number of
Africans, traders, traffickers, adventurers
internationalized Africans, so to speak have an
attitude towards the consumer society that
scarcely differs from that prevalent in the United
States or Europe. The taste for luxuries, for
consumer goods for the high life, in short
evident in the countries of the North has its
counterpart in the countries of the South, with
this difference, that its consequences, given the
deprivation that afflicts most of our fellow-
countrymen, are much worse. The spread, in
some cases the prevalence, of this constant
seeking after more is one of the hallmarks of
modern times.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
<-.
yÀ
a
The spare parts syndrome
by Bernard Teo
Above, a liver transplant
operation in a Paris
hospital.
BERNARD TEO,
of the Republic of Singapore,
has been teaching moral
theology and bioethics at the
Yarra Theological Union in
Melbourne (Australia) since
1991.
NE of the marvels of modern medicine is its
ability to repair people's lost or impaired
bodily functions with artificial devices
such as the pace-maker, the hearing aid, pow¬
ered limb prostheses and the dialysis machine.
Organ transplantation represents a further step
along this ingenious path. For patients suffering
from vital organ diseases, organ transplantation
may offer the only hope of survival.
The capacity to repair human beings brings
out the best in us. Unless we take care, however,
it may also bring out the worst our capacity to
fragment ourselves and our communities, and
our propensity to exploit and to dehumanize.
Provided that there is a scrupulous regard
for ethics in transplantation, the repairable human
can be a powerful symbol of our shared humanity,
adaptability and global interdependence, for suc¬
cess in organ transplantation would be impossible
without national and international co-operation
and exchange. To take one example, the devel
opment and widespread use of powerful
immunosuppressives, which are crucial to the
success of any transplant programme, are possible
only because of international collaboration and
a sense of compassion for the sick.
Organ transplantation differs from other
kinds of health care in that it depends upon full
participation by the community. A government
may legislate ethically sound transplant policies
and commit sufficient resources to ensure the
success of a transplant programme, but its efforts
will be doomed to failure if the public is unwilling
to donate organs and provide support.
Many countries have adopted policies to
ensure fair public access to donated organs, in
recognition of a demand that factors such as ability
to pay, race, gender, social status or religious beliefs
should not be barriers to anyone who really needs
a transplant. If a transplant programme is per¬
ceived by the public as denigrating a person's
humanity, or as introducing values that divide the 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Community, public goodwill and support in the
form of donated organs may come to a halt.
However, there is a great danger that trans¬
plant technology may encourage the objec-
tivization of the human being into a mere col¬
lection of body parts, subject to exploitation for
consumerist and utilitarian purposes.
Proposals to allow commerce in human body
parts constitute a fundamental attack on human
dignity and identity. To turn human body parts
into exchangeable commodities is to alienate a
person from his or her bodily life and under¬
mine human dignity and identity. The humani¬
tarian and communitarian foundation of organ
transplantation would be corrupted by such a
consumerist approach.
Trade in human body parts would also frag¬
ment the community, since it would transform
communal relationships into those of contractual
buying and selling; the poor would be exploited
while the wealthy would be able to buy their
way onto the priority list of transplant candi¬
dates. It would also undermine international
goodwill. It is well known that wealthy transplant
candidates from richer countries are in a position
to purchase organs from the poor in poorer coun¬
tries, often under exploitative conditions, and
that the poor are brought to the wealthier coun¬
tries to complete the commercial transactions.
Such practices not only shift the problems of
wealthier nations onto poorer ones, but also strip
the poor of their dignity by turning them into
commodities. There is an urgent need for inter¬
national co-operation to deal with these problems.
Governments should make policies to control
the situation, and impose penalties on their
nationals who cross international boundaries to
purchase organs from the poor. Those involved
in transplant programmes should also screen
patients and organ donors more thoroughly
before beginning any procedure.
Above all, the repairable human may reflect
an extremely myopic view of life: an aggressive
preoccupation with the preservation of our bodily
life, regardless of the financial and human costs,
points to an inability or refusal to confront the
reality of human mortality and to address the
question of whether the full meaning of human
existence may not be more than the preserva¬
tion of life as we know it.
Automating artificial limbs
in Haifa (Israel).
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
IWJJJ
THE UNESCO COURIER JULY/AUGUST 1993
THE DM) SOU <
m
ccoRDiNG to forecasts by the
United Nations Environ¬
ment Programme (UNEP),
if world energy consump¬
tion were to continue at its
.1990 level, oil reserves
would last 46 years, coal reserves
205 years and natural gas reserves
67 years. In addition, the produc¬
tion and use of these fossil fuels
are responsible for a constant
increase in water, soil and above
all atmospheric pollution by
nitrogen oxides, sulphur and
methane. The amount of carbon
dioxide, which stood at about 6.3
billion tons in 1988, could double
by the year 2010. "By the end of
the 1980s," writes Mostapha K.
Tolba, former Executive Director
of UNEP in his book Saving our
Planet (1992), "it had become
clear that current trends in energy
consumption especially of fossil
fuels could lead to increased
degradation of the global envi¬
ronment (from, for example, acid
rain, urban air pollution and cli¬
mate change), undermining
future development and well-
being across the planet."
Presented as a "clean" form of
energy, nuclear energy raised high
hopes, promising cheap and
abundant electricity. But the
Chernobyl accident, aging power
stations and the build-up of toxic
wastes that are difficult to process
soon cooled people's enthusiasm.
In addition, this form of energy
production is far too expensive
and technologically too onerous
for the developing countries.
Although they are not high on
the political or economic agenda,
probably because oil is cheap, the
so-called renewable energies
solar electricity, biomass, wind
energy, ocean energy have not
been as successful as they deserve.
And so Unesco has decided to
organize this year an international
conference on renewable energy
sources, the World Solar Summit.
The term solar is used symboli¬
cally to designate the different
renewable sources ofenergy. The
meeting, which will take place at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris
from 5 to 9 luly 1993 in close co¬
operation with relevant organi¬
zations, is designed as a summit of
experts.
The logo of the
World Solar
Summit
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
mi
IE DU SOLI Sill
m
A group of high-level special¬
ists will assess solar energy devel¬
opment in the two decades since
a conference was last held on the
subject by Unesco in 1973. They
will also explore the future of
renewable energy resources and
will consider the launching of a
World Solar Energy Decade (1995-
2005). The major objective, how¬
ever, will be to formulate a World
Plan ofAction to develop and use
renewable energy resources effec¬
tively.
The moment has come to assess
the state of political and techno¬
logical progress in this field and to
highlight the many advantages
renewable energy sources offer for
the environment, sustainable
development, health, cleaner
industry, a higher degree ofenergy
security and self-sufficiency for
nations. Research and develop¬
ment must be encouraged without
neglecting the socio-cultural and
educational aspects of the use of
solar energy which could change
our way of life. This mission
Unesco, within its fields of com¬
petence, is ready to undertake.
F..B.
34
Solar panels
provide energy
to power a
refrigerator at a
clinic in
Morocco
(above) and to
pump water in
Mali (top).
Left, bathers
soak in warm
water ejected
from the
geothermal
power station at
Svartsengi
(Iceland). The
waste water is
reputed to have
curative
properties,
particularly for
people suffering
from psoriasis, a
skin disease.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
DOSSIER
DOIT iffl
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
July 2893. A fleet of boats car¬
rying participants to a climate
conference unloads its pas¬
sengers directly onto the
twenty-sixth floor of the
United Nations building in
New York. The meeting is being held
too late. As a result of global
warming the polar ice caps have
melted and the sea level has risen to
the point that the twenty-sixth floor
windows are now on the water level.
This scene was described some
years ago in a United Nations peri¬
odical in an attempt to sound the
alarm about global warming.
Although wildly exaggerated, it is
part of a scenario linked to the
greenhouse effect which has
alarmed not only the inhabitants
of low-lying islands such as the Mal¬
dives in the Indian Ocean, but also
those of the Netherlands, where
land reclaimed from the sea is pro¬
tected by dunes and dikes. The
effects of such a scenario would also
threaten Bangladesh, the Nile Delta,
the east coast of the United States
and all flat coastal regions a par¬
ticularly serious prospect since 70
per cent of the world's population
lives less than 60 km from the sea.
What exactly is the greenhouse
effect which has been so much
written about in the last few years
and has caused such widespread
dismay? This is how the problem
has been described so far. Radia¬
tion from the Sun penetrates the
atmosphere and warms the Earth's
surface, which then radiates some
of the heat it receives back towards
space. Some of this heat, which is
vital for life on Earth and keeps
water from freezing, escapes, but
some is trapped as if by the glass
panes of a greenhouse by gases of
which there is an increasing build¬
up in the atmosphere such as
carbon dioxide, methane, nitrous
oxide, chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)
and tropospheric (low-altitude)
ozone. Edward Goldsmith, who
founded the British magazine The
Ecologist twenty years ago, believes
that atmospheric carbon dioxide
concentration has increased by 25
per cent since the beginning of the
industrial era, that the methane
Dolphins over
New York
(1974), by the
Argentine artist
Nicolas Uriburu.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
DOSSIER
concentration has doubled, and
that nitrous oxide and tropospheric
ozone concentrations are increasing
by 0.5 per cent each year.
In their book The Earth Report,
Edward Goldsmith and Nicholas
Hildyard describe the greenhouse
effect as "the most serious environ¬
mental problem facing the planet.
There is some disagreement whether
or not the rise in global temperature
of0.5° Centigrade in the last century
is due to global warming caused by
human activities or is a natural cli¬
matic fluctuation. However, it is
almost unanimously agreed among
climatologists that immediate action
to curb global warming is needed".
Goldsmith and Hildyard also quote
former British Prime Minister Mar¬
garet Thatcher as saying in March
1989 that "major changes in the
chemistry of the Earth's atmosphere
are taking place, with potentially
calamitous effects for mankind."
The alarmist remarks of environ¬
mentalists have thus been echoed
by politicians who in some cases
have gone so far as to compare the
greenhouse effect with a world
nuclear war.
FROM CERTAINTIES
TO DOUBTS
But is it possible that the certain¬
ties of 1989 have become improb¬
able hypotheses in 1993? Palaeocli-
matologists who study ice,
sediments, rocks, coral and the
trunks of ancient trees, admit that
they cannot calculate the tempera¬
ture of the Earth as it was 2,000 years
ago. The planet experiences climatic
cycles that are alternately hot and
humid and cold and dry. But
although a rise of 0.5°C has been
recorded in the second half of this
century (i.e., since precise temper
ature measurements began to be
made), peaking in the 1980s, no-one
today is prepared to state categori¬
cally that this provides incontro¬
vertible proofofglobal warming, or
that global warming is due to human
activities, since no-one knows what
happened before humankind
appeared on the scene. Gérard Lam¬
bert, a member of the Intergovern
mental Panel on Climate Change
(IPCC) set up by the United Nations,
says, "We know that the factors
encouraging the greenhouse effect
are increasing. We can measure the
atmospheric concentrations of
carbon dioxide, methane and CFCs.
We model the rest, but however
powerful our computers are, no
model is capable ofcopying nature."
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The greenhouse
effect.
The Intergovernmental Confer¬
ence on the World Climate Pro¬
gramme, which was held in Geneva
(Switzerland) from 14 to 16 April
1993, also yielded some surprises.
The meeting was co-sponsored by
the World Meteorological Organi¬
zation (WMO), the United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP),
the Food and Agriculture Organi¬
zation of the United Nations (FAO),
Unesco, the International Council of
Scientific Unions (ICSU), the United
Nations Development Programme
(UNDP) and the International
Océanographie Commission (IOC).
Entitled "The Climate Agenda", the
meeting reviewed, a year after the
Rio Conference, the current situa¬
tion with regard to the socio-eco¬
nomic impact of climate change
resulting from the greenhouse
effect. The 400 participants from
some 140 countries took note of
one obvious point. "Climate pre¬
diction," says one of the Conference
documents, "is a complex under¬
taking which is hindered by the gaps
in our knowledge. . . . Knowledge
of climatic processes must be deep¬
ened and we must improve obser¬
vation of the atmosphere, the
oceans, ice and the land areas of
the planet." All the speakers insisted
on the need to intensify research in
these fields.
COULD THE GREENHOUSE EFFECT
BE BENEFICIAL?
While the industrialized coun¬
tries already have satellite, rocket
and land-based observation facili¬
ties, as well as computerized cli¬
mate modelling systems, the devel¬
oping countries generally do not
have adequate facilities for
observing the local climate and its
variations, or for collecting and
analysing meteorological data. Con¬
sequently an appeal has been
launched for the rich countries to
participate in the creation ofobser¬
vation centres in the poor coun¬
tries. A budget has even been
drafted, although nothing has been
said about where the money would
come from. Gunnar Kullenberg,
secretary of the IOC at Unesco, told
us he was sorry that no state or indi
vidual has really taken a lead on this
issue. It seems as if governments
are waiting for the United Nations
Framework Convention on Climate
Change to be ratified. This Con¬
vention, signed by 154 countries in
June 1992 at the United Nations
Conference on Environment and
Development (UNCED), must be
ratified before it can come into
force. Its ultimate goal is to "stabilize
greenhouse gas concentrations in
the atmosphere at a level that would
prevent dangerous anthropogenic
interference with the climate
system".
Observers at the Rio and Geneva
conferences were very surprised
that nothing was said about the
need to reduce the production of
greenhouse gases by reducing pol¬
lution. On the contrary, at a press
conference at which FAO was rep¬
resented by Wim Sombroek,
Director of FAO 's" Land and Water
Development Division, and by René
Gommes, Secretary of FAO's Inter¬
departmental Sub-group on Cli¬
mate Change, we heard that "cli¬
mate change could also lead to
useful modifications from which
we should be ready to draw profit:
the increase in carbon dioxide con¬
centrations could have a beneficial
effect on world food production
when world population has dou¬
bled". Carbon provides plants with
food. Several other beneficial effects
of climate change have been iden¬
tified, including increased poten¬
tial for bio-fuels and higher tem¬
peratures in temperate zones. This
revolutionary assertion must have
surprised Edward Goldsmith.
Should we conclude from it that to
have bumper harvests we should
step on the accelerator?
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD-Unhsco
training programmeforAfrican
news-agencyjournalists.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
MEASURING LEAD LEVELS
Few states publish lead emission figures. However,
according to estimates made by UNEP, human activities
produce around 332,000 tons of lead annually world¬
wide, including some 12,000 tons of natural origin
(wind-borne volcanic dust). The lead in petrol repre¬
sents only 10 per cent of all refined lead but is respon¬
sible for 60 per cent of emissions caused by human
activity. Since it is deposited 100 metres each side of the
road, it is not advisable to eat plants and mushrooms
which grow in this area.
CONTRABAND CROCODILES
In January 1993, information from the Secretariat of
the Convention on International Trade in Endangered
Species (CITES) enabled customs officers in Montevideo
(Uruguay) to seize a cargo of 29,000 caiman skins.
Loaded into a container in Colombia, they were due to
be sent to Singapore via Curaçao and Aruba (dependent
territories of the Netherlands but not covered by the
Convention). Meanwhile, the authorites in Italy seized
10,000 caiman skins also from Colombia, which had
carried through Curaçao and Colombia respec¬
tively. It's not a good idea to be a crocodile in South
America.
fcUÍAWftnUTlFUL
ptíüTrt
ROCHA ANO tí»«« R0TH
BLUE
AND BEAUTIFUL
A remarkable little children's book
entitled Blue and Beautiful: Planet
Earth, our Home was published in
1990 by the United Nations. Its
authors, Ruth Rocha and Otavio
Roth, explain through short texts
illustrated with watercolours why
the Earth should be protected. The
best reason is that there is only one
Earth in the solar system. To obtain
the book, which costs $9.95, please
write to Clara Flores, United Nations
Publications Sales Section, Room
DC2-0853, New York, NY 10017,
U.SA.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
FIRE OR FLOOD
For years the rice-growers of California's Sacramento
Valley set fire to their fields after the harvest to burn off
the remaining straw. Smoke blanketed the valley, adding
an estimated one million tons ofpollution to the atmos¬
phere annually. In 1992, environmentalists suggested
that they should flood the fields instead of burning
them. Last December, 6,000 hectares of rice were
flooded. These wetlands have become a paradise for
wintering waterfowl. In spring the water is drained into
the Sacramento River, aiding the seaward migration
of young salmon.
BOTANIC GARDENS AND BIODIVERSITY
Around half of the world's 1,600 botanic gardens are
active in conservation, maintaining facilities ranging
from seed banks containing samples of hundreds of
species to small conservation collections kept in public
gardens or greenhouses. Unfortunately, these gardens
are badly distributed. Most of them are in the world's
temperate zones, where plant diversity is less rich.
Europe has 532 gardens and about 12,000 species;
North America has 265 gardens and 20,000 species,
whereas in South America, with an estimated flora of
80,000 species, there are only 66.
LUCKY STARS?
Asterias forbesi, the common starfish, is unpopular
with fishermen. A powerful carnivore, it feasts on mus¬
sels, periwinkles, snails, scallops and oysters. But
researchers love it, since its method of feeding is unique
in the animal world it pushes its stomach out through
its mouth and envelops its prey. If one of its arms is
wounded it casts it off and grows another. It has 5 eyes,
one at the end of each arm. Another amazing charac¬
teristic is its ability to change sex experiments have
shown that sex reversal from male to female occurs in
adult specimens when there is a shortage of females.
Perhaps such a wonder of nature deserves some of our
shellfish.
A NEW LAW FOR LAKE
BAIKAL
In September 1992, Russian and
German experts took part in a con¬
sultation on draft legislation for
Lake Baikal, threatened by pollu¬
tion from cellulose factories at its
southern extremity. According to
the representative of the World Con¬
servation Union who took part in
the consultation, the law would
establish the lake as a core protected
zone surrounded by a buffer area.
Lake Baikal, which is 634 km long,
from 25 to 79 km wide (the surface
area of Belgium) and 1,637 metres
deep, contains one-fifth of the
planet's fresh water. When I visited
it, I found there was a difference of
opinion between Grigori Galazy,
the former director of the Irkutsk
Institute of Limnology, and his suc¬
cessor, Mikhail Grachev. Galazy
believes that the lake is dying as a
result ofpollution, whereas Grachev,
who would like it to be included on
UNESCO's World Heritage List, is
convinced that the lake's water is
pure, a point of view confirmed by
American scientists whom I met on
the spot. After exploring the icy
waters of the lake in a pocket sub¬
marine, they told me: "The lake is
magnificent. The purest in the
world!" Let's hope that the law pro¬
tecting this vast water reserve will be
adopted.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
GREEN til
INITIATIVES
"Initiatives"
¡s a feature
designed to
highlight
examples of
environmental
action in
different parts of
the world. We
invite readers to
send us details of
their own
experiences in
this field for
possible
publication in
the column.
Gendarmes
on an
environmental
mission at a
disused factory
(France).
40
In France the gendarmerie is going green. In
October 1992, Captain Emmanuel Bartier was
appointed chief of a new environmental sec¬
tion. He claims, however, that there is nothing
new about his mission, pointing out that "The
gendarmerie policed nature in the country¬
side as early as 1903." Certainly the gendarmerie
a military body has always been more firmly
established in the countryside than in the towns.
Although 80 per cent of its environmental work is
preventive, the number of prosecutions has also
considerably increased. Whereas 30,000 offences
involving a fine and 2,800 crimes punishable by
prison and/or a fine were recorded in 1980, the fig¬
ures had risen to 62,000 and 5,500 respectively
by 1992. In 1987 the gendarmerie distributed a
memorandum on nature and the environment
to its staff of 90,000. This 700-page "green book"
covers such subjects as air and water pollution,
nuclear energy, control of chemicals, waste,
poaching of plant and animal life and the pro
tection ofparks, and explains what action should
be taken in each case. A training session has been
arranged to inform noncommissioned officers
and teach them how to use sampling equipment.
Captain Bartier, who has been travelling to meet
his opposite numbers elsewhere in Europe, notes
that so far there is no inter-state co-ordination
despite the fact that police forces are increasingly
concerned with environmental issues. He cites
as examples Italy, which has created a special¬
ized unit of 70 carabinieri, and Spain, where units
of the Guardia Civil have been specially trained
and equipped not surprisingly since protection
of the environment is written into the Spanish
constitution. This October, representatives from
different national police forces will hold their first
joint meeting at Interpol Headquarters in Lyons
(France). International co-operation should make
Europe cleaner, though the task of harmonizing
legislation will still remain.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
i/ 1 1 ü u LiiniiüE
The glass and concrete environment of modern cities sets up
barriers between inside and outside, cutting people off from
each other and from themselves.
Developed in France, this
"audiosphere" is used to
simulate street noise. New
sounds can be added to
study the effect they would
have on the urban
soundscape.
Sound barriers
by R.Murray Schäfer
IN the Tunisian restaurant in Montreal, the
proprietor and his wife share a carafe of wine
fitted with a spout from which they pour
the wine directly into their mouths by raising
and tipping it, in exactly the way the old wineskin
would have worked. The sensation of drinking is
entirely different when the liquid is squirted into
the mouth rather than sipped out of a glass or
sucked through a straw, and so arc the accompa¬
nying sounds, on this occasion a bright burbling
as the air seeks to replace the liquid through the
twisted thin spout. Nothing touches the mouth
but the liquid. It is probably the purest way to
drink, yet it has been replaced by the glass as
individual proprietorship has replaced tribal
sharing. The glass, replacing more tuneful recep¬
tacles, is raised and chimed at the beginning of the
meal, partly in compensation for mute con¬
sumption, an exercise denied its successor the
plastic cup.
The soundscape of every society is condi¬
tioned by the predominant materials from which
it is constructed. Thus we may speak of bamboo,
wood, metal, glass or plastic cultures, meaning
that these materials produce a repertoire of sounds
of specific resonance when touched by active T I
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
agents. Europe was a stone culture and to a large
extent still is, particularly in its smaller, less-
touched communities. North America was orig¬
inally a wood culture, passing, like modern
Europe, to cement and glass during the twentieth
century.
The glazed window was an invention of great
importance for the soundscape, framing external
events in an unnatural, phantom-like "silence".
The diminution of sound transmission, while
not immediate and occurring only gradually with
the thickening of glazing, not only created the
notion of a "here" and a "there" or a "beyond",
but also introduced a fission of the senses. Today
one can look at one's environment, while hearing
another, with a durable film separating the two.
Plate glass shattered the sensorium, replacing it
with contradictory visual and aural impressions.
In a study of fairy talcs, Marie-Louise von
Franz points out that glass "cuts you off, as far as
your animal activity is concerned. . . . People
very often say. 'It feels as if there were a glass wall
. . . between me and my surroundings.' That
means: T see perfectly well what is going on, I
can talk to people, but the animal and feeling
contact, the warmth contact is cut off by a glass
wall	 '"' The world of sounds and textures, the
palpitating, kinetic world, is zoned out; we still
watch it move, but from our (generally seated)
position indoors our physical contact with it has
ceased. The physical world is "there"; the world
of reflection and speculation is "here".
When the space within is totally insulated it
craves reorchestration: this is the era of back¬
ground music and of the radio, a form of interior
decoration, designed or absent-mindedly intro¬
duced to re-energize the space and render it more
sensorially complete. Now the interior and exte¬
rior can become totally contradictory. The world
seen through the window is like the world of a
movie set with the radio as soundtrack. I recall
travelling in the dome car of a train passing
through the Rocky Mountains with schmaltzy
music on the public address system and thinking:
this is a travelogue movie about the Rocky Moun¬
tains we are not here at all.
When the division between "here" and
"there" is complete, the glass wall will become as
impenetrable as the stone wall. Even thieves will
respect it. Shattered glass is a trauma everyone is
anxious to avoid. "He shall rule them with a rod
of iron: as the vessels of a potter shall they be
broken to shivers" is a potent acoustic image in
the Bible {Revelation 2:27). A keynote of the
Middle-Eastern soundscape under normal cir¬
cumstances, crockery became a violent signal
when broken. For us the same is true of glass. And
yet one cannot help feeling that the mind-body
split of the Western world will only be healed
when some of the glass in which we have sheathed
our lives is shattered, allowing us again to inhabit
a world in which all the senses interact instead of
being ranked in opposition.
ACOUSTIC TRADEMARKS
AND SYMBOLIC
SOUNDS
It is unnatural for our senses to be forcibly choked
off, and when they are, they often reopen with a
vengeance. One could study the suppression of
the different senses in terms of the great culture
revolutions in history. Right now we are being
overwhelmed by the audio-visual media, which
exclude other sensory stimulations. A measure of
their inadequacy: everyone feels the compulsion
to eat while watching movies.
Little by little the whole world is becoming
mediatized, that is to say, it is driven by sound
objects designed to manipulate or persuade. In
this way it is different from the natural world we
have left behind in which sounds stimulated us
but rarely tried to control our behaviour. Think
about this: there is scarcely a sound in modern life
that has not been manufactured and is not owned
by someone. The music we listen to is copy¬
right-protected and licensed. Carhorns are the
S
'ï?;
SM
SJ
W'
^ " I
The one and the
many. A lone
boatman on Lake
Dal in India (left) and
a Brazilian crowd
(right).
£
3cte
-.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
property of car drivers and often blowing them
is the only conversation drivers make as they
pass through the city streets.
Almost all the noises of the modern city
police sirens, jet noise, construction noise are
designed to fortify some special-interest group.
Thus, many sounds have become symbols for
social classes. A ghetto blaster says: "I'm talking,
you listen! " A portable telephone (silent in cars,
audible in restaurants or on trains) says: "I'm a
very successful person. I'm important." The
ubiquitous cash registers of shops and restau¬
rants proclaim: "Listen to how much business we
do here!" An alarm-bell system screams: "Hands
off!" Even the owner of a growling dog on a
leash is silently saying: "Meet my friend. He pro¬
tects me."
Much of this sound is pugilistic. Is this
inevitable? Is it the result of overcrowding in the
modern world or a means of dividing the rich
from the poor, the winners from the losers?
Poverty is quiet. It is affluence that has become
noisy. With the acquisition of more and newer
gadgets with impressive acoustic trademarks,
successful groups stencil their identities into the
contemporary soundscape and attempt to influ¬
ence social behaviour to their own advantage.
THE VOICE
OF THE CROWD
The only means available to the poor or disen¬
franchised to make their presence known is the
noting crowd. Certainly crowds arc a feature of
modern life and will undoubtedly become
increasingly significant in the decades to come.
Elias Canetti analyses the crowd question in his
book Crowds and Power, and emphasizes the
importance of touching in dense assemblies of
people. "It is only in a crowd," he writes, "that
man can become free of his fear of being touched.
This is the only situation in which the fear changes
into its opposite. The crowd he needs is the dense
crowd, in which body is pressed to body; a
R.MURRAY SCHÄFER,
Canadian composer and
author, is the founder and
director of the World
Soundscape Project in
Vancouver. A former professor
of Communication Studies at
Simon Fraser University
(Canada), he Is the author of
many published works
including The New Soundscape
(1969), The Tuning of the World
(1977) and The Thinking Ear
(1986).
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Skyscrapers in Denver
(U.S.A.).
crowd, too, whose physical constitution is also
dense, or compact, so that he no longer notices
who it is that presses against him."
Touch and sound arc intimately connected. In
the lower frequencies tactility and sounding meet
as the pedal tone breaks into a vibrating pulse.
This intimacy encourages the densely-packed
crowd to invoke sound as its most potent
weapon. In every other way it is vulnerable to
penetration and disunification by better-armed
opponents who seek to neutralize it. The crowd
remains outside the towers of glass in which the
elite have imprisoned themselves. It is primarily
with its voice that it defends itself and seeks to
remain invincible. The crowd roars, the crowd
chants, the crowd screams you don't count the
voices; there is only one voice. If it contains
within it individuals who have not entirely sur¬
rendered to its purpose by the encouragement of
touching, sound will reinforce the dedication of
the wavering. There is a passage in St. Augustine's
Confessions in which the fate of a man who had
forsworn gladiatorial shows is sealed after he
had re-entered the maelstrom of a crowd. "If
only he could have stopped his ears!" cries St.
Augustine despairingly.
There are many ways of characterizing a
crowd by its purpose, its credo or its numbers.
This is what the explainers, the media men and the
politicians try to do. But vocally the crowd is
beyond all understanding. How many nuances
are detectable in its bawling? Joy . . . anger . . .
exasperation . . . derision . . . rudimentary emo¬
tions, at times chaotic but more often unified
rhythmically in the repetition of slogans, for
unless the crowd speaks with rhythmic incisive-
ness it can be fractured, set upon itself internally
and be routed.
By the early twentieth century, urban noise
had increased to a point where it began to affect
writers in a similar way, and among the first were
the Futurists, led by F.T. Marinetti. "Through a
disjointed, feverish and posturing language
Marinetti was able to capture something of the
mood of a human crowd in motion	 " This is
Istvan Anhalt commenting on Marinetti's rhetoric
in a book in which he shows parallel develop¬
ments in twentieth-century music. Marinetti's
prose is "the text of a poster, a proclamation, or
a series of headlines. It is a throbbing, aggressive,
insistent language, brooking no dissent, dis¬
missing the need for reflection, intolerant and
destructive."1 In his Futurist Manifesto Marinetti
had proclaimed: "We will sing of great crowds
excited by work, by pleasure and by riot; wc
will sing of the multicoloured, polyphonic tides
of revolution in the modern capitals."3
The influence of these crowd-choirs is con-
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
spicuous in much contemporary music, first of all
in the bloated orchestras of Berg and Schoenberg,
then later in the statistical organization of
Xenakis' works, as well as in the cluster and
aggregate effects of Ligeti and the "mob" vocal
outbursts of Lutoslawski and other members of
the Polish school. Crowd power is everywhere
present in rock music, which could not exist
without it. "No-one goes to a rock concert unless
they're stoned or stupid," a teenager tells me,
and yet almost everyone has been there. And the
music ricochets from car radios and ghetto
blasters, through the streets, over the back yard
fences, and dribbles out of the Walkman of the
passenger next to you on the bus, where no-one
speaks. It is almost as if music is hacmorrhaging
all around us, exploding out of its containers;
and suddenly you realize that music is the glue of
the modern multiracial, multilinguistic city,
holding it together more effectively than any
political or social system, and you allow yourself
to hope that it will continue to do so, fearing the
consequences if it fails. We know that there are
more violent forms of intolerance than the
tyranny of the loudspeaker.
RITUALS OF TRANQUILLITY
When modern humanity gave up life in the
country for life in the city, when it deserted open
spaces for the dense packing of the metropolis,
when the alarm clock replaced the sunrise and fac¬
tory noise obliterated wind, rain and the birds,
when the drowsiness of natural life was surren¬
dered to the mad dash to get ahead, the frictions
of increased human contact, the hell of other
people, as Sartre put it, replaced the great gco-
botanic garden that had been the scene of past
existence and the quiet life it promoted. Has it
been extinguished from memory or can a new
ecological awareness help to recover it?
What we seem to need are rituals of tran¬
quillity in which large assemblies of people could
feel the serenity of a shared experience without
the desire to proclaim their emotions in destruc¬
tive or disfiguring action. In this sense we might
again study the model of the Western concert
audience to determine whether it might have
wider or evolving significance. When wc think
about it, how astonishing is the concert audi¬
ence, quietly sitting before the music, scarcely
breathing, engulfed by the mysterious vibrations
in the air about them. I suppose every piece of
music longs to be worshipped in silence, but few
achieve such a distinction, and some achieve it
only by the authority of habit rather than the
privilege of beauty. I have often wondered
whether the ritual of the concert could not be
transposed to other environments and trans¬
formed into a collective contemplation of a bird
dawn chorus, a summer solstice or an Earth Day
celebration.
If the future of the planet is destined to embrace
increasing numbers of people, it is absolutely vital
that wc discover means of taming the noises that
arc threatening to tear us to pieces. Noise pollution
is a world-wide problem but its solution docs not
lie in increased legislation and enforced prohibi¬
tion. It rests with a regaining of the still centre, a
discovery that there is a time for everyone to
speak and a time for each of us to listen. This is the
"great open secret" of the natural soundscape
where all sounds have their place but none
attempts to dominate or smother all others into
submission. There arc simply no sounds in nature
that are a threat to our hearing. As reports of an
alarming increase in deafness accumulate from
some of the most developed nations of the world,
we realize that humanity is the exclusive architect
of sounds that kill. Either we will voluntarily
reduce the sound sewage now threatening whole
populations or we will all become deaf. In either
case the world will be quieter.
Mourners from among
Indonesia's Toradja people
carry drink to a funeral in
bamboo poles.
1. Marie-Louise Von Franz,
Individuation in Fairy Tales,
(Boston and London, 1990).
2. Alternative Voices
(Toronto, 1984).
3. FT. Marinetti: Selected
Writings, cd. R.W. Flint
(London, 1972). 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Architects of disorder
by Fernando and Diego Montes
R
ECENTLY-BUILT public housing estates
cannot by any stretch of the imagination be
I regarded as examples of haphazard design.
On the contrary, they suffer from an excessive
enthusiasm for order on the part of their planners.
The order that reigns in them is so oppressive and
simplified that it distracts attention from the
shape of the buildings. It is the expression of an
earthbound conceptual art that pays too little
attention to the estate-dweller's desire for a gen¬
uine urban environment.
This discrepancy has always existed and has
never been resolved. Art is not, in this case, ahead
of its time but off on a side-track strewn with his¬
tory's bright but mistaken ideas, ideas that should
perhaps have been looked into cautiously before
large-scale building operations began. As it is, the
frustration of estate-dwellers, provided with a
roof over their heads but deprived of an urban
environment, is one of the discontents of modern
times.
The situation varies little from one country to
another. The rows of dreary blocks lining the
broad, empty avenues of the Moscow suburbs are
variations on a town-planning theme that recurs
in Barcelona, Santiago, Milan, Essen and the Paris
working-class suburb of La Courncuvc. With a
few allowances for climatic differences, the pic¬
ture is the same everywhere: long, narrow hori¬
zontal slabs, the same back and front, or "high-
rises", multistorey flats reaching up into the
power lines rather than into the clouds.
The only thing not in order about these end¬
less vistas, these repetitious excrescences that
bear so little resemblance to real buildings, these
unfinished but already run-down blocks, was
the decision to build them in the first place. Ever
since, it has been one long tale of false reasoning,
miscalculation and mistaken designations imme¬
diately shown up for what they are: "green
spaces" can never take the place of natural
greenery, and the "amenities" provided scarcely
qualify as public buildings.
IMPROVISED
ARCHITECTURE
Let us now look at the favelas, cases, villas-mis¬
erias, barriadas and other shantytowns that have
mushroomed around nearly all major agglomer¬
ations, from Lima to Lagos and from Cairo to
Mexico City. These indescribable encrustations
arc archetypes of a modern urban and architec¬
tural phenomenon. Once peripheral, like the ring
of shacks that used to occupy the "zone" just out¬
side the former fortifications of Paris, this type of
habitat has become commonplace, perhaps even
the commonest type it would, incidentally, be
interesting to compare the area covered, respec¬
tively, by shantytowns and by conventional types
of habitat in a Third World conurbation.
Slums, run-down or derelict dwellings the
traditional answers to the demand for urban
housing arc no longer sufficient to accommo¬
date the masses of people moving in from rural
areas that can no longer feed them. The drift
from the land is not an organized movement of
population; it just happens. The cities, the first
places the migrants from the countryside head for,
have done nothing to cater for the newcomers,
perhaps because there was nothing they could do.
It took Paris fifteen hundred years to reach a
population of a million. How long will it take to
reach ten million? As for Mexico City, it is
heading for a population of twenty million.
Apartment blocks on the
outskirts of a French city.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
11 II H
I liiiiniimiii
t..
V
V*>w
v:
A city is a cumbersome structure and its
growth is hard to control. An overnight deci¬
sion to triple its area and population, extend its
highways and its water-supply and sewage sys¬
tems, or increase the capacity of its public trans¬
port and schools, would set a technically and
physically impossible task.
Shantytowns are therefore improvised struc¬
tures, created out of anything that comes to hand
and by definition haphazard. It goes without
saying that planners and architects have had
nothing to do with them, nor do they meet
normal town-planning standards. But which of
these, strictly laid-out housing estates or hig¬
gledy-piggledy shantytowns, are the more rep¬
resentative of the spirit of modern architecture?
In the late 1960s, John Turner, a British-
born architect who teaches at the Massachu¬
setts Institute of Technology, emerged as a pas¬
sionate advocate of the architectural merits of
shantytowns. His message, relayed through the
world's leading schools of architecture and
avant-garde publications, is that there is much to
be learned from this architecture without archi¬
tects, an architecture dictated by need and
urgency, which he sees as being richly imagina¬
tive. This form of self-built housing is extremely
well adapted to the requirements of the inhab¬
itants, who do not receive welfare handouts but
are the protagonists in a tragedy they are obliged
to act out in order to survive.
At the other extreme, large-scale housing
projects planned, built and managed by a cen¬
tralized institution are the outcome of a ruthless
rationalization of social needs. The context of
their construction and of the decision-making
processes on which they depend is more often
than not a bureaucratic one, even in the most
free-market-oriented countries.
Turner's point of departure is the idea that, in
FERNANDO MONTES
is a Chilean architect who has
taught architecture in a
number of universities and
schools of South and North
America.
DIEGO MONTES
¡s a French student of
architecture and the theatre
who is currently preparing a
production of Albert Camus'
play Caligula.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
the conditions of extreme deprivation that prevail
in shantytowns, the mode of production takes
precedence over technical or aesthetic consider¬
ations. Basically, he believes that architecture, as
usually practised, is cither a luxury reserved for
developed societies or an art that is out of place
outside a stable social context: it requires, if not
order, at least a certain degree of methodical orga¬
nization. The new urban society of the shanty¬
towns, however, is a prime example of a social
body in the throes of change.
Do shantytowns open new horizons or do
they point up the need to rethink the hierarchies,
values and methods of architecture?
As a good dialectician of social progress,
Turner plays on the inseparability of the two
possibilities. According to him, it should be pos¬
sible to reconcile modern architecture with dis¬
order and foresight with spontaneity and achieve
a kind of hybrid form, something like jazz or
the music of Stravinsky or Gershwin, a mixture
of improvisation and highly complex orchestra¬
tion. But Turner has so far failed to carry opinion
with him, and modern architecture has still to find
its philosopher's stone.
A FRUITFUL ECLECTICISM
Fifty years earlier, Picasso, with his usual per¬
spicacity, had also put his finger on this dilemma.
In the middle of his cubist period, he said that,
after Van Gogh, everything had become possible
(disorder), but that what had been gained in
freedom had been lost in self-confidence.
History does not move forward in a straight
line but follows a strange kind of trajectory,
swinging one way then back again, leaping for¬
ward, stopping and accelerating. The innocent
observer might think that it never points the way
clearly, that it is constantly correcting its course
and changing tack.
The twentieth century, which got off to a
flying start in architecture only to finish in low
gear, has seen the pendulum swing time and
again and has had its share of skids and knocks
as well, but it may well have made an original
contribution to the history of art in that it has
been a time of greater eclecticism and diversity
than ever before. This characteristic feature of
the times is perhaps linked with the development
of the communication media and data-storage
facilities, which enables the particular and the
universal to coexist in the spirit of the global vil¬
lage, combining the parochial with the planet-
wide.
For centuries, the memory of humanity was
oral, written or pictorial. As its storage capacity
was very limited, its contents had constantly to be
weeded out. Thanks to chemical and electronic
devices, the storage capacity has increased immea¬
surably. Wc no longer need to discard whatever
is out of date or offbeat to make room for main¬
stream ideas. The two can exist side by side, just
below the surface of our memories, waiting for
the moment to rc-emerge. That moment may
come quite soon: the wheel of history, we are
told, is turning faster and faster. An Indonesian shantytown.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
The third bank of the river
by Roberto DaMatta
Above, a participant in the
Parintins carnival (Brazil). T
I o reflect on modernity is necessarily to
deconstruct a myth. But what arc myths? It
took us a long time to see them as anything
other than the irrational outgrowth of primitive
minds, but wc now realize that they provide a
framework within which societies define their
values, that they are devices for taking control of
time, time that bears within itself the seeds of
death and oblivion. Myths, then, are stories that
seek to escape the grip of time. That is why
mythologies are disturbing. When, therefore, the
heralds of post-modernity proclaim that the age
of great stories is over, they do so in order that
they can themselves construct the great (and true)
story of all times . . .
Ultimately this is the dilemma that lies at
the root of our civilization: how to find stable
values in a world that chooses to be unstable,
how to reconcile individuals who regard them¬
selves as the repositories of rights, desires and ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
so
subjective feelings with collective institutions
that have to be stable and objective, that require
duties to be performed and that guarantee the
existence of individual choice?
If myths are stories that reject the linear
chronology of cumulative history, how can they
be reconciled with a civilization that claims to
have invented modernity and defines itself as the
product of a history that continually transforms
people and institutions?
To answer this question is to recognize that
there is no such thing as a society exclusively
based on the future or on movement. Modernity
may have exorcised many myths, but it has not
abolished myth-making. Repressed and re
labelled (with that all-purpose prefixpost-), myths
constantly reappear above all when the death of
God or, worse, the end of humankind, is
announced. For myths, like dreams, signal unre¬
solved problems. The generous Western ideals of
social justice, individual freedom and political
equality for all are clearly based on a mythology,
and this mythology, even in the developed coun¬
tries, is still grappling with many deviant phe¬
nomena racism, anti-semitism, political and
economic marginalization that haunt or chal¬
lenge it. Thus, alongside the egalitarian credo
that underlies the ideology of professional success
in modern Western society, counter-mytholo¬
gies have emerged to denounce the advantages
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Modern Rio.
conferred by graduating from a great university,
by speaking English or French and, last but not
least, by being white!
Confronted with an enlightened, rationalist
and bourgeois West whose concept of time is
dominated by the idea of progress, other parts of
the world are obliged to make a synthesis between
the modern idea of a universal history centred on
utilitarian individualism and their own tradi¬
tional values, which hinge on personal loyalties to
the gods and to ancestors, families and friends. In
many parts of the world, and particularly in so-
called marginal or peripheral regions, a rap¬
prochement is taking place between bourgeois
mythology on the one hand, which refers to a
system in which the individual is the moral and
political centre of the universe, and, on the other
hand, stories based on very different premises.
The societies that survive this process are those
that invent mythologies combining these two
value-systems, previously regarded as incom¬
patible. This path has been followed by Japan and
by Asia in general, and, on an equally signifi¬
cant scale, by Latin America and particularly
Brazil.
EQUAL YET UNEQUAL
I have written that Brazilian society is struggling
to combine two mythologies. The first, taking its
inspiration from the modern tradition, considers
the individual as an autonomous moral entity
endowed with inalienable rights such as freedom
and equality. The second is based on a world -view
that denies individualism, distrusts progress and
rejects formal political equality. Whereas the first
of these mythologies leads to the modern concept
of representative democracy, the second reflects
a way of life in which personal relationships are
stronger than political institutions. Some see in
this way of life the imprint of an Iberian counter-
reformism which (by virtue of its myths, its
heroes and its forms of civilization) is a kind of
counterpoint in carnival dress to liberal individ¬
ualism, above all that form which flourishes in the
United States, which with its media, fast food,
tragic solitude and insurmountable ethnic, sexual,
age and occupation barriers is the paradigm of
modernity.
This convergence of mythologies clearly cre¬
ates a dilemma to which the Brazilian and,
more generally, Latin American solution lies in
a tendency to see all people as politically and
economically unequal but as morally of equal
worth. In this world we may be masters or slaves,
bosses or underlings; but face-to-face with death
we arc all equal. This paradoxical solution is an
attempt to reconcile modern cgalitarianism with
the inequality ingrained in traditional ways of
thought by recourse to an ethic of ambiguity.
Latin American mythologies adopt equality
as the framework of the legal and political system
and competition as the basis of the economic
system, without abandoning or curbing tradi¬
tional social practices based on inequality and
personal relations. As a result, the legal and polit¬
ical systems always seem to be either far ahead or
far behind what is really happening in society.
Here wc have a process of modernization
imposed from above by the state, which attempts
thereby to substitute itself for the creative forces
that gave the original system its spontaneity.
While modernity is based, socially and epis-
temologically, on the triumph of the individual,
it is also rooted in a system of rigid procedures,
valid for everyone, everywhere and in all
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
circumstances as if we were all really born
equal, as if we were all exempt from social oblig¬
ations and competed in reasonable conditions
of equality. Equality before the law conceals
inequality of social conditions. The so-called
"post-modern" mythology that relativizes and
fragments, reducing everything to the yuppy
nihilism of certain circles in Paris or in Berkeley,
can only function if certain conditions are met,
above all if a common denominator is attained, the
common denominator in question being an
almost blind obedience to the basic principles of
a universalist rationalism that structures the whole
system. But how can an egalitarian rationalism of
this sort be applied to traditionalist societies
based on the concept of difference?
A CAPRICIOUS
LIBERALISM
The result, in many cases, is a mythology that
believes in miracles, spirits and messiahs, that
invents a capricious and particularist liberalism in
which the laws of the market only work for the
powerful, and in which egalitarianism has been
wedded first to slavery, then to servility and a
system of patronage. From this arises a state that
is simultaneously large and small, strong and
weak, whose resources and spoils are diverted to
make sure that the poor are kept in their place, and
above all to increase the wealth of the rich. It is a
mythology that has reinvented Carnival, the fes¬
tival in which social roles are reversed without the
system being changed, and that has encouraged
delinquency founded on the morality of profit-
seeking, disculpating people and opening the
way to irresponsibility.
Here we have a collection of myths produced
from a kind of moral tinkering, a Frankensteinian
hotchpotch of institutions and practices taken
from here, there and everywhere, of moral rules
grouped under a double (or triple) ethic which
declares that everyone is equal before the law,
except for one's relatives and friends. Any refer¬
ence to universality in this context is made in
order to legitimize the market and profit, not to
protect the most fundamental rights.
But we must not disregard the generous and
constructive side of these trans-modern mytholo¬
gies, the side that wants everyone to be equal but
rejects the post-utilitarian equation between
equality and consumption, that wants freedom,
but not just to make money or to exploit the
masses marginalized by the media. In Brazil this
takes the form of a shrewd resistance to market
economics through the myth of a popular hero, the
brigand Pedro Malasarte. The stories featuring
this emblematic figure show how it is possible to
play the market against big money, and how the
rule of law that legitimizes exploitation of the
workforce can be turned against the boss. In these
trans-modern mythologies, morality is on the
side of a form of delinquency that compensates for
the inequalities resulting from the pressures of
the international market and of social elites.
*-.
A
mm .
'-*>
Right and opposite page
above, the adventures of
Pedro Malasarte, as
pictured by the illustrator
Teixeira Mendes.
Centre, labourers head for
work on a dam in Ceará
state (Brazil).
ROBERTO DAMATTA,
of Brazil, is the Edmund P.
Joyce Professor of
Anthropology and Senior
Fellow of the Kellogg Institute,
University of Notre Dame
(U.S.A.). Among his works
published in English are
Carnivals, Rogues and Heroes
(University of Notre Dame
Press) and A Divided World:
Apinayé Social Structure
(Harvard University Press).
' ¿?*Cr-Ji¿ ft . f.*üm- ' .
>w- '¿¿ms. >im*- s
<f&r*&*
r*JS,
9m
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
v I : V'-
£'.» * *í i
But the process of acculturation between the
modern and the traditional also has perverse
effects. In this twofold ethic, the possibility of
appealing alternatively to one system or the other
makes it difficult for individuals to know where
they stand. What I cannot do as a citizen I may be
able to do as a friend of the governor or a relative
of someone in authority. This is the dilemma
faced by communities in which the modern
nation-state is subjected to all kinds of external
and internal pressures and is confronted by social
expectations that have no outlet.
The mythologies of peripheral societies have
grown out of this dilemma. Hence our difficulties
with classic bourgeois heroes, those judicious
individuals who are always serious and who know
how to say yes or no. . . . Presented with a choice
but unable or unwilling to decide between the two
courses available to us, we prefer triangular situ¬
ations which blur distinctions and harmonize dif¬
ferent interests. This is why our mythology con¬
tains a certain number of truly trans-modern
characters such as Jorge Amados Doña Flor, who
chooses not to choose, or one of the heroes ofJoäo
Guimaracs Rosa, who decides to live on a magical
"third bank of the river" somewhere on the edge
of consciousness, from which he can always see
the other two banks and can appreciate the point
of view of everyone else, of all those who are par¬
alyzed by their tragic, yet nonetheless rich and
resilient, uncertainty. 53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
HERRIMG REU VOICES
Rejecting conventional
aesthetics, modern artists,
musicians and writers have
Dans le gris (1914),
oil on canvas by Wassily
Kandinsky.
made freedom of invention
the only rule.
54
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
A world steeped in music
by Isabelle Leymarie
ODERNlTY', in the most usual
sense of the word, encompasses
the world of today. It conjures up
a picture of a perpetually moving technolog¬
ical universe stemming from the Industrial Rev¬
olution, in which humanity is a slave to
machinery and feels anxious and cut off from
Nature and its own roots. WH. Auden empha¬
sized a more positive aspect of the modern age
when he defined it as born of "the transforma¬
tion of a closed society of tradition and inheri¬
tance into an open society of fashion and
choice".
In this modern world, which is both unstable
and alienating and makes a multitude of
demands, there is more music about than ever
before. In the street, in buses and on trains,
more and more people arc wearing headsets to
enjoy their favourite type of music, turned in on
themselves and announcing their refusal to com¬
municate with others. A non-stop flow of music
pours from radio and television stations, and can
be heard in restaurants, supermarkets, airports,
hairdressers' and other shops, dentists' waiting
rooms and post offices. Music is a component
part of films; concerts and music festivals are
proliferating internationally; and now some
bars in the West are starting to import karaoke
from Japan a device which enables the man in
the street to sing familiar songs to a pre-recorded
backing while the lyrics appear on a screen.
Thus music is ubiquitous, and listening to it
in its most varied forms is continually on the
increase. "Early music and non-European music
have never been so widespread," writes Paul-
Louis Simon. "Guillaume de Machaut, Mozart
and Ravi Shankar fill our auditory world; our
ears arc flooded with jazz, pop, disco music
and all kinds of songs; all these art forms arc
there for us to choose from, and form an integral
part of the art of our time."
The musicologist Jean-Paul Holstein points
out that music today is characterized by high
technology, internationalism and democratiza¬
tion. High technology in this context means
that composers use more and more complex
forms of expression, that instrumentalists display
increasing virtuosity, and that people listen to
music through the intermediary of more and
more sophisticated technology. Modern tech¬
niques such as mixing, dubbing, playback and
electronic distortion in the form of wawa,
reverb, fuzz and echoplex open the way to new
sound possibilities, but however advanced they
may be, they eliminate contact with the original
acoustic sound. Doris Rossiaud, a fine pianist
who performed with the Orchestre Suisse
Romande, refused to make recordings because
she regarded all the ways of correcting errors in
the studio with multiple takes and mixing as
forms of trickery.
As for Holstein's other two points, inter¬
nationalism here refers to the proliferation of
means of transport and communication, and to
the creation of new professions, especially in the
media, publishing and advertising, aimed at
publicizing and promoting various kinds of
music. Democratization is linked to popular¬
ization, the market economy, the emergence of
a wide audience and the requirements of hit¬
parades.
CROSS-FERTILIZATION AND
STANDARDIZATION
On the current music scene two trends are
asserting themselves in tandem: on the one hand
an urge to merge with and communicate with
other cultures, apparent in "world music", a
mélange of musics from different countries, and
on the other the increasing standardization of
commercial music, dominated by American and
English pop. As non-Western musics arc
absorbed by Western culture, the exotic becomes
commonplace and loses its character, and oppor¬
tunities for escape become more limited. The
various "ethnic" musics get cut off from their
social and religious context and become dehu¬
manized by excessive use of synthesizers (which
reproduce the sound of certain traditional instru¬
ments, but do not capture their subtleties) and
electronic "drum machines".
Mechanized and rendered insipid, the
Japanese shamisen and the Mandingo balafon
now serve only to add a semblance of tone
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
Recording a work for
clarinet and tape recorder
at the Institut de
Recherche et de
Coordination Acoustique-
Musique (IRCAM) in Paris.
New computer technology
adjusts the sound of the
recorded track to the
instrumentalist's tone and
phrasing as he plays.
colour to these new mixes. Then there is "fla¬
menco rock", an unholy mixture of guitar and
rhythm section, robbed of all duende, the pas¬
sion that gives Gypsy music its harsh beauty.
North African rai merges into reggae, reggae
into rap, and rap itself, with the "sampling"
technique made popular by young black Amer¬
ican disc-jockeys, which involves borrowing a
fragment from one piece and inserting it, collage-
style, into another, leads to mangling and the
production of rag-bag medleys. Musical
hybridization is more fashionable than ever,
and the media are all too ready to propagate it.
But while musical mixtures, like all contacts
between cultures, are positive, rewarding and
even essential for cultural growth, they can only
work for mutually compatible musics. A par¬
ticularly successful example is Latin jazz, a blend
of American jazz and Afro-Latin rhythm and
percussion that is flourishing in the United
States. It works because jazz and the black
musics of Latin America and the West Indies
have the same European and African roots. Fur¬
thermore, for osmosis to take place between
two or more musical traditions, a long ripening
process is usually required, such as the "cre-
olization" that, beginning in the West Indies,
Latin America and New Orleans in the early
seventeenth century, gave rise to such original
styles as jazz, rumba, mambo, calypso, the
beguine, samba and bossa nova, each with its
own rules and instrumentation.
The abandonment of tradition and the cul¬
tural legacy gives rise to continual changes and
inventions. Creativity may thereby be stimu¬
lated, but most commonly, where pop music is
concerned (now "popular" in name only, since
it is no longer rooted in a real tradition), the con¬
sumer society requires the continual production
of novelties which at once become outdated
and the frantic race to make "hits". These factors
disturb less commercially successful artists
unable to swim against the tide of fashion, and
also subject listeners to the diktats of the record
companies, for which sales considerations often
take precedence over quality.
The continual broadcasting of music as a
consumer product also leads to listener lazi¬
ness. Listening becomes passive rather than
active, and background music can even bring on
nervous fatigue. We arc reduced to hearing
instead of listening. Many employees working
in premises where the radio is always on end up
by simply blanking out the background noise in
order to escape the assault on their ears.
Pop music, now a common denominator
for the young, has nevertheless (despite its close
links with the consumer society) often been bit¬
terly critical of the violence and excesses of the
modern world. "You've never done nothing
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
A karaoke session in
Tokyo.
but build to destroy," proclaimed Bob Dylan in
"Masters of War". Jamaican reggae condemns
"Babylon" as the emblem of the decadent
modern city, in which hatred and corruption
are rife; and Michael Jackson, the very symbol
of commercial success, took on a redemptive
mission by proclaiming himself the messenger
of divine love.
MODERNITY
AND
CONTEMPORARY MUSIC
It is interesting to note that though we speak of
modern art, modern architecture and modern
furniture, we say contemporary music. The
latter uses a wide variety of musical techniques:
modal, serial, contingent, polytonal and atonal
languages, the use of stridency and of apparently
non-musical noises (pioneered by Eric Satie's
Parade), of unconventional and increasingly
graphic systems of notation, and of computers
and other electro-acoustic equipment
(IRCAM the Institut de Recherche et de
Coordination Acoustique-Musique in France
and the music departments of Columbia and
Princeton universities in the United States are
specialists in this field). Contemporary music
uses acoustic instruments to provide a repertoire
of unusual sound effects (for instance, John
Cage's prepared piano,1 Vinko Globokar's trom
bone pieces, flautists singing into their instru¬
ments, violins slapped and scraped, and the
ways in which the human voice is used in the
work of Giacinto Scelsi). So-called "happen¬
ings" such as Cage's Silence also enrich the
world of sound.
Contemporary music is still regarded by
many as "experimental", and people sometimes
find it confusing, but it has not yet been going
long enough to allow the necessary perspective
view. Moreover, now that patronage has ended,
present-day composers arc increasingly isolated
and find themselves in a precarious position.
Few of their works now arc commissioned
pieces with a specific social function, written for
the church, the court, ballet, opera or as pure
divertissement, or governed by a cosmogonie or
philosophical system. At the same time com¬
posers enjoy greater freedom and independence
now that they are no longer subject to the whims
of a patron.
Far from being popular, contemporary music
still attracts only a limited audience. But the
European tradition makes a hierarchical dis¬
tinction (often artificial and pernicious) between
so-called "art music", which is placed on a
pedestal, and other types of music. This is not the
case elsewhere. In Cuba, for instance, the various
musical genres are closely linked a phenom¬
enon that predates the rise of Fidel Castro 57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
thus vitalizing music in general. It is not unusual
for a member of a symphony orchestra to play
in an Afro-Cuban group in the evening and
then go on to improvise late at night with a jazz
outfit without doing any harm to his reputa¬
tion, rather the contrary. Several Cuban com¬
posers, such as Ernesto Lecuona, Gilberto
Valdés, Gonzalo Roig and Emilio Grenet have
written many works for the popular repertoire
and have taken legitimate pride in them.
THE QUEST FOR
AN AESTHETIC
In the field of aesthetics the idea of modernity
means something different. By and large, for
most people, it suggests skyscrapers and con¬
crete buildings, the advent of black cars, the
pure lines of 1920s dress fashions, rectilinear
furniture, Picasso. This aesthetic, perceived as the
obverse of classicism, romanticism, the ancient
world and other canons, is entirely relative.
Indeed, it has had its day. In the visual arts
people now talk about "post-modernism", and
in the world of jazz, following the excesses of
1960s free jazz, about "neo-classicism" exem¬
plified by musicians such as Wynton Marsalis,
the Harper brothers and Terence Blanchard.
Some architects like Philip Johnson, Gwathmcy
& Siegel and Mario Buotta are now opting for
softer, rounder shapes. Fashions in dress arc
also reverting to earlier styles.
The idea of modernity is far from being con¬
temporary. Some composers in the early decades
of this century, such as Charles Ives, Henry
Cowell, Edgard Várese, Carl Ruggles, Dane
Rudhyar, Ruth Crawford and Adolph Weiss,
were termed "ultra-modern" in the United
States in their day.
It is interesting to note that for these com¬
posers being modern meant, in music, following
only one's imperious inner drives, not outdated
canons. "Music written in the manner of another
century," said Várese, "is the result of culture,
and desirable and comfortable as culture may be,
an artist should not lie down in it." He added: "I
don't care about reaching the public as much as
I care about reaching certain musical-acoustical
phenomena, in other words, to disturb the
atmosphere because, after all, sound is only an
atmospheric disturbance!" Whereas until the
romantic period music was regarded as the man¬
ifestation of divine order, it later became the
expression of the composer's emotions and inner
life. The composer would break free, gain his
independence and impose his own laws, but at
the same time he would cut himself off from the
organic world to which he belonged.
In literature, the idea of modernity made its
appearance with Baudelaire, who in his essay on
the painter in the modern world exhorted critics
and art-lovers to discover the beauty of things
that possess "the essential quality of being the
TK>
ISABELLE LEYMARIE
is a Franco-American
musicologist whose study on
salsa and Latin jazz (La Salsa et
le Latin jazz) was published
earlier this year by PUF, Paris.
She Is currently working on a
study on the black music of
Latin America and the West
Indies, scheduled for
publication in 1994.
present", and by due appreciation of that beauty
to renew their links with the universal. In
painting, it coincides with Manet's Déjeuner
sur l'herbe, exhibited at the Salon des Refusés in
1863. With this work Manet claimed the painter's
prerogative of painting a picture for his own
aesthetic delectation, without bothering about
representation or allegory but only following his
own personal urges, in other words of pro¬
ducing "art for art's sake". In this sense
Kandinsky's credo could be that of many twen¬
tieth-century musicians: "The artist must be
blind to 'recognized' shape, just as he must be
deaf to the teachings and desires of his age. His
eye must be open upon his own inner life, and
his ear always pricked for the voice of inner
necessity. Then he will be able to use all methods
with impunity, even those which arc forbidden."
Schoenberg, the precursor of contemporary
music, also had a mystical approach. Beauty,
according to him, stems from the search for
truth, but a truth linked both to aesthetic
absolutes and to the composer's inner tempera¬
ment: "Beauty begins to appear when the non-
creator becomes aware of its absence. It does not
exist before, because the artist has no need of it:
for him the truth is enough. . . . And yet beauty
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
A concert by the rock
group Genesis in New York
in 1986.
gives itself to the artist even though he has not
sought it, having endeavoured only to find the
truth."
Some years later Elliott Carter opened up
new horizons for American music, and his
experimentation foreshadowed that of present-
day composers. His work, wrote Martin
Boykan, "is of importance to the postwar gen¬
eration not only because of its artistic power, but
also because it provides a moral lesson, because
it reminds the composer that it is his task
painful, perhaps, but inescapable to choose his
language freshly for each work, and to choose
from the whole range of musical possibilities."
Though fashion imposes new benchmarks
and new conventions, fashion and modernity are
ultimately opposed, and modernity (in the
artistic sense of the term) runs counter to
fashion. Being modern means freeing onself
from codes and conventions, whilst remaining
fully of one's time, from which there is no
escape. As Elliott Carter said, it means "choosing
one's language freshly for each work." As
regards music, "modern" composers must turn
away from traditional artistic categories and
find their own voice; and "modern" listeners
should stop making judgements on the basis of
outdated criteria and should greet new work
with flexibility.
As the car becomes more receptive, percep¬
tion becomes more acute and differing degrees
of listening develop. As with painting, about
which no-one talks more understandingly than
painters, so the professional musician, attuned
to harmonic niceties, counterpoint and phrasing
and the subtleties of rhythm, appreciates music
more profoundly than the amateur whose
instinctive understanding, however intense and
sensuous, operates at a more impressionistic
and superficial level.
So many different types of music can be
heard today that each of us must create our own
way of listening. This profusion makes life par¬
ticularly hard for the composer, who sometimes
gets lost in a maze of styles and methods. But in
the modern world, saturated as it is with sound,
the pleasure of a true musical discovery is all the
more wonderful in that it is getting rare. "I love
what never was," cried Odilon Redon, inviting
us with this piece of wordplay to continue
exploring the byways of discovery.
1 .A piano transformed into a percussion instrument by the
insertion ofvarious objects between the strings. Editor
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
Me and
my shadow
by Simon Lane
ataptaoeraphofyo>.rseUa J ow,
srar, wes.d
happensso.a»t^ V^J ssedby_
lt, »o ^
lea
went.
/
MasonLine-MasonLineis , ^ q{ a
Enghshman.Iseehtm^
hotel room ^^ductl0ad absurdum of
to happen, theperiect^ ^ ^.^ an
Modern Man. í^'din time and space,
anachronic ob,ect trapP Qns kept
ahaplesscoUecuono d ^ ion. Dld
for the moment, m .state o ^^^
disguised as fact?
/
r
t
/
v.pm<i Mason
LweprtnAfcs ««f^^Jsotfg«* »Pe'¬
er rf*^^^Äfce fife ofa Japanese
form an heroic act, saving w Riffel
'Trist who had slipped ^¡^J^^ely
Tower). fe^.^Ä hipped to
speaking. ^fZhave turned me into this
kmon ^db^Znenüy relanng on a
mild-mannered person>
hotelbedsomewhereinPans.
word "modern « ^o ^ x
inition "just now *°moking a cigarette. Just
siting. Just now I am sm £^ onto
now 1 can se5 * *Xa<W' andtheretsa
someone's heai Theresa ,
-just now", whlCVle^ustnows"? Where do
¿hathappens to f^J^o *e wake whtch
they all go? Dc, they faU m forwards,
eacn of us makes whenj, ^
pacingoneuredfoot^ ^
daring to^backer * ,^ .^ ks,
den^^^i-^^fSl »tops which so
traitements?
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
/ r
f^f the bath and
TcnseeMasonLinegetungouto^t q{
ïdraggedouttosea.
U*«. «*** lS,ZaZgh faction, but still a
existence, a ^^Sathroom-HissUdow
long time w spending sUp$ mder the door m
Is up from the bed ?£% ^ Mason! Are
W» see what he is up £ bedroom and
you ready to come ^^1character Or
lesumeyour existence as afict J? Mason
Zuldyou like ^¿Zkingofnothmgm
Line is lying m the bath, w ^ ^ s.
pUcul. He ào^jp ^ h
Zoning, so h^ThtnecLthatitsh^
itself to the nape o}hisn offh batb
masheetojwaterovr é p
its hand moving, *«"% aoor. Now it can
ksb and <T?%to^^Mf"Í
, j-ffp« from all other
other pmf¡e- **e<"nlJA« mood ',
<íWow sur« teuere multa>lted by we
con^etmg^g¡le fictional shadow
E^^^ffiU«* I ^^are
have a right to a Uttie y they are
Zny^ thel llVe fTey short of money
perfect lovers, they ^f^yiheHghtf^f
{always mpossessiorlofexacXly ^^of
uponexitmgtaxicabs)andWy ^ fe
herculean retentive power ^ . h
Zst£:eatedthem?
SIMON LANE
is a British writer whose novel
Still Life with Books will be
lew
_>u:i u|c ui
published later this year by
Bridge Works Publishing, N'
York. His first novel was
published in French translation
as Le Veilleur (Christian
Bourgois, Paris, 1992).
61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
Anything wrntenwluch- havedeclded
sothattherewdlbenoam gu^imag.n.ngthat
Witten this story, ^a^the story, cor-
X have wntten it- I have aboUt to send it
rected its mistake and *J J j wm the story
oi{ to UNESCO. Before^ >st
into the decku0Í;Xth0Sughly.Thenlputthe
and shuffle the deck tho^ 0 y ^ . he
deckof stones ^° ^ Je into a letter box.
street and drop t^°Äorder of the cards
t^n^-thing .mted.-
ferent.
l^^epossU.^^pLpen,
object to h***>f¿Z$t Und, exc^e to
empty o^nd-sel^ . $ tt?
the eye; a book a thin ^ ^
W» though^ ¿idemeonths
knife; or even my fatals no words, but if
foreign bed. The*»*» l can see something
\ hold it up to theligbU üme> the dl$tan
inside, a voice silenceä ^ t
message.
u Ul have got out of bed on
At other times, should_I ^ g drcumspect,
fhe wrong side, I -f ^onswith qualities
investingmy diun»Ua am ^^
designed to délibérât y microcosmic
Ufe'sprogress^hKhso J othep
span of exrstence corresp ^ side oi
¡Í the sun from east to we^t x ^^
thehoteHMasons.de)^^^^^^^
ever tried to understands
mv sWow, I can do magi or a mle
Through space I ^^Zrds the horizon
)ong. When the sun moves tc ^g £foe
£,5yo»e am see me I am ¡ y passlng
auai squashed and trampa y $ of
Tourists. At other^^J wheresoever
lght, I become¿«¿^ that I feel
t ,msh unnoticed, ignore» wlthout
station, for! ^*£$?SboM there
beafullmoon,itmayw
spicuous again.
61
u-V, Mason Line is seated is, of
TheroominwhtchM^ ^ ^
course, one of a chaino ^ hght
hotels dotted hke su m ^ a
years from one anoA^ye q ^md
distances« than onew«e J^^ h
finger in front o one ey w k
tightly,onewouldb^ hecksmtoth
outadozenorsoofthern havere d
forhim-Hewdlleaveth2q {romanothe
somebody else, another wlU
story 1 have yet to inven ^ actor>
perhaps, rehearsing some^ ^ wlU
avoid paying the buh
I will simply think, and my ^
recorded for the benefit ofalIP j ^
pendens of the spirit. I dono ^
,&» ¿mag«**«0»» S^C,C. /cr from Albion, but I
aesofaninebriatesaibb^r iQr
Uaninventanddisposeo^h^^
alacrity.Itis,afterall,my P ^^
more, nothing less. Somen , ^^
! permit my creations to hvhemcredlt
4neverhavetoWok.U mastateoi
cards, I allow them to S1 ^ ¿Jof Bel0n oys-
indolence, fed on a perp ^^however.
l^hlhlhrstendowthem.
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
A a fictional character he is ^p ¿
fashion-lbte^^^^^
him so thatl can write about ^ r
Si him, find out who he£ . ?
met, but we have a re^ ^^ ^0
short of perfect. 1 kno $ absolute y
kn0w about him and ne rargue.
nXngwhatsoeveraboutme;esF
We keep ourselves pt> has never
reared its ugiy
because lam dif-
Because I am a ^carn^n b ^wh
ferentjcansceintothelwes ^ .,
\tart out by being*I «« the
eventually, become me- ¿^ t the
protagonist in ^^tdenunder the bed ofa
pages of apaperback 'toa ^ m£ Qf a
movein sympathy.
.hesunissetting^Wa^^ut
!snearlyover;andthepe^on^heroom)there
the hotel has vanished W ^never
isnosignofhispassmg^^^me? But who am
existed at all, perhaps it was )U ^ dgar
tomymouthandhghn«tp hand,the
shakily in^^a moment ago, grasped
same one -hlC\\^ invisible ink? I turn
thefountainpen,fiUedwi x t
my hand over and inspec J ¿ upon
"w make out the^^J? really is my
it. So I cannot tell^ else's, that is.
hand. As opposed to som
, u- ^ the screen of my con-
Somewhere, behind the^ ,lc.But
sciousnessjiesatale-^ dduc,
aUIhavetogoonsofara.afe,iroomAndl
! have Mason Line m te ^^ ^0
haVC hlS Îtwhat le? Well, there's nothing
meninabath.Whateis norevelatory
tale? 63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
Pieces of music, music of pieces
by Leon Milo
64
LEON MILO
is an American composer and
percussionist. A graduate of
the Juilliard School of Music
(New York), he has been
working in France since 1989
after receiving grants from the
Fulbright Foundation. His
compositions have been
performed by the orchestra of
Radio France and by the Los
Angeles Philharmonic New
Music Group.
ACCORDING to contemporary scientific
theory, a "Big Bang" originating from an
infinitesimally small and dense object pro¬
jected countless atomic particles into space, and
these fragments, regrouping into an abundance of
elements and matter, make up the expanding and,
perhaps, eventually contracting universe.
In 1941, the composer Arnold Schoenberg
viewed "the Beginning" as a vision which only an
omniscient force could embrace and realize. "To
understand the nature of creation," he wrote,
"one must acknowledge that there was no light
before the Lord said: 'Let there be light. ..."
'There was Light' at once and in its ultimate per¬
fection	 Alas, human creators, if they be granted
a vision, must travel a long path between vision
and accomplishment . . . painstakingly connecting
details until they fuse into a kind of organism."
To transform a vision into an object, in this case
via musical composition, is a step-by-step opera¬
tion. Using an enormous vocabulary of symbols,
a composer communicates detailed musical
instructions to the performer while constantly
keeping in mind the desired shape of the final
work.
A vision of the "whole" does not, of course,
always appear to the artist as a flash of lightning
suddenly illuminating a landscape that needs
only to be transcribed onto canvas, paper or
audio tape. Even if a piece of music (oddly, the
word "piece" is used to describe an entire musical
composition) has been inspired by a non-musical
object or event that suggests a musical point of
departure, a "Big Bang" for example, it still
remains for the composer to organize, manipu¬
late and develop purely musical fragments into a
form which will be comprehensible to listeners.
"Object" and "fragment": are these modern
concepts? Do they have a relevance to our daily
lives that is specifically modern? Let us take the
dictionary definition of an object as "anything
that is visible or tangible and is relatively stable in
form." It may also be something that "can be
apprehended intellectually", and in this sense
could be applicable to a musical performance. A
fragment is "a part broken off or detached", some¬
thing that is by definition "incomplete" or "unfin¬
ished".
One composes music by combining sound
elements to create a musical structure: a con¬
tinuum of sounds. Listening to music, one relies
on memory to retain the succession of sounds that
identifies the composition as an entity. If a listener
is preoccupied with other matters or momen¬
tarily nods off during the performance, the con¬
tinuity is lost and he or she may wake up during
the last movement completely confused by the
sounds coming from the stage. Even if one is
awake throughout the performance, has one wit¬
nessed a "relatively stable" musical object?
By modifying the elements which make up the
object, conductors, performers and acoustic con¬
ditions all influence the outcome of the com¬
poser's vision and the reality that the listener expe¬
riences. If a musical performance were completely
stable we would not have a multitude of record¬
ings of Beethoven's Fifth Symphony. One would
suffice.
FROM STABILITY
TO
FRAGMENTATION
The composer's job is to build unity within a
composition so as to ensure that it is compre¬
hensible to the listener. This will hopefully out¬
weigh the various chance factors that occur during
performance.
Before the twentieth century, certain con¬
ventions of form developed that brought a degree
of stability and comprehensibility to musical
compositions. Before hearing the first perfor¬
mance of a piano concerto in the eighteenth cen¬
tury, an educated listener already knew many
things about it. The concerto would probably
have three movements medium fast, slow, and
fast with a solo cadenza section leading up to the
final chords, or coda. This cadenza was intended
to offer the soloist some freedom of expression,
imposing a minimum of constraints and enabling
him to show musicianship and virtuosity. As
time went by, even this "unstable" section of the
piece became more controlled, until finally the
cadenzas were entirely written out by the com¬
poser. So much "stability" and "built-in memory"
were present in music by the end of the nine¬
teenth century that composers could not find
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
nwiwv
their own form of self-expression within these
accepted conventions.
The stability factor had to be "rethought" to
achieve an expression that reflected the times.
Twentieth-century artists sought ways of making
their creations multi-dimensional, fluid and less
stable. The objects were broken down and the
fragments took on a new importance when
regrouped to create timbres of extreme purity
and complexity, rhythms of clarity and confu¬
sion, and musical forms that were less predictable
and conventional.
The Man from Vienna
(1990), acrylic on canvas by
Valerio Adami.
By the beginning of this century, a break with
conventions was evident in all the artistic disci¬
plines. Fragmentation was the underlying theme.
To see this in painting one need only compare the
work of Manet and Courbet with that of Picasso
and Klee, and more recently with that of artists
such as Robert Rauschenberg and Valerio Adami
(sec illustration).
In architecture, this "deconstructionist"
approach finds an echo in the work of Bernard
Tschumi, who describes his designs as "discon¬
tinuous" structures that explore concepts of
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
"superimposition" and "dissociation". He
describes his work in social terms, calling it "post-
humanist" architecture that disperses the "force
of social regulation".
In literature, compare the novels of Henry
James with the "stream of consciousness" writing
of James Joyce, or the poetry of Wordsworth
with the fragmented style of e.e. cummings,
which obliges the reader to reconstruct the dis¬
persed letters, words and ideas on the page. The
cubist painter Georges Braque concisely made the
point when he said: "I do not believe in things but
in relations between things."
VOYAGING
INSIDE SOUNDS
Each artist now finds his or her own underlying
system. Each work must find its own compre¬
hensible form and create its own universe. Michel
Zbar's Contacts for trombone (1973) is an example
of how the composer can "liberate" the performer.
The form of the piece is almost entirely decided by
the trombonist, following his own routes while
choosing pitches, rhythms and dynamics from
the pallets of musical fragments provided within
each stopping-off point. Visually this resembles
the screen image from the computer music pro¬
gram MAX, which allows a composer or per¬
former to enter sounds via microphone or elec¬
tronic keyboard and transform them in countless
ways when routed to various "object" boxes that
he or she controls via computer.
Tristan Murail, one of the founders of "spec¬
tral" music in France, is a composer whose
choices of basic musical materials and method of
construction draw on the laws of natural sci¬
ence. With the aid of computers and techniques
developed at the Institut de Recherche et de
Coordination Acoustique-Musique (IRCAM)
in Paris, Murail analyses the harmonic spectrum
or overtone series present when specific tones are
produced on various instruments.
Overtones are frequencies higher than the
fundamental pitch which occur whenever a note
is sounded. The presence or absence of over¬
tones and their balance in relation to the funda¬
mental determine the "timbre" or "tone colour"
of a sound. This explains why we can discern
the difference between an identical pitch played
on a flute and an oboe. In his composition Dés¬
intégrations, for seventeen instruments and elec¬
tronic tape, it is as if Murail took a magnifying
glass to view the minute details of the sounds
which make up the raw material of the piece.
The title refers to the composer's process of "voy¬
aging inside the sounds". The sounds are broken
down and fragmented to display their constituent
parts. In one part of the work, "the brilliant
clouds of high chimes are derived from the dis¬
integration of the timbres (overtones) of flute,
clarinet and muted trombone."
The contemporary German composer Karl¬
heinz Stockhausen devises specific methods of
working, new underlying principles and con¬
straints for each new composition. His pieces
have often been criticized on their first perfor¬
mance but have later come to be regarded as
accomplished works which shed light on new
techniques of construction and new modes of
comprehension.
"I build a whole tree of different generations
of inter-relating moments. ... I control how
much they have in common," Stockhausen has
written about his work Momente ( 1 96 1 ) for four
choirs and thirteen instrumentalists. "Instead of
starting with something very homogeneous and
66
A computerized image of a
sound.
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
then breaking the homogeneity . . . the tradi¬
tional concept of building a musical continuum
... I start with completely separate instants."
These "moments" are fragments of musical mate¬
rial, each exhibiting a unique character (melodic,
chordal or even rhythmic) and obeying a set of
rules that determines how often they appear and
how much they have in common.
In the language of the French composer Pierre
Boulez the term "object" takes on a special
meaning in relation to music. For Boulez, a piece
of musical material is not regarded as being "unfin¬
ished" or a "broken off" fragment, but rather as
a potential musical object which is the starting
point or model for a "structure". It is an entity
whose possibilities for being transformed into a
musical object depend on the way in which its
potentialities are unlocked and on its behaviour in
relation to other potential musical objects.
Let us take, for example, a chord played on the
piano in the low register comprised of five notes.
This objet unitaire or solitary object is the point
of departure. It has certain characteristics which,
when exploited and put into a context, could
define it as part of a musical form. If this five-note
W
SfcllUd_LLL,í
-$-
Q (U
I
m
m
r r'
-L
T* T
df9
O «=3
M
r
0 S 0
Above, the score of
Manda/a (1985), by the
Norwegian composer Rolf
Wallin.
Left, Zyklus ( 1 96 1 ), a work
for solo percussion by
Karlheinz Stockhausen.
-J 1 I. I J4Jra fc LOi-Q i
chord is followed by a chord of three notes in the
middle register, certain relationships begin to
become comprehensible.
A "structure" is created in which the two
objects are linked to each other and can have a rela¬
tionship with other objects and structures that
follow. As the American composer John Cage
has shown, even musically "foreign" objects such
as car horns or tin cans become musical objects
when put into a suitable context. Objects create
structures and form is created by the "struc¬
turing" of these local structures in their turn.
The terms that I have attempted to define
have become somewhat "less stable" as this
article has progressed. The fragment in
"modern" musical terms and in Boulez' defin¬
ition becomes more and more difficult to find.
The moment it becomes detached from the
larger structure it can be regarded as a new
entity, an object made up of its own unique
possibilities of transformation.
But this takes us back to the "Big Bang":
there too one fragmented object brought forth
numerous independent and interdependent
objects harmonizing with each other to create a
large object, in that case the universe. 6J
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
Rimbaud's quest
by Sami Na'ir
i
68
IMBAUD's quest, which he described as a
"fabulous opera", radicalized and trans-
1 formed the great modernist anguish which
originated with Baudelaire. In Rimbaud and
Baudelaire modernity found its most illustrious
representatives and perhaps its harshest critics.
Through their deliberate efforts to transcend
themselves, they both experienced the feeling of
time's fundamental newness, of its endless accel¬
eration and of the wounds it inflicts and
through the brilliant success of their testimony
they also demonstrated time's ambiguity.
What else do they have in common? Both
felt that the modern age fundamentally shifts the
boundaries of the sacred. What Baudelaire com¬
plained of was the disappearance of aura the
halo of spirituality that hovered over human
beings and objects beneath the weight of a
growing materialism and dehumanization of the
relations between peoples, the spirit of calculation,
and the horrifying philosophy of positivism the
iron heel crushing fragile humanity. As for Rim¬
baud, he dreamed even in youth of escape from
tedium the anonymity and tedium of an age
in which everything was reduced to statistics.
Escape from his home town of Charleville to
Paris, from Paris to the Orient, from the Orient
to Nothingness.
At the very start of his quest he called for
revolt in the name of art and defined creation as
the profanation of all the modern age holds
sacred. "One must be absolutely modern," he
wrote in the collection of prose-poems entitled
Une Saison en Enfer.
Absolutely modem! Whatever can this mean?
Not simply this is the poet's cry, let's not forget
desanctifying all kinds of knowledge, power and
belief. But also, and especially, life itself:
Seen enough. The vision has been
encountered in every air.
Had enough. The noise oftowns. . . .
Known enough. The halts of life	
("Départ", Illuminations)
The problem of modernity is thus revealed: it
paralyzes itself with its own complacency. All too
often are we reminded, as though his youthful
flashes of genius had been nothing but a kind of
bolt from the blue, that Rimbaud was terribly
afflicted by the evil genius of time. But by
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
x
ia
Left, Etude pour Rimbaud
(1978), ballpoint pen
heightened with gouache
by Ernest Pignon Ernest,
after a painting by Henri
Fantin-Latour.
Opposite page, Rimbaud as
sketched by the French
poet Paul Verlaine in 1 872.
SAMI NAIR
is a French philosopher who is
professor of political science at
the University of Lausanne
(Switzerland). Among his
published works are an essay
on immigration in France, Le
Regard des vainqueurs. Essai sur
les enjeux français de
l'immigration (Paris, 1992).
choosing flight and renouncing art, was he not
simply, in an all-too-human fashion, running
away from the vast abyss his vision had opened
up before him?
For even as a youth, already in flight "from
every moral law", he grasped with disconcerting
lucidity the poetic revolution he bore within
himself. In his famous letter to Paul Demeny in
May 1871, returning to a theme that he had
already raised in his correspondence with Georges
Izambard, he wrote:
I sayyou have to be a visionary, make yourself
a visionary.
A poet makes himself a visionary through a
long, boundless and systematized disorganization
o/all the senses. Allforms oflove, ofsuffering, of
madness	 Unspeakable torment. . . , where he
becomes among all men the great invalid, the
great criminal, the great accursed and the
supreme Scientist! For he attains the unknown!
. . . and if, demented, he finally loses the under¬
standing ofhis visions, he will at least have seen
them! So what ifhe is destroyed on his ecstaticflight
through things unheard-of, unnameable. . .
By disorganization of the senses, Rimbaud
means neither decadent behaviour nor degen¬
erate values. He wants to go further: to set aside
standards and conventions in order to perceive the
Unknown. To penetrate the Unknown is to
become Wise, to discover the duality of Being, the
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
Une Saison en Enfer (1 989),
a 2.5-metre-high wooden
sculpture by Luc Simon.
principle of Good and Evil, of their felicitous
and infinite combination.
This passage to the other side of existence, the
other side of a self-satisfied modernity, is made at
the cost of a true cathartic experience governed by
madness and disease, sacrilege and malediction.
The poet perceives what the run-of-the-mill imag¬
ination cannot conceive of: "If," writes Rimbaud,
"what he brings from down there has form, he
gives it form; if it is formless, he makes it formless. "
Here we see the poet both as a "stealer of fire" and
as the creator of a new "language". Art must over¬
turn and transcend the boundaries of the known,
the familiar, the visible of possession and power.
"The poet," Rimbaud adds, "should define the
amount of unknown awakening in his time in the
universal soul	"
The poet, then, is on the other side ofTime. He
is not within Time, he is ahead of it. To be
absolutely modern is to see the world's time from
ahead. Poets are citizens of this new time; they
dwell in it in their innermost selves because they
are bringers of fire the fire that consumes what
exists. The poet seeks, not to annihilate, but to
become that "not too discontented citizen of a
metropolis considered modern because every
70
known taste has been avoided	" ("Ville", Illu¬
minations)
While Baudelaire takes his contemporaries'
anguish as a starting-point the better to immure
himself within it, Rimbaud attacks the surfeit
oozing from every pore of society. He is on the
side of a "ferocious philosophy" which says "let
the rest of the world go to hell". It is hardly sur¬
prising that the surrealists found in him a kindred
spirit. What if one aspect of modernity should be
the overthrow of the modern, the rejection of
what exists at a given moment? What if being
modern entails making a virtue of Negation, as the
Stoics did of pain? Steering a course for the
unknown, attempting the leap to the other side of
the precipice:
/ am an inventor ofvery different meritfrom
all those who have preceded me. . . . I am dedi¬
cated to a new confusion	 / expect to turn into
a very troublesome madman.
("Vies", Illuminations)
This may sound pretentious. But what should
we expect poets to do? Recite the litany of our
mediocrity, to glorify it? Turn their attention
from the present towards the past? This is Hei¬
degger's thesis: that poets, discoverers of Being,
and therefore of the very Source, make an inquiry
into the deepest resources of language, and hence
that their attention is fixed on the past.
This may well be true for the German romantic
poets like Hölderlin, and perhaps even for the
nineteenth-century French romantics who
regarded the return to the source the journey to
the Orient as an initiation test for the conquest
of Truth and Beauty. But nothing of this sort
applies to Rimbaud. His revolutionary modernity
is entirely directed towards the future: he chal¬
lenges romanticism in the name of a radically
individualist libertarianism. This modernity of
Rimbaud's is no acquiescent passivity before the
disruptive force of science and technology, but
rather a quality of soul, a state of subjectivity, a kind
of spirituality, what is meant by the German word
Stimmung. Even more, it is opening towards the
elsewhere, getting an edge on the sacred, greeting
the breath of genius: "Let us know how to hail him
and see him, . . . follow his vision, his breath, his
body, his light." ("Génie", Illuminations)
Perhaps we are incapable of greeting in this
way; perhaps we are too cautious to understand
the poet's fire. But the artist, in moments of hap¬
piness which is to say in the states of rapture
which accompany true creation greets the
Unknown and presents it to us as an offering. The
face of the young Rimbaud is emblematic of this
experience. That is why it is so unforgettably,
outrageously beautiful.
There is a contemporary artist with the Bib¬
lical name of Luc Simon whose entire work is a
testimony to this Rimbaldian beauty. Rimbaud on
the walls of Paris in 1968, or astride the ruins of
another wall, now happily destroyed, in Berlin in
1989 Rimbaud the poet of our hopes and our
suffering, as youthful as adolescence, novelty,
Rimbaud eternally seeking "truth in a soul and a
body". ("Adieu", Une Saison en Enfer).
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
SCARVES
FOR THE
SILK ROADS
A fabric design competition
i the theme of the Silk
ad has been organized by
mce's Association
itionale pour la
"omotion des Arts
Décoratifs de Tissus
(ANPADT, Paris), in
collaboration with Unesco's
ten-year "Integral Study of
the Silk Roads: Roads of
Dialogue" project (1987-
1997). The five prize¬
winners were presented with
certificates during an
exhibition held at Unesco's
Paris Headquarters from 22
to 30 June. A limited number
of the winning entries each
te a silk scarf, numbered
and bearing the words
"Unesco, Routes de la
soie" will go on sale at a
price of FF 1,200 ($218).
iceeds from the sale will
to the Silk Roads project.
rder forms may be
named from
NPADT, 17, Rue de Cléry,
1002 Paris, France,
1.(33-1)42-36-59-10.
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
A FRIEND IN NEED
To improve water management in
Africa's arid Sahel region, a new
network, known as FRIEND, has been
set up under the auspices of UNESCO's
International Hydrological Programme.
An acronym for Flow Regimes from
International and Network Data Sets,
FRIEND will collect and centralize
hydrological data from nine countries
of central and west Africa: Benin,
Burkina Faso, Cameroon, the Central
African Republic, Côte d'Ivoire,
Guinea, Guinea Bissau, Mali and Chad.
Most of the region's drainage basins
extend across national boundaries, so
the information available within
individual countries is usually not
complete. Compiling the data will help
the countries plan their water use,
dams and irrigation schemes on a
more rational basis.
SAYING THE CHILDREN
On I April, the Director-General of
Unesco, Mr. Federico Mayor,
presented the Organization's gold
medal of Dubrovnik to Helmut
Thoma, Director-General of RTL,
Germany's largest private television
station. The award honoured Thoma's
contribution to the success of
"Children in Need", a fund-raising
campaign launched in Germany by
Unesco Goodwill Ambassador Ure
Ohoven in October 1 992. More than
$ 1 .6 million have been raised, most of
which will go to Bosnian refugee
children. The rest will help fund
educational resource centres in
Somalia and basic education
programmes for street children in Viet
Nam, Mexico and Romania.
NEWS OF THE WORLD HERITAGE
In February, UNESCO's World Heritage
Centre published the first issue of the
World Heritage Newsletter, a 1 6-page 71
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
periodical which will appear three
times a year in French and English and
will provide information on activities
and developments affecting sites
around the world. The first issue
reveals that the criteria for selecting
World Heritage Sites are to be revised
to enable cultural landscapes
described as representing "the
combined works of nature and
man" to be entered on the World
Heritage List, and notes that a data¬
base on the World Heritage,
incorporating reports and
photographs, is to be established.
Known as "Heritage 200 1 ", the
archive will store material relating to
some 200 sites and other properties
such as ancient manuscripts and
museum exhibits. The World Heritage
Newsletter is available on request from
the World Heritage Centre, Unesco,
7 Place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07
SP, France.
FROM THE DOUBLE HELIX
TO THE HUNAN GENOME
Nearly 300 scientists, including 14
Nobel Prize-winners, gathered at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris in April
for a symposium to mark the 40th
anniversary of the discovery of the
double helix. Among those present
were Francis Crick and James Watson,
who in 1 953 made the discovery of
the helical (spiral-ladder-shaped)
structure of the deoxyribonucleic acid
(DNA) molecule which carries our
genetic information, thereby opening
the way for a new branch of science,
molecular genetics. Discussions at the
3-day symposium focussed on the
"state of the art" in molecular genetics
and the directions it is taking. More
than fifty papers were presented,
notably on the organization of the
human genome, genetic diseases, and
the ethical and legal issues raised by
genetic experimentation.
12
PEOPLE AND PLANTS
To further the conservation of plant
species and knowledge of their use,
Unesco, the World Wide Fund for
Nature (WWF) and the Royal Botanic
Gardens Kew (UK) have launched a
project entitled "People and Plants:
Ethnobotany and the Sustainable Use
of Plant Resources". The aim of the
project is to bring ethnobotanists and
local people together in order to
study traditional ways of using plant
resources, with a view to improving
the life of rural populations in
developing countries. Five manuals will
be produced, first in English and then
in Spanish and possibly in other
languages later. The subjects chosen
are: invasive plants; ethnobotany and
conservation; priority sites for plant
conservation; the sustainable use of
wild plants; and plant conservation
databases. For further information,
please contact Unesco, Division of
Ecological Sciences, Man and the
Biosphere Programme, I Rue Miollis,
75732 Paris Cedex 1 5, France.
Listing
Pagan's monuments
Pagan (in what is now Myanmar)
became capital of the first unified
Burmese kingdom (1044-1287) during
the reign of King Anoratha. Today there
are more than 2,000 monuments at
Pagan about half the number
recorded in an inventory ordered by
King Mohnyin in the 15th century.
Earthquakes have since taken a heavy
toll, but the site remains one of the
world's most spectacular Buddhist sites.
The Burmese, an animist people
originally from central Asia, were con¬
verted to Buddhism by King Anoratha
(1044-1077), a great military leader
who also built many temples, monas¬
teries and stupas as well as a Pitakat
Talk (library) for the Pitaka, or scrip¬
tures, he had had brought from Thatön,
capital of the vanquished Mon people.
These religious edifices were con¬
structed of brick rather than the wood
and bamboo used for domestic pur¬
poses. Among Anoratha's most remark¬
able constructions were the temple of
Ananda, the magnificent Shwe-Hsan-
Daw stupa (built to house a hair of the
Buddha), and the Shwezigon stupa,
completed in the reign of his successor
King Kyanzittha, which Marco Polo was
to call the "Golden Pagoda".
In the wake of a devastating earth¬
quake that struck Pagan on 8 July 1975,
a decision was taken to make, with
UNESCO's participation, a systematic
inventory of the monuments of Pagan.
Started in 1982, the "Inventory Pro¬
ject" has collected data for 2,260 mon¬
uments, each one of which will be fea¬
tured, complete with line drawings,
photographs and descriptive notes, in a
nine-volume Inventory ofMonuments at
Pagan by Pierre Pichard. The first
volume (ISBN I 870838 01 7), pub¬
lished jointly by Kiscadale Ltd., the Ecole
Française d'Extrême-Orient (EFEO)
and Unesco, is now available, price
$145 or £75. For further information,
please contact Unesco Publishing, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP,
France. Tel. (33-1) 45-68-22-22; Fax
(33-1)42-73-30-07.
Françoise Legendre
This article is one
of a series in which
the Director-General
of Unesco sets out
his thinking on matters
of current concern
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
They could have done so much,
but dared to do so little...'
I am convinced that in the years ahead it is going to
be essential to be able to train fully-fledged citizens,
who will feel that unless they are participating in
the life of their community they do not exist. And in
order to exist, in order to exercise their responsibilities
as citizens, they will need access to knowledge. Edu¬
cation is not only instilling knowledge, but awakening
the immense creative potential that lies within each of
us, enabling all of us to develop our capacities to the full,
the better to contribute to the societies in which we live.
With regard to the dissemination of scientific and
technical knowledge, it is borne in on me every day
how sadly scientific information is lacking in the deci¬
sion-making process. Far too many decisions with
far-reaching consequences in the domains of energy
and the environment, for example are influenced by
the emotions. It is our responsibility to provide deci¬
sion-makers with absolutely reliable data enabling
them to reach objective conclusions.
I also feel that there are two ideas that we should
push as hard as we can to have accepted and applied.
The first is linked to lifelong education: the educa¬
tional process can no longer be defined as the acquisi¬
tion of knowledge which precedes entry into the
working world. It is and will of necessity become
increasingly a protean process extending over an
entire lifetime and covering a variety of activities.
The second concept is that of educational partnership.
When we think of education, we think of the state.
However, the responsibility for education is not the
state's alone; it is incumbent upon civil society at all its
levels and in all its structures. For it is only by making
the whole of society aware of its duty to take up the chal¬
lenge of education that we will be able to lay a firm
foundation for the training of fully-fledged citizens.
At this point, a word about higher education. To my
mind, this level of education has too long been con¬
sidered a luxury, and thus passed over by the developing
countries in favour of basic education, which has
attracted all the attention. It is true that higher educa¬
tion is only available to a privileged group of young
people: 92 per cent of the world's eighteen- to twenty-
three-year-olds do not have access to it. All the more
reason to be extremely demanding of those who do!
Society should make these young elites realize that
they are already part of the social fabric, and have
responsibilities to shoulder. At university, they must
learn to take the initiative, and begin to place their
imaginations and energies in the service of the trans¬
formations that this new era is demanding of all mem¬
bers of the community.
Finally, I should like to underscore the importance
of education in enhancing mutual understanding and
promoting co-operation between peoples. In a world
where distances are shrinking and differences abound,
there is nothing to be gained by locking the door and
withdrawing into oneself. The best way to survive,
and at the same time add a new dimension to one's life,
is to learn to live with others, and to listen to what they
have to say. Tolerance does not mean "tolerating"
others, but getting to know, understand, respect, and
why not? admire them.
What is needed most today, what young people
and particularly teenagers who are about to complete
their secondary studies are demanding of us more or
less explicitly, is guidance to help them chart their
course. Unless we supply them with this without delay,
we risk witnessing major social upheavals. We must
take action, even at the risk of making mistakes. The
worst of all would be to do nothing in the face of the
intolerable.
We are not prepared to rise to all the challenges of
the future poverty, population, the environment,
ethnic coexistence because we are still working with
the tools of the past. We must remedy this situation as
quickly as possible, so that our grandchildren will not
speak of us with Camus' terrible words: "They could
have done so much, but dared to do so little " h
73
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
Santísima Trinidad, memories of
slavery and sugar by Edouard ea^y
74
Three hundred and eighty kilometres
south-east of Havana on Cuba's
southern coast, a jewel of colonial
architecture lies far from the bustle of the
modern world. Backing onto the El Escam-
bray massif, whose foothills, the Gua-
muhaya, take their name from the region's
former indigenous people, the town of
Santísima Trinidad has not many more
than 30,000 inhabitants. Its narrow cob¬
bled streets are flanked by eighteenth- and
nineteenth-century churches and palaces,
and by houses adorned with wooden-
railed balconies and wrought-iron grilles
through which magnificent, Andalusian-
style garden courtyards can be glimpsed.
Every now and then a horse-drawn cart
with squeaking wheels emerges from a
side-street. Further on a mule laden with
jars of drinking water ambles along. No
cars or motorcycles disturb the town's
timeless peace.
Memories of the past of Santísima
Trinidad, which was included on Unesco's
World Heritage List in 1988, are concen¬
trated around the Plaza Mayor. Here, giant
palm-trees adorn the square-shaped cen¬
tral garden where young and old come to
sit as evening falls. Overlooking the Plaza
are the Convent of San Francisco, the
church of the Santísima Trinidad and a
number of noble houses.
The most imposing of these houses is
that which once belonged to Nicolás de La
Cruz y Brunei, the owner ofsugar planta¬
tions and hundreds of slaves, who in 1836
was made a count by the King of Spain.
The ochre-walled palace was built
between 1740 and 1808. Its ground floor
gives onto an inner patio considered to
be one of the most beautiful of its kind in
Cuba. The first floor, which now houses the
Romantic Museum, has a cedarwood
ceiling and furniture of precious local
wood. Chandeliers of Bohemian glass,
Sèvres vases, Spanish and Dutch porce¬
lain and French clocks decorate the
boudoirs and salons. There is even a
marble bath and two splendid spittoons
that were imported from England. The
Brunet Palace, which was restored a few
years ago, is a monument to the wealth of
the great families of Trinidad in the late
eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries.
AN ARISTOCRACY OF SUGAR
Trinidad is the third oldest town in Cuba.
It was founded in 1514 by Diego Velazquez,
who had just completed the conquest of
the island, the Caribbean's largest. He knew
that there were gold mines in a nearby
valley, and as a result built a small fort and
half a dozen houses a fewkilometres from
the coast. Fifty metres from the Plaza
Mayor stands thejigüe, a great tree planted
the day the city was founded, on the spot
where the first Mass was celebrated. A
commemorative plaque honours the
memory of Bartolomé de Las Casas, an
ardent champion of the indigenous inhab¬
itants who were massacred or reduced to
slavery by the conquistadors.
After suffering on several occasions from
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
the depredations of the pirates and cor¬
sairs who scoured the Caribbean, Trinidad
relapsed into tropical languor. Far from
Havana, the seat of the island's governors
and the crossroads of the main lines of
communication, it turned away from the
outside world and lived for two and a half
centuries on its sparse crops and the valu¬
able timber grown nearby. In August 1762,
it was abruptly awakened from its torpor
when, after a two-month siege, the British
seized the port of Havana, imposing on
Cuba free trade with the rest of the world.
In the eleven months during which the
island was occupied, a thousand ships
unloaded tons of merchandise and hun¬
dreds ofAfrican slaves.
After the British withdrew (accepting
Florida in exchange), the Creoles
Spaniards born in Cuba soon realized
that free trade favoured their interests
against those of the government in Madrid.
The successful sugar-cane producers
extended their estates beyond the
provinces of Havana and Matanzas,
forming the nucleus of the sacarocracia,
the sugar aristocracywhose influence was
to be crucial in shaping the island's history.
Their ambitions were furthered by the
arrival in 1791 of large numbers ofrefugees
from Haiti, where plantations and
refineries had been burned down by thou¬
sands of slaves under the leadership of
Toussaint L'Ouverture. This unexpected
influx of labour at Cuba's eastern tip and in
the Trinidad region gave a boost to the
economy.
Determined to win from the British and
French colonies the monopoly of sugar
exports to Europe, the owners of the
Cuban plantations began to organize
themselves. Five leading planters, who
between them owned dozens ofrefineries,
took control of the slave trade, thereby
enabling themselves to increase produc¬
tion. The slaves led a wretched life on the
ingenios, vast estates that gradually spread
over the island at the expense of the forests
and their rare species of trees. Theyworked
sixteen hours a day, with only one small
meal around midday. The day began and
ended with prayers signalled by the plan¬
tation bell, which was also used to sound
the alarm ifa slave escaped or a fire broke
out. The forty-five-metre-high Iznaga
Tower, the only surviving monument from
this era, still marks the entrance to one of
the great plantations of the San Luis Valley,
outside Trinidad. It has been completely
restored and is now topped by an obser¬
vation post and a belfry with fluted
columns.
On the estate known as the Santísima
Trinidad most Cuban ingenios had
names associated with the Christian reli¬
gion Esteban José Santa Cruz de Oviedo
prided himself on possessing the largest
criadero de criollos (literally, "negro stock-
farm"). There, penned like cattle, the chil
dren of slaves were prepared for the work
they would have to start at the age of
twelve. Their mothers were only allowed to
see them once every ten days. Don
Esteban exchanged or sold them at will.
His wife was sterile, but he had twenty-
six mulatto children. As a good father, he
sent his offspring to study in New York.
The six best students were rewarded with
a trip to Paris.
AN ILLUSTRIOUS GUEST
By the end of the eighteenth century, the
wealth of the plantations enabled
Trinidad's planters to build themselves
magnificent homes. The Padrón family
residence, at the corner of Desengaño
Street, today houses a Museum ofArchae¬
ology, and the Municipal History Museum
occupies the former home of the Justo
German Cantero family. Trinidad's patri¬
cian families have left traces of their
grandeur all over the town. Devoutly
Catholic, they contributed generously to
the building ofchurches and convents. In
the convent of St. Francis of Assisi, an
IUI
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
Opposite page, the Plaza Mayor, Trinidad
(Cuba).
Below left, a paved street In the Old Town.
Below, the Brunet Palace.
unusual museum recalls memories of
bandit-hunting and the struggle waged
by the people of Trinidad against both
internal and external enemies.
Trinidad is proud to count among its
guests Alexander von Humboldt, the cel¬
ebrated German naturalist and explorer,
who spent forty-eight hours there on his
first visit to Cuba, between December 1800
and March 1801. After leaving the port of
Batabano, on the south coast, the boat in
which he was travelling was forced to put
in at the mouth of the River Guaurabo,
half a dozen kilometres from Trinidad, in
order to take on drinking water. The gov¬
ernor of the region, a nephew of the
astronomer Antonio Ulloa, welcomed
Humboldt with all the respect due to such
a distinguished figure, and the rich planter
Antonio Padrón gave a reception in his
honour that was attended byTrinidad high
society. Humboldt gives a detailed account
ofhis stay in his correspondence, notably
describing an ascent ofPopa hill, where an
eighteenth-century church still stands, in
order to calculate its height with surveying
instruments.
Impressed by the welcome he received
from the leading families of Trinidad
and this despite his well-known distaste for
slavery Humboldt resumed his sea-
journey on the night of 15 March 1801. As
he left, a local priest and occasional poet
declaimed a sonnet from the quayside in
honour of the Orinoco delta, where the
illustrious scholar who recorded the
anecdote in his "Political Essay on the
Island of Cuba", republished in Havana in
1960 had first set foot on American soil.
Cubans, or at least the inhabitants of
Trinidad, regard him as the second des¬
cubridor (discoverer) of the island, after
Christopher Columbus.
EDOUARD BAILBY is a French journalist who
has been a correspondent with the weekly
(.'Express and a press officer in UNESCO's Office of
Public Information. He is the author of a guide to
Cuba (Cuide de Cuba, Arthaud, Paris, 6th edition,
1993) and a study on Oscar Niemeyer scheduled
for publication later this year.
75
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
reflections Traditions for Tomorrow
by Diego Gradis
ï
I RADiTiONS for Tomorrow is anon-gov¬
ernmental organization which is
active in most parts of Central and
South America, where it supports the
struggle of the descendants of the pre-
Columbian peoples to preserve their cul¬
tural identity. It was founded in 1986, and
has had an official working relationship
with Unesco since 1992.
Traditions for Tomorrow does not try to
persuade the groups with which it works to
return to their traditional ways but rather
to take their traditions into account when
building their future. The support that it is
asked to provide is always the result of a
spontaneous initiative from a local com¬
munity and is designed to increase that
community's awareness of the value of a
traditional form of cultural expression in
such fields as language, ritual, medicine,
handicrafts, dance, music or education.
Traditions for Tomorrow uses the word
culture in its widest possible sense as the
expression of a way of life. The type of
back-up the organization provides is
designed to supplement aid available from
other bodies working in the fields ofhealth
care and material welfare.
Our relations with those with whom we
work people such as the Maya peasants
of the Guatemala highlands, the Cuna fish¬
ermen who live on the San Bias Islands
off the coast ofPanama, the Aymara shep¬
herds of the shores of Lake Titicaca are
based on mutual respect. Each side makes
a contribution ofequal value. The financial
support we provide is neither more nor
less indispensable to a given project than
the expertise and motivation of our part¬
ners on the spot. A preliminary encounter
takes place in the field before any com¬
mitment is made. This is an opportunity
for us to listen, to look, and to take stock of
the situation, not an attempt to impose
or even to suggest a specific course of
action. The main goal of Traditions for
Tomorrow is to help people to realize that
cultural identity is an asset that can serve
development. How can there be any devel¬
opment if people do not assume respon¬
sibility for their own lives? Our work pro¬
vides its beneficiaries with their first
opportunity to take full charge of the
_ _ administration of a project.
* W Asenseofcommunityisoneofthemain
factors favouring the survival of minority
groups in Latin America. However, as a
result ofvarious religious, administrative,
educational and economic factors, the
cement that binds communities together
has been gradually eroded. In addition,
many forms of aid sidetrack the sense of
community and associate it with imported
modes of organization that are often ill-
adapted to the local situation. The pro¬
jects supported by Traditions for
Tomorrow seek to strengthen traditional
community structures within the frame¬
work ofactivities which have always been
associated with the community in ques¬
tion.
Three specific experiences, in Panama,
Ecuador and Chile respectively, provide a
good illustration of the organization's work
A CULTURAL CONGRESS IN THE
SAN BLAS ISLANDS
In recent decades the 40,000 Cuna Indians
who live in the San Bias archipelago off
These Afro-Ecuadorian children in
San Lorenzo (Ecuador) meet every day for
traditional dancing.
the Caribbean coast of Panama have
assimilated the Western-type structures
ofmainland Panamanian society. Because
space is limited many of the islanders have
migrated to Panama City, but these
migrants have, in spite ofbeing uprooted,
succeeded in maintaining close links with
their homeland, "Cuna Yala".
The Cuna have won an international
reputation for having preserved a large
degree of autonomy. However, frequent
contact with Panamanian society has
begun a process ofacculturation, above all
among young people, especially where
religion and spiritual life are concerned. To
halt this erosion, which they regard as a
threat to their internal cohesion and to
their eventual survival as a people, the
Cuna created in 1972 a "General Congress
of Cuna Culture" which meets for four or
five days several times a year, each time in
a different place, and is attended by all
their religious leaders, who are the
guardians of tradition. These meetings,
with their prayers, festivities, dances and
the commemoration ofCuna heroes, bring
together people from nearby islands and
create a bond between the Cuna people.
The Cuna have asked Traditions for
Tomorrow to help them to buy two motor
boats to enable representatives ofdifferent
communities to attend meetings of the
Congress. They have also asked us for help
in acquiring technical and office equip¬
ment that the young people will need to
carry out, under the auspices of the Con¬
gress, an in-depth survey on the history
and use ofmedicinal plants. The results of
the survey will be published.
IDENTITY AND SCHOOLING
For some time the Saraguro Indians of the
Tenta region of Ecuador have been
unhappy about the schooling that the
Quito-based educational system imposed
on their children. From the age of four,
their children had to leave behind in the
school cloakroom not only their tradi¬
tional clothing, but their language
(Quechua), the knowledge they had
received from their parents, and their spe¬
cific ways of thinking. What they learned
from their teachers, most of whom did
]]>
</page>
<page number="77">
<![CDATA[
Members of a Quechua community
in the Cuzco department of Peru gather
for a meeting with
Traditions for Tomorrow.
not speak Quechua, was remote from their
way of life and pushed them to become
school dropouts.
In reaction to this, in the late 1980s the
people of Tenta used local construction
methods to build their own education
centre where they could teach a syllabus,
devised by themselves, which consists of
adapted forms of the subjects taught at
the state schools and is complemented by
initiation in manual, cultural and pro¬
ductive activities. The five teachers are
members of the community and were
chosen by it. Their teaching calls for close
collaboration with the local people. The
results obtained since 1988 have been so
satisfactory that the school has been given
official status by the government. Today
some of its pupils have finished their pri¬
mary schooling, and for the first time chil¬
dren from Tenta are going to be enrolled at
the secondary school in the nearby town.
Traditions for Tomorrow responded
favourably to a request to help the school
obtain equipment. The money has been
used to improve the building and to buy
equipment such as a loom, printing
machinery, farm and woodworking tools,
sewing machines, clothes and musical
instruments.
ANDEAN CARNIVAL
In the last fifteen years, drought, mine clo¬
sures and overcrowding in the outskirts
ofLa Paz (Bolivia), have driven the Aymara
and Quechua Indians down from the
Chilean and Bolivian altiplano to the fer¬
tile valleys of the Arica region in northern
Chile. From a way of life centred on the vil¬
lage, traditional customs and the family
unit, hundreds of families suddenly found
themselves in a state of economic depen¬
dence in a land that was not their own.
The newcomers found that Chilean society
was often difficult for them to enter. The
younger generation, which has no experi¬
ence of its Andean origins and which feels
rejected by the majority society, is giving
way to delinquency (drugs, alcohol, pros¬
titution), thereby making the gulfbetween
the two societies even wider.
During carnival week, the Indians of the
Arica region have tried in recent years to
recreate in the Azapa valley an event that
would rekindle the spirit of the Andean
tradition and reunite this exiled popula¬
tion. First spontaneously, then in a more
organized fashion, the "carnaval Andino"
("Andean carnival") of San Miguel has
gradually become for the Quechua and
Aymara a meeting point between past and
future, an annual break during which
young and old alike return to their roots
and renew the links that traditionally
bound their community together.
Since the return of democracy, those
involved with the carnival have created
an association which, with the support of
Traditions for Tomorrow, is now working to
build a headquarters where meetings and
cultural events can be held. Traditions for
Tomorrow has also assembled a stock of
costumes and traditional Andean musical
instruments for the carnival. The organi¬
zation has received official recognition
from the government ofChile for this pro¬
ject, which in 1992 was also recognized
by Unesco's World Decade for Cultural
Development.
DIEGO GRADIS is a Franco-Swiss international
lawyer who has published many articles on
Amerindian problems and environmental issues.
He is the founder-president of Traditions for
Tomorrow (France. Switzerland, U.S.A.).
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="78">
<![CDATA[
portrait
Mahmoud Mokhtar
(1891-1934)
by Magdi Youssef
Atthe beginning of the Muslim era in Egypt,
the art of statuary, which had flourished to
an outstanding degree during Antiquity,
went into a long decline as a result of Islam's rejec¬
tion of representations of the human figure on
the grounds that they were an insult to the divine
privilege of creation. Bowing to this interdict,
Muslim artists turned to experimentation with
"abstract" forms that were simultaneously real
and visionary, as can be seen in calligraphy, the
arabesque and Arab-Islamic architecture.
Egypt's contacts with Europe during the Enlight¬
enment, culminating in the invasion by Napoleon
Bonaparte at the end of the eighteenth century, led
to a change of attitude towards the "modern"
plastic arts. However it was not until 1908 that
Cairo followed the example ofWestern cities and
acquired a school of fine arts and that young
people began to show enthusiasm for sculpture as
a creative discipline.
One student who enrolled at the school in the
year it opened was eighteen-year-old Mahmoud
Mokhtar. He distinguished himself as a sculptor,
and in 1911 won a scholarship to study in Paris,
where Rodin and Maillol reigned as the undis¬
puted masters.
At this period, Egyptian society was seeking to
define a modern frame of reference for its cul¬
tural identity, as a platform for national and polit¬
ical demands. Mokhtar was still living in Paris
when the Egyptian revolution of 1919 broke out.
With the clamour ofEgyptian crowds echoing in
his mind, Mokhtar conceived his most important
work, The Renaissance of Egypt. He exhibited a
scale model of it and dreamed of returning to
Cairo to continue his work there.
Like his predecessors in ancient Egypt, Mokhtar
wanted his statue to live for ever. He decided to
execute the monumental work in Aswan granite,
the stone that Egyptian sculptors had used at the
time of the Pharaohs. The costs ofhis project were
more than the government could afford, however,
and so a subscription was launched. Completed in
1928, the statue became a cultural landmark,
inspiring a number ofpoets and writers, including
Tewfik el-Hakim.
The Renaissance ofEgypt, which is four metres
long and three metres high, depicts a lion with a
man's head (an allusion to the Sphinx ofGiza) beside
which stands a proud peasant woman, one ofwhose
hands is placed on the lion's head as though she is
holding the animal back; with the other she draws
aside the veil that covers her face. Both figures are
looking in the same direction, perhaps towards a
new dawn, towards the rising sun, symbol of res¬
urrection for the ancient Egyptians.
In addition to this masterpiece and a number of
monuments that adorn the squares of Cairo and
Alexandria, Mahmoud Mokhtar executed a large
number ofsculptures, which can be seen today in
the museum recently restored by the Egyptian
Ministry of Culture that bears his name. They
depict peasant men and women at work and dis¬
play a masterly power of execution and a perfect
balance ofplanes and volumes. At the entrance to
the museum stands one ofMokhtar's majorworks,
The Keeper ofthe Secret (1 926), which has the mys¬
terious density of ancient statuary.
Mahmoud Mokhtar is a perfect example of cre¬
ative fertility shaped by training in Western tech¬
niques and used to serve an inspiration that was
authentically Egyptian.
78
The Renaissance of Egypt
(1928), a granite sculpture
(3x4 m.) by Mahmoud
Mokhtar that stands in
front of the University of
Cairo.
MAGDI YOUSSEF
is an Egyptian writer who is
vice-president of the
International Association of
Intercultural Studies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="79">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS OF THE WORLD
A voyage through
European
literature
by Edgar Reichmann
Lettres
eennes
HISTOIRE DE LA LITTERATURE EUROPEENNE
The recent publication of a 1 ,025 -page
illustrated Histoire de la littérature
européenne ("History of European
Literature") is an event that marks the con¬
clusion of an ambitious enterprise. The
editors and contributors faced a threefold
challenge to avoid becoming the pris¬
oners of a reductive Eurocentrism and
neglecting to take account ofwhat Europe
has inherited from other parts of the world;
to prevent their work from becoming a
vast catalogue in which European litera¬
ture is compartmentalized into linguistic
and national traditions; and to identify,
on the threshold of the third millennium,
and after the failure of the great ideolo¬
gies that have marked our century, any
new trends that may be developing to fill
the void these ideologies have left behind.
A MANY-FACETED LITERATURE
The History is the work of a team of 150
university teachers from all over Europe. It
shows that, while Europe has many dif¬
ferent literary traditions, there is never¬
theless a single European literature. The
editors, literary historians Annick Benoit-
Dusausoy and Guy Fontaine, describe the
contacts between Europe and the rest of
the world that encouraged the circulation
ofpeople and ideas and the movements of
peoples over the centuries. They rightly
remind us thatAsia and the Mediterranean
coast ofAfrica, the cradles of our civiliza¬
tion, have, together with the early Greek
myths, left an indelible imprint on Euro¬
pean literature past and present.
Via Spain, Arab poets influenced the
troubadours of Provence, while Asia
bequeathed to Europe a spirit of oriental
refinement. In the inter-war years Africa
south of the Sahara contributed to the dis¬
covery by European avant-gardes ofa new
view of reality. India and China, the Malay
archipelago and Oceania, mysterious
islands and deserts of fire and ice, all exer¬
cised their fascination on writers as varied
as Kipling, Rimbaud, Malraux, Daniel
Defoe, Jules Verne and the Polish-born
English novelist Joseph Conrad. More
recently such important figures as the
Q
J
¡V
B
C
Cj
H
Senegalese Leopold Sédar Senghor, the
West Indian René Depestre, Trinidad-born
VS. Naipaul, the South African André
Brink, Alejo Carpentier ofCuba, Tahar Ben
Jalloun from North Africa, Argentina's Jorge
Luis Borges and Isaac Bashevis Singer, an
American of Jewish extraction, have all
helped renew the European heritage
without turning their back on their own
traditions. By its very conception, the work
avoids the trap of isolationism.
A WORK OF CULTURAL SYNTHESIS
The authors also deserve praise for having
produced both a reference book and an
exercise in cultural synthesis. Authors and
their works are not listed alphabetically
according to their geographical affilia¬
tions. Instead the reader can trace the
Histoire de la littérature européenne
("History of European Literature"), edited
by Annick Benoit-Dusausoy and Guy
Fontaine, published by Hachette-Éducation,
Paris, 1,025 pp., complete with index and
bibliography.
development and mutual influence of the
Graeco-Latin, Judaeo-Christian, Byzan¬
tine and Nordic minds as expressed in lit¬
erature, up to the philosophy of the
Enlightenment and the collapse of the
ideologies that have stained our century
with blood. While exploring the principal
literary genres and trends, the reader
covers a vertiginous range of thought and
creativity.
The scholars who have told this fasci¬
nating story also set themselves the 79
]]>
</page>
<page number="80">
<![CDATA[
B00K5 OF THE WORLD
80
daunting task of relating important Euro¬
pean authors to other cultures, in some
cases geographically and chronologically
remote.
While Swift, Rabelais, Molière, Racine,
Cervantes, Chekhov, Proust and Kafka are
known all over the world, authors writing
in less widely-used languages are much
less familiar. It is true that good transla¬
tions of the Albanian Ismail Kadaré, the
Portuguese poet Fernando Pessoa and the
Czech novelist Milan Kundera have made
these authors well-known, and the essayist
E.M. Cioran and the dramatist Eugène
Ionesco, Romanians who have longwritten
in French, are equally celebrated. But the
fine Greek poet Constantine Cavafy, the
Polish 'novelist Tadeusz Konwicki, who
draws his inspiration from his Lithuanian
ancestors, or the late Danilo Kis, a Mon¬
tenegrin Jew who wrote in Serbian and
described metaphorically the similarity
of all forms of totalitarianism, are little-
read by speakers of the world's main lan¬
guages. The extraordinary diversity of
these literatures still remains largely unrec¬
ognized, as are their points ofconvergence
amid the infinite reflections of a unique,
multi-faceted reality. The authors of this
splendid work have brilliantly recon¬
structed the harmonious links between
different literatures as revealed in unex¬
pected and hidden convergences.
UNVEILING NEW TRENDS
What of the future ofEuropean literature?
The debate about post-modernism
opened in France by Jean-François
Lyotard's work La Condition post-mod-
erne ("The Post-Modem Condition", 1979)
is still continuing in the universities. But
the avant-garde and the nouveau roman
have run out of steam, socialist realism is
long dead, and those works that expressed
opposition to dictatorial regimes have lost
their raison d'être with the collapse of the
dictatorships, which has also put paid to
the old "official" literatures. Meanwhile,
the freedom suddenly accorded authors of
the former Eastern bloc to write what they
want has left them shell-shocked.
In the West narrative seems to be
coming back into vogue, and with it a
renewal of the attractions of classic story¬
telling, blending realism, magical realism,
folk- tale and myth. Historical novels and
works that dramatize real-life events are
both making something of a comeback.
Meanwhile, poetry refuses to fit into any
fixed category and goes its own way. Poets
cannot breathe when confronted by
tyrants' rules and regulations; they can
only flourish when they can get to grips
with words in an atmosphere of creative
freedom. However, it remains to be seen
which of today's movements and trends
posterity will remember.
by Isabelle Leymarie
TRADITIONAL
MUSIC
SWITZERLAND.
Zäuerli, Yodel ofAppenzell
Musics and Musicians of the
World
Unesco Collection/Audivis
CD D 8026
Ethnomusicologist Hugo
Zemp is a specialist in
yodelling and also, oddly
enough, in the music of the
Solomon Islands. On this
compact disc he presents some
surprising examples oí zäuerli
yodelling from the Swiss
canton ofAppenzell,
performed not as folklore but
in a workaday context by
mountain people while milking
cows or leading them to
pasture. These polyphonic
yodels have little in common
with the usual tourist fare. The
sometimes untempered
singing, with notes often
reached by glissandi, in some
ways recalls Mongol music,
and the cowbells in the
background contribute to the
oriental effect, like gongs in a
Chinese or Korean opera.
GUINEA.
The Nyamakalas from Futa
jalon
Music from the World
CD Buda 92530-2
Once considered as
miscreants by the fervent Peul
Muslims of Futa Jalon because
of their love of dance, music
and song, the Nyamakalas have
inherited a long musical
tradition. The group on this
record, however, was formed
relatively recently, following
the establishment of the
Second Republic of Guinea.
The singers are accompanied
by various stringed
instruments including the
nhènhèru, a sort ofviolin
consisting of a large hollow
calabash with a neck attached;
the bolon, similar to the
nhènhèru but plucked rather
]]>
</page>
<page number="81">
<![CDATA[
than bowed; the kèrôna, a
small four-stringed guitar
rather like the Wolof khalam,
and various flutes, drums and
castanettes. The group
performs delightful, lively
melodies and songs full of
aphorisms, such as "When the
left hand sins, the right hand is
not guilty" and "Life is all
change, you win it little by
little".
JAPAN.
The Spirit of Silence
Yoshikazu Iwamoto
(shakuhachi flute)
Music from the World
CD Buda 92543-2
The shakuhachi, a bamboo
flute, is linked to Zen and to the
Japanese aesthetic of silence,
the void, the concealed, the
unadorned. It has a limited
range and a misty sound, and
its music, in which the spaces
between notes are as important
as the notes themselves, brings
to mind the dreamlike
atmosphere ofJapanese films
such as Kwaidan and Onibaba
and certain works by
Mizoguchi and Kurosawa.
Iwamoto, a virtuoso of the
instrument, modulates the
different tonal elements with
great refinement, and does full
justice to the poetry of the titles
of the pieces he plays on this
CD: "Moon of the Heart",
"Deep Night", "Wind through
Pine Trees".
JAZZ
CHARLIE SEPULVEDA.
Algo Nuestro: "Our Thing"
Sepulveda (trumpet), David
Sanchez (tenor and soprano
sax), Edward Simon (piano),
Andy Gonzalez (bass), Adam
Cruz (drums), Richie Flores
(congas and bongos)
CD Antilles 3 1 45 1 2 768-2
Latin Jazz has been
bubbling in New York for the
last ten years, and this new disc
by the young, Bronx-born,
Puerto-Rican trumpeter
Charlie Sepulveda shows how
mature the music has now
become. Algo Nuestro is a
marvel. It introduces two
musicians surely soon to be
stars on the international stage:
Ed Simon, a Venezuelan pianist
still not as well known as he
deserves to be despite having
played at various European
festivals, and David Sanchez,
who combines an expressive
saxophone style with a strong
and subtle sense of rhythm.
Guest musicians also lend a
hand on some tracks.
Sepulveda and his companions
constantly spring surprises on
the listener, swinging on the
upbeat numbers, playing the
ballads poetically, and
sounding almost bucolic on
other tracks with a Puerto
Rican flavour. This is a group to
watch.
AHMAD JAMAL.
Live in Paris 92
Jamal (piano), James
Cammack (bass), David
Bowler (drums).
CD Birdology 849 408-2
This record is another
triumph for Jamal. The old
master of harmony, who often
starts his numbers with
seemingly interminable solo
preludes in which he lets his
imagination run free, toys with
the piano with disconcerting
ease. His music is full of superb
chord progressions, dizzying
runs that never seem out of
/
^ **"r
J» )
place, abrupt rhythmic breaks
and an astonishing sense of
phrasing. Jamal is one of those
great jazz stylists who impress
their personality on everything
they play, and who can
restructure and rework
material apparently endlessly.
FRANK FOSTER AND
THE LOUD MINORITY.
Shiny Stockings
CD Denon DC-8545
This disc contains a series
of Foster compositions (the
exception being the beautiful,
traditional "Hills of the North
Rejoice") that were recorded by
the saxophonist in 1977 and
1978 with some of the most
reliable and innovative
though not necessarily the
best-known New York jazz
musicians of the era. They
include the saxophonist Bill
Cody, who was tragically to be
killed by white racists, the
trumpeter Virgil Jones, the
drummer Charlie Persip, the
pianist Mickey Tucker and the
guitarist Ted Dunbar. Among
the vibrant, well-orchestrated
tracks is an inventive version of
"Shiny Stockings", named in
honour of the legwear of
Frank's wife Cecilia. Currently
the director of the Count Basie
orchestra, Foster is an
outstanding instrumentalist
and, with Quincy Jones and
Slide Hampton, one of the best
Europe, conducted by
Nikolaus Harnoncourt
CD Teldec 903 1-74884-2
"The entire Mass is an
appeal for peace," claims
conductor Nikolaus
Harnoncourt. The Missa
Solemnis powerfully evokes the
horrors of war through cries,
anguished recitatives, clashing
cymbals, trumpet calls and one
passage on the strings that
Harnoncourt aptly describes as
"gooseflesh set to music". It is a
big, majestic, lyrical work,
occasionally riven by what the
conductor calls "absolutely
stark passages", and the
musicians, soloists and chorus
on this recording perfectly
capture its sombre and moving
tone.
HENRYK GORECKI.
Symphony No.3, "Symphony
of Sorrowful Songs"
London Sinfonietta,
conducted by David Zinman,
with Dawn Upshaw
(soprano)
CD Elektra Nonesuch 7559-
79282-2
Composed in Katowice
(Poland) in 1976, this religious
symphony is elegiac in tone,
unfurling its great waves of
sound at a captivating and
almost imperceptibly slow
pace. The first movement
incorporates a fifteenth-
century Polish prayer, the
"Lamentation of the Holy Cross
Monastery". The sweep of the
work gradually carries the
listener away amid a rising
musical tension that
culminates in the lento
cantabile-semplice of the third
movement. This is a beautiful
work, more directly accessible
than Górecki's earlier
compositions.
arrangers in contemporary
jazz. HI*
CLASSICAL
BEETHOVEN.
Missa Solemnis
Arnold Schoenberg Chor.
The Chamber Orchestra of
h.
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="82">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
CHILDREN
OF THE WORLD UNITE
Last year, world leaders met in Rio de Janeiro
to discuss global issues concerning pollu¬
tion, to no avail. We face two choices: either
to carry on regardless, or to try to find a solu¬
tion to the problem ofpollution. Do we want
destruction or the continuity of life on Earth?
Above all, we must not forget the children
who live on our planet, for surely they
embody the balance needed for Earth's sur¬
vival. Children are prisoners of world deci¬
sions out of their control. It is high time that
we listened to their views concerning the
survival of Mother Earth. They hold the key
to the future.
Margaret Elizabeth Perkins
Broughton (England)
A TINE TO CARE
For the impressive panel of intellectuals who
contributed to your April issue ("A Time to Love
. . ."), the sole interpretation given to the much-
misused word "love" was that of (hetero) sexual
love, romantic love if you prefer, confusing
"loving" (durable) and "being in love" (all too
often transient). Not one ofyour authors used
the word in what seems to me its essential
sense, that oí caring. This led to the absurd sit¬
uation in which half a page of the magazine
was devoted to Don Juan, whereas Mother
Teresa did not get a mention. Nor was parental
love given the pride of place it should have
had, or the love of ordinary folk for their friends,
or the unquestioning trust of children, or the
touching bond that sometimes develops
between a human being and an animal. Yet it is
that kind of quiet affection that "makes the
world go round", not the glamorous Hollywood
stuff.
H. TlMSARI
Ville-la-Grande, France
LOVE WITH A CAPITAL L
Do you think it is easy for a fifteen-year-old to
read an issue of the Unesco Comieron Love? At
an age when we often suffer from what has
been called "the lobster complex", we need
above all, amid so many uncertainties, to have
a sound definition of Love. The posters of stars
like Marilyn Monroe, James Dean and Ava
Gardner on my bedroom wall are images of
Fullness and Emptiness the fullness written
in the faces, the emptiness ofwhat one expects
to receive from them. At our age we still attach
faces to our adolescent illusions; at forty it is too
late. For already the realization is dawning that
life is not eternal and that all these faces are
interchangeable.
This evening I have realized that inter-
changeability is inevitable if one loves Love
and not "being in love". I shall continue to
scatter myself to the winds, but I shall know that
it will be for the sake of an absolute, Love with
a capital L.
Claire Tançons
Boisripeaux (Guadeloupe)
WHAT HAS HAPPENED
TO DUTY?
I note that one feature of the world in which we
live is the growing number ofrightsthe rights
of the child, minority rights, the right to work,
to health, to freedom of speech, etc. But what
about those who are not covered by any of
these headings? Why such a diversity of rights,
such a profusion of categories? Are there so
many gaps in the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights? Are its provisions unsatisfac¬
torily applied?
What about duty, the opposite pole to
rights, and one from which they are in a sense
indissociable? No-one talks about duty any
more. The very word is no longer part of our
vocabulary. Why is this? Is it because we now
only possess rights and not duties? What can
happen to a society that insists only on rights?
What is life without a sense of duty?
Why not devote an issue of the Unesco
Courierto the notion ofduty as it has appeared
in different peoples and civilizations down the
agesspiritual, religious, moral, and civic duty,
duty to oneself and to others, individual, col¬
lective and professional duties? Is this concept
specific to human beings and if so what hap¬
pens when it is neglected?
Marcelle Achard
Versailles (France)
82
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, page 3: © Merkado, Paris. Page 2: © Farideh Jorjani Charon, Paris. Pages 4-5, 7, 9: © Sygma, Paris. Pages
6, 8: © Cahiers du Cinéma, Paris. Pages 10, 78: All Rights Reserved. Page I I: Giannichi/Photo Researchers ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 12: Claude Gaspari © FDAC, Conseil Général du Val de Marne, France. Pages 13, 19 (above),
45, 48: © Charles Lénars, Paris. Page 1 4: Chuck O'Rear © Wesclight/Cosmos, Paris. Page 1 5: © Seiko Epson. Pages
16-17: A. Wolf © Explorer, Paris. Page 17 (below): © Avice/AGE/Cosmos, Paris. Page 18: Julian Baum ©
SPL/Cosmos, Paris. Pages 19 (below), 68: © Jean-Loup Charmet, Paris. Page 20: M. Bellot © RMN, Paris. Louvre
Museum. Page 21: Morgan/Photo Researcher © Explorer, Paris. Pages 22-23: © Argos Film. Paris. Road Movies,
Berlin. Page 24: © Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, Mass. Page 25: Peter Willi © Explorer, Paris. Louvre Museum.
Pages 26-27: © Pascal Rieu. Pages 28-29: Siemens © Sygma, Paris. Page 29 (right): Mark Edwards © Still Pictures.
London. Page 30: F. Le Dlascorn © Rapho, Paris. Page 31: J. Andanson © Sygma, Paris. Page 32: R. Nowitz ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 34 (above): Billerey © Adème. Paris. Page 34 (middle): Courillon © Adème, Paris. Page 34
(below): Simon Fraser/SPL © Cosmos, Paris. Page 35: © Giraudon, Paris. Pages 36-37: Michael Gilbert/SPL ©
Cosmos, Paris. Page 38 (above): G. Zlesler ©Jacana, Paris. Page 38 (below): UN. Page 39 (above): WWF/Marek
Libersky © BIOS, Paris. Page 39 (below): Fred Winner © Jacana, Paris. Page 40: © Laboratoire photographique
central de la gendarmerie, Rosny sous Bols, France. Pages 41, 56, 57, 66: Philippe Gontler © Explorer, Paris. Page
42 (left): M. Freeman © ANA, Paris. Pages 42-43: Alain Keler © Sygma, Paris. Page 44: Graig Aurness © Cosmos,
Paris. Pages 46-47: Goudourneix © Explorer, Paris. Page 49: Collart/Odlnetz © Sygma, Paris. Pages 50-51: René
Burri © Magnum, Paris. Pages 52-53: Sebastiào Salgado © Magnum, Paris. Pages 52 (below), 53 (above right):
Teixeira Mendes © Ediouro. Rio de Janeiro. Pages 54-55: Peter Willi © Explorer, Paris. Musée National d'Art
Moderne, Paris, ADAGP 1993. Pages 58-59: Ebet Roberts/LFI © Cosmos, Paris. Pages 60-61: Gilles Peress ©
Magnum. Paris. Page 63: © Esteban Cobas Puente. Paris. Page 65: Courtesy Galerie Lelong © ADAGP 1993, Paris.
Page 67 (above): © Norwegian Music Information Centre, Oslo. Page 67 (middle): © Universal Edition, Vienna.
Page 69: Thierry Zeno. Charleville Mézières (France), Musée Rimbaud © Explorer, ADAGP 1993, Paris. Page 70:
Sartony © Luc Simon, SPADEM 1 993. Paris. Page 7 1 : © ANPADT/Unesco. Page 72: UNESCO-Michel Claude. Pages
74, 75: © Edouard Bailby, Paris. Pages 76, 77: Diego Gradis © Traditions pour Demain, Paris.
TheljNESCO
«^COURIER
46th YEAR
Published monthly in 32 languages and in Braille by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin. 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel. 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin {Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Prithi Perera
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Mehikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Var.ini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mef^a llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: S:din Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Alexandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donastia)
Thai: Pornnipha Limpapbayom (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Ghoti Khaweri (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Galician: XabierSenín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, jacque me Louise-Julie, Manichan
Mgonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tei. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tei. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tei.: 45.68.45 65
I year: 21 I French francs 2 years: 396 FF.
Biider for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: I 32 French f-ancs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
o-der of Unesco
Individual articles and photog^phs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads 'Reprinted from the Unfkd Couner", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are seit to the ed.tor. Signed arti¬
cles reprinted must bear authc-'s name. Non-copyright photos will be sup¬
plied on -cqucst. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompan ed by an Internationa reply coupon coverirg postage. Signed arti¬
cles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opmiois of Unesco or those of the editors of the UwtSCO Counc Photo
captions and headlines are written by tne Unhco Courier staff. The bound¬
aries on maps published n the magazine do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is pro¬
duced in microform (microfilm and'Or mk-ofiche) by: (I) UNESCO. 7
Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann
Arbor. Michigan 48 1 00 U.S.A.: (3) N.C.R. Mic-ocarc Edition. Indian Heac
Inc.. 1 1 1 West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A., (4) Beü and Howell Co.. Old
Mansfield Road. Wooster. Ohio 4469 1 , U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DE30T LEGAL: CI -JUILLET/AOÛT 1993
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N' 71842 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de "Unesco.
Impression IMAYE GRAPHIC.
Z.I. des Touches. Bd Henri-Becquerel. 5302: Lava Cedex (France)
ISSN 0304-31 18 Iv 7/8- 1 993-OP1-93-5 1 7A
Th s issue comprises 84 pages and a 4-page nsert aetween
pages 42-¿3.
]]>
</page>
<page number="83">
<![CDATA[
MUSEE DECHELETTE
ROANNE
7 JUILLET - 21 NOVEMBRE 1993
SAMARCANDE
ses terres secrètes
CÉRAMIQUES DU VHP AU XIIIe SIÈCLE
Le carnet
du professeur
MARQUE ET MODELE DEPOSES
L'outil pensé
par et pour
l 'enseignant
ta
m
BeriK 49, rue Claude Bernard 75005 Paris
Tél. : 43 36 36 99. FAX : 47 07 33 25
¡u
E
Q. Z
Si
o
a.
D
3
o
Sciences
Humaines
Le mensuel de vulgarisation
des sciences humaines et sociales
Sciences
Humaines
MJMtRO 30
IUILLCT 1993
32 F
CHAQUE MOIS
EN KIOSQUE
32 F
Des dossiers synthétiques
Les contributions des meilleurs spécialistes
Des articles clairs et didactiques
J Je souhaite recevoir, sans aucun engagement de ma part, un spécimen gratuit de ¡a revue
NOM	PRENOM	
ADRESSE
Code postal Ville	
PAYS !..
(Bulletin à découper ou à reproduire)
à retournera Sciences Humaines 83, rue de Paris 89000 Auffirre-TéJ: (16186512200 h3
]]>
</page>
<page number="84">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
EACH MONTH, ESSENTIAL
READING FOR AN
UNDERSTANDING OF THE
PROBLEMS OF TODAY AND
I ¿*J M L'J Hll'lj
w»JSSSSSS!SS&!
IN PRAISE OF TOLERANCE...
UNIVERSALITY: A EUROPEAN VISION? ...
THE KNOWLEDGE BEARERS ... TELEVISIONS
... THE CHALLENGE OF DEMOCRACY ... THE
COMPETITIVE WORLD OF SPORT ... EXPLORING
THE COSMOS ... VIOLENCE ...
PSYCHOANALYSIS: THE HIDDEN I ... A TIME
TO LOVE... WATER OF UFE ... MINORITIES...
WHAT IS MODERN?...
THEME
OF THE NEXT ISSUE
(SEPTEMBER 1991)
THE MEANING
1 OF RHYTHM !
H
AN INTERVIEWS
°E WORLD OF ART, LITER
AND GESTURE
Also featuring an interview
with the South African novelist
ANDRÉ RRINK
FRANCOIS MITTERRAND ... JORGE AMADO ...
RICHARD ATTENBOROUGH ... JEAN-CLAUDE
CARRIÈRE... JEAN LACOUTURE ... FEDERICO
MAYOR... NAGUIB MAHFOUZ ... SEMBENE
OUSNANE ... ANDREI VOZNESENSKY ...
FRÉDÉRIC ROSSIF ... HINNERK BRUHNS ...
CAMILO JOSÉ CELA ... VACLAV HAVEL ...
SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV ... ERNESTO
SÁBATO... GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND ...
CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS ... LEOPOLDO ZEA ...
PAULO FREIRÉ ... DANIEL J. BOORSTIN ...
FRANCOIS JACOB ... MANU DIBANGO ...
FAROUK HOSNY ... SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN ...
JORGE LAVELLI ... LÉON SCHWARTZENBERG ...
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN ... GABRIEL GARCÍA
MÁRQUEZ ... JACOUES-YVES COUSTEAU ...
MELINA MERCOURI ... CARLOS FUENTES ...
JOSEPH KI-ZERBO ... VANDANA SHIVA ...
WILLIAM STYRON ... OSCAR NIEMEYER ...
HIKIS THEODORAKIS ... ATAHUALPA
YUPANOUI... HERVÉ BOURGES ... ABDEL
RAHMAN EL BACHA ... SUSANA RINALDI ...
HUBERT REEVES ... JOSÉ CARRERAS ...
A LETTER FRON FREUD TO EINSTEIN ...
LUC FERRY ... CHARLES MALAMOUD ...
UMBERTO ECO ... OLIVER STONE...
ANNOUNCING A NEW FEATURE
IN THE SEPTEMBER ISSUE:
ARCHIVES
a selection of little-known documents from the archives of
the International Institute of Intellectual Co-operation,
relating to the great intellectual debates of the years
between the wars.
Contributors to these debates included such figures as:
MARIE CURIE, ALBERT EINSTEIN, TAHA HUSSEIN,
ALDOUS HUXLEY, THOMAS MANN,
GABRIELA MISTRAL, RABINDRANATH TAGORE,
ARNOLD TOYNBEE, MIGUEL DE UNAMUNO,
PAUL VALÉRY, THORNTON WILDER, STEFAN ZWEIG...
UCHMOMIH.»«.
]]>
</page>
</document>
