<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="190645eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
January-March 2011
Chemistry
and Life
The science and art of matter
JeanMarie Lehn
How it all started
Michal Meyer
I love laser
Tebello Nyokong
Pact against cancer
Anlong Xu
From dark to green ages
Jens Lubbadeh
Synthetic trees
Klaus Lackner
Letter to a young chemist
Akira Suzuki 
Topics:
Like hooked atoms
RolfDieter Heuer
Touki Bouki’s new life
Souleymane Cissé
United Nations 
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization,
ISSN 2220-2285
Courier
THE UNESCO
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
IYC 2011
The International Year of Chemistry 2011 (IYC 2011)
was proclaimed by the United Nations General
Assembly following a proposal by Ethiopia. It aims
to celebrate the contributions made by chemistry to
the wellbeing of mankind. Under the banner of
“Chemistry: our life, our future”, the Year will
highlight the role that science is expected to play in
such varied fields as health, food, the environment,
energy and transport. The Year is especially
addressed at youth and non-specialists, inviting
them to join in a whole range of interactive,
entertaining and educational events across the
world (www.chemistry2011.org/).
The year 2011 also marks the centenary of the
award of the Nobel Prize for chemistry to Marie
Sklodowska-Curie and of the establishment, in Paris,
of the International Association of Chemistry
Societies, which changed its name in 1919 to the
International Union for Pure and Applied Chemistry
(IUPAC). 
With its headquarters in Zurich (Switzerland),
IUPAC was founded by chemists from both
universities and industry, with the aim of
encouraging international cooperation in chemistry
and as a means to bridge the divide between
scientific research, industrial applications and the
public sector. It is because of IUPAC that chemists all
over the world share a common ‘language’, in terms
of nomenclature, symbols, terminology, standard
atomic weights, etc. Fifty-four National Adhering
Organizations and Associate National Adhering
Organizations are members.
UNESCO and IUPAC are jointly organizing IYC
2011, along with industrial partners. The
International Year of Chemistry 2011 will be
launched on 27 January 2011 at UNESCO
headquarters in Paris, with the participation of
several leading scientists and researchers. 
Jean-Marie Lehn
(France)
Klaus Lackner
Stephen Humphreys 
(USA)
Vanderlan da Silva Bolzani 
(Brazil)
Fatemeh Farjadian 
(Iran)
Marko Viskić
(Croatia)
Vicki Gardiner 
(Australia)
Ole John Nielsen
Jes Andersen
(Denmark)
Jens Lubbadeh
Rolf-Dieter Heuer
(Germany)
Michal Meyer
(Israel)
Tayra Lanuza-Navarro
(Spain)
Souleymane Cissé 
(Mali)
Bhagwan Singh Chandravanshi 
Shimalis Admassie
(Ethiopia)
Anlong Xu 
(China) 
Gabrielle Lorne
(Martinique - France)
Sunil Mani
Shiraz Sidhva
Somnath Das 
(India)
Tebello Nyokong
(South Africa)
Akira Suzuki
Noriyuki Yoshida
(Japan)
Philip W. Boyd 
(New Zealand)
OUR AUTHORS
Ana Alejandra Apaseo Alaniz 
(Mexico)
Kufre Ite 
(Nigeria)
© DR2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial – Irina Bokova, Director General of UNESCO 5
DOSSIER: CHEMISTRY AND LIFE
Chemistry: The Science and Art of Matter  Jean-Marie Lehn 7
Chemistry  quite a story 10
Chemistry: How it all started  Michal Meyer 11
The misfortunes of an over-materialistic alchemist
Tayra M.C. Lanuza-Navarro 13
Chemistry in everday life 17
I love laser – it’s my guiding light
Interview with Tebello Nyokong by Cathy Nolan 18
Monitoring the country’s health  Bhagwan Singh Chandravanshi 21
Herbs and metal: a pact against cancer  Anlong Xu 22
The primacy of nature  Vanderlan da Silva Bolzani 24
India’s pharmaceutical boom
An interview with Sunil Mani by Shiraz Sidhva 25
Seaweed for health  Vicki Gardiner 28
The new face of chemistry 29
New diet for the ozone eaters
Jes Andersen meets Ole John Nielsen 30
Global warming: Plan B
Iron tonic for the ocean’s anaemia  Philip W. Boyd 32
Synthetic trees  Katerina Markelova meets Klaus Lackner 33
Venus to the rescue  Jasmina Šopova 34
From dark to green ages  Jens Lubbadeh 35
Letter to a young chemist
An interview with Akira Suzuki by Noriyuki Yoshida 39
Young chemists around the globe 42
Studying chemistry in Ethiopia Shimalis Admassie 44
POSTSCRIPT
Science without borders  Susan Schneegans 46
UNESCO and CERN: like hooked atoms
Jasmina Šopova meets Rolf-Dieter Heuer 48
Art as a bridge between cultures  Stephen Humphreys 51
Touki Bouki’s new life
An interview with Souleymane Cissé by Gabrielle Lorne 53
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 3
The UNESCO Courier is published by the United Nations
Organization for Education, Science and Culture. 
7, place de Fontenoy 
75352 Paris 07 SP, France 
www.unesco.org/courier 
Publications Director: Eric Falt
Editor-in-Chief: Jasmina Šopova 
j.sopova@unesco.org 
Assistant Editor: Katerina Markelova
k.markelova@unesco.org
Editors: 
Arabic: Bassam Mansur assisted by Zaina Dufour 
Chinese: Weiny Cauhape 
English: Peter Coles 
French: Françoise Demir
Portuguese: Ana Lúcia Guimarães 
Russian: Irina Krivova 
Spanish: Francisco Vicente-Sandoval 
Photos: Eric Bouttier
Design and layout: Baseline Arts Ltd, Oxford 
Printing: UNESCO – CLD 
Information and reproduction rights: 
+ 33 (0)1 45 68 15 64 . k.markelova@unesco.org
Web platform: Fabienne Kouadio, Chakir Piro and 
Van Dung Pham
With thanks to: Danica Bijeljac, Fabienne Dumur, Cathy
Nolan, Michel Ravassard, Marie Renault, Susan Schneegans
and Fan Xiao
Articles and photos credited UNESCO may be reproduced
and/or translated providing the credit line reads
“Reproduced from the UNESCO Courier” and includes date
and hyperlink. Photos without UNESCO credit require
specific authorization.
Articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO.
Photographs belonging to UNESCO may be reproduced
freely. Photos must carry the following caption: © UNESCO
and photographer's name. For high resolution, please
contact the Photobank: photobank@unesco.org
Boundaries on maps do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations
of the countries and territories concerned.  
L Barium single-crystal fibres. Barium is mainly used in the
petroleum industry, as well as medecine (x-rays of the digestive
tract) and construction industry (anti-radiation heavy concrete).
© SPL 
Courier
THE UNESCO January-March 2011
United Nations 
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
In this issue
In 1932, the German physician, Gerhard Domagk,
confirmed the anti-bacterial action of a new dye
developed by the company, IG Farben. Seven years
later, Prontosil earned him the Nobel Prize, but,
because of the Nazi regime, he was unable to accept
it. Today, a South African, Tebello Nyokong, is
developing new treatments for cancer using
substances usually used for dying denim jeans. These
discoveries are not mere anecdotes; they mark a new
phase in a highly colourful science – chemistry. The
articles in this latest issue of the UNESCO Courier will
enable everyone to form a more complete picture of
progress in this science. 
Chemistry is so all pervading in our lives, that it
often passes unnoticed, says Jean-Marie Lehn, French
Nobel Prize laureate in chemistry in 1987. “A world
without chemistry,”  he says, in our Introduction,
“would be a world without synthetic materials, and
that means no telephones, no computers and no
cinema […] without aspirin or soap, shampoo or
toothpaste, without cosmetics, contraceptive pills, or
paper – and so no newspapers or books, glues, or
paints” (p.8).
After tracing the early history of chemistry, which
“began the moment our ancestors became human,”
(pp. 11-16), we take a look at its applications,
particularly in medicine. This is an opportunity to
inquire about the interactions between nature,
research and industry, from South Africa to Australia,
Brazil, China, Ethiopia and India (pp. 17-28).
Chemistry, though, is Janus-faced: one face
embodies the prodigious benefits to humanity; the
other the harm caused by pollution. The disaster that
struck Hungary last October sounded the alarm once
again (p. 35). All the more reason to focus on the
solutions chemistry can offer to the pollution it has
caused. Once again, we can travel from China, and
Europe, to the USA and New Zealand, to discover, in
the company of Philip W. Boyd and Klaus Lackner,
some attempts to tackle climate change (pp. 32-33).
An encouraging sign is that industry is “acting
much more responsibly” (p. 31), according to Ole John
Nielsen (Denmark), a member of the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC).
Chemistry is becoming this new science that Akira
Suzuki (Japan), Nobel laureate in Chemistry in 2010, is
dreaming of (pp. 39-41). New generations of young
chemists will undoubtedly steer it on the right course
(pp. 42-43).
As a supplement to these special features, the
Courier also gives a glimpse of the UNESCO World
Science Report 2010, commemorates the anniversary
of the creation of CERN and looks at culture, as the
International Year for the Rapprochement of Cultures
(2010) draws to a close. 
– Jasmina Šopova
L Historical vacuum line,
formerly used for gas phase
synthesis / From the
collections at the University
of Copenhagen
© Mikal Schlosser
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 5
Chemistry, and our ability to master its secrets, is
fundamental to our understanding of the
material world. The chemical elements are at the
core of all known matter. They are involved in all
living processes. We owe most of the 20th
century’s advances in medicines, the food
industry and technology to modern chemistry.
This science has revolutionized the manufacture
of drugs, clothing and cosmetics, as well as the
distribution of energy and the manufacture of
technological equipment. Chemistry is
everywhere in our daily lives – and if we are to
make the best use of it, we have to understand it
better.
At the initiative of Ethiopia, the United
Nations declared 2011 International Year of
Chemistry (IYC 2011) and entrusted its
organization to UNESCO. It provides a special
opportunity to improve our knowledge of this
science and the contribution it has made to our
ability to understand, control and transform
matter. It is also an opportunity for UNESCO to
further its efforts in its areas of competence,
namely, development and diplomacy through
science, strengthening the research capability of
Member States and quality science education for
all – where chemistry is an essential component.
IYC 2011 also celebrates the centenary of the
award of the Nobel Prize in chemistry to Marie
Curie, providing us with the perfect framework
for paying homage to and promoting the
contribution of women to science. And this
homage starts the same day the International
Year is launched, with a visit to UNESCO
headquarters by Hélène Langevin-Joliot, scientist
and grand-daughter of Marie Curie and daughter
of Irène Joliot-Curie, to speak at a conference on
the role of women in chemistry.
The latest World Science Report, published by
UNESCO in November 2010, demonstrated the
importance of science and science diplomacy for
peace and development. Basic research on the
building blocks of matter requires colossal
resources and the participation of a great many
researchers, from all over the world. This calls, in
particular, for a strengthening of international
cooperation and a more even global distribution
of research resources. Through initiatives such as
the SESAME research centre in the Middle East,
where chemistry is a major component, UNESCO
is endeavouring to help meet this need.
The future science of chemistry must, above
all, be responsible. It will undoubtedly be playing
a major role in the development of alternative
Editorial
Irina Bokova
I Irina Bokova, Director
General of UNESCO with the
Canadian astrophysicist
Hubert Reeves, at a
conference on the loss of
biodiversity, at the
Organization’s headquarters
on 3 November 2009.
© UNESCO/M. Ravassard
It provides a
special
opportunity to
improve our
knowledge of
this science and
the contribution
it has made to
our ability to
understand,
control and
transform
matter.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
energy sources and in feeding an ever-growing
global population. Discoveries made in chemistry
can help to meet the challenges raised by global
climate change – without chemistry there would
be no solar panels, no biofuels… These
discoveries can also help provide access to non-
polluted water supplies. The International Year of
Chemistry follows on from the International Year
of Biodiversity (2010) and takes on its full
meaning within the context of the United Nations
Decade of Education for Sustainable
Development  (2005-2014).
The chemistry of the future must also be a
science that is more evenly shared. The quasi-
absence of a “general culture of chemistry”,
compared to the culture of astronomy or
mathematics, prevents the general public from
having access to aspects of the world that affect
our daily lives and hampers our collective ability
to have a say in this. This lack of understanding
also fuels the public’s stereotyped view of
chemistry as diabolical, toxic and dirty. We need to
improve and to accelerate the teaching of
chemistry, training the chemists of tomorrow and
giving everyone, everywhere, the possibility of
understanding chemical processes and measuring
their impact. Interest in this fascinating science is a
resource for development. It is up to us to make
good use of it.
In order to attract young people to take an
interest in chemistry, UNESCO and the
International Union of Pure and Applied
Chemistry – its main partner in organising the
IYC, celebrating its centenary this year – are
launching a global experiment, the first of its
kind, to help schoolchildren gain a better
understanding of our most precious resource –
water. All across the world, schools will be testing
water for its quality and purity and will then be
able to share their results.
It is a priority for the years to come that we all
improve our understanding of science in general
and of chemistry in particular. As the United
Nations agency specializing in education, science
and culture, UNESCO will do its utmost to see that
this is achieved. It is our collective duty to make
decisions that are fully informed if we are to act
responsibly on the world around us. 
A POOR SHOWING FOR WOMEN NOBEL LAUREATES
The first woman to receive a Nobel Prize in chemistry was Marie Curie.
That was a century ago. Since then, the list of women laureates in
chemistry has not grown much longer. Just three names have been
added: Irène Joliot-Curie, Dorothy Mary Crowfoot Hodgkin and Ada
Yonath.
Since it was created in 1901, the Nobel Prize has been awarded to 40
women, across all disciplines, Marie Curie having been honoured twice. Born
in Warsaw (Poland) in 1867, Maria Skodowska (married name Curie) received
the Nobel prize in Physics in 1903, with her husband, Pierre Curie and Henri
Becquerelle, before being rewarded herself, in 1911, “in recognition of her
services to the advancement of chemistry by the discovery of the elements
radium and polonium.” 
In 1935, it was to be the turn of her daughter, Irène, to share this
prestigious award with her husband, Frédéric Joliot-Curie, “in recognition of
their synthesis of new radioactive elements.” 
It was nearly a further three decades before another woman was to
attract the attention of the Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences, when
Dorothy Mary Crowfoot Hodgkin (United Kingdom), was honoured in 1964,
“for her determination by X-ray techniques, of the structures of important
biochemical substances.”
Finally, 45 years later, Ada Yonath (Israel) shared the Nobel Prize in Chemistry with Venkaterman
Ramakrishnan (India) and Thomas Steitz (USA), “for studies of the structure and function of the
ribosome.” The year before, Ada Yonath had received the L’Oréal-UNESCO Award for Women in
Science (2008). 
Since it was launched in 1998 by L’Oréal and UNESCO, the Women in Science Programme has
been supporting women who are carrying out scientific research, designating one laureate for each
continent, every year. Also, 15 international fellowships have been awarded each year since 2000, to
young researchers, whose projects have been accepted by renowned research laboratories outside
of their country of origin.  
J.Š.
1. Chemistry, 4; Physics, 2;
Medicine, 10; Literature, 12;
Peace, 12.
L In 1967, the UNESCO
Courier devoted an entire
issue to Marie Curie. 
© UNESCO
The quasi-absence
of a “general
culture of
chemistry”,
compared to the
culture of
astronomy or
mathematics,
prevents the
general public
from having
access to aspects
of the world that
affect our daily
lives and hampers
our collective
ability to have a
say in this.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 7
E D I T O R I A L
Chemistry has a pivotal role to play, as much
because of its place within the natural sciences
and knowledge as a whole, as through its
economic importance and its omnipresence in
our daily life. But, because it is everywhere, we
often forget about it, and could even not
mention it at all. Chemistry doesn’t flaunt itself,
but without it, some truly spectacular
achievements would never have been made,
such as breakthroughs in the treatment of illness,
space exploration, and marvels of technology. It
makes an essential contribution to humanity in
food and medicines, clothes and housing, energy
and raw materials, transport and
communications. It supplies materials for physics
and industry, models and substrates to biology
and pharmacology, and properties and
procedures to the sciences and technology. 
Chemistry : 
the science and 
art of matter Jean-Marie Lehn
The science of chemistry is not just about discovery. It is also, and especially, about creation. It
is an art of the complexification of matter. To understand the logic of the latest discoveries in
nanochemistry, we have to take a 4-billion year leap back in time.
“May your search
be guided by the
highest dreams”
– Roland Barthes
L Chemistry is intrinsic to life.
Original drawing by Sejung
Kim (Republic of Korea).
© Sejung Kim
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
A world without chemistry would be a world
without synthetic materials, and that means no
telephones, no computers and no cinema. It
would also be a world without aspirin or soap,
shampoo or toothpaste, without cosmetics,
contraceptive pills, or paper – and so no
newspapers or books, glues, or paints. 
And we must be careful to remember that
chemistry helps art historians delve into the
secrets behind paintings and sculptures in
museums, and helps forensic scientists to
analyse samples taken from a crime scene and
quickly track down the perpetrators, as well as
revealing the molecular basis of dishes that
delight our taste buds. 
While physics decodes the laws of the
universe and biology deciphers those of the
living world, chemistry is the science of matter
and its transformations. Life is its highest form of
expression. Chemistry plays a primordial role in
our understanding of material phenomena, in
our ability to act upon them, to change them
and control them. 
For almost two centuries now, molecular
chemistry has put together a vast array of
increasingly sophisticated molecules and
materials. This discipline has not ceased to assert
its power over structure and the transformation
of material, from the synthesis of urea in 1828 –
which started a veritable revolution, by
providing the proof that it was possible to obtain
an ‘organic’ molecule from a mineral component
– to the synthesis of vitamin B12 in 2006 after a
quest that had started in 1948.
The molecule as Troy horse
Above and beyond molecular chemistry there is
the vast area of what is called supramolecular
chemistry, which is not so much interested in
what happens within molecules, as what
happens between them. Its objective is to
understand and control the manner in which
molecules interact with one another, transform
themselves, bind to one another, while ignoring
other partners. Emil Fischer (the German Nobel
laureate for chemistry in 1902) used the image of
the lock and key. Today we refer to “molecular
recognition”. 
It is in the field of biology that the role of
these molecular interactions is most striking:
protein units group together to form
haemoglobin; white blood cells recognize and
destroy foreign bodies; the AIDS virus finds its
target and takes it over; the genetic code is
transmitted by reading and writing the alphabet
of protein bases. In the vivid example of the ‘self
organisation’ of the tobacco mosaic virus: no
fewer than 2130 simple proteins join together to
form a helical tower.
A chemist finds the efficacy and elegance of
these natural phenomena so fascinating that he
is tempted to reproduce or invent novel
processes to create new molecular architectures,
with a panoply of applications. Why not imagine
molecules that can transport a fragment of DNA
to the very centre of a target in gene therapy, for
example? These molecules would be “Troy
horses” which would, in turn, cross supposedly
insurmountable barriers, like cell membranes. 
A great many researchers around the globe
are patiently creating ‘designer’ supramolecular
structures. They observe how molecules that are
jumbled with no apparent order can find and
recognize one another and then gradually
assemble themselves spontaneously, but in a
perfectly controlled manner, to reach the final
supramolecular edifice. 
So, inspired by phenomena that nature has
presented to us, the idea was born of eliciting
and guiding the appearance of supramolecular
assemblages – in other words, “molecular
programming”. The chemist conceives the basic
building blocks (molecules with certain
structural and interactional properties), then
applies the “cement” (assembly code) to link
them together. 
This yields a superstructure via self
organization. The synthesis of molecular blocks
capable of self organization is much more simple
than synthesizing the final edifice. This line of
research opens vast horizons, notably in the field
of nanotechnology – instead of fabricating
nanostructures, we let the nanostructures
fabricate themselves by self organization, thus
moving from fabrication to self-fabrication. 
Even more recently ‘adaptive’ chemistry has
emerged, where the system, in order to construct
itself, makes its own selection among the
available building blocks, and becomes able to
adapt its objects to the demands of the
environment. This form of chemistry, which I call
“dynamic constitutional chemistry”, has
something of a Darwinian flavour to it!
From matter to life
In the beginning there was the original
explosion, the Big Bang, and physics reigned.
Then came chemistry, with more clement
temperatures. Particles formed atoms, which
“Where Nature ceases to produce its
own species, Mankind begins, using
natural things, and with the aid of this
very Nature, creates an infinity of
species…” – Leonardo da Vinci
Satis utilitas catelli
corrumperet lascivius
apparatus bellis. Utilitas
syrtes insectat chirographi,
utcunque plane verecundus
umbraculi praemuniet
pessimus quinquennalis
agricolae.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
united to form increasingly complex molecules,
which, in turn, grouped together in aggregates
and membranes, giving rise to the first cells, as
life emerged on our planet, 3.8 billion years
ago. 
From divided matter to condensed matter,
then organized, living and thinking matter, the
unfurling Universe is nudging the evolution of
matter towards increasing complexity through
self organization, under the pressure of
information. The task of chemistry is to reveal
the pathways of self organization and to trace
the paths leading from inert matter, via a purely
chemical, prebiotic evolution, to the creation of
life, and beyond, to living and then thinking
matter. In this way, it offers the means to
interrogate the past, to explore the present and
to build bridges towards the future.
Through its subject matter (the molecule
and material), chemistry expresses its creative
force, its power to produce new molecules and
materials, that never existed before they were
created by the rearrangements of atoms into
original and infinitely varied combinations and
structures. Chemistry is, in some ways,
analogous to art, through the plasticity of the
chemical object’s forms and functions. As artist,
the chemist imprints matter with the products
of his imagination. Just as stone, sounds and
words do not contain the work that the
sculptor, composer or author shapes with them,
so the chemist creates original molecules, new
materials and unknown properties from the
elements that make up matter.
The particularity of chemistry is not only to
discover, but to invent and, above all, to create.
The Book of Chemistry is not only to be read,
but to be written. The score of Chemistry is not
only to be played, but to be composed. 
J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 9
Jean-Marie Lehn, is a chemist specializing in
supramolecular chemistry, Emeritus professor
at the University of Strasbourg (France), Nobel
laureate in 1987 with Donald Cram and Charles
Pedersen. Honorary professor at the Collège de
France and member of the French Academy of
Sciences, Jean-Marie Lehn founded the Institut
de Science et d’Ingénierie Supramoléculaires
(ISIS) in Strasbourg. http://www-isis.u-
strasbg.fr/
J Witherite in crystal form. The crystal makes it possible to shed
light on the relationships between the properties, chemical
composition and arrangement of atoms in materials. Chemists
“cultivate” crystals in order to study and visualize them and to
imagine new ones. This allows them to discover new materials,
with a wide range of applications. © SPL
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
1 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
Chemistry
 quite a
story
Rather like Molière’s Monsieur Jourdain, who
‘spoke in prose’ without knowing it, we all practice
chemistry, usually without being aware of it. Since
the dawn of time, all living beings, including
animals and plants, have manufactured the
organic compounds necessary for life. Then, with
the help of intuition, our ancestors invented
potions, dyes and alloys. They extracted elixirs,
scents and medicines. There is vast evidence of the
sometimes drastic transformations to which Man
has subjected matter, long before knowing the
laws of chemistry – from iron in Niger and tapirage
for American Indians, to paper in China.
Increasingly sophisticated methods were
employed, albeit sometimes bizarre, but always
inspired by nature, until the birth of modern
chemistry in the 18th century. 
Engraving of Robert Boyle’s air pump. An aspiring alchemical
adept, Boyle was also one of the pioneers of experimental
science (New Experiments Physico-Mechanicall, Touching the
Spring of the Air, and Its Effects, 1660. 
© Courtesy of Roy G. Neville Historical Chemical Library
(Chemical Heritage Foundation)
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Chemistry:
how it all started Michal Meyer
In the very early 1700s the Elector of Saxony and
King of Poland, August the Strong, locked an
alchemist in his laboratory and told him to make
gold. The young alchemist, Johann Friedrich
Böttger, failed in his royally-appointed task.
Instead he helped create a substance far more
beautiful and useful than gold – porcelain.  And
in a happy fairy-tale ending, the king was
pleased. For this was no longer a feudal world,
but a growing commodity-driven society, and
until that time porcelain had to be imported at
great expense from a technologically more
advanced China to feed a growing European
appetite for beauty and luxury. Wealth flowed to
the king, for the new Meissen porcelain soon
proved popular and a grateful king made Böttger,
originally a pharmacist’s apprentice, a baron.     
One more story, this one beginning in the
gutter: Around 1669 Hamburg resident Hennig
Brandt believed he might have discovered the
fabled Philosopher’s Stone, which could turn
lead into gold and open up the secrets of the
cosmos. An ex-soldier with experience in making
glass, Brandt began with old urine and boiled it
up and heated the residue until glowing vapours
– white phosphorous reacting with oxygen –
filled his glassware. Within a few years, Brandt
sold his secret and soon phosphorous was well
enough known that the secretive alchemist Isaac
Newton could begin a recipe for it with the
instructions, “Take of urine one barrel.” (Though I
do wonder where one could easily procure a
barrel of urine).  From urine to art – another
transformation –the moment of discovery was
L James Gillray’s satirical
etching shows a public lecture
at London’s Royal Institution
in the early 19th century. 
© Courtesy of the Chemical
Heritage Foundation
Collections
Photograph by Gregory Tobias
Chemistry began
the moment our
ancestors became
human.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
1 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
THE TOAD AND THE PARROT
The Achagua tribe living in the upper
reaches of the Meta River (Colombia)
know how to make their parrots grow
feathers of different colours, thus
increasing their value when used in
ceremonies, or their price when sold.
They obtain this result in the following
manner: “they first catch a live toad and
prick it several times with a thorn until it
bleeds. They then put the animal into a
pot and cover its wounds with pepper
and ground pigment. Enraged by this
cruel treatment, the toad distils the most
active ingredients in its humours, which
get mixed with the poison and blood.
They add to this a certain red powder,
which they call chica and, by mixing
these extraordinary ingredients
together, obtain a varnish. They then
pluck out the parrot’s feathers and
anoint it with the varnish, introducing it
into the holes left by the feather, with
the aid of a pointed stick. The parrot
does not seem happy with this
treatment, acting for days like a sick
chicken, all ruffled and sad. After a while,
its feathers grow back. But this time they
have become so splendid that their
beauty and elegance is the object of
great admiration. A variety of feathers
with red spots on a yellow
background stand out most
admirably against the
background of green
feathers.”
We owe this picturesque
description of tapirage carried
out by an indigenous tribe from
Colombia to the Spanish Jesuit,
Juan Rivero (Historia de las
misiones de los llanos de
Casanare y los Rios Orinoco y
Meta, written in 1728 and
published in 1883). It was cited by
Alfred Métraux, an American
anthropologist of Swiss origin
and former staff member at
UNESCO, in his article (in French)
entitled “A biological discovery by South
American Indians: artificial discoloration
of feathers on living birds.” (Journal de la
Société des Américanistes. Volume 20,
1928. pp. 181-192.)
“By plucking the feathers they need
from living [birds] kept in captivity, the
Indians spare themselves the trouble
of hunting and the risk of
damaging the feathers by killing
the birds with a number of
arrow wounds,” explains the
anthropologist, who
attributes the spread
of tapirage in
Amazonia to the
Arawak peoples,
who began
migrating some
three thousand
years ago.
– J.Š. 
immortalized in the eighteenth century in a
painting by Joseph Wright of Derby, and
recorded again as a mezzotint by William Pether
in 1775 as “The Discovery of Phosphorous.”  In
this work, the alchemist kneels in awe before the
glowing wonder in his alchemical laboratory.
Many years later, in 1943, in another
transformation, Brandt’s city burned when
thousands of pounds of phosphorous fell in the
form of bombs.
Homo chemicus 
We turn clay into porcelain, urine into
phosphorous, phosphorous into bombs, flour
into bread, grapes into wine, minerals into
pigments. There is almost no limit to the ways in
which we transmute matter. Biological
anthropologist, Richard Wrangham (United
Kingdom), believes that it is cooking that made
us human -- by making more energy available to
feed our growing brains. If that is so, chemistry
L An alchemist presents
liquid gold to amazed
courtiers. The alchemist’s
dream of turning lead into
gold remained alive until the
18th century.
© Courtesy of the Chemical
Heritage Foundation
Collections
Photograph by Gregory Tobias
© DR
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 1 3
began the moment our ancestors became
human. Homo chemicus – to be human is to
transform matter. And the material
transformations we – being human – make will
reflect the best and the worst of us.   
We cannot go back to that first chemical
moment when raw food turned into cooked
food, but we can go back to prehistoric humans
and their desire for beauty. Philippe Walter, of the
Centre de Recherche et de Restauration des Musées
de France, studies chemical processes and
substances in the ancient and prehistoric world.
While he says these prehistoric peoples did not
have an understanding of how or why processes
worked, they still produced practical chemists
who could mix natural ingredients to produce
pigments – whether to adorn themselves or the
walls of caves.  Four thousand years ago the
ancient Egyptians, says Walter, synthesized new
chemicals to treat eye diseases. Their lead-based
cosmetics – think Cleopatra and her kohl eyeliner
[see box] – stimulated the wearer’s immune
system in an early health and beauty regimen. 
Al-kimia
In Hellenistic Egypt, the refining of metals was
known as chemia. With the rise of early Islamic
civilization, Muslim scholars translated many
Greek texts, including ones on chemia, which
they called al-kimia. How matter changed, how
to purify substances, how to colour metals, all
came under al-kimia. A side benefit of this new
fascination was the refinement in practical
knowledge such as distillation and
The misfortunes
of an over-
materialistic
alchemist
In 1603, Giraldo Paris had already been
living in Madrid for 33 years, as advisor
to Philippe II on Flemish affairs. He had
grown up in Anvers and made his
fortune in the spice trade. He
entertained all the Flemings at the Spanish court, surrounding himself
with ambassadors and dignitaries, as well as pharmacists, doctors and
scholars. Having retired from commerce with an immense fortune,
Paris maintained a passion for alchemy. He was interested in the skills
and knowledge of diamond cutters, apothecaries, distillers and
herbalists. 
That year, some known enemies of Paris denounced him to the
Inquisition, accusing him of heresy. During the ensuing trial, it was
claimed that the Fleming “extracted quintessences, flowers of metal
and herbal salts.” It was also claimed that he was a great natural
philosopher, being interested in the “secret art of chemistry”. Paris was
condemned to one year of seclusion in a monastery and made to pay a
heavy fine.
Told in this way, his story sounds like one of a man pursued by the
Spanish Inquisition because of his activities as an alchemist. But the
reality is more complex. The distillations, the experiments with metals
and the herbal extracts were not what his Inquisitors were really
concerned about. The reason for the sentence lay in the alchemist’s
explanations for certain religious questions. Giraldo Paris, for example,
explained the Virgin Birth by comparing it to an alchemical procedure
where a pure substance is mixed with another, finding, at the end of
the operation, that the former had remained intact “without having
lost any of its virtue […] immaculate as it was in the beginning.” 
So the Inquisition took issue with Giraldo Paris not for his occult
activities but for his “mistaken theses”. At the time, Madrid had many
alchemists who were not persecuted for their practices, but
nonetheless, many of their works turned up on the Index Librorum
Prohibitorum (list of banned books). Also on the list was the Theatrum
Chemicum, the most complete compendium of alchemical knowledge
in 17th century Europe. The work was so important that the Inquisition
had to lift its ban, but did not omit to censor it.  
So, unless proven otherwise, it seems the Inquisition did not
persecute alchemists for their acts, but for their convictions on
material affairs, which were contrary to the dogma. 
Tayra M.C. Lanuza-Navarro is a Spanish historian of science. She is
currently working on a project on books on alchemy at the
beginning of the modern era.
l “La Pharmacie Rustique”, 1775. The
famous Swiss medical practitioner Michel
Schuppach examines a patient’s urine in his
pharmacy.
© Courtesy of the Chemical Heritage
Foundation Collections
Photograph by Gregory Tobias
J The hanging alligator shown in this scene
was commonly found in alchemical
laboratories. 
© Courtesy of the Chemical Heritage
Foundation Collections
©
 U
n
iv
e
rsita
t d
e
 V
a
lè
n
c
ia
. P
h
o
to
 : T. L
a
n
u
za
 2
0
1
0
Tayra M.C. Lanuza-Navarro
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
crystallization, still important skills in twenty-
first century labs. On a more theoretical level,
Muslim scholars built on earlier Greek
understandings of matter – the four elements
of air, earth, fire, and water – and its behaviour,
including the transmutation of one metal into
another. Al-kimia arrived in Europe in the
twelfth century, along with some knowledge of
al-iksir (elixir, which became known as the
Philosopher’s Stone). 
Unsurprisingly, alchemy ran into the same
kinds of problems that still occasionally plague
medicine – hucksters hawking miracle cures
and charlatans, etc. Even less surprising, this
caught the attention of both rulers and the
legal profession, if for different reasons. Later, in
England, it became illegal to succeed in turning
lead into gold, for this was considered as
debasing the currency. 
Some claimed that, since human
manipulation of matter was essentially inferior
to what nature does, naturally (an early version
of the still running natural versus artificial
debate – check back next century for an
update) human attempts at transmuting metals
were doomed. Despite such criticisms, there
were those who believed that human art was
powerful enough to transform the world. But
these were discussions for the elites at
1 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
L “An Alchemist at Work”,
Mattheus van Helmont,
Flemish, 17th century. Seated
in a disorderly workshop, the
alchemist appears as a figure
of folly.
© Courtesy of the Chemical
Heritage Foundation
Collections
Photograph by Will Brown
I Robert Boyle, by Johann
Kerseboom, 1689 (United
Kingdom).
© Courtesy of the Chemical
Heritage Foundation
Collections
Photograph by Will Brown
Every time you boil
an egg you
change the very
nature of matter,
in this case the
shape of the egg
proteins.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
universities. And matter in all its manifestations
was on the move through all social strata. We
don’t know who first created kohl or a clay pot,
who first tanned leather or brewed beer, and
we don’t know the names of the medieval
artisans who mixed sand, wood ash, and metal
salts to create the great stained-glass windows
of medieval cathedrals. But these people all
transformed matter and our lives.  
By the early modern period, the status of
painters, goldsmiths and artisans with an
intimate association with matter, was on the
rise. Science, long associated with
understanding rather than doing, and with
elites rather than common folk, was now
turning to the practical makers of things for
knowledge and power.  Such an approach,
where matter was central, found its expression
in Sir Francis Bacon’s 1620 manifesto Novum
Organum, and the origins of modern science.
Doing – poking, prodding, changing the
material world – would now be allied with
understanding, and our world of art, science,
and the everyday, would never be the same.
Robert Boyle (Ireland), of Boyle’s Law fame –
which connects the pressure, volume and
temperature of a gas – epitomized this new
experimental approach.  An inheritor of the
alchemical tradition, (almost by definition,
alchemists were experimentalists and careful
measurers) and an aspiring alchemist, Boyle is
considered a founding figure of modern
chemistry, in the 17th century 
. 
A colourful science
Many chemists believe chemistry became a
proper science in the eighteenth century. The
investigation of air by Antoine Lavoisier (France),
the discovery of oxygen by Joseph Priestly
(England), and the new scientific language of
chemistry, all played a part. But chemistry, or at
least its results, could not be confined to the
world of scientific research. The craze for hot-air
and hydrogen ballooning in the late eighteenth
century and the ballooning-related fashions in
clothes, playing cards, and ceramics were only
part of the story. Priestley’s invention of
carbonated water, as the poor man’s alternative
to the sickly rich drinking the waters at expensive
spas, continued chemistry’s association with
health that had begun with alchemy. On the
other hand, the Victorian craze for green-
coloured (courtesy of arsenic) wallpaper helped
create what might be the worlds’ first recognized
(and reported as such) environmental hazard. 
In 1856, an eighteen-year old Englishman,
William Henry Perkin, tried to turn coal tar into
the malaria-preventative quinine (a material
transformation worthy of an alchemist). Like
Böttger, he failed, and in his failure he launched a
colour revolution and inadvertently helped
found the German dye and pharmaceutical
industry. Perkin had created mauve, the first of
the synthetic aniline dyes that brightened the
world from the 1860s. Queen Victoria, before her
black phase, wore the new chemistry and started
a fashion for that shade of purple.  A rapidly
industrializing Germany adopted the colourful
anilines and made them its own, incidentally
creating the first strong link between chemistry
as a modern science and industry. A German
physician, Gerhard Domagk, working for I.G.
Farben, found, in 1932, that a modified red dye
L The French hot-air
balloon, Le Tricolore, taking
off, on 6 June 1874, in Paris.
© Library of Congress
(Tissandier collection)
DARKEYED CLEOPATRA
Everyone knows about Cleopatra’s famous eyeliner and her green
eyelashes. But what we didn’t know is that she used her makeup for
medicinal reasons, a detail left out of the history books.
A recent study published in the science journal Analytical Chemistry (15
January, 2010) shows that the ancient Egyptians’ makeup contained lead
salts, which produce nitric oxide. This dilates the blood vessels and opens
the way for macrophages – immune cells that devour foreign particles.
The French research team analysed residues found in “makeup bags”
in the Egyptian collection at the Louvre. With the help of
nanochemistry, they found that when lachrymal fluid is in contact with
the very low doses of lead found in ancient cosmetics, it creates a milieu
that is toxic for microorganisms. – J.Š.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 1 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
1 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
killed bacteria and so the first true antibiotics,
the sulfa drugs, came into use. The link between
fashion and medicine remained, for the skin of
patients sometimes turned red, an indication
that the drug was working. 
The very roots of the German chemical
industry lie in fashion, but the same industry that
began with the world’s brightest colours went on
to produce Zyklon B – the poison gas of choice in
the Nazis’ extermination plans. World War II is
known as the physicists’ war for the development
of the atomic bomb, but every war has been a
chemist’s war from the time humans learned to
smelt metal. Just before World War II, Lise
Meitner (an Austrian-born, later Swedish
physicist) showed that the alchemists were right
-- we can transmute one metal into another, in
this case via nuclear reaction, and, by the end of
the war, uranium 238 was transmuted into
plutonium.
The hallmarks of the old alchemists, the
grandiose goals and sometimes secrecy,
continue today in our chemical quests – the
creation of synthetic life, a cure for aging. At the
same time, every time you boil an egg you
change the very nature of matter, in this case
the shape of the proteins in the egg.
The rise of modern science and its growing
prestige, especially the professionalization of
science in the nineteenth century, pushed out
the non experts. We’ve lost that sense of
chemistry as the art and science of the
everyday, and of ordinary people. But we can
get it back. Recently, as part of the Chemical
Heritage Foundation’s museum programme, I
asked a glass artist to give a talk and
presentation of her work. She was a little
nervous at first, saying she had never studied
chemistry and didn’t know anything about it.
But after speaking about what she did -- her
tools, the furnace, how she pulled molten glass
about, the metals she added, what happened to
the glass at different temperatures – she turned
to me in surprise and said, “I am a practical
chemist.”
Near the beginning of this essay I wrote:  “To
be human is to transform matter.”  I’d like to end
it with a variation. To transform matter is to be
Mendeleev’s periodic table 
“The Man Who Brought Law and Order to Chemistry.”  This is the title
of an article in the June 1971 issue of the UNESCO Courier devoted
to Dmitri Mendeleev, the man who enabled “the passing of the
study of chemistry from almost medieval trial-and-error methods to
a modern science.”
What, then, was Mendeleev's theory all about? “Briefly,” the
article goes on, “he proposed arranging the elements in lines and
columns (also called ‘periods’ and ‘groups’) inside a rectangle, with
their atomic weights rising in number from left to right along the
same line, one line following the other down the page. The columns
were determined by elements possessing analogous properties, the
same kind of combining oxide, for example.”
So what was so revolutionary about this table? The theory of the
periodic classification of the elements according to their atomic
weights, that the 35 year-old Siberian presented to the Russian
Chemical Society, in March1869, was in fact the discovery of a
natural law. The method he used not only made it possible to
correct a large number of calculation errors, but also to predict the
existence of hitherto unknown elements, such as gallium, scandium
and germanium (which were given these names later, in honour of
the countries in which they were discovered).
The great discoverers and inventors stir people’s imagination.
There is the apocryphal story of Newton discovering the law of
gravitation when an apple fell on his head, or that a boiling pot
inspired James Watt to come up with the idea for the steam engine.
Similarly, some say that Mendeleev saw the periodic table in a dream!
“Man tends to overlook that while scientific truth may suddenly
strike one man's mind as a flash of lightning,” the article goes on,
“that same scientist may have spent years of arduous research on
his subject. Indeed, it was Pasteur who later commented that
‘chance favours only the prepared mind.’ If we take a look at
Mendeleev's activities before 1869, it becomes fairly clear that the
emergence of the periodic table was no mere accident.” 
Apart from the periodic table, one of Mendeleev’s statements
about petroleum will remain forever graven in the memory of
humanity: “This substance is too precious to be burned; when we
burn it, we burn money; it should be used as a raw material for
chemical synthesis.” – K.M.
Michal Meyer was born in Israel. She has
worked as a meteorologist in New Zealand
and Fiji and as a journalist in Israel. She has a
Ph.D. in the history of science and has worked
for the Chemical Heritage Foundation since
September 2009.  She is the editor in chief of
Chemical Heritage magazine
(http://www.chemheritage.org/discover/mag
azine/index.aspx)index.aspx
© DR
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1  . 1 7
Chemistry
in everyday
life
Since the birth of modern chemistry in the 18th
century, the full list of services that it has
rendered humanity would be long indeed. And
equally impressive is the list of solutions it
promises to offer our planet as the 21st century
begins, especially in the field of medicine.
Analytical chemistry is forever pushing back the
thresholds for detecting toxic substances. And
nanochemistry is performing miracles, even
though its potential dangers are yet to be
conquered. Meanwhile, new generations of
drugs offer increasingly effective treatments for
cancer. 
Even though we live in an age of combinatory
chemistry, with high-speed screening and
molecular engineering, we still continue to turn
to nature for new substances. And ancestral
knowledge is as valuable as ever.
© DR
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
I love laser 
– it’s my 
guiding light
1 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
What is the common thread that could possibly link denim jeans, cancer and pesticides?
None is evident. Yet when South African chemist Tebello Nyokong describes her
fascinating research, the link that emerges is light. Nyokong, a specialist in nanochemistry,
loves laser, and is using it in ways that could have a revolutionary 
impact on medicine and the environment. 
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Professor Nyokong, you are currently involved
in research on a new cancer diagnosis and
treatment methodology, intended as an
alternative to chemotherapy. Can you give us a
simple explanation of your work?
As chemists, we are designers. My research deals
with the development of drugs from compounds
called phtalocyanines. We call them dyes
because their molecules are similar to those of
dyes you use in colouring blue jeans. They are
used in a treatment of cancer called
photodynamic therapy, or PDT. It’s a
multidisciplinary approach – chemists, biologists,
biotechnologists are working together. As a
chemist I am in the centre of it because I make
the molecules. I have a big team, about 30
people. And then I have other people all over the
world who are doing the preclinical testing. 
Molecules that dye blue jeans can also treat
cancer?
Look at a plant - leaves are green because of
chlorophyll. Blood is red because of
haemoglobin. Those molecules are actually
almost the same, except the one in leaves has
magnesium in the centre, the one in blood has
iron in the centre. A small change like that can
make the difference between non-medicine and
medicine. The molecule in the jeans is the same
as mine, with a slight change, a different metal,
to make it do what you want it to do.
PDT is a new treatment?
No, what is new is the drugs we are making. PDT
is already available for some cancers, in America,
Europe and Russia. It works with light. The drug is
introduced into the body and activated with
light. The problem is that right now the side
effects are very strong. The drug must be
introduced into the body and it must go to the
cancer tissue. If it goes to healthy tissue, which is
the case with the drugs now available, the
patient has to stay indoors out of the sun or the
healthy tissue also begins to get killed, like
chemotherapy.
Your molecules are safer?
This is the whole aim. We are making molecules
that are cancer specific – targeted to cancer. 
Also, with my own drugs, you need very little in
order to absorb light. And I have gone much
further because I am now combining my drugs
with drug delivery, which has never been done
before. This is the nanotechnology aspect. The
molecules have nanomaterials called quantum
dots attached to them that can penetrate very
easily any part of the body. They are good at
drug delivery and secondly they also give off
light, so we can see more easily where the cancer
is. So it is just beautiful what we do.
Can this treatment be used for all kinds of
cancer?
This treatment cannot replace surgery. The light
(to activate the drug) is transported with tubes –
we are using laser and fibre optics. If the cancer is
spread throughout the body, this cannot work.
It’s localized treatment. You have to direct the
laser exactly where the cancer is.
How did you come to choose this domain for
your research?
It was accidental – that’s the beauty of chemistry.
Once you have the interest, you are always
thinking: ‘what more can I do with molecules?’
The bottom line for me is that I started working
with laser, because I just really love light. I love
laser. It’s bright, direct and it has different
colours. I started finding different applications
for it. That was wonderful for me. My interest was
laser, not cancer.
Is nanochemistry dangerous?
I am afraid it is. Because something that can
penetrate and enter any part of the body is
dangerous. Secondly, the molecules that we
have made so far, the nanoparticles, in the centre
of them there are heavy metals. If they leak out,
they can attach themselves to your
haemoglobin, to other parts of the body and can
be dangerous to you. With the help of biologists,
we are testing to see how toxic they are and
trying to develop those that are least toxic. We
do research both on applications and their
toxicity. 
How long do you think it will take before your
drugs are in general use?
There are many variables when it comes to using
these drugs on people. One thing which is
problematic for oncologists is that lasers are
expensive and difficult to maintain. I can do
nothing on my own. I am a chemist  - we can
develop things – but collaboration is what’s
important to see if they work. The Centre for
Scientific and Industrial Research is doing pre-
clinical testing for me in South Africa. Beyond
that, a group in Switzerland has developed a very
interesting way to test – using egg embryos. You
inject the dye into the veins around the embryo
and test its activity.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1  . 1 9
PROFESSOR
NYOKONG answers
questions put by
Cathy Nolan,
UNESCO
© Micheline Pelletier
for L’Oréal Corporate
Foundation
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
2 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
Your research also has environmental
applications.
These molecules are really magic. They can do so
many different things. The process can be used
to purify water that has been polluted,
particularly by pesticides. In our countries,
people still have to have water from open
sources – run-off from the fields ends up in
household water, and we have to deal with that.
Throughout time, light has been used to purify
water. You expect bacteria and so on to be killed
by light. But if you put these molecules in the
water, that process is made faster. And also the
products that are formed are less toxic. If you do
it just biologically – just the sun - they can form
molecules that are more harmful to the body. We
have managed, by using this drug and light, to
make molecules that are no longer toxic at all to
human beings. This is much closer to success –
we have just patented how to do it.
Your goal is to develop a product?
That is my mission. It will come more quickly
from the pollution side. Dealing with people has
so many rules, it will take much longer. But I
would like to do it so that young people can see
that, in South Africa, they can take science and
develop a product. They cannot imagine this,
they believe things come from somewhere else.
Did you imagine when you were younger that
chemistry would be your life’s work?
Not in a million years, no. We had no role models.
But I was always ambitious – I always thought I
could be a doctor or a dentist. And teachers are
very important. I met a lecturer when I was in my
first year at the University (of Lesotho) He was in
the Peace Corps from America. He just made
chemistry so much fun. He made me feel that
chemistry is the place to be, and then I was
I can do nothing
on my own. I am a
chemist  - we can
develop things –
but collaboration
is what’s
important to see if
they work.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 2 1
J Lasers have a host of scientific applications. Shown here is
“Reflections and drops of water”, an illustration of the “Giant Laser
Fountain” experiment at the Laser Physics Laboratory  (CNRS/Paris
13). It reveals the functioning of optical fibres while demonstrating
the fundamental principles of optics. 
See  www.fontainelaser.fr
© K. Penalba/INP-CNRS
hooked. I also had opportunities. The university –
I originally come from Lesotho – gave me the
opportunity to be trained as an academic. I won
a scholarship to train in Canada. I took that
opportunity and managed to complete my
masters and doctorate. And I am doing the same
for others now. I have lecturers from all over
Africa – from all over the world, in fact - training
with me for their universities.
As the first woman in your department at
Rhodes University, you have said you get
challenged by doing the “impossible”.
This is the reality – it was very difficult for me to
progress with very little support. Many women
give up because of this. You’ve got to be a little
mad to do what I have done. But what I vowed is
that I will help other women as much as I can.
Their confidence levels are not as high. I don’t
know why, but men are confident even when
what they are saying does not make much sense!
As a trailblazer, would you say this is a good
time to be a woman scientist in South Africa?
Yes, it’s a good time. I have a lot of girl students. I
attract them like bees, even though I’m a little bit
tough!
To be honest, I think people don’t take the
opportunities that are provided for us. We are in
a very lucky country. South Africa is both a first
and a third world country. There are very poor
people, eating from bins out there, and very rich.
The infrastructure is there and the government
has made a conscious decision that they are not
just going to combat poverty, they will also
develop science and technology. People must
really take advantage of this and work hard…but
apparently hard work is not very popular.
Funding is available for us to get equipment, to
get more students – I’m applying, I’m grabbing. 
Tebello Nyokong, 59, is a Professor of
Medicinal Chemistry and Nanotechnology at
Rhodes University (South Africa) and Director
of the Nanotechnology Innovation Centre for
Sensors (Mintek). She was one of the five
Laureates of the 2009 L’Oréal-UNESCO Awards
for Women in Science.
Monitoring the
country’s health
Chemistry can provide information about the
thorny question of heavy metal contamination,
playing an important part in decision-making in
Ethiopia, where the idea of making 2011
International Year of Chemistry first arose.  
Heavy metal contamination of the food chain is becoming a serious
issue, globally. Cadmium, lead, mercury and arsenic are polluting the air,
water and soil and turning up in foods. Meanwhile, rapid industrial
growth, the widespread use of chemicals in agriculture, and increasing
urbanization are all contributing factors. 
Heavy metals are present in nature in trace quantities, even
infinitesimally small amounts. In order to detect them, a range of
sophisticated analytical methods is needed, with three broad steps:
sampling, pre-treatment of the sample and analysis. The choice of
method depends on several factors, including cost, sensitivity (limits of
detection), speed and availability of equipment. The samples for
analysis can come from water, soil, fish, plants (especially khat, tea and
coffee), vegetables and fruit. 
While heavy metals occur naturally in small quantities in agricultural
soils, their capacity to accumulate makes them toxic. By detecting them,
we can identify their harmful effects, not just on the development of
crops, but also on human health. 
The research we are carrying out in Ethiopia provides baseline data
on the concentrations of heavy metals, enabling us to keep government
and the public informed of any potential risks. According to our
analyses, the concentration of heavy metals is still relatively low in
Ethiopia, but, because of human activity, may rise above natural levels
from time to time. Chemistry, then, is helping us to monitor the health
of our country. 
Bhagwan Singh Chandravanshi is professor in the Department of
Chemistry, Faculty of Science, Addis Ababa University, Ethiopia..
©
 D
R
Bhagwan Singh Chandravanshi
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Anlong Xu
2 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
Although significant advances have been made
in cancer prevention, diagnosis and treatment,
cancer remains one of the leading causes of
death in all societies. Until the 1960s, cancer was
treated by surgery and radiation therapy. But, in
the last fifty years or so, as people gain further
understanding of the molecular basis of the
disease, and with the rapid development of new
chemical agents in the treatment of cancer,
chemotherapy has become one of the most
powerful weapons against the illness.
The first modern antitumor drug, nitrogen
mustard, was discovered by chance during World
War II. Researchers accidentally noticed that
mustard gas – which got its name from its yellow
colour and was used as a chemical weapon in the
First World War – can reduce white blood cell
counts. In 1942 a team of Yale pharmacologists,
including Louis Goodman and Alfred Gilman,
used it to treat advanced lymphomas and found
that it could induce tumour regression if
administered systemically. In 1949 the U.S. Food
New chemotherapy cancer treatments aim to target the affected cells
without harming healthy tissues. Easier said than done, though.
Researchers are following a number of promising paths, including age-
old herbal remedies. One herb that has been used in traditional Chinese
medicine to treat digestive tract tumours is opening new horizons for
modern medicine. 
and Drug Administration (FDA) authorized
nitrogen mustard to be put on the market. This
gave a boost to the development of a number of
other chemotherapeutic drugs for the treatment
of various types of cancer.
But, as we know, these chemotherapy drugs
can cause serious side effects. We had to wait
until the beginning of the third millennium for
the dawn of a new era of molecular targeted
cancer therapy. This consists of a new generation
of drugs that are not dispersed throughout the
body (damaging healthy tissue as they go) but
target precisely tissues where the cancer cells are
to be found. 
Avoiding collateral damage
Most of the drugs applied in clinic for the
treatment of cancer are organic compounds, but
there are also drugs based on inorganic
compounds, particularly metals. The use of
metals to treat human disease can be traced
back to Antiquity. For example, 2,500 years ago,
Herbs and metal:  
a pact against cancer
L Fragments of
cancerous cells.
© INSERM/J. Valladeau
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
the Chinese discovered that gold could be used
as a medicine. More recently, platinum, another
precious metal, has become the basis for one of
the most frequently used anticancer treatments
in the world, cisplatin, shown in 1965 by an
American chemist, Barnett Rosenberg and his
colleagues, to block the spread of cancer cells.
Once again, though, the side effects were
toxic, which encouraged researchers to develop
drugs based on other metals, such as ruthenium.
Thanks to the pioneering work of chemists like
Michael J. Clarke (USA), Bernhard K. Keppler
(Austria), Peter J. Sadler (UK) and their colleagues,
ruthenium seems to be a particularly attractive
alternative to platinum. Like iron, it is able to bind
to transferrin, the blood serum protein that
transports iron to the organs. But, instead of
spreading throughout the body, it accumulates in
tumours, attracted by cancer cells, which have
approximately 5−15 times more transferrin
receptors than normal cells. In this way
ruthenium directly targets the cancer cell and
destroys it. Apart from their great precision,
compared with their platinum counterparts,
certain ruthenium complexes have the capacity
to inhibit tumour metastasis – in other words to
prevent the spread of cancer to other parts of the
body.
A novel strategy
Broadening its field of research to ruthenium
complexes, our research group has recently
reported that the combination of ruthenium and
the active ingredients of a Harmel (Peganum
harmala) may provide a novel strategy for
developing anticancer drugs. The powdered
seeds of this plant have long been used in herbal
formulas of traditional Chinese medicine to cure
tumours of the digestive tract. Today, some of the
chemical complexes formed by the alliance of
metals and herbs are able to halt the spread of
cancer cells much more effectively than cisplatin.
What is more, we have noticed that these
complexes can simultaneously induce apoptosis
and cytoprotective autophagy in human cancer
cells (see below). To our knowledge, this is the
first time this dual action has been demonstrated.
Apoptosis, sometimes known as
“programmed cell death” is a normal process that
results in the death of certain ‘damaged’ cells, at a
given moment. But with cancer cells, apoptosis is
switched off or deregulated, which may explain
their continuous proliferation. So, some of the
latest research in oncology is focusing on
molecules that can induce the suicide of cancer
cells. 
Autophagy, on the other hand, which literally
means “eating oneself,” is a mechanism that
enables a cell partially to digest its own contents,
in order to survive. But it is a double-edged
sword, as, although it can mean the survival of
healthy cells to the detriment of ailing cells, the
inverse can also be true. The molecules we are
working on aim to activate autophagy as a way to
destroy cancer cells that are resistant to
apoptosis. This is a new approach in the
treatment of cancer, which should help combat
the disease.
According to statistics provided by the U.S.
National Cancer Institute (NCI), the survival rates
of some types of cancer have been greatly
improved in the last few decades. Even so, cure
rates for certain types of cancer remain very low.
For example, the overall 5-year survival rate for
liver cancer is less than 10%. The United Nations
International Agency for Research on Cancer
(IARC) estimates that approximately 760 million
people died of cancer in 2008, and the number
could reach 1320 million in 2030. The war is not
over yet. 
The molecules we
are working on
aim to activate
autophagy as a
way to destroy
cancer cells that
are resistant to
apoptosis. This is a
new approach in
the treatment of
cancer, which
should help
combat the
disease.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 2 3
L Cell culture: apoptosis in a
dopaminergic neuron. 
© INSERM/P. Michel
Anlong Xu is Vice-president for Research and
Development, and Professor of Molecular
Immunology and Biology at Sun Yat-sen
(Zhongshan) University, Guangzhou, China. He
is the Director of State Key Laboratory of
Biocontrol, and serves on the expert
committee on new drugs at the State Food
and Drug Administration of China (SFDA). He
is also a member of the Pharmacopoeia
Commission of China.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
scientific relations between countries which
possess not only most of the organic substances,
but also the knowledge – often non-scientific –
surrounding these resources, and those countries
wishing to use them for industrial purposes. A
new page has turned in the history of the
exploitation of the extraordinary chemodiversity
of so-called ‘megadiverse’ countries. 
Chemodiversity is one component of
biodiversity. Secondary metabolites – alkaloids,
lignans, terpenes, phenylpropanoids, tanins, latex,
resins and the thousands of other substances
identified so far – which have a whole host of
functions in the life of plants, are also playing a
crucial role in the development of new drugs. 
And, although we are living in the era of
combinatory chemistry, with high-speed
screening and molecular engineering, we still
continue to turn to nature for the raw materials
behind many medically and economically
successful new treatments. Nature has provided
over half of the chemical substances that have
been approved by regulatory bodies across the
world over the past 40 years. 
Vanderlan da Silva Bolzani is Professor of
Chemistry at the Institute of Chemistry-UNESP,
(Araraquara, Sao Paulo, Brazil) and Past
President of the Brazilian Chemical Society
(2008 - 2010) 
2 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
Since the Earth Summit (Rio de Janeiro, Brazil,
1992), the exploitation of natural resources and the
socio-economic benefits of bioprospecting have
become increasingly poignant issues. One of the
principal goals of the Convention on biological
diversity, which was adopted at the Summit, is “the
conservation of biological diversity, the sustainable
use of its components, and the fair and equitable
sharing of the benefits arising from the utilization
of genetic resources.” But bioprospecting, which
consists of making an inventory of the
components of biodiversity with a view to
ensuring their conservation and sustainable use,
has, on the contrary, not ceased to be misused to
further the interests of industry, which often
patents the substances as they are found. 
The tenth Conference of Parties to the
Convention, held in Nagoya (Japan) in October
this year, will change the picture, though, as it
reached a legally binding agreement on the fair
and equitable use of genetic resources. As from
2012, this Protocol will regulate commercial and
Nature has
provided over half
of the chemical
substances that
have been
approved by
regulatory bodies
across the world
over the past 40
years. 
The primacy of
nature
Vanderlan da Silva Bolzani
L The Kallawaya are an
itinerant community of healers
and herbalists living in the
Bolvian Andes. The Andean
Cosmovision of the Kallawaya
was inscribed in 2008 on the
Representative List of the
Intangible Cultural Heritage of
Humanity.
© UNESCO/J. Tubiana
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
What explains the phenomenal growth of
India’s pharmaceutical industry, which has
become synonymous with the production of
high-quality, low-cost generic drugs in the last
few decades?   
One of India’s foremost science-based industries,
India’s pharmaceutical industry has wide-ranging
capabilities in the complex fields of drug
manufacturing and technology.  Industrial
turnover has grown from a modest US$ 300
million in 1980 to about US$ 19 billion in 2008.
India now ranks third worldwide after the USA
and Japan in terms of the volume of production,
with a 10% share of the world market. In terms of
the value of production, it ranks 14th for a 1.5%
global share.
Several factors have contributed to the industry’s
dynamic growth. In 1970, the government
introduced the Indian Patents Act to reduce the
hold of foreign multinationals (which had
dominated the Indian market since the country’s
Independence in 1947).  Favourable to
intellectual property rights, this policy allowed
Indian pharmaceutical companies to come up
with cost-effective processes for imitating
known products, by not recognizing
international product patents for
pharmaceutical products. 
In three decades, India’s pharmaceutical industry has
become the third most important in the world. Almost
self-sufficient in medicines, it holds first place for the
number of factories approved by the US Food and
Drug Administration (FDA). Specializing in the
manufacture of generics at
unbeatable prices, its
industry boasts some
5000 factories,
employing 340,000
workers. What is the
key to this incredible
success? And what is 
the downside? 
Interview with SUNIL MANI, by Shiraz Sidhva, 
correspondent for the UNESCO Courier
India’s 
pharmaceutical boom
© DR
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
2 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
This afforded the industry a long learning period,
which allowed Indian drug producers to become
experts in ‘reverse engineering’ (or the copying of
patented foreign pharmaceuticals drugs), or
developing technologies locally and in an
extremely cost-effective manner. 
Another factor that has fuelled the industry’s
growth is the copious supply of science
graduates. India’s higher education system is
biased in favour of natural sciences compared to
engineering and technology. During the 1970s
and 1980s, and even up to the 90s, the ratio of
science graduates to engineers was about 8:1
(eight science graduates for every engineer
produced). This gave India a comparative
advantage in science-based industries like the
pharmaceuticals industry. 
The Indian state also gave research grants and
tax incentives for setting up R&D facilities. 
How has the industry changed after 2005, when
India ended its protectionist policy and
amended its patent laws to comply with its
World Trade Organization (WTO) Trade Related
Intellectual Property Agreement (TRIPS)
obligations? Does the emphasis remain on
exports, even though the Indian domestic
market has doubled in the last decade? 
Much of industrial growth is fuelled by exports,
with exports growing by an average rate of 22%
between 2003 and 2008. India currently exports
drug intermediates, bulk drugs, APIs [Active
Pharmaceutical Ingredients], finished dosage
formulations, biopharmaceuticals and clinical
services. The top five destinations in 2008 were,
in descending order, the USA, Germany, Russia,
the United Kingdom and China.
The industry is made up of about 5,000 licensed
Indian and foreign manufacturers, which directly
employ about 340,000 individuals. It is
dominated by pharmaceutical formulations – the
process of combining different chemical
substances to manufacture a drug – and over
400 active pharmaceutical ingredients (APIs) for
use in drug manufacture. 
India is self-sufficient in most drugs, as witnessed
by a growing positive trade balance. The
pharmaceuticals industry is one of India’s most
innovative, in terms of R&D and the number of
patents granted, both in India and abroad. It is
very active in the global market for generics,
supplying even developed countries.  
India accounted for one out of every four
abbreviated new drug applications (generic
product approvals) from the US government's
Food and Drug Administration (USFDA) in 2007
and 2008. The Indian pharmaceutical industry
A long learning
period for the
nation’s industry
has allowed
Indian drug
producers to
become experts in
‘reverse
engineering’. 
Sunil Mani is Planning
Commission Chair in
Development
Economics at the
Centre for
Development Studies
in Trivandrum (India).
He is a contributing
author to the UNESCO
Science Report 2010.
© UNESCO/M. Ravassard
J Manufacturing drugs
wearing protective clothing
in India, one of the world
leaders in the pharmaceutical
industry.
©Sinopictures/dinodia/Speci
alist Stock
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
also accounts for approximately 25% of drug
master files with USFDA and has the highest
number of plants approved by that agency, of
any foreign country. 
Some Indian manufacturers who were at the
forefront of producing generic drugs are now
keen to formulate new drugs instead of copies.
Is India poised to launch its first domestically
developed drug? 
To bring a new drug to the market is an
extremely costly affair, sometimes involving
billions of dollars.  India also has regulations,
which may not be as stringent as those of the
USFDA, but they are not easy, because,
ultimately, the drugs are being used on people.
Clinical trials are extremely costly, and the failure
rates are extremely high. And the period
involved in these processes could easily take
nine to ten years. Drug discovery on a small scale
is already going on, but if it wants to become an
originator of the global drug manufacturing
industry, it will take quite a bit of time. It is
unlikely this will happen on a very large scale. It
calls for massive amounts of investment in R&D,
which most Indian companies are not in a
position to do. 
Could you elaborate on the recent emergence
of India as a hub for pharmaceutical research
and development, and a favoured destination
for foreign pharmaceutical companies to hold
clinical trials?   
One spin-off of India’s innovative capability in
pharmaceuticals is that it has become a popular
destination for clinical trials, contract
manufacturing and R&D outsourcing. These
capabilities hold great promise for the Indian
pharmaceutical industry, as an estimated   
US$ 103 billion of patented US drugs are at risk
of losing patents by 2012. Furthermore, the
global market for contract manufacturing of
prescription drugs is expected to grow from 
US$ 26 billion to US$ 44 billion by 2015 or so. 
The costs of conducting clinical trials in India are
much lower compared to Western countries.
Another important factor is that there is a large
supply of treatment-naïve patients, who have
never used drugs before – the study of the drug
being tested is much more effective on these
first-time drug users. The third factor is that there
are highly-skilled English-speaking doctors
available to conduct these trials (most higher
education is conducted in English in India). Also,
the time taken to conduct clinical trials in India is
much shorter, because it is easier to get patients
to agree to these trials.      
India continues to be a leading supplier of less
expensive antibiotics, cancer therapy, and AIDS
drugs to the developing world. What has been
the impact of generic drugs produced by Indian
companies on health care in India? And for the
rest of the world?
This is difficult to measure because the Indian
pharmaceutical industry has been more
interested in exporting to other developing
countries and also to the West. Indian
pharmaceutical companies have been
instrumental in dramatically lowering the prices
of anti-retroviral drugs, and this has made AIDS
treatments much more affordable. This is one of
the most important recent contributions of
India’s pharmaceutical industry to India and the
rest of the world. 
Unfortunately, however, the emphasis on exports
by Indian companies has prevented them from
manufacturing drugs for the so-called neglected
diseases, like malaria and tuberculosis, which
Western companies are simply not interested in,
because the markets are very small, and patients
suffering from these diseases are usually poor
and cannot afford to pay anything. There isn’t
much money in these drugs. Indian companies
also share the same ideology, so none of them
have any credible R&D projects to manufacture
drugs to combat these diseases. 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 2 7
The costs of
conducting
clinical trials in
India are much
lower compared to
Western countries.
Another
important factor is
that there is a
large supply of
treatment-naïve
patients, who
have never used
drugs before – the
study of the drug
being tested is
much more
effective on these
first-time drug
users.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
2 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
drugs can be encapsulated and released slowly.
Similarly, alginates are used in dressings, to absorb
wound fluids.
Marine algal extracts, such as fucoidan, have
great potential for further development as
products in the nutraceutical (from "nutrition" and
"pharmaceutical") and pharmaceutical markets.
However, one of the greatest challenges ahead for
the use of these types of ingredient, is sourcing
high quality seaweed.  With decreasing water
quality through heavy industrialization, it is
becoming increasingly difficult to find seaweed
that has low levels of toxins, such as heavy metals.
The other great challenge is to use this resource in
an environmentally sustainable way, so that the
biodiversity of the marine ecosystem is
maintained. 
Vicki Gardiner is a member of the Australian
Academy of Science and is Honorary General
Secretary of the Royal Australian Chemical
Institute (RACI).  She is Manager of Innovation
and Product Development at Marinova Pty Ltd
and is the RACI Convenor for the 2011
International Year of Chemistry. 
Soon after the archaeological site at Monte Verde
(Chile) was discovered in 1977, samples of nine
different seaweeds were found in a healer’s hut,
dating back over 14,000 years.  And, 17,000
kilometres away, in the Okinawa archipelago
(Japan) the health benefits of a brown seaweed
have long been known. It turns out to contain
fucoidan, which is rich in sulphated
polysaccharides (natural sugars).
Over the past 30 years, some 800 scientific
papers on fucoidan and other marine
polysaccharides have confirmed what the
Japanese have known for centuries – it is a
powerful anti-inflammatory and anticoagulant,
which blocks certain viruses and boosts the
immune system. And very recent research shows
that fucoidan-based products can also reduce the
symptoms of osteoarthritis of the knee.
Nowadays, a number of drugs and nutritional
supplements contain algae or their extracts. Whole
dried, milled kelp is used for its iodine content,
while agars and alginates have gelling properties.
Agars, which are extracts from red seaweeds, are
also commonly used as microbiological culture
mediums for identifying infectious agents, and in
proprietary laxatives.  Alginate salts form gels, a
property that makes them useful in patches, where
Seaweed for health Vicki Gardiner
Very recent
research shows
that fucoidan-
based products
can reduce the
symptoms of
osteoarthritis of
the knee.
K Wakame, or sea fern, is an
edible seaweed very popular
in Japan.
© Ian Wallace
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The new
face of
chemistry
Chemistry is behind most of the innovations
that have improved our lives, but, for much of
the general public, it is still the devil in disguise,
conjuring images of black smoke from factory
chimneys. And it is easy to see why – an
accumulation of drug scandals, toxic pesticides
and industrial disasters have tarnished its image
to such an extent that we often no longer see
the good it does. 
But there are chemical solutions to chemical
pollution. Over the past two decades, university
researchers and industrial chemists have been
competing to find ingenious responses to
climate change and environmental degradation.
“Green chemistry” has the wind in its sails, in
developed, emerging and developing countries
alike. This is born out by the enthusiasm of the
students who wrote to us. And they are just a
tiny fragment of the world’s young people who,
having abandoned chemistry, are now
returning, reinventing it at the same time.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1  . 2 9
© Mikal Schlosser 
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
After the chemical gas industry ran into problems with both the hole in
the ozone layer and then global warming, research has been carried out
to find less dangerous alternatives. Over the past few years, the potential
global warming effect of gases used in aerosol cans, refrigerators and
air-conditioning units has been reduced by a factor of 350.  
Anyone using a pressurized spray-can in 1973
was effectively helping to kill the planet. But no
one knew. A year later, the chemists Mario
Molina and F. Sherwood Roland (1995 Nobel
laureates in chemistry) had found the answer,
discovering that the Freon gas powering aerosol
sprays was destroying the ozone layer.
After that, a young graduate student, Ole
John Nielsen, developed a passion for predicting
the fate of chemicals in the atmosphere. He was
to go on to become a professor at the University
of Copenhagen, a member of the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change
(IPCC) and ‘chemical fortune teller’. 
According to Nielsen, “They were saying that
these chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) were going to
eat away the ozone layer protecting the planet
from ultraviolet radiation. The increase in
radiation would cause cancers… They were
practically announcing the end of the world.
And, being a young and naïve student of
chemistry, I naturally felt I had to study these
compounds, and how they affected the
atmosphere.” 
New diet for the 
ozone eaters
Jes Andersen
Danish journalist and
documentary
filmmaker, meets 
Ole John Nielsen
3 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
L It was not until the 1970s
that scientists discovered the
harmful effects of Freon gas,
used in aerosols. 
© iStockphoto.com/Franck
Boston 
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The idea that human activity could harm the
Earth’s atmosphere may have been novel in
1974. But by the mid-eighties it was confirmed –
CFCs were creating a hole in the ozone layer
above Antarctica. 
With CFCs also being used in air-conditioners
and refrigerators, millions of tons were being
released into the atmosphere. “Back then, you
just didn’t think about what might happen with
these compounds, or what their effect might be”,
remembers Ole John Nielsen. 
Having said this, the United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP) was becoming
concerned and was preparing to plug every
suspect aerosol nozzle. As a result, the Montreal
Protocol on Substances That Deplete the Ozone
Layer was opened for signature on 16
September, 1987. Today it has been ratified by
196 states. In essence, this international treaty
declared all compounds threatening the ozone
layer illegal. The death knell had been sounded
for CFCs.
Meanwhile Nielsen had built a reputation
within atmospheric chemistry. He was getting
ready to tackle the “ozone-eaters”. In one year he
and his group had published no fewer than 25
articles on the subject. So, when chemical
manufacturers approached him to test a new
compound that might replace CFCs, he wasn’t
surprised. “We were the right people at the right
time, with the right competencies,” says Nielsen.
The new compound was a hydro-
fluorocarbon, known as HFC 134a. And it really
was less dangerous for the ozone layer, even not
dangerous at all. So, as from 1994, HFC 134a
replaced CFCs in most applications. And for a
while Professor Nielsen thought that he’d better
find himself a new scientific field. 
But the Danish scientist didn’t have to
hang up his atmospheric gloves. The product
that he had pronounced safe for ozone
threatened Earth in a different way.
It turned out that HFC 134a prevents
infrared radiation from escaping from the
planet, producing a greenhouse effect. The
ozone-friendly compound turned out to have
a global warming potential (GWP) some 1400
times greater than CO2.
As it happened, the industry seemed open
to the idea of testing and adopting a better
refrigerant . “I have seen a gigantic shift in
attitude in my time,” says Nielsen. “Nowadays,
if someone wants to produce a compound in
large quantities, they will ask a specialist what
will happen if it is released. That wasn’t always
the case. Of course we also see legislation to
protect the environment, but it is clear that
industries, especially big corporations, are
acting much more responsibly today”.
From 2011, European automobile air-
conditioning systems in Europe will have to
use a refrigerant with a GWP below 150. HFC
134a had a GWP of 1400. Nielsen and his
team, have tested a new compound, HFO-
1234yf, which has a GWP of just 4. This should
help car manufacturers meet European
regulations. 
Next in line, says Nielsen, are bio-fuels.  It
may turn out that ethanol and butanol have
no effect on global warming but, in the
atmosphere they might generate products
that are harmful to man. “If bio fuels are to
replace diesel and gasoline, we’d better be
sure of what they do to the atmosphere
before we use them. And that holds for any
compound released into nature”, he says.  
Ole John Nielsen, is a
professor at the
University of
Copenhagen and a
member of the
Intergovernmental
Panel on Climate
Change (IPCC), which
was awarded the Nobel
Peace Prize in 2007. He
is a specialist in
atmospheric chemistry.
© Jes Andersen
The idea that
human activity
could harm the
Earth’s atmosphere
may have been
novel in 1974. But
by the mid-eighties
it was confirmed.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1  . 3 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Geo-engineering is a hot topic within the scientific community. Trying to limit
global warming by manipulating the environment is an idea with a whole raft of
ramifications currently being looked at by a growing number of chemists and
physicists, including Klaus Lackner (USA), Ian Jones (Australia), James Lovelock
(UK), and Paul Crutzen (Netherlands), to mention just those quoted here. 
They naturally hope that their research will bring us new sources of energy
to help slow down climate warming. But, in the meantime, they are working on
what they call “Plan B”. There are two preferred alternatives for saving the
planet from global warming – one consists of capturing CO2 in order to reduce
the concentration of greenhouse gases  (e.g. doping trees with nitrogen,
synthetic trees, seeding the oceans or covering the seabed with calcium); the
other involves deviating some solar radiation with giant parasols made up of
billions of minute glass discs, or a protective layer of salt or sulphate particles . 
While there are fewer risks with the former approach, scientists feel it is too
slow compared to the second option, which is considered too risky. In both
cases, the costs are very high and the efficacy of the solutions remains limited. 
Iron tonic for the
ocean’s anaemia?
Philip W. Boyd
Iron is one of the main elements
taken up by phytoplankton – the
microscopic organisms living on the
surface of the oceans. The iron
encourages these micro-algae to
proliferate, assimilating dissolved
carbon dioxide (CO2) through
photosynthesis as they grow. When
they die, a small, but significant
portion of the carbon remains
trapped in the ocean, sinking to the
bottom, where it is effectively taken
out of circulation. This natural
process is called a “biological pump”
for carbon. 
One idea for limiting global
warming is to use these pumps to
trap part of the CO2 released into the
atmosphere by man since the
Industrial Revolution, by ‘seeding’
the ocean with massive quantities of
iron in the form of micro-particles. 
Why? Because phytoplankton are
anaemic. Although iron is the fourth
most abundant element in the
Earth’s crust, it is very scarce in much
of the remote ocean, too far from the
Global
warming: 
Plan B
3 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
coast to be supplied with iron from
rivers. In about a third of these remote
waters, the phytoplankton are anaemic,
and just like humans, they do not
function well when they are run down.
Although small, these cells are found
over vast swathes of ocean, so their
collective anaemia has a global
influence, particularly on the climate.
Indeed, healthy phytoplankton produce
more oxygen than all the planet’s forests
put together.
This gave rise to the idea of artificially
‘fertilizing’ parts of the ocean with iron
particles in order to stimulate the growth
of algae. But, between cup and lip… 
Today, a growing number of scientific
experts are sceptical of the wisdom of
adding iron to the world’s oceans in
order to mop up CO2 emissions, and
warn of the possibility of creating
unwanted side effects, far from simply
imitating what Nature does. This ‘seeding’
with iron could lead to vast underwater
areas starved of oxygen (because the
algae take up oxygen that is then not
available for other marine species) and
thus more acidic, while possibly
encouraging the spread of toxic algae. 
Artificially fertilizing the oceans in
the hope of solving rising levels of
atmospheric CO2 is, then, a high-risk
venture that appears to be as expensive
as many other geo-engineering
schemes with much lower risk for
marine resources. These include
‘artificial trees’ consisting of a column
and the equivalent of branches,
designed to capture CO2. 
Philip W. Boyd is a professor in ocean
biogeochemistry at the joint National
Institute of Water and Atmosphere/
University of Otago Centre for Chemical
and Physical Oceanography based in
Dunedin (New Zealand). 
Synthetic trees
A meeting with Klaus Lackner
Katerina Markelova 
Topping the list of solutions to capture
CO2 and reduce the concentration of
greenhouse gases are synthetic trees,
invented by geophysicist, Klaus Lackner,
of Columbia University (USA). Although
still at the testing stage, this ‘CO2
scrubber’ should filter air rather like a
natural tree does, but with a much
higher capacity. “A CO2 scrubber of the
same size as a windmill can remove far
more CO2 than the windmill can avoid,”
explains Lackner.
He got the idea in 1998, “having
realised how much CO2 is in the air. My
daughter, Clare, did a science project and
demonstrated that she can take CO2 out
of the air.” In one night, he says, she was
able to capture half of the CO2 in the air.
Extending this experiment, Klaus
Lackner built a “vacuum cleaner” which,
when placed in a windy area, absorbs air
carrying CO2 and filters it, before
releasing the purified air again. Caustic
soda is the key to the method’s success.
When it is in contact with carbon
dioxide it makes a sodium bicarbonate
solution. This liquid is then compressed
until it forms a highly concentrated gas
that can be stored in porous rocks on
the sea floor. Because it is denser than
seawater, it cannot escape and can be
sequestered for millions of years.
For Professor Lackner, “the first step
is to remove some CO2 from the air. If it
proves cost-effective, it could balance
out emissions from cars and aeroplanes.
If air capture, together with other CO2
reduction technologies, manages to
stop the rise in CO2 in the atmosphere,
we could then start to use additional air
capture.” 
Synthetic trees provide another
piece of the jigsaw for international
negotiations on carbon dioxide
emissions, because the technology
makes it possible to collect CO2 on
behalf of another country. “Air capture
can separate the [CO2] sources from the
sinks” says Klaus Lackner. “This makes it
possible to import and export carbon
reductions.  It also makes it possible to
strive for a world in which all CO2
emissions can be addressed.
Automobiles and airplanes need not be
off-limits in this discussion.” 
At present, this process is still
expensive, “just like a hand-made car”,
says Lackner, who is nevertheless
optimistic that costs will come down.
But artificial trees are not a miracle cure.
As he explains, “the major energy cost is
in the compression, which, if it uses
electricity, would result in the release of
an equivalent of some 20% of the
captured CO2 at the site of a distant
power plant.” 
It is, though, a long and involved
process. “It needs time and
commitment,” says Lackner, anticipating
the increased use of renewable energy.
“We may be able to reduce the CO2 in
the atmosphere, but this does not give
us an excuse to continue to emit.” 
J J Evidence of purposeful iron supply driving a
phytoplankton bloom in offshore waters in summer
2002.  The ‘Ocean Color’ satellite image provides a
map of the stocks of phytoplankton in the ocean, with
blue denoting low stocks and progressively warmer
colours – from green to red – indicating higher stocks.  
© Courtesy of Jim Gower (IOS,
Canada)/NASA/Orbimage
I The capacity of plants to capture CO2 served as a
model for Kalus Lackner’s synthetic trees.
© UNESCO/Linda Shen
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1  . 3 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
possibility. He concludes that, “as there
is a high degree of similarity between
the upper haze layer on Venus and the
terrestrial stratospheric sulphate layer
(Junge layer), which is an important
regulator of the Earth’s climate and the
abundance of ozone, these
experimental and modelling results may
be relevant to stratospheric aerosol
chemistry and the applications of this
chemistry for geoengineering of the
Earth’s climate.” 
We are still at the stage of
hypotheses. SO2 is a gas that, at high
concentrations, can provoke lung and
cardio-vascular diseases, while
rendering the oceans more acidic and
corroding metals, etc. Researchers are
agreed that there is still a long way to
go before even thinking of applying this
kind of “sun screen” on Earth.  
Venus to the rescue
Jasmina Šopova
Does Venus hold the key to our
deliverance from global warming? In a
press release dated 5 November 2010,
the French National Scientific Research
Centre (CNRS) announced that an
international team of scientists had just
located a layer of sulphur dioxide (SO2)
in the upper atmosphere of Venus. “SO2
is of particular interest [to them] since
this gas could be used to cool down the
Earth via a geo-engineering process put
forward by Chemistry Nobel Laureate
Paul Crutzen [1995]”, explains the CNRS
communiqué.
Five years ago, the celebrated Dutch
chemist and meteorologist imagined an
emergency solution to accelerated
warming, which consisted of releasing a
million tons of sulphur into the
stratosphere.  Via a natural chemical
reaction, this would turn into sulphur
dioxide, then into particles of sulphate.
By reflecting the sun’s rays, these
particles would reduce the average
temperature of Earth. This idea was
inspired by research in the 1970s by the
Russian climatologist, Mikhail Budyko,
as well as by the eruption of the
Pinatubo volcano (Philippines), which
threw 10 million tonnes of sulphur into
the air in 1991, leading to a drop in the
Earth’s mean temperature of half a
degree the following year.
Xi Zhang, who carried out the
computer simulations that confirmed
the presence of SO2 in the upper
atmosphere of Venus, says that the
applications of this discovery to the
manipulation of climate are outside his
field of competence. Even so, the article
that this researcher and his team at the
Californian Institute of Technology [Cal
Tech] published in Nature Geoscience,
(31 October 2010), does not exclude this
K View of one face of Venus taken by the Magellan
probe.. © NASA/ Courtesy nasaimages.org
3 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 3 5
On 4 October 2010, disaster struck in Hungary. In
the aluminium plant operated by the company
MAL near the town of Kolontár, 160 kilometres
from Budapest, the walls of a reservoir gave way.
A two metre-high torrent of red toxic sludge
poured out, burying people and houses in its
wake. Nine people died, 150 were injured.
Several hundred thousand tonnes of toxic sludge
contaminated 40 square kilometres of land. The
sludge was a waste product of the aluminium
production process and hazardous because it
contained highly caustic sodium hydroxide as
well as toxic heavy metals such as mercury,
arsenic and chromium. 
In recent decades, chemical accidents have
repeatedly been the cause of worldwide horror
and dismay – and the apocalyptic images of
them have had a lasting negative effect on the
chemical industry. In 1976, dioxin gas was
released from a plant operated by Icmesa, a
subsidiary of Roche, in Seveso, a Northern Italian
town near Milan. The gas cloud, thousands of
times more toxic than potassium cyanide, left a
trail of death and destruction – plants shrivelled,
The chemical industry is one of the most important in the world, worth
a staggering US$3.6 trillion a year. For decades it was not interested in
sustainability or protecting the environment. But after major disasters
such as Bhopal and Seveso, attitudes have begun to change. Instead of
dirty chemistry, green chemistry is now all the rage all over the world.
Jens Lubbadeh
German 
correspondent for 
The UNESCO Courier
and journalist for 
Greenpeace Magazine
L The main principles of
Green Chemistry, which
emerged at the end of the
1980s, are to avoid producing
waste, to lower energy
consumption, improve
production efficiency and
explore renewable resources.
©123rf.com/Michal Rozewski
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
trees were defoliated, thousands of animals
perished. Pictures of children’s disfigured faces
and workers wearing gas masks and white
protective clothing went round the world. Eight
years later, there was an even more horrific
accident in India. Forty tonnes of highly toxic
Methyl isocyanate gas escaped from a factory
belonging to the US chemical giant Union
Carbide (now a subsidiary of Dow Chemical) in
the Central Indian town of Bhopal. Several
thousand people died and up to half a million
are still suffering from the after-effects of the
disaster today. Bhopal is considered to be the
most serious chemical accident to date. Two
years later, Europe became a victim again, when
a warehouse near Basel belonging to the
chemical giant Sandoz (now Novartis) went up in
flames. Toxic pesticides poured into the Rhine,
turning the water red for hundreds of kilometres;
tonnes of dead fish drifted down the river.
Nº1 polluter
Kolontár, Bhopal, Seveso, Sandoz. The reasons for
these disasters are almost always the same –
negligence, sloppiness and human error. And
almost always the companies try to cover up and
play down the causes and the consequences of
the accidents. The results are similar too –
devastated countryside, vegetation destroyed,
dead animals and, in amongst them, workers in
their protective gear, looking like aliens. The
general public is increasingly worried about
these invisible deadly dangers, now not just
radiation but chemicals, too. This lay behind the
establishment of the environmental movement
in the 1970s and 80s. More and more often, the
practices of the chemical companies are now
exposed – simply pouring their toxic waste into
the environment or dispatching it to poor
countries. In the eyes of an increasingly
ecologically aware public, the chemical industry
has become number one polluter. The word
“chemical” has become synonymous with “toxic”.
Today, products use the “chemical-free” tag to
boost sales. Within just a few decades, a dramatic
change in image has taken place. In the 1950’s,
nylon, plastic and Persil washing powder stood
for progress. By the 1970s and 80s the image of
the chemical industry was as dirty as its origins.
The Ancient Egyptian word kemi originally
referred to the black soil of Egypt, but also to
black eyeliner (kohl) [see p. 15]. In Arabic, kemi
became al-kimia, or alchemy [see p.13]. This
occult pastime had turned into a proper science
by the 18th century and, from the 19th century,
one of the most important industries in the
3 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
L In March 2010, a hundred
tonnes of dead fish filled the
Rodrigo de Freitas lagoon, in
Rio de Janeiro (Brazil). There
were several possible causes,
including discharge of sewage
carrying toxic industrial and
domestic waste. The
proliferation of algae is due to
an excess of nitrates and
phosphates, which could have
suffocated the fish.
© M.Flores – UNEP/Specialist
Stock
In the 1950s,
nylon, plastic and
Persil washing
powder stood for
progress. By the
1970s and 80s the
image of the
chemical industry
was as dirty as its
origins.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
world. This is when today’s global players were
founded: BASF, Bayer, DuPont and Roche. The
chemical industry manufactures over 70,000
different products, from plastics and fertilizers, to
detergents and drugs. Its total global annual
production is worth a breath-taking US$ 3.6
trillion, according to the American Chemistry
Council (ACC). It has dramatically changed and
improved our lives. It is impossible to think of
modern-day civilisation without it. 
But after a century-long success story, the
chemical industry, inflated by mechanised mass
production, has become the cause of a growing
number of ecological problems. It is enormously
resource- and energy-hungry; many solvents and
catalysts are toxic, disposal of its waste is
complicated and expensive, while toxic and
carcinogenic substances are released into the air
and water. According to the United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP), Western
Europe produced a total of 42 million tonnes of
toxic waste in the year 2000, five million of which
were exported in 2001. 
Green chemistry
The careless disposal of toxic waste was for a
long time tolerated or concealed by politicians –
the chemical industry was too important for the
economy. But after Bhopal and Seveso, they had
to respond – in the 1980s and 90s chemical
companies had to meet increasingly stringent
environmental requirements. In 1990 the United
States Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)
passed the Pollution Prevention Act, marking a
change of direction in policy. Manufacturing
processes and products had to be made
sustainable, pollution was to be avoided – dirty
chemistry gradually started to turn green. “After
defining the term ‘green chemistry’ in 1991 it
became clear that a design framework would be
desirable for those wishing to put the theory of
green chemistry into practice”, says Paul Anastas,
who is regarded as the “Father of Green
Chemistry”. He is the director of the Center for
Green Chemistry at Yale University and also
works for the EPA. In 1998 he published the
“Twelve Principles of Green Chemistry” along
with his colleague, Jack Warner. The first of these
principles dictates that “it is better to prevent
waste than to treat or clean up waste after it has
been created.” Also, harmless alternatives are to
be found to toxic chemicals and solvents. The
latest milestone on the path towards green
chemistry was the European Union’s 2007 REACH
Directive (Registration, Evaluation, Authorisation
and Restriction of Chemicals). Now it is no longer
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 3 7
L An ecological disaster in
Hungary in October 2010
killed nine people. The toxic
red sludge is a waste product
from the production of
aluminium.
© Waltraud Holzfeind/
Greenpeace
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
up to the authorities to demonstrate to
manufacturers that the substances they use are
potentially harmful; the shoe is on the other
foot. Thanks to REACH, some 40,000 chemicals
now have to be tested. 
Other goals of green chemistry are to lower
energy consumption, to improve the efficiency
of the production process and to switch to
renewable resources. After all, the chemical
industry also depends on petroleum,
consuming 10% of global oil production to
make 80% to 90% of its products. And the
chemical industry is energy-hungry: in 2008, for
example, the German chemical industry
consumed some 12.5% of the entire national
demand for energy. Since the 1990s the industry
has increasingly been pursuing the goal of
sustainability – while improving its image at the
same time. BASF, the world’s largest chemical
corporation with annual sales of 50 billion euros
and more than 100,000 employees around the
world, like other giants, DuPont, Dow Chemicals
and Bayer all want to become greener. “At BASF
we are running all our activities according to the
principles of sustainable development,” says
BASF CEO, Jürgen Hambrecht. And, he adds, “we
are developing products that help our
customers to save energy and resources, while
improving quality of life.” These are primarily
insulating materials that enable home-owners
to lower their heating costs and reduce carbon
emissions.
BASF publishes its carbon emissions, not
only for its own production facilities but for the
entire life cycle of its products – from the
extraction of the raw materials through to final
disposal. The company’s website reveals that
the production of BASF products led to the
overall release of some 90 million tonnes of CO2
into the atmosphere in 2010 – corresponding to
10% of Germany’s total CO2 emissions. By the
year 2020, BASF wants to lower its production-
related greenhouse gas emissions by 25 %
(compared with 2002). But since the production
process only accounts for part of the total, this
reduction target only represents 7.5 % of BASF’s
total emissions. 
Even so,  Hambrecht emphasises that BASF
products themselves also reduce carbon
emissions – a total of 287 million tonnes of CO2
per year, or three times as much as is released
during their manufacture, as the company
website proudly announces. Also, BASF
promises to implement the REACH directive by
2015, and to reduce the amount of organic
compounds, nitrogen compounds and heavy
metals released into air and water by some 70%
by 2020. On its website, BASF claims to have
already done so. And the company is on the
lookout for renewable resources, such as using
natural castor oil in the manufacture of
mattresses, and the biodegradable plastic Ecovio,
which is largely made from polylactic acid,
derived from maize. 
Green chemistry is not only booming in the
West. “Recently, there has been growing support
for and interest in green chemistry in developing
countries”, says Paul Anastas, who recently
addressed the Pan African Chemistry Network
(PACN), which he helped to establish, at the first
Green Chemistry conference. In emerging
nations, like India and China, he adds, “green
chemistry has been implemented in academia,
research institutions, and industry at a much
faster rate than anywhere else in the world.” It
seems that these countries do not intend to
make the same mistakes as the West. 
3 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
CHEMISTRY: 
a common denominator in Africa
The first African conference on green
chemistry was held in the capital of Ethiopia,
Addis Ababa, from 15 to 17 November, 2010.
It was one of a long series of continent-wide
seminars, conferences and workshops, that
bring together African and international
experts around themes as wide-ranging as
biodiversity, sustainable development,
education or water, with one common
denominator – chemistry. 
The conference was organized by the Pan-
Africa Chemistry Network (PACN), launched in
November 2007 on the initiative of the Royal
Society of Chemistry (RSC) and Syngeta, a Swiss
company specializing in chemistry and the
food industry. A year earlier, the RSC had
launched the Archive for Africa initiative, which
provides free access to specialized chemistry
journals for a large number of African
universities. 
PACN’s remit is to facilitate communication
between African chemists and thereby
encourage innovation and scientific
development across the continent. It operates
in partnership with the Federation of African
Societies of Chemistry (FASC), founded in 2006
with UNESCO support. To date there are three
centres in the network – in Kenya, Ethiopia and
South Africa. Other centres are expected to be
set up in Nigeria and Egypt. 
By awarding bursaries or contributing to
travel costs, the network facilitates the
mobility of African chemists, enabling them to
further their research abroad or to participate
in international conferences. Its specialist fields
are: food security, biodiversity and disease
prevention. – J. Š.
www.rsc.org/Membership/Networking/
InternationalActivities/PanAfrica/
Since the 1990s
the industry has
converted to
sustainability –
improving its
image at the same
time.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 3 9
Letter to a
young chemist
The 2010 Nobel prize in chemistry was awarded to
the American scientist, Richard Heck and to Ei-ichi
Negishi and Akira Suzuki from Japan, for their work
on organic synthesis, which paved the way for the
invention of one of the most sophisticated tools in
chemistry – cross coupling. One of the cornerstones
of this immense scientific endeavour is “Suzuki
coupling”, after the laureate we interviewed. In this
interview, Akira Suzuki talks about his research,
aiming above all at young people today, who are
deserting the sciences. He is encouraging them to
turn towards chemistry, with the idea of making it
into a new science.
AKIRA SUZUKI answers questions put by Noriyuki
Yoshida, journalist for Yomiuri Shimbun, Tokyo
What is cross coupling used for?
If I give you an example, you will understand
right away. After the Nobel I had so many
requests for interviews that my blood pressure
went right up! My doctor prescribed a drug to
bring down the pressure and the pharmacist
explained to me that it had been made by
“Suzuki coupling.” The procedure has also been
used to make certain antibiotics, as well as
drugs to treat cancer and AIDS. 
The process has also been used in the IT
and communications worlds to make liquid
crystals for television and computer screens,
and for organic electroluminescent displays,
which are widely used for small devices like
mobile telephones and so on.
How long did it take you to perfect this 
method?
The discovery of the coupling reaction only
took two or three years, at the end of the 1970s.
But I had worked on the chemistry of boron, a
metalloid close to carbon, since 1965, when I
returned from the USA, after finishing my
studies at Purdue University. That means it is
the result of over ten years of research.
What did other people think when you started
work in this field?
On the whole, they thought the chances of
success were zero. That is also why there were
so few researchers in this field, anywhere in the
world. But I am optimistic by nature and I
thought these disadvantages could become
advantages. I told myself that by overcoming
the difficulties, it would be possible to come up
with a stable synthesis procedure that would
be easy to use.
Some say that there is fair amount of luck in
research. What do you think?
At the outset, in research, one cannot rely on
chance. Research has, above all, to be rational.
Akira Suzuki, in Tokyo,
November 2010.
© Yomiuri-Shimbun
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
It is important to analyse the successes and
failures of experiments and to apply them in the
next phase. That is when chance can intervene.
Anyone can be lucky. But to attract luck, one has
to be attentive, to make an effort and remain
humble, above anything else. 
Were you interested in science as a child?
I was born in a small town called Mukawa, south
of Sapporo (in Hokkaido). Nowadays, the town is
called Shishamo. In primary school, I was just a
child, like all the others – I liked going fishing
with my friends and playing baseball. At that
time, the juku [private schools offering evening
classes] did not exist and I think that the children
were free and full of spirit. I was not especially
interested in science, but in junior high school, I
did like mathematics. Looking back, I think I did
like things that were clear.
Why did you choose to study chemistry at
university?
I entered Hokkaido University to study
mathematics. But during a chemistry class, I
stumbled on a manual, which had a great effect
on me. The author was a professor of organic
chemistry at Harvard. I had a dreadful time trying
to understand the English, but I found it very
interesting. And I ended up forgetting about
mathematics.
During my chemistry studies, I was very
influenced by Professor Harusada Sugino, who
taught me why chemistry was important and
what use it was. And Professor Sugino was not
just interested in chemistry. He was rector at
Hokkaido University, but was also president of
the Japanese national commission for UNESCO!
From 1963 to 1965, you studied in the USA. At
Purdue University, you also followed courses by
Herbert Charles Brown, 1979 Nobel laureate in
chemistry, who also had Ei-ichi Negishi as a
student.
When I was about thirty, I was assistant professor
at Hokkaido University, and I had to find a
research field. I went into a bookshop in Sapporo
and looked at books on chemistry. My gaze fell
on a book with a black and red cover – it looked
more like a novel – and I picked it up. It was by
Professor Brown. It was so interesting that I
stayed up whole nights reading it. I wrote a letter
to the professor, telling him that I wanted to
study with him, and that is how I left for the USA.
In the USA, I was a post-doc, but my salary
was four times higher than that of an assistant
professor in Japan. And meat and petrol were
cheap, too... I really noticed the difference
between the two countries. There were several
other foreign researchers and I was able to make
many friends. The discussions I had with them
opened up new worlds for me. When Japanese
people are together, they can understand each
other without saying anything, but I learned that
when one is immersed in another culture, one
has to say a lot to be understood. I also learned
English. I recommend young people to go
abroad, without hesitating. One learns a great
deal – and not just on a professional level or in
one’s specialized area.
4 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
L Akira Suzuki’s discoveries
have made it possible to
optimize the blue light in the
organic electroluminescent
diodes present in flat screens.
Shown here is a flat screen
made by Sharp. 
© Yomiuri Shimbun
“As I have already
said, just the wish
that you may find
in yourself enough
patience to endure
and enough
simplicity to have
faith”
– Rainer Maria Rilke,
Letters to a Young Poet
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
What did you learn from Professor Brown outside
of your research?
Professor Brown often said: “Do something that
would be worth doing a class on”. That meant do
something new, which could be published in a
lecture. And which could also be useful. That is
not easy. But I also ended up by telling my
students not to clean your lunch box with
toothpicks, as we say in Japan, meaning avoid
getting bogged down in details. I tell them, on
the contrary, to fill the lunchbox with their own
products.
Is there a method of working that guarantees
success? 
Even if it did exist, one couldn’t expect someone
else to adopt it. Everyone has their qualities and
what they can do is to make use of them. In my
case I think it was optimism. When experiments
were not working out well, I went for a drink to
relax with the students and, the next day, I could
resume my experiments with a new frame of mind.
What do you think needs to be done to attract
new generations to chemistry?
Young people are moving away from science and
it is a very serious problem. This phenomenon is
particularly apparent in Japan. The only thing to do
in a country with no natural resources, like Japan, is
to use ingenuity to create something new.
It is up to young people and them alone to
find their hopes and ideals in science. But I would
like to lend my support as an “elder”. Thanks to
the Nobel prize, the term “cross coupling” is
beginning to be known, even by children. The
dissemination and popularization of science are,
for me, a great source of motivation.
What links do you think we will have with
chemistry in the future? 
Chemistry is not very fashionable at the moment.
It is associated with bad smells, dirtiness, and can
provoke aversion. It was already like that when
we were young, but at the time, the
petrochemical industry was booming and
several students chose to study chemistry. 
Today, some people see chemistry just as a
polluting industry, but that is a mistake. Without
it, productivity would drop and we could not
enjoy the life we know today. If there is pollution,
it is because we are releasing harmful
substances. Obviously, we have to adapt
treatment and management regimes and work
to develop chemical substances and
manufacturing processes that respect the
environment.
Chemistry is indispensible for the
development of Japan, and for the world. I hope
that young people will study chemistry, with the
idea of creating a new science. There have been
many discoveries and developments so far, and
an incalculable number of substances have been
manufactured. Chemistry will always remain
important in the years to come.
Which are the areas of organic chemistry where
you think developments will be needed in the
future?
As Professor Negishi said, I think that we have to
turn towards the industrialization of
photochemistry, based on carbon dioxide, as for
example in plant photosynthesis. The energy
produced in this sector is still very low. Nature
produces complex organic compounds from
carbon dioxide, using sunlight as the energy
source. And these reactions take place in the
temperature ranges in which we live, in an
environment where water exists. I hope we will
be able to shed light on the mechanisms and
apply them.
2011 has been proclaimed International Year of
Chemistry. Do you have any particular message
for readers of the UNESCO Courier, who live in
the four corners of the world?
Chemistry plays a very important role in our lives.
Most specialisms and technologies in chemistry
are aimed at the manufacture of products to
improve the well being of humanity. There are a
considerable number of substances
manufactured in the world and no-one knows
exactly how many, but almost all are organic
compounds. This is why organic chemistry is one
of the most important branches of this science,
and deserves more people to be interested in it
and to contribute to its development. 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 4 1
L The Organic Light Emitting
Display (OLED) is one of the
many applications of “Suzuki
coupling”. 
© Yomiuri Shimbun
I recommend
young people to
go abroad,
without
hesitating. One
learns a great deal
and not just on a
professional level
or in one’s
specialized area.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Long live recycling!
My name is Ana Alejandra Apaseo Alaniz. I am 19
years old and am studying at the University of
Guanajuato in Mexico. I wanted to do a degree in
chemistry to help understand the world around
me. What I like about chemistry is that it can be
applied to anything. When I was little I used to
love boiling up plants to see what they tasted
like. I made myself sick more than once, I can tell
you! But that’s what I liked doing – research.
I am specially interested in organic chemistry
and its applications. Something I’d really like to
do in the International Year of Chemistry is to
develop a procedure for recycling products that
are made with polystyrene.  
And when I get a job, I want to start a project
on the creation of organic components used in
laboratories and the chemical industry, using
recycled materials. 
Ana Alejandra Apaseo Alaniz (Mexico)
I chose
chemistry
without
hesitating
My name is Somnath
Das. I am 21 years old
and am a second year
M.Sc student at the
Indian Institute of
Technology, in Kanpur, Uttar Pradesh.
When starting college, we had to choose
either physics, chemistry, or mathematics as the
major (honours). Without hesitation, I chose
chemistry. I was curious to learn how to control
the behaviour of molecules that we can’t even see
with the naked eye. I wanted to know about their
behaviour, their reactions. So I took chemistry, to
know more about the molecular world. 
I love everything about chemistry, except
when there is no theoretical explanation for a
reaction. For example, in most reactions using
chiral environments, one of the two enatiomers
is always dominant. As a rule we can’t explain
this selectivity, except in the few cases where a
model is available. Of the three major fields, I
prefer organic chemistry and want to do research
in this field. 
Somnath Das (India) 
4 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
Young chemists
around the globe
For the International Year of Chemistry (IYC 2011),
the UNESCO Courier was interested in young people
who decided to take up chemistry at University. We
carried out a survey of students who had joined the
IYC 2010 network. For most of them, chemistry is
more than just a career. It is a passion. 
©
 S
o
u
g
a
ta
 M
a
ity
©
 A
n
a
 A
le
ja
n
d
ra
 A
p
a
se
o
 A
la
n
iz
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The wisdom
of careful
attention
I was born in 1981 in
Shiraz, the cultural
capital of Iran. I grew up
in an adorable and
loving family. I was
already a curious student
at elementary school, so I chose experimental
science in high school, where my talent in
chemistry blossomed. I was very upset to learn
that there is no real cure for cancer, or treatment
for those affected by chemical weapons or certain
diseases. That’s what made me want to study
chemistry at university. I wanted to synthesize
new molecules. In 1999 I was accepted as a
degree student in pure chemistry at Yasuj
university. It was there that I realised that
chemistry is all around us. In 2006 I started on a
Ph.D in polymer chemistry at Shiraz University. 
Chemistry has taught me the wisdom of
careful attention, which affects all aspects of my
life. Now what I find most disturbing is the
neglect of governments and people in general
concerning the side effects of the use of
chemicals in industry, such as pollution, global
warming, illnesses, etc. All of these things should
be carefully studied by scientists. 
In 2011 I will be on sabbatical leave in
Germany, at Duisburg University, working on
membrane synthesis, which is widely employed
in the selective removal of impurities from
different media. After I finish my Ph.D I would like
to work on pollution control. 
Fatemeh Farjadian (Iran)
Chemistry is the ‘mother
of sciences’
My name is Kufre Ite, I
am 28 years old. At the
end of this year I hope to
finish my Master’s
degree at the University
of Uyo.  During my
junior high school days,
an introductory
technology course
kindled my interest in
science. I later opted for
chemistry because the principles of this science
underpin all the natural and applied sciences. It
is the “mother of sciences”. Chemistry reflects
Nature and also recreates it. I was very inspired
by a motto of the Chemical Society of Nigeria
(CSN) that asks “Is there anything around us that
is not chemistry?”  Everyone benefits from the
practical applications of chemistry every day,
from the soap we wash with to the clothes we
wear. I also appreciate the meticulousness and
precision of chemists.
For the IYC 2011 I have chosen to focus on
“chemists in modern society”. I would like to help
raise awareness of local and medium-sized
manufacturers on safety in the work place, and
the safe handling, storage and transportation of
chemicals and reagents. This should increase
public appreciation and understanding of
chemistry and its role in the public and private
sectors of our economy. 
Kufre Ite (Nigeria)
Don’t forget the 
test-tubes
I'm 21 years old and am
a student of applied
chemical engineering at
the Faculty of Chemical
Engineering and
Technology, University
of Zagreb, Croatia. For
me the study of
chemistry is an obvious
continuation of my love
affair with nature, which
has continued since I was a child. I appreciate the
multidisciplinary character of my studies, but
also dislike the heavy reliance on computers, as it
distances us from the traditional, experimental
approach. However, I'm aware that it also has
many advantages. After I graduate I would like to
study for a PhD in Croatia or abroad and learn
more about polymers. I would like to celebrate
the IYC popularising chemistry through
interesting yet simple experiments that explain
phenomena occurring around us. 
Marko Viskic (Croatia)
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 4 3
“Anyone can be
lucky. But to
attract luck, one
has to be
attentive, to make
an effort and
remain humble,
above anything
else...
It is up to young
people and them
alone to find their
hopes and ideals
in science."
– Akira Suzuki, 
©
 C
o
u
rte
sy o
f R
e
se
a
rch
 Lin
k N
ig
e
ria
©
 M
o
rte
n
 A
a
lb
a
e
k C
h
riste
n
se
n
©
 Fa
te
m
e
h
 Fa
rja
d
ia
n
©
 D
R
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Currently there are 27 full-time
academic staff and eight technicians in
the chemistry department. In the
present academic year (2010-2011),
there are 1121 undergraduates studying
chemistry, 81 postgraduates registered
for an MSc and 45 PhD candidates.
Department staff are engaged in
research areas such as the analysis of
trace and heavy metals (see page 21),
biosensors, the chemistry of natural
products, green chemistry,
electrochemistry, computational
chemistry and several other fields of this
complex science.
The department buildings cover an
area of some 2800 m2, with 25
laboratories and 13 associated areas.
Chemical and hardware stores occupy a
further 700 m2. High-grade instruments
for research and teaching include a 400
MHz NMR spectrometer, a high
performance liquid phase chromato -
graph, a Fourier Transform Infrared
spectrometer, an ultraviolet/ visible
light spectrophotometer and Gas
chromatography-mass spectrometry
(GC-MS) facilities. 
While the overall image of our
department is positive, there are still a
number of constraints affecting the
teaching and research activities,
including inadequate safety provisions,
too many students, inadequate
laboratories for undergraduate
instruction, poor administrative support
for research, the prohibitively high cost
of chemicals and scientific equipment.
Most research is carried out with the
very limited funds the department
receives from the university. Some
research projects do receive funding
from foreign organizations, such as the
Swedish International Development
Cooperation Agency (SIDA/SAREC),
International Programme in the
Chemical Sciences (IPICS), the British
Council Development Partnerships in
Higher Education (DelPHE) programme
and the International Foundation for
Science (IFS).
Another constraint is the lack of a
data analysis centre. We are very often
obliged to send samples abroad for
analysis, with obvious delays for
students, whose research has to be
completed in a limited time frame. 
Shimalis Admassie is Head of the
Department of Chemistry at the
University of Addis-Ababa, Ethiopia.
4 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
Studying
chemistry
in
Ethiopia
Since 1950 the Ethiopian university system has been trying to fill the country’s need for
high-level chemists. In just 17 years, a simple unit of the University College of Addis-Ababa
has become a full-fledged department of the Haile Selassie I University, offering a
Bachelor of science (BSc) degree in chemistry. In 1978 the department launched a Master
of science (MSc) programme in chemistry with four specialization options: analytical,
inorganic, organic and physical. A PhD programme was launched in 1985.   
© DRShimalis Admassie
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Science without borders
The UNESCO Science Report 2010, published by UNESCO last November, takes
a look at the latest trends in scientific research and cooperation across the
world. In particular it highlights an increasing number of partnerships, forging
alliances in science, but also in terms of international diplomacy.  – p. 46
UNESCO and CERN: 
like hooked atoms
The idea of creating a European Council for Nuclear Research (CERN) first arose
at the fifth session of the UNESCO General Conference, in 1950. For 60 years,
these two organizations have striven to facilitate access to scientific knowledge
and to promote scientific cooperation. We meet Rolf-Dieter Heuer, Director
General of CERN. – p. 48
Arts as a bridge between cultures 
Cultures have always mixed and interacted, creating new hybrid cultures. 
Yet they also have a tendency to reject neighbouring cultures. Looking at the
examples of North American and Arab/Muslim cultures, Stephen Humphreys
highlights the role of literature and the arts as special means for
rapprochement. – p. 51
Touki Bouki’s new life
Promoting African cinema, supporting its directors, safeguarding the film
heritage of his continent – these are the goals of the Malian director, Souleymane
Cissé, a fierce defender of African national languages. In 1997 he founded the
West African Union of Film-makers and Producers (UCECAO). – p. 53
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1  . 4 5
P
o
stscrip
t
K The Symbolic Globe by
Erik Reitzel (Denmark),
outside UNESCO
headquarters, Paris.
© UNESCO/Michel
Ravassard
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
4 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
From 2012 onwards, ground stations in
South Africa, Canary Islands (Spain),
Egypt and Gabon will be able to
access data from an Earth
observation satellite being
developed by China and Brazil. This
will be the third CBERS satellite
designed and launched by the Sino-
Brazilian partnership since 1999. Up
until now, these satellite images of
the changing landscape have been
delivered only to users in China and
Latin America: more than 1.5 million
of them since 2004. Now, thanks to
the CBERS Africa
initiative, the list of beneficiaries has
been extended to Africa. Since a
satellite does not stop at borders in its
orbit of the Earth, it makes sense to
share the collected data with those
countries in the satellite’s path and
thereby forge new partnerships. The
space race of the last century has
been replaced by a new paradigm,
space diplomacy.
This example cited in the newly
released UNESCO Science Report
2010 illustrates a growing trend: the
use of space technologies for
environmental monitoring within
Science 
without borders
If there is one field where globalization seems to be doing
good, it is research. Everywhere, partnerships are being
developed, forging scientific, and even diplomatic alliances
between countries that may sometimes be poles apart
geographically or in terms of resources. By working
together, partners can capitalize on one another’s
strengths and save time and money. Here are a few
examples from the UNESCO Science Report 2010. 
Susan Schneegans, Editor, UNESCO Science Report 2010 
“Increasingly, international
diplomacy will take the form of
science diplomacy in the years
to come.”
Irina Bokova
Postscript
K 5 June 1999. The Student Tracked Atmospheric
Research Satellite for Heuristic International
Networking Experiment (STARSHINE) leaves the cargo
bay of the Space Shuttle Discovery near the completion
of the almost 10 day STS-96 mission. The satellite is
covered by hundreds of tiny mirrors that reflect
sunlight to observers on the ground, to help students
study the effects of solar activity on the Earth's
atmosphere.
© NASA/courtesy nasaimages.org 
L Image taken by the CBERS-2 satellite , on 10 April
2005, showing Florianópolis, the capital of the State of
Santa Catarina in southern Brazil.  
The full version of this
article is published in
Planet Science
January-March 2011
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
L E  C O U R R I E R  D E  L’ U N E S C O  . J A N V I E R  M A R S  2 0 1 1 . 4 7T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H   
international collaboration. This trend is
one consequence of the growing
concern at the rapid degradation of the
environment and climate change. With
recognition of the interconnected
nature of the land, water and
atmosphere has come the realization
that data-sharing among countries and
continents will be crucial to improving
our understanding and monitoring of
the Earth’s environment. One
motivation for space diplomacy is thus
commonality of purpose. 
Space diplomacy is itself a subset of a
wider phenomenon today: science
diplomacy. Science diplomacy can span a
wide range of areas, including health,
information and communication
technologies and clean energy sources. In
June 2009, for instance, Sudan
inaugurated its first biofuel plant, built in
co-operation with the Brazilian company
Dedini. A second project in Sudan
involving Egypt at a cost of US$ 150
million ‘is producing second-generation
biofuels from non-edible crops, including
agricultural waste such as rice straw, crop
stalks and leaves’, according to the Report.
Under an agreement signed by the
two countries in 2003, Pakistan and the
USA now ‘contribute to a common fund
which is jointly managed by the National
Academy of Sciences in the USA and by
the Higher Education Commission and
Ministry of Science and Technology in
Pakistan,’ writes Tanveer Nair, who, as
Chair of the Pakistan Council for Science
and Technology, played a pivotal role in
securing this landmark agreement. ‘Each
year, proposals for research collaboration
are invited with at least one US and one
Pakistani scientist as principal
investigators,’ she explains. ‘The proposals
undergo peer review in both countries
and are selected on merit. This
programme has resulted not only in
capacity-building of Pakistan’s
laboratories’, she says, ‘but also in the joint
discovery of a vaccine to prevent a deadly
disease caused by tick bites which afflicts
those working with animal herds in the
southern region of Sindh in Pakistan.’
Cost-sharing 
Around the world, countries are
developing partnerships in science,
technology and innovation within a
wider policy to forge political alliances
and enhance their presence on the world
stage. But international collaboration is
of course also motivated by the more
pragmatic desire to pool resources in the
face of the escalating costs of scientific
infrastructure. The bill for one
international project to develop a clean
energy source by mastering nuclear
fusion has been estimated at no less than
10 billion euros. This is ‘the most
ambitious collaborative project in
science ever conceived’, writes Peter
Tindemans, a consultant who used to be
responsible for co-ordinating research
and science policy in the Netherlands.
The project is building an International
Thermonuclear Experimental Reactor
(ITER) in Cadarache, France, by 2018. 
That the project should involve not
only the traditionally dominant scientific
powers of the European Union, Japan,
the Russian Federation and the USA but
also China, India and the Republic of
Korea is a reflection of the growing
economic and technological might of
these countries. China, for instance, ‘will
assume 9.09% of the cost of
construction and spend over US$1
billion in total,’ writes Mu Rongping,
Director of the Chinese Academy of
Science’s Center for Innovation and
development, in the report. ‘Some 1000
Chinese scientists will participate in the
ITER project [and] China will be in charge
of developing, installing and testing 12
components,’ he explains. 
Winning new markets
The business sector has also been quick
to weigh up the advantages of
international scientific collaboration. In
addition to cost-sharing, international
consortia offer a tempting opportunity
to conquer new markets. The hugely
successful Airbus consortium is the
result of the merger of the formerly
independent aircraft manufacturing
companies of four European countries –
France, Germany, Spain and the United
Kingdom – and is a shining example of
what pan-European co-operation can
achieve.
Two decades after the fall of the Iron
Curtain, the Russian Federation is
witnessing a growing volume of
commercial contracts and joint ventures
in science and technology involving both
Russian and foreign companies. In 2010,
the joint-stock enterprise comprised of
the French company Alcatel-Lucent RT
and state corporation Russian
Technologies began investing in the
development, manufacturing and
marketing of telecommunications
equipment for the Russian market and
those of the countries of the
Commonwealth of Independent States.
Meanwhile, the jointly owned US–
Russian company IsomedAlpha has
begun producing high-tech medical
equipment like computer tomographs. 
International co-authorship
In addition to such factors as evolving
geopolitics and financial considerations,
the growth of international scientific
collaboration in recent years owes much
to the rapid spread of ICTs: Internet
access doubled between 2002 and 2008
from 11% to 24% of the global
population and even tripled in the
developing world from 5% to 17% of
the population. 
The past few years have not only
witnessed a surge in international co-
authorship but also a diversification of
research partners.  One of Australia’s top
three partners for scientific co-
authorship between 1998 and 2008 was
China, along with traditional partners the
United Kingdom and USA. In the
Philippines, top billing went to the USA
and Japan, followed by China. China was
even the number one partner for
Malaysia, ahead of the United Kingdom
and India. There are signs that the
growing role of China and India in
scientific authorship as a consequence of
their growing global influence is already
reshaping the scientific landscape in
Southeast Asia.
The closest neighbours do not
always make for the closest partners.
India, Iran and Pakistan all publish 20–
30% of research articles with scientists
abroad but most of their co-authors live
in Western countries. Just 3% of research
articles are published in collaboration
with scientists working in South Asia. In
Brazil, where international scientific
collaboration has remained steady for
the past five years at about 30% of the
total, ‘US scientists are the main partners’
write Carlos Henrique de Brito Cruz and
Hernan Chaimovich, respectively
Scientific Director of the São Paulo
Research Foundation and CEO of the
Butantan Foundation in Brazil. They cite a
2009 study which ‘found that 11% of
scientific articles written by Brazilians
between 2003 and 2007 had at least one
co-author in the USA and 3.5% a co-
author from the UK. Argentina, Mexico
and Chile combined represented just
3.2% of co-authors of Brazilian articles.’  
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
4 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
Today, beneath the buildings of the
European Organization for Nuclear
Research, which has kept its historic
acronym, is the world’s largest particle
accelerator. Some 27 kilometres in
circumference, the Large Hadron
Collider (LHC) is a gigantic instrument,
equipped with 9300 magnets.
On 30 March 2010, news coming out
of CERN set the world talking – LHC had
succeeded in colliding beams at close to
the speed of light. “With this
experiment”, says Rolf-Dieter Heuer,
CERN’s Director-General, “we got to
within a fraction of a second of the Big
Bang. “It’s a new step forward, opening
areas of research into the Creation of
the universe that we could never have
imagined before.”
The historical discovery of 30 March
was made possible through the “Atlas
Collaboration” which brings together
around 3000 physicists (including 1000
students) from 40 countries, and
belonging to over 170 universities and
laboratories. This an entire “virtual
nation”, to use an expression often
Few people today remember that the
idea of creating a European Council for
Nuclear Research (CERN) was mooted in
1950, in Florence (Italy), at the fifth
session of the UNESCO General
Conference.  At that time, the world was
still licking its wounds after the still
recent Second World War. European
intellectuals, men and women of the
arts and scientists had all understood
one thing – that cooperation was
essential for the construction of peace.
What was needed was a common
project around which European
researchers could join together, coming
from both Allied countries and the Axis
powers.
The Florence project was to enter
into force three years later, with the
signature of the final Convention on the
creation of CERN (the ‘Council’ having
metamorphosed into ‘Centre’). The
Convention was ratified by 12 countries1
in 1954 and the first stone of the
building was laid, just outside Geneva
(Switzerland), in 1955.
Postscript
Fostering scientific cooperation, making science education
more attractive, facilitating access to scientific knowledge
for a fairer world – these are common objectives being
pursued by UNESCO and the European Organization for
Nuclear Research, better-known by its historic acronym,
CERN. The two organizations have been closely linked for
60 years. 
Jasmina Šopova meets ROLFDIETER HEUER, Director-General of CERN
UNESCO and CERN : 
like hooked atoms
1. Belgium, Denmark, France, Germany, Greece,
Italy, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland,
United Kingdom, Yugoslavia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1  . 4 9
heard at CERN. “Motivation – and this
alone – can explain the success of this
gigantic undertaking. Although we
come from different regions of the
world, we’re all moving in the same
direction  – towards knowledge,” says
the Director-General. If, one day, we
discover the famous Higgs boson – a
hypothetical particle dubbed The Grail
by physicists, because they’ve all been
searching for it for half a century – it will
be thanks to the Atlas. “We know
everything about this particle,  except
whether it exists,” he says, smiling.
CERN is not alone in pursuing this
quest, though. There is also Fermilab,
just outside of Chicago (USA). “Today,
CERN has the most powerful accelerator
in the world, but until recently it was
Fermilab, and they have amassed a
huge quantity of data over 25 years,
whereas we have just begun. LHC was
only launched in September 2008. But,
having said this,” confides Rolf-Dieter
Heuer, “I think that, with it, we have a
good chance of beating them to the
discovery of the Higgs boson.” Do the
two organizations collaborate? “I call it
competitive collaboration or
collaborative competition. Fermilab
helped us a lot when the LHC went
down, [shortly after it opened].” And do
they exchange data? “Not for the
moment. Come back in a few years and
ask me that question again.” 
“There is no progress without
competition,” says Rolf-Dieter Heuer.
“Nor without cooperation.” This was at
the origin of the birth of CERN and
remains its driving force, but it is also
one of the permanent ideals of UNESCO.
And one of the Organization’s recent
projects is to support the Synchrotron-
light for Experimental Science and
Applications in the Middle East
(SESAME) centre in Allan (Jordan). In
terms of international scientific
cooperation, SESAME is the Middle
East’s equivalent of CERN. It brings
together Bahrain, Cyprus, Egypt, Iran,
Israel, Jordan, Pakistan, the Palestinian
Authority and Turkey. “We don’t have
the same fields of expertise,” explains
CERN’s Director-General, “but the idea of
using science for peace underlies both
projects. And CERN has not shied away
from helping create SESAME, especially
in terms of expertise.” 
In the framework of common
initiatives (SESAME, virtual libraries in
African universities, training teaching
staff, etc.), CERN puts its expertise at the
disposal of UNESCO, while UNESCO’s
International Basic Sciences Programme
(IBSP) offers the European Organization
a framework for cooperation with
researchers from countries that are not
its members. Indeed, CERN has 20
Member States, but its projects include
10,000 associate experts from 85
different nationalities. 
CERN also counts on UNESCO to
help it promote the idea of a new
approach to teaching physics and
mathematics on an international scale.
“We can no longer continue to teach
physics starting with theories
developed in the 18th century!” protests
Rolf-Dieter Heuer. “Current research on
the universe, for example, is very
appealing to young people. Schools
should start by stimulating their
curiosity and then gradually move on to
the basics. CERN cannot develop a
method that would suit all countries,
but it can raise awareness and train
teaching staff from all over the world.
And UNESCO can convince political
leaders that we absolutely have to make
science subjects more attractive to
pupils in secondary school, so that they
are not turned off.” The struggle could
be a long one. “I know, the battle is not
going to be a walk-over. But if we don’t
start with a battle, we have already lost!”
Basic science is another area where
the objectives of the two organizations
coincide. Decision-makers often
perceive basic science as too abstract,
because there may be no immediate
applications for its results. But for Rolf-
Dieter Heuer, this is nonsense.
“I define basic science as open
research with a focus on results, but not
Rolf-Dieter Heuer, a German physicist,
took over as Director-General of CERN
on 1 January 2009. He took up his post
just as the Large Hadron Collier (LHC)
started operating.
J The Universe of Particles exhibition aims to help
visitors to CERN understand the major issues in
contemporary physics. © UNESCO/J. Šopova
L Three years after the idea for CERN was first
conceived, the Convention for its creation is signed on
19 July 1953, at UNESCO. 
© UNESCO
with a focus on application. Imagine if
you had asked Wilhelm Röntgen to
invent a machine to photograph your
skeleton! He would never have come up
with radiation. And yet, without any
preconceived ideas, he discovered, in
1895, the X-rays that still underlie
modern radiography.” There is no lack of
examples to illustrate Heuer’s
conclusion – “We never know when or
how a result of basic science will be
applied. But it always is, in the end,
either directly or indirectly.” 
There is no progress without
competition – nor without
cooperation.
We never know when or how a
result of basic science will be
applied. But it always is, in the
end, either directly or indirectly.
©
 C
ERN
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
5 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
Essential UNESCO science publications 
involved in making realistic climate
predictions. They examine the Kyoto protocol
from different points of view, shedding new
light on the challenges at stake and the need
to foster international cooperation. Finally,
they outline the work ahead needed to both
develop effective climate prediction models
and to come up with countermeasures to
cope with the dangers facing our Earth and
society.
176 pages, figures, appendix, glossary, 
23.7 x 15 cm . €14.80 . 2005
EXPLAINING THE EARTH
Philippe Bouysse
The Discovering the World series proposes in a
few pages all you need to know about a
subject. Aimed at a young readership,
parents and teachers, the books are concrete
and richly illustrated. 
Explaining the Earth outlines the basic
geophysical aspects of the Earth and traces
its dynamic and ever-changing surface
properties and topographic evolution. A
better understanding of how our planet
functions is the key to learning how to better
respect the fragile and complex ecological
equilibriums that reign over the globe and
thereby guarantee the survival of future
generations.
48 pages, illust., photographs, glossary, 21.7 x
15.5 cm . €8.00 . 2007
WORLD HERITAGE N° 56
Heritage and Biodiversity: synergies and
solutions
 Synergies between World Heritage sites
and Key Biodiversity Areas
 Marine World Heritage: the time is now
 Climate change and a natural solution
 Cultural diversity, biodiversity and World
Heritage sites 
 Western Ghats: biodiversity, endemism
and conservation
 Kew Gardens and the conservation of
biodiversity
 Funding for biodiversity: implications for
World Heritage sites
88 pages,  photographs, 28 x 22 cm . €7.50 .
2010
ENGINEERING: Issues, Challenges and
Opportunities for Development
UNESCO Report
Engineering is as international as science.
The Report reviews the role of engineering in
development, and covers poverty reduction,
sustainable development, climate change
mitigation and adaptation. It presents the
various fields of engineering around the
world. It also discusses engineering issues,
applications and innovation, infrastructure,
capacity building, engineering education.
A platform for the better understanding of
engineering, and of the roles and
responsibilities of engineers.
396 pages, photographs, tables, figures, index,
28 x 21.5 cm . €26.00 . 2010
UNESCO SCIENCE REPORT 2010
The Current State of Science around the
World
‘What effect is the current global economic
recession having on national science systems?’
‘How fast are the national innovation systems
developing in the BRIC countries (Brazil, Russian
Federation, India, China)? Which new players
are emerging in an increasingly multipolar
world?’ and ‘which countries are experiencing
difficulties in maintaining their current status in
an increasingly competitive global
environment?’  ‘What new R&D priorities are
emerging in a world confronted with climate
change and growing food, water and energy
insecurity?’  The report answers all these
questions and more. It is divided into national
and regional chapters, each written by experts
who hail from the same country or region they
are covering. 
536 pp., fig., boxes, tables, photos, 29.7 × 21 cm .
€29.00 . 2010
CLIMATE CHANGE AND ARCTIC
SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT
Scientific, social, cultural and educational
challenges
The dramatic environmental and social
transformations due to climate change that
Arctic is undergoing have ramifications for
the entire planet. Today, the central
preoccupation of scientists is the exploration
of strategies for responding and adapting to
climate change. A truly interdisciplinary
approach is required. This book brings
together the knowledge and visions of
leading Arctic scientists in the natural and
social sciences, prominent community
leaders from across the circumpolar North,
and international experts in education,
health and ethics. 
376 pages, colour photographs, figures, tables,
references, annex, 24 x 18 cm . €22.00 . 2010
WATER AND PEACE FOR THE PEOPLE
Possible solutions to water disputes in the
Middle East
Jon Martin Trondalen
A clarification of the complexity of the water
conflicts in the Middle East, practical and
objective solutions. Unless the countries
involved co-operate, the consequences will
be devastating. The lack of plentiful and
clean water for the people will not only result
in severe human suffering, but could also
have grave geopolitical consequences. 
The book covers four critical areas:  the
Euphrates and Tigris Rivers,  the politically
sensitive Golan Heights, the Hasbani water
dispute between Lebanon and Israel,  the
longstanding water resource dispute
between the Israelis and Palestinians. 
246 pages, maps, tables, figures, photographs,
annexes, index, 24 x 19 cm . €38.00 . 2008
CLIMATE CHANGE
Guy Jacques and Hervé Le Treut
The basic scientific background and
information essential for understanding the
complex processes that bring about climate
change. The authors explain the difficulties
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Postscript
Any discussion of cultures in intimate
contact with one another—whether this
contact manifests itself as tension, as overt
conflict, or as a search for rapprochement—
ought to begin with some effort to define
culture.  In this presentation, I follow a
perspective developed by the American
anthropologist Clifford Geertz nearly forty
years ago.  Culture, he argued, does not lie
in patterns of behaviour and social
structures in themselves, but rather in the
ways we create and express meaning within
these patterns and structures.  A culture is
thus the body of ideas, beliefs, gestures,
rituals, and practices by which a society
comes to see itself as a coherent,
meaningful whole—in effect, as a people
apart, with a distinctive identity of its own.
Cultures are not hard-shelled; only
rarely can they shield themselves from the
pressure and influence of others.  Rather,
cultures are permeable, capable of
engaging in processes of interpenetration
and hybridization.  Cultures can exist side-
Art as a bridge
between cultures
Stephen Humphreys 
Since cultures have existed, they have mixed, interacted
and given birth to new, hybrid cultures. Yet, at the same
time, they have a tendency to split themselves off, and to
reject neighbouring cultures. Taking as examples North
American and Arab/Muslim cultures, Stephen Humphreys
highlights the role of literature and the arts as special
means for rapprochement.
by-side or be interwoven with one another
in a state of equilibrium.  Each interacts with
neighbouring cultures in a limited,
pragmatic way but has no trouble retaining
its sense of itself and maintaining its core
identity.
Conflict arises when two cultural
systems come to seem threatening to each
other.  This sense of threat often arises out
of the violent intrusion of one cultural
system into the space occupied by
another—“imperialism” on a small or large
scale, which is a constant and pervasive
feature of human history.  However, fear of
the other is most powerful and insidious
when it emerges out of a situation of rapid,
pervasive, uncontrollable hybridization.
Such hybridization creates an acute sense
of loss of control.  All the old rules of
behavior, symbols, beliefs, and rituals
dissolve and begin to seem foreign.  One
feels that he is becoming a stranger in his
own home.  This anxiety of hybridization is
what we confront everywhere in the world
today.  Almost every culture is infected by
it.  The question we face is whether it is
possible to heal or ameliorate this anxiety.
If so, how, and to what extent.
K Meeting at the heart of painting: diptych by Helga
Shuhr (Germany) and Youssef Fatis (Libya). 
© Helga Shuhr & Youssef Fatis 
Photo : UNESCO/R. Fayad 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1  . 5 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
5 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
Beyond stereotypes
In trying to answer this question, I will
focus on the U.S. response to Arab and
Muslim societies.  No one will be
surprised to hear that this response is
confused. In general Americans do want
to understand and even accept cultural
difference, but have a deeply rooted
belief in the superiority of “the American
way”. The American response focuses on
fears—specifically, of “Islamic
terrorism”—rather than on a
comprehensive and nuanced
engagement with the diverse and
complex cultures of Arab and Muslim
societies. A comprehensive engagement
of the kind required can be found in the
United States, but only in boutique
environments—in colleges and
universities, rather than the grand public
square defined by the mass media and
the internet. 
Inevitably, stereotypes about Arabs
and Muslims reign supreme.  The
problem is how to get a broad spectrum
of Americans to question stereotypes, to
confront their fears, and to engage with
Arab and Muslim cultures in a serious
way.
At this point we need to be honest
with ourselves.  Even if we succeed in
this task, there will surely remain cultural
differences that are too stark to be
absorbed, that challenge and offend
deeply held American values and ways
of life.  A single example will suffice.  To
the American eye, the burqu` and niqab
symbolize—indeed they epitomize—
the degradation and depersonalization
of women.  Almost no amount of
discussion and explanation will get rid
of this almost instinctive response.
Another caution.  One can come to
understand cultural differences and still
reject them as valid or acceptable
alternatives.  Does such a rejection
inevitably lead to conflict?  I have no
immediate answer to this question, but
it must be confronted thoughtfully and
honestly.
The mirror of suspicion
Cultural engagement requires
selectivity.  One cannot know everything
about everything.  But then what
aspects of Arab and Muslim cultures
should we focus on?  What groups will
we choose to represent these cultures to
us?  To this point Americans have tended
to fix their attention on two groups, to
the near exclusion of all others: militant
religious radicals and women.  The fear
and anxiety they engender are bound to
distort discussion and analysis.  
In regard to the first group, let us say
simply that among Americans, Islam is
viewed through the prism of September
11 and Arabs through the prism of the
the Israel/Palestine conflict.  The
converse is also true, I think: for Arabs
both in the Middle East and the
diaspora, the United States is also
viewed through the prism of
Israel/Palestine.  We are the mirror image
of each other’s suspicion, fear, and
resentment.  It is a perfect recipe for
mutual tension, distrust, and even
cultural repugnance.  
As regards women’s rights activists,
some are informed and culturally
sensitive, some are not.  In either case,
however, interventions in this arena
strike at the most intimate and bitterly
contested dimensions of Arab and
Muslim societies.  In this case, concern
and engagement may sometimes
increase rather than diffuse cultural
tension.
Culture as a go-between
Literature and the visual and performing
arts are a compelling means to get to
understand Arab and Muslim cultures.
An article in the New Yorker by Claudia
Roth Pierpont makes a telling statement:
“Arabic novels offer a marvelous array of
answers to questions we did not know
we wanted to ask.”   Precisely. The only
problem is that so little of the Arabic
literature published over the last twenty
years is available in English.
While novelists construct their own
worlds, which are not a simple mirror of
their cultures and do not speak for their
societies, but only for themselves, their
work is a direct, authentic product of the
societies and cultures within which they
live.  Much the same could be said of
musicians, painters, and sculptors.
In spite of all limitations and
reservations, literature and the arts are
the best way for outsiders to get inside
another culture. They give us the
broadest and most varied perspectives
on the self-understandings of Arab
cultures and on the myriad ways they
try to define themselves.  On the other
hand, in order to serve as a bridge
between cultures, these arts require
translators, performers, and
interpreters. Such cultural brokers are
often regarded with some
condescension, as simple conduits by
which the original creative efforts of
others can be transmitted to new
audiences.  Plainly that view does not
do justice to the depth of knowledge
and understanding required to make
the products of one cultural system
intelligible, meaningful, and even
usable to the members of another, very
different culture.  A translator’s work,
like a performing musician’s, is perhaps
not creative, but it is re-creative.  It is an
essential element in the process of
cultural rapprochement. 
In closing, I will argue that
Americans will only be able to come to
terms with the complex realities of Arab
cultures when the United States
develops a much larger body of
translators and interpreters than it now
has, and—even more critically—when
these brokers become integral
members, rather than  marginal players
in the country’s intellectual and cultural
life.  This will not happen anytime soon,
and in any case it will not resolve all the
tensions and hostilities between such
very disparate cultures.  But it would at
least allow Americans to move toward
seeing Arabs and Muslims as they really
are, in all their complexity.  In return, of
course, one hopes that Arab
intellectuals and scholars will make a
similar effort to make sense of American
life and thought—no easy task, I admit,
but one that must be undertaken if we
are ever to move beyond the mutual
confusion and suspicion in which both
cultures are so deeply entangled. 
R. Stephen Humphreys is Professor of
History and Islamic Studies at the
University of California, Santa Barbara
(USA). This article is taken from his
paper, Reflections on the Problem of
“Rapprochement des Cultures” presented
at UNESCO on 9 February 2010, as part
of the Forum held on the occasion of
the award of the seventh
UNESCO/Emirate of Sharjah Prize in
Arab Culture.
Postscript
A translator’s work, like a
performing musician’s, is
perhaps not creative, but it is 
re-creative.  It is an essential
element in the process of cultural
rapprochement.
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
Do you see cinema as a space for
dialogue between cultures?
Yes, cinema has made the world a
smaller place. It’s part of the idea of the
global village – I might even say ‘global
emotion’. Whatever the director’s
nationality, and no matter where a film
was made, it is a means of sharing a
vision. And the viewer has the feeling of
being transported to a universe where
the sounds and accents are unfamiliar. I
feel that one of the virtues of cinema is
to bring people together. 
You talk about the global village. But
at the same time there is a growing
trend for societies to turn in on
themselves, and for misunderstanding
to increase.
This kind of ambivalence is there, there’s
no doubt about it. In the past 30 years I
have seen the major distributors
gradually turn away from African films.
The distributors seem to be afraid of
difference. In 1987, my film Yeelen was
shown in all the mainstream cinemas
in France and Navarre and won over
audiences from every social class! I
don’t think that would be possible
today. But I don’t think the audiences
have changed. It’s the decision-makers
who won’t take risks any more. Neither
the risk of showing differences, nor
the risk of discovery. And even less so,
financial risks. And paradoxically, in
the South, we only go to see Western
films. 
Can this imbalance be put right?
There has to be real political
determination to overcome this
tendency to turn inwards. Poor ticket
sales have an impact on both the
quality and the quantity of our work.
And, as African film-makers, we have
to draw the right conclusions, such as
turning towards our own natural
audiences, in our own countries. But
no matter how many people go to see
our films, the public can’t pay enough
to finance them. This is why, in Mali,
film-making is poorer today than 20 or
30 years ago. 
Why do you always film in Bambara,
Mali’s national language? 
I have often been criticized for not
filming in French, the only official
language in Mali. I have chosen to film
in Bambara, because it’s the main
language spoken by 80% of Malians. It
is understood by over 20 million
people in West Africa. It is the language
used for business. This carries a lot of
weight and is not a mere detail. 
At the same time, having directed
dozens of actors, I can assure you that
you don’t get the same results when
the dialogue is in French as when it is
in Bambara, which is the language of
intimacy for us… We have often been
told that no-one will understand our
films outside of Africa, and that puts
us at a disadvantage, but I think that’s
not true. Language is there to serve
the story of the film. How could I have
made Yeelen is in French, when it is
about the esoteric knowledge passed
down from one generation to another! 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1 . 5 3
Postscript
Touki Bouki’s
new life
Filming in their own languages, helping African film-
makers, promoting their work, supporting contemporary
film and television, safeguarding Africa’s cinema heritage
— these are some of the objectives that the Malian director,
Souleymane Cissé, has set for himself. Here is a man of
spirit, with ambitions for his continent. 
Interview with  SOULEYMANE CISSÉ by Gabrielle Lorne, journalist from Martinique
J Souleymane Cissé at UNESCO, at the launch of the
International Year for the Rapprochement of Cultures,
on 18 February 2010. © UNESCO/A.Wheeler
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
5 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1
You go even further and say that
African States should renounce
colonial languages in favour of
national languages, which are not
officially recognized.
National languages bring citizens
together, they are indispensable for
nation building. In Mali, we have 13
national languages, but just one
official language – French. I’ve said it
before and I’ll say it again – national
language won’t kill off English, French
or Spanish. But I do believe that if
Mali does not look after its own
languages, the civilization that they
have been carrying for thousands of
years will finally disappear. 
And if I may make one political
observation, since the State has
chosen to become independent, it
has to go the whole way, and not be
afraid of upsetting the
Administration. There is still time to
take up the task again of codifying a
written form of each of our languages
and to respect the ideograms left to
us by our ancestors.
You are also very committed to
promoting African cinema. 
Yes, since Waati, my film about
Apartheid in South Africa, came out
in 1995, I realised that financial
support for African films started to
disappear, especially in Europe.
African States do not have the money
to invest in our films, but they can at
least help film-makers and the film
industry by creating an appropriate
legal framework. 
It was time that we, as
professional film-makers, took a stand
together to protect our work. So, in
1997, I set up the West African Union
of Film-makers and Producers
(UCECAO). Our aim is to promote
African cinema and to encourage
those in Africa who have the means –
the private sector, for example – to
support it. 
You also set up film festivals? 
In 1998, UCECAO launched the
Bamako Film Festival (RCB). Then we
started the Nyamina International
Festival (FINA), in the countryside,
because culture cannot just be
reserved for those living in towns.
FINA is not just for young directors,
but also for video makers and even
photographers.
You are now involved with Africa’s
film heritage. 
That is true. In 2007, in Cannes, I had
the pleasure of participating in the
launch of Martin Scorsese’s World
Cinema Foundation (WCF). A few
months later, UCECAO invited Scorsese
to Mali and he decided to invest in
preserving our film heritage. At the
following Cannes Festival, I was able to
show the restored version of Touki
Bouki, by Djibril Diop Manbety, from
1973. It had been 20 years since
anyone had seen the film, as it had
become very damaged by time and
poor storage conditions. 
Touki Bouki was the first film from
sub-Saharan Africa to have been
granted a new life. I was delighted with
this choice, because, for me, it is a
prophetic film, about emigration, since
it tells the story of a young couple
fascinated by the West.  
Souleymane Cissé is the first African
film-maker to have received an award
at Cannes (in 1987) for his feature film,
Yeelen. He is one of the great names
of world cinema. Now, at 70, with
some 30 films to his name, he is a
member of the High-level Panel on
peace and dialogue among cultures
set up by UNESCO in 2010. The Panel’s
first meeting, on 18 February 2010,
marked the launch of the
International Year of the
Rapprochement of Cultures, which
comes to an end in March 2011.
Postscript
L Poster for the film, Touki Bouki by Djibril Diop
Mambéty in 1973. The film was recently restored by
WCF.
© WWW.trigon-film.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
The “Parachicos in the traditional
January feast of Chiapa de Corzo”
(Mexico) were inscribed in 2010 on the
Representative List of the Intangible
Cultural Heritage of Humanity. 
The word Parachicos refers to both
the dances and the dancers in this
traditional Great Feast, which takes
place every year from 4 to 23 January.
This celebration of music, dance,
handicrafts, gastronomy, religious
ceremonies and feasting embraces all
spheres of local life, promoting mutual
respect among communities, groups
and individuals.
The dancers move throughout the
city, each wearing a carved wooden mask
with head-dress, serape, embroidered
shawl and multicoloured ribbons. They
are led by the Patron, who wears a severe
mask and carries a guitar and whip, while
playing a flute, accompanied by one or
two drummers. As they dance, he intones
praises to which the Parachicos respond
with cheers. 
The Convention for the
Safeguarding of Intangible Cultural
Heritage, was adopted at UNESCO in
2003, and came into force on 20 April
2006. It recognizes the importance of
intangible cultural heritage, which
resides not so much in the cultural
manifestation itself as in the wealth of
knowledge and skills that it passes
down from generation to generation.
To date there are 213 elements on
the Representative List of the Intangible
Cultural Heritage of Humanity, while the
List of Intangible Cultural Heritage in
Need of Urgent Safeguarding, numbers 16.
© 2009 Executive Coordination for the
commemoration of the Bicentenary of the 
National Independence and of the Centennial of
the Mexican Revolution of the State of Chiapas
 Intangible cultural heritage
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J A N U A R Y  M A R C H  2 0 1 1  . 5 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
