<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="193773eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
How
youth
drive
change
Young people in the world: 
so different and so alike
Monique Coleman 
Mobile revolution  
Gigi Ibrahim 
Spring of outrage
Alfredo Trujillo Fernandez
Miracle Weapons
Serge Amisi 
When poetry is louder than a bomb
Nate Marshall
Moonlight stars
Carol Natukunda
A young sughar 
Noshan Abbas
Rebels with a cause
Jens Lubbadeh 
Prescriptions for a sick planet              
Zhao Ying 
Green architecture 
Carlos Bartesaghi Koc 
Revolution: one of the 
great feats of civilization  
Khaled Youssef 
Courier
THE UNESCO July-September 2011
United Nations 
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization,
ISSN 2220-2285
e-ISSN 2220-2293
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Pierre Arlaud
Mathieu Ponnard
(France)
Merlijn Twaalfhoven 
(Netherlands) Zhao Ying 
(China)
Hiroki Yanagisawa 
(Japan)
Emna Fitouri
(Tunisia)
Gigi Ibrahim 
Khaled Youssef 
(Egypt)
Ingebjørg Bratland 
(Norway)
Silvia Bellón
(Spain)
Atti Tata
(Togo)
Majd Shahin
Betty Shamieh  
(Occupied Palestinian Territory)
Carlos Bartesaghi Koc
(Peru)
Ruth Pérez López
(Mexico)
Monique Coleman 
Nate Marshall
(United States)
Noshan Abbas 
Khalida Brohi
(Pakistan)
Josephat Gitonga
(Kenya)
Carol Natukunda 
(Uganda)
Barbara Mallinson 
(South Africa)
Serge Amisi 
(Democratic Republic 
of Congo)
OUR AUTHORS
“Five years away from the 2015 target date for achieving the Millennium
Development Goals, it is more important than ever to encourage young
people to dedicate themselves to achieving a more just and sustainable
world,” wrote Irina Bokova, Director-General of UNESCO, in her message
on the occasion of the launch of the International Year of Youth (August
2010 – August 2011) and of International Youth Day (12 August) .
Proclaimed in December 2009 by the United Nations General
Assembly, the international year puts the accent on dialogue and mutual
understanding. It aims to promote the ideals of peace, respect for
human rights and solidarity between generations, cultures, religions and
civilizations. 
During the year a large number of young people have been striving
to build a more just world, starting with the “Arab Spring”. All over the
world, they have been speaking out, demanding a place in their
country’s future. The 7th UNESCO Youth Forum, "How youth drive
change", to be held from 17 to 20 October 2011, will provide them with
an opportunity to discuss their experiences, present their projects and
exchange ideas. 
Since its creation, UNESCO has considered youth a major priority. Its Youth Programme aims to promote opportunities for
young people to be given greater responsibilities and to see their role in society recognized. 
From February 2010 to February 2011, the Organization jointly chaired the United Nations Interagency Network on Youth
Development, alongside the United Nations Programme on Youth. It was in this capacity that UNESCO participated in the
coordination of the International Year of Youth.
International Year of
Youth 2010–2011
Iris Julia Bührle 
Jens Lubbadeh 
(Germany)
Mila Zourleva
(Bulgaria)
Selen Demir
(Turkey)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
©
 G
h
a
ss
a
n
 H
a
lw
a
n
i
Courier
THE UNESCO July–September 2011
United Nations 
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
64th year
2011 – No. 3 
The UNESCO Courier is currently a quarterly published in
seven languages by the United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, place de Fontenoy 75352, Paris 07 SP, France
Free subscription to the Courier on line:
www.unesco.org/courier
Director of publication: Eric Falt
Editor-in-chief: Jasmina Šopova 
j.sopova@unesco.org
Managing editor: Katerina Markelova
k.markelova@unesco.org 
Editors: 
Arabic: Khaled Abu Hijleh 
Chinese: Weiny Cauhape
English: Cathy Nolan
French: Françoise Arnaud-Demir
Portuguese: Ana Lúcia Guimarães
Russian: Irina Krivova
Spanish: Francisco Vicente-Sandoval
Intern: Vanessa Merlin
Photos: Danica Bijeljac  
Design and layout: Baseline Arts Ltd, Oxford
Printing: UNESCO – CLD
Information and reproduction rights: 
+ 33 (0)1 45 68 15 64 . k.markelova@unesco.org
Web platform: Chakir Piro and Van Dung Pham
With thanks to: Mila Zourleva
Articles and photos credited UNESCO may be reproduced
and/or translated for non-commercial purposes providing
the credit line reads “Reproduced from the UNESCO
Courier” and includes date and hyperlink. Photos without
UNESCO credit require  special permission.
Articles express the opinions of the authors and do not 
necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO.
Photographs belonging to UNESCO may be reproduced
freely. Photos must carry the following caption: © UNESCO
and photographer's name. For high resolution, please
contact the Photobank: photobank@unesco.org 
Boundaries on maps do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations
of the countries and territories concerned.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 3
Editorial – Irina Bokova, Director-General of UNESCO 5
REPORT: HOW YOUTH DRIVE CHANGE
Young people in the world: so different and so alike 7
Interview with  Monique Coleman by Katerina Markelova
An act of survival  Emna Fitouri 9
Mobile revolution   Gigi Ibrahim 11
Spring of outrage  Alfredo Trujillo Fernandez 13
Youth, once upon a time 15
Young Czechs want to have their say – Mathieu Ponnard 16
My best friend Obami – Barbara Mallinson 18
Serge Amisi and his miracle weapons 20
Interview by Selen Demir 
Locked in the cycle of violence – Mila Zourleva 22
When poetry is louder than a bomb – Nate Marshall 23
Different dreams, yet… 25
A conversation with B. Shamieh, M. Twaalfhoven, I. Bratland and M. Shahin
by I. J. Bührle et K. Abu Hijleh
JR, art and the impossible – Jasmina Šopova 30
Patrimonito in Togo  – Katerina Markelova 31
Wonders of creativity – Silvia Bellón and Pierre Arlaud 32
Sport: only a starting point 33
Youth Olympic Games 33
Moonlight stars – Carol Natukunda   34
The young sughar from Balochistan – Noshan Abbas meets Khalida Brohi 36
An undeclared revolution  – Hiroki Yanagisawa 39
Rebels with a cause – Jens Lubbadeh   40
Prescriptions for a sick planet – Zhao Ying 44
Life in the bike lane  – Ruth Pérez López 46
Green architecture – Carlos Bartesaghi Koc 48
OUR GUEST
Revolution: one of the great feats of civilization 50
Interview with Khaled Youssef by Khaled Abu Hijleh
MILESTONES 
UNESCO welcomes  53
Hillary Clinton, Ban Ki-moon, Forest Whitaker, Shashi Tharoor... 
“Mordabella”,
mixed media,
2009. By
Lebanese artist
Ghassan
Halwani.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
In this issue 
4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
“Our focus doesn’t have to be on
changing the whole world,  just
changing our world.,” says American
actress and singer Monique Coleman,
appointed United Nations “Youth
Champion” for the International Year of
Youth 2010–2011 (pp. 7-8). That is
exactly what young people are doing to
change  the things that need changing.
At the beginning of 2011, they rose
up against existing political regimes,
first in Tunisia (pp. 9-10) then in Egypt
(pp.11-12), giving the rest of the world a
good lesson in democracy. Social
networks spread the movement to
other countries in the region, also
rousing European nations such as Spain
(pp. 13-14). Their tools, theirs slogans
and their goals are practically the same
everywhere. They are fighting for jobs,
social justice, free education and health
care, freedom of expression and above
all democracy. The inspiring news of the
“Arab Spring” went around the world,
held up as a symbol of a peaceful
revolution led by youth.
Elsewhere in the world, young
people mobilize in different ways, as for
example the students in Czechoslovakia
who have decided to “chip in” and have
their say in their country's affairs (pp. 16-
17), or the South African
businesswoman who created a social
network for disadvantaged schools (pp.
18-19), and the young people who are
hopeful they can vanquish racism,
xenophobia discrimination and conflict
through the “miraculous weapons” of art
(pp. 21-30).
One common denominator is
solidarity, illustrated in the activities of
young volunteers, scouts and athletes,
but also in the heartrending stories of
the Ugandan “stars” (pp. 34-35) and a
young Pakistani sughar (pp. 36-38). As
for Japanese youth, who displayed great
generosity during the March 2011
disaster, they have precipitated radical
changes in the old value system centered
on economic growth (pp. 39-40).
Finally, we are not surprised to
discover that young people are seriously
concerned about the future of the
environment. Particularly sensitive to
climate change issues, the new
generations are capable of waging war
against various forms of ecological
inertia. From the European Union to
China, Mexico and Peru (pp. 40-49),
thousands of young people are using
their diverse talents to work for a
healthier planet.
To conclude this issue produced
entirely by young writers we asked
Egyptian filmmaker Khaled Youssef to
give us his views on “Arab Spring”
(pp. 50-52).He shares his vision of the
events that rocked his country in the
beginning of the year and their impact
on the world, society and international
politics. ■
Jasmina Šopova
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
They number more than a billion and most of
them live in developing countries. The world
population of 15- to 24-year-olds represents
more than a billion hopes for a better future,
more than a billion ideas to change the world in
constructive ways, more than a billion potential
solutions to the problems of today. With or
without academic degrees, free or determined to
become free, young people are reinventing
culture, taking control of the new media,
recreating how we relate to each other. Yet few of
them are able to enjoy a carefree youth. Most of
them are battling every day against the obstacles
of poverty, unemployment, climate change,
restricted access to education and health care.
How to participate fully in creating the future,
when one is excluded from the decision-making
process? We must help them and support their
ambitions by giving them access to the immense
resources of education, science, culture,
communication and information.
The mighty wind of “Arab Spring” has amazed
us with the capacity of young people to widen
the horizons of possibility. The year 2011 -
proclaimed by the United Nations as International
Youth Year (August 2010 – August 2011) – will be
remembered as the year young people chose to
take up the torch of human dignity.
The Organization immediately mobilized to
provide support to these societies in their
transformation, at a turning point in their history.
In Tunisia and Egypt, UNESCO focuses on training
journalists, distributing educational material,
helping to reinforce freedom of expression and
media reform in view of upcoming elections. I
went there, to Cairo, to hear what the needs were
and to reinforce UNESCO’s intervention in its
areas of competence. The celebration of World
Press Freedom Day on May 3 in Tunis, co-
organized by UNESCO, opened up debate and
led to a major discussion on young people’s key
issues, such as the role of the internet and social
media in the fight against censorship. Last June,
our Organization was the first to launch a series
of seminars in Egypt as a forum for discussion on
civic engagement and democracy
Culture is a strong foundation for the new
democratic society. Young Egyptians proved to
be particularly concerned with safeguarding
their culture during the demonstrations,
spontaneously forming a human chain around
the Library of Alexandria to protect it from
looters. UNESCO wants to encourage this
consciousness among young people, the
collective maturity they displayed. It will support
it in the long term through the “Youth Heritage”
initiative, which will allow the heirs to a unique
heritage to immerse themselves even more in
the ancient values it conveys and to use it as an
instrument of social cohesion and innovation.
In the same vein, I will launch a Heritage and
Dialogue initiative at the next Summit of the
Heads of State of South East Europe that will take
place in Belgrade next September 2011. The Serb
I On her first official visit to
Croatia on 21-22 May 2011,
UNESCO Director-General
Irina Bokova (in white jacket)
opened the first South-East
Europe World Heritage Youth
Forum in Porec, to mark the
International Year of Youth
2010-2011. ©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
 /
 B
o
b
ir
 T
u
kh
ta
b
ay
e
v
Editorial
Irina Bokova
L Scene from “Silent
Evolution”, underwater
installation by British
artist Jason deCaires
Taylor, shown during the
2010 United Nations
climate change
conference (COP 16) in
Cancun, Mexico. Young
divers posing with
submerged statues call
attention to a climate
change threat: rising sea
levels.
©
 J
a
so
n
 d
e
 C
a
ir
e
s 
Ta
yl
o
r/
G
re
e
n
p
e
a
ce
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
capital was the theatre of a decisive revolution to
bring democracy to the region: the revolution
led by the young Serbs of the Otpor (Resistance)
movement, which instigated the fall of the
regime of President Slobodan Milošević. More
than10 years after this event, as the region
continues along the path to reconciliation and
democracy, UNESCO wants to give young people
the means to fulfill their ambitions, mobilizing all
the forces of culture to help them shape projects
to promote dialogue and mutual respect. This is
the primary purpose of UNESCO’s Young People’s
World Heritage Education Programme.  
UNESCO was the first UN agency to define
and develop specific youth programmes. World
War II had just ended and UNESCO was already
involved in organizing work camps for young
international volunteers to help in the
reconstruction of Europe. Today it is by
improving the quality of education for all, by
reinforcing protection for pupils and schools in
areas of conflict, by providing better professional
training that we create the conditions for a
brighter future. It is also by helping to establish
ties between young people in different parts of
the world based on shared values of human
rights. For this purpose our Organization has just
produced a short film with the participation of
pupils from UNESCO Associated Schools in
Albania, Azerbaijan, Brazil, Burkina Faso, Canada,
France, Indonesia, Lebanon, Uganda and the
Dominican Republic. The scenes of these
schoolchildren freely expressing their views
about gender, diversity, violence and exclusion
provide vital educational material that is
available to secondary schools throughout the
world.
Youth are a force for progress all over the
world. Let us enable them to speak out, to
participate fully in social and political life, to raise
our awareness and open blocked horizons. This is
the goal UNESCO pursues through its Youth
Programme, which supports civic engagement
and social innovation.
A Joint Programmatic Commission on Youth
facilitates cooperation between UNESCO and
NGOs. The Commission is made up of young
people and it is particularly involved in preparing
UNESCO’s Youth Forums. These events have been
held every two years since 1999 to enable young
people to submit recommendations to national
authorities and incite them to implement their
ideas and follow them up, in cooperation with
governments, civil society and the United
Nations system. This year the 7th UNESCO Youth
Forum, 17-20 October 2011, will be a wonderful
opportunity to hear what young people from all
over the world have to say and to discover their
needs and their points of view.
How youth drive change is the topic to be
discussed by the young representatives of
UNESCO’s 193 Member States and civil society.
The culture of peace, good governance and
economic opportunity will be examined from
the perspective of young people’s participation.
Achievements and lessons learned from the
International Year of Youth will also be reviewed,
notably the results of the High-Level Meeting on
Youth organized by the UN in July 2011.
In anticipation of this important event,
UNESCO will launch an on-line preparation
campaign in July, to enable young people to give
their opinions and suggest the subjects they
most care about. The results of these discussions
will nourish the Forum’s debates in October.
UNESCO has always considered young
people key partners in creating a world with
more justice. Youth is always calling on us to
innovate, to invent. Every day brings us more
examples of this positive momentum. I hope this
issue of the UNESCO Courier will inspire
everyone to action. Enjoy reading it! ■
“In the nobility of
your spirit, 
in the exuberance
of your youth,
in the quality of
your contacts,
in the unsullied
idealism that you
possess,
in the dedication to
our common
humanity that you
bring … I find the
hope of mastering
the challenges of
the difficult
transition ahead,
to complete the
revolution you
have initiated and
of building the
better Egypt that
your actions have
made possible.”
Ismail Serageldin
Director of the
Bibliotheca
Alexandrina
12 February 2011
J Graffiti representing a fist,
symbol of Otpor (Resistance),
the Serb youth movement that
brought down President
Slobodan Milošević’s regime in
2000. The symbol was
adopted by young insurgents
in Egypt. Photo taken 8 April
2011 in Mohammed
Mahmoud Street leading to
Tahrir Square, the epicenter of
the revolution in January
2011.
©
 M
a
g
g
ie
 O
sa
m
a
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
You were appointed Youth Champion
by the UN in November 2010. Three
months later you were off on a world
tour. What was your goal?
This trip is as much personal as it is for
the advancement of the Year. At some
point in life it is important to get out of
your own comfort zone, the things you
are familiar with, and to see something
new through the eyes of someone else.
Living in America I felt that I had a
limited view of the rest of the world. As
the Youth Champion and as a human I
couldn’t ever talk about poverty if I
hadn’t seen that with my own eyes. I
couldn’t talk about young people’s
amazing achievements if I hadn’t met
young people doing exceptional things. 
so different 
and so alike
As “Youth Champion” of the
United Nations, American
singer and actress Monique
Coleman, 31, has the mission
of bringing to life the themes
of the International Year of
Youth (August 2010-August
2011), which are dialogue
and mutual understanding.
She intends to make that
mission more than a
statement and to give young
people the opportunity to
express their ideas and
opinions.
MONIQUE COLEMAN was interviewed by Katerina Markelova
International Year of Youth 
http://social.un.org/youthyear/ 
K April 2011: A convivial moment on Monique Coleman's tour of India. (Photo by Gimmemotalk)
Young people
intheworld
©
 G
im
m
e
m
o
ta
lk
Our focus doesn’t have to be on
changing the whole world, our
focus can be just on changing
our world. 
J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The role of youth in Arab uprisings is
huge. Did it change your vision of your
mission? 
The first stop on the tour was initially
intended to be Tunisia. And the day I
was intending to leave was the day the
unrest started to break out. But for
security reasons we had to modify the
itinerary. One of my missions while I am
on this trip is to try to give voice to
issues before they exacerbate and
become an uprising. One thing that I
can do right now while traveling is get a
sense of what these issues are, bubbling
underneath the surface, to bring some
light and awareness. 
These young people are reacting
not only to their lifetime of pain but
their families’ and their parents’ lifetime
of pain, war and torment. I don’t think
they are being destructive. They can’t be
blamed for reacting in the way that they
know how, but I would like to look for
new peaceful ways. I’d like to remind us
all of Martin Luther King, Gandhi and
Nelson Mandela. 
I was in the Philippines last February
on the day that they celebrated the 25th
anniversary of the peaceful revolution
(that ended the Marcos dictatorship).
They were able to have a revolution
with women, pregnant women and
children, who were all standing up for
the same thing, and nobody got killed.
These are the kind of revolutions I want
to start. 
In your on-line talk show “Gimme MO”,
you emphasize the power of the
internet to give young people a voice.
“Gimme MO” is indeed a platform for
youth. It’s a place where I talk about
things that people don’t bring much
attention to and try to give a different
angle. I also interview celebrities,
experts, people that I meet out in the
world. 
The main purpose of this show is to
help young people see that even the
people you look up to share similar
interests and are basically the same, and
to break stereotypes. When I was in
Australia I interviewed a young Muslim
refugee who is living in public housing
in Melbourne. She is 21, she wears a veil,
and she completely rejects the
stereotype according to
which Muslim females are
oppressed and don’t have
their own voices. 
Are the young people
you meet on your trip all
the same, or are they
different from one
country to another? 
Young people are
actually very similar.
(laughs) The biggest
difference is that in
developing countries
the young people are
extremely aware of
world issues. They have
to be, because those
issues live on their
doorstep, they
approach them on
their way to school. 
Whereas in developed countries
sometimes we can be less aware of the
global issues. We sometimes tend to be
bogged down in our own personal
things. 
What are the most pressing issues
young people have raised?
In places like Australia the big thing is
self-esteem, to help young people feel
better about themselves. Suicide is a
huge issue. 
In Bangladesh it’s almost the
opposite. I had a student saying: “How do
you expect to bring awareness to the
people in developed countries who are
willing to take their own life while we are
struggling here just to survive.” And that
was really powerful. That said it all. 
The thing that remains the same is
that every young person is looking for a
place in the world. I try to explain to
them how limitless the possibilities are,
to convince each of them they have so
much value and potential, regardless of
their state, their social-economic class,
their religious background, their level of
privilege or disadvantage. We all have
obstacles that we have to overcome. It’s
up to us to overcome those things. And
once we have overcome them, it’s so
important that we liberate our global
brothers and sisters.
Our focus doesn’t have to be on
changing the whole world, our focus can
just actually be on changing our world.
Because if every person focused on their
community or village, then collectively
we would change the whole world. 
Once the Year is over, do you want to
continue to support young people
throughout the world? 
Absolutely, this is simply the beginning! I
intend to put much of my focus in
“Gimme MO”. I would like to see it move
into a television platform, as well as an
interactive internet place employing new
technologies. 
In my acting career I would like to
play roles that help enhance and move
this movement forward. I think that
entertainment and art is an incredible
way to deepen any message. Often,
when I talk to people about why they
decide to make a difference, why they
become a part of an organization, why
did they became passionate about
something, they tend to trace it back to a
book or a song or a movie. So, I would
like to continue to create such artistic
opportunities for inspiration. ■
J Monique Coleman on the
poster for  her on-line youth
talk show “Gimme MO”.
Young people are reacting not
only to their lifetime of pain but
their families’ and their parents’
lifetime of pain, war and
torment.
©
 B
a
zi
lle
8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
An act of survival
A scene from the
Tunisian revolution.
Tunis. Late January
2011.
In the eyes of student Emna Fitouri, the Tunisian youth uprising in January 2011 was more
than just a revolution – it was a matter of life and death for a whole generation.  
EMNA FITOURI
On 10 January 2011, I saw on Facebook
that people were getting ready to
demonstrate in Tunis. My classmates and
I arranged to meet outside the Ministry
of the Interior on 14 January. We
demonstrated for three days, on Avenue
Habib Bourguiba and in Place de la
Kasbah, in the city centre. We arranged
everything on Facebook, like most
young Tunisians. That is why a lot of
commentators have called ours a
“Facebook revolution”. But the reality
was much more complex. In fact these
social networks were just a tool that
young people used to get started, to
trigger a change in society, to fight
against unemployment and other forms
of humiliation, to stand up for human
rights and dignity. 
Having said this, it would be wrong
to play down the role of internet
completely, because it has proved to be
an awesome instrument in the
democratisation of Arab countries, while
reflecting the diversity of their politics
and culture. And a powerful weapon
against censorship. Now, no one can say
“It’s me. I’m in charge.” The internet will
stop them, by providing opportunities
for constructive debate. It is also
teaching us what “debate” really means. 
The previous revolution in Tunisia
ended with a “revolutionary
dictatorship”, with well-known results.
Today we are part of a non-violent,
“civilized revolution”, which is heading
towards democracy. 
But it is not all so civilized – the
media and analysts have made a lot of
the “peaceful” character of this
revolution, because young people took
to the streets unarmed. We need to
choose our words carefully. Peaceful, for
whom? For the people who crouched in
fear day after day, as the bullets flew?
For the soldiers and policemen who
were torn between their professional
duty and personal convictions? For the
young demonstrators who had never
seen so much blood flow?  The hell we
went through may not have been as
deadly as that of our brothers in Libya,
Yemen and Syria, but we still went
through some terrible moments.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 9
©
 N
a
ss
e
r 
N
o
u
ri
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Emna Fitouri, 21-year-old Tunisian, is
in her second year at the Preparatory
Institute for Literary Studies and
Humanities in Tunis, where she is
studying French. She is a scout captain
in Hammam Lif, a suburb in the south
of Tunis. 
©
 M
o
n
ia
 A
g
re
b
i
K Vox pop. Tunis, 27 January 2011.
©
 H
a
m
id
e
d
d
in
e
 B
o
u
a
li
I saw dead bodies; I was terrified; I
fainted because of the tear gas…
Hundreds of people from Sidi Bouzid –
the town where Mohamed Bouazizi set
himself on fire on 4 January, triggering
the revolution – came to the Kasbah in
Tunis, to join the demonstrations in the
capital. Some brought their wives and
children. They were cold, hungry and
miserable. I helped the scouts bring
them food and blankets and assisted
the doctor in charge of the scouts’
medical service.
But more than anything, I shouted.
For days on end. With all my might, I
shouted “GET OUT!” until Ben Ali left. I
wanted to put an end to a regime that
had made youth its most vulnerable
victims.
Instead of being the driving force
behind the economy, we had become
its scapegoat. That explains why we, the
young people, were the first to rise up.
In fact, we were trapped. On the one
hand we were receiving what was
supposed to be one of the best
educations in Africa, but, in reality, it was
not adapted to the needs of an ever-
changing market. Meanwhile, the
regime did not allow us to get jobs and
keep them. Continuing education, which
allows employees to keep their skills up
to date, does not exist in Tunisia. For
example, in the IT world, when the
technology changes, companies simply
get new software engineers and
technicians! Job insecurity has become a
disease, just as oppressive as the
impossibility for young graduates to find
work in the first place. I wonder if there is
a single family in the entire country that
doesn’t have at least one unemployed
graduate at home. 
The unstable education system and
the extremely cynical economic policy
made the younger generation feel
abused, exploited and suffocated. Our
first uprisings were acts of survival. Our
future actions will be part of a process
of building a new country. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
You lived in the United States between
2000 and 2008. You returned to Egypt
at the age of 22 and you were
immediately engaged in the socio-
political arena. Had you already been
an activist in the U.S.?
Yes, I was much more involved during
my stay in the USA in local issues such
as immigration laws. I joined a group
that was fighting for illegal immigration
rights because police officers were
enforcing immigration laws which were
discriminatory. I was also involved in
many activities that supported the
Palestinian cause. So whenever there is
a demonstration or an anti-war call, I
would be definitely a part of it. 
But to be honest, I was far from
being involved in what was happening
in Egypt at the time due to my rare visits
to Egypt. I also was not aware politically
enough because I lived abroad from the
age of 14 to 22. I was not aware of the
Egyptian opposition movement since it
was completely ignored in the
mainstream media. So, unless you were
living here and being part of it, you
would really know nothing about it.
Even people living nearby did not know
about it. Only close activists, journalists
and the political community knew what
was going on.
GIGI IBRAHIM was interviewed by Khaled Abu Hijleh
You can follow Gigi Ibrahim on Twitter at:
http://twitter.com/Gsquare86
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 1 1
Mobilerevolution
At the height of the revolution in Egypt in January 2011, a young woman mobilized crowds
on Facebook and Twitter, kept the internet community around the world informed,
organized street rallies and waved banners, her mobile telephone always within reach.
Gigi Ibrahim, 24, is a perfect example of the high tech generation Arab revolutionary. Not
all of Gigi’s compatriots who marched in the streets had computers at home – far from it –
yet social media played a crucial role in organizing this historical event that is changing
the world. And not just the Arab world. 
The 24 year old young Egyptian activist Gigi Ibrahim
during the Egyptian revolution in 2011.
© Al Jazeera English
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
I got in touch with the Egyptian
activists the first time when I got back
from the USA in 2008. Then, I took a
course on social mobilization under the
authoritarian regime at the American
University of Cairo (AUC). I started
learning politics and participated in the
protests in 2009 - 2010 where I met
many activists. This is how I got involved
in the framework of the revolutionary
socialists.
social youth group or a political group
to a popular movement with political
and economic demands. 
We started with 100 people, then we
became thousands and thousands of
people chanting against the regime.
People kept going in increasing
numbers to Al-Tahreer Square in the city
center.
When we arrived in the square,
people were chanting the same chants
the Tunisian people chanted, “People
demand the removal of the regime”. We
did not necessarily plan for this though
we hoped it would happen.
Sometimes, we made fun of what
we were doing, saying, “ooh, we are
planning for a revolution on Facebook!”
Nobody believed it would turn out the
way it did. But thankfully it did, because
people were fed up and so oppressed
they would do anything to get their
freedom.
What was the role of the social media
in these events in Egypt, and what was
the role of the young citizen
journalists? 
Before the revolution, social networks
played a really important role. They
were not the means of the revolution
but they were definitely the tools that
were used to communicate. 
Under an authoritarian regime,
every piece of news, every newspaper
and every mass media is of crucial
importance. Citizen journalism becomes
activism. Sorting out the truth,
providing information about the
subjects that the State tries to censor,
was very important.
It was our only means, before the
revolution, to expose and explain what
was happening on the ground. Many
people never heard of protests or strikes
that were going on. It was only through
the social networks, that stories reached
the independent media and the
international press like Aljazeera. These
tools were important to expose the
torture cases at the police stations.
Many of them were videoed by cell
phones. All these abuses were disclosed
by the means of Flickr, Facebook and
Twitter because they were uncensored
until the government began shutting
them down. 
It should be said that the people
who went into the streets and carried
out the revolution did not have access
to tools such as Facebook and Twitter or
even a computer. They went into the
streets and risked their lives to get good
healthcare, good education and a better
future for their children.
Although the people who carried
out the revolution had nothing to do
with these tools, social networks were
essential in mobilizing people and in
getting the attention of the
independent and international media.
As a young Arab woman, don’t you
think Egyptian women’s participation
in the 25 January uprising started
breaking down the wall of Arab
traditions? 
I disagree. Women have always been a
part of any mobilization or revolution
whether in the Middle East or anywhere
else in the world. 
This time in Egypt, women were
leading strikes, chants and protests and
getting arrested and being tortured. In
my experience in the Egyptian uprising,
there was no difference between men
and women within the mobilization
process or protests.
However, women struggle also for
their rights as women. But then they are
faced with a counterattack by people
saying this is not the right moment. But
when is the right moment then?* This is
not so unique to the Middle East: in the
United States, United Kingdom and
everywhere else, women struggle for
their rights too.
Do you think young people in other
countries may be inspired by the Arab
revolutions as a model of a peaceful
popular struggle to bring about
changes in their  own homelands?
We have already seen such youth
movements not only within the region
but also in other countries. There were
big marches in London on 26 March this
year. There were banners and slogans
similar to the Egyptian ones.
The Arab world has always been
stereotyped and defined as a backward
and violent region and a home of
terrorism. This time the Arab world was
held up as an example of democracy
that comes from the bottom up and
brings about real change through the
power of the people exerted in a
peaceful way. ■
* See our article on this topic ,“Now or Never”, about
the Italian demonstrations of 13 February 2011 in
the April-June 2011 issue of the Courier, “Women
conquering new expanses of freedom”.
Could you describe your role in the 25
January protests?
I had joined a handful of political
movement groups who called for mass
demonstrations on 25 January. We
coordinated the timing, place and the
content of the demands. 
Our major demand at that point was
the arrest of Habib Al-Adly, the Minister
of the Interior. We were calling for this
because of the death of Khaled Said on
6 June 2010 (Note, the young man was
beaten to death by police.) Other
demands were to dissolve the
Parliament, elected at the end of 2010,
and to establish a minimum wage.
Street protests were our way of bringing
those demands to the popular front. 
After the Tunisian uprising, Arab
people started to believe in their ability
to bring changes through street
protests and through a peaceful
revolution. This was also our intention:
to promote our movement from just a
L The mobile phone has become an essential tool in
the struggle for democracy in Egypt
©
 H
o
ss
a
m
 E
l H
a
m
a
la
w
y
1 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Since 15 May, Spain has been living in a climate of demonstrations and protests that have
taken most of the world by surprise. This “Movimiento 15-M” – or more simply, these
“indignados” – have left us wondering what exactly they might want? Isn’t Spain an
advanced, democratic country, not to be compared with Tunisia and Egypt? Yet on a closer
look, many Spaniards feel no one is listening to them and the established system is simply
denying them a future. And it is for this future that young Spaniards have decided to fight.
©
 S
lo
b
o
d
a
n
 K
. B
ije
lja
c 
ALFREDO TRUJILLO FERNANDEZ
The Spring  
The protests broke out spontaneously.
“No one saw it coming”, admitted
Cristóbal Ramírez, a 27-year-old Madrid-
based journalist, born in Cadiz. It all
started on 15 May, with a
demonstration in Madrid organized by
the Democracia Real Ya (True Democracy
Now) and Jovenes Sin Futuro (Youth with
No Future) movements. Then they
started to put up tents, which spread
across the country. As the days went by,
the demonstrators, who called
themselves the indignados (indignant
ones), saw their essentially young
numbers swelled by pensioners,
workers of every sort, cleaners,
granddads with their grandsons and
families with toddlers. 
This indignation is the direct result
of the serious economic crisis hitting the
country. Unemployment in Spain has
reached record rates for Western
Europe: 20.6 % in the first quarter of
2011. And among the young, the figure
has skyrocketed to 44.3 %. In 2007,
before the crisis, just 8.3 % of the
population were unemployed.
Nevertheless, even in the years of
economic prosperity, there were some
J "Spring", collage and gouache, 2011, by
Slobodan K. Bijeljac, French painter born in Bosnia-
Herzegovina. Created specially for this issue of the
UNESCO Courier. Visit his website:
http://bijeljac2.free.fr/
J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 1 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
through the forest of tents and
tarpaulins that have sprung up in the
city centre. “I am shocked to see how
hard it has become for citizens to get
themselves heard,” she says. “In my view,
all they want is to be listened to and
taken seriously...”  
Vitor Peiteado, a 32-year-old
political commentator from La Corogne,
sees the anger behind the wave of
protests. “There is a reaction of
indignation at the crisis, which the
workers did not cause, and yet, oddly,
they are the ones paying the price.”
Vitor, like hundreds of other young
Spaniards over the past few years, had
to go abroad to look for opportunities
and a salary he cannot get in his own
country. He is delighted at what is
happening: “For the first time, people
are saying that the problem is to be
found in the system itself, and that this
democracy, where we only get to vote
every four years, like the existing
economic system, just isn’t working.” 
Miriam also emphasises that the
main objective is to obtain “better
citizen participation, which could be
encouraged using the new
technologies.” Everywhere, in all the
meetings and debates, people are also
repeatedly saying that the politicians
have to represent the interests of the
people, not those of the banks and large
corporations. The movement is also
determined to keep the parties and
traditional unions away from their
protests, reinforcing their popular,
grassroots and, in a sense, “anti-system”
character.
The future will tell
But there has been no clear formulation
of the movement’s objectives, or of how
to go about meeting them. For Miriam,
this is because the process is still in its
early stages. “The question of ‘how’ is
still being worked out. We are in the
phase of realising that things have to
change, the reflection phase. By
discussing and debating the issues, we
will end by knowing what we have to
do,” she explains. Cristóbal thinks that it
is time to change a system, which at
present “is doing nothing about the
problems facing the poor.” Vitor admits
that many of the ideas are still “very
general” and that the demands remain
“vague”. But, he adds, “it is the first time,
for almost half a century, that a
movement this big questions the
legitimacy of the liberal partisan
democracy.” Olivia thinks that the
absence of detail and clarity is a
reflection of the crisis itself and the scale
of the problems facing Spain. And, she
concludes, “There are so many problems
to solve that we don’t know where to
start.”
In a sense, it is possible this lack of
definition is the outline of a movement
that will, in the near future, have clear
objectives and a well-traced roadmap
for reaching them. And, who knows, will
perhaps serve as an example for
‘indignados’ to follow in other European
countries also suffering from the crisis,
and sharing the same democratic spirit
as Spain. But if the energy of the first
weeks starts to fade, the Movimiento 15-
M could be lost in the sands of time, and
just become another anecdote in this
spring of hope and indignation, 2011. ■
It is the first time, for almost half
a century, that a movement this
big questions the legitimacy of
the liberal democracy founded
on particracy
warning signs that the machine was
grinding to a halt. In August 2005, in a
letter to the editor published in the
daily newspaper, El País, a young woman
from Barcelona coined the word
“mileurista”. It refers to the young
Spanish graduate, bristling with
diplomas, multilingual, usually with a
Master’s degree, and yet barely earning
1000 euros a month – the stigma of a
whole generation, better qualified than
ever before, that feels exploited in the
workplace and neglected by the system. 
In politics, before and after the 2008
economic crisis, the past few years have
been peppered with cases of corruption
involving members of the majority
parties. But almost none of them were
brought to trial. It is hardly surprising,
therefore, that in a survey carried out in
2009 by the Centre for Sociological
Research (CIS), six out of ten Spaniards
felt that corruption was somewhat or
very common among both Federal and
local politicians. And, in the same poll,
the majority of the sample admitted
they had little confidence in the political
classes or the system. 
Economic crisis, political corruption,
loss of confidence in the democratic
system – these are the main ingredients
of the cocktail that led tens of
thousands of indignados to take to the
streets across the country. 
At last, my country is waking up
On 15 May, Miriam Blanco, a 30-year-old
woman from Madrid, heard of the first
protest at the Puerta del Sol. “At last”,
she thought, “my country is waking up!”
With several degrees and speaking four
languages or more, Miriam has since the
very beginning been a member of the
committees that were formed. “They
told us: ‘you are the future’. But we are
neither the future nor the present,” she
says heatedly, trying to explain the
reasons for their indignation. “We are no
longer afraid. We have nothing left to
lose, as we have no future, and neither
do our children,” she adds. 
“People have had enough,” says
Cristóbal, who over these past weeks
has joined many of the indignado
demonstrations in the Puerta del Sol.
“We want a change in the system, so
that power comes from the citizens - a
true, more participative democracy,” he
says. And, every day, Olivia Waters, a 27-
year-old English woman who has been
living in the capital for five years, walks
L Spanish journalist Alfredo Trujillo Fernandez, 31,
works on the editorial team of UNESCO’s website
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
ia
 F
re
in
d
o
rf
1 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
One year after May 1968,
the UNESCO Courier
devoted an issue to “Youth
1969”*, this “youth in
ferment”, an “angry
generation” of dissent and
enthusiasm, and the
“malaise” of young people
in different parts of the
world. In many ways, “the
wave of protest and dissent
from world youth” in 1968
resembled the events of
“Arab Spring” 2011. The
following brief excerpts
from the article “The crisis
of modern society” prove
the point. 
Youth, once upon a time…
L "We asked to be heard. You refused....” This excerpt from the special issue “Youth 1969” was the caption for the
photograph on the back cover, reprinted here..
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 1 5
With their need for absolutes, the
young are less than ever able to
tolerate the injustices and disorder of
the world.
René Maheu, Director-General of
UNESCO
Youth have now achieved the status
of a distinct community. This has led to
the most basic conflict of all: it stems
from youth's determination to win from
society the status and esteem they
deem to be their right. 
Modern information media
familiarize youth with different cultures
while ignoring frontiers. On a world
scale, a sort of international "youth
culture" seems to have sprung up.
Young people display their
disapproval of racial segregation and
linguistic discrimination, they protest
against the paternalism and the living
conditions they must endure, they have
risen up against social conformity, they
have denounced the myths of ‘production
for production's sake’ and ‘consumption
for consumption's sake’.
They want freer, franker and
warmer human relations than what they
get from us. They are afraid that  the
national and international system into
which they are being driven contains
grave injustices to which they do not
want to be party.
*Find this issue in our archives:
www.unesco.org/courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Their names are Jan, Jana and Jirka and
they are in their early twenties. They
were all at one time or another involved
in Czech youth NGOs. This meant they
could express their opinions on a range
of subjects, either within their
organizations, in their town or – why
not – Europe-wide. Until reality caught
up with them... It was practically
impossible for them to be heard at
national level! “So we decided to change
things,” explains Jan Husak, 23, studying
European affairs in Brno, the country’s
second largest city, and coordinator of a
project that began in 2010. “Until then,
only active members of an institution
like the national children’s and youth
parliament – in other words, young
people already involved in the
democratic process – could express
their opinion,” he adds. But other young
people were left out...
Obviously, Czech youth does not
face the same problems as those in a
country like Uganda, but this does not
mean they are not discriminated
against. “There were a few bad
Young
Czechs
want to have
their say
“Kecejme do toho!” [Let’s chip in!] is a project started by
three young Czechs. Their idea is to give fellow citizens aged
16 to 26 the chance to express their opinion on matters
affecting them directly. It’s a lab for new ideas and a real
step forward for democracy for Czech youth.
MATHIEU PONNARD
experiences...” says Jan. “Some young
people sent round a petition and
demonstrated against a decision that
affected them directly – the
introduction of a new national
baccalaureate. But, even though one of
the priorities of the Czech Republic’s
youth policy is to involve them, the
politicians didn’t even have the grace to
accept the petition! To paraphrase
Shakespeare, I concluded there was
“something rotten in the State of
Denmark” – except it was the Czech
Republic!” It was this incident that led to
the creation of Kecejme do toho – its
founders wanted to show that
politicians can and must accept, at least
out of courtesy, young people’s right to
express their opinion nationally, in
accordance with the principles of
democracy.
Since then, Czech youth has been
asked its opinion on a number of issues
concerning their age-group, their
problems and expectations – ranging
from higher education fees, the right to
vote at 16, hazing and bullying at
school, the legalisation of cannabis, sex
education and jobs for teenagers, to
controversial “baby drop boxes”. Since
2005, Statim, a foundation for
abandoned children, has been installing
these boxes around the Czech Republic
so that desperate mothers can leave
their unwanted babies safely and
discreetly.
Like everywhere else, these young
people, whether unemployed, students
or those with regular jobs, use
Facebook, Twitter and the internet to
communicate and act collectively. 
How does it work?
In practical terms, the young people first
of all vote on a given topic, using
internet and social networks. Kecejme do
toho! then looks at the arguments “for”
and “against” and gathers information
that will be useful later on in discussions
as part of public debates held all over
the country.
During this second stage, the
organizers are happy just to facilitate
the discussion until a common position
is agreed. Through Kecejme do toho!
young volunteers are also invited to
organize these workshops and
discussion groups themselves, in their
classrooms, youth clubs or simply in a
café.
1 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
given direction... But that would not be
democracy. Compromise is
compromise.” Jan is categorical.
“Personally, I see our organization as a
very good school for democracy with
the creation of this compromise
position and its subsequent progress.
But we are still only at an experimental
stage! My original commitment was
based on a theory that made sense...
And I wanted to see if this theory
actually worked in reality. The main
thing is to prove that we live in a
democratic country, that if we do
something, we can obtain results,
educate and prove through positive
example it can work, and we can raise
the level of youth involvement in
national issues.”
A laboratory for democracy
Kecejme do toho! is an independent
organization that receives no funding
from private sponsors or political
parties. It is supported by a platform of
youth NGOs and the Czech Council for
Children and Youth. The organization
has received a promise from the
Ministry of Education, Youth and Sport
that the results of its final conferences
will be taken into account just like an
internal report on youth opinion. “This is
exactly what we wanted,” says Jan,
enthusiastically. “We wanted young
people using the principles of
democracy to be heard by the official
political system and for their opinion to
be considered alongside other points of
view.”
The  Kecejme do toho! experiment  is
receiving support from the European
“Youth in Action” programme and by
the European Commission
representatives in the Czech Republic –
a European dimension that its
coordinator does not disown. “We are
also part of the European Union
‘Structured Dialogue with Young People’
initiative,” he says, “which extends over
18 months and three presidencies
(Spain, Belgium and Hungary), on the
theme of youth employment. We held a
discussion on this subject and prepared
a report with the Ministry to present to
the EU. It was gratifying to see most of
the results of our discussions being
used within the European political
process. Similarly, our results are now
being discussed by the Commission, the
European Parliament, and the United
Nations Economic and Social Council
(ECOSOC)... This is a great source of
satisfaction!”
For the time being, Kecejme do toho!
is still unique, in a country where youth
has always stood up to those in power
and tried to change things. So far, the
organization has linked up only with
partners in Slovakia, to create points of
reference in a neighbouring country.
But this original initiative, involving a
country’s entire youth population,
deserves to be replicated everywhere,
so that a nation’s young people can
have their say on issues that concern
them. ■
Mathieu Ponnard, 34, is a French
journalist currently living in Prague. 
J Poster for European Youth Week, 15 to 21 May 2011
©
 D
R
In a third stage, those young people
who are interested are invited to a
public discussion, alongside politicians
involved in the issue, as well as the head
of a secondary school. Having discussed
the issue with these experts, the young
people are then able to finalize a
common position, which is then put to
the vote over the internet. 
In the final phase, the results of the
vote are presented to the media,
politicians and specialists in a
concluding conference, where the
young people once again have an
opportunity to question the decision
makers. The results are then passed
onto government, members of
parliament and senators. 
“On quite a few issues, my personal
position is not very different to the final
position adopted at the end, and which
is often fairly wide-ranging. Sometimes I
would like to nudge a position in a
©
 w
w
w
.y
o
u
th
w
e
e
k.
e
u
 
©
 C
ze
ch
 C
o
u
n
ci
l o
f 
C
h
ild
re
n
 a
n
d
 Y
o
u
th
L Jan Husak, 23, founder of “Kecejme do toho!”
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 1 7
The main thing is to prove that
we live in a democratic country,
that if we do something, we can
obtain results.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
I grew up in the leafy suburbs of
Johannesburg, and had the privilege of
receiving a private education. Being a
young white learner at a private school
meant that I was somewhat sheltered
from the pain that South Africa was
going through towards the end of
Apartheid, but I cherish, as dearly as all
my fellow South Africans, moments like
Mandela’s release and inauguration and
the World Cup in 2010, that have
defined our new democracy as well as
our national spirit ever since.
I had always imagined starting my
own business, but it wasn’t until after
completing my Bachelor of Business
Science at the University of Cape Town
and spending five years in London’s
corporate world, that Obami was born.
Back then (2007), Obami was an open
and generic social networking site, but
after Facebook opened up beyond its
college networks, I decided to target
Obami to schools. 
Obami is now a social learning
network that provides a communication
and learning platform for teachers,
learners and their parents. It combines
networking tools similar to those found
on sites like Facebook with
comprehensive learning management
tools like those found on Moodle (an
open source learning platform), all from
within a safe environment – it is
intended in large part for children. 
The platform was originally built in
London, but on a trip back to South
Africa in 2008, I made the decision to
move Obami home – if it could work in
Africa, it could (theoretically) work
anywhere. And more importantly, if it
did work, it would make an enormous
social impact in a place that needs it
most.
BARBARA MALLINSON
L A young girl doing school work outside her home in
a South African shanty town.
In 2008, the young South
African Barbara Mallinson,
created Obami, which has
since become the best
friend of pupils in schools
around her country. Neither
black nor white, Obami is
virtual; it is helping to
improve the quality of
education and thus the
quality of life. Obami’s
creator tells her story.
Obami
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
rr
yl
 E
v
a
n
s
1 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
My best friend
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
South Africa, a beautiful nation with
a remarkable mix of rich cultures, still
struggles with socio-political challenges
a full 17 years after the birth of its new
democracy. HIV/AIDS, crime, weak
infrastructure and maladministration
are just some of the reasons why South
Africa is one of the world’s poorest
performing nations with regards to
education standards. In 2010, only
23.5% of leavers qualify for further
education, according to an official
report in January 2011.
At 0.68, South Africa’s Gini
Coefficient is one of the highest in the
world (the figure was published by
Bloomberg agency on 25 February
2011). As this coefficient can vary from 0
to 1 with 0 representing perfect equality
of incomes, the figure is an alarming
sign reflecting a nation of great
extremes. Unskilled labour is in
abundance, while skilled labour –
especially in the medical, engineering,
IT, financial and technical fields – is in
severe shortage due to major
underperformance of mathematics and
science within the education sector. This
has only been further amplified by
South Africa’s “Brain Drain” endemic,
where a sizeable proportion of the
country’s professional workers have
emigrated over the past two decades.
Using Obami
It’s an ominous situation, one that can
only be resolved from the bottom up.
My vision was, and still is, to use Obami
in bringing about social change,
starting with education. 
Obami supports three critical areas
of education: resource distribution,
teaching and learning practices, as well
as performance measurement. Teachers
can create, share and access educational
resources using rich media content
tools, while the latest web 2.0 enhanced
interfaces (using Ajax technologies, for
instance) facilitate interaction and
collaboration between and amongst
them, the learners and the learners’
parents, using the model of blogs and
social media. The system also
incorporates an assessment application
for the continual measurement of a
learner’s performance.
I have striven to offer Obami to
schools for free. My motivation for
doing so? So that each and every child
can one day access a quality education
through Obami, no matter what
background they come from. Costs are
currently being supported through
private funding, and I have been
fortunate to receive valuable support in
the form of free hosting from the
country’s biggest Internet Service
Provider, Internet Solutions. I am also
collaborating with existing NGOs in the
schools sector – Edunova, who provide
Information and Communication
Technology (ICT) training to
underprivileged communities, and
Siyavula, who create high quality
educational resources. 
Challenges
However, I am also very aware of the
challenges I am taking on. Besides the
personal sacrifices that my husband
(who now works alongside me) and I
have made in running our own
business, Obami faces significant
external factors. The very market that
stands to benefit the most from Obami
lacks infrastructure and internet
accessibility. In 2009, only 23% of South
Africa’s 25,000 government schools had
a computer centre, and it is estimated
that today, less than 20% of all public
schools are connected to the internet. 
In stark contrast, nearly all of South
Africa’s 2,000 private schools were set
up with connected computer facilities. It
made natural sense for me to target
Obami’s offering to the independent
education sector at first. My strategy: to
capture the small, but highly connected
group of schools, here and abroad, and
leverage their competitive advantages
(i.e. skilled teachers, quality educational
resources, etc) for the good of all.
Already, less privileged schools have
been able to quickly access quality
educational resources created by others
through the platform.
But even in reaching the most
connected of schools, Obami has faced
difficulties. Schools are yet to embrace
the web 2.0 revolution like social,
business and niche communities have,
perhaps because of online safety
concerns – school decision makers have
a responsibility to act as gatekeepers to
what is unknown territory. It has taken
me time to convince them of Obami’s
social learning relevance and its
commitment to providing a safe
environment. Now that the product is
proving itself, with more than 40
registered schools, things have become
easier.
As for connectivity, change is
happening within the continent.
SEACOM, Main One, EASSy, and WACS,
all undersea cable systems connecting
Africa to the digital highway, are set to
exponentially boost Africa’s connectivity
and bring internet access costs down.
Mobile currently dominates Africa’s
internet access mediums, and will
continue as such – it is a giant
developing consumer market. For
schools though, falling hardware costs
(through increased cloud computing
services), will provide a real chance of
being able to set up technology centres
and bridge the digital (and educational)
gap. 
Obami was awarded a spot as one of
the world’s Top 10 Most Innovative
Technologies for 2011 by French
organisation Netexplorateur, in
partnership with UNESCO, Air France,
Deloitte, Orange and a number of other
large organisations, and I was pleased to
have been selected as one of the “Top
200 Young People to Take to Lunch” in
2010 by one of South Africa’s
newspapers, the Mail & Guardian. It’s
always an honour to receive recognition
for Obami – even though it still has so
much further to go. Every milestone
that Obami reaches will only aid in the
quest to improve education standards
and connect more schools across the
continent with rest of the world. ■
K Barbara Manlinson, now 30, is the creator of
Obami, a networking platform for South African
schools.
©
 A
ll 
ri
g
h
ts
 r
e
se
rv
e
d
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 1 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
“Ladj Ly, as seen by JR”. From the series
“Portrait of a generation” and reprinted by
courtesy of JR, specifically to illustrate this
article.  
It is 1997 in the Democratic Republic
of the Congo. A young boy is working
in the fields alongside his brothers.
Armed men appear out of nowhere.
His brothers run faster than he does.
He is taken away. He is made to wear
a uniform and smoke cannabis; he is
given a gun and ordered to shoot. He
obeys, as if playing a game of war. His
name is Serge Amisi, and, today, he is
a young man of about 25 – he doesn’t
know the exact year he was born.
Demobilized in 2001, on the death of
DRC president Laurent-Désiré Kabila,
Serge felt lost. It was hard to get back
into civilian life, but, luckily, he
discovered his talents as an artist. He
was able to regain his inner freedom.
He started a new life. Today, Serge
wants to help the 200,000 – 300,000
child soldiers worldwide to do the
same. He dances with his puppets,
makes sculptures and writes – for
himself, for them and for us all.
You were not even 10 years old when
you were taken away and forced to
fight with Laurent-Désiré Kabila’s army.
Up until 2001 you were a child soldier, a
kadogo. How do you look back on this
period?
The image I have of the war is nothing
like the way I saw it at the time. When I
was taken away, I was scared. We were
separated from our families and I soon
understood that they would not let us
see our loved ones again. Although we
were children, we were expected to give
our lives for the nation. I got into the
rhythm of the army and got used to the
people and the life there. 
We didn’t know anything about
politics. We were simply taught warfare
and to obey orders. We became soldiers.
We saw ourselves as belonging to the
same family and had a lot of fun.
Serge Amisi and his
SERGE AMISI was interviewed by
Selen Demir
* Les armes miraculeuses (Miracle weapons) is the
title of a collection of poetry by the Martinican poet
Aimé Césaire (1913 – 2008). ©
 jr
-a
rt
.n
e
t
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
You had fun! Weren’t you afraid you
would be killed?
We knew we were going to die, but
sometimes we thought death was for
the dying, not for us. We smoked joints
and saw ourselves as actors in a
Schwarzenegger film, as if death weren't
real. We were the stars of the army,
because the adults found the child-
soldiers very entertaining.
But we missed being able to play.
They paid my wages, but I had nothing
to spend it on, except maybe some toy
soldiers. |And when the war started
again I put my uniform back on and got
ready to play at fighting for real. 
I learned to live without fear or
humility. I couldn’t live like that today.
When I see myself in the army, it’s as if I
am looking from the outside. I don’t
recognize that child, because I am so
different now.
Did you have dreams, or did you stop
yourself from even thinking about
them?
We didn’t have time to think. We didn’t
think about the future. We didn’t even
think we might grow up one day. We
were there to fight in the war, and that’s
all there was to it. 
What do you think about the soldiers
who forced you to fight and who
continue to do the same thing to other
children today?
At the time we thought we were helping
the nation and were fans of President
Kabila. He was like a father for us and we
liked him a lot. We didn’t particularly
blame the soldiers, as they had given us
a power over adults that children do not
usually have. We were always competing
to see who was the strongest. The
civilian world was unknown to us. We
had power, why let it go?
I still don’t know enough about
politics to understand why the war
started and why these soldiers took us
away. But I do know that if you love your
country, you have to protect the
children. Who will free the country from
war if the children spend all their time in
the army? I am not angry, but I do not
agree with the soldiers either. I feel sorry
for them, more than anything. They
don’t know what they are doing. 
miracle weapons
Today you can see that you were being
manipulated. Do you feel you’ve freed
yourself from this military
programming?
I found it hard to get back into civilian life.
I was demobilized in 2001 and became a
civilian again. But I still thought like a
soldier. It is thanks to the Espace Masolo [a
resource centre for artists and
craftspeople, set up in Kinshasa in 2003,
the capital of the Democratic Republic of
Congo, by the Congolese artists Malvine
Velo, Hubert Mahela and Lamber
Mousseka] that I learned how to get
along better with other people. That’s
where I discovered art and found my
freedom and independence again.
During the war you were a musical
entertainer much appreciated by your
comrades. Did singing help you put up
with the situation?
Yes, I loved to sing and make people
laugh. Before the army, my elder
brothers used to sing me songs and tell
“People say we are war children, child-soldiers, kadogos, but we were
children in the war. I didn’t want to be in the war, I was made to carry
a gun, and I no longer had my parents or my family, I only had the
army and my gun, my gun that I was told was my mother and father.”
Serge Amisi, Souvenez-vous de moi, l'enfant de demain, Vents d’ailleurs, 2011
K Scene from a performance of “Congo my body” at
the Parc de la Villette in Paris (France), in 2010 
©
 2
0
1
0
 E
n
ri
c
o
 B
a
rt
o
lu
c
c
i /
 E
P
P
G
H
V
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
stories. In the army, some of the soldiers
had children that they missed. They used
to call on me to lift their spirits. My little
voice and child’s size made them laugh. I
was a kind of mini-star all on my own,
which made some of the other child
soldiers jealous. I loved to act and could
imagine myself as an artist.
What art forms do you use today?
I am a dancer, puppeteer and sculptor. I
have an idea for a solo project where I
combine all three art forms. Meanwhile, I
put on a play [Congo My Body] with my
friend Yaoundé Mulamba, who I knew
before the army and who was a child
soldier with me. In the past few years we
have played in different places in Europe
and DRC. I still can’t earn a living from
art, but I hope to find a studio where I
can work. I also have other projects,
simply as an artist, not as an ex-child-
soldier, and I am in contact with youth
groups in Mozambique and Germany.
How did you feel about performing in
front of other people when you first
started as an artist? Were you afraid?
I was afraid I would shock people and not
be able to deal with that. I was even afraid
I’d be threatened or judged. When I came
to France at the end of 2008, I suddenly
felt shocked by my own past and I started
to think about it a lot. I had the impression
I was reliving everything in my head. Now
I feel more at peace and avoid thinking
too much about it so that I can move on. If
I could have, I wouldn’t have gone to fight
in the war. I try not to feel guilty, by telling
myself that it was not my fault, that the
adults forced me to go and drugged me. I
have managed to distance myself from all
of that with the help of a few people who
have given me a lot of support. One day I
was given some notebooks and I started
to write my life story, just for myself. 
Last March, your book, Souvenez-vous
de moi, l’enfant de demain [Remember
me, tomorrow’s child], came out in
France, published by Vents d’ailleurs.
What message do you want to pass on to
today’s young people?
I published this book [using the notes he
wrote in Lingala in the notebooks
between 2004 and 2008] to leave a
record of what happened and to show
young people what I went through as a
child and what others went through or
are still going through in other parts of
the world. This could be useful to them. ■
Serge Amisi was interviewed in April 2011 in the Courier office by Selen Demir, 18, 
a French-Turkish student at the University of Paris IV (France). This is her first magazine
interview.
Locked in the cycle of violence
Some 28 million children are deprived of education because of armed conflict
around the world. “Armed conflict remains a major roadblock to human
development in many parts of the world, yet its impact on education is widely
neglected,” said UNESCO Director-General Irina Bokova. War destroys not only
schools and educational infrastructure, but also the hope and ambitions of
whole generations.
The 2011 Education for All Global Monitoring Report “The hidden crisis:
Armed conflict and education” points out that the problem is not only the
conflict itself, but also what comes along with it. 
Children drop out of school or their parents forbid them to go. There are
constant threats to children and teachers in and outside school boundaries. The
younger generation is terrorized, raped and kidnapped. Many abducted children
are put into the armed forces to fight. If they want to live and see their families
again, they have to go and kill. Rape is often used as a war tactic and in certain
countries the young are particularly targeted because they are defenseless.
“I was just coming back home from the river to fetch water,” says Minova, 15,
South Kivu, Democratic Republic of the Congo. “Two soldiers came up to me
and told me that if I refuse to sleep with them, they will kill me. They beat me
and ripped my clothes. One of the soldiers raped me. …My parents spoke to a
commander and he said that his soldiers do not rape, and that I am lying. I
recognized the two soldiers, and I know that one of them is called Edouard.”
(Human Rights Watch, 2009). 
While it is evident that armed conflicts undermine education, it is less
obvious that the failures of education can fuel conflicts. Yet an educational
system that fails to provide young people with the knowledge and skills to
avoid unemployment and poverty,  as well as the requisite tools to learn “living
together” and respect for other people, becomes an underground source of
hatred and discord.
Mila Zourleva, 22, Bulgarian student and intern, UNESCO Division of Public
Information
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
2 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
It isn’t a place exactly. Technically it
would be defined as an event. More
accurately it could be described as a
community. Perhaps though it would be
best characterized as a spirit that for
almost three weeks at the close of
winter each year inhabits a growing
number of educators, students, poets,
and spectators throughout the
Chicagoland area. It’s Louder Than a
Bomb, the Chicago Youth Poetry
Festival.
Louder Than a Bomb (LTaB) started
in 2001 as a poetry slam of 8 high
schools in what co-founder Kevin Coval
can only describe as a “rat-infested
basement.” By the time I began
competing in Louder Than a Bomb as a
13 year old the competition had grown
to 15 teams (mine being the only team
representing a middle school).  It was in
The marquee event of LTaB is still
the poetry slam. A poetry slam is an
Olympic-style poetry contest where
writers present original work without
the aid of music or props. The slam is,
by nature, ridiculously subjective in its
judging and there is a saying at LTaB
that the best poets never win. While to
many outside of the community this
sounds like an egregious injustice, the
secret of the slam is that it is a gimmick.
Slam uses the ruse of competition to
elevate the visibility of the art and voice
of young people. 
Poetry against segregation
This work would be important in any
place but in the city of Chicago it is an
essential labor. Chicago is a remarkably
segregated city. In the city Dr. Martin
Luther King once called “the northern
most racist city” there is still a culture that
rarely puts people of different racial or
socioeconomic backgrounds in the same
Creating community in a city notorious in the past for segregation, elevating the visibility
of young people’s art and voice, filling the silence of misunderstanding…. These are a few
of the achievements of the poetry slam with the resounding name of Louder Than a Bomb,
where Chicago’s budding poets get together. 
NATE MARSHALL
When
poetry
2003 and I vividly remember walking
into the opening event of the weekend,
an event known as “Crossing the Street”
and seeing a life-altering scene. Inside
the dark room I saw teenagers of all
colors gathered around in celebration of
themselves. The air was filled with the
smell of free pizza and the thump of hip-
hop music and I was mesmerized by the
energy in the room.
The part of the scene that most
drew me was a large and growing circle
of students in the background. As I
bordered on the outskirts of the group I
heard the voices of young people
rhyming. More than simply reciting
memorized lyrics they were
spontaneously composing raps, songs,
and chants. As I watched this freestyle
cipher for a few minutes, I was struck by
the radical democracy of the circle.
Everybody who wanted an opportunity
to rhyme got one. Skill was the only
measure by which everyone was judged. 
Poet, rapper and essayist Nate
Marshall, 21, reciting his work
at the poetry slam “Louder
Than a Bomb” in Chicago
(USA). 
© Siskel/Jacobs Productions
is louder than a bomb
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 2 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
room. LTaB’s demographic is so bizarre
because it defies the tendency towards
the monolith that is ever present in
Chicago. LTaB does important work every
year bringing students from all different
types of backgrounds to gather, listen,
and learn from themselves and each
other. 
Chicago’s literary legacy is an
enviable one and that is evident in the
work of the students. To hear a student
like Kush Thompson from the troubled
Orr High School on the West Side of
Chicago speak passionately about the
unfair body images that a “Mattel
branded” (makers of the Barbie doll,
notably) society propagates is an
amazing thing. It’s even more amazing to
see her share the stage with students
from marquee magnet schools and
wealthy suburban schools that can
identify with her story. This discovery of
commonality among students is creating
a new culture in the city. 
Even as Chicago in the past few years
has experienced a rash of youth violence
LTaB has remained an amazing example
of safe space. In 10 years of operation
LTaB has never experienced a violent
incident, even as they draw students from
across the invisible yet very real lines that
separate different neighborhoods and
gang territories. Despite the increasingly
steep competition, which now includes
over 70 teams and 30 individual poets,
the spirit of community remains intact at
LTaB. The cipher is still one of the most
common occurrences at LTaB and it is not
uncommon after a bout to see the
competing teams trading notes and
laughs at a local fried chicken restaurant.
Bomb debris
In 2007 US filmmakers Greg Jacobs and
Jon Siskel noticed this spirit. During the
next year they followed three individuals
and one team on their journey in
preparation for LTaB. I was lucky to be
among those they decided to follow.
From the hundreds of hours of footage
they built a documentary film to offer a
glimpse into the lives of a few students
and the way in which the slam has been a
life-shifting experience for the young
people involved. 
The documentary has garnered
positive reviews from famed film critic
Roger Ebert, Variety Magazine, and the LA
Times among others. Film festivals across
the U.S. and Canada have selected
“Louder Than a Bomb” and it has won
awards at many, including Palm Springs,
Chicago, and Austin. The film will be aired
in the fall of 2011 nationally on the Oprah
Winfrey Network as a part of her
documentary of the month club. The LTaB
film has even inspired an offshoot event
in Tulsa, Oklahoma. In April of 2011 I was
able to travel to Tulsa with Kevin Coval to
help organize the first annual LTaB Tulsa. 
Erika Dickerson, 2009 LTaB All-Star,
loves the platform of the festival as an
opportunity to “build community and
network with one another as well as
professional artists.” Cydney Edwards, a
two-time LTaB All-Star, said “Louder Than
a Bomb was a venue for me to align
“If you’re not here during the
first week of May, then you’re
not in best place. Louder Than a
Bomb is the coolest place on
the planet. “
Adam Gottlieb, contestant from 
2005 to 2008
Nate Marshall, 21, is a poet, rapper
and essayist. Main character in the
award-winning feature-length
documentary “Louder Than a Bomb”, he
was a finalist of the Chicago Literary
Guild’s Gwendolyn  Brooks Open Mic
Award 2010. His work has been
published in several poetry
anthologies. He is finishing his BA in
English and Afro-American studies at
Vanderbilt University in Nashville (USA).
myself with peers of mine from all over
Chicago and mold my craft.”  These
students, some of the champions of the
slam, represent the small section of the
participants who will pursue their literary
art as a career. For so many other
students, there is less focus on craft, but
that is perfectly fine. Louder Than a Bomb
produces great art, and elevates that art
in ways that it would not be otherwise,
but the most pressing work that LTaB
does is elevate young people. By
empowering them to use their words and
listen to each other, LTaB empowers
students to analyze and challenge the
world that they live in and its injustices
and shortcomings. As 2011 LTaB Indy
Slam Champion Malcolm London said
about the work of the festival, “this
doesn’t stop at LTaB.” These students
create community where segregation
existed for their parents. They fill the
dangerous silence of misunderstanding
with a symphony of stories. 
The power of LTaB is that sense of the
story, that sense of imagination, and
student using it to tell a willing audience
about the world they live while
empowering them to build the world
they dream. ■
L Scene from the film “Louder Than a Bomb”.
©
  C
ou
rt
es
y 
of
 S
is
ke
l/
Ja
co
b
s 
Pr
od
uc
ti
on
s
2 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
L Poster from the latest Louder Than a Bomb event.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Different
dreams, yet...
They come from different countries, have different occupations, speak different languages,
yet they have much in common: youth, art, a desire to connect with other cultures. Until
recently, they’d never even met: UNESCO brought them together. They were awarded the
title of “Young Artist for Intercultural Dialogue between Arab and Western Worlds”. Among
them, Betty Shamieh (USA/Occupied Palestinian Territory), Merlijn Twaalfhoven
(Netherlands) and two members of the Talent 2008 project, Ingebjørg Bratland (Norway) and
Majd Shahin (Occupied Palestinian Territory) answered our questions to share their
convictions, projects and passions with our readers.
Interview conducted by Iris Julia Bührle and Khaled Abu Hijleh 
View of the Morro da
Providencia favela in
Rio de Janeiro, Brazil,
with photos from JR's
August 2008 project
“Women are Heroes”
covering walls. 
© Courtesy of JR:
http://jr-art.net/ 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 2 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
How can the artist contribute to
building peace and mutual
understanding between people around
the world?
Betty Shamieh: Artists illuminate the
common humanity that we all share.
What is wonderful about theatre is that it
shows us how similar we are, not only
across the globe but throughout
generations. It shows us not only how we
should coexist peacefully, but also why.
When one sees a work of art, particularly
a work of theatre where a story that was
written in the time of the Greeks still has
resonance today, it becomes clear that
we do have a recognizable but
indefinable human essence. 
Ingebjørg Bratland: I think that music is
the language of the heart and when we
do not speak the same language, we can
communicate through music. The world
can sometimes seem very violent, so it is
great to come together and play music,
which is something that we are
passionate about. It is a break from the
world that we are living in, a kind of free
space. 
Majd Shahin: Music is the language of
the nations. I think music is the way to
make other people understand what you
are and what you feel. 
Merlijn Twaalfhoven: In my projects, I
usually avoid to use the word “peace”
because the term is surrounded by many
expectations, but also by moments of
disappointment or even frustration.
However, you can reflect about what are
conditions for peace. In my opinion, one
condition for peace is contact between
people. Therefore, I wanted to stimulate
contact and make people curious. Art is
an excellent way to make people curious,
not to give answers but to create
openings. When something is open,
when something is not exactly fixed,
people want to continue because they
want to learn more and look for the
truth. And that is what I believe can be a
condition for a road to peace and
understanding. I am happy when I leave
a place and people have many questions.
What kind of difficulties you have
faced in your projects? How did you
overcome them?
B.S.: One difficulty when you deal with
challenging subjects is that you need to
be able to not fully articulate your
And by doing that it became clear. But I
made many mistakes on the road by
making it too complex and by
expecting others to have the same
dreams. Everyone has different dreams
but once you start realizing, once you
just start doing, then people get
inspired and feel connections. 
How do you define your role as an
artist in the social and political life of
your own country?
B.S.: I think the role of the artist in any
society is to inspire. What I hope to
inspire in the people in the country
where I live, which is America, is a real
desire to be a citizen of the world, a
desire to know about other cultures and
to see different perspectives. 
When you live between two
cultures, it is also very important to
show the similarities between them.
Many works of Western artists about the
Middle East, for instance, focus on the
plight of women. I live in America where
women also have little political,
economic and artistic power. Therefore,
I feel that one of the things I need to do
as an artist is to talk about how women’s
situations across the globe are similar
because it is very easy to look at other
cultures, but people sometimes forget
to look at their own. As I live in two
worlds, it makes me question how
different cultures really are at their base.
M.S.: My country, Palestine, has a lot of
messages and a lot of dreams that we
want to send to the whole world. I think
that in my music I can do this. Of course
the messages are different inside and
outside Palestine. Outside, you have to
clarify a lot of things about your
country; inside, you have to support the
people. The reactions to this have been
quite different, but I feel proud of my
country’s cultural richness which I can
show to the world.
I.B.: Outside we only hear about
Palestine in connection to war, and it is
great that we see that there is music
also and that people are living lives in
Palestine. I myself as a folk musician in
Norway think that it is important that
there are young people continuing the
tradition of Norwegian folk music
because folk music has to be kept alive.
M.T.: As an artist, I hope to confuse and
to break the surface. People have a
perspective. Sometimes artists avoid
controversial issues because they think
they have to have answers or that they
have to be able to speak in a way that
no one can find fault with. I think that
artists should feel free to be wrong from
time to time. 
The other thing that I often face is
that people just assume that they know
my politics. My dream is that one day
the Middle East will look like the
European Union. Of course most people
immediately say that this is impossible
and then I remind them of the situation
in Europe one hundred years ago –
within the last century, Europe has had
two World Wars and countries were
occupying each other and tearing each
other apart. I want to challenge the
belief that we cannot change in the
Middle East. 
I.B.: The only problem for me was the
language. Some of the artists from
Egypt and Palestine did not speak much
English, and it can be a bit tough to
come together and make music when
you cannot communicate with words.
So we just had to use the music and
play!
M.S.: I did not have any problems with
the language and to cooperate with
musicians from other parts of the world,
but the music was a challenge. I am a
percussionist and for me it is difficult to
play a Norwegian song because the
beats are totally different from the
Oriental beats I usually play. But it has
been a very good experience!
M.T.: The difficulty in my work is that
when you want to do something
unconventional and you want to
convince others to go with you to an
unknown territory, then people do not
have the same idea in their minds as
you. In Cyprus, for example, I talked a lot
about the unity of the island and about
connecting both sides (north and south,
which are separate states) by music and
people did not know what I wanted and
what was my political agenda… So
finally I abandoned all my theories and I
just said: let’s go on the rooftop and
play music and listen to the other side.
2 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
I think that artists should feel free
to be wrong from time to time. 
Betty Shamieh
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
strong need to make the world around
them very clear and to put labels, and
after that it is very hard to change their
minds. So I believe confusion is needed
so that people realize that the labels do
not always fit and start looking what is
behind them. 
It is a privilege that I can go to
places about which I am curious, but it is
also important that I let others follow
me. If I travel to Syria it is a great
experience for me, but I try to find ways
that through my projects people in the
Western world can also travel a bit to
Syria. I feel that I have to share this
curiosity; it is not only for myself. 
I meet many artists in Holland who
are very focused just on the quality of
making music, but most people do not
ask whether they could use their quality
as a tool for making the world better.
Thanks to UNESCO, I have met more
people who think not only about art,
but also about art inside the world and
what it might change.
What are your plans in the near future,
after having won the UNESCO award?
M.T.: This recognition is very important
for me because my work takes place
outside concert halls or festivals or
programmes of orchestras. I do it on my
own with a small organization or with
freelancers, and with hardly any budget.
Sometimes I obtain media attention and
that is important, but as it is not inside
the infrastructure of culture my work is
hard to label, and therefore it is difficult
to find support and partners. Such a title
gives some clarity to the fact that I am
doing this type of work and that it has
some positive results. I also hope that the
next years I can follow up on the projects
that I started – for instance Al Quds
Underground in East Jerusalem. What I
have done so far is just a beginning!
B.S.: This title was incredibly meaningful
for me. It was the first time in my life that
I felt that both my Palestinian and
American origin were recognized; thus,
UNESCO has acknowledged the
complexity of identity. In addition to
continuing to develop as an artist,
I would like to support the efforts of the
late Juliano Mer Khamis (Israeli actor and
K Group photo taken at the nomination ceremony for “Young Artists for Intercultural Dialogue between Arab
and Western Worlds” on 13 April 2011 at UNESCO.
UNESCO’s young artists
Twenty-four artists aged under 35 were awarded the title of “Young Artist for
Intercultural Dialogue between Arab and Western Worlds” by UNESCO Director-
General, Irina Bokova, at a ceremony held at the Organization’s headquarters on 13
April 2011.This honour recognizes the exceptional contribution to dialogue and
exchange between Arab and Western cultures made by:
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l 
R
a
v
a
ss
a
rd
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 2 7
Ruti Sela and Mayaan Amir (Israel), artists and curators, designed the ‘Exterritory’
project as a way to bring together artists and intellectuals living in conflict zones,
especially Israel and the Occupied Palestinian Territory.
Sidi Larbi Cherkaoui (Belgium/Morocco), dancer and choreographer, has
produced performances that illustrate the meeting of cultures and explorations of
identity.   
Federico Ferrone (Italy), filmmaker, has produced several films on immigration,
suburbs and the contribution of immigrant communities to a country’s culture.   
Faïza Guène (France/Algeria), novelist, whose highly acclaimed writings portray
reality for those of North African descent living in French suburbs, and counter
clichés and prejudice.   
JR (France), photographer, is behind the ‘Face2Face’ project, which consists of
posting photographs side by side of Israelis and Palestinians doing the same jobs.   
Ibrahim Maalouf (Lebanon), trumpeter, mixes Western and Eastern musical styles
and works with artists from all over the world.     
‘Massar Egbari’ (Egypt), musicians, launched the ‘Music as a means of intercultural
dialogue’ project, inviting Western artists to share the stage in concerts.    
Betty Shamieh (USA/ Occupied Palestinian Territory), playwright, has written
plays that highlight intercultural relations, especially between Arabs and
Americans.  
Zuhal Sultan (Iraq), pianist, who, at the age of 17, founded the National Youth
Orchestra of Iraq, which works with several Western artists.   
The ‘Talent 2008’ project brings together nine young musicians playing traditional
European and Arab music (Occupied Palestinian Territory, Egypt, Norway). 
Merlijn Twaalfhoven (Netherlands), composer and musician, has started some
exceptional projects in Jordan, the Occupied Palestinian Territory, Syria and the
Netherlands, using music to create links and thus serving as a symbol of peace. 
As an artist, I hope to confuse
and to break the surface.
Merlijn Twaalfhoven 
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
An imam, a minister and a rabbi strike playful poses,
as part of the 2007 “Face 2 Face” project by
JR and Marco, who covered walls with portraits of
Israelis and Palestinians working at the
same jobs.© Courtesy of JR: http://jr-art.net/ 
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
theatre director, assassinated on 4 April
2011) who did wonderful work in Jenin.
We must not allow violence to scare us
away from continuing to do work and
continuing to aspire for the kind of future
that everybody deserves.
I.B.: I would love to visit other countries
and learn about their folk music. I think
that traditional music is a particularly
good way to learn about other cultures,
even better than classical music which
has become more universal. And in my
opinion, you have to visit the country
and to see how people live there and
how they play and use their folk music. I
also use some of the things that I have
learned from Arabic music and make
them a part of my own music.
Furthermore, as we have been in Egypt
and in Norway with the Talent project, it
would be great to visit Palestine as well
and do concerts there! 
Iris Julia Bührle, 29, is a German art
historian and also a specialist in
comparative literature. She has written
numerous articles and scholarly papers
on dance, literature and history
(including a thesis on France and
UNESCO from 1945 to1958). 
M.S.: I will also continue my path as a
Palestinian folk musician inside and
outside my country. The UNESCO title
encourages me and gives me a push to
take a step forward in my music life. It is
great to find people that understand
and appreciate your art. I was so
surprised when I met the other artists
who were attributed the title and saw
the other projects – you feel you are not
alone! There are people from
everywhere trying to do what you do. ■
JR, Art and the Impossible
JR, who took the photographs
illustrating this article, is a member
of the UNESCO young artists group.
This 28-year-old French ‘urban
artivist’ (sic) claims to have the
largest gallery in the world – the
street!
In 2001, JR began clandestinely
pasting onto the facades of Parisian
buildings photocopies of the
snapshots he was taking of his
friends doing graffiti on the
rooftops. His subjects quickly
became more diverse while the
images grew bigger, reaching 6 x 8
metres in 2004 with his “Portrait of a
Generation”, which made him
famous. That year he also exhibited
in the streets of New York, Los
Angeles, Paris and the Cité des
Bosquets social housing estate in
Montfermeil, a disadvantaged Paris
suburb.
In March 2007, with Marco, he
staged Face 2 Face, “the biggest
photo exhibition ever”. They posted,
side by side, giant portraits of
Israelis and Palestinians doing the
same jobs in several towns in Israel
and the Palestinian Territories. “Face
2 Face demonstrated that what we
thought impossible was possible,
even easy,” he said on 2 March 2011
at the TED prize awards ceremony in
Long Beach (USA)
(www.tedprize.org). 
In 2008 and 2009 his Women Are
Heroes project took him to Kenya,
Brazil, India and Cambodia. In spring
2011, he rushed to Tunisia to cover
police stations and political party
headquarters with photos, as part of
the Inside Out project. In 10 years, he
has achieved what we thought was
impossible. And he makes it all seem
so easy! – J. Šopova
See JR’s website: www.jr-art.net
K Staircase in the Morro da Providencia favela in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, covered with a photo from JR's August
2008 “Women are Heroes” project. 
©
C
o
u
rt
e
sy
 o
f 
JR
: h
tt
p
:/
/j
r-
a
rt
.n
e
t/
 The world can sometimes
seem very violent, so it is great
to come together and play
music, which is something
that we are passionate about.
Ingebjørg Bratland
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
What could be better than to plant a
tree that feeds the villagers while, at the
same time, it provides the material to
waterproof the tatas ? 
Working under the umbrella of the
Togolese NGO FAGAD (Frères
agriculteurs et artisans pour le
développement) and supported by the
Patrimonito project and CCIVS, these
young World Heritage volunteers have
identified and planted various
endangered plant species used in the
construction of the tatas. Within two
years, the site acquired 1,050 new trees
in a 2000 m2 area. A first step, providing
the necessary materials to restore the
tatas using traditional methods. 
But besides the tangible aspects of
Tamberma culture – another name for
the Batammariba – the volunteers
wanted to help preserve its intangible
aspects too, by becoming associated
with the first Tamberma Festival, from
26 to 30 March 2011. “This is the first
year the Festamber festival has been
held,” explains Atti Y. Tata, a 23-year-old
Togolese man who runs a camp that
hosted seven volunteers this year. “We
were very excited at the idea of taking
part in this new initiative, which
showcases the richness of our local
culture, languages, crafts and farm
products.”  These jewels, along with the
tatas, make Togo a stop not to be
missed on a cultural tourist’s itinerary in
West Africa. “For people who do not
know anything about this culture, which
was my case, this festival is a very good
way to get immersed in it in just a week,”
enthuses Linda Gustafssona, 24-year-old
Swedish volunteer. “I really hope it will
keep going, because it also gives the
Tamberma an opportunity to appreciate
the wealth of the Koutammakou site in
a new way.”
Based in Adeta, the young
volunteers were not daunted by the 400
km journey to Koutammakou. With no
vehicle at their disposal, they did the
best they could: “We travelled by taxi,
bus or motorbike, depending on the
state of the roads,” says Atti. Indeed, the
project is still a work in progress. “We
were supposed to help with
preparations for the festival, but by the
time we got there, there was hardly
anything left to do,” says Linda. But even
if it takes time to build up momentum,
what counts is the will to discover and
simply to get involved. ■
Patrimonito, a cartoon character representing a young
guardian of world heritage, made his appearance in 1995.
He is the mascot of World Heritage volunteers, taking his
young companions to Africa, Latin America, Asia and
Europe. The young volunteers take part in the preservation
and appreciation of emblematic World Heritage sites,
under the supervision of the World Heritage Centre and the
CCIVS*. 
K Atti Y. Tata, in  Koutammakou (Togo).
* CCIVS – Coordinating Committee for International
Voluntary Service
If the hundred-year-old tata mud
houses of Togo had arms, they would
reach out to hug these young people,
just like grandmothers hugging their
grandchildren. For the past four years
volunteers from Togo, Sweden, Japan,
and South Korea have been meeting up
in Koutammakou, a World Heritage site
in northeast Togo, to look after these
fragile old ladies. 
The tatas – traditional, tower-
flanked mud houses – seem to embody
all the wisdom of the Batammariba
people. But they are crumbling under
the weight of modernisation, with its
quick and easy building codes. And
Nature is not helping them either,
leaving a sad scene of collapsed houses
after the rainy season in August and
September. And even the Nere tree,
whose bark is used to make whitewash
for the walls of the tatas, is becoming
scarce.
That is where the young volunteers
decided to start. Just like the tree,
whose symbolic name means “it is
good” in Bambara, and whose roots
sometimes reach 60 feet underground
to find water and provide a harvest of
fruits packed with goodness, these
young people also went to the source.
Patrimonito
in Togo
KATERINA MARKELOVA
©
U
N
E
S
C
O
 P
h
o
to
b
a
n
k
© UNESCO
©
A
ll 
ri
g
h
ts
 r
e
se
rv
e
d
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Building citizenship. That’s how I
define my experience as a United
Nations volunteer. I recently
participated in the campaign “Unite to
end violence against women”
launched by the United Nations
Secretary-General. I helped set up
discussions on several social networks
to make Bolivians more aware of this
serious problem. One lesson I learned
from this recent six-month experience
- young volunteers are extremely
committed and professional. We are
young professionals who are eager to
learn and to help build social justice.
creativityWonders of
Youth volunteering can achieve so
much. Offer young people role models
and inspire them with a new outlook,
and their creativity pays dividends.
Take youth seriously, give them
responsibility and a place in society
based on trust, and they excel.
Volunteering empowers young
people to act and change the world
around them. In 2010, the United
Nations volunteering programme
deployed in 132 countries nearly 8,000
people from 158 countries. It
mobilized another 10,000 volunteers
who contributed to development
through the on-line volunteering
service. About 62% of them were from
developing countries and 80% were
young people between the ages of 18
and 35.
The year 2011 marks the 10th
anniversary of the International Year of
Volunteers. It is also the European Year
of Volunteering- yet another reason for
young people to exercise their right to
community participation. ■
United Nations Volunteers site: http://www.unv.org/en.html
Kenyan Scout Josephat Gitonga,
28, takes community service very
seriously. He treats it almost as a
“sacred duty”, which has earned him
recognition from the Kenya Scouts
Association and the job of director
of the Scout centre in his town,
Embu, located about 120 km
northeast of Nairobi. Passionate and
hardworking, Josephat threw
himself into this adventure by
reaching 200% of the objectives!
With the support of his Norwegian
counterparts, he succeeded in
opening the centre to the
community and making it practically
autonomous financially, though a
hostel and restaurant micro-project
that also created jobs.
Initially the centre planned to
hold only occasional scouting
activities. But Josephat dreamed of
turning Embu into a global village.
Never had the international Moots –
the big meetings of the oldest group
of Scouts, age 18 to 25 – been
organized in Africa. It was time to
take action.
Relying on the experience that
built his reputation among Scouts all
the way to Asia and Latin America,
Josephat quickly persuaded the
Kenya Scouts Association to
nominate his town as one of the
three Kenyan locations for the 13th
World Scout Moot (27 July-7 August
2010). The dream became reality:
more than 1,000 young world
citizens arrived in Embu, which had
never known so much friendship,
laughter and brotherhood as well as
discussion on today’s major
challenges. ■
Pierre Arlaud, Swiss student, 25;
Representative, External Relations at
the World Organization of the Scout
Movement. worldbureau@scout.org
Volunteering is perfect for tapping
into the idealism and drive of young
people. Despite appearances, our lack of
experience due to our young age is an
easily overcome obstacle. In addition to
its social value, community participation
through volunteering can be a means
for us young people to get our first
experience in the ethical principles on
which the dignity of individuals and
societies depend. This kind of
participation turns us into solution
makers, a force for development instead
of a vulnerable group. ■
Silvia Bellón, Spanish student, 23
K Opening of the Scouts' 13th World Moot in Kenya, on 27 July 2010.
©
W
S
B
 In
c.
 /
 V
ic
to
r 
O
rt
e
g
a
3 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
the meeting. Delegates also urged the
IOC to keep the spirit of the YOG alive in
the period between Games.
That spirit is certainly alive and well
in Innsbruck, Austria, where organizers
are in the final countdown to the first
Winter Youth Olympic Games in January
2012.  Meanwhile, Nanjing, China, is
preparing for the second Youth Olympic
Summer Games in 2014. ■
International Olympic Committee
www.olympic.org 
Johannesburg, the festival brought
together  for two weeks more than 250
boys and girls from disadvantaged
communities—from tiny rural villages in
Cambodia to the inner cities of the
United States, the slums of India to the
favelas of Rio. Conquering cultural
barriers, they came together through the
language of the game. They broadened
their horizons and gained the confidence
they needed to return to their homes
and shape not only their own destinies,
but those of their communities as well.
Empowering disadvantaged youth to
improve their lives is the goal of the
streetfootballworld network.  It unites
over 80 organizations with a special
approach to tackling social challenges
like HIV/Aids, crime and homelessness:
they use football to bring young people
into social development programmes—
and keep them there. Working with the
network and partners, streetfootballworld
aims to reach out to 2,000,000 young
people worldwide every year until 2015.
Football can help find solutions to
problems too complex to be solved by
conventional methods. The game is only
the starting point. ■
www.streetfootballworld.org
The International Year of Youth (IYY)
coincides with the creation of a new
Olympic tradition. The  Youth Olympic
Games (YOG) were inaugurated by the
International Olympic Committee (IOC)*
last August, just days after the start of the
UN Year. The Youth Games combine sport,
education and cultural activities in a
unique format for young people between
the ages of 15 and 18. At the games,
young people learn from athlete role
models and from each other in a setting
that encourages lasting friendships. 
The first YOG, held in Singapore, drew
about 3,500 young people from around
the world. The results exceeded
expectations on every level.  The
participants offered their assessment of
the inaugural YOG in December at the 7th
World Conference on Sport, Education
and Culture in Durban, South Africa,
cosponsored by the IOC and UNESCO.
In keeping with the theme of the
conference, “Giving a Voice to Youth,”
teenage delegates took an active role at
While the greatest players in football
were competing in Johannesburg
(South Africa) for the 2010 FIFA World
Cup, 32 teams of young people were
coming together from around the world
for a more unusual tournament, the
Football for Hope Festival 2010.
Organized by streetfootballworld,
FIFA, the 2010 FIFA World Cup Organising
Committee South Africa and the City of
Sport: only a starting point
Youth Olympic Games
* In late 2009, the IOC received official UN Observer
status.
©
 F
o
o
tb
a
ll
’s
 H
id
d
e
n
 S
to
ri
e
s 
–
P
e
te
r 
D
e
n
c
h
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 3 3
Empowering disadvantaged
youth to improve their lives is the
goal of the streetfootballworld
network. 
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From a distance, Kawempe division in
Kampala (Uganda) looks like any shanty
town: a sea of tiny shacks with mud and
wattle walls. But getting closer, the
stench of disease and despair hangs
about like the angel of death. Children’s
eyes glint warily as they peer at a visitor
walking past. But gallantly, they play
about joyfully. They have probably never
used toothpaste in their short lives, but
that is of no consequence. Their
haunting voices echo in the distance as
you move further into the swampy
slums. Kawempe is characterized by
swampy slums where most people are
not sure of their next meal. 
Unemployment rates are high, with
low family incomes and high
dependence on those who can earn,
increasing levels of poverty and the
inability to afford health services. Most
women here are involved in prostitution
or commercial sex to make a living. Such
is the condition that a few years ago
moved James Tumusiime,  a young
psychologist now 30, to tears. A recent
graduate, James was working as a
volunteer counselor at a local clinic in
Kawempe when he met the 19-year-old
mother. “She looked frail, and she said
her children were always falling sick. She
thought it was malaria. I advised her to
test for HIV,” James recounts and pauses.
The pause is so long that you are afraid
the interview is over. “The test was
positive. I felt bad. She cried so hard.
Although I tried to counsel her to live
with a positive mind, I never saw her
again. I tried to reach her on her cell
number in vain…I pray she did not
commit suicide,” he says. Even now as
James tells the story, his face darkens.
But that incident was the turning
point for this psychology graduate.
Together with seven other young people,
he set out to “break the ice” and reach
out to such vulnerable single mothers in
the area, most of whom were making a
living through commercial sex. Despite
the fact that in Uganda, commercial sex
is illegal under the constitution.
Getting the project going
Another 30-year-old man, who prefers
anonymity, recalls that he was also a
community worker when James
approached him. “There had been a
project before by Plan UK, a charity
organization which was only catering for
children. But in most cases when you
met children and asked who their
parents were, they did not know. So we
felt we needed a project targeting sex
workers that could help them live
responsibly.” Another young man in his
late 20s tells heartrending stories of
prostitutes fighting over “clients.” Once,
he says, his sister was beaten by a
prostitute who thought she too was
competing with her.
“I remember the day we started the
‘breaking the ice’ project. We went there
for a week, every night, to see for
ourselves. It was sad seeing even
policemen on night patrol demanding
sex from the girls. That strengthened our
will to do something to change lives,” he
says. “There were so many teen mothers
with children whose fathers they did not
know. Some of them were as young as
13. And most of them were in the age
group of 13 to 25. Some of them were
students, others barmaids and
waitresses,” James recalls.
In 2007, the ‘breaking the ice’ project
was launched. “We began with a group
of about 10 mothers we had interacted
with who had told us they were sex
workers. We asked them to identify
others,” says James, the project
coordinator. “We wanted the girls to
protect themselves from HIV/Aids and
other sexually transmitted diseases.
(STDs) We finally got 60 mothers whom
we trained as peer educators. It is easy
for the mothers to be listened to from
their experiences. Even for the men
involved in prostitution, they tend to
listen to a woman demonstrating the
use of a condom, for instance, rather
than to another man,” James says. 
By 2009, the number of beneficiaries
had swelled to 3,000 sex workers. At this
point, Reproductive Health Uganda
came in with  financial support from the
Japanese government to set up
Moonlight Stars Clinic, which offers free
counseling and testing services for
HIV/Aids and other sexually transmitted
infections.“We called our clients
Moonlight Stars because we did not
want a name that would marginalize
them,” James says. The beneficiaries are
given cards for identification, to avoid
having non-beneficiaries storm the
clinic for free treatment.
A call for donations
Florence Kyeswa,  head of the clinic, says
they receive on average about 70 clients
in a week from the slums in Kawempe
Division, most of them suffering from
STDs. The funds from the Japanese
government have also been used to
train the “moonlight stars” in tailoring,
bakery, arts, crafts and mechanical work.
Africa, unemployment, slums: a lethal combination leading Ugandan adolescent girls to
prostitution and ruin. Until a group of young people decided to take things in hand.
3 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
Moonlight
stars CAROL NATUKUNDA
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
James says the beneficiaries are divided
in groups of about 20, and each group
given 5 million shillings (about US
$2,500 dollars) as start up capital. And
the majority of those who have been
equipped have a story to tell.“I am now
able to fend for my children, without
having to give in to sex. I feel confident
and happy that I am laying a good
foundation for my daughter,” says a 17-
year-old mother of one, who bakes
pancakes for a living. Another 21-year-
old HIV-positive mother chips in: “There
was a time I felt I wanted to die. I did not
see any point facing the next day
because of my status. But now, I have
access to treatment and condoms,and a
sewing machine. I make about 5 dollars
on a good day from tailoring.”The one
challenge, according to James, is that
some sex workers are tempted to fall
back on vice. Also, he says, they rely on
donor funds, and the Japanese funding
is now finished. The moonlight stars are
looking for new donors. The project has
drawn several partners including the
United Nations Population Fund
(UNFPA), which has identified  sex
workers as a high risk group in the
spread of HIV. and hence is calling for
more attention to be paid to the
group.“HIV is not only spread through
married couples, as we tend to think.
Commercial sex workers are a forgotten
lot,” observes James.
Other partners are Uganda Youth
Development Link, an organization
which provides guidance and
counseling to street children and other
young people, and Beads for Life
Uganda, a non-profit organization that
empowers Ugandan women who make
handcrafted beads from recycled paper
and turn them into necklaces, bracelets,
and earrings. The two organizations are
Carol Natukunda, 28, is a Ugandan
journalist and the 2008 laureate for the
prestigious African education
journalism award organised every year
by the Association for the
Development of Education (ADEA).
L Solitude, light and shadow, somewhere in Africa. 
©
 A
ll 
ri
g
h
ts
 r
e
se
rv
e
d
©
 P
a
tr
ic
k 
L
a
g
è
s
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 3 5
Uniting against AIDS
World leaders gathered at a High-
Level Meeting on HIV and AIDS at the
United Nations General Assembly in
New York on 8-10 June 2011.
The meeting focused on the gains
made 30 years into the epidemic and
on the renewed commitment
required to achieve zero new
infections, zero discrimination, and
zero AIDS-related deaths. 
Member States promised “bold
and decisive action”. They adopted a
new Declaration that will guide a
sustained response to HIV and AIDS
based on change management rather
than crisis management, emphasizing
country- and people-owned
strategies. 
As a UNAIDS cosponsor,  UNESCO
will continue to lead efforts to engage
young people and the education
sector in the response to HIV and
AIDS and to support prevention
through sexuality education, gender
equality and human rights. ■
now actively involved in sensitizing
young people across the country in
responsible living. ■
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
It all began the day Khalida Brohi, now
22 years old, learned about the custom
of karo kari, or honour killing. Honour
killing is the murder of a woman or an
act of extreme violence against her
perpetrated by her male relatives when
she is perceived as having brought
dishonour upon her family. Horrified,
Khalida vowed to fight this heinous
tradition. Unable to take direct action to
oppose violence against women, she
began writing poems about karo kari
and within her community she
launched an aggressive awareness
raising campaign against honour killing.
The young sughar
from Balochistan
Khalida Brohi’s conviction
comes across instantly from
behind her bright eyes and
inimitable warm smile. Yet
who could imagine that this
petite young woman from a
conservative tribal
community in Balochistan,
southwestern province of
Pakistan, has been a change
maker since age 16, when
she first took a stand
against the centuries-old
tradition of honour killing? 
Noshan Abbas meets 
KHALIDA BROHI
I Young women learning to weave in a community
centre in Karachi, Pakistan 
But in a religious, conservative
community whose underpinnings are
encapsulated in the common proverb
‘zar, zan , zameen’ (women, gold and
land) - the three main possessions
directly linked to man’s honour – trying
to incite local community leaders to
make the distinction between ancestral
custom and religious practice was much
more dangerous than Khalida imagined. 
According to Human Rights
Commission of Pakistan (HRCP)
chairperson I. A Rehman, “Honour killing
used to be practiced only in remote
districts but now it happens in
metropolitan cities, in Karachi, Lahore
and Peshawar, for example. The settled
districts have acquired this evil too. It’s
one of the biggest problems women
face. Honour killings are not always
reported, although since the women’s
act of 2006, cases have started being
brought to the attention of authorities.
We have only an approximate figure,
which amounts to 800 to 1,000 killings a
year- there may be marginal variations
in the number from year to year but the
situation remains the same.”
Despite challenges of all kinds,
Khalida helped found in 2004 the
3 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
mindsets, she faced the wrath of the
traditional patriarchal status quo. Her life
was threatened and she was ultimately
expelled from her community. 
Tradition versus tradition
“In 2008 our organization faced several
threats against our safety,” recalls Khalida.
“We faced opposition from religious
leaders and community tribal leaders.
The time came when we had to leave
everything and flee.” At that point
Khalida’s father took her to Karachi to
safety so that she could finish her studies. 
But Khalida wasn’t about to give up
on this crucial issue. “While everything
had come to a halt, I kept on thinking
about what had gone wrong in the
programme. ‘I respect tradition,’ I
thought to myself. Suddenly I realized
we had to promote positive traditions
that could help end honour killing. And
that was how we came to work with
locals as our allies.”
Turning this inclusive strategy into
action still required perseverance from
Khalida and her team of 40 young
people. “We advocated the same cause
but less aggressively,” says Khalida , who
used local traditions to her advantage
and confronted the tribal leaders who
had previously threatened her. “In our
culture, you do not kick someone out of
your house - it’s not done.” Khalida
showed up with her team at the house of
one of the leaders, who was thus forced
against his will to listen and talk to the
group of persistent youths. “We spoke in
the local language and explained how
we wanted to promote local traditions
such as embroidery, music and poetry.”
Three leaders were responsive and even
clerics started giving sermons about
women’s rights in accordance to Islam. 
Promoting positive local traditions by
producing embroidery that is later
marketed through PDI, Sughar centres
have also provided a female friendly
platform for women to create financial
elbow room. In addition they receive
value added training and basic
education training in areas such as math,
writing and reproductive health.  For
Khalida, this has meant a window of
opportunity to raise awareness against
honour killing.  “Women’s attitude
towards honour killing is that of
acceptance. We are working to change
that by explaining the status and rights
of women as stated in Islam…they of
course become receptive to that,” she
says. Convinced women’s effacement in
the face of honour killing is a prime
cause for its continuation, Khalida has
targeted women but without neglecting
the involvement of men. Through
creative avenues such as cricket
tournaments, interactive theater, SMS,
FM radio, info-activism and digital
advocacy, PDI advocates for the rights of
women by educating men. With the
consent of tribal leaders, discussions with
men using the Islamic argument of
women’s rights are also organized. 
When asked how she measures the
effect of her work, Khalida answers, "We
started with 14 girls on our team and
now we have 40 both male and female
members so I feel attitudes are changing.
I have heard of cases of honour killing in
neighbouring areas, but not in my
community for the past three years.”
Brave Role Model 
With the help of savings and the
support of funding from various
organizations, Khalida Brohi has set up
Sughar centres in several districts of
organization Participatory Development
Initiatives (PDI). It has established
innovative ideas such as the Sughar
(which means skilled and confident
woman in the local language)
Programme to end honour killing by
enabling economic empowerment
among tribal women. 
“Over time I realized that most of
the honour killings were of those
women who were sitting at home.
Those who bring in income every
month are considered of value to the
family, and this also builds their
capacities for decision making and
contribution in their households and
lives,” says Khalida, zeroing in on the
power of making money. But she also
understood the challenge of changing
mindsets: “There are three main reasons
why honour killing happens. First is our
bad policies at the government level,
second is the negative perception of
women’s status and third, probably the
biggest reason, is that women accept
customs as their fate.” But before Khalida
embarked on the challenge of changing
©
 U
N
 P
h
o
to
/J
o
h
n
 I
sa
a
c
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 3 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Balochistan, becoming a fellow of the
Unreasonable Institute as well as
winning the Young Champion Award
and YouthActionNet fellowship award.
She has a ‘Wake Up Campaign Against
Honour Killing’ on Facebook that
updates members on honour killing
cases and other relevant information.
But Khalida is conscious that despite the
support from family, international
organizations and her team, naysayers
still exist: “Those who are against what
we do in our community are in minority,
so they don’t speak about it publicly,
but I know they’re waiting for us to slip
and make a mistake. That is why I am so
particular about making sure we try to
make no mistakes whatsoever.”
Expanding its outreach to women,
PDI was active in a 2008 national
programme, the Benazir Bhutto
Government Land Distribution to
landless Sindhi peasant women. It came
up with the programme Land for
Women and took responsibility for
monitoring the process. When major
discrepancies were detected, however,
PDI launched a support program for
women with the help of Oxfam.
Through the local radio, they
highlighted the land programme in far
flung areas; they provided help for
filling in forms, transport to open legal
courts and legal support to women who
faced land issue problems. “Within three
years the land for women programme
provided land for 50% of the 3000
women participants,” says Khalida.
Shuttling between Balochistan and
Karachi where she is finishing her
undergraduate studies in international
relations, sociology and economics,
Khalida has also worked to help flood
victims in the area of Sindh. Receiving
support from Oxfam and the Rockdale
foundation, she raised funds for 25,000
families in nearby areas, provided relief
for 12,000 people and helped establish
homes in the recovery phase. 
Looking back, Khalida identifies her
biggest struggle: maintaining the
culturally defined concept of a good
reputation, a sacred and often life
determining notion in her society. “The
issue of being or not being a ‘decent’ girl
becomes an issue as soon as you step
out of your house”. Even though
Khalida’s parents have been pillars of
strength and inspiration for her, Khalida
remembers even her mother being
upset when she was first invited to
Sydney for an Oxfam launch of a youth
partnership. Khalida laughs as she
recalls her mother’s words: “You will not
find a husband!”  
But Khalida is willing to brave the
risks and continue her battle to inspire
women to demand and protect their
basic human right to life.  ■
L Khalida Brodi (front, left) with some of the “Sughar” programme participants.  © Participatory Development Initiatives (PDI)
Noshan Abbas, 26, is a journalist from
Islamabad, Pakistan. She works for Al
Jazeera, BBC Urdu and BBC South Asia
online. For Plan International and
Rutgers WPF, she created Pakistan's
first Framework Policy for Adolescents.
©
 N
u
m
a
ir
 A
b
b
a
s
3 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
On March 11, 2011, Japan experienced
an earthquake of a scale unprecedented
in the modern age, resulting in more
than 14,000 deaths and leaving 10,000
more people missing. Just 15 hours after
the quake, a 32-year-old web director,
Hironori Nakahara,  and his friends
launched a website, buji.me, to collect
and display victims’ safety status and
location information, city by city. Buji
means “safety” in Japanese.
“The first thing that came to me was
what I can do to save victims’ lives. In a
situation like this, a prompt reaction is
necessary to save as many people as
possible,” said Hironori.
He walked three hours from his
apartment in central Tokyo to his
girlfriend’s home near the trendy district
of Shibuya. He and his friends met there
to discuss what they could do to help
and take action. The idea of buji.me
emerged from their brainstorming.
“I began writing the first line of code
at 6:00 p.m., five hours after the quake,
and the site was up by 6:00 a.m. the
next morning. I spent the next five days
without much sleep, determined to
improve the website to accommodate
as much ‘buji’ information as possible.”
Had Hironori and his team ever
planned to charge a fee for this project,
he estimates the figure at around US
$50,000. But the reward they received
cannot be calculated in financial terms.
“Through this project, I have
received many warm messages,
thanking us for helping them find their
loved ones,” Hironori recalls. His attitude
to work and money has changed as a
result. “Ever since this moment, for every
project that I work on, I ask –– is this
project going to help someone? I have
realized the importance of a project is
judged by its impact on society, rather
than the size of its budget.”
Gross National Happiness
Back in 1968, in his famous 18 March
speech, American politician Robert
Kennedy had already mentioned the
flaws of money-driven benchmarks to
measure prosperity:
“Our Gross National Product, now, is
over $800 billion dollars a year, but that
Gross National Product … counts air
pollution and cigarette advertising, and
ambulances to clear our highways of
carnage.... Yet the Gross National
Product does not allow for the health of
our children, the quality of their
education or the joy of their play. It
measures neither our wit nor our
courage, neither our wisdom nor our
learning, neither our compassion nor
our devotion to our country, it measures
everything, in short, except that which
makes life worthwhile.”
Subsequently, in 1972, Bhutan's
former King, Jigme Singye Wangchuck,
came up with an alternative benchmark
index that measures a country’s
prosperity based on people’s happiness
and wellbeing –– the idea of Gross
National Happiness (GNH).
Much has been written on the
subject since and in today’s Japan, GDP
is no longer synonymous with
prosperity. In the last 10 years, and
therefore long before the earthquake, a
shift in values has occurred in Japanese
society, primarily among young people,
who tend to view Japan’s present
economic stagnation as a good sign.
I Shibuya district in Tokyo is a symbol of Japan's
consumer society.
For a number of years,
young people in Japan have
been questioning the
benefits of a society
obsessed by economic
growth. When the
earthquake and tsunami
struck the country last
March, voices were heard
calling for a radical shift in
the value system, to give
priority to social well-being
and solidarity.
An undeclared
revoluti n
HIROKI YANAGISAWA
©
 Z
so
fi
a
 Il
o
sv
a
i
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 3 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
“Our economic activity has been too
big and out of control. Plus, ever since I
was small, I have felt surrounded by an
excess of everything,” said Youki Amagai, a
23-year-old university student from Chiba.
“Though I admit money is necessary to
keep my day-to-day life going, it is not
something that fulfills my internal needs.
Instead of going out shopping, I would
rather go out and chat with older people
and share thoughts. My main interest is to
discuss what we can do to improve our
society, especially the environment, and
mobilize for action.”
Ever since the non-profit organization
law was enacted in 1998, Japan’s non-
profit sector has flourished. Many active
and socially-oriented people have begun
engaging in volunteer activities. “In terms
of materialistic needs, Japan has reached
heights that would be difficult to surpass.
But when we look at Japan’s social
system, it is incomplete and
dysfunctional. Many active youngsters
and non-profit sectors have been
focusing and working on this gap,” said
Ikuma Saga, the founder of Service Grant,
Japan’s leading pro bono worker and
non-profit organization matching agency.
With Japan’s population decreasing
continuously, there is a possibility that a
growing number of countries will
surpass the country’s GDP in the near
future. Not to worry: Japan is surely
becoming happier and stronger, thanks
to its youth. ■
Hiroki Yanagisawa, 33, is a freelance 
journalist and the founder of EDGY
JAPAN (edgyjapan.jp), a web media
featuring and connecting edgy
creative talents, products, and
locations from Japan. He is currently
based in Tokyo and Hong Kong.
©
 T
e
rr
ie
 S
a
to
They’re young, connected and want to join the debate –
young people from all over the world have set up the
International Youth  Climate Movement so that they, too, can
have a say at conferences on climate change. After all, it’s
their future that is being discussed.
4 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
“I’m only a child and I don’t have all the
solutions, but I want you to realize,
neither do you!”
In 1992, Severn Cullis-Suzuki was only
12 years old when she gave her now
famous speech at the United Nations
Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro. “You don’t
know how to fix the holes in our ozone
layer,” she said. “You don’t know how to
bring salmon back up a dead stream. You
don’t know how to bring back an animal
now extinct. And you can’t bring back
forests that once grew where there is now
desert. If you don’t know how to fix it,
please stop breaking it!”
Nearly 20 years later, her words have
not been forgotten. Her YouTube clip, The
Girl Who Silenced the World for Six
Minutes, has become a hit, and still brings
a lump to the throat.
Severn Cullis-Suzuki is Canadian but
she was speaking for all of the world’s
children and youth, especially those who
are not as fortunate to have grown up in a
rich country like hers. Young people make
up one third of mankind – 2 billion
people who for the most part have no say
in politics. Yet it is their future that adults
are debating. “You are deciding what kind
of world we will grow up in,” said Severn.
A mortgaged inheritance
This conflict is serious – young people
have realized that the older generation
is leaving them with an economic and
ecological debt. In 2010, the 27 Member
States of the European Union (EU))
owed some €8.7 billion. And we find it
hard even to imagine what one billion
represents. It is one thousand million, or
‘1’ followed by twelve zeros. Every child
on the planet is born with a deficit of
about €17,000 in its account. This debt is
the result of a form of political
cowardice that dumps the burden onto
those who cannot defend themselves
because they are too young or not yet
born.
The ecological debt that generation
after generation has been accumulating
for nearly a century is colossal. We are
now consuming more energy and fossil
resources than the planet can bear.
Since the beginning of the industrial
revolution, mankind has been releasing
more and more CO2 into the air.
Because of the greenhouse effect, the
planet is getting warmer – the average
temperature of the Earth has risen by
0.74 degrees Celsius since 1905. The first
decade of the 21st century has been by
far the hottest since records began. And
the effects of climate change are already
being felt – the Arctic ice sheet is
receding, the frequency of climate-
related disasters is increasing, sea level
is rising, glaciers are melting. 
“We did not inherit the earth from
our ancestors, we borrowed it from our
grandchildren,” it says on the
International Youth Climate Movement
with 
a cause
JENS LUBBADEH
Demonstration against the oil and mining industry
at the September 2010 World Energy Congress in
Montreal (Canada).
©
 F
ra
n
ç
o
is
 P
e
sa
n
t 
/G
re
e
n
p
e
a
c
e
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 4 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
website (http://youthclimate.org/). This
American Indian proverb clearly sums
up the issue – it is the youth of today
who will end up having to pay for our
wasteful lifestyle. “As we move towards a
carbon-constrained world, it is the
youth that will fully experience the
future consequences of today’s actions
of humanity,” says the website. 
The International Youth Climate
Movement brings together young
people from all over the world, with
branches in countries on every
continent. Since the 2005 climate
summit in Montreal (Canada), each
national Member has been sending
delegates to the world climate meetings. 
“This generation understands that
everyone across the world will be
affected by climate change and so it is
the responsibility of us all to take
action,” explains 29-year-old Neva
Frecheville, who is International
Engagement Coordinator for the British
coalition. The youth of today does not
want to look on passively as adults
decide their future. “We are starting to
show we won’t stand for it. We will
create our own change,” adds Neva. 
In 2009, the national branches of the
Movement set up YOUNGO, which
represents all Youth NGOs and is
lobbying for an 85% reduction in CO2
emissions worldwide by 2050
(compared to 1990 levels). YOUNGO has
been officially recognized as a
Constituency representing the interests
of youth within the United Nations
Framework Convention on Climate
Change (UNFCCC). This status is still
provisional, but should change. “2011 is
an exciting year for the YOUNGO
constituency of the UNFCCC,” explains
Christiana Figueres, Executive Secretary
of the UNFCCC, “as this is the year in
which their status will be considered for
formalization. The formalization does
not mean a ‘start’ of engagement, since
children and young people have been
participating in UNFCCC meetings since
the year 2000.”
At the climate conferences in
Copenhagen (Denmark) and Cancún
(Mexico), young people were able to
speak for the first time with a common
political voice. “Like the other
constituencies to the UNFCCC,
YOUNGO’s constituency function is
limited to observer status,” explains
Neva. “In essence, we can’t take part in
the negotiations but rather watch and
try to influence through lobbying and
actions. Being recognized as having a
legitimate stake in the proceedings
means that young people have more
access to the process, to the negotiators
and the secretariat.” Christiana Figueres
agrees: “The constituency status
provides a conduit for the exchange of
information between young people and
the secretariat, and helps to orchestrate
the active participation of youth
representatives in UNFCCC meetings.”
And, adds Neva, “Young people are also
invited to make interventions which
give voice to young people across the
world at the highest level of the
UNFCCC.” 
Notably, for the past six years, these
young activists have regularly been
holding their own conference a few
days before the world climate summit. 
Not that apolitical
We often say that young people today
are not political. But on closer
examination, things are more complex.
It is true that young people are not very
interested in traditional politics, and
L “Silent Evolution”, underwater installation by British artist Jason deCaires Taylor, shown during the 2010 United
Nations climate change conference (COP 16) in Cancun, Mexico. Young divers swam among 400 submerged
statues to highlight the threat of rising sea levels.
©
 J
a
so
n
 d
e
 C
a
ir
e
s 
Ta
y
lo
r/
G
re
e
n
p
e
a
c
e
4 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
have little regard for politicians and
their parties – only around one third of
Europeans aged 16 to 29 trust them.
However, it should be pointed out that
this proportion is also low among older
people. Cécile Lecomte, a 29-year-old
Frenchwoman, campaigns for the
environment. She lives in Lüneburg, in
northern Germany and has attracted
attention for her spectacular stunts to
stop trains transporting nuclear waste
by hanging above the railway lines. For
her, “a lack of political interest is not just
the preserve of young people.” 
The now familiar lack of political
commitment by young people does
seem to be linked to this loss of
confidence in politicians. According to
Eurostat*, only 4% of young Europeans
are members of a political party. And
only 16% believe that parliament is the
best place to make oneself heard. 
In reality, their involvement in
politics takes a different form: “We’re
hugely political, and that’s increasing as
we become more disenfranchised and
disillusioned,” says Neva. Young
Europeans feel that non-parliamentary
political engagement is even more
effective – holding debates (30%),
taking part in demonstrations (13%) or
supporting a petition or NGO (11%).
Cécile agrees. She believes that there
has been an enormous increase in
protest actions by young people. 
This trend may be seen worldwide,
especially in countries where access to
traditional politics is tightly controlled,
in the absence of democracy. “As well as
the recent protests in the United
Kingdom over tuition fees, we also have
mostly youth-led movements in places
like Egypt and Tunisia,” says Neva. “And
youth in Europe are coming together to
bypass the ‘adult’ NGOs and get
together to influence EU policy.”
For Christiana Figueres, it is even
more important for young people to
become involved at national level than
internationally.  “I have constantly
encouraged youth to be actively
involved in the development of
negotiating positions and climate
friendly policies at home, at the
domestic level,” she says. “That is where
they can have the highest impact to
influence governments to take a long
term view in full recognition that it is
precisely the next generation that will
be most affected by climate change.”
It is interesting to see that young
people are more willing to trust political
institutions, like Parliament, than the
politicians themselves. And supra-
national institutions attract even more
support – 70% of young people have
respect for the European Parliament and
the United Nations. On this point, young
people set themselves clearly apart
from older people. They probably no
longer think in terms of national
frontiers and see networking and
cooperation as positive factors that
inspire confidence. Neva agrees: “Young
people have shown that it is possible to
place national interests to one side to
work together on a common good.”
The internet has certainly had an
influence. In 2008, 70% of young people
used the Web every day, and this figure
has increased in recent years. And there
is a real generation gap here, too –
young people have much greater
mastery of the possibilities of the
internet than older people. Social
networks, Twitter and chat rooms are
used much more and represent a new
style of relationships and contact.
“Compared to ‘older’ delegates at the
UNFCCC, we use new and social media
Jens Lubbadeh, 36, is a journalist for
Greenpeace Magazine, Germany. He
has been a correspondent for the
UNESCO Courier since 2009.
©
 C
la
u
d
ia
 W
ü
st
e
n
h
a
g
e
n
*The figures on youth in Europe cited in this article
are taken from Youth in Europe, A statistical portrait,
2009 edition, Eurostat, European Commission.
much more effectively,” explains Neva.
“We are more creative, innovative and
fun because we are not blinkered by old
campaigning styles and habits; we are
still setting the scene when it comes to
approaches. Our communications are
often much more positive – more ‘pro’
than ‘anti’ – because basically we are
trying to vision the future that we want
to live in.” ■
L A Boy Scout, under the Ticket to Life Project, helps clean Manila Bay, Philippines
©
 B
o
y
 S
c
o
u
ts
 o
f 
th
e
 P
h
ili
p
p
in
e
s
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 4 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Zhan Yufeng works 12 hours a day, seven
days a week. The 24-year-old is leading
the non-profit China Youth Climate
Action Network (CYCAN). “I’m quite busy,
managing climate-focused activities,
training volunteers, fundraising, and
meeting program partners,“ he says.
“Sometimes I stay overnight in my office.”
Zhan earned his degree in art and
design from the Beijing Institute of
Fashion Technology last year. He had few
ideas about climate change until he was
invited to help the CYCAN prepare a
campaign for United Nations Day, Oct.
24, 2009.
Zhan designed the logo, posters and
brochures for this campaign that
attracted student groups from 200
universities from across the country and
some 50 NGOs. It reached an estimated
population of more than 5 million. “I
worked hard for a month along with
many volunteers. I got addicted to the
work. It was like love at first sight,” Zhan
says. 
In December 2009, in
Copenhagen, Denmark,
strange doctors accosted
people on the street,
offering them check-ups
and prescriptions. Their
comportment was at odds
with the image of wise old
Chinese physicians, whose
traditional garb they wore.
No wonder: they were no
more doctors than the
people they accosted were
patients. Yet their diagnosis
of the planet’s condition
was all too accurate.            
Prescriptions
More than 30,000 young people
directly participated in the campaign,
which was supported by United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP) and
other organizations. There were various
performance techniques: youngsters
used fans to melt mountains of snow,
they painted their upper bodies blue to
remind people of the rising sea levels due
to global warming, they traveled by
bicycle and skates instead of driving, etc. 
“My peers were devoted and
energetic. I felt their passion,
perseverance, and power,” Zhan says,
adding that the opportunity showed him
another side of a commercialized society,
a side where young people are working
hard for a greener planet and a cleaner
future.
Upon the completion of this
campaign, CYCAN leaders began to
recruit candidates to attend the 15th
United Nations Climate Change
Conference COP15 in December 2009 in
Copenhagen, Denmark. This would be
the first time a delegation of Chinese
youth participated in international
climate talks. 
Chinese CYCAN got the idea when
they noticed that only one young
Chinese participated in the climate
negotiations in 2008 at Poznan, Poland.
Hundreds of youth leaders from the
United States, Europe, and countries
from other parts of the world
participated in the talks.
Zhan had hesitated: “My English was
not good enough for an international
conference. I was afraid I could not help
the team on such an important
occasion.” But finally he joined the
delegation, working as photographer
and program planner.
In addition to designing slogans, T-
shirts, and posters and photographing
events, Zhan and his partners managed
performances such as “Diagnosis for a
sick globe”, for example. Dressed as
traditional Chinese doctors, they gave
check-ups to participants. Those who
signed petitions against global warming
got “prescriptions” for fighting climate
problems.
The team also talked to Chinese and
international officers, media reporters
and climate negotiators, including
China’s Vice Minister of the State
Development and Reform Commission,
Xie Zhenhua, and U.S. Secretary of
Commerce Gary Locke.
Their slogan was No Other Way
(NOW), calling for immediate action on
cutting carbon emissions to save the
world from global warming.
Listening is not enough
COP15 showed Zhan the limits of the
Chinese young people’s capabilities.
Language was the main challenge. Most
of Zhan’s peers understood the
speeches, but only a few were able to
articulate opinions in fluent English.
Zhan was deeply impressed by the
professionalism of foreign young
delegates at the meeting. “They were
experienced, fully aware of the
4 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
for a sick
planet
ZHAO YING
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
mechanisms and policies of the
conference. They came up with
illuminating proposals and we listened,”
Zhan says. 
Few courses specializing in climate
issues are available at Chinese
universities, nor do young people have
frequent opportunities to exchange
relative information with their foreign
peers. 
In 2009, the CYCAN arranged
training programs before COP15 on
mechanisms of the talks, climate change
issues, fundraising, public relations and
event management. This was not
enough, Zhan points out. It is necessary
to arrange constant training to update
young people’s knowledge and skills.
Soon after he returned to China, he
joined the CYCAN as a full-time
employee.
The NGO, founded in 2007 by seven
Chinese youth groups, now has just
three full-time workers, and a large
portion of its operation relies on 51
volunteers in Beijing and nine core
members living or studying abroad.
Zhan became head of the
organization after being responsible for a
series of large-scale campaigns including
the International Youth Summit on
Energy and Climate Change held in July
2010 in Shanghai, and the clean energy
competition of Great Power Race that
attracted some 1,000 universities from
China, India and the United States.
Zhan, a native of the coastal
province of Guangdong in southern
China, used to roam Beijing’s art
galleries, watch stage shows and
movies, or play billiards with friends
after school. But his new work schedule
will not allow such habits.
If he had chosen to be a professional
designer after his graduation, his
income could have tripled, but “I’m not
in a hurry to make money,” he says. “At
my age, the priority is to improve my
overall abilities and the CYCAN is a place
where I keep learning things by meeting
people from all walks of life.”
What worries him are fundraising
and training volunteers. For three
months last year, the CYCAN workers
did not get paid due to lack of funds. “It
was hard but we managed to survive by
presenting constructive plans to
foundations and sponsors,” Zhan says. 
Additionally, some leaders left the
CYCAN to start new careers or study
abroad, forcing the organization to
recruit new members and train
L Zhan Yufeng demonstrating at the United Nations Climate Change Conference (COP15) in Copenhagen (Denmark), holding up the banner of his organization..
© Courtesy of Zhan Yufeng
Zhao Ying, 34, covering Shanghai's 
2010 World Expo for Xinhua News
Agency, which she joined in 1999. She
is a journalist for China Features, part
of Xinhua's network.
amateurs. “There are many youth
organizations active in China, but it’s a
pressing task to improve their expertise
so that their voice will get heard,” Zhan
says. ■
©
 D
R
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 4 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
The newly-created route is immediately
given its name: ciclovía ciudadana, or
citizens’ bike lane. The cost of the
installation, about US$1000, came out of
the young activists’ pockets. Though
traced without permission, the new bike
lane does not remain illegal for long. By
the very next day, Jalisco state’s
transport authority rules in favour of the
initiative. It pledges not only to improve
the bike lane and enforce respect for it
but also to recognize all such citizens’
initiatives in future, as long as they
conform to the Non-motorized Mobility
Master Plan.
What Master Plan? The story begins
in 2007, in Guadalajara, second largest
city in Mexico and capital of Jalisco state.
Citizens organized a protest against a
municipal decision to turn López Mateos
Avenue into an expressway. Paulina
drives to her classes at the university and
could have benefited, but she felt the
decision, made without consulting the
local community, was against her
interests. It happened to be the subject
she was studying at the time,
governance and transparency in public
action. As for Jesús, a philosophy
student and avid cyclist, he could only
be against an urban development
project that favoured the use of
automobiles. Today, at age 24 and 27
respectively, they have become full-
fledged experts in urban planning and
sustainable development. They speak
like professionals, negotiate with
authorities and give interviews to the
media. “We had to learn how to debate
and present our arguments to political
decision-makers,” explains Jesús. All the
more because their first protest
concerning López Mateos Avenue did
not have the results anticipated. But it
did make a lasting contribution to the
community by creating the citizens’
group Ciudad Para Todos (City for all).
Dialogue had thus been ongoing for
several years between the young
members of Ciudad Para Todos and the
Jalisco state authorities, with the former
doing their best to persuade the latter of
the importance of establishing a
network of bike lanes in the urban area
of Guadalajara, which comprises eight
municipalities including Zapopan. The
dialogue produced a Non-motorized
Mobility Master Plan, a document of
nearly a thousand pages written by a
firm of consultants with the
participation of civil society. But just as
the battle seemed to be won, a new
government came to power, one less
sensitive to the issue. Patiently, the
RUTH PÉREZ LÓPEZ
Photographer Gerardo Montes de Oca Valadez, 33,
is  a Mexican psychologist and artist and a member
of Ciudad Para Todos. 
See also: http://gmove.wordpress.com/  
Early one fine morning at
the beginning of 2011, a
group of 30 young people
invade the Avenue Santa
Margarita in Zapopan, a
town in Mexico’s Jalisco
state. They attach a line-
marking device to a tricycle
cart and off they go! By
noon, a five-kilometre
stretch of the avenue is
bordered by a white stripe,
bicycle pictographs are
painted on the tarmac and
road signs are attached to
poles.
Life in th   ©
 G
er
ar
do
 M
on
te
s 
de
 O
ca
Va
la
de
z 
(G
ua
da
la
ja
ra
)
4 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
young people started again from zero.
They approached the new government
with requests to allocate funds to
implement the Plan. To no avail. So they
decided to take matters into their own
hands and trace their own bike lane. “We
had no legal means to force them to put
the Plan into action,” recalls Jesús. “So we
decided we had to take charge.” Having
received a thumbs-up from authorities,
they created another bike lane in
Zapopan last March, using the same
method.
Conviviality and safety combined
But the battle waged by the young
members of Ciudad Para Todos does not
end there. In the last few years, they
have started numerous projects aimed
at reclaiming public space in different
city districts. Opposed to the
construction of an expressway on
Inglaterra Avenue, they launched, with
community support, the project “Linear
park” to make the central strip that
divides the avenue’s two lanes into
something beautiful. They transformed it
into a park and meet there every
Saturday to participate in all kinds of
activities, planting trees, designing
flower beds and putting on shows for
children. “Nomadic park” is another
project, which consists of occupying
space that is normally reserved for cars
by taking over one or two traffic lanes
and setting up games, playing music,
organizing races or football matches.
The object is not to block car traffic but
to slow it down and make up for the lack
of recreational space in the city. At night,
they organize open-air screenings of
films and documentaries.
In other words, these young people
do not simply protest. Brimming with
enthusiasm, they propose alternative
forms of urban development in a
dynamic and playful way. According to
Gerardo, a Ciudad Para Todos activist
who took the photos for this article,
public space must be laid out so it
encourages people to interact. It should
“be an invitation to conviviality, reinforce
community ties and preserve the
identity of neighbourhoods”. As Gerardo
also underlines, the group’s attempts to
transform the city and modes of social
interaction in public space help reduce
urban crime. On top of that, they
contribute to good citizenship and the
development of participative decision-
making. The young people’s actions thus
not only have an impact on public space
and residents’ lifestyles, they also
influence the city’s politics. ■
Ruth Pérez López, 34, is a Spanish
socio-anthropologist and member of
Bicitekas A.C., a group that champions
bicycles and sustainable transportation
in Mexico. She is the author of several
books and articles on poverty, youth,
public space and social change.
http://bicitekas.org/
©
 A
n
n
ik
a
 B
o
rm
, M
e
xi
co
   bik  lane
Scene from the “Nomadic park” project
© Gerardo Montes 
de Oca Valadez, Guadalajara
“Life is like riding a bicycle. To
keep your balance you must keep
moving.”
Attributed to Albert Einstein
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 . 4 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
We often wonder what takes our lives in
one direction or another. In my case, it
was a serious illness as a child that kept
me bedridden for several months,
hovering between life and death.
During this long period of solitude, my
reading and meditation turned into
arduous lessons that strengthened my
spirit and my personality. 
After several years of struggle, I got
well again. I felt that I had to use the
second chance I had been given and
devote my life and work to achieving
change and progress for the poorest of
the poor. 
The vocation I had chosen as a child
– architecture – is usually seen as being
far removed from the disadvantaged
members of society. It is most often
linked in peoples’ minds to the prestige
and fame of a few architects and their
spectacular, extravagant buildings. I
wanted to change this old-fashioned
and obsolete image of the impact
architects can have on society. That is
why I wanted to devote myself entirely
to the development of projects and
research in sustainable architecture,
new technologies, climate change and
the response of architecture to
mitigating natural disaster risks. 
After years of hard work, I graduated
at the top of my class from San Agustín
d’Arequipa national university, in my
home town in Peru. This was my first leg
up the ladder. Then, a few months later, I
had the opportunity to participate in an
international competition on
environmental initiatives. With the
support of my mentors, I prepared a
project to rehabilitate the Arequipa river
basin, with the aim of preserving
farming there, while encouraging
participatory tourism in the agricultural
areas. 
My project won an award and I was
given a trip to Germany to attend an
environment conference for young
adults, organized by Bayer. I was one of
about 100 young environmentalists,
What can be used to store
water, for overwintering, as
a shelter, an igloo, a water
mill, canoe or a raft? Hard to
find an answer? Yet the
object exists. It is made out
of recycled plastic bottles
and steel cables and is
called an ‘ecocylinder’. Its
inventor, the 26-year-old
architect Carlos Bartesaghi
Koc, explains why he
created this object and
many others.
This article was written in collaboration with Tunza,
the youth magazine produced by the United
Nations Environment Programme (UNEP). 
See: http://tunza.mobi/
©
 C
a
rl
o
s 
B
a
rt
e
sa
g
h
i K
o
c
K Panoramic view of  “Systemic Agrotourism”
project with “self-built shelters”, 2009
© Carlos Bartesaghi Koc
Green
architecture
4 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
CARLOS BARTESAGHI KOC
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
farming with participatory tourism. In
the former case, local inhabitants
provide free accommodation for tourists
who, in exchange, help out and learn
ancestral farming methods. The project
also calls for “self-built shelters”, which
are buildings made by farmers using
recycled materials and refuse produced
in urban areas. The second project is an
urban design for new tourist circuits
inside the famous sillar (volcanic rock)
quarries in Arequipa. Once they are set
up, these circuits will create new jobs,
while protecting and improving health
and safety conditions for quarry
workers, who risk illegal expropriation. 
At the moment I am working on a
project for an urban waste treatment
plant for Arequipa (for my qualifying
thesis), which will include a proposal for
a controlled landfill site and its eventual
landscaping into a park. The project
includes a plant for sorting inorganic
waste and a compost production unit.
The workers who are there now
informally will get official contracts
along with better health, hygiene and
safety conditions. They will be offered
training opportunities, childcare and
leisure facilities on the same site.
Children and young people will be able
to visit a waste dump museum and use
educational materials inside the factory.  
In the near future, I hope to
continue teaching and to develop low-
cost, environment-friendly architecture.
I would like to help bring more justice to
the world and make it a place more fit
for humans and nature. ■
Carlos Bartesaghi Koc’s websites:
http://www.wix.com/carlosbartesaghikoc/cbk)
http://issuu.com/carlosbartesaghikoc/docs/archit
ecture_portfolio_2005-2011  
gathered together to discuss scientific
and cultural means to combat climate
change effectively.
It was thanks to this trip that I also
started to write for Tunza, the United
Nations Environment Programme (UNEP)
youth magazine. And that is how I was
able to exchange opinions and
experiences with many other young
people around the world, which turned
out to be a fantastic source of inspiration
and motivation. 
I went on to organize exhibitions,
events and campaigns; I gave lectures
and was taken on as an assistant at the
university. Working with a local NGO, I
was able to design some larger-scale
social and environmental projects. These
led to me to travel throughout the
Peruvian sierra, where I saw the poverty
and social disintegration that are
increasing daily in our country. 
Innovative technologies
This experience confirmed my long-
standing conviction: in emerging
countries like mine, we must use very
low-cost technologies that can be
adapted to different social, cultural and
economic contexts. This is how the idea
for the ‘ecocylinder’ came about, for
example – a multifunction shelter made
out of recycled plastic bottles and steel
cables, fitted together  into sheets and
stuck on top of one another. This
cylinder can be used and adapted in a
thousand different ways, according to
local needs and weather conditions. It
can be used to store water, for
overwintering, as a shelter, an igloo,
water mill, canoe or raft. 
Other projects, like Systemic
Agrotourism and Quarry Ecotourism, are
part of the same original idea of linking
LK The ecocylinder invented by Carlos can be used
and adapted in multiple ways according to location,
need and climate conditions.
L Peruvian architect Carlos Bartesaghi Koc making
presentation as a “Young environmental envoy” for
Bayer in 2007 in Leverkusen (Copyright Bayer AG)
©
 C
a
rl
o
s 
B
a
rt
e
sa
g
h
i K
o
c
©
 C
a
rl
o
s 
B
a
rt
e
sa
g
h
i K
o
c
©
 B
ay
e
r 
A
G
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
5 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
KHALED YOUSSEF was interviewed by Khaled Abu Hijleh
Revolution
one of the great feats of
civilization
He does not deny the accusation that his films helped to incite the January 2011 Egyptian
revolution, but he does not claim any of the credit. For Khaled Youssef, co-director, with
Youssef Chahine, of “Chaos” (2007), the “Arab Spring” extends across generations and
borders. In this interview he offers his vision of the events and their consequences for the
arts, society and international politics.
Khaled Youssef at
UNESCO for the
screening of his
film "Chaos", 13
April 2011.
© UNESCO/Michel
Ravassard
O
U
R
 G
U
E
S
T Every generation
played a role in
this revolution,
even those that
are no longer
with us.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
You are one of the eminent people who
supported the demands made by
protestors during the 25 January
revolution in Egypt, in which you also
participated. What were your
motivations?
I think my involvement was a foregone
conclusion. I took part in the great
majority of demonstrations against the
regime since the 1980s, as president of
the students’ union. Then in the 1990s, we
opposed government decisions,
especially on the Gulf War, but also
domestic policies that perpetuated
oppression and social injustices.
So, when young people used
Facebook to call for demonstrations (in
the first place against the repressive
practices of the police), it was quite
natural for me to be involved, from day
one. 
When we arrived in Tahrir Square to
demonstrate on 25 January 2011 there
were about 20,000 - 25,000 of us. The
number of demonstrators kept increasing
all the time, reaching about 80,000 by the
middle of the night. That was when the
authorities ordered the use of force to
disperse the demonstrators. I saw a
determination in the eyes of the younger
generation that I didn’t find in my
generation. These young people
stood up against the
police with a
tenacity I’ve never seen before in
demonstrations. I thought then it was a
sign  there could be a revolution. And I
was sure of this by Friday 28 January,
when we took to the streets, divided into
three groups. One went to the Moustafa
Mahmoud mosque, in the Mohandessin
quarter, another to the al-Istiqama
mosque, in Giza, and the third to the al-
Nour mosque, in the Abbassiya quarter,
all of them near Tahrir Square, in the city
centre. I was in the Moustafa Mahmoud
mosque group. As I couldn’t see the size
of the procession behind us, I climbed
onto the back of a pick-up truck. The
crowd stretched out before my eyes was
so big I couldn’t see where it ended.
That’s when I said, it’s a revolution.
Do you think the films you made with
the great Egyptian director Youssef
Chahine, like “Chaos” in 2007, helped
raise political awareness among
Egyptian youth?
I can’t claim any of the credit for starting
this revolution. That is both an accusation
– which I don’t deny – and an honour I do
not deserve. But it is true that some
people think our films, some of them
made in the 1980s, played an important
role in shaping the consciousness of the
younger generations who spearheaded
the revolution. 
The youth of a country is not a
“spontaneous generation”. This kind of
realization by young people is the result
of influences coming from all
forms of human
expression, from poetry to politics, music,
theatre and cinema. It would be quite
right then to say every generation has
played a role in this revolution, even
those that are no longer with us. So, for
me, the director Atef al Tayeb [1947-1995]
played a part, as did Youssef Chahine
[1926-2008] and all those who believed in
the will of the people and sided with the
ordinary people.
Do you think the 25 January revolution
will influence your next films, in the
sense that it marks the beginning of a
new era?
There is absolutely no doubt this
revolution will change not only the
nature of films, but also all other art forms
and literature. I think the social
renaissance we are hoping for will be
accompanied by a cultural renaissance.
There will be new ideas as well as new
ways of representing them, reflecting the
dialectic interaction between political
climate and artistic production.
If we go back to the revolution of 23
July 1952 [which led to the declaration of
the Republic of Egypt], it also marked a
turning point in cinema history. It even
influenced love stories. Public and private
worlds intermingled. It makes me think of
the great Syrian poet Nizar
Qabbani [1923-1998] who, in his poetry,
wondered if two lovers could meet on the
banks of the Nile or the Euphrates
without seeing planes overhead on their
way to kill Palestinians, Iraqis or Lebanese.
But having said this, I think we are
going to witness a great renaissance in
the arts and literature, perhaps not
K Scene from the Egyptian
revolution, January
2011.  
©
 D
av
id
 V
ild
e
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
immediately, because human expression
takes a while to mature. 
We are heading for some major
changes, and anyone who is not able to
keep pace with the new Egypt currently
being created will find themselves alone
and isolated.
Cinema is, in the first instance, a
vision. But a vision with no image of the
future remains sterile. So cinema has to be
firmly rooted in reality in order to reflect it
faithfully, while also being visionary.
It is too early to draw any firm
conclusions about the 25 January
revolution, but do you feel the outcomes
are satisfactory for the time being? 
I am absolutely satisfied with what this
revolution has achieved, and very
optimistic about the future. Revolution is
a science of change. First of all it has led
to a change in the political system. There
was the symbolic fall of the ruling regime,
which we are in the process of replacing
with a new one based on the principles of
liberty, equality, democracy and social
justice – all key demands of the
revolution. I think these principles, held
aloft by the protestors, will be the basis
for changes in the very model of Egyptian
society. After the revolution of 23 July
1952, the middle classes, that made up
5% of society, increased to 90 %. At the
time, this represented a radical change
for Egyptian society. So I believe the
recent revolution will, soon and in the
same way, transform the established
social order, as well as the nature and very
structure of society. It is not possible to
go against the will of the Egyptians who
carried out this revolution.
I have always thought that the will of
the people carries the will of God within
it, which no one can defeat. Egyptians
took matters into their own hands
through this initiative   and I am talking
about this great revolution that
constitutes one of the great
achievements of civilization. It seems to
me very unlikely that the coming
Because of Youssef Chahine, I started making films
“After the will of God, Youssef Chahine is the reason I became a film-maker. Not
only because he trained me in film-making and gave me the opportunity to
exercise my vocation, but really because, without him, I would never have worked
in this field. I met Youssef Chahine when I was studying to be an engineer. I never
imagined that one day I would make films. Youssef Chahine discovered in me a
talent that I was not even aware of and constantly denied. After three years he
ended up by telling me that there is no harm in trying. It was only then that I
realised he was right. That is why I feel I owe all of my success to him.
The first ten years, when I worked with Youssef Chahine as co-screenwriter
on his films and as assistant director, represented the most important stage of
my career. That is when I learned the trade. My first full-length feature “The
Storm”, which was made in 2000, opened the way to the second stage, which
was the real beginning of my life as a film-maker. Since then and up to 2011, I
have made 11 films, one a year on average. Some of these films are important
steps in themselves, like “Chaos”, Hina Maysara (Until Things Get Better) and
Dokkan Shehata (Shehata’s Shop). These films have attracted the most interest
within Egyptian society and won greater recognition either in terms of the
reviews or in festivals. The critics, in fact, agree that these films have helped to
change Egyptian public opinion on questions of politics, society and art.” 
Khaled Youssef
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l R
av
a
ss
a
rd
citizen participation, for democracy and
freedom of speech, as well as an
equitable sharing of national wealth. 
As for a multi-polar world, this has
been demonstrated throughout history.
When one single nation exercises its
power and directs the world, it can only
be a transition phase between two
stages in the progress of mankind. It is
obvious that the USA will retain its role
as a super-power, but it will be alongside
others, like Russia, Japan, China, Europe,
led by Germany or France, and the Arab
world, led by Egypt. In this way, the Arab
world will enter into the alliance of
nations as a sixth force, putting its own
cards on the table alongside other
leaders, when the interests of the major
powers are at stake. ■
L French version of the poster for Youssef Chahine's
film "Chaos".
5 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  
The youth of a country is not a
“spontaneous generation”. This
kind of realization by young
people is the result of influences
coming from all forms of human
expression, from poetry to politics,
music, theatre and cinema.
changes will be superficial, or that the
new government will be built on a
repressive form of state control like the
previous regime. 
You have said that we are moving
towards a more multi-polar world in
which the Arab world, led by Egypt, will
have a prominent place. Can we expect
a global transformation in the Arab
world that confirms this vision of
things?
[Laughs] It doesn’t surprise me the
whole world is talking about the “Spring”
of Arab revolutions. Everyone has
noticed it, so it is not an illusion. It was
possible to see the current wave of
revolutionary dynamism coming. And
when a regional power like Egypt goes
through a revolution, we can be sure
that it is real. This is not a form of
patriotic chauvinism, but historical and
geographical fact. A change in Egypt has
consequences for the entire Arab world.
Just as, over the past forty years, when
Egypt turned in on itself and refused to
play its true role, the whole Arab world
was weakened and Egypt’s importance
was undermined, too. But when Egypt
takes up its true place as a leader, the
Arab world will experience a second
renaissance, you can be sure about that.
The revolutions in other Arab
countries will not necessarily take the
same form as ours. Each Arab society has
its own ways of working, but each will, of
necessity, evolve and the different
regimes will no doubt make room for
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
New global partnership for
girls’ and women’s education
United States Secretary of State
Hillary Rodham Clinton and United
Nations Secretary-General Ban Ki-
moon were the special guests of
UNESCO Director-General Irina
Bokova on 26 May 2011 at the launch
of the Global Partnership for Girls’ and
Women’s Education. The new
partnership will focus mainly on
secondary education and adult
literacy, especially in Africa and Asia.
Two Prime Ministers, Cissé Mariam
Kaïdama Sidibé of Mali and Sheikh
Hasina of Bangladesh, participated in
the High-Level Forum held the same
day at UNESCO. Also present were the
The future of books
“The Book Tomorrow, the Future of the
Written Word” was the theme of the
second UNESCO World Forum on
Culture and Cultural Industries (FOCUS
2011), which was held from 6 to 8
June at the Villa Reale in Monza (Italy).
Issues surrounding the rise of
E-books were discussed at the event,
organized by UNESCO and bringing
together some 200 authors,
publishers, scientists, media
professionals, librarians, sociologists,
bloggers, researchers and decision-
makers from about 40 countries.
“Today, the book is facing the
most profound changes in its
history,” said the Director-General of
UNESCO, Irina Bokova, at the
opening. “No single company or
library can pretend to have the keys
to the future. This World Forum
perfectly embodies the spirit of
openness we must maintain.”
Some 800 students were able to
follow the Forum proceedings,
which were streamed to secondary
schools in the area. ■
Aga Khan, founder and chairman of
the Aga Khan Development Network
Foundation, and representatives of
several corporate giants participating
in the partnership including Nokia,
Procter & Gamble, GEMS Education,
Microsoft, Apple and the Packard
Foundation.
Globally, some 39 million girls of
lower secondary age are currently not
enrolled in either primary or
secondary education, while two thirds
of the world’s 796 million illiterate
adults are women. Only about one
third of countries have achieved
gender parity at secondary level. ■
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
ia
 F
re
in
d
o
rf
Forest
Whitaker,
UNESCO
Goodwill
Ambassador
In recognition of his artistic and
humanitarian commitment, American
actor Forest Whitaker was named a
UNESCO Goodwill Ambassador for Peace
and Reconciliation on 21 June 2011 at
Organization headquarters.
Born in 1951 in Texas (United States),
Mr. Whitaker has played a variety of
memorable film roles including
Ugandan despot Idi Amin in Kevin
Macdonald’s “Last King of Scotland”, for
which he received an Academy Award in
2006. He is currently directing the a film
entitled “Better Angels” – the title is
taken from Abraham Lincoln’s inaugural
speech – about child soldiers in Uganda.
Forest Whitaker is also known for his
humanitarian projects, which have
earned him the Humanitas Prize, an
award for film and television writing that
promotes human dignity and freedom,
and the Hope of Los Angeles Award.
As a UNESCO Goodwill Ambassador
for Peace and Reconciliation, Forest
Whitaker will lend his support primarily
to youth programmes, particularly those
concerned with peace education and
human rights. He will participate in the 7th
Youth Forum at UNESCO next October. ■
©
 2
0
0
7
 N
ig
e
l P
a
rr
y/
C
P
I
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  5 3
M
IL
E
S
T
O
N
E
S
ERRATUM: In the printed version of the English-language April-June UNESCO Courier, in the photo caption on page 11,
President of Argentina Cristina Fernández de Kirchner is incorrectly identified as “Prime Minister”.
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
MAB’s 40th anniversary
To celebrate its creation 40 years ago,
UNESCO’s Man and the Biosphere
Programme (MAB) organized an
international conference, “For life, for
the future. Biosphere Reserves and
climate change” on 27 and 28 June in
Dresden, Germany.
The conference assessed the
pioneering achievements of the
programme, which seeks to promote a
harmonious balance between
environmental preservation and human
activity. Topics on the agenda included
Biosphere Reserves as implementing
instruments for climate change policy.
Biosphere Reserves seek to
reconcile biodiversity conservation
and socio-economic development.
Local communities are active in
management, research, education and
training projects in the Biosphere
Reserves, making them sites of
excellence for experimentation in
sustainable development.
With 18 new sites added in 2011,
the Network now numbers 580 sites in
114 countries. For the first time,
Biosphere Reserves were inscribed in
Lithuania, Maldives, Saint Kitts and
Nevis, and Togo. ■
Memory of the World:
spotlight on Australia
While stone, paper and parchment
are the guardians of the memory of
our past, films, multimedia and the
internet are the guardians of the
present for future generations.
Inspired by this idea, UNESCO
launched the Memory of the World
programme in 1992 to safeguard
humanity’s documentary heritage.
Every two years, new documents
enrich the Memory of the World
collection, and a person or institution
is awarded the UNESCO/Jikji Memory
of the World Prize in recognition for
their contribution to preserving
documentary heritage and making it
accessible.
In 2011, 45 new documents and
collections from all over the world
were added to the Memory of the
World Register, which now numbers
238 items. The US$ 30,000 Prize,
wholly funded by the Republic of
Korea, was awarded this year to the
National Archives of Australia (NAA).
The award ceremony will be held in
September.
Established in 1960, the National
Archives shares its professional
know-how with experts and
interested members of the public
and makes available open source
tools for digital preservation. The
NAA has also demonstrated
innovation on the preservation of
documents written in iron gall ink (a
corrosive ink containing iron salts, in
use in Europe for many centuries). ■
M
IL
E
S
T
O
N
E
S
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/B
ru
n
o
 C
o
tt
a
co
rd
a
5 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . J U LY  S E P T E M B E R  2 0 1 1
Social media
according to
Shashi
Tharoor 
The first Indian politician to use
Twitter in a professional context gave
a lecture at UNESCO on 7 June 2011.
Shashi Tharoor is a Member of
Parliament in India and a former
Under-Secretary-General of the UN,
as well as the author of numerous
books in English and a columnist for
India's three best-known English
language newspapers. To his
UNESCO audience, he underlined the
increasing significance of social
media in democratization (including
the Arab Spring uprisings), disaster
management (as in Haiti or Japan)
and public diplomacy.
Dr Tharoor used the example of
US President Barack Obama’s visit to
Ghana shortly after his election. After
the White House announced his trip,
President Obama received over
250,000 questions from Africans
across the continent via Facebook
and Twitter.
“Social media is here to stay,” he
said. “We have to live with it. So let’s
make the most of it.”
Dr Tharoor is certainly making the
most of it. His use of his political
website (www.tharoor.in) and new
media like Twitter made him famous
in India. He went on to become the
first Indian celebrity to get 100,000
followers on Twitter. ■
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
ia
 F
re
in
d
o
rf
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
the world
Discovering
In just a few pages you can find all you need to know on various subjects related to
UNESCO and its programmes, including: world heritage sites, oceans, biosphere
reserves, the climate, the Earth, the slave trade, crafts and “About UNESCO”. The
Discovering the World Series is a collection in Arabic, English, French, Spanish and
Russian that makes subjects accessible to young readers (from age 10 on).  
To order volumes from the collection: 
www.unesco.org/publishing
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
World Heritage 
In June 2011, 25 new sites were inscribed on the
UNESCO World Heritage List.
A selection:
Prehistoric Pile dwellings around the Alps
(Switzerland, Germany, Austria, France, Italy,
Slovenia)
Hiraizumi – Temples, Gardens and
Archaeological Sites Representing the Buddhist
Pure Land (Japan)
The Persian Garden (Iran)
Lake System in the Great Rift Valley (Kenya)
Ningaloo Coast (Australia)
©
 p
h
 R
o
m
a
n
o
 M
a
g
ro
n
e
 /
 T
re
n
to
 A
lt
o
 A
d
ig
e
©
 M
a
so
u
d
 G
h
a
d
ir
i
©
 K
aw
a
sh
im
a
 P
ri
n
ti
n
g
 C
o
m
p
a
n
y
©
 T
o
u
ri
sm
 W
A
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
Ningaloo Reef, Australia
Pink flamingos on Lake
Nakuru, Kenya
Môtsû-ji, garden
representing the Pure
Land (Buddhist paradise),
Japan
Vestiges of prehistoric stilt
houses in Lake Ledro, Italy 
The Persian
garden Bagh e
Shahzadeh, Iran
]]>
</page>
</document>
