<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="213061eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ISSN 2220-2285
e-ISSN 2220-2293
Dreams of science 
Michal Meyer
I am because you are
Michael Onyebuchi Eze
Humanizing globalization
Mireille Delmas-Marty
Where is humanism going?  
Sanjay Seth  
Welcome to the Anthropocene
Ruth Irwin
The Muslim phase of humanism
Mahmoud Hussein
Child soldiers: a new life ahead
Forest Whitaker 
A special place for the imagination 
Antonio Skármeta
Humanism, 
a new 
idea 
Courier
THE UNESCO
United Nations 
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization,
OctoberDecember 2011
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Mireille Delmas-Marty
(France)
Liu Ji  
(China)
Mahmoud Hussein  
(Egypt)
Oliver Kozlarek
(Germany)
Cristovam Buarque 
(Brazil)
Michal Meyer
(Israel)
Antonio Skármeta
(Chile)
Paulette Dieterlen
(Mexico)
Milad Doueihi
Cathy Nolan
Forest Whitaker 
Roger Ross Williams
(USA)
Sanjay Seth  
(India)
Asimina Karavanta
(Greece)
Prudence Mabhena  
(Zimbabwe)
Michael Onyebuchi Eze 
(Nigeria)
Salvador Bergel
(Argentina)
In 1951, during a ‘Discussion on the
Cultural and Philosophical Relations
Between East and West’ held in the
capital of India, New Delhi, from 13 to
20 December, UNESCO endorsed the
idea of a new holistic humanism. The
world was recovering from a terrible
war that had sullied the myth of
technological progress dominating
Western culture. In a discussion
document entitled ‘Towards a New
Humanism’, the participants at the
meeting spoke of a “confused
intelligence that has lost its soul” and a
“crisis of humanism”. They advocated a
“spiritual revolution” and “common
spiritual progress” calling for greater
exchange between East and West (p. 27).
Six decades later, the challenges
facing the world have moved on, as has
UNESCO in 2011: 
Towards a new humanism and globalization that
rhymes with reconciliation
OUR AUTHORS
our understanding of the meaning of
humanism. In March 2011, UNESCO held
a meeting of its High Panel on Peace
and Dialogue among Cultures at the UN
headquarters in New York. Comprising
some twenty distinguished figures from
all over the world, the Panel agreed that
“rethinking peace and reconciliation
resonated with the quest for a New
Humanism for the 21st Century,” called
for by the Director-General of UNESCO,
Irina Bokova.
“In the context of globalization,” says
the final report on the meeting, “this
concept has to concentrate on cultural
diversity, dialogue in the age of the
Internet, and reconciliation between the
North and the South […] The new
humanism has to be an authentically
pluralist cosmopolitanism, inspiring
reflections and expressing aspirations
from everyone everywhere.”
According to a section of the report
entitled ‘Towards a new humanism and
reconciled globalization’, the purpose of
the new humanism is to “create a
climate of empathy, belonging and
understanding, along with the idea that
progress with respect to human rights is
never definitive and requires a constant
effort of adaptation to the challenges of
modernity. Those challenges cannot be
met without ethical principles, which
should be at the foundation of what was
aptly coined ‘a public realm of values’.” 
The conclusions of the Panel meeting, in March
2011, can be found at the following address:
http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0019/001923/1
92362e.pdf
Ruth Irwin
(New Zealand)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  3
Editorial – Irina Bokova, Director-General of UNESCO 5
HUMANISM: A NEW IDEA
Where is humanism going? – Sanjay Seth 6
I am because you are – Michael Onyebuchi Eze 10
What happened to hospitality? – Asimina Karavanta 14
Justice and dignity – Paulette Dieterlen 16
Towards a humanist turn – Oliver Kozlarek 18
The Muslim phase of humanism – Mahmoud Hussein  22
For a world of harmony – Liu Ji 25
UNESCO in 1951: Towards a new humanism  27
Humanizing globalization – Mireille Delmas-Marty 28
interviewed by Jasmina Šopova 
Digital humanism – Milad Doueihi 32
Welcome to the Anthropocene – Ruth Irwin 34
Dreams of science  – Michal Meyer 36
Bioethics: unimagined challenges – Salvador Bergel 39
Seven pointers for the future of mankind – Cristovam Buarque 41
OUR GUEST
Child soldiers: a new life ahead – Forest Whitaker 44
interviewed by Katerina Markelova
THE FUTURE OF THE BOOK
A special place for the imagination  ‒ Antonio Skármeta 47
OVERCOMING DISABILITY
The flight of Prudence ‒ The story of Prudence Mabhena  51
As told by Roger Ross Williams to Cathy Nolan  
MILESTONES
UNESCO welcomes 53
Mohamed Ould Abdel Aziz, Alsou Abramova,  Blaise Compaoré, Roger-Pol
Droit, Jorge Edwards, Ángeles González-Sinde, The Grandmothers of Plaza de
Mayo, Herbie Hancock, Cristina Fernández de Kirchner, Pascal Irénée Koupaki,
Julia Kristeva, Alassane Dramane Ouattara, Brigi Rafini, Roberto Toscano,
Abdoulaye Wade 
Courier
THE UNESCO
October–December 2011
United Nations 
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
64th year 
2011 – No. 4
The UNESCO Courier is   quarterly published  in seven
languages by the United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
7, place de Fontenoy 75352, Paris 07 SP, France
Free subscription to the Courier on line:
www.unesco.org/courier
Director of publication: Eric Falt
Editor-in-chief: Jasmina Šopova 
j.sopova@unesco.org
Managing editor: Katerina Markelova
k.markelova@unesco.org 
Editors: 
Arabic: Khaled Abu Hijleh 
Chinese: Weiny Cauhape
English: Peter Coles, Alison McKelvey Clayson 
and Dashika Ranasinghe
French: Philippe Testard-Vaillant 
Portuguese: Ana Lúcia Guimarães
Russian: Marina Yaloyan
Spanish: Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
English translation: Peter Coles and Lisa Davidson
Photos: Sophie Suberbère   
Design and layout: Baseline Arts Ltd, Oxford
Printing: UNESCO – CLD
Information and reproduction rights: 
+ 33 (0)1 45 68 15 64 . k.markelova@unesco.org
Documentation: Pilar Christine Morel Vasquez
Web platform: Chakir Piro and Van Dung Pham
Intern: Landry Rukingamubiri
With thanks to: Danica Bijeljac 
Articles and photos credited UNESCO may be reproduced
and/or translated for non-commercial purposes providing
the credit line reads “Reproduced from the UNESCO
Courier” and includes date and hyperlink. Photos without
UNESCO credit require special permission.
Articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO.
Photographs belonging to UNESCO may be reproduced
freely. Photos must carry the following caption: © UNESCO
and photographer's name. For high resolution, please
contact the Photobank: photobank@unesco.org
Boundaries on maps do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations of the
countries and territories concerned.
From the series
Faces à l'Âme by
French artist,
Benjamin Bini.
Dialogue between
cultures. Fusion of
contemporary and
traditional art.
©
 B
e
n
ja
m
in
 B
in
i -
 w
w
w
.b
e
n
ja
m
in
b
in
i.c
o
m
  
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
In this issue
“The affirmation of human commonality
and dignity is something that is no less
urgent today than at any time before,” says
Professor Sanjay Seth (India), in his
introduction to this special feature (p. 6).
He puts forward a number of thought-
provoking ideas on contemporary
humanism, like questioning the notion of
a singular Reason, the cohabitation of
different visions of morality developed
around the world, or the need for a global
form of justice. Issues like these are
discussed in depth from a range of
viewpoints by Nigerian-born Michael
Onyebuchi Eze (p. 10), Asmina Karavanta
from Greece (p. 14) and Paulette Dieterlen
from Mexico (p. 16).
The humanist turn that is currently
underway draws on humanist traditions in
all cultures, according to the German
philosopher Oliver Kozlarek (p. 18). Indeed
certain aspects of contemporary Islamic
philosophy have their roots in the very
idea of humanism (p. 22), says Mahmoud
Hussein, an Egyptian political scientist and
Islamic scholar. And the doctrines of
Confucius and Mencius could be seen as a
model for the development of the new
humanism imagined by Professor Liu Ji of
China (p. 25).
If humanist principles are not turned
into practice, though, humanism will
remain no more than wishful thinking.
In these times of globalization, we need
to make use of the “envisioning forces”
of law to forge a humanist form of
justice that is pluralist and open, says
the French lawyer, Mireille Delmas-
Marty (p. 28). Among other evidence to
support her case, she cites two major
challenges of modernity: climate
change and new digital and biomedical
technologies, which are also discussed
by Milad Doueihi (USA) (p. 32), Ruth
Irwin, from New Zealand (p. 34), Michal
Meyer of Israel (p. 36) and Salvador
Bergel from Argentina (p. 39).
To conclude this special feature, the
Brazilian senator, Cristovam Buarque
outlines his proposal for a new
humanism based on seven pillars:
planetary politics, respect for diversity,
respect for the environment, equal
opportunities, production controlled by
man, integration through education and
ethical modernity (p. 41).
Our guest for this issue is the
American actor and film-maker, Forest
Whitaker, recently appointed UNESCO
Goodwill Ambassador. He is committed
to the cause of child soldiers,
explaining what drew him to this
barren and tragic universe, so far
removed from the luxury of Hollywood
(p. 44).
The future of the book is a subject
close to the heart of the Chilean writer,
Antonio Skármeta. Author of the novel,
Burning Patience (which inspired
Michael Radford’s film Il Postino) he
predicts that the various types of media
will continue to exist, side by side  – the
digital book, that faithful ally of
research and information, and the
paper book, which is ideally suited to
“non-utilitarian imagination” (p. 47).
To mark International Day of Persons
with Disabilities (3 December), we will
be publishing an interview with the
American director Roger Ross Williams,
whose film Music by Prudence won him
an Oscar for best short documentary.
He tells of meeting a young
Zimbabwean woman, Prudence, who
lost both her legs, yet, through her
singing, managed to overcome a
number of obstacles, including
rejection by her family, discrimination
and poverty (p. 51).
Jasmina Šopova
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
© Fred de Noyelle/Godong
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  5
Editorial
Irina Bokova
Humanism is an age-old promise, as well as an
idea that is always new, endlessly reinventing
itself. The humanist project has been part of our
history since Antiquity, yet it shines like new in
every epoch. In the early years of the third
millennium the word can no longer have the
same meaning as it had during the Renaissance
in Europe, when it was forged on the image of
the ideal man, master of himself and the
universe. It also goes beyond the meanings that
the Enlightenment philosophers gave it, and
which have remained, despite their universalist
aspirations, restricted to a Eurocentric vision of
the world.
Respect for cultural diversity is a core element of
21st century humanism. It is a vital constituent
during these times of globalization. No single
culture has a universal monopoly. Each and every
one can contribute to the consolidation of our
shared values. 
The current threats to the planet’s precarious
ecological balance, the ethical problems raised
by digital and biomedical technologies, the
economic and political crises –these are all
global challenges that demand concerted
responses. The humanism that is emerging today
has to provide a framework for our common
thoughts and reflections on global issues. 
And, beyond the theory, humanist values have,
above all, to be translated into practice, in every
facet of human activity. The adoption of the
Millennium Development Goals in 2000
constitutes a humanist agenda par excellence. A
central preoccupation is the promotion of
women’s rights and gender equality. Humanism
today also has a feminine side. 
Humanist values form the very foundations of
the philosophy of UNESCO. Written into its
constitution, they have been guiding the actions
of our Organization for 65 years, in the
promotion of a peace that is “founded upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.”
Building a responsible world of solidarity is a
long-term endeavour that has to draw on all the
creative forces of humanity. Culture, education,
philosophy, science, information technology, law,
and international cooperation provide us with
the means. Building the ramparts of human
dignity in everyday life is not a Utopian quest.
Humanism is a promise we must all keep.
I Irina Bokova, 
Director-General of
UNESCO, at the
Organization's
headquarters, in
February 2010, during
the first meeting of the
High Level Panel on
Peace and Dialogue
between Cultures. In
March 2011, the Panel
met again at the UN
headquarters in New
York, to discuss New
Humanism for the 21st
Century. ©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
d
re
w
 W
h
e
e
le
r
Beyond the theory, humanist values
have above all to be translated into
practice.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
Humanism is, amongst other things, the claim or
intuition that all humans have something
fundamental in common, and that this
mandates equal entitlement to dignity and
respect. This, however, does not serve to
distinguish humanism from other doctrines and
understandings, including religious ones, which
treat all humans as sharing a commonality (an
immortal soul, etc) which commands respect. 
What historically distinguished humanism
from the many other affirmations of human
dignity and worth was the specific form that this
affirmation took; in particular, two supporting or
buttressing arguments which, in affirming
human equality and dignity, give this
affirmation its distinctively ‘humanist’ cast. These
are, first, that human worth is affirmed
independently of god(s), and more generally,
that ‘man’ replaces god as the measure of all
things. Second, that what all humans have in
common at once consists of, resides in, and can
only be discovered through, a singular
rationality. 
Thus understood, humanism is not simply a
Renaissance phenomenon, but something that
comes to full flower in the Enlightenment, in the
form of the idea of a universal humanity and a
singular Reason. 
In this essay, I ask whether the affirmation of
human commonality and worth is best secured
by an anthropological understanding of the
world, and by the search for a singular rationality.
In short, is the aspiration to affirm human
commonality and dignity best served by
humanism?
Man at the centre of the universe
Edward Said1 declares that the ‘core’ of
humanism is the secular notion that the
historical world is made by men and women, and
not by God, and that it can be understood
rationally. At the core of humanism, then, is a
philosophical anthropology, which in according
centrality to man diminishes (though it does not
necessarily eliminate) the role accorded to
god(s). Once the purposes and the acts of gods
explained the world of men; with humanism, to
understand the gods of men you have to
understand the men, for their gods are the
fantastical creation of their minds. 
If the centrality accorded to Man as maker of
meanings and purposes involves a diminution of
the role once accorded to god(s), it also involves
a separation, a distinction, between a human
world and a non-human one. There are two
worlds, one of impersonal processes and laws,
the other of human intentions and meanings. 
Nature is not a realm of purposes and
meanings, and so to gain knowledge of nature is
to gain understanding of the impersonal and
often lawlike forces that shape it; knowledge of
the historical or cultural world is knowledge of
purposes and meanings, for the historical world
is where the meanings and purposes of men are
apparent in the traces they leave behind.
Knowledge of nature, the preserve of the natural
sciences, can lead to mastery of natural forces;
knowledge of the historical world, the preserve
of the human and humanist sciences, leads to
self-knowledge. 
Humanism replaces a view of a single world
shot through with meaning and purpose, in
which the purposes and designs of nature are
prefigured and reflected in the social world, with
two worlds, one devoid of meaning and purpose,
and the other constituted of the meanings and
purposes humans have given their world in
different times and places.
humanism going?
SANJAY SETH 
At the heart of the notion of
humanism is that something that
we all share and which sanctions
our aspirations towards equality,
despite our differences. The
Enlightenment philosophers
looked for it in the crucible of a
singular rationality; today we
need to search at the crossroads of
different visions of morality.
Where is 
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  7
K Part of the cycle, 'Theoria
Sacra' by French painter and
sculptor Richard Texier,
reproduced with the kind
permission of the artist.
www.richardtexier.com
There have always been critics of these
presumptions, including Hamann2, Kierkegaard3,
Adorno4, Horkheimer5, and Heidegger6. In the
non-Western world, just as there were many
who accepted and celebrated the values that
were part of western humanism, there were also
always those, like Gandhi7, Césaire8 and Fanon9,
who were critics of a ‘civilisation’ that in
purporting to exalt Man frequently degraded
men.  Nonetheless, it is the account of the birth
of this philosophical anthropology delivered by
those who are the progeny of it that has been
dominant, and this account celebrates its
ancestry. 
I suggest, however, that circumstances have
changed such that a critical reconsideration of
this defining aspect of humanism is required.
What has changed is, above all, an
environmental crisis that calls into question the
absolute privileging of humans, as well as the
sharp distinction between man and nature, that
are characteristic of traditional humanism (see
pp. 34-35). It is not only and obviously that our
privileging of man may have something to do
with the despoliation of the conditions that
make human life sustainable, but also that the
very distinction between the world that men
make and the world that exists independently of
them is in the process of collapsing. With global
warming and the mass extinction of species,
humans have become geological, and not (as
before) simply biological agents.
‘What has changed is, above all, an
environmental crisis that calls into
question the absolute privileging of
humans, as well as the sharp distinction
between man and nature, that are
characteristic of traditional humanism.”
1. Edward Saïd [1935-2003], Palestinian American literary
theorist and founding figure in postcolonial studies. Author of
Orientalism (1978) and Humanism and Democratic Criticism
(2004.)
2. Johann Georg Hamann [1730-1788], German philosopher,
friend and intellectual opponent of Immanuel Kant. He was
convinced that faith and belief, rather than knowledge,
determine human actions.
3. Søren Kierkegaard [1813-1855], Danish Christian
philosopher, known as the Father of Existentialism.
4. Theodor Adorno [1903-1969], German philosopher and
social critic, and member, with Horkheimer and others, of the
Frankfurt School of social theory and philosophy. 
5. Max Horkheimer [1895–1973], German philosopher and
sociologist, best known for his “critical theory” that combined
Marxist-oriented political philosophy with social and cultural
analysis informed by empirical research. He co-authored with
Theodor Adorno Dialectic of Enlightenment (1947). 
6. Martin  Heidegger [1889-1976], German philosopher, known
for his phenomenological exploration of the question of being,
and for his critique of philosophical humanism. Read: The
Question Concerning Technology and Other Essays , Harper
Torchbooks,1977; “Letter on Humanism”, in Basic Writings, 1993.
7. Mahatma Gandhi [1869-1948], political and ideological
leader, father of the Indian nation. His philosophy of nonviolent
resistance inspired movements for civil rights and freedom
across the world.
8. Aimé Césaire [1913-2008], French poet from Martinique, one
of the founders of the Négritude movement. Read: Discourse on
colonialism, Monthly Review Press, 2000.
9. Frantz Fanon [1925-1961] French psychiatrist from
Martinique, active member of the Algerian struggle for
independence. Well known as a thinker on the issue of
decolonization.  Read: The Wretched of the Earth, Grove Press,
1963.©
 A
rc
h
iv
e
 S
O
M
O
G
Y
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The Enlightenment project
If anthropology (and a consequent division
between nature and society) is one defining
element of humanism, the conviction that what
all humans have in common resides in, and can
only be discovered through a singular rationality,
is another. The project to establish this was at the
heart of the Enlightenment.
In his “Was ist Aufklärung” Kant10 famously
defined Enlightenment as mankind coming to
maturity through the exercise of its reason. But if
the pre-modern notion of a morally ordered and
purposive universe had been (in Weber’s later
phrase11) ‘disenchanted’; if tradition and custom
no longer seemed the source of Reason, or
indeed, even reasonable; and if Hume’s sceptical
challenge12 raised the possibility of as many
reasons as there are persons; then what Reason
was this, and whose Reason? 
The most enduring answer to this puzzle was
offered by Kant. Its power lay, above all else, in
the argument Kant called ‘transcendental’.
Instead of ‘dogmatically’ asserting certain
propositions to be true, or seeking to identify, on
empirical grounds, a set of rational principles
common to all men, Kant instead asked what
sort of beings we had to be to have cognitions
and perceptions in the first place. The
transcendental question allowed Kant to deduce
universal categories of Reason which were not
derived from human experience, which is varied,
but was the basis for our having any experience
in the first place. Kant managed to make a
powerful argument for a Reason that was
universal, because notwithstanding the immense
variety of human experience, moralities and
notions of beauty, it was the precondition for
humans having any sort of experience, morality
or conception of beauty. 
Modern knowledge, as elaborated and
defended by Kant and by the Enlightenment
more generally, could now stake a claim to
having validated or proven itself, thus revealing
all earlier knowledge to have been speculation or
dogma. And of course this singular Reason,
which does not vary from culture to culture,
proved that all humans, irrespective of the
differences among them, were to be treated as
ends in themselves, and not means.
It is testimony to the vitality of the line of
argument initiated by Kant that the most
sophisticated contemporary attempts to salvage
or retrieve the Enlightenment project, while
acknowledging, as they must, that Reason is
inseparably bound with interests, culture and
power, all do so by returning to Kant. The
criticism that can be levelled at such arguments,
unsurprisingly, is similar to the criticism that was
levelled at Kant by his contemporaries and
immediate successors, namely that such proofs
presuppose what needs to be proven. 
The example of the political philosopher
John Rawls13 is especially instructive. In his A
Theory of Justice and some subsequent works
Rawls sought to draw upon Kant to develop a
theory of justice (see pp. 16-18) that would be
grounded upon a few rationally defensible
principles that would be acknowledged by
almost all. In later works, he acknowledges that
his theory of justice, and his defence of
liberalism, already presuppose a certain kind of
public political culture, one shaped by the Wars
of Religion in Europe, by the separation of
politics from religion thereafter, and so on. The
aim of his later theory is thus to elaborate a
pragmatic and procedural defence of a justice
which is acknowledged to be Western and
liberal, and cannot be passed off as ‘universal’.
(Rawls 1995 and 1996). 
That which Rawls reluctantly comes to
‘concede’ has been levelled as an accusation by
others, who have charged that Reason always
turns out to be not a placeless universal, but
European. Here are their arguments: What we
have learned to call Reason is not rationality as
such, but a historically and culturally specific way
of constructing and construing the world.
Moreover, treating this tradition as universal has
been an essential part of the story of, and
justification for, colonialism. Armed with the
certainty that it possessed nothing less than
universal Reason, Europe could proceed with its
colonial conquests, no longer principally in the
name of bringing the true word of god to the
heathen, but rather in the name of bringing
Enlightenment and civilization to the benighted.
What were being encountered were not other
traditions of reasoning and other ways of being
in the world, but unreason. The institutions and
practices that constituted colonialism, or came
in its wake, were now seen to be educating the
colonized, so that they too might one day reach
their maturity and be able to participate in and
exercise the Reason that was to be Europe’s gift
to them. 
Lest there be any confusion, let me be very
clear that I am not suggesting that the
intellectual and cultural tradition of modern
10. Immanuel Kant [1724-1804], German philosopher and a
pivotal figure in modern philosophy. “Answering the Question:
What Is Enlightenment?” is the title of an essay published in the
Berlinische Monatsschrift (Berlin Monthly), in 1784.
11. Max Weber [1864-1920], German sociologist and
economist.
12. David Hume [1711-1776], one of the most important
figures in the history of Western philosophy and the Scottish
Enlightenment.  Known especially for his philosophical
empiricism and scepticism.
13. John Rawls [1921-2002], political philosopher. His book A
Theory of Justice (1971), is considered as one of the primary
texts in contemporary political philosophy. Quoted works:
“Justice as Fairness: Political Not Metaphysical” in Philosophy
and Public Affairs, 1995; Political Liberalism, Columbia University
Press, 1996.
Modern
knowledge, as
elaborated and
defended by Kant
and by the
Enlightenment
more generally,
could now stake a
claim to having
validated or
proven itself, thus
revealing all
earlier knowledge
to have been
speculation or
dogma. And of
course this
singular Reason,
which does not
vary from culture
to culture, proved
that all humans,
irrespective of the
differences among
them, were to be
treated as ends in
themselves, and
not means.
8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Sanjay Seth (India), held teaching or
research positions in Sydney,
Melbourne (Australia) and Tokyo
(Japan), before joining Goldsmiths,
University of London (United
Kingdom) in 2007, where he is
Professor and Head of Politics and
co-Director of the Centre for
Postcolonial Studies.
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  9
J “Homo Mundo”, sculpture by French artist,
Richard Texier, reproduced by kind permission
of the author.
www.richardtexier.com
Europe was the only one to think that it was
right and all others wrong, or the only
one that has sought to impose its
vision on others. Neither the modern
age nor Europe has had a monopoly
on arrogance or dogmatism. What I
am suggesting is that the
Enlightenment heritage – the
European conviction in a context
and tradition-free Reason – made it
possible for Europe to conquer and
rule not in the name of a tradition
that claimed to be superior to all
others, but in the name of something
that did not see itself as a tradition at all.
This was a knowledge which claimed not
only to be true, but declared itself to be
deduced from nothing less than
Reason itself, rather than being
grounded in the ideals and practices
of real historical communities. 
In the era after decolonization,
it should however be all too clear
that what humans have in
common, and what may allow us
to ‘ground’ their claims to dignity
and respect, neither resides in nor
can be discovered by a singular
Reason. All attempts to do so have
ended up, whether wittingly or
unwittingly, by substituting ‘European’
or ‘Western’ for ‘human’. The idea of a
singular Reason, although deeply
rooted in Western culture and
thought, cannot be sustained, and
needs to be critically re-examined.
New avenues to explore
I began this essay by suggesting
that humanism consists of an
affirmation that all humans,
notwithstanding their many
differences, have something
important in common, and
thus that all humans should
be equally accorded respect
and dignity; and that this
rests upon two supporting
arguments/presumptions.
One of these is a
philosophical
anthropology, which
makes the ‘discovery’
that men are the source
of meanings and values,
not gods, and discovers
also a domain of
nature that is devoid of
meaning and purpose,
an inert object that is
subject to human
knowledge and manipulation. The second is
the presumption that the counterpart of a
common humanity is a singular Reason. 
I have gone on to argue that
neither of these arguments or
presumptions can be sustained; they
were never true, and are more
demonstrably untrue today than
ever before. These were not ‘truths’
finally discovered, but rather have
been a particular way of construing
and constructing the world. As such,
they have been the source of many
human achievements; but they have also
entailed great costs, costs which are
especially apparent today, as the exaltation
of man despoils that which is the very
condition for any sort of human life; as the
distinction between the human and the
natural collapses; and as it becomes
increasingly clear that what all humans
have in common neither resides in, nor is
to be discovered through, the search for a
singular Reason that abstracts from the
differences that characterise humankind. 
The affirmation of human commonality
and dignity is something that is no less urgent
today than at any time before. Because such an
affirmation can plausibly be seen as being, in
some sense, at the core of humanism, we
cannot reject humanism, but rather need to
re-found and to reinterpret it. I suggest that
a reinterpreted and viable humanism, will
be one in which our moral intuitions
regarding human commonality and dignity
no longer rest upon a questionable
anthropocentrism or on dubious claims to
a universal Reason. I further suggest that
such a reinterpretation will be the
product of a dialogue between different
civilizations and moral perspectives,
rather than a declaration that one moral
perspective (that of the modern West) is
the correct one. ■
©
 F
ra
n
ço
is
-X
av
ie
r 
D
u
b
o
is
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
For many people in the Bantu language countries of Africa, the term Ubuntu/botho
encapsulates all the qualities of a respected member of society. But the term is also used
by Africanist scholars as a critique of colonialist doctrine and even forms the core of a
humanist ideology upon which the new democratic South Africa is constructed.
I am because 
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  1 1
MICHAEL ONYEBUCHI EZE 
Ask anyone on the streets of Harare,
Johannesburg, Lusaka or Lilongwe (in Southern
and Eastern Africa) what they understand by
Ubuntu/botho and they will probably list the
virtues to which a person in these societies is
expected to aspire – such as compassion,
generosity, honesty, magnanimity, empathy,
understanding, forgiveness and the ability to
share. Indeed, Ubuntu/botho (or the local
equivalent in the various Bantu language
groups)1 is understood as the very definition of
‘person’ or ‘personhood’. But the term
Ubuntu/botho impregnates societies in the
region to a much greater extent, forming the
basis for communitarian ethics, discourses on
identity and even a bourgeoning pan-African
ideology. 
In terms of contemporary Africanist
discourse, though, Ubuntu/botho is best
understood as a critique of the logic of
colonialism – the process of attempting to
“humanize” or “civilize” non-Western cultures
through colonization. Colonialism was a
powerful and condescending narrative that
thrived through a pretext of “humanizing” or
“civilizing” non-Western peoples. The
consequences of this false doctrine of humanism
were to become the bedrock of colonial practices
in Africa, as an institutionalized form of social
Darwinism2 nurtured by racialist capitalism. 
Racialist capitalism is a theory in which a
person’s race determines his or her life choices or
potential, like the kind of job to have, where to
live, the kind of person to marry, the kind of
school to attend, and so on. The effects of this
theory on the South African experience can be
seen in the many draconian laws aimed at
curbing the potentialities of the black person.
This system motivated the 1913 Land Act that
forbade blacks from buying lands in South Africa;
the colour bar of 1918; the Bantu Education Act
of 1953 which abolished the teaching of African
history; the job Reservation Act which gave
priority to whites in matters of employment; the
various segregation policies from as early as 1907
that restricted the movement of blacks and
reduced them to mere instruments of labour. 
As early as 1858, the South African-Boer
constitution had already ruled out any form of
equality between blacks and whites in matters of
State or Church. The prevailing argument was
that forced labour was ordained by God as a
divine privilege for the white race to claim
authority of domination over blacks, as the then
president of the South-African Republic, Paul
Kruger, informed his Volksraad [Peoples’ Council]
in August 1897 – “Our constitution wants no
equality and equality is also against the Bible,
because social classes were also applied by God.”
And, later, in his Memoirs, he wrote: “…where
there were only a handful of white men to keep
hundreds of thousands of blacks in order,
severity was essential. The black man had to be
1. The term Ubuntu/botho is generally derived from a
vernacular mode of referring to a ‘person’ among the peoples
of southern, eastern, (some western) and central Africa,
generally referred to as the Bantu language groups. The Shona
call a ‘person’ in the singular munhu and in the plural vanhu.
The Zulu, Xhosa, and Ndebele call a ‘person’ umuntu in the
singular and abantu in the plural. The Sotho and Tswana refer
to a ‘person’ as muthu in the singular and bathu in the plural.
2. A derivative of Charles Darwin’s theory of natural selection,
Social Darwinism means that stronger nations have the moral
authority or even an obligation to conquer, subjugate and
dominate weaker nations. It is simply the natural order of
things. 
Colonialism was a
powerful and
condescending
narrative that
thrived through a
pretext of
“humanizing” or
“civilizing” non-
Western peoples.
The consequences
of this false
doctrine of
humanism were
to become the
bedrock of
colonial practices
in Africa, as an
institutionalized
form of social
Darwinism
nurtured by
racialist
capitalism. 
©
 k
h
a
n
yi
se
la
.o
rg
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
1 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
taught that he came second, that he belongs to
the inferior class which must obey and learn.” 
This mindset would form the political
blueprint for South Africa’s colonial history and
was the foundation upon which the new South
Africa gained national sovereignty.  But if the
South African colonial state had been founded
upon the ideology of social Darwinism, what
should be the ideological foundation of the new,
democratic, independent state? This is where
Ubuntu/botho comes in. 
As a public discourse, Ubuntu/botho has
gained recognition as a peculiar form of African
humanism, encapsulated in the following Bantu
aphorisms, like Motho ke motho ka batho babang;
Umuntu ngumuntu ngabantu (a person is a
person through other people). In other words, a
human being achieves humanity through his or
her relations with other human beings. But this
understanding does not need to generate an
oppressive structure, where the individual loses
his or her autonomy in an attempt to maintain a
relationship with an ‘other’. 
Many Africanist scholars would describe
Ubuntu/botho as an arbitrary communitarian
ethics that admits the individual’s good and
welfare only as a secondary necessity. But a
critical reading of this condition of relationship
to others might suggest that a person’s humanity
flourishes through a process of relation and
distance, of uniqueness and difference. A
realization of the subjective gifts (of humanity)
we bear to each other motivates an
unconditional desire to view and harness other
people’s uniqueness and difference, not as a
threat but as a complement to one’s own
humanity. The Christian African philosopher, J. S.
Mbiti’s now classic phrase, “I am, because we are;
and since we are therefore I am”, captures a key
feature of this kind of subjective formation
through relation and distance. Mbiti subscribes
to an affirmation of human subjectivity that puts
communitarian good before individual good. I
disagree, however, with this prioritizing of the
community over the individual. Neither is prior.
The relation with the ‘other’ is one of subjective
equality, where the mutual recognition of our
different but equal humanity opens the door to
unconditional tolerance and a deep appreciation
of the ‘other’ as an embedded gift that enriches
one’s humanity.
A unifying ideology?
Within the contemporary history of South Africa,
there are three main ways in which Ubuntu has
been understood:
First is the assumption that Ubuntu is merely
an anachronistic philosophy produced by African
academics. Here Ubuntu functions as an
alternative narrative to replace colonial logic, a
desperate discourse of identity – a
sledgehammer kind of ethics that helps us to
deal with the traumas of modernity and
globalization. The argument is that, since we
cannot positively identify Ubuntu as an authentic
historical culture, it remains an invented
discourse, in an alien format. Being ‘invented’,
Ubuntu is more or less an ‘empty concept’
through which Africanist academics perform a
supple manoeuvre of identity formation using an
‘imported’ cultural nationalism. Evidence is
sought from different African cultural traditions
to homogenize a range of values that are then
represented as Ubuntu. Ubuntu is thus
generalized as a universal African value,
irrespective of the actual historical context of the
societies that practice it. However, Ubuntu does
not need to generate a homogenous historicity3
to become an authentic African value. And
neither does a lack of historical authenticity
deprive Ubuntu of such normative legitimacy. 
The second conjecture is that Ubuntu has the
character of an ideology, appropriated for
political ends, as was evident in its application
during the Truth and Reconciliation Commission
(TRC), and the initial draft constitution of South
Africa. As an ideology it can be applied as a
‘magic wand’ to deal with every emergent social
crisis. And as an ideology, its usage can also be
abused and ceases to be an ethical value,
becoming a value-commodity which is then
appropriated to create a positive corporate or
brand image, as in ‘Ubuntu security’, ‘Ubuntu
restaurant’, ‘Ubuntu linux’, ‘Ubuntu cola’, etc. 
The third sequence is a vision of history in
which Ubuntu/botho is considered within the
historical context in which it emerged. Being
historical, it also gains an emotional and ethical
legitimacy, since it is signified as a good that
remains internal to the practices of a community
where Ubuntu/botho values are invoked. 
The question, then, is whether
Ubuntu/botho, construed as an ideology,
precludes all possibilities of creative historicity?4
My answer is no! The context in which
Ubuntu/botho emerged (even as an ideology) in
the political history of South Africa was an
attempt to configure a theory of political
succession that is consistent with the vision of an
3. The idea that African historiography is a single historical
narrative irrespective of many cultures, people(s) and traditions
that inhabit the geographical place called Africa. 
4. Creative historicity argues that history is neither a fixation on
the past nor a mere chronology of events. Good history is open
to multiple influences and contexts. 
A beach for Whites only in
Cape Town, South Africa, in
January 1970
As a public discourse, Ubuntu/botho 
has gained recognition as a peculiar
form of African humanism.
Everyday life under
Apartheid
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
emergent national imaginary. Irrespective of its
doubtful origins, the moment at which
Ubuntu/botho became a public virtue that is
easily recognized by all South Africans,
constitutes its historicity. The lack of authentic
historical origins (in written records, or as a
nuanced cultural dogma) does not neutralize its
credibility. 
Understood as a narrative of a new national
consciousness, Ubuntu not only offers an
emotional legitimacy to displace the old political
order; it also gives the new political order a
sense of identity and political purpose. While the
old order thrived on a notion of citizenship
based on discrimination and difference, the new
regime attempted to gain legitimacy by trying
to forge a notion of democratic citizenship that
thrives through inclusion and civic virtues. But
the new dispensation has to be based on a
system that excludes the oppressive structures
of the past, and adopts instead a system of
values that is built on a notion of rights and the
unconditional dignity of the human person. At
this point, the ‘notion’ of Ubuntu assumes an
ethical character in forging a new sense of
national identity. 
Critics of the use of Ubuntu as a unifying
ideology argue that it is merely an incoherent,
invented ethics with no history. But ideologies
do not predate history; they emerge as a
response to specific issues within a historical
epoch, challenging, correcting or displacing a
mindset (or old ideology). The challenge, then, is
to see whether Ubuntu can be rehabilitated as
an ideology, focusing primarily on its normative
essence, or whether the lack of historicity will
always deny it any real substance. 
At the same time, the practice of the human
virtues through which a Bantu becomes a
Munhu, Umuntu, or a Muntu (etc) is not external,
but internal to the context where it is practiced.
Yet, Ubuntu has been able to transcend this
moral relativism by generating an ethical
practice, which all South Africans, irrespective of
their socio-cultural background, have judged to
be good. This evaluative norm was to become
the inspiration for building the new South
Africa, guarded by the need for reconciliation
and not division; forgiveness, not resentment;
understanding, not vengeance; and ubuntu, not
victimization (see the Truth and Reconciliation
Commission Documents of South Africa). These
were time-honoured values to which most
South Africans already aspired, paving the way
for a new national imaginary. And this gives
Ubuntu its moral authority. ■
Michael Onyebuchi Eze is a Nigerian-American
visiting research scholar at the Center for African
Studies at Stanford University, (USA). He received
his PhD in Intellectual History from Universität
Witten-Herdecke (Germany) and taught African
studies at the universities of Augsburg and
Frankfurt. He is author of two books, The Politics of
History in Contemporary Africa and Intellectual
History in Contemporary South Africa (Palgrave-
Macmillan, 2010).
O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  1 3
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/N
.M
c 
K
e
n
n
a
 D
u
rr
e
l
©
 U
n
it
e
d
 N
a
ti
o
n
 P
h
o
to
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
1 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
respective communities and cultures,
often diasporic, multilingual, and
intercultural. 
Because humanism is no longer
solely the product of European
monarchies and empires whose colonial
projects grounded their ideological
imperatives in Enlightenment ideals;
because it no longer defines the nation
exclusively as a monocultural,
monolingual construct, it is “making a
comeback” as a “newer variant, one that
reprises an earlier humanism in which
what is common to humans is not
rationality but the ontological fact of
mortality, not the capacity to reason but
vulnerability to suffering.”3
human being and a certain kind of
society, namely that of western cultural
values. 
The discrepancy between the
promise of humanism and its
instrumental role in colonialism,
imperialism, and the slave trade,
generated a severe critique of humanism
and its ethically and politically
contradicting principles that reached a
climax in the 1960s. This systematic
deconstruction of humanism as an
incontestable universal1 (see pp. 6-9)
has intensified the need to reconfigure
humanism from the perspective of
those who were “only recently
recognized as humans”2 and their
Two world wars, concentration camps,
sweat shops, and the other apparatus of
global capitalism whatever their
qualifying differences, are defining
events of the twentieth century as
having a very dark history. The victims
of anticolonial and civil wars must also
be factored in. This sombre tableau is
evidence of the destructive potential
that was lurking beneath the cloaks of
Enlightenment philosophers once their
humanistic discourses were
transformed into an ideological
privilege of only a certain kind of
An ongoing series of crises and a growing number of refugees have transformed the socio-
cultural landscape of the contemporary world.  To address the challenges these changes
have wrought, a new kind of humanism is required– one capable of responding to the
needs of communities made up of different cultures that are forever multiplying.
What happened 
to hospitality?
ASIMINA KARAVANTA 
©
 M
a
ri
e
.C
.C
a
m
b
o
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
J Demonstration in support of illegal migrant
workers. France, 2009
cultures. These ideas prompted heated
debate after they appeared in his
posthumously published Humanism and
Democratic Criticism. For Said, as for
others, humanism, “as the exertion of
one’s faculties in language in order to
understand, reinterpret, and grapple
with the products of language in
history, other languages, and other
histories,” […] “is not a way of
consolidating and affirming what ‘we’
have always known and felt, but rather a
means of questioning, upsetting, and
reformulating so much of what is
presented to us as ‘commodified’,
packaged, uncontroversial, and
uncritically codified certainties.” 
The need to engage the ‘complexity
of history’ by learning how to remember
the forgetting of those constituencies
and their heretofore marginalized and
rejected cultures has become an
imperative in the present age. If the 20th
century is the “age of exilic
consciousness,” as Said avers at the end
of Culture and Imperialism,5 the 21st
century is the age of anthropos, that is,
of the human species. Anthropos means:
having a human face.
Intercultural society 
The ancient Greeks believed the human
being’s specificity in relation to other
species was that he lived in a society
ruled by law, in other words, in a city
state (polis, in Greek). The philosopher
Aristotle [4th century BCE] developed
the idea of human beings as “political
animals” dwelling in the city [bios
politicos in Greek]. Closer to our time
the German-born American
philosopher Hannah Arendt has
depicted the modern day refugee as a
bios politicos par excellence, but one
bereft of a polis.
Humanism as a necessity
In view of the growing number of
refugees and stateless people, of the
successive economic and political crises,
the rise of fundamentalisms,
xenophobia and new forms of racism,
and the subsequent revolts of masses
demanding democracy, humanism
emerges as part of the “need” – in the
words of the Palestinian-American
writer Edward Said (1935-2003) − for
“deintoxicated, sober histories that
make evident the multiplicity and
complexity of history without allowing
one to conclude that it moves forward
impersonally, according to laws
determined either by the divine or by
the powerful.”4
Said is known for having analyzed
the historical, philosophical and literary
values of Western humanism; he has
studied Western humanism’s violent
ideological impact on non-Western
Today, the political and economic
crises raging in the world are not only
rapidly increasing the numbers of
refugees but also stripping those
recognized as citizens of a long-
established right to work and a right to
education. The citizen now becomes an
a-polis citizen, one who is being
deprived of rights. In the squares of
Madrid, Cairo and Athens, to mention
only a few recent cases of mass revolt,
the stateless refugee meets the a-polis
citizen. Even if their demands are
different, they are bound by their shared
claims to a democratic ideal that
recognizes the anthropos as its first and
most fundamental principle. Despite the
differences in their political and
economic positions, both the stateless
refugee and the a-polis citizen require
that a new polis be configured. In this
new polis, where diversity of languages,
traditions and myths constitute a daily
reality, the practice of translation and
transculturation are practices of survival.
One of humanism’s current
challenges is how to develop conditions
favourable to intercultural societies. In
other words, how to create societies
1. See Judith Butler, Ernest Laclau and Savoj Žižek,
Contingency, Hegemony, Universality. London & New
York: Verso, 2000.
2. See contribution of Joan Anim-Addo, “Towards a
Post-Western Humanism Made to the Measure of
Those Recently Recognized as Human.” Edward Said
and Jacques Derrida: Reconstellating Humanism and
the Global Hybrid. Eds. Mina Karavanta and Nina
Morgan. Newcastle: Cambridge Scholars Press,
2008. 250-274. 
3. Honig, Bonnie. “Antigone’s Two Laws: Greek
Tragedy and the Politics of Humanism.” New Literary
History, 41.1 (2010): 1-33.
4. Said, Edward, Humanism and Democratic
Criticism, New York: Columbia University Press,
2004.
5. Said, Edward, Culture and Imperialism, Vintage
Books, 1993.
K Exercise in a Lebanese secondary school to teach
about dialogue, tolerance and peace, in 2003.
Photo : Bassam Jamalelddine © UNESCO/Aspnet
“Only where things can be seen
by many in a variety of aspects
without changing their identity,
so that those who are gathered
around them know they see
sameness in utter diversity, can
worldly reality truly and reliably
appear.”
Hannah Arendt
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
1 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
6. Derrida, Jacques. Of Hospitality. Trans. Rachel
Bowlby. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2000.
7. Butler Judith. Precarious Life. The Powers of
Mourning and Violence. London & New York: Verso,
2004.
Asimina Karavanta holds a
doctorate in comparative literature
and teaches at the University of
Athens.  She is specialized in
postcolonial literatures and theories,
and is the co-author with Nina Mogan
of Edward Said and Jacques Derrida:
Reconstellating Humanism and the
Global Hybrid, Cambridge Scholars
Publishing, 2008.
that will allow both the refugee and the
native born citizen to establish exchanges
that are at once durable and productive.
When viewed as a common field shared
by multiple alliances and potential
affiliations, this intercultural society
presupposes a radical reconfiguration of
the institutions and social, educational
and political discourses that should be
addressing the needs of expanding
intercultural communities in the nation-
states and their supranational formations. 
Interculturality is a condition, both
ontological and political, that has
already transformed the nation-state
from within. But for human beings to be
socially and politically recognized as
singular yet also equal, it is necessary to
reform education so as to enable the
blossoming of an intercultural learning
and living that is − in the words of
French philosopher Jacques Derrida −
continuously opening the laws of
hospitality to the foreigner to whom
“hospitality is due.”6
Building this kind of humanism,
hospitable to the one who remains a
foreign anthropos, and which by
reconstituting its laws and discourses,
speaks to her/his often radically
different ontological and political
condition is the task of the humanities
today. According to the American
feminist scholar Judith Butler, this task is
“no doubt to return us to the human
where we do not expect to find it, in its
frailty and at the limits of its capacity to
make sense.”7 In other words, it is to
think of the human as the anthropos
always already at stake, always already
at risk, the face whose gaze is fixed on
us in an open and persistent invitation
for justice on a planetary scale. ■
Justice
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Despite the numerous treaties,
agreements and international summit
meetings of the twentieth century, and
the ongoing goal of combating poverty
and reducing inequality in the world,
one fact is clear: far from declining,
poverty continues to grow. According
to the World Bank, 1.4 billion people
were living below the poverty level in
2008, surviving on less than $1.25 per
day, per person. The planet now
supports nearly 7 billion people, which
means that 20 per cent of the world’s
population do not have sufficient
resources to meet basic needs; these
people suffer inhumane treatment and
are doomed to subsist in conditions of
social, economic and political exclusion. 
There is a theory in moral
philosophy that deals directly with
poverty and inequality: ‘distributive
justice’. This concept examines ways to
alter the principles governing the
distribution of goods and resources,
when these principles do not respect
the rights, worth and needs of each
person. 
The various facets of this theory
arise from the particular vision of the
human being that underpins one policy
of distribution rather than another. For
example, an approach that views the
most underprivileged people as
passive, unable to set goals for
themselves and determine their own
needs, gives rise to paternalistic
policies. Those receiving the distributed
benefits cannot voice their opinions nor
have any power over their essential
rights, as others are deciding in their
stead. This occurs frequently in many
countries. In Mexico, for example, as
part of a social housing programme,
the government decided to put a
laundry room into every house. But
women were used to taking their
washing down to the river. They turned
the laundry rooms into family shrines,
where their offerings ended up
blocking the pipes. 
Another version of distributive
justice defines individuals essentially as
economic agents seeking to ‘maximize
outcome,’ in other words, to boost their
income and/or their purchasing power.
Proponents of this theory, which
measures costs in monetary units and
results in terms of ‘units of outcome,’
push for policies geared toward
increasing the units of outcome for the
most impoverished, to improve their
well being and to mitigate their
poverty. In this case, priorities are set
according to their value for money. For
example, in the USA a decision was
taken regarding medical care that
favoured State funding for operations
to remove tonsils, rather than for renal
dialysis, even though dialysis patients
are far more seriously ill. The decision
meant reaching a larger number of
people at lesser cost.
If, however, we conceive of
individuals not only as means but also
as ends, the ensuing distribution
policies must foster better economic
and social conditions so that the
beneficiaries can work toward
achieving their life goals. This idea is
based on the concept of the human
being as an autonomous and worthy
individual, able to choose from among
the various options at hand. This is
certainly the most ethical and humanist
position offered by distributive justice.
The Mexican “Progresa” programme is
an example. Rather than offering food
handouts, it runs education and
information campaigns on health and
nutrition and allocates subsidies to
families, leaving them free to decide
how to use the money.
Global justice
That being so, should distributive
justice opt for the individual or the
social group as the unit of distribution?
This question pitches liberal thinkers,
who have adopted an egalitarian
position, against those who promote
more communitarian theories. The
latter maintain that individual-based
social policies are deficient in that they
fail to take into account the fact that
human beings do not live in isolation,
but are an inseparable part of a culture
or social group that defines their
identity. Hence the importance, for
communitarian theorists, of factoring in
the history and peculiarities of each
community — as each social group
Hundreds of millions of people suffer from hardship and
poverty throughout the world, a situation that sanctions a
philosophical approach promoting distributive justice. This
theory underpins a truly humanist intervention when it is
dispensed with respect for the dignity of the individual, his
or her autonomy and personal responsibility.
dignity
PAULETTE DIETERLEN 
and
J Outside the Brazilian Supreme Federal Court, in
Brasilia, 1998
© UNESCO/Ivaldo Alves
If, however, we conceive of
individuals not only as means but
also as ends, the ensuing
distribution policies must foster
better economic and social
conditions so that the
beneficiaries can work toward
achieving their life goals. This idea
is based on the concept of the
human being as an autonomous
and worthy individual, able to
choose from among the various
options at hand. 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  1 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
1 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
develops specific forms of production,
redistribution and consumption of
goods and services.
Proponents of individual-based
distributive justice maintain that
communities are not uniform in nature
and that it is therefore impossible to
meet the criteria of distribution without
giving priority to the individuals who
form these communities.
Yet a third version of distributive
justice exists, known as ‘global justice.’
This theory transcends the traditional
concept of the nation-state, focusing
instead on the problems posed by
poverty and inequality on a worldwide
scale. Theorists of global justice support
a system of international institutions
responsible for redressing injustices
committed against individuals as
residents of the planet, rather than as
members of a community, or citizens in
a particular country.
From a humanist viewpoint, these
three theories — individual,
communitarian and global — share the
same goal: to implement policies of
distributive justice, by viewing people
as worthy individuals capable of
exercising their own autonomy. The
Mexican government is currently using
incentives as part of its policies to
combat poverty – people are able to
express their needs and choose what
seems to them most essential. This
helps to strengthen the beneficiaries’
sense of responsibility and their ability
to make decisions.
If the person, in and of him- or
herself, forms the cornerstone of this
philosophy, and if policies to improve
quality of life with decent conditions of
equality and respect for rights are
proposed, distributive justice can be
said to comply with the values of
humanism. ■
In the 1960s social movements all around
the globe started to modify their
agendas. Instead of looking for universal
solutions — which were increasingly
identified with totalitarian ambitions —
they began to pay more attention to the
recognition of cultural, ethnic and sexual
differences and identities. The student
protests were perhaps the most
emblematic sign of a profound
reassessment of the role that culture
plays in human life that was also being
played out in theoretical debates and in
politics throughout the 1960s and 70s.
Simultaneously, intellectual and
academic debates began to be interested
more in culture and initiated what today
is widely recognized as a ‘cultural turn’ in
the social sciences and humanities.1
This ‘cultural turn’ strengthened and
propagated a number of values,
including cultural pluralism and an
awareness that, in our modern world, it
is important to reflect upon the
coexistence of distinct cultures and
forms of life, while at the same time
resisting the temptation to reduce this
plurality once more to an artificial,
abstract unity dominated by one set of
interests. And this provides us with a
glimpse of the critical potential of the
‘cultural turn’. In contrast to the idea that
all human cultures are being propelled
towards the same evolutional end-goal
(telos) — an idea that was promulgated
by the influential ‘modernization
theories’ in the first decades after World
War II — the cultural turn rescues the
idea that processes of civilization and
culture – and their results – do not
follow a logical, predetermined path.
But, however important the cultural
turn may have been, I also believe that
culturalism has given rise to a climate of
cultural relativism that is not only
dangerous but also incorrect. The errors
in these positions, though evident, have
been ignored for a long time. One of the
Paulette Dieterlen is a Mexican
philosopher and researcher, member
of the Instituto de Investigaciones
Filosóficas at the Universidad Nacional
Autónoma de México (UNAM), and an
expert on distributive justice and
public policy. She has published,
among other books, La pobreza: un
estudio filosófico (Poverty: A
Philosophical Approach), Fondo de
Cultura Económica/Instituto de
Investigaciones Filosóficas, 2002.
Instead of looking for the universal in biological nature, a
recent humanist turn in the social sciences and humanities
is focusing on what all human beings around the globe
share, without neglecting their differences. And instead of
thinking that a universal humanist culture has to be
invented or imposed on other cultures, the new approach
believes that universal ideas and values are already present
in all cultures. It also acknowledges that people
everywhere on the planet are sharing dehumanizing
experiences – which should encourage us to consider what
it means to live a humane and dignified life.
Towards a
Humanist 
turn  
OLIVER KOZLAREK 
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  1 9
most obvious is that different cultures
are incommensurable and cannot be
reconciled, while in fact they share
many affinities and similarities. 
The work of the German
anthropologist, Christoph Antweiler,
gives a spectacular account of how
many ‘norms, values and ideals’
different cultures share2. Antweiler
suggests that we often do not see these
similarities because we do not want to.
However, he also suggests that if only
we looked for similarities we would find
them. With the right attitude, Antweiler
tells us, we are able to see formulations
of human rights not only in the ‘West’
but also in Confucianism, Buddhism
and Islam. Antweiler’s main argument is
that the idea of the ‘Clash of
Civilizations’ — put forward by Samuel
Huntington, and which proposes that
different cultures are profoundly
incommensurable — is wrong.
Antweiler’s ideas seem to have hit a
nerve. We can already see signs that
culturalism is losing its energy. Many
authors feel the need to look for
normative tendencies across cultures,
not so much to deny the reality of
cultural differences, as to oppose
cultural relativism. The question then is:
with what can we identify, as human
beings, beyond the cultural and
national differences that separate us?
Many are looking for a new orientation
in some form of humanism. They seem
to think that the simple fact of being
human grants us a new form of global
solidarity. However, I do not believe
that this shared humanity is sufficient; it
is too abstract.
Instead, we must engage in a
dialogue between cultures to discuss
what it means to live a dignified life as a
human being. It is within and through
culture that we learn how to perceive
ourselves as human beings. By studying
and comparing different cultures we
can see just how much they share. The
‘humanist turn’ and the ‘cultural turn’
must complement one another. This
means that humanism must be
intercultural and involve dialogue.
Lessons from traditional humanism
All cultures and civilizations have
humanist traditions. But the ‘humanist
turn’ is not a return to traditional forms
of humanism. One of the problems with
traditional forms of humanism is that
they are inspired by historical
experiences that are no longer ours.
The humanism that accompanied the
European Renaissance, for instance,
cannot be detached from ambitions to
challenge the authority of the Church.
Another problem is that many
traditional forms of humanism are
overly linked to naturalism. Again, the
humanism of the European Renaissance
could be quoted as an example. It was
interested in discovering the ‘nature of
Man’ in accordance with the ‘nature of
the universe’. This tradition of naturalism
is still very much alive today in various
scientific ideas that tend to reduce the
human condition to biology. In contrast
to naturalism, a new humanism needs
to understand that we become human
in and through culture.
But it would be equally mistaken
simply to forget about the traditional
forms of humanism that can be found
in the legacies of many different
cultures. It is in these traditions that we
can find clear evidence for the fact that
human beings share, and have always
shared, very important ideas about
what it means to be human. But
learning from other traditions of
humanism does not only mean to
reaffirm what we already know. In his
book on Humanism in East Asian
1. Doris Bachmann-Medick, Cultural Turns.
Neuorientierungen in den Kulturwissenschaften,
Rowohlt Verlag: 2006.
2. Christoph Antweiler: Mensch und Weltkultur [Man
and World Culture], Transcript Verlag, 2010.
L "Study of the proportions of the human body according to Vitruvius" by Leonardo da Vinci at the end of
the 15th century, as reworked by Sri Lankan photographer, Janaka Dharmasena
©
 J
a
n
a
ka
 D
h
a
rm
a
se
n
a
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
2 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
Oliver Kozlarek is professor of political
and social philosophy at the Institute
for Philosophical Research, Universidad
Michoacana de San Nicolás de Hidalgo
(Mexico). He was a member of the
research project on ‘Humanism in the
Age of Globalization’ from 2007 to 2009.
Since 2010 he has also been director of
the research project ‘Modernity, Critique
and Humanism’ in Mexico. He is
currently co-editor of a major book
series on Intercultural Humanism. His
books include: Humanismo en la época
de la globalización: Desafíos y horizontes
(2009) (with Jörn Rüsen), Octavio Paz:
Humanism and Critique (2009).
3. Chun-chien Huang, Humanism in East Asian
Confucian Contexts, Transcript Verlag, 2010.
4. Erich Fromm (1900-1980), German-born
American humanist psychoanalyst, and author of
Escape from Freedom, 1941; The Art of Loving, 1956;
The Sane Society, 1955.
5. J.M Coetzee, South African writer, Nobel Prize in
Literature, 2003
6. Rubem Fonseca, Brazilian born writer
7. Octavio Paz (1914-1998), Mexican writer and
essayist, Nobel Prize in Literature, 1990
8. Theodor W. Adorno (1903 – 1969), German-born
sociologist, philosopher and musicologist
9. Jörn Rüsen/Henner Laass (eds.), Humanism in
Intercultural Perspective. Experiences and
Expectations, Transcript Verlag, 2010.
Confucianism3 Professor Chun-chieh
Huang explains brilliantly that East
Asian Confucianism was very much
concerned with the harmonious
relationship between human beings
and the social and natural world that
they are a part of. One cannot help
thinking that a strong sense of ‘world
harmony’ such as this could guide us
through the ecological and social
disasters accompanying the modern
destruction of the natural world as well
as the devastations of our social worlds.
Questions like this have to be discussed
within an intercultural perspective. And
I am convinced that the social sciences
and humanities provide excellent
spaces in which this kind of intercultural
dialogue among different traditions of
humanism can be cultivated.
Shared experiences of
dehumanization
An idea expressed by Erich Fromm,4
among others, supports the possibility
of a common humanist understanding,
despite differences. Humanism is always
a consequence of experiences of
alienation. It is an outcry from people
who feel that the conditions for living a
humanely dignified life are withering
away. In a world like ours, individual
experiences may vary greatly. In our
global, modern world, chances are
unevenly distributed, and economic,
political and military powers are
unevenly concentrated. However, it is
also a world in which certain
experiences of alienation seem to
transcend these differences. We are all
suffering from the destruction of our
natural environment; we are all living in
societies where social relations suffer
from a growing sense of mistrust. Those
who are better off may try to
compensate for the lack of satisfying
social relations through consumption,
while those who do not have the means
experience a desperate longing for
consumption. In most parts of the world
people are exposed to old and new
forms of violence and injustice. Political
and economic institutions behave in
ways that people can hardly identify
with.
Again, despite considerable local
and social differences, the experiences
of human beings under these
dehumanizing conditions tend to be
very similar all over the planet. And this
must surely be something we can learn
from, if we compare contemporary
cultures on a global scale. J. M.
Coetzee’s5 South Africa resembles
Rubem Fonseca’s6 Brazil; Octavio Paz’7
critique of modernity is similar to that
found in the writing of Theodor W.
Adorno8. Comparative research in the
social sciences and humanities could
extend our understanding of the
dehumanization that people all over the
planet are suffering.
Humanism in everyday life
By the same token, the ‘humanist turn’
should not be seen as an endeavour
confined to academic or intellectual
circles alone. Some time ago, the
German historian, Jörn Rüsen, explained
that humanism has to have ‘practical’
ambitions as well: “The idea of
humanism must always be put into
social contexts in order to make it
plausible and give it its place in real
life”9. What Rüsen expresses here seems
to me to be of fundamental importance.
It is only if humanism comes to
constitute a central influence on the
ways we think and act in everyday life
that it can hope to begin to foster a
humanist culture that is not only
theoretical and abstract. It is my
contention that this ‘translation’ of
humanist ideas and values into
everyday political, social and economic
practices represents above all a task for
political and economic institutions. But
again, the social sciences and
humanities can play an important role.
At least a part of their endeavour should
be dedicated to the cultivation and
promulgation of a humanist culture
beyond the ivory tower.
To sum up, the current humanist
turn that is starting to appear in many
academic and non-academic arenas,
seems to be motivated by the need to
move beyond the awareness of cultural
differences and to look for that which all
human beings share, without
neglecting the differences. Instead of
looking for the universal in biological
nature, or thinking that a universal
humanist culture has to be invented or
imposed on other cultures, the current
humanist turn presupposes that
universal ideas and values are already
present in all different cultures. At the
same time, the new humanism seems to
recognize that global modernity needs
normative orientations that all human
beings can agree upon. And last but not
least, it is a result of common
experiences of alienation that global
modernity has provoked in different
parts of the world. The most important
task, however, is to translate the ideas
and values into everyday practices. ■
L Painting courtesy of Indian artist, Ananya
Banerjee.
©
 A
n
a
n
ya
 B
a
n
e
rj
e
e
 −
 w
w
w
.a
n
a
n
ya
b
a
n
e
rj
e
e
.n
e
t
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
©
 B
e
n
ja
m
in
 B
in
i -
 w
w
w
.b
e
n
ja
m
in
b
in
i.c
o
m
International research 
The Project ‘Humanism in the Age of Globalization – an Intercultural Dialogue about Culture, Humanity and Values’ was
hosted by the Institute for Advanced Study in the Humanities (KWI) in Essen, Germany and directed by Jörn Rüsen. The
project initiated a dialogue between scholars from Africa, Asia, Europe and Latin America in order to show that different
humanist traditions have existed in different parts of the world, but also that these humanist traditions could become an
important inspiration in our contemporary modern world. Although the project concluded officially in 2009, after having
received generous financial support from the German Mercator Foundation, publication of the results continues. From 2009
to date a book series by the German publisher Transcript Verlag has published 14 volumes in German and English. The work
of the project is being continued in other projects. The project ‘Modernity, Critique and Humanism’ directed by Oliver
Kozlarek with funding from the Mexican Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología (CONACyT) can be seen as an offspring.
J From the Faces à l'Ame
series by French artist,
Benjamin Bini.
Instead of looking
for the universal in
biological nature,
or thinking that a
universal
humanist culture
has to be invented
or imposed on
other cultures, the
current humanist
turn presupposes
that universal
ideas and values
are already
present in all
different cultures.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Humanism did not arise in Europe in the
fifteenth and sixteenth centuries. This
period, known as the Renaissance, was
one period in the long history of
humanism, which began two thousand
years earlier in Athens and continued
during the Golden Age of Islam, from
the ninth to the twelfth century.
Renaissance thinkers referred
specifically to the legacy of ancient
Greece, which they revived and used as
a model. But they preferred to overlook
the Muslim period of humanism.
Those who make the same mistake
today do so because they believe that
the humanist approach is, by definition,
anti-religious. Yet for most of its history,
humanism developed within the
framework of religious thought, not
outside of it. Neither Leonardo da Vinci,1
Michelangelo,2 Shakespeare,3 Racine,4
Descartes5 or Newton6 ever questioned
the power of God.
Humanism objected to a certain
image of God: the image of an
inaccessible God, indifferent to human
suffering, who had determined the
personal fate of each and every person
for eternity. This was the image fostered
by the dogma of predestination,
according to which men and women
have no free will over their lives. Not
only does earthly existence have no
importance in and of itself—it is only a
Contrary to popular belief, humanism developed within the framework of religious
thought – first Greek, then Muslim and finally Christian. In the Golden Age of Islam from
the 9th to the 12th centuries, first the Mu’tazili, then the Falasifa explored the limits of
humanist thought and the concept of free will in a world dominated by a unique and all-
powerful God, anticipating the 18th century encyclopedic approach to knowledge.
MAHMOUD HUSSEIN
J The Abu Dulaf mosque in Samarra (Iraq) is one of
the most important works of architecture in the
Islamic world. It dates from the 9th century. The
Samarra archaeological city is inscribed on the
UNESCO List of World Heritage 
The Muslim phase 
of humanism
©
 Iz
ze
d
in
e
 -
 W
ik
im
e
d
ia
 C
o
m
m
o
n
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
path to heaven—but mankind has no
control over its destiny. There is no free
will. On the one hand was the absolute
power of God; on the other, the
absolute powerlessness of mankind.
“We were … chosen from the
beginning,” wrote Saint Paul, “under the
predetermined plan of the one who
guides all things as he decides by his
own will.”7 One millennium later,
traditionalists and classical theologians
of Islam adhered to this same belief;
seven centuries after them, Luther8 and
Calvin9 would use the same words. It
was against this concept of the all-
powerful divine that humanism fought.
But how was ancient Greece used
as a model for those who, first in the
Muslim world and later in the Christian
world, would wage the fight against the
dogma of predestination?
A perimeter of intellectual freedom
In a context entirely different from that
of monotheism, Greece had already
confronted this concept of
predestination. In their view, the
cosmos was a finite space, with a
harmonious and hierarchical structure,
in which everyone’s place was defined
once and for all. Mankind was not at
the top of the cosmic structure; gods
stood above them. But cosmic laws
applied to everyone, gods and men
alike.
The latter therefore endured a dual
burden: first, the abstract, impersonal,
immutable one of the cosmos; and the
more personal, familial and capricious
constraints of the gods. 
Man was powerless against the
order of the cosmos; he could only try
to navigate his own way. Yet with the
gods, who had superhuman powers
but were riddled with human frailties,
mankind learned how to negotiate,
trick and cheat. Ultimately, man
discovered that nature operated
according to specific laws of the
cosmos, which lay beyond the power of
the gods, and that men could therefore
work to learn and master these laws. 
This was the context in which
humanism developed. The Greeks
invented a new, specifically human
environment: the polis. Within it, the
individual was no longer subject to the
traditional power of tribes and clans;
citizens were equal before the law and
personal merit could prevail over the
privilege of birth.
In the democratic city, debate was
widespread and speech ruled supreme.
To convince others, one had to reason.
The principles of abstract logic, valid
everywhere and for all, encouraged the
exploration of philosophy and
mathematics. And with it, man
developed powerful leverage over
aspects of his life. 
Humanism in ancient Greece
therefore formed a perimeter of
intellectual freedom and efficiency,
through which human life—without
challenging the overall global order or
the power of the gods—became a
valued enterprise in and of itself.
Qudra or the power of man
The monotheistic God changed the
situation. He not only took over the
partial power wielded by the Greek
gods, but also the universal cosmic force
that applied to these gods as well as to
mankind. The abstract, impersonal
power of the cosmos was replaced by
the omnipotent, personal, creative and
active power of God. He became both
the One and the All-Powerful.
From this point on, the believer had
to explore his own freedom within the
orbit of this Almighty. There was no
question of pitting the derisory power
of man against the infinite power of
God. More humbly, it involved
cultivating the intellectual, moral and
aesthetic realms where human initiative
could be expressed, as distinguished
from the will of God, but without
challenging His supreme authority.
This realm was conceptualized for
the first time in the ninth century in
Baghdad, under the Abbasid Caliphate.
Islam was by then an immense,
powerful and prosperous empire that
encompassed a multitude of different
people, religions and cultures. Its
capital, Baghdad, had a population of
one million, while Rome had 30,000
people, and Lutetia, barely 10,000. In
trade, trust was the rule, so that a bill of
exchange signed in India was honored
as far away as Morocco. 
The great caliphs decided to
embrace this power and diversity,
opting to encourage intelligent
thought. They supported efforts to
1. Leonardo da Vinci,  [1452-1519], Italian painter,
polymath and humanist philosopher.
2. Michelangelo [1475-1564], Italian Renaissance
painter, sculptor and architect.
3. William Shakespeare [1564-1616], one of the
greatest English playwrights and poets. 
4. Jean Racine [1639-1699], classical French
playwright. 
5. René Descartes [1596-1650], French
mathematician and rationalist philosopher.
6. Isaac Newton [1643- 1727], English physicist,
philosopher and theologian.
7. Epistle to the Ephesians
8. Martin Luther [1483-1546], German priest and
father of protestantism.
9 Jean Calvin, [1509-1564], French theologian and
scholar, one of the main architects of the Protestant
reformation.
K Miniature by Al-Mubashshir (Syria) from the early 13th century. It shows Socrates (left) with two of his students
©
 M
u
sé
e
 d
u
 p
a
la
is
 T
o
p
ka
p
i, 
Is
ta
n
b
u
l, 
Tu
rq
u
ie
.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
2 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
revive ancient knowledge—including
secular knowledge drawn from the
legacy of Greek science and philosophy,
which would soon be translated into
Arabic.
This context fostered the
development of a theological movement
among religious scholars of the period;
these were the Mu‘tazili, who interpreted
the Quran from a viewpoint of rational
thought and inquiry. 
According to this interpretation, men
are distinct creatures, separate from the
rest of Creation, due to the fact that God
gave them an effective power (qudra),
once and for all time, by which they can
choose to act freely. 
This freedom allows them to act as
‘God’s lieutenants on earth.’ During their
time on earth, men are not supposed to
be self-effacing. Quite the opposite, they
are encouraged to be assertive, to display
a sense of initiative and to develop their
talents, all with the purpose of
constructing a fair and united Muslim
community.
Within this community, worldly
existence is celebrated for its own value. It
is recommended, insofar as is possible, to
improve the living conditions of others.
Beauty is prized, the body is honoured
and pleasures are encouraged, within the
limits of decency and moderation. 
“Allah is He Who made the earth a
resting place for you and the sky for a
canopy, and fashioned you and perfected
your shapes, and hath provided you with
good things ...” (Quran, Sura 40, verse 64).
On Judgment Day, each person will
have to personally answer for the good
and the evil they have done during their
lifetimes. As God has full knowledge of
their actions, He will reward or punish
according to a rational and moral justice. 
The Mu‘tazili approach was
supported and even imposed on the
religious elite by some of the greatest
Abbasid caliphs. But it was so bold and so
disturbing that, in the end, most of the
traditionalists, jurists and ultimately the
theologians themselves would unite
against it. 
All of them rejected the very idea of a
rational interpretation of the acts of God,
insofar as this placed limits on His all-
mighty power. Divine will is a mystery; it
is not subject to any limitation. Hence,
while having preordained the destiny of
each person, God reserves the privilege
of reward and punishment, according to
His unfathomable will.
This vision, which fully expressed the
dogma of predestination, may seem
unjust and immoral. What is required of
the believer is not understanding, but
rather acceptance and submission to God
through an unconditional embrace of
total faith. One is then allowed to place
one’s hopes in divine mercy and
compassion. 
Precursors of the Encylopedists
By the late ninth century, the
confrontation between the Mu‘tazili and
the traditionalists was decided in favor of
the latter. They not only eliminated the
concept of free will, but worked to flush
out and combat all the rationalist
movements that appeared in Muslim
thought.
They specifically targeted the Falasifa
(philosophers), who were pursuing an
encyclopedic approach that embraced
every sphere of knowledge. They
redeemed the secular disciplines
developed by the Greeks—medicine,
mathematics, astronomy and
pharmacology—and studied nature as it
was, and not as a reflection of the all-
powerful divine. 
Al-Kindi,10 al-Farabi,11 Ibn Sina
(Avicenna)12 and Ibn Rushd (Averroes)13
developed a new philosophy, through
which Aristotelian reason was reconciled
with monotheism; it would inspire
Maimonides14 and later, Thomas
Aquinas.15 There is no ontological
difference between the truths reached by
philosophers and those revealed by God
to His prophets. The prophets perceived
through instant illumination that which
philosophers discovered, step by step, via
rational thought.
The Falasifa therefore explored the
limits of humanist thought within a
monotheistic framework. Adopting the
argument of reason over that of
authority, even when the latter is based
on divine revelation, they heralded the
encyclopedic approach of the eighteenth
century.
The Falasifa had a longer, although
less specific influence than that of the
Mu‘tazili. They were in the forefront for a
time in Baghdad, Cordoba and Cairo, but
were also eclipsed for long periods. Their
doctrinal authority ended with the death
of Averroes in the late twelfth century.
In the meantime, the Islamic empire
split into two, then three rival empires.
Islam suffered major military defeats
against the Crusaders around Jerusalem
and the Catholic kings in al-Andalus.
Soon after, it was devastated by the
Mongol invasions. 
In various capitals, Islam was
undermined by doubt, and power shifted
from the hands of cultivated princes to
those of military leaders. The confident
quest for knowledge was replaced by a
cautious defense of well-established
beliefs. The concept of free will was lost in
the Islamic world. And with it, the
significance of a humanist approach. 
Yet the works of the Muslim Falasifa,
translated from Arabic into Latin, would
be taught in every European university.
For several centuries, they nourished the
great debates that would lead to
Renaissance thought. ■
10. Al-Kindi (Alkindus) [801- 873], one of the
greatest Arab philosophers, translator of many
Greek manuscripts. 
11. Al-Farabi (Alpharabius) [872- 873], Arab
polymath and commentator on the works of Plato. 
12. Ibn Sina (Avicenna) [980-1037], Persian
philosopher, writer, doctor, astronomer and
alchemist.
13. Ibn Rushd (Averroes) [1126-1198], Andalusian
philosopher, lawyer, mathematician, doctor and
Islamic theologian .
14. Moïse Maimonides [1138-1204], doctor,
philosopher and Andalusian rabbi.
15. Thomas Aquinus  [1224-1274], one of the
principal masters of scholastic philosophy and
Catholic theology.
Mahmoud Hussein (Egypt) is a
political scientist and Islamic scholar. His
latest book (in French), “Penser le Coran,”
is published by Gallimard, Paris: 2011.
L Avicenna as "Princeps Abinsceni" with crown and
sceptre, woodcut, Venice 1520
©
 A
ll 
ri
g
h
ts
 r
e
se
rv
e
d
 S
o
u
rc
e
 W
ik
im
e
d
ia
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  2 5
the origins of science to understand the
complexities of human behaviour and
advocated a synthesized philosophy of
science to bridge the gap between the
sciences and humanities, calling it ‘new
humanism’.
However, American literary critic
Irving Babbitt [1865 – 1933] is largely
New humanism is by no means novel
but rather a product of the evolutionary
path forged by humanity. Its prominent
emergence can be linked to George
Sarton [1884 – 1956], a renowned
Belgian-born American historian of
science, who redefined humanism
through a scientific lens. He turned to
considered a founder of the movement.
Shocked by a progressively materialistic
society in the United States, Babbitt
believed Western society had become
The Confucianists honour
benevolence, the Mohists
universal love, the Taoists
compassion, and the
Buddhists loving-kindness.
As society evolves at high
speed, the core values of
Chinese civilization can be
considered a blueprint for
the development of
universal harmony and,
thus, new humanism.
L "Love" an ink painting on rice paper pasted onto damask paper, by Zhen Ping Qiu. The artist donated this work
to UNESCO in 2006, on the 60th anniversary of the Organization. It is reproduced by kind permission of the artist.
For a world of 
Adapted from the speech, “Embrace the Era of New
Humanism”, delivered by Liu Ji at the 9th Euro-China
Forum on June 27-28 at UNESCO Headquarters.
LIU JI
©
 Z
h
e
n
g
 P
in
g
 Q
iu
/U
N
E
S
C
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
2 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
conscience to normalize social
behaviour. In contrast, Western
civilization regulates social behaviour
by external powers based on scientific
reasoning, hence the rule of law.
The dichotomy between Western
and Chinese civilizations is much like
the two hemispheres of the human
brain: the logical left side and the
emotional right side. Only when these
two hemispheres are mobilized
simultaneously can their full potential
be realized. Thus, logic and affection
should be combined together to give a
full-scale representation of new
humanism.
Chinese people attach extreme
importance to “the debt of gratitude”
they owe others, repaying debt at any
price. 
They hold family affection sacred,
and try to avoid public conflict like
suing relatives. However, the challenge
is to simultaneously attain loyalty to
the nation and filial piety, which is the
respect a child should show his or her
parents.
Harmony instils “good-tempered”
individual behaviour in Chinese social
order. Families believe that if they live
in harmony, they will prosper. Business
etiquette is based on the notion that
“harmony brings wealth.” In country
governance, harmony is the ultimate
pursuit, whereas Western society
believes in the “survival of the fittest”
and ‘a law of the jungle’ where “the
weak are the prey of the strong.” 
Harmony also encompasses the
ideal relationship of oneness between
man and nature, whereby man is an
inherent part of nature and thus
should act according to natural laws. 
The Confucianists pay tribute to
benevolence, the Mohists to universal
love, the Taoists to compassion, and
the Buddhists to loving-kindness. Love
seems to be an omnipresent topic for
all schools of thought in China.
Confucian roots of humanism
The great Chinese philosopher
Confucius (551 BC – 479 BC) described
benevolence as “loving people”; “You
yourself desire rank and standing, then
help others get rank and standing,” he
said. “You want to turn your own
merits to account, then help others to
turn theirs to account.”
For Confucianists, the ultimate
goal is to develop a world of universal
harmony where people love all
equally. As a result, those who are less
fortunate in society, the aged, orphans
and people with disabilities would be
supported by the community. Material
resources would be used for goodwill,
and social wealth owned and shared
by all. 
According to notable Confucianist,
Meng Ke, known as Mencius [372  -
289 BC), man possesses four initial
senses just as he possesses four limbs.
“The sense of compassion is the
beginning of benevolence; the sense
of shame the beginning of
righteousness; the sense of modesty
the beginning of decorum; the sense
of right and wrong the beginning of
wisdom.” These four senses
differentiate man from animal, and
only with their integrated
development can man really be
considered human. 
The doctrines of Confucius and
Mencius have been the cornerstone of
traditional Chinese culture for
thousands of years and are still
dominant today. According to some
thinkers, it is under the influence of
Confucianism that the Enlightenment
philosophers of the 18th century
constructed the monumental
Declaration of the Rights of Man and
of the Citizen in 1789.
Thus, the substance of new
humanism can only be enriched with
the ingredients of Chinese culture. As
human society evolves at high speed,
the construction of a harmonious
world, which has long been the
universal ideal of mankind, calls for the
rise of new humanism. ■
Liu Ji is honorary president of CEIBS
(China Europe International Business
School) and former vice president of
the Chinese Academy of Social
Sciences. 
victim to emotional and individualistic
instincts and thus campaigned for self-
restraint. An opponent of Romanticism,
his key principles conflicted with the
intellectual trend of his time and were
deemed controversial, yet sparked a
great philosophical debate, which
shaped conservative intellectual
thinking post-World War II. 
Babbitt’s humanistic philosophy
entered China’s political and literary
consciousness through numerous
Chinese scholars who studied with him
at Harvard University. Inspired by
Buddhist and Confucian values, Babbitt
appealed culturally to his students who
later adapted new humanism locally as
a counter-reaction to the May 4th
movement, which called for a rejection
of Chinese traditional values, Marxism
and radical beliefs. 
Virtue, affection and harmony
The practices of Chinese ancient
culture can be considered a blueprint
for the development of new
humanism. Specifically, The Book of
Changes (also known as the I Ching),
one of China’s oldest classic texts, said
to have been written by Emperor Fu
Hsi (2953-2838 B.C.). It focuses on the
balance of opposites and the
inevitability of change. According to
this text, “By observing the ornaments
of the sky, we may understand the
principle of the transformation of the
four seasons; by observing ethical
human relations and teaching the
common people, we may transform
social traditions for the better.” Thus,
we should observe human nature to
learn how to improve it, and in doing
so, follow the fundamental values of
Chinese culture such as virtue,
affection, harmony and love.
Throughout China’s long
civilization, virtue, both personal and
social, has guided people in their day-
to-day living, relying on one’s inner
The dichotomy between Western and Chinese civilizations is much
like the two hemispheres of the human brain: the logical left side and
the emotional right side. Only when these two hemispheres are
mobilized simultaneously can their full potential be realized. Thus,
logic and affection should be combined together to give a full-scale
representation of new humanism.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
were to insist on taking the pre-
eminence of human reason as absolute.
But man’s excessive and outmoded
pretensions today are to a total
awareness of his own truth and energy.
After four centuries of striving to
dissociate all things by means of
analysis, starting with himself, he is
coming back to a synthetic view of the
person, revivified by the soul. As a
consequence, all values, everywhere in
the world, and from all periods of world
history, not only find their use, but also
their order and hierarchy. Whether
these values have their origins in the
East or West, they are no longer rivals,
but are all converging towards this new
humanism, with its tendency towards
universalism arising from a real inner
impulse, and no longer from some 
questionable aspiration […]
But the impulse that is needed today is
to liberate the human spirit from the
bonds by which Western thinking has
held it captive for so long. The new
humanism will be one where the
methods of leadership and labour that
the Western intellect has been able to
acquire will be applied to the
rediscovery of spiritual domains that
have long been deserted. So, instead of
the intellect leading man to run the risks
that arise from his presumptions and
usurpations, it will need all the vivacity
and strength it can muster, this time to
serve the cause of the truly complete
man – not the man steered off course
into the material world by his intellect,
but a man with body and soul united,
using his mind to confront his own
mystery.
We believe that if this latter humanism
were to develop, East and West would
see the disappearance of much that
separates them, and the appearance of
all that unites them and that unites all
mankind […]
UNESCO in 1951: 
Towards a new humanism 
Sixty years ago, UNESCO
held a ‘Discussion on the
Cultural and Philosophical
Relations Between East and
West’ in New Delhi, the
capital of India, which
endorsed the idea of a new
holistic humanism. Here we
are publishing extracts
from the discussion
document submitted by
participants, under the title
‘Towards a new Humanism’.
At the time, Asian nations
were gaining
independence, while the
world was still suffering the
aftermath of the Second
World War. The first steps in
this humanist project,
supported by UNESCO,
aimed to bring Eastern and
Western cultures closer
together.
The full text of the document, written by the French
writer, André Rousseaux, can be found in UNESCO’s
digital archives (in French only):
www.unesco.org/new/unesco/resources/publicatio
ns/unesdoc-database/
J Photograph from the 'Reflections in an eye of
gold' series by French artist, Laurent Goldstein,
reproduced by kind permission of the artist. 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  2 7
[…] What Western man has, for four
centuries, been calling humanism is the
ambition to achieve mastery over
himself and the universe by the exercise
of his intellect in isolation from the rest
of his being. […] What it has called the
dominion of the complete man is the
contemplation of the entire world by a
man reduced to a part of himself. We
must abandon this error if we are to
repair humanism and expand it.
Certainly not to destroy it, nor, as we
have said, to renounce the conquests of
science, which are, after all, positive
achievements of the same spirit. For a
certain time and in certain places,
Western humanism has been the sphere
for human accomplishments that are of
inherently outstanding value. But we
can no longer allow it to be exclusive
[…] If the word humanism is the name
we have to give to the home of human
genius, humanism does not date from
the 16th century; its only and permanent
home is not Mediterranean Europe; its
sole source is not a certain idea of
Classical Greek and Roman antiquity
[…]. On the other hand, when modern
Western humanism is put squarely back
within the limits that need to be
imposed on it, the crisis that it is
currently facing comes as no surprise,
and is not a hopeless disaster. This
adversity would only be absolute if one
©
 L
a
u
re
n
t 
G
o
ld
st
e
in
/L
a
 C
o
lle
c
ti
o
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Are legal systems becoming
progressively more humanized with
globalization, or are they staying
much the same? 
At first sight, legal humanism seems to
be gaining in strength with the
multiplication of legal instruments and
international bodies monitoring the
observance of human rights, as well as
through the appearance of
humanitarian law and the emergence
of universally applicable criminal
justice. And in terms of the economy,
the global market should create jobs
and increase prosperity. 
So, on the surface, everything
seems to be for the better, in the best of
worlds… But globalization acts like a
kind of magnifying glass and is
revealing a series of contradictions,
raising a whole host of questions. How
can we reconcile the concept of
security with the principle of freedom?
Economic rights and protection of the
environment, etc? Globalization can
even makes the situation worse when,
for example, it separates already
globalized rights such as economic
rights, from social rights, which are the
preserve of States, themselves
weakened by constraints imposed by
financial markets. We could even
Making use of the ‘envisioning force’  of the law to forge a form of legal humanism that is
both pluralistic and open, in areas as diverse as lasting peace, global warming or the
regulation of new digital and biomedical technologies – in these times of rampant
globalization, this is the credo of the French lawyer, Mireille Delmas-Marty.
MIREILLE DELMAS-MARTY 
interviewed by Jasmina Šopova
I Work by the artist Najah Zarbout (Tunisia)
www.najahzarbout.blogspot.com
2 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R
Humanizing
©
 N
a
ja
h
 Z
a
rb
o
u
t
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
the notion of equitable development
has not been integrated, this synergy
will remain an illusion.
By modifying man’s fate, aren’t new
technologies adding to the
paradoxes?
Technologies have always been ‘new’.
What has changed is the rate at which
innovations are being made. So, for
digital technologies, French law is
unable to keep pace. By the time the
Constitutional Council has given its
ruling on a law, actual practice has
already moved on and escapes the
legislation!
Information technologies can help
strengthen democracy, as we have
seen recently in certain Arab countries,
but, at the same time, they encourage
a move towards a surveillance society. 
This ambivalence is equally marked
in the field of biotechnology, which
can be used to counteract sterility,
through artificial procreation, as well as
to select embryos using pre-
implantation genetic diagnosis, thus
moving towards eugenics, which is
considered a crime.
The widespread use of such
practices would reduce the
randomness of genetic selection – the
element of chance – and thus the
biological diversity of human beings.
And this is where the paradox arises –
in the name of individual liberty (being
in control of one’s body and one’s
offspring), our societies run the risk of
provoking a kind of artificial shaping of
the human species (see pp. 39-40).
Another paradox is that the more
we come to depend on digital
technologies, the more we lose our
autonomy; yet at the same time we are
making increasingly autonomous
robots. Robots can help the elderly and
the sick and contribute to general
wellbeing. But in both the USA and
France, programmes have been
launched to develop robots to replace
flesh and blood soldiers to carry out
‘clean wars’ and reach military
objectives without harming civilians.
This would mean entering ethical rules
into the robot’s programme, with all
the risks of error involved in
interpreting such a programme. The
most important ethical choices are
extremely subtle and difficult to
anticipate with mathematical
precision. 
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  2 9
wonder if there is not a contradiction
between the universalism laid down by
the 1948 Declaration on Human Rights
and the 2005 UNESCO Convention on
the Protection and Promotion of the
Diversity of Cultural Expression, which
qualifies cultural expression as the
common heritage of mankind.
How do these contradictions
translate into reality?
One of the most marked contradictions
concerns migration. Borders are open
for trade and capital but closed to
human beings. The trend is even
towards a tightening of control and
repression in many countries, to the
point of merging immigration and
crime together. But, by opening their
borders to the global market, these
same countries destabilize local
markets and encourage people to
leave. Basically, the same players are
simultaneously manufacturing
immigration and repressing it.
At the same time, the dissociation
of economic and social rights restricts
growth to economic and monetary
profit, while doing nothing to limit
increasing vulnerability and social
exclusion, whether in terms of
unemployment or poverty. As
prosperity increases, the gap between
the highest and lowest incomes
widens.
Finally, multinational companies
are often a driving force in the natural
resources sector and are behind a large
number of conflicts across the world,
notably in Africa and Latin America.
This is why war crimes, genocide,
crimes against humanity and crimes of
aggression continue, despite the
creation of an International Criminal
Court  (ICC).2 It is true that it only came
into force relatively recently (2002), but
there are also structural reasons – the
statutes of the ICC do not cover the
responsibility of legal persons,3 and so
enterprises go unpunished when they
commit a crime. This undermines the
dissuasive role of the ICC, which was
written into its statutes. Unlike ad hoc
tribunals, which judge crimes already
committed, the ICC sits permanently. 
And what of the contradictions
between economic rights and
environmental rights?
The imperative for development and
competitiveness is discouraging States
from taking action to protect the
environment. And this raises the
question of how best to protect the
planet against the negative effects of
climate change, declining biodiversity
or water pollution (see pp. 34-35).
While industrialized countries are
aligning their own commitments to
those of developing or emerging
countries, these latter countries are
invoking the notion of historical equity
– if industrialized countries were
originally responsible for the pollution
of our planet, they now need to join in
the general effort to preserve the
environment, while allowing others to
develop. The expression ‘sustainable
development’ is supposed to stimulate
synergy between economic rights and
environmental rights, but so long as
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
3 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R
All of these examples demonstrate a
process of dehumanization. What can
the law do?
Its role is difficult because, in a world of
accelerating change, we cannot return
to a static concept that we might call
‘legal humanism’, but need to establish
more dynamic processes of
humanization. Rather than repeatedly
affirming principles, we need to try to
reverse the movement towards
dehumanization in reality. Only through
the effective upholding of human rights
can we avoid some of the aberrations of
totalitarian politics, such as market
totalitarianism, notably in the financial
market. 
What resources does the law have?
The law does not offer a response to
each of the challenges I have
mentioned. But certain current legal
processes do offer the beginnings of a
response in order to humanize
globalization. For example, to create a
multi-tiered form of citizenship – it is a
slow and difficult process, but it does
respond to problems of immigration as
well as to those of the environment. 
The idea of global citizenship is a
dream that dates back to Antiquity. But
more recently, in the Germany of the
late 18th century, Emmanuel Kant
dreamed of perpetual peace between
nations,4 just as, Kang Youwei,5 in China,
dreamed of the age of great world
peace at the end of the 19th century.
This ‘Dream of the two Ks’ could
gradually become reality. We are already
seeing that the creation of European
citizenship tends to complement
national citizenship, rather than
undermine it. And on a planetary scale
the Global Forum on Migration and
Development6 is gradually instigating a
global approach, integrating a concern
for humanization alongside economic
constraints. While we wait for the
emigration countries to ratify the United
Nations Convention on the Protection of
the Rights of Migrant Workers (signed in
1990!), we can see the beginnings of a
process of recognition of certain rights
that foreshadows global citizenship. 
It is by looking towards the future,
to global risks, that we begin to see
humanity as a community with a shared
fate. But it is only by referring back to
the history of humanity that UNESCO
can help to establish, disseminate and
construct intercultural forms of
have neither the means nor the will to
pursue them, for fear of losing the jobs
they provide. And the parent countries
are rarely competent (and do not wish to
be) to pursue deeds committed abroad
against foreign victims. 
There is a very old text (Alien Tort
Claims Act, 1789) that empowers the
federal legal system in the USA to
prosecute anyone who has violated
human rights, even abroad and against
foreigners, which has been used recently
against multinationals. But sentences are
rare. And, in fact, I am not in favour of this
principle of ‘universal competence’ if it
transforms superpowers into judges
presiding over the whole world. In the
absence of a world court, we will soon
need an international convention which,
when multinationals violate human
rights, assigns competence to the parent
country and, if this country does not
prosecute the perpetrator, would provide
the country in which the corporation is
established with the resources (in terms
of personnel and logistics) to take the
matter to court. 
Could such a case not be referred to
the International Criminal Court? 
Even if we were to extend its range of
competence to include corporate bodies,
the multinationals would only be judged
for the most serious crimes – such as
genocide, crimes against humanity, war
crimes, etc. On the other hand, the ICC
can prosecute an incumbent Head of
State, which is something of a political as
well as a legal revolution. Unfortunately,
without a police force, it has no means to
citizenship  – that is intercultural rather
than multicultural, since it is not enough
to juxtapose cultures, but important to
aim for the more ambitious objective of
reciprocal humanism (see pp. 14-16).
Is it utopian to imagine global
governance founded on humanist
principles? 
At present it is still utopian. The unequal
distribution of power, shared between a
few States and multinational
corporations, renders the organization of
this kind of global governance extremely
difficult. In cases where human rights are
violated we need to be able to hold all
those in power to account. For States,
this kind of process is beginning to
operate within the Council of Europe
(with the Convention for the Protection
of Human Rights and Fundamental
Freedoms and the European Court on
Human Rights in Strasbourg), as well as
in Latin America (with the Inter-American
Convention on Human Rights not having
been ratified by Canada and the USA)
and more recently in Africa (with the
African Charter on Human and People’s
Rights). In the absence of a World Court
of Human Rights less restrictive
mechanisms are being established, but
they are inadequate and scattered.
And multinational corporations?
So-called ‘social’ responsibility is limited
to a few small islands of hard law7 in an
ocean of soft law (guiding principles,
codes of conduct, etc). In the case of
serious violations, the countries where
the multinational firms are established
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Both generations are concerned
about the dangers arising from
technological innovations, which you
have cited as one of the challenges
facing modern humanism.
We obviously cannot ban all
technological innovation. That would be
absurd, given that throughout history,
mankind has become humanized by
developing technologies and globalizing
them. We globalized the wheel, then the
wheel-barrow, the compass, etc. But this
does not mean that just because
something is possible it should be
allowed (as innovations are unavoidable,
it would be pointless to resist them). It is
therefore important to adapt the legal
responses to technological innovations. 
Relations between scientists and
politicians also need to be revised –
between knowledge and power –
because there is also a gap in global
governance there. States defend national
interests, corporate and private interests,
and, apart from a few international
organizations with few means of action,
noone is responsible for defending the
general interest. Experts fill the gap. In
principle, they do not have the power to
make decisions but in practice they often
play a key role regarding scientific
innovations and their applications. While
expertise still has no global status,
various scattered bodies are beginning
to guarantee the independence and
impartiality of experts in order to avoid
conflicts of interest. 
1. La Force imaginante is the title of a book by
Mireille Delmas-Marty not yet available in English
2 .Established by the Rome Convention of 17 July
1998, the International Criminal Court, which
entered into force in July 2002, is the first
permanent court set up to judge, according to its
preamble, the perpetrators of “…unimaginable
atrocities that deeply shock the conscience of
humanity.”
3. A legal person (persona ficta) is an entity, other
than a natural (human) person, with a legal
existence and, as such, has rights and
responsibilities.
4. In a 1795 text, Zum Ewigen Frieden (Perpetual
Peace), Kant summarized Enlightenment thinking
on peace and the idea of the federation of free
nations. 
5. Kang Youwei, Datong Shu, trad. L.G Thompson,
The One World Philosophy of K’angYu-wei, London,
1958. 
6. The Global Forum on Migration and
Development (GFMD), which held its first meeting
in Brussels in 2007, is a platform for exchanging
practices and experiences in an attempt to define
the means to use international migration to best
effect for development and to reduce its negative
effects.
7. Hard law refers to a traditional form of law, while
soft law is a norm that is not legally binding.
K "Borders are open for trade and capital but
closed to human beings," says Mireille Delmas-
Marty. This idea is illustrated in the "New World
Climax" installation by Cameroonian artist,
Berthélémy Toguo. 
make an arrest. At present it appeals to
States, as well as UN and NATO forces, to
cooperate, but with very unsatisfactory
results. The link between the law and the
forces of order still needs to be organized
on a global scale.
And the links between the law and
peace?
Ordinarily, lasting peace is not
considered possible if justice has not
previously been seen to be done. But
examples like the South African Truth
and Reconciliation Commission show
that peace can be re-established without
all the criminals being brought to justice,
but just those who refuse to recognize
their guilt. And in this respect, the
developed world has probably a great
deal to learn from Africa if it is to avoid
what I call ‘legal fundamentalism’, which,
like religious fundamentalism, means
limiting and rejecting any plurality of
interpretations. The exigency of the law
has to be reconciled with the need for
peace. And the refusal to let the guilty
go unpunished must not itself become
overly rigid. 
What do you think about our
responsibility vis-à-vis future
generations, which is already written
into the French Charter on the
Environment?
It is true that references to future
generations are beginning to appear in
legal texts, especially this charter, which
has constitutional validity. In practice, a
certain amount of imagination is
needed to introduce future generations
into the law. Who can represent their
interests? What is one responsible for
and for how long? How can we
compensate those who have not yet
been born? etc. I personally am
reluctant to speak about the ‘rights’ of
future generations, or the ‘rights’ of
nature or animals, because there can be
no reciprocity. But as responsible
beings, humans do have duties towards
their future descendants, and indeed
towards non-human living beings. 
But we still need to be careful,
because, for a long time, the notion of
‘human duties’ was part of the
argument used to legalize State tyranny,
whereas the expression ‘human rights’,
when attached to States, enables limits
to be placed on the abuse of power, and
to make it possible to ‘rationalize’ the
reasons (or lack of reasons) of State. On
the other hand, when relations are not
reciprocal, duties still need to be
recognized. The right balance has to be
found, because the duties that we have
with respect to future generations must
not obliterate the rights of present
generations. 
©
 L
a
u
re
n
t 
G
o
ld
st
e
in
/L
a
 C
o
lle
c
ti
o
n
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  3 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The global nature of communications
and what we have chosen to call the
‘information society’ are inviting
anthropologists to rethink, at least
partially, the basic matter and categories
of their discipline – forms of exchange
and the ways in which social links are
woven. 
For the French anthropologist
Claude Lévi-Strauss [1908-2009],
anthropology is not only a humanist
discipline, but also the product of forms
of humanism that have left a mark on
history and the development of Western
societies. As early as 1956, in a
document written for UNESCO,1 he
identified three forms of humanism in
conclusion to his analyses of the
relationships between the sciences and
social sciences: Renaissance humanism,
with its roots in the rediscovery of
classical antiquity texts; exotic
humanism, associated with the
knowledge of Eastern and Far Eastern
cultures; and democratic humanism,
associated with an anthropology that
embraces all the activities of human
societies. 
These three forms of humanism, it
should be pointed out, are linked to
discoveries of texts, oral traditions or
other expressions of culture, which
opened up new fields of investigation
and allowed the development of new
critical methods and, as a result, new
knowledge. In the case of Renaissance
humanism, it was the knowledge of
3 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
But adapting the law to encompass
practices arising from new
technologies, or trying to anticipate
the risks to come, is not enough…
Quite true. Ambivalences also have to be
taken into account. Technologies
engender dehumanizing effects, like the
emergence of a surveillance society or
shaping of the species, which we need to
resist if we are not to lose what we have
gained from humanization, on the
grounds that globalization would wipe
out the history of all peoples. 
What would be the components of this
human community of values? 
It is hard to tell in advance. They gradually
emerge through reciprocal humanization,
as cultures intermingle. Even the notion
of human dignity, which we might think
has been defined once and for all, still
needs to be consolidated, especially
regarding the status of women.
Even so, the list of crimes against
humanity, or prohibitions like torture
and inhuman or degrading treatment,
implicitly allow the common
components of humanity to appear,
such as the uniqueness of every
individual and their equal membership
of the human community. And the risks
created by new technologies suggest
that a third component needs to be
added – indeterminism. Human beings
are not determined in advance, this is
their share of freedom and the basis for
their responsibility. 
It is by referring to these three
components that the law could play its
real role – to resist, to render
responsible and to anticipate. Resisting
dehumanization, holding those who
hold the reins of global power
responsible for their acts, thinking
ahead about future risks. This could be
the instrument for a new form of
humanism, which would not be a fixed
dogma but conceived as a dynamic
process of humanizing practices. ■
Elected member of the French
Académie des Sciences Morales et
Politiques in 2007, Mireille Delmas-
Marty (France) has, since 2002, been
chair of ‘Comparative legal studies and
the internationalization of law’ at the
Collège de France where her course
on ‘Sense and nonsense in legal
humanism’ questions the
humanization of legal systems, at a
time when it seems more than ever
necessary. She is the author of several
seminal books, some of which have
been translated into English, including
Towards a Truly Common Law
(Cambridge University Press, 2002) and
Ordering Pluralism (Hart Publishing,
2009). She is noted for her
monumental work comprising several
volumes, entitled La Force imaginante
(Seuil), the latest volume of which will
be published in 2012. 
L Portrait of Mireille Delmas-Marty by Emmanuelle Marchadour.
©
 E
m
m
a
n
u
e
lle
 M
a
rc
h
a
d
o
u
r/
Le
 S
e
u
il
The notion of humanism is
evolving, apace with
scientific discoveries and
political developments. In
this digital age, technologies
are increasing the
opportunities of the
hybridization of cultures,
but also encouraging the
advent of democracy and
the emergence of a universal
form of humanism.
MILAD DOUEIHI 
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  3 3
Greek and Latin, an awareness of history
and an internal critique that
undermined the authority of an
institution as powerful as the Church.
For exotic humanism, the meeting of
East and West encouraged
comparativism, which in turn gave rise
to new sciences and disciplines, like
linguistics. And the humanism that
embraced all human societies gave rise,
among other things, to the structural
methodology. This enabled Lévi-Strauss,
in particular, to observe the world in its
globality and to discover an order
underlying the diversity of forms of
social organization and manifestations
of culture. For the father of
structuralism, this order was a mark of
the human mind.
It is also worth remembering that
these three forms of humanism
correspond to political developments:
the first was aristocratic, limited to a
privileged few; the second was
bourgeois, because it accompanied
Western industrial development; and the
third, democratic, as it excluded no one. 
It is this universal dimension that
urges me, in all modesty, to propose a
fourth humanism, digital humanism.
The fourth humanism
Digital humanism is the result of a
totally new convergence between our
complex, cultural heritage and a
technology that has become a space for
unprecedented sociability. This
convergence is new in the sense that it
redistributes concepts and objects, as
well as the practices associated with
them, within a virtual environment. 
And, like the three forms of
humanism defined by Lévi-Strauss,
digital humanism is linked to a major
discovery that opened multiple fields of
investigation – the new technologies,
which are overturning established
socio-cultural categories. 
Besides its technical and economic
aspects, which need constant scrutiny
and questioning, digital technology is in
the process of becoming a culture, in the
sense that it is changing our view of
objects, relations and values, and that it
is introducing new perspectives into the
field of human activity. 
1. “How the social sciences have humanised
technical civilisation,” a document dated 8 August
1956, first published in the UNESCO Courier n° 2008-
5, ‘Claude Lévi-Strauss: the view from afar.’ Available
in the digital archives of the Courier:
www.unesco.org/en/courier
©
 T
h
o
m
a
s 
Is
ra
ë
l
Cultural practices like writing,
reading or communication, for example,
have continually been subject to
transformation since the arrival of
digital technologies. As the French
anthropologist Marcel Mauss [1872-
1950] pointed out, technology can play
an essential role, when access to the
technical instruments not only modifies
individual behaviour, but also the entire
surrounding culture.
Digital technologies can play an
even more essential role by radically
changing categories of space and time,
thus facilitating meetings between
cultures and their hybridization –
through the elimination of frontiers and
geographical distances, the immediacy
of communication, etc. 
Of course, they have their
limitations – digital technologies have
been based on mainly Western socio-
cultural models; they have not managed
to overcome linguistic barriers, and they
are not immune to abuse. Also, their
global distribution is unequal, which
can exaggerate inequalities between
rich and poor.
But despite this, digital technologies
have become a global reality, a universal
means of communication, even an
instrument for democratisation, as we
saw in the Arab Spring at the beginning
of 2011.
The hybrid space of the digital
culture is a new way of “living together”,
with its myths, discoveries and utopias.
It makes the global village a reality.
Digital humanism is one way of thinking
about this new reality. ■
Milad Doueihi (USA) is a religious
historian and Chair of Research on
Digital Cultures at Laval University
(Quebec). He is the author of several
books, including Digital Cultures
(Harvard University Press, 2011) and A
Perverse History of the Human Heart
(Harvard University Press, 1998)
J 'Flux' an interactive video installation by Belgian
artist, Thomas Israel in the entrance hall of the
International Youth Office in Brussels (Belgium)
DIGITAL
humanism?
Digital humanism is the result of
a totally new convergence
between our complex cultural
heritage and a technique that
has become a space for
unprecedented sociability. 
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Apocalypse scenarios crop up often in
our modern civilization. We have seen
economically driven famines, wars over
gold, oil and diamonds. There are
threats of imminent ecological disaster
and global nuclear war. Civilizations
have disappeared in the past and ours
could also come to an end. Now climate
change, like nuclear winter, joins the
growing list of potential disasters that
could tip mankind towards calamity.
Unlike nuclear war, the agency that
triggers climate change is not clear-cut.
Science has ‘very high confidence’ that
the changes occurring in the
atmosphere are a result of human
industrial activity, pumping billions of
tonnes of greenhouse gases into the
lower atmosphere for the past 150
years.1
No single individual has triggered
climate change, any more than one
individual – not even an individual State
– is in a position to halt the industrial
technologies of modernity. It is true that
consumer decisions on a mass scale
could alter the way corporations
produce goods and services and this
could, in turn, have an impact on
climate change. But, more
fundamentally, to cope adequately with
climate change, the very role of
‘consumer’ needs to be transformed.
Individuals can and do lead very
ecologically friendly lifestyles. But they
soon realize how hard it is when the
community as a whole is not designed
to have a light ecological footprint.2
Ancient cities in Europe and the Middle
East are much easier to walk around
than the densely populated, sprawling
concrete jungles of the New World,
where public transport is a much more
effective way to get around. But in the
low-density suburban sprawl, if public
transport is not well organized, the car is
still king.
In the end, then, it is up to our
political leaders to make the right
decisions. Yet, on an international scale
– the scale on which our future is being
played out – there is an evident lack of
leadership. Every year in the
international conferences on climate
change that have been held since 1995,
our political leaders have failed to
challenge the technological norms that
prevail in modern societies. 
For me, the reasons that those in
leadership positions find it so difficult to
challenge the status quo lie in the twin
apparatus of modern technology and
global economics, which are central to
modern civilisation. And we are all
struggling with this. To transform them
seems impossible, tantamount to
changing civilizations, shifting from one
ecological epoch to another. But,
according to the Royal Society of Great
Britain, we have already done just that. 
In 2010 this venerable body officially
declared that the planet has shifted
from the temperate, placid, Holocene
epoch – which lasted for over 10,000
years, and saw the development of
agricultural and urban civilizations – to
the turbulent and probably catastrophic
Anthropocene epoch, influenced by
man’s activities (from the Greek,
anthropos: human).
The shift had undoubtedly begun
much earlier, at least by 1945 (with our
entry into the nuclear era) and, more
Since the industrial revolution, technological innovation
has been freeing mankind from many of the bonds that link
it to the rest of Nature. But this supposed progress could
have a tragic ending. Climate change is now showing us
that it is time we stopped behaving like strangers in our
own ecological niche.
RUTH IRWIN 
Welcome to the 
Anthropocene
L Maputo, Mozambique.
1. Climate change 2007, IPCC report
2. The ecological footprint is a measure of the
amount of land needed to fill the needs of an
individual (or population) according to his lifestyle:
consumption versus regeneration.
3. Workers' movement at the beginning of the 19th
century in England led by Ned Ludd, which turned
into the massive destruction of machinery, seen as
the main cause of unemployment.
likely, towards the end of the 18th
century, when the Industrial Revolution
significantly changed the way people
relate to their local ecosystems. 
Damaged links between man and
nature
Post-industrial technologies have given
modern man the feeling that he is free
from the bonds that link him to the rest
3 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  3 5
of Nature. In cities, we are no longer
dependent on local seasonal produce.
Thanks to refrigerated transport and
storage, people living in urban areas
can import food stuffs and other goods
from far afield, compared to a ten
kilometres or so walking distance in the
18th century. We will not die of hunger if
the crops fail, as we would have in the
past – and this has changed the
relationship of city-dwellers to their
local ecology. We may even be unaware
of floods and droughts in surrounding
rural areas, or where our drinking water
comes from, or how healthy our forests
are.  And, as the proportion of global
population living in urban areas grows,
cities are continuing to spread into the
surrounding countryside, with a
constellation of technological and
economic necessities, rather than
public need, dictating how they are
built. 
The physical shape of our cities, our
modes of agriculture, mining, energy
production, forestry, fishing and
commerce have all changed radically in
the space of a century and a half,
transforming the way much of the
world now looks.
Our communities have become so
embedded in the tempo and
expectations of modern technological
innovations that these are even
shaping our understanding of ourselves
as ‘individuals’, as humans, while
narrowing our view of the Earth,
rendering it increasingly remote.
Globalization – the new ecology?
While there has been a long tradition of
small groups of ecologically mindful
people, their impact on the norms of
modern life has been limited. Individual
ethics has meant little to the juggernaut
of modern progress. But climate change
has brought the scale of modern
industrial technology and its by-product
of greenhouse gas emissions into global
consciousness in an unprecedented
way. 
The Anthropocene epoch may
become one of the planet’s major
extinction periods, similar to when the
dinosaurs became extinct 65 million
years ago. For the first time, we can see
clearly the impacts of modern
technological progress on ecology at a
global, planetary scale - unless
something radical shifts. 
But this shift is slow in coming.
International schemes for trading
greenhouse gas emissions, for example,
show just how little the real scale of
ecological realities is being taken into
account.
This is not a Luddite, anti-
technological position.3 But we can no
longer remain strangers in our own
ecological niche. Modernity is global in
scope, and our ecological niche has
become global too. Climate change
makes it clear that ecological boundary
conditions need to be taken seriously.
Gone are the days when the human
imagination is free to construct an ideal
reality. Human activities, technologies
and economics need to be appropriate
for the harsh realities of ecological
conditions. 
The awareness of planetary ecology
that climate change has awakened in us
should force us to shift the normative
lens through which we comprehend the
world. We can do nothing without
strong political decisions on an
international scale. Perhaps
globalization can also be seen as the
‘new Green.’ ■
Ruth Irwin is Senior Lecturer in
Business Ethics at Auckland University
of Technology, New Zealand. She is the
author of Heidegger, Politics and Climate
Change (2008) and Editor of Climate
Change and Philosophy:
Transformational Possibilities (2010),
both published by Continuum, London.
©
 A
lf
re
d
o
 D
'A
m
a
to
/P
a
n
o
s 
P
ic
tu
re
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
MICHAL MEYER
Dreams of
science
Because of the power it bestows on
those who practice it and apply its
results to the real world, science
feeds our hope that planning and
organizing can drive human
evolution to a higher plane. This
has often proved a dangerous
quest.
3 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
Science and human identity
Take, for example, the case of
transhumanism, which focuses on
individual rather than societal
improvement. Transhumanism is future
oriented and relies on technologies
both new and as yet confined to the
pages of science fiction books. Its
ultimate goal is to transcend human
biological limitations and so create a
technologically based immortality.
While transhumanism’s technological
origins lie in post World War II
cybernetics, nanotechnology, and
genetic engineering, its essence
connects to the ancient alchemical
quest to create the Philosopher’s Stone,
which supposedly provided near
immortality to those alchemical adepts
clever enough to create it.  
Transhumanism ranges from the
currently realistic to the futuristically
surreal, from stem cell therapy to the
uploading of human consciousness into
machines—at which point it morphs
into a strange religious hybrid.
Transhumanist British thinker Max More
writes that transhumanism is a “blanket
After Victor Frankenstein’s Monster
escaped from the laboratory he went on
a rampage of murder and mayhem. Yet
the Monster had potential for good: He
craved friendship and love and he
helped a starving family. 
Mary Shelley’s1 famous tale is at
least in part the story of responsibility
abandoned. Victor Frankenstein,
scientist, had wished to “pour a torrent
of light into our dark world,” but had
ended by forsaking all moral
responsibility for his creation, which he
abandons in the hope he will forget
about what he has wrought. Out of that
theme has come a long list of
Hollywood mad scientists who seek
power by fleeing from responsibility.
Science (and technology) is power
over the world, and increasingly power
over our biological selves. The
combination of science and humanism
aims to harness science for the
betterment of humanity. Yet we tend to
forget that using science to better the
world is a project as old as science itself.
How we use science in the real world of
today brings up questions of meaning,
values, and responsibility. 
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  3 7
1. Frankenstein: the modern Prometheus, published
in 1818, is British author Mary Shelley’s (1797-1851]
most famous work. 
2. Jules Verne [1828-1905], a French writer, is best
known for his Voyage to the Centre of the Earth
(1864), From the Earth to the Moon (1865), Twenty
Thousand Leagues Under the Sea (1870), and Around
the World in Eighty Days (1873).
L  'Sparkle Man'. Group F. Firework display.
www.groupef.com
© Danica Bijeljac
Verne’s scientific romances2 captured a
wildly progressive view of science, with
such wonderful creations as deep-sea
submarines and ships to the moon.
Science dazzled the human imagination
and grounded a universal belief in
human progress, both moral and
material. But a darker side of that
term given to the school of thought that
refuses to accept traditional human
limitations such as death, disease and
other biological frailties.” 
Other older examples have also
given science the power to influence
what it means to be human. In the
second half of the 19th century, Jules
imagination emerged towards the end
of the 19th century. In the United States
a potent brew of cultural fears − high
immigration, cities as hotbeds of
depravity, evolution and degeneration −
intersected with the scientific
knowledge of the day to create
eugenics. 
The goal of the eugenicists was to
put science into the service of bettering
the human stock, and, indeed, some
appeared to regard humans as similar to
livestock when it came to avoiding
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
3 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
‘negative’ traits. In the U.S. and Britain,
eugenics was often class- and privilege
based, with the middle and upper
classes considered to be biologically
superior. For a while eugenics was
mainstream, subscribed to by scientific
humanists like the great science-fiction
author H. G. Wells,3 who was concerned
about species immortality.
Portraits of the ‘perfect’ scientist
Other scientific humanists, such as
George Sarton,4 one of the founders of
the discipline of the history of science
took a more benign (though still elitist)
approach. In 1924, in an article on ‘The
New Humanism’5 published in Isis, he
wrote that science is the “fruit of an
international and ageless collaboration,
one single organized body, the
common treasure of all peoples, of all
races; in fact, the only patrimony upon
which they all have equal rights.” For
Sarton, humanity’s true purpose is in
the “creation of new values, intellectual
values; the gradual unveiling and
unfolding of the harmony of nature, the
development and organization of what
we call art and science.” Yet again,
science was given power over values
and meaning. 
Another universalist, Morris Goran,
writing in The Journal of Higher
Education in 1943 described his perfect
scientist in a politically utopian vision:
“He will belong to mankind at all times,
serving human values, eternally vigilant
for transgressions, and policing society
against tyranny, intolerance, and
despotism . . . The threat of one
moment’s refusal by the scientists of the
world to do the bidding of tyrants
would forever ensure peaceful solutions
of world problems.” This is the scientist
as philosopher king, whose knowledge
of science gives him power and moral
authority. 
3. Herbert George Wells [1866-1946], English writer
of science fiction, is best known to readers for The
Time Machine (1895), The Invisible Man (1897) and
The War of the Worlds (1898).
4. George Sarton [1884-1956], the Belgian born
American historian, is known primarily for his 3-
volume Introduction to the History of Science. 
5. This article was originally published in 1918, in
Scientia, in French.
6 George Perkins Marsh [1801-1882], was an
American diplomat and philologist.
L Microscope photos of stem cells taken in 2001 by the Généthon laboratory in Evry (Génopole) in France.
Using science to better the world
is a project as old as science itself.
©
  P
hi
lip
pe
 P
la
ill
y 
/ E
ur
el
io
s 
/ L
oo
ka
tS
ci
en
ce
s 
In the 1970s, science and humanism
finally clashed when they intersected in
sociobiology. In this new discipline,
evolutionary theory was applied to
social behavior in animals and humans.
Extreme forms of biological
determinism argued that the social
status quo reflected biology. Society, in
effect, was being forced to mirror the
science of the day. Applying biological
determinism to male aggression, female
subjugation, or lagging IQ scores
among African Americans suggested an
unchangeable reality of inequality and
inferiority. 
Paleontologist and evolutionary
biologist Stephen Jay Gould fought the
determinists through such popular
books as The Mismeasure of Man (1981).
For Gould, humanity shared a common
genetic heritage, on top of which
existed significant social and cultural
differences. G. P. Marsh,6 the man who
first sounded a warning about
humanity’s environmental impact on
the natural world, beginning in the 19th
century, believed that science and
technology would solve the problems
created by humans, but in that solving
would create new problems. 
We will need both science and
humanism to work together in the
future. We should also learn from past
mistakes. We must not expect from
science that it will provide us with
ultimate meanings. It cannot tell us who
we should be and it cannot tell us what
“better” means. Science is a human
creation, and it has the meaning and
purpose that each generation gives it.
Responsibility and ethical behavior
should be central to the choices we
make. ■
Science cannot tell us who we
should be and it cannot tell us
what “better” means.
Michal Meyer was born in Israel. She
has worked as a meteorologist in New
Zealand and Fiji and as a journalist in
Israel. She has a Ph.D. in the history of
science and has worked for the
Chemical Heritage Foundation since
September 2009. She is the editor in
chief of Chemical Heritage magazine
(www.chemheritage.org/discover/ma
gazine/index.aspx)
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Bioethics did not arise through some
accident or sudden illumination on the
part of a clairvoyant thinker. Its
emergence can be explained by
historical, scientific and social factors.
Over the past fifty years, spectacular
progress in medical science has opened
up unforeseen possibilities for scientific
research, and has brought irrefutable
improvement in public health, while
raising unanticipated challenges in
terms of ethics and morals.
Each new breakthrough in biology and
the health sciences, such as organ
grafts, which have saved countless lives,
or assisted reproduction techniques,
which can solve fertility issues for
couples, has faced social and
psychological obstacles, and raised
religious and ethical questions. The
same is true of research on human
embryos—a particularly sensitive
subject as it touches on the origins of
life, and involves moral concepts as well
as scientific and even financial
interests—from pre-implantation
genetic diagnosis (a technique that
permits babies to be born who are free
of incurable inherited diseases), to the
use of stem cells (which can transform
into a wide range of specialized cells
and are crucial for the future of
regenerative medicine).
Faced with the major dilemmas raised by progress in bioscience and biotechnology,
bioethics needs to provide new ethical solutions, aimed at reconciling greater acceptance
of the potential of these disciplines with a vigilance and responsibility that is crucial for
protecting the values of humanism in all circumstances.
Bioethics: 
unimagined challenges
1. American scientist Van R. Potter was the first to
use the term “bioethics”, in an article published in
1970.
SALVADOR BERGEL
Bioethics has to find the right
balance between medical
progress and respect for
human life.©
 M
a
ss
im
o
 B
re
g
a
/L
o
o
ka
tS
ci
e
n
ce
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
4 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
These are not isolated or limited
discoveries. We are witnessing a genuine
biological revolution. In just a few
decades, scientists have managed to
decode the chemical basis of heredity,
the genetic code shared by all living
beings, and to lay the foundations for
molecular biology and a new genetics.
This has led to genetic engineering, in
other words, a ‘technoscience’ that can
manipulate and exchange genes
between members of a single species
and between different species. Mankind
can now manipulate and modify genetic
information for practical purposes, and
can even act on his own biological
nature as a species—which is certainly
the most disturbing aspect from a
bioethical point of view.
This progress in the life sciences has
repercussions for the very concept of
what it means to be human, and raises
ethical, social and legal issues that go
beyond science. This is where bioethics is
called upon, to arrive at a fair and
insightful balance between medical
progress and respect for human life.
Bioethics must recognize the
benefits of these scientific
breakthroughs, while remaining
constantly alert to the risks and dangers
they may present. While this progress
can lead to promising new ways of
eradicating diseases that have long
affected human health, it also raises
justifiable fears about undesirable effects
and possible misuse, such as genetic
manipulation and its various
applications, the return of eugenic
doctrines—which now have a range of
sophisticated tools at their disposal—or
experiments on vulnerable populations.
The appearance of bioethics
coincided with the widespread outcry
raised by the horrors of the Second
World War, a reaction that culminated in
the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights in 1948. The overriding goal of
bioethics is based on this humanist
principle, of affirming the primacy of the
human being and defending the dignity
and freedom inherent in the mere fact of
belonging to the species, in the face of
the shifting and constantly evolving
context of the life sciences.
Dialogue, consensus and tolerance 
Bioethics stands as a bulwark of
humanism both in terms of its goals as
well as its multidisciplinary nature. To
provide appropriate solutions to new
scientific challenges, for which
traditional ethics has proven to be
insufficient, we have had to find ways
for the natural sciences and social
sciences to communicate with one
another, each with its own
methodologies and specific viewpoints,
and to bring together different fields of
knowledge, ranging from philosophy,
medicine and biology, to law, sociology
and anthropology.
Bioethics also integrates the values of
humanism in its methods and practices,
aiming to achieve consensus through a
constructive and intelligent dialogue
with all the various sectors concerned.
Society is no longer content to look on
passively when faced with choices that
threaten its survival and compromise its
moral responsibility. Bioethics therefore
has to impose an attitude of openness
and tolerance, geared toward the
adoption of standards and laws that
respect the realities of multicultural
communities, with their own unique
traditions and beliefs. 
But these humanist values do more
than just encourage theoretical thought;
they also apply to specific issues in
everyday life, such as problems raised by
hospital practices. The field has also
expanded to include the social
dimensions of health, such as poverty,
food and access to safe drinking water, to
health services and drugs. 
Bioethics has sparked a global
militancy that is helping to turn the
ideals of world justice into reality,
through the initiatives of national ethics
committees and hospital committees, as
well as through teaching and research. It
should also be noted that, almost
without exception, medical schools now
include bioethics in their teaching
programmes, demonstrating its essential
role in medical practice. 
Hospital bioethics committees have
been set up in virtually every health
service, and there is not a single country
without a national bioethics committee
or an equivalent group of ad hoc experts.
Codes, standards and protocols
addressing bioethics have been adopted
everywhere, and UNESCO considered it
essential to create a forum for reflection
and debate—the International Bioethics
Committee—and to strengthen the
discipline by drawing up guidelines
based on human rights, as set out in
three Universal Declarations.
This alliance between bioethics and
human rights heralds a new form of
humanism that is in tune with the
expectations and challenges of our
times. This renewed humanism
recognizes the biological and ethical
components of human nature, whose
dignity must be safeguarded here and
now, while assuming the responsibility
and the duty to protect life in all its
manifestations, for generations to come
and ultimately, to guarantee the survival
of the species. ■
2. An example, among others is the aberrant
pseudo-scientific experiments to which prisoners in
the Nazi concentration camps were subjected. 
Salvador Bergel (Argentina) holds a
law degree, is a specialist in bioethics,
and occupies the UNESCO Chair in
Bioethics at the Universidad de Buenos
Aires.
L Flasks of liquid nitrogen containing paillettes
used in assisted reproductive technology. 
©
  M
a
ss
im
o
 B
re
g
a
/L
o
o
ka
tS
ci
e
n
ce
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  4 1
Humanism, as it appeared in the
Renaissance, resulted from a merging of
revived classical Greek thinking, with its
sense of the primacy of man over the
Earth, consolidating man as a being
apart from the rest of nature –
separated and dominant. This vision not
only prevailed, it was reinforced by the
absolute domina tion and
transformation of nature by man.
While this humanism has gained
ground, it nevertheless began a course
of dehumanization. The atomic bomb
alone is a symbol of the creation of a
schizophrenic civilization. The human
being dominated nature, using the
technology that he created, but
humanity started to be dominated by
technology that now defines the
characteristics of the social system,
destroying the environment and
increasing social inequality.
The uncertain future of our planet
means that we will have to rethink the
humanist project, which, for me must be
built on seven pillars.
Promoting planetary politics
What the city meant to the Athenians
has, today, become the nation state for
modern democracies. And citizenship –
this Greek creation that indicated the
commitment of city resi dents to the city
If, nowadays, value has been transformed into price, and a tree is only worth the timber it
produces, or an animal its meat and leather, it is, according to Cristovam Buarque, because
the humanist project has lost its way over the centuries. For a new form of humanism to
emerge that is founded on ethical modernity, it must take account of the planetary
challenges we are facing.
CRISTOVAM BUARQUE
This article is an extract of a presentation given by
Cristovam Buarque at the Third Global Forum of the
Alliance of Civilizations in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, in
May 2010.
Seven pointers for the future of©
 L
a
u
re
n
t 
La
ve
d
e
r 
/ 
Lo
o
ka
tS
ci
e
n
ce
s
"Moon Game", photograph
by Laurent Laveder
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
4 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
itself - began to turn into a commitment
to the whole country.
The present planetary crisis raises the
issue of our responsibility as citizens of
the Earth. In other words, it calls for an
individual commitment to the fate of
humankind and of the Earth. For me, this
new humanism must be sensitive to the
importance of all human beings, to the
feeling of global solidarity. 
Respecting cultural diversity
In the past, man has been contemptuous
of his fellow men, as witnessed by the
genocide against indigenous peoples of
America, the enslavement of Africa and
all the other forms of racism and
xenophobia that reveal a sense of
superiority. A new humanism must get
rid of ethnocentrism; it must become
‘acentric’ and respect cultural diversity.
We must calm the conflicts between
cultures and consider their variety as an
indicator of the wealth of civilization,
where their interaction is more than the
sum of the parts.
Caring for the environment
Humanism has been irresponsibly
arrogant with regard to nature, seeing no
value in it. It has exhausted natural
resources and undermined the
ecological balance to such an extent that
the continuity of civilization is
threatened. Only human labour or a price
set by the market generate value on a
threatened and worthless planet. The
value of trees is in its timber, that of
animals in its meat and leather. 
The new humanism that I am calling for
should seek a civilization that is fully
integrated into the environmental
balance. Economic output should no
longer be measured only by the sum of
material goods and services - GDP. It
must also take into account any costs
due to waste resulting from the
production process.
Guaranteeing equal opportunities
Humanism was an oasis for the dream of
equality, but capitalism widened
inequalities to such an extent that
differences in life expectancy now
depend on personal income. I dream of a
humanism that ensures equal
opportunities, that will act as a ladder for
social ascent, drawing ecological lines to
define the limits on a consumption that
is depleting the environment, while
protecting the dispossessed.
Promoting balanced production
The idea of valuing labour, instead of
land, made man the value-maker and
put workers at the centre of the
production process. However, this great
leap worked against humanism when
the value was transformed into a price
defined by mystical market forces
beyond human control. Explanations
replace justice, demands replace will,
and consumer desires replace the
fulfilment of needs. To build a new
humanism we must redefine the march
of nations and of humankind towards
an ecologically balanced production
process. And it must assign value to
non-tradable goods. 
The new humanism must also
abolish the slavery that continues to
imprison man by reducing him to a
mere cog in the production process.
Integration through education
Humanism in the industrial era
promised a world of equal income,
thanks to the economy. Capitalism said
that the increase in production and the
laws of the market would lead to a
‘trickle down’, distributing the income
from top to bottom of the social
pyramid; whereas in socialism, the
distribu tion would be ensured by the
state and the laws of planning.
Nowadays, under the new
knowledge and human capital
economy, the key to economic progress
and social justice must be sought in
quality education for all. The challenge
of the new humanism is to ensure that
each child has access to equally good
education, regardless of race, family
income or place of residence. The ‘trickle
down’ promised by capitalism will no
longer come from the market, but
instead from a ‘trickle up’ induced by
education.
The long-term purpose of this
process will be the integration of all
peoples around the world, using all
available techniques in a planetary
network.
An ethical technical modernity
The industrial process of civilization is
characterized by the pursuit of
technical modernity, defined by the use
of up-to-date technology. This required
the creation of an economic rationality
that justifies the products of cutting-
edge technology and leaves behind the
social goals, thus relegating ethical
values.
The new humanism must use ethical
values as vectors that set up the social
goals, and will see them as the
foundation of an economic rationality
that defines all technical choices. Even
here, techniques should be chosen
according to ethical and aesthetic
standards, not only in terms of
economic efficiency.
Technical modernity, defined by the
originality of technology and
humanism, will be replaced, in the new
humanism, by an ethical modernity. For
instance, instead of being defined by
the number of private cars in
circulation, modern transportation
would be judged by its results –
reduction in travel time, user comfort,
punctuality, universal access.
Like Einstein trying to dialogue with
God – in whom he did not believe – to
learn how he had drawn all the details
of the world, the new humanism must
imagine the ideal way to build a
civilization that is democratic, tolerant,
efficient for humanity and each human
being, and that respects nature. The
only way is dialogue between people
and between men and nature. The new
humanism will promote the dialogue
between cultures and Mother Earth. ■
Cristovam Buarque is a Senator and
Professor at the University of Brasilia,
and was Minister of Education in 2003.
He has devoted his political career
particularly to combating illiteracy,
implementing agrarian reforms,
improving the Brazilian health system
and improving working conditions in
the country.
Nowadays, under the new
knowledge and human capital
economy, the key to economic
progress and social justice must
be sought in quality education
for all. The challenge of the new
humanism is to ensure that
each child has access to equally
good education, regardless of
race, family income or place of
residence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Africa Week, 25 to 28 May.
Jean-Marie Lehn at the launch of
the International Year of Chemistry
on 27 January.
Stéphane Hessel at the
fourth University of the
Earth on 2 April.
8 March, International Women's Day: Irina Bokova
with a delegation from Thailand.
Mónica González Mujica (Chile), on 26 January. Homage to Franz Liszt by the Zoltan
Kodaly orchestra (Hungary) on 29 July.
Mimi Barthelemy (Haiti) dedicates her
latest children's books on 21 February. 
Claude Lanzmann launches
his film Shoah in Persian on
7 March, 2011
Modeste Nzapassara (Central African
Republic), 27 March.
Amos Coulanges, a year after the
earthquake in Haiti on 21 January.
Alasita festival, a Bolivian ritual, 24 January.
2
0
1
1
:  
U
N
E
S
C
O
 H
E
A
D
Q
U
A
R
T
E
R
S
International UNESCO-L'Oréal 
laureates, 2 March 2011 
An afternoon with some
astronautson 22 March.
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l R
av
a
ss
a
rd
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
ia
 F
re
in
d
o
rf
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l R
av
a
ss
a
rd
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l R
av
a
ss
a
rd
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l R
av
a
ss
a
rd
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l R
av
a
ss
a
rd
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
ia
 F
re
in
d
o
rf
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l R
av
a
ss
a
rd
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
4 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
In the 2008 film Kassim, The Dream,
where you were Executive Producer,
the hero is a former child soldier who
cannot forgive himself for the crimes
he committed.  Who is he?
The tragic story of the young Ugandan,
Kassim Ousama, is a good example. He
is a beautiful man, a great boxer who
was famous as a light middleweight in
the early 2000’s. But the demons from
his past caught up with him, preventing
him from realizing his dream. He quit in
the middle of training for the world
championship. In the film you see him
go back to Uganda and visit the grave of
his father, who was killed because of
him. Kassim has lost his self-esteem and
watches himself deteriorating from
within, as he tries to reconcile – not just
with the world, but with himself, with
the things he did as a child soldier.
Have many of the former child
soldiers that you met managed to
forgive themselves?
No. But I met a lot who still have
nightmares.  Some of those who had
committed atrocities had come to some
form of self-forgiveness, but it was not
complete. The most difficult part for
them is rejoining their own
communities, where they may have
O
U
R
 G
U
E
S
T
Child
soldiers:  
Recently appointed UNESCO
Goodwill Ambassador, the
American actor and
director, Forest Whitaker, is
doing his utmost to help
child soldiers. He uses every
available opportunity to
help them find a voice, to
rejoin the communities they
have been banished from, to
get an education, to forgive
themselves and regain their
self esteem.
FOREST WHITAKER interviewed by Katerina Markelova
a new life ahead
©
U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  4 5
J  Forest Whitaker at UNESCO in June, 2011.
carried out acts of violence against their
own neighbours. It’s one thing to know
that these children were taken away and
forced to kill, but a killer remains a killer
in the eyes of society. How, under these
conditions, does one forgive oneself?
How to heal oneself of such suffering? It
needs the most extraordinary efforts.
These young people need to find
activities that occupy them completely.
Otherwise it’s hard for them to move on.
I’m convinced that education
provides a way out for them. Education is
an opening of the mind, so that people
can see the possibilities that are available
to each of us. Education can bring
understanding, and then, hopefully, we
can move to a form of compassion. And
this, hopefully, can lead us to forgiveness,
which in turn leads to love – a love of
ourselves and a love of others. This is
something that child soldiers continue to
work through with the tools that they’ve
been given. And some are more
successful than others. 
What do the gangs in the USA and the
civil wars in Africa have in common?
That is precisely the question I look at in
the documentary “Common Destiny”
that we are working on right now. We
interviewed a Ugandan child soldier
and a member of the Blood gang in Los
Angeles. We started to compare their
stories and realized that they were
extremely similar. They were both
forced into violence. And they’re both
fighting people from their own
neighbourhood, even their own family. 
As a child, I grew up watching the
birth of the gangs in the United States,
particularly the Crips and the Bloods in
Los Angeles. I watched them as they
first named themselves and then
became international gangs. I lived in
the Blue or Crip neighbourhood, and my
cousin lived in the Red or Blood
neighbourhood. My cousin joined the
Bloods, and if I had joined the Crips, we
would have been enemies and might
have killed each other. In the conflict
zones of Africa, where armed rebels
kidnap children and turn them into
Why did you decide to support the
cause of child soldiers? 
I began working with child soldiers
four or five years ago. Before that, I’d
been campaigning against malaria in
Africa and working with organizations
dealing with physical abuse. I’ve also
worked with gangs in the USA. I see
parallels between the child soldiers in
Africa and some of the people I have
known in gangs. 
I don’t divorce myself from the rest
of the world. I see these young people
as parts of myself. I strongly believe
that we are part of a single entity and
that ultimately we want to connect as
one. Trying to understand and help
these young gang members and child
soldiers is, for me, not an intellectual,
or even an emotional choice. It’s a
spiritual choice. It doesn’t need to be
explained or justified, it’s in the natural
order of events. It’s the way I see the
universe and the way I perceive God.
K Child soldier with his family, Angola, 2004.
©
 U
N
 P
h
o
to
/C
h
ri
s 
S
a
tt
lb
e
rg
e
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
soldiers, don’t young cousins become
enemies in just the same way?
So there are similarities between the
gangs and child soldiers. They both
slowly get caught up in the world of
smuggling, trafficking drugs and arms,
even if they’re not always visible.
In ‘Common Destiny’ you are going to
show the mechanisms that can bring
peace to communities torn apart by
conflict. How do you intend to do this? 
We’re going to follow a number of
individuals around the world living in
conflict zones. With the support of
UNESCO, we will be following their
journeys, their struggles, their successes.
And at the same time there will be
interviews about what people feel peace
is. We will be talking to people from
government and to NGOs. The
documentary will allow people’s voices to
be heard, while giving examples of how
we come to peace.  
We haven’t yet decided which
countries we will be going to. I’m in the
process of doing that right now and was
in discussions earlier, here at UNESCO. 
I can just say that I think we will be looking
at different types of conflict, such as those
linked to the environment, migration, and
xenophobia. I think I will be working on
this project for about two years. 
Do you have any other projects as a
new UNESCO Goodwill Ambassador?  
I have a few. I’m going to be working on a
training process with youth on conflict
resolution. We’ll help child refugees to
move back to their countries of origin,
and will train others to support them on
their return. We will also set up an
Internet space, so that they can be
connected to the rest of the world and
each other. 
My own production company is
presently making about six
documentaries, most of them on peace
and reconciliation. We are also making a
feature film called ‘Better Angels’ with a
French company, Studio 37, on the same
subject. This film is about a war reporter
who goes to Uganda to interview Kony,
chief of the Lord’s Resistance Army,
which includes child soldiers. 
You are going to play that journalist,
aren’t you?
Yes, we went to Uganda a few months
ago to do some more research, to
interview some more soldiers and to
make sure that we were completely
accurate in what we were portraying.
Meanwhile we are doing a piece just on
compassion, and what compassion
really means. We’ve just started working
on a documentary about the Rwandan
cyclists who were caught up in the civil
war in the early 1990s. It’s an uplifting
film. And we shouldn’t forget that the
2012 Olympics in London will be the
first time a Rwandan cyclist has
competed. ■
4 6 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R
250,000 child soldiers worldwide
According to a UN report published in 2010, almost a quarter of a million
children worldwide have been recruited by rebel groups and armies. The
previous year, though, there had been some success in demobilizing child
soldiers, particularly in the Philippines, Democratic Republic of Congo, Southern
Sudan, Sri Lanka and Burundi, where they were reformed and reintegrated into
society. The UN pointed out that there are no statistics on the number of
children killed in conflicts around the world.
Children are easy prey for militias and other rebel organizations and can be
very useful to them. It is not hard to indoctrinate children or get them to take
greater risks than an adult, even to commit worse atrocities. Children are likely
to feel they have to do what an adult tells them to do. And they will more readily
take any drugs they are given. In the July-September 2011 issue of the UNESCO
Courier, the former Congolese soldier, Serge Amisi, who went on to become an
artist, gives a compelling account of his experiences.
2010 marked the tenth anniversary of the adoption of the Optional Protocol
to the Convention on the Rights of the Child, concerning the involvement of
children in armed conflicts. To date, 132 Member States have ratified the
Optional Protocol, while 24 have signed it and 36 have neither signed nor
ratified it.  – J.Š.
See: ‘Serge Amisi and his Miracle Weapons’ available on line:
www.unesco.org/new/en/unesco-courier/archives/ (use keywords to search
within the digital archive).
L Poster for the film, 'Kassim, the Dream', for which Forest Whitaker was executive producer in 2008.
©
 A
 B
e
lie
ve
 M
e
d
ia
 a
n
d
 U
rb
a
n
 L
a
n
d
sc
a
p
e
s 
fi
lm
 p
ro
d
u
c
ti
o
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  4 7
more imagination than money, I made
television programmes that went out
very late at night and were often in the
top ten most popular programmes,
rebroadcast all across Latin America.
This is not just a result of the vein of
magical realism that runs through Latin
American literature, with its spiritual
leader, Nobel laureate Gabriel García
Márquez,1 but also of a deep conviction
I am an incurable romantic who
admires the paper book, along with
ancient parchments and the cave art of
long-disappeared cultures. But that has
not stopped me from being one of that
species of writer that has not hated
television. For over ten years, and with
Since the turn of the 21st century we have been seeing a flurry of virtual libraries opening
on the Internet and eBooks getting off to a flying start. Are these new media likely to
dethrone King Paper, until now the unchallenged ruler of his kingdom? The Chilean
writer Antonio Skármeta, whose childhood experiences of radio started him on his career,
wagers that the ‘traditional’ book will survive the digital frenzy. 
A special place for 
ANTONIO SKÁRMETA
1. Colombian writer, who received the Nobel Prize
in Literature in 1982.
T
H
E
 F
U
T
U
R
E
 O
F
 T
H
E
 B
O
O
K
 
This article is taken from a paper presented by
Antonio Skármeta at the Second UNESCO World
Forum on Culture and Cultural Industries, Focus
2011, in Monza, Italy, 6 to 8 June 2011.   
'Book of Psalms, by painter and
sculptor,  Patrick Medrano and
photographer, Katy Anderson. These
two American artists work together in
Houston, Texas (USA) ©
 P
a
tr
ic
k 
M
e
d
ra
n
o
 &
 K
a
ty
 A
n
d
e
rs
o
n
  
w
w
w
.k
a
ty
a
n
d
e
rs
o
n
.c
o
m
 <
h
tt
p
:/
/w
w
w
.k
a
ty
a
n
d
e
rs
o
n
.c
o
m
>
  w
w
w
.p
a
tr
ic
km
e
d
ra
n
o
.c
o
m
 <
h
tt
p
:/
/w
w
w
.p
a
tr
ic
km
e
d
ra
n
o
.c
o
m
>
 
since childhood that tales that are
written down shine more brilliantly
when they capture the primary joy of
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
4 8 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
spoken language. This conviction did
not come to me through reading
Foucault2 or anthropologists like Lévi-
Strauss,3 but from living in a rural
village at the age of eight with my
grandmother, and, at eleven or twelve,
with my friends in a neighbourhood of
Buenos Aires.  
My childhood was a long love affair
with radio, and my first experience of
stories told without using any kind of
equipment. After dinner, when my
grandmother sat down to knit her
endless cardigans, she would ask me to
sit next to her, while she listened to
episodes of horrible melodramas with
plaintive music. She was so engrossed
in these radio serials that she would get
cross if anyone asked her a question or
if the telephone rang. And she would
rant at the stupidity of the protagonists
who were more reluctant than her to
act. 
I remember one serial where,
episode after episode, two crooks tried
in vain to steal a million-dollar diamond
ring from an aristocrat. Every time they
were about to succeed, something
happened – the maid came into the
bedroom, her husband came over to
kiss her, the lady shut herself in the
bathroom to take a shower. One day
they poured a sleeping draught into
her soup, and, when their victim fell to
the floor, they went about removing
her ring. But it was so tight that, after
ten minutes of struggling, they had to
escape without the jewel.  “The fools!”
she said to me, beside herself, in her
Croatian-tinted Spanish. My
grandmother was a passionate woman.
“All they had to do was chop off her
finger with an axe!”
Getting started as a writer
The electricity supply in the village was
precarious. The frequent power cuts
meant that it was impossible to keep
the radio on. My grandmother used to
curse if the power cut out at the height
of the action. So she would turn to me
and say, “So, Antonio, what do you think
is happening right now?” And with a lot
of gesticulating and “um’s and ah’s,” I
would tell her the story, with completely
fantastic details, just as she liked it,
straight out of my imagination. My
grandmother would nod and continue
her knitting, her eyes fixed on the
ceiling, as if that were where my story
was coming from.  
One Saturday, when the electricity
was working and her thriller was blaring
out of the radio at full volume, my
grandmother turned off the set and said
to me  “Antonio, I prefer it when you tell
the story.” This, I think, was what got me
started in my career as a writer – with no
help whatsoever!
As you will understand, satisfying
the appetite for fiction of a grandmother
was a fabulous invitation to embrace the
fragile condition of writer. The glowing
report handed out by my forebear for
my dramatic ‘supplements’ turned out to
be more encouragement for me than a
PhD in Creative writing from Harvard.  
For a Chilean teenager at the time, to
be a writer obviously meant being a
North American writer. And in New York!
Climbing to the top of the Empire State
Building with a pretty blonde in the
palm of his hand like King Kong. There,
in that great global city, was all the
excitement anyone needed. I’d have to
go ‘on the road’ like Kerouac4 and the
Beat poets. 
Being a writer who learned to love
literature without any material – except
perhaps the human voice and the
silence of the desert – it didn’t much
matter in which airport stories landed.
For me, the problem that literature
poses lies not so much in what media is
used, but in the lack of readers. If I sing
the praises of the paper book, it is
because, until now it has been the
vehicle that enabled me to find readers
in over thirty languages. But that is also
the case for the films based on my
novels, and even the operas made from
them. 
So I am not afraid of
transformations. On the contrary, I
welcome them. I use them. I know that
the letters my postman will deliver to
Pablo Neruda will provoke the same
emotion, whatever medium or surface
they are presented on, be it a book,
iPad, eBook, film or even a theatre play.
Literature is much more than
information
When I looked at the statistics on the
number of people reading electronic
books I noticed that, up to now, the
market for them in my own language,
Castillian, is disproportionately far less
than that in English.  
But I would like to put forward the
following idea – that the medium of
paper when used in literature, in other
words the book, is so sophisticated an
object, at least in the field of art, that it
will always hold its place alongside the
new media. And I even wonder if it will
not do so to its own advantage, for one
very good reason – the screen has
become the basic working tool for
mankind. 
L "Box of books", painting by Dominique Mantel
©
 D
o
m
in
iq
u
e
 M
a
n
te
l
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  4 9
Wherever we are, most of the
working day is spent between the more
or less strident flashes – according to
the quality of the machine – of
computers. The electronic world is
above all associated with work. It
intensifies our vision, and absorbs our
attention. It controls us.
Of course the computer also offers a
special place for communication
between individuals who feel
connected when they are using it. But it
is interesting that the most popular
form of expression between surfers on
the internet is the abbreviated, concise,
minimalist message. That of
information. Twitter.
whole days burning our retinas on the
movements of the stock market, and
then, in the evening, watch a superb
film where the beaches of Tahiti are
portrayed in three dimensions, with the
beauties painted by Gauguin. But what
we really want is to be on these
beaches, admiring the skin, enjoying
the breeze, swimming in the warm
cobalt waters of the sea, and not left
with a substitute. 
A sensible cohabitation between
media
In any discussion of the future of the
book, we need to remember that the
story carried by the paper – from
ancient parchments to modern print –
has created prestigious spaces for
communication, such as bookshops,
national and local libraries and book
clubs, and that these forms of
publication have joined with other arts,
transforming the printed and bound
story into an object like no other – with
2. Michel Foucault, [1926-1984], French philosopher
and Professor at the Collège de France.
3. Claude Lévi-Strauss [1908-2009], French
anthropologist and member of the Académie
française.
4. Jack Kerouac [1922-1969], American writer, is
best known for his novel On the Road. He belonged
to the Beat Generation (beatniks), young writers
and poets revolting against a society that they
considered to be materialistic and superficial.  
5. Pablo Neruda [1904-1973], Chilean poet, Nobel
laureate in Literature, 1971. In his novel, Burning
Patience, Skármeta tells the story of Mario Jimenez,
the postman on Isla Negra in Chile, where his only
client is Pablo Neruda, who went there to write in
peace and quiet.
I know that the letters my
postman will deliver to Pablo
Neruda will provoke the same
emotion, whatever medium or
surface they are presented on, be
it a book, iPad, eBook, film or
even a theatre play.
its graphic design, its illustrations, its
covers, and the people who flock
around them in public spaces. 
The publication of a good book
rapidly evokes collective admiration – it
is a cultural event. I doubt whether the
ghost-like publication of a story in the
private solitude of digital space ever
possessed the same enthusiastic grace
as the birth of a book printed on paper. 
©
 R
u
th
 L
a
n
tz
 -
 w
w
w
.lo
ca
l-
a
rt
is
ts
.o
rg
/u
se
rs
/r
u
th
-l
a
n
tz
But that is exactly the point.
Literature is so much more than
information. A scientific document is a
mine of information, and that is all that
textbooks are – information that has to
be understood, learned, mastered and
applied. 
Literature is far removed from these
pragmatic criteria. It is the pleasure of
words, conjuring images that transport
the soul to places that the language of
science has not yet codified. To be brief
but clear, creative literature, whether
narrative or poetry, belongs more to the
domain of pleasure than of work.  
I think that this psychological factor
– avoidance of the other – will protect
the book from the voracity of
information. From those who provide it
and those who ask for it. Obviously we
can buy a DVD and watch the latest film
to win an award at Cannes on a screen
at home. But we continue to go to the
cinema. We are apparently religious
enough that our intimate conversations
with God take place through prayer. But
we go to temples and churches and
take part in the rituals. We can obviously
speak words of love to a loved one by
telephone or by email – but we seek
them out so that our kiss can transport
us beyond their lips. We can spend
K "Blinking Transcendent" by American artist, Ruth Lantz
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
5 0 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
When we sit at home in front of the
TV, we have a whole range of
programmes to choose from, in several
languages. By zapping we can go all
over the world. But our initial inclination
is always towards local news, towards
the intimacy and sense of belonging
inspired by faces close at hand and the
events of our own country, which
provide the subject matter for our
everyday conversations and discussions. 
I do not see how the electronic book
could acquire this aura of admiring
simultaneity and collective attention
offered by the solid structure of the
publications industry and its networks of
distribution, from bookshops to
newspapers. What I am trying to say is
that the publication of a book using
existing methods is a cultural event that
puts the extravagant imagination born of
the writer’s fantasy onto the collective
agenda of the people. 
I wager that there will be a wide
cohabitation of many media – the digital
media will remain the faithful allies of
research, information, the ‘work’ of the
intellect, the ‘solitary’ contact with a story.
And print on paper will remain a special
place for the non-utilitarian imagination,
the combination of the arts that find
expression in the book as object. 
Meanwhile, the noble task that those
institutions concerned with universal
culture have set out upon – the creation
of virtual libraries  – deserves the highest
forms of praise. By making all the
magnificent knowledge of mankind
available to people, since stories were
first written down, is an event that we
welcome with joy, as it means that this
information will be distributed and will
influence the existence of millions of
people, who will, as a result, become
better informed, more sensitive and,
consequently, more free. 
Antonio Skármeta, is a Chilean writer
of Croatian descent. Between 1973 and
1989, he lived in exile, first in Argentina
then Germany, a country to which he
returned in 2000 as ambassador to
Chile. His novels include The Dancer
and the Thief (Norton, 2008), Burning
Patience (Pantheon, 1987), and I Dreamt
the Snow was Burning (Readers
International, 1985). His illustrated
children’s book, The Composition
(Groundwood Books, 2000), won him
the 2003 UNESCO Prize for Children’s
and Young People’s Literature in the
Service of Tolerance.
If the printed book is to survive
alongside the almost instantaneous
publication offered by the Internet and
the eBook, large bookstores and places
where books are sold have to become
more appealing. When someone likes a
book, they often think it would make a
good present. And a printed book is the
perfect choice. We are already familiar
with these large, communal spaces –
cinema has not killed off theatre,
television has not meant the end of
cinema, any more than the excellent
quality of reproductions has not sunk
museums and their originals... And there
is another aspect, which I have detected
as I move through various different
languages and continents – people
have a longing for intimacy, to be close
to the artist and the work of art, a wish
to flee all the ear-splitting braying, to be
in real life, at the heart of events. There
is a desire to by-pass the intermediaries.
This might be a minor trend now, but it
is on the increase.
Those who say that the book offers a
more intimate and less mediatized form
of communication with the reader are
right – there is no need to click on a
mouse to plunge in. May our dearest
dream be this intimacy with art, with
the artist and with the reflected silence
that comes from entering the world of
creation and coming away with the
inspiration to approach life with greater
joy and a bit more spice!
Today the printed book is still the
most intimate medium, the least
ephemeral, the most concrete, the most
sensual, the most visionary and even
the one that gives off the most
marvellous aroma – that of blessed ink
spread onto the page. ■
L The Open Book, temporary installation by Lithuanian sculptor Saulius Valius, exhibited at UNESCO in
January 2004 
©
 S
a
u
liu
s 
V
a
liu
s/
U
N
E
S
C
O
Print on paper will remain a
special place for the non-
utilitarian imagination, the
combination of the arts that find
expression in the book as object.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  5 1
How did you meet Prudence?
It was a friend from New York who told
me about her. I started writing to the
King George VI School for children with
disabilities that Prudence attends in
Bulawayo, Zimbabwe. The Headmistress
sent me some footage of the band
performing along with a three-page
text of Prudence recounting her life
story. It was so heart wrenching. What
ROGER ROSS WILLIAMS interviewed by Cathy Nolan
Prudence Mabhena does not have legs, but music has given her wings. Through singing,
this 22-year-old Zimbabwean has overcome several obstacles that hindered her journey: 
a congenital disease, amputation of both legs, family rejection, discrimination, poverty.
Together with seven other young people who shared a similar fate, she founded the group
Liyana (‘It’s raining’ in Ndebele), which inspired American film director, Roger Ross Williams
to produce the 2010 Oscar-winning short film, “Music by Prudence.” He tells us about his
encounter with Prudence that changed his life.
drama! Yet, such hope at the same time!
I then decided to make my first
independent documentary.
By Christmas Day 2008, a few
months later, I was already in
Zimbabwe. There, I followed and filmed
Prudence for two weeks. When I
returned to the United States and
watched the footage, I thought to
myself, “I have discovered a true star.”
Was Prudence cooperative with you?
Prudence took a little bit of convincing.
She didn’t really believe that I would
show up, since she was used to a life of
betrayal and disappointment. So, she
was amazed to see me.
Our first meeting was very intense
and emotionally charged. Never before
had Prudence been asked to talk about
what had happened to her. It was like a
3
 D
E
C
E
M
B
E
R
  
 IN
T
E
R
N
A
T
IO
N
A
L
 D
A
Y
 O
F
 P
E
R
S
O
N
S
 W
IT
H
 D
IS
A
B
IL
IT
IE
S
L Prudence Mabhena at the Mountain Film Festival, in July 2010.
©
 J
e
n
n
if
e
r 
K
o
sk
ie
n
e
n
The Flight of 
Prudence
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
5 2 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
psychotherapy session. The words just
poured out of her. She was in tears. I was
in tears. The cameraman was in tears. I
knew then it would be one of the most
important stories of my life.
I was determined to make it all the
way, but met with many roadblocks.
Filming in Zimbabwe is a physical
challenge. We were never safe from a
power outage, so we had to be sure that
cameras and projectors were
consistently charged. And to make
matters worse, it’s literally not allowed
to film in Zimbabwe. It’s lucky that I
wasn’t arrested or shot during the
election, which was a very violent
period. Several times we almost got
thrown out, and I had to talk my way
out of it at the immigration office. But,
we were in Prudence’s world, a school
for disabled children. We weren’t doing
anything political, and the government
knew that.
How did the film change Prudence’s
life?
Prudence was already a star in her
community, performing concerts all
over town. But, she wasn’t known in the
rest of her country. Now, she’s certainly
one of the most famous women in
Zimbabwe. When she arrived back in
the country after the film received an
Oscar, she couldn’t imagine what to
expect. When the plane landed, she saw
hundreds of people, dozens of media
from all over Africa, and the mayor of
Bulawayo waiting to welcome her. As
she was carried off the plane, her father
was at the foot of its steps on his knees,
tears streaming down his face, and
begging for forgiveness.
At this time, the mayor declared,
“Prudence Mabhena has taught all of us
in Zimbabwe that disability does not
mean inability, and we must change our
attitude towards the disabled.” The
newspapers resonated this idea, and
praised Prudence for putting her
country on the map. One notable
headline read, “Prudence brings Oscar
gold to Zimbabwe.” I don’t know if the
political mentality towards people with
disabilities will change, but one thing is
sure: Prudence has touched the hearts
of many. 
What attracted you to this subject? 
I often think about outsiders and people
who are left behind, forgotten. I identify
with being a minority, I always have.
Mainly because I’ve usually been an
outsider, myself. So Prudence’s story
struck a personal chord with me. I was
abandoned by my father too, although
not to the same extent as Prudence.
Every one of us feels admiration for
people who succeed in triumphing
above their suffering. Prudence did it.
And today, she is sending her message
loud and clear through her song, ‘Never
give up’. She was always determined
and convinced that life would one day
get better. She believes you have to go
through the hard times to appreciate
your gifts in life.
And your film shows that outcasts
can have extraordinary gifts to share.
Disabled children, especially in
developing countries – and particularly
girls – are the last anyone will pay
school fees for, or anything else. They’re
at the bottom of the pecking order. 
And yet, every disabled child who is
abandoned and cast off represents
budding potential. They could grow up
to be singers, writers or even the
president of the United States. 
What has Prudence been doing since
the Oscars?
I connected her with Human Rights
Watch and several NGOs who support
people with disabilities. She has been
training, to travel around the world, as
an advocate for this cause.
What kind of impact did meeting
Prudence have on you?
An enormous impact. Getting close to
Prudence made me realise that the
things I complained about were
actually insignificant. Prudence, she
never complains. It put my life into
perspective. I’m much more thankful for
what I have and all that has gone right
for me. And of course, meeting
Prudence has had a profound effect on
my career. I’m not just speaking about
the Oscar. I mean, this film has given my
work a whole new dimension: it’s
become an opportunity to do some
good in the world. Hopefully, it will
inspire countries, families and
everybody to fully appreciate people
with disabilities. ■
Visit the website of Prudence Mabhena:
www.musicbyprudence.com/
J Roger Ross Williams  in the UNESCO Courier
offices in December 2010
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/M
ic
h
e
l R
av
a
ss
a
rd
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
Félix Houphouët-Boigny 
Peace Prize, 2010 for Plaza de
Mayo Grandmothers
The Félix Houphouët-Boigny Peace
Prize for 2010 was awarded on 14
September 2011, in a ceremony at
UNESCO HQ, to The Grandmothers of
the Plaza de Mayo, a non-
governmental organization, based in
Argentina which was represented by
Estela de Carlotto, President of the
organization. The Prize, which
consisted of a cheque for US$ 150,000,
a gold medal and a peace diploma,
was awarded by Irina Bokava,
Director-General of UNESCO, in the
presence of several Heads of State
and of Government: Cristina
Fernández de Kirchner (Argentina);
Alassane Dramane Ouattara (Côte
d’Ivoire); Blaise Compaoré (Burkina
Faso); Abdoulaye Wade (Senegal);
Mohamed Ould Abdel Aziz
(Mauritania); Pascal Irénée Koupaki
(Benin) and Brigi Rafini (Niger).
UNESCO chose the
organization in recognition of its
tireless battle for over thirty years
in favour of human rights, justice
and peace. It was founded in
1977 to locate the biological
families of children kidnapped
during the political repression of
the military dictatorship in
Argentina. 
The Félix Houphouët-Boigny
Peace Prize created in 1989 and
awarded by UNESCO annually,
honours people, institutions and
organizations that have
contributed significantly to the
promotion, research, preservation
or maintaining of peace. ■
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/D
a
n
ic
a
 B
ije
lja
c
Russian singer
Alsou
Abramova
named 
UNESCO Artist
for Peace
In recognition of her commitment to
help the world’s most vulnerable
people, 28-year-old Russian singer
Alsou Abramova, was named UNESCO
Artist for Peace on 7 July at a
ceremony at UNESCO headquarters. 
Her ‘Radouga’ [Rainbow]
Foundation helps restore schools and
hospitals, build churches and
mosques. The musician also supports
several orphanages. 
In her new role, Alsou will devote
even more attention to education and
medical aid for children, as well as
building orphanages.
Born in Tatarstan, she won
recognition on the Russian musical
scene when she was 15 with her first
album, Alsou. A year later she was
chosen to represent Russia at the
Eurovision Song Contest in Stockholm
(Sweden), where she won second
place. 
Singer, songwriter, pianist and
actor, Alsou joins the list of
distinguished Artists for Peace, that
includes Céline Dion (Canada),
Franghiz Ali-Zadeh (Azerbaijan) and
Marcel Khalifé (Lebanon). The title is
awarded to internationally renowned
personalities who lend a particular
resonance to the messages of
UNESCO. ■
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
ia
 F
re
in
d
o
rf
T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1 .  5 3
Humanism 
in the digital age
‘Is the new humanism the response to
the scientific and cultural challenges
of our time?’ This is the theme of a
conference organized by the
Permanent Delegation of Spain to
UNESCO at the Organization’s
headquarters on 14 and 15 November
2011. The thirty participants will
include the Spanish Minister of
Culture, Ángeles González-Sinde,
Chilean writer, Jorge Edwards, Italian
writer, Roberto Toscano, French
philosophers Julia Kristeva and Roger-
Pol Droit, Spanish philosophers Adela
Cortina and Víctor Gómez Pin, the
Senegalese writer, Fatou Diome, as
well as other jurists, journalists,
scientists and experts. ■
For further information contact:
dl.spain@unesco-delegations.org.
Tel: (+ 33 1) 4568 3385.
M
IL
E
S
T
O
N
E
S
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
Promoting peace 
through sport 
Herbie
Hancock   
is appointed
UNESCO
Goodwill
Ambassador
Herbie Hancock, the prominent US
jazz musician, was named as a
Goodwill Ambassador by the
Director-General of UNESCO, Irina
Bokova, in a ceremony on 22 July,
2011 at UNESCO HQ, for his
dedication to the promotion of
peace through dialogue, culture and
the arts.
“I watch the news, I vote, I have
opinions about the world I am living
in. I am living in this world just like
everybody else […] I want to justify
my life and the only justification is
how you have fought the battle to
serve humanity,” said Herbie
Hancock in an interview during the
ceremony.
Now aged 71, the jazz musician
was born in Chicago, Illinois, and
started with a classical music
education from the age of seven. He
is now in the fifth decade of his
professional career, with an Academy
Award for his film score to Round
Midnight and 14 Grammy Awards. In
addition to being recognized as a
legendary pianist and composer,
Herbie Hancock has been an integral
part of every popular music
movement since the 1960’s. ■
©
 M
á
la
g
a
 C
lu
b
 d
e
 F
ú
tb
o
l
The first football match in which the
Málaga Club wore UNESCO jerseys
was against the Qatari Al-Rayyan
Sports Club, on 20 July 2011, in the
Marbella Football Centre.
This game was held after the
Director-General of UNESCO, Irina
Bokova, and the President of the
Málaga Football Club (Málaga CF),
Sheikh Abdullah Al-Thani, had
signed a four-year agreement at the
Picasso Museum in Malaga, Spain,
on 1 June 2011, to promote peace
through sport, the internet and
social media.
A joint commission with
representatives of UNESCO and
Málaga CF will develop initiatives to
reach these objectives. La Academia,
the training centre for Malaga CF’s
youth team, serves as a practical
laboratory for the agreement, to
inspire young people with a new
understanding of peace. The
internet and social media will also be
used to promote UNESCO’s values
concerning intercultural dialogue
and the importance of education. At
present, 15 teams of young
footballers aged 6 to 19 (i.e. 500
players in total) are trained there. ■
See the Málaga Club website:
www.malagacf.com/?home
5 4 . T H E  U N E S C O  C O U R I E R  . O C T O B E R  D E C E M B E R  2 0 1 1
©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
/A
n
ia
 F
re
in
d
o
rf
UNESCO and Japan  
come to the aid of Pakistan
The tragic severe floods in Pakistan
has triggered UNESCO to launch, in
July 2011, a major project in
cooperation with the Government of
Japan with the aim of upgrading the
flood forecasting and early warning
systems of Pakistan, and to conduct
risk mapping of flood plains along
the Indus River. The project will be
implemented by UNESCO (Science
Sector ) in close collaboration with
the Japan International Cooperation
Agency (JICA) and in coordination
with the Government of Pakistan. 
The project will benefit from the
technical expertise of the International
Centre for Water Hazard and Risk
Management under the auspices of
UNESCO (ICHARM), which developed
a concise flood-runoff analysis system
as a toolkit for more effective and
efficient flood forecasting in
developing countries. 
Pakistan suffered its most severe
floods in living history in 2010. The
floods began in late July 2010, in the
Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Sindh, Punjab
and Baluchistan regions of Pakistan. ■
M
IL
E
S
T
O
N
E
S
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
Migration and Climate Change 
Edited by Étienne Piguet, Antoine
Pécoud and Paul de Guchteneire
Migration and Climate Change provides the
first authoritative overview of the
relationship between climate change and
migration, bringing together both case
studies and syntheses from different parts of
the world. It discusses policy responses, normative issues and critical
perspectives from the point of view of human rights, international law,
political science, and ethics, and addresses the concepts, notions and
methods most suited to confronting this complex issue. ■   2011
History of Humanity
Volume VII: The Twentieth Century
Edited by Sarvepalli Gopal and
Sergei L. Tikhvinsky
The product of almost fifteen years of
intense effort, the seven-volume History
of Humanity is a radically new work that
sheds light on hitherto unknown
historical events, in the light of new facts
and methods of historiographical investigation.
This major undertaking required an International Commission and the
co-operation of some 450 distinguished specialists from all over the
world. The seventh volume is devoted to the history of the 20th
century. ■   2008
Investing in Cultural Diversity and
Intercultural Dialogue
This report analyzes all aspects of cultural
diversity, which has emerged as a key
concern of the international community in
recent decades, and maps out new
approaches to monitoring and shaping the
changes that are taking place. It highlights,
in particular, the interrelated challenges of
cultural diversity and intercultural dialogue and the way in which strong
homogenizing forces are matched by persistent diversifying trends. The
report proposes a series of ten policy-oriented recommendations, for the
attention of States, intergovernmental and non-governmental
organizations, international and regional bodies, national institutions
and the private sector on how to invest in cultural diversity. ■   2009
www.unesco.org/publishing
Human Rights: Questions and
Answers 
By Leah Levin with cartoons by Plantu
Human Rights: Questions and Answers provides
clear, concise and up-to-date information on
human rights standards, mechanisms for their
promotion and protection, organizations
working for human rights, and major
international events. It also includes reflections on the main
challenges to human rights. First published in 1981, it has been updated
several times and translated into over 30 languages. This revised edition
reflects substantial recent developments in the field of human rights. The
publication is one of UNESCO’s contributions to the International Year of
Human Rights Learning (2009) and the World Programme for Human
Rights Education, launched in 2005. It is a useful guide for anyone
interested in the subject and aims to contribute to a universal culture of
human rights. ■   2009
The UNESCO Universal Declaration
on Bioethics and Human Rights 
Background, principles and
application
Edited by Henk A. M. J. ten Have
and Michèle S. Jean.
In October 2005, UNESCO Member States
adopted by acclamation the Universal Declaration on Bioethics and
Human Rights. For the first time in the history of bioethics, some 190
countries committed themselves and the international community to
respect and apply fundamental ethical principles related to medicine,
the life sciences and associated technologies. ■   2009
Freedom from Poverty as a Human Right 
Who Owes What to the Very Poor?
Edited by Thomas Pogge
Collected here are fifteen cutting-edge essays by
leading academics about the severe poverty that
today afflicts billions of human lives. The essays
seek to explain why freedom from poverty is a
human right and what duties this right creates
for the affluent. Addressing even the most
complex aspects of human rights in clear language, these
discussions are accessible to specialists and lay readers alike. ■   2007
Migration and Human Rights 
The United Nations Convention on Migrant
Workers' Rights
Edited by Paul de Guchteneire, Antoine
Pécoud and Ryszard Cholewinski
The International Convention on Migrant
Workers' Rights is one of the UN's main human
rights treaties. It sets a standard in terms of
access to human rights for migrant workers
and their families. Yet hardly more than 40
states have ratified it and no major developed country has
done so. Although migrant labour is essential in the world economy,
the human aspect of migration - and especially migrants' rights -
remains a neglected dimension of globalization. ■   2009
Introducing Democracy: 
80 Questions and Answers 
By David Beetham and Kevin
Boyle with cartoons by Plantu
What is democracy? What is the
relation between democracy and
individual rights? Is majority rule
always democratic? How can
democracy be maintained and
improved?
This revised edition also takes into account new challenges facing
our societies, from international terrorism to the HIV and AIDS
pandemic. ■   2009
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
The Universal Declaration on Cultural Diversity
celebrates its 10th anniversary
Detail from the
poster for the
UNESCO
Universal
Declaration on
Cultural Diversity. ©
 U
N
E
S
C
O
The UNESCO Universal Declaration on Cultural
Diversity, adopted on 2 November 2001, raises cultural
diversity to the level of "the common heritage of
humanity [...] as necessary for humankind as
biodiversity is for nature" and makes its defence an
ethical imperative indissociable  from respect for the
dignity of the individual.
]]>
</page>
</document>
