<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="014255eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^^ *^V A window open on the
ne
world
r
August-September 1967 (20th year) U.K. : 3/-stg. - Canada: 60 cents - France: 2 F
WAR OR PEACE
Which will it be: the way of the dinosaur
or a united world to build the future?
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES Enormous upraised hands, symbols of supplication, figure on many of the tens of
thousands of tombstones carved by the Bogomils in Bosnia and Herzgovina (Yugo¬
slavia). The Bogomil graveyards vast stone communities of the dead are the mem¬
orials of a medieval religious cult which found refuge in the Balkans. The authors of
this extraordinary and still largely unknown art decorated tombs, sarcophagi and
coffins with subjects ranging from geometrical designs to scenes from daily
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier Page Special double issue
AUGUST-SEPTEMBER 1967
20TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg.; $3.00
(Canada); 10 French francs or equivalent;
¿years: ¿7/-stg.;18 F. Single copies 1/6-stg.;
30 cents; 1 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office. P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly In The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
10
22
28
36
40
WAR OR PEACE ?
INQUIRY INTO A DISARMED WORLD
First results of an international poll
SCIENCE AND DISARMAMENT
By Philip Noel-Baker
THE CHALLENGE OF PEACE
By Vadim Ardatovsky
DEVELOPMENT, NEW NAME FOR PEACE
Encyclical Letter of His Holiness Pope Paul VI
TO BUILD A NEW ORDER IN THE WORLD
By René Maheu, Director-General of Unesco
KUBOYAMA
The saga of the " Lucky Dragon "
By Richard Hudson
MAN DOES NOT LIVE BY POLITICS ALONE
By Jawaharlal Nehru
AUROVILLE
India's international city of concord
TISTOU OF THE GREEN FINGERS
A story on war for children and grown-ups
By Maurice Druon
UNESCO AND THE SEARCH FOR PEACE
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
The hand of the Bogomils (Yugoslavia)
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-78, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managin
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
g Editors
Edition: Ronald Fenton (Paris)
Edition: Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Edition: Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Research: Olga Rodel
Layout & Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence shouldbe addressed to the Editor-in-Chief
U
2
This extraordinary photograph was
taken by the French film producer,
Georges Bourdelon during an expe¬
dition to the Sunda Isles (Indone¬
sia) in 1 957 to locate the creature,
and is shown in Georges Bourdelon's
film, "The Lizard of Komodo".
Photo © Georges Bourdelon, Paris
Cover photo
This is a rare photograph of that elu¬
sive monster the "Dragon of Komodo",
a giant lizard, 10 to 20 feet long, still
found in parts of Indonesia. One of
the world's last surviving prehistoric
animals, its massive body and giant tail
and claws are reminiscent of the dino¬
saurs that once roamed the Earth. This
living fossil could well symbolize war
that other anachronistic fossil of today.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
WAR
OR
PEACE?
Arab refugees
in the Middle East.
T.HIS issue of the "Unesco Courier" goes to press
at a time when peace in our world is poised over a precipice.
Wars and conflicts, though "limited" in nature, have spread
a broad swathe of death and destruction across many lands.
And no sooner has one area of conflict ceased firing than
the flames seem to attack another. At the same time the
spectre of the nuclear and "conventional" arms race
continues with mounting ominousness.
Just under three years ago, the "Unesco Courier"
reported, in an issue devoted to the problems of
disarmament (Nov. 1964) that the world's expenditure
on arms had reached the astronomical figure of
$ 120,000,000,000 a year. Today we are spending incredibly
higher sums, and the arms race mania is engulfing many
more countries.
Despite this or rather because of all this the voices
that are being raised to put an end to the headlong race
towards Armageddon are growing louder and louder.
Resort to violence, as a means of settling differences, is
being denounced more vehemently than ever before. And
for millions upon millions of people everywhere in the
world, war today is seen for what it really is man's
greatest folly, a monstrous anachronism in an age where
the survival of humanity itself is at stake.
Last November, the Plenary Session of the General
Conference of Unesco adopted a resolution which called
on all its Member States to reject war once and for all as an
instrument of national policy and to condemn all forms of
direct and indirect aggression and interference in the
domestic affairs of States; to renounce recourse to vio-
Photo © Sanda Holme8-Lebel
lence in settling their differences; respect the right of
all nations to self-determination and independence; and to
take all action to contribute to an agreement on general
and complete disarmament under international control.
The resolution also called on Unesco, as a world
organization, "to disseminate the truth that war is no longer
a possible solution to man's problems," and adopted as
Unesco's mandate the U.N. Secretary-General's request
that "Unesco bring home, at all times, to all peoples and
governments in all parts of the world, what war means
today." It recalled U Thant's message to Unesco in which
he declared that "in the past 20 years, the very progress
of science and technology has brought new, terrible and
ever-present dangers to mankind as a whole, the dangers
inherent in the new weapons of mass destruction."
It is to this purpose that the present issue of the "Unesco
Courier" is devoted: on the one hand, to review the
situation created by the present arms race with its
escalation of nuclear weapons; on the other, to underline
the urgency of reaching agreement on practical methods
for the de-escalation of arms and weapons, that is,
disarmament, and the no less urgent task of assuring the
peaceful growth and progress of all countries, developed
and developing alike.
Which is it going to be? The way of the dinosaur and
the end of our species; or a united world building a
common future? It is up to the peoples and governments
of all nations to face the reality that all men have a
common destiny today, and that that destiny must be to
build a world community in peace by a combined effort
Vietnam.
Photo © Holmes-Lebel
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
First results of
an international poll
undertaken with
the aid of Unesco
INQUIRY INTO
A DISARMED
WORLD
Il OW do people today visualize the stage will cover at least 13 countries (Czech-
future of the world? A vast international oslovakia, Denmark, Finland, Federal Rep-
inquiry based on public opinion polls has been ublic of Germany, Italy, Netherlands, Norway,
in progress for the past three years in an Poland, U.K., U.S.S.R., Sweden and Yugosla-
effort to obtain an answer. The poll is. being via), under the over-all direction of Professor
carried out by the European Co-ordination Johan Galtung of the International Institute of
Centre for Social Research and Documenta- Peace Research in Oslo, Norway. The inquiry
tion, in Vienna Austria, an independent unit will make it a special point to poll the opinions
of the International Social Science Council, of young people, particularly with regard to
with the financial aid of Unesco. their views about a world in the process of
The inquiry is divided into two stages. The partial or total disarmament. The full inquiry,
first, on the theme Image of a Disarmed World alon9 with an analysis of the findings, is not
was carried out in three countries, France, expected to be completed before several
Norway and Poland, under the direction of years.
Professor Jean Stpetzel, of the University of Qn the fo||owing pageSi the «Unesco
Pans, and is now completed. The second Courier" is pleased to present some of the
stage is at present getting under way and first results of the ¡nquiry on the , e of a
will comprise an even more far-reaching pro- Disarmed World Some 5,000 persons, corn-
gramme of inquiry on the theme The World prising a representative sampling of the popu-
in Year 2,000. lations of France, Norway and Poland, were
The public opinions polls for the second interviewed at their homes during the winter
CONTINUED ON PAGE 7
In the answers to the questionnaire, figures
indicate the percentage of the total persons
polled except where otherwise stated.
How would you like
to see the world
organized after
total disarmament?
As at present	
With a world government	
and no national frontiers
Maintain national sovereignty as now,
but strengthen the role of international
organizations such as the U.N	
Form regional groups of countries with
common interests	
No answer
France Norway Poland
17 17 14
19 7 29
25 48(a) 29
25 23(b) 12
14 5 16
Norwegian version:
(a) "About as now, but with a stronger United Nations. "
(b) "With regional unions of nations that belong together"
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Imagine for a moment that total
disarmament has taken place
in the whole world.
Do you think that would mean
any changes in the lives
of people like yourself?
Yes
No .
No answer
France Norway Poland
53 61 74
38 25 24
9 14 2
In all countries of the world people discuss how the
Government should spend public money.
What do you think of your Government's effort
in the following fields; do you think
it should do more; that it is doing enough;
or that it should do less?
6
Military defence
More	
Enough 	
Less
Don't know ,. . .
Industry, develop¬
ment
More	
Enough
Less	
Don't know	
Assistance to dev¬
eloping countries
in Africa, Asia and
Latin-America
More	
Enough
Less	
Don't know	
Education
More	
Enough
Less	
Don't know	
France
9
37
40
14
46
36
2
16
Norway
6
26
64
4
55
30
10
5
15 18
29 42
44 36
12 4
64 56
28 38
1 4
7 2
Poland
Social we/fare and
health
12
23
32
More	
33
Housing
24
More	
43
13
20
Agriculture,
development
More	
5
15
29
51
Communication,
roads
43 More	
42
5
10
France Norway Poland
61 55 62
24 3d 20
1 4 4
7 2 14
77 80 73
20 16 18
1 2
3 3 7
45 30 64
19 45 19
1 20 4
35 5 13
80 84 61
16 13 22
1 1
4 2 16
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
INQUIRY INTO A DISARMED WORLD (Continued)
of 1964-1965. The French poll was carried
out by the French Institute of Public Opinion
under the supervision of Madame Hélène
Riffault; the Norwegian survey, by the Inter¬
national Institute of Peace Research in Oslo,
under Johan Galtung; and the Polish inquiry
by the Polish Institute of Public Opinion,
under Professor A. Sicinski.
Persons polled were all 18 years or older,
of both sexes, and were asked to reply to a
series of some 30 questions on aspects of
disarmament and world affairs. The initial
inquiry sought to determine, first, how well
informed people are on international affairs
generally, and to what extent they are inte¬
rested in such problems. Another series of
questions sought their views on the prospects
of disarmament, and how they thought resour¬
ces thus released could best be used.
A detailed analysis of the replies should
help to throw light on the attitudes and values
that influence public opinion on such ques¬
tions as disarmament, and may be extremely
helpful in revealing factors most likely to
contribute to the attainment of world peace.
Already, however, one point is quite clear.
The polls carried out thus far in countries
with widely differing social and economic
systems, foreign policies and cultural and his¬
torical backgrounds, might have been expect¬
ed to reveal widely differing points of view.
The contrary has been found to be true with
a striking identity of views on most of- the
questions asked. Although this first stage of
the inquiry was limited to three countries, its
results suggest that it may well be a preview
of general opinion regarding attitudes towards
the world of tomorrow in which armaments
are drastically reduced or completely
discarded.
In your opinion what is
the greatest danger
man is facing today ?
(Open question)
Nuclear weapons, nu¬
clear warfare 	
World war, war ('nu¬
clear' not mentioned)..
Hunger, poverty, over¬
population	
German militarism ....
China (a)	
Disease, cancer 	
Conflicts between na¬
tions, between races. . .
Communism	
Wages too low, high
cost of living, unem¬
ployment	
Armaments, armament
race (b)
Other answers 	
No answer
Total (c)
France Norway Poland
63 59 51
27 13 43
18 5 10
12
17 4
14 5
8 2 8
6 3
4
1 6
9 8 9
3 5 7
169 100 151
(a) Norwegian version: China and its atom bomb.
(b) Not included in French questionnaire.
(c) The answers in the Norwegian survey add up to 100 %,
the French and the Polish results show multiple answers.
Taking for granted
that money should
be given
to the underdeveloped
countries of Africa,
Asia and Latin
America, should that money
go directly from the rich
countries to the poor,
or should it be deposited
with an international organization
which would then decide how
it should be used, or should aid
be given in both ways ?
To an international
organization	
Directly	
Both
Don't know 	
France Norway Poland
46 48 40
23 33 17
14 13 9
17 6 34
What do you think
would be the result
of a third world war
for your country?
Total destruction . .
Irreparable losses .
Heavy losses, but
not irreparable (a).
Don't know 	
(Fixed alternatives)
France Norway Poland
30 39 51
29 20 30
29 35 6
10 6 12
(a) Polish version: "Heavy losses but with perspectives for
reconstruction. " Norwegian version (two items are put
together): "Heavy losses but not irreparable", "Not so heavy
losses ".
7
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
INQUIRY INTO A DISARMED WORLD (Continued)
8
In terms of war,
peace and
disarmament,
what do you think
the world situation
will be like in 5 years
and in 20 years, will there be :
The same situa
tion as now
In 5 years 	
In 20 years 	
More armament
In 5 years 	
In 20 years 	
Partial disarma¬
ment
In 5 years 	
In 20 years 	
World war
In 5 years 	
In 20 years 	
Total disarma¬
ment
In 5 years 	
In 20 years 	
Don't know
In 5 years 	
In 20 years 	
France Norway Poland
31 49 29
9 16 4
25 16 23
11 10 4
22 20 15
18 23 13
4 3 6
9 10 17
4 1 3
18 11 15
14 11 24
35 30 47
Would you approve
of the integration
of a part of the armed
forces of your country
into a permanent
international force
under United Nations command?
Yes 	v.
Perhaps	
No 	
Don't know
France Norway Poland
33 45 24
34 29 24
15
33 11 52
Which of
the following
is the most important
factor in assuring
world peace?
(order of choice)
The good sense of
leading statesmen.
That the big powers
do not want war. .
Public opinion
against war 	
The balance of
power between the
blocs	
Treaties, conferen¬
ces and meetings
between nations . .
The United Nations
The power of the
Western bloc	
The power of the
Eastern bloc	
France Norway Poland
1 1 1
2 3 3
3 5 2
4 6 4
5 4 7
6 2 5
7 7 7
7 10 6
Figures for France and Poland give the order of choice of
the most important factor. Those for Norway indicate "very
important" factors. Norway's questionnaire offered a choice
of four classifications: "very important", "somewhat impor¬
tant", "of no importance", "negative importance".
Do you think that
in the years ahead
your standard of living
will increase,
decrease or stay
the same?
Increase 	
Stay the same
Decrease	
No answer . . .
France Norway Poland
39 36 38
35 46 36
14 11 13
12 7 13
Do you speak any
foreign languages?
Yes	
No
No answer
France Norway Poland
26
74
0
37
63
0
Question not included in the Norwegian questionnaire.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
®For each example
in this list
of possible
news items, say
whether it interests
you a great deal,
a little or not at all
Á new disarma¬
ment proposal in
Geneva
A great deal . . .
A little 	
Not at all 	
?	
The independen¬
ce of a new
nation in Africa
A great deal . . .
A little 	
Not at all 	
?	
A new develop¬
ment in another
country
A great deal . . .
A little 	
Not at all 	
?	
A political event
in your own
country
A great deal . . .
A little 	
Not at all 	
?	
The result of a
national football
match
A great deal . . .
A little 	
Not at all 	
?	
An increase in
the cost of liv¬
ing
A great deal . . .
A little 	
Not at all 	
?	
Franco ' Norway " Poland
41 50 43
27 35
26 22
6
16 9 24
30 40
46 35
8 1
11 11 13
32 37
52 49
5 1
20 15 28
28 46
38 25
14 1
22 3 15
24 19
49 65
5 1
79 11 64
12 20
8 14
1 2
(1) The Norwegian question asked: "Which two items would
you like to know more about?" Norwegian figures are based
on the foremost choice in terms of interest aroused.
(2) ? = "No answer" or "Don't know."
Have you travelled
abroad during the last
ten years?
Yes.. 	
No .......
No answer
France Norway Poland
40 73 12 -
60 27 87
0 0 1
The Norwegian questionnaire asked: "Have you ever
travelled abroad."
In which
of these cities
is the headquarters
of the United Nations
located ?
Geneva ....
New York . .
Washington
Vienna	
Other	
No answer .
France Norway Poland
34 8 15
36 73 64
10 10 6
0 0 0
1 0 0
19 9 15
®lnthe summer of 1963,
a treaty was signed
in Moscow between
the Soviet Union,
Britain and
the United States.
What was the treaty about?
A ban on certain
nuclear tests 	
A joint programme
for space research .
A settlement of the
Cuban problem. . .
No answer 	
France Norway Poland
52 59 54
6 14 9
6 11 3
36 16 34
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE
AND DISARMAMENT
by Philip Noel-Baker
Nobel Peace Prize, 1959
10
PHILIP NOEL-BAKER, one of the world's
leading authorities on questions of disar¬
mament, was awarded the Nobel Peace
Prize in 1959. He has devoted many years
to research on problems of peace and
disarmament and has written numerous
works on these subjects, including "Disar¬
mament" (1926); "The Private Manufacture
of Armaments" (1936); "The Arms race:
A Programme for World Disarmament"
(1958) and many other studies. In 1932 he
attended the League of Nations Conference
in Geneva, the first of the major world
conferences on disarmament, in which 64
countries took part. Philip Noel-Baker has
been a member of two British Govern¬
ments (1942-1945 and 1945-1951) and is
a member of the present British Parlia¬
ment. In November 1966 on the occasion
of Unesco's 20th anniversary celebrations,
he took part in the round table meeting
which appraised Unesco's contribution to
peace (see page 64). Philip Noel-Baker
has always been closely associated with
sport. He was a member of the British
Olympic track team in 1912, 1920 and
1924 ; team captain in 1920 and 1924 and
silver medalist in 1920. He is now presi¬
dent of the International ^Council of Sport
and Physical Education.
"The time is not far distant when man will
get hold of Atomic Energy a source of
power which will enable him to build his
life as he likes . . . Will man be able to make
use of this power and direct It for good,
and not for self-destruction? Is he old
enough to know how to utilize the power
which Science must inevitably give him?"
Academician V. I. Vernadsky of the
U.S.S.R., February 1922
"Science has been glamorized for so long
that many people firmly believe it can do no
wrong."
Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh, 1963
ITH the beginning of the
modern arms race about a hundred
years ago, science and engineering
became the major factors In prepara¬
tion for war. Until then, manpower
numbers, training and discipline had
been of decisive Importance in deter¬
mining a nation's military strength.
During and after the Franco-Prussian
war, the importance of armament
weapons, equipment, armour, trans¬
port, signals rapidly Increased.
Expenditure on ordnance and warships
grew greater every year.
Before the First World War began,
the General Staffs had grasped the
fact that superior armament might be
decisive. During the First World War,
new weapons were introduced, to the
production of which scientists had
made their contribution aircraft, poi¬
son gas, flame-throwers, tanks, and
many more. Before the Second World
War far-seeing members of the Brit¬
ish and German General Staffs had
Invited eminent scientists to join their
Defence Departments as permanent
advisers.
But It was only after the Second
World War had actually begun that the
military leaders of the belligerents
fully grasped the proposition which
Professor Isldor Rabi long afterwards
expressed as follows: "The combin¬
ing of military techniques and science
makes it easy to apply scientific prin¬
ciples to kill people who are not
strong structures." (1).
From 1939 onwards, scientists came
in mounting numbers into every war
department; military research was
rapidly expanded; scientific methods
were applied by leading scientists to
the actual conduct of operations by
land, sea and air. After the war was
over, this process did not stop. On
the contrary, It has continued with
accelerating momentum until today.
This has revolutionized the arma¬
ments that governments maintain, and
the training of their national forces. In
consequence, it has changed the prob¬
lems of disarmament and has made
it essential that the scientists should
play a leading part in disarmament
negotiations.
.In the League of Nations Conference
of 1932, the major problems to be
solved were the techniques by which
manpower could be equitably reduced
and limited; the abolition of military
aircraft; naval disarmament, by the
abolition of "capital" ships and sub-
and the limitation of other
budgetary reduction and
marines,
vessels;
control.
The negotiations in the League Pre-
(1) New York Times, January 1, 1958. Pro¬
fessor Rabi was chairman of President
Eisenhower's Scientific Advisory Committee
and has been consultant of the Military
Research and Development Board since 1946;
he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics
In 1944.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 12
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Mutilated, deserted, its great cities In ruins will this be the face
of our planet after a Third World War? This bronze sculpture,
"Globe", is the work of the young Italian artist, Arnaldo Pomodoro.
In many of his sculptures the artist portrays the crucial problem
of man today: universal harmony or complete annihilation.
Photo © Paolo Monti
3SP^^P%*~ £V¡£í¿->B an ' Vi i« t- ' v.
A^mÊ^fi f 1 IS ¿ '
M M-
m
fl ^r^ L^^' ^^MB <j^^pbp^pS HÍ
fl ^r« * ^^V? K 1*P^F^ **^Ë ; A
V í Tti ,
ft iVnj*' d PP^ - P' ImP iHst.iRfll]
B ; y W^ ^-"¿ \ m 1 P1 40> ' ' SaC Hfl
f *?**1 l^ fe n*l Lrl MP lili
\ * PJ -_> «P'.P P^_ I mit Jll
1 ""
BFTF"^ "npt ú ¿- -ü * rfr
1.1 PI &MKI fS
1 .m -m m ¿l^fUíd Kfl
Br It' ii UM ~ \ le *T^C*T ^r-vb
/
K^^aEMkHH^^BB
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND DISARMAMENT (Continued)
12
paratory Commission and in the con¬
ference Itself were more thorough,
more serious, and technically much
more successful than any that have
taken place since 1945. They were
conducted by leading statesmen who
had military and civil service advisers
to help them. Every technical problem
of a general disarmament treaty was
satisfactorily solved; only the political,
decision to sign the treaty was requir¬
ed. Much of the work done . (for
example, on the four problems men¬
tioned above) still remains valid today.
Yet it Is doubtful if a single scientist
was present in the League commission
and conference from first to last.
Things are different now. Scien¬
tists have made the modern weapons;
they must play a major part in solving
the . new technical problems which
these weapons involve, and In draft¬
ing the detailed clauses of the disar- .
marnent treaty; they must helpto form
the public opinion by which a treaty
can be carried through.
The iollowlng table of expenditure
by two important countries shows how
"the combining of military techniques
and science" has expanded since
1939 (1).
Expenditure on military
research and development,
all defence departments
.... . United
Period JAL States
	K'n9dom of ^
(£ million) ($ million)
1938-1939 	 5.7 Nil
1939-1940 	 7.9 26.4
1947-1948 	 40.0 529.2
1951-1952 	 80.0 821.0
1953-1954 	 100.0 1569.2
1956-1957 	 204.0 1407.9
1960-1961 	 228.0 8 400.0
1964-1965 	 250.0 13 400.0
(1) In considering the meaning of these
figures, allowance must be made for the
factor of Inflation. At 1953 prices, the United
Kingdom figure would be £210 million, I.e.,
in real terms it had more than doubled in
ten years. (£ = 2.8 dollars at the current
exchange rate.)
There are no figures publicly avail¬
able which show United States and
United Kingdom expenditure during
the war years. But Dr. Vannevar
Bush has described the creation of
the Military Research Organisation of
which he was the head In the United
States; he had 35,000 scientists under
his direction. In addition there was
the very large international team, under
Dr. Robert Oppenhelmer, working on
the Manhattan District Project for the
production of the first atomic bomb.
These are large figures; but the num¬
bers, both in the United States and
the United Kingdom, have greatly
Increased since then. In his Econom¬
ic Message to Congress In January
1963, President Kennedy said: "The
defence, space and atomic energy
activities of the country absorb about
two-thirds of the trained people avail¬
able for exploring our scientific and
technical frontiers."
A small part of "atomic energy acti¬
vities of the country" is devoted to
civil ends; thus It is perhaps true to
say that 60 per cent of the United Sta¬
tes scientific and technical experts are
engaged in military work. The propor¬
tion in the United Kingdom is less;
20 per cent of the experts, and 40 per
cent of the national expenditure on
research. But President Kennedy's
words were true of £>oth countries
when he said: "We have paid a price
by sharply limiting the scarce scien¬
tific and engineering' resources avail¬
able to the civilian sectors of the eco¬
nomy."
The scale of the enterprises made
possible by a budget of $ 13,400 mil¬
lion is immense. In the platform
adopted by the Democratic Party for
the presidential election in August
1964, President -Johnson pledged him¬
self to "maintain the world's largest
military/ research and ; development
effort, which has initiated more thetn
200 new programmes since 1961, tb
ensure American leadership In wea¬
pons systems and equipment".
New weapons
developed
since 1945
There is no information about the
Soviet Government's expenditure on
military research: but its startling
achievements in multi-megaton nuclear
weapons, ICBMs (intercontinental bal¬
listic missiles), sputniks and space
flight show that It must be very high.
It is known that the Soviet General
Staff have devoted much attention to
tactical nuclear weapons and to other
types of new weapons.
There is no doubt that other govern¬
ments are doing the same. It was
recently revealed that French expendi¬
ture on military research had been
greatly Increased. It Is unlikely that
German and Italian expenditure is much
less. Mainland China, India, Israel,
Pakistan, the U.A.R. and many other
countries certainly have military re¬
search establishments, though prob¬
ably as yet on a much smaller scale.
If Increased power of offensive
attack Is the purpose of military
research, then the governments have
certainly got their money's worth. All
the weapons of offence used against
Hitler aircraft, tanks, artillery, sub¬
marines have been enormously "im¬
proved". New weapons of every des¬
cription have been added. Three cate¬
gories of weapons of mass destruction
nuclear, chemical and biological
have been developed.
Although it seemed In 1955 that the
"ultimate" weapons had been devised,
everything produced in that year is long
since out of date; there is now a total
revolution In military equipment every
five years. Professor Rabi has warn¬
ed us that the "progress" made in
the next twenty years will be no less
rapid or dramatic than that of the last
twenty.
Conventional weapons
It is already difficult to remember
that in May 1945, when Hitler's Ger¬
many surrendered, there were no nu¬
clear weapons; no ballistic missiles
except Hitler's rudimentary V2; no air¬
craft that could travel faster than
400 m.p.h.; no bomber with a range of
more than 1,000 miles. There were no
nuclear-powered submarines or sur¬
face vessels; the conventional torpedo
was still the deadliest naval weapon.
^Potent new poison gases had been
prepared by German chemists, ' but
Hitler's subordinates, already con¬
scious of defeat, had successfully pre¬
vented them from being used. Both
sides had arsenals of "biologicals",
but dared not risk the general oppro¬
brium and the strategic hazards which
their employment would have meant.
Broadly, up to the day when Hitler fell,
the war had been fought with improved
versions of the conventional weapons
produced by the First World War.
Twenty years later, those conven¬
tional weapons have been further and
enormously Improved.
Two of the latest types of United
States military aircraft are the B-58
and the B-70. The B-58 can carry a
50-megaton load of bombs, I.e., the
equivalent of 50 million tons of TNT.
It has travelled from New England to
Paris In just over three hours. The
B-70 is designed to travel at three
times the speed of sound; if it is cons¬
tructed in numbers for the United Sta¬
tes Air Force, It will cost $ 100 million
per aircraft. The British TSR-2, If it
were built, would "hedge-hop" at twice
the speed of sound; it could be guid¬
ed by instruments to its target and
back; the pilot, need only Interfere If
something went wrong. All these air¬
craft, refueled in the air, would have
a range of many thousands of miles.
The modern submarine is propelled
by nuclear power. It can cruise for
thousands of miles, and for periods
of weeks, without coming to the sur¬
face. It can navigate under the Arctic
ice-cap, and can break the ice and fire
its missiles. Or It can fire its missiles
from many feet below the surface of
the open sea.
The United States Government is
now installing what President Johnson
called "the new over-the-horlzon
radars giving us almost instantaneous
knowledge of ballistic missiles launch¬
ed for attack". Aerial reconnais¬
sance photography has been so much
improved that a handful of aircraft
could photograph the whole of Russia
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
in a few hours; from a height of
60,000 feet, they could reveal the smal¬
lest objects (a golf ball) on the ground.
Similar Improvements have been
made In tanks, artillery, naval surface
vessels, especially aircraft carriers and
amphibious landing vessels, and even
in rifles, machine guns, and all the
other conventional weapons of the
Second World War.
But most attention, and most expen¬
diture, has been concentrated on the
weapons of mass destruction.
Nuclear weapons
The basic facts about nuclear wea¬
pons are well known: the Hiroshima
bomb was more than 1,000 times as
powerful as the conventional "block¬
busters" used by the RAF against Ber¬
lin; the 20-megaton (1) weapons now
carried by United States bombers
and no doubt by Soviet bombers too
are more than one thousand times
as powerful as the Hiroshima bomb.
Thus the "yield" of the unit of air
attack deliverable by a single bomber
has been multiplied a million times.
One 20-megaton weapon Is equivalent
to nearly fourteen times the explosive
power of all the bombs dropped by
all the Allies on Germany in six years
of war. We forget that almost all the
cities of Germany lay in ruins in 1945.
One 20-megaton bomb
more devastating
than 1,000
Hiroshima bombs
The 20-megaton bombs exist in large
numbers. They can be delivered by
United States B-52 bombers, by the
obsolescent B-47, the B-58, by the
Soviet Bear and Bison, and the British
V bombers, and by some types of
Soviet intercontinental ballistic mis¬
siles.
But many authorities believe that a
20-megaton bomb Is larger than any
military or civilian target would require.
The British Home Office Manuals of
Civil Defence calculate the results of
a 10-megaton bomb on London; if it
were "dropped centrally", there would
be "irreparable damage over most of
the London County Council area" (i.e.
a. circle of total destruction roughly
eight miles across) "with minor
damage over the whole of the metro¬
politan area" (a circle perhaps
thirty-two miles across). In most
other British cities, however, a good
deal of potential damage would
consist of open country."
In other words, there is only one
target in the United Kingdom large
enough to need a 10-megaton bomb
for its total destruction. In fact a
1 -megaton bomb would probably
put all but the largest cities out of
action. The new United States
submarine missile, Poseidon, which
Is replacing the Polaris A3, has a
yield of 1.5 megatons (i.e. 75 times
Hiroshima.) Its greater yield is due
to the newly discovered, and more
potent, nuclear explosive, pluto-
nium-241. In 1961, the U.S.S.R.
exploded a 57-megaton bomb, and
boasted not without reason that It
could have been 100 megatons.
It has been calculated that the
United States has a stockpile of
nuclear weapons with a total yield
of 50,000 to 60,000 megatons; the
Soviet Union a stockpile of
20,000 megatons or more; the
British and French much less. The
United States stockpile includes "tens
of thousands of 'tactical' weapons".
The United States Secretary of State
for Defence, Mr. McNamara, has warn¬
ed us that new processes may soon
make the production of nuclear wea¬
pons cheaper and easier than it is
now. He has said that, in spite of
"fail safe" and the "permissive link"
(sometimes called the "electronic
key") and other devices to guard
against technical and human failure,
there remains a grave danger of "acci¬
dental" or "unintended" nuclear war.
Biological weapons
In the view of some qualified au¬
thorities, the menace of biological
weapons is now hardly less grave
than that of the nuclear stockpiles.
Brigadier-General J. H. Rothschild
was head of the United States Chem¬
ical Corps until 1957. (The Chem¬
ical Corps is in charge of both chem¬
ical and biological weapons.) In a
recent book, "Tomorrow's weapons",
Brigadier Rothschild says that the
small quantities required make "bio-
logicals" the Quartermaster's dream;
they can be used, says Rothschild, to
attack "hundreds of thousands of
square miles." A cloud of the chosen
agent can be released on to a favour¬
able wind; "a deep cloud several hun¬
dred miles across will be able to travel
long distances and still be effective".
All the diseases which attack man
are potential agents. The most suit¬
able are those with highest "infec-
tivity" and "virulence". Rothschild
adds: "The microbes can be made
more resistant to antibiotics, thereby
rendering treatment of the diseases
more difficult."
Another authority, Major-General
Brock Chisholm of Canada (2), com¬
mented In 1957 on this development of
biological weapons, which was then
beginning: "Research is at present
going forward with a view to making
the bacteria of more general diseases,
e.g., cholera, typhus, etc., much more
virulent, so that the vaccination, etc.,
now carried out might not serve as a
protection to anyone who was infect¬
ed. This line of Investigation is very
dangerous to the future of mankind."
Modern
microbe hunters
of death
(1) "Megaton" = 1 million tons of TNT.
(2) Major-General Chisholm, Commander
Canadian Royal Army Medical Corps, Second
World War, in personal charge of experiments
with biological weapons. After the war,
he was first Director-General of the World
Health Organization.
(3) WarjPeace Report. New York, July 1964.
There can no longer be any doubt
that blologicals are potential weapons
of mass destruction. The American
Chemical Society estimates that a
single large bomber, distributing only
450 pounds of the selected agent, could
spread~the disease over 34,000 square
miles; between 25 and 75 per cent of
the population would become casual¬
ties, although not all would die.
Expenditure on biological warfare
research has greatly increased in
recent years.
There is another serious objection
to the present rapid development of
biological weapons. Once research
has solved the technical problems of
producing and stocking these wea¬
pons, and of delivering them against
an enemy, their large-scale production
Is very cheap the amount of an agent
needed to attack a very large area is
very small. Thus an enormous power
of destruction might become available
to many nations at an almost negli¬
gible cost. This danger will certainly
confront the world within a measura¬
ble future, if the arms race goes on.
Chemical weapons
An American reporter, Mr. James
Polk, has vividly described a nerve gas
plant at Newport, Indiana.
"The killer chemical which emerges
from the plant's ovens and chilling
chamber is nerve gas. A stealthy
assassin. It Is odourless, tasteless and
virtually invisible. A drop, breathed
or soaked into the skin, can be fatal.
"At the end of this unique assembly
line, laced with 40 miles of pipes, the
nerve gas is poured into rockets, land
mines and artillery shells destination
secret . . . The plant has now been
in operation twenty-four hours a day
for three years" (3).
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND DISARMAMENT (Continued)
14
The nerve gas "paralyses and kills
by attacking the body's Cholinesterase,
a key substance In transmitting nerve
signals for muscles to expand. When
this fluid is crippled, muscles continue
to constrict, and the body strangles its
own vital organs".
A United States Army handbook says
that this gas can cause "death within
four minutes", and that it Is so potent
that, delivered only on a small scale,
Its effect can approach that of nuclear
weapons. "The gas Is very cheap;
the Newport plant costs only $3.5 mil¬
lion per year to run."
Brigadier Rothschild, in the book
referred to above, confirms all
Mr. Polk's assertions. The gases first
discovered by Hitler's chemists, which
they called Tabun and Sarin, Roths¬
child labels "GB". He says that GB
is thirty times as lethal as phosgene
the most deadly of all the gases of the
First World War. It can therefore be
used In expensive rockets. In high
concentrations, readily attainable in
the field, it cannot be detected until
the lethal dosage has been inhaled.
Brigadier Rothschild also describes
a class of less volatile anti-chol-
inesterase agents which he labels
"V-agents". He says: "These are very
effective through the skin, because
practically none evaporates. A tiny
droplet, if not removed immediately,
will be absorbed and cause death.
Such a droplet on the skin might well
go unnoticed, since the process of
absorption Is painless."
V-agents used in aerosols cause
long-term hazards drops which re¬
main on the ground, on trees, on build¬
ings, do not evaporate.
The American Chemical Society on
Civil Defence has calculated that one
big bomber carrying a load of nerve
gas could distribute the gas over "an
immediate effective area" of 100
square miles; the gas would cause
casualties to 30 per cent of the popu¬
lation in the area; not all the casualties
would necessarily be fatal. A group
of five bombers could cover a large
city. The United States, it says, has
no effective present defence 	
The brief assortment of facts recited
above may give a general impression
of what the scientists have achieved
In weapon development in the last
twenty years. It gives no idea of what
a war fought with these weapons would
be like.
No governments, and few scientists,
have even attempted this task. Yet
is it not essential that the peoples
should understand what would happen,
if the armaments for which they pay
were ever used? It is certainly essen¬
tial that the reader of this article should
have some picture in his mind, if he
Is to grasp Its point.
Two brief quotations may, therefore,
be reproduced quotations which des¬
cribe the probable effects of nuclear
bombs. The first ¡s a description,
based on material in the British Home
Office Manuals of Civil Defence, of
what would happen if a 10-megaton
bomb were burst over a central point
in London. It was given to a con¬
ference of the World Federation of
Mental Health in Paris in 1961:
"One 10-megaton bomb, burst
6,000 feet above Trafalgar Square,
would wipe out London: its centre
blasted to dust and rubble; a pillar of
flame a mile high, twenty miles across;
winds of hurricane force; gas mains,
tanks, petrol stations all exploding;
the air sucked from every shelter, re¬
placed by carbon monoxide; every
escape route blocked with crashed
vehicles and fallen buildings; every
person in the open within forty miles
blinded, their retinas burnt to nothing
by the thermo-nuclear flash, 1 ,000 times
brighter than the sun; the drivers of
trains and cars and lorries, the pilots
of aircraft, sightless, helpless, hurtling
to their doom."
The second is an account by two
eminent American scientists, Dr. Harri¬
son Brown and Dr. James Real, of
what a similar bomb would do, If it
were exploded above Los Angeles (in
Community of Fear, 1960). They asked
their compatriots to imagine that "the
bomb hits during the working hours of
a week-day".
"The blast effects would extermi¬
nate virtually all but the most deeply
sheltered living things within a radius
of five miles. Blast casualties would
be severe up to ten miles. But the
phenomenon that would complete the
devastation of life in the entire area
would be fire. The area would be one
great sea of fire which would burn
until there was nothing more to con¬
sume.
No survivors
in a 50-mile wide
sea of fire
"A good proportion of the metropoli¬
tan area's 3.5 million car and trucks
would be lifted and thrown like gro¬
tesque Molotov cocktails, to spew
flaming gasoline, oil, and automotive
shrapnel onto and Into everything in
their paths. In an instant most under¬
ground gasoline and oil tanks would
rupture and explode within the blast
area, and a large proportion of the
remainder within the firestorm radius
would follow, each In its own particu¬
lar manner pumps and pipes sheared,
and finally higher and higher ambient
temperatures, which would soon ex¬
pand, rupture and explode the remain¬
der."
The authors then describe how the
remaining area of Los Angeles, "row
upon row of cheap, flammable, com
mercial structures" would be burnt,
and what would happen to the "bush-
covered hills and scrub forest" on the
city's borders. They say that "anyone
unacquainted with the remarkable
explosive nature of the oil-carrying
grease-wood, sumac and scrub pine is
surprised and frightened by the vola¬
tility of the material, even when it is
wet. The novel aspect of a thermo¬
nuclear conflagration, however, is that
most of these highly flammable mate¬
rials would break into intense flame
simultaneously a phenomenon never
before achieved either by man or by
natural causes".
Dr. Harrison Brown and Dr. James
Real then say that, in their belief, in
Los Angeles "at least a twenty-five
mile radius (i.e., a circle fifty miles
across) . . . would be, within minutes,
engulfed in a suffocating firestorm that
would persist for a long time". No one,
they think, would survive unless Inside
very deep shelters, with built-in oxy¬
gen supply and cooling system. Even
so, the chance of reaching safety
would be "slim", after the firestorm.
"A major problem would be trying
to get through ankle-high to knee-
high ash containing numerous hidden
pitfalls; clambering for dozens of miles
over huge smoking piles of radioactive
rubble, burned out timber, wire and
steel. If the survivor made It to the
edge of the devastated area, he in all
probability would have accumulated by
that time a fatal dose of radiation which
would shortly claim what was left of
his life."
Radioactive fall-out
The two quotations above deal with
the effects of a single bomb delivered
on a single city. But in a general war,
in which the whole, or a large propor¬
tion of the nuclear stocks were used,
radioactive fall-out would be by far
the most potent cause of casualties.
Dr. Ralph E. Lapp, who has the unique
distinction of having been Nuclear
Research Adviser to all three of the
United States Defence Services, has
calculated that if a 20-megaton bomb
were burst in the air, so vast a quan¬
tity of radioactive bomb debris would
fall back to earth that it would give a
lethal dose of radiation to everyone In
the open over an area perhaps as
great as 5,000 square miles (1).
If the United States and Soviet Go¬
vernments decided "to destroy each
other's society" (this is the phrase in
current use to explain "deterrence")
each of them, as said above, could
launch an attack amounting to 20,000
megatons or even more. A lethal
mantle of fallout covering 5 million
square miles would be genocide on a
comprehensive scale; the wind would
take an ample part to other nations
perhaps neutral In the war.
This section on the achievements of
the scientists engaged in military res¬
earch may appropriately be ended by
(1) Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists,
April 1963.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 16
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
v^
This striking work by the famous sculptor Zadkine commemorates the
ordeal of Rotterdam, the big Netherlands' port which burned for
40 days and nights after a devastating bombardment in May 1940.
Many other striking works of art erected in the reborn city testify to
its afflictions during the war which caused the deaths of 20,000 persons.
Photo Unesco - Dominique Roger
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND DISARMAMENT (Continued)
16
a quotation from one of the most emi¬
nent of them. Writing in October
1964, Dr. Jerome Wiesner used the
following words : "Both sides of the
arms race are thus confronted by the
dilemma of steadily increasing military
power, and steadily decreasing mili¬
tary security . . . The clearly predict¬
able course of the arms race is a
steady open spiral downwards Into
oblivion." (1).
There are some scientists and
others who still believe that disarma¬
ment is a mirage. Dr. Edward Teller,
frankly leaving science for politics,
argued this at length in an article In
1957 (2). He foresaw the arms race
going on indefinitely for decades, with
Western experts saving freedom by
keeping ahead in armament technique.
This is a conception of international
relations which armament experts have
always held Dr. Teller was only giving
it a modern look.
To bolster up this view that national
security depends on constantly in¬
creasing armaments, attempts have
been made to show that the arms race
has brought indirect, but great, advan¬
tages in the promotion of scientific
knowledge, in the stimulation of indus¬
trial advance, and, In consequence, in
general social well-being. These
claims may be briefly reviewed, to
see whether, in fact they constitute a
valid off-set against the heavy cost
and the grave dangers which the arms
race involves.
Advancing scientific
knowledge ?
The discovery of atomic energy Is
usually quoted as, in itself, conclusive
proof that military research has paid
a handsome dividend in greater scien¬
tific knowledge.
No one would dispute that the re¬
lease of atomic energy "a source of
power which will enable man to build
his life as he likes" was accelerated,
perhaps by many years, because
Einstein and others perceived in 1939
that it might produce the decisive
weapon of the Second World War.
But it might be argued that It would
have been better for mankind if this
great discovery had been delayed until
the United Nations had built up a solid
system for settling international dis¬
putes and until the governments had
carried out a general agreement to
disarm. No doubt the making of the
first atomic bomb, with the vast resour¬
ces it involved, ushered in a cumulative
advance of modern physics; but it is
not yet certain that it has permanently
advanced the cause of human pro¬
gress; that depends on decisions still
to come.
In any case, It has been suggested
by Mr. Gerard Piel, an author who
commands respect, that, since military
research has now produced the "ulti¬
mate" weapons, its contribution to true
science is at an end.
Mr. Piel makes a distinction
between science and technology.
"Science", he says, is concerned with
the discovery of the unknown . . . The
work of Science is to increase our
understanding of the universe around
us, and of the world that Is within
each of us." Technology is "the
exploitation of the already known". It
must be clearly distinguished from
"the discovery of the unknown", which
is science.
Mr. Piel goes on: "Contemporary
weaponeering is essentially a process
of miniaturization, of packing more
devastation into a smaller and more
portable warhead . . . This is not
Science. It is Technology of a high
order, and it is exploiting whole reg¬
ions of knowledge only recently won
from the unknown . . . But the fact
remains that the immense research
and development activity sponsored
by the Pentagon will contribue nothing
to human understanding, and can yield
little else but an Increase in the
efficiency, flexibility and enormity of
our destructive power."
Military research
a spur to
industrial progress?
Mr. Piel concludes that a fully mili¬
tarized world, while constantly advan¬
cing in technology, would be "a world
without much science" (3).
Some experts would, perhaps, dis¬
pute this view. But few would deny
that, If the manpower and resources
given to military research had been
given to civil research Instead, the
resulting contribution to our "under¬
standing of the world around us and
of the world within us" would have
been much greater than it is (4).
It Is often said that military research
has been the dynamo of progress in
civil Industry, and has thus contributed
greatly to the material prosperity of
mankind. Indeed, this assertion has
been used as a major argument to
justify the vast expenditure on military
research.
Again, no one would dispute that
the sophisticated technological ad¬
vance of the armament Industry has
given results that are of benefit to
civil industry as well.
But the point is often over-stated.
It was claimed not long ago that among
the "better known" discoveries by
which military research has helped
civil industry were the following: "nu¬
clear power; the modern aircraft; high
temperature alloys; and the modern
automobile transmission". A subsi¬
diary list of "less known" contributions
included fire retardant paints, helicop¬
ters, anti-icing equipment, new plas¬
tics, and automatic electronic compu¬
ters.
It is ridiculous to assert that all
these inventions would not have been
made if there had been no military
research. The Wright brothers had
constructed an aeroplane, the first
heavier-than-air machine, Bleriot had
flown the Channel, there had been a
decade of important progress, before
any War Department showed the
slightest interest in aviation.
This progress would have unques¬
tionably gone on if there had been no
world wars and no military research.
Indeed, It can be reasonably argued
that, without war and preparation for
war, more and earlier attention might
have been given to the development
of civil aircraft, and to the creation of
a world system of passenger and
postal transport.
And If credit for progress In avia¬
tion is to be given to military research,
there is something to be set on the
other side of the balance sheet. Hun¬
dreds of thousands of airmen killed In
battle, millions of civilians blasted or
burnt to death by air bombardment,
the destruction of great cities and of
irreplaceable artistic and architectural
treasures these were the price paid
for the more rapid progress in aviation,
together with the vast economic cost
of maintaining the national air forces
In time of peace.
In any case, the benefits which in¬
dustry has derived from military re¬
search constitute only a tiny proportion
of the latter's output and they are an
accidental, not an intentional, result.
Its overwhelmingly preponderant effect
is to increase the complexity, the cost,
and the destructive power of arma¬
ments; to increase the capacity for
surprise attack; and thus to multiply
the dangers of the arms race and the
risk that unprovoked aggression might
succeed.
Indeed, to say that military research
is socially desirable because of the
benefits it brings to civil Industry is
not only an economic absurdity; it Is
the exact contrary of the truth. Pro¬
fessor Seymour Melman and his col¬
leagues have shown that the vast con¬
centration of eminent scientists and
technologists on armament work in the
United States has starved American
industry of the experts it needs, and
has caused it to fall behind the stan¬
dards of modern equipment and indus¬
try of other countries (5).
(1) The Scientific American, October 1964.
Dr. Wiesner was Chief Scientific Adviser to
President Kennedy.
(2) New York Times, 8 June 1957.
(3) Mr. Piel Is Publisher of the Scientific
American. He was awarded the Unesco
Kallnga Prize for the Popularization of Science
In 1963.
(4) Dr Peter Hodgson of Oxford University
writes: "I would guess that I per cent of the
resources spent on weapons research could
probably produce a far greater scientific
advance than the weapons programme Itself."
(5) A Strategy for American Defense,
Columbia University Press, 1963. See also
Professor Seymour Melman, Our Depleted
Society, Holt, Rinehart & Winston, 1965.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Prime Minister of Britain made
the same point in December 1964:
"Defence is taking too big a share of
our real resources in terms of foreign
exchange, scarce types of manpower
and load on the most advanced In¬
dustries . . . Defence uses one-fifth of
all qualified scientists and technolo¬
gists who are engaged on research
and development, and defence now
accounts for about 40 % of all re¬
search and development expenditure."
Social benefits ?
Other contributions to human advan¬
ce which have been attributed to mili¬
tary research include "the following:
yellow-fever eradication; chlorlnation
of water; blood-plasm substitutes;
advanced weather prediction tech¬
niques
It is enough to ask two questions.
If the resources in money and expert
knowledge devoted to biological wea¬
pons had been given instead to Inter¬
national research for the eradication
of disease, might not far greater medi¬
cal results have been obtained?
If the resources in money, equip¬
ment and scientific genius given to
nuclear weapons had been used ins¬
tead for research into what causes the
weather, and for computers to turn the
increased knowledge into reliable fore¬
casts, might not a much advanced
meteorology have made a large addi¬
tion to mankind's annual income of
food and other usable wealth?
The conclusion of this section of the
argument is plain. There are some
scientific, industrial, and social bene¬
fits from military research but they
constitute a minimal off-set against the
waste and dangers of the arms race.
If the scientists and technicians engag¬
ed on this work could be diverted from
"improving" armaments to peaceful
industrial, agricultural and medical re¬
search, and if they were given the
same equipment and resources that
they have today, their achievements
might quite quickly revolutionize man's
individual and social life.
Science
and
Conscience
The scientists have made the mod¬
ern weapons; for a hundred years,
scientists have contributed to every
development in armament technique.
With what motives have they done
so? Do they carry any special res¬
ponsibility not shared by their fellow
citizens?
Some of the men who have made
important new contributions to arma
ment technique did so, no doubt, in
the hope of making money. Some
who made money Alfred Nobel, for
example believed that their inventions
would help to abolish war. Nobel
wrote to his friend, the Baroness von
Suttner: "My factories may well put
an end to war sooner than your con¬
gresses. The day when two army
corps can annihilate one another In
one second, all civilized nations, it is
to be hoped, will recoil from war and
discharge their troops » (1).
Haber suggested the use of poison
gas to the German General Staff In
1915. He was the winner of a Nobel
Prize for Chemistry, he knew that poi¬
son gas would violate the accepted
law of war; but he had spent the win¬
ter of 1914-15 as a private in the
trenches and he foresaw the long
years of strategic stalemate and of
senseless slaughter which would
come, unless some new weapon could
break the stalemate and bring hos¬
tilities to an end.
Einstein, Szilard, Pelerls and Rotblat
all detested war; they knew the im¬
mense perils which nuclear weapons
would involve; but they thought the
greatest danger was that Hitler should
get nuclear weapons first. That was
what made them persuade President
Roosevelt to authorize the Manhattan
District Project; that was what inspired
their colleagues in the Project team to
the stupendous efforts which they
made. This could, no doubt, be
regarded as only a special case of the
general compulsion of the arms race;
but it was a case in which men pre¬
eminently endowed with social cons¬
cience acted from the highest motives,
In the interest of humanity as a whole.
The same could certainly be said of
Sir Robert Watson-Watt, who brought
the priceless gift of radar to the Royal
Air Force to help it meet the threat
of Goering's bombers. And it could
certainly also be said of many lesser
scientists, who have volunteered their
contribution to the military defence of
causes in which they ardently believed.
But, no doubt, for the great majority
of the men who have worked in mili¬
tary research in various countries, no
such special motive was required.
Their governments invited them to enter
this branch of Its service, precisely as
it invited (or compelled) other men to
join the fighting forces. They accept¬
ed the invitation, or obeyed the order,
with the same sense of patriotic duty
which all good citizens should feel.
Do the scientists engaged in
military research carry a special
responsibility for the present dan¬
gerous arms race a responsibility
which their fellow-citizens do not
share?
The following propositions will
probably command fairly general
assent:
1. No citizen of a democratic coun¬
try can escape a share of respon¬
sibility for what his government
does in matters of national defence.
If he pays his taxes, he is financing
the work on weapons which the
scientists complete.
2. It is open to a scientist to refuse
to work in military research one
example being that of Professor
Otto Hahn, who first split the uran¬
ium atom in 1939, when he led
eighteen foremost German physi¬
cists in 1957 in declaring that they
would "never take part in any way
in the production, testing, or use
of atomic weapons". This is equi¬
valent to the stand of the conscien¬
tious objector, who declares that
he will play no part in war. It is
worthy of all respect. But to most
scientists it will not seem an
acceptable way out of the dilemma
with which the arms race now
confronts them.
The responsibility
of the
scientists
(1) Quoted In August Schou, The Nobel
Peace Prize.
3. If a scientist accepts employment
in his government's military re¬
search, and if he feels, as he
normally will, that his nation's
security depends on his work in
keeping the national forces ade¬
quately equipped with modern
weapons, then it is his duty to
make the utmost efforts to improve
those weapons, and to keep his
national forces up to the highest
standards of fighting power achiev¬
ed by other nations.
4. In carrying out his share in mili¬
tary research, the scientist is nor¬
mally under orders from generals
and ministers. If there is guilt in
making the modern means of war,
it lies primarily on the shoulders of
the ministers who make the politi¬
cal decisions that these means of
war shall be produced, and on the
parliaments who pay. If the scien¬
tists were simply under orders, like
other civil servants, this would be
the main answer to the questions
now being discussed.
5. But in reality the scientists
engaged in military research are 1 "7
not simply under orders; they are ' '
not simply civil servants with no
direct responsibility for what is
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND DISARMAMENT (Continued)
18
done. On the contrary, they know
so much more about modern wea¬
pons, and about the possibility of
further "improving" them, than the
generals or the politicians can
possibly know, that they inevitably
play a large part in the process
of decision-making.
Of all the new departures in
United States nuclear weapons
policy since 1945, all but one were
initially conceived and put forward
by scientists: the Oppenheimer-
Baruch plan for nuclear disarma¬
ment; the "fusion" or hydrogen
bomb; the development of so-call¬
ed "tactical" or "battlefield" nuc¬
lear weapons; the ballistic missile
for the delivery of nuclear war¬
heads; and the ban on nuclear
tests. The only exception was the
doctrine of massive retaliation,
which was the brain-child of John
Foster Dulles.
In so far as scientists are effec¬
tive participants in decision-making
about weapons, they share the kind
of responsibility borne by generals
and ministers; and in view of their
greater knowledge, their true share
of responsibility for what is done
may be greater than the share of
their military or political chiefs.
6. This special knowledge and
Influence of the scientists lays on
them a special duty which they
cannot escape. This is the duty
to explain to their General Staffs,
to their ministers, and to all their
fellow citizens the real destructive
power of the new weapons which
they have devised, introduced and
perfected. This means, in plain
language, that they should do what¬
ever is needed to warn their own
nations and the world of the grave
dangers of the present arms race.
7. But this special duty does not
end with explaining the nature of
the modem armaments, and the
danger of their accidental or un¬
intended use. It must also include
an obligation to help devise the
technical clauses of a disarmament
treaty by which the arms race can
be ended and to join in the educa¬
tional effort needed to create the
public opinion by which the policy
of disarmament can be made to
triumph. This is a duty which lies
inescapably on those scientists
who are engaged, or who have
been engaged, in military research.
8. As pointed out in paragraph
4 above, the scientists share re¬
sponsibility for the making of the
modern weapons with the generals
and the ministers under whose
orders they serve. It follows that
the duty described in paragraphs
6 and 7 lies also on the generals
and ministers, and that the pro¬
gramme of action described in later
sections of this article should be
undertaken by them all.
In principle, it is impossible to
dispute this proposition. But today
it is necessary to recognize
the facts of international life.
Twenty years after the second
"war to end war", the generals as
a class have shown small belief
that war and armaments can be
abolished; they regard it, rather, as
their duty to explain the difficulties
and dangers of disarmament; so
far, very few of them have made
constructive proposals for ending
the arms race.
The ministers have been willing,
year after year, to accept resolu¬
tions in the General Assembly of
the United Nations declaring that
disarmament is the most important
objective of their foreign policy.
But they have failed to give their
delegates the instructions which
would enable them to negotiate a
disarmament treaty.
Against
the complicity
of silence
There is no point in arguing
which nations have been most to
blame. The fact is that the minis¬
ters will only feel able to take
grave decisions which disarmament
requires when there is an over¬
whelming body of public opinion
throughout the world on which
they can rely to give them support.
9. Only the scientists can create
this body of opinion. They can
speak with an authority which the
ordinary citizen, the non-scientist,
cannot challenge, and to which he
is compelled to listen. Since they
cannot hope for much help from
the generals or the ministers, they
must act by themselves, in a
supreme endeavour to avert the
mortal dangers which confront
mankind.
How far do the propositions set
forth in the previous section apply
to scientists who are not engaged, and
who have never been engaged, in
military research?
At first sight, it might seem that the
responsibility and duty of these
scientists is less than that of scientists
who are so engaged. Their respon¬
sibility for the arms race is less; their
knowledge of the weapons and their
influence on government decisions are
less.
But three further propositions will
not be disputed.
Many scientists outside govern¬
ment service have contributed to
the general body of knowledge on
which military research has drawn
in its work on weapons. A vast
army of physicists built up the
knowledge of nuclear energy from
which the making of fission and
fusion weapons resulted. Many of
them made contributions of new
knowledge without which the wea¬
pons could not have been made,
even when they had no idea that
they were helping to create a new
and more dangerous kind of arms
race.
In so far as they understand the
weapons, and the dangers to which
the weapons give rise, better than
non-scientists, they have a duty
to help in the task described above.
By reason of their greater
knowledge, they will have more
influence on public opinion than
non-scientists. For example, phy¬
sicists, whether engaged in military
research or not, can explain the
dangers of the nuclear arms race
better than non-scientists; and
they will carry greater weight with
the average citizen. The same is
true of medical practitioners and
biological weapons; and of chem¬
ists and poison gases and incen¬
diary weapons.
In short, no one with a specialized
scientific training can escape a moral
obligation to share in this essential
work of education. And those who are
not in government employ have full
freedom to speak their minds; govern¬
ment scientists may be bound to
silence by the terms on which they
are engaged.
The scientists have a large share of
responsibility for another development
of sinister significance: the use or
misuse of language to obscure the
realities of the present arms race and
of nuclear war.
Sir Solly Zuckerman, for long the
Chief Scientific Adviser to the British
Ministry of Defence, and, since 1966,
Chief Scientific Adviser to the British
Government, has given a strong warn¬
ing about the danger which this
involves. Writing in 1962 In the United
States journal Foreign Affairs, he
spoke of "the way the military have
altered the concrete nature of certain
military problems by turning them into
abstractions. One dangerous example
of this tendency is the term "in¬
terdiction targets". Another is the idea
that nuclear weapons are just a new
and more powerful form of artillery,
CONTINUED ON PAGE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
A single 10-megaton bomb can wipe out a major city and cause
damage over a surrounding area of nearly 800 square miles.
Photo © Gene Smith - Magnum
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND DISARMAMENT (Continued)
20
and that one exchanges nuclear-fire
like counter-battery fire. A third is
that one is able "to restore a situa¬
tion" with nuclear fire".
Sir Solly went on to explain that the
destruction by nuclear weapons of
"interdiction targets" bridges rail¬
way Junctions, mobilization depots
and so on would Inevitably mean
the destruction of towns and a large-
scale attack on civilian targets ; that
the "exchange of nuclear-fire" would
not simply mean the obliteration of
the enemy's guns or launching sites,
but the devastation of a large area
of territory; that an adverse battlefield
situation could not be "restored" by
nuclear weapons as it might be by
artillery bombardment the nuclear
weapons would only add to the military
chaos, and would, by fall-out, be a
grave danger to troops using them (1).
Kilotons and Megatons
These were illustrations of the
general propositions which Sir Solly
stated thus : "We must avoid the
conceptual framework derived from the
military' terminology of pre-nuclear
warfare. One may fairly ask what
meaning there Is to the idea of using
nuclear weapons 'to defend our
territories and peoples'. One can
deter with nuclear weapons. Can one
defend?" (2).
Sir Solly was discussing the misuse
in the nuclear age of previously
accepted, and valid, strategic terms.
But there is also a large body of
newly-Invented jargon; a whole
vocabulary of phrases, unintelligible
to anyone but the expert, for describ¬
ing the nuclear weapons, the. various
kinds of attack for which they might
be used, and the "responses" (coun¬
ter-attacks) which might most advan¬
tageously be made.
One part of this jargon is mathe¬
matical and, no doubt, necessary, both
for the scientists and the General
Staffs. To express the explosive
power of a nuclear weapon, it is
described as either in the "kiloton"
or the "megaton" class.
A kiloton Is the equivalent of 1,000
tons of TNT; a megaton Is the equi¬
valent of 1 million tons of TNT. The
bomb that destroyed Hiroshima was
approximately 20 kilotons; the first H
bomb exploded at Bikini in March
1954 was 15 megatons; in September
1961, the U.S.S.R. exploded a bomb
of about 60 megatons. If this bomb
had had an outer sheath of uranium-
238 instead of lead Its power might
have exceeded 100 megatons.
These terms "kiloton" and "mega¬
ton" obscure from the ordinary citizen
the great destructive potential of the
weapons. A half-kiloton weapon
sounds like something very small; in
fact it has the explosive power of 600
to 700 twelve-Inch shells with a charge
of TNT. One twelve-Inch shell was
considered a very formidable weapon
in the First World War.
The effect of a megaton weapon can
best be understood by remembering
that all the Allies succeeded In drop¬
ping only 1.2 million tons of bombs
with chemical explosives on German
territory during six years of the Second
World War. In doing so, they ruined
most of the German cities, and they
destroyed a great part of German
industry, oil stocks and oil production,
and almost all the German railway
system. The smallest megaton weapon
has the same explosive power.
There is another insidious danger
in these mathematical terms, especially
when they are used in "the conceptual
framework derived from the military
terminology of pre-war nuclear war¬
fare". A United States scientist,
Dr. Donald Brennan, has expressed it
thus: "Even among professionals, I
have observed an occasional tendency
to think of kilotons as tons." (3)
The new military
jargon
a dangerous
word game
"Professionals" i.e., soldiers sail¬
ors and airmen trained with conven¬
tional weapons and experienced in
conventional military operations come
to think of the new weapons as similar
to those which they employed in the
two World Wars. This is a singularly
perilous aberration, which disguises
the real nature of operations from
those who plan them.
But, in spite of these dangers, the
use of these mathematical terms is
not only useful, but also necessary, as
noted above, both for scientists and
General Staffs. They cannot write out
"the equivalent of thousands (millions)
of tons of TNT" thousands of times,
to explain their meaning.
The problem is to ensure that all
who use the terms, including military
"professionals", journalists, commen¬
tators and the general public, really
grasp the significance of the terms;
that they really come to understand
that kiloton weapons are at least a
thousand times as powerful as the
shells and bombs used in the Second
World War, and may be up to 50,000
times as powerful; while even the
smallest of megaton weapons is at
least a million times as powerful as
(1) Foreign Affairs, January 1962.
(2) ibid.
(3) Arms Control and Disarmament.
the twelve-inch shell, and the largest
so far made, 60 million times.
There are other parts of this new
"strategic" jargon for which there Is
less intellectual excuse. The weapon
which destroyed Hiroshima was called
the "nominal" bomb. Perhaps the
word "nominal" was convenient. At
least it evoked no unpleasant
memories; perhaps this was not its
greatest merit to those who used it
first. For when "experts" and poli¬
ticians want to make the uninitiated
appreciate the power of a nuclear
device, they abandon the word "nomi¬
nal", and speak of "Hiroshima".
Seeking to persuade the House of
Commons of the great strength of the
proposed British "independent"
nuclear deterrent, Sir Alec Douglas-
Home said that the eighty Polaris
missiles in the five United Kingdom
nuclear-powered submarines "will
have a strikeload of 2,500 or 3,000
Hiroshima bombs".
"Hiroshima" evokes, "nominal"
disguises, the reality of what the
bombs would mean. The same is true
when a 2-megaton warhead, which, as
already mentioned, Is nearly double
the explosive power of all the bombs
dropped on Germany in six years of
war, is called a "low-yield thermo¬
nuclear device".
Some of the new jargon passed
into journalistic, and Indeed, into
general, use. The commonest and the
most misleading of the euphemistic
phrases which are employed is the
word "tactical" applied to the smaller
types of nuclear weapons.
Euphemistic phrases
No one thought that the Hiroshima
bomb was tactical in 1945. It had
caused casualties many times as great
as the total strength of the British
Army of the Rhine. It was a substitute
for, and had averted, an Allied cam¬
paign against Japan, to which several
million troops had been assigned,
and which was expected to last for
18 months. It caused the enemy's
immediate and unconditional surrender.
. The United States Lilienthal Com¬
mittee, which drew up the first draft
of the Baruch-Oppenheimer Plan,
writing in their report in March 1946
while the impact of the first bombs
was still quite fresh, spoke of: "The
really revolutionary character of these
(atomic) weapons, particularly as
weapons of strategic bombardment
aimed at the destruction of cities and
the eradication of their populations."
This view of A-bombs was univers¬
ally accepted until the first H-bomb
was exploded in 1954. Only then did
General Staffs begin to say that A-
bombs were "tactical". They called
them "tactical" because something
bigger and more devastating had been
devised. Having these bigger weapons,
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
the Staffs, by an almost subconscious
process of thought, began to make
plans for war in which A-bombs were
regarded as artillery. Marshal of the
Royal Air Force Sir John Slessor, in
Strategy for the West, spoke for many
of the experts when he said: "We may
use nuclear power in a bomb or shell
tactically for conventional purposes.
That is merely to employ one projectile
to do what we had to use thousands
to do in Korea".
This was written with the most
honest intent. But in fact, no nuclear
weapon, not even the half-kiloton
bazooka-launched infantry bomb, the
Davy Crockett, bears any relation to
what artillery used to do. It is entirely
different in kind. And, of course, only
a very small proportion of the so-called
"tactical" or "battlefield" weapons
have as low a yield of explosive power
as the Davy Crockett. The vast major¬
ity have a yield as large as the
Hiroshima bomb; and very many are
more powerful still.
In the summer of 1964, Mr. McNa-
mara, the United States Secretary of
Defence, said the average yield of the
different weapons classed as "tactical"
was 100 kilotons, I.e., five times as
powerful as the Hiroshima bomb. It
is evident that, by all hitherto accepted
canons of military literature, such
weapons are what the Lilienthal
Committee called them "weapons of
strategic bombardment", and that they
are capable of the "destruction of
enemy cities and the eradication of
their populations".
'Megadeath'
'megacorpse'
and other
abhorrent phrases
The use of the word "tactical" to
describe them has done more than all
the rest of the jargon put together to
distort the thinking of the "experts"
about the use of nuclear arms, and to
lead the general public to accept what
in 1945-46 almost everyone agreed
was utterly unacceptable.
But there are other dangerous
words. When missiles with hydrogen
warheads became operational, the
General Staffs based their plans on
the assumption that these more power¬
ful weapons would be used for the
"destruction of enemy cities and the
eradication of their populations".
But the eradication of civilian popul¬
ations was an unpleasant thought. It
was less distasteful to plan for the
elimination of "military" targets. The
phrase "counter-force strategy" was
invented to describe the policy of
making the first major, strategic
nuclear onslaught against these milit¬
ary targets Staff headquarters ;
manpower depots; airfields; missile
sites; naval, especially submarine,
bases and dockyards; munitions
factories; "interdiction targets", such
as major bridges, railway junctions
and marshalling yard, road transport
centres and the rest.
Of course, many of these military
targets are situated in, or near, towns
and cities; they could not be attacked
with megaton weapons (and a strate¬
gic onslaught would mean that) or
even with multikiloton weapons, with¬
out killing a great number of civilians
as well. But it sounds more civilized,
more in accordance with Grotian Inter¬
national Law, to speak of attacking
military targets first; "counter-force
strategy" has soothing overtones.
The alternative to "counter-force
strategy" is "counter-value strategy".
"Counter-value" means directing the
first strategic nuclear attack not on
the military targets but on centres of
population and industry. The delibe¬
rate purpose of this attack would be to
wipe out the enemy's towns and cities,
exterminate his civilian population, and
destroy his industrial production.
Blanketing the facts
There are human beings who advo¬
cate the adoption of a "counter-value
strategy"; they believe that to announ¬
ce the adoption of a "counter-force"
policy must weaken the strength of the
deterrent. Fortunately their numbers
are few; but the invention of the phrase
('counter-value') to describe the mur¬
der of a nation will rank with historians
of the future as a classic example
of the militarist thinking of 1965.
So will the parallel phrase, "bonus
kills". In strategic planning, it appe¬
ars, it is convenient to calculate only
the casualties that will be immediately
caused by the flash, blast and fire
effects of a given kilotonnage or meg-
atonnage of nuclear bombs. It is on
this basis that the plans for an ope¬
ration are drawn up, the weapons
allocated, and so on. If, In addition
to these primary casualties, other
people die as a result of fall-out, they
are referred to as "bonus kills" (1).
There are other jargon phrases, just
as abhorrent on moral and Intellectual
grounds: "megadeath", to mean the
death of a million people; "mega¬
corpse", to mean a million dead
bodies; "overkill", to express the
power to destroy the entire population
of an enemy country more than once.
Whatever its technical advantages,
there are dangers of various kinds
inherent in the use of this euphemistic
jargon. Others besides Dr. Brennan's
"professionals" think they are speak¬
ing of tons when they speak of kilo¬
tons; the error is common among
journalists, amateur strategists, and
the general public. In 1964, It led
a candidate in the United States pre¬
sidential election to speak of tactical
nuclear weapons as "the successors
of yesterday's conventional arms" (2);
he urged that officers in the field
be given authority to order their use.
Let no one think that this is a small
matter, or that the sinister importance
of euphemism has been over-stated.
The constant repetition of disingenu¬
ous phrases like those cited above
has led to a kind of self-induced
hypnosis among those who ought to
understand the dangers of the mod¬
ern arms race and particularly among
the politicians; while for the general
public it has simply blanketed the
facts. The scientists engaged in mili¬
tary research must carry their full share
of the blame for this result.
The first efforts
by scientists
to warn
the world
The scientists who asked President
Roosevelt to authorize the effort to
make a nuclear bomb did so with
heavy hearts. Those who served in
the international team of the Manhattan
District Project shared their doubts
and fears. Dr. Arthur Compton has
described how they "prayed that they
might not succeed".
When in 1944 it became evident that
their prayers would be In vain, and
that the age of nuclear fission was
dawning, the most eminent among
them, Niels Bohr of Denmark, wrote a
memorandum for President Roosevelt,
warning him of the Immense dangers
to mankind that nuclear weapons
would mean.
"Unless some agreement about the
control of the use of the new active
materials can be obtained in due time,
any temporary advantage, however
great, may be outweighed by a per¬
petual menace to human society... No
kind of customary measures will suf¬
fice for this purpose (the control of
atomic energy). The terrifying pros¬
pect of a future competition between
nations about a weapon of such for¬
midable character can only be avoided
through a universal agreement In true
confidence."
Already Niels Bohr foresaw the
perils that were being unleashed; he
foresaw that the necessary Internation¬
al agreement must be universal and
that It must breed true confidence.
His anxiety was shared by many of
his colleagues. In the same year,
1944, in the so-called Frank Report,
(1) Ralph E. Lapp, Kill and Overkill. See Ol
also footnote page 40 on his book "The ¿^ |
Voyage of the Lucky Dragon'.
(2) Senator Goldwater, The Times, 18 August
1964.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 68
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE CHALLENGE
OF PEACE
by Vadim Ardatovsky
E
ARLY In June 1967, as
participants In an international meeting
of journalists held in Strasbourg, we
tried to forget the outside world and
spent an agreeable week discussing
the recent progress of technology and
Its growing impact on the press.
In our small way, we tried to make
a contribution to that increasingly
popular exercise which has been
VADIM ARDATOVSKY, a Soviet journal¬
ist, is a well-known commentator on inter¬
national relations In the U.S.S.R. He has
taken part in several international confer¬
ences of journalists devoted to studies
and discussions of world' affairs and on
world problems of mass communications.
termed "Futurology" and which some¬
times skims fairly close to Science
Fiction. We tried to visualize the
world of tomorrow and more espe¬
cially what a "Golden Age" of journal-
Ism might be like tomorrow. We saw
artificial satellites whirling through
space, transmitting facsimile news¬
papers to every corner of the globe.
Any family could select any of the
world's newspapers at the touch of a
button, and some of them were even
"talking newspapers" which added a
more personal touch. Stories by
news reporters on the spot were sent
directly to automatically operated
composing machines, while front page
dispatches were flashed instantan¬
eously via laser beams.
Our tiny international group, made
up of journalists from France, U.K.,
U.S.S.R., U.S.A., the Arab countries,
Japan, Yugoslavia, Ireland, Czecho¬
slovakia and other countries, even
went so far as to work out how long
it would take for such innovations to
be introduced, whether in the next
twenty, fifty or a hundred years.
By tacit agreement we omitted any
mention of politics despite the fact that
a war had broken out in the Middle
East that very week and no one could
then predict whether it would be
possible to circumscribe the conflict
that had erupted or whether it would
eventually spread to other countries.
Our discussions on the future progress
of the communications industry were
Weapons of war (left).
Tools for peace (right).
But a tank costs far
more than a tractor and
nations squander
astronomical sums to
maintain their arsenals
of modern weapons.
The cost of a new
prototype bomber with
full equipment, for
example, equals the price
of 50,000 tractors, or
75 fully equipped 100-bed
hospitals or 30 science
faculties each with
1,000 students (see
"Unesco Courier",
November 1964).
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
-A
based on what seemed a natural
assumption that the world would
develop peacefully in the foreseeable
future.
Clearly no one except a compara¬
tively small group of professional
military men can think of drawing up
vast plans for the future with the
perspective of a world war in front of
him. The architect breaking ground
for a new skyscraper, the gardener
landscaping a new park, the artist
starting on a new painting, all think
ahead to the future enjoyment and
benefit of their work to society for
years and even generations to come.
To put it another way, the need for
peace is as natural to man as his need
for oxygen, and the most important
instinct of man the instinct to stay
alive.
A Swiss scientist, Jean-Jacques
Babel, has recently calculated that in
the course of history man has waged
14,500 major and minor wars, and the
French sociologist, Gaston Bouthoul,
is the author of a study entitled 8,000
Traités de Paix (8,000 peace treaties).
Someone has worked out that man's
"Golden Age" when peace has
reigned throughout the world has
been of surprisingly short duration,
hardly more than a total of 220 yearsl
I wonder whether we shouldn't stop
and reflect on this a moment, and ask
ourselves how much those 14,500 wars
Photo © APN - Ivanov
have Impeded the advance of civiliza¬
tion.
People may differ widely in their
opinions about Karl Marx's philosophy
but no one, I believe, could argue with
the following statement he made about
war : "From a purely economic point
of view, it is tantamount to a nation
throwing a portion of its capital into
the sea."
In the course of the Second World
War, 60 per cent of the national rev¬
enue of the belligerent countries was
drained away and lost forever. In
addition, this terrible holocaust claimed
the lives of 50 million persons who
died in a sea, not of water, but of
blood.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE CHALLENGE OF PEACE (Continued)
The rocky road
to international agreements
It would hardly seem necessary
today to describe once again the
horrible consequences of a new world
war, a war fought with nuclear wea¬
pons. The destruction involved
would go far beyond what any of us
could possibly imagine. The world's
press has on various occasions quoted
a figure which is in no sense an
exaggeration : the death of 700 to 800
million people as a result of the first
nuclear attack.
c
24
LEARLY, therefore, neither
common sense nor the spirit of huma¬
nity give mankind any other choice
today than the establishment of a last¬
ing peace. Yet it is a secret to no one
that we live in a world of unstable,
uneasy peace. Time and again we have
seen the flames of war erupt In Korea,
Algeria, Suez, Vietnam and the Middle
East ... As dangerous for peace today
is the present tendency of the majority
of nations to stockpile armaments.
Professor George Schwartzenberger,
of London University, was certainly
right when he said that present-day
relations between nations are permeat¬
ed with mutual distrust and constant
fear of other nations' intentions.
It would therefore appear quite
logical that nations seek to perfect the
means for their own defence. But
there does not seem to be any formula
fordoing away with the "world Inarms"
and the suspicions which derive from
it, other than the elimination of the
material basis of this fear and distrust,
that is, the armaments themselves.
It is only since the end of the 19th
Century and in the brief Interludes
between wars in our own time that
world political thought has been led to
consider seriously the theory of gene¬
ral disarmament. In the past, disar¬
mament was applied to a country after
it met defeat ; it had to surrender its
arms, its fortifications were destroyed
and other measures of a similar nature
were taken. Bitter experience has
taught us that far from preventing new
wars and conquests this increased the
danger of war.
That is why, during the Second
World War with its untold destruction
and millions of victims, people every¬
where were made acutely aware of the
urgency of establishing a lasting peace
based on the one means of definitely
guaranteeing it, namely, disarmament.
Even before the war had actually
ended, Moscow, London, Washington
and Paris were already seeking ways
to build the peace of the future.
In October 1943 a meeting of the
Ministers of Foreign Affairs of the
Four Allied Powers was held in
Moscow. In the declaration they
jointly signed it was emphasized that
the problem of disarmament should be
resolved in the same spirit of unity
which had been displayed by the
Great Powers of the Anti-Nazi coali¬
tion.
The approach to the problem of
disarmament at that time was perhaps
somewhat naive : the soldiers would
return home after victory and would
abandon their rifles and uniforms
forever ; at the same time production
of guns, tanks and bombers would be
stopped.
The appearance of a new type of
weapon and its production by one of
the Powers changed the situation.
Disarmament became even more vital
than before, but the solution to the
problem became even more difficult.
At the first session of the United
Nations General Assembly In 1946,
the U.S.S.R. proposed a "draft inter¬
national convention to prohibit the
production and employment of wea¬
pons based on the use of atomic
energy for the purpose of mass
destruction." This plan called for the
destruction within three months of all
atomic weapons and, what Is often
forgotten nowadays, the setting up of
an international control body with very
wide powers. This body would have
had access to atomic installations In
all countries and made sure that no
state infringed the convention.
wI AD this project been
adopted, the atomic bombs in the pos¬
session of the United States would
have been destroyed, and neither the
U.S.S.R. nor Great Britain, nor France
nor any other nation would have been
able to produce their own Atomic and
Hydrogen weapons. The problem of
disarmament would have resumed its
"pre-nuclear" aspect and might have
been easier to resolve.
At the time, however, it was argued
that the Soviet Union was seeking to
destroy weapons it did not possess
and thus obtain a military and strategic
advantage. In view of the ideas
prevailing at that time, this attitude
could well be justified. But had it
been possible in 1946 to foresee the
situation twenty years later, this
argument might well have lost Its full
force and appeared politically short¬
sighted.
Scientific and technical progress is
governed by its own laws which are
often independent of politics. Even
in the days when Leonardo da Vinci
was designing his flying machines,
men vaguely foresaw the possibility of
rockets and supersonic planes. Had
the great atomic physicists and mathe¬
maticians whose names are now fami¬
liar to everyone (with a timelag of 10 to
20 years) never been born, there can
be no doubt that other scientists would
soon have discovered atomic energy
along with its immense potentialities
for destruction as well as for peace.
The spread of nuclear energy and
weapons to other countries was thus,
obviously, only a question of time.
T HE question of the control
of nuclear weapons has certainly been
the big stumbling block of all discus¬
sions on disarmament. There was
once a time when heated debates
occurred over the question "which
came first the chicken or the egg?"
In our present age we have seen
endless discussions on whether con¬
trol should precede disarmament or
disarmament precede control. It must
be obvious, however, that the only
rational formula must be : "No disar¬
mament without control, and no control
without disarmament." In theory every¬
one is in agreement on this, both in
the United States and the Soviet
Union ; but in practice	
In practice the means of war and
destruction continue to be stockpiled
and perfected. For this reason it is
more important than ever to do
everything possible to facilitate a
detente in international relations, and
to prepare the ground for eventual
total disarmament by an effort to limit
the present arms race.
The first successful attempts in this
direction was made in 1963 when the
Powers signatory to the Moscow
Treaty agreed to ban nuclear weapon
tests in the atmosphere, in outer space
and under water. Agreement came
following a whole series of discus¬
sions, all of which centered on the
major Issue of control.
Today, more than four years after
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
V MI ». .TIP*'
* .-v-.-.v *:
V'v.-* ; wK
gi-v*- r^*
«r .!
i
>. ' .'
»
. « 'V-Jv*$s
V-.
'.*.
# . *
.l ' ' ' '
t 'V
\y..y : * .; '>
i_ >_+. V; ' _» ' *** -i '
9
Photo © "Soviet Union"
The Nuclear Test Ban Treaty signed in Moscow on August 5, 1963 prohibited
nuclear weapon tests in the atmosphere, in outer space and under water.
France and Mainland China, who were not signatories, have since carried out
nuclear tests in the atmosphere." Top, scientist examines a radiogram which
reveals extent of radioactive pollution in the atmosphere. Tests have shown
that contamination by fall-out particle» decreased considerably after the signing
of the Moscow Treaty. Above left, dots and spots on a radiogram made
in the autumn of 1962 indicate density of radioactive particles in the air.
Above right, a 1965 radiogram has only four spots (circled).
us cause for optimism and are an
incentive for further steps in the same
direction. Thus, the time may well
be ripe now to convene a world confer¬
ence in which every nation possessing
nuclear weapons would pledge itself
not to be the first to make use of such
weapons. Then too, apart from
Antarctica there are many parts of the
world where denuclearized zones
could be established. Plans have
already been put forward for the
denuclearization of Scandinavia, the
Balkans, Africa, Central Europe as
well as other areas.
There are also various proposals
(including one from the U.S.S.R.) for
the reduction of all military budgets by
10 to 15 per cent, or by any other
agreed amount, although events In
South-East Asia and the Middle East
have made it extremely difficult to
carry such projects out.
The prohibition of underground
nuclear explosions, however, now
appears closer to a solution. Two
years ago, at the 18-nation Geneva
disarmament talks, several non-com¬
mitted countries put forward a compro¬
mise plan calling for a ban on high-
powered underground explosions and
a moratorium on all other underground
explosions, pending the conclusion of
a general agreement on the question.
This proposal does not correspond
fully to the Soviet position but It has
been accepted by the U.S.S.R. as a
palliative to give the discussion a new
start.
the agreement was concluded, the
sceptics and Doubting Thomases have
been proved wrong. National detec¬
tion devices have shown their complete
effectiveness in assuring reciprocal
control.
On December 19, 1966 the General
Assembly of the United Nations
unanimously adopted a historic treaty
on principles governing the activities
of States In the exploration and use of
outer space including the Moon and
other celestial bodies. The treaty
specifically bans the orbiting in space
of "any objects carrying nuclear
weapons or any other kinds of wea¬
pons of mass destruction." This
"demilitarization of outer space" treaty
was simultaneously signed in London,
Moscow and Washington on January
27, 1967. I was privileged to be
present at the signing of this impor¬
tant document in Moscow which took
place in the same building where the
Moscow Nuclear Test Ban Treaty was
signed in 1963.
We should not forget however that
as early as 1959 the Antarctic Treaty
(signed by 12 countries operating in
the southern continent) guaranteed
that Antarctica "shall continue forever
to be used exclusively for peaceful
purposes and shall not become the
scene or object of International
discord." The treaty prohibits the
establishment of military bases, military
manoeuvres and the testing of any type
of weapons, and bans nuclear explo¬
sions or the disposal of atomic waste
in the Antarctic. The demilitarization
of Antarctica has assured the constant
friendly co-operation of scientific bases
and expeditions at work there.
I feel that these steps, limited
though they may appear to some, give
IT was with great interest
that I read an article by Walter Lipp-
mann published in the "Unesco Cour¬
rier" of October 1965 on the search
for ways to establish peace on a
lasting basis. While I admire the logic
and the approach taken by Mr. Lipp-
mann in his article as well as the
feelings they inspire, I feel I cannot
agree with one of the points made
by the distinguished American jour¬
nalist.
Mr. Lippmann writes : "...War bet¬
ween nuclear powerb can no longer be
an instrument of their national policy.
This will still be the case even if, as
is most probable, a considerable num¬
ber of states acquire nuclear weapons.
For no nation can risk the use of these
weapons anywhere because, having
these weapons it is subject itself to
fearful retaliation... Therefore, the
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE CHALLENGE OF PEACE (Continued)
The arms race,
the gravest issue of our time
prospect of averting great war by
mutual deterrence is a reasonably
good prospect."
Unfortunately, military conflicts have
their own laws, or rather, they do not
obey the laws of common sense. The
events of last June in the Middle East
are proof that recourse to arms
between states or groups of states Is
neither impossible nor infrequent.
Can we really therefore be sure that
if armed conflicts occurred between
"small" nations possessing nuclear
weapons that the deterrent factor
would hold true and that these nations
would not make use of every weapon
in their arsenal ?
I am more inclined to agree with
another American journalist, John
Günther, when he says that in the
event that all countries gained posses¬
sion of atomic weapons even the
smallest country could spark off a
world conflagration.
I
26
,VEN a tiny country with a
per capita revenue from 22 to 25 times
smaller than that of the United States
may soon be in a position, I believe,
to produce atomic weapons. Today
some 10 to 15 countries possess
nuclear reactors destined for peaceful
purposes. But technical advances
and the dissemination of scientific data
are such that, with the reduction in the
cost of producing nuclear arms, soon
there will be not just 10 to 15 countries
but 50 or more potentially capable of
undertaking the manufacture of wea¬
pons of mass destruction.
For these reasons the conclusion of
an agreement on the non-proliferation
of nuclear weapons seems to me
particularly urgent. Most people are
familiar with the arguments for and
against this question. They have
been voiced repeatedly at the Geneva
disarmament meetings, in diplomatic
circles and In the world press. The
most telling argument against a non-
proliferation treaty stresses that such
a treaty would perpetuate the mono¬
poly in atomic weapons of the present
nuclear nations. This overlooks the
point that an agreement on the non-
proliferation of nuclear weapons Is not
an end in itself but only a first indis¬
pensable step towards the total
banning of these weapons and their
destruction in arsenals everywhere in
the world. Furthermore, should such
a non-proliferation treaty become a
reality, it is proposed that the non-
nuclear powers would be completely
guaranteed against any possible
nuclear attack by a nuclear power.
Another argument against non-pro¬
liferation holds that the banning of
production of nuclear weapons (as
well as the control necessary to
enforce the ban) would hamper tech¬
nical development in the contracting
countries by preventing them from
using atomic energy for peaceful
purposes. It should not be difficult,
however, to devise forms of control
that would not prejudice a nation's
industrial development. Furthermore,
the pooling of knowledge and research
in the peaceful use of atomic energy
would increase as the possibility of Its
being employed in the manufacture of
arms was eliminated.
It is easy to understand though not
always easy to approve the reasons
that prompt nations to keep arms in
their arsenals. But the sums spent
are staggering. In 1964 the world
poured down the drain the astronomi¬
cal sum of 120,000 million dollars for
armaments. The figure is consider¬
ably higher today. If some Imaginary
inhabitant of another solar system
was to visit our planet he would no
doubt find it hard to understand why
we Earthlings squander our resources
and energies so uselessly.
The examples of Vietnam and the
Middle East make it abundantly clear
that in this day and age no problem
can be resolved by resort to war.
And even less so by resorting to
nuclear weapons. The problem of
armaments today and their destructive
nature is thus the most poignant issue
of our time.
|N 1967, the U.S.S.R. will
spend 14,500 million roubles (13.2 per
cent of its budget) on defence. (1)
There are undoubtedly many ways in
which this money could be usefully
employed in the Soviet Union. The
United States spends even huger sums
on arms, including the war in Vietnam.
(/) Editor's note: The U.S.S.R. does not
include research and development costs in
its defence budget. Total actual defence
expenditure for 1966 has been estimated
at over 35,000 million dollars. (The
exchange rate of the rouble is one rouble
= 90 U.S. cents.)
And it too still has many social prob¬
lems to solve, bottlenecks in educa¬
tion, public health and science, where
these resources now spent on arms,
could be usefully employed. .
On the assumption that arms expen¬
diture remained at the present level
(which no one really wants), the Soviet
Union will spend 230,000 million rou¬
bles in the course of the next 20 years.
If general and complete disarmament
were to become a reality, and suppos¬
ing even that 20 per cent of the money
saved by disarmament were diverted
for the developing countries, the
U.S.S.R. would still have 230,000
million roubles left over for useful
purposes. The money could be spent
for an Infinite variety of purposes, to
raise the standard of living of the
Soviet people, to launch large-scale
development projects in Siberia, irri¬
gate desert lands, etc...
A look at a map of world
development shows us that entire
continents are in need of resources
and assistance to carry through their
full development. To cite only one
example, the harnessing of the world's
water resources could transform vast
regions of our planet. In Asia, the
Indus and the Mekong, the Tigris and
Euphrates ; in Africa, the Nile and its
tributaries, and the Congo ; in Latin
America, the Parana and the Amazon.
Mankind is only now becoming
aware of the great riches and possi¬
bilities at its disposal. Were these to
be effectively exploited, they could
eliminate hunger, sickness and many
other problems due to low living
standards, such as illiteracy which still
affects many hundreds of millions of
the Inhabitants of developing countries.
By the rational use of its energy and
intelligence, mankind could fulfil its
destiny at a much more rapid pace,
and even on a universal scale now
that man is moving beyond the limits
of the earth's gravity.
In ancient times, people used to
dream about the "Golden Age". But In
the times of Plato or Thomas More,
this was in fact a Utopia, a mere
dream of happiness. Today, with the
help of electronic machines we can
calculate the extent to which progress
in various spheres of human existence
would be speeded up should an epoch
of general peace and complete dis¬
armament be ushered in.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Henri Mardyks Detail of a study by Auguste Rodin (1840-1917) for "The Citizens of Calais", the famous f\"l
group of bronze figures on which the sculptor worked from 1884 to 1889. In 1347, during £f
a war between England and France, six burghers of Calais volunteered to give their
lives to save their besieged city. Though they were eventually spared, the event has gone
down as one of history's most outstanding examples of the spirit of self sacrifice.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
DEVELOPMENT
NEW NAME FOR PEACE
Encyclical Letter
of His Holiness Pope Paul VI
On March 26, 1967, His Holiness Pope Paul VI issued a far-reaching
Encyclical Letter on the Development of Peoples, calling on all men of
goodwill to join in freeing the world of its present poverty and inequities.
"The peoples in hunger are making a dramatic appeal to the peoples blessed
with abundance", His Holiness said. Pope Paul stressed the urgency of
the action that should be taken in a spirit of universal solidarity to assure
the development of all mankind. "Development", he affirmed, "is the new
name for Peace."
The Pope made an unprecedented gesture by addressing the first copies
of the Encyclical, bearing his signature, to U Thant, Secretary-General of
the United Nations, to Mr. René Maheu, Director-General of Unesco and
to Dr. Binay Ranjan Sen, Director-General of the U.N. Food and Agriculture
Organization.
We publish below salient passages from the Encyclical, and on page 35 the
response of Mr. René Maheu, inspired by the message of this historic
document.
F
28
reedom from misery, the greater
assurance of finding subsistence, health and fixed employ¬
ment; an increased share of responsibility without oppres¬
sion of any kind and In security from situations that do
violence to their dignity as men; better education in brief,
to seek to do more, know more and have more in order
to be more: that is what men aspire to now when a
greater number of them are condemned to live in con¬
ditions that make this lawful desire illusory.
Besides, peoples who have recently gained national inde¬
pendence experience the need to add to this political
freedom a fitting autonomous growth, social as well as
economic, In order to assure their citizens of a full human
enhancement and to take their rightful place with other
nations. (6)
Colonization and colonialism. Though insufficient for the
Immensity and urgency of the task, the means inherited
from the past are not lacking. It must certainly be rec¬
ognized that colonizing powers have often furthered their
own interests, power or glory, and that their departure
has sometimes left a precarious economy, bound up for
instance with the production of one kind of crop whose
market prices are subject to sudden and considerable
variation.
Yet while recognizing the damage done by a certain
type of colonialism and its consequences, one must at the
same time acknowledge the qualities and achievement of
colonizers who brought their science and technical know¬
ledge and left beneficial results of their presence in so
many underprivileged regions.
The structures established by them persist, however in¬
complete they may be; they diminished ignorance and
sickness, brought the benefits of communications and Im¬
proved living conditions. (7)
| ncreasing imbalance. Yet once this is admitted, It remains
only too true that the resultant situation is manifestly in-
dequate for facing the hard reality of modern economics.
Left to itself it works rather to widen the differences In
the world's level of life, not to diminish them; rich peoples
enjoy rapid growth whereas the poor develop slowly. The
imbalance is on the increase: some produce a surplus of
foodstuffs, others cruelly lack them and see their exports
made uncertain. (8).
U ndeserved hardship. At the same time social conflicts
have taken on world dimensions. The acute disquiet which
has taken hold of the poor classes in countries that are
becoming industrialized, is now embracing those whose eco¬
nomy is almost exclusively agrarian: farming people, too,
are becoming aware of their "undeserved hardship."
There is also the scandal of glaring inequalities not merely
in the enjoyment of possessions but even more In the
exercise of power. While a small restricted group enjoys
a refined civilization in certain regions, the remainder of
the population, poor and scattered, is "deprived of nearly
all possibility of personal initiative and of responsibility, and
oftentimes even Its living and working conditions are un¬
worthy of the human person". (9)
V* onflict of civilizations. Furthermore, the conflict between
traditional civilizations and the new elements of Industrial
civilization, break down structures which do not adapt
themselves to new conditions. Their framework, some¬
times rigid, was the indispensable prop to personal and
family life; older people remain attached to it, the young
escape from It, as from a useless barrier, to turn eagerly
to new forms of life in society.
The conflict of the generations is made more serious
by a tragic dilemma: whether to retain ancestral institu¬
tions and convictions and renounce progress, or to admit
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photo United Nations
techniques and civilizations from outside and reject along
with the traditions of the past all their human richness.
In effect, the moral, spiritual and religious supports of
the past too often give way without securing in return
any guarantee of a place In the new world. (10)
Dangerous confusion. In this confusion the temptation be¬
comes stronger to risk being swept away towards types
of messianism which give promises but create illusions.
The resulting dangers are patent: violent popular reactions,
agitation towards insurrection, and a drifting towards tota¬
litarian ideologies. Such are the data of the problem.
Its seriousness Is evident to all. (11)
E conomic growth not enough. Development cannot be
limited to mere economic growth. In order to be authentic,
it must be complete: Integral, that Is, it has to promote the
good of every man and of the whole man. . . (14).
A world responsibility. But each man is a member of
society. He Is part of the whole of mankind. It is not
just certain individuals, but all men who are called to this
fullness of development. Civilizations are born, develop
and die. But humanity is advancing along the path of
history like the waves of a rising tide encroaching gradually
on the shore. We have inherited from past generations,
and we have benefitted from the work of our contempora¬
ries: for this reason we have obligations towards all,
and we cannot refuse to Interest ourselves in those who
will come after us to enlarge the human family. . . (17)
|he ambivalence of growth. . . All growth is ambivalent.
It is essential if man is to develop as a man, but In
a way it imprisons man if he considers it the supreme
good, and it restricts his vision. Then we see hearts
harden and minds close, and men no longer gather
together in friendship but out of self-interest, which soon
leads to oppositions and disunity. The exclusive pursuit
of possessions thus become an obstacle to individual ful¬
filment and to man's true greatness. Both for nations and
for individual men, avarice is the most evident form of
moral underdevelopment. (19)
T owards a more human condition. If further development
calls for the work of more and more technicians, even more
necessary is the deep thought and reflection of wise men
in search of a new humanism which will enable modern
man to find himself anew by embracing the higher values
of love and friendship, of prayer and contemplation. This is
what will permit the fullness of authentic development, a
development which is for each and all the transition from
less human conditions to those which are more human. (20)
I deal to be pursued. Less human conditions: the lack
of material necessities for those who are without the
minimum essential for life, the moral deficiencies of those
who are mutilated by selfishness. Less human conditions:
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
NEW NAME FOR PEACE (Continued)
oppressive social structures, whether due to the abuses
of ownership or to abuses of power, to the exploitation
of workers or to unjust transactions. Conditions that are
more human: the passage from misery towards the pos¬
session of necessities, victory over social scourges, the
growth of knowledge, the acquisition of culture. Addi¬
tional conditions that are more human; increased esteem
for the dignity of others, the turning toward the spirit of
poverty, co-operation for the common good, the will and
desire for peace. . . (21)
| ndustrialization. The introduction of Industry is a ne¬
cessity for economic growth and human progress; it Is also
a sign of development and contributes to it. By persis¬
tent work and use of his intelligence man gradually wrests
nature's secrets from her and finds a better application for
her riches. As his self-mastery increases, he develops a
taste for research and discovery, an ability to take a cal¬
culated risk, boldness In enterprises, generosity in what
he does and a sense of responsibility. (25)
Liberal capitalism. But it is unfortunate that on these new
conditions of society a system has been constructed which
considers profit as the key motive for economic progress,
competition as the supreme law of economics, and private
ownership of the means of production as an absolute
right that has no limits and carries no corresponding social
obligation.
This unchecked liberalism leads to dictatorship rightly
denounced by Pius XI as producing "the international im¬
perialism of money." One cannot condemn such abuses too
strongly by solemnly recalling once again that the economy
is at the service of man.
But if it is true that a type of capitalism has been the
source of excessive suffering, injustices and fratricidal con¬
flicts whose effects still persist, it would also be wrong to
attribute to industrialization itself evils that belong to the
woeful system which accompanied it. On the contrary
one must recognize in all justice the irreplaceable contri¬
bution made by the organization of labour and of Industry
to what development has accomplished. (26)
U rgency of the task. We must make haste: too many are
suffering, and the distance is growing that separates the
progress of some and the stagnation, not to say the
regression, of others. . . (29)
I emptation to violence. There are certainly situations
whose injustice cries to heaven. When whole populations
destitute of necessities live in a state of dependence barring
them from all initiative and responsibility, and all opportunity
to advance culturally and share In social and political
life, recourse to violence, as a means to right these
wrongs to human dignity, is a grave temptation. (30)
R. evolution. We know, however, that a revolutionary
uprising save where there is manifest, long-standing tyran¬
ny which would do great damage to fundamental personal
rights and dangerous harm to the common good of the
country produces new injustices, throws more elements
out of balance and brings on new disasters. A real evil
should not be fought against at the cost of greater
misery. (31)
R, eform. We want to be clearly understood: the present
situation must be faced with courage and the injustices
linked with it must be fought against and overcome.
Development demands bold transformations, innovations
that go deep. Urgent reforms should be undertaken
without delay. It is for each one to take his share in
them with generosity, particularly those whose education,
position and opportunities afford them wide scope for
action. . . (32)
A t man's service. . . It is not sufficient to promote
technology to render the world a more human place in
which to live. The mistakes of their predecessors should
warn those on the road to development of the dangers
to be avoided in this field. To-morrow's technocracy can
beget evils no less redoubtable than those due to the
liberalism of yesterday.
Economics and technology have no meaning except from
man whom they should serve. And man is only truly man
in as far as, master of his own acts and judge of their
worth, he is author of his own advancement, In keeping
with the nature which was given to him by his Creator
and whose possibilities and exigencies he himself freely
assumes. (34)
Efforts to achieve literacy. It can even be affirmed that
economic growth depends in the very first place upon
social progress: thus basic education is the primary object
of any plan of development. Indeed hunger for education
is no less debasing than hunger for food: an illiterate is
a person with an undernourished mind. To be able to
read and write, to acquire a professional formation, means
to recover confidence in oneself and to discover that
one can progress along with the others.
As We said in Our message to the Unesco Congress
held in 1965 at Teheran, for man literacy is "a fundamental
factor of social integration, as well as of personal enrich¬
ment, and for society It is a privileged instrument of
economic progress and of development".
We also rejoice at the good work accomplished in
this field by private initiative, by the public authorities
and by international organizations: these are the primary
agents of development, because they render man capable
of acting for himself. . . (35)
D emography. It is true that too frequently an accelerated
demographic Increase adds its own difficulties to the
problems of development: the size of the population
increases more rapidly than available resources, and things
are found to have reached apparently an impasse. From
that moment the temptation is great to check the demo¬
graphic increase by means of radical measures.
It is certain that public authorities can intervene, within
the limit of their competence, by favouring the availability
of appropriate information and by adopting suitable
measures, provided that these be in conformity with the
moral law and that they respect the rightful freedom of
married couples. Where the inalienable right to marriage
and procreation is lacking, human dignity has ceased to
exist.
Finally, it is for the parents to decide, with full knowledge
of the matter, on the number of their children, taking into
account their responsibilities towards God, themselves,
the children they have already brought into the world,
and the community to which they belong. In all this
they must follow the demands of their own conscience
enlightened by God's law authentically interpreted, and
sustained by confidence in Him. (37)
P romotion of culture. In addition to professional organiza¬
tions, there are also institutions which are at work. Their
role is no less Important for the success of development.
"The future of the world stands In peril", the Vatican
Council gravely affirms, "unless wiser men are forthcoming".
And it adds: "many nations, poorer In economic goods,
CONTINUED ON PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
A street In Lahore (Pakistan)
Photo © Paul Almasy, Pans "It is true that too frequently an accelerated demographic increase adds its own difficulties
to the problems of development: the size of the population Increases more rapidly than
available resources, and things are found to have reached apparently an impasse."
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
NEW NAME FOR PEACE (Continued)
32
are quite rich in wisdom and able to offer noteworthy
advantages to others".
Rich or poor, each country possesses a civilization hand¬
ed down by their ancestors: institutions called for by life
in this world, and higher manifestations of the life of the
spirit, manifestations of an artistic, intellectual and religious
character. When the latter possess true human values,
it would be a grave error to sacrifice them to the former.
A people that would act in this way would thereby lose
the best of its patrimony; in order to live, it would be
sacrificing its reasons for living. . . (40)
O pirit of solidarity. There can be no progress towards
the complete development of man without the simultaneous
development of all humanity in the spirit of solidarity. As
We said at Bombay: "Man must meet man, nation meet
nation, as brothers and sisters, as children of God. In
this mutual understanding and friendship, in this sacred
communion, we must also begin to work together to build
the common future of the human race." We also suggested
a search for concrete and practical ways of organization
and co-operation, so that all available resources be pooled
and thus a true communion among all nations be
achieved. (43)
D rotherhood of peoples. This duty is the concern
especially of better-off nations. Their obligations stem
from a brotherhood that is at once human and super¬
natural, and take on a threefold aspect: the duty
of human solidarity the aid that the rich nations
must give to developing countries; the duty of social
justice the rectification of inequitable trade relations
between powerful nations and weak nations; the duty of
universal charity the effort to bring about a world that
is more human towards all men, where all will be able
to give and receive , without one group making progress
at the expense of the other. The question is urgent, for
on it depends the future of the civilization of the world.
(44)
VV ar against hunger. . . Today no one can be Ignorant
any longer of the fact that In whole continents countless
men and women are ravished by hunger, countless numbers
of children are undernourished, so that many of them
die in infancy, while the physical growth and mental
development of many others are retarded and as a result
whole regions are condemned to the most depressing
despondency... The campaign against hunger being
carried on by the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)
and encouraged by the Holy See, has been generously
supported. . . (45)
Let each examine his conscience. But... it is not just
a matter of eliminating hunger, nor even of reducing
poverty. The struggle against destitution, though urgent
and necessary, is not enough. It ¡s a question, rather,
of building a world where every man, no matter what
his race, religion or nationality, can live a fully human
life, free from servitude imposed on him by other men
or by natural forces over which he has not sufficient control;
a world where freedom is not an empty word and where
the poor man Lazarus can sit down at the same table
with the rich man. This demands great generosity, much
sacrifice and unceasing effort on the part of the rich
man.
Let each one examine his conscience, a conscience that
conveys a new message for our times. Is he prepared
to support out of his own pocket works and undertakings
organized in favour of the most destitute? Is he ready
to pay higher taxes so that the public authorities can
intensify their efforts in favour of development? Is he
ready to pay a higher price for imported goods so that
the producer may be more justly rewarded? Or to leave
his country, if necessary and if he is young, in order
to assist in this development of the young nations? (47)
D uty of human solidarity. The same duty of solidarity
that rests on individuals exists also for nations: "Advanced
nations have a very heavy obligation to help the develop¬
ing peoples". . . Every nation must produce more and
better quality goods to give to all its inhabitants a truly
human standard of living, and also to contribute to the
common development of the human race.
Given the increasing needs of the under-developed
countries, it should be considered quite normal for an
advanced country to devote a part of its production to
meet their needs, and to train teachers, engineers,
technicians and scholars prepared to put their knowledge
and their skill at the disposal of less fortunate peoples. (48)
5 uperfluous wealth. We must repeat once more that the
superfluous wealth of rich countries should be placed at
the service of poor nations. The rule which up to now
held good for the benefit of those nearest to us, must today
be applied to all the needy of this world.
Besides, the rich will be the first to benefit as a result.
Otherwise their continued greed will certainly call down
upon them the judgement of God and the wrath of the
poor, with consequences no one can foretell. If today's
flourishing civilizations remain selfishly wrapped up in
themselves, they could easily place their highest values
in jeopardy, sacrificing their will to be great to the desire
to possess more. . . (49)
A World Fund. . . At Bombay, We called for the estab¬
lishment of a great World Fund, to be made up of part
of the money spent on arms, to relieve the most destitute
of this world. What is true of the immediate struggle
against want, holds good also when there is a question of
development. Only world-wide collaboration, of which a
common fund would be both means and symbol, will
succeed In overcoming vain rivalries and in establishing a
fruitful and peaceful exchange between peoples. (51)
A id without strings. There is certainly no need to do
away with bilateral and multilateral agreements: they
allow ties of dependence and feeling of bitterness, left
over from the era of colonialism, to yield place to the
happier relationship of friendship, based on a footing of
constitutional and political equality.
However, if they were to be fitted into the framework of
world-wide collaboration, they would be beyond all suspi¬
cion, and as a result there would be less distrust on the part
of the receiving nations. These would have less cause
for fearing that, under the cloak of financial aid or technical
assistance, there lurk certain manifestations of what has
come to be called neo-colonialism, in the form of political
pressures and economic suzerainty aimed at maintaining
or acquiring complete dominance. (52)
A rms race an intolerable scandal. Besides who does
not see that such a fund would make it easier to take
measures to prevent certain wasteful expenditures, the
result of fear or pride?
When so many people are hungry, when so many fami¬
lies suffer from destitution, when so many remain steeped
in ignorance, when so many schools, hospitals and homes
worthy of the name remain to be built, all public or private
squandering of wealth, all expenditure prompted by motives
of national or personal ostentation, every exhausting arma¬
ments race, becomes an intolerable scandal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
We are conscious of Our duty to denounce it. Would
that those In authority listened to Our words before it is
too I ate I (53)
D ialogue among all peoples. This means that it is
absolutely necessary to create among all peoples that
dialogue for whose establishment We expressed Our hope
In Our first Encyclical Ecclesiam Suam. This dialogue
between those who contribute wealth and those who
benefit from it, will provide the possibilty of making an
assessment of the contribution necessary, not only drawn
up In terms of the generosity and the available wealth of
the donor nations, but also conditioned by the real needs
of the receiving countries and the use to which the financial
assistance can be put.
Developing countries will thus no longer risk being
overwhelmed by debts whose repayment swallows up the
greater part of their gains. Rates of interest and time for
repayment of the loan could be so arranged as not to be
too great a burden on either party, taking into account
free gifts, interest-free or low-interest loans, and the time
needed for liquidating the debts. Guarantees could be
given to those who provide the capital that it will be put
to use according to an agreed plan and with a reasonable
measure of efficiency, since there is no question of
encouraging parasites or the indolent.
And the receiving countries could demand that there
be no interference in their political life or subversion of
their social structures. As sovereign states they have
the right to conduct their own affairs, to decide on their
policies and to move freely towards the kind of society
they choose.
What must be brought about, therefore, is a system of
co-operation freely undertaken, an effective and mutual
sharing, carried out with equal dignity on either side, for
the construction of a more human world. (54)
Vv orld peace at stake. . . This common task will not
succeed without concerted, constant and courageous
efforts. But let everyone be convinced of this: the very
life of poor nations, civil peace in developing countries,
and world peace itself are at stake. (55).
Equity in trade relations. The efforts which are being
made to assist developing nations on a financial and tech¬
nical basis, though considerable, would be illusory if their
benefits were to be partially nullified as a consequence
of the trade relations existing between rich and poor
countries. The confidence of these latter would be
severely shaken if they had the impression that what was
being given them with one hand was being taken away
with the other. (56)
I ncreasing disproportion. Of course, highly industrialized
nations export for the most part manufactured goods, while
countries with less developed economies have only food,
fibres and other raw materials to sell. As a result of
technical progress the value of manufactured goods is
rapidly increasing and they can always find an adequate
market.
On the other hand, raw materials produced by under¬
developed countries are subject to wide and sudden fluc¬
tuations in price, a state of affairs far removed from the
progressively increasing value of industrial products. As
a result, nations whose industrialization is limited are
faced with serious difficulties when they have to rely on
their exports to balance their economy and to carry out
their plans for development. The poor nations remain
ever poor while the rich ones become still richer. (57)
Liberalism in question. In other words, the rule of free
trade, taken by itself, is no longer able to govern interna¬
tional relations. Its advantages are certainly evident when
the parties involved are not affected by any excessive
inequalities of economic power: it is an incentive to pro¬
gress and a reward for effort.
That is why industrially developed countries see in it a
law of justice. But the situation is no longer the same
when economic conditions differ too widely from country
to country: prices which are "freely" set in the market
can produce unfair results. One must recognize that it Is
the fundamental principle of liberalism, as the rule for
commercial exchange, which is questioned here. (58)
Obstacles to overcome: Nationalism. Among still other
obstacles which are opposed to the formation of a world
which is more just and which is better organized toward
a universal solidarity, We wish to speak of nationalism
and racism.
It is only natural that communities which have recently
reached their political independence should be jealous of
a national unity which is still fragile, and that they should
strive to protect it. Likewise, it is to be expected that
nations endowed with an ancient culture should be
proud of the patrimony which their history has bequeathed
to them. But these legitimate feelings should be ennobled
by that universal charity which embraces the entire human
family.
Nationalism isolates people from their true good. It
would be especially harmful where the weakness of national
economies demands rather the pooling of efforts, of
knowledge, and of funds, in order to implement programmes
of development and to increase commercial and cultural
exchange. (62)
R acism. Racism is not the exclusive lot of young
nations, where sometimes it hides beneath the rivalries of
clans and political parties, with heavy losses for justice
and at the risk of civil war. During the colonial period it
often flared up between the colonists and the indigenous
population, and stood in the way of mutually profitable
understanding, often giving rise to bitterness in the wake
of genuine injustices.
It is still an obstacle to collaboration among disadvantaged
nations and a cause of division and hatred within countries
whenever individuals and families see the inviolable
rights of the human person held In scorn, as they them¬
selves are unjustly subjected to a regime of discrimination
because of their race or their colour. (63)
For a unified world. We are deeply distressed by such
a situation which is laden with threats for the future. We
are, nonetheless, hopeful: a more deeply felt need for
collaboration, a heightened sense of unity will finally
triumph over misunderstandings and selfishness.
We hope that the countries whose development is less
advanced will be able to take advantage of their proximity
in order to organize among themselves, on a broadened
territorial basis, areas for concerted development: to draw
up programmes in common, to co-ordinate investments, to
distribute the means of production, and to organize trade.
We hope also that multilateral and international bodies,
by means of the reorganization which is required, will
discover the ways that will allow peoples which are still
under-developed to break through the barriers which seem QQ
to enclose them and to discover for themselves, in full 00
fidelity to their own proper genius, the means for their
social and human progress. (64)
CONTINUED ON PAGE 36
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
"Freedom from misery, the greater assurance of finding subsistence,
health and fixed employment; an increased share of responsibility . . .in
security from situations that do violence to their dignity as men;
better education in brief, to seek to do more, know more and have more
in order to be more: that is what men aspire to now..."
Photo © Mireille Vautier
<-
'^ *
i*-,.» »y J*t
*v '; *s
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
NEW NAME FOR PEACE (Continued)
A rtlsans of their own destiny. Such Is the goal we must
attain. World unity, ever more effective, should allow
all peoples to become the artisans of their destiny. The
past has too often been characterized by relationships of
violence between nations; may the day dawn when inter¬
national relations will be marked with the stamp of mutual
respect and friendship, of interdependence in collaboration,
the betterment of all seen as the responsibility of each
individual.
The younger or weaker nations ask to assume their
active part in the construction of a better world, one which
shows deeper respect for the rights and the vocation of the
individual. This is a legitimate appeal; everyone should
hear it and respond to it. (65)
U evelopment, the new name for peace. Excessive eco¬
nomic, social and cultural inequalities among peoples
arouse tensions and conflicts, and are a danger to peace...
Peace cannot be limited to a mere absence of war, the
result of an ever precarious balance of forces. No, peace
is something that is built up day after day, in the pursuit
of an order Intended by God, which implies a more perfect
form of justice among men. (76)
A n end to isolation. The peoples themselves have the
prime responsibility to work for their own development.
But they will not bring this about in Isolation. Regional
agreements among weak nations for mutual support, under¬
standings of wider scope entered into for their help, more
far-reaching agreements to establish programmes for closer
co-operation among groups of nations these are the
milestones on the road to development that leads to
peace. (77)
N eed for a world authority. This international collabora¬
tion on a world-wide scale requires institutions that will pre¬
pare, co-ordinate and direct it, until finally there Is estab¬
lished an order of justice which is universally recognized.
With all Our heart, We encourage these organizations
which have undertaken this collaboration for the develop¬
ment of the peoples of the world, and Our wish is that
they grow in prestige and authority.
"Your vocation," as We said to the representatives of
the United Nations in New York, "is to bring not some
people but all peoples to treat each other as brothers. . .
Who does not see the necessity of thus establishing pro¬
gressively a world authority, capable of acting effectively
in the juridical and political sectors?" (78)
H rogress of the human family. Some would consider
such hopes Utopian. It may be that these persons are
not realistic enough, and that they have not perceived
the dynamism of a world which desires to live more fra¬
ternally a world which, in spite of its ignorance,
its mistakes and even its sins, its relapses into barbarism
and its wanderings far from the road of salvation, is, even
unawares, taking slow but sure steps towards its Creator.
This road towards a greater humanity requires effort and
sacrifice; but suffering itself, accepted for the love of
our brethren, favours the progress of the entire human
family. . . (79)
u niversal solidarity. We have desired to remind all men
how crucial Is the present moment, how urgent the work
to be done. The hour for action has now sounded. At
stake are the survival of so many innocent children and,
for so many families overcome by misery, the access to
conditions fit for human beings; at stake are the peace
of the world and the future of civilization. It is time for all
men and all peoples to face up to their responsibilities. (80)
TO BUILD
by René Maheu
Director-General of Unesco
T
HE Encyclical is addressed
to the Church and, more generally, to
all men of goodwill. Unesco, a strictly
secular organization, is essentially a
world-wide venture in goodwill. The
Holy Father may be certain that his
message will evoke a particularly
favourable response in this Organiza¬
tion . . .
I should like, on behalf of Unesco,
to convey my sincere appreciation to
the Holy Father who, in this vital
document, has reaffirmed the truly
fundamental importance which should
be attached to literacy, and who has
recognized the value of the efforts
being made to combat the under-nour-
ishment of men's minds which is no
less debasing than under-nourishment
of their bodies. I see in this an
assurance of the Church's active co¬
operation in the campaign for basic
education and functional literacy which
Unesco is striving to promote through¬
out the world.
But, just as the cause we serve
goes far beyond our action, limited
as it is by the inadequacy of our
resources and too often hampered by
our own shortcomings, so what
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
A NEW ORDER IN THE WORLD
touches us most in the Encyclical,
beyond the support and assistance
extended to our work, is the profound
agreement which clearly emerges in
the spirit, and sometimes almost In
the letter, between the views of the
Holy Father concerning the problems,
aims and methods of development
and those which Unesco has cons¬
tantly promoted since the beginning
of this decade. 1 should like to draw
attention to the essential points on
which we find this harmony of views.
First of all, concerning the nature
of the problem. Like His Holiness
Paul VI, we believe that development
is, in the strictest sense of the terms,
a work of "justice and peace".
For the Twentieth-century world,
underdevelopment is what the social
question was for the countries which
were carrying out their industrial revo¬
lution in the Nineteenth century. As
the Encyclical makes clear, it is in
fact the same problem that is involved,
but extended to the scale of the world
as a whole: the old problem of In¬
equity in the organization of society.
"Too many are suffering, and the
distance is growing that separates the
progress of some and the stagnation,
not to say the regression, of others."
There is no true remedy for this
inequitable situation other than mea¬
sures increasingly urgent measures
to secure justice. This should not be
interpreted as meaning arrangements
to make bitter poverty bearable and
inequity less shocking; what is needed
is the establishment of an order which
will gradually reduce and ultimately
eliminate the causes of this inequity
and poverty. Above all, we must see
that we do not have " one group
making progress at the expense of
the other", since this betokens a radi¬
cal injustice affecting the basic struc¬
tures and conditions of social
dynamics.
But if development ¡s a work of
justice, it is also a work of peace, and
here the most elementary and the most
general interest combines with the
loftiest duty.
The weakness of the poor presents
a dangerous temptation to the greed
and the lust for domination of the
powerful. And exploitation and domi¬
nation in turn engender revolt. It
would be wrong to delude ourselves
concerning the apparent tranquility
that has followed the accession to
political Independence of so many
countries which but yesterday were
still subject to colonial rule. Deep
currents are stirring in the developing
countries as they make the bitter
discovery that the independence so
ardently desired is still relative.
This deprived section of mankind
has lost nothing of its extraordinary
capacity to endure poverty; on the
other hand, it Is less and less ready
to accept inequity precisely because
of its newly-acquired political aware¬
ness. History records many terrible
outbursts of righteous anger from the
oppressed; the world has been
shaken by similar upheavals even in
the present century.
Among the distinguished thinkers
to whom the Pope appeals to study
our troubled world, I know of some
who are asking themselves anguishing
questions about what the next decade
will bring, when overpopulation, hun¬
ger, poverty and racial antagonisms
reach their peak at the same time
and combine to form one great tragic
problem. They are increasingly aware
that development is the only way of
avoiding upheavals on a planetary
scale.
Development is alsoindirectly
but nevertheless essentially Inter¬
connected with it the best way of con¬
verting force to peaceful purposes . . .
I am quite aware that the world
conflicts of modern times have set
the most highly developed countries
in opposition and that, in many res¬
pects, these conflicts have derived
from the contradictions inherent in
development itself. But this was a
development of power, seeking con¬
stantly to possess more, and not a
development of humanity, seeking to
" be more ".
Development, as we now under¬
stand it the development which
calls for assistance to the weak within
the context of a just and rational
organization of mankind as a whole
cannot be achieved or even conceived
unless objectivity rules the mind and
brotherhood the heart, these being
the very principles of the will to
peace. And if it is true that economic
necessity will one day compel us to
choose between universal develop¬
ment and the headlong arms race, it
Is even more evident that the pro- -_
found, whole-hearted commitment of X 7
the rich and powerful nations with all *"
their resources to the work of devel¬
opment would represent, and result
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
A NEW ORDER
IN THE WORLD
(Continued)
Between this hand
learning the rudiments
of writing (right)
and mechanical
"hands" used to
handle radioactive
materials in a nuclear
research laboratory
(far right) lies the
immense gap
separating the world
of illiteracy from the
world of science.
Education alone can
assure the
implantation of
science in the
developing countries
whose economic
progress will reduce
the present imbalance
in the world's
standards of living.
Photo Unesco - D. Seymour
The human mind on the march
38
in, a general conversion of mankind
to peace.
The second point of agreement
that I should like to note is the concep¬
tion of development. We in Unesco
also believe that " in order to be
authentic, (development) must be
complete: integral, that is, it has to
promote the good of every man and
of the whole man" . . .
To proclaim the overriding need
for the integral development of what
is human is, in concrete terms, to
affirm the primacy of the individual in
the process of development, as the
subject, agent and end of that devel¬
opment.
It implies the condemnation of
technocracy, which is the cult of effi¬
ciency measured by standards that
leave the individual altogether out of
account and which, as the Encyclical
puts it so well, " can beget evils no
less redoubtable than those due to
the liberalism of yesterday". In more
general terms, it implies subjecting
economics to ethical considerations,
or rather infusing humanism into
economics so that, abandoning the
abstract for the concrete, it may lake
on new life. " Economics and tech¬
nology have no meaning except from
man whom they should serve ".
Finally and above all, it means recog¬
nizing that is to say, demonstrat¬
ing that there can be no real
development except that brought about
within himself by a man's indepen
dent efforts. " Man is only truly man
in as far as, master of his own acts
and judge of their worth, he Is author
of his own advancement", which
amounts to saying that the only true
progress is endogenous.
The requirements of practical action,
no less than the essentially humanis¬
tic mission it has to fulfil, have made
Unesco increasingly aware of these
essential truths, which clearly reveal
the significance of Unesco's particular
contribution to development. Once it
is realized that the only development
is that of man, through man and for
man, then it becomes evident that
education, science and culture are the
foundation and the culmination, the
driving force and the justifying end of
development in its essence. It has
been said that development is pri¬
marily a state of mind; we might go
further and say that development is
the human mind on the march in
history.
is preparation,
is discovery and
Education, which
science, which
explanation, culture, which is exami¬
nation and assimilation, represent the
decisive phases and aspects of this
progress of the mind. It Is for this
reason that we find them, at the most
essential level, in the gradual unfold¬
ing of development. Everything
begins with education, since no appro¬
priation, utilization or development of
nature and society is possible without
education: hence the universal priority
accorded to it.
The implantation of science is the
key operation in development; it differs
very greatly from the mere Import of
techniques which, even if it leads to
local progress generally superficial
and seldom lasting perpetuates the
economic and intellectual dependence
of the developing peoples. Finally, it is
abundantly clear that there can be no
development from within except where
scientific civilization has taken root, in
other words, where science has
ceased to be an alien magic and has
become culture.
This, then, Is the humanistic concep¬
tion of integral development which we
share. Yet perhaps the most
remarkable statement of views In the
Encyclical Is the declaration, knit¬
ting, together the whole, that there
can be no progress towards the com¬
plete development of the individual
man without the simultaneous deve¬
lopment of all men in the spirit of
solidarity. And of that, too, we In
Unesco are profoundly convinced.
Indeed, that belief is the very reason
for our existence.
It is therefore an immense source
of satisfaction and encouragement for
us that the Holy Father should lay
such stress, as he did before the
General Assembly of the United
Nations, on the necessity for a world
authority and on the urgent need, in
the meantime, to increase the resour-
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
ces, activities and prestige of the
International organizations concerned
with development.
It is very true that the efforts of
these institutions can do more than
any other form of aid to bring about,
as desired in the Encyclical, " a system
of co-operation freely undertaken, an
effective and mutual sharing, carried
out with equal dignity on either side,
for the construction of a more human
world ". Not because greater resour¬
ces are available for those efforts
as we know, that Is very far from
being the case but, first and fore¬
most, because they alone are comple¬
tely disinterested. And also because
they are better suited to the nature of
the task, which is the organization of
a new order in the world . . .
If I have drawn attention, even at
the risk of repeating the obvious, to
the main points of a fundamental har¬
mony of views on development
between the Encyclical and the ideas
on which Unesco's action and its very
existence are based, it is in no way
merely to record for history the fact
significant as it isl that a Church
now resolutely open to the world and
an intergovernmental institution which
is becoming increasingly aware of the
spiritual dimension of its intellectual
and practical undertaking have come
together in the service of man.
It is, firstly, in order to be able
to give the Sovereign Pontiff a clear
assurance that his ideas will meet
with particular understanding within
Unesco. It is also, and perhaps above
all, to convey to him my conviction
that Unesco, at its own level, and
without departing from its own princi¬
ples and methods, will spontaneously
answer his appeal with action . . .
For myself, though I cannot pre¬
judge what that action will be, I will
say that I share the anguish of the
appeal and endorse its fervour.
Yes, I believe that "the hour for
action has now sounded" and that "at
stake are the peace of the world and
the future of civilization". It is my
ardent desire that the peoples should
feel this, and governments understand
it, while there is still time.
So far as governments are con¬
cerned, would it be too much to
express the hope which I can do only
in my personal capacity that in the
near future a conference of the world's
responsible leaders may be held at
the highest level to consider the
problems of development, not separ¬
ately, sector by sector, as is usually
done, but as a whole, with a view to
finding radical overall solutions ?
I mean a conference which would
reorganize the relations between the
wealthy nations and the poor nations,
like the conferences held after great
world conflicts to reorganize the rela¬
tions between the powers, but one
more deserving than were those set¬
tlements and partitions, of the fair
name of Peace Conference, since the
object would be to forestall violence
by justice, not to repair its effects by
force after the catastrophe.
Such a conference would have to
deal, among other things, with the
Photo Unesco - Jack Ling
question of trade relations between
industrialized countries and under¬
developed countries, the present ine¬
quity of which the Holy Father has so
rightly emphasized. It could also take
steps and no doubt would quite
naturally be led to do so to strengthen
very considerably, if necessary by
rationalizing it, the system of inter¬
national organizations which can play
a decisive part in the building of a more
just and more fraternal world order.
Of course, any intergovernmental
action of this kind is possible only
If every citizen, every person feels
personally concerned by development
and takes it upon himself as a uni¬
versal task. In the developed
countries particularly, it would be a
good thing for all those holding posi¬
tions of responsibility to have had
personal experience of the nature and
methods of development, and indeed
of service in its cause. The conver¬
sion of every individual to that work
of universal salvation, development, is
the great spiritual mutation which is
essential for mankind today.
Development, as I have said, is a
state of mind. It is above all a matter
of conscience. It was very necessary
to remind the world of this.
Extracts from the speech by Mr René
Maheu, Director-General of Unesco, on the
occasion of the presentation, by Mgr Joseph
Zabkar, Permanent Observer of the Holy
See to Unesco, of a signed copy of the
Encyclical, Populorum Progressio, address¬
ed by Pope Paul VI to Mr Maheu.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
KU BOYAMA
and the Saga of
the Lucky Dragon'
by Richard Hudson
Drawings
by Ben Shahn
"Kuboyama and the Saga of the 'Lucky Dragon'" (1) recounts the story of
the crew of a Japanese fishing boat which was in the vicinity of Bikini Atoll
when the first Hydrogen Bomb was exploded on March 1, 1954. Kuboyama
was radio operator on board the "Lucky Dragon". Neither he nor his crew
mates realized the nature of the apocalyptic spectacle they had witnessed.
But the people of Japan and the entire world were soon to learn of the
fate that awaited Kuboyama.
Text and drawings ©. Reproduction prohibited
K UBOYAMA'S last jour¬
ney to sea got under way on Friday
January 22, 1954, shortly before noon,
when the Fukuryu Maru (Lucky Dra¬
gon) headed out from Yaizu.
The crew had been told they were
going south into seas near the Solo¬
mon Islands. But Fishing Master Mi-
saki and the vessel's owner, Nishi-
kawa, had decided that the Lucky Dra¬
gon would fish near Midway Island,
(1) This text is reproduced from "Kuboyama
and the Saga of the 'Lucky Dragon" by
Richard Hudson, published in New York and
London by Thomas Yoseloff and copyrighted
© 1965 by A.S. Barnes and Co., Inc., New
York (S5.95; 42¡-stg.). Mr Hudson's story is
based on an earlier book entitled "The Voya¬
ge of the 'Lucky Dragon'", by Ralph E. Lapp
(Harper and Row, New York).
over 2,500 miles to the east of Japan.
They had pored over the carefully
kept records of Japanese fishing boats
and had been favorably impressed
by the good catches of albacore, or
"American tuna" as they called them
in that area. They were reluctant to
tell the crew, however, since they
knew there would be strong objections
to fishing in those notoriously stormy
waters.
According to custom, Captain Tsut-
sui, Chief Engineer Yamamoto and
Radioman Kuboyama should all have
been consulted in selecting the fishing
grounds. Kuboyama voiced angry
doubts as to whether the Lucky Dra¬
gon was sturdy enough to withstand
the battering that she might run into
in storms around Midway. Yama-
40
moto expressed fears that his engine
might break down, which in rough seas
could be disastrous. Tsutsui objected
too, but he could not overrule his fish¬
ing master. The real boss aboard a
Japanese tuna boat is the fishing mas¬
ter. The Lucky Dragon continued on
Its course toward Midway.
Long before dawn on February 7,
some two hundred miles south-west
of Midway, Misaki climbed to the
bridge, rang the ship's bell, and order¬
ed the waiting deck hands: "Begin
to throw out the linesl"
The Lucky Dragon moved ahead at
her top speed of seven. knots. Work¬
ing under electric lights, the crewmen
laboured to pay out the line fast
enough. Other crewmen rapidly bait¬
ed big steel hooks with eight-inch-long
frozen mackerel that had been stored
in the hold since they sailed from
Yaizu. A lighted buoy attached to
one end of the long line went out first
and then, after every three hundred
yards of line, a green glass buoy with
a bamboo pole and flag on it followed.
After nineteen of the green buoys
had been dropped, a second lighted
buoy went down. Then more green
buoys, another lighted buoy and so
on. Almost four hours later the one
long line was out, extending away from
the Lucky Dragon about thirty miles.
It hung in a series of festoons about
two hundred feet below the surface,
suspended by float lines from three
On Friday, January 22, 1954, a
Japanese fishing vessel, the
"Lucky Dragon" set out from the
small port of Yaizu to fish for
tuna in the Pacific, over 2,500
miles to the east of Japan. None
of the fishermen suspected
that a terrifying experience
awaited them in the Pacific.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Kuboyama, radio
operator on the "Lucky
Dragon", was the
most popular and
shrewdest member of
the crew.
hundred buoys. More than fifteen
hundred baited hooks waited for pass¬
ing tuna with appetites.
The crewmen ate their breakfast of
rice, soup, and tea with savour, spe¬
culating on how the first throwing of
the lines would come out. Four hours
after the last buoy had been dumped
over, they began to retrace their pre¬
vious course to haul in their catch.
The fishermen watched the buoys
with intense interest as they recovered
their lines. The men worked thirteen
hours, until after midnight, before the
lines were all in. The catch totaled
fifteen fish weighing altogether only
a few hundred pounds. They had put
out more than that in bait. The crew
grumbled, blaming Misakl for bring¬
ing them to Midway rather than to the
Solomons.
IHE following day winds
caused a rough sea, so that lines could
not be thrown. The day after that, long
before daylight, the lines went out for
the second time. Two hours before
sundown it was discovered that the
main line had parted. Had the lines
become caught on coral that sometimes
juts sharply toward the surface in these
seas? Or had currents sucked the
lines into entanglements on the ocean
bottom itself? Whatever the explana¬
tion, the breaking of the main line was
a disaster. The fishermen cursed
their luck and, especially, they cursed
Misaki for bringing them here. But
their bitterness did not detract from
the diligence of their search for the
buoys that might mean recovery of
the lines.
The Lucky Dragon searched that
night and the following two days, find¬
ing only a few buoys with short lengths
of line attached. The day after that,
Misaki gave up the search. With
almost half his line lost, he called
together the captain, chief engineer,
radioman, boatswain, and chief deck-
man to determine their course of
action. They would of course continue
fishing, for they still had enough line
and fuel to make a respectable catch.
"I believe we should go north,"
Misaki said. "There are high-priced
fish there."
"This old ship could not stand the
rough seas of the north," Kuboyama
objected.
"The main bearing of the engine has
already burned out once," Yamamoto
said. "It would be very dangerous if
this should happen again In a storm
such as is common in the north."
The others sided with Kuboyama and
Yamamoto, who proposed instead that
they go south to the calmer seas of
the Marshall Islands. There should
be big-eyed tuna there, they argued.
At length Misaki agreed.
With Its fortune running true, the
Lucky Dragon turned south to avoid
storms and quickly ran into a bad
one. Engine trouble followed. But
when clear skies finally did appear,
the spirits of the crew rose and fishing
was resumed.
On March 1 a few minutes after
three o'clock in the morning Misaki
gave the order to start fishing. It
was still dark when the throwing of
the lines was completed two and a
half hours later. Misaki ordered the
engine cut, and the Lucky Dragon drift¬
ed silently in the sea.
Some of the crew were sleeping;
others were below deck preparing for
breakfast. The few who were topside
were suddenly amazed when a huge
incandescence arose on the western
horizon. Yellowish white light flash-
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
KUBOYAMA (Continued)
After running Into difficulties
while fishing near the Midway
Islands, the "Lucky Dragon"
turns south to try its luck
near 'the Marshall Islands.
The sun rises in the West !'
the fishermen exclaim
ed over the sea and against the clouds
that partially covered the sky. The
brilliance became a glaring yellow, and
then a blazing orange. The fisher¬
man watched in awe. One of them
rushed below and excitedly told his
shipmates, "The sun rises in the
westl"
"What could this be?" the men
asked each other frantically. Almost
Immediately it was suggested that
they might have witnessed a pika-don
a compound word meaning "thunder-
flash" that entered the Japanese lan¬
guage after the bombing of Hiroshima.
"But if it's a pika-don." Kuboyama
wondered, "where is the mushroom in
the sky?" True, there was no mush¬
room, and soon the great light began
to fade. Some of those who had been
sleeping, like Captain Tsutsui, found
that by the time they reached the deck
pre-dawn darkness had returned.
Just as the men were beginning to
calm down, about seven minutes after
the beginning of the flash, the Lucky
Dragon was seized with a violent shak¬
ing. A few seconds later two reports
that sounded like distant rifle shots
were heard. The sailors threw them¬
selves to the deck and covered their
heads.
42
HEN quiet returned, the
debate was resumed over the strange
occurences. Some suggested that
the U.S. Navy might be holding
gunnery practice. Others guessed
again that they must have seen a
pika-don. Shrewd Kuboyama made
a simple calculation based on the
difference in time between the sight¬
ing of the flash and the arrival of
the sound wave that shook the Lucky
Dragon. "We must be about 87 miles
away from where the flash took place,"
he said. Misaki consulted his charts.
About 85 miles away, in the direction
from which the light had come, lay
Bikini Atoll. Whatever the flash was,
It had come from Bikini.
Since the long line was still out, a
decision had to be made. Should It
be cut so the Lucky Dragon could
leave the area immediately? Many
thought so. They were afraid that If
there had been a bomb test an Ameri¬
can reconnaissance aircraft might spot
them, and the crew watched the sky
anxiously. They recalled that when a
small Japanese fishing boat had disap¬
peared without trace In fair weather
in 1952, it had been rumored that Ame¬
rican guns had sunk it. They felt sure
that the Americans would not hesitate
to provide a similar fate for the Lucky
Dragon.
Misaki consulted the officers; then
he ordered the lines hauled In. The
crew made haste to get the job done.
After they had been working about
two hours, a strange fog formed in
the sky. Then a drizzle of very small
whitish flakes began to fall on the
Lucky Dragon. The fishermen brush¬
ed them out of their eyes, noses,
mouths, hair. "It ¡s a sandstorm at
seal" exclaimed one.
Kuboyama took off his straw hat to
observe the ashlike particles. Could
they be salt? He tasted a flake. It
had no taste, nor did it have an odour.
The radioman noted that the ash had
become so thick on the deck that he
left footprints as he walked.
Leaning over his charts, Misaki con¬
sidered a sample of the ash. It had
substance. It might be volcanic; it
might be coral ... He recalled the
eruption of Krakatoa, which had spread
cinders for thousands of miles around,
But his charts showed no active volca¬
noes in the area. Captain Tsutsui, who
was steering, suggested that if the
morning's flash had been a pika-don,
then it might be coral dust that was
falling on them. Mlsaki's charts could
not confirm this either. The Lucky
Dragon was outside the restricted area
that fishing boats were not supposed to
enter. Eniwetok, which the Maritime
Safety Board had warned them about,
was three hundred miles to the west.
Could the Americans have had a bomb
test at Bikini instead?
Some of the deckhands complained
that the white dust hurt their eyes.
Nevertheless, the work went ahead,
and after six hours the line was all
in. Only nine fish were caught, seven
of them big-eyed tuna. These were
cleaned on deck, with the white ash
coming down on them steadily.
Finally the flakes stopped falling. The
Lucky Dragon headed north on its
homeward journey.
s=lEA spray and breezes
carried away most of the thin blanket
of white ash that covered the main
deck and other exposed surfaces.
But the flakes clung in corners, in cre¬
vices of the deck and hull, in the wet
lines, and in the rims of portholes.
Most of the men took baths. Kuboya¬
ma, who remained uneasy about the
mysterious dust, went below with the
others to wash himself thoroughly.
The men talked more of their poor
catch than of the white dust. They
would arrive in Yaizu when prices for
fish were high, but they would have
little to sell. This would mean hard
times for their families, and this wor¬
ried them.
Chief Engineer Yamamoto, who had
been on deck during most of the driz¬
zle of ashes, had felt nausea at lunch
timé and had not eaten. In the en¬
gine room he Jiad difficulty reading
the dials. He "took a nap to restore
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
himself, but when he awoke he felt
worse. His eyes were clogged with
a sticky discharge, and the engine
room dials were harder than ever to
read.
Other members of the crew had
similar symptoms. At dinner time
many of them complained of not being
hungry. To bolster their drooping mor¬
ale Kuboyama produced a bottle of
sake that he had hoarded for a special
treat. The men drank it, but it did not
help.
In succeeding days, the crew con¬
tinued to wonder about the "sand¬
storm", they had seen at sea. One
sailor gathered a sample of the dust
In a piece of paper and gave it to
Kuboyama. As he accepted it, the
radioman admired its whiteness "like
the coral of an atoll" and suggested
that they must have it examined after
their return to Yaizu. Kuboyama put
the packet under his pillow, where he
slept on it every night until they
reached port.
A variety of ailments befell the crew.
At first they complained of itching
skin, especially around the hands and
neck. Their faces turned a leaden
colour, darker than the robust hue of
a tropical sun tan. There were com¬
plaints of fever, nausea, loss of appe¬
tite, general weakness, diarrhoea, scalp
sores, and runny eyes. Yet none of
the crew was confined to bed for the
entire homeward voyage.
The feeling grew that they had indeed
seen a pika-don. Kuboyama read in
one of his books about the bombing
of Hiroshima to see if he could unco¬
ver a clue as to why .there was so
much illness among the crew. But at
Hiroshima all the people injured had
been within a few miles of the explo¬
sion. The Lucky Dragon was 85 miles
from Bikini on March 1, so how could
there be a connexion?
His last doubts vanished during a
talk with Boatswain Kawashima. When
Kawashlma happened to scratch the
side of his head, his hand came away
with a tuft of black hair on it. "My hair
is falling outl" he exclaimed. The
sailors were amused. Kuboyama
playfully snatched at Kawashlma's
head, and he too pulled off a wad of
hair. Before long the clutches of his
companions had shorn Kawashima of
most of the hair on the left side of
his head.
Kuboyama soon found out that
others of the crew also had falling
hair. . Then he recalled that loss of
hair was one of the symptoms of
"atomic bomb disease" after the
attacks of Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
He wondered if somehow the strange
ash had caused the men to be hurt
by radioactivity. He sought out Mi¬
saki to discuss his thoughts. They
agreed that the men should go to the
hospital immediately after landing.
0 N Sunday, March 14, after
fifty-one days at sea, the Lucky Dragon
drew into her home port of Yaizu. The
owner, Nishikawa, and a few others
were on the pier to meet her. Nishi¬
kawa was much more disturbed by the
sickness of the crew than by the small
catch and the loss of line. He was
shocked by the muddy colour of their
faces.
Kuboyama did not follow his own
advice. Instead of going to the hos¬
pital he first dropped off some wireless
equipment at a friend's house and then
he continued home. He held a towel
around his face so that people would
not stare at him because of his strange
pigmentation. For the same reason he
entered his own home by the back
door.
"Daddy's homel" called out one of
his three daughters. As he embraced
his wife and children, Miyako, his
oldest daughter, said with surprise in
her voice, "How black Daddy is. He
looks like a Negro."
After a while the children went out-
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
The fishermen recover their lines
suspended 200 feet below the
surface by float lines from
300 buoys. On about 30 miles
of line with 1,500 hook» they
caught only 15 tuna.
Drawings © A.S. Barnes
and Co., Inc., New York
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
KUBOYAMA (Continued)
At 3 a.m. on March 1,
1964, the crew of the
"Lucky Dragon" saw
an Immense fiery light
on the western horizon.
One man suggested it
might be a "pika don"
(thunderflash), as the
Japanese call an atomic
explosion. The ship
was only 85 miles
from Bikini Atoll.
The port
of
'crying fish'
44
side to play, and then Kuboyama told
his wife about the atomic explosion
they had seen and the white ash that
had fallen on them. "Don't worry,"
he said, "I will be all right." In a while
he left, saying he was going to the
doctor. But instead he returned to
the Lucky Dragon, where he made
some repairs to his wireless.
Some of the crew did go to the hos¬
pital. The doctor, who did not have
a Geiger counter, told the fishermen
they had no serious trouble. But
Misaki urged that two of the men be
sent to Tokyo to see an expert on
atomic sickness. The doctor In charge
reluctantly agreed to write a letter of
introduction to such an expert for
them.
The pair caught an early train the
following day to Tokyo. In the hospi¬
tal the doctors were startled when they
held a Geiger counter to one of the
fishermen's heads; it clicked loudly,
showing he was radioactive. They
decided to go to Yaizu to see the rest
of the fishermen.
Since the small port of Yaizu did
not have its own daily newspaper, it
was two days before the Yomiuri
Shimbun In Tokyo learned of the Lucky
Dragon story and broke it in front-page
banner headlines. It quickly spread
around the world. Reporters and pho¬
tographers flocked to Yaizu. When
scientists arrived they held their Gei¬
ger counters over the deck of the
Lucky Dragon and were astounded at
the fierce rattling sound. Fear struck
the crew members when Geiger coun¬
ters held near their heads chattered
ominously. Within a few days all
twenty-three fishermen had been mov¬
ed to two hospitals in Tokyo.
One scientist as soon as he read
the story, took his Geiger counter to
the marketplace at Osaka. He tested
various tuna and found only normal
radioactivity about twenty counts per
minute. But then he checked one from
Yaizu that caused his Geiger counter
to emit two thousand clicks per minute.
It made such a noise that bystanders
gasped. "The fish are crying!" From
then on, the contaminated fish were
known as "crying fish."
Since fish is a staple of the Japa¬
nese diet, the "crying fish" caused a
panic in the markets of the country.
Prices slumped as housewives refus¬
ed to buy fish. The Misaki market
shut its doors on March 19; the Yoko¬
hama market was next; then the Tokyo
Central Wholesale Market closed for
the first time since the cholera epi¬
demic of 1935. Shopkeepers posted
signs stating: OUR FISH ARE NOT
RADIOACTIVE. Customers were not
convinced.
The attention of the nation focused
on the twenty-three hospitalized
fishermen. Their white cell counts fell
alarmingly. The normal count is from
five thousand to nine thousand cells
per cubic millimeter. After several
weeks the counts of the Lucky Dragon
crew fell below four thousand; in two
cases it went as low as eight hundred
and a thousand. By May the men
were also sterile.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Toward the end of June more than
two-thirds of the crew including Kubo¬
yama came down with jaundice. Ku-
boyama's recovery was slower than
the rest but by August 5 he felt well
enough to be the crew's spokesman
at a press conference. Then the
radioman's condition took a turn for
the worse. On September 1 he told
his wife, "It's no use any more. My
sufferings are too great."
Kuboyama slipped into unconscious¬
ness, and was put on the critical list.
He rallied several days later to the
point where he could eat and recognize
his friends. But on September 20 he
was again in critical condition, although
fully conscious. He said, "My body
feels like it is being burned with elec¬
tricity. Under my body there must be
a high tension wire."
The family again gathered at his bed¬
side. "I will get well," he told his
mother. "Promise me so," she said,
and he replied, "Yes, I will hold out."
It was late in the afternoon of Septem¬
ber 23 when Kuboyama began his last
fight for life. His family, his fellow
fishermen and his doctor were with
him as he fought.
Shortly before seven o'clock that
evening, the doctor examined "Kuboya¬
ma with his stethoscope. He turned
to the family and said quietly, "It is
his last moment." The doctor buried
his face in his hands and sobbed.
"Alkichi, you break your promise!"
his mother cried. Kuboyama was silent.
His eyes opened and his face stared
vacantly. Kuboyama's wife touched a
tiny cup of water the symbol of a last
earthly drink to his lips. Kuboya¬
ma was dead.
Everyone present including the
fishermen who had so loved him wept
without restraint. The crowd that had
gathered outside the hospital to pray
for the fisherman was told of his death.
Moments later the news was flashed
by radio and television. Throughout
the night messages of sympathy
including many from ships thousands
of miles at sea, arrived at the hospital.
The following day the American am¬
bassador sent a letter of condolence
with a check for a million yen to
Mrs. Kuboyama.
Kuboyama's body was cremated and
his ashes placed in an urn. His widow,
dressed in the traditional black
kimono with the family crest, carried
the urn in the funeral procession in
Yaizu. His eldest daughter clutched
a wooden mortuary tablet on which
were inscribed the words, "The soul
of the deceased Aikichi Kuboyama"
while his second girl carried a photo¬
graph of her father. At the end of
the ceremony two hundred university
students sang "A-Bomb Never For¬
given" and a score of white pigeons
were released In the air. Then the
urn was placed In a marble vault In
the mountainside above Kuboyama's
native Yaizu where It remains today.
Why did Kuboyama die?
Fatalists will say that Kuboyama was
on a collision course with death and
All over Japan people waited
anxiously for news of the
23 crew members of the
"Lucky Dragon" who had
been hospitalized suffering
from radiation poisoning.
Drawings © A.S. Barnes
and Co., Inc., New York
On September 1, Kuboyama told his
wife: "It's no use any more. My
sufferings are too great."
that there was nothing he could do
about it. Is the world likewise on a
collision course with death ? Are we
sailing our ships of state into waters
upon which death will rain from the
sky? There have always been wars
and we have changed nothing so as to
make war impossible; therefore it is
logical that there should be a war. A
war In which most or all of us will
perish.
Or can we reject fatalism and deter¬
mine our own destiny? Can we un¬
derstand the historical forces that
threaten us and bend them to our will?
Can we smash down these weapons
that have grown too terrible for man
to endure? Can we build a world
order in which the hostilities among
men and nations will be dealt with
through law not force? Can men of
all colours, religions, economic sys¬
tems and ideologies live together on
this planet without engaging in mass
murder?
These are the questions that face
us as a society and that face each of
us as individuals. Are we as helpless
before them as was Kuboyama? If the
answer is Yes, then the radioman will
have been the first of many millions of
victims of the thermonuclear age. But
if the answer is No, then we may be
able to count him as the last victim.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
MAN DOES NOT LIVE
BY POLITICS ALONE
by Jawaharlal Nehru
ft
46
THE MAN WITH THE ROSE. India's
distinguished statesman, Jawahar/a) Nehru
(1889-1964) played a leading role in the
work of the United Nations and in meetings
between nations. The rose that he usually
wore in his buttonhole remains a symbol
of his faith in a universal humanism which
inspired all his efforts ' for peace and
for the accession of his country to modern
life. "Man does not I1.3 by politics alone."
he said at Unesco's General Conference at
New Delhi, in 1956. Visiting Unesco in
1962, two years befe: his death, Jawa¬
harlal Nehru declared nnt 'ode the spirit
of tolerance is j.-'Oie .it'"<¿S£/v :'un ever
before. "Science and technology are ne¬
cessary," he said, "but a spiritual back¬
ground no less so." In September 1966,
Unesco and the Government Of India jointly
organized a round table on the role of
Jawaharlal Nehru in the modern world.
Earlier this year a Nehru Memorial Exhibi¬
tion was held in Unesco House, Paris. On
these pages we publish major passages
from an address that Jawaharlal Nehru
delivered at the inauguration of the Indian
Council for Cultural Relations in New
Delhi on April 9, 1950.
IATIONS, individuals and
groups talk of understanding one
another and it seems an obvious
thing that people should try to
understand one another and to learn
from one another. Yet, when I look
through the pages of history or study
current events I sometimes find that
people who know one another most,
quarrel most. Countries which are
next door to one another in Europe
or in Asia somehow seem to rub one
another up the wrong way, though
they know one another very thoroughly.
Thus knowledge, by itself, does not
lead to greater co-operation or friend¬
ship.
This is not a new thing. Even the
long pages of history show that. Has
there been something wrong in indi¬
vidual nations or in the approach to
this question? Or is it something else
that has not worked as it should have
done? When we talk of cultural rela¬
tions, the question that immediately
arises in my mind is what exactly is
the "culture" that people talk so much
about?
When I was younger in years, I
remember reading about German "kul-
tur" and of the attempts of the German
people to spread It by conquest and
other means. There was a big war to
spread this "kultur" and to resist it.
Every country and every individual
seems to have its peculiar idea of
cult ire.
When there is tal)< about cultural
relations although it is very good in
theory what actually happens is that
those peculiar ideas come into conflict
and instead of leading to friendship
they lead to more estrangement. It is
a basic question what is culture?
And I am certainly not competent to
give you a definition of it because
I have not found one.
One can see each nation and each
separate civilization developing its own
culture that had its roots in generations
hundreds and thousands of years ago.
One sees these nations being intima¬
tely moulded by the impulse that
initially starts a civilization going on
its long path. That conception Is
affected by other conceptions and one
sees action and interaction between
these varying conceptions.
There is, I suppose, no culture in the
world which is absolutely pristine,
pure and unaffected by any other
culture. It simply cannot be, just as
nobody can say that he belongs one
hundred per cent to a particular racial
type, because in the course of hun¬
dreds and thousands of years un¬
mistakable changes and mixtures have
occurred.
So culture is bound to get a little
mixed up, even though the basic
element of a particular national culture
remains dominant. If that kind of thing
goes on peacefully, there is no harm
in it. But it often leads to conflicts.
It sometimes leads a group to fear
that their culture is being overwhelmed
by what they consider to be an outside
or alien influence. Then they draw
themselves into a shell which isolates
them and prevents their thoughts and
ideas going out. That is an unhealthy
situation, because in any matter, and
much more so in what might be called
a cultural matter, stagnation is the
worst possible thing.
Culture, if it has any value, must
have a certain depth. It must also
have a certain dynamic character.
After all, culture depends on a vast
number of factors. If we leave out
what might be called the basic mould
that was given to it In the early stages
of a nation's or a people's growth, It
is affected by geography, by climate
and by all kinds of other factors. The
culture of Arabia is intimately governed
by the geography and the deserts of
Arabia because it grew up there. The
culture of India is influenced obviously,
as we see In our own literature, by
the Himalayas, the forests and the
great rivers of India among other
things. It was a natural growth from
the soil.
Of the various domains of culture
like architecture, music and literature
any two may mix together, as they
CONTINUED ON PAGE 48
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Learning more about a
civilization's historic past makes
for easier understanding of its
present characteristics. Art,
like literature, is a major road of
communication between cultures.
This visitor to the Museum of
Teheran appears to be in earnest
conversation with the statue of a
human-headed bull, 2,500 years
old, that once crowned a pillar
in the city of Persepolis.
Photo Unesco - Dominique Roger
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
NOT BY POLITICS ALONE (Continued)
often did, and produce a happy
combination. But where there is an
attempt to improve something or the
other which does not naturally grow
and mould itself without uprooting
itself, conflict inevitably arises. Then
also comes something which to my
mind is basically opposed to all ideas
of culture. And that is the isolation of
the mind and the deliberate shutting
up of the mind to other influences.
My own view of India's history is
that we can almost measure the growth
and the advance of India and the
decline of India by relating them to
periods when India had her mind open
to the outside world and when she
wanted to close it up. The more she
closed it up, the more static she
whether of the in-
nation or society, is
dynamic, changing,
Whatever stops that
also injures it and
became. Life,
dividual, group,
essentially a
growing thing,
dynamic growth
undermines it.
We have had great religions and
they have had an enormous effect on
humanity. Yet, if I may say so with
all respect and without meaning any
ill to any person, those very religions,
in the measure that they made the
mind of man static, dogmatic and
bigoted, have had, to my mind, an evil
effect. The things they said may be
good but when it is claimed that the
last word has been said, society
becomes static.
The individual human being or race
or nation must necessarily have a
certain depth and certain roots some¬
where. They do not count for much
unless they have roots In the past,
which past is, after all, the accumu¬
lation of generations of experience and
some type of wisdom. It is essential
that you have that. Otherwise you
become just pale copies of something
which has no real meaning to you as
an individual or as a group.
On the other hand, one cannot live
In roots alone. Even roots wither
unless they come out in the sun and
the free air. Only then can the roots
give you sustenance. Only then can
there be a branching out and a
flowering. How, then, are you to
balance these two essential factors?
It is very difficult, because some
people think a great deal about the
flowers and the leaves on the
branches, forgetting that they only
flourish because there is a stout root
to sustain them. Others think so
much of the roots that no flowers or
leaves or branches are left: there Is
only a thick stem somewhere. So, the
question is how one is to achieve a
balance.
Does culture mean some inner
growth in the man? Of course, it must.
Does it mean the way he behaves to
others? Certainly it must. Does it
mean the capacity to understand the
other person? I suppose so. Does it
mean the capacity to make yourself
understood by the other person? I
suppose so. It means all that.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 50
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
A project to build an international
city of peace and harmony for men
and women of all countries,
irrespective of creed, ideology or
nationality is now being planned in India.
Named Auroville, after the Indian spiri¬
tual leader and philosopher, Sri Auro-
bindo, who died in 1950, it would be
built near Pondicherry on the Bay of
Bengal. Designed to house a community
of 50,000 people, it would seek to
foster the ideals and teachings by
which Sri Aurobindo sought to con¬
tribute to international understanding
and the promotion of peace. As shown
in these photos of a model of the pro¬
ject, Auroville would be concentric in
shape and its main streets, converging
towards the heart of the city (above
and left), would meet at a Park of
Unity, in which a Sanctuary of Truth
would dominate the city from a crown
of gardens (right, rear of photo). Four
zones residential, international, cultural
and industrial would be built over the
next 15 to 20 years. In the International
Zone pavilions of all nations and of the
Indian states would serve as embassies
of the culture, arts and handicrafts of
each country. In the zone designed
to illustrate the cultural wealth of each
civilization, Academies of Arts and
Science would welcome artists and
scientists from all parts of the world.
The proposal to build Auroville was
made in connexion with the commemo¬
ration of Unesco's 20th anniversary in
1966 when the idea was applauded
by Unesco's General Conference.
AUROVILLE:
INDIA'S
INTERNATIONAL
CITY OF CONCORD
Photos © Edouard Rousseau, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
*
NOT BY POLITICS ALONE (Continued)
What is a scientific approach to life's problems?
It is one of seeking truth
by trial and error and experiment
50
A person who cannot understand
another's viewpoint is to that extent
limited in mind and culture, because
nobody, perhaps barring some very
extraordinary human beings, can pre¬
sume to have the fullest knowledge
and wisdom. The other party or the
other group may also have some
inkling of knowledge or wisdom or
truth, and, If we shut our minds to
that, then we not only deprive
ourselves of it but we cultivate an
attitude of mind which, I would say, is
opposed to that of a cultured man.
The cultured mind should have the
capacity to understand another view¬
point fully even though it cannot always
agree with it. The question of agree¬
ment or disagreement only arises when
you understand a thing. Otherwise it
is blind negation which is not a cul¬
tured approach to any question.
I should like to use another word
science. What is a scientific approach
to life's problems? I suppose It is
one of examining everything, of
seeking truth* by trial and error and
by experiment, of never saying that
this must be so, but trying to
understand why it is so and, if one
is convinced of it, of accepting it,
of having the capacity to change one's
notions the moment some other proof
is forthcoming, of having an open
mind which tries to imbibe the truth
wherever it is found. If that is culture,
how far is it represented in the modern
world and In the nations of today?
Obviously, if it was represented more
than it is, many of our problems,
national and international, would be
far easier to solve.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Photo © G. Bern
- Rune Hassner
Symbol of the
spread of today's
technological
civilization,
a visiting
automobile excites
the interest of an
African village child.
Civilizations,
cultures and ways
of life today mingle
as never before.
And problems
created by their
Interpénétration are
increasingly giving
way to the desire
for mutual
understanding.
Almost every country in the world
believes that it has some special
dispensation from Providence, that it
is of the chosen people or race and
that others, whether they are good or
bad, are somewhat inferior creatures.
It is extraordinary how this kind of
feeling persists in all nations of the
East as well as of the West without
exception. The nations of the East
are strongly entrenched in their own
ideas and convictions and sometimes
in their own sense of superiority about
certain matters.
Anyhow, in the course of the last
two or three hundred years, they have
received many knocks on the head
and they have been humiliated, they
have been debased and they have
been exploited. And so, in spite of
their feeling that they were superior
in many ways, they were forced to
admit that they could be knocked about
and exploited. To some extent, this
brought a sense of realism to them.
There was also an attempt to escape
from reality by saying that it was said
that we were not so advanced in
material and technical things but that
these were after all superficial things,
but nevertheless, we were superior in
essential things, in spiritual things, in
moral values. I have no doubt that
spiritual things and moral values are
ultimately more important than other
things, but the way one finds escape
in the thought that one is spiritually
superior, simply because one is inferior
in a material and physical sense, is
surprising. It does not follow by any
means. It is an escape from facing
up to the causes of one's degradation.
Nationalism, of course, is a curious
phenomenon which at a certain stage
in a country's history gives life, growth,
strength, and unity, but at the same
time, it has a tendency to limit one,
because one thinks of one's country
as something different from the rest
of the world. The perspective changes
and one is continuously thinking of
one's own struggles and virtues and
failings to the exclusion of other
thoughts.
The result is that the same nation¬
alism, which is the symbol of growth
for a people, becomes a symbol of the
cessation of that growth in the mind.
Nationalism, when it becomes success¬
ful, sometimes goes on spreading in
an aggressive way and becomes a
danger Internationally.
Whatever line of thought you follow,
you arrive at the conclusion that some
kind of balance must be found. Other¬
wise something that was good can turn
into evil. Culture, which is essentially
good, becomes not only static but
aggressive and something that breeds
conflict and hatred when looked at
from a wrong point of view. How you
are to find a balance I do not know.
Apart from the political and economic
problems of the age, perhaps, that
is the greatest problem today, because
behind it there is a tremendous conflict
in the spirit of man and a tremendous
search for something It cannot find.
We turn to economic theories
because they have an undoubted
importance. It Is folly to talk of culture
or even of God when human beings
starve and die. Before one can talk
about anything else one must provide
the normal essentials of life to human
beings. That is where economics
comes in. Human beings today are
not in the mood to tolerate this
suffering and starvation and inequality
when they see that the burden is not
equally shared. Others profit while
they themselves only bear the burden.
We have inevitably to deal with these
problems in economic and other ways
but I do think that behind it all there
is a tremendous psychological problem
in the minds of the people. It may
be that some people think about it
consciously and deliberately and
others rather unconsciously and dimly,
but that this conflict exists in the
spirit of man today is certain. How
it will be resolved I do not know.
One thing that troubles me is this:
people who understand one another
more and more begin often enough to
quarrel more and more. Nevertheless,
it does not follow from this that we
should not try to understand and that
is something which really cannot be
done in the context of the modern
world. Therefore, it becomes essential
that we try to understand one another
in the right way. The right way is
important. The right approach, the
friendly approach, is important, be¬
cause a friendly approach brings a
friendly response.
I have not the shadow of a doubt
that it is a fundamental rule of human
life that, if the approach is good, the
response is good. If the approach Is
bad, the response is likely to be bad,
too. So, If we approach our fellow
human beings or countries in a friendly
way with our minds and hearts open
and prepared to accept whatever good
comes to them and that does not
mean surrendering something that we
consider of essential value to truth or
to our genius then we shall be led
not only towards understanding but
the right type of understanding.
So I shall leave you to determine
what culture and wisdom really are.
We grow in learning, in knowledge and
In experience, till we have such an
enormous accumulation of them that it
becomes impossible to know exactly
where we stand. We are over¬
whelmed by all this and, at the same
time, somehow or other we have a
feeling that all these put together do
not necessarily represent a growth in
the wisdom of the human race.
I have a feeling that perhaps some
people who did not have all the
advantages of modern life and modern
science were essentially wiser than
most of us are. Whether or not we
shall be able in later times to combine
all this knowledge, scientific growth
and betterment of the human species
with true wisdom, I do not know. It
is a race between various forces.
I am reminded of the saying of a
very wise man who was a famous
Greek poet :
What else Is Wisdom ? What of man's
[endeavour or
God's high grace, so lovely and so
[great ?
To stand from fear set free, to breathe
[and wait,
To hold a hand uplifted over Hate,
And shall not Loveliness be loved for
[ever ?
(from Euripides' "Bacchae").
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
TISTOU
of the green fingers
by Maurice Druon
of the Académie Française Drawings by Jacqueline Duhème
In "Tistou of the Green Fingers", the French author, Maurice Druon,
has written a story for children and grown-ups alike of enchanting origin¬
ality. Tistou discovers that he has green fingers. Seeds blown by the
wind, lying fallow in crannies and crevices blossom at his touch. Tistou
uses his green thumbs in mysterious and astonishing ways to abolish
slums, make the animals in the zoo happy and cure the sick. In the
passages we present below from this charming yet profound tale, Tistou
uses his remarkable gift to put an end to war.
Text and illustrations ©
Reproduction prohibited
52
|T sometimes happens that,
when grown-ups raise their voices,
little boys do not listen.
" Do you hear what I'm saying,
Tistou ? "
And Tistou would nod his head,
saying, " Yes, yes " in order to seem
obedient, though he had not heard a
single word.
But as soon as grown-ups lower
their voices and start talking secrets,
little boys at once listen as hard as
they can and try to understand what
was not meant for their ears. All little
boys are alike in this, and Tistou was
no exception.
For some days past, there had been
a good deal of whispering in Bright-
bourne. There were secrets in the air,
the very carpets of the Shining House
were redolent of them.
Mr. Father and Mrs. Mother sighed
deeply as they read the newspapers.
Carolus, the manservant, and
Mrs. Amelia, the cook, gossiped in
undertones at the washinq-machine.
Even Mr. Turnbull seemed to have lost
his trumpeting voice.
MAURICE DRUON, the French novelist,
was born in Paris in 1918. His numerous
works include plays, essays and novels.
His books have been translated into many
languages. Among the best known are:
"Les Grandes Families" ("The Curtain
Falls", Hart-Davis, London, and Scribner,
New York, 1959); "Les Rois Maudits"
("The Accursed Kings", a historical group
of several volumes; Hart-Davis, London and
Scribner, New York, 1956); "Les Mémoires
de Zeus" ("The Memoirs of Zeus", Hart-
Davis, London and Scribner, New York,
1964). "Tistou of the Green Fingers" has
been translated into 1 1 languages. Mau¬
rice Drouon was elected to the Académie
Française in 1966.
"As they read the newspapers,
Tistou caught words of ill omen:
'tension'... 'crisis'... The next day
another word was on everyone's
lips: 'war'."
Tistou caught words of ill-omen on
the wing.
"Tension..." said Mr. Father, his
voice grave.
"Crisis..." replied Mrs. Mother.
" Worsening... " added Mr. Turnbull.
Tistou thought they were talking of
illness ; he was very concerned and
went off, his fingers at the ready, to
find out which member of the house¬
hold could be ill.
A turn In the garden proved to him
that he was wrong: Whiskers was in
perfect health, the thorough-bred
roans were gambolling in the field,
Gymnast showed every sign of being
in perfect condition.
But the next day another word was
on everyone's lips.
" War... it was inevitable, " said
Mr. Father.
" War... poor people I " said
Mrs. Mother, sorrowfully shaking her
head.
"War... and there we arel Just
another one, " said Mr. Turnbull. " It
only remains to be seen who'll win. "
" War... how terrible I Shall we
never have done with them? " groaned
Mrs. Amelia, on the point of tears.
"War... war... always wars", repeat¬
ed Carolus, the manservant.
Tistou thought of war as something
improper since people spoke about it
with lowered voices, as something
ugly, a grown-up disease worse than
drunkenness, crueller than poverty,
more dangerous than crime. Mr.
Turnbull had already mentioned war
to him and shown him the Bright-
bourne War Memorial. But since
Mr. Turnbull had spoken rather loudly,
Tistou had not properly understood
him.
Tistou was not afraid. There was
nothing of the coward about the boy;
in certain respects he might indeed
have been thought rash. You have
already seen how he used to slide
down the banisters. When he went
to the river to bathe, he had to be
stopped diving off the champions' high
dive ten times in succession. He would
take a run and launch himself Into
the air, his arms widespread, in a
swallowdive.
But his Idea of war had nothing
to do with courage or fear. He
merely found the Idea intolerable, that
was all.
He wanted information. Was war
really as horrible as he imagined it
to be ? Obviously, the first person
to consult was Whiskers.
" I hope I'm not interrupting you,
Mr. Whiskers," he said to the gard¬
ener, who was clipping a box hedge.
Whiskers put down his shears.
" Not at all, not at all, my boy. "
" Mr. Whiskers, tell me, what do
you think about war?"
The gardener looked surprised.
."I'm against it," he replied, tugging
at his whiskers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
"Have you actually seen gardens annihilated by war?",
asked Tistou. "Yes", replied Mr. Whiskers, "I've seen
a garden full of flowers die in two minutes."
" Why are you against it ? "
" Because... because even a little,
unimportant war can annihilate a very
big garden. "
" Annihilate, what does that mean ? "
" It means destroy, abolish, reduce
to dust. "
" Really ? And have you actually
seen gardens... annihilated by war,
Mr. Whiskers ? " asked Tistou.
It seemed barely credible. But the
gardener was not joking. He stood
with bent head, his thick white eye¬
brows contracted in a frown, twisting
his whiskers in his fingers.
" Yes, yes, I've seen it happen, "
he replied. " I've seen a garden full
of flowers die in two minutes. I saw
the greenhouses smashed into a
thousand pieces. So many bombs
fell in that garden that It was no use
ever thinking of cultivating it again.
Even the earth was dead. "
Tistou felt his throat contract.
" And whose garden was it ? " he
asked.
" It was mine, " said Whiskers,
turning away to hide his grief, and
picking up his shears.
Tistou was silent for a moment. He
was thinking. He was trying to imagine
the garden about him destroyed as
Whiskers's garden had been, the
greenhouses broken and the earth
barren of flowers. Tears came to his
eyes.
"Well, I shall go and tell everyone
about it I " he cried. " Everyone
must know. I shall tell Amelia and I
shall tell Carolus... "
" Oh, Carolus is worse off than I
am. He lost his country. "
"His country? He lost his country
in a war? How Is that possible?"
" Well, it's what happened. His
country has completely disappeared.
He could never find it again. That's
why he's here. "
" I was quite right In thinking that
war is a horrible thing, if you can lose
your country in it like you lose a hand¬
kerchief, " Tistou thought.
" There's even worse than that, "
Whiskers added. " You mentioned
Amelia, the cook. Well, Amelia lost
her son. Others have lost arms or
legs, or their heads even. Everyone
loses something in a war. "
It occurred to Tistou that war was
the greatest and most horrible disor¬
der that could happen In the world,
since everyone lost in it what they
loved best.
" What can be done to prevent its
happening?..." he wondered.
Mr. Turnbull must be against war,
since he hates disorder so much. I
shall talk to him about it to-morrow. "
Mr. Turnbull was sitting behind his
desk. He had recovered his trumpet¬
like voice and was shouting Into three
telephones at the same time. It was
clear that Mr. Turnbull was a very
busy man.
" It's always the same when a war
breaks out somewhere in the world, "
he said to Tistou. " Our work at
Brightbourne is doubled at once. "
And, Indeed, Tistou had noticed that
morning that the factory siren had
blown for twice the usual length
of time and that twice the usual
number of workers had appeared. The
nine chimneys were making so much
smoke that the whole sky was
darkened.
" I'll come back when you're not so
busy, " said Tistou.
" What did you want to ask me ? "
" I wanted to know where this war
has broken out. "
Mr. Turnbull rose to his feet and
led Tistou to an enormous globe of the
world. He turned It round and placed
his finger on the centre of it.
" Do you see this desert ? " he
asked. " Well, it's there. "
Under Mr. Tumbull's finger Tistou
saw a pink, lozenge-shaped expanse.
" Why has the war happened there,
Mr. Turnbull?"
"It's not very difficult to under¬
stand."
When Mr Turnbull said something
was not very difficult to understand,
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
"Mr. Whiskers, what do you think
about war," asked Tistou. "I'm
against it," replied the gardener.
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
TISTOU (Continued)
54
Tistou's heart sank ; it was generally
very complicated indeed. But this
time Tistou was determined to listen
attentively.
" Not at all difficult, " repeated
Mr. Turnbull. " This desert belongs
to nobody... "
" To nobody, " Tistou repeated to
himself.
" ... But on the right is the country
of the Go-Its, and on the left the
country of the Get-outs. "
" Go-its... Get-outs..." Tistou repeat¬
ed to himself once more; he was
really being very attentive.
" ... Well, some time ago the Go-its
announced that they wanted this
desert ; the Get-outs replied that they
wanted it too. The Go-its sent a
telegram to the Get-outs telling them
to go away. The Get-outs replied by
radio that they forbade the Go-its to
remain in occupation; so now their
armies are on the march and when
they meet there'll be a battle. "
" What is there in that pink lozen¬
ge... I mean in that desert?"
" Nothing at all. Stones... "
" So they're just going to fight for
stones ? "
" They want to own what's under¬
neath. "
"What's under the desert?"
"Oil."
"What do they want oil for?"
" They want it so that the others
can't have it. They want oil, because
oil's an essential material for making
war. "
Tistou had known that Mr. Turnbull's
explanations would become very
difficult to understand.
He shut his eyes In order to think
better.
" If I've understood properly, the
Go-its and the Get-outs are going to
fight a war for oil because oil is an
essential material for fighting wars. "
He reopened his eyes.
Tistou has a lesson in geography,
followed by a lesson in business;
the conflict between the Go-its and the
Get-outs spreads in an unforseen manner
"Well, It's stupid," he said.
Mr. Turnbull's ears turned scarlet.
" Do you want to get O for your
lesson, Tistou ? "
" No, " replied Tistou, " but what I
do want is that the Go-its and the
Get-outs should not fight."
This proof of goodheartedness for
the moment ameliorated Mr. Turnbull's
anger.
" Of course, of course, " he said,
shrugging his shoulders. " No one
wants war, ever. But it has always
existed... "
" What can I do ? " wondered Tis¬
tou. " Put my fingers on the pink
lozenge ? "
" Is the desert far away ? " he
asked.
" Half-way between here and the
other side of the world. "
" So the war can't spread as far as
Brightbourne ? "
"It's not impossible. Once a war's
begun, one can never tell where it
will end. The Go-its may call a Great
Power to their assistance, the Get-outs
ask help of another. And the two
Great Powers will fight. It's what's
called an extension of the conflict. "
Tistou's head was positively buzzing.
" Yes ", he said to himself. " War's
really like some appalling sort of
couch-grass growing on the face of
the globe. What plants can I use to
fight it with?"
" We'll now go to the factory, "
said Mr. Turnbull. " You'll see it
working to capacity ; it'll be an Instruc¬
tive lesson for you. "
He shouted some orders into his
three telephones and then accompa¬
nied Tistou downstairs.
Tistou was at first deafened by the
noise. The steam-hammers were
banging away with all their might, the
machines were humming like a million
spinning-tops, chains were clanging ;
one had to shout to make oneself
heard, even with a voice like Mr. Turn-
bull's.
Tistou was blinded by the fountains
of sparks rising on all sides; molten
"The armaments
were being
packed up with
as much care as if
they had been
china."
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
steel gushing down to the floor like
huge burning brooks; the heat was
appalling, the workmen seemed small
and black against the huge back¬
ground of the factory.
After the foundry, Tistou visited the
burnishing, turning and fitting depart¬
ments, the departments where rifles,
machine-guns, tanks and trucks were
made, for Mr. Father's factory made
everything required for making war in
the way of arms and munitions.
The following day was the day for
despatching and the armaments were
being packed up with as much care
as if they been china.
Finally, Mr. Turnbull showed Tistou
two huge guns, as long as cathedral
spires. They were as bright and
gleaming as if they had been covered
with butter.
Suspended on chains, the guns
moved slowly through the air ; then
they were lowered gently, gently, on to
truck-trailers which were so long you
couldn't see the end of them.
"Those are the guns which have
brought wealth to Brightbourne, Tis¬
tou, " said Mr. Turnbull proudly. " With
every shell they fire they can destroy
four homes as big as yours "
This information did not appear to
impress Tistou with a similar pride.
" So, " he thought, " each time one
of these guns fires, there'll be four
Tistous without a home, four Caroluses
without a staircase, and four Amelias
without a kitchen... Those must be
the things by which people lose their
gardens, their countries, their legs or
members of their families... Well,
really I "
And the hammers were pounding
and the furnaces glowing white hot.
" Whose side are you on, Mr. Turn-
bull ? " Tistou asked, shouting at the
top of his voice because of the
appalling din.
"What's that?"
" I said: whose side are you on in
this war?"
" Oh, the Go-its, " Mr. Turnbull
shouted back.
"And my father?"
" He is, too. "
" Why ? "
" Because they've been our loyal
friends for a long while. "
" Of course, " thought Tistou, " if
one's friends are attacked it's quite
right to help them defend themselves. "
" So those guns are going to the
Go-its ? " he went on.
" Only the one on the right," shout
ed Mr. Turnbull. "The other's for
the Get-outs. "
" How do you mean, for the Get-
outs ? " cried Tistou Indignantly.
" Because they're good customers,
too. "
So one Brightbourne gun would be
firing against another Brightbourne
gun, and a garden would be destroyed
on each side I
" That's business, " Mr. Turnbull
added.
"Well, I think your business is
horrible I "
"What's that?" asked Mr. Turn-
bull, lowering his head because the
noise of the steam-hammers drowned
Tistou's voice.
" I said that your business is hor¬
rible, because... "
A terrific box on the ear stopped
him short. The conflict between the
Go-its and the Get-outs had been
suddenly extended to Tistou's ear.
" That's what war's like I You ask
for an explanation, you give your opi¬
nion and what happens ? You get
a box on the earl I Supposing I made
some holly grow In your trousers,
what would you say then ? " thought
Tistou, as he gazed at Mr. Turnbull
with his eyes full of tears. " That's
it, holly in his trousers, or perhaps
thistles... I "
He clasped his fingers together...
And it was then that the idea, the
great idea, came to him.
The business lesson, as you can
well imagine, tame to an end there.
Tistou got two Os, and Mr. Turnbull
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
TISTOU (Continued)
Surprising pieces of news
follow hard upon each other
reported him at once to Mr. Father.
The latter was extremely disappointed.
His Tistou, who was one day to suc¬
ceed him and become the master of
Brightbourne, was really showing very
little propensity for controlling so
splendid a business.
" I shall really have to talk to him
very seriously, " said Mr. Father.
"Where Is he?"
" He's gone to take refuge with the
gardener, as usual, " replied Mr. Turn-
bull.
" Very well, we'll see about that
later. At the moment we must finish
the packing. "
Because of the urgent orders, the
factory was working without stopping.
All night long, the nine chimneys wore
great, red, glowing crowns.
But, that night, Mr. Father, who had
not even taken time off to dine and
was watching the work of the depart¬
ments from a little glass tower, was
pleasantly surprised. Tistou had
returned to the factory and was walk¬
ing slowly along the line of packing-
cases containing rifles, then he
climbed into the trucks, leaned over
the engines and slipped In among the
big guns.
" Well done, Tistou, " Mr. Father
said to himself. " The boy's trying to
make up for his double 0. Splendid 1
There's still some hope for him I "
And, Indeed, Tistou had never
appeared so serious and so busy
before I His hair was standing straight
up on end. He was continually put¬
ting his hand in his pocket and
pulling out little pieces of paper.
" It even looks as If he were taking
notes, " thought Mr. Father. " I hope
he doesn't pinch his fingers among
those machine-guns. He's a good boy
when all's said and done, and quick
to see when he's at fault. "
There were surprises in store for
Mr. Father.
¿
"Ivy, briony, bindweed, ampélopsis, knot-grass and dodder
formed an Inextricable skein about the guns."
Everyone knows that newspapers
always talk of war in capital letters.
These letters are kept In a special
tray. And it was precisely before this
capital-letter-tray that the editor of
the Brightbourne Star, a well-known
daily newspaper, was standing in
some hesitation.
The editor kept turning about,
sighing and wiping his forehead, which
is always a sign of emotion and per¬
plexity. The man was most disturbed.
Sometimes he took out a big capi¬
tal letter, the kind that is kept for
important victories ; but immediately
put it back again. Sometimes he took
out a medium-sized capital letter, the
kind that is kept for wars which are
not going very well, for campaigns
which show no signs of coming to an
end, or for unexpected retreats. But
this size of capital letter would not
do either ; he put it back in the
cupboard.
At one moment he seemed to have
made up his mind to use very small
capital letters, the kind that are used
for announcements which put everyone
In a bad temper, like sugar shortage
or new tax on jam. But these would
not do either. And the editor of the
Brightbourne Star sighed all the more.
He was really very disturbed indeed.
He had to tell the inhabitants of
Brightbourne, his faithful readers, a
piece of news that was so unexpected,
and so serious in its consequences,
that he did not know how to set about
It. The war between the Go-its and
the Get-outs had miscarried. And how
was one to admit to the public that
a war could just stop like that, without
a winning or a losing side, without an
international conference, without
anything at all ?
The poor editor would have loved
to have been able to print right along
the top of his first page some sensa¬
tional headline such as LIGHTNING
GO-IT ADVANCE or HEAVY GET-
OUT OFFENSIVE.
But this was out of the question.
The reports from the pink patch on
the map were definite: the war had
not taken place and the reason for its
failure to do so cast doubts upon the
quality of the arms delivered by
the Brightbourne factory, upon Mr.
Father's technical competence and
that of this workshops and workers.
In fact, a disaster had occured.
Let us try, with the editor of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
"A rain of foxgloves, bluebells and cornflowers had fallen on the Go-its positions
and they had replied, inundating the Get-outs with buttercups, daisies, and cowslips.
Peace between the Go-Its and the Get-outs was concluded on the spot"
Drawings by Jacqueline Duheme
© Rupert Hart-Davis, London
Brightbourne Star, to reconstruct these
tragic events.
Climbing, romping, clinging plants
had taken root In the cases of arms I
How had they got there? Why? No
one could explain.
Ivy, briony, bindweed, ampélopsis,
knot-grass and dodder had formed
an inextricable skein, matted with the
glue of the black henbane about the
machine-guns, sub-machine-guns and
revolvers.
Neither the Go-its nor the Get-outs
had been able to unpack their cases.
The correspondents, in their des¬
patches, emphasized the particularly
harmful qualities of burdock, which
had fastened itself by means of the
little hooks upon its burs to the
bayonets. What could be done with
rifles that flowered, with bayonets that
you couldn't poke and whose effi¬
ciency was completely destroyed by
pretty bunches of flowers ? They had
to be thrown away.
Equally useless were the magnificent
trucks, which had been so conscien¬
tiously camouflaged with grey and
yellow lines I Brambles, goose-grass
and several varieties of nettles, the
stinging variety In particular, were
growing In abundance upon their seats.
The drivers all got nettle rash, and
were thus the only casualties in the
war. White-coated nurses made these
soldiers, whom cruel ¡tchings preven¬
ted from sitting down, lie still while
they applied warm compresses.
And here must be recorded a really
pitiful incident caused by balsam. That
a modest wild flower should be able
to create a panic among soldiers is
perfectly comprehensible if you know
that balsam has pods which explode
at the slightest touch.
The engines were all full of it. Bal¬
sam swarmed in the carburettors of
the armoured cars, in the tanks of the
motor-bicycles. At the first contact of
the selfstarter, at the first kick at the
starting-pedal, there was a growing,
spreading sound of dull explosions
which, If they did no harm, neverthe¬
less had a shattering effect on the
morale of the troops.
What of the tanks ? Their turrets
were blocked up. Eglantine mingled
with gorse and herbbennet enclosed
their mechanism in a mass of roots,
clusters, stalks and thorny branches.
The tanks were also, therefore,
useless.
A rain of foxgloves, bluebells and
cornflowers had fallen on the Go-its'
positions and they had replied, ¡nun-
dating the Get-outs with buttercups,
daisies and cowslips. A general had
had his cap knocked off by a bunch
of violets.
Countries are not taken with roses,
and battles of flowers have never
been looked on as very serious
engagements.
Peace between the Go-its and the
Get-outs was concluded on the spot.
The armies retired and the desert, a
pink-coloured lozenge, was left to the
sky, to solitude and to freedom.
This text from "Tistou of the Green
Fingers," by Maurice Druon Is published
by kind permission of the author and
publishers. Translated from the French
by Humphrey Hare. Published in Great
Britain and © 1958 by Rupert Hart-Davis,
London. The book has also been publish¬
ed in the United State» under the title
"Tistou of the Green Thumbs" © 1958
Charles Scrlbner's Sons, New York. Other
editions exist In German, Italian, Spanish,
Japanese, Swedish, Dutch and Danish.
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND DISARMAMENT (Continued from page 21)
58
Dr. Leo Szilard, Dr. Eugene Rabino-
witch and others dealt with both the
long-term and short-term problems
which the new weapon would create.
They urged, with Niels Bohr, that
in the long term the prevention of an
international race In nuclear arms
should be the prime objective of post¬
war foreign policy, both for the United
States and for all other powers.
They urged that this objective would
be easier to attain If, in the short
term, the first bombs were used, not
against targets such as Hiroshima and
Nagasaki, but in some unpopulated
place where the Japanese generals
could observe the stupendous power
of the new weapons, but where no
human casualties would be caused.
Szilard and Rablnowitch and others
fought for this short-term objective
with passion. But not all their col¬
leagues were agreed. In the event,
those who objected to the use of
Hiroshima and Nagasaki as the targets
were over-ruled by the President and
the Secretary of State, in whose hands
the final decision lay.
But when the bombs were used in
August 1945, the holocausts In the two
doomed cities convinced almost every¬
one throughout the world that Niels
Bohr was right all nuclear weapons
must be abolished under international
control. On the initiative of the British
Prime Minister, Mr. (now Earl) Attlee,
the General Assembly of the United
Nations set up a United Nations Ato¬
mic Energy Commission (UNAEC), and
charged this commission with the task
of drafting the necessary treaty.
At its first meeting, the United
States Government proposed the basic
principles on which a treaty might be
made. This proposal was put forward
by the United States delegate, Mr.
Bernard Baruch, and has always since
been known as the "Baruch Plan".
In fact, it was the work of Dr. Robert
J. Oppenheimer, who had been the lea¬
der of the team that made the first
atomic bomb.
It may be doubted whether the plan
in its original form would have been
adopted or proved workable; it propos¬
ed an International Atomic Energy
Authority, which would own and ope¬
rate all the world's nuclear plants.
At the time, however, most scientists
believed that something on these lines
was needed. The UNAEC adopted the
Oppenheimer plan as the basis of its
work, and for nearly three years many
of the most eminent scientists (1) In the
world debated every aspect of the pro¬
posal in the utmost detail. They showed
a persevering devotion which proved
their ardent desire to obtain a satisfac¬
tory result. Their final failure does
not alter the fact that eminent scien¬
tists in government employ had made
a bold effort to solve the problem
their war-time work had created.
Meanwhile, other scientists of the
Manhattan District team, who had left
government employ, were likewise
working on the problem. Some of
them, with Szilard and Rabinowltch in
the lead, formed the United States
Federation of Atomic Scientists. The
constitution of the federation said:
"The Federation of Atomic Scientists
is founded to meet the increasingly
apparent responsibility of scientists in
promoting the welfare of mankind and
the achievement of a stable world
peace."
Other scientific bodies did parallel
work on problems of the arms race.
The Pugwash
Movement
is born
Also in 1945 the Bulletin of the Atom¬
ic Scientists was founded by Hyman
Goldsmith and Eugene Rablnowitch.
For twenty years it has done solid
and brilliant work on armament prob¬
lems; it has mobilized the interest of
scientists in disarmament, and has
given them a platform for the serious
discussion of the issues involved.
But after the failure of the Oppen-
heimer plan, many of the scientists in
government employ came to accept the
nuclear arms race as an Inevitable fact
of life. They concentrated their efforts
on developing the fission-fusion, or
hydrogen, bomb and on bringing out
a large range of "tactical" nuclear
weapons of all kinds. Some of them
Professor Isidor Rabi, Dr. Hans
Bethe, Dr. Jerome Wiesner, Sir John
Cockcroft still preached the doctrine
of controlled disarmament; others
wrote and spoke against disarmament,
and against a test ban.
The latter category argued, first, that
deterrence by nuclear weapons was
the surest safeguard against aggres¬
sive war; and second, that nuclear
war was feasible, and would not obli¬
terate mankind, nor even the comba¬
tant nations involved (2).
It was in protest against this accep¬
tance of a nuclear arms race and
against the conception that nuclear
(1) The following were among those who
took part In the work of the commission:
Dr. R. Oppenheimer, Dr. Charles Thomas,
Dr. J. B. Conant, Sir James Chadwick, Sir
Charles Darwin, Sir George Thomson, Sir
William Penney, Professor F. Joliot-Curie,
Professor F. Perrin.
(2) Dr. Edward Teller has elaborated this
view in a recent book The Legacy of
Hiroshima, by E. Teller and Allen Brown,
New York, Doubleday, 1962.
war was feasible, that Dr. Albert Ein¬
stein and Bertrand (Earl) Rüssel made
their famous declaration In 1955:
"In the tragic situation which con¬
fronts humanity, we feel that scientists
should assemble in conference to
appraise the perils that have arisen as
a result of the development of wea¬
pons of mass destruction, and to dis¬
cuss a resolution In the spirit of the
appended draft. . .
" The general public, and even many
in positions of authority, have not rea¬
lized what would be involved in a war
with nuclear bombs. The general pub¬
lic still thinks in terms of the oblitera¬
tion of cities. It is understood that the
new bombs are more powerful than
the old, and that while one A-bomb
could obliterate Hiroshima, one
H-bomb could obliterate cities such as
London, New York and Moscow.
"No doubt in an H-bomb war great
cities would be obliterated. But this
Is one of the minor disasters that would
have to be faced . . .
"No one knows how widely such
lethal radioactive particles might be
diffused, but the best authorities are
unanimous In saying that a war with
H-bombs might quite possibly put an
end to the human race . . . Many
warnings have been uttered by eminent
men of science and by authorities in
military strategy. None of them will
say that the worst results are certain.
What they do say is that these results
are possible, and no one can be sure
that they will not be realized . . . Here,
then, is the problem which we present
to you stark and dreadful and Inesca¬
pable: Shall we put an end to the hu¬
man race; or shall mankind renounce
war?"
Impact on world opinion
This Einstein-Russell appeal ended
with a resolution urging the govern¬
ments of the world to find peaceful
means of settling all the then-existing,
and all future international disputes.
It was signed by other famous scien¬
tists: Max Born, Percy Brldgman, Leo¬
pold Infeld, Joseph Miller, Linus Pau¬
ling, Jollot-Curie, Joseph Rotblat, Cecil
Powell and Hideki Yukawa. It had an
enormous Impact on world opinion.
Among other results, the manifesto
led to the creation of the Pugwash
Movement. The Pugwash Movement
has been, and remains, the most
important collective effort of scientists
to arouse governments and people to
the menace of nuclear war, and to the
necessity for general controlled disar¬
mament as the only real long-term
safeguard for mankind. (See article,
Unesco Courier, Nov. 1964 - Editor.)
The novel and vitally significant fea¬
ture of the Pugwash Movement is
that it brings together the leading
scientists from both Eastern and West¬
ern Europe. The first meeting was
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
held In Pugwash, the birthplace and
one of the homes of Mr. Cyrus Eaton,
the Canadian-American millionaire,
who paid for the journeys of the parti¬
cipants and who entertained them dur¬
ing their stay. Those who took part
included leading men from the United
States, the United Kingdom, France
and other Western countries, together
with prominent members of the Acade¬
my of Sciences of the Soviet Union, of
Poland, and of other member states
of the Warsaw Pact.
The first conference was so success¬
ful that It has been followed by sixteen
others, held in different countries.
Each conference has made some new
and significant contribution to general
thinking about the armament problem.
Pugwash studies of the need for, and
the difficulties to be surmounted In,
a test ban helped to advance govern¬
ment action. Mr. Gromyko's proposal
for a "minimum nuclear deterrent"
(now usually referred to as nuclear
"umbrella") was based on a discussion
at a Pugwash meeting.
But the movement's greatest contri¬
bution was contained in the general
declarations made at the major con¬
ferences held in Kitzbühel and Vienna
in 1958, and in London in 1962.
'The risk of local
conflicts growing
into major wars
is too great...'
The Vienna Declaration is still
regarded as the Pugwash "credo". It
said, in part:
"We meet In Kitzbühel and in Vien¬
na at a time when it has become evi¬
dent that the development of nuclear
weapons makes it possible for man to
destroy civilization and, indeed, him¬
self; the means of destruction are
being made ever more efficient.
"It is sometimes suggested that loca¬
lized wars, with limited objective, might
still be fought without catastrophic
consequences. History shows, how¬
ever that the risk of local conflicts
growing into major wars is too great
to be acceptable in the age of wea¬
pons of mass destruction. Mankind
must therefore set itself the task of
eliminating all wars, including local
wars.
". . . if, in a future war, a substantial
proportion of the nuclear weapons
already manufactured were delivered
against urban targets, most centres of
civilization in the belligerent countries
would be totally destroyed, and most
of their populations killed. This would
be true whether the bombs used deriv¬
ed most of their power from fusion
reactions (so-called 'clean' bombs) or
principally from fission reactions (so-
called 'dirty' bombs). In addition to
destroying major centres of population
and industry, such bombs would also
wreck the economy of the country
attacked, through the destruction of
vital means of distribution and com¬
munication.
"We believe that,' as scientists, we
have an important contribution to make
toward establishing trust and co-op¬
eration among nations. Science is,
by long tradition, an international un¬
dertaking.
"The ability of scientists all over the
world to understand one another, and
to work together, is an excellent Ins¬
trument for bridging the gap between
nations. . .
". . . education should stress impro¬
vement of all forms of human relations
and should eliminate any glorification
of war and violence."
At the London Conference in 1962,
250 leading scientists from thirty-six
countries took part. They unanimous¬
ly adopted a declaration which said,
in part:
"Our chief concern is to prevent
war, and to relieve humanity of the
fearful anxieties and the grave econo¬
mic burdens caused by the arms race.
A general war with nuclear weapons
would be a disaster of unimaginable
magnitude. It would destroy a large
fraction of the people now alive, and
jeopardize the conditions of life of the
survivors.
"Throughout the world competition
in armaments absorbs an. immense
amount of talent and resources. This
is wasted, because, so far from giving
security, it increases the risk of
war . . .
"Disarmament and a stable peace
are essential conditions for making a
new society In which poverty could be
abolished. The prospect of such a
world is no longer Utopian. The tech¬
nical and scientific triumphs of our
times have already far outstripped the
boldest dreams of recent generations
and knowledge increases ever more
rapidly.
"In our Conference we have there¬
fore concentrated attention on the
complex problems of disarmament...
The experience of our Conference
leads us to believe that scientists have
a special contribution to make to the
solution of these problems. . . Scien¬
tists of all nations have a command¬
ing duty to help their fellow citizens
to understand that war is obsolete, and
what steps can ensure peace. They
should, we believe, recognize their
responsibilities to promote disarma¬
ment, and should invite Governments,
learned societies and other institutions
to support them in this task."
The London Conference ended its
declaration with these notable words:
"We are now at a stage in which gene¬
ral statements of principles are not
enough; action is needed. . .
"We re-assert our conviction that
the goal of full disarmament and per¬
manent peace is realistic and urgent.
This work is truly to be seen as part
of a long struggle for the progress of
mankind, and It Is one in which scien¬
tists have a responsible part to play.
We call upon scientists everywhere
in the world to join with us In this
task."
That the Pugwash Movement has
been managed with wisdom and skill
Is proved by the fact that its Influence
with governments has steadily increas¬
ed, while its standing with the general
public has improved. Many eminent
men have contributed to its success;
outstanding have been the services
rendered by its Secretary-General,
Professor Joseph Rotblat, of St.
Bartholomew's Hospital, London.
11,000 scientists
from 40 countries
petition for
a test-ban treaty
It would not be right to end this sec¬
tion without recalling the special con¬
tributions made by two individual
scientists contributions which are
particularly relevant to the theme of
this article.
In 1958, Dr. Linus Pauling of the
California Institute of Technology orga¬
nized a petition to the United Nations
on the subject of nuclear tests. The
petition urged that the "added amount
of radiation" resulting from tests cons¬
tituted a danger to human health, and
was liable to cause "an Increase In
the number of seriously defective chil¬
dren that will be born in future gen¬
erations."
It further argued that a test ban
"could serve as a first step towards a
more general disarmament" and the
"ultimate effective abolition of nuclear
weapons." This petition was drafted
by Dr. Pauling, together with a circular
letter Inviting scientists throughout the
world to sign it. All the secretarial
work was done by Dr. Pauling and
his wife and all the postage and sta¬
tionery were paid for from his pri¬
vate purse.
When the petition was presented a
few weeks later to the Secretary-
General of the United Nations, it bore
the signatures of more than 11,000
leading scientists from more than forty
countries. They included thirty-six
Nobel Prize winners, and thirty-five
Fellows of the Royal Society. There
is no doubt that the petition helped EQ
powerfully to persuade President wV
Elsenhower to approve the Geneva
negotiation which began in 1958, and
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND DISARMAMENT (Continued)
60
which ultimately resulted In the Mos¬
cow Test Ban of 1963 (1).
The second Individual contribution of
which mention must be made is an
article published in the United States
journal Foreign Affairs, In January
1962.
The article is entitled "Judgement
and Control In Modern Warfare", and
it was written by Sir Solly Zucker-
man, who, as, already mentioned, was
then, Chief Scientific/ Adviser In the
British Ministry of Defence. Sir Solly
raised the fundamental question whe¬
ther any. nuclear weapon, "tactical" or
"strategic", could be used In a- popu¬
lated area without disaster to all .con¬
cerned, including the troops that used
it first. Discussing a British Army
Exercise known as "Spearpoint",
which took place In October 1961, in
Northern Germany, Sir Solly wrote:
"In a war game involving just three
NATO Corps, nuclear weapons were
used against military targets only, In
an area of 10,000 square miles which
contained no large towns or cities.
In this 'battle', lasting only a few days,
It was assumed that the two sides
together used a total of between 20
and 25 megatons In not fewer than
500 and not more than 1,000 strikes.
It turned out that 3.5 million people
would have had their homes destroyed
if the weapons were air-burst, and
1.5 million if ground-burst. In the
former case, at least half the people
concerned would have been fatally or
seriously injured (i.e., 1.75 million). In
the case of ground-burst weapons, all
1.5 million would have been exposed
to a lethal radiological hazard, and a
further 5 million to serious danger from
radiation" (2).
The strange apathy
of mankind
to the threat of
thermo-nuclear war
Sir Solly goes on to point out that
in a real land battle there would also
be nuclear "interdiction" attacks out¬
side the area of local engagement, and
that nuclear attacks would be made by
both sides on distant airfields or mis¬
sile sites. All this, he argues, would
create such chaos on the battlefield
that it would be impossible as,
indeed, it proved in "Spearpoint" for
the General Staff to keep control of
what was happening or to pursue any
intelligible military plan.
But Sir Solly foresees a still graver
peril. Stressing the danger, in the
context of a NATO land battle; of "trip¬
wires which unwittingly set Into opera¬
tion the whole panoply of strategic
deterrence", he continues:
"Let us be quite clear about this.
There are those In the West who
already believe that the use of
any nuclear weapons in a war involv¬
ing NATO would mean the opening of
a third World War. There are Indica¬
tions that the Soviet leaders believe
the same thing. If this view is right,
all freedom of choice may be lost, and
all possibility of exercising judgement
and control in a? future war between
the great powers."
Sir SofTy's* argument leads him to
the conclusion which has been quoted
above, but' which, In view of -its' crucial
. importance, will bear repetition:
"The very existence of nuclear."
weapons is thus the most urgent chal¬
lenge that has ever been presented to
military judgement and control. As
weapons to deter aggression, they
serve a very precise purpose; the con¬
text of field warfare in which they
might be. used is an entirely diffe¬
rent matter. . . One may fairly ask
what meaning there is to the Idea of
using nuclear weapons 'to defend our
territories and peoples'. One can
deter with nuclear weapons. Can one
defend?"
Sir Solly is here saying in polite lan¬
guage what Professor Rabi said more
crudely In 1958 : "There is a dan¬
gerous misconception which is glossed
over by the use of the word 'tactical'
in reference to bombs of the explosive
power of thousands of tons of TNT.
Such bombs used in profusion would
destroy the country which is the scene
of a battle as completely as Hiroshima
was destroyed. . . Although such
bombs can be used tactically in war
in a desert or at sea, or over very
sparsely populated territory, the situa¬
tion is quite different in Western
Europe or in some of the heavily
populated countries on the borders of
the Communist complex" (3).
The evidence given in the last sec¬
tion shows that many scientists, both
In government service and outside it,
have made genuine and sustained
efforts to bring home the dangers of
the present arms race to their minis¬
terial and military chiefs, and to the
public at large. Yet it Is obvious that,
so far, they have failed.
On the last day of 1957, Professor
Isidor Rabi said: "The facts about
modern warfare have just not pene¬
trated; and that goe.s for the heads of
governments, for otherwise they would
ponder these facts every day as the
daily number one problem" (4)	
The average citizen has been even
less concerned; his apathy and Igno¬
rance are one of the strangest myste¬
ries in the history of democratic
society. Writing five years after Rabi,
Professor Warren E. Olsen said: "Des¬
pite statements by such diverse figu¬
res as Norman Cousins, Herman
Kahn, Harrison Brown, and former
President Elsenhower concerning the
imminence of a third World War, the
unspeakable toll of lives such a war
would entail, and the probability of
killing untold millions who have no
part in the East-West quarrel, recent
surveys indicate that few Americans
are deeply troubled by the threat of
a thermonuclear holocaust" (5). The
same is probably true of almost every
nation, except the Japanese.
OPERATION
'VOX POPULI'
A call for a world
movement of opinion
Nor have the scientists made much
progress in their efforts to persuade
the governments to carry out disarma¬
ment, and to abolish war.
These depressing facts do not mean
that the Pugwash Movement should
give up its work, or that other scien¬
tists are justified in regarding that
work as useless or Utopian. On the
contrary, the challenge of the London
Pugwash Declaration quoted above is
even more topical than it was In 1962:
"Scientists of all nations have a
commanding duty to help their fellow
citizens to understand that war Is obso¬
lete, and what steps can ensure
peace. They should, we believe, rec¬
ognize their responsibilities to pro¬
mote disarmament, and should Invite
governments, learned societies and
other institutions to support them in
this task."
And again: "We re-assert our con¬
viction that the goal of full disarma¬
ment and permanent peace is realis¬
tic and urgent. This work Is truly to
be seen as part of a long struggle for
the progress of mankind, and it is one
in which scientists have a responsible
part to play. We call upon scientists
everywhere in the world to join with
us in this task."
Today with wars and crises in vari¬
ous continents, the task is even more
urgent than it was when the London
(1) Other notable contributions to dis¬
armament thinking and literature by Individual
scientists have Included books by Professor
Max Born, Dr. Ralph Lapp, Dame Kathleen
Lonsdale, Bertrand Russell and Sir Robert
Watson-Watt. Outstanding Is Sir Robert
Watson-Watt's Man's Means to his End. Sir
Robert makes a devastating analysis of the
present arms race and Its dangers, and sets
out the case for disarmament with great
cogency. Sir Robert Is the discoverer of radar,
which enabled the Royal Air Force to defeat
Hitler's Luftwaffe In the Battle of Britain.
(2) Foreign Affairs, New York, January 1962.
(3) News of the World, 15 July 1958.
(4) New York Times, 1 January 1958.
. (5) Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, March
1963.
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
This monument, erected
In memory of the
thousands of children
killed by the explosion
of the first atomic bomb,
on August 6, 1945,
stands in the Peace Park
at Hiroshima.
Photo © Siegfried Sammer,
West Berlin
Declaration was written. But if there
is to be any hope of practical success,
the task must be undertaken on a far
vaster scale, with far greater resour¬
ces, and with far more ambitious
hopes, than have Inspired the move¬
ments started since 1945.
What is the task?
It is to make the average citizen in
every country understand the urgent
danger In which he stands today; to
persuade him that the armaments which
create the danger must be abolished;
and to evoke, to lead, and to organize
his demand for swift and radical
action.
It is to rid the world of a threat to
civilization even greater than that of
Hitler's Nazism in 1939, and to do so
by creating a tidal wave of Informed
opinion. It might be called: "Opera¬
tion Vox Populi: The Challenge of
the Peoples to Militarism and Death."
The operation should be thought of as
having no less urgency and impor¬
tance than the Manhattan District Pro
ject had in 1939. It should have the
same claim on the services of scien¬
tists of the highest rank.
The international committee. An
International committee should be
formed of men of world repute, some,
if not all, of whom have themselves
played a prominent part in military
research, and in the application of
scientific methods to the conduct of
military operations in time of war. In
other words, they should be men who
will command the respect of their
fellow scientists, of governments, of
General Staffs, and of the public.
The committee should be widely
representative of nations from both
Eastern and Western Europe. It
should include, among others, repre¬
sentatives from the United States, the
U.S.S.R., France, the United Kingdom,
Italy, India, Japan, and if possible,
China.
The members of the committee
would, of course, have to give their
whole time and energy to their su¬
premely important task. They should
be given leave of absence from their
normal employment, whether it be in
government service, in the universities,
in scientific institutes, or in industry.
This leave of absence should be for
one, two, or more years, as the suc¬
cessful conduct of the operation might
require. Their posts should, of course,
be kept open for them, whenever they
desired to return.
The committee should have the same
freedom from financial restrictions as
the scientists who worked in the Man¬
hattan District Project; it should have
whatever sums of money it might judge
to be required. It should have at its
disposal whatever was needed in
qualified scientific personnel, in ad¬
ministrative and secretarial manpower,
and in other expert help.
Before these practical aspects of
the operation and its organization are
discussed, it may be useful to set out
in more concrete form the substance
61
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND DISARMAMENT (Continued)
62
of the message for which the opera¬
tion Is to mobilize support.
The substance of the case. The fol¬
lowing are the main Issues on which
world opinion requires a clear and
decisive lead from scientists:
1. The real nature of the present
weapons of mass destruction
nuclear, chemical and biological
and the scale of the casualties and
destruction which their use would
involve.
2. The question, raised by
Professor Rabi and Sir Solly
Zuckerman, whether any nuclear
weapons, even of the smallest
"tactical" category with which the
armies are equipped, can be used
without disasterdisaster both to
the civil population of the area
where the weapons are used, and
to the armed forces which use
them first.
3. The probable future develop¬
ment of weapons of offence if the
arms race goes on and military
research continues to receive the
vast resources now placed at its
disposal.
4. The possibility of active
defence against the weapons of
mass destruction, whether by anti¬
missile missiles, or in other ways.
This should include a study of the
cost of any possible system
of active defence, its probable
efficacy or inefficacy, and the risk
of increased fall-out which it might
involve.
5. The possibility of passive, or
"civil" defence against nuclear
attack, by shelters, evacuation, etc.
This should include a study of the
cost of such passive defence, of
its efficacy and its effect on the
social standards and industrial
efficiency of any country that made
a serious attempt to carry it out.
6. The danger of accidental or
unintended nuclear war, whether as
the result of mechanical failure in
the systems of weapon control and
command, or of human failure
(mental breakdown) in the officers
or ministers in charge of them.
Warnings of the possibility of
accidental war are often given in
general terms; but glib statements
of a reassuring nature are
also often made, based on the
infallibility of the "fail-safe" system,
of the "permissive link", etc. The
great complexity and cost of these
safeguarding devices proves in
itself how real is the danger of
accident; and no one who under¬
stands the matter denies that it is
possible that they may fail. This
is a subject on which the peoples
have been kept in almost total
ignorance. But they have a right
to know the risks they face; a
detailed and authoritative state¬
ment is urgently required.
7. The character of the new
strategic jargon in current use in
discussions of nuclear war. This
should include a study of the
psychological and political assump¬
tions (or fallacies) of most of the
so-called "analyses" of nuclear
strategy carried out by individual
"experts" or by "institutes" or
"corporations" of various kinds.
The study should examine the
assertion made by expert govern¬
ment "consultants" that the NATO
Command have approved a war-
plan which accepts 200 "mega-
deaths" (200 million dead), apart
from the more numerous victims
of fall-out.
8. A study of the so-called
"technical" difficulties of con¬
ventional, nuclear, chemical and
biological disarmament, with de¬
tailed technical proposals as to
how these difficulties can be
overcome in a general international
treaty. This should include a
study of the technical, political and
psychological problems of inter¬
national inspection and control,
and should suggest the detailed
methods, of whatever kind, by
which faithful observance of the
obligations of the disarmament
treaty can be reasonably ensured.
Ill-informed and tendentious debate
has obscured the whole subject of
inspection in a miasma of suspicion
and doubt.
9. A study of the short-term
effects of general disarmament on
the employment prospects of the
50 million men and women now
engaged throughout the world in
national armed forces or in the
manufacture of armaments.
10. A forecast of the gain to
human welfare if the brain power
and resources now given to arma¬
ments and preparations for war
were diverted instead to work for
the betterment of health, for the
promotion of intellectual and
artistic achievement, and for the
increase of usable wealth.
11. An estimate of the gain to
science, and therefore to humanity,
if all present restrictions on inter¬
national scientific collaboration
were removed by the disarmament
treaty, and if all scientific research
of every kind were open to the
world.
The four stages. There should be
a memorandum (or book) on each of
the eleven subjects specified above,
and on any additional aspects of the
armament problem which the interna¬
tional committee might judge to be
required.
The authors of each memorandum
should be specialist scientists, whose
authority on the subject with which
they dealt would be unchallengeable.
On each subject there should be co¬
authors from both Eastern and Western
Europe. The authors would be cho¬
sen by the International committee and
would work under the committee's
general direction.
Taken together, the memoranda
would make a detailed and unanswer¬
able case for the conviction expressed
by the participants in the Pugwash
Conference of 1962: "The goal of
full disarmament and permanent peace
Is realistic and urgent." They would
constitute a body of doctrine on which
the whole operation would be based.
The manifesto. When the prepara¬
tion of the memoranda was complete,
the International committee would
publish them and secure the widest
possible distribution for them.
The committee should then draw up
a relatively brief manifesto, setting
forth the main conclusions to be drawn
from the memoranda. The manifesto
would state succinctly the real dan¬
gers of the arms race; the urgent nec¬
essity of a world-wide disarmament
treaty under international control; the
conviction of the authors that a safe
and practicable treaty could be speed¬
ily drawn up; and the benefits to
all nations which such a treaty would
bring.
The committee should secure the
signatures of eminent scientists for
the manifesto perhaps 100 leading
men from each of the major countries,
and a corresponding number from
smaller countries.
The manifesto would then be pub¬
lished with the great collective author¬
ity of these famous personalities be¬
hind it.
The mass endorsement of scientists.
The international committee would next
endeavour to secure massive support
for the manifesto from the scientists of
all nations. Every man or woman with
adequate scientific training (e.g., with
a university degree in one or more
scientific disciplines) should be invited
to give his, or her, support. The pur¬
pose should be to attract the adhesion
of as large a proportion as possible
of the scientists of the world. A mil¬
lion signatures would not be too high
a target.
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
The world petition. The interna¬
tional committee would then proceed
to organize the world expression of
popular opinion, which it is the pur¬
pose of the operation to evoke.
It cannot be doubted that, if the first
three stages outlined above were sub¬
stantially successful, the greater part
of the intellectual leaders of every
country writers, politicians, univer¬
sity professors, the teaching profes¬
sion, lawyers, doctors, etc. would be
aroused by the scientists' warning
about the dangers of the arms race,
and would be ready to accept the
drastic, world-wide, internationally ins¬
pected disarmament proposed.
With the adhesion of these intellec¬
tual leaders, It should be possible to
organize a world petition far greater
and more comprehensive than any ever
drawn up before. There would be no
disposition among the ordinary citizens
of any nation to challenge the authority
of the scientists, or to reject their
appeal. The signatories of the world
petition, hundreds of millions of them,
would pledge themselves to support
their respective governments in any
action which these governments might
take to draw up and execute a treaty
of general disarmament without delay.
Towards a world
petition with
hundreds of millions
of signatures
Scientists' aversion to manifestos.
It has been suggested that the scien¬
tists of the world would be unwilling
to adopt the plan proposed above be¬
cause they have a natural and a
deeply ingrained aversion to mani¬
festos, and to other simplified exposi¬
tions of facts and arguments on which
they may feel doubts or reservations.
It is, of course, true that scientists,
more than other men, desire exact
precision, and that, faced with grave
political or social issues, they may
think it probable that there are refine¬
ments of argument that are not sus¬
ceptible of popular exposition.
But the scientists who drew up the
Vienna and London Pugwash Declara¬
tions felt no such doubts about the
armament problem. They saw it as a
naked choice between an intensifying
arms race in nuclear, biological and
chemical weapons, with constantly
recurring crises, on the one hand; and
peaceful co-existence based on disar¬
mament and world law, on the other.
Without hesitation, they chose
peaceful co-existence, disarmament
and world law. What scientist need
quibble about the niceties of the argu¬
ment, when It was Einstein who launch
ed the Pugwash Movement, and, with
his dying breath, called on mankind to
revolt against the use of nuclear
weapons, and to abolish all armaments
and war?
Long-term education. Some people
believe that general disarmament
under International control would make
such a revolutionary change In world
affairs, and in the relations of nations,
that all danger of war would disappear.
Others consider that the risk of inter¬
national conflicts would remain, and
that the ideas of militarist thinking
might revive.
Those who take the second view
hold that education in all countries
should be adapted to the changed
conditions of a disarmed world. The
Vienna Pugwash Declaration had most
important things to say in support of
this proposition.
Dr. Peter Hodgson has graphically
described what he thinks would be
required: "What is needed is some
continuing action that will steadily grow
In importance. Education is the key.
Is it not possible to arrange for all
this to be taught in schools? Could
not 'Survival in the Nuclear Age' re¬
place 'The Wars of the Roses' in Bri¬
tain's General Certificate of Education
history syllabus? It could well be
made a compulsory subject. Could
not more international schools be
founded to help the education of a
new generation who will work and
think In international terms? Could
not Studentships and Fellowships
and Colleges be founded to further
continuing studies and work on the
problem? This would ensure that the
impetus and interest generated by
'Operation Vox Populi' is not lost, but
forms the basis of a continuing effort
for lasting peace."
It may well be hoped that, if "Op¬
eration Vox Populi" succeeded, such
a reform of education could be
obtained. . .
The whole of this article has been
founded on the Vienna and London
Pugwash Declarations which have
been quoted above. Those declara¬
tions set forth the conviction of many
most eminent scientists from many
countries that the whole philosophy of
power politics is out of date; that the
arms race is a grotesque and very
perilous anachronism; that in the nu¬
clear age, and with modern means of
transport and communication, the vital
Interests of nations are not in conflict,
but are common Interests which they
share and which they can only promote
by common action.
This article is an attempt to show
how the new philosophy of the Pug¬
wash scientists might be made part of
the accepted thinking of civilized
mankind. It would require a supreme
effort from scientists themselves; a
massive acceptance of the Pugwash
assertion that they have a "command¬
ing duty to help their fellow scientists
to understand that war is obsolete",
and that, If they could be persuaded
to "recognize their responsibilities to
promote disarmament", they might
exercise a decisive Influence on the
course of history.
But is there
still enough
time?
(1) Professor Max Born, Bulletin of the
Atomic Scientists, April 1964. "Max Born
Is one of the founders of modern physics,
and was awarded the Nobel Prize In 1954",
the Bulletin says. Professor Born worked on
military research for Germany during the
First World War.
Everything depends on whether the
scientists are ready to undertake the
task. They, and they alone, can rouse
the nations from the "dogmatic sleep"
which allows the arms race to go on.
But they must recognize the revolu¬
tionary character of what they have to
do. One of the most eminent of them,
Professor Max Born, writing for fellow
scientists, said not long ago:
"Our hope is based on the union of
two spiritual powers; the moral
awareness of the unacceptability of a
war degenerated to mass murder of
the defenceless, and the rational know¬
ledge of the incompatibility of techno¬
logical warfare with the survival of the
human race.
"The only question Is whether we
have enough time to let these realiza¬
tions become effective. For the pre¬
sent situation is highly unstable, and
becomes, through its own mechanisms,
increasingly dangerous day by day.
The failure of an individual, or an appa¬
ratus, the blind passion of a leader,
the Ideological or national delusions
of the masses can at any moment lead
to a catastrophe. . .
"All of us must fight against official
lies and encroachments; against the
assertions that there is protection from
nuclear weapons through shelters
and emergency regulations; against
the suppression of those who enligh¬
ten the public about it; against narrow-
minded nationalism, "gloire", passion
for great power; and we must espe¬
cially fight against those ideologies
which pronounce the infaillibility of
their doctrines and thus separate the
world Into irreconciliable camps.
"There is still hope, but it will only
come true if we stake everything on the
battle against the diseases of our
time." (1).
"If we stake everything!"
"The only question is whether we have
enough time."
This text is a slightly abridged version of
an article published in Unesco's quarterly,
"Impact of Science on Society", No 4 1965.
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
and the search for peace
u
64
NESCO'S general con¬
cern with peace and disarmament is
based on its Constitution, whose
preamble affirms in its opening words:
"That since wars begin in the minds
of men, it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed."
The preamble to the Constitution
emphasizes the importance of promot¬
ing equality in the access to educa¬
tional, scientific and cultural facilities
a task implying close links between
Unesco's efforts and those of the
United Nations In the cause of social
and economic development.
The Unesco Constitution, however,
defines the relationship between so¬
cial and economic development and
the promotion of peace by stating that
peace cannot be based exclusively
on political and economic arrange¬
ments between governments, but
must be founded upon the Intellectual
and moral solidarity of mankind. This
means that Unesco's action for peace
has to reach individual men and
women.
Unesco does not itself undertake
professional research. Unesco's scien¬
tific departments and services seek to
promote and encourage research at
the national, regional and international
levels, and to facilitate scientific com¬
munication across political and cultu¬
ral borders.
In its very earliest programmes
Unesco devoted considerable atten¬
tion to a series of problems presented
under the heading of "Study of
International Tensions", which soon
expanded into research projects on
international and intra-national social
tensions. A large number of psycho¬
logical, sociological and economic
studies were carried out within this
framework from 1947 to 1956, of which
the following are a few examples:
How Nations see each other, by
William Buchanan and Hadley Can-
tril; Urbana, University of Illinois
Press, 1953. *
In the minds of men, by Gardner
Murphy; New York, Basic Book
Service, 1953.*
Democracy in a world of tensions,
by Richard McKeon; Stein Rokkan,
ed.: Chicago, University of Chi¬
cago Press, 1951. *
Tensions affecting international
understanding, by O. Klineberg;
New York, Social Science Research
Council, 1950. *
Tensions that cause wars, by
G. W. Allport, G. Freyre, G. Gur-
vitch et al.; Hadley Cantril, ed.;
Urbana, University of Illinois Press,
1950.*
The older studies carried out under
Unesco's programme are only partly
relevant to present-day peace res¬
earch. More recent ones which come
very close to peace research proper
and therefore lead up to present
preoccupations are:
International social science journal:
Peace research, Vol. XVII, no. 3,
1965. Compromise and the settle¬
ment of conflicts, Vol. XV, no. 2,
1963. The social Sciences and
peaceful co-operation, Vol. XII,
no. 2, 1960. * (see page 67.)
International social science bulletin:
Techniques of mediation and con¬
ciliation, Vol. X, no. 4, 1958.*
Unesco has launched a series
of studies which began with a survey
of the institutional framework within
which scientific research on peace
and disarmament at the international
level is currently pursued in Unesco's
member states.
It was this basic concern with
institutional organization and the
exchange of information on current
research among the various national
Institutions that led to the compilation
of an International Repertory of Insti¬
tutions specializing in research on
peace and disarmament and to the
establishment of a new non-govern¬
mental organization, the "International
Peace Research Association" (IPRA),
whose "Newsletter" on current peace
research Is published with Unesco's
assistance.
This Association has also recently
* Out of print. We refer readers to their
local library.
INSTITUTIONS FOR RESEARCH
ON PEACE AND DISARMAMENT
Seven international organizations are working exclusively on peace
research:
International Peace Research Association, Groningen, Netherlands.
Peace Research Society, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, U.S.A.
European Co-ordination Centre for Research and Documentation in the
Social Sciences, Vienna, Austria.
International Centre for Inter-Group Relations, Paris, France.
International Institute for Peace, Vienna, Austria.
Pugwash Conference for Science and World Affairs, London, U.K.
World Federation for Mental Health, Geneva, Switzerland.
In December 1966, national institutions specializing in peace research or
partly engaged in peace research numbered 73. They were distributed as
follows:
32 in North America (U.S.A. and Canada).
39 in Europe (Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, Denmark, Finland, France, Fed
eral Republic of Germany, Eastern Germany, Greece, Netherlands,
Norway, Poland, Romania, Spain, Sweden, U.S.S.R., U.K. Yugoslavia).
1 in Asia (India).
1 in Latin America (Mexico).
The number of peace research institutions will undoubtedly increase as
new peace research centres and sections, founded by universities or other
institutions, expand and co-ordinate their resources and activities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
been commissioned to make an
exhaustive study and an analysis of
existing hypotheses on peace and
disarmament. From the latter phase
of this study it may be possible to
establish a typology of such hypo¬
theses. The results of this study will
be published.
Interest In the institutional frame¬
work of peace research has also
brought about further and closer co¬
operation between Unesco and the
Pugwash Conference on Science and
World Affairs. Two scientific studies
are being carried out in close colla¬
boration with the Continuing Com¬
mittee of the Pugwash Conference,
the first bearing on the legal and
political aspects of intervention, and
the second dealing with the problem
of guarantees.
Another study is a limited survey,
based on public opinion data, of the
image of a world in the process of
disarmament (see page 5).
Unesco activities relating to peace
research will be further expanded In
1967-1968. Among other studies, a
critical appraisal will be made of the
extent to which university courses in
international law and international
relations take into account the concept
of living peacefully together. This
study will be made by some ten
countries with different social and
political systems.
A major event during Unesco's
20th anniversary celebrations in Nov¬
ember 1966 was the round-table
meeting at which a score of distin¬
guished international figures, including
three Nobel Peace Prize winners
(Lord Boyd Orr, Linus Pauling and
Philip J. Noel-Baker) appraised
Unesco's contribution to peace.
Appreciating "the valuable contribu¬
tion Unesco has made to peace in
its first 20 years", and considering
present world problems (among
others, the arms race, inequality of
living standards, the population explo¬
sion...), the participants appealed to
all peoples and all governments "to
reject war once and for all as an
instrument of their international poli¬
cy".
Unesco is to produce in 1967-1968
a world anthology of writings desi¬
gned to strengthen peaceful relations
between peoples. The first anthology
will be devoted to the theme, "The
Horrors of War" and will comprise
passages from works by great writers,
from letters and from accounts of eye¬
witnesses of war. Unesco National
Commissions in member states have
been asked to submit texts for inclu¬
sion in the anthology.
The educational and scientific acti¬
vities of Unesco which, though not
dealing specifically with peace and
disarmament, nevertheless have a
relatively direct and constant bearing
on peace, are those connected with
the implementation of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights.
This applies particularly to Article 2
-Courier
The cover of our
November 1964
Issue devoted
to the problems
of disarmament.
nbet 1964 (17th year)
1200000t)000<Ä
of the Universal Declaration, which
proclaims that everyone is entitled to
all the fundamental human rights
"without distinction of any kind such
as race, colour, sex, language, reli¬
gion, political or other opinion,
national or social origin, property,
birth or other status".
Almost since its inception, Unesco
has undertaken a wide range of edu¬
cational activities and scientific stud¬
ies whose aim has been to promote
the extension of human rights. Scien¬
tific studies, for example, have been
the basis for a number of basic decla¬
rations relating to problems of racial
discrimination:
The race concept. Results of an
inquiry; 2nd edition, Unesco, 1958.*
This book gives a report of the dis¬
cussions which led to the adoption,
by an international meeting of experts
in 1951, of a declaration on the
concept of race and racial differences.
The General Conference of Unesco in
1960 called for a revision of this
declaration in the light of the most
recent scientific knowledge. Two
international meetings were convened
in Moscow in 1964 and in Oxford in
1965 to re-examine respectively the
biological aspects of race and the
social and cultural aspects of human
rights. The conclusions of the first
meeting were published under the
heading Biological aspects of Race.
in the International social science jour¬
nal (Vol. XVII, no. 1, 1965).
Other studies dealing with different
aspects of the race question include:
On genetic and biological aspects
Race and biology, by L. C. Dunn
7th ed., Unesco, 1965. ($0.60
3/6.) * *
Race mixture, by Harry L. Shapiro;
3rd., ed. Unesco, 1965. ($0.60;
3/6.) * *
The significance of racial differen¬
ces, by G. M. Morant, 4th ed.,
Unesco, 1961. ($0.30; 1/6.)**
On sociological, psychological and
historical aspects:
Race and culture, by Michel Leiris;
6th ed., Unesco, 1965. ($0.60;
3/6.) * *
Race and psychology, by Otto
Klineberg; 6th ed., Unesco, 1965.
($0.60; 3/6.) * *
Race and society, by Kenneth L.
Little; 5th ed., Unesco, 1965.
($0.60; 3/6.) * *
Racial myths, by Juan Comas; 6th
ed., Unesco, 1965. ($0.60; 3/6.)**
The defence of human rights in
Latin America (16th - 18th centur¬
ies) by Silvio Zavala; Unesco,
1964. ($0.70; 3/6.)
Race and class in rural Brazil, by
C. Wagley, ed.; 2nd ed., Unesco,
1963. ($2.00; 10/-.)
Contacts de civilisations en Marti¬
nique et en Guadeloupe, by Michel
Leiris; Reprint, Unesco, 1961.
($1.75; 9/6.)
Race relations and mental health,
by Marie Jahoda, 2nd ed., Unesco,
* * Studies reprinted in a single vol¬
ume, "The Race Question in Modern
Science", 1956 and 1959 (out of print).
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO AND THE SEARCH FOR PEACE (Continued)
Everything begins with education
1961. ($0.50; 2/6.)
Recent research on racial rela¬
tions, International social science
journal, Vol. XIII, no. 2, 1961.*
The roots of prejudice, by Arnold
M. Rose. 7th ed., Unesco, 1963.
($0.30; 1/6.) * *
Race and history, by Claude Lévi-
Strauss; 4th ed., Unesco, 1961. * **
Les élites de couleur dans une
ville brésilienne, by Thaies de
Azevedo; Unesco, 1953. *
On religious aspects:
The Catholic Church and the race
question, by Yves M. J. Congar;
reprint, Unesco, 3rd ed., 1966.
($0.50; 2/6.)
Jewish thought as a factor in civi¬
lization, by Leon Roth; 2nd ed.,
Unesco, 1961. ($0.50; 2/6.)
Buddhism and the race question,
by G. P. Malalasekera and K. N.
Jayatilleke; Unesco, 1958. ($0.50;
2/6.)
The ecumenical movement and the
racial problem, by W. A. Visser't
Hooft; Unesco, 1954. *
On legal aspects:
Equality of rights between races
and nationalities in U.S.S.R., by
I. P. Tsamerlan and S. L. Ronin;
Unesco, 1962. ($1.50; 1/6.)
Racial Equality and the law, by
Morroe Berger; Unesco, 1954.*
Among studies dealing with educa¬
tional aspects of the race problem,
one of the most important was that
carried out, under the auspices of
Unesco, by Cyril Bibby, entitled:
Race, prejudice and education;
London, Heinemann, 1959. (9/6.)
Unesco has actively promoted inter¬
national understanding through edu¬
cation.
It has organized international semi¬
nars to study the most effective
methods of developing such education
in schools; it has been concerned with
the production of specially designed
teaching materials and aids; and It
has collaborated with governments
and professional associations for the
improvement of school textbooks from
the point of view -of international
understanding.
Among other examples are the
recent experimental project for the
international exchange of geography
textbooks for revision and comment
by experts, and a similar project for
history textbooks now being planned.
In addition experts are made available
to governments (on request) and to
Unesco-aided teacher training institu¬
tions.
A notable Instance of direct action
by Unesco for the Improvement of
curricula and methods In this field of
education is the programme known as
the Associated Schools Project, which
has now been in operation for more
than ten years.
It consists of a network of co-ordi-
UNITED NATIONS
PUBLICATIONS ON DISARMAMENT
the
united
nations
1945-1965
UNITED NATIONS
Just published
THE UNITED NATIONS AND
DISARMAMENT 1945-1965
340 pages, Clothbound: $4.50
Reviews the deliberations and
negotiations on disarmament in
the United Nations during a 20-
year span (1945-1965).
66 Economic and Social Consequences of Disarmament, 1962.
Vol. 1: $0.75; 5/-stg; Vol. II: $3.00
nated pilot projects in schools In differ¬
ent countries (about 400 primary and
secondary schools and teacher-training
institutions in 50 countries).
Its purpose is to test ideas on edu¬
cation for international understanding
under differing circumstances and to
exert a direct influence on education
generally by developing knowledge of
world affairs, of international co-op¬
eration in problems of world signifi¬
cance, of other cultures and ways of
life, and of the principles of human
rights.
The project has influenced educa¬
tional practice outside its own area of
application and has demonstrated that
teaching for International understand¬
ing need not add to the load of school
programmes but In fact may enrich the
content and Increase the impact of
ordinary curricula.
It has contributed to the develop-
mept of methods and research and
techniques of evaluation for such
teaching and, by arousing the Interest
of educational authorities in the prob¬
lem, has paved the way for broad
national programmes in this field.
Unesco's continuing activities with
adult education and youth organiza¬
tions and movements include conside¬
rable emphasis on the promotion of
international understanding. The fol¬
lowing are a few examples:
Evaluation of the Major Project:
The Major Project and school edu¬
cation; reprint of articles from
Orient-Occident bulletins, Vol. VIII,
Nos. 2 and 3, April and June 1965.
International understanding at
school; Unesco, 1965.
Note on organization of program¬
mes in the primary school, Unesco,
1965.
Organizing programmes of educa¬
tion for international understand¬
ing, Unesco, 1965.
Youth and peace; Unesco, 1964.
Teaching about the Orient, by
David T. Ivor; Unesco, 1961.
(These six publications are available
free of charge.)
Telling the UN story: new approa¬
ches to teaching about the United
Nations and its related Agencies,
by Leonard Kenworthy; Unesco,
1963. ($2.00; 6/-.)
Some of the studies on socio-eco¬
nomic development and technological
change touch only incidentally upon
problems of International tensions,
conflict or danger of war, whereas
others specifically refer to these prob¬
lems. Examples of the more direct
approach are:
Social implications of the peaceful
uses of nuclear energy, by Otto
Klineberg, ed.; Unesco, 1964.
($2.00; 10/-.)
The nature of conflict, International
Sociological Association; Unesco,
1958.*
w
EC
<
Q.
Z
5
o
ce
o
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
SOME UNESCO PUBLICATIONS ON PEACE
Just published
DECISIONS AND DECISION
MAKERS IN THE MODERN STATE
Introduced by Jean Meynaud
(Series: CURRENT SOCIAL
ISSUES)
The role of the executive
in the modern state
The parliamentary profession
H Technical change and
political decision
Citizen participation
in political life
1967, 276 pages
$5.50, 28/- (stg.) 20 F
EDUCATION FOR INTERNATIONAL
UNDERSTANDING
Examples and suggestions for
classroom use drawn from schools
in many countries
2nd imp. 1964, 118 pages
$1.50, 7/6 (stg.) 5.25 F
RESEARCH ON RACIAL
RELATIONS
(Series: CURRENT
SOCIAL ISSUES)
Reviews of research on
racial relations spanning
every continent
1966, 265 pages
$ 5.00, 25/- (stg.) 17.50 F
INTERNATIONAL SOCIAL
SCIENCE JOURNAL
An international forum on
developments in the social
sciences. In each issue
leading specialists
examine extensively a
single major subject of
topical interest
(quarterly)
Single copy:
$2.00, 10/- (stg.) 7 F
Yearly subscription:
$7.00, 35/- (stg.) 24 F
research on
racial relations
social implications of the
peaceful uses
of nuclear energy
SOCIAL IMPLICATIONS
OF THE PEACEFUL
USES OF NUCLEAR
ENERGY
(Series: TECHNOLOGY
AND SOCIETY)
An international survey of
present knowledge,
opinions and attitudes
regarding the peaceful
uses of atomic energy
1964, 169 pages
$2.00, 10/- (stg.) 7 F
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Longmans of Australia Pty Ltd., Railway Crescent,
Croydon, Victoria; sub-agent United Nations Associa¬
tion of Australia, Victorian Division, 4th Floor, Askew
House, 364 Lonsdale St., Melbourne C. I. (Victoria);
for the Unesco Courier only : Dominie Pty Ltd, 463 Pitt-
water Road. Brookvale (N.S.W.) ($A 2.25). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications: Editions
"Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-We-
tenschappelijke Uitgeverij Belgiëlei 1 47, Antwerp. I. For
The Unesco Courier (1 40 FB) and art slides (488 FB) only :
Louis De Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP
3380.00. CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
($ 3.00). Lake House Bookshop, Sir Chittam-
palan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244. Colombo, 2 (Rs. 7).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CYPRUS.
"MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, Ltd., Prags Boulevard 47, Copenhagen S. (D.
Kr. 17). ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O.
Box 1 20, Addis Ababa (1 0/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40).
FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy,
Paris-7'. C.C.P. 12598-48. (10 F). GERMANY. All
publications: R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse
145, Munich, 8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only)
Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P.
276650 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd., Atlantis House, Commercial Street, POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens; Librairie Eteftheroudakis, Nikkis 4, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64, Nathan Road,
Kowloon. HUNGARY. Académiai Konyvesbolc,
Vici u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Kónyvtárosok Boltja,
Népkóztirsaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd., Nicol
Road, Ballard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson
House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New Delhi.
1 ; Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery Co., 1 7
Park Street, Calcutca 1 6 and Scindia House, New Delhi :
Indian National Commission for Cooperation with
Unesco, Ministry of Education, New Delhi 3. (Rs.
10.50). INDONESIA. P.T.N. "Permata-Nusantara"
c/o Department of Commerce 22, Djalan Nusantara
Djakarta IRAQ. McKenzie'* Bookshop, Al-Rashid
Street, Baghdad; University Bookstore, University
of Baghdad, P.O. Box 75, Baghdad IRELAND. The
National Press, 2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin.
4. (15/5). ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly Blum-
stein's Bookstores, 35 Allenby Road and 48 Nahlat
Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8). JAMAICA. Sang-
ster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street, Kingston. (15/-).
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome, Nihon¬
bashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo (1,200 yen).
JORDAN. Joseph I. Bahous & Co., Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (10/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co.,
Ltd., P. O. Box 2942, Kuwait LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286. Monrovia (10/-).
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-
Rue, Luxemburg (F.L. 140). MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications Ltd., Times House, River Valley Road,
Singapore, 9; Pudu Building (3rd floor), 110, Jalan
Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50). MALTA. Sapienza's
Library, 26 Kingsway, Valletta, (15/-). MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis (15/-). MONACO. British Library, 30, Bid.
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. G. C.
T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Cura¬
çao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW ZEALAND. Govern¬
ment Printing Office, 20, Molesworth Street (Private
Bag), Wellington; Government Bookshops: Auckland
(P.O. Box 5344), Chnstchurch (P.O. Box 1721), Dune.
din (P.O. Box 1104) (15/-). NIGERIA. C.M.S. Book¬
shops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-). NORWAY.
All publications: A.S. Bokhjornet, Akersgt 41-
Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Norvesens Litte-
raturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6, (17.50 kr.). PA-
KISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco
Publications House, P.O. Box 374 G.P.O., Lahore;
Showrooms : Urdu Bazar, Lahore, and 57-58 Murree
Highway, G/6-1,lslamabad. PHILIPPINES.The Modern
Book Co., Inc., 928 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632,
Manila POLAND. All publications: ORWN PAN Palac
Kultury, Warsaw. For the Unecco Courrier only;
"RUSH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10 (zl. 60.).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda. Livraria Portu¬
gal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115.
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. SOUTHERN RHODESIA.
Textbook Sates (PVT) Ltd., 67, Union Avenue, Salisbury.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P. O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications : A/B CE.
Fntzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stock¬
holm 16. For the Unesco Courier: The United,
Nations Association of Sweden, Vasagacan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse, Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit Mansion, 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok,
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala (1 0/-). SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications : Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty) Ltd.,
Libri Building. Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only : Central
News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. (R1.-50).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38. rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent :
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES.
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St, New York,
N.Y. 10016($ 5.00). U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga Terazije, 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
Photo Unesco - Dominique Roger
BUILDING FOR THE FUTURE Grandfather and grandson
in an Iranian village.
]]>
</page>
</document>
