<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="015480eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^^ ^V A window open on the world
Courier
February 1966 (19th year) U.K. : 1/6 stg. - Canada : 30 cents - France : 1 F
-'v
Two
children
born
every
second
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
0
The Algerian Girl
(Modigliani)
Colour reproduction (55x 32,7 cm;
21 y2 x 13 in.). Publisher. Verlag
Anton Schrolland C°. Vienna (Austria)
Price $ 8.50.
Wallraf-Richartz Museum, Cologne
(Federal Republic of Germany)
Modern techniques have brought high-quality colour prints of masterpieces, such as this portrait of an Algerian girl by
Amedeo Modigliani, within the reach of a wide public. Modigliani, an Italian painter who worked in Paris,
failed to achieve fame during his short life (1884-1920). But today his portraits and figure studies are classed
among the most prized works of museums and private collections.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
DOW Ort« O« TMI WO« 10
rier
FEBRUARY 1966 - 19TH YEAR
Page
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg. ; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
¿years :27/-stg.; 18 F. Single copies 1/6-stg.;
30 cents; 1 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line. reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus da'te of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied to editors on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
tne opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly In The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', F/ance
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Japanese Edition
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Italian Edition :
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
Allcorrespondence shouldbe addressedto the Editor-In- Chiet
10
12
16
20
21
25
27
30
31
31
33
34
OUR SHRINKING PLANET
By Erik N. Valters
TO BE OR NOT TO BE
That will be the question
By Binay Ranjan Sen
AN EQUILIBRIUM OR ELSE...
By Arnold Toynbee
TALES FROM MANY CITIES
INTERNATIONAL RICE YEAR
THE WORLD HEADING FOR A COLLISION
By Gunnar Myrdal
HONG KONG, A THIRSTY CITY
By W. H. Owens
OUR PINT-SIZE ANCESTORS
By Vladimir Vlastovsky
YOUTH 1966
A message from the Director-General of Unesco
United Nations Charter for Youth
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
KEY TO INTERPLANETARY MESSAGE
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Cover photo
All parents like this Liberian
mother and child want their
children to grow up under the
most favourable conditions of
health and security in order
to enjoy a rich and fruitful
life. But every year the
world's population is growing
by 60 million persons. Whe¬
ther or not this is really a
threat is examined in this
issue along with some of the
possible consequences of th,e
population expansion today
and in the foreseeable future.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
OUR
SHRINKING
PLANE
by Eric N. Valters
ODAY, there are 60 million more people in our
world than there were only a year ago.
If this trend continues the world's population will surpass
the 7,000 million mark within a generation, by the year 2000
more than doubling the number of people alive today
and doubling also mankind's needs for food and shelter,
fuel and clothing, and all the other things that go into the
making of a decent human life.
During the month of September last year, more than
800 men and women from almost 90 countries met in
Belgrade, Yugoslavia to attend the Second World Population
Conference sponsored by the United Nations. They came,
not as representatives of their governments but in their
individual capacity as specially qualified doctors and statis¬
ticians, economists and lawyers but most of all as demo¬
graphers, experts in population questions.
Their theme: the world's population, and its unprecedented
growth in recent years. They, adopted no recommendations
and took no decisions. Rather, they confined themselves
to a thorough debate and exchange of views, aware that
no country in the world would want to have a population
policy dictated to it from outside.
But even without decisions it was a most important meet¬
ing by virtue of the fact that it conclusively showed the
existence of a world-wide awareness of the population
problem, of world-wide concern with it. And this in itself
is something relatively new.
As put by one participant, Dr. Bakari Kamian, an educa¬
tionist from the Republic of Mali: "At present the develop¬
ment of the growth of the world population is such that
it poses very important problems. If this growth continues,
it will pose problems of such gravity as to affect the very
fate of mankind, even raising the question of man's survival."
From Asia came this view from Anup Dutta Sharma, an
economist from India: "This rapid growth of world popula¬
tion and its growing imbalances in the different regions
is the cause of human anxiety and sufferings, and this
may cause political and social conflicts."
An economist from Chile, Dr. Julio Morales, highlighted
the problem as it affects Latin America in these words: "In
its history, Latin America has never experienced a demo¬
graphic growth as high as the one now in existence. In
fact, it is not only the highest in Latin American history;
at the same time it is the highest in the world."
4
ERIK N. VALTERS is a staff member of the United Nations.
This article is an adaptation of two U.N. radio programmes written
by Mr. Valters for the series "Perspective Sixty-Five" on the basis
of interviews and statements recorded for U.N. Television and
U.N. Radio at the time of the Second World Population Conference
in Belgrade last September.
From the Soviet Union, a Moscow demographer, Dimitri
Valentey, expressed a different point of view: "We con¬
sider that there is no basis for pessimism," he said. "We
consider that the human mind can ensure that the growing
world population will have the energy, mineral, and water
resources and all the other things which it will need."
In the keynote address to the Conference, delivered by
Dr. B. R. Sen, Director-General of the U.N. Food and Agri¬
culture Organization there was, however, a marked element
of concern indeed alarm about the eventual results of
the rapid growth of the world population.
"It is a simple arithmetical calculation," said Dr. Sen, "that
if food output everywhere just kept pace with population
growth at the present level of consumption, by the end
of this century the number of people who would be subject
to hunger and malnutrition would be double what it is
today." (See text page 10).
I N addition to food, there is also the growing
need for housing, clothing, fuel, education. Can
the world provide all these to an expanding population? On
this crucial question, these were differences of opinion,
strongly held, among the participants in the world Population
Conference.
Professor Alfred Sauvy of France, one of the world's fore¬
most demographers, described this disagreement during a
U.N. television interview in these terms: "We do not agree
for various reasons, because, after all, in the heart of
every scientist there exists a sentiment which more or
less dominates his mind more or less consciously. In parti¬
cular, there are optimists and pessimists. There are those
who believe in future progress progress which has not
yet been achieved but which should be there at the
appointed time. And there are those who, like Doubting
Thomas, only believe what they see and what they touch,
and who say that which they see and which they touch
does not suffice to provide 3,000 million human beings with
the 2,500 calories a day and with the many other things
which they need."
This kind of disagreement, of shall we say, difference in
emphasis, found among experts, is exemplified by the two
following points of view. The first by Professor Philip
M. Häuser, of the University of Chicago: "If you assume
that all of the world's resources, present total product, all
goods and services produced, were available, and then
ask how many people could the world support at the
European level of living, the answer is: about 1,500 million,
and we already have a population of 3,200 million.
"If you ask what can the total world product support
at the North American level of living, the level of living
CONT'D ON PAGE 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
CHÜd'UNE
ARRIVAL * OOWTUfrí
Japan
(259 persons
per square
kilometre)
is making a
determined effort
to keep its
population under
100 million.
It has cut its
annual population
increase by half
In the past
15 years.
Picture on
right symbolizes
population pressure
in Japan and
other countries.
White-gloved
guards are
used in Tokyo
stations to
"help" passengers
Into trains.
© Dalmas, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
OUR SHRINKING PLANET (Cont'd)
6
in Canada and in the United States, the answer is: only
500 million, and we have 3,200 million."
"Now, if everybody on this earth lived at the level of
living, let us say, of South-East Asia, then we can stand
many more people than the earth already has. So there
is no one answer to this question. But this is clear: with
present rates of growth and with the present population
of the globe, it is going to be extraordinarily difficult to
raise levels of living in the developing areas very much
during the remainder of this century, unless rates of popu¬
lation growth are decreased."
Dimitri Valentey, Chairman of the Council of Population
Problems of the U.S.S.R. Ministry of High and Secondary
Specialized Education, in Moscow, has summed up the
second view in the following words: "Potential geological
world resources of oil are estimated at 250-300 thousand
million tons or more. Potential geological resources of
natural gas exceed 200 billion cubic metres. Nor must we
forget atomic energy which increasingly takes its place in
the world's energy balance. Finally, there are the sources
of energy which we call 'exotic'. I mean the forces of the
wind. and of the sea tides, the temperature difference at
various depths in the oceans, and lastly, the energy of
the sun. Energy is life, and we have enough energy on
earth and in our universe to provide human life with every¬
thing necessary 100, 200 or 1,000 years hence."
The highest birth rates obtain in the world's developing
regions: rates averaging 3 per cent per year, as compared
to 1.3 per cent in the already industrialized countries. And
so the question naturally arises (and was also discussed in
Belgrade): can these developing nations which are despe¬
rately trying to improve their living standards attain this
goal while maintaining their current high birth rate?
The answer to this question is by no means obvious,
because experts today agree that there was and there Is
no constant and significant direct effect of population
increase on the rate of rise of per capita production.
As put In Belgrade by Professor Simon Kuznets of
Harvard University in the United States: "In some countries,
high rates of population increase were accompanied by
high rates of growth in per capita product. In others,
low rates of population growth were associated with low
rates of growth in per capita product. In still others, low
rates of population increase were combined with high
rates of growth in per capita product. This diversity of
relations is found in countries within both the developed
and the developing regions."
On the other hand, it must also be said (it was In
fact said by Professor Kuznets) that a rate of population
increase which is high in absolute terms, such as that In
many developing countries, might well be a problem.
This was confirmed in Belgrade by numerous participants
from the developing countries.
For example, from Mali, with an annual population
Increase of 31 per cent, Balari Kamian, Director General
of the Ecole Normale Supérieure in Bamako, declared:
"We have to build many more schools, build many more
hospitals and sanitary installations to take care of the
human beings who come into this world. We must also
provide for future investments to be able to employ these
young people once they have reached the working age.
And we must provide for other investments to open up
new opportunities and, above all, to solve the problem
of additional supplies that will be needed."
Professor Sohandal Nagda of Bhopal in India, spoke about
his country's population growth rate and its effect on India's
economic development: "The growth rate currently is placed
at the figure of 2.5 per cent per annum by some. This
growth rate as a rate is high, without doubt; applied to
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
IN THE PAST 10 YEARS
The world's population increased by
480,000,000
or more than the total population of India
or of Europe (excluding the U.S.S.R.)
IN 3 YEARS (1960 to 1963
The world's population increased by
170,000,000
or as much as the combined populations
of Japan and Brazil
India's 475 million people at the moment, it presents a
colossal problem and a great obstacle to India's effort to
improve its lot. In fact, India is adding to its numbers
11 million persons every year. Any increases in the
national output have to be put side by side with the needs
of increasing numbers."
India's Deputy Minister of Health, Mrs. Soundram T.S. Ra-
machandran, who also attended the Conference, had this to
say on the subject: "We are developing fast as far as in¬
dustries, irrigation, and so many other conveniences are
concerned. There is a planned programme. But there are
11 million children born every year. Just these figures
upset that planning. Therefore family planning has become
a national programme, so that planning the family and plan¬
ning for the nation can go hand in hand and show good
results."
Birth control or family planning is a very touchy and
sensitive issue in many parts of the world both advocated
and rejected on the basis of convictions which are deeply
held.
Addressing the opening meeting of the Second World
Population Conference, Philippe de Seynes, United Nations
Under-Secretary for Economic and Social Affairs, emphasiz¬
ed that the United Nations itself was neutral on the
subject of birth control out of respect for all beliefs and
in view of the present state of our knowledge. But he said:
"We cannot fail to mention the fact that some govern¬
ments, representing a considerable proportion of the world's
population, are now engaged, by means of birth control
methods, in trying to curb a population growth which has
acquired an alarming momentum.
"They have reached the conclusion, in some cases after
much hesitation and heart-searching, that at the present
rate of their population growth, too great a part of their
total product is inevitably channelled toward the needs of
the most elementary consumption, and that capital formation
is dangerously slowed down; in some instances, the prob¬
lem is even seen in terms of sheer survival." And the UN
Under-Secretary added: "We are ready to respond to
all requests for assistance from any country which, on
the basis of its own assessment of the situation, has
decided to embark on such a policy or to explore its
possibilities."
According to a statement made at the World Population
Conference, more than half of the people in the developing
regions today live in countries that have established
national policies favouring the limitation of births. Almost
invariably, the reason given for such a policy is the desire
to promote economic and social development without hav¬
ing to devote a disproportionate share of the increase in
the national product to the needs of an overrapidly in¬
creasing population.
However, some participants said: "Do more for economic
and social development, and the birth rate will decline by
itself, without any artificial measures."
This view was expressed, among others, by T.V. Ryabush-
kin, Deputy Director of the Institute of the Economics of the
World Socialist System, Moscow, U.S.S.R.: "We consider
that social and economic conditions are the decisive factor
for the demographic process. We hold the view that the
birth rate declines when industrialization takes place, when
women are involved in the process of social production, and
when the cultural standard of the people rises. That is
why there is no necessity of taking some special measures
which could artificially decrease the birth rate further."
Artificial birth control has further been opposed on reli¬
gious grounds for instance, by the Roman Catholic Church.
In Belgrade, the Holy See observer, Father Henri de Ried¬
matten, urged greater respect for human life and more
faith in man's future: "The population problem is a prob-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
OUR SHRINKING PLANET (Cont'd)
Changing views on family planning
8
lern' of life, and therefore it is linked up with realities which
are essentially dynamic realities. It is from this point
of view that we approach this World Population Conference
with the wish that, in spite of the fears which certain
countries show with regard to the population phenomena
(which are disquieting but which must be interpreted in
a doubtful fashion), one should not lose sight of the fact
that it is essential in a problem of this kind to proceed,
despite everything, with faith in life, with faith in the
inventive and productive possibilities of the human genius,
and avoiding the risk of leading humanity into other adven¬
tures in order to escape from dangers which today appear
imminent."
Not all religions have a negative attitude towards birth
control and family planning. A Moslem point of view was
expressed by Abdel Moneim El Shafsi, Director of the
North African Demographic Centre in Cairo, in the United
Arab Republic.
"Islam does not prohibit any person from planning his
family," Dr. El Shafsi told a U.N. radio reporter. "We will
find that family planning was practised more than a thou¬
sand years ago, even in the days of the Prophet, and
the contemporaries of the Prophet have mentioned the
fact, and he did not prohibit it. And one of the greatest
theologians of Islam, about 800 years ago, went into the
matter very deeply and scientifically, and found it justi¬
fiable for anybody to plan his family, and even specified
the best method to be practised."
Have national policies favouring the limitation of births
had any effect on the birth rates? The answer is: they are
beginning to have in some places. At the Conference in
Belgrade, we talked to the moderator of a meeting on
fertility, Professor Ronald Freedman of the University of
Michigan, in the United States. He told us: "We are, I
think, going to see, perhaps by the end of 1965, certainly
within the next three or four years, for the first tim©
in the history of the world, an acceleration of birth-rate
decline as a result of a large organized programme in
LEADING SOVIET DEMOGRAPHER
ON FAMILY PLANNING
In the European and North American countries the
lowering of the mortality rate has been accompanied
by a lowering of the birth rate. It seems clear that
in a number of developing countries, too, the problem
of reducing the birth rate must find a place alongside
industrialization, social reform and cultural growth if
a sound basis for economic progress is to be assured.
In some of these countries the birth rate will be
reduced as a result of women participating in pro¬
duction, a higher level of culture and the development
of industry and urban life. In others, however, a
definite demographic policy to reduce the birth rate
must be considered essential. The example of Japan,
where the birth rate has been halved, is instructive.
The spread of the idea of family planning makes
for a richer spiritual life for the woman and at the same
time helps keep population growth at the optimum
level. Demographers in each country must determine
the rate of population growth that is economically
¡deal and must ensure that such rates are maintained.
Boris Urlanis
In a special statement to the Unesco Courier
four particular populations Korea, Taiwan, Singapore and
Hong Kong; I think we are going to have that develop¬
ment In those four places. Now, these are small places,
they don't constitute a very large part of the population of
the world. Nevertheless, it is a historic event that this
should happen, and it points the way to what may happen
in the other countries."
Another example may be India. This is what we were
told by Mrs. S.T.S. Ramachandran, doctor of medicine and
India's Deputy Minister of Health: "In India also, a declin¬
ing birth rate is being indicated, especially in Bombay.
It has come to 27 births per thousand, which is comparable
to any developed nations. And in the rural areas also,
where we are working intensively, within four years we
have shown a decline in birth rate from 45 to 36."
"When we heard that in some of the developing coun¬
tries they are showing very good results, we were happy
to tell them, even though we have not achieved such
O Magnum - Brian Brake
>* ; Liitö*i& ' «' ' ^¡¿¡Asilas 'i k'fc^?1
- tit i
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
results as a nation wide programme because of India's
vast country and vast millions; but still we are making
good progress in those areas where people are more
conscious of the problem. And this is sure to catch up,
so that we can achieve much in the next five years."
Mrs. Ramachandran told us that India's family planning
programme emphasizes two methods of birth control: an
inter-uterine contraceptive device for women, and sterili¬
zation for men. She went on: "The family planning
programme is very well received in the cities, but it is
equally well received in the rural areas also. You see,
there are various factors which promote family planning
in our country: the desire to have a better life; to have a
better education; and also consciousness to have a smaller
family, so that parents can give all the opportunities to
their children."
The delegates to the World Population Conference in
Belgrade tended to agree that, in general, the African
continent was under-populated and not over-populated, and
that some countries were suffering from manpower short¬
ages rather than from population surpluses.
In Latin America, however, the situation is different.
Though there are no national family planning programmes,
there do already exist in some Latin American countries
small experimental projects, designed to study the prob¬
lem of controlling the birth rate.
As a Mexican economist and demographer, Victor L.
Urquidi, pointed out: "Surveys carried out in Latin Ameri¬
ca reveal that there is a demand for information on family
planning. The governments are not yet executing policies
in this area and it will be necessary to pass through a long
period of study, of preparation, but there is no doubt that
there is already a consciousness of the fact that in addi¬
tion to whatever is done to stimulate economic develop¬
ment, there is need to convince the people that it is neces¬
sary in some way to limit the family, without, of course,
prejudicing the stability of the home or creating artificial
problems."
In conclusion, we should like to stress once again that
the recent World Population Conference took no decisions
either on birth control or, for that matter, on any other
aspect of the population problem. Rather, the conference
was planned as a forum for debate, for the exchange
of views, for throwing some light on one of the great
problems of our time while always reserving the question
of action, if any, to the exclusive competence of national
governments.
In the decade ahead more than 600 million will be added to the world's population more
than twice as many people as are believed to have existed on earth at the start of the Christian era.
Today, the population of India (below) grows by ten million every year.
PS
tf far:*' .A. t ' V> YV-
M ,*
UP
#
«
» hít
g»/ m ¿M f
W^Í0k4
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
TO BE
OR NOT TO BE
that will be the question
by Binay Ran]an Sen
Director-General, FAO
N
10
ATIONS are increasingly aware of the implica¬
tions of an unprecedented rate of population
growth for the future well-being of mankind.
The first World Population Conference which was held
in Rome over ten years ago concerned itself mainly with
the promotion of genetic research and the collection and
co-ordination of demographic statistics, and made a valu¬
able contribution to the international understanding of
population problems.
During the decade that has elapsed since then, the study
of population growth has assumed critical importance as
a major factor in determining the pace of economic and
social progress in the developing countries. Nevertheless,
it has to be admitted that while the consequences of the
continuation of the current situation have not escaped the
attention of individual scientists, historians and sociologists,
international organizations, including the United Nations,
had to observe great caution in discussing matters of popu¬
lation policy, especially those relating to population stabi¬
lization, in order to avoid hurting the susceptibilities of
member nations. The 1965 Conference therefore initiates
a welcome departure from the approach that has so far
marked the consideration of population problems under the
auspices of the United Nations.
It would, I believe, be correct to say that among the
international intergovernmental organizations which have
consciously and progressively approached the subject with
an open mind and have tried to set the problem of popula¬
tion growth in a proper and realistic perspective in terms
of their goals is FAO, the Food and Agriculture Organization
of the United Nations.
FAO's primary tasks, as laid down in its Constitution, are
to assist member nations to raise the nutritional levels of
their peoples through improved production and distribution
of food, to raise the living standards of rural populations
and to contribute to an expanding world trade in agricultural
products. In carrying out all these tasks the question of
population growth comes inescapably into play as a basic
factor.
The first opportunity we had to have the problem pre¬
sented authoritatively to our member governments was in
1959 when Professor Arnold Toynbee, the eminent historian,
delivered the first McDougall Memorial Lecture at the 10th
Session of the FAO Conference (see page 12). Professor
Toynbee's address made an immediate impact, but it was
clear from the reactions of the delegates present that world
public opinion was not yet ready to face the issue and
discuss the implications.
Two years later, at the next FAO biennial conference
in 1961, we invited Mr. John D. Rockefeller III who devoted
most of his McDougall Memorial Lecture to the theme of
population and food supplies. He said: "The grim fact of
population growth cuts across all the basic needs of
mankind and, more than any other single factor, frustrates
man's achievement of his higher needs." From the reac¬
tions to Mr. Rockefeller's address it appeared that the
subject was no longer anathema and that there was a
possibility for this problem to be discussed more freely
than before.
At the Economic and Social Council in 1957, and again
in 1958, I had raised the problem of hunger and want as a
reflection of underproductivity and pleaded for concerted
action by the United Nations family. In November 1959, the
FAO conference approved my proposal to launch the Free¬
dom from Hunger Campaign in order to create a world-wide
awareness of the perilous dimensions of hunger and malnu¬
trition and of the urgency of taking timely action tô avert a
deepening crisis. The wide support that the Campaign
received from its very inception was a proof of the growing
anxiety concerning the problem and the impetus it gave
has been growing ever since.
The year 1962 was marked by the historic pronounce¬
ments of Pope John XXIII. In his Encyclical "Pacem In
Terris" Pope John dwelt at some length on man's rights
and duties in a changing world. The great good man did
not live to see how profoundly he had stirred the cons¬
cience and thinking of mankind, nor to follow up the implica¬
tions of the great Encyclical.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The general world
outlook is
indeed alarming.
In some of
the most heavily
populated areas
the outbreak
of serious famines
within the next
five to ten
years cannot
be excluded.
And it is a simple
arithmetical
calculation that
if food output
everywhere just
kept pace
with population
growth, by the end
of this century
the number of people
who would
be subject to hunger
and malnutrition
would be
double what
it is today.'
The Encyclical states that any human society, if it is to be
well-ordered and productive, must lay down as a foundation
the principle that every human being is a person; meaning
that his nature is endowed with intelligence and free will,
and that, by virtue of this, he has "rights and duties of his
own, flowing direct and simultaneously from his very nature,
which are therefore universal, inviolable, and inalienable."
The first of these "universal, inviolable, and inalienable
rights" is defined as "the right to life and a worthy standard
of living", comprising "the right to the means which are
necessary and suitable for the proper development of life",
including primarily food and other necessary goods and
services.
The first of the "universal, inviolable, and inalienable
rights" is a dual right, not merely the right to life but also
the right to a worthy standard of living. The text of the
Encyclical does not itself comment on the implications of
the stipulation of this dual right, affecting, as it does, the
issue of the rapid rate of world population growth.
The problem before mankind is that whatever practical
new measures, may be taken nationally and internationally,
now or in the near future, aiming at the accelerating expan¬
sion of productive capacity for the provision of food and
other means of livelihood, a continuation of the present
trends of population growth may well lead to a situation
when "the right to life" of those not yet living, that is of
larger and larger numbers of future generations, will no
longer be a right parallel to, but will be in conflict with,
"the right to a worthy standard of living."
In 1962 FAO launched a number of basic studies relating
to its major fields of work in preparation for the World
Food Congress which was held in 1963. One of these
studies, "The Third World Food Survey," clearly showed
that 10 to 15 per cent of the world population are under¬
nourished, and up to half suffer from hunger or malnutrition
or both. This survey also furnished food supply targets,
both short-term and long-term, taking into consideration
population projections and the need to eliminate under-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
THE QUESTION (Cont'd)
nutrition and provide a modest improvement in the nutri¬
tional quality of the diet.
To reach the short-term target by 1975 it would be
necessary, according to this survey, to obtain an annual
growth rate of 4 per cent in food supplies in the developing
countries. This increased rate of food supplies has not
been reached so far in the developing regions; in fact, the
average annual rate of increase in food supplies during the
last five years has not exceeded 2.5 per cent.
It is against these developments that at the 38th Inter¬
national Eucharistie Congress held in Bombay in 1964, as
head of one of the members of the United Nations family,
for the first time I spoke candidly on the urgent need to
face the question of population stabilization. I said:
"The important factor to watch is that the development
of available resources and the production of goods and
services keep pace with population growth. Where there
is maladjustment between the two, famine, pestilence, wars
have in the past intervened to restore the balance. Can
mankind reconcile itself to this kind of remedy in this age
of science which has opened up almost unlimited possibili¬
ties for satisfying basic human needs? Can we any more
turn our faces away from the concept of family planning
when the alternative is starvation and death?"
In May 1965, a resolution of the World Health Organiza¬
tion authorized WHO "to provide, on request, technical
advice on birth control methods to its member govern¬
ments"; this is another important step forward.
Early in 1965 in New York I addressed the United Nations
Population Commission, and said that the prospect seemed
dark indeed unless there was a combined world-wide effort
to raise agricultural productivity in the developing countries
along with determined measures to control population
growth.
The majority of the Commission felt that the social and
economic development of the developing countries would
be considerably accelerated by population stabilization
measures and were definitely in favour of public action.
Some members, however, expressed the opinion that the
difficulties inherent in the rapid population growth could
be overcome by vigorous and well-planned measures to
promote economic development and not by attempting the
promotion of family planning. They would rely heavily on
the social and cultural checks resulting from industrialization
and urban development.
But what is the real issue? Is it what might be the ideal
solution in the long run, or is it whether in the cir¬
cumstances of the developing countries today, the growth
rate in agricultural productivity can be increased fast
enough to meet the essential food needs of the immediate
future?
It is now less than seven years since there was any
appreciable increase in food production per head of the
world's population, seven very lean years for the developing
countries. In two regions in particular, the Far East and
Latin America, per capita production is still less than it was
before the last war, more than a quarter of a century ago.
Many countries in these regions have been able to main¬
tain their wholly inadequate dietary levels only by reducing
exports, or by increasing imports of food, including in some
cases a very heavy dependence on food aid.
Where this increased demand is not matched by a
corresponding increase in supplies, food prices increase
rapidly. This has a particularly serious inflationary effect,
for in developing countries food represents much the lar¬
gest part of total consumer expenditures. Such has been
the case in India, where rising food prices are causing
great hardship to consumers.
The general world outlook is indeed, if I may say so,
alarming. In some of the most heavily populated areas the
CONT'D ON PAGE 14
12
TO ESTABLISH AN EQUILIBRIUM
ALL over the world till lately, and In most
of the world still today, mankind, in its
sexual life, has been following the course of
Nature: that is to say, it has been breeding up
to the maximum. To let Nature take her extra¬
vagant course in the reproduction of the human
race may have made sense in an age In which
we were also letting her take her course in deci¬
mating mankind by the casualties of war, pesti¬
lence, and famine. Being human, we have at
last revolted against that senseless waste. We
have started to impose on Nature's heartless play
a humane new order of our own. But, when
once man has begun to interfere with Nature,
he cannot afford to stop half way. We cannot,
with impunity, cut down the death-rate and at
the same time allow the birth-rate to go on tak¬
ing Nature's course. We must consciously try
to establish an equilibrium or, sooner or later,
famine will stalk abroad again. And here we
come back to the heart of our problem. The
death-rate can be reduced by public action taken
by the few ; the birth-rate can be reduced or
stabilized only by private action taken by the
many...
by Arnold Toynbee
... What is the true end of Man? Is it to popu¬
late the Earth with the maximum number of human
beings that can be kept alive simultaneously by
the world's maximum food supply? Or is it to
enable human beings to lead the best kind of
life that the spiritual limitations of human nature
allow? The first of these two possible objectives
seem irrational. What matters, surely, is not that
the surface of this planet should hold, say, four
thousand million instead of three thousand mil¬
lion living human beings; what matters is that
living beings, whatever their number, shall
develop the highest capacities of their nature;
and, if this is the true end of Man, what we
should aim at is the optimum size of population
for this purpose in the economic and social
circumstances of each successive generation.
From "Population and Food Supplies," the first McDougall
Memorial Lecture, delivered by Professor Toynbee in Rome
at the 10th FAO Conference on November 2, 1959. The
lectures were established by FAO to commemorate Frank
Lidgett McDougall, one of its founders and leading figures,
who died in 1958.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
THIRTY-FIVE YEARS
FROM NOW (2000 A.D.)
THE WORLD'S POPULATION
WILL REACH 7,000 MILUON
AND WILL NEED
60 million teachers
for 2,000 million children aged 5 to
14 (35 per class). Today there are 10
million teachers.
7 million doctors
to provide one doctor per thousand
population-the proposed WHO mini¬
mum. The world now has 1,500,000
doctors.
3 times more milk, meat, eggs and fish
than are produced today, if the people
of every country are to be adequately
fed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
^3
THE QUESTION (Cont'd)
A simple arithmetical calculation
P. Almasy, Paris
14
outbreak of serious famines within the next five to ten
years cannot be excluded. And it is a simple arithmetical
calculation that if food output everywhere just kept pace
with population growth at the present level of consumption,
by the end of this century the number of people who would
be subject to hunger and malnutrition would be double what
it is today.
The situation clearly requires specific production targets
on the basis of realistic figures of population growth; and
this again means working for a much higher rate of agri¬
cultural productivity in the developing countries rather than
attempting, at least in the foreseeable future, any significant
extension of cultivable land.
We have calculated that a sustained increase of 4 per
cent per annum in food production, as against the present
average of 2 1/2 per cent in population increase, over the
next 15 years, would be necessary to avoid any serious
breakdown of the current precarious balance between
population and food supplies. The question is, can this
rate be achieved by the developing countries?
There can be no doubt that in most of the developing
countries it should be possible to increase crop yields
per acre significantly by judicious investment of resources
in land improvement, application of fertilizers, use of more
efficient tools and machinery, improved crop varieties and
seeds, and in plant disease control. To start with, they
will have the advantage of underdevelopment itself as a
factor favouring a rapid rate of growth.
It is true that our knowledge of the basic factors for
improving tropical agriculture is still very inadequate.
But we know that there is enough scientific and technical
knowledge available from temperate zone research for
revolutionizing backward agricultural practices in most
parts of the world; in the initial stages all that is necessary
is to adapt this knowledge to local conditions.
The greatest impediments to progress however, lie in
social and institutional factors. The farmer, who for the
past centuries has remained static, largely due to lack of
incentives and to general neglect, must now be assisted
to step into the market economy with the hope of a better
return for his labour. He must be given price and other
incentives and also, what is equally important, adequate
marketing facilities for his produce.
Special attention will have to be given to provide basic
education to the farmer to make him more receptive to
new ideas. He must be given proprietary rights in his land
so that he feels that he can improve his conditions by the
fruits of his own labour.
All this will also need massive investment for which the
domestic savings of these countries will be inadequate.
We calculate that to enable the developing countries to
achieve a rate of growth of 5 per cent per annum in
national income, the amount of foreign capital inflow by
1975 should reach about 50 billion dollars a year (at
1960 prices), as against the current, almost stagnant, rate
of about 7.5 billion dollars. Much will also depend on the
expansion of export markets for the products of developing
countries, since the bulk of foreign exchange receipts of
these countries at present about 75 per cent are provided
by commodity exports.
Having in view the urgency of stepping up agricultural
production and productivity, FAO is now working on an
"Indicative World Plan for Agricultural Development". The
Plan is designed to provide an international frame of ref¬
erence for our member nations in their national planning and
one within which donors and recipients can see more
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
ft V
t
A*
>-
O Holmès-Lebel - Ray Pinney Smiles and expert care for newly-born children in a European maternity hospital.
Progress in medicine and hygiene
has reduced infant mortality in more than 60 per cent
of the countries of the world since 1960.
clearly the priorities in respect of agricultural development
in developing countries.
As we know development policies are determined and
implemented by national governments, acting either unila¬
terally or in concert with other governments in regional or
other groupings, or as members of world bodies which
influence international policies.
The Indicative World Plan will not imply any departure
from this fundamental principle of national and international
action for development. It will exert an influence to the
extent that its analyses and recommendations enjoy the
confidence of governments and of the bilateral and multi¬
lateral agencies dispensing aid. The success of the plan
will of course depend on the co-operation and participation
of all concerned in its formulation and application.
What then is the answer to the question I have posed?
Taking all relevant factors into account, can we expect the
growth rate in agricultural productivity in developing
countries to keep pace with the population growing at the
present rate?
If we go by the experience of some countries who have
gone through this process of development, the prospect is
by no means reassuring. It took Japan more than 40 years,
beginning from the third quarter of the last century, to
double her agricultural production the average annual rate
of increase did not exceed 2 per cent. The population
growth in Japan during this period was below one per cent
per annum. There was also a parallel growth of industriali¬
zation which relieved land of the population pressure.
The experience of the Soviet Union, which started with the
advantage of vast unused and under-used physical resour¬
ces, has not been any better.
I can therefore only repeat what 1 said to the U.N. Popu¬
lation Commission: "One is left wondering whether the
large increases can in fact be achieved over a decade
or so. Doubts arise because the necessary effort to reach
the targets may not be made. The financial resources
required may not be forthcoming. A sustained effort to
expand production may be lost in a feeling of despair."
The question of population stabilization must therefore
be viewed against this background. The demographers will
tell us that for the next 20 or 25 years the current pattern
of short-run growth in population is likely to continue more
or less unchanged. Despite all these so-called food
"surpluses" that we can possibly muster, the hard possibi¬
lities are that we may not be able to forestall and avoid
some large-scale breakdowns in the next few decades, at
least in some parts of the world. The greatest danger in
that respect lies in the Far East.
Yet if such large-scale breakdowns are to be brought
within a measure of control, then, side by side with a
concerted effort to increase productivity of agriculture in
the developing countries, population stabilization must be
undertaken simultaneously as a social policy of urgent
priority without further delay. It should be undertaken
nationally under the moral leadership of national leaders
on as wide a scale as possible, supported internationally,
not only through provision of scientific information but
also with the necessary equipment and trained staff as well
as finance.
The next two or three decades will be a critical period
in man's history, and will either see the beginning of
mankind as a whole taking responsibility for its destiny
or the drift towards disaster. But inaction will be a counsel
of despair. Man with his inexhaustible resources of intelli¬
gence and inventiveness is capable of meeting the challenge.
What is necessary is to put moral ardour and unbending
will into the heart of this intelligence. Only thus will human
fellowship and human rights acquire their true meaning.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
TALES
OF
MANY CITIES
NETHERLANDS HAS
HIGHEST POPULATION
DENSITY
The most densely populated
country is the Netherlands with
356 persons per sq.km. (right,
street scene in Amsterdam and
an aerial view of the city). At
the other end of the scale with
fewer than two persons per sq.
km. are Australia, Libya, Mauri¬
tania and Mongolia.
The average world population
density is 23 persons per sq.km.
Europe is the most densely
populated continent with an ave¬
rage of 89 people per sq.km.
(38 sq. miles). Asia comes next
with an average of 64 persons
per sq.km. followed by Africa,
North America and the U.S.S.R.
with 10 each and Oceania with
two persons per sq.km.
"MILLIONAIRE" CITIES
INCREASE FROM 30 TO 8C
IN 20 YEARS
Some 80 of the world's cities now
have one million or more inhabitants.
Only 60 cities of that size existed in
1955 and two decades ago the number
was 30. These figures, given by the
United Nations Demographic Year-
book-1964, are based on population
statistics for the city proper and not
on those for overall urban areas.
MUSHROOM GROWTH
The population of Caracas, capital
of Venezuela, has quintupled in
the past twenty years. Cairo, Afri¬
ca's largest city, now has 3,518,000
inhabitants compared with 2,000,000
in 1947. The population of Bogota,
capital of Colombia (photo right), in¬
creased from 648,000 to 1,680.000
between 1951 and 1964. Brazil's new
capital, Brasilia, had only 12,823 in¬
habitants in 1957; today, it has over
130.000.
rates125 to 179 per 1,000 births-
are reported by Basutoland, Upper
Volta, Haiti, Turkey, Morocco, India,
the United Arab Republic and Indo¬
nesia. In contrast, infant death rates
have decreased in 113 out of
180 countries and territories since
1960. In Sweden the rate has been
reduced to 15 per 1,000 population
and is only slightly higher in the
Netherlands, Norway and Finland.
WOMEN OUTLIVE MEN
In all but four countries Cambodia,
Ceylon, India and Upper Volta
women can expect to live longer than
men. In the U.S.A. baby girls have
a life expectancy of 73 years com¬
pared with 67 for boys. In India,
one of the countries where expec¬
tation of life is lowest, male babies
© Shell
can expect to live 42 years and female
babies 41.
In some countries a sharp rise is
noted in life expectancy from the
age of one. In El Salvador, for
instance, male children at birth have
an expectation of life of 45 years
which rises to 52 years if they survive
until their first birthday.
For persons 30 years old total life
span expectancy is usually higher
than it is for those born today because
the older persons have already passed
through infancy and early childhood
during which mortality is likely to be
high. In Canada, for example, male
children born today can expect to live
to 68 years of age, whereas men now
aged 30 have on the average another
42 years to live an advantage of four
years over the newborn. Canadian
men who have reached 70 years of
age have on the average another
1 1 years to live.
16
62 BIRTHS
PER 1,000 POPULATION
The world's highest reported birth
rate is in Mali: 62 per 1,000 population.
Among other countries with high birth
rates are El Salvador (46.8 per 1,000)
and Mexico (45.1). Birth rates in at
least 15 European countries have
followed an upward trend in recent
years.
Infant mortality is high in many
developing countries. In Mali, the
Central African Republic, the Congo
(Brazzaville) and Niger, 200 or more
of every 1,000 babies born alive die
in their first year. High infant mortality
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Nationaal Foto Persbureau, Amsterdam KLM Aerocarto
MARRIAGE AND DIVORCE
The largest number of marriages for
every 1,000 persons in the population
is registered in Europe and the Soviet
Union.
Of some 150 countries and terri¬
tories, more than half report a
downward trend in marriages. The
rates have decreased in virtually all
countries of South America. In Can¬
ada, the U.S.A. and almost half of
trie European countries, however,
marriage rates have increased since
1960. A typical European marriage
rate is found in Italy and Czechoslo¬
vakia (8 annually for every 1,000 per¬
sons). Rates in other parts of the
world range from 9.9 per 1,000 in
Japan and 9 in the U.S.A. to 6.9 in
Chile, 7.4 in Australia and 8 in New
7ealand.
In most European countries there
are between 2 and 10 divorces per
5,000 persons. In the U.S.A. there
are 1 1 divorces yearly for every
5,000 persons. In South America the
rate is about one or two divorces
annually for every 5,000 persons.
WORLD'S 12 LARGEST
COUNTRIES
Km2
U.S.S.R	 22,402,000
CANADA 9,976,177
CHINA (Mainland) 	 9,561,000
U.S.A	 9,363,389
BRAZIL 8,511,965
AUSTRALIA 	 7,695,094
INDIA 3,046,232
ARGENTINA 	 2,776,656
SUDAN 2,505,823
ALGERIA 2,381,741
CONGO (Leopoldville) 	 2,345,409
SAUDI ARABIA 	 2,253,300
(Figures from the United Nations Demo¬
graphic Yearbook 1964)
HOW MANY CHILDREN
WOULD YOU LIKE?
"How many children would you like
when you get married?" To this ques¬
tion which the Czech youth daily, Mia¬
da Fronta put to readers, the majority
replied that they would like two child¬
ren. Responses to the newspaper's
questionnaire on marriage, which were
analyzed by specialists of the State
Population Commission, showed that
only one boy and one girl in 100 want¬
ed five or more children and only four
young people in 1,000 had decided not
to have children. Inquiries in other
countries among the population as a
whole show that in Austria, the Federal
German Republic and Hungary most
people want two children. In the U.K.,
France, Switzerland, Italy, Norway, the
Netherlands, U.S.A. and Ceylon the
average preference is for three child¬
ren. In Ghana and the Philippines, the
average couple wants five children.
© Czechoslovak Ulfe, Prague
WORLD'S 15 BIGGEST CITIES
If only the city proper is counted
and suburban areas are excluded, the
following 15 cities are the largest in
the world (United Nations Demogra¬
phic Yearbook - 19641:
Inhabitants
Tokyo	 8,733,000
New York 8,086,000
Shanghai 6,900,000
Moscow 	s 	 6,334,000
Bombay 4,538,000
Peking 4,010,000
Chicago	 3,550,000
Cairo 3,518,000
Rio de Janeiro 	 3,223,000
Tientsin 3,220,000
Leningrad 3,218,000
Osaka	 3,197,000
London 3,184,600
Sao Paulo 3,165,000
Mexico City	 3,118,000
Total urban population figures
including those of suburban areas put
New York in first place with
11,291,000 inhabitants, followed by
Tokyo (10.428,000); London (8,187,000);
Paris (7,369,000); Buenos Aires
(7,000,000); Chicago (5,959,000); Cal¬
cutta (4,580,000) and Leningrad
(3,607,000).
MOST POPULOUS COUNTRIES
Ten countries share between them
two-thirds of the total world popu¬
lation, according to figures compiled
for 1963 by the United Nations. The
ten most populous countries are:
Millions
CHINA (Mainland) . . . (approximately) 650
INDIA	 460
U.S.S.R 225
U.S.A 189
INDONESIA 	 .'	 100
PAKISTAN 99
JAPAN 96
BRAZIL 76
FED. REP. OF GERMANY 	 55
U.K	 54
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
TALES OF MANY CITIES
(Cont'd)
700 MILLION CITY DWELLERS
Nearly one quarter of the world's
population (approximately 720 million
persons) was living in cities with 20,000
inhabitants or more in 1960 a 35%
increase in the urban population
within a single decade.
The trend continues. Urban popu¬
lations are increasing at a greater
rate, especially in the developing
countries, than the overall growth of
world population. In some large
cities the annual growth rate is now
8 per cent. Pakistan estimates that
by 1985 its urban population will have
increased by 25 per cent in East and
40 per cent in West Pakistan. The
cost of urban expansion may absorb
half of Pakistan's development effort
over the next 20 years.
The large scale concentration of
urban populations is a comparatively
new development. Cities with 100,000
inhabitants probably did not exist
before the Greek or Roman period.
In 1800 there were 900 million people
on the globe. Of these, 15,300,000
lived in cities of 100,000 inhabitants
or over, 21,600,000 in cities of 20,000
or over and 27 million in towns
of over 5,000 inhabitants. Between
1800 and 1950 world population
increased over two and a half times.
But the urban population increased
far more rapidly 26-fold in towns
of 5,000 or more inhabitants, and
20-fold in cities of 100,000 or more.
CONTINENTAL INCREASES
Within the overall world population
increase of 1.9 peV cent annually there
is a great disparity between the rates
of increase in developed and deve¬
loping countries. The populations of
Latin America, Africa and Asia mul¬
tiply much more rapidly than those
of Europe and North America.
Populations by region in mid-1964
and their average annual rates of
increase were as follows:
Population % Annual rate
in millions of increase
Latin America 	 237 	 2.8
Africa 	 304 2.5
South Asia 	 943 	 2.4
Oceania 	 17 2.2
East Asia * 	 340 	 1.4
North America 	 211 1 .6
U.S.S.R	 228 	 1.6
| Q Europe 	 440 	 0.9
* China (Mainland), China (Taiwan),
Japan, Korea and other adjacent areas.
»«
"U'lllllllltlll!
"nullum,,,,,
minium,mu
iiiiiiimmimi
fiiiriiniiHiiii)
liiifiiria*iÍMflíi""<
11
II
II
II
II
II
III
ill
I.P.N. - Marc Pialoux, Parla
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
" ,,!,I,,,,»»mi
miiiiimimimiiiHiiiiiiiiiiii;,,,,,,!,,,;,
Ilfllllilllllllllllllllllt!
IIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIIHHIIIÜIIIUIIlMjMI
.
I
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL RICE YEAR
Rice is the staple food of one third of the world's
people 1,100 million human beings. At the present
rate of population growth that third will have become
one half of mankind by the end of the century,
and when that happens famine may be added to
undernourishment. It is for the millions of rice-
eating people of the world that FAO has dedicated
1966 as International Rice Year. In 23 rice-produc¬
ing countries special efforts will be made to produce
bumper crops (through the distribution of improved
seeds, better water managment, greater use of
fertilizer, mechanization programmes, pest and
disease control and more rational methods of
marketing and storage). Seven thousand varieties
of rice are grown from the Equator to Czechoslovakia
and Hungary, from the tropical swamps of Liberia
to the Himalayas. A word-wide campaign has now
been launched. Special aid will be available to
rice-growers. Experimental stations will be increas¬
ed and demonstrations given of machinery and
cultivation techniques. To meet the challenge of
growing food needs, Asia has in a decade added
more than 25 million acres . to her paddy, Latin
America more than four million acres and Africa
about 750,000 acres. Some countries can point to
spectacular results: production doubled since 1954
in the United Arab Republic, for example. In the
world as a whole production has increased 25%
in ten years, but it is still insufficient, and in many
countries the annual harvest still fails to meet
national needs. Yields per acre are two to three
times higher in the economically developed countries
(Europe, North America and Australia) than in the
developing countries. Only by the use of science
and technology can the rice needs of tomorrow's
populations be met.
,f*
; V
;«fS> :/ -~rs :
I H \
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
THE WORLD IS
HEADING FOR
A COLLISION
by Gunnar Myrdal
WE must have the candour to face the fact that,
as a prominent American agricultural econo¬
mist, Professor Earl L. Butz, has expressed it: "The world is
on a collision course. When the massive force of an
exploding world population meets the much more stable
trend line of world food production, something must give.
Unless we give increased attention now to the softening of
the impending collision, many parts of the world within
a decade will be skirting a disaster of such a proportion
as to threaten the peace and stability of the Western
world."
In contemplating the threatening world food crisis we
have to recall that in several very big countries like India
and Pakistan and many smaller ones, it would have
already broken out, had it not been for the availability of
large-scale food imports granted without foreign exchange
compensation, mainly from the surpluses in the United
States.
An intensification of the food crisis would create an
internationally intolerable situation. In spite of all tension
and clashes, we are now much more one world than
we were a generation ago. Communications have revolu¬
tionized our relations. I have no doubt that when the
crisis comes, people in the rich countries will suddenly
respond.
If the lid of production restriction is lifted in the United
States, food production could rise very much; Canada,
Australia and a few other countries are in a similar
situation. But we should not expect these countries to
send this food and carry the financial burden alone.
Other rich countries will have to share the financial
burden, but they will do it only if this food aid is inter¬
nationalized. Under these conditions it is well that we have
an international agency, working under the auspices of the
U.N. Food and Agriculture Organization, The World Food
Programme, already in operation on an experimental scale,
and that according to unanimous opinion it has been run
economically and effectively.
Internationally organized food aid, however, can under no
circumstances, be a permanent solution of the problem: it
GUNNAR MYRDAL is one of the world's best-known figures in
sociology and economics. A member of the Royal Academy of
Sciences in Sweden and former executive secretary of the United
Nations Economic Commission for Europe, he is now a professor
of international economy at Stockholm University. This article is
the conclusion of a lecture he delivered in November 1965 at
Rome under the auspices of FAO.
can merely bridge over an emergency. As a staff econo¬
mist in the U.S. Department of Agriculture, Lester R. Brown,
has recently pointed out the increase in grain consumption
by 1980, necessary in order to meet the expected population
increase and a modest rise of 10 percent in per capita con¬
sumption, would boost grain production requirements by
almost as much as the current output of North America
and Western Europe combined.
A similarly forbidding calculation could be made of the
shipping facilities necessary for an extensive food aid
program. The sharp impact of that type of flight into
fantasy is that, even if for a short time the first shocks
of the food crisis can be absorbed by aid from the rich
countries, the very great increase in agricultural produc¬
tion that is urgently needed if disaster is to be averted
must begin to take place in the vast underdeveloped regions.
How this is going to be accomplished is the main busi¬
ness of the agricultural ministries in underdeveloped coun¬
tries, of this organization, and of the present conference.
Even if reforms can have their full effects only in the
somewhat longer run, it is urgent that they are under¬
taken without delay and that they are planned in such
a way that they will have as much result as possible, as
quickly as possible. As a matter of fact, I feel much less
concerned about how things will look at the turn of the
next century. In the long run much will happen; we will
perhaps have entirely new techniques to produce the
food; the entire world situation will be different in all sorts
of ways; forecasts are bound to be proven wrong; perhaps
we may feel optimistic that things will in some way take
a radically new turn as we have often seen happening
before. It is the years to come in this decade and the
next about which I am worried. In the short run, our
forecasts are more reliable and they point to danger of
world calamity.
BOUT the policy measures to be undertaken I
will restrict myself to a few brief observations.
I want first to emphasize that, contrary to the experience
in the developed countries, what increase of food production
there has been in -the underdeveloped countries not enough
to match the population increase, but there has been an
increase has mainly been due to an extension of the
cultivated area, while the yields per acre have hardly
risen at all; this is true even in a country like India with
a very high man/land ratio and very low yields. New
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
HEADING FOR A COLLISION (Cont'd)
Have we passed the point of no return?
22
cultivable land is becoming scarce or else the costs of
cultivating it are forbiddingly high. Yields are generally
very low, which by itself should be reason for hope, if
there could be such a change in agricultural technology
that the yields would rise.
While, of course, there is much technology available,
the application of which is continuously proving itself to
be of importance, nevertheless there is to a large extent
need for a entirely new technology that has to be invented
and applied. This is due to two circumstances. For one
thing, most of the underdeveloped countries are in the
tropical and sub-tropical zones and there has been very
little of that specialized and localized practical research
which in the developed countries has made possible the
rapid rise in yields.
We are all aware of the disappointments that are often
experienced when applying fertilizers, for instance, or trying
to use seeds which should give bigger crops. Very much
more programmed, practically directed, specialized and loca¬
lized research into food production in these areas with
their particular climates and soil conditions, would be
warranted.
Moreover and this is too often overlooked even by
agricultural experts while from the beginning agricultural
technology in the now developed countries could reckon
with a decrease of labour in agriculture, most under¬
developed countries will have to adjust their technology to
an agricultural labour force that is now under-utilized and
for a generation will rise in numbers about as fast as the
present very rapid population increase.
FORTUNATELY, the road seems now to be open¬
ing for a much more determined policy of
spreading birth control among the masses. But we would
deceive ourselves if we counted on a rapid decline in fer¬
tility. Also, the relatively greater number of children, which
is a reflection of the higher fertility up till now, implies that
the population increase has a tremendous momentum. The
braking distance is so long.
This does not mean that a decrease in fertility would
not always and immediately improve income per head and
living levels, by lessening the dependency burden in the
families, but it does imply that the birth curve in a nation
will not be lowered as fast as if the age distribution were
a more normal one, adjusted to a more stable population.
Finally, the effects on the labour force are delayed for
fifteen years and will be very inconsequential for a whole
generation. The future workers are already born or will
soon be born.
To this comes the fact that industrialization in most of
the underdeveloped countries, even if it proceeded much
faster than it does, will not for decades absorb much addi¬
tional labour. I would like too to spell this out in a little
more detail but just cannot do it. You will have to take
it from me that the increase in labour demand is a function
not only of the speed of industrialization but of the level
from which it starts. Under certain circumstances indus¬
trialization will even throw out more labour in traditional
industry and craft than it gives new employment. This is
no reason for not trying to industrialize as fast as possible:
when once a higher level of industrialization is reached,
industry will increasingly employ more labour on a large
scale. Meanwhile, however, a swelling flow of refugees
from the countryside to the cities is not productive.
All this amounts to saying that agricultural technology
must try to increase yields per acre by putting to more
effective work a labour force which is now already under¬
utilized to a vast extent and which will be rapidly increas¬
ing for decades. This new, extremely intensive labour
technology is in part yet to be developed by fresh research.
A substantial and rapid increase in agriculture yields
has rarely, if ever, occurred in traditional self-sufficiency
farming, where illiteracy is prevalent and the relation
between the farmer and his land is such that he has little
possibility and little incentive to exert himself.
Among the several institutional problems raised by this
observation I would give high priority to the need for
land reform in the broadest sense of the word. It would
have a different direction in countries with different
systems of ownership and tenancy and it has to be accom¬
panied by other induced changes in regard to education,
marketing, availability of credits, etc. It must often be
costly in order to be effective in raising yields, and I think
we should begin to consider whether international credits
could not be given to make it more possible for under¬
developed countries to speed up land reforms and under¬
take all the other measures necessary to render these
reforms really productive.
But that assumes that these underdeveloped countries,
or rather those in these countries who have the political
power, begin to take seriously the urgent need for
reorganizing the relations between the toiler and the land
he tills. I think it is tragic and a contributory cause of
no small importance to the grave situation we face today
that local vested interests have made a sham of land
reform in so many countries.
FAO has for many years courageously and competently
laboured with land reform, and I have a feeling that in
recent years it has been reaping results in a greater
interest in many countries to do something effectively to
solve the problem, even if in other countries I sense a
tendency to try to forget about it and focus public atten¬
tion only on the more technical problems.
I fear that we are becoming accustomed to living
on happily and attending to the business of the
day while not giving much thought to the possibility or proba¬
bility of the unthinkable ahead of us. To this category I
reckon the outcome of the atomic armament race and the
less publicized preparation for biological and chemical war¬
fare; as time goes on without effective intergovernmental
agreement to stop this development, improvements in tech¬
nology must make it easier and cheaper for all sorts of
countries to equip themselves for genocide.
To this category of unthinkably menacing calamities
belongs also the gathering food crisis. We seem to be
taking the pattern from the entirely rational way in which
we as individuals live on happily from day to day and work
and enjoy ourselves, though we know we are soon
approaching the personal catastrophe of death. Otherwise
life would be unbearable; nothing can be done about it
anyhow; and our nations and mankind do not perish with
us but will survive.
But this attitude rational for an individual is danger¬
ously irrational for society, when we take it as members
of a nation and of mankind. Social catastrophes are differ¬
ent from the certainty of death for the individual, as they
can and should be averted. And if we do not use foresight
and take measures against them, we all perish and there
will be no posterity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
*?
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
	 	;:* ^
	 ¡r . 			
n	-ir--
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
In Hong Koitg,
one of the world's big
cities with
3,800,000 inhabitants,
shortage of
water has long
been a problem.
In 1963 a fleet of
water tankers
was needed to bring
12 million gallons daily to
the drought-stricken
city. Since
then large scale
reservoir construction has
improved the situation.
Photo shows
the new workers'
city with a monster
"wash" hanging
out to dry.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
HONG KONG
A THIRSTY CITY
by W. H. Owens
ITIES all over the world,
faced with huge popul¬
ation Increases that are expected to
double the rate of water consumption
within the next 20 years, are now
much concerned with the expansion
of their water supplies. Man's fast
growing demand for more water
everywhere, and the consequent need
to develop new sources of supply, is
the reason behind the International
Hydrological Decade, a world-wide
ten-year programme of scientific re¬
search launched by Unesco last year.
Many cities, of course, are fortunate
in being able to draw on virtually
unlimited sources of water from major
rivers or abundant underground
springs close at hand. But for many
others, situated in drought areas, it
means the construction and main¬
tenance of costly pipeline and conduit
systems to bring water across desert
or parched bush country from the
distant rivers and lakes. For all cities,
however, there must be increasing
expenditure on larger storage re¬
servoirs, more pumping and purifica¬
tion plants, and the wider extension
of water distribution mains to new
housing and industrial estates on city
outskirts.
Water is a most precious commodity
to the 3,800,000 people who live in
Hong Kong, the small, densely popul¬
ated island city and mainland territory
off the south coast of mainland China.
Shortage of water has been a perennial
problem there from the early days of
the trading port to its present status
as a highly industrialized centre of the
Far East, which lives by selling
manufactured goods all over the world.
It Is ironical that the great economic
and social advancement in Hong Kong
of recent years has made the water
supply problem much more acute.
Since the first reservoir was built
about a century ago, Hong Kong's
water storage capacity has been
vastly Increased. But the population
grows so fast that before one new
reservoir is completed, another and
larger one is required. With no major
rivers or large lakes within the
territory, its water supply depends
mainly on the annual rainfall, three-
quarters of which falls during the
monsoon season between May and
September.
This rainfall is by no means depend¬
able, however, and all too often the
monsoon period has passed with in
sufficient water stored, so that
additional restrictions on its use have
had to be imposed through the long
winter months. Indeed, over the past
thirty years it has only rarely been
possible to provide a constant
domestic water supply in Hong Kong.
Every available space suitable to
catch rainwater on the main island
has been turned into a reservoir. So
Hong Kong's biggest water storage
scheme so far the gigantic Shek Pik
reservoir completed in 1963 had to
be built on the smaller outlying island
of Lantau, from which the water is
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
In 1963 and 1964
Hong Kong suffered
its worst-ever
drought. Water
supplies to houses
were turned on
only four hours
every fourth day.
In the streets
long queues of
people lined up
with buckets and
other receptacles at
water points that
opened every
two days.
Government Information
Services, Hong Kong
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
HONG KONG - A THIRSTY CITY (Cont'd)
30,000 million gallons
of fresh water by 1968
brought to the city through a sea-bed
pipeline eight miles long.
The Shek Pik reservoir lay empty
for many months, however, because
the 1963 rains failed and Hong Kong
suffered one of the worst droughts
ever. For the third time in the
territory's history, water had to be
brought from mainland China by tanker
vessels. At great expense, because
drastic action was needed, the Hong
Kong Government chartered a fleet of
water-carrying tankers which brought
some 12 million gallons daily to the
drought-stricken city from the Pearl
River.
During the year the tanker shuttle
service made a total of 1,371 round
trips, bringing 4,228 million gallons
or almost one-third of the whole water
consumption during the period. Even
so, for more than twelve months the
city was strictly rationed to only four
hours of water supply every fourth
day.
Then, when the rains finally came,
in May 1964, there were typhoons of
great violence, and on a single day
no less than eleven and a half inches
of rain fell. As water poured into the
reservoirs, supply restrictions were
eased to every other day. But while
the heavy rains relieved one great
anxiety, the typhoons caused very
extensive damage and loss of homes
costing several hundreds of lives be¬
fore their fury was spent.
While the drought was at its height,
Hong Kong celebrated the completion
of the Shek Pik water scheme one
of the most advanced in South-East
Asiawhich cost £15 million ($42 mil¬
lion) to construct. The vast reservoir
can hold 5,400 million gallons of water,
bringing the territory's total storage
capacity to almost 16,000 million
gallons. In other words, it has
increased Hong Kong's available
water by about 50 per cent. Mile upon
mile of catchment channels surround
the Shek Pik reservoir to ensure that
the maximum amount of rain is
collected, and the drainage area
extends across more than 8,000 acres.
The Shek Pik Water Scheme was
something much more than a remark¬
able and complex feat of engineering.
It has changed the social and
economic standards of the people of
Lantau Island, where the primitive
way of life and barren landscape had
remained unchanged for centuries. It
has brought the villagers new homes,
schools, medical clinics, communic¬
ations and public utilities, including a
piped water supply.
Two small villages Shek Pik itself
with 200 inhabitants, and Fan Pui with
62 inhabitants lay in the way of the
new dam. The Shek Pik villagers
elected to move into new shops and
apartments at Tsuen Wan on the
mainland. But those of Fan Pui, who
wished to stay in the area, were
provided with a completely new
village with modern amenities just a
few miles away from the old and
primitive one.
Vast as the Shek Pik scheme is, it
is still not adequate to meet the long
Crowded on Its
island, with no
major rivers or
large lakes,
Hong Kong depends
mainly on rainfall
for Its water supply.
When the rains
come there are
sometimes typhoons
of great violence:
in a single day
111 Inches
of rain fell.
Air France
term future water needs of Hong
Kong. Engineers are therefore already
engaged on what is by far the largest
and most ambitious water storage
project yet attempted. At Plover Cove,
in the New Territories on the mainland,
a sea inlet of the coast is being
enclosed by a main dam, one and a
half miles long, and two subsidiary
dams. When these are completed, the
trapped sea water will be pumped out
and the inlet converted into a fresh¬
water lake.
By 1968 Plover Cove will, be ready
to hold 30,000 million gallons of
water five or six times as much as
the Shek Pik reservoir. Moreover, by
heightening the enclosing dam at a
later stage, its capacity can be
increased to 40,000 million gallons, a
figure which makes interesting com¬
parison with the 16,000 million gallons
total storage capacity of Hong Kong's
present fifteen reservoirs.
When the Plover Cove scheme is
fully completed, it will take the form
of a circle of tunnels 25 miles long
round the edge of Tolo Harbour, with
a connecting sea bed pipeline across
the entrance. Water from streams
overhead will be diverted into the
tunnels by a series of drop shafts
and branch tunnels. By means of a
complex system of weirs, gates and
pumping stations, the water can be
passed in two directions, either to a
treatment works feeding new service
reservoirs for the city or, during
floods, to a large storage reservoir at
Plover Cove.
For some years the governments of
Hong Kong and mainland China have
had an agreement by which Hong Kong
has drawn water from the Sham Chun
reservoir in Kwangtung Province just
over the border. This supply proved
unreliable, especially at times when
Kwangtung itself suffered drought. So
in 1964 a new agreement was made
under which Hong Kong buys a
guaranteed 15,000 million gallons a
year from the East River. This is
brought south into the territory from
mainland China by overland pipeline.
With this Chinese supply and her
own gigantic reservoir schemes
together with further projects which
are still in the planning stage the
long standing water shortage in Hong
Kong should be overcome within the
next decade and all future water
supply requirements in the territory
assured.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Museum visitors are often puzzled
by suits of ancient
armour. How on earth
did the sturdy
warriors of the past squeeze
inside such tiny metal
shells ? The answer is
simple. They were smaller
than the men of today. In
this century alone the
average man has grown
taller by from 7 to 10 cms
(3 to 4 ins). Armour shown here
is a 16th-century German
suit weighing 35 kg
(77 lbs) displayed
In the Army Museum,
Paris.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
OUR
PINT-SIZE
ANCESTORS
by Vladimir Vlastovsky
CIENTISTS in the economically advanced coun¬
tries have been struck by the fact that children
for the past one hundred years have been growing and
developing faster and are taller when they reach adulthood.
Doctors in many countries are working to determine
whether this accelerated growth is actually harmful for
the health of young people or not. There are many educa¬
tionists and psychiatrists who now feel that a reappraisal
and indeed a sweeping revision is called for with regard to
our present ideas about the physical and psychological
development of children, as well as the age when sex
education should begin. The rapid growth of children is
also having widespread repercussions in unexpected do¬
mains like the size of school desks and other furniture, sizes
of junior models of clothes for boys and girls, etc.
In the past 30 or 40 years it has been found that the aver¬
age height of new-born babies has increased by almost half
an inch (one centimetre) and weight at birth has also shown
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
i: 3333: TTTT xnx miimmmm xxrx xnx xroxnx -14- 1 ~r xnx xnx TTTTTTpi Xjxr. xrrr xxrx :
I44I--H44- 1 1 1 1 Tiii iiTÍ Ml 'TT' liii mm mTT. 1TI1 i i 4-44- lli ! T ' 1 ' 1 IT -
ixx
H
A
HAMBURG WARSAW
28
OUR PINT-SIZE ANCESTORS (Cont'd)
a slight rise. New-born babies now double their weight one
month earlier than in the past.
Compared to children of the second half of the 19th
and the turn of the present century the height-to-weight ratio
of today's youngsters has increased much more rapidly.
The differences are particularly noticeable at the age of
puberty as shown in the graph published above comparing
the height of 13-year-old boys in several countries.
Further information reveals that the average height of
these 13-year-old boys has increased by almost one inch
(2 centimetres) in a decade and their weight by nearly three-
and a half pounds (Ii kilos). Amongst boys in the 14 to
16 year age group the rate of increase is even greater.
Figures on 15-year-old boys studying in Soviet vocational
schools and boys of the same age who worked in Russian
industry in 1822 reveal that today's youth are on average
seven and a half inches (19.5 cms) taller and thirty five
pounds (16 kilos) heavier than their counterparts of 150
years ago. A less marked increase has also been noted
amongst girls.
Comparing the growth rate of children living in towns
and rural areas in various parts of the world it has been
found that children in large cities grow and develop faster
than youngsters in small towns, and small town children in
turn develop faster than those in rural areas. In some
countries a difference has been observed in the develop¬
ment rate of city children belonging to different social
groups.
One consequence of the increase in height and weight of
youngsters has been an acceleration of the advent of
puberty. A century ago European girls attained puberty
on average at the age of 16 or 17. Now it is usually 13 or
14. Similar findings have been made for boys.
Other indications of accelerated development in children
today are the earlier cutting of teeth and the ossification
of different parts of the skeleton, including the cartilages
at the end of the long bones an important factor determin¬
ing body growth.
This accelerated growth also means that children now
stop growing at an earlier age. In the past, growth contin¬
ued until the age of 18 or 20; today most youngsters are
fully grown at 17 or 18, and girls at 16. This does not
prevent them, however, from growing to be taller than
their parents.
Investigations carried out in the Soviet Union show that
for the past 60 years young people have been maturing at
least two years sooner than before, so that a 15-year-old
boy of today is as mature physically and sexually as a
17-year-old youth was at the start of the century.
Research in many countries, such as France, Italy, Poland,
Czechoslovakia, Great Britain and the United States, indi¬
cates that young people are now six to eight inches (15-20
cms) taller on average when they reach the age of puberty
than those who lived a hundred years ago. The average
height of adults, during this same period, has risen by three
to four inches (7-10 cms).
Many theories have been advanced in an attempt to
explain this quickened growth, among them the effects of
extra sunshine, improved diet, pre-natal care and even the
stepped up pace of city living. In my opinion the chief cause
is probably genetic in nature. In 1924 a Soviet scientist, Vic¬
tor Bunak, in analysing changes in the height of young men
of military age from several European countries suggested
that height and growth were not only influenced by economic
and dietary factors but also by the genetic changes resulting
from the inter-marriage of different populations.
There can be no doubt however that the material condi¬
tions of life strongly determine the growth rate and are
instrumental in favouring or retarding the genetically prede¬
termined potential for growth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
LENINGRAD
© APN
As to the psychological acceleration noted in modern
youth, all research conducted in this domain points to the
fact that the children of our times are intellectually more
developed than those of 50 or 100 years ago. But scientists
do not always agree in their assessments of children's capa¬
city for work or their ability to think critically.
Some scientists consider that physical and intellectual
development in children proceed simultaneously and in
harmony, while others maintain that the intellectual growth
lags beind physical growth.
The question naturally arises as to whether such accele¬
rated growth has a negative effect on the health of the
growing generation. The widely-held theory that an early
development of the body leads inevitably to premature old
age and a shortened life span has never been confirmed.
To the contrary, it appears that today's women, aside from
reaching sexual maturity earlier, retain the capacity for child-
bearing three to five years longer.
Futhermore, some problems of eyesight characteristic of
old age develop five to eight years later now than was the
case a hundred years ago.
Nevertheless, some scientists remain apprehensive about
the effect of this accelerated growth on health. They cite
cases of spine deformations, a tendency toward asthenia
(weakness and fatigue), an increase irTthe number of child¬
ren suffering from rheumatism at an early age and numerous
cases of hypertension (high blood pressure). So far these
apprehensions are insufficient for any final conclusions but
they merit the attention of biologists and doctors.
Educators ask: Is this early development good or bad;
should we be pleased by it, ignore it, or try to slow it
down? There is still no exact answer.
Did this acceleration really start in the 1830s, or is it
rather a process that has been taking place since the
beginning . of mankind and which is gradually gaining
momentum?
It appears that the changes in man's growth have their
ups and downs or so some anthropologists and medical
reasearchers feel. In the areas where archaeological and
paleo-anthropological reasearch have been able to trace
successive populations over millenia, scientists note that
the size of men underwent much slower and more varia¬
ble modifications.
There have also been variations in the age of puberty
among European women. It apparently was the same from
ancient times until the 15th century. The women of South¬
ern Europe reached puberty at 14, those of Northern Europe
at 15. Then it became increasingly late until, by the end
of the 18th century, it was reached at 17 or 18. But since
the 1830s the trend has been reversed sharply.
Where does the over-all acceleration tendency stand
today? Since it is slowing in some countries and social
groups, one can assume that in the economically advanced
regions it will come to a halt in the next 20 to 25 years. In
the developing countries, on the other hand, the next few
decades of improving economic and cultural standards will
be accompanied by an acceleration in the growth rate.
Will we then see a period of relative stability, or will there
be a decrease in growth and development? At present, it
is difficult to judge.
VLADIMIR VLASTOVSKY, a biologist, heads the laboratory for the 9fl
study of the physical development of children and adolescents
at the Institute for Child and Adolescent Hygiene of the U.S.S.R.
Academy of Sciences.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
TO ALL YOUNG PEOPLE
TWENTY YEARS OLD
A message
from
René Maheu
Director-General
of Unesco
for the
New Year
1966
AS the New Year begins, my thoughts and my good wishes go out especially
to you, young people all over the world, who will be twenty this year
First of all because good wishes are the natural companions of hope,
and you who stand on the threshold of the springtime of life are indeed
our hope. And also because Unesco is your age; like yourselves it will be celebrat¬
ing its twentieth birthday in 1966.
There is no doubt that between you and Unesco there are those affinities, that
spontaneous fellow-feeling which historians find in a given generation like the very
air it breathes. May there be between you and the Organization an understanding
no less great than this resemblance which will gradually be revealed in the mirror
of history! , ...
Meanwhile, you are a mirror for those who set up the Organization or who, like
myself, have served it from the beginning. In your eyes, which turn towards the
future, we see our past, and the way it will probably look to coming generations.
In your hearts, your souls, we see the value of our work.
For it was indeed for you, first and foremost, that the founders and original ser¬
vants of Unesco worked, and the true measure of our success is the contribution
we have been able to make to the conditions that ensure your dignity and your
happiness.
We are of course fully aware that our endeavours are not free of imperfections
and mistakes, and these we deeply regret.
I know that we have not wholly succeeded in persuading you that justice and
reason, tolerance and goodwill, must inspire your thoughts and govern your actions,
when, in the world which we are handing on to you, injustice and hatred, misunder¬
standing and violence, are still rife. We have not succeeded in making you bend
your energies exclusively to the work of securing the unity of mankind, which is
peacewe who still inflict on you the spectacle of our discords and rivalries. And
I know all too well that we have not given you equality and that in spite of truly
substantial advances we have not yet managed to provide for each of you sufficient
education, science and culture to ensure that you all have equal opportunities of
self-fulfilment.
-All this I know. But I also know, and can assure you with equal certainty and
conviction, that never, especially for the young, have there been so many opportunities,
so many means, so many reasons to give expression and reality to that humanity
which is in each and every one of us. Never has it been so possible, and so
necessary, to be a man, and nothingno lack, no flaw in today's worldmust turn
you aside from this inspiring and sacred task.
We live in an age when nature has been mastered, an age of which a great
scientist has said: "For the first time in the course of history, man on earth faces
only himself; he finds no longer any other partner or foe."
We live in an age when men are being brought together into a single brother¬
hood by the instantaneous nature of communication media.
We live in an age of tremendous perils which threaten the very survival of our
race, but, for that very reason, compel us to carry out a radical reform, political and
moral, towards a better and safer destiny.
And we live in an age when the reign of Man in his full universality is being
organized. States have set up institutions designed to establish it step by step.
The peoples of the world must support those institutions and help them forward.
Unesco is one such agency. Born at the same time as yourselves, it was created
for you. It has grown up with you, it is through you that it will come to be what
it must be to fulfil the great hope it carries of achieving peace through the conversion
of men's minds.
On behalf of Unesco I wish you, my friends, most heartily, a happy New Year
and a happy start in life.
As for Unesco, its future is in your hands.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
U.N. CHARTER FOR YOUTH
N December 7, 1965, the United Nations General Assembly
unanimously adopted a historic declaration on youth. The U.N.
Declaration on the Promotion among Youth of the Ideals of Peace, Mutual
Respect and Understanding between Peoples, as it is officially termed, calls
directly on the younger generation to help safeguard international peace
and security. "Young people," it declares, "must become conscious of
their responsibilities in the world they will be call upon to manage."
The idea and a first draft of a U.N. Declaration on youth were originally
proposed by Rumania in 1962, and the final text was adopted after four years
of discussions and consultations between states, U.N. bodies and youth
movements throughout the world. Unesco was closely associated with
this work in consultation with its national commissions and with the
Unesco-sponsored International Conference on Youth, held in Grenoble,
France in 1964.
In a message to Mr. Amintore Fanfani, then President of the U.N. General
Assembly, Unesco's Director-General, Mr. René Maheu, hailed the adoption
of the Declaration as an event of far-reaching importance, and the
Declaration itself as a valuable tool for Unesco in its efforts to foster
international understanding among youth. "1 think that Unesco's long-term
programme for youth should help to give practical reality to the
Declaration," Mr. Maheu said. "This programme seeks to help youth take
an active share in the economic, social and cultural development of their
communities and to participate in projects for international co-operation.
It also seeks to give youth an opportunity to use their energies for the
building of a more just and brotherly world."
Below we publish the full text of the six principles set forth in the Declara¬
tion which the United Nations has called on governments, non-governmental
organizations and youth movements to recognize and act upon.
From the Unesco New
O Young people shall be brought up
in the spirit of peace, justice, free¬
dom, mutual respect and understanding
in order to promote equal rights for all
human beings and all nations, economic
and social progress, disarmament and
the maintenance of international peace
and security.
Cm All means of education, including
^^ as of major importance the guidance
given by parents or family, instruction
and information intended for the young
should foster among them the ¡deals of
peace, humanity, liberty and internatio¬
nal solidarity and all other ideals which
help to bring peoples closer together,
and acquaint them with the role entrust¬
ed to the United Nations as a means
of preserving and maintaining peace
and promoting international understand¬
ing and co-operation.
©Young people shall be brought up
in the knowledge of the dignity and
equality of all men without distinction
as to race, colour, ethnic origins or
beliefs, and in respect for fundamental
human rights and for the right of peo¬
ples to self-determination.
©Exchanges, travel, tourism, meet¬
ings, the study of foreign lan¬
guages, the twinning of towns and uni¬
versities without discrimination and
similar activities should be encouraged
and facilitated among young people of
all countries in order to bring them
together in educational, cultural and
sporting activities in the spirit of this
Declaration.
Ck National and international associa-
^-' tions of young people should be
encouraged to promote the purposes of
the United Nations, particularly interna¬
tional peace and security, friendly rela¬
tions among nations based on respect
for the equal sovereignty of States, the
final abolition of colonialism and of
racial discrimination and other violations
of human rights.
Youth organizations in accordance
with this Declaration should take all
appropriate measures within their res¬
pective fields of activity in order to
make their contribution without any
discrimination to the work of educating
the young generation in accordance
with these ¡deals.
Such organizations, ¡n conformity with
the principle of freedom of association,
should promote the free exchange of
ideas in the spirit of the principles of
this Declaration and of the purposes of
the United Nations set forth in the
Charter.
All youth organizations should con¬
form to the principles set forth ¡n this
Declaration.
0A major aim in educating the young
shall be to develop all their facul¬
ties and to train them to acquire higher
moral qualities, to be deeply attached
to the noble ideals of peace, liberty,
the dignity and equality of all men, and
imbued with respect and love for huma¬
nity and its creative achievements. To
this end the family has an important
rôle to play.
Young people must become conscious
of their responsibilities in the world
they will be called upon to manage and
should be Inspired with confidence in
a future of happiness for mankind.
Knowledge of man
and the universe
On the occasion of the tenth anniversary
of the deaths of Albert Einstein and Pierre
Teilhard de Chardin, an international sym¬
posium on "Science and Synthesis of
Knowledge on Man" was organized last
December by Unesco at its H.Q- in Paris.
Among the distinguished scientists who
took part were Robert Oppenheimer, Julian
Huxley, Louis de Broglie, Werner Heisen¬
berg, Pierre Auger and Georgio Santillana.
Refrigeration
protection for spacemen
Refrigeration of spaceship crews may
be one way of protecting them against
radiation dangers suggests Professor No-
rair Sissakian, Soviet biochemist and mem¬
ber of the Academy of Sciences of the
U.S.S.R., in a recent issue of Unesco's
quarterly, Impact of Science on Society
$.75, 4/-stg, 3 F). In
Sissakian's broad re-
the issue deals with
the impact of television on society, progress
in water desalting techniques and the
expansion of technological education in
India.
(Vol XV, 1965, No 3;
addition to Professor
view of life in space,
Food helps build
schools and roads
Food aid worth $1.5 million from the
World Food Programme is to help build
roads and community facilities in the isolat¬
ed highlands of Peru. It will go to 4,000
workers and their families 20,000 people
in all. The volunteer workers are to build
1,452 kms (900 miles) of roads, and schools,
health centres and other community ame¬
nities. Non-food cost of the project will
be paid by the Peruvian Government
($2.6 million) and by a U.S. Export-Import
Bank loan ($2 million).
Pilot project
in chemistry teaching
Unesco is sponsoring a pilot project in
chemistry teaching for Asian schools. Tea¬
chers from universities in South and South
East Asia are now at work in Bangkok with
Unesco specialists, preparing films, pro¬
grammed instruction materials, laboratory
equipment and guides to experiments in
chemistry. Study groups from countries
taking part in the project will later expe¬
riment with the teaching materials and will
adapt them to national school programmes.
Thus by 1968 these countries will dispose
of modern chemistry teaching materials for
secondary schools and teacher training
colleges.
Prodigal use of oxygen
The earth's 3,000 million inhabitants are
consuming as much oxygen as 43,000 mil¬
lion persons according to the director of
the biotechnical Academy at Lauffen, near
Salzburg, Austria. Industrialization accounts
for the excess. On a 600-mile drive a car
uses as much oxygen as a human being
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
BOOKSHELF
READINGS IN THE HISTORY
OF MANKIND
The New Asia.
Religions and the Promise of the
Twentieth Century.
The Evolution of Science.
The Nineteenth-Century World.
The first four books in a new Mentor
paperback series edited by Guy
S. Metraux and François Crouzet for
the Unesco-sponsored International
Commission ¡for a History of the
Scientific and Cultural Development
of Mankind. The New American
Library, New York and Toronto; The
New English Library, London (7/6
and 95 cents per copy).
SIX BOOKS ON LANGUAGE
AND LANGUAGE LEARNING
The Practical Study of Languages.
By Henry Sweet (10/-).
The Tongues of Men and Speech.
By J.R. Firth (8/6).
The Teaching of English.
By A.H. Smith and Randolph Quirk
(6/6).
Modern English.
By Neile Osman (9/6).
The Principles of Language Study.
By H.E. Palmer (7/6).
Linguistics and Style.
By Nils Erik Enkvist, John Spencer
and Michael A. Gregory (6/-).
Oxford University Press, London,
New York and Melbourne.
To Accomplish These Aims:
Seven views on international co-ope¬
ration.
By Alberto Lleras Camargo, Moha¬
med Kamel Hussein, Gabriel Marie
d'Arboussier, Walter Lippmann, Mik¬
hail Millionshchikov, Allanhbuksh
K. Brohi and Edgar Faure.
United Nations, New York ($1.75).
The International Civil Service:
Its origins, its nature, its evolution.
By Georges Langrod A.W. Sythoff,
Leyden-Oceana Publications Inc.,
Dobbs Ferry, N.Y., U.S.A. (358 pp.,
$13.00).
Disarmament is Possible:
Special report by the World Veterans
Federation, 16, Rue Hamelin, Paris,
France. ($1, 7/6, 5 F).
South: Man and Nature in
Antarctica:
Scientific discoveries on the frozen
continent during the International
Geophysical Year. By Graham Billing
and Guy Mannering. University of
Washington Press, Seattle, U.S.A.
(207 pp, 207 photographs, $15.00).
needs in one year. To burn a ton of coal
takes the normal yearly oxygen ration of
ten persons. Forests and green belts, na¬
ture's dispensers of oxygen, are fast dis¬
appearing in the industrial regions where
they are most necessary.
New homes for seals
Soviet authorities plan to blow up rocks
on the Komandor Islands in the Bering
Sea to make more room for seal rookeries
in these long-established breeding grounds.
It is reported that sea herds, once deci¬
mated by wanton slaughter, are now
growing again as a result of a convention
signed by Canada, Japan, the U.S.S.R. and
U.S.A.
Science teaching
by television
The largest educational television system
yet planned in Britain has been ordered for
a new science building at Edinburgh Uni¬
versity. The installation will include nine
fully-automatic television cameras and 51
receivers for the distribution network linking
lecture theatres and viewing rooms.
Tanzania's
new community farms
Farm families at Miale, southern Tanza¬
nia, stand to increase their former earnings
of $60 per year five fold within three years
through organized crop-raising, improved
farm practices and co-operative man¬
agement of community affairs. Under a
settlement scheme financed by the people
of Ireland as a contribution to the FAO
Freedom from Hunger Campaign, 235 fami¬
lies have been settled on 20-acre plots
around three villages. They are growing
maize for their own needs, fodder for their
animals and tobacco as a cash crop. To
Ireland's $389,000, the Tanzanian Gov¬
ernment has added $313,000.
Mythical sea mounts
and phantom shoals
Oceanographers have been asked by the
International Hydrographie Bureau In Mo¬
naco to help remove mythical sea mounts
and phantom shoals from the world's nau
tical charts. Each year hundreds of ships
report seeing unexpectedly shallow depths
on their echo recorders. These may well be
uncharted sea mounts, but are more often
a dense school of fish or a plankton layer.
Even when doubtful reports are eliminated,
at least 40 or 50 have to be publicized
because they might be of océanographie
interest or mark a shipping hazard. The
54-nation Intergovernmental Océanographie
Commission recently urged members to
give greater emphasis to hydrographie
observations in research programmes and
thereby help to reduce the volume of doubt¬
ful hydrographie data.
Toy libraries
for Indian children
Toys instead of books go out on loan at a
new library in New Delhi the Chacha
Nehru Toy Library opened last year by the
Share Your Toys Foundation for young
people under 15. Chidren may take only
one toy at a time on loan for seven days.
If the toy has been well looked after, a
rose flower (Chacha Nehru's red rose) is
marked on the child's membership card.
And when a child has eight roses a toy is
given as a prize. If a toy is damaged or
destroyed, the librarian marks a cross on
the card. Two crosses debar the child
from borrowing toys for a month. However,
during eight months no one was asked to
replace a toy. The experiment in New
Delhi has proved such a success that si¬
milar toy libraries are planned for 10 other
Indian cities including Bombay, Madras and
Calcutta.
In defence of human rights
Over 100 judges, lawyers and law pro¬
fessors met In Vienna recently to discuss
international protection of human rights on
a regional basis throughout the world. The
meeting was organized by the Council of
Europe.
Danish aid for
teacher training
A grant of $100,000 from the Danish
Government will provide scholarships for
200 young Arab refugees for their first
year of study at the United Nations Relief
A PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT FOR THE UNITED NATIONS
The World Federation of United Nations Associations
(WFUNA), which celebrates its 20th anniversary
this year, is honoured on the first commemorative
stamp issued in 1966 by the U.N. Postal Administration.
A people's movement for the United Nations, the Fed¬
eration co-ordinates and fosters activities of member
associations on every continent and promotes research,
information and education about all aspects of the U.N.
The new U.N. stamp is issued in 5 and 15-cent de¬
nominations. As agent in France of the U.N. Postal
Administration, Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks all
U.N. stamps and first day covers currently on sale.
For further details write to the Unesco Philatelic Ser¬
vice, Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7e).
WORLD FEDERATION
OF UNITED NATIONS
ASSOCIATIONS
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
and Works Agency Teacher's Training Cen¬
tre at Ramallah, Jordan. In 1962, $145,000
donated by the Danish Council for Refugees
enabled the centre to double its capacity.
Schoolboy's water
desalting plant
Yaacov Wald, a schoolboy from Tel Aviv,
has built a small water desalting device
which won him a prize in the 1965 Israel
Science Model Contest organized by the
Weizmann Institute of Science at Rehovot.
Yaacov's device Is based on the principle
that water boils at a lower temperature
when the pressure is reduced. In his unit
a vacuum is created by suction and water
boiling under low pressure is converted into
steam which is condensed into fresh water,
heat being obtained in the process.
More U.S. libraries
Two hundred and thirty three new public
libraries and 124 new college libraries are
being built in the U.S.A. A further 130
public libraries and 161 college libraries
are being improved and enlarged. U.S.
Federal grants and loans for library con¬
struction totalled $212 million in 1965.
Greetings from the sky
Passengers on some 15 airlines have re¬
cently been sending Christmas and New
Year greetings to friends in all parts of the
world in the form of a long-playing record,
"International Piano Festival", issued by the
U.N. High Commissioner for Refuges. The
record, costing $4.00 or 30/-, features six
famous pianists (Claudio Arrau, Wilhelm
Backhaus, Alexander Brailowsky, Robert
Casadesus, Byron Janis and Wilhelm
Kempff). Proceeds from the "Greetings
from the Sky" campaign will go to help
refugees.
Flashes
The world has nearly 250,000 cinemas,
produces 400.000 book titles annually and
in ten years has quadrupled the number
of television sets according to the latest
edition of the Unesco Statistical Yearbook.
The newly-founded International Agency
for Research on Cancer is to make its
headquarters in Lyons, France, reports
WHO. Australia and U.S.S.R. have now
joined France, Fed. Rep. of Germany, Italy,
U.K. and U.S.A. as participating countries.
The world-wide Freedom from Hunger
Campaign, begun in 1960, will be extended
to the end of the U.N. Development Decade
in 1970, reports FAO. More than $405
million have already been contributed to
the Campaign's programmes.
Australia is to have an 84-inch optical
telescope the biggest in the southern
hemisphere. It will be built in New South
Wales for use by the Cornell (U.S.A.)-
Sydney University Astronomy Centre in
conjunction with existing radio telescopes
near Canberra, Australia and Arecibo,
Puerto Rico.
Youth hostels in the 37 member countries
of the International Youth Hostel Federation
now number 4,049 an increase of over
1,000 in the last ten years.
1-2 = 3 Did you decipher the
interplanetary message ?
Here is the solution to the interplanetary message (reproduced below) which we
offered as a puzzle to readers in our January issue. The message was originally
published in the "Japan Times", Tokyo, on January 22, 1960, and the solution
A B C D E F G H.I.J.K.L M.N.P.Q.R.S.T.U.V.W.Y.Z
mv n-i,',',"-flii,',i-'ca
n.'M-mi,','i'n:ii-i'inga
JKALAA; JKBLAB : AAKALAB. JKJLBN ; JKJKJLCN
? r.-'/r. i'fi.,1 a
» Enzammma
H^ll"-'ll'rflJI.'l'l,-lll"ll'lfl.llffl<lli,Kll
" f.'-'HWI-'IWr1
:qSSEHE3
was given the following week, when the author of the message, Ivan Bell,
explained how he had devised it. Ivan Bell wrote (in part): "We start with
the assumption that there are Beings living on another planet who are able to
receive our radio signals... At first glance the situation looks pretty hopeless.
We know nothing about their physical senses. Do they depend on sight, hearing,
a radio sense, telepathy or what? However, there is one ray of hope. We do
know that they understand physical science with its mathematical basis. Somehow
we must make use of this fact... Our only common 'language' is mathematics,
and as the situation is very difficult, we must start with the simplest possible state¬
ments and processes, namely counting and then adding.
KEY TO 24 SYMBOLS
ABCDEFGHIJKLMNPQ
123456789 10+ = Ox :
R = to the power of; S = 100; T= 1,000; U = 1/10; V=1/100; W = (decimal point);
Y= (¡s approximately equal to); Z = "jt (pi).
MESSAGE TRANSLATED
1. A list of the 24 symbols used the alphabet minus letters 0 and X.
2. Identification of the first ten symbols A through J with the numbers 1
through 10.
3. Use of symbols for "plus" and "equals": 1+1=2; 1+1+1=3 and so on.
4. Use of minus sign: 3 1=2; 4 1=3; 9 7 = 2.
5. Zero introduced: 3 + 0 = 3; 8 + 0 = 8, and so on.
6. Positional notation based on 10 is introduced: J = AN translates J into the
decimal form 10; 10 + 1=11; 10 + 2=12 and so on.
7. Use of multiplication symbol: 2x3 = 6; 5X2=10; 6X10 = 60.
8. Use of division symbol: 6-^2 = 3; 10^-2 = 5; 60-^6=10.
9. Exponents are introduced: 3==9; 2S=32.
10. Use of symbols for 100 and 1.000: 10x10= 102 = S = 100; 10X10x10=10"=
T= 1,000; 10X100=1.000; 10x1,000=10*.
11. Use of symbols for 1/10 and 1/100: 1-^10 = 1/10; 1/10-M0 = 1-M00=1/100.
12. The decimal sign is introduced: 1/10 = . 1; 1/10x2=.2; 1.4 1 = .4 = 4X1/10.
1/100 = .01; 1/100X3=.03; 1 /1 00"H0 = .001 ; 1/1 00-M 00 = .0001.; 10x5.678 =
56.78; 100X5.678 = 567.8.
13. The sign for "approximately equal to" is introduced: 79.98 = 80; 1,000 + 3
1,000. Sign for pi is introduced: 77 = 3.1416.
14. 4X-7TX.00923
3
The final item (No. 14) is the formula for the volume of a sphere; in this formula the
radius is expressed by the figure .0092. As Bell recognized when he gave the
answer to his message, there is an ambiguity here. The formula suggests that
an actual sphere is being described. If the receivers of the message are
on a planet in our solar system, they should be clever enough to deduce that
the sun's radius is providing the unit of length, and that the radius of the
third planet from the sun is approximately .0092 of the sun's radius. The
expression therefore gives the volume of the Earth in relation to that of the sun
and is the sign-off statement indicating the source of the message.
When the "Japan Times" first published this puzzle six years ago, only four correct
answers were received. As this issue goes to press, and with replies received
from three countries only France, Belgium and the U.S.A. twelve correct replies
have reached us. We congratulate these readers from France: G. Doyen, P.-J.
Féron, M. Peeters, F. Prudhon, R. Creton, J.-C. Froelich, C.-F. Durler, J. Houssain,
and E. Giraud (a 14-year old student from southern France who writes that he
will have to leave school this year because his parents cannot afford to pay for
his further studies); L Dessy, of Belgium; and D.S. Blacklock of the International
Language Review, in the U.S.A. Our twelfth reader, from France, signed his
name in code.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
COURIER IN THE CONGO
Sir,
As an inspector for commercial
education in the Democratic Republic
of the Congo, I use various Unesco
publications for their public relations
value. Following the revision of the
educational system here, one of the
subjects introduced into the pro¬
gramme was "technology", on which
no manual was or still is available.
However, the Unesco Courier is an
ever-inspiring source of material as a
base for discussion. Articles are read
with the greatest interest and inspire
teachers and pupils with new ideas.
Johan M. Baijens
Unesco Specialist
Democratic Republic of the Congo
NOT 'THE' HIGHEST
Sir,
In a photo caption with the interest¬
ing article on the Asian Higway (June
1965) I was surprised to read
that a road tunnel being completed in
Afghanistan to carry the Asian High¬
way through the Hindu Kush range at
an altitude of 3,300 metres (10,800 ft)
described as the highest in the world.
As a Peruvian I should like to correct
this statement. On the central road
that crosses my country through the An¬
des, linking the cities of Lima and
Huancayo, there are three tunnels
built at a slightly higher altitude than
the one in Afghanistan. Vehicles
have been using this road for a good
many years.
You may also be interested to know
that the Central Railway of Peru (over
50 years old) follows the same route
and passes through a tunnel 2 kilome¬
tres (2,200 yds) long at an altitude of
4,774 metres (15,650 ft).
Carlos J. Molestina
Turrialba, Costa Rica
CANOE-SHAPEP COINS
Sir,
Among the illustrations accompany¬
ing the article on coins, (Ambassa¬
dors of Art and History by Otto Paul
Wenger; Feb. 1965) was a reproduc¬
tion of four silver coins minted
in Siam between 1851 and 1868
(below). Around 1904 a relative
presented me with four of these
pieces of money representing different
values of the tical, two cup-shaped
silver pieces marked with the king's
head and two bronze pieces represent-
34 0 O.P. Wenger
ing canoes of different lengths, but
otherwise unmarked. According to
what I was told canoe-shaped coins
in silver had also existed, but were
transformed into nugget shaped pieces,
some of which still show traces
of the original canoe designs. The
nugget coins are of different sizes
according to the lengths of the canoes
and of course represent different val¬
ues.
G. Poirot
Pont-à-Mousson,
France
REVOLUTION IN BOOKS
Sir,
I should like to contest Professor
Escarpit's complacent remarks about
the interpretation of literary master¬
pieces on radio and television (The
Revolution Books, Sept. 1965). He
says that the interpretation...may per¬
haps be a misconstruction of the work,
but that it is certainly of the type
of those that have been called creative
misconstructions.
In radio, the cinema, or television
a creative misconstruction is such a
rarity that it is almost without sig¬
nificance. I do not believe that such
interpretations foster either the inter¬
ests of the original authors of these
works, or the interests of mass cul¬
ture. To create a literary masterpiece
sustained effort is required, and the
portrayals which are frequently made
in all these three mediums, rarely add
to the original author's work, they
do not create anything new, and more
often than not they present such a
superficial and desultory picture of the
work that the original meaning is
temporarily lost, let us hope not irre¬
vocably.
I must also take up Professor
Escarpit in what he says about
reading the books of films. I have
never seen a film which bore any real
relation to the book from which it
was adapted. One of the productions
of Wuthering Heights in the early days
of the cinema bore some ressem¬
blance to the original story, but I
remember only one scene that carried
any of the force of Emily Bronte's
writing. I have seen "good" films
which have been adapted from books,
but whose merits rested rather In
the camera work than in their making
a true adaption of the story, that Is
to say a small masterpiece had been
made by using as a background, a
story which had another meaning.
And in these instances I think It is
best if the films and the books con¬
cerned are regarded as being In
separate contexts.
The worst enemy in all this Is
television and I do not think It can
be regarded as any kind of cultural
medium until a great many Improve¬
ments are made In the programmes.
As to reading a book after seeing a
film or a production of an adaption
on television, I do not see how this
can ever be more fruitful, because
It Is difficult to detach oneself from
the images seen on a screen, and
the greatest works of literature are
great not only by their wording but
by the pictures they distil in one's
mind.
Jane Thomas
Shabbington
England
WORLD OF BEAUTY
Sir,
It is very difficult to tell you how
much I enjoyed the December issue
of the Unesco Courier. Just be¬
cause I did enjoy it so much.
Sometimes, beautiful things can
strike you with a strange pain. The
pictures of the sad, little figure on
page 1 and the majestic Maya head on
the last colour page did so. It may
be very sentimental but I wept inside
when I saw them. I was so surprised
to see the beauty of this world after all
this time that I was desperate be¬
cause of the "protest singers", those
youngsters who show you the world
is bad. Of course it is, but you won't
improve it when you are only bitter.
I think the Courier is doing more
positive work by showing people the
magnificence of this world and the
greatness of its cultures. I thank
you for giving me the opportunity to
learn that I can be happy with this
world. I hope that more young
people will agree with me.
Joan-Helen Zéguers
Berg en Terblijt (Z-L)
The Netherlands
A RAPID RISE
Sir,
The rise of Unesco Courier subscri¬
bers in Belgium to 20,000 last year
was marked with a special tribute
paid to Mr. Louis de Lannoy, general
distributor of the Courier in Belgium,
by the Belgian National Commission
for Unesco. Mr. de Lannoy was pre¬
sented with a medal at a ceremony
held during a meeting of the Belgian
National Commission.
F. Vendenborre
Secretary General
Belgian National
Commission for Unesco
A further increase has now brought
Belgium's subscribers close to the
25,000 mark Editor.
BURSTING WITH VITALITY
Sir.
I find the Unesco Courier a most
fascinating magazine; I think it very
fine to be able to read an Intelligently-
written article dealing with things of
vital interest. I wonder whether there
will be any articles on Israel In the
future? This Is a country which, to me,
appears to be bursting with vitality and
new Ideas, and would obviously make
wonderful reading.
Cyril Golding
Solihull, England
u
z
z
ci.
<
z
o
OL
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
JUST PUBLISHED
hSi I
!^2r «- 1 a a
Catalogue de reproductions
en couleurs
de peintures antérieures à i860
Catalogue of colour reproductions
of paintings prior to i860
Catálogo de reproducciones
en color
de pinturas anteriores a i860
A completely revised
and enlarged edition
catalogue de reproductions
en couleurs de peintures
1860 à 1965
catalogue of colour reproductions
of paintings
1860 to 1965
catálogo de reproducciones
en color de pinturas
1860 a 1965
«ctfvvv» - «
561 pages
35/- stg.
$7.00
unesco pans
Over 1,000 recommended colour reproductions,
including many examples from Asia, Africa, Aus¬
tralia and Central Europe, are listed in this beau¬
tifully presented, 379-page Unesco catalogue.
Each painting is reproduced in black and white
with full details of the original work, name of
publisher and price of colour reproduction.
30/stg. $6.00 21 F.
An up-to-date listing of colour reproductions of world-famous
paintings, with descriptions and black and white illustrations of
1,589 full colour prints. This Unesco catalogue is compiled from
the Unesco collection of reproductions selected by internationally-
known art experts on the basis of fidelity of reproduction, signifi¬
cance of the artist and importance of the original painting.
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
'Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
Boek-handel, Belgièlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
1 1 2, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Rangoon.
(	). CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
(Î 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir
Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B, 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 13/50). -CHINA. World Book CoLtd.. 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1,Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L..
Spalena 51 , Prague 1 (permanent display) ; Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks-
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47, Copenhagen S (D. Kr."17).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja-
kauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*. C.C.P.
12598-48. (10 F.). GERMANY. All publications:
R.Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich.
8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahren-
felder-Chaussee 1 60, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P.
27Í650 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd. Atlantis House Commercial St., POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road. Kowloon. HUNGARY. Kultura,
P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol
Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson
House, 1/24 Asaf AM Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New Delhi 3.
(Rs.7). INDONESIA. P.T.N. " Permuta-Nusantara" c/o
Dept.of Commerce, 22, D|alanNusan tara.DJakarta. IRAQ.
Mackenzie'sBookshop,Baghdad.IRELAND.The National
Press, 2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. 4. (1 5/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Ton-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph L. BahousSc Co., Dar ul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (1 0/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd. .Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore, 9; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (1 5/-). MONACO. British
Library 30, Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). - NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-).
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For the Unesco Courier also: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks
115 (17.50 kr.).' PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Pu¬
blishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box
374 56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILI¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda. Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA. The Book
Centre, and Educational Supply Co., Colonial Mutual
Building, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publi¬
cations : A/B C.E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1 21 1 , Geneva 1 1 , C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). - TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala (10/-). REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA. All publications : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pre¬
toria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Cen¬
tral News Agency P.O. Box 1033, johannesbourg. (R1.-
50). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librai¬
rie Kasr El Nil, 3 8, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 St. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St, New York,
N.Y. 1 001 6 ($ 5.00) - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Kn-
jïg, Tzrazija 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
2 babies every second
120 babies every minute
7,200 babies every hour
172,800 babies every day
63,100,000 babies every year
]]>
</page>
</document>
