<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="028352eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
May 1966
(19th year)
U.K.: 1/6 stg.
Canada : 30 cents
France: 1 F 4
Man and Space
A GREAT
INTERNATIONAL
VENTURE
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ii
ir
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART ©
© Jean Suquet
Gallic dancer
Though remarkably modern in appearance, this six-inch bronze statuette of a woman dancer
actually dates back well over 2,000 years. An outstanding example of early European art, it was
unearthed in the Loire Valley area of France in 1861, with other similarly styled figures fashioned
by Celtic artists of ancient Gaul. Celtic art continued to exert an influence in later centuries
and some of its outstanding characteristics are incorporated in Roman and Gothic sculpture
Orléanais Historical Museum, Orleans, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
MAY 1966 - 19TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7".
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg. ; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2years:27/-stg.; 18 F. Single copies 1/6-stg.;
30 cents ; 1 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) In English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied to editors on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly In The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co.. New York.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 1", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Page
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Illustrations : Betsy Bates
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
Allcorrespondence shouldbe addressedto the Editor-in-Chief.
13
14
17
19
24
27
29
31
32
36
38
THE HEART OF THE MATTER
Statements by Yuri Gagarin and Walter Schirra
A GREAT INTERNATIONAL VENTURE
The peaceful exploration of outer space
By A.H. Abdel-Ghani
'IT DOES NOT MATTER WHO REACHES
THE MOON FIRST...'
By Anatoly Biagonravov
'JOINT SPACE ENTERPRISES
ARE NOW A GOING CONCERN...'
By Arnold W. Frutkin
TRICKS PLAYED ON HAND AND EYE
SPACE FLIGHT AND THE RULE OF LAW
By Eugène Pepin
COLOUR PAGES
EUROPE'S GROWING STAKE IN SPACE SCIENCE
Ten countries pool their efforts in space research
By Pierre Auger
WHY WE ARE OUTWARD BOUND
The viewpoint of a scientist-astronaut
By Konstantin Feoktistov
FROM DREAM TO REALITY
LUNAR INTERNATIONAL LABORATORY
By Bruno Friedman
HEROES, HOBBIES OF JUNIOR ASTRONAUTS
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Cover photo
Astronaut's view of space and
earth photographed from Vos-
khod (Sunrise) I capsule during
a 24-hour flight on October 12,
1964. Ghostly polygons of light
are caused by rays of sunlight
reflected on spacecraft window.
Piloted by Vladimir Komarov,
Voskhod carried the first trained
scientists to venture into space
Boris Egorov, a research phy¬
sician, and Konstantin Feokis-
tov (see article page 27) who
took this photograph, and whose
studies in space included obser¬
vations of the different layers
of the atmosphere.
© APN
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE HEART OF THE MATTER
Five years ago, on April 12, 1961, Yuri Gagarin whirled
into orbit around the earth and became the first man in
space. We open this issue devoted to international
co-operation in space research and exploration with
statements addressed to the Unesco Courier by
two famous astronauts: Yuri Gagarin and Walter
Schirra. In 1962, Walter Schirra accomplished a solo
spaceflight and in 1965 he was one of four astronauts
who made the first manned rendezvous in space.
Yuri Gagarin:
On the occasion of the 5th anniver¬
sary of the first manned space flight,
I greet all who work in the field of
space research, and especially my
colleagues, the American and Soviet
astronauts. The age of cosmic flight
and bold research ventures in the
far reaches of space has begun. I am
firmly convinced that greater inter¬
national co-operation is needed for
the mastery and utilization of outer
space so that each manned flight
and each launching of a space
station or laboratory for cosmic
research can serve man in positive
and peaceful ways.
© APN
Walter M. Schirra:
It is perhaps an obvious fact, but
nonetheless an important one, that
there are no boundaries a hundred
miles up, and there are none visible
on earth when it is viewed from a
space capsule.
That the exploration of space goes
beyond political boundaries was no
doubt in the minds of the framers of
the Space Act of 1958. The act
which established the National Aero¬
nautics and Space Administration
and dedicated our nation to the
exploration of space included as one
of its objectives co-operation with
other nations and groups of nations
in the peaceful applications of our
space efforts.
NASA
A.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Man and Space
A GREAT
INTER¬
NATIONAL
VENTURE
by A. H. Abdel-Ghani
HE myriad of organizations, governmental and nongovern¬
mental, national and international, scientific and technical,
pursuing their legitimate interests in the field of outer space
exploration seems at times to be sufficient to fill the vast expanse
of outer space itself.
Each organization may be concerned with but a single facet
of space exploration. The World Meteorological Organization
follows with increasing interest the development of earth-orbiting
weather satellites; the International Telecommunication Union must
continually grapple with the growing problem of space commun¬
ications; the possibility of a navigational satellite system catches
the attention of the International Maritime Consultative Organization
and the International Civil Aviation Organization; Unesco explores
the potentialities of space communications for public information
and education; and the Committee on Space Research (COSPAR)
of the International Council of Scientific Unions is primarily
concerned with the scientific aspects of space research.
These are but a few, and one need only consult a calendar of
meetings devoted to aspects of space exploration to note the profu¬
sion of organizations involved and the variety of interests displayed.
One group, however, occupies a special position in the extensive
network of organizations active in this field. The United Nations
Committee on the Peaceful Uses of Outer Space is the only inter¬
governmental body exclusively concerned with all matters connec¬
ted with outer space activities. The committee, made up of twenty-
eight member states (1), has a broad membership which includes
the two major space powers and a representative group of countries
at varied levels of economic and scientific development, and there¬
fore provides an effective forum for consideration of the problems
of outer space. At the same time, the committee furnishes the "fo¬
cal point for co-operation in the peaceful exploration of outer space"
envisaged by the U.N. General Assembly.
Because of its central position, the committee is well placed to
make an overall survey of international co-operation efforts in the
space field; to provide a basis for objective, technical assess¬
ments of international programmes and their economic and social
potentials; and to provide a "rallying point" for the many organiza¬
tions engaged in this field by furnishing encouragement and support
on an international governmental level.
In undertaking these important functions, the committee is assist¬
ed by its two specialized sub-committees one scientific and
technical, the other legal and by a small group of experts in the
United Nations Secretariat the Outer Space Affairs Group. It also
benefits from the experience of the specialized agencies and other
bodies invited to participate in its work.
When the committee was first established, there were only two
nations capable of launching earth orbiting satellites and planet¬
ary probes, the United States and the Soviet Union. At this point,
there was no doubt in any mind that the primary objective for the
committee in this field was to attempt to avoid the .extension of
national rivalries into outer space and to ensure its uses for peace¬
ful purposes only. All plans had to reflect this overwhelming
desire and necessitated, therefore, taking into account the polit¬
ical ramifications of any United Nations action in this area.
(1) Albania, Argentina, Australia, Austria, Belgium, Brazil, Bulgaria, Canada, E
Chad, Czechoslovakia, France, Hungary, India, Iran, Italy, Japan, Lebanon, Mexico, **
Mongolia, Morocco, Poland, Rumania, Sierra Leone, Sweden, U.S.S.R., United Arab
Republic, United Kingdom, United States.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL VENTURE (Cont'd)
In this spirit, the committee submitted to the General Assembly
in November 1963 a declaration of legal principles governing the
activities of states in the exploration and use of outer space. The
declaration was unanimously adopted by the General Assembly.
(See article page 17).
In addition to pursuing its consideration of the legal problems
and principles, the committee has presented a series of recommend¬
ations on the exchange of information, the encouragement of
international programmes, the creation of international sounding
rocket launching facilities, potentially harmful effects of space exper¬
iments, and education and training which lay the groundwork for
further practical action to develop international co-operation.
Recently, the working group of the whole recommended to the
committee the holding of an international conference in the latter
half of 1967 on the peaceful uses of outer space. The conference
would have two objectives: an examination of the practical benefits
to be derived from space research and exploration on the basis
of technical and scientific achievements and the extent to which
non-space powers, especially the developing countries, may enjoy
these benefits, particularly in terms of education and develop¬
ment; and an examination of the opportunities available to non-
space powers for international co-operation in space activities,
taking into account the extent to which the United Nations may
play a role.
As the first decade of outer space exploration nears its comple¬
tion, it is clear that many nations of the world are now aware of
their stake in this new activity of mankind. The nations are deter¬
mined to build the necessary international structure which will
ensure the peaceful exploration of outer space for the benefit of all.
C ABDEL HAMID ABDEL-GHANI is head of the United Nations Outer Space Affairs
Group and secretary of the U.N. Committee on the Peaceful Uses of Outer Space.
Between 1949 and 1961, he represented the United Arab Republic on several
bodies in the United Nations.
FIRST OF THE MANY. Not long ago
the "space pilot" was thought
of as a character from science fiction.
Today, well over a score or men
and one woman Valentina Tereshkova
have flown in space, and many
more are being trained
to follow them.
Below, animal pathfinders
who paved the way for man
include dogs,
mice and guinea pigs.
Photos © APN
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
It d
w
w
is
to
oes not matter
ho reaches the moon
hat counts
the benefit
first;
man
by Anatoly Blagonravov
WE are now in the ninth year
of the Space Age, the
period of history that opened with the
launching of Sputnik 1 in 1957.
Nobody now doubts that the con¬
quest of space is one of the para¬
mount problems facing mankind today.
The leap into space marked an impor¬
tant stage in the history of civilization.
The most alluring prospects, hitherto
undreamed of possibilities, have open¬
ed up before man.
Space research is a branch of
science in which all mankind has a
stake. In the final analysis, the results
of the research should benefit all
people the world over, irrespective of
which country obtains them. The study
of outer space helps man understand
the general laws governing the uni¬
verse that surrounds us, the knowledge
gained promotes progress in science
and technology, and today scientific
and technical achievement reaches
most of the world's inhabitants.
Man today needs space research,
but the tasks involved, especially
flights to outer space, demand a tre¬
mendous concentration of effort and
ANATOLY BLAGONRAVOV, a distinguished
Soviet astrophysicist, is chairman of the
Commission for the Exploration and Use
of Cosmic Space, U.S.S.R. Academy of
Sciences.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
FOR THE BENEFIT OF MAN (Cont'd)
A gigantic natural laboratory
8
funds which puts it beyond the resour¬
ces of many countries. It is no wonder,
therefore, that the Soviet Union and the
United States of America, countries
in which science and technology have
reached the highest development,
should take upon themselves the main
burden of space exploration. Their
successes in this field go far beyond
the bounds of mere national achieve-
men they are of service to all man¬
kind.
Scientific achievements are signif¬
icant not merely because they solve
various practical problems but mainly
because they accelerate progress.
It took man many millenia to find
out what our earth is made of and
what position it occupies in the uni¬
verse; to learn the rudiments of mech¬
anics, physics, mathematics and astro¬
nomy man toiled for hundreds of years.
It was this gigantic labour that pre¬
pared the "way for the amazing leap
forward that science has made in the
past few decades, the leap that led to
the accomplishment of space flights.
In a relatively short time earth satel-
Unlted Technology Center
lites, spaceships and interplanetary sta¬
tions have provided scientific material
of tremendous value that would have
required long years of persistent and
often useless labour to acquire by the
old methods. Space research has
compelled scientists to reconsider the
physics of the upper layers of the
atmosphere. It has enabled man to
photograph the side of the moon never
seen from the earth and has provided
valuable Information on Mars and Ve¬
nus and on primary cosmic rays, solar
radiation, meteoric matter and the in¬
terplanetary medium. Space research
has also thrown fresh light on the ef¬
fect of solar activity on geophysical
processes.
Rockets and artificial earth satel¬
lites have given us ultra-violet ray
and X-ray astronomy, new methods
of studying the universe. The So¬
viet automatic station Luna 9, mak¬
ing a soft landing on the moon, has
sent back photographs of the lunar
landscape and other valuable infor¬
mation. More recently, Luna 10 be¬
came a satellite of our natural satellite.
Earlier in the century scientists had
Space stations will be
of vital Importance In the
future exploration of the
universe. Whatever form
they are given, they are
likely to be built from
prefabricated parts
launched Into orbit for
astronaut technicians
to assemble. Artist's
Impression (right) shows
a space platform shaped
like a lighthouse with a
spacecraft "docked" in
foreground. Drawing
below shows astronauts
assembling a space
station with the
aid of "tractor" rockets
(foreground and in rear).
Some scientists believe
that a large wheel will be
the most likely shape for
a large space platform.
When completed it would
be spun to provide
artificial gravity
for the crew.
already begun to feel the need to
extend the study of outer space and
to obtain scientific material that could
be made accessible only by using the
universe itself as a natural laboratory.
At first glance our planet appears
to be a completely isolated celestial
body, but actually thousands of threads
connect the earth with the various pro¬
cesses taking place in outer space.
It has long been known, for instance,
that solar light and heat play a unique
role in the life of the planet and of
man; in more recent times it has been
discovered that the sun is the source
of other types of radiation that also
exercise considerable influence on the
earth. We now possess information
concerning sun-earth relations whose
existence we formerly never even
dreamed of.
Other and more distant cosmic
bodies also have an undoubted effect
on terrestrial processes. Some of these
bodies, for Instance, are sources of
what is known as cosmic radiation
whose intensity determines the radia¬
tion background at the earth's surface.
One could list other examples of the
way the "terrestrial" depends on the
"cosmic", but it will be better to sum
them up by saying that a profound un¬
derstanding of many earthly phenom¬
ena, the study of their real causes
and the explanation of their nature,
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
V,- tftww*
v
^>
\
would be impossible without proper
consideration of cosmic factors.
That, however, is only one aspect.
Science, as we know, progresses from
study of individual phenomena to the
discovery of general laws that operate
In nature. This is the only way mod¬
ern science can solve the gigantic
problems Involved in harnessing ever
new and more powerful natural pro¬
cesses for the benefit of man.
If the researcher hopes to under¬
stand these processes fully he cannot
remain on earth; his sphere of activity
must widen to embrace outer space
as well as our own planet.
To study the laws of the structure
and evolution of the earth we must
have data for comparison from other
bodies in the solar system with which
the earth is connected, not only by
their external similarity, but also by
their common origin. To study the
sun we must have information about
similar stars in other parts of the
universe. Even the study of the shape
of the earth requires observations
made from space by means of artificial
earth satellites.
Thus many problems of a terrestrial
nature require a transition from
planetary to cosmic research.
The cosmos, outer space itself, is
a gigantic, inexhaustible, infinitely var
ied laboratory created by nature.
Here we can observe and study new
phenomena, reveal new laws of nature
and then use the knowledge obtained
for the benefit of man, for the solution
of practical problems on earth.
Progress in science requires a con¬
stantly Increasing volume of Information
about phenomena In the universe.
Conventional terrestrial research must
be developed but at the same time
the area from which information is
gathered must extend into space.
LL scientific and technical
progress depends on the
speed at which many modern, disci¬
plines develop especially physics
chemistry, astronomy, biology and
cybernetics; the development of these
sciences also determines the rate of
production growth In the community,
and these are the branches that stand
in ever greater need of information
from outer space.
However, the main purpose of today's
space research of space flights in par¬
ticular, is to learn more about the part
of the universe surrounding our planet.
We should not expect, therefore, the
data obtained by space research to
have an immediate application,
although in time this knowledge will
find an increasing number of uses.
© APN
Even today we can name quite a
few scientific discoveries that have
come to us straight from the depths
of space. Take atomic energy, for
example. From early days astronomers
studying the sun and other stars realiz¬
ed that they are powerful heat radiators.
It was obvious that a new type of en¬
ergy was involved, since none of the
hitherto known sources of energy could
provide such a colossal output as that
observed. The discovery of this fact
was a powerful incentive to scientists
to step up the study of the sun and
other stars. The parallel study of the
structure of matter developed inten¬
sively until man's efforts enabled him
to release and harness the energy
contained in the atomic nucleus.
How many still unknown sources of
energy are there? How many natural
processes that can be placed at the
service of man does space still hide
from us?
No matter how we look at the spe¬
cific nature of modern science we are
led to the conclusion that develop¬
ment of space research is absolutely
essential.
As we have said, not all space prob¬
lems can be solved by terrestrial ob¬
servation. More and more problems
are coming to the fore that must be
studied outside the earth's atmosphere,
either in outer space or from the sur-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
FOR THE BENEFIT OF MAN (Cont'd)
Efforts repaid a hundredfold
10
face of other celestial bodies. For
this scientists must have space vehi¬
cles capable of delivering measuring
instruments and apparatus and the
researcher himself to various points
in space. The era of the study and
conquest of space, the main feature
of which is space flights, is an
essential stage in man's development.
The space era in the development
of terrestrial civilization, however, is
not merely a matter of launching arti¬
ficial earth satellites and making space
flights. It is the use of an ever-grow¬
ing concentration of the forces of
science and of funds to study the
numerous phenomena occurring on
earth and outside the earth and to
carry out extensive research on both
a planetary and cosmic scale.
HE broader the scope of
scientific research, the
greater the scale on which it develops,
and the greater the need for closer
international co-operation. Research is
most likely to bring the desired results
if it follows an agreed programme and
uses standardized instruments, and
also if the data acquired are processed
and analysed jointly. The effort thus
expended will pay for itself a hundred¬
fold, as joint international research con¬
ducted In recent years has proved most
convincingly. The International Geo¬
physical Year and the Year of the
Quiet Sun are excellent examples of
such fruitful co-operation to say noth¬
ing of the pre-arranged programmes
under which the scientists of different
countries study solar eclipses and
other astronomic phenomena.
Today the attack on the secrets of
nature is being waged with increasingly
powerful scientific forces. In a number
of countries mighty accelerators and
big optical and radio-telescopes are
being built, and the latest achievements
of physics, electronics, cybernetics
and other sciences are being mobi¬
lized in the service of astronomy.
In turn space exploration exerts a
strong influence on the development
of other fields of science and technol¬
ogy. For instance, it stimulates the
further development of cybernetics
and electronics and compels scientists
to seek ways of creating micro¬
miniature laboratory equipment.
For this mighty technical array to
be used most effectively, for scientific
progress to be achieved at maximum
tempo, there must be a broad ex¬
change of information between scien¬
tists of various countries, concerted
effort and close contact. A good
example of such collaboration is the
United Nuclear Research Institution in
Dubna, near Moscow, where scientists
from many socialist countries work
side by side.
Another example of international
co-operation in space exploration is
the joint Soviet-French experiments
in colour TV transmissions using
the French Secam system via the
Soviet space communications satellite
"Molniya" (see page 23).
There has also been some success¬
ful co-operation between Soviet and
American astronomers; in one in¬
stance a Soviet scientist, A. D. Kuzmin,
worked at the observatory of the Calif¬
ornia Technological Institute for
several months. Joint research produc¬
ed some interesting data on physical
conditions on Venus. World science
forums are being held more and more
frequently.
The tendency to unite scientific
effort to develop international research,
is one of the outstanding features of
contemporary science, especially in
the field of space research. This, in
turn, leads to greater international co¬
operation and mutual assistance be¬
tween different countries and different
social systems, and leads to a streng¬
thening of world peace.
The successes of modern science
in designing space vehicles of various
types power carrier rockets, space¬
ships and steerable automatic stations
have enabled researchers to pro¬
gress from the passive study of
phenomena to experiments in the
upper atmosphere and in interplanet¬
ary space.
Experimentation is the most rapid
and effective way of acquiring know¬
ledge. The observer always has to
wait for the right conditions; the exper¬
imenter creates the conditions he
needs; he can change them at will
in the course of the experiment, and
then observe the results of the
changes.
The first experiment in space was
the launching of an artificial earth
satellite. It was preceded by theoret¬
ical calculations based on celestial
mechanics and it proved that our
previous knowledge of the structure
of the solar system and the laws
governing the motion of heavenly
bodies was correct.
When a manned satellite went into
orbit the possibilities for observation
and experimentation increased Immeas¬
urably, for man's actual presence in
space is essential for precise seien-
Photos C APN
PIONEERS OF
ASTRONAUTICS
The names of many men figure in the
story of man's progress from the
concept of space flight to actual accom¬
plishments in astronautics. One such
man is Konstantin Eduardovich Tsiol-
kovsky (above), a Russian school
teacher who was born in 1857 in Kaluga.
When the first aeroplanes were being
coaxed to leave the ground, Tsiolkovsk/
was already writing about satellites,
"ether suits" (space suits), the use of
plants to provide oxygen and food for
space travellers and even the coloniza¬
tion of the planets. In the latter part
of his life (he died in 1935) his genius
was fully appreciated, and today a
crater on the moon bears his name.
His vision inspired Soviet scientists who
in 1929 founded an organization for
studying rocket motors. Above right,
members of this group are seen with an
experimental rocket they built in the
early 1930s. In the group is Serge
Korolyov, later to become a celebrated
Soviet designer of rockets and space¬
ships, who died earlier this year.
Another authentic pioneer was a U.S.
physics professor, Robert Hutchings
Goddard. In the early 1920s. Goddard
not only worked out calculations on roc¬
ketry and space flight, but also experi¬
mented with fuels, built rockets and
actually flew them. Right, in March 1926,
Goddard prepares to launch the world's
first liquid fuel rocket, the forerunner
of the powerful engines that hurl space¬
craft into orbit todey.
USIS
tifie work. As we have said the main
purpose of our invasion of space, for
the time being at least, is to obtain
a more profound understanding of our
immediate surroundings.
In space itself it is possible to make
a direct study of phenomena and pro¬
cesses still unknown to science, and
this of course, means that the space
explorer must inevitably face the
unknown. As man penetrates further
and further into space that unknown
will gradually become more and more
extraordinary; it will be more and
more difficult to relate it to what is
known and it will be necessary on
each occasion to find new, original
approaches to problems.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
With science and technology at
their present level such research can
be done only by man, because the
human brain possesses potentialities
far in excess of the most perfect of
our modern electronic computers and
other cybernetic apparatus. Situations
may arise during a space flight that
have not been foreseen, and the
optimum decision that has to be made
instantaneously can be made only by
man.
Research during space flights be¬
came still more practicable when Soviet
scientists and engineers designed
the multi-seat spacecraft that made a
successful flight carrying astronauts
Komarov, Yegorov and Feoktistov.
Spaceship crews may include such
specialists as astronomers, physicists,
biologists, doctors and engineers; each
of them, working in his own field, can
conduct continuous and varied obser¬
vations. There is no doubt that in the
relatively near future we shall see
many scientific discoveries made on
board spaceships.
Another important advance in space
exploration was made during the
flight of the Soviet spaceship Vos-
khod 2 when an astronaut, Alexei
Leonov, stepped ont of his ship into
space for the first time; he remained
outside for ten minutes protected only
by the spacesuit he was wearing. This
was a scientific and technical
achievement that ranked with such
other accomplishments as the orbiting
of the first artificial earth satellite
and the flight of Yuri Gagarin, the first
astronaut.
N astronaut must have a
, certain freedom of move¬
ment in flight if he is to carry out all
the operations necessary for an effec¬
tive exploration of space, but the cap¬
sule of the spaceship hampers his
movements considerably. The flight of
Pavel Belyayev and Alexei Leonov
showed that this obstacle can be sur¬
mounted. Using a special spacesuit
which supplies him with oxygen and
protects him from the hazards of space,
the astronaut can leave the ship, move
freely in space and carry out different
tasks.
A short time later this experiment
was repeated by U.S. astronauts.
Since it has been shown that a man
can leave his ship in space, it will be
much easier to do such things as join¬
ing two spaceships, building research
stations in orbit and landing expedi¬
tions on other heavenly bodies.
U.S. scientists have made an impor¬
tant contribution to the conquest of
space. Among other things U.S.
spacemen have made flights along
ballistic trajectories the first step
towards the future establishment of
inter-continental rocket transport; they
have also developed the technique of
landing on water.
Valuable information was sent back
to earth by the U.S. space stations
Mariner 2 and Mariner 4 from the vici¬
nity of Venus and Mars; another U.S.
contribution was made by photographs
transmitted by the Ranger Space Sta¬
tion as it approached the moon.
U.S. scientists have carried out
fascinating experiments with lasers to
determine the orbital position of artifi¬
cial earth satellites. This was done by
reflectors on the vehicle powerful
enough to send the light signals of the
lasers back to earth. This method of
observation showed the position of the
vehicle in orbit with an accuracy of 15
metres. Various types of lasers, work¬
ing in different wavebands, are an im¬
portant new tool for space studies.
U.S. scientists and engineers have
achieved outstanding successes in the
practical use of space vehicles; one
example being the systems of meteor¬
ological and communications satellites
they have created.
An important new stage in the
conquest of space was marked by the
flight of Soviet Automatic Station Luna
9. The moon being our nearest neigh¬
bour in space, its study is of tremen¬
dous interest to science, and the soft
landing constitued a substantial contrib¬
ution to lunar exploration.
The comprehensive study of the nat¬
ure of the moon, the structure of its
surface and interior, the composition of
lunar matter and the physical condi¬
tions prevailing there will greatly ex¬
tend our knowledge of the structure of
the planets of the solar system and of
the history of their origin and develop¬
ment. In the final analysis this will
help us study our own planet and make
the best use of its colossal natural
resources.
The astronomers' dream of an orbital
observatory beyond the terrestrial
atmosphere is already coming true.
The idea of building a space station
on the moon at some future date is a
fascinating one. Such a station, func¬
tioning in a vacuum and in a gravita¬
tional field one sixth of the strength of
that of the earth, could be an invalu¬
able cosmic observatory and a physico-
chemical laboratory in which scientists
could study various processes under
unusual conditions.
Soviet scientists made an extremely
important step forward in space ex¬
ploration at the end of 1965 and the
beginning of 1966 when automatic in¬
terplanetary probes Venera 2 and
Venera 3 were sent to Venus. After a
three-month flight, the Venera 3 probe
reached the surface of the planet on
March 1, 1966 and delivered a pennant
with the emblem of the Soviet Union.
This precision landing was achieved
by a correction of the probe's trajectory
successfully carried out on December
26, 1965.
Venus became the second celestial
body, after the moon, to be reached by
a man-made space vehicle.
Problems on a planetary scale are
being solved in the course of space
exploration, and this makes it an area
in which all-round co-operation be¬
tween scientists of a number of coun¬
tries would be most effective. Space
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
H
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
FOR THE BENEFIT OF MAN (Cont'd)
Weather eyes
open in space
research itself, moreover, must be
conducted on a broad basis. Soviet
' scientists are convinced that rockets
and spaceships must serve the cause
of peace and the progress of humanity.
Data obtained from space satellites,
to complement information from ground
meteorological stations, is an important
factor in reliable weather forecasting.
Following a Soviet-American agree¬
ment, a round-the-clock communication
channel now provides for a two-way
transmission of meteorological data,
meteorological charts and photographs.
This channel will assume a special
significance when a continuous action
system of weather-service satellites
is put into orbit.
Some international space studies
have already been carried out, among
others the Anglo-Soviet radio trans¬
missions through the U.S. satellite
Echo and through the moon and Venus.
Radio signals transmitted from Britain's
Jodrell Bank Observatory were reflect¬
ed from the surface of one of these
planets and picked up by the Soviet
radio-astronomic station at Zimenki,
near Gorky.
The purpose of these experiments
was to extend our knowledge of the
conditions under which radio waves
penetrate the upper layers of the
earth's atmosphere. This is of great
practical importance for the develop¬
ment of long distance radio communi¬
cation of the earth-spaceship-earth
type, to ensure reliable radio commun¬
ication between the earth and space¬
ships and other objects that in the
future will be placed in orbit.
Special communications satellites,
put in high orbits to ensure prolonged
operation, are of major significance in
establishing a world-wide system of
radio communication and television.
The sucessful launching of the Molniya
relay satellite by the Soviet Union, for
example, has made possible a regular
television link between Vladivostok and
Moscow.
Actually, it does not matter which
country is first able to send an expedi¬
tion to the moon or is responsible for
some other success in space; the im¬
portant thing is the benefit it will bring
to people; this is the real purpose of
all these achievements.
The history of science shows that
when outstanding scientific discoveries
are made in any country, their further
development is due to the joint effort
of the scientists of the whole world.
The conquest of space will be no
exception.
t
*n
BLAST-OFF FOR ARIEL
The first international satellite,
Ariel I, a joint United Kingdom-
United States co-operative pro¬
ject, rises from a U.S. launching
base (above) on April 26, 1962.
Ariel I (in drawing, left, as it
would appear in orbit) was de¬
signed to collect information
about the ionosphere (a layer of
the earth's upper atmosphere)
and how it is affected by solar
radiations. The Goddard Space
Flight Center in the U.S.A.
launched the satellite and later
picked up its data through a
world-wide network of tracking
stations. The U.K. designed
and arranged the instruments
to carry out six experiments to
measure cosmic, ultraviolet and
X-rays. A second satellite,
Ariel II, was launched into orbit
in March 1964, and work on a
third Ariel is now proceeding.
Photos NASA
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Joint enterprises are now
a going concern
in the exciting field
of space research'
by Arnold W. Frutkln
INTERNATIONAL co-operation In the scientific exploration of
space provides both a present reality which is yielding practical
benefits and a highly attractive prospect for future contributions to the
knowledge and welfare of all nations.
The United States civilian space agency, the National Aeronautics and
Space Administration (NASA), since its establishment in 1958, has carried
out a broad and varied programme of co-operative space activities involving
70 countries and jurisdictions. The objectives of this programme are to
afford opportunities for the best brains abroad to participate in space
research, to stimulate technical development abroad, to help reduce eco¬
nomic and political strain between states, and to provide a framework within
which countries can pool their efforts and join in cost-sharing and comple¬
mentary programmes.
Existing international co-operative
space activities demonstrate the values
which flow from joint participation in
this relatively new and exciting branch
of scientific investigation and technical
development.
NASA has placed in orbit six satel¬
lites designed and engineered by
scientists and engineers in Canada,
France, Italy and the United Kingdom
and has agreements to launch eight
more co-operative satellites. From the
experiments conducted with these
spacecraft, the countries concerned
have derived a large volume of signif¬
icant information which they are shar¬
ing with the United States and the
ARNOLD W. FRUTKIN, Assistant Admi¬
nistrator for International Affairs at the
National Aeronautics and Space Administra¬
tion (NASA), Washington, has been re¬
sponsible for NASA's programmes of co¬
operation with foreign governments and
agencies in space science and technology
since 1959 when he was appointed Director
of the Office of International Programmes.
He is a member of the U.S. delegation to
the U.N. Committee on the Peaceful Uses
of Outer Space. Before joining NASA,
Mr. Frutkin served as Director of Public
Affairs and later as Deputy Executive Direc¬
tor of the U.S. National Committee for the
International Geophysical Year.
rest of the world scientific community.
Foreign scientists are invited by
NASA to propose individual experi¬
ments for inclusion on NASA satellites.
These proposals are reviewed In com¬
petition with those submitted by Amer¬
ican scientists and, if selected, are
funded and prepared by the sponsor¬
ing agencies abroad. Four such ex¬
periments have already flown success¬
fully, sixteen additional ones have been
scheduled for later flights and several
more are under consideration. NASA
has opened virtually all categories of
its spacecraft, including the Apollo
manned spacecraft, to foreign partici¬
pation on this co-operative basis, thus
providing opportunities for foreign
scientists and engineers to obtain
valuable data and experience.
Co-operative sounding-rocket pro¬
jects have special international appeal.
To nations wishing to initiate space
programmes, they offer relatively low-
cost opportunities on a smaller but
significant scale. They offer the use
of launching locations of unique scien¬
tific interest and permit simultaneous
launchings in different locations, a
practice required for certain scientific
objectives. More than 130 rockets
have been launched in joint NASA pro¬
jects with 17 countries.
Sounding rocket projects have
brought into being a large number of
ranges in scientifically significant re¬
gions of the world auroral, equatorial,
southern hemisphere and these
ranges now make possible increasingly
important programmes in rocket
astronomy, meteorology, aeronomy,
and ionospheric physics.
A study of atmospheric circulation
of the Indian Ocean basin, with both
India and Pakistan participating, has
resulted in valuable contributions to
scientific knowledge. A particularly
interesting by-product of this bilateral
programme has been the establish¬
ment of the first international sounding
rocket range, at Thumba on the geo¬
magnetic equator. This range is open
to all users who follow a code of
open investigation laid down by the
United Nations. To the extent that
unique advantages may be derived
from their geographic location, there
may be room for the establishment of
more such ranges.
O NE of the attractive aspects
of bilateral sounding rocket
projects is that they tend to serve as
nuclei for broadening international
activity. Ionospheric studies conduct¬
ed under a U.S. agreement with Nor¬
way have led to collaborative efforts
among all three Scandinavian count¬
ries. Argentina and Brazil are now
undertaking with NASA joint sound¬
ing rocket studies which serve as ele¬
ments in an experimental inter-American
meteorological sounding rocket net¬
work. This network, it is hoped, will
eventually engage western hemisphere
meteorologists from the Antarctic pen¬
insula to the shores of Hudson Bay.
Argentina and Brazil together have
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
JOINT SPACE ENTERPRISES (Cont'd)
Satellite beacons for ships and planes
formulated an agreement which pro¬
vides a framework for future co-opera¬
tion in space research to which these
countries can bring capabilities devel¬
oped in the co-operative programmes
with NASA.
Co-operation in ground-based pro¬
grammes has been of the greatest im¬
portance for flight projects and has
permitted participation in space pro¬
grammes of great scope without re¬
quiring expensive vehicle or space¬
craft hardware. In meteorology, the
co-operative sharing of practical space
benefits has reached new levels
through the inclusion of an Automatic
Picture Transmission (APT) system on
United States advanced meteorological
satellites.
The APT camera can provide con¬
tinuous read-out of cloud-cover photo¬
graphs. A simple and relatively inex¬
pensive ground station permits direct
and immediate acquisition and printing
of cloud-cover photographs taken by
the satellite as it passes within range.
Thirteen countries have acquired APT
sets at their own expense and used
them successfully, many reporting
direct improvements in weather fore¬
casting. Numerous other countries are
acquiring the sets which offer both
immediate forecasting and long-range
research gains for weather service and
university interests.
14
OMMUNICATIONS satel¬
lites made possible early
dramatic transoceanic telephone and
television demonstrations and have
now entered the phase of direct com¬
mercial application with the clear pro¬
mise of cultural and economic benefit.
The early experimental co-operation,
in which a dozen countries undertook
construction of ground stations at their
own expense, under agreement with
NASA, undoubtedly contributed to this
implementation.
Another prospect, of potential bene¬
fit to both air and sea transportation,
is that of navigation satellites. The
increasing density of traffic on aircraft
and shipping routes may make it
desirable and profitable to develop a
satellite navigation system which would
contribute to the safety and economy
of transportation, particularly on the
most heavily travelled routes.
Of primary importance to programmes
of space exploration and experimenta¬
tion are ground stations for tracking
and reception of data sent back by
radio. International co-operation in the
location, construction and operation of
these stations is clearly essential. In
all countries where NASA has estab¬
lished tracking and data acquisition
stations, local technicians are invited
to work side by side with United States
personnel and, in most cases, do so.
Indeed, in a number of locations, the
stations are operated entirely by crews
of the host country. This co-operation
not only provides necessary services,
but contributes to the spread of
modern technologies and the con¬
tinued growth of understanding.
Personnel exchanges and training
arrangements are important in most
international efforts. Programmes have
been set up under which senior scien¬
tists from abroad may spend a year or
more in research or experimental work
at NASA centres. Fellowships at the
graduate level are available in Ameri¬
can universities for foreign students.
Training necessary for the execution
of co-operative projects in which the
United States participates is made
available at appropriate NASA centres.
In these latter two programmes, the
requirement that the sponsoring coun¬
tries meet travel and subsistence costs
assures careful selection of personnel
selected for training, and their future
utilization at home.
In each of the co-operative projects
referred to, that portion which is the
responsibility of the co-operating coun¬
try is in fact a bona fide contribution
of that country, funded by it without
financial support from the U.S. Each
of the projects referred to is of
mutual interest to the participants and
possesses valid scientific objectives.
The scientific results of each of these
projects are made available to the
world scientific community.
What are the limitations on con¬
tinued expansion of international co¬
operation in space research and explor¬
ation? It would be unrealistic not to
recognize that constraints exist and
that the primary ones are money, tech¬
nology and will (which in turn may be
a function of the level of appreciation
of the broad benefits which can in fact
be derived from an engagement in
space technology).
One means of reducing costs to indi¬
vidual participating countries is the
banding together of a group of coun¬
tries, as in the European Space
Research Organization (ESRO) and the
European Launcher Development Orga¬
nization (ELDO) (see page 24). Other,
CONT'D ON PAGE 16
North American Aviation
TRICKS PLAYED
ON HAND & EYE
Venturing into outer space, man
encounters new, bewildering con¬
ditions that play tricks with his
vision. The earth's atmosphere
produces diffuse reflection of
light, but in space the astronaut
can see only bright objects illum¬
inated by the sun and visible
against an absolutely black
background. Such misleading
and unstable perspectives dis¬
tort human perceptions of depth
and shape and produce optical
illusions. Astronauts are taught
to beware of mirages in space.
Hold this figure (Necker's cube) at arms
length and keep your eyes fixed on it.
Its aspect will change. First the top (or
bottom) will appear as viewed from above,
and then from below. You will not be able
to retain one image for very long. This
illustrates the kind of optical illusion that
may complicate the work of astronauts in
assembling the sections of stations in
space. Against the blackness of space a
cube becomes diamond-shaped and a circle
takes on elliptical form. Right two drawings
by the Dutch engraver, Maurits-Cornelis
Escher, illustrate the same kind of optical
illusion. In "Belvedere", the men on the
ladder are placed ¡[logically, the lower one
inside and the upper one outside the edi¬
fice; below them a seated figure contem¬
plates Necker's cube. In "Perpetual Mo¬
tion", a drawing trick makes the water
falling on the wheel appear to climb again
to give the mill an unending water supply.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Stresses experienced
by an astronaut
in flight acceleration,
weightlessness, heat,
oxygen intake, magnetic
disturbances
can affect
his perceptions
and actions.
Left, checking the effect
of acceleration
on the human eye.
Circular pattern
is projected on the eye
and photographed
after flight to reveal
change caused by rapid
acceleration.
erratic squiggles, Right,
recalling certain works
of modern art,
are gestures
of astronauts
with electric bulbs
fixed to their wrists,
photographed during
simulated space flight.
1
PlSl
£ ^P
1 Jn \
IS
M 1 JL
3
T- *'
Courtesy "Jardin des Arts", Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Shadowgraph reveals
the shock wave
and turbulence set
up by the profile of a Mercury
space capsule. Tests
under laboratory
conditions determine
how the capsule will
behave at high speeds
in the atmosphere.
JOINT SPACE ENTERPRISES (Cont'd)
Bridges between the continents
16
regional groupings might perform a
similarly useful function.
The scope for advanced projects of
mutual interest is also limited by dis¬
parities in the development of the
required technology. The past few
years of space activity, through nation¬
al, regional, and NASA-co-operative
projects, have, however, already estab¬
lished a significant base for more
advanced projects. Disparities in tech¬
nology can be further reduced through
regional space research organizations,
such as ESRO and ELDO, in which
each participant concentrates on those
areas of science and technology in
which it is most proficient.
Finally, genuine co-operation re¬
quires the will to co-operate on the part
of all participants. The will to co-oper¬
ate presupposes a conviction that co¬
operation can serve the common inter¬
est It is of some interest that the
United States has steadfastly sought
to open new opportunities for space
co-operation with the Soviet Union.
A certain limited success has been
achieved by the two countries. Follow¬
ing specific proposals for co-operation
by President Kennedy in 1962, nego¬
tiators were designated by both sides.
The resulting talks between the late
Dr. Hugh L. Dryden and Academician
A. A. Blagonravov produced an agree¬
ment dated June 8, 1962.
The agreement provided for three
undertakings. The first was for co¬
ordinated launchings of experimental
meteorological satellites and the
exchange of data thus obtained over a
conventional communications link. This
link has been established and is being
used for the exchange of conventional
meteorological data pending the avail¬
ability of satellite data from the Soviet
Union.
The second undertaking was for the
launching by each country of an earth
satellite equipped with absolute magnet¬
ometers and the subsequent exchange
of data. The third part of the agree¬
ment was for co-operative communica
tions experiments by means of the
United States passive satellite Echo II.
The communications project has been
completed. The exchange of magnetic
field data obtained by ground-based
instruments has begun and will provide
a basis for analysis of satellite data.
The most recent evidence of United
States willingness to join with others
in the exploration of space is
President Johnson's suggestion of
December 1965 that countries may wish
to co-operate in a major new space
endeavour of greater magnitude and
more far-reaching technological implic¬
ations than anything proposed hereto¬
fore. The President's proposal is, in
effect, a response to the frequently-
stated desire of other developed coun¬
tries for greater participation in the
development of advanced space tech¬
nology.
Other interested nations may wish
to share in the benefits which America
is deriving from major advanced tech¬
nological programmes through a com¬
bination of advanced management
techniques, technology and a fruitful
TURTLE-TRACKIN6
SATELLITES
Satellites have proved
their worth in many
fields, including
meteorology and
telecommunications.
They may soon be helping
zoologists discover how
green turtles navigate
1,400 miles of sea
to reach the sites where
they lay their eggs.
Professor Archie Carr,
zoology professor at
the University of
Florida, suggests that
satellites be used to
track turtles equipped
with a radio
transmitter fixed to
their shells (right).
NASA Is studying
how to co-operate
in these
turtle-tracking studies.
partnership of government, university
and private industry. Such collabora¬
tion could contribute to the develop¬
ment of mutual Interests transcending
space technology, relating it to other
technology so as to employ the total
capability for broader progress and
understanding for all peoples.
In his report to the Congress on
United States Aeronautics and Space
Activities for 1965, President Johnson
said, "As our space programme con¬
tinues, the impact of its developments
on everyday life becomes daily more
evident." It continues to stimulate our
education, improve our material well-
being, and broaden the horizons of
knowledge. It is also a powerful force
for peace.
"The space programme of the United
States today is the largest effort ever
undertaken by any nation to advance
the frontiers of human knowledge.
What we are discovering and building
today will help solve many of the great
problems which an increasingly com¬
plex and heavily-populated world will
face to morrow."
O Archie Carr
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
\K¡üHb&J5m¡
i
ffifl K
l8*il
From behind a plastic
planisphere, specialist
at the Brétigny aero¬
space centre. France,
indicates (on right)
point where French
FR-1 satellite went into
orbit, and (on left)
where it passed over
Europe on orbit one.
0 P. Lei lèvre
fê*£
mr'i
' :
;..
\
joy Eugène Pepin
What happens if a
spaceship launched
by one country
lands in another?
Can any nation
claim sovereignty
on the moon?
What are the
responsabilities
of a country
whose satellite
collides with
a communications
satellite placed
in orbit by
another country?
SPACE FLIGHT
AND THE RULE
OF LAW
J:IURISTS did not wait for
the launching of the first
Sputnik, on October 4, 1957, before
they started considering the problems
which would arise as a result of the
exploration and utilization of space
by artificial satellites. The articles and
discussions of the "pre-Sputnik" era,
however dealt mainly with theoretical
questions, such as the scope and lim¬
its of national sovereignty in space.
Very soon, Soviet and American
space successes forced jurists to con¬
sider more practical problems resulting
from the progress of the new science
of astronautics. International and na¬
tional associations of jurists studied
and discussed the legal aspects of
EUGENE PEPIN, President of the Inter¬
national Institute of Space Law (Inter¬
national Astronautical Federation) is pro¬
fessor of air and space law at the
Institut des Relations Internationales
Contemporaines, Paris. He was formerly
director of the Legal Department of the
International Civil Aviation Organization.
space flight, and reported their findings
to various international bodies.
On December 13, 1958, the United
Nations General Assembly, recogniz¬
ing the common interest of mankind
in the exploration and use of outer
space, established an ad hoc Com¬
mittee on the Peaceful Uses of Outer
Space, and included on the list of the
technical studies to be undertaken a
survey of the nature of legal problems
which might arise in carrying out pro¬
grammes of space exploration.
The first legal principles for guidance
in the exploration and use of outer
space were adopted by the U.N. Gen¬
eral Assembly on December 20, 1961,
in a resolution which affirmed that:
International law, including the
Charter of the United Nations, ap¬
plies to outer space and celestial
bodies.
Outer space and celestial bodies
are free for exploration and use by n
all states in conformity with inter- ' «
national law and are not subject to
national appropriation.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
SPACE LAW (Cont'd)
No national sovereignty in space
18
In this resolution, the General As¬
sembly, envisaging the United Nations
as a focal point for international co¬
operation in the peaceful exploration
and use of outer space, called upon
states launching objects into orbit to
give the United Nations full informa¬
tion for keeping a public register of
launchings.
The need for adding to the two basic
principles proclaimed in this resolution
became evident in March 1962, at the
first meeting of the legal sub-commit¬
tee of the new permanent Committee
on the Peaceful Uses of Outer
Space. Whilst priority was given to
two important problems assistance to
astronauts and space vehicles and
responsibility for damage resulting
from space activities the Soviet Dele¬
gation submitted a draft declaration of
the principles which should govern the
activities of states in outer space, to
be signed by all countries. At subse¬
quent sessions, further lists of general
principles were submitted by the
United Arab Republic, the United King¬
dom and the United States of America.
HE first question to be
settled was that of the
general legal principles. In 1963, the
U.N. Committee on the Peaceful Uses
of Outer Space and its legal sub¬
committee discussed at length not only
the principles themselves, but also the
form in which to embody them: as an
agreement for signature or as a
General Assembly resolution. A com¬
promise text was drafted and present¬
ed to the 1963 U.N. General Assembly,
which adopted it unanimously. This
was the Solemn Declaration of Dec¬
ember 13, of the "Legal Principles Gov¬
erning the Activities of States in the
Exploration and Use of Outer Space."
It did not, however, satisfy all states,
some of which regarded it merely as
a recommendation; so the General
Assembly recommended that the Com¬
mittee on the Peaceful Uses of Outer
Space consider the possibility of in¬
corporating these principles in an
international agreement.
This Declaration of 1963 is both a
reasonable compromise calculated to
unite and not divide members of the
United Nations, and, at the same time
a further illustration of international co¬
operation in space activities, comple¬
menting the resolution banning nuclear
weapons in space, which was adopted
by acclamation on October 17, 1963.
This called on states to refrain from
placing in orbit around the earth any
objects carrying nuclear weapons or
any other kinds of weapons of mass
destruction, or stationing such weapons
in outer space in any other man¬
ner; also to refrain from encouraging
or in any way participating in such
activities.
The U.N. Declaration endorses the
legal principles for guidance in the
exploration and use of space adopted
In 1961, and defines them in greater
detail. The main principle proclaimed
is, as before, that all nations shall be
free and equal as regards the explor¬
ation and use of outer space and the
celestial bodies, providing that:
H the exploration and use of outer
space shall be carried on for the
benefit and in the interests of all
mankind;
the activities of states in the explor¬
ation and use of outer space shall
be carried on in accordance with
international law, including the Char¬
ter of the United Nations, in the in¬
terest of maintaining international
peace and promoting international
co-operation and understanding;
states shall be guided in their activ¬
ities by the principle of co-opera¬
tion and mutual assistance and shall
conduct them with due regard for
the interests of other states.
The Declaration also proclaims that
outer space and celestial bodies are
not subject to national appropriation by
claim of sovereignty, by means of use
or occupation, or by any other means.
The remaining articles contain a brief
enumeration of other principles to be
proclaimed in subsequent conventions.
Another problem which, since the
beginning of the space age, has pre¬
occupied countries engaged in space
research is that of giving aid to astro¬
nauts and space vehicles in diffi¬
culty and assisting their return. The
Declaration contains provisions on
these points.
As regards space vehicles the Dec¬
laration states that ownership of
objects launched Into outer space, and
of their component parts, is in no way
affected by their passage through
outer space or by their return to the
earth, and it stipulates that such ob¬
jects or their parts found beyond the
limits of the country of registry shall
be returned to that country, which
shall furnish identifying data upon re¬
quest before repatriation takes place.
As for astronauts, they should be
regarded them as envoys of mankind
in 'outer space and therefore given
every possible assistance in the event
of accident, distress, or emergency
landing on the territory of a foreign
state or on the high seas. Astronauts
who make such a landing shall be
safely and promptly returned to the
state of registry of their space vehicle.
FOR the application of these
principles detailed provi¬
sions will have to be laid down. A
number of draft conventions have been
submitted to the Committee on the
Peaceful Uses of Outer Space, but no
definite text has yet been drafted.
Although the need for rendering
assistance to astronauts in difficulties
is generally accepted, discussion con¬
tinues as to whether astronauts should
be returned to the state of registry of
their space vehicle, and whether such
vehicles or their components should
be returned to the country of origin in
all circumstances, or only when launch¬
ings are made in conformance with
the general principles of the Declar¬
ation of 1963.
The problem of the responsibility
for damages resulting from activities
in outer space has now ceased to be
a theoretical one. Objects launched
into space or fragments from them can
cause damage when they fall back to
the earth. For instance in November
1960 cattle were killed near the village
of Olguin, Cuba, by debris from a
rocket; and fragments of rockets have
been found on the ground on several
occasions, particularly in Canada, the
United States and South Africa. With
more and more objects (rocket-stages,
CONT'D ON PAGE 35
© NASA, Washington
COLOUR PAGE, OPPOSITE: Turbulent cloud formations reveal presence
of storm approaching the Moroccan coast near Agadir in this photograph
taken from space by U.S. astronauts Gordon Cooper and Charles Conrad,
during their eight-day Gemini 5 mission in August 1965. Today meteorol¬
ogists are no longer confined to a "worm's eye" view of the weather. The
first meteorological satellite launched in 1960 televised over 22,000 photo¬
graphs of global weather conditions in eleven weeks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
-*>.
¿.v.*v
^¿j^ *+
.«>
>--
T.
U** ..^._vi*JH
ThV»,,1'
* .. *
» S
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
BQfóH
^a
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
*-* «r;
^ttML^*. **._« "Í3L i
"^^ ". ^^^ ^
Í*** 1^
£â*+^ ' *» i' '':«
T *
H
HH HBHHHI : .
3&§^ HB
.
H yS BmsS HHa
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Colour page, opposite : Photographed by U.S. astronauts Frank
Borman and James Lovell from the spacecraft Gemini 7, the moon
hang? like a lamp against the dark backdrop of space. Gemini 7,
whose nose is seen lower left, travelled 5.7 million miles and
stayed in orbit for 14 days.
© NASA
ASTRONAUT-PHOTOGRAPHERS
AT A RENDEZVOUS IN SPACE
Centre colour pages.
Left, two views of Gemini 7 taken as Gemini 6, with astronauts
Walter Schirra and Tom Stafford aboard, closed in for the first
rendezvous in space. This space chase lasted nearly six hours
during which time both craft travelled three and a half times
round the globe. Top, Gemini 7 seen from the rear. Bottom, the
two craft nose to nose, orbiting in formation some 20 feet apart
while travelling at 17,500 m.p.h., 160 miles above the earth. Right,
a spectacular panoramic view of the eastern Mediterranean.
Photographed by Gemini 7 during its 56th orbit, it reaches about
600 miles from Egypt and the Red Sea to Turkey and Cyprus.
Numbered on reproduction right are (1) Nile Valley (2) Nile
Delta (3) Red Sea (4) Bitter Lakes (5) Suez Canal (6) Sinai (7)
Dead Sea (8) Sea of Galilee (9) Israel (10) Syria (11) Jordan (12)
Lebanon (13) Turkey (14) Cyprus. Spaceborne cameras have
< already brought back new knowledge of great value to ocean¬
ic ographers, meteorologists, geologists, cartographers and other
Q scientists. And pointing their cameras into the reaches of
ó space, astronaut-photographers can take pictures of the moon,
| planets and stars without the distortions picked up from the
S earth's atmosphere in ground-based optical equipment.
FLOWERS
VIA
SATELLITE
^P Bn
flKufJ^BBB*
flSBBMBBBB
& ' -- BS
- tip . a
The U.S.S.R. and France were linked for . ':..; .; ' ' . .
the first time by colour television on Nov ! \
ember 30, 1965, when a programme put bV 1
out by Moscow was re-transmitted by the « V -: . Jkj^
Soviet communications satellite, Molniya 1
(right). The programme, picked up in 1% W j^bbI
France by the Pleumeur-Bodou station, TzsZ	
presented a number of films, including
BBBBBBBBBB^BBBtä» K À' BBBBBBBBBBBBBBBBBbI
BBBBBBBBBBBBBBBB»¡m^yfi^>M*^BBBB""»""""»"
one on flowers from which the colour photo ' ^SjjV^.
of columbines (left) is taken. Launched ^^ j^2|l '
in April 1965, Molniya (Lightning), made ^^WbP^L
possible the first regular television trans
* (*'!& ^^ ' ^bV
missions between Moscow and Vladi
vostok. Since 1958, increasingly complex
" ...» . .
communications satellites have been put
.-.... i, . - » .
into orbit, including Telstar I, which first Photo ® APN
relayed live TV pictures across the Atlantic
in 1962. Among other vistas opened by
"comsats" is the possibility of three being
placed in an orbit at the right distance 23
\% from the earth to relay telephone and tele-
© vision signals over most of the world.
=
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
TEST BENCH
FOR SPACE
EXPLORERS
To operate successfully in the vacu¬
um of outer space, man-made
satellites have to withstand extremes
of temperature heating on the sur¬
face facing the sun and the bitter
cold of space itself, with tempera¬
tures dropping as low as 270 de¬
grees below zero C. Last January a
large vacuum chamber for carrying
out temperature tests on space satel¬
lites was put into service at the
European Space Technology Centre,
at Noordwijk, Netherlands. Right,
model of the international satellite,
Esro I in this chamber. Esro I, due
to be launched late in 1967, will be
used for studying the ionosphere
and polar aurora. Far right, twin
domes at the European space range
now being completed inside the Arc¬
tic Circle at Kiruna, Sweden, cover
telemetry equipment for picking up
data transmitted by sounding rockets.
Photos ESRO
EUROPE'S GROWING STAKE IN SPACE SCIENCE
s
24
PACE research through
international co-operation
might be said to function like a three-
stage rocket launching a space vehicle
into orbit, with each stage completing
its task and then handing over the
operation for the next stage to carry
it one step further.
The first stage is obviously one of
paper work and planning the co-ord¬
ination of programmes, choice of norms
and general planning at the interna¬
tional level. An outstanding example
of this stage is the work done by the
Committee for Space Research (COS-
PAR) of the International Council of
Scientific Unions.
PIERRE AUGER is Director-General of the
European Space Research Organization, which
he helped to set up, and president of the
International Computation Centre (Rome).
A leading French physicist, he was head of
Unesco's Department of Natural Sciences
from 1948 to 1959. He is the author of
"Current Trends in Scientific Research", a
comprehensive survey of world scientific and
technological research (3rd ed., 1963, Unesco,
Paris; 33¡-, $6.75. hard cover).
by Pierre Auger
Next comes co-operation and the
joint implementation of specific parts
of national programmes through special
agreements and associations as, for
example, the launching by U.S. rockets
of Canadian, British, French and Italian
satellites.
The third stage, a pooling of resour¬
ces that makes it possible to carry out
an international project, is today
represented by various collective Euro¬
pean programmes set up by two
Inter-governmental organizations: the
European Space Research Organiza¬
tion (ESRO) and the European
Launcher Development Organization
(ELDO). It is primarily the work of
ESRO that I propose to deal with here.
The aims of this organization are
purely scientific. They are the study
of conditions in outer space (including
the outermost layer of the atmosphere,
at altitudea-of 150 kilometres, 93 miles;
and beyond), and the study of celestial
bodies by rockets, satellites and long
distance probes launched into space.
It is hardly surprising, therefore,
that the initiative which led to its
creation should have come from
scientists themselves. The idea was
in fact originally conceived at a meet¬
ing of the space research committee
of the International Council of Scien¬
tific Unions in 1960.
Subsequently, the programme and
operational arrangments for the future
organization were worked out in
greater detail, and a preparatory com¬
mission, presided over by Sir Harrie
Massey and subsidized by France, was
created the same year. Between 1960
and 1964 the work of setting up the
new international organization was
completed, and in March 1964 a
convention established ESRO.
ESRO's membership at present
consists of ten European states: Fran¬
ce, where it has its headquarters; the
Netherlands, where the main technical
centre is being built; the Federal Repu¬
blic of Germany, where the data-pro¬
cessing centre is being installed;
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Sweden, in whose far north the sound¬
ing-rocket launching range is located;
Italy, where the advanced research
laboratory is to be built; Belgium,
which is to have a satellite tracking
station; the United Kingdom, Denmark,
Spain and Switzerland.
The organization aims to promote
collaboration among European states
in space research and technology,
exclusively for peaceful purposes. To
do so it has drawn up a scientific and
technical programme which concen¬
trates mainly on the construction, per¬
fecting and launching of space ve¬
hicles, sounding rockets and satellites
capable of carrying scientific apparatus
designed and produced by research
teams in member states. These teams
work, as a rule, either in universities
or in large research laboratories.
In short, ESRO is designed to help
scientists and researchers by providing
them with means of putting their appar¬
atus into orbit or at least of launching
it temporarily out of the atmosphere.
The organization will keep track of the
space craft and apparatus it launches
by means of a world-wide network of
tracking and telemetry stations. It will
pick up, process and analyse tJata
from space.
The organization was launched with
an 8-year financial plan totalling three
hundred million dollars, with the reser¬
vation that annual budgets may, after
the preparatory period, attain fifty
million dollars. This clearly rules out
any very major projects such as send¬
ing men to the moon; and in any case
ESRO has decided to confine itself to
unmanned space vehicles. It has,
however, been able to draw up a pro¬
gramme of rocket and satellite laun-
chings that will enable scientists to
carry out a variety of experiments in
cosmic physics and astrophysics. The
organization will procure sounding
rockets from France and the United
Kingdom; satellite-launching appara¬
tus from the United States.
T HE programme provides
for the launching of some
hundreds of sounding rockets able to
reach altitudes of between 150 and
300 km. (90-190 miles); and of a series
of artificial satellites of three types:
small satellites placed in orbit by Amer¬
ican Scout rockets, medium satellites
orbited by Thor Delta rockets, and
large satellites weighing about a ton
and needing far more powerful laun¬
chers. It is probable that the large
satellites will be placed in orbit by the
3-stage rockets of the type now being
constructed by the European Launcher
Development Organization (ELDO), an
organization which was set up at about
the same time as ESRO through the
association of seven governments,
those of the United Kingdom, France,
the Federal Republic of Germany, Italy,
the Netherlands, Belgium and Australia.
The first item on ELDO's programme
is the. design, development and cons¬
truction of the three-stage "Europa"
satellite-launching rocket. The first
stage will be the British Blue Streak
rocket, the second, the French rocket
Coralie and the third, a German rocket.
The satellite test vehicles are being
built by Italy, while Belgium and the
Netherlands are producing various
types of telemetry and guidance equip¬
ment and Australia is providing the
launching range at Woomera.
What kinds of experiments are
carried out with the aid of apparatus
which has been and is to be placed
in these rocket-heads and satellites?
They are designed to make a study
of the uppermost strata of the atmos¬
phere and the ionosphere, in particular
the auroral region, for which the site at
Kiruna, 200 km. (125 miles) inside the
polar circle, was selected; and to
investigate the solar radiations which
are the cause of most of the phenom¬
ena occurring in this part of the
atmosphere. Data will be obtained on
25
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
EUROPE'S GROWING SPACE SCIENCE (Cont'd)
© Mount Wilson and Mount Palomar
Observatories
SOLAR FLARES AND POLAR AURORA.
Satellites and sounding rockets have
been sent up to probe the mysteries
of solar activity which emits high-energy
particles (cosmic rays) and a "solar
wind", a stream of gas formed of pro¬
tons and electrons which is blown from
the solar corona. Millions of times less
brilliant than the solar disc itself, these
low-energy solar particles are only visi¬
ble during total eclipses of the sun
when the disc is obscured by the moon,
as on the photo above, taken during the
solar eclipse of June 8, 1918. Entering
into collision with molecules and atoms
of the earth's upper atmosphere, the
charged particles can produce the glow¬
ing aurora borealis (below).
© Upsala Ionosphere Observatory
electronic density, the temperature of
electrons, night glow, the turbulence
and temperature of the upper atmos¬
phere, and also on the ultra-violet,
X and gamma rays of the sun in its
periods of activity and calm.
Special activities will be undertaken
during the annular eclipse of the sun
(when the moon's disc eclipses the
whole of the sun except an outer ring),
which is due to occur on May 20, 1966.
Five small rockets of the Areas type
are to be launched at regular intervals;
also three large Centaure-type rockets
immediately before, during and directly
after the maximum eclipse phase.
The most important part of the scien¬
tific programme is obviously that relat¬
ing to satellites. The first two satelli¬
tes are to be launched in 1967 by the
National Aeronautics and Space Admi¬
nistration (NASA), from American
bases. One of them, Esro I, will be
an auroral satellite; the other, a cosmic
satellite. In other words, the first will
study the particles responsible for the
upper atmosphere auroral displays of
light in the polar regions; the simul¬
taneous launching of rockets during
the useful life of the satellite is also
planned.
To obtain maximum results from
these simultaneous launchings a
telemetry station will be set up at
Tromsö, in Norway. Here the data
transmitted back to earth will be pro¬
cessed and analysed immediately.
The second satellite, Esro 2, is to
concentrate on cosmic radiations, in
particular those emanating from the
sun. It will also study the rays "trap¬
ped" in the earth's magnetic field and
circulating in the vast cloak of radiation
known as the Van Allen belt.
Yet a further step forward will be
marked by the launching, scheduled
for 1968 and 1969, of medium stabilized
satellites, that is, satellites able to train
their apparatus on to any particular
region of the sky the sun, a planet, or
certain stars. The first of these (named
TD 1 because it will be launched by
a Thor Delta unit) is to concentrate
on spectrographic observation in radia¬
tion fields extending from the infra-red
to gamma ray radiation which, be¬
cause of atmospheric absorption, never
reaches the earth's surface.
It is hoped that interesting sources
will be revealed by these means; but
the satellite will in addition make a
more detailed survey of the ultra-violet
spectra of certain stars. As is known,
our ignorance of these spectra is an
obstacle to checking the validity of
theories about the origin and evolution
of the stars. Lastly, attention will
be paid to X and gamma rays: the
former in relation to radiations which
may have their source actually in
space; the latter, in relation to stel¬
lar radiations.
The second medium satellite, with
a total weight of approximately 400 kg.,
is to be placed on a polar orbit, so
as to pass over both the earth's polar
regions in succession; and its main
task will be to study the sun and its
effects during the phase of its maxi¬
mum activity. The experiments it will
carry out will be related to the ultra¬
violet and X-ray radiation from the sun
and the low energy particles streaming
from the sun, which are the sources
of the solar wind.
Other experiments will concentrate
on the emission of light from the upper
atmosphere due to the ionizing influ¬
ence of the sun; and lastly, on the
electronic density in the upper part of
the Ionosphere, studied from outside
the atmosphere instead of by sound¬
ings from the earth, as hitherto.
The fifth medium satellite Heos,
on which work has now begun, will
be launched into a highly eccentric orbit.
Heos will concentrate on the ter¬
restrial and solar magnetic fields, the
solar wind, and the radiation fluxes
occuring in the zone outside the mag-
netosphere, a zone which, thanks to
its elongated orbit, it will be able to
explore. It will attain a distance of more
than 200,000 kms. (125 000 miles) from
the earth.
We now come to the most ambitious
part of the satellite programme the
construction and launching of a large
astronomical satellite about a ton in
weight, designed for detailed spectro¬
scopy of the stars.
Some features of this satellite still re¬
main to be defined. But its equipment
will include telescopes that can be
accurately directed on selected stars,
spectrographic devices, and ultra-violet
radiation receivers or detectors.
Work on the European Space
Technology Centre (ESTEC) at
Noordwijk, the Netherlands, the Euro¬
pean Space Data Centre (ESDAC) at
Darmstadt, Federal Republic of Ger¬
many, and the launching base atKiruna,
Sweden, is now in full swing. The
launching base may even be inaug¬
urated this year, and ESTEC and
ESDAC in the course of next year.
Four satellite tracking stations are
being built, located respectively in Bel¬
gium, Alaska, Spitsberg and the Falk¬
land Islands, so as to cover as much
of the surface of the globe as possible.
Lastly, a site has been selected near
Rome for the European Space
Research Institute (ESRIN).
It can thus be seen that the orga¬
nization has made great strides since
it was officially set up in April 1964.
Meantime, several sounding rockets
have already been launched from the
Italian base in Sardinia, for European
scientists are impatient to pursue their
research.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Photos © APN Floating through the air with the greatest of ease, astronaut Adrian Nicolaiev learns to
cope with conditions of weightlessness during training session in an aeroplane in flight.
WHY WE ARE OUTWARD BOUND
by Konstantin Feoktistov
KONSTANTIN FEOKTISTOV, the author of
this article, learns to withstand acceleration
stresses. On October 12, 1964, the Soviet
spaceship Voskhod 1 made a 24-hour flight.
It carried Vladimir Komarov, the pilot, Boris
Egorov, a research physician and Konstantin
Feoktistov who carried out scientific studies
while in flight.
^^U HEN the first artificial earth
" satellite was launched a
friend and I made bets on the year in
which the first manned vehicle would
go into orbit. Our prophecies were
both wrong, but I won either by pure
luck or because I was the more
optimistic. Yuri Gagarin's flight took
place much sooner than could have
been foretold nine years ago.
What is it that compels man to leave
the confines of his own planet? Is it
rational to spend so much effort and
material on the exploration of outer
space when there are still so many
unsolved problems In our own world?
To what extent is this expenditure on
sputniks and luniks and other vehicles
justified when so many people still
lack food, clothing and proper housing?
It is doubtful whether anyone would
try to give a definitive answer to these
questions. Each answer could, at
best, be only one of many possible
points of view.
The idea of space travel has
absorbed me for many years and will,
it seems, keep me busy till the end
of my life. Here I should like to set
down some ideas on the subject that
derive from my own personal
experience.
When I was about ten I came across
a book called Interplanetary Travel
and, reading it, caught the "moon
disease". The flights seemed to me
to be so real and so easy to
accomplish, and the need for them
was so indisputable that, with all the
sincerity of youth, I accused the grown¬
ups around me of laziness and
lack of scientific acumen. I could not
reconcile myself to the idea that earth-
moon communications had not been
established. So my elder brother and
I decided to get busy on the problem
immediately.
We had to postpone our naive plans,
however. War broke out, my brother
was killed and I was wounded.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
CENTURIES BACK
Cyrano de Bergerac, the French writer, in
"Voyages to the Moon and the Sun" (1650)
imagined a weird method of becoming
space borne. His hero reasoned that the
sun causes the morning dew to rise, so
went aloft by attaching vials filled with
dew to his body. On the moon he en¬
countered another earthling, carried there
in a machine powered by geese (above).
This was the adventurous traveller describ¬
ed by the English author, Francis Godwin,
In "The Man in the Moone". (1638).
NOT SO LONG AGO
In his cell at the Peter and Paul Fortress
in St. Petersburg, where he had been
imprisoned for revolutionary activities, a
young Russian, Nicolas Kibaltchitch (1853-
1881). speculated about space flight and
devised a rocket type machine for cosmic
travel. Drawing above Is based on his
sketches of this rocket-propelled spacecraft.
YESTERDAY
The 19th-century science fiction works of
Jules Verne were a mixture of scientific
accuracy, astute speculation and outright
imagination. In "Around the Moon," a 900-ft
cannon fires a capsule into space. Illustra¬
tion shows Verne's astronauts floating hel¬
plessly in a state of weightlessness in their
cabin. But Jules Verne correctly foresaw
many space problems, including the need
for tremendous speed to escape earth's
gravity and for a means to change course
while in space by the use of retro rockets.
WHY WE ARE OUTWARD BOUND (Cont'd)
At 40, I have not lost hope
of landing on the moon
28
Despite all the dramatic events of the
war years, my dream of space travel
never left me; it was with me when
I enrolled in the higher technical school
and when I was working as an
engineer. I chose it as the subject
of the thesis I presented for the degree
of candidate of science.
Two years ago I spent a day and a
night in orbital flight as a member of
the crew of the spaceship Voskhod I.
My dream has still not been fulfilled,
but 1 am on the right road. There is
every reason to believe that the age
limit for astronauts will be progressively
raised as technical improvements
are made, and although I recently
celebrated my fortieth birthday I have
still not lost hope of one day stepping
out of a spaceship onto the moon. If
I do not, my life will seem incomplete.
The "Call of the Cosmos" emerged
from a dream. Like almost every
dream it came before its time, far in
advance of man's technical capabilities.
Eduard Tsiolkovsky (an early Russian
theorist on the principles of space
flight, see page 10), translated Jules
Verne's pure fantasy into a potentially
attainable scientific concept.
The generation born at the beginning
of this century began the job of
embodying Tsiolkovsky's ideas in
metal and of turning his prophecies
into convincing facts. At first the
work was sporadic and unorganized,
and as has often been the case in the
history of science, eccentrics and
enthusiasts watched over the cradle
of the new-born science.
When the group for the study of
rocket motors (GIRD) was founded in
Moscow, followed by the laboratory
of gas dynamics (GDL) and still later,
in 1955, by the rocket institute,
experiments that had hitherto been
rather primitive became part of the
state plan of the U.S.S.R. One of the
founders of GIRD was Sergei Korolyov,
later a member of the U.S.S.R.
Academy of Sciences and a designer
of carrier-rockets and spaceships,
who died at the beginning of this year.
If a man has begun to take an
interest in a problem, he is already
mature enough to penetrate more
deeply into it. Every problem is a
challenge to man, every problem
makes him think. Thinking leads to
plans for the solution of the problem.
A sort of chain reaction sets in.
When you have given some thought
to the problem of supplying power
for a heavy interplanetary vehicle you
come to the conclusion that an
expedition to another planet cannot
use chemical fuel the engines must
be more effective, they must be ion
or plasma motors.
And when you think of the duties
of the crew that is to carry out a
certain mission you also begin to
think of the people who will compose
that crew. This naturally gives rise to
problems of providing food, water and
air for the crew during flight. Here it
is obvious that a complete ecological
cycle must be maintained on board
the spaceship) the crew must be
provided with everything necessary to
support life, and their body wastes
must be eliminated or, better still, used
in a rational way.
As this huge skein of problems is
unravelled we begin to visualize the
space expedition of the distant future.
The very possibility of visualizing turns
a man's thoughts, whether he wishes
it or not, to the search for new
solutions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
From dream to reality
From far off times man has been ob¬
sessed by the idea of space travel, and
usually the goal of his imaginary jour-
teys has been the moon. Indeed, story
ellers, poets and writers reached the
earth 's natural satellite well in advance
of the sate/lite moon probes sent out
by space science. To do so they devised
a wealth of ingenious, however imprac¬
tical, methods.
TODAY
he first guided automatic
iterplanetary station was
lunched towards Venus
y Soviet scientists on
aU^iam 10 ioßi r^;«k*-\
he station weighed 1,419
)s. Strange looking ve-
icles like this one. in
fhich science has outdone
science fiction," are blaz-
ig a trail to the planets.
TOMORROW
The four-armed monster,
in this drawing, called the
"Schmoo." is an unmanned
repair craft sent out by the
wheel-shaped space station in
background to render assist¬
ance to a nuclear-powered
space vehicle in difficulty.
A concrete scheme of experi¬
mentation and designing is born of the
free play of intellects. These flights
of fancy are becoming a necessary
stage in preparatory work that
sometimes takes years to complete.
The basis of it all is a perfectly
comprehensible and natural human
quality man finds it difficult not to
yield to the temptation to think ahead
of his time.
It would of course be naive to
suggest that this one human quality
is sufficient explanation of man's urge
to get out into the great universe.
There are objective causes of a
demographic and social nature that are
rather more difficult to understand.
One can quite easily imagine the
time, a few hundred years from now,
when the population of the world will
become so dense that each continent
will be turned into one big city like
Moscow or New York. Man will feel
the overcrowding physically so that
for him the mastery of considerable
areas in outer space will have a
practical significance. The future
spread of man is bound up with space
since he will be unable to confine
himself to his own planet, even if, for
the time being, he has not realized
this. This, too, was one of Tsiol-
kovsky's ideas.
Long before the physical over¬
crowding is felt, however, people will
begin to feel a spiritual constraint. A
surplus of energy within a close-knit
community must find an outlet or there
will be stagnation and retrogression.
Man always stands in need of a goal
that mobilizes his spiritual and physical
energy. Sooner or later all mankind
will unite and there will be no further
danger of the nuclear self destruction
of civilization.
Then, to a greater degree than now,
the single community will have before
it a great purpose the conquest of
space, beginning with circumsolar
space.
Today's space flights are mere
reconnaissance; the means for a
thorough study of conditions in space
and dangers that await man there have
still to be created. The dangers I
have in mind are solar flares, lethal
radiation, dust clouds, meteoric
showers, the effect of long periods of
weightlessness on the human organism
and other hazards specific to travel
beyond the bounds of the earth.
Wé have still to develop, on the
grand scale, ways of studying the
planets, their surfaces and their
composition, their atmosphere and
their radiation and magnetic fields.
Lastly we have still to design
spaceships capable of journeys to
other planets that may last several
years, provide them with ultra-long¬
distance communications and with
navigation instruments, and supply
oxygen, food and water for the crew
under conditions in which every ounce
of weight counts.
To do all this cybernetics will have
to be extensively developed, electronic
computers and analysers perfected
and a "Sun Service" organized that
will provide a series of circumsolar
automatic satellites to transmit data
predicting solar flares, the direction
in which radiation streams are being
generated, and so on. Space biology
and planetology must also be further
developed. There will be a need to
build observatories in space, artificial
inhabited planets from which studies
of the universe can be made and
which can be used to facilitate space
travel.
Even this sketchy programme of
space exploration gives some idea of
the colossal effort man must make
and the expenditure that will be
necessary to put it into effect.
Has not the world perhaps begun its
invasion of space prematurely? Is not
the expenditure of effort and resources
inadvisable since it has to be made
now, whereas people will live in space
in hundreds of years' time? Would it
not be more reasonable to create better
living conditions everywhere on earth
and let space wait its turn...?
In principle, one cannot open the
door to a new sphere of activity and
then suddenly slam it shut again, not
even for the sake of economy. The
process works only one way; it is
irreversible if the technical means
for space travel exist they cannot
remain unused. The exploration of
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
Why we are
outward bound (com-d)
space, moreover, is already bringing
beneficial results, even at this initial
stage.
The implementation of an intricate'
programme for the design of carrier
rockets, automatic space stations and
spaceships is promoting the rapid
development of the more progressive
branches of science and engineering
cybernetics, physics, biology and
medicine, radio engineering and the
aerodynamics of supersonic velocities.
The results of this development also
effect ordinary "terrestrial" life
because they promote general tech¬
nical progress and thus better living
standards.
Some of the achievements of space
engineering have already made their
mark in economic and cultural life.
Retransmission satellites are used for
telecommunications, including tele¬
vision on a global scale. Navigation
satellites make sea travel more
reliable. Meteorological satellites are
reducing errors in forecasting weather
conditions in various parts of the
world.
I think it is a mistake to weigh space
exploration against man's efforts to
improve his living standards. These
are different aspects of the totality
of human progress and they are not
contradictory.
The two "space powers", the
U.S.S.R. and the U.S.A., are working
separately, independently of each
other. Does this have a negative
effect on the rate of development and
the results of space exploration?
Personally, I think not; I believe
that this involuntary rivalry has not,
up to now, been a hindrance. When
anything new is started, an approach
from different angles tends to further
its development.
Steps have already been made along
the road to co-operation. Work on
the U.S. satellite Echo 2 has begun
on an international scale. There are
also prospects of space collaboration
with France. We may expect the next
stage in the development of this
co-operation to be the exchange of
information, the exchange of orders for
the manufacture of various installations
and a certain degree of specialization.
It is quite obvious that as the
exploration of space proceeds, sooner
or later problems will arise that cannot
be solved by any one country but
which will require the united efforts
of all mankind.
MOON CRAWLER. Capable, sturdy self-contained vehicles will be re¬
quired for lunar exploration and development. This drawing shows
one concept of such a vehicle. Equipped with threepoint caterpillar
treads for stability and a rocket system, this hybrid vehicle
would be able to crawl or make short flights over moon terrain.
It would carry geophysicists, geochemists, geologists and
other scientists on long range investigations over the moon's surface.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Drawing Northrop, California
** T-.X5
Goodyear, Ohio
MAMMOTH TYRES (above)
are a mock-up of those
being developed for a
U.S. moon vehicle. Though
16 ft. in diameter,
each will weigh only 125 lbs.
LUNAR LANDSCAPE.
The surface of the moon
photographed last February
by the Soviet moon probe,
Lunar 9, first spacecraft to
make a soft lunar touchdown.
LUNAR
INTERNATIONAL
LABORATORY
by Bruno Friedman
S OMETIME around 1970 a
human being will, for the
first time in the history of the universe,
set foot upon the moon. The visible
vehicle that will carry him there will
be a rocket. Yet in a very real sense
the true thrust will be generated not
by burning fuel, but by the surge of
science over the centuries.
The truth of this statement is reveal¬
ed when it is realized that the epochal
feat will be synthesized out of major
contributions from virtually every
branch of modern science (and of
engineering, as well): chemistry, phy¬
sics, electronics, mathematics, medi¬
cine, bacteriology, psychology, astro¬
nomy, geophysics, metallurgy, and
others.
Now let us note for it is germane
to what follows that science is, above
all, international. There is no branch
of science that has been developed by
a single nation. Rather, every branch
of science is the creation of know¬
ledge-seekers, great and obscure, of
all nations, each making his contribu¬
tion over the course of time to erect
the total moon-achieving structure.
With science so much the shaper of
the achievement, it is most fitting that
science will be a great beneficiary of
man's installation on the moon. As
Dr. Frank Malina states it: "Just about
every branch of science will find the
moon, with its unique environmental
conditions no atmosphere, a gravity
only 1/6th that of earth., very weak or
non-existent magnetic field a great
laboratory for a host of experiments
and observations essentially impos¬
sible to perform on earth. Great pro¬
gress must inevitably be stimulated."
Dr. Malina speaks as Chairman of
the Lunar International Laboratory
(LIL) Committee of the International
Academy of Astronautics (IAA). And
the LIL Committee, composed of
distinguished space scientists from
several nations, is the embodiment of
the awareness that the moon's great
potential for science can best be
realized if the investigations are
"onducted as an international venture
and in an international laboratory.
The LIL Committee came into being
in August 1960, when the concept
of a lunar international laboratory
was put forward by Dr. Malina at
Stockholm during the 11th Congress
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
LUNAR LABORATORY (Cont'd)
Will the moon disclose
a lost record of the universe?
of the International Astronautical Fed¬
eration (IAF) and was welcomed as a
meaningful project by the then newly-
formed Academy (1).
The committee has two purposes:
to awaken the interest of the world's
scientific community at large in the
lunar laboratory, and to explore by
means of discussions and symposia
the various lines of research that can
be profitably conducted on the moon.
These are generally held at the annual
IAF congresses, whose seats are the
capitals of the world.
'HE committee's efforts
_ have met with considerable
success. Its meetings and a discussion
panel held at Warsaw in 1964 have pro¬
duced a broad overall view of lunar
science. Now the sciences are being
explored in depth at symposia devoted
to particular subjects. At the first
symposium at Athens in September
1965, the papers presented dealt speci¬
fically with lunar geosciences and
astronomy and astrophysics. The sub¬
jects for the Madrid symposium, in
October 1966, are the life sciences and
lunar medicine.
That the majority of the papers are
presented by experts who are not
committee members reveals the wide¬
spread response of the international
scientific community to the idea of
a lunar laboratory.
From these studies will be evolved
a sound scientific programme for a
laboratory, when the time is ripe for
it. When? The committee foresees
that this will be sometime in the period
1975-85.
The scientific investigations on the
moon may greatly advance our under-
32
(J) Its present roster Includes such lumi¬
naries of the space sciences as: M. Florkin
of Belgium; N. Boneff of Bulgaria; A. Dollfus
and L. Malavard of France; H. Oberth of the
German Federal Republic; F. Zwicky of
Switzerland; L.I. Sedov of the U.S.S.R.; AC.
Clarke, Z. Kopal and Sir Bernard Love//
(Vice-Chairman) of the U.K.; and W.H.
Pickering, S.F. Singer, L. Spitzer Ir., H.
Strughold and H.C. Urey of the U.S.A. Noralr
Sissakian of the U.S.S.R., was also a member
until his death last March.
standing of man, his environment and
the universe in which he lives.
The priority subject will be, of
course, the moon itself. The founda¬
tion work will be done at the national
level by the first moon explorers,
American and Soviet, perhaps acting
in co-operation as the nations do in
Antarctica.
The large-scale work of mapping the
moon's geographical, geological and
geophysical features will be done by
circumlunar satellites, some put into
orbit even before the first human
landings, others after. These highly
sophisticated orbiters, using infra-red
sensors, radar, radio microwaves,
radiation counters and other devices,
will not only map the surface, but
probe under the surface.
The lunar scientists themselves will
make direct observations and experi¬
ments to determine the nature of the
lunar rocks, the moon's seismic and
volcanic activity, its internal tempera¬
ture and structure.
What is learned about the moon
may help answer many questions
about our earth. The geological
record of the earth's history has been
greatly damaged and obscured by the
volcanic, seismic, erosive and sedi¬
mentary processes to which the crust
has been subjected over the 4.5
thousand million years of the earth's
existence.
This is much less true of the moon,
with no atmosphere, no oceans and a
far cooler interior. Reading the geolo¬
gical record of the moon, which is
as old as the earth, may reveal much,
by analogy, particularly about the
earth's formative period, its first one
thousand million years.
Moreover, this reading of the moon's
early history, taken together with anal¬
yses of the remains of meteorites on
the lunar surface, will give the scien¬
tists valuable clues as to how the
solar system itself was formed.
Meteorites are artifacts of the solar
system's genesis, relics left over from
the age when dispersed matter agglom¬
erated to form the planets and their
moons. These invaluable information
carriers from the past reach the earth
in frustratingly limited numbers, for
very few survive the fiery passage
through the atmosphere. But the
moon's surface will be rich with their
remains.
CONT'D ON PAGE 34
Heroes & hobbies
of the junior
astronaut
The conquest of space fascinates
young people the world over. Right, Polish
youngsters perch beneath pictures of U.S.
and Soviet astronauts their real-life
heroes. Far right, reverie beneath
a large-scale model of a lunar landscape.
Right, young Soviet space enthusiast
displays a model interplanetary
station he has designed and made; it will
join spacecraft and installations on the
model of a future inhabited planet (below)
made by other members of a
junior astronauts' club in the U.S.S.R.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
vS s V fr*
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
LUNAR LABORATORY (Cont'd)
A superb new window
on the far reaches of space
34
Valuable indications as to how life
evolved on earth may also be found
in the lunar surface. That any life
forms, or even remains of life forms,
will be discovered is doubtful, given
the moon's harsh conditions. Yet the
lunar scientists may find carbon com¬
pounds, produced by natural chemical
reactions, which represent intermediate
stages in the formation of the first
primitive carbon-based living mole¬
cules from which all life on earth devel¬
oped. This would be a resounding
discovery.
There is even a remote possibility,
points out Prof. H. Florkin of the Uni¬
versity of Liege, that primitive life
forms or their remains may be found
in lunar micro-environments, where the
conditions are far less severe than
in the gross environment. Such micro-
environments may be, for example,
deep pits in craters, the interiors of
porous rocks or some metres down
in the lunar surface layer.
To the new insights that lunar
science may provide about the solar
system, earth and life, add those that
may be gained about the origins and
formation of the great universe itself,
because the moon will be such a
superb observatory for both optical
and radio astronomy.
On earth, the atmosphere greatly
limits the passage of light waves and
radio waves. Moreover, man himself
is a considerable impediment, pro¬
ducing enormous quantities of artifi¬
cial light and interfering radio waves
from all forms of electronic equipment.
Astronomy on the moon will gain
greatly from the absence of these
disadvantages, as well as from specific
lunar advantages, such as a far slower
rotation period, enabling astronomical
instruments to follow their targets over
a much longer period of time.
Lunar telescopes, optical and radio,
will be able to probe much farther out
into the reaches of space, will be able
to "see" heavenly objects far dimmer
than can be now seen from earth,
will be able to resolve much finer
details of these objects, will be able
to "see" much better into the interior
of our Milky Way, a typical spiral
galaxy.
From the new information gained
as, for example, by the accurate
counting of distant galaxies it may be
possible for cosmologists to decide
between two current conflicting hypo¬
theses about the origins of our universe
or to reject both and propose a
better one.
The moon will also be an outstanding
meteorological observatory, helping to
raise weather prediction to new levels
of accuracy, it was noted by Prof. K.Y.
Kondratiev and co-workers of the Uni¬
versity of Leningrad in a paper pre¬
sented at the Athens LIL symposium.
Telescopic observations from the
moon will' follow the large-scale move¬
ments of clouds and air masses in the
earth's atmosphere. Their big view
will complement the smaller-range,
more detailed observations made by
a system of meteorological satellites
orbiting the earth.
LL the above is a very
incomplete catalogue of
science on the moon. In addition,
observations, presently impossible from
earth, will be made on cosmic rays
and on the nuclear particles that fill
interplanetary space; experiments in
considerable variety will be made in
chemistry and physics in the lunar
vacuum and in plant and animal biology
in rigorous lunar conditions. Important
advances in all these fields cannot fail
to result.
Moreover, much will be learned
about man himself: about his physio¬
logy, his psychology and his sociolog¬
ical relationships in the high-stress
lunar environment. The LIL scientists
themselves will be the guinea pigs.
For, as Prof. C. Stark Draper of
the Massachusetts Institute of Tech¬
nology has emphasized, humans will
be in short supply in the lunar labor¬
atory for a long time because of the
high costs of placing men and equip¬
ment there. Much of the data gathering
will be done by compact automatic
sensors. These data, after conden¬
sation in the laboratory's lightweight
computers, will be telemetered to co¬
operating research centres and uni¬
versities on earth for analysis.
Which points up a question: How
will a lunar laboratory be created,
organized and managed as a co-oper¬
ative international activity?
The LIL Committee cannot deal with
this question, for this is a matter that
governments must resolve. Quite
possibly, however, a suggested scien¬
tific programme evolved out of the
committee's work will be helpful when
the intergovernmental deliberations
regarding a laboratory begin.
The committee feels that possibly
the lunar international laboratory could
be established under the auspices of
an existing international organization,
such as the U.N. or Unesco. And
an indication of Unesco's awakening
interest in the matter is the fact that
it is contributing funds to enable
scientists to attend the 1966 Madrid
LIL symposium.
Certainly these bodies, the U.N. and
Unesco, have long been interested
in the establishment of international
scientific centres.
A few such centres have indeed
been created: CERN (European Centre
for Nuclear Research) at Geneva and
the International Computation Centre
at Rome, both founded through
Unesco initiative, though they are
not Unesco bodies; also, there are
the United Institute of Nuclear Re¬
search at Dubna, U.S.S.R. (the Eastern
European equivalent of CERN), the
European Launcher Development Or¬
ganization (ELDO) and the European
Space Research Organization (ESRO).
So the nations can get together.
Moreover, the problems of establishing
a lunar centre, a lunar international
laboratory, may be much reduced by
comparison with those which have
blocked the founding of terrestial sci¬
entific centres, by the moon's remote¬
ness thus reducing the conflicts of
national self-interest and by its power¬
ful appeal as a human adventure. So
the world's states may have a stronger
will to bring a laboratory of this kind
into being.
The foundations for a lunar interna¬
tional laboratory may well have been
laid on December 13, 1963, when the
General Assembly of the United Na¬
tions unanimously approved a Dec¬
laration of the Legal Principles Gov¬
erning the Activities of States in the
Exploration and Use of Outer Space.
The first principle states:
"The exploration and use of outer
space shall be carried on for the bene¬
fit and in the interests of all mankind."
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
SPACE FLIGHT AND THE RULE OF LAW
Continued from page 18
Who put me into orbit the
wrong way round?
O Plem
What did I do with my space-
pilot's licence?
Lookl the Martian canals are
simply abstract paintings.
satellites, fragments) circulating in out¬
er space and liable, sooner or later, to
fall back to earth, the danger of their
colliding either with other similar ob¬
jects or with space vehicles traversing
the atmosphere will increase as time
goes on.
The 1963 Declaration already pro¬
claims, as a general principle, that each
state which launches or originates the
launching of an object into outer
space and each state from whose terri¬
tory or installations an object is launch¬
ed, is Internationally liable for damage
to a foreign state or to persons or
property within its borders by such
object or its parts, whether the dam¬
age is caused on the earth, in the air,
or In outer space.
This provision in general terms needs
to be followed up by an international
convention such as that which the
Committee on the Peaceful Uses of
Outer Space is at present engaged in
drafting, on the basis of proposals
submitted by Belgium, Hungary and
the United States. The convention
will need to define what is meant by
"damage" (material damage, moral
damage, financial loss and so on). The
extent of liability will also have to be
specified. Should provision be made
for exemption or attenuation? Is lia¬
bility to be limited? How is liability
to be shared out in the event of joint
enterprises by several states?
In the case of launchings carried
out by an international organization,
who will be responsible for damage
caused? The Declaration of 1963
simply states that "responsibility for
compliance with the principles set
forth in this Declaration shall be borne
by the international organization and
by the states participating in it." Is
provision to be made for joint respon¬
sibility? Procedures to be followed
to obtain compensation for damages
will also have to be drawn up.
In addition to these two important
legal questions, now being considered,
the Declaration mentions various others
for which international agreements will
doubtless be necessary. There is, for
instance, the principle whereby states
shall conduct their activities in outer
space with due regard for the corres¬
ponding interests of other states. This
provision was included on account of
certain experiments in the past which
gave rise to some agitation amongst
the users of space, in particular astron¬
omers.
The Declaration outlines an arrange¬
ment whereby if a state believes
that an activity or experiment in space
which it or its citizens plan to carry
out might interfere with the peaceful
exploration and use of space by other
states, it should first consult them.
Conversely, such consultations could
also be requested by states if they
considered that certain activities pro¬
posed by other states might interfere
with the peaceful exploration and use
of space. However, this text lacks
precision, and lays down no specific
procedure for such consultations or
for following them up.
HE broader principle of
ensuring that certain ex¬
periments cause no harm to mankind
as a whole has been the subject of
detailed studies both at the Institute of
International Law in Brussels and at the
David Davies Memorial Institute of
International Studies in London. Both
have stressed the danger that might
result from any modifications of the
earth or the celestial bodies, their
atmosphere or space itself, by the in¬
troduction of elements liable to upset
the existing equilibrium, such as by
changing the climate or meteorological
conditions of specific regions.
The British institute has drawn up
various regulations designed to pro¬
vide against and sanction any such
activities. Here again, a convention
is called for; also a convention to
prevent biological, radiological or
chemical contamination of outer space
and the celestial bodies by vehicles
from the earth and vice-versa.
With the installation, in the near
future, of manned scientific stations
first on the moon and subsequently
on other celestial bodies, the legal
status of such stations, will naturally
have to be considered. In view of the
general principles proclaimed in the
Declaration of 1963 the installation of
such stations will not, of course,
constitute grounds for national appro¬
priation of the moon or celestial
bodies, or even of the particular area
on which such stations are located.
35
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
An alphabet is born
Six major West African languages have
now been given a unified alphabet. Meet¬
ing at Bamako, Mali, under Unesco's aus¬
pices (see the Unesco Courier, March
1966) an international group of linguists
has produced a simple alphabet that en¬
ables all the sounds in six languages the
Mandingo languages, Songhay-Jerma, Ta-
mashek, Hausa, Kanuri and Fulani to be
accurately represented. The alphabet's six
languages, in roman letters, will be basi¬
cally identical, and Fulani, Hausa, Tama-
shek and Songhay-Jerma will require only
eight new letters. Six linguistic groups
spread over seven nations now have alpha¬
bets that should enable them to transcribe
an immense heritage of oral literature, and
governments have national languages for
adult literacy teaching and primary edu¬
cation.
World's longest radio
antenna
A steel and aluminium cable almost two
miles long has been stretched over a
fjord in northern Norway. It is an antenna
the longest in the world and one of
the links in the international Omega navi¬
gational trial system which so far com¬
prises transmitters in Trinidad, Hawaii, and
Forestport, New York
Space is 'in'
What is uppermost in the minds of
Americans today? Visitors to the Ameri¬
can Library Association's computerized
library exhibit at the New York World's
Fair gave a clear indication that it is
travel in space. Visitors were able to put
questions to a computer which responded
by producing reading lists at five educa¬
tional levels, or essays in English or four
languages on 75 current interest topics.
"Travel in Space" led in both the number
of reading lists and essays requested.
Helping deaf children
to speak
A combined headphone-microphone unit
designed in the United Kingdom can help
partially deaf children to speak. It can
be used to magnify the volume of sound
without distortion so that even a deaf child
can listen to its own first efforts at forming
sounds and words. In the classroom the
children's headphones can be connected
to a common amplifier set before the teach¬
er, whose voice can then be heard by the
children.
Colourful highways
A laboratory in the Federal Republic of
Germany has perfected a method of per¬
manently colouring road surfaces. Experi¬
ments now being conducted indicate that
colour-coded roads might eventually replace
the forest of warning signs that distract
almost as much as they instruct the driver
on high-speed freeways.
Electricity from a coconut
Coconut milk, as well as the Juice from
sugar cane, yams and certain fruits, can
be used to produce electricity. The tech¬
nique perfected by a group of U.S. scien¬
tists, involves the use of bacteria (aero-
monas formicans) which turn the coconut
milk into formic acid. This is an electro¬
chemical fuel from which a battery can
draw electric current. The system, known
as the biochemical fuel cell, has already
been used to power a transistor radio.
World population atlas
Soviet scholars have begun the com¬
pilation of a "World Population Atlas".
Maps showing the migration of populations,
their distribution and location, social and
cultural features will provide a picture of
the varied character of the world population
today. The atlas will also contain maps
showing the settlement of nomads, urbani¬
zation, the rise and growth of new metro¬
polises and the connexion between the
spread of the population and irrigation
developments.
Unesco - Dominique Roger
An international group of jazz artists donat¬
ed their services for a concert given at
Unesco headquarters recently for the bene¬
fit of the world campaign against illiteracy.
Among them were the trios of Art Simmons,
Michel Sardaby, Ron Jefferson and Errol
Parker; instrumentalists Don Jetter, Hal
Singer, Nathan Davis (above, on left) and
Glen Ragland; Singer Jenny Gordee, Ruble
Blakey, who introduced the artists, and
Ted Easton's Jazz Band. Proceeds from
the concert, which was organized by the
Jazz Club of Unesco's Staff Association,
will be used to help finance literacy
projects in various parts of the world.
Space flight and the rule of law (Cont'd)
36
The David Davies Memorial Institute
of International Studies has suggested
that these stations should be placed
as soon as possible under United
Nations control, but that the state
which has established, or permitted
its nationals to establish such a station
should retain jurisdiction over all
persons inhabiting it, and over such of
the surrounding area as has to be
traversed for the use and upkeep of
the station.
In the event of two stations
belonging to different states being
installed in close proximity on a celes¬
tial body, it would be essential to
define their respective fields of compe¬
tence and also to take certain other
measures designed in particular to
prevent interferences in their radio
communications.
The status of lunar or planetary
stations, and also of space platforms,
now presents an urgent legal problem
for jurists to take into consideration.
Other legal problems either have
arisen or will arise as a result of the
recent development of communications
by satellite, a new system which
clearly holds great promise not only
as a means for supplementing and
facilitating communications by the trad¬
itional methods, but also for the rapid
spreading of education and devel¬
opment of cultural exchanges. Such
communications will, however, require
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Tracing fresh water 'leaks'
in the ocean
A new method of locating underground
water is being used by the U.S. Geolo¬
gical Survey. Infra-red photographic detec¬
tors, sensitive to heat, are mounted on
aircraft and are used to scan the coast¬
lines of Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands
In search of much needed fresh water
sources. Since the fresh water is either
warmer or cooler than the ocean water,
the heat detectors can clearly distinguish
it flowing into the ocean from underground
water-bearing rocks. Scientists then trace
these "leaks" to their source, which can
eventually be tapped.
Roadbuilding
around the world
The Soviet Union has begun to con¬
struct a 620-mile (1,000 km.) freeway that
will link Moscow and Wolgograd (formerly
Stalingrad). A 1.300-mile (2,090 km.)
road Is to be built in India from Dehra Dun
to Amingaon through the states of Uttar
Pradesh, Bihar, West Bengal and Assam,
paralleling the Ganges River for most of
the way. Work will begin this year on a
one mile (1.6 km.) tunnel under
the River Elbe, by-passing Hamburg, Fede¬
ral Republic of Germany. Some 1,200-
miles (1,930 km.) of road were built in Inner
Mongolia In 1964.
School for community
leaders
A college of a new kind has been
founded in Palermo, Sicily, by a group of
Italian, Swedish and British specialists.
The Sicilian Institute for the Training of
Development Workers, as it is called, will
train unionists, co-operative members,
farmers, teachers and other potential local
leaders to take greater responsibility and
Initiative in the development of their own
communities.
Level of Caspian falling
Between 1930 and 1965 the depth of the
Caspian, the world's largest inland sea,
dropped by 2.5 metres (8 ft.) and is
expected to fall a further metre by 1976.
Soviet scientists say this is due in part
to the warming up of the Caspian basin
which has reduced the flow of rivers, but
the construction of large reservoirs has
also contributed. The drop has doubled
the need for dredging in ports and canals
and has caused a decline in fish catches.
The oceanography committee of the Soviet
Academy of Sciences is studying several
schemes to halt the decline.
Martian laboratory
A chamber reproducing the climate and
atmosphere of the planet Mars has been
developed at the Microbiology Institute of
the U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences to study
the behaviour of bacteria. It automatically
reproduces (under an atmospheric pressure
one-hundredth of that on earth) the changes
that take place in a Martian day, and tem¬
peratures varying between 60 degrees
and' + 30 Centigrade.
Flashes...
Jupiter, the largest planet of our solar
system, radiates two and a half times as
much heat as it receives from the sun,
report astronomers at the University of
Arizona.
A new teleprinter developed in the
United Kingdom can transmit 1,250 words
a minute 76 times faster than conventional
teleprinters.
About 750,000 seafarers are employed
on the world's foreign-going ships, but
only 1 % of them are women reports
WHO in a world-wide study on the health
of mariners.
A new National Park, the third in France,
is being created in the Pyrenees. Cover¬
ing 125,000 acres, it adjoins the Spanish
frontier south of Lourdes.
0 More than 10,000 foreign students are
enrolled in Austria's universities and tech¬
nical colleges and comprise about 20 %
of the country's total student population.
BOOKSHELF
Art Treasures of the United Nations
By Jacob Baal-Teshuva. On the art that
embellishes U.N. .Headquarters. Thomas
Yoseloff, New York and London, 1964
($7.50).
Management of Wild Mammals in Capti¬
vity
By Lee S. Crandall, General Curator Emer¬
itus, New York Zoological Park. The Uni¬
versity of Chicago Press, Chicago and
London ($13.50).
The Black Ship Scroll
By Oliver Statler. An account of Commo¬
dore Perry's expedition to Japan in 1854,
based on contemporay records and Japan¬
ese scroll paintings in full colour. Charles
E. Turtle Company, Rutland, Vermont,
U.S.A., 1964 ($.5.00).
The Housewarming and other selected
writings
By Rabindranath Tagore. A Signet Classic
(paperback), The New American Library,
New York and Toronto (75 c.) ; The New
English Library Ltd., London, 1965.
The Arabs
By E.C. Hodgkin. A new volume in The
Modern World series. Oxford University
Press, London, 1966 (paperback; 7/6).
The Birth of the Gods:
the origin of primitive beliefs
By Guy E. Swanson. University of Michigan
Press, Ann Arbor, U.S.A.; Ambassador
Books Ltd. Toronto. Canada, 1960 ($5.95).
The Population Dilemma
A picture of population trends and pros¬
pects in the world presented by eleven
authorities and edited by Philip M. Häuser.
(The American Assembly, Columbia Univer¬
sity series). Prentice-Hall Inc., Englewood
Cliffs, N.J.. U.S.A., 1963 (Paperbound, $1.95;
clothbound, $3.95).
the elaboration of new laws, espec¬
ially when it becomes possible for
radio and television signals transmitted
from some part of the earth to be
received direct, via a satellite, at any
other point on the earth.
Even at the present stage in the
development of telecommunications,
numerous legal difficulties have arisen,
for which a solutions must be found.
Some of these difficulties were dis¬
cussed recently at a meeting of experts
on the use of space communications
by the mass media, held at Unesco
Headquarters, in December 1965.
They are due, for instance, to such
things as differences in the laws on
the use of satellites in transmitter and
receiver countries, differences in libel
laws, variations in copyright laws
according to whether or not countries
are parties to the copyright conven¬
tions, and whether or not advertising
is allowed in radio programmes.
There will be a need for special
regulations governing the composition
of programmes for universal transmis¬
sion, so as to avoid infringing certain
regulations in force. The Preamble to
the Declaration of December 13, 1963
recalls that a General Assembly resol¬
ution of November 3, 1947, which
condemned propaganda designed or
likely to provoke or encourage any
threat to the peace or act of aggres¬
sion, is applicable to outer space.
As the science of astronautics
achieves new successes in the con¬
quest of space, fresh legal problems __
will arise, in addition to those outlined g/
above, calling for solution by wide
international co-operation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WHAT IT IS...'
Sir.
Why not send a pamphlet such as
"Unesco, what it is, what it does,
how it works" to each new subscriber
along with the first number of the
Unesco Courier? This would give your
new readers a clear understanding
of Unesco's aims and show them its
wide range of activities, and they
would get even greater benefit from
reading the Courier.
G. Thevenot
Châteaudun, France
An excellent suggestion which has
been adopted. Arrangements are
being made for a copy of 'Unesco,
what it is, what it does, how it works',
in English, French or Spanish, to
accompany the acknowledgement of
each new subscription Editor.
SPACE-AGE REAPING
Sir,
We are interested to see that your
January 1966 issue contains an article,
"Messages to the Stars", by Dr. D.M.A.
Mercer, one of a series of papers
delivered at the Science Fiction
session of the Southampton meeting
of the British Association for the
Advancement of Science last year.
We should be obliged if you would
find space to insert a note drawing
your readers' attention to the fact
that this paper and the other three
papers In the Science Fiction session
are available In "The Advancement
of Science", the Journal of the British
Association (Vol. 22, No. 98, August
1965, price 5/-). The titles of the
other three papers are Travel In Space
and Time, Problems of Alien Biology,
and Alien Sociology.
J.M. Robertson
Editor, The Advancement of Science
3 Sanctuary Buildings
20 Great Smith Street, London S.W. 1.
WOMEN IN SCIENCE
38
AND TECHNOLOGY
Sir,
In connexion with International Co¬
operation Year we have Just been
celebrating, I would like to call your
attention to an activity of international
co-operation: to help promote the
education of women In scientific-tech¬
nological fields where women repre¬
sent a valuable, yet relatively untapped
source, and where there is a need
for them to supplement manpower.
In 1964, the First International
Conference of Women Engineers and
Scientists was held in New York and
brought together over 500 women
engineers and scientists from 35 coun¬
tries and all 50 states of the U.S.A.,
who shared experiences, plans and
aspirations with each other. They now
look forward to the second such Inter¬
national conference, to be held in Eng¬
land in July 1967, one of whose
themes will be "Enough for Everyone
the application of technology to world
food problems." (The conference
secretary is Mrs I.H. Hardwich, AEI
Power Group Research Laboratory,
Trafford Park, Manchester 17, England.)
I have been a Unesco Courier
subscriber for many years and have
contributed toward a better under¬
standing of the U.N. and especially
of Unesco's immense programmes
throughout the world by putting on a
local radio information programme
and city-wide displays to familiarize
the people of my community. I also
initiated in Connecticut the adoption
of a Unesco Gift Coupon Project for
Ecuador. Now I would like to see
publicity being given to the fact that
there is an urgent need and a place
for women, properly qualified and
interested, in science and technology
all over the world.
Vera H. Zepler
Chairman, Connecticut Section,
Society of Women Engineers, U.S.A.
YOUTH OF GABON
GREET UNESCO
Sir,
Members of the Central Club of
Gabonese School Activities for Unesco
(Lycée Léon Mba, Libreville) and the
young people of Gabon as a whole
were deeply stirred by the New Year
message to youth from the Director-
General of Unesco published in your
February issue. As general-secretary
of the Unesco club, I wish to thank
the Director-General and to ask him
to accept the good wiàhes of the
youth of Gabon for 1966. If there is
anyone to whom the world's young
people should send their greetings,
that person is certainly the Director-
General of Unesco, who is helping
them and working for them through
the organization he directs.
Joseph Boussamba-Koucka
Libreville, Gabon
VOLUNTEERS OF VALUE
Sir.
Your issue on Youth (July-August
1965) contained an enthusiastic article
on the work of young volunteers. It
might influence people who hold
opposite views and sometimes discuss
the Idea of stopping all recruitment of
young volunteers workers If they heard
the story of the two volunteers I know
most about.
Tony Sleight and Steve Cuthbert,
came from the United Nations Associ¬
ation of Great Britain and Northern
Ireland in 1964-65, to help me at the
Ramallah Men Teacher Training Centre,
an institution for Palestine refugees
set up in Jordan by the United Nations
Relief and Works Agency (UNRWA).
From the start they showed ability
and willingness to do any job. Tony
Sleight, a graduate in chemistry, had
a real talent for experimental work,
and took charge of the chemistry
laboratory. Steve Cuthbert, a physics
graduate, took over the physics labo¬
ratory. They worked hard to keep
their laboratories in running order,
repaired instruments and built teaching
devices.
In the first semester we were short
of one science instructor, so our
volunteers became teachers and des¬
pite the language barrier were able
to give students valuable guidance in
experimental work. In the second
semester we were able to make greater
use of portable science kits with which
teachers in schools without labor¬
atories can demonstrate some 500
experiments in physics, chemistry and
biology. This inspired our volunteers
to produce a 50-page English-Arabic
science dictionary and a 25-page
glossary. To finish this before leaving
Jordan they often worked long after
school hours. They also helped to
plan a summer in-service training
course and took part in it too.
It is easy to criticize and to quote
cases where volunteers have created
nothing. However, providing they are
the right kind of young people and if
they have a chance to work creatively
and are made to see that we need
their help, we have in them a power¬
ful force to reinforce the efforts of
the developing countries.
Karl Slemming
Ramallah, Jordan
Mr Slemming Is a mathematics and
science specialist loaned to UNRWA
by the Danish Refugee Council
Editor.
BUILDING PEACE
Sir.
I consider the Unesco Courier to
be one of the most significant publica¬
tions of our times, and I loan my copy
and quote from it amongst my friends
and business associates, and at my
Rotary and sports clubs.
Many people despair of the United
Nations, but they see only the distrust
and bickering of the political section.
If despite Its undoubted weaknesses
In this area, the United Nations can
keep us out of major war which would
inevitably escalate Into total destruc¬
tion of our civilization, there is some
reason to hope that the other bran¬
chesWHO, UNICEF, Unesco, etc.
will set In motion an avalanche of
enlightenment which will overwhelm
those whose fingers itch on the trigger.
Leslie J.V. Henry
North Rockhampton
Australia
u
z
2
a.
ci
<
z
<
OL
o
UJ
O
ä
E
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
GLOBAL VIEW OF
WORLD COMMUNICATIONS
First published in 1950, World Communications has won recognition as an
authoritative reference work for communication studies, for use in schools
of journalism and as a handbook for mass media enterprises.
The latest (4th) edition is a completely revised version and discusses recent
developments in mass media : the use of space satellites to relay word and
image between continents ; television as entertainment and as a tool for
teaching ; the development of transistors and the growing use of radio fac¬
simile and teletypesetting for the simultaneous publication of newspapers in
different continents.
Two offprints from World Communications
newspapers
and
news agencies
world radio
and
television
%
380 pp
unesco
40/-; % 8.00; 28 F
unesco unesco
159 pp 15/-; $3.00; 10.50 F 159 pp 17/6; $3.50; 12.50 F
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Department. Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria): United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
"Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
Wetenschappelijke Uitgeverij Belgièlei 1 47, Antwerp.
For The Unesco Courier (1 40 FBJand art slides only : Louis
De Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir Chittampalan
Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B, 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 1 3/50).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1,Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CYPRUS.
"MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent display); Lahranicni
literacura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, Ltd., Prags Boulevard 47, Copenhagen S, (D.
Kr. 17). ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O.
Box 120, Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40).
FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy,
Paris-7\ CCP. 12598-48. (10 F.). - GERMANY. All
publications: R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse
145, Munich. 8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only)
Bahrentelder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P.
276650 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd. Atlantis House Commercial St., POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akademiai
Konybrbnolt Vici U. 22" Budapest V. Allami Könyv¬
terseszto Vallalat, P.O. Box 240 Budapest ICELAND.
Snaebjörn lonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(1 20 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd.. Nicol
Road, Ballard Estate, Bombay 1:17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson
House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16; Scindia
House, New Delhi. Indian National Commission for Co¬
operation with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs.7). IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Al-
Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND.The National Press,
2,Wellington Road.Ballsbndge,Dublin.4.(1 5/5). - ISRAEL
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstem's Bookstores, 35 All-
enby Road and 48 Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-). Maruzen Co. Ltd.. 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph 1. Bahous& Co., Dar ul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66. Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop. P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (10/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd.. P.O. Box 286, Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 140). -MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd. .Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore, 9 ; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur ( M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta.
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (1 5/-). MONACO. British
Library, 30, Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V., Willemstad. Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4.50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag), Wellington ; Government Book¬
shops: Auckland (P.O. Box 53 44), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104) (15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-). -
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For Unesco Courier only: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litteraturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6, (17.50kr.).
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd.,
Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374 G.P.O. Lahore;
Showrooms : Urdu Bazar, Lahore, and 57-58 Murree
Highway, G /6-I, Islamabad. PHILIPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda. Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. SOUTHERN RHODESIA.
The Book Centre, and Educational Supply Co., Colonial Mu¬
tual Building, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
. P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publi¬
cations : A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescorädet. Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse, Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1 211, Geneva 11, C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.
Suksapan Panit Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box1 45, Kampala (1 0/-). SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications *. Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty) Ltd.,
Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only : Central
News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.-50).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent :
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office. P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
ii London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 3 4th St, New York,
N.Y. 1 001 6 ($ 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga Terazije, 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
^
	 1
1
I
1
ft.
ALOuETTt II y"
áil / 1
[
STAMPS HONOUR
FEATS IN SPACE
All over the world stamps are being issued to mark
landmarks along the road into space. Depicting
space capsules, orbital flights, communications
satellites and moon probes, stamps serve to remind
millions of people of the dramatic progress made
in space exploration. Here we present stamps
which honour accomplishments in space research.
noHT/, CCCP
non CCCP noHTfl cccp Iv>k non cccp
U. S. S. R.
(^pVAUME DU
BURUNDI
B ' m
|*$ /J
B //mW V
1 A^W > '
BURUNDI
1	 	1
B (*f: \ ..,
B Ä 5°
B iBiW'ILi
sssssB
AUSTRALIA
]]>
</page>
</document>
