<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="032667eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
June 1966
(19th year)
U.K.: 1/6 stg.
Canada : 30 cents
France: 1 F
A window open on the world
ner
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
^JP^ ^y^ g Jk ^
OLD o -^^^rjT\\I?J^^^^^¿^^¿^S^^^;
^TIV/fosvVá
J¡
jtfwiffi<hr«wff.»rr. r. r v ßj.VNVS 'ClewCV5 : <zT-JLhj
TTTTnTIV -mwA »
ra| ¿7W**
Negotiations between William the Conqueror and Harold of England
Cooks prepare a meal for William and his barons
The Bayeux Tapestry
TREASURES
WORLD ART
With its hundreds of human figures, scenes from husbandry and the chase and its
minute detailing of military techniques, the Bayeux Tapestry is a unique illustrated
guide to life in war and peace during the eleventh century. The work is actually an
embroidery on which needlewomen of that century used woollen threads of
8 colours to depict the Norman conquest of England. With its 72 panels spread
across a linen band measuring 70 metres by 50 centimetres (230 ft. by 20 ins), it
could be called an ancestor of the cartoon strip. Above, scenes from the epic of 1066.
© City of Bayeux Museum, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
JUNE 1966 - 19TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Parls-7°.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg. ; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2 years : 27/-stg. ; 1 8 F. Single copies 1 /6-stg. ;
30 cents; 1 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied to editors on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is Indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Russian Edition : Victor Gollachkov (Paris)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
dition
Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Illustrations : Betsy Bates
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence shouldbe addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
Page
4
11
15
16
22
30
32
33
34
IBN KHALDUNMAN OF HISTORY
A 14th-century forerunner of the modern historian
By Barbara Bray
CRACKS IN A CONTINENT
Exploring the anatomy of Africa's rift valleys
By Brian H. Baker
IS ARABIA ADRIFT?
MASTERPIECES FROM A LOST KINGDOM
Rare finds in a royal necropolis
By Ezat 0. Negahban
WHY 1101 - 13
New approaches to mathematics teaching
By Nicole Picard
INTERNATIONAL TROPHIES FOR FAIR PLAY
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
'ONE DAY'S EXPENDITURE ON ARMS'
A lead from Iran in the struggle against illiteracy
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Cover photo
This humped bull with gold
earrings in its pierced ears is
actually a vase whose spout is
formed by the animal's muzzle.
A red1 pottery figurine, 3,000 years
old, it was found in northern Iran
when archaeologists uncovered
the royal cemetery of Marlik, a
long-forgotten kingdom. Marlik's
tombs yielded a remarkable col¬
lection of funerary objects, includ¬
ing ritual vessels and figurines,
ornaments and jewellery, and
pottery of all kinds (see page 16).
Institute of Archaeology, University of Teheran
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Al-Azhar University,
where the historian,
Ibn Khaldun, taught after
moving to Cairo in 1383.
He spent his last years
in this city
which he described as
the "metropolis of the world
enlightened by luminaries
of learning".
He died there in 1406
at the age of 74.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
éiÀ IBN KHALDUN
OF HISTORY
A universal history of the world written six centuries ago by
Ibn Khaldun establishes this great Arab scholar as the first
person to treat history as the proper object of a special
science. The story of this forerunner of the modern historian,
presented below, includes a recently-discovered account in
Ibn Khaldun s own words of his memorable meeting with
Tamerlane the Conqueror.
! . >\
by Barbara Bray
~J%
i ¿a
w;
i«:
"".i
.^
H E opened his eyes on a life
of culture and elegance,
where fountains played in sunny court¬
yards, where books and music and
quiet meditation divided the time with
exciting and often dangerous affairs
of state.
His family, which originated in the
Hadramaut in Southern Arabia, had
emigrated from there to Spain In the
eighth century, during the early years
of the Moslem conquest. By the elev¬
enth century they had become the
intellectual and political leaders of the
city of Seville. But before the middle
of the thirteenth century and in time to
escape the Christian reconquest of the
town, these proud patricians crossed
over into Northwest Africa, where
influential friends and relations soon
helped them to establish new positions
of wealth and honour.
In order to understand the world
into which Ibn Khaldun was born, and
which he spent his life studying and
BARBARA BRAY is a journalist, translator
and literary and dramatic critic, and was
formerly a lecturer in English at the Uni¬
versity of Alexandria. This article is adapt¬
ed from a radio programme she wrote for
Unesco to commemorate the birth of Ibn
Khaldun.
analysing, we need to take a gênerai
look at a period of history too often
neglected, and remind ourselves of
what Arab civilization as a whole, as
well as Ibn Khaldun in particular, con¬
tributed to the sum of human know¬
ledge.
After the founding of Islam by the
Prophet Mohammed around 630, the
new civilization rapidly spread out¬
wards from Arabia its centre until by
the middle of the tenth century, when
it was at its zenith, it included by far
the greater part of the inhabited world.
To the west it took in Egypt and the
entire North African coast, the islands
of Sicily and Crete, and nearly all of
Spain. To the north, Syria, Armenia
and the south-east regions of the Cau¬
casus were under Islamic rule; then,
further east, Mesopotamia, Iraq, Per¬
sia and Afghanistan, Transoxania and
parts of India's northern plains.
Both the cultural and geograph¬
ical horizons of Europe were boun¬
ded in nearly all directions by Islam,
which enjoyed the summit of its pros¬
perity at the time when the civilization
of the West slumbered in its deepest
darkness.
By the twelfth century the decline
of the medieval Islam had set in, and
in Ibn Khaldun's lifetime it presented
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
IBN KHALDUN (Continued)
Unable to keep out of hot water
a spectacle which while still splendid
was fatally touched by disintegration.
But in the years of its greatness it not
only kept alight and handed on the
torch of knowledge kindled by Greece,
but also made valuable contributions
of its own to human understanding and
power.
Navigation, commerce, architecture,
together with nearly all the arts and
crafts were cultivated, and their fruits
and techniques handed on to the West.
In science and philosophy, Arab
thinkers first preserved what the
Greeks had won, then in certain
important, though mostly practical
ways, developed and perfected it,
thus acting as a necessary connect¬
ing link between ancient and modern.
European interest in the works of
Aristotle, for instance, was first
awakened through acquaintance with
Arabic thought.
The Arabs produced eminent schol¬
ars and practitioners in medicine, as¬
tronomy, physics and the natural
sciences. They were the inventors
of algebra and trigonometry, and they
contributed much to the development
of arithmetical calculation.
The literary and purely intellectual
influences of Islam are harder to trace
than the scientific ones, and here as
in every field of Arabic studies much
necessary material is lost or still
unexplored.
By the twelfth century the works of
Arab scholars had begun to be trans¬
lated and accepted as authorities in
the West in Europe; and in the
thirteenth century the Arab world and
the West were intellectually much
more closely aligned than they have
ever been since.
In the sixteenth century the revolu¬
tion brought about by Copernicus in
astronomy, the reform of alchemy and
medicine by Paracelsus, and the new
anatomy of Vesalius struck great
blows at traditional Arab erudition.
Then when the Moors were defeated
and the Moslem empire in Europe came
to an end, all the eastern learning that
had not already been assimilated was
lost.
But much had been assimilated, and
Arabic no less than Hellenic lore con¬
tinued to be respected right down
until both were crushed by the advent
of modern scientific method.
Of this method Ibn Khaldun, the
first man to treat history as the proper
.*»*
6
From "The Muqaddimah" by Ibn Khaldun
© Bollingen Series XLIII, Pantheon Books, New York, 1958
MEDIEVAL WORLD MAP. The "Muqaddimah" or "Prolegomena", which Ibn
Khaldun wrote as an introduction to his monumental history of the world,
outlines and discusses contemporary ideas on geography that were based on
a still scanty knowledge of the globe. Ibn Khaldun illustrated his geographical
descriptions in the "Prolegomena" with this map of the world on which the
south is at the top and the north at the bottom. "By turning it upside down
one can pick out the outlines of Africa, the Mediterranean Sea, the Indian
Ocean and the land masses of Europe and Asia in the northern hemisphere.
object of a special science, was an
amazingly early forerunner. How did
he come to be so much ahead of his
time?
For an answer to this question we
have to look at the circumstances of
his life.
When he was seventeen Khaldun
lost both his parents and many of his
teachers in the Black Death. Three
years later he was given an important
appointment at the court of the Hafsid
rulers of Tunis, but he preferred to
leave this and travel gradually west¬
ward across North Africa, pursuing his
studies, and passing the years from
1354 to 1363 at the Merinid court in
Fez. The development of a Moslem
scholar was regarded as a lifelong pro¬
cess, and the list Khaldun scrupu¬
lously gives of the men at whose feet
he sat is a formidable one. But in
giving the list he was also presenting
his academic credentials, and these
show that his interests were wide,
not to say encyclopedic, rather than
specialized. This is an important factor
in relation to his life-work.
North Africa was at this time divid¬
ed into three warring kingdoms, each
of whose ruling dynasties was torn by
internal dissension. It was here, taking
an active part in politics, that Khaldun
got most of his material for his theories
about the rise and fall of nations. In
such an atmosphere it was hard for
someone like him to keep out of hot
water. At one period he found himself
on the wrong side and spent nearly
two years in prison, and later he
found it prudent to cross over into
Spain, to Granada. But in 1365 he
was back in North Africa, in Bougie,
as Prime Minister.
The nine years from 1365 onwards
were the most precarious in all Khal-
dun's hazardous career. It was no
easy matter to be always on the right
side in the complicated and fluid chaos
that North Africa had become. Khal-
dun's services as judge, civil servant
and politician were always in demand,
and all his attempts to escape to
scholarly peace and quiet were foiled
by suspicious rivals and demanding
princes. Finally, however, he managed
to get permission from the ruler of
Tunis to install himself and his family
in a secluded pavilion at Ibn Salamah
in the province of Oran. Here he spent
over three years in comfort and soli¬
tude, and started to write his great
history of the world.
"I completed the Introduction in the
remarkable manner to which I was
inspired by that retreat, with words
and ideas pouring into my head like
cream into a churn," he recorded.
It took him three more years, and
the opportunity to consult the libraries
in Tunis, before he completed his
enormous work, and even after that he
was always correcting it and bringing
it up to date.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
© Paul Almasy, Paris
In Fez, Ibn Khaldun completed his education in association with the circle of scholars »
which Sultan Abu Inan had gathered around him for study and teaching. /
Here too he met many other scholars, physicians, astrologers and artists
passing through the court of the sultan who was a great friend of scholarship.
Above, the 14th-century Bab Sagma gate in Fez, Morocco.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
IBN KHALDUN (Continued)
Historian and conqueror face to face
8
The first volume consists of the
Muqaddimah or Prolegomena, which is
probably Khaldun's greatest claim to
lasting fame, containing as it does the
first real theory of history. Volumes II
to VII deal with the events of the pre-
Islamic world and Arab and Eastern
Moslem history.' But Volumes VIII and
IX deal with the history of the Moslem
West. Much of the material is based
on first-hand knowledge, and it remains
our most important source for North¬
west African and Berber history.
In November or December 1378,
Khaldun returned to his old home in
Tunis where he taught, did research,
and of course made both friends and
enemies at court. In 1382 he thought
it best to ask the ruler's permission to
make the pilgrimage to Mecca, and
sailed for Alexandria on October 24,
leaving his family behind, perhaps as
hostages. From this time on his only
contacts with the West were by cor¬
respondence and through meetings
with travellers. He reached Alexandria
after more than forty days at sea, and
after a' few weeks moved south to
Cairo where, apart from occasional
travels in the Moslem world to the
east, he spent the rest of his life.
Egypt, ruled by the Mamelukes, was
at this time the most stable and
prosperous part of Islam. Khaldun
was overwhelmed by the beauty of
Cairo, with its colleges, mosques,
crowded streets, and gardens that
seemed to him like something out of
paradise.
He was soon "giving lectures at
al-Azhar University and as soon as
the post fell vacant the ruler Barqûq
appointed him professor of Mâlikite
jurisprudence in the Oamhîyah College.
Soon after he was also made chief
Mâlikite judge of Egypt. (The Mâlikite
rite was one of the four schools of
Islamic law.) So there he was once
again in positions of both prestige and
power.
In the year 1387 Khaldun went at
last on his pilgrimage to Mecca, return¬
ing to new academic appointments and
honours. In 1399 Barqûq died and was
succeeded by his ten-year-old son.
In 1400 Khaldun, as one of the four
chief judges of Egypt, officially accom¬
panied the young prince Faraj to
Damascus, making a detour on the way
back to visit Jerusalem and Bethlehem
and other holy cities, Moslem and
Christian, as a pilgrim. Christ is of
course regarded as a prophet by
Moslems.
By the autumn of the same year
Timur or, as we now call him, Tamer¬
lane, "Timur the lame" was threaten¬
ing Syria with his cruel and all-
conquering hordes of Tartars. Khaldun
was obliged, much against his will, to
bestir himself yet again and accom¬
pany Faraj as judge and counsellor on
an expedition to relieve Damascus. A
contemporary described this ineffec
tive force as "an army without a gen¬
eral and a general without an army."
There were various inconclusive
engagements between the two forces
in the country outside Damascus, but
in the first week of the year 1401 came
news of a threatened revolt back in
Egypt, and Faraj returned home, leav¬
ing at Damascus Ibn Khaldun and
others of his retinue to fend for them¬
selves and save the city if they could.
These temporary residents of the
city, together with the civilian authori¬
ties, decided to surrender, against the
wishes of the military. Tamerlane
knew of Khaldun's presence and
expressed the desire to see him, so
he was secretly lowered by ropes from
the walls of the city and brought into
the presence of the conqueror.
Until a few years ago the only autho¬
rities for this fabulous encounter were
various Arab historians of the fifteenth
century, who all obviously embroidered
such facts as were available to them.
In all hitherto known manuscripts Khal¬
dun's own autobiography stopped in
the year 1395. But less than twenty
years ago three new manuscripts (the
second and third are simply copies of
the first), were found in Istanbul and
Cairo. (The most important was anno¬
tated in Khaldun's own hand.) And
they brought his story up to within a
few months of his death.
So now at last, after five and a half
centuries of speculation, we have a
detailed and verbatim account of one
of history's most colourful meetings.
T the time of their conver¬
sations, which were spread
out over January and February of 1401,
Khaldun was nearly seventy and
Tamerlane about five years younger.
Khaldun was described by those
who knew him as good-looking and
attractive in manner, and this was
confirmed by the speed with which he
was always admitted to favour wher¬
ever he went. Tamerlane, according
to an Arab chronicler, was "tall in stat¬
ure, with a large brow and a great
head, and very strong. His complexion
was white mixed with red; he was
broad-shouldered, had thick fingers, a
flowing beard, was paralysed in one
hand and lame in his right leg. He
had brilliant eyes, a loud voice, and
was fearless of death. He reached
the age of eighty in full enjoyment of
his senses and strength."
They were a well-matched pair who
lost no time in sizing one another
up. Although Khaldun as a historian]
was certainly intrigued to meet so
outstanding a maker of history, his
chief concern was to extricate himself
and his colleagues from Tamerlane's
clutches and get safely back to Egypt.
Tamerlane, on the other hand, knew
that Khaldun was the greatest living
expert on the Maghreb (this is to say,
the Western Islam from Tripoli to Gran¬
ada), and was anxious for military
reasons to attach him to his intelli¬
gence services.
Let Khaldun now take up the story
in his own words, from the moment
of his first arrival in Tamerlane's
reception tent:
When my name was announced he
summoned me and as I entered the
audience tent he was reclining on his
elbow while platters of food were
passing before him, which he sent out
one after the other to groups of Mon¬
gols sitting in circles in front of his
tent. Upon entering I spoke first:
Peace be with you and I made a
gesture of humility. Thereupon he
raised his head and stretched out his
hand to me, which I kissed. He made
a sign to me to sit down. I did so just
where I was, and he summoned from
his retinue one of the erudite Harrafito
jurists whom he bade sit there also
to serve as interpreter between us.
Tamerlane got straight to the point
by asking Khaldun questions about the
Maghreb, which Khaldun skillfully
evaded. They fenced for some time,
then Tamerlane got tired of beating
about the bush.
/ am not satisfied, he declared.
/ should like you to write down for me
a description of the whole country of
the Maghreb, treating all its features
in such a way as I might seem actually
to see it.
Bowls of rishta a sort of macaroni
in soup were then brought in. Khal¬
dun took some and did it justice, and
this seemed to go down very well
with his host.
But soon they both fell silent. Khal¬
dun couldn't help thinking of what his
fate would be if he made a wrong
move.
At this moment news came that the
city gates had been opened and the
civil authorities were coming out to
surrender.
Tamerlane appeared to be having
trouble with the lame knee which had
been wounded by an arrow in his
youth, and so was carried out, with
bands playing "until the air shook with
them," and rode off towards Damascus.
Khaldun duly set about writing his
account of the Maghreb. He was left
unmolested, although around him the
city was being sacked and burned.
The paper written and handed over,
Tamerlane treated Khaldun with
various marks of respect, asking him
to give his opinion on legal matters,
for example. But they still had not
got round to the vital question of
whether the scholar was to be allowed
to return home to his studies.
Khaldun decided he had better take
the bull by the horns but as tactfully
as possible.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
^^ífe5¡
Vati
?&"J?'m "
V
AN AUDIENCE WITH TAMERLANE
Tamerlane granting audience to subject princes
on the occasion of his accession
(15th century Persian miniature).
Founder of the second Mongol empire, Tamerlane
conquered all of the Middle East
and Eastern Europe, but was also known
as a patron of art, literature and science.
He was born four years after Ibn Khaldun,
in 1336, and died one year before
the great Arab historian, in 1405.
From "Bihzad and his Paintings in the Zafar-Namah"
by Sir Thomas W. Arnold, © Bernard Quaritch Ltd., London
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
IBN KHALDUN (Continued)
Author of the first real theory of history
10
/ chose from the book market an
exceedingly beautiful copy of the
Koran, a beautiful prayer rug, a copy
of the famous poem, al-Burda, by
al-Busiri in praise of the Prophet may
Allah bless him and grant him peace
and four boxes of the excellent Cairo
sweetmeats. I took these gifts and
entered to him in the palace of Qasr
al-Ablaq.
Khaldun pondered how to begin.
May Allah aid you / have some¬
thing which I wish to say before you,
he said.
Speak! replied Tamerlane.
/ am a stranger in this country in
a double sense. First because I am
away from the Maghreb. My other
absence is from Cairo. I have come
under your protection, and I hope that
you will give me your opinion regarding
what may solace me in my exile.
Speak. Whatever you desire I
shall do for you.
What do I desire? My state of
exile has made me forget what I
desire. Perhaps you may Allah aid
you will know for me what I desire.
Move from the city of the camp
and stay with me, and if Allah wills I
will fulfil your highest aim.
For the moment Khaldun had to be
content with this ambiguous sug¬
gestion. However, on the strength of it
he did succeed in getting a safe-
conduct for the Egyptian officials who
had been left behind in Damascus.
But left alone Tamerlane seems
to have reconciled himself to the idea
of letting Khaldun go, and the next
time they met he let this become
apparent, somewhat wistfully, though
characteristically he cut his losses in
a very novel way. He asked Khaldun:
You have a mule here?
A mule? Yes.
Is it a good one?
Yes.
Will you sell it?
Sell it?
/ would buy it from you.
May Allah aid you one like me
does not sell to one like you. But I
would offer it to you in homage.
/ meant only that I would requite
you for your generosity.
Is there any generosity left
beyond what you have already shown
me?
He was silent, writes Khaldun; so
was I. The mule was brought to him,
and I did not see it again.
Are you going to travel to Cairo?
asked Tamerlane.
Khaldun answered, delighted and
surprised, but still nervous.
May Allah aid you indeed my
desire is only to serve you ... If the
journey would be in your service,
surely. Otherwise I have no desire
for it.
No, but you will return to your
family and your people.
Khaldun rounds off the story by tel¬
ling how he finally arrived back in
Egypt. Soon after his return a messen¬
ger came with some money for the
mule not the full price, but the
messenger swore that was all he
was given. Khaldun warily asked the
ruler of Egypt whether it was all right
for him to take the money, and receiv¬
ing an affirmative answer, pocketed it
with a sigh of relief at having got off
so lightly.
He lost no time in writing off to
the Maghreb to tell about the infor¬
mation he had been forced to give, and
to try to counteract any ill-effects this
might have by giving his fellow-
countrymen all the useful facts he
could muster about Tamerlane. In
fact Tamerlane never did attack North
Africa. The rest of Khaldun's life was
spent in study, writing and official
duties. He died on March 17, 1406,
and was buried in the Sufi cemetery
outside the Nasr gate of Cairo. The
site of his tomb is now unknown.
In the centuries that followed, the
influence of Khaldun's teaching grad¬
ually gathered momentum, though his
name is not found mentioned outside
the Islamic world until 1636. Until the
beginning of the nineteenth century it
was the Ottoman Turks who showed
the most constructive interest. Then
European scholars began to discover
in his work ideas hitherto considered
to have been formulated more recently
in the West.
As far as we know Khaldun was
the first historian ever to regard history
not as a chronicle of more or less for¬
tuitous events, but as a continuous,
collective and organic movement
governed by hidden but discernible
laws. Moreover he identified the
science of history with the science of
civilization as a whole, and realized
that only a study of man in all his
innumerable activities can reveal the
true significance of so-called historical
events, so that the study of those
events may act as a practical guide
to the statesman.
So Khaldun, considering everything
as a function of man and his social
organization, takes all knowledge as
his province, and re-evaluates every
aspect of the highly developed civili¬
zation in which he lived.
The element of intellectual orthodoxy
from which he could hardly be expect¬
ed to escape only serves to emphasize
the real originality and breadth of his
mind. Picturesque and touching as it
is, then, it is no wonder that Professor
Arnold Toynbee, one of the most cele¬
brated historians of our own day, cites
this fourteenth-century Arab as the
inspiration of his own monumental
work, and salutes Ibn Khaldun as the
founder of the science of history.
Paul Almasy, Paris
In 1362 Ibn Khaldun left Fez and went to the court of the King of Castille
as ambassador of the Sultan of Granada. On his return
the sultan rewarded him with lands and a palace in Granada.
Above, the 14th-century Myrtle Court of the Alhambra, Granada, one of
the palaces where the landscape garden art of the Arabs flowered
in sheltered patios filled with flowers, shade, pools and fountains.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Rugged landscape of Adi Arkai (north-west Ethiopia) strikingly illustrates
the effects of subsidences in the earth's crust that have made the great rift valleys
which cleave East Africa from Zambia to the Red Sea.
Paul Almasy, Paris
CRACKS IN A CONTINENT
Probing mysteries of the earth's crust
in the rift valleys of Africa
by Brian H. Baker
HE rift valleys which trav¬
erse a large part of east¬
ern Africa, and the high plateaux and
volcanic mountains which are associat¬
ed with the valleys, are some of the
most beautiful and interesting parts of
the continent.
The floor of the rift valley is often
occupied by lakes, and the higher
parts of the surrounding plateau are
the sites of intensive agriculture, while
the high volcanic mountains are cover¬
ed with forests. It is the rift valleys
BRIAN H. BAKER is director of the Geo¬
logical Department of Kenya's Ministry of
Natural Resources and Wildlife, in Nairobi,
and chairman of the Sub-Commission on
African Rifts of the Upper Mantle Project of
the International Union of Geodesy and
Geophysics. He has written many studies
on the geology of East Africa.
and the associated uplifted plateaux
and high volcanoes that provide much
of the scenic variety in East Africa,
and incidentally provide the basis for
much of the agriculture, forestry and
other industries.
The system of African rift valleys
extends from Zambia through eastern
Africa to the Red Sea, and continues
northwards as far as Syria. This zone
of fractures in the earth's crust is ap¬
proximately 8,000 kilometres (5,000
miles) long, and represents one of
the world's major structural features.
The rift valleys in Africa are now
known to be connected in some way
at the south end of the Red Sea with
the even more extensive mid-ocean
ridges which encircle the globe. The
recognition that the African rift sys¬
tem is the extension of the mid-ocean¬
ic ridge of the Indian Ocean, via
the Gulf of Aden, means that the sys
tem is part of the world rift system
(see the Unesco. Courier, October
1963).
, Although the rift valleys of the Afric¬
an continent are likely to differ in
some respects from the equivalent
structures which are so much more ex¬
tensive on the ocean floors, they are
readily accessible for study, and pro¬
vide excellent opportunities for re¬
search into several fundamental proces¬
ses in the earth's crust, including vol¬
canic action and vertical tectonic
movements.
Now that the African rift system is
seen to be part of a global structure
the most important structural feature
of the earth's crust, in fact its study
has taken on a new significance. For
example, if the continents have been
drifting slowly apart during geological
time, as some scientists believe, and
if the mid-oceanic ridges are the zones
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
CRACKS IN A CONTINENT (Continued)
Titanic forces
at work 400
miles beneath us
along which the rupture of the original
super-continent took place, then the
African rift system may be the early
expression of the break-up of this
continent.
It is possible therefore that there is
the opportunity in eastern Africa to
study the early stages of continental
fragmentation. In future geological
ages parts of eastern Africa may be¬
come detached islands, like Madagas¬
car is at the present day. It should
be emphasized, however, that this is
likely to be a very slow process, which
would take many millions of years to
operate.
Apart from the desirability of under¬
standing more fully the surface struc¬
ture of the African rift system and its
connexion with the oceanic structures,
there is also the question of causes.
The major structural effects of the
earth's crust the long mountain ran¬
ges, the deep troughs filled with sedi¬
ments, the zones of fracturing and ver¬
tical movement are caused by forces
generated in the plastic sub-stratum
called the upper mantle of the earth,
which occurs to a depth of about 700
kilometres (430 miles) beneath the
thin, relatively rigid crust.
It is possible to obtain a surprising
amount of information concerning the
nature of the upper mantle by indirect
geophysical methods, and study of the
differences between the upper mantle
in the zone of African rifts and else¬
where would provide information to
help to understand the development
of the crust of earth and the role of
the upper mantle in its evolution.
The African rift valleys consist of
a variety of structures, most of which
are well preserved on the surface of
the earth, since they were formed in
comparatively recent geological peri¬
ods, mostly, within the last 20 million
years. Typically the valleys are
troughlike subsidences of the earth's
crust about 50 kilometres (30 miles)
wide, varying from about a hundred
metres to 1,500 metres (a few hundred
to 5,000 ft.) in depth. In the northern
part of the rift system the valleys tra¬
verse broad volcanic highland areas
such as the Kenya and Ethiopia high¬
lands, which rise to levels of over
3,000 metres (10,000 feet).
The sides of the valley are steep
rocky escarpments, sometimes a
single high escarpment, or a series of
step-like escarpments descending to
the valley floor. The floor of the valley
may be cut up into a large number of
narrow blocks, with many small escarp¬
ments, as if the floor of the valley had
CONTINUED ON PAGE 14
Ste* -*l
© Haroun Tazieff
The expedition which explored Niragongo set
up its camp on the higher of two terraces
which overlook the central well of the crater.
This terrace is surmounted by á vertical wall
180 metres (600 ft.) high (above). Two hundred
metres (650 ft.) below this terrace a narrow
platform encircles the vast molten lava lake
(right). This great expanse of molten rock,
sometimes calm and sometimes whipped into
whirlpools and fountains of lava, awed even
the most experienced members of the party.
DESCENT
FIERY PIT
The only lake of permanently molten
lava in the world is the deep Nira¬
gongo crater, a volcano situated to
the north of Lake Kivu (Democratic
Republic of the Congo). In this area
alone there are eight active vol¬
canoes. Their presence and the exis¬
tence of a zone of earthquake activ¬
ity show that further movement and
volcanic activity can be expected
along the great African rift valleys.
The 1,100-metre (3,600 ft.) wide Nira¬
gongo crater is difficult of access,
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
INTO THE
and involves climbing a mountain
almost 3,600-metres (12,000 feet)
high. The molten lava lake, covering
13,000 square metres (140,000 sq.
ft.), is situated in a deep well over¬
hung by a vast ring-shaped terrace
(see the Unesco Courier, Oct., 1963).
The crater was first explored in 1958
by an expedition of Belgian, French
and Japanese geophysicists and vol-
canologists. Right, Haroun Tazieff,
leader of the expedition, descends
into the crater on the end of a cable.
Photos © Haroun Tazieff
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
CRACKS IN A CONTINENT (Continued)
Geyser power and minerals in plenty
broken into narrow strips along vertical
fractures. In some places the valley
is occupied by large volcanoes, lakes,
or spreads of lake sediment. In the
Red Sea sector the valley is under¬
water.
The highlands adjacent to the rift
valleys are commonly broad plateaux
areas composed of lava, but high
ranges like the Ruwenzori mountains
of Western Uganda, and the Cheran-
gani range of Kenya are blocks of
ancient rocks which have been pushed
up to heights in excess of 4,300 metres
and 3,400 metres (14,000 and 11,000
feet) respectively during the formation
of the rift valley. Other high mountains,
which occur mainly on the flanks of
the valley, are the great volcanoes
such as Kilimanjaro (5,900 metres;
19,300 ft.), Mt. Kenya (5,200 metres;
17,050 ft.), and Mt. Elgon (4,300 metres;
14,100 ft.), and the Aberdare Range
(4,000 metres; 13,100 ft.).
It can be deduced that the original
land surface has been lowered to
below sea-level in the lower parts of
the rift valleys, and the total relative
displacement reaches to between
3,000-4,500 metres (10.000-15,000 feet)
in some areas.
Broadly, the movements of the
earth's crust during the formation of
the rift valleys were a general bulging
or up-lifting of wide areas, with the
rift valley traversing the up-lifted areas
as a strip of country which appears to
have collapsed (or been dragged
downwards) in relation to the general
rise of the area. While the movements
were in progress massive volcanic
action took place in several areas, and
continued almost to the present day.
The existence of a zone of earth¬
quake activity along the rift valleys
shows that the rifts are still active,
and the widespread occurrence of very
young volcanoes indicate that further
movement and volcanic activity can be
expected at any time.
In recognition of the importance of
studying the African rift system in
greater detail, a number of scientists
met last year in Nairobi, Kenya, under
the auspices of the International Upper
Mantle Project and Unesco (1), to
consider how to co-operate in further
research. Scientists from several Afri¬
can countries agreed to take part in a
programme aimed at producing an up-
to-date account of the geology and
geophysics of the rift system, and also
to stimulate new research.
Subsequently the Upper Mantle
Committee of the International Union
of Geodesy and Geophysics establish-
(1) The 34 scientists who took part came
from Ethiopia, Kenya, Malawi, Uganda,
Sudan, Tanzania, Zambia, U.S.A., lapan,
U.S.S.R., Belgium, and U.K.
ed a Commission on the World Rift
System, and the group concerned
with the African rifts became one of
its subcommissions. The first steps
towards a programme of co-operation
in geology and geophysics for the
study of this most interesting feature of
the African continent have been taken.
Already some research is in progress,
and other projects are being planned.
The existing knowledge of the Afri¬
can rift valleys shows that study of
this structure is of more than purely
academic interest. Associated with the
rift system are a number of bodies of
igneous rock derived from great depths
which contain valuable metals such as
columbium and the rare earths, which
are of increasing importance in modern
technology.
As a result of the internal drainage
of the rift valleys and of their volcanic
activity there are great saline accumu¬
lations such as the sodium carbonate
and sodium chloride (salt) deposits of
lakes Magadi and Natron, on the
borders of Tanzania and Kenya, and
the potash deposits of the Afar
depression in Ethiopia. These deposits
are among the largest in the world
of these substances.
As a result of the very recent volca¬
nic activity in parts of the rift system
there are areas in which ground¬
water is heated. These geothermal
areas contain numerous hot springs,
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
geysers, steam jets and gas jets, and it
is possible that geothermal steam or
gas can be tapped in some of these
areas as a means of generating elec¬
tricity. Some preliminary investiga¬
tions of this possibility have already
been carried out in Uganda and Kenya,
and these potential energy sources
are of great interest because the
cost of electricity generated from
geothermal steam is normally less than
that from conventional fuels.
Although there have been few de¬
structive earthquakes in the rift zone,
it is recognized that there is a poten¬
tial hazard from earth tremors (2).
Studies of the nature and distribu¬
tion of the earthquake activity are indi¬
cated to determine the areas likely
to be affected. It is also desirable
to establish codes of building con¬
struction that will minimize damage in
the event of destructive earthquakes
taking place.
It is very encouraging that scientists
in some African countries can partici¬
pate in the International Upper Mantle
Project, and that they are contributing
to the solution of one of the major
problems of the nature and develop¬
ment of the earth's crust.
(2) A severe earthquake did in fact occur
in Uganda on March 20, 1966, causing 100
deaths and widespread damage.
Hundreds of thousands
of pink flamingoes
grace the waters
of Lake Nakuru (Kenya)
which has now become
one of the country's
national parks.
Although this lake '
has not been formed
in a crater,
it is surrounded by
volcanoes and its waters
are heavily impregnated»
with salts.
L vast underwater mountain range estimated at 40,000 miles (64,000
kilometres) in length, several hundred miles in width and often
10 to 15,000 feet (3,000 to 5,000 metres) high encircles our planet,
mainly in mid-ocean, but also meeting the continents in western North
America, the Gulf of Aden and northern Siberia. Part of this ridge
comes down the Atlantic, turns around Africa and runs through the
Indian Ocean into the «Arabian Sea, after which, via the Gulf of Aden,
it invades Africa along the Great Rift Valley (see map above). If, as
some scientists believe, the continents have drifted slowly apart during
geological time under the impulsion of convection currents coming from
deep within the earth's mantle and if the mid-oceanic ridges are the
zones along which the rupture of the original super-continent took
place, then the African rift system may actually be an early stage in
the break up of the African continent. If, as has also been suggested,
Arabia is moving slowly in a north-easterly direction, a new ocean
basin may be forming in the area of the Gulf of Aden and the Red Sea
(see map below). Some scientists foresee that millions of years hence
parts of Africa may become detached islands, like Madagascar is today.
: Recent geophysical
research has produced
new data in support
of the theory that the
Red Sea and the Gulf
of Aden were formed
by the gradual drifting
of Arabia towards
the North-east, and
that this movement is
still going on at the
rate of about two
centimetres a year.
Direction and distance
of movement of
different parts of
Arabia are indicated
by arrows. Dotted
lines show Arabia's
original coastline
positions.
X*
****" <^
li
¿4
k*^J
V \ V
t -/\
Vy % \
w
ARABIA
I /
From "New Scientist", January 27, 1966
_-»:.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
A royal
necropolis
hidden
for 3,000
years
is unearthed
in Iran
by
Ezat O. Negahban
MASTERPIECES FROM A LOST
Humped bulls stand in the tomb
from which they have just
been excavated on the rocky
hillside of Marlik (above).
Photos © Ezat O. Negahban, Teheran
MLASH, a town on the
Sea, in northern
Iran, has long been a centre for traffic
in artefacts of inestimable archaeolog¬
ical value plundered from sites in the
highlands of the Elborz mountains.
Objects in pottery and bronze, silver
and gold, stealthily excavated and
taken to Amlash, have found ready
buyers among antique dealers, and
have later been resold in Teheran,
Iran's capital, and abroad. This illegal
trading in cultural treasures has been
going on for so long and has reached
such proportions that merchandise of
this kind is now called "Amlash."
Iran's archaeological authorities,
anxious to put a stop to this illegal and
harmful traffic, decided that a neces¬
sary first step would be to carry out a
thorough archaeloglcal survey. As
part of a survey of the entire country,
work was begun late in 1961 in the
Rahmatabad of Rudbar area of the
province of Gilan. We chose this
area because we knew it was one of
great potential archaeological wealth,
EZAT O. NEGAHBAN is director of the
Institute of Archaeology, University of
Teheran. He has written a comprehensive
account of the excavations at Marlik, "A
Preliminary Report on Marlik Excavations.
Gohar Rud Expedition, Rudbar 1961-62"
(text in Persian and English), which has
been published jointly by the Iranian Ar¬
chaeological Service and the Institute of
Archaeology, University of Iran.
but about which little was definitely
known. It was thus that we brought
to light historical remains of the long-
forgotten Kingdom of Marlik, dating
back over 3,000 years.
After several weeks, during which
we investigated many ancient mounds
and dug test trenches in those which
did not have sufficient surface remains
for identification, we entered the Gohar
Rud Valley, a rich green land of rice
paddies and wheat fields, dotted with
groves of olive and wild pomegranate
trees. There, on a barren, rocky hill¬
side called Marlik tepe (or Cheragh-Ali
tepe, after its last owner) we dug ano¬
ther test trench, the twelfth of our
survey.
The trench yielded, among other
objects, two small bronze figurines of
cows, two cylinder seals and fourteen
gold buttons. A thorough excavation
of the tepe was started and gradually
we came to realize that what appeared
to be simply a natural hill was a burial
ground containing a fabulous treasure
the royal cemetery of Marlik.
In all 53 tombs were uncovered, dug
into the crest of Marlik tepe by a
people who had inhabited the sur¬
rounding territory for several hundred
years during the late second and
early first millenium B.C. These tombs
constituted the only archaeological
layer on the hill. Nothing lay above
or below except for a few miscella¬
neous objects near the surface.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Male figure holding
a long-spouted
vessel to his chest
(detail). Like most of
the human figures in
pottery found at
Marlik, Iran, it has
six toes on each foot.
Seated female bear
in red pottery
(27 cm.; 11 in.).
The Marlik animal figures,
are actually vases.
They usually have pierced
ears and a muzzle
forming a spout.
Photos © Ezat O. Negahban, Teheran
KINGDOM
The people who built these tombs
simply dug a hole, cleared the earth
away from the bedrock and construct¬
ed the tomb walls of broken stone and
mud mortar, incorporating the bedrock
wherever possible. Any spaces left
outside the walls were filled with dirt
and rubble. After the body had been
placed in the tomb with the accompany¬
ing funerary objects, it was covered
with a brownish-red earth different
from the natural soil of the mound.
Yellowish stones, again different from
the natural stone of the site, were
placed irregularly over the burial
chamber after it was filled.
Thus, when we reached such a heap
of stone, we knew a tomb lay beneath,
and when we struck the brownish-red
earth, the funerary objects were close
at hand.
A bewildering variety of objects had
been placed in these roughly construct¬
ed tombs from simple domestic uten¬
sils to elaborate ceremonial vessels.
There were also decorative and ritual
figurines, bronze weapons, personal
jewellery, pottery of all kinds, pieces
of textiles, cylinder and stamp seals,
toys and gaming pieces, small models
of various tools, and beautifully decor¬
ated bronze, silver and gold bowls.
The pottery at Marlik ranges from,
utilitarian objects to decorative vessels.
Either red or gray and unpainted, it is
sometimes burnished. Pots were
CONTINUED ON PAGE 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A LOST KINGDOM (Continued)
Detail of decoration
on a silver vase
(14 cm.; 5 1/2 in.)
shows a warrior grasping
a leopard by the throat.
This is one the few
illustrations of the dress
worn by the Marlik people.
FASHIONED
MASTER
GOLDSMITHS
Left, two rows of
. j
:
gracefully prancing unicorns
moving in opposite
directions adorn this ' \9
elegant gold vase |
(17 cm.; 7 in.).
Many elaborate silver
and gold vases were
recovered from Marlik's
royal cemetery. I
On some, the heads of 1
animals are projected in Il
high relief, almost in the
round one of the special
techniques of Wk>
Marlik's goldsmiths.
j£» ^%
Right, griffins and, 1
below them,
winged bulls Tl
embellish this vase
fashioned in gold.
Both these fabulous
monsters are
ancient motifs of the
Middle East, developed .^
with distinction by
the master artists .J
of Marlik.
*i
%'
Photos © Ezat 0. Negahban, Teheran IS
p
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
J0 * f*.
V
»111
<-' ;
*r
' *"
%*
Li
"'**
5;
11
«
^
^\
1 R
i LX «-T
M
i 14
m
Ä^
te uk^ »V «3
;'}j »
tWC
1 '\Sl \
' < ~£~<5 X.	 '
a- F.
X
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Several objects mounted on wheels, which may have been children's toys,
were discovered at Marlik. Below, group figurine in polished,
burnished red pottery depicts a charioteer, naked with a huge sword at his waist,
standing between a pair of horses, the whole mounted on four wheels.
Photos © Ezat O. Negahban, Teheran
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Far left, bronze figurine
of crouching leopard
(12 cm.; 5 in.) found in
what was probably the tomb
of a famous hunter.
Centre, bronze figurine of a
mountain goat with
crescent horns and human feet
mounted on three bronze
rods (22 cm.; 9 in.).
Left, grey pottery vase with long
spout shaped in the form of a
crane's neck and »head
(25 cm.; 10 in.).
A LOST KINGDOM (Continued)
Animal grace and vigour caught in clay
often decorated with impressed de¬
signs around the neck, shoulder or
handle. One beautifully proportioned
vase reproduces the graceful curve
of a crane's head and neck, a bird still
seen in the region. A motif based on
the wild pomegranate is common.
The pottery animal figurines have a
modern air because of their simple
abstract shapes, and in addition they
were functional, being for the most
part hollow with the muzzles formed
into a spout. Animals predominate,
but there is also a charioteer, naked
with a hugh sword at his waist, who
stands between a team of horses, the
whole mounted on four wheels.
Several other objects on wheels may
have been children's toys.
The pottery figurines representing
human beings are notably cruder than
the animal figurines, having flattened
and distorted faces.
Animals were also depicted in
bronze, but in greater numbers are
the many weapons fashioned from this
metal spears, daggers, arrowheads,
swords and maceheads. Among the
replicas of tools and equipment are
three models of hump-backed oxen
with yoke and plough.
The variety and artistry of the jewel¬
lery and decorative objects is extra¬
ordinary. A beautiful gold bracelet
has spiral butterfly beads and a pome¬
granate pendant. Among the pen¬
dants is a cage decorated with gran¬
ulation, a double-headed eagle and
a disk decorated with an abstract
design.
The most magnificent of the objects
found at Marlik are the gold ritual
vessels masterpieces of the gold¬
smith's art. One small gold cup de¬
picts mountain goats at rest with their
legs tucked under their bodies in the
Scythian fashion. On two small gold
bowls, decorated with eagles and
rams, the heads of the creatures pro¬
ject from the body of the bowl in full
relief, one of the special techniques
perfected by the Marlik goldsmiths.
Unicorns, griffons and winged bulls
are repeated motifs all ancient sym
bols of the Middle East, and developed
in a distinctive fashion by the master
artists of Marlik.
On one tall gold beaker the life
story of a mountain goat is portrayed.
Four rows of decorations, in which the
same motif is repeated around the
body of the beaker, show a young kid
being suckled by its mother, a young
goat standing on its hind legs and
eating from the Tree of Life, wild boars
apparently the enemy of the goat
and finally the carcass of the goat from
which two large vultures are plucking
the entrails.
A magnificent gold bowl, which we
have called "The Marlik Bowl", is
decorated with two pairs of winged
bulls standing on each side of the tree
of life. Their bodies are in profile and
their heads in full relief, projecting out¬
ward from the body of the bowl almost
two centimetres. The power and
strength of the winged bull is beauti¬
fully expressed here in figurines full
of vitality and life. This bowl is decor¬
ated on the bottom with a rosette, as
are most of the Marlik gold bowls.
Here the rosette represents the sun
surrounded by the leaves of the Tree
of Life.
We still have much to learn about
the Marlik people who they were,
where they came from, where they
went after the destruction of their
kingdom. It is apparent that Marlik
was the royal cemetery of a people
who controlled extensive areas of
northern and northwestern Iran 3,000
years ago. Their art clearly influenc¬
ed much vaster areas. The period of
the Marlik kingdom seems to begin
toward the end of the traditional
Mitannian art period and to end before
the formation of the New Assyrian and
Median powers. The influence of the
Marlik artists on Urartian, New Assy¬
rian, Median and Achaemenid art was
extensive and long lasting.
It seems probable that the Marlik
people and their culture played a direct
and major role in the formative stages
of the later empires of the Medes and
the Achaemenids.
Detail of a burnished
red pottery antelope
with one pierced
ear, its head
turned gracefully
to one side
(28 cm.; 11 in.).
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The latest kinds
of teaching
techniques
put mathematics
in the form of a
language which
describes
the relations
and interrelations
among objects
and sets of objects.
One of the first
steps is an exercise
in reasoning.
Here children learn
to identify
and to group
objects on the
basis of shape,
volume and
colour, and learn
to recognize how
they are related
to one another.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
New approaches to mathematics teaching
WHY 1101 13
Mathematics teaching is ceasing to be a series of formal and complicated
drills through which children acquire the skills needed in solving exam¬
ination problems. Increasingly, teachers and educational researchers are
evolving and testing a kind of teaching that eschews learning by rote.
Experience with these new techniques shows that not only arithmetical
operations, but also fundamental concepts of mathematics can be learned
intelligently by young children of primary school age. Last January an
international group of specialists met in the Unesco Institute for Education
in Hamburg, Federal Republic of Germany, to examine the results of
recent research into the learning of mathematics by children aged six to 12.
Below, a member of this group, Nicole Picard, describes some of the class¬
room and curriculum innovations of this new approach to mathematics.
by Nicole Picard
HE urgent need for a new
approach to the teaching
of mathematics has gradually become
evident over the past ten years to
those responsible for education.
The advent of a scientific and tech¬
nical civilization and its gradual exten¬
sion throughout the world has brought
far-reaching social changes, and in
particular compulsory schooling. In
the 1880s, education concerned chil¬
dren of six to ten years of age only;
nowadays, in many countries that have
reached a high degree of industrial
development, it is compulsory for chil¬
dren of six to 14 or even 16. The basic
objectives . of education have also
changed and urgent educational prob¬
lems have arisen which now confront
industrially-developed and developing
countries alike.
As long ago as 1912 the distinguish¬
ed British mathematician and philo¬
sopher Alfred North Whitehead wrote:
"Before long science will be making
spectacular new progress and for
those who have not received an ade¬
quate education there will be no re¬
dress."
It is just as important to solve the
problem of intellectual undernourish¬
ment as that of bodily undernourish¬
ment; indeed, it is only by solving the
first problem that solutions will be
found for the second.
NICOLE PICARD is a specialist in research
on mathematics teaching at the National
Pedagogical Institute in Pans. She has
written many studies on the introduction to
mathematics In primary education.
When the idea of compulsory school¬
ing began to develop and spread about
1880, it was put into practice with great
haste; everyone was to be taught to
read, to write and spell correctly and
to count, and the programmes were
drawn up on that basis. In primary
education mathematics was confined
to the use of numbers. The pupil
learned to do sums and solve arithmet¬
ical problems, but he was hardly ever
called upon to use his judgment. Few
children reached the stage where
reflective thought is required, and
those who did mostly came from the
socially privileged classes.
Gradually, advances were made in
technology. The horse-drawn vehicle
was replaced by the railway, the car
and the aeroplane. Distances dimin¬
ished and contacts between different
countries became easier. Nowadays
networks for rapid communications
cover the surface of the globe and
even space itself has become a sphere
of activity for man. Similarly, inform¬
ation is transmitted by more and
more powerful means. The volume
of knowledge within reach of each of
us increases continuously; but in order
to assimilate it, we need to develop
faculties of reflective reasoning and
critical appraisal.
Today technological development
and increasing automation are gra¬
dually eliminating the employment of
unskilled labour. By 1970 nearly half
the working population of the indus¬
trialized countries will be composed of
middle-ranking technicians and super
visory staffs. At the same time the
need for more higher-level tech¬
nicians and administrators is increas¬
ing.
Reading, writing and arithmetic are a
far from adequate stock-in-trade for
making one's way in our twentieth-
century world. A person who has not
received more than that has been
intellectually starved.
The new patterns of economic
growth and employment revealed the
need to prolong compulsory schooling.
The advantages of an educated com¬
munity, in terms of national economic
progress, became apparent, and high¬
er education was therefore made
accessible to an ever-larger number
of students, especially those studying
science and technology.
At the same time the content of
teaching and teaching methods and
aids have been changed. In mathe¬
matics in particular, the reform be¬
gan at the top, in higher education.
This was brought about by the vast
accumulation of new scientific know¬
ledge which revised many basic scien¬
tific concepts. Mathematical res'earch
became the main instrument for this
revision.
In fact there should not be one kind
of mathematics for school teaching and
another for practical use. The basic
core of mathematical reasoning and
structures, together with their symbols,
should be known to all. Detailed stud- n n
ies should follow in mathematical re- ¿v
search and in other scientific fields
physics and chemistry obviously, as
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
WHY 1101 = 13 (Continued)
Replacing symbols, jargon and routine
24
well as medicine and psychology.
Mathematics is also being increasingly
used for research in sociology and
history.
In the introductory teaching of
mathematics, it is not just a matter of
using the formulae of numerical calcu¬
lation or the spatial ideas of Euclid¬
ean geometry. What is applied now
in any field of learning, when we are
attempting to organize new facts, is
the mathematical language of structure,
relations, functions and symbols.
This is sometimes called, "modern"
mathematics. The new branch of math¬
ematics, concerned with theories of
sets and relations, which 20 years ago
was reserved for a small number of re¬
search specialists, has become, in the
last ten years or so, a subject for
higher mathematical education. This
evolution in mathematical studies has
forced a reform in the mathematics
curriculum at various levels.
However the introduction of the new
mathematics created serious problems.
Teachers noted that because what they
were explaining was so completely
new, their students were not able to
take it in and benefit from it unless
their minds were first "de-condition
ed." They needed to acquire a new
way of thinking; the old mathematical
frame was much too compartmentaliz¬
ed. It was obvious that training along
the new lines must begin at the secon¬
dary level (12 to 16 years of age).
Several groups were therefore set
up to study the reform of mathematics
teaching at this level. An interesting
fact was that the groups included
educational psychologists, logicians
and specialists on problems of learn¬
ing.
One of the many working groups of
this kind is the International Commis¬
sion for the Study and Improvement
of Mathematics Teaching, which began
its work in 1950. This group has used
the method of international seminars:
it has co-ordinated the work done in
various places and has drawn up
guidelines for further research.
It was observed, in the first place,
that the reform of mathematics teach¬
ing could not be achieved unless It
took root in the nursery school and
extended to the university; secondly,
that there was a very close connexion
between initiation into mathematics and ,
the development of the faculty of rea¬
soning and intelligence; and lastly, that
the revised subject matter demanded
new teaching methods.
In countries where school attendance
is compulsory up to at least 14, prim¬
ary education is designed to lay solid
foundations on which to build second¬
ary education. Primary mathematical
education should aim to provide a
variety of experience. Concrete exam¬
ples should serve as the basis from
which it will be possible effectively to
abstract (in the etymological sense, to
"draw from") and generalize math¬
ematical concepts. This should be pos¬
sible from the ages of 12 to 16.
In this way children will have had five
years of experience in formulating
ideas about mathematical structures.
This learning will build the foundations
of their mathematical knowledge.
Many programmes have been drawn
up for this purpose. They differ in
their approaches and also in the
volume of their content. It seems clear
now as a result of the work of child
psychologists that from the age of
seven, and not only from the age of 12
as was formerly thought, children are
in fact capable of something more than
merely memorizing calculation drills
and acquiring routine skills.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Right, the meaning
of symbols. Exercises lead
children from everyday
things with which
they are familiar to
the abstract idea
of numbers.
They work first with elements
that compose sets, then
learn to recognize when
sets have the same kind
and number of elements.
Association of equivalent
sets then leads to the use
of numerals to identify them.
Left, fingers still come
in handy for this boy
to show the teacher
that he has the right answer
to the problem.
In fact experience shows that from
the age of seven children are capable
of understanding mathematical shapes
and sizes (provided they are suffi¬
ciently simple), and while playing with
these concrete objects are able to
deduce from the experience many
mathematical relations. They can also
solve practical problems, provided, of
course, that the methods used are di¬
rectly related to their sense of manipu¬
lation and tactile skill. They should be
given a variety of materials to enable
them to manipulate various forms of
mathematical structures.
Of the methods used for the reform
of mathematics education, those for
arithmetic employ the most traditional
approach. They consist in utilizing
materials for manipulation that have
the same structure as the ordinary
numerical system. Instead of learning
addition and multiplication tables by
heart, children study addition and multi¬
plication by an ordered arrangement
of concrete elements.
Notable examples are the Cuisenaire
rods and the blocks used by Catherine
Stern. These were devised on the
basis of the pioneering research of
Maria Montessori. Arithmetical opera-
Photos © Institut Pédagogique National - Jean Suquet, Paris
tions are represented by material
arrangements to be performed by the
children. Playing is, in itself, perform¬
ing an operation: the action of putting
bars together in line with the ends
touching one another corresponds to
the operation of "addition." Two bars
a and b are equivalent to one bar c
which has the same length as that
obtained by putting the bars a and b
together end to end:
O^
If we symbolize the placing end to
end by +, we have a + b = c; b +
a = c; in the same way that 2 + 3 =
5; 3 + 2 = 5.
A similar procedure can be used for
discovering the properties of the mul¬
tiplication of numbers. As a corollary,
the fact that addition and subtraction
are inverse operations can also be
seen, as well as the relation between
multiplication and division. These
methods are in use in Belgium, Canada,
the United Kingdom and Switzerland,
and to some extent in France.
Let us take a look at numeration by
position. According to one of the
known principles of the psychology of
intelligence, a concept is assimilated
better when all the possible compon¬
ents are made to vary. In the case
of numeration by position, this means
in particular that we must vary the
bases. When we write a number, we
make use of a sign-position. Thus,
in order to write 1966, we use
the numbers 1, 9 and 6-, however, in the
"word" 1966 the first and the second
"6" do not have the same significance.
Our sign - positions constitute an
"alphabet," the meaning of each sign
depending upon its place in the word.
If our alphabet has ten signs we are
using a system of numbers "with the
base ten," if it has three signs, a
system of numbers with the base three
and so on. Electronic computers use
the base two, the Babylonians used
the base twelve, certain primitive peop¬
les use the base five. In teaching
this implies that instead of speaking
only of units, tens, hundreds, thou¬
sands, etc., we shall speak of suc¬
cessive groups, based on a certain
method (a numeration with the base
2, 3, or 5 for example, or of 10, as
CONTINUED ON PAGE 27
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CONCRETE
STEPS
TO
ABSTRACT
CONCEPTS
As more purposeful mathematics
teaching is introduced, children learn
to count on other bases than that of
the decimal system. Here a class
learns how to calculate with a numbers
system based on four. (1) The teach¬
er gives each child a cube and
divides the class into groups of four.
(2) She calls each group in turn, takes
their four cubes and gives in exchange
to the group leader a rod which is
four times bigger than a cube. (3) Call¬
ing out four group leaders at a time,
she exchanges their rods for a single
block that is four times bigger than
a rod (or sixteen times bigger than
a cube). All the children participate
in these successive collections and
exchanges of objects whose relative
sizes correspond to the number base
being used. Experience shows that
by their second year in primary school,
children are able to add, subtract,
multiply and divide on any number
base. They have not been taught
these operations by rote but have
discovered them experimentally.
Photos Unesco - Dominique Roger
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Children make their own discoveries
WHY 1101 = 13 (Continued)
in the case of the decimal system).
From the time they begin to study
numeration, children learn to count in
terms of different bases: for this they
use what are called Multibase Arith¬
metic Blocks.
If we say that we have 13 2 1
objects, that will mean that,
H with the base four we have 1. 43 +
3.42 + 2.41 + 1.4° objects;
with the base ten we have 1.103 +
3.102 + 2.101 + 1.10° objects,
and with the base n (n > 4 as we
have at least, the signs 0, 1, 2, 3),
1.n3 + 3.n2 + 2-n1 + 1.n° objects.
In this equipment of blocks with
base n, the power zero is represented
by small cubes, the power one by a bar
of n cubes, the power two by a plate of
n bars of n cubes, the power three by
a cube of n plates, the power four
by a bar of n cubes of n plates, etc . . .
so that our number 13 2 1 will be
represented by the objects as follows:
In this way children are led to make
successive groupings and exchanges,
following a model which varies accord¬
ing to the base used, the exchanges
being imposed by the fact that, for
example with four as the base, four
plates must always be put together
to make a cube.
From their second year of primary
school, children are capable of per¬
forming the four arithmetical operations
on any base. An interesting point is
that the operational techniques are not
learned, but discovered experimentally.
As regards methods based on the
notion of sets, these necessitate much
more extensive changes in the pro¬
grammes than the previous method.
They are based in particular on: (1)
work involving the introduction of math¬
ematical logic; (2) work in the sphere
of psychology, concerning the evolu¬
tion of the child's mental structure and
his grasp of mathematical concepts.
The methods have in fact a much
wider and more ambitious aim than
giving an understanding of mathema¬
tics. Experiments made in the past
few years indicate that where these
methods have been used there are no
longer any pupils good at literary sub¬
jects who are bad at mathematics.
These same methods, which are based
on notions of sets, operations with
sets, and the logic of sets, do indeed
help to develop a child's intelligence,
by helping to organize his reasoning
abilities. Experiments In the use of
such methods were started this year
with mentally retarded children but the
results have not yet been assessed.
In these methods, an integral number
is considered as a property of a set.
The notions of set and property are
thus fundamental ones, and the notion
of number is built upon them.
Two sets, A and B, have the same
cardinal number (that is, the same num¬
ber of elements) when their elements
can be put into one-to-one correspond¬
ence with each other.
The two sets A and B have a com¬
mon property, namely that they each
have four elements.
As we have said, before even talk¬
ing of number the children "manipu¬
late" the notions of set and property.
A set can be defined either in terms
of its extension by enumerating all
its elements once and once only; or
in terms of what it comprises by
defining the elements of the set by a
common property characteristic of
them (all the children in the class
wearing a blue pullover for example).
Two sets are equal if and only if they
are composed of the same elements:
thus, if A is the set of even numbers
above 1 and below 10 and if B = (2,
4, 6, 8), then A = B.
Notions of the property of an object
gradually lead to the notion .of the
property of a set. Operations with
sets provide the introduction to opera¬
tions with numbers. In addition, the
intuitive study of sets does not merely
have the utilitarian purpose of introduc¬
ing the child to numbers, but gives
him, at a very early age, an initiation
into the logic essential to organized
thought.
Studies of the mental development
of the child have shown that children
of the same age differ vastly according
to their social origin. Many children
have not been able to get from their
family background the cultural comple¬
ment necessary to the full flowering of
their intelligence. The new teaching
methods involve notions of sets, opera
tions with sets and also the fundamen¬
tal notions of relatians that are
indissolubly associated with them.
They thus give children, from their
nursery school days, habits of classific¬
ation, order and comparison. This
offers each child the possibility of
developing his own faculties to the
maximum.
In fact these methods are meant
to be introduced at the nursery school
stage in the form of games and mani¬
pulations. This has been done mainly
in England, France, Belgium, Northern
Europe and the U.S.A.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
To keep their records of trade and gov¬
ernment administration the Egyptians need¬
ed large numbers 5,000 or more years ago.
So they made up a set of numerals by
which they could express numbers of dif¬
ferent values from units up to hundreds of
thousands. Above, the number 27,529 as
written by the early Egyptians.
Among the oldest systems of numerals are
those used by the Chinese, and later
adopted by the Japanese. These have
naturally changed somewhat in the course
of the centuries. One type (shown above)
is based on the use of sticks laid upon a
table and used for calculating. It was also
used in written documents.
VVVV=2I966I
The Sumerians of the Mesopotamian valley,
over 3,000 years ago, had one system of
calculating for everyday use and another
which was taught in special schools and
used exclusively in texts on mathematics
and astronomy. Cuneiform, or wedge-shap¬
ed, numerals were adopted for both sys¬
tems. In the "scientific" system, the value __
of each numeral, starting from the left, is ¿J
sixty times that of its neighbour on the right.
Thus the cuneiform numerals above signify
216,000 + 3,600 + 60 + 1 = 219,661.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
CAN YOU SOLVE THE PROBLEM OF THE CHINESE NECKLACE ?
Since ancient times the Chinese have shown- a
pronounced taste for mathematical games and puzzles.
Here is an extremely simple example. We invite
readers to try their hand at it.
During a long journey a merchant takes a room at
an inn. His pockets are empty but he expects a
messenger to arrive with money in 63 days. The
innkeeper, however, insists on being paid for the
lodging every day. The merchant has a necklace of
63 pearls and he proposes to use these pearls to
settle what he owes from day to day. The innkeeper
agrees to this arrangement and they fix the value of
one day's bed and board at one pearl. When the
messenger arrives, the merchant will settle his bill
with the money he receives, take back his pearls and
restring the necklace. To do this he is anxious to
make as few cuts in the necklace as possible. While
paying the innkeeper exactly what he owes each day,
what are the smallest number of cuts he will need to
make in the necklace?
The answer will be published next month.
(7x23)+(1x22) + (Ox2') + (1x2°) = 13
Notation on the decimal scale, which originated in the
number of fingers on the hands, is by far the most widely
used system. Certain peoples have made use of other
notations, including one based on 20 (the Mayas) and
the binary (using the base 2). Reference is made to the
base 2 in a Chinese book believed to have been written
about 3000 B.C. Paradoxically it is the system used
by ultra-modern electronic computers. The binary scale
employs only two symbols: 0 and 1 and the digits re¬
present powers of 2. Its importance is in relation to the
use of perforated cards in computers. Since it has only
two digits any number can be represented by a series
of switches which are either "on" for. one or "off" for
nought. The use of perforated cards dates back well
over a century and a half when the French engineer,
Joseph Jacquard, perfected an attachment for the power
loom in which a chain of punched cards passed before
the needles of the loom (left). Only the needles facing
the holes are able to carry out the process of weaving.
© IBM
28
WHY 1101 = 13 (Continued)
In mathematics, the notion of "rela¬
tions" cannot be dissociated from that
of sets. A relation can be represented
by a "diagram". Thus, if we repre¬
sent by>	 the relation "having the
same shape as" between cut-outs
stuck onto a sheet of paper, we get the
following "diagram":
Experience shows that from the age
of six, children are capable of repre
senting non-oriented relations (a dash
instead of an arrow). Reflexivity (each
element is of the same form as itself)
as a concept is still too subtle for them,
but at the age of eight it can be un¬
derstood without difficulty.
The importance of "representations"
(graphs, plans, diagrams, tables) is that
they enable the child to express in
pictures what he would be completely
incapable of expressing in words. In
schools where teaching methods based
on representations of this kind have
been tried out, it has been found that
not only are the children capable from
the age of six of making their own dia¬
grams; they also draw conclusions
from them and thus make a first attempt
at reasoning. This is interesting not
only in pedagogy but also from the
viewpoint of studying a child's way of
thinking and powers of reasoning.
The study of relations from earliest
schooldays has been tried out in Bel¬
gium and France with very interesting
results.
A situation can easily be mathematic-
ized if it can be expressed in a form
directly accessible to logical reason¬
ing. This procedure has been tried
out in the countries mentioned above
and also in the U.S.S.R., where some
interesting research has been done.
Experience has shown that algebra
can be introduced into the curriculum
from the age of eight provided that
concrete materials which can be manip¬
ulated are used. In fact it makes
possible a great saving of mental
recapitulation. For the solution of
problems traditionally set in the prim¬
ary school, children find It much easier
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
DÜRER'S MAGIC
SQUARE
In Albrecht Dürer's famous engraving "Melancholia" (detail
left), there appears a device about which more has been
written than any other form of mathematical amusement:
the "magic square". This consists of an array of numbers
in a square which, when added up by rows, diagonals or
columns, yield the same total. In Dürer's square the numbers
are: 16, 3, 2, 13, 5, 10, 11, 8, 9, 6, 7, 12, 4, 15, 14, 1, and
their sum is 34 in all directions. As a final refinement, the
celebrated German artist has included the date of his work,
1514, in the bottom row.
TOWER
OF HANOI
ME
The Tower of Hanoi was invented by the French
mathematician Edouard Lucas and sold as a toy
in 1883. The problem is to transfer the tower
of eight disks to either of the two vacant pegs in
the fewest possible moves, moving one disk at a
time and never placing a disk on top of a smaller
one. The minimum number of moves required is
expressed by the formula 2B_1 (n being the
number of disks). Thus three, disks can be
transferred in seven moves, four in 15, five in
31 and so on. To transfer the eight disks and
rebuild the tower 255 moves are required.
Proving that n disks in the Tower of Hanoi can be
moved to another peg in 2"_1 steps is an excel¬
lent exercise in mathematical induction.
Glraudon, Paris
to use simple forms of algebra than
the complicated arithmetic they are
normally taught.
It would obviously take too long to
review all the research that is being
done. Some relates to the introduc¬
tion of geometry (this is being studied
especially in Belgium, Canada, Italy
and the U.S.A.); another branch deals
mainly with simple experiments in
mechanics and physics. Research, in
fact, is going on in a great many
countries including Denmark, Norway,
Poland, Hungary, to name only four.
In the developing countries the
problem of establishing a suitable sys¬
tem of education takes a different form,
and is perhaps even more acute than
in the industrialized countries.
The most urgent question facing
educational authorities in developing
countries is the definition of the role
of education. Many of these countries
now need to train a large number of
teachers in the next few years. Un¬
doubtedly this will involve great diffi¬
culties, but paradoxically, these coun¬
tries have an advantage over the in¬
dustrialized countries. They have to
train, not to re-train their teachers.
They do not have to face the problem
of "deconditioning" hundreds of thou¬
sands of teachers who have become
used to rigid and stereotyped methods.
The people responsible for education
in these countries are generally very
enthusiastic. They need to be given
as much information as possible about
the educational reforms we have been
describing. This will ensure that from
the outset the teaching of mathematics,
which is also a factor in the develop¬
ment of intelligence, will become, not
a conditioning to out-of-date techni¬
ques, but an opening of the mind and
a development of aptitudes.
Moreover, as this new teaching
proceeds on the experience of experi¬
ments with children, it can very well
be adapted to different cultural back¬
grounds and related to the social
context in which children and adults
grow up.
Similarly, the study of science can
also be made relevant to the actual
living conditions of a particular com¬
munity. In fact one can form math¬
ematical structures and relations by
deriving them from the study of other
ordinary elements of concrete objects.
Source material for this can be select-
from a number of simple, everyday
experiences.
When sociologists and ethnologists
make their contribution to the already
promising research of the mathema¬
ticians, logicians and educational psy¬
chologists, even more fruitful results
can be expected.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL TROPHIES FOR SPORTSMANSHIP
Fair Play?
Simply a question of honesty'
An athlete, a team of women gymnasts, a football referee and two football teams have
been awarded the second annual International Fair Play Trophies (for 1965). These
Unesco-sponsored awards are designed to honour men and women who place the
highest values on a spirit of sportsmanship, even at the cost of losing a contest Eugenio
Monti, the Italian bobsleigh champion, who received the first of these awards last
year, affirmed that the International Fair Play Trophy would become "the world's most
coveted award." The committee which designates the winners is composed of represen¬
tatives of Unesco, of the International Sporting Press Association, of the International
Council of Physical Education and Sport and of leading international sports federations.
On March 17, 1966, the latest winners of the Fair Play trophies were present at a cere¬
mony in Unesco House (right) to receive their awards from Mr. J.E. Forbes, Unesco's
Assistant Director-General, in the presence of M. François Misoffe, French Minister of
Youth and Sports and of M. Jean Borotra (standing), France's veteran tennis champion,
who heads the Fair Play Committee of the International Council for Education and Sport.
In November 1965,
the British Ladies Gymnastic team,
about to meet
a team in Hungary,
heard that one of the Hungarians
had been injured
while training.
Unanimously the British girls
chose to withdraw
one of their own members to even
the chances and the Hungarians
won by a narrow margin.
A Fair Play Trophy was
presented to Mrs. Pauline Prestidge,
coach of the British team.
Left, her daughter,
16-year-oid Mary Prestidge,
a member of the British team.
^ |
I I
1!
iii m ii
11
I I 1 I 111
^i
Unesco - Dominique Roger
Magyar Tavirati iroda
Some 80,000 fans
packed the stands
at Wembly Stadium, London,
on May 19, 1965 to watch
the finals of the
European Cup Winners' Cup
tournament (right) between
the British team,
West Ham United, and
the German champions,
the Munich 1960 club.
The referee and the
two captains,
West Ham's Bobby Moore
and Munich's Peter Radenkovic,
all sensed that the
enthusiasm and excitement
of the crowd might
easily turn into
noisy demonstrations.
But the match was played
so cleanly and with
such skill that
the referee, Istvan Zsolt,
of Hungary, was not obliged
to award a single penalty.
West Ham won, 2-0, but
the newspapers of both countries
were unanimous in
praising the spirit
of fair play shown by both
teams. Captains and
referee were presented
with Fair Play trophies.
© UPl, London
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
1. 1. i.u
-p*^
U.S. woman athlete, Willye White
(right), silver medalist in the Olympic
long jumps at Melbourne and Tokyo,
has just beaten Mary Rand (above),
British Olympic gold medal winner,
her rival in the U.S. Amateur
Athletic Union games in New York.
To everyone's surprise,
Mary Rand failed even
to qualify for the finals.
Discovering that the British
athlete had mistaken some track
markers unfamiliar to her,
Willye White pursuaded officials
to give Mary Rand
another chance whereupon
the British girl went
on to win the event.
"Fair play", said Willye White,
on receiving her Fair Play trophy,
"is simply a question of honesty.
Everybody wants to win,
but nothing is won
if an error made it possible."
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
World Festival of Negro Arts
Flags of 40 nations flew over Dakar,
Senegal, from March 30 to April 24, for
the First World Festival of Negro Arts.
More than a thousand performers took part
in a programme which included displays
of paintings, sculpture, literature, music
and dancing. All Dakar's theatres and
cinemas as well as its Parliament building
were used for lectures and discussion
groups, including a symposium on "the
function and significance of Negro African
art in popular culture," held under the
sponsorship of Unesco and the African
Society of Culture.
32
BOOKSHELF
Cultural and Social Anthropology :
Selected Readings
Edited by Peter B. Hammond. An
introduction to the problems involved
in the study of man. The Macmillan
Company, New York; Collier-Mac-
millan Ltd., London, 1964 (30/-;
$3.95).
Industrialization and Society
Edited by Bert F. Hoselitz and Wilbert
E. Moore. The Social Implications
of Industrialization and Technical
Change. Unesco-Mouton, 1963 (42/6,
$7.50; hardback).
West African Urbanization
By Kenneth Little. A study of volun¬
tary associations in social change.
Cambridge University Press, 1965
(35/-; $6.50).
Geography of Coastal Deserts
By Peveril Meigs (Arid Zone series;
volume 28). Unesco, 1966 (33/-,
$6.50; paper cover).
World Guide to Science Informa¬
tion and Documentation Services
(bilingual: English-French).
Unesco, 1965 (13/-, $2.50, paper
cover; 20/-, $4.00, hardback).
15 Years and 150,000 Skills
An anniversary review of the U.N.
Expanded Programme of Technical
Assistance, United Nations, New
York, 1965 ($2.00 or equivalent in
other currencies).
Child Study
By Norman J. Maynard. An intro¬
duction to educational psychology
for teachers in Africa (Teachers' Li¬
brary). Oxford University Press,
1966 (10/6).
Spain offers fellowships in
soil science & plant biology
An international training course in soil
science and plant biology will be held,
with Unesco's assistance, at the univers¬
ities of Seville and Granada, Spain, from
October 1966 to May 1967. Spain is offer¬
ing full fellowships, including travel expen¬
ses, to selected participants. All lectures
will be given in Spanish. For further details
write to: Prof. Emilio Fernandez Galiano,
Instituto Botánico A.J. Cavanilles, Plaza de
Murillo 2, Madrid 14, Spain. Application
forms must be returned by August 15, 1966
Food from leaves
A machine for extracting edible protein
from the leaves of tropical plants has been
designed and developed by a British scient¬
ist. Tropical leaves, which often contain
as much as ten to twenty-five per cent
protein, are crushed to produce a purée,
and steam is used to curdle the protein
which can be filtered off through cloth.
About 500 pounds of leaves can be pro¬
cessed in two hours. A number of these
protein-extracting machines are being used
experimentally in India, New Guinea, Jamai¬
ca and Uganda.
Space phones
in Australia
Western Australians may be making
overseas telephone calls by satellite later
this year because of U S. plans to land
men on the moon in Project Apollo. The
Overseas Telecommunications Commission
(Australia) will provide satellite communica¬
tion channels and a ground station in
Western Australia for use during the Apollo
project. The station will communicate with
two Early Bird type satellites which are
being put in orbit over the Pacific and the
Atlantic this year. Channels will be pro¬
vided for both Project Apollo use and for
Australian uses, giving the country its first
commercial space communications link.
India to treble
fertilizer production
As part of her plans to meet massive
needs in food, India aims to treble her
fertilizer production. India's newest fertil¬
izer factory the world's largest nitrophos-
phate plant is at Trombay, 15 miles from
Bombay. The factory, which went into
production some months ago, is built on
a 527-acre site and is designed to produce
320,000 tons of nitrophosphates a year.
India's fertilizer consumption is still low
one kilogramme per acre compared with
27 kgs. in France and 95 kgs. in Japan.
SPECIAL DOUBLE ISSUE
OF THE UNESCO COURIER
FOR JULY-AUGUST 1966
The next issue of the Unesco Courier
will commemorate Unesco's 20th an¬
niversary and will include additional
pages in full colour. Readers are
asked to note that this special double
number for July-August will appear
at the end of July.
Educational problems
of the Arab world
Ministers of Education and Ministers for
Economic Planning of the Arab states
recently met to study the educational
problems of the Arab world at a conference
convened by Unesco in Tripoli, Libya.
Although the number of young people in
the Arab countries receiving education has
increased from eight to 12 million in the
past five years, almost half the children
aged from six to 1 1 still do not attend
school Overall gains, however, show that
primary school enrollment is up from 6 3 to
9 8 million, of whom 35% are girls, and
secondary enrollment is up from 1,124,000
to about two million, of whom 26% are girls.
New home for World Health Organization
AUN stamp issued on May 26 commémorâtes the opening of a new headquarters
building in Geneva for the World Health Organization. Situated a stone's throw from
the Palais des Nations, the new headquarters comprises
an 11-storey Secretariat building, a cube-shaped meeting
hall for the WHO Executive Board and a one-storey
annex. The U N. commemorative stamp is issued in
denominations of 5-cents and 11-cents. As agent in
France of the U.N. Postal Administration, Unesco's
Philatelic Service stocks all U.N. stamps and first day
covers currently on sale. For further details write to
the Unesco Philatelic Service, Place de Fontenoy,
WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION paMq n°\
HEADQUARTERS-GENEUA.19G6 ra"a L' }
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
New technique for reading
fire-damaged manuscripts
Ancient papyri which have been so
charred by fire as to be unreadable can
now be deciphered thanks to a new tech¬
nique developed by Dr. Anton Fackelmann,
restorer at the National Library of Vienna.
He uses an electrically charged plate to
remove a thin layer from the papyrus, thus
rendering the writing visible. Dr. Fackel¬
mann also discovered how to unroll
desiccated papyri by softening them with
fresh papyrus sap. He also found the
secret, lost in the Middle Ages, of making
"Goldschlag parchment" a very thin
parchment treated with lime which was
used to protect old papyrus from humidity.
Radiation energy for
heating and cooling
Successful experiments in using solar
radiation to heat houses and terrestrial
radiation to produce spectacular drops in
temperature are described in the Unesco
quarterly "Impact" (Vol. XV, No 4, 1965;
4/-; $0.75). They are reported by Professor
Felix Trombe, director of the French solar
energy laboratory at Montlouis in the
Pyrenees. At Montlouis prototype houses
have been constructed to capture the sun's
energy with built-in solar collectors and
accumulator walls. These techniques have
reduced the price of a solar kilowatt-hour
to less than one-third of a U.S. cent.
Professor Trombe writes: "House and water
heating can be envisaged in cloudless
countries where there are long periods
of sunny cold weather... In warmer parts
it is now possible to envisage applications
of terrestial radiation that could improve
living conditions and be used to preserve
food."
Flashes...
France is to establish a "National
Institute of the Sea" at Brest, on the coast
of Bntanny, with places for 1,000 oceano¬
graphy researchers, students and techni-
More efficient diagnosis of atheroscler¬
osis the most common cause of coron¬
ary heart disease will, it is hoped, result
from a special WHO study in Czecho¬
slovakia, Sweden and the Soviet Union.
Yugoslavia has become the 52nd country
to ¡om the Unesco-sponsored Universal
Copyright Convention, which calls on coun¬
tries to grant foreign works the same
protection accorded to works by their own
nationals.
A 70-year-old grandmother, Daw Thein,
was among the 2,429 students who recently
received their degrees from Rangoon Uni¬
versity, Burma.
A new university, the 42nd in the Soviet
Union, has been opened at Donetz in the
Ukraine.
'ONE DAY'S
EXPENDITUDE ON ARMS'
A gift of $700,000 to be used in the
fight against illiteracy has been made
to Unesco by Iran. The gift was
announced to the Unesco Executive
Board, meeting in Paris on May 2, by
Mr. René Máheu, Director-General of
Unesco. Mr. Maheu read a letter he
had received from the Shah, who
explained that the contribution was
"the equivalent of one day's expendi¬
ture under our military budget." The
Shah's action follows the proposal he
made to the Unesco-sponsored World
Congress of Ministers of Education on
the Eradication of illiteracy, held in
Teheran last September, that all
nations should help to finance literacy
by making small deductions from their
military budgets. At a press confer¬
ence in Unesco House on May 2,
Mr. Fereydoun Hoveyda, Iranian Vice-
Minister of Foreign Affairs, announced
that the Shah had addressed a solemn
appeal to all governments to make a
special contribution to assist the
struggle against illiteracy throughout
the world. Mr. Hoveyda added that
his country would be ready to repeat
its donation if there were a favourable
response to the Shah's appeal. Below
we publish the text of the Shah's letter
to Unesco :
You will remember that at the opening of the World Congress of
Ministers of Education on the Eradication of Illiteracy, 1 said that, as
many of the countries afflicted by this scourge have insufficient financial
resources, international solidarity can and must come into play. Speaking
of the possible sources of finance, I added that it would perhaps not
be so very fanciful to ask the governments of the world to devote a
negligible proportion of their military budgets to this great work. I also
said that so far as we were concerned, we had made a national effort
of this sort by setting up the Education Corps, and that we were ready
to extend our efforts internationally for the good of all peoples.
I am now happy to tell you that as the Iranian year begins, with the
budget just voted by Parliament, I have decided, in pursuance of the
statement I made last September and of the recommendations of the
Teheran Congress, to make available to Unesco the equivalent of one
day's expenditure under our military budget, in order to assist in the
struggle against illiteracy throughout the world. This represents a sum
of about $700,000 drawn from thé Iranian military budget for the year 1345
(1966-1967).
The eradication at the international level of the social evil of illiteracy
naturally demands time and money on a far larger scale than that of
my government's modest contribution. But it is to be hoped that this
decision which, for a developing country like mine represents a real
sacrifice, will be followed by many others and will perhaps enable Unesco
to institute a special fund for carrying out an historic undertaking which
is among those of greatest urgency for the economic, social and cultural
development of mankind.
I am glad that the implementation of the recommendations of the Teheran
Congress coincides, in 1966, with Unesco's twentieth anniversary that
you will be celebrating in a few months' time. I take this opportunity
of saying how heartily I desire that your Organization's efforts in the
struggle against illiteracy, as in other important spheres of education,
science and culture, may be crowned with success.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
34
OUR THIRSTY
HUNGRY WORLD
Sir,
I read with great interest your March
and April 1966 issues which covered
ground very familiar to me. I was first
engaged in hydrological work during
the 1914-18 war when 1 organized
and directed water supply activités in
the Middle East, and I continued to
work in this field after the war in
much of Africa, Arabia and parts of
India, where the people, in ignorance
of ground water prospects and the
means of its recovery, largely depend¬
ed on ponded water and polluted
streams for their domestic supplies.
I thus experienced the conditions under
which an explosion of population was
endangering food supplies. I have
also .many times seen the distress
caused by rain failure, pests and
disease.
I have just renewed my subscription
to the Unesco Courier for a further
two years, and would like to say how
much I enjoy reading every Issue. I
am about to enter my 94th year and
am in semi-retirement, but I am still
actively engaged in writing my memoirs
which cover a period of 60 years, and
include my experiences in petroleum
exploration and oil-field development
In all parts of the world.
A. Beeby-Thompson
London, England
WITH APOLOGIES
TO ROSINANTE
Sir,
As a reader of the Courier for the
past seven years I have learned to
appreciate its qualities of reliability
and interest. Reading the piece on
Cervantes (Great Men, Great Events)
in your March 1965 issue, I was sur¬
prised to find Don Quixote's nag des¬
cribed as a mare. Rosinante, of
course, was a horse. Please restore
to the famous mount of the Melan¬
choly Knight its proper sex and
rightful dignity. Bravo! for commem¬
orating the anniversaries of great
events and of the great men and
women whose significance is univer¬
sal.
Jacques Decamp
La Madeleine, France
JUNIOR OLYMPICS
Sir,
I am 14 years of age and an Aus¬
tralian. I know everyone enjoys and
realizes the tremendous value of the
modern Olympic Games. They must
spread tremendous goodwill between
the various competitors of different
religions, races, colours and Ideol¬
ogies, but nevertheless all these com¬
petitors are generally mature adults
who have firm opinions on most things
of importance by the time they
compete. Sometimes these opinions
can be an obstacle to really close
friendships with other people.
My idea is that there should be a
Junior Olympic Games with children
from all the nations entered in the
real Olympic Games. What a wonderful
way of promoting friendship, goodwill
and physical fitness this would be.
The Junior Games could be held every
four years (as are the real Olympics)
but in a different city. I think the
idea has great possibilities and I wish
someone could do something concrete
about it.
I came across the Courier in our
local library. I find it very interesting
and intend to take out a subscription.
Gavan Keating
Ballarat, Australia
THREE CHILDREN
EVERY SECOND
Sir,
The Unesco Courier is one of the
outstanding voices of our time a his¬
toric time of integration for the human
family, a kind of new Renaissance in
which all social structures are undergo¬
ing constant and decisive changes.
In this complex situation the popula¬
tion explosion has become Factor
Number One, and your February 1966
issue rightly emphasizes this, starting
with the front cover which tells us
that two babies are born into the
world every second.
This figure set me thinking. If we
take 65 years as man's average
lifespan, the annual global mortality
rate is about 15.5 per thousand. This
means that about 50 million of the
world's 3,200 million inhabitants die
each year. Since the total annual pop¬
ulation increase in the world is 60 mil¬
lion, the total annual number of births
must be around 110 million. And since
there are approximately 31 million
seconds in one year it seems to me
that the correct figure must be
3.5 babies born every second. Am I
right?
Alberto J. Scardiglia
Cordoba, Argentina
We agree with our reader that the
figure of two children born every
second is an overcautious estimate.
Although global demographic figures
are necessarily approximate (in many
countries precise and up-to-date sta-
tisticé are still not available) it would
no doubt be more realistic to consider
three births a second as the world
average. It Is the actual population
increase that has now reached the rate
of two people a second a yearly total
of 60 million Editor.
THE OPPENHEIMER
HOSPITAL
Sir,
I can confirm, as N. V. Baldwin
states in the letter published in the
December 1965 issue, that the picture
shown on page 29 of the issue on
Racialism (April 1965) is in fact the
Oppenheimer Hospital at Welkom,
some 185 miles from Johannesburg.
My knowledge of this Is that I
designed and planned the new town
of Welkom.
In 1946 the late Sir Ernest Oppen-
heimer commissioned me to design
the new town of Welcom and his
instructions were that it should be not
only an example of Good New Town
Development in South Africa, but
throughout the world.
The late Sir Ernest was very keen
on the best conditions for all the
inhabitants and desired to establish
a permanent labour force for the gold
mines, living in the, town.
In his effort to do this he endeav¬
oured to establish family life in the
mining areas and the township for
as many as possible of the permanent
employees, instead of the normal
migrant labour, which necessitated the
men leaving their families.
Wm. O. Backhouse
Johannesburg, South Africa
YOUNG PEOPLE
OF ISRAEL
Sir,
In your issue on Youth, bearing the
symbol of International Co-operation
Year, 1965, I was surprised that no
mention was made of the young peo¬
ple of Israel. We have first-rate youth
hostels; the international youth work¬
ers' service is doing valuable work
in our country; our "higher technical
school" has a world-wide reputation;
we have youth clubs; our young people
have done all kinds of pioneering work
and, like youngsters in other countries,
they are fascinated by every aspect
of science. They deserved at least a
mention because of some special
characteristics. Our young people
are composed of disparate and
complex elements not easily combin¬
ed into a single whole. They are the
result of a distinctive mingling of
different peoples; each has inherited
characteristics of his country of origin,
but all are determined to attain a new
unity.
Mary Heimann
Kirjath Bialik, Israel
u
z
<
OL
<
U
Z
od
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
A NEW UNESCO STUDY which suggests
practical ways of improving methods and
materials for effective geography teaching
at the primary and secondary levels.
Prepared by the Commission on the Teaching
of Geography of the International Geo¬
graphical Union, the Source Book for
Geography Teaching deals with :
The importance and educational
value of geography and the nature and spirit of
geography teaching ;
Teaching techniques based on direct
and indirect observation;
Teaching material and the use of a
geography room.
A Longmans, Green- Unesco co-edition. Exclusive dis¬
tribution in the United Kingdom : Longmans, Green, Lon¬
don. 254 pp. illustrated.
16/- stg.; $3.50; 11.50 F. (paper)
21/- stg.; $4.50; 15 F. (hard-bound)
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See Ust
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
"Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
Wetenschappelijke Uitgevenj Belgiëlei 147, Antwerp.
For The Unesco Courier (1 40 FB) and art slides only : Louis
De Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00.
CANADA. Queen's Printer. Ottawa, Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir Chittampalan
Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 1 3/50).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1,Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CYPRUS.
"MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent display); Lahranicni
literatura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. E|nar
Munksgaard, Ltd., Prags Boulevard 47, Copenhagen S, (D.
Kr. 17). ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O.
Box 1 20, Addis Ababa (1 0/-). FINLAND. Akateemmen
Kirjakauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40).
FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy,
Pans-7-. CCP. 12598-48. (10 F.). - GERMANY. All
publications: R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse
145, Munich. 8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only)
Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd. Atlantis House Commercial Street, POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann. 28, rue du Stade,
Athens; Librairie Eleftheroudakis Nikkis 4, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 64, Nathan Road.
Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akademiai Konybrbnolt
Váci U. 22* Budapest V. Allami Konyvtersesztö
Vallalat, P.O. Box 240 Budapest ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd.. Nicol
Road, Ballard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson
House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16; Scindia
House, New Delhi. Indian National Commission for Co¬
operation with Unesco, Ministry of Educación, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs.7). IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop. Al-
Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2,Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. 4.(1 5/5). - ISRAEL
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumscein's Bookstores, 35 All¬
enby Road and 48 Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv(l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O.Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph I. Bahous& Co., Dar ul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 301 67, Nairobi (1 0/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. KUWAIT The Kuwait Bookshop
Co., Ltd., P. O. Box 2942, Kuwait LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia
(10/-). LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg (F.L. 140). MALAY¬
SIA. Federal Publications Ltd., Times House, River
Valley Road, Singapore, 9; Pudu Buildmg(3 rd
floor), 110, jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (1 5/-). MONACO. British
Library, 30, Bid. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Ni|hoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V., Willemstad. Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag), Wellington ; Government Book¬
shops: Auckland (P.O.Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104) (15/-). NIGERIA.
CM.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-).
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokh|ornec, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For Unesco Courier only: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litteraturieneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6, (17.50kr.).
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd.,
Unesco Publications House. P.O.Box 374 G. P.O. Lahore;
Showrooms : Urdu Bazar, Lahore, and 57-58 Murree
Highway, G /6-I, Islamabad. PHILIPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. SOUTHERN RHODESIA.
The Book Centre, and Educational Supply Co., Colonial Mu¬
tual Building, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publi¬
cations : A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12): SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse, Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1 211, Geneva 11, CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box1 45, Kampala (1 0/-). SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications : Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty) Ltd.,
Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only : Central
News Agency P.O. Box 103 3, Johannesbourg. (R1.-5 0).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38. rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent :
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff,* Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Cencer, 317 East 34th St, New York,
N.Y. 100161$ 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenskl
Kniiga Terazije, 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
	
m I
é(L¿-L
I
/i
^ß
© APN - V. Tarasevitch
NEW LOOK IN MATHEMATICS. Economic progress, in developed and developing coun¬
tries alike, demands more and more engineers, scientists and teachers, and thus depends
a great deal on the quality of school mathematics. Educationalists have been studying
traditional teaching methods, and now propose a new approach to mathematics (see p. 22).
]]>
</page>
</document>
