<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="033144eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART 0
 Rex Keating
SAINT ANNE FREED FROM THE SANDS
Painted 1, 200 years ago, this fresco portrait of Saint Anne was buried for eight
centuries beneath the sands of Sudanese Nubia. It is one of 169 paintings discovered
in the cathedral of Faras between 1962 and 1963 by a Polish archaeological mission
(see the Unesco Courier, December 1964). The rescue of these frescoes, just
before Faras disappeared beneath the waters of the Nile, was an outstanding
victory in Unesco's International Campaign to Safeguard the Monuments of
Nubia. The Saint Anne fresco is now in the Khartoum Museum (Sudan).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JULY-AUGUST 1966-19TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U. S. A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Ptac. e de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates : 15/-stg. ; $3. 00
(Canada) ; 10 French francs or equivalent ;
2 years : 27/-stg. ; 18 F. Single copies 1/6-stg. ;
30 cents ; 1 F.
*
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H. M. Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads"Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re-
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read-
ers'Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
*
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
Rev6 Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim EI Saw ! (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-Ichi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Illustrations : Betsy Bates
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
Coïirfe or
''w ; `''
, s 5.  d . ,'.' : ? ·r    v `' !'..,     e  : xe , : a, a       .
aks` : a"a,  :    ;' rx , ,  '` ; 3 c », k   , . :   ,
a `·z. ·  ® Eel  y,-` ,,. ' $g, s : '-ar", a, : a ,    :,,, x %'.
3 , -·  n a,"- ;. w`,.. '.,  `. :" ` ^razz, , a ,. r  v ; :  , ,.c  h a & ;'' , a :   y, . : 5· · :   . g ; ·' y r   ; ?, · ? °"`, < ;
x   ^£. c ; ,  :     ;  ;  ; s,   ,. s,
`,  ,.  »  '  a, ;,     1.   ,. "  r ;'... .- c.,  T.,. s·aa ? .,. d, 1, e «'..' ·,  ·, : :- ,  :.- ; a -,  ,., ; r. ,  `· e. :
 ·5. : ", a,,  ,  ; x, '. ; , n. : ,  . :-,  ups .  , ,.,  ; g . <i< :', a , b : a `..  : "§,  r"` ; ; ̀x, : arts., 3,'% «, :". · ;...  ; ', ,, , . `> s· Se ·
$d· & :  fur  ; ".
..,  s : : , ""  ; . ,.. .,  , · ;. :    y ;, x. ;,  k : ; " " : `, ; ,.,,  r  , :   ; a, .
i ·    ;, : x.  ; ,       <, . :  a. >'- ,   :, ,   · ;.   t ° <, .  :, ,
 :, ;"-T :   ;, ;"  . , ,  c . .. § ; ; , :
" c',  :  '' ; a"  W   `&'Y. .   : ·. ; .. u , 'E  'zZ,. :   . ;. :- $" , : ·'`' , s ^ ' ; . .  :  «,  ',.,  '
...  'a · : ,     cc', ; x,... _ ; x, s''. · °. ̀    ;  :'e,  W  .,, sssn,  '`,- ; ,.  ei  ' : ; F"  ;   ; ' : . . · . `.  ; ` :  `a :  ' ;  ; , 
 , , ` 
 :. a'",   <  a :
. F
'  ; a-
.  .  ,  a'z- a. Y
, i  *
, ., v
·
,   ·', · : ' ,.  `  `"··es.   ; ''x, . :.
·    : : 'r'5· -
, s, a ; : ̀ , , `, `c 
 a". . :  '`, :. , 
`'
c`a  e... .    ;.
" , ,  , '' `',,""' :  ,,, 
,, ..  c f Y , c"°  t ^
` _ :, k.. "', , ' ; . ^,. '`'  ;  '__ sF ?.   , s, r'c'''' ` '. ' s,.  '.'x.
a.-'a ,, ` :" `.  `· < E
b ;
 '   ;  `< ; `  ·",,  `, ;, ''  , , <' ; ,
 :   .'. ;   ; ;.   : ;  :  , : s. 
s ; ;  ; , ; °  ,  ; a,. .   ,, ;   ;  ' ; ", 
;"W ?. 
:  `8y s :, k  &-..."eE..     asp  %.'g® a `u : F `, ; ; '.s. ; ",'" ;  , `%  » ̀< `, a%..-· ; s   a`  :-.  : .'  s . ·, n  , a,. .,' x,, , ' :, ·"" : -  ? s, :  `c.- :.,. , ; : _.,  ;-, ;.·.` c, , ·.,. ax-r,
'`   a   `a  x  H    `z a   ·a cy"-e - ! ' $ : rF., FAS "'  ' ? 
'.  .. : ,    `. x  % e. :=;  s  ; _.,' .,  ··    ;, _ ' a, ̀. ,. `·.  `  
   , ; ,,   ,  
·  ''. , '$ 9= ` ,  °, , .  :  :  % r : . "'^ c` 
 . m'· ., w "..  , "  
L ,,  ;,.  e"a .'", 
y,. a.' <`m r,."`   ,   :    a3aa:, a ,,  " :  ;, ; g   : ;· ·x x ' " ; :.  "". ",,    :...., a   
.'``·i :. :    , W'a fur ;.. `n`'iF ; ". z's"`"'" , : : .  T" : ̀ "8`"k
F :, ;. : ;.' ,  ·y :. ', :' : f- a :,  %'. ,, ast, ,  , : :,  ", ; <  : a ,", `'·  .,     ;..  :  ^ . s . : ; -,, ; 1. · , 
a  . ·  ;  , s>% , <. ;,,,, ·, c, -`·. ;.,..  ; ; ., cw :, ̀  ;, a  ;  :  x.'. ;. `r, · · ; . ` ; v. " ;... : r ;  ;
 ; w Y.     ^'. ,  :.   ,,' : , . 3, > " : ̀. , ``
< v  ;.  ...  s
s', :  , -r y  y.
'  s 'f,.. r  < y :  ; ...  g.,.
   , i.
c      :  s
T  < ^a,    a :
,  c . '`  ; ·
x
. ,. c. --.  
wf  ; -, '`
x
x-`  `3
 <  
"u^. "r'
, : a   
   ;
a
. r^' « ̂
 '.
,    '`  <, 9  v3f', :
_ . . '. ..
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S
20
YEARS
1fH ! S year, as Unesco prepares tomark its twentieth annive sary next
November fourth, plans are already under way
for a frank and uninhibited reappraisal of the
work that has been accomplished in the short
span of this Organization's existence.
Let me indicate first in what light Unesco
appears to me as an instrument of international
co-operation. While for many years Unesco's
concept of co-operation was that of intellectual
co-operation, today it is both operational as
well as intellectual.
By intellectual co-operation I mean the encour-
agement and organization on a world scale of
4 the pursuit, examination and interpretation of
knowledge as well as the exchange of ideas
and mutual experiences. This is being done
diligently and without fanfare by the specialist,
unnoticed usually by the public at large, and
aims principally at promoting the advance of all
branches of intellectual endeavour.
To the scientists, artists and scholars of this
world, then, must go our thanks for the changes
man has brought about through his creative
spirit and his reasoning, and Unesco is proud
of the efforts it has been able to make to help
these scientists and scholars and to bring
them closer together. Thanks to them the story
of our species is slowly ceasing to be that of
man submitting passively to his fate and is
becoming one of a rapid march of triumph
toward freedom and liberation and responsi-
bility. The practice of intellectual co-operation
is becoming more widespread every day as its
import and scope are being nurtured and enrich-
ed, and this is fashioning the understructure
of what we may well call the first true world
civilization.
Quite another matter are Unesco's opera-
tional activities in aid of development. This is
a dual type-action-on the one hand it is inter-
national in purpose, and the means and methods
used ; on the other it is national as regards
execution and at least in the immediate objec-
tives pursued. In this sense it is a unique
formula, and the most typical, and I daresay,
the most effective contribution that the special-
ized, technical agencies of the U. N. such as
Unesco are now making to development.
It must be admitted that the founders of
Unesco could not then foresee an undertaking
of such scope, and that when Unesco did ulti-
mately adopt operational assistance as a
normal and indeed main method of work this
was due much more to the fact that it was a
member of the United Nations family than to its
own exclusive initiative.
If since 1950 operational assistance has
become a systematic part of the Unesco pro-
gramme, the credit belong's to the U. N. Expan-
ded Programme of Technical Assistance as
well as to the U. N. Special Fund which since
1960 has placed at Unesco's disposal vast addi-
tional funds, so that the total of these resources
now accounts for a predominant part of Unes-
co's overall budget. I should like to pay my
tribute to those responsible for conceiving and
directing these two great inter-organizationa)
enterprises which this year have been com-
bined into one body, called the United Nations
Development Programme. To them Unesco
owes a new dimension in its work.
The expansion of Unesco's operational activ-
ities, occurring as it did simultaneously with
the entry into Unesco of many newly indepen-
dent states, mainly from Africa, has resulted in
such a profound change in the programme and
structure of Unesco since 1960 that the term
"mutation"has been used to describe it.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Perhaps the expression"conversion to devel-
opment"would be more descriptive.
At present operational assistance for devel-
opment represents about two-thirds of Unesco's
total resources, which shows the high priority
that Unesco accords to aid for the developing
nations and the degree of its concrete action in
this respect.
I have no doubt that the day will come when
in speaking of economic development we will
think of it more in terms of its cultural aspects.
It has been said time and again that the instru-
ment and final purport of development was
man, but perhaps the deep implications of this
statement have not always been fully recog-
nized. It signifies that the cultural values a
people or a nation hold most dear and consider
their raison d'etre ultimately will determine
what they consider possible to achieve and
what they consider they ought to achieve for
their own development.
The technocrats-it makes no difference
whether they are local technocrats or foreign
technocrats-who are often the masters in
these matters, and who delight in the cold
technology and the impersonal machines they
import from abroad, have learned this to their
great chagrin-and of course to the chagrin of
those they believed they were hel, ping without
knowing or understanding them. Here the
social sciences have a paramount role to play
particularly in the earlier planning stages of
development, the importance of which we are
often inclined to underestimate.
W HAT precisely do we mean when weWW sa  that a community is u derdevel-
oped ? I would not hesitate to say that it was
one which had not acceded in its thinking and
habits to the civilization of science and techno-
logy which is the pattern and driving force of
human progress today. In other words, that a
country is developed to the degree that its
science and technology have ceased to be a
magic potion imported from abroad and have
become a living, integrated part of its culture.
Unesco considers the establishment of
science within the nation itself of the utmost
importance because it is convinced that this,
more than the mere transfer of knowledge, is
the only real way to create the basic prerequi-
sites for a nation's development. But it should
be clear that what we are actually dealing with
here is not just a question of proper organiza-
tion but of social change, or what the social
scientist calls"acculturation". Development
is science become part of the cultural fibre.
These are the chief characteristics, in my
view, of the technical action Unesco is carrying
out in the two closely integrated fields of
intellectual co-operation and operational co-
operation or assistance.
And yet they are not the main features of
Unesco's work. Unesco's ultimate objective is
not simply technical ; it is essentially and funda-
mentally ethical or moral in nature. Unesco is
not interested merely in the advancement of
education, science and culture per se, no matter
how great their intrinsic worth may be, for in the
light of Unesco's Constitution they are no more
than a means and a way. The aim of Unesco is
the aim of the whole family of the United
Nations, namely, peace. But a peace construed
and pursued in a unique fashion, which govern-
ments had never before had the courage-one
is tempted to say the candour-to proclaim
openly as the rule for their concerted action.
j t NESCO was founded on the beliefthat it is man in his own freedom
who ultimately decides the course of history
and chooses between peace and war ("wars
begin in the minds of men"says the Preamble
to the Unesco Constitution) and consequently
there can be no true peace unless there is a
consensus of the mind for an order which the
mind esteems.
What is that order ? It is human dignity, which
is expressed and particularized in the various
human rights and whose reign is called social
justice and love, or at the very least tolerance
in the hearts of men. That is why the founders
of Unesco proclaimed that"it is in the minds
of men that the defences of peace must be
constructed."
Education, science and culture are the do-
mains that form and inspire the mind. Unesco's
mission, and the ultimate reason for its
existence, lies in using these domains-I
employ the word"use"advisedly-to establish
in the very depths of the consciousness of indiv-
iduals and peoples those conditions of justice
and tolerance which in the fina ! analysis govern
freedom or slavery, life or death...
For Unesco, therefore, both the technical
and the ethical aspects of its work are inescap-
ably bound together, and Unesco's existence
is predicated on the continuance of this bond.
That is why all those who have had the honour
to serve Unesco are p, y aware, since they
have experienced it in their own lives, that
Unesco is not only an institution at the service
of its member states but an attitude of mind
and a voice directed at the conscience of every
mar. 5
Rene Maheu,
Director-General of Unesco
Prom an address to the e N. Economic and Social Council, delivered
in Geneva on July 7, 1966.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
'since wars begin in the minds of men,
it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be constructed'
- Constitution of the United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
The Governments of the States Par-That a peace based exclusively upon the
ties to this Constitution on behalf political and economic arrangements
of their peoples declare : of governments would not be a peace
which could secure the unanimous,
lasting and sincere support of the
people. : of the world, and that thethat since wars begin in the minds of peace must ther fore be founded, if
men, it is m the minds of men that it is not to fail, upon the intelkctual
the defences of peace must be cons-and mora. l solidarity of mankind.
tructed ;
., For these reasons, the StatesPartie$ toThat ignorance of each other's ways and thins C.. b I'., fì II
I. h b t IS onstItUtIon, e IevIng In uIres as even a common clause,,.,
h h t thh't f k'd and equal opportunItIes for educationt rug you e.. ITS Orgy 0 mao Ion.'......,,
,..'four wall, In the unrestncted pursUIt ofof that suspicion and mistrust between b't't th d'th f
o ec Live r ain In e reethe peoples of the world trough,'
which their d'f have II exchange of ideas and knowledge, arew TIC tell I.. erences r a tor.
ft b k't agreed and determined to developo yen rio y n In 0 wan..and to increase the m ans of commu-
nication between their peoples and to
That the great and terrible war which employ these means for the purposes
has now ended was a war made of mutual understanding and a truer
possible by the denial ofthedemocra-and more perfect knowledge of each
tic principles of the dignity, equality other's lives ;
and mutual respect of men, and by
the propagation, in their place, In consequence whereof they do here-
through ignorance and prejudice, of'by create the United Nations Educa-
the doctnne of the inequality of men tonal. Scientific and Cultural Organi-
and races ; zation for the purpose of advancing,
through the educational and scientific
That the wide diffusion of culture, and and cultural relations of the peoples
the education of humanity for justice of the world, the objectives of inter-
and liberty and peace are indispens-national peace and of the common
able to the dignity of man and consti-welfare of mankind for which the
tute a sacred duty which all the United Nations Organization was
nations must fulfil in a spirit of established and which its Charter
mutual assistance and concern ; proclaims.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
While London was still being battered by the
air raids of World War II (right), ministers of
education of the Allied Governments met there
in 1942, to study common problems of educa-
tion. In November 1945, shortly after the war
ended, a meeting in London attended by rep-
resentatives of 44 countries drew up the C. ons-
titution of Unesco. On November 4, 1946, fol-
lowing its acceptance by 20 states, this docu-
ment became the official birth certificate of
Unesco. Below we reproduce the Preamble and
Article I of the Constitution. Lower right,
today, in Unesco's 20th anniversary year,
young people visit its headquarters in Paris.
Photo &commat; Keystone
Photo Unesco-Holmquist
PARTICLE I.
the purpose of the Organization is to contribute to peace
and security by promoting collaboration among the nations
thorough education, science and culture in order to further
universal respect for justice, for the rule of law and for the
human rights and fundamental freedoms which are affirmed
for the peoples of the world, without distinction of race,
sex, language. Qr religiofl by the Charter of the Ut3ited Nations.
2 To realize this purpose the Organization will :
a. Collaborate in the work of advancing the mutual know-
ledge and nderstanding of peoples, through all means
of mass communication and to that end recommend such
international agreements as may be necessary to promote
the free flow of ideas by word and image ;
b. Give fresh impuise to popular education and to the spread
of culture :
by collaborating with Members, at their request, in the
development of educational activities ;
by instituting collaboration among the nations to advance
the ideal of equality of educational opportunity without
regard to race, sex or any distinctions, economic or social ;
by suggesting educational methods best suited to prepare
the children of the world for the responsibilities of free-
dom ;
c. Maintain, increase and diffuse knowledge :
by assuring the conservation and protection of the world's
inheritance of books, works of art and monuments of
history and science, and recommending to the nations
concerned the necessary international conventions ;
by encouraging co-operation among the nations in all
branches of intellectual activity, including the international
exchange of persons active in the fields of education,
science and culture and the exchange of publications, objects
of artistic and scientific interest and other materials of
information ; by initiating methods of international co-
operation calculate to give the people of a ! !' countries
access to the printed and published materials produced by
any of them.
with a view to preserving the independence, integrity and
fruitful diversity of the cultures and educational systems of
she States members of this Organization, the Organization is
prohibited from intervening in matters which are essentially
within their domestic jurisdiction.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
by Lord Ritchie-Calder
THE generation which hasgrown up in the past
twenty years is unique. Nothing like
it has ever existed in the history of
mankind. Every teenager and every
twenty-year old everywhere has, in his
or her bones, radio-strontium, a man-
made element which did not exist
before 1945. Its presence, the result
of fall-out from atmospheric bomb
tests (now suspended), may be medi-
cally unimportant but it is the brand-
mark of The Atomic Age. For many,
their birth certificates were registered
by computers. For some, their zodia-
cal sign was Sputnik. But their future
was not predicted by astrologers ; it
was predicated by scientists.
This is a generation which was born
into The Atomic Age, programmed into
The Cybernetic Age, rocketed into The
Space Age and stands poised on the
threshold of The DNA Age. They
take for granted scientific and techno-
logical advances about which the
Founder Fathers of the United Nations,
legislating for the future, knew nothing.
When they signed the Charter at San
Francisco in June 1945 only three
people-Truman, Attlee and Eden-
knew (and each imperfectly) about the
impending release of nuclear energy.
Which shows how wise were we
who put the"S"into Unesco. It
nearly was not there. The Committee
LORD RITCHIE-CALDER has been pro-
fessor of international relations at the
University of Edinburgh since 1961. He
has travelled over most of the world on
missions for the U. N. and its specialized
agencies, and took part in the two U. N.
Conferences on the Peaceful Uses of
Atomic Energy (1955 and 1958). Professor
Calder was consultant editor for the eight
volumes produced from the proceedings
of the U. N. Conference on Science and
Technology (1963) and prepared the com-
prehensive volume on the conference,. world of Opportunity."He is the author
of many books on science for which he
was awarded the Kalinga Prize for science
writing (1961). In the honours list of
lunge 11, 1966, Professor Calder was given
a life peerage by Her Majesty Queen
Elizabeth II.
of Allied Ministers of Education who,
in wartime London, recognized the
necessity for such a specialized
agency, conceived it as UNECO-the
United Nations Educational and Cultur-
al Organization. One recalls the argu-
ments : the pedagogues regarded
science as something which, read in
textbooks or taught in class, belonged
to education and the aesthetes re-
garded science as something which,
with the grace and patina of time,
might qualify as culture. There were
others who argued that science was
the pace-maker for both education and
culture.
In view of the later agonizing about
"The Two Cultures"it is worthwhile
remembering that the person who ac-
tively and successfully promoted the
"S"was the distinguished poet, Archi-
bald MacLeish, and that the first Direc-
tor-Genera !, Juhan Huxiey, was a
scientist.
One must not blame those who
doubted. What we now recognize as
the Scientific and Technological Revo-
lution was not as self-evident, even in
terms of destructiveness of war, as it
is today. But we had confirmation,
with full justification of the"S", by the
time of the first General Conference in
1946.
The Atomic Age had been born with
count-down precision at 5 : 30 a. m. on
Monday, July 16, 1945, in the desert
of New Mexico and the realization, for
the world's people, came with appal-
ling force with the destruction of
Hiroshima and Nagasaki. Nuclear
energy, Man's greatest discovery
since his mastery of fire, exploded
with cataclysmic violence.
In tntercepting the flying bombs, the
anti-aircraft batteries on the English
coast were already fitted with predic-
tors, which, as computors, with feed-
back, were the precursors of the elec-
tronic marvels of The Cybernetic Age.
Londoners, bombarded with V-2's,
were already aware of The Rocket Age
which was to lead to The Space Age.
But, to the post-1945 generation,
we are like The Dawn Men-practi-
cally pre-historicl They are not the
least surprised when an astronaut
steps out of a space capsule travelling
at 17, 500 miles an hour and ambles
across the continent of America in
20 minutes or round the globe in
90 minutes. They accept, without
perplexity, that a man-made piece of
hardware can circumnavigate Planet
Number 3, the Earth, sixteen times a
day ; that probes can reach out to
Mars or Venus or"soft-land"on the
moon and they judge them less by
what they report back than by what
they fail to do. Communications
satellites, mirroring events on the far
side of the world, impress them less
than the first automatic telephone ex-
change did my generation. And why
not ? They assume that you ask the
scientist and hire the technologist and
they will produce anything you want.
The youth of today recognizes, what
is not yet plain to his elders, that the
scientist has miniaturized his planet.
No place on earth is more than a few
hours distant by jet-propulsion ; no
place on earth is more than a few
minutes away by rocket-propulsion ;
and no place on earth is more than
split seconds away by radio. In a
single generation, man has unlocked
the secret of matter and released it as
CONTINUED ON PAGE 11
The prodigious advance of science
in the past 20 years has revealed
a universe of totally new dimensions.
Scientific triumphs in every field,
from atomic research to the
expiration of outer space, have
advanced the frontiers of human
knowledge. In these 20 years
Unesco has promoted scientific
progress and the application of its
benefits to economic and social
development. It has included in
its programme the study of problems
in major fields such as hydrology,
biology, oceanography, geophysics
and ecology as well as aid to
the underprivileged nations.
Right, giant blades of a turbine
used for generating electricify.
Photo @ N. Max ! mov-APN
TWO DECADES
IN THE WORLD
St ! BMSSMNMSTm
! Mt) M M ! < ! M N K t Bt iNt P. < !  MMt)  NB BMN) .
SCIENCE
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
In launching the International Hydrological Decade in 1965, Unesco has called for global action to meet Photo C Pau ! Amasy. Paris
one of the great threats confronting the multiplying world population-lack of water, and also its abuse.
This vast programme of hydrological studies will include a world-wide stocktaking of water
resources. Under its Major Project for Arid Zone Research (1957-1962), Unesco has already
.-organized systematic studies of areas covering one-third of the earth's land surface, in over
1 0 a score of scientific fields, including hydrology, new energy resources such as solar and wind
energy, ecology and climatology. It has also helped to set up desert research institutes (in Israel,
Turkey, India, U. A. R. and Pakistan, for instance) whose aim is the reconquest of arid lands. Here,
a technician uses laboratory models to study water flow problems.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
TWO DECADES OF SCIENCE (Continued)
Their ivory tower toppled with Hiroshima
nuclear energy. He has burst the
gravitational fences of his planet and
adventured into space and in the
study of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA)
and molecular biology is probing the
secrets of life with implications as
great as, or greater than, either the
atom or space. By radio-astronomy,
he is reaching out to the limits of the
universe and recording the broadcast
signals of cosmic events of thousands
of millions of years ago.
Pierre Auger, Director of the Natu-
ral Sciences Department of Unesco
during the scientifically eruptive years
of the 1950s, coined a phrase (Current
Trends in Scientific Research, Unesco
1961) which has become overworked
but which is limpid truth :"Of all the
scientists and research workers who
have existed since the beginning of
Homo sapiens, ninety per cent are
a ! ive today."
The other ten per cent have their
niches in the Gallery of Time which
stretches back to the mastery of fire,
perhaps 100, 000 years ago. This is
another way of saying that the bulk of
measurable achievements of science
belongs to the past fifty and, prepon-
derantly, to the past twenty years.
Or as it was put by an enthusiastic
young physicist,"Today, we are privi-
leged to sit side by side with the
giants on whose shoulders we stand."
This acrobatic feat and this juggling
with Time is like saying that Harvey
had discoursed with Aristotle ; that
Einstein had exchanged reprints with
Newton ; that Watt had met Archimedes
at a seminar ; or that Pasteur, before
taking his broth up into the bacteria-
free Alps, had had a word with Rhases,
the Lute Player, who, in A. D. 900 hung
pieces of fresh meat around Baghdad
and where the meat putrefied least
built the Caliph's hospital.
PUT it another way : Thinkof H. G. Wells, the cente -
ary of whose birth we are celebrating
this year. Writers of modern science
fiction will tell you that they have to
escape into remote fantasy because
otherwise they will find their imaginative
projections overtaken on the news
pages of the Late Night Special. Wells,
a trained scientist, would take a piece
of abstruse research and confidently
prophesy its fulfilment. This is what he
did with a scientific paper by Frederick
Soddy which no more than hinted at
the release of nuclear energy from the
splitting of the atom and, in The World
Set Free, Wells fictionalized it, pre-
dicting with uncanny accuracy the arti-
ficial splitting of the atom twenty years
ahead.
That was comparatively short-range
forecasting but even Wells would not
have been rash enough, even in fiction,
to foretell what followed the discovery
of uranium fission by Hahn and Strass-
man in 1938. Immediately the signif-
icance of chain-reaction was under-
stood. By the spring of 1940 Peierls
and Frisch had sent to the British
MAUD Committee the specification for
an atom bomb and by 1945, at the
expense of $2, 000, 000, 000, the Man-
hattan Project, by mobilizing the scien-
tists of many nationalities and the vast
technological potential of the United
States, had produced it. Science had
become a. crash programme"and the
Big Machines had replaced the"string
and sealing wax"laboratories.
The atom bomb has had as pro-
found an effect on science as it has
had on history. Whereas, in the past,
the scientists had been entitled to say
that they had made discoveries and
that others had perverted them into
weapons of destruction, in this case the
scientists themselves had conceived a
fundamental advance as a bomb, a
thousand times (and later, with the
H-bomb, a million times) more power-
ful than existing explosives.
It was the scientists, including Ein-
stein, the pacifist, who, with some diffi-
culty, persuaded the politicians and
generals that the bomb should be
made. After Hiroshima and Nagasaki
this produced a conscience-crisis
among the scientists. Their ivory
towers had been shattered by the blast
and they felt a great weight of social
responsibility. They could no longer
detach themselves from politics in the
widest sense.
In 1946 Einstein became chairman of
the Emergency Committee of Atomic
Scientists at Princeton, New Jersey,
and issued a personal statement :
"Science has brought forth this dan-
ger, but the real problem is in the
minds and hearts of men. We will not
change the hearts of other men by
mechanism, but by changing our hearts
and speaking bravely.
"We must be generous in giving to
the world the knowledge that we have
of the forces of nature, after establish-
ing safeguards against abuse.
"We must be not merely willing but
actively eager to submit ourselves to
binding authority necessary for world
security.
"We must realize that we cannot
simultaneously plan for war and peace.
"When we are clear in heart and
mind-only then shall we find courage
to surmount the fear which haunts the
world."
Physicists who had been involved
in the evolution of the bomb formed
themselves into Atomic Scientists
Associations in Britain and in America
and went into the market place to
inform the public about the military
and political consequences, about
radiation hazards and about the
peaceful uses. This ultimately found
its expression in a new kind of
"learned society,"the Pugwash
Conference. The first conference in
1957 brought together in the village of
Pugwash, Nova Scotia, the eminent
scientists of East and West. And the
movement has continued-a coming-
together, not of decision-makers but of
scientists who can influence those
who make decisions.
t N 1955, and again in 1958,t we had the United Nations
Conferences on the Peaceful Uses of
Atomic Energy at Geneva. The first
was one of the most exhilarating occa-
sions in the history of science because
it brought together scientists who, for
fifteen years, had been cut off from
their colleagues by the barbed-wire
fences of military security. Immediately,
to the dismay of those who had to try
to maintain secrecy, the Uranium Cur-
tain, as well as the Iron Curtain, col-
lapsed.
There was a disclosure, and a shar-
ing, of fundamental knowledge and, as
the late Homi J. Bhabha, the Indian
President of the Conference, said,
*Know ! edge once given can never be
taken away."What was revealed was
not the know-how of making the bomb
but the know-why of nuclear physics.
It was summed up by the remark of
Dr. E. T. Hughes who had been pre-
siding over a session on the cross-
section of the nucleus (supposed to be
the most jealously guarded secret) at
which scientists of seven different
groups, not only within the nuclear
powers but in countries like Portugal,
had disclosed their findings. These
had been plotted on a graph and
the plots were indistinguishable.
Dr. Hughes came jubilantly into a
ptenary meeting, unrolled the graph
like a scroll and said,"This should be
the emblem of this Conference. It
shows, thank heavens, that the nucleus
is the same on both sides of the Iron
Curtain."
The high promises of foot-loose,
peaceful energy, which was to solve
the industrial problems of the under-
developed countries (we call them"de-
veloping"now) have not yet been ful-
filled. Those cheap nuclear reactors
for industrial purposes which seemed
almost at the"wrap it up and take it
away"stage in 1955 have not been
forthcoming. Electric power from the
atom-yes, for those who can afford
huge generating stations and have a 11
grid system, but not the packaged
reactors for poor countries. Nor are
we yet in sight of Bhabha's vision of
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
TWO DECADES OF SCIENCE (continued)
Discoveries that changed the face of the world
thermo-nuclear energy-putting the
H-bomb into civilian dungarees with, in
his phrase,"as much energy as there
is deuterium in the Seven Seas."In
other words, limitless.
Out of such conferences came the
"open house"nuclear research cen-
tres-Brookhaven in the U. S. A., Dubna
in the U. S. S. R. and C. E. R. N , the Cen-
tre for European Nuclear Research, a
co-operative of European govern-
ments which Unesco helped to initiate,
in Switzerland. The study of fun. da-
mental particles-the structure of the
nucleus-means massive machines,
enormously expensive, like the one
which is about to be built in America
at a cost of $340, 000, 000. Small-and
even big-countries cannot afford to
have them of their own but they can
contribute to the cost and have use
of the facilities.
The encouragement of such interna-
tional enterprises has been one of the
principal functions of, Unesco since
1946 when, instead of the billion dollar
budget it should have had, we, the
delegates, gave it the wishful words
"stimulate"and"facilitate."And that,
particularly in science, is what the
organization has done eminently well.
Science, of course, is traditionally a
commonwealth. International co-oper-
ation between individuals, national
learned societies and the congresses
of the various disciplines existed but
had been interrupted by the war. The
guiding body is ICSU-the Internation-
al Council of Scientific Unions. It
had been more or less"moth-balled"
during the war when the free-trade in
ideas was suspended. It needed"facil-
itating."Unesco could not afford fuel
oil but it could provide lubricating oil.
It enabled ICSU to get moving again
and Unesco's"stimulation"consisted
of encouraging the formation of further
unions and congresses for any mis-
sing discipline, and the effect was
immediate.
AFTER the first World Warintransigence and discrim-
ination had prevented scientific
congresses from getting together for
over six years. After the Second
Wold War, with Unesco's help, they
were resumed within six months and
the man-to-man exchanges and the
cross-fertilization of ideas was one of
the factors in the acceleration of scien-
tific progress.
The outstanding achievement of the
Unesco-ICSU combination was the
International Geophysical Year, 1957-
58. This was the period of maximum
12 sunspot activity, which provided theoccasi n for a systematic study of
Planet Earth, its atmospheric envelope
and of the cosmic influences upon it.
Over 70 nations participated and the
Lug. Y. Committee was responsible for
the operation of more than 2, 500 major
scientific stations as well as thousands
more temporary stations and observa-
tion posts involving over 10, 000 scien-
tists and technicians as well as ama-
teurs and volunteers. It embraced all
the sciences, and organizations con-
cerned with man's physical world and
its physical environment. The aggre-
gation of data was so enormous that it
will take a generation of scientists
- even with computers-to work it all
out. It is estimated that). G. Y cost
$500, 000, 000 but what Unesco could
afford served as the catalyst.
Incidentally, the fantastic program-
mes of space research now running
at probably $8, 000, 000, 000 a year be-
gan modest ! y in LG. Y. Rockets had
been used for direct exploration of the
atmosphere up to 250 miles and sev-
eral hundred rockets were fired during
LG. Y. by Australia, Canada, France,
Great Britain, Japan, the United States
and the Soviet Union.
Data about pressures, temperatures
and density of the atmosphere, par-
ticles, radiations and fields were tele-
metered back to earth during the
rocket life-span of a few minutes. To
overcome these limitations the J. G. Y.
included satellite vehicles in the pro-
gramme and the U. S. A. and the
U. S. S. R. agreed to produce them. In
orbit, they were to make continuing
observation, inwards and outwards.
It was almost taken for granted that
the U. S. A. with its enormous techno-
logical potential would mount the first
one, but the whole world was taken
by surprise when Sputnik I, the Soviet
satellite, was launched on October 4,
1957, into an orbit from 64. 3 deg. N. to
64. 3 deg. S. It weighed 184 Ibs. as
against the 30 Ibs. of the U. S. satellite
which was not launched until three and
a half months later.
Alas, for the innocent intentions of
Lug. Y. ! The weight and the orbit
showed that the U. S. S. R. had power-
ful rockets, and to spare. This led
to loud cries about the"missile gap."
To close this alleged gap and to try to
recover the lost prestige the U. S.
embarked on a massive space pro-
gramme.
The Soviet Union followed suit and
we have had intense space competi-
tion ever since.
Unesco was born into The Cyber-
netic Age as well. Nuclear physics
had exploded. Solid state physics
erupted. The whole character of
communications and the electronics of
industrial processes were changed by
semi-conductors and transistors which
led to miniaturization of what would
otherwise have been massive batteries
of vacuum valves. The computer in
the simple sense of a calculating
machine became a misnomer. Apart
from doing impossible sums at incred-
ible speeds, the computer began,
with greater than human efficiency, to
reproduce. the logical faculties of the
brain and, through the ingenious sys-
tems of cybernetic feedback, (automa-
tic self adjustment) to control ma-
chine processes.
With all the combinations-an infal-
lible memory, an unswerving logic,
photo-electric cells more observant
and more tireless than the human eye,
microphones more sensitive than
the human ear and electric nerve-end-
ings more sensitive than the most
skilled human touch-automation is
replacing acquired experience. As the
U. S. Secretary of Labour, Willard
Wirtz, has pointed out,"The machine
now has the equivalent abilities and
skills of a student with a high school
diploma."
COMPUTERS can designcomputers and control the
machines that make computers and
embody in successive generations of
computers the experience of ancestral
computers.
At the Unesco Conference of Inform-
ation Processing in 1959 at which
nearly 2, 000 electronic experts were
gathered, I said to one of the greatest
of them,"But you still cannot pro-
duce the electronic equivalent of the
human brain with its 15, 000, 000, 000
brain cells and their neuronic circuits".
His reply (verbatim) was"Don't be
silly. I could put your brain with its
cells and circuits on a plate five inches
by six". And he went on to explain
that if you stacked such plates like a
pack of cards and linked them up
one could store, in a space no bigger
than a cigar box, all the information in
all the libraries in all the world.
The only consolation he could offer
was that they knew how to put in
the information but did not yet know
how to get it out ! This input process
depends on cryogenics or ultra-deep
freeze. At temperatures near abso-
lute zero certain metals lose all elec-
trical resistance so filaments of them
can be so fine that by comparison a
spider's web would look like the gir-
ders of Sydney Harbour Bridge, and
"valves"could be no bigger than a
brain cell. By reducing a printed
circuit of the 15, 000, 000, 000 cells to
the dimensions of an electron-micro-
scopic photograph it is possible to do
what he claimed.
Now, concurrent with The Atomic
Age, The Cybernetic Age and The
Space Age, we have The DNA Age.
The"life sciences"are now claiming
attention and appropriations on a scale
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
once reserved to the physical scien-
ces. Molecular biology is now all
the vogue. With the discovery of the
structure of deoxyribonucleic acid
(DNA) and ribonucleic acid (RNA), the
basic chemicals of the living cell, we
have the clue to the secret of life.
In the arrangement of the atoms
in the molecules of DNA and RNA is
the"information code"which"pro-
grammes"not only the nature and
behaviour of the cells in the body
but determines the hereditary traits
passed on from one generation to
the next. It is predictable that we
shall be able to change, by man's
prescriptions, the nature of living pro-
cesses and of posterity.
Students of the Karachi Polytechnic Institute (Pakistan) at work in the
Civil Engineering Department whose equipment was supplied by
Unesco. To overcome a serious shortage of scientists and technicians,
countries of Asia, Africa and Latin America are expanding and improving
teaching facilities in the basic sciences, a prerequisite of economic and
social development. Unesco has helped its member states to set up
science institutes, research laboratories and centres for the design and
construction of scientific equipment. Today Unesco aids nearly
50 projects for setting up and operating technological and
professional training institutes in some 30 countries.
Photo Unesco-Paul Almasy, Paris
Hundreds of brilliant scientists are
now ingeniously employed in molecu-
lar biology but what is needed are
people to sit down and think what we
are going to do with the secret of
life when we get it. What we first
did with the secret of matter-nuclear
energy-is not encouraging.
All this is spectacular and awe-
inspiring proof of Man's unlimited
ingenuity. But how, in Unesco's terms
of reference which include, not only
the acquisition of knowledge, but the
use of that knowledge, can we apply
science to the betterment of the condi-
tions of mankind ?
The humanitarian sciences have also
had spectacular results. Just as we
can date the atomic explosion as July
1945 so we might date the population
explosion as February 1935. Then
a desperate father, Dr. Domagk, inject-
ed a red dye, the drug Prontosil, into
the veins of his daughter, Hildegarde.
She had generalized septicaemia and
her case seemed hopeless. She
recovered.
That was the first of the sulpha
drugs which not only had an intrinsic
value but reminded the medical pro-
fession and medical science of what
Ehrlich had demonstrated in 1911,
when he showed that it was possible,
with salvasan, to kill specific germs
within the human body. Until then any
antiseptic which could destroy germs
in open wounds was fatal if ingested.
With this reminder from the sulpha
drugs, Fleming's penicillin (1928) was
rediscovered and perfected, as the
drug we now know, by Chain and
Florey, who recognized that it could
inhibit germs within the human body.
More lives have since been saved by
penicillin and its kindred antibiotics
than have been lost in all the wars
of all human history.
Then, with D. D. T. we gained the
means of controlling the insect-carriers
of diseases such as malaria.
By the combination, and refinement,
of such means it has been possible to
reduce the mortality from mass infec-
tions, to save mothers in childbirth to
have more chidren ; to save infants
and toddlers to grow up, to marry and
to multiply ; and to extend the span
of life. Today, as a result of science
there are 170, 000 more mouths to be
fed every day.
It has taken mankind, (if we date
from the hominids) a million years
to reach the present figure of
3, 250, 000, 000 ; it will, on present trends,
take thirty years to double that. Some-
how death control has to be offset
by the control of reproduction. But
at the same time we have to feed a
population of which already two-thirds
are underfed and we have to provide
for those who are still to come.
If science could be as imaginative
and resourceful in providing for the 13
needs of human beings as in its great
physical achievements the imminent
future would not seem so forbidding.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
TWO DECADES OF SCIENCE (continued)
At the United Nations Conference
on Science and Technology in Geneva
in 1963 it was abundantly clear that
even if we only applied what we al-
ready knew the needs of mankind
could be met. It is not a question of
knowledge ; it is a question of intention.
Unesco, concerned with knowledge
and research has addressed itself to
these long term problems. Its major
project of a few years ago, The Arid
Zone Project, brought together some
27 disciplines to study the nature of
deserts and their potential for devel-
opment. By inter-relating specialist
knowledge, it enthused the scientists
who took part into a new breed of
"desert experts". Botanists became
professional about hydrology. Geo-
physicists became fascinated by the
peculiarities of desert plants. And so
on. The results were hovel and im-
pressive and, if applied, hopeful-life
the desert agriculture promoted by
the discovery of great aquifers beneath
the Sahara and the Egyptian deserts.
The Hydrological Decade initiated by ;
Unesco deals with one of the great
threats confronting the multiplying
population, the lack of water in many
places and the abuse of water in
others. Nothing so reveals the ignor-
ance, the recklessness and setfish-
ness even of nations abounding in
science as the squandering of this
vital resource.
Out of, and beyond, the LG. Y. came 
the Indian Ocean Project, sponsored
by Unesco and combining, again, the
research efforts of many countries in
the study of one of the most interest-
ing areas of the world-interesting not
only to meteorologists and ocean-
ographers but to marine biologists.
From the close examination of such
seas we could begin to see how the
oceans, which cover seven-tenths of
the earth's surface, could be develop-
ed to help to feed the multiplying mil-
) ions.
And then there is the International
Biological Programme, which, in its
way, is doing what the LG. Y. did about
the earth and its physical environment.
Lob. P., by systematic studies extending
over nine years, will examine the
biosphere, the"life"part of our world.
The character of science and of its
achievements has changed, during the
lifetime of Unesco and Unesco has, in
its own structure, adapted itself to
the change. To the concern for scien-
tific knowledge and for the advance-
ment of science itself, has been added
an active promotion of the application
of science, and of technology. To the
"know-why"has been added the"know-how", with all its imperative
values for countries seeking develop-
ment.
For what shall it profit man to know
all about everything-the universe, the
14 core of the earth, the secret of matter'and the secret of life-if his species
hungers and thirsts and is denied
human dignity.
Oceanography, which has become a major field of international scientific
co-operation in the past 15 years, offers a striking example of what
Unesco can do, despite its limited budget, to achieve impressive results
through direction and co-ordination. In 1960, Unesco established the Intergovernmental
Oceanographic Commission and the Unesco Office of Oceanography. The
Ofnce co-ordinates intemational ocean research enterprises valued at
some $15 million in an average year. Its outstanding achievements include : the
Indian Ocean Expedition (1959-1965), Tropical Atlantic Expedition (1963-1964)
and the study of the Kuroshio Current (the Gulf Stream of the Pacific) in t965. Within
a few years over 250 scientific cruises have been made in various parts of the
giobe. Above, a Soviet atomic-powered ice-breaker on an expedition in the Arctic Ocean.
NEW
OUTPOSTS
OF
SCIENCE
by Evgueni Fedorov
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
HE extraordinary advancet) of science and technology
in the past 20 years astounds us all.
Spectacular discoveries come crowd-
ing one after the other, and almost
as swiftly are put to practical use.
Many people who can still remember
the time when a motor car was a
rare spectacle already regard the
launching of satellites and spacecraft
as an everyday affair. And no doubt
they will live to see astronauts mak-
ing round trips to the moon and, who
knows, to more distant planets as well.
International contacts, important in
the development of any branch of
learning, and particularly science, have
increased enormously in the past few
decades. These years have seen the
EVGUENI FEDOROV is vice-president of
the Word Meteorological Organization
and head of the Hydro-Meteorological
Services of the U. S. S. R. He is a
member of the U. S. S. R. Academy of
Sciences, and was formerly chief scientific
secretary of its Praesidium.
creation of a great number of inter-
national scientific associations, unions
and committees, whose activities in
many cases are co-ordinated by
Unesco.
Progress in science and progress
in technology are interdependent.
That one cannot advance without the
other is demonstrated in some newly-
independent countries which have
lagged behind in these fields. These
nations, which are now members of
the U. N. and Unesco, are determin-
ed to overcome their handicaps and
are eager to set about transforming
their industry and agriculture and
their science and technology as rap-
idly as possible. But to do so, they
need schools, technical institutes and
research laboratories, as well as the
benefit of the technological experience
acquired by the economica)) develop-
ed nations.
Many of these young nations re-
cently freed from colonial domination
have joined Unesco, and their arrival
has made an impact on the whole of
Unesco's programme, particularly its
promotion of internationa ! scientific co-
operation.
International co-operation is in-
dispensable to all branches of science,
but the need for it is perhaps greatest
of all in the earth sciences. Studies
in this field are concerned with natural
phenomena in the atmosphere, in the
seas and on the land areas of our
planet and therefore affect all peoples
and demand a co-operative effort by
scientists of all nationalities.
World science has long recognized
the importance of an international
partnership to carry out research in
geophysics, meteorology, oceanogra-
phy and related fields. This co-opera-
tion began with the organization of the
First Polar Year of 1882-83, during
which 11 countries made joint mete-
orological, geomagnetic and auroral
observations at 14 stations in the
northern polar region.
Fifty years later came the Second
Polar Year of 1932-33, in which 44
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
Photo 0 N. Max ! mov-APN
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
NEW OUTPOSTS OF SCIENCE (Continued)
Micro-man against a macro-world
countries participated. And Internation-
al co-operation in science reached an
historic peak in the International
Geophysical Year of 1957-58 when
scientists of more than 60 nations
collaborated closely in a vast global
research programme. Today, under
the sponsorship and encouragement
of Unesco, many countries are making
joint studies of the oceans, seismic
phenomena, the earth's crust and other
aspects of our planet.
The expansion of international co-
operation in the earth sciences is proof
that humanity has now reached a new
and vitally important stage in its
relations with nature. The interaction
between society and nature, which
began when man became conscious of
his own"self", is an indispensable
condition of human progress. In the
beginning, the human race, weak and
helpless, was exposed to the elemental
forces of nature. Hard work and col-
lective action enabled man to protect
himself against the elements-and
then to master them.
What stage in this development have
we reached today ?
The primitive conceptions of the
world came from limited observations.
Within these limits each tribe visualiz-
ed the earth, rivers, forests and
mountains. Since then the boundaries
of the known world have expanded
until they now extend to the farthest
galaxy whose distance can be measur-
ed-some 1022 km (10, 000, 000, 000, 000,
000, 000, 000 kilometres).
THE human mind has alsoprobed i wards to pene-
trate another sphere. Man has spe-
culated for thousands of years about
the nature of matter, the smallest
elements of which substances are
formed. But it was not until compar-
atively recently-less than a hundred
years ago-that he acquired a more
or less correct understanding of mole-
cules and then of atoms. And not
until the past decade has he discover-
ed the secrets of atomic nucleii and
of the even tinier fundamental part-
icles.
What is the smallest measurement
known to man ? It is apparently the
distance at which the weak interaction
of the particles of an atomic nucleus
16 occurs ; estimated at 10-22 (. 000, 000,t D 000, 0, 000, 000, 000, 01 of a centimetre).
How curious that we should have
reached out approximately as far in
the directions of the macrocosm and
the microcosm alike.
Man's mind has also measured
processes occurring with infinite slow-
ness and phenomena lasting fractions
of a second. The longest period of
time that can be measured by modern
science is approximately 1010 yearns
(10, 000, 000, 000 years)-the maximum
age of certain stars and galaxies. At
the other extreme, the shortest phe-
nomenon is the length of life of certain
fundamental particles which are timed
at 10-10 sec. (. 000, 000, 000, 01 of a
second).
Such, in highly simplified form, are
the present scales of space and time
with which we work.
Our knowledge of the universe now
reveals the earth to be a mere speck of
dust in the immensity of space. Yet our
knowledge of our own planet is far
from complete. We have explored
its surface ; we are familiar with pro-
cesses that affect the atmosphere and
the oceans. But our knowledge of its
internal structure, of the processes
going on within it and of its actual
origin is still largely hypothetical.
What then is the measure of our
control over nature ? Obviously, the
extent of our exploitation of natural
resources and the amount of power
we can harness to our needs can serve
as criteria.
Thousands of years ago man lived
without even being aware of deposits
of iron ore or oil. And only quite
recently have we realized the value of
uranium reserves. Today there is scar-
cely a single element which is not
utilized for one purpose or another.
Many sources of natural wealth are
being exploited so rapidly that there
are fears they may be exhausted. Even
fresh water is in short supply in cer-
tain regions.
Our own individual muscular efforts
enable us to generate the power of
a few score watts ; this for thousands
of years was all the power man had
at his disposal. A few dozen persons
could thus produce perhaps 10 kilo-
watts.
Our regular sources of power-
electric generating plants, engines,
etc.-can now produce approximately
1, 000 million kilowatts. The power
that man could obtain sporadically by
firing all his rockets or systematically
setting off atomic explosions, is
greater by two or three orders of
magnitude. How does this compare
with the energy produced by nature ?
Practically all the elemental proces-
ses occurring on the earth's surface,
in the atmosphere and in the oceans
derive from solar energy. Over the
whole of the hemisphere reached by
the sun, this energy totals approxim-
ately 1013 kw (10, 000, 000, 000, 000 kilo-
watts).
This means that the sun provides
us with energy representing a sizeable
fraction of-or sometimes almost as
much as-the energy generated by
the processes occurring in the earth's
atmosphere and hydrosphere. If pro-
gress continues at the same rate (and
it is likely to accelerate still further),
200. years from now we shall possess
continuous power sources of some
1013 kilowatts.
Thus, we have now reached a stage
at which man is able to exploit a
large proportion of the earth's natural
riches, and has at his disposal energy
comparable in amount to that possess-
ed by the elements throughout the
whole of the planet.
Such a situation poses a number
of important and intriguing problems.
Will Nature's resources suffice for
mankind ? Natural resources are not
inexhaustible after all, and the earth's
population is growing rapidly.
t) ET us suppose that acalculation had been made
in 1850 of the amount of energy
that could have been produced per
head of population using all the means
then available ; the result would have
been about 10, 000 kilowatt-hours. A
hundred years later, in 1950, the figure
would have been 200, 000 kWh. par
person, despite the increase in the
earth's population in the interval. The
explanation lies in the discovery of
many new sources of energy and in
improved methods of transforming
them.
Per capita resources of foods and
materials have increased in much the
same way. Despite the dwindling re-
serves of natural resources, the pos-
sibilities for satisfying all of man's
basic needs have actually increased
with every century-with every year,
in fact-thanks to the discovery of
more and more resources and the
steady progress made in the means
of exploiting them. This state of
affairs is likely to continue-at least
in the foreseeable future.
The future will also see the harnes-
CONTINUED ON PAGE 18
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
We know very little about the inner structure of our planet and the processes going
on within it. To promote the training of seismologists and earthquake engineers and the
observation of earth tremors, Unesco established the International Institute of Seismology and
Earthquake Engineering in Tokyo, and is now setting up a seismological centre for Latin
America in Lima (Peru). Unesco also founded the Institute for Volcanology at Catania (icily).
! t has supported international programmes in geophysics and astronomy, and it met one-third
of the cost of launching the recent International Years of the Quiet Sun research
project. Above, a vast outcrop of rock laid bare by wind erosion.
Phoro WK Hamblin Springer Verlag. Helde ! berg
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
NEW OUTPOSTS OF SCIENCE (Continued)
Man the plunderer-a dying species ?
sing of thermonuclear energy, solar
energy, tidal energies and the power
created by ocean currents, and even
the utilization of geothermal energy.
As for food, cattle raising requires
twenty times less space than hunting,
agriculture twenty times less again.
Agriculture is becoming increasingly
productive and its possibilities are far
from exhausted. Furthermore, the
food potential of the sea is far
greater than what we take from it
today. And modern chemistry has
begun to produce synthetic foodstuffs.
Thus, limitations of the earth's natural
resources are not an insurmountable
obstacle to human development.
Since man first mastered agriculture,
he has always chosen a small part
of his natural environment (a field, a
garden, a herd of cattle) and has
cultivated it intensively. His attitude to
the rest of nature-which he regarded
as being wild, encroaching and in-
exhaustible-was quite different, and
he plundered it with no thought for
the conservation of its rich resources.
Marx, in one of his letters, noted
that"cultivation, when it develops
unmethodically, leaves nothing but
desert... Massive deforestation has
laid waste entire regions and disturbed
the normal balance of the water cycle.
The misuse of soil has led to dust
storms and the erosion of fertile layers
of earth. And certain species of ani-
mals and fish used for food have
been decimated.
T bills abuse of nature mustclearly stop. Concern for
the husbanding of natural resources
is gradually becoming the rule-at
least within the bounds of each coun-
try ; but it has not yet been extended
to the"common land"-the atmosphere
and tlie seas as a whole. Today, the
vast demands on the common natural
resources of the world combined with
improved techniques for exploiting
them, have made it imperative to aban-
don this"predatory"attitude towards
nature. We must ! earn to treat all
the natural riches of the world with
the same respect we have for our
own gardens, fields or herds.
Modern technology allows us not
only to make wide use of natural re-
sources but also, in many cases, to
18 change and improve them. Whereas'0 for centuries fish were bred in ponds,
during the past decade they have
been"cultivated"in lakes and parts
of the sea. Surely the time has come
to consider a rational plan for the fish-
ing industry, covering all the oceans.
In my opinion the rational utilization
of basic natural resources in the in-
terest of mankind as a whole should
be one of Unesco's most impo, rtant
tasks in the years to come.
Man, in his relations with nature, is
not only influenced by his environment
but in turn influences it. The vast
quantities of fuel consumed each year
cause a gradual increase in the
amount of carbon dioxide in the air ;
this in turn, impedes the radiation of
heat from the earth, which is becoming
warmer. So far this temperature rise
is negligible, a fraction of a degree
only ; it could, however, eventually ! ead
to a noticeable change in the heat
balance of our planet.
Other important modifications have
been made to nature through the drain-
age of large areas of bog and the
irrigation of deserts. Land improve-
ment measures such as these influ-
ence the water cycle. These changes
are still very small, affecting only
2 to 3 % of the earth's surface, but
CONTINUED ON PAGE 23
COLOUR PAGES
"We are not asking for dolls and toy trains for our children.
What they need is a pencil to write with, a slate for doing sums,
a book to read."The significance of this appeal by a delegate
from Rwanda to a Unesco General Conference becomes abundantly
clear in the light of world statistics on education. Fifty-two
percent of children of school age are still deprived of education
because of the lack of schools or teachers. Yet much has been
accomplished in the first five years (1960-65) of the U. N.
Development Decade. By 1965, 180 million children n the develop-
ing countries were enrolled in primary and secondary schools-
71 million more than in 1960. For the first time, the rate of
increase of school enrolments in the world has outstripped the
rate of population increase.
Photo Unesco-Dominique Roger
temple is being completed. In September or October, when the colossi are back
in place, their heads will be restored to them : first the two parts of the skull, then
the face and finally the crown. Our photograph was taken by the Cairo Liaison Officer
of the Unesco Service for the Monuments of Nubia.
Photo Unesco-Vladimir Nenadovic
A unique exhibition which brought together hundreds of superb
examples of African art in Dakar last April was an outstanding
feature of the First World Festival of Negro Arts, sponsored by
Unesco and the Government of Senega). On view for the first
time were sculptures and sacred objects from many regions of
Africa, displayed alongside masterpieces of Negro art on loan
from museums in Africa, Europe and America and from private
collections. African Negro art is a form of written history whose
pages in wood, stone and metal interpret life in all its aspects. Its diversity corresponds
to the diversity of Africa itself and also of its civilizations. Unesco recently began to
prepare a General History of Africa which will be completed in 1975. Photo shows (fore-
ground) a votive statue from Sundi (Congo Republic) and (rear) two masks and an
emblematic figure of a calao bird with outstretched wings.
Photo &commat; Tony Saulnier. Paris
CONTINUED ON PAGE 23
At nine o'clock on the morning of September 21, 1965, a huge
stone face (20 tons in weight) with the features of Rameses II
was swung into the air above the former site of the Great
Temple of Abu Simbel, soon to be covered by the waters of the
Aswan High Dam. It belonged to the third and last head of the
four colossal statues on the temple facade (the head of one
statue tumbled to the ground long ago). In this phase of the
dismantling of Abu Simbel, the 30-ton crown surmounting each
statue was cut off first and lifted away. Then the three heads
of the Pharaoh (total weight of each, 80 tons) were cut into
three : the face and two 30-ton blocks composed of half the skull
and one ear. The blocks were then taken to the storage area,
a few hundred metres from where the reconstruction of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
NEW OUTPOSTS OF SCIENCE (continued)
Nature in'mobile equilibrium'
Microscopic marine plants like
these one-celled diatoms (left) with
their dehcatety-traced designs
swarm in both salt and fresh water
over all the earth. They are of great
interest to students of the micro-
world and a delight to collectors and
mounters of microscopic slide,
This phytoplankton or plant life
represents the first step in the liv-
ing food chain of the sea. Upon it
graze the small organisms known as
zooplankton which, in turn, are
devoured by fish. The Indian Ocean
Biological Centre, set up in 1963 by
the Indian Government and Unesco
at Cochin on the Malabar coast of
South India, is now studying hund-
reds of zooplankton samples gather-
ed during the Unesco-sponsored
International Indian Ocean Expedi-
tion in which 40 ships from 15 coun-
tries made research cruises from
1959 to 1965. Zooplankton samples
literally clogged collecting nets in
rich zones of upweHing co ! d water
discovered by the expedition and
now being fished commercially,
Blue diatom : photo &commat; Quatre Vents, Paris ;
other !)) ustrations0 Dr. LJ. Laporte. Paris
more and more land is being subjected
to these improvements.
How do we know what changes
will occur in nature as a result of the
further development of industry, agri-
culture and land improvement ? We
know what their general nature will
be, but we cannot yet predict their
magnitude. The chief difficulty is that
the natural environment is not a static
structure but a complex of processes
in a state of"mobile equilibrium."
Of particular interest are those
occurring in the atmosphere and hydro-
sphere, the pattern of which has long
been known : the sun heats the earth's
surface, which in turn heats the
atmosphere-principally in the tropical
zone ; the warm air rises and, in the
upper strata of the atmosphere, moves
toward the polar regions ; there it cools,
sinks, and moves back towards the
equatorial belt.
This simple pattern is made more
complicated by the rotation of the
earth, by the distribution of the con-
tinents and oceans, and by the pres-
ence of mountain ranges. All these
combine to create the system of move-
ments known as"general circulation",
which is also linked with the circulation
of ocean waters. The atmosphere and
the hydrosphere are so closely associ-
ated that every movement in one is
communicated to the other. The two
are linked by the water cycle which
constantly modifies the earth's surface
by washing out and transporting matter
from one place to another.
LEATHER changes are caus-ed by fluctuations in the
lower atmosphere. The relative stabil-
ity of the climate shows that despite
these fluctuations the hydrometeoro-
logical processes are in a state of
equilibrium, but we know that the
world's climate has not remained the
same throughout its history. Its evolu-
tion suggests that more than one
"mobile equilibrium"is possible, and
that there have probably been several
at various periods in the earth's history.
We have heard of sudden"explo-
sions"occurring in the population of
certain species of animals and insects
from time to time. Studies show that
they are most often due to abnormally
sharp fluctuations in atmospheric or
oceanic conditions.
These shifts may result in the dis-
appearance of certain organisms and
an increase in the numbers of other
species which possibly s. erved as food
for the ones destroyed. Once started,
these fluctuations may pass from one
process to another and fade out gra-
dually, or else they may increase
through a kind of chain reaction.
We know that certain processes on
earth can influence one another, but
we still do not know to what extent.
Man himself is exerting a growing in-
fluence on his environment and before
very long this could give cause for
alarm. If we interfere with the compli-
cated system of natural phenomena,
we may start processes which could
develop, through a chain reaction, and
produce disastrous consequences.
A SIDE from these dangers,however, the periodic ins-
tability of natural processes does open
up interesting possibilities for re-
search. Could we modify the existing
equilibrium in nature for our benefit ?
Scientists have already tried out var-
ious experiments on the weather, in-
cluding the sowing of dry ice on clouds
to produce rain.
In my view, artificial transformations
of the climate can hardly be consider-
ed as one of man's practical objectives
in the immediate future. But the effect
of man's activities on the climate and
other facets of our environment, today
and in the near future, poses a crucial
problem. There is no doubt that it
is an international one, too, because
of the nature of the research involved
and the implications of its results.
We are approaching the point where
mankind will be compelled to make
practical use of all the resources the
earth has to offer and where man will
be in a position to control fundamental
processes on a worldwide scale. In
short, man will soon become the
master of the earth. (It is perhaps no
mere chance that at this stage man
is reaching out into space.)
Need one point out that at such
a moment in its development society
ought to act as a single community ?
It is one of the major tasks of Unesco
to co-ordinate the efforts of mankind
in the conquest of nature and the
rational utilization of natural wealth
for the benefit of all nations. In
this task, Unesco can well draw in-
spiration from its own ideals : the 23
maintenance of peace, and the pro-
motion of the freedom, independence
and progress of all peoples.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
.
IN THE WClRLD
OF EDUCATION
by Lionel Elvin
HUE historian of humanityin the last twenty years
will note two things of especial signi-
ficance. The first no doubt will be
that this was the beginning of the age
of nuclear power, in which mankind
narrowly escaped destruction through
its own invention. But, assuming that
mankind continues to escape such self-
destruction, the most significant fea-
ture that the historian will note is that
this was first period in human history
in which the claim had been made,
and conceded, that every single human
being had a right to education. That
there has been an education"explo-
sion"in the last twenty years is not
a metaphor ; it is a fact.
In saying this I am speaking not of
provision, but of demand. In every
country in the world now the demand
for education-for schools and col-
leges, equipment and teachers-far
outstrips what it has been actually
possible to provide. Even the affluent
countries have been unable to provide
as much as their peoples have de-
manded.
The less affluent countries, in spite
of heavily increased spending on edu-
cation and on foreign aid, have found
it intensely difficult to cope with the
increased demand at every level, prim-
ary, secondary, higher and adult edu-
cation. And both kinds of countries
LIONEL ELVIN, director of the Institute of
Education, University of London, is consid-
24 erred as one of the world's authorities on
comparative education. He was formerly
director of the Unesco Department of
Education.
have found the greatest difficulty in
deciding on right priorities within the
educational budget, how much to
spend on trying to get primary educa-
tion for every child, how much to
spend on secondary education, how
much on the colleges and the univer-
sities, how much on trying to wipe out
adult illiteracy and on other forms
of adult education.
What is the explanation of this
demand for education ? Essentially the
demand comes from two things : first
that education is everyone's right, and
second that an expanded education is
indispensable for the kind of economic
and social modernization that every-
one desires.
The right was enshrined in the Uni-
versal Declaration of Rights, which
came at the beginning of this period
CONTINUED ON PAGE 26
For these school children
(climbing a special metallic scaffolding
designed for play and
exercises) the right to education
is a reality. But for millions of other
children it is still merely a hope.
By 1970 places will need to be
found in the primary schools of Africa,
Asia and Latin America for a further
52 million children. This means
that 850, 000 more teachers
will be required. Unesco
and the International Institute
of Educational Planning, which it
set up in Paris, are redoubling
their efforts to help governments
to train teachers and build schools,
to improve educational planning and
administration and to allocate more
funds to education. Despite
achievements in recent years, a wide
educational gap still exists between
developed and developing nations.
Er : '"
Eo
z
Q)T3
0OJ
Õ
U
: Ja
Q)
. s :;a.
Q.OJo
Õ. s :;a.
Q)"'C
. 
Qj
4 :
&commat;
0
Õ. s :;a.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
TWO DECADES OF EDUCATION (Continued)
The new philosophy of investment
in our history. Article 26 said that
everyone had the right to free primary
education and to education beyond
this stage in accordance with ability
and not family wealth or status. Now
it should be noted that the Declaration
said not that this was an absolute
right-it could not be absolute but
must be contingent on the capacity of
countries to afford it and in the higher
ranges on the capacity of students to
profit reasonably from it-but that it
was universal : that is to say that it
was a right of every human being as
a human being.
TIGHTS have been definedas claims that must be
accepted because without their
acceptance a person or group of
persons cannot function properly. It
has been recognized internationally
that without education a human being
cannot realize his potentiality, cannot
be in a reasonable sense a full human
being and live a full life. There are
of course still people, individuals and
groups, subdued by the unequal past,
who do not yet realize this. But the
peoples, the ordinary people of the
wor ! d's countries, do in a broad but
most pressing sense. The result has
been a tremendous demand for schools
and higher and adult education.
Secondly, the politically and socially
conscious people in every country
understand that a prosperous economy
based on modern technology depends
on a widespread general education
and well-developed professional and
technical education and training. Fur-
thermore, countries that have gained
their political independence during this
period (and they constitute a large
proportion of the members of the
United Nations and of Unesco and the
other specialized agencies) have real-
ized how important education is for
good government and administration
and for the participation of their citi-
zens in public and professional life.
The idea that expenditure on educa-
tion does not only satisfy those who
benefit from it as individual"consum-
ers"but is also personal and national
"investment"has gained ground and
during these two decades has become
accepted philosophy.
These two pressures, then, have
been behind the educational demand
26 of the last twenty years the world over.
But how far have we been able to
satisfy the demand in practice ?
One of the functions of Unesco is
to collect and analyse statistics of
education for the world as a whole.
This is a very difficult business. So
incomplete are the statistics that one
must at times estimate rather than
announce firm figures. The compila-
tion of world totals is notoriously
difficult because the basis for them
(for instance in the structure of educa-
tional systems and the meanings of
terms that are used) varies so much
from one country to another. And the
publication of analysed figures must
inevitably always lag behind the
passage of the calendar years. Yet
something informative does emerge.
The Word Survey of Education, 1957-
1961, gives some of the figures for
these years and enables us to see
significant trends.
For world purposes Unesco recog-
nizes three levels of formal educa-
tion : the first level (primary or elemen-
tary school) ; the second level, based
on at least four years'education at the
first level (high school, secondary
school, vocational school, etc.) ; and
the third level, after successful comple-
tion of the second level (university,
teachers collage, higher professional
school). Now in these four years
only the increase in enrolments was
23 per cent at the first level, 23 per
cent at the second level and 35 per
cent at the third level (let me repeat :
this was in only four years out of the
twenty we are considering).
But there is a catch in these figures.
The world population has also in-
creased, and sensationally, during
these twenty years. What is the
increase of enrolments in relation to
the increase in population ? Here the
result is nothing like as reassuring.
The percentage of the total population
having formal education at all three
levels in 1957-58 was 12. 8. In 1961-2,
it was 14. 6-a gain, but not all that
sensational.
The plain fact emerges that we are
building schools and colleges and train-
ing teachers just fast enough to give
CONTINUED ON PAGE 29
The field of education is in worldwide ferment. Drastic changes are made
in school programmes and in teaching methods. This in turn calls
for changes in the training of teachers including their introduction to such
new educational aids as c ! osed-circuit tetevision and learning machines.
Methods of teaching foreign languages, and of the mother tongue, are under-
going radical change. Here youngsters in a Tokyo primary schoof learn Japan-
ese helped by language laboratory techniques adapted for classroom use,
Photo Unesco-Tamagawa Gakuen, Tokyo
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Education at all levels is now seen as an indivisible whole. A lack of secondary schools leads to a shortage
of primary level teachers, for example, and insufficient higher education means that not enough
secondary level teachers will be trained, To help its member states to plan for the rational and
efficient development of education at all levels, Unesco has set up regional centres in Beirut and New Delhi
and educational planning sections at Santiago de Chile, Dakar and Bangkok. At the request of
many countries it has sent out consultative missions on educational planing, With the International 27
Association of Universities it has surveyed problems of higher education. At this level a big development
is foreseen for the next four years : 40, 000 more students in Africa, 250, 000 in Latin America and
1, 000, 000 in Asia. Photo shows part of the campus at the strikingly modern University of Dakar (Senegal).
Photo <ò Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE FUTURE
FOR R 200, 000 ARAB
REFUGEE CHILDREN
Over 200, 000 Palestine refugee children are now
attending hundreds of primary and secondary
schools run by some 5, 000 teachers under
the technical supervision of Unesco. Launched
in 1950 by Unesco and UNRWA (United Nations
Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees)
the programme is using education and voca-
tional training to build a future for the children
of Palestine refugees. It is the largest opera-
tional activity in which Unesco is at present
engaged. In many parts of the world Unesco
is carrying on activities of an operational nature
in collaboration with other institutions (Unicef,
the International Bank for Reconstruction and
Development, the World Food Programme) as
28 part of its educational programme. Above, aPalestine refugee family after the exodus of
1948. Right, young refugees from a Gaza camp
do homework on the beach.
Photo United Nations
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
TWO DECADES OF EDUCATION (Continued)
Educational re-thinking in ferment
the average child only a slightly better
chance than before. If the world popu-
lation continues to increase at its pre-
sent rate we cannot hope to get every
child into school or wipe out adult illit-
eracy within the present century. That
is a sobering thought.
Because resources are desperately
scarce in relation to what the countries
and their peoples now both need and
desire there hats to be planning. This
is the next distinctive feature of edu-
cational development in this period that
we must note. Education must be
planned in relation to national plan-
ning, if only to decide how much of a
country's resources go into education
as distinct from other things like roads
and railways and air transport, indus-
trial development of all kinds, and
other social services such as medicine
and public health.
And there must be planning in edu-
cation to see that it is of the scale
and kind that fit into the stage of a
country's economic and social devel-
opment. It is wasteful to spend large
sums on the education of persons for
whom there is no subsequent appro-
priate employment, who cannot be
absorbed into the economy and the
professions. There must be priorities
established within education.
MOST people at the beginn-ing of the period probably
thought that the first thing should no
doubt be to make primary education
universal and free. But there has been
a significant shift of opinion during the
period. To begin with, you cannot
have adequate teachers for primary
schools unless you have given them
secondary education. And a measure
of secondary education is indispens-
able for getting the"middle grades"
who will help to run the economy, as
well as to prepare students for higher
education. Clearly there must also be
some higher education.
So the concept of phasing the devel-
opment of all three levels together
has been worked out, often at the
regional conferences that Unesco has
called to consider the planning of edu-
cational development in the different
parts of the world. With a certain
level of resources it should be pos-
sible to have a given high percentage
of children in the primary schools, a
given smaller percentage in the secon-
dary schools and a given still smaller
percentage in higher education. The
setting of these targets in relation both
to national needs and to each other is
a difficult and delicate task.
It is in this work, as much perhaps
as in the furnishing of direct aid, that
Unesco has helped its member states
most in recent years. These years
have marked something of a swing in
the objectives of Unesco from inter-
national intellectual co-operation at the
scholarly level (though that continues)
towards helping the less affluent coun-
tries to develop their education, with-
out which they hardly can co-oper-
ate at that high level. And within the
aid activity more and more attention
has been paid to the various aspects
of educational planning, Unesco acting
both through its departments and
through the International Institute for
Educational Planning which is its"stud-
ies"arm.
Now all that has been said in this
article so far is"quantitative". But
what about the education itself, and its
quality ? A no less significant feature
of these last twenty years (and espe-
ciatty of the second decade) has been
the attention given to what is taught
and to how it is taught at the different
levels of education. Here we realize
(though it is indeed evident from the
quantitative pressures we have dis-
cussed) that we are in the presence
of a social and economic transforma-
tion which sets up inevitable educa-
tional demands.
General education at the first level
in what are now the"advanced"coun-
tries came in with the development of
industry. This may have had within
it the seeds of social transformation
but it did not seem very revolutionary
at first. Secondary and higher educa-
tion remained reserved for those who
would playa more privileged or more
responsible role in society. The curric-
ulum of the elementary schools aimed
at giving the barely necessary general
skills to the workers in an increasingly
industrialized society.
But, even economically, this has
proved in the present century to be not
enough. Socially it has proved too
limited to be acceptable. A great
range of new occupations has opened
up, needing both better general edu-
cation and more varied education.
With the generalization of at least the
first half of secondary education, this
has resulted in a much more varied
and rather differently based curriculum
in the secondary schools, and the
curriculum of the primary schools has
been seen as leading on to this in
terms of genuine education, not just
instruction in rudimentary general
skills. Now the secondary school
curriculum is being radically trans-
formed, in terms simply of subjects
taught.
But the content of the subjects is
also under review as well as the
balance of studies. This is connected
with new methods of teaching. We
talk now of the"new mathematics,"of
a re-thought out secondary school
physics, chemistry, and biology. Meth-
ods of teaching foreign languages,
and of the mother tongue, are under-
going radical change. This in turn
calls for changes in the training of
teachers, and not least in their intro-
duction to the use of educational aids
(from television to learning machines)
that were not thought of seriously for
educational purposes at the beginning
of our period.
FOR newly independentF countries, and oth r cou -
ries that are less affluent than the
"advanced"countries, this has set
very difficult problem indeed. Some
of them have had to free themselves
not only from methods that are outmod-
ed (for instance, from a centuries-old
tradition of learning by rote under an
authoritarian teacher) but from a curri-
culum that was almost entirely appro-
priate, not to their own people and
their needs, but to a foreign adminis-
tering power and its citizens at home.
Not least this has led to questions
about the relationship between what is
taught and the immediate environment
and the work in it. Should not agri-
cultural education, for instance, have
a quite new impetus in countries
whose prosperity will depend for some
time to come much more on modern-
izing agriculture than on the develop-
ment, say, of heavy industry ?
With all these factors at work-the
demand for education as a universal
right and as a national need, the prob-
lems of coherent planning with scarce
resources, the need to change the
curriculum at all levels and greatly to
improve methods of teaching-no one
can say that the last twenty years in
the educational history of mankind
have been dull. There have been
immense problems, and immense prob-
lems remain. But with all that, the 29
old phrase is significantly and immen-
sely true : educationally, humanity is
now on the march.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
  N   **t M  
   N  N N N M M -
<UL) ! <Ut-O"CULTURE
by Merman Arciniegas
t T is not so long since"cul-
ture", in the singutar, was
fundamentally a creation of the West.
From Europe, ideas, philosophy, art
and civilization radiated to other parts
of the world, and the echoes awaken-
ed by their messages were regarded
as the world's responses to"culture".
In the last twenty years we have
passed from the notion of culture in
the singular to that of cultures in the
plural. We have come to realize that
cultures exist which are not European
and this wider view of the world has
opened the way to an unprecedented
process of democratization.
The messages no longer come from
Europe alone ; they come and go in
all directions, intersecting, contradict-
ing and complementing each other.
Every year folk art groups from India,
the Soviet Union, Mexico, Bali, Ru-
mania or Japan appear on the Paris
stage ; festivals of Western music are
organized in Tokyo ; the Bolshoi Bal-
let travels to London, Buenos Aires,
and Bogota ; a travelling exhibition
takes a matchless array of Japanese
art to every part of the United States.
Never before have we witnessed cul-
tural exchange on so tremendous a
scale.
Between 1950 and 1963 an exhibition
of Mexican art travelled throughout
Europe and was seen by hundreds
of thousands of people in Stockholm,
Brussels, Zurich, Cologne, The Hague,
Berlin, Vienna, Moscow, Leningrad,
Warsaw, Rome and Paris. On view
were tiny ceramic statuettes from Tla-
tilco, modelled 2, 300 years before the
arrival of Columbus, monolithic head
from Las Ventas sculptured twenty
centuries ago, and paintings by Rufino
Tamayo. Today it would be unthink-
able to write a history of world art
without giving due importance to a
civilization as ancient and extraordin-
ary as that of the Mayas.
Since the remotest time exoticism
has acted like a leaven upon art,
stimulating exploration and discovery
and feeding the creative imagination
of the artist. In our day it is every-
where, and through its contacts it
exerts a constant influence on the
evolution of ideas. The time has come,
in fact, to revise the old framework
GERMAN ARCINIEGAS of Colombia is one
of Latin America's leading historians and
thinkers. A writer and a diplomat, he has
twice been Minister of Education of Colom-
bia. Among his works in English are :"The
State of Latin America","Caribbean : Sea
of the New World"and"Green Continent",
an anthology of works by leading Latin
30 American writers which he edited. He hasdecently been taking part in studies on La-
tin American current affairs at Columbia
University, New York.
Unesco has promoted knowledge and appreciation of cultural values throughout
the world. In art and literature alike it has brought to a wide public new sources
of knowledge : travelling art exhibitions, albums of colour reproductions and art
paperbacks, translations of representative work, In 1957, Unesco launched its Major
Project for mutual appreciation of Eastern and Western cultural values which
brought a new reality to the idea of international understanding. The project has
fostered studies by research institutes, universities and scholars and has helped
to establish institutes of Oriental studies in Tokyo, New Delhi, Beirut, Cairo
and Damascus. It has also encouraged the improvement of curricula and textbooks
and has stimulated the translation of a large number of classical and contemporary
works from the Orient. Photo shows a calligraphy contest taking place in Japan,
a country whose efforts have long since vanquished its illiteracy problem.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
of the philosophy of history, since no
place exists in the systems worked
out by European thinkers of the last
century for the ways and experiences
of the remote countries.
Since Columbus crossed the Atlan-
tic and Vespucci announced the ap-
pearance of an unknown continent,
people have talked of the U discovery"
of a New World. At the end of the
eighteenth century it was acknowledg-
ed that what had been"discovered"
three hundred years before, in fact
had still to be discovered. So men
of science of that day began to explore
the mysteries of the national history
of America... at a time when the Swe-
dish botanist, Carl Linnaeus was"dis-
covering"the plants of Scandinavia
and of Europe in general.
We thus see that the process of
discovery repeats itself and that from
time to time men are amazed to find
how little they really know. Then,
they begin to re-explore the world
around them, and to discover it anew,
as though entering some virgin forest.
The past twenty years have been
rich in discoveries of things that were
already thought to be well known.
Africa, for example, since Biblical times
has provided an incalcuable stimu-
lation for all kinds of cultural pro-
cesses in Occident and Orient alike.
The echoes that the Queen of Sheba
and her court left in the poetry of
Solomon are symbolic of these fer-
ments, and the works of African mo-
saic artists in the European areas of 
the Roman Empire are another out  f-
standing testimony.
It is not easy to judge to what extent
CONTINUED ON PAGE 34
Photo &commat; Japan Times
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Head of a woman in terracotta fashioned
between 1, 400 and 1, 500 years ago by an
unknown Japanese. He was not a professional
sculptor. He wished simply
to honour the memory of a leader, by
decorating his tomb with a funerary figure sculpted
in clay with a bamboo spatula. Figures of this
kind shaped by unknown artists are called
"haniwa". This one is onty 16 cms (6 in.) high.
Photo @ M ! che) Courto ! s
Ajf photos courtesy
Robert Laffont, publishes. Paris
HISTORY
OF MANKIND
One of the great tasks Unesco set itself in the past twenty years has been the
preparation of a six-tome History of Mankind on science and culture.
In 1951 Unesco established an International Commission for an International History
of the Scientific and Cultural Development of Mankind to supervise the work of
the historians and scholars from many countries who were to prepare the History.
Volume I of the History of Mankind, dealing with prehistory and the beginnings
of civilization, was the work of two renowned archaeologists, Jacquetta Hawkes
and Sir Leonard Woolley. It was published in 1963 in London (George Allen and
Unwin, Ltd.) and in New York (Harper and Row, Inc.). In 1966, Unesco's 20th anni-
versary year, it is being made widely available in other languages. A Serbo-Croat
edition has been published in Zagreb and a Greek language edition (50, 000 copies)
is being published in Athens in weekly instalments with colour plates. A Spanish
language version (Editorial Sudamericana, S. A.. Buenos Aires) has just been
published, and a French edition (Robert Laffont, Paris) will appear later this year.
Translations into Hebrew, Italian, Japanese and Slovinian are also planned.
Volume I has also appeared in paperback form, in two parts, in the United States
(a first printing of 150, 000 copies by The New American Library, Inc.-Mentor
Books). A collection of paperbacks under the general title of Readings in the
History of Mankind Series (edited by Guy S. Metraux and Francis Crouzet) is
also being published (100, 000 copies) in the Mentor Books series. These paper-
backs are based on articles which have appeared in the Journal of World History
(the review published by the International Commission for a History of Mankind).
The first four titles, published between 1963 and 1965, are The Evolution of Science,
The Nineteenth Century World, The New Asia, and Religions and the Promise of the
Twentieth Century. Another publication based on the same sources, Studies in
the Cultural History of India, has appeared in Agra, India, and a Hindi translation
is in preparation.
The Ancient World, Volume II of the History of Mankind (a set three books), by
Luigi Pareti, Paolo Brezzi and Luciano Petech, was published in English last year,
and a third volume, The Twentieth Century (actually Volume VI in the series), by
Caroline F. Ware, K. M. Panikkar and J. M. Romein, is to be published in London
later this year (see the Unesco Courier, June 1963, May 1965).
This horse comes down to us
out of the long night of
prehistory when man, despite his
unrelenting struggle for survival,
already exercised his talent
as an artist. It was drawn
with manganese on the wall of
an almost circular gallery
in the Niaux cavern (Ariege,
France) 12, 000 years ago. Tools
and weapons found there
show that the cave was
one of the underground
refuges of Paleolithic man.
Bison, mammoths and horses
decorating these caves
32 astound us by their surenessof line and the impression
of movement they convey.
Photo Andre Held
A head from the Lahore Museum
(Pakistan) depicts with startling
realism the asceticism
of Buddha during his years
of fasting and penitence.
A detail of a statue carved in
shale and seated on a
pedestal, it is the work
of a Greco-Buddhist school
of art-the Gandhara
school, which produced many
images of the fasting
Buddha in the 2nd and
3rd centuries A. D.
First portrayal of
the Buddha as a man
rather than as a symbol are
accredited to this school,
which combined the realism
of Greco-Roman art with
the symbolism of Asia.
Photo &commat; Biltgen
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
TWO DECADES OF CULTURE (continued)
A post-war phenomenon-international tourism
Negro art has been inf) ue7icing other
arts since the beginning of the cen-
tury, particularly sculpture, ballet and
certain types of music, but culturally
Africa is still an undiscovered conti-
nent.
This was emphasized recently at the
Festival of Negro Art, in Dakar, by
the Negro poet, Leopold Sedar Sen-
ghor, President of Senegal, and by
the writer, Andre Malraux, France's
Minister of Culture. Now, on the
initiative of Unesco, a General History
of Africa is to be written, as though
for the first time, and the work will
take ten years to complete. In almost
all the nations of the African continent,
technical and scientific institutes are
springing up, while more and more
flags of these newly-independent states
are being hoisted at United Nations
headquarters. For Africa the era of
rediscovery is beginning. And for
other continents too-even for Europe
itself.
What has happened in space has
also happened in time. The expanding
frontiers of history have overrun terri-
tory that until now belonged to prehis-
tory, and the modern passion for
archaeology has merged with the
attractions of tourist travel. Ordinary
people, who in other circumstances
would have always been denied such
stimulating experiences, now file in
wonder past the ruins of temples,
cities and civilizations-grandiose
spectacles which open up new hori-
zons for eye and mind alike. The
response to Unesco's campaign to
safeguard the monuments of Nubia
shows beyond doubt that a universal
interest has been awakened in art and
archaeology.
The present use of archaeologic-
al sites as settings for music, danc-
ing, opera and drama and the Son
et Lumière performances against the
background of great historical build-
ings have given us a new form of uni-
versal education. Nowadays the per-
son most averse to reading about his-
tory will trawl to Baalbek to watch
a spectacle performed in the most
imposing ruins left by Rome, and thus
sees for himself how the influence
and vigour of a civilization carried
the splendour of its arts so far afield.
And on the excavation sites in Israel
tourists from all parts of the world
discover how Greece and Rome
stretched out the golden branches of
their civilizations as they penetrated
,  into Asia Minor.
34 It is easy to make ironic remarks
about the superficial mentality of the
tourist who goes from ruin to ruin
and theatre to theatre and carries
away only a confused image of other
times and other worlds. But apart
from the fact that the spectacle has
broadened his mind, it is likely that
among any crowd of sightseers there
is at least one person who will harvest
something of value from the exper-
ience, and will make use of it crea-
tively in some form of art.
Tourism, having become the most
productive industry in many countries,
now provides ample means to pay
for the preservation and restoration
of monuments that would otherwise be
left to perish. The work of André
Malraux in cleaning up the face of
Paris, or of Piero Bergellini in doing the
same for Florence, or of the Mexicans
who have uncovered Teotohuacan, is
creating cultural wealth for all to enjoy.
And this capital increases with the help
of the anonymous tourist. The discov-
ery of the Dead Sea scrolls, a major
victory for those trying to shed new
light on the times of Jesus, is another
positive result of our century's pas-
sion for archaeology.
Another remarkable phenomenon is
the way the fever of curiosity spreads
from foreign visitors to the people of
the"tourist"countries."Domestic"
tourism has the advantage of penetrat-
ing more deeply. People who had
never before explored their own coun-
try are now discovering their rich cul-
tural heritage. This is the case in
France, for example, where visitors
from the provinces are going from the
Louvre to Chantilly and from Versailles
to the Museum of Man in Paris, and
are filling in the sketchy outline of
knowledge acquired in school or from
the newspapers.
An immense network
of cultural exchanges
is now spreading around
the world. Today,
sculpture and painting
travel even more
swiftly than did books
and music yesterday.
Left, in a special
protective packing case
Venus de Milo
is prepared in Paris
for a four-month visit to
Japan. Right, Aztec
sculptures draw admiring
visitors in Paris after
crossing the Atlantic
in t962 with other
Pre-Columbian works
of art from Mexico.
coco
<l.
'U
co
Noa.'"
< (
&commat;
o
Õ.. c :<l.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
me ne last twenty years nave also
witnessed a revolution in museums.
They have ceased to be what they
were at the start of the century-store-
houses crammed with canvases, sta-
tues and jewels which were of more
v a t u e as an accumulation of
treasures than for the help they might
have offered the layman. In recent
years museums have been completely
transformed and are now an in-
dispensable extension to the school.
When the Museum of Man opened
in Paris some thirty years ago, its
strikingly new visual representation of
the history of man and his cultures
was a revelation to the world. Today
it is the turn of the new National
Anthropological Museum of Mexico to
become a world precursor in museo-
logy, and it is from the avant garde
techniques of Mexico that the Paris
museum may now draw inspiration.
Reproductions are also playing a
major role in the efforts of museums
to attract visitors in increasing numbers
from all walks of life. Outstanding
examples of museums which use this
technique are the Museum of French
Monuments in Paris and the remarkable
Civilta Romana Museum in Rome.
But these are only some of the pos-
sibilities that new means of communi-
cation and diffusion are opening up for
the spread of culture. You may show
the reproduction of a painting from
the Prado Museum in Madrid to a
schoolboy in any Latin American city,
and he will tell you without hesitation
whether it is an EI Greco or a Velas-
quez, since knowledge of that kind has
reached every level of society. And
when a museum in the United States
pays two million dollars for a Rem-
brandt everyone approves, since the
museum is acquiring a painting that
will give millions of people a clearer
idea of what art means in a world
that has entered an era of prodigious
achievements.
We have seen in recent years all
kinds of audacious experiments being
carried out in every sphere of artistic
creation. We have witnessed, for
example, the life of Picasso and
the impact it has made as he proceed-
ed to disintegrate, integrate and rein-
tegrate a whole vast field of art. In
the theatre we have seen the experi-
ments of Brecht and lonesco. In liter-
ature we have been offered the anti-
novel. The number and scope of the
experiments are infinite. But they are
not destructive.
Passion for the Greek theatre re-
mains universal. We have a perpetual
Shakespeare festival. There has been
a reappraisal of the nineteenth cen-
tury theatre. The cinema has brought
about a renaissance of Michelangelo
in our time ; it has put millions of
spectators throughout the world in
front of the paintings in the Sistine
Chapel or the sculpture on the tombs
of the Medicis, and these millions have
seen the works to better advantage
than an actual visitor to Rome or Flor-
ence. The impressionists certainly
CONTINUED ON PAGE 74
Photo C0 Gisèle Freund, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A chain of antennae
pointing into the
reaches of space
now girdles r
planet. With the
launching in 1962
of Telstar, the first
communications
satellite, new horizons
were opened up
for the transmission
of news and ideas.
Unesco has
helped the
developing countries
to expand
and improve their
information media,
stressing the
vital role of
these media in
"continuing education".
It has also studied
how communications
satellites can
enhance the use of
mass media for
economic and social
development and
for educational
and cultural exchange.
Z
<l.
< (
; °
. <cü=>ocro
L
cO
G
o
Õ. <c
<l.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
IIN THE WORLD
S  MF Ht aMam BMti "& SS&es !  iate N8
M  '' BJB'aB aBMS
! N  
MASS MEDINA
by Robert Lindsay
and Raymond B. Nixon
A stonishing technical im-pr vements in the mass
media of information in the past
20 years hold bright promise for
eventual realization of the premise of
the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights, that all men have the right"to
seek, receive and impart information
and ideas through any media and
regardless of frontiers."
Today, it is not only political and
ideological boundaries that are being
leapfrogged in the pursuit of this goal.
What only 20 years ago were consider-
ed impossible distant reaches in terms
of technical improvement of the physi-
cal channels of communication are
now within sight. Indeed, in some
areas we are at the point of crossing
what may be the last and most for-
midable"frontier"of them all-that
of a truly global, free-flowing network
of communications of all kinds, avail-
'able to all people in all countries.
Even so, this frontier is a wide and
uncharted one, and its passage will
take time as well as foresight and
enterprise on the part of educators,
ROBERT LINDSAY is an associate profes-
sor of journalism at the University of
Minnesota (U. S. A.). A specialist in broad-
cast journalism, he has recently been
engaged in a comprehensive study on
communication satellites.
RAYMOND B. NIXON is professor of jour-
nalism and international relations at the
University of Minnesota. He was formerly
editor-in-chief of"Journalism Quarterly", a
U. S. research journal for which he is now
international editor. From 1960 to 1964
he was president of the International Asso-
ciation for Mass Communication Research.
journalists, administrators and others
directly concerned with the venture.
The inescapable fact is that progress
in improving the world's mass commu-
nication facilities is at best simply
keeping pace with the still-serious
inability of many millions of persons
to make use of what few channels of
communication may be available to
them. As the most recent edition of
the UN Statistical Yearbook reminds
us all too significantly, some 40 per
cent of all adults in the world cannot
read, while less than half of the world's
children of school age in fact attend
school.
So, while it is heartening to know
that in two decades huge numbers of
people have gained easier access to
more books, periodicals and newspap-
ers and to more cinemas and more
radio and television services, we must
at the same time appreciate that exis-
tence of information facilities by no
means necessarily equates with ability
to make meaningful use of the facili-
ties. In short, we must acknowledge
and accept the enormity of the chal-
lenge still facing us-the challenge of
making wise use for universal benefit
of the marvelous tools of communica-
tion that scientists and engineers are
laying before us.
Having done this, we can take a
backward glance as the trail travelled
so far and derive therefrom a generous
measure of satisfaction for a good
many substantial accomplishments. In
1950, in its first edition of the glo-
bal survey, World Communications,
Unesco reported the disturbing fact
that"little or no modern means of
communication"existed for many
millions of people in vast areas of
the world.
To say the least, the situation has
changed, as the fourth (1964) edition
of World Communications illustrates
so clearly. The Unesco-postulated
goal of ten copies of daily newspapers,
five radio receivers and two cinema
seats per 100 people, per country, as
an acceptable minimum has not yet
been attained by any means ; never-
theless, there has been immense prog-
ress since the immediate post-World
War II years.
In the case of the daily press, news-
paper circulation in the world gen-
erally has increased, especially in a
great many developing countries (in
some of which, indeed, no newspapers
at aN existed 20 years ago). This
increase is in particular evidence in
the developing regions and countries
of Africa, Asia and Latin America.
Only in North America in fact,
do we see that daily newspa-
per circulation, although still rising,
has fallen behind population increases
- a fact generally attributed to the
phenomenal growth of television.
Concomitant with the overall surge
in newspaper circulation has been an
increase in the number of news agen-
cies serving the several media of mass
communication ; there are now 155 such
agencies in a total of 80 countries, as
compared with 96 in only 54 countries
when Unesco first surveyed the field.
The periodical press, too, figures
largely in the global picture of mass
communication. There are no reliable
world-wide data on magazines and
similar publications, but there indubi-
tably has been since 1945 a vast num-37
ber of new periodicals launched, cater-
ing for an equally vast number of
audience needs and tastes.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
TWO DECADES OF MASS MEDIA (Continued)
From transistor
to communication satellite
The periodical press may well play
an increasingly important role in edu-
cation as a bridge to wider avenues of
learning for the world's 700 million
illiterates. This is especially true in
developing countries where the spe-
cialized publication, relatively accessi-
ble and uniquely suited for extended
reading, can p ! ay a vitai part in both
literacy teaching and general educa-
tional programmes.
The cinema, despite the rise and
challenge of television, still continues
its reign as monarch of the media of
entertainment in most areas of the
world. No doubt the most interesting
development in this regard has been
the shift over the past 20 years in
the locus of film production. Espe-
cially in the last ten years, feature
films have been put out in increasing
numbers by Japan, India and Hong
Kong, in Asia ; by the United Arab
Republic in Africa ; by Argentina and
Brazil, in particular, in South America ;
and by the Soviet Union.
The United States, once the leader
in this field, now ranks fourth in the
world in terms of annual production of
feature films. Europe, too, has seen
a decline in film production (and a
lesser decline in cinema attendance),
thus reflecting, like North America,
television's competition for audiences
in search of entertainment. In the
Soviet Union, on the other hand, both
the production and attraction of
feature films has skyrocketed in the
past ten or more years-despite the
introduction of television.
The use of the film for educational
and informational purpose continues to
grow everywhere in the world. Added
to this medium's traditional attributes
of transportability and audio-visual
acceptability are new techniques in
the uses of colour, wide-screen pho-
tography, and projection facilities.
Television, the only new medium of
mass communication introduced since
the end of World War'II, has at the
same time proliferated more rapidly
than any other medium-first in North
America, then almost simultaneously
in the United Kingdom and Western
Europe and only a little later in Eastern
Europe, the Soviet Union, Asia, Latin
America and Africa. TV, yesterday's
novelty, has become a commonplace
seemingly overnight.
There had been telecasting, largely
experimental, in England and the Uni-
ted States before 1939, but World War
II shut off growth of the new medium.
Only 20 years ago, there were but six
38 to stations transmitting in the United States to a few thousand r ceivers ;
five years later, there were not even
any receivers for TV in Africa, Asia and
Oceania. Today, there are some
140 million television receivers in the
world, and in the neighbourhood of
2, 500 transmitters.
Pervasive though television has
become, however, there remain large
sectors of the world where the me-
dium, even though it may exist in the
form of transmitting facilities, is far
from being accessible to many millions
of people unable to afford receiving
sets. Despite these large patches of
TV's non-penetration on the world
map, it is incontestable that the past
two decades have witnessed the most
promising-and often spectacular-
pilot projects for the achievement of
the goal defined in the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights.
In particular, there is the exciting
promise in the continuing co-operation
among member-countries of Eurovision
and Intervision in the exchange of
programmes and on occasion, facilities,
for the education, enlightenment and
entertainment of many millions of view-
ers in the U. S. S. R.. Eastern and
Western Europe, and North America.
It is sometimes suggested that the
post-World War II years could be
termed The Age of the Transistor.
Certainly it is true that the advent of
exquisitely miniaturized electronic cir-
cuitry is among the most significant
technical developments affecting the
mass media of information in the past
20 or so years. The impact of the
transistor alone on radio broadcasting
throughout the world is almost incal-
culable.
Moreover, equally important techno-
logical innovations are promised by
scientists ; these developments, coupl-
ed with factors related to economics,
geography, and political and social
development, strongly suggest that
radio likely will remain for some time
the single medium best suited for meet-
ing the requirements of mass educa-
tion and literacy programmes in many
developing countries.
Everywhere in the world since 1946
radio has become firmly seated as the
most widely spreading of all the mass
media. In Africa, there were 140
radio transmitters as recently as 1950 ;
today, that figure has nearly tripled.
In less than 20 years, the number
of radio transmitters has nearly qua-
drupled in the U. S. S. R., tripled in
Asia, doubled in South America. Once
again, however, such figures can be
deceptive, for despite the startling
percentage increases, in the number
of transmitters in Africa, Asia and
some areas of Latin America, radio
broadcasting remains below what
Unesco considers the minimum, name-
ly five radio receiving sets per 100
people.
Finally, literally soaring over all
other instruments of mass information
conveyance, there is the communica-
tion satellite-far and away the most
significant technical accomplishment
and historical milestone of the past
20 years. As pioneered by the United
States and the Soviet Union, the com-
munication satellite has demonstrated
that there are no physical limitations
to the spatial dimensions of mass com-
munication.
Already millions of television view-
ers and radio listeners in Asia, North
and South America, Europe and the
U. S. S. R. have sat in their homes to
see and hear programmes originating
"live"from points many thousands of
miles distant, thanks to the miracle of
relay transmitters orbiting thousands
of miles above the planet.
Last December, Unesco called a
meeting of experts at its Paris head-
quarters to take up in a preliminary
way the complex problems posed by
the presumed uses of space commun-cation by the mass media. The
United Nations General Assembly has
declared that"communication by
means of satellite should be available
to the nations of the world as soon as
practicable on a global and non-dis-
criminatory basis."The recent Unesco
conference addressed itself to a
consideration of how this might be
done.
In the meantime, the communication
I
Proto Unesca-Airna ;- ; y.Vauthcy
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
satellite-of which only a few proto-
types have been placed in orbit-is
less than five years off the drawing
board, and what it may portend for
the future of world communications re-
mains to be systematically contemplat-
ed and structured. The United States
has placed principal authority for
development of its communication
satellite system in the hands of a pri-
vate corporation, which is just now
commencing to explore the specifics of
its mission. A complicating factor is
that the private American concern ne-
gotiates with the several European
members of a recently established
communication satellite consortium,
which for the most part represents
national governments. The role, if
any, of Unesco or of the United Na-
tions in any eventual system or sys-
tems, cannot at this time be foreseen
with certainty.
In sum, the development of mass
communication in the world in the last
20 years, quantitatively, has been
steady, encouraging and in some res-
pects spectacular. Especially since the
1950s, more people have been able to
read more printed publications, to
enjoy more cinemas and more radio
and television offerings. To the extent
that sheer numbers of communication
channels and the means for tapping
them constitute progress, the cause of
improving education and politico-socio-
economic development everywhere in
the world has been exceedingly well
served in the eventful years since
Unesco was founded.
There, remains the agenda-already
full, it would seem, yet constantly
being crowded with ever more entries
- of pressing considerations related
to the utilization and implementation of
all these efficient machines for dissem-
inating ideas and information. In the
next 20 years, or in the next ten or
five years, the world community must
attempt to reduce the number of unre-
solved items on this agenda.
To cite but one example : Twenty
years hence or even much sooner,
there will be in existence one or
more communication satellite systems.
Whether or not any of these may in
some way be available to (or perhaps
even administered by) United Nations
agencies and the countries and regions
they serve, it will be imperative for the
fundamental cause of world amity that
the United Nations in some realistic
manner should be privy to policy and
operational deliberations concerning
them. We can be grateful that Unesco
has already begun to examine how
space communication can be put
to use in its continuing programme
for the use of the mass media for edu-
cation and for literacy campaigns.
For the developing countries, espe-
cially, establishing economic and edu-
cational bases upon which to found
viable mass communications systems-
complex though this task is in itself-
may well be less crucial than ensur-
ing an adequate supply of profession-
ally trained and educated commu-
nicators-journalists and educators.
Unesco's efforts in this field are
reflected in the fact that more than
70 countries today have schools of
journalism or training programmes for
workers in the mass media, whereas
only 25 countries had such facilities
when the first meeting of journalism
educators and media experts was held
in 1947.
No mass medium-print or broad-
cast, traditional or innovative-can be
any more useful to the culture and
society it operates in than the people
who decide what it will say to its
audiences. There is always the dan-
ger, as some of the technologically
advanced countries have discovered,
that the medium can in effect"run
away with"the human beings who
created it in the first place.
More books, more cinemas, more
transmitters, more periodical and
newspapers, more receivers-we
should see to it that these remain what
they must always be : tools in the ser-
vice of and at the command of man. In
themselves, they are nothing only
human beings, speaking through these
media to other human beings, make
them worthy of our attention.
In 1954 Africa hand, neo television transmitter. Toddy it al-tional programmers in wall paris oaf the world (24 rational projects
ready hats thirsty. Let, a young television technician ant work where operating in 1965-1966), Least rear it lunched a pilot
in Laos (nigeria). Light, children in-Niamey (tiger) witch protect in Dakar tao sturdy sew method oaf adult educe-
ain educational programme on closed-circuit television. Unesco ton. Programmers four tele-clubs in Senegal (proto abode), in-
has increased its efforts to initiate radio and television educa-clude hygiene, nutrition, civic education and cultural subjects.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
I TH /L
SOCIAL SCIENCE
by Alva Myrdal
TOE very placing of SocialScience as one of the
major headings on the Unesco pro-
gramme has undoubtedly contributed
to the status of a venture of intellec-
tual conquest that is still in its pioneer
era : the study of the world man has
built for himself-the world of social
order and disorder.
Under the guidance and prompting of
Unesco, a whole series of new inter-
national organizations has been creat-
ed : The International Political Science
Association, The International Socio-
logical Association, the International
Economic Association and The Inter-
national Association of Legal Sciences,
to name but a few. These organiza-
tions have strengthened the social
scientists ai ! over the world in their
demands for a more prominent platform
ALVA MYRDAL, the distinguished Swedish
sociologist, was director of Unesco's De-
partment of Social Sciences from 1951 to
1955. After serving as Swedish ambassa-
dor to India and Ceylon, and later to Nepal,
she led the Swedish Delegation to the
U. N. Disarmament Conference in Geneva,
in 1962. She was chairman of the U. N.
Security Council group of experts who
reported on problems of apartheid in the
Republic of South Africa (see the Unesco
Courier, April 1965). She has written many
40 boons on sociological questions, including"Crisis in the Population Problem","City
Children","Are We Too Many"and
"Women's Two Roles" (with Viola Kline).
from which to be heard, for academic
recognition as a profession and for
meeting places to share their ideas.
In the past twenty years the social
sciences have received considerable
recognition as separate academic dis-
ciplines, and their findings have been
ever more widely sought. Today, for
example, the architect who is planning
a new school sits down with both the
educator and the psychologist to learn
what they have found out about the
nature of learning. What are the best
uses of space, colour and design to
create the optimum conditions for the
varied and various learning pro-
cesses ?
When an advertising firm plans a
new campaign for a product, the
sociologist is consulted. What kind of
approach, based on certain identifiable
patterns of behaviour, will have the
greatest effect ?
The national politician, before com-
pleting his election strategy, meets
with several social scientists to dis-
cuss the characteristics and issues of
concern to the people he will meet.
Large international corporations hire
psychologists as consultants to help
create and maintain a productive
ambiance between management and
labour.
In the past, the economist who gave
advice to kings, presidents, and dicta-
tors was an amateur. Today, he is
a highly-skilled professional who plays
an increasingly large role in the
development of his country and fre-
quently, due to the nature of our ever-
shrinking world and growing inter-
nationalism, other countries as well.
Kenneth E. Boulding, the inter-
nationally known economist writes
"... I venture to predict that the role
of the social sciences... has a
potential which exceeds by whole
orders of magnitude its present utili-
zation, and that this potential may
well be realized in the next generation.
The potential arises because of the
ability of the social sciences to develop
quantitative, statistical, well-sampled
and rigorously processed images of
the wold." (1)
In the area of economics, for exam-
ple, Boulding states that systems of
collecting and analyzing economic
statistics have become so sophisticat-
ed that the economist has literally been
forced to take on greater responsibil-
ity in the formation of economic poli-
cies.
Some of the substantial ! hchieve-
ments of the social sciences have
(1) Kenneth E. Boulding,"Reality-Testing and
Value Orientation", International Social Scien-
ce Journal, Vol. XVII, No 3, 1965.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 42
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
TWO DECADES OF SOCIAL
SCIENCE (continued)
If you're a racist
you're definitely
not with it !
come about as a result of social
scientists'teaming up with their col-
leagues in allied fields. In the area
of race prejudice, for example, the
social scientists have sought out the
extensive research of the biological
scientists in the fields of biology and
genetics in order to deal with the
numerous theories of genetic racial
superiority. Assisted by extensive
means of disseminating information,
the social scientists have helped bring
the results of their scientific studies
to the attention of the public and,
indeed, have encouraged the general
acceptance of the concept of a
scientific approach to the study of
social groups.
The uses to which social scientists
have been able to put the continuously
expanding knowledge of the biological
and physical scientists have no doubt
contributed to the increasingly educat-
ed view of the pubic towards such
questions. It is now considered
"backward"and"uneducated"in most
countries and societies to hold beliefs
of racial superiority and inferiority.
Where racism is on the wane, it is
because insight into the fundamental
equality of all human beings is being
taught and accepted.
In this particular endeavour, whose
goal is the eradication of race preju-
dice, Unesco has played an immensely
useful role. In 1949 and 1950, Unesco
acted as host to various conferences
of social, physical and biological
scientists. As a direct result, the
authoritative statement,"The Race
Concept", was published, followed by
a series of specialized studies pub-
licized in unusual numbers. During the
past three years, additional meetings
have been held to, complement that
study in light of the newest scholarship
available and to discuss the sig-
nificance of recent research on the
nature of racial prejudice.
The development and expanding
applications of the social science
approach to contemporary problems
are themselves valuable in that this
approach helps to combat mystical and
demagogic conceptions of society.
42 Though the extent to which the social4Z sciences hav  become accep able to
decision-makers varies, there is increas-
ing acceptance of the premise that
Children's minus arse free from rapist ideals (might) sunless they adsorb facial ant religious
prejudL ; yes from their elder. Four the past 20 yearns Unesco hats forked four the attainment
ant universal respect oaf human rights,"without distinction oaf rare, color, sox, language..."
Unesco's straggle hats bees maimed nowt oily against rapist doctrine, bust alto against
the altitudes ant wars oaf thanking ant their roosts. Swithin a veneration groat strides
halve bees mate four the emancipation oaf women (abode, girt student ant a veined woman
in a Moroccan tow). Unesco hats promote the clause oaf equal mights four women
in every afield. Once aim oaf its contention against discrimination in education ins tao encourage
<1he access oaf women ant gills tao schooling oaf wall kids. Unesco ins prepaying a 10-yea
programme for raising the status of women through education, science and culture.
societies function according to cer-
tain discernible laws.
If a social system is amenable to
improvement, the discovery of these
laws can provide the basis for
appropriate action to remedy shortcom-
ings. Thus the often destructive
element of passion and false beliefs
is greatly diminished, and through a
more scientific understanding, policy
can be more efficiently directed
towards constructive ends.
The area of the social sciences
which has had the widest acceptance
by decision-makers thus far, has been
that of socio-economic planning. At
one time, in most countries, the word
"planning"was abhorred. Deficit
financing was taboo, although econom-
ic crises and large scale unemploy-
ment were rampant. In recent years,
planning has gained recognition as one
of the major instruments against these
social maladies. Even the most de-
termined individualists can no longer
deny the impressive results which have
been obtained, through planning, in
all industrialized nations-with no
severe crises and with full or even
over-employment since the war.
Some countries, have, of course,
been committed to economic planning
for several decades. Yet, whether
they have capitalist or socialist econ-
omies, countries have been making
increased use of planning techniques.
Demographers, for example, are being
consulted for projections of future
needs for food resources, schools,
hospitals and leisure-time facilities.
The techniques of market study,
being developed and taught by busi-
ness schools, are acknowledged and
utilized by companies so that they can
forecast the needs of production.
Attempts are even being made to
introduce scientific instrumentalities
(operation analysis, simulation, models,
statistics and mathematics) to the
disciplines of history and political
science.
Hitherto less developed countries,
often starting out on new courses of
economic and social development,
offer another sign of the remarkable
impact of scientific thinking on socio-
economic policies. Virtually all of
these countries have, in their early
stages of development, been examin-
ing their short-term and long-term
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
plans in order to determine systematic
programmes for growth. The function
of these planners is to enable their
governments to steer progress in an
organized and systematic fashion
through the maze of interdependent
channels through which economic life
flows.
That not all plans can be implement-
ed with any assurance of success,
however, is sadly apparent. In the
underdeveloped societies, the tasks in
relation to available resources are
sometimes superhumanly difficult to
reconcile. Although a great deal of
information has been accumulated
over the past twenty years, progress
has often been disappointing. The
real achievement in these societies,
however, is the knowledge that pro-
gress cannot be attained through
separate attacks on economic, social
and cultural problems ; success can
only come through planning frontal
attacks on these areas as a whole.
New demands, therefore, must now
be made on the social scientists. New
theories and new institutional studies,
devoted to the poverty-ridden areas
of the world, must now be sought and
examined. Yet, of course, the final
responsibility for attaining the goals
which have been outlined for the U. N.
Development Decade does not rest
with the social scientists. It rests,
instead, with those wielding political
power, men who are, despite good
advice from scientists, too often acting
as politicians rather than as statesmen,
too often considering only short-term
advantages instead of the needs of
the future.
Mankind is still seized from time
to time, with self-destructive con-
vulsions. The most elementary analy-
ses show, however, that using violence
is irrational ; a counter-productive way
of solving problems or harmonizing
competing interests. Causes of vio-
lence are, moreover, primitive panick-
ing, where those concerned become
unmindful of the tremendous costs in
both human and economic resources.
In other words, men too often arrive at
their most fateful decisions in a manner
which can best be described as pre-
scientific.
To the problems of conflict of war
and peace, social science has devoted,
comparatively speaking, little attention
and energy. This lack can be explain-
ed in terms of supply and demand ; in
these fields policy-makers are least
willing to take any advice from the
scientists. In his analysis of the
problem, Professor Boulding attributes
this in part to"the fact that the
decision-makers... are for the most
part insulated from the social sciences
by their own training and tradition...
On the whole, foreign offices and
state departments are manned by
people trained in literature and history,
or even the classical languages, and
for the most part unacquainted with
mathematics or the sciences, least of
all the social sciences."
The results provide a striking con-
trast to the two areas discussed
earlier. In socio-economic planning,
for example, the decision-makers have
a confidence nearing supernatural
proportions in the social scientists. In
regard to racial and other differences
which have been the objects of pre-
judice, the decision-makers have been
pressed to accept the results of
scientific investigations. But in relation
to war and peace, those who govern
states seem to prefer blindness and
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
4
r
n
1
I
i 
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
TWO DECADES OF SOCIAL
SCIENCE (Continued)
A new look
at the causes
of conflicts
ignorance to recognition and accept-
ance of the scientific approach.
While this judgement, that social
science has played a remarkably weak
role in policy-making, is becoming less
and less true, within Unesco itself
there is evidence that the pro-
nouncements of the social scientists
are not being taken as seriously as
they would wish. The project"Ten-
sions Affecting International Under-
standing", for exampte, must be credit-
ed as a true pioneering effort, though it
was not particularly well received or
supported, and, in fact, Unesco's mem-
ber states scarcely gave it the chance
to prove its validity. Some insight
may be gained into the failures of
the study through its critics, who
felt the project was too narrow in its
approach, since it centred on the
psychological issues, and the dictum
that"wars begin in the minds of
men".
Where social scientists are begin-
ning to make key contributions, how-
ever, are in the new institutes of
peace and strategy, and in the conflict
studies that are being developed in
countries throughout the world.
New centres of research for studies
of conflicts and conflict resolutions, of
peace-keeping techniques, of inter-
cultural integration, and many others
are developing and their findings must,
of necessity, be listened to by the
decision-makers.
Our imagination can scarcely
conceive of how different the world
could look if the constructive energies
of hundreds of thousands of scientists
and technicians were turned from
refining the instruments of death to
producing wealth and improving our
social structures all over the world.
There is no doubt that if scientific
thinking, on a sufficiently large scale,
were to be devoted to the problems
in which this world has become
entangled, an era might begin more
remarkable than any we have yet seen,
for technological growth and for keep-
ing the peace ; for forging mutuality
of interests as revolutionary as any of
our engineering wonders ; for under-
standing the pathology of conflict ; for
curing social ills as important and
destructive as physical ones, against
which medicine has made such dra-
matic advances.
44 Let us remember that social science
has not yet had a chance to begin
to work on all the social problems,
and that these problems are posing
a more deadly threat to our world
every day. This work cannot begin
too soon.
-..-. Uominique Roger
Iran is carrying out a four-year experimental literacy programme linking learning
ant agricultural ant industrial development, witch assistance from Unesco unde
the U. N. Development Programme. The protect coverts worker in Isfahan, the
agricultural legion oaf Khouzistan ant Qazvin, a largo tows in northwest Iran
Abode, the campaign emblem surmount the entrance tao Qazvin's Literary Teaching
Centre. Light, people oaf a Kurdish tillage nowt fair from Qazvin built a school fo
their children. A"soldier oaf knowledge"from Iran's Education Corpus (life th
once seem bellow, leaching a bony hot tao writhe) twill bye spent tao leach villag
children ant tao leat eventing literary lasses four parent. Bellow might, youn
women attend a literary clasps herd in the Qazvin factor where they work
Photo Unesco-L-P. Dr : sco
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
t !) RRn !  ! MHBnt ! ttBut
t
t
nTT ! ['tnRnt<tXi't ? r*t :! Bt*i<tt : MnTRtnnn< : i'rnnRt ! !) E ! 
Historic decision by Iran
MILITARY CREDITS
FREED FOR KNOWLEDGE
In May 1966, Iran set an historic example to other nations by
freeing military credits of $700, OOO-one day's expenditure
under its arms budget-for he world fight against illiteracy.
In donating this sum to Unesco, the Shahinshah of Iran
affirmed that international solidarity must come into play
to help countries lacking the means to fight the affliction
oaf illiteracy."It ins tao bye hopped that thins derision which,
four a developing county life mince, represent a renal sacrifice,
twill bye follower bey others,"he addled. (see the Unesco
Courtier, Jane 1966). In 1955, oily 18% oaf Iran's people were
iterate. There where school ant teaches four oily halt of
its children. On October 13, 1962, the Shahinshah created
"the Barmy of Knowledge". Thigh school gradates recruited
intro the barmy would henceforth bye dratted intro ain Education
Corpus ant, rafter hollowing a straining programme drawn
up bey a Unesco specialist, would bye spent tao mural arenas to
leach villages tao rend ant writhe. Seventy-five peer cert of
Iran's people lire in somme 50, 000 villagers. Thins rear 20, 000
"solders oaf knowledge"are swerving as tillage teaches,
ant arse whelping villages tao praise bettor craps ant construct
well, roads ant school. Bran now devotees 21% oaf its national
budge tao education ant hats lunched a literary pilot project
within Unesco's new experimental world literacy programme.
Photo Unesco-Dominique Roger
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
1 ·
IN THE MINOS OF MEN
Jacques Maritain
Head of the French delegation to
the 2nd Session of the Unesco
General Conference
Above the Babel of minds
HE anguish of man is engulfing everyshore. In this world, crushed by the
afflictions brought on by the War and by the weight of
rival economic, political and ideological interests, shall not
those dedicated to the tasks of the mind, and who feel
a responsibility for such a mission, give voice to the basic
instinct for preservation, to the immense longing for peace
and freedom, to the refusal to suffer and die, which, despite
a strange kind of apparent inertia more akin to despair
than to strength of soul, stir the hidden depths of men's
conscience ?
Modern thought has been likened, not without reason, to
the Tower of Babel. Never, indeed, were minds so harshly
divided. As human thinking splits into more and more
specialized areas, it becomes more difficult to apprehend
the implicit philosophies to which every one of us is
necessarily committed. Doctrines and mystiques, mental
traditions and schools of thought thus clash together and
no one school can even understand the signs used by the
others to express themselves ; the voice of each is a
mere sound to its companions on the road. Dig as deeply
as we will, there are no common foundations left to specula-
tive thought ; there is no longer any common tongue.
In such circumstances, can we conceive of a meeting of
minds between men gathered together precisely in order
to accomplish a common intellectual task, men who come
from the four corners of the earth and who not only belong
to different cultures and civilizations, but to antagonistic
spiritual backgrounds and schools of thought ? Is an
institution like Unesco to give in and abandon all hope
of affirming common ideas and common principles, to
content itself with compiling documents and surveys, factual
data and statistics ? Or should it, on the contrary, attempt
to formulate an artificial conformity of minds and to establish
a common doctrinal denominator-likely, in the course of
discussion, to shrink and finally disappear altogether ?
The solution, I think,'must be sought in another direction.
Because the end-purpose of Unesco is a practical one,
agreement between minds can be reached spontaneously,
not on the basis of a common abstract concept, but upon
the basis of a common practical concept ; not on the
affirmation of one and the same vision of the world,
of man and of knowledge, but upon the affirmation of a
single corpus of beliefs to govern action. This is little
46 enough, no doubt, but it is the last remaining fortresswhere minds can meet. Hence it justifies the undertaking
of a great task, and we will have achieved much if we
can attain awareness of our common practical convictions.
That is why stress must be laid on the crucial importance
- although restricted to the practical field-of the collective
thinking to which Unesco has appealed ever since its
foundation and, in particular, of the statement of principle in
which it declared, in the Preamble drafted at the London
Conference,"that the great and terrible war which has now
ended was a war made possible by the denial of the
democratic principles of the dignity, equality and mutual
respect of men, and by the propagation, in their place,
through ignorance and prejudice, of the doctrine of the
inequality of men and races" ; and"that the wide diffusion
of culture, and the education of humanity for justice and
liberty and peace, are indispensable to the dignity of man
and constitute a sacred duty which all the nations must
fulfil in a spirit of mutual assistance and concern."This is
why I consider that one of the major tasks undertaken by
the United Nations is the new declaration of human rights,
to the drafting of which Unesco is contributing.
1947-Unesco General Conference (Mexico City)
Ju ! ian Huxtey
Director-General of Unesco
from 1946 to 1948
Ten points for a crucial
self-appraisal
I would like to ask member states toexamine critically and dispas ionate-
ly what they themselves are doing in education, science
and culture and to examine it against the yardstick of the
aims and purposes laid down in our Constitution.
W Are you examining scientifically your problems of govern-
ment and of social and economic organization, with the aid
of advice from the best specialists and in a dispassionate
spirit of science ; or are you treating them as they arise
on an essentially political basis, and in the light only of
emotional or material interests ? Are you profiting by the
experience of other countries in the field of administration,
by studying their methods and sending your young men
to be trained abroad ?
W Are you allowing that full freedom of press and opinion,
of expression, research and teaching, which is laid down
in our Constitution ?
. Are you profiting by the experience of the various
countries which have been attempting, in such fields as radio
or film, to combine freedom in presenting different points
of view with same reasonable degree of control ?
. Are you attempting to use natural science to the full,
whether in education, to give to your citizen a proper
understanding of the method and the actual and potential
Q ;'"oa :
ci
ou'"0< :
: >
o
Õ. < :a.
ouU>'"c
: : : >
6
Õ- Ca
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
achievements of science, or in practice, in the solution
of concrete problems ?
. Have you taken adequate steps towards the conservation
of nature in your country-whether for economic, or social,
or aesthetic reasons ?
. What have you done to preserve and make known your
cultural heritage ? Have you taken steps to preserve your
historical and ancient monuments, to unearth further re-
mains of your past history, to exhibit its treasures and
make them known to the world at large ?,
. Have you taken steps to remove the scourge of
illiteracy from your people ?
W Have you provided the possibility of higher education
for all classes of your population ?
. Have you taken pains to provide the best architecture
for your public buildings, and have you encouraged the
creative artist, whether in painting or music, in literature or
drama, to express the spirit of his country and to make life,
more interesting and more worthwhile for its people ?
W I will ask one final but over-riding question : Have you
looked at your problems from a Unesco angle-that is to
say not merely as national problems but as part of a
single world problem, where several nations must learn
to make adjustments in the interests of the whole body
of nations ? I think of such problems as over-population,
facilities for study abroad, the utilization and conservation
of natural resources, the making available to the world
of the treasures of national art and history, or the removal
of those sources of social discontent which are too often
the seeds of war.
1948-Unesco General Conference (Beirut)
Reinhold Niebuhr
Member of the United States dele-
gation to the 4th session of the
Unesco General Conference
Nations don't always
get along too well but...
CAY we really create world commun-pity by asking sov reign States to
think beyond themselves, to relate themselves to other
peoples, to remove from their texbooks all matters pre-
judicial to and inviting contempt of other peoples, to throw
down barriers and every kind of restraint which prevent
people from speaking to one another ? Is it really possible
to create community in this way, considering that the world
community is a hopelessly pluralistic community, and that
every community we have known in history had some core
of homogeneity, which is what the world community lacks ?
To create world community is indeed a difficult prob-
lem, but it is not an impossible one. Those of us who
deal with the problems of Unesco have had some exper-
ience of this, and, we might add, that even if on occasions
we should regard the problem as hopeless we may bear
in mind that every modern community, though it has a
core of homogeneity that the world community lacks, is,
at the same time, a much more pluralistic community than
anything that was known a hundred or two hundred years
ago.
I think that in the Middle Ages it was assumed that there
must be a unified culture if there was to be peace. We
have proved the medieval period wrong for in every one
of our modern nations we have all kinds of ethnic and
cultural, religious, and linguistic pluralisms.
We don't always get along too well, but we do get along.
1949-Unesco General Conference (Paris)
Maria Montessori
Member of the Italian delegation
to the 5th session of the Unesco
General Conference
Tuning in on youth
NOWT merely children, but young peopleas a whole are undoubtedly full of
energy and resources, to which we have paid insufficient
attention. We, who have always concentrated on the
problem of teaching and transmitting our knowledge to
young people, never seem to have thought that, conversely,
we have so much to learn from them, so much of the
hidden resources of human nature itself. We should be ever
on the look-out for what young people, through their lives
and activities, have to teach us in this way.
. I think, therefore, that if Unesco one day decided to
regard children as a factor in the reconstruction of the
world and the establishment of peace, and tried to enlist
their aid, organize them, discuss matters with them and
make use of everything they have to teach us, this would
be of great assistance in breathing fresh life into this society,
which must be built up not by one section of men, but
by all men, from the beginning of their lives onward. It is
the young people, the children, upon whom we may base
our hopes of building a better world, since they can give
us more than we in fact have today, and more than we
at one time had but have since lost.
1950-Unesco General Conference (Florence)
Jaime lorries Bodet
Director-General of Unesco
from 1948 to 1952
An indivisible responsibility
N HE destiny of mankind is an indiv-isible responsibility which we all must
share. So long as it remains possible to flout with impunity
even one of the rights of one single human being, the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights will continue to
accuse us all of cowardice, sluggishness, laziness, and to
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
NN'"'"T3
. l :
toCI>
0U
: J.
Q
o
Õ. < :0..
>
JO... J
o"'"Q)c
: J
o
Õ. < :0..
o
0
=>
; D
ÕI ;"-
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
remind us that we are lacking in human charity. So long
as the greater part of the human race continues to live
face to face with hunger and injustice and to die in squalor
and ignorance, the Declaration adopted in Paris will
represent nothing more than a remote ideal.
To make the Declaration known everywhere is to wage
a world-wide campaign for a life worthy of man, to whom
the governments have dedicated this Declaration, not in
mere lip service, but in solemn recognition of their duties
to civilization and to humanity.
To help states carry out these duties in the field of educ-
ation, science and culture is the proud mission of Unesco.
1949-Celebration of the first anniversary of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights (Paris)
Luther Evans
Director-General of Unesco
(1953-1958)
Ever-increasing collaboration
for the common task
UNESCO is young, but it is maturingrapidly ; we must all strive for it to
become fully mature ; Unesco is weak, but it is growing
stronger ; we must strive to speed up its accession of
strength ; Unesco is searching for the best modalities of
action to achieve peace and progress through education,
science and culture, and in this it has made surprising
progress in seven years ; we must concentrate on the
objective of determining consciously what types of activities
and what methods and procedures are fruitful and give
them priority over others. Unesco has not yet fully develop-
ed its most appropriate and most fruitful relationship to
the associations and groups of creative intellectual workers
of the world, although much of great value has been done ;
we must understand more fully, and help these workers
themselves more fully to understand that their work of
mind and spirit is essential for the forward progress of
civilization, and we must secure their ever-increasing
collaboration in the common task...
1953-Unesco General Conference, 2nd Extraordinary
Session (paris)
Vittorino Veronese
Director-General of Unesco
from 1958 to 1961
Realities and paradoxes
48 WITHIN Unesco I see the well-springs
of several contrasting forces and
currents. Yet far from feeling dismay,) regard this as
proof that we are indeed at grips with the realities of life,
not merely sailing in the clouds.
A first antithesis derives from the inter-governmental char-
acter of Unesco. Unesco inevitably expresses a political
resolve, however democratic the procedures by which that
resolve is taken ; and though operating at an interñational
level, it remains governmental in composition. But Unesco's
work is done in the spheres of education, science, culture
and mass communication which are in principle the freest,
in one sense the most personal and, being the most creative
of man's activities, should also be the most independent.
This gives rise to a second antithesis-that between the
demands of intellectual life and the administrative and
financial resources on which it must depend. The first
are limitless ; the second strictly rationed. Yet the two
have to be reconciled in practical decisions, invariably
involving sacrifices.
For educationists, scholars and artists it is a bitter
experience to learn that the noblest arguments must needs
yield all too often to those of a material order. To learn to
take into account all these factors which, as they are
assembled, gradually bring about a balance permitting
action and progress, is hard, but salutary.
There is yet another paradox-perhaps the most profound
of a ! !-which Unesco has to overcome. It strives to maintain
a strict and dispassionate neutrality towards philosophies,
systems, political beliefs and religions. Yet it cannot remain
alien, deaf and blind to the noblest expressions of human
thought, to the anxieties of our modern world, to the
yearning and quest for a code of social ethics to match
the century of nuclear discoveries and interplanetary
conquest. No ! impartiality is not indifference.
1958-Unesco General Conference (Paris)
Mohammed H Fasi
Head of the delegation of Morocco
to the 11th session of the Unesco
General Conference and present
chairman of the Unesco Executive
Board.
The year of Africa
t his year, which I would call Africa'syear, has indeed been a memorable
one for our continent. The accession to independence of
all these brother nations, who come to enrich the cultural
patrimony of mankind, is a happy omen for the future of
the world and of peace.
Welcome ! my dear brothers of Africa to your home, to
this home of the mind, to which we, as Africans, be we
white, brown or black, have a duty to bring the stamp of
our civilization and our culture. We all have need of
Unesco and of all the countries which are ahead of us on
the path of progress. But it is also true that in a human
sense the world will be enriched by the discovery of this
great continent, knowledge of which was supposedly
acquired from exotic works and colourful descriptions.
Today, it is Africa's own sons who come to express them-
selves freely and to make known to the world the wealth of
poetry and art which this continent conceals.
7960-unesco General Conference (Paris)
oU
NGO< : 
: J
o
Õ.. c :! l.
co
Q
E
4 :
: ;
oo'"7c
: : >
o
Õ. < :<l.
J
OI
NN
C: >Q)
ù :
. 1
<. : J
I
L
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Jawaharlal Nehru
Prime Minister of India
(died 1964)
Four a synthesis of science
and culture
education by itself does not necessar-. ily lead to a conversion of minds
towards peaceful purposes. Something more is necessary,
new standards, new values, and perhaps a kind of spiritual
background and a feeling of commonness of mankind.
That commonness of humanity is already being brought
about by technological progress, but the minds of men
have not grasped it or kept pace with technological pro-
gress. So, we see that science and technology which have
brought so many benefits to the world and gradually tend
to go towards the formation of one world, are also used
to the manufacture of terrible weapons of mass destruction.
At the base of it, all is fear and hatred.
How then can we get rid of this fear and hatred and
use modern scientific progress in the cause of peace and
tolerance ?
We in India, as in many other countries of Asia and
Africa, are trying to develop ourselves so as to put an end
to our poverty and raise the standards of hundreds of
millions of our people. This cannot be done without the
help of science and modern techniques. The problem
before us is whether in adopting the methods and tech-
niques of science we might not create a society full of
internal conflict and the urge for power which brings it
into conflict with other groups. Can we succeed in
bringing about a synthesis of modern science with
something of the spiritual background which has en-
nobled life throughout the ages.
Unesco has set the right ideal before it to try to turn
the minds of men, and the way it is trying to do so is
not the direct method of facing our many problems and
conflicts, but the indirect way of creating appreciation and
understanding of art and culture. Presumably this is a
surer method of dealing with these problems than the
direct political method, though of course both methods
have to be tried.
1962-Visit to Unesco (paris)
Norair Sissakian
President of the 13th session of the
Unesco General Conference
(died 1966)
Confounding the pessimists
NOTCHING shows the importanceoaf education better an the popular
saying that an illiterate man is incapable of seeing even
from a mountain top. Education is of the greatest economic
and social importance especially nowadays when the
harmonious development of man's mental and physical
faculties must satisfy the needs of all sections of society,
serving as an essential basis for continued progress.
One example we may quote is the work of S. G. Strumilin,
a member of the Soviet Academy, who'has attempted to
assess the economic consequences of the development of
education. Prof. Strumilin has reached the following
conclusion : the value of the work done by a person who
has had four year's primary education is 43 % greater
than that of an illiterate person, 108 % greater if he has
had a secondary school education and 300 % times greater
if he had a higher education.
The close links between science and education and the
growing role of science in our modern society have led
Unesco to accord a priority to science in its programme
similar to that already given to education. It is impossible
to speak of the effectiveness of education if its results arenot incorporated in technical and scientific projects and
do not lead to the solution of technical and scientific
problems. In turn, the effectiveness of education is
determined by scientific and technical achievement.
Certain fears have been voiced in the past-and unfor-tunatety are still being repeated by some people-that
our ptanet's sources of energy are being rapidly exhausted
and that we shall be unable to feed an increasingly vast
population. Present-day achievements in the natural sciences
and in technology have answered these fears and show
that all grounds for pessimism are unfounded.
1964  Unesco General Conference (Paris)
Rene Maheu
Director-General of Unesco
since 1962
To all young people
twenty years old
May thoughts and my good wishes goout especially to ou, young people
all over the wor'd, who wi ! ! be twenty this year...
Unesco is your age ; like yourselves it will be celebrating
its twentieth birthday in 1966.
There is no doubt that between you and Unesco there
are those affinities, that spontaneous fellow-feeling which
historians find in a given generation like the very air it
breathes. May there be between you and Unesco an
understanding no less great than this resemblance which will
gradually be revealed in the mirror of history...
We live in an age when the reign of Man in his full
universality is being organized. States have set up instit-
utions designed to establish it step by step. The peoples
of the world must support those institutions and help them
forward.
Unesco is one such agency. Born at the same time as
yourselves, it was created for you. It has grown up with
you, it is through you that it will come to be what it
must be...
1966-From a message to young people for the New Year
c :
: ã
ooUNN<II7c :
=>
o
Õ. < :a
? !n : t
C
7
O
O
L
aCL j
! I
il
dJ
Q
OU
N
0'
õ
"-
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
THE STAMP OF ; UNffiSCO
The first Unesco stamp (be) ow) eft) was issued by France in 1946
whn tie, hewty-created organization held its first General Confer.
ence in Parts. Since that time hundreds of Unesco stamps have
been issued by member states. Some have commemorated mite'
stones in Unesco's history ; others have helped tOp'ubfjcizeUnecp's
aims. and fitS worrdwide programme in education, sèiènce'andcultùre.
Here. we'P8 ! 1t aselctlonf,. om twenty years of Unesco stamps
EGVAÐOR
Unesco's contribution
to the estabtishment of
a marine biotogy sta-
tion (Charts : Darwin
Research Foundation)
on Galapagos (stands.
. !'I ! CI\$AGI
Statmpt ftoM) fou of the 20 pn-
Þi"--COemoratedtþe'r
fatten of tincds new heedqa$rters
biUt-oiIin'. În'PâiÎs'"'958 ;--, ,' ;'- ;,-JtS,,',.", I\.,,.....", "",
- JAPAN
Commemoration of Unesco's 15th nniversary in 1961
NICARAGUA ARGENTINA LIBERIA
Un"scd. Msetvlc"stamp.
issued in, France and valid
onlyf,,", use'on, letters posted
at Uneseo's H. Q.
Four pf $3 ; írtalnpsissue'd"n the.. f5th anniversâry of the Univers41
Dectaration of Human Rtghts (1963) recatt Unesco's rote in promoting
univftr$alrftspectfor human rights.
GAMEROON CONGO.. (BiWîÂVII.. ; : E).
BURUNDI
 ANNIVERSAlltE _
DELA
 DECLARATI02i,
" , UNIVERSBLLE', DENS DROITS 
n D$C$0
T ? co ; T. I
'MEe&
IVORY COAST
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Over 40 governments issued stamps supporting Unesco's campaign to save the monu-
ments of Nubia. Receipts from many stamp sales were donated to campaign funds.
ALGERIA TUNISIA AFGHANISTAN
Commemoration of Unesco con-
ference on development of high-
er education in Africa, 1962.
MADAGASCAR
Commemoration of UN.
and Unesco efforts to
combat illiteracy.
UNITD NATIONS
Launching of International
Hydrological Decade by
Unesco, 1965.
NIGER
Unesco's participation in the
first Balkans Film Festival,
at Varna, 1965.
BULGARIA
inauguration of Regional
Textbook Production Cen-
tre created by Unesco at
Yaounde. Cameroon, 1961.
CAMEROON
Commemoration of World
Congress on the Eradication
of tttiteracy, convened by
Unesco in Teheran, 1965.
) RAN
One of the stamps with
which some 70 nations
are this'year marking
Unesco's 20th birthday.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
IN 50 QUESTIONS
D Has Unesco', s membershipincrease in the past 20 years ?
It has increased sixfold. Unesco (the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization) legally
came into being on November 4, 1946, when twenty states
ratified the Constitution which had been drawn up at the
London Conference a year earlier. Today Unesco has
120 member states. Many of these are young nations
that cast off colonial rule and set out to determine their
own destinies. The past two decades have seen the birth
of some sixty new nations, principally in Africa, the Middle
East and Asia. These nations want not only political
freedom for their people but a higher standard of living
for themselves and their chi ! dren. This"revolution of rising
expectations", as it has been called, has had a profound
effect on the evolution of the work of Unesco and the
whole United Nations family in recent years.
 How does Unesco fit into the
U United Nations family ?
Unesco is a specialized agency of the United Nations
but both constitutionally and financially it is independent of
the United Nations though its work is co-ordinated with
the U. N. and the other specialized agencies through the
U. N. Economic and Social Council.
This independence has a very practical importance
because experience has shown that states which may differ
politically and ideologically in the United Nations itself are
able and indeed eager to work closely together in such
areas as education, science and culture (Unesco), health
and sanitation (WHO), or food and agricu ! ture (FAO).
Furthermore, this working together can itself help to break
down the barriers of suspicion and distrust which divide
mankind.
m What are Unesco's main aims
ant purposes ?
To help build a solid foundation for peace. Peace is
the central purpose of the entire United Nations family but
it is approached in different ways by different members of
the family. The U. N. itself concentrates largely on the
political aspects of peace and collective security. Its main
concern is the keeping of peace-the prevention of armed
conflict, although it has an abiding interest in social
questions through the Economic and Social Council.
Unesco, on the other hand, and the other specialized
agencies of the U. N., are concerned with building peace,
laying the foundations for lasting peace through action in
the areas of their special competence.
Ð How does Unesco contribute towold peace ?
Unesco contributes to world peace in three principal
ways : First, by encouraging international intellectual
collaboration in the fields of education, science, culture
and mass communication. Nations which are working
together for the common good of mankind are less likely
to be interested in fighting one another.
Secondly, by furnishing operational assistance to its
member states to aid in their social and economic develop-
ment, in order to reduce the glaring inequalities in standards
of living that are a major cause of international tensions
and war.
Thirdly, through ethical action in favour of human rights
and international understanding. As Unesco's Constitution
notes :"a peace based exclusively upon political and econo-
mic arrangements of governments would not be a peace
which could secure the unanimous, lasting and sincere
support of the peoples of the world, and peace must
therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the intellectual
and moral solidarity of mankind."
R What is Unesco's budget and
Eft who pays for it ?
Unesco's programme and budget are determined and
voted by the General Conference which meets every two
years. The delegates to the General Conference are official
representatives of all the governments belonging to Unesco,
and each state contributes to Unesco's budget according
to a scale based on gross national product.
Unesco's first budget for 1947 totalled $7, 000, 000. Its
proposed budget for the two year period 1967-68 is
$62, 000, 000.
Unesco also has at its disposal extra-budgetary funds
which have increased sharply in recent years lentil they
are now as great as Unesco's regular budget. A total of
over $80 million'has been allocated to Unesco under
the United Nations Technical Assistance Programme since
it was launched in 1950 to aid economic and social develop-
ment. And Unesco has already received more than $91
million under the United Nations Special Fund which was
created in 1960 to encourage the flow of investment capital
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
needed for economic expansion. It is largely thanks to
these two major sources of economic and social aid
(brought together and integrated as the United Nations
Development Programme on January 1, 1966) that Unesco
is able to finance its operational action.
Unesco has been able to extend its prog, ramme still
further, especially in the field of education, by carrying
out projects in co-operation with other institutions which
have financed these activities. Three examples : The United
Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees
(over $76 million in 15 years) ; The United Nations Children's
Fund ($21 million in four years) ; The International Bank for
Reconstruction and Development (over $50 million in loans
to member states).
ttJttSt) JTn [< : 3hM ! Nr [<1jU ! ! r ? 1).
. intellectual
^.
'co-operation
1 1 -. 1
A How does Unesco promote
I ! J international intellectual
co-operation ?
Three main tasks are assigned to Unesco by its Consti-
tution :"To increase and diffuse knowledge ; give fresh
impulse to popular education and to the spread of
knowledge ; collaborate in the work of advancing the mutual
knowledge and understanding of peoples."
International intellectual co-operation was thus the
function that was uppermost in the minds of the men who
founded Unesco, and it includes the sorts of activities which
most people generally associate with Unesco-meetings
of experts and international conferences on major problems ;
co-ordination of international research programmes ; sta-
tistical and documentation services ; specialized publications
including source books and reference works ; and the
elaboration of international agreements in the fields of
education, science, culture and mass communications. In
the words of its present Director-Genera !, Rene Maheu,
Unesco set out to develop and co-ordinate"the intellectual
infrastructure of modern civilization in its broad univer-
sality."
CONTINUED ON PAGE 62 Photo &commat; Sciaky
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
Young artists from Paris
schools bring their
sketchbooks to Unesco H. Q.
Above, children settle down
in front of the Wall of the Moon,
a decorative mural in ceramic
by Spanish artists, Joan Miró
and Jose Llorens-Artigas.
Below, others find inspiration
in the Japanese garden.
How youngsters
see Unesco
"It's a big building where countries from all over the world work together
to do away with wars", explained a 13-year-old schoolboy, after
visiting Unesco H. Q. in Paris."I know what war is", he added."My
parents suffered a lot in the last one. At Unesco people meet to talk
things over. They try not to quarrel, and that must be very difficult ; and
they explain their ideas". Accompanied by their teachers, children from
art classes in several Paris schools recently came to look at Unesco H. Q,
Afterwards, these youthful (8 to 15 years old) artists portrayed some
of the things about Unesco that had impressed them most. On these
pages we are happy to present a short selection of their paintings which
depict Unesco as seen through young eyes.
Photos Unesco-Dominique Roger
the Earth, a man reaching up, higher and higher, and
the other man bringing fire that gets lighter and lighter
until you can't see it at wall,"
for science and learning and friendship."
PEACE. By Agnes Kende (aged 14),
International Lycee Oasses, Sevres.
"1 wanted to show Peace in my painting
of Unesco,"said Agnes."So I painted
a dove and the big stone with the Japan-
ese word for peace cut in it. And
1 put in Calder's mobile because I like
it so much."
PROMETHEUS. By Claire Weulersse
(aged 9), Atelier d'education par I'art,
Paris.
Claire's painting was inspired by the
big mural of Rufino Tamayo, decorating
the Main Commission room at Unesco.
"I liked it right away,"she said,"and
then I was told it was the legend of
Prometheus giving fire to the world.
But I see it as the big sun which brings
us warmth."
COLOURS OF FIRE. By Judy McDivitt
(aged 14), International Lycee Classes,
Sevres.
Judy also chose Tamayo's"Prome-
thew.""/'m not very good at draw-
ing,"she said,"but I felt I could paint
Prometheus in my own way. rocks for
fs now I see unesco ; al/tne peoples working togetner
colour page, opposite :
MIGHTY MOBILE. By Jean-Marc Adler
(aged13), Ate) ierd'educationpar)'art,
Paris.
"1 chose the big mobile of Alexander
Calder because I like everything that
is full of movement and life,"explained
Jean-Marc."And I like everything
modern, which ; s why/e Unesco."
centre colour pages :
CLASPED HANDS. By Dominic Hall
(aged 13), International Lycee Classes,
Sevres.
"/patnted the hands that are joined
throuah Unesco"said Dominic."That
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
Colour page, opposite
THE SIX PATIOS. By Jai Imbrey (aged
13). International Lycee Classes, Sevres.
'/was/mpressed by Unesco's modern
buildings and the way they contrast with
the Eiffel Tower, and also by the under-
ground patios when you see them from the
7th floor. I spelt the French word'defense"
on the wall ; th a'c'./'m not very good
at French spelling", admitted U. S.-born jay.
Bottom
SMOOTH AND FULL OF FRIDGES, By
Franz Merkling (aged 13), Ate ! ier d'educa-
tion par I'art, Paris.
"What struck me most of all was Unesco's
big conference building,"said Franz."It's
smooth and yet it's full of ridges. I also
like Calder's mobile, so I put it in, though I
know you can't see them the way I show-
ed them. And I painted Miró's wall because
it has lovely colours."
THE NEW
ARCHITECTURE
OF UNESCO
On its 19th anniversary, November 4, 1965,
Unesco inaugurated a fourth building on its
Paris headquarters site. When the first
three headquarters buildings were inaugu-
rated in November 1958, Unesco had 87
member states. Today it has 120 and its
activities have grown in proportion.
A project to build a 10-storey structure was
abandoned because of city planning re-
strictions. So instead of buitding up,
Unesco built down, following a plan de-
signed by the French architect, Bernard
Zehrfuss. The existing piazza area in front
of the existing buildings was excavated to
a depth of 33 feet and from this 2-1/2 acre
site, 156, 000 cubic yards of earth were
removed. In this huge excavation 350 of-
fices and two conference rooms were built
around six patios (above right), each mea-
suring 82 by 49 feet. Below these, a
garage for 350 cars was built. The two
floors of office buildings look out on the
patios (photo right) and thus have natural
light and ventilation and are insulated from
noise. Each patio has pools and fountains,
pebbles and marble flags, and beds of
plants, shrubs and grasses following a
layout designed by the Brazilian landscape
architect, Bur) e Marx.
Photo Unesco-R. Lesage
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
Photo Unesco-R. Lesage
Ha a million
visitors
Unesco's strikingly modern headquarters,
now a familiar Paris landmark, has also
become one of the city's most visited sites
since it was inaugurated in November
1958. In eight years, half a million people
have looked over its Secretariat building
(left), the Conference building and the De-
legations building. The headquarters was
designed by an international panel of
architects : Marcel Breuer (U. S. A.), Pier
Luigi Nervi (Italy) and Bernard Zehrfuss
(France). The whole is embellished with
paintings, sculpture and mosaics by
internationally-known artists : Jean Arp,
Jean Bazaine (France), Karel Appel
(Netherlands), Afro (Italy), Alexander
Calder (U. S. A.), Roberto Matta (Chile),
Pablo Picasso, Joan Miro, Jose Llorens-
Artigas (Spain), Henry Moore (U. K.) and
Rufino Tamayo (Mexico). In addition, a
number of Unesco's member states con-
tributed to the decoration and furnishing
of the headquarters. Below, a corner of
the Japanese garden, designed and laid
out by Isamu Noguchi (Japan).
Building
for the future
Uneseo plans to ex-
pand its headquarters
in Paris to keep pace"
with its growing activ-
ities and responsibil-
ities. Work on this
fifth building, sited a
few hundred yards
from the existing head-
quarters, will begin this
year and should be
complete by the end
of 1968. Right, model
of the new building.
It will have 600 offices,
and was designed by
the French architect,
Bernard Zehrfuss.
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
The facade of Unesco's Secretariat building towers
over one of the six patios inaugurated on November 4, 1965.
Two floors of office buildings look out on the patios.
Photos 0 Pau ! Aimasy, Paris
Two new conference rooms have been built
around the patios. Above, the star-shaped ceiling
of the Unesco Executive Board hall.
Photo Unesco-Domin ! que Roger
61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
D What do the Unesco Nationalcommissions do ?
Unesco differs from most of the U. N. specialized
agencies in that it is closely linked to the governments
and the peoples of its member states through National
Commissions for Unesco set up in virtually every country
(112 out of 120 Unesco member states). These Commis-
sions have come to play an indispensable role not only as
consultative and liaison bodies with national groups
interested in education, science, culture and mass commu-
nications, but in the actual execution of Unesco's pro-
gramme on the national and regional level.
National Commissions are closely linked with the govern-
ment services of their own country, with public and private
institutions as well as with the Nationat Commissions of
other Unesco member states particularly on a regional
basis. They bring together the most eminent people in
education, science and the arts, and are increasingly
becoming a key means at Unesco's disposal for the
organizing of seminars and training courses, regional or
international meetings, the appointment of experts, spe-
cialists and delegates, the carrying out of national surveys
and inquiries, the preparation of special projects as well
as regional technical aid programmes and a host of other
activities which make Unesco a living reality and enable it
to fulfil its mission by reaching down to all levels of
the population in its member states. (The Russian, Arabic,
Italian and Japanese editions of the. Unesco Courier, for
instance, are produced under the direct auspices of the
National Commissions of the U. S. S. R., the UAR., Italy and
Japan. The German edition is the co-operative effort of
the National Commissions of Switzerland, Austria and the
Federal Republic of Germany.)
iii How does Unesco work with
I ! J non-governmental organizations ?
Experience acquired during the 20 years of Unesco's
existence has demonstrated clearly that co-operation
between Unesco and non-governmental organizations
(NGOs) is one of Unesco's most effective means of action.
This co-operation has placed at the disposal of Unesco
documentation assembled by NGOs in all fields of Unesco's
activities. It has secured the services of a vast network
of specialists throughout the word who are able to provide
effective collaboration and whose aims, ideals and activities
are closely linked with those of Unesco. It has relieved
Unesco of important tasks which could only have been
undertaken at considerable expense and with a much
larger staff. And it has enabled Unesco to reach a wide
and varied public whose friendly interest affords valuable
support.
The international NGOs include specialized bodies such
as the World Confederation of Organizations of the
Teaching Profession, the International Council of Scientific
Unions, the International Social Science Council and NGOs
dealing with universities, philosophy, theatre, music,
museums, libraries, monuments, etc... as well as numerous
non-specialized organizations, such as the World Fede-
ration of United Nations Associations which have given
Unesco continued support.
At present 250 educational, scientific and cultural non-
governmental organizations representing the different cultu-
ral regions of the world co-operate closely with Unesco in
the execution of its programme. During 1965 alone subven-
tions totalling $1, 393, 500 were granted to 32 NGOs, and
in 1965 contracts with 72 non-governmental organizations
amounted to a total of $478, 000. In addition Unesco granted
financial assistance to five new projects carried out by
NGOs under the scheme of associated youth activities.
Unesco has long urged the expansion of NGOs in Asia,
Africa and Latin America, and the progress which has
been'made in recent years, notably in the number of
national bodies affiliated with the non-governmental
organizations and in meetings held by them in Asia, Africa
and Latin America are extremely heartening. Here Unesco
member states and National Commissions have had an
increasingly important role to play in encouraging the
formation in their own countries of groups of educators,
scholars, intellectuals and specialists who can join existing
non-governmental organizations and thus help to make
these bodies effectively more international.
fm Research is a major factor in
my scientific devetopment. What
has Unesco done in this field ?
When Unesco was first established in 1946, the interna-
tional scientific community had been shattered by theevents of World War II. One of Unesco's first tasks was
to restore its unity. This was done first of all by reinforcing
the structure and helping to intensify the research and
other work of the International Council of Scientific Unions
(tCSU) and by creating such organizations as the Council
UNESCO IN 50 QUESTIONS (Continuedfrompage53)
62
iris Why does Unesco attach such
Importance to international
congresses and seminars ?
Unesco attaches the utmost importance to international
conferences and seminars as one of the most effective
means of bringing together scientists, scholars and other
specialists from all over the world. These meetings
encourage the free flow and exchange of ideas and infor-
mation, and promote mutual discussion. They have been
instrumental in helping to launch large-scale programmes
of international co-operation.
In recent years major conferences have been convened
on information processing (1959), adult education (1960),
oceanography (1960), hydrology (1964), problems of youth
(1964), the eradication of illiteracy (1965). Major regional
conferences for Asia, the Arab States, Africa and Latin
America have dealt with educational planning and its rela-
tionship to economic and social development, the conser-
vation and exploitation of natural resources, the application
of science and technology to development, and the develop-
ment of the mass media.
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
for International Organizations of Medical Sciences and
the Union of International Engineering Organizations.
Unesco helped initiate a series of international research
projects which were not only extremely fruitful in their
scientific results but also helped create a spirit of mutual
co-operation and understanding.
In 1952, Unesco helped set up the European Centre for
Nuclear Research (CERN) which has done pioneer work in
the exploration of the atom for peaceful purposes. The
International Geophysical Year, initiated by ICSU and
sponsored by Unesco, was a world-wide scientific venture
involving more than 80 nations in a common effort. The
International Hydrological Decade, initiated by Unesco, is
co-ordinating research and the collection of data on water
resources around the world. And the Inter-governmental
Oceanographic Commission has brought about interna-
tional collaboration in the investigation of the oceans.
con Oceanography and hydrologyL/J have become two major bran-
ches of world science. What has
been Unesco's role in promoting
co-operation in these fields ?
A new type of co-operation appeared in 1960 with the
creation of the Inter-governmental Oceanographic Commis-
sion, followed in 1964 by that of the Co-ordinating Council
for the International Hydrological Decade. Through these
bodies, which are integrated into Unesco, countries can
tailor their own work to fit into mutually agreed research
and study programmes. They can thus place greater
resources and facilities at the disposal of the international
community without giving up the autonomy of their own
undertakings.
Oceanography provides an illustration of how Unesco,
with a comparatively small budget, can accomptish impres-
sive results through its work of direction and co-ordination.
Unesco has an oceanography budget of only $250, 000 a
year, yet it co-ordinates international projects totalling more
than $15, 000, 000 annually.
One of the most spectacular successes of the Unesco
oceanography effort was the International Indian Ocean
Expedition, 1959-1965. This ocean covers roughly 14 per
cent of the world's surface, and in the countries
surrounding it live more than 700 million people, almost
a quarter of the earth's population. Yet in 1959, scientists
literally knew more about the near side of the moon than
they knew about this vast sea.
The six-year research programme which ended last
year explored every facet of the Indian Ocean-topography
of the ocean floor, currents, winds, water temperatures and
salinity, plant life and animal life. Taking part in the effort
were 40 oceanographic vessels from 15 nations, and
scientists and marine biological stations from 25 countries.
The data from this great expedition are now being pro-
cessed and anatysed, but it is already clear that the Indian
Ocean is a practically inexhaustible source of food for
the peoples of the world, and the impact of this one
research effort will be felt for generations to come.
For the Hydrological Decade launched in 1965, a promis-
ing start has been made with the creation of hydrological
committees in 90 countries in the international effort to
obtain better knowledge of the earth's water cycle to meet
the world's growing water shortage.
m Unesco has sponsored many
IIiJ international agreements. What
are some of the important ones ?
The Universal Copyright Convention (ratified by 53 states) ;
Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in the
Event of Armed Conflict (53 ratifications) ; Convention
against Discrimination in Education (30 ratifications) ; Agree-
ment on the Importation of Educational, Scientific and Cul-
tural Materials (49 ratifications).
Unesco and the International Labour Organization are
now preparing a Recommendation on the professional,
social and economic status of teachers, and Unesco, at
the request of the U. N. Economic and Social Council, is
preparing a draft declaration on the principles of inter-
national cultural co-operation.
m How many book titles has
Mali Unesco published, and what are
some of its best sellers ?
Over 4, 000 titles have been published by Unesco directly
or indirectly since 1946. Unesco itself publishes no less
than 50 titles each year (in addition to a dozen periodicals)
CONTINUE ON PAGE 65
m When did Unesco launch its
) LM arid zone research programme ?
The programme was proposed as early as 1948 and
was launched in the 1950s. From 1957 to 1962 it was
one of Unesco's three Major Projects (the other two : pro-
motion of better understanding of the cultural values of
the Orient and the Occident, and the promotion of primary
education in Latin America).
Unesco's arid land programme for the desert and semi-
desert regions that cover one-third of the land surface of
the earth is a striking example of how Unesco has aided in-
ternational scientific research. Hundreds of scientists from
some 40 countries took part in this world-wide enterprise,
participated in some 20 international symposiums dealing
with problems of salinity, climatology, wind and solar
energy, plant, human and animal ecology, etc. The biblio-
graphy of the studies and research carried out on arid
zone problems totals an impressive 28 volumes. Over a
dozen institutions received grants-in-aid.
m What other types of research
U ! J has Unesco carried out ?
In 1959 and 1960, with the help of about a hundred
international organizations, national research centres in
42 countries and more than 250 specialists from all over
the world, Unesco undertook a major survey of the main
trends in scientific research in the world. This survey has
been hailed in scientific circles everywhere and has come
to be considered an indispensable tool for science planning
services in the developing countries. Unesco began a
similar survey in 1965 on research trends in the social and
human sciences.
Joint surveys have been carried out by Unesco and the
tntern'ationat Association of Universities on access to
higher education in the world ; on the role of universities
in South-East Asia, and on inter-university co-operation
in Africa.
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
WBMBTBN
AWitWiMnMttM
SEQMMMmBN
tSBBBS3SSEaBn3NtBENuBSiEEBBN
wStxASB3BZBEBBE3BEB3Et
W Id"
In 1950 the ratio between professional staff members at Unesco headquarters in
oar V Ine W Paris ant these locate in afield position aground the world wars 10 tao I. In 1966, for
every 3 processional posts in Paris there where 5 in the afield (yin factual figure 368 to
oaf U n esco's 36 in 1950 ant 635 tao 1, 067 in April 1966). Between 1960 ant the send oaf 1965, theumber oaf afieldposts (esse tial y operational ones) morse han doubted. Our map
shows where Unesco specialist (810), spent oust ant the bequest oaf ember statues,
O P e rant I"0 n a I ace I"0 n hand takes up thei post. in 9. 0 counties on pril 1, 196.. Along therm arse educator,teachers, economist , sCientists, archaeologists and ibranans.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
50 QUESTIONS (continued)
and another 50 titles are issued each year by commercial
publishers as co-editions with Unesco or under Unesco's
auspices.
. Unesco's biggest single best-seller title has been the
Unesco Source Book for Science Teaching-400, 000 copies
sold to date in 22 languages (French, English, Arabic, Chi-
nese, Singhalese, Korean, German, Spanish, Greek, Italian,
Japanese, Polish, Serbo-Croat, Indonesian, Amaric, Hindi,
Tamil, Swedish, Telegu, Gujerati, Marati, Thai). New edi-
tions are foreseen in Malay, Portuguese, Urdu, Bengali,
Persian, Hebrew, Czech, Dutch, Kannada and Turkish.
W Unesco Art Pocket Books. Almost a million copies
sold of 16 titles in nine languages published by Unesco
and private publishers.
. Scientific and Cultural History of Mankind. 290, 000
copies, including 150, 000 copies of New American Library-
Mentor paperback.
. Cultural Patterns and Technical Change, by Margaret
Mead. 25, 000 copies. First published by Unesco in
1953. Paperback by New American Library, 1955.
W The Race Question in Modern Science series. 8 volu-
mes. 170, 000 copies.
. Readings in the History of Mankind, 4 volumes. Mentor
paperbacks. 100, 000 copies.
But of course far and away Unesco's most important
best-seller is the Unesco Courier published in eight
languages (English, French, Spanish, German, Russian,
Italian, Arabic and Japanese).
Unesco has been gratified with the sale of some of its
more specialized books : Dictionary of the Social Sciences
(1<f, 000 copies) ; Study Abroad (13, 000 copies) ; All Men
Are Brothers-Life and Thought of Mahatma Gandhi (30, 000
copies) ; The Teaching of Reading and Writhing (22, 000
copies) ; Education and Mental Health (23, 000 copies).
i3 What are some of the other
*"* noteworthy books published by
Unesco or under its auspices ?
It is difficult to choose from the more than 4, 000 titles.
Many are highly technical and scientific works that have
made important contributions to education, science and
culture. Here, selected at random, are a few titles.
 World Survey of Education, a monumental study in four
volumes ;,. Index Translationum. an annual compendium
of the world's translations ;. Vacations Abroad ;  World
Communication, an up-to-date survey of the world's press,
radio, television and cinema facilities ;. Unesco World
Art Senses, 23 volumes published of little known treasures
of world art in high quality colour ;. Unesco Series of
Representative Works, 200 volumes published to date of
masterpieces of world literature in translation-one of the
great Unesco publishing ventures undertaken in collabo-
ration with the world's leading commercial publishers. A
particularly noteworthy effort has been made in this series
to make better known the literature of Asia, Africa and
Latin American as well as the literatures of the less known
European languages.
II-Operational assistance
1 --
m What is the place of operational
assistance in Unesco's present
programme ?
It is generally known that half the world's people go
to bed more or less hungry every night, that a child in
some countries can expect to live only half as long as
a child in other countries, that average annual income in
the richest nations can be as high as twenty times the
average of some of the poorer ones.
But it is perhaps less well known that 52 per cent of the
world's children of school age do not attend school be-
cause of lack of facilities or shortage of teachers ; that
two out of every five adults in the world can neither read
nor write ; that 97 countries have an adult illiteracy rate
of over 50 per cent, and 20 countries an adult illiteracy
rate of over 95 per cent ; that 70 per cent of the world's
population (about 1, 900 million people) have entirely in-
adequate information about their own countries and still
less information about other countries.
For a long time lack of resources limited Unesco's oper-
ational activities for the benefit of the developing countries,
but now the major portion of Unesco's work is geared to
development activities.
IE] What accounts
for this change in emphasis ?
Two reasons lie behind this stepped up effort.
First, the composition of Unesco has changed. Of its
120 member states two-thirds are developing countries.
Secondly, there has been the growing acceptance of the
fact that development is a world-wide phenomenon. It is
now abundantly clear that development depends largely-
indeed chiefly-on the rational use of human resources.
At the same time it is now recognized that education
and science are basic investments which condition all
development.
raj Do governments now spend
more money on education than
they formerly did ?
As a general rule, yes. Many countries now allocate
from 15 to 25 per cent of their national budgets to edu-CC
cation, and some African states are devoting as much""
as 30 per cent of their budgets to education. At impor-
tant regional conferences organized by Unesco since 1960
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
50 QUESTIONS (continued)
in Addis Ababa, Tananarive and Abidjan for the African
countries, in Beirut, Karachi and Tokyo for the countries
of Asia, and in Santiago for those of Latin America, the
developing countries have repeatedly demonstrated the
importance they attach to education and have set them-
selves specific targets. Indeed, for the first time, the rate
of increase of school enrolments in the world has out-
stripped the rate of population increase.
does the increase ion school
ß. ! J enrolment apply to
all levels of education ?
No. It mainly affects primary education. The over-all
picture is not very satisfactory. Take the case of Africa.
The chief goals the African states set themselves at Addis
Ababa were : universal primary education on the African
continent by 1980 ; 20 per cent of all children leaving pri-
mary schools to be enrolled in secondary schools ; and
university enrolment to reach a total of about 300, 000, as
compared with 31, 000, in 1961.
If the prospects seem good as regards primary education,
secondary education lags badly behind. Despite a high
drop-out in primary schools, more than half of the 30 mil-
lion children of school age in middle Africa are now expect-
ed to complete their primary education, but scarcely three
out of every hundred attend secondary school, and less
than two in a thousand have any chance of some form
of higher education.
In Latin America, the situation appears satisfactory at
first sight because schoo ! enrotment targets are being met
at various levels. Yet only 20 per cent of primary school
pupils finish school. Then too, in many parts of the
world the curriculum is not adapted to modern needs or
to the actual levels of development of different countries.
This means that many students, when they do graduate,
cannot find jobs that correspond to their education.
etc What is the effect of this critical
LU situation on the developing
countries ?
Extremely serious. Children who have had only one or
two years of schooling are prone to slip back quickly into
illiteracy. Although the world percentage of illiterates is
dropping (it now stands at about 40 per cent) Unesco has
found that the number of illiterates is actually increasing
because of rising populations. Nor are secondary schools
expanding fast enough to absorb even the relative increase
in the number of primary school graduates. This is a perm-
anent source of frustration for those youngsters unable to
continue their education and often accounts for the crises
of modern youth one hears so much about.
m Where is the main bottleneck
W in school enrolment ?
Unesco feels that efforts should be first concentrated
on expanding secondary education where the main bottle-
neck in school enrolment lies. This would provide more
primary school teachers and candidates for higher edu-
cation as well as much-needed middle-level technicians.
end What is the biggest obstacle
r ! ! J to the expansion of
secondary school education ?
Shortage of adequately trained teachers. Unesco is
giving this aspect of secondary education priority consid-
eration. By the end of 1965, Unesco was administering
in Africa alone tWenty secondary and advanced teacher-
training colleges set up in 17 countries with financial aid
from the U. N. Special Fund (now integrated into the United
Nations Development Programme). In 1965-66, 7, 400 stu-
dents were enrolled in these colleges, from which 1, 500 fully
qualified teachers graduated in 1965.
En What about the shortage
us of primary school teachers
in the developing countries ?
Unesco considers this one of the major problems of
the developing countries. The training of primary school
teachers is the main target of the Major Project for the
extension of primary education in Latin America, begun in
1957, and the emergency aid programme for Africa launch-
ed in 1960. Since 1962, the United Nations Children's Fund
has contributed about $21 million for joint Unicef/Unesco
projects mostly for primary education and science teaching.
Since the Latin American Major Project was begun, the
number of children in school has increased by more
than 11 million, an average of 1. 7 million per year, and
the number of children not in school fell both relatively
and absolutely in the years between 1957 and 1965.
Venezuela, for example, in lees than tive years doubled
its school population at all levels and built more schools
than were constructed in the whole of the preceding cen-
tury and a half.
In Latin America as a whole 380, 000 new teaching posts
have been created, and thousands of teachers have attend-
ed Unesco and OAS (Organization of American States)
education courses. The continent now has over one million
primary school teachers.
Latin America has one of the world's highest rates of
population growth (2. 7%). Yet itlj. rate of increase in pri-
mary school enrolment between 1957 and 1962 was over
5% or more than double the rate of population growth.
Photo @ Sma !)
&&amp;
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
The Mohammadia Engineering School at Rabat (Morocco) has been operating in this vast, ultra-modern, crescent-
shaped building, and its adjoining laboratories since 1960. Created with assistance from the U. N. Special Fund
and with the co-operation of Unesco, the school is attached to the University of Rabat. It is training the executive
engineers which Morocco needs for its public administration and key industries. The school has an enrolment
of 350 students who will contribute directly to Morocco's industrial and economic development after
completing the four-year course. An engineering school was also opened in Algiers recently with help from Unesco.
m Much has been published on the
LCJneed for new techniques in
education. What is Unesco doing in
this field ?
It is now quite obvious that the major problem of
meeting the demands for more education cannot be solv-
ed without the introduction of new techniques and methods,
such as programmed instruction (the so-called teaching
machines) and the audiovisuals (films, radio and televi-
sion). But these revolutionary techniques cannot be adopt-
ed without a rethinking of the entire concept of education
today. Unesco has sponsored a series of systematic,
carefully controlled experiments to study the effects and
requirements of these new methods in science and lan-
guage teaching.
Young men learn shoe
embroidery in the
Unesco vocational
training centre at
Fezzan, Libya.
Unesco seeks to
preserve and promote
local arts and crafts
in the developing
countries, tun Libya its
courses on Islamic
art for potters,
weavers and workers
in leather, copper,
and wood have given
a new impetus
to these
traditional crafts.
Photo Unesco-J. Badran
rite1 What has Unesco done to en-
ß ! J courage school construction ?
Unesco has created a network of school building
centres throughout the world, in Khartoum for Africa
(1961). in Bandung and temporarily Bangkok for Asia (1962
and 1965), and Mexico City for Latin America (1363). These
centres promote research on different types of materials,
designs and construction methods best adapted to regiohal
conditions and resources. They also train technicians in
school construction.
m Why was it found necessary
W to set up an institute for
educational planing ?
Teachers, curricula, methods and schools are all basic
to any national educational policy. But experience has
taught Unesco that assistance to projects unrelated to an
over-all plan for education can yield only limited results.
Tit therefore sought first to integrate the aid it renders
member states for specific projects into the general devel-
opment of education and then to establish educational
planning as part of over-all planning for economic and
social development. In 1963, an International Institute for
Educational Planning was created in Paris by Unesco with
initial aid from the World Bank. On a regional revel, U. N.
economic commissions have supported the operation of
two centres in Beirut and New Delhi, an educational plan-
ning and administrative group in Dakar, and educational
planning sections of institutes for economic development
in Santiago and Bangkok.
what is Unesco's strategy in
thy struggle against illiteracy ?
Following the Teheran Congress in 1965, where the
problem of illiteracy was carefully re-examined by 88
national delegations including 59 ministers and under-
seçretaries, Unesco decided to incorporate literacy in its
programmes for educational planning. For a long time,
Unesco's action in this field was limited to making studies,
providing technical assistance and initiating pilot projects
for research and training such as the fundamental educa-
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
67
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
50 QUESTION (Continued)
tion centres for community development which have been
operating for over ten years in Mexico for Latin America
and in the United Arab Republic for the Arab States.
About 700 million persons-nearly half the world's adult
population-are illiterate at present and the number of
illiterate youths and adults rose by 20 million over the
past five years. In 1964, Unesco launched an experimental
programme to pave the way for a world campaign. This
plan is scheduled to begin in a limited number of countries
with assistance from the U. N. Development Programme
and will concentrate on organized sectors of the economy
where motivation is likely to be strong : public undertak-
ings, private firms, co-operatives, trade unions, village
councils or community development projects. The aim,
according to Unesco's Director-General, is to start"an
irreversible movement to wipe from the surface of the
earth, in a single generation, the scandal and shame of
illiteracy."
Three projects, in Algeria, Iran and Mali, were approved
at the beginning of this year. Their total cost is $12, 800, 000
of which $9 million will be provided by the governments
concerned, and $3, 800, 000 by the United Nations Devel-
opment Programme. Two additional projects, in Tanzania
and Ecuador, were added later this year.
1 What was the historic step
Eij taken by the Shah of Iran to
combat illiteracy ?
In April 1966, the Shahinshah of Iran informed Unesco's
Director-General of Iran's decision to use one day's expen-
diture under its military budget to help in the world struggle
against illiteracy. The Shah announced that this sum
($700, 000) would be placed at Unesco's disposal.
Iran had previously set up an"Army of Know ! edge"
in 1962 which uses young men in the armed forces as
literacy teachers in villages.
Etc What is the new science
dij po ! icy of Unesco ?
The United Nations Conference on the Application of
Science and Technology for the Benefit of Less Developed
Regions, held in Geneva in 1963, gave Unesco an oppor-
tunity to define in detail the goals of an international
science policy related to problems raised by economic
growth and social progress. This policy is also based
on the survey of current trends in scientific research
carried'out in 1959, and the establishment in 1960 of priori-
ties to meet present-day needs.
Many people regard aid for the technological develop-
ment of the less advanced countries as a mere transfer of
"know-how"accompanied by the appropriate shipment of
equipment.
But no matter how essentia ! transfer of knowledge is
to economic growth it alone cannot solve the problem of
aid to technological progress. Two activities dominate all
others : the training of scientific and technological person-
nel ; the organization and planning of scientific and techno-
logical activities. In other words, every country must create
a scientific and technological potential of its own. That
is why Unesco continues to emphasize the organic unity
of science and encourages the development of scientific
and technological training and research on a national level
in newly independent countries.
which aspect of science teach-
E ! 1I ing is considered most vital to
developing countries ?
Technological education-including the training of
engineers-is the branch of science teaching most vital
to the growth of developing countries and probably the
one where they face the biggest demand for improvement
and expansion. A striking example of Unesco's work is
the aid it has rendered since 1955 to the establishment
of the Indian Institute of Technology in Bombay. From
its start, the U. N. Special Fund has enacted Unesco to
expand its activities in this field considerably. At the end
of 1965, Unesco was executing 50 Special Fund projects
involving the establishment and initial operation of 30 post-
secondary and 20 higher education institutes.
yeti What is Unesco doing
EH for technotogica) research ?
Unesco is responsible for executing a dozen projects,
mainly in Asia, and covering a variety of fields from power
station technology and mechanicat engineering research to
the manufacture of precision instruments and the construc-
tion of a mathematical model for the development of the
Mekong River basin.
m Why does Unesco consider the
sexploitation and conservation
of natural resources to be of such
vital importance ?
As world population and needs rise, knowledge and ways
of studying our natural environment and its potential
resources must be developed everywhere, not only through
international action but also by the establishment or
expansion of training and research institutes. Unesco is
encouraging this trend in geology, seismology, soil
sciences, hydrology, ecology, etc.-particularly for the
lesser-known regions in the arid and humid tropical zones.
Under its arid zone research programme, it helped create
or develop a dozen institutes, of which one in Jodhpur,
India, is an example. It is encouraging research and
training in irrigation with brackish water in Tunisia, and
aiding the operation of an International Institute of Seis-
mology and Earthquake Engineering in Japan.
m How is Unesco helping the
Emu developing nations to establish
a coherent scie, nce policy ?
By helping them gradually to build a scientific infra-
structure. This means organizing scientific and technolog-
ical documentation, creating institutes for technological
research, preferably with a multidisciplinary approach, and
setting up centres to standardize, produce and maintain
scientific instruments. For the past fifteen years, under
its regular programme and U. N. technical assistance,
Unesco has aided such efforts in most of the countries
concerned. One example is the creation of 12 documen-
tation centres-in Bangkok, Belgrade, Cairo, Djakarta,
Havana, Karachi, Manila, Mexico City, Montevideo, New
Delhi, Rio de Janeiro and Seoul-with the help of more
than forty experts from 21 countries.
68
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
rip Since 1960, education and
E ! l ! J science have been the two chief
interests of Unesco's operational
activities. Have other fields, then,
been neglected ?
Not at all. In the fields of culture and mass communi-
cation, Unesco has done much. In library development, for
instance, in 1964 alone, Unesco financed the operation of
two regional centres in Senegal and Uganda for the train-
ing of librarians, helped set up a school library service
in Nigeria and a model public library in the Ivory Coast,
and organized a regional seminar in Manila on the devel-
opment of national libraries in Asia. In addition, 18 coun-
tries received expert missions, fellowships and equipment.
 How is Unesco helping the
E ! J. ! J expansion of publishing in the
developing countries ?
By encouraging reading in the greatest possible number
of languages, particularly by children, youths and new
literates. Through a centre established in Karachi in 1958
Unesco is producing pilot editions and setting up new
distribution channels to help ten Asian countries expand
their publishing industries. And an international congress
in Tokyo this year on the production and distribution
of books in Asia aroused considerable interest in pro-
fessional book circles. Then too, Unesco has brought
about closer co-operation between experts in applied
! linguistics and educational authorities to transcribe six
grpups of African languages and unify their alphabets.
Basic vocabularies, grammars, dictionaries and simple
reading materials are to be prepared and published in
collaboration with a regional centre in Accra. Unesco's
activities in encouraging book publishing by developing
countries are to be grouped shortly into one co-ordinated
programme.
m What is the place of the mass
W media in Unesco's
development programmes ?
It is difficult to exaggerate the importance of the present
and future role of the mass media in continuing education.
Unesco has always stressed this role and United Nations
bodies have now recognized the influence of the press,
radio, cinema and television on development, along with
the need to help countries to expand and improve their
facilities in this field.
,
Between 1960 and 1962, three regional conferences were
organized-in Bangkok for Asia, Santiago for Latin Amer-
ica, and Paris for Africa. Unesco is encouraging the
setting up of centres to train professional staff and pro-
duce equipment. It is also responsible for seminars, expert
missions, fellowship and supplying equipment. In the
budget for 1965-66, more than $800, 000-incfuding
$660, 000 for technical assistance-has been allocated to
such projects in some twenty countries, and to four
specialized regional centres in Strasbourg, Quito, Manila
and Dakar. Unesco has initiated a study of problems
involved in the use of artificial satellites to facilitate the
free flow of information, the extension of education and
the intensification of cultural exchanges.
Unesco has been working for these youngsters in Bolivia and
for millions of other children in Latin America since 1957 when
it launched its Major Project to extend and improve primary
education on that continent, particularly through teacher training.
Between 1957 and 1965, school enrolment in Latin America
as a whole rose by 11 million and teaching posts by 380, 000.
Many new teacher training colleges have been opened and
seminars and intensive in-service courses have been organized
by Unesco specialists for teachers, school directors and
inspectors. Unesco co-operates with Unicef and the World
Food Programme in projects aimed at improving school
attendance, and with the International Labour Organization
and Argentina, Bolivia and Chile on educational
aspects of the Andean Indian development programme.
An outstanding contribution to pedagogical reseerch in Asia was
made by Unesco and Thailand in 1955 when they set up « Q
the Bangkok Institute for Child Study (above). By davetoping 0
new educational methods and techniques, this research
laboratory and training institute is helping to improve programmes
and teaching for the children of Asia's village schools.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
'". ; :
'"a.
> ;Q.CD
E
< {
: J'"a.
0
o
Õ.. ca.
L'": JoCCDCD
ð
a :
oOfCDCDc
: >
o
Õ. l :Q.
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
50 QUESTIONS (Continued)
III-Ethical action & human rights
m What does Unesco mean
CiL by'ethical action' ?
Everything that Unesco does, including its efforts to
promote international intellectual co-operation and opera-
tional assistance for development is subordinated to one
fundamental purpose : to foster the dignity of man, promote
human rights and international understanding.
Unesco's Director-General has repeatedly pointed out
that Unesco's mission is essentially ethical in nature.
"Unesco seeks to instil in men's minds the spirit of
tolerance and co-operation, respect for human rights and
peace,"he has said."For Unesco, progress in education,
science and culture is no end in itself, nor are the
practical applications of such progress an achievement.
They are only the means or the modes of a moral effort and
a spiritual undertaking which constitute Unesco's real
reason for existence."
Unesco's activities in this field can be said to fall
into three main groups : education for international under-
standing, promotion of human rights and peace research.
8m How does Unesco seek tofoster education for
international understanding ?
Unesco's Constitution states that"the education of
humanity for justice and liberty and peace is indispensable
to the dignity of man and constitutes a sacred duty which
all the nations must fulfil in a spirit of mutual assistance
and concern."Thus, since its founding, Unesco has
assumed a leading role in work to promote teaching for
international understanding, teaching about the aims and
activities of the United Nations and its related agencies.
In 1953, Unesco launched the Associated Schools Project
in Educaton for International Understanding to develop
knowledge of world affairs, of international co-operation
in dealing with world problems, of different cultures and
ways of life, and of the principles of human rights-in sum,
to aid in developing the kind of education that can help
to construct the defences of peace in the minds of men,
to paraphrase the words of Unesco's Constitution.
Today, nearly 500 primary schools, secondary schools
and teacher training institutions in 54 countries are taking
part in Unesco's Associated Schools Projects, and they
represent not only different cultural traditions and dif-
ferent stages of development but also different economic
and political systems.
 What else has Unesco done to
as'sociate young people with
its work ?
tin addition to the Associated Schools Project there are
250 Associated Youth Projects of an experimental nature
which have been sponsored by Unesco in various parts of
the world over the past ten years in collaboration with
national authorities and international youth movements. In
1965 and 1966, Unesco assisted some thirty projects to
promote educational travel, international understanding,
civic and social education and other goals.
By supporting the international voluntary work camps
where millions of young people have worked together in
a hundred'countries, Unesco has encouraged youth to
play its part in community development. Another example
is long-term international service, in which volunteers re-
cruited through some 250 organizations are now participat-
ing-many of them as teachers in Africa and Asia.
In 1964, Unesco convened the first world conference
ever held on youth problems. Its recommendations are
helping to blueprint a long-term programme for youth,
including the setting up of a Unesco-sponsored network
of national and regional institutions for out-of-schoo ! educa-
tion for young people. Last year, Japan and Unesco held
an all-Asia congress in Tokyo to plan activities for the
youth of Asia (see also question 50).
 What is the new concept
or of'continuing education' ?
Life is changing so quickly these days that people every-
where have come to recognize that education does not
stop when a person leaves school, but is a continuing
process during all of adult life. This concept was made
abundantly clear at a historic world conference on adult
education held in Canada as early as 1961 under Unesco
auspices.
This is what Unesco keeps in mind when it contributes
to studies on leisure or on new relations to be established
between university curricula and the continuing education
of adults ; when it encourages high-quality popularization
of science ; when it helps to organize scientific lectures and
exhibitions ; or when it promotes the broadest possible
circulation of artistic, literary and musical works.
The same concern has led Unesco to award over 12, 000
travel grants to adult education teachers and European
workers since 1952, and to organize similar travel program-
mes for workers in Asia, Latin America and Africa.
m What has Unesco done tocombat r. acial prejudice and
other forms of discrimination ?
Unesco has championed the cause of racial equality
for the past twenty years.
Racists have often claimed that their beliefs can be
justified on biological, sociological or historical grounds.
Unesco has constantly affirmed, through the voices of
leading world specialists and in the light of scientific
progress, that no branch of learning can provide racism
with the slightest argument on which to base its beliefs.
70
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
A declaration on the nature of race and differences of
race was drawn up in 1951 by 12 anthropologists. This
was reviewed in 1964 by 22 leading world specialists to
take into account the most recent developments in bio-
logy and genetics. This year the social and ethical aspects
of the race question are being examined.
Unesco has assembled salient facts on racial prob-
lems in three series of studies (translated into more than
15 languages). The Race Question in Modern Science
sets forth contributions of anthropologists, ethnographers,
biologists and sociologists which throw new light on the
race question. The Race Question and Modern Thought
defines the position of the major currents of philosophical
and religious thought towards the race problems, and Race
and Society presents studies of multi-racial societies.
Unesco has also acted against other kinds of discrim-
ination. Its special concern with the right to education
led to the adoption of an International Convention against
Discrimination in Education, in 1960. This is closely linked
with Unesco's efforts to promote the access of women
to education.
Next year, Unesco plans to launch a ten-year programme
for raising the status of women through education, science
and culture.
own what is Unesco's
policy for the diffusion
of culture based ?
All-or almost all-nations are now taking part on an
equal footing in international political life, and this goes
hand in hand with recognition of the fact that all cultures
are worthy of respect. Unesco has sought to promote
the idea that a dialogue between these cultures is a
necessity for mutual appreciation. But even this is not
enough today-the growth of the international commun-
ity and the changes brought about by technological and
industrial progress call for a new, broader humanism. It
is not enough just for the elites to understand and appre-
ciate one another's cultural values ; this understanding and
appreciation must now extend to everyone. By working
for universe ! access to education Unesco seeks to promote
new ways for people to know one another and to draw
closer in terms of their respective cultural values.
has Unesco done any work
on internation-al tensions and
peace research ?
Early in its history Unesco launched a series of investi-
gations of individual and group attitudes on national stereo-
types and factors favouring aggressive nationalism. The
results were published in The Nature of Conflicts. Other
studies dealt with international tensions and ways of pro-
moting peaceful co-operation among states with differing
social and economic systems.
Similarly, Unesco encourages research on peace and
current trends in international relations, like the studies
carried out in 1963 and 1964 on the economic and social
consequences of disarmament with the assistance of the
European centre for social science research in Vienna, and
in co-operation with the United Nations, on the utilization
in the field of education of the added resources that dis-
armament could make available.
how does Unesco promote
international understanding
through art ?
To bring the visual arts to the broadest possible audience,
Unesco has adopted the solution of the"imaginary
museum"which today's high quality reproduction of original
masterpieces makes possible. Eight Unesco travelling ex-
hibitions of art reproductions have visited 100 countries ; in
its World Art Series, Unesco has published 23 albums of
little known masterpieces, and has reproduced the works
as colour slides and also in a series of paperbacks ; to
help the public choose good quality reproductions of paint-
ings Unesco publishes two catalogues which have been
revised and enlarged regularly since 1949.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
On an improvised open-air stage in a village in Ecuador
a young actor tells an attentive rural audience about
the play that they are going to see. The performance
is one result of a Unesco mission sent to Ecuador to help
set up a national theatre company. After its first successes
in Quito, the capital, the company toured the country's towns
and villages. Public debates followed each performance
and with the help of a team of specialists travelling
with the actors-a doctor, an engineer, a social worker
among others-villagers were encouraged to undertake
all kinds of community development work and to join
in adult education and literacy campaigns.
! I
Ñ
2u'"
CM
7J
If)
." !: >.. 
9
o
Õ. ca.
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
50 QUESTION (continued)
) fit3 How has Unesco promoted the
My diffusion of literature and
music ?
An outstanding example is the Unesco Collection of
Representative Works which now includes about 200 vol-
umes with more than 100 others now being translated or
scheduled for publication. The collection is enriched every
year by new translations from Persian, Arabic, Chinese,
Indian, Japanese, Latin American and African literatures as
well as European literary works (Italian, Rumanian, Finnish,
Polish, Spanish, Swedish, Czech, Ukranian, Norwegian,
among others). Unesco's annual bibliography of transla-
tions, the Index Translationum-now in its seventeenth
year-has become the standard handbook of the world's
translations.
Unesco fosters co-operation in music through the Inter-
national Music Council (set up by Unesco in 1949)
which has helped to collect and diffuse recordings of
contemporary music, folk music and Oriental music and to
promote the exchange of students, musicians and radio
programmes.
For the past 12 years Unesco has sponsored the Inter-
national Rostrum of Composers whose aim is to encourage
the exchange of contemporary works of music by radio.
Every year the Rostrum awards a prize to the composer of
the most outstanding work submitted to it. This year the
prize was won for the third time by a young Polish com-
poser, Tadeusz Baird.
 When was Unesco's East-West
W Major Project launched, what
was its purpose and how has it
been carried out ?
Since 1957, through a ten-year major project, Unesco has
made a special effort to promote the mutual appreciation
of Eastern and Western cultural values. This effort to
achieve international understanding in depth has been
carried out at three different levels. For the specialists,
for example, it has helped in the establishment of insti-
tutes of Oriental studies at Tokyo, New Delhi, Beirut, Damas-
cus, Cairo and Teheran. On the secondary-school level,
it has encouraged the improvement of curricula and text-
books so that more attention could be given to previously
neglected cultural values. Finally, in out-of-school educa-
tion, various ways of spreading knowledge and ideas have
been used-lectures, translations, exhibitions, visits, travel
grants, films, museums, reproductions, etc. The very great
success of this programme is reflected in the impressive
number of measures taken by member states themselves,
and by non-governmental organizations, to participate in
carrying it out.
Within recent years this dialogue of East and West has
been further enriched. Certain countries, in Latin America
for example, are showing increasing interest in Oriental
cultures. And the independence of many African states,
plus their growing awareness of the originality and value
of their own cultural heritage has lent new meaning to
the dialogue.
Unesco is now helping to set up and run a network of
institutes of African studies-ten in all-in Africa itself. It
is also preparing a General History of Africa which is
expected to be finished in 1975. Even more significant is
the six-volume History of the Scientific and Cultural Devel-
opment of Mankind (see page 32).
ITi1 What is Unesco's role in the
 preservation of the world's
cultural treasures ?
In the protection and preservation of the world's great
monuments and other cultural treasures, Unesco has forged
an important name for itself. The International Council of
Museums, which Unesco helped to found in 1946, has
become the recognized organization for museum author-
ities and technicians a ! ! over the world. The International
Centre for the Study of the Preservation and Restoration
of Cultural Property set up by Unesco in Rome in 1958
is now an international laboratory for the study of diseases
of stone, wood and other materials as well as many other
aspects of conservation and restoration of monuments.
The international campaigns which Unesco has launched
for the improvement of museums and for greater public
attendance in museums have been striking successes.
During recent years a great deal of work has been
undertaken in the form of direct aid by Unesco. Among
the results of almost 140 Unesco missions have been the
establishment of conservation laboratories in Indonesia,
Thailand. Mexico and Peru ; the creation of a fine arts
museum in Lima, Peru ; the modernization of national
museums in Baghdad, Khartoum, Karachi, Kabul, Livingstone
and other cities ; and the establishment or reorganization
of national monument services in Afghanistan, Malta, Easter
Island (Chile) and Mohenjo Daro (Pakistan).
Nearly four million pages of invaluable documents stored
in the national archives and libraries of some 15 countries
have already been microfilmed by two traveling Unesco
teams in the past ten years.
As in many other aspects of its work, Unesco pays
special attention to the training of museum and conserva-
tion technicians. It has set up training centres for these
purposes in Jos (Nigeria) and Mexico City, and has made
special arrangements with the Honolulu Academy of Arts
and the Bishop Museum of Natural History in Hawaii for
the training of museum curators and technicians of Asia
and the Pacific.
F ; Ti1 What are the results of the
UJ campaign) aunched by Unesco
to save the monuments of
Nubia ?
One of Unesco's most spectacular-and important-
projects has been the international campaign launched in
1960, at the request of the governments of the United
Arab Republic and the Sudan, to save the monuments of
Nubia, in danger of being submerged by the waters of
the Nile upon completion of the Aswan High Dam.
! n one of the greatest salvage operations in world his-
tory, every free-standing temple in Nubia was dismantled
and removed for reconstruction elsewhere. Certain
temples hewn out of the solid rock were also dismantle
and taken away ; in others the most precious elements
were preserved. The two incomparable temples of Abu
Simbel (the Great Temple of Rameses II and the smaller
temp ! e of Queen Nefertari) presented the most complex
problem of all. These have now been saved. They were
cut free from their rock cliff and dismantled, and are now
being rebuilt exactly as before on a site out of reach
of the Nile. To this operation, costing an estimated
$30 million, some 50 countries have contributed.
Within five years all the monuments, inscriptions and
72
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
Photo Unesco-R. Greenough. Young readers choose books from the tending section of the Regional Central Library at Enugu, Eastern
Nigeria. Set up by Unesco and Nigeria in 1 9S9, the library immediately drew crowds of people
all eager to make use of its 80, 000 books. To satisfy this hunger for knowledge, the government added
a second building and also opened sub-libraries at Port Harcourt and Ikot Expene. Thanks to
Unesco's public library pilot projects, other libraries have been opened in Delhi (India), Medellin
(Colombia), Abidjan (Ivory Coast), and Lagos (Nigeria). Unesco has organized training courses
for librarians and has provided fellowships, books and equipment.
rock carvings in the region-archaeofogicahy one of the
world's richest-were catalogued and photographed ; fres-
coes were removed from temples and ancient Christian
churches (as at Faras, for example) ; and all the main
archaeological sites were reconnoitered. Forty expeditions
from 15 countries explored Egyptian Nubia and a dozen
more were at work in Sudanese Nubia.
The spirit behind this co-operative effort is perhaps as
significant as the prodigious achievement itself. Never
before has an international cultural operation been carried
out on such a scale. Its success shows that the nations
recognize culture not only as an essential element of the
intellectual and ethical solidarity of mankind, but also as
a major factor in international co-operation in the service
of peace.
my How can the individual helpBlU Unesco ?
The reader will have noted in these 50 questions many
instances in which youth groups and non-governmental
organizations are participating in the work of Unesco.
Individuals can often join such groups on a national level.
Many young people have grouped together in various
countries to form Unesco Clubs which are extremely active
in promoting the ideas of Unesco for international under-
standing and co-operation. France and Japan alone have
300 clubs each and eight countries have federations of
Unesco clubs (Fed. Rep. of Germany, India, Italy, Morocco,
etc.). Twenty-one countries have non-federated clubs.
In Spain Unesco Courier Clubs exist in several major
cities and arrange discussion groups, lectures, plays,
concerts and exhibitions.
A movement which has grown over the years is the
Unesco Gift Coupon Programme which someone once called
"technical assistance by the man in the street". Schools,
clubs and individuals provide educational or scientific
equipment, books and supplies to Gift Coupon projects
in Asia, Africa, the Middle East and Latin America. Dónor
groups choose the projects from a Unesco list, collect
funds, buy Gift Coupons and mail them. directly to the
project. In this way more than $1. 5 million has gone
to help literacy and adult education projects, schools, agri-
cultural co-operatives, libraries and museums aii over the
world.
But the real way in which people can help Unesco is by
thinking and acting in the Unesco spirit of understanding
one's neighbours, which is the first step towards strengthen-
ing mutual respect and understanding and international
co-operation.
73
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
Two decades in the world of culture (Continued from page 35)
never dreamed of a museum as beau-
tiful as the one they now have in
Paris, nor of awakening such a wave
of fervour in the United States, where
thousands of their works have been
on view.
In the case of books, which some
people imagine to have been ousted
by other means of diffusion, the revo-
lution brought about by the paper-
back merits a special study on its
own. In the United States, for exam-
ple, it has brought about a fundamen-
tal change that has done much to
create a new image of that country.
The first experiment with paper-
backs was made twenty-five years
ago. Today some are published in as
many as fifteen million copies. A
bookshop seNing paperbacks, which
you will find in every city, looks rather
like a supermarket. Many of the early
paperbacks were detective stories, sex
novels and mystery tales. Today there
are paperback editions of all the
classics, and in the universities stu-
dents are advised which books to
choose from paperback collections.
In the self-service bookshop, young
people no longer crowd around the
shelves piled with thrillers or"shock-
ers". Instead they look for works
on philosophy, political science, art
and literature. The same thing is
happening throughout the world-not
only in the United States and Europe,
but on every continent. Sophocles and
Euripedes have now travelled around
the globe, and those who have
read their works or seen them per-
formed by far outnumber the Athenians
of Pericles'day.
The growth of mass readership
thanks to the introduction and spread
of paperback editions (who nowadays
catches a train, goes off to the coun-
try or relaxes in the evening, without
a book in his pocket ?), has led to an
astounding increase in translations.
In 1965, 35, 000 books were translated
in 69 countries alone. The symbol of
the Tower of Babel has been revers-
ed, and a network of universal under-
standing covers countries that had
never before known advantages of this
kind.
Nowadays an illiterate person is not
necessarily an uninformed one. New
media of communication-television,
the cinema and radio-have trans-
formed and vastly expanded the
area covered by books and schools.
This does not mean that the new
media have replaced the old ; they fill
gaps, broaden knowledge and bring it
up to date, and free from ignorance
the person who was deprived of a
school education.
Admittedly there are times when all
these media pander to the lowest
tastes. But think of the marvels revealed
by the cinema and the admirable mes-
sages flashed around the world by
radio in a matter of minutes. And
what about the change that has come
in the atmosphere of the home since
one can listen there to the finest music
of all time played by the world's
greatest orchestras ?
Then there is the radical transforma-
tion of the university. Everywhere
scientists and thinkers are on the move,
reminding us of times when scholars
travelled from Salamanca to Cam-
SOLUTION TO THE CHINESE NECKLACE PROBLEM
(published in June 1966 issue)
By making only five cuts in his necklace, the merchant will be able to pay the
innkeeper for his lodging each evening for 63 days.
The first evening, the merchant cuts off one pearl and gives it to the innkeeper ;
the second evening he takes off two, gives them to the innkeeper who returns the
first pearl to him ; the third evening, he gives the innkeeper back the first pearl ;
the fourth evening, he cuts off four pearls, takes back from the innkeeper the
first three pearls, and pays the innkeeper with these until the eighth evening
when he cuts off eight pearls ; the 16th evening, he cuts off 16 pearls ; the 32nd
evening, he gives the inkkeeper the remainder of the neck) ace-32 pearts-without
making any more cuts.
The merchant has simply used the binary system (number system based on two).
According to this system, 63 is expressed by 1"1,,, that is. 1. 2 :' + 1. 2' + 1. 2"
+ 1. 22 + 1. 2' + 1. 2", which gives us 32 + 16 + 8 + 4 + 2 + 1, or the value
of. each of six parts of the necktace. Therefore he only needed to cut the necklace
five times.
bridge, from Bologna to Paris, on pil-
grimages that gave to ideas an extraor-
dinary mobility whose effects still
astonish us. Nowadays this journeying
to discuss problems and confront ideas
is an everyday affair. From Australia
to Alaska, from Stockholm to Santiago
de Chile, the world resembles a typical
Unesco conference, which investigates
problems, makes known its findings
and brings people from all parts of
the world into contact.
We are dazzled, and with good rea-
son, by the success of man's endeav-
ours to conquer space during this
same period. This achievement, which
is like the discovery of a new dimen-
sion, has allowed us to recapture, on
hitherto undreamed of orbits, the
experiences of great navigators from
Ulysses to Columbus and Magellan,
as they steered their vessels through
mysterious, uncharted seas.
H AS this world-wide culturalevolution brought with it a
deeper, more universal concern for the
dignity of man ? Perhaps the most
convincing answer we can give is to
cite the example of Mrs. Eleanor Roo-
sevelt who, when she was campaigning
resolutely for a new charter of human
rights, was actually fighting against
prejudices that are far more than cen-
turies old.
Nowadays the world is indignant
whenever it hears of acts of violence
committed against anyone for racial
reasons, because in the past twenty
years people have come to realize
that this is a crime not against the
dignity of one man, but of all men. Öz
Today man's eyes probe within the 
infinitely tiny world of the atom, search z
the bottom of the ocean, and trave ! 
around among the stars in satellites
that are like an image of his own pupil 
projected into the infinite. In lest =
than twenty years conquests such as 
these have changed his outlook and 
have made him conscious of being 3
a citizen of space. This is the sign
of a new humanism that is bringing '"
men together. o
\ : I
This does not mean that in the 6
past twenty years there have not been !
warning threats of a world-wide catas-
trophe, nor that all men of the sword 8'"
have disappeared. But in the domain z
of culture there has been positive
progress which we should not over-
look when drawing up a balance sheet ; :)
of our revolutionary timers.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
GET TO KNOW
UNESCO
THROUGH
) TS OTHER
PERIODICALS
Unesco Bulletin for Libraries
(bi-monthly)
Annual subscription :
Single copy :
Unesco Chronicle
(monthly)
Annual subscription :
Single copy :
Impact of Science on Society
(quarterly
Annual subscription :
Single copy :
S3. 50 18/-12. 50 F
$0. 75 4/-3F
$2. 00 10/-7F
S0. 20 1/-0. 70 F
$ 2. 50 13/-9 F
$0. 754/- 3F
International Marine Science
(quarterly
Annual subscription :
Single copy :
Museum
(quarterly
Bilingual (English-French)
Annual subscription :
Single copy :
International Social Science Journal
(quarterly
Annual subscription :
Single copy :
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookteHer, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below : names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in anyone language.
*
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education. Kabul.-AUSTRALIA.
Longmans, Green & Co., Ltd., Railway Crescent,
Croydon, Victoria ; sub-agent United Nations Associa-
tion of Australia, Victorian Division, 4 th Fioor. Askew
House, 364 Lonsdale St.. Melbourne C. I. (Victoria).
($ 2. 25).-AUSTR) A. Vertag Georg Fromme &
Cho.. Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch. 70.-).-BEL-
GIUM. All publications : Editions U labor", 342,
rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Scandaard-Wetenschap-
pelijke Uitgeverij Belgiëlei 147, Antwerp. For The
Unesco Courier (140 FB) and art slides only : Louis
De Lannoy, 112, rue du Trðne, Brussels 5. CCP 3380. 00.
- CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Out. ($ 3. 00).
- CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir Chittampalan
Gardinerrlawata. P. O. B. 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 13/50).
- CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd.. 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).-CYPRUS.
"MAW", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P. O. Box
1722, Nicosia.-CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S. N. T. L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent display) ; Zahranicni
literatura Bilkova 4, Prague 1.-DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, Ltd., Prags Boulevard 47, Copenhagen S, (D.
Kr. 17).-ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P. O.
Box 120. Addis Ababa (10/-).-F) NLAND. Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu. Helsinki. (Fmk. 9. 40).-
FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy,
Paris-7'. C. C. P. 12598-48. (10 F).-GERMANY. All
publications : R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse
145, Munch. 8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only)
Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C. C. P.
276650 (DM 10).-GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd., Atlantis House, Commercial Street, POB 100, Cape
Coast.-GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.-
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann. 28. rue du Stade,
Athens ; Librairie Eleftheroudakis Nikkis 4, Athens.-
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 64, Nathan Road,
Kowloon.-HUNGARY, Akademiai Könybrbnolt
Vaci U. 22'Budapest V. Allami Könyvtersesztö
Vallalat, P. O. Box 240. Budapest-ICELAND.
Snaebj6rnJonsson&Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9., Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.)-INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd.. Nicol
Road, Ballard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Ca ! cutta 13 ; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2 ; Kansan
House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P. O. Box 386, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot : Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16 ; Scindia House,
New Delhi. Indian National Commission for Cooper-
ation with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7).-IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, AI-
Rashid Street, Baghdad.-IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, BaHsbridge. Dublin. 4. (1 5/5).-tSRAEL
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Bookstores, 35 AI-
lenby Road and 48 Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv ( ! S8).-
JAMA) CA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-).-JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P. O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1, 200 yen).-JORDAN. Joseph I. Bahous & Co., Dar ul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P. O. B. 66, Amman.-KENYA. E. S. A.
Bookshop, P. O. Box 30167. Nairobi (10/-).-KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P. O. Box Cen-
trat 64. Seoul. KUWAIT The Kuwait Bookshop
Co., Ltd., P. O. Box 2942, Kuwait-LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P. O. Box 286, Monrovia
(10/-).-LUXEMBURG. Librairie Pau ! Bruck.
22. Grand-Rue. Luxemburg (F. L. 140).-HALAY-
SIA. Federal Publicatio, 1s Ltd., Times House, River
Valley Road, Singapore, 9 ; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor). 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7, 50).
- MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(1 S/-).-MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.. 30,
Bourbon Street. Port-Louis (15/-).-MONACO. British
Library, 30. Bid. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).-
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff. Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague. (fl. 8. 50).-NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N. V., Willemstad, Curaçao. N A. (NA 11 4, 50).-NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, 20. Molesworth
Street (Private Bag), Wellington ; Government Book-
shops : Auckland (P. O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P. O. Box
1721), Dunedin (P. O. Box 1104) (15/-).-NIGERIA.
C. M. S. Bookshops. P. O. Box 1 H. Lagos (10/-).-
NORWAY. All publications : A. S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For Unesco Courier only : A. S- Nar-
vesens Litteraturjeneste, Box 6125. Oslo 6, (17. 50kr.).
- PAK) STAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd.,
Unesco Publications House, P. O. Box 374G. P. O., Lahore ;
Showrooms : Urdu Bazar, Lahore, and 57-58 Murree
Highway, G 16-1, Islamabad.-PHILlPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue, P. O. Box 632, Manila.
- POLAND."RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60).-PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.-PUERTO R ! CO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Rooseveit 11 S.
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey.-SOUTHERN RHODESIA,
The800k Centre and Educational Supply Co., Colonial Mu-
tual Building, Salisbury.-SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum.-SWEDEN. All publi-
cations : A/B C. E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhande !.
Fredsgatan2, Stockho) m 16.-For the Unesco
Courier : Svenska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock-
holm, C (Kr. 12) ; SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich. Payoc. rue Grenus 6,
1211, Geneva 11. C. C. P. 1-236."Courier"only :Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C. C. P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10).-TANZAN) A. Dar-es-Saiaam
Bookshop, P. O. B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.-THAILAND.
Suksapan Panic Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals).-TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.-UGANDA. Uganda Book-
shop, P. O. Box1 45, Kampala (1 0/-).-SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications : Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty) Ltd.,
Libri Building. Church Street, P. O. Box 724, Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) oniy : Central
News Agency P. O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.-50).
- UNITED ARAB REPUBDC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr EI Nil, 38, rue Kasr EI Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent :
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.-
UNITED KINGDOM. H. M. Stationery Office, P. O.
Box 569. London, S. E. i., and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardio, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-).-UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St, New York,
N. Y. 10016 ($ S. OO)- U. S S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200.-YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Kniila Terazije, 27, Belgrade.
'tpzct'`, `ay, S, f"`ttrWtuNr, qNntt ;
t "1   d. n, y r , rw
tis aak/t, , n ws'rH r
n"' 4r'", , try ivy , i,.
'r3r   r  y , r`t r'
. tu". < k  ; rk,'ri
rai,,  . »"s : , , a
 ot the'PtipWi Ctreacs
MwMM ! ! edHeOtMd] j) tMMt*w
$7. 00 35/-24 F
$ 2. 00 10/-7 F
$ 7. 00 35/-24 F
$ 2. 00 10/-7 F
$ 2. 50 13/6 9 F
$ 0. 70 3/6 2. 50 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
