<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="044515eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ï
A window
open on the world
&
S -
V
Alexander The Great
A true likeness from his father's tomb?
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
^^
Photo Vahry Photography Ltd. © Auckland Institute and Museum, New Zealand
Maori chief and his children
New Zealand
\9JUtUi979
This monumental statue depicts Chief Pukaki embracing his two children. Shaped from a giant tree by
craftsmen of the Arawa tribe of the North Island (New Zealand), it once formed the upper
part of the gateway to a fortified village. This masterwork of Maori art is today preserved in
the Auckland Institute and Museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JUNE 1979 32nd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian
French Hindi
Spanish Tamil
Russian Hebrew
German Persian
Arabic Dutch
Japanese Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an International reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster. Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto^Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra Arkin (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Peter Mwômbela (Dar-es-Salaam)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
A NEW DAWN FOR SUKHOTHAI
With Unesco aid Thailand is restoring
an ancient metropolis to its former splendour
by M.C. Subhadradis Diskul
12 COMMON HERITAGE OR LICENCE TO EXPLOIT?
A new world economic order: a hard look at its meaning
for international law
by Mohammed Bedjaoui
18 THE ROYAL TOMBS OF MACEDÓN
A surprising archaeological find that may be the tomb
of Philip, father of Alexander the Great
by Manolis Andronicos
21 FOUR PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
32 THE MYSTERY OF ELCHE
A seven-century-old sacred drama
performed each year in a Spanish city
by Juan Carlos Langlois
35 JANUSZ KORC2AK
The doctor who lived and died for children
by Stanislaw Tomkiewicz and Béatrice Maffioli
38 REMEMBERING MARGARET MEAD
by Claude Lévi-Strauss '
42 IN BRIEF
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
NEW ZEALAND: Maori chief and his children
Cover Is the ivory miniature reproduced on our
cover a portrait of Alexander the Great 7 The
tomb in which it was found, possibly that of
his father Philip II of Macedón, is one of
several discovered recently at Vergina,
northern Greece. As Professor Manolis
Andronicos explains, they are believed to be
part of the royal necropolis of the ancient
kingdom of Macedonia. The preservation of
mankind's constantly growing cultural
heritage is one of Unesco's primary
concerns. With Unesco aid, the Government
of Thailand is restoring the Buddhist statues
and temples of the ancient Thai kingdom of
Sukhothai, whose splendours are described in
an article by Thai historian Subhadradis
Diskul. But our cultural heritage is more than
just stones and artefacts. The sacred mystery
play of Elche (see central colour pages) is an
example of a tenacious tradition, spanning
some seven centuries, that has recently been
recorded on film for posterity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A new dawn
for Sukhothai
With Unesco aid Thailand
is restoring
an ancient metropolis
to its former splendour
by M.C. Subhadradis Diskul
IN northern Thailand, some five hundred
kilometres from Bangkok, stand the
ruins of Sukhothai, once the capital of
a historic Thai kingdom.
The "Sukhothai kingdom" only lasted
about two hundred years but it is regarded
as the cradle of Thai civilization, and its art,
considered to be the most sublime in
Thailand's history, exercised a strong in¬
fluence on later Thai art and on the arts of
neighbouring countries such as Laos.
Sukhothai should therefore be seen as
belonging to all humanity and not to
Thailand alone.
The city of Sukhothai (the word literally
means "the dawn of happiness") was vir¬
tually abandoned in the late fourteenth
century, but many monuments have sur¬
vived as reminders of its glory, although
they have suffered from the ravages Of time
and vandalism. The ruins rise against the
backdrop of a mountain range, some
distance away to the west; to the east the
land is flat. Two canals bring water to the
city from the northeast and the southwest.
Twelve kilometres away on the river Yom is
the later town of Sukhothai, which was
founded by King Rama I in 1786.
The Sukhothai kingdom was probably
established in the middle of the thirteenth
century AD, after the expulsion of Khmer
overlords. According to the latest research
M.C. SUBHADRADIS DISKUL, eminent Thai
historian and archaeologist, is Dean of the
Graduate School, Silpakorn University,
Thailand. After graduating from the Faculty of
Arts at Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, he
completed his studies in the history of art and
eastern archaeology in London and Paris. He is
the author of many books and articles on the
history of art'and archaeology of Thailand and
neighbouring countries.
there seem to have been nine kings of the
Sukhothai dynasty, ruling from about 1240
to 1438. The most famous of these mon-
archs is probably King Ram Khamhaeng
the Great, the third king of the dynasty,
who reigned from 1279 to 1298 and extend¬
ed Sukhothai territory to its furthest limijs.
He invented the Thai alphabet in 1293 and
as "Pra Ruang" features in many Thai
legends as the possessor of great magical
powers.
His successor. King Loethai, seems to
have lost much of the territory he inherited.
Ram Kamhaeng's grandson, King Lithai,
who reigned from 1347 to about 1368,
restored the kingdom's unity though
without recovering all the lost lands. A
zealous adherent of Theravada Buddhism
which had reached Thailand from Sri
Lanka, King Lithai was the first monarch in
Thai history to spend part of his life as a
monk. He resisted the power of the
Ayudhya kingdom which was set up in the
south in 1350 and according to one stone
inscription was forced to abandon
Sukhothai and settle at Pisnulok, an impor¬
tant town in the east of the kingdom.
From that time onwards, although there
were three more kings of the Sukhothai
dynasty, the city of Sukhothai was over¬
shadowed by Pisnulok and by Chakangrao
or Kampaengpet in the south. The last king
of the Sukhothai dynasty probably died in
1438, and from then on the kingdom form¬
ed part of the Ayudhya empire.
A contemporary stone inscription gives a
detailed picture of the paternal administra¬
tion of King Ram Khamhaeng: "In the life¬
time of King Ram Khamhaeng, this Muang
(town) Sukhothai is good. In the water
there are fish, in the fields there is rice. The
ruler does not levy a tax on the people who
travel along the road together, leading their
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
When two Thai chieftains, Pha Muang and Bang Klang Thao, revolted against their Khmer
overlords and proclaimed the first independent Thai kingdom of Sukhothai in the 13th century
A.D., they not only laid the foundations of present-day Thailand, they also opened the way to
a flowering of Thai sculptural and architectural art whose influence remained long after the
kingdom they founded had sunk back into oblivion. The Buddha images created by Thai
sculptors were the most original contribution of the Sukhothai period. They portrayed a new,
supernatural, more idealized conception of the Higher Being. These images were cast in
bronze or fashioned in stucco on a core of laterite, a reddish-coloured weathered rock.
Above, still imposing In their serenity despite the ravages of time, these laterite cores of stucco
Buddha images guard the remains of Wat (temple) Pra Kaew, at Kamphaeng Phet, some fifty
kilometres south-west of Sukhothai.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Located at Wat Sri Chum
in the north-western
outskirts of Sukhothai,
this imposing Buddha, in
the cross-legged "victory
over Mara" attitude,
measures over 11 metres
from knee to knee. The
sanctuary in which it is
housed is surrounded by a
moat and has walls 3
metres thick and 15
metres high.
Photo Palrot Chlrapong
© Cultural Committee
of the Thailand National
Commission for Unesco
>oxen on the way to trade and riding their
horses on the way to sell. Whoever wants
to trade in elephants, so trades. Whoever
wants to trade in horses, so trades.
Whoever wants to trade in silver and gold,
so trades. When a commoner, noble or
prince is dead, let his ancestral home, his
clothes, his elephants, his family, his rice
granaries, his servants and his ancestral
groves of areca-nut and betel all devolve on
his children. If commoners, nobles or
princes have a difference and dispute, [the
King] makes a true investigation and then
only does he decide the matter for his sub¬
jects uprightly, without siding with him
who steals or showing preference for him
who conceals. On seeing the rice of others,
he has no covetous desire. On seeing the
wealth of others, he has no seething
desire. To anyone who comes on elephant
to see him, he affords aid and assistance. If
he lacks elephants and horses, men and
women, silver and gold, he gives them to
him... If he captures a fighting foe, he does
not kill or beat him. At the gateway there is
a bell hung up. If anyone of the public has a
complaint or grievance of body or of mind
to place before the King, it is not difficult.
He goes to sound the bell that is hung up.
King Ram Khamhaeng hears him call and,
on questioning him, makes an upright in¬
vestigation for him."
As for Buddhism, King Ram
Khamhaeng's stone inscription tells us:
"The people in this Muang Sukhothai are
charitable, pious and devoted to alms¬
giving. King Ram Khamhaeng, the ruler of
this Muang Sukhothai, as well as princes
and princesses, gentlemen and ladies of
the nobility and men and women, one and
all, have faith in the Buddhist religion,
everyone observing the precepts during
Buddhist Lent [rainy season], at the end of
which Kathin offerings [presentation of a
monastic robe] take place for a whole
month. In the Kathin offerings there are
heaps of cowries, heaps- of areca-nut,
heaps of flowers, cushions and pillows.
The Kathin accessories presented each
year amount to two million. For the recital
of the Kathin resolution people go even as
far as Aranyik [forest monastery] yonder.
On their return to the city, they line up from
Aranyik yonder to the border of the open
ground, joining together in striking up the
sound of musical instruments and lutes,
carolling and singing. Whoever wants to
play, plays. Whoever wants to laugh,
laughs. Whoever wants to sing, sings. This
Muang Sukhothai has four main gateways.
People would flock in to see the King light
the candles and play with fireworks. This
Muang Sukhothai is noisy as if it would
burst."
The old town of Sukhothai is rec¬
tangular, 1,810 metres long and 1,400
metres wide, surrounded by three rings of
earthen ramparts. There are three gates at
each of the four cardinal points; in front of
each inner gate traces of a semi-circular
earthen and brick fort can be seen. A moat
about twenty metres wide lies between
each rampart.
Inside the town stand the ruins of sixteen
Buddhist monasteries, four Hindu shrines
and two Buddhist wat (monasteries). There
are also four large ponds inside the town.
Among later constructions are a statue- 1
monument of King Ram Khamhaeng and j
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Left, stone inscription from the old city of Sukhothai dating from
the time of Ram Khamhaeng, greatest of the Sukhothai kings, who
reigned during the latter part of the 13th century. "In my father's
time", runs part of the inscription, "I served my father, I served my
mother... When I conquered a town and captured elephants, men or
women, silver or gold, I gave them all to my father. When my father
died, then came my elder brother's time. I served my brother just as
I served my father. My brother died and I received the whole
kingdom for myself". Below, view of part of the old city of
Sukhothai which is situated in central Thailand some 500 kilometres
north-west of Bangkok. At centre, the chedi (a solid round
monument with a tall finial or spire) of Wat Sra-Sri. The old city has
been designated as an historical park. Work on preservation and
restoration of its priceless monuments is being undertaken by the
Government of Thailand In co-operation with Unesco.
Photos Alexis Vorontzoff, Unesco
* *3&-> "*^*: ÜT
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
This impressive 12.5-metre-high
stucco figure of Pra Attharot, a
standing Buddha figure, at Wat
Sapan Hin, looks down on
Sukhothai from the summit of a
hill to the west of the city in an
area known as Aranyik. The right
hand is held out in the attitude of
dispelling fear.
> the Ram Khamhaeng National Museum.
Outside the town are about seventy
monuments: some have been restored;
others await restoration.
The most important monument in old
Sukhothai is Wat Mahathat, situated in the
middle of the town. At the centre of the
wat is a lotus-bud stupa (a solid monument
built to enshrine the relics of the Buddha)
typical of the Sukhothai period. The royal
palace may have stood to the northeast of
the wat, but the buildings were con¬
structed in wood and so far no traces of it
have been found.
In the southern part of the town, Wat Si
Sawai, with its three imposing towers, was
probably built as a Hindu shrine and later
became a Buddhist monastery. To the
north stand two important monuments:
Wat Trakuan, whose round chedi (a com
memorative shrine of the Buddha with a
base and a tall finial) derived from Sri
Lanka, and San Ta Pha Daeng, a laterite
Hindu shrine which may have been built in
the early twelfth century.
Wat Chetupon, south of Sukhothai, is
noted for its four stucco images of the
Buddha, each in a different attitude: walk¬
ing, standing, reclining, and seated (at the
centre of the wat).
About one kilometre north of Sukhothai
stands an important monument called Wat
Pra Pai Luang, which may have been the
original centre of a settlement which ex¬
isted before the Thai constructed the old
town of Sukhothai. Three laterite prang
(towers like those of Khmer sanctuaries),
dating from the late twelfth or early thir¬
teenth century used to form part of the
main structure of the wat, but only one of
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
them is still standing. On the eastern side
of the wat are many Buddhist ruins of the
Sukhothai period.
Traces of forty-nine ceramic kilns have
also been discovered in this area. These
kilns produced Sukhothai ware at the same
time as Sawankhalok ware was being made
at Sisatchanalai, a twin city of Sukhothai in
the north. These glazed ceramics were the
chief exports of the Sukhothai kingdom
and were sent far and wide. According to
one hypothesis, production may have con¬
tinued until the middle of the fifteenth cen¬
tury, when it came to an end because of
the wars between the kingdoms of
Ayudhya and Chiengmai (in the far north of
Thailand). However, archaeological
evidence from sunken cargo ships along
the eastern coast of Thailand suggests it
may have gone on until a century later,
when it was ended by the wars between
Burma and Thailand.
Outside the town to the northwest
stands another important Buddhist
monastery, Wat Si Chum, which has a
huge seated stucco Buddha ¡mage under a
mondop, a square structure with a pointed
roof. The mondop, which may have been
constructed later than the Buddha ¡mage,
has a double wall in which there is a tunnel
leading to the top of the building.
In the hilly area known as Aranyik, west
of the town, are many ruins of Buddhist
monasteries, the most important of which
is probably Wat Sapan Hin. There, on a hill
some 200 metres high, stands Pra Attharot,
a standing Buddha figure over twelve
metres high.
An outstanding monument to the east of V
the town is Wat Trapang Tong Lang, noted f
The base of the chedi complex of
Wat Mahathat. A row of stucco
Buddhist disciples walk round in
adoration beneath two Buddha
images.
Photo Pairot Chirapong
© Cultural Committee
of the Thailand National
Commission for Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
tor its beautiful stucco scene representing
the Buddha descending from Tavatimsa
Heaven after preaching to his mother.
Professor Silpa Bhirasri, an Italian-born
artist, who devoted his life to the study of
Thai art, has paid a striking tribute to the
art of Sukhothai in his comments on a
superb Sukhothai statue of the Buddha
after His Enlightenment, His body in com¬
plete, repose. "The features are serene",
Bhirasri wrote, "and a faint smile reflects a
state of total inward contentment. After
His Enlightenment, the Buddha attained
Nirvana and to express this condition the
Thai conceived an almost ethereal form of
statuary. Sitting, walking or reclining, their
¡mages of the Buddha convey an impres¬
sion of soaring, undulating movement
which renders the bronze immaterial. Yet
such spirituality does not detract from the
sculptural qualities of the statues, for
although they are highly simplified and
idealized, the human forms are exquisitely
modelled... In the Sukhothai statues there
is always a harmony between the abstract
idea and its material realization...
"Exceptional artistic skills are not
enough where representing the ¡mage of
the Buddha is concerned, because the
idealized forms also have to convey the
essence of Buddhist doctrine. Indeed, it is
the doctrine which inspires the image, not
the actual physical form of the Teacher.
Did the sculptors of old Sukhothai solve
this complex problem? Perhaps it would
not be excessive to say that they solved it
in an incomparable way. The expression of
these statues is such as to give us strength
to master the tumult of our passions,
whereas the faint smile tells us how hap-
10
piness may be achieved by mastering our
animal instincts."
Professor Silpa Bhirasri has also analys¬
ed the bronze walking Buddha, portrayed
in the round, a form of depicting the Bud¬
dha which is the major innovation of
Sukhothai art. "The representation of the
walking Buddha had a special appeal for
the artists of Sukhothai", he noted, "and
truly they succeeded in creating master¬
pieces. When we look at these beautiful
statues, they seem to move gently forward:
with a gesture of the fingers symbolizing
the circle of the Law, the Teacher advances
to announce the Doctrine. The body seems
to undulate gracefully as a result of the har¬
monious movement of legs, trunk and
downstretched arm. The head is shaped
like a lotus bud and the neck spreading at
its base is elegantly attached to the
shoulder. The delicately shaped lobes of
the ears turn slightly outwards. This and
every other detail serves to emphasize the
harmony of the whole composition. The
hands look more divine than human, so ex¬
quisite is their modelling".
The Thai Government has now decided
to create a national historical park in
Sukhothai and the surrounding area. The
monuments will be restored and everything
possible will be done to recreate the splen¬
dour of Sukhothai as it is described in King
Ram Khamhaeng's inscription.
Agriculture will be developed, water sup¬
plies will be improved, and plants mention¬
ed in the inscription will be regrown. The
promotion of tourism also forms part of the
project, which aims not only to safeguard
the site and its monuments but also to
develop the whole region for the benefit of
the local population.
To bring the Park Development Project
to fruition Thailand needs approximately
$11 million. Financial aid and equipment
are being sought from other countries and
from foundations. Working in close col¬
laboration with the Thai Government,
Unesco is playing an active part in this pro¬
gramme of international co-operation.
Work has already begun on the restora¬
tion of the town of Sukhothai and the
monuments nearby. Many young
specialists from Thai universities have car¬
ried out surveys of the local topography
and are engaged in research on possibilities
for development, urban settlement and
irrigation systems. Archaeologists are
excavating sites in search of traces of
monuments and dwellings. An¬
thropologists and ethnologists are studying
the oral traditions and folk-tales of the local
population, together with their customs
and the tools and utensils they use in every¬
day life. Two festivals based on the
description of life in Sukhothai given in the
Ram Khamhaeng inscription have been
performed. Illustrated books in Thai and
other languages have been published to
help arouse public interest in the Historical
Park. With adequate funds and specialist
aid, this vast project sponsored by Unesco
should be successfully realized.
M.C. Subhadradis Diskul
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Not only did the sculptors of the Sukhothai
school bring a new spirituality to their
representations of the Buddha, they also were
the first to introduce the walking Buddha
beneath whose footsteps "the ground became
level and the lotus blossomed". Buddha was
depicted in four postures, reclining, seated,
standing and walking. The typical Sukhothai
Buddha has hair curls which come to a point in
the middle of the forehead and a prominent
ushnisha, or cranial protuberance, surmounted
by a rasml, or flame-like motif symbolizing
power and glory. Photos : above, walking
Buddha on a four-sided mondop, or pavilion, at
Wat Chetupon; each of the other three sides has
a Buddha image in a different posture. Top right,
walking Buddha, now preserved in the Bangkok
National Museum, reflects the serene, meditative
spirituality the Sukhothai sculptors sought to
convey through deliberate stylization of both
facial features and the body. Left, wall
decoration from a mondop at Wat Trapang Tong
Lang, perhaps the finest example of Sukhothai
stucco-work, depicts the Buddha descending
from the heaven of the Tavatimsa (thirty-three
gods), flanked by Indra, Brahma and other gods.
Right, 47-centimetre-high bronze from Chieng
Mai, now in the Bangkok National Museum,
depicts Buddha making the imprint of his foot
after descending from the heaven of the thirty-
three gods.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Common heritage
or licence to exploit?
A new world economic order:
a hard look
at its meaning for international law
by Mohammed Bedjaoui
social and cultural systems; to exercise full
permanent sovereignty over all its posses¬
sions and to regulate the activities of
transnational corporations and foreign in¬
vestment; to suffer no discrimination in in¬
ternational trade, within the context of in¬
ternational co-operation; to form organiza¬
tions of producers with other States; to
share in technological progress and to en¬
joy its rewards.
Nowhere, it 'is true, is the right of
i-ï.îr-iKï
WHAT should be done about the
resources of our planet? The
whole development of modern
international law seems to hinge on this
crucial issue, which brings into play a con¬
test between two principles, that of the
sovereignty of the State and that of the
common heritage of mankind.
Work on the codification of the law of
the sea has shown the price to be paid
before the idea of a common heritage of
mankind can come into its own. One-third
of the surface of the world ocean has been
allocated to thirty-five States in the form of
an "economic zone", extended to 200
miles by the Conference on the Law of the
Sea and by national jurisdictions; thus the
application of the principle of the common
heritage of mankind is excluded from vast
areas of the planet. What is more, this
heritage is so constituted as to afford the
State, at least the technologically and
financially powerful State, many oppor¬
tunities to prosper.
The Charter of Economic Rights and
Duties of States, adopted by the General
Assembly of the United Nations on 12
December 1974, can also be seen to
crystallize a number of contradictions.
Sovereignty is made much of in this
document as being particularly desirable to
the poor countries, favouring their attain¬
ment of international dignity and respect
for their rights.
In the Charter the idea of sovereignty is
refracted into myriad facets which reflect
above all the new-found economic
sovereignty of the developing countries. It
stresses that each State has a sovereign
right to choose its own economic, political.
MOHAMMED BEDJAOUI is Ambassador of
the Democratic and Popular Republic of Algeria
in France and his country's Permanent Delegate
to Unesco. He is a member of the United
Nations International Law Commission and an
associate of the Institute of International Law.
This article is taken from his book Pour un Nou¬
vel Ordre Economique International, published,
in French, by Unesco. An English edition is to be
published shortly.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
sovereignty, expressed in such terms,
regarded as being designed for Third World
States alone. But it is no secret that the
rich countries have held sway not only
within their own frontiers but in other
countries too. Recognition of the right of
sovereignty was not being solemnly enjoin¬
ed and re-expressed with the rich countries
in mind but for the other, less developed
States whose enjoyment of sovereignty
had hitherto been frustrated.
At the same time, however, the Charter
seems to outline a theory of
"responsibility" or "responsibilities" which
devolve on States as a counterpart to this
sovereign right. In particular, it declares
that States have a duty to respect the
legitimate interests of other States when
exploiting natural resources which they
share. This is clearly an allusion to com¬
modities which may be affected, now or in
the future, by the application of the con¬
cept of a common heritage of mankind.
The duty of States to contribute to the
development of world trade and to en¬
courage the progress of other peoples as*
well as their own, also evoked in the
Charter, suggests a theory of "solidarity"
based on possible developments of the
concept of a common heritage.
And so these two approaches, which are
leaving their imprint on international law as
it is now taking shape, appear to be utterly
irreconcilable.
The first approach boils down to the
claim that all States possess permanent
sovereignty over their natural wealth and
resources. Certain jurists consider this
claim to be scandalous. Dubbed "intoxica¬
tion with sovereignty" by some, and as a
thoroughly "retrograde" sovereignty by
others, it is not seen by everyone in its
historical perspective as the driving force
behind a great'change towards a more
equitable world.
The second approach looks to the no¬
tions of "collective economic security" and
the common heritage of humanity for its in¬
spiration. As voiced by some these ideas
have emerged strongly as demands which
run counter to the sovereign rights of
States. As a result this approach is regard¬
ed with suspicion in Third World countries.
It is, in fact, perfectly clear that certain
current trends of thought in the West
reflect a belated discovery of the virtues of
collective economic security. But these vir¬
tues are presented more as a justification
for maintaining access to the vital or impor¬
tant resources of a Third World which is
determined to claim full sovereignty over
them than as part of a desire to make this
new economic and juridical order pro¬
gressively more equitable.
Any attempt to impress on Third World
countries that they bear certain respon¬
sibilities, arising from their legal authority
as nations for managing natural resources
which are theirs yet are needed by the
whole world, must be preceded by a
recognition that their claim for effective
control over these resources is a legitimate
one. It is clear that the organization of
world interdependence and solidarity on
bases that are at once fair and rational
presupposes the economic independence
and sovereignty of the developing coun¬
tries, as well as the preparation of all States
.for the individual and collective respon¬
sibilities which they must assume in the in¬
ternational community, for the benefit of
all.
Secondly, if Third World States are
perfectly justified in voicing some suspicion
of the "unilateral pooling" of their
resources in the name of an innovating
concept such as "collective economic
sovereignty" or "the common heritage of
humanity", they are nonetheless still in
favour of the concept as long as it is ap¬
plied impartially to everything and
everyone. .
It has been pointed out that the basins of f
Sphere 6, a bronze globe by the Italian sculptor Amoldo Pomodoro.
Photo Dick Wolters © Boymans van Beuningen Museum, Rotterdam
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
In a world that has shrunk to the
dimensions of a "global village",
isolated solutions to problems of
the protection of the environment
and the use of natural resources
are no longer possible. The planet
itself has become the microcosm
suggested by this image of the
creation of the world portrayed by
Hieronymus Bosch on the back of
the wing panels of his famous
triptych The Garden of Earthly
Delights.
Photo © Mas, Barcelona. Prado Museum, Madrid
the Amazon and the Congo, the world's
* most abundant source of oxygen, could be
taken as typical examples of the common
heritage of humanity. On these grounds,
and because oxygen is absolutely vital to
the life of the whole planet, the States
which control these basins should be ac¬
countable to the whole international com¬
munity for their management of this vital
resource.
There is nothing intrinsically shocking in
this idea. But it must be seen in the context
of a pooling of the earth's resources and
wealth founded on solidarity and excluding
all selfish considerations of national self-
interest. The behaviour of the nations, not
to mention the tacit assumptions on which
it is based, gives the impression that it is up
to the Third World to shoulder the obliga¬
tions inherent in the application of the con¬
cept of the common heritage of humanity,
while the industrialized countries enjoy the
corresponding rights and benefits.
In other words, a kind of international
division of labour would perpetuate and ex¬
acerbate the mechanism of domination,
obliging Brazil and the Congo, for example,
to preserve oxygen so that the industrializ¬
ed powers could use as much of it as they
pleased. Thus no account is taken of the
obligation incumbent on the rich countries
not to destroy the thin layer of the earth's
atmosphere by the extravagant and anar¬
chic use of the internal combustion engine.
The notion of a "common heritage of
humanity" therefore only achieves a signifi¬
cant degree of credibility insofar as it em¬
bodies an equitable sharing of the rights
and duties of States, or incorporates ine¬
quality only as a means of compensating
the developing countries. If oil is part of the
common heritage of humanity, then it
should be considered as such wherever it is
found, regardless of its geographical
location.
American, British, Norwegian or Soviet
oil should belong to everyone just as much
as oil from the Middle East. And before oil
is even considered, agricultural foodstuffs,
of which the North American continent is
still by far the biggest source of supply,
should be declared part of the common
heritage, with food producers being
answerable to the international community
in general and, in particular, to the hungry
multitudes of Asia and Africa.
It has been pointed out that if such con¬
ditions are not met, and if the concept of a
common heritage is promoted before its
time, "instead of facilitating the coming of
A world working in harmony is
evoked in this sphere from a
monumental clock on which the
Flemish painter Quentin Massys
(c. 1466-1530) depicted a variety of
domestic and agricultural tasks.
Photo © Louvain Museum, Belgium
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
a new and equitable system of relation¬
ships, [it] could well establish a basis for a
return to relationships of dependence bet¬
ween the strong nations, on the one hand,
which would like to remain in a predomi¬
nant position and continue to exercise the
prerogatives of strength, and, on the other,
the weak countries which would continue
to hanker vainly after real equality of oppor¬
tunity which would continue to elude
them".
But the fact is that the two approaches
examined above, reflecting on the one
hand the sovereignty of the State over its
natural resources and on the other collec¬
tive economic security and the common
heritage of humanity, only appear to be ir¬
reconcilable. Transcending their points of
conflict, they both contribute to the evolu¬
tion of international law in the direction of
more elaborate forms of collective welfare
and above all to the establishment of a new
law for all mankind.
Were we rash enough to lift a corner of
the veil which conceals from us the future
of humanity on this planet, we might see
that mankind is today at a turning-point
and that international law is on the brink of
drastic changes.
Any reference to the principle of a com¬
mon heritage as an idea which has a conti¬
nuing validity necessarily means that pre¬
sent generations are answerable to future
generations for their stewardship of this
heritage. This holds unprecedented im¬
plications for international law, which
transcends the self-interest of individual
men and States and, in a truly global ap¬
proach, relates to all humanity. For the first
time man can reflect on his ultimate goals, i
not only as an individual but as a species. I
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Constructive thought along these lines,
concerning the common interests of
mankind in the vast unexploited areas of
the planet such as the ocean floor, the
polar regions and the world's rivers as well
as the atmosphere and outer space, would
only be a beginning and would by no
means exhaust the juridical and political
possibilities of the concept of a common
heritage.
The idea of a common heritage of
humanity has already been suggested with
regard to cultural property. Its progressive
extension into many other fields would be
nothing less than revolutionary in its im¬
pact and would effect a complete transfor¬
mation of international law, corresponding
to profound changes in the way of life and
the quality of life of all mankind.
But only a Utopian dreamer could im¬
agine that the time is yet ripe for the abrupt
framing of laws in this spirit. At the present
stage of human development, the widest
possible application of the notion of the
common heritage of humanity in interna¬
tional law is simply not a practical possibili¬
ty. However, the day may come when its
scope will be extended to all spheres of the
"international law of land, water and sky",
and this would constitute a tremendous
revolution. Through this concept, the new
international law could not only apply to in¬
ert matter and manufactured goods but
directly to peoples and to man himself, for
whom the standards of international law
are primarily intended.
Work has yet to begin on the standards
and institutions that would enshrine the
concept of a common heritage of humani¬
ty. States and international organizations
will be faced with enormous, totally new
problems, by no means the least of which
are those of human rights and the conser¬
vation of the environment. Each of these
problems is of the highest importance to
the idea of a common heritage, for what
would be the point of exploiting the
tremendous riches of the ocean floor for
the benefit of humanity if human dignity or
integrity are threatened or if the environ¬
ment is despoiled to the point where
human life is imperilled.
On 4 July 1976, on the occasion of the
200th anniversary of the Declaration of In¬
dependence of the United States by the
representatives of the thirteen English col¬
onies of North America, a Universal
Declaration of the Rights of Peoples was
adopted in Algiers under the auspices of
the Lelio Basso Foundation. Article 17 of
the Declaration extols "the right of every
people to use the common heritage of
humanity, such as the high seas, the ocean
floor, and outer space". This text is
another signpost boldly pointing the way to
a wider application of the principle of a
common heritage. But let it not be forgot¬
ten that if this principle is to achieve its
fullest significance the mainspring of the
law must be service to mankind, for the
foundation stone of the common heritage
of humanity is man himself.
There is today a growing awareness that
the problems facing the world must be
seen in a truly global perspective. Nowhere
is this need more apparent than in the case
of ecology. One American diplomat has
proposed the creation of an "international
authority for the environment", since "the
ecology of our planet eludes all national
compartmentalization". At the seventh
session of the Third Conference on the
Law of the Sea, held in Geneva in April and
May 1978, speakers concerned about the
dangers of oil slicks and other forms of
marine pollution urged that the obligation
to protect the marine environment be
recognized as a fundamental tenet of inter¬
national law. Such a step would endow the
new law of the oceans with the capacity to
safeguard the interests of all States and all
peoples, including environmental conser¬
vation, through the application of the con¬
cept of a common heritage which makes
present generations accountable to future
generations for the environment.
The notion of a common heritage of
humanity seems to be of fundamental im¬
portance to the establishment of a new in¬
ternational economic order. Science and
technology offer a vast potential as a
source of rational solutions to the problems
that plague humanity. The misguided use
of this potential to promote the kind of
development which would only benefit a
minority must one day come to an end. The
fundamental irrationality of the kind of
development imposed on man throughout
history cannot be perpetuated or rein-
vigorated to challenge and negate
technological, scientific and human pro¬
gress.
To allow new forms of energy and new
human resources to become the
prerogative of a minority of nations and
social classes will be to invite nuclear
apocalypse. A perverted use of the concept
of the common heritage of mankind would
be the worst and most precarious solution
to the problems of the future of our planet.
As for the idea of "collective economic
security", it is all-encompassing, or it is
nothing: it must apply to all States and to
the totality of their resources. The
possibilities this concept has to offer will
only become credible when its all-
encompassing nature is fully accepted.
With the fulfillment of this condition,
which today seems a very distant prospect,
the time will have come for a real and
beneficial change from a world of division
to a world of sharing.
Mohammad Bedjaoui
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
«
Disarmament, ecological
problems and the
exploitation of natural
resources are issues that
involve the interests of all
mankind and call for a
growing spirit of solidarity.
Yet, though men are
becoming increasingly
aware that this solidarity is
a necessary pre-condition
of their development as
equals (symbolized by this
remarkable ninth-century
Irish cross, left, depicting
the twelve apostles),
communities throughout
the world are today striving
to preserve their Identity
with a tenacious fidelity to
their cultural traditions that
is a vital source of
enrichment for the world's
cultural heritage. Right,
three images of this
cultural diversity (from
top): a fragment of Coptic
cloth (Ethiopia) bearing a
design representing the
Nile, with men, birds, fish
and other animals; majestic
figures on the façade of the
small temple of Abu Simbel
(Egypt); aerial view of
pattern of fields and
dwellings (Mali).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The royal tombs of Macedón
A surprising archaeological find that may be
the tomb of Philip, father of Alexander the Great
by Manolis Andronicos
VERGINA, a small village located twelve kilometres south¬
east of Veroia, Macedonia, (northern Greece), is the site
of one of the most spectacular archaeological discoveries
in recent years.
Close by lies another larger village, Palatitsia, whose name, "the
small palaces", derives from the Hellenistic ruins located in the
vicinity. These remains were first spotted in 1855 by the French ar¬
chaeologist Léon Heuzey. He began excavations at the site which
were continued in 1938 by K.A. Rhomaios of the University of
Thessaldniki and completed between 1958 and 1975 by G.
Bakalakis of the University of Jhessaloniki and the author. Two
Macedonian tombs were discovered in this area and it seemed like¬
ly that similar burials might also be located nearby.
My long personal acquaintance with Vergina. began in 1937
when I took part in excavations carried out by my teacher
Rhomaios with whom I worked until 1940. In 1949 I entered the
Greek Archaeological Service and by good fortune I was given a
position in Veroia which included responsibility for Vergina.
I first explored the Megali Toumba, or Great Tumulus, whose
height dominated an extensive cemetery of other smaller tumuli, or
mounds. My initial attempt proved fruitless, yet I was convinced
that the Megali Toumba, which has a diameter of approximately
110 metres and an elevation of 12.5 metres, was indeed con¬
structed in Hellenistic times and covered a large Macedonian
tomb.
In the following years, I investigated the surrounding tumulus
cemetery which dated mostly from the Early Iron Age (1000-700
BC) although it was used until the end of the Hellenistic Period.
The excavated tombs belonged to its first period (1000-700 BC)
and they were rich in pottery, bronze, jewelry and iron weapons.
After this excavation I tried again in 1962 and 1963 to resolve the
secret of the Great Tumulus. After reaching a depth of 1 1 .5 metres
without coming across any finds, I became convinced that the ac¬
tual tomb was to be found below the fill of the tumulus in virgin
soil. Several fragmented grave stelae, including a painted one of
fine workmanship, were discovered ¡n the fill. The latest of these
stelae dated from the beginning of the third century BC.
Only in 1976, after an interruption to excavate the palace with
my colleague George Bakalakis, did I return to resume my efforts. I
knew that it would take more than one season to reach the depth
of 12.5 metres and begin the actual search for the tomb.
I was lucky, however, from another point of view; the 1976 finds
and the destruction observed in the cemetery lent support to the
identification of Vergina with the ancient city of Aegae, the
reputed burial place of the Macedonian kings, proposed by the
British scholar Nicholas Hammond of Bristol University. The re¬
mains unearthed in the filling of the Great Tumulus could be
associated with the looting of the royal tombs the Galatian
mercenaries left at Aegae in 274/3 BC as garrisons by Pyrrhus, the
king of Epirus, who invaded Macedonia, defeated Antigonus
Gonatas, the king of Macedón, and captured many towns.
If this hypothesis was correct, a logical conclusion would be that
the Great Tumulus was built by Antigonus Gonatas (320-239 BC),
who regained Aegae the next year, in order to cover the looted
tombs and protect his own royal tomb from similar vandalism in
the future.
With high hopes I began excavating in 30 August 1977 with my
assistants Stella Drougou and Chrysoula Paliadeli. After working
thirty-five days and removing 18,000 cubic metres of earth, we
reached the natural ground level in the centre of the tumulus. Five
trial trenches were dug 2.5 to 3 metres deeper so that we reached a
total depth of fifteen metres from the top of the tumulus.
The result was a great disappointment: there was no sign of
construction or human activity. But during the final days of the
1977 season, while preparing an access ramp for work to be carried
out in 1978, I noticed an older, smaller tumulus hidden under the
south-east perimeter of the Great Tumulus. Digging into this bar¬
row we came upon an odd piece of wall which was coated with
lime on the top and on one of its sides.
A few days later another piece of masonry appeared near a i
massive well-constructed wall. The next day, between these two |
CONTINUED PAGE 25
MANOLIS ANDRONICOS, professor of classical archaeology at the
University of Thessaloniki, is the author of many studies on Greek
archaeology and history. Among his works translated into English are: The
Acropolis, Delphi and Olympia, all three published by Caratzas Bros., New
Rochelle, U.S.A., 1975. He also contributed to Greek Museums, Barrie
and Jenkins, London 1976.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
A mere two centimetres in height, these astonishingly powerful ivory
miniatures, above, may well be the most authentic known portraits of
Philip of Macedón (right) and his queen Olympias, the father and
mother of Alexander the Great. Along with the portrait reproduced on
our cover, they were discovered lying in the dust of ages on the floor of
the main chamber (No. 3 in drawing page 20) of a Macedonian tomb
uncovered by Professor Manolis Andronicos at Vergina, northern
Greece, in November 1977. Their presence, coupled with that of certain
other intriguing objects, lends weight to the Professor's hypothesis that
the tomb is that of King Philip II of Macedón (382-336 BC). The
sculptor perhaps the great Leochares himself has captured the king's
imperious mien, made even more sinister by his injured eye. The
resemblance between the portrait of the woman, above left, and the
features of Alexander the Great (see page 27) are strikingthe same
mouth, the same way of carrying the head, the same piercing look.
Surely this is Olympias, Alexander's mother, later cast aside by Philip.
Left, bearded Silenus, the constant companion of Dionysius the god
of wine, adorns a silver pitcher found in the main chamber of the
tomb. Far left, a silver vase from the same tomb bears the face of
Heracles from whom, legend has it, Alexander was descended.
According to the Greek author Plutarch, thirty-eight generations
separated Heracles from Alexander.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Revealed to the light of day after 2,000
years of interment, this vast fresco (5.5
by 1.2 metres) spanned the full width
of the facade of the great tomb at
Vergina (No. 2 in drawing). An
unsurpassed example of 4th-century
BC art, the painting depicts a hunt for
lion and wild boar. Hunters on
horseback and on foot pursue their
prey across a winter landscape, the
season being indicated by a number of
leafless trees.
Photo © Spyros Tsavdaroglou, Athens
Left, this cutaway drawing of the great
tomb gives a clear idea of the layout of
the first unplundered royal Macedonian
tomb ever found. It indicates the exact
positions of some of Professor
Andronicos' major finds in what was,
perhaps, the last resting-place of Philip
of Macedón, father of Alexander the
Great: (1) the main entrance to the
tomb; (2) the hunting-scene fresco; (3)
the main chamber; (4) the first
sarcophagus and gold casket holding
bones that may have been those of
Philip of Macedón (photo page 21);
(5) shield cover and various bronze
vases; (6) connecting door; (7) opening
to antechamber made by the
archaeologists; (8) antechamber;
(9) second sarcophagus and smaller
funerary casket; (10) golden quiver and
a pair of greaves, or leg-shields, of
unequal length (photo page 21).
Colour page
The rich treasure trove of objects
discovered in what Professor Manolis
Andronicos believes to be the tomb of
Philip of Macedón provides a number
of indications that support his theory.
Bottom photo, this magnificent gold
quiver, with a decoration in relief
depicting the sack of Troy, found in
the antechamber (No. 10 in drawing)
beside the connecting door to the main
chamber, must surely have belonged
to a king. Beside it lay a pair of gilded
bronze greaves, or leg-shields. The left
one is 3.5 centimetres shorter than the
righta significant detail when it is
recalled that PhiliD was lame. Top
photo, found inside the marble
sarcophagus in the main chamber (No.
4 in drawing),' this solid gold larnax, or
funerary casket, weighing nearly 11
kilograms, contained burned bones
that may have been those of Philip
himself. The cover is embossed with
the Macedonian sunburst emblem.
Photos © Spyros Tsavdaroglu, Athens
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
1- ü'KW^SÄ^wÄffe
'suS ^r^-^r "'
3 Sir #
IB "tVi
K/ J^Bk '^
Pi!
HtH
M
m
.:?
, -; .i:'.
*u< "
.*.-*
Sees '
ÜH :-
..<
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
V
: .
M
1*8
*;>.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Centre colour pages
Performed annually for some seven centuries, the
medieval Mystery of Elche retains today all its
ancient vitality and splendour (see article page 32).
Left, the principal members of the cast are
gathered in the Church of Santa Maria for the
climax of the play. The apostles and the people
look on as the Virgin Mary, after her death, is
elevated, soul and body, and crowned Queen of
Heaven. She is accompanied heavenwards by two
angels, singing and playing a guitar and a harp.
Above waits God the Father, flanked by the
Angels of the Coronation. All the roles are played
by the people of Elche, except that after her death
the Virgin Mary is represented by a statue. Top
right, detail from the previous scene shows the
Virgin Mary rising to heaven with the two
accompanying angels. Below, the living Mary is
portrayed, in accordance with ancient tradition, by
a young boy from Elche.
Photos James Wedge
© Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C
Colour page, left
Photo top left. Although Buddhism was the
dominant religion of the Sukhothai period (see
article page 4), Brahmanism co-existed with it
and the Sukhothai school produced a series of
bronze Brahman statues remarkable for their
attention to detail and their beauty. Photo shows
detail from a full-length (155 cm), 14th-century
bronze statue from Sukhothai which represents
Uma, wife of the Brahman god Siva.
Photo top right. Sukhothai sculptors usually
portrayed the seated Buddha cross-legged with
the left hand lying palm upwards on the lap and
the right hand resting on the right knee with the
fingers pointing downwards. This is known as
the "victory over Mara" or the "calling the earth
to witness" attitude. It represents an important
moment in the life of Buddha when Mara, the
evil one, the tempter who is the lord of the
world of passion, attempted to defeat him and
prevent him from attaining enlightenment.
Unmoved by Mara's army of demons, however,
Buddha sat in meditation until Mara and his
armies fled vanquished. With his hand Buddha
touched the ground to call the earth-goddess to
witness his victory over evil.
Bottom photo. This bronze-gilt reclining image
of the Mahaparinirvana (Buddha who has
attained the final nirvana) dates from the 14th or
15th century and was taken to Bangkok from
Wat Pra Luang, Sukhothai, at the beginning of
the 19th century. The couch-pedestal, the statues
of the two disciples and the background painting
of the faithful assembled to hear the Buddha's
last words all date from the 19th century.
Photo Hans Hinz © La Sculpture en Thaïlande, by Jean Boisselier and
Jean-Michel Beurdeley, Editions Office du Livre, Fribourg, Switzerland
Photos Alexis Vorontzoff, Unesco.
Continued from page 18
walls, we uncovered the roof of a rectangular tomb which had
been opened in the past and had seemingly been plundered. We
had found three structures next to one another. Two of them were
underground, the third had been built on the surface.
The structure on the surface had been totally destroyed and only
its foundations were preserved. Yet a number of marble pieces had
been carefully placed next to the foundations; they b»longed to
the superstructure of the building and displayed extremely fine
workmanship. The Galatian destruction of 274/3 BC no longer
seemed an abstract speculation but was confirmed by our
findings.
The interior of the "small" tomb measured 3.5 by 2.09 by 3
metres. It had obviously been violently plundered and little remain¬
ed of its contents. The contents had no doubt been valuable, pro¬
bably consisting of gold, silver and bronze jewelry and utensils.
It was obvious that the tomb must have been unusually lux¬
urious because the upper parts of three of the walls were
decorated with frescoes of excellent quality. On the long north wall
there was. a magnificent painting of "The Abduction of
Persephone by Pluto". This is the first fourth-century BC fresco to
be found in Greece. The confidence and the ease of the painter's
hand, the inspiration of the design and the subtleties of the colour
scale, the power of the expression and the mastery of perspective
indicate that this is the work of a great master.
I consider that this fresco may well have been painted by
Nicomachos, the well-known Greek painter of the mid-fourth cen¬
tury BC, who had portrayed this rare theme and was famous not
only for the perfection of his work but also for the rapidity with
which he executed it. The frescoes on the other two walls depict
female figures, excellently delineated but less elaborately coloured.
When we began clearing the neighbouring wall we came upon a
pile of sherds, ashes and burnt bones of small animals. The sherds
belonged to pots which had been made around 340-330 BC, cer¬
tainly before 320 BC. The masonry of the wall led to a similar con¬
clusion, and this was particularly interesting. As we dug, the
peculiar façade of the tomb began to appear; it was topped by a
cornice with splendidly painted palmettes.
Underneath we expected to see triglyphs and metopes of the
Doric style; instead we encountered a flat surface which seemed
painted. The figure of a standing youth with a spear soon ap¬
peared; close by were a roebuck and a horseman. The entire pain¬
ting, 5.5 metres long and 1.2 metres high, was a unique composi¬
tion from a period of Greek painting whose beauty had only been
guessed at from later Roman copies and imitations, like those in
Pompeii, Herculaneum and Boscoreale.
The main subject was a boar and a lion hunt (no. 2 in drawing
page 20). Three horsemen and seven men on foot, with spears,
dogs and beasts, make their way across a winter landscape which
is indicated by two leafless trees. The rendering of the figures, the
unexpected perspective, the mastery of composition and the quali¬
ty and alternations of the colour reveal the hand of a great painter.
I think that this fresco could be the work of the painter who made
the original depiction of the battle of Issos, on which the famous
mosaic in Naples is based. This unique work by "The Painter of
Vergina" gives us the first opportunity to appreciate the
achievements of Greek painting in one of its highest periods; and it
constituted the first major discovery of the excavation.
Further excavations revealed the entablature of the building, the
metopes and the triglyphs as well as the epistyle and the capitals of
the columns and antacapitals. They were all well preserved with
their original colours intact. Naturally our attention turned to the
middle of the façade where one would expect to find the door.
Realizing that it was impossible to complete the cleaning of the
entrance during this season, we decided to remove the earth from
the top part of the door so that we could see inside and eventually
enter the tomb. This plan was based on the assumption that the
tomb had been plundered and that as a result the door was broken
and had fallen into the tomb. When we reached the lintel,
however, we experienced a great and very pleasant surprise: the
door was intact, a good indication that the tomb had not been
looted (no. 1 in drawing page 20). I had never expected such luck.
Here at Vergina was one of the largest Macedonian tombs, the
oldest to my knowledge, with a unique painting on its front, and it
had not been plundered it was the only intact Macedonian tomb
yet discovered! From that moment, the excitement on the excava- w
.tion grew even more intense. t
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The exquisite beauty of
Greek 4th-century wall-
painting had only been
guessed at, from
descriptions in ancient
Greek literature and from
Roman copies such as
those found at Pompeii,
before the discovery of the
Vergina tombs. Left,
detail from the dramatic
fresco depicting Pluto
abducting Persephone that
embellished the northern
inside wall of the plundered
small tomb.
Photo © Spyros Tsavdaroglou, Athens
The problem was now how to enter the tomb. It would be ¡m-
possible to open the door; this could be done only from the inside
and after the entrance to the floor had been cleared. Behind the
façade we had so far uncovered only a small portion of the roof.
We knew that the tomb was vaulted, like all known Macedonian
tombs, and so there was only one way to enter: by uncovering the
vault and removing the keystone, as the ancient grave robbers had
done.
When the earth, which at that point was six metres deep, was
removed, another unexpected situation arose. In the rear part of
the roof there was a mudbrick structure which had collapsed under
the weight of the earth fill. In this rubble we found two iron
swords, the point of a sarissa (a long pike used by Macedonian
soldiers) and many fragments of iron harnesses, all of which show¬
ed signs of burning. They had probably been placed in the funerary
pyre and then on top of the tomb, bringing to mind the famous
Homeric scene of Patroklos' burial where Achilles burned four
horses along with his dead friend.
On 8 November 1977 we finally removed the keystone of the
vault. With the help of a flashlight I looked through the opening in¬
to the chamber, 4.46 metres square. Across the room was a mar¬
ble door leading into the antechamber (nos. 6 and 8 in drawing
page 20). The coating of the walls, where one might have ex¬
pected painted decoration, was very poor, as if it had been hurried¬
ly applied. Yet in the chamber there were two groups of objects;
bronze vessels and weapons in one corner, silver vessels in the
other. On the floor there was a pile of decomposed materials in¬
terspersed with sheets of gold. Directly below the opening I could
discern a rectangular marble slab which covered a marble sar¬
cophagus (no. 4 in drawing page 20). The spectacle was
fascinating. We were supplied with a ladder and descended into
the chamber which was at a depth of 5.3 metres.
It is impossible to mention everything that was found. The
group of bronze vessels and weapons included two tripods, three
large vessels and some small ones, as well as many iron points of
spears and javelins and two greaves, or leg armour. A remarkable
find in one of the vessels was a sponge which was still soft and
elastic. The group of silver objects included many silver vessels of
high quality. Both their shape and decoration displayed excellent
craftsmanship and unique sensitivity. Nearly all had handles en¬
ding in small heads representing such figures as Herakles, Silenus
and Pan. These small heads constitute a real treasure for the study
of the Greek art of working metal in relief.
There were some other unique pieces. The bronze group was
dominated by a large round object resembling a shield (no. 5 in
drawing page 20). When we moved it, however, we realized that it
could not have been a shield because it had neither a handle nor
any other fitting characteristic of a shield. Neither could it have
been a vessel such as a cauldron. Behind the object lay a pile of
gold and silver bands, a round ivory plaque and the fragments of
two small ivory statuettes.
Careful examination convinced me that all these pieces belong¬
ed to a shield, which originally had a wood and leather frame with
ivory and gold decorations, and handles "adorned with beautiful
relief figures in gilded silver. Such a precious shield was un¬
doubtedly not used in battle and was probably ceremonial. It
would have needed protection; and the bronze object could thus
be its cover.
Next to the shield we found the iron helmet of the deceased,
with the crest typical of the Macedonian helmet and a figure of
Athena in relief on the front. This is the first Macedonian helmet
ever discovered. Some distance away we found a cuirass made of
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
iron sheets covered with leather and cloth. It was adorned with
three golden bands, six gold lions' heads and a rectangular gold
plaque with the figure of Athena in relief; on a fringe at the bottom
were more than fifty gold strips. A sword lay between the cuirass
and the helmet. Its sheath, made of wood with semicircular ivory
end-trimmings, was bound with a series of golden bands and was
decorated with gold palmettes.
The outstanding craftsmanship displayed by this wonderfully
decorated armour testified that the deceased could not have been
a commoner. Moreover, there was another unique find; a ring-
shaped gold and silver object with its ends inserted into a small
cylinder. It was decorated all over with lozenges and, on the small
end-piece, there was a relief design depicting the knot of a ribbon
and the ends of a band. In all probability this is a diadem, or head¬
band. It is similar to those seen in the portraits of such Hellenistic
rulers as Attalos III of Pergamon, Antiochos III of Syria and An¬
tigonus Gonatas of Macedón. Even Alexander the Great was
depicted with such a diadem, for example, in the portraits at
Rossie Priory in England and in the Boston Museum of Fine Arts.
This interpretation then leads us to the inevitable conclusion that
a king had been buried in the tomb. All our finds dated from bet¬
ween 350 BC and 325 BC. From 359 to 336 BC, however, there
was only one king in Macedón, Philip II, remembered not only as
the father of Alexander the Great but also for consolidating the
Macedonian kingdom and establishing its hegemony over Greece
in 338 BC. Alexander, who succeeded Philip in 336 BC and reigned
until 323 BC, died and was buried outside Macedón. Thus, we are
forced to the startling conclusion that if the deceased had been a
king, he was Philip!
Photo © Courtesy Museum of Fine Arts, Boston
If. the standard burial practices had been followed, the cremated
bones of the deceased ought to have been contained in an urn
placed in the marble sarcophagus. We expected to find a richly
decorated amphora, perhaps gilded. When we removed the cover
of the sarcophagus, however, we made an unprecedented find; a
gold larnax, or casket. Not counting the feet on which it stood, it
measured approximately forty centimetres in length, 33.5 cen¬
timetres in width, and 17 centimetres in height. With the bones it
contained, it weighed 10.8 kilograms. It was decorated with
palmettes, rosettes, vines and, on the cover, with a star.
Inside were the cremated bones, in a remarkable state of
cleanliness and, on top of them, a gold wreath with acorns and oak
leaves. Some of the bones and the bottom of the larnax were col¬
oured with a bluish-purple tint. Specialists later confirmed that this
came from the purple cloth with which the bones had once been
wrapped, reminiscent of Homer's descriptions of the funerals of
Patroklos, Hector and Achilles, the great heroes of the Trojan War.
We thought that this find must surely be the climax of a
remarkable excavation. Yet even more surprises were in store,
unexpected finds which further supported the tomb's association
with Philip. On the floor in front of the marble sarcophagus we
found remains of what may have been a wooden bed or piece of
furniture decorated with gold and ivory figurines. The ivory heads,
hands and legs lying on the floor, were left where they were, to be
removed later by specialists.
One day, however, as I was studying the interior of the tomb, I
decided to pick up one of the pieces. To my great surprise, I
discovered that it was an excellent portrait of Philip, showing him
as a mature man, somewhat tired, his injured eye subtly depicted,
yet clearly reflecting his strong personality.
I lifted a second head, and this time I could scarcely believe my
eyes. I looked again carefully. Surely I could not be mistaken! It
was the best portrait I had ever seen of Alexander the Great, depic¬
ting him with his neck stretched and turned, his vivid eyes looking
upward, his gaze intense, precisely as he is described by Plutarch
CONTINUED PAGE 30
Face of a conqueror
"Mine is the earth; thou, O Zeus, content
thyself with Olympus." The arrogant
boldness these words imply emerges
clearly from the portraits of Alexander
that have come down to us, such as this
bronze statue, left, in the style of the 4th-
century-BC Greek.sculptor Lysippus. Now
in the Louvre Museum, Paris, it originally
depicted Alexander holding a lance.
Although, according to Plutarch,
Alexander ordained that only Lysippus
should portray him, several more or less
idealized portraits of the great conqueror
by other artists exist. Far left, preserved in
.the Acropolis Museum, Athens, this head
of Alexander with its leonine shock of
hair, sensual mouth and intelligent intense
expression is the work of another great
Greek sculptor, Leochares. Centre left,
with head inclined and eyes turned
heavenwards, this statue from the
Hellenistic period, now in the Museum of
Fine Arts, Boston, reproduces the
characteristics traditionally ascribed to
Alexander in literature. Just visible is part
of the royal diadem often seen in portraits
of sovereigns of the Hellenistic period and
strikingly similar to the diadem, above
left, found in the main chamber of the
great tomb at Vergina. Wrought in gold
and silver, it bears a diamond-shaped
pattern completed by a knotted ribbon
motif in relief. Yet none of these portraits
conveys the same sense of stark realism
that exudes from the portrait, thought to
be of Alexander, discovered at Vergina
and reproduced on our cover.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
M
m
Photo © Roger Viollet, Paris. Hellenic Institute of Byzantine Studies, Venice
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
The Alexander legend
The fame of Alexander spread throughout both the eastern and the
western world, reaching incredible proportions after his death. As well
as being the incarnation of the supreme victor, the conqueror of Greece
and of Asia became a quasi-mythical hero, endowed with all the virtues
and capable of all kinds of miraculous exploits. Illustrations and
legendary accounts of his feats abounded. A life of Alexander written in
the second century AD by a Greek author, the so-called "pseudo-
Callisthenes", was translated into Latin during the fourth century ;
during the eleventh and twelfth centuries it was taken up again by a
number of French poets, some of whom, to honour Alexander, wrote in
a verse form with lines containing six iambic feet which became known
as Alexandrines. He is also immortalized as one of the four kings in a
pack of cards. Many and varied were his legendary exploits. Photos : (1)
Space-traveller. Under the astonished gaze of his soldiers, Alexander
explores the heavens in a special cage borne up by two "hideous and
grotesque" griffins. (2) Explorer of the ocean depths. In this miniature
from a 14th-century French romance, La Vraie Ystoire dou bon Roi
Alexandre (The True History of the Good King Alexander), the intrepid
hero descends in a glass barrel to the strange world of the ocean bed,
with its curious whales, fish and mermen. The conqueror of the world
was the pupil of Aristotle and was viewed also as the conqueror of the
world of knowledge. (3) The model son. Pictured here in a medieval
Byzantine manuscript, Alexander leads his mother Olympias into the
presence of his father king Philip II of Macedón in the hopes of
effecting a reconciliation between the estranged couple. This must be
considered one of his rare failures ; indeed, historians are generally
agreed that Olympias later engineered Philip's assassination. (4)
Prophet. An illustration from a 15th century French manuscript shows
Alexander telling the tree of the sun and the tree of the moon of his
forthcoming death.
Bibliothèque Royale Albert I, Brussels
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
Death of a hero. This fine 10th-century Persian miniature, from Ferdousi's famous Shah-Nama
(Book of Kings) evokes the tragic character of Jhe "Great Iskandar's" death. His body rests
on an elaborate bier, in the customary style of the Emperors of China. In the foreground, the
mourners wring their hands in grief. Olympias, in the centre, half lies across his bier, the
epitome of maternal distress, while from behind the bier the great Aristotle looks for the last
time at his former pupil.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The ancient Indian province of
Gandhara marked the most
easterly point reached by
Alexander's conquering armies.
During the 2nd century BC,
Gandhara came under the
domination of Indo-Greek rulers
and the distinctive Greco-
Buddhist art style that
developed there was a unique
amalgam of Hellenistic, Roman,
Syrian and Persian influences.
This Apollo-like head of Buddha
is a detail from the Boddhisattva
of Shabhaz-garhi, now in the
Guimet Museum, Paris.
i (see front cover). Nearby, a third portrait resembled that of Alex¬
ander, but it was that of a woman. I decided later that it
represented Olympias, Alexander's mother.
Further away were two more portraits, one of a male and the
other of a female, both with vigorous features which, however, I
could not identify. I remembered how, after the Battle of
Chaeronea in 338 BC, which had established Macedon's
hegemony over all Greece, Philip had commissioned statues of his
family from the great sculptor Leochares. The statues, to be
dedicated at Olympia, represented Philip, his parents, Alexander,
who had fought alongside Philip at Chaeronea, and Olympias.
It is very probable that at the same time the king commissioned
various pieces of furniture decorated with figures of his family. If
this were so, these small portraits may have been executed by
Leochares himself or in his workshop. Their exceptional quality in¬
dicates that they were made by a great master. There can be little
doubt that these are the best and most authoritative portraits not
only of Philip but of Alexander as well. The archaeological
evidence discovered so far therefore leads to the hypothesis that
the tomb belonged to King Philip. I emphasize the fact that this is
not a conclusion, but a hypothesis, which must be further confirm¬
ed by epigraphical evidence.
The tomb, like all large Macedonian tombs, consisted of a
chamber and an antechamber, divided by a two-leafed marble
door. Opening this sealed portal would not be an easy task. In¬
stead of forcing the heavy door, therefore, a block was removed
from the partition wall to enable us to enter the antechamber (no. 7
in drawing page 20). We had hoped that the walls or the vault of
the antechamber would be decorated with frescoes but we did not
expect to find more objects. Once again we were taken by sur¬
prise.
First of all, the wall plaster was of high quality, white on the
lower and Pompeian red on the upper part, but there were no
frescoes. The presence of a second marble sarcophagus, slightly
larger and more elongated than that in the main chamber, was
totally unexpected. On its cover, a pile of decomposed organic
matter looked as if it might have been the remains of flowers or
ears of wheat. Microscopic examination proved, however, that
this material actually consisted of feathers of large birds. Such
feathers were also found on the floor mixed with a large quantity of
other organic matter, presumably the remains of clothing and
wooden furniture.
High up on the walls were nails from which fabrics had probably
been hung. Fine gold sheets, broken glass and ivory scattered over
a large area of the floor indicated that the furniture had been gilded
and elaborately decorated. A gold wreath of myrtle leaves and
flowers lay on the floor next to the sarcophagus.
Many alabastra were found in the space between the door jambs .
and the marble door. Yet the most impressive discovery was a gold
quiver or gorytus, similar to those found in the royal tombs of the
Scythians in Southern Russia (see Unesco Courier, December
1976).
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
It was decorated in relief with scenes that probably depict the
sack of Troy. Behind this gold plaque We found arrows; part of
their wooden shafts had been preserved in fairly good condition. A
fourth pair of greaves lay beside the quiver (no. 10 in drawing page
20). In this case the greaves were gilded. The left one was 3.5 cen¬
timetres shorter than the right, a fact which reminded us that Philip
was lame.
The final surprise came from the sarcophagus in the
antechamber. When we removed the heavy cover, we found
another golden larnax, sightly smaller and with simpler decoration
than that of the main chamber, yet with the same characteristic
star on its lid (no. 9 in drawing page 20). The cremated bones in¬
side the casket had been wrapped in a purple cloth interwoven
with gold thread; its border was decorated with a wave pattern, its
centre with vine leaves, flowers and branches. Beside the bones, a
very elegant diadem of golden flowers and twigs had been placed,
or rather pushed. In all probability this diadem had belonged to a
woman.
The quantity of finds, their opulence and, most of all, their quali¬
ty supported the view that we were in a royal tomb. Since the en¬
tire chamber belonged to Philip II, who could have been buried in
the antechamber? It might be supposed, for instance, that the
deceased was a woman, as the elegant diadem and myrtle wreath
suggest, and therefore that she might be Philip's last wife,
Cleopatra, who was either executed or forced to commit suicide.
This interpretation, however, raises problems, the most important
of which is the absence of female jewelry in the antechamber. We
would prefer to wait until more research has been done before put¬
ting forward any conclusions.
Such were the results of excavations carried out in 1977.
When we continued our excavations in the summer of 1978 we
made another important find. On 5 August we found the façade of
another Macedonian tomb, a small distance to the north of the
Great Tomb, which we opened on the 22nd of the same month.
The new tomb (tomb III) is smaller but architecturally similar to
the great one. It consists of a chamber and an antechamber, and
on its façade is a similar frieze. However, the mural painting on the
façade, unlike that of the Great Tomb, has been totally destroyed
because it was executed on some kind of organic material,
possibly a wooden panel, and not on the stucco of the wall.
Inside the chamber one of the two leaves of the inner marble
door was found lying broken on the ground. Instead of a sar¬
cophagus there was a "table" with a cavity in its upper part, into
which had been put a silver hydria, or pitcher, containing the burn¬
ed bones of the dead. On its shoulder was a golden wreath of
leaves and acorns. Almost the entire floor was covered with the re¬
mains of organic substances similar to those which had already
been discovered (a wooden bed, pieces of leather, ivories etc.). In
one corner there were many silver vases of high quality; in another,
two big vessels of silvered bronze. Near them was a tall silvered
iron lamp-stand. The clay lamp had fallen on the ground. At the
other side there was a pair of greaves, two wreaths of gilded
bronze and some other objects. A few pieces of the ivory decora¬
tion of the wooden bed could still be seen.
On the floor of the antechamber we found the remains of a
leather garment adorned with gold. At the other side of the
antechamber among other organic remains were strigils, in¬
struments used for scraping the skin after exercise or at the bath,
and the lower part of a gilded spear. Finally, the walls of the
antechamber are covered with a continuous narrow frieze depic¬
ting a chariot race. Although the painting cannot be compared
with those of the two other tombs, since its character is only
decorative, it is nevertheless of very good quality and quite well
preserved.
From the fragments of the ivory relief decoration of the bed,
technicians have so far restored an exquisite group scene depicting
Pan and a dionysiac couple, possibly Dionysos and Ariadne or
some other couple in a "thiasos", or procession of worshippers.
The occupant of the tomb must have been very young, but I am
certain that he also belonged to the royal family. My first impres¬
sion is that the new tomb is earlier than the great one, but I cannot
be fully certain until I have studied the objects fully.
After this new discovery, I think that it is possible that we are in
the area of the royal necropolis and that it is highly probable that a
new tomb will be found as the excavation continues. Certainly
there is an increasing awareness of the importance of the
discovery. The objects that have been found so far offer extremely
precious material for the study of the art of the 4th century BC,
especially for the study of the painting of this period which has
hitherto been almost unknown.
Manolis Andronicos
./
;L
Krxmr: > ;>> a
fwC./.
û " . <
. * < 	 « - *	 j_-
Darius III Codommanus, king of the
Persians from 335 to 330 BC, died at
Hecatompylos (present-day Damghan
some 200 kilometres east of Teheran),
stabbed to death by Bessus, the satrap
of Bactria. Alexander, in hot pursuit of
the Persian king, arrived on the scene
shortly afterwards and ordered that he
should be buried at Persepolis with full
royal honours, married his daughter
Stateira and proclaimed himself Darius'
successor. In this exquisite Persian
miniature from the 15th-century Shah-
Mama (Book of Kings), Alexander is
seen supporting the dead king's body.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
*" Mr
\¡ ©
©
O)
T3
0>
5
«
I E
CD
-)
O
I
One of the opening scenes of the Mystery of Elchethe Apostles and the angels enter the
Church of Santa Maria in procession. The Mystery was filmed in its entirety for the first time
last year by a group under the direction of Michael Dodds and journalist and film-director
Gudie Lawaetz whose idea it was to preserve for posterity a complete record of this unusual,
centuries-old spectacle. The latest cinematographic techniques were used in the project,
which was partly financed by Unesco's International Fund for the Promotion of Culture.
The Mystery of Elche
A seven-century-old sacred drama
performed each year in a Spanish city
by Juan Carlos Langlois
JUAN CARLOS LANGLOIS, of Argentina, is
executive secretary at Unesco of the Interna¬
tional Fund for the Promotion of Culture. He has
undertaken a number of artistic and literary
studies in his own country and his paintings
have been frequently exhibited. A specialist in
international co-operation for development, he
was formerly European representative of the
Inter-American Development Bank.
THE profusion of Romanesque and
Gothic monuments which rose in
Christian Europe during the Middle
Ages form a precious part of the world's
cultural heritage. These religious buildings
are an intrinsic part of Europe's physical
and spiritual landscape, and European
Governments today are rightly concerned
with preserving and restoring them.
It is relatively easy to restore stonework.
But is it possible to recreate the human and
religious atmosphere of medieval times?
And if so, can it be done without recourse
to stage or screen reconstructions which
only give a rough idea of the feelings of
medieval people for whom the Church was
the centre of community life?
The answer to this question is to be
found in the Spanish city of Elche, in the
province of Alicante. There, ever since the
fourteenth century, a medieval mystery
drama has been staged on 14 and 15
August to celebrate the feast of the
Assumption. In the sixteenth century the
Council of Trent forbade the performance
of drama in churches, but the Elche
Mystery was exempted from this prohibi¬
tion by a special dispensation from Pope
Urban VIM.
The survival of this production, the only
one of its kind in Europe, owes much to the
devotion of the people of Elche. For nearly
seven centuries they have preserved the
form and spirit of the "Misteri d'Elx" in an
atmosphere of collective enthusiasm which
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
authentically recreates the world of
medieval religious drama.
Between the twelfth and the sixteenth
centuries the staging of scriptural dramas
or "mysteries" in churches became widely
popular in France, England and Spain.
Hundreds of actors took part in these pro¬
ductions, which went on for days at a time
and involved the use of highly elaborate
scenery and equipment. Some of the texts
which have survived have over 30,000
verses.
These medieval dramatizations of the
scriptures, whose lineage in some respects
stretches back to the ancient Greek and
Roman mysteries, were the precursors of
Renaissance drama and music in Europe.
But nothing in the West changes more
rapidly and more constantly than the
dramatic arts. Apart from certain texts,
musical notations and, since the last cen¬
tury, a handful of productions which are
for the most part merely pious attempts to
reconstitute a vanished tradition, little re¬
mains of medieval scriptural drama and the
upsurge of fervour with which it was im¬
bued.
This is why the Elche Mystery is so im¬
portant and why there was a pressing need
to record for posterity this presentation of
the mystery of the Assumption, the only
one to have survived virtually intact the
vicissitudes of European history and the
changing pattern of religious practices and
customs in Europe.
Elche is situated near the Mediterranean
littoral, twenty-four kilometres from
Alicante. Founded during the Roman Em¬
pire, it was subsequently occupied by the
Visigoths and then by the Arabs. During
the reign.of Abd ar-Rahman III in the tenth
century Elche enjoyed a period of spec¬
tacular development, with the construction
of buildings, fortifications and an irrigation
system which led to the creation of the
most important oasis in south-eastern
Spain and a 600-hectare palm grove, the
biggest in Europe.
The combination of Arab-Muslim ar
chitecture, palm-trees and the blue
Mediterranean sky make a setting not
unlike that in which Christianity began, and
explains why Elche is sometimes known as
the "Spanish Jerusalem".
Elche is not a remote, inaccessible town
but a major industrial and agricultural cen¬
tre with a population of 160,000, situated
twelve kilometres from a busy international
airport. Rapid expansion in recent decades,
industrial development and a growing in¬
flux of tourists have brought many changes
to the city but have in no way affected the
Mystery play. Why, it might be asked, has
the Elche Mystery survived in an age when
urban growth, the spread of tourism and
the mass media have tainted or even
destroyed so much traditional popular
drama and ceremonial in many parts of the
world?
One of the answers surely lies in the
complex links which have for centuries
bound the people of Elche to "their"
Mystery. Today, as in the Middle Ages, the
community as a whole is committed to its
success. The actors who year by year
polish their performance as Apostles,
angels or members of the crowd, are
workmen, craftsmen and technicians who
live and work in the modern world; but
they are very much aware of being the
repositories of a remarkable tradition.
One surprising and reassuring feature of
the Mystery is that the participants do not
belong to a single age-group. People of all
ages take part, united by a common en¬
thusiasm. Children and youths, for exam¬
ple, take female roles, in accordance with
medieval custom. The Virgin Mary is cur¬
rently played by an eleven-year-old boy,
Manolito.
The Mystery consists of two parts, the
"Vespra" and the "Festa", which take
place on 14 and 15 August respectively.
The former begins when the Virgin enters
the church and ends with her death, or dor-
mition, in the midst of the Apostles. Mean¬
while four angels descend from "heaven"
and then return to the cupola bearing an
¡mage of Mary symbolizing her soul. On the
15th, there is a dramatization of the solemn
burial of the Virgin and her coronation,
which takes place to applause and cries of
jubilation from the crowd, while the organ
plays, bells ring and fireworks explode.
The Catalan writer Eugenio d'Ors, who
first attended the Elche Mystery in 1934,
noted that in a lifetime as a theatre-goer he
had never experienced such depths of
emotion: "Here nothing separates the
stage from the public", he wrote. "Nothing
separates drama from religious ceremony,
heaven from earth, domestic anecdote
from supernatural crisis. The apse becomes
a nave; the altar an alcove. Temple and
street are one. Plain-chant merges into
polyphony; polyphony into operatic
melody. Flourishes of organ music punc¬
tuate the recitative. The distinctions disap¬
pear between psalmody and chant, chant
and prayer, cries and sobbing. We applaud
in the church and pray in the street".
For Eugenio d'Ors the Elche Mystery, the
oldest opera in the world, combines an
even vaster range of forms of expression
than those of Wagnerian Bayreuth. "The
cosmic rapture and ecstasy unleashed by
the Elche Mystery are not even attained in
the Holy Week processions in Seville," he
wrote. "The immersion in the unconscious
brought about by such a unique spectacle
is a profound revelation of the very essence
of theatre".
From an artistic point of view, the
Mystery may be considered as one of the
most important precursors of the operatic
music and drama of Renaissance Europe.
The poetry of the text, recited in Valencian,
a dialect of the Catalan language, probably
has roots in the literature of the Provençal
troubadours. Both text and music were
modified after the expulsion of the Jews
from Spain in 1492 and assumed their pre¬
sent form in 1639. Their power is undimm-
ed by time.
A few years ago it was suggested that
the Elche Mystery should be filmed in its
entirety so that the unique spectacle could
be preserved for posterity. The project was V
carried out with aid from Unesco's Interna- f
Mary, the mother of St. James
the Less, and Mary, the mother
of St. John, are seen seated,
left, next to two angels, on the
enclosed podium on which lies
the body of the Virgin Mary. The
podium forms the stage on
which various scenes from the
Mystery are enacted. In the
background, the public watch as
the drama unfolds.
Photo James Wedge
© Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Manolito, the eleven-year-old boy from Elche who plays the part of the Virgin Mary, at
home with his father and grandfather, both of whom have taken an active part in the
performance of the Mystery in previous years. The Mystery has taken deep root among
the people of Elche and each year hundreds of families of the city are involved in the
spectacle. The tradition of having a feminine role played by a boy was not peculiar to
sacred medieval plays; in Shakespeare's England and in some other countries female roles
were normally played by boys.
tional Fund for the Promotion of Culture,
and filming was completed in August 1978.
The technicians triumphantly surmounted
the technical obstacles of recording the
Mystery; to ensure the maximum of
authenticity there was no trial run-through
before filming. It was also imperative not to
hamper the movements of actors and con¬
gregation, a total of more than 3,000
persons.
From the resulting three-hour-long
recording a 110-minute film was made, the
first ever of a complete medieval scriptural
mystery. It was shown for the first time in
Washington last April and has already been
bought by a number of national television
networks.
With aid from the Unesco Fund further
studies are being carried out on the origins
of the Elche Mystery, the reasons for its
survival and also its possible influence out¬
side Spain. Certain popular religious rituals
in Latin America, for example, may well be
offshoots of medieval Spanish mysteries.
Will all the mysteries enshrouding the
Elche Mystery ever be cleared up? Perhaps
not, since according to one definition a
mystery is "something inaccessible to
reason which must be considered as an ar¬
ticle of faith".
Scientific and technological develop¬
ment is an imperative of our time, but its
aims and consequences are today no
longer regarded as "articles of faith". The
respect for cultural identity and the desire
felt by communities and individuals to
rediscover, safeguard and promote their
traditional cultural values are re-emerging
as preoccupations of overshadowing im¬
portance. Elche is a community in which
these values have never been forgotten.
Juan Carlos Langlois
The International Fund for the
Promotion of Culture
Established by Unesco in 1974, the International Fund for the Promotion of
Culture is intended to promote cultural values, to assist artistic creation in all Its
forms and to 'encourage regional and International cultural co-operation.
The Fund is administered by an Administrative Council composed of fifteen
members appointed in their personal capacity by the Director-General of Unesco.
The initial financial resources of the Fund were contributed by a number of
Unesco Member States (Chile, Egypt, India, Indonesia, Iran, Ivory Coast, Nigeria,
Saudi Arabia, Senegal, Venezuela and Yugoslavia) and by various foundations,
institutions and private individuals.
The Fund, which became operational in April 1977, has up to now approved grants
worth more than a million dollars to assist cultural promotion projects in all the"
major cultural regions of the world.
Projects financed by the Fund include: the establishment of the Mudra-Africa
Centre, in Dakar, for the training of performing artists; a study to examine the
feasibility of establishing, in Colombia, a company to produce and market cultural
goods and services ; the creation of an Inter-cultural School of Music, in Venice ;
the production of a film and a textbook as aids to the teaching of design based
on traditional cultural values, for the National Institute of Design, India ; the
creation of an experimental television teaching centre in Venezuela ; a
programme for the recording of Arab music.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Polish educator, doctor and author, Janusz Korczak (1878-
1942) introduced many revolutionary innovations in the field
of child care and teaching and eventually died at the
Treblinka concentration camp with the orphaned children to
whom he had devoted the greater part of his life. Korczak
taught that every child had the right to be respected as an
individual and as a child. Left, at a holiday camp for poor
children from Warsaw, in 1907, Korczak listens intently to a
child reading, while all those around him seem concerned
only with what the photographer is doing.
Janusz
Korczak
The doctor who lived
and died for children
by Stanislaw Tomkiewicz
and Béatrice Maffioli
AN educator whose ideas broke new
ground, a pioneer of child psychi¬
atry and a prolific writer, Janusz
Korczak was a passionate and lifelong
defender, not of childhood as an abstrac¬
tion but of individual children who suffered
oppression, hardship and neglect.
Korczak and his work have been famous
for many years in Poland, Israel, the Soviet
Union and Germany but they are still not
widely known in other parts of the world.
This year Unesco is celebrating the hun¬
dredth anniversary of his birth (see Unesco
Courier, April 1979 page 34) and publishing
a selection of his works in French as part of
its literature translations programme.
STANISLAW TOMKIEWICZ, head of the
department of psychopathology at the Universi¬
ty of Paris VIII (Vincennes), is director of
research at the National Institute of Health and
Medical Research, Paris, and scientific director'
of the Institute's unit for research on the mental
health of young children and disturbed
adolescents. A paediatrician andpsychiatrist, he
was born in Warsaw, and after surviving the
Warsaw ghetto rising against the Nazis he was
deported to the concentration camp of Belsen.
He has lived in France since 1945.
BEATRICE MAFFIOLI, French specialist in the
history of fascism, works at the National In¬
stitute of Health and Medical Research, Paris,
and is an active member of the French "Friends
of Doctor Janusz Korczak Association". She
has also worked in Africa as a sociologist and
educational consultant.
Korczak (whose real name was Henryk
Goldszmit) was born in Warsaw, then oc¬
cupied by Tsarist Russia. His family belong¬
ed to the so-called "assimilated" stratum of
the Jewish community. The Goldszmits
were patriots imbued with Polish language
and culture; they did not practise their
religion assiduously but neither did they
deny their Judaism. They subscribed to the
liberal reformist ideas of the intelligentsia of
their time, and dreamed of the in¬
dependence of Poland and of a society
from which poverty would be banished.
The grandson of a doctor and the son of
a famous barrister, Henryk enjoyed a happy
childhood. Then, when he was seventeen
years old, his father died after a long period
of confinement in a psychiatric institution.
The nature of his illness is not fully
understood. Korczak had to provide for his
mother and sister and learned for himself
what it was like to be poor.
Korczak's personality was profoundly
marked by his experience of being both a
Jew and a Pole, by his transition from
wealth to poverty, and by his fear of
hereditary madness.
Paying his way by giving private lessons,
he passed his baccalauréat and then began
to study medicine. In these years he made
friends with young people in the poorest
districts of Warsaw. In 1900 he helped to
organize the first holiday camps for Polish
working-class children, a revolutionary idea
at that time. After specializing in
paediatrics in hospitals in Berlin and Paris,
he soon won a reputation as a paediatri¬
cian, treating the children of wealthy
families. However, he devoted more and
more time to hospital work, to his writing,
to educational problems and to the welfare
of needy children.
In 1905, recently qualified-, he took part
in the Russo-Japanese War as a doctor with
the Russian army where he encountered
the first soldiers' soviets. In gatherings held
to discuss the liberation of the working
man he took the floor and pleaded for the
liberation of the child without which, he
said, the liberation of humanity would be
an absurdity.
In 1910 he spent some time as a teacher
in children's holiday camps. Out of this ex¬
perience came two short novels, Joski,
Moski i Srule and Joski, Jaski i Franki,
which were read by children and adults
alike. In them Korczak describes with sen¬
sitivity and humour the behaviour of poor
children on holiday and their impressions
when they discovered the countryside and
community life for the first time, in an at¬
mosphere where hierarchy and repression
were non-existent.
Soon after the publication of these
works Korczak took the step which was to
determine the course of the rest of his life.
He helped to plan a new building for a War¬
saw children's orphanage, and when it
opened was appointed its director, physi- V
cian and head teacher. From this time until f
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
>his tragic death in 1942 his life would be
devoted to this children's home, except for
a four-year absence during the First World
War. After 1920 he only left the orphanage ,
for short periods of travel, including visits
to Palestine in 1934 and 1936.
His fear of hereditary madness prevented
Korczak from marrying and having a family
of his own. His only children were those of
others.
From 1922 to 19o6 he also worked as a
teacher and physician at an orphanage for
Catholic children. He lectured at Warsaw
University and between 1934 and 1938
broadcast each week on Polish radio under
the pseudonym of "the old doctor". First
of all he presented a programme in which
he told stories for children; later he gave
advice to parents and spoke in defence of
children's rights. The texts of these popular
talks were later published in a book entitled
Droll Teaching. Even at this time Korczak
had high hopes of the possibilities of audio¬
visual methods in popular education and
ranks as a pioneer in this field.
The rise of Nazism in Germany brought a
threat to the Jews of Poland. Korczak's ter¬
rible sufferings on account of this brought
him closer to Judaism and even to a certain
mysticism.
Korczak broadcast again on Polish radio
in September 1939, raising the people's
morale during the heroic defence of War¬
saw against the Nazi attack which left parts
of the city in ruins. From the very beginn¬
ing of the occupation Korczak refused to
wear the yellow star which the Jews were
obliged to display, and although he was
subjected to physical violence and sentenc¬
ed to a term of imprisonment on this ac¬
count, his resolution did not weaken.
In October 1940 the orphanage was forc¬
ed to move into the newly-created Warsaw
ghetto. Death took a terrible toll, especially
of the children, scores of whom died in the
streets every day. But wretched and starv¬
ing though they were, Korczak's orphans
lived in an island of relative peace and
security. Right until the end, Korczak's
force of personality and unremitting efforts
ensured that their minimum needs of food,
hygiene and above all affection were met.
In 1942, two weeks before they were
sent to their death, Korczak had the
children perform Rabindranath Tagore's
play The Post, the story of a sick child who
dies dreaming of running through the
fields, in the hope of familiarizing them
with the idea of death. He received several
offers of safety if he would consent to leave
the ghetto, his orphanage and his children.
But he refused to countenance such a
possibility. On 5 August 1942 he was with
the 200 orphans when they began their last
journey to the gas chambers of the
Treblinka death camp.
Korczak's was a rich and complex per¬
sonality. First and foremost he was an
author who wrote whenever he had a spare
moment in his crowded life of teaching and
caring for children. He was still writing only
a few days before his death. His novels,
scientific articles and studies, short stories,
pamphlets and plays reached a vast public
of children, parents, doctors and
educators.
His children's books were widely read
and loved during his lifetime and are still as
relevant as ever. If some passages have
worn less well than others, his harrowing
descriptions of needy Jewish and Catholic
working-class children in Poland under the
Tsarist occupation and between the wars
find an echo in the experience of certain
children of migrant workers today and are
as powerful and as topical as when they
were written. Some parts of his work are
unbearably moving; others are rich in
humour. Korczak had an unfailing gift for
capturing children's imagination, an in¬
stinctive understanding of their desires and
fears.
A year after the appearance of his two
short novels about life in a children's holi¬
day camp, he published Fame, his first
novel written specifically for children. In it
he evokes the dream of omnipotence, the
desire for fame and the impossibility of
fulfilling this desire in childhood.
true, in defiance of common sense and pro¬
bability.
In spite of their humour, these books are
profoundly sombre. They show how
dreams of grandeur, if they remain mere
fantasies, are always thwarted when they
come up against the realities of life.
But Korczak's last story for children,
written in 1938, reveals how such dreams
can be fulfilled. Entitled A Stubborn Boy, it
is a fictional biography of Louis Pasteur.
The creation of the famous "Little
Review", the first weekly journal entirely
written by children and adolescents, had an
important place in Korczak's literary ac¬
tivities. With its 2,000 correspondents aged
from six to eighteen, the magazine voiced
all the preoccupations of Poland's
schoolchildren. It brought out the true im¬
portance of seemingly trivial events in
children's lives, their injustices and
In King Mathias I, a novel which has
been translated into twenty-two
languages, this dream comes true, as Korc¬
zak portrays the greatness and ultimate
downfall of a boy king who sets out to
establish a world of justice and peace for
children and adults alike. The work satirizes
the high and mighty, gives a comic ex¬
planation of the machinery of power and
shows a topsy turvy world in which
children are workers and adults attend
school.
Little Jack Goes Bankrupt (1924)
presents the dream of grandeur in a dif¬
ferent form: a little boy enters the business
world, not to make a fortune but to replace
the profit motive with a co-operative
system.
In Jo/o the Magician (1934) a child
comes to realize that he has supernatural
powers when some of his wishes come
pleasures, joys and sorrows, focussing on
all those things that adults tend to dismiss
as trifles because, unlike Korczak, they
have forgotten how important they are to
children.
"I should like my children's newspaper to
be printed on cigarette paper", Korczak
once said, "just like the literature pro¬
hibited under Tsarist Russia and in Poland
between the wars. I should like this
newspaper to say things that adults will not
know about because they will be afraid to
read it."
The "Little Review", still a revolutionary
idea even today, ceased publication when
the Nazis invaded Poland in 1939.
Korczak left no academic treatises, no
turgid textbooks, no abstract theories. He
was not intellectually incapable of writing
for a restricted academic audience, but he >
did not wish to do so. The destiny of each f
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Korczak's work with children
began while he was still a young
medical student and in 1900 he
helped organize the first holiday
camps for poor children in
Poland. In 1913 he opened the
orphanage for Jewish children at
92, Krochmalna Street, Warsaw,
to which he was to devote his
life. In 1922 he became, in
addition, co-director and medical
superintendent of Nas Dom (Our
Home), an orphanage for Catholic
children. Photos, top right,
children of the Nas Dom
orphanage in Warsaw and,
bottom right, at a holiday camp at
Bielany. Centre right, children
from the Jewish orphanage at
their last holiday camp, at
Goclawek, In 1940. In October
1940 the Jewish orphanage was
transferred to the newly
constructed Warsaw ghetto. Left,
Janusz Korczak in 1938. At a time
when the rising tide of Nazism
had already swamped Austria,
Korczak wears the troubled look
of a man anxious about what the
future holds for his beloved
children.
' ' :- ^
"Ï
Üä
'm*?*
^ ,
t y
*c i
i, ir- '
* T-
.
W^jfi
r^¿ ^
±jj**'**
ùt '*& ¿^?
'* Hi
ÎB^'
M IllPikP
wrWM
1 ^^^^^Ht f^BBKf V^k
>^ M£
.- ' 'i
1
5
*> * ^Ä - fttk
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
L individual child took precedence over
'generalizations which might turn out to be
arbitrary or unfounded.
How to Love a Child, writen in a field
hospital during the First World War, shows
how Korczak transmuted experience and
theory into poetry. His works often consist
of aphorisms, thoughts and anecdotes
seemingly jotted down at random. A close
reading, however, reveals that they have a
structure and that behind the apparent
discursiveness is a coherent system based
on protection, love and respect for
children. Children were the subject of vir¬
tually all his writing and the mainspring of
his life.
Korczak's literary, social and scientific
publications for adult readers are not easy
to classify because they eschew pedantry
and jargon for humour and tenderness.
Among the most important of these works
are:
Ghetto Diary, the reflections of a man
without illusions on a world collapsing into
cruelty and horror;
The Child's Right to Respect is a
veritable proclamation of the Rights of the
Child, a denunciation of the love that stifles
and a defence of the love that encourages
independence. In this work Korczak also
denounces the oppression of children and
suggests ways of ending it;
How to Love a Child is a compendium of
Korczak's ideas on education. Although
the first part dealing with infancy is now
somewhat outmoded, the sections on
«ll^HTTWIIlTi»'.-.
boarding education and on schools in
general contain ideas which are still regard¬
ed as advanced today.
Janusz Korczak never completely aban¬
doned medicine. He practised as a
paediatrician, specializing in the study of
relationships in the family and at school. He
may be considered as a forerunner of the
modern "antipsychiatrists" although, like
almost all physicians at the beginning of
the century he was a positivist, a materialist
and a firm believer in scientific method. He
was a defender of theories of heredity and
even of eugenics, and yet he was also con¬
vinced of the perfectibility of the child
through love and education.
Knowing where beliefs in eugenics and
hereditary theories of behaviour led in Nazi
Germany, we may feel that this paradox is
a tragic contradiction in. Korczak's thought.
But it must be remembered that he lived in
the pre-Nazi era when such notions were
the dogmas of Western medicine and
psychology. It was only when Hitler took
these theories to their ultimate conclusions
that scientists came to understand the im¬
portance of the biological, affective,
cultural, political and social environment in
the child's development.
But Korczak's place in the history of
human thought is as an educator rather
than a writer or a physician.
In the Warsaw orphanage he was able to
apply his educational ideas. There, instead
of the traditional structure of discipline bas¬
ed on the power of the adult and the obe-
SAMORZQD w SZKOLE.
EH
%
Jsr
Maly PAIY TRZEGLAD
f'liMO DZfEr.1 I KtMZfEZY
htitipetr to FFBtt« rano
#« " * * F * '
60 PRHM4M1
tygorJniowy oodatex bezptauty to Nr. ZT* 12708) JI«U3» PncUlte".
CZTERY LATA MAtEGO PRZEGLADU.
LJaly do Malaga Pn«gl«du.
¡TÏT Is,'- -,"',!,*, i *
^i^'i^lS*^^-'^|^ 2APH0J2EKE qo kiha.
dience of the child, he created an elected
parliament, an elected system of self-
government, a daily wall newspaper and a
diary written by the children.
Perhaps the most original institution of
the orphanage was the children's court,
also elected by the orphans. It settled
disputes, judged misdeeds and good
deeds, whether these were done by the
children or the teachers. Korczak himself
was not exempt from its jurisdiction. It en¬
forced a code drawn up by Korczak with a
judicious mixture of humour, understan¬
ding and kindness. The punishments in¬
flicted were purely symbolic.
Korczak always saw the children placed
in his care as human beings. He refused to
consider them as miniature adults; each
child was unique.
In words and acts he proclaimed that the
orphans had a right to happiness. Before
the war this was a novel idea and even to¬
day it seems more subversive than it may at
first appear. To make children happy in an
institution is an extremely arduous task.
Even the best educational blueprint in the
world is no guarantee of success. Korczak
said that children become what institutions
make of them.
Perhaps it would be fitting to end this
evocation of Korczak's life and work with
his own words on the so-called immaturity
of the child: "They say that children are im¬
mature. Well, immaturity is a very odd
thing! An old man of seventy says that a
man of forty is immature; people from rich
countries say that those from poor coun¬
tries are immature; the bourgeoisie say the
workers are immaturewhatever would
become of them without us? It's just the
same when we say that children are im¬
mature. And it's not true; it's a way of
keeping children down."
Stanislaw Tomkiewicz and Béatrice Maffioli
Sprawozdanie Sekretärin
«Kl I HCWri OTBTHM a aama ^«-M» ,»
SÍ&"
	 ! K^zè r3îeïAÎï
It». MO*. ^ W^f
In 1926, Korczak founded Maly Przeglad (The Little Review),
perhaps the first large-scale newspaper in the world to be
entirely written, edited and produced by children. Maly
Przeglad had a network of 2,000 young correspondents
throughout Poland and continued publication right up to the
Nazi invasion in 1939. Left, the front page of number 279 of
Maly Przeglad included a graph of the number of articles
sent in by its young correspondents, showing clearly defined
holiday peaks, and a report on the school year 1929-1930.
The headline on an inside page, SAMORZAD w SZKOLE,
introduced an article on self-government in schools.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Photo Robert Levin © Rapho, Pans
Margaret Mead in 1966. In December 1971 the noted
American anthropologist became the first woman to be
awarded Unesco's Kalinga Prize for the popularization of
science.
Remembering
Margaret
Mead
by Claude Lévi-Strauss
STRICKEN with cancer, Margaret
Mead went into hospital on 4
October 1978 and died on 15
November, the very day on which the
seventy-seventh General Assembly of the
American Anthropological Association
took place. Margaret Mead herself would
have been seventy-seven a month later.
There is something symbolic in the repeti¬
tion of the number seventy-seven, so
closely was Margaret Mead connected,
one might even say identified, with
American anthropology all through her life.
Margaret Mead was born on 16
. December 1901 in Philadelphia. But her ties
were unquestionably Middle Western. If I
am not mistaken, her great-great-
grandparents had founded the little town
of Winchester in Ohio. Her grandmother
was a schoolmistress, her father a pro¬
fessor of economics and her mother a
sociologist who had written a thesis on the
Adaptation of Italian Immigrants. So her
roots in a particular territory and her roots
in a scientific environment both went back
several generations. She was, in fact, a
third generation "blue stocking".
She herself told how throughout her
childhood her parents moved house no less
than four times a year, going from one
university to another, for, as we know, a
university career in the United States is
CLAUDE LEVI-STRAUSS, world-renowned
French anthropologist and philosopher, has
been professor of social anthropology at the
Collège de France, Paris, since 1959. From 1934
to 1938 he was professor of sociology at the
University of Sao Paulo and led several scientific
expeditions to the Mato Grosso and the
Amazon. During the Second World War he
taught at the New School for Social Research,
New York. He is the author of many
authoritative works which have been widely
translated; those available in English include:
Race and History, Unesco, 1952; The Savage
Mind, Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1966; Struc¬
tural Anthropology, Allen Lane, 1968; The Raw
and the Cooked, Jonathan Cape, 1970; From
Honey to Ashes, Jonathan Cape, 1973; Tristes
Tropiques, Jonathan Cape, 1973. This article is
based on an address given at the Centre Na¬
tional de la Recherche Scientifique, Paris, and
published in MSH Informations, the bulletin of
the Maison des Sciences de l'Homme.
largely itinerant. It is perhaps because of
this contrast between her dual deep-
rootedness and this constant uprooting
from her surroundings that she was able to
keep to the unshakeable convictions that
spurred her on right through her career,
and to acquire her unbelievable powers of
adaptation.
After a period of undistinguished study
in small provincial universities she went to
Barnard College, Columbia University, and
worked under the prestigious supervision
of Franz Boas and his assistant at the time,
Ruth Benedict. We know how Margaret
Mead revered these two scholars. She ob¬
tained her Bachelor of Arts Degree in 1923,
her Master's in 1924 and her Ph.D in 1929.
She had not yet got her Ph.D. when she
set off on her first expeditions, to Samoa in
1925 and to Manus in the Admiralty Islands
in 1928-1929. She was also to work among
various tribes in the United States, around
1930, in New Guinea with her second hus¬
band, Reo Fortune, from 1931-1933, in Bali
and again in New Guinea with her third
husband, Gregory Bateson, between 1936
and 1938.
Then war broke out. I would not go so
far as to say that this prompted Margaret
Mead to break completely with the past
(for she never gave up her original voca¬
tion), nevertheless, there was a superficial
change, for she spent the next ten years on
national research in the United States
itself, interviewing minority groups and im¬
migrants.
Her colleagues did not give her their
whole-hearted support. I remember a
rather lively discussion in June 1952 at the
headquarters of the Wenner-Gren Founda¬
tion during a large symposium on "An¬
thropology today", attended by about
eighty anthropologists. She had been
taken to task for converting to applied an¬
thropology, and gave a spirited definition
of what she understood by applied an¬
thropology: it was not, she said, a kind of
anthropology that had practical 'applica¬
tion, but one which was undertaken more
from necessity than from an unselfish
desire to learn and understand. And she
added, "If someone were to give me a
guarantee that everything in the world
would remain pleasant and comfortable,
and that no research of this kind need be
done for the next twenty-five years, I
wouldn't touch national character for the
next twenty-five years because I think it is
more important to go back to New
Guinea". And she ended by saying, "Near¬
ly all of us who have dedicated our time to
these studies for the last ten years would
much rather have done something else".
So we see that she was not pleading in
favour of a new anthropology nor of a
complete shift in our aims and methods.
But she was a woman inspired by a sense
of civic duty and profound religious feeling,
for she had been converted when she was
very young, although her parents were not
practising Christians. It was the feeling that
she owed herself to her contemporaries, to
her country and to the international com¬
munity that set her on the path she was to
follow during the second half of her life,
the path of untiring campaigning across
the United States and across the world,
through the medium of broadcasts, univer¬
sity lectures, articles and books. It also ex¬
plains her feminist struggle whose source
of inspiration was so different from that of
all the others which the United States and
other countries have known.
As far as she was concerned, it was not a
matter of trying to replace various norms
with new ones, but rather of helping to
establish a social order that would allow all
differences to find expression. In this
respect, she remained faithful to the end of
her first book. Coming of Age in Samoa,
published in 1928 more than fifty years
agowhere she expressed the hope that
by studying societies with different norms
from ours, people would be able to attain
that high degree of individual choice and
universal tolerance to which only a
heterogeneous culture can aspire. Samoa
only recognizes one kind of life and this she
imposes on her children. But why
shouldn't we, who have learnt to under¬
stand many different kinds of life, leave our
children free to choose from among them?
It was, therefore, a lesson in tolerance
and freedom that she tried to give her con¬
temporaries. Like all her other philo- 1
sophies, her feminism was never dogmatic. I
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Honours were relatively late in coming to
' her, if we consider the importance of her
work. She received the gold medal of the
Viking Fund in 1957 and only in 1975 was
she elected a member of the National
Academy of Sciences of the U.S.A. But
she received many memorable tributes in
her last years. For her seventy-fifth birth¬
day in 1976 the American Museum of
Natural History set up the "Margaret Mead
Fund for the Advancement of An¬
thropology" which is, in a way, an institu¬
tion designed to help American an¬
thropology over the bad patch it is going
through along with other institutions, as a
result of the world crisis. Also, a five-day
film festival in which she took part was
organized in her honour at the American
Museum of Natural History in 1977.
What I would most like to say is that
Margaret Mead was a great ethnologist.
She is known to a vast reading public
through books that can, in some respects,
be regarded as works of popularization.
These are: Coming of Age in Samoa and
Growing up in New Guinea; but we must
not overlook the fact that each of these
books had a counterpart in the form of a
technical treatise: for the first, Social
Organization of Manua, and Kinship in the
Admiralty Islands for the second.
It so happens that this year for my course
at the Collège de France I have had to delve
once more into these treatises which are
the work of a very young anthropologist;
she was only about twenty-five to twenty-
eight years of age when she did her first
research in the field. I was very surprised to
find with what accuracy and acumen she
had identified a number of problems which
our New Guinea-specialist colleagues
thought they had discovered in, shall we
say, about 1950, and which are still a topic
for discussion.
Some of these problems are, firstly, the
very special place reserved for cross
cousins as a result of complex systems of
relationships which make them related by
both blood and marriage and, consequent¬
ly, the element on which the whole social
structure hinges; Margaret Mead had
already described it as the "nodal point" of
the whole system. Secondly, the change
from kinship to barter as the basis of the
social structure and the fact that to achieve
this societies had to suppress "the binding
forms of purely blood ties". Thirdly, the
way in which these societies manage to
become emancipated from blood ties
through the medium of procedures such as
adoption and the financing of marriage by
"All over the world a new age is struggling to be born, an age
in which all children can grow up in families and all
adolescents can have time to become individuals who are
able to meet the demands of a fully adult life." Margaret
Mead saw the family as the basic unit of human living in
every society and the strength of the relationships within this
unit are powerfully captured in these studies by her long-time
collaborator Ken Heyman. For Margaret Mead, Heyman was
more than a photographer; he was a fellow anthropologist
who, she declared, "brought individuals and scenes literally
and symbolically into focus. Behind the single caught gesture
there would always be the intricate social and political
realities." (1) Ghana, (2) Japan, (3) Turkey, (4) Ireland,
(5) Mexico.
intermediaries who later came to be known
as "big men". Margaret Mead had correct¬
ly identified what she so aptly described as
the idea "of translating kinship form into a
basis for extra-kinship activity".
I remember that a few years ago I again
had occasion to use the documents that
Margaret Mead had brought back from
Sepik and, more particularly the ones from
Mundugomar, and I tried to draw diagrams
from them. I was a little afraid that they did
not quite correspond to reality, so I sent
them to her along with my text. A few
weeks later she wrote me that after con¬
sulting her old notes she had arrived at the
same conclusions with regard to the
diagram. I mention this not boastfully, but
only to show that at no time, not even dur¬
ing that period of her life when she was
thought to be completely engrossed in
social and political activities, had she turn¬
ed her back on New Guinea or on
theoretical anthropology, to which she in
fact returned at regular intervals.
Her most original contribution was cer¬
tainly that she was not content to make a
merely surface study of customs, beliefs
and institutions. She sought to understand
how people live their culture from the in¬
side, how they learn it from the moment of
their birth and during their infancy; also,
how they react to this culture, whether
they conform by adopting it or whether
they rebel or try to cheat it.
Now (and this is the dual background to
which I referred at the beginning), by
breaking new ground in this way, Margaret
Mead was using to best advantage some of
what she had learnt from Boas who had
already paid a fair amount of attention to
what different individuals felt. She herself
tells us that it was Boas too who first in¬
terested her in Polynesia, by giving her as
her first assignment a study of adolescents
and the extent to which they succeeded in
integrating into their group.
We should also pay tribute to Margaret
Mead for her exalted conception of an
thropology. As far as she was concerned, it
was not a special field working alongside
others, but the only field capable of syn¬
thesizing all the different types of research
on the subject of man. "The rôle of an¬
thropology", she said, "is to try and bridge
the gap between the humanities which
have never realized that man is an animal,
the natural sciences which would like to ig¬
nore the fact that man has a conscience,
and social science which merely rehashes
outmoded theories of physics". She took
the sociologist to task for relying on the
psychologist who, in turn, relied on the
biologist... Anthropology alone operates
on various levels. t
She apparently said in 1977, "My body is
not going to last as long as I thought it
would". So she could feel that the end was
near.
When, after her first stay there, she left
the village of Pere in the Admiralty Islands
to which she was to return many times, the
natives cried out in tears, "You are like an
old turtle who is taking to the sea and will
never come back". And it is true that late in
life Margaret Mead was a little like an old
turtle. But I would say a Lewis Carroll turtle
who could sometimes be sententious and
dictatorial, but sometimes too could be as I
saw her only two years ago in Uppsala
when, despite her age and illness, she
dropped the most graceful curtsey to the
young King of Sweden.
We parted at Stockholm airport; she was
on her way back to the United States and I
to France. The last thing she said to me
was that almost as soon as she got home
she expected to set off again for New
Guinea. That, no doubt, is where she
would have liked to end her days. But this
was not to be. However, we are sure that
she will be remembered both as a great
research worker in the field, and as the per¬
son whose work did most to earn for an¬
thropology its rightful place in today's
world.
Claude Lévi-Strauss
t&m*
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
in brief. . . in brief
Unesco's Co-operative
Action Programme
(CO-ACTION) and the
International Year
of the Child
Unesco's Co-operative Action Programme
offers individuals, groups and institutions the
opportunity to participate in self-help
community projects throughout the world.
During the International Year of the Child 1979 it
has been decided to concentrate on six special
projects, described below, which are particularly
concerned with pre-school education, the
problems of handicapped children, education
related to the environment and the promotion of
books and library services for children.*
"Donations, in the form of cheques, international
money orders or bank transfers, as well as requests for
further information, should be addressed to: Unesco,
Co-operative Action Programme, OPI, 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, France.
Books for Children
Everywhere
As illiteracy diminishes in the developing coun¬
tries, the demand for books increases. But many
children and adults who have learned to read
lose their newly acquired ability for lack of
suitable reading material. Moreover, the Third
World countries need books in local as well as in
the international languages. The International
Federation of Library Associations which since
1973 has been co-sponsor with Unesco's Co¬
operative Action Programme of the Books for
Children Everywhere project has been doing its
best to ensure that young readers can obtain the
books they really require. During the Interna¬
tional Year of the Child renewed efforts are be¬
ing made to ensure an adequate supply of
suitable books for children's libraries. Ten coun¬
tries have been selected for special support in
1979: Bangladesh, Brazil, Indonesia, Jamaica,
Jordan, Kenya, Lebanon, Nigeria, Peru and
Senegal. Those wishing to contribute to this
project can indicate in which country they would
like their contributions to be employed.
In Peru
The Centre for Special Education at Chimbóte,
in northern Peru, created by the local communi¬
ty in 1969 as a self-help project, has an enrol¬
ment of 500 pupils. It is now the country's
largest school for what it prefers to call "excep¬
tional" rather than "handicapped" children and
young people who suffer from blindness or
deafness, speech and learning problems or a
combination of these disabilities. The Centre's
services, provided free of charge, include pre¬
school training for infants within their own
homes, specially adapted courses in basic
education and physical rehabilitation, and voca¬
tional and workshop training. Thanks to Co-
Action the Centre, which also provides training
for teachers in all areas of special education, will
be able to promote preventive health campaigns
and the early detection of illnesses such as polio
and meningitis, which are the cause of so many
crippling handicaps.
In Malaysia
For the past fifty years, the St. Nicholas School
and Home for the Blind, in Penang, Malaysia,
has provided an academic education and
courses for physical rehabilitation for a limited
number of the country's 20,000 blind and visual¬
ly handicapped children. Sporting activities, in
particular cycling, help to develop the children's
sense of direction and to encourage a spirit of
self-confidence and independence. Among re¬
cent graduates of the school was one of the first
blind climbers to have reached the summit of
south-east Asia's highest mountain, Kinabalu
(4,150 metres). Co-Action contributions will help
the school to expand its activities and to take
part in the fight against the causes of blindness
(cataract, glaucoma, etc.), 70 to 80 per cent of
cases of which, according to the World Health
Organization, could have been avoided.
In Benin
Like many other Third World countries, the Peo¬
ple's Republic of Benin, in west Africa, is striv¬
ing to establish an educational system which,
bearing in mind the country's limited resources
and basically agricultural economy, will fit the
children for life and work in an increasingly
technological society, without alienating them
from their rural background and traditions.
Benin's children aged between three and five
number some 400,000 and this age group is ex¬
pected to double by the end of the century. To
meet this challenge a system of pre-school cen¬
tres is being created which are to be run by
specially trained members of the children's own
communities. Co-Action support will provide
simple equipment for these centres, including
furniture and toys, sanitary and cooking facilities
and materials for vaccination and primary health
care.
In Lao
Three-quarters of the adult population of the
Lao People's Democratic Republic, in south-east
Asia, depend on agriculture for a living, yet only
four per cent of the country's territory is arable
land. With a view to opening up wider pros¬
pects, the government is striving to ensure that
all children of school age actually attend school
(even if this is often no more than a simple
thatched bamboo hut) and to eliminate illiteracy
among adults and young people. With an
average enrolment of 500 pupils in each primary
school and at least forty pupils per class,
resources are strained to the limit. Materials of
all kinds are lacking; paper is in short supply and
exercise books are a luxury often replaced by
blank pages saved from newspapers and
magazines. Even the smallest contribution to
Co-Action funds would make a difference; a
thousand dollars would keep one school sup¬
plied with classroom materials for one year.
In Ethiopia
been lucky enough to begin studies at a special
school, deaf pupils are quickly discouraged
when they move on to regular schools which
lack the facilities to help them continue their
education. Support for Co-Action will help in the
establishment of a system of pre-school training
that will teach deaf children, from the earliest
possible age, to communicate and interact with
the world around them. Other objectives are the
establishment of a model school which will both
educate the handicapped children and provide
in-service training for a new generation of
teachers.
It is estimated that in Ethiopia there are some
600,000 children, young people and adults who
are totally deaf or hard of hearing, whether from
birth or as a result of injury. There are very few
schools for the deaf and only two equipped to
provide secondary education. Even if they have
Bookshelf
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
AND PERIODICALS
Hydrological Problems Arising
from the Development of Energy, a
preliminary report, by George H. Davis
and A.L. Velikanov. (No. 17 in Unesco's
"Technical Papers in Hydrology" series).
1979, 32 pp. (8 F)
II Coin Collections: Their Preserva¬
tion, Classification and Presentation,
by David William MacDowall. 1978, 82
pp. (18 F)
Statistics on Radio and Television
1960-1976, by the Division of Statistics
on Culture and Communication of
Unesco's Office of Statistics. (No. 23 in
Unesco's "Statistical Reports and
Studies" series). 1979, 124 pp. (14 F)
Democratizing Higher Education
is the major theme of Prospects,
Unesco's quarterly review of education
(Vol. IX, No. 1, 1979). Each issue 12 F; .
subscriptions 42 F for one year or 70 F for
two years.
Pedagogics , of Social Science:
Some Experiences is the major theme
of Unesco's quarterly International
Social Science Journal (Vol. XXXI, No.
1, 1979). Each issue 23 F; subscriptions
70 F for one year or 1 16 F for two years.
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The Image of the Buddha
an outstanding survey
of oriental art
A far-reaching study compiled by a group of distinguished
scholars under the auspices of Unesco, THE IMAGE OF THE
BUDDHA illustrates and explains the many different forms in
which the ideal of Buddhahood has found artistic expression
over some 2,500 years.
Surveys the development of Buddhist thought in the
Indian sub-continent and across Asia, and traces the changes
that have taken place in the use and meaning of Buddhist
symbols, gestures and images.
Lavishly illustrated with 58 superb colour plates and 310
black and white illustrations.
General editor: David L. Snellgrove, Fellow of the British
Academy and Professor of Tibetan at the University of London.
482 pages 220 French francs
Co-published with Kodansha International Ltd., Tokyo, who are the
exclusive distributors in the USA. Other exclusive distributors: Serindia
Publications in the U.K. and Vikas Publishing House in India.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor In your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not lis¬
ted, along wtth subscription rates in local cur¬
rency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking.
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Tahrir Square,
Cairo. - ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box
29%, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. -
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach
140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific
maps only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830.
Other publications: S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung,
Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/München.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1,
Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HUNGARY. Akadémiaí
Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok
Boltj'a, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna
Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1;
80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House,
New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and
Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., '28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, AI -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational .Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286,
Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication &
Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling
Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street,
Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. . MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco
Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat
71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. ;
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio, v- SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Thailand's
'Dawn of Happiness'
Sukhothai ("the dawn of happiness") became in the 13th century AD the capital
of a Thai kingdom and the cradle of a school of artists who created a distinctive
style of depicting the Buddha (See article page A). With its intricately worked
diadem, perfectly oval face, and arched eyebrows curving gracefully into the
bridge of the nose, this head of a Buddha, although it belongs to a later period,
illustrates the lasting influence of the Sukhothai school on Thai art. It is part of a
153-cm-high bronze bust dating from the 17th century.
ftm
M m
HfiHB
hH
'mi
::
\
¿if Sculpture en Thaïlande foy Jean Bosselier and Jii
]]>
</page>
</document>
