<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="045086eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Q)UrÍer A window
open on the world
il
ÂA
A CHINESE EMPEROR'S CLAY ARMY
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
©
Nepal
The birth
of the Buddha
The birth of Siddhartha
Gautama, the founder of
Buddhism, is portrayed in this
eighteenth-century gilt-bronze
statuette (56 cm high). Gautama
Buddha as he is known to his
followers (Buddha, meaning
Awakened or Enlightened One,
is a title and not a proper name)
is traditionally thought to have
been born around 563 BC in the
grove of Lumbini in present-day
Nepal. In this traditional
rendering of the birth scene he
is emerging from the right side
of his mother Maya, who holds
the flowering branch of a tree.
The encrustation of coloured
gems is typical of the
craftsmanship of Nepalese
bronzeworkers and jewellers.
Photo Ç Union of Naiional Museums, Guimet
Museum, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco ÇoUFlPF
DECEMBER 1979 32nd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's Issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER .is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co.. Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier Is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander B roîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
5 A CHINESE EMPEROR'S CLAY ARMY
by Gu Wenjie
9 THE HOLY PLACES OF UPPER NEPAL
by Corneille Jest
25 THE BUDDHIST VISION IN THAI ART
by Adul Wichiencharoen
EIGHT PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
29 ANCIENT GOLD FROM THE MELTING-POT
OF CENTRAL ASIA
by Viktor I. Sarianidi
35 THE PAINTINGS OF PAGAN
Temple walls that tell the story of the Buddha's many lives
by Klaus Wenk
I
42 UNICEF GREETING CARDS
43 UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1979
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
NEPAL: The birth of the Buddha
Cover
Since 1974, Chinese archaeologists have
been unearthing a fabulous life-size army of
clay warriors discovered In an underground
vault in Shensi province, China. In his
article, Gu Wenjie tells us that each figure
in this ,6,000-strong army is a true portrait
of a individual member of the emperor's
bodyguard, fashioned with artistry and
meticulous attention to detail (cover
photo). Other articles in this issue, which is
devoted to Asia, discuss a rich
archaeological find in Afghanistan and the
Buddhist influence on life and art in Nepal,
Thailand and Burma.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
A Chinese emperor's
clay army
by Gu Wenjie
IN March 1974, villagers from a
people's commune near the city of
Sian in Shençi province, China, were
responsible for one of the century's most ex¬
traordinary archaeological finds. While drill¬
ing a well they struck, not water, but a tun¬
nel which turned out to be filled with an ar¬
my of life-size warriors, horses and chariots,
all modelled in terra-cotta.
The clay phalanx, several thousand
strong, was found buried just over a
kilometre east of the tomb of the Emperor
Qin Shihuang (Chin Shih Huang), the ruler
who unified China's warring states over
2,000 years ago. When all the pieces have
been lifted from the earth, restored and put
on display in a permanent museum, they
may capture the world's imagination as
strongly as the other monumental achieve¬
ment for which the mighty Emperor is
remembered, the Great Wall of China.
The villagers reported their discovery to
the authorities and a team of archaeologists
was called in to supervise scientific excava¬
tions of the area. They discovered a subter¬
ranean pit, 210 metres long by 60 metres
wide, filled with pottery figures. A
preliminary dig over an area of 1,000 square
metres revealed 520 clay warriors (each bet- k
ween 1 .78 and 1 .87 metres high) and f
For two millennia, a 6,000-strong legion of
life-size warriors, modelled in clay and
complete with weapons, horses and war
chariots, have kept a silent, subterranean
vigil over the tomb of Qin Shihuang (Chin
Shih Huang Ti), a fitting escort for the man
who built the Great Wall and ruled from 221
to 210 BC as the first emperor of a unified
China. This long-buried army is gradually
being uncovered at a site to the east of the
emperor's tomb, near the city of Sian in
Shensi province. The legion was interred in
battle array in a huge earth and timber
vault. As the photos (exclusive to the
Unesco Courier) on these two pages show,
not all the figures survived intact the
collapse of the roof following a fire caused
by a rebel army three years after the
emperor's death, and their shattered
remains are now being painstakingly pieced
together by Chinese archaeologists. The
site is protected by a huge hangar which
will eventually become a permanent
museum.
GU WENJIE, of the People's Republic of China,
is a specialist in archaeology and a staff reporter
of China Features.-
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
m ft
a <i s. - Ji Í
««( a >J«+x
« .j. » n t m
*"h « -v » *
100 . 0 . . 100«
Map shows location of emperor Qin
Shihuang's tomb (1) and of the
underground vault (2), 1,225 metres to the
east, in which the clay army was found. A
modern highway runs close by the northern
side of the tomb which has not yet been
excavated and is believed to be intact. The
emperor's last resting place, a veritable
underground palace, is reputed to have
taken 700,000 workmen thirty-six years to
complete. Experts say that it will take two
generations to unearth all the treasures
buried within the tomb complex.
Below, plan of the underground vault,
drawn up in 1975, showing (1) trial
exploratory trenches, left and centre, and
excavated area, and (2) the sloping
entrance passageways. Right, detailed
diagram of the excavated area of the vault
In the eleven corridors can be seen the life
size figures of warriors and horses.
twenty-four life-size pottery horses. Experts
have since estimated that there may be as
many as six thousand ceramic models on the
site.
The warriors, which are in an excellent
state of preservation, are well-proportioned,
and the delineation of their features in¬
dicates craftsmanship of a high order. Some
of them are stamped with the names of the
potters who made them. Armour, belts, leg¬
gings and boots are all modelled with careful
attention to detail. But perhaps the most
remarkable thing of all is that each figure is a
unique portrait. One soldier, perhaps a
veteran, is shown with knitted brows and
tightly compressed lips; another, with arch
ed eyebrows and blazing eyes, might have
been a raw recruit; a third has a curled
moustache and the cheerful look of an op¬
timist untroubled by thoughts of death on
the battlefield. No two of them are alike.
Flecks of colour on the models and in the
earth where they were found indicate that
they were originally painted in an array of
mineral colours: red, pink, purple, blue,
green, yellow, orange, black, brown, grey
and white.
Study of the site has shown that the army
was buried in a massive underground vault
Whose ceiling, supported by wooden
beams, collapsed after a great fire. The ar¬
chaeologists began work at the east end of
the rectangular vault. They unearthed five
downward-sloping entrance passageways
leading into the chamber, where they came
upon a host of warriors, three deep, all fac¬
ing eastwards in battle formation. Three
figures, one in the middle and one at each
end of the first row, were probably the com¬
manders.
These lightly equipped warriors, armed
with cross-bows or hand-bows and quivers,
appear to have been the vanguard. Behind
them is deployed the main body of the
force, densely packed columns of infan¬
trymen interspersed with chariots, each of
which is drawn by four horses. Most of
these soldiers were armed with lances or
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The astonishing individuality of each
member of emperor Qin Shihuang's terra¬
cotta army seems to indicate that these
figures are true-to-life portraits of actual
members of the imperial bodyguard (see
portrait gallery at left). The kneeling
figure, second from top, is an archer who
originally held a real hand-bow. The top
three figures wear variations of the
distinctive hair-style with a bun on top of
the head adopted by most of the warriors,
while the fourth figure at the bottom of the
page wears a flat cap held in place by an
elaborate chin-strap (see also detailed
drawings, above).
halberds, although some carried short-
handled weapons. Some wear robes; others
are in armour. The horses, just as lifelike as
the warriors, have forward-pointing ears and
curly manes. They look ahead intently, alert
for a sign from their masters. Their tails are
knotted, as if to allow them to gallop more
freely.
The northern and southern flanks of this
main phalanx are each guarded by a column
of warriors two deep, facing outwards.
These "side-guards" are armed with the
same weaponry as the vanguard.
Trial excavations at the western edge of
the pit have also brought to light the soldiers
of the rearguard, who face west. The whole
well-organized symmetrical array of war¬
riors, horses and chariots armed with a
diversity of weapons and ready for battle in¬
dicates the terrible array of the Emperor's
legions.
After comparing the model soldiers and
horses with previously unearthed pottery
figures of the Qin (Chin) dynasty, ar¬
chaeologists concluded that they were
funeral accessories which had been buried
with the Emperor Qin Shihuang
(259-210 BC), whose tomb has never been
excavated. According to historical records,
the construction of Qin Shihuang's tomb
began long before the Emperor's death, and
it seems almost certain that the manufacture
of the ceramic figures formed part of these
preparations.
Qin is one of the most important figures of k
early Chinese history. During his reign, f
Right, Chinese experts put the finishing
touches to figures resurrected after their
2,000-year interment.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Fashioned in terra-cotta and with the same
extraordinary vigour and realism as the
warriors, hundreds of magnificent horses
have been unearthed at the site near Sian.
Some served as mounts for the light
cavalry, while others, harnessed four
abreast, pulled the emperor's war chariots
which had proved themselves to be a
battle-winning element on the rolling plains
of China. Each chariot carried a driver and
two other soldiers armed with spears,
swords and cross-bows.
China's system of writing was standardized,
as were its weights and measures, coinage
and calendar. He ordered the construction
of irrigation canals and post roads which
linked the whole of his empire. He joined up
walls built earlier by individual states, thus
forming the Great Wall, a solid barrier
against the threat from nomadic tribes to the
north.
He dragooned millions of men into work¬
ing on these immense construction projects,
and forced rich and influential people to
move from the provinces to the capital.
Hundreds of intellectuals were massacred
for daring to criticize the Emperor's policies,
and books dealing with subjects other than
agriculture, medicine, pharmacy and
astronomy were burned because he con¬
sidered such knowledge to be subversive.
Only a small portion of the vault near the
Emperor's burial mound has so far been ex¬
cavated but it has already yielded, as well as
warriors, horses and chariots, a rich store of
iron farm implements and objects of gold,
jade and bone, linen, silk and leather. Many
well-preserved bronze weapons have also
been unearthed: arrowheads, and swords
which have remained shiny and sharp; and
cross-bows found in such numbers as to
suggest that they must have been a widely
used weapon in the China of Qin Shihuang.
A museum is being constructed over the
site. It will shelter both the finds and the ar¬
chaeologists, who are faced with years of
painstaking work before the vault gives up
all its secrets.
Gu Wenjie
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The holy places
of upper Nepal
by Corneille Jest
'O
lN the summit of the sacred moun¬
tain a precious jewel like a crystal
stupa;
On the east side the dwelling of the Three
Precious Protectors;
On the south side the palace of the divinity
Tara;
On the west side the pa/aces of the divinity
Dor/e Pamo and the Dakini fairies;
On the north side the pa/ace of the divinity
Dorjechang...'
The "sacred mountain" of this Nepalese
poem is Mount Dhaulagiri, one of the
highest of the great Himalayan peaks; with
Everest, Annapurna and Kanjiroba it forms a
towering backdrop to the kingdom of Nepal.
Just three decades ago, Nepal wasw
known only to a handful of fortunate out- P
For the people of northern Nepal's high
valleys, every moment in life is imbued
with sacred significance. Monks officiate at
birth, marriage and death, and also give
their blessing to a host of everyday
activities such as building houses and
marking out the boundaries of fields. The
lama ("master") is a spiritual guide who
attends to the welfare of the community.
His many duties include the performance of
protection rites for people and their
possessions and casting out the souls of
the dead to protect them from capture by
demons. Protection rituals also accompany
the treatment prescribed by the lama-
doctor, right, whose battery of cures
ranges from herbal remedies to cupping
(drawing blood from the body by forming a
partial vacuum over a certain spot).
CORNEILLE JEST, of France, is director of a
mu/tidiscip/inary research programme of the Cen¬
tre National de la Recherche Scientifique in the
Himalayas. A Unesco consultant for the cultural
heritage in Nepal, he has published numerous ar¬
ticles on the Himalayan region. Lavishly illustrated
with his own photographs, his book Tarap, une
Vallée dans l'Himalaya was published in 1974 by
Editions du Seuil, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
, siders, but over recent years it has gradually
become more open to the world. The trickle
of mountain climbers, occasional travellers
from the West and visitors anxious to learn
about its culture, has become a flood of
tourists seeking the exotic and escape from
their own environment.
Perched high up in "the roof of the
world", Nepal stretches some eight hundred
kilometres from east to west. From north to
south, stepped hills descend to the Ganges
plain below; rivers and mountains divide the
landscape into a vast chequer-board of
natural regions of immense diversity.
Situated as it is in the heart of the
Himalayan range, Nepal has assimilated and
preserved cultural influences both Indian
and central Asian in origin. With their com¬
parative isolation making exchange difficult,
the peoples of the upper valleys have, until
recently, maintained their way of life, their
religion and their architecture unaffected by
outside influences. And whereas the
peoples of the middle valleys look towards
Kathmandu and the south and speak or
understand Nepalese and follow the Hindu
religion, those who live in the high valleys of
the north and in the foothills of the
Himalayas are of Tibetan or Tibeto-Burmese
culture and language and most of them are
Buddhists.
The upper valleys dominate the passes
between Tibet and Nepal. With their high
altitude, harsh climate and the very low rain¬
fall to the north of the upper range, they can
support only marginal agriculture, including
the cultivation of barley, buckwheat and,
more recently, potatoes. The breeding of
the yak and its hybrids, of sheep and goats,
provides an additional source of food and
raw material for weaving. These meagre far¬
ming and breeding resources are sup¬
plemented by exchanging local grain for salt
from the salt lakes of the Tibetan plateau.
In the spring, when the crops have been
sown, the herds are sent up to spend the
summer in the higher mountain pastures;
summer is also the time for the exchange of
grain and salt. In autumn, after the harvest,
some of the inhabitants go down to the mid¬
dle valleys to market their products such as
textiles and medicinal plants.
Religious life hinges round Buddhism, the
pattern of which was first developed in Tibet
in the 8th century. Time is reckoned accor¬
ding to the lunar calendar. The New Year
falls in mid-February and this is when the
ritual of the expulsion of evil takes place. In
midsummer there are ceremonies to ensure
the abundance of crops and the fertility of
livestock. Places of worship are numerous
and include village temples and private
chapels as well as monasteries in which
gather men or women who have vowed to
live a life of meditation.
It should be noted that Buddhism has
adopted a highly structured form in these
regions. The priests or lamas fulfil a decisive
role as spiritual guides without whose
assistance man would be deprived of any
hope of salvation. The monks provide the
laity with access to liturgical or magical for¬
mulae and constitute a powerful hierarchical
organization which finds collective expres¬
sion in complex rituals and rigid formalism.
The monk may belong to a contemplative
order and live in seclusion from the outside
world, or may devote himself to imparting
his knowledge to the members of the com¬
munity as an educator, teacher, painter of
religious pictures, doctor or astrologer. The
10
monastic system, which a few centuries ago
had great significance in northern Nepal,
has experienced a renaissance in more re¬
cent times, particularly under the influence
of the lamas who came from Bhutan
towards the end of the 19th century.
The early beliefs of Upper Nepal were cen¬
tred on the divinities of the mountains and.
are preserved in the oral tradition in the form
of tales and narratives still known to
everyone. The whole mountain area belongs
to an extremely ancient sacred geography
which has been assimilated by Buddhism
and, to a lesser degree, by Hinduism. The
legend of Padmasambhava, the saintly pro¬
pagator of Buddhism in the region of the
Himalayas in the 8th century, refers mainly
to the transformation of the old divinities of
the mountains and lakes into defenders of
the new faith.
The traveller who journeys up from the
south, through dense forests of oak and fir,
or from the north across a countryside of
blossoming mountain plants, suddenly
comes upon the sanctuary of Muktinath,
perched high above the Kali Gandaki valley.
Here on the arid slopes men have settled,
setting out terraced fields and building reser¬
voirs to conserve and control the irrigation
water on which their survival depends.
Whether because of the powerful massifs of
Nilgiri and Dhaulagiri that tower above it, or
the presence of natural gas that bursts into
flame on contact with the air, Muktinath, in
its unique setting, has become a focal point
for the religions of the Himalayas.
Around a pagoda-temple, water from a
sacred spring spouts forth in a hundred and
eight jets in which pilgrims take purifying
baths. Here too stands a statue in gilt bronze
which is worshipped by some as Vishnu and
by others as Buddha Lokeswar. An ar¬
chaeologist attempting to identify the
statue, but who hesitated to do so because
the hands were hidden behind gilt or¬
naments, was told that the smile of wisdom
on the face was the best guide. Set in the
midst of a treeless landscape, the sanctuary
itself is surrounded by poplars, said to be the
staffs of the eighty-four yogi, "The Perfect
Ones", who have passed on the occult doc¬
trines revered by both the Hindus and the
Buddhists.
Lower down, where the natural gases
burn, is the small "temple of the miraculous
fire". Sala mabar Dolamebar. Here, where
"earth, stone and water burn", the pilgrims
come to make their offerings and to collect
holy water. Near this spot stands the Gompa
sarwa, "the new temple", built in 1938 by
the chief of the village of Dzar; it is
remarkable for its size (the main building
measures. 14 x 23 metres) and the delicacy
of its sculptures and its decorated wooden
panelling. And to the north-east stands the
Marma Lhakhang, "the temple of the
lamps", which contains a large statue of
Padmasambhava.
Just below the pilgrimage site stand "the
six villages", each of which is situated on a
hill. The largest of these villages is called
Dzong, "the fort", or Rab gyal tse, "the
Peak of Supreme Victory". The mud walls
which mark out the site of an old fortified
palace give an idea of the size of the original
complex of buildings; a temple and a few
monastery buildings still stand nearby. In¬
side, one can appreciate all the splendour of
a vast assembly hall (9 x 12.5 metres) with
its wooden panelling and six finely sculpted
pillars. The altar is crowned by a statue of
CONTINUED PAGE 14
Colour photo
The remoteness of the high
Himalayan valleys of Nepal has
fostered the survival of many
ancient traditions among people
who feel a deep sense of
communion with the barren,
windswept landscape around
them. These rocks beside a
pilgrims' way in the Khumbu
region have been engraved with
prayers by the faithful. Such
sacred rocks hark back to very
ancient pre-Buddhist beliefs in
mountain spirits.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
-.:-
¡tè&- í>
^fc
t¿X1S
MP»''*"
i
LJDK'fljP £p
:
» "
*
/"* -
j
"
^Wl» t."
^L>*r * - *
.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
* V
:WrK,
^
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Colour page left
Religious traditions in the Oolpo region of
upper Nepal are strongly influenced by the
form of Buddhism known as Bon, which
absorbed religious teachings from India and
combined them with pre-Buddhist beliefs
akin to shamanism. In this part of the
Himalayas special rites are sometimes
performed to banish evil spirits. Kindly
divinities are invoked and appear in the
form of masks worn by the monks, who
perform sacred dances. Top photo shows a
participant at an exorcism ceremony
wearing the blue mask of the mythical bird
Garuda. In Nepal Buddhism and Hinduism
are practised side by side and their
- traditions have intermingled. Below,
gilt bronze statue in a pagoda-temple at
Muktinath, a focal point of Himalayan
religions. It is revered by Hindus as the God
Vishnu and by Buddhists as the Buddha
Lokeswar. Another sanctuary at Muktinath
honours Padmasambhava (the
"Lotus-Born"), the Indian mystic who in
the eighth century introduced to the
Himalayas the form of Buddhism known as
Tantrism (so named after its holy
scriptures, the Tantra). To his followers
Padmasambhava is a great Tantric God
rather than a historical figure.
Right, a chorten or tomb-sanctuary high in
the Ta rap valley, northern Nepal. In
addition to the major conservation
programme now being carried out by the
Nepalese Government and Unesco in the
Kathmandu valley, Nepal's department of
archaeology Is taking steps to safeguard
and preserve the monuments of northern
Nepal. A team of Unesco specialists is
helping to draw up an inventory of the
most important monuments and sites.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The chequer-board, right, is
being used for a game which
is something more than a
game. It is divided into one
hundred and four squares, each
of which represents a phase
of existence in a "sphere of
rebirth". At the centre of
each square is one of six
letters. A, S, R, G, D or Y,
which also figure on the
sides of a dice. The letter
which comes up when the
dice is thrown determines
the thrower's"'region of
rebirth". A player who
throws the letter A five
times, for example, is reborn
in the Paradise of
Padmasambhava. What is for
some of the players merely a
source of diversion is for the
monks one way of
approaching the verities of
Buddhism.
High in the Himalayas, tea is
prepared according to a
special recipe. After being
left to boil for a long time, it
is poured into a churn and
mixed with yak butter and
salt. This highly nutritious
emulsion is consumed in
large quantities.
n
"7
1
Wi
1/1 1
1 ' H\ P -J
w'A ^^W w^\
*mI lu I 1
^*¿Lg
m^Jr^mf V
^1¿- Mk
MHH *
\\f*
14
, Sakyamuni (the Buddha) and the murals
depict the Medicine Buddhas.
The sanctuary of Muktinath comes to life
at the end of August, when some of the
faithful celebrate the "midsummer festival";
others pay tribute to Vishnu at the full moon
of Bhado (August-September). The pilgrims
make their way to Muktinath, in family
groups or by entire villages, wearing the
clothes of the plains, simple loincloths with
cotton turbans knotted on their heads, or
clad in wide cloaks lined with brocade and
bright with jewels.
The followers of Vishnu or Siva take a
ritual bath; the Buddhists make offerings to
the sacred fire and walk round the site one
hundred and eight times, following a precise
itinerary. Then follow the festivities, games
of skill, archery and horse races in honour of
the divinities of the earth and mountains.
The whole mountain becomes a huge sanc¬
tuary. Then the pilgrims wend their way
back to a nearby oasis or to the distant plain
of Terai, confident that their meritorious
acts will ensure a good harvest, long life
and, most important of all, a better re-birth.
For the inhabitants of the upper valleys of
Nepal nature is in communion with the
divine, and this rapid survey of the holy
places, the traditional way of life and the
ceremonies through which they give expres¬
sion to their profoundly religious tempera¬
ment, brings us to examine the question of
how best to protect and if possible maintain
the vitality of a culture now confronted with
Western technology and ways of thought.
The cultural future of northern Nepal will
be affected by two important factors the
introduction of modern materials that have
only recently become available for the
maintenance and restoration of buildings,
and the impact of a rapidly developing
tourist trade on traditional life.
The architecture of northern Nepal was
designed to withstand rigorous climatic con¬
ditions; unlike those in the Kathmandu
valley, the buildings are very simple on the
outside, all the splendour and decorative
CONTINUED PAGE 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Flat roofs of houses in this Himalayan
village built on a mountain slope provide
the villagers with a terraced walk between
each dwelling, a meeting-place, and a spot
for drying grain and piling up firewood.
Prayer banners can be seen flying from the
masts. As they flutter in the chilly air,
these "horses of the wind" bear messages
to the sky gods and invoke their protection.
To bring good fortune to the house they
are building, these two men are tracing a
Ungarn, the generative emblem of Shiva,
the god of creation, on a stone which will
form part of the'fireplace.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Lines of pilgrims wend their way towards
Buddha-ri, a sacred mountain in the Dolpo.
They will walk around the peak, and on
reaching a cairn and a prayer-mast at the
Orolma col will prostrate themselves before
attaching new prayer flags to the mast. The
cult of the mountains, still a living tradition
high in the Himalayas, is associated with
very ancient beliefs absorbed by Buddhism
and (to a lesser extent) Hinduism.
During the midsummer festival (July-
August), the young people of the Dolpo
region are given the task of whitewashing
and decorating the holy buildings known as
chorten (a Tibetan word meaning
"receptacle of offerings"). The chorten ¡s a
form of stupa, the characteristic Buddhist
structure. The faithful walk around these
sanctuaries intoning mantras (sacred
formulae for communion with the gods).
Below, a row of chorten in
the grandiose setting of the
Tarap valley.
Photos © Corneille Jest, Paris
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
At the midsummer festival, held each year
to ensure that livestock will prosper and
crops will be abundant, the inhabitants of
the isolated valleys of the Dolpo region
gather to attend religious ceremonies held
in monasteries, chapels and, as in photo,
the village temple.
This man from the Tarap valley is wearing
the mask of the drekar, or white devil. If he
appears during the period before the New
Year in which the monks go into retreat,
custom has it that he must be given some
butter, some tsampa (grilled barley-meal)
and a measure of salt. Accepting these
gifts, he replies:
"White is my right cheek
Like that of the king of India,
My left cheek is black
Like that of the king of China,
Sun and moon upon my brow
Like the master Padmasambhava,
Oh my nose a cowrie shell
In the manner of "tse tse" the goat."
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Clad in brightly coloured robes, the demons
dance during a ritual exorcism ceremony
performed to protect the Tarap valley from
evil spirits (see also colour photo page 11).
Divinities invoked in the course of rituals
form the backdrop of this temple altar in
the Dolpo region. The figurines in the
copper bowl in the foreground represent
the spirits of the mountains. The form of
Buddhism practised in this region of the
Himalayas is a synthesis of Mahayana and
Tantric Buddhism, which involves the
invocation of innumerable divinities;
representations of these divinities have to
conform to strict rules.
k skill being reserved for the interior. It should
not be forgotten that buildings are tangible
representations of the Spiritual Embodiment
of the Buddha. Construction follows strict
rules; the outline is more or less square, the
form depends upon the size and therefore
on the supporting structure, and the type of
building depends upon the number of pillars
used. The most commonly encountered
temple is of the "four pillars and eight
beams" type.
Great care is taken over the choice of site.
Whenever possible the façade faces east,
"the great white way leading to the rising
sun"; the area to the south is bordered by a
river "identical to the turquoise dragon"; to
the west the temple is set against "a moun¬
tain like a red bird"; and, finally to the north,
a mountain "in the shape of a turtle"
encloses the sacred area.
In the past, dwellings were grouped
together for defensive purposes and
situated so as to get maximum sunlight,
leaving free the spaces most suitable for ir¬
rigated crops. But it is becoming increasing¬
ly difficult and expensive, in a market
economy, to build in the traditional style us¬
ing local materials and qualified craftsmen.
Unfortunately, attempts to use cheap, resis¬
tant materials have not met with success
and have been detrimental both to tradition
and to the environment.
With their practical approach and active,
enterprising nature, the men of the upper
valleys tend to make use of new materials
such as corrugated iron, cement, nails and
glass without anticipating their possible
drawbacks. These newly introduced
materials are used without taking traditional
forms into consideration, with the result that
new constructions and existing buildings are
ill-matched. But with wood expensive and
difficult to come by and skilled labour in¬
creasingly scarce, and as problems of finan¬
cing and efficiency that were unknown to
the old way of life arise, the development of
a new style becomes inevitable.
With the appeal of the high mountains
and the growth of interest among
Westerners in Asian culture, Himalayan
tourism is bound to develop. The exploits of
those who have scaled Everest, the ex¬
periences of young people who have made
the pilgrimage to Kathmandu, and the grow¬
ing interest in Tibetan forms of Buddhism
are all having the effect of attracting tourists
to Nepal.
Doubtless the side effects, both good and
bad, of mass tourism will soon become evi¬
dent. There has already been a significant
revival of craft industry; the villagers carve
ritual formulae in wood or stone, or paint
thangkas, the traditional medium for the ex¬
pression of religious feeling, for tourists
eager to buy. But it is still too early to assess
the effects of the contact between the in¬
habitants and the tourists who are ill-
prepared to appreciate an austere way of life
in which poor resources and a harsh climate v
are the predominant factors. Nevertheless, f
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Afghanistan
, this contact will undoubtedly be made easier
by the respect evoked by a courageous peo¬
ple with a kindly attitude towards foreigners.
The conservation activities undertaken so
far by the Nepalese Government and
Unesco, with the support of private institu¬
tions of various countries, have been mainly
concerned with Kathmandu and the sur¬
rounding valley. These activities supplement
the work being carried out by the Depart¬
ment of Archaeology, under the direction of
R. J. Thapa, for the maintenance of
monuments in the northern part of the
country.
The view that it is important for the
Nepalese to take on the task of preserving
their cultural heritage is shared by many
lamas and village representatives. 'But a
great deal remains to be done to ensure the
survival and conservation of the country's
traditions and cultural wealth.
Corneille Jest
Beneath the drum on which he beats out
the solemn rhythm of his prayers, a
Buddhist monk (above) copies out sacred
texts. In the upper valleys of the Dolpo
region Buddhist scriptures consist of three
types of worksthe Vinaya, or books
dealing with religious discipline, the Sutra,
writings which extol the power and virtue
of the Buddhas and hold them up as an
example to men, and the Tantra, texts
which expound the religious rituals and
practices necessary to the achievement of
Buddhahood.
In the calm solitude of his roof-top retreat,
a lama reads and meditates on a sacred
text. During the 18th century an edition of
the Buddhist scriptures was printed by a
wood-cut process, still used today.
Gold galore
Some 20,000 gold objects, buried
with mysterious Asiatic
potentates, have recently been
discovered in Afghanistan. One
puzzling feature of this amazing
find (see article page 29 and
back cover) is why and how the
rulers came to be interred with
jewellery bearing the imprint of
widely diverse Greek, Indian,
Chinese, Persian and other
traditions. Colour photos, some
published for the first time,
show samples from the treasure
(clockwise from top right): tree
with discs as fluttering leaves
and fruit in the form of pearls
threaded to the branches; belt
plaque with female figure
straddling a snarling lion, a
theme which may be of Persian
origin (the whole belt is shown
on back cover); buckle depicting
winged deity astride a dolphin;
another buckle with the same.
typically Hellenistic motif; gold
coin of Indian origin, the only
one of its kind ever found,
shows on one side a man rolling
the "wheel of life", on the other
a lion with upraised paw; two
plaques of beasts frenziedly
coiled and snapping at their own
paws and tails recall Scytho-
Siberian objects crafted by
nomads of the steppes; figurine
of a musician clutching a
stringed instrument.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Vk
-M
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
¡m
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
.".**
K V
M
>>
..c
«X'Ü'
ü^j
n
»,
L "HÄ » \
r
:
4%& m
Kr j
^i*»$j
ÄÄ
íf*W§^>
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Jil -
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
1
52 3
4
Thailand
The murals that adorn Thai temples draw
their themes from the Jataka, the tales of
Buddha's previous lives before his final
incarnation in which he attained enlight¬
enment (see centre colour pages), and from
his historical life (see colour page left).
Centre colour
pages
(1) Bhuridatta in the realm of the Nagas
A scene from the Buddha's incarnation as
Bhuridatta, son of Dhatavatta, king of the
Nagas, half-serpentine beings who inhabit
the subterranean realm of Naga-loga. From
the Phra Thinang Phuthaisawan temple.
12 and 3) Gods in the Tavatimsa heaven
Details from an illustration of an event in
the life of the Buddha in his incarnation as
King Nemi. The central scene (not shown
here) depicts Nemi enthroned in the hall of
the Tavatimsa (thirty-three gods). Some
gods and goddesses, instead of listening to
Nemi's words, sneak off to enjoy each
other's company under the trees outside
the wall encircling the hall of the gods.
This work is unusual in that the name of
the artist, Khru Thong Yu, is known.
Another peculiarity is that the trees are
painted in gold, a colour normally reserved
for the Buddha. From Wat Suwaranan, it
dates from the reign of Rama III (1824-1851).
14) The return of the Buddha from the
Tavatimsa heaven
Descending the triple ladder from the
heaven of the Tavatimsa, the Buddha is
flanked by Brahma, who holds the parasol
of honour, Indra and other divinities. This
late 18th century mural comes from the
Phra Thinang Phuthaisawan temple,
Bangkok.
(5) The return of Maddi hindered by wild
beasts
An incident from the Buddha's incarnation
as Prince Vessantara. The prince goes into
the wilderness with his wife Maddi, his son
Jali and his daughter Kanhajina. While
Maddi is absent,' Vessantara, in accordance
with the divine will, gives the children to
the Brahmin Jujaka. Fearing Maddi's
reaction should she find her children gone,
three deities take on the form of a lion, a
tiger and a leopard and prevent her return.
From Wat Ratchasitharam.
Colour page left
Top, Siddattha cuts the hair off his head
After leaving the luxury of his life at
Kapilavatthu, Siddattha reflected that his
long hair did not become the character of
the poor ascetic he had decided to become;
but as no one was worthy to touch his hair,
he cut it off with his own sword. Hovering
over Siddattha is the god Indra. To the left,
Channa, his charioteer and companion,
crouches with his favourite horse
Kantthaka. Brahma is kneeling before the
future Buddha holding in one hand a
golden vessel on which lies a monk's gown
and in another hand a monastic begging
bowl. From Wat Ratchasitharam.
Bottom photo, 77ie wedding of
Suddhodana and Maya
The Buddha was born in about the year
563 BC. His father Suddhodana was
monarch of the Kingdom of the Sakyas (on
the borders of present day India and
Nepal). His mother. Queen Maya, gave
birth to the Buddha at the grove of Lumbini
while on her way to visit her parents (see
also page 2). From the Phra Thinang
Phuthaisawan temple, Bangkok, the
painting dates from about 1800.
The Buddhist
vision
in Thai art
by Adul Wichiencharoen
THAI traditional painting, of which
the mural is the most important
category, is characterized by the
insistent flow and rhythm of elegant and
graceful lines. Many of these murals are
creations of great artistic value by the stan¬
dards of any age or culture, but they could
only have been the work of devout Bud¬
dhists who conceived and executed them
anonymously as an act of love and worship.
For like the world-renowned sculptures of
Thailand, Thai mural paintings are religious
and didactic, their primary purpose being to
convey the essence of Buddhist philosophy
with its emphasis on the virtue of overcom¬
ing the baser desires and evil thoughts.
Yet this conception of visual art as a
means of spiritual edification, and the re¬
quirement that it should be consistent with
the Buddhist view that visible forms and the
world of matter are deceptive, presented the
early Thai artists with a seemingly insur¬
mountable problem. Naturalistic representa¬
tion would have focused the viewer's
thoughts on what he saw and, by pre¬
venting him from thinking about the reality
that lay behind, would have become an ob¬
stacle to imagination and thus to inspiration.
ADUL WICHIENCHAROEN, of Thailand,
formerly rector of Silpakorn University, is chair¬
man of the Thai National Committee on Land Use
and a member of the National Education Council
and of the National Environment Board. He is the
author of many studies and articles on Thai soci¬
ety andphilosophy as well as on international law,
development planning and public administration.
The illustrations for this article are taken from
Mural Paintings in Thailand, by Klaus Wenk, Inigo
von Oppersdorff Verlag, Zurich, 1975-1976;
photographs by Franz Horisberger.
With great artistic ingenuity, made possi¬
ble only by a deep understanding of Bud¬
dhist tenets and inspiration, the artists of the
' Sukhothai period (1238-1350 AD) solved the
problem of representing the image of the
Buddha by creating an idealized form
presented in terms only abstractly related to
the human physique and in such a manner
as to evoke peace of mind and contentment
in the beholder. This stylized, symbolistic
representation of the Buddha, used in both
sculpture and painting, gave rise to the
rhythmical and graceful curvilinear forms so
typical of Thai painting.
After the Sukhothai period, this idealized,
curvilinear form was also used to depict
Bodhisattvas, other celestial beings, royalty
and dignitaries who are portrayed in
rhythmical, flowing lines with the symbolic-
oval shape of the head, delicate facial
delineations and graceful gestures of the
hands; the facial expression is serene, slight¬
ly smiling or impassive. Emotions such as
joy, sorrow, reverence, hate, rage or love
are expressed by conventionalized lines and
gestures.
Humble folk are usually stylized, but less
elegantly, and they are portrayed with a
variety of facial expressions and explicit
gestures. The rough, tough characters, on
the other hand, and those in folklore scenes,
are more realistically depicted with some
degree of exaggeration employed to express
ridicule, sympathy, humour and lighthearted
sentiments..
Representation of bad characters is left :
entirely to the imagination and artistic skill of
the painter, with the results that Jujaka, the
Brahmin rascal in the Vessantara Jataka,
looks different in different murals, but he is
always identifiable. Scenes of hell are k
depicted in fantastic imagery and in folklore t
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
^ scenes and in portrayals of the rank and file
characters from the Jataka and the life story
of Buddha the artists give full rein to their
originality and creative talents. Thus,
despite the elements of conventionalism in
Thai painting, the individuality of the artist
still shines through.
Thai murals are two dimensional, ex¬
cluding both linear and atmospheric
perspective. They obtain the effects they
desire by linear treatment, with colour fulfill¬
ing only a secondary function. Never by
itself a statement of form, colour is an ac¬
cessory adding to the fluent affirmations of
the elegant flowing lines and as such must
not be a distraction. Colours are subdued
and mellow and thus specially effective in
lending an air of mysticism where this is
needed. The chromatic effect is enriched by
gilding the crowns and ornaments on
celestial beings and on royal personalities as
well as the ornamental parts of palaces, the
overall effect of the combined colours
blending harmoniously with the linear
forms.
The colours used are not intended to
represent the visible colours of objects in
nature. The sky may be bright blue and the
forest foliage green, but Thai artists vary
their colours according to their conceptual
scheme. There are some conventions in the
use of colours: royalty and the upper classes
are always painted in white or a very light
tone, while darker tones are reserved for the
lower classes.
A unique feature of Thai mural painting
lies in the technique of constructing and
blending many different scenes into a
unified large picture on the wall. The unity
of construction is such that, at a distance, a
mural appears as a whole picture with its
various component parts artistically arrang¬
ed. But when attention is drawn to any par¬
ticular part, the observer sees a picture,
complete in itself, depicting a certain scene.
This ordered composition interests the eye
and prompts the observer to range im¬
aginatively over a mural from one scene to
another unimpeded by any visual barrier.
Although the fresco technique was occa¬
sionally used in Thailand, as witness the
15th century murals at Wat Tatburuna in the
old capital of Ayuthya, tempera answered
the needs of Thai painters better and was
almost universally adopted. Unlike the
tempera emulsion commonly used in Europe
and elsewhere, which was prepared by mix¬
ing powdered colour with egg yolk or the
whole egg and then thinned with water, the
binder used in the preparation of Thai
tempera was gum from the Nakwid tree.
This was mixed with pigments of local origin
made from plants and mineral substances.
These natural pigments contributed to the
mellowness and harmony of colour achieved
in the old Thai murals. It was the glaring
vividness of imported chemical pigments
that threw the traditional harmony of colour
out of balance in the murals of the later
Bangkok period.
With few exceptions, mural paintings in
Thailand are located in the complex of
buildings that makes up the typical Thai
Buddhist temple-cum-monastery institution
known as a Wat. The murals may be on the
inside walls of the Vihan (a hall housing the
Above, the Vihan (hall of the Buddha) at Wat Phra Singh, the most
important monastery at Chieng Mai. The monastery was founded in
1345, but the Vihan was built in 1806 and the mural, right, which
adorns its north wall dates from about the middle of the 19th
century. The mural recounts the story of Prince Sang Thong. Cast
off by his father. Sang is brought up by a man-eating ogress named
Phanthurat. One day, in her absence, he discovers that in a part of
her palace which he is forbidden to enter are pools of silver and
gold as well as a golden staff which enables anyone holding it to
fly. In the right foreground Sang is seen dipping his finger into the
silver pool; on the left he is bathing in the pool of gold; above he
grasps the magic golden staff, while hovering near him is a ghost¬
like mask in which he disguises himself to escape from
Phanthurat's palace.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Above left, the imposing monastery
complex of Wat Ratchasitharam. The large
building centre left is the Ubosot (hall of
ceremonies) on the south wall of which is
the mural, left, depicting the "allegory of
the three strings". In the wilderness
Siddhattha lies on a bare rock, semi¬
conscious with exhaustion from rigorous
fasting and meditation. Five ascetics kneel
before him and at his feet is Indra playing a
three-stringed guitar. When Indra plucks
the first string it sounds harsh because it is
too taut; the second string lacks resonance
because it is too slack, the third string,
which is moderately taut, gives forth the
sweetest sound. This Siddhattha
interpreted as meaning that he should
avoid extremes and follow "the middle
way". From this time onwards he gave up
excessive fasting.
Buddha image), the Chedi (stupa), the
Prang (a tower-like stupa), or the Sala Kan-
parien (preaching and study hall), but those
inside the Ubosot (hall of ceremonies) con¬
stitute an organic part of the overall design
of the interior in relation to various other
parts, in particular the large, principal Bud¬
dha ¡mage which, by convention, is placed
among the smaller images on the altar at the
west end of the hall facing the entrance on
the east side.
Paintings cover the four walls and are ar¬
ranged in a set pattern. The entire top sec¬
tion of the wall above the entrance facing
the large Buddha ¡mage is devoted to the
scene of the Temptation and the Triumph
over Mara, a symbolic representation of the
overcoming of Evil. On the opposite wall,
behind the large Buddha ¡mage are scenes
of Lord Buddha's Sermon in Heaven and His
Descent to Earth, or, less frequently, a por¬
trayal of Buddhist cosmology. On the upper
portion of the two side walls are rows of
Buddhas with disciples, or rows of celestial
beings in the act of worship. Below these
are narrative murals depicting the life of the
Buddha, or stories from the Jataka, or, oc¬
casionally, scenes from the Ramayana, the
Hindu epic poem. Narrative murals also
cover the lower east wall below the Tempta-*
tion and the Triumph over Mara, while
graceful guardian figures adorn the inner
sides of the doors and shutters.
Apart from the primitive cave paintings
found in several parts of Thailand, the
earliest Thai traditional murals known to re¬
main are those of the Sukhothai period
(1238 - 1350 AD) found at Yala, in southern
Thailand, and at Sukhothai, the ancient Thai
capital. These are believed to have been
painted during the last quarter of the 13th
century. In the Sukhothai murals can be
seen the stylized representations of Buddha
¡mages which later became conventional.
Towards the end of the Ayuthya period
(1350 - 1767 AD), Thai mural painting came
to full maturity, but we know little of its
evolution since only four examples of murals
from the early and middle Ayuthya periods
are still extant. As in pre-Ayuthya murals on¬
ly four colours, black, white, red and yellow,
were used; composition remained simple
with the portrayal of Buddha figures either
alone or with attendants arranged in rows.
But at the beginning of the late Ayuthya
period, around the first quarter of the 17th
century, a new chapter in Thai mural pain¬
ting was opened.
The many murals that remain from this
period show a number of innovations. A
wider range of colours was introduced and
the conventional, stylized forms, postures
and gestures were fully established. The
simple, ceremonial designs of the Sukhothai
and earlier Ayuthya periods gave way tow
more complex compositions. After the fall f
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Above, mural at Wat Phumin
Nan, depicting Nemi on the way
to the Tavatimsa heaven, was
heavily restored in about 1870.
The Buddha, in a previous
existence as King Nemi, was
famed ior his lavish distribution
of alms and his obedience to
moral precepts. The thirty-three
gods of the Tavatimsa heaven
all wished to hear the royal sage
and Indra sent the heavenly
carriage to bring him before
them. On the journey, Matali,
the driver of the carriage,
showed him all the wonders of
the infernal and the heavenly
regions.
Right, portrait of "the physician
Kumanaphek" dates from about
1875 and comes from Wat
Phumin Nan. It is not known
whether the painting is a true
portrait or an ideal ¡mage of a
physician or a legendary
character. His features and the
style of his beard are unlike
those of any peoples of northern
Thailand or Laos. His clothing
seems equally foreign to the
region, but his long finger nails
indicate that he is of high rank.
k of Ayuthya in 1767, the tradition established
in the late Ayuthya period continued to
flourish, with variations, through the Thon-
buri period (1767-1782) and the early
Bangkok period (since 1782). But in the se¬
cond half of the 19th century, mural painting
began to degenerate due to indiscriminate
adoption of Western art techniques, the
blending of Western perspective, shading
and realism with traditional elements as well
as the use of glaring chemical colours prov¬
ing disastrous.
In recent years there has been a revival of
interest in traditional painting among artists.
Some are working along conventional lines,
while others are experimenting with dif¬
ferent compositions, forms and ideas in an
attempt to find a new direction. Outstanding
among the latter group is Thawal Dachani,
whose many works include wall-size can¬
vases and murals.
In the true tradition of the old masters,
Thawal seeks to express the Buddhist con¬
cept of truth through symbolism and
idealistic form, but in his own personal,
original style. His work is a continuation of
traditional painting, developed in one
specific direction, which seeks to convey the
Lord Buddha's message in a bolder, more
forceful style. It was precisely this cor¬
respondence between the Buddhist ideal in
life and the old masters' ideal in art that
enabled them successfully to develop their
own unique, idealistic style of painting.
Adul Wichiencharoen
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Ancient gold
from the melting-pot
of central Asia
ON a narrow strip of land below the
foothills of the Hindu Kush in nor¬
thern Afghanistan stand the majes¬
tic ruins of Emshi-tepe, one of the great
cities of ancient Bactria. The flat landscape
around the ruins is dotted with small
hillocks, one of which is known locally as
Tillya-tepe the Golden Mound. This three-
metre-high rise in the ground caught the at¬
tention of a Soviet-Afghan team of ar¬
chaeologists because the shards of pottery
littering its surface were quite unlike any
they had discovered elsewhere.
Test diggings revealed the brick floor,
pillars and surrounding wall of a massive
building containing the vestiges of an altar.
This temple, built at the end of the second
millennium BC, had remained in use for
some five hundred years. Excavations con¬
tinued, and on 15 November 1978 the ar¬
chaeologists working on the Golden Mound
literally struck gold when they discovered
the first of seven ancient graves which turn¬
ed out to contain a veritable treasure trove
of ornaments and jewellery. Coins found in
the tombs made it possible to date the
burials to between 100 BC and 100
AD 500 years after the temple,
whose ruins, it appeared, had been used as
a necropolis by a local ruling family.
THE JOINT SOVIET-AFGHAN ARCHAEO¬
LOGICAL EXPEDITION, which is responsible
for the discoveries described in this article and of
which Viktor Sarianidi is the leader, is sponsored
by the Afghan Ministry of Information and
Culture. Professor Sarianidi, of the Soviet Union,
is a senior member of the Archaeological Institute
of the USSR Academy of Sciences. He is the
author of a dozen major works including studies
of the ancient agriculturalists of Afghanistan
(1978), of the hidden art treasures of Karakum
(1968), and an account of the first excavations at
Ti/lya-Tepe (1972). His Central Asia before the
Achaemenides was published in London in 1972.
by Viktor I. Sarianidi
Of the six graves excavated so far, all ex¬
cept one (which had been infested with
mice) were undisturbed, although the
skeletal remains themselves were in a poor
state of preservation.
The occupants of the graves had been laid
to rest on their backs, dressed in clothing
richly embroidered with gold and pearls and
adorned with small golden plaques. Each
grave contained between 2,500 and 4,000
decorative objects made of gold (some
20,000 have been unearthed so far). As each
layer of clothing rotted away, these artefacts
had piled up haphazardly one on top of the
other, so that it was only by removing them
one by one that their initial arrangement
could be determined.
Foremost among the objects discovered
was a great variety of small, convex plaques
produced by stamping fine gold leaf on
specially prepared matrices. Many of these
plaques are decorated with ornamentation
in relief, and their edges are perforated so
that they can be stitched to a piece of
clothing.
The dead had been dressed in cotton or
silk garments, and the most important of
them had been buried with golden crowns,
their heads resting in silver or golden bowls.
Solid gold pendants, usually in pairs, were
attached to the taller headdresses. One
represents a lordly figure wearing a crown
encrusted with turquoise and lapis lazuli,
with long hair falling to his shoulders. The
face is broad-cheeked, possibly Mongolian,
with narrow, slanting eyes emphasized by
curved brows. The centre of the forehead
bears the imprint of a caste or marriage
mark. The arms are outstretched, and the
clenched fists rest on two winged dragons
with twisted bodies and bent legs. The
dragons, which have horse-like heads, are
baring their teeth; their eye-sockets are in¬
laid with cornelian, and turquoise decorates
their manes (see photo page 31).
A number of equally remarkable pendants
bear the image of an almost naked female
figure, portrayed full face. Her left hand,
holding a fruit, is close to her breast, while
her right arm hangs loosely at her side. This
figure, which may represent a goddess of
fertility, is flanked by wild animals with
snarling wolves, heads and fishes' tails. The
bases of these pendants are richly encrusted
with turquoise and shaped to resemble the
heads of fish, while their top corners are
decorated with figures of birds.
The many discoveries made so far in¬
clude: necklaces of large, hollow beads
decorated with fine pearls and encrusted
with turquoise rosettes; solid gold, open-
ended bracelets; rings (often with precious
stones, some bearing engraved designs);
gold buckles; golden scabbards and belts;
engraved gold plates; silver mirrors with
Chinese inscriptions and mirrors with ivory
handles; gems incised with images of gods
from the Greek pantheon or of fabulous
beasts; golden and bejewelled pendants in
the form of feet or palms with widespread
fingers; ivory combs from India, carved with
human figures; golden clasps, also shaped
in human forms. The number and variety of
the objects are such that specialists in
several countries have described the
treasure as "the find of the century".
The. burials date back to a dark and
enigmatic period in the history of a region
which in ancient times came under many
cultural influences. Although the written
and archaeological evidence is slender, it is
enough to tell us that Bactria was con¬
quered by Alexander the Great in 331 BC
and after his death became first a Seleucid
and then a Greco-Bactrian kingdom,
governed by Hellenized Bactrians and Greek
colonists. This fusion of two different
cultures was to condition the region's
development for many centuries to come.
By the middle of the second century BC,
nomadic hordes were pressing down from!
the steppes towards the fertile oases of the'
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Statuette of a half-
naked winged
goddess, left, seems
to be a portrait of
Aphrodite, the Greek
goddess of love, but
also has an Indian
caste or marriage
mark in the middle of
the forehead.
Elegant gold bracelets
in the form of
galloping antelopes
(right). Corners of the
eyes and other
teardrop-shaped inlays
are of turquoise.
Right, image of the
Greek goddess Athena
wearing a long fluted
robe was incised into
a ring and probably
used as a seal.
Skeleton key
to a
mysterious past
Remains of a noble (above) as discovered
by Soviet and Afghan archaeologists in a
2,000-year-old necropolis in northern
Afghanistan. Richly adorned with
turquoise-studded gold finery, the body lay
in a wooden coffin with a round bronze
Chinese mirror on its chest, its wrists
encircled with a pair of bracelets (see top
photo page 31). Objects found in the
necropolis reflect an amalgam of
mythological themes and designs from
different regions. Scholars think
that the burial ground contains members
of a ruling family from an obscure
period during the emergence of the Kushan
Empire which eventually stretched
across a vast expanse of Asia.
30
Detailed treatment of
a mountain goat (left)
is worthy of the finest
traditions of realistic
Hellenistic art.
Elaborately worked
pendant, right, depicts
a figure holding at bay
two cavorting dragons
with teardrop-shaped
turquoise manes. The
face with its narrow,
slanting eyes may be
Mongolian; the caste
or marriage mark in
centre of forehead
suggests Indian
influence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
, south. Their advance spearheaded by the
Yueh-Chih, whose previous homeland had
been in the vicinity of Mongolia and who
had themselves been driven westward by
the Hsiung-nu (or Huns), the nomads
reached the Amu Darya (Oxus) river, over¬
threw the Greco-Bactrian kingdom and
established five principalities in its place.
One of these principalities they called Kuei
Shuanga name which would subsequent¬
ly be transformed into the more familiar
"Kushan".
Little by little, the former nomads fell
under the spell of urban life, and finally set¬
tled down themselves. Slowly but surely,
the Yueh-Chih built up the Kushan Empire,
until it ranked with the other great empires
of the time (see Unesco Courier, February
1969). It is the transitional period between
the fall of the Greco-Bactrian kingdom and
the rise of the Kushan Empire about which
the Tillya-tepe excavations can give us so
much information, for the city of Emshi-tepe
outside whose limits it lies may well have
been chosen by the early Kushan rulers as
the residence of a provincial overlord. There
are even grounds for believing that the
necropolis belonged to the Yueh-Chih family
which actually founded the Kushan dynasty.
The burials appear to have been carried
out in a summary fashion, perhaps under
cover of darkness, the bodies being placed
in simple rectangular graves which could be
dug in two or three hours. The wooden cof¬
fins, which were anchored in the soil with
iron staples, seem to have had no lids, but to
have been covered with blankets sewn with
gold and silver discs.
The graves were roofed with logs,
forming a burial chamber which was filled
with earth later on when the vaulting col¬
lapsed. In the earth above one of them the
archaeologists found a horse's skull, which
appeared at some time to have been wrap¬
ped in leather and which recalled the funeral
rites of the nomadic Scythians (see Unesco
Courier, December 1976).
The presence of a number of women's
golden diadems provided further evidence
that the graves contained thé remains of
members of a formerly nomadic people,
since it was only among nomads that the
female sex enjoyed high status a fact
which invariably provoked the astonishment
of the writers of Antiquity.
However, the burials indicate that the first
Kushan rulers had broken almost completely
with certain of their nomadic traditions. For
example, the discovery of a silver coin in¬
serted between the teeth of one of the
skeletons shows that a strong Greek
religious influence had replaced some of the
ancient funeral rituals of the nomads. The
conical form of the burial mound, which
recalls the kurgans in which their ancestors
were buried with great piles of ritually
sacrificed horses is virtually the only link
which these former nomads retained with
their past.
Although technically speaking the Tillya-
tepe jewellery is of a high standard, the
aesthetic criteria of the early Kushan rulers
fell far short of those generally accepted in
the then "civilized" world; the stiff, full-face
compositions of this "official" art produced
for a ruling class are a far cry from the
realistic and lively Hellenistic productions of
earlier Greco-Bactrian craftsmen. If the
rulers wanted jewellery, it was quantity and
variety, rather than inherent artistic value, t
that interested them. As a result, although r
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
> many of the ornaments represent divinities
from the Greek pantheon and even entire
compositions on themes from Greek
mythology, their execution falls short of the
standards of classical Antiquity. The Bac-
trian craftsmen sized up the new market,
strove to keep up with the fashion, and
cared little about the artistic quality of their
work.
This is particularly evident in a series of
moulded buckles representing Eros seated
on a dolphin. The Bactrian jeweller obvious¬
ly had an imperfect grasp of the theme,
which occurs widely in the art of Antiquity,
and replaced what was for him a strange
and unknown creature with more familiar
models the fish which abounded in the
Amu Darya river of his native land. Nor
could any Greek craftsman possibly have
been responsible for the large and graceless
nose of the goddess Athena as she is por¬
trayed on one of the gold rings found at
Tillya-tepe.
But the synthesis of concepts which are
local and traditionally Bactrian with those
which are purely Greek is carried so far that
it is not always possible to determine with
certainty the origin of many of the pieces.
Thus, while certain figurines depicting wing¬
ed goddesses recall Nike, the Greek goddess
of victory, a similar divinity, seated on a
throne or a dragon, is found in numerous
Bactrian Bronze Age carvings of the second
millennium BC. Likewise, the goddess
seated on a lion which decorates a golden
belt from Tillya-tepe may seem at first to be
associated with Cybele, the mother-goddess
worshipped in Ancient Greece, yet a com¬
plex composition which also represents a
winged divinity straddling an animal is found
"on Bactrian seals of the same period.
These examples show how the Kushan
artists turned not only in the traditional
direction of ancient Greco-Roman imagery,
but also to the Bronze-Age beginnings of
local Bactrian mythology.
The golden ornaments also highlight the
cultural influence of Parthia [a land cor¬
responding roughly to the modern region of
Khorasan in Iran], Scholars already knew
from coin discoveries in central Bactria that
Parthia had expanded eastwards into Bactria
and politically dominated the principalities
established by the Yueh-Chih on Bactrian
soil, especially in the region near the modern
town of Shibarghan, a few kilometres away
from the necropolis. The Tillya-tepe
discovery now brings further evidence of
Parthian influence, for the golden or¬
naments bear a strong resemblance to ob¬
jects found in a Parthian burial ground in
faraway Nineveh, in northern Mesopotamia.
This cannot be a mere coincidence.
The animal imagery on the ornaments is
particularly interesting because it seems to
show the direct influence of the so-called
Scytho-Siberian animal style found in the art
of the Sarmatian tribes. This suggests that
the arrival of the nomads in Bactria was of
considerable artistic significance. Although
scholars differ as to the birthplace of this
animal style, some setting it in Eurasia,
others in Central Asia, the images found on
the golden plaques of Tillya-tepe, where
animals are rolled into the form of a ring or
tied together in a knot, frenziedly snapping
at their own paws or tails, certainly seem to
derive from the ancient art forms of the High
Altai in Siberia (see Unesco Courier,
December 1976).
32
Analysis of the human imagery of the
Tillya-tepe jewels suggests that Bactria at
the dawn of the Christian era was populated
by more than one ethnic group. One series
of figures (including the "lord with dragons"
shown on page 31) has broad-cheeked
faces, slanting eyes and stubborn chins of a
Mongolian cast, possibly reflecting the ap¬
pearance of the Yueh-Chih, whose Central
Asian origin is also supported by other data.
Other figures (including the winged god¬
dess shown on page 30) portray an entirely
different type: women whose oval, rather
moon-shaped faces, wide eyes and thick lips
are more reminiscent of the features of the
original inhabitants of the Bactrian plain.
Warriors with classically Greek profiles are
portrayed on a number of gold buckles (pro¬
bably imported from Greece itself), and on
certain other objects. Other external in¬
fluences, revealed in the mirrors from China
and the carved ivory objects from India, re¬
mind us that this region lay astride the Great
Silk route which ran from China to the
Mediterranean.
Tillya-tepe can tell us much, not only
about the streams of imported goods from
Greece and Rome, India and China, that
flowed together in Bactria, but also about
the local culture which resulted from the
bizarre blending of different styles and
cultures from elsewhere. A colourful exam¬
ple of this amalgamation is a gold scabbard
whose decoration includes swastikas from
ancient India, Chinese dragons, and the
branched antlers of the Siberian stag.
The themes treated in the "lord and
dragon" gold pendants are derived from
Eurasian art, but the lord himself looks very
much like a Yueh-Chih. His noble rank is in¬
dicated by a typically Indian caste mark on
his forehead. As for the dragon with which
he is wrestling, its legs are bent backwards
in full accordance with the Scytho-Siberian
animal style. !
But this reconciliation of different cultural
traditions and influences is most apparent in
the objects whose themes are related to
Greek mythology. Some of the winged god¬
desses portraying Aphrodite have Indian
caste marks on their foreheads, while others
have broad-cheeked "Asiatic" faces. There
could be no clearer indication of the extent
to which Greco-Bactrian art had been
transformed.
It may well be that the Tillya-tepe finds are
the first examples of a "Hellenistic art"
derived from the merging of Greco-Roman
and Eastern traditions. Behind this cultural
phenomenon we may also discern the
outlines of the historical circumstances
which attended the birth of the Kushan Em¬
pire, whose builders' roots lay in the distant
Scytho-Altaian world. After heading a con¬
federation of Central Asian tribes and over¬
throwing the Greco-Bactrian kingdom, the
Yueh-Chih found themselves for a time
dependent to some extent on neighbouring
Parthia; then, in the second century AD,
they began to create their own great Kushan
Empire. It was during this period that the
first signs of a truly Kushan culture emerged
from a blend of Greco-Bactrian, Chinese, In¬
dian and Persian traditions. It is to be hoped
that further excavations by the Soviet-
Afghan archaeological expedition will shed
more light on the development of this
culture.
Viktor I. Sarianidi
The Lord of the
Tavatimsa heaven
This portrait of Indra, the lord of
the Tavatimsa heaven ("the
heaven of the thirty-three gods")
is one of many little-known
mural paintings which grace the
temples of Pagan, Burma's
ancient holy city and capital (see
article page 35). Indra, one of
the highest gods in the Hindu
pantheon, is also revered in
Buddhism where the gods have
the task of proclaiming and
venerating Buddha. The
painting, which shows Indra
kneeling and touching a stringed
instrument with a bow is in
Kamma Kyaung U temple. It
probably dates from the 18th
century. Although already badly
deteriorated when this photo
was taken, the decorative
colouring still succeeds in
communicating the richness and
magnificence of the god's
garments, the musical
instrument and the background.
In 1975 an earthquake caused
even worse damage to this
jewel of Burmese art.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
O06^pXBC0^GCODO0CgO:. ' sjcxïjmoxWQ^^
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The paintings of Pagan
Temple walls that tell the story
of the Buddha's many lives
by Klaus Wenk
Scenes from
Buddhist scripture
Mural-covered temple walls in
Pagan (accent is on second
syllable. Pagan) have been
likened to a picture-book of
Buddhist scripture and tradition.
Many of the wall-paintings,
whose place in Burmese and
Oriental art is now coming to be
more fully appreciated, portray
incidents from the Jataka, the
tales of the Buddha's previous
lives before the final human
incarnation in which he
achieved enlightenment (see
also photo caption page 25).
Colour photo top left shows
Brahmadatta king of Benares
clasping a palm tree while
captivated with the splendours
of nature. Strange-shaped
bushes sprout in foreground
where a tiger peeps out from a
forked branch. This mural, from
Ananda Okkyaung temple, is
one of many painted in the late
18th century, when a new
flowering of artistic creativity
came to Pagan six centuries
after the city had been sacked
by the armies of Kublai Khan.
"The Bodhisatta Medankara's
Flight from the World", (bottom
colour photo), is a mural from
Upali Thein, the "Ordination
Hall", which was named after
the thirteenth-century monk
Upali. It is inspired by an event
from the Buddhavamsa ("the
lineage of the Buddha"), which
describes the lives and work of
twenty-four Buddhas who lived
before the Buddha Gautama.
Preening parrot, top right, from
Yadana Myitzu temple, shows
how Pagan mura lists could also
turn their hands to purely
ornamental painting. Photo this
page shows decorative motif on
the ceiling of Ananda
Okkyaung. A figure with a
crown and royal ornaments rises
from the centre of a circle.
BURMESE painting is one of the
"great unknowns" of world art, and
except for a handful of specialists
few people are aware of the wealth of mural
paintings in the monuments of Pagan, Bur¬
ma's ancient capital.
Pagan itself, situated on the east bank of
the Irrawaddy river, some 145 kilometres
downstream from Mandalay, is an
astonishing spectacle. A forest of shrines
and temples (the Burmese Archaeological
Service has counted as many as five thou¬
sand) stretches as far as the eye can see.
Some of them are in ruins, others are
relatively well preserved in spite of the
vicissitudes of Pagan's history and nature's
slow process of decay, to which the earth¬
quake of 8 July 1975 added a disastrous
hammer-blow. (See Unesco Courier, May
1976).
Standing out from among the host of pin- k
nacles and pointed cupolas on this gran- f
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
diose site is the delicately-proportioned
white mass of Ananda, the most famous
temple in Burma.
Just in front of Ananda's north entrance
stands a more insignificant, though still
massive, tower-like building of brick covered
with plaster. In Burmese it is known simply
as Ananda Okkyaung, "the brick temple (in
front of) the Ananda Temple".
This rather unsatisfactory situation beside
a dominating neighbour may explain why
Ananda Okkyaung attracts few visitors ex¬
cept for those who know that within its
shadowy passages are the crowning glory of
eighteenth-century Burmese painting, a set
of murals which are still well preserved.
The visitor who steps into the temple
through the entrances with their low, round
arches, cannot fail to be impressed. From
the mystical atmosphere of semi-darkness,
shines out a gallery of paintings the like of
which as far as number and completeness
are concerned, can no longer be seen
anywhere else in Burma.
The murals, although the work of various
hands, give the impression of forming a
complete whole. They illustrate many typical
characteristics of Burmese painting, and to
be fully understood they must be seen as
part of a long tradition which is itself in¬
separable from the history of Pagan.
First of all, Burmese painting is on the
whole Buddhist painting. Its most important
impulse came from the great religious move¬
ment that originated in India in the 5th cen¬
tury BC and subsequently spread across the
whole of south and east Asia the teachings
of the Buddha, the great one who overcame
the world.
In Burma the Theravada variant of Bud¬
dhism became dominant during the reign of
King Anawrahta (1044-1077) who united the
country politically and initiated the develop¬
ment of Pagan as one of the most important
centres of Buddhist learning in South-east
Asia. According to Theravada beliefs, pain¬
tings on the walls of temples are considered
only as incidental decorations which
demonstrate and illustrate the teachings of
Buddha. For believers such works could
never in themselves be the object of
aesthetic contemplation.
But Burmese painting does not owe its
development and refinement to this one im¬
pulse only. It also reflects the teachings of
Mahayana Buddhism, the Buddhism of the
"Great Vehicle", which in contrast to the
stricter teachings of Theravada Buddhism
permits belief in a large number of holy men
and Bodhisattas (enlightened beings
predestined for Buddhahood) and thus
meets the need for a more popular doctrine
of salvation. Other influences were due to
the geographical proximity of India and
Tibet, intensive contacts with Ceylon, and
the deep-rooted animist beliefs of the peo
ple. Hindu deities are also depicted on the
walls of many temples at Pagan, and there
are signs of the influence of Tantrism, the
so-called "magic Buddhism" which was
formerly practised primarily in Tibet and
which stresses ritual, the strict observance
of cults, initiation, consecration and magic
formulae.
Few monuments from Anawrahta's reign
have survived, and it was not until the time
of his second successor Kyanzittha
(1084-1112) that the era of great temple
building began. The mural paintings that
can still be admired on their walls mark the
start of the artistic tradition of which the
Ananda Okkyaung paintings are a later
brilliant expression.
Well preserved murals from this early
period can still be seen today in the Wetkyi-
in-Kubyauk-gyi temple, which was probably
completed in or a little before the year 1200,
because fortunately the mortar layer on the
temple walls is relatively thick and well
smoothed-down, and has thus provided a
durable support for the paintings. (This is
not always the case at Pagan, where mortar
was often made of local red soil which pro- .
vided a breeding ground for insects. As a
result, the greater part of the plaster in most
of the temples has fallen from the walls, and
where it remains, the surfaces and con¬
sequently the murals are covered with the
nests of wasps, termites and other destruc- h
tive insects).
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Enormous figure
of a snarling
lion outside a
Burmese
pagoda was
meant to keep evil
spirits at bay.
Pagan's forest of Buddhist temples and
stupas (some 5,000 monuments in all)
extends across a site covering over 70 sq.
km. Opposite page, the gleaming white
contours of the famous Ananda temple can
be seen on the horizon from the terraces of
Thatbyinnu, Pagan's tallest edifice (it is as
high as a 20-storey building). In July 1975
this unique site was rocked by a violent
earthquake which caused extensive
damage. Murals in some of the temples
sustained irreparable harm. The Burmese
authorities are carrying out a major rescue
operation (below) on Pagan's stricken
monuments.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
"At the River Televaha", above, is inspired
by a Jataka text which contrasts the
behaviour of two hawkers, one of whom is
predestined for Buddhahood. In this
unusual example of a Burmese painting
depicting water, one of the hawkers
(probably the man standing upright with
hands upraised in the stern of the boat) is
seen crossing the River Televaha on his
way to the town of Andhapura (All photos
on this double page show eighteenth-
century murals from Pagan's Ananda
Okkyaung temple).
y The year 1287 brought to an end the first
dream in Buddhist history: a Mongolian ar¬
my conquered and devastated Pagan, burn¬
ing down its wooden monastery buildings,
its palaces, and the houses and huts of the
inhabitants. It seems that Burma had lost all
sense of political realities in the second half
of the 13th century, for only a few of these
buildings lay within the area protected by
the city walls. One of the most splendid
manifestations of Buddhist piety collapsed
all too easily, a prey to the Mongol hordes.
For the next five hundred years there was
no Burmese Empire. Various dynasties of
the different peoples living on each side of
the Irrawaddy and Walwin Rivers warred
with each other inconclusively. New capitals
and new centres of culture came into be¬
ingAva, Sagaing, Amarapura. The great
age of Pagan would not be matched until
the end of the eighteenth century with the
creation of the incomparable paintings
which were executed in many of the little
stupas (commemorative relic mounds or
shrines) and temples of Pagan. Ananda Ok¬
kyaung, built between 1776 and 1785, was
part of this renaissance, which began with
the accession of King Alaungpaya in 1752
and restored to Pagan its former role as Bur¬
ma's cultural metropolis.
Executed in dominant tones of red and
brown, with ochres obtained from the iron
géodes which litter the bed of the nearby Ir¬
rawaddy, the Ananda Okkyaung murals take
up the Buddhist themes which had inspired
the artists of Pagan hundreds of years
before. Many of these themes are taken
from the body of Buddhist scripture known
as the Jatakas, a collection of stories, anec¬
dotes and pithy sayings which relate
episodes from one of the many lives of the
Bodhisatta, or "Buddha-to-be".
According to tradition, the Buddha
Gautama, before his Great Enlightenment,
had undergone many existences in many dif¬
ferent forms living among men as a god, a
king, a minister, an ascetic, a merchant, a
gardener, a musician, and adopting other
human guises. He also appeared in the form
of various animals or birds. In the Jatakas,
the Buddha-to-be, in one of his former
births, plays a part as the hero or as some
other character. Sometimes he is merely an
onlooker, but he always shows one or more
of the virtues, such as sympathy, compas¬
sion or altruism, by which he prepared
himself for Enlightenment.
The enormous popularity of the Jatakas
as vehicles for Buddhist teaching is revealed
in the number of texts and pictures they
inspired.
What is particularly remarkable about the
Ananda Okkyaung murals is the freedom
with which the painters conceived their sub¬
jects. As the illustrations on these pages
show, they do not depict only what is
necessary to narrate the Jakata stories, they
also make use of the opportunity to paint
genre scenes from court life and from the
lives of ordinary people of the time. In this
way they present a wealth of interesting
facts about the cultural history of the
Burmese people.
The murals belong to a tradition in which
the representation of reality, of the external
world, is based on certain formulas and
matrices which, once fixed, became univer¬
sally valid. In executing each picture and
each part of a picture, the Burmese artist
took certain basic figures or models as his
starting point. Traditionally, four artistic
elements were used in the composition of
Burmese painting: Kanut, Nari, Kapi and
Gaja, which are Pali and Sanskrit terms used
to define both subject and treatment.
Kanut designates every type of ornamen¬
tation in the form of rounded or curved
lines. Vegetation, especially the com¬
ponents of the lotus plant, is depicted in this
way, but these curved, climbing motifs are
often used for snakes and other creatures,
stylized waves and clouds, and abstract
figures.
Nari, which literally means "woman", i
describes more generally any depiction of I
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Although the youngest of a
hundred brothers, prince
Gamani is elected king
because of his wisdom.
Above left, two of the
brothers on horseback and
one mounted on an
elephant. They are
accompanied by servants,
canopy-carriers and soldiers
armed with guns.
Preceded by ten
servants carrying
golden vessels,
and followed by a
canopy-bearer
and two other
attendants, an
elegantly attired
wedding guest
rides through an
open gate, left.
Detail from a
mural illustrating
the marriage of a
young man to the
daughter of the
King's Treasurer,
described in the
Jataka. The
framed object at
left of the
document is part
of a loom.
Slim, graceful lady of the court,
above, seems to be dancing to
the rhythm plucked from a
crocodile-shaped musical
instrument held on his knees by
the man seated behind her. The
painters of the Ananda
Okkyaung murals did not limit
themselves to portraying
Buddhist themes, and their
fondness for depicting genre
scenes from court and everyday
life is a source of many side¬
lights on Burma's cultural past.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
KLAUS WENK, professor at the Department of
Oriental Studies at the University of Hamburg,
Federal Republic of Germany, is the author of a
number of important works on the history,
literature and art of south-east Asia. These in¬
clude a three-volume illustrated study Mural Pain¬
tings in Thailand (1975-1976), and Murals in Bur¬
ma, Volume I, Paintings from Pagan of the Late
Period (1977), which includes a contribution by
professor U Tin Lwin of the University of Man-
dalay, both published by Inigo von Oppersdorff
Verlag, Zurich. Both these works, from which the
illustrations for this article and the article by pro¬
fessor Adul Wichiencharoen (page 25) are taken,
have been awarded the International Emblem for
Works of Art and Culture. Franz Horisberger car¬
ried out the photographic work for Paintings from
Pagan in 1975, shortly before the area was hit by a
devastating earthquake. For many murals only
the photographic record remains.
k the human body, as well as representations
of the gods and of the Buddha.
The term Kapi strictly refers to the pain¬
ting of monkeys, but is extended to cover
the portrayal of animals of any kind, as well
as various mythological creatures. On the
whole, the term Kapi is linked with the idea
of rapid movement, birds in flight, leaping
animals, with the playfulness of monkeys,
the capricious laziness of the Kinnari (half-
man, half-bird), and the playing of celestial
musicians.
Gaja is the term used to describe the por¬
trayal of the elephant, which is a common
figure in Burmese painting. The body of the
elephant is associated with the idea of size,
height and length, as well as the idea of
strength and immobility.
The whole of Burmese painting, with few
exceptions, is composed of these four basic
types. It represents the concrete, the visible,
the material form of things, the surface.
Those things that cannot be depicted or can
only be suggested the element of at¬
mosphere, the mental and spiritual forces by
which man is moved, emotions and com¬
prehension, the various degrees of con¬
sciousness of salvation or of the wrong
path are immanent in the paintings and
can be deduced from the material forms. In
a Buddha delineated with solid contours,
without the link of colouring that might have
an aesthetic appeal, a viewer who inhabits
the Buddhist world of ideas spontaneously
sees a depth of inner peace and acquires the
deepest insight into the forms of existence.
In other words, in Burmese pictures we
find decorative painting with its origins in
floral ornaments, which in the course of
development has emerged as geometric
forms; we find figurative painting in which
solid, undifferentiated forms are found side
by side with ethereal and attractively and
gracefully painted figures; we find action
painting represented by playful animal
movements or by the gay frolics of
mythological creatures; and we find the
painting of objects, which cannot basically
be compared with still-life painting but
40
which depicts large dimensions and through
these immobility.
Finally, like all Eastern painting, Burmese
painting is arranged in parallel perspectives.
It is set out in surfaces; it spreads out figures
and objects in front of the viewer and for
this reason does not, with a few rare excep¬
tions, give the impression of spatial depth.
There is no horizon. Painting of this kind
must necessarily rely on a framework of
drawing, on outlines and on linear designs.
Horizontals and verticals merge with each
other. They merely divide up the surface and
do not create space.
Figures and objects are placed in a
sequence or in a group as if in a picture
book. Landscape and figures are not usually
in harmony with each other, and the figures
are isolated from their environment. The
Kanut formulae are linked neither in shape
nor in colouring with the Nari painting, and
only in some of the murals is there even a
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
"Once upon a time in the Kasi
country the squire of a certain little
village had promised a sacrifice to
the Fairy of a banyan-tree which
stood at the entrance to the village.
Afterwards he offered for sacrifice
a number of creatures and betook
himself to the tree to get released
from his vow.
"But the tree-fairy standing in the
fork of the tree repeated this
stanza:
Take thought of life hereafter
when you seek
Release, for this release is
bondage strict.
Not thus the wise and good
release themselves;
For this the fool's release in
bondage ends.
"Thenceforth, men refrained from
such taking of life and by walking
in righteousness thronged
thereafter the city of the Devas".
n this mural from Ananda
Okkyaung, the sovereign figure of
the deity stands in the centre of a
tree whose roots, trunk and
branches flicker like flames. The
foliage might be a nimbus for the
deity. At right of the tree the
walled estate of the "rich citizen"
begins; behind it, in the courtyard
of his domain he reclines on a
couch, surrounded by his wives. On
the roof a monkey performs playful
tricks. This genre scene, only
loosely connected with the Jataka
narrative, recreates the opulent
atmosphere surrounding a man
who could afford to sacrifice many
sheep, pigs, cattle and fowls.
partial removal of the alienation between
one person and another, between object
and object.
The whole mode of representation in
these remarkable paintings at Pagan is thus
unemotional and rational. There is a sense
of order. Society is arranged on hierarchical
principles, and the whole cosmos is a
system ordered according to Hindu-
Buddhist cosmography.
Klaus Wenk
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
ROBERT JACQUEMIN, who has been
responsible for the design and lay-out of the
Unesco Courier since its inception, retired at
the end of 1979. Combining the imagination of
an artist with the meticulous rigour of a true
professional, he left the imprint of his talent on
the hundreds of issues of the magazine
published with his collaboration over more
than thirty years, a period during which the
Unesco Courier achieved recognition and suc¬
cess with a vast international readership. Both
for his professional ability and for his human
qualities Robert Jacquemin has earned the
high esteem and gratitude of all who worked
with him.
Unicef greeting cards
Artists and museums from many countries have ¿gain contributed designs to this
year's UNICEF greeting cards and stationery. The collection of all-occasion cards, in
full size or mini format, note-cards, and sets of matching stationery, cards.and lined
envelopes, offer designs from a wide variety of sources including a 17th-century
Chinese wood-jcut, Ireland's 7th-century Illuminated manuscript "Book of Durrow",
a pre-Columbian tapestry and a stamped Nigérian coronation cloth. Proceeds from
the sale of these items, available at UNICEF sales points throughout the world, will
enable UNICEF to continue and expand its vital work of bringing better nutrition, in¬
creased educational opportunities and improved health care to needy children in
some 100 developing countries of Asia, Africa and Latin America. Also available is a
trilingual (English-French-Spanish) engagement calendar featuring children's games,
toys and songs from twenty countries on five continents. Highly popular educational
toys are UNICEF's three "Educoll" cardboard cut-out kits for building traditional
dwellings of Africa and Indonesia, and a colourful "Friendship" jigsaw puzzle show¬
ing children from many countries, folding hands in a circle. Shown here, set of twen¬
ty different all-occasion mini-cards,
BOOKSHELF
Recent Unesco books
and periodicals
Towards a New International
Economic Order, by Mohammed Bed-
japui. First in a new Unesco series entitl¬
ed "New Challenges to International
Law". Published and sold exclusively
throughout the world by Holmes and
Meier Publishers Inc., New York, and
Holmes and Meier Ltd., London. 1979.
287 pp.
New Trends in Home Economics
Education, vol. I. Edited by Vincent G.
Hutchinson and F.L. Calder. Reports by
specialists from many countries on the
role of home economics in national
development. 1979, 139 pp. (24 F).
National Science and Technology
Policies in Europe and North
America, 1978. Present situation and
future prospects. Presents national sum¬
maries from among the 37 countries
attending the second Unesco
MINESPOL II (Ministers responsible for
science and technology policy in the
European and North American region)
conference held in Belgrade, 1978. 1979,
458 pp. (28 F); Science, Technology
and Government Policy. The working
documents and concluding texts of the
1978 MINESPOL II conference. 183 pp.
(20 F). Numbers 43 and 44 in Unesco's
"Science Policy Studies and Docu¬
ments" series.
Research and Social Goals is the
theme of Unesco's quarterly Impact of
Science on Society (Vol. 29, No. 3,
1979). Each Issue 12 F; subscriptions
40 F for one year, 66 F for two years.
Patterns of Child Socialization,
theme of Unesco's quarterly Interna¬
tional Social Science Journal (Vol.
XXI, No. 3, 1979). Each issue 23 F;
subscriptions 70 F for one year, 116 F for
two years.
Mathematics for Real Life is the
special theme of Prospects, Unesco's
quarterly review of education (Vol. IX
No. 3, 1979). Each issue 12 F; subscrip¬
tions 42 F for one year, 70 F for two
years.
Unesco's Literature
Translations Series
India
The Hermit and the Love-Thief.
Sanskrit Poems of Bhartrihari and
Bilhana, translated by Barbara Stoler
Miller. Columbia University Press, New
York, 1978, 127 pp.
Songs of KRSNA, translated from the
Bengali, Sanskrit and Hindi by Deben
Bhattacharya. Samuel Weiser Inc., New
York, 1978. 191 pp. Japan.
Japan
A Certain Woman (Aru Onna), a
novel by Arishlma Taleo. Translated by
Kenneth Strong. University of Tokyo
Press, 1978. 382 pp.
Europe
Wild Tales (Divi razkazi), translated
from the Bulgarian by Michael Holman.
Peter Owen Ltd., London, 1979. 239 pp.
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier
Index 1979
January
INTERNATIONAL YEAR OF THE CHILD. The silenced majority (E. Boulding). Cradled in
hunger (F.M. Barros). Fairy tales (J.-E. Adoum). The road to self-expression (A.
McKenna). Declaration of the Rights of the Child. What's in a name? (H. Alphandéry).
Children in exile. Art treasures: Mother and child from Mohenjodaro (Pakistan).
February
THE HUICHOL (J. Negrin). Are we heating up our planet? (W. Kellogg). The Mayas (Y.
Knorozov). Mayan language (V. Kuzmischev). Haitian art (R. Depestre). World's-eye view
of history (G. Barraclough). Art treasures: Ivory trio (Greece).
March
CHILDREN AND THE MASS MEDIA (K. Goto). Television (J. Halloran). Children as
actors (F. Truffaut). African childhood (C. Laye). Children's books (M. Soriano). Unesco
and International Year of the Child. Racism in textooks (H. Ortega; B. Banfield). Whizz-
kids (A. Petrovsky). Art treasures: Country boy (France).
April
THE ARMS RACE. The will for peace (A.M. M'Bow). The Arms Race (U.N. report):
Rising tide of military expenditure; New technology for overkill; The quality spiral; The
deadliest weapon of all?; Military waste and human want; Three myths; The military
establishment; Can the arms race be halted' Art treasures: Phoenician fertility symbols
(Tunisia).
May
EINSTEIN (J. Ehlers). Relativity in a nutshell (I. Asimov). The test of time (P. Dirac). Eins¬
tein's universe. The Mole and the Butterfly (P. Thuillier). Frontiers of science (A. Migdal).
The scientist's dilemma (A. Einstein). Art treasures: The smiling boy (India).
June
ROYAL TOMBS OF MACEDÓN (M. Andronicos). Sukhothai (M. Diskul). Common heri¬
tage or licence to exploit? (M. Bedjaoui). The Elche Mystery (J.-C. Langlois). Korczak (S.
Tomkiewicz and B. Maffioli). Margaret Mead (C. Lévi-Strauss). Art treasures: Maori chief
and his children (New Zealand).
July
MEDICINE'S "GREEN REVOLUTION" (J.-M. Pelt). Avicenna (H. Said). Come-back for
medicinal plants (M. Atisso). African medicinal plants (D. Ekong). Unesco and chemistry
of natural products. Tibet's medical thesaurus (L. Khundanova). Chinese medicine (Wei-
Wen). Neptune's pharmacopoeia (M. Piattelli). Mexican plants and human fertility (P.
Crabbé). Plant cures from Brazil (0. Gottlieb and W. Mors). Herbal therapy for drug addic¬
tion. Bulgarian folk remedies (V. Petkov). Art treasures: The swinging Totonacs (Mexico).
August-September
GENERAL HISTORY OF AFRICA (A.-M. M'Bow). A continent viewed from within (J. Ki-
Zerbo). The written word. Dialogue with time (B. Hama and J. Ki-Zerbo). Oral tradition
(A. Hampate Bâ). The Hamitic myth (D. Olderogge). Prehistoric rock paintings; The cradle
of mankind (J. Ki-Zerbo). African prehistory and the evolution of man (chart). Egypt's
inventors and technologists (R. El-Nadoury and J. Vercoutterl. The Empire of Kush (J.
Leclant). Matriarchs of Meroe (A.M. Ali Hakem with I. Hrbek and J. Vercoutterl. Mali
Empire (D. Niane). Swahili civilization (V. Matveiev). Art treasures: Mother and child
(Mali).
October
PAPUA NEW GUINEA. Cultural roots of a new nation (J. Kolia). New Ireland's Malang-
gan art (P. Godin). Profile of Papua New Guinea. Children of apartheid (M. Kunene). Ber-
tina in Rome (B. Wijngaarden). Agrarian reform (FAO). Music of the Gulf (H. Tourna).
Minaret of Jam (A. Bruno). Art treasures: Mother-goddess (Turkey).
November
SCIENCE, TECHNOLOGY AND DEVELOPMENT (I. Abdel Rahman). Twelve "musts" for
development (J. Frank da Costa). Widening chasm between rich and poor (N.A. Cox-
George). The candle of learning (A. Salam). Diminishing returns of technology (0.
Gianni). Search for a global strategy (D. Gvishiani). Meiji Japan (K. Oshima and K.
Furuya). The decision-makers (F. Papa Blanco). Art treasures: Motherhood in marble
(United Kingdom).
December
A CHINESE EMPEROR'S CLAY ARMY (Gu Wenjie). Holy Places of Upper Nepal (C. Jest).
Buddhist vision in Thai art (A. Wichiencharoen). Ancient gold from Afghanistan (V. Saria¬
nidi). Paintings of Pagan, Burma (K. Wenk). Art treasures: Birth of the Buddha (Nepal).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (Sm list
below; names of distributors In countries not lis¬
tad, along with subscription rates In local cur¬
rency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P 0.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept , P O Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent'
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House. 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Ham, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch-,
handlung, Industnehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien BANGLADESH Bangladesh Books International
Ltd , Ittefaq Building, 1, R K Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N V Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co Ltd , 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S N.T.L , Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display), Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1 For Slovakia only Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P O Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48 - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G D R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps
only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830 Other
publications. S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Ange¬
rhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germenng/Munchen.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P.O. Box 195,
Accra, Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P O. Box 7869, Accra: The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón, P O. Box 1,
Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HKI Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Konyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V, A K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI ICELAND. Snaebjorn
JonsSon & Co., H F , Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. - INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13, 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2, 8-3/7 Asaf All Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 Sub-Depots Oxford Book Et Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scmdia House, New Delhi,
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardmata III, Jakarta, Gramedla Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta, Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat IRAN Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co , 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P 0 Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat Comm for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd ,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12 ISRAEL. ABC
Bookstore Ltd , P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
- JAMAICA, Sangster's Book Stores Ltd , P O Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc ,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-
ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P O
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942. Kuwait - LESOTHO
Mazenod Book Centre, P O Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. - LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd , P O Box
286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P 0 Box 34-35, Tripoli
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
Jl 222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. MALTA Sapienzas, 26
Republic Street, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis - MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo - NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koener" Dutch edition only Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75^ Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications N V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9,
The Hague - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V , P O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao NA.- NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P O. Box 5344. Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P 0. Box 1721 Christchurch, Alma Street, P O
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin,
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife, The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P 0 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos.The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana. NORWAY. All publications; Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only A S Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P O Box No. 729, Lahore 3 - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw, Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livrana
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd , Kingsgate House, P O. Box 131, Mahé. -
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19 - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio SOUTH AFRICA. All publications Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only Central News agency, P O Box 1033, Johannesburg
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVTI Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata POB 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN All publications A/B C E Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel,' Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CC P 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop,
POB 9030 Dar-es-Salaam - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co
Ltd , 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok, Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St, Clair, Trinidad, W I -
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P O. Box 145,
Kampala - UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S E I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New' York, N Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade, Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Gleaming treasures
from a crossroads of history
These bejewelled gold ornaments are just a few specimens of thousands recently unear
ihed in an ancient piincely necropolis neat Shibarghan, northern Afghanistan. Through
their fascinating mixture of styles and cultural influences, the treasures are yielding vital
information about the shadowy history of a society that stood at the crossroads of East
and West 2,000 years ago (see story page 29). Clockwise from right: scabbard adorned
with cavorting beasts; buckle featuring the winged goddess of Victory, a couple
(perhaps Dionysus and Ariadne) riding a fabulous beast, and a kneeling satyr; braided
gold belt; golden bowl, once a dead ruler's headrest; coronet of gold trees and perching
birds, encrusted with pearls and turquoise.
Photos Viktor I Sarianidi, Moscow Soviet Afghan Archaeological Expedition
A
WSBSvÊ
'
0, .VtB 1
«H pj
vBtiELFfjEtE/im
Kp3Pl
m
i^rà^ÊmFÊ^Ê
m
mm
0i
ma
ai?^1*
á^^S?
te>r*
]]>
</page>
</document>
