<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="060488eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
June 1965 (18th year) U.K.: 1/6 stg. - Canada: 30 cents- France: 1 F
MY FIRST STEPS
IN SPACE by Aleksei Leoriov
'
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
MONUMENTAL OBSERVATORY
© Werner Bischof - Magnum
Sixty miles southwest of Delhi stands the observatory of Jaipur, a remarkable monument to ancient astronomy.
It was built in 1728 by Jai Singh II, Maharajah of Jaipur, a skilled mathematician, astronomer and architect.
Photo shows part of a giant sundial-type instrument in stone in this open-air observatory (see page 18).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JUNE 1965 - 18TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO,
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7B.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg. ; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2 years : 27/-stg. ; 1 8 F. Single copies 1 /6-stg. ;
30 cents ; 1 F.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Page
12
18
22
27
32
34
MY FIRST STEPS IN SPACE
A first-hand account written specially for The Unesco Courier
By Aleksei Leonov
THE GREAT ASIAN HIGHWAY
A striking example of international co-operation
By M. S. Ahmad
THE STONES OF JAIPUR
SPEAK OF ASTRONOMY
Monumental observatories of an Indian Prince
MOHENJO-DARO
A 5,000-year old heritage threatened with destruction
By H. J. Plenderleith, C. Voute and Th. de Beaufort
THE CITY OF THE DEAD
The mystery of Mohenjo-daro
By Marcel Brion
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris T, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence shouldbe addressedto the Editor-ln-Chiet.
CO
(J
5
CD
Cover photo
For the first time a man walks in outer
space. This first step into another
world is that of the Soviet astronaut
Aleksei Leonov ; it marks an historic
moment in the conquest of space.
The photograph was taken by a camera
which Leonov had just attached
to the space capsule and which
filmed his extraordinary adventure.
© APN
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
MY
FIRST STEPS
IN
SPACE
by Aleksei Leonov
arch 18, 1965 is a date that will be remembered in the
history of astronautics. On that day, Aleksei Leonov
became the first man to leave a space vehicle and walk
about in outer space. The thrill he experienced as he emer¬
ged from the capsule, hurtling around the earth at more
than 28,000 kilometres an hour, and what he saw during
his extraordinary adventure Is recounted to us in this article
specially written for the readers of The Unesco Courier by
Aleksei Leonov himself. Photographs are reproduced from
the colour film taken by Leonov and his colleague aboard
4 Voskhod II, P. Belyayev. This film was given its world pre¬
mière at Unesco House, Paris, on IVIay 6, 1965.
Photos © APN
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The outer door of Voskhod ll's air lock opens into cosmic space. Aleksei Leonov emerges slowly into
the blinding sunlight. Far behind the astronaut (right of photo), the curving edge of the sunlit earth.
O NLY the unforgettable moments at
the take-off and the recollection of
the long months of flight training forced me to believe
in the reality of the scene that unfolded before my
eyes as I viewed the spaceship while i floated through
the vacuum of space. Voskhod II sailed with an awe¬
some majesty, its antennae like the whiskers of
some monster probing the emptiness of space. Its
portholes looked like enormous eyes contemplating
fixedly my each and every movement. The lenses of
the television and photographic cameras were trained
on me.
Before me blackness: an inky-black sky studded with
stars that glowed but did not twinkle; they seemed immo¬
bilized. Nor did the sun look the same as when seen from
Earth. It had no aureole or corona; it resembled a huge
incandescent disc that seemed embedded in the velvet
black of the sky of outer space. Space itself appeared as
a bottomless pit. It will never be possible to see the
cosmos the same way on Earth.
Below me our sky-blue planet drifted by. It did not look
round but completely flat, like a giant physical map. Only
the curvature of the horizon showed that it was round.
Everything about me looked like a scene from a science
fiction film. The only thing missing was the electronic
music. This was the fantastic setting I was to work in.
Interplanetary exploration has been developing at an
unprecedented tempo. Four years ago my countryman
Yuri Gagarin, spent only 108 minutes in space. Today
spacecraft make flights lasting several days. Nor is space
flight still restricted to the cosmonaut-pilot. Last October,
Voskhod I carried aboard not only the cosmonaut Vladimir
Komarov but also a scientist, Konstantin Feoktistov, and a p
doctor, Boris Yegorov. 3
In the future spacecraft will be spending more and more
time in orbit, and there will probably be several in flight
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
!l
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Freed from the effects of gravity,
Leonov floats In the silent immensity
of outer space, protected from Its
deadly vacuum by his pressure suit.
Here there Is no top and no bottom.
The earth with Its curving silhouette
passes before him. It Is partly cover¬
ed with clouds, but during a few minu¬
tes Leonov saw the Mediterranean,
the Volga River, the Ural mountains
and several large Siberian rivers.
Photos © APN.
MY FIRST STEPS IN SPACE (Cont'd)
I unstrapped and floated into the airlock
at the same time. The number of crew members will also
increase. Scientists are already studying the problem of
setting up permanent stations in orbit. Man will naturally
want to explore other planets.
But if this is to be possible man must learn to assemble
heavy spacecraft directly in orbit. He must be able to pick
up the crews of orbiting space laboratories, move from
one ship to another in cases of emergency or simply main¬
tain contact with fellow human beings during interplanetary
flight. For this to be feasible, man had to learn to leave
his spacecraft and find the best way of doing so. But the
question arose was it possible for man to leave a space
vessel and survive? If so, could he work in space? Could
he, for example, carry out the assembly work that is
indispensable to the rendezvous of spacecraft?
This is what the great Russian scientist, Konstantin
Tsiolkovsky saw as an answer to these questions in 1926.
He wrote:
"It is easier to perform work of every kind in space
than on earth. In the first place, there is no limit to the size
of the projects that can be undertaken, and the most frail
materials can be used since they are not endangered by
stress and strain since space is weightless. In the second
place, man is able to work here in any position that he
desires provided that his feet or another part of his body
are firmly held in place. There are neither vertical nor hori¬
zontal planes; there is no top or bottom. One cannot fall.
"No object not even the heaviest can crush a man at
work, for it falls nowhere even when unsupported. No
member of the body, regardless of its size, is subject to the
pressure of another member. Objects displace themselves
at the slightest touch irrespective of their mass and dimen¬
sions. All that is needed is a single impulse proportional to
the mass and to the square of its velocity: then the bodies
are in perpetual movement."
This was no more than a theory, though an ingenious
one, based on his knowledge of the Laws of Mechanics,
but it had still not been confirmed in practice.
As a result of the flights of artificial satellites and
manned-spacecraft, scientists had theoretically defined all
of the problems connected with man's exit into space.
They were familiar with the ambient conditions in space:
the intensity of radiation, the effect of weightlessness.
But no one knew exactly how man would react to weight¬
lessness in the open space of the cosmos.
Pavel Belyayev, commander of Voskhod II, and I had the
good fortune of being chosen for the space flight of
March 18 that aimed to give the first answers to these
questions and to verify in practice the hypotheses and cal¬
culations of the scientists. We believe that we have
resolved these problems and justified the hopes that had
been placed in our flight.
This is what happened.
Two minutes after the ship had been placed in orbit we
began making preparations for my sally into space. There
was no time to waste admiring the wonders and beauties
of space; this would have to wait until our mission had been
accomplished.
During flight training on Earth we had tested time and
again the air lock controls and the systems regulating
man's body condition as he steps forth into space; and
we rehearsed the exit and re-entry procedures. We
had tested them under conditions simulating those with
which we would be actually confronted. In spite of this,
as the ship went throught its first revolution we rehearsed
the operation once again.
When we were over Kamchatka Commander Belyayev
started preparing me for my exit from the craft. He helped
me to put on the cylinder containing my air supply. I
checked the connexions linking my breathing mixture to
the spacesuit. Belyayev opened the inner door of the
air lock. Together we fastened to my spacesuit the tether-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
MY FIRST STEPS IN SPACE (Cont'd)
I found the spaceship bearing down on me
cable that would keep me attached to the ship. Built into
the tether was the telephone cable that would be my link
with the ship and Earth. I unstrapped myself from the
seat and floated into the chamber of the air lock.
I gave a hand signal to the commander. The inner door
closed behind me. Belyayev at once began to empty
the chamber of air in order to equalize the pressure with
that outside the ship. I could feel this happening from
the way my spacesuit became inflated. Suddenly the outer
door of the air lock opened out into space. A blinding
burst of sunlight poured into the chamber of the air lock.
So brilliant was the light it seemed as if someone were
welding close by with an acetylene torch.
I
8
MADE my way forward in the lock toward the
exit and poked a bit of my head out. We
were over the Mediterranean. I was in a hurry to leave
the lock, get a look at the Earth from space and see the
ship, but Commander Belyayev restrained me: the time¬
table had to be followed precisely.
Before we were over Simferopol, Belyayev signalled me
to cast off. In my impatience to get out, I pushed off too
vigorously from the edge of the air lock and left the ship
like a cork popping from a bottle. Below directly under¬
neath me was Kerch. I saw the Black Sea, the blue
swath of the bay near Novorossisk, the cloud-capped
mountains of the Caucasus. Visibility was magnificent. I've
done a great deal of flying in my time, more than 550 hours,
but I find that you see everything better from space, the
relief is much sharper than from an aeroplane. I distinctly
saw, for example, that the region of Sochi was enjoying
fine, sunny weather.
I found myself spinning and was powerless to control
it. I had had the same experience when Belyayev and I
were practising in the aeroplane-laboratory the technique
of exit and re-entry under conditions of weightlessness.
So I did nothing about it. I merely waited for the kinking
of the tether to slow down the rotations. And, as I ex¬
pected, I noticed that the angular momentum was decreas¬
ing little by little. I was, of course, still turning on a
transversal axis. I could have checked this by grabbing
hold of the tether, but I preferred to keep on rolling
because this enabled me to see better.
BELOW the majestic green mountain ranges of
the south of our country floated by. I reco¬
gnized the Volga; then I saw the Urals, and the mighty
Siberian rivers, the Ob and the Yenisei.
I removed the lens guard of the motion picture camera
that was to photograph all of my movements in the vacuum
of space. It was mounted on a special stand near the
edge of the air lock. A moment later, to pull myself for¬
ward, I tugged rather vigorously at the tether and found
the ship bearing down on me. I warded it off with my
hands, otherwise I might have knocked my pressurized
helmet against its hull. By stretching out my arms I was
able to break the impact. It is clear that once man has
adapted himself to the extraordinary conditions in space,
he can move about in a sufficiently co-ordinated and pre¬
cise manner.
While I was drifting in space, I was always in telephonic
contact with Pavel Belyayev and with Earth. I spoke to
Yuri Gagarin who was on duty in the control room of the
spaceport. I heard Radio Moscow announce the launching
of our craft.
While over the Yenisei, Commander Belyayev gave me
the signal to re-enter the ship. I was feeling wonderful,
in excellent spirits, and was in no hurry to leave open space.
So I pushed off once again from the edge of the air
lock as I wanted to find out what produced the angu¬
lar movements immediately following the push-off. It turned
out that these movements were caused by even the slight¬
est displacement in the angle of the force of thrust in
relation to the axis of the space capsule.
I then carried out Commander Belyayev's order and
began to approach the ship. On the way I picked up the
camera from its support.
I wanted to enter the air lock directly, but this proved
anything but easy. The inflated spacesuit constricted, my
movements. I had to use all of my strength to re-enter
the air lock. But before long I was back in the cabin
alongside Pavel Belyayev.
.0 ended the experiment in which a man climb-
'ed out of a capsule into space. I had spent
twenty minutes outside the cabin. During this time, Vos¬
khod II had gone far from the Mediterranean over which
we has been travelling when I first went into the air lock;
we were now approaching the Pacific Ocean.
Was I afraid?
I am often asked whether I was frightened when I left
the ship to enter space, whether I thought my life was in
danger. Each time my reply is the same: "No, I was
not." Now, why waán't I afraid?
In orbit my spacesuit was the only thing protecting me
from the sun's rays, from radiation, sudden variations in
temperature, and other phenomena no less dangerous to
man. But I had faith in the spacesuit and in all of the
equipment on board the capsule. My faith was born in the
long months of training that preceded the flight.
An integral feature of the Soviet school for space
flight training is that the cosmonauts participate directly in
the development and testing of all the new systems and
equipment that have been produced for their mission. They
have no secrets for us; we know exactly how they will
function in space.
Both Belyayev and I, for example were in on the design¬
ing of our particular ship, the air lock and its controls,
the spacesuit and all the new gadgetry and equipment that
our spaceship had and Voskhod I didn't. All these pro¬
jects were approved in our presence. We tested the
equipment ourselves, not wishing to rely exclusively on
professional testers. After the tests we suggested modi¬
fications which we felt were essential, and the constructors
and engineers never failed to take account of our recom¬
mendations.
It was also reassurinq to know that if anything went
wrong during my flight in space Commander Belyayev, who
is also one of my best friends, could always come to my
assistance. If necessary, he could even have de-pressur-
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
warn
© APN
COSMONAUT IN A HALO
OF DARKNESS AND SUNLIGHT
This image of Leonov spinning
in space has a dramatic, unreal
quality. Brilliant rays of sunlight
piercing the velvet black of the
sky in outer space have struck
the camera lens and trace
strange, ghostly patterns of light.
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
MY FIRST STEPS IN SPACE (Cont'd)
Next goal : a rendezvous in outer space
10
¡zed the ship, abandoned it and, with the aid of a spare
tether, himself climbed into space.
Under these circumstances why should I have been
afraid? Quite honestly, if I had been afraid, I don't think
I'd have gone aboard the space capsule.
At the spaceport, after returning from our landing spot,
the journalists asked me, "Which was your greatest moment
of joy, when you came out of the capsule or when you
climbed back into it?" I replied that my greatest thrill had
been leaving the spaceship. And I wasn't being boastful.
O UR flight confirmed all the hypotheses of the
scientists. It is really possible for man to leave
a space vehicle and move about outside. More than that,
he can also work in space successfully. Naturally he must
learn to co-ordinate his movements and train himself to
act under the unusual conditions of weightlessness. But
this is not a terribly complex problem.
I think that scientists and engineers can now give serious
thought to the problem of linking up spacecraft, of
assembling heavy spacecraft in orbit for interplanetary
travel, and of setting up permanent space station labora¬
tories.
The air lock system was also given a thorough testing
during the flight. In my view scientists have found the
method highly satisfactory for exiting into space. What
advantage does this air lock system have over the complete
depressurization of the ship?
In the future, exiting into space will be required for
transfering from one ship to another or to allow a rendez¬
vous between . spacecraft or to carry out repairs while in
orbit. In all likelihood, this will be the work or selected
cosmonauts and not of all members of the crew. For it
would make little sense for all crew members to wear
spacesuits as, in fact, they would be compelled to do if the
cabin were depressurized.
It would be far more logical for the one or two cosmo¬
nauts who are going to perform the work to don spacesuits,
then to leave by the air lock and seal the inner door. This
would enable the other crew members to carry on their
own activities inside a cabin where normal conditions pre¬
vail, as was done, for example, by the crew members of
Voskhod I Komarov, Feoktistov and Yegorov.
Let us consider another problem: the rendezvous of
spaceships. It is extremely unlikely that spacecraft will
succeed in linking up porthole to porthole. What probably
will be required is a linking chamber similar to the flexible
"concertina" device which joins up the carriages of passen¬
ger trains.
Our flight demonstrated that cabin pressure can be main-
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
tained if an air lock is used for exit and return.
Commander Belyayev verified that there was no variation
in the pressure of the cabin either when I left or when
I returned. Thus at no time was it necessary for him to put
on a spacesuit. This is most important; the spacesuit is
anything but ideal for working inside the cabin.
As for working conditions in the cabin, they are in no
way different from those in an .ordinary room. Through¬
out the flight of Voskhod II, the cabin temperature never
exceeded 18 degrees centigrade. At no time did we
perspire excessively which would have resulted in dehydra¬
tion of the body. If we did perspire occasionally, it was
simply the result of physical effort or over-exertion.
When we weighed in after the flight, we had both lost
500 grammes Qust over one pound); neither of us attributes
this loss to our sojourn in space. In all probability it was
due to the fact that prior to the flight we were weighed in
the morning, and after our return, in the evening. In other
words our flight was normal in every respect.
Through The 'Unesco Courler, I should like to thank all
who have congratulated Belyayev and myself on the mission
that it was our privilege to carry out.
SOVIET ASTRONAUTS VISIT UNESCO
On May 11, two Soviet astronauts, Valentina Tereshkova
and . her husband, Andrian Nikolayev, were received at
Unesco House by the Executive Board of Unesco, meeting in
Paris. After the chairman of the Executive Board, Mr Moham¬
med El Fasi, and the Director-General of Unesco, Mr René
Maheu, had welcomed the astronauts, Professor Norair Sissa-
kian, chairman of the 13th session of the Unesco General
Conference, spoke briefly on Man in Space. Valentina
Tereshkova became the world's first spacewoman on
June 16, 1963. She remained in space for 70 hours, her
capsule orbiting the earth . simultaneously with that of the
Soviet astronaut, Valeri Bykovsky. The previous year, on
August 11, 1962, Valentina Tereshkova's husband made a
space flight of 64 orbits aboard Vostok III.
Leonov had the Impression of taking
part In a science-fiction film. Left, In
this close-up shot, the hand of the
astronaut, outlined against the mass
of the earth, has just removed the
lens guard from the automatic camera
mounted on the space capsule. Right,
Leonov returns to the spaceship.
Here he enters the air lock and in a
moment will close its outer door.
When the commander of Voskhod II
has repressurized the air lock, Leonov
will open the inner door to the cabin.
Photos ©APN
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
THE GREAT ASIAN HIGHWAY
by M. S. Ahmad
ir *
I
A great highway network, often following the caravan routes ol
antiquity, will soon span the continent of Asia from Turkey and
Iraq to Singapore and Saigon. Known as the Great Asian
Highway it is being built by the international co-operation of
some 20 countries working within the framework of the United
Nations. When completed it will offer the motorist an opportunity
for new contact with the people of Asia by driving across
35,000 miles (55,000 kms.) of international roads.
:.«
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Left, motor-lorries and far¬
mers 'carts share this asphal¬
ted section of the Asian
Highway crossing Afgha¬
nistan, but in a mountain
pass close to the Pakistan
frontier (right) a signpost
directs motor-traffic one
way and sends camels and
horses on a separate track.
Photos © Paul Almasy. Paris
HE story of man can be told in the language
of travel: travel of people and travel of goods.
In Asia, the movements of peoples and the development
of caravan routes have been decisively influenced by geo¬
graphy. To penetrate the Himalayan ranges to the north
of India the pioneers of the trade routes naturally sought
out the mountain passes (most of which are still in use)
and followed the rivers. Whenever possible, caravan routes
"were preferred to the sea, where travellers faced greater
hazards both from piracy and storms.
Around 300 B.C. the ancient route that connected Hama-
dan (ancient Ecbatan) in Iran with the then rich valleys
of Mekran and of Luni in India passed through towns in
which one of the very early civilizations that of Mohenjo-
daro and others existed (see page 27).
The great silk route for example started from Sian
(capital of the Hans of China) passed through Turkestan,
Rhea and Hamadan, and proceeded to Europe either
through Asia Minor or with a slight detour through Baghdad,
Mosul and Antioch. From this city a branch route led to
Egypt through Damascus.
The account of world travellers such as Ibn-i-Hakhal,
Fa Hien, I Tsiang, Chang Kun, Ibn-i-Batuta and Marco
Polo give an idea of the then existing caravan routes and
their conditions.
Chang Kun's mission to Yu-Chi was carried out during
138-125 B.C. Fa Hien, the Chinese Buddhist pilgrim who tra¬
velled in India during 399-414 A.D., arrived by the land route
but returned to China via Java. Yuan-Chwang travelled
extensively early in the seventh century A.D., entering
India from the north west through Peshawar.
The Romans in the period 266 B.C.- 476 A.D. built roads
which extended over three continents. During the By¬
zantine Empire caravan trade with the East flourished.
The Imperial power at Baghdad gave the Moslem world
good roadways along which lay serais or inns with pro
vision made for relays of mounts for traders, pilgrims and
official couriers.
These roads constituted the great trade routes between
the East and the West. Through these international land
communications the Asian countries established contacts
with the outside world for trade and commerce. Without
these roads progress of civilization in the regions would
have taken much longer.
Unfortunately, because of political developments and
the shifting of natural frontiers, many of the land routes
in Asia fell into disuse. Although attempts were made from
time to time to restore and develop these communications
not much was achieved because efforts were not co¬
ordinated and resources were inadequate.
Europe and America meanwhile continued to develop
their international highways. The Pan American Highway,
an 18,000 mile (28,960 km) network from Alaska to the
tip of South America, is a unique example of an inter¬
national highway in the true sense of the word.
During the last decade road traffic throughout the world
has increased at a breath-taking speed. Much attention
is now being paid in all countries to the improvement of
highways and methods of construction. Europe and Ame¬
rica have made great progress in the development of their
highways. Many international highways have been built
and many studies made to achieve uniformity in road
design and to ease customs formalities. Progress in Asian
countries has been much slower.
However, governments are aware of the need to improve
transport systems, and fully appreciate the important role
international highways could play for economic, social and
cultural development. This goes particularly for land¬
locked countries such as Afghanistan, Laos and Nepal.
The fact remains that Asia had no international highways
to speak of.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
TURKEY
THE ASIAN HIGHWAY NETWORK
- Road at present not motorable
Priority route.
Distance in kilometres.
IRAQ
Other routes.
SAUDI ARABIA
NORTH
VIET-NAM
Priority route A-1 of the Asian Highway, 6,600 miles (10,590 km) long,
will run from Bazargan (on the Turkish frontier) to Saigon (Republic of Viet¬
nam) passing through Teheran (Iran), Kabul (Afghanistan), Islamabad (West
Pakistan), Delhi (India), Calcutta (India), Dacca (East Pakistan), Golaghat
(India), Mandalay (Burma), Aranyapradet (Thailand) and Phnom Penh (Cam¬
bodia).
Priority route A-2, 7,700 miles (12,350 km) long, will run from the Iraqi
border to the eastern extremity of Java (Indonesia) passing through Teheran
and Isfahan (Iran), Rohri and Lahore (West Pakistan), Delhi (India), Kathmandu
(Nepal), Dacca (East Pakistan), Rangoon (Burma), Bangkok (Thailand), Kuala
Lumpur (Malaysia). A ferry boat will link Singapore (Malaysia) with Djakarta
(Indonesia).
The network will be completed by link roads. The countries concerned
have given high priority to developing these roads which will join up the
sections of the Asian Highway.
The boundaries and names on this map
do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by the United Nations.
UNITED NATIONS MAP
14
THE ASIAN HIGHWAY (Cont'd)
The idea of linking Asian countries through a network
of international highways was born in November, 1958 at
the Highways Sub-Committee of ECAFE, the United Nations
Economic Commission for Asia and the Far East. The
proposal was to establish an international highway system
linking existing main roads all the way between Viet-Nam
and Iran, and then bringing them up to a minimum stan¬
dard. For this purpose five standards were laid
down, and the countries were required to conform to the
lowest, this minimum standard to be raised as and when
traffic had increased sufficiently and funds became available.
The Asian Highway will be reminiscent of the ancient
caravan routes between Europe, the Middle East and Africa,
and will produce great economic advantages. It will pro¬
vide movement within each country and facilitate overland
international trade; many of Asia's traditional commodities
such as rice, rubber, cotton, timber, fuel and minerals,
which now move between countries by circuitous sea routes,
could be moved more economically by road and be inde¬
pendent of rising ocean freight rates.
Besides developing trade, the Asian Highway will sti¬
mulate tourist traffic within Asia and enable lower income
groups to enjoy the wonders of this great continent. Tour¬
ists will be able to journey by road to places of historical
interest and visit the many pilgrim centres, now almost
inaccessible except at very great expense. The opening
of the international road will be welcomed by millions of
Buddhist, Hindu and Moslem pilgrims.
The Asian Highway will also open new vistas for the
hundreds of thousands of small villages in the densely
populated areas of the region.
Road transport will continue to provide a major means
of inland transport. It provides direct and indirect em¬
ployment and thus contributes to economic and social
advance. When eventually completed, the Asian Highway
system will serve an area of about 2è million square
miles (6i million sq. kms) with a population of over
700 million people.
Gaps forming a very small percentage of the total length
in the Asian Highway will have to be filled, major bridges
built and many routes upgraded. That will cost money.
It may be asked: "Will the immediate gain justify the heavy
Investment?"
Well, to begin with, it is not intended to raise all the
roads of the Asian Highway to a high International stan¬
dard immediately, and a fairly modest standard has been
laid down as the initial minimum. Governments, of course,
will consider carefully whether long-range advantages out¬
weigh foreseeable returns. In the case of land-locked
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
"^L-> I 'S.
/-^
mh
-
>-
¿**
&?£
JETir
~-3--
United Nations
THE ASIAN HIGHWAY (Cont'd)
HIGHEST TUNNEL. The highest road tunnel
in the world is now being completed in Afgha¬
nistan. It will carry the Asian Highway
through the Hindu Kush range at an altitude
of 10,000 feet (3,200 m.). Left, construction
of the approach road to the Salang tunnel,
8,200 feet (2,750 m.) long, that will shorten
the existing road by 120 miles (190 km.).
V
AT
LONGEST BRIDGE. Bridge completely span¬
ning the horizon is Asia's longest 10,000
feet (3,300 m.). It has been built across the
River Sone in India about 375 miles (600 km.)
from Calcutta. Seven major bridges will be
built for the Asian Highway in East Pakistan.
A road system for a whole continent
16
Afghanistan, Laos and Nepal, the terrain and economic
conditions are such that only an international highway sys¬
tem can provide cheap and adequate access to neighbouring
countries and the ports for external trade.
What progress has been made since 1959? The existing
routes in all the countries to be included in the Asian
Highway system have been agreed upon together with
construction standards. These provide for a staged
development, with standards being improved as traffic
increases.
A highway traffic code governing the conduct of inter¬
national traffic has been drafted and a uniform system of
road signs agreed upon. To concert national efforts, a
co-ordinating body composed of representatives from
each of the countries involved has been established under
ECAFE.
The sub-standard sections of the Asian Highway in Iran,
Afghanistan, Pakistan, India and Indonesia have been
surveyed by United Nations teams, and the data already
collected have formed the basis for an estimate of costs
for the sections covered.
An application has been submitted to the United Nations
Special Fund to provide the funds for an economic and
engineering survey of existing gaps in the Highway, includ¬
ing studies of economic and engineering feasibilities in
Afghanistan, Iran and Pakistan. The Special Fund has
engaged a firm of consulting engineers to assess the request
for pre-investment surveys, and its report has been sub¬
mitted.
What progress has been made in the construction and
improvement of the priority routes of the Asian Highway?
It is gratifying to note the enthusiasm and zeal with which
governments are trying to implement the project. The
roads of the Asian Highway have to a large extent been
included in national high priority road programmes. For
instance, thanks to extensive road repairs and the rebuilding
of bridges, it is now possible to motor from Bangkok to
Siemreap (Angkor Wat) in Cambodia in a day.
'ONSIDERABLE road work is also in progress
'in other parts of the road between Choomporn
and Panga in Thailand, and it will then be possible to drive
through from Thailand to Malaysia. In the north, a bridge
has been jointly financed and built over the Messai river on
the Thai-Burnese frontier.
In India, the work on the missing links between Silchar
and Imphal is progressing satisfactorily.
In East Pakistan, intensive road construction activities,
particularly on routes included in the international network,
are under way.
In Nepal, road building activities are being vigorously
pushed through and the standard of the road between
Kathmandu and Rexol is being raised. Surveys are being
conducted for building a road between Tanakpur and Gal-
galia, towards Sivok.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
' 'í
v V".v.ví:.^v -;:- . EBfe
United Nations
fill
2#
SMARTEST VEHICLE. Colourfully-
decorated motor lorries, like this one
in Pakistan, are a common sight on the
roads of Asia. The custom of smarten¬
ing up carriages with ornate designs
and symbols also exists in the Middle
East, and is a centuries-old practice
in Sicily as regards ordinary carts. Paul Almasy, Paris
In West Pakistan, the road improvement programme is
being resolutely pursued.
In Afghanistan, the road between Kabul and Torkham
(Afghanistan-Pakistan frontier) has been asphalted; the road
between Kabul and Kandahar on the priority route is
being built as an asphalt road; while the road between
Kandahar and Herat is being concreted.
In Iran, the road section from Bazargan to Takestan
via Tabriz and Zanjan is under construction. It is to be
completed as a first-class paved road within the next two
years and will then link on to the roads in Turkey and
Europe, joining the Teheran-Sari section. A road from
Sari to Shahpassand is under construction and will be
completed within the next two years. The section between
Shahpassand and Ghouchan is already a good gravel road.
From Ghouchan to Toos, the road is fair, and will be raised
to a higher standard within the next few years. From Toos
to Sang-Bast via Mashad there is a good black-top road,
but the last section from Sang-Bast to Taibat is in poor
condition. This is to be improved within the next three
years.
Another priority route runs from the Iran-Iraq frontier
at Khosravi to the Middle Eastern Highway network at
Mijaveh via Isfahan, Kerman and Zahidan. The section
between Khosravi to Hamadan has been recently built
as a first-class paved road; from Hamadan to Saveh, the
road te a good gravel one; from Saveh to Teheran runs
a firs.t-class paved road and the road from Teheran to
Isfahan via Ghom will shortly be complete'd as a good
tarmac road. The road from Isfahan to Kerman via Yazd
is to be improved to a good gravel road within the next
four years. The remaining section from Kerman to
Mirjaveh (Iran-Pakistan frontier) is to be surveyed, with
an economic appraisal of the project.
However, even though all this progress has been commen¬
dable, much work remains to be done owing to technical
and financial difficulties, and some gaps have still to be
filled. The total length of the missing links in the priority
route A-1 (Turkey to Viet Nam) is approximately 260 miles
(419 kms.) and in A-2 (Iraq to Singapore and Indonesia)
870 miles (1,397 kms.) while sections in A-1 and A-2 requir¬
ing improvement come to 5,470 miles (8.790 kms.). These
are small gaps, considering that the total length of A-1
route is 6,600 miles (10,590 kms.) and that of A-2 route
7.700 miles ( 12,350 kms.).
The Asian Highway project is undoubtedly a grand
concept, and it has created great expectations as its mat¬
erialization will be of great help in building an edifice of
human brotherhood and peace, besides serving economic,
social and cultural purposes. Four years is not a long
period for the fulfilment of this international road network,
and substantial strides have already been made. Never¬
theless, this progress will have to be sustained and
everything done to hasten the day when streams of cars
and trucks will flow along the roads linking the various
capitals, trading posts, cultural and historical sites of the
regions.
It will be some years before the Asian Highway is
finished, but the plans have to be made now and work taken
in hand according to the economic requirements and
resources of each country.
17
M.S. AHMAD is chief of the Transport and Communications Divi¬
sion of the U.N. Economic Commission for Asia and the Far East.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Structures that seem close to space-age architecture are astronomical sight¬
ing devices built in the 18th century in the courtyard of the palace
of Prince Jai Singh at Jaipur, 60 miles from Delhi, in India. Himself a
mathematician, astronomer and architect, the prince built this open-air
observatory when he constructed a handsome capital at Jaipur in 1728.
The stones of Jaipur
speak of astronomy
Photos Ç Paul Almasy, Paris
Above, in background and topped by a
cupola over an observer's post rises the
Samrat Yantra, "the emperor of instruments."
Over 90 feet tall it is the largest of all the
sundial-type instruments at the Jaipur obser¬
vatory. In foreground (and in photo left)
are miniature versions of the Samrat Yantra.
The observatory has a complex of twelve
such devices named the Rasi Valya, each
structure being aligned on a zodiacal sign.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
I N the courtyard of the splendid 18th century palace
at Jaipur, sixty miles from Delhi, in India, stands a
complex of huge yet graceful stone structures. They are as old
as the palace itself, but with their clean, functional lines they look
like ultra-modern examples of space-age architecture.
If these structures have a functional kind of beauty it is because
they are in fact scientific instruments in stone, the equipment of
an observatory built by a powerful Moslem ruler, Prince Jai
Singh II, in the new capital he raised at Jaipur in 1728.
A skilled mathematician, astronomer and architect, the prince
conceived a single grandiose project that englobed his interest in
all these fields. He ordered the construction of a network of
astronomical observatories in the Amber Territory which he ruled
under the Moghul Emperor Mohammed Shah. Mobilizing skills
and resources with a lavishness that recalls some of the building
feats of the Egyptian Pharoahs, Jai Singh raised five open-air
observatories in the largest towns of his kingdom: Jaipur, Delhi,
Mathura, Benares and Ujjain.
© Lucien Hervé, Paris
The contributions of Moslem science in mathematics, medicine,
physics and chemistry to the knowledge of the medieval world are
well known. Among the most important in astronomy were its
splendid observatories and its outstanding versions of such astro¬
nomical instruments as the astrolabe and sextant. Moslem astro¬
nomers and mathematicians were able to calculate precisely the
latitude and longtitude of their cities at a time when this achieve¬
ment was almost unheard of in Western Europe.
Jai Singh II followed in this tradition. In building his observa¬
tories he had as predecessors the observatory of al-Mamun, caliph
of Baghdad in the 9th century, the medieval Moslem observatories
at Cairo and Maragha and the outstanding one built by Ulugh-Beg,
a grandson of Tamerlane, at Samarkand in the 15th century.
Jai Singh was, in fact, the last of a series of Moslem rulers
who down the centuries had built observatories and drawn up
astronomical tables on which to base and maintain accurate calen¬
dars. For in the ancient world the promulgation of a calendar was
CONT'D ON PAGE 21
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
As the powerful ruler of
the Amber territory. Jai
Singh ordered five observa¬
tories to be built in the
cities of Jaipur, Delhi, Ma-
thura, Benares and Ujjain
so that the observations and
calculations of his astrono¬
mers and mathematicians
could be verified and cor¬
roborated. Right, huge yet
ethereal structures preserved
in the Delhi observatory.
Lucien Hervé, Paris
Above, right and below, three giant
instruments in stone at Jaipur.
Above, stairway leading to obser¬
ver's post at top of Samrat Yantra
structure which is oriented in a
north-south direction to point at
the Pole Star. Right, another
smaller observation tower built by
Prince Jai Singh casts its graceful
reflection in a lake in the palace
grounds. Below, part of one of
the large hemispherical pits at the
observatory. Its graduated marble
surface acts as a bowl sundial.
Black patterns in the bowl are
cutouts through which observers
behind the shell sighted the stars.
Photos © Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Paul Almasy, Paris
THE STONES OF JAIPUR SPEAK OF ASTRONOMY (Cont'd)
not only an important practical need; it was a mark of sovereignty,
and also had a religious significance.
The observatory built by Jal Singh at Jaipur was primarily for
this purpose and his aim in constructing a network of similar
centres spanning his territory was to allow verification and corro¬
boration of the observations and calculations made by his mathe¬
maticians and astronomers.
The Jaipur observatory, still in a remarkable state of preserva¬
tion, offers one of the most striking examples of astronomical
architecture. Everything about it, from the large circular observa¬
tion bowls set in the ground to a giant 90 feet high sundial-type
instrument, the Samrat Yantra (Emperor of Instruments) ¡s on a
grandiose scale.
The monumental size of the devices was dictated by the need
for accuracy. No telescopes were used at Jaipur and because of
the limited acuity of the naked eye, instruments equipped with
very large scales were essential.
Like today's giant nuclear accelerators used in physics research
and huge modern radio telescopes, the stone instruments at Jaipur
had also to be large in order to do their job, though for obviously
different reasons.
With his inquiring mind and enthusiasm for astronomy and
mathematics Prince Jai Singh was the last royal Moslem astro¬
nomer in the medieval tradition. His observatory at Jaipur is both
an outstanding monument to and the culmination of all of ancient
and medieval astronomy.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Characters in a system
of writing that was used
fifty centuries ago
the Valley of the In
have come dow
engraved i
Une
1964). Far. right,
found at Mohenjo-daro
and now displayed in
the museum opened on
the site of this ancient
Indus Valley city. The
handful of sculptures,
found in its ruins are
works of original and
graceful beauty, like
this bronze figurine
a young- dancing gir;
Nedeco, Amersfoort, The Netherlands
MOHENJO-DARO
A 5,000-year old heritage
menaced by destruction
by
Harold </. Plenderleith
Caesar Voute
Theodoor de Beaufort
The vast ruins of Mohenjo-daro, an incomparable monument to a great civilization that flour¬
ished in the Indus Valley some 5,000 years ago, are threatened with complete destruction
within the next few decades unless major protective work is undertaken. Last year at the request
of the Pakistan Government, Unesco sent a mission of specialists to make an on-the-spot
22 investigation and to see what could be done to halt the ravages of salt erosion in the ruins.
Here, these specialists describe the dramatic situation at Mohenjo-daro and suggest
techniques for preserving one of the most striking monuments of the dawn of civilization.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Paul Almasy, Paris
OHENJO-DARO in the valley of the Indus,
400 miles up-country from Karachi, is to-day no
more than a complex of ruins in burnt brick covering an
area of some 250 acres (100 hectares). But it provides,
with another such site, Harappa, evidence for the existence
of a great urban civilization an Indus Valley Culture in
the 3rd millennium B.C., antedating the Aryan invasions.
The site was completely buried. We owe its chance dis¬
covery in 1922 to an officer of the Archaeological Depart¬
ment who, when excavating a Buddhist stupa and
monastery, was struck by the prevalence of so much burnt
brick in the area. It was left to Sir John Marshall, then
Director-General of Archaeology, and later to his succes¬
sor In office, Sir Mortimer Wheeler, to excavate, as far as
possible, what turned out to be the remains of a great
city lying beneath and extending far beyond the Buddhist
remains. '
The importance of this monument is unquestioned. The
tragedy lies in the phrase "as far as possible" and the
explanation in the fact that erratic movements of the great
Indus river have caused the site to become eroded In
some places and covered with alluvial deposits in others.
Moreover, the river has a tendency to raise its bed and
consequently the water-table in the adjoining plains. This
process has been aggravated by the irrigation of the fields
and under such conditions satisfactory drainage is impos¬
sible.
Not only has the water-table risen considerably during
the past few years, but there has been a great accumulation
of soluble salts as a result of the very arid climate. These
salts by capillary actions have invested the whole area to
such an extent as to give it the appearance of a covering of
snow. This is a very serious problem as the salts cause
large scale destruction of the brickwork, "eating" it within
a matter of years.
Now in these parts a rainstorm is a rare occurrence, but
it had actually rained on the day preceding our arrival in
January 1964, to the chagrin of the custodians who had
taken pleasure in observing our wonder at their tales of
saline deposits. We were impressed, just the same, by such
of the salt as had survived in odd corners. This was as
nothing, however, to our amazement at the crystallizations
that were seen after a couple of days' sunshine: glassy
CONT'D ON PAGE 25
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE TRIES TO SAVE
A SALT-RIDDLED CITY
Drawings below show the increasingly destructive effects on
Mohenjo-daro of invading mineral salts, and illustrate four
possible ways of saving this vast brick-built monument last
inhabited about three thousand five hundred years ago.
O Salt-impregnated water rises by capilliary action and
erodes the bricks. This underground water could be removed
by pumping or drainage.
Ö Salty water also infiltrates to walls through surrounding
earth and debris. This can be stopped by clearing the area along¬
side the walls.
%) Dust-laden winds carry salts and deposit them on bricks.
Falling rain helps the salts to penetrate the brickwork. Walls
must be cleaned regularly of dust and salts.
Cr Accumulated salts within the bricks erode the walls.
The Pakistan Government is studying was of leaching out the
salts with fresh water.
Eaten away by salts, the
walls of Mohenjo-darg
are gradually crumbling
into dust (above). White
stains are caused where
salts are deposited by
infiltrating waters. Salt
erosion is but one aspect
of a wider world problem,
now being studied by
hydrogeologists and soil
scientists: the invasion
and poisoning by salts of
fertile soils in lands with
arid climates. This threat
raises serious problems
as to choice of irrigation
methods (see Unesco
Courier, December 1962).
Restoration of damaged
walls is facilitated by the
fact that bricks still made
today in the area of Mo¬
henjo-daro (right) have
exactly the same form
and colour as those from
which city was construc¬
ted 5,000 years ago.
Photos © Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
MOHENJO-DARO (Cont'd)
needles a centimetre in length sprouted from shady walls
and, where the ground was rough and exposed to the direct
action of the sun, the salts formed a white cushion like
masses pressing upwards as in a vegetable garden well
stocked with cauliflowersl
What could be done to control this? How could the
water-table be lowered? How could the old buildings be
preserved? What would it all cost? Such were the ques¬
tions to which answers were required, but it was only on
arrival that we learnt that inundations had hindered digging
to the extent that the all-important foundation layers of the
city had never been actually excavated, nor could they be,
as long as the ground remained water-logged.
Faced with this veritable labour of Hercules, we began by
making an assessment of the position and found two contin¬
gencies in our favour. The first was the intimate knowledge
of the ancient city possessed by the superintendent of Anti¬
quities of West Pakistan. We studied his experiments in
protection as by introducing damp-proof courses in stra¬
tegic places and were much interested in the use of mud
bricks to cap the old walls and trap the salt. In him we
should have a staunch ally.
The second consoling feature lay in the fact that Pakistan,
dependent upon the success of her rice crops (for which
not only a plentiful supply of water is essential, but also
an adequate control of the water-logging and salinity prob¬
lems), had accumulated a body of hydrological knowledge
upon which we. could draw in working out a scheme of pre¬
servation for the area.
It was clear that there could be only one practical way of
getting rid of the great bulk of saline material, namely, to
redissolve it and to return it to the Indus by pumping the
liquid into drains or canals. The tube-well is the recognized
type of equipment brought into operation for this purpose.
The fundamental activity was that of preparing a large
contour map of the immediate neighbourhood. Information
was accumulated from this, from a study of various features
on the aerial photographs and in the field, from the analysis
of soils and salts and water samples from which it was
possible to form some definite ideas concerning the sub-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
26
MOHENJO-DARO (Cont'd)
surface geology, and, what was even more vital, concerning
the movements of moisture and salts in the soil and build¬
ings. Only then did it become possible to have views
regarding the adequacy of the existing dykes (bunds) and
to consider the siting of water outlets and the distribution
of pumping equipment.
The lowering of the water-table was possible, but this
was not enough. A second major problem concerned
getting rid of the vast quantity of salt that would be left
behind when the water receded. This could only be done
by redissolving the efflorescences and using the ancient
drainage system which apparently, was very carefully
planned by feeding it from a multiplicity of smaller land
drains and sumps set in strategic places. Even the old dry
wells might have to be brought back into temporary service
during the period of desalinization.
It would be altogether too optimistic to suppose, however,
that, with an annual rainfall amounting to about three inches,
the ground could be cleared in a reasonable time. Finding
the cheapest, most effective method of leaching the bricks
has turned out to be a rather complicated matter. The
first tests concerning the leaching of bricks with fresh
water to determine how rapidly the salts can be extracted
have been carried out.
The next and more complicated series of tests will take
place during 1965-66 to enable specialists to prepare a
more detailed programme of conservation for Mohenjo-daro.
Quite clearly, the cost will depend in the first place
upon how far it is necessary to lower the water-table,
whether only enough to save the visible remains, or, at the
other extreme, to dry the foundations and make complete
excavation possible. The limit will no doubt be decided on
financial grounds but a limit there must be, if only because
an early result of our enquiry has been the unexpected dis¬
covery that the ancient city of Mohenjo-daro covers an
area of at least twice the size that has been supposed.
The Pakistan authorities, recognizing their great respon¬
sibilities, could not have been more co-operative and are
deeply anxious to save as much as possible of this major
monument, this mysterious "City of the Dead", that flour¬
ished 5,000 years ago.
HAROLD J. PLENDERLEITH Is director of the International Centre for
the Study of the Preservation and the Restoration of Cultural Property,
created In Rome by Unesco. THEODOOR DE BEAUFORT Is an
engineer specializing In drainage operations. He Is attached to the
Netherlands Land Development and Reclamation Society (Amersfoort,
The Netherlands). CAESAR VOUTE Is a geologist and a member of
the Consulting Department, Training Centre for Aerial Survey, Nether¬
lands Engineering Company (Delft, The Netherlands).
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The mystery of Mohenjo-daro
CITY OF THE DEAD
by Marcel Brion
of the Académie Française
WHEN the Aryans of antiquity invaded the Valley
of the Indus in the year 2,000 B.C. or there¬
abouts, they came upon many cities which had attained
a high degree of civilization and material progress.
The most ancient monuments discovered thus far do not
date back much beyond the middle of the fourth millenium
but far earlier civilizations may well have existed in this
region of Asia before then. We are undoubtedly in for a
number of surprises and startling discoveries once the
bottom-most strata have been excavated and all the ruins
of Mohenjo-daro and Harappa are brought to light. The
ruins visible today represent indeed no more than a tiny
fraction of the great complexes of urban area still awaiting
excavation today. This is true despite the tremendous
operations which have been carried on over, the past forty
years by the Antiquities Service . and the extraordinary
results achieved up to now.
The discovery of the dead cities of the Indus was due,
like so many other archaeological finds, to chance. It
was while a railway line was being constructed that it was
noticed that the bricks used for ballast came from what
had been a large number of edifices, spread over a vast
area; steps were at once taken to prevent these buildings
from being destroyed and to consolidate them. Archaeolo¬
gists then set to work to identify the "occupation strata"
left by the successive inhabitants of these sites. The
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
CITY OF THE DEAD (Cont'd)
What became of the inhabitants?
early history of India and Pakistan was then shrouded in
mystery; absolutely nothing was known about the inhabi¬
tants of the region, where they had come from, to what
race they had belonged, and what level of civilization they
had attained.
It was at Harappa that investigations were begun; and
the significant discoveries made there encouraged archaeo¬
logists to embark on new excavations at Chanhu-Daro,
Jhangar, Jhukar, Amri, Rupar, Ali Murad and Nal, where
remains were found of different, though no less interesting
cultures. Large quantities of pottery were brought to light
and studies of these potsherds soon revealed sequences
of civilization which showed that the sites had been
occupied over very long periods.
Though the pioneer archaeologist of the Indus first broke
ground at Harappa, this city in fact yielded less than
Mohenjo-daro, since it had either been destroyed by
invaders or had decayed through the neglect of its own
people. Harappa, which lies near the Ravi, a tributary of
the Indus, was nothing but a shapeless heap of debris; a
few objects were discovered there but the whole site had
been so thoroughly disturbed that it provided no evidence
of real scientific value, although some scholars have seen
in the pictographic characters engraved on the seals found
in the city of Harappa, the origins of the Indian alphabet.
A few years later, however, exacavations In the ruins of
a Buddhist monastery on the site of Mohenjo-daro, some
four hundred and fifty miles (700 kms) from Harappa,
brought to light bricks similar to those used in the building
of Harappa; it was thus seen that Harappa and Mohenjo-
daro were the work of the same culture which had used
exactly similar materials to build these cities hundreds of
miles apart. Though not intact, Mohenjo-daro was fortu¬
nately far less dilapidated than Harappa, and excavations
revealed the remains of a city comparable in its size and
the quality of its buildings with the famous sites of Meso¬
potamia and Egypt.
When the work began, there was nothing to be seen but
a large number of mounds whose brick-red, reddish ocre
and light red colours stood out sharply against the greyish
hue of the surrounding landscape. Unlike the tells of Meso¬
potamia, formed by the accumulation of a "layer cake" of
strata left by successive occupations on a single site, the
Indus Valley mounds consisted of vast heaps of bricks
fallen from buildings demolished by wind and rain over a
period of more than five thousand years. Ancient tradition
had given this group of mounds the name of Mohenjo-daro,
in the language of Sind, "the place of the dead."
Standing on the banks
of the Indus River, Mo¬
henjo-daro was a pros¬
perous trading centre.
Left, modern impression
of a busy quayside (Mo¬
henjo-daro museum).
© Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
This name does not seem to be justified by the presence
of large numbers of skeletons, for no major cemetery has
yet been unearthed there, nor are there any of the funeral
deposits much prized by the archaeologist. It is quite
possible that the inhabitants of Mohenjo-daro, like those
of present-day India, burned their dead; those corpses
which have been exhumed appear to have died a violent
death, perhaps at the time of the capture of their city
by invaders.
No tombs containing objects to throw light on the
precise nature and quality of this civilization have yet
come to light, but archaeologists excavating the ruins of
a house have found a score of corpses, several of them
decapitated and the skeleton of a woman who had fallen
head first down a flight of steps leading to a well set
below the level of the street.
There were no objects with skeletons, unlike the case of
another group found in the citadel at Harappa, in 1946.
These men and women, the family of an ivory-carver, had
apparently fled from the attackers taking their treasures
with them; they had been caught by the enemy who car¬
ried off the treasures but left behind two elephant's tusks
(discovered with the skeletons), apparently considering
them of little value or too cumbersome to be worth taking
away.
The cemetery at Harappa contained several corpses wrap¬
ped in reed shrouds and placed in wooden coffins, together
with vases and bowls decorated with animal and plant motifs,
similar to those discovered in Mesopotamia. There must,
in the third and the second millenium, have been active
trade and perhaps also cultural contacts between the val¬
ley of the Indus and the valley of the Euphrates, during
a period marked by considerable exchanges between civi¬
lization as far apart as those of Ur and Mohenjo-daro (1).
The same reed shrouds have been found at Sumer, and
a similar arrangement of corpses, stretched out and with the
head towards the North. A vase from Tell Agrab is adorned
with a bull-god in his stable-temple similar to those found
on seals from the Indus Valley; excavations at Khafajah
have brought to light another seal which was fashioned in
the Indus Valley and almost certainly brought there from
Mohenjo-daro, in the same way as the cornelian pearl
belonging to the "treasures" of the royal tombs of Ur.
HERE is every indication that during its greatest
prosperity Mohenjo-daro was a busy trading
centre, a meeting place for local and foreign merchants,
owing to its splendid position on the banks of the Indus.
Harappa also stands on the banks of a large river and the
populations of the two cities, despite the distance between
them, probably resembled each other judging by the similar¬
ity of their cultural structure. The types of people repre¬
sented by the skeletons at Harappa belong to four dif¬
ferent races: Proto-Australoid, Alpine, Mediterranean and
Mongoloid, the single Mongoloid skull discovered showing
the same characteristics as the very early ones found
in the necropolises at Tepe Hissar, near Damghan.
We can visualise what the people of Mohenjo-daro looked
like at the time the city was a flourishing trade centre, by
taking a look at the human figures engraved on the seals
(1) For other facts on Mohenjo-daro, see Vol. I of the 6-tome History
of Mankind (Prehistory and the Beginnings of Civilization, by Jac¬
quetta Hawkes and Sir Leonard Woolley), published by George Allen
and Unwin, London (£6.6.0.) and Harper and Row Inc., New York
($15.50). See also The Unesco Courier, June 1963 and May 1965.
or modelled in the round on the handful of statues which
have been unearthed.
To learn how these people lived, we need to examine
the town itself which is now quite accessible to visitors.
What strikes everyone most of all are the "modern" build¬
ing methods and the systematic use of town-planning, which
are at once obvious to anyone who strolls through the
streets and enters the houses.
As in all hot countries, and the valley of the Indus is
one of the hottest areas in the world, where people have
to protect themselves against the sun, the streets are
mostly narrow, little more than alleys, and on the street
side, the walls of the houses have no openings except their
doors. Light and air came from the inner courtyards
round which the houses were grouped. The main thorough¬
fares of the town, however, were wider; outside the centre
of the city they were as broad as modern motorways.
The commonest building material used was brick, for
this is a country where both stone and wood are scarce.
The bricks were made of baked red clay, sometimes eked
out by adding earth, or "pisé" (puddled clay) enclosed in
a baked brick casing. The bricks were held together by
cob-mortar, giving sufficient solidity for the houses to be
several storeys high, as was necessary in a densely popu¬
lated town with the dwellings and shops crowded into
a small "business centre."
FOR water-supplies and rubbish-disposal, there
was a complicated network of canals, under¬
ground pipes and sewers, forming a system described
by some archaeologists as the most complete and in¬
genious ever devised in antiquity. Excavations have led to
the discovery of draining-wells, thanks to which the small
street sewers, when choked up, could easily be cleared
simply by removal of the brick cover.
Water was brought into the city via the canals and fed
into small wells inside the houses. Those in the poorer
quarters had apparently no such amenities and their in¬
habitants were obliged fetch their water in pails and vessels
from the houses of the rich.
While the rich had their own bathrooms, there were also
public bathing establishments for those who had no baths
of their own or who preferred to meet their friends at
the public baths. These thermae seem to have played as
important a part in the social life of Mohenjo-daro as they
did in that of the Romans. The bricks walls of both baths
and wells were coated with gypsum and sometimes with
bitumen to make them watertight.
In a town like Mohenjo-daro, whose streets were laid out
in a draught-board pattern, intersecting at right-angles and
generally running in the direction of the prevailing north-
south and east-west winds, keeping down the dust must
have been a difficult problem. To meet it, the ground was
consolidated by means of a kind of macadam made of
fragments of pottery combined with ground brick, which
was then damped and rammed down into a hard surface.
All this indicates a decidedly utilitarian attitude, a desire
for material comfort and a rational use of the Mohenjo-
daro site and its resources. Yet our insight into the
"Mohenjo-daro culture" is confined to what we know about
its town planning programme and how this was carried
out. The most important monuments discovered so far
are completely utilitarian ones: the Granary and the Town
Baths. No traces have been found of either a palace or
a temple; though it must be remembered that we do not 29
yet know how large an area the town covered it must
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
IMMMM
Paul Almasy, Paris
CITY OF THE DEAD (Cont'd)
Miniature engravings and chiselled jewellery
30
have extended far beyond the zones so far excavated
so it is quite possible that royal and religious buildings
were located in a part of the city that the archaeologists
have not yet found.
In the absence of objects in the tombs and caches of
temple treasures, our knowledge of the social and religious
life of the inhabitants in the Indus Valley in the fourth and
the third millenium is confined to what we can learn from
their pottery» children's toys, jewels and seals.
Indus sculpture is represented by a few very curious and
beautiful statues, including one in steatite, a soft stone,
depicting a thick-set man with a heavy face and slanting
eyes, wearing a cloak with a trefoil decoration, and a
bronze figurine of a young dancing girl, her long arms
adorned with bangles from wrist to shoulder.
It Is difficult to date these objects, since we do not
know either how long this culture flourished before the
Aryan invasion put a stop to its development or how
much time elapsed between the remote beginnings of a
chalcolithic (copper and bronze working) age or even
a stone age and the epoch when it reached its full deve¬
lopment.
This development is seen in the exquisite craftsman¬
ship of the objects fashioned in gold, silver, bronze, cop¬
per and tin brought from Rajputana, Baluchistan, Burma
and Bombay, perhaps also from the mines of Oman; and in
the consummate skill with which Mohenjo-daro jewellers
worked the precious and semi-precious stones cornelian,
jasper and agate, as well as the jadeite imported from
Tibet to produce jewellery of the most Intricate and
exquisite designs.
The divinities which presided over spiritual and material
life in the The City of the Dead are familiar to us from the
figures on the seals, though it is not always easy to tell
whether a particular animal was depicted because of its
religious attributes or symbolic significance, or whether the
artist was simply inspired by the pleasure of depicting
buffaloes, monkeys, tigers or elephants. These seals were
used either as amulets or talismans, or else for protecting
the contents of some recipient by stamping it with a sacred
image calculated to inspire awe and respect. It Is these
seals rather than the statues that demonstrate the out¬
standing talent and artistic taste of the Mohenjo-daro
engravers.
The animals on the seals are usually depicted in a bold
gracefully naturalistic style. Tiger's teeth for instance, are
painted in minute detail; Brahmin bulls, which appear fre¬
quently, are represented sometimes with a swollen hump
and sometimes with a flabby one, according to how well-
nourished the animal Is.
In a religious context these animals the rhinoceros,
tiger, elephant and bull are associated with the cult of a
deity known, for want of a better designation, as the Horned
God. This god is usually represented by a figure depicted
front-view, seated on a low table forming a sort of throne;
his arms are covered with bracelets and he has two large
horns on his head.
We also find a Homed Goddess, surrounded by the
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The bull is one of the
commonest motifs found
on seals from the Indus
Valley. Right, a bull and a
written inscription from one
of these seals, decorates
the facade of the museum
at Mohenjo-daro. Left,
a team of oxen pulling a
cart a clay toy found in
the ruins of Mohenjo-daro
Nedeco, Amersfoort
same animals as the Horned God. She is often shown
standing upright in a tree which botanists believe to be a
pipai, a tree which the people of modern India still revere
as sacred, and which they deck with jewels and vases.
It may be that the modern cult of the pipal, which is also
believed to be the habitation of the goddess Lakshmi, origi¬
nated in the worship of this sacred tree associated with
the Horned Goddess in the ancient culture of Mohenjo-daro.
The discovery of this site, with all that it has already
taught us about the prehistory or the proto-history of India,
concerning peoples whose very existence was hitherto
unknown, has made Mohenjo-daro one of the focal points
of modern archaeology, more important even than Harappa
and the other Indus valley excavation sites.
The energy and efficiency with which the Pakistan Depart¬
ment of Antiquities has set about excavating and preserving
the remains of this great trading city, deserves the highest
praise. The results obtained in a bare forty years are
indeed remarkable, both scientifically and artistically that
Is, from the point of view of both the specialist and the
tourist.
The world's archaeologists were therefore greatly alarmed
when it was learned that the ruins were threatened, not so
much by the flooding of the Indus, which is not a serious
danger, as by salts attacking the brickwork and causing
it to disintegrate. The danger is so great that according to
some estimates, the monuments now unearthed may be
completely destroyed by erosion within a few decades,
unless immediate protective measures are taken.
It is the irrigation of the areas round the excavation sites
(for the development of agriculture), together with the
decomposition of all the organic waste accumulated in so
large a city during a period of occupation which lasted at
least a thousand years certainly from 2,500 to 1,500 B.C.
and probably much longer that are responsible for these
salt deposits which are filtering into the walls and being
carried up through the bricks by capillary action. These
salts are even . more deadly when they attack pisé or
unbaked brick; and their destructive action is further
accentuated by the effects of rain and sandstorms, dust and
the scorching sun.
Aware of this danger and wishing to help in remedying
the situation as rapidly as possible, Unesco sent an
international mission of specialists to make an on-the-spot
investigation at Mohenjo-daro (see page 22). The report
of this mission proposes methods for halting the erosion
caused by the salt and for preventing its reoccurence.
When the preservation and restoration of Mohenjo-daro
are finally completed and its masterpieces of art assembled
in the nearby museum, The City of the Dead, rescued from
thousands of years of oblivion, will no doubt become a
new tourist attraction on a par with the architectural
wonders of Iraq, the cyclopean palaces of the Incas, the
shrines of the Aztecs and Mayas, and the temples of
Angkor which have been wrested from the engulfing jungle.
MARCEL BRION of the Académie Française is an historian and
the author of authoritative works on the German Romantic period
and the Italian Renaissance. His book, 'La Résurrection des Villes
Mortes", has been published in most European languages and is
considered as one of the classics of archaeology. Its English language
version, 'The World of Archaeology', was published by Elek, London
(2 volumes, 1962) and by Macmillan, New York (1962). Others of
his works translated into English are: "Romantic Art" (Thames ana
Hudson, London, 1960; McGraw Hi», New York, i960) and "Leonardo
da Vinci" (Heinemann, London, 1955).
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
32
PLEASE HELP THE READER
Sir.
I write to you on behalf of a great
number of people your large reader¬
ship outside England, Canada and the
United States. You want us to subscribe
to your magazine, we do. You want us
to recommend it to others, we do. You
want us to become interested in the
articles you write, we are. You want
us, probably, to appreciate the informa¬
tion you give and at the same time you
withhold certain information which often
gives the whole meaning to the subject
treated. I am talking of the figures you
use. You speak of miles, gallons, square
miles, yards, etc. They mean nothing
to those of us who have been educated
to use the metric system. Why not add
the metric equivalent In parenthesis.
Some articles indicate figures in metres
and kilometres, and this must be equally
frustrating to the people educated In the
United States and elsewhere.
R. Hoff
Hellerup, Denmark
FROM A WIDER WINDOW
Sir,
The letter from Mr. Titas Alfonsovich
Milashius, of Minsk, U.S.S.R. (Dec. 1964)
Is completely contradictory in context.
He stated: "The window open on life is
small; it should long since have been
enlarged and the glass polished up," and
later: "The Courier should be the chron¬
icle of the cultural and scientific life of
our planet." This microscopic view
would Indeed "narrow" the window since
science and culture are only two of the
many facets of life.
That this reader's aspect of life is
confined solely to science and culture
Is proved by his statement: "I cannot
imagine why the story of the Indian girl
who wanted to go to school was publish¬
ed In the April 1964 Issue. It Is of no
Interest from the artistic or any other
angle." The entrancing story of the
Indian child who longed for literacy was
by no means a waste of the readers'
time as he erroneously assumed.
This story was of vital humanitarian
interest to thousands of Courier readers
whose Interests are more comprehensive,
their vision wider and their imagination
more enlightened and less inhibited and
Introverted than his own.
Mr. Milashius seems to have misun¬
derstood the whole concept of the Cou¬
rier which is to promote friendship across
the frontiers by widening our knowledge
of the conditions which obtain In all other
countries and by such knowledge creat¬
ing better understanding between the
nations,' to the mutual benefit of all
mankind. Universal literacy is basically
essential to this purpose.
The frontiers of the world are not
confined to those of the U.S. and the
U.S.S.R., nor the world's Interest to that
of rocket development and space travel.
The peace and prosperity of all people
are the vital issues of the moment. May
the Courier continue to promulgate these
issues In the future, as has been Its
purpose in the past. By so doing it can
never degenerate Into the "cheap nove¬
lette" or "rubbish" category as falla¬
ciously prophesied by Mr. Milashius.
Charlotte Chalmers Carrington
Torquay, England
HIROSHIMA TODAY
Sir,
When I was a schoolboy I was very
upset when I heard about the Atom Bomb
explosion In Hiroshima (August 1945).
Since that time I have become more and
more convinced over the years that to
prohibit the use of Atom Bombs would
be one of the greatest blessings to
mankind. In the November Issue you
published an article "Nuclear Weapons
and World Sanity" by Linus Pauling.
This made very satisfying reading,
excellent both in content and style. Let
me, an ordinary citizen from Mongolia
salute Linus Pauling for his efforts on
behalf of lasting peace and the preven¬
tion of war.
May I suggest that The Unesco Courler
publish material on Hiroshima, the life
of its Inhabitants and the long-term
effects of Atom Bomb radiation. This
would help to mobilize everyone in the
world working for peace. I think that
Unesco should also do everything to
support The Pugwash Movement. Disar¬
mament, of course. Is an urgent, problem
as indeed are the social and economic
problems facing the developing regions
of the world.
Badamin Lkhagvaajav
Ulan Bator, Mongolia
RACE AND PREJUDICE
Sir,
Congratulations on your articles des¬
cribing racism in South Africa (April
1965) which are a first-rate example of
clarity and moral courage. I hope your
study will help many people to reflect
a little more objectively on the so-called
"scientific reality of racism" and still
further encourage all those who are
fighting, racism.
David Boublil
Champlgny, France
Sir,
I was absolutely astounded by the
articles on Apartheid. As a European
I am horrified by the Idea that other
Whites can approve of and impose such
a despicable thing as Apartheid; as a
result the position of Europeans through¬
out the world is compromised without
their being able to do anything effective
or immediate to redress the situation.
As a citizen of the Netherlands I feel
dismay and disgust that those responsible
for this avowed racialist policy speak our
language and dare to remind us of their
links with The Netherlands. Times have
changed; there Is no longer a cruiser at
the disposal of President Kruger; and
I wonder what we have done, or neglected
to do, to deserve the calumny of even
a iinguistic association with the South
African Republic. The article In the
United Nations Charter which prevents
states from Interfering in the internal
affairs of other states would seem to
invalidate the other articles relating to
justice and human rights. Is it really so
difficult to put an end to this senseless
scandal?
R.H.J. van Kuyk
Bussum, The Netherlands
HE READS THEM TWICE
Sir,
How can I obtain all the 1963 issues
of The Unesco Courier? In some of
the articles published In 1964 there are
references to a great deal of Interesting
material that appeared tho previous year.
To me your magazine is a fountain of
knowledge and I am not exaggerating
when I say that I have read all the 1964
Issues at least twice. They have a
special place in my library and I really
treasure them.
Esteban Perez
Jovellanos, Cuba
Ed note: Readers requiring back Issues
should order them from their nearest
Unesco National Distributor (see list
page 35).
THE WRONG IMPRESSION
Sir,
I recently watched an excellent BBC
television programme on the Impact of
television on some 80 or so countries.
Many of them are developing countries
with low literacy, and the Impact of tele¬
vision, whether watched at home in a
town or in a village communal centre, Is
tremendous.
Since governments and commercial
networks try to give as many viewing
hours as possible and local talent Is limit¬
ed, a great deal of viewing time Is given
over to poor quality films of the cheap
and nasty variety with an over emphasis
on violence and sex. The African and
Asian must acquire in consequence a
most distorted view of what to him
represents western civilization and stan¬
dards of behaviour, and young people
especially cannot remain unaffected by
exposure to what they see night after
night.
Unesco has done so much to further
the education of people In developing
countries. Could It not also sponsor the
making of good quality films made
available at low rates to the television
services of these and other countries to
be an alternative to undesirable films now
being shown? In doing so, Unesco would
be furthering still more the educational
cultural needs of all ages In the commu¬
nity and the cause of better understanding
and goodwill.
Margaret Esllng
St Leonards, Tasmania
Ed. note: The Idea suggested by our
reader has been discussed by the Unesco
General Conference, but so far ways and
means of implementing it have not been
found. .
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
1 Propylon (entrance way to¬
wards the sacred precinct
of Aphrodite) in the ruins of
Aphrodisias. Restoration began
here in 1963.
2 Odeon (small concert hall)
"uncovered at Aphrodisias
since 1962. Restoration was
begun in 1963 to consolidate
seats, mosaics and marble revet¬
ments.
O Headless statue of Claudia
" Antonia Tatiana recovered
from the ruins of the Odeon at
Aphrodisias. It dates from the
third century A.D.
A The " Bishop's Palace " at
"Aphrodisias. Its restoration;
including the re-erection of co¬
lumns, was started last year.
More on
Aphrodite's
city
Sir,
Being the Field Director of the New York
University excavations at Aphrodisias in Turkey,
I was naturally pleased to see the attractive pic¬
tures by Ara Güler in the reportage entitled
"Aphrodite's City Resuscitated" (January 1965).
May I point out that a slight misunderstanding
may arise out of the way in which the text reads
in part. It is quite accurate that the Turkish Minis¬
try of Education and the Direction of Antiquities
and Museums originated the removal of the village
of Geyre from the site of ancient Aprodisias and
continues to show great interest in our work,
even assisting us financially in 1963 and 1964 in
several restoration projects that we have initiated.
However, the excavations themselves and their
results since 1961 are activities under the aegis
of New York University. Through our constant
and often thankless efforts .during the past four
years, sizable amounts of money were raised
and spent, including three grants in counterpart
funds obtained through the Department of State
of the United States, under its Cultural Pro¬
gramme. The often spectacular discoveries made
by the expedition, the preservation and discreet
restoration policy adopted since the very first
campaign of excavations in 1961 can be best
illustrated by some photographs that I am
enclosing.
I would be grateful to you if you were good
enough to publish this mise au point, thereby
clarifying our own contribution to the rebirth of
Aphrodisias and the role played by New York
University in this project.
Let me also add that the photograph on p. 23
of the January 1965 issue does not show the new
village of Geyre (transfer to which was already
begun, by the way, in 1961, and not in 1963),
but a new village near Didyma and its ancient
temple of Apollo, which was built after an earth¬
quake had seriously damaged neighbouring
villages at Yortan and Yeni Hisar in the late 1950's.
Kenan T. Erim
Associate Professor of Classics
New York University
Field Director, Aphrodisias Excavations
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
VACATIONS ABROAD: The latest edition
of "Vacations Abroad" (Vol. XVII.
1965), Unesco's annual handbook on all
types of international holiday opportunities
for young people, has now appeared. Its
information covers 66 countries, each
country being listed in a separate chapter
in English, French and Spanish. All three
languages are used in entries relating to
international organizations (Further details
on opposite page).
FOR AFRICAN DEVELOPMENT: An Afri¬
can Training and Research Centre in
Administration and Development has been
set up In Tangie'rs by agreement between
the Moroccan government and Unesco.
It will co-ordinate and carry out research
and studies on problems of public admi¬
nistration In Africa and will give training.
OUTSTANDING WORK: "World Com¬
munications", Unesco's survey of
what is going on in television, press, film
and radio In the world today, has been
selected as one jof the outstanding refer¬
ence books of 1964 by the Reference
Services Division of the American Library
Association. The latest (4th) edition of
this basic reference work costs (cloth
bound) 47/- (stg); $11.00 or 33 F.
SCIENCE & DISARMAMENT: Every year
between 15.000 and 20,000 million
dollars are spent on military research and
development. If world disarmament can be
achieved how can these tremendous scien¬
tific and technological resources be best
put. to peaceful uses? Under Unesco's
continuing programme of peace research
and studies on disarmament, an interna¬
tional group of scientists recently dis¬
cussed this and related problems at a
meeting In Unesco House, Paris. The
group's recommendations for further action
and studies by Unesco In this field have
since been submitted to the 14th Pugwash
Conference on Science and World Affairs
meeting In Venice.
NEW APPROACH TO LITERACY: Unesco
has sent missions, each consisting of
an educationalist and an economist, to
Algeria, Ecuador, Iran, Tanzania and Pa¬
kistan five of the thirty countries which
have asked to participate in the pilot pro¬
jects In literacy which Unesco plans to
carry out between 1966 and 1968 (see "The
Unesco Courier," October 1964). These
missions follow Unesco's decision to adopt
a "selective strategy" approach toward a
worldwide attack on illiteracy and to start
with a series of experimental three-year
programmes in areas where literacy can do
most to advance economic and social
development.
PROMOTING RESEARCH: An internatio¬
nal science promotion operation in
which Unesco has shared has enabled the
National University of Buenos Aires, Argen¬
tina, to develop an Important laboratory
research programme In solid-state physics.
To help launch this research, Unesco sent
physicists from Sweden and Hungary to
Buenos Aires on technical assistance mis¬
sions. Laboratory equipment was provided
by grants from the 'National Reseach Coun¬
cil of Argentina and the Ford Foundation in
the United States.
HEADWAY IN EDUCATION: Cambodia
has increased its primary school atten¬
dance from 210,000 in 1952 to 680,000 In
1964, reports Mr. Jean Griffon, a Unesco
specialist who recently returned from a
mission to this country. Fifty-five per cent
of Cambodia's children aged between
six and fourteen are now in school. The
Cambodian government, in co-operation with
Unicef and Unesco, has prepared a plan
for further improvement, covering teacher
training, teaching methods, school Inspec¬
tion, and the creation of 14 model schools.
SAVING ABU SIMBEL: Funds available
for the transfer of the Abu Simbel tem¬
ples part of the International Campaign to
save the monuments of Nubia launched by
Unesco rose from the equivalent of
$270,000 to the equivalent of $6,840,000
during the first three months of this year.
The U.S. Government has contributed the
equivalent of $6 million in Egyptian pounds,
half of its total contributions to the Abu
Simbel operation, while $571,463 was re¬
ceived from Afghanistan, Italy, the Nether¬
lands and Switzerland. Protection of the
temple façades, mainly by covering the
gigantic statues with sand, is practically
finished. Steel scaffolding erected inside
the monuments Is also nearly complete and
tests are being made to determine what
equipment and materials should bemused
to cut up and reinforce 'the rock temples.
AFRICA'S NEW SCIENTISTS: Unesco
has announced the opening of a Re¬
gional Centre for Science and Technology
for Africa at Nairobi, capital of Kenya. The
new centre will help governments to Imple¬
ment the plan approved by 28 African
countries to increase by fifteenfold the
number of scientists In Africa during the
next fifteen years. The Nairobi centre will
hold conferences, symposia, seminars and
training courses for Africa's scientists.
A 1964 Unesco survey of 41 African
countries revealed a total of only 5,000
scientists; to make the best use of its
natural resources, Africa will be needing
between 50,000 and 70,000 scientists by
1980.
DANGERS FROM PESTICIDES: The In¬
ternational Atomic Energy Agency and
the Food and Agriculture Organization are
jointly studying the danger to human beings
of residues in chemicals used to combat
plant or animal pests. A special panel of
experts met in Vienna recently to examine
this problem and to submit recommenda¬
tions on the use of radioisotopes and irra¬
diation techniques in the detection and
study of pesticide residues.
34
U.S. SCIENCE WRITER TO RECEIVE KALINGA PRIZE
Dr. Warren Weaver of the United
States, who has had a distinguished
triple career as a professor, adminis¬
trator and popularizer of science, has
been selected as the thirteenth winner
of the International Kalinga Prize for
the Popularization of Science. Award¬
ed by an international jury appointed
by Unesco, the Kalinga Prize of £1,000
sterling is a personal donation of
Mr. Bljoyanand Patnaik, an Indian In¬
dustrialist, who Is a director of the
Kalinga Foundation named after the
empire ruled by the peace-loving Aso-
ka in India twenty-two centuries ago.
Born in 1894, Dr. Weaver began his
career as a professor of mathematics
at the California Institute of Techno¬
logy and the University of Wisconsin.
He is now vice-president and execu¬
tive director of the Alfred P. Sloan
Foundation In the United States, and
is a former president of the American
Association for the Advancement of
Science. He is the author of numer¬
ous articles and books. Among them
are Lady Luck The Theory of Proba¬
bility, The Mathematical Theory of
Communication, Science and Com¬
plexity, and People, Energy and Food.
Previous winners of the Kalinga
Prize since Its foundation In 1951, have
been: Louis de Broglie (France), Julian
Huxley (United Kingdom), Waldemar
Kaempffert (United States), Augusto Pi
Suner (Venezuela), George Gamow
(United States), Bertrand Russell (Uni¬
ted Kingdom), Karl von Frisch (Ger¬
many and Austria), Jean Rostand
(France), Ritchie Calder (United King¬
dom), Arthur C. Clarke (United King¬
dom), Gerard Piel (United States), and
Jagjit Singh (India).
Flashes.,
The U.S.S.R. has now over half a million
scientists, including 200,000 women, and
some 4,500 scientific institutions. The
U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences alone
has some 20,000 scientists, among them 500
academicians and corresponding members.
Some 7,500 workers engaged on the
project to harness the waters of the Lower
Mekong River Basin In South East Asia
are to receive food to improve their fami¬
lies' diet as part of their wages. The FAO
World Food Programme Is sending the
food at a cost of $1.7 million.
Seventy-two countries now have nation¬
al librairies, reports the Unesco Statistical
Yearbook. In the U.S.A., the Library of
Congress has over twelve million volumes,
in France, the "Bibliothèque Nationale"
houses six million and in the U.S.S.R. there
are 16 national libraries whose collections
total 62 million volumes.
During the second half of 1964 the Inter¬
national Bank for Reconstruction and Deve¬
lopment made 16 loans totalling $421 mil¬
lion. This brings the total number of loans
made by the Bank to 402 In 74 countries
and territories.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
M Should old-age homes be abolished ?
M How "scientific" are the social sciences ?
M Are political leaders sufficiently well-informed to avert war ?
M Which has proved to be the most successful treatment of criminals ?
international
social science
journal
Max Weber today
Biological aspects of race
ftblnbed quArterly Sa 10 -{atg.j ; i
These are some of the important
questions which you will find dis¬
cussed in the International
Social Science Journal . Each
issue covers a different topic.
Contributions by top specialists
around the world. An ideal way to
keep yourself abreast of the debate
on to-day's major social problems.
Price : $2.00 ; 10/-; 7 F. per copy.
$ 7.00 ; 35/- ; 24 F. per year (four issues).
Order directly from Unesco, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris 7\ or through national
distributors (see below). Free specimen
copy from Unesco on request.
Vacances à l'étranger
Vacaciones en el
xvn 1965
extranjero
Co»m y viaje* d* «eludió,
la m pu> iatrrsuuitutkl d»
trabaja valasurio
Just published
The latest edition of VACATIONS ABROAD
(Vol. XVII, 1965) is your indispensable
guide to low-cost, educational, useful travel
abroad. It gives you full facts on vacation
courses, summer schools and seminars,
study tours, student and youth hostels,
summer camps and centres, international
voluntary work camps and other interna¬
tional educational exchange schemes offer¬
ing a chance for study and travel abroad.
Information comes from over 950 institu¬
tions and organizations in 66 countries and
includes details of financial aid available.
162 p. $2.00; 10/-; 7 F.
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
'Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
Boek-handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
1 1 2, rue du Trfine, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Rangoon.
(	). CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
(Í 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop.. Sir
Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B, 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 1 3/50).-CHINA. World BookCoLtd.. 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1,Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51 , Prague 1 (permanent display) ; Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks-
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D. Kr. 1 7).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120.
Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja-
kauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7\ C.C.P.
12598-48. (10 F.). GERMANY. All publications:
R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich.
8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahren-
felder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P.
276650 (DM 10). - GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd. Atlantis House Commercial St., POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Kultura,
P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn
Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol
Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1:17 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 13;Gunfoundry Road,Hyberabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf AM Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). - INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (15/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (1 5/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph L. BahousS. Co., Dar ul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (1 0/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286. Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 140). -MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd.,Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore, 9; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Port-Louis (1 0/-). MONACO. British Bourbon Street,
Library 30 Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW-
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) WelMngston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-).
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For the Unesco Courier also: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks
115 (17.50 kr.).| PAKISTAN. The.West-Pak Pu¬
blishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box
374 56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILI¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia. 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA. The Book
Centre, Gordon Avenue, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI
Bashir Bookshop, P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWE¬
DEN. All publications : A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbo-
khandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoridet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus
6, 1211, Geneva C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala (1 0/-). REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA. All publications : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pre¬
toria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Cen¬
tral News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.-
50). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librai¬
rie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil Cairo. Sub/agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.EJ. and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES.
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St, New York,
N.Y. 1001 6 ($ 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Kn-
jïg, Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
'*«ë?l
N¿£
«V
- -V
¡SÄ Um
WËÊÊÈÊÊÈ
Egg
-:;vv.
/
4rr
Z>
*'
1
i# y
v^»
^»
I
¿r . y^
THE GREAT
ASIAN
HIGHWAY
In a few years time a journey by road from Turkey to Viet Nam or to Malaysia
and Ceylon will at last become a realistic proposition for the average motorist.
Thanks to the United Nations and to international co-operation modern highways
are being built to replace low-grade and often hazardous road sections on the
world's largest continent. Most of Asia's countries will benefit from the new
Asian Highway (see p. 12). Here the Asian Highway snakes through a deep
gorge in Afghanistan, leading to the Khyber Pass and the Pakistan frontier.
United Nations
]]>
</page>
</document>
