<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="060718eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
Eternal cinema
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Atimetolive...
26 India
Living dangerously
Danger is a way of life for film stunt men, the
unsung heroes of the cinema. Jumping off roof¬
tops, falling off horses, crashing cars at high
speed, day after day, film after film, they risk
their lives to add vicarious excitement to the
humdrum existence of the average cinema-goer.
Above, a tense moment for two Indian stunt men
during filming of the Second World War adven¬
ture film Lalkar.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco Courier
A window open on the world
Editorial August 1984
37th year
IT is a cruel paradox that the cinema, the most popular art of the
twentieth century, should also be the most threatened. No art
form has been (and continues to be) a prey to such destruction
which, whether wilful or accidental, has caused losses on a massive
scale.
The disastrous implications of these losses for the memory of
mankind are now fully appreciated. In this issue of the Unesco
Courier, which is entirely devoted to the safeguard and preserva¬
tion of the world's film heritage, the two major causes of destruc¬
tion are analysed in detail. One stems from attitudes of mind to
films and the cinema; the other has to do with the chemistry of
motion picture film.
The cultural value of the cinema was ignored and even denied for
far too long, and the film was considered exclusively as a commer¬
cial commodity. In many countries huge quantities of film were
thrown onto the scrap-heap, wantonly despoiled in ruthless and
reckless waves of destruction unleashed whenever they seemed to be
required by changing tastes and fashions in film and new technical
developments.
Films are at the mercy of the support on which they are recorded:
this support is always fragile and has a life-span that may be limited
unless certain precautions are taken. "Chemical death" may strike
very quickly and has played havoc with the films which were pro¬
duced before the. 1950s and recorded on nitrate material; in the case
of these films losses have assumed the proportions of a cultural
catastrophe.
A handful of.pioneer film enthusiasts responded to the situation
early on, bidding to win acceptance of the cultural value of the
cinema and, often working in a climate of hostility, to preserve
films they considered outstanding in collections which were the im¬
perfect but useful prototypes of modern film archives. The Interna¬
tional Federation of Film Archives (FIAF) was founded before the
Second World War. The creation of the Federation, with its cen¬
tralizing role, was the first step towards a world film archive.
As the years have passed it has become increasingly clear that this
form of defence of the cinema, if it is to be effective and com¬
prehensive, can only be achieved as a result of international co¬
operation. In the last decade or so there has been a ground-swell in
this direction which led in 1980 to the adoption by Unesco of
a "Recommendation for the Safeguarding and Preservation of
Moving Images" which fully recognized the status of an art which
had siiffered unjust treatment, and proposed to the international
community measures for protecting both the heritage and the
future of this great medium of communication.
In April of this year, a consultation hosted by the Austrian Film
Archive and the Austrian Film Museum in Vienna was organized
by Unesco in collaboration with FIAF, the International Federa¬
tion of Television Archives (FIAT), the International Association
of Sound Archives (IASA), and the International Film and Televi¬
sion council (IFTC). The meeting brought together some twenty
representatives of archives from all over the world to draw up a ten-
year programme of action and to prepare a questionnaire enabling
the effects of the Unesco Recommendation to be evaluated in 1986.
Safeguard and rescue these are two strands in the pattern of ap¬
proach and action evoked, as usual from a broad international
perspective, in this issue of the Unesco Courier in the hope that the
fragile art of film may survive and flourish.
Cover: An old photo before and after restoration by neutron activation.
This process for restoring faded details of photos to visibility can also be
used with moving images. The original photo was taken in the nineteenth
century by the pioneer English photographer William Henry Fox Talbot.
Photo © The National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institu¬
tion, Washington, D.C.
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
4 The fragile art of film
by Raymond Borde
7 Africa: the images that must not fade
by Paulin Soumanou Vieyra
9 Egypt's national film archive
by Khaled Osman
10 The nitrate ultimatum
by Ray Edmondson and Henning Schou
12 The electronic alternative
by Kerns H. Powers
14 Napoleon makes a come-back
A rediscovered epic of the silent screen
by Roy Malkin
17 Wanted!
The search is on for the world's missing films
by Sam Kula
20 The video grapevine
by Halo Manzi
22 India: it's never too late.
by Paramesh Krishnan Nair
24 Thailand: when the camera was king
by Dome Sukvong
25 Cuba: a people in its pictures
by Manuel Pereira
26 Cine qua non
An ABC of film preservation
by Frantz Schmitt
27 Birth of a notion
by Boleslaw Matuszewski
29 Switzerland: a living film archive
by Freddy Buache
Lifting the veil of secrecy
30 The Gosfilmofond of Moscow
by Vladimir Yurevich Dmitriev
32 Unesco and the preservation of moving images
by Wolfgang Klaue
34 The International Federation of Film Archives
by Robert Daudelin
2 A time to live...
INDIA: Living dangerously
Published monthly in 27 languages
by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French, Spanish
and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N° 8 - 1984 - OPI - 84 - 1 - 413 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The fragile art of film by Raymond Borde
THE cinema is a fragile art. Before the
first film archives were established
it suffered grievous losses and it
remains vulnerable to the unconsidered
destruction of negatives and prints.
The scale of these losses is horrifying.
There are grounds for believing that almost
half of all the films made throughout the
world in the period between the invention
of the cinema in 1895 and 1950 have disap¬
peared. There were variations from one
country to another; but taking into account
the history of the cinema as a whole, varia¬
tions in production methods, the evolution
of the market and technical progress in the
conservation of film, this is a reasonable
estimate of average losses between the
period in which destruction was rife and the
present era in which conservation is a prime
concern. It provides overwhelming
justification for the call for a world policy
for the safeguard of "moving images".
The underlying reason for these losses is
to be found in the very nature of films,
which are both a form of merchandise and
objects of cultural value. For half a cen¬
tury, commercial considerations were up¬
permost. Producers simply destroyed old
films that were out of date, had lost their
RAYMOND BORDE, French film historian and
critic, is the founder-curator of the Toulouse
Cinémathèque and Vice-President of the Inter¬
national Federation of Film Archives (FIAF).
His study Les Cinémathèques was published
in 1983 by L'Age d'Homme publishers,
Lausanne.
popularity or, for technical reasons, were
no longer marketable. The idea of moving
images as being part of the cultural heritage
developed only slowly, thanks to the efforts
of historians and those who pioneered the
first film archives.
The first wave of destruction on a
massive scale occurred in about 1920. The
principal victim was the so-called "early"
cinema the cinema of the fairground and
the popular entertainment houses. Pan¬
tomimes, spectaculars, one- or two-reel
melodramas and comic chases full of
special effects which delighted popular au¬
diences were the first to be scrapped, but the
early "art films" of the period immediately
preceding the First World War, which
sought to earn the cinema a status com¬
parable to that of the theatre, also suffered
the same fate.
Tastes had changed. After 1918 films
became more ambitious, more realistic, and
ran on average for an hour and a half. Ac¬
tors of quality replaced the light-hearted
entertainers of the pre-war years and film-
directing became an art in itself. There was
a complete break with the past, with the
"old" cinema as it was termed disdainfully.
Distributors hurried to get rid of their
stocks of films which had lost their com¬
mercial value, selling them off to dealers
who washed them to recover the silver salts
contained in the emulsion.
The same thing was happening
everywhere. The American Film Institute
has estimated that eighty-five per cent of
the films made in the United States between .
1895 and 1918 disappeared in this manner.
The figures are similar for France, Italy and
the Scandinavian countries. The works of
Georges Meliès and Ferdinand Zecca suf¬
fered particularly, but the early films of
Abel . Gance, Mauritz Stiller and Victor
Sjoestrom were not spared either. This was
spring-cleaning with a vengeance.
The second wave of destruction, just as
wholesale as the first, took place around
1930 with the transition from silent to talk¬
ing pictures. The cinema underwent a
radical change. As far as the film itself was
concerned, the standard gauge remained 35
mm, but the image was reduced in size to
make room for the sound track. Projectors
were replaced or modified. Speech, song
and operetta invaded the screen. A new
generation of actors drawn from the theatre
replaced film stars who could mime but not
speak their parts.
Within two years, the cinema industry
throughout the world found itself with
enormous stocks of rejected film on its
hands which were bundled off to the scrap
dealers. Global statistics concerning the
losses of films of the 1920s, the golden age
of the silent cinema, do not exist, or remain
to be compiled, but approximate estimates
put these losses at eighty per cent for Italy,
seventy-five per cent for the United States
and seventy per cent for France. In coun¬
tries where State Film Archives had been
created in time to preserve at least one
negative or print the figures are somewhat
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
This year, in a notable example of interna¬
tional collaboration between film archives,
the Gosfilmofond of Moscow enabled the
Cinémathèque of Toulouse (France) to pre¬
sent a programme of 38 little-known Soviet
films of the 1920s and an exhibition of 350
photos taken from them. Below and on op¬
posite page, 4 of the photos. From left to
right, shots from: Katka's Reinette Apples
(Katka, Bumajnyi ranet) by Friedrich Ermler
and Edouard lohanson (1926), a portrayal of
ways of life in the Soviet Union at that time.
The Extraordinary Adventures of Mr. West in
the Land of the Bolsheviks (Neobytchainye
prikliutcheniia mistera Vesta v strane
bolchevikov, 1924), by Lev Kuleshov. The
actor in photo is the great Soviet director
Vsevolod Pudovkin (1893-1953). Aelita by
Yakov Protazanov (1924). The costumes
and sets for this science-fiction film were
designed in the constructivist style. Photo
shows Aelita, ruler of the planet Mars,
played by Julia Solntseva. The Girl and the
Hooligan (Barychnia i khuligan) by Vladimir
Mayakovski and Evgeni Slavinski (1918).
This was the second of3 films written for the
Neptune company in 1918 by the poet Maya¬
kovski (1893-1930), shown in the photo.
Above Durutta ippeiji ("A Page of
Madness") a dramatic story filmed in 1926
by Kinugasa Teinosuke, one of the great
pioneers of Japanese cinema. The scenario
was by Kawabata Yasunari (Nobel Prize for
Literature, 1968). In this masterpiece, set
almost entirely in a lunatic asylum,
Kinugasa used a wide range of ingenious
techniques to heighten the visual intensity,
including the superimposition ofbars in cer¬
tain sequences. For many years it was
thought that all the prints of the film had
been lost until Kinugasa himself discovered
a copy in 1971 in his garden shed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
lower (forty per cent in Germany and ten
per cent in the USSR).
Whatever the exact figures, these
catastrophic losses had the effect of alerting
public opinion and launching the idea of
film archives. Journalists and men of letters
took up the cause and, whilst recognizing
that there were economic constraints,
argued in favour of conserving the products
of the industry as part of the cultural
heritage.
The third wave of destruction occurred
much more recently, during the early 1950s.
Until then, the thin strip of material used as
a support for the light-sensitive emulsion in
which moving pictures were recorded had
been made of cellulose nitrate (celluloid) a
highly inflammable and dangerous
substance. When a number of governments
prohibited the use of cellulose nitrate,
manufacturers generally turned to non-
inflammable cellulose acetate as the sup¬
port for what came to be known as "safety
film"
At this time, in the early 1950s, it was not
yet realized that old films of any kind might
one day acquire renewed value as material
for television programmes or as the focus of
retrospective projections in avant-garde or
experimental film theatres. Masterpieces
were preserved but run-of-the-mill movies
which appeared to have had their day were
scrapped. The deposit of nitrate films in na¬
tional archives was encouraged in some
countries, but the rate of destruction re¬
mained high. Here again, global statistics
concerning total cinematographic output
between 1930 and 1950 (the period between
the arrival of talking pictures and the
replacement of nitrate by acetate film) are
lacking, but it has been estimated that some
thirty per cent of all films from this period
were lost.
So far we have spoken of losses that can
be ascribed to human negligence or to com¬
mercial considerations of profitability. But
the laws of chemistry have also been
responsible for the disappearance of many
films. Nitrate film is unstable and gradually
decomposes. Colour films fade and lose
their harmony and chromatic balance as a
result of chemical reactions among the
three basic colouring materials. Victim of
human negligence, the cinema has also
come under a sort of technical curse which
makes it one of the most endangered of the
Egged On (1926) by the
American director and actor
Charley Bowers. The film was
recently discovered in France
in a gypsy's caravan.
arts. Thus the role of the chemist has
become determinant in the salvaging of this
element of the cultural heritage.
This salvage operation constitutes the
substance of the long history of film
libraries and archives. As long ago as 1898,
a Polish cameraman. Boleslaw
Matuszewski, published in Paris a pam¬
phlet entitled Une Nouvelle Source
d'Histoire (A New Source of History), in
which he proposed the creation of a
cinematographic museum where motion
pictures of historical, educational, in¬
dustrial, medical and theatrical interest
could be preserved. Matuszewski's aim was
to transmit to future generations the
authentic image of his own age, the idea be¬
ing to establish an official archive for the
statutory deposit of cinematographic works
which would also be authorized to accept
films in the form of gifts, bequests or on an
exchange basis. Priority was to be given to
the conservation of negatives and the ar¬
chive was to be open to the public.
The project was ahead of its time and
failed to materialize. Thirty-five years were
to pass before Matuszewski's prophetic
message was rescued from oblivion. (See
extracts from his pamphlet on page 27).
It is true, however, that up to the end of
the silent film era collections were built up
in various countries, but their purpose was
utilitarian. The aim was not to preserve
cinematographic works as such, but rather
to assemble various categories of films for
a specific purpose. This could be military
(as in the case of collections in the British
War Museum, in London, B.U.F.A. in
Berlin and the Section Cinématographique
of the French Army, in Paris); religious (the
collection of the Abbé Joye, in Basle); legal
(the Library of Congress collection in the
United States, preserved for copyright pur¬
poses, and the Gaumont, Pathé, Metro-
Goldwyn-Mayer and other studio archives);
educational (the Soviet Documentary Film
Archive, created in 1926); or even
philosophical (the Albert Kahn Collection,
in Paris).
Not until 1933 was the first film archive
in the modern sense of the term an institu¬
tion which has as its prime function the
safeguarding of moving images as part of
the cultural heritage established. This was
the Svenska Filmsamfundet, set up in
Stockholm by a group of film enthusiasts
who had been shocked by the wholesale
destruction of silent films. This modest in¬
itiative proved to be a landmark in the
history of film archives. Film collections
were soon established in other countries:
in 1934, in Berlin (the Reichsfilmarchiv),
and in Moscow (the V.K.I.G., the School of
Cinema Archive);
in 1935, in London (the National Film
Library), New York (the Film Library of
the Museum of Modern Art) and Milan (the
Mario Ferrari Collection, which later
became the Italian Film Archive);
in 1936, in Paris (the Cinémathèque
Française);
in 1938, in Brussels (the Belgian Film
Archive).
The same year, 1938, saw the creation of
the International Federation of Film Ar¬
chives (FIAF), which at first only had
members in Berlin, London, New York and
Paris, but which gave international form to
the new awareness and the common ideal.
The public too was beginning to discover,
thanks to retrospective showings of early
films, that the cinema already had a cultural
history and that it belonged to the artistic
heritage of mankind.
After the Second World War, this move¬
ment grew in strength and wherever a na¬
tional cinematographic tradition existed na¬
tional film archives were created. Today,
FIAF comprises seventy-two institutions in
fifty States, and the trend seems irreversi¬
ble. The Recommendation for the
Safeguarding and Preservation of Moving
Images, adopted by the General Conference
of Unesco in 1980, is also bearing fruit. The
developing countries are showing a steadily
increasing interest in the preservation and
utilization for cultural purposes of films
and other audio-visual material from the
past.
At the same time, the concept of film ar¬
chives has itself evolved. The pioneers of
the 1930s were strong-minded people and
their tastes and preferences coloured their
judgment in selecting films for preserva¬
tion. They behaved more like collectors
than archivists and some of them were
unaware that there was a technical aspect to
the process of storing films. Nevertheless,
credit is due to them for the historic role
they played in creating the first film ar¬
chives and in saving for posterity thousands
of films which would otherwise have disap¬
peared. With the extension of film archives
has also come the development and imposi¬
tion of international standards for preser¬
vation and cataloguing.
Nowadays, scientists and jurists have as
important a role to play as film enthusiasts.
Their task is to render the concept of archiv¬
ing credible to today's more understanding
film-makers. After more than a few set¬
backs, as well as successes, the great adven¬
ture launched prophetically by a Polish
cameraman in 1898 is nearing fulfilment,
and this is surely the best guarantee that the
cinema will never again suffer the destruc¬
tive acts that have marked its history in the
past. _ _
Raymond Borde
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Poster for Vent de Sable (1982-1983), a
Franco-Algerian film by Mohamed Lakdar-
Hamina which examines the question of
women's situation in a Third World country.
Africa: the ¡mages that mast not fade
PAULIN SOUMANOU VIEYRA. Benin-born
Senegalese film critic and director, is head of
the film section of his country's Ministry of In¬
formation and a professor at the university of
Dakar. He has produced many film reports and
short features, mainly on African subjects.
Notable among his published works is Le
Cinéma Africain des Origines à 1 973, the first
part of a two-volume study.
THE finest examples of the African
cultural heritage are today to be
found outside Africa. This became
glaringly apparent during the exhibition of
traditional art at the World Festival of
Negro Art, held in Dakar, Senegal, in 1966.
Indeed, feelings ran so high at the time that
the idea of retaining in Africa the works
which had been loaned for the festival was
much discussed.
Subsequent efforts on the part of
Africans themselves to create public
by Paulin Soumanou Vieyra
awareness of the importance of the cultural
heritage for the education of their people,
through the medium of such movements as
Présence Africaine and La Société Afri¬
caine de Culture, made the recovery of
works of art and their return to their place
of origin an issue of continuing concern.
The claim is a legitimate one, against
which the only argument offered by the
West is a technical one namely, that the
conservation of the works in question poses
material and financial problems which none ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Poster for Finye or
le Vent ("Finye" or
"The Wind", 1982)
by the Malian direc¬
tor Suleymane
Cisse. Profoundly
African in spirit, the
film evokes the links
between the dif¬
ferent generations,
the young and the
old, and traditional
culture.
Le lilrncte Souleymane Clsüc
t
ff
V
LE VEN
FINYE
of the African States, struggling as they are
at present with the life-and-death issues of
under-development, is in a position to
resolve. But neither this argument, nor the
observation that no concerted cultural
policy has ever been seriously envisaged by
the countries in question, is sufficient to
justify the continued pillage of African art,
even though it must be admitted that their
transfer to museums in Europe and the
USA has saved a great many works from
destruction.
With regard to "moving images" we may
consider as being part of the African
cultural heritage all the films made about
and in Africa by non-Africans at a time
when Africans themselves were not in a
position to make such records themselves.
What remains to be done is to make an in¬
ventory of these documents so that they can
be systematically classified and given an
African re-interpretation. This huge task of
sorting, classification and duplication
would require the allocation of substantial
resources.
The same process must be applied in the
case of material produced since in¬
dependence, whose origins are easier to
determine. Emerging as sovereign States,
the countries of Africa rightly wanted to
record for themselves, in moving images,
their own national realities.
Among the French-speaking countries of
Africa, Senegal took the initiative of mak¬
ing provision, within the framework of the
Ministry of Information, for a Cinemato¬
graphic Service whose task it was to pro¬
duce newsreels. These were at first made on
a monthly basis and made available, free of
charge, to two film distribution companies.
Later, when they were produced on a fort¬
nightly basis, they were screened so ir¬
regularly that the State was obliged to in¬
tervene, making projection obligatory and
imposing a screening fee. When the
distributors and cinema proprietors failed
to screen the national newsreels, arguing, in
obvious bad faith, that they already had
foreign newsreels available for projection,
the State intervened once more, putting an
end to the screening of foreign newsreels
and allowing only the Senegalese newsreels
to be shown.
At this point the French Government
proposed a co-operative arrangement bet¬
ween the interested African States and
In 1971, the
Senegalese director
Ousmane Sembène,
one of the most
outstanding figures
of the African
cinema, made his
third feature, Emitai
("Thunder God").
The film shows the
animist Diola people
at odds with the
French colonial
authorities. Sem¬
bène used non¬
professional actors,
and skilfully mingl¬
ed fact and fiction.
Left, a poster for
Emitai.
French and other foreign newsreel pro¬
ducers within an association known as the
Consortium Audiovisuel International.
This led to the joint production of a weekly
newsreel in three parts, the first comprising
national news, the second, news of more
general African interest culled from the
newsreels of the participating States, and
the third, consisting of international news
provided by the foreign producers.
The arrangement stipulated, among
other things, that the Consortium would
assume half the costs of processing the films
and would provide each participating State
with the services of a reporter-cameraman
and the equipment necessary for filming. In
return it had the right to incorporate
material shot in Africa in the newsreels it
distributed throughout the world. In this
way, there began to accumulate, not only in
Senegal but also in Tunisia, Algeria,
Cameroon, Madagascar, the Ivory Coast,
Togo, Benin and Chad, the African
heritage of moving images. With the
development of television in Africa, this co¬
operative venture came to an end and in
1980 the Consortium was disbanded.
In English-speaking Africa, the heritage
of moving images has been built up in a dif¬
ferent manner. When independence came
to this part of the continent, newsreels were
not produced systematically. Instead, films
were made on the occasion of important of¬
ficial events, such as visits by Heads of
State. The films themselves were, of course,
processed in London, just as those made in
Portuguese-speaking Africa were processed
in Lisbon. Other European countries, in¬
cluding Sweden, Denmark, Yugoslavia,
Italy and the Soviet Union, as well as
Canada and the United States of America,
also took part in this work.
Today, newsreel films have practically
disappeared from Africa, thanks to the
development of television which has thus
become the principal source of the heritage
of moving images. Quite a lot of televised
news is produced, but the ephemeral all too
frequently takes precedence over the essen¬
tial and the documents produced are only of
relative value. There are better ways of fur¬
nishing a country's collective memory.
With regard to the conservation of
documents, there is a lack of proper
organization. Store-rooms are poorly ven¬
tilated or lack adequate air-conditioning,
while the work of classification is not
always entrusted to specialists. Financial
resources are lacking. The stored material
deteriorates and eventually becomes
unusable.
Another problem, again due to lack of
resources, arises from the fact that the tapes
bearing the sound tracks that accompany
filmed material are erased for re-use, leav¬
ing silent pictures that are virtually mean¬
ingless. Both sound and image disappear
when video-cassettes are used a second
time. Efforts are doubtless made in the first
instance to erase only what seems to be of
least importance, but when there is a serious
shortage there is a tendency to take cassettes
at random from a pile of material that has
not always been carefully classified. Where
television is concerned, the State is the
authority and is thus responsible for the
conservation of moving images, just as it is
for the creation of archives for printed
material. Feature films produced by private
companies or official bodies have, on occa¬
sion, been preserved simply because, in the
absence of laboratories in Africa, the
negatives have been stored abroad.
It should be noted that Africa has two im¬
portant film libraries, in Cairo and Algiers.
Only Egypt, however, thanks to its own
highly developed film industry, has archive
services in Cairo and Alexandria with
adequate conservation resources. Every
country should, of course, possess its own,
well-organized film archive. For the time
being, however, one solution might be the
creation of two regional archive centres at
Dakar and Nairobi.
Many African States are undoubtedly
aware of the importance of preserving any
document that has a contribution to make
to the history of their countries. Never¬
theless, whole chapters of this history in
moving images are disappearing for ever,
partly because of lack of resources, and
partly through negligence. The time has
come for the countries of Africa to pay
serious attention to the problems posed by
the preservation of moving images and the
safeguarding of the African cultural
heritage in this as in all other domains.
Paulin Soumanou Vieyra
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Egypt's national film archive
by Khaled Osman
UNLIKE most developing countries,
Egypt has a very old film heritage.
The Lumière brothers organized
film shows in cafés in Cairo and Alexandria
as long ago as 1896, and shortly afterwards
films began to be made in Egypt, at first by
foreigners (mainly French, Italian and Ger¬
man film-makers) and then, from 1927 on,
by Egyptians.
This heritage, almost a century old, is a
mine of information for the film historian
to whom it reveals traces of a conception of
cinema which has to a large extent been in¬
herited by modern Egyptian film-makers,
and also for the general historian seeking to
reconstitute a historical period.
In Egypt the problem of preserving films
was for many years neglected by the
authorities who did not appreciate the in¬
terest films could hold for future
generations
If many old films have been preserved or
rediscovered in spite of the absence of pro¬
visions for mandatory deposit in the past, it
is due to private initiatives which were
praiseworthy but imperfect and necessarily
incomplete.
A special role in the field of preservation
was played by Misr Studios, which were
founded in 1935 by the great Egyptian
economic and industrial pioneer Talaat
Harb. When the Studios were created,
storage facilities were built for the preserva¬
tion of both newsreel films (which began to
KHALED OSMAN, of Egypt, is a graduate of
the Ecole des Hautes Etudes Commerciales in
Paris, and holds a law degree from the univer¬
sity of Paris. He is engaged on research into
the Egyptian cinema.
be made on a regular basis in 1925) and
feature films.
But such concern was extremely rare at
that time, when films were considered
primarily as products for short-term use, as
revealed in this anecdote. When the great
actress Fatma Roshdi was about to release
"Under the Sky of Egypt", her previous
film "Catastrophe over the Pyramids" ap¬
peared, was panned by the critics and booed
by the public. So as to maintain her status
as a star by preventing the second film
(which was in the same vein as the first)
from being shown to the public, Fatma
Roshdi, who was also the film's producer,
simply decided to destroy all existing copies
of it. Such losses are irreparable, and the
only information we have about these
vanished films is to be found in the many
fascinating art magazines published at that
time.
The initiative taken by Misr Studios was
extremely laudable, and it was a heavy blow
for Egypt when a fire caused by the
negligence of a janitor ravaged part of the
Studios in July 1950, notably affecting the
archive premises.
A growing awareness of the problem of
film preservation in the mid-1950s led to the
creation of the Egyptian Film Archive by
the Office of Arts. In the same year Egypt
participated for the first time (as an
observer) in the work of the International
Federation of Film Archives (FIAF).
But the odds seemed to be stacked against
the Egyptian Archive, for in August 1958
another fire, in this case caused by the spon¬
taneous combustion of nitrate film,
destroyed part of the collection which had
been patiently assembled .from gifts of
Egyptian and foreign films and from films
seized by the Customs.
After the fire the Archive continued to be
supplied in this way, with the addition of a
more important source in 1968 when the
Ministry of Culture was persuaded to
establish a mandatory deposit obligation.
The tide now began tó turn, although
some restrictive practices continued to ex¬
ist. The 1968 decree was not backed up by
sufficiently dissuasive sanctions; the
authorities banked on the hope, which
proved vain, that private producers would
co-operate with them, following the exam¬
ple of the Egyptian General Cinema
Organization, a public body. In 1971 the
Organization ceased its production ac¬
tivities because of an enormous chronic
deficit. However, a step forward had been
taken the year before when Egypt joined
FIAF.
But piecemeal measures were no longer
tolerable; legislation was needed. Such
legislation now exists in the shape of Law
no. 35 of 1975, which requires producers
and distributors jointly to deposit at the
Film Archive (now known as the National
Archives) a 35 mm copy made at their own
expense of any film produced for public
showing in Egypt or elsewhere.
Initial application problems have been
overcome, and today the law has given the
Archives a new lease of life; the practice of
mandatory deposit is satisfactorily carried
out since copies are subject to quality
control.
Nevertheless, the situation is still fragile;
certain producers and distributors would
like, on grounds of lack of film, to replace
the mandatory deposit requirement by pay¬
ment of a guarantee.
But this is not of central importance.
Today the path to be followed has been
signposted, and the importance of the
preservation of films is fully recognized.
Directly or indirectly, Egypt's film heritage
bears witness to the country's tormented
history in this century, with its joy and pain,
its defeats and victories, its fears and hopes.
Fortunately, the major part of it has been
saved.
Famine scene from Lashin (1937). Directed
by Fritz Kramp (dialogue by Ahmad Rami)
Lashin was a milestone in the development
of the Egyptian cinema, showing on the
screen for the first time the struggles and
sufferings of the Egyptian poor. Public
screening of Lashin was at first prohibited,
but the film later became a tremendous
popular success. Today only a few stills
from this key work survive.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The nitrate ultimatum by Ray Edmondson and
Henning Schou
Cellulose nitrate film in
various stages of decomposi¬
tion. The film produces a gas
which bleaches the photo¬
graphic images. Then it
becomes sticky, bubbles,
solidifies and finally crumbles
into a brown powder.
IF there had been newsreel cameras in the
days of the Pharaohs we might today
have the answer to one of history's most
intriguing questionshow did they build the
pyramids? The ancient Egyptians left many
records from which modern man has
reconstructed their culture: stone tablets,
papyrus scrolls, the pyramids themselves
and their contents. But a newsreel would
have brought it all to life, unconsciously cap¬
turing the things the Egyptians might not
have thought to record in their writings.
Even if they had been able to match the in¬
ventions made around the turn of the cen¬
tury, we should not have been able to see
the results today: while the pyramids and
RAY EDMONDSON, of Australia, is the Direc¬
tor of the National Film Archive, National
Library of Australia, Canberra.
HENNING SCHOU, of Australia, is head of the
preservation department of the National Film
Archive, National Library of Australia and
chairman of FIAF's Preservation Commission.
some papyrus have survived for thousands
of years, the movie film would have perished
within the first hundred, leaving nothing but
containers full of brown dust for the ar¬
chaeologist to puzzle over....
The motion picture as we know it is less
than a century old. It is a child of technology:
unlike older forms of art and record, it can be
created and used only through mechanical
or electronic means. It has become the
universal medium of mass communication,
the first genuinely new art form in thousands
of years, andalmost without our realizing
itit has become one of our principal forms
of historical record.
Until 1951, most professional motion pic¬
ture film was made of a mixture of cellulose
nitrate and camphorsometimes called
celluloid or nitrocellulose. Durable in heavy
use, easy to splice and work with, it met the
most important and immediate re¬
quirements of film-makers and cinema
operators. But it has two serious disadvan¬
tages: it is highly inflammable, and it has a
limited life-span (generally from forty to
eighty years).
When ignited, a roll of nitrate film is im¬
possible to extinguish, even by submersion
in water, and it burns with an almost ex¬
plosive ferocity. Under certain conditions, it
is capable of spontaneous combustion.
The second disadvantage, the instability
of the material, did not particularly concern
the film industry, at least at the time that mat¬
tered. During most of the "nitrate era"the
period from the popularization of movies in
the 1890s until the discontinuation of nitrate
manufacture in 1951film was largely
perceived as popular entertainment, and
little thought was given to its permanent
value or to the problems of preserving it.
Because the industry itself exercised such
far-reaching control over the exhibition and
ownership of film prints it was not a problem
that entered the public consciousness
either. And it was not until the latter years of
the nitrate era that a significant amount of
film had actually reached the end of its
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Chemical life and the nature of the nitrate
time-bomb became obvious.
What happens to nitrate film as it ages?
From the moment of manufacture, cellulose
nitrate slowly decomposes. Some of the
chemical bonds between the cellulose and
the nitre groups break, resulting in release of
heat and of nitrogen oxides, mainly the diox¬
ide, which accelerates the process as the
reaction products accumulate. This decom¬
position may take many years, showing no
external signs of disintegration. However,
eventually the gases bleach the
photographic image (first stage of decom¬
position). The emulsion carrying that image
becomes sticky, then the reel becomes soft
and exudes blisters of "nitrate honey" and a
pungent smell. In the fourth and final stage,
the film congeals into a solid mass and then
Scene from Quo Vadis ? (Italy,
1912-1913), a historical spec¬
tacular directed by Enrico
Guazzoni which had a sensa¬
tional success in many coun¬
tries. Guazzoni was a pioneer
in constructing enormous
sets, which he designed
himself. This classic of the
early Italian cinema has been
reconstituted and transferred
onto non-inflammable film,
with the aid of the Italian Film
Archive, the Cineteca Italiana.
disintegrates into brown powder giving off
an acrid odour. This may occur rapidly, in a
matter of a few months.
The rate of decorpposition is temperature-
dependent, roughly doubling with every in¬
crease of 5°C. Storage, therefore, needs to
be as cold as possiblewith low humidity to
prevent the nitrogen dioxide from reacting
with the water in the atmosphere and the
photographic emulsion to form nitrous and
nitric acid which, in turn, attack the film. The
Preservation Commission of the Interna¬
tional Federation of Film Archives (FIAF)
recommends that nitrate be stored at 2°C
and 50 per cent to 60 per cent relative
humidity. Colder conditions, while more ef¬
fective in slowing the decomposition rate,
are economically impractical; actually, for
financial reasons, most archives are obliged
to store nitrate at 5°C or higher.
How do you preserve nitrate film? There
are no economically practical means of stop¬
ping the relentless decomposition: sooner or
later every reel of nitrate film will turn to
"honey" and then to brown powder. To
preserve the visual, audiovisual content of
silent and sound nitrate films, respectively,
copies must be madeon the more stable
safety film stocks whose potential life can be
estimated in hundreds of years. The copying
process can be complicated by the condition
of the nitrate reel. Shrinkage, brittleness,
scratches, tears and image fading are just
some of the problems that are often en¬
countered. Technical restoration and ar¬
chival printing is specialized work often far
removed from the mainstream expertise of
commercial film laboratories.
Once made to a satisfactory standard, the
new preservation copy must thereafter be
put into an administrative system which will
protect it from future degradation. It will
need to be stored at the correct temperature
and humidity, handled only by those
technically competent to do so, and its con¬
dition regularly monitored. Its existence,
description and use will need to be ap¬
propriately recorded, catalogued and con¬
trolled. And these steps are vital. No matter
how perfect the preservation copy, the ex¬
pense and effort spent in making it will be
wasted if the copy is damaged, worn, or
even lost. It is from the preservation copy
that duping copies (intermediate printing
masters) and, thence, new screening copies
in future will be derived, and whatever
blemishes it accumulates might mar the film
forever.
Already, film archives are being forced to
make value judgments about which films to
copy, and which films they will allow to
distintegrate and be permanently lost.
Already large portions of the work of many of
the world's outstanding film-makers have
vanished, or are at this moment in danger.
Does it really matter? How much would it
have mattered if 95 per cent of the works of
Shakespeare had been lost? Or if the cre¬
ations of Leonardo da Vinci, Tolstoy or
Beethoven had been discarded?
Whatever our response, there isn't much
time to answer the question!
Ray Edmondson and Henning Schou
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The electronic alternative
by Kerns H. Powers
FROM the beginnings of large-scale
television operations in the late
1940s, motion pictures on film have
been a major source of television pro¬
gramming. Even to this day, a majority of
programmes aired in prime viewing time are
originally produced on film, including those
produced exclusively for television. When
first aired, these films are converted to video
in a telecine machine (a combination film
projector/television camera) but are general¬
ly stored for later replay in the video-tape
medium.
Over the past decade, we have witnessed
an explosive growth of new media for
distributing motion picture features to
homes: Pay TV on cable and multipoint radio
distribution systems, prerecorded video
cassette tapes, and video-discs. Soon to
follow are the direct broadcasting satellites.
All of these media as well as the normal
television broadcast systems require a con¬
version of the feature from film to video.
We have also witnessed the spawning of
a new industry, that of the film-to-tape
transfer houses, of which there now exist
several dozen in the United States alone.
These transfers require colour correction as
a minimum, and may require timing ad¬
justments and other edits as well. Most
houses offer a broad range of video produc¬
tion and postproduction services. As a con¬
sequence of the less-than-orderly develop¬
ment of this new industry, a typical motion
picture feature when distributed by several
video media might find itself duplicated in
four or five electronic masters, no two of
which are identical.
In fact, these "dupes" are technically far
from being identical to the master film or its
release prints. Not only is the colorimetry a
variable, the resolution (the ability to resolve
fine detail in the images) more closely
matches 16 mm film than the 35mm master
stock. Furthermore, the features have been
KERNS H. POWERS, of the USA, is vice-
president for communications research, Radio
Corporation of America Laboratories, David
Sarnoff Research Centre, Princeton, New
Jersey. He is also chairman of a future
technologies working group of the Society of
Motion Picture and Television Engineers.
Charge-coupled device (CCD)
chips are used as electronic
"eyes" of a new portable
solid-state colour television
camera for news and sports
coverage. The CCD tech¬
nology is being developed for
electronic production of mo¬
tion pictures.
converted in frame rate from the twenty-four
¡mages per second of the original shooting
to sixty modified images per second in the
video format (sixty per second in the North
American and Japanese television stan¬
dards, fifty in Europe). These "modified" im¬
ages in the frame rate conversion are either
repeated in a nonuniform repeat cycle or are
blurred in a lap dissolve between two adja¬
cent frames of the film stock. Thus motion in
the scene may appear to the viewer to be
jerky or smeared out in the video format.
Finally, a substantial portion of the original
scene is usually cut out during the conver¬
sions. The aspect ratio (the ratio of the width
to the height of the displayed scene) has
been modified. The wide-screen format of
the cinema has given way to the narrower
aspect ratio (four-to-three) of television. It is
this latter mutilation of the original that has
the most significant effect on the viewer's
perception.
The recent developments of high-
definition television (HDTV) and digital video
technology promise for the future a way out
of this dilemma. Digital video effects
generators have been used for the past ten
years to create a vast array of electronic
special effects and image manipulations
during the postproduction (editing) of TV
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
programmes. These techniques are now
finding their way into motion picture films
with computer-generated animations and
electronic "opticals" (laboratory optical
special effects such as fades, wipes, and lap
dissolves).
In digital video, the electronic signals that
represent the red, green, and blue primary
colour components of each picture element
(pixel) of the scene are digitized into bits
(binary digits) for storage in computer-like
memories, and the images are processed
under computer control with "software"
flexibility. A "studio quality" television
signal in either the 525- or 625-line stan¬
dards requires digital encoding at a rate of
approximately 200 million bits per second.
High definition television promises for the
future a TV system of resolution equal to that
of 35mm film, a widescreen aspect ratio, and
a universal frame rate selected to minimize
the image deterioration in the frame rate
conversions for all release media. A digital
HDTV signal would require encoding and
recording at rates exceeding one thousand
million bits per second, a value beyond the
current state-of-art.
Although HDTV cameras (even with
analog signals) are expected to be more ex¬
pensive than quality film cameras for many
years to come, their use could be cost-
effective relative to film in shooting because
of the immediacy in screening the results of
a shoot. In any event, the use of improved
resolution digital video technology in elec-
This projection device with a
sprocket camshaft was made
in 1908.
tronic postproduction could be cost-effective
very soon, even if both original shooting and
release are accomplished on film.
One significant advantage of postproduct¬
ion in digital technology is that a single
digital master tape can be generated during
editing under the watchful artistic eye of the
producer or director, with the assurance that
all subsequent copies whether they be film
release prints or television video-tapes will
be derived from either the digital master
itself or identical clones of it. A property of
the digital video format is that copies can be
made through multiple (conceivably, hun¬
dreds of) generations without errors in col-
orimetry, contrast range, brightness level, or
pixel position.
The digital master can be archived on
digital video-tape having far less suscep¬
tibility to magnetic fields or "print through"
than is characteristic of analog tape media.
It is believed that digital optical video-discs
will have even longer storage life with,
possibly, higher storage density (bits per
cubic metre) than video-tape. Current
estimates of the near term technology
predict that a two-hour sound motion picture
feature of television studio quality (220
million bits per second) can be stored digital¬
ly with ruggedness for multiple replays and
in convenient environments for many
decades of life in a volume of 1,500 cubic
centimetres on tape cassette and 1,200 cu
cm on disc, as compared with 4,000 cu cm
in 16mm film cans. Each of these numbers
should be multiplied by a factor of about five
for wide screen HDTV quality and 35mm
film.
The major impediment to this panacea for
electronic archiving is not the technological
development required but is, rather, the lack
of common standards. There not only exist
three different frame rates to contend with,
but motion picture films are released in no
fewer than five different aspect ratios spann¬
ing the range from 1.33 to 2.35. An ideal
solution to the standards problem would be
for the motion picture and television in
dustries to reach an agreement on a single
aspect ratio and a single frame rate to be us¬
ed worldwide in future productions, both
electronic and film. Backward compatibility
with both existing cinemas and television
systems can be achieved through standards
conversions for the release film and tape
media.
The standards discussions have com¬
menced for high definition television within
the Comité Consultatif International des
Radiocommunications (CCIR), the study
arm of the International Telecommunica¬
tions Union, based in Geneva. The studies
are being supported by the world's major
Broadcasting Unions such as the European
Broadcasting Union and by the international
engineering professional societies such as
the Society of Motion Picture and Television
Engineers in the USA and the British
Kinematograph, Sound and Television
Society in the United Kingdom. The CCIR
has set as a target date its Plenary Meetings
in 1986 for approval of a recommendation
for HDTV standards for television studio use
and for international programme exchange.
Hopefully, the common worldwide stan¬
dards developed for television will also serve
the needs for electronic production and ar¬
chiving of motion picture films as well.
I Kerns H. Powers
Regina Linnanheimo and Otso
Pera in a scene from Nuroena
Nukkunut (1937). This Finnish
film directed by Teuvo Tulio is
thought to be lost. (See article
page 17).
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
.Jill
|r|r[:F
HI
t^at
il rediscovered epic of the silent screen
NAPOIEON
mate« a tome-back
by Roy Malkin
ON three evenings in July 1983, the
3,700-seat auditorium of the Palais
des Congrès in Paris was packed
with expectant audiences impatient to see a
film which had been made over half a cen¬
tury before, had been received with acclaim
by public and critics, and had then virtually
disappeared without trace. The film was
Napoléon, the greatest creation of the
legendary French director Abel Gance (its
full title is actually Napoléon vu par Abel
Gance). It traces the career of Napoleon
ROY MALKIN is assistant editor of the English
edition of the Unesco Courier.
Bonaparte from his schooldays to the mo¬
ment when, as heir to the ideals of the
French Revolution, he took command of
the army of Italy in 1796.
Napoléon was vast in its conception and
proportions. The version seen by Paris au¬
diences in 1983 lasted five and a quarter
hours (one version prepared by Gance and
shown to critics in 1927 lasted nine); it was
accompanied by an orchestra of forty-eight
musicians playing a score specially compos¬
ed and conducted by U.S. composer Carl
Davis; and its last twenty minutes revealed
the revolutionary wide screen "triptych"
process called Polyvision which Gance had
invented, twenty-five years before
Cinerama, to present epic scenes using three
simultaneously projected images (in one in¬
stance Napoleon is shown in close up on the
central panel while his marching army ap¬
pears on the two flanking screens).
At the end of the performance surviving
veterans of the film actors, actresses,
technicians went on stage and received the
acclaim of the audience. Two men, one ab¬
sent, one present, also shared the applause.
The first was Abel Gance himself, who had
died two years before at the age of ninety-
two before he could see the homecoming of
the prodigal son he had created. The second
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Presentation of Napoléon af a
London cinema in November
1980, with orchestra con¬
ducted by Carl Davis.
was British film director and historian
Kevin Brownlow, who had reconstituted
Gance's film after many years of painstak¬
ing efforts, with the collaboration of the
Cinémathèque Française, the British Film
Institute, and film archives in many parts of
the world.
Brownlow has written a book, Napoleon,
Abel Gance's Classic Film*, which vividly
describes how Napoléon was made and then
reconstructed. In it he tells how his
obsessive enthusiasm for Gance's work was
first kindled in 1954 when, as a fifteen-year-
old film-mad London schoolboy, he found
in a suburban film library two reels of a film
called Napoleon Bonaparte and the French
Revolution and acquired it for his hand-
cranked home projector. "The two reels
contained such superb sequences that they
left me breathless," he wrote. "The in¬
troduction of the Marseillaise, the pursuit
of Napoleon across Corsica, the storm at
sea intercut with the storm in the Conven¬
tion. For someone accustomed to showing
Felix the Cat to bored relatives, this was an
unforgettable event."
The reels were of 9.5 mm film, a gauge
invented for home cinemas. If they are so
good, he thought, what must the rest be
like? He set off combing through junk
shops, photographic stores and old film
libraries. Miraculously he found more reels,
and the more he found the better, he
thought, the film became. He began show¬
ing it to his friends. "I felt it was up to me
to do what little I could to show my modest
'rediscovered' version to as many people as
possible. I set up twin turntables, selected a
range of 78 rpm gramophone records and
presented the film with full orchestral ac¬
companiment, the thunder of which was
equal to any Napoleonic cannonade. My
audiences were always stunned".
Film critics and historians began to hear
about Brownlow's version of Napoléon and
some came to see it for themselves.
Brownlow began to find out what he could
published in the UK by Jonathan Cape and in the US
by Alfred A. Knopf.
about Gance, discovered that he was still
alive, wrote him a fan letter and received a
warm reply. He found that Gance was one
of the great figures of the early cinema, the
self-taught, daemonic, epic figures who
were inevitably drawn to epic subjects. He
had been born in 1889 and by the time he
began to make Napoléon in 1925 was
already famous as the director of an anti¬
war film, J'accuse (1919) with an extraor¬
dinary final sequence in which the
mutilated dead of World War I rise and
march towards the audience to ask whether
their loss was justified, and La Roue (1922)
a film about railway workers in which he
pioneered rapid cutting techniques to create
rhythm and pace.
Gance may have been unique in that he
seems to have believed that the cinema had
a kind of divine mission. A speech he made
during the making of Napoléon to the hun¬
dreds of extras (strikers from the Renault
factory at Billancourt) taking part in the
siege of Toulon gives something of the
measure of the man. "It is imperative that
this film should allow us to enter once and
for all into the temple of the arts by way of
the huge portal of history. An unspeakable
anguish grips me at the thought that my will
and the gift of my life even are nothing if
you do not give me your undivided loyalty
and devotion... The task is without
parallel... My friends, all the screens of the
world await you!" When interviewing
veterans of the film in the 1970s Brownlow
found that they often made a slip of the
tongue, saying "Napoleon" when they
meant "Gance".
Shooting of Napoléon began in January
1925, and ended late the following year. A
film of the filming and photos taken at the
time show some of the ambitious technical
innovations for which Napoléon would
become celebrated: a camera mounted on a
sledge plunging down a bank of snow to
bring animation to the filming of a
children's snowfight; a camera lens sur¬
rounded by a sponge so that the fighting
boys can punch it; a camera mounted on
horseback and powered by cylinders of
compressed air to film a chase in Corsica;
remote control cameras; frames of a
The ghosts in the Convention, a sequence
regarded by Gance as the best in the pic¬
ture. Before leaving Paris to join the Army of
Italy, Napoleon visits the empty meeting hall
of the National Convention, the Assembly
that governed France from 1792 to 1795.
Gradually the hall is peopled with phantoms.
In foreground are the ghosts of the guillotin¬
ed revolutionary leaders : (left to right)
Saint-Just (played by Gance himself),
Robespierre, Danton, Marat (Antonin Ar¬
taud), and Couthon. They tell Napoleon that
the Revolution will die if it does not expand
beyond France; he promises them that he
will liberate oppressed peoples.
pillowfight which divide into nine separate
images in a checkerboard effect; a swinging
pendulum camera to create sweeping move¬
ment in a scene, involving over a thousand
extras, in the Hall of the Convention, the
Assembly that governed France during the
most critical period of the Revolution; the
siege of Toulon so realistic that each night
wounded extras were hospitalized; a
machine devised to simulate a storm at sea
that doused Albert Dieudonné, the actor
who played Napoleon, with thousands of
litres of water rushing down chutes from
massive barrels poised above.
Then came a financial crisis, the realiza¬
tion that the five more Napoleon films
would never be made, a race against time as
Gance prepared a three-and-a-half hour
version of the film, accompanied by music
composed and directed by Arthur Honeg-
ger, for its triumphant première at the Paris
Opéra, the later showing of the version
definitive to the critics. Then... silence.
There were paralysing legal disputes with
distributors who, in France and elsewhere,
wished to reduce the film to a length they
could exploit more easily. But above all the
success of The Jazz Singer, the first film
with synchronized speech, in the same year
of 1 927 , heralded the new age of talking pic¬
tures. Cinemas now had to invest in the new
sound equipment; it was unlikely that they
would buy the machines needed by Gance's
Polyvision process. Gance's great project
foundered.
Gance's material was chopped up into
many different versions, "adjusted" for^
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Marat, played by the French
actor and poet Antonin Ar¬
taud, is stabbed in his bath by
Charlotte Corday in a scene
from Napoléon inspired by the
painting by Louis David.
In Spain during the Second
World War Abel Gance
prepared to make a film about
the celebrated matador
Manolete. He wrote the script
andshot a few scenes (such as
the one shown here with the
Spanish actress Isabel de
Pomés) but the film was never
completed. It is thought that a
300-metre fragment of
Manolete discovered in 1983
by the Spanish Film Archive,
the Filmoteca Española, is all
that remains of the project.
audiences around the world. Sequences
were changed or cut. Discarded scenes were
thrown away or stored and forgotten.
Prints were acquired by collectors who
showed them to their families. Bravura se¬
quences were occasionally resurrected to
whet the appetites of enthusiasts. But for
many years fragments big and small of
Gance's 1927 Napoléon lay forgotten all
over the world like so many pieces of a
jigsaw puzzle waiting to be reassembled to
reveal its grand design.
Interest in Gance seems to have revived in
the mid-1950s. Henri Langlois, the head of
the Cinémathèque Française, who had
preserved several versions of the film,
showed the final triptychs at the 1955
Venice Film Festival and in the same year a
truncated sound version Gance had made in
1935 was successfully shown in Paris. By
this time Brownlow was working as a film
editor, had met Gance several times, and
was still hunting for Napoléon material.
But there were endless difficulties. One trail
which began in the Paris Flea Market led to
the discovery of a rare print of fresh
material which he tried to incorporate into
his growing version, only to find that they
were the same scenes he already had, but
shot with different cameras. "I wondered
how many versions of Napoléon one might
have seen in 1927... and how difficult it
would be to produce one authentic ver¬
sion." (In fact at the end of his book he lists
no less than 19 versions of Napoléon
prepared between 1927 and 1982.) He met a
collector who showed him a rare 17.5 mm
print of the Opéra version. But what he
wanted to do was to restore the film on the
professional gauge of 35 mm on which it
was originally shot.
His chance came at the end of the 1960s.
As Brownlow tells the story, "A strange
series of circumstances enabled me almost
forced me to put my hands on a substan¬
tial print and to start the reconstruction. A
year or so later, Abel Gance undertook his
own version which, with extra shooting,
emerged as Bonaparte and the Revolution.
He gave me access to all his negatives. Extra
scenes came, literally, from all over the
world, thanks to Jacques Ledoux, head of
the Royal Belgian Film Archive. When he
heard what I was doing he contacted every
archive that had even a reel of the picture
and told them to send it to me. When I had
finished, the reconstruction was shown by
the National Film Theatre in London,
followed by the American Film Institute's
Theatre in Washington and the Pacific Film
Archive in Berkeley. At the last show was
the American director Francis Ford Cop¬
pola who said 'What a terrific experience.
Wouldn't it be wonderul to do it again with
three big screens and a live orchestra
conducted by my father?' " But nothing
happened for several years. The project was
completed but no one seemed interested in
showing the film.
Then in 1979 an American named Bill
Pence decided to present it at the Film
Festival he directed at Telluride, a Col¬
orado mining town in the Rocky Moun¬
tains. The 89-year-old Gance was persuad¬
ed to attend. As Brownlow tells it, "In this
picturesque mining town, there was no
building large enough to accommodate the
film with its three-screen Polyvision climax,
so the organizers held the show in the open
airfrom 10:30 at night to 3:30 the next
morning. The cold was intense and we'all
felt like survivors from the Retreat from
Moscow. When the Polyvision sequence
began, I was as overwhelmed as everyone
else. For although I had seen the rest of the
film hundreds of times, this was the first
time I had seen it complete with its three-
screen ending. It was an incredible moment.
What the 89-year-old Gance thought, half a
century after he had made it, I could not
wait to find out. He had watched it all from
his hotel window overlooking the park, and
when I raced up to his room I found him
surrounded by enthusiastic admirers. He
pronounced it 'as good as the première'...
He received a splendid ovation from the
crowd, despite their frostbitten hands."
Nothing could outdo that, Brownlow
thought. He was wrong, however, for in
1980 a British TV Company, with the
British Film Institute, sponsored the first
screening of the reconstruction with a live
orchestra playing the Carl Davis score.
Then Francis Ford Coppola followed up his
idea and brought the film, with a live or¬
chestra conducted by his father Carmine, to
Radio City Music Hall in New York, where
it received a rapturous welcome from pack¬
ed houses of 6,000 spectators. Gance was by
this time too frail to attend. "Using the
backstage phone we contacted him in Paris
at the end of the performance and let him
listen to the wave upon wave of applause
and cheers. He was overwhelmed. He wept.
(So did we.)" There followed an American
tour, a showing at the Colosseum in Rome
to an audience of 10,000 on a screen 50
metres wide with a 90-piece orchestra, a
showing at the 1981 Edinburgh Festival.
Meanwhile Abel Gance had died while the
acclaim for his film poured in. Then came
the final triumphant homecoming of the
film to Paris under the auspices of the
Cinémathèque Française. "I decided,"
Brownlow says, "that this occasion would
symbolize the end of the reconstruction of
Napoléon. But now Nelly Kaplan, a close
associate of Gance in the 1950s and 1960s,
has produced a documentary about the
making of the film called Abel Gance et son
Napoléon. And in her film is a shot from
Napoléon I have never seen before!"
Roy Malkin
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
WANTED!
The search is on for the world's missing films
by Sam Kula
THE statistics on "lost" filmsmore than half the films
produced before 1930 are not known to have survived
indicate the magnitude of the loss, but they do not convey
the sense of what has been lost, the diminishment of the world's
cultural heritage that resulted from sixty years of neglect, accident
and acts of vandalism.
The losses occurred with equal severity in every type of film¬
making, fiction and non-fiction, film as documentary record and film
as artistic expression. The loss is equally tragic whatever the intent
of the film-maker, but perhaps the loss that is most poignant, most
affecting, is the feature film. These were films seen by millions, a vital
part of the popular culture, and their total disappearance is almost
a personal loss for everyone who shares that culture.
Several months ago the members of the International Federation
of Film Archives (FIAF) were asked to nominate one title "not known
to have survived" in any country, as either representative of the
"lost" films in their country, or as a particularly significant loss due
to its historic role in the national production, or because of the impor¬
tance of the film-makers. The members were also asked to send a
still from the film, or a photograph of a poster if no still survived, and
some of the choices may have been based on the fact that the ar¬
chives held a good quality still, rather than on the relative historical
or cultural significance of one film among several possibilities.
The films represented on this and the two following pagesall
recorded as missingillustrate that losses have occurred in every
sector of the industry. Neither the size of the budget, the scale of the
production, the celebrity of the stars, nor the reputation of the direc¬
tor appear to have guaranteed that a film would survive. The losses
include both huge commercial successes and artistic successes that
apparently failed to find an audience in their day.
What is particularly frustrating is that so many "firsts" have ap¬
parently been lost. Films which marked the beginnings of serious
film-making in a country, or which film historians now recognize as
milestones in the development of the art of the cinema. That frustra¬
tion, and the hope that the films have survived, is worldwide.
SAM KULA is director of Canada's National Film, Television and Sound
Archives.
India, for example, is still searching for Alam Ara (1931), the first
sound film produced in that country; Argentina has nominated El
Apóstol (1917) among the many critical losses in that country,
because it is the first feature length animated film known to have
been produced anywhere in the world; Canada still believes that
Evangeline (191 3), the first feature film produced in that country still
lives, somewhereafter all film that was buried in the permafrost of
the Yukon Territory for almost fifty years (the Dawson City Collec¬
tion) was recently discovered and restored; New Zealand would
dearly love to recover The Birth of New Zealand (1921), not only the
first feature film produced in New Zealand, but an extremely impor¬
tant historical document as well; Australia has not yet given up hope
that The Story of the Kelly Gang (1906), arguably the first feature
length film ever produced anywhere in the world, has survived,
despite the fact that "The Last Film Search", the systematic search
throughout Australia for surviving nitrate film that was launched laót
year (more than 300,000 feet have been recovered), has not yet
unearthed a print; and Sweden is firmly convinced that a film such
as De Landsflyktige (1921), by a director with the international
reputation of Mauritz Stiller, a film sold to thirty-two foreign countries,
still exists, probably under a name that was arbitrarily assigned by
the local distributor (it was called In Self Defense in the USA, Guard¬
ed Lips in the UK).
The phrase "not known to have survived" rather than the more
dramatic "lost" is a necessary qualification since there is no com¬
prehensive world-wide catalogue or inventory of films held by ar¬
chives, and there are thousands of films of all ages still in the vaults
of producers, distributors and laboratories throughout the world. In
addition films are continually being recovered from the attics and
basements of film-makers and their descendants, or discovered in
other archives where they have been hiding under assumed names.
If publication of these stills, therefore, results in someone coming
forward with a copy of a film proclaimed as "lost", the members of
FIAF will be delighted. The search continues in every country with
an established moving image archive. It is a race against time for
films produced before 1 950, films of the nitrate era, and if this article
can lead to the discovery and restoration of just one of these "lost"
films, the collaborative effort that this article represents will be judg¬
ed to have been well worthwhile.
Der Golem, Ger¬
many 1914. Direct¬
ed by Heinrich
Gateen.
Paul Wegener in
the title role in the
first version of the
story, scripted by
Wegener and the
director.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
.retí! ¡g RJI
« T^ir
V '
~t'.
n
Alam Ara, /nd/'a
7931. Directed by
Ardeshir M. Irani.
India 's first sound
film was a romantic
drama with music,
revolving around
the King of Kumar-
pur and his two
queens.
Photo National Film
Archive of India, PoOna
Evangeline, Canada
1913. Directed by
E.P. Sullivan and
W.H. Cavanaugh.
Believed to be the
first feature-length
dramatic film pro¬
duced in North
America, Evange¬
line deals with the
expulsion of the
Acadians from Nova
Scotia by the British
in 1755.
Photo ( National Film,
Television and Sound At
chives/Public Archives of
Canada, Ottawa
13 aüátllurrifiriü
Barro Humano, Brazil 1929. Directed by
Adhemar Gonzaga.
Gracia Morena starred in this social
drama regarded as an important
historical and cultural document, as
significant for its portrayal of life at that
time as it was in the evolution of the
Brazilian cinema.
i	 ,-v;i "H .i,'
ff 1 ' ' *
Death of Dan Kelly & Steve Hart
The Story of the Kelly Gang, Australia
1906. Directed by Charles Tait.
The first Australian feature film was
based on fact and helped to establish the
bushranging mythology as an important
element in Australian popular culture.
Photo © National Film Archives/National Library
of Australia, Canberra
"*,
The Greatest Thing in Life, USA 1918.
Directed by D. W. Griffith.
Any film by Griffith is a vital link in the
evolution of film technique. Lillian Gish
(above) who played the leading role op¬
posite Robert Harron, insists that this
was one of the best films Griffith ever
directed.
El Apóstol, Argentina 1917. Directed by
Angel Ducaud.
Produced by Federico Valle, El
Apóstol is thought to be the first feature-
length animated film in the history of
cinema.
ê *
! C^
f^V^-
V^^AV^i
_u, fljTJfl^
Sk^>^V
\ ® Jf\
^ ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
De Landsflyktige
("The Exiles "),
Sweden 1921.
Directed by Mauritz
Stiller.
Despite its con¬
siderable interna¬
tional successthe
film was sold to 32
countriesno copy
is known to have
survived.
Photu Cinnmaleket.
Sven ska Filntin$tilulel.
Stockholm
- CHOU T1ATÄ0
WELTO^
Sàtit 5 H lÜFtttE rj« '
*LAr-
Hll'lllllll lllllilll
bll. br lr.:-: fa ,
¿ml LV 4
-.* (
11 FUSUCO
m Revolución Zapatista, Mexico
1914.
This programme is the only
trace known to have survived
of this historically important
feature-length documentary
on the career of Emiliano
Zapata and the Mexican
revolution of 1910.
Photo Cmetucj Nacional, Mnxico Cil y
FT
Napasta, Romania 1928.
Directed by Ghità Popescu.
Ecaterina Nitulescu
Sahigian featured in this film
based on a play by Ion Luca
Caragiale.
Photo Archiva N.iMonal.a de Fl
Bucarest
Fager er lien ("Beautiful is the Mountain), Norway 1925. Directed
by Harry I varson.
This romantic drama featured Aase Bye and Olafr Havrevold, two
leading actors with the National Theatre of Norway. Photo also
shows Oscar Larsen in the role of the grandfather.
Phoio '. fvors* Filminstiiutt,
Sachta Pohfbenych Idei ("The Shaft of Buried Ideas"),
Czechoslovakia 1921. Directed by Rudolf Myzet.
A drama set in the Ostrava mines in 1918. The screenwriter, A.L.
Havel, incorporated the poetry of Petr Bezruc into the intertitles.
Pholo Filmovy Archivi'Czesfcoslovensky Filmoby Ustav. Prague
The Birth of New
Zealand, New Zealand
1921. Directed by Harr¬
ington Reynolds.
All that is known to
have survived of this
historic panorama of
European settlement in
New Zealand is this
original handbill.
ilm Vivid Pares of New Zealand's, earty History Revealed on
th r Vrrvn In a Sarins uf FasrLnatinff inrj Exquisito Scmibr.
THE COLOSSAL HISTORICAL FILM CLASSIC
The Birth of New
Zealand.
SEW ZEALAND ClHtHA L NTE It PR I i. ts LTD.
W11U «linutuL *lt*BEiqii lu
dtmlv Mnu Rarirdlaii oí
044 Flit OF IHII« Wr-UNBB.lt UNO HHtAlIMEhT!
- .-lli 11.I-*. h.|ii. nun ..r 1he TfqjU I ribn ..liui
i i r V i ain . \t* .'
G0CT9 OWN CuUSTKY.
/
1
U
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The video grapevine by ítalo Manzi
OVER the past three years, film
enthusiasts throughout the world
have acquired a new passion. As
happens with many literary and artistic
movements, a number of individuals, quite
independently and spontaneously felt a
need whose fulfilment was to become a
world-wide phenomenon.
It all started with an apparatus invented
by the Japanese the video-recorder. As
everyone knows, video-recorders enable
one to record a television programme in
one's absence and to view a programme or
a film again or at a more convenient time.
From the moment the video-recorder ap¬
peared on the market, new and hitherto un¬
dreamed of possibilities were opened up for
the film enthusiast.
Without wishing to underrate the
achievements of preceding or succeeding
decades, it is probably true to say that the
period that most interests film enthusiasts is
that of the 1940s and 1950s. Apart from
films of certain specific directors, or those
that can be classified in "cycles" or
"festivals", art cinemas are usually reluc-
ITALO MANZI, Argentine film critic, has
published a number of books and articles in
Argentina and elsewhere. He was formerly
director of foreign language studies at the
Faculty of Psychology of the university of
Buenos Aires and is currently working with
Unesco in Paris.
tant to show "ordinary" films of that
period because they are considered
wrongly to be of little importance. Some
of them are, in fact, exceptional produc¬
tions that have been unjustifiably forgot¬
ten; all of them, however, are typical of an
epoch and have a special flavour of their
own.
Thanks to national television services,
which do not have the same "scrupulous"
approach as the art cinemas, and to ex¬
changes amongst collectors in different
countries, the film enthusiast can now not
only view but also own copies of these films
which, up to three years ago, he could never
even hope to see.
Film enthusiasts are now running short
of space to house their collections, which
are growing at an alarming rate. An increas¬
ingly complex and fascinating traffic in
cassettes of films has begun in many coun¬
tries which is conducted either by mail or
with the help of well-disposed friends who
travel. Although this may appear to be in
breach of copyright, the fact is that collec¬
tors derive no monetary advantage from the
cassettes since they only view them in
private and exchange them with fellow
collectors.
Let us take a typical example. Mr. X,
who lives in Paris, owns two video-
recorders. In addition to recording
whatever interests him on French television,
he has friends in Barcelona, Berlin, London
and Buenos Aires who send him recordings
made from their local television pro¬
grammes. But Mr. X is, in turn a friend of
Mr. Y, who has friends who are doing the
same thing in Rome, Vienna and Brussels.
Mr. Z, on the other hand, has friends in
Finland. Someone else who lives in Brazil
knows somebody who records for him what
interests him on Rome television, but
before they are despatched to Rio the
cassettes make a stop in Paris at the home
of Mr. X who copies what interests him op
his friends Y and Z, who in turn have
friends who... and so on ad infinitum.
People have always collected 16mm
films, but never on a massive scale. Now,
thanks to this new video-recording hobby,
countless films, which for decades were
nowhere to be seen and which otherwise
would have been lost, are circulating again.
In this way also an entire cinematic tradi¬
tion can be rescued from oblivion and be
subjected to a new appraisal.
This is what has happened to a fringe
cinema such as that of Argentina. For more
than a decade, from about 1936 to 1946, the
Argentine cinema was the most popular in
the Spanish-speaking world. Outside that
area it was known through a number of
post- 1950 films such as those of Leopoldo
Torre-Nilsson and a few others that won
prizes at international festivals. Carlos
Gardel's films are also known, but none of
them is truly Argentine since they were
made in Paris or New York.
During the golden decade of the Argen¬
tine cinema Buenos Aires was the capital of
the Spanish-speaking world. Its streets,
parks and places of entertainment knew no
frontiers. The fashions, speech and
sophistication of Buenos Aires, made
known by Argentine film stars, were im¬
itated in the other Spanish-speaking coun¬
tries. The picture thus conveyed, although
by no means false, was incomplete, since
nothing was shown of life in certain social
classes.
Nedda Francy, a blonde of the Marlene
Dietrich type, paraded her charms in Monte
Criollo and Palermo. Mecha Ortiz, the
The Argentine actress Imperio Argentina,
one of the great stars of the first half of the
century, with Spanish actor Miguel Ligero in
the Spanish film La Hermana San Sulpicio
(1934) directed by Florian Rey. Once
thought to have disappeared, La Hermana
San Sulpicio has recently been shown on
television thanks to a copy preserved by a
film enthusiast.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The young Eva Duarte in La
Pródiga, directed by Mario
Soffici in 1945. Forgotten for
almost 40 years the film is only
now being shown for the first
time. It was made shortly
before Eva Duarte became Eva
Perón when she married the
President of the Argentine
Republic, who apparently
refused to allow his wife to ap¬
pear on the cinema screen.
Not even photos were publish¬
ed of Eva as an actress.
Argentine Garbo with the inimitable voice,
made her mark on the Spanish-speaking
world in such films as Los Muchachos de
Antes no Usaban Gomina, Safo and El
Cante del Cisne. There were also Mirtha
Legrand, Amelia Bence, Paula Singerman
and the great comic actresses Nini Marshall
and Olinda Bozán.
But the actress who perhaps achieved the
greatest and most lasting fame was Libertad
Lamarque who immortalized so many
tangos in Besos Brujos, Ayúdame a Vivir
and Madreselva. After a quarrel with the
supporting actress in La Cabalgata del Cir¬
co (1943), who was none other than Eva
Duartesoon to become Evita Perónshe
was obliged to emigrate to Mexico where,
initially directed by Bunuel (in the excellent
Gran Casino, so belittled by "serious"
historians of the cinema) and then appear¬
ing in tear-jerking melodramas, she won
new laurels that have lost none of their
freshness, since she is now pursuing a suc¬
cessful career in her native country.
Then there are the actors. José Gola,
Roberto Airaldi, Hugo del Carril and Juan
Carlos Thorny must be counted among the
matinee idols, and Enrique Muiño, Enrique
Serrano and Elias Alippi among the
character actors.
Many of these films were, of course,
"potboilers", but there were also more im¬
portant works which marked their epoch
and have lost none of their quality with the
passage of time: Viento Norte (Mario Sof¬
fici, 1937), Asi es la Vida (Francisco Mu-
jica, 1939), Prisioneros de la Tierra (Mario
Soffici, 1939), Crimen a las Tres (Luis
Saslavsky, 1935), La Guerra Gaucha (Lucas
Demare, 1942), and so on.
Thanks to the video-recorder, students
and enthusiasts have been able to recover
and preserve many products of a cinema,
which in those days had an average output
of fifty films a year. They have also been
able to follow the careers of such interesting
and creative directors as Luis Saslavsky,
Alberto de Zavalía, Francisco Mujic and
Mario Soffici, as well as of some foreign
directors such as Pierre Chenal who spent a
large part of his career in Argentina where
he produced at least two of his best films
El Muerto Falta a la Cita, a thriller that was
very modern for its time (1944), and Todo
un Hombre, based on the novel by Miguel
de Unamuno (1943).
Similarly it is possible to follow the
careers of a large number of non-Spanish-
speaking actors, who appeared in many
films during those years of plenty, in¬
cluding Emma Gramática (two films),
A ä
W
^PT^ Jr M L^bbWJ
H W
Florence Marly (three films), June Marlowe
(five films) and Rachel Bérendt.
Before we leave the Argentine cinema we
should mention two examples of rescued
films which have been of unusual
significance. The first was not an Argentine
but a Spanish film the version of La Her¬
mana San Sulpicio directed by Florian Rey
in 1934although the story began in
Argentina where the star of the film, Im¬
perio Argentina, one of the international
cinema's most authentic superstars, was
born.
Until a year ago, to own a film in which
this actress appeared was a film enthusiast's
dream. A cassette of the film in question,
recorded in Argentina, where the film had
been shown on television, was circulating in
Paris. Shortly afterwards, in June 1983,
Spanish television decided to broadcast a
film cycle, in the presence of the actress
herself, which would include all her
available films. Nine of them were collected
including two made in Argentina, the Ger¬
man film Carmen, la de Triana, made in
Berlin in 1938, and La Tosca (Italy, 1940),
in which Imperio, supported by Rossano
Brazzi and Michel Simon, was directed by
Jean Renoir assisted by Luchino Visconti.
Poster for Mario Soffid's
Viento Norte (1937), a key
work in the history of the
Argentine cinema.
Photos & Cinemateca Argentina, Buenos Aires
It was also planned to include La Her¬
mana San Sulpicio in the series. Only one
16mm copy of the film survives and it is
owned by a Buenos Aires collector who had
lent it from time to time to Argentine televi¬
sion and had promised to lend it to the
Spaniards. But at the last minute he had
misgivings about sending it overseas. Short¬
ly before, the Paris enthusiast mentioned
earlier had made a copy of the film which he
sent to a Madrid enthusiast in exchange for
a cassette of another film of the same ac¬
tress. The Spaniard lent his cassette to the
television service and the public were able to
become acquainted, or to renew acquain¬
tance, with a delightful, subtly and
unusually irreverent film based on the novel
by Armando Palacio Valdés.
In our second example the rescue of the
film was not due to video-recording (pirate
copies are said to be on sale in London but
this has proved impossible to verify) but to
more complex reasons of a political nature.
The film in question was La Pródiga, made
by Mario Soffici in 1945 and starring Eva
Duarte. She had already played secondary
roles in a number of films and a bigger role
in La Cabalgata del Circo, but this was the
first time she had played the leading role in
a big-budget film, based on a famous work
by Alarcón.
The filming took place at a time of
political unrest (Eva's marriage to Perón
and the Iatter's nomination as President).
Obviously the film could not be screened.
Photographs of the actress in this film were
never seen and people even came to doubt
whether it had ever been completed. It was
also said that all copies had been destroyed.
Now, forty years later, the film is going
to be screened. Apparently one of the pro¬
ducers saved a copy which lay in a safe in
Uruguay awaiting the day of its resurrec¬
tion. Film enthusiasts in search of rare
items are now anxiously looking out for a
cassette of La Pródiga which, after the suc¬
cess of the opera Evita, and all that has been
written about this controversial personali¬
ty, will enable us freely to see the real Evita.
H ítalo Manzi
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
INDIA
It's never too late...
by Paramesh Krishnan Nair
Afew years ago, a well-known Indian
film pioneer told me that of the forty
odd films he had made he con¬
sidered that only two or three were worth
preserving in the National Film Archive of In¬
dia. This in a way reflects the attitude of most
of our film-makers to archival preservation of
their films.
The average film-maker in India does not
believe that what he is doing is of any
historical consequence, let alone of cultural
interest. For him, as for his colleagues
elsewhere, film-making is first and foremost
a commercial proposition meant for mass
consumption. His primary interest is to get
his investment back with a reasonable profit
within the shortest time span. Setting aside
one of the fifty odd prints made for the initial
release of a film would not cost him much
compared with his total production costs,
but his attitude would be: "Why should I
leave a new print lying idle in the Archive
vaults when it could be bringing in a good
return on the screens of local cinemas?"
The multi-theatre simultaneous release
craze means that the producer/distributor
has to make several prints from the original
picture and sound negative. He is not in the
least concerned that every time a new print
is made the useful life of the original
negative is reduced. In the Indian film in¬
dustry it is not customary to make inter-
negatives or inter-positives. The "Colour
PARAMESH KRISHNAN NAIR is director of
the National Film Archive of India. He has
taken part in a wide range of activities in India
and internationally to promote the safeguard
and protection of moving images and con¬
tributed, as a specialist, to the drafting of the
Unesco Recommendation. He has published a
number of studies and articles on aspects of
cinema.
Reverso Inter-negative" process is prac¬
tically unknown and all release copies are
printed from the original negatives. As a
result, a large number of original negatives
of highly successful films have been damag¬
ed beyond repair due to indiscriminate
duplication of positive prints, both 35mm
and 16mm.
In India the cinema has never been ac¬
corded high priority. To the intelligentsia and
educationists the cinema was something to
be looked down on with contempt and it was
often bracketed with social evils such as bet¬
ting, gambling, drinking and prostitution.
But the masses developed a passion for the
cinema, finding in it an instant escape
medium in which to forget the drudgery of
daily life. They patronized it so ardently that
the Indian cinema has by now become the
most prolific of all the national cinemas.
With a stupendous annual output of over
750 feature films, in fourteen major
languages, which find their outlet through
some ten thousand permanent cinema
houses throughout the country, the cinema
industry has become very much a part of the
Indian reality. Audiences have lived with it,
laughed with it, wept with it and virtually
grown up with it. It has shaped their lives,
their attitudes, values and consciousness.
Neverthless, its importance has only
recently been recognized. As a result,
although India started making films at the
turn of the century, at the same time as the
rest of the world, nobody thought we should
have a Film Archive to take care of our film
heritage. Even after independence, it took
us nearly seventeen years to start collecting
films in an organized manner. By that time
some sixty to seventy per cent of our pre-
independence output had vanished. Films of
that period were not available for love or
money. Their negatives had crumbled and
turned to powder, or after extraction of the
silver from the nitro-cellulose base, had
been turned into bangles and ladies'
handbags.
One such film was Alam Ara (1 931 , in Hin¬
di), the first Indian talkie, which is still not
traceable. When contacted two years before
his death, Ardeshir M. Irani, the maker of
this film and the man who brought sound to
Indian cinema, told us that he had kept some
reels of the film in his office at the Imperial
Studio (now Jyothi Studio). But his son
Shapoorji took us aside and confided: "The
old man still thinks the reels are lying around
in his office, but I know for certain that they
have been disposed of as junk. I myself did
it as they were creating a fire hazard". What
a pity! The man had no idea that he had
allowed one of the most important historical
records of the Indian cinema to be
destroyed.
Among the most important landmark films
of the Indian cinema that have thus vanished
into oblivion are:
Dhiren Ganguli's ß/7ef Ferat ("England
Returned"), 1921An early social satire on
anglicized Indians who blindly import
Western values into traditional Indian
society.
D.N. Sampat's Bhakta Vidur, 1921A folk
tale in which the film director himself played
the central role as a sensitive nationalist
leader; he wears modern dress whilst all the
other characters don suitable mythological
garb.
Baburao Painter's Saukari Pash ("The
Indian Shylock"), 1925A middle-class
peasant family's struggle against the ex¬
ploitation of a heartless money-lender.
»Balidan ("Sacrifice"), 1927Based on
Rabindranath Tagore's Bisarjan.
Imperial's Anarkali, 1928, directed by R.S.
ChoudhuryAn ill-fated romance between
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
4 Sairandhari (1933), by Ra-
jaram Vanakudre Shantaram,
was the first colour film made
in India. This superproduction
was an adaptation of the
Mahabharata epic. Shantaram
was one of the founders of the
Prabhat Studios, based in
Poona, and specialized In
films on social and
mythological themes.
Emperor Akbar's son, Prince Salim, and a
dancing girl, in which the title role was
played by the beautiful Sochana (Ruby
Meyers), the highest paid star of the Indian
screen of those days.
The same director's Khooda Ki Shaan
(Wrath), 1931The central character of this
film was a Gandhi-like figure.
Bhal G. Pendharkar's Shyam Sunder,
1932The first film in the Marathi language
to have a successful silver jubilee run.
Prabhat and V. Shantaram's Sairandhari,
1933The first colour film made in the
country (it was processed in Germany using
one of the early colour processes introduced
by Agfa)A costume spectacular from the
Mahabharata.
Sarvottam Badami's Griha Laxmi
("Educated Wife"), 1934.
Nandlal Jaswantlal's Indira M.A., 1934.
Mohan Bhavnani's Mill Mazdoor,
1934Based on Munshi Premchand's
powerful story about the rights of the work¬
ing class.
Devaki Bose's Seefa, 1934In this film
gods and goddesses were portrayed for the
first time as simple human beings without
their haloes or heavenly charisma.
Wadia Bros' Hunterwali, 1935In this film
Nadia, the fearless, brought a new image of
the liberated woman, in keeping with the
awakening national consciousness of the
times.
Sohrab Modi's Khoon Ka Khoon,
1935An adaptation of Shakespeare's
Hamlet.
Balayogini ("Child Widow"), 1936About
the sufferings of a widow and her daughter
in an orthodox Hindu society.
Saukari Pash ("The Indian
Shylock", 1925) was directed
by Baburao Painter, who had
founded the Marhastra Film
Studios at Kolhapur in 1919.
The Indian director R. V. Shan¬
taram played a starring role in
the film.
Shanta Apte played the role of
Radha, the god Krishna's
beloved girl cow-drover, In
Gopalkrishna (1937), directed
by Damle and Fatehlal.
Vinayak's Chaaya ("Holy Crime"),
1 936About man's inhumanity to his fellow
human beings, based on a story by V.S.
Khandekar.
... and many more.
No study of the Indian cinema would be
complete without having access to these
and many other films that are believed to
have been permanently lost. However,
"lost" films have turned up in the most unex¬
pected places and the film archivist keeps
on hoping that the film he is looking for will
one day be found. He hopes for miracles;
and miracles do sometimes happen.
The idea of establishing a national library
of films was first broached in 1 964, when the
Government of India instituted the National
Film Awards. But this was to be limited to
award winning films only. The concept of an
Archive as a repository of all national films of
permanent historical value did not
crystallize until some ten years later.
Why, it is often asked, should public
money be spent on preserving all the junk in
the way of cheap entertainment being made
by unscrupulous speculators? The question
becomes all the more pertinent in face of the
glut of films produced in India in recent
years. The archivist finds himself in the dif¬
ficult position of having to decide what to
keep and what to discard. Selection
becomes unavoidable. But such doubts will
persist as long as the cultural role of the
cinemaeven of escapist cinemais not
fully accepted. The task of the film archivist
becomes less taxing once there is a national
awareness of this important issue.
Thereafter what is required is the good-will
and co-operation of film-makers and well-
wishers.
Cinema and television are the most impor¬
tant cultural forces developed by man in the
twentieth century. The preservation of
cinema culture is a moral responsibility, a
duty we owe to future generations. We shall
be failing in our duty if we do not take care
of our film and television heritage.
Better late than never...
I Paramesh Krishnan Nair
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THAILAND
When the tornera was king
by Dome Sukvong
THE story of the cinema in Thailand
began eighty-five years ago when
S.G. Marchovsky brought some
reels of "Lumière" films and showed them
in Bangkok on 1 0 June 1 897. Thailand's first
film was made in 1900 by the younger
brother of King Rama V, and the year 1927
saw the start of the feature film industry in
Thailand. Since then more than 100,000
kilometres of film and some 3,000 feature
films have been produced in Thailand.
We can be almost sure that more than half
the footage of these films made in or brought
into Thailand has been lost forever, while the
other half is scattered in private collections,
in forgotten corners of attics, garages, store¬
rooms and old movie theatres, with termites
and rats as their only custodians.
In 1 980, 1 started to gather all the available
data concerning Thai films and in one year
I had amassed enough data about most of
the films made in Thailand, or made by Thai
DOME SUKVONG, of Thailand, is a founder of
the Old Films Preservation Project launched at
Thailand's Institute of Technology and Voca¬
tional Education.
nationals, between 1 897 and 1 945 to be able
to start looking for the films themselves.
In 1981, when this search started, I came
across 50,000 feet (15,200 metres) of film in
a very old railway go-down (warehouse).
This footage had been shot by the State
Railways of Thailand between 1922 and
1945. The originals were all black and white
negatives made of nitrate film. At least half
of this footage may not be in a condition to
be salvaged.
Hoping somehow to salvage the other
half, I contacted the officials of the National
Archive and asked them to approach the
State Railways and have the film transferred
to the Archive so that it could be salvaged
and preserved. All the State Railway films
are now kept in the Thai National Archive.
Since then we have been able to locate at
least ten more sources of old films. Some of
them had been lying forgotten for at least
half a century. One interesting and impor¬
tant discovery came from a lady who hap¬
pened to read a newspaper headline about
my discovery of the State Railway films. She
found forty reels of old films in a store-room
in her house. Later she contacted me and we
immediately recovered the films only to find
that the 35mm black and white nitrate prints
were in bad condition.
These films were originally the personal
effects of the late King Rama VII (1 926-1 935)
who was known to enjoy movies and film¬
making. The films had come into the posses¬
sion of her father who had at one time been
a member of the King's palace staff.
Together we found forty reels of film each
some 1 ,000 to 1 ,500 (300 to 450 metres) feet
in length. Among them were films of the
King's personal and State activities, such as
royal ceremonies and his trips in the South-
East Asian Peninsula, to Europe and to the
United States of America. The films in this
category were made by film companies of
the countries he was visiting. The visit to the
United States, for example, was filmed by
Paramount Pictures. There were also a
number of films made personally by the King
while visiting Japan, as well as some
Hollywood silent features starring Douglas
Fairbanks, the King's favourite film star.
The most exciting discovery was that of
two reels of film with a sound track made in
the year in which the 150th anniversary of
the founding of Bangkok was celebrated.
The film was made in 1932 by the Srikung
Sound Film Company, a famous early Thai
film production firm and the first in Thailand
to produce sound films. The Srikung Com¬
pany played a great pioneering role in
starting up the popular film industry ih
Thailand; but during the inter-war years,
after rising to a peak, business declined and
the Company closed down just after the
Second World War. These two reels are
A Handful of Rice, one of Thailand's earliest
films, was made in 1939 by a Swedish pro¬
duction team and a Hungarian director who
had been invited to shoot a film in the coun¬
try by a Thai prince. The story of a young
peasant couple, it was set in a mountainous
forested region of northern Thailand. Local
people acted in the film which won a prize at
the 1939 Venice Film Festival. Both a work
of fiction and a valuable anthropological
document about a traditional way of life, A
Handful of Rice was preserved in the
Swedish NationalArchives and was recently
presented by Sweden to the Thai
authorities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
4 Three stills from Suvarna of Siam (1923).
The first feature film made in Thailand, it is
being sought by the Thai Film Group,
created in 1982.
Photos © National Archives of Thailand, Bangkok
perhaps all that remains in Thailand of the
films made by the Srikung Company.
Another fruitful source of old films was the
Siam Society which provided us with 270
reels of 16mm diacetate film, each 400 feet
(120 metres) in length. These films had also
been the personal property of King Rama VII
and had been made between 1926 and
1945. Some reels had been shot by the King
himself.
The Thai Film Group, founded in 1982 to
celebrate eighty-five years of movies in
Thailand and to promote the preservation of
old films, now has a forty-square-metre room
for film preservation at the Department of
Photography and Cinematography of the
Bangkok Technical Institute. All the films
that we have discovered are stored in this
room. We hope in the future to establish a
proper store-room when sufficient money
becomes available.
At present we have no experts to restore
the films in our possession. However, the
35mm nitrate films are in fairly good condi¬
tion except for a little shrinkage.
As' far as the 16mm diacetate films are
concerned some forty per cent of them are in
various stages of deterioration. Some have
already dried up and become brittle; others
are twisted or have melted. Unfortunately,
we know of no technique for upgrading
these films.
In an attempt to supplement our collection
by exchanges we have, during the past two
years, contacted overseas film archives and
have asked for their help in tracing certain
lost films. There are two films that we are
desperately trying to locate. The first, called
Suvarna of Siam, or The Kingdom of
Heaven, is the first feature film ever made in
Thailand. It was produced by a Hollywood
company under the supervision of a Mr.
Henry MacRae in 1923. The other film, en¬
titled Berne: Arrivée du Roi de Siam, is the
first film ever to portray the Thai people.
If one day we are able to obtain these two
films it would be a significant step towards
the establishment of a Thai National Film Ar¬
chive. It is my personal conviction that our
immediate target for the future should be to
launch a crusade to recover the approx¬
imately 3,000 feature films that have been
produced in Thailand since 1923.
I Dome Sukvong
CUBA
A people in itspictures
by Manuel Pereira
CUBA'S film archive (Cinemateca) was created in 1960 with
the purpose of selecting, locating, acquiring, classifying
and conserving all forms of material relevant to knowledge
and study of the cinema from its origins until today.
Before the creation of the Cinemateca, no Cuban institution was
consistently concerned with collecting and protecting film material,
with the exception of the University of Havana's department of
cinematography which, in spite of its slender economic and
technical means, managed to salvage a number of interesting films.
The indifference of official circles towards the conservation of
films has had disastrous results. To take one example, almost all the
films produced in Cuba during the silent era (approximately 70
short and feature-length films) have been lost forever; only five
have survived, three of them incomplete. Over a third of the films
produced in the 1930s, 1940s and 1950s have also disappeared.
The Cinemateca already has a major collection of over 6,000
films, including works by the most outstanding directors in the
MANUEL PEREIRA is a Cuban novelist and journalist. His novels El
Comandante Veneno and El Ruso have been translated into a number
of languages. He is also a film critic and screenwriter and has been
editor-in-chief and deputy director of Cine Cubano magazine.
history of the cinema as well as all the films made in Cuba since
1959, the year which saw the birth of the Cuban film industry (the
Cuban Institute of Cinematographical Arts and Industries,
ICAIC).
One of the most important and least known tasks of the
Cinemateca is the conservation of film stock. In order to protect ar¬
chive films and to keep them available for projection, the
Cinemateca makes duplicate copies of films of which it only has a
positive. (This is the case with most "old" films). As a result of its
film stock restoration and salvage programme, over 200 acetate
copies had been made by 1972. Films which were originally on
nitrate stock have also been transferred to safety (acetate) stock;
over a third of these are films made in Cuba before 1959.
The work of the Cinemateca's conservation department, the con¬
tinual updating of its collection, constitutes a complex task ranging
from restoration and reconstruction and including the transferral
of images (and sound) to new supports. This is the only way to
preserve these precious materials which form part of the national
and international cultural heritage.
In addition to this, as the director of the Cinemateca, Hector
Garcia Mesa, explained to me, "it is also necessary to add Spanish
titles to silent films which still have their original titles in different
languages."
The Cinemateca is currently in the final stages of transferring to
safety film the relatively few films which are still on inflammable
nitrate stock. Another urgent task is the transposition onto new
colour stock of film whose colour is considered to be rapidly,
decomposing.
The Cinemateca also makes sure that its holdings of black and
white, colour, and nitrate films are properly air-conditioned, using
control systems which meet international technical standards.
Through systematic checking, airing, and physical examination of
the films, it is possible to detect signs of decomposition in time for
the films to be copied as a matter of urgency in the case of single
copies or copies of which there is no negative or duplicate negative.
A shot from Lucia (directed by Humberto
Solas, 1967), an outstanding production of
the powerful Cuban cinema which has
emerged since the Revolution.
2S
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CINE QUA NO
An ABC offilm preservation
by Frantz Schmitt
OUR civilization today is confronted
with a flood tide of recorded moving
¡mages, a heritage which poses
serious problems for those responsible for
its transmission, even in part, to future
generations. How can they ensure its sur¬
vival, the full recognition of its cultural value,
and its free circulation?
It is impossible, within the scope of this ar¬
ticle, to elaborate a fundamental theory on
this question, and so far as methods are con¬
cerned, the identification of priorities must
be guided by commonsense rather than by
doctrinaire considerations, even if this
means repeating what for some people are
elementary facts.
For all those who have responsibilities
at the national level in this matter, the
preservation of films should be envisaged
and planned in a long-term perspective,
never only in the short- or medium-term. Col¬
lection is not preservation.
Whatever the size of a country's produc¬
tion, the collection and subsequent preser-
FRANTZ SCHMITT, French film-maker, has
worked on many short films as director,
cameraman or editor. A member of FIAF's
preservation committee, he took part in the
preparation of the Unesco Recommendation
on moving images. He is head of the film ar¬
chives service of France's National Centre of
Cinematography, and teaches in the depart¬
ment of film and audiovisual research at the
University of Paris III.
vation of films calls for the intervention and
active participation of the State, not only
because this work, if well done, is always
costly, but also because nowadays the State
is inevitably involved in the legal, ad¬
ministrative and even scientific and
methodological measures which must be
adopted.
In many film-producing countries the
collection of films for safeguarding has been
neglected for too long not only through indif¬
ference but also for reasons associated with
safety. Inflammable film was still being used
A French banker and philanthropist, Albert
Kahn (1860-1940), was an early believer in
the idea of creating and preserving for
posterity a pictorial record of everyday life
in different countries. To constitute his "Ar¬
chives of the Planet", he despatched
cameramen throughout France and to many
other countries including China, India and
Japan with instructions to "record once and
for all aspects, practices and modes of
human activity whose inevitable disap¬
pearance is only a matter of time. ' ' Between
1910 and 1930 his team took 170,000 metres
ofdocumentary film and 72,000 autochrome
photos. The project came to an end after
Kahn was ruined in 1929 but today his
astonishing collection is preserved at the
Fondation Albert Kahn in the Paris suburb of
Boulogne. Below, street scene in Beijing, a
still from a film in the Archives de la Planète.
until the 1950s and it was difficult if not im¬
possible to store it in premises of national in¬
stitutions responsible for statutory deposits
or copyright. Nowadays the collection of
films can no longer be left to private in¬
itiative. The necessary administrative
measures must be taken to ensure that there
is a statutory obligation to deposit a copy of
every film produced in the country.
Where difficulties of one kind or another
hinder compliance with this requirement, the
authorities could invoke the financial aids to
productionwhich exist in various forms in
many countriesto encourage the statutory
deposit of a sizeable proportion of the coun¬
try's production. If many Western countries
are today deprived of a large part of their film
heritage, it is because they took too long to
recognize this fact and to take appropriate
measures.
The problem of selecting films for
preservation is a false one. As a matter of
principle, a selection should not be made
between one category of film and another.
All products of the "non-commercial"
cinema, whether they be advertising films,
industrial documentaries, propaganda,
amateur films or local reportage, should be
accepted with the same respect as the latest
work of a famous director.
In the past, too many national film ar¬
chives made unhappy choices when they
gave preference to, amongst others, fiction
films. By doing so they encouraged the
authorities, who are not very generous when
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
it comes to allocating funds, in the belief that
after all the need to preserve films as objects
of cultural value can be satisfied while adop¬
ting a compromise solutiona solution
devised by people who, consciously or not,
possess the mentality of technocrats. Ac¬
cording to their school of thought a film
about industrial robotization may be of more
interest in fifty years time than the tenth ver¬
sion of Les Misérables. Selection, if per¬
missible at all, can be based only on prac¬
tical administrative needs.
Where responsibility for safeguarding
different categories of film is assigned to
several bodies in the same country, it is
essential that their respective respon¬
sibilities be strictly defined and that they
adopt common technical criteria. It is an illu
sion to think that the proliferation in some
countries of regional, local, specialized and
decentralized film archives will improve the
long-term chances of survival of a greater
number of films.
In too many instances the only functions
that are properly discharged by these bodies
are those of distribution and presentation,
and it would be desirable that the sole or
master copies in their possession be handed
over to an official central archive. A film ar¬
chive's pride in finding an "only" copy and
repeatedly projecting it until it is worn out
has often been responsible for the disap¬
pearance of a film for all time.
Whenever an archive has to envisage
the restoration of films made before the
disappearance of "nitrate" film, and for
budgetary reasons it cannot undertake all
the restorations at once, it should in my opi¬
nion be guided by five basic criteria when
choosing its priorities.
It should consider the state of
deterioration, especially chemical
deterioration, of the film, the most
threatened films being given priority. For
various technical reasons, these are not
necessarily the oldest. In France, for in¬
stance, it has been found that the original
soundtracks of films made during the
Second World War are very often in an
advanced state of decomposition, where¬
as silent films dating from 1910 are still
perfectly intact. Genuine priorities can be
established objectively on technical
Birth of a notion
by Boleslaw Matuszewski
This text is extracted from A New Source ofHistory (The Creation
ofa Depository ofHistoric Cinematography), a pamphlet publish¬
ed in Paris in March 1898 by Boleslaw Matuszewski in which for
the first time the idea was launched of creating a cinema archive.
THE cinematographic film, in which a scene is composed of
a thousand images and which, projected from a source of
light onto a white sheet, makes the dead and the absent
arise and walk, this simple celluloid ribbon on which an image has
been produced, is not only a historical document but a slice of
history which has not vanished and which has no need of a genie
to resuscitate it. It is there, barely asleep and, like those elementary
organisms which have a latent life and reawaken after years have
gone by through the action of a little heat and humidity, all it needs
to awaken and relive the hours of the past is a little light passing
through a lens in the midst of darkness!...
What must be done is to give to this possibly privileged source of
History the same authority, the same official existence, the same
access as other archival sources which already exist...
All that will be necessary is to assign to cinematographic films
which have a historic character a section of a museum, a shelf in
a library, a cupboard in the archives. The official depot will be
either at the Bibliothèque Nationale or at the library of the Institut,
under the guardianship of one of the Academies which are concern-
Photo from a very early film, Cataracte du
Niagara ("Niagara Falls"), made in 1896 by
the French director Edwin Rousby.
ed with history, or at the Archives, or at the Museum of Versailles.
We shall choose and decide. Once the institution is in existence, free
or even purchased items will flow in. The price of the
"cinematographic reception apparatus" (camera) and of reels of
film, which was very high in the early days, is dropping rapidly and
coming within the means of ordinary amateur photographers.
Many of them, not counting the professionals, are starting to take
an interest in the cinematographic application of this art and ask
for nothing better than to contribute to the constitution of a
history. Those who will not give their collections will be happy to
bequeath them. A committee will accept or reject documents which
are on offer, after considering their historical value. The negatives
which it accepts will be sealed in cases, labelled and catalogued;
they will be the types (originals) which will not be touched. The
same committee will decide on the conditions of access to the
positives, and will keep in reserve those which, for special reasons,
will only be put before the public after a number of years have gone
by. The same practice is followed for certain archives. A curator of
the chosen establishment will take charge of this new collection,
which will initially be small, and an institution of the future will be
created. Paris will have its Depository ofHistoric Cinematography.
m
A shot from a Dutch documentary, Sergei
Eisenstein's Visit to Holland, made in 1929
when the Soviet director toured the
Netherlands. The film was discovered by
Jan de Vaal, director of The Netherlands
Film Museum. A duplicate negative, a fine
grain copy and projection prints were made
in the nick of timethe original nitrate print
has now completely decomposed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
grounds by applying the control methods,
such as stability tests, recommended
by the International Federation of Film
Archives (FIAF).
Before undertaking the lengthy pro¬
cess of restoring a film that is believed to
be the only copy, it should be confirmed at
the national and international levels that a
better copy does not exist in some other
archive with which exchanges can be
made. The development of such ex¬
changes, which is partly linked to the
greater availability of computerized infor¬
mation facilities, especially in regard to
cataloguing, should in the future eliminate
costly and unnecessary duplication,
something which is still too common. Also,
recognition of the special role of film ar¬
chives in safeguarding national heritages
should gradually allow for some relaxation
of the regulations governing the protec¬
tion of copyright and other rights, which in
too many cases paralyse exchanges.
Save in exceptional circumstances,
priority should be given to safeguarding a
country's own films. This may appear to
be a selfish attitude, but it can be compen¬
sated to some extent by organizing
systematic exchanges of work.
For an equal degree of physical or
chemical deterioration, priority should be
given to a country's oldest films, so that
that part of its heritage which is least
known because it is older is made more
rapidly accessible to the public. I have had
many occasions to observe how projec¬
tions of French "incunabula" dating from
before 1915 (Lumière, Méliès, Emile Cohl,
for instance, but also short films by
unknown directors) were received en¬
thusiastically by viewers of all ages, thus
indirectly helping to draw the attention of
official circles to the need to provide better
financial support for the most urgent
essential rescue operations.
Finally, in the case of important ar¬
chives which still possess hundreds or
even thousands of "nitrate" films which
must be copied onto safety film, speedy
action for the largest possible number of
films should take precedence over the
quest for perfect restoration. Previously
unknown sequences from Gance's
Napoléona film which Kevin Brownlow
took years to reconstitute (see article page
14)have just been discovered, but this
approach cannot be followed by archives
that have millions of metres of film for
transfer and have to act quickly to
reproduce hundreds of silent films, even
though some sections may be temporarily
missing.
A film archive does not really deserve
the name unless it has taken certain
technical measures to ensure the long-term
survival of the material in its possession. In
particular, it should give absolute priority to
the preservation of matrices: negatives,
inter-positives, duplicate negatives. If it only
has copies which it uses for consultation or
projection, it has not yet become a real ar¬
chive. A film archive cannot be compared to
a public library. It must have strict rules
about limiting the use of its material. If it
engages in restoration it should at the same
time and as far as possible make several
safety versionsduplicate, inter-positive,
copyfor each title, otherwise it is only
postponing the problem for a few decades.
Of course, an archive with long-term ob¬
jectives will take all the scientific and
technical precautions to preserve its
material that are recommended by the Inter¬
national Federation of Film Archives: strict
air conditioning, careful choice of con¬
tainers, absolute segregation of nitrate and
acetate film, separate storage of originals
and copies, checking of safety and quality
control arrangements, measuring the
thiosulphate residue for copies made by the
archive. There is nothing optional about any
of these precautions.
The everyday work of the archivist also
includes the collection, cataloguing,
safeguarding and, where necessary,
restoration of all those documents and other
material which constitute the historical,
documentary or technical background to a
film. These include scenarios, photographs,
posters, contemporary magazines, publicity
material of various kinds, apparatus,
patents, all of which should be associated
with the films themselves. Indeed, in many
cases they help to restore their identity more
completely.
Very often the student or professional
who comes to an archive to study a film also
needs to have access to this non-film
material, such as catalogues, in order to
complete his research, and it is a pity that
sometimes material of this kind is dispersed
amongst other bodies, such as museums
and libraries.
While it is desirable that every archive
should keep itself well informed about
developments in new technologies and
should try to apply them in its work, this does
not mean that it should constantly postpone
adopting technical solutions for its problems
in the hope that eventually some new
development will supply a radical solution to
its present difficulties. It is already some
time since the introduction of magnetic
tapes for images, but neither these nor other
much-heralded innovations such as the
video-disc, high definition television, the
holographic image or data processing are
likely to cause major upheavals in the
organization of the world's leading archives.
As long as film continues to be used, recent¬
ly created audio-visual archives whose
directors think in terms of the distant future
should be cautious about committing
themselves to new techniques whose value
is still unproved. Can one seriously imagine
that, if all the books and manuscripts in the
great national libraries were transferred to
high definition video-discs, the originals
would be thrown out? The situation will be
the same for the film, and people will always
have recourse to the negative when
possible.
On the other hand, because they
guarantee a much longer life for copies,
there is no doubt that the new positive colour
films which have come on the market in re¬
cent years are likely to have a considerable
influence on the choice of technical solu¬
tions adopted by archivists, and that the
preservation of colour films at very low
temperatures (a very costly and troublesome
system) will in many cases be abandoned.
Frantz Schmitt
The Lumière brothers, Auguste (1862-1954)
and Louis (1864-1948) were two French
scientists who invented an early motion-
picture camera and projector called the
cinématographe. From 1896 until they aban¬
doned production in 1903 they sent a team
of cameramen-projectionists to cities
throughout the world to show their films and
shoot "documentaries" of everyday life.
Left, Tverskaya street, Moscow, a still from
the Gazette des Frères Lumière.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
SWITZE
A living film archive
by Freddy Buache
THE depositing of copies of films in
film archives should clearly be
subject to rules dictated by their
owners; the first implication of this is that
reels of film should not be allowed to leave
the premises of the institution. But it is
equally clear that the conservation of film
archives in total secrecy would lead to the
absurd situation in which, ultimately, no
one could claim to consult them for the pur¬
poses of historical research, and that ar¬
chivists would be acting as the guardians of
cemeteries, which is not their purpose.
Collecting works produced in the past
only makes sense if it is possible for contem¬
porary art to match itself against such
works with a view to preparing for the
future. A living film archive is thus a
meeting place where today's creators,
historians, theoreticians and students can
freely consult documents. Consequently it
is indispensable to provide them with easy
access to an accurate, detailed and com¬
prehensive catalogue. Access to the films
themselves should be under the constant
supervision of the staff responsible for the
archives.
The Cinémathèque Suisse has always
tried to reconcile, in a generous spirit of col¬
laboration, the requirements of research
students with respect for the wishes of
depositors. It takes steps to ensure that
there is never the slightest opportunity for
piracy, and gives an unqualified guarantee
FREDDY BUACHE, of Switzerland, is director
of the Swiss Cinémathèque. He is also the
supervising editor of a series of studies on film
history and theory published by L'Age
d'Homme publishers, Lausanne. He is the
author of studies on American cinema, Swiss
cinema, and Buñuel, which have been publish¬
ed in this series.
*^P^F**
mm
Pr?S»ir jaw -m?^
W m(m JLJbI Hol?' ^i
ail ft V 1 W JL1*"' _ . ^
to this effect to all who wish to entrust films
to it. It is proud to have regularly expanded
its activities for more than thirty-five years,
constantly improving its relations with pro¬
fessional circles without ever ceasing to play
its public service role. Our fundamental
task is to supervise the constitution (or
reconstitution) of the Swiss film heritage, a
priority field which makes a heavy claim on
our financial resources especially for mak¬
ing "safety negatives", drawing up a com¬
plete catalogue, and restoring films.
The Swiss actor Michel Simon in La Voca¬
tion d'André Carrel, the first film in his long
career. The film, made in 1925, was thought
to have disappeared, but the Swiss
Cinémathèque discovered a copy which was
in poor condition and had it restored. This is
an example of a film which belongs to a
private owner but which is nevertheless
preserved by a film archive.
LIFTING THE VEIL OF SECRECY
"M~yOR many years the film industry was hostile to collections
m~i of films, and the earliest film archives were constituted
JL independen tly offilm producers and often against their will,
in an attempt to stem the destruction of negatives and prints.
Catalogues of rescued films were kept secret so that holders of
rights would not exercise their rights and demand the restitution of
prints. Until I960 secrecy was the rule, and exchanges of informa¬
tion were limited to specific titles. Furthermore, the only catalogue
produced collectively in the International Federation of Film Ar¬
chives (FIAF) concerned silent films, for which sufficient historical
perspective seemed to have been achieved. A planned inventory of
talking films made between ¡929 and 1934 did not come out. The
files offilm archives remained shrouded in mystery.
But in the early 1960s one European archive, the Cinémathèque
Suisse, ventured to lift this veil ofsecrecy andpublished a complete
list of itsfeaturefilm holdings, whatever their origin. Nothing hap¬
pened; no claim or demand for restitution was made.
In the meantime, a new generation ofproducers, more interested
in the history of the cinema, had replaced the old tycoons and a
more trusting relationship had developed:
Many archivists have signed the deposit agreement proposed by
the International Federation of Film Producers Associations
(IFFPA);
Unless they have obtained express authorization to show them
elsewhere, they only show films on their own premises;
They help rights holders to trace prints and other materials;
As for the producers, who are today confronted with piracy,
they know that a copy held in afilm archive is protectedfrom illicit
exhibition. What once seemed to them a risk is now a safeguard.
Archivists now have nothing to fear if they circulate their files
and inventories. The old reflex for secrecy no longer has any
justification. A major obstacle has been removed.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Gosfilmofond of Moscow
by Vladimir Dmitriev
GOSFILMOFOND, the federal State film
archive of the USSR, has one of the
world's richest collections of film. A
State-financed body, it is an integral part of the
Soviet cinema system.
Located some sixty kilometres from
Moscow in the village of Bielye Stolby,
Gosfilmofond came into being on 4 October
1948. Films were being collected in the USSR
long before then, however, especially by the
Cinema School which already had a collection
in 1934.
The Second World War, which destroyed so
much precious cultural property in Europe,
also dealt the Soviet cinema a terrible blow. As
a result, immediately after the war a single
centre was created to collect, restore,
reproduce and safeguard in the best scientific
and technical conditions all the films which
VLADIMIR YUREVICH DMITRIEV, sower film
archivist, critic and historian, has been work¬
ing with the Gosfilmofond of Moscow since
1 962 and also plays an active part in the work
of FIAF. He is the author of over 20 studies on
the cinema.
had been dispersed throughout the cities of
the USSR. The centre even accepted film that
had almost entirely decomposed in the hope
that it could be salvaged.
The collection originally consisted of
negatives and copies of Soviet films by
Eisenstein, Vsevolod Pudovkin, Alexander
Dovzhenko, Lev Kuleshov, the Vassiliev
brothers, Mark Donskoi, Mikhail Romm and
many other directors who have contributed to
the glory of the cinema. It was soon enriched
with films by great directors from other coun¬
tries. Its expansion dates largely from 1957
when it joined the International Federation of
Film Archives (FIAF) and began to exchange
films with other film archives on a large scale.
The prime task of every national film archive
is of course to collect and preserve the pro¬
ducts of its own country's cinema. But each in- .
stitution is faced with the same problems:
should it preserve all films? Should it spend
large sums to save for posterity works which
were misunderstood or rejected by the public
when they first appeared? Should complex
restoration work be carried out on films that
may be of no interest to anyone?
Gosfilmofond closely follows international
discussions about problems related to the
preservation of archives and knows the
arguments in favour of a selective approach.
But it is guided by another principle, namely
that the entire output of a national cinema,
without exception, should be preserved ir¬
respective of artistic or any other criteria. This
is the only way of avoiding fatal errors resulting
from personal bias or hasty decisions. Since
Gosfilmofond was created, it has not
destroyed a single metre of film without mak¬
ing and keeping a good copy.
All State bodies connected with the cinema
in the USSR respect this principle. Every film
studio is obliged to provide the archive, at its
own expense, with the original negative of the
cut version of a film, the interpositive, the
sound track and the copy passed for exhibi¬
tion. Since this requirement applies to all films
produced, it naturally creates storage prob¬
lems and means that new facilities are con¬
tinually being built. On the other hand, it
enables Gosfilmofond to have a collection in
good condition and to replace defective copies
when necessary.
A shot from Mechanics of the
Brain (1926), directed by
Vsevolod Pudovkin
(1893-1953). This scientific
documentary presents the
work of the Russian
physiologist and medical doc¬
tor Ivan Pavlov whose study of
conditioned reflexes led him
to establish laws governing
the activity of the higher ner¬
vous system.
Scene from Que viva México, made in Mex¬
ico between 1930 and 1932 by Sergei
Mikhailovich Eisenstein in collaboration
with the American writer Upton Sinclair. The
film was never completed. After a che¬
quered career, it was reconstituted by the
Soviet director Grigori Alexandrov, who had
worked with Eisenstein, and today, un¬
finished though it is, Que viva México Is
recognized as a classic. The film, made in
Spanish, helped launch the Mexican
cinema.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Gosfilmofond has a long-term programme,
now nearing completion, for transferring old
positives, interpositives and negatives onto
non-inflammable film and then destroying the
inflammable material. Not all the inflammable
film has been destroyed, however. Some of it
is being permanently conserved in special
facilities. Some original negatives and positive
colour copies have been kept, including some
old hand-painted copies whose polychromatic
colour-scale could not be reproduced even
under the most sophisticated conditions.
Thanks to its membership of FIAF Gosfilmo¬
fond has been able to reconstitute the
originals of such films as Abram Room's
Tretya Meshchanskaya ("Bed and Sofa",
1927) with the aid of the Bulgarian Film Ar¬
chive, and two films by Grigori Kozintsev and
Leonid Trauberg, Union of a Great Cause
(1927), with the aid of the Royal Belgian Film
Archive and the film archives of the German
Democratic Republic, and The Overcoat
(1926) with the aid of the New York Museum
of Modern Art.
In turn Gosfilmofond has helped film ar¬
chives in many countries to complete their col¬
lections by supplying them with films produc¬
ed in those countries and preserved in the
Russian archives since the beginning of the
century. It has, for example, sent to the United
States the first film made by the Universal Pic¬
tures Company, Neptune's Daughter (1914);
to France La Terre, a film based on Zola's
novel made by the famous stage director An¬
dré Antoine, and a series of Max Linder films;
to West Berlin films featuring the German ac¬
tress Henni Porten. Other films have been
supplied to the national archives in Poland,
Czechoslovakia, Hungary, the German
Democratic Republic, Belgium, Denmark, The
Netherlands, and many other countries.
A film archive should regard no films as
"untouchable". Nervertheless, some films are
given privileged treatment because the
slightest damage to them would diminish the
national and world film heritage. Among such
works are the films of Sergei Eisenstein,
Vsevolod Pudovkin and Alexander Dov-
zhenko, whose ninetieth birthday is being
celebrated this year. Gosfilmofond has
restored copies of Dovzhenko's films Arsenal
(1929), Earth (1930), and Shchors (1939) so
that people all over the world can appreciate
the philosophy that inspired them as well as
their artistic qualities.
Because of the constantly increasing cost of
preserving 35 mm films, some archives have
reproduced them in 1 6 mm format and others
in 8 mm or Super 8. The reason for this is that
the films take up less space and their preser¬
vation costs less. But reproduction impairs the
quality of the image, and by adopting this
practice an archive may fail to perform its duty,
which is to preserve a copy whose quality is as
near as possible to that of the original.
m
1
«I '
Gosfilmofond thus follows the traditional prac¬
tice and as far as possible preserves films in
their original format.
Today, film archivists are wondering what
benefits they can expect from video-cassettes,
video-discs and other modern supports for
moving images. Some insist that all film collec¬
tions should be reproduced on these new sup¬
ports, pointing out the lower cost of preserva¬
tion, the greater ease of reproduction, and
other advantages offered by these new
methods.
Gosfilmofond is closely following the
development of these techniques, but feels
that at present the quality of a video recording
is not as high as that of an image on film. It
believes, therefore, that it would be premature
to switch to video at this stage. Even if video¬
discs are perfectedand in terms of quality
they have better prospects than video-
cassettesthey will be no more than auxiliary
supports in archive work. Gosfilmofond will
continue to collect and make reproductions
from original material.
In the light of its thirty-five years' ex¬
perience, Gosfilmofond has reached the con¬
clusion that national film archives can only
carry out their mission adequately if they enjoy
the full support of the State, develop close
contacts with archives in other countries, and
have free access to all the films produced in
their respective countries.
Vladimir Dmitriev
One of the founding fathers of
Soviet cinema, the Ukrainian
directorAlexander Dovzhenko
(1894-1956) is here seen in ac¬
tion on the set of one of his
films. His great work Earth
(1930) was included on the list
of the 12 great films of all time
at the World Film Festival held
at Brussels in 1958.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Unesco and the preservation
oímoving images by Wolfgang Klaue
WE live at a time when there is every¬
where a growing awareness of
the importance of history and of
the need to preserve the cultural heritage of
past centuries from destruction. Yet,
paradoxically, we are allowing important
products of our own audio-visual age the
cultural heritage of future generations to
be destroyed or irretrievably lost. More
filmed material has been lost since the
beginning of the present century than has
been preserved.
What Bela Balacz, one of the most im¬
portant theoreticians of the cinema, said
over fifty years ago is, unfortunately, still
valid today: "We have libraries and picture
galleries, museums devoted to the history of
art and of culture as a whole, special collec¬
tions and archives for every imaginable sub¬
ject from shoemaking and tailoring to
brush-making, but none for the art of the
film. The Louvre possesses a complete col¬
lection of regimental buttons, but epoch-
making masterpieces of a new art form
WOLFGANG KLAUE is director of the national
film archive of the German Democratic
Republic and president of the International
Federation of Film Archives (FIAF). He played
an active part in the preparation of the Unesco
Recommendation on the safeguarding and
preservation of moving, images. Among his
publications are Filmcataloguing and a
number of books on the history of the
documentary film.
(which also captures and records real life
better than any other) are nowhere to be
seen. The creation of a museum of film art
would appear to be an urgent task for the
State".
In 1913, in his Das Kino und die
Gebildeten (the Cinema and Educated Peo¬
ple) Hermann Häfker developed a com¬
prehensive concept of the tasks and func¬
tions of a film archive. But these proposals
were far ahead of their time and evoked no
reaction. A few film collections were
established in the 1920s at a local level or in
specialized form.
The nationalization of film production in
the USSR created favourable conditions for
the collection and preservation of films in
State archives, but it was only at the end of
the silent film era that an important interna¬
tional movement for the preservation of the
moving image heritage came into being.
Film experts in a number of countries
(Henri Langlois in France, Iris Barry in the
USA, Bengt Idestam-AImquist in Sweden)
undertook this mission with great en¬
thusiasm. The first film archives were
private foundations (Cinémathèque Fran¬
çaise, Paris) or part of larger museums
(Museum of Modern Art Film Department,
New York).
The pioneer work accomplished in those
days to save part of the moving images
32
heritage is still worthy of our admiration.
But it was not enough to halt the massive
destruction of films which, through indif¬
ference, ignorance or hostility to culture,
went on just as before. The International
Federation of Film Archives (FIAF),
established in 1938, failed to develop inter¬
national activity on any significant scale. It
resumed its activities in the immediate post¬
war period, but these were confined mainly
to the traditional film-making countries. In
many instances archives did not receive suf¬
ficient material support and lacked a
satisfactory legal status, and as a result
there were further losses during this period.
The fact that, for a variety of reasons, the
moving image heritage received little or no
attention in the cultural policies of many
States and even in the Unesco Programme
prompted the Delegation of the German
Democratic Republic to take an initiative at
the 18th General Conference of Unesco
which was to focus greater attention on this
problem. The Delegation's proposal was
supported by several States. Resolution
3422 of the 18th General Conference re¬
quested the Director-General of Unesco to
examine the technical, legal and ad¬
ministrative aspects of safeguarding mov¬
ing images, and to discuss the advisability
of adopting an international recommenda¬
tion or convention for the protection of
moving images from destruction.
Annie Bos in Majoor
Frans (1916), one of
the many silent
films from an active
period of produc¬
tion in The
Netherlands that are
not known to have
survived.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
A preliminary meeting of experts was
held in Berlin (capital of the German
Democratic Republic) in 1975.
Of particular interest was the discussion
of the question as to how, given the domi¬
nant role of the audio-visual media in social
communication, the importance of the
cinema and television as instruments of
entertainment, education and culture, and
as a form of documentary reflection of con¬
temporary events and phenomena, this
medium has been so undervalued as a
heritage.
The reasons are complex. Following the
development of cinematography the film
was regarded in many countries primarily
as a form of cheap, low-level entertain¬
ment, an expression of a sub-culture and
not as a means of artistic expression or con¬
temporary historical documentation.
Another cause of losses in the moving im¬
age heritage is the lack of adequate material
and financial support for carrying out this
task. There is probably no form of cultural
property whose safeguarding and preserva¬
tion costs as much as that of moving im¬
ages. If the storage conditions are less than
optimal, films suffer decomposure through
chemical reactions and are ruined by fungi
and bacteria. In the case of colour film, its
instability leads to fading of the colours.
Only heavy investment in equipment to en¬
sure optimal storage conditions (e.g. in the
case of colour film, at a temperature of
- 7°C and a 25 per cent humidity level) and
in restoring damaged films can guarantee
safeguarding and preservation over long
periods.
The problems connected with collection,
selection, cataloguing, documentation,
restoration, technical processing, storage
and air-conditioning are new ones that de¬
mand scientific study. Furthermore, the
development and dissemination of know-
how relating to archives for moving images
Model design of a futuristic
city was produced by Erich
Kettelhut for Fritz Lang's
visionary film Metropolis
(Germany 1925-1926). A
reconstitution of Metropolis
has been made from the
original script and a hand-
coloured version is being
shown for the first time in
Paris this summer.
are essential if further destruction is to be
avoided. This is especially true for Asia,
Africa and Latin America. These regions
now produce more than two thirds of the
world's output of feature films, but the
development of their archives for moving
images has not kept pace with their film
production.
There is another aspect of moving images
which has affected, and still affects, their
safeguarding and preservation. The pro¬
duction of moving images necessitates
much heavier investment than does that of
other works of art. Moving images have a
twofold character. They are both works of
art, and merchandise. Their distribution
must cover production costs and provide a
profit. Fears that material stored in ar¬
chives would escape the control of pro¬
ducers and distributors, and that their in¬
terests would suffer as a consequence, have
accompanied moving image archives since
the beginning.
On 27 October 1980 the Recommenda¬
tion for the Safeguarding and Preservation
of Moving Images was adopted by consen¬
sus at the General Conference of Unesco in
Belgrade. It is a document of historical im¬
portance. For the first time, eighty-five
years after the invention of the
cinematograph and fifty years after the in¬
vention of television, Unesco called upon
its Member States and the international
public to treat moving images, because of
their educational, cultural, artistic, scien¬
tific and historical value, as an element of
national culture and to protect and preserve
them for transmission to future
generations.
The Recommendation includes a list of
fundamental legal, administrative and
technical measures for protecting the mov¬
ing image heritage, its use, and the develop¬
ment of international co-operation in this
field. The Recommendation had to take ac¬
count of differing interests and concepts
and this is reflected in its compromise
character.
The document presents a series of choices
in the scope, contents and methodology of
measures to achieve this aim. For instance,
in addition to the "mandatory deposit"
provision, which exists in most countries in
regard to books, other measures, such as
deposit, purchase or donation, are recom¬
mended whereby moving images can be
transferred to archives. The rights and
powers of archives in regard to the
safeguarding and use of their collections
and the treatment of foreign works are also
defined in a manner which reflects differing
points of view.
The implementation of a recommenda¬
tion of this scope demands time, but the
progress already achieved in the past three
years is encouraging. The Recommendation
has attracted the attention of many govern¬
ments and specialized bodies. The situation
of existing archives for moving images has
been improved in many countries as a result
of legal measures and financial support. In¬
itiatives have been taken in Asian, African
and Latin American countries to create the
necessary conditions for the preservation of
the national heritage of moving images.
This development has been promoted and
accelerated by the adoption of measures in
the Unesco Programme.
M Wolfgang Klaue
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
In the last 20 years or so, the China Film Ar¬
chive has assembled over 100,000 reels of
film from China and elsewhere. Thirty per
cent consists of inflammable and increas¬
ingly fragile nitrate film which the Archive is
restoring in a specially created laboratory
and transferring onto safety stock. Techni¬
cians have succeeded in restoring to a
usable condition a nitrate print of one of the
first talkies made in China, Cai Chu Sheng's
Song of the Fishermen (1934) which has not
been seen by the public for 40 years (left).
The film had irremediably shrunk, and a
specially adapted system was developed to
pass it through the projector. The Song of
the Fishermen, which won an award at the
1935 Moscow Film Festival, has already
been shown on Chinese television and is to
be presented in a forthcoming retrospective
ofChinese filmsofthe 1930s and 1940s. The
China Film Archive has been a member of
FIAF since 1980.
The International Federation of Film Archives
by Robert Daudelin
FOUNDED in 1938, the International Federation of Film Ar¬
chives (FIAF) today has a membership of seventy-three
archives throughout the world: four in Africa, seven in North
America, twelve in Latin America, nine in Asia, thirty-eight in Europe
and three in Oceania.
The Federation has four main objectives:
to promote the preservation of films considered to be works of art
or historical documents;
to encourage the creation and development of cinémathèques
(film archives) in all countries;
to facilitate collection and international exchange of films and
documents concerning the history and art of cinematography so as
to make them accessible to the widest possible audience;
to foster increased co-operation between its members.
Members of the Federation are independent, non-profit
cinémathèques whose aim is to study the history and art of the
cinema and whose services are available to the public. Their prin¬
cipal task should be the acquisition, preservation and cataloguing of
films and documentation relating to the cinema.
In order to foster the culture and art of the cinema, members are
authorized, indeed encouraged, to undertake other activities such
as the organization of film showings, exhibitions, symposia and
ROBERT DAUDELIN, of Canada, is Director-General of the Cinémathè¬
que of Quebec, and has been for the last six years Secretary-General
of FIAF.
meetings and the publication of books, pamphlets and periodicals.
The Federation itself has published several technical works which
have become essential reference sources for both newly-formed and
longer-established archives.
From modest beginnings, when it had all the appearance of a
private club, the Federation has become as it were the "United Na¬
tions" of the moving image. Its annual congress, which now includes
historical and technical symposia, is attended by over one hundred
delegates from all over the world. The proceedings of these
meetings and symposia regularly give rise to publications that have
become essential tools for researchers and historians of the cinema.
These publications include such works as The Influence of the
Soviet Cinema on World Cinema, The Cinema from 1900 to 1906,
and The Problem of Selection in Film Archives.
In 1983 alone, the collections of Federation member archives in¬
creased by more than thirty thousand films (both feature-length and
shorts). In the same year some eighty million metres of film were ex¬
amined by technicians of member archives. Also in 1983, twenty-
four member archives started work on or completed construction of
specialized film conservation store-rooms many of which met the
standards required for the preservation of both video-tapes and
cinematographic film.
The permanent secretariat of the International Federation of Film
Archives (FIAF) is located in Brussels (Coudenberg 70, 1000
Brussels, Belgium). Further information can be obtained from the
secretariat concerning the activities of the Federation and the help
available to those wishing to establish new archives.
Editorial. Sales and Distribution Offices:
Unesco. 1, Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French francs. 2 years Ivalid only in
France): 1O0 French frenes. Binder for a year's issues:
46 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs nor copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted I rom the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non -copyright photos will be supplied on
reciuest- Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the ooi nions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun¬
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offr
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United
Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or
microfichal by: [1) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor.
Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (2) NCR Microcard Edition. Indian
Head. Inc . Ill West 40th Street. New york. U.S.A.; 13) Bell
and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Woostsr. Ohio 44691.
U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn IParis.)
French: Alain Lévêque (Parisl
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Parisl
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov IParis)
Arabic: Sayed Osman IParis)
German: Werner Merkd (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima ITokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti IRomel
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa IMadras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broido {Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheranl
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp]
Portuguese: Benedicto Sil^a (Rio de Janeiro}
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istarribul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed ^aid (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur}
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es- Salami
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen IPekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofreí
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Neda el Khazen
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ain sa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should he addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief In Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Where to renew your
	 subscription	
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller
or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors
in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
Just published
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 1 75,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011,
Vienna.
BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box N-3138, Nassau.
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq
Building, 1r R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill
Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, ayenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13.
BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O. Box 91, Gaborone.
BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552 Merchant Street,
Rangoon.
CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street
West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHAD. Librairie Abssounout, 24 av. Charles de Gaulle, B.P. 388,
N'Djamena.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing.
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1
(Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague
1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam.
6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35
Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa..
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koîvuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64.
FRANCE. Librairie de ('Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, CCP. 12598-48.
GABON. Librairie Hachette, B.P. 3923, Libreville.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach
140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D 5300 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1,
Legón.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI.
ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a,
Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh,
Hyderabad 500001 (APJ; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Banga-
lore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of
Education and Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad
Road, New Delhi 110001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat.
IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal
Shjrazi Street, Enghélab Avçnue. P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran;
Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. Seyed Jamal Eddin Assad Abadi
Avenue 64th Street, Bonyad Building P.O. Box 1533, Teheran.
IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd, Ballymount
Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12; Tycooly International Publ. Ltd 6
Crofton Terrace, Dun Laoghaire Co., Dublin.
ISRAEL. A.B.C Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1 283, 71 Allenby
Road, Tel Aviv 61000.
ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.) Via
Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome
Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 1 1 3.
KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571,
Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait;
for the Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA
4541, Kuwait.
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod. Lesotho,
Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286,
Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg.
MALAWI. Malawi Book Service, Head Office, P.O. Box 30044
Chichiri, Blantyre 3.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala
Lumpur 22-11.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.
NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1118, 1 000 BC Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1 104, Dunedin,
Mulgrave Street, Prívete Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers),
Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1; Universitets Bokhandelen,
Universitetssentret, P.O.B. 307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3.
PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O.
Box 632, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box 48, Mahé; New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown.
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2
Jurong Port Road, Singapore 2261.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio.
SOUTH AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only:
Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam
Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 1 50 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5 Rämistrasse.
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP.
12-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle, Berne, Vevey,
Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich.
TANZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1 71 5 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco,
18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC IX 9 OS.
UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East 42nd Street, New York,
N.Y. 10017. Orders for books & Periodicals: Box 433, Murray
Hill Station, New York, N.Y. 10157.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/1 1, Zagreb; Cankarjeva
Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/1 1 , Belgrade.
ZAMBIA. National Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd.,
P.O. Box 2664 Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue,
Harare.
The Communication Tree
is an album of 115 photos
and prints illustrating the
complexity of the world's
communication networks.
While raising the question
of whether age-old modes
of communication are
doomed to perish,' the
volume also illustrates the
strivings summed up by
Unesco's Director-General,
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow in the preface:
"The challenge faced today
by each of the peoples of
the world is that of coming
fully into its own while
making of its specific
nature one of the paths to
universality."
Devised and written by Dominique Roger
and Jane Albert-Hesse
Design by Monika Jost
1984, 71 pages, 50 French francs
Trilingual English/French/Spanish
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A "new ' art barely a century old. and a major form of historical record, the motion
picture is a fragile medium. Many treasures of the early cinema have disappeared
through neglect or vandalism but today there is a growing awareness that the
world s heritage ot film should be preserved for posterity. One urgent problem is
that most early motion picture film was made of a highly inflammable and perish¬
able form of celluloid or cellulose nitrate. These nitrate " films are subject to
decomposition and if they are not copied onto more durable 'safety film they will
be lost forever. Above, scenes from a copy, recently made from a deteriorating
nitrate original, of The Red Spectre, a hand-tinted film made around 1907.
Photo . ~i.t Derjart-ner: George casrrran house. New York
]]>
</page>
</document>
