<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062195eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
^--^ A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
Courier
SEPTEMBER 1964 (17TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. ( U.K.) - 30 CENTS (CANADA) - 0.70 F (FRANCE)
«*
WOMEN IN THE NEW ASIA
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
FREEDOM OF THE CITY
Paul Almasy, Paris
In Asia today an increasing number of people are
leaving the villages and moving to big cities (above).
Here, women find it easier to free themselves from
traditional social and religious restrictions and
thus take up occupations that have hitherto been
closed to them. In the new Asia, economic and
social .changes have made possible the evolution
of a new Asian woman (see article page 5).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Couri er
SEPTEMBER 1964
1 71 H YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
In Asia, as in other parts of
the world, there have been
revolutionary changes in the
status of women. In this issue
four women from Ceylon,
Burma, Thailand and Viet-Nam-
describe the impact of these
changes on their lives and on
family life in general in the
new Asia.
Unesco - E. Aubert de la Rue
Page
4 WOMEN IN THE NEW ASIA
5 THE SURGE TO THE TOWNS
By Barbara Ward
7 CEYLON : SILENT VICTORY
By Subada Siriwardena
13 BURMA: FAMILY IN TRANSITION
By Ni Ni Gyi
17 THAILAND: WOMAN'S PLACE IN THE HOME
No longer 'the hind legs of an elephant'
By Pramuan Dickinson
18 THREE VILLAGES UNDER A MICROSCOPE
Studying the children of Asia
22 VIET-NAM: 20 YEARS OF CHANGE AND TURMOIL
By Le Kwang Kim
28 IS THERE A SOLUTION FOR DELINQUENCY?
Conclusion of a special inquiry on teenagers today
By William C. Kvarceus
33 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
THE UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
Published monthly by UNESCO
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Monelm El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and Auf uit when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English. French, Spanish, Russian, German.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed muse bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Uneaco Courier ¡a Indexed monthly In The Readera* Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : IO/-stg. ; S3.00 (Canada) ; 7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
(M.C. 64.1., 194 A)
N* 9, 1964
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN IN THE NEW ASIA
Almost the whole world has seen revolutionary
changes in the status of womenpolitically, legally,
economically, educationally. What do these
changes amount to in practice? What has been the
effect of this newly-granted status upon day-to-day
domestic living?
In an attempt to answer these questions, Unesco has
recently published a collection of studies entitled
Women in the New Asia: The Changing Roles of Men
and Women in South and South-East Asia (1) edited by
Barbara Ward. Its purpose is to put before the ordi¬
nary reader material gathered for two years under the
Unesco Major Project on Mutual Appreciation of Eas¬
tern and Western Cultural Values, and thus enable a
more realistic appraisal to be made of the past, present
and future of millions of women in Asia.
Mrs. Ward points out in her introductory essay that
these studies "may help us to emerge a little from the
cocoon of our preconceptions, including our own cultur¬
ally derived sterotypes about what are truly 'mascu¬
line' and what 'feminine' social rolesand also about
what are really 'Eastern' and what 'Western' patterns
of living."
The book examines the impact of the new status of
women upon the private domestic lives of both sexes
of families, in fact in eleven countries: Burma, Cey¬
lon, India, Indonesia, Laos, Malaya, Pakistan, the Phi¬
lippines, Singapore, Thailand and Viet-Nam and presents
personal accounts by women from these countries.
In the preface to "Women in the New Asia", Barbara
Ward writes : "In this book Unesco is daring to ask for
troublefor to study the relation between the roles of
the two sexes is to do just that. Probably no other
topic excites more argument and less agreement, and
probably on no other topic is the argument more heated
and the disagreement more profound. Nevertheless, we
have endeavoured to set out facts and suggest con¬
clusions for the common reader in the West, and also,
we hope, in the East, to ponder upon. We hope our
endeavour will provoke new argument perhaps less
heated and more enlightened ; we even dare to hope
that it may produce some measure of agreement here
and there."
The Unesco Courier is pleased to present selected pas¬
sages from this stimulating new work contributed by
authors from Ceylon, Burma, Thailand and Viet Nam.
(1) Published by Unesco, 1963. Price: (paperbound) 40 sh. (stg.) ; S 8.00;
28 F; (clothbound) 50 sh. (stg); S 10; 35 F 50. Available from Unesco
Sales Agents, see inside back cover.
Unesco Courler Archives
The vast majority of the people of South and South
East Asia live in villages or towns of less than
20,000 inhabitants. Hardly more than 10% live in bigger
cities, as compared with an average of 42% in North
American and between 30% and 35% in Europe. But
today this picture is changing and from fishing villages,
and rural hamlets alike there is a surge towards the
towns. Perhaps the most striking example of this trend
is Hong Kong (left). To meet Hong Kong's population
"explosion"city authorities have had to embark on major
projects to provide housing and increase water supplies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
THE SURGE TO THE TOWNS
by Barbara Ward
I n 1953 something quite new happened in the
I Chinese fishing village of Kau Sai, which lies
on one of the many islands in the territory of Hong Kong:
several fishermen sent their daughters to school. Pre¬
viously this had been the privilege of sons only. But in
the early 1950's Kau Sai was becoming prosperous. Some
of the fishing junks were fitted with diesel engines;
catches were larger and more regular, incomes higher.
With higher incomes, wives and daughters, as well as
sons and grandsons, wanted to buy things. The city had
plenty of things to sell, but to find the shops you needed
to be able to read read the shop signs, the street names,
the figures on the buses and their destinations. Modern
communications were laid on, travel and goods were at
the women's disposalbut first they had to be able to
read.
Paul Almasy, Paris
In the village literacy was not necessary; town living,
even town visiting, was difficult without it. The
schoolgirls of Kau Sal Illustrate very neatly the inter¬
dependence of the many different factors in contemporary
social change.
More than that, they illustrate also the surge towards
the towns. Between 1951 and 1959 four young fisher boys
left the village prosperous though their families undoub¬
tedly were for work in the city, and one girl was lucky
enough to marry a townsman.
This, which made her the envy of every other woman
and the ideal of every schoolgirl in the village, meant
that she went to live in a wlndowless cubicle about 9 feet
long and 5 feet broad, whose hardboard walls reached a 5
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN OF NEW ASIA (Cont'd)
From the most beautiful scenery to a slum
: 3
height of about seven feet and which was flanked by six
or seven similar cubicles with whose occupants (together
with those who slept in the passageway) she now shares
a common kltchen-cum-lavatory about ten feet square.
The fourth floor of the tenement which contains this
cubicle is reached by a steep, straight stairway, a yard
wide, down which all refuseincluding night-soilhas
to be carried, and which, being no tenant's property, is
no tenant's business to keep clean. The tenement is, of
course, only one In a street of such buildings, and in
scores of such streets. There is a standplpe for water
about a hundred yards away. The good fortune of this
girl, who now has two children both under three years old,
is still the talk of her old friends in the village. She has
achieved their highest ambition: she lives in town.
What has she gained? In the eyes of her friends and
herself two precious things: freedom from the ceaseless-
ness of toil in the village, and access to glamour and
excitement. Both the "push" from the country and the
"pull" to the towns are here reflected. There is no doubt
that in most countries peasant rural Ufe is an endless
round of physically demanding work.
Chinese fishing families are perhaps an extreme
example, since they live always (men, women and
children) on their boats and many of them work far into
the night; moreover they are driven all the time by the
constant desire to make good in the material sense. By
no means all the other nationalities in South and South-
East Asia share this motivation, and, without it, most of
them, living in a climate and environment which do not
force absolutely continuous effort, do in fact lead a less
strenuous life.
Nevertheless, even for them, the work Is usually
demanding and unending; often especially so for the
women who, in addition to the inescapable dally chores
of child care, cooking, cleaning, collecting water and
firewood, laundering, and other domestic duties, usually
have the more continuous, if less arduous tasks of agri¬
culture laid upon themplanting out, for instance, and
weeding.
Though Ceylon's women
themselves and men's atti¬
tudes towards them have
changed, only a relatively
small number of women
have in practice been able to
add to their traditional roles
of wife and mother or change
their position in comparison
with men. In Ceylon most
people live in rural areas
where change has hardly
occurred at all. Right,
paddy fields rise tier upon
tier like a giant staircase in
the countryside of Ceylon.
I n the towns tasks disappear ; water comes
I from a tap (what is a hundred yards or so
down the street compared with a quarter of a mile or
more on a rough village path?); food can quite often be
bought ready cooked; charcoal and firewood are in the
market; there is electricity. All this and glamour too:
things to see, shops to look at, the cinema, a fire engine,
buses, crowded pavements, curious foreigners, rich people,
perhaps processions for funerals and weddings. The
fascination of town life for the imaginations of peasant
women is not hard to understand.
The question of how far their expectations are fulfilled
can hardly be answered. For the fisherman's daughter
from Kau Sai they undoubtedly were. Though to middle-
class Western eyes she may appear to have exchanged a
healthy open-air Ufe in some of the most beautiful scenery
In the world for an overcrowded slum, she is a truly
happy woman. She told me so; and I could see that it
was true. But for the pavement sleepers of other parts
of Hong Kong (or Calcutta, or Bombay, or elsewhere) I
cannot say.
Overcrowding, unemployment, slum housing these are
common in all large Asian cities and there are probably
many who wish they had never left the land. But we
do not always see the alternatives. We need information,
more factual studies of the relative advantages of poor
town and poor country living and the actual reasons
behind the decisions to migrate.
Moreover it is as misleading to think solely in terms of
poverty and overcrowding as it is to ignore them. Asian
towns have their well-to-do inhabitants too. Further¬
more, in Asia as elsewhere, it is town life that gives the
greatest opportunities for recreation, cultural activities of
all kinds, education, diversified employmentafter all,
as the derivation of the word shows,'towns are the seats
of civilization. And, as often as not they are also the
places in which it is easiest for traditionally secluded
women to emerge from purdah.
In this they are atypical. Apart from city-states like
Singapore, the proportion of the total population living
in towns containing a population of 20,000 or more
nowhere in our region exceeds 22 per cent, and the average
is not much above 10 per cent. In North America it is
42 per cent (1950), in Europe (excluding Russia) 35 per
cent, in the U.S.S.R. 31 per cent. One of the difficulties
in the way of mutual understanding between East and
West is that the overwhelming majority of Asians are
villagers or small-town dwellers still.
Nevertheless it is certain that there is a surge towards
the towns in Asia, and that it is increasing.
Barbara Ward is a British author and an assistant editor
of "The Economist". A former lecturer at Harvard
University, she is at present a visiting lecturer in the
department of anthropology at Cornell University, Ithaca,
New York. Among her most recent books are "India
and the West" (1961) and "The Rich Nations and the
Poor Nations" (1962).
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
© Paul Almasy, Paris
CEYLON SILENT VICTORY (PART 1)
by Subada Siriwardena
he coming of the British to Ceylon in 1796
marked the start of a new era in the history
of this country, which from then onwards began to
undergo the many changes that paved the way for its
present emergence as one of the leading countries in
South-East Asia. Plantations of coffee, tea and rubber
were introduced, and with them the economic develop¬
ment of the country began. With the introduction of
British government the seeds of democracy were sown.
With the improvement of the means of communications
the country was opened up and became more closely knit.
The traditional legal systems of the country were
supplemented and modified to meet modern requirements.
Health services began to be within the reach of everyone.
Education began to be considered the right of all irres¬
pective of sex, creed or ethnic group, and not as the
privilege of a few. More than in anything else there
opened a new chapter in the life of women in this
country.
Traditionally, society in Ceylon was ordered strictly on
a caste basis, which roughly corresponded with a class
basis. Those who belonged to the so-called higher caste
were the rich upper class, who were landed proprietors
and who held responsible posts In government. Until
the country fell Into the hands of the Portuguese, the
Dutch and later the British, these posts ranged from
those of ministers and commanders-in-chief down to
village headmen, and after the British occupation, from
maha mudaliyar down to the village headmen. All the
paddy cultivators, too, belonged to this Golgama caste,
although they were not rich. The rest of the people
belonged to the so-called lower castes, each with its
traditional caste occupation (1).
Buddhism was the religion of the Ceylonese and Hin¬
duism that of the Tamils, until Christianity obtained
converts from both Ceylonese and Tamils. Moslems have
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
(1) For example: Karava caste (fishermen) , Berava (drummers) ,
Salagama (cinnamon peelers), Vahumpora (toddy tappers),
Durava (minor arts and crafts), Rada (washermen), Navandanna
(blacksmiths, silver and goldsmiths), Rodiya (outcasts). The
caste structure of the Tamils is very similar, but the Moslems
have only a class structure.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN OF CEYLON (Cont'd)
Most fathers
decide...
always followed Islam. Religion was the basis of the
culture and the way of life of the people.
In traditional Ceylon it was difficult to draw a hard
and fast line between town and country. Even today
three-quarters of the population consists of rural people,
and the distinction between rural and urban society is
something that has been developing only since the begin¬
ning of the twentieth century.
To be a good wife and mother was considered the
ideal and the perfection of womanhood in all religions
and caste groups from the earliest times and even after
the coming of Christianity. Religion also fostered this
ideal of the perfect wife-mother for the Ceylon woman.
Careers were not meant for women... Economically
gainful employment for women was unheard of until
the coming of the British. Girls had none of the oppor¬
tunities open to boys to get a formal education in the
pirivena schools run by Buddhist monks or at the feet
of Hindu Brahmin teachers. The few women who
happened to be literate had been taught at home by
their fathers, or elder brothers, or other elderly male
relatives.
Women's position in Ceylon was far from favourable,
and they were always considered inferior to men in all
aspects, and as a constant source of trouble and wicked¬
ness. Even the Buddha is said to have at first refused
to admit women to the Sasana (Buddhist clergy) because
it was considered very difficult for a woman to lead the
austere life of renunciation, since her mind is more prone
to be fickle, unsteady and emotional than that of a man.
I t Is the general belief among Buddhists that
one must be a male to become a Buddha, and
that arahantship (the second highest state of "enlighten¬
ment") is more difficult for women to attain. To be
born a female is itself considered the result of bad karma
in a past birth, and much merit has to be accumulated
to be born a man. Hindus have the corresponding belief.
It is these beliefs that moulded women's position in
society.
Woman was expected to be an affectionate and sub¬
missive helpmate to man. She was to be the responsible
one in the domain of household duties, of bearing and
rearing children, cooking and cleaning, sewing and
mending, and ministering to the needs of the husband,
parents and parents-in-law and children. It was
contemptible for a woman to shirk, these duties which
had been assigned to her by birth itself...
Today, with the progress of compulsory education,
cultural influence from the West and universal franchise,
society itself has changed radically. Caste is less rigid
and class less coincident with it. The acquisition of
education and wealth has been responsible for a visible
mobility In society resulting in the growth of a new
middle class to which may belong people of any caste,
creed or ethnic group. The majority of the middle class
are clustered In the cities and towns. The quest for
money and education has further resulted in the rise of
a working class of skilled and unskilled labourers, also
clustering in the towns except for those working on the
tea and rubber estates.
Thus, today's society can be roughly divided into rural
and urban sectors. The rural category can be subdivided
into the non-cultivator land-owning upper class and
the working class engaged in small-scale paddy and
other cultivation or in labour. The urban society can
be divided Into the elite upper class, educated and well-
off, In Important administrative positions or in business,
the middle class, educated and moderately well-off in
white-collar jobs, and the working class, performing
skilled or unskilled labour, with or without a primary
8 education, and poor. All the previously mentioned castes
are represented in all these strata of urban and rural
society In Ceylon.
These and other changes in the structure of society
In modern Ceylon have not been without their repercus¬
sions on the life of women. There are now equal oppor¬
tunities for education from the primary school to the
university for both men and women.
In 1957, English and vernacular schools totaled 8,188
of which there were 618 boys schools, 540 for girls and
7,030 mixed. There were 986,333 boys and 846,741 girls
attending school, and 1,990 young men and 728 women
at the University of Ceylon.
Women now have equal opportunities for employment
In any profession or occupation, excepting the Civil
Service, and today women in Ceylon do have more chance
of promotion. But at the same time it must be said that
though Ceylon's women themselves and men's attitudes
towards them have changed, this still applies only to a
few men, and relatively few women are actually able
to avail themselves of the opportunities open to them.
The position of women has changed, but only for a few.
The old ideal is still popularly accepted, that is, that of
getting married and being a successful wife and mother.
Only a small percentage of women, and those especially
in the urban areas, have been able to add to their roles
or change their position In comparison with men. But
Ceylon is largely a rural country and the majority live
in rural areas where change has hardly occurred at all.
Men of the upper and middle class, even those who
have gone through a higher education course at the
university or other institutions, prefer to marry stay-
at-home wives with a dowry; not salary-earning, educated
career women. They also feel that a woman with a
higher education and a monthly salary would acquire
a sense of indépendance and not be sufficiently sub¬
missive to their husbands. Such men often resent women
going out to work or undertaking such activities as
driving a motor-car or cycling.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Thus, many highly educated career girls find it difficult
to marry men of equal social and economic status and
often continue to Uve as spinsters. Only a handful are
fortunate enough to find husbands who demand neither
old-fashioned submissiveness nor a dowry. It is true
that working-class men and those of the lower middle-
class, where incomes are insufficient to make ends meet,
do want their wives to add to the family income by going
out to work, but once they become economically well-off
they too would wish to keep them safe at home.
As a result most fathers decide to give their girls only
a secondary education and stop their schooling after
that or even earlier. Instead, they wish to collect money
for their daughters' future dowry and trousseau, and
train them in household work. Rich parents want their
girls to learn accomplishments like music and dancing,
which are considered assets in getting a husband with
social prestige perhaps a doctor, a civil servant or a
lawyer. But generally speaking, extra pains are not
considered worth while in educating girls on equal terms
with the boys.
Ost of the women of the present generation
who are educated are asserting their rights
silently, but effectively, and have found themselves in
paths of employment which were never trod by women
before. Thus today we have women who are highly
qualified teachers, university lecturers, doctors, lawyers,
(1) In July 1960, Ceylon elected the first woman Prime
Minister in the world.
librarians and Members of Parliament and, recently,
even a woman Cabinet Minister (1).
During 1958, more women students than men entered
the University of Ceylon. In the teaching profession,
for the year 1957, there were 27,101 women, as against
28,309 men, and of these 890 were graduate women
teachers. The nursing profession is entirely a woman's
profession. Many more are employed as sales-girls,
typists, stenographers and clerks.
All this is the result of education, especially the spread
of English education. And the cost of living is so high
that most husbands are beginning to feel that It would
be a blessing to have an additional Income. Nevertheless,
for various reasons according to surveys of the city of
Colombo and two villages made by the writer, from ten to
20 per cent of the children of school age today are not
attending school. Thus, most girls are not in practice
able to avail themselves of the opportunities theoreti¬
cally open to them.
Girls are today going to foreign universities at their
own expense or through scholarships sponsored by
Unesco and the International Federation of University
Women, etc. They go for courses ranging from uni¬
versity academic courses to courses In home science,
nursing and beauty culture. Many educated women are
engaged In social service work, running crèches, female
adult education, poor relief work, etc. The Lanca Mahila
Samitiya Is a women's association for such voluntary
work.
There is many a working mother In every social class
who, after the husband's death, has had to shoulder the
burden of bringing up the family entirely alone. n
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN OF CEYLON (Cont'd)
SILENT VICTORY
(Part 2)
I was born on December 12, 1928, in a township
called Bope in the southern province of Ceylon.
My father came from a village In Kalutara district and my
mother from another village in the Matara district, both
low-country villages. They both belong to families doing
paddy cultivation as an occupation.
My father's parents were both illiterate but well-to-do
farmers, and father was the youngest child in a family
of thirteen. He was educated in the pirivena schools
at the feet of Buddhist monks and was successful in the
Cambridge examinations through his own efforts. He
acquired a government scholarship to the University of
Oxford, where he received his B. Litt, in Western Classics.
From there he proceeded to Berlin University, where he
did further linguistic studies and to Queen's College,
Benares, for a further course in Sanskrit. He was head
of the Department of Indo-Aryan Languages at the
University of Ceylon for some time.
My mother's parents were both literate, and were also
rather well-to-do farmers. She was the fifth in a family
of eight children. She was an uncertified Ceylonese
teacher when she was given in marriage at the age of
24 to my father, who was in his forties at the time. No
dowry had been asked or given. The parents had deci¬
ded for her and she had simply to consent. My father
did not wish her to go out to work, and with reluctance
she had to give up her job. Within one year after
marriage I was born. My grandmother and my mother's
elder sister helped to bring me up as a baby. After two
years my brother was born and when he was two years
old a sister also arrived.
Wse lived in a country house surrounded by a
large garden and paddy fields, with the
tributary of the Kalu Ganga flowing past on one side.
Our childhood was a very happy one until my father
died of a heart attack when I was just 11 years old. My
father was strict, but also a lovable companion. He used
to play with us indoors and outdoors and take us bathing
in the river, and he helped me in my studies. He did not
make me read books all the time. He took me out for
walks and made me observe the surroundings, and
recounted incidents about his travels abroad. He Instilled
in me as a young child the Idea of what a long, unending
but happy process learning is. He took me out on visits
to the "Sunday Fair," to the city of Colombo, and to my
paternal relations In the village, who were all Illiterate,
hardworking and simple farmer folk.
My father never for a moment forgot or belittled his
native village or even the areas around it. As a monu¬
ment of his love for the villagers, he founded an English
school for them with his savings, the first and the only
such school for miles around, at that time the early
1930s. Very low fees were levied and he was the prin¬
cipal. This school was handed over to the government
one year before he died in 1939.
On my father's death the burden of bringing up the
family fell on my mother's shoulders. More than any¬
thing else she strove to meet my father's last wish on
his death bed to give us children a good education.
The other important influence in our lives has been
my maternal uncle, who is a Buddhist monk engaged
for the last twenty-five years in missionary work in
Penang (Malaysia). He has been my spiritual guide ever
since the death of my father, and even now we seek his
advice on all Important matters.
By the time I was 14 my mother had trained me to
cook and sew and look after the younger ones. We were
all also sent to both Christian and Buddhist English
schools in the cities of Panadura and Colombo. Later
my brother and I both graduated at the University of
10 Ceylon, but my sister gave up school after a few years.
CONT'D ON PAGE 12
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
NEW LANDS WON FROM THE JUNGLE
Photot WHO-Paul Almaty
In the Gal Oya valley of Ceylon, bulldozers rip their way into the jungle and build
roads (above). They have already opened new lands for 50,000 farmers. Over
40 villages have been completed and more than 200 square miles of former jungle
land no"w produce an average of 1 ,200 to 1 ,500 kilogrammes of rice per acre. Malaria
has been eradicated and the valley's main town, Amparai, with a population of
5,000 has a daily air link with Colombo, Ceylon's capital. Above left, led by its ox
cart, a family moves towards lands wrested from the jungle. Left, a family installed
in its new home. Loans are available for the purchase of cattle, seeds and food until
the first harvest. Although the land remains the property of the state, the head
of the household can bequeath his rights to his heirs, whether sons or sons-in-law.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN OF CEYLON (Cont'd)
Career woman
but...
I was given in marriage In 1956 at the age of 27 to
my husband, who was 30 at the time. The marriage
was arranged by my parents, but subject to my consent.
My husband is a Food and Drugs Inspector, educated
in Ceylon and England. Dowry was not asked or given
at our marriage, which was an orthodox Ceylonese
Buddhist ceremony but for the fact that it was held at
a public hall. We are of the same caste and religion.
We live with my own mother and her family in Kandy,
an arrangement which is very convenient for me as our
baby daughter, who was born within a year after our
marriage, can stay happily at homewhile I continue
with my university work.
Immediately after graduation I took to the teaching
profession, the vocation I had chosen ever since I was a
little pupil under my great father; and I acquired the
diploma in education at the University of Ceylon three
years after graduation and on the eve of my marriage.
My husband soon understood my desire to continue to
learn and, as he was convinced that I would not assume
undue independence, he allowed, and indeed encouraged,
me to start reading for the M.A. in Education. This I
am now doing.
I travel dally to the university in my own car, which
I drive myself. My husband takes pride in my work,
even in the face of some criticism from his colleagues.
I have not seen a husband more interested in his wife's
continuing to study, even denying for himself much of
the attention traditionally due from a wife.
B.ut although I have a certain amount of ln-
1 dependence which most women in Ceylon do
not enjoy, this does not mean that I have deviated much
from the ideal pattern of the wife and mother: My
position at home follows very much the traditional
pattern. My husband decides all important matters, and
often it is acceptable to me. He commands and I obey.
Except on scholarly matters it is not for me to argue
with him. I have to accept the fact that he knows best
and that this is all for my own good. I never go out
or do anything outside the precincts of the home without
his permission. But we do discuss important matters
together, although the tendency is for him to decide
finally. I feel quite happy and secure in this manner.
We have no special preference for either sons or
daughters, and when our daughter was born we were
both happy. She is given the comforts that we can
afford, by way of food, clothing, toys and attention. As
a rule once we are back home for the day after work,
we give her our company and it is seldom that we leave
her to go out for an evening. We should feel sorry to
deprive her of our company them. She loves to play
and talk to us. I feel very proud that I breast-fed my
daughter for ten full months, just as my mother did for
me.
We hope to give her the best education available in
this country, and later even in England if she turns out
to be enterprising and interested. We shall leave it to
her whether or not to choose a career or what career to
choose. Whether she has a career or not, we wish to see
her happily married to an intelligent, educated good-
natured, ' well-mannered and understanding Ceylonese
Buddhist. Provided these characteristics are there we
do not mind her making the choice of the young man
without allowing us to arrange her marriage.
Subada Siriwardena is a Ceylonese educationist. Since
writing this article she has obtained her M.A. and
\2 !S now working for a Ph. D degree in education. She
intends to publish a loork on "Growing up in a Ceylon
Village" in the near future.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
BURMA
FAMILY
IN
TRANSITION
by Ni Ni Gyî
The 324 foot spire and
gleaming dome of the
Shwehmawdaw Pagoda
dominate the skyline of
the city of Pegu, 60 miles
from Rangoon, the Bur¬
mese capital. "Chin-
the", giant statues of
mythological animals,
guard the entrance to
this pagoda which was
largely destroyed by an
earthquake some 30
years ago. It was even¬
tually rebuilt with the
help of funds subscribed
by the people of Burma.
© J. Ph. Charbonnier -
Realities
hat her grand-daughter in short sleeves and
high-heeled sandals should be at a cocktail
party with a glass in her hand (even though it be orange
or tomato Juice) is hardly a picture that my grandmother
Daw Mein Ka Lay would have imagined In her wildest
dreams half a century ago. We have certainly come a
long way since the ya-hta-lone, the Burmese horse and
buggy days. In her time Ma Mein Ka Lay, as my grand¬
mother was called, was dedicated to the home and spent
all her time at household chores, and would never go out
at night except maybe to a pagoda festival, and then only
In the company of the whole family.
Thus it Is evident that even the staid and conservative
Burmese culture which had always boasted of being
Impervious to the influences of "foreign matter" is show¬
ing signs of thawing...
My family cannot be described as a typical Burmese
family, as the typical Burmese family would live on a farm,
be literate In Burmese only, be engaged in farming and
maybe never get to the big cities except on a pilgrimage.
My family can best be described as urban (we settled
down in Rangoon when my father retired from govern¬
ment service) with the socio-economic status of a middle-
class family, and we are staunch Buddhists...
It should be interesting to find out the changes that
have taken place from the days of my grandmother, who
lived under the last reigning Burmese king, to mine, the
post-Independence days. The span of time Includes
Burma under the rule of Burmese kings, the British
regime, Japanese rule, re-occupatlon by the British and
independent Burma...
In my childhood the family was made up of my grand¬
mother, father, mother, my sisters, an aunt (my mother's
cousin) and cousin who was really a poor relative living
with us. The family was mobile In the sense that it
moved wherever my father was transferred (he was the ^3
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN OF BURMA (Cont'd)
Children of the calendar
principal of a high school) and he was posted in each
town for a few years at a time...
The family system was very strong and absolute respect
and obedience were shown all along the line. Even the
children had to obey the next In line, according to their
ages. The deep-seated belief is that one is to show
respect for people even if they are one day older than you
are. My grandmother, being the oldest in the household,
formed the apex of authority and respect and she was
followed by father, mother, aunt and cousin down to the
children, from the eldest to the youngest. Burmese
children from childhood are instilled with the idea of
absolute reverence for the following in the order given:
Lord Buddha, his teachings, the clergy, parents and
teachers. This Is the reason why implicit obedience is
accorded the parents.
The attitude Is somewhat changed now; the trend is
towards more rational obedience, and relations between
my mother and ourselves are on a more informal plane.
I noticed as a child there was never any familiarity or
outright friendliness between my grandmother and my
father or mother; she was treated with too much awe to
allow that. Whereas now, if my mother makes a certain
decision, we are able to explain things to her and even
disagree with her and she takes it in the best light. In
fact, when I accompanied my husband on a world tour
In 1955 my mother was very much against it, but I was
able to make her understand my point of view and even
got her blessing for the trip...
I n the matter of giving names to children there
lis still much adherence to tradition. Every
Burmese child's name depends on the day of birth. Since
time immemorial, wise men have laid down a code
making certain sounds synonymous with certain days of
the week. To give myself as an example, as I was born
on a Saturday my parents could only name me from one
of the following sound: "ta", "hta", "da", "na".
In other words my name could being with only the T,
D or N sounds. Accordingly I was named Ni Ni. It is
only a first name and has nothing to do with my father's,
since In Burma we do not have family names. No strict
Burmese family will have any other criterion for choosing
a name for a baby. Thus in Burma it is quite easy to
guess someone's day of birth once you hear the name.
The only modern touch In the matter of names is that
most modern families are coming to realize the confusion
caused by having only personal names and are beginning
to add the father's name to the daughter's for purposes
of identification.
For example, just as Mary, daughter of Mr. Smith, is
Mary Smith, Ni Ni, daughter of U Maung Maung Gyi, is
now called Ni Ni Gyi. Wives, too, are beginning to take
on their husband's names in addition to their own, thus
if I wanted to be modern I could call myself Ni NI Nyunt,
as my husband's name is U Hla Nyunt.
In the matter of education, my grandfather went to a
monastery where he learned the three Rs but more of
religious instruction. My grandmother went to a lay
school were she studied the three Rs and scriptures as
well. The reason for the girls going to a lay school was
that it was not proper for the monks to teach girls. By
the time my mother went to school, Rangoon could boast
of a modern school called the Empress Victoria Buddhist
Girls' School and my mother and aunt were proud to be
its pupils and to learn English there. At that time my
*m maternal grandmother's idea was to give them enough
"modern education" to enable them to read English news¬
papers and she made them leave school after middle
grade. It was strongly felt that a full education was
only for the men...
The philosophy with regard to education had greatly
changed when we reached school age. My father, in
particular, had a very practical philosophy. Since he had
no sons he was determined to give his daughters the best
education he could. He explained that the best legacy
parents could give children was education, and often
repeated the well-known cliché that education is a pot
of gold that no one can steal. He thus sent us as boarders
to a convent renowned for its high standard of education.
My grandfather was at first very much against the idea
of our going to an English school where we wore only
European clothes and were given English names. He
could not for a long time resign himself to the Idea that
we were giving up our national dress (even though tem¬
porarily) and our own names for the sake of learning to
speak English, but he finally gave way in favour of the
cause of education.
In our generation two of the daughters got the benefit
of. foreign education. One of my sisters went to study in
England before the war. At that time the usual reaction
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Photos © J. Ph. Charbonnier- Réalité«
In an open-air restaurant set amid the stalls of a Rangoon market, Burmese families (left)
enjoy a meal of "mohinga " (soaked rice pounded and passed through a sieve before being cooked)
accompanied by fish or meat and sauces. This animated scene contrasts sharply with the Rangoon
marriage group (above). The young wife wears a traditional bridal robe and her husband is
dressed in a tunic and a ceremonial "paseo", a kind of sarong reserved for great occasions.
to the idea of a young unmarried girl going abroad was
not very favourable. Quite a few of our elderly relatives
criticized my parents for letting a young girl go alone
to a stange country, where she might be exposed to the
"wild ways of Western civilization." When I went to
study in the United States as a State scholar a decade
later opinion had changed considerably and my going
abroad met with complete approval from everyone.
t the present time every family takes pride
lin having a member going abroad to study.
In fact things have reached the point where even elderly
people would love to go abroad if "they could only get
the chance," at least on a pilgrimage. This is a clear
indication of social change and changing attitudes
towards travel and the lessening of suspicion of the West
and what It has to offer.
To return to the matter of dress: my grandmother wore
white cotton jackets (almost Chinese style) complete
with cloth buttons, fixed her hair up with one or several
combs on the top and walked sedately so that not even
her ankles showed. Her tight sleeves came down to her
wrist and her longyi to her ankles, and her hair for formal
occasions was done up like a cake on her head.
The above style of dress still prevailed until the end
of the war. However, the post-war fashion is to wear
short or three-quarter sleeves and now the present
generation of teenagers and young girls go in for sleeveless
jackets, brassieres, short knee-length skirts and high-
heeled sandals.
I feel it is pertinent to write a few lines here about
certain Innate beliefs and mores that neither education
nor modern times can shake off. In spite of the fact that
the Burmese woman has "gone modern" in more ways
than one, it Is almost paradoxical to see the way she
sticks to certain of her ultra-traditional ways. Speaking
for myself, I will never leave on a journey on the "bad"
days of the month and will invariably undertake major
items like choosing the day for the wedding, shifting
house, buying property, etc., only on the "good" days, and
these "good" and "bad" days are specified on each month
of the Burmese calendar.
To give another example, I would never bath or shampoo
my hair while my husband was away on a journey unless I
had definitely asked for permission to do so, prior to his
departure, as washing one's hair when a member of the
family is away Is believed to bring Ill-luck to the traveller.
On the other hand I fight with grim determination against
the custom that one is not to cut one's hair or nails on a
Friday, Monday or on the day you were born, and I do
It any time the necessity arises. Nor do I adhere strictly
to the mealtime custom of giving the first serving of every
dish to the oldest or masculine member of the family.
If a husband and wife are eating together, traditionally
the wife is not supposed to help herself to anything until
she has given a small spoonful to her husband first. This
custom is fine in that it is a symbol of respect, but we
find it more convenient to by-pass it and have done so
by mutual agreement between ourselves. If, however, my
15
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN OF BURMA (Cont'd)
World of the new
'rice winners'
mother or any elder Is with us for a meal, both my husband
and myself are prompt with the symbolic gesture.
One feature of our generation which was not common
In the time of my mother and grandmother is the emer¬
gence of the career woman. Burmese women have always
been noted for their shrewd business acumen and their
ability to stand on their own as village chiefs, and have
even sat on the throne at different stages of Burmese his¬
tory, but their taking to regular careers is a new pheno¬
menon.
The rising cost and standards of post-war living have
made it necessary to have two incomes in order to live
well. Although, the husband's Income may be sufficient for
the basic needs of the family, any additional income
contributed by the wife will afford the family the extra
amenities of modern living. In addition to this economic
reason, the modern educated woman feels a sense of
independence in having her own career and is thus eager
to make use for the excellent opportunities now offered
to educated women. Besides, it adds a touch of prestige
to the family's reputation as both are bread-winners.
I n my grandmother's and mother's day, the
I position was reversed. The husband took
pride in the fact that he was the sole "rice-winner" and
that his wife could afford the luxury of staying home.
We find that the modern career woman-cum-housewife
Is heavily burdened with social obligations after office
hours. In addition to her own professional social
contacts, she Is also expected to keep up with her
husband's. Consequently, the woman who combines the
roles of housewife and career woman has a full-time job,
out-of-offlce-hours professional obligations, her evening
social engagements, and the task of running a home,
does take a great deal out of the modern woman . . .
The Burmese woman has always had a distinct place in
public life. Theoretically speaking, there is no social or
legal . barrier to her holding any position in the. land.
Throughout Burmese history, the position of -Burmese
women has always been on a par with that of men.
Traditional law recognizes us equally with men and all
through our history we have had full Inheritance rights.
However, apart from the days when women ruled the
country, the Burmese women have not taken any great
Interest in politics. There is no great political conscious¬
ness such as is to be found in some other countries.
Accordingly, there is no Burmese counterpart of the
political stature of Mrs. Pandit, Mrs. Sun Yat Sen or Mrs.
Roosevelt . . . This apathy towards politics may be
attributed to the general passive philosophy of the
Burmese Buddhist mind.
We have certainly come a long way from the days of
my grandmother. We have marched forward but with
restraint. If In some ways the pendulum of social change
has swung too fast, it has been because we were swept
on by the Inevitable chain of social evolution.
Tt/1 ». *> rt°
From "Bangkok" by Martin Hurlimann
© Thames' and Hudson, London, 1963
ni ni gyi was educated in Rangoon. Burma, and in the
United States where she went to study as a State scholar.
fg She has sitice held several literary posts. She is married
to U. Hla Nyunt, a leading Burmese scientist, whom she
met tohile a student at Columbia University, New York.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
This narrow lane running between gardens and courtyards was typical of
old Bangkok before modern roads were driven through it. It is now a
metropolis of over one million people and with its many transformations has
come a wave of social changes. Today Thai women are taking advantage
of the new standards of equality of opportunity for both sexes and the new
economic order. Education has given them access to positions of influence
in a more specialized society. Freed from home-centered workwomen nowa¬
days often engage in petty trade, home industry or salaried office positions.
THAILAND
'I AM NO LONGER
THE HIND LEGS
OF AN ELEPHANT'
by Pramuan Dickinson
When I asked my parents' approval of my deci¬
sion to get married, my mother said: "If your
grandmother were still alive she would be shocked by
this." This was because I had decided to marry a young
man from a place far from our community, and our hemi¬
sphere In Canada. It was so unusual that a strong
protest was to be expected, at least at first. "But the
world has been changed a great deal," said my father,
"how can one resist such a great change?"
My father was right. The world has been changing a
great deal from my grandmother's days to our present
time. My grandmother married a man from the same
community, but whom she had never met before. My
mother became a little acquainted with my father before
they married, but he came from a place In Central Thai¬
land far from her community. This was something of a
shock because my father spoke a different dialect and no-
one in the family had ever heard of the village he
came from.
When my parents married, one part of the country
seemed almost like a foreign country to another. A wild
mountainous jungle between the north-east and central
districts made it very difficult for people to travel back
and forth. It used to take my grandfather two months to
cross by elephants. Now, on a modern highway, one can
cross within two hours by car.
In my grandmother's day it was unusual for women,
especially unmarried girls, to travel very far from home.
My grandmother, like all girls of her age, was educated at
home only. She was taught by her mother to work In the
household cooking, spinning, weaving and sewing. My
grandmother did not learn to read and write because It
was thought not proper for girls to do so.
My grandmother had nine children altogether. The
first, a boy, was sent to study with the monks when he was
about 12 years old. My mother was the second child. My
grandmother did not object to her daughters learning to
read and write at all. Therefore my uncle was encouraged
to teach his younger sisters in his spare time from the
monastery.
When my grandmother's fifth child was about 10 years
old, a school for girls was set up in the community, and
she was sent to it. My mother was too old to go, so she
continued to study at home until she married my father
who helped her to learn both reading and writing.
In my generation education was compulsory up to the
fourth grade. But most parents who could afford It liked
their children, boys and girls alike, to continue up to the
end of secondary school which was available in the home
town, and if possible to have further study In Bangkok.
CONT'D ON PAGE 21
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
THREE VILLAGES
UNDER A MICROSCOPE
Left, pupil teachers
in the science lab¬
oratory of the Thai¬
land-Unesco Rural
Teacher Education
Project at Ubol,
Thailand, 400 miles
from the capital,
Bangkok. This joint
venture by the
Government of
Thailand and Unes¬
co was launched
eight years ago to
train more teachers
for primary schools.
The Rural Teacher Training College at Ubol is one of several educational
projects that Unesco is assisting in South-East Asia, particularly in Thailand,
where the Unesco Regional Office for Education in Asia is situated. Above,
Thai youngsters play a lively game of musical chairs between classes in a
Thailand village school. Below, a young miss gets her regular weight-and-
height check-up in a village school. The teachers in this school come from the
nearby Ubol training college. During their second year of training teachers
have 11 weeks of practical teaching experience in "laboratory" schools near Ubol.
Below, a building with striking modern lines where some 500 fledgling
girl teachers live during their two year course at the Ubol teachers'
training college. There are now|J4 similar colleges operating in Thailand.
DURING the past year or so three
remote country villages in Thailand
have been put under the micro¬
scope. In Napa, In the central rice-
growing plain of the Bangkok region,
Udorn, on the edge of the jungle in
the north east, and Umeng, in the far
north near the Burmese border, a cross-
section of some 200 children and their
families have been observed, studied
and interviewed at length, each commu¬
nity survey lasting about six months.
These operations are part of a unique
survey carried out by the Bangkok
Institute of Child Study, founded nearly
nine years ago jointly by Unesco and
the Government of Thailand. The study
was carried out because Thailand, like
many other countries, is trying to improve
and extend its education system, and
knowledge about the nature of the child
is the cornerstone of any development
in education.
During the survey, researchers have
been asking questions such as "What
do you fear most In school and out of
school?" "What do you enjoy most and
why?" "What kind of responsibilities
and home tasks do you have and how
do they effect your going to school?"
"Do you like having girls (or boys) with
you In class?" Mothers have also been
interviewed and the general make-up
of each village with its economic and
social structures has been thoroughly
investigated.
In Thailand today social changes are
taking place in rural areas where, as
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
19
Photos Unesco R. Greenough
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Pupil teachers at Ubol
training college in Thai¬
land learn English aided
by up-to-date audio
visual teaching devices.
While mastering the
intricacies of the lan¬
guage, particularly its
pronunciation, they sit
in separate booths using
tape recorders and indi¬
vidual earphones to
listen to the playback
of their own voices.
About 1 ,000 young men
and women are cur¬
rently taking Ubol's two
and four year courses.
Three villages (co-rd)
20
in most Asian villages, little has changed
in the past century until recently. New
ways of behaving and living challenge
traditional customs. The staff of the
Bangkok Institute therefore has been
investigating the factors in home, school
and community life that affect the adjust¬
ment of children to learning and to
becoming responsible citizens.
They have been seeking the answers
to questions like these: "What are the
existing and potential points of stress
and strain on children entering school?"
"What kinds of teaching methods and
what aspects of educational programmes
are best fitted to ease the transition from
one kind of society to another?" "What
techniques may lead to conflict between
the child and the school or the child
and the family?"
No final conclusions from the survey
will be available until a fourth village,
in the south towards the Malay penin¬
sular, has been visited later this year.
But it is already clear that from the
experience gained by the researchers
it will be possible to evolve a new
methodology which can be used for
similar investigations in other Asian
countries.
This is already of great value because
the methods and yardsticks used in
Western surveys of child and family
psychology have been found to be of
little value in Asia. Any system of
education is part of a whole pattern of
values, social aspirations, traditions and
folkways. An attempt to transplant
educational ideas, techniques or methods
bodily from one culture to another may
destroy this pattern.
SOME differences were at once
apparent when tests used in
Western surveys were applied to
Apian children. It was found that in a
general way the Asian child's mind is
more contemplative, more shy and
withdrawn, less impulsive and aggressive
and less competitive than that of the
Western child. The survey showed too
that the Asian child has a tremendous
and genuine desire and respect for
learning, probably due to the influences
of the village Buddhist temples which
for many years were the sole repositories
of education.
Side by side with these surveys, the
Bangkok Child Institute has been
carrying out a nation-wide programme in
curriculum evaluation. Nearly 300
schools, some 70,000 children and 1,200
teachers have been involved in an
operation which made use of tests
and questionnaires. Achievement tests
were devised to measure a child's abili¬
ties in arithmetic, reading, writing, geo¬
graphy and natural sciences.
In addition to its research work, the
Institute has a training programme as a
graduate school for Bangkok's College
of Education with two-year courses in
general, educational and clinical psycho¬
logy, child development, statistics and
physiology, leading to a Master's Degree
in Education. Sixteen graduate students
are now taking this course. Fellow¬
ships, including some from Unesco,
have been granted to students from 1 1
countries, emphasis being given to pro¬
vide facilities for training Asian students
in research and teaching methods for
use in Asian villages.
The Institute's work is directed by
Dr. Lemaimas Saradatta, a leading Thai
woman educator, and its staff includes
two Unesco specialists and a number
of Thai graduate researchers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN OF THAILAND (Cont'd)
Reading and writing now proper for girls
Boys still had a better chance because they could stay at
monasteries in Bangkok. Only rich people could afford to
send their daughters to expensive boarding schools, but
every year the government granted some scholarships to
both boys and girls to study In the field of education.
This was the only chance for girls of poor families to go
to school in Bangkok, and only provided that they were
very bright.
At present it is quite different. ' Girls have many more
opportunities for education. They may now choose careers
as teachers, doctors, lawyers, and many other professions.
When I was of school age, my father decided to take
over the running of a mine of precious stones in the
wilderness of the jungle. There was no school at the
mine, which was at least one week's journey by elephants
from the nearest town, so my parents decided to leave
me with my grandmother.
I stayed there for some years. Then the time came
when I had to leave for further study in Bangkok. I was
sent to a well-known boarding school for girls. I was
the first girl of the family to come out of the home to
a school so far away. I was to go even further later on
when I was given a Unesco fellowship to study at the
University of Toronto, in Canada, where I met the man
who became my husband.
Looking back at the family history, I can see a tremen¬
dous change in the expectations about women's roles in
the family. My grandmother used to tell me how she was
selected as a wife. One day as she was weaving, an elderly
The fish pond at the college farm attached to the
Ubol teacher training college. Here, students
destined for schools in rural areas learn agriculture,
animal husbandry, poultry and fish raising as part
of a programme in community development.
Graduate teachers report wide village acceptance
of changes in agricultural practices as, for example.
Photos Unesco- tne rais'n9 °' vegetables and even cotton and jute
R.Greenoügh crops outside the present rice-growing season.
"x? &<%>
lady whom she knew dropped by and watched her closely
as she worked. It dawned on my grandmother that the
lady had a son who was Just at the right age to get
married. He had entered the monkhood for one period
of the Buddhist Lent, and was now accepted as being a
mature man who was ready to "have family." It was
the mother's duty to look for a suitable wife for her son.
If she had someone in mind, she would make a thorough
check as to whether the girl was good at home-making,
especially cooking, weaving and spinningthe handicrafts
expected of her. My grandmother was right. A few days
later, her mother told her that the lady had asked for
her to be married to her son.
I told my grandmother that I would have been angry
because nobody seemed to care what the girl herself might
feel, and also that the girl should have the right to select
her husband. My grandmother laughed and said:
"Grandchild, we girls at that time did not bother very
much talking or even thinking about 'rights' as you do
now, but we were still very happy. There Is an old saying,
'A woman Is the hind legs of an elephant.' That means
that you are to be the follower only, and I had done my
duty as a good follower. That's all."
I did not know my grandfather, who died very
young. He alone worked outside the home.
He gave all the money he earned to my grandmother
who kept the budget, ran the household, looked after the
children and made cloth for the whole family. Besides
being the place to live In, the home was a school and a
small factory In Itself. It was the only place for a
woman to work.
In my mother's day, the majority of women still stayed
at home. Very few had Independent careers. Wage-
earners were almost all men. There was only one woman
in the local town who had a job as a teacher. Another
woman, a nurse, worked in Bangkok.
At present, it is not unusual for women to earn their
own living. Most young wives and mothers take Jobs
outside their homes. All my female cousins of my age
are now wage-earners. Families have become smaller
than those in my mother's day. Most families can no
longer take in all the distant relatives as dependents In
the household. In most cases where mothers work,
servants must be hired to help In the home.
My grandmother always quoted the old saying: "Your
husband is a shading umbrella to protect your head. He
makes you look pleasant and respectable to all eyes.
Therefore, obey him." At present, some wives might say:
"But the world has changed a great deal, man and wife
must be mutually dependent toward each other, there Is
no such thing as absolute obedience on the wife's part
now."
Within three generations, roles expected of men and
women, boys and girls, have been tremendously modified
by the great change of the world. And the rate of change
has increased rapidly. I believe there was little difference
between the social life of my grandmother and her own
mother. But in the case of my mother and myself, one
can see a big gap between the two generations, and the
change is still going on very rapidly.
By the time my own children are grown up, what will
they think of their great-grandmother's days?
PRAMUAN Dickinson is the young Thai wife a Canadian.
She met her husband while studying at the University of
Toronto under a Unesco fellowship. She now lives in
Bangkok where she holds a research post in the Thailand-
Unesco Institute for the Study of Child Development
(See article, page 18).
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
VIET-NAM TWENTY YEARS
OF CHANGE AND TURMOIL
22
by Le Kwang Kim
I am thoroughly bored with this -essay on
Voltaire! I have no desire this evening to
emulate his caustic wit. Saigon, in this stormy May
weather is oppressive; in the hot and humid air the body
is damp with sweat and the mind is Incapable of effort.
Nevertheless, I must finish my essay or else I know what
I shall hear from the professor on the subject of the
usefulness of higher education for girls, on their proper
place in the home, on the quality of their intelligence . . ."
When these words were written in May 1940, girls who
wanted to continue their education beyond the primary
stage had to study at the mens' college. Thus every
year four or five courageous or foolhardy young women
adventured on the road to a bachelor's degree. It was
Indeed an adventure. The powerful and inflexible Confu¬
cian tradition forbade any companionship, any familiarity
between the sexes. They never exchanged a word except
on occasions of urgent necessity.
Nowadays, after 20 years, if I meet one of my former
classmates, bald, stout, married, the father of a family,
we cannot help laughing when we recall the past. How
things have changed since the morning when our group
of girls, wrapped In a haughty and dignified silence, arri¬
ved for the first time at Petrus Ky College, and made our
way along the corridors, following the red arrows which
would direct us, as .we supposed, to the lecture room, but
which in fact, to our great confusion, led to the lavatories!
At 18, like most of my companions, I wore my long,
straight, black hair in a heavy knot at the back of my
neck. Out of doors I wore silk trousers black or white
according to whether or not It was rainingbeneath a
flowing high-necked tunic. A wide conical hat of plaited
palm-leaves protected my complexion for, paradoxically
enough, while Europeans get themselves tanned and
CONT'D ON PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
© Paul Almasy. Paris
HARVESTS GATHERED IN. Viet-
Nam is a country of huge rice fields
which at harvest time spread a golden
carpet as far as the eye can see.
Here, the harvested grains are dried
on trays which look for all the world
like giant water lilies covering a lake.
In the countryside a woman's life is
still bound to the incessant and
arduous round of farming work;
in the towns the status of women
has been significantly improved by
social changes that have taken place.
GIRL WITH A GUITAR. Whereas
they once remained at home, directly
under the authority of their fathers or
their husbands, the women of Viet-
Nam, like most of the others in the
New Asia, are now finding places for
themselves in a wide variety of occu¬
pations. The young woman seen
here playing the "pipa", a form of
guitar, is a professional musician.
Unesco Courier Archives
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN OF VIET-NAM (Cont'd)
'With these earrings I thee wed'
bronzed by the sun till their skins are amber-coloured, we
who are naturally brown-skinned endeavour by every
means, including face creams and large hats to preserve
a clear complexion. My lacquered wooden shoes clattered
at every step. I rode to my classes every morning in a
rickshaw which, by my mother's orders, conveyed me four
times a day to and from my home. Mothers in those
days exercised a strict supervision over their daughters.
In 1940, Viet-Nam, together with Cambodia and Laos,
were part of French Indo-Chlna. It comprised Tonkin
In the north and Annam in the centre, both French Pro¬
tectorates, and Cochin China, a French colony, in the
south. As citizens of Cochin China we learned French
and were educated in the French manner like young girls
In France, although at home we lived according to the
Confucian traditions and oriental customs of Viet-Nam.
This circumstance may make it easier for women of other
countries to understand our reactions and behaviour,
which sometimes might surprise them.
Now on that May evening, while I was struggling with
my essay, I heard my father coming upstairs. Good
heavens, what could I have done to displease him? When¬
ever he came up to my room it was to scold or lecture me
reminding me of a young girl's duties to her parents
and her family. This might go on for hours for my
father, like every self-respecting, well-educated man,
was never In a hurry.
In these circumstances there could be no thought of my
essay; as usual I should have to listen, sitting motionless
with downcast eyes, looking as docile as possible. In
Viet-Nam, filial piety is the first and fundamental prin¬
ciple engraved on our hearts.
My father came in and sat down on the large couch of
polished wood, without mattress or pillows on which we
Paul Almasy, Paris
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Left, two young women of Viet-Nam the one in a "cycle cab" with a child on her knees; the other
on a bicycle in the traditional female costume of wide-legged trousers and split tunicwait for the traffic
lights to change at a Saigon street intersection. Today, many women of Viet-Nam are entering the
teaching profession. The one shown above is giving a lesson in child care to pupils of a village school.
Unosco-Piorre Pittol
used to sleep, our heads resting on those oblong, wicker-
work blocks which though very pretty with their brightly
coloured covers, were very hard and most uncomfortable.
He looked at me over his spectacles and quietly said:
"Tomorrow you will take your books back to the libra¬
rian at the college and give this letter to the vice-
principal before giving up your studies. Your mother and
I with the approval of your grandparents, have arranged
a marriage for you with the sixteenth son of Madame H.
The young man is one of the most eligible matches In the
country. They are Catholics and have asked that you
should become one, and therefore you will do so. It is
of no importance since, as a girl, you would not have to
be responsible for the cult of the ancestors. Your brother
will undertake this honourable duty. The day after
tomorrow you will attend Instruction at the Cathedral of
Saigon."
TíHus speedily, clearly and without discussion,
the two most important decisions of my
life my conversion and my marriage were taken by my
parents.
Do not be surprised that, a girl of 18, educated in
Western culture for many years, should submit with such
meekness to decisions of great moment affecting her
personal life so closely. In Viet-Nam the family ruled
everything, decided everything, but also took all respon¬
sibility for the consequences and supported all its members
in any trouble... I could not, therefore, live my own life
as an independent and responsible person.
In the turmoil of the months before my marriage I
was scarcely able to apprehend the change which had
taken place in my life, to question or to understand the
real significance of events. One thing struck me, however,
the presence beside me of the man with whom I was
soon to share my life. As he had not been able to get the
bishop's permission to take part, he merely stood respect¬
fully by while, on the day of our bethrothal, I carried
out alone the customary prostrations before the altar
of my ancestors, presenting my future husband to them.
After the ceremony he asked me affectionately If I was
pleased with the jewels his mother had given me. These
were a pair of earrings the traditional betrothal gift, like
the ring in the West with a pendant and bracelet to
match.
The southern part of Viet-Nam, before the second world
war, was a country of huge rice-fields, which at harvest
time spread a golden carpet as far as the eye could see.
Small hamlets or trim peaceful villages lay In the
shade of clumps of trees or green bamboos. A luxuriant,
fertile and prosperous land! That was why Its children
were gentle, amiable, and smiling; too gentle, Indeed, to
be energetic or pugnacious, too amiable to be firm and
decisive, too cheerful to be sober and ambitious.
The Chinese, who ruled us for a thousand years, were
not far wrong when they called our country "Annam"
the peaceful South. The easy Ufe, the bland Confucian
ethic, the tropical heat all these conspired to make us
what we were in those tranquil and peaceful days. But
one Is never sufficiently distrustful of still waters.
These same Annamites (as we were called), good,
generous and peaceable, suddenly exploded, as witness-
the events of 1945, when the people of Viet-Nam rose
with incredible violence and put an end to eighty years
of French rule.
This was the classic story of the Insurrection of a
dependent territory against foreign domination, with
guerillas, massacres, bloodshed and martyrs. It was also
the awakening of a people. Finally, it was the prelude
to a shock which affected every member of the community
CONT'D ON PAGE 27
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Some of the hundreds of junks in the "floating city" at Cholon, for long an industrial and commer¬
cial centre linked with the port of Saigon. These boats, moored along a watercourse known as
26 the "Chinese Channel", serve as homes, shops, storehouses and workshops. Cholon was
founded towards the end of the 18th century by hardworking and enterprising Chinese immi¬
grants, and has retained intact the traditional culture and character of a typically Chinese city.
Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
WOMEN OF VIET-NAM (Cont'd)
Achieving the 'golden mean' of Confucius
without exception and rocked the very foundations of
society.
The family shrank to Its simplest expression father,
mother and children. Individuals generally, and women
in particular, no longer protected within the framework
of the Great Family, began to measure their capacity
to cope with life. As a result, there was a frantic rush
to secure diplomas and enter professions. The young
girl's future had indeed changed; marriage still was to
be hoped for, but was no longer the one and only end.
For me personally the 1945 revolution was a harsh
ordeal. I was then a widow with a 2-year-old son and,
without a profession, without an income. I had to take
refuge with my parents who, when our property had
been destroyed by fire, had gone to live in a small house
they owned In the capital.
las, old age and the sorrow caused by the
.destruction of his possessions took toll of my
father's delicate health and in due course he died, leaving
my mother, seventeen years my senior, and my young
brother of 13. He was at the awkward age and had never
submitted to discipline, except from my father, who had
devoted himself to training him to be the future guardian
of the cult of the ancestors.
I spent three years of my life In this atmosphere of
mourning, insecurity and increasing disintegration, while
my mother continually bewailed the cruelty of fate, the
heartlessness of friends, and the outlook of post-war
society; to the end of her life she never succeeded in
adapting herself to the changing world.
All this was too much for me at the age of 22. Never¬
theless our troubles quickly matured me. When I consi¬
dered my brother, my child and my mother, I realized
that if I did not quickly take action, if I did not decide
to be "the man of the household", we would soon find
ourselves adrift.
What does a person do who has to support a woman
not equipped for the battle of life, to educate a boy,
to bring up a baby? She works. So be it, I would work.
But a rapid assessment of my capacities clearly showed
that I could achieve very little by that means, and who
would help me to carry out my heavy responsibilities?
To marry again was out of the question; it was not
considered fitting for a woman to marry twice. Was my
reluctance to marry due to a desire to show myself worthy
of my mother-in-law, that Indomitable woman, who
though widowed, was bringing up her children alone?
No, I think rather, though I was unaware of it at the
time, that the fact of being able at last to take my life
and my future into my own hands, having no longer
either father or husband in authority over me, liberated
me from my bonds, so that I intended to preserve my
new-found freedom at all costs.
I was, so to speak, intoxicated with sense of
being no longer a minor, no longer under
tutelage, being able at last to make decisions for mysef.
I experienced to some extent the feelings of a person who,
having just learnt to drive, takes the steering wheel of his
new car. It was the exhilaration of emancipation. It was,
however, a time of groping, of feeling one's way, the
discovery of life, of reality, for until then I had lived only
at second hand.
It was not without pain and suffering but for me it
was a time of great enrichment. Soon I realized that
in order to fight one must be armed, and well armed, and
that in every field my weapons were inadequate. 'To
educate two boys one must oneself be educated, and I
had not learned nearly enough; therefore, It was here
that I had to begin.
I managed to collect enough money to enable me to
go abroad and begin my studies again, at the same time
supervising those of my brother and my son. Through
this close contact with Europe I became, without noticing
It, and in spite of myself, progressively Westernized; this
was Inevitable.- The culture I had partially acquired,
now freed from the inhibiting influence of the family,
gradually developed and took root In me, soon permeating
me entirely.
I became completely adult, In the Western meaning
of the term; making decisions for myself, assuming
responsibilities, engaging In undertakings, discussing,
persuading, settling questions, becoming dally more sure
of myself and of my capacities and my potentialities;
already I was able to manage my two boys with some
competence and authority. This went on for seven years,
at the end of which I believed myself to be trained for
life. Having taken my degree, I returned to Viet-Nam
with my son.
In Asia, although the rhythm varied In different
countries, in general changes took place with the sudden¬
ness of revolution. In Viet-Nam particularly the speed of
change was stupefying. By reason of its geographical
situation the pivotal point of an Asia suddenly risen
to Importance Viet-Nam Is at the exact centre of the
South East Asian countries. Her capital, which had been
French when I left, had when I returned become cosmo¬
politan.
Nevertheless, cutting across all the penetration by
different civilizations, and the wider opening towards the
West, there was a persistent and definite return to the
traditions of the past, as if the people, alarmed by so
many new things and new Influences, were conscious of
a need to rediscover themselves.
I EEPLY influenced, In spite of ourselves, by
Western culture, we now found ourselves In a
completely different, environment, divided between two
opposing trends. Readjustment was not altogether com¬
fortable. It is impossible to define the effect on one's
mind of the passage from an organized society to a society
In course of organizing Itself as ours Is today while In
spite of everything It is still part of ourselves. One Is
conscious of being at once strong and weak, at home and
at the same time foreign, doubtful and also assured.
It took months for us to adjust ourselves to the pace
of the new Viet-Nam. After having learned to advance,
we learned to retreat, which we thought useless but which,
nevertheless, Is necessary. It Is only when one has learned
to move in both directions, that one really knows how to
drive.
It has taken me several years to achieve that delicate
balance "the golden mean" of Confucius between the
frenzied urge towards Westernization and the simulta¬
neous need to cling passionately to the old traditions,
both of which are characteristic of Viet-Nam today. This
gives me a sense of fulfilment and satisfaction which one
can only experience when one's personality has become
finally Integrated. It Is a strength and a stimulus to feel
that one has at least achieved stability In a changing
world.
le KWANc Kim is actively associated with women's
movements in Viet-Nam and in other Asian countries and
in particular with civic and social welfare projects. A 27
trained pharmacist, she has travelled widely and now
lives in Cholon (.Saigon).
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
WORLD SIDE STORY
CONCLUSION OF
OUR SPECIAL
INQUIRY
In its May and June issues. The Unesco Courier published
three articles on juvenile delinquency based on the results
of a special inquiry carried out for Unesco by William C.
Kvaraceus, Director of Youth Studies at the Lincoln Filene
Center for Citizenship of Tufts University, Medford, U.S.A.
In this final article, the author discusses delinquency as a
community problem which, he stresses, should be dealt
with by the community as a whole and not simply left for
schools, churches and police courts to handle. The full
report of this inquiry has now been published by Unesco
(in English, French and Spanish) under the title "Juvenile
Delinquency: A Problem for the Modern World". For further
information write to Public Liaison Division, Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
The photos shown here may seem
to many adults as typical of the attire
of the juvenile delinquent. Formidable
as it may be with its trappings of
chains, horseshoes, cowboy boots,
photos of "pop" singers, kerchiefs
knotted above the knee, etc.to
the psychologist and youth guidance
specialists such eccentricities are not
necessarily signs of delinquent inten¬
tions. The specialists admit, however,
that gangs, of boys (and even girls)
do form a major element in the over¬
all pattern of juvenile delinquency.
Photos © Comet, Zurich
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
IS THERE A SOLUTION
FOR DELINQUENCY?
by William C. Kvaraceus
(elinquent behaviour is not a twenty- four hour
malady that attacks a child like some virus
disease. Since a child does not become delinquent
overnight but as the result of a long and Intricate series
of reactions, any realistic plan to help that child will not
be easy to formulate. Any person, or any community,
hoping to change a specific delinquency problem must
accept the fact that It is a long process, often one of
discouragement and delay. It is expensive In terms of
money, time and effort. It need hardly be pointed out,
however, that the results of delinquency are twice as
costly.
What emerges clearly from many studies, reports and
surveys is that delinquent behaviour must be the concern
of the entire community, not just dismissed as a problem
to be handled by local schools, churches, police courts or
professional agencies.
Unfortunately even the most honest and earnest
attempts to curtail delinquency may fail without two
essentials: funds and facts. Any operation should have
as its .foundation a validated theoretical frame of refe¬
rence about the causes of delinquency. The community
should have available facts on the local youth situation
and there must be individual facts on the individual child
who shows a tendency towards delinquency or who has
already broken the law.
Such measures as curfews, restricting movie attendance
or closing a dance-hall, are irrelevant to the real problem
and, for the most part, accomplish little.
We know that there are many forces which decisively
affect the growth, the development and the ultimate
behaviour of the child. Among these are the home, the
school, the church and church organizations, health and
welfare groups and recreation organizations for young
people.
One of the most crucial forces, If we consider simply
the number of years during which it exerts an Influence
over the child, is the school. The school cannot solve the
problem of delinquency alone or even attempt to prevent
It single-handedly. However, Its role should always be
considered as a vital part of a well-planned community
programme.
Together with the home, the school provides the basic
learning experience for all children. Admittedly the
school cannot ever completely compensate for the lack of
a decent home or wise and loving parents. But it can
CONT'D ON NIEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
WORLD SIDE STORY (Cont'd)
When the school 'fails' the child
do much to make the child aware of his own basic values
and teach him how to develop them.
This is precisely what does not happen in the case of
the Juvenile delinquent. The records of many schools
show with monotous regularity that these youngsters
establish habits of failure and inferiority in their school
years. Therefore, the question that must concern the
community and the school why do children fall? Is not
easy to answer. The reasons for a child's failure vary
with each pupil. The teacher often faces real limitations
in trying to discover them. He is not always able to visit
the child's home, he Is not a psychologist, a health spe¬
cialist or a case worker.
Many educators believe that far too many schools adhere
too rigidly to a curriculum that is not appropriate for nor
of value to every pupil. After all, they point out, good
schools begin with youngsters who are already quite
different from each other and enable each to develop
according to his talents. The school programme which
provides only a narrow, one-track academic curriculum
that squeezes out overyone but the students aiming for
higher education Is denying equal opportunity to all
youngsters by such an exclusive focus on traditional
academic objectives and prestige.
I
30
F we agree that the child who might become a
good mechanic Is not to be considered inferior
to the child with an Interest in medicine then we must
also acknowledge that a single school should accommodate
and benefit both of them. Pouring all students into a
single academic mould causes many children who might be
vulnerable to delinquency to come a good deal closer to it.
The authorities and the community should consider setting
up different types of school experiences for children who
cannot benefit by a standard academic education or for
those children who, for different reasons, cannot hold
their own in the regular classroom.
In trying to relate the problems of delinquents with
their problems at school, some educators have asserted
that an Inability to read is frequently a strong factor in
their failure. Certainly the child who cannot read ade¬
quately will only be confronted with such a rapid
succession of tensions and frustrations in any classroom
that It is not surprising if school becomes a place to be
feared or despised. Vandalism of school property is a
protest; escape is\the only solution. Such a pupil may
resort to truancy or drop out when he reaches the legal
age.
If the school curriculum is a realistic one, there will
be remedial help available, but first the child must want
to improve. If a pupil has been humiliated too often, he
may never make the necessary effort. The school that
expels a child, or fails him year after year, is more or
less urging that student to get out when he is least
prepared to build his own life. If the school must reject
a pupil, then every effort should be made to find what
other help can be offered to that child by other commu¬
nity agencies and organizations.
But it must be pointed out that in many cities of the
world the problem of juvenile delinquency and the role
of the school is eclipsed by more urgent considerations.
It is not always a question of improving schools for some
countries, but of creating them. There is a bitter humour
in the suggestion that a teacher should do something
about a child's emotional problems when many teachers
In Asia and Africa face a classroom each morning
knowing that some children are sick and ill-fed.
It Is sufficiently tragic that each year more than three
million children are deprived of the right to education
but It is no less depressing to learn that many schools fail
to make their pupils feel that education Is a personal and
Interesting experience. These schools work hard but the
return from their work, if not the quality, is Inadequate.
While there are many children of the world who wish for
education, it can hardly be denied that there Is also an
Impressive number who want to escape It. And a high
During a day of violence
and vandalism at the
English seaside town of
Margate earlier this year
police arrested about 40
teenagers, members of rival
juvenile gangs from London
who style themselves the
" Mods " (short - haired,
suede-booted and jacketed)
and the "Rockers" (who
wear black leather jackets
and fringed cowboy hats).
Here, "Mods" chase a
group of "Rockers" across
the sands. Holiday makers,
watching the scene, were
obliged to dodge salvos
of milk bottles and broken
legs from deck chairs as the
rival gangs fought a series
of battles, broke shop win¬
dows and ransacked cafes.
proportion of these children who dread school become
involved in some form of delinquency.
Any school will make its maximum contribution to delin¬
quency prevention and control by becoming a better
school. It cannot achieve this alone. Ideally the school
should have some link with the health, welfare and
recreation agencies that exist In a community. For even
if a teacher is aware that a child is 111 or needs glasses,
she cannot provide medicine and a pair of glasses if the
family fails to do so. If a teacher is aware that a child
is disturbed or damaged by emotional problems, she can
only recommed a source of help. If a youngster has no
place to go and nothing to do except loiter on a street
corner, without outside help the most concerned and
conscientious teacher cannot create a better world for
him after he leaves the class.
I elinquents, for a variety of reasons, frequently
do not have an accepting or reassuring re¬
lationship with their parents. They can rarely discuss
any problems with an older member of the household.
They are not encouraged to share their own lives or
emotions with their families and this, in itself, is a
damaging restriction for a child. Any education pro¬
gramme or any counselling that the community makes
available to parents, providing it is wisely presented, can
often be a turning point. .
Some city communities have established neighbourhood
centres where Informal educational activities are conduct¬
ed. These activities include parent discussion groups.
Through these neighbourhood centres, people of all back¬
grounds who have a natural ability for different kinds of
leadership can be found and involved in committee and
recreational work. The basic premise of any education
programme is that citizens should be educated to help
themselves.
Little scientific data exists to show exactly what preven¬
tive procedures have been effective. If we think of
prevention as referring both to the forestalling of delin¬
quent behaviour and also to the reduction In Its frequency
and seriousness, then there are only meagre signals to
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A
*
guide us in certain directions. The very concept of delin¬
quency prevention is still a vague, experimental one.
As in the case of prevention, the control and the. reha¬
bilitation of a juvenile delinquent often begins with the
community. In highly industrialized countries, many
communities have a number of services established for
the benefit of all children and all youth.
These existing facilities are rarely the result of any prior
overall community planning and forethought. All too
often, they operate as separate little islands weakening
their value by the very distances between them. It is one
of the most urgent responsibilities of any community
programme that attempts to prevent, let alone control,
delinquency to know what these resources are, how they
function, how they can be improved if necessary and in
what manner they can most efficiently work together.
It is defeating, for example, for a social caseworker to
try to help a delinquent when his teacher, the policeman
on the corner and the people in the neighbourhood coun¬
teract her efforts, when the poverty of the family com¬
pounds the problem, and when she cannot procure for the
child the treatment he many need. There should be a
continuity and a high degree of co-ordination among the
services offered by a community, a close co-operation
between private and government agencies if their existence
is to make sense. No hope exists for the delinquent unless
guidance personnel, psychologists, psychiatrists and
psychiatric social workers are easily and quickly accessible
to the individual child through the school and the
community.
Depending on the nature of the offence, a delinquent
often is put in custody of a detention centre until his
hearing comes up in court. This may be days or weeks.
Many detention centres begin the punishment, for they
resemble gaols and the "detained" are given an all too
clear understanding of prison life. Other juvenile delin¬
quents throughout the world are even confined in a local
gaol and their cases are reviewed In the same courtroom
where criminals stand and are sentenced.
The exceptionally lucky delinquent may be referred to
a court which has a number of services at its disposal: a
(O Associated Press
decent and well-staffed detention centre, clinical resources
for child study, a highly-qualified professional probation
staff and an effective liaison with other child welfare
agencies. But It is a question of contrasts. Vast differen¬
ces exist not only between nations but often there are
extreme variations between courts In the same country
or province.
The establishment of special Juvenile courts with
trained judges and special legislation and practices Is
encouraging; many experiences and research studies have
proved the value of handling the Juvenile delinquent in
special courts and special institutions.
In the last fifty years probation and juvenile courts have
spread to many European countries, and have come to
rank among the most Important measures of treatment
and rehabilitation of the Juvenile delinquent. Probation
has been defined as "a method of dealing with specially
selected offenders ... it consists of the conditional suspen¬
sion of punishment while the offender Is placed under
personal supervision and is given individual guidance and
treatment."
^ometimes, possible methods of prevention,
control and even rehabilitation tend to overlap.
Police chiefs have often been heard to protest that many
youth workers act and talk as though the police had no
duties or responsibilities except to Juveniles. And yet the
importance of the police In a community with delinquency
can hardly be overstated since they often represent the
first official contact between the young offender and the
law.
The policeman or juvenile officer is the one who must
frequently decide whether to let the child off with a
reprimand or to refer him to a juvenile court or some
other agency set up to deal with such children. The
police also supervise the areas where youth gather to play
public dance-halls, movie houses, public parks, street
corners. How much the policeman understands about
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
WORLD SIDE STORY (Cont'd)
Success for the local police
© Magnum-Wayne Miller
In many places where special juven¬
ile courts have been set up to deal
with the juvenile delinquent, with
trained judges and auxiliary services
a decent and well staffed detention
centre, clinical resources for child
study, a highly-qualified probation
staff and an effective liaison with
other child welfare agencies en¬
couraging results have been obtained.
delinquency can clearly be measured in his attitude
towards them, which should be neither too vengeful nor,
of course, too indifferent.
In several countries the evolution of the work of the
police has given rise to more definite forms of action of
a preventive nature. In Denmark, the Copenhagen police
run four leisure-time clubs for boys in the 10 to 16 age
group who come from poor quarters of the city and who
have no adequate supervision in their homes. The police
have also organized and maintained a club for young
people over 18 years of age. All these clubs are devoted
to sports and gymnastics.
In Liverpool, England, a city police programme known
as the Liverpool City Police Juvenile Liaison Scheme has
been developed since 1949. Its object is to deal with
youngsters under 17 years of age who manifest some
behaviour disorders or who have already committed petty
offences. The children are referred to the Juvenile Liai¬
son Officer through normal police channels. The liaison
officer visits the child and parents often. He tries to
advise and assists them in various ways.
What is most significant about the Liverpool plan Is that
it improves the relations between the police and the
public in general. Police officers are presented not merely
as awe-inspiring law-enforcing agents, but in the
unexpected role of a protector of children and adviser to
parents. It Is claimed that this special operation was a
contributing factor in diminishing the figures of juvenile
delinquency in Liverpool, a city with the unhappy distinc¬
tion of once having the highest delinquency rate in
England.
A
32
Nother police training programme, that con¬
centrates not only on deterring delinquency
but coping with it and helping the delinquent personally,
is provided by the Delinquency Control Institute at the
University of Southern California, United States of
America. The training programme lasts twelve weeks and
the course provides the officers with an excellent
background for work with children in their own
community. They return to their jobs with an Increased
ability to understand the reasons behind delinquent
behaviour.
In highly developed countries, the community that
attempts to cope with the individual problems of the
delinquent without having the resources of a child gui¬
dance clinic close at hand places some severe, perhaps
Insuperable, limitations on its programmes. The work of
the child guidance clinic is related to the study, diagnosis
and treatment of troubled children.
All case studies involve an elaborate inquiry into the
home and family of the delinquent but through the case
study approach it is hoped to uncover the numerous
factors which relate significantly to misbehaviour and
which can finally be synthetized and analysed within a
scientifically supported frame of reference.
To sum up: where there is a strong will to help the
delinquent and when this is tied firmly to a sound know¬
ledge of the meaning and implications of the delinquent
act, there will emerge a promising pattern for delinquency
control and prevention.
One of the most obvious reasons for our concern with
Juvenile delinquency is the fear of continued adult crime.
It has been pointed out in one country that a very large
number of men in prison began their criminal careers
before they were thirteen years of age.
Therefore, we must look in two directions at the same
time: Immediate action and help for today's delinquents
and the often neglected long road of research to give us
validated methods for detecting and helping minors whose
behaviour may lead to delinquency. At the same time we
need to learn why certain children bend in the direction
of delinquent behaviour. -
Such research might seem to exclude the layman. It
will be done by professionals and be interpreted by pro¬
fessionals. But this need not discourage any person from
doing his own type of research through reading. Too
often one's knowledge of delinquency is confined to what
one reads hastily in the newspapers or sees in the films
where a delinquent often appears as the stereotyped
villain in a second-rate plot.
Our own judgement about his crime Is sometimes
inflamed by a dramatic denunciation in the Press. But
the delinquent needs neither our indignation nor our
sentimentality. He needs, most of all, to achieve what so
many adults have never attained: the knowledge of what
he is and what, with help, he could become.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
TTESTS FOR TEACHING AIDS: A six
year pilot project for the production
and use of audio-visual teaching aids in
adult education is being put into operation
this year by the Government of Senegal
and Unesco. Films, TV, radio, filmstrips
and posters will be tested and evaluated
for their value in language and literacy
teaching, professional and vocational train¬
ing, health education and agriculture. Stu¬
dies on TV will be made at a new TV
station to be set up by Senegal and
Unesco.
W1HOENICIANS IN THE CAUCASUS:
* An inscribed stone tablet discovered
at Maikop in the northern Caucasus may
prove to be a link between the Phoenicians
and the peoples inhabiting the Caucasus
about 1300-1200 B.C. According to a Sov¬
iet language specialist the hieroglyphs on
the inscription are similar to those used by
the Phoenicians before they devised their
alphabet. (See The Unesco Courier,
March, 1964).
YOUTH's ROAD TO INDIA: A prac-
tical guide to help young people to
travel overland from Europe to India as
cheaply as possible has now been published.
Based on practical experience, the guide
gives full information and advice on how
to plan and make the journey. "Overland
Route: Guide to Western Asia" was pre¬
pared with the support of the Unesco
System of Associated Youth Enterprises,
and can be obtained from Indo-European
Youth Hosteling Expedition "Elmwood,"
Clopton, Woodbridge, Suffolk, England,
price 3/-.
f~1 LASSES ON THE AIR: A nation-wide
^ network of radio courses in literacy
and other subjects is being organized in
Ecuador by a team of Ecuadorians helped
by volunteers of the European Peace
Corps. Receivers have been provided by
the International Labour Organization.
Local technicians are being trained to take
over the operation of the network at a
later stage.
Ci OSMIC CO-OPERATION: An experi-
^ ment in space communication carried
out by means of the American satellite,
"Echo 2," has linked scientists in the
U.S.A., the U.K. and the U.S.S.R. Over
a period of 12 days, specialists at Zimenki
Observatory, near Gorki, in the U.S.S.R.,
received 28 messages relayed through the
satellite, and nine bounced off the moon
after transmission from Jodrell Bank Obser¬
vatory, in the U.K.
Jfk RT BY RADIO: A series of program-
-*r mes on world art now being broad¬
cast on the Bavarian radio network is be¬
coming a firm favourite with listeners in
the Federal Republic of Germany. By
paying a subscription, listeners receive a
set of colour reproductions of paintings
and sculptures on view in museums in the
Federal Republic. These works are des¬
cribed and analyzed by an art specialist
during weekly programmes which were
inspired by a similar venture started in the
Netherlands some years ago (see The
Unesco Courier, Sept., 1959).
UNESCO PUBLISHES
15TH GUIDE TO
WORLD TRANSLATIONS
"Index Translatlonum," the interna¬
tional bibliography of translations
published each year by Unesco,
reveals In its latest edition (1) that
32,787 translated books were pub¬
lished in 70 countries in 1962 (com¬
pared with 32,931 In 77 countries In
1961).
The bibliography lists only translat¬
ed works actually published during
a single year and on this basis the
Bible remains the most published of
all translations (221 In 1962). The
works of Lenin, which usually follow,
fell behind N.S. Khrushchev's writ¬
ings which came second with 204
translations.
The centenary of Rablndranath
Tagore In 1961 brought the great
Indian writer to the fore and with
129 publications of translations of
his works, he ranked as high as
Tolstoy, the world's most translated
novelist. Other perennial favourites
with translators were as follows:
Shakespeare (112 translations pub¬
lished), Dostoïevski (95). Gorki (77),
Mark Twain (59), Hemingway (54),
Balzac (53), Dickens (50).
As In previous years, literature
outweighed other classifications with
more than half the listed works.
Social sciences, law and education
accounted for 3,686 titles; history,
geography and biography for 2.724;
applied sciences 2,659 and philology
and linguistics 113.
(J) J 5th edition, price :%20.5O: i.5.2.6.
(stg) ; 71.75 F.
Flashes . . -
IÎ CESKOSLOVENSKO
.1
Ï
¡If»
¡14..
Ü
it CULTUS PACISi
m
CESKOSLOVENSKO t\
i» CESKOSLOVENSKO
CZECH
STAMPS
HONOUR
GREAT
SKI
Shakespeare, Galileo and Michelangelo,
whose fourth centenaries are being celebrated
this year, and King George Podiebrad of Bohe¬
mia, who in 1464 proposed the creation of an
organization of states committed to main¬
taining peace, are honoured in a new series
of commemorative stamps issued in Czecho¬
slovakia. The stamp designs show (on left
from top): King George Podiebrad; two sculp¬
tures by Michelangelo; a scene from "A Mid¬
summer Night's Dream" and (above) Galileo
seen beside his telescope and other instru¬
ments. These stamps can be obtained from
The Unesco Philatelic Service, place de Fon¬
tenoy, Paris-7 . Write for prices and details
of other stamps from Unesco member states.
An electronic computer recently solved
in 30 minutes the problem of planning a
large building in Moscow. The same work
would have taken one man 40 months.
The computer worked out the dimensions
of the building and the number and size
of the rooms, lifts, .'.'aireases, and halls.
A device which keeps a constant check
on radioactive contamination in the ocean
depths has been perfected by the Japanese
Meteorological Agency. Equipped with a
scintillating counter and an automatic re¬
corder, it can be lowered to depths of
4,000 metres and it is able to distinguish
between natural radioactivity and artificial
radioactive contamination.
g The World Health Organization reports
that the main cau.vs of 70 per cent of
deaths in 22 countries and territories of
North America, Europe and Oceania are
as follows: heart disease, cancer, strokes,
accidents, influenza and pneumonia in that
order.
| Where a few semi-nomadic farmers
scratch a bare living from the soil the
Government of Ghana is now putting
21,000 acres of land under irrigated crops.
This is the outcome of a three-year survey
of the Lower Volta River flood plain
undertaken by a joint team from Ghana
and the Food and Agriculture Organization.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
AVOID DIDACTICS
Sir,
In view of the large number of
subjects you deal with and inform¬
ation you want to give your readers,
I fully understand your desire to
offer a greater variety of interesting
articles. But this approach is not
without certain dangers, for by so
doing you deal with too many
subjects and hence tend to be super¬
ficial. For me, the value of The
Unesco Courier has been its deep
approach to problems and the way it
has summarized and given form to
questions inadequately presented by
radio and press.
The suggestion that you alternate
"special issues" and "issues with a
varied table of contents" is only
partly satisfactory, since it would be
to the detriment of the special issues.
Your technique of serializing articles,
such as those on underdevelopment,
seemed to me to offer all the
advantages of the "special theme"
dealing .with a question in depth,
reviewing present knowledge of the
subject and in addition, making it
possible for the reader to assimilate
the material in easy doses. This has
the further advantage of not taking
up all the pages of an issue and
allowing space to be devoted to other
subjects. Another solution might be
to publish a few articles on a given
subject in the same issue when desired,
which would not prevent you from
adding articles on other subjects to
vary the contents.
I realize that your readership is
very varied and that there is no ideal
solution. The best solution, perhaps,
might be to strike a fair balance
between the possibilities. But for
goodness sake don't give us the class¬
room approach, which attempts to
cram. Instead, prepare apt minds to
understand and act in the world.
Brigitte Thiéblin
Neuilly-sur-Seine, France
TV TO FIGHT ILLITERACY
Sir,
I read your article "330 Million
Brains for a New Era" (The Unesco
Courier, July/August 1963) and I felt
deeply impressed about UNESCO's plan
"for making some 300 million adults
between the ages of 15 and 50
literate within 10 years."
Many countries are using television
as the easiest way maybe the only
possible one to reach the isolated
villages. If Colombia, for example,
can have T.V. network programmes
that cover 90% of the country, why
cannot other countries do the same?
Isn't it possible to start a campaign
to get the interest of teachers, priests,
pastors, judges, mayors, anyone who
is literate in each community and
who can afford a television set?
Each educated person should be a
teacher in a sense.
Can't Unesco launch a campaign to
get two free hours a day from each
channel for teaching and free lessons
published by newspapers and
magazines? I believe in many
countries much help can be got from
all communication media.
I hope you can realize your dream
of world-wide literacy. Millions of
people will bless you if you can at
least begin this remarkable task.
Helena Rocha de Tejera
Washington D.C., U.S.A.
MARIA MONTESSORI
Sir,
My pleasure at finding Dr. Maria
Montessori the subject of an article
in your April issue turned to dismay
and chagrin that Maria Remiddi
should write: "She undoubtedly follows
the great tradition of Rousseau..."
Such an observation is as jejune
and unscholarly as to conclude that
the Christian sacraments are in the
"great tradition" of the pagan mystery
cults.
In this time of unparalleled Christian
scholarship, when sensitivity to spiritual
values and to ecumenism is universal
(and when it is no longer de rigueur
even among the sophisticated to ignore
Christianity), why should not the sole
and the correct source of Dr. Mon-
tessori's inspired and dedicated labours
her Christian concept of human
dignity be recognized and applauded?
Jean-Jacques Rousseau indeed ! The
suggestion is, to put it mildly,
unseemly.
It is disconcerting to think that the
editor of a magazine of The Unesco
Courier's stature should wittingly or
unwittingly have allowed such a piece
of nonsense to appear in an article
marred only by the author's incom¬
prehension of Dr. Maria Montessori's
individual religious genius.
(Rev.) James W. Gray
Muenster, Sask., Canada
REGULAR COLOUR COMING
34
In response to the many requests received from read¬
ers all over the world we are happy to announce that
starting with the January 1965 issue The Unesco
Courier will introduce pages in full colour on a regular
basis. We plan to offer readers 20 full colour pages
grouped in four or five issues each year.
To make this innovation possible an adjustment will
of course be necessary in our annual subscription rates
and single copy price. This is further dictated by the
fact that the subscription rate of The Unesco Courier
has remained unchanged for the past six years des¬
pite continually mounting production costs.
On October 1, 1964, our new rates will go into effect as follows:
Annual subscription 15 - (sterling) 10 French Francs
2 year subscription 27/- (sterling) 18 French Francs
Single copy price 1 6d (sterling) 1 French Franc
Dollar rates will remain unchanged at >'3.00 and 30 cents.
In certain countries of Latin America, Asia and Africa no, or
only limited, price increases are envisaged.
SPECIAL OFFER
If your subscription expires before Dec¬
ember 31. 1964, you can renew for one
year at the present lower rates (see
inside backcover) provided you send
your renewal cheque or money order to
the sales agent in your country before
October 1. New or gift subscriptions will
also be accepted at our current rates
before October 1.
SUBSCRIBE OR RENEW YOUR
SUBSCRIPTIONS TO-DAY AND SAVE.
DON'T WAIT.
u
z
<
<
z
<
o
a:
O
LU
U
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
WORLD
COMMUNICATIONS
A new, completely revised
and enlarged edition
In its February 1964 issue. The Unesco Courier published
highlights from facts on the world's press, radio, film and
TV services reported by the latest edition of "World Commu¬
nications". We are pleased to announce that this 380-page
special Unesco report is now available to readers.
Since the first edition was published 13 years ago.
there have been tremendous developments in mass
media. This new, 4th edition discusses them all,
including outer space communication, television as
entertainment and as a teaching device, the world of
transistors, and the spread of radio facsimile and
teletypesetting for the simultaneous publication of
newspapers in different continents.
WORLD COMMUNICATIONS is a basic reference
work for communications studies, for use in schools
and as a handbook for mass media enterprises.
Price (cloth bound edition) 47 sh. (stg); 33 Fr.
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Prest Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. 1. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C-., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions "Labor",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Betgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis De Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 9). CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. Cyprus National Youth Council, P. O. Box 539,
Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30 Ve
Smeckich, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard.
Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120.
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 540). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP.
1 2598-48. (7 F.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag,
Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. 8, For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP. 276650(DM 8). GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol Road, Bellard
Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13;
Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1; 36a, Mount Road,
Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf AM Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, N usantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/3).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. (10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.,
6 Tori-Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo
Central, Tokyo. (Yen 670). JORDAN. |oseph L. Bahous
& Co., Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop. P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd.,
Times House, River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. $ 500).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta. (1 0/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins. Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V.. Willemstad, Curaçao.
N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office
20, Molesworth Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1
Government Bookshops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344),
Christchurch (P.O. Box 1721). Dunedin (P.O. Box 1104)
(10/-). NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos (1 0/-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet. Lille Creme
7 Oslo For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvcsent
Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks 115
(kr 1 3.20). PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILIPINES.
The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46x Warsaw 10
(Zl. 50). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda. Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA «. NYA-
SALAND. The Book Centre, Gordon Avenue, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE.
Fritzet Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 1 6.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska Unescoridet, Vasa-
gatan 1 5-1 7. Stockholm, C (Kr. 10); SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Payot, 40, rua du
Marché, Geneva CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 8). TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 litiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF SOUTH
AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News Agency. P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). Librarle Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil,
Cairo. Sub/agent: La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-
Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government
Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Man¬
chester, Birmingham and Bristol. (10/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St,
New York, N.Y. 1 001 6 ($ 5.00) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, New York,
27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, Moscow.
G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Paul Almasy, Paris
A BEACH I CEYLO
These fishermen's wives follow a way of life that differs decades, an increasing number of women are now living
little from that led by their grandmothers. But in the middle an entirely new kind of life. One of them, an edu
classes that have come into being in Ceylon in recent cationist, describes her personal experiences on page 7.
]]>
</page>
</document>
