<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062188eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Jl m
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
mam
JULY-AUGUST 1964 (17TH YEAR) - PRICE 2/-STG. ( U.K.) - 60 CENTS (CANADA) - 1 .40 F (FRANCE)
- ¿ >-».c
. *
' to ***» * ' * %to " ' *mw*- V
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
U.S. Bureau of Reclamation
GRE
DIVI
For millions of years surging river waters have gouged out mighty ravines
in the crust of the earth. The energy that once flowed away to the sea
is now serving economic development (see page 32). Above, construction
work on the Glen Canyon Dam (now completed) across the Colorado
River (U.S.A.) whose water will irrigate 560,000 acres of farmland.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
During seemingly endless
weeks and months land
and peoples of South Asia
have sweltered under the
searing heat. Now, as the
monsoon brings relief a
young Indian women joy¬
fully raises her face to greet
the first drops of rain (see
photo story on page 42).
© Magnum - Brian Brake
JULY-AUGUST 1964
17TH YEAR
SPECIAL DOUBLE ISSUE
Water and Life
Page
5 THE INTERNATIONAL HYDROLOGICAL DECADE
by Michel Bâtisse
11 WATER IN THE WORLD
by Luna B. Leopold
15 UNDERGROUND WATERA WASTED TREASURE
by Vladimir N. Kunin
19 SCULPTURE WITH WATER
The beauty of stalactites and stalagmites
20 THE THIRSTLESS CAMEL
23 CAN WE STOP THE CANCER OF RIVER POLLUTION?
by René Colas
29 WHERE WE STAND WITH WATER DESALTING
by Ronald S. Fenton
32 RIVERS OF INTERNATIONAL CONCORD
by Gilbert F. White
34 THE NEW NILE
40 DROPS IN THE HYDROLOGIST'S BUCKET
42 MAY THE RAINS COME
Waiting for the monsoon
44 PEOPLES OF THE DELTAS
A see-saw battle between river and sea
by Adriaan Volker
48 THE HIGH WALL OF THE LOW COUNTRIES
54 FLOODS! FLOODSII FLOODS!!!
by Maurice fardé
60 HYDRAULIC CIVILIZATIONS
by Pedro Armillas
64 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
THE UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL, SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
Published monthly by UNESCO
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7". France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition :
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
: Jane Albert Hesse
: Arturo Despouey
Victor Goliachkov
: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER il published monthly, except in July and August when
ic ii bi-monthly ( I I issues i year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian. German,
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 56?, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re-
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier It Indexed monthly In The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilaon Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : IO/-stg. ;S3.00 (Canada) ;7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
(M.C 64.1.. 193 A)
N* 7-8, 1964
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy. Paris 7:
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The great waterfall of the Iguassu River, on the frontier be¬
tween Brazil and Argentine (237 feet high and one and a half
miles wide) is even mightier than Niagara Falls. Every
second more than 61 ,660 cubic feet of water pour over the
Iguassu Falls to supply the need (per second) of
a community of 80 million people. The River Iguassu rises
in eastern Brazil and runs for 380 miles before joining the
Parana River on which there are the even larger Guayra
Falls which have the biggest outflow of water in the world.
© Alias, Paris
\
*
V
*
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The International Hydrological Decade
A WORLD-WIDE PROGRAMME
OF SCIENTIFIC RESEARCH
et
by Michel Bafisse
OJUR need for water is constantly increasing, whether wc arc
turning a tap in our own home, irrigating our fields or
running the cooling equipment in our nation's electric power stations and
industries.
There is an automatic increase due to population growth. Because of this
increase alone, in 20 years time we are likely to be needing more than three
cubic metres of water where two suffice today. The overall
improvement of living standards to which all men aspire, the fight against
hunger through the irrigation of more land for food growing, the creation and
expansion of new industries all foretell the need for even greater water supplies
throughout the world. Though it is difficult to calculate the exact amount,
it is safe to say that in 20 years' time the demand for water will roughly
double.
Such a rapid increase in water consumption can only be met through water¬
works programmes of tremendous scope and diversity. In many places wc
shall be obliged to turn to increasingly remote and inaccessihlc sources for
our water, or obtain it through the costly processes which purify polluted
water for further use or remove the salt from sea-water.
In any case, whether we are concerned with transporting water over great
distances, storing it in reservoirs or maintaining its quality, the installation and
construction work involved in doubling our water supply within the next two
decades will cost a fabulous amount possibly several millions of millions of
dollars for the world as a whole.
Faced with such a situation it is obvious that we should search as widely as
possible and with every available means for those sources of fresh water that
seem to be the least costly. But where do these sources exist? Only a
sustained and co-ordinated programme of scientific observation and research
in hydrology will tell us the answer. This is the purpose of the International
Hydrolological Decade.
The water resources in a region, or a country or even for the whole world ^
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
HYDROLOGICAL DECADE (Cont'd)
can only lie estimated through quantitative studies of the water "balance sheet"
of the river basins. As with any balance sheet, we first have to add up the
entries on the "credit" side, that is, the quantities of water that are received
in the form of rain or snow. Then we have to total up the "debit" side: what
happens to this rain, how much of it runs off to the rivers, how much seeps
underground, how much evaporates into the atmosphere, how much is absorbed
by plant life and then discharged into the atmosphere by the process of trans¬
piration. Other studies relating to changes in the quality of water or the
impact of man's actions on the hydrologie cycle are also needed.
All this work and all these aspects of research are the domain of hydrology
the science of the world's waters, the different forms in which they exist, their
circulation and distribution over the globe, their physical and chemical pro¬
perties, their interactions with the environment, including their responses to
human activity.
As everyone realizes, there is always a period between the discovery of
scientific facts and their practical application. In hydrology, however, we still
know too little about many aspects of the subject to be able to produce rational
solutions to water supply problems that will be facing us tomorrow. There are
plenty of examples to support this view.
The chief problem for the hydrologist, for instance, is that he has to deal
with a most unreliable clement. During certain months or years, the river
levels are low and wells run dry. Agriculture and hydro-electric production
arc hampered by shortages of water. Conversely, some periods are too wet and
disastrous floods are unleashed.
If hydrology is really a science, it should enable us to forecast the behaviour
of the natural phenomena Avith which it deals. The hydrologist should be
able to tell the dam builder what the maximum flood level is likely to be over
the next 100 years. He should be able to forecast how much water will be
available during a dry summer. Unfortunately, in the field of hydrological
forecasting we have still no reliable means of finding out these things, since
Ave lack records of observations carried out over a sufficiently long period, and
because we still know too little about the laws governing fluctuations in climate
and the movement of Avater.
uInderground water reserves are much larger than those on the
surface, but as they are unseen we tend to underestimate them.
It is vitally important that Ave make use of these underground reserves, but
never blindly or haphazardly. For example, where does the water come from
Avhich avc find in one or another of the underground water bearing layers (the
"aquifers") ? How does it move? How is it renewed? The age of an under¬
ground aquifer the time the Avater has been there may vary from a few
weeks to several thousand years. The aquifer may even be completely
"fossile" and never be renewed at all. And if this water is used, what effect
Avili it have on the discharge and future level of the water table? What are
the laAvs of hydrogeology? Despite the immense progress of recent years, all
these questions have still not been fully ansAvered.
Water storage in a natural reservoir under the earth, free from evaporation
and sedimentation Avhich plague surface dams, the pumping of these sources
and even replenishing them should their supply become exhausted all these
offer the engineer a vast field full of remarkable possibilities. But here too his
action must be based on accurate knoAvledge of the phenomena he is using or
creating, and so far Ave are only just beginning to glimpse this knowledge.
A similar need for scientific research exists in the branch of hydrology that
deals Avith the quality of Avater. In nature there is no Avater like the pure Avater
defined by chemists, made up only of hydrogen and oxygen. River water,
ground-Avater and even rainwater ahvays contain other dissolved or suspended
elements, and these, even Avhen present in small quantities, play an important
role. In the case of irrigation fanning, for instance, every drop of Avater brings
with it a little salt: the Avater evaporates but the salt remains and gradually
6 poisons the soil and plants. In general Ave now know Iioav to remedy this
problem of salinity with the help of leaching and drainage. But many ques-
A
GROWING
PROBLEM...
fe»&r-'
Water bubbles and foams as it
reaches the surface through an
artesian well drilled deep under the
desert at Ouarga in the Sahara.
The hidden water is reached at
widely varying depths : 240 feet at
El Golea, 3,280 feet at Ouargia and
nearly 5.000 feet at Touggourt.
The reserve of water locked up
in the immense artesian basin of
the Sahara has been estimated at
16 million million cubic yards.
© J.-D. Lajoux
Every day the city of New York
uses up over 1,000 million gallons
of water. These supplies are
checked weekly for purity, and
beach and harbour water is
watched constantly. Here an engi¬
neer of New York's health depart¬
ment takes samples in the harbour.
usis
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Thanks to irrigation in the south
of the Sudan, some 250,000
acres of parched land have been
reclaimed for crop-growing. But
here, as in other parts of the
world, the effects of irrigation on
the quality of the soil and on
underground water reserves has
created still unsolved problems.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
...IN
EVERY
COUNTRY
iij; ' *m n
Í 583:
m - 4 - - -
** 2 m - -i îl 4
HsitilL
tions remain unanswered regarding the effect of irrigation and drainage on the
quality of ground-water and the possibility of maintaining the ground-water
level below the zone of plant roots Avhile bringing to the surface the water
necessary for irrigation.
What happens exactly in this thin layer of soil which preserves the moisture
necessary to plant life? What form, liquid or vapour, docs the water take in
this zone? What forces act on the water, depending on the kind of soil pre¬
sent? How long will this life-giving moisture last? Evaporation from the soil
and transpiration of vegetation are responsible for the direct return to the
atmosphere of more than half of the water which falls on the land.
How exactly do these phenomena, which represent an enormous loss of
resources, occur? What part does a forest play in the Avater balance-sheet
of a given area? Does it act merely as a Avatcr-consuming mechanism operating
through the absorption and transpiration of trees, thereby reducing the
quantity of runoff which reaches the rivers or, on the contrary, does it result
in a slow seepage into the earth which can later be recovered in the form of
ground-water, while at the same time avoiding erosion? These arc the kinds
of problems which have still to be resolved in relation to all known yardsticks
and all the different cases which arise in nature; the ansAvcrs will only be
found through a vast programme of scientific research.
CIENCE has never progressed in isolation. To increase interna-
"tional contacts between hydrologists is already an effective
way of promoting hydrology, just as international co-operation among physicists
helps to promote physics.
However, in the case of hydrology the subject itself has an international
character. Rivers and ground-water reserves know no frontiers. No country,
however large, can hope to have within its borders all the possible kinds of
hydrological situations which must be studied and compared so that basic
conclusions can be drawn. The presence and distribution of water on a
continent or in any area of the globe is the result of water circulation on the
earth as a whole; in other words, hydrology's laboratory is the world at large.
There are still other reasons to justify an international programme. Every
country, whether economically developed or not, is facing problems created by
the rapid development of hydraulic resources. But everywhere there is a
shortage of top specialists and technicians in hydrology. While more have
to be trained the best use must be made of those we already have, in order
to help the many countries which are still inadequately equipped in this field.
Finally, more students must be encouraged to take up hydrology; public and
official interest in water problems must be aroused, before even more difficult
situations arise; and every appropriate scientific resource should be put at the
service of hydrology. We shall only achieve these goals by creating a strong
force of public opinion, which Avili only make its full impact if internationally
based.
The variability of hydrological phenomena from year to year mitigates
against the concentration on an international programme over a short period
during one year for instance as has been the case in other fields of science.
This is why the idea of a decade was proposed. From the hydrologist's view¬
point a 10-year study is not a very long one. Hydrologists prefer wherever
possible to work from observations made over much longer periods. But a
decade should give time for many scientific investigations and enable the
goals which have been set at the international level to be reached.
The general programme of the International Hydrological Decade was
worked out by an intergovernmental meeting of specialists held at Unesco's
headquarters last April. It is a vast programme, embracing all aspects of
hydrology. The meeting also singled out plans for action during the first
part of the Decade, which is due to begin early next year. These plans
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
HYDROLOGICAL DECADE (Cont'd)
A unique stocktaking of our resources
are based on the contributions for the general programme proposed by nearly
60 nations.
An initial group of activities covers the collection of basic data. Thanks
to the Decade, observation of hydrological events the quantities of rain and
snow that fall, the discharge of rivers and underground sources, the amount
of sediment that is moved, etc should be given a major boost, especially in
the developing countries.
Basic data of this kind are not only the raw material of hydrological
research; in many cases they will be of practical use to engineers for the
simple reason that if in 20 years time water works are to be constructed on
a river about Avhich little is known at present, now is the time to start making
hydrological observations.
Comparisons can only the made at the international level and a general
pattern of rules deduced on the basis of uniform and reliable measurements.
This is why hydrological stations in each country will be designated as Decade
Stations. In the well-equipped countries, this simply means that some existing
stations Avili be chosen and given special tasks. But in other countries Decade
Stations Avili have to be built, so as to create an international network that is
sufficiently dense and representative.
A second group of activities Avili deal with inventories and water balance
sheets, starting with those of the small basins and working up to the large
rivers, to continents and even to a world scale level. Research of this kind
assumes that sufficient basic data already exist to bring out a pattern which
alone can give an overall picture of the basin concerned. For a better under¬
standing of the hydrologie cycle as it operates in various natural, characteristic
areas, corresponding for instance to different climates, many countries will
set up "'representative basins" which may cover a surface area of seA-eral
hundred square kilometres. These areas will include at least one Decade
Station, and comprehensive observation facilities. "'Experimental basins,"
Avhich will be smaller than the representative basins, Avili also be set up. Here,
the natural conditions will be deliberately modified the vegetation will be
changed for instance so that the effect of these modifications on the hydro-
logic cycle can be studied.
Electric generating stations use
enormous amounts of water. To
overcome the problem of obtaining
water on this scale, ways have been
devised to make use of the same
water again and again by pumping
it through cooling towers, like
the one shown below at Etiwanda,
in California. The hot water
evacuated from the generating plant
is taken to the top of the tower. As
it drops to the bottom it is broken
into droplets by millions of wooden
slats and crosspieces inside the
tower and cooled by huge fans.
usis
A final group of projects will investigate a broad range of prob¬
lems involving scientific research in its strictest sense.
Scientists Avili be looking for answers to the kind of problems that have already
been mentioned. Every branch of hydrology runoff, soil moisture, evapora¬
tion, movement of ground-water, the dynamics of lakes, estuaries and deltas,
the evolution of glaciers or the geochemistry of Avater raises a whole series of
fascinating problems of immense theoretical and practical significance.
The International Hydrological Decade is planned as an international ven¬
ture in scientific co-operation. It is up to individual countries to make
Avhatever contribution they can to the programme. Since hydrology concerns
many different sectors in every State, National Decade Committees are being
set up to co-ordinate national activities. Some forty such committees have
already been formed. To provide oA'erall direction at the international level, it
is planned to set up, during Unesco's General Conference in November, a
Decade Co-ordinating Council comprising representatives from 18 countries.
Unesco plans to make a major contribution toAvards the success of the
Decade, by arranging for the exchange of scientific information, the organi-
8 zation of working groups and, in particular, the training of hydrologists in
countries where they are most needed. Other U.N. organizations, above alL
-
J
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
INDUSTRY NEEDS
220 GALLONS OF
WATER TO PRODUCE:
the World Meteorological Organization and the Food and Agriculture Organi¬
zation are also preparing to contribute actively to the Decade. Finally, many
international scientific organizations will also participate, especially the Inter¬
national Association of Scientific Hydrology which has Avorkcd for more than
forty years for the advancement of this science.
The International Hydrological Decade is a unique co-operative scientific
undertaking which will bring immense practical results. It will promote rapid
development of hydrological knowledge and should provide reliable scien¬
tific foundations on which to base the complex and delicate decisions which
governments must soon take if man is to obtain all the water he needs.
440 to 880 lbs of coal
20 to 140 lbs of steel
15 to 45 lbs of paper
4 1/2 lbs of rayon
Michel Bâtisse, a French physicist and engineer, has been a member of Unesco's
Department of Natural Sciences since 1951. A specialist in arid zone problems,
he was appointed as co-ordinator of Unesco's Major Project on Arid Zones in
1957. Since 1960 he has been head of the Division for Research Relating to
Natural Resources, which is launching the International Hydrological Decade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Cl
About 97 % of the world's water
is in the oceans. Over two-thirds
of the fresh water reserves- are
frozen up in glaciers and, above
all, in the polar icecaps. If the
Antarctic icecap melted it would
produce enough water to feed all
the world's rivers for about 800
years. The earth's land areas are
dotted with hundreds of thou¬
sands of lakes which contain 100
times more fresh water than all
the rivers and streams combined.
This gigantic cliff of solid ice is
a section of the Lituya glacier
on the Pacific, coast of Alaska.
© Bradford Washburn. Boston
WATER
THE WORLD
by Luna B. Leopold
he earth, Including Its oceans and atmo¬
sphere, ls a giant distillation system whose
operation brings about the distribution of Iresh water
throughout the world, from the frozen wastes of polar
regions to the burning- equatorial deserts. Stated In the
simplest terms, distillation, condensation and liquid flow
are the elemental processes which, on a grand scale,
distribute and circulate throughout the world the water
which ls essential for all Ufe.
Water in liquid form absorbs heat energy, chiefly from
the sun, and the absorbed energy changes the water from
liquid to gaseous form. Transported in the atmosphere,
the vapour later meets cooler conditions and condenses
as precipitation, some of which replenishes the water in
land areas.
Because water is continually being transformed from
liquid to vapour and back to liquid again, the whole
sequence of events ends where It began. That ls, the
condensed moisture in the form of precipitation runs
Into or off the surface of the earth, and a part of It
collects in rivers which flow to the ocean. The events
together form what is called the hydrological cycle.
The cycle cannot be stopped, fortunately, owing to
the fact that the energy which streams constantly to the
earth from the sun is inexhaustible. I say fortunately
because, were this cycle to stop, there would no longer be
that essential renewal of water as rain and snow to
maintain rivers and soil moisture and to grow the plants
and sustain animals on the continents. Indeed, were the
cycle to be stopped for some cosmic reason, all water
would finally come to rest in the oceans, and life could
continue only in the marine realm.
Though man is not able to alter the global cycle mat¬
erially, he may interrupt it locally by managing water to
serve his needs. That part of the cycle from which man
may take water contains but a small part of the world's
total. Of the water which ls precipitated as rain or snow
in the land areas, somewhat more than two-thirds is
returned to the atmosphere as water vapour through
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
WATER IN THE WORLD (Cont'd)
Antarctic ice = world's
river flow for 800 years
evaporation and transpiration by plants. These processes,
then, have first call on precipitated water and their
demands must be met before any runoff can occur in
rivers.
Considering how Important ls the water in rivers,
lakes and ground-water reservoirs, it is surprising how
little of the total water of the world is in forms and
places from which man may draw it with relative ease
to meet his needs. In the present state of technology
and water economics, the amount of water which can be
drawn from salty sources such as the ocean ls insigni¬
ficant compared with man's total need. Yet the reservoir
of salty water constituting the oceans is by far the major
portion of water on the earth. The oceans of the world
contain 97% of all the water in the globe. The next
largest Item in the water budget is also essentially
unusable by man: more than two per cent of the world's
water frozen up in glaciers and icecaps (see chart below).
The amount of water in the icecaps is large compared
with that In rivers. If the Antarctic icecap were melted,
the amount of water freed would, if supplied at a uni¬
form rate, feed the Mississippi River for 50,000 years.
It could provide the flow of all the rivers in the world
for about 800 years.
Rivers constitute for mankind as a whole the principal
source of water. Yet, surprisingly enough, this principal
source contains at any one moment only about one
hundredth of one percent of the water on the globe.
Being such a small percentage, it ls therefore under¬
standable that the surface water varies In availability
owing to the exigencies of day-to-day and month-to-
month weather and the large differences in climatic
character from place to place on the continents.
Because water is essential for man's existence, ways of.
providing him with what he needs have been discovered
and rediscovered by successive generations and under a
great variety of environmental conditions. Many civili¬
zations and certainly many cultures have derived their
particular stamp and character from the conditions of
life within which local water supplies had to be derived.
Man has shown great versatility in finding ways of
WORLD'S ESTIMATED WATER SUPPLY
12
LOCATION
Water volume
(cubic miles)
% of total
water
30 000
25 000
300
16 000
1 000 000
1 000 000
0.009
Saline lakes and Inland seas.
Average in rivers and streams
Soil moisture and near-
surface ground water ....
Ground water within depth
0.008
0.0001
0.005
0.31
Ground water-deep lying... 0.31
Total liquid water in land
2 070 000
7 000 000
3 100
317 000 000
0.635
2.15
0.001
97,2
(From Raymond L. Nace, United States Geological Survey)
making use of water as it occurred in its great circle
through the hydrologie ring.
Modern water problems, in fact, seem tó be merely
variants of the age-old difficulties that mankind has
faced again and again. The water problems in the
modern world are largely problems In learning to manage
a variable resource. This is exactly the problem faced
by ancient civilizations when man first began to build
small dams for the diversion of water in surface channels,
when he learned to dig wells, and more recently when he
developed the centrifugal pump and iron pipe.
Consider again the statement that the water most
easily available to man is an extremely small part of
the total water on the earth. The ease of withdrawal is
of course influenced by the amounts from which with¬
drawal is to be made, and these amounts are highly
variable. The resource would be much more variable-
than it actually is were it not for the effect of the porous
soil which acts as a simple but universal natural regu¬
lating reservoir.
Storage of any commodity tends to even out the Varia¬
tions of supply and to provide a more uniform output.
Winter storage of water ls one way to reduce seasonal
variations and to make the supply sufficiently uniform
to last during periods of deficient rainfall. Storage, there¬
fore, is the key both in the natural environment and in
man's hydraulic works, to decrease the variability of the
inflow. Outflow from a storage reservoir can be uniform
even though inflow to the reservoir is very erratic.
Water flows in river channels even during long rainless
periods because the precipitation from previous storms
has been temporarily stored in the ground and is now
being slowly released. Thus streamflow ls less erratic
than precipitation because of the storage provided by
the porous earth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
) Ijy Transpiration"
THE WATER
CYCLE
All water comes from the
ocean and is returned to it
in a continuous hydrolo¬
gical cycle. Subcycles, or
short circuits, occur on land
where water evaporates or
is transpired by vegetation.
The water vapour contained
in the atmosphere amounts
to less than a one hundred
thousandth part of the
waters of the globe. A
single cabbage may with¬
draw and transpire one
quart of water daily, and a
quite ordinary tree as much
as 50 gallons. The immense
reserve of underground
water (3.600 times the
volume of the water flow¬
ing in all the world's
rivers) in the first half mile
of the earth's crust shares
in this cycle of water
movement by flowing into
rivers, lakes and the sea.
Drawing iÇ) "Natural History".
January 1904
But man still has much to learn about using the natu¬
ral storage provided by nature. An example of how large
is one part of this natural storage is the amount of
water in the ground. Water stored naturally in the
ground within the upper half mile of the earth's surface
amounts to about a million cubic miles of water. This
Is some 3,000 times larger than the amount of water in
the rivers of the world at any given moment in time.
It is also 20 times larger than the amount of water in
all the fresh water and saline lakes and inland seas in
the world.
By far the largest amount of usable water at present
not used by man is underground. Compared with this
stored ground water, the amount which can be stored by
dams on rivers is small indeed. The difficulty is that
ground water, lying unseen, is not as easily surveyed or
estimated, and usually requires considerable technical
knowledge and modern equipment to exploit on a large
scale.
Moreover, because ground water ls a stored reserve, its
exploitation may under certain circumstances lead to its
exhaustion. Or exploitation may lead to lowering of the
ground water levels to such a depth that further exploi¬
tation becomes too costly. This might be described as
economic exhaustion.
One of the great needs, therefore, is to learn how to
put water underground Into the natural storage reser¬
voirs provided by porous rocks and gravel, in large quan¬
tity and economically. If this were done, one could with¬
draw the water again by pumping during times of shor¬
tage and would avoid the losses by evaporation which
may be important in surface reservoirs.
Furthermore, the storage space available underground
In porous materials is nearly everywhere very much lar
ger than the space even in the largest man-made surface
reservoir. But we have not yet learned how to use the
underground storage In the most practical ways.
In summary, there is much more water on the earth
than man can use, but most of it is salty and relatively
little ls actually available for human use. The small
amount available ls variable In time and space and these
variabilities are the cause of water problems.
The principal approach to eliminating variability is
storage and the natural storage provided by rocks and
unconsolidated materials just beneath the earth's surface
exceed by far the surface storage facilities man has built
or could build even In the most advanced countries.
Advanced technologies allow withdrawal of ground
water faster than it can be replenished by natural
recharge. Overdraft on water in one place relative to
another may worsen water problems by increasing the
geographic variability of usable water, as is described in
other articles in this Issue of The Unesco Courler. The
International Hydrological Decade ls an attempt by
Unesco to attract world attention to the Importance of
learning more about water on the earth. It is hoped
that the results of such improved knowledge on the
occurrence of water and the processes involved will
improve man's ability generally to utilize this resource
better and more efficiently for the good of mankind.
Luna B. Leopold is chief hydrologist of the U.S. Geological
Survey, Dept. of the Interior, Washington, for which he
directs studies on river measurements, ground water and
water quality. He has written many studies on hydro-
logical problems and his most recent work, "Fluvial Pro¬
cesses in Geomorphology" was written in co-authorship
with M.G. Wolman and John P. Miller.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Even in the mo« arid deserts palm trees sometimes
survive (as in this striking. air view of the Sahara)
by drawing nourishment from underground water.
But there is always the threat that they may be
buried by sand dupes displaced by desert winds.
c EmH Brunne». Bi .vitmland
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
UNDERGROUND WATER
-A WASTED TREASURE
by Vladimir N. Kunin
^* LTHOUGH the tremendous world increase in the use
of water has taken scientists by surprise, they are
confident that future water needs can be fully met. With wider
recognition of the fact that water is a world priority problem, science
should have no difficulty in quickly making up for lost time.
Apart from the water reserves in the world's rivers, lakes and
seas, there is an almost untapped source underground water. Ray¬
mond L Nace, a leading American hydrologist, has estimated that
the first half-mile of the earth's crust contains about one million
cubic miles of water. It would take the annual flow of all the
earth's rivers 132 years to fill such a reservoir! Modern science
should learn to use this wealth of underground water to the full.
The great civilizations of the ancient East among them Assyria,
Babylon, Egypt, and Khorezm in central Asia all evolved in desert
regions where people had to make the best use of very little water.
These civilizations grew up in the basins of big rivers. But these
same big rivers as well as their tributaries rise in places far
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
WASTED TREASURE (Cont'd)
Tools of today's water detective
radio and aerial photography
removed from the deserts; they are "strangers" to the
places where they bring the greatest benefit. By using
local water man has also farmed desert and semi-arid
areas in places far beyond the areas watered by these
"stranger" rivers. I am sure that if a proper study
were made of all the traditional methods employed by
the desert peoples to obtain and make use of water, and
If modern science and engineering were applied to per¬
fect these methods, many water supply difficulties would
be overcome. This would give temporary relief until
such times as cheap ways of pumping underground water
and of demlnerallzing and purifying surface waters (and
of using them several times over) are Introduced.
The underground waters in some of the Transcaspian
deserts for instance are all highly mineralized; yet from
far-off times man has successfully bred livestock in these
deserts. He solved his problem in two ways: by artificially
creating fresh subsoil water and by giving cattle and
sheep saline water to drink.
Fresh subsoil water formed by the Infiltration of rain
from the catchment basin has been utilized since ancient
days. At the end of the nineteenth century engineers
began to use a method of regulating water resources by
the artificial replenishment of subsoil waters. Desert
peoples, however, had actually been using similar methods
for centuries.
Such techniques, of course, are only practicable when
there are sufficient rains, an extensive catchment basin,
a high run-off from the surface and suitable geological
conditions for the accumulation of subsoil waters. An
annual rainfall of 80 mm., of which half should be
concentrated in two or three months, has been found
sufficient.
Even in a desert with clayish soil the run-off only
accounts for between l/10th and l/5th of the
of the total rainfall. However, the. use of synthetic
substances to form artificial drainage areas should pro¬
duce a higher rate of run-off. Other methods to assist
'PIPELINES'
FROM
THE PAST
Long lines of giant "mole hills" running cross the countryside in Iran (below) mark the route
of underground galleries called "kanats" (also spelt "qanat" and "ghanat"). Pockets of water
that collect underground at the foot of the mountains are tapped and flow along these tunnels,,
sometimes for many miles, to crop-growing areas. The "mole hills" mark the site of vertical
shafts through which earth was excavated during tunnelling operations, and which now provide
ventilation. Kanats were first developed in Iran some 3,000 years ago and their immense net¬
work made possible the economic prosperity on which the power of the Persian Empires of
antiquity was founded. Without the kanats, cities like Teheran, Tabriz and Chiraz would probably
never have existed. Today more than 30,000 kanats are still used in Iran, mostly for irrigation.
Michel Bâtisse
16
V ?*
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
ft
Weil- - I Vadosa Watet* _«0*í>í¿*íC2<*£Ía
Casing - - *4[£ "t. |
pewatered"4Sround Wa,et< t - -
^FÍocharge _ |-£
Beneath most land areas of the world there is a zone where the pores
of rocks and sediments are completely saturated with water. Hydrologists
call this "ground water", and the upper limit of the saturated zone is called
the "water table". They are now studying how to detect and make
use of the deep layers of water and also how to avoid exhausting them.
Drawing © "Natural History", January 1964
LEGENDS OF THE SPRINGS
The peoples of the ancient world
saw no particular relationship be¬
tween rain or storms and the under¬
ground water in wells and hill-side
springs. "The waters of the ocean
penetrate deep into the earth under
wind-pressure and rise to feed the
springs thanks to gravity, which com¬
presses the rocks", said the Greek
philosopher and astronomer. Thaïes
of Miletus, in the 7th century B.C.
Plato also thought that water reaching
the surface came originally from the
ocean, through a deep abyss descend¬
ing to the centre of the earth. "My
observations", said Seneca, "show that
rainfall cannot explain the formation
of springs, for it can penetrate only a
little way into the ground whereas
it is evident that springs sometimes
originate at great depths... rain is never
sufficiently strong or continuous to
sink more than ten feet into the
ground." It was only in the 16th cen¬
tury that science began to offer expla¬
nations moreakin to present-day views.
the replenishment of subsoil waters will also have to be
used until anti-evaporation substances that effectively
retain fresh water have been devised. These substances
will be most effective if used In small basins where there
is no disturbance of the water.
Because rainwater provides only a minimum water
supply the desert herdsmen have had to train their stock
to drink salt water. Some valuable animals camels and
caracul sheep, for Instance drink water with a salt
content of from 10 to 12 or even from 15 to. 16 grammes
per litre, gain weight regularly and breed normally.
There is no reason why similar uses should not be made
of such water in other areas.
RECENTLY much has been written about the
use of heavily saline water for irrigation; and
many international symposia have been devoted to this
Important problem. It is even proposed to use water with
as much salinity as seawater (35 grammes per litre) to irri¬
gate farmlands. In my opinion, attention should first
be paid to the development of reliable methods for the
irrigation of a variety of crops using water with a salt
content of 10 to 15 grammes per litre. This would be of
great economic value and would bring new life to very
extensive regions.
Desert dwellers get water from great depths by digging
wells. I once saw a well 880 feet deep made by a man
who could neither read nor write. In the desert and
arid regions wells over 300 feet deep are not a rarity.
One of the most remarkable devices for getting water in
the desert is the underground tunnel or gallery known by
different names klariz, kanat, fogghza, etc. in different
lands. But whatever the name, the principle Is always
the same.
Iran offers the best examples of the kanat technique.
It is hardly likely that anybody has ever counted all the
existing tunnels, but there are said to be some 30,000.
Many thousands of communities, large and small, In an
area stretching from North-West Africa to the eastern
extremes of Central Asia, rely on kanat water for all
their needs, expeclally for irrigation. The total length
of these tunnels ls probably over 300,000 miles. Even
if this figure is not entirely accurate, the wealth of
tunnels shows what a gigantic and laborious task was
performed by the people of these arid regions in their
search for water.
In the kanat or kiariz technique the water ls collected
underground in hilly areas and is brought through long
tunnels by the force of gravity until it reaches ground
level In lower-lying areas. The extensive networks of
kanat tunnels in places where nothing on the surface
reveals the presence of ground water are a tribute to
the creative genius of the desert peoples. Today, In
regions where electricity is too scarce to be used for
raising water, the kanat would certainly prove its worth.
Kanats can also be combined with drilled wells to
Increase the water Intake.
THE search for fresh ground water in the
deserts is of first-rate Importance and
although initial prospecting costs are high they are usually
justified by the results. Western Turkmenistan for Ins¬
tance, a big industrial area with oil wells, railways, towns
and ports, relies entirely on subsoil water drawn from the
"waterless desert". This still-developing area will continue
its economic expansion with the help of underground
water.
In the desert regions of the U.S.S.R. a new method of
locating fresh water has been developed. This is a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
WASTED TREASURE (Cont'd)
Fantastic reservoirs
of the lower depths
variation of the already widely-employed radio-pros¬
pecting technique of geophysics. Radio waves reflected
from the surface of the underground water (the angle of
reflection varying according to its salinity) are picked
up by an aircraft flying overhead. Engineers are thus
able to find concentrations of underground water and
assess the water resources of wide areas rapidly and
effectively. There are great possibilities for further deve¬
lopment in this technique.
It ls obvious that economical ways of assessing the
amount of underground water contained in such aquifers
must now be found. The various electrical prospecting
methods now being used reduce well drilling to a mini¬
mum, but these methods can only be used to locate
water concentrations relatively close to the surface.
Desert geographical conditions have a direct influence
on many characteristics of the upper layers of under¬
ground waters, especially their high salinity; but they
probably have no effect at greater depths. Thus in the
desert, as elsewhere, there may be both fresh and mine¬
ralized waters at great depths.
If the desert is close to a mountainous region in which
rainfall ls plentiful In an otherwise arid zone, the moun¬
tains with their bare slopes and sparse vegetation will
supply water to replenish the underground waters of the
desert lowlands. Some examples are the huge artesian
basins adjoining the Tian Shan mountains in Central
Asia, the Altai mountains of southern Siberia and Mon¬
golia, and the Atlas Mountains in Morocco.
-
: .
18
I F local water resources are to be used for the
development will depend on our learning far more about
the lower geological strata than we know today.
Until 1940, engineers considered that detailed topo¬
graphical and geological charts were indispensable as
guides to the test drilling that precedes more compre¬
hensive studies and the actual construction of water-
raising installations. To produce such charts takes a
great deal of time and money and today simpler methods
may be used.
Aerial photographs enable scientists to divide the
earth's surface into its natural divisions and determine
the most likely distribution of the upper layers of under¬
ground water. The general distribution pattern of deeper
waters may be gauged from geological structure charts
similar to those used by oil prospectors.
The oilman first looks for geological structures where
oil is likely to accumulate and when he has found them
he begins looking for the oil itself. Using the same
technique the water prospector will probably meet with
greater success, for there ls water in all permeable rocks.
Charts of this type can be compiled from regional seismic
and gravimetric data. More precise information can
then be obtained by any of the various electrical
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
*^i. :
i«?
l
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
These forms sculpted by the hand of nature, from a collection made by the
speleologist, Norbert Casteret, are now on view at the Fontaine-de-Vaucluse
Museum in southern France. Below left, stalactite with an "eccentric"
ending. Below, "ballet" of calcite deposits. Right, a "cauliflower" stalactite
formed by water impregnated with aragonite, a carbonate of lime.
Photos© Reporters Associés. Paris
SCULPTURE
WITH WATER
In the darkness of the world's
caves and grottos, centuries
and eons of time have
chiselled out graceful pil¬
lars and draperies in stone.
These mineral deposits are
caused by water seeping
through porous limestone
rocks. Dripping from the
ceiling of a cave, the water
leaves particles of lime. In
time a " stalactite" is formed,
hanging from the roof. The
drops deposit more lime as
they splash on the floor of the
cave and so form "stalag¬
mites" which point upwards
like icicles in reverse. Some¬
times stalactites and stalag¬
mites join together to form
pillars. When infiltrating water
runs down the cave walls
it forms stone curtains or
drapes, as in the cave of La
Clamouse, at St.-Guilhem-le-
Désert in the south of France
(left). As the other photos
show, these stone formations
can take on far more eccentric
shapes. This happens when
the drops of water are diverted
to one side or when air
currents in the cave produce
more evaporation on one
side of the mineral formation.
© Arnoud. Paris
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE
THIRSTLESS
CAMEL
The Unesco Courier draws its
readers' attention to a most beau¬
tiful book just published entitled
"Animal Worlds " by Marston
Bates portraying the infinite va¬
riety ofanimal homes to be found
on land and in the waters of our
planet. Recommended by the
World Wildlife Fund as "not only
a thought-provoking and beauti¬
ful 'art book' but an authoritative
introduction to natural history,
the book emphasizes that the
destruction of the animals' world
is the path to destruction of man
himself." The text is supplemen¬
ted with 242 illustrations. 100 in
full colour by some of the finest
wild life photographers. Pub¬
lished in the U.S.A. by Random
House Inc., New York. ($15)
and in Great Britain by Thomas
Nelson St- Sons Ltd. (84J-). The text
alongside is reproduced from
"Animal Worlds", © 1963, Random
House. Reproduction prohibited.
A.P.N.
Two-humped Bactrian camels from central Asia.
WASTED TREASURE (Cont'd)
Water galore if we're wise
20
prospecting methods; if this plan is used the amount of
test drilling ls greatly reduced and the data obtained
shows the filtration properties of the area selected and
the degree of salinity of the water.
Some major problems, however, still remain. How
much water is available ? What Indications are there to
warrant further large-scale prospecting and an assess¬
ment of quality? This aspect of the work is the most
difficult and the most expensive; it is here that science
must provide new methods of investigation that will
radically change the situation.
We possess simple and cheap methods of estimating
atmospheric precipitation and surface run-off. It Is
not difficult, for Instance, to calculate the approximate
rainfall over an area with a given geological structure,
and to assess the amount of water that has escaped
beyond the boundaries of that area. We cannot, however,
say how much of the water has gone to replenish under¬
ground water because we have no cheap and reliable
methods of measuring infiltration and evaporation over
large (or even small) areas.
THE present gap between scientific knowledge
and the needs of man should soon be closed.
We shall then be able to use the balance method (the
ratio of water runoff to rainfall) to assess the amount
of water in each geological zone that goes to replenish
underground water. Thus we shall have more precise
knowledge about the water resources on which prospect¬
ing and other search methods should be used. Scientists
maintain that the water-balance method can become a
universal technique of assessing water resources. But this
method will only become the cheapest and most rapid
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
^» S everyone knows, there are two
living species of camels: the larger,
one-humped dromedary of North Africa
and Arabia; and the two-humped, hairier
Bactrian camel of central Asia. These
are geographically widely separated from
their nearest relatives, the llamas of
South America. Many kinds of fossil
animals of the camel type, however, are
known from Europe and North America,
showing that at one time they were a
common and widely distributed group of
grazing animals. Our present camels
and llamas, then, are relics surviving
from the geological past. Why they sur¬
vived, or why all of the others became
extinct, is anyone's guess.
ONE can argue as to whether any of
the present-day camels are truly
wild. Or on the contrary, one can main¬
tain that no camels are truly domesticated.
The latter line of reasoning, used by many
people experienced with camels, is that
camels are simply stupid enough to allow
men to use them up to certain limits.
The stories of camel stupidity and obsti¬
nacy are endless enough, and maybe it
was this low I.Q. that led to their extinc¬
tion in all parts of the world where no
one bothered to look after them. There
are, to be sure, herds of two-humped
Bactrian camels wandering over the
plains of central Asia, but these wild
animals look no different from those
raised by men, and the two interbreed
freely. In the case of the African dro¬
medaries, any apparently wild animals are
supposed simply to have wandered off
from some camp or caravan.
Stupid or not, camels have been very
useful to the peoples of the Old World
desert areas, carrying considerable loads
for days across waterless terrain. How
large a load they can carry, and how
many days they can go without water,
depend on who is telling the story and
probably also on the camel and on the
weather conditions. Camel facts are
scarce, which is what led Knut Schmidt-
Nielsen to study their physiology.
Schmidt-Nielsen [a Norwegian scientist,
working with a subvention from Unesco
see "The Camel, Facts and Fables",
Unesco Courier, N° 8-9, 1955] found that
in the cool winter months in North Africa,
grazing camels were not watered at all;
they got all of the water they needed from
the plants they ate. He decided to see
what would happen if a camel were put
on a very dry diet; for this purpose he
tried thoroughly dried dates stuffed with
peanuts. Camels, it developed, do not
take to new food easily, but he finally
got one animal to eat this diet, until the
oasis where he was conducting the
experiment ran out of peanuts. It turned
out that in cool weather a camel could go
for several weeks without drinking even
on this dry food, but it steadily lost
weight. Camels, Schmidt-Nielsen disco¬
vered, could lose up to 25 per cent of
their body weight without apparent ill
effect. When offered water, however,
they would rapidly drink enough to bring
their weight back to normal: one animal
drank twenty-seven gallons of water In
ten minutes.
The water is not stored in any parti¬
cular place not in the hump, which is
pure fat, nor in the stomach, though this
always has digestive Juices. Like the
kangaroo rat, the camel manages by
being very economical in its use of
water. The urine is highly concentrated,
and sweating is greatly reduced. Camels
meet the sweat problem by not trying to
maintain a steady body temperature. On
a warm day, body temperature wil rise
up to 105 degrees F. before sweating
starts; during the cold night body tempe¬
rature drops, so that it may be as low
as 93 degrees F. at dawn, which gives
the animal a head start in meeting the
heat problems of the day. Body tempe¬
rature fluctuations, however, are much
smaller in the case of animals with free
access to water. The camel's hairy coat
also serves as insulation against the
heat of the day, an animal that was
shaved produced 60 per cent more sweat
to control body temperature than animals
with normal protective hair covering.
DONKEYS are also fairly successful
animals In dry country, and Schmidt-
Nielsen decided to compare them with
camels. He found that under similar
conditions, a camel could go for seven¬
teen days without drinking, a donkey for
only four days. The donkey maintained
a much more constant body temperature
and had to use sweat for this. Both
could lose up to 25 per cent of the body
weight, but the donkey could get it back
much faster by drinking in two minutes
instead of the camel's ten. It would
take a man several hours to drink an
amount of water equivalent to a quarter
of his body weight. Marston Bates
if an extensive network of observation stations is set up,
well equipped with automatic apparatus. The forth¬
coming International Hydrological Decade should help
solve this problem.
There is a saying "Great oaks from little acorns grow".
Care of water is one of the little things that can prevent
a great disaster; in the arid areas the upper level of
underground water ls often polluted through the wells,
and if the flow of water from artesian wells is not regu¬
lated by stopcocks much of the water is wasted.
In terms of waste, the chief water user, irrigation, is
also the chief water waster. In many countries a huge
amount of water from main canals and Irrigation systems
is used unproductively; more ls wasted in the fields and
reservoirs. The greater part of this lost water flows to
the underground waters and raises their level, producing
secondary mineralization and bogs. Thus, not only is
fresh water lost; it reappears as an enemy. The uni¬
versal introduction of scientific principles and technical
improvements into irrigation are an essential condition
for the conservation of surface and underground waters
in those areas where water is scarce.
Man need have no fear of a water shortage. All that
ls needed to ensure practically unlimited supplies of water
is a wise and rational approach to the problem and to
the use of all types of water resources. The long-term
prospects for water seem promising. They undoubt¬
edly will be if we are able to use most of the water
circulating in the land part of the globe and to reduce
the amount of fresh water flowing into the ocean. The
evaporation from the surface of the ocean will not be
noticeably reduced and the total rainfall on the land
surface will remain at approximately its present level.
Fresh-water resources will thus be considerably increased.
Vladimir N. Kunin, a leading Soviet specialist in hydro-
logical problems of the arid zones, is a member of the
Unesco Advisory Committee on Arid Zone Research.
Since 1937 he has worked at the Geographical Institute
of the U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences in Moscow, and
has contributed many papers to the Academy's publica¬
tions. He has made intensive research into water
resource problems of the central Asian deserts.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
With rivers and lakes perma¬
nently used as sewers, water
pollution is a growing cancer
of industrial society. Once
limpid streams are now foul-
smelling and filled with scum
and filth. Water pollution se¬
riously threatens publichealth.
has annihilated whole popula¬
tion of fish and other water
creatures and has ruined
countless holiday resorts for
swimming and aquatic sports.
In Finland thousands of lakes
are totally polluted. Lake Ge¬
neva is "off limits" to bathers
in many places etc. Drinking
water though "purified" che¬
mically is often disagreeable
in flavour as this Paris "water
taster's" grimace testifies.
Photos < Paul Almasy. Paris
CAN WE STOP THE CANCER
OF RIVER POLLUTION?
by René Colas
NE of the unwelcome features of modern civilization is the mass of
waste and refuse it seems to produce. Refuse from all kinds of
human activity industry, agriculture, recreational pursuits even has actually
become a kind of yardstick with which to measure the degree of civilization reached
by any community or country.
The problem of refuse disposal, of course, is one that has faced man throughout
history. But in the past the solutions adopted were usually much simpler than those
demanded by modern sanitary rules and regulations. In medieval times, for
instance, refuse was often simply dumped into the street where it helped to touch
off many a devastating epidemic.
Confined within their defensive ramparts, the cities of the middle ages had often
no alternative but to live literally on top of a garbage heap. The surprisingly high
level of some Paris streets above their surroundings is simply due to the amount
of rubbish and refuse left there in days that are perhaps not so distant as one
would imagine.
The problem was not the same in the countryside where by a natural transfor¬
mation process refuse was eventually returned to the soil as it still is and became
a valuable fertilizing agent. Today too this process is the very basis of good soil
preservation in some countries.
But the unpleasant image of piles of refuse being left to rot in the streets of
medieval towns tends to obscure the fact that even in ancient times some cities had a
sewage system whose design and construction had much in common with our
modem installations. And even in those times some refuse found its way into the
rivers, though only in quantities which the self-purifying qualities of these water¬
ways were able to handle, thus rapidly restoring the natural biological balance.
In early 13th century Paris, during the reign of Philip-Augustus, the waters of
CONT'D ON PAGE 25
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Sorvice de la Navigation
do la Seine - Chevallier
Detergents have become one of the chief agents of water pollution. At locks and weirs where water is troubled, the
detergents are whipped up into masses of foaming suds like those above, near the locks on the River Seine at Mericourt,
between Rouen and Paris. Below, waters of the Rhine polluted with oil wastes. Even one thirtieth of an ounce of
oil products can make 200 gallons of water sufficiently poisonous to kill aquatic life and also unfit for domestic uses.
A NEW CULPRIT : DETERGENT SOAPS
^a^
24
Studies have shown that the worst
agents of pollution are the world's
big cities with their huge output of
sewage water. The greatest offenders
are of course those capital cities
which have been built on the banks
of rivers.
In recent years the use of detergents
in the home and in factories has in¬
creased tremendously, and the results
can be seen in rivers and lakes in
which the presence of detergent pro¬
ducts is revealed by masses of foam.
This is formed when even a minute
quantity of detergent is present in the
water.
The products which make dishwash¬
ing and the laundry so easy are
poisonous for aquatic animal and
plant life. Water plants turn brown
and lose their leaves when water is
invaded by even a microscopic
amount of detergent. Slightly higher
concentrations kill off the tiny water
animais which form the foodstocks for
many fishes, and even tiny fish them¬
selves.
Detergent manufacturers are trying
to reduce the amount of foam produced
which inconveniences industry just as
much as the housewife with her wash¬
ing machine.
But sanitary engineers are worried
by the appearance on the market of
detergents which produce little or no
foam. Though the evidence of pollution
will be reduced, the toxic effect of the
detergents will in no way be lowered.
The water in lakes and rivers is
only renewed very gradually by the
cycle of nature and this is an im¬
portant reason for stepping up the
battle against pollution.
The waters of Lake Constance, on
the frontiers of Germany, Switzerland
and Austria, are renewed every four
and a half years. But as water does
not flow into the Rhine from every
part of the lake the complete renewal
of the waters may take even longer.
Water pollution costs the United
States over one thousand million
dollars every year. An effective
campaign against water pollution
might cost as much as 600 million
dollars, but this would still leave an
overall saving of 400 million dollars.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
RIVER POLLUTION (Cont'd)
Waters that die a slow death
the Seine were crystal clear and from the bridges a passer-by could see the fish
swimming between the stones and the green plants carpeting the river bed.
In London, at the turn of the 17th century it is reported that between sessions of
Parliament, one of the pastimes of the honorable members was to fish for salmon In tho
Thames.
Gradually, the waste disposal networks expanded, and at the same time as towns organized
the collection of domestic garbage they also arranged for the systematic discharge of
waste and cess waters into rivers.
The spread of the "sewage system", combined with the progressive use of sanitary equip¬
ment lavatories, bathrooms, washing machines, etc. has consequently sent all waste
waters into the rivers where, thanks to the introduction of refuse-grinding devices In tho
home, they may soon be joined by much of our domestic garbage.
Any increase in urban population causes a corresponding rise In Industrial production.
And, as industry develops and production processes grow more complex, water consumption
increases at an even faster rate than population growth itself.
While, in the developing countries, the total annual consumption of water per head is
between 200 and 260 cubic yards, nations with Industrialized economies are already using
between 650 and 800 cubic yards of water for all purposes and today the annual per
capita consumption in the United States is nearly 2,000 cubic yards a figure which is
expected to rise to over 2,600 cubic yards within the next 40 years.
Much, if not all, of this water is discharged with all kinds of polluting elements In it: viruses,
microbes, organic matter, floating particles.
Once the mass of pollution discharged into a river exceeds a certain amount the river Is
no longer able to destroy it. All animal and vegetable life disappears. The river Is trans¬
formed into an open sewer: it dies.
WHO- Jean Mohr
HIS has been the case just outside Paris where, in certain years, the Seino
has flowed downstream as a mixture of half water, half sewage.
So, when we add up all the possible sources of pollution industrial waste In the form
of chemical products, toxic elements, particles that give water an unpleasant taste, oil
discharged by shipping and the increasing quantity of detergents it is easy to understand
how river water becomes unsafe, not only for drinking but even for Industrial use. This
situation has coincided with an increase in demands for good quality water, and when towns,
finding underground water sources insufficient to meet these demands, have been compelled
to turn to rivers for their drinking water.
The case of Paris is typical of many large cities. During the 19th century, spring water was
brought into the capital via aqueducts which, for the time, were models of hydrological
design and engineering. Until the early part of the 20th century, Paris managed with the
water that came through these ducts from 60 and even 120 miles away. But the day came
when Paris was obliged to introduce into its supply network water from the Seine, which
up to then had been used only by industry. Full precautions were taken by slow filtering
and then sterilizing. This was originally intended to be merely a reserve supply for the
summer, a time when water sources diminished while consumption increased. But the needs
of the capital quickly grew ; buildings were modernized, new urban areas were being
developed and the suburban population was increasing all the time.
Since there was no room to extend the filters or build new ones, the only way to treat the
increased supply was by introducing stronger purification techniques: chlorination and ozoni¬
zaron. The quantity of water from the Seine and the Marne supplied to Parisian homes thus
gradually increased, while that of spring water remained virtually the same.
A few years ago the low-water period of the Seine coincided with a marked drop in the
spring supply. This created a critical situation and almost caused a breakdown in the Paris
water supply. In the suburbs water was distributed by water tankers and in some places
was sold in large bottles and even by the litre.
On one occasion Parisians complained bitterly about the Seine water they were drinking
because of traces of chlorophenol which were produced by the combined effect of chlorine
used for purification and phenol discharged into the river by a factory. This problem was
overcome by using chlorine dioxide and by stopping the factory from discharging any more
phenol into the Seine.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
RIVER POLLUTION (Cont'd)
Six million tons of filth
On another occasion an abundance of microscopic water plants in a tributary of the Marne
again affected the taste of the water and also seriously hindered the fuctionihg of the filters.
Though in every case purification measures were taken, the people of Paris lost confi¬
dence in their water supply and the sales of mineral water and bottled table waters soared.
At the recent Congress on Hygiene held at the Pasteur Institute in Paris the quality of the
city's drinking water was again strongly criticized and plans were put forward for the
construction of a new supply network to provide drinking water of exceptionally high quality.
This would meet a daily need of five or six litres per person euid would provide for other
purposes water free from harmful bacteria but possibly unpleasant to drink.
Quite understandably, these proposals were considered Utopian by the specialists at the
Congress, who finally voted for a system that would provide a single quality of water
the best. Such examples illustrate the water supply difficulties which all towns are up against
today.
.OMETIMES situations become so critical that towns have to consider regene¬
rating part of their used water so that it can be reintroduced into the supply
network after being treated or purified naturally.
This recycling is already practised in some industries whose water supply is inadequate
and in some cases such water is recycled nearly 100%. In industry as in public utilities,
however, this technique is limited by the increase in the amount of dissolved salts. Care
must be taken to ensure that the limits laid down in nearly every country regarding the salt
content of drinking water are not overstepped, and that strict standards of water cleanliness
are maintained.
It is here that new methods currently being studied and applied for removing salt from
sea water and brackish water so as to help supply arid regions can be used. The use of integral
regeneration processes contemplated for space travel is also being studied.
We know that some underground water sources have still to be prospected and a better
distribution of water resources, with dams and intercommunicating channels between river
basins, would satisfy growing needs for some time to come.
Few people realize, for instance, that water flowing in all French rivers totals over
220,000 million cubic yards a year, of which only between 26,000 and 32,000 million cubic
yards are actually used by man? From the Loire basin alone about 13,000 million cubic
yards flow unused to the sea each year.
But obviously the battle against pollution is still a vital and urgent task. Some countries
have already realized this and have introduced regulations and taken firm action to combat the
disastrous effects of pollution.
j i i.V fJ
Comet, Zurich
HERE are, for instance, institutions in the Federal Republic of Germany which
control the water administration in the Ruhr : "Emscher Genossenschaft,"
"Ruhrverband", etc. The work of the English "River Boards" has quite recently been taken
over by the newly-formed "Water Authorities." In Belgium, the U.S.S.R. and the U.S.A. rivers
have been surveyed and classed according to their state of pollution and in France a bill has
been presented to Parliament, which provides not only for the classification of surface waters
according to their degree of pollution but also for the setting up of public boards, which, in the
worst zones, will help solve the overall problems of water supply and assist in combating
pollution.
In the meantime the French Water Commission (founded in 1959) which actually drew up
the Parliamentary bill, has established administrative machinery which will help all regions in
France to carry out the enormous task of meeting the demands of a rapidly growing population
and industry.
More than 20 million French town dwellers and many people in rural areas discard their
waste directly into rivers without any purification process. The annual flow of French rivers
carries with it 7,000 million cubic yards of filthy water containing polluted matter which would
fill 10,000 trains carrying 600 tons each.
To this must be added the drainage from farm lands which have been treated with chemical
26 fertilizers and insecticides, the hydrocarbons from boats and oil tankers which add to river
pollution, the detergents, the rise in river temperatures caused by the discharge of cooling
water from factories, and the growth of minute aquatic plants due to an increase of "nutritive
DEADLY
About five million
children die each year
from intestinal diseases
caused by water, re¬
ports the World Health
Organization. In some
developing countries as
many as 90 % of the
population either have
an inadequate piped
water service or are
being supplied with
water that is unsafe.
Many people still have
to rely" on drinking
water taken from wells.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
/
f s
/
S / /
.--«?
VA -
lé AîÇ*"-1^*-
At a time when ever greater use is being made of rivers and lakes for sailing, bathing, water ski-ing (above) and other aquatic
sports, our waterways are also becoming increasingly polluted with the waste products of densely populated and industrialized
areas. It. is neither pleasant nor beneficial to go sailing or swimming in polluted water or to walk on river banks that are
clogged with dirt and silt. And there are growing complaints from anglers in many places that their sport is being ruined.
WATER
rivers and other sour¬
ces open to contamina¬
tion with disease-trans¬
mitting organisms. For
some people water is
so dear that they can¬
not buy the minimum
amount needed for ade¬
quate living. In the
world's less developed
areas water-borne
diseases such as chol¬
era, typhoid and dys¬
enteries are the lead¬
ing causes of death
and many sicknesses.
salts" of phosphorus and nitrogen found in the water. The final picture of pollution is
one which, at some periods and in some areas, has well nigh reached saturation point.
Similar situations are found in other countries, even where regulations have been introduced
and public works carried out. Despite such measures these countries are losing the battle
against pollution because the costs are more than they can afford.
To "clean up" river water in France and comply with current regulations would cost
between £576 million and £1,152 million. And to maintain a satisfactory quality of water the
annuel cost of water purification and protection would probably be between £14 million and
£28 million that is, between 0.15% and 0.3% of the French national revenue.
In most countries the price paid for water by the consumer is much lower than its real
value. The revenue from water charges often fails to cover the cost of supply, let alone to
finance research into new resources or to promote purification of used water.
The time has now come to apply moderate increases to water supply rates and taxes and
thereby maintain the quality of what is, after all, a precious element of wealth and prosperity.
Perhaps too the moment has come to affirm that water is an asset belonging to all men
which no individual has any longer the right to use as he pleases, and that it must be protected
as the most vital of our natural bounties.
René Colas is director of the French Institute of Industrial Sanitation and Hygiene Techno
logy, and is chairman of the French Water Information Centre.
"Eaux et Industries" (Water and Industry).
He is editor of the review
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
FRESH WATER FROM THE SEA is produced in this giant distillation plant
the world's largestat Kuwait, on the Persian Gulf. Kuwait once used to
import fresh water by tanker, but in the past 15 years a series of sea-water
distillation plants have been built to meet the needs of Kuwait's ever-expanding
petroleum industry. ,which provides fuel for these plantsnatural gas and oil.
Photos© Paul Almasy. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
WHERE WE STAND WITH
WATER DESALTING
by Ronald S. Fenton
Water, water everywhere, nor any drop to
drink." The words of the Ancient Mariner
in Coleridge's famous poem evoke the feelings of many
a shipwrecked seafarer, adrift In the immensity of the
ocean, but unable to slake his thirst.
Covering three-quarters of the surface of the globe,
the oceans contain practically all the world's water
supply, but in a form so heavily impregnated with all the
minerals that have been washed out of the land that it
would be fatal to drink it in anything like the quantities
normally required by the human body. Human beings
only survive because a very small fraction of ocean water
daily changes its form by natural processes and moves
to places where men, animals and plants can use it.
If only ocean water could cheaply be separated from
its salts and brought to places where fresh water ls
desperately needed, some of man's most pressing prob¬
lems would be solved. Arid lands would be relieved
from the fear of drought and in economically-developed
lands the threat of water shortages due to population and
industrial growth would be a thing of the past.
Conversion of sea or brackish water to fresh is not a
new idea. For many centuries man has known how to
do It; just boll the sea water and condense the resulting
vapour. The basic method is as old as history. Starting
with the Ancient Greeks, sailors have been distilling sea-
water in this way for over 2,000 years. Even primitive
man desalted water, but in this case by evaporating the
water to obtain the salt.
Wider application of distillation came with the advent
of the steamship and its requirement of fresh water for
boilers. Since then shipping owners have found that
distilling sea-water is generally much cheaper than
setting aside cargo or passenger space to store it; the
différence In costs can amount to 545,000 a year for a
medium-sized tanker.
Iesalting ocean water is thus no longer a
problem on board ships and is now common
practice. Its real significance today is for the relief of
water shortages on land. That is why scientists and
engineers are searching for more efficient and economical
ways of converting water from the world's greatest,
cheapest natural resource the oceans and from vast
reserves of inland brackish water, into water fit for use
in the home and by industry.
The technique of desalting is already well advanced.
Widely-scattered land based plants now in operation have
a total estimated daily production capacity of about
40 million gallons. But this is still only a "drop in the
ocean" it is no more than would satisfy the water needs
of an American industrial city of 350,000 people.
The reason is that only special economic and geogra¬
phical situations have so far justified the setting up of
large desalting plants. One example is Kuwait, on the
Persian Gulf, where vast petroleum resources began to be
developed on a giant scale about 15 years ago. At that
time water had to be imported by tanker at exorbitant
cost. Since then a series of large-scale water distilleries
has been built, fueled by natural gas and oil. Today
these plants produce well over 10 million gallons a day.
Yet although the fuel ls virtually free, the water is not
cheap compared with the cost of supplying water in
many other parts of the world. But for Kuwait desalting
water was cheaper than importing It.
Normally, the costs of providing water In areas lucky
enough to be endowed with a good, natural supplyare
much lower than for any other commodity on earth.
Thus, water supplied by desalting processes will only
become competitive with water from conventional sources
when technological Improvements have increased the
efficiency of these processes and brought down the basic
costs of production.
he stumbling block in the use of distillation
to make the oceans supply the water needs
of industry is the cost of providing the large amounts
of energy needed for the conversion processes.
There are already encouraging signs, however, that the
gap between the cost of water produced by desalting and
water from conventional sources is closing up. Since
1951 intensive research and development in the United
States have brought down desalting production costs,
even In pilot demonstration plants, from #5.00 per 1,000
gallons to between $1.40 and $1.00, as compared with an
average cost of $0.40 for municipal water delivered to the
public. At the same time conventional water costs have
been climbing slowly, thus further closing the gap. Some
specialists maintain that within the next decade or so
further technological improvements may reduce the cost
of desalted water to between $0.40 and $0.60 per 1,000
gallons.
The Important programme of research and develop¬
ment in the United States which produced these lower
cost conversion results was initiated In 1952 by the
Office of Saline Water. This U.S. agency was establish¬
ed by the Department of the Interior to "develop new
or Improved conversion processes . . . conduct research
and technical development ... to make engineering
studies to ascertain the lowest investment and operat¬
ing costs and to determine the best plant designs and
conditions of operations."
Since then It has been attacking these problems with
the help of demonstration plants erected in Freeport,
Texas and San Diego, California (both with a dally pro¬
duction capacity of one million gallons) and at Webster,
South Dakota. Other demonstration plants are being
built in North Carolina and New Mexico. All five employ
different techniques for desalting water. The U.S. saline
water conversion programme ls certainly the most exten¬
sive In operation today.
Another achievement in the campaign to reduce produc¬
tion costs comes from the island of Aruba In the Carib¬
bean. Here, a large distilling plant has been combined
with a thermal power station. Steam passes through
the turbines to generate electricity and ls then used
to heat the sea water. About half the water produced
on Aruba is used by an oil refinery, and the remainder
is the sole source of supply for some 54,000 people on
this completely waterless Island.
Another place where it has been found worthwhile to
set up a sea-water distillation plant ls Guernsey, an
island in the English Channel. Ordinarily Guernsey gets
enough rain to produce a bumper crop of tomatoes on
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
WATER DESALTING (Cont'd)
Squeezing molecules through plastic pores
which Its economy largely depends. But about once In
every eight years a drought occurs at a critical time and
the tomato crop fails. When the islanders found that
for the price of crop insurance premiums they could have
a desalting plant, they built one with a capacity of
500,000 gallons a day. Though it will not be used very
often, It represents an investment in a cheap form of
crop insurance.
Until recent times seagoing distillation plants were
simple contraptions in which salt water was boiled in a
kettle atop which was attached a coiled metal tube that
trapped the steam and condensed It to a trickle of fresh
water. Modern water stills are vastly more complex
and more efficient. Most of the heat applied to water at
one stage ls recaptured and transferred to the next stage
to vaporize more water.
But the chief problem ls still the high cost of power.
Can atomic energy offer a solution? Some scientists
now maintain that with further research it will be
possible to combine the production of electricity and the
conversion of ocean water in giant atomic power plants
and thereby produce both electric power and fresh water
at costs well below today's figures.
These scientists have calculated that water can be pro¬
duced for about $0.25 per 1,000 gallons In plants delivering
1,000 million gallons of fresh water daily. They main¬
tain that even this low cost could be further reduced
through the use of breeder reactors which differ from
present conventional atomic reactors in that they
literally breed or create additional fuel supplies as a by¬
product.
Distillation, of course, is only one of many methods
now known for desalting water and, in terms of present
knowledge and experience, it is so far the most efficient
and widely-used process. Distillation plants produce
very pure water: less than ten parts of salts for one
million parts of water. It makes little difference In cost
whether the process starts with sea-water (35,000 parts
per million) or brackish water (1,000 to 10,000 parts per
million).
The costs of an entirely different type of desalting
process known as electrodlalysls, however, vary with the
salt content of water. In electrodlalysls the energy
consumed ls proportional to the amount of salts remov¬
ed. Thus, where the need ls to make brackish water fit
for human needs it has a basic advantage over distilla¬
tion. Little energy is needed to purify brackish water
(typically about 2,000 parts of salts per million) to a level
that meets public health standards for drinking water
(500 parts per million in the U.S.A.).-
Electrodlalysls depends on plastic membranes that act
somewhat like chemical sieves. This is how they work
in the case of the common salt found in sea-water. Each
molecule of salt is composed of one atom of sodium and
one of chloride. When salt is dissolved in water it splits
into two particles called ions one a negatively charged
atom of chloride and the other a positively charged
atom of sodium. In electrodlalysls the electric current
causes the two kinds of ions to flow in opposite direc¬
tions through banks of plastic membranes forming a
series of compartments. The process leaves less salty,
though not entirely purified, water in one compartment
and more salty in the next, and so on down the entire
bank of membranes.
The amount of salts retained in the water can be
adjusted as required to the level needed in drinking
water, for instance. (Water produced by distillation is
unpalatable because nearly all the salts have been re¬
moved.) Many commercial plants use electrodlalysls and
countries which have set up such plants include Israel,
Japan, the Netherlands, the Soviet Union and South
Africa.
iNother promising method on which research
lis now being pursued is the desalting of sea-
water by freezing. The first ice that forms when sea-
water freezes contains practically no salt and can be
melted down Into fresh water. Freezing has two big
advantages over distillation: less energy is required to
freeze water than to vaporize it; there is no formation
of mineral deposits on equipment as is the case when high
temperatures are used. Offsetting these advantages are
the need for expensive mechanical equipment to handle
Ice by the carload and the difficulty of eliminating the
salt water and brine which tend to cling to the crystals
of frozen fresh water. A good deal of the fresh water
produced has to be used for washing the crystals. But
the stage has now been reached where demonstration
plants have been built and are operating on an experi¬
mental basis.
Among all the methods of desalting the simplest is
distillation by the heat of the sun. Its chief attraction
is' that it makes use of energy supplied absolutely free
of charge. The apparatus used is simple and relatively
inexpensive to build. The typical solar still consists of
a trough of salt water beneath a slanting roof of glass
or clear plastic. The water slowly evaporates, condenses
30
'HARD' WATER IN
THE FAR NORTH
In the Far North Eskimo wives keep their
stocks of drinking water as blocks of
solid ice piled up in the open air (left).
When only sea water is available this
can be frozen to remove the salt a
method employed in the Arctic seaboard
areas of several regions. Shallow basins
are filled with six inches of sea-
water and when the salty water has
frozen to a depth of just over half an
inch, the ice is collected and the brine
beneath poured away (the first ice that
forms when sea-water freezes contains
practically no salt). Plants which desalt
sea-water by freezing are now being
used experimentally in several countries.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
BONNEVILLE SALT
FLATS in the United
States stretch for miles
acrossthe northwest cor¬
ner of the state of Utah.
Today, an unbroken
line of telegraph poles
marches to the horizon
and roaring motor cars
set world speed records
on this natural race
course. Bonneville Salt
Flats and the surround¬
ing Great Salt Lake
desert are the former
bottom and shores of a
vast fresh-water lake
that covered over 20,000
square miles in this
area between 10,000
and 15,000 years ago.
The part of it that
is left today is called The
Great Salt Lake. Under¬
ground water, seeping
up from below the for¬
mer lake bottom, and
rain waters, continuous¬
ly dissolving salts from
rocks, have left evapo¬
rated sal:ne deposits
estimated at more than
one thousand million
tons. Recovering this salt
is now a major industry.
Photo Fritz Goro. from Life
Magazine© 1963 Time Inc.
on the under side of the roof, and trickles down into a
gutter. Solar distillation plants are naturally of the
greatest value to areas that are not only rich in sunshine
and poor in other fuels, but also where land space is not
at a premium. They take up a lot of space if used for
large-scale desalting and U.S. engineers have estimated
that an Installation covering 40 acres would be needed
to irrigate 120 acres of farm land.
While electrodlalysls and distillation have already
proved their worth and freezing shows progressively en¬
couraging results, scientists and engineers are investigat¬
ing at least a dozen other desalting processes. One new
line of research concerns the use of plastic membranes
of a somewhat different type from those used in electro¬
dlalysls. In this process the membranes simply strain
salt ions from sea-water. The pressure of a powerful
pump squeezes the water molecules through the mem¬
brane pores, leaving the salt behind.
Those working on desalting research do not anticipate
anything approaching an Immediate major advance that
would revolutionize development in their field. They are
up against the hard fact that taking salt out of water
has much in common with oll-refinlng: both Involve
chemical separations that demand much energy and
expensive equipment.
Nevertheless, present research promises to lead to
significant economies that will expand the potential use
of desalted water. Development of cheaper or long-
lasting membranes would cut the cost of electrodlalysls.
New methods for controlling boiler scale the hard
coating of mineral deposits that tends to be deposited on
hot metal surfaces by sea or brackish water would lead
to increased efficiency In all distillation processes.
Engineers are also trying to gain more efficiency by In¬
genious combinations of different processes.
Each new Installation results in some improvement and
paves the way for more efficient operation. The expe¬
riences with new and larger plants coupled with continu¬
ed research efforts should hasten the day when more
of the world's people with no reasonable source of Iresh
water may have access to the benefits of high-quality
water produced by desalting plants.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL
CONCORD by Gilbert F. White
uINTiL fifty years ago man tended to manage
streams, great and small, for a single purpose
affecting only a small area. True, a few ancient river
structures in China and Iran served the joint purposes
of mechanical water power and irrigation or of flood
control and navigation, but by and large construction
was for a single purpose.
Shortly after the turn of the century the idea of inter-
grated development of streams found currency in plans
for individual water basins. The technology of moving
earth cheaply in great quantities, of building with
concrete, and of transmitting electricity long distances
made this possible.
One aspect of the Idea was to manage water for several
purposes at the same place. The thirteen new dams on
the Volga River, for example, serve not only to store water
for navigation and for urban water supply, but generate
huge blocks of hydro-electric power. The great new
dam rising on the Lower Volta River In Ghana will not
only provide for navigation facilities downstream but will
generate power on which an alumium industry will be
based.
A second aspect of this idea is that river basins in¬
creasingly have been treated as units. Instead of design¬
ing projects for solely one reach of a stream, projects
for water control now are seen as fitting into a broader
network throughout the drainage basin. This is the case
with the Damoder Valley and other basin projects in
India, in the Snowy Mountains of Australia, with most of
the newer river schemes in the Soviet Union and the
United States, and with the planning that is going on in
a number of the basins of Latin America under the
sponsorship of the Economic Commission for Latin
America.
Still a third aim that has become prominent in the last
twenty-five years is the vision of using large-scale water
control works to affect basic changes in the life of the
people of the entire region. This was the goal of the
Tennessee Valley Authority in the United States which
used a system of dams to generate power, control floods,
and provide navigation in such fashion that soil and
forest resources would be Improved and the people's
income and employment pattern would be bettered.
CONT'D ON PAGE 36
TEAM WORK
ON THE INDUS
Down the River Indus and its five tri¬
butaries one of the world's greatest ri¬
ver systems pours an annual waterflow
double that of the Nile. Some 40 mil¬
lion people in West Pakistan and ten
million more in India rely on the Indus
to irrigate 30 million acres of farm land.
In September 1960 a long-standing dis¬
pute over the use of the Indus waters
was settled by India and Pakistan which
agreed to share them through a vast
international river development plan. Eight
countries including India and Pakistan,
and the International Bank are helping
to pay the cost of dams, artificial lakes
and an irrigation system. Irrigation will
no longer be at the mercy of seasonal
climatic changes or fluctuations in river-
flow. The project will also increase
hydro-electric resources and give better
flood protection to both India and Pak¬
istan. Right, a mighty dam wall on
the Indus at Gudu, Pakistan. Left model
reservoir for studying sluice gate and
water flow operations.
Photos © Paul Almasy. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
?',.
© UPI - Al Ahiam
NEW
NILE
The first stage in the building of Egypt's
High Dam at Aswan was completed on
May 14 by the opening of a huge diversion
canal. Here, courage and ingenuity combine to
meet problems created by today's population
"explosion". Two centuries ago Egypt's popu¬
lation numbered two and a half millions. To¬
day it is 27 millions and by 1972 will have grown
to 36 millions. For thousands of years the peo¬
ples of the Nile Valley were at the mercy of the
river's whims; starvation or prosperity were
entirely dependent on the vagaries of rainfall
in the highlands of Ethiopia. The building of the
first Aswan dam at the turn of the century and
its enlargement in 1912 and 1933 were really
no more than provisional measures. Now, for
the first time in its history, the Nile is being
completely harnessed for man's use. When
completed the dam will span a distance of over
3,900 yards, and its waters will create the world's
second largest man-made lake (after the Kariba
Dam in Rhodesia) some 30Ó miles in length. The
new dam will make possible a 30 % increase
in agricultural production, the production of
10,000 million kilowatt hours of electricity
per year to give new impulse to industry, and
will ensure complete protection against serious
flooding. The dam is due to be completed
by 1967 and the hydro-electric equipment should
be functioning by 1969. Egypt has undertaken
this huge task with financial aid amounting
to 1,300 million roubles from the Soviet Union
which also supplied equipment and 1,800 en¬
gineers and technicians. Newly-built villages
are now replacing those due to disappear under
the waters of the new dam. Thanks to an inter¬
national campaign launched by Unesco, funds
have been collected for the biggest archacelo-
gical operation of all time including the safe¬
guarding of the temples, at Abu Simbel. The
progress of this campaign and the rescue of
Nubia's monuments have been described in The
Unesco Courier, particularly in two special
issues (Feb. 1960 and Oct. 1961). Another spe¬
cial number devoted to Nubia is being planned.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
DIVERTING
THE WORLD'S
LONGEST RIVER
Photos on left were taken before and after
tho opening of tho diversion canal on tho
Nile, the world's longest river, during con¬
struction of the High Dam at Aswan. Tho
flow of the Nile (from left to right) has been
checked by a mainstream coffer dam (seen
on left). While tho diversion canal was being
dug the waters of tho Nile wero halted by
a sand dam (arrowed in photo far left).
When an explosive charge broko open this
sand dam on May 14, 1964, the torrent of
waters began to flow in a new bed (photo
left). From hero they will pass through six
tunnels in which hydro-electric turbines
will be installed. Tho day tho Nile waters
were sent along their new course.there wero
wildly enthusiastic scenes (below) as
technicians and workers hailed tho end of
the first phase in a gigantic engineering feat.
O Tass - V. Dudan
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL CONCORD (Cont'd)
36
The tricky art
of taming nature
The idea of integrated river development now is
widespread. It ls applied to management of small
mountain valleys as well as to huge basins reaching to
the ocean. It ls carried out with great care in a number
of the streams of the Soviet Union, notably the Volga-
Kama, Don, Dnieper, and Syr-Darya.
The United States has used this concept in plans not
only for the Tennessee but for the whole upper Ohio,
the Missouri, the Colorado, and perhaps most notably
for the Columbia and central Callfornian basins. In
only a few places, such as parts of the arid Colorado
basin in the U.S.A. and the 111 basin in central Asia has
development reached what might be considered maxi¬
mum. In most basins water still flows to the sea unregu¬
lated and the power of its fall remains unharnessed.
Each year, however, sees additional water regulated and
additional stream reaches captured by construction of
dams.
The great Integrated developments have taken place
chiefly on streams which lie wholly within one country
or in a single nation's portion of a stream. Thus, the
developments on the Rhone have been planned solely
within France in the first instance and those on the
Tigris-Euphrates were designed wholly for Iraq. Only
a few international streams have received integrated
treatment although the international streams account
for a large proportion of the drainage areas of the world.
|ome of the mighty rivers of the worldthe
'Nile, the Amazon, the Congo, the Ganges-
Brahmaputra, La Plata, the Amur and othersare dis¬
tinctively international streams.
Until recent years only a few of these had received
unified, co-operative treatment from the countries which
contribute the water and share in the opportunity to
use it. The Danube has been the subject of collaboration
in hydrologie data collection and navigation regulation
for a long time (see photo story p. 38). Agreements for
the maintenance of navigation works and, more recently,
the management of polluting wastes have developed In
the Rhine In Western Europe. International accords
affect much of the water of the Nile.
On the North American continent after many years
of negotiation Canada and the United States have
agreed on related plans for the Columbia basin. On the
southern border, long-standing treaties affecting the
regulation of the Rio Grande and Colorado are operated
by Mexico and the United States, but revisions must be
considered as new conditions arise.
Perhaps the outstanding case of direct investment in
an international stream is on the Indus River where
under the leadership of the International Bank for Recon¬
struction and Development a special programme of river
development has been planned by India and Pakistan
with a condominium of other interested countries (see
page 33).
The most elaborate collaboration In planning of inter¬
national river development before actual construction
has taken place is in the Lower Mekong where four coun¬
tries, Cambodia. Laos, Thailand, and Vietnam have joined
in carrying out basic scientific and engineering studies
(see page 46). In this work they have been joined by
eighteen other countries and several foundations and
international agencies.
It now is possible to find teams of French and Indian
engineers who are designing water management works
in Cambodia using maps based on Canadian air photo¬
graphs, geology from an Australian study, hydroiogic
data from a United States programme, and reconnais¬
sance survey work from Japan. A co-operative inter¬
national study currently is in the organizational stage
for Senegal drainages in West Africa, also with the spon¬
sorship of the United Nations.
Integrated river programmes place special demands on
the Interlocking of scientific, technological, educational,
and cultural activities. A great river basin is an ex¬
tremely complex web of relationships which show them¬
selves not only in the hydroiogic cycle of water but in
the movements of eilt and in the movements of people
and their products.
Governments have learned that when a dam is built it
is more than a single structure which stores water from
the flood season to be used in the dry season. It alters
the regimen of the river downstream and thereby affects
the flow and quality of water and the river channel. It
changes the fish and plant population of the water. It
may have a profound Impact upon the peoples way of
earning a living, and it may disturb roads, market faci¬
lities and the channels of government.
Quite aside from such instances as, for example, above
the high Aswan dam on the Nile, where valuable archseo-
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
BAIKAL
Worlds
deepest
fresh-water
lake
With its volume of 5,300 cubic miles,
of water. Lake Baikal in southern
Siberia is tho greatest fresh-water
lake in tho world. It is also tho deepost
(5,400 feet) and has a length of 390
miles. Tho animals and plants found
at Baikal aro ono of its most remark¬
able features. About 1,200 species
and varieties of animals and about
700 plants have been found there.
Some of tho animals aro quito uniquo.
Baikal is fed by 336 rivers, but only
one flows from the lake the Angara
River. The rain and snow that fall
each year on the lake total 2.2 cubic
miles enough water to fill Lako
Zurich in Switzerland twice over.
© Tass-APN
logical remains are threatened by reservoir construction,
water management brings into play new forces that
may profoundly alter the society which they are intended
to aid. It does not always follow that a huge concrete
dam, however appealing It may be as a symbol of eco¬
nomic development and mastery of Western technology,
will yield net benefits to the area where it is built. The
cost it imposes upon society may exceed the gains which
flow from it.
If agricultural extension, credit and marketing facili¬
ties do not shift to help farmers use the new opportu¬
nities effectively, an irrigation structure may fail to
improve their output. Moreover, it may carry the hazards
of disease. Today more than 100 million people in the
world are suffering from the debilitating disease bilhar-
ziasis whose spread has been largely encouraged by
construction of irrigation projects which were intended
to build up the economy of the very population which is
debilitated by the disease.
It would be preferable before a river management pro¬
ject were undertaken to forecast with a fair degree of
accuracy what its effects would be upon flows of water,
silt, people, and income in a given culture area. Today,
however, only a part of these Impacts can be foreseen.
The best that can be done is to marshal as much special
study and judgment as can be obtained before fateful
decisions are made as to further harnessing of the
earth's waters.
It Is not enough simply to develop engineering designs.
These must be based as far as possible on accurate scien¬
tific knowledge of the phenomena of water and ecological
relationships which will be changed. These effects must
be measured not only in the direct -costs of construction
and operation, but in the broader benefits and costs of
changes in productivity and culture which will result
from them.
But even gains in productivity cannot be assured unless
there ls knowledgeable effort to assure the cultural and
social conditions in which change may take place. Often
this revolves upon education. Thus science, technology,
social science, and education are mutually dependent in
arriving at fruitful management of the earth's rivers.
Gilbert F. White has served as a member of the Unesco
Advisory Committee on Arid Zone Research and is the
author of many works on natural resources including
"Science and the Future of Arid Lands," published by
Unesco in 1961 (republished 1963). He is chairman of the
Department of Geography of the University of Chicago
and has worked on water conservation and development
problems for the Mississippi Valley Committee and other
U.S. water authorities. Professor White is well known to
readers of The Unesco Courier (See "Thirsty LandsPast
and Future," May, 1962).
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
THE DANUBE, EUROPE'S GREAT
In a pleasant little valley
of the Black Forest, a tiny
stream comes tumbling
down the rocks and, gath¬
ering strength from
springs and rivulets, begins
to cross southern Ger¬
many. This little stream,
the Brege, with its twin
sister, the Brigach, is the
source of the Danube the
greatest river in Europe
next to the Volga, and
1,800 miles in length. The
course of the Danube which
passes through eight coun¬
tries the Federal Republic
of Germany, Austria, Hun¬
gary, Czechoslovakia, Yu¬
goslavia, Bulgaria, Rumania
Deutsche Zentrale für Fremdenverkehr, Frankfort
Tho waters of three rivers the Danube, the Inn and
the llzmeet at Passau (Federal Republic of Germany)
an ancient fortified town dating from Roman times.
and the U.S.S.R.has been
determined bytheconforma-
tion of the European land¬
scape. The Alps, the pla¬
teau of Bohemia and the
Transylvanian Alps send it
in a west-east direction,
and. in the broad plains of
Hungary and Rumania it
runs from north to south
and back again. The Dan¬
ube gathers its water from
over 300 tributaries and its
basin covers an area of
500,000 square miles. Na¬
vigable throughout nearly
its whole length, the Da¬
nube has been since ear¬
liest history a great water
highway, a road for cul-
The Danube is navigable along nearly
the whole of its 1,800 course, down
to the Black Sea. Far right, a barge puts
in at one of the many river ports.
The castle of Gmunden (left) is built
on a tiny island in the Traunsee, a lake
in upper Austria, through which runs
the River Traun, a Danube tributary.
Paul Almasy. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
WATERWAY
ture and for trade between
Western Europe and the
Levant. In the first cen¬
tury A.D. it was the north¬
ern frontier of the Roman
Empire and a defence line
which disappeared with the
Germanic invasions. In
1856 a treaty was signed
declaring Danube naviga¬
tion free to all nations.
From Ulm in Germany to
Kilia on the delta near the
Black Sea great city ports
line the river and barges,
towboats and rafts loaded
with products of all kinds
ply their way along this
vital commercial waterway.
© Inge Morath-Magnum
With its banks still rich in architectural treasures from the past, the Danubo
has now become a vital artery of modern technological civilization.
© Leonard Freep
AUSTRIA RESEARCH PLAN The Danube basin offers a rich field for international hydrological
research. Studies now being carried out by Austria, for example, not only aim at the development of
this country's own hydrological resources, but also assist the long-term international programme in hy¬
drology now being prepared by Unesco. Some of the work, described in a recent report from Austria
to Unesco, includes hydrological and thermodynamic studies in mountain areas and other hydrological
studies, in the Danube basin. This research, of benefit to all countries along the river, covers the
improvement of hydrological forecasting, erosion problems, investigations of sediments carried by the
river, and studies of the effects of industrial development on the river system, including pollution problems.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
DROPS IN THE HYDROLOGIST'S BUCKET
WHEN WATER
GROWS OLD
The idea of water "growing old" Is one
that never occurs to most people. In the
popular 6ense water begins to "age" from
the moment It Is collected In a receptacle.
However water Is actually "born" the
moment It condenses from a cloud and falls
to the earth as rain, snow or hail. Water,
In fact, starts to "age" the moment It begins
to run over the surface of the ground and
starts from watercourse to watercourse on
Its way to the sea.
If It starts to Infiltrate Into the ground,
where it will circulate and be stored, Its
chances of "survival" Increase considerably.
Today, the dating of waters that have
been stocked In the water-bearing rocks of
the earth's crust for thousands of years or
perhaps only for a few centuries has
assumed great importance.
When the "water capital" of a given area
Is being exploited it Is Important for water
engineers to know how far this "capital"
has already been drawn upon when catch¬
ment or pumping begins. This means they
must find out the ratio between the volume
of water which each year reaches the water¬
bearing terrain the aquifer and the
volume of water extracted from it. This
gives an Idea of how long the stock will
last.
Nowadays underground water is looked
on less and less as a fully-renewable
natural resource. It tends more and more
to be "mined" like ores, whose eventual
exhaustion can be predicted. This calls
for a change in the outlook of the user,
and so greater efforts are being made to
recharge the aquifer, that Is, to build up
its reserves by injecting water into the
ground so that this can subsequently be
recuperated for man's use.
Research into the dating of water enables
us to follow the effect of these restocking
operations on the evolution of underground
reserves. Use is made of radioisotopes,
such as tritium or carbon 14, to determine
the age of an underground water supply.
Isotope tests have shown that large
underground stocks of water may well have
been deposited (especially In arid lands)
during the rainy periods of the Quaternary
Age when, long before the present desert
climate, forests grew in the Sahara.
FRESH WATER
SPRINGS IN THE SEA
'WATERBORNE' WELL. Fishermen's wives at Ganvié, in Dahomey,
draw drinking water from an artesian well which has been sunk through
© Paul Almasy Paris l^e '3ec' °* a 'a9oon t0 reach a fresh water pocket situated far beneath it.
40
What could be more surprising than to
watch a fishing boat leave the Greek coast
at Corinth, or the Moroccan coast at Agadir,
and make for a predetermined spot In the
open sea to take aboard a supply of fresh
water?
Yet these Greek and Moroccan fishermen
have long been doing this thanks to the
knowledge, handed down from generation
to generation, that at certain points fresh
water springs In the relatively shallow sea¬
bed send water to the surface that Is
practically uncontaminated by salt.
These springs are generally fissured beds
of limestone that drain surface water from
the land and release great quantities of
fresh water through faults or fractures on
the sea-bed. Detailed studies of sub¬
marine springs have recently been made
In Greece with a view to recovering these
wasted water supplies for the benefit of
the nearby land which is in dire need of
them. The presence of the sea-water
from which they emerge, the instability
of the water-mass pressures and, finally,
their relative Inaccessibility, all complicate
the task of recovery.
Geological research of the kind used to
locate oil deposits on the shore or under
the sea has led to the catchment of artesian
pockets of fresh water beneath the sea¬
shore at Istanbul In Turkey and at Recife
in Brazil at depths of between 500 and
650 feet. Here the techniques of the
geologist have joined hands with age-old
experience and knowledge of Greek and
Moroccan fisherman.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
USIS RAINMAKERS. Scientists are seeking ways to control the weather. Such research may reveal ways of
bringing rain to areas which now suffer from drought and of protecting other areas against floods, cyclones,
hailstorms and tornadoes. Above, a cloud of ice fog produced by throwing a can of water into cold air (minus
40 degrees C.) during weather research experiments in Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, U.S.A.
WATER WITH
A CUTTING EDGE
The many uses of water, from its role as
a basic necessity for men, plants and
animals to the part it plays alongside coal
and oil in supplying energy, are well known.
Less well known is the fact that the power
of water may be used In factories and
workshops like a cutting tool, with the
simple difference that it will never get
worn or need sharpening.
In September 1961 the Bulletin of the
Water Information Center in the United
States reported that a big machine-tool
factory at Los Angeles had designed and
built a machine in which a fine stream of
water with a pressure of over 14,000 lbs
per square inch is used to cut cement,
wood and plastic . materials. For cleaning
all kinds of metallic surfaces, this device
works more quickly and efficiently than
any existing abrasive material.
Basically, it Is the old story of the drop
of water which falls on to a stone,
gradually eating a hole In It, though now
adapted through new technological know-
how for use In modern Industry.
CITY BUILT
ON A 'JELLY'
The centre of Mexico City, and in
particular Alameda Square and the Fine
Arts Theatre, is subsiding at the alarming
rate of nearly 12 inches a year.
Mexican engineers blame the continuous
pumping operations that go on near the
city for this subsidence. The explanation
Is as follows:
At the beginning of the Quaternary Age,
the area of Mexico City had been a large
and very deep valley which was closed
abruptly" by a flow of lava from Mount
Popocatepetl, Mexico's largest volcano.
Once sealed off, the valley rapidly
became a lake between 2,000 and 2,600 feet
deep. This In turn was gradually filled with
volcanic ash from subsequent eruptions.
Finally, only a shallow depth of water was
left while deep down the ash instead of
settling formed a glutinous mixture with
the water until the land became rather like
a jelly In consistence.
The present site of Mexico's capital was
still a lake when the Spanish conquistadores
arrived in the country, and when the Aztecs
established their capital there they were
thinking of its natural defensive advantages.
But the "ground" here Is actually composed
of"15% of solid matter suspended in 85%
water.
Pumping operations In this waterlogged
earth creates a vacuum under more recent
surface alluvia and gradually the under¬
ground structure is being destroyed. That
explains why the stage and reception
rooms of Mexico City's Opera house and
neighbouring buildings sink lower and
lower each year.
The city's centre Is now about 35 feet
below its original level, and is thus even
lower than the surface of Texcoca Lake all ^
CONT'D ON PAGE 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
%xf:wa
I *
w./ ad0
-1p-^-
1 -*liil r .-~*pr#^ *7 t eau
r.jr
. '
\
pr ../?#rj "«
m « BT 1
-
\
J f -
»
42
MAY THE
RAINS COME
Eloquent hands speak the thoughts of an Indian farmer as he waits for the summer monsoon to bring the
longed-for rains. Drawn inward by low pressure over the heated interior of Asia, the summer monsoon carries
moisture from the Indian Ocean and brings downpours to countries of south-eastern Asia. All rural life in
these regions is regulated by the monsoons. When the rains fail or are late, drought brings severe famine.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
UMBRELLA TIME
IN BOMBAY
A signboard in Bombay, India, announces
the approach of the monsoon. Now the
stifling May days are counted until down¬
pours bring relief to land and people alike.
\
s of v
Photos © Magnum - Brian Braka
CITYBUILTON (Cont'd from page 41)
that now remains of the once vast lake on
which the Aztec rulers built their capital.
This situation, coupled with one of a
more geographical kind, namely that tho
town Is situated in an enclosed Inland
basin, has created a serious problem of
waste-water disposal for the municipal
authorities. Since the basin is completely
closed, the water can neither be returned
into the ground nor evacuated into a canal
or river. Furthermore the roads leaving
Mexico City situated at an altitude of
7,870 feet climb up to 9,190 feet and to
even higher levels before they are free to
turn down the Atlantic slopes on one side
or the Pacific slopes on the other.
Thus the only possible way to dispose of
sewage water Is to pump It out of tho
enclosed basin and into the Atlantic basin.
How Important this pumping has become
can be gauged from the fact that over four
million people live In tho area.
The public health services and tho
government Itself keep constant watch on
the multitude of pumps used for this
operation for a general breakdown would
allow Invading sewage waters to flood the
city to first floor level within 24 hours.
DEW MOUNDS AND
'LILY RESERVOIRS'
The ancient peoples living In desert areas
built "dew mounds" of large flint pebbles
around each fruit tree and vine to attract
the dew and convey it quickly to the roots
of the plants.
Today, people still find ways of collecting
dew which condenses naturally in some
local areas. An Ingenious method of dew
collection has been devised by a farmer on
the Island of Brava In the Cape Verde
archipelago. There Is little rainfall In tho
Cape Verde Islands and It never rains
during the long dry season. But the land
is generally shrouded by heavy mists or
fogs and this produces much natural
condensation on to the leaves of plants and
directly on to the soil. This moisture is
often sufficient to carry crops through the
dry season. But drinking water is in short
supply and the farmer In question had to
transport water for some distance.
However, he noticed that dew was
condensing so heavily on the leaves of a
giant lily that it dripped on to the soil. So
he tied the leaves In such a way that the
dew dripped from leaf to leaf and down to
the ground. He then planted 60 of these
lilies in a row down a slope and made a
gutter from the highest to the lowest by
placing the large boat-shaped leaves of
other lily-plants on the ground. At the end
of the gutter he constructed a small
reservoir, from which he has since collected
an average of 200 litres of fresh water
daily. When the fog Is dense his row of
plants collects 600 litres in a day.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
PEOPLES OF THE DELTAS
A see-saw battle
between river and sea
by Adriaan Volker f
44
he delta of a river ls the last gift to man of
the watercourse on Its way to the sea The
classic example, of course, ls Lower Egypt, but the des¬
cription also applies to many other delta areas which
range among the most productive and most densely
populated parts of the world.
In the delta the river drops the sediments, silt and
sandthe products of erosionthat It has been carrying
all along its course from the mountains to the sea or to
the lake Into which it flows. The slope that provides
the driving force for the flow of the water and the sedi¬
ments flattens out when approaching the coastal area,
the river's velocity decreases and to carry the flow from
upstream still further. It must split up into a number
of branches or distributaries.
At the point where this happens, the apex, the deltaic
and final reach of the river begins. In this reach the
velocity decreases still further and the flow ls finally
backed up by the sea water. Unable to carry the sedi¬
ments any further, the river starts building up land.
Thus, as the land area expands at the expense of the
sea's domain some of the soil lost by erosion is recovered
and restored to man.
But the sea fights back. Tidal currents and storm
surges remove some of the sediments deposited in the
delta and carry them to great depths.
A continuous struggle goes on in a delta between the
river and the sea, and when Man Intervenes to utilize
the land, he too must face the destructive power of the
tidal waters.
Not all rivers build up deltas on reaching the sea.
When the forces of the sea prevail because of strong
tides, great depths and the impact of the waves, or
when the delta area is rapidly subsiding, a single
estuary ls formed over which the sea is master.
Although favourable conditions for delta formation are
found in shallow lakes without tides and waves, the
largest deltas have been formed along the coast of
oceans, seas and inland seas for It is here that the
largest rivers emerge.
When a river reaches its delta the scenery changes,
the horizon widens, land and water mingle, the river
becomes less turbulent and near, the sea it ls dominated
by the slow breathing rhythm of the tides. The Greek
astronomer and geographer, Pytheas, who visited nor¬
thern Europe in the 4th century B.C., described the
delta of the River Rhine as the "Sea-Lung," which he
said was "somewhere in the north where ice, water and
air minglewithout doubt the end of the earth." And
(as a man from the Mediterranean), he was struck by
the much greater rise and fall of the North Sea tides.
Even the atmosphere changes In the delta; the light
which is filtered and reflected from all sides becomes
more diffuse. The special qualities of light found In
deltas Inspired and Influenced the Dutch school of
painters.
/
Monsoon floods in¬
vade a Cambodian
village whose houses
are raised on stilts.
The floods, which
irrigate the rice fields,
are welcomed, for the
people have learned
to adapt their lives
to flood conditions.
Farmers become
fishermen and every¬
one travels by boat.
© Rapho
Claude Ghioneaud.
-
&
Delta areas are blessed with many natural advanta¬
ges which encourage man to make use of them. All the
water from the river basin reaches the delta situated
at its lowest point, and water is therefore relatively
abundant. The fine-grained soils are fertile and deep
and floods bring a constant supply of new sediments.
The high underground-water table provides a natural
supply for crops.
Only in arid climates may the underground-water table
not be high enough during the whole year. The
remedy, irrigation, is relatively easy to apply because
of the flatness of the land and Its low elevation with
respect to river water levels. The dense network of
river branches and creeks provides an excellent and
safe communication system.
In the early stages of human settlement men made
their homes on the natural ridges or levees along the
river branches and creeks where the land is higher
than in the central part of the delta areas and
affords a certain degree of natural protection against
floods. In some deltas this stage was followed by the
dredging of a network of canals to open up the area.
Once again farm houses were built along these new
watercourses and thus the characteristic type of settle¬
ment In the deltas is one of ribbon development.
Soon the need was felt to control the flood waters
from the river. Embankments were thrown up along
certain reaches of the river branches, thus providing
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
ér
'3
!1
*
«^
partial flood protection and leaving other areas open
as ways of escape and release for the highest floods.
To extend the flood protection system, dikes were
built encircling the low-lying areas so as to exclude the
flood waters completely. As this hampered the natural
drainage of excess rainwater, it became necessary to
install a drainage system with sluices equipped with
movable gates, drainage canals, ditches, etc.
In the deltas in semi-arid zones, Irrigation was in¬
troduced at an early stage. Classic examples are the
delta of the Nile and the internal deltas of the Euphra¬
tes and Tigris and the Indus which became sites of
early civilizations.
The natural advantages of deltas were "recognized in
an early stage of history but it was soon realized that
to gain the full benefit of these advantages certain
technical problems would have to be solved.
First there is the problem of floods. Deltas are in¬
vaded by floods from two sides: from the rivers and
from the sea. To a certain extent the river floods are
beneficial. They supply the land with fresh sediments
thereby improving the soil structure and raising the
land elevation. The river flood ls the main agent in
building up the delta. The flooding of the land does
not necessarily preclude use of the land for farming.
All depends on the nature of the floods, the climate and
the adaptability of man "to live with the floods."
The large and densely populated deltas of the River
Mekong in Viet-Nam, the River Chao Phya In Thailand
and, to a certain extent, the River Irrawaddy In Burma,
which are flooded annually, show that the land can
be used for agriculture and human settlement.
But two conditions must be met. Firstly, the floods
must be gentle ones, I.e. where the water level rises
slowly, remains at about its maximum for quite a long
period, and then slowly recedes. Secondly, the climate
should allow a crop of rice to be raised during the
flood season.
Rice ls the only profitable crop that can grow In
rising water, providing that the rate of rise is small.
Rice still grows in water several metres deep and is
salt tolerant. Hence It ls the most suitable crop for
deltas In the humid tropical zone which, lacking flood
protection works, are exposed to inundation.
The most Interesting example of intensive use being
made of a deltaic area which is flooded regularly ls
the delta of the River Chao Phya. Here a crop of
rice is raised during the wet monsoon from May until
November. Since rainfall during that period is not
usually adequate to meet the crop needs the additional
water supply by flooding is an absolute necessity. The
gently rising flood waters are beneficial and if they
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
HARNESSING THE MEKONG
THE Mekong, seventh longest river in
the world, descends from the snows
of the High Tibet plateau and flows
for 2,500 miles before reaching the South
China Sea. During its journey it crosses
six countries Mainland China, Burma,
Cambodia, Laos, Thailand and Viet-Nam.
A few small dams have been built on its
tributaries in Thailand and some channels
cut for irrigation, drainage or navigation,
but nowhere is the main channel crossed
by a bridge; nowhere is It curbed by a
dam. Most of the water flows from source
to sea without being used by man. Today
the Mekong is the scene of a historic inter¬
national project in river development.
Under the auspices of the United Nations,
14 countries have begun to help the peo¬
ples of Cambodia, Laos, Thailand and Viet-
Nam to make use of the abundant waters
of the lower Mekong. Because none of
the four countries nor even all of them
together have the technical or financial
resources for such a huge project, the
United Nations helped them to set up a
committee to study the Lower Mekong
Basin, whose present population of 20 mil¬
lion is expected to double within 25 years.
Two major cities of southeast Asia Sai-
gon-Cholon and Bangkok, each with a
population of one million are outside the
basin. Except for the 500,000 people in
the Cambodian capital, Phnom Penh, and
the 100,000 in the Laotian capital, Vien¬
tiane, the population of the basin is largely
rural. Rice-growing, the basic activity of
the majority, is dependent on the monsoon
cycle. The water management plan will
make possible flood control and increased
irrigation, and thus the cultivation of a
second annual rice crop over large areas.
A number of dams are planned: in the
Pamong gorges, 20 miles from Vientiane;
at Khemarat, near the confluence with the
Unations
River Mune; at the falls of Khone and at
Sambor. Finally, a dam built on the Tonle
Sap river between Cambodia's Great Lake
and the Mekong will increase the lake's
capacity as a flood reservoir. The Mekong
will become a year-round deep water
channel right up to Vientiane 1,000 miles
from the sea. Unesco is supervising the
preparation of a mathematical model show¬
ing the Basin's present hydraulic charac¬
teristics and how they will be modified.
DELTA BASIN (Cont'd)
Floods that bring fertility
46
fall to occur the crop suffers damage by drought.
People in the Chao Phya delta have got accustomed to
the cycle of the floods and have learned how to live
with it.
Things are very different when the floods are of the
flash type or when the climate ls unsuitable for rice-
growing. Flash floods, appearing suddenly and causing
rapid variations of the water level, are destructive.
In such cases little use can be made of the land areas
In the delta unless a system of flood protection works,
such as embankments, has been made. Thus in the
delta of the Red River in North Viet-Nam, where flash
floods occur, dikes have been built to protect the land.
This system of flood protection may be more than two
thousand years old. However, in the delta of the River
Mekong in Viet-Nam, where the flood waters rise and
fall slowly, there are no dikes.
Although a good crop of rice can be raised under
conditions of natural flooding, the yields remain rela¬
tively modest. To obtain the high productivity level
of the paddy fields in Japan, China, Spain, and Italy,
for example, adequate water control is an absolute
necessity, and this naturally entails flood protection,
drainage and irrigation.
The menace of floods from the sea is even more
serious than that from rivers. During storm surges
the sea level may raise several metres above the
normal, and If the dikes fail vast areas become deeply
Inundated with salt water. Sea floods are unpredictable
and always destructive. Thousands of casualties were
reported during storm surges or typhoons which hit the
coastal and deltaic areas of Holland in 1953, Japan in
1959, Germany in 1962 and East Pakistan in 1960 and
in 1963. Considerable damage by loss of property, loss
of crops and sallnlzation of the soil occurred.
The history of the deltas is marked by a succession of
flood disasters. Man however has not abandoned his
land but has fought back, strengthening his systems of
defence against the possible return of similar or even
greater floods. Thus the storm flood disaster of 1953
in the Netherlands led to the execution of the Delta
Plan aiming at the enclosure of tidal estuaries of the
River Rhine (see page 48). Similar works were carried
out in Japan in the area of Nagoya after the 1959 floods.
Not all deltas are exposed to storm surges from the
sea. In the deltas of the River Irrawaddy in Burma
and the River Chao Phya in Thailand flooding of the
coastal strip only occurs during exceptionally high tides
and few protective works are needed.
Even if the land is well protected against direct inva¬
sion by the sea a secondary problem may arise through
the infiltration of salt water into the river branches and
the land areas of the delta. The sea water penetrates
into the open estuaries and, being heavier than fresh
water, it creeps over the bottom of the river in an
upstream direction. It mixes to some extent with the
fresh water on top, making the river water brackish
over a considerable distance from its mouth and thus
unsuitable for irrigation or drinking.
This happens especially in the dry season when the
river flow which normally halts the saline water is at
its weakest. The saline water also enters the subsoil
and even at shallow depths the underground water may
become quite brackish. This underground water may seep
out and ooze to the surface, contaminating water in the
ditches and canals. In developed delta areas consi¬
derable amounts of salt are admitted when ships
coming from the sea enter locks. Another source of
salt pollution is the waste water from mining and
chemical industries.
Thus the protection of fresh water supplies in the
coastal zone of a delta is nowadays a major problem.
It is a latent menace, less spectacular but no less serious
than the more obvious and direct attacks of the sea.
Early settlements in deltas were usually above the
limits of the salt water Intrusion, but with increasing
population pressure and need for more arable land and
with the construction of harbours close to the coastline,
use has to be made of areas exposed to penetration by
salty waters.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Left, a Cambodian
technician using a
surveying instrument
during preparatory
studies for the Lower
Mekong River Basin
Project. Right, flood
level markers on the
banks of the Mekong.
Unesco - Mandin
The most drastic and effective measure to halt the
salt water invasion ls to dam off the estuaries and tidal
inlets. In the enclosing dam, sluices with movable gates
are provided. These remain closed during high tides
and storm surges and are opened to evacuate the flood
waters of the river. Projects of this type have been
carried out on a large scale in Japan and in the
Netherlands. The enclosed water areas of the estuaries
turn into fresh water reservoirs, the coastline is shor¬
tened, the drainage and irrigation facilities of the
adjacent areas are improved, etc.
Thus deltas offer a never-ending challenge to their
Inhabitants: each interference with the natural process
of flooding and sedimentation provokes repercussions
leading to further action by man.
Many deltas have undergone considerable develop¬
ment. The most ancient example ls that of the River
Nile. The deltas of the River Po in Italy, the Red River
in northern Viet-Nam and the Yellow River in the
mainland of China are other examples of highly pro¬
ductive regions.
VICTORY FOR
THE RIVER
The development of deltas
can make striking changes
in the outlines on a map.
These four drawings show
the effects of the progres¬
sive silting up of the Persian
Gulf by sediments brought
down the Tigris and the
Euphrates: A. 3000 B.C.;
B. 2000 B.C.; C. Roman
epoch ; D. present day.
The delta areas of many smaller rivers In Japan' and
the delta area of the River Rhine in the Netherlands
have become industrialized areas where the largest ports
of the world are found. Other deltas are relatively pro¬
ductive, but still In the first stage of technical develop¬
ment.
Their further development calls for the use of specia¬
list knowledge of problems In the fields of hydraulic
and agricultural engineering, soil science, agronomy,
coastal engineering, geo-hydrology, etc. The problems
of the deltas are of a rather special nature and there
are still too few experts In these fields.
The United Nations Economic Commission for Asia
and the Far East (ECAFE) at Bangkok took the initia¬
tive at a conference In 1960 to promote the technical and
economic development of the many large deltas In that
region. A general Inventory of the area and a survey of
the many problems Involved were made by a mission
of experts from Japan and the Netherlands who had on-
the-spot discussions with the local authorities. The
results of this study were discussed during a symposium
at Bangkok In 1963 which was focused on the "flood
control, reclamation, utilization and development" of
delta areas in the ECAFE region.
The general scientific aspects of deltas In the humid
tropical zone were discussed in a symposium organized
by Unesco In March 1964 and held at Dacca (East Pa¬
kistan). This symposium covered a wider field than
the ECAFE meeting without entering into the technical
questions of engineering and economics which were the
main topics of the Bangkok meeting.
Research into the various hydrological problems of
delta, estuarine and coastal areas Is also one of the
Items of Unesco's Hydrological Decade for International
collaboration in the field of hydrology.
From "A History of Land Use in Arid Regions",
edited by L Dudley Stamp and published
by Unesco. 1961.
Adriaan Volker is senior engineer in charge of the Service
for Water Management in the Netherlands. He is presi¬
dent of the International Association of Scientific Hydro¬
logy and a member of the International Commission for
the Protection of the River Rhine Against Pollution. He
has written many studies on lake hydrology, ground water,
salinity and water management.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
THE HIGH WALL
OF THE LOW
COUNTRIES
Unesco-A. Tessora
:.:j¿aj£&
ALL ROUND DEFENCE
The great Haringvliet dam is one of the most
remarkable engineering projects ever devised
to overcome a double threat from sea and river.
It has been provided with 17 large sluices
(each 62 yards long) through which excess
water and ice from the Meuse and Rhine rivers
can be allowed to reach the sea. This group
of sluices in the open sea will have an overall
length of 1,092 yards (drawing above). Left,
the huge sluices during construction. The
arms of the dam will reach to the islands of
Voorne and Goeree. Roads built along the
dam walls will turn them into causeways.
Juring the next 25 years the Netherlands will
carry out a gigantic engineering project thanks
to the progress of modern technology and the efforts of
a people who over the centuries have literally wrested
their land from the sea.
The Netherlands is a country that has challenged the
sea and won a resounding victory. With much of its
territory situated at lower levels than the high tides of
the powerful North Sea, the Netherlands has not only
defended itself, but has expanded its land area thanks
to a remarkable system of pumping stations and coast
defences running for over 1,000 miles. For over seven
centuries Its people have multiplied the sea dikes, greatly
reducing the coast line in the north. One simple dike,
the Barrier Dam, 20 miles in length, has pushed back
48 the North Sea 50 miles and shortened the coastline by
nearly 200 miles. Behind its massive walls, the former
Zuyder Zee has become a fresh water lake called the
Ijselmeer, and part of It has been drained to give the
Netherlands over half a million acres of new land.
Other, shorter sea-arms in other coastal areas have also
been closet, by dikes.
Yet even with all its formidable sea defences the
Netherlands suffered a reverse in 1953 when a terrible
storm surge of tide and wind broke through several dikes,
submerging parts of the islands in the south west.
Through the tremendous efforts of its people, the
Netherlands filled the breaches and drained out the
inundated lands within a year. And within three weeks
of the disaster a commission had been set up to study
the problem of sea defences and to decide whether to
raise existing dikes or to dam off altogether the sea arms
in the region known as the Delta Area, where three
CONT'D ON PAGE 61
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Netherlands Information Service
GIANT DAMS
AGAINST
THE SEA
Under the "Delta Pro¬
ject" massive dams will
close off four broad deep
sea inlets : the Haring-
vliet (construction dates,
from 1957 to 1968); the
Brouwershavensche Gat
(1963-1970); the Eas¬
tern Scheldt (1964-
1978) and the Veersche
Gat (1957-1962). Sec¬
ondary dams will be
built in the Zandkreek,
the Grevelingen and the
Volkerak. When the pro¬
ject is finished, the
coastline will be shorter
by 435 miles and inun¬
dation by the sea will
no longer threaten the
southern Netherlands.
NORTH SEA
Brouwershavensche Gat Dam
Veersche Gat Dam
THE DELTA
PLAN
eih »rater dimmed off ¡> ihown in DARK GREY
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
/
t' .' i K ^
*% iß-
© Mastboom Vliegbedrijf-Hof meester
;>» -
rjse*?
i KLM Aerocarto
THREE ISLANDS
BECOME ONE
In April 1961 the last of seven great
sluice caissons was moved into place
to close the gap in the Veersche Gat
dam (above). The caissons were left
in position to serve as the core of the
dyke which has since been completed
(left). This dam and a secondary one
in the Zandkreek are parts of a single
project, the Three-island Project, in
which they link the islands of Walcheren
North Beveland and South Beveland.
By thus completing its arterial network,
the Netherlands has given an economic
boost to this part of the country.
AMSTERDAM
:thehaguej
;haaq;
-ROTTERDAM^
THE
NETHERLANDS
LVii Ifllf»JM3¿i
This drawing shows what the Netherlands would look tí
like if it had no dikes. The dotted line marks the ¡5
present frontier of conquests over the sea. On these M
reclaimed lands live two-thirds of the population of II
the Netherlands. If the inhabitants were to leave H
0 . . MUM
P ,	 , 60MILCS1
and Amsterdam would disappear beneath the sea.
From " Holland Rides the Sea", by Klaas Graftdik. World's Window Ltd., Baarn
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
THE HIGH WALL (Cont'd from page 48)
rivers the Rhine, the Meuse and the Scheldt run Into
the sea.
Thus was born the Delta Project a complex of
engineering works to give new control over the sea. The
work will take 25 years to complete and will bring a
physical and economic transformation to a large part of
the country.
Under the Delta Project four major sea-arms will be
dammed off (see map) and secondary dykes will be
constructed. This will give protection against the sea to
the entire south west of the country. Two of these sea-
arms, the Niewe Westerweg and the Wester Scheide, the
approach routes to the ports of Rotterdam and Antwerp,
will be left open, but their dykes will be raised and
strengthened. To allow the discharge of excess waters
or blocks of ice coming down the Meuse and the two lower
Rhine arms the Waal and the Lek a block of 17 sluices
is being built in the dam enclosing the Haringvliet
estuary. To make this possible a giant construction pit
was made which, when the enclosed waters had been
pumped out, formed a man-made island. The 17 sluices
built here will have a total length of over half a mile.
The Delta Project is more than a weapon to defeat the
sea. It will have a tremendous effect on the fresh water
economy of the Netherlands. Today salt water penetrates
canals and drainage channels and Infiltrates to the land
on the Islands and in the coastal areas of the mainland,
harming the soli by salt Impregnation. When the new
dams are built, fresh water from the rivers will be used
to desalt canals and land alike. An immense reservoir of
fresh water will be built up behind the dams in exactly
the same way that the immense IJselmeer lake was filled
by the River Rhine when the Zuyder Zee was closed olí.
Three dams will be built on the lower Rhine to allow
part of Its waters to flow to the IJselmeer instead of
directly to the sea. Similarly, water from the Meuse and
the Waal will be diverted via Rotterdam.
The Delta Project will also give an important boost to
the Netherlands' economy. An interconnecting system of
roads will be built along the dams, linking hitherto
isolated islands with the mainland. The broad beaches
of Zeeland will also become more accessible. And the vast
new expanses of fresh water will become a paradise for
devotees of water sports and sailing.
Not all the landscape of
the Netherlands has the
checkerboard appearance
of these fields divided by
drainage canals. But if
all the country's ditches
and canals were laid end
to end they would still
cover two-thirds the
distance to the moon.
© KLM. Aerocarto
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
//... Ä^
52
POWER FROM
In the Netherlands, the windmill is still a familiar
part of the landscape. There are fewer today,
of course, than in the 18th century when they
numbered some 9,000. But of the 1,750 that
still exist, some 1,300 are still doing a job of
work grinding corn, sawing wood, pumping
water from the canals. Despite the development
of more powerful pumping apparatus many of
the windmills are still doing the work they were
built for many years ago. Some have been
kept in a perfect state of repair for centuries.
Symbols of a long history of hard work and
ingenuity, the windmills of the Netherlands are
classed as historic monuments. There is even
a "Windmills Association" whose efforts are
deployed to preserve and restore these graceful
and picturesque buildings and, when possible,
to extend their working life. Left, a windmill
at work draining water from a polder reclaimed
land protected by dikes. Above right, adjust¬
ing the angle of a windmill sail. On the skill of
this man depends the efficiency with which the
mechanism will capture power from the winds.
How a series of windmills are used in relays to
pump water uphill from one canal to the next
until it is high enough to run back to the sea.
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
FLOODS !
FLOODS !!
FLOODS
by Maurice Pardé
54
he sight of a large river in flood ls a memor¬
able experience. As the flow of water suddenly
Increases, rising by as much as 20 or 30 feet In a few
hours, it sweeps all before it, tumbling bridges, uprooting
and carrying away trees, tearing down houses and
covering the countryside with mud, sand and rocks. This
is Nature revealed in a mood of wild rage and devastating
power.
Equally Impressive, though less savagely spectacular,
is the type of flood that sometimes spreads out from the
lower reaches of large rivers. Stretching further than
the eye can see, the floodwaters are sometimes 30 to 60
miles in width and extend along the river for 300 to
600 miles or more.
Long before men began to spread over the earth, floods
ravaged Its surface. At the very dawn of history we
find man afflicted by them. Stories of flood tragedies,
like the epic of Noah and the Ark, are woven into the
traditions and folklore of many ancient peoples. And
sometimes, traces of the floods recounted in these stories
have actually been found by modern archaeologists.
Once floods were accepted as accidents unpredictable
and unavoidable. But men have learned more about the
part rivers play In the great "hydroiogic cycle" and are
now using this knowledge to predict floods, in some cases
to control the damage done by them and in others to
prevent them from happening.
To find the most .effective ways of combatting floods,
science has set out to learn as much as possible about
the major ones: their basic causes, the levels they reach,
their maximum discharges, the total volume of water
produced and the speeds of their rise and fall. Each
river network has its own distinctive features, or perhaps
it would be truer to say that many rivers can be placed
in distinctive categories. One of the basic aims of
Potamology (the scientific study of rivers) is the identifi¬
cation of these "river species."
The River Ardèche. a western tributary of the Rhone
River in France, is a typical example of the kind of river
where sudden floods occur. The Ardèche quickly swells
to Its greatest size when it receives between seven and-
eight inches of rain in a matter of hours from its 730
square miles of catchment upstream from Vallon. Many
other Mediterranean rivers in France, Spain and Italy
are just as easily aroused and are sometimes equally
redoubtable.
In many subtropical and tropical regions the effects
of rapid flood rises on the rivers are even more alarming.
In such regions great downpours of four to eight inches
of rain may fall within an hour over a surface of from
20 to 70 square miles or over an even greater area. River
levels rise with terrifying speed; sometimes within hours
the flood has reached its peak.
In contrast, on very long and gently sloping rivers like
the Mississippi and the lower Yangtse-Kiang, the peak
is reached only after the waters have been rising for
four or six weeks. They sometimes take even longer to
arrive if the floods are caused by successive downpours
whose effect is continuous and cumulative.
The amounts of water involved seem slight when cal¬
culated in relation to each square mile of the receiving
area. But when we look at the gross figures of the
volumes of water flowing they are seen to be enormous:
nearly 3,000,000 cubic feet in August 1954 for 540,000 square
miles on the Yangtse-Kiang at Hankow; more than
300,000 cubic feet including the water overflowing the
banks for 1,200,000 square miles on the Mississippi at
Vicksburg in May 1917.
The rainfall which causes major floods of this kind
covers a huge area 700,000 square miles or more and
is thus well below the average Intensity of the downpours
on the Ardèche and still less so the deluges of places like
Texas, the Philippines or Japan, all of which are confined
to small areas. For Instance, in 1931, the Yangtse-Kiang
above Hankow received about 18 inches of rain, but over
a period of two months.
The essential cause of the unprecedented floods on the
Volga, 2,400,000 cubic feet in the Kubyshev region for
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
(Q Anpfoto, Amsterdam
470,000 square miles, is the melting snow, whose water
equivalent, including additional river inflows, totals some
12 inches within a single month. And the giant floods
of the Yenesei and the Lena in the U.S.S.R.possibly
totalling respectively 1,040,000 and 960,000 cubic feet
which are the highest in the world after those of the
Amazon, are no doubt due to thawing snow which, added
to the rainfall, amounts to seven to eight inches in a
month, as far as can be estimated.
Floods which are from twenty to a hundred times
slower in rising and falling than the ultra-rapid ones
nevertheless attain colossal proportions because of the
enormous amount of water flowing and the immensity of
the area they cover. Between these two extremes nature
produces a wide range of floods of intermediate size and
varying characteristics.
HIowEVER, major river floods are not caused
exclusively by excessive rainfall or abnormal
thaws or a combination of the two. They may also occur
without any exceptional increase in water flow when the
river bed is blocked, usually for only a period, by obstacles
of a solid and bulky kind.
Sometimes the river itself is responsible. Blocks of
ice may pile up in narrower or shallower sections of the
river channel. Blockages are formed across slow rivers
subjected to intense cold, either when the surface is
frozen or much more frequently, when the thaw drives
the frozen debris downstream.
One example of this kind is the disastrous flood on the
Rhine at Coblenz and Cologne in January 1784. In
Cologne the levels of the waters were at least 10 feet
higher than in any earlier known "iceless" floods. Ice
too played a part in the flooding of Budapest when in
March 1838 the Danube rose six feet above any previous
(or subsequent) recorded level. At the time of the Hun¬
garian catastrophe, a storm wind drove the waters and
ice before It and more than half the buildings in Pest
were destroyed.
Even higher and more watertight obstacles can be built
up in deep and narrow mountain reaches by the arrival
of inflowing glaciers.
Spectacular examples occur in the Indus system behind
the Himalayas or as it passes through the wild gorges
several thousand metres below the peaks. In 1840, a lake
820 feet deep was formed by an obstacle In the Indus at
the toe of Nanga Parbat, and one 196 feet deep was creat¬
ed In the Chayog, a tributary of the same river, upstream
of the Chang-Kumdan glacier in the Karakoram in 1939.
The worst feature of these obstructions ls that sooner
or later they break up and waves of swirling and roaring
ice and debris plunge Into the valleys where they sweep
away and crush everything In their path.
Glaciers can also be the cause of other disasters that
are not always predictable. In the night of July 12-13.
1892, the Tête Rousse glacier to the south of Mont Blanc
suddenly released 7,000,000 cubic feet of water enclosed
in a pocket at a height of more than 10,000 feet.
Rushing down the mountain side this mass of water
scooped up rocks and earth from the slopes until it in¬
creased five-fold, forming a terrifying stream of "lava"
the term used for floods which contain more mud, sand,
pebbles and rock than water. There were 175 victims,
most of them in the little town oí Saint-Gervals.
Flood disasters occur above all where river-beds have
been made too narrow by Nature or have been restricted
by man-made works, or where the slope ls too small
to carry away the high discharges that can occur on
these rivers. In Canada, for example the memorable
April-May 1950 flood on the North Red River coming
from the United States caused unbelievable damage In
Winnipeg and nearby, despite the fact that its discharge
at the time was not considered dangerous by specialists.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
FLOODS (Cont'd)
The river mouth wandered 300 miles
56
As on many other sites, the riverside populations had
increased the already dangerous narrowness of the river
by constructing far too many buildings, including many
factories and warehouses, in the flood plain.
Yet even allowing for the results of man's thoughtless¬
ness and rashness In siting homes in valleys subject to
flooding, it is clear that material damage is in fact
directly proportional to the power and the nature of
the floods In any given river sector.
In the tragic disaster of the Riera de las Arenas and of
other small and very steep Catalan rivers in the hilly
country behind Barcelona at Tarrasa, Rubu, Sabadell, and
other villages, there were a number of causes for the
flood which killed more than 700 people in the night of
September 25-26 1962.
Firstly, furious discharges of water, occuring in an area
of a few dozen square miles, were produced by storm
rainfall of short but crushing intensity more than four
inches in three-quarters of an hour. A second reason was
the Irregularity of the river beds, whose width and depth
were far too small to contain the discharges. The crown¬
ing misfortune was lack of foresight In choosing locations
for residential and Industrial buildings. At places where
the bridges were too small and too low, wreckage piled up
before "exploding" and sweeping all before it. Buildings
were shattered and carried away. The roaring masses of
water unleashed In these Catalan streams were as deadly
as the torrential "lava" already described.
'ivERS of all sizes draining vast, subarid
.regions, which are virtually unprotected
against erosive runoff by their scant vegetation, may
Increase their volume by 20% to 30% or more through
the addition of mud.
Towards Its entry into the vast deltaic plain, the Yellow
River, the Hwang Ho, has been known to carry down more
than 500 kgs. of sediment per cubic metre of water, in
spite of its relatively gentle slope. Although these minute
particles do not slow down the discharge as would bulkier
fragments, the river-bed still cannot contain the water
during heavy floods. The water level is swiftly raised by
the dropping of the extra solid load especially of fine
sand and the river flows over what is actually a flat yet
still protruding embankment covering an area of more
than 58,000 square miles.
When the river has broken through one of its dykes,
its murky waters engulf the land and in some places leave
layers of mud, several yards thick, around the surviving
houses. The waters are unable to return to their former
course and several times have flowed to the sea on first
one and then the other side of the Shantung Peninsula,
250 to 300 miles from their former mouth.
On September 29, 1887, the Hwang Ho flood waters
rushed through a breach in the southern dyke upstream
of Kalfeng. Within a few days they had reached the
Hwal, itself a dangerous river, and then flowed on to the
Yangtse-Kiang. A million Chinese are said to have
perished during this catastrophe.
On the Yangtse-Kiang, floods can threaten as many
as 25 to 30 million people. An International enquiry
showed that in the floods of July and August 1931, some
140,000 people were drowned or were crushed beneath the
wreckage of their homes. Many more died of pneumonia,
typhoid or hunger.
On the North American continent, and in past times
(in 1882, for example), the inadequately banked and
dammed Mississippi invaded vast areas, but they were
then far less populated. In April and May 1927, when
the Mississippi transformed 35,000 square miles into a sea
of muddy water, there were 214 victims.
The Ohio is another U.S. river subject to major floods.
Its swollen waters are often partially or even entirely
responsible for the great Mississippi floods. In February
1937. it surpassed its previous highest level by nine feet
at Cincinnati and by ten feet at Louisville. In March
1936, the disastrous flood on the upper Ohio alone rose
^
¿N,
WATER SNAKE. This
striking air view of the Ken¬
tucky River, a tributary of
the Ohio River ¡n the United
States, was taken as raging
floods swept through the
towns of Hazard (top) and
Lothair (bottom) last year.
Some. 25,000 people were
forced to flee their homes.
Photo © Associated Press
«H
*-*
above the highest flood level ever recorded by nearly
five feet at Pittsburgh, where 110,000 people were left
homeless and some forty lost their lives.
Another memorable U.S. flood, but this time further
West, devastated the Kansas River valley and the valleys
of the neighbouring Neosho and Osage rivers in July 1951,
yet caused only 19 deaths. Records show that a previous,
but smaller flood in this area in May-June 1903 claimed
over 100 victims. The low casualty list in the recent
flood points to remarkable progress made in flood warning
and rescue arrangements.
Another U.S. flood, almost as disastrous, occurred in
New England in August 1955. Violent currents, flowing
down steeper slopes than those in Kansas, made these
waters even more sudden and violently erosive. Fed by
the torrential rainfall from cyclone Diana, and following
a super saturation of the ground by cyclone Connie a few
days earlier, the flood raised the River Delaware to greater
heights than anyone could recall. But even more as¬
tounding and terrifying were the increases on modest
coastal rivers like the Naugatuck and the Quinebaug,
or small rivers like the Farmlngton and Westfleld which
run Into the Connecticut. Almost 180 people died in
this flood.
Floods that produce sudden and far more overwhelming
discharges of water during cloudbursts can make a host
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
of streams in at least one half of the United States
irresistible and devastating.
Of the ultra-rapid type of flood in France, those in the
Cévennes, Languedoc and Roussillon, although nothing
like as powerful as the Texan floods, often have disastrous
results.
On September 22, 1890, some 40 people were drowned
by the Ardèche and its tributaries. Nearly 70 years later,
on September 30, 1958, the Ardèche flood was less terrible,
but the Gardon and the Cèze, which always rise at the
same time, reached record heights and claimed 36 victims.
Other floods which France experiences are less swift
but even more striking because of the size of the area
inundated, the rivers responsible being very large ones.
Two notable floods of this kind occurred between June
23-25, 1875 and March 3-6, 1930 in the basin of the River
Garonne.
The first, in which quite exceptional floods swept down
the Pyrenean rivers, the Ariège and the upper Garonne,
caused an unprecedented disaster. Five hundred people
perished, including more than 200 in Toulouse. The
water was 10 to 15 feet deep in the streets of Agen.
In March 1930, flood levels once again rose almost as
high In Agen. This time the water came not from the
upper Garonne, but from the Tarn, the Aveyron and the
Agout whose maximum flows were perhaps such as occur
only once in a thousand years. There were 200 deaths.
Including 120 at Molssac.
In May and June 1858, flood water swept over the
smiling and fertile Loire Valley from the Bec d'Alller down
to Nantes at the river's mouth as the dykes gave way in
160 places. Water covered more than 400 square miles.
For many centuries, man has endeavoured to protect
towns and rich and populated valleys by building earth
dikes along one or both banks of rivers.
An area of 20,000 square miles of land towards the
mouth of the Mississippi and its tributaries, are safe¬
guarded in this way against flood risks by 2,800 miles of
dikes.
However, by their very success in preventing flooding
these river bank defences concentrate the water In a
confined channel and thus greatly Increase the speed of
the floods and hence their maximum discharge capacity.
On the lower Mississippi at its confluence with the Ohio
River, the progress made between 1882 and 1937 In extend¬
ing and improving dikes has also raised the heaviest river
discharges by from six to ten feet. The smaller number
of dike failures all along the River Po in Italy almost
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
Photo Cuban Delegation to Unesco
FLOODS (Cont'd)
Early in October 1963, eastern Cuba was ravaged by catastrophic floods. Swollen by rains
from a cyclone, the rivers Contramaestre and Cauto and several tributaries overflowed their
banks. Hundreds of square miles of land disappeared under the waters. Over 1,000 people
were drowned and thousands lost all their possessions. Above, salvaging a stranded bus.
Curbing an angry torrent
throughout the past century have similarly been offset by
an obvious rise in the water level three feet or more in
certain sections where the bed had not been deepened
at all.
This has led to the extra expense of raising the crest
and thickening out the body of the dikes to enable them
to hold In the higher water levels that they have them¬
selves made more dangerous. Then, on short stretches
which have to be safeguarded at all costs, the earth
embankments are replaced by narrow vertlcle concrete
floodwalls.
In very critical situations, dikes are gradually raised
with sacks of sand and cement to form a makeshift
barrier which prevents them from being overtopped and
thus inevitably destroyed. In August 1954, during one
of the greatest of all floods on the Yangtse-Kiang, as
many as 280,000 workers at a time laboured for weeks,
progressively raising the crest of the dikes for a dis¬
tance of 85 miles. Their efforts saved three large towns-
Hankow, Wuchang and Hanyang from inundation.
I NSTEAD of raising the banks with dikes, it is
sometimes considered more advisable to deep¬
en the bed by dredging. However, it has often been found
that the level and surface relief of the bottom conforms
to a certain natural balance governed by the slopes and
the solid and liquid discharges of the river. Thus, even
after dredging the waterway eventually restores the
former levels by depositing gravel or sand.
In other cases, one or several river bends are lopped
off by digging a straight channel which soon takes all
the flow. Shortening the course increases the slope,
often sufficiently for the accelerated current to carve out
a deeper bed at the bottom. This lowers the flood levels,
as it did on the Mississippi where, after 13 bends had
58 been cut off the drop was from five to ten feet between
the confluences with the Arkansas River and the Red
River.
When topographical conditions allow and relatively
limited damage is likely to be caused to existing property,
new beds, by-passes or diversions can be made to switch
excessive surplus discharges away, from areas to be pro¬
tected. For example, the Sutter by-pass on one side of
the city of Sacramento in the United States, and the
Yolo by-pass on the other, are used during flood level
conditions to relieve the normal bed which passes through
the city. Again, upstream of New Orleans, the Bonnet
Carré floodway on the right bank of the Mississippi di¬
verts substantial dischargesnearly 200,000 cubic feet
in 1937 towards Lake Pontchartraln and the sea.
Another flood antidote which has captured popular
imagination is re-afforestation. However, certain aspects
of its effects are still not sufficiently well-known, and in
the main, the results so far obtained have been irregular
and somewhat unpredictable.
In one Important respect, the function of re-afforesta¬
tion cannot be questioned. A good forest overburden
will always reduce erosion and hence the carrying away
of solid matter. This helps to prevent the possible silting
up of reservoirs and above all the silting of river beds
and the rise in their level following floods. However the
quantitative effects of re-afforestation differ immensely
from one basin to another, depending on the interplay
of the different factors involved.
In the vast majority of small basins and in almost
every situation, the effect of re-afforestation is favour¬
able, not so much on the total flood volume but on the
maximum discharges of water. Woodland has several
properties which tend to reduce these discharges: the
interception of the water by branches and especially by
leaves and needles, the usual permeability of the soil,
disturbed and worked over by the roots, the curbing of
runoff by undergrowth or by wood debris.
Woodland is sometimes completely successful in pre¬
venting rivers ( from becoming swollen. However its pro¬
perties are obviously most effective when dealing with
moderate downpours, when temperatures are high and
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
after long periods without rain. Against heavy rain
falling on vegetation and ground that has already been
soaked a forest is virtually Ineffective.
Even when the full impact of afforestation on floods ls
known, It should be remembered that these effects are
more or less proportional to the percentage of wooded
area In a particular basin. Many people, tend to forget
that Increasing the wood area from 10 to 20% or even in
certain cases 50% will hardly alter the flood situation.
And in most heavily populated and modern countries, the
practical possibilities for retlmberlng are no greater than
these.
A sure remedy, for floods, provided it can be applied,
Is to build dams big enough to intercept the dangerous
discharges for as many hours or days as may be needed.
This ls the water which, if it were to flow off naturally
beyond the reservoirs, would flood the places In need of
protection.
The Chinese have recently completed dams which pro¬
mise to tame the floods of the Hwai River. They have
built an even more elaborate structure across the Yellow
River at Sanmen, in a rocky narrows not far from the
entry to the delta plain. The dam is 300 feet high
with a storage capacity of 2,275,000,000,000 cubic feet. The
most formidable maximum discharge that could be
expected will be reduced to a fifth by the reservoir.
In Texas, the Travis reservoir on the Colorado River
can cope with 84,000 million cubic feet of water which is
more than the total volume of the worst sudden but brief
floods which are let loose in this river basin.
| ozENS and even hundreds of other examples
could be given of Isolated or Interrelated
reservoirs now in service which are designed to reduce the
maximum flood discharges either permanently or in
emergencies. Many such reservoirs exist in the Massif
Central, in France, in the Harz Mountains and the high-
lying areas of the Rhineland in the Federal Republic of
Germany and in the mountains of Bohemia. There are
many more in Japan and in the United States. In the
Tennessee valley network, for example, there are 27
dams storing as much as 945,000 million cubic feet of
water. And on the middle Missouri, three dams alone
Peck, Oahe and Garrisonwould be capable of
stopping, if necessary, more than 2,800,000,000,000 cubic
feet which is more than the total annual discharge of
the river.
On many rivers quite excellent results are obtained by
combining several methods: reservoirs, dikes, Improved
bed-lines, removal of bends, diversions and so on. In
addition roads and railway tracks are moved away from
river courses and raised on embankments.
When a project for any river basin is drawn up, the
hydrologist first has to calculate the maximum discharges
that are likely to occur, the total volumes of water that
may flow and the duration of the longest anticipated
floods. He is, in fact, trying to determine the charac
teristics of floods that are only likely to occur once every
100, 500. 1,000 or even 5,000 years or more.
Probability computations are used for drawing up these
forecasts based on all the past river and rainfall data
recorded in the basin.
Much shorter-term forecasts with precise data are
needed by people living close to rivers that have not been
effectively protected against flooding. The inhabitants
must be given enough time to remove themselves and
their possessions to safety. The ability to produce these
forecasts depends on various factors: the anticipated
time-lapse between the flood warning and the arrival
of the flood waters; and whether the floods are caused
by rainfall or snow or to something happening on the
river itself.
In the present state of scientific knowledge, it ls im¬
possible to predict with certainty several months or weeks
In advance that there will be a rainstorm on a given
day or even within a given week.
However, reasonably accurate predictions are often
made 24 or 36 hours in advance as to whether a rainstorm
of a certain intensity will fall on a given basin or not.
But in general, it ls not possible to say with great preci¬
sion how long the rainfall will last or what its total
volume and varying Intensities will be.
The element of doubt In working out temperatures ls
much smaller and thus it ls easier to know how much
snow will melt on the next day and the following one.
When a rainstorm has already produced flows of water
that are liable to swell the rivers, an efficient communica¬
tions system enables a good tentative assessment to be
made of likely flood levels.
The most reliable short-term forecasts are above all
hydrometrical. They are based on accurate information
from stations upstream where the discharges or levels
have been sucesslvely recorded.
In basins where extensive experience of observations
has removed some uncertainty factors effective and even
remarkably forecasts can be made, as in the case of the
very heavy floods on the middle and lower Mississippi,
where peaks of 40 to 60 feet can be predicted to within
about four inches a fortnight or a month ahead.
However, for places that are invaded and devastated
by floods within an hour or so after the end of torrential
downpours of the type that occur In Texas or even in
the Cévennes, It will still be very difficult and sometimes
impossible to give warning in time In spite of improved
telecommunications.
Maurice Parde is professor of physical geography and
river hydrology at the University of Grenoble, France. His
many works on hydrology include "Fleuves et Rivières"
(Rivers and Streams) published by Armand Colin, Paris,
1947 and "Potamologie" (Potamology) published by the
University of Grenoble in two volumes, 1954.
-r^K?
THE DELUGE. An 11th
century mural painting in
the church or St. Savin-sur-
Gartempe, France, depicts
Noah's Ark afloat on the
waters of the Flood. This
deluge is described in the
Bible, which relates that the
the rain "was upon the
earth for forty days and
forty nights", and the story
is also told in some texts
written in cuneiform. Tales
of great floods are woven
into the traditions and le¬
gends of many ancient
peoples. Sometimes traces
of such floods have been
found by archaeologists.
Archives Photographiques. Paris
59
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
HYDRAULIC
CIVILIZATIONS
by '
Pedro Armillas
GODDESS OF THE WATERS. This
kneeling statue is Chalchiuhtlicue, Aztec
goddess of the waters, and a feminine
counterpart of Tlaloc, god of the rains.
She wears a breast-plate composed of
four rows of green stones and a head¬
dress of sea shellssymbols of water.
he oldest civilizations of the worldancient Egyptian,
Sumerian, and Harappan arose on arid lands made
productive by great rivers whose floods moistened the parched
ground and enriched the soil with deposits of silt; these centres of
higher culture were situated in the Nile River valley, the alluvial
lands between the lower courses of the Euphrates and the Tigris, and
the area watered by the Indus River and its tributaries in Punjab
and Sind.
Other old, independent growths of civilization took place either in
desert zones where conditions made the collection of underground
moisture or irrigation by diversion of surface streams a prerequisite
for agricultureor In areas where the vagaries of rainfall extreme
variability from year to year, frequent droughts or delays in the start
of the rainy seasonbrought the threat of crop failure and
consequent disaster to the people.
An example of the first of these cases is the ancient Peruvian
civilization which, long before the Incas, attained its zenith on the
riverine oases scattered along the Pacific coast; the second conditions
prevail over most of China, and especially In the Huangho basin
where Chinese civilization first blossomed, and also over the central
Mexican Plateau which was the homeland of a civilization already
old when the Aztecs arose to imperial power.
The evolution of civilization is marked by profound changes in
economic relations and the structure of society, which in their turn
have created new forms of political organization.
Our knowledge of the early stages of development of the ancient
civilizations Is admittedly very sketchy. Recorded historythe
keeping of annals and writing of chronicles is one of the con¬
sequences of the expansion of intellectual horizons that goes hand-
in-hand with the birth of civilization. Thus, the beginnings of the
social processes that led to the transformation can only be dimly
perceived in the twilight of the past or else must be inferred from
archaeological discoveries.
N
60
Jevertheless, in the examples we are concerned with here,
in some cases these social processes certainly were, and
In others, may well have been, closely linked with the wide-scale use
of labour for. land Improvement (land reclamation and soil conserva¬
tion) and increased food-production through intensive cultivation.
Any doubts about this are due to lack of knowledge concerning the
early stages of civilization in the Indus River Valley and in central
Mexico.
In arid lands or in areas afflicted by recurrent droughts or subject
to catastrophic floods by the same rivers that brought them life,
people were forced to undertake two kinds of water-works:
productive (reservoirs, irrigation canals) and protective (dikes).
They did so to produce sufficient food for large and stable populations,
to obtain the surpluses needed to support the superstructure of
civilization, and also to avert the calamity of a total loss of harvests.
Potentially fertile but swampy alluvial lands were also reclaimed
by means of drainage ditches or artificial gardens floating on shallow
waters (chinampas In the lakes of central Mexico and gardens of the
same type in the Vale of Kashmir). All this has been done since
remote times to enlarge the areas available for farming.
Although small-scale Irrigation does not necessarily produce radical
changes in farming communitiesas evidenced, for example, by the
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
-
.
#
archaeological record on irrigation and society among the prehistoric
Hohokam people of southern Arizona (although here the failure to
grow can be explained by the very limited water supply)it certainly
has potential effects on social and political development.
Firstly, it creates landholdings with different levels of productivity,
and thus tends to promote private ownership of improved land and
the accumulation of wealth. Secondly, when a number of com¬
munities become dependent on the flow of the same stream, inter-
communal competition eventually requires the establishment of
supra-communal' authority to allocate water-rights and to mediate
in conflicts.
An agricultural economy depending on small Irrigation works may
lead to the establishment of feudal societies, as happened in China
during the Chou Dynasty (from 1100 to 250 B.C.) or in ancient Japan.
Large scale water-works, on the other hand, require mass-
mobilization of the labour force; hence, such projects presuppose the
existence of a political machine with power to demand service from
the people.
The building of extensive canal networks in ancient Sumer
(southern Mesopotamia) certainly post-dates the establishment of
dynastic states and may well have taken place no earlier than the
rise of empires. There is no available evidence that state hydraulic
enterprises existed In Pharaonlc Egypt during the Old Kingdom
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
EARLIEST WATER
WHEEL. A "noria" on
the River Orentes in Syria,
a rare existing example of
the earliest machines used
to draw power from the
waters of rivers. It car¬
ries water to an aque¬
duct built by the Romans
to irrigate nearby fields.
Photos © Musée da I'Hommo. Paris
61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
HYDRAULIC CIVILIZATIONS (Cont'd)
OF RIVER
BONDAGE
© Pierre Verger
INCA WATER-WORKS. In the steep
valleys near the ancient Inca capital at
Cuzco, in Peru, many sections of massive
aqueducts, 50 to 70 feet high, still exist.
The Incas built them to carry away water
from a network of drainage canals, often
hundreds of miles long, in a region
where it rains heavily for half the year.
ROMAN AQUEDUCT. No fewer than
30 cities of Roman Gaul were supplied
by aqueducts. The most massive of
all, (below) which carried water to Nimes,
still stands astride the River Gard, a
tributary of the Rhone, in southern
France. It was built in 20 B.C. (the
time of Augustus Caesar). It is 880 feet
long and rises 157 feet above the valley.
Paul Almasy. Paris
period; the first recorded undertaking of this kind was the linkage of
the Nile to the Fayum depression, so as to use Lake Moerls as a
reservoir to regulate the floods, under the Twelfth Dynasty. In
ancient China, historians agree that construction of large-scale
water-works did not begin until the Period of the Warring States
(481-255 B.C.), when Chinese civilization was already one thousand
years old.
To understand the processes Involved in the growth of hydraulic
societies it ls worthwhile to note that the development of water-
control in China at that time ls linked to the technical revolution
brought about by the appearance of Iron tools, the use of oxen to pull
the plough, and the increasing practice of manuring the fields to
sustain fertility.
The greater productivity of agricultural labour led to the dis¬
integration of the feudal system and stimulated the growth of private
land ownership; the breakdown of feudal bonds left a mass of former
peasant-serfs liable to be drafted for the construction of public
works. At the end of this period of development, the opening of the
Chengkuo Canal in 246 B.C. brought prosperity to central Shensi and
gave the King of Ch'in power to subjugate the rival feudal states,
thus achieving imperial unification of the country.
¡ overnment management of large scale water-works led to
l the development of a bureaucracy and the dependence of
the subject classes upon it. The term "hydraulic civilizations"
refers specifically to those states whose social structures were shaped
by these forces.
The Increase of water-control and the development of hydraulic
societies appear to be reciprocal processes and the fact has long been
recognized. The connexion between farmers' dependence on water¬
works and the structure of society was remarked on by Pedro de
Cleza de Leon, one of the Spanish conquistadores of the northern
Andean region of South America. Cleza noted the contrast, on the
one hand, between the submissiveness of the civilized Peruvian
Indians, long used to obeying masters and paying taxes, and the easy
downfall of the powerful Inca Empire and on the other, the rebellious
character of the uncivilized tribes of Colombia who long resisted
colonization. The reason for this, writes Cleza in his description
of these peoples (first printed at Seville in 1553) is that the Colombian
tribes never had centralized political organization, were unused to .
servitude and depended on rainfarming. When harried by the
Spaniards, they easily escaped to the bush where new clearings
allowed them to raise their crops and live free from outside inter¬
ference.
On the desert Peruvian coast, the chronicler continues, men were
bound by nature to the riverine oases, and agriculture depended on
the state-controlled irrigation systems. Restrictive geographical
conditions also prevailed in the Andean highlands, where, the crops
grown on terraced mountainsides relied on water conveyed by
elaborate systems of aqueducts; hence, the Indians could not rebel
without risking their means of livelihood.
Another example ls ancient China where public hydraulic enter¬
prises undertaken at the closing of the feudal era played a paramount
role in creating economic bases for political domination. These in
turn led to imperial unification. Chinese historians of the ensuing
period (Han dynasty) were thus well aware of the relationships
between state-power and water-control. Some perceptive observations
on this subject are found in the Book of the Earlier Han (Ch'ien-han
Shu) which was given its final form by the Chinese historian, Pan
Ku, who lived from 32 A.D. to 92 A.D.
Modern theoretical analysis of ' hydraulic civilizations owes Its
beginning to students of society and culture, and since the early
1930's, some distinguished researchers have produced studies
analyzing the structure of these communities, describing the
processes of their development, and explaining their role in social
evolution.
Pedro Armillas, Mexican historian, archceologist and ethnologist, is a
leading specialist in the pre-Columbian history of the Americas. He
is now working for the Anthropological Museum of Michigan, U.S.A.,
for whom he has carried out numerous archceological excavations in
Guatemala, Honduras and El Salvador.
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
m
Paul Almasy. Paris
Like an ancient frieze brought to life, a camel train cros¬
ses the River Zayendeh at Shahristan, near Ispahan, in
Iran. This striking brick and stone bridge dates from
the 11th century, Mohammedan era (17th cent. A. D.).
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
COLOUR FORTHE UNESCO COURIER
Sir,
Congratulations on your excellent issue
of May 1964 with its articles on juvenile
delinquency and on Galileo. I hope that
the lives and work of other great men
will be given an equally fine presentation
in future numbers.
There is something else I have been
thinking about for some time. You have
covered subjects such as the stained glass-
of Rheims cathedral and the art treasures
of Nubia in past issues as well as astro¬
nomy in your May issue. I feel sure
that all these first-rate numbers would have
been greatly enriched by the inclusion of
a full colour plate.
In view of your large circulation I am
sure that the cost of such an innovation
would not call for a very large increase
in your subscription rate. Many people,
like myself, would welcome this added
feature. The Unesco Courier, a magazine
of world standing, would be even more
appreciated and treasured by its readers.
Georges Forclnal
Bron, France
Ed. Note: The Unesco Courier will
introduce full colour pages on a regular
basis with the January 1965 issue. See
announcement back cover.
CHINESE CALLIGRAPHY
Sir,
I greatly enjoyed your issue on "The Art
of Writing" (March 1964). However, I
feel that such a vast subject deserved an
additional half-page or so devoted to bib¬
liographical sources. Do you know of
any works dealing especially with Chinese
and Japanese ideograms and Chinese, Japa¬
nese and Arabic calligraphy and particularly
from an aesthetic point of view? I have
already read Etiemble's book, "Writing",
published by Editions Delpierre, Paris.
Paul Robert
Sceaux, France
Ed. Note : The general bibliography pub¬
lished in our March issue listed several
works of interest to the general reader.
These, in turn, furnished a much more
comprehensive and varied bibliography on
the subject of writing. For Chinese writing
we recommend "Chinese Calligraphy" by
Chiang Yee, published by Methuen and
Co., London. There are many other books
on these subjets, but most of them have
been published in China or Japan and are
in the languages of these countries.
CALLING ALL SCHOOLS
Sir,
I am one of a small group of teachers
in Liège who have been carrying out a
programme of their own creation for the
past year. Though in no way inspired by
official directives, it is none the less closely
and vitally linked with our vocation as
teachers. Broadly its purpose could be
summed up as "fellowship with all men".
Each month we choose a subject from the
pages of The Unesco Courier to introduce
in our classes. Several of these themes
racism, hunger in the world, the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights have been
of the greatest value to the children we
teach.
This year we are concentrating on
another aspect : international correspon¬
dence between schools. We wish to make
contact with a network or correspondents
from schools in all parts of the world.
Can you help us ? ' We can cover postage
costs from the resources of our school
co-operative and take care of the problem
of translations at least in three main
languages of world communication :
English, Spanish and German. Our children
are aged from 11 to 14 and all come from
working class homes. Our address is 44
Avenue Reine Elizabeth, Liège, Belgium.
Francis de Bruyn
Liege, Belgium
WHEN SPORT GETS OF FOCUS
Sir,
M. Maheu's timely address "Sport is
Education" has created a great deal of
interest in New Zealand. Apparently, only
extracts of it appeared in The Unesco
Courier (Jan. 1964) and in commenting
on parts of it, one runs the risk of quoting
out of context. However, the topic is
of such importance that the risk must be
taken.
Most people will agree that Pierre de
Coubertin went too far in claiming that
the modern Olympics should be considered
a religion. Fortunately, this has not
happened yet at Olympic level, but in
some countries, enthusiasm for certain
sports bears the hallmarks of religious
fervour. Often, the hold on the human
personality is such that one particular
game, and the competition that supports
it, is almost the sole topic of conversation
all year round. This commitment to a
sport is very close to fanaticism. Once
having, as it were, stepped on the sports'
stage, some people are psychologically
incapable of stepping off it again. Surely
this is sport out of focus?
Sport is important, and has been so
since homo sapiens freed himself from
the burden of unremitting toil. The
individual's biological need for physical
activity must be met, and sport is a
superlative way of doing this. Nevertheless,
it is not as important as feeding hungry
people, promoting better human relation¬
ships, eliminating war, curing cancer or
any one of a hundred other pressing
human needs. Too often, it seems, skill
and success in sport are elevated above
attitudes. To me the latter include not
only the conventional postures about sports¬
manship, but also a true evaluation ot
sport as play and recreation something
apart, bound by special rules, truly
significant and meaningful to the par¬
ticipant but part of the world of play,
of make-believe, not to be confused with
the larger world of reality.
Except with children, this play-world
can never be as real or as important as
the larger world outside the arena. When
it is so regarded, the image is distorted.
The article mentions the element of
truce. As far as we know, the truce of
Ophites and Lycurgus was honoured by
athlete and spectator alike and the only
criterion was athletic ability. But in recent
years we have seen, in some international
competition, something very near the
substitution of one kind of conflict for
another. When this happens, sport divides
people instead of uniting them. In
expounding the ideal we should not close
our eyes to the reality.
In Malaya, where there is difficulty in
uniting four peoples English, Chinese,
Malays and Tamils into one nation, sport
is being used as a universal medium of
education. In the schools this is showing
great promise. Children learn quickly to
appreciate good performance and conduct,
regardless of race and language. It will
be interesting to see if sport exercises the
same influence at adult level, where
¡deals are not so important when emotions
run hot. Even so, the simple fact that
sport is being used deliberately to bring
different peoples closer together is further
recognition of the validity of de Cou-
bertin's philosophy.
Sport is character education. This part
of the talk must have been severely
condensed for, without explanation, it
appears trite and overworked. In this
context,- character and sportsmanship are
rarely defined. We seem to be on
reasonably sure ground when we discuss the
play of children for it is play that does
most to develop group and social
consciousness in them. This happens
because fairness and obedience to rules
are not just verbal concepts to children.
They become a kind of living, organic
morality.
Even so, there is an element of self¬
ishness in this. The group interest
gradually becomes the child's interest and
a social being is created. Whatever changes
may have been effected in the child's
attitudes and character during this process,
it is still his own interest that is being
served. He has, however, adapted it to
the group.
When adolescence is reached, attitudes
to rules, fairness and appropriate conduct
become more particularized and may vary
between one sport and another. The codes
are not all equally observed. It is here
64
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
that we begin to have doubts about sport
and character with some participants. If
the code serves their interests (e.g. winning)
then it is obeyed. If it does not serve their
interests, it may still be obeyed because
of the social pressures of team ir.-ics,
opponents and spectators, but if it can be
broken without censure, this often happens.
Is it a virtue to observe a code of
behaviour under pressure?
My contention here is that it is too
easy and often erroneous to generalize
about sport and character, especially among
adults. Perhaps its greatest contribution
in iidult life is self-discovery, the sometimes
shattering revelation of one's true status.
This still leaves wide open the whole
question of whether sportsmen generalize
what they learn on the sports field. Some
do. Others don't. And in any case, games
are worth playing for their own sake,
regardless of moral, public or character
values.
It is difficult for some educators to
appreciate the importance of sport as
culture. Some intellectuals believe that
attending a Shakespearean drama is a
cultural experience whereas attending a
game is beneath the notice of an intelligent
person. Is the mime of the sports field
any less cultural than the sound of the
stage ? Is the drama any less intense ?
Roles in both circumstances have been
created externally the one by an author,
the other by an authority. In some ways
the stage is much more circumscribed
than the field, the action more severely
restricted and with less creative oppor¬
tunity. Many sports events outdo ballet
in complexity and beauty of action. Top
levels in both require dedication of a high
order. Does the mass appeal of one
cultural form degrade it?
Movement was a universal language
long before the first word was spoken and
it speaks even more eloquently in the
trained and refined action of the modern
athlete. It is hard to understand why
seeing the young Hamlet carelessly killing
Polonius should be a cultural experience
and seeing Valerie Brumel clearing seven
feet should not. Motive and plot are
deeper and more devious in the former
and elemental passions are more acutely
involved. Does treason, murder and
revenge make Hamlet a cultural drama?
Does simplicity of purpose and absence of
passion make the drama of the high jump
any less cultural ? Many believe that
skill and perfection of controlled bodily
movement are among the most beautiful
of human accomplishments.
Culture is not the sovereign right of any
group of disciplines. In this context it is
surely the complete mastery of some skill,
whether this be the perfect manipulation
of a musical instrument, the vocal facility
of a prima donna, the histrionic ability
of the actor, the craft of an accomplished
writer or the kinesthetic intelligence of the
pole vaulter. And if it is "cultural" to
watch the one, it is surely "cultural" to
watch the other. Much so-called "cultural"
experience comes from watching, provided
always that there is real understanding at
the same time.
The vexed question of amateurism is a
difficult one and many would wish to
have ideas as clear cut and definite as
these in the Unesco Courier article.
Undoubtedly, it is time the practical issues
of the situation were faced. Practices vary
so much from one sport to another. What
is condoned in one is condemned in
another and this needs tidying up. But
we should be aware, as far as possible,
of all the implications of paying athletes
and games players. Immediately, the sports
concept of Plato "for nothing but the
sheer pleasure of doing it", is at an end.
Payment removes sport from the play
element in culture and turns it into work.
If players must be paid, so be it, but this
will, in turn, alter the whole nature of
sport and some other name may have to
be found for it.
M. Maheu says that the concepts of
Pierre de Coubertin related to a social
situation and a stage in the technical
development of sport which are now out
of date and that the new conditions must
be faced. It might be salutary to remind
ourselves that sportsmen are under no
compulsion to enter expensive and time-
consuming activities, nor to provide large-
scale spectacles for public amusement.
There are many interesting and worth¬
while sports which cost very little in
either time or money. Might it not turn
out that the Olympic Games itself has
become too large, too unwieldy, too
expensive and too closely allied with
national prestige and that this is the major
factor to be faced, not a fundamental
alteration in the rules of amateur sport.
Can it be that the Games are not worth
the toil, sweat, trouble and expense and
that much more good could be accomplish¬
ed by small exchanges of sportsmen
between different countries?
No student, of history can fail to have
some misgivings at the suggested intro¬
duction of professionalism into the Olympic
arena. It seems inevitable if the Games
are to continue, but it will certainly spell
the end of sport as we have known it
for the past fifty years.
D. R. Wills
Superintendant of Physical Education
for New Zealand, Wellington. N. Z.
THE NEW NATIONS
Sir,
May I compliment you on the excellent
presentation and contents of The Unesco
Courier. However, I should like to support
one of your Soviet correspondents,
Anatoly Chetverikov, in asking you to
publish articles on the nations which have
come into being in recent years and parti¬
cularly those in Africa. The daily press
tells us very little about them, and I for
one would like to know more about their
ways of life, their resources, their state
of civilization and what Unesco is doing to
help their development.
E. Philippe
Bourges, France
GUIDE FOR READERS
Sir,
A collection of issues of The Unesco
Courier is a veritable encyclopaedia which
presents to its readers a panorama of the
work, the resources and the problems of
the world, particularly in the context of
modern times. But this fine source of
documentary material and cultural know¬
ledge should be made into a still more
handy tool. One should be able to trace
immediately any article it publishes or any
subject it deals with without having to
thumb through a pile of back numbers.
A list published annually of the contents of
each issue would solve this problem and
would also provide a classification of
contents by subject. With this innovation
The Unesco Courier would add to its
reputation and far greater and more fruitful
use would be made of the rich store of
facts which it offers readers.
René Barb
Montpellier, France
Ed. note : The possibility of publishing
an index for The Unesco Courier covering
the years 1957-1963 ii at present being
studied. Readers will be informed as soon
as this project has been completed. We
would remind our correspondent that an
index of contents published in 1963
appeared in our December 1963 issue.
MARTIN-LUTHER UNIVERSITY
Sir,
The credit for the photograph with the
article "A Family of Asian Scripts" (March
1964 issue, page 18) of a plaque found in
the Indus Valley reads "Archaeological
Seminary of the University of Halle, Federal
Republic of Germany." The city of Halle,
however, is in Eastern Germany, not the
Federal Republic of Germany. The uni¬
versity's full name is "Martin-Luthcr-Uni-
versitat, Halle-Wittenberg, in Halle (Saale)."
Werner Hiickel
Leipzig, S 3, Eastern Germany
WORLD SOIL SURVEY
Sir,
In The Unesco Courier, (April 1964)
there are extremely interesting articles on
bacilli and the successful fight against the
many ills man is heir to. Consequently
world populace grows apace. What about
food?
Astronomical sums of money are spent
on defence by East and West. What is
done to halt the ever diminishing area (by
erosion) of cultivatable soil on which human
life depends? This problem needs greater
attention than ever before.
Could a world survey on this very urgent
problem be a subject for a future number ?
Shortage of food increases tuberculosis and
halts the progress of man in many peaceful
directions.
T. Kloppenburg
Republic of South Africa
Ed. Note: See our special July /August
1962 issue on Freedom from Hunger.
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
This draft programme, presented to the
Unesco Executive Board when it met
during May and June by M. René Maheu,
Unesco's Director-General, maintains
Unesco's priority 'on education but also
calls for a substantial increase in scientific
activities. The programme and budget will
be submitted to Unesco's General Con¬
ference which meets in Paris in October
and November.
BOOKS FOR ALL: The world's book
production is today concentrated in
ten countries and 70% of all translations
are made from only four languages
English, Russian, French and German
declared M. René Maheu, Director-General
of Unesco, addressing the Second Inter¬
national Congress of Booksellers, which met
in Unesco House, in June. M. Maheu added
that the technical revolution which had
made possible low-cost book production on
a mass scale must now be extended to
developing countries.
KALINGA PRIZE FOR INDIAN
WRITER: Jagjit Singh, science wri¬
ter and adviser on operational research to
the Indian Government, has been selected
as the 12th winner of the international
Kalinga Prize for the popularization of
science. Awarded by an international jury
appointed by Unesco, the Kalinga Prize is
a personal donation of Bijoyanand Patnaik,
an Indian industrialist who is a director of
the Kalinga Foundation in India. Jagjit
66
Unesco C. Bablin
KIERKEGAARD CENTENARY
Young people crowd the aisles in
the packed conference hall at Unesco
House, Paris, during the International
colloquy marking the close of the
Kierkegaard Centenary celebrations
In April. The debt which modern
philosophy owes to the great Danish
thinker was underlined by Mr. René
Maheu, Director-General of Unesco
in his opening address and by inter¬
nationally-known philosophers such
as Jean Paul Sartre, Jean Wahl, Enzo
Pace and Gabriel Marcel who spoke
at these meetings. The work of
Kierkegaard, the centenary of whose
birth was celebrated during 1963,
and Its Impact on contemporary think¬
ing were also evoked during a
series of round table discussions.
Singh was awarded the prize for his scien¬
tific writings, and in particular for those
dealing with fundamental theories of cos¬
mology, relativity and space time and
astrophysics.
PUPPETERS' RENDEZ-VOUS: Twenty
amateur puppet theatre companies
from different countries met in Karl¬
ovy Vary Spa, Czechoslovakia, recent¬
ly for an International Puppet Festival.
Groups from Great Britain, Australia,
Bulgaria, France, Yugoslavia, Hungary, the
Federal Republic of Germany, the Soviet
Union and Czechoslovakia, among others,
gave performances and took part in dis¬
cussions on,the art of the puppeteer during
a four-day festival conference.
PROBING THE BLACK CURRENT':
A new venture in co-operative re¬
search at sea has been launched by the
Intergovernmental Océanographie Commis¬
sion. Meeting at Unesco House in June
the Commission approved plans for the
study of the Kuroshio Current (its name
is Japanese and means "black current")
in the northwest Pacific. Vessels from
six or seven nations will investigate this
current, whose variations are believed to
influence fishing conditions and the weather
in this part of the Pacific.
SMOOTHING TV'S ROAD: Efforts to
pave the way for systematic devel¬
opment of television services in Africa will
be reviewed at a Unesco meeting in Lagos,
Nigeria, in September. Directors of na¬
tional TV and broadcasting organizations
and other specialists will examine the prob¬
lems of organization, technology and
finance which are posed by the launching
of TV in Africa and will discuss how TV
can contribute to social, educational and
cultural development.
rNESCO« MONUMENTS CAM¬
PAIGN: One June 2, Unesco launched
a six-months' international campaign for the
preservation of historical monuments. Hail¬
ing Unesco's campaign as "an outstanding
contribution to the preservation of the
world's cultural legacy," President Johnson
of the U.S.A. pledged his country's
wholehearted support for it.
A TEACHER'S CHARTER: Since 1963
Unesco and the International Labour
Organization have made a joint study of
the status of teachers, a problem that
affects all educational planning. A further
step towards the elaboration of a charter
for teachers was taken recently when an
international committee of specialists, meet¬
ing at Unesco House, drew up recommen¬
dations concerning its scope and content.
These referred to the appointment and
working conditions of teachers, their rela¬
tions with education services and their
rights and duties. The draft charter will
be submitted to an intergovernmental
conference in 1966.
UNESCO PLANS FOR 1965-66:
Unesco's proposed programme for
1965-66 calls for a budget of $47,460,000.
RACE RELATIONS IN AFRICA: For
the first time in Unesco's history,
a specialist in race relations has been sent
into the field at the request of a member
state in this case the United Kingdom. The
specialist chosen is Mr. Kenneth Kirkwood,
since 1955 Rhodes Professor of Race Rela¬
tions at Oxford University, who will occupy
the newly-created chair of race relations at
University College, Salisbury, Southern
Rhodesia. In this post he will study and
do research work into the entire problem
of race relationships in Africa.
PROTECTING CULTURAL PRO¬
PERTY: Measures to prohibit and
prevent illicit export, import and sale of
cultural property have been proposed by
a committee of specialists from 30 countries
which met recently in Unesco House. The
action proposed includes the drawing up of
national inventories of cultural property,
protection measures, international agree¬
ments for the restitution of illegally expor¬
ted objects, and provisions for a bona fide
purchaser of illegally exported property to
obtain damages or compensation. These
recommendations will be presented to
Unesco's General Conference in October.
F/ashes...
On June 8, 1964, Iceland became
Unesco's 115th member state.
The Belgian Government has offered
$13,000 to Unesco for a survey into the
possibility of setting up an institute for
basic research into the life sciences.
The Government of India has asked
Unesco to help establish a Commission to
survey and assess India's entire educational
system.
| Rodolfo Baron Castro, of El Salvador,
was recently elected chairman of the Unesco
Executive Board in place of Mr. C. Edward
Beeby of New Zealand, who has resigned
for health reasons.
g Dr. Linus Pauling of the U.S.A., a dou¬
ble Nobel Prizewinner (chemistry, 1954 and
peace, 1962) recently gave a talk on
"Science Education and Social Responsi¬
bility," at Unesco's H. Q. in Paris.
| Through the intermediary of Unesco, the
International Development Association has
extended a credit equivalent to $4.6 million
to enable Tanganyika to build two sec¬
ondary schools and extend and equip
53 others.
Under an agreement between the
Moroccan Government and Unesco an
administrative training and research centre
for African development will be opened in
Tangiers at the end of this year.
g During recent océanographie research in
the tropical Atlantic, a U.S. Bureau ' of
Fisheries vessel sent its findings direct to
the Océanographie Data Centre in Washing¬
ton via a communications satellite in orbit
over the Brazilian coast.
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
Vacations Abroad
Vacances à l'étranger
Vacacionê» en cl
extranjero
m 1964
unesco
STUDY ABROAD
Vol. XV, 1 964-1 966
648 p. $4- 20/stg - 14 F
Unesco '.~i~SÍ'
VACATIONS ABROAD
Vol. XV, 1 964
175 p. $2- 10/stg. - 7 F
SOME RECENT
UNESCO
PUBLICATIONS
SCREEN EDUCATION
Teaching a critical approach to
cinema and television.
(In the series "Reports and papers
on mass communication")
99 p. $1 - 5/-stg. - 3.50 F
WOMEN
IN THE NEW ASIA
529 p.
$8 - 40/stg - 28 F
(paper)
$1 0 - 50/stg. 35,50 F
(cloth)
THE DEFENCE OF HUMAN RIGHTS
IN LATIN AMERICA
(16th - 18th centuries)
(In the series "Race and Society")
65 p. $0.70 - 3/6 stg. - 2,50 F
HANDBOOK ON THE
INTERNATIONAL
EXCHANGE OF
PUBLICATIONS
(3rd ed. rev.)
767 p.
$7.50 38/6 stg. - 27 F
(paper)
$8.50 42/6 stg. - 31 F
(cloth)
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Prest Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions "Labor",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and arc slides only: Louis De Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). - CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 9). CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. Cyprus National Youth Council, P. O. Box 539,
Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51,
Prague 1 (permanent display); Zahrahnici literatura
Bilkova- 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard,
Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120.
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 540). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*. CCP.
1 2598-48. (7 F.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag,
Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. 8, For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP. 276650(DM 8).-GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol Road, Bellard
Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13;
Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1; 36a, Mount Road,
Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Screet, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2. Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/3).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35. Allenby Road
and 48. Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. (10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.,
6 Tori-Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo
Central, Tokyo. (Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L Bahous
& Co., Dar uI-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd.,
Times House, River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. $ 500).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta. (1 0/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins. Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). - NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff. Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). - NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao.
N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office
20, Molesworth Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1
Government Bookshops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344),
Christchurch (P.O. Box 1721). Dunedin (P.O. Box 1104)
(10/-). NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos (1 0/-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornel, Lille Grense
7 Oslo For the Unesco Courier onlv: A.S. Narvttcns
Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo. Postboks 115
(kr 1 3.20). PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony. Lahore. PHILIPINES.
The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(Zl. 50). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912. Hato Rey. RHODESIA & NYA¬
SALAND. The Book Centre, Gordon Avenue, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. AI Bashlr Bookshop,
P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 1 6.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasa-
gatan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 10); SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Payol, 40, rue du
Marché, Geneva C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 8). TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit. Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop. P.O. Box 145. Kampala. UNION OF SOUTH
AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033.
Johannesburg. (10/-). - UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). Librarie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil,
Cairo. Sub/agent: La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-
Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government
Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Man¬
chester, Birmingham and Bristol. (10/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St,
New York, N.Y. 1 001 6 ($ 5.00) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, New York,
27, N.Y. U-S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, Moscow.
G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
REGULAR COLOUR COMING
In response to the many requests received from
readers all over the world we are happy to announce
that starting with the January 1965 issueThe Unesco
Courier will introduce pages in full colour on a
regular basis. We plan to offer readers 20 full col¬
our pages grouped in four or five issues each year.
To make this innovation possible an adjustment will of
course be necessary in our annual subscription rates and
single copy price. This is further dictated by the fact that
the subscription rate of The Unesco Courier has remained
unchanged for the past six years despite continually
mounting production costs.
On OCTOBER 1, 1964 our new rates will go into effect as follows:
Annual subscription
2 year subscription
Single copy price
15/- (sterling)
27/- (sterling)
1/6d (sterling)
10 French Francs
18 French Francs
1 French Franc
Dollar rates will remain unchanged at $3.00 and 30 cents.
In certain countries of Latin
America, Asia and Africa no,
or only limited, price increases
are envisaged.
SPECIAL OFFER:
If your subscription expires before December 31, 1964, you
can renew for one year at the present lower rates (see inside
back cover) provided you send your renewal cheque or money
order to the sales agent in your country before October 1. New
or gift subscriptions will also be accepted at our current rates
before October 1.
SUBSCRIBE OR RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
TO-DAY AND SAVE. DON'T WAIT.
]]>
</page>
</document>
