<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062404eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
F
^ ^ A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
Courier
JANUARY 1963 (16TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (U.S.) - 0.70 F (FRANCE)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
~~rS
TIMELESS ART OF THE GAULS. This Janus-like head adorn¬
ing a terra-cotta vase discovered in northern France in the
18th century is a remarkable example of ancient Gallic art.
Excavations have brought to light many magnificent works of
sculpture, ceramics, jewels and coins which reveal the great
originality and richness of the ancient civilization of Gaul. © Jean Suquet
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier JANUARY 1963
16TH YEAR
Contents
No. 1
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
French
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
This young African Is one of
many thousands of people
who have fled from their
homes In Rwanda. Most of
these refugees have found
sanctuary In the Kivu Province
of the Republic of the Congo
or In Uganda, Tanganyika
and Burundi. But this African
exodus has created a gigantic
problem of rehabilitation and
resettlement which the United
Nations High Commissioner
for Refugees and other inter¬
national relief groups are
trying to solve. (See p. 14).
UNHCR photo
Page
4 A MUSEUM OF THE ALPHABET
The story of writing as a key to mankind's progress
By David Diringer
10 THE LIBRARY OF THE FUTURE
How automation and electronics will change the world of books
By ]. H. Shera
14 AFRICAN EXODUS
The dramatic problem of 150,000 refugees
By Stanley J. C. Wright
20 A SPUTNIK'S EYE VIEW OF THE EARTH
Space-vehicles take the measure of our planet
By L Samsonenko
24 GLOBES FOR SPACEMEN... AND SCHOOLS
26 UNESCO ART POCKET BOOKS
A new venture in art publishing
27 UNESCO IN RETROSPECT AND PERSPECTIVE
By Jane Albert Hesse
28 THE HIDDEN FACE OF THE CINEMA
Pt. II. The vast machinery of film distribution
By Paul Léglise
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(MC. 42.1.176 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*. France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in Jul/ and August whan
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationery OfMce. P. O. Box 56?, tondon, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors ol THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Uneaco Courier la indexed rnonthly in The Readers' Cuide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 French Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
Ml correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A MUSEUM
OF
THE ALPHABET
by David Diringer
amrrfm rjuEïj rannomPflgBnaiiniltTi
T'*:r"i::t!ïii*ïïïr~",TîniTT!TiIlii^:;mmiin
. i.m'inrfSVrfiii iiiftriin*mKinmn]n:
. ¡iiiim|tii::ii'i;i:,iin:)i:^nBjTn-T:iii"
Kii'iiiaiiiuiM3iJ|rinit][[.::TTiTl!Trr1ur
I'i'jtarllJili'i li;;[l|[1:]|J|,i:[::LiniirL
. i : i 'Tfji . ]. j jj I ' 1 1 ! i ; 1 1 r i [ : ^: ; in i : j [ : [ i T : TT
.i : TlMIIIIII III! IIHI'irr.illB
nmSJt&füi	. 	'"-üjeij i -i
:umniijii:Milii¡ .l!!:iIi:i!ffj:|IJSjL-.
IoTsj]u:MmMi[f1iri[UmnlJ.ríij]!EÍiiH]
pHggfcTini ii'ii '¡i' .ii ni -fiunttsk
Man has used all kinds of methods
and devices for transmission of
thought, images, symbols or arbi¬
trary signs. One symbolic device
was the "wampum" of the North
American Iroquois Indians (left). It
was a sort of broad belt formed by
strings of shells or beads arrang¬
ed in patterns according to the
story to be recorded. The most
convenient and adaptable system of
writing used by man is the alpha¬
bet. Right, an example of one
early alphabetic script, Aramaic.
This Canaanlte-Aramaic Inscription
Is one of the few that have come
down to us from between the 9th
and 7th centuries B.C. Aramaic
had little importance when a chain
of Aramasan sates stretched from
Mesopotamia to western Syria in
the 8th century B.C. The decline
of these states, however, marked
the beginning of Aramaean cultural
and economic supremacy in Western
Asia. Aramaic then became the
"lingua franca" of the Near East.
For more than a thousand years
it was the vernacular of the jews,
and thus of Jesus Christ and the
Apostles. It was probably the origin¬
al language of the Christian Gospels.
Writing Is so much a part and parcel of our
lives today that It Is difficult to imagine a
world in which writing is unknown. Yet for by far the
greater part of his immense past man was without
writing. Nor is it easy to realize in these days of popular
education, that for a great part of the time since its
invention, writing has been the prerogative of a few.
This was still the case in the not-too-distant past when
mankind had already reached a fairly high level of cul¬
ture. In some famous civilizations writing was cultivated
almost exclusively by the priestly classes. So great was
the magical power it exercised over the unlearned, that
this precious possession was regarded as something
beyond man's unaided powers of creation.
Ancient peoples held writing in such awe that its inven¬
tion was frequently attributed to leading divinities. The
ancient Egyptians assigned it to Thoth or Isis; the Baby¬
lonians to Nebo, sun of Marduk, who was also the god
of man's destiny: the ancient Chinese to the dragon-faced
Ts'ang Chien; the ancient Greeks to Hermes and others
of the Olympians; the Romans to Mercury.
The Teuton god Odin or Wotan was credited with the
invention of the Runes; the Celtic god Ogmios with the
invention of the Oghams. The Aztecs attributed their
writing to Quetzalcoatl; the ancient Indians to Brahma.
Even amongst the Jews there was a tradition that con¬
sidered Moses the inventor of the Hebrew script.
The position in more recent times is generally known.
Even in the more advanced countries, up to almost yester¬
day people could not read or write. The assaults of the
"awakening masses" on the ramparts of "privilege" have
been a frequent theme in radical or democratic teaching.
In an elementary sense writing and here need one be
reminded that the power to write includes the power to
readin effect, access to education was a focal point of
privilege.
Briefly, as a key to knowledge and learning, writing was
also a key to social and, in effect, to political power.
Here we are not concerned, even if space allowed, to look
at the vast complex of social, economic and political prob
lems , to which, over some hundreds of years, this posi¬
tion has given rise. The events and movements involved
in the endeavour to solve them, are the stuff of modern
history; nor least important is the shattering French
Revolution with its reverberating cry "Liberty, Equality,
Fraternity."
Much nearer to our immediate concern Is the place of
writing in the general picture. For it is the development
of writing which forms the subject of the Alphabet
Museum in Cambridge, England. As will have been
gathered, the field Is vast. The endeavour has been to
cover all ages and all lands. In fact, the story is broadly
traced in the co-ordinated assembly of material covering
this wide field. The story, however, is more than the story
of writing. It is a story which, it is thought, gives some
insight into the history of man's social and spiritual deve¬
lopment; for writing, especially under the dominion of
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Kfflg>^B^M
PholOS fíO*" "The Alphabet" b/ David Di rincer,
published by Hutchinson, London
the Alphabet, is probably the greatest instrument which
has helped Man in his upward struggle from a more or
less tribal state.
In this broad picture, the Alphabet has a special place.
It is often a matter of great surprise to learn that the
alphabetic system is distinguishable from writing in gene¬
ral. Indeed, for long the two were regarded as one and
the same. The truth is that the Alphabet was invented
long after the dawn of writing roughly about the eight¬
eenth century B.C.
In this article we can but draw attention to one or two
aspects of the Importance of the alphabetic system in the
general history of writing. Its great virtue due to Its
intrinsic phonetic principle is its value in simplifying
writing, reducing the number of symbols or letters to
small compass usually between 25 and 45 letters. So
by lightening in no small degree the task of teaching and
learning in itself an immeasurable gainIt opened more
and more widely the doors of education.
Today, popular education, with all that it means for
the working of a true democracy, Is a tribute to the alpha¬
betic system. Not least of the merits of the system is its
easy adaptability; so that it has, in fact, been adopted
for almost every important language of the world. Even
the Chinese have now officially adopted it.
Thus, we get some inkling of the part played by the
Alphabet over an enormous field. Great thinkers such as
Kant, Mirabeau, Carlyle, reflecting on human progress,
have referred to the invention of writing as the real
beginning of civilization. They were writing in an age
when the fruits of the alphabetic system were already
CONT'D ON NEXT PACE
In the history of writing there
have been various scripts called
Ideographic which are a develop¬
ed form of picture writing.
Some have disappeared but
among those that are still known
is the script used by the Na-khi,
a people who lived an indepen¬
dent existence within the fron¬
tiers of China until the 18th
century. No one knows when
and hew the script originated,
but it is believed to have been
created by tombas or medicine
men. Left, the first page of an
illustrated Na-khl manuscript.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THE ALPHABET (Cont'd)
^!ÖSEISä!&^^ &£tt£&^^
Photos from "The Alphabet" by David Diringer
Writings on the wall
'SQUARE' ALPHABET. Pali is the language in which
the sacred literature ot Buddhism is written. Originally
oral, it began to be put into written form in the 5th
century B.C. The script employed for writing these
books is not easily readable. The letters were painted
with a broad brush and were correspondingly thick.
Above, Pali script from the sacred book "Kammuwa"
widely apparent. In our own day, an American scholar,
H. Breasted, has been even more definite; in his opinion,
writing was of greater Importance in uplifting the human
race than any other intellectual achievement.
ODAY, writing and in this context we include
such secondary forms as printing has entered
into the whole fabric of our civilization. Almost without
our realizing it, it has become an indispensable part of
our whole system. Not only in education, but in scientific
and technological development, In the great and varied
field of government, in all the vast and complicated
mechanism for maintaining and promoting the well-being
of large populations, writing if only in the modest role
of recording plays an all-penetrating, if a strangely
unobtrusive part. Nor should we forget that, in this role,
it provides a basis on which knowledge is built up, giving
it permanence and passing it on, with an assurance of
accuracy, from one generation to the next.
Yet, astonishing though it may seem, the history of
writing is the true Cinderella with learned men and lay¬
man alike. It has escaped formal study in most univer¬
sities and secondary schools; great international founda¬
tions, which assist so worthily in so many directions, are
not concerned with it; no important museum has thought
it necessary to offer a comprehensive exhibition of the
story of writing. Yet, almost every scholarly discipline
touches upon writing at some point, often in matters of
considerable importance,
It forms the basis for two significant branches of
research: epigraphy (dealing with the decipherment and
interpretation of ancient inscriptions) and paliography
(dealing with the decipherment and interpretation of
texts written on soft materials, such as parchment, papy¬
rus, paper, linen, wax). The study of epigraphy has revo¬
lutionized knowledge of the ancient world and has led to
the rediscovery and reconstruction of entire civilizations;
the study of palaeography has been of the greatest prac¬
tical importance for ancient and medieval history, for the
study of philology, for textual criticism, and so on. More¬
over, Egyptology. Assyriology, anthropology and ethnology,
Sinology. Indology, and many other branches of learning
are based on particular sections of the history of writing.
Here we have something of the most far-reaching
importance and yet, somehow, the most elusive. Like sun¬
light and the air we breathe, it is so "common," so
"ordinary," and so well "understood" a thing that often
it is not understood at all. The Alphabet Museum and
Seminar aims to offer, or rather to help in offering, a
corrective.
The Museum was formally opened by Sir James Pitman,
M.A., M.P., on June 8, 1959; it assembles the results of
many years' research by the present writer. The structure
itself is a modest one, built in the rear of his private resi¬
dence in Cambridge. Yet, in my humble judgment, it
provides an archive more comprehensive than any so far
attempted in this field. Indeed, as a "documentary" on
the development of script, it is, I think, unique in the
world.
The large collection includes original inscriptions on
stone and clay, casts of inscriptions, original manuscripts,
photographs of many more, charts and maps, and lantern
slides. The items are drawn from the world over, from
North-East Siberia to Central Africa and Peru, from the
Pacific Islands through Indonesia, India and Central Asia,
through Europe to North America; and the age ranges
from prehistoric times to the present day.
I Ts main interest for the West-European
student will doubtless be the wealth of
material on the development of the Greek and Roman
and related alphabets; for the East-European student,
the abundant material on the development of the Cyrillic
alphabets and their adaptation to dozens of other alpha¬
bets including Finnish, Turkish and Iranian.
For the Far-Eastern student, there is material on the
development of the Chinese, Japanese, Korean, Mongolian
and other scripts. The Indian and Indonesian student
will find much on the development of the numerous
branches of the Indian and Further-Indian scripts.
The Islamic student will find explanations of the origin
and development of the numerous Arabic scripts, the
Jewish and Old Testament student, on the development
of the Early Hebrew and Square Hebrew scripts, and t¿ie
Central African student, on the interesting memory-aid
devices and the adaptation of the Latin alphabet to lan¬
guages far removed in character.
CONT'D ON PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
SIBERIAN GIRL'S LOVE LAMENT aShoswrnan;e"
diagram (left) is a Siberian girl's love lament written in ideographic script (symbols rep¬
resenting ideas) of the Yukaghirs of north-eastern Siberia. "I am alone my home," the
text reads, "You have left and gone far away (to Russia). You love a Russian girl ; you
have married her, but yours is an unhappy marriage notwithstanding your children.
I shall remain sad and will always love you, though there is another man who loves me."
The umbrella-shaped symbols (numbered 1-6) indicate persons. Pointed lines on the top
of 1 and 2, indicate "pig-tails," i.e. women ; '2, wears a skirt wider on the top than No. 1 :
she is a Russian. No. 1 is in a house, shown by lines A-B; the other girl lives far away
(i.e. in Russia), as indicated by the "house" C-D, of which only the roof can be seen.
The man Indicated by No. 3 is the husband of No. 2 (they live under the same roof),
but they are not happily married (as indicated by the cross lines Z-2), though they
have children (5 and 6). Our heroine (No. 1) loves passionately (lines W-Y) the
man No. 3, this love being broken (line V cutting lines W and Y) by the wife of her
beloved ; our girl will continue to love him (line U), although she herself is loved (line S)
by another Yukaghir man. No. 4. Her great sadness is indicated by the cross-lines TT-TT.
SAYINGS OF THE EWE. Right, symbolic
proverbs of the Ewes of West Africa. From
left to right: (1) Two adversaries with bows
and arrows "two enemies cannot hold the
field. (2) Man between the world (repre¬
sented as a nut) and a tree, meaning "the
world is a baobab" world cannot be
bent round, encompassed, changed, trans¬
formed." (3) The Ewe symbol for "I": Man
indicating himself or holding hand on breast.
.... ¿
STRANGE SCRIPTS AND
OLDEST WESTERN ABC. This tablet found
at Marsiliana d'Albenga, Tuscany Italy, is
inscribed with the 26 letters of the early
Etruscan alphabet. It belongs probably to the
end of the 8th or beginning of the 7th century
B.C. and is the oldest Western ABC extant.
THE ALPHABET (Cont'd;
tree with 350 branches
It Is of no small help to see these numerous scripts in
their appropriate places In the general picture of the
development of writing. There is in fact here assembled,
and scientifically arranged, what has been displayed, with
perhaps greater plcturesqueness, in large university halls
and public galleries.
On entering the Museum, a visitor first sees a striking
wall-chart, painted in colourthe "Alphabet Tree." It is
a many-branched tree, dealing with some 350 alphabets
and showing their relationships in the light of up-to-date
research. Some scripts far removed geographically, are
seen In surprisingly close relationship. Green leaves repre¬
sent the many scripts in use today; brown leaves, the
alphabets in effect dead.
Where particular scriptsbecause of their use for
ritual or religious purposes onlyare removed from the
normal competition for survival (although assured of
"life" at least as long as those who revere them endure),
they are represented by leaves partly green and partly
8 brown; in this way are shown the Samaritan and Coptic
scripts. Likewise represented are the Welsh, Irish, Manx
and other scripts only partly used.
An interesting point sometimes, causing great surprise,
is clearly evident from the Chart: all alphabets, however
widely separated geographically, even alphabets long
abandoned, are probably descended from a common
ancestor, the North-Semitic.
In this setting there is an endeavour to show how
writing sprang out of the deep soil of human enterprise
and mutual understanding; and how from the needs of
social intercourse and mystical spiritual expression, the
demands of superstition and magic, and of the higher
religions, not to speak of those of trade and the economic
pressures, there resulted a growth of primitive means of
communication in various parts of the world.
Where the soil was favourable to the seeds of higher
attainment, there developed more advanced systems of
writingthese are symbolized by smaller trees on either
side of the main tree; they are the non-alphabetic
systems (scientifically known as "analytic," but generally
though wrongly called "Ideographic") of the ancient
Egyptians, the Mesopotamlan peoples, the Hittites, the
ancient Cretans, the Chinese, the Mayas, the Aztecs, and
so on.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
NORTH SEMITIC GREEK ETRUSCAN LATIN MODERN CAPS
*
OLDEST LATIN TEXT. Professor David Diringer.
author of our article, holds in his arms the oldest
preserved Latin text: cast of the cippus (or
small column) from the Roman Forum, dating
from the late 7th or the early 6th century B.C.
ANCIENT ALPHABETS
II IHM:ll :ll
l^A A
i r*>ru
raim»it'V>jiti|
|[«ifJlrtlt|
UrZJi^imi=ii=iHi:n ii-ii-ii:ii:itii;M:j
IMML©l®!®l^l®i
viz \V
MIVUI1I
Äira^ixir/iiMr
^
1111117
IL^LIblEIUIJIJLIEII HJl:«;ll;ll:l
w|\a;1vV|WI/
IHKiljiMKIkTIiyjkTIkTILilltlLII
ÍEIfinÜHHHMMHMMl
HOW OUR CAPITALS EVOLVED. The
chart on the right explains how monumen¬
tal characters developed from their North
Semitic forms in the late Second Millennium
B.C. down through Greek, Etruscan and Latin
forms to give us modern capital letters.
ifcjiíáíDirüin
llluatrationi courte«, of Dr. D. Dlringar
The syllabic scripts also claim attention, particularly
those of the Japanese and the ancient Cypriotes. In the
region of the tree-roots are indicated the probable or
possible factors which gave rise to the particular scripts,
or otherwise influenced their development; here, too, are
references to the various theories on the origin of the
Alphabet.
Wall panels show the development of the main writing-
systems and of the individual alphabets. The panels are
supplemented by a great variety of material, including
specimens from manuscripts, photographs of inscriptions,
alphabet-tables, maps and so forth.
In this vast field, one is all too conscious that much
remains to be done and development in fact proceeds as
opportunity offers. This applies. In varying degrees to
almost all the 22 individual sections which, of course,
cover the whole history of writing. Parts of these sections
come within the sphere of "Writing and Art," and the
department dealing with this, as well as one or two other
departments, are being carefully studied with a view to
development
The realization of so large a project of development pre¬
sents formidable difficulties; but the effort seems worth¬
while. In no other field of culture Is the spiritual unity
of Man so clearly manifest. In the early endeavour
where speech could not serve to form a method of com
munication between individuals, in the effort through the
ages to perfect such a method, an effort in which so many
peoples have taken part, Irrespective of age or clime, race,
creed or form of speech, we see at work something more
than a great co-operative principle. There Is something
which forms a basis for mutual respect between peoples.
The Alphabet Museum, It is hoped, helps to make clear
this underlying unity.
The "Seminar," an adjunct of the Museum, is the
meeting-place for discussion of problems concerning the
history of writing, and is open to members of the Univer¬
sity and, Indeed, to scholars everywhere. Facilities for
study and research, including a specialist library, are
being made available.
Professor David Diringer, curator of "The Alphabet
Museum" in Cambridge, England, is a lecturer in the
Department of Oriental Studies at the University of
Cambridge. He is the author of The Alphabet a key to
the history of mankind. First published in 1943 by
Hutchinson's Scientific and Technical Publications, this
work is now being revised by the author in the light of
the most recent scientific discoveries and will shortly
appear in a new edition.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
How many books are published in the
world each year ?
What are the chief vernacular lan¬
guages spoken in Africa ?
I am 15 years old. Which books on
space science should I read?
Who said : " The foundation of every
state is the education of its youth " ?
What will the library of tomorrow look like ? A peek at what
it may be one day was allowed visitors at the ' Library 21"
exhibition at the Seattle World's Fair last year. The chief
keynote was electronics and automation revolutionizing
methods of storing, retrieving and communicating know¬
ledge to future library users. Visitors saw how specially
"programmed" computers (right) can already provide
The machine replies,
up-to-the-minute information on different countries, supply
printed excerpts from the writings of the world's great
novelists, thinkers and scientists, and offer specially "tail¬
ored" bibliographies on subjects ranging from the arts to
space science according to the individual's age, education
and degree of interest. The transparent spheres, below, tell
the story of communication with three-dimensional models
depicting cave painting, the development of writing,
papermaking, printing, the telescope, and other wonders
from among some of the newer media in the field of education.
Pan American
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Woiinn neo vi* Univ., C IcweUrnJ, Olno. U.'j A.
THE LIBRARY OF THE FUTURE
by J. H. Shera
an, In his long struggle up from savagery, has
undergone many experiences and evolved
many Ideas which would be important to our own quest
for a better life If we could but retrieve them from the
past. But, because we do not yet possess efficient means
of access to the store of recorded human knowledge, we
have rediscovered that which was already knownre¬
invented the wheel, many times.
Worse, we have probably re-invented "square wheels,"
without knowing, or even suspecting, that they had long
ago been rejected. A degree of prodigality in research
may be unavoidable, and if properly controlled perhaps
even desirable. But, contrary to popular lore, ignorance is
not characteristic of a state of bliss and what we do not
know can hurt us.
As early as 1937, Frederick P. Keppel, then president
of the Carnegie Corporation of New York, sought an Ima¬
ginary solution to the problem of Improving man's
recourse to the records of the human adventure by pro¬
jecting himself into the library world of 1958, of which
his imaginary librarian said:
"I blush to think how many years we watched the
so-called business machines juggle with pay rolls and
bank books before It occurred to us that they might be
adapted to dealing with library cards with equal dex¬
terity. Indexing has become an entirely new art. The
modern Index is no longer bound up in the volume, but
remains on cards, and the modern version of the old
Hollerith machines will sort out and photograph
anything that the dial tells it. . . we librarians must
keep up with all these applications of science, and
I admit it takes a fair share of our time to do so."
The almost uncanny accuracy of Keppel's prophetic
vision will have been quite apparent to visitors to the
"Library 21" exhibit at last year's World's Fair in Seattle,
Washington, U.S.A. There, on the shores of Puget Sound,
a computer, manned by professional librarians and tech¬
nical assistants provided inquirers with short annotated
bibliographies on selected subjects tailored to the
education, age, and language capability of the indivi
dual patron. The computer was also stored with selected
texts from the "Great Books of the Western World." to
provide the visitor with quotations on appropriate subjects
from the great classical authors.
In reality the Seattle exhibition was far less dramatic
than the real developments that have actually taken
place during the quarter of a century that ha« followed
Keppel's prophetic words. Moreover, the Importance of
these innovations is not to be interpreted solely In terms
of the machine, for automation Is only the outward mani¬
festation of the Intellectual revolution that Is taking place
In llbrarianship today.
The most Important phrase in Keppel's statement does
not relate to the gadgets that he hypothesized, but to the
assertion that "indexing has become an entirely new
art." The bases of that art. Keppel might have added,
are the semantic relationships among ideas, concepts,
and words, and only Incidentally the innovations In elec¬
tronic circuitry.
One should not minimize the Importance of the
machine, for the machine has made a fundamental con¬
tribution in redirecting and refocussing the thinking of
librarians concerning the intellectual processes which the
management and efficient utilization of recorded know¬
ledge involves. But the machine is still an instrument
and nowhere is Its Instrumentality more apparent than
in its role as a library catalyst.
Traditionally, library procedures and methods have
derived from ad hoc assumptions concerning the nature
of books and the ways in which they are used. Such
library classifications as those of Dewey, the Library of
Congress, and the Brussels Institute are based upon the
implicit assumption that books resemble biological speci¬
mens which can be arranged in a hierarchical order of
genus and species according to a major characteristic of
their intellectual content. Similarly, the subject entrieg¬
ln the card catalogue are terms which are assumed to be ..
not only meaningful descriptors of the content of books "
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
THE LIBRARY OF THE FUTURE (Cont'd^
Electronics invades
the world of books
but also the terms which the library user would associate
with the subject of his search.
But because the standard library classifications and the
subject catalogues have worked reasonably well, in some
Instances surprisingly well, librarians did not much con¬
cern themselves with research Into the underlying theory
of Information storage and retrieval until the decade of
the 1950's brought an unexpected proliferation in recorded
knowledge that far surpassed the capabilities of con¬
ventional library and bibliographic instruments.
Simultaneously with these new demands upon the
library came the rise. In other areas of intellectual endea¬
vour, of automation, and librarians turned in hasty
desperation to the machine as a potential source of sal¬
vation. Tw.o early twentieth-century inventions, the Hol¬
lerith punched card and the micro-photograph or micro¬
film, seemed to hold the greatest promise, and much expe¬
rimentation was begun in adapting these, in a variety of
ways, to the storage and retrieval of recorded Informa¬
tion.
Subsequently magnetic tape was added to the arsenal
of the automated library. But despite the engineering
skill lavished upon other devices, results fell far short of
expectations because these mechanisms were not logi¬
cally derived from an understanding of the Intellectual
process that takes place when the library patron searches
a library file.
This charge of failure does not imply condemnation.
Ill-considered as some of these experiments were they
represented a necessary stage In the development of
man's progress in improving library procedures. Every
social innovation must shake itself free from a morass
of misconceptions, false starts, and exaggerated hopes.
Moreover, automation has already proved- Itself, perhaps
in more ways than most people realize, as an effective
means for facilitating certain types of bibliographic and
indexing operations.
The preparation of concordances, which formerly was
regarded as the work of a lifetime, can, through the use
of punched-card or magnetic tape equipment, now be
accomplished in months. A number of libraries are using
similar equipment for the reproduction of catalogues and
specialized bibliographies thus greatly extending the use¬
fulness of their respective collections.
he punched paper tape typewriter, such as the
Flexowriter, with a print-out speed of more
than six hundred pages an hour, offers possibilities for
improving library and bibliographic operations that are
only beginning to be fully realized. The Key Word in
Context (KWIC) system now being used successfully by
Chemical Abstracts Service for the superficial indexing of
chemical literature employs high-speed computers to
facilitate Its operations.
The indexing and abstracting methods devised at
Western Reserve University have been fully automated
and are In dally use in an information retrieval service
offered by the American Society for Metals. And, on a
much less sophisticated level, libraries had, even before
the outbreak of the Second World War, begun to employ
limited automation In their acquisition and other busi¬
ness routines, as well as for the circulation records of
their books.
Today, these limited uses of electronic and mechanical
devices no longer seem strange or out-of-place In the
library, and the time Is doubtless not far distant when
much more Intricate mechanisms for the performance of
much more complex library and bibliographic operations
will be accepted by librarians and general public alike as
standard library equipment. We should remind ourselves
that not so very many decades have passed since the first
library schools, before the typewriter became prevalent,
regularly offered courses in a form of penmanship known
as "the library hand."
In a world transformed by automation what, then, will
be the form of the library of the future? Obviously the
applications of automation to librarianship are so new
BOOKS ARE STILL
BASIC. The "Library
of the Future" (general
view right) designed
by the American Li¬
brary Association, by
no means neglected
books. Books and
other printed materials
will continue to re¬
main basic to all edu¬
cation in the next cen¬
tury. The library was
a prototype of six or
seven core libraries
which will serve vast
areas of America in the
next 100 years. These
libraries will be linked
together so that every
important document,
book and pamphlet
will be available to
every library user no
matter where he lives.
and imperfectly understood that prognostication is dan¬
gerous. One can certainly say conservatively, however,
that these new electronic mechanisms that simulate man's
mental processes should give us new Insights Into the
operations of the human mind and hence a better under¬
standing of the ways in which the human being seeks
out, acquires, and utilizes knowledge.
One also seems on solid ground in saying that machines
are not likely to replace librarians any more than com¬
puters replaced mathematicians. On the contrary, these
new devices will not only provide the librarian with
means for improving the services he can render, but also
will increase his understanding and appreciation of his
role in society.
Finally, one can say with some confidence that the book
is very far from becoming obsolete. To be sure, techni¬
ques for its miniaturization will doubtless become even
more prevalent than they are today, and for purposes of
storage the book in its traditional form does display cer¬
tain marked disadvantages. But for use the book is so
admirably adapted to the ends it serves that man has not
been able to improve upon It since the parchment codex
evolved from the papyrus scroll. The book is here to stay,
and library architecture Is not likely soon to deviate from
a form making possible efficient shelving of books.
To those who are punch-drunk from the impact of
scientific innovation, the library of the future is apt to be
envisaged as a phantasmagoria of flashing lights, spinning
tapes, and rattling teletypes. To be sure, rapid progress
in facsimile transmission, mechanized character recog¬
nition, data processing, and trans-world communication
will doubtless leave their mark upon the library, and one
may properly expect to find In the library of the future
a variety of electronic and other devices that today would
have appeared to many as being out of place.
But the most striking characteristic of the library of
the future will be not so much its physical form, as the
intellectual activity that will take place within its walls,
and this may be traced back at least as far as the great
library established by the Ptolemies in Alexandria at the
mouth of the Nile.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
ValllcWorld'a fj¡r
The library of the future, then, should be a true infor¬
mation centre a collection of graphic records of every
variety, assembled and used to the ultimate limits of Its
resources by a community of scholars educated both In one
of the traditional academic disciplines and in the new
science of librarianshlp and proficient in the scholarship
of their new profession.
This is a new concept of librarianshlp only in its
insistence upon the librarian as scholar and its emphasis
upon the new tools which modern science will provide for
improving the efficiency of his work. But before these
tools can be designed and fabricated, and before tha
Intellectual and functional dimensions of the library of
the future can be identified and described, much important
research into the physical and psychological nature of the
library process must be completed.
Research in libraries has, from the beginning, been one
of the major reasons for the creation of the Institution,
but research in librarianshlp is of such recent origin that
its importance Is not yet fully comprehended even among
librarians. Librarianshlp as the proper subject of orga¬
nized research must have brought to bear upon it the
work of many disciplines in the physical, biological, and
social sciences If it is to be rescued from suffocation by
its very riches.
But however much the profile of the library may
change under the impact of this research, the library as
a service agency will remain, though the concept of that
service may well undergo dramatic alteration In the tran¬
sition from a passive organization to one that reaches out
to the patron without waiting for his initiative.
In this the new media of communication can play a
very Important role, not only In bringing to the patron
the required information in a variety of new forms, but
also in expediting inter-library co-ordination by forging
ever more strongly the bonds of co-operation that will
eventually make available the total intellectual resources
of a nation at any one point of need.
Architecturally, the library of tomorrow must be func¬
tional rather than monumental a form In which change
can be made quickly and economically In anticipation of
rapid obsolescence. We do not build for the future by
architecturally crystallizing or ossifying the present;
change is the only constant. When the responsibilities of
the librarian were regarded as primarily custodial, and
preservation was generally accepted as hLs first concern,
the library as mausoleum was archltectually appropriate.
With the twentieth century came a new and more
dynamic concept of library service. The library as a gothlc
cathedral expired with James Gamble Rogers' great ana¬
chronistic outcry at Yale. The new functionallsm dic¬
tates modular constructionan empty shell with a mini¬
mum of bearing walls and fixed partitions. In fact, the
library of the future may not be a single building, but a
complex of Interrelated structures which provide not
only for the acquisition, utilization, and dissemination of
traditional library materials, but also are true "Informa¬
tion banks," dedicated to the fullest possible use of
recorded human knowledge In whatever form. Already
Johns Hopkins University is planning a new library
building that will Include a computing center for mecha¬
nized literature searching.
There is no limit to the potentialities of the library of
tomorrow except the boundaries of the human imagina¬
tion and our willingness to work. No longer Is the library
a social embellishment for the perpetuation of local or
personal prestige. It is essential to the survival of
society for the simple and obvious reason that our culture
has become so complex and Interdependent within and
among its constituent parts that It cannot survive without
constant intellectual nourishment.
Knowledge, then, is the life-blood oí our civilization, and
the library of the future may well be regarded as the
instrument by which its continuing circulation of know¬
ledge Is maintained. What goes on, then, in the library
of the future may or may not be outwardly spectacular
but It will probably Influence substantially the course of
the human adventure.
Dr. Jesse H. Shera is Dean of the School of Library
Science at Western Reserve University, Cleveland, U.S.A.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
- . ' 'é *<
K'Av*
THE DRAMATIC PROBLEM
OF 150,000 REFUGEES
By
Stanley
J. C. Wright
PEOPLE WHO WAIT.
Like many thousands of
their fellow people from
Rwanda, this mother and
her son (left) have found
sanctuary, but the sadness
in their eyes tells of a home
lost perhaps forever and
doubts about the future.
Right, other refugees
climb into a truck sent
by the League of Red Cross
Societies which will take
them to one of the four
resettlement centres in the
Kivu Province of the Con-
So far over 21,000
refugees have been taken
care of in these centres.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
AFRICAN EXODUS
During recent years, the
Office of the United Na¬
tions High Commissioner
for Refugees (UNHCR) and
the League of Red Cross, Red
Crescent, Red Lion and Sun
Societies have been carrying
out a number of joint opera¬
tions. From 1957 onwards
they gave relief and main¬
tenance to the Algerian re¬
fugees in Morocco and Tuni¬
sia, an operation which ended
with a repatriation move¬
ment to which both organiza¬
tions lent active assistance.
Elsewhere in Africa, in Togo,
UNHCR and the League
joined in giving relief to a
small group of exiles needing
reestablishment. In the Congo
(Leopoldville) an operation
was undertaken in 1961 to
help over 100,000 refugees
from Angola who could be
settled locally. At present,
UNHCR and the League are
trying to solve the problem
of the refugees from Rwanda
in the Kivu Province. Parallel
to this action, UNHCR has
been taking an interest in the
Rwanda refugee situation in
Uganda, Tanganyika and Bu¬
rundi. (On July I, 1962, the
Trusteeship territory, Ruan-
da-Urundi, administered by
the Belgian Government until
June 30, 1962, became inde¬
pendent as two sovereign
statesRwanda and Burundi).
In all these undertakings, the
two organizations plan and
work together at all levels.
The League relies on support
from its national societies and
accepts the responsibility for
storing and distributing relief
and, in some cases, the co¬
ordination of activities in the
field. UNHCR for its part
maintains liaison with govern¬
ments, seeks funds for pro¬
jects from governmental and
private sources, and delegates
"Chargés de Mission" who
work in close co-operation
with League operational per¬
sonnel in the areas concerned.
Both organizations are of a
non-political and a purely
humanitarian character.
band of perhaps a hundred people have
gathered in the shadows of a cluster of banana
trees. They are sitting quietly on the ground by a
primitive sandy track, waiting. Among the tall men and
women are several almost too ill to move, their bodies
emaciated by starvation and disease. Many babies and
children are frighteningly thin with swollen bellies. They
are refugees from Rwanda, who have come to the Kivu
Province of the Congo.
But soon the ordeal of these "waiting people" Is over.
Three-ton trucks painted with the emblems of UNHCR and
the League of Red Cross Societies pick them up and,
after a five to ten hours' journey over primitive tracks,
bring them to one of the four resettlement centres in the
Kivu.. There they find medical aid and food. Later they
will be given the means to start a new life.
The exodus of Rwanda refugees began when political
unrest led to violence between the two major tribesthe
Batutsi and the Bahutu. The Batutsi, a tall, handsome
people, came to Rwanda some six hundred years ago,
probably from far away Ethiopia. Although forming even
today not more than sixteen per cent of the population,
these shepherd warriors subjected the local tribes of the
Bahutu and set up a feudal society both In Rwanda and
Burundi under separate kings called Mwami. During this
century, under the impact of education and, later, of the
movement towards Independence, the social structure in
both countries underwent certain changes.
In Rwanda, where the segregation of the two peoples
was maintained over a longer time than in Burundi, the
Batutsi. as the ruling class, came to be identified with the
more traditional and conservative form of government.
When the king was deposed in January 1901 and Rwanda
became a republic, political clashes led to tribal violence.
Hundreds of people were killed, villages burned and crops
and cattle destroyed.
An exodus began which culminated in a tragic flight
of over a hundred thousand Rwandcse. By September
1962 it was estimated that 150,000 refugees had found
shelter in the countries bordering on Rwanda: 00,000 in
the Kivu Province of the Congo, 40,000 in Burundi, 35,000
in Uganda and 15,000 in Tanganyika.
Some of these refugees, particularly those in Uganda,
brought with them their anlmaLs, the long-horned cattle
so reminiscent of the oxen on Egyptian bas reliefs. The
overwhelming majority, however, found themselves
destitute, without means of livelihood.
At the time of this exodus, Rwanda and Burundi were
passing through one of the periods of famine characteristic
of the area. The administration had distributed the
existing reserves to those refugees who had earlier sought
protection near the Catholic missions inside both
countries. This meant that the fleeing populations were
weakened and open to disease.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
AFRICAN EXODUS (Cont'd)
m
UNHCR photos
FLIGHT for over
100,000 refugees from
Rwanda began in Novem¬
ber 1961. Some, parti¬
cularly those who reached
Uganda, managed to bring
with them their animals
(left) long-horned cattle
reminiscent of the oxen
on Egyptian bas-reliefs.
But the immense majority
found themselves desti¬
tute, without any means of
livelihood. Right, at the
Kalonge reception camp in
the Kivu Province, re¬
fugees queue up for manioc,
beans and palm oil.
'We are ready to learn and work'
The Kivu also was passing through a difficult phase as
a result of the administrative dislocation in the Congo.
Access to the large Ruzizi Valley, for instance, was barred
by rebel soldiers, thousands of refugees found themselves
in unhealthy marshland cut off from every form of help.
The Batutsi used to live in the mountains; they were not
used to the heat, nor the unhealthy conditions in the
lowlands. They were therefore particularly vulnerable to
malaria. No statistics exist regarding the death rate but
starvation, intestinal diseases caused by polluted water,
malaria and scabies took a very heavy toll.
When in March 1962 a joint fact-finding commission
(UNHCR, the League of Red Cross Societies, UNICEF and
UNOC) succeeded in reaching this area they reported
"the general health situation (among the refugees in
Kivu) to be bad and very bad, with the exception of areas
south (the Ruzizi Valley) where the situation must be
considered catastrophic."
Indeed, in one of the villages visited by the fact-finding
mission a family of eight was completely wiped out In the
course of a fortnight. Said Dr. Volgtberger of WHO in a
report to Geneva, "the refugees have become a reservoir
of Infectious diseases that threatens the entire region."
The situation, although extremely precarious, was not so
tragic everywhere. The refugees who had gone further
inland and reached the Masisi territory had found
temporary work and help from the settlers who had
migrated in earlier years under plans to alleviate the over¬
population problem in Rwanda. These settlers, though
Bahutu, received the Batutsi In their midst and allowed
them to work on their land. Those who had stayed in
Goma, Bukavu and Uvira, the three main Kivu towns near
the border, received occasional assistance. Others in rural
areas found work on local farms and plantations, but even
among them there was occasional famine.
When the UNHCR "Chargé de Mission" in the Congo
visited the Kivu in December 1961, there was not only
an urgent need for relief but also for action which would
give the refugees a possibility to move away from the
unhealthy areas and to resume life in more normal
conditions.
At the request of UNHCR, sixteen tons of food and
three thousand pounds of medical supplies were flown in
by UNOC planes from Leopoldville. Forty-five tons of food
were shipped by river to Stanleyville and carried by UNOC
trucks along the one-thousand kilometre tracks to Goma
(the distance from Geneva to Rome).
The Oxford Committee for Famine Relief in the United
Kingdom made £10,000 available to the Norwegian Pro-
'" testant Mission in Bukavu so that food supplies could be
bought locally, and later sent another £10,000 to the
ïC2
Swedish Protestant Mission in the
same town. The Swedish Mission in
Rwanda sent four tons of food to
Goma when the supplies of the
Catholic Mission there ran out.
Eighty tons of milk from the United
States' surplus food were carried by
UNOC trucks from Usumbura' in
Burundi to the Kivu Province.
In the meantime, the League of
Red Cross Societies had agreed to a
joint action with UNHCR. A plan
was drafted to create resettlement
areas in the mountainous areas of
the Kivu and, with the full approval
of the Prime Minster of the Province,
Mr. Miruho. It was put into opera¬
tion almost overnight.
Under the Belgian Administration,
several attempts had been made to
establish Rwanda farmers in the
highlands. An organization, the MJP (Mission d'Installa¬
tion des Populations), had been created which for several
years had been entirely in the hands of Congolese officials.
On its own initiative it had begun to help refugee families
by assisting with their establishment in Northern Kivu,
but their efforts had been hampered by lack of food.
On the strength of this experience, it was decided to
create four resettlement centres in Iuhula, with the help
of the White Fathers; in Bibwe with the MB?; in Kalonge
with the Norwegian Misson, and in Lemera with the
Swedish Mission. These centres were all situated in thinly
populated areas where the implantation of refugees is
unlikely to cause any social, economic or political distur¬
bances in the future and where the land offers excellent
prospects for agriculture.
It is actually wrong to speak of "centres." Bibwe, for
instance, which has already received more than 5,000
people, Is now composed of six villages and more will be
created as the number of refugees increases. Each family
has received four hectares of land and there is enough
virgin forest around to carve out a four-hundred hectare
tea plantation which is one of the projects of the
programme.
Practically every day one or more lorries bought with
UNHCR funds by the League of Red Cross Societies picks
up groups of refugees in Goma or from the border areas.
Every day also refugee families arrive on foot, some having
walked over a hundred miles.
Upon arrival they are registered and given temporary
shelter in communal accommodation until they' can build
their own huts (which takes about two weeks). They
tf
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
w
unsntrs r*^4^
Pt^/JW
receive an average of three kilos of food per person per
week (manioc, beans and palm oil). Each family Is allotted
a machete, a hoe and some seeds for immediate planting.
A beginning has been made with community develop¬
ment plans: the creation of a tea plantation, the establish¬
ment of a saw mill, the setting up of a community store
where the refugees will eventually be able to buy essentials
(seeds, tools, fertilizers, etc.), and the organization of the
sale of handicrafts which will help to maintain the 130
widows and their children who have come to Bibwe.
There is a heartening spirit of pioneering among
the refugees. Several students who studied In Europe
or who were in technical schools in the Congo when
events in Rwanda prevented their return, have come to
Bibwe to settle provisionally. It is they who have built
the huts for the widows, the two schools and a mission
house. Several are acting as unpaid teachers to the
350 children of school age.
Right now activities are concentrated on planting
manioc, sorgo, maize, potatoes, sweet potatoes and beans
the staple diet of the population. By early 1963, the
refugees, if all goes well, ought to be completely self-
supporting. In two years' time, thanks to the community
plans, the standard of life In the new villages will rise
above subsistence level and allow for further development.
Many of the refugees are, in fact, looking ahead with
quiet hope to better times. They want to build houses of
stone, give their children a chance to learn better methods
of agriculture, raise the standard of health. "There Is
no reason why we should not do as well as the planters
around here," says Brother Alphonse, a Catholic monk.
himself a refugee. "It may take time, but our people arc
ready to learn and work."
The part taken by the Congolese and the refugec-.s
themselves Is indeed one of the important aspects of the
resettlement of the refugees in the Kivu Province. They
are actively associated with the drafting of plans, work
out all the administrative details, and are fully responsible
for the execution of the projects. To them, the presence
of UNHCR. Red Cross League and UNOC officers is a
guarantee of continued support and friendly help.
So far, the contribution of the International community
to the Kivu operation has been comparatively modest,
even if without it the operation could not have been
undertaken with any chance of success. UNHCR has
already contributed $70,000. UNOC, .$50,000, UNICEF
$24,000, the Oxford Committee for Famine Relief $50,000,
the League of Red Cross Societies $25,000, to which must
be added United States' surplus food, and private dona¬
tions. At least $65,000 more will be required to complete
the operation. The League has two officers In the areas, a
Swiss and a Dane.
So far, over 21,000 refugees have been resettled In the
four centres. Their number may rise in the next few
months to 40,000, possibly even more. Within less than a
year they will have travelled the road from starvation to
plenty, a short road Indeed, thanks to their own energies,
the understanding and active assistance of the local chiefs,
and support given by the international community.
Stanley J. C. Wright is Chief of the Information Section, Office
of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, Geneva.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Leaving fear and famine behind them, refu¬
gees from northern Rwanda set off on the
road to a new life. One group (left) climbs
aboard a Red Cross truck which will take
it to the Bibwe reception camp in the
Kivu Province of the Congo. Below, a small
girl, wearing a makeshift dress cut from a
food sack, patiently waits her turn. A few
hours later, greeted by shouts and waves
of welcome (below left) the group arrives
at the camp of the Reinstallation Mission.
The refugees are determined to build them¬
selves a new life and become self-support¬
ing. At the weekly food distribution (below,
centre) the men select the best beans for
planting. As the framework of a new home
takes shape (below right) hopes rise and
smiles broaden. After work is over there
is time to enjoy traditional festivals and
dances (right). The land is good. New
crops will soon raise their heads. Life once
again begins to take on a real meaning.
k TK
ON THE ROAD...
-w
TO A NEW LIFE
18
im 11/ n 'Li i.mir. kulTbjli,
. CHEF »A CIIA.VTiri! ADA
IMBWA IIT/AMA
'/->iv san
'
a j»
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
A SPUTNIK'S EYE VIEW
APOGEE
it»
"Man pierces the ce¬
lestial vault and ex¬
plores the spheres".
Today, this prophetic
16th-century woodcut
(right) by an unknown
engraver has become
fact. With the help of
artificial satellites
launched into orbit
around the earth man
has "taken the mea¬
sure" of his planet.
Other, more far-rang¬
ing "cosmic laborator¬
ies" have begun "the
exploration of the
spheres". Diagram on
left shows (schema¬
tically) the changing
path of a man-made
satellite observed at
the perigee (nearest
point) and at the apo¬
gee (point farthest
away from our planet).
\\ \ \\ V
" OF THE CIRCUMFERENCE
^T- ' \ '
Y' \ ,' ' ..' .* '
.* /'' \ . '
£a\\¥ 1 ~Ä1&'',i§S^/V'^«S>MBE21 0F ,HE CIRCUMFEI!ENI:E
^m . . Tv " l,',\r..'' V V *
,'"'' -"'' ' >- Jr^'V'-V: "*
>_>.;- '; . t* ? ISv \ ' ?
- .' * í 0S V' , *» ..
H ' :ik:: m "' yjKíLiW KWB CENTRE OF THE EARTH Sgl
- :.jSBB . ': -'::"\^'r-v-i. *;V *"!.
Unesco
ERATOSTHENES' WELLS. Twenty-five centuries ago,
Eratosthenes, poet, philosopher and astronomer, in¬
geniously calculated the earth's dimensions. As dia¬
gram shows, he observed that while the sun's rays
shone vertically into a well at Syene in southern
ESypt (at midsummer noon) their angle from the
vertical at Alexandria corresponded to 1 SO of the
circumference of a circle. His calculation of the dis¬
tance between the two towns as 1 SOth of the earth's
circumference gave him a total distance of about 24,700
miles (best modern measurement is 24,860 miles).
When asked what shape the Earth is we usually
say without thinking that it is a sphere. But
how many of us could give proof that this is really so?
Probably only the spacemen who have flown round the
Earth at a height of several hundred kilometres have a
real visual perception of the sphericity of our planet.
The circular border of the Earth's shadow as it moves
across the moon's disc during an eclipse, and the gradual
rise of a moving ship as it approaches the observer, gave
the ancient Greeks, with their keen, penetrating minds,
the idea that the Earth on which they lived was like a
ball. All those proofs of the roundness of the Earth that
a teacher recounts nowadays to ten-year-old schoolchil¬
dren were recorded by Aristotle about 2,500 years ago.
Eratosthenes, curator of the famous Alexandrian libra¬
ry, poet, philosopher and astronomer, who lived about the
same time as Aristotle, based his calculations on the
dimensions of the Earth on the assumption that it Is a
spherical body. His method was simple but bore all the
hallmarks of genius.
He had observed at Syene (Southern Egypt) that the
sun at midsummer noon was directly overhead so that It
shone on the water of the deepest well. When the sun
was observed at the same moment from Alexandria, where
Eratosthenes lived, its angle from the vertical corres¬
ponded to one-fiftieth of the circumference of a circle.
Lines drawn from Syene and Alexandria to the centre
of the Earth would enclose the same angle; therefore,
reasoned Eratosthenes, the distance from Syene to Alexan¬
dria must be one-fiftieth of the Earth's circumference.
This gave him a figure of approximately 24,700 miles as
the Earth's circumference (the best modern measurement
is 24,860 miles) and Eratosthenes lived twenty-five cen¬
turies ago!
Is the Earth a true sphere in shape? Before we can
answer this question we must decide exactly what we
mean by shape. There are plains, plateaux, deep hollows
and high mountains on the Earth's surface. But It is the
relatively uniform surface of the ocean, covering as it
does three-quarters of our planet, that represents more
exactly the real shape of the Earth. It is not very diffi¬
cult to transfer this concept to dry land ; in fact it is done
when we speak of heights being so many feet above sea
level.
Sir Isaac Newton, who lived over three hundred years
ago, knew that the Earth could not be a true sphere.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Fron "Le Soleil" published by Arthaud, for the Federation d'-s Cooperatives Mijros. Zurich. 1961
This was the proof he offered: let us imagine two wells
sunk from the surface of the Earth to its centre, one at a
Pole and the other on the Equator. If the Earth did not
rotate the water would be at the same level (reckoned
from the centre of the Earth) in both wells.
Because the Earth does rotate, the water in the equa¬
torial well would rise, under the influence of centrifugal
force, until the pressure of the additional column of
water compensated weight lost by centrifugal action.
The same thing must actually happen to the water In
the seas and also to the body of the planet itself, since
there are no absolutely rigid bodies In nature; this means
that the Earth must be slightly flattened at the poles and
bulge a little at the Equator, its shape resembling that of
a tangerine or a pumpkin.
The measurements made by eighteenth century French
scholars proved the accuracy of Newton's theory; working
at the Equator and beyond the Arctic Circle they found
that the meridian is 40,009 kilometres in length and the
Equator 40,075 kilometres; the polar and equatorial radii
differ by 21 kilometres. Newton computed the amount of
flattening of the Earth (the ratio of the difference bet¬
ween the equatorial and the polar radii to the equatorial
radius) to be 1/230. Huyghens, a Dutch scholar living at
about the same time, made the same calculation and
arrived at the figure of 1/530.
One may well imagine the consternation of the learned
world when this big difference was made known. It was
soon discovered, however, that the two scholars had based
their calculations on different assumptions. Newton had
assumed that the Earth's density is uniform throughout
and does not change with depth, whereas Huyghens had
assumed that the Earth's gravitational pull Indicates that
Its mass Is concentrated mainly in the centre, i.e., that
density rapidly Increases with depth.
Later measurements showed that the actual difference
in the length of the radii is about 1 unit in 300 so that
Newton was closer to the truth than Huyghens; the den¬
sity of the Earth does increase with depth but not as
greatly as Huyghens assumed. From this Jt- follows that
accurate measurements of the Earth's dimensions can
help us understand something of what Is inside It, thou¬
sands of kilometres below the surface.
It has now been demonstrated that the simplest and
most accurate measurements of the shape of Earth may
be made by observations of artificial earth satellites.
Man-made satellites circle the Earth In elliptical orbits,
so that the distan«; from the Earth to the satellite is
constantly changing. If the Earth were a true sphere the
satellite would pass through the same points at its apo¬
gee and perigee in each orbit (relative of course to the
fixed stars).
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
SPUTNIK'S VIEW (Cont'd)
Space-vehicles help to measure our planet
To put it another way, If, say, the perigee of the vehicle
were visible from the Earth in line with a certain fixed
star, the direction would be the same for each orbit. If,
however, the Earth is an oblate spheroid and not a true
sphere, this would not be strictly true.
Actually the perigee of a vehicle orbiting round the
Earth changes with each orbit and gradually moves
round the Earth; the amount of the shift for each orbit
depends firstly on the flattening at the poles, the greater
the flattening the greater the shift, and secondly on the
angle between the plane of the vehicle's orbit and the
plane of the terrestrial Equator (the smaller the angle the
22
Unesco
ISAAC NEWTON'S WELLS. In the 18th century,
Sir Isaac Newton declared that the earth could not be a
true sphere. To support his theory he imagined two
wells sunk from the North Pole and the Equator to
the centre of the Earth. If the Earth did not rotate, he
said, the water would be the same level in both wells.
But because of the earth's rotation, water in the equa¬
torial well would rise under the influence of centrifugal
force. The same must happen to the water in the seas and
the body of the planet. Thus the Earth must be slightly
flattened at the poles and bulge a little at the Equator.
greater the shift). The movement of the vehicle's perigee
(or apogee) around the Earth, therefore, enables mathe¬
maticians to determine the exact shape of the Earth.
When the vehicle is in flight the position of its perigee
among the stars is noted; on each successive orbit the
position is again noted and the difference in position,
between successive orbits gives us the angle of displace¬
ment of the perigee. Knowing this displacement, the ave¬
rage distance of the vehicle from the Earth's centre, the
time taken for one orbit and the declination of the orbi¬
tal plane from the Earth's equatorial plane, an astrono¬
mer can calculate the oblateness of the Earth by the use
of ready-made formulae.
In practice, of course, the position and dimensions of
the orbit are much more difficult to calculate because
they are affected by the resistance of the terrestrial
atmosphere in a complicated manner that is not yet fully
understood. The usual method is to strike an average for
a large number of orbits.
It is important to observe the sputnik's perigee and the
displacement of it from as many points on Earth as possi¬
ble; this requires the co-operation of many countries and
all continents.
In the twenties of this century the American scholar,
John Hayford, spent some years analyzing geodesic data
that had been accumulated over dozens of years and
found the difference in the polar and equatorial radii to
be 1 unit in 297. In 1940 a large group of Soviet geodesists
headed by F. Krasovsky completed their many years of
work on the same problem and arrived at the figure of
1 in 298.3. A few months' observation of Soviet Sputnik II
and American Vanguard I produced the figure of 1 in
298.2, and the data was analyzed within a few weeks.
Observations of artificial earth satellites are made by
over one hundred stations in the Soviet Union; positions
of the vehicles in space are recorded by means of visual
observation and by photographs taken with specially de¬
signed precision cameras. These observations have pro¬
vided further information on the peculiarities of the
Earth's shape.
We now know that the Earth is not a simple
oblate spheroid. It is made like the figure
known in geometry as a triaxial ellipsoid, that can be
obtained by squeezing the sides of an oblate ellipsoid.
The Earth's Equator is not a true circle, it is slightly
flattened on two sides and has its greatest diameter
approximately on the meridian of Prague. True enough,
the difference is very slight not more than 200 metres.
By careful observation of the displacement of the peri-
. gee of a "Sputnik's" orbit, scientists have discovered that
the northern hemisphere is "higher" than the southern,
the distance from the centre of the Earth to the North
Pole being between 30 and 60 metres greater than from
the centre to the South Pole.
This is only the beginning of the space age. Artificial
satellites have been used for less than five years, but the
observations have produced some outstanding discoveries.
The study of the Earth with the aid of small satellites
has a tremendous future. If we know exactly how a
"Sputnik" is moving and measure its position simultan¬
eously from two points on the ground, we can measure
the distance between those points accurately.
By locating observation posts in different continents and
repeating the measurements over a number of years we
can decide whether the continents are movingare the
positions of Eurasia, America, Africa and Australia fixed,
relative to the Earth's centre, or do they drift about?
Changes in the character of an artificial satellite's orbit
described above (the motion of the perigee) are caused
by the greater concentration of mass in the vicinity of
the Equator and the slight flattening; this excess of mass
(in relation to the main mass of the Earth) helps to pull
the satellite out of a "regular elliptical orbit".
It follows that the path of a satellite will change with
every change in the Earth's gravitational pull so that the
motion of a satellite over a mountainous area must be
different from its motion over seas, because the mountains
are composed of material that is denser than water and
effect a greater pull on the satellite.
The satellite, furthermore, will "feel" big deposits of
some extra heavy or extra light substances burled deep
below the Earth's surface because of the difference In gra¬
vitational pull and will change its course accordingly.
Thus we see what great prospects for the study of the
Earth's interior are opened up by the observation of even
tiny man-made moons In flight.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
*
. W *
» » -/
« r H*»P
$
SPUTNIK TRAIL INTO SPACE. Soviet
rocket carrying the world's first arti¬
ficial satellite on October 4, 1957,
soars aloft, its path marked by a lu¬
minous trail in the night sky. Since
the first "Sputnik" went into orbit,
the flight of space vehicles has been
plotted by technicians and scientists
on tracking boards resembling huge
cobwebs (right). Observations of and
from these vehicles have given man
new information on the peculiarities
of the earth's shape and shed new
light on the composition of its interior.
Official Soviet photo
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
All photos © Three Lions, New York
24
GRAPEFRUIT-SIZED GLOBE in centre of photo
above is part of a dual plastic model of the earth and the
heavens. A transparent globe of the earth is placed inside a
larger sphere on which the sun, the planets and the stars
are indicated. A globe of the earth similar to inner
one shown here, has been used in U.S. space capsules.
FLAT EARTH. Like a flash-back to an old historical
belief, the earth is flat on this plastic sheet (left) but it
will be heated, then inflated with air to achieve the
rounded contours of our planet (above). These large
globes for schools are painstakingly made by hand.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
GLOBES FOR SPACEMEN... AND SCHOOLS
As he hurtles round the earth in his space capsule, a U.S. astronaut has gauged his
approximate position at a glance by looking into a box. Inside the box is a grape¬
fruit-sized plastic globe which the spaceman sees through a window marked with a
black dot. The globe automatically turns on its axis like the earth. The position of the
black dot indicates the position of the space vehicle in relation to the earth. This is
one space-age use found for the plastic worlds created by an American from Philadel¬
phia, Robert Farquhar. In addition to his space globes, Farquhar and a team of five
men also produce plastic model worlds for schools and government agencies. These
globes are larger than those built for space capsules. Farquhar also produces a novel
type of transparent globe within a globe showing the earth and the stars (left).
NORTH MEETS
SOUTH as the globe-
maker fits together
the two sections of
a three-foot globe.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A new venture
in art publishing
UNESCO ART
POCKET BOOKS
A Frenchman writes on
UNESCO
IN RETROSPECT
AND PERSPECTIVE
by Jane Albert Hesse
Anew international and multilingual publishing
venture by Unesco has made its mark in
the field of art book production. Collabo¬
rating with publishers in eight countries Unesco has
launched a series of art books in pocket form.
The striking fact about this new collection, in which
four volumes have already appeared, is that it pre¬
sents colour reproductions of great works of art of
a high quality normally only found in expensive art
books, in a pocket-sized format at well within the
normal level of pocket book prices which are usually
around 5/- or less than $1.00. This has been made
possible by the scale of the enterprise and the
co-operative arrangements between Unesco and
publishers in Britain, the United States, France, the
German Federal Republic, Italy, Mexico, the Nether¬
lands and Spain.
EACH Unesco Art Pocket Book contains 28
plates of colour reproductions, additional illus¬
trations in black and white and an introductory
text by an international scholar in which the histor¬
ical background and an analysis of the works it
covers are presented in a simple, straightforward
way for the man in the street.
In "Egyptian Wall Paintings from Tombs and
Temples", Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt, Cura¬
tor of the Department of Egyptian Antiquities at the
Louvre in Paris, discusses the delicate frescoes
painted some 3,000 years ago in the tombs and
temples of the Nile Valley. "Persian Miniatures
from Ancient Manuscripts" is introduced by Basil
Gray and presents some of the great art treasures
of the world in the form of miniatures now preserved
in the Gulistan Palace of Teheran.
THE third book, "Spanish Frescoes of the Roma¬
nesque Period", introduced by Juan Ainaud,
opens the door to a brilliant and little-known
period of European art. Lastly, "Russian Icons from
the 12th to the 15th Century", with its colour plates
and an introduction by Victor Lazareff, presents a
vivid overall picture of the different schools of
Russian icon paintings.
More titles are to be added to the series which
has so far appeared in English, Spanish, French,
Italian, German and Dutch language editions. By
this multilingual approach and the fact that these
books will be on sale in every kind of bookshop
and bookstall, in railway stations and large stores,
Unesco's aim to bring fine quality colour reproduc¬
tions of world art masterpieces within reach of a
wide public will have been achieved.
The success of Unesco's earlier initiative in art
publishing its handsome World Art Series albums
promises to be repeated by its new Art Pocket
Books. (See page 35 for further details.)
I t may seem surprising that Unesco is still an
unknown organization to certain people. Is
it not an international organization which has been in
existence for 16 years, the co-operative enterprise of 113
countries which has been reported and commented on by
the world press ? Its headquarters are in the centre of
one of the world's great capitals In a strikingly-designed
building of concrete and glass a new sightseeing at¬
traction for the visitor to Paris, but primarily the labor¬
atory of a new 20th- century humanism.
Educators, scientists, artists and specialists of all kinds
follow Unesco's work either by participating directly or
through reading the books, periodicals and the studies
which it publishes. But other people, the vast majority,
in fact, only hear of Unesco through the necessarily brief
and fragmentary reports that appear in the press. Some,
in fact, think of Unesco either as an institute for study
and research or a body with humanitarian aims on the
lines of the International Red Cross.
Though comprehensive studies on Unesco have appeared
in some countries, in France. Unesco's adopted home, no
exhaustive work on how it came into being and what it
has since achieved had ever been published until recently.
This gap has now been filled.
A remarkable book published by the famous French pub¬
lishing house, Gallimard, * recounts the Unesco story
telling of its aims and problems, its failures and succes¬
ses. The book has set out to dissipate widespread igno¬
rance and misunderstanding regarding Unesco, yet even
the reader well-aquainted with Unesco will find revealing
facts and information in its pages. Bearing the simple
sitie, "Unesco", the book was written by a Frenchman,
Tean Thomas, who knows Unesco well. He served Unesco
from 1947 to 1960, first as head of its Cultural Activities
Department and later as Deputy Director-General. He
shows how the name "Unesco" United Nations Educa¬
tional, Scientific and Cultural Organization embodies
both the historical reasons for the creation of this U. N.
Specialized Agency after the Second World War, and why,
face to face with the urgent needs of a swiftly-changing
world, it has had to choose between one road and another
at various periods of its life.
u
26
nesco was born in London in November 1945,
when representatives of 45 countries met to
found a new organization dedicated to education, science
and culture. The atmosphere of this period was
influenced by the many still-unhealed wounds and the
resolve of nations to "erase from men's minds the seeds
of fanaticism and hatred." There was thus a need, as
Miss Ellen Wilkinson, Britain's Minister of Education, said
at the time, for an association of states which would
make education one of Its main fields of action, but not
its sole objective.
Unesco's forerunner, the International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation, established in 1926 by the
League of Nations had been conceived on very different
linesas an "association of minds", to recall the words of
Paul Valéry. In the case of Unesco, the greatest emphasis
was on education and the Agency was founded, to quote
its own Constitution, "for the purpose of advancing,
through the educational and scientific and cultural
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Henry Moore
relations of the peoples of the world, the objectives of
international peace and of the common welfare of
mankind."
The rapidly changing situation of the postwar world
and the emergence of so many former colonies and trust
territories as independent nations soon made it clear
which were priority tasks. Even before political develop¬
ments sparked these changes, the economically-developed
countries had stated clearly and unequivocally the degree
of responsibility they felt towards their less fortunate
neighbours.
H ow can Unesco carry out its work, asked Sir
I Julian Huxley, in his first report as Director-
General to the Unesco General Conference, In a world
where more than half the people are illiterate and lack
the skills and knowledge necessary to build for themselves
a healthy life and prosperous conditions of agriculture and
also to make the most effective use of scientific dis¬
coveries?
The need was clear: give top priority to providing educ¬
ation where there had been none, never forget the human¬
istic ideal of universality and always show a genuine
understanding and respect for cultural values whatever
their origin.
At Unesco's preparatory conference in London in 1946,
representatives of 44 states were present. The next year,
a total of 23 had ratified the Constitution and took their
seats as member states at the General Conference. The
numbers grew: 37 by the end of 1947, 55 in 1950, and
today, 113.
Equality in status for the member states of Unesco did
not, however, remove a flagrant Inequality of fact: the
number of newly-developing countries In Unesco grew
unceasingly and the dividing line between these and the
more favoured was clearly economic.
It was to meet this grave situation that the Expanded
Programme of Technical Assistance was conceived,
adopted in principle in 1948 and applied, in Unesco's case,
as from 1950. In applying this aid, Unesco always kept
in mind the aims affirmed in its Constitution. "Unesco
was the only international organization," writes Jean
Thomas, "to take to heart the truth that people have not
only material needs, but spiritual ones too, which are no
less important."
This faith in the primacy of education and the resolve
to see it universally acknowledged stand out clearly
throughout the book. They are its real animating force
and spirit. The author has not given to his account the
chronological form that might have weighed down his
narrative. Nevertheless the whole story of Unesco how
it faced up to increasingly complex tasks, how it main¬
tained course and purpose despite difficulties and crises
and how, finally, it came to maturity stands out clearly
in his account.
No one could say that Unesco's task has been simple.
It has encountered many difficult and dangerous situa¬
tions in its lifetime and one of its major problems has
been the question of its moral autonomy. "How can the
unanimity which for so long has been missing from the
United Nations be achieved in Unesco?" asks Jean Tho
mas. Yet while in no way underestimating the difficul¬
ties, he considers that Unesco Is proving Its worth, and
explains why. However, to Judge Its circctiveness. he
adds, "each one of Unesco's projects must be examined
separately and each time on the basis oí different cri¬
teria."
How then has Unesco coped with two major tasks: the
fight against illiteracy and the reclamation of the world's
arid lands?
It Is not Unesco's role to take over education for chil¬
dren or for adults In any country. This Is the responsibi¬
lity of governments. Through a system of co-operation
between governments, educators and appropriate orga¬
nizations, Unesco has offered advice on educational tech¬
niques that might be used, has suggested the lines for
development programmes and has passed on the results
of experiments that have been tried successfully elsewhere.
It has given direct aid to countries when they have a.sked
for It.
For the arid zone problems, "through co-operation
between specialists, Unesco has encouraged and co-or¬
dinated scientific activities related to these problems and
has helped member states within the action of the Tech¬
nical Assistance Programme."
Thus any evaluation of Unesco's effectiveness must take
into account Unesco's alms, the methods It uses and the
means It Is given to work with. None of this Is likely
to be Immediately obvious to the man In the street. It
is here that the Jean Thomas' book reveals lLself as an
Indispensable guide to those concerned with public Infor¬
mation. It analyzes clearly and precisely Unesco's rela¬
tions with its member states and with the United Nations
and explains how Unesco co-ordinates the delicate balance
between Its activities.
N o matter how slight his previous knowledge of
Unesco, the reader Is left with the Impression
of having shared in an unfolding adventure of high
endeavour. For, says the author. Unesco's Constitution
has given It a task high In the scale of moral values: "the
maintenance of peace and security among the nations".
But the roads of peace are rarely triumphal highways,
modest, rather, and always difficult of access.
Here, in its "public relations", Its relations with the
peoples of 113 countries Unesco Is accomplishing its mis¬
sion. Thousands of peace treaties have been swept
away by the winds of history. Unesco today strives to
build the defences of peace In the minds of men.
And this Is by no means the least Important of the
lessons olTered by this book which the author concludes
on a resolutely optimistic note, still further underlined by
the frankness with which he has described the temporary
setbacks and permanent problems facing Unesco. "When
one takes stock." he says, "of all the multitude of different
activities and intellectual disciplines Involved In Unesco's
work, the resulting array of strength Is so great as to
banish any fears as to the resources open to It. What It
must learn to do is to draw and marshal 'around It all
these forces of goodwill."
* Unesco by Jean Thomas, published by Gallimard. Paris. 1962.
Price 13.50 Fr. frs.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
MrÔlDDonÂu^
OF THE CINEMA ~V
L PT. 2 FILM DISTRIBUTION ^^^^H
In its December issue, The Unesco Courier began the publication of a
series of articles on the lesser-known aspects of the cinema industry
based on a world-wide survey by Paul Léglise. In his second article, the
author turns a spotlight on the vast and complex machine through which
films of all kinds are distributed to the world's 170,000 commercial cinemas
as well as to the multitude of specialized non-commercial cinemas.
film has been completed. Soon It will be
i presented to the public in cinemas around the
world. Its makers hope that it will turn out to be a
major box-office success, drawing record audiences to the
cinema. As the American producer, Walter Wanger, once
wrote in The New York Times: "The film must appeal
Just as much to an eight-year-old child as to a man of
eighty; it must entertain people of every race and every
country, Irrespective of their religions, and political or
social systems."
This is the salient principle of the universal audience
and what American film-makers mean when they speak
of "universal appeal." But the cinema-going public is not
a homogeneous group of people. Innumerable influences
exert pressure upon the cinema audience. Sex, age, in¬
come, social position, level of education, character, likes
and dislikes, working hours, seasons, periods of prosperity
and economic crisis all help 'to mould the audience, as
does publicity In all its forms. And, moving alongside
the entertainment film, the specialized production now
holds an increasingly important place In the cinema world.
By way of example let us simply take one of these
factors age. Surveys and polls conducted in different
countries all indicate that, from childhood on, film-going
Increases with age to reach its maximum among teen¬
agers (between 15 and 20). From then on attendance
declines. Thus the film public and the public in general
are not one and the same and because of this, film dis¬
tribution has to be geared to meet the special character-
. istics of the film-goers. Its first problem is publicity:
what is the most effective way to publicize a newly-
completed film?
The greatest impact on the man-in-the-street is made by
the "spectacular" aspect of publicity the use of huge
poster hoardings and eye-catching boxed items in the
press. Through other columns in newspapers and perio¬
dicals he also tastes some of the atmosphere and feverish
excitement of international film festivals the gala
openings, carnival-like processions and cocktail parties.
All this is dismissed by some people as trivial and frivo¬
lous. And yet this kind of artificial effervescence is vital
to the cinema. This was so in the past and is still the
case today. As to the future, there is a need for the
development of more mature tastes in the . spectator
28 and the means to satisfy them. Tomorrow's film-goer
will be more responsive to the qualities of what he or
she sees on the screen, and the cult of the film will be
FANS AND FLASHLIGHTS. Flashbulbs pop
while fans and the curious crowd around some of
the stars in the galaxy attending the Cannes
Film Festival in France. Behind the glitter and
excitement of such occasions the gala openings
carnival-like processions, receptions and cocktail
partiesis another world : the serious, down-
to-earth business world of the film industry.
replaced by a love of the cinema. Already film criticism
is making a positive contribution in this direction.
But the general public has, on the whole, little inkling of
the things that go on behind this glittering facade: the
negotiation of contracts, the planning of future produc¬
tions and the sale of current films on the world market.
The number of contracts signed during a fortnight-long
festival is a fair measure of the concentration of "stars"
and big names in the cinema at any of these "fairs" of
the film world.
While business may occupy pride of place at the great
film festivals, cultural values are not forgotten. Meetings,
discussions and round-tables are not exclusively concerned
with professional matters, but deal with such subjects as
artistic expression, intellectual trends, the art of editing
or décor. -. [
Festivals at Cannes, Venice, Berlin, Moscow, Tokyo. Mar
del Plata, St. Sebastian and Locarno are primarily devoted
to feature-length entertainment films. There is never
any question of other aspects of the cinema being given
the place of honour nor can they always even squeeze
their way in to a folding seat or a stool in the aisle. This
explains the mushroom growth of film festivals that we
have seen recently in many parts of the world.
Some (Oberhausen, Tours) are solely devoted to short
films or, more generally to cultural and documentary films
(Cork, Mannheim, Manila). But above all nowadays the
movement is towards subject specialization (mountains
and exploration at Trento; sports films at Cortina d'Am¬
pezzo; industrial films at Harrogate, Rouen and Antwerp;
cartoons at Annecy; music and dance films at Valencia;
touristic and folklore films at Brussels).
An important co-ordination problem concerning film
distribution is how to keep the organizers of film screen¬
ings properly informed about the material that is
currently In circulation. The difficulty Is not so great in
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
<0 furoprc.î, Pari.
the case of feature-length and even short entertainment
Alms shown in cinemas thanks to the excellent compre¬
hensive catalogues distributed each year by the national
trad.- organizations. But for cultural, educational, scien¬
tific, technical or Industrial films the situation is far more
complicated. How is one to find the way through a forest
of catalogues that overlap, but do not necessarily present
a complete picture, and amid card indexes of the most
varied types and sizes.
One way of getting around this problem was suggested
by a round-table gathering organized by Unesco in Venice
In July 1959. This meeting recommended that national
information centres should be set up to supply facts about
all films produced in their respective countries. A similar
suggestion came from the conference organized In London
in February 1961 by the Council of Europe, on the distribu¬
tion of cultural films.
Subsequently, at Unesco's request, the International
Cinema and Television Council appointed a specialist to
make a thorough study of the problem. In a remarkable
and comprehensive report, this specialist has outlined all
the facts on the basis of which a rational and effective
plan of action could be co-ordinated and applied.
As recommended by the Venice round-table and the
London conference, the national cataloguing centres would
assemble and list all films and television programmes for
eventual publication in a General Film Catalogue, similar
to existing national bibliographies. To meet the delicate
problem of bringing cataloguing standards into line,
Unesco has published, International Rules for the Cata¬
loguing of Educational, Scientific and Cultural Films and
Filmstrips.
In the early days of the cinema a film might be produc¬
ed in hundreds of copies which were sold by the yard and
shown by travelling showmen until completely worn out.
The film trade was first alerted to the need for a reform
in this sphere by a former French lawyar, Edmond
Benoit-Lcvy, in a key article that appeared In the review
Ciné-Gazette which he founded in 1905. Writing under
the pen-name of Francis Malr, he asked, "What is a film?
Is it ordinary merchandise which the purchaser can use
as he thinks fit? No, a film is a literary and artistic
property. In order to show it royalties must be paid.
Future discussions will be concerned with the fixing of
such royalties."
The first to adopt this formula was the French newsrcel
pioneer, Charles Pathe, who in 1907 set up five regional
companies in France and gave them a 20-year monopoly
to exploit his productions.
The results of this reform in distribution methods were
revealed quite clearly when the second International
congress met In Paris under the presidency of Georges
Melles in February 1909. This was attended by film
company representatives from the United States, Great
Britain, Denmark, Italy and France. Faced by a looming
crisis In the cinema business and wishing to fix uniform
prices for films as well as to prevent the over-long use of
prints, the congress decided to Introduce the first regula¬
tions governing the sale or release of films. Producers
agreed that In future they would supply films only to those
who had signed an agreement and who were prepared
to certify In writing that they would return the films,
carriage paid, to the producers within four months.
This was the beginning, however embryonic, of film
distribution as we know it nowadays. Today a product
of the film-maker's art Is protected as an original work
under the Berne and Geneva Conventions on Copyright,
and only its authors have the right to authorize its re¬
production and screening.
CONT'D ON NEXT PACE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Cont'd)
A trade in
'intangible property'
Who. are, in fact, the authors of a film? For many years
this controversial question provoked lively discussions at
international congresses. The 39th Congress of the World
Literary and Artistic Association, held In Budapest in 1930,
appeared to reconcile the conflicting views on the problem
when It defined the term "author" as covering the writer
of the original work, the composer of the original score and
the film's director, with the producer retaining exclusive
ownership of the cinematographic rights in the work for a
period of seven years.
For some years afterwards, however, producers, pressed
home the view that the producer was the chief, if not
the sole, author and that he alone had the right to
authorize the reproduction and showing of a film.
N
30
owADAYS the film is generally considered
as a collective work and while each film may
be judged as an individual case, the prevailing view Is
that the co-authors of a cinematographic work are the
creative collaborators (director, scenario writer, music
composer and producer).
These co-authors grant most of the rights which they
have inherited in the work to one of their number, the
producer, but retain a moral right which covers the inclu¬
sion of their names in the film credits and in advertising
and enables them to refuse to accept any changes that, in
their view, detract from the integrity of their work. For
the distribution of the work, the producer may in turn
grant the rights which are his by contract to other per¬
sons. Thus the distribution machinery Is set in motion.
It seems reasonable to suppose that not only the financ¬
ing arrangements of a film, but even more so its distribu¬
tion would call for a full knowledge and clear understand-
ing of its authors' rights, any contracts involved as well as
any disagreements and ensuing legal decisions. It is
surprising, therefore, that only a few countries such as
France, Italy and Federal Germany, require these basic
facts to be listed In a central registry.
Though film distribution may be looked upon in principle,
as a trade in what jurists call "intangible property"
(having no material existence in itself, but attaching as a
right or profit to some actual thing) it does involve many
aspects of a more material nature.
After signing a contract with the producer and as we
have already seen, this often takes place when the question
arises of financing a planned film the distributor, acting
for the producer, launches a publicity campaign aimed at
exhibitors. Screenings for members of the film trade are
arranged and distribution company, salesmen make the
rounds of cinema managers' offices to offer films that are
available.
Blind-booking doing business in films that are still In
the planning stage is practised less often nowadays. Yet
the risks involved in rentals of this kind are still accepted
by some first-run cinemas which thereby put up a percen¬
tage of the money needed to finance the production.
Large companies whose interests cover simultaneously
production, distribution and exhibiting are also obliged to
adopt this system in their cinema circuits so as to ensure
the distribution of their own films. And for similar rea¬
sons, so are the cinema organizations in countries with
socialist economies.
Another method frequent and deep-rooted is block-
booking which consists of not selling the exhibiting rights
to a given film but to a series. Exhibitors buy a locomotive
(a film sure of box-office success) and a string of trucks
(films whose profitability is far less certain) on the basis of
"all or nothing at all." This is the reason for the uneven
and incongruous series of programmes that some cinemas
other than those which specialize in a certain type or
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
DRA1ERLIM.
Magic
Made
¿ASV
Magic by Merlin is an
eye-opener (above) for
this 12-year-old "star"
of the film, "School Sau-
cery" an awardwinning
production by the Wal¬
ton County Secondary
School Film Unit in
England. Each year the
best school film unit pro¬
ductions compete in
a nationwide contest
sponsored by Great
Britain's National
Union of Teachers.
Litter bin is pressed
into service by a youth¬
ful cameraman (right)
"on location" at a sea¬
side resort. Film pro¬
duction gives youngsters
a deeper and more se¬
rious interest in the
cinema and develops
initiative. Below, a 15-
year-old artist at work
at. the animating desk
on a cartoon sequence.
All photos W.-Iton County Secondary School Film Unit
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The right angle for the
close-up. Schoolboy
cameraman prepares
to "shoot"' the girl
"star" of the film
"Crosswise" (right).
Below, a camera team
photographs the end
titles for "School Sau-
cery"', a short film.
FILM FESTIVAL FOR THE JUNIOR SET
year for the first time
school-age and teen-age film
producers are to have their own inter¬
national festival. The Tenth Muse
Competition" organized by the Inter¬
national Centre of Films for Children
(241, rue Royale, Brussels) is to be
held at the Venice Lido and will
award prizes for the best films made
by young people. It will be world¬
wide in scope and open to two age
groups: those under 16 and those
between 16 and 18 years of age.
Films may be in colour or black and
white, 8-mm. or 16-mm., but they
must be silent and must not run
longer than 15 minutes. The Tenth
Muse Competition (adding a new
one to the nine muses in classical
mythology) reflects the place now
given to films in the classroom and
in education generally. Film produc¬
tion by the pupils themselves is now
a regular feature in the curriculum
of many British schools. Photos on
these pages show some of these
junior British film-makers at work.
r
I
I ' rT
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Cont'd)
Boom in art and experimental films
32
class of film offer their customers; programmes that
always surprise cinema-goers who would like to see
something corresponding to their tastes rather than
simply "go to the cinema."
How many prints of a film will be needed by the distribu¬
tor? The answer can vary considerably. It all depends
on the success of the film, the cinemas involved and
whether the film Is to have a. mass release or a gradual
distribution. Copies reduced to a 16-mm. format instead
of the standard trade format of 35-mm. will be needed for.
use on rural circuits and in the non-commercial field.
In the case of foreign language films, sub-titles must be
added or, through the more complex operation of post-
synchronization, actors voices dubbed in the national or
local language.
Then the next phase in distribution begins. Films have
to be despatched and on their return the condition of
copies checked carefully. This alone calls for an ade¬
quately-developed technical department, according to the
size of the firm and the number of rental contracts.
Equally Indispensable Is an extensive book-keeping
department. The distributor, in fact, is the real cashier of
the cinema and as such he often becomes a kind of
production banker. He draws up the invoices, sees that
these are settled and pays over to the producers the sums
that are due to them. Supervision of receipts, especially
where a system of percentage rentals is involved, is often
a far from straightforward operation.
It Is here that corporative or State bodies can often be
of great help since taxation and financial authorities have
a direct interest in the control of cinema business. In
France, for instance, all tickets sold at cinema box-offices
are supplied by the National Cinematographic Centre.
After each programme is screened, the Centre receives a
declaration of receipts, showing the first and last numbers
of tickets sold during the performances.
In the socialist countries distribution and production are
associated in nationalized firms which come directly under
the ministries concerned with films: Film Polski (Govern¬
ment Film Monopoly in Poland), Ceskoslovensky Film
(Czechoslovak Films), Sovrofilm (Rumania) and so on.
I iSTRiBUTioN . problems like those already
described create new difficulties in developing
countries where the technical resources to cope with
them are not always available. Shortage of raw film and
a polyglot language situation complicate matters still
further.
These are the kind of problems that Inspired the Bang¬
kok Conference on the development of information media
in South East Asia (January 1960) to suggest the creation
of a regional co-operation bureau. Though this body
would not itself actually distribute films, it would assist co¬
ordination between national 'film departments and would
produce local-language versions of films.
Under what kind of legal conditions is film distribution
operated? Without going too deeply into the judicial
complications of contracts we find two main categories.
In the first of these the distributor obtains the exclu¬
sive right to handle a specific film within a specified area
and for a fixed period at an agreed price or, alternatively,
against a share of the receipts from rental. He may also
grant these rights to another distributor.
The second type of contract determines the general
conditions in which films are exhibited. It gives the
exhibitor the right to screen a copy of a film in a specific
cinema for an agreed number of sessions, on pre-arranged
dates and on payment of a lump sum or a fixed percentage
of receipts. He may not, however, pass on this right.
This type of contract usually includes clauses granting
benefits to certain cinemas: sole rights (only the benefi¬
ciary has the right to show the film within a specified
region and for a set period) ; priority (the right to screen
a film before other exhibitors) ; first or second showing
rights; protection periods (the length of time prior to or
following the screening of a film during which no compet¬
ing exhibitors within a named area may also exhibit it).
Programme patterns vary from one country to another.
By far the most common practice is to open with a
newsreel and one or more short films and then present
the main feature film. But this seems to be increasingly
replaced by the "double feature" two major films in the
same programme. This trend Is to be regretted for it
leads to the suppression of short films and a corresponding
growth of the so-called "B films."
There are of course, other kinds of cinema programmes.
In the "news theatre," for example, newsreels and short
films provide about an hour's entertainment, and some
other cinemas provide a complete programme of shorts.
Today art and experimental cinemas grouped within the
International Federation of Art and Experimental Cinemas
United Nations
A vast number of educational films are produced
nowadays, but their distribution is handicapped by
lack of standardization in cataloguing and indexing
systems. Unesco has now made a study of the various
systems with a view to co-ordinating and assembling
Information about educational films which would be
of special benefit to countries in which this kind of
film production is small or non-existent. Above,
an image of rural life in Ceylon being filmed by a
cameraman from a U.N. travelling motion picture
unit for a film entitled "A Field In Asia", showing
developments in U.N.-aided projects throughout Asia.
are experiencing a remarkable boom throughout the world
by distributing top-quality programmes of the kind that
are often hard to exploit commercially. The development
of special programmes for young people should also be
taken into account.
Generally speaking, cinemas receive newsreels on a
subscription basis. Payment is calculated on fixed sum or
a percentage, depending on how up-to-date the newsreel
is by the time it is shown. In South America, for example,
the rental cost is frequently a multiple of the price of the
best seats in the house (five times the cost of a ticket
for the most expensive seat in Brazil; ten times the price
in Paraguay). In some countries, including Argentina,
Bulgaria. Czechoslovakia, German Federal Republic, Hun¬
gary. India, Israel, Italy, Japan, Peni, Poland and Spain,
the showing of newsreels is compulsory.
(To be continued.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
ROADS TO FAMINE
Sir,
I read Mr. Zottola's article "Famine,
the Greatest Scourge of History" (July-
August 1962) with much interest. It
also made me wonder why historians
have so seldom stated the combination
of factors which leads to famine. If
these were better known perhaps many
famines could have been avoided or
the damage caused considerably re¬
duced. The Bengal Famine of 1942
was triggered by fear, followed by
hoarding of food grains in damp and
unhygienic stores where it was des¬
troyed by fungi and store pests. If
there had been air-tight bins and mod¬
ern silos in India on a sufficient scale
there would have been no famine.
How many of the European famines
have been brought about by mould
fungi and micro-organisms?
You mentioned that Sir Jack Drum-
mond said, "We had no idea how to
revive these dying victims of hunger."
Between May and November 1942 I
had the task of going into Burma
to help our refugees. I fed the first
meal to more than 22,000 starving,
exhausted and often disease-ridden
refugees. During the first few days
I killed off 9 people with rum or bran¬
dy and another 9 with too much food.
This meant in terms of figures that I
lost 18 refugees out of about five
thousand. During the next four and
a half months when conditions were
much worse, I lost one woman out of
seventeen thousand people.
Twenty years later, reading the
numerous books about over-popula¬
tion, agriculture and hunger, I am
wondering if everyone has forgotten
the advice that Joseph gave to Pha¬
raoh about building storehouses and
silos. Air-tight bins and silos do not
seem to be mentioned in the reports
of the United Nations. Why?
A.R. Tainsh
Stockholm, Sweden
HOW BIG IS BUENOS AIRES?
Sir,
In your July-August issue under
the heading "Big Cities Getting Still
Bigger" you published a handsome
photograph of the port and city of
Buenos Aires. Under it you say that
Buenos Aires and its suburbs "have
6 1/2 million inhabitants almost
the total population of the country in
1914." This information is wrong
unless you consider that the suburbs
of Buenos Aires spread over a dis¬
tance of 300 miles and more from
the city itself.
According to a study made by Al¬
berto Cataldi, of the Latin-American
Demographic Centre in Santiago, the
population of the Argentine capital,
comprising greater Buenos Aires and
its immediate suburbs, was 3,795,813
on September 30, 1960, the date of
the last census. The rest of the pro¬
vince of Buenos Aires, including such
important cities as La Plata, Mar
del Plata and Bahia Blanca, had by
then 2,938,735 inhabitants.
Consequently, the population of
6,734,548 (sum of the figures quoted
above) corresponds to the province
of Buenos Aires, including the fede¬
ral capital.
Alejandro Kchcgoycn
Santiago, Chile
WORLD'S WORST EVII	
Sir,
I was very moved by the articles
you published on the world fight
against hunger (July-August). With
the mechanized methods that exist in
the world hunger should have long
ago been banished. Unhappily this
redoubtable curse will always be with
us as long as there is no just and
equitable sharing out of all kinds of
consumer goods. In France alone
scores of thousands of under-nour¬
ished people try to exist on salaries
or ""pensions that shame a self-pro¬
claimed progressive country. In my
view the worst evil in the world is
money and as long as it remains
paramount, the ravages of hunger
will continue. The so-called advanc¬
ed countries speak of helping under¬
developed ones. They should first put
their own houses in order, above all
morally.
Andre Tosolini
Clermont-Ferrand, France
...AND MOST SERIOUS MALADY
Sir,
Although I have read many issues
of your journal the most serious
disease of modern times has not been
tackled. Mistrust between the na¬
tions of the world can do more harm
than any other disease known to the
peoples of the world. Tun Uni.s-
co Courier is read throughout the
nations of the world, thus what bigger
audience can ¡here be?
I appreciate that yours is not »a
political paper, but would it not be
possible to utilize a whole issue on
each of the countries in Unesco...
on the ways of life of the people,
food and agriculture problems, medi¬
cal services, working conditions, plans
for the future etc. etc. If only the
ordinary man in the street could be
made to understand that the ordinary
man in the other countries wants the
same things from life as he docs,
then perhaps there may be a chance
of peace in this world.
H. II. King
London, England
YOUTH ON THE MOVE
Sir,
I am particularly interested in tra¬
vel, living with people of other na¬
tions which I think is so important.
We recently travelled to Turkey,
through Yugoslavia, Greece and
Crete by any means of transport avail¬
able ox-carts, donkeys, on fool, in
passing Schick's and iclving on the
hospitality of the people for food,
etc. l.vcryone was so helpful and
kind the «hole journey has left a
deep impression on us. '1 he poverty
and yet the simplicity in which these
people took it for granted to shaie
with us the little they had overwhelmed
us. Since then 1 have taken to
the road many times, travelling in
the same way, meeting people and
exchanging ideas. 'I his has brought
about a tremendous desire lo travel
even further in the Middle and far
Last but this time I would like to
woik with some kind of organization
I do not care how small my part
may be in it. I wonder how it is
possible to go about finding such a
job and wonder if you can help inc.
llarhura Hasllan
London, I'nglaml
Lonok's no 1 1.: Young persons of
cither sex interested in working abroad
can contact ¡he Co-ordination Cont-
initec ¡or International I'oluntury
Work Camps, (>, rue Franklin, Paris
l(i", France. An article on the Volun¬
tary Work Camps will lie published
shortly.
BRAVE NEW UNIFORM WORLD
Sir,
Your aim, as far as I can sec, is
to make us, as civilized literalc peo¬
ple, aware of the plight of people
(underdeveloped people seems lo be
implied) in underdeveloped countries
and to help them materially and in¬
tellectually to attain a high standard
of living similar to our own. Also
there is the luxurious preservation of
wilde and rare beaslies and the con¬
templative obscrvalion of all manner
of crawling things and coloured stones
which I do admit could contribute
quite a lot, in its own sophisticated
way, to the furtherance of scientific
knowledge; but in what direction?
The most basic, real, attainable aims
of the organization arc the cultura-
blc and cducatablc peoples of the
world. Ihc eventual success of all
these high endeavours will be a brave
new uniform world, devoid of form
and so devoid of culture, religion and
superstition and everything that
man as a proper cultured unit feels
in his soul.
The progress of communication in
the present century has been a curse
to every existing culture in the world.
To sponsor a thought-flux be¬
tween civilizations is a prolific sophis¬
tication begetting only sophistications,
all of which arc barren. Certainly,
one day the world will be uniform
but do not let the dominant culture
select those parts of the subsidiary
cultures that it fancies. Let there be
mature conflict, let there be evolu¬
tion and no willing synthesis...
Michael Ferron
Londonderry, Northern Ireland
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
RENÉ MAHEU ELECTED DIRECTOR-GENERAL OF ONESCO
M RENE MAHEU of France has
been elected Director-General
of UNESCO by the 12th Session of
the UNESCO General Conference
meeting in Paris. With 89 out of 99
delegations voting for his nomination,
Mr. Maheu was elected on November
14 with a larger majority than any
previous UNESCO Director-General.
Previously he had been Acting Direc¬
tor-General since the resignation of
Mr. Vittorino Veronese in 1961.
Born in France In 1905, Mr. Maheu
graduated from the Ecole Normale
Supérieure and taught philosophy at
the University of Cologne, the French
Institute of London and the Franco-
Moslem College at Fez, between 1931
and 1942. He Joined UNESCO in
September 1946 as head of the Divi¬
sion of Free Flow Information. In 1949
Dr. Jaime Torres Bodet, then Director-
General of UNESCO, appointed him
as Director of his Office. He was
appointed Assistant Director-General'
by Dr. Luther Evans In July 1954, and,
with the same rank, UNESCO Repre¬
sentative to the United Nations in New
York in November 1955. Mr. Maheu
returned to UNESCO headquarters In
December 1958 and in November 1959
was appointed Deputy Director-Gene¬
ral by Dr. Vittorino Veronese. An¬
nouncing Mr. Maheu's election for a
1^ ARTHQUAKE-PROOF HOMES: A
J Unesco specialist sent to Iran follow¬
ing the disastrous earthquake on Septem¬
ber 1, 1962, in which 12,000 people lost
their lives, has suggested how mud-walled
village homes there could be simply and
inexpensively reinforced against future seis¬
mic shocks. He proposes the use of steel
straps which in two hours can be fitted by
four men on poles at each corner of the
house and tightened by turnbuckles.
MONACO'S SCOLATEX' CONTEST:
Following the success of its inter-
school and international educational phila¬
telic exhibition, "Scolatex I", in 1959, the
Monaco National Commission for Unesco
is this year organizing a philatelic contest-
exhibition, "Scolatex II", which will be
open to all young people under the age of
18. Individual or group competitors will
be asked to illustrate, by means of stamps, a
theme or idea of their choice. For full in¬
formation write to the Commissaire Gene¬
ral de Scolatex II, Commission Nationale
Monégasque pour I'Unesco, B.P., 9, Mon¬
aco.
FIRST-AID FROM THE SKY: Austra-
lia, which initiated the Flying Doctor
service to cover vast "outback" areas is
now launching another airborne medical
Unesco - Dominique Roger
term of office of six years, the Pre¬
sident of the General Conference,
Professor Paulo de Berredo Carneiro
of Brazil praised the choice of
Mr. Maheu who, he said, was "a direct
product of the UNESCO Secretariat
and, therefore, an international man."
service First-Aid Parachuters. The St.
John's Ambulance Brigade is forming its
first parachute division whose members are
already amateur parachutists.
ELECTRONIC 'JELLYFISH': An elec¬
tronic apparatus designed by biophy¬
sics scientists at Moscow University, is based
on the jelly-fish's aural system which picks
up the infrasounds of an oncoming storm.
The apparatus is able not only to forecast
storms 15 hours in advance, but also to pre¬
dict their force and the path they will take.
TV IN THE KINDERGARTEN: Chil¬
dren at over 100 infant schools in
Venezuela now watch a daily television pro¬
gramme put out by the Ministry of Edu¬
cation over Radio Caracas, that includes
plays, films and stories. Venezuelan spe¬
cialists are agreed that this audio-visual
teaching helps to develop creative abilities
and powers of observation, aids the study of
the 3 R's and expands vocabularies.
COMPUTER VS. LITERARY RIDDLE:
Using an electronic computer, 'two
Harvard University mathematicians recent¬
ly identified the authorship of 12 essays
believed to have been written by the Amer¬
ican statesman, Alexander Hamilton, and
by James Madison (4th president of the
United States) which were published anon¬
ymously in 1787 and 1788. The mathe¬
maticians fed information on the frequency
of key words in the essays and in the known
writing of the two men, and from the
results identified Alexander Hamilton as
the author of 1 1 of the essays.
"¡VEW WAY TO LEARN FRENCH: In
-1- a Leeds (England) school a French
woman teacher took a junior school class
for all subjects, speaking nothing but French.
After two weeks the children were able to
understand all that was said to them . and
after nine weeks spoke French fluently, had
a large vocabulary and were obviously able
to think in French as well. Similar experi¬
ments in three London schools have met
with equal success.
AWARD TO UNESCO RECORD COL¬
LECTION: A Unesco record collec¬
tion, "Musical Anthology of the Orient"
(See The Unesco Courier June 1962)
has received one of the awards given in
1962 by the Académie du Disque Français.
The first five records in the Unesco collec¬
tion present traditional and folk music of
Laos, Cambodia, Afghanistan and Iran.
SWEDES SERVING U.N. CAUSE: At
least 12,000 Swedes have so far been
engaged in the United Nations supervision
and control services in various parts of the
world. Over 11,000 Swedish soldiers have
been stationed in the Gaza district and in
the Congo. Others have served in Korea
and the Lebanon.
MAN IN SPACE SYMPOSIUM: One
hundred and fifty scientists from 19
countries met recently in Unesco House,
Paris, for an international symposium on
environmental problems of man in space.
The meeting highlighted the growing colla¬
boration brought about by the new prob¬
lems in space science between biologists,
on the one hand, and physicists and engi¬
neers on the other.
Flashes...
B Six more countries have recently joined.
Unesco, bringing its total of member states
to 113. The countries, in their order
of joining, are: the Mongolian People's
Republic, Trinidad and Tobago, Jamaica,
Rwanda, Uganda and Burundi.
A special Soviet non-magnetic ship, the
"Zarya" is now on a 32,000 mile voyage
around the world to continue magnetic
mapping of the oceans that was begun
during the International Geophysical Year.
| Over 630,000 fruit and timber trees were
planted in Ceylon during the first six
months of last year's tree planting cam¬
paign. More than half these came from
nurseries created by schoolchildren and
rural societies.
The Unesco Coupon Scheme under which
countries are able to buy badly-needed
books, scientific and educational equipment
in "hard currency" areas, paying for them in
their own national currency, has had a turn¬
over of over $48 million since it was
launched in 1948.
An Asian Regional Institute for school
building research sponsored by Unesco has
been opened in Bandung, Indonesia. Other
similar special centres for Asia include New
Delhi (educational planners and administra¬
tors); Bangkok (Regional Office for Educa¬
tion) and Manila (teacher training).
u
z
<
o
z
<
o
LU
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
SCfcS'coesFRES
a«?««
fOnU**
SS«»' """IS *
UNESCO
ART POCKET BOOKS
First four t/t/es :
EGYPTIAN WALL PAINTINGS FROM TOMBS AND TEMPLES
PERSIAN MINIATURES FROM ANCIENT MANUSCRIPTS
SPANISH FRESCOES FROM THE ROMANESQUE PERIOD
RUSSIAN ICONS FROM THE I2TH TO THE I5TH CENTURY
obtainable through local booksellers
A new publishing venture
Price per volume :
5/"
3.50 French francs ;
$ 0.95 (U.S. edition)
Each volume contains many
fine quality full-colour repro¬
ductions and other illustra¬
tions in black and white.
ALl^inTings
4F^w_ '*'n
UNESCO ART POCKET BOOKS are published in
six languages (English, French, Spanish, Italian,
German and Dutch) and in eight different editions.
They are published in London by Collins.
""" <"¡^77
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor In your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I.. Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C-., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lan noy,
22, place de Brouckère. Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd.. 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckach, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Norregade.
Köbenhavn K. (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 1 20. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppar 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco. Place
de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP. 12598-48. (7 F.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosen-
sheimer Strasse 145, Munich. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only) Bahren-felder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP. 276650 (DM 8). GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE, Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 1 49. Budapest, 62. INDIA. Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, 1 : 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf Ali Road. P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
Indian National Commission for Co-operation with
Unesco, Ministry ol Education, New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7).
INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti, D/alan
Nusantara 22. Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press.
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge. Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.. 35, Allenby
Road and 48. Nahlat Benjamin Street. Tel-Aviv (1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spalding*.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co..
Dar ul-Kutub. Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission lor Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286. Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück. 22. Grand-Rue.
Luxemburg. MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd., Times House,
River Valley Rd., Singapore MALTA. Sapienza's Library
26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-). MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd.. 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library. 30 Eld des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS. N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff. Lange Voorhout. 9. The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad. Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Offi.e
Wellington, and Go/err.ment Bookshops, Autkl.nd,
Wellington, Christchurch Dunedin (10.-). NIGEslA.
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 17*. Lagos. (10/-). NOR
WAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grenie. 7, Oslo
For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Litteratu r
Tieneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Postboks 115 (kr 13.20
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Cor
Ltd.. Unesco Publications House. P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-). PHI.
LIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue
Manila. POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza
Nr. 46, Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50). PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrada Lda. Livraria Portugal, Rua
do Carmo 70, Lisbon. RHODESIA & NYASA-
LAND. The Book Centre, First Street. Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SWEDEN. A/B CE. Frittes
Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
For The Unesco Courier: Svenska Unescoradet,
Stockholm, C (Kr. 7.50);
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse
rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
only: Georges Losmaz, 1, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP. 1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA.. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9. Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Caddesi. Beyoglu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145. Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier only: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johan¬
nesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office. P.O. Box 569. London. S.E.I. (10/-).
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third
Avenue. New York, 22. N.Y. (J 5.00.) and (except
periodicals): Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way. New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja
Kniga. Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslo-
venska Kn|iga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
Vasagatan 15-17,
SWITZERLAND.
Zurich. Payot. 40.
1-236. " Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO ART POCKET BOOKS St. George Slaying the Dragon: a favourite subject of Russian icon
painters. Here St. George has been depicted by a painter of the Nov¬
gorod School (late 14th century). This work, now in the Russian Museum. Leningrad, is one of many reproductions in full colour pre¬
sented in "Russian Icons from the 12th to the 15th Century", one of Unesco's new Art Pocket Books. (See p. 26 and back cover).
]]>
</page>
</document>
