<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="063456eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m 111 I M
JANUARY 1962 (15TH YEAR) - PRICE : 1 -STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (U.S.) 0.70 NF (FRANCE)
ANTARCTICA
INTERNATIONAL
LAND
OF SCIENCE
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
¿3»<^ -
BEAKFUL FOR BABY. At the start of the Antarctic autumn vast
colonies of Emperor penguins gather pn the coasts of sixth comment
and nearby ¡slandf*to mate.. During the .winter polar night these
penguins lay their eggs and* raise their young. When spring arrwes ^ .
and the youngsters, like the one being fed by mother, àj^ sufficiently ~
mature, the colonies vanish northwafd. :,The cycle is reversed for jrll
other penguins which arrive in spring. (See áftitle page "dSIßt^fi
i acques Masson © Expedition« polaires françaises -***
« TR\j
V- H 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier JANUARY 1962
15TH YEAR
Contents
No. I
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
American
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
Antarctica today is the scene
of intensive scientific acti¬
vity as men from many coun¬
tries continue the vast inves¬
tigations begun in 1957 dur¬
ing the International Geophy¬
sical Year. Here two scien¬
tists working with a French
expedition in Adélie Land
Investigate Ice formation by
removing sample cones with
special tools (story p. 28).
Jacques Masson (c) Expédi¬
tions Polaires Françaises
Page
4 A FROZEN CONTINENT OF MANY PARADOXES
By Georges Laclavère
7 THE TWO FACES OF ANTARCTICA
The old and new map of the sixth continent
9 ANTARCTICA, INTERNATIONAL LAND OF SCIENCE
By Ross C. Peavey & Laurence M. Gould
I 5 DISCOVERY, EXPLORATION, ADVENTURE & COURAGE
By Gordon de Q. Robin
1 7 TRAIL BLAZERS OF ANTARCTICA
18 AMUNDSEN AND SCOTT
The first men at the South Pole
2 1 LIVING AT 70° C. BELOW ZERO
By Paul A. Slple
29 OF SUNSPOTS, MAGNETIC RINGS & POLAR LIGHTS
By Alan F. Moore
32 JOURNEY INTO THE INACCESSIBLE
By M.M. Somov.
36 UNIQUE SPECIES THREATENED BY MAN
By Rodolfo Panzarini
4 1 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
42 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C 6I.I.I65 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7\ France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Amin Shaker (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchl Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July end August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I Issues a year) in English. French, Spanish. Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of Issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed mvil bear author's name. Uniol'icited mtnutcnpti cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinion« of UNESCO or those of the editors o( THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Uneico Courier la Indexed monthly in The Reidera' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilfon Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U, S. $ 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A FROZElfCONTÎ
i
HOWLING WINDS, bitter cold,
and a vast white desert of shifting
snow, slippery ice and hidden
crevasses make all movement a
laborious and hazardous enter¬
prise. This is Antarctica against
whose inhospitable climate scien¬
tists and explorers must prevail
in their efforts to uncover the
secrets of the icy continent.
Photo shows tracked vehicle and
sledge of French Polar expedi¬
tion bogged down in deep snow.
Jacques Masson
Expeditions Polaires Françaises
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
NENT OF MANY PARADOXES
by Georges Lacla vera
'-y**-- ,.-^-
£\ ntarctica, with a total surface of about live
* »million square miles, covers an area as large
as Europe and the United States combined. If one
Includes the great Ice shelves which fill the deep seas and
the bays surrounding the continent, another half million
square miles must be added to Its Immensity. Further¬
more, in winter the outlying seas freeze over for hundreds
of miles, and when the ice pack has reached the limit of
its extension, Antarctica becomes a solid mass of more
than fourteen million square milesequal to a quarter of
the earth's entire land surface.
Antarctica ls the highest of the world's continents.
Great mountain chains, with peaks often rising higher
than 10,000 feet, crisscross it In every direction. But these
mountains are visible as such only around the edges of the
continent. As soon as one penetrates a short distance
Inland they vanLsh and only the tips of their peaks emerge
from the Ice.
The entire land relief of the interior Ls in fact engulfed
under a gigantic Ice cap. This ice cap mantles Antarctica
from the coast inland, rising slowly until It reaches an
elevation of 12,000 feet near a point known as the "Pole of
Inaccessibility", situated some 600 miles from the geogra¬
phic South Pole which Itself ls no more than 9,800 feet
above sea level.
The thickness of the ice Ls greater than four kilometres
(two and a half miles) In certain places. Even on an
average It is more than two kilometres (one mile) thick.
If all the Antarctic ice were to melt, the level of the seas
would rise to drown most of the seaports of our planet
together with great stretches of fertile coastal plains.
The climate of Antarctica ls the severest known any¬
where on earth. The world's lowest temperature of
-88.3° C (-126.9° F.) has been recorded at Vostok, the Soviet
station situated some 800 miles from the coast at an
altitude of 12,000 feet. The annual mean temperature
along the coast drops to -30" C. (-22" F.) Winds of
incredible velocity and violence rage unceasingly across
the continent and make the bitter cold even more
difficult to bear.
Plant life ls practically non-exLstent save for certain
mosses, lichen and algae. Animal life, however, Ls abun¬
dant along the coasts and In the seas. Teeming colonies
of seal, penguins and petrel abound, and the ocean waters
are rich in plankton and deep sea creatures. (See article
page 35).
One of the many amazing features of Antarctica is its
shape which Is almost a perfect circle. ThLs has an enor¬
mous Influence on meteorological conditions all over the
continent with far-reaching effects throughout our globe.
Two vast seas cut deeply into Antarctica, the Ross Sea
and the Weddell Sea. The most southerly point of the for¬
mer is only 350 miles from the Pole, and it was this route
that both Amundsen and Scott took to get to the South
Pole. But to do so they had to cross the forbidding Queen
Maud range, a precipitous mountain chain whose peaks,
towering more than 15,000 feet, are amongst the highest
In Antarctica.
Against great odds they made their way through this
jagged barrier by following the great glaciers which carry
the Ice of the polar cap in its slow flow towards the sea.
Scott travelled along the Beardmore glacier which Ls more
than 60 miles long and 18 miles wide. Despite its .huge
size, it Ls by no means the giant of Antarctica's glaciers.
Between the Ross and Weddell Seas an extraordinary
mountain peninsula shaped like a horn extends to the 5
north. It Ls a prolongation of the Cordillera of the Andes
which, when it reaches the southern tip of South America
CONT"D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
FROZEN CONTINENT (Cont'd)
Under the polar cap, remains of a desert
at Tierra del Fuego, sinks beneath the waves of the
Atlantic Ocean to re-emerge in Antarctica.
A glance at the map of Antarctica may lead one to
suppose, as did certain geographers when our knowledge
of the continent was much more superficial, that the Ross
and Weddell Seas are joined by a channel filled with ice,
and that Antarctica is in reality divided into two parts.
This gave rise to the much debated question: "Is Antarc¬
tica a continent or an archipelago?"
The answer has come only In the past few years as a
result of the many expeditions which have explored the
area., These expeditions set out to determine what the
coastline of Antarctica would look like if the ice were to
vanish, by carrying out systematic measurements of the
thickness of the ice.
The method used is to set off an explosive charge on the
surface. The concussion wave travels down through the
ice until it reaches rock when it is reflected back to the
surface and the echo recorded on instruments. Since the
speed of the concussion wave is known, we can measure
the time elapsed between the explosion and the return¬
ing echo, and thus calculate how far down the rock lies.
As a result of these measurements, scientists now feel
fairly sure that the major part of Antarctica is made up
of a single rockbed dating back to very ancient times.
However, a separated rock mass has been recently dis¬
covered on the edge of the Bellingshausen and Amundsen
Seas. This has been found to be of more recent origin
and of different composition from that of the rest of
Antarctica. It is separated from the main continent by
a very deep channel filled with ice several miles thick.
So, despite the fact that since the start of the Inter¬
national Geophysical Year in 1957 scientific expeditions
have undertaken numerous soundings, our knowledge of
the topography and geology of Antarctica's hidden rock
masses Ls still uncertain, and many enigmas remain
unfathomed.
Thus, the recent discovery that certain portions of
Antarctica's coastline are very similar to those of South
Africa has raised anew Alfred Wegener's theory of conti¬
nental drift. (1) Again, carbon deposits have been found
which indicate that in former geological times Antarctica
enjoyed a hot and humid climate. Elsewhere, vestiges of
an arid burning desert intrigue geologists.
J usT as ash and sand have preserved civili¬
zations of the past so the Antarctic ice has
served to protect the history of the Earth.
Better still, the snow turned to ice and slowly deposited
on the surface of Antarctica may soon tell us the story
of the evolutions of climate during the course of many
millions of years. Tests carried out on ice crystals
with radio Isotopes now enable scientists to distinguish
between the different seasons, and so it will soon be
possible for us to know the temperatures that existed in
Antarctica when the ice crystals were formed aeons ago.
Here, indeed, are the real archives of our planet, and
neither natural forces nor vegetation nor human
Influences have altered them-.
For how many hundreds of thousands of centuries have
volcanic ash and the dust of meteorites been deposited
here ? Perhaps they hold the key to the intriguing puzzles
of the Ice Ages and their causes, and the mysterious vicis¬
situdes of climate.
(1) Editor's note: How the continents originated and came to
occupy their geographic positions has from early times been a subject
of controversy. In 1915 Alfred Ly Wegener of Germany set forth his
theory of continental drift in his book The Origin of Continents and
Oceans {published in English translation in 1U24). According to
Wegener, the continents were separated from an original continuous
or nearly continuous land mass by drifting apart and a shifting of
the poles. Wegener s¡>oke of a general westward movement and a
drtft of the continent* away from the poles. The way in which the
bulge of South America can be fitted into the coast of West Africa
ii'nv offered as supporting evidence for the theory.
But let us leave this subject of the distant past, fascinat¬
ing though it Ls, and return to the Antarctica of today
which is of no less interest.
If the amount of the ice in Antarctica should increase
it will be at the expense of the waters of the ocean, the
level of which will drop. If, instead, the ice diminishes
the oceans will benefit from this and, as already noted,
the seas will rise. The danger, of course, is in no way
imminent, yet a rapid melting of the ice is not at all
inconceivable and would have incalculable repercussions
on the state of our world economy.
Scientists have therefore been attempting to find out
whether the balance sheet for Antarctica's ice is positive
or negative. To do this, they calculate the amount of
water vapour which the winds blow over Antarctica from
the surrounding oceans where it then falls as snow. At
the same time, they also calculate the losses, that is,
how much snow is driven into the sea by the winds, how
many icebergs "calve" or break off from the ice cap and
drift away, how much ice melts on the surface of and
within glaciers, etc.
The findings have been most contradictory.
Certain scientists claim that. Antarctica's
mass of ice is stationary. A number of observations prove
without possible doubt that the line of coastal ice is
definitely receding. But the correlation of all the data
assembled since the International Geophysical Year was
launched tends on the contrary to show an increase in
the amount of ice. This increase corresponds to an
annual condensation in the Antarctic equal to a film of
water three millimetres (about one eighth of an inch) thick
taken from all the oceans of the world. Yet there is no
trace of such a drop in the level of the oceans from any
of the hundreds of coastal observation stations which
carry out daily testing throughout the globe.
Of more immediate importance are the problems of me¬
teorology in Antarctica which can be summed up in two
questions: 1) What Ls the role of the Antarctic continent
on the general circulation of the atmosphere? 2) How
does the Antarctic influence air circulation globally?
The South Polar region probably holds more than 90%
of the world's supply of permanent ice. It is thus an
enormous reservoir of cold temperature and acts on the
earth's climate by cooling the masses of air which circu¬
late above its surface as well as the waters surrounding
it. In addition, the circular shape of the continent, with
the Pole as its centre, increases air circulation in the area.
The winds reach fantastic velocities, churning the seas
into mountainous waves all along the 40th parallel, and
it is no wonder therefore that seamen refer to this part
of the world as the "Roaring Forties."
These winds provoke the transfer of heat (or cold) be¬
tween Antarctica and the rest of the planet. But to what
extent? This can only be determined by a minute and
prolonged study of Antarctica's meteorology. And one of
the most important contributions to a better understand¬
ing of our planet during the I.G.Y. was no doubt the
setting up of a network of 57 meteorological stations on
the continent and the islands of the sub-Antarctic zone.
Most of these stations are still in operation today. An
international meteorological centre to assemble and
analyse their data was created in Melbourne, Australia,
after the central meteorological post at "Little Amer¬
ica V" was closed down at the end of the Geophysical
Year.
But science's interest in Antarctica is by no means limit¬
ed to geology, glaciology and meteorology. Like the Arctic,
which it resembles in many ways, it is an ideal place for
the study of the upper atmosphere and the complex phe¬
nomena caused by solar radiation and solar particles
under the influence of the earth's magnetic field.
These studies alone would have justified the extraor¬
dinary efforts made by the twelve nations who partici¬
pated in the International Geophysical Year programme.
CONTD ON PAGE 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
From " Secrets of Antarctica " by Dr.
Raymond J. Adie, " New Scientist ",
May 25, 1961
SOUTH PACIFIC OCEAN
SOUTH SHETLAND ISLANDS
AMUNDSEN
SEA
BELLINGSHAUSEN SEA
M fi-
JfJ
ICE-LESS ANTARCTICA.
This map of Antarctica shows
perhaps one of the most start¬
ling geographical discoveries of
the century how the continent
would look if all the ice melted.
Marie Byrd Land would be
reduced to a series of islands
separated from the mainland by
a 500-600 km. channel. Freed
from the tremendous weight of
ice, the continent would rise
a total of 500 to 600 metres.
ROSS SEA
- - .#
-
m4rj« bVrd
t4D
o
. -'
r ^W
è
- t.
ELLSWORTH
HI CHADS'.
A r FiLCHNER I
ICE ¿HELF
SOUTH
ATLANTIC
OCEAN
WEDDELL SEA
r ¥\
- %
y . y
f . *
- >
Q
N?
.
/ ROSS ICE
CAPE ADARE
-fr-
SOUTH POLE
#r
.^mCTORIA LAND . v
MAGNETIC
? POLE^
GEOMAGNETIC
*P0LE
^^ Ol
POLE OF INACCESSIBILITY
I.G.Y. VALLEY
o ^ N
POLE 0F -
COLD
Á,bELIE LAND
tiryï-
7 -
N N ^f> *
©
©
]((£* ;" Í ^r' CAPE ANN
C E A N
U.S.A.F. map, adapted with aisutance of SCAR
THE TWO FACES OF ANTARCTICA
Stations occupied, winter 1961, below latitude 60° south
1. - Stonington Island (U.K.) 13.
2. -Adelaide Island (U.K.) 14.
3. - Argentine Islands (U.K.) 15.
4. - Port Lockroy (U.K.) 16.
5. - Gonzalez Videla (Chile) 17.
6. - Melchior (Argentina) 18.
7. - Deception Island (U.K.) 19 .
8. - Decepción (Argentina) 20.
9. - Aguirre Cerda (Chile) 21.
10. - Arturo Prat (Chile) 22.
1 1. - Bernardo O'Higgins (Chile) 23.
12. -View Point (U.K.) 24.
Esperanza (Argentina)
- Oreadas (Argentina)
Signy Island (U.K.)
Hope Bay (U.K.)
Matienza (Argentina)
Fossil Bluff (U.K.)
Ellsworth (Argentina)
General Belgrano (Argentina)
Halley Bay (U.K.)
Norway station (South Africa)
Novolazarevskaya (U.S.S.R.)
- Syowa (Japan)
25. - Mawson (AUS.)
26. - Davis (AUS.)
27. - Mirny (U.S.S.R.)
28. - Vostok (U.S.S.R.)
29. - Wilkes (AUS.)
30. - Dumont d'Urville (FR.)
31.- Hallett (N.Z.-U.S.A.)
32 .- Amundsen-Scott (U.S.A.)
3 3. -Scott (N.Z.)
34. -McMurdo Sound (U.S.A.)
3 5.- Byrd (U.S.A.)
Station Data supplied by SCAR
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
FROZEN CONTINENT (Cont'd)
Now these efforts are being continued year after year
under the auspices of the Scientific Committee of Antarc¬
tic Research, better known as SCAR.
The economic value of Antarctica, apart from whaling,
is practically nil. The only resource which seems to exist
in any abundance is coal but its exploitation hardly seems
feasible. The real wealth of the Antarctic lies in the
ocean and the living things within it. It is not at all im¬
possible to conceive that this great reserve of protein rich
food may one day play an important part in nourishing
our planet.
Many suggestions have been made to put the Antarctic
to use, some quite fantastic and crackpot. One idea put
forward was to turn it into a cold storage warehouse.
Stocks of meat would be frozen in icebergs which when
needed would be towed across the oceans for delivery to
the consumer.
Another idea has been to fly sealed containers with
radioactive waste from nuclear factories to the heart of
the continent and drop them on the ice cap. The slow
creep of the ice flow would not bring them to the ocean
before several thousand years when they would have lost
most of their radioactivity and become harmless.
The creation of trans-Antarctic airlines has been envi¬
saged between South Africa, South America and Australia,
but the estimated commercial traffic would hardly jus¬
tify the highly expensive installations which this scheme
would require.
ANTARCTICA,
Co-operation between twelve nations dur¬
ing the International Geophysical Year
made possible the most ambitious scientific
exploration yet carried out in the conti¬
nent of Antarctica. Here, the "Lena"
unloads supplies and equipment for the
Soviet expeditions' Antarctic stations.
T he world now celebrates the 50th anniversary
_ of the conquest of the South Pole by Amund¬
sen and his companions on December 14, 1911, reached
only a few weeks later by Scott and his party who met a
tragic fate. How much progress we have seen in the short
span of 50 years!
The expedition of Admiral Byrd, and the international
Maudheim expedition in which Great Britain, Norway
and Sweden took part, to cite only these two examples,
were the prelude to the parties which set out for Antarc¬
tica during the International Geophysical Year.
The IGY expeditions reaped a rich scientific harvest
but let us not forget that they embodied the most
impressive effort of international scientific co-operation
the world has ever seen despite the most inhospitable
continent on the globe and the most inhuman of living
conditions.
In 1955 the Special Committee of the IGY decided to set
up a special group to prepare an Antarctic programme.
Fears were expressed that political difficulties might
threaten the success of the project. But all such diffi¬
culties were happily overcome and every scientific confe¬
rence on Antarctica, before, during and after the Inter¬
national Geophysical Year has taken place in a friendly
atmosphere of mutual understanding which has greatly
contributed to the success of all scientific undertakings.
All governments tacitly agreed not to allow political fac¬
tors to impede the work of the expeditions.
This has led to the Antarctic Treaty which has now
been ratified by the 12 nations who had dispatched expe¬
ditions to the Antarctic during the IGY. The treaty gua¬
rantees freedom of scientific research in Antarctica for a
period of thirty years. The signatory countries promise
to use the treaty zone defined by the 60° South Parallel
only for peaceful purposes, to ban nuclear explosions in
this territory as well as the deposit of atomic waste, and
finally, to exchange their programmes and scientific data.
This is the first treaty ever drafted to protect scientific
research and to entrust a non-governmental organization,
the Scientific Committee of Antarctic Research of the
International . Council of Scientific Unions, with full
power to determine the programmes. Here is a precedent
and the pattern of a concrete formula for harmonizing
relations between science and governments. Is it not a
paradox that the continent most hostile to man should
be the one to have done the most for the cause of peace.
Georges Laclavère is president of the Scientific Commit¬
tee for Antarctic Research and served on the Special
8 Committee for the International Geophysical Year. He
is head of the Department of Cartography at the Na¬
tional Geographic Institute, Paris.
Tass
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
NTERNATIONAL LAND OF SCIENCE
hy Ross C. Peavey
& Laurence M. Gould
L
ong a mystery, later the scene of ad¬
venture and exploration, and finally
an area of the world whose principal
product is fundamental scientific infor¬
mation: this is the history of Antarctica.
The last and most important stage has
been characterized by international
scientific co-operation for the benefit
of mankind without the intrusion of
political tensions and national rivalries
so prevalent in other regions of
the world. (cont'd on next pace)
nil : 1*1 1 \
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
LAND OF SCIENCE (Cont'd)
A TREATY WITHOUT PRECEDENT IN MODERN WORLD HISTORY
The culmination of Antarctic collaboration took place
on December 1, 1959, when a 12-nation treaty was signed
at Washington, D. C, ensuring that Antarctica will
continue to be used for peaceful purposes only. The
Antarctic Treaty, unique in modern diplomatic history,
must be listed as one of the more Important results of the
International Geophysical Year (IGY) of 1957-1958.
The IGY, man's most ambitious attempt to understand
better his physical environment, inevitably focused much
attention on Antarctica. The IGY was an endeavour-
to observe our whole planet and the atmosphere that
surrounds it; to ensure a global picture, it was necessary
to enlist the co-operation of the scientists of all nations
and to co-ordinate their observations. Full geographic
coverage demanded specific data from the southern
continent. Thus it was that the global aspect of the IGY
led to the scientific investigations which opened up
Antarctica, and to the international collaboration which
has been the essential ingredient in scientific under¬
standing of the Antarctic.
In recent years international scientific collaboration
has assumed new meanings and importance, now widely
recognized by national leaders throughout the world. For
this reason, and because of the growing recognition of the
need for even greater knowledge of the world in which
we live, it is profitable to examine the history of the
Antarctic scientific programme, the factors which have
contributed to its extraordinary success, and to look
toward the future.
The Antarctic research programme of the International
Geophysical Year was the first large-scale and concerted
international effort to investigate the scientific secrets of
this vast unknown continent and Its environs. Never¬
theless, the numerous expeditions of geographical
exploration and scientific study conducted in the decades
La Uruguay, Ar¬
gentine vessel
which rescued the
crew of the Swedish
shi p, Antarctica,
trapped in southern
ice pack in 1903,
is shown on this
stamp issued on
50th anniversary of
Uruguay's exploit.
science in the context of an Antarctic programme. In
summary, they are:
Scientific knowledge derives from the synthesis of
ideas, principles, and research developed by able scientists
of all nations.
Science develops best in the environment of free
communications.
Direct access to things and processes in nature is
fundamental to basic scientific advances.
Common standards of observation and measure¬
ment and a common pool of basic data are essential for
s.s - , .,' .-- ..
\ mhñvmm's.wm
Antarctic penguin and
Japanese Antarctic ship.
Soya, figure on this 1957
stamp issued to mark part
played by Japan in the
IGY Antarctic research.
the description and understanding of the physical
phenomena under investigation.
Means for full co-operation among scientists have
become necessary for detailed observation of varying
phenomena, a criterion particularly applicable to the
study of transient geophysical phenomena.
Modern means of transportation and communication
and many post-war developments in scientific instru¬
mentation facilitated application of these principles and
thus made possible a concerted programme of geophysical
research in the Antarctic during the International
Geophysical Year.
From the start of the planning, international co-op¬
eration and a willingness to adjust national programmes
for common goals prevailed in the development of the
IGY Antarctic programme. First, scientists of each
country prepared their own plans to implement IGY
objectives. Scientists of many countries (Argentina,
Australia, Belgium, Chile, France, Japan, New Zealand,
Norway, South Africa, the United Kingdom, the U.S.S.R.,
and the USA) then met in a series of regional conferences
before the IGY provided scientific contributions of great
value which can never be discounted in the unfolding
scientific knowledge of the continent.
Some of these expeditions were, in fact, primarily
scientific in purpose and several were international In
character (in recent history, for example, one should note
the collaborative work of the Norwegian-British-Swedish
Antarctic Expedition of 1949-1952, the British-Australian-
New Zealand Antarctic Research Expedition of 1929-1931
and the British-United States Wilkins-Hearst Antarctic
Expedition in 1928-1929).
The work of scientists on all of these previous expe¬
ditions provided an invaluable base on which to develop,
as a major part of the IGY programme, a co-ordinated
attack in the geophysical sciences in Antarctica. Here,
in particular, factors of terrain, inhospitable environment,
remoteness, and the great size of the unknown area
clearly postulated an international approach for the
programme. These factors are related so directly to the
guiding principles upon which the whole IGY programme
was based that it may toe useful briefly to consider these
principles for international scientific co-operation in
Belgian explorer, Adrien
de Gerlache, who led
an Antarctic expedition
In 1897, is seen on
stamp by which Belgium
commemorated expedi¬
tion's 50th anniversary.
BF1GII BLLUIUUll
to exchange information on these plans and to consider
necessary adjustments.
As in the global IGY programme, the spirit of
international collaboration and scientific give-and-take,
in the common interests of the maximum Antarctic'
research effort, was notable. Mutual problems were
discussed and resolved, gaps in station coverage of
Antarctica were defined and voluntarily filled by
increased programme efforts of several countries, mutual
logistics-support arrangements were outlined, and a
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
successful plan for Interstation radio communications
was established.
Similarly, the actual IGY Antarctic operational pro¬
gramme was replete with occasions of international
collaboration. Space does not permit recounting all of
these occasions, but a few of the more significant should
be briefly cited. An IGY International Antarctic Weather
Central was established, not only to permit Immediate
research in Antarctic meteorology tout also to permit the
regular development and dissemination of dally weather
forecasts so important to all of the Antarctic stations in
the day-to-day conduct of their research arid logistics
operations. Although operated by United States scien¬
tists, the Weather Central was truly international in
character with scientists from Argentina, Australia,
France, New Zealand, Union of South Africa and the
U.S.S.R. participating fully in its work.
A programme for the exchange of scientists was Institut¬
ed, whereby research workers of one country joined In
the programmes of other countries, thus enabling a free
and prolonged exchange of scientific information, ex¬
perience in working with different equipment, and mutual
collaboration in standardization or interpretation of data.
The Antarctic radio communications network proved
effective in many ways: meteorological data were rapidly
collected for use by the Weather Central and forecasts
then disseminated; warnings of significant geophysical
:^	7\]
IWTESN
GEOFTBSK JU
1ISÏIt«
Wa^^
Norway's Antarctic ter¬
ritory, Queen Maud Land,
is shaded area on the
map of the continent seen
in this stamp marking
Norway's contribution In
IGY Antarctic research.
events were promptly distributed throughout the contin¬
ent; mutual scientific problems were discussed; and
emergency situations were made known where common
assistance could be of help.
Several countries conducted scientific traverses, each for
their own specific research objectives with common
scientific goals, but all contributing to a comprehensive
understanding of the extent of the vast Antarctic Ice cap
which covers the continent and to a delineation of the
underlying terrain features.
In some cases stations were operated jointly, as in the
case of the Hallett Station at Cape Adare where New
Zealand and United States scientists have now colla¬
borated for some five years.
Perhaps most illustrative of International co-operation
in Antarctica and the surrounding oceans is the direct
logistics assistance given to other expeditions; the record
of the scientific effort in this region is full of examples In
which nationality had no part of icebreakers relieving
ice-bound ships or aircraft flying to the rescue of beleag¬
uered personnel.
Although it is not the purpose of this article to recount
or evaluate in detail the scientific findings in Antarctica
since the inception of the IGY, It ls profitable to summar¬
ize at this point three significant contributions of the
programme.
First, the purely scientific results, and their scientific
meanings, both regionally and globally, have been unpar¬
alleled in history.
Second, quite aside from the importance of the research
investigations themselves, these findings are destined to
ROSES IN THE ANTARCTIC, but In this case on a
cake being cut by Phillip Law, of Australian Antarctic
Expedition. Cake was baked for a reception given to Aus¬
tralia'» Antarctic team at French base of Dumont-d'Urvllle.
have practical Impacts of great value. Here It ls only
necessary to suggest the progress already occurring In the
understanding of Antarctic meteorology and the conse¬
quent Improvements to Southern Hemisphere weather
forecasting, or the advances to be anticipated In radio
communications through our Increased understanding of
physical processes In the Antarctic upper atmosphere and
Ionosphere.
Third, International collaboration in the programme
has led to the close and personal association of able scien¬
tists from many countries, associations which, unimpeded
by political restraints, have been down-to-earth and have
led to lasting friendships and scientific associations,
mutual appreciation of problems and goals, and perhaps
even In some measure, to the relaxation of current-day
political tensions.
Fourth, successful negotiation of the Antarctic Treaty.
As the Antarctic scientific programme progressed, It
soon became apparent that the scientific discoveries were
coming too fast and their significance, both regional and
global, was too great to stop with the official termination
of the IGY research effort. Much had been learned, but
scientists In many fields recognized that the search for
scientific knowledge had only begun. Moreover, great
effort and Investments in station facilities and scientific
equipment had been made, which could be capitalized
upon to continue the programme at relatively little extra
cost.
Consequently, even during the first months of IGY,
recommendations were made to the International Council
of Scientific Unions (ICSU), that a means be found to sus¬
tain international scientific co-operation in Antarctic
research following the close of the IGY. The ICSU
responded by establishing a Special Committee on Antarc¬
tic Research (SCAR) with representation provided by
Interested constituent scientific unions and by the scien-
11
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
LAND OF SCIENCE (Cont'd)
WORLD ROSTER OF SCIENTISTS
tifie academies of the twelve countries already conducting
Antarctic research.
As in the IGY programme, SCAR has preserved and
extended the character and conduct of international co¬
operation in planning and implementing Antarctic re¬
search. The close personal relations initiated during IGY
among scientists of many nations have been cemented in
the continuing SCAR deliberations and have been valu¬
ably augmented by a growing body of participants with
first-hand Antarctic experience.
Through working groups in each principal scientific
field SCAR has built upon and extended the IGY pro¬
gramme of research. New programmes in the fields of
biology, geology, and cartography have been added to
those in geophysics. At each SCAR meeting the status
of the scientific programme is assessed and modified as
necessary, so that scientists of all participating countries
are working toward common goals with mutual interna¬
tional scientific appreciation of the programme aims.
12
In several fields SCAR has initiated new efforts
in international collaboration. A SCAR inter¬
national register of scientists has been established by
which research workers from any country can make their
interests in Antarctic research known to the planners in
countries already conducting programmes; this register,
although only established in recent months, affords a real
opportunity to find and utilize mature and able scientists
to best advantage in research without regard to their
national origins.
At its fourth meeting in September 1960, SCAR recog¬
nized the special problems of nature conservation occa¬
sioned by continued human activity in the Antarctic.
SCAR noted the Antarctic environment as one of the im¬
portant bio-geographical regions of the world from a
scientific standpoint and developed a series of recommen¬
dations for international co-operation in protection and
conservation of its unique life forms.
SCAR early made arrangements for continuation of the
IGY International Antarctic Weather Central as a perma¬
nent part of the post-IGY scientific programme; with the
collaboration of the Australian Meteorological Service, a
permanent International Antarctic Analysis Centre was
established at Melbourne in 1959. This Centre, continuing
the work of the IGY Weather Central, is placing greater
emphasis on basic meteorological research and its south¬
ern hemispheric effects. To date, scientists from Argen¬
tina, Australia, France and the United States have parti¬
cipated in the work of the Analysis Centre.
In related fields also, SCAR has taken measures to colla¬
borate with other international programmes in geophy¬
sics: the World Magnetic Survey, the ICSU international
programme for the Year of the Quiet Sun, studies of the
earth's crust and upper mantle, and the SCAR Indian
Ocean Expedition are particularly noteworthy in this
regard.
Thus, through many avenues SCAR has recognized the
urgent need for international scientific co-operation in
Antarctic research. As in the IGY, such research becomes
the vehicle by which scientists of many nations, collabo¬
rating fully and freely, can provide the common ingre¬
dient so necessary to further scientific understanding of
the region.
Political leaders throughout the world have recognized
the unique qualities of the Antarctic research pro¬
gramme and, in 1958, moved to preserve this amicable
accord. Upon the invitation of President Eisenhower,
representatives of the 12 nations then conducting Antarc¬
tic scientific investigations met to develop the terms of a
treaty which, in the words of the President, would
promote:
ARMADA
OF PEACE
A U.S. Navy tractor team (above)
leaves Little America on a 600 mile
trip to a scientific base in Marie Byrd
Land. Right, an American photo¬
grapher-scientist learns about An¬
tarctic weather the hard way when
caught in a three-day blizzard. Note
face mask coated with ice. Below,
International solidarity of science :
Soviet and U.S. explorers meet
at the South Pole (shown opposite).
USIS-
A. Maximova-Soviet photo
CONT'D ON PAGE 14
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
!AÍ
U.S. Navy
I
SOUTH POLE
Air view of Amundsen-
Scott Station set up by the
U.S.A. for IGY research.
Exact site of geographic
South Pole (at top) is 'mark¬
ed by a circle of barrels. This
South Pole Station was estab¬
lished and is maintained by
"Operation Deep Freeze".
USIS 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
LAND OF SCIENCE (Cont'd)
NUCLEAR EXPLOSIONS BANNED
"Freedom of scientific investigations throughout An¬
tarctica by citizens, organizations and governments of all
countries; and a continuation of the international scien¬
tific co-operation which is being carried out so success¬
fully during the current International Geophysical Year."
These overtures resulted in an Antarctic treaty confe¬
rence which convened in Washington, October 15 to
December 1, 1959. The product was the Antarctic Treaty,
agreed to by representatives of all twelve nations, and
now ratified by all of them. The treaty contains the
following important principles governing future activities
in Antarctica:
The continuation of international scientific co-op¬
eration which characterized activities of the IGY and
SCAR programmes.
The reservation of Antarctica for peaceful purposes
only.
Preservation of the status quo on all national terri¬
torial claims for 30 years and a provision that no scientific
activity during this period shall be used as the basis
for asserting a claim.
The prohibition of activities for military purposes
and the prohibition of nuclear explosions, and
A system of free inspection of any part of Antarctica
by observers of signatory nations.
The successful negotiation of the Treaty can
only be ascribed to the groundwork in interna¬
tional collaboration laid by the world's scientists in
planning and undertaking the comprehensive Antarctic
scientific programme of the IGY and the following years.
Especially during the decade preceding the IGY, several
nations had attempted to secure international agreements
on Antarctica through negotiations within the United
Nations. All of these attempts had foundered on the
troublesome problems of territorial claims and for want
of the harmonious and co-operative international arran¬
gements developed by the IGY and SCAR programmes.
This unprecedented contribution by science to interna¬
tional diplomacy was widely acknowledged by national
throughout the Treaty negotiations and, indeed,
is the theme of the preamble of the formal Treaty
document.
It is not surprising, therefore, that continued inter¬
national co-operation in Antarctic scientific investigations
is also the central theme of the Treaty Articles of Agree¬
ment. During the 30-year tenure of the treaty, provision
is made for full international exchange regarding nation¬
al scientific programmes in Antarctica, the exchange of
scientific personnel between expeditions and scientific
stations, and the full and free interchange of scientific
observations and results.
There seems little doubt that new scientific data and
results will continue to be the principal export from
Antarctica for many years to come. Successful negotia¬
tion of the Antarctic Treaty acknowledges science as its
goal, and the Treaty Agreements preserve the favourable
climate for international scientific activities. Thus, in
Antarctica the coming years should continue to produce
scientific discoveries and results of great significance to
basic research as well as many practical applications for
the benefit of all.
14
Ross C. Peavey and Laurence M. Gould are respectively
executive secretary and chairman of the Committee on Polar
Research U.S. National Academy of Sciences. Dr. Peavey is one
of the editors of the two-volume study, Science in Antarctica
produced by the Committee for the National Academy of Sciences
(Publication N". 839 and 878). Dr. Gould has led expeditions to
the Arctic and Antarctic and was director of the U.S. Antarctica
programme during the IGY.
Photos Courtesy Scott Polar Research Institute
DISCOVERY
EXPLORATION
ADVENTURE
8c COURAGE
by G. de Q. Robin
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
DISCOVERY & EXPLORATION (Cont'd)
First winter on the icepack
Cook's voyage farthest south by penetrating the Weddell
Sea to 74° 15 S with two small vessels, the brig Jane of
160 tons and the cutter Beaufoy of 65 tons.
John Biscoe circumnavigated the continent during the
years 1830-32 in similar ships under trying conditions,
during which the effective crew of each ship was at times
reduced to three men due to scurvy and other illnesses.
He sighted similar rising snow slopes to those seen by
Bellingshausen, but thought them caused by the freezing
of the sea. He then saw the rock peaks exposed at about
50° E which he named Cape Ann. After retreating to
Tasmania during the winter, he discovered the Adelaide
Islands near the Antarctic peninsula.
Two other sealing captains, Kemp and Balleny, made
further discoveries of land within the Antarctic circle at
60° E and 165° E during this decade, but national expedi¬
tions were responsible for the major discoveries during
the period 1837 to 1843.
The first of these was the French expedition of 1837-40
under Dumont D'Urvllle, who worked westwards around
the continent from the peninsula. On January 22, 1840,
he discovered Terre Adâie in 138° E, and landed there
to take formal possession for France. Nine days later he
sighted another stretch of coastline, but by one of those
strange twists of fortune that occur in Antarctic history,
it was found that the United States Exploring Expedition
of 1838-42 under Charles Wilkes had sighted the same
coast a few hours earlier.
This latter expedition sailed only after considerable
public pressure on the United States Government to
Initiate exploratory activities at least equal to those of
European countries. Wilkes claimed the discovery of
some 1,500 miles of coastline from around 166° E to 106" E.
Although some of the eastern stretch of this "continental"
coastline was subsequently shown not to exist, most of
his work has proved substantially correct.
The British expedition of 1839-43 sent out by the Royal
Society of London and the Admiralty under the command
of James Clark Ross, the discoverer of the north magnetic
pole, also had the joint aims of scientific investigations
and discovery. Ross was given a chart of Wilkes's
discoveries and he knew of the work of Dumont D'Urville.
Realising that he was unlikely to reach the south
magnetic pole by following their tracks, he struck farther
east hoping to find a more southerly passage which would
lead him to the magnetic pole.
Instead he succeeded in charting 500 miles of the
mountainous coastline of Victoria Land, and 500 miles of
a floating ice barrier, now called the Ross Ice Shelf, which
made further progress to the south by sea impossible. He
completed his circumnavigation by adding his contribution
to the known islands in the region of the peninsula, in
this case on the less accessible eastern coast.
These discoveries by sealing ships and national expedi¬
tions were used for Colton's map of the Antarctic In 1855
which showed the outline of an Antarctic continent much
as we know it today. In terms of the available ships and
techniques, the achievements between 1819 and 1843 were
unparalleled.
Interest In the Antarctic dropped during the next fifty
years, although commercial activity in hunting the
dwindling stock of seals and in exploiting the large whale
population continued in sub-Antarctic waters. But a
notable contribution was made during this otherwise quiet
period by the voyage of the Challenger of 1872-76. In
addition to this expedition's many contributions to
biological and physical oceanography, and its charts of
several sub-Antarctic Islands, it showed that rocks
dropped from Antarctic icebergs on to the ocean bed were
typical of a continental origin.
With the twentieth century came steam power, providing
a new means of manoeuvring ships through pack ice.
Stirring appeals at meetings of the International
Geographical Union stimulated such activity that expedi¬
tions set out from many countries during the twenty years
preceeding World War I. In 1893-94, a Norwegian
whaling expedition under C. A. Larsen mapped the east
ICE-BOUND Antarctic exploration vessel, the "Gauss", photographed from a captive balloon. The German
expedition led by Erich von Drygalski used the balloon to extend the range of observation. Filled with
hydrogen it rose to about 1,000 feet from where the observer in its basket could relay information by
telephone. This photograph of the "Gauss" in the pack ice was taken by Emile Philippi, on March 29, I 902.
From " Deutsche Sud Polar Expedition ", 1901-1903 by E. von Drygalski. Reimer, Berlin, 1912.
^CV~' '. .1*1 j *
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
James Cook F. Bellingshausen
Julian Irlzar J. Baptiste Charcot
J. Dumont-d'Urville A. de Gerlache J. Clark Ross E. von Drygalskl
E. Shackleton Roald Amundsen R. Falcon Scott Richard Byrd
TRAIL BLAZERS OF ANTARCTICA
JAMES COOK (1726-1779). British
navigator, first to cross Antarctic Circle
(1773) and map deep southern latitudes.
Failed to find Antarctic land, but believed
a frozen continent existed to far south.
FABIEN BELLINGSHAUSEN (1778-
1852). Russian explorer, first to reach
Antarctica on January 28, 1820 and cir¬
cumnavigate it between 1819- 1 82 I. His
ship, "Vostok" was accompanied by the
"Mirny" under M. P. Lazareff. He sighted
mountains thus confirming that land and
not merely a frozen sea existed there.
JULES DUMONT D'URVILLE (1790-
1842). His French expedition was first to
land on Antarctic terrain on January 22,
1840. He named it Adélie Land.
JAMES CLARK ROSS (1800-1862)'.
Leader of British scientific expedition which
charted 500 miles of Victoria Land and
500 miles of floating ice barrier (now
named after him) while searching (1839-
42) for South Magnetic Pole.
ADRIEN DE GERLACHE (1866-1934)
whose Belgian expedition (1897-99) waa
the first to winter south of Antarctic Circle.
ERICH VON DRYGALSKI (1865-1 949).
led German expedition in specially built
vessel "Gauss" to carry out important
scientific studies ( I 90 1-03). Made meteo¬
rological and magnetic observations with
Scott's "Discovery" expedition.
JULIAN IRIZAR ( I 869- 1 93 5), Argentine
naval officer, whose ship "Uruguay" rescued
Swedish expedition of Otto Nordenskjold
marooned in 1903 after its ship, "Antarc¬
tica" was crushed the ice.
JEAN-BAPTISTE CHARCOT (1867-
1922). French scientist and explorer,
charted large areas of western Antarctica
during voyages in 1903 and 1908.
ERNEST SHACKLETON (1874- 1922)
whose British expedition (1907-09) came
to within 97 miles of South Pole and
reached South Magnetic Pole. For story
of Endurance see page 1 5. Died while
leading a later expedition to Antarctica.
ROALD AMUNDSEN (1872-1928).
Norwegian Antarctic and Arctic explorer,
he led first party to reach the South Pole
(See page I 8).
ROBERT FALCON SCOTT (1868-
1912) led first parties to penetrate any
distance into Antarctica (1901-1904).
Reached South Pole one month after
Amundsen (sec page 19).
RICHARD BYRD (1888-1957). United
States explorer and leading figure in deve¬
lopment of modern Antarctic exploration
methods, employing aircraft and mechan¬
ical vehicles. Led three expeditions
between 1928 and 1941.
coast of the peninsula to 68" 10' S, and returned unscathed
a feat which has not been repeated so far south on this
coast to the present day. The coastline south of this
point has been mapped only by aircraft and dog-sledging
parties during recent years.
The first major national expedition of this period came
from Belgium under de Gerlache in the Bélgica, with an
international complement of scientists and crew, Including
the mate, Roald Amundsen, who subsequently reached the
south pole. The doctor was F. A. Cook, who subsequently
claimed to be the first man to reach the north pole,
although Peary's claim has since been generally accepted.
The Bélgica was caught for the winter In the pack ice,
and the party thus became the first men to winter south
of the Antarctic circle
Before the Bélgica returned, the first expedition to make
a planned wintering on the continent had set out in the
British vessel "Southern Cross" under Borchgrevink, the
Norwegian explorer, with a party mainly consisting of his
compatriots. This expedition carried out a planned series
of scientific observations at Cape Adare while the ship
retired out of the pack Ice and returned the following
summer, thus setting a pattern which ls followed exten¬
sively at the present time. Borchgrevink also landed on
Ross's ice barrier and sledged a short distance over the
ice shelf to reach 78° 50' S, the record at that time.
Again, this pattern was widely followed during the next
twelve years.
Due perhaps to newspaper rather than official backing,
and to some shortcomings In the scientific results,
Borchgrevlnk's contributions to the techniques of
Antarctic exploration have been overshadowed, probably
unjustly, -by the more famous nationally sponsored
expeditions of the following four years.
These national expeditions all carried experienced
scientific staffs to Investigate fields such as biology and
geomagnetism, as well as furthering geographical
exploration. The German expedition of 1901-03 under
Drygalskl In the Gauss wintered in the pack about 90°E,
close to the coastline, which was reached by sledging
parties. This expedition, and that of Scott at the same
time, sent observers aloft on captive balloons to extend
the range of discoveries, but this technique has not since
been used.
The Swedish South Polar Expedition of 1901-04 under
Dr. Otto Nordenskjold wintered on Snow Hill Island early
in 1902 off the eastern coast of the Antarctic peninsula.
Their ship, the Antarctic, under CA. Larsen, was unable ^
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
A VICTORY
A
---«... *"
AMUNDSEN. On December 14, 1911,
Roald Amundsen pitched a tent at the South
Pole and took this historic photograph of his
companions standing bareheaded before Nor¬
way's flag. Amundsen's journey had begun
In 1910 when he set sail from Norway in the
From, the ship already made famous by the
arctic exploits of the Norwegian explorer,
Fridtjof Nansen. By February 19 I I, Amundsen
had reached the Ross Ice Shelf where he win
tered at a latitude of 79 degrees. In October,
at the start of the Antarctic spring, he set
off with four companions, five sledges, 70 dogs
and provisions for four months. Crossing the
Ross Ice Shelf, the party advanced Into the
interior of the continent, covering about 20
miles each day. To do so it had to pass over
the mountains of the Queen Maud Range at
heights of 13,000 feet and later the polar
plateau at over I 1,000 feet. The five men
were the first to reach the South Pole. Con¬
sidering the terrible weather they encoun¬
tered they accomplished their journey with
Incredible speeda total of 97 days outward
and return. Born In Norway in 1872, Amund¬
sen dedicated his life to exploration. On
June 18, 1928, he left Tromso by air to
help in the search for the missing Arctic
expedition of the Italian general Nobile. From
this flight Roald Amundsen never returned.
DISCOVERY & EXPLORATION (Cont'd)
to reach them the next summer and two men from the
ship set off by sledge to try to contact the expedition. The
Antarctic was finally crushed in the ice, the crew taking
refuge on Paulet Island.
The two-man sledging party finally reached the main
party on Snow Hill Island in October, 1903, after a winter
spent feeding on penguins, in a primitive stone hut.
Meanwhile the lack of news led Argentina to send out a
naval vessel, the Uruguay, to search for the expedition,
which was located on November 8. A few hours later
the first survivors from Paulet Island reached the base at
Snow Hill, just before the relief ship was due to sail. The
whole expedition was then safely extricated, thanks to
this extraordinary good fortune and the successful search
under Captain Irizar of the Argentinian Navy.
Scott's Discovery expedition of 1901-04 was the chief
British National Expedition of this period. The ship
remained frozen into the Ice of McMurdo Sound for two
years while Scott led the first parties to penetrate any
considerable distance into the interior of the continent.
He first sledged south over the Ross Ice Shelf to 77° 59' S,
and then, the following summer, through the mountains
of Victoria Land on a journey to the west. He found only
a high, featureless plateau of ice beyond the mountains.
The fourth notable expedition of this time, the Scottish
National Antarctic Expedition of 1902-04, under W. S.
Bruce, tried to penetrate the ice of the Weddell Sea and
discovered Coats Land on the eastern side of the Sea. It
was a forbidding, ice-covered land bounded by high cliffs
which prevented a landing.
The expedition started a meteorological and magnetic
observatory on Laurie Island in the South Orkneys, and
since they were unable to ensure its continued support
j g from Scottish sources, they handed it over to Argentina
at the end of the expedition. The observatory has since
been maintained continuously by Argentina, and provides
the longest run of meteorological records now available
from such a high southern latitude.
Meanwhile, the French Antarctic Expedition of 1903-05
under J. B. Charcot, was working on the western side of
the Antarctic peninsula, and from 1908-10 Charcot
continued investigations in the same area.
Edward Shackleton, the most outstanding leader of men
in the Antarctic during the twentieth century, led the
British Antarctic Expedition of 1907-09. After wintering
at Cape Royds in McMurdo Sound, he followed his earlier
path with Scott over the Ross Ice Shelf, using ponies to
draw the sledges over the flat surface. Shackleton
discovered the Beardmore Glacier, which he ascended to
the polar plateau by manhauling, and pressed on to within
97 miles of the south pole. At this point, so close to
success, he estimated that he could go no further if his
party was to return alive, so he turned around and was
just able to get back to McMurdo Sound.
His judgment in returning has never been questioned,
since most leaders would have turned back sooner.
Instead, he was widely acclaimed for the biggest advance
of any expedition towards either of the poles. His
northern sledging party under Professor Edgeworth David
reached the South Magnetic Pole for the first time while
Shackleton was making his dash.
The next five years not only saw the struggle to reach
the pole, and Shackleton's attempt to cross the continent,
but also ushered in an era of increasing scientific study.
It is little wonder after Shackleton's success that Scott's
Terra Nova expedition of 1910-13 should choose ponies as
the main form of transport in preference to dogs, which
had not performed well on the Discovery expedition.
Amundsen, on the other hand, handled dogs superbly,
and after wintering in the Fram in 1911 at the Bay of
Whales on the far side of the Ross Ice Shelf from Scott,
he was the first to reach the pole by a month.
The heroism of Scott's struggle to reach the pole, only
to find the Norwegian flag there, and his ill luck with
weather on the way back which caused the deaths of the
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A DRAMA
«i
Fifty
years ago
FIRST MEN
REACH THE
SOUTH POLE
Photos courtesy Scott Police Reseirch Instil
SCOTT. On January 17, 1912, Scott reach¬
ed the Pole only to find the Norwegian flag
(above) which had been raised there by
Amundsen nearly one month earlier. Scott
did not follow the same route to the South
Pole as Amundsen, and he took motor-sledges
and ponies with him instead of dogs. But the
sledges were soon out of action and the
ponies had to be destroyed on the outward
journey which was made In fierce snow
blizzards and lasted no less than 79 days.
It is easy to Imagine the despondency and
disappointment of Scott and his companions
when they realized they had lost the race to
the Pole. Ill luck dogged them on their return
journey when the same blinding blizzards
lashed them, for 57 days, bringing their
venture to a tragic end. Evans and Oatcs
were the first to die. Scott, Bowers and
Wilson still steadfastly guarded their notes,
their photographs and the geological speci¬
mens which proved that a sub-tropical climate
once existed In Antarctica. They perished of
cold and hunger less than a dozen miles from
a depot of food and fuel. In the diary, which he
kept until his strength ebbed away, Scott wrote:
"I do not regret this journey... We have been
willing to give our lives for this enterprise...
Take comfort In that I die In peace with
the world and myself and am not afraid."
S
'0
u^
Il 4^/>~
7. p*"
' /t&f.
At the end of 1961 an Anglo-Norwegian ceremony took place at the South Pole
Amundsen-Scott station of the United States. To mark the fiftieth anniversary
of the conquest of the South Pole a commemorative plaque was placed there (below)
to honour the first two expeditions to reach the Pole. The plaque bears the names
of Roald Amundsen and his companions O. B|aaland, H. Hansscn, E, Hassel and
O. Wistingand those of Robert Scott and his partyE.A. Wilson, L.E. Oatcs,
H.R. Bowers and E. Evans. It was placed In position by Tore Gjclsvlk (standing
behind 'It, centre) of the Norwegian Polar Institute and, Gordon de Q. Robin (author
of this article, standing left of the plaque). Left, photo taken on December 14, 1911
at the South Pole showing Olav Bjaaland and Oscar Wisting making meteorological
observations. The photo was autographed by Bjaaland In 1 960 shortly before his death.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
DISCOVERY & EXPLORATION (Co»«)
From dog sledges to sno-cats
members of the party within 11 miles of ample food are
well known. The scientific investigations of the expedition
set standards which many have tried to follow but few
have attained. Amundsen's example with dogs has been
widely followed, and at present many still consider them
the safest' form of transport for detailed study of difficult
mountain regions of the Antarctic.
At the same time as Amundsen and Scott were
establishing their bases, Filchner's German South Polar
Expedition of 1910-12 succeeded in reaching Vahsel Bay
at 78° S, the southern-most point of the Weddell Sea, but
was forced to winter on the expedition ship in the
drifting pack. Unlike Shackleton's, four years later,
Filchner's ship survived.
Shackleton, with the British Imperial Trans-Antarctic
Expedition of 1914-16, attempted to reach Vahsel Bay to
establish a wintering base from which to cross the
continent, but he also was forced to winter in the pack
ice. After his ship Endurance sank, his achievements In
extricating his party without loss of life were an epic.
The work of Bruce, Shackleton and Filchner at this
period resulted in the mapping of most of the eastern
side of the Weddell Sea.
Japan entered Antarctic exploration for the first time
with its South Polar Expedition of 1911-12 under Shirase,
while the Australian Antarctic Expedition of 1911-14 under
Mawson, who had accompanied David to the south
magnetic pole, mounted two bases and mapped extensive
coastal areas to the south of Australia.
This expedition was the first to maintain radio
communications with the outside world. The long radio
wave lengths used at that time necessitated an interme¬
diate station on Macquarie Island to relay messages to
Australia, and the project was a success. The extreme
winds experienced at the expedition's main base, Cape
Denison, deserve mention, as they poured down off the
slopes from the inland ice and averaged some 50 ¡m.p.h.
during the whole year.
Although the first years of this century have
been called the heroic era of Antarctic explor¬
ation, they foreshadowed the mechanical era which
followed. Shackleton in 1907-09 took the first mechanical
transport to Antarctica, an Arrol-Johnson motor car
which performed usefully over the sea ice of McMurdo
Sound. Scott took three tracklaying vehicles south, two
of which helped drag stores over the Ross Ice Shelf.
Mawson's expedition of 1911 might well have led the way
in polar flying but for an accident to the aeroplane in
Adelaide which destroyed .the wings. They, nevertheless,
took the reanainder of the plane south and used it as a
propellor-drlven vehicle for some short runs. None of
these experiments, however, proved of major benefit at
the time.
The effectiveness of mechanical transport in Antarctic
exploration, both on the surface and in the air, was
shown between the wars. The main credit for this must
go to the United States expeditions under Byrd and
Ellsworth, although British and Norwegian expeditions
also developed the technique. The first flight in
Antarctica was made by the British and United States
Wilkins-Hearst Antarctic Expedition. Wilkins, in spite of
bad weather, flew to 71° 20' S down the Antarctic
peninsula, which he concluded was not continuous, but
consisted of a series of islands.
This was disproved by the British Graham Land
Expedition of 1934-37, who used a light aircraft and dog
sledging methods to explore chiefly the west coast, where
they discovered ICing George V Sound, which was
subsequently shown by Ronne in 1941 to separate
Alexander (Is) Land from the main mass of Antarctica.
Charcot (Is) Land was also considered to be an island as
a result of flights by Wilkins' second (British) expedition.
The three United States expeditions led by Byrd in
20 1928-30, 1933.-35 and 1939-41 all made extensive use of
aircraft ana mechanical vehicles, although some dog
transport was also used, particularly on a long journey
led by Gould during the first expedition. Although he
made the first flight over the South Pole in 1929, Byrd
concentrated mainly on exploration of the sector south
of the Pacific Ocean which had defeated direct approaches
from the sea. He showed that there was no connexion
between the ice shelves at the head of the Ross and
Weddell Seas, and mapped new mountain ranges and
sections of coastline. His second expedition was the first
to try seismic shooting techniques to measure ice
thicknesses in Antarctica.
Another United States citizen, Lincoln Ellsworth, made
several notable flights over the continent, including one
crossing from the peninsula to the Ross Sea. Further
mapping was accomplished by the Norwegian whaling
fleet of Lars Christensen, by the British-Australian-New
Zealand Antarctic Expedition of 1929-31, and the German
New-Schabenland expeditions. The British Discovery
Investigations carried out extensive océanographie studies
of Antarctic and southern seas between the wars but the
war put a temporary stop to exploration by European
countries in 1939 and by the United States in 1941.
The remaining gaps in the Antarctic coastline
were filled In, largely by aerial survey, during
the five years from 1945-50. The United States Navy
operation "Highjump," a private U.S., expedition under
Ronne and the British Falkland Islands Dependencies
Survey all helped to fill major gaps. It has therefore
taken around 130 years to discover the main features of
the Antarctic coast and to open the way for more detailed
studies. Such investigations in the region of the penin¬
sula have now continued for the past fifteen years, where
the topographical mapping by the British, hydrographie
surveys by Argentina and some Chilean work warrant
special mention.
Early in 1950 two expeditions landed on the main block
of "East" Antarctica, the French near 140° E and a com¬
bined Norwegian-British-Swedish expedition at 11° W.
Their use of modern technique to study the upper atmo¬
sphere over the continent and their observations of the
thickness, nourishment and temperature of the ice sheet
showed the need for a comprehensive attack on the
scientific problems of the continent.
The subsequent planning of the International
Geophysical Year opened the way for a major inter¬
national effort, of which the achievements are too
numerous to mention in a short article such as this.
Overland parties have covered some 9,300 miles, generally
sounding the ice cover along their routes, and many miles
of aerial reconnaissance and mapping have now given us
an idea of the nature of four-fifths of the interior of the
continent, and of the principal mountain ranges. The
huge dome of ice of "East" Antarctica, rising to some
13,000 feet above sea level, contrasts with the two great
seas and ice shelves located in the western hemisphere.
Between these shelves the few mountains exposed could
better be called islands than continents since great
thicknesses of ice rest on a rock floor below the present
sea level over wide areas. In fact, should the ice sheet
be removed, it is likely that the great Antarctic peninsula
would toe a large island separated from continental East
Antarctica.
It is clear that the discovery and exploration of the
Antarctic continent cannot be credited to any one nation.
It is the result of the work of very many expeditions
a truly international achievement to the credit of a few
generations between the eighteenth and twentieth
centuries.
Gordon de Q. Robin is director of the Scott Polar Research
Institute in Cambridge, England, and secretary of the
Scientific Committee for Antarctic Research of the Inter¬
national Council of Scientific Unions (ICSU). He was a
member of the Norwegian-British-Swedish Antarctic
Expedition (1949-1951).
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
LIVING AT
BELOW
TO° C
ERO
by Paul A. Sipie
This scientist participating In America's "Operation
Deep Freeze" in Antarctica, wears full face mask and
dark goggles as protection against wind, ice and snow.
In Antarctic temperatures a nose can freeze In seconds.
The U.S.A. established five major Antarctic stations
during the IGY, four of which are still In operation.
USIS. US Navy
Most persons who view Antarctica only from a
great distance, recoil at the thought of per¬
sonally visiting the region, sure that they could not stand
the torture of Intense cold. Even those who live In parts
of the world where snow Is unknown have sensed the
unpleasant sensations and pain associated with unsea¬
sonably cool periods. If I feel so miserable on a chilly
CONT'D ON PACE 24
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
i '-'« Vi'* M.-"
* £, /«' ¿ J*
RE NO WAN EVER TROD
sftig td over 16,000 feet this
ighty mass of rock dominates
II other peaks or the Sentinel
nge in the Ellsworth Highlands
Antárctica. No man ever set
ot on these desolate slopes.
--
U.S. Navy
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
70° BELOW ZERO (Cont'd;
The secret of
keeping comfortable
day, they reason, how could I ever stand temperatures
of minus ten, let alone minus seventy.
Fortunately for the explorers of Antarctica, who of
course need to learn the technology and use of protective
clothing and shelter, nature too helps to make the cold
more tolerable. First of all, the body itself adjusts by an
acclimatization process to conserve its heat better and
tolerate the sensation of cold more comfortably. This
adjustment alone is roughly worth the equivalent of at
least one layer of clothing. Secondly, cold climate visitors
are relieved to discover that intensity of pain sensation
does not increase proportionately to the degree of cold¬
ness.
Pain due to cold is nature's way of warning the cons¬
cious mind that unless something is done to correct the
situation, we may get into trouble. It is like a fire alarm
which is just as loud and noisy for a little fire as it is for
a disastrous conflagration. Therefore, anyone exposed to
an unseasonably chilly day in the temperature or even
sub-tropic zone when inadequately clothed or sheltered,
may suffer just as much as one exposed to extremely low
temperatures in polar regions.
L¡
24
rviNG and working in Antarctica is not at all
(Impossible for anyone who has the desire to
learn how. In fact, it can be enjoyable much of the time.
But there are many things to master and sometimes the
difficulties seem insurmountable to the novice. All his
reading and concepts seem different from what he
actually encounters.
Getting comfortable is perhaps the first problem
learning not to get overheated in exercise. Perspiration
can cause accumulation of a kilo or two of water in one's
clothing which later evaporates to chill the wearer or
turns into ice and makes him still more uncomfortable.
An old polar hand working next to the newcomer, just
as hard, ventilates or controls sweating at the right
moments and has dry clothing and no excessive after-
chilling.
Every normal task outdoors seems to take much longer
to perform. Walking is slower, gloved and stiff fingers
hinder dexterity, bulky clothing gets in the way, small
tools laid down beside a worker disappear like magic if
there is enough breeze blowing to shift grains of snow
about. Boxes, barrels, and whole caches of material can
disappear from sight in one blizzard and can be lost for
all time if not marked with poles.
Visibility is hampered by fog and drifting snow or by
white-outs a phenomenon occurring when the whiteness
of cloud cover and the snow surface blend into a shadow¬
less world. Distance becomes hard to judge when there
are no familiar landmarks, such as trees or houses on the
horizon. Wind is not only a furious force, at times whip¬
ping up and filling the air with snow, but the breeze also
intensifies the feeling of cold to three times that of a
calm day. Sun and wind burn the face and dryness cracks
the lips.
Still, after one gets adjusted, the beautiful calm days,
sunsets that last for days, halos, Aurora australis, the vast
quietness, and the quaint animal life, add a charm found
nowhere else. Many learn to love life in the Antarctic and
return time and again.
Man can look back on a long process of overcoming and
adjusting to the extreme environment of the polar regions.
Eskimos developed adequate, though primitive solutions
Photos courtesy of Scott Polar Research Institute
FIRST BALLOON. Members of Scott's "Discovery" expedition
(1901-1904) prepare to send aloft a captive balloon with an observer
in the basket. This method was also used by the German expedition
under Drygalski but was later abandoned as too risky an operation.
FIRST AEROPLANE in the Antarctic was brought by the Australian
expedition under Douglas Mawson (1911). After the wings were
destroyed in an accident, it was used as a propellor-driven vehicle.
Wooden skis protected the propellor from danger of nosing over.
for clothing and shelter against cold. Early polar tra¬
velers adopted these principles and survived. Fur cloth¬
ing, snow or sod huts and dog teams, however, are no
longer compatible with the life and activities of modern
Antarctic exploration.
Roald Amundsen and Robert Peary owed their success
in being first to reach the earth's poles to adopting Eskimo
clothing, protection, and travel methods. Shackleton and
Scott met with less success in their efforts to attain the
South Pole because they tried less well-proven techniques.
On the other hand, though Scott and his men lost their
lives and Shackleton failed to reach the Pole by less than
two degrees of latitude, their parties were equipped to
make better scientific observations.
As a member of Richard Byrd's various Antarctic expe¬
ditions I had the personal privilege of experiencing first
hand the transition of polar technology from the primi¬
tive to modern. In 1928, some 17 years after Amundsen's
and Scott's South Pole ventures, we arrived at the Bay of
Whales, Amundsen's old base site. We not only had dog
teams aboard our sailing vessel, but also three new advan¬
ces in polar technology airplanes, aerial mapping came¬
ras, and radios, offering a safeguard against loss of life
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
FIRST MOTOR CAR to be used in Antarctica was this Arrol-Johnson
12-15 H.P. which Shackleton took with him on his 1907-09 expe¬
dition in the "Nimrod". It proved to be very useful when running
on hard sea ice, but was unable to travel across soft surfaces.
Ta»
FIRST VEHICLES used were sledge and dog teams. Many specialists
still consider them the safest form of transport for detailed study of
difficult mountain terrain. Sometimes they are equipped with a
bicycle wheel and mileometer for clocking distance covered.
on the trail. Radios could have saved the lives of Scott
and his men who died of cold and hunger only a few
miles from help. Primitively, however, we still depended
upon fur clothing, lived in congested quarters to conserve
coal, and our food included use of whale, seal, and pen¬
guin meat to supplement canned, salted and dry rations.
By 1934 most of our material was transported by re¬
inforced metal freight vessels, and tractors were available
to augment dog-team transportation. Six years later our
housing was far more comfortable by comparison and less
congested. Fur clothing was retained for emergency trail
and flight use only. Tractors and airplanes supported
ground parties so that dog teams were no longer heavily
laden. Food included frozen meats, vegetables and fruits.
Amateur radio channels permitted frequent voice contacts
with friends and loved ones. Electric lighting replaced
candles and fuel oil lamps. Labour expended for living
began to lighten and men were free to carry on research
between stints of shoveling snow which had to be melted
for water, little of which was available for baths and
laundry. Toilet facilities were unheated.
After World War II powerful ice-breaking vessels and
Polar town-planning
fast ice-worthy freighters became available. New scien¬
tific curiosity of world-wide geophysical phenomena
pointed to the polar regions as keys to important new
knowledge. The scientific demand for tills knowledge
rose to Its height at the outset of the International Geo¬
physical Year (1957-1958). Not only did 12 of the GO co¬
operating nations decide to establish or utilize some
50 stations in high southern latitudes, but bold concepts
arose to establish observation stations Inland, and criss¬
cross the continent by traverses to study past climate con¬
ditions by seismic measurements of snow accumulation
and total thickness of the ice.
The urgency to learn more about earth phenomena
transcended fears of the ley unknown which In the past
had claimed the lives of men pitted against Its frigid
elements. In 195G France, the United Kingdom, the Soviet
Union, and the United States planned Inland stations In
addition to their coastal quarters at least three of which
were later to house In excess of 100 men over winters.
Although the science programmes were internationally
closely correlated, logistics were largely the responsibility
of the Individual nations. Some countries, such as Bel-
glum, Japan, and New Zealand and South Africa, had not
had recent experience In modern polar operations and
had to make a fresh start; Argentina, Chile, and Great
Britain, on the other hand, converted their operating
bases to IGY use. France had been established in Antarc¬
tica since 1950, Norway, and the United States had more
recent bases, and the U.S.S.R. had developed Its com¬
petence In the high Arctic. Exchange of technology was
freely dispensed to those who needed help, and communi¬
cation, rescue plans and logistic aid, where possible, were
jointly planned.
E nation had its own tastes in housing,
clothing, food, and transportation so that the
stations had their own individual character despite simi¬
larities of purpose. Some stations were built on solid,
snow-free land and others on kilometre-thick snow fields
with no bare rock in sight for hundreds of miles In any
direction.
Building houses on rock or rubble permitted more con¬
ventional construction techniques; foundation excavation,
however, was difficult. Cold and lack of sand Inhibited
the use of concrete and a short summer construction
period demanded the use of impromptu techniques rather
than the best. Sewage and waste dLsposal was difficult,
If Immediate access to the sea was not available. Ponds
or snow patches for water supply were at times located
at considerable distance from the houses. Cables were
essential to anchor the houses against heavy wind and at
least at Hallett Station, the Joint New Zealand-United
States Station, penguins from an adjacent rookery had to
be removed and fenced out to permit flat space for the
camp.
Placing a station on deep snow requires different tech¬
niques. The foundation must be compacted or excavated,
Insulated and blocked to prevent differential settling. At
some stations a deep pit ls dug in which the house ls
erected. Then snow which fills In around the building
provides Insulation necessitating less heating than is
required for houses built on open ground, fully exposed to
excessive wind-chill.
Another technique not requiring excavation Is to build
the houses on the surface and simply let snow drifts
accumulate around the buildings until they are covered
up to the eaves. In this latter construction method stacks
of stores are placed around the houses, covered by chicken
wire and burlap or dunnage and tarpaulins, to form
passages or framed tunnels. Houses buried from the start
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
70» BELOW ZERO (Cont'd)
Fire one of greatest hazards
Australian official photograph
AUSTRALIAN EXPLOR¬
ER demonstrates latest
clothes style in Antarctica.
are usually connected by snow
tunnels dug between build¬
ings. Excavated snow rooms
and snow block storage shel¬
ters save on materials which
must be brought in. Sewage
and refuse are usually dump¬
ed directly into pits. Snow
for water supply is always
close at hand in areas upwind
away from station contamin¬
ation. Ventilation for buried
camps becomes a problem at
times. Added floor vents are
required as well as ventilator
outlets. Carbon monoxide
created by snow covered flues
or icing of condensed moisture is often a hazad.
Fires at isolated drifted-over stations is perhaps the
greatest hazard to men in polar camps. Fires seem to
occur on the coldest or windiest days. Passages can fill
with smoke and fighting tre in submerged snow is next
to imposible. Notonly is Are disastrous to men and
equipment inside the building, but the fire fighters during
a nocturnal blizzard are also exposed to danger decause
often in their haste they rush to the emergency with
insufficient time to clothe themselves properly. The most
disastrous Antarctic fires occured in the 1960-1961 season
at the Soviet Mirny Station where eight Uves were lost
and at the American McMurdo Station with an estimated
property loss of about two-hundred thousand dollars.
Some stations are built from lumber and . materials
similar to normal frame houses, but much time is saved
by having houses prefabricated. A large house can be
assembled in a single work day, if the panels arrive
undamaged and no parts are lost in the thousands of
miles of transit and frequent handling. Gable-roof houses
shed melt-water better, but drifts build higher than on
flat-roofed structures. In deep snow-field areas, drifts
engulf the entire camp to the height of the largest struc
ture. Thin towers or observation booths placed above the
surface on legs, permit the wind to blow past without
dumping its load of snow.
Inland stations were handled in different ways. The
British built South Ice Station, Lat. 82° S., Long. 29° W.,
in a hole by constructing a sturdy building for three men
of timbers taken in by tractor. France's Station Charcot,
Lat. 69° 30' S., Long. 140° E., was a small, arched roof
bungalow built on sleds and dragged to its destination by
tractors. The various Soviet inland stations of Vostok I
and II, Pioneerskaya, Komsomolskaya, and Sovietskaya,
located at or en route to the Geomagnetic Pole and the
Pole of Inaccessibility, were uniquely designed tractor
quarters which could be expanded at the wintering des¬
tination and re-supplied by air.
The American Byrd Station at Lat. 80° S., Long. 120° W.,
was the largest inland station designed for 25 men. It
was originally supplied by great tractor trains and later
by air. The American geographic South Pole Station,
named Amundsen-Scott, where I served as the Scientific
Leader during its first year of occupation, was a station
for 18 men, supplied by C-124 Globemaster parachute
drops and a few P2V and R4D ski-plane landings. The
altitude of over 9,000 feet required jet assist to lift off
the planes, even lightly loaded ones. Since 1960 C-130
turboprop aircraft land at the pole to discharge their
cargo directly.
The coastal stations at some places are near or even
north of the Antarctic circle so that although they have
little daylight in winter, they virtually have no sunless
or continuous daylight periods and the coldest tempera¬
tures in winter rarely go below -40° C. Summer time
temperatures frequently rise above 0° C. Inland con¬
ditions aire much colder even if not as windy.
The stations farther poleward have sunless periods in
mid-winter and continuous sun in midsummer, and at the
geographic pole there are six months of each. On the
high, mid-continental plateaus, extreme temperature in
winter drops below -75° C. and in some places perhaps
down to nearly -90° C. At the South Pole the first year
BURIED TO THE CHIMNEYS in a sea of snow this Australian outpost, 50 miles from the
Wilkes Antarctic base, permits scientists to live and carry out research for an extended period.
Photo R. Dingle-Antarctic Division. Australian Department of External Affairs
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
US Navy
SPRING CLEANING for the walls of a snow tunnel which Is the main street of America's Byrd Station at an
altitude of 5,000 feet in the mountains of Marie Byrd Land. Here, as In all ma|or U. S. IGY stations, research
was made in meteorology, geo-magnetlsm, glaclology, physics of the Ionosphere and studies of the aurora.
there were 159 successive days during which the tempe¬
rature never rose above -40° C. and the wind averaged
over 15 knots.
Inside the quarters at most bases the temperature was
maintained at a comfortable (15 to 18° C.) shirt-sleeve
temperature (i.e., a wool shirt over heavy underwear).
Men sleep in beds with sheets, blankets, and pillows.
They have excellent libraries, warm toilets, showers, and
laundry facilities, movies, and normal meals except for
the absence of fresh greens. At some stations greens were
grown and at Mirny a herd of pigs solved both the gar¬
bage disposal and fresh meat problem. In short, life
indoors was fairly normal at all bases except for the
absence of women.
One time at the South Pole two of our men
wanted to go out and see how long they could
stay in the open it was about -72° C. with a 12 knot
wind. We knew that under exposed conditions we had
clocked freezing time of noses, cheeks, and ears at about
30 to 45 seconds. But they were well bundled up in several
layers of clothing totaling about 12 to 13 kilogrammes
including their boots and a belt of batteries next to their
bodies to light a head lamp.
It was dark outside and they planned to move about.
One man stayed out three hours and the other four hours.
They quit not so much because it was cold, but because
they were growing tired ; they had already put in their
day's work and were cutting into their bed time. They
were cold in spots, but they suffered no frostbite or other
ill effects.
There are some physiological limitations to the extreme
environment of Antarctica. With fast'walklng or heavy
work at sea level, when temperatures drop below about
-50° O, men become winded and they may start to
cough and spit blood. They have not frosted their lungs
but have ruptured capillaries in their bronchial trachea.
At high altitudes men working heavily at low tem
peratures despite ample food tended to lose a tenth of
their body weight in a month's time. Leaving eyes unpro¬
tected from bright reflection from the snow and sky In
summer time, caused painful temporary blindness.
Although there ls a wide variety In clothing from sta¬
tion to station and sometimes an equal diversity from
man to man In any single station, the basic principles are
nearly the same. In summer, when temperatures range
between 0" C. and -20° C, the men who arc outside for
considerable periods and quite active, wear surprisingly
light clothing, often only a light set of loose-fitting cotton,
windproof trousers and hooded Jackets over wool or heavy
cotton underwear. More sedentary or unaccllmatized
persons will wear an Intermediate layer of wool trousers
and wool shirt, sweater or vest.
Boots vary widely. There are oversized ski boots, or
mukluks with room for heavy socks and insoles, felt
boots, or the Insulated boot (the Invention of which I was
associated with) which is a double-layer rubber boot with
insulation sealed Inside a light pair of socks ls all that
ls worn Inside.
Hand gear ls usually in two layers a wool mitt with
a leather or canvas protective cover. Special thin contact
gloves are used by some who work with delicate Instru¬
ments and heavy work gloves are generally preferred by
mechanics.
Head gear ranges from the conventional wool cap and a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
NO IRONING.
When laundry is hung
outside in Antarctic
winter it becomes as
stiff as an ' ironing
board within minutes.
US Na//
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
FROZEN HISTORY
Scientists from many countries are now busy
studying Antarctica's ice. New methods
make it possible to tell what temperatures
existed when the ice was formed aeons ago.
Here French Polar expedition members
remove cylindrical ice samples (left and below)
and measure the density of granular ice (right).
Photo Jicquis Misson i£. Exploration! rjol»ir« françiis«!
70° BELOW ZERO (Cont'd)
Vacation land
of the future?
long wool cap which has a face opening to leather or
fabric helmets with ear flaps. For bushy-haired active
individuals a ski headband with open crown, giving ear
protection, suffices until the sun goes behind a cloud or
the wind rises. A supplementary windproof cloth hood,
usually attached to the jacket, is pulled up over the head
for added protection. Dark glasses or goggles that cut
down about 75 to 95 % of the light complete the ensemble.
Winter clothing follows the same principles, but
increases in thickness or number of layers,
and usually has more positive closures to keep out the
wind at the neck, waist, ankles, and wrists. Head gear,
boots, and mitts increase to optimum values. Some men
include a felt, chamois or windproof face mask, others
grow beards. No amount of clothing will keep an inactive
man protected for more than an hour or two, but if his
heat production is increased by activity, the same clothing
will keep him warm down to 40° C. or even below
C.
Because of the law of diminishing returns for insulation
over cylindrical shapes (i. e., the surface for losing heat
increases more rapidly than insulation is gained in
thickness), the approximate optimum thickness of insula¬
tion is as follows: Fingers less than 1 cm; head, hands,
and feet; 2 to 3 cm; legs and arms 3 to 5 cm; torso and
sleeping bags 10 to 20 cm.
Transportation across snow surfaces is now almost
exclusively accomplished by tracked vehicles. Numerous
countries have introduced their own versions. The Ame¬
rican-built Sno-Cat, with tracks over four triangular pon¬
toons where wheels would be on a normal truck, has per¬
haps been the most popular. These were used by Fuchs
28 on his transcontinental trip. Hillary, on the other hand,
used small Ferguson farm tractors with added belt tracks
most successfully.
Heavy freighting is carried on by the largest sized trac¬
tors manufactured with sleds that can hold several
thousand kilogrammes. Russian tractors at the begin¬
ning of IGY had too narrow a tread width, but with each
succeeding year they came back with new designs and
have developed enormous tractors with built-in living
quarters that have been used over wide areas of East
Antarctica. They visited the South Pole in 1959-60 and a
year later the Americans delivered giant D-8 tractors over¬
land to the Pole. The World War II American Weasel, or
vehicles of a similar design, serve as light, faster trans¬
portation.
Speed of the larger tractors is usually only 3 or 4 knots,
but the lighter vehicles cannot go much faster than 6 to
15 knots because of the sastrugi (drifts of snow on the
surface). Crevasses, which are great cracks in the snow
and ice surfaces, frequently bridged over by drifting snow,
form unseen hazards to travelers. Several lives have been
lost by tractors dropping into these pitfalls.
Future Improvements in Antarctic living are already on
the horizon. Increased air travel makes direct contacts
with neighboring continents possible throughout the
summer. Winter-night flights have been made. We may
soon expect year around contact. Women have visited the
continent and some have wintered over. An increasing
percentage can be expected to make up family teams or
to serve as scientists and technicians in their own right.
Use of atomic reactors to supply heat, power, and
lighting, is projected for the near future. The new Ame¬
rican Byrd Station (1961-1962) is being modeled after the
U.S. Army Greenland research station Camp Century,
with deep excavated trenches cut by Swiss Peter Snow
Millers. Both Chile and Argentina have carried out paid
tourist visits in summer and soon anyone who wishes to
badly enough may visit Antarctica almost any time he
prefers. Commercial flights and even tourist hotels have
been seriously discussed.
Paul A. Siple, U. S. explorer, geographer and author, was
the youngest member of the first Antarctic expedition of
Admiral Richard Byrd (1928-30) having been chosen from
among 600,000 American boy scouts. He has since taken
part in many Antarctic expeditions and was the scientific
leader of the U.S. IGY Amundsen-Scott South Pole Sta¬
tion in 1956-57. He is the author of 90 Degrees South
(Putnam, New York).
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
OF SUNSPOTS, MAGNETIC RINGS
AND POLAR LIGHTS'
by Alan F. Moore
Antarctic research has only recently developed
because the lack of overland routes makes it
expensive and hazardous even to travel there. In the First
(1882-83) and Second (1932-33) Polar Years very few
stations were set up on the continent and no overall pic¬
ture, even of Antarctic weather, emerged from these and
subsequent pioneer studies.
Aâ the International Geophysical Year (1957-58) was
concerned with weather, radio, oceans on a global scale,
a special effort had to be made for the Antarctic region
and twelve nations set up more than 60 stations on
the ice-covered continent. Much of this work ls now
being continued on a permanent basis.
Recently, greater use of aircraft and mechanical vehicles
has given us more accurate Antarctic maps, but a million
square kilometres of the continent have not yet been seen,
even from the air.
The continent is covered by 20 million cu. kms. of ice,
and its weight has depressed and deformed the original
land surface beneath. Norwegian, U.S., Soviet and Belgian
parties echo-sounding with small explosive charges
(seismic shooting) have shown that a layer of ice (shelf
Alan F. Moore, former lecturer in Geophysics at Imperial
College, London, was largely responsible for the organization of
the Royal Society Antarctic Expedition to Halley Bay during the
IGY. He is now on the administrative staff of the Royal
Society, Great Britain.
ice) lies beyond the true coast of Antarctica and ls
grounded at others, whilst Inland the rock surface below
the Ice resembles fjords.
American geophyslclsts have shown that the coastal
mountains of Marie Byrd Land3,500 m. highare the
tops of a series of offshore Islands separated from East
Antarctica by a 500 km. wide channel filled with Ice.
This channel reaches depths of 2,500 m. below sea level
In places and Joins the Ross and Bellingshausen Seas, but
further work is needed to decide If there ls a minor
branch of it linking up with Uic Weddell Sea.
The rocks of East Antarctica, the older region, are
related to those of South Africa and India, but the
different ones In West Antarctica are similar to those In
the Andes of South America. This ls further evidence
that Antarctica may be at least two major land areas
covered by a single Ice sheet.
Measurement of the depth of the Antarctic rock surface
gives the Ice thickness and so the volume of water locked
up as Ice can be calculated. Studies of the Antarctic
rocks reveal that 160 million years ago they were in a
sub-tropical climate. If these conditions ever returned
then the ice would melt and the global sea level might
rise as much as 65 metres, as already Indicated earlier In
this Issue. In the process of melting a great weight
would be removed from the rocks and they would rise.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
TAKING THE WEATHER'S PULSE. Battery of weather anemometersfor measuring wind forcearc here
being calibrated at Little America station before Installation on towers. During the IGY, a network of weather
stations covered Antarctica for the first time and their reports were sent several times dally to the Weather Central
at Little America. Here, an International team of meteorologists worked together to produce continental weather
charts and forecasts. At one Soviet base a strange phenomenon was seen in July I 9 59: a blizzard of reddish snow.
US Nivy
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
«ft« II I» I
SOUTHERN LIGHTS, immense luminous
rays, arcs and curtains in the heavens (right)
flash and glow in the depth of the polar night.
These aurora are caused by the concentrations
of electrically-charged particles shot from the
sun's surface into two rings the auroral
zonesaround the earth's two magnetic poles.
Jacques Masson © Explorations polaires françaises
Official Soviet photo
EARS 12 MILES HIGH. A radio-sonde
balloon (left) is launched from the Soviet Mirny
Station. Such balloons can make records of
atmospheric conditions up to 12 miles in
height and report back their findings by radio.
Aurorae of different colours and shapes
The map of Antarctica might then look very different.
(See page 7.) Much more evidence is needed before we
can decide if the ice sheet Ls at present growing or
decaying, and all the information must be continually
exchanged in order to do this.
The ships which relieve the Antarctic bases at the turn
of each year visit small islands on the way and are used
to Investigate ocean depth, water circulation and fish of
all kinds. Continuous surveys can be made, such as the
Japanese radio measurements between Tokyo and Showa
Base. British scientists in late 1960 towed an instrument
behind a ship from South America to Graham Land and
made ' a magnetic survey of a submarine mountain
range the Scotia Arc. In late 1961 they exploded small
charges for echo-sounding in the same area to extend
this work on the geological similarities between Graham
Land and South America. All the work in the oceans
around the Antarctic continent requires considerable
expansion for at the moment it has a much lower priority
than the land-based studies.
R
30
ECORDS from magnetic observatories founded
before 1900 show a slow secular change in the
Earth's magnetism, regional in character consisting of 10
or more areas of increase or decrease. Recently IGY data
have revealed that one the largest regions of annual
magnetic change is in the Antarctic region and magnetic
observations must now be obtained from many more sites
there, which will make an important contribution to the
current World Magnetic Survey.
The Earth's magnetic field concentrates some of the
electrically-charged atomic particles which are shot at
high speeds from the sun's surface into two rings the
auroral zones around each magnetic pole. These
particles gradually increase to a maximum number about
every 11 years as the sunspot maximum is reached and
cause an increase in the number of nights on which
aurorae or "polar lights" are observed.
The aurorae appear in different colours and shapes, e.g.
rays, arcs and curtains, which change throughout the
night, and every few minutes all-sky cameras can record
all the shapes from horizon to horizon. Two ordinary
cameras on a known base-line give data about the height
of the aurora usually 100 km to the lower edge. Ana¬
lysis of the light from aurorae tells us about the kinds
of air molecules there are at great heights and important
work of this type has been done at French Antarctic
bases.
The location of the Antarctic auroral zone was a
primary object of the IGY sunspot maximum programme
but new inland bases are required to obtain more data
for at least one sunspot cycle before the work is
completed. This southern hemisphere work could not be
attempted until the IGY, and then it was found that
aurorae occur in the same hours, maybe simultaneously,
in both the Arctic and Antarctic zones, although not
necessarily in the same form.
The observatories recording the very slow geomagnetic
secular variations mentioned above also record the large
and rapid ones magnetic storms which often accom¬
pany intense auroral displays. These variations are
related to the large fluctuating electrical currents set up
by the incoming solar particles and their analysis helps
us to learn more about the constitution of the high
atmosphere over the poles.
Long distance radio communication is made possible
by layers of electrified particles the ionosphere in the
upper atmosphere and the E layer, about 120 km (75 mi)
high, and the F layer, about 350 km (220 mi) high. In
middle latitudes the changing height of these layers, the
maximum radio wave frequency they reflect, and the
drift of irregularities in them have been measured and
analysed for a decade or more, but little similar work was
done in the southern hemisphere until the IGY provided
a very necessary expansion.
The ionosphere can be greatly disturbed by Incoming
CONT'D ON PAGE 40
Government of Japan
PARABOLA ANTENNA for radar observation of atmospheric
phenomena at the Showa Antarctic base where a Japanese observa¬
tion party wintered for the the fourth year in succession (1960-61).
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
JOURNEY INTO THE INACC
by Mikhail M. Somov
32
Before the International Geophysical Year began
in 1957, no scientific expedition had ever wintered
in the heart of the Antarctic Continent. Since then
the United States, the U.S.S.R. and France have
all set up research stations deep in the interior.
Below we publish an account of the arduous
journey across 1,300 miles to reach Antarc¬
tica's Pole of Inaccessibility the point furthest
removed from the coasts where the lowest temper¬
atures on earth's surface have been recorded.
Well before the International Geophysical Year
began five years ago, scientific circles the
world over were already engaged in heated discussions
about the grandiose projects foreseen as part of this
unparallelled assault on our planet.
In the sweltering summer of 1955 scientists from many
lands gathered In Paris to map out the work they were
soon to undertake in common on the frozen sixth
continent of Antarctica. Their first step was to apportion
the various tasks among the different countries
participating so that the whole of the Antarctic would
be systematically covered by a network of observation
posts.
At the time, few scientific stations existed on the sixth
continent and these were located only in the more
accessible regions near the coast. The rest of the huge
ice-covered area had virtually never been studied, except
in summer when certain zones had been visited (more
recently with the additional help of aircraft). No one
had ventured Into the heart of the continent In winter,
and hence no one had yet observed the exact conditions
prevailing there during the polar night.
The scientists at the Paris conference voiced their
DIFFICULT CLIMB is made by three members of a Soviet
Antarctic expedition up the side of a giant iceberg
which has broken off from the main continental ice-mass.
Kapitza-Tass
common conviction that It was Imperative not only to
increase the number of coastal stations but to set up a
number of new stations In the interior equipped to carry
out research and observations all year round. The four
most characteristic points in the centre of the continent
were particularly studied and it was decided to set up
scientific stations in each of them.
The first was the geographic South Pole where the
geographic meridians converge.
The second, the Magnetic South Pole, where the
magnetic needle points and where the magnetic
meridians converge.
The third was the Geo-magnetic South Pole, where the
Magnetic Pole would theoretically be found if the
magnetism of the globe were uniform which it is not.
The area is of particular interest to science because the
intensity of geophysical phenomena occurring in the
upper atmosphre varies with the distance from this spot.
The fourth was the Pole of Relative Inaccessibility, the
point furthest removed from the coasts and one of the
last blank spaces left on our planet. It ls located in the
toughest part of Antarctica to get to, where scientists
felt the climate should be most markedly continental and
the winter temperatures therefore exceptionally low.
None of the men attending the Paris meeting
underestimated the enormous . difficulties Which would
face the expeditions assigned to set up these four stations
in the far off and as yet unknown tracts of the south
polar continent.
The United States volunteered to set up a station at
the geographic South Pole. France agreed to set up
another in the region of the Magnetic Pole. The U.S.S.R.
undertook to establish two stations, one at the Pole of
Inaccessibility (about 1,300 miles from the projected Soviet
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
BUSTLE OF DEPARTURE surrounds Soviet tractor convoy
as it sets off at first light for one of the great |ourneysof th».¿
International Geophysical Year. Its goal: to reach the point
In Antarctica which is the farthest ^rVom the coast and study
the exceptional conditions found there during the polar night.
coastal base at Mirny),
Pole.
the second at the Geomagnetic
To head straight for the Pole of Inaccessibility
Immediately on landing In Antarctica was obviously
unthinkable. An assault of such difficulty, Into the mos"
inhospitable part of the continent, had to be conceived
as an operation in several stages.
A first expedition (1955-1957) was entrusted with
reconnoitring Antarctic weather conditions and in¬
vestigating the possibilities of setting up stations In the
interior. A second expedition (1956-1958) was to carry
out a combined operation with land transport and
aircraft to set up these stations, and a third (1957-1959)
was to complete whatever the second expedition was
prevented from doing by lack of time.
Such was the plan. And with the exception of a
number of modifications found to be necessary as the
operations progressed, It proved perfectly feasible. Even
before the Mirny base was completed at the foot of the
massive Helen Glacier, the first expedition completed
several aerial reconnaissances which produced vital
information concerning possible routes to the Pole of
Inaccessibility and the Magnetic Pole.
The first reports to come in showed that the Mirny
region was cut off from the interior to the south by an
area of impassible Ice crevasses. The danger zone was
found to be about 30 miles wide. The crevasses them¬
selves varied in width, ranging from a few inches to a half
hundred or more yards, with depths estimated at
anything from 50 feet to hundreds or even thousands
of yards.
These crevasses are particularly dangerous since they
are often covered by "snow bridges" piled up by frequent
storms. The bridges are of varied thickness and solidity,
some easily supporting the weight of a 12-ton tractor,
others giving way when a man steps on them. Sometimes
they collapse from their own weight.
A crevasse covered over by such a bridge ls completely
Invisible and hard to detect even from the air. It ls no
exaggeration to say that crossing through such a zone of
camouflaged crevasses Is like walking across a minefield.
Luckily, air pilots spotted a narrow passage through
this zone, and a land team was later able to mark out
the route with bamboo poles. Thus the vital question as
to whether land transport could be used to penetrate
into the interior to set up the observation stations was
now answered.
Other flights over the Interior revealed that there were
no landmarks on the Ice cap, thus making it Impossible
to take bearings on ,the route from Mirny to the sites
of the future stations.
Shortly after the completion of the main building sites
at Mirny, a new effort was made to obtain Information
on the inland regions. A convoy of sledges drawn by
two 80 h.p. diesel caterpillar tractors left Mirny on April
2, 1956 and headed south. Its mission was to reconnoitre
the land and gather data on the conditions likely to
confront future expeditions. The convoy covered 235
miles moving in the direction of the magnetic south pole
and reached an altitude of over 9,000 feet on the snow
plateau. Here they halted and subsequently became the
first scientific station to be set up in the Interior of the
continent the Ploneerskaya Station.
It was an arduous journey, made particularly hazardous
by long projections of ice which rose from the surface
to a height of a yard or more, and by the deep soft snow
in which the treads of the tractors sank or skidded. The 33
men on the sledges suffered cruelly from the rough going.
Such a journey requires not only tip-top physical shape
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
INTO THE INACCESSIBLE (Cont'd)
WORLD RECORD FOR DEEP-FREEZE
and a talent for acrobatics, but dedicated enthusiasm as
well.
This first expedition into the interior of the continent
began in April when the Antarctic autumn is well
advanced and the slopes of the ice plateau are almost
ceaselessly swept by winds driving the snow before them.
In such weather even the briefest halt may have
catastrophic consequences. A motionless sledge is
immediately covered over with snow and what may have
begun as a momentary pause can turn into a forced halt
lasting two or three days or even a week. Only after
the storm has ended and the winds abated can the men
think of freeing the sledges and moving on.
Because of the late date of departure from Mirny the
men of the expedition and their work were plagued by
the high winds and the extremely low temperatures which
dropped well below -50° C. (-58° F) towards the end of
the journey. Moreover the intense cold severely tested
the solidity of their equipment, even those items made
of steel.
The expedition proved that another factor seriously
hampered living and working in the interior, i.e. the
sharp drop in atmospheric pressure due to the high
altitude of the ice cap. This not only put a strain on
the men but also interfered with the functioning of their
vehicles operating with internal combustion engines.
r,he second Soviet Antarctic expedition, led by
A.F. Trechnikov, reached Mirny at the end of
1956-early 1957. With it came ten powerful caterpillar
tractors designed for travel to the heart of the continent.
Preparations for the journey began at once. All the heavy
equipment for setting up the Vostok station on the Geo¬
magnetic South Pole including housing for the men, elec¬
tric generators, radio gear, a kitchen, etc. was loaded on
sledges ready for installation on arrival. At the same time
the new caterpillar tractors were tested under Antarctic
conditions.
On February 14 the vehicles of the second expedition
left Mirny to set up the auxiliary station of
Komsomolskaya. After many hardships the convoy
finally reached its destination. Fuel reserves were by now
exhausted and the late season made it extraordinarily
difficult for aircraft to land. It was considered too
dangerous for the party to winter on the spot, so after
the convoy had been "weatherproofed" the entire team
was brought back to Mirny by air.
On February 28, a second convoy set out to reach the
site for the future Vostok station. Again, snowstorms and
soft snow, temperatures of -55° C. and the rarefied
atmosphere hindered progress. The convoy halted at an
altitude of 10,600 feet some 400 miles from Mirny. Here
a temporary inland station named Vostok I was set up
and soon began its scientific investigations.
On October 8 a tractor-drawn sledge train left Mirny
for the geo-magnetic pole. Huts, a generating station,
a navigation post and an electric kitchen were loaded
onto six tractors and the convoy with its team of 27 men
under A.F. Trechnikov set off.
As it advanced it was supplied with fuel from the air,
and by November 4, having passed the Pioneerskaya and
Vostok I stations, it reached the point where a base had
been prepared for the Komsomolskaya station during the
previous autumn. From there it proceeded southeast and
on December 16 it reached the vicinity of the Geo¬
magnetic South Pole where the new Vostok station was
established at an altitude of over 11,000 feet, some 875
miles from the coast.
It is in this region that a new Pole the Pole of Cold
was discovered where the lowest deep-freeze temperature
of our planet was found when a thermometer reading of
-83.3° C. was recorded. The strain on research staffs
« - of living and working in these rigorous winter conditions
M during the polar night can well be imagined.
Soon a third Soviet Antarctic expedition reached Mirny
and prepared for the final push to reach the Pole of
Inaccessibility.
On December 26, 1957, a convoy from this expedition
composed of ten all-purpose tractors and 20 improved
sledges left Mirny. After delivering urgently needed
stores to the Vostok station and visiting the Komso¬
molskaya station, it set its bearings due south-easterly.
The deeper it thrust into the Interior the more powdery
the snow became until the tractors found themselves
sinking to depths of 80 inches and more.
By February 10, the convoy had travelled some 880 miles
from Mirny and had reached an altitude of 11,700 feet.
At this point the Sovietskaya station was established
and five days later was in operation. In the meantime,
the scientists and specialists at the Mirny Base had been
making full use of the winter to prepare new expeditions
for the spring.
On October 24, a convoy started up its motors
and moved off for the Pole of Inaccessibility.
Just over one month later it reached the Sovietskaya sta¬
tion and after a halt of five days set off on the final lap of
the expedition. Eighteen men led by E.T. Tolstikov made
up the group. At the end of 11 days and 1,300 miles from
the main base at Mirny, the convoy finally reached the
point designated as the Pole of Relative Inaccessibility.
Here a new continental observation post was set up. When
scientific observation had been completed the convoy
began the return journey to Mirny.
Until this venture ideas about the central area of eastern
Antarctica were largely based on conjecture. Once an
up-to-date scientific station had been set up In this
region its former mystery disappeared. Instead of merely
being able to pass on to the world's centres of science
scraps of information picked up during reconnaissance
trips, these new stations set up in the heart of the
continent were now able to transmit detailed and exten¬
sive reports on all the geophysical processes taking place
in the remotest corner of our planet.
A vast amount of scientific knowledge was also
amassed by the convoys of tractor-drawn sledges used to
set up the various stations. Observations were made
throughout these expeditions and a thorough investiga¬
tion was thus made of eastern Antarctica, the least
accessible of all regions.
Aircraft played a major part In the setting up of the
inland stations. They flew a total of 635,000 miles over
the ice-cap and their observations made it possible to
draw up a contour map of the surface of the east
Antarctic ice-cap.
The existence of the sixth continent of our planet has
only been known for the past one hundred and forty
years. Its study has proceeded at a slow pace and its
contours have only gradually been filled in on maps. Its
secrets were only truly revealed during history's greatest
science research project the International Geophysical
Year.
Although the IGY has now ended officially, this re¬
markable example of scientific co-operation continues to
develop through the international Antarctic Treaty which
makes Antarctica the only continent of peace on our
planet where not only war but every form of military
activity is forbidden. As such, its importance to hu¬
manity grows greater every day for it shines as a brilliant
example for all other continents.
M. M. Somov has been active in polar research since 1938. He
was head of the drifting ice-floe station North Pole-2 (1950-51)
and of the first Soviet Antarctic expedition (1955-57). Holder
of the title, Hero of the Soviet Union, he was awarded in 1959
the Vega Gold Medal of the Swedish Anthropological and Geo¬
graphical Society, and in 1961, the Patron's Gold Medal of the
British Geographic Society. Dr. Somov is deputy director of the
Arctic and Antarctic Research Institute of Leningrad and is
also a permanent member of the Scientific Committee on
Antarctic Research.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
THE THREAT
OF HIDDEN
CHASMS
Trans-Antarctic Expedition
t"Hk-ß+-
¡
USIS
The vast white spaces look reassuringly smooth and safe. But tho mantle of snow
conceals deadly trapsenormous chasms largo enough to swallow up ontiro
convoys of tractors and sledges. During tho Commonwealth Trans-Antarctic
Expedition in 1958, a Sno-cat tracked vehicle in the party lod by Vivian Fuchs
broke through the lid of a deep chasm (left) and remained suspended across It
like a bridge. To guard against such dangers, American explorer-technicians
have devised a vehicle equipped with electronic detectors, (above) which reveal
the presence of invisible crevasses. Below, tho towering walls of a crevasse.
USIS
I
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
WILD LIFE
Nature has created unique species in
the world's coldest climate. The arrival
of man now threatens their existence.
by Rodolfo N. Panzarini
Antarctica presents us with an environment
singularly unsulted to the development of
living things. It ls in fact the largest of the world's
deserts where freezing weather and winds, the absence of
fresh water and the extreme rarity of soil surfaces all
combine to make it impossible for plants to thrive. And
it is on plants that all animals must depend for food,
either directly or Indirectly.
The picture is totally different when we turn to the
Antarctic waters. Here we find conditions highly
favourable for the growth of a marine flora of microscopic
plant organisms which in spring and summer multiply
by the millions and provide the basic nourishment for an
abundant animal life.
The vegetable and animal kingdom of Antarctica is
composed of a relatively small number of species but each
is represented by an incredible number of individual
creatures. They are a striking demonstration of how
evolution has operated a high degree of specialization to-
adapt life to the harsh and very special conditions of a
particular environment.
And since this environment provides very little food on
land we find that no exclusively terrestrial animals exist
anywhere in Antarctica. This explains too why birds and
animals are to be found only on the shores and islands
where nourishment in abundance is available from the
sea; why so many animals emigrate from the region in
autumn; why there are forms of life typically and
exclusively Antarctic in nature; and why, finally, all plant
and animal life is circumpolar in distribution.
On the mainland the chief botanical species are algae,
mosses and lichens, but on the sub-Antarctic islands a
sparse tundra has succeeded in establishing itself.
Despite the sub-zero temperatures micro-organisms are
known to exist in the atmosphere, and scientists have
recently been successful in obtaining a proliferation of
life from air samples cultivated in low-temperature labor¬
atories. Various species have been isolated Including
several of the micro-fungi yeast variety.
I t
he Antarctic seas have been found to be
teeming with an extraordinary multitude of
microscopic unicellular algae of the diatom family. These
form the greater part of the phytoplankton upon which
birds and sea animals, including whales, regularly prey
for food.
Land creatures are limited to the lower forms of life,
a number of which are capable of subsisting in a state of
suspended animation when conditions are particularly
unfavourable. Birds and mammals are all of the marine
variety except for the white-plumed Antarctic sheathbill
which haunts the rookeries of penguins and is known for
its predatory attacks on their eggs.
Rear-Admiral Rodolfo Panzarini is director of the "Instituto
-_ Antárctico Argentino" and was in command of Argentina's
«*> Antarctic expeditions in 1950-51 and 1952-53. He was previously
head of Argentina's Maritime Meteorological Service and is the
author of "La Naturelza del Antárctico."
The penguins are the best known of the sea birds of
Antarctica, and their social habits are both curious and
fascinating. Every spring they arrive on the islands and
coast of the frozen continent and gather together in
gigantic colonies. Here they breed and raise their chicks
which must be strong enough by autumn to be able
apparently to migrate to warmer latitudes further north.
The emperor penguin, the largest and stateliest of all the
penguins, behaves in quite a different fashion. It makes
its appearance in these latitudes not in spring but when
the autumn is drawing to a close. No nest ls built, and
each couple produces only a single egg. The egg is
incubated during the dark polar night by placing it on
the feet of the male who shelters it under a fold of skin
hanging apron-like from his abdomen.
In January the colonies of emperor penguins disperse
and set themselves adrift on ice-floes moving out to sea.
Where they spend their time until the following autumn
remains a mystery.
Petrel, albatross, tern, gull, cormorant and skua, which
all make penguin chicks their preferred prey also nest in
Antarctica and remain there during the milder season.
Of the five species of seals only one the sea ele¬
phant is not a uniquely Antarctic creature.
Among the others are the leopard seal, an Implacable
enemy of the penguin which it hunts voraciously and
devours when they meet in the water. The fur seal
belongs to another group which was almost completely
exterminated by indiscriminate hunting about the middle
of the last century. Now, after a hundred years, its popu¬
lation seems to be recovering.
Whales, our planet's largest animal, visit Antarctica in
the spring to feed almost exclusively on the millions of
tiny shrimplike crustaceans known as "krill." Over 80 per
cent of the world's whale oil comes from Antarctic waters
with the result that the whale is in perpetual danger of
extermination.
The plants and animals of Antarctica, both those found
on land and in the waters, form an integrated community
with all its members closely dependent on each other for
survival in this harsh climate which is a permanent
challenge to them. All forms of life there play a role that
is important from the standpoint of science, aesthetics
and economics.
For the scientist Antarctic wildlife is of exceptional
interest because the environment has given rise to forms
of structural, physiological and ecological adaptation
which are astonishingly specialized and refined, and which
are to be found nowhere else in the world. And also
because the same environment has led certain species to
form colonies during the reproduction season and to
disperse and seek refuge elsewhere during the remainder
of the year. The former type of behaviour ls usually
associated with a highly developed social organization and
the latter with migratory habits.
From the aesthetic viewpoint Antarctic animals possess
not only great beauty but elegance and grace, and the
charm that one attaches to things rare. Their very
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
»5 Jean Prévost TEETH OF A KILLER. Holding open the jaws of a sea leopard, or leopard seal, this biologist member of a
recent French polar expedition, displays the powerful fangs of the mortal enemy of the penguins. Named for
the variegated colours of Its fur, this Antarctic seal can grow to I 2 feet In length. It Is an especial foe of the small
Adélle penguin; In the stomach of one leopard seal the remains of nofewer than I7pengulns were recently found.
presence brings life to the austere landscape, breaking
its natural monotony and softening the feeling of dismay
and oppression which the white wasteland makes on the
human mind. Most of the animals show no signs of fear
in the presence of man and allow him to approach to
study their behaviour at close range. Though only of the
most rudimentary type, the vegetation found in Antarctica
also helps to break up the all-pervading whiteness.
The animals of Antarctica have an economic value too,
since several species provide marketable products and In
emergencies can be used by explorers for fuel and food.
At present the economic value of its wildlife cannot com¬
pare with its scientific and aesthetic Importance but this
situation may well change before long.
The Antarctic is the last of the earth's continents to
have been invaded by man and the only one still almost
entirely in its natural state. But nature cannot escape
the effects of man's arrival. By merely Installing ourselves
in the few places where vegetation can grow and animals
congregate during the breeding season we threaten the
flora, already extremly rare, and inevitably do damage to
the fauna, the more so when we decimate their numbers
for our own ends.
Such inroads can do irreparable harm and lead to the
extinction of entire species of the utmost importance. In
the past the damage caused by the massacre of animals
hunted for their meat or skins has been disastrous even
though limited to a few species.
Today's scientific invasion of Antarctica is obviously not
aimed at hunting down the wild life of the region. Yet
though inspired by totally different motives it constitutes
a new but no less dangerous threat to the vegetable and
animal kingdom of Antarctica.
Along with the great influx of men have come animals
and other forms of life alien to the snow-covered
continent, resulting sometimes In competition and even
open hostility to the native fauna. The ccnturles-
long Isolation of Antarctica made It unnecessary for the
species there to build up defence mechanisms to meet the
challenge of outside encroachment. Ill-equipped to
defend themselves they found themselves especially
vulnerable to attack and their very survival was thus
threatened .
Two examples of man's improvidence In Antarctica
deserve special mentionthe whale and the fur seal. The
whale ls being hunted In such numbers today that there
are signs of Its serious depletion. The seal, as already
noted, has not been hunted on a commercial scale for
the past century and ls only now recovering from the
ravages of the past.
Both need protection, the whale to avoid reaching the
danger level of extinction, the seal until studies have
shown that its population ls stabilized and a safe maximum
hunting quota has been determined.
Fortunately, when uncontrolled hunting eventually
reduces catches to such an extent that commercial
exploitation ls abandoned, the recuperative power of the
animals still appears to be strong enough to save them
from total extinction. But It takes a long time before
the species recover. Nevertheless it ls both dangerous 37
and uneconomical to approach this critical point.
Dangerous, because any unforseen big catch may have
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
WILD LIFE (Continued)
Forbidden sanctuaries
catastrophic consequences on the survival of the depleted
species; uneconomical because prolonged idleness in a
commercial enterprise involving many men and machines
obviously spells financial loss.
Although no one can deny man's right to turn to plants
and animals to satisfy his needs we should remember
that it would be unwise to do so in excess of what nature
can provide. For example, the mass collection of eggs
does not really affect the result of a breeding season since
many of these eggs would never have reached the hatching
stage anyway in the cold Antarctic climate. But the
parent birds may be so disturbed as to abandon their usual
mating grounds and seek another which it is very difficult
to find outside of Antarctica.
If science is to progress, however, some measure of inter¬
ference is Inevitable and must be accepted, if only in the
interests of nature preservation itself which depends on
science and its findings to achieve positive results.
The problems of nature protection and preservation in
Antarctica were first taken up in March 1959 at the third
meeting of the Special Committee on Antarctic Research
held in Canberra, Australia. A provision covering the
subject was later included in the Antarctic Treaty signed
in Washington the following December.
The preservation methods now recommended are based
on general principles and on what little we know about
the Antarctic biological world. It goes without saying
that they will be revised in the light of new facts as
they emerge from future scientific investigations.
But it is already abundantly clear that man's presence
in Antarctica, which is increasing with every passing year,
represents an increasing threat to the flora and fauna,
and that protective measures are needed before it Is too
late.
38 The whole of Antarctica should now be recognized by all
countries as a nature reserve, and even predatory species
should receive protection so as not to disturb the natural
Photos Jacaues Masson © Expéditions Polaires Françaises
LOW-FLYING HELICOPTER dumping supplies near Adélie pen¬
guins. This can often be a source of disturbance and danger to Antarc¬
tica's bird colonies especially during the breeding season. The small
Adélie penguins are among the most comical and endearing of this
family of Antarctic sea-birds. They bow, swagger, chatter and doze.
They seal their courtship with a kiss (above) and watch carefully (below)
over their downy chicks. Undoubtedly they look like ugly ducklings when
compared with the handsome chicks of the emperor penguin opposite.
5 Jean Prévost
/Mm
*«K
'PENGUINS* THAT FLY. Though true penguins are only found
in the southern hemisphere in Antarctica, certain northern oceanic
birds are also mistakenly referred to as penguins. These belong to the
Alcidae or Auk family whose members nest in great colonies from
Greenland, Iceland and Spitzbergen to North America and Northern
Europe. Unlike Antarctic penguins these northern birds can fly (photo
below) though one of their number, the great auk, became extinct
because it could neither fly nor run. Two centuries ago millions of
great auks still existed, but so many were killed off in a short-sighted
hunt for their flesh and feathers that finally not one was left alive.
© Dragesco, Paris
CONT'D ON PAGE 40
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
^T
EMPERORS AND
KINGS OF THE
PENGUIN WORLD
O fcyjione
Largest of Antarctica's flightless birds are the emperor penguins, above, seen warming chicks
between their feet, and king penguins, below, out for a stroll along the seashore. Fossil bones
of penguins found In the Antarctic show that some species must have been as tall as a man.
Emperor penguins stand 3 1/2 feet high and weigh 90 pounds or more. They breed In the
depth of winter, their single egg being hatched on the feet of the male (he maintains a fast,
totalling 90 days before and during Incubation). The emperors feed chiefly on fish or small
octopuses (most other penguins eat shrimp) and usually live as monogamous couples.
<
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Sunspots and magnetic rings (Cont'd from page 30)
solar particles and its study near the southern auroral
zone ls very important. During intense magnetic storms
the radio signals are absorbed and communication becomes
impossible. During quiet periods near sunspot maximum,
radio signals on higher frequencies than usual can be
transmitted over very long distances and during 1958
European television sound signals were received in the
Antarctic.
Ionospheric phenomena are easier to analyse at stations
just outside the auroral zone but near to the geographic
pole; one such station is that of the United Kingdom at
Halley Bay. It was one of the very few Antarctic stations
equipped for detailed IGY radio studies and many more
like it will be required in the coming years to track the
Important horizontal and vertical movements of ionized
gas observed there.
The weather of the southern hemisphere is controlled
to a large extent by the ice covering of Antarctica-
temperatures of -86° C were recorded at a Soviet station.
Countries like Chile, Argentina, South Africa, Australia
and New Zealand have always sought meteorological data
from that region to improve their weather forecasts.
Since the IGY many more stations are contributing data
secured with radio-sonde balloons which transmit from
heights up to 20 km (12 miles).
During the IGY weather data was sent several times a
day, by radio, from each station to the Antarctic Weather
Central at Little America. There United States meteo¬
rologists worked with colleagues from the U.S.S.R.,
Argentina, etc., to produce continental weather charts and
forecasts.
Ozone gas, flowing at a height of about 25 km is a
valuable indicator of air movements at high altitudes.
The necessary delicate measurements have been done at
some French and British Antarctic bases, and have shown
that its annual variation differs from that in the Northern
Hemisphere. Upper atmosphere sounding rockets fired
from ships In Antarctic waters have also contributed to
our knowledge of the upper atmosphere. We are begin¬
ning to understand the general circulation of the atmo¬
sphere up to great heights over the southern hemisphere
but many more extensive and detailed measurements will
be required before major advances in forecasting can
take place.
This article has not touched on the rapidly expanding
programme of biological research that has just begun,
for these equally important activities are dealt with in
a separate article by Rear Admiral Panzarini (See p. 36).
More observations of all kinds are required from the
interior of Antarctica and in the coming years
experimenters travelling by tractor or aircraft will improve
the maps and gather data about Antarctic rocks and
ice thickness. Modern techniques, such as meteorological
satellites showing the area of ice as well as the amount
of cloud cover and radio-isotope powered automatic
weather stations (The Unesco Courier, September 1957,
page 20) sending regular radio reports, will gradually come
into greater use. However, Antarctic research will never
progress without the adventurous spirit which leads brave
men to work in lonely huts, tending delicate apparatus in
the face of many hazards.
Antarctic research became a major field of studies at
the time of the IGY and the sunspot maximum; it will
be further expanded in 1964-1965 at sunspot minimum
with the International Year of the Quiet Sun (IQSY)
programme and the peaceful conditions and free access
permitted by the Antarctic Treaty will guarantee further
expansion in the next few decades.
Wild Life (Cont'd from page 38)
biological equilibrium of the region. Areas deemed to be
particularly important or vulnerable must be given special
status as "sanctuaries" where human intrusion or inter¬
ference of any kind would be strictly forbidden.
Special attention should be given to the protection of
food sources from the sea. This could be done by
prohibiting the exploitation of rich marine areas near
points where birds and animals congregate.
Since nature recognizes only natural frontiers, inter¬
national co-operation is indispensable if we wish
conservation measures to be effective. These measures
must also be the result of the international effort of all
the countries now working together in the Antarctic in
view of the circumpolar distribution of species, the isola¬
tion of the region and the precarious balance of the food
cycle for all wild life.
Furthermore, no plant or animal species new to the
region should be introduced before scientists have carefully
examined all the possible consequences such action might
entail. Domestic animals should be imported under strict
control and limited to the minimum according to their
chances of survival, their breeding capacity and usefulness
to man.
Overall protective measures should be aimed particularly
against actions likely to cause the most serious damage,
.f. i.e. allowing dogs to run loose, permitting helicopters,
planes and motor vehicles to frighten or disturb bird
colonies, setting off explosions or discharging firearms in
the vicinity of seal rookeries during the mating season,
molesting birds and seals by too frequent visits, permitting
ships to discharge oil into the coastal waters.
Authorization can be granted, however, to obtain
specimens of the flora and fauna of Antarctica provided
that this is done under appropriate controls to ensure the
conservation of the species. Thus the granting of
permission would be considered quite legitimate for the
completion or maintenance of zoological and botanical
collections, for scientific collections or study, for enriching
private collections of stuffed animals (for this purpose
animals should never be killed but must have died a
natural death). It is equally legitimate when required
for the feeding of men and animals in Antarctica, and
for commercial exploitation with the proviso that this
be carried out in accordance with the established
principles of nature preservation.
But it is not enough to define the elements of the
problem and admit its importance, to pursue the study
of the behaviour and characteristics of Antarctic plant
and animal life, to lay down standards based on these
findings and then prepare an international agreement for
their application. What is needed, perhaps above all, is
for each of us to feel personally responsible for the
defence of a common interest. Without this the world
at large may soon be deploring the loss of a beautiful and
irreplaceable heritage which the wild life of Antarctica
represents.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
MAKES WORLD SEEM SMALLER
Sir,
I would like to congratulate all
concerned for the excellent way in
which The Unesco Courier is helping
towards a genuine international under¬
standing. Reading the magazine
makes the world seem a much smaller
place and makes me, and I am sure
others also, feel responsible for
situations elsewhere. I am very
interested in the various philosophies
and religions of the world and would
welcome a greater coverage pn these
lines.
L. W. J. Pennington
Newcastle, N.S.W., Australia
A THIN HARVEST
Sir,
I was told your magazine was of
general cultural interest, dealing with
the sciences, painting, music, etc. Yet
since I became a subscriber I have
only been attracted by one article,
dealing with fish a rather thin
harvest as I think you will agree. As
I am neither Jewish nor Arab, neither
a coloured person from another
country nor a woman school teacher
your only satisfied readers, I am sure
I can assure you that I very much
regret taking out a subscription for a
magazine whose contents have so far
left me entirely unsatisfied.
M. Petit
Paris, France
PROVOCATIVE
BUT NOT SATISFYING
Having taken The Unesco Courier
for several years now, I would like
to thank all concerned for providing
me with so much information and
entertainment. My only complaint is
that the articles often lack depth.
Whilst I can see that it may be your
object to create an interest in a
subject rather than to satisfy an
existing curiosity, I often feel a sense
of disappointment on reaching the
end of an article, having been present¬
ed with only a brief survey of
something that has intrigued me for
some time. Still I appreciate that
space is limited and yet a wealth of
information is packed into a very
inexpensive volume.
B. J. Burton
Manchester, England
THE FACTS ABOUT RACISM
Sir,
I am more than ¿satisfied with my
first year's subscription to your
magazine. For a soldier, cut off from
his usual sources of contact with the
world, it is stimulating and a pleasure
to read.
Naturally, I have not been interested
to the same extent by all issues, but
two in particular impressed me greatly:
the one devoted to Velazquez and the
one concerning Racism. This latter
issue is one which should find its way
into schools, universities and homes
all over the world.
T. Vcrgcly
French Army
PHOTOMICROGRAPHY
OR MICROPHOTOGRAPHYT
Sir,
With all due respect to you and
the dictionaries, D. K. Edwards of
Victoria, British Columbia, is quite
correct ; it is now accepted English
scientific and technical usage that a
photomicrograph is a photograph
taken through ' a microscope and a
microphotograph a very small photo¬
graph. And, since scientists and
technicians are the main users of
photomicrographs that is an excellent
reason for their usage to be generally
accepted. Possibly an even better
reason is that to do so gives different
and precise meanings to two different
words for two different things, to
the consequent enrichment of the
language. If, as you say, "in common
usage the two terms arc synonymous"
then common usage is slipshod and
should not receive your editorial en¬
couragement. I believe that the
Germans use "Mikrophotographie"
for what we call photomicrography,
which is perhaps a pity but does not
alter my argument.
II. J. Walls
Newcasllc-upon-Tync, England
RELIGIOUS FANATICISM
Sir,
An issue devoted to the harm
caused by religious fanaticism would
provoke wide discussion among your
readers for it is undeniable that
different religions have always claimed
for their own teachings the exclusive
title of the true faith. There would
be no need to go back to the days
of the Inquisition. There are still
people who hate others because of
religious beliefs.
G. & A. I'iou
Rezé-Ies-Nantes, France
ART IN THE LIFE OF MAN
Sir,
As an artist and instructor of art
may I say Dr. d'Arcy Hayman's
"Art in the Life of Man" should
rank high among the works done to
date to put men closer to the ordered
way of cultural symphysis. Few
authors have seen recorded so
candidly the cultural pitfalls of our
day, few have -had the vision of the
possibilities, truly wholesome and
joyful, of lives well lived, of the total
of the cultures fully grasped.
Truly this job will not be himple,
nor does Dr. I layman lead us to
believe so, but if all men could see
this common good in Art, then we
have hopes and works worthy of
ourselves and our children.
Let every man of good will, having
this vision share it. J'irai the ¡utist
through his work, second the users
through (heir request.
K. I". MiCovirn
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
FASTEST GROWING CITY
Sir,
In the your June ¡sine. Tibor Mende
states in "Men of the Land" that in
the capital city of one of the Latin
American j-epublics "about once every
minute a new building was complet¬
ed". According to this, 60 buildings
an hour arc completed here, which
amounts to 1,440 buildings (60x24)
in twenty-four hours. Consequently,
in one year total construction in this
capital cquah no less than 450,000
buildings. Wc would like to know
which republic in Latin America has
a capital with such a highly develop¬
ed building industry.
Syukhln, U.S.S.R.
Ed. note. Tibor Mende was referring
to the city of Sao Paulo in Brazil
which is considered the fuMcM growing
city in the world, ¡iuilding there docs
not, of coune, go on 24 hours a day
or on weekends. A more realistic
estimate based on a 4H-hours week
gives a yearly total of approximately
150,000 buildings per year Mill an
amazing figure. Mr. Mende, however,
.said "...about once every minute."
MUSTS FOR LIBRARIES
Sir,
Writing on Books and Libraries in
your May, 1961 issue André Maurois
stated: "Our civilization is the sum
of the knowledge and memories
accumulated by the generations that
have gone before us. Wc can only
partake of it if wc can make contact
with ideas of those past generations.
The only way to do this and so
become a "cultured person" is by
reading.
I agree with this wholeheartedly,
but immediately wonder what books
one should read. Quite apart from
choices made on the basis of personal
tastes, which arc always controversial,
there no doubt exist a series of "key"
books of universal value. What are
the 10, 25, 50 or 100 books which
Unesco thinks should be on the shelves
of every library?
Leopoldo Bustillo Sanchez
La Felguera, Spain
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New:
MORE MASS MEDIA FOR AFRICA
AFRICA has a lower level of literacy and is poorer in information facilities
than any other region of the world. For every 100 people in this continent
there are only, on the average, 1.2 copies of daily newspapers, 1.8 radio
receivers and 0.5 cinema seats. Most of the African countries have no news
agencies of their own and no television services.
Ways of providing Africa with the means of mass media it so badly needs,
by aiding the development of newspapers, news agencies, radio broadcasting,
films and television, will be considered at a Unesco-convened meeting in
Casablanca, from January 24 to February 6.
The meeting, to which specialists from over 30 countries as well as observers
from international organizations have been invited, is expected to recommend
ways of expanding the rural press and promoting the use of radio and TV
for news and information. Suggestions will also be made for improving film
production and distribution and for training journalists in all the mass media.
Special stress will be laid on the use of the media for education, a basic element
in Africa's economic and social development. (Less than one year ago a
Unesco Conference of African States in Addis Ababa drew up a five-year
plan for extending primary education in the region).
The Casablanca meeting itself forms part of a world survey, which Unesco
is making for the United Nations, on the problems of helping the less developed
countries to build up their mass media. Two other regional meetings have
been held at Bangkok (for South-East Asia) and at Santiago (for Latin
America) and the final results of the survey will help the United Nations to
evaluate the resources needed for a development programme.
s<
42
' OVIET EYE' ON STORMS:
The highest scientific station in the Soviet
Union has been set .up at a height of
13,780 feet in the Baubashata Mountains
(Southern Kirghizia) to study atmospheric
electricity. Swept by thunderstorms every
five or six days, the Baubashata area is
the centre of the greatest storm activity in
Central Asia. From its mountain-top
vantage point the station will make obser¬
vations of the conditions of storm develop¬
ment, the parameters of lightning dischar¬
ges, the Earth's electric field and ionisa¬
tion of the air, in conjunction with the
Uzbek and Tajik Academies of Sciences.
AFRICA'S FLYING DOCTORS:
Nigeria has recently created a Flying
Doctor Service on the pattern of that
which has saved countless lives in Aus¬
tralia's vast outback areas. Like the
Australian service, Nigeria's will use
the latest version of the two-way pedal
radio. Power is generated by working
a pair of pedals on a frame, but today's
transceiver radios, powered by transis¬
tors, weigh only 15 pounds. Over
1,000 of them are now use in Australia.
¡Shakespeare in new york:
Free, open-air performances of Shake¬
speare's plays have recently been drawing
large crowds of New Yorkers nightly to
the Wollman Memorial Skating Rink
Theatre in Central Park, New York City.
The occasion has been the Sixth American
Shakespeare Festival which is financed by
contributions from over 5,000 donors
trade unions, business firms and founda¬
tions, students and other individual well-
wishers and by a subsidy from the New
York City public funds.
REPORT ON THE GALAPAGOS:
Two UNESCO-sponsored expeditions to
study the animal life of the Galapagos
Islands of the coast of Ecuador (see
The Unesco Courier, Jan. 1958, Sept.
1961) have been led by Dr. J. Eibl-Eibes-
feldt of the Max Planck Institute for
Behaviour Physiology in Seeshaupt, near
Munich. The findings of the expedi¬
tions have now been collected in a rich¬
ly illustrated 218-page report entitled
Galapagos (published by R. Piper
& Co., of Munich) which gives com¬
pletely new information about the uni¬
que fauna of the islands and suggests
measures to protect it from extinction.
JÜARGEST SCIENCE LIBRARY
The world's largest scientific and techni¬
cal library is now being built at the Siber¬
ian Division of the Academy of Sciences
of the U.S.S.R. in Novosibirsk. The build¬
ing is intended as a repository for ten mil¬
lion books. There will be sixteen reading
rooms accommodating 3,000 readers.
MENTAL HEALTH TODAY:
World Health, the monthly magazine
of the World Health Organization
(WHO) reports that psychiatry and men¬
tal hygiene, instead of being among the
least hopeful branches of therapeutic
and preventative medicine, now belong
to those which offer most promise.
"Today" , says the magazine, "we have
perhaps reached a point where the men¬
tal disorders, which are among the most
important mass diseases of the 20th cen¬
tury, can be attacked with the same ex¬
pectation of success as were communi¬
cable diseases some decades ago.
What is needed above all to further
mental health is scientific research."
UNESCO PHILATELIC SERVICE
UNITED NATIONS
si 1946-1961 as
NATIONS UNIES
Cince its foundation in December
^ 1946, the United Nations
Children's Fund (UNICEF) has been
helping many hundreds of mil¬
lions of needy children and their
mothers in all parts of the world
through programmes covering
maternal and child welfare services,
disease control and child nutri¬
tion. Last month the work of
UNICEF during the past I 5 years
was commemorated in the stamp
shown above issued by the United
Nations Postal Administration as the
fifth in its 1961 series of comme¬
morative stamps. In addition to
the 4 cent (gold, blue, green and
brown) denomination shown here,
the UNICEF commemorative stamp
was also issued in 3 cent (gold,
orange, yellow and brown) and
13 cent (gold, purple, pink and
green) versions. As the agent in
France of the U.N. Postal Adminis¬
tration, Unesco's Philatelic Servi¬
ce stocks all the United Nations
stamps currently on sale. It also
has stamps and first day covers
issued by many Unesco member
states to commemorate important
events in the history of Unesco
and the U.N. (inauguration of
Unesco's headquarters, Human
Rights Day, World Refugee Year).
Information on items available,
their price and methods of payment
will be sent on request by the
Unesco Philatelic Service, place
de Fontenoy, Paris-7*.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
January
LEARNING MEANS LIGHT. Education in the Arab lands. Becoming
an educated man in our modern world Lincoln Center, America's
capital for music & the arts The kingdom of the octopus The idea¬
lism of Leo Tolstoy World Leprosy Day Christianity & anti-Semi¬
tism.
tors Triumphs of modern architecture Brasilia, world's newest
capital Changing face of Latin America 70 million illiterates Men
of the land.
February
THE FACE OF NEW AFRICA. An African looks at the world New
schools for Africa Unesco's two-year plan for world action Unesco's
work for racial harmony Velazquez à la Picasso They call their
telescope "Bima Sakti".
March
REBIRTH OF A SHATTERED CITY. Canaletto, the painter of
Warsaw The world of prehistoric man New horizons for Asia's
Moslem women How the cinema affects children The curse of the
albatross.
April
ACCIDENTS NEED NOT HAPPEN. World's third worst killer -
Greatest risks in the home The dangerous world of childhood
Whose fault is it on the highway ? Safety is finest factory product
Danger stalks the farmer Treasures from the Parthenon Japan
misrepresented in foreign textbooks.
May
OF BOOKS AND LIBRARIES. The public library in the world
today Unesco survey of learning and leisure Eye banks for the
sightless Science's latest donor bank for blood vessels Micropho-
tography reveals an invisible world Strobophotography captures
the world in motion.
June
LATIN AMERICA: ISO YEARS OF INDEPENDENCE. Prelude
to independence The revolt which swept a continent The libera-
July/August
ART & SCIENCE IN THE LIFE OF MAN. Art In mathematics
Science, man & society Are men no better than ants ? World
survey of scientific research A science reporter speaks of "babelogy"
A tooth was the clue In the search for our ancestors Taras Shev-
chenko, Ukraine's poet of freedom.
September
AFRICA'S WILD LIFE IN PERIL. The vanishing herds - Poaching
Wild life as a world asset The drama of Screngetl Two men and
a "flying zebra" Fight for life at Ngorongoro Crater The Canadian
caribou, a disappearing species Galapagos Islands, a living laboratory
of evolution.
October
ABU SIMBEL, NOW OR NEVER. Ingenious engineers o( 1,000
years ago Jacking up a mountain of stone How Phllae's temples
will be saved Nubia, a vast archaeological camp from the land
of the pharaohs Floating laboratories on the Nile Journey to the
Land of Kush Nubia's Christian Age.
November
TODAY'S CRISIS IN ANTHROPOLOGY. Saving our vanishing
forests U.N. family at work Cosmic rays from outer space The
saga of Fridtjof Nansen UNICEF greeting cards Artists from Canada's
Far North A lighter side to wild life.
December
RABINDRANATH TAGORE, A UNIVERSAL VOICE. Ccnte-
nary homage to Tagore Portrait of a man Rebel with a universal
cause Realm of songs and melodies The enchantment of lines
Revelations of a Nobel Prize In literature Readings from Tagore
Art of Ethiopia's painter-scribes Tumultuous history of ancient Nubia.
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Press Department. Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I.. Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C-., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 50.-). BELGIUM. Office de Publicité S.A..
16, rte Marq. Brussels. CCP 285.98. NV Standaard-
Boekhandel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courrier( I 00 FB) and arc slides only : Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. S.SO). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. (S 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World|Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd.. Section I, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd.. 30 Ve Smeckách, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Norregade,
Kobenhavn K. (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 120. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kinakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinski.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy. Paris, 7». C.C.P. 1 2598-18. (7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier, Vertrieb Bahren¬
felder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld. CCP.
276650 (DM 8). Other Publications: R. Oldenbourg
Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. GHANA.
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100. Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 25, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chlmbtr, Nico! Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, I; 3 6a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asal All Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
(Rs. 6.70). INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat " Permata ",
D|alan Nusantara 22, Diakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10'-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35, Allenby
Road and 48. Nahlat Beniamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbathi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central. Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64. Seoul. LIBERIA. J. Momolu
Kamara, 69, Front and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück. 22. Grand-
Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYAN FEDERATION
AND SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd.. Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore. MALTA. Sa-
pienza's Library, 26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-). MAU¬
RITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N.V. Mirtinas Nijhoff, Lange Voorhouc, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G.C.T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemsud. Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications Centre,
I 00 Hackthorne Road, Christchurch. ( I 0/-). NIGERIA
C.M.S. Bookshop. P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR¬
WAY. For the Unesco Courier: A.S. Narvesens Littera-
lur-Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Postboks II 5 (kr. 13.20)
Other publications. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grenscn,
7, Oslo. PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co.,
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gufberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a. No. TI-49, Apartado
da Correos 2018. Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-).
LIPPINES. Philippine Education Co. Inc., I 104 Castille¬
jos. Quiapo, P.O. Box 620. Manila. POLAND.
" RUCH " ul.Wilota Nr. 46, Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda. Livrana Portugal,
Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. RHODESIA t, NYASA-
LAND. The Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SWEDEN. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Uneicoridet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications A/B C.E. Fritzes
Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse
Zurich. Payol, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-236. «Courier» only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers. Geneva. C.C.P. 1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit. Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isciklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O.. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier: Central News Agency. P.O. Box 1033, Johan¬
nesburg. (10;-). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). L» Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pisha,
Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 56», London, S.E.I. (10/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third
Avenue, New York, 22. N.Y. ($ 5.00.) and (except
periodicals): Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way. New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja
Kniga, Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslo-
venska Knjïga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Jacques Masson <; Expéditions polaires françaises.
WEATHER MEN IN THE 'ICE BOX'. The vast frozen mass of Antarcticasometimes called the "Ice Box" of the globe
a tremendous influence on world weather conditions and also with respect to glaciers and ocean currents.
Today, scientists of many nations are working to probe the secrets of Antarctica and thus replace mysteries by sure,
scientific information. France's scientists have been working in Adélie Land where, during the International Geophysical
Year (1957-58), they established their Charcot Station 200 miles inland towards the magnetic pole. Charcot Station made
research into magnetism and recorded weather information with meteorological observation equipment shown here.
]]>
</page>
</document>
