<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064092eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m mura
JULY-AUGUST 1961 (14TH YEAR) - PRICE : 2/-STG. (U.K.) - 60 CENTS (U.S.) - 1,40 NF (FRANCE)
ART IN THE LIFE OF MAN
SCIENCE IN THE LIFE OF MAN
MINBTRJ £ f h! L-tPW ^V>uöv;C i;
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
FORMS FROM FORMULAE. This photo looks like the work of a modern abstract artist.
In reality it is'the three-dimensional projection of a mathematical formula, known as Pluckner's
conoid. It is displayed in the Mathematics Hall of the Palace of Discovery, Paris. See page 24.
(c) Paul Almasy. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
JULY - AUGUST 1961
14TH YEAR
Contents
No. 7-8
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
German
American
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
The human figure has been
a favourite subject for artists
of all ages. On the cover,
from top to bottom : (1) A
procession from an ancient
Egyptian fresco. (2) Section
of Picasso's Guernica. (3)
Frieze from Angkor Thorn
temple (4) Detail of Japanese
painting of market scene,
Hokusal school. (5) Section
of Nth century Bayeux tapes¬
try, France. (See page 4.)
Photos © Bulloz, Giraudon, Paris
SPECIAL DOUBLE ISSUE
Art and Science
Page
5 ART IN THE LIFE OF MAN
by D'Arcy Hayman
25 ART IN MATHEMATICS
Museum of Discovery, Paris
3 1 SCIENCE, MAN AND SOCIETY
A biologist outlines a philosophy for life
by Sir James Gray
34 ARE MEN NO BETTER THAN ANTS?
40 WORLD SURVEY OF SCIENTIFIC RESEARCH
A physicist charts global trends in science
by Daniel Behrman
46 A SCIENCE REPORTER SPEAKS OF
Ritchie Calder Unesco Kalinga Prize winner
48 A TOOTH WAS THE CLUE
In the search for our ancestors
by G. H. R. von Koenigswald
53 TARAS SHEVCHENKO
Ukraine's Poet of Freedom
by Pauline Bentley
57 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
58 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
BABELOLOGY
(M.C. 6I.I.I60 A>
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Gordon Behrens
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Amin Chaker (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English. French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of Issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U.S. "*' 3.00; IO/-stg". ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be oddressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UiäL
H5r ' *T¿ At^M E^isssk ' t '"*
-Ja *.^fl
Detail of metal screen around tomb in
the Church of the Archangel, Moscow.
J» <i*
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
\
Vr
wv
v
y¿ÑX
\ A^
Vj
L/
\
r l.	 J - '
:-*j
/^/^
4?
iL
J
f
K^
\
ÍS¿I
IN THE
LIFE OF
MAN
by Dr. d'Arcy Hayman
Head of Arts Education Section
Arts and Letters Division, Unesco
-41
< ^
Sot
Ü5**s
4
y*îfc
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
S? 'Treating the commonplace with the
sublime gives art its true power'
Jean-François Millet
Anatomical study, Leonardo da Vinci.
Photo © Anderson-Giraudon, Paris
Jn
very child, every man, every culture gives
'form to its feelings and ideas through art.
Art is the essence of that which is human ; it is the embo¬
diment of the human experience and goal. From the
moment in our history when man became distinguishable
as man, art was the mark that distinguished him, and
ever since, man has continued to be an artful creature.
The art act and object provide constant evidence and
demonstration of the human act and objective.
In this contemporary world of growing technology, man
views his place along the path of human activity with
mixed feelings of pride and doubt. The promise of a
tomorrow liberated by human imagination and devotion
yet threatened by narrowness, coldness, disintegration,
puts man at a crucial point in time and space at which
he must carefully re-examine and re-assess the values by
which he lives. It is especially important now that we
carefully examine the vital functions of the arts in culture
and give renewed attention and emphasis to the inherent
contributions of the arts to the survival and development
of man.
A culture gives evidence of the will and participation
of the individual. Art functions in a society much as it
functions in the life of an individual. It becomes the
emblem of a group, just as it is the mark of a single man.
It is a universal and personal implement with which men
protect and liberate themselves. It is a plan by which the
crowd and the man apart from the crowd can make cohe¬
rent the fragments of existence. It is an all-embracing
sentiment that brings men together, preserving for them,
still, their uniqueness. It is a moment in time when every
child and every man is beautiful and fulfilled. Art is a
dynamic, ubiquitous source which serves human need and
manifests the human potential.
A;RT can and should be an experience shared by
-all men every day of their lives; this does not
mean that all men must be painters, architects, authors,
composers, nor does it mean that men must spend all
their evenings in theatres and concert halls. Rather, it
means that man's innate sensitivities to the arts must
be allowed to develop, and, by early encouragement and
education, must be given opportunity for growth so that
the whole man can emerge.
The art experience embraces all " forms of involvement
with art: the production of works of art on the part of
the professional artist, the primitive craftsman, the lay¬
man, the child, as well as the active appreciation of art
on the part of the universal art audience which looks at,
listens to, reads and uses the work of art with personal
interest, understanding and love. The ultimate dimension
of the art experience is that which enables each man to
become aware of the aesthetic of his own environment,
brings to his attention the endless excitement of form
and colour, the richness of texture, the force, rhythm and
sound of human interaction, the poetry of nature and
man.
In the complexity of a modern world, it has become
necessary for men to "specialize" in their vocations, their
work. As a result, the human disciplines of art and
science, of philosophy and technology, have been sepa¬
rated, to the detriment of each. This twentieth century
phenomenon is at the peril of man, himself. It is as if
man had attempted to sever his head from his body in
order to isolate one faculty of his being from another.
Leonardo da Vinci lived in an age when one man could
embrace both fields of investigation simultaneously. In
the tradition of most oriental cultures, we find that a
man, whether he be statesman, businessman, or scientist,
in order to be considered a complete man, a whole man,
must have an intimate understanding of and sensitivity
to the arts. As art and science reach their purest form,
the parallel objectives, experiences, procedures, and end
products, almost merge into a single image, with the
scientist crediting his own intuitive senses and the artist
discussing problems of energy and matter.
Albert Einstein has said :
Man tries to make for himself in the fashion that
suits him best a simplified and intelligible picture of
the world; he then tries to some extent to substitute
this cosmos of his for the world of experience, and
thus overcome it. This is what the painter, the poet,
the speculative philosopher and the natural scientist
do, each in his own fashion. He makes this cosmos
and its construction the pivot of his emotional life,
in order to find in this way the peace and security
which he cannot find in the narrow whirlpool of per¬
sonal experience.
But in these words of Einstein, we cannot overlook the
phrase "each in his own fashion", for here is the key to
the difference between art and science. It is true that the
realm of science, like art, offers man an area in which his
imagination is given free rein, and it is even possible for
the man of science to arrive at his answers intuitively,
just as the artist does. But the paths to scientific and
aesthetic solutions differ greatly, and the final products
of each effort manifest these basic differences. The fact
that art is different from all other fields of human endea¬
vour makes it irreplaceable and indispensable in the life
of man.
Art functions in man's life in many nameless ways. In
any analysis of the role of art in human existence, one
can only attempt to describe those qualities of the art
experience that appear, at a specific moment in time and
space, to be of particular value to man. Each individual,
each culture, each age, will arrive at different points of
CONT'D ON PAGE 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Detail of Old Man Seated, by Rembrandt. From the Gulbenkian Museum, Lisbon.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
--,'
«sszik;
rfIN/ THE
A '
Tine art is that in which the hand,
the head, and the heart go together'
John Ruskin
ma
1\H^
Aàm /
In a graceful line-up, young Danish ballet
students execute a difficult tip-toe exercise.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
© Paul Almasy, Paris
As they work, craftsmen like this designer
producing a floral motif on glass, discov¬
er new possibilities within their materials.
Painting offers these children of nursery-school
age a medium for free and uninhibited expres¬
sion. For children art is a way of discovery.
USIS
'Art is science in the flesh'
Jean Cocteau
emphasis according to its own need and history. It ls
even true that a work of art produced to satisfy one
human need in one period of time can function in an
entirely different way in another culture.
The best one can do when one hopes to verbally clarify
and classify the functions of art, is to attempt to single
out those ways in which art seems to be of significant
value to human existence and development at a particu¬
lar moment. Other men In other times and places have
described and will continue to describe the functions of
art differently, for art, like man, is ever changing, ever
evolving and becoming, ever new. But let us now (speak¬
ing out of our own frame of reference) consider those
ways in which art functions in the life of man.
To be alive is to be aware, curious, active, sensitive, pro¬
ductive, adventurous, concerned, involved. To be dead is
to be none of these things. Art increases our state of
aliveness by expanding and deepening our state of
awareness. Jean Cocteau once commented that to write
is to kill something of death. Art discovers, heightens,
and refines life experiences; it brings our emotions to our
attention and makes us fully feel them. Art is a selection
and examination of the physical and social world in order
that we may apprehend in ideal simplicity the selected
properties and values usually evident only obscurely, if at
all, in ordinary experience. Art serves to clarify our
feelings. Until we express emotions we do not know what
they are. The artist's vision, both analytic and panora¬
mic, makes perceptible at once the parts and the whole.
It has been said that man does not create; he regene¬
rates. Perhaps this means that man does not actually
create new forms, new orders, new life; rather, he dis¬
covers the fundamental forms and processes of his uni¬
verse and gives them new energy and function. What we
call "creativity" in human beings may, in fact, have to do
with that human discovery of a pre-existing fact, a
"cosmic truth".
P
JL i
'erception involves that discovery which man
makes about his environment conditioned by
his past experience; it is the combination of the physical
make-up of the object in relation to the symbolic asso¬
ciations made by human minds and senses. Discovery in
and through art includes not only that finding the artist
makes about his work, but the discovery the work of art
makes about him. The work of art sums up and reflects
the discoveries the artist has made about his environment
and about himself. For the child, as for the man, art is
a way of discovery which leads to new understanding of
the physical world in which he lives and of the self; it
gives new meaning and significant form to his life.
The life experience of man is a concert of involvements.
The degree to which a human being involves himself with
life differs according to the kinds of things that determine
and shape the moments of his existence. Art intensifies
man's involvement with life; it gives evidence and symbol
of human energy; it clarifies, vivifies human experience.
Art deals with the emotional realm of man; it supplies
stimulus for his capacity to feel and react, it expands his 9
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
'All arts are brothers each
one a light to the others'
Voltaire
area of sentiment. The art experience sharpens and
rewards the senses, and thus it develops all human
faculties.
It is the function of art to develop man's ability to feel
and to know beauty. Delacroix wrote in his diary: "In
many people the eye is untrue or inert; they see the
objects literally; of the exquisite they see nothing."
But when we speak of beauty we must be careful to
point out that concepts of beauty change and manifest
themselves differently according to the culture, the time,
the individual. Both classical Greek and African primi¬
tive art are beautiful; both Oriental and Occidental music
are beautiful. But concepts of beauty in these cultures
differ. We can easily appreciate standards of beauty that
are familiar to us, but it is with more difficulty that we
develop an appreciation of other kinds of beauty than
our own.
We meet the same difficulty when we consider,
the difference that time makes upon our no¬
tions of what is beautiful. It is well known that many
of the artists whom we now list among "the great
masters" were considered radical, ill equipped, even mad
for their own daring to express an individual concept of
beauty which was too advanced for their time. Rem¬
brandt, El Greco, Blake, Rodin, Van Gogh and countless
other artists, composers, poets were criticized, ridiculed
or ignored in their time. Whole periods of art were simi¬
larly berated: "Gothic" was a name applied to the art
and architecture of medlaevel times in depreciation by
Renaissance scholars who considered it crude and ugly.
The problem is ever the same. Today, that which is
called "modern art" or "abstract art" is met, in many
parts of the world, with public indignation and bewilder¬
ment. It is true that new forms of art are difficult to
evaluate because they often require new criteria for eval¬
uation, new standards for judgment. Surely not all of
our contemporary paintings, architectural structures,
musical and literary works will survive the critical per¬
spective of time. But we must trust that time will select
out of our age those key works which intensify our
moment in history and become part of the next genera¬
tion's visual landscape.
One of the greatest problems in our contemporary civi¬
lization is the inability of large numbers of people to
commit themselves wholly and intensely to an ideal, a
cause, an objective. Where once the mark of youth was
vitality, courage, energetic involvement, we now find
growing numbers of the young people of the world drifting
carelessly into a gutter of nothingness and decay.
Art is among the human disciplines that allow for and
depend upon the intense commitment of man to cons¬
tructive action.
A problem assuming gigantic proportions in our new
technological world is that of "mass leisure". Men once
dreamed of the day when physical slavery would be abo¬
lished, when the common man would work at the
necessary tasks of the society for a minimum amount of
time, to be released from these chores to enjoy a great
10 portion of his life in leisure. That day is gradually coming
CONT'D ON PAGE I 3
I i>
Bahnar cemetery statues, in southern Viet Nam.
Mosaic from the Sforza Castle Museum, Milan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Woman in Tears, by Pablo Picasso
Collection Roland Penrose. London.
African wooden statuette.
Classical Kabuki dancer, Japan.
Mythological figure, Pre-lnca
Chimu civilization, ancient Peru.
Woman at work.
Indonesian wood carving.
Basel Ethnological Museum,
Switzerland.
Bulloz, Paris
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
«63
12
TtlE
mm
imk
1/ \lï'\X
'Man is tougher than iron, harder than
stone and more delicate than the rose'
Turkish proverb
/
« o
Joan of Arc. Painting by Georges Rouault. Museum of Modern Art, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Indian National Museum, New Delhi
The love story of Radha and Krishna is an epic theme of Indian miniature painting. Thousands of
works were done recounting this story. Here, a 17th century work in northern Indian style
for a large measure of the world's people. Instead of
bringing the utopia it promised, new problems are grow¬
ing. Men feel an emptiness and bewilderment at suddenly
acquiring large blocks of leisure time without the psycho¬
logical preparation and education for it.
As a result of this new technological gift, television sales
have zoomed, entertainment has become a four thousand
million dollar a year business in America alone, but along
with these statistics we can find that the rate of alcoho¬
lism, drug addiction, mental illness and juvenile crime
has risen to alarming proportions. The "threat of
leisure" is the result of a new class of people who have
successfully fought and won the battle of rights and pri¬
vileges for the working man only to fall into the aimless
and decadent pattern of playboys.
The role of art in education has great meaning here.
The art experience which involves the feelings of children
and men encourages incentive and allows for commitment.
Art makes leisure time and all time a thing of meaningful
excitement and beauty. The challenge of art is to enríame
and intensify in order to evoke deep emotional and in¬
tellectual responses united with those responses felt by
human beings in their relationships of man to nature and
man to man.
Art is that area of human experience which encom¬
passes expressive activity. Storytelling, celebrating,
acting, singing, painting and dancing are the fruits
of man's need for expressive activity. We often
classify cultures upon their expressive activity alone.
Different societies may have the same mores and the same
work habits, but if their art is different, the societies are
different.
Self-expression, as manifested in art, distinguishes in¬
dividuals, as well as cultures. Man's life differs from that
of most other organisms in that individualization has
become more important to him than strict conformity to
type. Individual capacity, viewpoint, choice, and action
are qualities that make us human. Sartre in his exis¬
tentialist philosophy presents a strong plea not to forget
that Individual men and women and children are neither
machines nor logical terms. We cannot find them, nor
can they find themselves merely in systems, either poli¬
tical or metaphysical. We cannot explain them by stereo
types. Each individual living with "nothingness" at his
heart must fill that void in his own way.
The human individual is solitary and unique. As such,
each is irreplaceable; to understand him is each time a
new problem. We must come to a place where we are able
to apprehend a person in his uniqueness, to understand
what makes him different from everyone else. Sartre has
established one absolute value for man: freedom. Free¬
dom and free choice are man's duty as well as his natural
condition. A person not only may make his life significant
by living according to meanings and values which he has
chosen, but he ought to do so.
Man can and should renew himself each moment
through his capacity for free choice. Chekhov once said
that his aim in Ufe was to squeeze the slave out of him¬
self. In a letter to a friend he described himself in youth
as one who was brought up to fawn on rank and accept
without questioning other people's ideas, one who behaved
hypocritically toward God and man without the slightest
excuse but that he was conscious of his own worthlessness.
As a man, Chekhov was able to find his worth, his pur¬
pose, in his art and the opportunity it gave him for per¬
sonal expression.
Art expression enables man to see himself and com¬
municate with himself for it gives voice to the self. The
artist's product makes the man unique as much as his
thumb print and signature single him out. The artist does
not deal in categories but in particulars, and he deals
directly with them. This individuation of experience, of
emotion, is made possible through art.
Anthropologists and archaeologists have estimated that
it was just about a million years ago, at the beginning of
the Pleistocene period, that man emerged from the world
of primates. There have been many attempts to describe
and identify the human characteristics of man. But
whatever the historian's conclusions, they are always
based, in large measure, upon the artifacts and aesthetic
expressions which automatically reflect the individual and
his particular time and culture.
One of the distinguishing features of the human spirit
is its need to record personal and group experience. The
finger-tracings, drawings, engravings, bas-reliefs and
paintings on the wans of caves inhabited by earliest man
tell a clear and direct story about the dawn of human
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
'Art is the one way possible
of speaking truth*
Robert Browning
culture. The historian knows that the art of every age
and every culture is an outgrowth, an extension of that
age and culture. There is no more accurate description
of a certain time and place than is given to us by the
artifacts we find from the remains of that civilization.
When we trace the history of man up to current times
we can find recorded and reflected in the art work of each
period the life and death, the beliefs and fears, the joys
and sufferings of human beings.
The work of art stands as summary and chronicle of
human experience. Man still has need of leaving a
record of his life experience. But many a man or child
is frustrated in his attempts to manifest his observations
in the complicated and abstract signs and symbols of a
highly technical society. Record making in the natural
and personal symbols of art enables all men, all children
to record the uniqueness and significance of their own
lives.
One of the greatest of human gifts is the highly de¬
veloped capacity to communicate; it is in the act of
communication that men can relate themselves to other
men near and far in time and space. For the purpose of
communication men have invented symbols, and this
symbol-making function is one of man's primary acti¬
vities; in fact it is the fundamental process of the mind
and goes on all the time. This process actuates human
aims, fancies, consciousness of value, awareness and
enthusiasms.
»
Chinese landscape painting, now
in the Musée Guimet, Paris
S:
14
kl. Hayakawa has said that the task of art is
"perpetually to search for emblems with which
adequately to symbolize and thus to enable us to cope
with our experience. Symbol making is basic to man.
Man must record his experiences and feelings in symbols
in order to communicate them to other men. A whole
system of communication sprang from the earliest draw¬
ings and paintings. The alphabet and all written lan¬
guage are outgrowths of these earliest recorded images.
The visual and musical arts offer man means of com¬
munication that go even beyond the scope of words. The
painter, the composer have invented symbols that can be
passed from man to man so that concepts and feelings
can be conveyed directly.
Just after the turn of the century, Kandinsky wrote
one of the first explanations of "non-objective" art as a
means of communication. Kandinsky drew upon his own
first art experience in music as a basis for his argument
that form and colour in themselves constitute a language
adequate to express and communicate emotion just as
musical sound acts directly on the soul. He believed that
it was not necessary in the visual arts to have the kind
of material subject matter found in literature. Form itself
is the expression of inner meaning.
Art as a tool, as a medium of communication has many
implications for the life and education of man. In these
times when the development, even the survival of man,
depends upon full and successful intercultural commu¬
nication we cannot afford to overlook or ignore any area
or form of communication. The aesthetic level of human
interaction is one which is Indispensable in the life of all
persons.
CONPD ON PAGE I 6
Executioner preparing the cross.
By Albrecht Dürer, Bonnat Collection
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Starry Night, by Vincent van Gogh, now in Museum of Modern Art, New York, Giraudon, Paris
Unesco - Marc Riboud Buddhist sculpture, on wall of Borobudur Temple, Java.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Hieroglyphic carvings,
Great Temple of Abu Simbel, Egypt.
Interior with Egyptian Curtain, by Henri Matisse. The Phillips Gallery, Washington Intention, a painting by Paul Klee.
'Art hath an enemy called ignorance*
Ben Jonson
16
If, in the human order of things, each man is an indi¬
vidual with a particular set of senses and special arrange¬
ment of capacities, then each man's vision is different,
and the record each makes of his life and. environment
will be a unique interpretation.
All of the arts are formed upon a set of basic symbols.
Music, language, painting, involve abstractions that live
as separate and self-contained entities, but when these
symbols are long studied and learned, they act as a mag¬
nifying glass, a microscope which is turned back upon
ourselves. Art makes fundamental relationships visible
to the half-closed eye. Caught up in the complexity of
civilizations man often loses sight of his human objective.
The artist then not only records the physical facts of his
being, but must act as interpreter, translator of the
human experience. Art acts as diagnosis, definition, and
rationale for the human condition.
The Pyramids of Gizeh, the Parthenon, the temple of
Vishnu, the cathedral at Chartres, the United Nations
buildings stand, not only as a record of the time out of
which they were built, but as translations of that time.
The paintings of Giotto, Rembrandt, Tung Yuan, Grune
wald, Miro, Pollack, de Kooning are highly personal, yet
they become universal interpretations of human expe¬
rience.
Art does not stop at recording natural facts; art, as
the Swiss thinker Amiel once said, reveals nature by in¬
terpreting its intentions and formulating its desires.
Artists do not merely record what they see; they have
always put themselves and their culture and their age
into their art. African sculpture is filled with the great
power and dignity of the African people. We can look
back at the magnificent art of Egypt and see how the
artist's pictorial representation took in all he saw and
believed; we see how the Greeks breathed life into their
schematic forms, how mediaeval man brought his own
passion and devotion to the art forms he produced, how
Chinese and Japanese artists have reflected the contem¬
plative quality of their culture. And the contemporary
artist in all cultures endeavours to select out of his expe¬
rience those salient observations and felt responses in
order to interpret them for others through his craft.
In speaking about his friend, Picasso, Jean Cocteau
once said: "...he never let himself be bothered by external
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
M
lililí '!!'
Woven cloth design, Tlingit
Indians, Alaska and N.W. Canada.
1 '{i
Painted canvas, Chimu
Indian civilization, Peru.
Arabic lettering on the grave of Shah Zindeh, a. 14th century shrine in Samarkand.
views: they are after all simply the field which he har¬
vests, for he is a harvester. He is an inspired ragpicker,
the king of ragpickers. He picks up whatever lies in his
path and makes it serve him." The artist acts not only
as translator of his individual experience, but as inter¬
preter of the whole human experience as well.
The artist consciously or unconsciously seeks to change
and improve upon the human condition. When all
things as they are please a man, the stimulus toward
creative activity is absent. Whatever the designer's area,
the painter's subject, he, as a member of the human race,
is concerned with the betterment of mankind. The ar¬
chitects of our time, Le Corbusier, Mies van der Rohe,
Frank Lloyd-Wright, Nervi, Neutra, Buckminster, Fuller
and others, are profoundly concerned with human pro¬
gress. They devote their energies to the study and
meeting of human needs and problems.
Schiller wrote this shortly before he died: "One of the
most important tasks of culture is to submit man to the
influence of form... to make his life aesthetic by intro¬
ducing the rule of beauty wherever possible; because only
from the aesthetic can morality develop".
The painter and the sculptor have long been actively
engaged in social and spiritual reform. Goya and Dau-
mier and Orozco, who etch upon our eyes and mind
appalling moments of man's treachery; Kirchner and
Munch and Bacon, who point out the problems of a civi¬
lized society all contribute, along with the philosophers
and statesmen and scientists, to social reform within the
human society.
The artist traditionally has taken part in many kinds
of reformation, for it is the very essence of his craft to
"re-form" his environment. When we view the word in
this original sense we can see that the artist is the master
of reform; he takes the pigments and fibres and wood
and clay and rook and metal from their natural organic
and inorganic states and gives them new form; he takes
the everyday visions and values of men and "re-forms"
them as well.
Perhaps the most elusive quality of man is, that which
we call the spiritual. We cannot locate its source in the
physical make-up of men, but we know that the human
spirit is one of the things that defines the human being.
Spiritual reform is one of the tasks of the artist. Today's
painter attempts to escape the superficial, to penetrate
the façade, and to enter into the realm of the spirit of
man. Just as the Haiku poet endeavours to express a
cosmic truth in seventeen syllables, the painter, with
poetic economy, strives to capture the universe in a rain
drop.
Charles Morris has written: "Art is the language for
the communication of values... art does not, except inci¬
dentally, make statements about values, but presents
values for direct experience ; it is not a language about
values, but the language of value."
Art enhances life. Just as the artist, by his very act,
attempts to alter his environment, he also seeks to enrich 17
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
IMTpE
'All the arts relating
to human life are linked
together by a subtle bond*
Cicero
18
it. Art can touch every phase of human life and make
it that much more comfortable and beautiful. The art
products that serve our physical needs, our clothes and
furniture and automobiles should function as utilitarian
as well as art objects. The art products that meet our
Intellectual-emotional-spiritual needs, paintings, sculp¬
ture, the ceremonial vase, the tapestry, the book illustra¬
tion, the film, the flower garden, serve other human
requirements. But all of art serves man's aesthetic needs,
and aesthetic needs are common to all. Thomas Aquinas
said: "The senses delight in things duly proportioned as
in something akin to them; for the sense, too, is a kind
of reason as is cognitive power."
Aesthetic pleasure has been the source of productivity
in art since prehistoric times. The "home art" of Mag-
dalenian man included delicate engravings on utensils
and tools; at the same time Central and North American
men dyed and decorated the animal skins, they wore,
painted intricate motifs on their canoes. Wood carving,
basketry, pottery, leather work, and jewellery making are
among the first accomplishments of man. When we look
at the magnificent use of colour and form in an ancient
Peruvian textile or in a Zuni jar of the North American
Indians we become aware of man's earliest need to act
upon, control, change and enhance his environnent.
The gardens of Villa d'Esté, the canals of Venice, Len¬
ingrad and Bruges, the tapestries of the Lady and the
Unicorn, the Angkor Wat carvings of Cambodia, the Ja¬
panese Nô drama robes give glowing evidence that man's
need to beautify has persisted. Today, the artist still works
to make the moments of our life more pleasurable: a
Scandinavian chair, a Parisian gown, a New York stage
set, Japanese packaging are the contemporary designer's
contribution to the visual excitement and reward of our
daily lives.
Mass production, made possible by the technological
progress of our times, has been the cause of many of our
societies' current problems. One of these problems is that
of the badly-made object, mass-produced by insensitive
or irresponsible persons, and forced upon an innocent
public through the vicious misuse of advertising and
other forms of propaganda, so that the public level of
taste is consistently lowered until it actually selects the
poorly constructed object in preference to the well de¬
signed one. The machine age has given us cities that
look like prisons, highways and streets vulgarized by
endless signs, billboards, neon lights.
But the machine in the hands of an artist can become
a miraculous tool. The industrial designer, a product of
Venus du Mas, antique marble
statue found in 1 876 at Mas
d'Agenais, south-western France.
© Giraudon, Paris
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
I Bulloz, Paris
IH
Virgin and St. John, detail of The Crucifixion, painted by the 15th
century German artist, Grunewald. Now in the Colmar Museum, France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
'Art is the conveyance of spirit by means of matter'
our modern world, has been working to make "good
design" available to all men through mass produced fur¬
niture, textiles, utensils, buildings, automobiles, clothes,
etc. There are many problems to be solved in this field,
but we can look to the future with enthusiasm.
In consideration of art as enhancement we must come
again to the question: What is beauty? We know that
beauty is "relative"; for what may be deemed "beau¬
tiful" by one person, one culture, one age, may be con¬
sidered "ugly" by another. But this is the very factor
that makes the aesthetic object a human thing: it brings
men together in agreement and at the same time separ¬
ates them as individuals who see things in their own way.
This is one of the major tasks of artists in society: to
discover and establish new forms of beauty. When the
day comes that all men are educated through art, as
Herbert Read advises, they will learn to understand and
respect the varying nature of beauty while at the same
time maintaining a selective eye in -their standards of
aesthetic quality. And they will learn, as well, how
aesthetic awareness can give new incentive, new enrich¬
ment to their Uves.
Another factor to be considered when we look at the
way in which art functions to enhance life is that which
embraces the "pleasure principle." Running parallel to
man's need for self-discipline, control, "denial," is the
human need for fanciful escape, distraction, release from
the self-inflicted tensions of civilized living.
We need only to look at the long and fascinating history
of games, to find evidence of this fact. "Play" assumes
an all important role in the world of the child; in the
adult's life, the need for play persists, but the quality
of play, the complexity of the games change and increase
as the individual matures.
T
20
he arts offer man an opportunity for play.
Schiller has described this function of art in
man's life in this way: "In the midst of the awful realm
of powers, and of the sacred realm of laws, the aesthetic
creative impulse is building unawares a third joyous
realm of play and appearance, in which it releases
mankind from all the shackles of circumstance and frees
him from everything that may be called constraint; to
grant freedom by means of freedom is the fundamental
law of this kingdom."
There is an international relatedness, a coherence of
things. The physical world, the universe, provide a
highly structured and intricately formed environment for
man. And man is a unit in the endlessly complex
pattern; he is a form, within a form. Man's need for,
search for relationship, order, springs from a primordial
sense of consistency. This is the motive of inquiry, dis¬
covery, creativity; this is the basis for logic. But some¬
times we see man, in his paradoxical attempt to destroy
himself, deny and work against this innate sense of order.
We find evidences of this contradiction in highly civilized
societies where men inflict chaos upon themselves and
then retreat in escape to overcrowded mental hospitals
and psychiatrists' couches.
The superstructure of modern day man's institutional
life is marked by a spreading disintegration. Specializ¬
ation in occupations, compartmentalization in social acti¬
vity separate human need from related human need and
divorce human capacity from its use and fulfilment.
The aesthetic experience enables man to bring the bits
and particles of his life into an ordered structure, and it
provides for the interaction of the human organism with
environment.
Man, the artist, seeks to disentangle the most essential
strands of existence and weave them into a beautiful
fabric of intense validity, characteristic of himself and his
culture and his time. The order and form we find in a work
of art are not superimposed; they originate in the human
act of creation and are an organic event.
Greek philosophy was deeply and inherently connected
with Greek art, for it embodied not only rational thought,
but also vision (theorica) which apprehends objects in
relation to each other, and sees the idea in everything,
namely visible pattern. Giotto, like his contemporary,
Dante, saw life as a connection of parts. And later,
Leonardo da Vinci sensed the same order in the universe
and in the life of man. Paul Klee has commented that
the artist is so well oriented he can put order into the
flux of phenomena and experience. All men of art at
all times are concerned with the total web of relationships
among the parts of their existence.
Just as philosophy is characterized more by the for¬
mulation of its problems than by its solution of them
(incomplete patterns possess their own inherent élan),
and mathematics by a tendency toward completion, so the
realm of art is a condition of this tendency toward
completion, a search for order and harmony. Thus,
when we speak of art as order, we really cannot narrow
our thinking to some formula for peace and serenity that
the realm of art offers man as a way of life.
The art experience, for child and man, is the manifes¬
tation of the human and universal search for order out
of chaos; the work of art is the embodiment of this
search. We can respect it and be grateful for it as
such, in these times when the tendency toward order
© Giraudon. Paris
Gold necklaces and jewellery, India.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Salvador de Madariaga
and form is more and more frustrated and inhibited.
Involvement in art gives incentive to our forming power
and makes dynamic the order that we may find.
Our twentieth-century existence is marked by a
growing disintegration: the child is separated from his
parents, the parents are separated from each other, the
family members are separated from the community,
labour Is separated from work and further separated into
parts, each compartment is again separated, science is
separated from art, philosophy from religion, and religion
is splintered into opposing bits, formal education is
separated into endless departments, the senses are
separated from the intellect, and man is separated from
man.
Man is, basically, filled with the urge to form, with the
need to find harmony and build order. But it can happen
that as societies and civilizations become more organized,
more compartmentalized, more categorized, man becomes
more confused, defeated, and dehumanized. For there
can be order without integration; man can establish a
system that puts the fragments of his existence into a
rigid order. He can tightly regiment the moments of
his life, thus making for himself an orderly plan by which
to live. But the very neat and precise order he builds
can become a series of separate prisons that divide and
hold the many aspects of his being apart, and thus lead
to his disintegration. Man not only needs to establish an
orderly arrangement of the parts of his life, but he must
integrate the parts into a meaningful whole, and the
whole must become even more significant than the orga¬
nization of the parts.
The synthesis of intellect and emotion is possible only
on an aesthetic level of experience. Establishing rela¬
tionships between the world of fantasy, imagination,
thought, and the physical world of objective reality then
is another of the functions of art. For, when the artist
externalizes his visual image, he gives form to it and it
Decorative tassels made in France.
CONT'D ON PAGE 23 Traditional decorations of wooden
dwellings in Batak village, Sumatra.
mm¿ '
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
tfflS
wkwi
Composition in Red,
Yellow and Blue, by Mondrian.
Detail of exterior wall design
of modern Mexican skyscraper.
I Paul Almasy
) Paul Almasy Traditional decorative designs, Ndebele tribe, South Africa.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
'Great art is an instant in eternity'
James Huneker
IH I ii
Bulloz, Paris
Supreme poetic masterpiece of Gothic art, the six tapestries known as "La Dame à la Licorne" (The Lady
with the Unicorn) are supposed to have been made for an early I 5th century French nobleman as a gift for
his bride-to-be. Five of them represent the Allegories of the Five Senses while the sixth shows the Lady
under a canopy. Above, a detail from the Allegory of the Sense of Taste. The Lady is seen taking a sweet
from a bowl proffered by her attendant. The exquisitely woven animals and flowers are set against a red
ground and a blue carpet. The mythical unicorn symbolizes purity and stability. Cluny Museum, Paris.
becomes a fact. The great artist is one who has success¬
fully Integrated vast areas of human experience.
The problem of the integration of man, of society, is one
that has long, concerned philosophers, psychologists,
educators, and all who study human need and behaviour.
Eastern cultures have given emphasis to this problem of
man's oneness, selfhood, union. Zen Buddhism, which is
a culmination of several ancient Indian, Chinese, and
Japanese philosophies, attempts to liberate the energies
stored in each man, which are, in ordinary circumstances,
cramped and distorted so that they find no adequate
channel for activity; Zen develops the art of seeing into
the nature of one's own being.
Zen Buddhists have long known and respected the
power of art as integration; they know that when a man
is intensely involved in his craft, he is at one with It, and
thus he is at one with nature and with himself. The
form of painting practised in Zen is known as Sumiye; it
attempts to catch the Spirit as it moves; everything
becomes, nothing is stationary; the artist must follow his
inspiration as spontaneously and absolutely and instantly
as it moves. Sumiye painting, like much of the abstract
painting of contemporary occidental cultures, calls upon
the whole man at once; his physical, his emotional his
intellectual, his spiritual selves are integrated into one
act, one moment, one man.
Today the entire society of man, threatened with
spiritual and physical disintegration is becoming aware
of its own separateness, emptiness, purposelessness. We
are a human race in search of meaning, in need of form
to shape the welter of incoherent fragments that enter
our experience. Only when art has reintegrated, re-
humanized society will the human race be ready, in
Goethe's words, to live manfully in the whole, the good,
and the beautiful. If we are to find new motivation, new
direction, new harmony for our life, we must turn to art,
for the plan and model is there.
Dr. d'Arcy Hayman, who directs the Programme in Art Education
for Unesco, has been a member of the Faculties of Art and Art
Education at the University of California, New York University
and Columbia University. She is an American educator, author,
and painter. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
SS ABEL ABOUL-WÉFA i
1 --LMt:^hff(1^ .i-*M.:iiv %
.*- ».i
? - '
Ç
j piRALs in space, graceful whorls rising in the
^J monumental architecture of our time, billow¬
ing honeycombs and cubist dreams are all on exhibition
in a museum which, even though it is located in Paris,
has nothing to do with art.
The museum is the Palais de la Découverte just off the
Champs-Elysées and Its "sculptures", easily the rival of
avant-garde art, are nothing but mathematical forms
projected in three dimensions.
A walk through the Mathematics Hall of this "Palace
of Discovery" is quite an experience for the layman.
Accustomed to abstract art, he experiences the shock of 25
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Apparently works of abstract sculpture, these forms present two of
the infinitely many possible shapes representing third degree equations.
Photos © Paul Almasy
encountering its forms as expressions of the basic reality
of mathematics.
The result is a head-spinning world in which lines
intersect harmoniously, mountains rise out of a lunar
surface and curves seem to have been moulded by the
loving thumb of the sculptor shaping clay to conform to
an image in his mind. It is a gallery of forms, some
beautiful, some perhaps nightmarish, but all with an
emotional content for the spectator.
The most amazing aspect of these "works of art" is
that they could have been produced by a robot an elec¬
tronic computer capable of plotting equations in space.
26 Their beauty lies in their abstract mathematical order
liness, the very effect to which so many modern artists
strive in non-figurative works.
Obviously, this is not art for art's sake and the layman
is somewhat of an intruder in the Mathematics Hall. The
Palais de la Découverte is a science museum widely used
by students in Paris and its "sculpture" illustrates basic
mathematical formulae.
Take, for example, the case of a honeycomb structure
whose jutting prow might well be the façade of some
experimental housing project. The honeycomb is com¬
posed of curves constructed according to Gauss' law,
which lays down the so-called normal distribution
encountered in many problems of probability and statis¬
tics. A dancing spiral of wire is, in mathematical terms,
"a canal surface generated by moving a sphere of constant
CONT'D ON PAGE 28
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
ART IN MATHEMATICS (Cont'd;
Moving straight lines in space can generate curved surfaces of unusual beauty. One of these
surfaces is Plücker's conoid (above), named after one of the inventors of projective geometry. 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
ART IN
MATHEMATICS
(Cont'd^
Mathematical title of
this composition : "a
canal surface genera¬
ted by moving sphere
of constant radius
along circular helix".
28
radius along a circular helix"... which is one way of
saying "winding a length of wire around a circular rod."
An abstract basket ls Plücker's conoid, produced by
moving straight lines through space in differential geo¬
metry.
Models of these equations have been known to mathe¬
maticians for three centuries, but they usually remained
on their desks as esoteric objects reserved for the ini¬
tiated.
In 1937, the Palais de la Découverte introduced them to
the Paris public and this mathematical art show has been
a steady success ever since, both for budding mathemati¬
cians and visitors who happen to encounter a strange
world created by man's genius a world in which poetry
and harmony are produced by nothing more than equa¬
tions.
This sculpture-by-formulae is a classical example of
how science and aesthetics can meet to produce art. This
same meeting has been brought about more recently in
such fields as microphotography, crystallography, the
study of cosmic ray images on photographic plates, or
even in nuclear physics (the architectural symbol of the
Brussels World Fair was a gigantic atom).
And, paradoxically enough, while scientists are pro¬
ducing art, many present-day artists are turning to
science and technology in their efforts to reflect the
reality of this new and unexplored era in which we are
living. One can only conclude that the so-called divorce
between science and art between the humanities and
technology, if you prefer is not as irrevocable as it may
first appear.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Two mathematical models
shown here illustrate (left)
solids which permit an equi-
partition of space and (be¬
low) a third degree surface
on which 27 "real" straight
lines 'are possible.
Photos © Paul Almasy
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE, I
30
Scientists take advantage of every important
eclipse to make solar studies with specialized
instruments and thus discover more about the
nature and activity of our giant, life-giving sun.
Photo shows an eclipse being recorded at Kuwait.
George Rodger © Magnum Photos, Paris
_
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
w
MAN AND SOCIETY
By Sir James Gray, F. R. S.
Former President of the British Association
for the Advancement of Science
A British scientist
looks at Our world
through a biologist's
spectacles
i
One of the most important aspects of modern
science is its repercussion on International re¬
lationships, and when it begins to threaten the existence
of the whole human race, it really does seem to be going
just a step too far. There will always be danger and
appalling waste of human effort until individual nations
can be persuaded, or are forced, to think in terms of the
welfare of humanity as a whole. It is not our job to
suggest how this might best be achieved by moral or
political agreement. A scientific approach must be com¬
pletely dispassionate, but we shall not make much im¬
pression on public opinion so long as men's minds are
biased by fear and suspicion. Frightened or angry
politicians, like frightened or angry animals, cannot be
trusted to react wisely.
There is not the slightest doubt, however, that the
discoveries of physics have frightened mankind and that
there are far too many intelligent people looking askance
at Science and wondering where it is leading them. In
trying to link Science to the humanities our primary
objective should be to depict Man's position in the world
of Nature as a source not of fear or doubt, but of cou¬
rage and inspiration.
Our second main objective should be to demonstrate
the place of Science in a general philosophy of life. To
be of real value, such a philosophy must rest on
knowledge and experience which has already proved
acceptable over a very wide range of local environments
and national interests, and it must, at the same time,
be closely concerned with problems of everyday Ufe. In
these respects Science is unique.
Except when subjected to political restraint, scientists
of all nations have always co-operated in solving Nature's
jig-saws, and as Professor A.V. Hill has said, "The funda¬
mental principle of scientific work is the unbending
Integrity of thought, following the evidence of fact
wherever It may lead within the limits of experimental
error and honest mistake."
This attitude of mind is not peculiar to scientists; it
is common to all who have a respect for the truth.
But in the fields of law, language, history, literature and,
above all, politics, our general outlook and our individual
range of knowledge depend to a very dangerous extent
on local environment and national tradition. By freedom
from such limitations Science provides ground perhaps
the most solid ground for wider co-operation.
But the gap between a scientific and a humanitarian
outlook cannot be bridged by the statistical laws of
physics and chemistry ; we are forced to apply less precise,
but not necessarily less important principles from the
world of living organisms. The challenge is, therefore,
to the biological sciences, especially those which deal, at 31
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND SOCIETY (Cont'd;
THE PROPER STUDY
the borderline of sociology, with the behaviour of orga¬
nisms and their relationship to their environment. The
extent to which they can yield broad principles applicable
to Man may well decide how far Science can claim to be
of direct cultural significance.
Man's position in the world of Nature is brought most
sharply into focus by the concept of natural evolution.
Cosmic, biological and human evolution can be regarded
as phases in a continuous natural process and, from this
point of view, astronomy, geology, biology, archaeology
and history form a continuous spectrum of knowledge.
To pass through many millions of years from a primaeval
nebula to modern man without any sudden break in
continuity of thought gives a feeling of intellectual tidi¬
ness, but quite apart from this it enables us to visualize
Man against the background of his past and to regard
him as Nature's supreme masterpiece. At the same time,
he must not get too big for his biological boots or tend
to exaggerate the gap between himself and the rest of
the animal kingdom.
N o animal can manufacture aeroplanes, or
I Asdic ; but the prize for aeronautics must go
to the shearwater which navigated the Atlantic without
compass or chart, that for Asdic to the ears and vocal
cords of our nearer relatives, the bats. By surrounding
themselves with an electric field, some fish (e.g. Gym-
narchus) can, in total darkness, detect foreign objects in
the surrounding water with very remarkable precision.
The total weight of the mechanism involved including
the animal's brain amounts only to a few grammes;
a man-made instrument of comparable performance
would involve at least a ton of highly complex electronic
machinery. Again, there is no laboratory in the world
which can compete with the biochemical skill of even
the smallest living organism.
In fact, as delicate and precise pieces of machinery,
Man's Inventions so far compare very unfavourably with
those which have come into existence during the natural
course of biological evolution. On the other hand, we
may fairly claim that we have accomplished in a few
centuries things for which Nature required many millions
of years. Nevertheless, we need not be in the least
ashamed of the older members of our evolutionary
family; we have still a great deal to learn from them.
To visualize Man's position in the animal world, it
may be useful to define his main diagnostic characters.
He is a highly gregarious bipedal mammal with unspe-
cialized limbs but a very large brain. He is the only
animal which has developed the symbolisms of speech
and writing, and he may well be the only animal capable
of rational thought. He is, therefore, the only organism
which can hand on patterns of acquired learning from
one generation to another. To these advantages he owes
his dominant position in the world today.
They have enabled him to exploit his environment
and increase his numbers and his range of distribution
far more quickly and far more extensively than any
animal of comparable size. He has eliminated some of
his competitors and exploited others for his own use,
but the time has now come when different races of men
are competing with each other within the closed arena
of a limited environment, and it is not easy to see where
it will end.
There is nothing equivalent to this in the Inanimate
32 world; but, when a biologist looks at the general trend
of events, he is inclined to say, "Where have I seen
something like this before, what is it due to, and how
does it usually end?"
Nature has made, not one, but two great experiments in
the design of social animals. The first was carried out
in Mesozoic times when Man's mammalian ancestors
were beginning to emerge from reptiles. The results of
this experiment are represented today by the social
Insects notably the ants.
There are a very large number of different species of
ants, none of which interbreed; among them is found
a range of complexity of social behaviour which is not
only unique in the animal kingdom but which forms
a very remarkable parallel to different races of human
beings.
At one extreme are species forming small communities,
restricted to localized or specialized environments and
exhibiting relatively little subdivision of labour between
individuals.
At the other extreme are large and often aggressive
communities with marked differentiation of structure
between different grades of individuals; populations of
this type display high levels of co-operative effort involv¬
ing, in some cases, the rudiments of agriculture and
husbandry. In all cases, however, ant societies are orga¬
nized on a straightforward totalitarian basis, the
contribution made by each individual towards the welfare
of the community is determined from the time of birth;
each grade of individual is structurally adapted for pre¬
determined tasks.
How far ants can communicate with each other may
be doubtful, but it is tolerably certain that members of
the same community recognize each other by a charac¬
teristic smell, and as the brain of an ant is about the size
of the head of a pin, it is perhaps not surprising that
ants should attack or kill an individual from another
colony with a smell slightly different to their own. It
is much less easy to understand why a man, with a brain
of an entirely different order of complexity, should, at
times, react almost equally violently to skin pigments
different to his own.
But it is not only in respect to individual relationships
that the study of ants is relevant to Man. Ants are the
only organisms which apart from Man indulge in orga¬
nized warfare raiding the nests of other species and
incorporating captives into their own societies. But
perhaps the most striking facts relate to species which
have changed their habits and distribution within recent
times.
T;wo instances of territorial expansion are
known to have occurred in the last 150
years. Early in the nineteenth century an Eastern
species (Pheidola megacephala) , having spread rapidly
over North Africa and South Europe, managed to reach
the islands of Madeira and Bermuda; in both places it
exterminated the smaller native races.
Meanwhile, a similar policy had been carried out by
another species (Iridomyrmex humilis), from the Argen¬
tine, which, having landed at New Orleans, very rapidly
overran the southern United States; in due course, it
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
OF MANKIND IS MAN
too reached Bermuda, where it proceeded to eliminate the
earlier invader.
In the world of ants there is no place for small peaceful
communities unless they can isolate themselves effect¬
ively from larger and more powerful neighbours, nor does
there seem any lasting peace between large aggressive
communities. Solomon's advice has, I suspect, been
misinterpreted. It should read: "Consider the ants, and,
if you use your intelligence, you will see how not to deal
with International problems."
Having designed the ants, Nature waited for about
150 million years before embarking on her second or
human experiment. She waited, in fact, until it could
be carried out with a species in which an individual's
contribution to society was no longer based on inherited
structural characters but on the power of inter-commu-
nicatlon with other individuals; In other words, until
Man's brain had reached a level of development which
enabled him to control his environment, and to deal
rationally with the subdivision of labour between indi¬
viduals and with the distribution of natural resources
between different groups of individuals.
At the same time she arranged that such groups should
not be physiologically isolated from each other. Different
races of men can interbreed, or they can, if they wish,
come to mutual agreement about the distribution of world
resources. The first policy would seem to lead to a
world state with uniformity of social pattern and of
material interests; the second involves territorial limita¬
tions and economic agreements. Both, as we know only
too well, involve great practical difficulties. All the same,
men ought to be able to do something better than ants.
The second basis of comparison between Man and
animals concerns the factors which control his behaviour.
The past 50 years have produced a very great increase
in our knowledge of animal behaviour. For present
purposes, however, attention may be focused on two
problems: the extent to which animals can profit from
extraneous instruction, and the extent to which they
are able to learn for themselves.
ê
We can explore the first of these fields by
means of the conditioned-reflex technique,
whereby an animal learns to associate a specific visual, or
other sensory stimulus with forthcoming food or impend¬
ing danger. In order to establish this result it is necess¬
ary to conform with five basic principles all of which
have their counterpart in the training of human beings.
(1) The response expected from the animal must not
be unduly complex; the animal must be able to
reach the food or escape the danger by making
reasonably simple movements. In other words, the
problem must not be too difficult.
(2) The lesson must be presented to the animal under
conditions which ensure freedom from extraneous
disturbance. It will not learn If its attention ls
constantly diverted by other changes in its envi¬
ronment.
(3) The problem must be presented to the animal on
an adequate number of occasions; the more fre¬
quent the lesson, the fewer the mistakes become.
(4) There must be an "incentive" to learn a reward
for success or a punishment for failure. Further,
the "reward" must be related to the needs of the
animal.
(5) Finally, the experimenter must possess adequate
skill and patience. The ability of an animal to
learn depends to a very large extent on the per¬
sonality and enthusiasm of the teacher.
These five principles apply equally well to the education
of human beings if we make suitable allowances for
Increase in complexity of the lesson and for changes In
the nature of the incentive to learn. But we can go a
little further, for, as with men, different individuals of
the same animal species learn at very different rates.
Curiously enough, however, there does not seem to be any
clear correlation between an animal's ability to learn
and its position on the evolutionary tree.
It is possible to trace the structural evolution
of the human brain through each of the main
classes of vertebrate animals; the large paired hemi¬
spheres of our brain arose in the Devonian lung-fishes
and the cerebral cortex in the early Permian reptiles.
It would be very convenient if step by step with an
increase in size and complexity of the brain It were
possible to trace a corresponding Increase in complexity
of behaviour and in ability to learn. This is not the
case ; some fish without hemispheres or cortex can exhibit
behaviour patterns which seem just as complex as those
of reptiles or even of some mammals.
In due course this difficulty will be resolved, but for
the time being one can only say that there seems to
be one feature common to all species which learn easily,
namely, a vivacious but not unduly excitable tempera¬
ment rats, monkeys and children all have a natural
tendency to explore their environment and they are inter¬
ested in anything new or strange; they are all, perhaps,
potentially good scientific observers.
But the value of the instruction given to human beings
by a teacher is largely judged by the extent to which it
enables a pupil to make use of his acquired knowledge
and to go on to learn more by himself. Within the animal
world there is very little evidence to suggest that expe¬
rience acquired from one pattern of environment or from
one problem can be readily applied to others of a some¬
what different nature. An animal's own approach to a
problem, like that of a very young child, is very largely
one of random exploration; once it has found the solution
by chance, the number of ineffective responses on future
occasions becomes less and less until the correct response
is stabilized.
How far animals display evidence of the higher levels
of mental analysis associated with "intelligence" in
human beings is not too clear, for it is extremely difficult
to subject intelligence to an agreed standard of measure¬
ment. When judged by human standards the I.Q.s. of
all animals are, undoubtedly, very low; but, it may be that
we are not always setting them quite the right type of
examination.
Although it is difficult to correlate an increasing capa¬
city to learn with an increase in size and complexity of
the brain throughout the main classes of vertebrates, it
seems clear that there is a substantial increase in 33
CONT'D ON PAGE 36
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
ARE MEN NO BETTER
THAN ANTS?
r.
^ w 'ta '
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
WAR IN THE ANT WORLD. In the world of ants there is no place
for small peaceful communities unless they can isolate themselves from
larger and more powerful neighbours, nor does there seem any
lasting peace between large aggressive communities. Warfare in the
world of ants is graphically shown in these photos taken from a new
Walt Disney film, "Secrets of Life." Left, a black ant overcomes an
opposing red ant by crushing him against the roof of his underground
tunnel. Above, pitched battle between red and black ants. The fight
forsurvival in Nature's teeming world of insects becomes open warfare,
even between families of the same species, and the battles that rage
between the red ants and black ants are among the deadliest. Below,
the headhuntera red ant returning with four heads, his own and
those of three rival black ants who lost theirs in battle.
Photos taken from " Secrets of Life " ©Walt Disney
y
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND SOCIETY (Cont'd;
MAN VIEWED THROUGH
BIOLOGICAL SPECTACLES
learning ability as soon as an animal's brain reaches a
level of structural complexity comparable with that of
man.
The young chimpanzee, like a human baby, is typicaUy
a friendly, playful creature dependent on and with an
affection for its mother. But as it grows up, it begins to
show marked signs of individuality; some become morose,
unfriendly and vicious, others retain a friendly dis¬
position towards their neighbours and a co-operative atti¬
tude towards human teachers.
The abiUty to respond to training shown by the latter
type of Individual is, of course, very remarkable, but when
left to itself a chimpanzee seems to rely on an initial
process of trial and error. Like many other mammals, it
can give audible and visible signs of fear, anger or pain ;
but there is no evidence that a chimpanzee can make au¬
dible or visible signs which other individuals associate
with specific material objects; the mental development of
the adult ape seems roughly equivalent to that of a
human baby before the latter has learnt to speak.
I
36
JN short, nothing can possibly disguise the
enormous difference between an adult ape
and an adult man in ability to learn and to control their
environments, but it might be argued that a relative test
of the brains of the ape and of Man as computing instru¬
ments should be conducted on the basis that neither
pupil nor teacher should be allowed to speak, read or
write: the gap between animals and men might narrow
very appreciably.
The third and perhaps most important biological aspect
of Man's behaviour concerns the gregarious habit. Here
again the distribution among vertebrate animals is
curiously unrelated to their evolutionary history: it is
weU marked in certain species of fish, birds and mammals
but absent in others. In some cases the existence of a
herd or flock is clearly of survival value; a pack of wolves
has a wider choice of food than an individual operating
by itself.
But it is not always clear why one species should be
more gregarious than another to which it is closely
related. In the present state of knowledge it may be
safer to say that some animals are restless or uneasy
unless in close proximity to individuals of the same
species that they have, in fact, a deep-rooted antipathy
to isolation or loneliness. In any event the resultant
grouping establishes the herd as a unit which responds as
a whole to an external stimulus applied to one or a few
individuals.
The response is most clearly marked when the stimulus
evokes an emotional reaction of fear or anger in the
individuals directly concerned, and one of the most dis¬
tinctive features of herd behaviour is the speed at which
these emotions spread throughout the community. If
certain individuals are more highly susceptible than others
to external stimuli the response of the group is deter¬
mined by the most timorous or the most belUgerent mem¬
bers of the community.
The majority of the herd subjugate their own individual
behaviour to that of a few, and in the long run the in¬
dividual benefits by greater security from predators or
greater certainty of obtaining food. If an individual is
unduly insensitive to emotional stimulation by its neigh¬
bours, it is likely to be eliminated by natural selection the
sheep that walks by itself gets eaten and the solitary
wolf may starve.
These principles were applied to the analysis of human
behaviour by Wilfred Trotter (described in his book, "The
Herd Instinct in Peace and War"). In order to avoid phy¬
sical or mental isolation men are prepared to subjugate
their own immediate needs or predilections to those of
society as a whole. Antisocial activity is kept in check by
fear of inteUectual or physical isolation; feelings of in¬
creased security and greater freedom from personal doubts
and fears are set off against loss of individual freedom of
action.
How far psychologists have developed or rejected
Trotter's suggestions I do not know, but there can be
little doubt that they opened up a useful biological
approach to sociology by suggesting that our instinctive
reaction to something new or strange is, as in animals, to
conform with our neighbours, and that, at moments of
crisis, it is better to follow a leader than rely on personal
judgments. These and allied problems belong to the
domain of psychology. All I wish to stress is that the
phenomena of mass psychology in Man, like other aspects
of his behaviour, have their roots far down in his evolu¬
tionary history.
Perhaps the most striking difference between the social
habits of Man and those of animals is the existence of a
hierarchy or grading within human society. Only in a
very few cases does this appear to exist within the animal
kingdom. The nearest approach seems to occur in birds;
a flock of jackdaws feeding in a restricted area resolves
itself into a well-marked order of feeding priority.
Konrad Lorentz has recently reported that If a high-
ranking male decides to mate with a low-ranking female,
the latter rises In social status and feeds with her
husband; all this sounds reasonably familiar to human
ears.
This is perhaps as far as a zoologist ought to go in
trying to view mankind through biological spectacles. But
one does not need to be a professional biologist to appre¬
ciate that the rates of change in the pattern of human
behaviour and in the nature of our environment have,
during the past five thousand years, been incomparably
greater than those of any other organism at any period
of its history; our clothes, houses, habits and social orga¬
nization change with successive generations.
The fact is that if one were forced to choose
the organism which best displays the pheno¬
menon of persistent evolutionary change one would
undoubtedly choose Man.
In suggesting further points at which biological
principles seem to be applicable to the evolution of
human society, a zoologist can only look towards
Archaelogy and Anthropology and hope that his spec¬
tacles are not completely out of focus. In its very
early stages human society must have been organized
into quite small units, each dependent on the natural
resources of a small circumscribed environment.
The discovery of fire and development of agriculture
must have increased the range of the environment and
the optimum size of the population required for its exploi¬
tation, and the stability of the group would become more
and more dependent on the maintenance of an effective
subdivision of labour; but the larger the population and
the greater the degree of specialization, the greater the
limitations imposed on individual freedom of action.
A new and very important social factor seems to have
come into action when natural phenomena became linked
with supernatural concepts fear of isolation or reprisals
from fellow-men being reinforced by fear of a super¬
human agency and a sense of greater security inspired
by reliance on supernatural support. Such beliefs had
no material basis but they would be the cement which
held society together and, as such, be of immense survival
CONT'D ON PAGE 38
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Although the difference in ability to learn between man and
ape is enormous, scientists are now not too sure towhat point
animals can actually carry put high-level mental analyses asso¬
ciated with "intelligence." In I.Q. tests animals usually rate
very low, but many scientists believe that present methods of
testing may be wrong. Photo shows research worker
studying the reactions of a chimpanzee to different situations.
Unesco-Marc Riboud
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
_
1 9 t il
*~\ rj <> '.:#-£
.£ £.
The drive ¡n ail modem countries to develop trade and a higher standard
of living for all depends largely on the ability to make and exploit new
scientific discoveries. In many countries a large percentage of higher
educational resources Is now being used to train professional scientists
and highly skilled technicians. Photos show, from left to right,
students at Moscow University listening to a lecture on organic chemistry.
HUMANITIES AS A COMPLEMENT TO SCIENCE
value. But it is difficult to avoid the conclusion that
such beliefs, like scientific theories, must undergo change
as Man's knowledge increases and his environment alters.
It is easy to say that Science should be welded to the
humanities, but much less easy to suggest how this should
be done. Each of us has a different view according to
our particular Interests. I confess that my own approach
is based on personal experience.
About fifty years ago I chose to specialize in biology,
and from time to time I have been asked "If you had
known that you would spend a good deal of your later
life studying the movements of animals, what subjects
apart from biology would you have read at school and at
the university?" The answer is simple: Apart from
modern languages, I would have read physics, chemistry,
mathematics and mechanical engineering.
The moral is that no young scientist should be allowed
to forget that new discoveries tend to arise from the
borderland between different subjects where the disci¬
pline of one is applied to another. Had I appreciated this
I would have been a much better biologist, but whether
I would have been a better human being is another
matter.
If I am asked the 64 thousand dollar question, "Had
you known that you would have had to adjust yourself
to a rapidly changing and somewhat uneasy world, what
additional training would you like to have had?", I think
my answer would be that I would like to have been trained
to think dispassionately about social and political affairs
in the light of experience drawn from the past, and to
have been taught to appreciate beautiful things.
But could I have acquired this knowledge whilst train¬
ing as a scientist? Perhaps not, but I still think that I
could have been shown a wider picture. Having been
taught to visualize the spectrum in terms of the wave-
38 lengths of light, could not I have been encouraged to
learn a little about colour as a source of aesthetic plea¬
sure? Why learn about the properties of iron and carbon
without reference to the Industrial Revolution? I might
even have developed a taste for the classics if I had
known that Aristotle had written a very good textbook
of zoology.
Perhaps I expected too much in hoping to appreciate
an artist's view of Nature from the standpoint of a scien¬
tist. But I am not completely convinced. A scientist's
attitude towards his observations does not seem to me
to be so very different from that of a poet towards his
words or a painter towards his colours; isolated observa¬
tions have no more value than single words; it is only
when they fit into a satisfying pattern that the scientist
feels he has achieved his end.
If this argument is unconvincing, and if it still seems
impossible to combine the vision of the artist with the
outlook of a scientist, I can only suggest that Leonardo
da Vinci and Sir Christopher Wren seem to have had
pretty good shots at it.. It would be very interesting to
know the sort of training they had in early life.
But a plea for a wider outlook in the teaching of
Science ls nothing new. It was urged again and again in
Great Britain by Sir Richard Gregory. In 1933 the
declared aim of the London County Council was that they
"wished their pupils to obtain a broad view of nature,
to study mankind and his environment from various
standpoints, more particularly from the point of view
of both the biological and physical Sciences."
In 1946 the Advisory Council for Secondary Education
in Scotland was even more explicit: "The study of man
in his world, like the study of science, is a unity which
should not be broken by any sharp division into 'sub¬
jects'... the theme must be one."
In 1958 a committee of the Science Masters Association
urged that "The schools have the duty of presenting
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
N
: -*
\ 1
/ 7
^&1
/
Student engineers using electrical equipment at the University of
Grenoble, France, and a Japanese chemistry student concentrating on a
laboratory experiment at Kelo University. How to reconcile specialist
training with a good all-round education the kind that moulds opinions
and equips to the greatest advantage the average boy and girl for
later life is one of today's problems discussed by Sir James Gray.
Science as part of our common cultural and humanistic
heritage; it should be taught In harmony with and not
in opposition to the various Arts subjects..." It seems
fair to say that this is a goal towards which we would
all wish to strive; but when we try to approach it the
road proves extremely hard, and most of us, In practice,
fall by the wayside.
We cannot shut our eyes to the fact that our national
economy depends on our ability to make and exploit new
scientific discoveries. If we wish to maintain or extend
our standards of material comfort we must have more
professional scientists and highly trained technicians
and we must be prepared to devote an adequate fraction
of our educational effort to get them.
But highly trained specialists form only a very small
proportion of the population, and we may be paying for
them in very hard currency if we have to deny to a very
much larger fraction of the community a reasonable
chance of "seeing life steadily and as a whole." A demo¬
cracy has to decide how much of its total educational
effort should be devoted to an ever-increasing standard
of living and how much to raising the intellectual
standards whereby the majority of the population forms
its judgments on things which involve personal prejudice
or political propaganda.
It is not easy to assess the factors which mould public
opinion, but a recent enquiry indicates relatively clearly
that the attitude of mind of an individual towards a
changing environment is directly related to the nature
and extent of his full-time education and that it is this
training which largely determines, in later life, his res¬
ponse to other potential sources of education such as
libraries and broadcasts.
If we wish to awaken a widespread interest in Science,
or still more, wish to contribute toward the formation of
an enlightened public opinion, we must sow our seeds in
the schools and in organized centres of adult education.
But the key to the main problem lies In the schools,
and the responsibility resting on schoolteachers can
hardly be exaggerated. Too many are asked to do two
jobs at once to provide a training for potential specia
lists and at the same time give a training which will best
equip the average boy or girl for later Ufe.
If we are to pay more than lip-service to the belief
that a good all-round education is the best means of rais¬
ing the intellectual level of the community, we must
recognize that our most urgent need is for good general
practitioners in the art of education. Really inspired
teachers working with adequate but simple equipment
will achieve more for general education than specialists
in highly equipped laboratories.
But the scales have been heavily weighted in favour of
specialization. Almost exclusively, our universities are
producing specialists. Some of these return to the schools
where they in turn teach on a specialized front. So the
spiral of specialization has gone on. It is only natural
that able teachers get an intellectual stimulus by prepar¬
ing boys and girls for scholarship examinations and so
providing recruits for fields of research in which they
themselves are interested; but it is by no means clear
that their work is necessarily more important, or more
difficult, than that of those whose primary object is to
persuade people that they cannot live by bread alone.
Much can be done by relatively formal teaching, but if
I may judge from personal experience more depends on
the extent to which people are given the time and oppor¬
tunity to educate themselves by contact with men and
women of entirely different interests and outlook.
But when all is said and done, Science can only make
its full contribution to the welfare of mankind if it is
used as a means of encouraging a dispassionate but opti¬
mistic attitude towards all aspects of human affairs. To
move from national traditions and aspirations to others
based on international welfare may prove less painful if
we are prepared to look on Man and all his problems as
a phase in the evolution of the universe and if we have
the courage to believe and to teach that he can, by means
of his intellect, control and direct his own evolution and
destiny.
This text is an abridgement of an address, "The Proper
Study of Mankind is Man", delivered in Sept. 1959 before
the British Assoc, for the Advancement of Science. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
WORLD T
SCIENTIFIC
By Daniel Behrman
Science affects both directly and
indirectly almost every human
being. So vast is the field, and so
rapid the growth of research in
the past few decades, that it has
been all but impossible to chart
its progress. Now, a comprehen¬
sive survey of world scientific
trends and technological research
is being published by UNESCO.
Prepared by Professor Pierre
Auger, it marks a milestone in the
history of international science and
its uses for peaceful purposes.
The Herculean task of taking a global look at
the world of science, detecting the principal
lines along which research ls being undertaken in fields
running from cancer to fluid mechanics and then chart¬
ing a future course of International action has just been
accomplished.
All this is under one cover and on 250 pages in "Current
Trends in Scientific Research" which has just been
brought off the press by u.n. and Unesco. It is the work
of a leading French physicist and former head of
Unesco's Department of Natural Sciences, Professor
Pierre Auger, who has carried out this survey for the
United Nations, following a resolution passed by the
U.N. General Assembly in November, 1958.
Some idea of its scope can be obtained from the
massive support which Professor Auger was able to enlist
in collecting his data. Among contributors are numbered
no less than twenty-nine intergovernmental orga¬
nizations, sixty-six international non-governmental orga¬
nizations, national research organizations from forty-
two countries and, last but certainly not least in impor¬
tance, 255 scientific experts from the world over.
But a much more vivid idea of what this survey was
intended to encompass can be found in Professor Auger's
own introduction to his book. It is quite simple: of all
CONT'D ON PAGE 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
WORLD SCIENCE SURVEYED (Cont'd)
Photos © Paul Almasy
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Paul Almasy
The Institute of Applied Science in Mexico City develops and conducts
research in meteorology, hydrology and related sciences in order to
promote effective use of water and other natural resources. Modern
laboratories and classrooms were made available by the University
of Mexico in 1956, and Unesco has actively participated in the
programme by providing experts, equipment and fellowships for
Mexican scientists. Above, a scientist and his assistant take a sample
of air near a factory chimney for chemical analysis. Left, one of the
Institute's scientists adjusts an actinometer, a sensitive instrument
for measuring the intensity of sunlight in different parts of the
spectrum. Below, a solar radiation observatory on the roof of the
Institute. The instrument in the foreground records the brightness
of the sky. The circular metal band shades receiver from sunlight.
RECOMMENDATIONS FOR
INTERNATIONAL ACTION
the scientists and research workers since the beginning
of time, 90 per cent are alive and working today! In our
world of rapid change, Professor Auger notes, scientific
activity is increasing at the rate of ten per cent a year
which means that it more than doubles every decade.
Merely keeping abreast of this activity has become an
impossible task: while there were only 1,000 scientific
journals in 1850, .there are nearly 100,000 today.
"Current Trends in Scientific Research" is therefore
neither a panorama nor an encyclopaedia. It probably
could be compared to- a moving picture, edited from miles
of film (in this case, mountains of data) to bring out the
most important of all the events taking place before the
camera's eye. Professor Auger has used another meta¬
phor: when a ship gives its position, it reports its latitude
and longitude but always adds its direction and speed.
The position of modern research is not a fixed one.
In his recommendations for international action, Pro¬
fessor Auger has not necessarily selected the most im¬
portant realms of scientific research but specific tasks
which are beyond the reach of national or private efforts.
Here, too, are to be found a number of fields which tend
to be overlooked because they do not promise immediate
returns in terms of national policy or economic benefits
although their long-term promise is immense.
T;hese are some of the highlights of his sug¬
gestions (unfortunately, space does not allow
us even to summarize all of them) :
An International scientific conference to standardize
measurements and remedy a "chaotic state of affairs".
An international system to enable countries to com¬
municate their meteorological and seismological findings
to electronic computer centres for processing. Professor
Auger points out that such findings must be processed
immediately if. they are to be used by scientists seeking
more knowledge of our environment.
M More joint centres of high energy physics, such as
the European Centre for Nuclear Research (CERN) ori¬
ginally inspired by Unesco, which is now operating the
world's most powerful particle accelerator.
An Information service on current research work to
avoid waste and duplication incurred aU too often when
institutes or laboratories in different countries spend
years working on similar projects.
An international study of the long-term effects of
small doses of radiation.
An international conference on artifical seismic
shocks (earthquakes) induced by explosions. Interpreta¬
tion of the results of such explosions is not yet clear.
The establishment of a major astronomical observatory
in the middle latitudes of the Southern Hemisphere.
A scientific conference on cloud physics to assess the
effectiveness of various methods now used to create "arti¬
ficial rainfall".
U A study of living conditions of certain populations not
"enjoying" modern civilization to learn why the incidence
of cancer varies from one country to another. This is
urgent because traditional ways of life are dying out
faster than they can be studied.
International measures for protection against pollu¬
tion when it spreads beyond borders, as in the case of
nuclear fall-out or river pollution.
43
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
WORLD SCIENCE SURVEYED (Cont'd)
MOVEMENT TOWARD UNITY IN SCIENCE
44
B Improvement of traditional methods of fertilization
and soil improvement by placing them on a scientific
basis and, at the same time, international research to
increase productivity of plants.
An international co-ordination of research aimed at
developing inexpensive nuclear fuels.
a An international conference on problems of energy
storage, especially those arising in intermittent sources
of energy such as wind or sun. In addition, international
support is needed for development of the direct produc¬
tion of electricity through the light or the heat of the
sun (through photoelectric or thermoelectric cells instead
of the inefficient cycle of the steam engine).
< A series of steps to assist new countries to formulate
scientific policy and to train scientists, technicians and
engineers.
Despite this arbitrary summary of Professor Auger's
recommendations, it should not be assumed that he pro¬
duced his survey by placing scientific discipUnes in arbi¬
trary pigeonholes. On the contrary, he brings out very
clearly that the trend of the past years toward specializa¬
tion is now being accompanied by a parallel movement
toward unity in science. The old barriers are falling with
the growth of new sciences bearing such names as astro¬
physics, mathematical chemistry or physico-chemical
biology. At the same time, the role of mathematics itself
has broadened to the point where it pervades all sciences,
substituting precision and prediction for groping.
Another barrier is also crumbling: the one between
applied and fundamental science. While Professor Auger
notes that applied research has grown to the point where
there is a danger at times that it might squeeze out
disinterested research which would be as absurd as killing
the goose that lays the golden eggs there is now a for¬
tunate tendency toward blending of the two.
The old distinction, therefore, does not stand up in the
modern world. Professor Auger replaces it by a new clas¬
sification of scientific research into four types :
Free fundamental research or pure research; oriented
fundamental research; applied research and then the
final stage of development work to secure economic or
social benefits. All are intimately linked.
On the basis of the survey, Professor Auger has
brought out an even dozen main trends in
world scientific research. He begins with the extension
of physical frontiers, pointing out that, today, "the
scientist can produce on the spot, in his laboratories,
conditions which occur only in inaccessible regions such
as the centre of the stars or the depths of the earth, or
which perhaps do not exist anywhere in the universe".
Chemical frontiers, too, are being extended in the
development of hitherto impossible purity of certain
substances. At the same time, nuclear reactions have
made it possible to extend the periodic table beyond 100
elements.
In both physics and chemistry progress is directly relat¬
ed to constant improvement in the accuracy of measure¬
ments which, Prof. Auger points out, automatically opens
the way to new discoveries.
The third main trend is automation, a science in its
own right. Not only is it revolutionizing industrial pro¬
duction, but it is taking the human error out of measure¬
ments.
The whole fascinating process of research on the
earth's crust, the ocean depths, the polar regions and the
vastness of interplanetary space forms a trend which Prof.
Auger succinctly sums up in one word exploration.
"Man against nature" is a fifth trend, englobing all of
our efforts not only to explore nature but to force it
into a mould suiting our purposes. This trend, Prof. Au¬
ger remarks, has already added years to the human life
span.
The study of natural equilibria and cycles is a trend
of increasing importance at a time when man is modi¬
fying these cycles by transforming water conditions, using
up coal and oil reserves deposited over eons and stripping
the earth of its forests. This research is essential to eco¬
nomic planning today.
Dwindling of natural resources has intensified a scien¬
tific trend aimed at increasing our supply of energy. This
has already led to nuclear fission energy and to research
on fusion or thermo-nuclear energy. Side by side with
this search for new sources of energy is to be found
revived interest in old ones: the sun, the wind, the tides
and waterfalls.
The problem of energy, Prof. Auger remarks,
was mastered by the nineteenth century. It
is the twentieth century that is mastering, in another
major trend, the analysis of the structure of matter. We
can now "see" the structure of solids, liquids, living cells
or molecules through new techniques of analysis.
While science studies existing structures, it is also
devising new ones. This synthesis of complex chemical
systems is giving us substances such as plastics which imi¬
tate or improve the properties of natural structures.
Mathematical research is closely tied to this trend.
Transport is another main field and Prof. Auger divides
current scientific research here into two aspects: electri¬
cal transport and material transport. Considerable work
is being done to cut losses in. the tranmission of electri¬
city while there is a trend to simplify the movement of
materials through the use of giant tankers or huge
pipelines.
Communications, termed by Prof. Auger as "the trans¬
port of complex patterns", are also leading scientists to
seek ways of reducing losses in transmission. At the same
time, methods must be found to move an increasing
number of "messages" of all kinds over a limited spectrum
of usable waves.
Finally, Prof. Auger singles out the interaction between
the various sciences themselves as his twelfth main trend
in the world of science, with mathematics in a royal role.
"Almost as if they could foresee the needs that would
gradually come to be felt by physicists, chemists and bio¬
logists," he remarks, "the mathematicians have almost
always evolved in advance the purely logical theories
containing the required tools of thought."
In the eyes of Professor Auger, these present trends in
science are not creating a science-fiction world dwarfing
man into insignificance. On the contrary, he stresses that
human biology is to be found at all levels of pure and
appUed research today. Automation has not replaced the
observer and the demands of the human mind are the
very source of fundamental discoveries in science.
The interaction of all sciences and this emphasis on
man are two overall movements which, the author of the
report concludes, "are jointly making a powerful contri¬
bution to the unification of scientific thought".
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Industrial research plays an ever growing role in the application of
scientific knowledge to man's needs. Above, an Industrial hygiene spe¬
cialist at the University of Rochester In the State of New York, U.S.A.,
studies harmful air-borne particles from certain factories and prepares
to count the concentration of dust particles by plating them with
metallic selenium. Such research also includes testing the toxicity of
dusts on animals. Below, this maze of tubing Is part of the instrumen¬
tation apparatus atop the head of a nuclear reactor in an American
atomic-electric generating plant. The tubing feeds information from
the reactor to the control room where readings are automatically
recorded on charts and gauges. Scientific research plays a direct part
in the development of nuclear power as in the autonation of industry.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
KALINGA PRIZE
A SCIENCE
REPORTER
SPEAKS OF
'BABELOLOGY'
46
by Ritchie Caflder
On June 20 during an impressive ceremony
in Unesco House, Paris, Ritchie Calder, the
British science writer, became the ninth winner
of the annual international Kalinga Prize for
the Popularization of Science. At this cere¬
mony, Ritchie Calder was told by Mr René
Maheu, Acting Director-General of Unesco:
"You . have the gift of describing the most
intricate scientific problems in a way that
appeals both to the reason and feelings of the
public and arouses curiosity and surprise."
Some of Ritchie Calder's books, said Mr Maheu,
had been translated into 12 languages and dealt
with every aspect of scientific research from
tropical medicine to the hydrology of arid zones
and the biology of the Far North. His reports
had appeared in over 1,000 newspapers in
some 40 countries. The Kalinga Prize, donated
by Mr B. Patnaik, of the Orissa Legislative
Assembly, India, offers, recognition to
leading interpreters of science whose works
have shed light on the social implications of
scientific progress. The winner is chosen by an
international jury of scientists and editors of
popular science journals appointed by Unesco.
Previous winners include: Louis de Broglie:
(France), Julian Huxley (United Kingdom),
Waldemar Kaemppfert (United States), Au¬
gusto Pi-Suner (Venezuela), George Gamow
(United States), Bertrand Russell (United King¬
dom), Karl von Frisch (Germany and Austria)
and Jean Rostand (France). Traveller, writer,
journalist, film-maker and lecturer, Ritchie
Calder was science editor of the "Hews Chro¬
nicle" in London, 1945 to 1956, and of "The New
Statesman and Nation" from 1945 to 1958.
Aged 54, he is now Professor of International
Relations at Edinburgh University. His books
on scientific subjects include "Men Against
the Desert", "Men Against the Jungle",
"Science Makes Sense" and "Profile of
Science". His latest work, "The Inheritors",
tells the story of man and the world he made.
Many of his articles have appeared in The
Unesco Courier. On these pages, we publish
salient passages from Ritchie Calder's address
at the Kalinga Prize ceremony.
I regard myself as a reporter, re¬
cently translated to academic life
but claiming none of the academic distinction of the
eminent scientists whose names emblazon the roU of the
KaUnga Prizewinners. Rather do I count myself in the
succession of my late friend Waldemar Kaemppfert, the
third (recipient of the award. As science-editor of the
New York Times, he was the doyen of our craft, who
set the standards of integrity and lucidity which I have
tried to follow and who faithfuUy respected the interna¬
tional character of science, and who beUeved as I do that
the mere explanation of science is not enough; its
meaning has to be translated into the Uves of ordinary
people.
I have long since given up apologizing for the fact I had
no formal scientific education or training. If someone
with- an education as limited as my own could, in time,
understand the mysteries of science, so with patience and
the use of the cûmmon-tongue, laymen the world all over
can have the veils of science lifted. There have to be in¬
terpreters. They may be academic scientists, of whom
notable examples are to be found among the Kalinga
Prizewinners; or they may be scientists who, with a fuU
training and with degrees, turn to professional science-
writing as a career; or they may be trained journalists,
who, like myself, discover an interest in science, and learn
to explain it to that much-maUgned, misunderstood,
anonymous creature, "The Average Reader."
But exposition is not confined to the written word;
there ls the spoken word, of the platform and the radio;
and there ls the power of the visual, of the film and of
television, with the capacity to share the experience of
the scientists with the millions of viewers, to bring to
them some of that excitement and the awe which comes
to the experimenter in the laboratory or in Space
when the unknown becomes visible under the microscope
or on an oscillograph. We are only at the beginning of
this shared adventure which is science-exposition.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
It needs patience patience on the part of the scientist
who has to explain; patience on the part of the expositor
who has to win and pass on that explanation; and
patience on the part of the reader or the viewer who has
to be wooed into an understanding of the discoveries and
developments which are dominating and revolutionizing
his life and the society in which he lives.
The tools of my trade as a science-writer have been
apart from a typewriter three questions: "What are
you doing?" "How are you doing it?" and "Why are
you doing It?" With patience on the part of the
scientist and patience on the part of the inquisitor, there
are few things in science, however apparently abstruse or
novel or difficult, which cannot be explained in compre¬
hensible terms.
One of the major difficulties is the terminology the
jargon of science. The scientists in the various branches
and discipUnes of science have invented their own
language of convenience. Where once the terms were
descriptive they are now cryptic sometimes one feels that
Uke the code names for military operations, they have been
deliberately invented to mislead and, like the sign lan¬
guage of the mediaeval crafts, designed to preserve the
inner mysteries for the few.
Sometimes Uke "barn" in nuclear physics or "hard¬
ware" in the jargon of the electronic engineer they are
survivals of common-room jokes. Sometimes they are
borrowed, like the confiscation of the word "plasma" by
the physicist from the biologist. What the scientist, who
in the restricted company of his colleagues uses them as
commonplace terms, does not always realize is that such
words are like index cards; to him they convey a whole
filing cabinet full of meaning but he- forgets that others
do not have access to that filing cabinet.
This is, alas, inevitable. With the proliferation of
science, the scientist is entitled to his "language of
convenience" but he must, when necessary, define those
terms. A century ago, any man of science was intelligible
to any educated man that educated men were an élite
is another matter; terms had a common-root etymological
meaning and in that sense were descriptive. Today, I
repeat, they are cryptic.
I have sometimes described myself as a "babelologist,"
a student of that babel of tongues which is science. I also
boast that I am an expert on experts one who knows
to whom to turn for the information one has not got. In
that I personify the science-reporter, who is the trustee,
for the common man for whom he seeks enlightenment in
the common tongue: who never relies on what he knows
but turns to the expert sources for current guidance; and
who does not make the mistake which many academics
do of confusing ignorance with lack of intelligence.
I have, after thirty years of trying to explain
science, a reinforced confldence'ih the capacity
of ordinary people to grasp what is made inteUigible
provided that their interest has been enUsted and their
imaginations iUumined. But that after all is surely the
essence of all good teaching.
May I be more profound? The crisis of our times is the
break-down of communications not just in the sense
of political barriers, but in this all important area of
science. Our lives, our hopes, and our survival depend
upon the uses which are made of science. To progress,
we have to use scientific knowledge and discovery to its
utmost advantage. Science, in the advanced countries,
is developing so fast that it is almost impossible to keep
pace with the knowledge and the gadgets which are
aggregating. I believe that some 3,000,000 original scien¬
tific papers a year are published. No one can compass so
much information.
The various branches of science are out of step. Cults
of science are developed and encouraged by dispropor¬
tionate budgets. Large areas of science are enclosed in
the compounds of military security; others are segregated
merely by over-specialization; the fences are up. One
set of scientists does not know what another set is doing,
and yet there may be an important affinity of material
value to mankind.
There are too few communicators within science and the
bridges are -broken between the humanities and science.
Those who have to make the social judgments about
science have usuaUy no scientific training worse, their
own education makes them feel that anything which
involves such intensive training is beyond their compre¬
hension and that they must "rely on the expert". But
there is Uttle in the training of the scientist, preoccupied
with all that has to be learned in his own subject, which
gives him the capacity for social judgments.
We are in danger of being subjected to the tyranny of
the experts faceless men at the elbows of the uninstruct-
ed. They are not tyrants by disposition but by our default.
How are we to teach people enough about science to
allow them to make judgments, to decide priorities,
instead of encouraging cults by gusts of emotion, and
to see that, with the inalienable rights of curiosity and
the quest for knowledge unimpaired, science, with all
its potential for good or evil, is directed to the advantage
of mankind?
H ow much more resources and attention should
we be giving to the problems of this planet on
which 4,000,000,000 people wUl have to contrive to live
20 years from now? Is space adventure more important
than the food and population problem, for instance?
This is not a question of one or the other but of how
much? And how, with aU the spectacular advances of
today, can we close the widening gap between the pros¬
perity of the scientifically advanced countries and the
impoverished ones?
These are social judgments fraught with stupendous
consequences, and they must be based on the understand¬
ing of science and what it can make available.
Without arrogating to the science-writer all the wisdom
of the world, it is true that he has the opportunity for
better understanding. He is a "synoptic scientist"; he
travels across the advancing fronts of all branches of
science and can see, at first hand and in survey, what
preoccupied scientists cannot see for themselves and
what men of affairs can never see panoramically. His
job is to pass that knowledge on either along the line of
science or to the pubUc. He is, by the accident of his
trade, as a collector and disseminator, the prototype of
what should exist in academic and public life, the
communicator of information on which judgments can be
made.
In his own working Ufe, his function is to convey to the
mass of the people the facts about science but also, I
suggest, to convey an interpretation of the social
implications of new developments. I know that many of
my colleagues think that they should confine themselves
to description and explanation and leave the value
judgments to others. I disagree profoundly. Our access
to information, our point of vantage on the scientific
scene gives us responsibilities which, in the present
situation, we must not shirk.
I am still by instinct and by training a reporter. My
work as a journalist opened the once-closed doors 'of
science, but the insight and experience which I gained
opened for me doors on to a wider world. For the past
15 years, I have had the privilege and opportunity of
traveUing round the world, mainly for the United Nations
and its agencies, to see how science and technology can
help the less-developed countries to achieve material well-
being for their people.
That combined experience is what I am now taking
into university life as Professor of International Relations
at Edinburgh. The only "international relations" I am
qualified to teach is how by the common understanding
of science, and by the proper application of that
knowledge to the common needs of mankind, we may
achieve a greater common understanding between
peoples. In that purpose, I am confirmed by the Kalinga
Prize, awarded to me because that is what its founder
hoped to encourage. 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
IN A HONG KONG MEDICINE SHOP
A TOOTH WAS THE CLUE
by Prof. G.H.R. von Kdnigstvald
A leading anthropologist and paleontologist, Professor von
Khas done extensive field research in Indonesia and
South China, where he made important finds concerning Peking
Man and the Pithecanthropus-Group in general. He has occupied
the chair of anthropology at Utrecht University since 1948.
J UST over a century ago, in 1856, a skull was
brought to light in the Neanderthal, near Dus¬
seldorf, Germany. It was unmistakably a human skull,
but so different from that of modern man that most
scientists had no hesitation in identifying it as belonging
to a type of human being who no longer exists today.
The discovery of the Neanderthal Man was a red-letter
day in the history of man's efforts to delve into his past
and to record everything connected with it. Since then
the search has gone on everywhere, and many remarkable
discoveries of science stand out as landmarks in the
history of mankind over the past 100,000 years.
But the story of what happened to man before this time
is less weU known. The oldest undoubtedly human
remains are only about 800,000 years old and discoveries
dating back to earUer periods are of doubtful value.
Even so, scientists have unearthed at least enough ma¬
terial to be able to reconstruct about one milUon years of
human history. This seems like a staggering length of
time until we remember that the evolution of horses can
be traced back some fifty miUion years and that of
elephants for over forty milUon.
Our own history, too, goes back a very long way but
much of the evidence we would need to reconstruct It
still eludes us for various reasons. For one thing most
of the remains discovered are very incomplete: single
teeth and a few jawbones and skulls, most of which are
fragmentary. Not one complete skeleton of the older
types is known.
Another reason is that discoveries have been
made in all parts of the Old World, from
England to South Africa and from Spain to Northern
China. Thus this branch of scientific research has
become, in the fullest sense, an international one. Only
by pooling aU discoveries can we hope to turn a spotlight
on our distant past; the true and complete solution to
this great enigma can certainly not be reached from
evidence collected within the frontiers of one single
country.
There is a third factor which greatly complicates the
work: the problem of determining the age of the sites
in which finds are made and the need to make a com¬
parison of sites which are vast distances apart. We there¬
fore make studies of extinct mammals discovered in asso¬
ciation with extinct men. But as can be imagined, it is
difficult and often impossible to decide whether an
archaeological site in, say, Java, is older than another one
in South Africa. The difficulty of placing finds in chrono¬
logical order and of interpreting fragmentary relics
means we are faced with a variety of alternative conclu¬
sions and this has led to wide controversy over the sig¬
nificance of certain finds.
Disagreement exists, for example, over the remains of
an ape found in the lignite deposits of Northern Italy.
Unlike living anthropoid apes, this one has a remarkably
48 small eye tooth, and other aspects of its dentition are
similar to those found in man. Is this really a prede¬
cessor of man, ten million years old, as some half-
informed and sensationalist newspapers would have us
believe? Specialists capable of judging the discovery are
by no means all of this opinion. The preparation of a
skeleton, which one of our Swiss colleagues has discovered,
with much effort and expense, is still not quite finished,
but it already shows extraordinarily long forearms.
Where can we hope to find the remains of our fore¬
fathers? The richest treasure troves are caves where
men sheltered, especially during the last Ice Age, and
where they buried their dead. But cave homes are gene¬
rally not more than 100,000 years old.
In the deepest strata we find Neanderthal man who
is only a step removed from us. He was smaller and more
stockily built than we are, his chin was lacking and he
had a massive, jutting brow in front of a low forehead.
His only implements were of chipped stone and he had
not learned to make pottery, but he already believed in
a life after death. He buried his dead and gave them the
best of tools and food for their journey into eternity.
This is why Neanderthal Man is the only fossil man of
CONT'D ON PAGE 50
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
photos G.H.R. von Koenigswald
Strange as it may seem, some of the most
remarkable clues to man's earliest ances¬
tors have come from Chinese medicine
shops where "dragons' teeth" (remains of
fossil animals) are collected, ground up
and sold as medicaments. From these
shops came the first tooth of Gigantopi-
thecus and also the teeth of Peking Man.
In 193 5, Dr. von Koenigswald combed
these "archaeological treasure houses" in
the Western Market of Hong Kong (left)
for traces of early man. Among the canine
remains of panda, bear, tapir and orang¬
outang he found the upper molar of giant
ape, Gigantopithecus, shown (enlarged) at
right alongside a human molar. Above, a
tooth of Peking Man (arrowed) among
other "dragons' teeth" and a recipe.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
A TOOTH WAS THE CLUE (Cont'd;
GIANT MAN OR
GIANT APE?
whom we have a complete skeleton. In the case of all
older discoveries we have only isolated remains mostly
of the victims of accidents. Thus we find human bones
in limestones, and burled in sandstones and gravels and
rock fissures.
We also find them in medicine shops and these "paleon¬
tológica! treasure houses" are certainly the most remark¬
able of all. I am, of course, not talking about just any
apothecary shops, but about Chinese ones where almost
anything which the vegetable, animal and mineral king¬
doms of China have to offer can be bought.
Such remains are used as ingredients for medicine and,
to judge by the overpopulated state of China, they are no
more dangerous than our own remedies. Among various
other medicaments "dragons' teeth" are highly prized.
These are not, as their name might suggest, the teeth of
saurians and other large reptiles, but the fossilized
remains of extinct mammals. It is already over a century
since specimens of this kind gave us our first insight Into
the fossil mammals of China and they have since proved
to be Important links in the research chain leading us
back to fossilized man.
When I was working as a geologist in Java, we
became very interested in "dragons' teeth".
Did they, we wondered, come from Java or from China?
We soon found that they all came from China but when
we went into the question more closely we found that in
ancient China there were once animals which are still
living in Indonesia. The most surprising example was
the orang-outang, the large anthropoid ape, which stiU
inhabits Borneo and Northern Sumatra.
To be absolutely sure that these remains came from
China, a visit was made to Hong Kong in 1935, and the
large apothecary shops in the "Western Market" were
thoroughly combed. The result was astounding. The har¬
vest included teeth of orang-outangs, tapirs, the Malayan
bear, Panda (the friendly Bamboo bears) of deers, pigs,
tigers and many other animals. But not one single jaw
could we find. Large porcupines had gnawed away all
the bones and teeth roots and only the crowns of teeth
remained. It was clear that all this material must
actually have come from Southern China.
The largest of all the ape teeth found had a smooth
surface Instead of the fine wrinkles found on an orang¬
outang's teeth. I immediately felt sure that we had come
across a new type of ape of enormous size. Subsequently,
In 1935, on the basis of this single find I described Gigan¬
topithecus, the giant ape of the Chinese apothecary shops.
Some of my colleagues disagreed, declaring that the
tooth was much too large for an ape, and one of them,
Professor Weidenreich, at first maintained that it was
simply that of a very large orang-outang. I made further
journeys to China, and in Canton I found a magnificent
upper molar, and in another apothecary shop in Hong
Kong an unworn lower molar. In certain respects both
these teeth show much resemblance to the teeth of man,
and Weidenreich, who had been so sceptical at first,
completely changed his opinion, saying that he now
considered my Gigantopithecus to have been a huge man.
One German anthropologist even wanted to change the
name to Giganthropus (anthropus man; pithecus ape),
and even made a fantastic reconstruction of the jaw bone.
Finally, 22 years after the discovery of the original
tooth, we were able to reach a more positive conclusion.
On February 17, 1957, my old friend and colleague, Dr. Pel
Wen Chung, exhibited in Peking an enormous jaw which
had been found in a cave in Kwangsi, in Southern China.
It was a lower jaw with a somewhat less specialized an¬
terior dentition than that of the living anthropoid apes.
But it was an ape: the tooth found In the Hong Kong
chemist's shop had not lied.
The Kwangsi jaw is larger than that of a gorilla,
50 which means that Gigantopithecus itself was larger than
Von Koenigswald, Utrecht
Taken from : Menschen der Urzeit by August
and Burian, published by Artia-Verlag, Prague 1 9 60
Above, a reconstruction of the Java Pithecanthropus made by
Professor Z. Burian of Prague. Its forehead was flat and the skull,
though lower than that of modern man, was about the same
length and width. Below, child's skull of the Australopithecus
group found in South Africa. The name means "Southern ape"
(Austral-south; pithecus-ape) but recent discoveries show
Australopithecus was similar to man and could walk upright.
Von Kcenigswald
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
In 1937 at this site
in Central Java, Dr.
von Koenigswald sol¬
ved a-40-year problem
that had puzzled
scientists ever since
a flat-topped skull and
thigh bone of Pithe¬
canthropus Erectus
had been found else¬
where in Java. Was
this man or ape ? The
answer was man. It
was confirmed by
later discoveries of
Dr. von Koenigswald.
Photos von Koenigswald and © L.J.B. Leakey, Nairobi
Three skulls which show that Asia and Africa (and Europe)
were all inhabited by the primitive man, Pithecanthropus,
half a million years ago. Top, skull discovered at Olduvai,
Tanganyika, by Dr. L.J.B. Leakey in I960. Centre, skull
discovered by Dr. von Koenigswald in Central Java in 1937.
Bottom, skull of Peking Man (Sinanthropus) found near
Peking in 1929, curiously similar to the Java find.
40 YEAR CONTROVERSY
OVER A FOSSIL SKULL
this ape, the largest and most powerful of anthropoid
apes living today. My Chinese colleagues estimated that
it must have been at least three metres tall. I am still
getting letters from people asking whether Gigantopithe¬
cus might not have been the "abominable snowman"
from the Himalayas, and people are very disappointed
when I have to tell them that I do not think so.
Another discovery was made which, although perhaps
not so dramatic, was no less fruitful. In 1900 a German
engineer named Haberer brought back a large collection
of "dragons' teeth" to Germany and our first extensive
knowledge of the fossil mammals of China is based on
the description of these specimens. The most remarkable
item was a human tooth, extremely worn and apparently
very old. It too had come from an apothecary shop in
Peking, and the search for the fossilized remains of
human beings was therefore concentrated on this area.
This led to a now celebrated event: the discovery of
the Peking man (Sinanthropus) of which, In the first
place, a single tooth had been unearthed. This was
claimed by Professor Davidson Black to be a hitherto
unknown fossil man. A skull found in 1929 by Dr. Pel,
who made many other important discoveries, proved that
Black was right. Successful excavations are still being
made today on the same site.
The teeth of the Peking man are very large and simi¬
lar to some of those found among our apothecary shop
specimens from Hong Kong. There were also smaller
teeth and because of the red clay which was found on
one part of the jaw, Father Tellhard de Chardin (whose
name is also linked with the discovery of the Peking Man)
identified it as coming from a Late Stone Age horizon
which is often to be found in caves. This was the jaw
of a "modern" man, only a few thousand years old. One
of the teeth is so similar to the first tooth found in the
Peking apothecary shop that both must have come from
the same strata. It was, therefore, a modern tooth which
put us on the track of Peking Man !
The discovery of the Peking Man brought the solution
to an earlier problem: whether the remarkable flat skull
cap dug up in Java by E. Dubois in 1890 was that of a
man or an ape. In 1891 an indisputably human thigh
bone was added to the earlier find though there was no
direct proof that both discoveries belonged to the same
subject. Dubois combined the two and his "erect
walking Java Ape-Man", the Pithecanthropus erectus,
remained the most controversial fossil for nearly 40 years.
T he main reason for this was that the ear
region of the Java skull was missing and it is
precisely this part of the skull which makes it possible to
reach a clear decision. In the case of the Peking man
a complete skull was available and in spite of his primi¬
tive characteristics he was, anatomically speaking, indis¬
putably human. This is also shown by the simple stone
implements and the layer of ashes found at the place of
discovery, which makes it clear that he already knew
about tools and fire.
The shape of the Peking skull was so similar to that
of the controversial Java find that Black concluded that
the Peking Man and the Java Man must have been close
relatives. The remarkable thing was that Dubois, the
discoverer of Pithecanthropus, disagreed with this theory.
Although he had always previously defended the human
characteristics of his find, he now denied that it was
related in any way to Peking Man and even went so far
as to declare that his Pithecanthropus was an ape.
The only way to resolve such a confused situation was
to redouble' our efforts in searching for the Java Man.
We found a promising site in Central Java with exposed
strata in which there were many remains of the same
extinct deer, antelopes and elephants as those discovered
by Dubois in association with his Pithecanthropus.
For years we worked In this area. During the rainy
season the downpour of water scattered the loosened ^
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
A TOOTH WAS THE CLUE (cont'd)
AFRICA, EUROPE AND ASIA ALL KNEW
PITHECANTHROPUS ERECTUS
fossils over the hillsides and we eagerly went to work,
soon assembling a large collection of teeth and bones of
extinct animals. This included the remains of hippopo¬
tamus no longer found in Asia various elephants, deer,
pigs, tigers, rhinoceros and other animals.
Then, one day in September 1937, we made an impor¬
tant find. One of my enthusiastic Indonesian collectors
came across a piece of skull. The next day I hastened
to the spot and promised the workers ten cents for every
piece of skull they brought me. I myself soon found
a large piece of the frontal bone, but my collectors only
brought me small fragments.
Too late I discovered what happened; the workers
had broken up all the larger pieces in order to make
more money! I was eventually given more than 40 pieces,
but fortunately there was very little difficulty about
joining them together since the skull was over one centi¬
metre thick.
It soon became clear that we had actually found a
second Pithecanthropus skull. It would be difficult to
find two skulls in a modern anthropological collection
which are so completely alike as Pithecanthropus I and
II, although the places of discovery were 30 miles apart.
The new find was finally complete enough to Include the
ear regions on both sides of the skull. One glance was
enough: Pithecanthropus had undoubtedly been a human
being. After 46 years the puzzle had finally been solved.
T he Pithecanthropus-Group which lived bet¬
ween 400,000 and 600,000 years ago, had a
thick brow with strong supraorbital ridges. The forehead
was flat and the skull, though lower than that of modern
man, was about the same length and width. Owing to
the thickness of the skuU bones, the space available for
the brain was very limited: Pithecanthropus had a brain
capacity of from 750 to 1,100 cubic centimetres; modern
man's is between 1,350 and 1,500.
A whole series of lower jaws of Peking Man were dis¬
covered unfortunately the best of these specimens were
lost during the Second World War and studies of the.se
revealed that they had a common link with other famous
discoveries. It became clear that the celebrated Heidel¬
berg jaw Europe's oldest and most primitive human
relic discovered in 1907 and the large Ternifine mandi¬
bles from Algeria, recently discovered by Professor Aran-
bourg and described as a relic of Atlanthropus, belonged,
like Peking Man, to the Pithecanthropus-Group.
That this group also occurs in Central Africa was shown
by the latest find of Dr. L.J.B. Leakey which has just
been announced. In the Serengeti steppes of Tanganyika
there is a gorge about 100 metres deep known as the
Olduvai Gorge. This has been cut through a thick layer
of horizontal strata, the majority of which had been
deposited in an old lake basin. In addition to numerous
remains of fossil mammals, most of them extinct, there
are also stone implements here.
Dr. Leakey, the curator of the Corydon Museum in
Nairobi, who discovered and described these remains,
found no less than ten different levels containing stone
Implements. In the deepest strata we find simple pebbles
which have been converted into a cutting tool by having
the two sides knocked off. These are the implements of
the "Oldowan culture" and the higher the stratum the
better are the tools. First of all we find large hand axes
of the "Chelles Culture", with their irregular cutting
edges, and higher still the thin oval axes with the straight
edge of the "Acheul Culture;".
These last two cultures were also known In Europe and
derive their names from the French places of discovery.
But nowhere in the world can the evolution of the hand-
axe cultures be followed step by step as they can in
Olduvai. I was able to visit the diggings under Dr. Lea¬
key's guidance and it was an unforgettable experience.
Who made these stone implements? Although Dr. Lea-
52 key began his research shortly after World War I, it is
only in the past few years that decisive discoveries have
been made. A skeleton discovered there in 1913 proved to
be of too recent interment to have any significance.
We can deal here only with the two most important
discoveries at Olduvai, the first of which was made in
1959 by Mrs. Leakey. This was a skull which came from
the lower stratum of the primitive "Oldowan culture".
Zinjanthropus, as Leakey called It, surprised us all for
it had a small ape-like skull (brain capacity about
600 cubic centimetres) with a low crest,- a large, coarse
face and powerful teeth. The molars were actually
almost twice as large as those of modern man while the
eye teeth and incisors were disproportionately small.
Leakey gave this find the name "Nutcracker man" on
account of the extraordinary dentition.
As a type, Zinjanthropus was by no means unknown to
us. We had already seen such examples of the Australo¬
pithecus-Group from deposits found in rock fissures of
South Africa. The name literally means "Southern ape"
(Austral south; Pithecus ape), and reminds us how
controversial these first discoveries were, though it has
been shown by new discoveries that Australopithecus was
similar to man and could even walk upright.
All members of this group have small brains and large
jaws. The result of this combination is that the bunches
of muscles for moving the. lower jaw meet together at the
top of the head and form between them a bony ridge
the crest already mentioned.
Similar conditions are found among anthropoid apes.
Among the forerunners of men we find a constant decrease
in the size of the chewing apparatus and a marked
increase in cranial capacity In other words, precisely
the opposite trends.
For these reasons we consider and I believe that most
of my colleagues will agree with me that Australo¬
pithecus was a side branch of the human family tree
which died out, and not a direct predecessor of Pithecan¬
thropus, still less of Homo sapiens, the modern type of
Man. Specimens of the Swartkrans Australopithecus, also
known as Paranthropus, have a crest-like ridge exactly
like that of the Zinjanthropus found at Olduvai.
N evertheless, Australopithecus is a primitive
man and this at once raises a difficult query:
did Australopithecus make implements? Various autho¬
rities have provided different answers to this question;
however, the possibility that he did use tools should not
be ruled out. But we now face another problem. Was
it really Zinjanthropus who was responsible for the
Oldowan culture? Should we consider him as a logical
predecessor of the hand-axe culture, which certainly has
nothing to do with Australopithecines?
As we were expecting, this last supposition has now
been confirmed by the latest discovery at Olduvai. On
December 2, 1960, Dr. Leakey found an almost complete
skull along with primitive hand-axes of the "Chelles
Culture 3." Though no detailed scientific description
has yet been published, the striking resemblance between
this new find and the skulls of the Pithecanthropus
Group is obvious from photographs.
This would provide a link with the North African
discoveries, for the lower jawbones of Atlanthropus
(found in Algeria) are comparable to those of the Peking
Man. It can therefore be assumed that the new find
is related to Atlanthropus, also discovered along with
primitive hand-axes, or rather with its forerunners. In
comparison with the Asiatic Pithecanthropus, the
Olduvai skull seems to have much heavier bony ridges
above the eyes.
Thus, these latest discoveries show us that Asia,
Europe and Africa were all inhabited by primitive Pithe¬
canthropi as much as half a million years ago, long
before metal was discovered and before the invention
of radio and aeroplanes which today make it so easy
and so difficult for us to get together.
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
Ahundred years ago a poet who was one of the
world's great champions of freedom died in St.
Petersburg. This year, his centenary is being celebrated
not only in his own land, Ukraine, but throughout the
Soviet Union, and in many great cities of the world
including the American capital, Washington, where a
statue is to be raised in his commemoration. This man's
name is Taras Shevchenko, the Ukrainian poet and patriot
who not only established his country's literature high
among world letters, but who actually lived his poetry.
A torchbearer of liberty, his whole life mirrored the suf¬
ferings of his oppressed country and the unconquerable,
indomitable will of its people to freedom.
The vast territory of Ukraine with its population
of 40 million stretches from Poland and Czechoslo¬
vakia to the Black and Azov Seas, and is the second
largest nation within the U.S.S.R. Of it Voltaire wrote
"L'Ukraine a toujours aspiré à être Ubre", for Its his¬
tory Is one of endless Invasion and national effort to
throw off oppression. Its literature goes back to the
tenth century but at that time it mostly made use of an
artificial language based on the ceremonial Church Sla¬
vonic; only in 1789 (the year of the French Revolution)
did the Ukrainian writer Kotlyarevsky introduce the
spoken language in literature and so lay a foundation
for Shevchenko to elaborate on.
Taras Shevchenko was born in a village near the
banks of the Dnieper in 1814; he was born a serf, a
scrap of humanity without rights or privileges, belong¬
ing entirely to the local landlords. It is perhaps diffi¬
cult to imagine what harsh misery the enslaved poverty
of serfdom meant to the Ukrainian peasant at this time,
but the waves of change which had brought American
Independence and the French Revolution, which had
washed away the old autocratic orders in Europe and
North America, had rippled to stagnation before reach¬
ing the East.
In 1814 Ukraine was still a feudal land under Tsarist
tyranny. The fertile beauty of the countryside of Taras'
childhood stood in cruel contrast to the living conditions
of his people but both these aspects of the life around
him affectedl him deeply ; from one he learnt a passion¬
ate patriotism, a love of his country which was to
remain uniflmmed by exile or absence, and from the
other he.- learnt a hatred of tyranny, of oppression and
injustice: Which inspires his poetry with the divine fire
of llberttE...
O dear and quiet land
O my Ukraine
Why do they plunder thee?
Why has death come to hut and lea?...
... Break your chains and live as brothers.
In a foreign country
Do not seek and do not search for
What is non-existent...
In your home, you'll find your justice
And your strength and freedom...
The world has only one Ukraine
Dniepro cannot be found elsewhere...
As a boy Taras showed early a vivid Imagination and
a passion for drawing. When he was left an orphan at the
age of twelve, he sought a teacher and from a brutal drun¬
ken clerk did learn to read and write though this man's
harshness finally drove him elsewhere. He quickly
exhausted the meagre local sources of learning open to
him and after a disconsolate speU of village cattlemind-
ing, he was summoned to work as scuUion in the manorial
kitchens. From there he attended the young master,
Pavel Vasilyevitch' Engelhardt, who took him as part of
his retinue on his travels.
A new world opened up before Taras; he won-
deringly absorbed all he could of this unaccustomed gran¬
deur, and secretly studied the art treasures housed round
him. One night in the Engelhardt establishment at
Wilno, the master returned late to find Taras absorbed
in copying a print by candlelight. He had the boy flogged
next day for his temerity but was so impressed by the
quality of the copy that he decided to allow Taras to
study with the Wilno painter, Rustem, and later, on
moving to St. Petersburg, apprenticed Taras to the painter
Shirayev, a harsh and cruel master who turned his pupils
into drudges.
Taras had little leisure, but in the white nights of the
early summer he would go to the Summer Gardens of
St. Petersburg to sketch the ancient statues there for his
own pleasure. It is on such an occasion that he is said
to have met a fellow Ukrainian, Ivan Soshenko, who was
studying at the Imperial Academy of Arts. 53
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
TARAS SHEVCHENKO (Cont'd;
POET OF A PEOPLE'S SUFFERING
Soshenko introduced Taras to his friends, to the Imper¬
ial Academy circle and the famous painter Bryulov, who
at once decided that Taras must study at the Academy
too. As a serf, Taras was ineligible to do this. Engel¬
hardt proved unwilling to part with his talented protégé
and finally only agreed to sell him his freedom for the
almost prohibitive price of 2,500 silver roubles.
To raise this sum, Taras' new friends rallied round;
Bryulov interested the celebrated poet Zhukhovsky who
commissioned a Bryulov portrait of himself and had it
auctioned by private lottery. On April 22, 1838 (a year
after the death of Pushkin) Engelhardt received his
2,500 roubles; Taras Shevchenko became a free man for
the first time in his Ufe.
From the grime of Shirayev's garret he was transported
to the enchanted halls of the Academy where his work won
him acclaim and whence he graduated honourably in
1845. He made many friends in the open-hearted
Bryulov circle, including the actor Shchepkin, and he
began thirstily to fill the gaps in his education, absorbing
all he could of literature and the arts, but underneath all
his sophisticated activities he could not forget Ukraine, the
sufferings of his people or the family he had left there
unable to share his freedom.
There arose in him a new passion, to express all his
homesickness and love for his country in Ukrainian verse.
Years later he wrote of this period spent in Bryulov's
studio in these words, "And what did I do in that holy
of holies? It is strange to think of it. I occupied myself
with writing Ukrainian verses ... I cherished In my
heart my blind Kobzar and my bloodthirsty Haydamaks
as In the shadows of the wild steppes I saw pass before
me the shades of our good hetmen.
"Before me stretched the steppe, studded with burial
mounds. Before me lay my fair, my unhappy Ukraine in
all Its chaste loveliness. And I mused, lost in thought;
I could not tear my inner eye from that enchanting
beauty. It was a vocation, that was all."
It was a vocation. In 1840 an enthusiastic Ukrainian
merchant found Shevchenko's verses while sitting for
his portrait in the artist's studio and immediately
published them at his own expense. Shevchenko called
the Uttle book Kobzar, after the name of the old Ukrai¬
nian wandering folkbards. Keeping to the traditional
folksong form and within the Romantic current of the
day, he idealizes the stern and bitter conflicts which the
Kozaks of old had waged for independence, glorifying the
Kobzars who alone had kept alive the memory of Ukraine's
heroic age.
Kóbzar marks an epoch and the beginning of a new
Ukrainian literature; it throws a bridge between its
ancient treasures, the later work of Kotlyarevsky, and
modern literature. For the first time a major poet emerges
to pour out his heart In his native tongue and express
the sufferings of his people and their past. And because
he lived so deeply in their thoughts and feeUngs, they
accepted his poems as their own songs and composed
music to them: today his works are in almost every
Ukrainian home and are sung throughout Russia.
But his poetry is more than just folksong; it has the
magic simplicity' and melody of pure verse. "Owls are
calling/ sleeps the forest/ stars are shining brightly . . ."
"Like the sea the field whitened/ by the driving snow-
flakes ..." Countless country images reflect the poet's
mastery of his art. Together 'with this evocative lyricism,
his poems are permeated with his innate humanism.
No one knew better than he the harshness of the
peasant way of life. In the theme for instance
of the village girl transgressing the moral code, he
poignantly and repeatedly makes a plea for compassion
and tolerance. In his long epic poem The Haytlamak,
which came out in 1841 and recalled the 1768 revolt of the
Ukrainians against their Polish overlords, he writes "Why
should people destroy each other? . . . Only see, they are
the same kind of people, they could live, they could be
friends."
In 1843 he gave way to his intolerable longing and
returned home to Ukraine; he was welcomed everywhere
as a national poet, portrait commissions flowed in, all
doors were open before him, but the terrible sufferings
he saw among the peasants on his travels throughout
the country brought about a sharp change in his work.
His idealization of the Kozak epoch gave place to stinging
Shevchenko knew from his own personal experience the
kind of harsh treatment meted out to political prisoners by
authorities determined to crush the spirit of freedom. He
wrote of it in his poems and depicted it in paintings like
those below taken from his series entitled "The Prodigal
Son", showing (left) punishment by the insertion of a
heavy stick into the mouth to prevent speaking, and
(right) the despair of prisoners chained together in a cell.
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
castigation of the enslavement, despotism and tyranny
he saw everywhere exercised on behalf of the Tsar
Nicholas I. He became openly rebellious to every institu¬
tion, whether religious or civil, which seemed to tolerate
such terror, cruelty and injustice as were suffered by the
Ukrainian serf. He began a series of poems which from a
literary standpoint are considered his most perfect. Poli¬
tically they were dynamite ; they could not possibly be
published in the Russia of that time and their circula¬
tion even in a private album which Shevchenko called
Three Years figured greatly in his arrest in 1847.
Among these poems, The Great Grave recounts in
mystical terms the immortal freedom-loving spirit; The
Dream, written in a form of fantastic satire, contains an
acid attack upon the Imperial family in which the poet
ridicules the Court and likens the Empress to a dried
mushroom; the whole poem is one of his bitterest attacks
against tyranny.
"The people's loud cries and their laughs are not
[heard . . .
They strip the patched clothing from off of the beggars
They strip with the hides for the poor must find shoes
For youthful young princes. They pummel the widow
To pay her poll taxes; they fetter her son
Her son, her one son, the only child that she has;
Her hope and they send him away to the army
But for a while yet in filth and in mud
The boy is soon bloated from hunger he dies,
His mother is reaping the wheat at forced labour . . ."
In another poem, The Caucasus, Shevchenko celebrates
the struggle of the mountain people for their freedom.
He sent this poem to Paris to the Polish revolutionary
and poet Adam Mickiewicz, a follower of Mazzlni, and
it shows his widening interest in the cause of freedom
not only In Ukraine but everywhere.
"And our human spirit dies not
And our freedom dies not . . .
It is for us to keep on weeping
With bloody sweat and bitter tear . . .
And mix each day with our daily bread
Truth will rise and so will freedom . . .
And meanwhile the streams are flowing
Streams of blood are flowing."
At about this time appears the poem The Feeble Minded
(Jorldyvyl) in which Shevchenko, a contemporary of
Abraham Lincoln, wrote
"When shall we receive our Washington, '
With a new and righteous law
And receive we will some day . . ."
In Kiev during this period he found sympathetic friends
among a group of young Pan-Slavic revolutionaries called
the Society of Saints Cyril and Methodius; their revolu¬
tionary ideals for peasant enlightenment and emancipa¬
tion encouraged him to write The Heretic, a poem hon¬
ouring the Czech reformer Jan Huss and glorifying him
not so much as a great scholar but as a representative
of the common people.
"Seer you caught the glimpse of freedom,
Freedom and of truth,
And the Slav wide-scattered family,
Sunk in dark and slavery,
You collected all together . . ."
The existence of this Society was betrayed to the
authorities In February 1847 and they acted swiftly and
savagely suppressed It. By AprU Shevchenko and his
friends were arrested and sent to St. Petersburg. In
prison there the poet produced a number of verses in
which he expressed his concern for the future of his
country and the fate of his people. His main indictments
were the "outrageous and to the highest degree insolent"
poems and the Three Years album confiscated at his
arrest.
On May 30 he was sentenced to serve as an ordinary
soldier in the bare Orenburg steppe, "a broad, unlocked
prison." On his sentence file papers Tsar Nicholas I wrote
in his own hand, "under the strictest supervision with
a prohibition of writing and sketching."
Shevchenko had been free for only nine years; now
he was back in a bondage more terrible than before,
torn away from Ukraine and condemned to live among
rough and brutalizing soldiery in the remotest area of
Eastern Russia. At first sympathetic officers allowed
him clandestinely to draw and write,
"Am I to live in this sad plight,
Still many years, forever wasting . . .
But I am looking, while my heart's flying,
To a dark garden in Ukraine . . ."
When the St. Petersburg authorities got to know of
this, the Tsar's instructions were carried out to the letter.
Shevchenko Was sent to a still wilder place, the fortress
of Novopetrovsk on the Caspian Sea. Of this place he
wrote, "Sand and stones; if only there were one blade of
grass, only a tree, but nothing." The endless drill, the
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
From childhood Shevchenko showed a vivid imagination
and a passion for drawing. As a serf he was ineligible to
enter the Imperial Academy of Arts and was only able to
do so after friends had bought his freedom for 2,500 silver
roubles. Then the painter also began to fill in other gaps
in his education and became a poet and writer too. Below,
two of Shevchenko's works: left, an illustration for his
poem "The Prisoner"; right, the village girl, Katherine.
p-^äf5¡
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
TARAS SHEVCHENKO (Cont'd)
POWER AND PROTEST
absolute deprivation of any creative work or interests
wore him away. "There is nothing more bitter than to
recaU freedom in captivity", he wrote at this time, but
even though his health was affected, his spirit remained
unbroken and he was able to note in his diary, "all
this unspeakable grief, every kind of degradation and
harshness passed as if without touching me . . . Not
a single aspect of the inner me was changed."
He was to languish nearly seven years in Novopetrovsk
since, even after the death of Nicholas I, Imperial feelings
were still tender from the "dried mushroom" episode.
The new Tsar Alexander did not include Shevchenko in
his general amnesty, and not until two years more had
passed did friends finally secure his release, when he
returned to St. Petersburg to enjoy great moral and poli¬
tical prestige.
One of his first compositions after being freed was
The Neophytes, a daring comparison of the Tsar with
Nero, for Shevchenko had returned from exile with his
hatred of Tsarism equaUed only by his hatred of slavery
Taras Shevchenko's first
fame came as a painter,
especially for his por¬
traits (see self portrait
at left). But his fame
today rests with the poe¬
try in which he captured
the heart, soul and ¡mage
of his native Ukraine.
As early as I860, trans¬
lations of his poems
appeared in Poland, and only a little later Czech
and Bulgarian translations also appeared. In 1870,
Georg Obrist translated his poems into German
and six years later they were published in French.
By 1903 his works were translated into English. In
the past fifty years, Shevchenko's poems have been
translated 400 times into 41 languages, numbering
12,000,000 copies. In the poet's native language,
for Ukrainians around the world, his works have been
published 245 times in almost seven million copies.
56
for him these two evils were related and he never
counted the cost in fighting them.
No other European literature has a comparable protest
against serfdom and there is no other poet of genius
sprung from the serfs who has shown up the ugliness
of serfdom with such powerful effect as Shevchenko.
He contributed much to the abolition of serfdom by
influencing liberal public opinion which played a large
part in inducing Alexander to initiate liberal reforms.
He interested himself in etching at the Academy,
becoming an Academician in 1860, and achieving work
which caused other artists to call him .the "Russian
Rembrandt." A Negro actor, Aldridge, cam.s to the city
and played Othello there: Shevchenko had always been
deeply influenced by Shakespeare; he was much moved
by Aldridge's performance and the two men became
friends. And he continued to write, raising the flaming
banner of his verse in the same causes of justice and
liberty as before. Although he risked immediate retalia¬
tion, he did not hesitate to sign a statement defending
the civil rights of the Jews which where in question, and
he consorted openly with the leading radicals of the day,
King Lear and his Fool. Illustration by Shevchenko
for a Russian edition of Shakespeare's tragedy.
including Chernyshevsky who spoke up for a new edition
of Kobzar, which was allowed to be published in 1860 pro¬
vided none of the post-exile poems were included in it.
But despite his valiant spirit, Shevchenko returned
broken in body and weary from his exile. Personal
unhappiness and loneliness weighed heavily upon him
and his last poems, including Mary in which he deliber¬
ately changes the sacred story to that of an ordinary
peasant woman, have more austere, often Biblical,
sources; they carry a message emphasizing mankind's
need for truth and love and brotherhood.
Against the day of peasant emancipation he wrote a
primer for use in schools, but his very last poem is a
swansong and a testament of faith that he will in another
world	 "on Phlegethon, or on the Styx in heaven, or
on Dniepro, that mighty river . . ." find a happiness which
this Ufe denied him and which, towards the end, he most
patheticaUy sought.
He died on March 10, 1861, and was buried as he had
asked
"in a lofty tomb
out upon the steppes unbounded
in my own dear Ukraine;
so that I can see before me
the wide stretching meadows
and Dniepro, its banks so lofty,
and can hear it roaring . . ."
His grave lies near the small town of Kanev where
in 1939 a memorial was raised to him which has been
called "an object of special reverence among his country¬
men, the Mecca of all Ukrainian patriots." So it is,
but this poet of Ukraine, who took his language as it had
been developed, and by the power of his genius ensconced
it in modern literature, this apostle of liberty, enemy of
all oppression, Taras Shevchenko, goes beyond the narrow
limits of one country. He is a poet of humanity; his
message of brotherhood and love, truth and justice, and
above all, of freedom, is worldwide in scope, universal in
significance. Other poets have sung his song, other poets
are perhaps better known, but none by the pure identifi¬
cation of his life with his inspiration deserves greater
homage or recognition.
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
CITY ON STILTS
Sir,
I read with great interest the arti¬
cle on the Canadian town of Aklavik
situated inside the Arctic Circle in the
permafrost zone. Soviet engineers in
similar territory are building towns,
settlements, factories, railways and
roads, aerodromes and canals in our
permafrost belt. The building is
going on today on a very large scale
and at high speed.
A good example is the town of
Norilsk, about 100 kilometres to the
East of the River Yenissei in Siberia
and well beyond the Arctic Circle.
The climate is much more severe than
in Canadian Aklavik the tempera¬
ture drops to -50°C, accompanied
by strong winds. Average annual
temperature is -8.7 °C. The perma¬
nently frozen layers within the town
are from 80 to 150 metres thick.
Norilsk, beyond the Arctic Circle
Norilsk has been built literally in
a few years; it only reached the status
of a town in 1953 but already has a
population of over 100,000 people of
various nationalities. Its streets are
lined with tall blocks of apartments
with water, electricity, heat and other
utilities. A heat-and-power station
provides electric current and hot wat¬
er for heating and domestic purposes.
The buildings are erected on ferro¬
concrete piles sunk 6 to 8 metres deep
into the frozen ground; they freeze
into place and become part of the
permafrost. Under each building
there is a hollow space allowing the
free passage of air to preserve the
frozen ground and prevent thawing.
Water mains, drains and other com¬
munications are partly underground
and partly above the surface, as at
Aklavik.
The town possesses a TV centre, a
drama theatre, four cinemas, two
sports stadiums, a swimming pool,
clubs, libraries (about thirty), schools,
hospitals, etc. Communication with
the outside world is by rail to Du-
dinka, a port on the Yenissei (the
railway has been laid over perma¬
frost), and by air from an airport
some fifteen kilometres from the
town.
Experience gained in Norilsk is
being applied in other parts of the
Soviet permafrost zone.
Sh. Akbulatov
Krasnojarsk, U.SJS.R.
PHOTOMICROGRAPHY OR
MICROPHOTOGRAPHY ?
Sir,
Upon reading your excellent edition
of May, 1961, I felt that I had to
write to you to correct a rather
serious misnomer in your article enti¬
tled "The Invisible World". You
were not discussing "microphoto-
graphs," a word used in the title of
the article, and many times through¬
out, but "photomicrographs." A
"microphotograph" is merely a small
photograph; a "photomicrograph" is
a photograph of an enlarged picture
of an object, taken, for example,
through a microscope. The subject
under discussion, therefore, was "pho¬
tomicrography", and not "micropho¬
tography" as stated in the title of the
article. The term "microphotogra¬
phy" may be used in connection with
micro-filming, or any process wherein
the photograph represents a "reduc¬
tion" in the size of the object.
I have always enjoyed reading The
Unesco Courier, and I wish you
much success with future editions.
D.K. Edwards
Victoria, B.C. Canada
Ed. note: Technically our correspon¬
dent is correct but in common usage
the two terms are synonymous. Both
Oxford and Webster confirm this
usage, the Oxford English Dictionary
quoting 1858 as the first date of the
use of microphotography to mean pho¬
tomicrography.
THE RACISM ISSUE
Sir,
We are an "independent" theatre
in Buenos Aires, i.e. one that is not
subject to the limitations of the com¬
mercial stage. Last season, we pro¬
duced and are still running a play
"Hot Summer Night" by the Eng¬
lish author, Ted Willis. This deals
with the problem which now exists
generally in London through the mi¬
gration of Jamaican coloured workers
to England.
To decorate one of the walls of our
entrance hall and illustrate at the same
time the subject of the play, we have
used the material of your issue on
Racism, as well as the letters to the
editor on this subject, which you
published in a later issue, letters which
reveal the existence of the kind of
prejudice that motivates the play.
We take this opportunity to tell you
how much in agreement we are with
the trend of thought expressed by your
magazine, whose material is always
of outstanding cultural and informa¬
tive interest.
"La Mascara" Theatre
Buenos Aires, Argentina
Sir,
Many people, are of the opinion
that racial prejudice can be easily
refuted through the publishing of
results of scientific investigations
which show potentially at least no
difference between, say, white and
black. This is all very well but it
does not seem to take account of the
complex of inadequate views which
create racial tension and which the
prejudiced fail to recognize as being
part of their own way of think¬
ing. For instance, there used to be a
school of thought which considered
the Negro as some sort of half-way
stage between the "missing link" and
"homo sapiens". Perhaps there is an
unconscious acceptance of this view
by the person who says of some Afri¬
can in the news "But hasn't he a high
forehead!" I feel that an almost men¬
tally purgative action would follow
from publishing articles examining
and criticizing the eccentric evolutio¬
nary theories and the pseudo-socio¬
logy on which the opinions of the
racially bigoted now rest.
If racial intolerance is irrational,
conversion from it may not follow
from a parade of rational arguments
condemning it. What is needed is
an attempt at collective psychoanaly¬
sis so that the origins of present in¬
tolerance may be exposed.
W.A.C. Swan
Oxford, England.
VELAZQUEZ A LA PICASSO
Sir,
In your February issue there was
a note on Velazquez in the Picasso
Manner. I cannot understand how the
image drawn by Picasso and dis¬
gustingly distorting Velazquez' picture
demonstrates the "all-round talent" of
. that artist.
Will you please explain the point
of view of those people (I know there
are many of them) who consider such
images to be works of art and allow
them, as can be seen from the pho¬
tographs on pages 7 and 11 of the
same issue, to be reproduced even on
the walls of the Unesco building.
In what does Picasso's talent
consist? What benefit do his draw¬
ings, published in your journal, bring
to people and what pleasure do they
give?
M. Cherkasova
Secondary School Teacher
Moscow, U.S.S.R.
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
THIRTY-FIVE STATES SIGN «ADDIS ABABA PLAN'
FOR VAST EXPANSION OF EDUCATION IN AFRICA
TWO bold plans for the educational development of Africa were unanimously
approved recently at a conference convened in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, by
Unesco and the U.N. Economic Commission for Africa. The first, a short
term plan, aims to raise primary school enrolment in Africa from its present
figure of 40% of the school-age population to 51% by 1966 from eleven million
to nearly 15 million children. In addition secondary school enrolment should rise
from 3% of the primary school population to 9%. This five-year project will
cost an estimated $4,150,000,000.
The second plan, scheduled to take place over 20 years, provides for the estab¬
lishment of universal, primary education throughout Africa by 1980, with 30 % of
the children who complete primary schooling going on to secondary schools. This
same plan allows for a tenfold increase of present university enrolment figures.
Costs of the long-term programme should reach their peak in 1970 when total
annual expenditures would amount to $1,790,000,000.
Both programmes form part of what has been called the "Addis Ababa Plan",
signed by the representatives of 31 African states and territories and of four
European powers with African responsibilities. The plan catalogues Africa's edu¬
cational needs and lays down priorities for expanding secondary education, teacher
training at all levels, the reform and adaptation of existing school curricula. It
also lays greater stress on agricultural and technical education.
mammals, birds, reptiles and fish are
of local origin, but others like the little
foxes had to be "repatriated". The
biblical zoo has some 700 animals.
58
M. O STAMP OUT MALARIA: Eradi¬
cation of malaria, a priority goal for the
World Health Organization (WHO), is "the
greatest international health endeavour
ever undertaken.'" To help finance it,
WHO has suggested that member states
issue anti-malaria stamps on World Health
Day, April 7, 1962, under the slogan: "The
World United Against Malaria." Countries
issuing stamps may either contribute a
percentage of the proceeds from their sales
to WHO or donate stamps for sale.
ARID LANDS & THE FUTURE:
Arid and semi-arid regions are estimated
to cover more than one-third of the
earth's land surface; cultivated ground
represents barely one-tenth. For each
acre of cultivated land, three or four
acres are practically unused by man
because they are desert or covered with
sparse vegetation. At its present rate
of increase the world's population of
2,700 million will double in fifty years.
Facts like these which add up to a major
world problem are described and dis¬
cussed by Professor Gilbert White of
the University of Chicago, in "Science
and the Future of the Arid Lands."
This 96-page pamphlet, published as
part of Unesco's Major Project for
encouraging scientific research into the
development of arid lands, can be
obtained free of charge from Unesco,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris V.
T WO NEW UNTVERSITIES: A spe¬
cial committee has drawn up plans for a new
European University to be located in Flor¬
ence. It is intended that the university
shall provide an international .centre for
post-graduate study either in fields inade¬
quately covered by existing universities or
in subjects which, in view of the current
and future problems of a uniting Europe,
need to be studied from a specifically
European angle. In Nigeria a new uni¬
versity is to be built for students of the
Western Region at Ife, 55 miles from
Ibadan, capital of the region. Ife, whose
name is derived from a word meaning
"genesis" or "expansion", is the cultural
cradle of the Yoruba people, the heirs of
one of the oldest and most remarkable
civilizations in this part of Africa.
! BATTLE WITH BRINE: Fresh wat¬
er supplies in the Netherlands are being
threatened by the infiltration of sea
water, and canals irrigating more than
1,300,000 acres of land are becoming
useless for this purpose as their increas¬
ing chlorine content is harmful to agri¬
culture. The vast Delta Plan now
being carried out to protect the land
from flooding in the south will help to
prevent the seepage, but in addition, the
Netherlands will have to turn increas¬
ingly to fresh water supplies provided
by rivers flowing into the country from
the east, principally the Rhine. This in
turn will require countries bordering the
river to limit the amount of industrial
waste released into its waters.
M JERUSALEM'S BIBLICAL ZOO:
"The foxes, the little foxes that spoil
the vines" mentioned in Solomon's
Song of Songs have been brought back
all the way from Australia to Jerusalem.
But they have not been released in
Israel's vineyards; they are now
inmates of a zoo, unique of its kind,
which now exists in a wooded park
just outside Jerusalem, and which is
reserved specifically for descendants of
animals of biblical fame. Most of these
H OUSE ON SPRINGS: An earth¬
quake proof house, set on special shock
absorbers, has been built at Ashkhabad,
capital of the Turkmenian Socialist Soviet
Republic. The walls do not touch the
ground at any point, but are erected on
reinforced concrete "cushions". The
water pipes and drainage pipes are
connected by flexible corrugated rubber
muffs. The designer made use of the
experience of the ancient Central Asian
builders who erected huge buildings such
as mosques on cushions of reeds.
THE UNESCO
PHILATELIC SERVICE
NATIONS UNIES St {t M
< /(jf^i, To unite our sîrenqth 5
5 W$P ,,AI i ~
*
OB-bEAMHEHHblE HAU.MM
The 3 0 cent stamp (shown above) is
the latest addition to the series of
regular stamps issued by the United
Nations Postal Administration. It
shows a collection of flags in red,
yellow, blue, orange and green on a
light grey background. These sym¬
bolize In design and colour the
accompanying text, "To unite our
strength" one of the key phrases in
the Preamble to the United Nations
Charter. The new stamp is expected
to be used primarily on air mail
letters to Europe and North Africa,
but it will also be employed for
special delivery mail in the United
States. This stamp and other phila¬
telic items can be obtained from the
Unesco Philatelic Service which has
stamps and first day covers issued by
member states to commemorate
important events in the history of
Unesco and the United Nations. As
the agent in France of the U.N. Postal
Administration, Unesco's Philatelic
Service stocks all the United Nations
stamps currently on sale. Information
on items available will be sent on
request by the Unesco Philatelic
Service, Place de Fontenoy, Parls-7*.
<
z
<
oí
o
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
Just published :
the changing
social
position
of women
in Japan
by Takashi Koyama
During the first half of the 20th century a wide range of political,
economic and social developments has taken place in nearly all
industrialized countries, accompanied by a tremendous change
in the social position of women. In Japan during the same period
the forces which operate to free women from the bondage of
feudalists tradition have not had their full impact. They have
encountered strong opposition from the conservative elements
in Japanese society. It is only since the end of World War II that
women in Japan have been gaining a voice in the major institu¬
tions of society. Professor Takashi Koyama and a group of colla¬
borators present the history and the present state of women in
Japanese society, including their rôle in thefamily.theever-increas-
ing part they play in Industry, commerce and in civic activities.
$2.00 10/- 7 NF 152 p.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Educación, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne Universiey
Press, 369 Lonsdale Screec, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria. (A. 1 5/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C0., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Seh.
50.-)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, C.C.P. 338.000. (fr. b. 1 00.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, C.C.P. 285.98;
N.V. Scandaard-Boekhandel, Belgielei 151,
Antwerp.
BURMA. Sarpay Beikman Institute,
361 Prowe Road, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
One. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associaced Newspapers
of Ceylon Led, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7, Apartado 113, Havana. (2.25 pesos)
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard, A/S
Tidsskrifcafdelingen, 6 Nörregade, Köben-
havn K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. Incernacional Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akaceeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Paris, 7°. C.C.P. 12598-48.
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier,
Vertrieb Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bah.enfeld, C.C.P. 276650
(DM 8). Other Publications: R. Older-
burg, Verlag, Rosenheimerstr. 145, Munich
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapesc, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Led. Indian
Mercancile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bombay
I; 17 Chiccaranjan Avenue, Calcucta 13;
Gunfoundry Road, Hyderabad, I; 36a,
Mounc Road, Madras 2; Kanson House,
24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 3 86, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Scaeionery Co., 17 Park Screec Calcucta 16,
Scindia House, New Delhi. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusac "Permaca",
Djalan Nusantara 22, Djakarea.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Nacional Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Led.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Screec, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-).
JAMAICA. Sangscer's Bock Room, 91
Harbour Screet, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 670).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kucub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LIBERIA. J. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( 1 0/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.
30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid dés
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
G. CT. Van Dorp & C- (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Wülemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Cenere, 100 Hackchorne Road, Chrise-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop. P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-).
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornec. Lille Gren-
sen,7, Oslo. (N. kr. 13.20).
PAKISTAN. The Wesc-Pak Publishing
Co, Led., Unesco Publicacions House,
P.O. Box 374, 56-N Gulberg Induscnal
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Culcural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. TI-49, Apareado de Correos 20 I 8,
Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3.-).
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Educación Co.
Inc., ; I 04 Cascillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46,
Warsaw. 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
RHODESIA & NYASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia.
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel.
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA Dar-es-Salaam Book¬
shop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panic, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals).
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Screec, Precoria. (10/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.[.( I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S 5.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjîga,
Terazjje 27/11. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
ARE MEN NO BETTER THAN ANTS?
Ants are the only organisms which
frq¡¡| manindulge in organized
warfare, raraing the nests of other spe¬
cies and incorporating captives into
their own societies. Here, a red ant
overcomes a black opponent, using his
powerful pincers to bisect the enemy.
Taken from the film "Secrets of Life" © Walt Disney.
0
w"
' #
"#
à i
]]>
</page>
</document>
