<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064515eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
vBv l^lHÎfl/VilT
'f Cr
ÖS t i4ÍM*l»J ,
'Hflfr.rffn
IB
fXfittÍAJt1
vi
MjMjîy
iw
AW
TrrírVVVV
4îm-mMJ|
ïlflr
fj||V
[{«
iÄ}jWjijv
'/) Pf f?rïr
JANUARY
1960
(/3th year)
Price : l/-stg. (U.K.)
ents (U. S.)
N F. (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
MAGNETIC MEMORY MAKERS. Electronic computers are progressively getting bigger and bigger in terms of work capacity
can now average ten thousand operations a secondbut the components are getting smaller and smaller. Today transistors
no bigger than a grain of rice have replaced radio valves and some cells which store information are a 250th of a millionth of an
Inch in diameter. Below, magnetic "memory stores" for use in electronic digital computers being made in a British factory. Above,
windings forming part of the "memory", into which information is fed and stored, are soldered into position. Wires are threaded
through tiny cores, sometimes only one-twentieth of an inch in diameter, so threading the thousands that are used demands a
keen eye and much dexterity. This wiring by hand illustrates the vital part still played by the skilled worker in the age of automation.
Photos British Embassy, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 WINDOW OHM ON THI WOI10
ner
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
JANUARY 1960
13TH YEAR
Contents
No. I PAGE
4 CONTRACT WITH CONSCIENCE
The life and work of Anton Chekhov
By Pauline Bentley
IN THE STEPS OF ANTON CHEKHOV
Return visit to a former convict island
CHEKHOV-MASTER OF THE SHORT STORY
By Professor Maria Yelizarova
PARADOX OF DESOLATION AND PROSPERITY
Patagonia, last frontier of the inhabited world
By E. Aubert de la Rue
COVER PHOTO
This month the centenary
of the birth of Anton
Chekhov, great Russian
writer and dramatist, is
being celebrated in all parts
of the world. (See page 4)
Official Soviet photo
26 THE WORLD'S KNOWLEDGE INSIDE A CIGAR BOX
The story of modern electronic computers
By Ritchie Calder
29 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
30 BOOKS ON WHEELS
A library comes to a Greek village
2 LABORATORY FOR DESERT LIVING
Air-conditioning and delicious meals in the Sahara
By Daniel Be h r man
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7; France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavarlanl
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
/// correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (I2 issues a year) in English.
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 80 I Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza I-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 59. 1. 143 A).
Individual articles. and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 700 Fr. frs
(7 New Francs) or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg.
30 cents (U.S.) ; 70 Fr. frs. (70 centimes, New Franc).
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
CHEKHOV WROTE FOR THE THEATRE ALL HIS LIFE. HIS EARLY PLAYS WERE ONE-ACT COMEDIES. WITH MATURITY CAME WORKS
OfTicial Soviet píiota
Contract with
conscience
by Pauline Bentley
Article copyright. Reproduction prohibited
Anton Chekhov at the age of 28, an unfinished
sketch made by his artist brother Nicolas.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
WITH A DISTINCTIVE STYLE OF PSYCHOLOGICAL REALISM
Official Soviet photo
LIKE 'THE CHERRY ORCHARD' PRESENTED HERE BY THE MOSCOW ART THEATRE
A
It is just 100 years since the birth of the great Russian dramatist, author and humanist Anton
Pavlovitch Chekhov. Born on January 17, 1860 at Taganrog on the Sea of Azov, the son
of a tradesman and the grandson of a serf, Chekhov had a relatively short creative life for he
died at the age of 44. Yet the works he produced in less than two decades were sufficient
to place him as one of the greatest contributors to Russian and world literature. In 1960,
homage will be paid to Chekhov in all parts of the world with the commemoration of the
centenary reaching its apogee in the Soviet Union. Unesco is associating itself with the anni¬
versary celebrations. It is distributing special articles on Chekhov in its Member States and
is sending a specially produced documentary radio programme to some 130 broadcasting sta¬
tions. Schools will receive a Unesco filmstrip on Chekhov with accompanying booklet in
English, French and Spanish. As its share in this universal homage, The Unesco Courier
devotes several pages of this issue to Chekhov, his life and work. The article below is based
on Unesco's radio programme written by Pauline Bentley, British actress and playwright who
has devoted many years to the study of Chekhov and the theatre. On page 13, Professor
Maria Yelizarova, a Soviet authority and author of several books on Chekhov's artistic crea¬
tions discusses Chekhov as a master of the short story.
MONG writers there are those who die enriching
life and literature not only with their work, but
sometimes leaving behind them as well a
legend which can exceed the truth from
i which it springs.
The Russian writer, Anton Chekhov, who
I was born just a hundred years ago, will very
likely evoke an immediate recollection of
melancholy and gentle futility. His legend is
one of pessimism. How did this come about?
There were in a way three Che'khovs the funny .writer for
the Moscow comic papers, the serious short story writer,
and the playwright. And it is perhaps as a playwright
that he is best known.
Outside his own country, his last four great plays,
"The Seagull", "uncle Vanya", "The Three Sisters" and
"The Cherry Orchard", are nearly always presented with
a deliberate accent on their minor key and inconclusive
content. And yet from many letters and the notebooks
which he left we can see how much Chekhov fought
against this interpretation of his work and how little he
would have cared for his legend. He was far too lucid
and humorous to wallow in melancholia for its own sake.
Perhaps it should be remembered he was writing at a
time when the society around him was decaying, restless
and frustrated. After the exhilaration of the reforms
which had taken place in Russia in the 1860's, Russia
was in the doldrums before the storm of the Revolution
and Chekhov caught this mood of his times. Many of
his stories and characters reflect it, since he was one of
the most truthful of writers, but time and again he points
beyond to a hopeful future, and his natural optimism
shines through.
Here is how another writer, Korolenko, a friend of his,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
CHEKHOV (Continued)
6 1 hate violence and
lies of any kind'
Photo taken from "Europe", Paris
Anton Chekhov and his wife Olga who had been
an actress in the Moscow Art Theatre. When,
in 1904, Chekhov went to Badenweiler in Ger¬
many for the sake of his rapidly failing health,
she accompanied him on that last trip. After
her husband's death, she resumed her car¬
eer in the theatre and was eventually honoured
with the Soviet title of Artist of the People.
described the young Anton when they met in Moscow,
in 1887.
"Before me stood a young man who looked indeed
younger than his years, a little above average height,
with an oval face and regular, clear cut features, still
retaining the soft contours of youth. There was something
unusual about the face, something which I was not able'
to define at first. Despite the fact that it was obviously
the face of an intellectual, it suggested a simple-hearted
country lad. It was that which made his face so
attractive. Even his eyes, luminous and deep, gleamed at
once with thought and with almost childish naivete.
"His whole appearance, his gestures, his way and
manner of speaking, like his writing, radiated simplicity.
On the whole, at this my first meeting with him, Chekhov
struck me as a profoundly cheerful soul. The endless
source of wit and spontaneous gaiety which fills his
stories seemed to well up in his eyes. But beneath it we
sensed there was something deeper that had yet to develop
and was bound to develop for the best. I got a general
impression of sincerity and charm."
Behind Chekhov at this time there already lay an
unhappy childhood, and the first signs of the tuberculosis
which killed him when he was only 44. He was one of
six children, born in the little seaport town of Taganrog
on the Sea of Azov in south Russia. Unlike the aristocratic
writers, Turgenev and Count Tolstoi, who Was later his
.friend, he came of peasant stock. His grandfather was
a serf who bought the family's freedom for 700 roubles
a head. His own father was an unsuccessful grocer who
made Anton's childhood miserable with enforced piety,
frequent beatings and rigid schooling.
When Anton was sixteen, the shop failed and the family
fled its creditors to Moscow, leaving him behind in
Taganrog to finish his schooling and fend for himself by
coaching others and doing odd jobs for the merchants of
the town. These were years of poverty and hardship but
Anton survived them with characteristic gaiety and high
spirits. He even managed to write cheering letters to
the family in Moscow.
He used these years to educate himself in every way,
to deliberately free himself from the limitations of birth
and class. In a letter describing his ideal of a writer which
he wrote years later to an editor called Suvorin, he recalls
something of his struggle during the years alone in
Taganrog:
"In addition to a profusion of talent and material,
something else is necessary to a writer. First, a mature
mind, and, secondly, a feeling of personal freedom. The
plebeian intellectuals have to purchase with their youth
what the aristocratic writers receive gratis from mother
nature. Why don't you write a story about a young man
whose father was a serf, a young man who was in turn
salesman, choirboy, schoolboy and student, brought up to
treat rank with respect, to kiss the hands of priests, to
worship other men's ideas, to express gratitude for every
bit of bread he eats, constantly flogged, going about
giving lessons in worn boots, fighting with other boys,
torturing animals, fond of dining with rich relatives,
acting the hypocrite before God and men, for.no other
reason than consciousness of his own insignificance. Go
on' to describe how this young man squeezed the slave
in him out of his system drop by drop, till one fine
morning he wakes up and discovers there is no more
slavish blood coursing through his veins it is all real
human blood."
He was nineteen when he first arrived in Moscow and
became a student at the Medical Faculty of the University
city; and because he found the family in far worse cir¬
cumstances than he expected, he cast about for a means
of earning money to support them while continuing his
studies. His choice fell more or less by chance upon
writing. From Taganrog he had sent his brother,
Alexander, a home-made weekly news sheet which he
called "the Stammerer". This aped the low-grade comic
news sheet which was fashionable in Moscow at the time.
Alexander had already managed to place some of this
material in the Moscow papers, which he worked for, and
Chekhov now simply enlarged this activity. He adopted
a series of nicknames, amongst them that of Antoshe
Chekhonte. So, while working at the Medical School, he
poured out an endless stream of jokes, captions, sketches,
social gossip and even dramatic criticism for the miserable
pay these papers offered him.
Another writer of his time, Bunin, has described these
inauspicious beginnings of Chekhov as a writer...
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
A DAY WITH
TOLSTOY
One day In 1901, Chekhov, who
had taken up residence at Yalta on
the Black Sea on the orders of his
doctors, went to visit Leo Tolstoy
who was also living in the Crimea.
As they sat talking on the verandah
of Tolstoy's villa, they were photo¬
graphed (right) by Tolstoy's wife.
Chekhov was a keen admirer of his
great contemporary whose works, he
said, had influenced his own writing.
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
"He began his work in the midst of a large family,
suffering poverty all through his youth, and he not only
worked for the most wretched pay, but in an environment
which might have damped the most ardent inspiration
in a tiny apartment, amidst hubbub and loud talk, often
sitting at the end of the table around which were gathered
not only the entire family but a number of student
boarders. Even later he endured a long period of want.
But no one ever heard him rail against his fate, and this
not because his standards were low although leading a
life of rare and lofty simplicity, he nevertheless detested
bleakness and drabness."
Chekhov gave no serious attention to his writing at this
time. He regarded medicine as his vocation and writing
as merely hackwork. Even later, when success came to
him, he persisted in calling medicine his wife, and litera¬
ture merely his mistress. And success did come, slowly
and steadily. First one St. Petersburg editor, Leykin, then
another, Suvorin, of the conservative weekly "New Times",
offered him contracts. These contracts reduced the finan¬
cial pressure of supporting his family and allowed him
to expand from 80 to 150 lines per story.
In 1884 he qualified as a doctor. Though he never
practised medicine regularly, he did work in Moscow and
in country hospitals. He drew heavily for his characters,
both from the sophisticated Moscow artists and intelli¬
gentsia and the country peasants. But even with his
growing fame, he still regarded literature as the lesser of
his occupations, until in 1886 the appearance of a story of
his called "The Gamekeeper" provoked an older, and much
respected writer, Grigorovitch, to write congratulating and
advising him to respect and husband a talent as great
as his.
Chekhov was thunderstruck: "If I do have a gift to be
respected, I must confess that I have hitherto not given
it any respect. I felt I had some talent but had fallen
into the habit of considering it trifling. Hitherto my atti¬
tude towards all my literary work has been extremely fri¬
volous, negligent and casual. I don't recall a single story
upon which I have spent more than 24 hours. I wrote
"The Gamekeeper", which you liked, in a bath-house.
I have composed my stories as reporters write their
accounts of fires, mechanically, half consciously, with no
thought for their readers or themselves.
"I am going to stop doing work that must be done in a
hurry, but not just yet. There is no possibility of my
getting out of the routine I have been following. I don't
mind going hungry I've already experienced this but
there is the family to be thought of. I give to writing my
leisure hours two or three during the day and a small
A VISIT FROM
GORKY
Shortly after he went to live at
Yalta in I 899, Chekhov wrote to his
friend, Maxim Gorky, asking him
to come and stay with him. A few
months later Gorky arrived in the
Crimea and was photographed with
his host. The two were regular
correspondents and Gorky made
a point of sending a copy of each of
his works to Chekhov as soon as
it came off the printing press.
In 1900 Chekhov was elected an
honorary fellow of the Academy of
Science, but resigned when the
election of Gorky to the Academy
was cancelled by the Government.
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
CONT'D ON PAGE I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
CHEKHOV (Continued)
x
	
f
¿**y* 4
^*W¿-<"
(
1
1
r
it
r
<rri^^kJ£~£ A. V-^
< *«*
^ t^y A -**;»*
rV.fcifJT
Jf «k. «>>
o**%->. ^»J
¿«W*«'* (
l>0mmm*f*'*~- 1
I
Ctf. .:_.	:	 	:			;	:	-^l	
Photos taken from "Chekhov and the Theatre", Moscow, I 9
TRUE TO LIFE. The theatre of Chekhov's day was traditionally a melodramatic affair with stock, heroic characters. Chekhov
wished to "de-theatricalize" it; he wanted to reveal the lives of ordinary people, to make a dramatic play of'character rather
than plot. He found the formula he was seeking when he wrote "The Seagull" in 1895. Produced in St. Petersburg, it was
a disastrous failure neither actors nor public could understand this new sort of play. In 1 898 it was revived by a new thea¬
tre now famous Moscow Art Theatrewhich was just struggling into existence under Nemirovich Danchenkp*end Stanis¬
lavsky. This time its success saved both play and theatre. The Moscow Art Theatre still bears the emblem of a seagull
on its curtain. Photos show (top) members of the Moscow Art Theatre listening to Chekhov reading "The Seagull" in 1 898 ;
(bottom) the company in I 900 at Chekhov's home in the Crimea, where they performed "The Seagull" and "Uncle Vanya".
8
54
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Flickering
flames
of social
protest
After the success of "The
Seagull", Chekhov's con¬
nexion with the Moscow Art
Theatre became very close
Indeed. Three of his great¬
est works"Uncle Vanya",
"The Three Sisters" and
"The Cherry Orchard"
were produced there bet¬
ween 1899 and 1904. Pho¬
tos show scenes and cha¬
racters from present day
productions of these works
by the Moscow Art Theatre.
Right and below, "The Three
Sisters" in which the small
sparks of social protest
which had been discerned
in earlier works now seemed
to blaze up more fiercely
and openly. The play had
its opening during a period
of social unrest which was
soon to explode In the revo¬
lution of 1905. Right (above)
Fers, the aged servant In
"The Cherry Orchard", who
symbolizes the old order;
(below) Astrov, the country
doctor In "Uncle Vanya".
Chekhov expressed many of
his own ideas through the
character of Doctor Astrov.
Official Soviet photos
The . Unesco Courier. January 1960
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
CHEKHOV
(Continued from page 7)
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
'The Seagull' saves a theatre
part of the night. In the summer, when I have more
spare time and living costs are lower, I shall take up
serious work..."
And take up serious work he did. Antoshe Chekhonte
disappeared and from then on Chekhov published under
his own name. He slowed down the phenomenal output
of his stories from an average of a hundred stories a year
to only a score or so. Usually they deal with one main cha¬
racter surrounded by vaguer ones and they recount not
so much a story, as a slice of life. At first glance they
seem to be written haphazardly, but so brilliant is their
construction in fact that their apparent formlessness is
impossible to copy, as many of his imitators have found.
The writer Maxim Gorki, whom Chekhov encouraged
from the beginning of his career and who became his
great friend in Yalta towards the end of his life, wrote
to another colleague, Andreev: "Learn compactness and
economy of expression from Chekhov, but God prevent
you from imitating his language it is inimitable and
you'll only be spoiled if you copy it it is like a beauty who
is passionless and gives herself to no one."
His last stories are classics in their own right. In them
are reflected his ruling creative principles of an unwaver¬
ing respect for truth and objectivity, and the sense of an
artist's responsibility which he once described himself:
"My holy of holies is the human body and brain, talent,
inspiration, love and personal freedom freedom from
force and lies whatever form the last two may take.
Had I been a great artist that is the line I should like to
have followed. I am not a liberal, or a conservative or an
evolutionist or a monk. I should like to be a free artist,
that's all. I hate violence and lies of any kind. Pha-
riseeism, stupidity and licence are to be found not only
in middle class homes and police stations. I see them in
science, in literature and among young people.
"It seems to me that the writer of fiction should not
try to be the judge of his characters and their conver¬
sations, but only an unbiased witness. An artist must
judge only of what he understands. He observes, selects,
guesses, combines. Only the stating, not the solution, of
a problem is compulsory to an artist. In "Anna Kare-
nina" and "Eugene Onyegin" not a single problem is
solved but they satisfy you completely because the prob¬
lems are correctly stated.
Plays as complex and
simple as real life
ççryi he writer is not a confectioner, a cosmetician or an
I entertainer. He is a man who has to fulfil a
contract with his conscience and his sense of
duty, and however much he may hate it, he must over¬
come his fastidiousness and soil his imagination with the
dirt of life. To a chemist the notion of dirt does not exist
.and the writer must be as objective as the chemist. He
must renounce every subjective attitude to life. You've
only to look at the writers whom we consider immortal or
even good the best of them are realists and depict life
as it is there is a conscious aim in every line they write
so that you feel, as well as depicting life as it is, they
depict life as it should be."
Life as it should be. This was Chekhov's cry. Nothing,
nothing deflected him from his purpose, which was to
point his optimistic belief in the future. He himself built
schools and hospitals in the village where he bought his
country house. His treatise on the savage penal settle¬
ments which he voluntarily visited on the desolate island
of Sakhalin helped to spark some prison reforms there.
But it was by his writing, and particularly in his last four
plays, the work of his maturity, that Chekhov carried out
his intention of pointing to a better life ahead by illustrat¬
ing the miseries of life around him.
It is no accident that Chekhov's maturest works were
his plays. He wrote for the theatre all his life; he publish¬
ed many popular one-act comedies in his early Moscow
days and as time went by he developed very definite ideas
about playwriting : "On the stage everything should be
as complex, and as simple, as real life.. People are having
dinner, and while they are having it, their future happi¬
ness may be decided or their lives shattered. The hero
and heroine of a play are always expected to be dramati¬
cally effective. But in life people don't shoot themselves
or hang themselves or fall in love or deliver themselves
of clever sayings every minute. They spend most of their
time eating, drinking, running after women or men, talk¬
ing nonsense. A play ought to be written in which the
people come and go, dine, talk of the weather or play
cards, not because the author wants it but because that is
what happens in real life. Life on the stage should be as
it really is and the people too should be as they are, not
stilted."
Unfounded legend of
Chekhov's melancholy
The theatre in his day was traditionally a melodrama¬
tic affair with stock, heroic characters, full of action
and high-sounding phrases. Chekhov wanted to
change all this, to use the theatre for a different purpose.
He wanted to reveal the lives of ordinary people, to make
a dramatic play of character rather than plot. He found
the formula he was seeking when he wrote "The Seagull"
in 1895. This was the first play in which he established his
own distinctive style of psychological realism. Its first
presentation in 1896 was unsuitably cast and it was a
disastrous failure neither actors nor public could under¬
stand this new sort of play, where they were shown the
complicated relationships and states of mind of a set of
characters to whom nothing in particular seemed to
happen.
The failure of the play deeply affected Chekhov's
weakening health and he returned to Yalta where he had
been living for some time on the advice of his doctors.
It was only with great difficulty that he was persuaded to
allow "The Seagull" to be done again by another, new
theatre which was just struggling into existence in
Moscow. This was the now famous Moscow Arts Theatre
under Nemirovich Danchenko and Stanislavsky. These
two men had the idea of bringing much of the same sort
of realism into theatrical production as Chekhov had
wanted to bring into playwriting, and they chose his
"Seagull" to be part of the first season.
The public were no more ready for this new kind of play
presentation than they had been for the first production
of "The Seagull", and the Moscow Arts Theatre looked as
though it was going to fail at its outset until Stanislavsky's
production of "The Seagull" in 1898 saved both play and
theatre. To this day the Moscow Arts Theatre bears the
emblem of a seagull on its curtain and ranks Chekhov
amongst its patron authors. AH his three major remain¬
ing plays, "Uncle Vanya", "'The Three Sisters" and "The
Cherry Orchard", were presented by Stanislavsky with
great artistic and commercial success.
The productions were all marked by argument
and discussion. This Was true for "The Cherry Orchard"
which Stanislavsky persisted in treating with melancholy
although Chekhov himself wanted it to be more optimistic
in tone.
It was largely out of such disagreements and Stanis¬
lavsky's establishment of his interpretation of the plays
that Chekhov's legend of melancholy was born. Stanis¬
lavsky's low-key interpretation need not obscure the fact
that Chekhov's inspiration was a positive one, as he him¬
self stated once when he was talking to the theatre critic,
Tikhonov: "You tell me that people cry at my plays. I've
heard others say the same. But that wasn't why I wrote
them. All I wanted was to say honestly to people: 'Have
a look at yourselves and see how bad and dreary your
lives are'. The important thing is that people should
realize that, for when they do, they will certainly create
another and better life for themselves. I won't live to see
it, but I know, that it will be quite different, quite unlike
our present life."
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
CHEKHOV (Continued)
HIS THREE IDEATS:
TRUTH, INTEGRITY
HUMAN DIGNITY
JOURNEY TO SAKHALIN
(Continued)
The peculiar and unique distinction of Chekhov's plays
is the style, the way in which they were written. Like his
stories, they seem haphazard. When the curtain goes up
on a Chekhov play one is not aware of watching a set of
people detached from one's own life, one simply feels that
one has been able to become an extension of their lives.
His influence as a writer on the theatre today lies to a
great extent in the important place he takes in that rea¬
listic theatrical movement which started in Europe
towards the middle of the nineteenth century, and whose
effects can still be felt today. As soon as his works were
published outside Russia, they were avidly read and much
admired. The Irish playwright, George Bernard Shaw,
emulated his style deliberately in his play "Heartbreak
House", though he intellectualized the characters in it
instead of keeping them the essentially human beings
that Chekhov always created.
Between the plays of another Irishman, Synge, and
Chekhov's there is a similarity of inspiration, though this
was not deliberate. On the American school of playwrit¬
ing of the 1920's Chekhov's influence can be seen in
writers like Sherwood Anderson and Saroyan and in con¬
temporary writers of the Tennessee Williams' school. But
perhaps Chekhov's strongest influence on the theatre
today grew not out of his writing as such, but out of the
method of presentation which his plays inspired the
Moscow Arts to give them, a reforming ideal and preoccu¬
pation with the souls of their characters rather than plot.
Strong impact on
writers in the West
As a writer outside the theatre Chekhov's influence on
those who read him in the West was considerable,
and more direct. After Guy de Maupassant he came
to be recognized as the master of the short story. Writers
as varied in nationality and intention as Katherine Mans¬
field or Virginia Woolf, James Joyce, Ernest Hemingway,
William Faulkner, and Thomas Mann, who describes Chek¬
hov's work as that of "genius in a nutshell"all these
have written and spoken of the effect upon them of this
gentle, compassionate Russian.
In 1904, Chekhov Went to Badenweiler in Germany for
the sake of his rapidly failing health. With him went
Olga, his wife, a famed actress in Russia, who has left a
record of that last trip: "...Anton Pavlovich took his
departure for another world quietly and calmly. Early in
the night he woke up and asked me for the first time in
his life to send for the doctor. I remember one ghastly
moment of bewilderment the sensation of the nearness
of hundreds of people in the great, sleeping hotel, and
at the same time the feeling of my own utter loneliness
and helplessness..."
"The doctor came in and told me to give him cham¬
pagne. Anton Pavlovich sat up and said to the doctor,
very loudly and meaningly, in German, a language which
he knew very little: Teh sterbe'. Then he picked up the
glass, turned his face towards me, gave his wonderful
smile and said T haven't drunk champagne for a long
time...', drained the glass, lay quietly on his left side and
very soon fell silent for ever... And the terrible quiet of
the night was only broken by the violent flutterings of a
huge black moth, which kept knocking itself painfully
against the lighted electric lamps, and hurling itself about
the room..."
And so Chekhov died. The dignity of human beings,
the integrity of the artist, truththese were the ideals by
which Chekhov lived and by which he Would have wished
to be remembered.
12
IN THE STEPS OF
ANTON CHEKHOV
A major event in Anton Chekhov's life was the visit he made to the
convict island of Sakhalin, off the Siberian coast and to the north of
Japan. Not only did it give him material for two books, "The Island of
Sakhalin" and "Siberia", but it also helped him to mature as a writer
and did much to determine the trend of his future work. Chekhov
left Moscow in 1890 and after a long and difficult journey reached his
goal. He visited the prisons and entered the cellsdamp hovels
crawling with vermin where prisoners lay chained to planks. His
study of Sakhalin was thorough and objective and the precise and impar¬
tial book he wrote on his return caused such a stir that the Government
was forced to send out an investigating commission. (Photo, right,
brought back by Chekhov, shows convicts being put in chains.) Sixty-
eight years later, in the summer of 1958, Sergei Mikbailovich Chekhov,
an artist and the nephew of the great Russian writer, accompanied by
his son, Sergei, a student artist, covered in ten flying hours the 7,000
miles from Moscow to Sakhalin which it took Anton Chekhov three
months to reach, travelling by train, poste-chaise and boat. They
went there to complete aseries of pictures called "Chekhov Landmarks"
whose execution had already taken them to many other parts of Russia.
At Sakhalin they sketched and painted the places and things that Chekhov
had seen and written about. They found and drew (above) some of the
low, dark, hideous buildings which have still survived from those days.
And they also recorded the striking changes that have taken place
there with new towns and settlements springing up (below). They
found that the memory of Chekhov lives on in stories and legends,
in the names of towns and settlements and they met people who still
speak of the writer's self-sacrificing effort to ease the lot of the convicts.
Official Soviet documents
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
I III 	:*+-mm
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
-". r'*^: /*" ** "*
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
CHEKHOV-AN UNSURPASSED
MASTER OF THE SHORT STORY
as an unsurpassed master of the short story,
had to overcome innumerable difficulties in
his early years and to struggle against many
moribund traditions before he gained the
recognition of both readers and critics and
took his place in the world of great literature.
In his letters, Chekhov often alluded to these
difficulties and to his own genre that nobody would recog¬
nize. He had to wage a prolonged struggle to obtain
acceptance of this style. Nobody wanted to print his story
than a Sparrow's Beak", for example, and it
was returned to him contemptuously, but still he was not
discouraged.
Though Chekhov himself believed that everything he
had written would be forgotten in a few years, he never¬
theless realized that he was .breaking new paths in lit¬
erature: "Everything I have written will have been for¬
gotten in five or ten years; but the paths I have broken
will remain, whole and undamaged, and that is my contri¬
bution to literature."
Chekhov made innovations both in ideology and style.
"An author's originality is not only in his style but also
in his mode of thinking, in his convictions, etc.," he wrote
in 1887.
The artist, he believed, must have a new word to say, he
must find a new angle from which to look at the world,
at the life that surrounds him and the people he depicts,
and this means that he must also find a new way of
revealing these phenomena in his art, he must find a new
form for his works.
The Russian literature of the period immediatly pre-'
ceding Chekhov (the sixties and seventies of the last cen¬
tury) showed a great tendency to follow the lines of the
by Professor Maria Yelizarova
magazine essay; Chekhov endeavoured to re-establish the
short story in its own right. His short story is frequently
a "snapshot" photographed by a master; a sketch or draft
that has, nevertheless, crystallized into an integral,
finished product with its own specific rules of style.
Some of Chekhov's sketches, studies or portraits which
at first sight claim to do nothing more than play up some
curious incident in everyday life, depict some accidental
meeting or conversation, photograph some moment in the
lives of very ordinary people, suddenly and quite unexpec¬
tedly reveal a broad picture of Russian life to the reader.
Writers of world renown have spoken admiringly of
Chekhov's. ability to create an unforgettable story out of
simple, everyday material. The British writer, John
Galsworthy, said in 1918: "Chekhov's great success is in
his ability to make tranquillity exciting in the same way
as prairies or deserts excite those who see them for the
first time."
As early as the eighties, the formative period of
Chekhov's short story genre, he had already evolved a
clear-cut system of aesthetic views that enabled him to
give frequent advice and act as guide to other writers. In
1883, writing to his brother he said that it was not the
personal, the subjective that was important in literature,
but "Stress... that which is vital, that which is eternal,
which stimulates genuinely human and not petty feelings."
"To the people you must offer people and not yourself,"
said Chekhov in another letter.
He also spoke of his ideas on short story writing. "The
short story consists of a beginning and an end," he assert¬
ed, "and understatement is better than overstatement."
A writer should try to be clever, but should not be afraid
to write nonsense. "Only he who is not afraid to write
nonsense," he assures us, "'is a freethinker."
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
CHEKHOV (Continued)
'Brevity is the sister of talent'
At the time when he wrote his short stories Chekhov's
aesthetic ideal was brevity. "Brevity is the sister of
talent; talented writing is terse writing/" Chekhov said.
Chekhov's own writing in the 1880-1886 period Was a
brilliant realization of this ideal. He had no rivals in his
own sphere. Even such great masters of the short story
as Mérimée, Mark Twain, Turgènev and Maupassant could
not conceive of a story no more than one and a half pages,
a single page or even three-quarters of a page in length.
At times Chekhov's stories really did consist solely of a
"beginning and an end."
The civil servant Chervyakov, an official of the type
produced in countless numbers by the bureaucratic ma¬
chine of old Russia, one day sneezes on the bald head of
a general sitting in front of him in the theatre C'Death
of an Official"). He is seized with mortal terror. He must
apologize, he must explain to the general that it was not
his fault. The general's wrath will have terrible conse¬
quences for him, a petty clerk of no importance. He goes
again and again to apologize until the general, losing his
temper with him, drives him away. Chervyakov is beside
himself with horror, goes home... and dies.
Everything is there in this tragi-comic story of a civil
servant; it is brief, compressed to the limit, but nothing
can be added to it Chervyakov is a real-life type, a tre¬
mendous generalized character drawn full scale, life size.
Chekhov deliberately avoids giving an extensive, all-
round description of a character. He does not draw a por¬
trait, does not relate intimate details of his life and does
not give the reader his biography, his previous history.
One moment only out of a mass of vital facts and events
is seized upon and that moment is reproduced as a story.
The artist is not interested in anything that does not
bear on the episode the sneeze and the pseudoconflict
with the general everything else is outside the frame¬
work of his creative thought.
The image possesses a certain schematism, for it is sim¬
plified to the extreme. But this simplification is the deli¬
cate method of an artist, it is the principle underlying his
creation of a type. The figure of Chervyakov retains only
that which determines the very nature of the soul of offi¬
cialdom, a soul that has for ages been trained in unac¬
countable fear for its own fate, in submission to authority
and in absolute humility.
By exaggeration, amounting at times to hypertrophy of
the humility, fear and crushed spirit of the civil servant,
in places even by a caricature of it, Chekhov reveals in
him that which he himself so aptly defined in a single
phrase: "Russia is a land of officialdom."
A new outlook on the surrounding world compelled the
artist to make new demands of the short story and to
revalue many such concepts as "subject", '"character",
"event", etc.
Chekhov wittily ridiculed the old, generally accepted
principles of structure in story and descriptive writing
that had become established in literature. "The subject
must be new but there need not be any plot," he said.
Chekhov's parodies broke down old stereotyped methods
INCOMPARABLE STORYTELLER. It was only after 1886 that
Chekhov found the necessary leisure and independence to give full
expression to his imaginative experience and ideas in his stories. In
14
the. next few years he attained perfection in his style and produced a
series of masterpieces. Above, illustrations from current Russian
editions of Chekhov's stories. From left, "The House with the
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
courageously and purged literature of outmoded traditions.
In many respects Chekhov had learned from Turgenev,
had inherited much from him, but nevertheless he realized
that Turgenev's school of writing was a thing of the past.
"Descriptions of nature are good, but... I feel that we have
already outgrown that sort of description and need
something else."
And all Chekhov's creative writing showed what that
"something else" ¡was. His descriptions of nature are
devoid of floweriness, ornament and excesses; they are
severe, simple, artless and sometimes deliberately terse.
"The sun came up," "A drizzle of rain began," "The frogs
in the pond called to each other angrily, exerting them¬
selves, and you could even make out the words: 'And so
are you... And so are you' " "A rumble of thunder as though
someone were walking barefoot over an iron roof" and
these unbelievably simple, everyday words build up pic¬
tures that no reader is likely to forget.
Such stories as "Happiness," "Dreams," "Huntsmen," "In
the Shed," "Dead Body," "Sorrow," and others are amazing
in their simplicity and their powerful lyricism.
In "Happiness" there is no subject; action, as usually
understood, does not develop; nevertheless there is a
clearly discernible overgrowth of lyricism. Three people,
lost in the great open spaces of the steppe, ponder over
and speak of happiness can it be reached and how is
it to be ¡found?
"Happiness" is a popular local term for buried treasure
supposed to be hidden somewhere in the steppes. It is
quite obvious, however, that the story is not about buried
treasure but about human happiness in the fullest mean¬
ing of that word; it is elusive and fantastic, it is beyond
the reach of man, but he will never stop seeking it and
yearning for it...
Drawings by Kukryniksy
Maisonette", "Lady with the Dog", and "Grief". Drawings are joint
works of three artists who sign themselves "Kukryniksy", from the
first syllables of their names: Kuprianov, Krylov and Nikolai Sokolov.
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
While the characters are talking, the darkness of night is
gradually dispelled, the sky grows pale, the stars are ex¬
tinguished and suddenly, over the horizon, "the blood-red
sun makes its appearance surrounded by a light haze."
All nature smiles and flaunts her gay colours to welcome
the sun, and this picture of sunrise conquering the dark¬
ness of night seems to give the story an enthusiastic note,
confirming the legitimacy and reality of man's dream of
happiness...
Chekhov employs an endless variety of methods. His
ability to reveal the simplest and most ordinary things in
a new way is a great art and one that he mastered to
perfection. He compels us to see the world through the
eyes of Semushka the Fool, who was, in reality,.possessed
of the wisdom of a simple artless soul ("Dead Body"), or
through the eyes of a child who sees his environment
more perfectly and profoundly than adults who are bur¬
dened with petty cares and greedy calculations and are
strangers to real poetry C'Vanka," "Event," "The Run¬
away," "The Cook Gets Married," "Grisha", "Worldly Tri¬
fles," "Steppe," and other stories about children); or,
lastly, through the eyes of animals with their own specific
"philosophy" ("Kashtanka," "Whitebrow," "Boarders").
Outstanding in Chekhov's artistic method is his ability
to incorporate a grand picture of human life, intricate,
full of contradictions and drama, with all its manifold
entanglements, in a subject that is often extremely simple.
That is why his longer stories are accepted by readers in
all countries as a great genre that deals 'with life's most
complicated problems; you feel in them the movement
of the "human ocean" behind the life-stories of individual
characters.
In his longer stories Chekhov introduces us to charac¬
ters who are tormented by their search for truth, cha¬
racters filled with vague alarm and anticipation ('"The
Teacher of Literature," "The Duel," "My Life," "On Busi¬
ness," "Three Years," "The Bride" and others).
The uneasiness felt by the characters is passed on to
the reader. Chekhov accomplishes this by his original
manner of telling a tale that is outwardly calm but in¬
wardly always tense and disturbed. The reader is con¬
fronted with questions that cannot be avoided. Gorky
once called Chekhov's stories "a book that worries", preci¬
sely because of the way they trouble the conscience of the
reader by asking him, "Why have you lived your life?"
In an article entitled "Chekhov", Thomas Mann shows
with typical insight what it is in the Russian writer's
work that makes him kin to the best writers abroad.
He says that even today Chekhov has "brothers of the tor¬
mented soul" because the conditions of life "under which
there exists an impassable gulf between truth and reality
have still not been eradicated from society. These writers
are tormented by the knowledge of their inability to
answer the question, "What is to be done?' They are
unable to say what meaning their work has, but despite
this they go on working and they work to the very end."
Readers throughout the world are amazed at the power
and lyricism of Chekhov's writing, his ability to pose pre¬
cisely and sharply those questions that trouble people
everywhere, whatever their nationality or language.
They are equally astounded at the striking simplicity of
Chekhov's words and the meaningfulness that can be
understood by all. The decadents of Chekhov's time, both
in Russia and abroad, declared that the words available
to a writer were all worn out, they no longer expressed
anything and did not, therefore, possess the power to
create the tensest dramatic situations.
John Galsworthy spoke of the kinship of Chekhov's
manner of writing to that of authors in other lands:
"Throughout the past twenty years Chekhov has been the
strongest magnet for young writers in many countries."
The Danish writer Bang dedicated the Russian transla¬
tion of his novel "Without a Country", published in 1911,
to Chekhov. "I want this book to be dedicated to Anton
Chekhov," he wrote. "I dedicate it to the memory of one
for whom I feel a stronger love than for any other Russian
writer... He was connected with the deepest roots of the
people, he shared the sufferings of the people... He offered
the people the creature of his genius in which the heart of
the people themselves was beating... The grandeur of his
creative work was in its humanity... His soft voice was
heard far beyond the bounds of the Russian land."
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
PATAGONIA
PARADOX OF DESOLATION
HAND PROSPERITY
by B. Aubert de La Rue
7 here are places in the world whose
names set the imagination afire.
Among them are those at the
southernmost tip of Latin Amer¬
ica. Patagonia, the Strait of Ma¬
gellan, Tierra del Fuego, Cape
Horn all these conjure up a remote and desolate land
with a harsh, hostile climate; a land swept by ¡winds and
storms; a land of forbidding shores lashed by giant
breakers. This, undeniably, is the general run of weather
on this frontier of the inhabited world, Where swirling
waters have tossed many a ship on the rocky shores. Yet
this narrow extremity of the American continent, stret¬
ching down towards Antarctica, is not an utterly deso¬
late place, but abounds in natural beauties and resources.
Western Patagonia belongs to Chile which now has plans
for integrating the region's three hitherto isolated and
neglected provinces of Chiloé, Aysén and Magallanes, more
closely into the economic life of the nation. This
mountainous and maritime region is a kind of Norway of
the south where the mighty Andes and the Pacific Ocean
seem to intermingle as the coast of southern Chile breaks
up into a maze of islands.
It contrasts strongly with the eastern side, adjoining
the Argentine border, which comes into the Pampas belt
and comprises many plateaux and plains, culminating in
16
the flat or slightly undulating country on either side of
the Strait of Magellan.
Chilean Patagonia covers an area of some 96,000 square
miles, or roughly a third of the whole country, but only a
small percentage of Chile's population lives here (about
220,000 people out seven million). As a first step in their
plan of integration, the authorities in the Chilean capital,
Santiago, intend to carry out a vast survey of the southern
territories and to make a detailed inventory of the varied
natural resources of the area. This is a job calling for
more funds and technical personnel than Chile can
provide, and the government hopes that some help will
be forthcoming from the United Nations Special Fund for
Technical Assistance, and in particular from Unesco.
In appointing me to carry out a preliminary on-the-spot
survey and to report on the means for putting the main
project into operation, Unesco added a new region to the
many in which it has already operated.
Patagonia is situated at a latitude which, in the northern
hemisphere, offers an essentially temperature climate, a
latitude on which most of the great capital cities lie, yet
it has a cold climate characterized not so much by severe
winters as by the absence of summer heat. It has only
one town of any size, Punta Arenas. Other than this,
there are only small, isolated settlements, cattle-breeding
stations and scattered farms, separated by vast empty
stretches of country which is difficult to cross and still
often unknown territory.
Because of its immense icefields, this rugged region
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
Photos © Paul Almasy
cannot be linked by road with the rest of the country.
The air link from Santiago to Punta Arenas covers 20
degrees of latitude and takes just over five hours. The
flight is a remarkable experience. Chilean pilots have
every reason to consider the route one of the most
dangerous in the world, but to the passenger it offers a
fantastic panorama of volcanoes, lakes and fjords, wild
valleys, lush forests, jagged coastlines, snow-clad peaks
and glistening ice-fields.
Santiago in summer enjoys constantly fine, hot weather
and shimmers in a dazzling light. The last traces of snow
on the nearby Andes have melted away, leaving only a few
glaciers perched on peaks at altitudes of 16,000 to 20,000
feet and glistening in the sun. Taking off for Patagonia,
the plane climbs steeply over the vast patchwork of crops
in the irrigated fields of the Central Valley, bounded on
the Pacific side by the slopes of the coastal mountain
chain and on the East by the main mountain range.
Rising up on this side are the spectacular series of volcanic
peaks which have laid dormant with the exception of the
gently-smoking Viela Rica since the memorable eruptions
of 1932.
The aridity of central Chile soon gives place to a more
humid, verdant region dotted with rivers and lakes. This
is Chile's "Switzerland," the most attractive part of the
country. Here the climate is pleasantly cool and grassland
alternates with forests. It is an agricultural and cattle-
raising area, much frequented in summer by holiday-
makers.
Then, like a sentinel standing guard at the ramparts
of the grim wilderness of Patagonia, the cone-shaped
outline of Osorno with its snow-capped peak comes up on
the horizon. Beyond it are other famous mountains
Tronador, followed by the gaping crater of Calbuco.
Thus, after a two-hours' flight, the aircraft reaches
Puerto Montt. At this point the continent suddenly
breaks up and Patagonia begins. From here on, the
Central Valley, garden and granary of Chile, gives place
to a fantastic labyrinth of promontories and islands,
narrow channels and fjord-like inlets. It seems incredible
that ships on their way to the far-off Strait of Magellan
can manage to wend their way through this maze, beset
eus they are by violent currents, blinding rain and, as they
get ever further south, snow squalls. Navigation along
this coast is indeed a delicate and dangerous enterprise.
First of the endless chain of islands which run parallel
to the continent and extend down to Cape Horn, fringing
the coast for hundreds of miles, is Chiloé. It is
overpopulated and its people cling to the past, observing
archaic customs and traditions. Living in a few old-
fashioned townships or a multitude of tiny country
villages distinguished by picturesque wooden houses, the
Chilotes, a people of mixed Indian and Spanish blood, are
spreading to all parts of Patagonia and now form the
main element of its population.
In their home country their main occupations are
fishing, cattle-breeding and farming, but the archaic
methods they use give but poor results. Many of the
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
PATAGONIA (Continued)
Photos © Almasy, Paris
Sfij 9a ' i iXi- : \ ' m' "
»
wi 1
'MM
9kt*y<> ' aWEfS^W^ -
8i2*^J^k^3l
Br7^*ç-É^P^îl --wis « *$
« ' ^rvl P' e*K
Iki .riffi JPBBfcg"' <Bqpîa^E
01
P^Lmm ft - «kW
MmW ftP li
¿mm.
:. f'..:«riji^^^. j "' ip "i
**'.* : j
"-"r
2.Ä pO
©E.A ubert de la Rue
MOST SOUTHERL
EDGE OF AMERICA
Patagonia gets its name from
the Spanish word patagones
(big feet) for there is a
legend that the Indians who
once lived there were giants
with huge feet. Today
despite a century of immi¬
gration into the area the
population density of most
of Chilean Patagonia is less
than one person per square
mile. Some descendants of
the Indians have mingled .'*
with the immigrants and
have become lumbermen and
fishermen. Others (above
and left), continue to live
like their ancestors in shel¬
ters made of wood, brush
and tarpaulins. Among them
are the Yaghans, the south¬
ernmost people in the world,
now reduced to a handful
and living in the extreme
south of Tierra del Fuego.
Abundance of timber in the
region is shown by wooden .
houses of Fuerte Bulnes, a
village on the continent's tip.
.1
J
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. , January 1960
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
PATAGONIA (Continued)
DESOLATION
& PROSPERITY
(Continued from page 17)
Chilotes live poverty-stricken lives. Yet their island
enjoys a mild climate and is free from frost and snow.
Cereals ripen well there and the island is noted for its
potatoes. It is, in fact, from Chiloé rather than from the
high plateaux of Bolivia and Peru, that the first potatoes
are supposed to have come.
Today, the Chilotes have settled in most parts of
southern Chile. In the Chonos islands, where they have
become lumberjacks, they fell huge quantities of cyprus
trees and turn them into fencing posts most of which are
bought by Argentina and used to build sheep pens. Others
have set up colonies along the coasts and the more
protected valleys of the nearby mainland, and often live
nomad lives on the channels in search of the few remain¬
ing otters and seals which have survived the wholesale
slaughters of the past.
Still other Chilotes work for small fisheries, canning sea-
urchins, spider crabs and all kinds of shellfish, including
the mariscos, giant mussels which are also dried and
smoked. Countless heaps of shells marking former camp¬
ing sites along the coasts show that these mussels were a
staple food of the original Indian inhabitants of these
regions. Today mariscos are in great demand throughout
Chile. Chilotes are also employed as shepherds on all the
farms, and are regarded as good workers.
As the outlines of Chiloé become dim and blurred by
the fluffy cumulus clouds over the Pacific, the aircraft,
winging its way south, now flies over the startlingly
green western slopes of the Andes. The southern forests
which cover them are usually dripping with moisture for
here torrential rain falls on an average of 300 days each
year.
Senseless squandering of Nature's wealth
With its evergreen trees and its undergrowth of
. quila, a species of bamboo which forms impene¬
trable thickets, the forest has all the luxuriance
of a profusely growing tropical one. Beginning on the
coast, it can be seen extending unbroken along the
valleys and up the mountain sides.
Yet this fine, thick carpet of verdure is sometimes
scarred by dull streaks and patches of grey where forest
fires have left nothing but bare trunks, some still upright,
others strewn over the ground. Flying over Patagonia I
saw forest fires from Chiloé down almost to Cape Horn.
Most are started by isolated farmers who find flames an
easier tool than the axe when they wish to clear land for
cultivation. Unfortunately they disregard the strong
winds which fan the flames and spread the flrei unchecked
over huge areas.
Hundreds of thousands of acres of forest have been
destroyed in this way during the past century of
settlement in Patagonia. The ostensible reason for the
fires is to open up more land for pasturing, but in fact
they are often started quite uselessly and at the risk of
setting off the deadly process of soil erosion. The
authorities are well aware of this danger and of the
senseless squandering of this source of natural wealth, but
so far no laws or regulations have put an effective stop
to the practice.
Beyond the grim, majestic Aysen fjord the character of
the landscape becomes far more harsh and severe. The
glaciers become larger and soon one is flying over a polar .
landscape which continues almost uninterruptedly as far
as Tierra del Fuego. Here, at an equivalent Southern
Hemisphere latitude to that of the European Alps, the
famous San Rafael glacier and many others run right
down to sea level, forming a patch of the fantastic blue
colour, which appears to be a peculiarity of the glaciers
of Patagonia.
Amid the dazzling snow-capped peaks and glaciers,
mighty granite needles stand out and two in particular,
Fitzroy and Cerro Paine, mark the end of the crossing
of the Great Cordillera and the beginning of the
Photos © E. Aubert de la Rue
1-2. LAST LARGE CITY, Punta Arenas, with a population of 50,000,
claims to be the southernmos city in the world. (Ushuaia, in the
Argentine part of Tierra del Fuego, is further south, but has only 7,000
inhabitants.) Situated on the Strait of Magellan, Punta Arenas
has a free port status and exports large quantities of wool (above).
3. LAST GROUND. Among the tufted grasses of Diego Ramirez
islandlast terrain of Patagoniaa colony of albatrosses installed in
its nesting quarters. Albatrosses usually lay their single eggs on the
bare ground. These birds in rainy Patagonia have learned to keep
their eggs dry by building raised mounds of mud as nesting places.
4. LAST KITCHEN GARDEN. In this vegetable patch at Puerto
Williams on Navarino island, lettuce and potatoes grow well as long as
they are protected by wooden screens from the sweeping westerly
winds. Puerto Williams is the world's most southerly established village.
5. LAST FLOWERS. Primroses growing on Lennox Island, near to
Cape Horn. The nearest terrain to the south of here is the vast
icy wasteland of Antarctica with its scientific observation stations.
20 CONT'D ON PAGE 22
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
PATAGONIA (Continued)
LAND OF FIRE
LAND OF ICE
Explorers, navigators and scientists
are remembered In the names given
to many places on the southernmost
part of the American continent in and
around Tierra del Fuego (The Land of
Fire). Exploits of Ferdinand Magellan,
the Portuguese navigator and the first
European to sail these waters, are
commemorated In monument (right) at
Punta Arenas, capital of province of
Magallanes, also named, together with
Magellan Strait, for this explorer.
Below, Cape Horn, given its name in
1616 by William Schouten, a Dutch
sailor, for his native town of Hoorn.
Photographed on a calm, sunny day,
the towering cliffs seem to belie their
sinister reputation as the scene of so
many shipwrecks. Far right, the Italia
glacier, one of several which appear to
hurl themselves down from the Darwin
Cordillera (named for the great scien¬
tist) and crash Into the Beagle Channel,
which recalls the voyage of H.M.S.
Beagle during which Darwin gathered
the material on which he based his
"Origin of Species". The centenary
of Its publication and the I 50th anni¬
versary of Darwin's birth which coin¬
cided last year were marked by celebra¬
tions with which Unesco was associated.
Almasy, Paris
Photos © E. Aubert de la Rue
dun-coloured steppes extending as far as the eye can see
to the Strait of Magellan and beyond. . .
Now the flight is almost ended and as the plane loses
height it is possible to see details of the pampas below,
squared off into enclosures containing thousands of sheep
looking from above for all the World like ants' eggs.
There are between two and three million sheep in Chilean
Patagonia and the breeding industry which supplies wool
and frozen meat for export is still the main economic
resource of the southern provinces. The white-walled
buildings of the sheep farms, protected against the
perpetual westerly winds by screens of trees or planks,
are connected by dusty tracks with Punta Arenas which
now appears in the distance as a large red patch lying
at the foot of mountains still decked with snow. A final
circuit over the Strait of Magellan, broad at this point and
flowing between foam-flecked shores, and the aircraft
lands on the airfield of Chabunco.
After the wild solitudes of the Patagonian Andes, it is
astonishing to find a modern city the size of Punta
Arenas so far from civilization. Much changed within the
past few years and still developing, Punta Arenas has a
population of close on 50,000. Some of its prosperity is
due to the discovery of oil in nearby Tierra del Fuego
which has brought an influx of technicians.
The city, capital of the province of Magallanes, also
enjoys the status of a free port. This right was granted
in recent years so as to aid the economic development of
the southern provinces. It allows the Importation, duty
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
free, of ail kinds of foreign goods that are inexistent or
prohibitively expensive in the rest of the country, where
their importation is strictly controlled. But customs
officials can sometimes be tolerant, and more and more
people find it worth while to come all the way from
Santiago to do their shopping in Punta Arenas.
The town manages somehow to remind one both of
Canada and Central Europe because many of the houses
are built of wood though this practice is now dying out
and many of the inhabitants came originally from
Yugoslavia, drawn here at the end of the last century by
the discovery of gold in Tierra del Fuego. Descendants of
these people now run most of the local trade and
Dalmatian and Croatian names abound in all the streets.
Punta Arenas lays claim to several distinctions in¬
cluding that of being the cleanest and best-kept town in
Chile and the one with the highest living standards. It
also boasts of being the capital of the province with the
smallest proportion of illiterates and, lastly, of being the
southernmost town in the world. This it may well have
been at one time, but its position has now been usurped
by Ushuaia, a rapidly growing town in the Argentine
part of Tierra del Fuego, which already has 7,000 inhabi¬
tants. In Puerto Williams, however, Chile can still boast
of having the most southerly established village in the
world. Round about, there are still a few cattle farms
and also the tiny Mejillones reserve where some twenty
to* thirty Yaghans, the last survivors of the Fuegians, live
to . this day. (For the story of what happened to many of
the Indians see The Unesco Courier, issue N° 8-9, 1954.)
From Puerto Williams on Navarino Island on the
farthest tip of Chile Where aeroplanes can land I
boarded a Chilian naval vessel which took me through
the Beagle Channel to the surrounding islands and round
the ill-famed Cape Horn. On the beautiful calm day
when I saw it it had nothing sinister about it whatever.
This trip around the channels of Patagonia was fol¬
lowed by long excursions on foot through the forests of
antarctic beech which clothe the mountains of Navarino
Island, where the only living things one meets are flights
of parrots with their shrill calls and herds of the graceful
guanacos which inhabit these solitary parts.
I also went to look at the glaciers which seem to hurl
themselves down from the heights of the Darwin Cordil¬
lera and then crash into the Beagle Channel. Travelling
by lorry along the roads and tracks of Tierra del Fuego,
where hundreds of wild geese take flight as one appro¬
aches, I visited several ranches, the Sombrero oilfields and
also the fishing-grounds off Useless Bay.
Back again on the mainland, I crossed the particularly
arid steppe country the home of sheep and wild ostriches
which borders the Strait of Magellan on the Atlantic'
side. Further north, I visited several lignite mines.
Today these are worked on a scale sufficient to meet local
needs only, through the area between Punta Arenas and
Puerto Natales has enormous deposits of this mineral.
New treks on foot across the pampas brought me to the
CONT'D ON PAGE 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
PATAGONIA (Continued)
E. Aubert de la Rue
LASHED BY WILD WINDS
With its grey skies, heavy rains
and tempestuous winds, Patagonia
is . a country of wild appearance,
The beech tree (above) on Navarino
island, its upper trunk blown into
an almost horizontal position, has
become a weathervane of nature.
Here, the great west winds blow
with gale force almost every day.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January I960
At an altitude of
1,500 feet the blan¬
ket of forest is so
exposed to the fu rious
westerly winds that
trunks become twis¬
ted and tormented
into a tangle through
which it is almost
Impossible to pass.
© E. Aubert de la Rue
Children at Punta
Arenas play among
the bare timbers of
a wrecked vessel.
Patagonia Is one of
the stormiest regions
on earth, and Its
swirling waters have
tossed many an un¬
lucky ship to disaster
on the rocky shores.
© Almasy, Paris
beauties of the Cerro Paine region, whose mountain tor¬
rents, like many of the icy streams in the south, abound
in salmon.
Crossing into another province, I visited the island of
Chiloé where some of the old-established settlements
irresistibly recall parts of Canada. If the resources of
the "Big Island" as the local people call it its forests,
farms and the sea around it were properly exploited, it
should be possible to raise the present low living standards
of the people.
In the few summer months I spent travelling all over
Chilian Patagonia, using every kind of transport, I was
able to see the striking contrasts offered by this country.
Calm sunny days, sometimes even hot ones, alternated
with spells of icy rain, snow-squalls and hurricanes.
This preliminary survey, including as it did the possi¬
bility of sounding out and listening to local viewpoints,
was an invaluable first step to working out a programme
of research along the lines envisaged by the Chilean
Government. Great hopes are placed on the rational
exploitation of the resources of its southern provinces.
These resources are complex, bearing on such varying
activities as cattle-breeding and agriculture, lumbering
and marine biology (to aid the development of the fishing
industry) and tourist travel for which the grandeur and
beauty of certain areas would be an undeniable attraction.
Of considerable importance, too, are the prospection for
mineral deposits and the use of Patagonia's widespread
potential hydro-electric resourcesvital elements in the
industrialization of some sectors of the country's economy.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
o,
Aj
k*^ &
THE WORLD'S KNOWLEDGE
^ T
H INSIDE A CIGAR BOX
WKËBBÊÊÊÈ
fr
\í
>.
A% í>£í ..¿¿i JkM% '
r .iL-/ wfáHE km'
fcy Ritchie Calder
'--vilLU
Ehen, in 1801, Jacquard invented a loom, in
which a series of punch cards enabled a machine
to weave figured fabrics which had once de¬
pended on the art and skills of hand-weavers, he
nearly lost his life in the riots which followed.
In Britain, when Kay devised the flying shuttle,
the weavers destroyed his house. When Ark-
wright, Hargreaves and Crompton further mechanized
weaving, the workers rose and burned the factories. The.
poet, Lord Byron, intervened impassionedly on behalf of
the despairing worker, whose livelihood was being taken
from them by the machines.
Yet these machines eventually meant work for millions,
cheaper goods for the people, and economic prosperity.
Until about fifteen years ago, the great engineering
advances were in machines to relieve men of muscle drud¬
gery. What this means might be illustrated by the fact
that the turbines of an ocean liner of today represent the
muscle-efforts of three million galley slaves, pulling on
oars. And the average modern worker in an up-to-date
factory can, with the flick or a switch, have at his disposal
work-power equivalent to a hundred human slaves.
But, in the past dozen years or so, new types of machines
have come into existence which are causing uneasiness not
only among workers who see "automation" replacing their
skills but also among philosophers. The machines are
called Electronic Computers and the name suggests what
they were originally, just calculating machines, or glorified
electrical versions of the "bead-frames" on which children
26
learn to count. The name now is quite misleading because
these machines do not just do arithmetic. They imitate
many of the functions of the human brain and control
and direct other machines which replace, not only muscle
effort, but the human senses.
At the International Conference on Information Proces¬
sing, organised by Unesco in Paris (June 15-20
1959), the two thousand scientists and engineers who
attended were seriously discussing machines which would
memorise all the knowledge in the world and in which the
equivalent of an individual human memory could be
reproduced on a piece of glass, 5" by 6" the size of
a photographic plate. They were describing machines
which can produce business decisions and be "taught" to
think for themselves and to form valued judgments. As
Dr. Edward Teller, of California University, pointed out,
once a machine can form value judgments, it is conceivable
that it will develop emotions.
DWENTY years ago, all this was impossible.
Even electronic calculations seemed impracti¬
cable. Three hundred years ago, the French
mathematician Blaise Pascal invented a
mechanical calculating machine. Over a hun¬
dred years ago, Charles Babbage, an English
mathematician, worked out a machine which
could do mathematical calculations and analyses on a
punch card system like that which Jacquard employed in
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. January 1960
Photos IBM, Paris
POWERFUL AND RAPID calculation instrument, this electronic
data processing machine is usually used tosolvescientificand engineer¬
ing problems. It is really a set of interconnected machines composed
of an input unit, processing unit and output units. From the console,
the operator, can supervise the performance of millions of data-
processing steps by the units. Opposite page, part of a plate of
magnetic core storage (the "memory" unit) composed of thousands
of tiny doughnut-shaped ferro-magnetic rings threaded on wire.
his loom. Cash-registers and mechanical comptometers,
hand-operated, were doing complicated calculations before
the Second World War. But the first of the electronic
computers began to function only twelve years ago.
Radio valves replaced the cogs of the mechanical compto¬
meters (or, more elementarily, the beads of the counting-
frame).
The early machines consisted of massive racks of radio
tubes and tangles of wires but they could do addition,
subtraction, multiplication and division and work out, in
split seconds, mathematical equations which would have
taken hours, or days, of pen-and-paper calculations.
Today, regardless of the number of digits in the sum a
computer can average ten thousand operations in a
second. The latest are a thousand times faster than those
of three years ago and a million times faster than those of
ten years ago. The only limit to their ultimate speeds is
the velocity of light which is 186,000 miles a second but
the distances the signals have to travel in a computer are
not reckoned in miles but in fractions of millionths of an
inch. So that "the Computer People" can talk glibly of
getting results in hundreths of millionths of a second.
The machines, in terms of work-capacity are getting
bigger and bigger but the components are getting smaller
and smaller. Instead of having radio valves they are being
constructed with transistors no bigger than grains of rice.
But even that is gigantic compared with recent advances.
In what is called the "cryotron", the cells which store
information are a 250th of a millionth of an inch in dia¬
meter. The circuits consists of "wires" of similar
dimensions a spider's web, which only an ultra-powerful
microscope can see. These circuits and '"cells" are print¬
ed on glass and a temperature of 270 degrees below zero
is maintained by "deep-freezing" the units in liquid hydro¬
gen. At that temperature certain metals offer no resis¬
tance to the currents of electricity which can therefore go
on flowing, at the speed of light, indefinitely and without
loss of signal-strength.
Ehen one gets down to those dimensions it will
be possible to store all the information of all
the books of all the libraries of all the world
in a space no bigger than a cigar-box.
The problem then is how to get it out.
Humans are forgetful when they cannot recall
information which is in their memory. Too so,
the problem in the electronic brains is how to retrieve it,
when, and in what form, one wants it. As one expert at
the conference put it "An electronic computer is a bank
in which information is deposited, put away in a vault,
and eventually paid out."
To "pay in" the information the computer expert has
it typed out as punch-holes in a paper tape. And on the
tape also he gives instructions as to how it is to be used.
This is called "programming". The information is then
recorded on a magnetic memory by the computer. It will
pay it out exactly as instructed by the programmer. It will
transfer its information again to a punched tape which will
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE WORLD'S
KNOWLEDGE
(Continued)
automatically operate a typewriter, so that the result is
readable.
The computer began as a fast way of doing arithmetic
but any logical process can be converted into numbers and
thus into a code by which all kinds of information can be
stored or processes executed.
For example, a computer can be put in charge of a ma¬
chine Which is working on some large and complicated
piece of machine cutting like carving, to precisions of
thousandths of an inch a huge block of metal into the solid
and complex shapes of a supersonic aircraft, or a rocket.
The computer will help to work out the specifications and
the mathematical contours of the part. The programmers
will then feed into it the instructions which it has, itself,
helped to produce and it will then control the automatic
machine-tools which will cut the metal in three dimensions
simultaneously.
With its electronic allies, like photoelectric eyes; the
Merton grating (which gives a machine the sense of touch
and greater accuracy than any skilled craftsman); and the
servo-motors which manipulate parts (with a '"feed-back"
like a mechanized nervous-system) the computer can carry
out, if need be, any job a human operator can do. In
other words, it can work out ¡the details of a computer
more advanced than itself and then control the machines
to make those parts and (eventually, if not yet) assemble
them. It could, in fact, reproduce itself breed other
computers.
NTENSiVE work by linguists, mathematicians
and engineers, is going on all over the world
to secure mechanical translation of languages
from Russian into English, Japanese into
French and so on; The progress is slow
because one does not just exchange words;
there is the grammar and structure of senten¬
ces and idioms which are peculiar to each language. But
in translation of scientific works, articles have been trans¬
ferred from one language to another in terms which are
quite comprehensible to experts in the branch of science
concerned. Success has already been achieved in the
translation of work into the language of the blind, Braille.
What the experts are now seeking is "pattern identifica¬
tion" which means that the computers, instead of having
to be fed with punched tape, would be able to read directly
from a printed page or identify the sound-pattern of the
spoken word and then to translate into the other .language.
That is still some years off.
But the scientists and engineers have already given to
the computer enough human attributes to worry (many
people. The president of the Paris : Conference,
Dr. Howard Aiken, of Harvard University, wanted to reas¬
sure them. He said that, while they must always bear in
mind their social responsibilities, the scientists and engi¬
neers could feel that, so far from making men the slaves
of the machines, the machines were liberating them from
slaving at tasks that were drudgery, making possible a
higher standard of life for everyone, and leaving people
free for creative work.
28" -
To store information It receives the
electronic data-processing machine on
the previous page uses plates made
up of tiny rings (shown here In com¬
parison to a matchbox). One memory
unit is composed of 36 plates made
up of 4,096 rings each. The core
storage Is the most powerful and the
fastest working memory of the machine.
IBM, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
L etters to the Editor
THE AIR WE BREATHE
Sir,
I should like to bring to your atten¬
tion a rather important error which
affects two statements in your March
issue on Air Pollution. Your introduc¬
tory article states: "Each adult needs
1 cubic metre of air, i.e. 1 kg..."
If we take it that a man breathes on
the average 16 times a minute (I litre of
air per breath) he breathes in 11,520 li¬
tres a day. Expressed in weight (1 litre
of air at normal atmospheric pressure
and 0 degree C. weighs 1 gr. 293) this
gives 15 kgs. in round figures.
Thus 1 m" and 1 kg. 5 indicated in
your article should read 11 m1 520 and
15 kgs.
a second article by Professor A.I.
Haagen-Smit (whom I admire for his
many works on questions of pollution)
it is stated: "The air we breathe is a part
of our diet, and there is every reason to
be as particular about the quality of the
air as we are about our food. The
amount of air we inhale per day is in
the order of 30 cubic feet, weighing
about three pounds. An air pollutant at
a concentration of only one part in a
million adds one milligramme to our
daily diet..."
By reason of the previous calculation
these indicated quantities should be mul¬
tiplied 11 to 12 times and thus the
example of the toxic substance with a'
millionth-part concentration in the air
breathed becomes increased to a daily
dose of 11 to 12 milligrammes instead
of 1 milligramme. You must agree that
there is all the more reason to make
these corrections since they considerably
strengthen the viewpoints expressed.
JJ. Laffargue
National Council Against Air Pollution
Uccle-Iez-Brussels, Belgium
DON'T HIT HIM-TELL HIM
Sir,
It was late afternoon and I hailed a
.cab. "Lady what do you think of the
U.N.?" asked the cab driver. "I'm in
no mood for an argument", I answered,
"I just did a long day's work." "No, no
kidding, I'm not going to argue" said
the talkative guide, "I really want to
know. I don't think the U.N. is any
good. They don't do nothing."
"Are you willing' to listen?", I asked.
He said he was and this is what I told
him:
I was a nursery teacher. The children
used to come into school in the beginning
of the school year and if they wanted
a toy which another child had, they
would hit the child in order to get it.
We used to say to the children, "Don't
hit him; tell him."
Each day for the whole year we said:
"Don't hit him, tell him." At first the
children paid no attention. They would
strike out with a block or shovel.
After a few months of patient repetition
of our favourite phrase, the children
began to say, "Don't hit him; tell him."
But they still continued to hit. About
the eighth or ninth month, one could see
the change take place. The children not
only verbalized but they actually did
"Tell him". You could often hear them
saying "I want that. Give me that."
And so that is what the United Nations
is for, young man, It's to teach the
world "Don't hit him, tell him."
We arrived at my destination. The
taximan got out and opened the cab
door for me. "No kidding," he said,
"I never understood before."
Esther Schattman
New York
TRUE WAY TO PEACE
Sir,
There is an opinion frequently voiced
that in order to safeguard peace one
must resort to nuclear deterrents, and
that peace among men can be maintain¬
ed through superiority in the production
of the means of war. Are we not only
deceiving ourselves when we adopt so-
called "expedient" policies of imagined
"strength" which bring but fear and mis¬
trust to international life? We would
do well to remember in this connexion
E.B. White's remark that, "the bomb
has given us a few years of grace
without war, and now it offers us a
few milleniums of oblivion."
It is time that citizens all over the
world and particularly those of the
nuclear nations should begin to reflect
and resolve the dilemma in a moral and
humane way. In 1952, when the contro¬
versy on bacteriological warfare was
boiling, the Federation of American
Scientists denied the charges that bw
(Bacterial Warfare) weapons had been
used by the U.N. forces in Korea, and
put the issue squarely as follows: "The
question raised in the world's mind is
not so much whether we did use bw
in Korea but whether we are in fact
prepared and willing to use it in the
future." The question in the case of
nuclear warfare is the same. It is not
the question at to who might in future
become guilty of starting a nuclear
war: The responsibility and guilt for
this unimaginable holocaust lies right
now and here on the shoulders of every¬
one and every nation which produces
and possesses the bombs and which
conducts its policies accordingly. The
bombs and the missiles and the air bases
have become the challenge to our
conscience and to our sense of mercy.
There is an alternative way, a non¬
violent policy of reconciliation, of co¬
operation and mutual aid; it was prac¬
tised by men like Gandhi, and in more
recent years of Middle East conflict by
Ralph Bunche, and it was incorporated
in the U.S. Point Four programme not to
mention the projects carried out by non¬
governmental agencies. It is up to us
to take the initiative instead of waiting
for others to do better.
Herbert Jehle
Lincoln, Nebraska, U.S.A.
RIGHT TO PEACE & QUIET
Sir,
In a recent issue you published an
article concerned with the basic right to
listen (to news broadcasts, information
etc). I wish you would also devote an
article to the right. "not to hear", the
right to silence, to peace and quiet.
This is a right which is ignored or tram¬
pled on in our so-called civilized coun¬
tries.
J. J. Lonlan
Geneva, Switzerland
Sir,
Your issue on radio lacked one more
article subject: "the right not to listen."
It was bad enough when we had to
contend with echoing floorboards, walls
which let through every sound and the
neighbour who insists on listening to
opera on his radio with all his windows
open. Now we have the transistor ra¬
dio which means that any solitary and
peaceful spot can be spoiled by din.
The author of another of your articles
offered a radical answer to this wear
ear plugs. I for one refuse to adopt
this defeatist solution before even any
action has been taken against people
who have no thought for their neigh¬
bours. When shall we see an issue of
The Unesco Courier on the subject of
noise, or rather, of silence? -
Jean Delannoy
Biarritz, France
MENTAL ILL HEALTH
Sir,
In your special issue on the problems
of mental ill-héalth (May 1959) I fre¬
quently came across such terms as
"psychological", "psychiatric", "neuro¬
tic" etc., but nowhere did I find the
term "psychoanalysis". I am therefore
wondering if psychoanalysis is consid¬
ered as a therapeutic method that can
be used by psychiatrists.
G. Haine
Haiue-St-Paul, Belgium
Editor"s< note: Psychoanalysis is so
used in many European and American
countries. In certain others the Soviet
Union, for example it is not accepted
as a method of treating the mentally ill.
Sir,
I read the whole of your special issue
on mental illness with the greatest in¬
terest. But why is it that no publications,
medical or otherwise, speak of that other
great problem the mentally retarded;
and the possibility of a cure in such
cases ?
P. Simon
Caen, France
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
._ ,
.
MOBILE LIBRARY 'SETS UP SHOP' IN THE VILLAGE SQUARE.
CHILDREN MAKE EXCITING FINDS IN THEIR OWN SECTION.
MY library was dukedom large enough," says Pros¬
pero in Shakespeare's "The Tempest," and happy
is the modern man who is able to build up his
own library at home. But in the rural districts of Greece
where books are scarce and the means for establishing
permanent libraries scant, the weekly visits of Mrs. Stella
Peppa-Xephlouda with the Mobile Library is looked upon
as an important event in the life of every community.
The joys of literature and the benefits of education by
means of technical books are being brought to the doors
of the villagers in the Greek countryside.
The Mobile Library of the Ministry of Education today
possesses ten thousand books in Greek and other lan¬
guages and operates in a car donated by Unesco.
Soon it is anticipated there will be at least ten cars
and over a hundred thousand volumes. Everything must
have a beginning and in this case the beginning was the
book-lending centres in various country districts and the
activities of those great propagators of Greek cultural
development, the schoolteachers...
Photos K. Paphaélides © Elkin. Athens "Pictures from Greece" magazine
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
BOOKS EELS
A library comes to a Greek village
VILLAGE TEEN-AGERS IN PARTICULAR FLOCK TO SEEK INFORMATION ON EVERYTHING FROM COOKERY TO RADIO TECHNOLOGY.
If you happened to be in the picturesque little village
of Villia when the Mobile Library arrived, you would
see a constant procession of young and old returning
books and taking out new ones. And you would be aston¬
ished at the type of books that are frequently asked
for.
They are not novels, thrillers or romances as you might
expect. They are technical and agricultural books, books
on electrology, radio, technology, handicraft, handbooks
on child-care for mothers, and cookery or domestic
science books for young girls.
Six thousand five hundred people are at present regis¬
tered readers of the Mobile Library, which maintains a
total of seventy-eight book-lending centres in Central
Greece, Euboia and the Péloponnèse.
According to the programme drawn up by Mr. Kour-
noutos, Director of Art and Letters in the Ministry of
Education, the Mobile Library will gradually extend its
activities to the rest of the country. In addition, this
institution will serve as a kind of adviser in the founding
of local lending libraries. Such libraries are starting to
operate in Kiato in Corinthia and in Menidhi and Koropi
in Attica, and will refer for information and guidance to
the collection and catalogues of the Mobile Library.
In Polydroso there is already a local library possess¬
ing ten thousand volumes. While other villages are not
so fortunate, in such places as Bralos, Amphikleia, Hairo-
neia, Karya and Aliartos, the villagers' interest in books
increases day by day.
The people running the Mobile Library are doing a
good job and doing it enthusiastically and with a smile.
The cultural warmth that radiates from the Mobile
Library of Mrs. Peppa-Xephlouda is a conquest over the
arid intellectual soil of some of the country districts and
more and more people are coming to realize the impor¬
tance of books as companions in everyday life.
Rome was not built in a day, nor are kingdoms and
dukedoms established in so short a period. The Mobile
Library has begun a work of enlightenment among the
small communities that is undoubtedly contributing to the
cultural progress of the country.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
LABORATORY FOR
DESERT LIVING
by
Daniel Behrman
SAHARA OIL TOWN. A city
of several thousand people has
grown up around the oil wells at
Hassl Messaoud In the heart of
the Sahara. Problems of desert
living, ranging from family life and
housing to diet and working hours
are under constant study here.
Photos CFP.
i %
#1
X
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
1^ ms is a world where science shatters a myth
a day ... and the latest one to go by the board
is the old illusion of the Sahara Desert as a
trackless inhuman waste producing only
sandstorms and tales of adventure.
"Man can work' in the Sahara without any visible harm
to his health, and his productivity there can be as high
as it is in Europe . . . provided certain conditions of diet
and housing are met."
This statement came from Dr. Georges Lambert, a young
French medical man who is assistant director of
"Prohtjza" a word made up of the French initials for
"Study and Information Centre for Human Problems in
the Arid Zones."
Prohuza, financed by the French African Industrial
Bureau and companies developing the Sahara, is attacking
many aspects of the problems raised by transplanting
modern industrial civilization into the heart of the desert.
Its studies on the adaptation of European workers to
the Sahara were carried out at Hassi Messaoud, some 500
miles inland from the Mediterranean and sixty miles from
the nearest oasis, where oil was discovered in 1957.
Experiments were carried out with three five-man
teams of oil drillers, Dr. Lambert explained. He believes
that these were the first scientific experiments on the
adaptation of man to a desert climate actually carried out
in the field and not under simulated laboratory conditions.
"Unlike what most of us have always thought, the
climate in the Sahara is not too harmful for skilled
workers," Dr. Lambert said. During the experiments,
careful measurements were made of food intake and
losses of men in the oil fields working around the clock in
three eight-hour shifts.'
In the heat of a
desert summer, it was
found that the 3,500-
calorie diet offered in
the ultra-modern din¬
ing room at Hassi Mes¬
saoud camp was quite
adequate for skilled
workers on a difficult
job. Protein consump¬
tion rose slightly above
what it would have
been in Europe.
"The main food prob¬
lem at Hassi Messaoud
is psychologica 1,"
Dr. Lambert admitted
somewhat ruefully.
"You see, when the oil
company started hiring
men for the Sahara,
candidates were pro¬
mised good jobs and good food. Fate should be avoided
in the desert they're hard to digest but the men want
to eat well. You find some oil prospectors eating pâté de
foie gras and sardines when it's 122°F. (50°C.) in the
shade!"
As for the dining-room, it offers the same menu as a
good Paris restaurant. "'Look what they had for lunch
one day last August," said Dr. Lambert, flipping open a
notebook, "Charcuterie (that is, sausages and pâté) and
lettuce for an appetizer, followed by escalope à la crème
(veal steak with a cream sauce), vegetables, Camembert
cheese and fruit. We'd like to change this menu, but it's
hard to go back on our promises."
The ideal meal for desert workers, he explained, would
consist of a mixed salad, an appetizer, grilled meat, then
cheese and fruit, with a heavy accent on fresh vegetables.
Actually, such a menu would be very expensive since the
fresh fruit and vegetables on which it is largely based,
cost 110 francs ($0.20) a pound just to fly in.
The Unesco Courier. January 1960
European oil drillers in the Sahara are heavy drinkers . . .
of water. They lose 14 litres (more than 3 gallons) a day
in perspiration and they drink an equivalent amount of
Evian or Vittel water brought into Hassi Messaoud in
special cardboard or aluminium containers.
There is water at Hassi Messaoud, but it contains too
many ¡minerals to be drunk safely in large quantities. So,
paradoxically, the salty water on the spot goes unused
while salt must be added to the diet in the dining-room.
Scientific research has shown that the traditional food
of the Saharan nomads is an excellent desert diet. It is
rich in spices salt and pepper and contains very little
fat (the meat is usually roasted on a spit).
Diet is only half the story in providing suitable working
conditions in an arid zone. The other half is housing and,
of course, all quarters must be air-conditioned. The
system, however, is different from that used in most
towns.
The usual method of air conditioning, Dr. Lambert
explained, consists of a compressor producing very cold
and very dry air. In the Sahara, this would dry out the
skin immediately. Instead, an evaporation system is used.
Based upon the principle that water absorbs heat when it
is evaporated, it consists simply of a powerful turbine
blowing water through air. It cools a house bringing the
inside temperature down to 86°F. (30°C.) when it is 122°F.
(50°C.) outside and, at the same time, it humidifies it.
This air-conditioning costs much less to run and install
than a conventional system. There's just one hitch: it
can only be used in the Sahara or in a similar climate
where the humidity of the air is less than 10 per cent.
In New York or Bombay, for example, it wouldn't work.
Each Sahara day is like another
Q ç t-jrohuza" has studied certain other factors affecting
r^ the adaptation of man to desert conditions. At
present, employees have a choice of three different
schedules: three weeks at Hassi Messaoud, then one week
in Algiers ; nine weeks in the desert and three weeks in
France; or six weeks on the job and two weeks in Algiers
or in France. In each case, they work seven days a.week
without any time off on Sundays or holidays.
Studies show, Dr. Lambert stated, that the three to one
system is the least advisable. "Three weeks are just
enough time for a man to adapt himself to the desert;
he's hardly settled in and it's already time to go on leave,"
he explained. "In the end, he adapts himself neither to
the job nor to the leave."
This raises a series of psychological problems which are
just as important as food or housing. Scientists at Hassi
Messaoud have observed a rapid increase in the rate of
labour turnover in recent months.
But according to L\r. Lambert that is only normal. The
first oil workers in the desert were young men with an
itch for adventure. They were excellent during the
prospecting stage but now that' a city of 2,000 has grown
up around the oil wells, they have become restless.
This has led to the hiring of older men to handle the
job of extracting and shipping oil and the appearance of
a new set of problems revolving around family life and
housing.
"Everyone has his own opinion on the matter," Dr. Lam¬
bert said. "The basic problem is that men are too far
from their normal environment of friends and families."
Three possible solutions are now being studied: leaves
of absence long enough to enable the oilmen to return to
Europe; bringing the families to Algiers; or bringing them
to Hassi Messaoud.
No decision has yet been taken, but Dr. Lambert believes
that all three will be used, varying from one individual
case to another.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
N EW DEPUTY DIRECTOR-GEN¬
ERAL FOR UNESCO: Mr. Vittorino Vero¬
nese, Director-General of Unesco, has
decided to re-establish the post of Deputy
Director-General which no longer existed
since 1952. Mr. René Maheu, Assistant
Director-General since 1954, and a member
of the Unesco Secretariat since 1946, has
been appointed as Deputy Director-General,
from December 1, 1959.
FORTY YEARS OF AIR TRAVEL :
Forty years of international co-operation
in solving problems of air transport
were commemorated last year when the
International Air Transport Association
marked the anniversary of its founda¬
tion in 1919. The Association was
formed by six European airline com¬
panies, meeting in the Hague. Today
its members number 90 companies and
their routes link points all over the
globe. Some idea of the growth is
shown by the fact that the smallest
helicopter service now transports yearly
more passengers on its interurban lines
than all six Iata companies carried in
1920. The Iata has worked to eliminate
problems posed by differences of
language, laws, currency, commercial
systems and technical and economic
regulations.
I NDIA'S FIRST TV STATION: New
progress in the development of television
in South Asia has been marked by the
inauguration in New Delhi of the first
Indian TV station which has been set up
with the co-operation of Unesco. The
station is likely to serve as a kind of
pilot project for the development of TV
generally and educational TV in particular
THE UNESCO
PHILATELIC SERVICE
FOLLOWING the announcement
in our December number of the
issue of a new United Nations
stamp honouring World Refugee
Year, many philatelists have asked
us where they can obtain United
Nations stamps. Unesco's Philatelic
Service has stamps and first day cov¬
ers issued by many Member States
to commemorate important events in
the history of Unesco and the U.N.
(inauguration of Unesco's New Head¬
quarters, Human Rights Day, World
Refugee Year). As the agent in
France of the U.N. Postal Adminis¬
tration, Unesco's Philatelic Service
stocks all the United Nations stamps
currently on sale. Information on
items available, their price and the
methods of payment, will be sent on
request by Unesco's Philatelic Ser¬
vice, Place de Fontenoy, Paris T. .
TEN FULL PAGES OF COLOUR
will be featured in our next issue devoted to
THE PRESERVATION OF
THE TEMPLES OF ANCIENT EGYPT
destined to be swallowed up by the Aswan Dam
All subscribers will receive this colour issue without
extra charge
RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION TODAY
in the South-east Asian area. Unesco's
interest in the project dates back to 1957
when it was able to provide India with
information on experience gained in rural
viewing in France, Japan and Italy where
tele-clubs have been set up with aid from
Unesco. Such information was particularly
valuable to India where community viewing
will be the principal form of reception.
'A LITTLE UNITED NATIONS': At
the George Washington High School,
New York City, teaching and learning
about the United Nations is a practical
as well as an academic activity, for the
5,000 students include boys and girls
from 52 member countries of the U.N.
Students at the school, which has been
called "a little United Nations in itself"
take part in U.N. compaigns and orga¬
nize a variety of activities to promote
knowledge of U.N. work and greater
international friendship essay contests,
pen-pal programmes, plays, displays of
posters and a student club which meets
fortnightly to discuss world affairs.
w ORLD NEWSPRINT HUNGER:
World demand for newsprint will more than
double by 1975, rising from 11,280,000 tons
in 1955 to 17 million tons in 1965 and
26 million in !1975 reports the U.N. Food
and Agriculture Organization. Experts
state that world production can meet pres¬
ent needs and expansion plans should take
care of increased consumption up to 1965,
but supply and demand trends must be
reviewed regularly if the expected growth
after 1965 is to be met. Pulp and paper
industries must be developed in the econo¬
mically less developed countries, where
increased supplies are an essential factor in
economic, educational and social progress.
HELP FROM A TO B: Young polio
victims being treated in Bombay are to
benefit from modern aids and equip¬
ment purchases through the efforts of
students, teachers and citizens of Ams¬
terdam, Holland. After Unesco passed
a request for aid from the Bombay
Society for the Rehabilitation of Crip¬
pled Children to the Netherlands, the
Unesco-Centre in Amsterdam, the muni¬
cipal authorities, teachers, children and
their parents adopted this Unesco gift
project. From their efforts a first ins¬
talment of Unesco Gift Coupons worth
some 7,500 dollars has been handed
over. In addition Dutch students sent
letters to the children they were help¬
ing, thus fulfilling another important
aspect of the Unesco Gift Coupon pro¬
gramme and informative exchan¬
ges between persons in different coun¬
tries.
u
z
<
z
<
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
r swam*
4Ê> ^7^
radioisotopes
in the service
of man
by Fernand LOT
unesco
Never a day passes without
newspapers and magazines
reporting some new applica¬
tion of artificial radio-active
elements: tumours removed
by radio-active iodine or
treated by " cobalt bombs, "
insecticides developed by
"marked" mosquitoes, hith¬
erto impossible diagnoses
today achieved through
radio-active isotopes. Iso¬
topes play an ever-increasing
part in an ever-widening
range of fields: analysis of
metals and lubricants, petro¬
leum research, océanogra¬
phie investigations and even
the fixing of geological and
historical events. How is all this made possible ? The answers are given in an 80-page publi¬
cation, "Radio-isotopes in the Service of Man," in the series "Unesco and Its Programme."
The author, Mr. Fernand Lot, traces the history of the new "pure gold" of modern
alchemists, from the discovery of natural radio-activity to the latest uses of the latest
discoveries in that field.
The author leads the reader into the heart of the atom, shows how the atom disintegrates,
how the radiations are produced, how reactors operate, how physicists, medical doctors,
biologists, chemists and agronomists make use of the astonishing results of the experi¬
ments of Becquerel, Rutherford and the Curies which have given us the amazing key
to a new era.
PRICE : U.S. $1.00 ; 5/- (stg) ; 300 FF. (3 NF.).
üL'l
BINDERS FOR YOUR
COLLECTION OF
Unesco Courier
We offer subscribers a special binder
for their copies of THE UNESCO
COURIER holding 12 issues of the
magazine. Handsomely produced In
halfcloth with the spine in an attractive
blue and the title (in English, French
or Spanish according to the edition to
which you subscribe) and Unesco co¬
lophon embossed In gold, these con¬
venient and attractive binders, costing
$2.50 ; 12/6 stg. ; or 600 Fr. frs, (6 N. F.)
can be ordered from UNESCO agents.
Study Abroad
Études à l'étranger
Estudios
en el extranjero
"S, * ¿síss¡
fit * >.. ''.,"
* /% "4""»»
>&«.,'
v,
T:ü.
Vol. XI 1959-60
Last year some 177,000 students enrolled for higher
education in countries other than their own. This fact
alone shows the usefulness of this most popular Unesco
handbook. Volume XI, just published, brings you the
latest information on 90,000 fellowships and scholarships
offered by governments, universities, foundations and
other institutions in III countries and territories. A
perfected system of classification will help you. to find
rapidly all the details: who can study what subjects and
where, what is the amount of each award and how and
where applications may be made.
An invaluable manual for anyone contemplating study in
a foreign country. An indispensable reference book for
all libraries, universities and information centres. A
useful instrument in promoting educational contacts
throughout the world.
800 pages. Price : U. S. $3.00; 15/- (stg); 10.50 Nf"
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
