<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064522eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
[special issue
^iiH
52 pages v
February 1 960
(13th year)
Price 2/6stg (U.K.)
60 cents (U.S.)
NF. 1.75 (France)
lii¿i5W5t5WWIfljatiTi:
SAVE THE
OF I
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
^- 1 1 \i-\ 1 - M
THE TEMPLE OF ISIS, marvel of the island of Philae, is
inundated by the Nile for nine months of the year. Photo,
taken last October, shows the waters held back by the
present Aswan Dam slowly invading the temple. The
monuments of Philae are among the hundreds of historic
treasures in Nubia which are now threatened with inun¬
dation by the construction of the new High Dam at As¬
wan. Unesco is launching a world appeal to save them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
A Message from the Director-General of Unesco
or countless centuries the Nile has given life to the lands through which it
flows. Today, the inhabitants of these lands, who are increasing rapidly in
number, must ask their mighty river to give more than in the past. The
High Dam which is soon to rise at Aswan will usher in a new era of eco¬
nomic progress destined to provide more food for millions of people.
These are the people to whom we owe one of the greatest civilizations in history.
On the banks of their river they raised edifices the beauty and grandeur of which have
never been surpassed. But with the new dam a vast lake will be created in Nubia, a
lake which threatens to engulf some of the most glorious of these monuments for ever.
An agonizing dilemma therefore faces the authorities charged with developing the
Nile Valley: how are they to choose between the needs and welfare of their people
and the treasures which belong not only to their country but to humanity as a whole?
The authorities are fully aware that they are the depositaries, before all the world,
of the monuments of the Nubian Valley, and they are eager to ensure their safeguard.
It is these motives which led the United Arab Republic and the Government of the
Sudan to appeal to Unesco for the purpose of obtaining the international aid which
is indispensable.
As soon asl received these appeals, I recognized that Unesco could not possibly
fail to respond. The action it is being asked to undertake is in full conformity with
the essential objectives of the Organization. We cannot allow temples like Abu
Simbel and Philae, which are veritable gems of ancient art, to disappear; nor can we
abandon forever the treasures which lie buried in the sand on sites not yet systema¬
tically excavated.
Here is an exemplary occasion for demonstrating the international solidarity which
Unesco has been striving to make a reality in all domains. No one, indeed, can
deny the urgency of this cause and the effort required, or the need for sharing the
burden among as large a number of countries as possible.
Moreover, in return for the international assistance given, the Government of
the United Arab Republic is offering not less than fifty per cent of the finds excavated
in Nubia, authorization to carry out further excavations in other parts of Egypt, and
the cession of precious objects and monuments, including certain Nubian temples,
for transfer abroad. The Government of the Sudan, for its part, is offering fifty per
cent of the finds from excavations to be made in its territory.
An International Consultative Committee will be responsible for advising the com¬
petent government authorities on the plans for prospective excavations, on the use
made of financial contributions, and on the distribution of counterparts offered by
the United Arab Republic.
There can be no doubt that the preservation and excavation operations which
can, and must, begin within the next few months, will provide a new impetus to
archaeology. The history of civilizations, religions and art, and our knowledge of
prehistoric times will be immeasurably enriched as a result.
At my proposal, the Executive Board of Unesco has decided that I should issue an
appeal for international co-operation. This appeal, which I intend to launch in the
very near future, will be addressed not only to governments and to the public and
private institutions concerned, but also to public opinion in all countries of the world.
A group of Patrons and an International Action Committee will support Unesco in
this world campaign. I feel certain that all those who clearly understand what is at
stake will wish to participate, for they will recognize that an unprecedented task
calls for an unprecedented effort.
VITTORINO VERONESE
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
FEBRUARY 1960
1.3TH YEAR
Contents
No. 2
FRONT COVER
Part of the façade of the
Great Temple of Abu
Simbel, one of the great
architectural masterpieces
of the world and the most
monumental ensemble of
ancient Nubia. It has been
called the "Cathedral of
Notre Dame" of ancient
Egypt. Abu Simbel Is
threatened to be flooded by
the waters of the Nile
within the next four years.
BACK COVER
One of the stone figures
from the sacred avenue
of sphinxes leading to the
Temple of Wadl es Sebua.
Ever since the first Aswan
Dam was thrown across
the Nile early In this century,
It has been partially under
water nine months out of the
year. The new dam, how¬
ever, will flood It for ever.
Cover photos Christiane
Desroches- Noblecourt.
SAVE THE TREASURES OF NUBIA
PAGE
3 A MESSAGE FROM VITTORINO VERONESE
Director-General of Unesco
5 THE DRAMA OF NUBIA
By Georges Fradier
8 THE LEGACY OF NUBIA
By Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
16 THE TEMPLES OF RAMESES II AT ABU SIMBEL
Marriage of the colossal and the beautiful
20 FREED FROM A GRAVE OF SAND
The saga of the discovery of Abu Simbel
By Louis A. Christophe
23 COLOUR MAP OF THE NILE VALLEY
Waterway of art and history
By Rifaat Nasr
24-30 SPECIAL COLOUR SUPPLEMENT
3 1 THE SUN WAS A WITNESS AT PHARAOH'S MARRIAGE
By Jaroslav Cerrry
PHILAE, THE SACRED ISLE
By Etienne Drioton
IN THE STEPS OF GREECE AND ROME
By André Bernand & A. Ahmed Aly
UNDER THE SIGN OF MAAT, GODDESS OF PRECISION
Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt
THE MODERN PYRAMID OF ASWAN
The Sadd El Aali on the Nile
By Albert Raccah
SUDANESE NUBIA, «TERRA INCOGNITA'
By Jean Vercoutter
QUESTION MARKS IN THE DESERT
By Anwar Shoukry & François Daumas
46
50
This issue was prepared with the collaboration of Madame Christiane Desroches-
Noblecourt, Curator of Egyptian Antiquities, Louvre Museum, Paris, and
Unesco Consultant at the Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo.
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7; France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 59. 1.144 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7".
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
%W^m&WWIwSiïmSK'QX
Unesco-Laurenza
TWO NILE GODS wreathing the floral emblems (papyrus and lily) of Lower and Upper Egypt round the hieroglyphic symbol for
"to unite." These carvings decorate two thrones of the colossi of Rameses II on the façade of the Great Temple at Abu Simbel.
THE DRAMA OF NUBIA
by Georges Fradier
OMEONE once said that it is best to announce a
great calamity like a fire, a massacre or a
tidal wave, in measured tones and in simple
words. I shall therefore say quite simply: The
monuments of ancient Egypt, among them
Philae, Amada, Kalabsha and Abu Simbel, are in danger.
But I wonder if the full significance of this sentence will
not escape some persons. What it really means is that we
ourselves are in danger. The construction of the High
Dam at Aswan threatens to engulf these monuments, or
to disintegrate them. In other words it will obliterate
them completely and amputate a portion one of the
most extraordinary portions of our memories.
I say "memories" advisedly. By definition as well as
etymologically, a monument is something that reminds
us; it is a memorial, a remembrance (the Latin verb
monere from which it comes means "to remind").
To the artist and the historian, a monument even
creates memory, and is sometimes the foundation of a
whole branch of learning.
Painted caves and rock carvings are monuments: they
do more than recall the world of hunting and magic In
which men lived ten thousand years ago. They alone have
revealed this world. Before they were discovered, this
world was completely unknown and did not exist.
In its place were all sorts of preposterous suppositions.
But when we discovered it, we added thousands of years
of knowledge, of conscious and unconscious adventures,
to our past. In fact, the revelation is still so new that we
have not had time to glean all it can teach us about our
distant ancestors, that is, about ourselves.
The Upper Nile has hundreds of prehistoric sites,
mostly unexplored. Three or four rivers of the world,
and the tenacity and genius of those who first lived along
them, are the sources of what we call our arts and our
sciences. But it was hardly fifty years ago that we began
systematically excavating prehistoric strata in the valleys
of the Tigris and Euphrates, the Indus and the Nile. Such
excavations are expensive and yield no gold or ivory trea¬
sures. But there was plenty of time to dig or so we thought.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THE DRAMA
OF NUBIA
(Continued)
These great
cannot be
testaments in stone
allowed to perish
Suddenly the Aswan dam project has raised a cry of
alarm; within five years, within four years, the unexplored
sites of Egyptian Nubia will be forever beyond our reach.
According to further plans which have already been
announced, the artificial lake will rise southward as far as
the Dal (third) Cataract, and most of Sudanese Nubia
will also be swallowed up in its turn.
In the Sudanese part of Nubia, more than 400 kilo¬
metres of alluvium, sand and sandstone hold the secrets
of the first colonists of the Nile. They built their villages
at the edge of a Sahara which was probably still savanna;
no doubt it Was they who Were the preceptors of Egypt.
Will we now abandon hope of piercing the mysteries of
that remote culture buried at the junction point where
the Mediterranean world and the African world meet, and
the study of which can throw so much light on the origins
of both and on the links which perhaps unite them ?
To resign oneself to such a loss would mean blithely
accepting a kind of partial amnesia, like that of a man
who has no memory of his early childhood or of his
parents. It is quite possible that he may be happy
without it. But we should pity him for having been
emptied of his history and for not knowing where he
came from. On the excavation sites which must be open¬
ed up immediately in Nubia, archaeologists and pre-
historians may find the memories we lack (and this lack
is cruelly felt, as soon as we are aware of it), memories
which give dimension and proportion to mankind.
To save the temples
international
aid is necessary
Other monuments were destined for more solemn pur¬
poses. The kings who created Philae, those who had
colossal statues and halls carved deep in the rock of
Abu Simbel, those before them who built the pyramids,
believed they knew and sought to proclaim until the end of
time "whence we come, who we are, whither we are going."
We do not share their conviction, but we do not smile at
it either. We know it to be the most precious depository
of our collective memory: what we have come to call
culture, or as we used to say, the humanities.
No progress or decline of civilizations has prevailed
against this beauty, which remains irresistible today even
to the most ignorant men. These temples and statues are
still, after twenty or thirty centuries, the models of the
beauty they served to define. One does not need to grasp
their whole historic significance in order to realize that
they are among the highest works of man among the
really great achievements which justify our speaking of
humanity and make us feel, in 1960, beholden to the
architects, the painters, the sculptors, the priests and even
the workmen of the divine pharaohs.
There are other bonds, too. Anyone may if he so desires
have brotherly feelings in his heart for the thousands of
millions of men who preceded us on earth; or be moved
by the thought of the long, slow development of technical
mastery. Yet a nobler kinship is revealed to us by the
most ancient masterpieces of art; they are manifestations
of a need to go beyond what was done before, of a fervour
and a pride about which history, without them, would
tell us practically nothing.
These irreplaceable monuments (and irreplaceable they
are, for no museum can ever be substituted for a tem¬
ple, the sacred ground about it and the sky that bathes it)
are more valuable than all the gold mines of the world.
And there are not so many such monuments. The true
masterpieces of art, and especially of architecture, are
rightly said to be universal: they are part of the heritage
of all peoples, and that means that all of us need them.
Only a few cities, however, only a few periods in history
have reared them. A few countries hold what remains of
the marvels which it was the privilege of certain centuries
to amass along the shores of the Mediterranean, in China
and in Egypt. Time, conquerors and merchants have
destroyed so much already that there is dangerously little
left.
We need only a bit of violence, a bit of neglect, a bit of
avarice, and Greece, China and Egypt herself will have no
more to show us than formless ruins like those in a
little town of Burgundy where, 160 years ago, there still
stood the greatest of Romanesque churches, the master¬
piece of the European Middle Ages, Cluny.
Today, an international institution exists which would
have opposed the demolition of Cluny, even if the
destroyer had invoked public necessity as his excuse. This
institution is Unesco ; one of its tasks is to safeguard the
cultural and scientific heritage of mankind. It has heard
the appeals of the United Arab Republic and the Republic
of Sudan. For indeed no one desires to destroy the glories
of Nubia. The authorities who have decided to build the
high dam are the very ones who are trying to do every¬
thing to preserve the monuments in the valley that will
be submerged. But to do everything means to have the
financial and technical resources which the authorities
regrettably do not possess. International aid is therefore
indispensable.
No one should imagine that this campaign was conceived
on the spur of the moment, that it is just panic at the
eleventh hour. The Government of the United Arab
Republic, thinking of the fate of Nubia, turned to Unesco
nearly five years ago. A Documentation and Study Centre
on the history of the art and civilization of ancient Egypt
was then founded; it has been working under steadily
greater stress to carry out a full scientific survey of the
monuments in jeopardy. (See page 40.)
However, saving the temples themselves, with their sites
and, in some cases, the cliff they form part of, requires
resources on a much vaster scale. Furthermore, even
before the rescue operation can begin, thorough geogra¬
phical and geological studies of the ground must be made.
Excavation expeditions
in Egypt & Sudan
to receive 50 °/o of finds
In July 1959, Unesco sent a special mission to the author¬
ities of the United Arab Republic and shortly after¬
wards, in agreement with them, asked the Institut
Géographique National in Paris to make a photogramme-
tric survey of the area, both from the air and from the
ground. In October, Unesco convened in Cairo an inter¬
national committee of Egyptologists, archaeologists and
engineers. The experts journeyed up the Nile from the
Aswan district as far as the Sudanese frontier and explor¬
ed most of the monuments along the valley which is to be
submerged a few years hence.
At the first meeting of the committee, the Egyptian
Minister of Culture and National Guidance, H.E. Seroit
Okasha, made an extremely important declaration on
behalf of his Government. In exchange for the interna¬
tional assistance requested, the United Arab Republic has
offered (1) to surrender at least half of all future excava¬
tion finds made in the threatened area except for certain
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
specimens which may be considered unique or essential
to Egyptian museum collections; (2) to authorize excava¬
tions on other Egyptian sites; (3) to cede certain temples
of Upper Nubia and permit them to be shipped abroad;
(4) to give up an important collection of ancient objects
which are State property.
The Government of the Sudan, in exchange for inter¬
national assistance, has offered, with the same reserva¬
tions, 50 % of the finds made in the area.
Today, the Director-General of Unesco, after a unani¬
mous decision by the Executive Board, is launching a
solemn appeal to governments, appropriate public and
private institutions and to the citizens of all countries to
take part in this great international rescue operation.
The Director-General now is in possession of the
experts' outline of the first emergency steps envisaged in
the plan to rescue the monuments of Nubia. This plan
includes a detailed list of all the threatened monuments,
and what must be done to save each of them from des¬
truction. Frescoes must be taken down; bas-reliefs must
be cut out; small temples must be taken apart stone by
stone and rebuilt in a safer place, some in oases which
the dam waters will create, others abroad.
One would not
dismantle
Westminster Abbey
However, as regards the famed ensembles of Philae
and Abu Simbel, the verdict of the experts is cate¬
gorical: the only solution is to preserve them where
they stand. One would not dismantle Westminster Abbey
and set it up again elsewhere. One cannot "save" the
Parthenon by reconstituting the Acropolis in an open air
museum.
The Island of Philae, tragically flooded nine months
out of the year since the first Aswan dam was built in
1902, can, on the contrary, become an island again. The
rock of Abu Simbel can and must escape the muddy
waters which need only to lick the feet of its colossal
statues to cause them to disintegrate within a few years.
The most imposing and most urgent task is the one to
be undertaken here. A group of engineer-advisers at this
very moment are on the spot making the necessary
surveys and studies.
To build dikes between the high dam and the artificial
lake, downstream, so that Philae may find its purity and
native sun again, to raise a rampart off Abu Simbel, so
as to preserve not only the most majestic temple of the
Upper Nile but also the light and shadow which make
its statues live this undoubtedly will cost money. Much
more money than we are in the habit of giving to archeo-
logists, art historians and museum curators. The sum
may reach $30,000,000. But When we think that it is being
asked of 81 States, among which are the richest and most
powerful countries in the world, it seems hard to feel
frightened by such a figure. One is even irresistibly
tempted to compare it with that of the most modest
armaments' budget... However, comparisons of this kind
are, it would appear, in bad taste and frowned upon as
unrealistic...
So let us look at the photographs in this issue of the
dwellings built for the gods thousands of years ago and
which have suddenly become so fragile. Men and women
of all ages, of every rank and language, will be looking
at them with us. But not one of us is without responsi¬
bility: not one of us is powerless in our country, our com¬
munity, our city. While we turn these pages, we cannot
be indifferent to the fate of these great testaments of
stone, these proud, tragic affirmations of an eternal,
invincible will to ennoble mankind.
Photos Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo
Prince Amen-her-Kepshef, one of the two hundred
children of Rameses II, nestles between the feet
of the second colossal statue of his father on the
façade of the Great Temple at Abu Simbel. At some
unknown date, the head and torso of this colossus
broke off from the mountain side in which the figure
had been carved. The story goes that a hole was
bored into the chest at neck level and wood hammered
and pounded in. Water was then poured inside
causing the wood to expand until the top of the
statue split off. The headless figure is seen in the
large colour photo on centre pages (26-27) with the fal¬
len rock at its feet and boring gashes at shoulder level.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
ike a landscape before a terrible storm,
when the horizon lights up in a translucent
glow and an unearthly hush envelops all
nature, Nubia has never been more beau¬
tiful.
The danger hanging over Nubia, it is
true, has never been so great for it is now
doomed to total obliteration. Despite the
countless tragedies it has known up until the present,
it has managed, for several weeks of the hot summer
months each year, to preserve the general aspect that
thousands of years of succeeding civilizations have given
it. During these summer weeks, all the temples strung
out along the banks of the Nile are visible and emerge
from the waters which, since the beginning of the century,
submerge many of them most of the year.
It may be difficult for those who have never set eyes
on the extraordinary shores of the Nubian Nile to imagine
the majesty of the sites, the fascination of the sanctua¬
ries, and the charm of the villages difficult, in fact, to
grasp the immensity of the tragedy. Many persons are
undoubtedly familiar with Pierre Loti's poetic description
of the "Death of Philae", and have heard about the
building of the Aswan Dam and the raising of its level on
two occasions.
8
At the beginning of the century it was found necessary
to raise the Aswan Dam in order to provide a more
systematic irrigation system for Egypt and to prevent the
river from draining away into the sea. The iron sluice¬
gates in the huge dam wall (made out of the same pink
granite and taken from the same quarries nearby which
the ancient Egyptians used for their giant obelisks) are
closed almost all year long. They are opened only at the
end of July when the river has turned red from the thick
alluvion collected upstream, and the fields are then
flooded and only the causeways and a few villages perched
on arid hillocks emerge from the waters.
In Nubia meanwhile, the level of the water now drops
and the narrow strip of land along the river turns green
again. The inhabitants attend to their farming, and the
fields are soon thick with millet and water-melons. When,
during this brief three-month respite, the river keeps to
its bed, the harvest can be gathered. In mid-October,
when the dam is closed, the waters again invade the
stubble-fields, now parched and cracked by the drought
and the extreme heat. The palm-trees are engulfed up
to their tousled heads, and from the far-off banks seem to
be floating on the surface. Beneath these waters the great
sanctuaries lie buried.
It is not easy to visualize this extraordinary open-air
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
THE LEGACY OF NÜBIÄ
JOURNEY
TO A LAND
CONDEMNED
by Christiane
Desroches-Noblecourt
Curator, Department of Egyptian Antiquities,
Musée du Louvre, Paris
Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo
THE TEMPLE OF THOT, Egyptian god of wisdom and writing, at Dakka (left). Photo was taken
just before the start of the temple's annual inundation in October. By the end of November all that
can be seen above the water are the cornices of the temple pylon. To save the temple of Dakka it is
proposed to dismantle it stone by stone and rebuild it in the safety of a nearby oasis. Above, in
the Temple of Nefertari at Abu Simbel, a bas-relief depicts the Queen receiving the protection of
the two goddesses Isis and Hathor. The work has conserved the full tones of its original colouring.
museum nearly 300 miles long, containing monuments
often surpassing Gothic cathedrals in size, submerged
most of the year round. Under the waters lie not only
temples but tombs by the hundred, quarries and nume¬
rous fortresses. The fortresses were built as trading posts
and strongholds to defend vitally strategic points along
the caravan routes, such as the centres fed by the gold¬
mines, the relay stations to distant deposits, the settle¬
ments specializing in artifacts, and the administrative
centres of the country.
But in this land of eternity, even the inundation of the
monuments is not permanent, for like the cycle of rebirth
in Nature itself, they reappear regularly every summer,
if only fleetingly.
At the time of the first Aswan dam at the beginning of
the century, excavations and "soundings" Were made to
test the vulnerability of the menaced fortresses and
necropolis centres built out of unbaked clay. For the
temples, hurried missions were sent to make copies and
descriptions of them before they were engulfed. The con¬
solidation work, feverishly yet carefully executed under
Gaston Maspero and continued subsequently, proved to
be truly effective.
Not only did the temples remain intact when submerged,
but the water even helped to remove their corroding salts
and incrustations. Only the ancient paintings were
washed away, sometimes actually enhancing the beauty
of the carvings underneath. The monuments built of
unbalked clay, however, could not resist the waters and
were washed away by the floods for the most part.
The temples erected in this region had been built of
blocks of sandstone hewn from the finest quarries of
Nubia, and this stone is most resistant. The situation is
quite different for the sanctuaries located further to the
south outside of the present flood zone. The temples here
were built into the sides of the cliffs of the Libyan and
Arabian mountain chains bordering the Nile. They were
cut out of stone so friable that they cannot possibly hope
to resist the action of water.
It is these temples that the waters of the Sadd el Aali
high dam will engulf if nothing is done to save them.
Since the new water level, once reached, is not expected
to drop again appreciably, everything that is submerged
will be covered up for all eternity.
Thus all of Nubia will become a vast lake and an
entire country will shortly vanish definitely and irrevo¬
cably. The inhabitants will be able to move into the lands
freshly reclaimed from the desert, and into the oases
especially created near the largest wadis (valleys) of
western Nubia. But the ribbon of land 300 miles long,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THE LEGACY
OF NUBIA
(Continued)
THE EPIC OF KADESH.
Carved on the northern wall
inside the Great Temple of
Abu Simbel are scenes from
an epic of Egyptian history
battle of Kadesh (1285
B.C.) where the courage of
Rameses II saved Egypt's army
from defeat at the hands of the
Hittites. Central panel shows
Rameses on his throne before
battle Is joined holding a
council of war with his vizier
and officers. Lower panel
shows the Egyptian camp with
the soldiers' shields arranged
around It In a kind of stockade ;
in centre two spies are forced
to yield their secret. In upper
section we witness the charge
of the Hittite cavalry-, curved
line represents Orontes River
in Syria which flowed round the
citadel of Kadesh. On far right
are mounted archers of Rame¬
ses. (See also pages 31-33.)
Documentation Centre on
Ancient Egypt, Charles Nims
with its remains of the creative genius of ancient Egypt
which have withstood the elements for thousands of
years, will be lost.
Egypt is the cradle of Mediterranean civilization and
the archaeologist's living book of history. Its scattered
pages, discovered one by one, were pieced together and
read with patience and devotion and now constitute the
most prodigious and profound chapter on remote anti¬
quity. But despite the wealth of material found, many
pages are still missing. Some of the most valuable are
now lost, like the famous library at Alexandria, destroyed
by fire, or, what is less known, the ancient papyrus scrolls
which until the last century peasants Were wont to burn
when scouring the ancient ruins for fertilizer.
No effort should therefore be spared to find and preserve
all the vestiges which may throw light on the history of
our forbears, for was this not the crucible in which the
basic elements of Western civilization were forged?
Not all the treasures of Nubia have yet been discovered.
Those that do remain are of such vital significance that
it is our duty, regardless of nationality, to help in preserv¬
ing them. For they are the links in a great chain which
is significant and meaningful only by their cohesion.
What does Nubia have to offer? The imprint of more
than four thousand years on a narrow, semi-desert land
10
bordering the Nile, left by men who gradually absorbed
a coherent civilization through their growing contacts
with the Egyptians of the north. Nor is this all. It also
brought a foreign contribution to Egypt proper, enriching
the land of the Pharaohs by acting as the intermediary
for trade with the more southerly regions. It was a
reservoir of skilful craftsmen, of brave soldiers and
officers, of diligent and honest civil servants; even brilliant
statesmen who came to be so influential that with the
rise of the New Empire in the 14th century B.C. their
power steadily rose until they could help new dynasties
to mount the throne of the Pharaohs.
If we sail up the Nile in summer, when the flood-waters
have receded, we can see all the remaining monuments and
in the end have a vivid, impressive image of the past. Our
journey will not be in strict geographical order, but does
this really matter? Perhaps it will be all the more
attractive since our pilgrimage into the realm of antiquity
will be made not with some futuristic "time machine" but
through the magic of hieroglyphics, that ingenious
mechanism which Champollion revealed to us.
No sooner have we passed the First Cataract than Philae
looms up out of the water, iridescent amidst the blue-
pink reflections of the Nile. It looks almost like a bird
which is perched on an island pointing straight south.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Here is a group of sanctuaries We must always see
preserved in its religious and geographical context,
inseparable from the sacred site on which it was built to
proclaim its message to the world.
Sailing around the island, the great colonnade moves
past us with its individualized capitals which announce
the Hellenistic period of Egypt's Pharaohs. We pause a
moment to admire the romantic Kiosk of Trajan and
then spy the first gigantic pylon of the temple itself,
pierced on the west by the "mammis" gate where the
Great Isis gave birth to the young god Horus. What an
amazing itinerary the goddess Isis has followed down the
centuries. She was the presiding deity of Philae, the
supreme Mother-Goddess, and -her cult extended all the
way to the shores of the Western world, penetrating into
the sanctuaries of the boatmen of Lutetia (the arms of
modern Paris still bear an image of the boat which can
be traced back indirectly to her).
It is in this region that Lower Nubia is at its most arid,
a phantom river flowing between rock banks, bare of all
but the scantiest vegetation, like a landscape in hell.
Now we drive deeper into Africa and soon come upon the
little kiosk of Kertassi near the famous quarries which
yielded the stones for the temples of Philae. The removal
of this kiosk should present no very serious difficulties.
The rear wall is covered with old Greek inscriptions, and
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
busts in niches are cut directly out of the rock. The
earliest ones date from the time of the quarrying of the
stone for Philae.
Here now is the Graeco-Roman temple of Debod. It is
completely under water in winter as are the small chapels
built in the region where the Nile narrows sharply before
reaching a point where the rocks, purple-hued on the
eastern side and sand-yellow on the western, form a gorge
which the Egyptians call the Gate of Handcuffs (Bab
Kalabsha). Beyond this gorge, Nubia becomes more
fertile: a thin ribbon of cultivable soil on the edge of the
desert. Here, Augustus had the temple of Kalabsha
rebuilt in the style of those of the Pharaohs. The largest
of the Roman temples in Nubia after Philae it is almost
intact, as are the chapels surrounding it. Its inner walls
are covered with religious representations dominated by
figures of the young god Mandulis, the Nubian form of
Horus, and numerous versions of the bountiful Isis
(Wadjet) in all her radiance.
It is often a tiny detail In this wealth of monuments
that discloses invaluable information. Thus, for instance,
a pilgrim's votive offering (a simple image clumsily
engraved at the foot of a column) showed us the popular
form in which the local deity was worshipped, and
enabled us recently to identify a figure found on an object
amidst the treasure of a tribal chief (the Blemmyes of
Kustul) who had terrorized the Nubians when the region
was under Christian influence. This picture, in Its turn,
showed that the Blemmyes continued to venerate certain
debased forms of the ancient Egyptian gods long after
the religion of the Pharaohs had officially disappeared.
Kalabsha is a temple that must not be permitted to
perish. It could be dismantled and transported elsewhere
stone by stone. The little nearby sanctuary of Beit el
Wali, founded by Rameses II, must also be rescued at all
costs. But it presents an entirely different problem, for
it stands at the top of a cliff and Is almost entirely hewn
in the rock. The stone will have to be cut into, and blocks
of the cliff-face removed an operation the experts assure
us is perfectly feasible.
Elephants' tusks, ostrich
feathers & sacks of gold
The monument is Well worth the trouble. If the colours
on the two side walls of the entrance hall have
disappeared, the reliefs themselves are admirably
preserved. They depict Rameses' army in action In the
northern regions as well as scenes extraordinarily rich in
detail on life in ancient Nubia. One panel shows a village
with Pharaoh's chariots approaching to restore law and
order. Another shows tribute paid by Nubia to the lord of
the whole Nile down almost to the Fourth Cataract.
Alongside sacks of gold, ostrich feathers, elephants'
tusks, leopard skins, tame animals led on a leash, and
ebony Woods, are depicted various articles produced by
Nubian craftsmen. Famed for their skill, they worked
for Pharaoh's court fashioning pieces of furniture and
other objects in pure Egyptian style. They produced
inlaid gold ornaments of bold design which depicted
whole scenes from the everyday life of Nubia as well as
the fauna and flora of "The Land of Gold." The walls
inside the temple of Beit el Wall are adorned with
religious paintings, their colouring as fresh today as when
the artist applied them several thousand years ago.
Continuing southwards we cross the Tropic of Cancer
and stop at the little temple of Dendur, leaving behind a
number of important monuments. Standing high above
the Nile it is entered by a monumental stone doorway
preceded by a broad terrace. The temple is dedicated to
two heroes who drowned and were later deified. Augustus
himself worshipped them.
Like nearly all the monuments of Nubia, Dendur was
"Christianized" by the Copts. One inscription tells us
that a certain Presbyter Abraham erected a cross here at
the command of the Nubian king. Dendur is one of the
temples the United Arab Republic proposes to offer as a
grant, in return for foreign aid.
We are approaching an important religious centre
where Rameses II had no less than six temples hewn out
of the Nubian mountainside. At the top of a cliff,
between two Wadis a sanctuary with terrifying colossi juts
out over the river at Gerf Husein which ^must have
commanded the trembling respect of the local inhabitants.
The Nile valley now broadens and the cliffs give way
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
THE LEGACY
OF NUBIA
(Continued)
Will the palace of Heka Nefer
be found before Nubia is engulfed?
to a spacious plain covered with desert sand. A hundred
yards from the water stands an elegant temple with its
main axis parallel to the Nile (the only one in Nubia
with Philae, oriented north-south). This is Dakka,
dedicated to Thot, god of writing (hieroglyphics) and
wisdom. It belongs to the late Egyptian period and Was
the last edifice reconstructed by the Nubian king Erga-
menes in the reign of Ptolemy IV on the ruins of a much
earlier sanctuary. It contains charming reliefs which
have added many new details to our knowledge of
Egypt's past. Dakka stands at the border of the empire
established by the Greeks in Lower Nubia. It could be
dismantled and removed.
This will probably not be possible for the temple of
Wadí es Sebua, partly hewn in the rock by Rameses II.
Lying on a bend of the Nile and silhouetted against a
background of bluish hills reminiscent of an Alpine lake
scene, it is the only sanctuary in Nubia which still
possesses its "dromos" (sacred avenue flanked by
sphinxes). It was later transformed into a church the
remains of which are of major importance. There are
several Christian paintings done in Byzantium-inspired
style which could be removed along with the sphinxes.
In the Holy of Holies recess of the temple, Rameses can
be seen offering large bouquets of flowers to the gods of
the sanctuary, but in the bottom central part the god
Amon is now covered over by a painting of Saint Peter
holding an enormous key in his hand.
A few miles to the north, excavations have laid bare
one of the many towns of mediaeval Nubia the fortress
of Ikhmindi preserved on the top of a cliff. It is
surrounded by a thick stone wall, except on the river face
where the steepness of the cliff was considered protection
enough. The inner streets have vaulted roofs and a
church stands in the heart of the town.
In a small Christian chapel just south of Ikhmindi's
walls, a foundation stone was discovered last year
inscribed with the name of the governor of the fortress-
town and explaining that it had been built to protect the
people and their cattle from the attacks by the Blemmyes.
We should have to stop every mile if we were to indicate
all the ancient necropolises in this region, all the remains
of settlements and chapels, all the rock inscriptions
telling of local gods, of the passage of Egyptian armies
since the Old Kingdom four thousand years ago, of the
Greek mercenaries who crossed Nubia since the 7th
century B.C. Here, at Kuban, is a stela indicating the
waterpoints and wells dug for Pharaoh's soldiers; there
the ruins of a large brick fortress of the Middle Kingdom
(2000 B.C.); further on the remains of a temple; and
then the entrance to the Allaki valley leading to ancient
gold mines, their rocky walls covered with inscriptions.
In a fertile plain bounded by a semi-circle of mountains,
we spy Korosko, starting-point of the great caravan route
to Abu Hamed in the Sudan. Here the Nile describes a
great curve to the northwest and we come upon the little
temple of Amada, dating back over 3,000 years to the
beginning of the New Empire under Tuthmosis III and
Amenophis II. Amada has exquisite reliefs and two
monumental stelae of major historical significance. They
relate the feats of the Athlete King Amenophis (the
Egyptian version of Hercules) in Syria and Nubia. Amada
is sure to be given high priority by the architects charged
with "removing" the sanctuaries of Nubia.
The great temple of Derr stands a short distance away,
almost entirely cut out of the rock on the east bank of
the river. Built by Rameses II and dedicated to the sun-
god Re, the third god of the Empire, it is one of the
temples which the United Arab Republic has agreed to
offer, wall by wall, to foreign museums as a grant for
helping to save the monuments of Nubia.
Beyond Derr the Nile valley again trends to the
southwest and We emerge onto a broad expanse of plain
at Aniba (ancient Miam), the present and former capital
of Lower Nubia. But nothing now recalls the splendours
of the palaces of the Nubian viceroys which must once
have been built here. Perhaps they are buried in the
sand waiting to be discovered.
A NEW THREAT TO PHILAE. The danger to which the
island of Philae is exposed is quite unlike that of any of the
other temples of Nubia which threaten to be engulfed by the
Aswan High Dam. At present the island is tragically under
water all year long except for a brief three-month period.
12
Unesco-Raccah
When the new dam is built, Philae will find itself in a "sandwich"
position between the two dams and a major portion of Its
monuments will be permanently out of water all year long.
But the danger to Philae will be even greater than before since
the base of the temples up to a height of 15 feet will be attacked
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
We know though that these viceroys were important
noblemen who were virtually independent, and that their
principal tombs are found at Thebes, the great capital of
the Egyptian Empire. One of these, the Tomb of Huy,
Viceroy of Nubia in the reign of Tutankhamon, contains
a series of remarkable paintings in multiple register.
They show this high official receiving his appointment as
"overseer of the southern lands," accepting the royal
signet-ring of gold investing him with full powers, and a
procession of Nubian princesses arrayed in the habit of
court ladies. One of them is represented riding in a
chariot drawn by oxen and with a parasol of ostrich
feathers growing out of her diadem.
Finally the viceroy Huy is seen receiving the homage
of the princes of Aniba, foremost among whom is a
certain Heka Nefer, "the prince of Miam," richly clad in
the dress of a Nubian chief: a leopard skin on his back
and girded around his waist like an apron, ostrich
feathers in his hair, and large rings in his ears. He is
shown prostrating himself before the viceroy.
From inscriptions in Nubia and Egypt and other
sources, we have now been able to piece together part
of Heka Nefer's life story and thus get a better idea
of his station and origins. The son of a rebel chief of
Nubia, he had been brought north to the royal palace at
the time of a revolt suppressed by Pharaoh's officers. His
standing as a Nubian prince and as the son of a local
chief was recognized, and he was sent to the college of
royal princes at Thebes where he became an intimate
friend of the king's children, sharing their up-bringing,
their games and sports and their military training.
Thereafter, thoroughly steeped in the sophisticated
culture of the capital and an enthusiast of Pharaonic
civilization, he returned to his warmer native land to
fulfil his role of prince. Nevertheless, he donned native
dress again and garbed thus he greeted the viceroy.
Perhaps one day before Nubia disappears, excavations
in the region may uncover the remains of his palace as
well as his tomb hidden in some valley of the Libyan
range. Who knows, it may be in an even more isolated
and distant spot than the tomb of Pennut, another
high official who served under Rameses VI thirty-two
centuries ago, and whose burial chapel, located on the
slope of a solitary hill two miles from Aniba, is covered
with well-preserved paintings (it is hoped to remove it to
a neighbouring oasis).
Looming up almost across the river from Aniba, stands
the rock of Ibrim dominating the whole vast plain that
stretches south from the capital of Nubia. Since remote
times it has been the site of the largest fortress in the
region. At the foot, facing the Nile are rock chapels
whose paintings should be removed to a safe place.
Let us leave the chapels that dot the banks, the
prehistoric cave paintings rivalling in beauty those in the
"rock shelter" at Wadi es Sebua, with their galloping herds
of oryxes, ibexes, giraffes, elephants and ostriches, and
let us push deeper south to where the Nile grows wider
as it winds towards its source.
About 200 miles upstream from the First Cataract, a
long way from Thebes, the official city of the god Amon
and even more distant from Tanis, the capital chosen by
Rameses on the Eastern Delta, stands the grandiose site
of Abu Simbel. It is virtually on the same latitude as the
diorite quarries in the western desert to which Egyptian
working parties of the Old Kingdom swarmed in search
of the ornately-grained green stone favoured by King
Khephren's sculptors for his statues in the Valley Temple
of the Second Pyramid.
Here, at the scene of one of man's supreme achieve¬
ments, we have reached the climax of our journey in
Lower Nubia. The monumental majesty of Abu Simbel
completely dwarfs other sanctuaries nearby, although
these are by no means lacking in treasures. Two of them
the rock chapels of Abu Oda and Jebel Shams were
heWn out of the living rock at the command of the last
kings of the 18th dynasty (about 1340 B.C.) one of which,
later transformed into a church, still enshrines the oldest
Nubian inscriptions of Christian Egypt.
The two rock temples of Abu Simbel (the Great Temple
of Rameses and the Small Temple of Nefertari), rise on
either side of a river of golden sand running down from
a natural amphitheatre of pink sandstone. The most
important sanctuaries built by Rameses in Lower Nubia,
they are also the most remote, the most harmonious and
the most colossal. Rameses built temples all over Nubia,
each dedicated to one of the gods of the Empire. At Abu
Simbel he brought the three great gods together and
added his own image, raised to divine rank.
Here, therefore, he reigns, a god among gods,
surrounded by his entire family. Rameses imposed the
cult of the Sun-King, born of the sun, the spouse of a
goddess transformed into a woman, the ravishing Ne¬
fertari. The queen is depicted in the flower of her beauty
in the temple dedicated to her by Rameses to the north
of his own sanctuary, identifying her with Hathor, the
presiding goddess.
Unesco-Laurenza Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo
Dy the waters several times a day. Under this treatment the
monuments will eventually disintegrate and crumble to the
ground. To save the sacred island it is envisaged to raise a
protective wall around Philae, thus creating an artificial lake
amidst which the island with its monuments will be perma
nently above water and hence out of danger. Left, photo
taken in January when only the tip of the Temple of Isis is
above ; centre, as waters subside, the temple and the "kiosk"
of Trajan (on right) appear once more; right, the island as
it appears when completely freed from the invading Nile.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE LEGACY OF NUBIA (Continued)
Born aloft like a Venus
emerging from the waves
The four colossi, adorning the façade of the Great
Temple and standing over 65 feet high are an un¬
forgettable sight. The extraordinary harmony and
delicacy of the heads completely counterbalances the
deliberate heaviness of the bodies and the huge mass of
this fantastic pylon cut from the very face of the rock.
From the wall of her small temple, Nefertari seems to
become alive and to step forward, radiant in her feminine
beauty, towards her eternal destiny. It is impossible, in
a few words, to attempt to describe the magnificence of
this temple of temples, the purity of the carvings in the
queen's sanctuary, the images of Nefertari as a young ,
girl, surrounded by wondrously slender, graceful
goddesses, who seem to bear her aloft like a nascent Venus
emerging from the waves..
On the walls of the Great Temple, historic scenes of
the utmost importance, royal inscriptions, and murals
heralding a new trend in art, precede eloquent religious
scenes which lead to the sanctuary where four statues
again show the king in the company of his fellow gods.
Politics and diplomacy often take precedence over prayer
in this temple of Rameses with its dual message.
The scenes, the inscriptions, the Osirian pillars in the
first hall all recall the innovations of the great king. They
mark a major turning point in the history of Egypt and
find a small echo to this day in other parts of the globe.
Thus the chronicle which Rameses caused to be carved on
the south side of the terrace the Marriage stela with its
surface now scarred and pitted with the wind-blown sand
of centuries commemorates the conclusion of an age¬
long struggle between two peoples.
The Stela recounts the marriage of a Hittite princess
whose epic story (see article page 31) unforgotten up
to recent times, inspired one of Leconte de Lisle's Poèmes
Barbares. The frail princess Nefru Re is depicted on the
arched top of the Stela which then tells how Rameses
ventured forth in mid-winter, crossing his northern
frontiers to meet her in his fortified castle. With the
appearance of the Sun-King a miracle occurred; the mists,
enveloping the earth were dispelled and the sun shone
forth from a clear sky, spreading warmth over all things.
A St. Martin's summer had been brought about by the son
of Re, and the princess immediately received the name
occasioned by this phenomenon. Henceforth she was
Maat Hor Nefru Re "She who sees Horus, the life force of
the Sun God."
Protected where they stand in their hallowed bay,
preserved in the rock so frail that no water can touch
them without disintegrating their stones, the two temples
of Abu Simbel cannot be allowed to perish. They must
remain facing the rising sun whose brilliant rays each
day awaken the colossal statues of the Great Rameses.
14
v r. ' x* f 4¿. -r-.-». . -r w - _^" *¿. « _
*st_1J
-:-""v* ~^:SL'
GODDESS WITH VULTURE HEAD¬
DRESS. One of the six huge figures
carved in pure Graeco-Roman style on
the outer wall at the rear of the temple
of Kalabsha. Goddess (above) wears a
vulture headdress, symbol of the god¬
dess-mothers. These were often worn by
Egypt's queens including the famous
Cleopatra. The headdress is surmounted
by the sun nestled between the horns
of the cow of heaventhe hieroglyphic
for Isis. Temple of Kalabsha (left) built
in the reign of the Roman emperor
Augustus on the site of a sanctuary
dating from the 15th century B.C., is the
most important monument in Nubia after
Abu Simbel and Philae. Like the other
flooded Nubian temples, Kalabsha re¬
mains under the waters nine months of
the year. To save it, it must be taken
down and rebuilt on another site in Nubia.
Photos Documentation Centre on Egypt, Cairo
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The
thirsty
lands
These two photos symbolize the dilemma of
Nubia: how to bring water to its thirsty
lands and people and yet safeguard the treasures
placed in jeopardy. Right, site of the future
High Dam at Aswan in the dry season. The
blazing sun has cracked the river-bed of the
Nile creating a pattern resembling a vast
crazy paving; below, colonnade of the " birth
house " in the forecourt of the Temple of
Isis on Philae, the sacred isle, which is one of
a group close to the site of the new Aswan Dam.
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
.
HL
,<*¥
Photos © Albert Raccah.
The essential part of Egypt is a
green gash of teeming life
cutting across brown desert
wastes. The line of demarcation
between life and nonlife is start-
lingly clear: one may stand at the
edge of the cultivation with one
foot on the irrigated black soil and
one foot on the desert sands. The
country is essentially rainless; only
the waters of the Nile make life
possible where otherwise there
would be endless wastes of sand
and rock.
But what a life the Nile makes
possible! The little agricultural
villages contract themselves within
the smallest compass, so as not to
encroach upon the fertile fields of
rice, cotton, wheat, or sugar cane.
When properly cared for, the land
can yield two crops a year...
The richness is confined to the
green Nile Valley. Only 3.5 per
cent of the modern state of Egypt
is cultivable and habitable. The
remaining 96.5 per cent is barren
and uninhabitable desert. Today
perhaps 99.5 per cent of the popu¬
lation lives on the 3.5 per cent of
the land which will support popu¬
lation. That means an even
greater contrast between the
desert and the sown, and it means
that on the cultivable land there
is a concentration of people close
to the saturation point.
John A. Wilson
quoted from "The Intellectual
Adventure of Ancient Man."
Published by University of Chicago
Press © 1946.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ABU
Marriage
of the
Colossal
and the
Beautiful
Rameses II was one of the greatest
builders among all the rulers of Egypt.
The great rock-hewn ensemble of Abu
Simbel is his most monumental and
glorious architectural achievement.
The Great Temple (right) measures
108 feet in height, 124 feet In width.
On the façade, the four colossi, 67
feet high, representing the Pharaoh,
look down from the cliff on to a maj¬
estic sweep of the Nile. Above right,
a detail of one of the giant statues'
feet. The scale of its proportions
can be judged from that of the human
figure. One of Rameses' children is
visible between the colossal legs.
CONTINUED ON PAGES I8 TO 22
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ABU SIMBEL (Continued)
îgm^Fttiw
r*
Unesco-Laurenza
THEY SAID IT WITH FLOWERS
...THREE THOUSAND YEARS AGO
For over 3,000 years, six mighty figures (opposite page) have
flanked the portal to the Nefertari Temple at Abu Simbel.
Two figures of Nefertari stand between those of Rameses II.
On the interior walls of the Temple are carved figures of the
queen (right) and Rameses II (far right) making offerings of
papyrus flowers. Head carved on the sistrum, the ritual ins¬
trument held In the queen's right hand is that of Hathor, also
seen on detail of pillar (above). In place of the second ritual
sistrum, the queen holds a sheaf of papyrus whose leaves,
when shaken, give off a sound similar to that of the sistrum.
The huge heads (top of page) from the nearby Great Temple
façade are 13 feet from ear to ear. Mouths are 42 inches wide.
18
if?
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
Photos Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ABU SIMBEL (Continued)
"Try to imagine the Cathedral of Notre Dame carved out of a
single block of stone... nothing in our part of the world can
convey an Idea of the labour that must have gone into this
gigantic achievement." Thus wrote the French author, Maxime
20
FIRST PHOTOGRAPH: 1850. This is the first photograph ever made of the Great Temple of Abu Simbel.
A daguerrotype, it was taken by Maxime du Camp in 1850. The façade lies half hidden under the sand which
obstructed the Temple so completely in 1817 that it lay hidden even though the Nefertari Temple was known.
When discovered, the 67-foot statues were so deeply buried that no one could tell if they were sitting or standing.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. February 1960
du Camp, after visiting Abu Simbel 100 years ago. Above
left, first panoramic photograph of Abu Simbel taken in 1905,
showing the river of sand flowing down between the temples.
Above, Great Temple (on left) and Temple of Nefertari today.
n September 1812, a 28-year-old Swiss
traveller named Johann Ludwig Burck-
hardt arrived in Cairo. His object was to
join a caravan going to Fezzan and from
there to explore the sources of the Niger.
While waiting for this opportunity to occur
he decided to travel up the Nile to see the
monuments of ancient Egypt which were then for the first
time being revealed to Westerners.
At this early period of the 19th century it was impossible
for Europeans to journey up the Nile by boat beyond the
town of Derr, some 150 miles south of Aswan. And no one,
until then, had yet undertaken the arduous journey by
land except one Englishman named Legh who in February
1813 had obtained permission to travel by camel to the
fortress of Ibrim, 15 miles or so south of Derr.
But Burckhardt was no ordinary European. He had
studied Arabic in London and Cambridge. He had spent
several years in Syria as well as the Lebanon and Pal¬
estine in the guise of a Mohammedan trader from India,
and had gained such an intimate knowledge of Arabic, of
Islamic religion and of the manners and customs of the
people that he had come to be considered as learned as
the Ulema themselves, if not more so. He was later to
become the first European to perform the rites of
pilgrimage at Mecca and adopted the name Ibrahim ibn
Abdallah (he is the famous "Sheikh Ibrahim").
And so early in 1813 Burckhardt decided to explore the
Nile valley south of Derr by land, and struck across the
desert with his camels, venturing into the Sudan as far as
Dongola well beyond the Third Cataract of Dal. On his
way southward he followed the right (East) bank of the
Nile, halting at Ibrim and then at the tiny hamlet of
Ferrayg where he inquired about the Pharaonic ruins
which might be visited in the region. He was told that
at a place called Ebsambal (Abu Simbel) just north of
Ferrayg, but on the other side of the river, there existed
a small temple. The inhabitants, it should be noted, spoke
of only one temple, and eyen a year later the people of
Derr and Ibrim told a traveller that only one existed.
On his return trip northward from the Sudan,
Burckhardt now followed the left (West) bank of the Nile
in order to explore the sites on that side of the river and
particularly Abu Simbel which no one had yet described.
On March 22, 1813 he made a halt on the plateau, left
his camels with his Nubian guide and went down into the
sand-choked ravine. He inspected the small temple (of
Nefertari) at his leisure and then, as time was passing,
prepared to rejoin his companion.
"Having, as I supposed, seen all the antiquities of
Ebsambal", he wrote in his travel diary, "I was about to
ascend the sandy side of the mountain by the same way
I had descended; when having luckily turned more to the
southward, I fell in with what is yet visible of four
immense colossal statues cut out of the rock, at a distance
of about two hundred yards from the temple..."
Almost totally buried in the sand for more than a
thousand years, the façade of the Great Temple of Abu
Simbel and as Burckhardt quite logically surmised an
edifice hollowed out of the rocky cliff were thus restored
to their rightful place as one of the most stupendous
monuments of ancient Egyptian architecture.
We do not know if he made a written report of his
discovery before returning to Cairo in June 1815. We do
know though that the British consul-general in Alex¬
andria at the time, Colonel Ernest Missett, whom
Burckhardt met, did speak of the find to others and
spurred interest in it. No longer was Nubia an unknown,
inaccessible region, and the path now was open for the
intrepid traveller to reveal its archaeological treasures.
Explorers were soon at the site but they were either
disheartened by the huge mountain of sand blocking the
façade or failed to get the local help to clear it. The
colossal facade was to wait until 1817 before its entrance
was first freed from the sand by Giovanni Battista Belzoni
himself a colossus of a man, six feet seven inches tall
and of amazing strength. Belzoni arrived at Abu Simbel
CONT'D ON NEXT FAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ABU SIMBEL (Continued)
Drawing by David Roberts. Photo Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo
CARVED INTO THE MOUNTAIN: A drawing made in 1855 of the inner entrance hall of the Great Temple with
its eight colossal statues of Rameses II, each 30 feet high. Statues stand knee deep in the sand. Each is hold¬
ing the crook and the scourgethe two symbols of kingly power. To penetrate the temple the artist had to let
himself slide down the steep mounds of sand which blocked the doorway. Everything about the Great Temple Is
colossal. Carved out of solid rock it Is 108 feet high, 124 feet wide and goes over 200 feet into the mountain.
in September 1816 at the head of an expedition supported
and financed by the new British consul-general, Henry
Salt.
Like his predecessors he was dogged with difficulties and
the refusal of the local people to help. Finally on August
1, 1817 the Great Temple of Abu Simbel was officially
opened in the presence of Belzoni, Salt's secretary H.W.
Beechey and two Royal Navy captains.
Twenty-two days were needed to remove enough sand
to reach the entrance. For the first five days 100 local
workers did the clearing, and when they refused to go
on, Belzoni, Beechey, the two Navy captains, a Turkish
soldier and a Greek servant took over alone, working 10
hours a day with the heat averaging 112° F. in the shade
(44° C). They worked from dawn to eight in the morning
and from two p.m. (the mountain then shaded them)
until dusk. The sand removed rose up 50 feet.
As they were consolidating the menacing mass of sand
a toad emerged from the opening they had made in the
upper left-hand corner of the temple door. When the
creature had disappeared the whole team slid through
the small aperture, crawled over the sand barrier filling
the entrance corridor and followed the gentle slope down
to the interior hall with its Osirian pillars. By the light
of their torches and despite the smoke and stifling heat,
they gazed in awe at the colossal figures before them and
at all the reliefs they saw in the succeeding chambers.
One question was still unanswered: were the colossal
statues of the façade standing or sitting? This was
answered in the winter of 1818-1819 when a large expedi¬
tion entirely cleared the southern (extreme left) colossus.
22
As a safety measure the legs of the statue next to it were
also cleared thus revealing the now famous Greek
inscriptions dating back to the Nubian campaign of
Psammetichus II. (see page 39).
From then on, the great names in Egyptology visited
Abu Simbel and drew on its riches : Bonomi, Lane, Burton,
Wilkinson, Champollion, Rosellini, Hay, Lepsius, Mariette,
and many others.
Despite repeated clearing operations, the sands kept
blowing back into the Abu Simbel ravine from the
Western desert. In 1892 sand-diversion walls were erected
on the summit of the desert plateau. In 1902, when
the level of the Aswan dam was first raised, Gaston Mas-
pero, then director of the Egyptian Antiquities Service
instructed the architect Barsanti to reinforce these di¬
version walls. Thus, it was only in 1909-1910, when all
danger from the blowing desert had passed, that all the
sand was at last cleared by Barsanti from the four
colossi, from the terrace, the forecourt and the temple
approaches.
It is thus barely fifty years since the monumental
ensemble of Abu Simbel has really been revealed to us,
thanks to the successive efforts of these men. Had it not
been unknown and buried in the sand for so many cen¬
turies it might well have ranked among the Seven Wonders
of the world. From Burckhardt to Barsanti, travellers,
explorers and scientists of all nationalities followed each
other during the 19th century in order to free one of the
finest masterpieces of Pharaonic art from its tomb of
sand. Their example justifies the hope that a second
wave of international solidarity will save the great temple
of Abu Simbel from the watery grave that now awaits it.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
MEDITERRANEAN
PORT SAID
GAZA
EL ALAMEIN EL ARICH
ISMAILIA
THE NILE
waterway of
art & history
On the banks of the Nile innumerable
artistic treasures and historical re¬
mains testify to the events of a glorious
past. The construction of the new
High Dam at Aswan and the artificial
lake which this will create (shaded on
the map) will flood forever hundreds
of sites in ancient Nubia in both
Egyptian and Sudanese territory. The
Nubian monuments are shown in red.
GIZEH CAIRO
SUEZ
SAKKARA
%»
EL FAYUM BENI SUEF'
SINAI
EL MINYA
fl"V i 1£TELL EL AMARNA
FARAFRA OASIS
ffffff
ASSIUT
KHARGA OASIS
RED
SEA
1st CATARACT
SADD EL AALI
KERTASSI
BEIT EL WALI
KALABSHA
Ê
DAKKA"
WADI ES SEBUA
ANIBA I
DERR
ABU SIMBEL
EGYPT_
SUDAN
.AK.SJHA ,
LLLLUf f|
BUHEN WADI HALFA
2nd CATARACT
SEMNA ? KUMMA
fMm "*
.o
RiFAAT NASR
m
AKASHA^
3rd CATARACT
M
Map especially drawn for "The Unesco Courier" by Rifaac Nasr
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Photos Christiane Desroches- Noblecourt
WADI ES SEBUA. This
name ("The Valley of the Lions"
in Arabic) comes from the
sacred avenue lined by sphinxes
which leads from the Nile (in
background) to the great rock-
hewn temple dedicated by
Rameses II to the god Amon.
DAKKA. Graeco-Roman sanc¬
tuary dedicated to Thot, god
of wisdom and writing. It was
built in the third century B.C.
by King Ergamenes of Ethiopia.
This is the only temple of Nubia
facing north instead of south.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
^fc.
Mí
I
Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
ABU SIMBEL. Two of the eight pillars representing the god Osiris with the features of
Rameses II. The statue-pillars are located in the inner underground court of the Great Temple.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
jr~"
ABU SIMBEL. Four colossal statues of the Pharaoh Rameses II flank the entrance portal
to the Great Temple, built by Rameses II to honour the gods Horus, Amon and Ptah, as well
as his own deified image. Topping the façade is a row of baboons to greet the rising sun.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
ABU SIMBEL. Profiles of the giant statues of Rameses II
on the facade of the Great Temple. They are carved out of
sandstone rock on the western cliff of the Nile In Lower Nubia.
I
Photos Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
ABU SIMBEL. Temple of Queen Nefertari. Part of façade of
the Small Temple dedicated by Rameses II to his queen and to
the goddess Hathor. Nefertari stands between figures of Pharaoh.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
PHILAE. The Graeco-
Roman "Kiosk" with its
fourteen imposing col¬
umns, erected by the
Roman Emperor Trajan,
seen here isolated by the
flood waters of the Nile.
Christiane Desroches-
Noblecourt
PHILAE. Façade of the
first great pylon of the
Temple of Isis. Motif to
the left of the gateway
represents the Pharaoh
making offerings to Isis.
© Albert Raccah
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
PHILAE 'PEARL OF EGYPT'. The celebrated colonnade on the island of Philae leading
to the Great Temple of Isis. The colonnade was built during the reigns of Augustus and
Tiberius. Philae's temples form a grandiose ensemble, with the Nile and the island of Bigeh
as a backdrop, when the last rays of the setting sun strike its rose-hued sanctuaries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
.. .
<3C> *
*i r
GERF HUSEIN. Columns outside the temple dedicated by Rameses II to the god Ptah
and hewn out of the rock overlooking the Nile. In the past a stairway lined by crouching
stone rams led to the temple with its giant statues, but all traces of it have vanished.
Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
Documentation Centre on Ancient Eçjypt, Cairo
Eaten away by the elements, lashed by sandstorms, the "Marriage stela" cut Into the sandstone rock on the terrace of the Great
Temple at Abu Simbel recalls some aged and yellowing document whose words can hardly be made out, yet whose story, once
deciphered, is all the more moving. The Stela tells of the marriage of Rameses II with the daughter of the King of the Hittites in the 13th
century B.C. On the fragment shown here, the princess is seen arriving followed by her father (right) wearing the ancestor of the
Phrygian cap. Rameses is on extreme left under the marriage dais. The marriage took place on a dull winter's day, but when the
pharaoh appeared the sun pierced the clouds. So the princess was named "She who sees Horus, the life force of the Sun God."
THE SUN WAS A WITNESS
AT PHARAOH'S MARRIAGE
by Jaroslav Cerny
Professor of Egyptology, Oxford University
W~W n immortal text graven in stone is one of the
M^M, precious records of the past threatened in
Nubia. It is the so-called "Marriage stela" of
W § King Rameses II of the XEXth Dynasty, Who
F ' reigned from 1290 to 1223 B.C. It is cut in the
vertical sandstone rock on the southern side of the
terrace of the larger rock temple at Abu Simbel and is
one of the copies of a document composed at Rameses II's
court and sent to various Egyptian temples to be
immortalized on their walls.
The copy at Abu Simbel is the only one to have come
down to us in its entirety; three others are known from
the temples of Aswan and Karnak in Egypt and from the
temple at Amara in the Sudan. None of these versions,
however, can vie with the one at Abu Simbel from the
point of view of preservation, though even at Abu Simbel
the inscription has not escaped some damage. To start
with, the sculptor who had been instructed to carve the
document in the rock did not find the available surface
sufficient. He succeeded in cutting only forty-one lines
of the inscription, and though he made his signs smaller
and smaller as he proceeded, he was forced to stop when
he had reached the bottom of the rock wall and so left
out the end of the story. Moreover, the inscription was
subsequently exposed to the weather for a long time
for centuries probably until it was finally completely
sanded up. By then sand driven against the inscription
had considerably obliterated the surface of the stone.
No wonder, therefore, that the German scholar Carl
Richard Lepsius, who was the first to study the stela in
December 1843, and again in August of the following year,
copied only eighteen lines, and these with many gaps,
the bottom of the stela being probably still beneath the
sand. It was only towards the end of the last century
that the French Egyptologist, E. Bouriant, recorded,
however imperfectly, the whole inscription. Much of the
original is badly mutilated by corrosion and often whole
words, even whole lines, are so indistinct, especially in
daylight, that a scholar can only hope to obtain a
satisfactory result by having enough time and strong
electric lighting by night at his disposal.
Such conditions were afforded to the scholars sent by
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
PHARAOH'S MARRIAGE (Continued)
THE WALLS SING
THE GLORY
OF RAMESES II
tfcyfcjfrf'
Cut into the rock walls of the first hall of
the Great Temple at Abu Simbel are the
stories of the exploits of a king who was
also a god for his subjects. The principal
story is told in the poem of Kadesh, scene
of the battle where Rameses II by his
personal courage saved his army from utter
defeat by the Hittites. These works are
considered to be among the most out¬
standing examples of narrative poetry of the
period and the figurative representations
are of a beauty worthy to accompany the
poems. Right, from the southern wall,
in another of his campaigns, Rameses in
his war chariot pursues the enemy. To
leave his hands free he has tied the reins
round his waist, guiding his team of horses
by movements of his body. Beneath the
enemy citadel (bottom left of the bas-relief)
a shepherd flees before the Pharaoh (detail
below). Opposite page, below, a warrior
dies, pierced by the Pharaoh's spear, in a
scene from another battle on the same wall.
Unesco during the past four years to co-operate with the
Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, in Cairo.
Moored for weeks in front of the temple, they had both
time and strong electric reflectors, but even so, many
hours of night work were required before the inscription
yielded all its contents. The story which the inscription
has to tell is remarkable enough to deserve the attention
of anyone interested in ancient history.
The "Marriage stela" records the marriage of Rameses II
with a princess sent to Egypt by her father, the king
of the Hittites, to strengthen the peace between their two
countries, whose relations had been far from peaceful in
the past. Ever since the reign of Rameses IPs father,
king Seti I, the Hittites, whose ¡kingdom was situated in
Asia Minor, had been pushing south into Syria, a country
which the Egyptians always considered as lying within
the sphere of their interest.
A military expedition led by Rameses II in the 5th
year of his reign (1285 B.C.), had resulted in the battle
of Kadesh, a town of great strategical importance on the
river Orontes in Syria. The Egyptian army still on the
march and not in closed ranks had been taken by surprise
by the Hittites and their allies, and only Rameses II's
personal bravery had saved the Egyptians from a
disastrous defeat. Despite the Egyptian claim, the battle
must have been undecisive, and fighting probably went on
for some time until a peace treaty was concluded between
Rameses II and the Hittite king, Muwattali, in the 21st
year of Rameses' reign, that is in 1269 B.C. The text
of the treaty was drawn up in two versions, "one' in
Egyptian and in hieroglyphs, the other in the Babylonian
language and in cuneiform writing. Both versions are
still preserved.
One would expect that the conclusion of the treaty was
the right moment for the diplomatic marriage. The
"Marriage stela" is not, however, dated in Year 21, the year
of the peace treaty, but in Year 34 when Rameses II was
already a man of about sixty.
It is best to leave it to the stela itself to recount the
event as well as all that had led up to it. After a long
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
I
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
"TrTT,
M ÄS5£M if * '
CZ
1
!'^^.'?
/-
m
r'-;
~--¿
£1 2
lit
ai*
y ^\ / \
'"VV.'-'V V" rí
*' W¿- "»
Photos Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo
M.1:'
introduction filling the first twenty-five lines and
containing the customary adulation and praise of the
Egyptian king, the text continues:
"Then he (that is, Rameses II) equipped his infantry
and chariotry so that they might strike against the land
of the Hittites. He seized it alone by himself before the
eyes of his whole army. He made a name for himself in
it for ever. They will remember the victory of his arm.
Who escaped his hand, those he abuses; his might is
among them like a burning torch. And after they had
spent many years, while their country was perishing and
devastated by disasters from year to year through the
might of the great living god Rameses, the great king
of the Hittites wrote appeasing his
majesty, magnifying his might,
extolling his victory and saying:
'Desist from thy discontent, re¬
move thy punishment, let us
breathe the breath of life. Thou
art the son of (the god) Sutekh in
truth! He ordained to thee the
land of the Hittites and we bring
tributes consisting of whatever
thou desirest. We carry them to
thy noble palace. Behold, we are
under thy feet, O victorious king,
it is done to us according to all
that thou hast ordained.'
"'And the great king of the Hitti¬
tes wrote appeasing His Majesty
year after year, but he never
listened to them. And when they
saw their country in this bad con¬
dition under the great wrath of
the king of Egypt, the great king
of the Hittites spoke to his soldiers
and his notables saying: 'It is a
long time that our land has been
in decay and our lord, (the god)
Sutekh angry with us. Heaven
does not send rain upon us, all countries are enemies
fighting us all. Let us despoil ourselves of all our
property, my eldest daughter at the head of them, and let
us carry gifts of propitiation to the goodly god (Rameses),
so that he may give us peace and we may live.' Then he
caused his eldest daughter to be carried and splendid
tribute before her, consisting of gold, silver, common
metal, slaves and horses without number, oxen goats and
sheep in tens of thousands...
"One went to give the message to His Majesty saying:
'Behold, the great king of the Hittites has caused his
eldest daughter to be brought with many tributes
consisting of all (kinds of) things. They cover her who
is at the head of them, the princess of the Hittites, and
the great notables of the land of the Hittites who carry
them. They have behind them many mountains and
difficult passes and have reached the frontiers of His
Majesty. Let the army and notables go to receive them.'
And His Majesty was delighted and the palace was in joy
when he heard this marvellous event which had never
before been experienced in Egypt...
"When the daughter of the great king of the Hittites
proceeded towards Egypt, the infantry, chariotry and
notables of His Majesty were in her following, mixed with
the infantry and chariotry of the Hittites, foreign
warriors and Egyptian troops alike... And the great kings
of all countries which they passed were puzzled, and
turned back discomfited when they saw psople of the
land of the Hittites joined with soldiers of the king of
Egypt."
Here the text of Abu Simbel abruptly comes to an end,
but some idea of the sequel is conveyed by the
fragmentary versions of Karnak and Amara. From
these it can be gathered that when the princess and her
convoy reached the residence, Rameses found the Hittite
princess very beautiful; he installed her in his palace and
was seen every day in her company... From then on, the
great enemy of old, the people of the Hittites, were like
subjects of Egypt, whose people could live in peace and
without fear because of the victories of Rameses II.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
PHILAE
The sacred isle
by Etienne Drioton
Professor at the Collège de France
The riches of the island of Philae with its exquisite temples
and colonnades and the graceful " kiosk " of Trajan have
consecrated its renown. The temples are not the work of a
single pharaoh. Each new king embellished and extended
what his predecessor had done. But practically all the build¬
ings which still stand are due to pharaohs of the Hellenistic
period or to the Roman Emperors who governed after them.
Right, bas-relief on the first pylon of the Temple of Isis shows
Horus between his mother Isis and the goddess Hathor.
Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
For the generation before mine, the temple of Phi¬
lae was still the pearl of Egypt.
My teacher, Georges Bénédite, who copied its
inscriptions in 1887 and 1888, ten years before the
building of the first Aswan dam was begun, often
spoke of Philae as one of the most remarkable experiences
of his life. He would describe his feeling of enchantment
each time he crossed the grim granite-rock desert of
Aswan and came within sight of the sacred island of Isis.
There stood the temple of the goddess reflecting her
pylons, porticoes and kiosks in the blue waters of the Nile,
surrounded by palm-trees and acacia mimosas. It was,
Bénédite said, the vision of Paradise for one emerging
from hell.
But it was not for its beauty alone today somewhat
diminished, since the flooding of the island throughout
most of the year has destroyed the vegetation that Phi¬
lae was famous in ancient times. In the last period of
its history, it' had, with the adjacent islands, become one
of the great religious centres of ancient Egypt, replacing
Abydos in the cult of Osiris.
Philae is the smallest of three islands, which are the
remains of a granitic shelf, running from south-west to
north-east, from which the rapids of the First Cataract
begin, and winch the Nile has demolished in carving out
its course. Philae is also the most easterly of these
islands. To the, west, separated from it by a narrow
channel, is the island of Bigeh, twelve times its size;
then comes El-Hêseh, three times larger than Bigeh,
beside the west bank of the river.
On his journey about 450 B.C., Herodotus did not get as
far as this region. He stopped at Elephantine, four and a
half miles below Philae, and merely questioned the in¬
habitants about points of interest that lay beyond.
From what they said he gathered that the country above
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Unesco-Laurenza
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
PHILAE
sacred
isle
(Continued)
Flute player
Elephantine was mountainous and that one could see the
chasms from which the Nile issued, between the crags
named Krophi and Mophi. However, he noted nothing of
interest before the island of Takhompso, twenty miles
farther south. There was, then, presumably nothing
remarkable about the region at that time.
This agrees with negative archaeological data. The
oldest building remaining on the island of Philae is the
small temple of Nectanebo II (359-341 B.C.). This monu¬
ment is dedicated to Isis, identified with Hathor and asso¬
ciated with the gods of Bigeh.
The remains of the temple of Bigeh are the façade of
a vestibule built under Ptolemy XIII (father of the cele¬
brated Cleopatra) and the central part of a pylon
decorated under the reign of the Emperor Augustus. The
building replaced another one, dating perhaps as far
back as Sesostris III (1887-1850 B.C.), and in any case as
far as Thutmosis III (1504-1450 B.C.) and Amenophis II
(1450-1425 B.C.). These last two kings had adorned it with
statues. The gods worshipped there were those of Ele¬
phantine, the ram Khnum and his companion goddesses,
assimilated to Hathor. Nothing in the composition of its
pantheon revealed any particular pre-eminence given
either to Osiris or to Isis.
However, their supremacy was established in the area
by the first century A.D. The historian Diodorus Siculus
wrote:
"Others maintain that the bodies of these two divinities
(Isis and Osiris) are not at Memphis, but near the fron¬
tier between Ethiopia and Egypt, in an island of the Nile,
near Philae, called for this reason 'the sacred plain'.
The monuments of the island are shown in support of this
opinion: the tomb of Osiris, venerated by the priests
throughout Egypt, and the 360 vessels for libations
surrounding it. The priests of the locality fill these vessels
with milk every day, and with lamentations invoke the
divinities by name. Apart from the priests, no one is
allowed on the island."
Hieroglyphic inscriptions carved in the temple of Philae
confirm and add to the information given by Diodorus
:o-L-'' , ^êWSSêM
-^ . Ä
m
\m\í
m
fe*í
ê'i-t *
If
fei
^êVj
2d
Siculus concerning the group of sacred islands at Philae.
In particular, a divine edict on the subject is inscribed in
two versions on the portal of the Emperor Hadrian. The
better-preserved of them may be translated as follows:
"The Holy Mound is the sacred golden domain of Osiris
and his sister Isis. It was predestined therefore from the
beginning (of the world)... Milk shall not be lacking to
this Mount of the Sacred Wood, nor to the temple where
Osiris is buried. Let there be provided for him, round this
place, 365 tables of offerings, upon which there shall be
palm leaves, in order that libations may not cease, that
water may never be lacking about him. Let there every
day be divine service by the appointed high priest;' let
there be a libation to Isis, Lady of Philae, when the liba¬
tion of each day is poured. Let there be no beating of
drums or playing of harps or flutes. No man shall ever
enter here; no one, great or small, shall tread upon this
spot. Nor shall any bird be hunted, nor any fish taken,
within 40 cubits to the south, to the north, to the west,
to the east. No one here shall raise his voice during the
sacred time of the days when Isis, Lady of Philae, who is
enthroned, shall be here to pour the libation each tenth
day. Isis, Lady of Philae, will embark for the Sacred
Mound on the holy days, in the sacred bark of which the
name is... (effaced).
"Re has signed this writ; Shu son of Re has signed
this writ; Kêb son of Shu has signed this writ, which
Thot himself has composed."
Photos Unesco-Raccah
Tambourine player
Harpist
Such was the religious character of Bigeh during the
second century A.D. All or part of it was sacred to Osiris
and had become, according to the Greek term, an Abaton,
that is, an area within which it was forbidden to pene¬
trate. The sleep of the dead god beneath his sacred wood
must not be disturbed. The same rule of silence was
imposed, during that period, in all the sanctuaries of
Osiris, notably those of Memphis and Abydos, which also
had their Abaton. But none of them achieved the fame
of Bigeh.
Close by this island dedicated to the dead god, Isis
in her temple of Philae belonged to the world of the
living. For this very reason, so as to provide a link with
the world of the departed, she devoted herself to
maintaining the cult of her brother-husband. On all holy
occasions, the idol of Isis was taken from its tabernacle,
embarked on the river and disembarked at Bigeh, where
it presided over the solemn libations at the tomb of Osiris.
The religious geography of the Philae site would be
incomplete if mention were omitted of the function of
the island of El-Hêséh. The excavations carried out by
the American archaeologist G.A. Reisner have led to the
discovery of some funeral stelae which prove that the
westernmost and largest island in the group contained a
necropolis in which the faithful could be buried as near
to him as possible, though the Abaton discipline kept
them away from the tomb of Osiris. The custom was
inherited from the oldest traditions of Abydos.
As we see, the history of Philae mirrors the religious
trends which inspired Egypt in the days of the Ptolemies
and the Roman emperors. During the Assyrian, Babylo¬
nian and Persian invasions, the people gradually turned
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
away from the gods of the State religion, the sun gods
who had been unable to protect Egypt.
The faith of the people was transferred to Osiris, whose
legend explained all ills and authorized all hopes. The
cult of Osiris spread rapidly in those calamitous times,
and it is not surprising that it should then have reached
the threshold of the Cataract, where only the gods of
Elephantine had been honoured before.
The same trend was observable throughout Egypt. A
legend was created to explain why there were so many
temples of Osiris, for which the ritual required that each
of them should have a tomb of the god. Seth had cut
Osiris' body into sixteen parts and dispersed them
throughout Egypt in order to prevent Isis from reassem¬
bling them. She, however, went in search of these
fragments and, wherever she found one, she made a tomb
for it and consecrated a temple. Bigeh, for instance, was
supposed to possess Osiris' left leg.
But this arrangement did not lead to harmony amongst
the temple clergy; each temple claimed to be the sole
possessor of the authentic relics. So finally a legend
prevailed according to which Isis, in order to baffle Seth,
had deposited many coffins of Osiris in different parts
of Egypt; but only one of them, which could not be
distinguished from the others, contained the god's body.
Thereafter, each temple had no trouble in claiming that
its coffin was the right one Bigeh just like the others.
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
Another feature of religion at this time, unknown in the
Pharaonic period, was the tendency to give more impor¬
tance to Isis than to Osiris. This tendency is apparent
in the religious establishments of the Philae group. The
mortuary character of Osiris being accentuated, Isis
remained the living element, helpful to men, of the divine
couple. The temple of Philae was dedicated to her. We
should also bear in mind that, assimilated to the Great
Goddesses from Asia, it was she who, in the Roman
Empire, patronized the mysteries whose epithet was not
"Osirian" but "Isiac".
While speaking of all the mirabilia which antiquity
attributed to the Philae island group, we cannot fail to
mention that the old legend of the Krophi and Mophi
crags, sources of the Nile, as related by Herodotus, finally
took up its abode there. A bas-relief in the temple of
Philae shows, hidden under the earth in the midst of the
rocks of Bigeh, crouched in a cavern from which he dis¬
patches his flow of waters, the god Nile. The ancient
Egyptians, whose armies had many a time taken the road
to the Sudan, knew as well as we do that the Nile came
from much further south. But they also believed that its
peculiarities its regular floods and the fertilizing power
of its waters were due to a good genius hidden some¬
where in the bed of the river, perhaps in the Cataract, the
swirling of which proclaimed his presence and his activity.
This was not physical geography, but mythical geography.
WC-#*
3 /*.'? '
Unesco-Raccah
A magnificent view of the Temple of Isis at Philae. Foreground, the second pylon ; behind it the first pylon with white line near
top showing high water mark in the Nile flood season. In background, colonnade is just barely visible. The name Philae is said
to come from the word Pillaq meaning "the end", the island being at the southernmost limit of Egypt in the Nubia area. In the
Arab period it was known as Qasr (castle) or Qasr Anas el WogQd, a legendary personage from the Arabian Nights. The three mus¬
icians shown on opposite page are some of the charming representations found on the columns in the Temple of Hathor.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
k<*4MttULki V' kV
©Albert Raccah
THE SACRED BOAT of the goddess Isis, depicted here on a bas-relief in the Isis temple of
Philae. On all holy occasions, the idol of the goddess Isis was taken from her tabernacle,
embarked on the river and landed at the nearby island of Bigeh, where she presided over
the solemn libation ceremonies at the tomb of the god Osiris, her husband and brother.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
THE STEPS OF GREECE & ROME
by André Bernand
French National Council for Scientific Research
and Abdullatif Ahmed Aly
Professor, Faculty of Letters, Cairo University
A tragic paradox today presides over the destiny of Egyptian
Nubia. This region rich in relics of the Graeco-Roman period
I with oyer 1,200 Greek inscriptions, 16 free-standing temples,
and seven hewn out of the living rock, and with that
I architectural gem of the New Empire, the temple of
Rameses II at Abu Simbel, where one of the oldest Greek texts in the
world is to be found, is doomed to disappear for ever beneath the
waters of the High Dam.
The hand of man, which built these temples, carved these statues and
reliefs, and engraved these inscriptions, will, within a few years, undo
the work of ten centuries, to speak only of the Graeco-Roman period.
In point of fact, the geography and history of Nubia are stamped
throughout by paradox. Paradox of the Nile which unlike any other
river, widens as one approaches its source, and instead of flowing
straight, as is erroneously imagined, winds interminably round the Jebels
of Africa. Paradox of the valley, sometimes narrow, as at Bab-el-KoIab-
sha, where the cliffs form a kind of rocky gateway, under which the
waters of the Nile rush tumbling with a loud roar; sometimes, as in the
plain of Dakka, spread out to the width of a lake, where violent storms
sometimes blow up. Paradox of the desert land so barren that it is
difficult to imagine its supporting human life, yet bearing countless
traces of Graeco-Roman military and religious establishments.
Even the history of the region is paradoxical. Here, on the confines
of the Greek world, in these distant "marches" of the Roman world, the
mercenaries of King Psammetichus, of the Ptolemies and of the Roman
Emperors have left their imprint. What were they seeking in this far-off
land reaching almost to the' countries at the source of the Nile?
Inscriptions in verse
We can glean little about the history of Graeco-Roman Nubia from
the writers of antiquity. Herodotus, Diodorus Siculus, Agathar-
chides, Pliny and Ptolemy seldom give us any historical facts,
confining themselves mainly to ethnographic details, and much of what
they tell us is vague or fanciful.
Fortunately, the Greeks left behind over 1,200 inscriptions in Nubia,
but they have never been recorded in a Corpus and many of them are
little known, as few photographs have been taken of the sides and texts.
For the whole of Nubia, only about a dozen Latin inscriptions have been
traced; much still remains to be done, since the Roman occupation of
Nubia lasted from the time of Augustus to the end of the Roman Empire.
This epigraphic material, which is our chief source of information
about the history of Graeco-Roman Nubia, cannot be fully utilized until
all the texts have been deciphered from the stone itself, but they have
already been severely damaged by their annual immersion, particularly
those at Kalabsha, most of which were painted.
Thanks to Unesco's assistance and the work of the Documentation
Centre on Ancient Egypt, copies, rubbings and photographs were taken
of the inscriptions at Abu Simbel in April 1956 and of those at Jebel
Abu Duruah in September 1959. But all the other inscriptions will have
to be inspected again before the dam is completed.
It is particularly important to assemble these texts because Greek
inscriptions in Nubia are not usually, long. Seldom do we find inscrip¬
tions of more than a few words. Among these are the decree of Aurelius
Besario, the civil governor of the nome (ancient Egyptian province) of
Ombos and Elephantine, at Kalabsha, dating from the second third of the
Third century A.D. and giving the people of Talmis (the present day
Kalabsha), at the request of the high priest Myro, fifteen days to clear
the village of the swine that were polluting the temple; and the famous
inscription of King Silko, also at Kalabsha, dating from the Christian
period and commemorating the victories of the "king of the Nobatae
and of all the Ethiopians" at Talmis and Tophis over the Blemmyes who
had invaded his territory. At Abu Simbel, the longest text runs to no
more than five lines and records the expedition led by the mercenaries
of Psammetichus II in Upper Nubia.
However, the most striking and interesting inscriptions are a series
of epigrams or inscriptions in verse ten at Philae, five at .Talmis and
two at Pselhis. Elusive though their meaning often is, some of these
epigrams have great charm and reflect the high cultural level of the
pilgrims who used to visit the shrines of Isis.
One of them reads: "Our journey has brought us to the beautiful and
sacred island belonging to Isis, in furthermost Egypt, on the borders of
Ethiopia (i. e. Nubia) ; on the Nile we can see swift vessels bringing
(stones for) temples from Ethiopia to our country, a fertile granary, well
repaying a visit and revered by all mortals." The epigrams of Nubia
packed with delicate imagery in this vein, are difficult to decipher, and
it is to be hoped that a specialist on such inscriptions will be able
to come and read them on the spot before they disappear for ever.
Prayers in stone
The other Nubian inscriptions are either dedications of temples or
shrines, the names of priests or military leaders, or else pros-
cynemata, that is prayers by pilgrims to a god to recommend a
beloved one to his care. Many of these texts are dated, and most of the
others can be dated by analysis of the writing or archaeological study
of the building. Brief though they are, these relics provide some basis
for a history of Graeco-Roman Nubia, which has never yet been written,
for want of a Corpus of inscriptions. (1)
Yet what a stirring history it would be! At Abu Simbel, as we stand
dwarfed by the towering figure of Rameses II, our thoughts are carried
to Psammetichus' expedition to Nubia, the story of which is related on
the leg of one of the colossal statues, a precious record giving us insight
into the complex organization of the Egyptian army:
"The King Psammetichus came to Elephantine and those who accom¬
panied Psammetichus, son of Theokles, and made their way upstream
from Kerkis as far as the river was navigable had this inscription engra¬
ved. The foreign legion was under the command of Potasimto, while
the Egyptians were led by Amasis. This inscription was engraved by
Arkhôn, son of Amoibickhos, and Pelekos, son of Eudamos."
At Philae, with its countless inscriptions covering not only the faces
of the pylon but many other parts of the temple, we can picture the
throng of pilgrims at the splendid festivals in honour of Isis, who conti¬
nued to be worshipped long after the issue of Theodosius' decree (end of
fourth century A.D.). From the top of the citadel of Ibrim (the ancient
Primis), the Eastern gate of which is Roman, and where, to the north
of the plateau, rises a building dating from the time of Emperor Septi-
mius Severus (193-211 A.D.), our eyes can follow, from the dizzy slope
of the hill, the course of Queen Candace's desperate flight from the
armies of the Roman prefect, Gaius Petronius, in 22 B.C.
Desert garrison towns
From 29 A.D. onwards, the Romans established their protectorate of
Lower Nubia, but here again, they seem merely to have followed
the example set by the Ptolemies. It was under the rulers of the
Egyptian dynasty preceding the Ptolemies that Greeks came to settle in
the region extending from Philae southwards to Tachompso.
This part of the country never seems to have formed a separate nome
but was a territory attached to Philae. Judging by the inscriptions and
remnants of military structures, it was only in exceptional circumstances,
as during the war against Candace, that the Romans seem to have
driven further into Nubia.
The texts from Kalabsha (known as Talmis in Graeco-Roman times)
bear witness to the soldiers' cult of the Nubians' god Mandulis, who also
had his shrine at Philae, in the second century A.D. From those at
Pselkis (modern Dakka) we learn that the worship of Thot (Hermes)
was much practised. Both towns were obviously garrison centres guarding
the road to Africa and protecting Egypt against the southern "barba¬
rians."
Kertassi was both a military station and a quarrying centre supplying
(1) The only general reference work on Graeco-Roman Nubia h La Nubia
Romana by Ugo Monnerei de Villard (1941), running to a mere SO or sa pages.
CONT'D ON PAGE 50
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
OF MAAT
GODDESS OF PRECISION
Maât, goddess of precision and equi¬
librium, Is the emblem of the Documen¬
tation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo.
*^*~-*>*
N the desert shores of- the Nile in Lower
Nubia, a small army is waging a battle unique
in history. Its task is twofold: to safeguard a
heritage thousands of years old, and to record
the lesson its treasures have to teach before
they are obliterated within a few years.
This army with its headquarters in Cairo, its flotilla on
the Nile, its liaison officers, its reconnaissance patrols and
its working parties operating in the field, represents a new
force in the service of humanistic studies and the protection
öf beauty. For almost the past five years, under the sign
of Maât, Egyptian goddess of precision and equilibrium, it
has been running an inexorable race against time. It calls
itself in all simplicity Documentation Centre on Ancient
Egypt, a modest title indeed for a unique archaeological
operation about to assume truly Pharaonic proportions.
Under the torrid Nubian skies, the Egyptologists of the
Centre and their teams of technical experts have been on
the job year after year, advancing as fast as the exacting
nature of their operations allows. The time these
missions can spend in the field is limited by the intolerable
summer heat, the floods of the Nile and the inundations
caused by the sudden, unpredictable torrential rains which
sweep the upper reaches of the river. Every single day
is precious to them and following the Egyptian decision
to go ahead with the gigantic project of the Aswan High
Dam (the Sadd el-Aali) the time factor has assumed even
more dramatic proportions.
The Aswan project meant that the whole of Nubia with
its irreplaceable monuments would be submerged by an
artificial lake some 300 miles long. In the face of this
major undertaking, sparked by the imperative economic
needs of today, it would have been a waste of time to
deplore its effects on the civilizations of yesterday. There
was work to be done, and done quickly.
At the beginning of September 1955, the first teams of
Egyptologists arrived on the Abu Simbel site, the most
important in the whole of Nubia. Here, twenty-five miles
north of the Sudanese border, and downstream from the
second cataract, the awe-inspiring tawny facades of the
two sanctuaries of Rameses II still stand today in the
dazzling desert light.
40
At the feet of Rameses and his queen, Nefertari,
scaffolding went up. Archaeologists, philologists, photog¬
raphers, draughtsmen, architects and moulders arrived on
the site. Work began at dawn and often went on far into
the night since the heat and blinding light prevented pho¬
tographers from working in the afternoon. Invaded by
cameras, searchlights and generating plants, the age-old
sanctuary began to look like a film studio.
Every square inch of the great Abu Simbel group was
minutely examined. Since then, black and white and colour
photographs, photogrammetric negatives, architects' notes,
casts and copies of hieroglyphic texts, rock graffiti and
Greek, Coptic and Semitic inscriptions, have gradually
been amassed in the Cairo Documentation Centre. Already
this material constitutes the fullest and most accurate in¬
ventory of facts about these monuments that has ever been
collected. Systematic surveys of the temples of Debod,
Kalabsha and Wadi-es-Sebua and the chapels of Abu Oda
and Jebel Chams are now also nearing completion.
'Noah's Ark' on the Nile
While doing this urgent field work, the Documenta¬
tion Centre has also had to set up and equip its
own headquarters. From the very start of the
Nubian expeditions it had to keep teams supplied and to
protect photographic material. It would be difficult to
exaggerate the difficulties this involved in the grilling heat
of Nubia. The work, however, has become much easier
since the Centre acquired a five cabin boat, the 1" Horus ",
which is used to' carry out rapid missions and tours of ins¬
pection and to relieve working teams. Now the Centre
is to receive another boat, a kind of " Noah's Ark ", built
specially to its specifications by the Egyptian Government.
This floating laboratory can be towed along the Nile and
moored close to the sites where work is in progress. It will
carry workshops, offices, stores and a library and will pro¬
vide the teams with living quarters.
Finally, a year ago, the Centre itself took on. concrete
form as an attractive modern building in Cairo, close to
the Corniche du Ml. It has been planned and equipped
CONT'D ON PAGE 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
Institut Géographique National, Saint-Mandé
Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo
I
	i
. ' . 	*-	~.,B .	! > À
¡TV
:	
i ^*¿' \ '
%v :.\v' V X
-*»«
CAPTURED BY
PHOTOGRAMMETRY
The photographs on this and the
following pages show the remar¬
kable results achieved by a new
science photogrammetry which
makes it possible to determine the
shape and dimensions of an object
from two stereoscopic photographs
and then to reconstitute it in the
laboratory in the form of an exact
model. The work shown here was
carried out at the request of the
Documentation Centre on Ancient
Egypt, Cairo, by the French National
Geographic Institute. Photos show:
1. An ordinary photograph of a bas-
relief showing a group of prisoners
at the foot of the colossal statue of
Rameses II to the right of the
entrance to the Great Temple of
Abu Simbel.
2. The frieze as it appears with all
the contour lines plotted as a
result of stereoscopic photography.
4I
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
PHOTOGRAMMETRY (Continued)
3. Contour plotting is then placed in a pantograver. This 5. Detail of one of the figures before levelling pro
4. Contour lines are reconstituted on a block of plaster duction is accurate to one-half of a millimetre (a fiftieth
which is placed at the other end of the pantograver. of an inch) and shows amazing results of photogrammetry.
Äll^jfe)^
Photos © Institut Géographique National, St Mandé
H .
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
UNDER THE SIGN
OF MAAT
{Continued)
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
Documentation Centre
on Ancient Egypt
down to the smallest detail for the recording and use of
Egyptological material. Its lecture halls, library, card in¬
dexes and its air-conditioned photographic laboratories and
archives have already made it an ideal centre for these
studies.
The Documentation Centre was set up in May 1955 by
the Antiquities Service of Egypt with the direct co-opera¬
tion of. Unesco. It is an Egyptian body, financed by the
Government of the United Arab Republic. Unesco has a
representative on the Board of Directors of the Centre
and provides technical aid in the form of international
specialists.
Race against time
in Lower Nubia
From the days of Champollion the founder of scien¬
tific Egyptology the work of preserving monuments,
organizing excavation work, research and documen¬
tation studies has been carried out by a great many foun¬
dations, museums and universities in Egypt, Europe and
America. It has often been done most successfully, but
almost inevitably in a piecemeal fashion. Never until now
has so systematically organized a body as the Cairo Centre
been at work in this field. Its operations have called for
powerful resources and the services of large teams of full-
time specialists working in a synchronized operation.
Originally, the Centre had chosen as its first task to
make systematic surveys of the Necropolis of Thebes where
the tombs, once well-preserved, had shown signs of dete¬
rioration. The announcement of the High Dam project
changed the order of priorities and began the race against
time in Lower Nubia. In the next five years something
like one hundred missions are planned with a clear-cut
programme of work relating to the monuments threatened
by the Aswan High Dam.
The archaeologists and philologists attached to the
Centre co-ordinate all operations taking into account exist¬
ing documentation and data. They direct work in the
field and then record the results of every mission on card
indexes.
Painting and sculpture
recreated by the camera
Facts needed to complement copies and descriptions
are assembled by the technical section. Architects
prepare plans, sections and elevation, complete to
the most minute detail every brick, every flagstone and
even the smallest hole in a wall is marked in. Experts in
architectural drawing trained at the Centre use photo¬
graphs to prepare exact plans of groups of monuments.
The old method of making tracings from actual monuments
is no longer used except for small details, or in cases where
monuments are too closely hemmed in or in too bad a state
of preservation for satisfactory photographs to be taken.
Copies of those reliefs which are renowned for their beauty
or historical interest and of any hieroglyphic inscriptions
likely to provoke controversy, are made by moulders, who
also prepare architectural models.
Photographers find themselves working closely with most
of the other specialists. Following details of the master
plan, they develop their test film each day on the spot
before sending the negatives to the developing laboratory
in Cairo. At the same time they take identical photographs
on colour film. Yet even all this work is not enough.
The photographic reproduction of works of art, and of
sculpture in particular, is as André Malraux has termed
it a phenomenon of recreation. Freed from the recesses
where they were hidden away, sculptures seem to spring
into life again when viewed in this new light, becoming
familiar and acquiring fresh significance.
Photography, like drawing and even architectural plans,
contains a certain element of subjectivity which can pro¬
duce various degrees of distortion. To obtain the absolute
accuracy demanded by scientific recording, use has been
made of photogrammetry, a process that has been em¬
ployed for the past forty years in the preparation of geogra¬
phical maps.
This method was first used to survey a monument in
1850 and today provides invaluable documentary mat¬
erial for archaeologists. The stereoscopic photographs,
taken with the aid of a phototheodolite, give precise in¬
formation down to the smallest detail of a relief and thus
make possible the creation of an absolutely faithful copy
in reproductions, models and casts.
New horizons opened
by photogrammetry
Photogrammetry opens up new horizons in the know¬
ledge of forms and techniques. It may even make
possible the discovery of architectural laws as yet
undisclosed by Egyptologists, and may add to our know¬
ledge of sculptural techniques. For instance, the contour
lines taken on the face of the North-West Osirian colossus
(23 feet) in the inner court of the Great Temple of Abu
Simbel, and those taken on the face of the South colossus
(65 feet) on the façade, show some striking resemblances
between the two even down to the modelling of the carti¬
lage of the nose.
When all the survey programmes are completed, the
Documentation Centre in Cairo will be a rich, permanent
source of information both for Egyptological studies and
for works destined for the man in the street. As a safety
measure, all the archives are to be microfilmed and one
copy of every document will be given special security treat¬
ment to guard against any possible destruction or
deterioration.
Thanks to the international action undertaken by Unesco
there is now reason to hope that these majestic monuments
will be saved from the encroaching waters and that pre¬
sent and future generations will still be able to visit the
giant statues of Rameses II and the island temples of
Philae. Furthermore, the extensive work undertaken by
the Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt will give the
world's Egyptologists the possibility of adding to our know¬
ledge of one of the areas of the Ancient World which has by
no means finished yielding up its secrets.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
THE MODERN PYRAMID
OF ASWAN: SADD EL AALI
by Albert Raccah
Albert Raccah
COAL.' Electric power production in Egypt will be given a tremendous boost when the Aswan High Dam (The Sadd El
Aali) is completed. Water from the dam will be used to operate 16 turbine units buried more than 300 feet underground which to¬
gether with the existing power station at Aswan will give Egypt a total annual electricity production of 15,000 million kilowatt-hours,
reducing its cost to consumers by two-thirds. Photo was taken during the construction of the present Aswan power station. Map on
opposite page shows the relative positions of the sites of the two dams. Between them lies group of islands including Philae.
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
fanning out in
GYPT is a gift of the Nile." Thus wrote
Herodotus, the Greek historian and tra¬
veller of the fifth century B.C. Indeed,
all of this land of nearly 400,000 square
miles would be nothing but a vast desert
from the Libyan frontier to the Red Sea
and from the Mediterranean to the
Sudanese frontier if the Nile did not
cross it from south to north before
a vast delta 100 miles from the coast.
This is a rain-starved country. On an average there
are six rainy days in Cairo per year and only one at
Aswan. It is easy to understand why the ancient Egyp¬
tians considered the Nile of divine essence: it was the
very source of all life in Egypt.
One also understands Why all agricultural development
is at the mercy of the amount of water taken from the
Nile. During the flood season, an immense volume of
water is lost to the sea. The present Aswan dam was
built to harness a part of it for irrigation in spring and
summer.
Called in Arabic "El Khazzan"
(the reservoir), it was built at As¬
wan between 1899 and 1902 on the
granite rock of the river bed in the
middle of the First Cataract. The
dam, 100 feet high, was to make it
possible to store 980 million cubic
metres of water in an artificial lake
extending upstream for 140 miles,
thus inundating the island of Philae
and its sanctuaries, as well as part
of the cultivated land.
Between 1907 and 1912, the height
of the dam was raised another 16
feet, giving a total capacity of 2,400
million cubic metres to the artificial
reservoir which then backed the
waters of the Nile upstream to a total
of 185 miles.
Finally, between 1929 and 1934, the
dam was further raised, by 30 feet
bringing the reservoir's total capacity
to five thousand million cubic metres.
The artificial lake reached back as
far as Wadi-Halfa, 225 miles up the
Nile from Aswan.
The present dam contains one and
half million cubic metres of masonry
(the Great Pyramid of Cheops had
two and half million originally).
The dam wall is over a mile long and has 180 sluice
gates operating on two levels. The iron control gates are
all opened in July, during the high water season, so that
the Nile's muddy waters may flood and fertilize the
country. Early in October the sluices are closed and the
river is kept back. In early spring when Egypt begins to
lack water, the Aswan dam acts as the reservoir which
irrigates the country.
A vast inland sea
covering 1,150 sq. miles
But the Aswan reservoir is inadequate for Egypt's pre¬
sent-day needs. For the past half-century, agri¬
culture and industry have been unable to keep pace
with the problem of food for its rapidly rising population.
Egypt urgently needs more land for cultivation, better and
higher crop yields, hydro-electric energy for its expanding
Industry.
This "living space" can be won thanks to the Nile, the
real wealth of Egypt, and by the construction of a new
dam, the Sadd El Aali. The purpose of the High Dam,
the preliminary engineering work on which has already
been done, is the total utilization of the Nile's waters.
Not a drop of the river will be lost in the sea.
The dam wall, to be erected on a site four miles
upstream from the present Aswan dam, will rise 225 feet
and have a crest three miles in length. It will create an
artificial lake 300 miles long with a capacity of nearly
130,000 million cubic metres and a surface area of 1,150
square miles. Several localities, including the city of
Wadi Haifa will be submerged. Since the rapids of the
Second Cataract will disappear under 30 feet of water,
regular navigation between Egypt and the Sudan will
become possible for the first time.
Two and a half million acres
of desert land will bloom
In a climate as hot as that of Nubia, it is to be expected
that such a vast expanse of water will give rise to
evaporation. It is estimated that the atmosphere will
annually absorb 10,000 million cubic metres of the 130,000
million stored. The resulting rise in the humidity ratio
of the Egyptian and Sudanese regions neighbouring on
the artificial lake is certain to have
an important effect on vegetation
growth.
80 "
; m. \
Some of the water reserve is also
sure to be lost through fissures under
the lake-bed. The Nile already pays
a heavy tribute to the desert as it
crosses Nubia and Upper Egypt. In
these regions, it flows over a veritable
sieve. During the flood season in
August and September, 5,000 million
cubic metres are estimated to be lost
between Aswan and Asiut, and 100
cubic metres a second between Asiut
and Cairo. The volume seems in¬
significant compared with the Nile's
flow at that season: nearly 9,000 cubic
metres a second.
However, the average flow of the
river is only 2,510 cubic metres a sec¬
ond, much less than that of the Rio
de la Plata (25,000 cubic metres a
second) or the Mississippi (18,000 a
second).
Map: Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo
With the great reservoir which the
Sadd El Aali will create, Egypt will
be able to increase its arable land
surface by nearly half. In reality it
is expected that as much as two and
a half million acres of desert land will be brought under
cultivation and that 750,000 acres now flooded will be
reclaimed.
Although the greatest advantage of the Sadd El Aali
lies in the possibility of opening up new areas for farming
and ensuring their regular water supply, the energy out¬
put foreseen for the dam would in itself foe enough to
justify its construction. Four tunnels for water evacuat¬
ion during flood periods and four chute tunnels will service
16 turbine units buried more than '300 feet under the
granite rock. They will operate all year round with a
'"head" (height from which the water drops) ave¬
raging 200 feet. The turbines will have an estimated
total capacity of 2 million H.P. and an annual production
of 10-12,000 million kilowatt-hours a year, nearly ten
times present total consumption in Egypt. The Boulder
Dam in the United States produces only half as much
power. The combination of the hydro-electric potentials of
both the Sadd El Aali and Aswan dam will raise Egypt's
capacity to more than 15,000 million kilowatt-hours a year.
When the High Dam of Aswan is completed, four years
will be needed to fill its basin capacity. In that period,
the population of Egypt will probably continue to increase
at the same rate as in previous years and this increase
(8,000,000 persons within the next ten years) makes the
building of the Sadd El Aali a vital necessity.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
SUDANESE NUBIA
'TERRA INCOGNITA' OF ARCHAEOLOGISTS
by J. Vercoutter
Director of the Antiquities Service, Republic of the Sudan
rchaeologically speaking the Sudanese part of
threatened Nubia is practically a "terra
incognita". It has never been systematically
surveyed. But it is ¡known to contain a vast
number of unexplored sites which lie buried
under the sands. These sites could provide
valuable data about the early history of mankind, and
their disappearance forever under the Waters of the Nile,
if not thoroughly investigated beforehand, will be an
irreparable loss.
Sudanese Nubia was a meeting ground of civilizations.
It was the borderland between Egypt, with its Medi¬
terranean and Asian affinities, and Africa proper, and it
was the gateway through which objects and ideas passed
between the ancient world and Africa, and vice versa.
As the link between two continents, the importance of
Sudanese Nubia cannot be overstated.
The reservoir of the high dam of Aswan will ultimately
flood about 115 miles of the present banks of the Nile in
the Sudan. By 1964, when the first stage of construction
is scheduled to be completed, over 40 miles of Sudanese
territory will be permanently under water. And these
40 miles are the area with the country's richest store of
archaeological remains, containing 47 known sites and
others likely to be unearthed in the course of prospection.
But in the entire 115 miles region of the Sudanese Nile
in jeopardy, only ten sites have thus far been partially
excavated. However, a rapid ground survey together with
an air survey recently carried out by the Sudanese Survey
Jean Vercoutter.
MASTER-WORK
OF
ARCHITECTURE
Much of Sudanese Nubia which is to be flooded
is unknown territory, archaeologically. In the
past few years alone over 100 sites have been
recorded in this area. Photos right and oppo¬
site page show one of them: a master-work of
Egyptian military architecture, the great castle
of Buhen near Wadi Haifa. The fortress has
just been discovered by Professor Walter
B. Emery of the University of London who led
two expeditions to Buhen last year and in 1958
for the Egypt Exploration Society. The disco¬
very has already revolutionized previous con¬
ceptions of pharaonic military architecture.
The fortress was built in the early Middle
Kingdom as one of a series of trading posts
and strongholds erected 3,900 years ago to
defend the strategic area of the Second Cata¬
ract dividing Upper and Lower Nubia. Sacked
about 1675 B.C. its vast fortifications were
rebuilt and enlarged in the New Kingdom
(1570 B.C.). Excavations are still under way
and have already unearthed the skeleton of
the earliest horse known in Egypt and a quan¬
tity of torn-up papyrus which may be the re¬
mains of military dispatches. On opposite page
is a reconstruction of the Middle Kingdom
castle, made by British artist Alan Sorrell, with
the help of Prof. Emery and based on his plans.
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1960
"** ¿nuit rî
Illustrated London News
Department has revealed the existence of more than
100 sites! The discovery of a remarkable Egyptian fortress
of the Middle and New Kingdom recently made by Pro¬
fessor Walter B. Emery at Buhen (in the' immediately
menaced area) shows how much Sudanese archaeology
has to give (see photos left and above). Can we allow
all these sites to be destroyed without their having been
at least partly explored, excavated and recorded?
The situation is no less urgent as regards the known
monuments of the Sudan. Among the ruins still standing
or clearly apparent and which will be engulfed by the
waters, are seven ancient towns, four Pharaonic temples,
at least 20 Christian churches (including some with
frescoes), rock graves of the 18th Egyptian dynasty, rock
chapels of early Christian date, numerous cemeteries, and
sites with rock drawings or rock inscriptions. Special
mention must be made of prehistoric sites, both Neolithic
and Palaeolithic, one of which has recently been dated
6 300 B.C. by the radio carbon process.
Among the sites which will disappear forever are the
two temples of the XVIIIth Dynasty inside the twin for¬
tresses of Semna and Kumma; the small temple of
Rameses II at Aksha, still buried in the desert sand; the
lovely temple of Buhen with its magnificent carvings and
paintings; the sites, mostly Egyptian citadels of the
Middle Kingdom (2065-1500 B.C.) of Mirgissa, Dabenarti,
Shelfak and Uronarti to mention but the most important
monuments known today.
Each year, survey and inspection tours carried out by
the Antiquities Service of the Republic of the Sudan
reveal new sites; trial excavations lay bare unexpected
finds such as the paintings of the Djehuty-hetep tomb at
Debeira or the Faras alabaster vase which was found in
a site thought to have been excavated.
In the Sudan, therefore, everything, or nearly every¬
thing, still remains to be done. But in the short time avail¬
able and with its very limited staff, the Sudan Antiquities
Service is unable, on its own, to carry out the urgent work
of surveying and excavating, of removing and safeguard¬
ing the monuments, and recording for posterity all these
operations.
The important, the urgent thing is to start, as quickly
as possible, a complete archaeological survey, mile by mile,
of the whole area to be flooded. A survey of this kind has
never been carried out before.
In 1955, when the Sudan first learned of the proposed
building of the new dam at Aswan, its Antiquities Service
prepared an emergency plan of action. In order to get a
clear picture of what would have to be done it started a
ground survey. But as this proved too slow a job with the
limited staff available, an air survey was made. The
entire threatened zone was photographed from the air in
1956-57 by the government's Survey Department, and this
air survey has now become the basis for the Sudan's
rescue plan. Thanks to Unesco, a specialist is now work¬
ing on the archaeological interpretation of these photo¬
graphs and the first precise archaeological map of the
region will soon be available.
What is urgently needed now is a photogrammetric
contour map of the area for which aerial stereoscopic
photographs have just been taken. Once the photogram¬
metric contour map is available it will be possible for the
ground survey to get under way. It is envisaged that
these surveys will be carried out on each bank of the Nile
with prospecting teams for a general survey preceding
excavation teams.
Most of the monuments in the threatened area are built
of mud brick and cannot be dismantled; but some have
frescoes painted on brick and these will need to be remov¬
ed. Four stone temples (Aksha, Buhen, Semna West and
Kumma) could and should be dismantled and taken to a
safe place. The temples at Semna and Kumma stand on
a rocky barrier, possibly the site of an ancient Egyptian
dam, and offer an imposing landscape. The ideal thing
would be to preserve them where they are.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
SUDANESE NUBIA (Continued)
J. Vercoutter
1 MIRGISSA FORTRESS. Aerial view of one
' of many Sudanese sites still only partially
excavated. Situated on a steep rock close to
the Nile, south of Buhen, it has recently yielded
important finds Including the archives of a post
office chief of 4,000 years ago. Girdle walls are
made of sun-dried bricks. Site also contains
the ruins of a small temple built by Sesostris III.
O AKSHA TEMPLE. Remains of wall from
* temple built by Rameses II at Aksha, in the
Sudan, about 25 miles south of Abu Simbel. The
temple was dedicated to the great sun god Amon
to whom Rameses (far left and centre, kneeling)
is offering devotion. Much of this stone-built
temple is still buried beneath the desert sand.
3-4. SEMNA EAST & WEST. About 40 miles
south of Wadi Haifa the Nile narrows and
flows between granite cliffs forming impressive
rapids. To guard this passage (the southern
limit of Egypt under the Middle Kingdom) the
Pharaohs built two massive forts on either side of
the river. On the left bank lies West Semna ; on
the right East Semna, or Kumma. Both have impor¬
tant temples dating from 1500-1400 B.C. of which
the photos on the opposite page show details.
C TEMPLE OF BUHEN. Just north of the 2nd
" Cataract and opposite Wadi Haifa lie the ruins
of the lovely temple of Buhen bullt by Thutmosis II
and Hatshepsut over 3,000 years ago against a
high cliff overlooking the Nile. Photo shows only
a corner of the large Hall, but the temple has
remarkable carvings and paintings many of
which still retain much of their original colouring.
^|
t\
\i~4- Hi n
Courtesy Oriental Institute, Univ. of Chicago
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier, February 1960
Photos Courtesy Oriental Institute, Chicago
Mile by mile excavation survey imperative
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
QUESTION MARKS IN THE DESERT
by Dr. Anwar Shoukry
Director of Pharaonic Antiquities, Antiquities Service of Egypt
and Professor Francois Daumas
Director, French Institute of Oriental Archaeology, Cairo
No one who visits present-day Nubia
at different times of the year can
fail to be struck by the two sharp¬
ly contrasting landscapes. In
winter, during January for instan¬
ce, the country has become a sort of nar¬
row lake which extends to the cliffs on the
Libyan and Arabian sides of the Nile valley,
on which stand villages with large houses,
painted and adorned with earthenware tiles.
But in summer particularly in August and
, September when the sluice gates of the
Aswan dam have been opened to let through
the flood waters the Nile retreats almost to
its old bed. Wide stretches of black earth
appear, providing a few green crops which
often do not even ripen. And in places,
great temples, most of them almost invi¬
sible under the winter waters, now tower
up in the shape of imposing ruins: Ka¬
labsha, Dendur, Dakka.
When the building of the first dam was
decided on, the Antiquities Service of Egypt,
then under the direction of Gaston Mas-
pero, not only consolidated the temples,
but also carried out excavations in the area
before the dam was raised and then each
time it was heightened until the flood-
water level reached the 121 metre mark.
It might at first be thought, therefore, that
only the land above spot level 121 would
remain to be excavated before the erection
of the High Dam.
In archaeology, however, things are
never as simple as they may first appear.
How can one be sure that a valley has
been properly excavated when, despite the
fact that it is not very wide, it is hundreds
of miles long? Is there any chance of find¬
ing something in the areas flooded in
winter? What may be found above spot
level 121? Have excavations in Nubia left
no mysteries still to be penetrated?
First of all there are certain sites where
the excavations carried out have been
inadequate. They should be continued as
long as we are lucky to have the low
waters during the summer, particularly in
the case of the great Nubian temples. The
scientists who were sent to monuments
like Kalabsha or Wadi es-Sebua cleared the
inside of the temples but did not explore
the surroundings.
In 1956, a study was made of the struc¬
ture of the various walls that surround the
temple of Kalabsha. It did not take long
to realize that one of these walls could be
explained only by the presence of a sacred
lake. Only one such lake that of Den-
dara has come down to us intact.
Excavations at Kalabsha are thus clearly
imperative. Clearing work carried out to
the west of the supposed lake by the Anti¬
quities Service in September 1959, has
already brought to light the roofs of two
chapels which are apparently intact. Un¬
fortunately, the Nile rose abnormally high
during this period so that excavation work
had to be interrupted. This is not the
place to enter into a discussion on the
theological reasons justifying these excava¬
tions but it will be readily understood that
a detailed knowledge of the way a temple is
arranged is important if one is to get really
to the heart of Egyptian religion.
In the present case, what is at stake is
not merely an architectural survey but the
interpretation of an essential element in
ancient temples. And this may be all the
more important because in Nubia, where
the population has never been very dense,
the monuments have suffered less then else¬
where.
The situation is much the same as re¬
gards the temple of Wadi es-Sebua. Exca¬
vations in the past cleared only the avenue
lined with sphinxes (the dromes). We
know nothing of the entire front part of
the sanctuary buried under the high
waters of the Nile and which could provide
information of the greatest importance.
Some sections of the exterior wall are still
visible, but no one has ever thought of
surveying or exploring them. Thus with¬
out citing any other example, excavations
will certainly yield major results as far as
the study of religion is concerned.
But even during the high-water season,
archaeological work could very well yield
excellent results. The research carried out
on the two occasions when the height of
the old dam was raised, laid bare a stran¬
gely refined yet primitive civilization, that
of the Blemmyes, dating from the sixth
century A.D.: well-provided royal tombs,
furnished with coffers richly inlaid with
ivory, pottery of all kinds, games, even
completely accoutred horses.
The Meroitic culture the name comes
from Meroe, the capital city of its kings,
near Shendi has brought to light many
facts of which we had no inkling, in parti¬
cular the penetration of Greek influences
in these somewhat remote regions of Afri¬
ca. Recently, in a Meroitic cemetery bor¬
dering the high waters, an Italian mission
unearthed a copper bowl engraved with the
image of a cow, of very fine workmanship.
The same mission, last year, resumed exca¬
vations at Ikhmindi and had the luck to
discover an inscription describing how the
city was founded, in the Byzantine era.
The German excavations at Amada have
likewise been very encouraging.
But there are still points in doubt. It
is to these that attention should be drawn.
Research that starts from reflexion may
well lead to more interesting discoveries.
Upper Nubia has many traces of the
Middle Empire and the XVIIIth Dynasty
whereas in Lower Nubia the remains date
mostly from the XDCth Dynasty and the
Graeco-Roman era. But we are convinced
that, if the temples of Lower Nubia had
been more carefully excavated, they would
have yielded a larger number of ancient
documents.
There is an even more tantalizing ques¬
tion. The viceroys of Kush, who governed
the country from the XVIIIth to the XXth
Dynasty, seem to have resided at Aniba.
But only one tomb of any importance has
been found that of Pennut. No necro¬
polis of viceroys. No residence. Yet
these mighty chiefs of Egypt's African em¬
pire, would not have been satisfied with a
mere house, however large. They must
have had a palace. Funeral statuettes,
called Oushebtis, of other viceroys, show
that they had tombs, at least secondary
ones, even if their bodies were brought
back to Egypt. Where may we find these
vestiges of the Egyptian occupation of the
country in remote antiquity?
These are the kind of questions excava¬
tion expeditions will have to find answers
to. We hope they succeed before the great
sheet of water submerges Nubia forever.
IN THE STEPS OF GREECE & ROME
(Continued from page 39)
stone for the Philae temples. The guild of agents, known as Hie
"gomos," which was responsible for the transport of the stones, had its
priests and dignitaries who made a point of engraving their names on
the tablets cut into the façade of the speos. At Abu Duruah, about
three miles to the east of Dakka, we find proscynemata dating from the
time of Antoninus Pius (middle of second century A.D.), proving that this
rock shrine with its Pharaonic decoration, far from having fallen into
disuse, was a centre of worship for the god Min and Hermes Peithnuphis.
All these texts shed a great deal of light on the life of the Roman
garrisons, their composition and dates and the cults they practised.
The material already available proves that Nubia, for all its aridity,
played a not inconsiderable role in antiquity. To begin with, from the
military point of view, the region was both a bastion of defence and
an operational base. Then, from the economic standpoint, hunting must
have flourished, as indicated by the many names of elephant and bird
hunters to be seen at Abu Simbel, and by the engravings at Jebel Abu
Duruah, representing giraffes, oryxes, ostriches and buffalo.
Down the Nile sailed convoys loaded with the treasures or the gold mines
at Wadi Allaki, facing Dakka, or white stones quarried at Kertassi.
Viticulture and the use of sakieh or water wheel, of which there is
evidence in Nubia, bear witness to the flourishing state of agriculture.
Lastly, from the religious point of view, the Nubian gods went to swell
the Graeco-Roman pantheon. It was in the first and second centuries
A.D. that Philae reached the pinnacle of its glory with the construction
of the gateways of Augustus and Tiberius and the Trajan kiosk.
And so Nubia, from the days of antiquity, has stood as an example
and a token of what man can achieve when his toil and ingenuity are
pitted against the elements and an unfriendly climate. The Greeks and
Romans sought, in ancient Nubia, to convert a barren, thankless region,
doomed, it might have seemed, to everlasting poverty, into a source of
spiritual and material wealth, strength and pride a goal that is still
being pursued by the architects of modern Nubia.
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
X
Documentation Centre on Ancient Egypt, Cairo
PRINCESS WITH THE SISTRUM. The princess Bent-Anta, one of the daughters of
Rameses II, shown playing the sistrum in a carving at the entrance to thetemple öf Abu Simbel.
The sistrum, an ancient Egyptian musical instrument, ¡s a form of metal rattle. It has an
oval frame crossed by loose rods and when shaken produces a high-pitched tone.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
THE
DROWNING
SPHINX
]]>
</page>
</document>
