<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064690eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A W I N D O W O P E N O N T H .£ W O R L D
ner
NEW PATHWAYS
FOR THE BLIND
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
CONCERT
OF THE
in
The "concert" given by blind men at the
St. Ovide's Fair in Paris in 1771. This
humiliating scene so revolted Valentin
Haiiy that he decided to devote his life
to helping the blind. He initiated the art
of embossing books with raised lettering
which the blind could be taught to read,
started the earliest library for the blind
and created in Paris the world's first
school for blind children, which still
exists as the National Institution of
the Young Blind. In time he was to
become known throughout Europe as
the Father and Apostle of the Blind.
'I1 s he was strolling through the streets of Paris one September day in 1771, a young French-
i man, Valentin Haiiy was attracted by the sight of a crowd hooting and laughing in front of a
large booth at the St Ovide's Fair, then being held in the Place Louis-le-G rand (now Place
Vendôme). On a platform raised above the tables of this open-air café, ten blind men scraped
their bows in pantomime, drawing shattering discord from violins, cellos, basses and viols.
They stared blankly at sheet music turned on the racks so that the notes were visible to the
jeering audience. Their sightless eyes were ringed with huge pasteboard spectacles devoid of
glass. They wore grotesque robes, with dunces' caps and asses' ears. Every day for two months
they had scraped, fiddled and kept up a monotonous accompanying chant, While their audience
jeered, banged tankards on the tables and screeched bawdy jokes.
Haiiy viewed the scene with a mixture of pity and horror and, years later, recalling this signi¬
ficant moment in his life, he wrote:
"Why was it that a scene so dishonourable to humanity did not perish in the instant of its
conception ? Why was it that poetry and picture should lend their divine ministration to the
publication of this atrocity Ah ! It was impossible that the scene before my eyes, bringing deep
sorrow to my heart, should not inspire and arouse my soul.
"Yes," I said to myself, seized by an exalted enthusiasm, "I will substitute the truth for this
mockery. I will make the blind read. I will put in their hands volumes printed by themselves.
They will trace the true characters and will read their own writing, and they will be able to
give harmonious concerts. Yes, atrocious malinger, whoever thou art, the ears of the ass with
which thou would'st degrade the head ofmisfortune, shall be attached to thine own."
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 WINDOW Op(N ON FHI WOILD
ner
JUNE
1 3 T H
19 6 0
YEAR
Contents
No. 6
Page
COVER PHOTO
Blind students at the Arizona
State School for the Deaf
and Blind, U.S.A. running a
race on their outdoor track.
Athletes are guided by
special rails, but with practice
touch on the rail is almost
dispensed with. Dangling
strings enable Blind runners
to count thelaps-eight to the
mile. They are so arranged
that they gently brush the
runner's face as he goes
past them. See page 24.
Photo Ray Manley © Camera
Press Ltd., London.
4 WHEN IS A PERSON CONSIDERED BLIND?
By Nino Frank
7 STILL NO ELECTRONIC SUBSTITUTE FOR SIGHT
By M. Robert Barnett
1 1 MORE BLIND IN CALCUTTA THAN IN CANADA
By W.H. Owens
14 VICTORY IN SIGHT OVER THE BABEL OF BRAILLE
By Sir Ciutha Mackenzie
15 STAMPS TO HONOUR AND HELP THE BLIND
By C.W. Hill
17 THE GULF IS VANISHING
By Pierre Henri
20 OUT OF THE DARKNESS
The blind in the U.S.S.R.
By A. Kondratov
23 DO'S AND DON'TS FOR THE SIGHTED
By F. Potter
25 FIFTEEN MILLION FRANCS OVERNIGHT
French scouts & Unesco Clubs chalk up a success
27 LET'S STOP PLAYING BLIND MAN'S REBUFF
By Léon Bataille
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*. France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 60.1.148 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
ILO
International Labour Office expert A. Asenjo (above, on right of photo)
himself blind, is helping Brazil to develop its vocational rehabilitation
services for blind persons. He is seen here in a Sao Paulo printing
shop with blind workers who are assembling Braille publications.
Opposite page, at London's School for the Sightless, the boy reading
to his friends from a Braille book of medieval legends does so with
such speed that no one hearing him would guess that he is blind.
WHEN IS
A PERSON
CONSIDERED
BLIND?
by
Nino Frank
Absolute and total blindness is almost an anomaly.
Most blind people can "see" to a certain extent or at
least recreate for themselves the image of what they
can no longer directly perceive, using what are sometimes
called "'the eyes of the mind" or "the eyes of memory".
For the fact is that only four blind, persons in every
hundred are under 20 years of age and rarer still are
those afflicted with blindness before the age of five
by which time a child's eye has absorbed a multitude
of images of the surrounding world. Whereas the pro¬
portion of blind to seeing people in the world is about
350 per 100,000 inhabitants, that of children under five
is only seven per 100,000.
Sustained by hearing, by touch and even by smell, a
person who has lost [his sight still has the power to create
a light Within himself and to reconstruct the world
around him. Thanks to this capacity he is no longer
someone '"different" from his fellows and has certainly
no need of the Ikindi of hurtful and upsetting pity which
people so often show towards him. .
What he does need and has the right to is the con¬
sideration and help of society and this at once raises, as
it has always done, the problem of the exact status of
the blind in the community. As total blindness is com¬
paratively rare, the problem, in most cases is to decide to
what extent a person's power of vision is impaired, thus
placing him In a special situation. Blindness therefore,
has come to toe measured in practical or occupational
terms, by which the expression "blind" denotes "any
person who, by treason of the physical condition of his
eyes, cannot live a completely normal 'life'".
What, then, is a blind person? If some are deprived
of the least perception of light, others can still register
light and shade, can see colours if they are strongly lit,
but cannot distinguish forms; others, again, can perceive
forms, but are incapable of determining the exact place
of these in relation to others. There are many other
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
Camera Press Ltd., London
variations. Some people have relatively good visual
acuity in the morning and virtually none in the evening.
In some a perfectly adequate power of sight is undermined
by physical defects such as nystagmus (a regular, in¬
voluntary oscillation of the eyeball). Others, with suf¬
ficient central vision, have a reduced peripheral field. If
such people are not literally '"blind" ab oculis, or "depri¬
ved of eyes'", a conception etymologically preserved in the
French word aveugle they nevertheless are unable to
live a normal life to work, to study or to move about as
freely as others.
The concept of the visual field is a leading factor in any
definition of blindness. A normal eye covers 135 degrees
on the horizontal axis, and both eyes together, about
180 degrees; the field of vision on the vertical axis is
less about il05 degrees as it is limited by the arch of
the brow. In reaching definitions of blindness, several
countries make use of these elements.' In the United
States, for instance, a person is considered legally blind
if his central vision is less than a tenth of the average or
his visual field is less than 20 degrees.
The French definition of blindness includes anyone
whose central vision, even when corrected toy spectacles,
does not reach a .twentieth power of normal sight
anyone, that is, who cannot distinguish at one metre,
something which a person with normal sight could see at
twenty metres.
German law is far more rigorous and only recognizes
as blind and legally entitled to assistance those whose
vision is one-sixtieth of the normal. Bavaria goes even
further and its definition of blindness only covers those
with one-hundreth of normal vision.
Several countries still measure blindness by the distance
at which the outstretched fingers of the hand can be
counted a metre in most cases, but as much as three
metres in Egypt until recently. The two extremes in
criteria are those of Switzerland which in general recog¬
nizes any person as blind if he is unable to perform
work requiring sight, and India, which only acknowledges
total blindness.
Variations like these have stimulated the search for
some standard definition which Would at once provide a
universal criterion for use by all countries and Which
could eventually be established by international agreement.
A standard definition of this kind was outlined in a report
. submitted in 1954 to the U.N. Social Affairs Division. The
report was ,also presented the same year to the General
Assembly of the World Council for the Welfare of the
Blind (WCWB) in Paris. It proposed that the benefits
enjoyed by the blind should be given to persons possessing
not more than 3/60ths of normal vision (after correction
by spectacles) or suffering from a defect of vision (i.e. a
reduction of the visual field) which reduces its practical
efficiency to 3/60ths.
Statistics on blindness throughout the world are not
strictly comparable because of the variation in national
definitions. The proportion of blind people in the United
States appears higher than in France because the Am¬
erican definition takes l/10th vision as its standard while
France takes l/20th. After laws to improve the lot of
the blind were passed in Britain, the number of registered
blind people increased from 28,000 to 60,000. Furthermore,
in some countries with high proportions of blind people
Egypt and India, for example available figures
are not absolutely reliable.
How many blind people are there in the world? A
report submitted to the World Council for the Welfare
of the Blind in Rome, last year, estimated that there are
about nine and a half million, or 3.58 in every thousand
people, and that of these more than seven million live
in rural areas. The report, presented by Dr van
Schalkwijk, Chairman of the Rural Activities Committee,
said that over 3,600,000 could be rehabilitated, more than
two million being capable of agricultural work.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Pierre ßaudin
JOBS OF EVERY KIND are now open to the blind thanks to modern appliances. Blind shorthand typists, for example, now
have an almost noiseless machine for shorthand dictation at a speed of 140 words and more a minute. The French typist shown
here is working from a tape-recorded text. On his right is a special pad on which he can make notes by perforating the paper with
a stylet, guided by a slotted mobile ruler. Some of the world's early typewriters were devised primarily for the use of the blind.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
Despite host
of gadgets
SCIENCE STILL SEEKING TRUE
ELECTRONIC SUBSTITUTE FOR SIGHT
by M. Robert Barnett
W
f HETHER it be a simple device for the writing
of Braille, or the exciting promise of vision
through electronics, the problem of persons deprived of
eyesight has long attracted the interest and energy of
scores of technical scientists. Throughout the 130
years since Louis Braille came up with his system
of embossed printing the variety and number of mechanical
or electronic appliances designed to offset the handicap of
blindness has been extensive and yet, modern science still
has brought no major breakthrough that would constitute
real news for the world's blind persons.
The student of the problem must first attempt to under¬
stand just what is the handicap of blindness; that is, if he
himself is not blind. The world-famous Helen Keller has
often said that the greatest problem facing the blind is the
attitude of society toward them and while she was
referring primarily to the handicap of social segregation
and to barriers to employment, her statement does have a
direct significance here.
Basically, most people believe that the loss of sight
reduces the human being into a vegetable-like organism
that lives and breathes but which has lost all power to
function normally. Upon closer inspection, experience or
study, this exaggerated concept is found to be quite un¬
reasoning. Notwithstanding loss of sight, the average
human being of normal intelligence and stable tempera¬
ment has an amazing array of personal capacities. Blind¬
ness, per se, does not change this fundamental fact. The
blind person can be assisted greatly by special tools and
devices but only too often the proposed tangible devices
upon examination do not prove useful in a working situa¬
tion. Even the otherwise skilled and well-meaning inven¬
tor is not free of misconceptions and is often startled at
not meeting with enthusiastic acceptance of his ideas by
agencies serving blind persons or by the blind themselves.
An examination of the many reports of experiments
and existing catalogues of practical appliances shows a
consistent adherence, however, to a recognition of the real
problem which blindness imposes. This problem breaks
down, generally speaking, into two large challenges to
scientific imagination communication and mobility. The
first, more simply stated, means the obvious barrier of
blindness to reading and writing, while the second refers
to the more subtle and complex question of how to get
about efficiently and safely from place to place.
Past accomplishment and future lines of design and
production depart from these two major challenges into a
variety of less dramatic types of appliances that assist the
blind person to meet various tasks in the household or on
M. Robert Barnett is Executive Director of the American Founda¬
tion for the Blind, Inc., and the American Foundation for Overseas
Blind, Inc., New York. He is also Chairman of the Committee on
Technical Research, World Council tor the Welfare of the Blind.
the job. The essential and most significant fact at the
moment nevertheless is that none of the dreams of blind
persons themselves or of their imaginative scientific friends
about an outright electronic substitute for sight in reading
and in travel have even begun to be realized.
Throughout the world at this very moment there is a
growing awareness of the need for an intensive objective
re-analysis of the basic theories that most technologists
have accepted in the pursuit of a particular experiment.
In the English language there is a growing usage of the
words "'human engineering," an expression designed to
convey the need to fit the machine to the man rather than
fitting the man to the machine.
-W1
URTHER, most of the recent advances in either
the field printing or of personal mobility
devices overlook the cold facts of economics. Those
intended for the acceleration of the printing of Braille
books, for instance, may actually involve an increase in
cost of production over what already is an expensive
matter. Those intended for the use of individuals even
if found to be of practical valuewould be units whose
cost would be far beyond the ability of average people to
purchase or for social agencies to supply at public expense.
Finally, a general lack of exchange of information
among the small but noteworthy army of thinkers and
designers often causes the expenditure of time and funds
upon fines of research or the actual construction of
prototypes that earlier and similar experimentation already
has shown to be unproductive of practical results.
An informal appraisal of the total picture, however, has
a brighter side. Within recent months, there has been a
refreshing new attempt to bring some of America's best
minds to bear upon basic problems. It is generally
believed of late that much of the lack of success in this
field is due. to failure to examine the real impact of sensory
deprivation upon the human being. Similar lines of
thinking recently have been expressed openly in
Scandinavian and United Kingdom circles concerned with
service to blind people. Such utterances and conferences,
however, must at some point be brought to recognizable
stages of crystallization of thought.
During the past five years, there has been an acceleration
and diversification of efforts to examine the potential for
this field which arises through the use of electronic
computers. While the imagination of many persons has
been stimulated to believe that machines such as the IBM
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
NO ELECTRONIC EYE (Cont'd)
FROM SELF-THREADING NEEDLES
TO LIBRARIES OF TALKING BOOKS
704 may somehow produce in the form of Braille type
books and periodicals for blind persons in a matter of
minutes, these interpretations have not been kept in proper
perspective. Nevertheless, remarkable progress has been
made in programming such machines to produce advanced
forms of Braille in an economically short time, provided
that some new light can be shed upon the most practical
types of input and output. At the moment, there is
intense interest throughout the world in the present status
of such experimentation as well as a desire to examine the
long-range implications.
The application of modern techniques in the field of
sound recording, relatively well-known in English-speaking
countries for a quarter of a century, has only recently
been introduced in others. The first "'international"
recorded library service has been under way for European
countries for about three years, and is enjoying gratifyingly
rapid expansion.
ADiCALLY new designs are being suggested
* thanks to new impetus among private concerns
who are showing a tendency to believe that there is a
general market for longplaying recording machines.
Within recent months, the library programme of the blind
in the United Kingdom has partially introduced the use
of cassette-type tape playbacks. The United States with
more than 50,000 disc-type record players in use is reluc¬
tant to convert, but is carefully studying local and foreign
experience with tape.
There are in existence a number of highly useful
"gadgets" available in various countries which do help
blind persons in everyday tasks of daily living, study, work,
and recreation.
Changes in daily living as a whole have had a
kaleidoscopic effect on blind people. Radios, telephones
and electricity have done a great deal for them, as well
as central heating, insecticides, antibiotics, typewriters and
recorders. There are, however, a great many special aids
of various kinds which make life easier, for a blind person.
These include Braille watches, dials for cooking stoves,
measures for food, self-threading needles, bread cutting
boxes, signature guides and many others. For the blind
woman there are aids for personal grooming, for the blind
man safety and electric razors have been a boon.
Nowhere is the blind person better off today than in
the home, for here gadgetry has come to its fullest bloom.
To an astonishingly large extent, the devices to simplify
life for people with sight have also simplified life for those
who are blind.
There are sufficient tools in existence to enable the blind
student to pass courses in physics, mathematics, chemistry,
biology or geology. A vacuum forming process is produc¬
ing relief maps at low cost and can be used for designs
and diagrams and in other ways to assist the study of the
sciences. Special mathematical devices are available that
can work out calculations of the most intricate kinds.
There are special appliances that enable a blind person
to do a job, and persuade an employer that the job is
possible. For instance, there are measuring devices for
length, weight, temperature, time, relative humidity,
barometric pressure, blood pressure, voltage, current,
resistance and capacity. The blind shorthand typist today
has an almost noiseless machine on which he can take
shorthand dictation at a speed of 140 words and more a
minute. Other tools are produced for the use of blind
workers, such as piano tuners, shoe repairmen and
carpenters. Blind telephone operators are enabled to
function with the aid of special adaptations to standard
switchboards.
A constant search for new games and other recreational
aids is going on. Among standard games especially
adapted for the blind are chess, draughts, dominoes,
puzzles and playing cards. Bingo boards can be had, as
can a game of fairly recent origin called scrabble which
can also double as an anagram game when extra tiles are
secured. For the active blind adults there are many
activities such as rowing, riding, skiing, wrestling that can
be carried on with little or no assistance. A portable
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
'You just must watch
what you are doing'
As blind Joyce Rominger handles the tele¬
phone calls that come through her switchboard
at an industrial plant in Chattanooga, Tennes¬
see, she manipulates the keys and controls as
deftly and swiftly as her sighted colleagues.
She can do so thanks to a special Braille dial
switchboardone of many now in use in various
countries. Joyce graduated from the Alabama
School for the Blind in 1956 and afterwards
took Braille switchboard training. She over¬
came her next big hurdle when she found an
employer who believed she could handle a
dial switchboard and was ready to go to the
trouble and expense of installing one. The
Braille attachment to the switchboard is a
square box containing rows of plungers under
each of which is a station number in Braille.
When a call comes in, the corresponding
plunger pops up with a buzz. Joyce locates
the plunger, reads the Braille below it (left,
below), runs her fingers across a strip of
Braille on the switchboard to locate the station
number (left, above), inserts the jack, reads the
Braille strip under the switches and flips the
correct one. "How in the world do you keep
from getting all those lines tangled up?"
someone once asked her. " Well, you just
have to watch what you're doing," she replied.
Photos © Camera Press Ltd., London.
bowling rail is the only special piece of equipment which
comes to mind.
When blindness is the sole disability there is probably
no great need for research into medical aid. Often,
however, blindness is one aspect of a systemic disease as
in diabetes or Hansen's disease (leprosy) or multiple
sclerosis. For the blind diabetic, special syringes with
devices for locating the centre of the rubber cap on the
insulin vial and with automatic injections are available.
For other purposes there are clinical thermometers and drop
measures.
Helen Keller's example has helped bring into focus* not
only the needs of the deaf-blind but their potentialities as
well. A growing number of deaf-blind persons are finding
employment and the need has been met for a suitable alarm
clock which would shake the bed at the proper time for
rising. A device, such as the American Tellatouch, has
been developed which activates the appropriate Braille
symbols from a keyboard similar to the typewriter
keyboard.
The increasing concern about past failures and future
promises currently is the basis for a proposed international
congress on technology in blindness. With the formal
endorsement of the World Council for the Welfare of the
Blind and the active co-operation of national agencies in
a number of countries, interested bodies in the United
States are now attempting to arrange for the financial
support that would be needed to prepare and carry out
such a conference. While the proposed meeting, probably
to be held in late 1961, will of course provide an
opportunity for exchange of information and views on
every appropriate item, its principal objective will be to
establish if possible just what lines of investigation and
construction hold the most promise for eventual success.
A profoundly honest re-searching of concepts is hoped
for. At its conclusion, and with the expected co¬
operation of all organized research centres and agencies
for the blind, there should be the establishment of a
continuing system for the reporting of research in progress
and results obtained such information to then be available
to others who wish to enter their ideas into what is
undoubtedly an exciting challenge.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
B rai
trans
11
la t ion
by computer
Today much attention is being given to the
automation of Braille publishing so as to give
blind readers greater access to specialized
books and articles. Needs of the blind far exceed the
Braille books available despite the efforts of Braille
publishing houses and volunteer transcribers.
Now a new programme has been developed by
IBM using its famous 704 electronic computer, in co¬
operation With the American Printing House for the
Blind. Together they have developed a process of
using the computer to translate the printed text
into Braille. The machine can convert a 300-page
book into Braille in one hour a job that would take
skilled translators more than six days. Writing
Braille is a complicated process where symbols often
change their meaning in a different context and
many special contractions and abbreviations, much
like shorthand, are used.
Texts to be translated by the electronic computer
are first transcribed on punched cards. These are
then fed directly into the computer, which has had
stored in its memory a programme or set of rules
for conversion of English into Braille. The IBM 704
executes as many as 600 instructions per word in
less than a fortieth of a second. Contractions and
abbreviations are determined by matching the letters
against an alphabetical table of Braille equivalents.
How does the process compare with that made by
a human translator? For example, suppose that the
word "changeable" is to be transcribed. A skilled
human transcriber would write this as seven
Braille characters, Ch-a-n-g-e-a-ble, where ch and
ble are contractions each represented by a single
Braille character. Though there is also an "ea"
contraction in Braille, the transcriber does not use
it because here "e" belongs to a root .Word, "change,"
while the "a" belongs to a suffix, "able."
To accomplish the same result, the IBM 704 goes
through about 600 separate steps for the average
word, but converts 4,000 words per minute into
Braille roughly 100 times faster than the human
transcriber. This is made possible because electrons
travelling at thé speed of light, enable the machine
to handle 40,000 instructions per second.
The translated text emerges from the computer in
coded symbols on a punched cards and these, in
turn, are fed to the 704's printer unit which re¬
produces Braille symbols above the English text for
editing purposes. After editing, the corrected
punched cards are fed into an embossing machine
which produces metal plates for a rotary press.
In some respects the programme of machine
conversion to Braille resembles mechanical transla¬
tion from one language to another a much more
difficult problem on which many research organiza¬
tions are working. Diagram beJow shows how Braille
translations are made by the IBM computer.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The' Unesco Courter. June 1960
WHO Photo by Homer Page
EYE INFECTION Is a major cause of blindness, and trachoma the chief culprit, disabling some 400 million people throughout
the world. In India, with more than two million, blind persons, trachoma ranks as the largest single cause of preventable blindness.
Above, Dr. Jatnam Singh, member of a medical team, examines a young trachoma victim in a village of northern India where in
some rural areas between 80 and 90 per cent of the people suffer from this infection. The team, with WHO help, works its way
through the region, examining patients, organizing mass antibiotic treatment, and carrying out research on spread of infection.
MORE BLIND PERSONS IN CALCUTTA
THAN IN THE WHOLE OF CANADA
by W. H. Owens
More than a century of effort, mainly through volun¬
tary societies, has opened up a new world of oppor¬
tunity for sightless people.
While the incidence of blindness is still fairly high in the
advanced countries, normally preventable blindness has
been reduced to a minimum through the progress and
general availability of medical, hygiene and social services.
But the condition of the infinitely larger blind popula¬
tions in the lesser developed parts of the world is very
different indeed. It is worst of all in Asia and Africa where
about four-fifths of all the world's blind people live, and
where, until very recently, blindness was fatalistically
accepted everywhere as one of the irremediable conditions
of mankind. Although the highest incidence of the loss
of sight is in Africa, where in the upper reaches of the
Nile more than 4,000 per 100,000 population have defec¬
tive vision, by far the greatest concentration of blindness
is in Asia.
India alone has more than 2,000,000 blind persons, of
whom at least 100,000 are children. In the city of Cal¬
cutta there are more blind people than in the whole of
Canada. Existing welfare services hardly touch more than
one per cent of those without sight, most of whom are
widely scattered in villages all over the vast sub-continent
and are doomed to live, as the blind of India have always
lived, as beggars or family dependents, often in misery
and want.
Probably 90 per cent of all the blindness in the lesser
developed countries is caused by preventable disease. In
West Africa, for example, over 400,000 people su fier from
CONT'D OH NEXT FAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
CALCUTTA (Cont'd)
FOUR-FIFTHS OF WORLD'S
SIGHTLESS IN RURAL AREAS
onchocerciasis, or river blindness, an eye disease spread
by carrier flies. This is so rampant in the northern parts
of Ghana and Nigeria that these regions have been called
"the country of the blind". (Unesco Courier, April 1956.)
Trachoma, which has been a major cause of blindness
for over 2,000 years, claims millions of victims in many
parts of the world and, in fact, only western Europe, North
America and Australasia are relatively free from it. But
with modern drugs trachoma can now be cured.
In the past ten or twelve years some remarkable progress
has been made. Since its foundation in 1949, the World
Council for the Welfare of the Blind has grown from a
small group, representing mainly the countries of Western
Europe and North America, into a truly international body
drawing its members from all the five continents. Central
organizations for blind training and welfare are now
established in many Asian, African and Latin-American
countries where nothing of the kind existed previously, and,
what is also very important, methods to check the spread
of eye disease are being put into effect on a steadily
increasing scale.
The United Nations and its special agencies have taken
active interest in the problems, of the blind by intensifying
research into the causes of blindness, by controlling disease-
spreading pests, and by improving living conditions and
treatment facilities. Mobile eye dispensaries are operating
successfully in Egypt, India, Pakistan and elsewhere. The
World Health Organization and the U.N. Children's Fund
contribute greatly to the world wide anti-trachoma cam¬
paign.
Valuable research projects have been carried put in
West Africa by the Royal Commonwealth Society for
the Blind. (This British voluntary organization,
founded in 1950, is working through local blind welfare
associations in about thirty emergent territories throughout
the world.) In the course of a four-year investigation of
blindness in West Africa an ophthalmic team, led by
Dr Frederick Rodger, travelled more than 100,000 miles
through Ghana, the Cameroons and Northern Nigeria,
often under very difficult conditions in remote and wild
country.
Intensive ophthalmic examinations of more than 8,000
individuals, selected from widely different areas and racial
groups throughout the region, showed that trachoma, cata¬
ract and onchocerciasis are the main causes of blindness
but that much sight is also lost through smallpox, measles,
tuberculosis and syphilis. The 350-page report resulting
from this investigation, entitled "Blindness in West
Africa", is the most detailed and exhaustive study of its
kind ever made and has won international acclaim.
For a century or longer the training of blind people has
been confined almost entirely to handicraft workshops in
towns and cities. Some 80 per cent of the world's blind
live in rural areas, however, and up to now very little
indeed has been done for them apart from the limited
though excellent work of foreign missions. Realizing this,
the 1959 Assembly of the World Council for the Welfare
of the Blind passed a resolution urging the need for train¬
ing in agricultural and rural crafts so that sightless people
might become useful members of their own communities.
This new conception of blind training has been
pioneered with great success in five African countri s and
12
also in the Far East by the Royal Commonwealth Society
for the Blind. The results have been so promising that
similar schemes of rural training may soon be launched
in other countries. They have demonstrated the value of
a policy which, if it were to be applied on a really large
scale for example, through the community development
programme of a country like India might in a few years
open up a new age for very large numbers of blind people
in the lesser developed parts of the world.
A typical rural training scheme in Africa is the 60-acre
Ikeja Farmcraft Centre, near Lagos, which is run for the
Nigerian Government. Blind villagers who attend this cen¬
tre, often with their wives, live for a year in surroundings
which are quite familiar to them. During an intensive
course the students learn about every branch of agriculture,
from the clearing of virgin bushland to the harvesting and
marketing of the crops they grow.
Experiments have been made with the cultivation of a
wide range of local crops such as yams, maize, groundnuts,
cotton, ochra, sun hemp, pineapples and so on. Using
mud, bamboo and palm leaf, the students learn also to
build their own living quarters and shelters for the
livestock. Students also spend a part of each day in
the workshop learning to make articles from home-grown
materials which will have a ready sale in the villages.
The first sixteen blind students attending the Ikeja cen¬
tre arrived in a helpless condition and most of them were
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
THE BLIND LEADING THE BLIND. This scene which recalls
Breughel's painting is a tragic everyday fact in large areas of Africa.
The blindness Is caused by a disease called onchocerciasis for which
a little black gnat is responsible. When It bites a human being,
It transmits microscopic worms which multiply under the skin,
then invade the tissue of the eyes, eventually bringing total blindness.
WHO
HELEN KELLER
WORLD CRUSADE
FOR THE BLIND
~%i
<^^ '
Helen Keller, known as the Ambassador of the
Blind, celebrates her 80th birthday this month.
To mark this event, the American Foundation
for the Overseas Blind is raising a $1,250,000 fund,
"The Helen Keller World Crusade for the Blind",
to be used for work among the world's sightless
people. Miss Keller has been associated with
the Foundation since its inception more than
40 years ago and as its International Relations
Counsellor has spent much time in areas of the
Middle East, Asia, Africa and Latin America
where nine-tenths of the world's blind live. Blind
and deaf from early childhood, she rose above
her handicaps to become one of the best-known
figures In the modern world. At 24 she graduated
from college ; since then has been constantly
travelling, writing and working to improve condi¬
tions for the world's blind. She has given cou¬
rage and assistance to innumerable blind people
for she believes that the blind should live and
work like their fellows, unremarked and with
full responsibility. She herself is a vivid example
of what special education and training can achieve
and she can look back on a lifetime studded
with achievements. Perhaps better than anyone
she can preach the gospel of self help for she
has lived It. Below, during one of her journeys
Miss Keller examines a broom made by blind
craftsmen in Kfar-Urlel, Village of the Blind, Israel.
-.«a ~ vv
undernourished. By the end of the year's training,
however, they were all 100 per cent physically fit, able to
tackle almost any job on the farm, and confident they
could be accepted as useful members in the village com¬
munities to which they returned.
How important rural training can be in a country where
four-fifths of the blind population are villagers has been
shown' at the Malayan fishing village of Kuala Besut in
Trengganu. For less than £50, the community built and
equipped a workshop and dormitory where blind villagers
can now provide the local fishing industry with rope, fish
frames and traps, brooms and rakes all made from
locally grown materials.
The National Association for the Blind in India has
shown keen interest in such schemes of rural training
because, as mentioned earlier, most of the 2,000,000 blind
of that country live in scattered village communities. The
problem in India may be measured by the vast numbers
involved, but a start may be made soon.
The second All India Conference for the Blind, held at
Bombay in June, 1959, passed a resolution urging the
Central and State Governments, together with voluntary
societies working for the Indian blind, to establish agricul¬
tural and rural training centres which would provide sight¬
less people with adaptive training in simple pursuits in
their familiar rural surroundings. Such schemes, it is
hoped, may be included in India's third five-year Plan.
USIS
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
VICTORY IN SIGHT OVER
THE BABEL OF BRAILLE
by Sir Clutha Mackenzie
In the century since Louis Braille invented his
ingenious "touch" alphabet of raised dots, a Babel
of Braille developed as his system was applied
in a variety of ways in different languages. In
1949 the Government of India asked Unesco to
take up the problem of the unification of Braille,
and rapid progress was made towards a broadly
uniform Braille system for all languages and
scripts. In 1952, a World Braille Council was
set up under the aegis of Unesco. Chairman of
the Council was Sir Clutha Mackenzie, himself
blind, who had been in charge of Unesco's work
in this field throughout this time. Here, Sir
Clutha describes some of the results that
have already been achieved through Unesco's
efforts to aid the unification of Braille scripts.
The task, to Which Unesco set its hand for two and
a half years from July, 1949, has brought rich rew¬
ards in the field of Braille reading and writing. It brought
an end to the long arguments over conflicting systems in
many Asian, African and Latin-American countries and at
the same time resulted in the rationalization of the systems
used in Yugoslavia and Spain. Through the generosity of
the American Foundation for Overseas Blind, Braille
presses have been established in many centres throughout
the world to print much-needed school text books, maga¬
zines and general literature; this has all gone along with a
big upsurge in the general rehabilitation of the blind of
these great areas.
I first encountered Braille conflicts in 1939 when, at the
request of the Government of Bombay, I studied the
schools for the blind in that Province. One of the most
glaring defects was the existence of two divergent Braille
systems in the city of Bombay itself with the result that
the children and ex-students of the two schools could not
read one another's Braille forms.
When I returned to India in 1942 to establish an Indian
St Dunstan's for the rehabilitation of the war-blinded, it
appeared that India had no less than eight rival systems.
These arose from the fact that early missions, in founding
small scattered schools, adapted Braille in their own ways
to local languages. About half of these systems followed
the original letters of Louis Braille, the gallant, blind
Frenchman who had designed the Braille alphabet in 1827.
As Indian languages, however, employ from fifty-five to
sixty-five letters, the possibilities of the twenty-six Roman
letters were soon exhausted; and almost no uniformity held
good among the remaining letters.
Braille, it should be explained, is comprised of the sixty-
three possible combinations of dots employed in the
domino sox (three dots high and two wide). This is
ample for a script of from fifty to fifty-five letters plus
punctuation and accent marks; but difficulties arise when
the letters exceed these numbers. The schools were all
alive to the grave handicaps this situation imposed, but
conference after conference failed to bring agreement.
The attitude most of the schools took up was that each
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
would be delighted to attain uniformity were its own code
accepted.
The Central Government's Department of Education
made a new approach in 1940 when it set up a special
committee to study the problem and to recommend a code
for Ail-India. It is accepted practice among modern
workers for the blind that Braille matters should be decided
by the users of the system, the blind themselves. The
Education Department, unfortunately unaware of this,
appointed four sighted men, only one of whom had any
extensive experience of Braille teaching.
Its report, published in 1943, only contributed to
further confusion by adding a ninth system. The findings
were referred to me in my capacity as secretary of a Joint
Committee of the Departments of Health and Education
appointed to report on the big question of the problems of
blindness in India. It was impossible to recommend this
new code as it complied with none of the basic rules of
the Braille system. Simply put, these were that the same
letter or the same or nearly similar sound of a letter should
everywhere be represented by the same Braille character.
Were the Indian blind to confine their reading and contacts
to only one language, this would be of little importance;
but the fact that the educated Indian blind almost invariably
learn at least one foreign language (and often two or even
three) makes this principle essential.
Another factor of importance is that most languages
employ "contracted Braille." With European languages
this form is based on frequency studies of the common
combinations of letters used as prefixes, suffixes and
digraphs. In English, for example, "ing," "ed," "dis"
and the ch, gh, sh and th all have their single Braille
sign. A few of these had been embodied in the earlier
Indian systems, most Indian languages expressing these
sounds by their own single letters. Again, Indian and
many other Oriental languages have more vowels than
English, but the additional vowels can mostly be
accommodated by the extra vowels of European languages.
We gathered together an ad hoc committee of blinded
Indians, each knowing from three to five languages, and
the blind English head of a school for the Blind in the
Madras Presidency. This Committee designed an Indian
code which would fit in with these principles. Their
report was duly discussed with the Education Department's
Special Committee, but this had no immediate effect on
the situation.
Today, however Braille books, especially for educational
and vocational training purposes, are being printed at
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE.
Stamps to honour
& help the blind
by C. W. Hill
Although by its very nature philately is one of the
cultural pursuits which the blind are unable to
enjoy, the philatelist can make an interesting and ithought-
provoking collection of stamps which have been issued in
aid of funds for the blind, or in honour of those who have
devoted themselves to helping the blind.
One of two stamps issued in France last December in
aid of Red Cross funds portrayed Valentin Haiiy who,
inspired by the efforts of his contemporary, the Abbé de
l'Epée, on behalf of the deaf and dumb, opened a school
in Paris for the education of young blind persons. The
work which he began in 1784 is now carried on in France
by the Valentin Haiiy Association and his school has
become the National Institution for the Young Blind.
Haiiy's experiments with the printing of books in a
raised type which the blind could read with their finger¬
tips were continued by Louis Braille, a pupil and after¬
wards a professor at the National Institution. Braille's por¬
trait is shown on a French stamp of 1948 which paid tri¬
bute to his work and the 150th anniversary of his birth
was marked last year by the issue in the Soviet Union of
a stamp which also bears his portrait. The universal bene
fits of the Braille type are illustrated on a Brazilian stamp
of 1954 issued to celebrate the centenary of the founda¬
tion of the Benjamin Constant Institute for the Education
of the Blind in Brazil. The design shows a portrait of
Constant and the hand of a blind person reading a book
in Braille.
Many countries regularly issue stamps bearing a pre¬
mium in aid of social work among handicapped persons,
including the blind. One stamp of the Netherlands charity
series issued in 1956 appropriately showed a Rembrandt
etching of "Old Blind Tobias", and the two French Red
Cross stamps of 1957 reproduced engravings by the seven¬
teenth century artist, Jacques Callot, in which the miseries
of poverty and blindness are portrayed with the realism
typical of his work. The provision of radios for the blind
is another branch of social work for which a French
stamp was issued, this being in 1938.
When the new underground Basilica was consecrated at
Lourdes two years ago, Monaco celebrated the occasion,
and the centenary of the Apparition of the Virgin Mary,
by issuing a series of commemorative stamps. One of these
recalls the miracle of the workman Bourriette, who had
lost the sight of an eye in a mining accident and claimed
the complete restoration of his sight when he bathed his
eyes in water from the spring of the Massabielle Rock.
A collection of stamps connected with the blind would
be incomplete without the issues which honour blind men
who have contributed to our cultural heritage. Many
Greek stamps recall the epics of Homer, who by tradition
was blind, and a bust of the poet forms the design of two
recent Greek issues. One of Britain's greatest poets, John
Milton, was also blind and his portrait is to be found on
a stamp of the Soviet Union issued in 1958 to mark the
350th anniversary of his birth.
¡5
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
BABEL OF BRAILLE (Cont'd)
Dehra Dun, and for the first time in India in a uniform
code capable of serving all the different languages of the
sub-continent. At this, the first central institution of its
kind in India, a small but very valuable beginning is being
made with the immense task of attacking what is one of
the major social problems of that country.
Making a report for the Government of China in 1947
we found a similar situation to that in India eight
conflicting codes. . Workers for the Blind in China
however had the justification that Chinese ideographic
script of 50,000 characters was a much harder nut to
crack.
The blind British manager of a Peking bank had designed
quite an original system. Reuters' Telegraph Co. had
discovered that the Chinese language was composed of
some 400 syllables and tone marks. Instead of trying to
telegraph the 50,000 ideographic characters, Reuters had
serially numbered the syllables. The bank manager
replaced these with their corresponding Braille numbers.
The result was a system which the Chinese child could
master in the course of time, coming to recognise the
numbers as the syllables which they represented.
The adaptations of Braille for the various languages
employing Arabic script numbered about fifteen. These
included, not only the various dialects, but also certain
distinct languages from Hausa in the West to Malay in the
East. Some of them read from right to left and some
from left to right this directional problem was only solved
after some difficulty, but the Arabs courteously yielded to
World Braille practice.
I had the pleasure, in Pakistan in 1954, of receiving
forty sets of Koran in the new International Arabic Braille
from an Arabic Braille Press in Hashemite Jordan, and of
presenting them to schools for the blind and leading blind
mullahs as a gift from the American Foundation for
Overseas Blind. The Braille was so closely akin to the
new Urdu Braille of Pakistan that it could be read
immediately by blind Pakistanis. The blind Pakistani is
fond, too, of Persian poetry and will be delighted when
Persia has her own Braille press and publishes these works
in International Iranian Braille.
The two and a half years I was with Unesco were
entirely taken up with the solution of orthographic Braille
problems in five continents; but with their end Unesco
bequeathed the continuation of the task to the World
Braille Council, a small body to which I was nominated
Chairman. Much work remained to be done, not only in
16
getting the new International Braille systems adopted, but
also in other fields of Braille where disunity persisted,
notably in muse notation and mathematical and chemical
symbols.
Louis Braille was an intelligent pupil of the first school
for the blind in the world, that was founded in Paris in
1782. He became both an organist and a Professor of
Mathematics at the School, and naturally he commanded
the services of his six dots so that they could adequately
represent these subjects as well as orthography. In the
course of their spread, however, divergencies have also
grown up.
In Paris in 1954, under the joint auspices of Unesco
and of the World Council for the Welfare of the Bund, we
held our International Conference on Braille Music Nota¬
tion. A new International Manual has been published
which has led to an improvement in International
uniformity, but not yet to the degree anticipated. Nev¬
ertheless, negotiations continue in the hopes of gaining
more complete agreement. During 1959 at the W.C.W.B.
Conference in Rome (which now has totally succeeded
Unesco as our old parent body) it was agreed that the
study of mathematical and chemical symbols should be
proceeded with, this task to be in the hands of Professor
Pierre Henri, himself blind and the ultimate successor of
Louis Braille in the same post in the same school in Paris
Institution Nationale des Jeunes Aveugles.
The adaptation of African languages to International
Braille, when reference is made to the International Pho¬
netic Alphabet and the special Table of Braille Signs for
African Languages, contained in the Unesco publication,
"'World Braille Usage", presents no real difficulty. The
Committee on Bantu Languages is engaged at this moment
in planning alphabets for four South African languages
and similar work is under way in Central, East and West
Africa. The problems arising from the publication of sev¬
eral forms of Spanish contracted Braille in Latin-America
have also been solved ; and thus the excellent work, under¬
taken by Unesco, has yielded and is still yielding rich
results in all three departments of Braille.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
THE GULF IS VANISHING
by Pierre Henri
T
\\ "Tp he blind need more than knowledge or university
degrees if they are to have equal chances in the
world of those who can see... A hundred years ago
it was a great achievement to be able to teach
a sightless person how to read, write, count and
to provide him with a minimum of general knowledge.
Today It means very little."
When I wrote this in an article for The Unesco Courier
(The Blind are Achieving a Fuller Rôle in Everyday
Life March, 1952) I was, in no way asserting as has
since been said that it is pointless to educate the blind.
To have upheld such a viewpoint would have been absurd.
In a world where educated men and women are striving
to bring the benefits of education to those who have so
far been deprived of them, it is inconceivable that one
group of human beings the blind should be ignored.
Furthermore, anyone who is deprived in some measure
of his physical or sensorial powers must make greater
demands on his intellect to compensate for what he lacks.
Even the sighted person sees as much with his mind as
with his eyes. But where the sighted person perceives, the
blind one must learn to understand and to familiarize
himself with what he cannot see: the implements he uses,
his home and his town. He has to use his imagination
and create a mental picture of so many things. If John
Locke the English philsopher called for "'a sound mind in
a sound body," we might in the present context affirm
that "'the less sound the body the greater the need for a
sound mind."
If the personality is deprived through an infirmity of
one of its elements, frustration is likely to occur. Unless
there is some form of compensation, sightlessness tends to
cause an imbalance. Education provides just such a
compensation: by widening vision through the mind it
acts as a safety valve, prevents the development of
Pierre Henri is Vice-Chairman of the World Braille Council,
created under Unesco's auspices, and is professor at the National
Institution of the Young Blind, Paris.
frustrations and reduces the danger of inner emotional
conflicts.
A man does not live in a vacuum, however, nor act by
and for himself alone. He is an integral part of an entity
where physical world, social universe and individual self
come togelther. From this viewpoint, education offers to
the blind person a way to restore himself in the eyes of
other men and thus, as it were, in his awn eyes. Thus
the feeling that it will compensate for their reduced
physical state stimulates the hunger of the disabled for
education.
It is in this respect that the Braille system, that
indispensable tool of learning which helps the blind to
equality with other men, has proved its worth. It was,
in fact, regarded at one time as a cure-all, as the answer
to the most difficult problem in the rehabilitation of the
blind. But whereas the development of intelligence and
the acquisition of knowledge are certainly useful elements
in this process of rehabilitation, they are by no means
the only ones.
The American psychologist, Thomas Cutsforth, himself
blind, advanced views in a study published in 1933 which
rather shocked people at the time, but which are
generally accepted today. Cutsworth argued that, no
matter at' what age it occurs, blindness immediately begins
to shape the personality in direct relation to the fact of
sightlessness. This is perhaps most apparent to the
ordinary person in a physical way. We have only to think
of the peculiarities of stance or gesture which are exhibited
by some blind people. They are so completely related to
blindness as to be known as "'blindisms."
The uninformed person would regard these as nervous
tics caused by blindness. They are in fact, usually fixed
habits, mostly acquired in very early childhood: a display
of hostility to the physical world (head thrown back, fore¬
arms held horizontally with hands hanging down, walking
on the heels with toes raised and feet apart) ; photophobia
(head held down); muscular activity designed to
compensate for a sedentary existence (movements of the
CONT'D ON PAGE 3 I
BLIND COUPLE
RAISES A FAMILY
Leading a happy family life in spite of blindness
has been the achievement of Mr. and Mrs. James
DiBiase of New York City. They play with
their children, Janet and Billy, have family
outings and are busy keeping up their modest
but pleasant home. With so many interests,
they have no time for self-pity. Marjorie
DiBiase does her own housework, and Jimmy
DiBiase has three jobs, running his news-stand
in the daytime, teaching music at the Brooklyn
Industrial School for the Blind in the evening,
and playing the piano in cafés during weekends.
Marjorie, a vivacious, cheerful woman, lost
her sight when she was nine years old; Jimmy
was only two when blindness struck him.
Both their children have normal vision. A
stranger, watching the group gathering around
the piano (left) would never realize that two
were sightless. "There are just a few things
we do differently from other people," says Mar¬
jorie "If the children want us to see something,
they have to put our hands on it. They accept
this as natural, because they grew up with it."
USIS
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
'DO-IT-YOURSELF'
STARTS EARLY
Among children under five only seven
in every 100,000 are blind whereas the
proportion of blind people in the world
as a whole is nearer 3 50 for every
100,000 inhabitants. Thus most blind
children have had sight at some time and
benefit from a visual memory which is
a definite aid to education. In many
countries this education is given in special
classes or special schools but as far as
possible it follows the lines of that given
to sighted children. Today many thou¬
sands of the young sightless are learning
to step out without fear, to play and work
with the seeing and to surmount their
disability. Above, reading a Braille book
in a U.S. school; left, young cooks in the
making at an English school; right, learn¬
ing to clamber about fearlessly on these
bars is part of the experience of living,
studying and playing together which all
children, sightlessor sighted, should have.
Campbell Press Studios Ltd., London.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
USX...
The blind
in the U.S.S.R.
OUT OF
THE
DARKNESS
by A. Kondratov
Deputy Chairman, All-Russian Society
of the Blind
il
he 1897 census in Russia recorded 250,000 blind
I persons. They lived mostly in regions inhabit¬
ed by national minorities with low living and cultural
standards and where infectious diseases (trachoma,
smallpox, blennorrhoea) were prevalent.
The majority of the blind then lived on a miserable
pittance granted them by charities or on alms from the
public. In the whole of Russia there was only one crafts
centre for the blind (in St. Petersburg) where a few dozen
persons were employed making brushes and weaving
baskets, though small groups of blind persons were also
employed in the workshops of the Moscow, Smolensk,
Samara and Kostroma Schools for the Blind.
In 1925 the All-Russian Society of the Blind was
founded as a voluntary association of blind citizens in
order to integrate the blind into society. Somewhat later,
similar societies Were founded in each of the Soviet
Republics.
To obtain funds the Society opened shops and dining-
rooms, barbers' shops and shooting galleries, organized
collections in offices and factories and arranged lotteries
and concerts. Work was found for individuals and for
small groups of blind persons in co-operatives for invalids
and in factories and offices. It soon became apparent that
it would be more useful to open special workshop schools
for the blind. The earliest of these were simple' little
workshops of the cottage industry type where brushes,
baskets and felt boots were made.
Today, all workshop schools are under the management
of the Society of the Blind which runs 268 such institu¬
tions. In 1960 these will produce a variety of articles
valued at approximately 1,700 million roubles.
The past seven years have seen the transition from the
traditional types of manual labour for the blind to work
in highly mechanized factories Where complicated
techniques are used. The Society's Moscow factories fill
20
government orders for a wide range of articles, including
luminescent lamp regulators, electric motors, spare parts
for seed drills, and electrical equipment; Leningrad
factories turn out low-voltage transformers and conveyor
belts for reaping machines; a Chelyabinsk factory makes
cushioned seats for tractors, and a Gorky factory produces
air filters for motor vehicles (nylon and metal). Other
items produced by the blind are coarse and fine filters for
oil and diesel engine fuel, signalling apparatus for mines,
cardboard boxes of all types, electronic apparatus, '
mechanics' tools, spare parts for motor vehicles, tractors
and combine harvesters and plastic articles.
The workshop schools accept people who have lost their
sight at a mature age and have to change their occupation,
as well as young people who have graduated from the
state secondary schools for the bünd.
The type of school workshop, is selected with a view to
employing, as far as possible, only blind persons; the
equipment, its arrangement, safety precautions, etc., are
all adapted to the work of blind persons. Only those
operations beyond the scope of the blind are performed
by sighted workers; as a rule their number (including
clerks and specialists) does not exceed 33% of the total
number of employees.
The usual shields and guards over moving parts of
machines that are considered adequate for sighted Workers
are quite inadequate when the machines are operated by
blind persons. Die presses operated by the blind must
be fully enclosed though this is not necessary for sighted
workers. Factories, and even many co-operative
workshops employing invalids, do not find it necessary to
break up production processes into a number of single
operations, but where the blind are employed this
is absolutely essential. Blind workers also need automatic
stopping devices, sound signalling systems and magnetic
switches in place of knife switches.
In the Soviet Union, factories employing blind persons
are run at a profit. In 1959 total profits amounted to 306
million Toubles all of which was used to improve the
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
BLIND CHILDREN
LEARN TO DRAW
Drawing lessons for blind children sound just
as strange as music lessons for the deaf. Yet
various methods which make this possible
have been devised in different countries. A
graphic system of teaching known as "typhlo-
graphy" is employed in Russian schools for
blind children, for example, and enables them
to think in terms of space, to develop their
spatial imagination and to draw objects on
paper as they "see" them. The process
includes the use of easily-made and easy-to-
understand outlines of objects such as the
icebreaker (far left). Different sides of the
object are shown so . that when these are
combined (details of the icebreaker's deck
are shown below side view) the child has a
good idea of the complete object, even when
it has a complicated form. Typhlography goes
much further than simple drawings and iden¬
tification. It can teach sightless students
such skills as geometrical diagrams and pro¬
jections and industrial design. As in all
modern schools for blind children, the methods
used here follow as closely as possible those
of equivalent grade schools for the sighted.
The result is a development of character and
behaviour patterns that include the fun and
satisfaction of teasing a schoolmate by giving
a tug at her plait as she climbs the stairs, (left).
Photos E. Don
working and living conditions of blind persons and to
provide for holidays and medical treatment. This income
enables the society to carry out all its activities and to
expand its operations without government subsidies.
The law on universal compulsory seven-year education
applies equally to the blind and the state provides special
schools in which the blind are given a normal education.
Children receive a general education and new methods,
employing relief models, make up for the lack of visual
aids to teaching; the syllabus is fully comparable to that
of the ordinary schools.
In the Russian Federation of the U.S.S.R. there are 62
boarding schools for bünd children, 11 evening schools for
young workers and three inter-regional, correspondence
schools providing a full secondary education without loss
of working time. School graduates may continue their
education or engage in some productive work.
D n recent years particular attention has been
paid to the technical side of education.
Workshops are being opened at schools where pupils work
at cardboard-box making and at die presses, do mecha¬
nics' jobs and woodworking and make brushes. In addi¬
tion to technical training and production practice in the
school workshops the pupils of some schools get extra
practical training in factories belonging to the Society of
the Blind. When a blind person is graduated from a
secondary school he has, in addition to his general edu¬
cation, learned some trade.
There are several hundred blind persons among the
students of Soviet schools of higher learning. Their state
scholarship grants are 50% higher than those of sighted
students which enables them to hire readers. There are
blind barristers, blind schoolteachers and blind lecturers
in colleges. At Moscow University alone there are nine
blind professors and lecturers.
There are 1,500 various kinds of libraries for blind
people with 824,000 books printed in Braille. From 275
to 350 titles of books are printed annually. The Societies
publish several periodicals in Braille. The monthly "Life
of the Blind" has a circulation of 12,000.
Persons invalided by blindness enjoy considerable
privileges. They do not pay income tax. They work only
six hours a day and have longer annual holidays than
sighted workers. They do not pay fares on city transport.
The blind are also granted pensions on favourable terms.
A youth of 21 (blind from childhood) would be granted a
pension of 85% of his month's wages up to 500 roubles
and 10% on all over 500 roubles, plus 15% for nursing;
the pension is payable in addition to wages. Old age
pensions are also higher. A blind woman is entitled to
an old-age pension at the age of 40 provided she has
worked for ten years; a blind man who has worked for
15 years is entitled to an old-age pension at the age of 50.
The public health bodies carry out a periodical examina¬
tion of all blind persons to check up on the possibility
of treatment or for the provision of artificial eyes; they
also render therapeutic or other medical assistance. In
Pyatigorsk there is a special sanatorium for the blind.
Year by year the working and living conditions of the
blind improve. This year the All-Russian Society of the
Blind plans to spend some 142 million roubles on building.
As a general rule factories, houses, clubs, schools,
kindergartens and nurseries are built on a single lot, as
one big complex. This allows for the concentration of
the blind and provides better conditions for the organiza¬
tion of their leisure.
Pre-revolutionary statistics registered only those persons
who were totally blind but the present system of record¬
ing regards as blind those whose better eye has a visual
acuity of 8 % or less (with correction) or with a diminished
field of vision up to 10 degrees.
In the Russian Federation there are 97,900 persons who
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
OUT OF THE DARKNESS (Cont'd)
are classified as first category invalids (i. e., helpless
invalids) on account of loss of sight; they include the
totally blind, those with a visual acuity of less than 4 %
with correction and aged persons whose weak vision is
due to senility.
The All-Russian Society of the Blind also has on its
books about 68,000 persons with imperfect sight. They
have a visual acuity of more than 4 % but are granted
the same privileges as the totally blind and are given
employment in the Society's factories or in invalid co¬
operatives; some of them are also found employment in
ordinary factories.
TATisTTcs for the past forty years show that
I the number of totally blind adults has been
reduced to one third of the former figure and the number
of totally blind children to one fifth. In view of this the
question of reducing the number of schools for the blind
has been raised. Greater attention is being paid to the
establishment of interregional boarding schools. It is
planned to set up separate schools for blind children and
for those With impaired vision; the latter will employ
special visual teaching aids and suitable optical devices
and lighting. In this field there is still much to be done.
The initiative of The Unesco Courier in devoting a
special issue to the problems confronting the blind
throughout the world will draw the attention of the gen¬
eral public to those problems and result in greater contact
between Societies of the Blind in different countries, a
pooling of their experience and an extension of their
work.
22
Official Soviet photos
WORLD AT THEIR FINGERTIPS. Boys and girls in a Soviet school
for the blind follow a geography lesson with the aid of special globes on
which the features stand out in relief. Top photo, members of the
sports club do special exercises which help to develop poise and balance.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
DOS & DON'TS
FOR THE SIGHTED
by F. Potter
One of the greatest causes of depression, frustra¬
tion and sometimes of acute pain to the
blind is the" attitude of other people towards them.
One naturally feels sympathetic towards anyone who is
handicapped by blindness, and one is anxious to render
him assistance whenever possible; but the manner in which
that help is given can make a great deal of difference in the
effect produced.
It can make the blind person feel that he is still just
like other people except for his lack of sight, or it can
make him feel that he is a helpless encumbrance, and the
person who has only recently been deprived of his sight is
particularly vulnerable. Here are a few suggestions for
When a blind person is seen standing near the edge of
a pavement, it is very likely that he wishes to cross the
road. But anyone wishing to help should not just take his
arm and try to lead him across without a word; he may
be waiting there for a friend. "Can I help you?", will
cover the situation quite adequately. If, however, he has
decided to attempt the crossing unaided which may even¬
tually happen if he has waited unsuccessfully for assistance
for a long time do not stop him in "mid-stream" to ask
whether he needs your help, for. then the strain of trying
to concentrate his attention on the traffic sounds all
around him and of answering your question at the same
time is very great. Just take his arm and lead him to safety,
parting from him with a "you are all right now", or "you
have just crossed... street". And don't forget to give
warning of kerbs and steps "step up", or "step down".
Some good folk, when leading a blind person, seize his
' arm in a vice-like grasp and try to hoist it up to shoulder
level. (Such over-anxiety to render maximum assistance
giving aid in the manner in which it will be most
appreciated.
It is obviously very desirable for a sightless person to
carry a white stick in the street primarily as a means of
mobility, and also to make clear his incapacity and need
of assistance under certain conditions. Yet many blind
people feel that it is degrading to carry such a stick
because of the exaggerated pity which it evokes in the
minds of the sighted. Such half-whispered remarks (which
are usually clearly heard by the blind) as, "Look at that
poor blind man! How terrible!" are often the cause of the
man never carrying a white stick again.
Don't lift him bodily on to the bus
has sometimes even resulted in the man being lifted almost
bodily on to a tous.) A light grip on the arm with firm
pressures for directional guidance and verbal instructions
regarding steps are all that are really necessary, and do not
cause the person to feel clumsy and awkward. After you
help him across a street, it is unlikely that he will ask you
to accompany him further, thereby causing you incon¬
venience. The fact that he is out alone will indicate that
he is quite able to go on his way unaided, requiring assis¬
tance only when crossing busy roads.
A visually handicapped person sometimes finds it diffi¬
cult in a crowded room to know exactly when he is being
addressed, especially if the speaker is some distance from
him. Under such circumstances, confusion and embarrass¬
ment are avoided by the use of his name when opening
a conversation.
Never '"talk over" him to his guide, as he would much
prefer to speak for himself.
Don't assume all the blind have keen hearing
There are a number of fairly widespread misconceptions
about the blind which might usefully be corrected. The
most common one is that blind people have unusually keen
hearing. This belief is particularly fallacious in western
countries where the great majority of the sightless become
blind after the age of fifty 50 per cent after sixty.
Thus, for physiological reasons, most blind people are not
likely to have a more acute sense of hearing than the ave¬
rage sighted person with normal hearing. However, lack¬
ing sight, the visually handicapped are obliged to make
greater use of other senses, and are thus able to con¬
centrate their whole attention on what they hear and smell
so as to gain information about their surroundings. An
"observant" blind person can learn quite a lot about a
stranger from his footsteps, his breathing, his handshake,
and, of course, his voice, manner of speaking, and laugh.
It is also erroneous to think that most blind people read
Braille. Because of the relatively high incidence of blind¬
ness after the age of fifty, the majority of blind people are
Fred Potter, who is blind, is a member of Unesco's secretarial staff.
unable to cultivate a sufficiently sensitive touch to read
Braille with any great fluency, and this has led to the de¬
velopment of the "Talking Book" (recorded on discs)
which is increasing in popularity as reproducing apparatus
becomes cheaper. The Braille system is easily memorized,
but the cultivation of a sensitive touch usually takes many
months or even years.
Music in all its forms is obviously a potential source of
great pleasure to the blind, but it is certainly not true to
say that all blind people are musicians or even enjoy music.
If a man is tone-deaf before he loses his sight, he remains
tone-deaf afterwards. In short, generalizations about the
blind are just as misleading as those sometimes applied to
races and nations.
Broadly speaking, one should treat blind people as per¬
fectly normal individuals who happen to be without sight
but who are in complete possession of all other faculties.
If, in a moment of forgetfulness, you were to ask a blind
man what he thought of your new shoes, he would be very
amused and feel himself complimented.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Photo Ray Manley
All the volley
ball players |
here are blind
A game of volley ball in progress at the New York
Institute for the Education of the Blind. The large
soft ball wouldn't hurt even if it hit a boy on the
head. In the centre of the court under the net is a
metronome which helps the boys to judge their
distance from the centre line. Athletics are very
much open to the blind. At the Arizona State
School for the Deaf and Blind, members of a group
of wrestlers pair off and practise some handstands
(above) to get themselves in top condition. Athletics
at the School include running and cycling (deaf and
sightless students ride together on tandem bicycles).
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June I960
French scouts &. Unesco
Clubs chalk up a success
FIFTEEN MILLION FRANCS OVERNIGHT
UNKRA
YOUNG KOREAN ORPHAN in the National School for the Blind at Seoul writes with one
of the special Braille plates supplied to the school through Unesco's Gift Coupon Programme.
Other Korean schools for the blind received help through the same programme which for the
past ten years has made possible a person-to-person international aid, with individuals and
groups in 14 countries raising funds to help pay for worthwhile educational projects in other
lands. Braille plates for the Seoul school were paid for by donors in U.S.A. and England.
IV
I ^B ever in the 10-year history of Unesco's Gift
^ Coupon Programme has there been a campaign
as dramatic and instantaneously successful as the unique
. nationwide public appeal launched last November in
France for funds to assist schools for the blind in various
parts of the world.
Sponsored by the French National Commission for
Unesco and conducted by the French Federation of
Unesco Clubs, with the aid of Boy Scouts' organizations,
the campaign was sparked by a radio broadcast on the
night of November 24. Before morning, over 15 million
francs ($30,000) had been collected from all over France.
Equal to the monetary success, which virtually wiped
out the most urgent needs for educational equipment of
five institutions for the blind on Unesco's Gift Coupon
project list, was the campaign's effectiveness in acquaint¬
ing a widespread audience with Unesco's overall efforts to
spur educational development, not only for the blind, but
for all people everywhere.
The Gift Coupon Programme has for ten years been a
popular vehicle for just such focussing of public attention
on problems in education throughout the world, as well
as for enlisting individual co-operation in working to
solve them. Designed at first to help reconstruct schools
and school systems destroyed or neglected during the
war, the programme has since been extended to include
educational institutions of all kinds on its project list:
schools, of course, community centres and development
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
FIFTEEN MILLION
FRANCS OVERNIGHT
(Continued)
MORE THAN 400 UNESCO
CLUBS GO INTO ACTION
projects, technical institutes, libraries, co-operative
training groups, rehabilitation centres, women's and youth
organizations and many others. To-day, people of
14 countries in Europe and North America are talking part
in this person-to-person international aid by working
through their organizations to raise funds, buy the
UNEsco-issued Gift Coupons and then send them to the
project they select. Recipients use the coupons as a sort
of international "money order" to buy the needed
educational equipment from any supplier, who sends the
coupons to Unesco for redemption.
The organizers of the French campaign chose their
theme "Aid for the World's Blind" to commemorate
the 150th anniversary of the birth of Louis Braille,
inventor of the system of writing which bears his name,
and also to marik the 10th anniversary of the world
uniformisation of the Braille notation system under
Unesco's auspices.
Person-to-person aid goes
to Ghana and Indonesia
Although it is more- than a century since the Braille
alphabet was invented, most of the blind people
throughout the world still lead the same existence
as those in the Middle Ages. They are beggars, fortune¬
tellers, street-singers. The Braille alphabet has indeed
been adapted to nearly all languages, but in many
countries there is not a single library of works in Braille
and there are far too few specialized instructors. Africa
and Asia, which have the highest proportion of blind
persons, particularly lack teachers and equipment.
With these stark facts in mind, the French Unesco
Clubs set out to collect enough money to buy all the
Braille books and supplies, all the musical instruments,
all the physical training equipment and all the arts and
crafts materials listed as vitally needed items by the
institutions for the blind among Unesco's projects.
One of these is the school at Akropong in Ghana, which
started in 1946 when Church of Scotland missionaries
took three blind children into their care and began to
instruct them in Braille. Today, with some 50 sightless
pupils, the school has grown into a pioneering model cen¬
tre for blind training in Ghana, among whose 4 million
inhabitants there are some 50,000 blind persons.
The perfection and extension of instructional techni¬
ques in an Indonesian institution will also be assisted as
a result of the campaign. The Foundation for Rehabili¬
tation of the Blind in Semarang, the capital city of Cen¬
tral Java where the number of blind is estimated at more
than 100,000 persons, has established in its home and
school a comprehensive training programme.
Similar institutions in Ceylon, Iran and Tunisia com¬
plete the group of projects benefitting from the French
campaign, which from the outset was original in planning
and efficient in execution. The whole effort was designed
to generate widespread interest prior to the radio broad¬
cast in November.
First, the more than 400 Unesco clubs participating
organized action on the local level. Press articles on the
life and career of Louis Braille, on problems of the blind,
on the projects to be aided and other promotion literature
were appropriately distributed. A central point, usually
the town hall, for the collection of funds was selected.
Co-operation of local scout groups was arranged to man
these booths on the night of the broadcast.
Another innovation was the plan to offer a postcard-
record to the first 100,000 donors responding to the radio
appeal. This card featured an original design by artist
Jean Lurçat and a recording of a traditional Christmas
carol, arranged by organist Jean Langlais and sung by
the choir of the French Institute for the Blind. Since
then, 25,000 copies of this postcard-record have been
ordered by the German National Commission for Unesco
with the idea of starting a similar campaign in the Fed¬
eral Republic of Germany.
Pre-campaign publicity did not speak of fund-raising
or the exact nature of the programme to be carried out
on the night of November 24 during the popular broad¬
cast "Vous êtes formidables" over radio station "Europe
N° 1". On that night radio personalities launched the
appeal to millions of listeners, describing the projects,
giving background information on Unesco and its work,
and asking listeners to go to the central collection points
and donate to the cause.
The result truly was "formidable". Blind persons in
five countries will long toe grateful to the people of France
for this singular demonstration of good will.
MATERIALS FOR THE BLIND
GRANTED FREE ENTRY
Under its programme to promote the free flow of
information between countries, Unesco works for
the elimination of import duties and postal charges
on information materials needed by the blind.
Duty-free entry for books and other publications in
Braille is granted under the UNESCO-sponsored Agreement
on the Importation of Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Materials, now applied by 32 countries. These countries
also grant free entry to other educational, scientific or
cultural materials if consigned to approved institutions,
and provide import licences and foreign exchange for
all materials for the blind.
Acting on a proposal inspired by Unesco, the Universal
Postal Union decided in 1952 to allow publications for
the blind to be mailed abroad post-free. In an appeal
to Member States, Unesco asked governments to apply
this concession liberally and to exempt such publications
from internal postal charges as well. A number of
countries have since granted these concessions.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
, Photo © Pierre Baudin - Association Valentin Haiiy, Psris
THE ANATOMY LESSON is an important element in the training of a masseur. Here, at the training centre of the Valentin Haüy
Association in Paris, two blind students (on left) study the formation of the human skeleton while a blind instructor gives other
students a lesson in the technique of massage. Blind people have increasingly shown themselves to be adept at this work.
LET'S STOP PLAYING
BLIND MANS REBUFF
by Léon Bataille
ST"he blind?" "Useless members of the community."
"Unless a blind person has a streaik of genius, he
should steer clear of intellectual pursuits." These
two opinions were recorded during a recent inquiry in
France where a cross section of all classes and ages was
asked for its views on the place of the blind in society.
Such negative views were by no means isolated ones,
even in the country of Louis Braille and of Valentin Haiiy,
the great pioneer in the field of social rehabilitation for
the blind. The enquiry showed too that even people With
good educational backgrounds viewed blindness as an
affliction which condemns its victims to a life of apathy.
Most people seemed to think that work could never be
anything more than a pastime for the blind, a kind of con¬
solation or simply something to distract them from their
infirmity.
But there are others in the world who think differently.
Henry Ford, the American automobile magnate, renowned
for his practical common sense, wrote in his auto¬
biography:
"The subdivision of industry opens places that can be
filled by practically anyone. There are more places in
subdivision industry that can be filled by blind men than
there are blind men. And in each of these places the man
who shortsightedly might toe considered ah object of
charity can earn just as adequate a living as the keenest
and most able-bodied. Industry organized for service
removes the need for philanthropy."
What about the blind themselves? What do they think?
In their minds there are no doubts whatever. To them
work is something far more important than a means of
gaining a livelihood. It is no mere chance that Article 2
of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights "everyone
has the right to work, to free choice of employment"is
so often quoted by speakers at the international con¬
ferences of the blind.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
LETS STOP PLAYING
BLIND MAN'S REBUFF
(CONT'D)
As Pierre Henri, professor at the
National Institution for the Young
Blind, in Paris, has expressed it:
"The desire to be useful, to lose the
feeling of being a burden on others,
to earn their living 'like other people'
is, in the case of the blind, no mere
wish; it is an aspiration, an
obsession."
History may well be studded with
the names of blind men who achieved
fame through their talent or genius,
but the right of all blind men to
work is a comparatively new concep¬
tion.
Since 1945 most of the European
countries and those of North America
have taken steps to assist the social
and occupational rehabilitation of
their blind citizens though the
resources brought to this task are
widely divergent as also are the
methods used and results achieved.
Some countries consider they have
solved the problem by granting pen¬
sions to the blind. Others feel it is
enough to provide educational and
entertainment facilities. Most,
however, have tried to help the
blind to equip themselves for a gain¬
ful occupation, and to find jobs.
Higher productivity &
lower accident rates
For far too long the only possibility
open to the blind was to enter
some restricted, overcrowded
profession such as piano- tuning or
playing in an orchestra; more
recently they have been able to take
up massage. All that most of them
have been taught, however, are jobs
like making brushes or re-seating
cane chairs despite the fact that
there are more and more jobs in in¬
dustry and business which could be
adequately filled by blind people.
The experience of business and
industrial concerns in, among other
countries, France, Great Britain,
Canada, the Soviet Union, Denmark
and the United States, shows beyond
doubt that the blind are capable of
performing a wide variety of jobs,
including complicated ones, provided
production methods are suitably
adapted and simplified. They are
conscientious workers and their pro¬
ductivity is equal to or even higher
than that of equivalent sighted
workers, especially when they have
been given a thorough training.
Moreover, man for man, they have
fewer accidents at work since their
blindness makes them take special
care. Finally, employers have been
amazed by the psychological effects of
JUST LIKE ANY
OTHER FACTORY
At the Saurma factory in the Paris suburb of Suresnes there is
the hustle and bustle typical of any busy factory. Here men
are unloading raw materials from a truck; there a Woman fills
cartons with tins of floor polish while across from her a man packs
soap tablets into boxes. At bench and machine, men and women
work swiftly and deftly. Yet most of these Workers are blind and the
rest are deaf and dumb. There is only one unhandicapped person
the foreman.
In this factory which turns out soap and household cleaning pro¬
ducts, the skills and capabilities of blind and other handicapped
people are used to the full. The enterprise has four aims: to turn
people into qualified workers after only a few weeks' training; to
provide gainful employment for the physically handicapped; to earn
profits which can be used to help blind and other disabled persons;
to demonstrate convincingly ' to employers that they need have no
hesitation in taking blind workers on their, staffs.
This last goal is certainly the most important. One of the chief
obstacles with which blind people have to contend in their struggle
to make their way in Ufe is the reluctance of many firms to put them
to work.
Thus a factory like the Saurma a private undertaking and en¬
tirely self-supporting-^has many useful lessons to offer. AU its
workers were trained on the spot and their working conditions, salaries
and social benefits are, in general, equal or superior to those prevailing
for equivalent workers in other factories.
Not only is the factory run at a profit, but the individual produc¬
tivity of its workers is comparable to that of sighted ones. This was
shown when studies were made of such operations as the riveting of
openers on tins of floor polish, the moulding of bars of soap and the
folding, filling and sealing of their paper packaging.
The day when employers realize that blind people, once properly
trained, can efficiently carry out jobs in factory, workshop and office,
a great step will have been taiken towards the full integration of the
handicapped into society.
IEven ¡n the factory laboratory the work is carried out by blind people.
Here a workerfills a mixer with the ingredients for making soap. Certain
jobs, in the factorythe filling of tins with hot, liquid floor wax, for example
however, given to sighted persons (the deaf and dumb).
2 Filling up cans with liquid floor polish from a pump is a job which blind
people manage easily after a short period of training.
3 Another kind of work which the blind have no trouble in learning to
execute swiftly and efficiently is packaging. Here, a woman worker
folds cardboard into the form of a box and packs it with bars of soap.
4 For reasons of security all the machines used by the blind workers
are worked by individual hand or foot controls. Thus the operator
chooses the moment to work the machine, and at the same time is able
to maintain a steady rhythm of production.
28 CONT'D ON PAGE 3 0
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
PHOTOS © ALMASY, PARIS
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
LETS STOP PLAYING
BLIND MAN'S REBUFF
(From page 28)
taking blind persons on their staffs
and the spirit of solidarity that grows
up between those who can see and
those who cannot.
In Great Britain today there are
more blind people working in industry
than in special workshops or at home.
In the United States, which has
98,000 blind people between the ages
of 15 and 54, 20,000 are working in
industry amongst sighted people. Of
the 6,000 blind in Denmarik, 10% are
in paid employment, either full or
part-time. A thousand of the 3,500
blind people in Norway (out of a total
population of three and a half
million) are employable.
Of the nine and a half million blind
people in the world today over seven
million live in rural areas and the
majority of these in countries now
in the throes of economic develop¬
ment. Thus, though the ever increas¬
ingly widespread application in the
economically developed countries of
the right of the blind to work
represents a great step forward, this
does not mean that the problem in
the world as a whole is anywhere
near being solved.
Millions could train
for work on the land
The problems of giving effect to
this right are obviously not the
same in the industrialized coun¬
tries as in the agrarian ones. In the
latter Where three-quarters of the
world's blind people live, they must
be trained for agricultural work,
except where industrial development
provides some openings.
Today a vast effort is being made
in this direction in Africa, Asia and
Latin America, with the help both of
the United Nations and several of its
Specialized Agencies, and of non¬
governmental organizations such as
the World Council for the Welfare of
the Blind, the World Veterans Federa¬
tion and the British Commonwealth
Society for the Blind.
Special centres where the blind are
trained in agricultural work have
been set up with the help of inter¬
national specialists, and the ex¬
periences of the countries which
have done a great deal of social
and occupational rehabilitation are
being adapted and put to use in less
advanced regions.
Results naturally vary from one
country to another, but in general
there is no doubt that for blind
people the World over a new era has
opened since the end of the Second
World War.
TO EARN THEIR LIVING like everyone else is an ardent desire of the blind. For
long they were restricted to a few overcrowded professions, but growing experience
in business and industrial concerns of many countries has shown that the blind are capable
of doing a wide range of jobs provided production methods are suitably adapted and
simplified. Above, students learn to use a sewing machine at a special course organized
in Paris by the Association Valentin Haiiy, which takes it name from the great French
pioneer of the rehabilitation of the blind. The women turn out work for hospitals and
public institutions in the French capital. Below, in the printing shop run by the same
association. The worker on the left is preparing zinc plates for printing Braille books.
His left hand reads the Braille text and his right controls the stamping of the characters.
Photos © Pierre Baudin-Association Valentin Haüy, Paris
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
THE GULF IS
VANISHING
(Cont'd from page 17)
PROBING THE PSYCHOLOGY
& BEHAVIOUR OF THE BLIND
body or head, hand rubbing, passing spread fingers in
front of the eyes in cases where there is still some ability
to distinguish light). To the lack of spontaneous imita¬
tion can be attributed that facial inexpressiveness which
gives young blind people an appearance of precocious
maturity and is also responsible for the non-socialization
of gestures.
The psychological and psycho-social effects, though
unseen, are none the less real. They include a tendency
towards an intellectual and social egocentricity which
leads the blind person to develop an idea of the world
around him and of his relations with others purely in
terms of self. They also include an inclination towards
excessive verbalism (which is misleading as to actual
intellectual endowment), egocentric day-dreaming (which
makes up for a decrease in outside activities and opens
up a pleasant world which can be shaped at will) , motory
inertia and an integration with the limited circle of his
own kind.
'Voiceless' objects 'speak'
through his finger tips
The effects on character, which are simply the conse¬
quences of the above personality traits, are more
familiar to those closest to the blind person. They
may run from aggressivity to a habitual or systematic
withdrawel into a private world, depending on tempera¬
ment and circumstances, and they open the way to end¬
less disputes.
In reality the picture is not as blacik as would appear.
Here a deliberately pessimistic approach has been taken
in order to show the effect produced by a physical
handicap when it becomes the dominant element in the
development of personality. At the same time it reveals
clearly the scope of the efforts which are needed to offset
this disturbing influence. Generalizations should be
avoided, however, because of various factors that exert
their influence.
Firstly, in Occidental countries at least, congenital
blindness is rare and even those who become sightless
before the age of six or seven before they have had time
to acquire the attitudes of the normally sighted and to
absorb a sufficient number of visual images are a small
minority, probably making up less than 5% of the blind
people of a given country. And it should be kept in mind
that two-thirds of the known blind are over 60 years of
age. Thus most blind people have been able to see for
most of their lives and have amassed visual images' to
which they continue to cling.
Secondly there is the vital impulsion which subcon¬
sciously brings a person to refuse the idea of being
defeated: it pushes the child to explore, to conquer, to
master his world and to imitate the sighted people around
him. This attitude, above all others, opens the way to
freedom for the afflicted from their affliction, and can
lead them to the supreme victory of no longer being
conscious of it.
Thirdly, and directly related to this; the attitude of
those surrounding the blind person must be taken into
account. Studies have shown that the development of
the young blind person is above all conditioned by that
attitude, which is itself governed by the affectivity (or
even the neuropathic state) of the parents especially the
motherrather than, by their intellectual capabilities.
It should be clear that we can do more for those "in the
shadows" than merely bring them "intellectual light",
valuable as this may be. The education of such an
individual calls for more than the mere removal of
ignorance; it is primarily a question of "normalization",
of removing as far as possible the consequences of the
"abnormality".
On the physical level this involves repair, the reduction
of the ocular results of the malady. If they are to be
accepted in a climate which is free of pity and of anything
likely to induce an instinctive revulsion, then certain
things must be done without delay for the blind person.
Certain other physical handicaps are scarcely noticed in
the sighted person, but take on a major importance when
accompanied by blindness.
Closely related to the foregoing but with an additional
intellectual element is the problem of coping with space
and the world around. The man with normal vision does
not have to learn to move about, nor to use makeshifts
(awareness of obstacles, for instance), nor to interpret
such fleeting signs as small sounds, subtle smells and
vocal inflexions. There is no limit to the number of
"voiceless" objects which are therefore not apparent to
the sightless person: he must take the initiative and
make them "speak" to him through his finger-tips. A
whole course of specialized instruction is needed.
The world of people is no less difficult for the sightless
than the purely material world. Blindness is the subject
of numerous preconceived ideas which are distinctly to
the disadvantage of the victim. The sense of inferiority,
insecurity, frustrations or inner conflicts induce in the
blind "associai" or even "anti-social" reactions. Once
again, this calls for a course of emotional training and
character moulding which may not involve visible
instruction but which is none the less a permanent
preoccupation of those concerned with the education or
re-education of the sightless. Additionally, there is the
question of social conduct, imitation and non-verbal
conventions which the normally sighted person acquires,
preserves or adapts through spontaneous imitation but
which must be induced (or maintained) in the blind unless
they are to become "desocialized".
These questions enter little, if at all, into the
education of the normally sighted; but for those
whose sight is seriously impaired, they are of more
importance than grasping some subtle grammatical point
or reading the classics, or learning dates or extracting
square roots. Of course, the two things are not mutually
exclusive, but if a choice must be made there can be only
one answer:
Serious danger of creating
social & vocational misfits
Since We are concerned above all With a work of social
rehabilitation, it is as well to stress that this should
be based not so much on the subject's background as
on the surroundings in which he will eventually live. All
educational systems tend to involve a loss of social
standing precisely because they seek to "raise up". But
where individuals With a normal sensory equipment are
concerned, there are so many forms of employment
available to them that out-and-out failures are
comparatively rare. For the blind, openings are limited
and changes of occupation difficult. The school is some¬
times responsible for social inadaptability. In western
countries where mixing and levelling-out tend to
obliterate racial or social differences, this happens only
in the sphere of professional activity, as some blind
university graduates have found.
v The problem becomes of still greater significance when
methods of educating or re-educating the physically
handicapped, are passed on to economically under¬
developed countries.
There have been missions or other religious groups who,
not so long ago, took the blind, young and old alike, from
their villages in Asia and Africa; who gave them a
European education and then, unable to find employment
for them, sent them back home where they were literate
in an illiterate society, equipped to do Work unrelated to
local needs and customs and where sometimes even their
traditional religion was no longer acceptable to them.
Nothing could be better calculated to increase the
difficulties of the blind and extend the gulf which
separates them from society when that society is
unprepared to assimilate them.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WAGING WAR ON THE LOCUST
Sir,
The map accompanying the
article which you published on the
war against locusts (A Desert in the
Heart of London) did not include
Madagascar where an anti-locust unit
does in fact exist. Unfortunately,
because the species of Locusta Mi¬
gratoria Capito which it fights is
autochtonal, the unit receives no
outside aid although locust invasions
sometimes cover as much as two
thirds of the island an area as large
as the whole of France. Today the
anti-locust unit is equipped with
aircraft specially designed for
insecticide spraying operations, and
it was certainly the first to use this
form of attack just over ten years
ago, on lanuary . 17, 1950. The
decisive action of this service has on
many occasions kept famine at bay
in Madagascar.
L. Suniaki
Madagascar
FROM A MULTI-RACIAL CLUB
Sir,
Mauritius is a small Island in the
middle of the Indian Ocean, and
500 miles from Madagascar, the
nearest large land mass. It is very
densely populated ; about 400,000
persons of Indian, 160,000 of mixed
African, Indian and European,
20,000 of Chinese and about 10,000
of European, mainly French, descent.
By some curious social process it
happens that each of these groups
plays a pretty specialised part in our
society and economy; in other words
we are all dependent upon each
other's presence here.
A number of us to-day about 100
have founded a movement here to
maintain and extend our Mauritian
unity. We are mainly professionals,
and we include doctors, lawyers,
priests, engineers, civil servants
including senior British civil servants,
Cabinet Ministers, merchants and
planters ; Hindus, Roman Catholics
Buddhists, Anglicans and Mo¬
hammedans like myself ; and people
of French, Indian, Chinese, African,
English and Scottish origin whose
ancestors have lived on the Island
for decades or even centuries. We
are now flourishing enough and the
pressure to join us is great enough
for us to think of building a centre
at which we can enjoy the freedom
of talk, contact and informality
which is our object.
A British firm has very kindly and
disinterestedly presented us with
plans and advice to enable us to build
club premises, which will, we hope,
possess friendly atmosphere and
will provide "neutral" ground on
which members of all communities
may meet without reserve. Un¬
fortunately the cost of building,
about £15,000. is far beyond our
means and I hope that any of your
readers who share our determina¬
tion to take positive action to
ensure that men and women of
goodwill shall not be kept apart by
social and racial barriers will help
us to assemble some part of this
amount.
If so, and if they will write to
me in Mauritius or to Mr. G. J. M.
Schilling of Blyth, Greene lour-
dain and Co. Ltd., Plantation
House, Fenchurch Street, London
E.C.3, we shall be very happy to
acknowledge contributions or to
give further information. When
the club premises are complete we
shall keep on record in a prominent
place the names and nationalities of
those who helped us to preserve
this tiny ocean island from the
darkness of racialism.
Abdul Cader Rahman
Chairman, Stella Clavisque Club
Mauritius
MEASURING HIDDEN ICE
Sir,
I found the articles on the ocean
depths and on icebergs, by David
Gunston in the December number of
The Unesco Courier very interest¬
ing. May I, however, point out that
the proportion . of submerged to
protruding part of antarctic icebergs
was known for some time as seismic
determinations of the thickness of
ice shelves from which the tubular
icebergs are detached had 'been re¬
peatedly made.
F. Loewe
Dept of Meteorology
University of Melbourne
Australia
Ed note : David Gunston writes.
"Yes, but the Russian experiment
I described was the first successful
attempt to test these theories by
actually measuring an iceberg in
situ."
TRIBUTE DUE TO KARELCAPEK
Sir,
I have just finished reading the
issue of The Unesco Courier
devoted to Chekhov. I think it is
excellent and I want to commend
you for it.
May I suggest that a similar issue
might well be devoted in the future
to Karel Capek, a great Czech
author whose writings have an all
human focus. It would be a tribute
to a man who has not been given
his due.
Michael J. Flack
Pittsburgh, U.S.A.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1960
SEARCHLIGHT FOR
SIGHTLESS CHILDREN
Despite blindness and near-total deafness, elderly Helen
Day of New York has for most of her life been editor of "The
Searchlight" a Braille magazine for blind children issued by
The Lighthouse, the New York Association for the Blind.
"The Searchlight", now in its fiftieth year, was founded as
Vecchio from Three Lions, New-York
a 12-page quarterly. Today it averages about 80 pages and
is sent free to children ten times a year from September through
June. Stories are selected by Miss Day with the help of
girl scouts who read material from other magazines to her (2).
She selects those she wants and mails them to The Light¬
house. Here, they are put on a dictaphone record. A Braille
secretary, who is blind, transcribes the articles on to a Braille
printing plate (3). The Braille plate is placed on the press (1)
and the magazine is run off, each page being printed indivi¬
dually.. Miss Day, who has edited The "Searchlight" ever
since she left college, does her own housekeeping, shopping
and cooking. She has a constant companion in her dog,
Celia, who she is seen taking for a walk (4). Celia is now
well-known through Miss Day's column in "The Searchlight".
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Ne
¡Storing up sunshine: a new
system of individual or central heating has
just 'been developed by French scientists at
Mont-Louis in the Pyrenees where, since
1952, a solar furnace has been operated on
an industrial basis for the manufacture of
refractory products. To extend the use of
solar furnaces to heating buildings meant
finding a way to store the calories produced
by the sun in the summer for use during
cold weather. The Mont-Louis scientists
have now developed a method of storing
solar energy in a sort of battery. Mass
production of heating apparatus, they say,
is already possible at a reasonable cost.
AFRICAN STATES REQUEST
UNESCO ASSOCIATE MEMBERSHIP:
Unesco has received requests for
admission as Associate Members of
the Organization from the Governments
of eight states of the French Commu¬
nity: the Mali Federation, the Republics
of Madagascar, Gabon, Chad, Ivory-
Coast, Niger, Dahomey and of Central
Africa. The requests will be considered
by Unesco's General Conference when
it meets in November.
JBlOLOGY COURSE ON FILM:
A full year's high school biology course
consisting of 120 colour motion pictures
will be available to secondary schools in
the U.S.A. later this year. Prepared by
the American Institute of Biological
Sciences, the films are basically of the lec¬
ture-demonstration type. Their sequences
include material on living plant and animal
life in forest, marine, mountain, desert and
prairie environments, not normally available
in the classroom. The series has been
designed to be so flexible that schools of
all kinds can make use of it, in part or
in full.
NIGERIA'S EDUCATION DRIVE:
In Nigeria there are more schools and
more children going to school in
relation to the total population than in
any other country in Africa. Latest
statistics published {covering 1958)
show that in Lagos, the federal capital,
more than 84 per cent of the children
attend school; figures for the Eastern
and Western provinces are respectively
81 and 73 per cent. Compared with the
previous year secondary schools have
increased from 477 to 514. Higher
education shows an impressive trend.
Ten years ago future doctors, lawyers,
engineers and administrators studied in
British universities. Today the Fede¬
ration has its own up-to-date University
College in Ibadan and an engineering
college at Zaria.
J\ BOOKMOBILE FOR CALLAO:
Eighteen months ago, a mobile library
provided by Unesco arrived in the Peru¬
vian port of Callao. Within 12 months the
loans registered by the bookmobile were
more than twice those of the Municipal
THE UNESCO
PHILATELIC SERVICE
aw;
^??2.8i7 f\ f \ M 1 »
«fl2^7l77fgJ¡HI0íL'7iy
This stamp (denomination 40 hwans)
has been issued by the Republic of
Korea in honour of the U.N. World
Health Organization. It can be
obtained from The Unesco Phila-.
telic Service which has stamps and
first day covers issued by many
Member States to commemorate
important events in the history of
Unesco and the U.N. (inauguration
of Unesco's New Headquarters,
Human Rights Day, World Refugee
Year). As the agent in France of
the U.N. Postal Administration,
Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks
all the United Nations stamps
currently on sale. Information on
items available, their price and the
methods of payment, will be sent
on request by Unesco's Philatelic
Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
Library itself25,888 compared to 11,729.
Reading tastes sometimes provided sur¬
prises: in one group of houses of a poor
community above the River Rimac, the
authors most in demand were found to be
Gandhi, Goethe, Lin Yutang, Cervantes,
Shakespeare and the Abbé Pierre. The
bookmobile of Callao has proved its value
	 Next Month	
DOUBLE JULY-AUGUST NUMBER
EXPLORATION OF THE SEA
Two issues in one - 68 pages
JEAN ROSTAND
RECEIVES
KALINGA PRIZE
JEAN ROSTAND, French scientist,
science writer and philosopher,
was awarded the 1959 Kalinga
Prize for the popularization of
science during a ceremony' held
recently at UNESCO House in Paris.
Mr. Rostand was the eighth
winner of the £1,000 award, a
personal donation of Mr. B. Patnaik,
an Indian industrialist, which is of¬
fered annually by the Kalinga
Foundation in the Indian State of
Orissa as recognition to a leading
interpreter of science and also to
strengthen ties between India and
the world's scientists. The winner is
chosen by an international jury ap¬
pointed by UNESCO.
The seven previous winners of the
prize have been Louis de Broglie
(France), Julian Huxley (United
Kingdom), Waldemar Kaempffert
(United States), Augusto Pi-Suner
(Yenezuélo), George Gamow (United
States), Bertrand Russell (United
Kingdom) and Karl ron Frisch
(Germany and Austria).
The award of the Kalinga Prize
to Mr. Rostand at the age of 66 is
another laurel in a long career
which has already seen his election
to the Académie Française. It would
not be quite true to call Mr. Rostand
a science writer: he is both a scien¬
tist and a writer. He is known
throughout the world for his re¬
search on heredity and genetics,
based upon three decades of experi¬
mentation with frogs and toads. At
the same time, he has written forty-
odd books on his fields of research
as well as on scientific thought,
philosophy and pure science.
in bringing works which open new horizons ¡3
of knowledge and afford a broader view z
of the world around them to people who gc
might otherwise never have visited a library. 2
ORIENT-OCCIDENT' FELLOWS:
Twenty-four study grants are being
offered by the Government of Czecho¬
slovakia to enable Asian and African
specialists and educators to study Czech
culture, literature and music and the
country's education system. The grants
are a contribution to UNESCO's Major
Project for mutual appreciation of
cultural values of the Orient and
Occident. Among studies open to the
fellows will be research on Comenius,
marionette techniques, Slav languages
and applied arts. .
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Where to obtain
Unesco
publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria. (A. 13/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, CCP. 338.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
1 6, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP. 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151,
Antwerp.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pee Zayas
505-7 Apartado I 13, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.- (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris, 7». CCP. 12598-48
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6).
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ I Asaf AM Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Rajkamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco. Avenue du Musée. Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 9 I
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.( 1 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
3 3, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, 135, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 1 00 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174. Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass, 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374, 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de Correos 2018,
Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46.
Warsaw. 10 (Zl. 50.)
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. ( 1 0/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 7).
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi. Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church'
Streec, Pretoria ( I 0/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).-
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office. P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.(I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($ 3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York. 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjlga,
Terazije 27/11. Belgrade.
The International Social Science Journal
is published quarterly. Its contributors are
specialists of renown, from all countries, who
are asked to prepare a series of articles on the
subject of scientific interest chosen for each
issue. In the treatment of these subjects, an
attempt is made to bring out the interdisci¬
plinary and international character of social
problems and the social aspect of present day
life. Occasionally an issue contains studies
involving only one discipline, dealing usually
with problems of particularly great interna¬
tional interest.
A separate section of each issue is devoted
to the subject on which the contributions are
centred. Another section deals with the
organization of work in the social science
field and provides information on current
research, news or accounts of various research
institutes and teaching centres, and abstracts
of publications and documents relating to the
social sciences issued by international orga¬
nizations. A summary account is also given
of the results of the main conferences or
meetings at which social science problems are
discussed. The multi-disciplinary approach
of the International Social Science Journal,
is one that can do much to satisfy the growing
interest of all groups of society in the social
sciences.
Last issue: Citizen participation in political
life, a study of political behaviour in England,
Finland, France, Israel, Norway and the
United States.
In preparation: The sociology of leisure.
Yearly subscription . $6.50 32/6 (stg.) 20 NF
Single issue 	 $2.00 10/- (stg.) 6 NF
A free specimen copy will be sent upon
request.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
sßC!
' « -A t
-O
BLIND BALLERINAS
At recreation time the co-educational school on Novo Alexyevskaya
street in Moscow echoes to the shouts and laughter of youngsters
playing or racing up and down stairways and corridors. The school
is little different from thousands of othersexcept that all the chil¬
dren are blind. Photos shows a gay troupe of young girls enjoy¬
ing à lesson in the school's dancing class. See story page 20.
CP. Voss, Moscow
^<
I-
-
< ; .>
-<* í i
,
!
?
.
J
«,
.
\
\
'\
\
H#
]]>
</page>
</document>
