<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064692eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
I
JP" --.'Sí
»*
|J ü LY-AUGUST
1960
(I3th year)
Price : 2/-stg. (U.K.)
60 cents (U. S.)
1.40 NF. (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TIGER OF THE SEA. In the fish market
at Singapore, a worker cuts up the
carcase of a giant shark so as to extract
the liver, whose oil is one of the most
important sources of Vitamin A. More
than 150 species of shark exist, the
most ferocious being the great white
shark found in the tropical oceans.
* © Pierre Pittet, Geneva
'«£
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JULY-AUGUST 1960
1 3 T H YEAR
Contents
No. 7-8
COVER PHOTO
Like some space ship land¬
ing on an unknown world, the
French Navy bathyscaph
F.N.R.S.3 explores the
depths near the ocean bot¬
tom. As it neared the bottom
of the Toulon Canyon In
southern France, It was nearly
engulfed by a subsea ava¬
lanche. Underwater research
vessels often pass through
zones of dense marine life
of tiny organisms
that look like the Milky Way
and thick schools of shrimp
like those pictured drifting
past the bathyscaph here.
Rolf Kiep © National
Geographic Society, U.S.A.
18
23
28
37
38
40
49
54
56
63
TURN TO THE SEA
By Athelstan Spilhaus
A UNESCO SHIP TO SAIL THE SEAS
By Augusto Pérez-Vitoria
EXPEDITION TO THE INDIAN OCEAN
EXPLORING THE WORLD'S DEEPEST TRENCHES
By Anton F. Bruun
IN THE REALM OF THE TRIPOD FISH
By Pierre de Latil
FROM AQUALUNG TO BATHYSCAPH
By Jacques-Yves Cousteau
BALLET OF THE OPHURIANS
DANGER 1 500 MPH TIDAL WAVE APPROACHING
By Bernard Saint-Guily
THE WAVE MYSTERY OF D-DAY 1944
By Ritchie Calder
FROM TROPICAL WATERS TO ISLANDS OF ICE
By L Zenkevitch and A. Laktionov
THE OLD (AND NEW) MEN OF THE SEA
By Henri Rotschi
THE WEATHER AND THE SEAS
By Peter B. Collins
WANTED: BETTER OCEAN-GOING RESEARCH SHIPS
By H.F.P. Herdman
NEPTUNE'S LITTLE JEWELS
FISH: THE GREAT FOOD POTENTIAL
By Donovan Bartley Finn
ATOMS OVERBOARD t
By George W.C. Tait
NOTE TO SUBSCRIBERS IN U.S.A.: The July/August number is a true double
Issue, but In accordance with U.S. postal regulations, arrangements are being made to
extend by one issue all subscriptions due to expire with the May 1961 Issue or earlier.
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7; France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventls
Spanish Edition : Jorge'Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavarlanl
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the EdItor-ln-Chlef;
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. SeTond-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 60. 1. 1 49 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of Issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.); 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7:
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TEXAS TOWERS. Stimulated by the search for oil
under the continental shelves, men have already built
artificial islands in the seaTexas towers, first used off
the coast of this U.S. State and taking their stance on
the continental: shelf. Islands of this kind may be built on
many of the shoals in the oceans or rise up from the top
of sea mounts close to the surface. Anchoring a ship in
thousands of fathoms of water is also now practical through
the use of light, self-buoyant anchor cables of nylon.
U.S. Hydrographie Office
m-w
Wf9Kf$'y
nil« "I jpt»
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
TURN TO THE SEA
by Athelstan Spilhaus
I o understand our earth, sun, the
wÊÊÊÊÊÊ^^ other planets of our solar system
and the space through which they move, we must treat
them as a whole. The birth of the earth was part oj the
origin of our galaxy. To follow the evolution of the earth
and pf life upon it one has, to consider everything, from its
hot molten centre, out through the mantle of plastic-like
material, to the crust we live on, the oceans thai surround
us, the air we breathe, and even the space beyond.
Through this space comes the sunshine which provides the
energy of all our fuels (except the nuclear ones) and of
the food, the fuel for all life, both plant and animal.
Through space, rays of tremendous energy and cosmic
origin arrive, which, by bombarding earthly substances,
cause radio-active isotopes which are the clocks and
calendars for telling the birthdays of events on earth.
We live on land and know more about that part of the
earth's surface than anything else. Because the age of
our earth is a sizeable fraction of the age of the galaxy on
whose fringe we ride, the study of the history of our planet
is a laboratory study of the history of the universe. But
three-quarters of our laboratory is under water!
This inner space on our planet which is in many respects
more important to us, more unknown, and at least as
interesting as outer space, is inundated by ocean waters
which cover much of the record of history beneath them.
They hide the shape of the sea floor; they make it difficult
to go down and drill into that floor; and they cover fossil
sediments, the layers of which are the pages of earth
history. This huge volume of water, the world ocean, we
can neither see through without instruments nor explore
without special vessels to carry us. The most pressing
problem on earth is to feed the multiplying population, and
to meet this ever-present challenge we must study the sea.
Let us, in our effort to understand earth, sun and space,
turn to the sea.
Athelstan Spilhaus is a trustee of the Woods Hole Océano¬
graphie Institution, Dean of the Institute of Technology, Uni¬
versity of Minnesota and a member of the Committee on
Oceanography of the National Academy of Sciences-National
Research Council of the United States. He was a member of
the Unesco Executive Board from 1954 to 1958.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
TURN TO THE SEA (Continued)
OUR PLANET EARTH
IS MISNAMED
The terrestrial globe has a total surface area of S 1 0 million square kilometres.
Of this, the sea accounts for 3 6 I million square kilometres or 70.8 per cent,
leaving the land areas the modest share of 29.2 per cent. Therefore the
planet we call Earth should really be called Ocean. The total volume of
water in the sea occupying 70,8 percent of the planet's surface Is 1,370 mil¬
lion cubic kilometres, representing an over-all average depth of 3,800 metres,
as against an average land altitude of 840 metres above sea level. Contrary
, to what was believed for centuries, the ocean bed is not flat: indeed, the
depth over 76 per cent of the area varies between 3,000 and 6,000 metres.
The sea has been found to contain, in solution, practically all the known
natural elements of Mendeleieff's classification; it is our planet's greatest
depository of minerals of every description. All forms of life started in the
sea and today its animal population comprises some 300,000 species
whose habitats range from the coastal shallows to the deepest cavities of
the Pacific, and from sunlit waters to depths to which daylight never pene¬
trates. Some species are vegetarian, others carnivorous; some sluggish,
others active; some static, others mobile. Furthermore the existence of
the sea means 250,000 kilometres of coastline: a whole world of earth
and stone endlessly remoulded by the wavesto man's profit when silting
provides new room for human enterprise, or to his loss when erosion attacks
his blockwork, harbour installations or other artificial sea defences.
Presenting a continuous fluid mass from the Poles to the Equator, its thermal
inertia has something analogous to a "flywheel effect" on extremes of tempe¬
rature in tropical and polar regions alike, constantly modifying climates by
partially transferring to colder regions the heat absorbed in low latitudes.
Moreover, while the great continental rivers discharge into the sea 13 million
cubic kilometres of water every hour, the sea as steadily returns it to the
atmosphere in an endless cycle in which the vapour drawn up from the sea
by the sun forms clouds which travel as the winds direct, discharging on the
most distant lands the rain or snow which mean life to them. The sea,
then. Is the world's bank of minerals, organic substances, and thermal and
dynamic energy derived from the sun; It regufates our climate, provides
fresh water, and is the generator of all life, terrestrial and aquatic alike.
© Niton Design Studio Washington
o LABORATORY OF
THE UNIVERSE
H NCE upon a time, four and a half
billion years ago, the earth new
born, was hot, round, and pockmarked all over by the
turmoil within and without. There were no well-defined
continental rises and no marked depressions in its surface.
There was no water, no atmosphere as we know it, and of
course no life. How did the distribution of continental
elevations and oceanic depressions come about? How did
the water fill the ocean basins? Were they filled slowly?
Or was the mantle of water always about what it is today?
How did the atmosphere's present composition come
about? And how did life begin in the oceans? How did
the chain of evolution begin and develop to the wealth of
plant and animal life that we know on our planet today?
These are the primary questions of the natural history
of our earth in which the oceans play a leading role. Eons
ago they were the birthplace of life itself. Even today,
they supply the moisture in our atmosphere, provide us
with life-giving rain, temper our climate, and have an
unknown potential, almost untapped, of food and minerals
needed by man. As population on earth increases, the
resources of the continents that poke out from beneath the
sea become strained to meet humanity's needs, and to
support our life that began in the sea we have once again
to turn to the sea.
Science, contrary to popular belief, gives no final
answers. For each question answered by scientists half a
dozen others are raised; thus, the known unknowns about
our planet, our origin, and our universe multiply more
quickly even than people! This is a fortunate thing;
otherwise the material on which to feed man's curiosity
would dwindle. And so man with his theories supposes
solutions but nature continually proposes new problems.
When the earth first began to form not long after the
origin of the universe, it was not as compact as it is today,
but gradually it shrunk to its present size and degree of
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
solidity. In fact, the diffuse protoplanet from which it
formed may have had a hundred times the mass of material,
consisting mostly of light gases which, because of their
violent motion, escaped to space. Only after this did our
geologic record begin and we date the age of the earth
from that time. The age of the universe is estimated by
observing the. rate at which stars far, far away recede from
each other. In receding, their light shifts to the longer
wave length, red, just as the whistle of a departing train
lowers in pitch as it speeds away. From this rate of
spreading of the stars we can calculate how long ago they
were all close together.
The Martian observer from his distance would not
detect details of our coast lines. He would probably be
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
struck by the curious assymmetry of the planet, where
water appears as the mirror image of land. Four
continents he would discern the dominant pattern of
three petal-like land areas stretching down from the
northern hemisphere the Americas, Europe-Africa, and
Asia-Australasia the tips pointing toward but not
reaching the fourth continent, Antarctica. Diametrically
opposite, across the globe from each of the continents, he
would see a corresponding ocean the Arctic Ocean
opposite the Antarctic continent, the Pacific Ocean
opposite Europe-Africa, the Indian opposite the Americas,
and the Atlantic opposite Asia-Australasia. These
oceans, too, he would see as petal-shaped, starting in the
southern hemisphere and reaching upward with their
points toward the Arctic Ocean.
Fl
^11 ow the earth's crust developed con-
B^B"^ tinents and ocean basins is explain¬
ed by some as due to the slow convection that is, rising
of hot material and sinking of colder in doughnut-like
cells of the semi-plastic material beneath. The continents
were formed where two doughnuts touched and the out¬
flows toward each of their edges converged. The oceans
similarly formed at the centre of the doughnuts where the
flow outward toward the edges of the ring diverges, leaving
a hollow.
This would mean that during geologic time the continents
have grown and the ocean basins have deepened. We
find by measuring the decay of radioactive substances into
stable ones, the same method that gives us the estimate of
the four and a half bilhon year age of the earth, that the
oldest rocks are generally found toward the centre of the
continents, thus supporting the idea of slow growth
around the edges, ¡and the ocean basins are '"younger" or
newer material brought up from the earth's insides.
Four continents and four great oceans four regions
where our doughnuts of hot plastic material converge and
leave the surface slag of continents and four doughnut
centres where tthe spreading flow hollows oceanic
depressions. This simple hypothesis might be the
All land engulfed in 100 million years
beginning of an explanation of the interesting pattern of
oppositeness that we have in our land and sea distribution.
One of the unsolved questions is whether the ocean
waters and the atmosphere were formed before the be¬
ginning of geologic record or whether they grew slowly
throughout time squeezed out from our planet. In favour
of the slow growth of the oceans is the fact that the rate
of flow of water from volcanic springs at the present time
is more than sufficient to have filled the oceans through
geologic time. And in a large area of the Pacific Ocean
there are coral atolls and sea mounts with their flat tops far
below present sea level.
This could have come about only by a deepening of the
ocean bottom from which they rise due the continuing inter¬
nal convection or to the increase in the amount of water in
the ocean basins, or most probably both of these. Some of
this deepening seems to have taken place only in the last
hundred million years and would indicate that perhaps a
fourth of all ocean water has been squeezed to the surface
of the earth by the turmoil within it in the last fortieth of
its age. If the internal activity Which causes this increase
of water continues, we may have a completely water-
covered planet after the next hundred million years.
Slumbering centuries in the ocean chasms
o explain life in the sea we must
understand its origin, its evolution,
and the total relationship in the cycle of sunshine and
nutrients to plants, to grazing animals, to predators, and
back to nutrients through the action of bacteria. We must
understand also the linking of life in the sea to birds and
land animals, including the greatest predator, man.
Life began in the oceans and has continued there far
longer than it has existed in air or on land. Every major
large family of life on earth has its most primitive members
in the ocean and finds its earliest forebears there. But
because the ocean performs for life the same function it
performs for our climate, namely a steadying flywheel
effect with no marked or rapid changes, the challenge for
development of new species is not as great as on land, so
that rates of evolution in the ocean have not been as rapid.
In spite of the much longer time life has existed in sea
water and the fact that there is more ocean than land, only
twenty per cent of all the species alive today are in the
ocean. The rate of evolution is in fact faster on land,
adapting species to the more widely varying and rigorous
conditions there.
In places that are alternately wet and dry, such as
shorelines where the oceans and land meet, and the tides
rhythmically submerge the beach and expose it to searing
heat or bitter cold, the challenge to survival has produced
the greatest concentration of different kinds of life. We
should expect that the rate of evolution is slower the
deeper one goes in the ocean because uniform conditions
do not promote selection and because of the lower tempera¬
tures which cause all chemical reactions to go more slowly.
Of course, the ocean shields its life from cosmic rays
which can produce mutations, but it seems likely that
cosmic radiation is unimportant compared to the natural
mutation rate provided by the thermal agitation of matter.
So we find living fossils, forms of life that have not
changed for millions of /ears, such as coelacanths, perhaps
the hnk between fish and the vertebrates on land. As we
find better ways to observe and collect in the ocean, we
will find many more forms unchanged through ages
lower branches of the tree of evolution.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
TURN TO THE SEA (Continued)
' ' .:.'::' :-: r'. ' ', ': ' ':^ " ' ' ! :"
0 EYES TO PIERCE THE NIGHT
Felton Design Studio
STATIONS IN THE SEA like those shown here will enable men to live in, observe and explore
the ocean depths. From the tallcigar-shaped buoy (on left) they will be able to record physical and
biological interplay. Horizontal tubular construction on right will provide a permanent observation
post. There will be submarine "tractors" with mechanical arms and suction tubes for collecting
plants, animals and geological specimens. Above the tractor is a jet-propelled bathyscaph.
he oceans have been represent¬
ed as a fearsome thing. The
earliest maps always showed the land then known girdled
by a ring of impenetrable seas. But understanding
dispels fear, and if we chart them properly, the oceans can
help to bring world friendship as highways of international
commerce and exchange.
This means that we must have maps showing the
contours of hills and valleys, ridges and trenches, and the
nature of the bottom whether it is a good mirror for
sound waves or a poor one. The mid-Atlantic ridge
beneath the sea, probably the greatest mountain range on
earth, may look entirely different from continental
mountains because it has never been subjected to such
severe processes of erosion. As Maury charted surface
currents and winds, modern Maurys will chart the speed
and direction of currents at all depths in the oceans.
Only recently great subsurface rivers, equivalent to a
thousand Mississippis, have been found underneath the
huge surface currents, such as the Gulf Stream and its
counterparts in other oceans. As we get differences of
gravity on land due to the presence of mountains, valleys
and plains and the different material in them, so gravity
varies in the ocean and charts of its variation and of the
variations in the earth's magnetic field will be a further
aid to navigators.
Airplanes flying over land now seldom use the earlier
navigational methods. In ordinary flying the country is
criss-crossed by radio beams tracks along which the
airplane runs unerringly to its destination. On land we
have networks of radars which plot the positions of all
aircraft to prevent collisions. It cannot be too long before
we will have the counterpart of these criss-crossed networks
in the sea submarine beacons radiating sound beams for
the guidance of underwater craft as the lighthouse uses a
light beam to guide ships on the surface. Sound receivers
must be coupled together in a vast underwater spider web
of millions of miles of cables which, like radar in the air
space, can keep track continuously of normal comings and
goings, yet single out any stranger.
We must with our instruments and vehicles be able to
see through the ocean to understand it. And best of all
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
is to go down into it and use our senses directly! Scientific
instruments extend the range of our senses, and vehicles
extend the reach of our arms and legs. By instruments
alone we know something of the distant space above us
where we have never been. Similarly we know a little
about the deep ocean where we have never been by the
probings of instruments on long wires. Instruments can
detect the whole of the electro-magnetic spectrum from
the longest radio waves to the shortest gamma and X-rays
but including the narrow range encompassed by our eyes.
They can hear above or below the pitch to which our ears
are tuned, measure pressures too small to feel or too great,
for us to withstand, and analyze substances far more
accurately than we can do by natural taste and smell.
The eyes are of little use where there is little to see, as
in space. So that man, in space, is only a repairman of
the sensing instruments transmitting information to earth,
or an experimental animal, or a space-craft chauffeur until
he can land on an extraterrestrial body. But ultimately all
recorded bits of information are put into the scientist's
brain through his eyes. In unexplored regions where
there is so much to see that is hitherto unknown there is
great advantage in having la watcher on the spot so that
the information goes directly into his brain and the
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
exploration plan can be developed as it unfolds. The
ocean is such a region.
It is only in the last few years that we have begun to go
down into the ocean to see things for ourselves. Up to
that time our knowledge came from the chance gathering
of nets operated from surface vessels like a blind man
making a butterfly collection. Because vehicles to take us
deep down in the sea were not available, we have
concentrated on developing instruments for measuring its
characteristics from the surface. Now bathyscaphs, deep-
diving manned ocean balloons, have gone down nearly
seven miles, and skin diving enables almost anyone to see
the profusion of life in the shallow edges of the sea. In
the next few years we will see a corresponding develop¬
ment of new vehicles to let us take the plunge with our
new instruments.
We will have different kinds of bathyscaphs some that
can operate at 12,000 feet can investigate one-third of
the ocean which is shallower than that; others that can go
down half again as deep can cover ninety-five per cent
of the area of the ocean's bottom; and finally, the stronger
bathyscaphs like the bathyscaph manned by Piccard and
Walsh that made the record dive and that can withstand
Photo Conrad Limbaugh, University of California, Scripps Institution of Oceanography
SANDFALLS on the ocean bed are the counterparts of waterfalls on land. One shown here,
about 30 feet high, is in the Cape San Lucas submarine canyon, Baja California. Currents
feed the sand from nearby beaches into the canyon. Photograph was taken during, an
expedition made by the University of California's Scripps Institution of Oceanography.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
TURN TO THE SEA (Continued)
the pressures of the deepest ocean trench, seven tons per
square inch, over seven miles down, will cover the
remaining five per cent.
These deep diving, manned vehicles, which we will soon
have, will be like a lobster, able to go up and down, move
horizontally in the water in any depth and crawl along the
bottom. They will have mechanical arms like claws
remotely controlled by the man in the pressure-tight shell.
His eyes will be extended by a television circuit where the
pickup will be on the end of the controllable hand. More
flexible than our own eyes, it will be able to turn in any
direction and present what it sees on a screen to the man
inside. If it sees a rock of interest, the claw-like hands
can take an underwater geologist's hammer and collect
the specimen. If it sees a fish, they can collect it with a
net. If it sees ripples and sediments, it can photograph
and measure them. Directed by the knowledge and expe¬
rience of the investigator inside the cabin, it can multiply
many times over the amount of information that could be
secured by instruments alone. __
Furthermore, when we descend to these depths we have
to protect ourselves from the tremendous external
pressures by a strong water-tight cabin which maintains our
normal air pressure of fifteen pounds per square inch
inside. Animals that have adapted themselves to the
darkness of the depths and the pressure of seven miles of
sea water on top of them die when caught by chance in
trawls operated from the surface because now, when they
are brought to the surface, the change in pressure kills
them. But with the bathyscaph they will be collected and
placed in a strong container which will keep them at their
accustomed pressure, temperature and darkness while they
are brought to the surface alive to be studied in oceanaria
specially designed to reproduce the physical conditions
under which they live and in which they may reproduce
themselves.
These small deep water bathyscaphs will be launched
from and return to a mother ship. The mother ship
will be a surface vessel at first but later we may see large,
very-deep-water submarines acting as bases for the small,
inquisitive, manned bathyscaphs which would scatter from
her to collect the data to report and return to her from
time to time. These new means of gathering data will
lead to world-wide maps of the ocean's plant, animal, and
total biological fife. We do not have these yet, and neither
have our aquaria grown to the size where, under controlled
conditions that we can observe, we can study the interac¬
tions of total communities of ocean life.
But we will have huge marine biotrons or oceanariums
where we can learn why organisms and fish perform
migrations, vertical and horizontal, whether they navigate
celestially as the birds perhaps do, how creatures in the
darkest recesses seven miles down generate their own lights
within their bodies, and how they withstand the tremendous
pressures. We are just beginning to have the tools and
materials to build these immense facilities, and Whether
we will take large samples of the ocean and place them
in plastic tanks on land, where we can control temperature,
pressure, nutrients, and other conditions, or whether we
will build plastic houses at the bottom of the sea so that
we can observe the denizens at home, I do not know.
I expect we will probably do both.
Photo O.F.R.S. © Les Requins Associés, Paris
FILM PRODUCERS gather in an underwater "studio"a rocky, seaweed covered grotto100
feet down under the sea near Marseilles. Modern Improvements in construction of waterproof
filming and lighting equipment and, above all, the development of the aqualung diving apparatus
have made possible some remarkable accomplishments in underwater filming in recent years.
I0
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
0n studying our planet we have to
I know the geographical distribution
of its physical and biological make-up. But we also need
to know how things change at one and ithe same place
with time. On land we watch the response of animals
and trees to the changing of seasons in one locality. We
can relate animal behaviour and plant response to the
varying conditions of the weather recorded by instru¬
ments against time at one place. But in the ocean, so
far, no one has anchored a ship and made a series of
measurements, except in rare instances, for more than a
few days. Yet measurements of the time variations of
temperature, salinity, currents, light, correlated with
biological observations of the variations of plankton and
fish populations at a fixed position over a long period,
would be extremely revealing.
Stimulated by the search for oil under the continental
shelves, we already have built artificial islands, Texas
towers, marching into the sea and taking their stance on
the continental shelves. These can be the first stations
in the sea, and artificial islands of this kind may be built
on many of the shoals in the oceans or rise. from the top
of sea mounts that reach up nearly to the surface. In
very deep water the next step would be to anchor an
ordinary surface ship for a period of a year. Anchoring
in thousands of fathoms of water is now practical because
we can use self-buoyant anchor cables.
Formerly the main problem of anchoring in deep water
was not that the forces of wave and swell on the ship
Les Requins Associés, Paris.
broke the cable but that the very weight of the long cable
itself caused it to part. Now with nylon or other plastic
materials having the same density as sea water the cable is
weightless, and anchoring even in the deepest parts of the
sea is possible.
Next to come, and better than a ship, will be vertical
floating tubes, hundreds of feet long, cigarlike in shape,
heavy on the bottom and projecting a few feet into the
air at the top. These will be moored in one place. The
men in this tall tubular buoy floating in the sea will be able
to live, watch, and record the physical and biological
interplay never before observed. Initially we may use
submarine hulls standing on end for these buoys, and in
the not-too-distant future permanent stations of this kind
will be scattered all over the oceans. Not only will they
be useful for understanding the sea but they will be mid-
ocean lighthouses and emergency shelters for ocean trav¬
ellers and fishermen.
As well as these anchored buoys, there will be
manned, drifting buoys travelling slowly with the currents,
and for each manned buoy, drifting or moored, there will
be numerous unmanned ones at surface, mid-depths
and bottom, sending what their instruments measure au¬
tomatically to the manned stations to be re-transmitted by
radio to great central storage computing and analysis
centres, either on land or at sea.
These networks of buoys in and on the sea will not
replace surface océanographie ships but will, rather,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
TURN TO THE SEA (Continue,
increase the need for them because the buoys will have to
be supplied, attended, and their data collected. Aircraft
flying above the sea also will be used to gather the
information about the oceans. From an aircraft at high
speed a view of the ocean can show currents, wind streaks,
boundaries between water of different kinds, and
concentrations of marine life. Also, the buoys in the sea
can transmit their data from the depths first by sound to
the surface and then by radio to an aircraft flying above
them. The airplane could question many buoys at the
same time and get a synoptic or simultaneous bird's-eye
picture of the situation.
The airplanes, too, can drop measuring instruments
which, as they sink down into the depths, transmit the
conditions of the different layers through which they pass.
We may expect to see large mother ships letting down
bathyscaphs and sending up helicopters to gather the total
data that we will need about the sea. Not only these
special vehicles for océanographie research but also ocean
liners and fishing vessels can be equipped with continually
recording instruments which, without interfering with their
normal business, can chart temperature, salinities
abundance of plant and animal plankton, and fish
populations. Only by the use of all of these can we hope
to obtain the world map of the huge oceans relating their
physical conditions to the distribution of life in them.
This map will give us the basis to understand the
complicated relationships that will enable us to make
useful predictions for fisheries, for ocean travel, for
underwater communications, and out of it will come many
other uses of ocean forecasting. All these together will
provide the network of observations of both ocean and
atmospheric conditions necessary for the numerical
weather predictors that we have today and for the
electronic oceanic forecasting computers that we will have
tomorrow.
o TAKING THE SEA'S PULSE
LTHOUGH we all chuckle and poke
fun at the weatherman, there is no
doubt that weather forecasts, even in their present state,
save lives and money in untold amounts each year. To
forecast ocean conditions will be increasingly useful and
important as mankind turns more to the sea. Ocean and
atmosphere work together, each influencing the other, so
that improved océanographie forecasts and better informa¬
tion of sea conditions will improve weather predictions,
and better weather predictions, such as being able to
foretell the strength of the winds over the sea, will improve
the predictions of wave, surf, and swell. Accurate predic¬
tion of these factors will reduce transoceanic crossing
times, increase passenger comfort, reduce ship maintenance
and repair costs, and save the lives of men and ships.
Knowing how strong a wind and how long a distance or
fetch it takes to generate waves lets us predict the height
of the pounding waves a vessel may expect to encounter.
The pulsing of the sea that we observe in the high and
low tides is the phenomenon that can be forecast most
accurately. Basic theory of the tides applies only to the
very deep ocean where, so far, we cannot measure them.
Yet, curiously enough, we can predict tides for coastal
points where as yet we don't fully understand them. The
tide periods can be broken down from a long record at
any place into regular cyclic ones, reconstructed and
extrapolated into the future. This is because the tide
generating forces are governed by the precise and highly
predictable motions of earth, sun, moon and other bodies
in our planetary system.
Another particular ocean forecast that has been used
for many years is the prediction of the coming and going
of ice in northern seas. Ice forecasting was highly
developed quite a long time ago in the Baltic Sea. Because
of the great amount of trade that went in and out of its
numerous ports it was important to know in advance when
the ports would be open or be closed by ice. A more
menacing kind of ice in the ocean, the treacherous
floating icebergs which show only a small fraction of their
huge bulk above water, also has been watched and
predicted for some time. Since the Titanic collided with
an iceberg in a disaster that shocked the world, an in-
12
ternational ice patrol service has studied conditions, made
forecasts, and issued warnings to steer shipping clear of
this danger. To do this the time and amount of calving
of the icebergs from glaciers is studied and the currents
that carry them down in the Baffin Bay area are watched
beyond the Grand Banks where they cross the main ship¬
ping lanes, right to their final melting, as they meet the
eddying fringes of the warm Gulf Stream.
How the surface winds affect the production of food
on which fish graze and how they affect the infant
mortality of the fish sets a basis for future fishery
forecasting. Already one remarkable example of the
value of forecasting can be found in haddock fishing on
George's banks. Here the strength and duration of
offshore winds during the haddock's annual spawning
period makes it possible to predict three years in advance
the probable size of the harvest of three-year-old-fish.
Both the wave and fisheries forecasts depend on knowing
from the weatherman the winds over the sea and the
forecasts will improve as the observing network at sea is
improved.
In the oceans we use sound waves not only for
communication and for echo-sounding the depth of the
ocean bottom but also for locating schools of fish. Good
or poor sound transmission depends on the distribution of
temperature and salinity and the location of mysterious
scattering layers and other conditions that can be
measured. The ionosphere influenced by the sun affects
our ability to communicate by radio through atmosphere.
Just as we have a central radio propagation laboratory to
predict and recommend the best wave lengths, so physical
conditions in the sea that affect sound will be measured
and an important part of ocean forecasting will be the
prediction of sound propagation in it.
Predictions of changes of major ocean currents,
themselves partly driven by wind, may provide a way of
foretelling their influence on subsequent weather. Océano¬
graphie forecasting has the advantage that changes are
much slower than those of the weather. Even if unreliable
at first, their usefulness and wide application will make
the world ocean forecasting service a necessity in the next
few years.
CONT'D ON PAGE 14
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
TURN TO THE SEA (Continued)-
oTHEGR
' MiMMMWl
STURES
OF TOMORROW
Photo © E. Aubert de la Rüe, showing salt being " harvested'
from seawater evaporating ponds at Djibouti, Somaliland.
EFORE human beings existed the sea was supplying that vital need '
for life on land water freshened by. the natural process of distilla¬
tion by the sun. Producing fresh water artificially from the sea is still an expensive process but is
already done for domestic purposes in isolated islands or places of military strategic or economic
importance such as on the coral atolls of the Pacific and the oil towns in the desert on the edge of
the Persian Gulf. In certain areas of the world, limited in their industrial development solely by
the shortage of water, the value of fresh water will increase and the cost of producing it from the
sea will decrease through technological advances. Fresh water will be the major product that we
will extract artificially from the sea in years to come.
Making fresh water by taking the salt from sea or brackish water is already done on a large scale
in many places. It is done by various methods. First there is the one that emulates nature by
distilling the water by boiling it off with the heat of fossil or nuclear fuels or the sun's heat and
leaving the salt behind. An electrical method whereby a current causes positive salt ions to flow
in one direction and negative ions in the other, thus separating the salt, is another possibility.
Also, we have thin membranes which let pure water through while blocking the flow of salts.
There are certain synthetic liquids, too, which absorb large quantities of plain water but reject
the salts. In contrast to the boiling or distillation production of fresh water where we must add
heat, we can emulate nature again and by taking heat away freeze sea water to separate the salt.
Natural sea ice is far less salty than the water from which it freezes. As the freezing process
proceeds, most of the salts are excluded, but one of the problems of this method is that crystals of
salt cling or are included in the frozen fresh water. The method is interesting because it takes
much less energy to freeze water than to boil it. There are biological methods, too, which hold
promise. It has been suggested that certain salt-absorbing algae might be used to de-salt sea water.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
hen people think of what we get
from the sea, they think first of
fish. Apart from the sun's natural extraction of water,
what man takes out of the sea in the greatest quantity are
its living resources. In countries such as Japan fish form
the most important part of the protein diet. Total world's
protein for human consumption, animal foods and other
purposes, taken from the sea, amounts to thirty million
tons a year (about a tenth is used in the United States).
The amount has increased by about one-half in the last ten
years.
With growing world populations to feed, it is certain
that the world's fisheries will increase their harvest, and
we are sure that the sea can give this increase if we can
learn better to husband and garner her resources. Since
only a few kinds of fish of the large number of known
varieties are taken and since many parts of the ocean,
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
especially in the southern hemisphere, are scarcely fished
at, all, we are sure of this. The living bounty of the sea
on which man will become increasingly dependent is self-
renewing provided we do not overfish as we once over-cut
our timberlands.
Over-fishing is not yet a problem except for a few
species-. However, they are among the more valuable
(salmon, haddock, halibut, whale). Those which can be
captured easily and command a high price have been
decimated in the past, such as Steller's sea cow now
extinct. Conservation of all these is an important national
and international task, and Whale hunting is now
rigidly controlled by international agreement. Although
the fishing boats use modern navigation, sonar and
aircraft to spot their catches, they employ methods nets,
trawls and lines which have not changed for hundreds of
years.
Floating cities foreseen in the Antarctic
OWEVER, new methods of fishing,
based on wider knowledge of the
available fish and their life cycles, will increase the poten¬
tial harvest tremendously while at the same time increasing
the need for wise conservation. We must bear in mind one
essential difference between land and sea resources: that on
land the property belongs to an individual who, in his own
interest, must conserve its resources; whereas the sea, being
open to all, is exploited to the fullest extent, limited only by
the economics of the fishing.
The fish harvest of the world is used to feed people not
only directly but indirectly through feeding poultry and
livestock and fertilizing plants. In countries with
abundant . agricultural land people eat only a limited
quantity of fish and, being economically able to pick and
choose, only a few varieties. The average person in the
United States eats eleven pounds of fish a year. This
amount has not increased in twenty years in spite of all
the improvements in refrigeration, freezing, transportation,
and so forth.
In Japan, where people crowd the land, fish is their
principal source of animal protein and they eat on an
average seven times as much as those in the United
States. They have learned also how to prepare hundreds
of varieties tastily and they eat not only the animal life
but many kinds of seaweed. Seaweed is gathered in other
countries, too, but is generally not eaten directly but
processed into a substance called algin, used in cosmetics,
textiles, paper, ink and drugs as well as in chocolate milk,
jellies and jams.
As the needs of the world for food increase, new and
different ways of fishing will be used. Today in the
Caspian Sea fish are attracted by underwater lights and
sucked aboard the fishing vessels by pumps. There will
be efficient new methods, too, of finding the fish. Sonar
and aircraft can locate them and studies of how their
food is blown by the wind can tell us where to capture
them.
As times goes on, the counterpart of agriculture in the
oceans, aquaculture, will catch up with the latest
agricultural methods on land. We will make sure that a
greater percentage of eggs hatch and that infant mortality
in fish is decreased so that more larvae and, above all,
young fish survive. We may hatch and raise small fish
in controlled oceanaria just as we hatch chicks in a brooder
or raise trout in hatcheries. We will increase the pro¬
ductivity of sea water by '"ploughing" the sea just as we
till the land, because the productivity of the sea seems to
depend on the bringing of dissolved substances from deep
layers to the surfaces.
One way of doing this would be to have a nuclear
reactor at the bottom of the sea to heat the lower water
and make it rise upwards and mix by convection, as we
would heat a pan of water on the stove. We will even
fertilize the sea artificially. We will not use phosphates
and nitrates as we do on land, even though these are the
basic nutrients for fish growth, because the volume of water
is suoh that the quantities of these basic nutrients would
be too great to contemplate. It will be possible, however,
to introduce trace elements in minute quantities to affect
growth in the ocean.
Like the whale factories which process the whole Whale
efficiently in Antarctic waters, we will see marine plant
and animal processing ships supplied by the catching boats
which scour the seas around them. The processing ships
will operate in essence as huge floating chemical
engineering factories. Their development will make fish
harvesting cheap enough to use a much wider variety of
fish than before, including what we now call trash fish.
Unappetizing-looking marine life will be transformed at
sea in these factories to tasty, nutritive protein. In the
most productive areas of the ocean as off Peru and in
Antarctic waters we may see floating industrial cities of
these processing plants.
The most important regions for aquaculture are the
shallow, almost land-locked waters that lie in estuaries all
over the world. These estuaries are important to our
food harvest from the sea for several reasons. First, it
is there that valuable shell fish reside permanently, and
second, they are the nursery where baby shell fish and
other fish begin their lives before they grow up to move
out into the ocean. Third, aquaculture can be carried on
there more easily than in the open sea. With the
competition for land for building, manufacturing, docking,
and tidal wave protection at the ocean edge, the charac¬
ter of estuarian waters may be vitally affected in a way
which would seriously harm these resources of the sea.
Coastal city planners, engineers and manufacturers must
consult the fishery biologists if man is not going to
intervene in a harmful way with the productive life of the
ocean.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
TURN TO THE SEA (Continued)
° GIANT VACUUM CLEANERS
TO MINE THE SEA FLOOR
NGiNEERS are concerned with the
erosion of land due to the powerful
wave action upon our coasts. They study the force of the
waves, the way in which different types of coastline
withstand this force, and how to modify coastlines to make
them more resistant. These studies involve how wave
energy is generated, how it is bent and reflected, and
how it is dissipated. The valiant efforts to preserve the
coastline must be carried out in a way that will satisfy the
many competing uses of the seashores and not kill the
precious life in the sea that depends on estuaries.
Of great importance to life in estuaries is the rate of
flushing. How soon will the natural tidal pumping
scavenge and dilute any polluting materials poured into
them? There are pockets in certain estuaries where this
pumping is insufficient and where, in consequence, waste
should not be put. This problem is particularly impor¬
tant when we consider radioactive waste materials in
estuaries or the radioactive fallout from some use of a
nuclear weapon or when atomic bombs are used for the
peaceful purpose of blasting out artificial harbours of the
future.
Besides fresh water and its living resources for food,
the sea gives us other raw materials for use in our civili¬
zation salt, magnesium, and other minerals. Because of
the tremendous volume of the sea, the total amount of
any mineral in it is a staggering quantity and leads to
dreams such as "gold from the sea." But with few
exceptions, so dilute is the concentration that extraction is
as uneconomical as processing a very, very low grade ore
on land. Salt from the sea by evaporation is an ancient
industry and for thousands of years man has taken it for
his use by allowing the sun to evaporate off the water from
shallow salterns. Nowadays not only sodium salts but
potassium and magnesium salts are separated from sea
water. Bromine gas is a valuable byproduct of both salt
works and magnesium production. Lightweight magne¬
sium, second most abundant metal in sea water, is
extracted by such a simple process that it is economical
even though there is only a tenth of one per cent of it in
sea water whereas normal rock and soil on land contain
forty times as much.
The whole question of whether or not we extract
anything from sea water depends on whether it competes
favourably with getting the same substance from
somewhere else. But as in the case of the artificial
distillation of fresh water, as time goes on the scarcity of
substances previously in abundant supply raises their value
and makes processes, formerly prohibitively costly, econo¬
mical.
Some minerals are contained in nodules which lie on
the bottom in plentiful quantities over vast areas of the
deep sea. How they formed over millions of years is not
properly understood. We will mine the sea floor two
thousand fathoms below the surface for the small per¬
centages of cobalt, copper and nickel which are contained
in nodules of manganese and iron that now lie exposed
there. They will be mined by using huge vacuum cleaners
TEMPEST
IN A TANK
Large, rotating tank (right) at Woods
Hole Océanographie Institute in the
U.S.A. is used for studies of ocean
currents. Rotation of the earth,
heating, cooling and wind condi¬
tions can be duplicated In the model.
Through studies of this kind, scien¬
tists try to learn more about the con¬
ditions that produce such maritime
catastrophes as the hurricane "Carol"
which devastated the Atlantic coast
of the United States in 1954. (Photo
opposite page shows small boat
owners saving their craft in the
early stages of Carol's rampage).
Woods Hole Océanographie Institution
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
to suck them up into the holds of surface ships or by
submarine caterpillar-tracked earth movers that scrape the
valuable nodules into submarine mine hoists.
Under the shallower water of the continental shelves we
are now tapping valuable reserves of petroleum and will
turn to the sea more and more for oil. Petroleum, the
stored sunshine of ancient marine animal fossils, lies not
only under our land where the sea once was but also four
hundred billion barrels of it, about a third of all remaining
on earth, waits in reserve underneath the sea bed.
The sea has been used from time immemorial as a great
trash can. As long as wastes are organic or ordinary
chemicals the sea can turn them «into useful nutrients or
at least dilute them enough to be harmless. Now man
has a waste radioactive waste that he can neither burn
and blow into the atmosphere, nor allow to seep into the
ground, nor without thought discharge into the sea. The
sea is still considered and is being studied as a convenient
place to dump radioactive wastes. Seventy per cent of
the fission products of all our nuclear bombs fall on the
sea because the sea covers that percentage of the area of
the earth. And even though sea water dilutes them, some
biological organisms in the food chain that leads to man
can concentrate radioactive isotopes thousands of times.
It has been thought that perhaps a thousand tons a year
of nuclear radioactive ashes can be deposited safely in the
deep isolated basins of the ocean, but we cannot be sure
until we know how long water stays in these deeps.
Rounded rocks have been found at the bottom of them,
a possible indication that currents there are faster than we
think. It would be a pity if man, who often unthinkingly
has harmed his environment on earth by denuding forests,
making whole species of animals extinct, causing eye-
watering smogs in his cities, over farming land and making
it sterile, should by ignorance affect the animal popula¬
tions of the deep sea and set up a chain reaction which
might harm everything living in the ocean.
Before we put these Ionglived radioactive materials into
the sea, we should wait for our research to tell us whether
or not it is safe. Because the need to dispose of these
wastes is pressing, we must speed up our studies of the
currents, chemistry, geology and biology of the sea and its
fife so that we can answer the question: Will it be harmful
to future generations?
There is great energy stored in the sea. The most
obvious that we can tap is the ebb and flow of the tide,
especially at places where tides are unusually high, such
as the Bay of Fundy where they rise and fall the height
of a four-story building. Other extraordinarily high tides
are in southern Alaska and at Inchon in Korea. The
great tides of the world occur because the twice-a-day pull
of the moon happens to be in synchronism with the natural
mode of vibration of the water in the particular estuary
basins. Attempts are now being made to harness the
tides in France, and the Passamaquoddy project to utilize
the water's rise and fall in the Bay of Fundy is still alive.
Another way of using the energy of the sea is to drive
heat engines by the difference in temperature between the
warm surface and the cold deep water of the oceans.
I do not suggest cutting back the exciting exploration
of space, but m : rely point out that for a comparatively
tiny sum we could preserve a balance in investigating our
own earth which, as I have stressed, is a most convenient
and accessible laboratory to understand the problems ; of
the universe.
Much of the undersea landscape, hidden from our eyes,
is less well known than the face of the moon that we see!
With minerals resting on it, nutrients sinking toward it,
geologic history locked in its sedimentary layers, and petro¬
leum beneath it, the sea's bottom is at least as interesting,
and certainly more immediately useful to mankind, than
the moon's back side. What we need to do to investigate
the sea can be done for a yearly cost which is a small
fraction of what we now spend on space.
To understand earth, sun and space we must balance
the expenditures of our resources, human and material,
so that we do not neglect, in our enthusiasm over sun and
space, our own earth. It is wonderful to look out and
try to understand space; it will be exciting to go out; but...
we should not forget the earth on which we stand and the
great storehouse of living needs... ours for the taking...
held for us in the seas.
© Jan Hahn
Woods Hole
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A UNESCO VESSEL
TO SAIL THE SEAS
by Augusto Pérez-Vitoria
Dept. of Natural Sciences, Unesco
A Unesco ship may soon be sailing the high seas. An
international vessel designed for oceanological
research and weighing between 1,000 and 1,200 tons,
it will be both a floating laboratory with equipment
for an international group of scientists to work
on board and a training school for young oceanographers
chemists, physicists, geologists and biologists. The blue
and white flag of the United Nations flying from its mast
may become a familiar sight in the ports of the Indian
Ocean.
Why has the Indian Ocean been chosen for its opera¬
tions? Because this is the least known of all the oceans
one of our last unexplored frontiers. Since 1873 less than
two dozen vessels have carried out océanographie inves¬
tigations there. The international ship will be of service
to all nations wishing to do research in these still unknown
waters. It will also be an outstanding demonstration of
practical international co-operation between the scientists
of many nations.
The idea of putting an océanographie vessel at Unesco's
disposal was born several years ago. It was first considered
by the Economic and Social Council of the United Nations
in 1946 and approved in 1952 by the Indo-Pacific Fisheries
Council, in 1955 it was discussed by a Unesco body, the
international Advisory Committee on Marine Sciences;
finally, Unesco's General Conference decided in 1958 to
submit the project to an international conference meeting
in Copenhagen, from July 11 to 16 this year.
The cost of adapting the ship (about $300,000) and the
annual operating expenses (approximately the same
amount) would be covered by Unesco's ordinary budget. It
is hoped that Unesco will receive the ship as a gift or at
a symbolic price. So as to develop the work more rapidly,
it is also proposed to set up a special fund made up of
voluntary contributions from individual States and
organizations.
Vast programme
of marine research
If the first stage of this international océanographie
venture gives the results that are hoped for, it can be
followed by another more ambitious plan: the
construction of a large, up-to-date océanographie vessel
filled with the last word in equipment which, because of
its cost or complexity, has never yet been installed in any
nationally owned ship. This would provide ideal condi¬
tions for leading specialists in the marine sciences to
undertake a series of top-level research projects, without
entirely giving up the training of a group of young ocea¬
nographers. But the cost of this ambitious and worth¬
while project runs into several million dollars so that the
first international action will have to be on a more modest
scale.
But the plan to build and operate an océanographie
vessel is not an isolated project. It will be accompanied
in Unesco's programme for 1961-62 and subsequent years
by a large-scale plan of océanographie study and
research.
Already for some years past Unesco has been carrying
out work in the various branches of the marine sciences.
It has granted fellowships, met the requests of Member
States for specialist advice and material aid, and has
provided other assistance for scientific publications and
meetings. It has helped to organize regional seminars
and round tables and has taken part in international,
congresses such as the first International Océanographie
Congress convened by the American Association for the
Advancement of Science, which was attended by over
1,200 scientists from fifty countries, at U.N. Headquarters,
New York, last September. Two months later, Unesco
convened in Monaco, in collaboration with the Interna¬
tional Atomic Energy Agency, the International Confe¬
rence on the Disposal of Radioactive Wastes, whose work
both from the social and scientific viewpoints,, aroused
the greatest interest.
Deep sea venture
for 14 Nations
These long-established activities will be greatly expanded
if a proposed 500% increase in the budget is accord¬
ed them. Attention is first to be given to the Indian
Ocean: here Unesco will contribute to the international
programme drawn up under the supervision of the
Special Committee on Oceanic Research (SCOR) of
the International Council of Scientific Unions. Ships
and scientists from 14 countries will share in this pro¬
gramme, carrying out intensive studies in the area for
the next four years. Fellowships will be granted to
young oceanographers from the region so that they can
do practical work on the ships taking part in SCOR'S
international campaign; other students will receive
grants for studies in research establishments of other
countries. Several international specialists will join the
staffs of regional centres of physio-chemical oceanography
and marine biology. These centres will receive new
equipment to enable them to study and classify a portion
of the samples and specimens collected.
Experts sent out by Unesco will also take part in region¬
al in-service training courses and round-table discussions
at which the progress of' the expeditions will be reviewed
as well as the value and scope of the results obtained;
scientists from the SCOR expedition will also attend
meetings when their research vessels make calls in these
regional centres.
The neighbouring coastal regions of South-East Asia
will also benefit to a certain extent from Unesco's assis¬
tance, which will gradually, be increased and extended to
other parts of the world. -Unesco's océanographie vessel
will also make its contributions in all regions where it
can be made available.
A widespread effort to improve the teaching of the
marine sciences and to increase the number of university
chairs and océanographie institutes is also planned. More
students and research workers must be attracted to' the
marine sciences for without them any large-scale pro¬
gramme of study and research will run into serious
obstacles.
Finally, Unesco's Océanographie Section will prepare
and supervise that part of the international study and
research plan with which the Organization is directly
concerned and will assist in all the joint projects of
Governments represented on the Intergovernmental Océa¬
nographie Commission to be set up within Unesco. The
same group will ensure the co-ordination of related
projects launched by other Specialized Agencies of the
United Nations and by the different Océanographie Asso¬
ciations and Councils already at work on an interna¬
tional level.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August I960
THE CHINA SEA
IN BOTTLES
Years and years of patient work
went into the assembling of this
impressive océanographie collec¬
tion in the Nathrang Institute,
Viet Nam. Tens of thousands of
animals and plants from the China
Sea are preserved in these bottles.
Pierre Pittet
EXPEDITION TO THE INDIAN OCEAN
a HE first systematic attempt by
science to survey an entire ocean
will get under way later this year
when ships in ports around the globe
weigh anchor and head out to sea en route
for the Indian Ocean. They will be the
advance guard of a fleet of vessels from
some 15 countries which will sail to join
the International Indian Ocean Expedition
a 4-year venture virtually unparalleled
in the history of oceanology, sponsored by
the Special Committee on Oceanic
Research (SCOR) of the International
Council of Scientific Unions.
With its 28 million square miles, the
Indian Ocean covers 14% of the earth's
surface reaching from Antarctica to India
and from E. Africa to Australia and
Tasmania. Surrounding it are some of
the world's most densely-populated
countries which represent over a quarter
of the globe's people. It is unique among
the world's seas for several reasons.
It is one of our last unexplored frontiers.
Only the most general features of its
topography and marine life distribution are
known. Nowhere else are the winds and
currents completely reversed with the
seasons. For 6 months of the year the
monsoons blow from the northeast while
the rest of the year they blow in the
opposite direction, southwest. This has
far-reaching effects on both currents and
sea life but how and why are still a
mystery.
Then too, the vast northern part of the
ocean, including the Bay of Bengal and
the Arabian Sea, is practically sealed off
from exchange with other oceans. Great
rivers ' like the Indus, Ganges, Tigris-
Euphrates and Zambesi pour millions of
tons of soil-rich water into the Indian
Ocean which makes it ideal for studying
the effects of this runoff on the composition
of sea water, particularly its metal and
mineral concentrations.
It is estimated that the expedition will
cost roughly about $13.5 million and will
reach the full peak of its activity in 1962
and . 19T53. Research vessels will be
provided by marine laboratories from
Australia, France, Great Britain, India,
Japan, Union of South Africa, U.S.A. and
U.S.S.R. Ship time may also be provided
by the Federal Republic of Germany,
Netherlands, the Scandinavian and other
countries.
Already, a cruise pattern, splitting the
entire Indian Ocean into sections of a grid
has been agreed on by SCOR. Completing
the grid may require 15 ship-years of
operation over a total of 225,000 miles.
Ships will cruise twice along the same track
in particularly important areas.
The expedition will not only provide
basic scientific knowledge about the Indian
Ocean and oceans generally, but is also
expected to have immediate economic
consequences by identifying likely fishing
areas, indicating what to fish for and when,
and suggesting the magnitude of the fishery
resources of the Indian Ocean. Meteoro¬
logical studies may lead to better long-
range weather forecasting and in the
monsoon flood areas this could well be
a major achievement. Knowing how ocean
currents vary in intensity and location may
lead to more economic routing of ships as
was the case in the North Atlantic where
it resulted in savings as high as 10% in
fuel consumption. Charting the ocean
floor will also be useful for navigation,
while sampling the continental shelves and
the sea bottom may reveal rich untapped
resources.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
EXPLORING
o
THE WORLDS
DEEPEST
TRENCHES
by
c
Anton F. Bruun
Dr. Anton F. Bruun of the Zoologiske Museum,
Copenhagen, is considered by many as the world's
leading authority on life in the deep sea. In
1950-52 he headed the famed Galathea Ex¬
pedition, and has just won the coveted Agassiz
medal awarded by the National Research Council
of the U.S. National Academy of Sciences for
his work in oceanology. Dr. Bruun's article opens
on July 21, 1951, with the Galathea at Oceano-
logical Station 41' above the 34,500-foot Philippine
Trench, hauling the deepest dredge yet lowered.
Uly 21, 1951, was a tense day aboard
the frigate Galathea, carrying the
Danish Round-the-World Deep-Sea
Expedition of 1950-52. The 10,000-metre depth of the
Philippine Trench was showing on the recording paper
of our echo sounder. We had found a suitable even bottom
for towing a trawl. Since We had left Copenhagen in
October, 1950, we had made many successful hauls four
or five kilometres down in the Atlantic and Indian Oceans,
but it is one thing to climb the Alps and quite another to
try to climb Mount Everest. And so it is in the ocean
except that Mount Everest would have about 2,000 metres
of water above its peak if this giant mountain were placed
in the bottom of the Philippine Trench.
Depths of more than 7,000 metres are found in deep
ocean trenches. Only 18 of these trenches are known:
one in the Indian Ocean, two in the Atlantic, and no less
than 15 in the Pacific, including the only ones five in
number which are more than 10,000 metres deep. The
record depth of 10,863 metres found by the British Chal¬
lenger expedition in 1951 in the Mariana Trench may
still be considered the world's deepest until more recent
observations, claiming a few hundred more metres in the
same area, have been published in detail.
But why should a scientific expedition use its time and
precious equipment for trawling in these tricky trenches?
20
They certainly are tricky: at depths of ten thousand
metres, the flat bottom of a trench is only about one kilo¬
metre wide. Letting out a trawl with 12,000 metres of
steel line and trying to follow this narrow strip is not
nearly as easy as fishing at depths of 2,000 to 6,000 metres
where wide stretches of flat bottom are found. Trench
fishing at such depths is comparable to flying an airplane
at 10,000 metres and trying to tow an instrument along
the surface of the earth with only an echo sounder to
keep it on a strip no more than one kilometre wide.
If we touched the rugged slopes of the trench, we might
tangle our wire in the rocks, losing it along with the
trawl. But, if we succeeded, then we would have accom¬
plished something more important than merely fishing
deeper than anyone else. But We wanted to find out if
life could exist 10,000 metres down where hydrostatic
pressure is one thousand atmospheres or one ton per
square centimetre.
At the beginning of this century, Prince Albert of
Monaco fished at 6,000 metres, tout it was only in 1948
that a Swedish deep-sea expedition brought up a few
animals from depths of 7,625 to 7,800 metres in the Puerto
Rico Trench. Then, in 1949, the Soviet Vityaz Expedition
brought up life from 8,100 metres in the Kuriles-Kam¬
chatka Trench. Experiments on shallow-Water animals
had shown, however, that they could not live at a pres¬
sure of 1,000 atmospheres. This meant one of two things:
either the deepest of the ocean depths were lifeless or the
organisms living in them had to be different from any
others known to science, especially in their biochemical
and physiological aspects. We already knew of organisms
adapted to the low pressure of lofty mountains, but could
there be life in a world of extremely high pressures?
That afternoon, we began to pay out our steel line. At
its end was fitted a 3-metre sledge trawl; if the net of
this trawl were torn, a small dredge" could still bring up
something from the bottom. It took us several hours to
get out all our 12,163 metres of line, tout finally there were
only a few turns left on the big drum of our winch. We
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
LIFE UNDER SIX
MILES OF WATER
One of the most significant achievements of the
Danish Galathea expedition was the trawling of the
Philippine Trench, over 10,000 metres (six and a
half miles) deep. Two tiny sea-anemones clinging to
a stone from the bottom of the trench, proved that
higher animals could live at depths of 1 0,000 metres.
Below Dr Bruun, on right, and bacteriologist Claude
Zobell, study small whitish anemones on a stone
with rounded edges from the trench bottom. Fingers
point to anemones, smaller than a finger nail. Left,
two sea-cucumbers, less than two inches long,
dredged up from 22,000 feet in the Kermadec
Trench, near New Caledonia. On an earlier expe¬
dition, Dr. Bruun caught a six-foot larval eel whjch
has raised conjectures on the existence of sea
monsters. Previously, the largest larvel eel for
which adults were known only measured one foot.
Theoretically, a six-foot larval eel could produce a 45-
foot adult, but no giant adult has ever been caught.
stared at the line anxiously wondering if we had given
our engineers sufficient data in calculating the dimensions
of the cable. Had they made any errors?
Yet everything depended upon that steel line. Besides
bearing its own weight, it had to resist water friction
along a length of twelve kilometres, the weight of the
trawl and the friction of the trawl on the bottom. And
not least, we wondered if we had been correct in calculat¬
ing the length of the cable in relation to the depth of
the trench and the speed of the ship. If we let out too
little line, then the trawl might not touch bottom; if we
let out too much, then the line itself might create friction
on the bottom. Despite all this, things went as smoothly
as if we had been fishing at our usual 5,000-metre depth.
The sun set and the night was almost gone when our
trawl came up again.
There, deep down in the clear water, was the faint out¬
line of the large triangular bag of the trawl. The night
was still pitch-black, but the quarterdeck lay bathed in
the beams of our spotlights. Then the results came in
rapid succession. "There's clay on the frame," someone
yelled. "It's been on the bottom." And then... "There
are stones in the bag!"
There, on a rather large stone, were some small whitish
growths: sea anemones! Even if no other animals had
been found, this would have been the biggest haul of
our expedition. It was proof that higher animals could
live at depths below 10,000 metres. Is it surprising that
we were overjoyed? And our joy turned into real excite¬
ment when, out of the grayish clay bearing gravel and
stones, we picked a total of 25 sea-anemones, about 75
sea-cucumbers, five bivalves, one amphipod crustacean and
one bristle-worm. It was an unexpectedly rich variety of
bottom-dwelling animals.
It was obvious that this haul had been made on the
bottom and, fortunately, we had proof that it lay between
10,150 and 10,190 metres. We toad navigated carefully
according to the profile of the bottom which we had labor¬
iously pieced together from echo soundings carried out
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
WORLD'S DEEPEST TRENCHES (Continued)
for days previously. Wind and sea had been very slight
from the north, almost dead ahead and as favourable as
they could possibly be. Our long night vigil was forgotten.
Our first success had to toe followed up and repeated.
And it was repeated here and later on in the Sunda,
Banda, New Britain and Kermadec Trenches, all over
7,000 metres deep.
In the Philippine Trench we had found a whole little
animal community of eight different species, representing
all the large groups of invertebrates: polyps, worms,
molluscs and crustaceans. Our bacteriologist also suc¬
ceeded in cultivating bacteria isolated from the sediments.
He has now studied them for years, keeping them alive
under the same temperature (about 2.5 °C) and the same
pressure (about 1,000 atmospheres) as at the bottom. And,
most important of all they only grow at such a high
pressure. Thus, organisms adapted to a very special world
of life under high pressure had been discovered. .
Technically we have named these trench depths the
hadal zone, those which correspond to the current terms
for the oceanic continental slopes, (bathyal) and the ocea¬
nic depths between about 2,000 and 6,000 metres (abyssal) .
Naturally, pressure must also be at work at depths less
than about 6,000 metres and several examples of distribu¬
tion indicate that the abyssal zone may be subdivided into
an upper and a lower zone.
The hadal animals also have a very important bearing
on the evolution of species. They all stem from abyssal
species which have become adapted to the extreme
pressure. But once a species during the elapse of from
a hundred thousand to millions of years has descended
into the trench, it cannot freely move into another trench.
This means its fate is very closely connected with that of
the trench itself. Therefore a comparative study of the
hadal zone and its organisms may yield important facts
about the history of the trenches, which really means the
history of the earth.
The study of the lower abyssal and the hadal zones is
a much-needed one; all the more so if the ocean in the
coming years should be used for dumping atomic waste
from atomic power plants. So far, this work has only
been followed up and with remarkable success by the
Soviet Vityaz Expeditions. The combined efforts of the
Galathea and the Vityaz may be summarized as follows:
out of 85 different species found deeper than 7,000 metres,
no less than 62 species or 74 per cent were discovered
exclusively in the true hadal zone. Such a high per cent
of endemism is very rarely found in nature and may well
match such well-known examples on land as the Gala¬
pagos Islands or New Zealand.
To-day we finally know that a varied world of organisms
can live almost anywhere on the earth Life has con¬
quered high mountains and the deepest oceans, dry hot
deserts and cold polar regions. It is from comparative
studies of these worlds that much of our understanding of
life comes. But the fields of physiology, biochemistry, etc.
have barely been applied to the hadal creatures.
The hadal environment was called a new world, but the
Galathea also added a fragment to our knowledge about
a very old world more than 300 million years old. This
was done towards the very end of the expedition when,
on May 6, 1952, the trawl brought up from 3,570 metres ten
inconspicuous-looking limpet-like molluscs and three
empty shells of the same species. It took our specialist
some years of careful study at home before he could
state convincingly that ' the creature, which he named
Neopilina galathea, was not a snail or a bivalve, nor
related to any known class of the recent molluscs, but a
representative of a class supposed to have become extinct
since the palaeozoic era, more than 300 million years ago.
Thus it is a case parallel to the famous Coelacanth fish
from the Comoro Islands, first found in 1938. The Coela¬
canth is also a living fossil, a survivor from the Cretaceous
time which dates back only some 70 million years.
The Neopilina is of extreme zoological interest, since it
is the most primitive mollusc known and in many ways its
importance might be compared to that of the primitive
egg-laying mammals of Australia in our understanding of
the evolution of all other mammals. With the Neopilina
we have in the flesh what was formerly only known as
some very characteristic fossils from Cambro-Devonian
times. But apart from its zoological interest, Neopilina
has also something to tell us about the living conditions
in the deep sea of past times. The reason why no traces
of it have been found in sediments is that, ever since the
Palaeozoic era, it has lived at such a depth that no sedi¬
ments have been elevated to the level of present land.
Nowadays, it lives at temperatures of less than about 4°C
which are typical of the abyssal zone. It must have taken
a very long time for these animals to have become adapted
to the high pressure and low temperature, so different
from that of the shallow Palaeozoic coastal seas. There¬
fore we can safely conclude that for millions of years
there must have been sufficient oxygen in ocean depths!
This requires a .circulation of the water masses.
But should we conclude that the Neopilina, and a second
species recently found by the United States "Vema" expe¬
dition, are the last interesting creatures that will be
discovered in the deep sea? Certainly not! We probably
only know half of the species living in the ocean. Past
expeditions have barely opened the oceanic world; the
time has come when we must start a co-ordinated study
of its organisms on a big scale. This will result in a deeper
insight into the world we live in,, but at the same time it
will also bring us badly-needed knowledge which is Indis¬
pensable for the utilization of the organisms of the grand
ocean.
C.E. Zobell, Scripps Institution, California Galathea Expeditions
LIVING FOSSIL. Most dramatic of the Galathea's discoveries was a " living fossil ", the mollusc Neopilina (right) believed to
have been extinct for 300 million years. Before it was found 12,000 feet down near the Costa Rica coast, zoologists recognized
five classes of molluscs (including clams, snails and squids). The Neopilina is so biologically distinct that a sixth and separate
class has been added. Left, electron micrograph greatly magnifies clump of rapidly reproducing bacteria, isolated from mud
found six and a half miles down in Philippine Trench. It was kept alive at sea bottom pressure of about 1,000 atmospheres.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
This tripod fish hops across the
sea floor on built-in stilts. It was
photographed from the bathyscaph
Trieste off Guam , in the Marianas
islands, seven thousand metres
under the surface. Previously,
scientists believed that it trailed its
two long pelvic fins and caudal
appendage as feelers. But the
bathyscaph's observations snowed
that the fish uses its extremities
as a kind of landing gear, springing
across the bottom like a cricket.
The creature on the right is » Halb-
porphyrus, casting the shadow of
its characteristic " double tail n,
¡g. Capt. Georges S. Houot, French Navy
.,<*
IN THE REÁ1M OF
THE TRIPOD FISH
u
v4 ow can living creatures exist in the
I I great depths of the sea? How must
-^^» -^^- they adapt themselves physiologically
to survive in an environment characterized mainly by
enormous pressure, eternal night and virtually never
changing conditions? These questions fascinate the
human mind, for this universe on our own planet may
be more different from our land universe than that found
in many a planet in outer space. How has life evolved
below that sparkling veil which hid it from our eyes for
so long?
First of all, one very serious misconception must be
cleared up, namely that great pressure makes life impos¬
sible. We still live in the grip of such beliefs. Many of
us, for example, continue to cling to the same erroneous
ideas which long hindered the development of a true
diving suit. After all, how many inventors tried to
"protect" the diver's face or abdomen from water pres¬
sure while leaving the other parts of his body exposed?
It meant nothing less than condemning him to death.
Let's imagine that a man's head remains at normal
pressure while the rest of his body is receiving water
pressure 40 metres down at five kilogrammes per square
centimetre. In this case, the helmet "protecting" his head
is nothing less than a suction cup drawing up the
unfortunate diver's blood and emptying it through his
nose, eyes and ears. If, on the other hand, pressure is
by Pierre de Latil
uniformly distributed over his body and the air he
breathes is at the same pressure as that of the water
around him, then the diver has absolutely no feeling of
being crushed. His skin and his internal organs are at
the same pressure, and everything functions in perfect
balance. Thus physics sets no limit on the depth which
a human being, or any other living creature, can reach.
But there is chemistry, too... and this complicates things.
Chemical reactions are not the same when the
substances involved are under pressure. When our blood
is at normal atmospheric pressure, oxygen combines with
it very easily, and nitrogen hardly at all. But if the
pressure is increased, our blood becomes charged with
nitrogen. This gas is a poison although actually it
creates a feeling of intoxication which is quite pleasant.
The diver who' goes too far down (around 40 or 50 metres
for the untrained man) runs the risk of coming under
the influence of "depth rapture" which can put him to
sleep... and put him to sleep forever because as he loses
consciousness he lets go of the mouthpiece of his breath¬
ing apparatus.
There is another danger, too, when he returns to the
surface. Once the pressure returns to normal, the blood
no longer takes up nitrogen. The nitrogen then starts
to escape and the diver's blood becomes like soda, water
filled with gaseous bubbles which can cause blood clots.
These facts about what happens to the human diver
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
enable us to understand more clearly the physiology of
deep-sea animals. There is no physical limitation to the
depth at which life can exist. In fact, an animal will
always be in equilibrium with its environment. Its blood,
body fluids and all its cells will be under equal internal
and external pressures, and these opposite pressures will
always cancel themselves out. We can now realize how
wary we must be of those statements, we often read (even
in some scientific books) which tell us that fish "burst"
when they have been brought to the surface from the
depths of the sea.
The Danish oceanographer, Anton Bruun, leader of the
celebrated Galathea expedition, has fished 10,000 metres
down, as he tells us in another article in this issue. He
is quite definite on this point: fish from the great depths
of the sea cannot explode. And there you have another
sea legend to be thrown overboard! If these fish usually
reach the surface in poor condition, it is merely because
they have been roughly handled during the long journey
of the net up from the bottom of the sea.
The basic difference between a deep-water animal and
a surface animal is found in the chemical exchanges in
its organism (perhaps better referred to as its meta¬
bolism).
The main problem in the biology of the ocean depths,
however, is one of food, and its characteristics change
considerably the deeper you go. First of all, we must
remember that, whether on land or on the sea bottom,
all organic matter comes from plants which synthesize it
from mineral matter through the action of sun on chloro¬
phyll. Algae are therefore the starting point of the food
chain in the sea. Since they need light, they live only
in shallow waters for example down to 200 or 300 metres.
However, there is nothing absolute about this limit. Most
of the time, these algae are floating freely in the depths
and they can rise or descend according to the movements
of the currents.
Banquets on the surface
leftovers in the depths
Microscopic algae are eaten by tiny animals which, in
turn, are the food supply for bigger animals which
are devoured by even bigger ones... and so on. This
perpetual hunt and this gigantic feast are not limited to
the zone of the sea where the sun penetrates. A school of
small shellfish, for example, which has eaten algae on the
surface may then go 200 metres down to be eaten by
small fish; while bigger fish from the depths may rise
to hunt the little fellows. Algae from the surface can
fall to the bottom as well. The most intense zone of
marine life appears to go down to 1,500 or 2,000 metres,
depending upon the ocean.
Then what do creatures eat further down? The answer
is: the leftovers from that sunlit banquet on the surface,
and the corpses of plankton animals which literally rain
down like a continuous supply of manna.
But this manna becomes rare near the bottom after
everyone has had a chance at it on the upper floors.
At the same time, animal life becomes rare as well.
Nevertheless, . this rain accumulates on the bottom and
there life again becomes more intense. If the bottom is
extremely deep, then the food supply may be exhausted
before it reaches it. That is why animals are rare and
small in size at depths of 8,000 or 10,000 metres, or even
further down. They are simply "undernourished" because
the cycle of life can be begun only by the sun on the
surface.
Despite this gradual waning of life as depth increases,
life on the bottom is not homogenous. In this very special
environment, adaptation has not taken place along any
clearcut lines. Down there, as on land, the only law seems
to be diversity, manifold forms and the inexhaustible
"ingenuity" of nature's solutions. In other words, the law
is that there is no law. Only the colours of these
creatures, which become more pale, represent any common
evolution.
24
REALM OF THE TRIPOD FISH
(Continued)
INTO THE WORLD
OF LIQUID NIGHT
Official Soviet photo
Above, with its searchlight probing the darkness, this Russian
diving chamber can go down to depths of 2,000 feet for obser¬
vation of underwater life. Right, a beak-nosed skate on the
desertlike sea floor 7,200 feet down. . Photo was taken from a
French Navy bathyscaph. The 2 1/2 foot skate, a relative of
the ray, ignored the bathyscaph and glided by the gondola.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
LAMP
ANTENNAE
THAT SPELL
DEATH
The voracious angler fish of the ocean
depths carry on their heads "fishing
antennae" bearing lights. They wave these
in front of their mouths and their victims
seem to be attracted and drawn inside.
Official Soviet photos
For example, let us look at their feeding organs. For
certain fish, the apparently logical solution is an enormous
mouth capable of catching prey "blindly" by gulping
anything that comes within reach. But others have
normal mouths and some animals on the bottom have
nothing but a tiny suction apparatus.
Let us look more closely at these wide-mouthed fish,
especially the ones in the Stomiad family. Their lower
jaw is articulated in an amazing manner at the back of
their skulls. It is designed to be thrust forward and then
pulled back as if it were a steam shovel. Everything
identifies this fish as a hunter which can thrust its lower
jaw forward, seize its prey in its pointed fangs (which are
made for gripping, not grinding) and then literally throw
its victims into the back of its gullet.
Creatures with 'parking lights'
& mouths like steam shovels
Proof of this interpretation is the fact that the
lower jaw of a certain Stomiad, the Malocosteus indi-
cus, is reduced to a bone no more floor of the mouth,
no more skin covering the bony structure. Here, there is
really nothing more than a steam shovel in front of the
true mouth of the fish. With a "net" as open as this one,
it is hard to imagine how this animal can fish blindly.
For that matter, how can we visualize the kind of
hunting which involves seeing in a totally obscure world?
There you have the first illogical aspect of life on the
bottom. While it is easy to" understand how animals
feeding on microscopic prey can hunt by merely filtering
water or digging in the mud, the secret of fish living on
larger prey is impenetrable.
Phosphorescence in these creatures is even more
Illogical. Many of them display lights of different colours.
The oceanographers of the second half of the 19th
Century have all described their astonishment at the sight
of a net being opened on the deck of a ship at night.
We also know that some animals, which have never been
observed alive, shed light because the tissues of their
light-producing organs have been identified.
How can we interpret these facts these bright lights,
soft glows, varied colours with our human logic? We
can imagine a fish lighting its way just as a motor car
does at night, but it cannot light the sea brightly
enough to hunt. And why do some of these animals have
lights around their bodies like the illuminated portholes
of a ship? Why do they have "parking lights" in the
rear or else glowing tips at the end of long appendices?
And, most of all, what is the use of light to beings which
quite often are blind?
But how blind are these animals? Every stage of atrophy
of the eyes has been observed, to the point of their
complete disappearance. On the other hand, perfectly
formed eyes have been observed in fish living at depths
where, we know, they never can be used because of total
darkness. Then why have certain eyes degenerated while
others have remained "functional"? This puzzle has
become even more complicated since scientists have
learned that none of the creatures of the greatest depths
react to the searchlights of bathyscaphs. The deeper you
go, the more "whys" you seem to find.
But the biggest mystery of all is probably that of the
male parasites of certain Cerates. We can understand
that the male of a species may be a great deal smaller
than the female. But, here, the male is minute. It lives
as a parasite on the skin of its "mate", just an appendix
on the female's body. Linked to the female's blood system,
it has no organs of its own and it is nothing more than
a male sexual gland.
An entire biological universe awaits discovery. More
surprises are certainly In store for us in this liquid night
which has been barely opened to our exploration and
which still remains closed to our logic.
Courtesy Capt. Georges S. Houot, French Navy, and National Geographic Magazine
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE WRECK
OF THE
WASA
:or many years, historians, scientists and amateur
investigators searched near the entrance of
Stockholm harbour for traces of a Swedish
naval vessel, the Wasa, which unaccountably
capsized and sank at the start of its maiden
Voyage on August 1 0, I 628. Then, four years
ago, an amateur skin-diver, Anders Franzen,
came across a hump on the sea-bottom opposite
one of the Swedish Navy's dry docks. Further
investigations confirmed that under this mud
bank lay the 64-gun man-of-war of which all
trace had been lost since the last attempt to
raise her was made in 1663. Plans were made
to open up this treasure trove and also, if
possible, to raise the wreck in one piece. The
condition of the first objects brought to the
surface from the Wasa showed that the waters
of the Baltic with their low salinity had acted
as a preservative. The finds included a prow
figure head, an ornately decorated bronze
cannon and many pieces of carved woodwork.
Divers from the Royal Swedish navy set to
work to hollow out tunnels in the mud under
the wreck and, finally, last year, huge steel
cables were passed through them and the
Wasa was lifted up from its three-centuries-old
bed and dragged some distance towards the
shore. The old hulk withstood the operation
which was repeated 16 times, until the ship
had been moved 330 feet nearer land and
from a depth of I 00 feet to only 45 feet under
the surface. Specialists are now working out
the last stage of the recovery operations.
^^W
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
LION'S HEAD carved In wood (opposite page)
once ornamented the bowsprit of the Wasa,
a 17th-century Swedish man-of-war. Along
with carved figures of tritons, warriors and
mermaids, it was recovered from the mud of
Stockholm harbour, where the Wasa capsized
and sank in. 1628. Left, artist's Impression of
the Wasa being lifted by two salvage pontoons
which ¡n a series of operations dragged it Into
shallower water. Work was made more diffi¬
cult because available pontoons were half the
length (80 feet) of the sunken vessel. Illustra¬
tions below show different aspects of the reco¬
very operations. Diagram on right shows
position of hulk on sea bed. Divers cleared
passages through the mud beneath the keel
with water spraying jets (left), the mud thus
loosened being carried away by suction tubes.
Photos and drawings taken from Woso, by E. Clauson and
A. Franzen, © Nordiska Uppslagsböcker, Stockholm
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
QUALUNG TO BATHYSCAPH
DIVING SAUCER, seen here resting on the ocean
bed, might, well be called the helicopter of the
deepit is light, extremely man and,
down to depths of 1,000, ft. can " land " anywhere
A cloud of air bubbles rising from his aqualung,
Commandant Cousteau (author of the article on this
page) writes last minute instructions for the crew
of the saucer, which he will hold up to one of the
portholes. This French research vessel, now being
used for undersea exploration, weighs only three
and a half tons and can easily be stowed in the
hold of its mother ship, the research vessel, Calypso
(above left). It accomodates an observer and a
pilot, seen (below right) peering from a porthole
after the saucer's hatch has been clamped down.
Photos © Les Requins Associés, Paris
' 1""~«&B»»fc,
by
Jacques-Yves Cousteau
u nul our day, the oceans have
always raised huge barriers to
man's curiosity and understanding. Enormous distances
and stormy weather made early navigation uncertain
and perilous. For the diver the sea was a hostile environ¬
ment which discouraged or limited his daring. And even
the fisherman, who draws his food from the deep, is still
compelled to grope blindly the only hunter in the world
who does not see or who does not know his quarry.
Finally, the oceanographer still lowers his instruments
more or less haphazardly, rather like an explorer setting
out to discover a new continent with modern equipment,
but with his eyes blindfolded.
Seeing under water, in order to be better able to under¬
stand and interpret what we are doing, will be an obvious
necessity tomorrow. Only yesterday, it was an impos¬
sibility; today, it represents a conquest which, while barely
begun by self-contained divers, has just been completed
with the historic descent of the bathyscaph Trieste.
It is now possible for us to descend, to observe and to
take action at any depth.
From the surface to a depth of 40 metres, there are
fifteen million cubic kilometres awaiting the self-
Commandant Jacques-Yves Cousteau, world famous for his
Calypso undersea expeditions, is co-inventor of the Aqua-Lung,
"the passport to inner space," and director of the Océanographie
Museum at Monaco. He is president of the World Underwater
Confederation.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
UNDERSEA CONQUEST (Continued)
contained diver. This is the sea's most living layer the
one that washes the coasts, the one where nearly all the
plant life of the oceans is produced by photosynthesis.
Life here obeys the alternation of day and night, it follows
the rhythm of the seasons. At sunset, hosts of animals
rise from depths as far as 600 metres down to come close
to the surface and feed on microscopic algae or wage
silent combats. At dawn, all these intruders, fearing light
for various reasons, disappear back into zones reached
only by a dim glow.
Most of the time, sea water is clear. In the open sea,
it is not unusual to find underwater visibility of more
than 60 metres. There, sight is a vital and perhaps a
predominant sense. The diver, equipped with a mask,
can enjoy sight on equal terms with the fish. He feels
reassured and at ease; often, he even feels daring.
Crystal waters turn milky
when the sea is in bloom
The crystal of the ocean waters turns milky in .the spring
when the sea is in bloom. Along coasts battered by
breakers and washed by tides, water is often rather
clear. But near harbours and estuaries, countless particles
in suspension diffuse the light and at times divers cannot
even see a hand in front of them. In these troubled
waters filled with alluvial material or small grains of sand,
many micro-organisms die because of their vulnerability
to such conditions. Certain algae and most corals cannot
survive here. But fish sometimes teem in such waters,
either because of fear or hunger. Their eyes are of no
use in such "foggy" conditions but other senses take over:
for example, there is the sense which enables them to
interpret the slightest pressure wave and tells them all
that is going on in the fog.
In the "sunny layer," divers equipped with breathing
apparatus can stay down for an average of twenty minutes
and enjoy considerable security and freedom of movement.
Diving to a depth of forty metres, is becoming so simple
that it is no longer an affair for professionals alone. It
is a great deal easier to teach diving to a geologist than
to teach geology to a diver!
Milne Edwards was the first man to dive with a helmet
and make observations of interest to marine zoology.
Later, Pierre Drach pioneered scientific research with free-
diving apparatus. Under his leadership, the divers of
the Calypso methodically gathered harvests in the Red
Sea in 1951. In Germany, Hans Hass inspired university
men to become divers. In the United States, the Woods
Hole Océanographie Institution trained an underwater
photography, and exploration team; at the Scripps
Institute in California, young scientists dived to dis¬
cover new species, geologists observed and filmed the
phenomenon of cascading, measured the resistance of
sediments on the spot and studied an underwater canyon.
In the Mediterranean, underwater archeology was born.
Applied to the hunt for oil, geological prospecting has
made use of self-contained divers whether in the Persian
Gulf or the Gulf of Mexico. Diving has rapidly become an
indispensable tool for the scientific exploration of the sea;
its use is already being extended to polar expeditions.
Let us end with a comparison: on land, in our own
element, it can be said that the volume of space actually
inhabited is that of a layer going from the ground to
the tops of the highest trees. That adds up to about
four million cubic kilometreshardly more than a quarter
of that upper layer of the sea accessible to divers!
Below 40 metres, light seems to come from all sides:
there are no longer any shadows. When you look up to
the surface, you can no longer make out the reassuring
gleam of the sun. Self-contained divers breathing air
begin to feel the first attacks of "depth drunkeness"in
other words, nitrogen poisoningwhich threatens their
safety by dulling their instinct for survival... pressure,
shadows and cold underscore the hostility of the marine
world to man. Around 300 metres, in the visible part of
the spectrum, there is only a pale light, sufficient to
30
make out objects a short ' distance away once your eyes
have become accustomed to the darkness. Beyond that
it is practically night.
The "twilight zone" of eighty million cubic kilometres
includes all of those provinces of the sea known as the
continental shelf. Often, it infringes upon the steep slopes
of the talus. This extremely rich zone is still not very
well known even though it is the most widely used area for
deep-sea fishing. The continental shelf represents 8 %
of the surface of the sea; that is, an area slightly smaller
than Asia.
Self-contained diving apparatus has enabled us to enter
the twilight layer: breathing air, Italian divers have
managed to reach a depth of 120 metres for a few seconds.
With a mixture of helium and oxygen, an Englishman
has gone down to 165 metres. But these forays must be
classed as isolated feats and a few seconds at such a
depth must be paid for with hours of decompression
under medical supervision. Between 40 and 300 metres,
the explorer must protect himself with a rigid shell;
either a sphere hanging from a cable or, even better,
small free-moving submarines.
The French Office Française de Recherches Sous-
marines (O.F.R.S.) and the research ship Calypso have
just successfully put into service such a submarine at
depths down to 300 metres. Its flattened shape has earned
it the title of "diving saucer." The saucer only weighs
three-and-a-half tons, it is easily stowed in the .hold of
a ship 40 metres long, and it accomodates two persons, a
pilot and an observer. It can remain submerged more
than twelve hours and it has enough electrical energy
to run six hours under normal conditions. Its speed is
modest (3 kilometres an hour) but adequate for ex¬
ploration. It is propelled by hydrojets and the shape of its
hull was designed for extreme maneuverability. It is
equipped with a gyro-compass, sounding apparatus in
three directions, a radio-telephone, a tape recorder,
cameras to take still and motion-pictures, and a "hydraulic
hand" to take samples.
Strange attacks of dizziness on
the brink of a submarine gulf
Practically speaking, the saucer is the equivalent in
the twilight layer to self-contained diving apparatus
in the sunny layer. After sixteen test and training
dives off the West Indies, the Cape Verde Islands and
Corsica, the first saucer immediately began its scientific
career. Professor Edgerton of the Massachusetts Institute
of Technology and Professor Pérès of the Faculty of Aix-
Marseilles in France went down to make observations,
and scientists from many countries will follow in their
wake beginning this summer. In the very near future, the
twilight layer will be invaded by a number of submarines
of the "'diving saucer" class.
When, aboard a diving saucer, you reach the edge of
the continental shelf, you are struck by the abruptness
with which the floor of the sea suddenly falls away.
Under the bright gleam of your searchlights, the bottom
disappears into the blue. You have to reason with yourself
to fight off a feeling of dizziness. Then you put your
bow down, on occasions as much as 30 or 35 degrees, to
follow the slope downwards. Its surface is often scarred
by underwater canyons, abrupt and extremely narrow,
which sometimes have steps cut into their walls like giant
staircases. Over such terrain, the best echo sounders in
the world are unable to transcribe what you see through
the portholes of a submarine designed for exploration.
But, at 300 metres, you must stop and turn the job to a
craft which does not yet exist. However, the two bathy¬
scaphs conceived by Professor Piccardthe F.N.R.S. III
and the Italian "Trieste," (later acquired and transformed
by the U.S. Navy)are capable of descents to depths of
4,000 metres just as if they were lifts without any cables.
Twice, I was able to go down in a bathyscaph with
Commandant Houot in the Toulon canyon. Sometimes
broken up into tormented shapes, sometimes covered with
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
French Navy and National Geographic Magazine
I Les Requins Associés, Paris
SHADOWY MASS in the water (above)
is the hull of the French Navy's bathyscaph
F.N.R.S. 3, built seven years ago according
to the design of Professor Piccard, creator
of the bathyscaph Trieste. Ghostly looking
web-footed figure is one of a team of
aqualung divers which carries out safety
check before vessel plunges to the depths.
When bathyscaph wishes to return to
surface ballast is dropped by electroma¬
gnets activated from inside the hull.
Divers doublecheck that locks on electro¬
magnets have all been removed. If even one
failed to work bathyscaph crew would be
trapped below the surface. Left, sub¬
marine "scooter." Powered by an electric
motor, it can propel an aqualung diver for
two hours at a speed of three knots.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
UNDERSEA CONQUEST (Continued)
Drawing by Barney M. Reid © Navy League of the United States, I960
RECORD PLUNGE into the ocean depths was made on January 23, 1960 by the bathyscaph "Trieste"
which went down seven miles below the surface of the Pacific in the Marianas Islands, into the
deepest trench so far known to man. Locked in a windowed gondola, 6 1/2 feet in diameter, the
crew of two looked out on a scene of mysterious life none had ever witnessed before.
mud, these "pre-continents" plunge sharply down toward
the flat and uninteresting stretches of the seabed.
The great ocean basins, occasionally pierced by isolated
rocky peaks, volcanoes or even mountain ranges, are
mainly huge sedimentary plains. This zone, probably rather
monotonous in appearance, is found at depths of between
3,500 and 6,000 metres. It alone accounts for 67 % of the
total area of the seas and the oceans.
Earlier, I defined the boundaries of the "medium
depths" as 300 and 4,000 metres. While the upper limit
corresponds clearly to a physical and geological, dis¬
continuity, the lower limit, on the contrary, is dictated
only by our present-day technical possibilities.
So far, the "medium depths" have been penetrated
about sixty times by the F.N.R.S. III and the "Trieste,"
two bathyscaphs based upon the principle of a large
float filled with petrol to give buoyancy to a heavy steel
nacelle. These heavy, delicate and not very mobile devices
are the glorious pioneers of deep-water exploration.
But their principle goes back to pre-war days, then-
construction was considerably delayed and, in fact, they
were obsolete as soon as they were born.
Today, we can and we should be able to get along
without any float at all down to a depth of 4,000 metres.
Techniques of building hollow structures have made such
progress that small submarines are to be built which
will resist pressures of 400 atmospheres with an acceptable
safety coefficient, but still with sufficient buoyancy.
The "Aluminaut" project in the United States is taking
advantage of this technical progress by using light alloys.
With three men on board and a full range of scientific
apparatus, the "Aluminaut" will be able to cruise the
sea several thousand metres down and will be small
enough to be transported aboard a medium-sized océano¬
graphie vessel.
In France, the O.F.R.S. is studying a project for an even
more maneuverable submarine, in which extensive use
is made of the most recent discoveries in plastics. This
technical research has been made easier by the cal¬
culations of a safety co-efficient which becomes lower and
lower as operational pressures rises higher and higher
(this is quite logical because relative changes in pressure
caused by an accidental change in depth are smaller for
32
a submarine designed to operate at 4,000 metres than for
one built for 400 metres.
Until the "Aluminaut" or similar devices go into
service the bathyscaphs have opened new vistas in our
knowledge of the "medium depths." The scientific balance
sheet of the F.N.R.S. 3 is firmly on the credit side.
Among the numerous observations made through its thick
plexiglass portholes, two general conclusions have been
brought out: in the open sea, the density of plankton
certainly does not decrease regularly with an increase in
depth (it is not at all rare to run through an extremely
dense layer of plankton at 1,000 metres); and, secondly,
the bottom of the sea, covered most of the time with thick
layers of sediments, is the scene of intense underground
life. There is hardly a square, yard without holes small,
medium-sized or large and these holes are dens whose
inhabitants are still very much of a mystery to us.
The great ocean trenches (the Mariannas, the Philip¬
pines, Tonga, Porto Rico, etc.) are narrow furrows, located
mainly in the Pacific. Their realm, properly speaking,
can be said to begin at a depth of 6,000 metres and
represents only 2 % of the total area of the sea. But they
are critical spots on the earth's crust where it is either
very thin or the scene of intense seismic activity. The
systematic study of these deep trenches is of . such great
interest that "superbathyscaphs" are on drawing-boards
or even under construction.
These superbathyscaphs will be large vessels with
enormous floats containing petrol or other light sub¬
stances, and having spherical hulls with room for a large
amount of scientific apparatus. They will have enough
power for a satisfactory range and cruising speed. The
vast adjacent provinces between 4,000 and 6,000 metres,
which the submarines of the "Aluminaut" type will be
unable to probe, will be the hunting grounds of the
superbathyscaphs.
The "Trieste," equipped with a special spherical nacelle,
was able to descend into the bottom of the Marianna
Trench, thus conquering the "Anti-Everest." It was a
landmark in the history of oceanography, but though
remarkable, this performance was really something of a
special exploit. The "Trieste" is actually very poorly
adapted to the path which it has opened to its successors,
the superbathyscaphs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
BEGINNINGS OF UNDERWATER PHOTOGRAPHY. The first underwater photographs go back to the end
of the 19th century. Amongst the earliest is this one by Professor Louis Boutan, of the Museum of
Natural History in Paris, taken in 1898 and captioned: "The team's legssnapshotthe men are immersed
in water just up to the waist." Professor Boutan was already using magnesium flares for these shots.
LT
PHOTOG. SOUS-MARINE 1898
par LOUIS BOUTAN
Tirée par PIERRE PETIT, Phot.
17-19, Place Cadet, PARIS
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Ballet
of the
At first sight, choreography and oceanography seem literally oceans apart. But are
they ! For the oceanographer, ophiurians are a group of marine animals somewhat
similar to starfish, but with long, slender brittle arms. These creatures travel
along the seabed from the coastal waters to the ocean depths. But one scientist-
photographer, Jean-Marie Baufle, of the Museum of Natural History in Paris, caught
the ophurians in a graceful ballet. He entitled the different movements (I) Entry of
the "première ballerina". (2)' First steps. (3) Invitation to the Waltz. (4) Dance.
o Photos © J.M. Baufle, Paris
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
DANGER!
500 mph tidal
wave arriving
On May 21, Chile began to shake and shudder in
the grip of major earthquake shocks which con¬
tinued for weeks afterwards accompanied by volca¬
nic eruptions and tidal waves. Chile's catastrophe
soon reverbrated across the Pacific. Seismic loaves
created by the upthrusting of the sea bed went
racing across the ocean at more than 500 m.p.h In
mid-ocean the movement was slight, but as the
waves reached other Pacific coasts, they came
crashing in with a force that varied according to
the form of a coastline and the shape of a shore. In
some placesAlaska, Fiji, Tahitithey merely
caused tide fluctuations. In Japan the onrush of sea
caused a major disaster and overall tidal wave
damage in the Pacific ran into many millions of
dollars. In this article, Bernard Saint-Guily, of the
Paris Museum of Natural History, describes different
kinds of tidal waves and how they are caused.
T
iDAL waves are among the most terrifying of
-^^- the natural phenomena that occur on our
planet. An abnormal expansion of the surface of the sea
in the form of a single wave or several successive ones,
they are produced either by earthquakes or volcanic erup¬
tions or again by storms, cyclones or typhoons. They
are in no way related to the normal tides caused by the
attraction of the moon and sun; their effects simply super¬
impose themselves on those of the tidal movements.
Thus, the name they have been given in English for
example, is hardly apposite. Nowadays scientists tend
to use the Japanese word tsunami; its advantage lies in its
precise etymological meaning which describes specifically
the effect rather than the cause of the phenomenon;
tsunami comes from tsu (port or bay) and nami (wave).
The frequency and violence of tidal waves in Japan have
given the word used to describe them very real meaning
in everyday language; one reflecting actual experience for
it is in the ports and bays that tidal waves produce their
most terrible effects.
It is easy to conceive how mechanical causes move¬
ments or vibrations in a part of the ocean bed or in a
coastal zone create waves on the surface of the sea.
These waves, like the movements which create them, pro¬
duce only a feeble effect in the open sea and are hardly
felt by ships sailing there. Propagated far away, they cross
oceans quite rapidly. Their speed, proportional to the
square root of the ocean depth, actually reaches nearly
500 m.p.h. when they are travelling above depths of
around 13,000 feet. The increase in their amplitude and
form when they reach the shallower coastal waters depend
on the outline of the coast and relief of the seabed.
As it reaches the coast a tidal wave causes either a
sudden withdrawal of the sea (negative wave) or an inva¬
sion of the land by the sea (positive wave). The first
positive wave, however, is generally of medium size; it is
followed by a withdrawel of the sea and then by a second
invading wave which does the most damage.
Ships swept over city walls
On October 28, 1746, the earthquake which utterly des¬
troyed the Peruvian city of Lima was accompanied
by a tidal wave which struck the port of Callao.
Survivors described it as follows:
"'After the earthquake, which destroyed all the houses
in the port, the sea receded, although no one could see
how far it went. Soon it came in again, making a terri¬
fying noise and forming an enormous wave which rose
high into the air and came crashing down on the ram¬
parts, carrying all before it. There were 23 ships in the
port and most of them were smashed and sunk; the larg¬
est, four in number, were lifted by the wave, swept over
the city walls and carried into the countryside behind.
36
by Bernard Saint-Guily
The sea receded and came in again several times; out
of 4,900 inhabitants, only 200 managed to escape".
The collapse of cliffs, the fall of great masses of
rock into the sea, landslides and submarine eruptions
can all cause tidal waves. During the mighty eruption
of Krakatoa, in the Sunda Strait, on August 27, 1883, the
destruction of most of this volcanic island and the explo¬
sions that occurred when the molten lava and the volca¬
nic gases came into contact with the sea created a terrible
tidal wave which drowned 36,000 persons at Merak and
Telok-Betang. The disastrous effects of this tidal wave
were limited to the Sunda Strait but the sea movements
it caused were recorded on tide gauges around the world.
In both cause and effect, tidal waves of meteorological
origin, or "storm surges" as they are called, differ greatly
from those of seismic origin. They are unusually high
rises in the level of the sea due to violent winds which
accompany storms, cyclones and areas of low atmospheric
pressure as they move close to coastlines. These storm
surges behave in a much more complicated way than the
seismic tidal waves. They do not necessarily cause the
sea to recede and, generally speaking, take the form of
positive waves whose irregular movements are superim¬
posed on the normal rise and fall of the tides.
Bengal wave killed 215,000
Storm waves of this kind are frequent on the coasts of
Bengal. On these low-lying, flat coasts with their
dense populations the storm surges sometimes cause
veritable cataclysms. The death roll from the 1876 storm
wave was estimated at 215,000.
The storm surges which occur in the North Sea seem
almost tame by comparison. But recent flooding in the
Netherlands and in Great Britain has shown that Euro¬
pean coastlines can still be threatened by such calamities.
The tidal waves which hit these countries on January 31,
1953, were caused by an atmospheric depression which
came from the south of Iceland with 100 mph winds.
Thanks to the large number of permanent observation
stations in this area it was possible to carry out a great
deal of study and research, much of it through the Inter¬
national Union of Geodesy and Geophysics.
Will it be possible to predict -tidal waves in the near
future? Probably so in the case of storm surges. But
tsunami of seismic origin are more difficult. Yet all that
is required is the ability to recognize from among the many
seismic disturbances, those which are capable of causing
tidal waves. Earthquakes are recorded in advance of tidal
waves since seismic shocks travel through the earth with
a speed of at least ten times that of the liquid waves which
make up the tsunami. In any case, the forecasting of
tidal waves will only become possible through patient
research and regular observation all around the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
Atlas Photo, Paris
THE WAVE-MYSTERY
OF D-DAY 1944
by Ritchie Calder
H UR scientific knowledge of waves
dates back to D-Day, 1944.
True ? or False ? Absurd as it
may seem, it is true. For all those thousands of years
since some unknown, prehistoric ancestor found himself
adrift in a cockleshell on the surface of the sea, men have
been tossed around, battered into nausea, and drowned,
by the action of waves the Argonauts, the Vikings, Colum¬
bus, the Pilgrim Fathers and all the millions of travellers
who have contemplated waves with sea-green distaste.
They knew what waves did; they never knew what
they were.
Then, at the Quebec Conference which decided on the
Normandy Landings, someone asked "How do waves
work?" The answer was important because, remember,
they were going to build artificial harbours and jetties
and lay a pipeline across the English Channel. Rough
or smooth, a huge expeditionary force had to be landed
on a split-second timing.
And nobody knew the answer not the Blue Water Men
of the allied navies nor the scientists. They knew about
tides, of course; Newton had given them the scientific
explanation of the drag of the forces of the Moon's gravity
and their almanacs could give a precise prediction of the
level of the tide at any given point on the Normandy
Coast. But not the waves they were just something that
naval men endured, and their's not to reason why.
So the scientists had to scratch their heads. Apart from
the mechanism of wave formation, there were all sorts of
factors the nature of that funnel, the English Channel;
the configurations of that coast-line on which the waves
would break erratically and even the geology of the sea¬
shore. And on that, a long-haired British professor (who,
even in uniform, would not cut it) recalled how he had
been bathing on that coast after a stormy night and had
noticed that the surf was peaty. Was that relevant? It
was so relevant that a commando raid was immediately
organized to steal ashore and take geological cores of -the
possible landing-places.
Temporary answers were found not all of them, as
events proved, satisfactory, but enough to underline the
need for scientific knotwledge and measurements about a
phenomenon which had more attention from the poets
and the painters than from the scientists.
CONT'D ON PAGE 66
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
In July 1957 began one of the great scientific
co-operation enterprises of our time when the
International Geophysical Year (I.G.Y.) was launched
with the participation of some 70 nations. Though con¬
ceived at first as an 18-month world venture to advance
knowledge of our planet, all the participating countries
unanimously agreed to extend it for another year the
year of International Geographical Co-operation (I.G.C.).
During this period, oceanography and marine research
made tremendous progress. Scientists acquired greater
knowledge of the seas and the oceans, of the history
of the earth, of the life of deep-water creatures, the
forces affecting weather and the geography of the sea
bottom, to name but a few fields.
Now, scientific bodies in all countries have decided
to continue their collaboration, and the Indian Ocean
the least studied stretch of water in the world has been
chosen as the theatre of research operations for the next
four or five years. (See page 19.)
Four Soviet research vessels the Vityaz, the Lomonosov,
the Ob and the Sevastopol are equipped for this work.
The Vityaz, a ship belonging to the Institute of
Oceanology of the Soviet Academy of Sciences, has done
most of her work in the Pacific and Indian Oceans. At
the beginning of the 1958-59 period, she had completed
her twenty-sixth expedition and then, in the following,
months, she made four trips and started on a fifth, her
thirty-first expedition, to the Indian Ocean. This scientific
Odyssey has seen the Vityaz log more than 100,000 miles,
making 600 stops for research.
The processes going on in the ocean are so closely inter¬
woven that they can be understood only through detailed
study of all their aspects. Scientists aboard the Vityaz
are mainly interested in the life story of the ocean, the
pattern of chemical distribution, the circulation of deep
waters, the distribution of deep sea life, the study of
biological processes, examination of seabed deposits by
drilling and acoustic prospecting, rate of sedimentary
deposits, and the geography of the ocean floor.
FROM TROPICAL
WATERS TO
ISLANDS OF ICE
Behind this matter-of-fact list lie some fascinating
objectives. For example, the study of the sedimentary
deposits making up the ocean floor may throw consider¬
able light upon the history of our planet and its seas.
Even today, the prevalent theory on the origin of the
earth's seas holds that they were formed by condensation
of atmospheric vapour which had accumulated during an
earlier and warmer period. Many scientists, though,
believe that the oceans were formed by the spewing out
of water from the Earth's crust by volcanic action.
This agrees with the theory that celestial bodies were
formed by the accumulation of meteoric matter which
later grew hot as the result of radioactivity. If this
theory is correct, it provides a new explanation of why
the sea is salty. Salinity, some scientists maintain, did
not come from an accumulation of salts washed into the
ocean by rivers, but from primary matter expelled from
the earth's crust along with the water.
At any rate, reading the story in deposits on the bed
of the sea should enable us to reconstruct the story of
the earth more accurately than by merely studying its
land surfaces. Remains of micro-organisms found in
.
»
É
p. *
t -
1 1
Ataaùrf» "L^^r »-3ÄÄ»*#^»* .
m¡1
Official Soviet photo Unesco-Bill Simmons
SCIENTIFIC ODYSSEY of the Soviet ocean-going research ship Vityaz (left) has taken it over 100,000 miles, which Included
more than 600 halts for observation and studies. Right, buoys on deck of another Soviet research vessel, the Mikhail Lomonosov
ate used in making detailed maps of the ocean floor. Dropped into sea with a light wire attached, the buoys are then anchored to
the bottom. A flag on top and a radar reflector permit scientists from the ship to make accurate measurements of the sea floor.
Photo was taken last year when vessel docked in New York, where the First International Océanographie Congress was being held.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
these seabed deposits have already given scientists a clear
picture of those changes of climate which occured during
ice ages when hot and cold periods alternated.
The Vityaz worked in both the northern and southern
Pacific, straddling the Equator. Her measurements of
the Pacific's "trenches" showed the greatest depth
11,034 metres in the Marianna depression. Her scientists
also made the noteworthy discovery of swift-moving
currents on the ocean floor and even in certain deep
trenches. In some places, these currents were found to
move at the rate of 7.9 inches a second. On one of her
southern expeditions, the Vityaz linked up with an Ob
expedition to the Antarctic, covering an entire meridian.
Biologists studying the deep trenches of the ocean
found some strange and very ancient forms of life.
Research by the Vityaz and the Danish vessel, the
Galathea, has led to a map showing the distribution of
life on the ocean bed. In deep water, there are only
a few milligrammes per square metre of these microscopic
animals, but the quantity often rises to several kilo¬
grammes per square metre offshore.
Deep-water currents deadly to fish
Then the Vityaz left at the end of 1959 on its latest
expedition to the Indian Ocean. On this trip, she has
covered 30,000 miles with 247 halts for (research work.
A new map of the ocean bed has been plotted and it shows
wide plateaus, isolated mountains, new deep-sea currents
and many forms of animal life unknown to science. In
some parts of the Indian Ocean, scientists found large
deposits of the teeth of extinct species of sharks and
the beaks of squids. Elsewhere, biologists studied the rich
life of coral reefs and, in the western part of the ocean,
they found shoals of tuna and other food fish.
In the Gulf of Aden and the Arabian sea, the Vityaz
concentrated upon certain deep-water currents which are
poor in oxygen and wreak havoc among fish whenever
they rise to the surface. This expedition was accompanied
by three Indian scientists, including the well-known
marine biologist, Prof. Nil. Prasad.
Elsewhere, océanographie research has yielded major
results in the Arctic Basinthat deep-water area of the
Arctic bounded by a continental shelf. Research vessels
are unable to reach this region and the work has been
done mainly by aircraft and by stations established on
drifting ice floes. Both Soviet and American scientists
have worked in this area.
The most extensive study of all has been made of the
Arctic ice pack. Its drift was measured by 100 radio
beacons and 50 automatic meterological stations installed
over a large area. The average rate of general drift has
been found to be about two kilometres a day.
The most outstanding feature of the Arctic Basin is the
presence of old ice in the ice pack. This ice, many years
oía, makes up about 70 % of the total, the remainder
being under two years old. Under the influence of the
wind, the boundaries of the great Arctic ice pack may
shift as much as 600 or 700 kilometres. At all times of
the year, stretches of open water appear in the ice pack
because of the irregularity of its drifting but there are
areas in which open water appears regularly and remains
for long periods.
Large fields of ice, known as "ice islands" are found
within the pack. Some have an area as great as 200-
300 square miles. Since they often have a smooth, flat
surface, these "islands" are convenient sites for research
stations working over long periods.
Research in the Arctic has also told us a great deal
about the bed of this ocean. One discovery was that
of the Lomonosov Range, a chain of underwater mountains
running from the New Siberian Islands to Greenland. The
highest known point in this range is at a depth of 954
metres, but there may be even higher peaks awaiting
discovery elsewhere.
Those are a few of the results which have been gathered
on océanographie expeditions by one country, the Soviet
Union. No one country is able to gather all information
about the ocean. Only the co-ordinatioñ of the efforts
of all countries connected with the sea can arm science
with the information needed to make the sea's wealth
available to all mankind.
Official Soviet photo
LIGHT PENETRATION in sea is being measured from the deck
of the Vityaz with a hydrophotometer. Research by this ship in the
Pacific included measurement of ocean gulfs and discovery of rapidly mo¬
ving currents on the ocean floor and even in certain deep trenches.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
DENIZENS OF THE OCEAN FIGURE PROMINENTLY IN THIS KHMER RELIEF CARVED ON THE BAYON TEMPLE AT ANGKOR THOM IN CAMBODIA.
A t the dawn of civilization, as far
back as the earliest knowledge we
possess of the science of our
ancestors, the ocean '"girdling the earth with Its
endless stream" was looked upon as a circular river
running round the edges of the world like the rim
of a wheel; and to cross it was a homeric adven¬
ture to be attempted only by men of exceptional courage
or lust for gain.
Long before anything of the kind was tried, generation
after generation of traders, had probably for many cen¬
turies been making their way in fragile vessels propelled
by oars, equipped with primitive sails but without
rudders, along the coastal waters of the lands which held
in their interior all the treasures of that age essences,
spices, ivory, gold, silver, gums and precious woods.
Two thousand years B.C. long before the Trojan war
the Phoenicians, pioneers of international trade and
ocean exploration, set up trading posts on the shores of
the Red Sea and the Indian Ocean. In the Persian Gulf
the first lighthouses appeared, served by a priestly caste
responsible for maintaining the fires night and day; these
lighthouses also served as mail offices and information
centres for mariners in those days, collecting all infor¬
mation on routes followed, dangers met with, naviga¬
tional techniques used, coastal topography, and winds
and currents. Soon schools were founded which taught
Henri Rotschi is in charge of the Physical Oceanography
Section of the Institut Français d'Océanie (Noumea, New
Caledonia). He took part in the Capricorn expedition
organized in 1952-53 by the Scripps Institution of Oceano¬
graphy of the University of California. He is also a mem¬
ber of the Physical Oceanography Section of the Comité
National Français de Géodésie et Géophysique. This arti¬
cle was abridged from "Man Discovers the Sea" which
appeared in a special issue of Impact of Science on
Society, on the marine sciences. (Vol X [1960] N° 2.)
40
the art of navigation and of plotting a course from
astronomical observations..
The real cradle of seafaring was the Mediterranean. It
was there that the tremendous adventure started which
led men out on to the high seas, spurred on at first purely
by the desire for gain, but later by the thirst for know¬
ledge for its own sake. The Phoenicians, swarming west¬
wards through the Pillars of Hercules, turned south along
the coast of Africa and north up the coasts of Europe as
far as Britain until the cold, fog, high winds and their
helplessness against the powerful tidal currents, unknown
in the Mediterranean, caused them to turn back once
more to the south.
This small-scale . coastal traffic carried on by traders
more mindful of their profits than of the advancement
of geography was succeeded very soon by the era of long¬
distance ocean exploration started in 330 b.c. by Pytheas
of Marseilles, geographer and astronomer, who sailed
north as far as the Arctic Circle, turning back only when
floating ice barred further progress. He seems to have
sighted Britain, the Shetlands .and Iceland or Norway.
As to the fruits of his voyage, he brought back neither
gold nor silver nor any merchandise, but a first report
on the Arctic approaches and a precise astronomical
explanation of the Midnight Sun, entitling him to rank
as the first oceanographer. He it was, too, who first used
astronomical calculations to plot the position of fixed
points.
The great ocean journeys of exploration captured the
imagination of the learned throughout the Mediterranean
and encouraged them to exercise their minds on all the
aspects of geography perceptible by man in their day.
Pythagoras deduced the spheroid form of the earth from
the accounts of mariners and together with Herodotus,
Aristotle, Hipparchus and Ptolemaeus, laid the founda¬
tions of what was later to become the science of oceano¬
graphy as we know it today. Soundings were taken,
charts plotted and the positions of harbours determined;
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
Pathfinders of yesterday and today
THE OLD MEN
(& the new ones)
OF THE SEA
by tlenri Rotschi
Pierre Pittet. Geneva
distances traversed were calculated from the stars; and
currents, winds and tides ceased to be terrifying mani¬
festations of the wrath of heaven and became aids which
men had learned to use to extend the ocean routes
carrying the flow of trade and serving in turn as a vehicle
for armies, ideas and wealth.
The greatest, strongest and most influential countries
were those with the most and the largest harbours,
equipped with the best facilities, and situated in the best
places to attract the steady flow of trade which is the
mainspring of all human activities; and the approaches
to these ports were studded with carefully tended lights
and guiding marks. Power came from the sea, by the
sea, and did not exist apart from the sea.
The Pax Romana changed all this: conquest on land
was preferred to ocean adventure, and the old primitive
terrors and superstitious fears reasserted their hold over
the heirs of the first explorers.
Those who kept the sacred fire alight were the Vikings
and the Arabs. The Arabs gave the West the hinged
rudder, the compass and the astrolabe, and once these
technical improvements were in use the way was opened
to long-distance navigation. Nevertheless it was without
their help that the Vikings, in open wooden ships with
a single square sail, explored the North Sea, reached
Gaul and southern Britain and then discovered in succes¬
sion the west coasts of the British Isles, Iceland, and
Greenland, to land finally in America.
A few centuries later Prince Henry the Navigator sent
forth his caravels to open the route to the lands rich in
Drawings taken from " Man and the Underwater World ", by Pierre de Latil and Jean Rivoire.
«5-
(a) Greek diver of the 4th cent.
B.C., as described by Aristotle.
(b) Breathing tube and underwater
mask (design, Leonardo da Vinci)
(c) "Articulated diving suit" invent¬
ed by William Carrey, in 1802. i
(d) Underwater fishing device of
Le Batteaux, a Frenchman, 1853.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
PATHFINDERS OF THE SEA (Cont'd)
OCEANOGRAPHER PRINCE
Oceanography really came into being in 1 872 during the research
voyage of the British corvette H.M.S. Challenger which during
three and a half years sailed and steamed nearly 70,000 nautical
miles around the globe. A few years later, in 1885, Prince
Albert I of Monaco began to equip vessels for océanographie
work. Right, one of these ships, the Princess Alice II dwarfed
by the immensity of a fjord in Spitzbergen at the beginning
of this century. Below, Prince Albert (in white, with tropical
helmet) supervises the lowering of a triangular shaped fish
trap which he devised and used on his expeditions. The Prince
founded the Océanographie Institute in Paris, and in 1910
created the now famous Océanographie Museum in Monaco.
Photos Océanographie Museum. Mon;
spices and gold, and less than 100 years after that Vasco
da Gama reached India. This gradual eastward thrust
from the western countries was balanced by the more or
less contemporaneous irruption into the Pacific of the
Polynesians, trusting their lives to frail outrigger canoes
and to their knowledge of the stars.
After that, once Christopher Columbus had shown the
way to the Americas, there was a rush in search of new
and hitherto unknown direct routes to Asia and in quest
of the last continent still awaiting discovery, Antarctica,
credited in the contemporary imagination with far more
amenities than in fact it possesses. Balboa then discov¬
ered the Pacific; Magellan circumnavigated the world
and made the first soundings of the ocean deeps, while
Cook found a south polar ocean girdling the globe instead
of the Antarctic continent he had expected, and traversed
the Pacific from north to south and east to west. After
him came Bougainville and a host of others, of whom
many were sealers and whalers.
Finally came the search for the North-West Passage,
where the great names are Davis, Hudson, Barents and
Bering.
At the dawn of the nineteenth century the terrestrial
globe or most of it was well known. All that remained
to be done was to discover a few islands lost in the vast-
ness of the ocean and to explore the Poles. But still
nothing was known of the ocean deeps or of the nature
or conformation of the bottom of the sea.
After the four thousand years and more since the first
man, driven by curiosity and the lust for gain, took to
the sea, how did things stand? In his Physical geography
of the sea, published in 1855, Lieutenant Maury of the
American Navy epitomized the centuries' accumulated
lore on winds and currents which he had been able to
collect from the seafarers of all nations. By collating
all the material given him, Maury was able to issue charts
which enabled sea captains to change the routes of the
long ocean passages and cut weeks off the sailing time,
say, to Australia or round the Horn. These were the first
Sailing directions, to this day the bedside book of every
ship's captain and every navigating officer; they contain
all that is known of the physical geography of the seas,
coastal approaches, winds, currents and tides, hazards
and seamarks; and without them many a ship would be
lost by seeking to approach inhospitable coasts.
Obviously, much information had been put on paper
before this by ships' captains anxious to benefit by the
lessons of experience. Unhappily, all these navigational
aids, being, ipso facto, the keys to wealth and power, were
the carefully guarded secrets of shipowners and masters;
The most ancient reference works which have come
down to us are the portolani and peripli, and from them
we can form some idea of the technical knowledge of
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
h
mariners in the ancient world. The portolani were
charts showing landing places on the Mediterranean
coasts and were used in conjunction with the sailing
directions then in force; the peripli, on the other hand,
supplied all necessary details of coastlines, havens and
supply facilities.
Next came more specifically marine charts. The earli¬
est still extant date from the end of the sixteenth
century and are confined almost entirely to the waters
of Western Europe and the East Atlantic; but little by
little geographical knowledge increased with a corres¬
ponding improvement in the accuracy and coverage of
the charts publicly available. However, by far the best
charts were those produced by the private companies
such as the Compagnie des Indes (East India Company)
which maintained their own hydrographers and had
remarkable collections of charts which were among their
most jealously guarded professional secrets.
It was thanks to Maury's initiative that the advantages
of pooling navigational knowledge became so obvious that
the way to the production of the present-day sailing
directions and accurate charts was abruptly opened.
But the sea is a very big subject and has other physical
aspects which have attracted scientific interest. In the
seventeenth century Varenius published a Geography of
the lands and seas of the earth, epitomizing the whole
contemporary corpus of astronomical and meteorological
knowledge and giving the first scientific description of the
periodical phenomena which took place in the sea and
which, incidentally, had already attracted the boundless
curiosity of Leonardo da Vinci. Next, the fast-growing
science of mathematics turned its attention to everything
that could be brought within its sphere of reference, with
Newton and Laplace proffering the first scientific expla¬
nation of the tides, and Bernoulli! paving the way for the
analysis of the motions of fluids by the future science of
hydrodynamics. Concurrently great interest developed
in everything relating to the sea. Zoology embarked on
the description of marine animals, concurrently with the
appearance of the first marine zoological collections, while
geographers mapped out the ocean bed.
When the nineteenth century opened, scientists, econo¬
mists, and politicians alike the thinkers and the doers
had grasped the importance of the part played by the sea
and everything connected with it in all human activities.
Now men were no longer concerned to find new routes
or new continents, to seek out new gold-mines or alter¬
native sources of consumer goods, but only to extend their
hold on a watery universe which they could not yet
control and which only detailed knowledge, still complet¬
ely lacking, would enable them to use for their own ends.
Consciousness of ignorance in the matter gradually
increased, with the result that the great maritime nations
began to dispatch scientific expeditions to every corner
of the seas, following the example of the British
Challenger, the world's first, océanographie ship to
embark on a four-year course of ocean research. Thus
oceanography was born, and the sea came into its own
as a field of scientific study. .
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
PATHFIN DERS OF THE SEA (Continue,ti d)
What we have is oceanography generally, that is, the
whole range of specialized "marine" sciences dynamics,
dealing with horizontal and vertical circulation and, per¬
manent or temporary, periodic or aperiodic water move¬
ments; physics, which is concerned with the sea's optical,
acoustic, electric and similar properties; chemistry,
dealing with the nature and properties of sea-water and
variations in those properties having associations with
dynamic or biological phenomena; biology, studying the
nature of the living creatures in the sea and the bionomy
or biological cycle of the several species; and physical
geography, geology and geophysics which are concerned
with the morphology of coasts and the ocean bed, and
the nature of the sediments and substrata appertaining
thereto.
Oceanography really came into being during the voyage
of the Challenger the culmination of all the voyages for
gain or knowledge, which from Columbus and Magellan
downwards had gradually lifted the veil of ignorance and
superstition hiding the sea. The Challenger was a four-
masted corvette with auxiliary engines,, and her cruise
lasted four years. Under the guidance of Britain's most
eminent scientists, research, was carried out in every
branch of marine science, and an amazing range and
quantity of samples and specimens of every kind, as well
as observations and measurements, was brought back to
Edinburgh.
The study, analysis and description of these data
yielded the material for 40 volumes which, for many years
after their publication, ranked as the standard work on
oceanography, opening up all the main departments of
oceanographical knowledge, more particularly with
regard to the morphology and geology of the ocean bed
and the physics and chemistry of the sea. These
chapters were subsequently expanded, and will, it is
hoped, be completed as the result of present and future
research.
Once the example had been given, it merely remained
to follow it, and up to tne second world war, similar
cruises were frequently undertaken by German, French,
American, Russian and Scandinavian scientific expedi-
tions.The deep water areas were sought out and deeps
(Puerto Rico, Mindanao, Japan, Mariana, Tonga-Kerma-
dec, etc.) discovered, descending to 8,000 or 10,000 metres.
Live species were collected at ever greater depths; the
main features of the sea-floor relief began to be per¬
ceived, and observed data on the nature of the marine
sediments gradually accumulated.
New tools to plumb the deep
As the methods for measuring physical and chemical
properties, at sea and in the laboratory alike, improv¬
ed, so did knowledge of the physics and chemistry of
the sea become more accurate. Certain physical properties,
such as density and specific heat, were quickly deter¬
mined, whereas others, such as viscosity and transparency
governed by the dynamics of water in motion, presented
a more stubborn problem. Towards 1880 an accurate
method of determining the composition of sea-water was
discovered, and 20 years later its relative invariability
was established. This is one of the most important facts
in physical oceanography, since most of the salinity
analyses so far published are based on the constant rela¬
tion of salinity to the chlorine content.
Next, studies were carried out on the influence of
mineral salts, found in low concentrations in the upper
levels of the sea, in the first phases of the nutritional
cycle, and on the part they play precisely analogous to
that of soil fertilizers in the photosynthesis of marine
algae. The biologists, initially, concentrated almost
entirely on descriptions of the vast numbers of species
peopling the sea, but progressively, as more taxonomic
categories came to be clearly . established and their
structure thoroughly determined, they shifted their
attention to the complex interrelations of the different
organisms with one another and with their environment.
At last the dynamics of the sea began to be intelligible;
not only did direct study of the major ocean currents
make it possible to plot their course and evaluate their
importance but the application to the study of the sea
of fluid mechanics and of the theories worked out for
atmospheric circulation provided a solid mathematical
basis for our knowledge of the movements of water
masses; while the description of surface and internal
waves and of tides was facilitated by the development of
hydrodynamics.
Such developments in research and the corresponding
increase in the sum of knowledge were only possible as
a result of the great improvements achieved in ocean
observation and sampling techniques. Apart from the
innovation of steam propulsion, the most spectacular
progress has unquestionably been in deep-sounding
methods which have progressed from the hand-operated
deep-sea lead, and mechanical sounders with line and
weight, to the modern continuous echo-sounder which
does in a few seconds what would have taken, with the
old mechanical sounder, several hours. To begin with,
samples of ooze were taken with grabs or bottom sam¬
plers of only moderate efficiency. With the advent of
the core sampler, however, there was steady improvement
until sediment cores several metres in length could be
secured.
Water temperatures at different depths were measured
with a degree of accuracy approaching a hundredth of a
Centigrade degree, using the so-called "reversing" ther¬
mometer specially designed for the purpose. Current
meters of many types, both direct-reading and recording,
were devised for fixed-point current measurement at dif¬
ferent depths, while on the biological side dredges were
designed for collecting organisms living at the bottom of
the sea, as well as various types of sieve net for studying
the distribution of microscopic animal life at all depths.
Special sieve nets were also invented for studying the
microscopic algae of the phytoplankton.
The second world war caused gigantic strides to be .
taken in oceanography. For tactical purposes, it became
essential to know more about the physical properties of
the sea and, in particular, its acoustics, sonic and ultra¬
sonic detection methods having become of prime impor¬
tance with the appearance of instruments such as Asdic,
or directional beam ultrasonic range-finders. As the
speed of sound transmission in water varies with the
latter's density i.e., with its temperature and salinity,
the former being much the most important at the
shallow depths at which submarines operate the rapid
measurement of the continuous variations of temperature
at different depths became a necessity. The result was
the invention of the bathythermograph, which plots the
variations down to 300 metres on a smoked glass plate.
After the war, as sonar continued to improve with
steadily narrower and more accurate directional beams,
so did the precision of the echo-recording equipment
increase; the error for depths of over 5,000 metres is now
less than one metre. Core samplers were completely trans¬
formed, so that it is now possible to extract cores 20 metres
in length and thus be able to study sediments deposited
about 150 million years ago, while seismic refraction
methods afforded precise measurements of the thickness
of sediments.
WALKING THE PLANK-1960. Not a victim of modern
pirates about to take the fatal plunge, but a scientist at
sea supervising the lowering of a 50 gallon water sampler
from the U.S. research vessel Crawford of the Woods Hole
Océanographie Institution. Samples from various depths
collected during the International Geophysical Year have
been analysed and tested in U.S. and European universities.
© R-E. Baylor. Woods Hole, U.S.A.
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
Magnetic and gravimetric studies carried out at sea
established a connexion between certain characteristics
of the submarine topography and variations in the
magnetic field, and made it possible to detect petroleum
deposits; improved equipment for taking specimens allows
of accurate work at any selected intermediate depth;
buoys transmitting radio signals opened the way to the
direct and widespread study of both surface and deep
ocean currents; and radioactive tracers offered new
methods for studying sediment dispersal and for eva¬
luating the amount of living matter produced in the
upper levels of the sea.
The enlistment of electronics for research at sea made
it possible not only to fix the positions of research vessels
more accurately by radio navigation, but also to determine
many variables on the spot, besides providing devices for
the continuous measurement of variations in temperature
and salinity according to depth; another apparatus
devised was a direct-reading current meter for use by
ships under way. In a word, oceanography has become
the business of highly specialized scientists, drawn from
disciplines as different as geophysics and chemistry, elec¬
tronics and pure mathematics; and research at sea has
become a team job, with ¡the effectiveness of each one's
work dependent on the backing of the team as a whole.
For the fact is that any advance in one direction inci¬
dentally increases the general sum of knowledge, since
in the sea the tiniest particle settling on the ooze in the
profoundest deep is the endproduct of a vast complex of
phenomena of which some at least have no direct
connexion either with submarine geology or with sedi¬
mentation.
Oceanographers without knowing it
Marinees for many centuries were oceanographers
without knowing it. While oceanography, pre-emi¬
nently a "high-cost" science with an influence on
innumerable human activities, has never received the
publicity with which other examples of man's spirit of dis¬
covery have been hailed, the fact remains that all those
with any degree of responsibility for the future course of
the world's economy are becoming daily more aware of the
part which the sea must play in the relatively near future.
In view of the rapid and almost universal rise in
standards of living and the consequent readily calculable
increase in requirements in industrial raw materials and
energy, it is clear that the natural resources of the
earth will not long be able to meet the enhanced demand
for animal and vegetable proteins, coal, petroleum and
metals.
It follows that the sea with its inexhaustible reserves
will be the first rextra-terrestrial" source of these
products on which we shall have to draw, long before the
moon or some planet or other is in a position to supply
them in appreciable quantities. Fisheries will expand
and be carried on more scientifically; large quantities of
protein will probably be extracted from plankton, and
"aquiculture" will be developed in suitable areas, with
methodically worked "fields" of algae yielding food and
industrial raw materials. The sea will be harnessed to
supply low-cost energy to countries not possessing their own
natural hydroelectric or fossil fuel power sources, and
part of the power available will be used for working the
mineral reserves in solution in sea-water, or embedded in
the abyssal ooze.
While there is nothing far-fetched about this picture,
it will only become a reality when certain prerequisite
conditions have been met.
First and foremost, improvements are essential in the
quality and quantity of the tools available to oceano¬
graphers laboratories, ships, and general and research
equipment. In relation to what they have to do, they seem,
indeed, today to be ludicrously inadequate. Some countries
have understood this and have started national oceano-
graphical institutes with considerable funds at their
disposal contributed by various departmental budgets
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
PATHFINDERS OF THE SEA (Continued)
NEW WINE IN OLD BOTTLES
More than 2,000 years ago a cargo ship bound from Greece
to Marseilles and carrying amphorae filled with wine sank
shortly before reaching its destination. A few years ago
divers from Commandant Cousteau's team found these gra¬
ceful two-handled earthenware amphora where the ship had
sunk (below left). They bore the identification mark (a trident)
of the shipowner-wine merchant who had despatched them.
Through it, they were able to identify the villa where this mer¬
chant, Marcos Sestios, lived at Delos in Greece, (below right)
and where the trident mark was inscribed in the mosaic paving ,
To celebrate their find, the diver-archaeologists, dressed in
costumes of the ancients, held a feast at which they ate
from plates found in the wreck and filled their glasses with
20th century wine poured from a sea-weathered amphora.
© Les Requins Associés
(e.g., defence, industry), and equipped with large vessels
for work at sea.
Research in its eternal pursuit of greater efficiency,
must inevitably be organized on an international basis.
The joint operations conducted in the North and equato¬
rial Pacific by Canadian, American, Japanese and French
vessels, and the era of international co-operation inaugu¬
rated in connexion with the International Geophysical
Year, point the way which will be followecLby oceanogra¬
phy in the years to come, thus presenting the maritime
nations with fresh opportunities for better mutual under¬
standing and more effective mutual help.
Although the sea has been a source of inspiration to a
great many poets, story-tellers and musicians, there can
be no doubt that it is in the economic sphere that its
influence has been greatest. It is therefore not surprising
that when oceanographical research has had practical
implications the result has usually been an improvement
of the world economic situation apart from any influence
that wars may have had on the development of the
marine sciences. Among the human activities more
closely connected with the sea which have benefited most
from research, there is one whose importance extends far
beyond the circle of maritime nations proper and which
takes immediate rank as a common world interest: navi¬
gation.
World history and the history of the growth of interna¬
tional trade go hand in hand. From the earliest times
the seas have been used not only for overseas trade but
for short- and medium-range coastal traffic between
places in the same country; and everywhere the sea
antedated roads as the gateway through which sovereign
States achieved economic and political progress. Just as
improvements in maritime transport for long depended
on advances in our knowledge of the sea, of coastal topo¬
graphy and of winds and currents, so today are such
improvements in many respects bound up with the pro¬
gress of oceanography which is still destined to play a
decisive role in the exploitation of the world's great trade
routes.
Keeping a ship at sea may run to a considerable sum
per day. Accordingly, whenever a vessel cargo or
passenger is to make an ocean passage, the course
plotted makes allowance, firstly, for the nature, strength
and direction of the major ocean currents which might
be met with en route, representing a gain or loss of costly
hours or even days, and secondly, for the prevailing
meteorological conditions, their probable evolution, and
their effect: calculable with a high degree of accuracy on
the state of the sea. Thus oceanography's study of the
major currents such as the Gulf Stream, the Labrador
Current and the equatorial currents, their causes, courses
and fluctuations, has rendered priceless service to inter¬
national trade.
The world's harbours, natural and man-made, are under
continuous assault from the swell, the waves and the cur¬
rents. This may take the form of a direct attack on the
protective works or, more insidiously, of an invasion of
silt blocking the basins and channels. In the first, case
the whole port would sooner or later be overwhelmed, and
in the second would be left miles inland, high and dry.
Men have therefore had ,to create a Whole science of
coastal defence, building moles and breakwaters or
modifying the forms of harbour works wherever it is
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
necessary to deflect a current, create an artificial bed of
silt or check swell-heave. AU this must be based on a
profound knowledge of the coastal dynamics and the
associated tidal and current regimes, as well as of the
regime of swell-heave and waves, whose propagation is
affected by every shallow or headland, being ultimately
linked with the prevailing meteorological régime and the
interaction of sea and atmosphere. Thus meteorology
and dynamics, hydraulics and sedimentation, are essential
factors in questions pertaining to coastal developments.
Again, not only must the ports be kept in an efficient
state to handle the traffic based oh them: the coast on
which they lie must also be safe for navigation, i.e., all
the dangers and hazards they present for vessels of
varying tonnage must be fully ascertained, recorded and
"'pin-pointed". This is usually the task of national
hydrographie services which are responsible for producing
detailed charts of coastal waters giving all necessary
information on currents, shallows, leading marks, etc.
These charting operations, formerly carried out by
laborious soundings with the hand-lead, can now be
executed much more rapidly thanks to the introduction
of ultrasonic echo-sounders: but while some coastal areas,
Where ocean traffic has always been heavy, are
remarkably well-charted, there are others, mostly in the
underdeveloped countries, where the task remains a
gigantic one.
In such cases only revolutionary methods can give rapid
results, but they do exist, the war having helped their
development. Where there is a sand bottom, photo¬
graphs of the bottom, seen through the water are scanned
for variations in the brilliance of the sand, which varies
according to its depth; while for general use on any coast
the characteristics of the waves are first observed in deep
water, the depth being then determined by noting the
changes in their height and speed of translation, both of
which depend on the intensity of friction against the
bottom, which varies with the depth. Here again, the
technician has found unintended but not unprofitable
ways of applying the purely theoretical studies which
oceanography has developed over the last few years.
The discovery of submarine petroleum deposits has
given considerable impetus to the geophysical prospection
of the continental shelf i.e., of the relatively flat part
of the submerged continental mass running down from
the waterline to a depth of about 200 metres, when the
angle of slope mostly changes and there is a steep plunge
into deep water. The shelf is a submerged extension of
the adjacent land mass and, having undergone the same
upheavals and submersions, is the same in structure and
hence in mineral resources. It is estimated that the total
continental shelf area of the world contains some 120 mil¬
lion cubic kilometres of petroliferous sediments, with a
reserve of crude oil of about 400 thousand million barrels,
or nearly 40,000 million tons. This is equivalent to one-
third of the world's total reserves, to 45 times the 1956
consumption figure and to nearly 5 per cent of the total
reserves of fossil energy. It will thus be apparent that the
possibilities of the sea as an oilfield are far from negli¬
gible, and that extraction will be extended, as fast as sea-
drilling techniques are improved, to increasingly greater
depths, the sole obstacles at present being the effects of
corrosion, swell-heave and waves on equipment not
designed for working under such severe conditions.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
PATHFINDERS OF THE SEA (Continued)
Another prospect is that coastal development works will
afford fresh ppssibillties for using the tides for power
production. In view of the lower operating costs of tidal
generating stations, it is probable that under certain con¬
ditions, and when the coastal configuration makes their
installation relatively easy, it would be more economical
to use them rather than have recourse to atomic power.
The fact that the projected Severn Estuary scheme is
expected to yield 2.3 thousand million kilowatt-hours, the
Cobscook Bay scheme (Fundy Bay), 340 million kilowatt-
hours and the Mont St. Michel scheme 12,5 thousand mil¬
lion kilowatt-hours, shows that there are massive reserves
of energy still available in the sea, apart from its other
reserves in the form of thermal energy, which will be on
the market as soon as a few technological obstacles have
been overcome. Both types of energy are the more im¬
portant in that they belong to the category of permanent
marine resources which can be drawn on indefinitely and
can never be exhausted.
Spectacular developments, over the last few years, in
submarine geology and the techniques of "abyssal" pho¬
tography have served to reveal that great stretches of
the sea bottom are covered with metalliferous concretions,
called nodules, mainly iron and manganese oxides, but
with an admixture of appreciable quantities of rarer
metals such as nickel, cobalt and copper. Considering the
immense area involved, this represents a reserve of mine¬
rals of incalculable richness, and steps will certainly be
taken to exploit it when land supplies are exhausted. The
areas are ready to hand, and only technical difficulties
stand in the way of their being worked forthwith.
suspected that doing this might provoke an excessive
extension of glaciers in Europe and North America; up to
now the idea has been rejected in view of the possibility
that the dry winds from the north might pick up moisture
in their passage over an Arctic Ocean free of ice and
empty their clouds on the already snow-capped mountains
of the Northern Hemisphere, thus bringing about a gra¬
dual fall of temperature.
Conversely, a rise in mean temperatures might possibly
result from the present-day excessive consumption of coal,
petroleum and other combustibles, with the consequent
discharge of vast tonnages of carbon dioxide into the
atmosphere Part of this is absorbed by the sea, but the
rest goes to raise the atmosphere's C02 content and may
in the long run increase air temperatures by Io to 2°C.
by holding back long-wave radiations near the earth's
surface. The result could be a chain reaction culminating
in the melting of the polar ice and consequent submersion
of great areas of the present land masses. The fate of
mankind depends on the sea's power to absorb carbon
dioxide and on the cyclic mechanism which raises all
the subjacent water layers successively to the surface.
Here again man could intervene in an attempt to restore
the balance upset by his own interference.
Finally, as man's future as a power user depends on the
harnessing of thermo-nuclear energy, it should be borne
in mind that the sea is the world's greatest hydrogen
reserve.
Melting the Arctic ice-cap
The sea also has other marine mineral resources which
will become extremely . important, once economical
methods of extraction from sea-water have been per¬
fected. Already the residual brine of salt marshes yields
sodium sulphate, potassium chloride, magnesium chloride
and exychloride of magnesium. Borax, bromine and
lithium, and salts of potassium and sodium are extracted
from extinct seas such as Lake Searles in California, and
from the Dead Sea where the degree of salinity is 10 times
greater than in the ocean; and what time and nature
have done again and again and throughout Earth's geolo¬
gical history man can try to reproduce with all and any
of the energy sources at his command.
For instance, engineers may be led to use nuclear power
to get fresh water from salt for the reclamation of areas
which are now arid, reducing the costs of the operation
by recovering the kinds of industrial raw materials
referred to above from the residual brine; they might
even get uranium which is found in solution in sea-water
in such high concentration that its fission would yield
100 times the amount of energy required to evaporate the
water. Of course, when we reckon out the details of such
an operation and compare them with the action of the
sun on the sea and the energy expenditure represented
by evaporation from the ocean surface 10,000 times man's
total consumption of power from all sources, coal, petro¬
leum and hydro-electric power put together we can see
that our means of modifying the situation are limited
and our radius of action extremely restricted.
However, an idea is gradually gaining ground that the
balance of energies which regulate the interactions of sea
and atmosphere and produce the climates that we know
is metastable to the same degree that certain atmospheric
processes are found to be so. A slight pressure on some
local phenomenon could lead to large-scale modifications.
When the mechanisms controlling weather and climates
are fully known, it will probably be possible to identify the
climatic sensitive points on which man can operate to
modify atmospheric conditions as required.
For instance a possible subject for serious and
exhaustive investigation would be the idea of using
nuclear power to melt part of the Arctic ice-cap which
blocks Siberian sea communications, although it is
48
Woods Hole Océanographie Institution
GRIMACING MONSTER is the underside of the head of a shark.
Belonging to the family Oxynotidae, of which only one group with
three species are known in Mediterranean and Australian waters, these
3-foot sharks have peculiar teeth not possessed by any other species.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
Atlas Photo
0
by Peter B. Collins
Science Correspondent of "The Sunday Times"
OME Mediterranean beaches, where conditions
seem ideal for seaside holidays, are practically
deserted. There are few people bathing, no
big hotels. One thing, in fact, is wrong: the sea is too
cold, and the reason is: the weather !
What happens is surprisingly simple: the steady off¬
shore wind keeps pushing the warm upper layers of water
out to sea, and their place is taken by the upwelling of
cooler water from below. Even in summer this sort of
circulation takes place, when the warm air from the land
might be expected to warm the sea.
From the scientists' point of view there is a ceaseless
interplay between the atmosphere and the sea. Yet in
spite of the thousands of years of man's experience of the
sea and the weather, we know very little about what
actually happens at the critical boundary, the surface of
the sea where water and atmosphere meet.
All the same, we do know that the atmosphere does not,
as one might imagine, get its heat from the sun directly,
for short-wave solar radiation passes right through it.
What the atmosphere does is to pick up its energy from
the surface beneath it... over the oceans, in fact, from
the surface of the sea. How much, and in what ways
this happens, is part of the problem of "'energy-budgets''
as they are called, the profit-and-loss accounts of the
energy transfers that go on at the air-sea surface.
Our knowledge of these things is at best empirical.
Although it is not particularly difficult in principle to
find a formula to cover reactions between two such, sys¬
tems, the fact is that atmosphere and ocean are so vast
and variable that as yet we simply have not got enough
data to provide more than a few general answers.
Thus, it is evident that the upper layers of the sea are
a sort of vast reservoir of heat. When the Wind blows
the surface waters about, causing currents, huge quanti¬
ties of heat are moved to and fro. How much, depends,
on how far down the heat of the sun has penetrated, and
how strong the wind is, and how much of the heat is
already being lost to the air. These are the sort of things
that cause great storms, and similar phenomena... the
ways, in fact, in which the seas affect the weather, instead
of the weather affecting the seas. Thus, we do know
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
THE WEATHER AND THE SEAS
(Continued)
that some of the regions where great storms form, espe¬
cially in the tropics, are those where the atmosphere gets
large quantities of heat and moisture from the sea. But
what we would like to know more clearly is how much
energy is transferred in this way.
Obviously, we need much more data about both sides
of this endless equation the sea, and the weather. We
need data on the force of the wind, the variation of its
effects on the sea, and simultaneous data on the tempe¬
rature of sea and air, the atmospheric pressure and other
factors. But here, we run into another big group of diffi¬
culties. For one thing, these measurements, to be of any
real use, need to be taken at the same time and place,
and the number of such observations required is obviously
such that they have to be made by people who are not
scientists; there simply are not enough of the latter to
go round, even if places could be found for them on ships
all over the seas.
Old Salt's watery wrndspeed gauge
The ship itself, from which such measurements have
to be made, is a far from ideal place for accurate
scientific investigations. It has, for example, its own
"microclimate." Being made of metal, and being warm,
Inside at least, even in the worst weather, it will affect air
temperature readings made from its decks. As it moves, it
creates its own draught, and thus affects measurements
of the speed of the wind. Then again, the fact that it .
is a moving platform makes it difficult to keep a compa¬
ratively sensitive instrument like a barometer, steady; it
affects, too, the accuracy of rainfall measurements.
Yet to find out what really is happening between sea
and sky, these things must be observed... and not just
now and then, at a few places, but again and again and
again, in as many spots over the world's oceans as can
be managed.
As an example of the difficulties, consider the business
of measuring the temperature of the sea, at or near its
surface. This is normally done either by dipping a
specially designed bucket into the sea, and taking the
temperature of the collected water, or by taking the tem¬
perature of the cold sea water intake leading to the ship's
condensers. The first problem is that whereas the bucket
will test a sample of water from the surface, the condenser
intake is several feet down and the results, therefore,
will not be strictly comparable.
There are bound to be delays in reading the thermo¬
meters in either case. It may not always be possible to
take such readings at special times, as is normally the
case for meteorological observations.
Thus errors may creep in, and what seems simple
enough, becomes a complicated and unreliable affair
especially since the time at which an observation is made
is as important as the observation itself.
Some of the phenomena of weather at sea have, of
course, been studied since long before meteorology became
a science, and none more so than the wind. A German
sea captain named Petersen developed a system for telling
the strength of the wind, based not only on what the sea
looked like but also on what sort of sound it made! (This
was in the days of sail, when sailors were, so to speak,
much closer to the sea itself, and could hear the great
waves all too well.)
The trouble was that he recorded his ideas in German
and used some rather unusual phrases, which were hard
to translate into another language when it was desired
to internationalize his scale. A critical point, for example,
. was that at which the sea began to "roar". However,
some experts who had talked with the old man maintained
that what he meant was translated better by the word
"tumble", which would seem to refer more to what was
happening to the waves than to their noise.
Modern ways of measuring wind and sea have shown
that even with all their experience, the old sea-captains
could be wrong. For the appearance of the sea's surface,
it seems, depends not only on the force of the wind, but
also on sea and air temperatures. The greater the
difference in temperature, the less the surface of the sea
is likely to give a true guide to the force of the wind.
One weather man has described how he was crossing
the Atlantic, when a fairly strong '"Force 5" wind was
blowing. The ship's officer judged this correctly, as
checked by the instruments on board. A little later, the
sea appeared much less rough, and the officer made a
new, lower estimate; later again, it became rough once
more and he considered it had returned to force 5, until
the meteorologist pointed out that in fact, the wind had
never changed. What had changed was the temperature
of the sea... when they passed a cold patch of water, the
sea had seemed calmer because of the big difference in
temperature between it and the air.
Nonetheless, despite all the problems of getting to know
the weather at sea, a great mass of data is gradually
accumulating. This is largely thanks to the work now
centred on the World Meteorological Organization, which
through its Commission for Maritime Meteorology runs
what is called the "'selected ship scheme."
Regular, official weather ships are too few and far bet¬
ween for anything like an adequate reporting system on
the weather over the oceans. So WMO has enlisted the
help of some 3,500 merchant ships, whose captains agree
to run a voluntary observing service. The officers who
do this are not trained meteorologists, nor have they
time for lengthy observations, nor for handling complex
scientific equipment among all their official duties.
Sailor & Met man help each other
But in spite of what must at times be a scarcely
welcome additional duty (though at others, it may
equally be a relief from the boredom of many a long
voyage) the co-operation is there. One of the minor
triumphs of international meteorology, in fact, is that
among the ships working on this scheme are a number of
antarctic whalers. These ships, engaged in one of the
most highly competitive of all maritime activities, keep
their positions as secret as possible; when transmitting
the data they collect, they give their position in a special
code, known only to the> ship itself and to the meteorolo¬
gical station receiving it. But the fact that they will do
this shows that seamen, like scientists, know how much
can be gained by an ever more complete network of ship-
stations to tell us more about the weather at sea.
As the sailor and meteorologist help each other, so they
both too help the other group of scientists whose main
interest is the sea: the oceanographers. Together, all
three combine to build up a picture of the sea as it really
is. It helps the sailor, and incidentally, it may help you,
too, the passenger, by sea or air.
Certainly, there Will always be storms, and hurricanes,
just as there will always be places where the beach looks
tempting and the sea is disappointingly cold! But as
the scientists and the sailors get together, the effects
of the weather on the sea, and the sea on the weather
will matter less. It is common to hear people say that
"'science is one"; certainly, Oceanography the science of
the sea, moves ever closer to Meteorology, the science
of the weather... and as they do so, every one of us will
be the better off for it.
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
WANTED : BETTER OCEAN¬
GOING RESEARCH SHIPS
Photo courtesy Offshore Exploration Group Inc.
FLOATING LABORATORIES. Research vessel has just detonated an
explosive charge." The sound waves reflected from submarine rock
layers are recorded by hydrophones trailed behind the boat, giving
scientists a picture of ocean bed relief. For the oceanographer, the
ship in which he works is his major toollaboratory and mobile observa¬
tion platform. Widening demands in his field and increased specializa¬
tion nowadays call for large ocean-going vessels with ample space for
staff and for handling a mass of complicated and delicate apparatus.
by H.F.P. Herdman
National Institute of Oceanography, Great Britain
Does an oceanographer really need a
ship? This is a question often asked
by those who have to provide the
money to build and maintain oceanographical research
ships, but the oceanographer himself is quite certain that
no matter how much he needs shore facilities at a later
stage for processing data, it is on the original observations
made at sea that his work mainly depends.
One cannot, for instance, measure deep oceanic or
even surface currents in a shore laboratory, nor can one
determine the shape of the sea-bed or its composition.
The study of sea and wave motion, and the inter-relation¬
ship of these with the atmosphere requires in the first
instance a complexity of observations at sea. Most of the
problems associated with fish detection by acoustic means
cannot be solved in a laboratory tank; and such know¬
ledge as we have of life in the sea has only been gained
by routine sampling of the oceans at all depths.
These are only a few of the problems now being studied
by oceanographers at sea, and for which specially designed
research ships are necessary. The bathyscaph, and the
deep-diving aluminium submarine now being designed in
the United States of America, are new methods being
developed for exploring the deep oceans. Their use, how¬
ever, is likely to remain purely complementary to that of
surface ships for many years to come. Nevertheless,
the fact that these "vehicles" carry a crew is perhaps
a major step towards overcoming one of the greatest
difficulties which confront the oceanographer that of
knowing what his apparatus is doing when it sinks below
the surface.
Much progress has been made in the use of deep sea
cine cameras, and, in a more limited way, of television
cameras, but these are a poor substitute for direct
observation by the human eye. Ideally, each research ship
should be large enough to act as a parent ship to a
deep-diving submarine. Many of the teething troubles
now experienced with experimental apparatus for use in
the sea could then be detected by direct observation
below the surface. Much could be done from conventional
submarines but their depth range is limited and it is at
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
WANTED ! RESEARCH SHIPS (Continued)
the greater depths that information on the behaviour of
instruments is really needed.
The oceans cover an area of the earth's surface more
than twice that occupied by land but away from the
beaten track they are virtually unexplored. Only research
vessels, whalers, survey and cable ships visit the out-of-
the-way parts of the oceans and then rarely. There are
few research ships capable of extended operations in
distant waters and few trained oceanographers to sail in
them. Knowledge of outer space is, no doubt, necessary
but, for many years to come, man's livelihood will be
bound up with the sea, and the cost of oceanic research,
even on a world-wide scale, would be but a very small
fraction of the money spent on attempts to survey outer
space or provide long-range rockets. Sailors, fishermen,
harbour engineers and meteorologists are among those
who benefit from oceanic research but, without adequate
ships, oceanography is deprived of its major tool.
The ever increasing use of electronic equipment has
made it possible to tackle many oceanographical problems
previously not attempted, except to a limited extent. The
height of waves can now be measured accurately from
a ship and observations of the effect of wind on wave
form have been made in mid-ocean by a specially designed
free-floating buoy launched from a research ship. Deep
ocean currents and the general movement of the water-
masses are today measured by tracking a neutrally-
buoyant float, precision depth recording by modern echo-
sounding equipment, to study the outline of the sea
bed, reaches a degree of accuracy unthought of ten years
ago and photographs of the sea bed at all depths can
now be obtained as a routine.
Cores of deep sea sediments up to 70 feet in length are
now obtained by research ships; these are of immense
value to the geologist in tracing the history of the earth
back for some millions of years. Seismic soundings from
ships in mid-ocean reach much deeper into the sediment
than coring devices and are one of the major experiments
made by geophysicists in their study of the structure of
the earth's crust.
From the biological angle, to mention one use alone,
present-day electronic instrumentation makes it possible
to use the carbon-14 method to measure the rate of
photosynthesis and the underwater camera has been used
with striking effect to photograph deep sea squid. These
examples are but a few of the aspects of oceanic research
and it cannot be too strongly stressed that comprehensive
and up-to-date research ships of a reasonably large size
are essential if the study of oceanography is to be worth¬
while.
The small research ship may be of considerable value
in coastal or inshore waters, where it is probably used
mainly as a collecting agent for a laboratory near at
hand ashore. Being within easy reach of its base such a
ship can however easily change over from one branch
of oceanography to another and so be fully employed. On
the other hand the obvious place to study oceanography
is in the deep oceans, far from land, and any ship thus
employed must be large enough to carry not only the
various teams of scientists needed to get a comprehensive
picture of oceanic conditions but be large enough also to
house a considerable bulk of varied apparatus.
Many factors determine the best size for a research
ship. These include the ability to keep the seas in all
weathers, the number of scientists available to man her,
the type of work she is to do and where she is to do it,
the availability of funds for upkeep and, not the least
consideration in many countries, compliance with govern¬
ment requirements for the standard of accommodation, etc.
Able to operate in all weathers
In a comprehensive research ship, that is to say one in
which there are adequate though not perhaps full facili¬
ties for research in all branches of oceanography, the
internal space allocated to laboratories and the deck space
necessary for handling awkward overside gear, has
Increased immeasurably in the last decade; this factor
alone will determine largely the size of the ship.
Opinions differ widely on the ideal size. The Soviet
Union already has three long range research ships of
about 6,000 tons displacement, and is building at least
two more, whereas in the United States of America
possibly because of higher building costs a smaller ship,
of approximately 1,000 tons displacement, is thought
suitable, though plans have been prepared for ships
approaching 3,000 tons. In Great Britain, the R.R.S.
"Discovery II" of 2,100 tons displacement, has been in
service for over 30 years and is an excellent example of
a ship which can keep the seas in all weathers.
Nevertheless, it is now difficult, in cramped laboratories,
Photos © National Institute of Oceanography, Gt. Britain
HARDWORKING BUOYS figure largely among ever-growing mass of equipment and instruments used by oceanographers.
Buoy on left is launched from ship as an independent recording unit to measure relations between air pressures and wave profiles.
Instruments it carries include a small scale barograph (for measuring air pressures) and a roll gyro (for maintaining instruments
in equilibrium). Right, fish-shaped float houses part of precision echosounding equipment used for making records of the profile
of the ocean bed. This is towed alongside the ship connected to the depth recorder in the ship's laboratory by the towing cable.
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
Courtesy U.S. Navy
A MILLION MILES on voyages of research have been sailed by the
Atlantis. Built in 1931 for the Woods Hole Océanographie Institution,
Massachusetts, this 142-foot ketch has made some 160 cruises.
to fit in her all the electronic equipment now associated
with even simple oceanic observations; accommodation
too, is neither sufficient for the large scientific teams now
necessary to man the highly-specialized equipment
carried, nor does it meet present-day standards either
for crew or for officers.
To meet all requirements for housing modern scientific
equipment, provide adequate living accomodation for
scientists and crew, allow sufficient space for future
scientific needs, be able to generate enough electricity
for a small town and have a ship economical to run and
maintain are some of the prime considerations in the
design of a research vessel. Others, as already mentioned,
include the ability to keep to the seas in all weathers, and
for a long time, possibly for periods of four to six weeks;
fuel for a range of at least 15,000 miles is thus necessary.
Perhaps the most important point which the designer
has to bear in mind is the hull form of a research vessel.
In the past, less attention has perhaps been paid to the
sea-keeping qualities of a research vessel in relation to
the needs of science than the oceanographer deserves,
and so considerable attention must be paid not only to
the "seà-kindliness" of the ship, that is to say, her
ability to ride the seas not only easily but safely and not
take much water on board, but to ensure at the same
time that her stability is such that a reasonably steady
working "platform" for the scientist, and his apparatus,
is provided in all but the worst weather.
This need for a stable "platform" arises mainly when
the ship is stopped to lower apparatus and collect data,
and it is suggested that stabilisation by means of tanks
would suffice. It is also desirable, but not entirely
necessary, to keep the ship reasonably stable when pro¬
ceeding to the next observation point.
Taking everything into consideration it seems that the
needs of the oceanographer for some years to come can,
to a very large extent, be met by a ship of some 2,800-3,000
tons displacement, with a high ratio of beam to length.
A beam of 43 feet to a length of about 260 feet, with a
draught of 18 feet, seems adequate to meet the need for
stability. With these dimensions speed would suffer, unless
engine space and running costs are increased but the
oceanographer does not need a fast ship; a service or
economical speed of 10-11 knots is adequate since it
leaves a reasonable time between observation points or
"stations" as the scientist calls them, for servicing equip¬
ment and for the preliminary plotting of results.
Space for crew, scientists, equipment
Designs for research ships about this size are now being
prepared by various countries and proposals for an in¬
ternational ship, sponsored by Unesco, have been
under consideration for some time. Naturally, there is
some divergence of opinion on design but most countries
are agreed that the ratio of laboratory space and
accommodation for scientists to that required for purely
ship purposes must greatly be increased in favour of the
scientist. This, however, can be met in modern ships,
without greatly increasing the size of the ship, by the
reduction in space now required for engines. Diesel-
electric propulsion, or diesel engines driving a controllable-
pitch propeller, not only satisfy the oceanographer by
providing the very slow speeds sometimes needed; they
also provide a considerable reduction in machinery space
and fuel tanks over that required by a conventional steam
engine, boilers and a large fuel capacity.
Some difference of opinion exists also on a desirable
ratio of scientists to crew, especially in the smaller vessel,
where space is at a premium. The increase in the use
of electronics in oceanography has created quite a
different situation to that of twenty years ago. Then a
small team of scientists and one or two scientific
assistants (in the "Discovery II" between 1929 and 1939,
the average scientific team on five two-year commissions
was seven, of whom two were assistants) could manage
all routine sampling and analysis. Now, specialist teams
of scientists, technicians and assistants are required in
each branch of oceanography and to find space for them
in a small ship is not easy. The ratio of 50:50 for
scientists and crew, as advocated in the U.S.A., envisages
much handling of overside apparatus by the scientific
staff. Other countries prefer to use professional seamen
for this work and leave the scientist, and technician,
more time to work on the results and the apparatus.
Little has been said about the difficulties under which
the deep-sea oceanographer must work. Long periods at
sea carrying out routine experiments in all weathers,
maintenance of complicated apparatus far from shore
facilities and a restricted life are his part. To do it well
he needs ships and good ships at that for the successful
addition to our knowledge of the seas.
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
NEPTUNE'S TINY JEWELS
âUtet*
a^Ù
srsei *
ÄQff
'!£&* JaHlMWMM. ^V^4
, ike diamond bracelets and rings, the
dazzling gems above are microscopic
diatoms, plant plankton whose shells of
pure silicon crystals have been magnified 130 times.
A cupful of sea water may contain millions upon
millions of tiny plant cells, each of them far too small
to be seen by the human eye, or it may swarm with
an infinitude of animal creatures, none larger than
a dust mote, which live on plant cells still smaller
than themselves. Called "plankton" a word derived
from the Greek, meaning "wandering" and drifting
where the currents carry them, this strange commun¬
ity of animals ( Zooplankton) and marine plants
(phytoplankton) also includes other marine creatures
mostly in their larval state. From the nutrient salts
in sea water which nourish the phytoplankton, itself
a food for Zooplankton, the food chain of the sea
leads from plankton-feeding fishes to fish-eating
fishes, to squids that prey on fishes and finally to the
great whales who may live on fishes, on shrimps or
on some of the smallest of the plankton creatures.
The remarkable shapesstrange and beautifulof
the plankton, and of the marine creatures in their
larval state are strikingly revealed in these
photomicrographs, taken by Douglas P.Wilson of the
Marine Biological Laboratory, Plymouth, England.
54
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
S »t
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
5*-"^
^^^^^^^^^
,..-.;
m
Above, magnified 70 times, is the veliger
larva of " Nassarius incrassatus ", a sea
snail, with the lobes of its swimming organ
(velum) fully expanded, showing the rapidly
beating minute hair-like appendages (cilia)
by means of which it swims. Left, larval
starfish (magnified 25 times) looks like
ballerina. Five Starfish arms will emerge
from " skirt ". Right, worm-like creature,
phoronis, which when adult lives buried in
ocean bed silt (here magnified 60 times).
All photos i; Douglas P. Wilson,
Marine Biological Laboratory, Plymouth
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
,. X' .. .
... "w'-.'.lf^J
Scripps Institution of Oceanography. U.S.A.
Penguins find an unexpected haven on harpooned
whale (below) and form ranks to salute the colours
attached to marker harpoon. Whale was caught by
Soviet fishing fleet operating ¡n Antarctic waters. Above,
a whale dives straight down to evade capture. Whales
are not fish and must rise to the surface to breathe.
FISH
The great
food
potential
by D.B. Finn
Director, Fisheries Division, Food & Agriculture Organization
How great is the potential world
supply of fish for food?
First, as far as existing fisheries
go, there are many reasons to believe that the trend 'will
continue upward, especially in Asia and the Far East, in
Africa and in South America. Expansion in these areas
will depend, to a large extent, on the rate at which the
countries concerned are able to mechanize their fishing
fleets, introduce modern gear and equipment ,and train
their fishermen In the use of mechanized boats and new
fishing techniques. This is a slow, gradual business. Fur¬
thermore, we still do not know to what extent the
existing fisheries of these countries can support increased
exploitation, although the evidence before us suggests
that substantially increased catches can be made. This
is being successfully demonstrated in India, Ceylon and
elsewhere.
Another important factor is that most of the fishing
carried out today is confined to the continental shelves,
which are estimated to form only about 10 per cent of the
marine area. However, experience during recent years
shows that pelagic fish, such as tuna, may be caught over
wide areas of the oceans and seas. For example, Japanese
fishermen operating from the coast of Brazil into the
South Atlantic have consistently made substantial catches
of several species of tuna. Similarly, a big tuna fishing
industry has been built up by French fishermen operating
56
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
A SCHOOL OF MENHADEN SURROUNDED BY A SEINE NET OFF THE U.S. COAST.
© Ian Hahn, Woods Hole, U.S.A.
from Dakar, West Africa, while Japanese fishermen have
also shown that there are substantial tuna fisheries to be
developed along other parts of the African coast; they are
also operating successfully in various areas of the Indian
Ocean, the China Sea and, of course, the Pacific Ocean.
Another example of such possibilities for increasing fish
production is to be found in Haiti where an FAO expert
has proved by experimental fishing that there are plenty
of tunas in nearby waters. Indeed, he has put forward
a proposal for establishing in Haiti a tuna fishery similar
to that already established in Cuba.
In the past few years, we have had many encouraging
reports on fish stocks from our experts working in various
countries, all of which clearly point to great possibilities
for increasing fish production. For example, an FAO
expert working in Saudi Arabia was able to help organize
fleet fishing operations in the Red Sea and proved in
this practical way that the stocks of fish there are
sufficient to support a fishing enterprise. In fact, this
was another instance where increased production of fish
led to many other problems, particularly those of
transport, distribution and marketing.
The Mediterranean is generally regarded as a poor
fishing sea, but our experts have obtained some encourag¬
ing results in experimental fishing off the coasts of
Syria and Tunisia. Until recent years, shrimp fishing was
of little importance in the Mediterranean and, in fact,
some people believed there were no worthwhile shrimp
stocks in this sea. Then, shortly after the Second World
War, some French fishermen discovered substantial stocks
of big shrimps of an excellent quality. As a result, trawlers
working from Algeria, Egypt, Italy and Turkey are fishing
these stocks and a very profitable shrimp trade has been
developed.
All these facts support the view of many fishery experts
that the stocks of fish in several parts of the world are
underexploited. These areas include the Arabian Sea and
the Persian Gulf, where anchovy and similar species are
caught, the southern waters of Australia, the west coast
of South America, and the English Channel, where there
are substantial stocks of pilchards.
Support for the point of view that there are very large
unfished stocks in the oceans and seas is to be found
in the sudden disasters which from time to time overtake
fish populations. For example, in 1957, a ship from the
U.S.S.R., sailing through the southeastern part of the
Arabian Sea, came upon vast quantities of dead fish.
According to the Soviet report, the fish were found between
60°-70° E and 10°-12° N, covering an area of about 200,000
square kilometres. The fish were said to be 20 to 25
centimetres in length, in which case they would weigh
about 100 grammes each. If we assume that one tenth
of the area reported contained dead fish at a density of
10 to the square metre, some 20 million tons of fish
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
THE GREAT FOOD POTENTIAL (Continued;
perished. But even if it was only a tenth as serious as
this conclusion suggests, some two million tons of fish
were killed.
Probably this mortality was caused by a layer of water
known as the tropical subsurface oxygen minimum.
Under certain conditions this layer is brought up to the
top by strong upwellings and the fish die from lack of
oxygen. It is not a rare occurrence as many reports of
this phenomenon have been made by eye witnesses. For
instance, in April 1956, a ship sailing through the Arabian
Sea saw the water begin to "boil by the sudden appearance
of many thousands of fish about the size of mackerel."
A number of other phenomena of this kind have been
reported from this area.
The important point in this_ connection is, of course,
the vast quantity of fish observed, amounting to millions
of tons. Such fish form part of the underexploited or
unexploited stocks available in the world, and it is
interesting to speculate on the vastness of the stocks
which can survive such disasters. Therefore, it does not
seem overoptimistic to suggest that many millions of
tons of fish could be taken regularly every year from
such stocks.
One has only to look at the extraordinarily rapid
development of the pilchard fishery of South Africa to
appreciate something of the huge potential of the sea.
Here a thriving fishery has been developed in a few years,
yielding hundreds of thousands of tons of fish in that
short time.
New stocks of crustaceans and molluscs have been dis¬
covered in recent years in various parts of the world.
Crustaceans have been discovered 'off the east coast of
America, off the east coast of Australia, and in the Gulf
of Mexico, while crayfish are being fished in South Africa
and Western Australia. This by no means exhausts recent
discoveries and it seems most likely that, with the more
intensive development of fisheries which is taking place
in all parts of the world, new fishing grounds for crabs,
lobsters, shrimps, oysters, and so on, will be discovered.
This refers only to fish, crustaceans and molluscs taken
from the sea, but there is also the fresh-water fish to be
considered. A substantial increase in fish production from
inland waters has already taken place and I think it is
safe to forecast that production will be further increased.
Those who have seen the tambaks of Indonesia and the
live carp on sale in China will realize that fish culture
is an ancient and traditional art in those parts of Asia.
It is a practice which has been passed down from father
to son and from master to apprentice. It is an art rather
than a 'science, the techniques of which were perfected
in relation to a certain set of conditions laboriously
worked out by a process of trial and error. While this
empirical system produced fish, little was known of the
reasons why things worked. Today, a new approach to
fish culture has been prepared by the intense study by
scientists of the basic principles involved. A scientific
basis for the art of fish culture has been worked out and
is being further developed . and this has made it possible
to cope with problems and conditions which have defeated
fish culturists in the past. Today, we can bring into use
water that once lay idle and unmanaged.
The potentialities for fish production in inland waters
are vast. For example, it is estimated that there are
37 million hectares of cultivable inland waters in the
Indo-Pacific region alone. If all this water were put into-
use, it is obvious that a substantial harvest of fish could
be reaped from it each year.
There are many advantages to be accrued from such
fish culture, particularly in the economically under¬
developed areas. For instance, fish may be reared where
they are needed and harvested when they are required,
which eliminates many of the problems of transport,
preservation and marketing, invariably serious hindrances
to the development of trade in underdeveloped countries.
Work is also being done to encourage fish farming in
Central America where, without doubt, a considerable
industry could be established which would do much to
add to the supply of animal protein in the diets of the
people of those countries. Again, there is the success
which has attended the introduction of fresh-water fish
in wet rice paddies. These experiments have shown that
the fish feed on insect, animal and plant pests, with a
resulting beneficial effect on the rice crop. Many people
believe that the rice yield may be increased by as much
as seven per cent and, of course, there is besides the
production of fish. It is quite obvious that this type of
fish farming should be introduced on a wide scale in
India, Egypt, Burma and in other countries where rice is
grown in wet paddies.
Surveys made of the potential supply of fish from ma¬
rine and fresh water lead invariably to the conclusion that
the present world fish catch could be more than doubled.
There is much evidence to suggest that the existing
known stocks are sufficient for a catch of 50 to 60 million
tons to be made and maintained yearly «without taking
into account the possible discovery of new fisheries.
Drawing © Felton Design Studio, U.S.A.
NEW WAYS OF FISHING. Most fishermen still use methods that have not changed for centuries. But now science is giving
them newtools. Left to right, boat equipped with pump sucks schools of fish on board. Bubble "fence", produced by compressed
air spurting from holes In trailing pipe, "herds" fish towards pump. Overhead a plane scouts for new schools. Boat in centre
uses device for creating an electric "fence", based on knowledge that fish are attracted or repelled by positive or negative poles of
electrical field. Right, locating fish precisely with sonar (sound echo) equipment, showing both depth and importance of school.
58
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
r
SEAWEED
FOR THE
DINNER
TABLE
Seaside peasant girl rakes ¡n
a harvest of seaweed on a
Japanese beach. In Japan,
fish is the principal source of
animal protein. The Japanese
eat seven times more fish
than the Americans, for
example. Japanese eat not
only the sea's animal life, but
many kinds of seaweeda
rich source of vitamins and
minerals. Seaweed is gather¬
ed in other countries too,
but is generally not eaten
directly. Instead it is pro¬
cessed into a substance called
algin.usedin cosmetics, tex¬
tiles, paper, ink, and drugs
as well as in jellies and jams.
© Almasy, Paris
GREAT STRIDES IN FISHING INDUSTRIES
m t is estimated that only a fraction of one per
cent of the food consumed by human beings
is fish from the oceans and seas, although these cover
more than 70 per cent of the surface of the earth.
It should be possible to obtain greatly increased
quantities of food from this source for the sea is, acre
for acre, about as productive as arable land.
The world catch of fish has increased substantially in
the past few years and is now approaching 34 million
metric tons a year. This is about 14 million tons more
than was caught in 1938. The largest increases, achieved
by the technically developed countries, are largely due
to the use of improved boats, gear and equipment,
especially the use of electronic devices to help locate fish
and the development of fleet fishing techniques. In some
cases, large increases have also been the result of inten¬
sive fishing of one or two particular species of fish.
For example, the Danish and Norwegian production of
herring has more than doubled since 1938 because Danish
and Norwegian fishermen have developed the fishing of
winter herring.
In Iceland, great development has taken place in the
cod fishery. The catch of some 90,000 tons in 1938 has
increased considerably in the past decade and in 1957
exceeded 24,200 tons.
The United States provides an example of the develop¬
ment of tuna fishing. Before the Second World War tuna
was a virtually unexploited species so far as United States
fishermen were concerned, but it has since become a
major commercial product. The development of this
fishery in the United States has called for a very heavy
capital investment in fishing boats and fish processing
plant and equipment.
Perhaps the most dramatic increase in fish production
since 1945 has taken place in the Union of South Africa
(including South West Africa). This catch is based on
the pilchard stocks which were virtually unfished com¬
mercially in 1938. Since then, a major fishing industry
has been developed more than 300,000 tons of pilchards
being landed in 1957 and more than 400,000 tons in 1958.
More recently, there have been some astonishing
developments in the fishing industry of the U.S.S.R., both
as regards number and type of fishing vessels employed
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
GREAT STRIDES IN FISHING (Cont'd)
and the size of the catch. The Soviet catch has, in fact,
increased by more than a million tons since 1938, when
it amounted to something over 1,500,000 tons. In 1956,
it was more than 2,620,000 tons. During this same period
the number pf fishing boats in the U.S.S.R. increased
from 36,406 to 60,443. The most significant increase took
place in powered craft, whose number jumped from 2,727
to 12,387. Thus, in a few years, the Soviets have put into
operation some very large new fishing fleets and they are
now making substantially greater catches.
Again, one of the notable postwar fishing developments,
which is adding to the trend toward bigger catches by the
industrialized nations, is the emergence of the factory-
ship. The British have successfully introduced factory-
ship operations with the Fairtry, a vessel which can go
to sea for two or three months and fish and process her
catch on board. The Soviets, too, have developed factory-
ships and are reported to1 have some dozens in operation.
One of the most impressive expansions in fisheries since
the Second World War has been the increased catch made
by the fishermen of Japan. In 1938, they caught more
than 3,560,000 tons of fish and in 1953 over 5,505,000 tons.
Japan, indeed, is far in the lead among the fishing nations
of the (world and catches some 2,830,000 tons more than
the second nation, the United States.
The Yearbook of Fishery Statistics lists the leading
eight nations (in order of importance) as Japan, United
States (incl. Alaska), China (mainland), U.S.S.R., Norway,
India, United Kingdom, Canada (includ. Newfoundland).
The most interesting point about this list of leading
fishing nations is that India has joined the select few
with a catch exceeding 1 million tons a year. This is
especially significant because India is one of the countries
where there is a great and urgent need to provide the
people with a diet richer in animal protein, and the
increase in the fish catch reflects the efforts to develop
and modernize the Indian fishing fleets and fishing
industry.
Äs in other fields of human activity agriculture, in¬
dustry, science, médecine, etc. the gap between the
developed and the underdeveloped countries tends to
widen rather than narrow. For example, northern
Europe has increased its fish catch from 1,750,000 tons in
1938 to 3,160,000 tons in 1957an 80 per cent increase.
Compared with this, the increase in the fish catch of Asia
has been from 9,360,000 to 12,880,000 tons. Yet Asia is in
need of far greater food supplies. This is a typical
situation which illustrates the necessity for international
co-operation, for the developed countries to aid the under¬
developed. In the case of Asia the situation is worse than
appears at first sight because one country alone Japan
accounts for 5,399,000 tons, leaving about 7,400,000 tons
for all other countries in the region. A similar situation
exists in Africa and also in South America..-
The problem of raising the productivity of the under¬
developed countries can be looked at in a different light.
For example, by 1957 the total food production of the
world had more than regained the prewar level per
head of population: yet, more than half the people in
the world some 1,500 million persons even today lack
sufficient animal protein to keep in good health. It is
true that there has been a great increase in agricultural
production in recent years but nearly half of it has taken
place in North America, which supports . only seven per
cent of the world's population.
In the Far East, where more than 50 per cent of the
people of the world lives, food production has not
advanced beyond prewar levels and these were, as most
people today know, quite inadequate to maintain human
beings healthy and vigorous. And, although more food
is being grown in the underdeveloped countries, this is
being offset by the increased survival rate, so that there
remain vast areas of the world where populations continue
to live close to the starvation point.
It is not suggested that the resources of the sea are
60
WORLD'S BIGGEST FISH MARKET
so vast that, given the men, money, means and equipment,
it would be possible to make a huge increase in food
production from this source. All that can safely be said
at this time is that substantial increases can be obtained
from known resources, as demonstrated in India. Nobody
knows the extent of the resources of the sea, and one of
the great tasks confronting mankind is to explore and
investigate these resources and determine their nature
and extent. But enough is known for fishery biologists
to predict that production of fish, crustaceans and mol¬
luscs can probably be doubled without damaging present
known resources. This is an encouraging outlook which
helps to promote realistic planning to increase production.
The immediate aim is not to double fish production
generally but to bring about a substantial increase in
those areas of the world where the need for animal
protein is most urgent.
Such an increase in production involves many problems
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
Photos © Almasy, Paris
Tunny carpeting the quay at Tokyo (above) are part of the 1 ,500 tons of fish which change hands each day by auction (above left) in the
city's fish marketthe largest in the world. Fish provides the most important parTof the protein diet of Tokyo's 9,300,000 inhabitants, as
it does for most Japanese. Japan is far in the lead among the fishing nations and each year catches well over five million tons.
and factors which at first sight are not apparent. It
calls, for example, for international co-operation to
conserve, develop, husband and manage the world
fisheries. Not even the most powerful of the technically
developed nations can expect to operate successfully alone
in a programme to increase fish production. So much
of commercial fishing is competitive and it often takes
place in areas of the oceans and seas over which no
nation has tenancy or exclusive legal rights, so that
international agreement must be introduced if the fisheries
are to be preserved and maintained in a healthy state.
This is probably a factor of the utmost importance for
those countries which are now developing, or hope to
develop, their fishing fleets to operate in waters outside
territorial limits.
Again, apart from considerations of national or inter¬
national policy in the development of fisheries, there is
need to mechanize fishing fleets, introduce new and
improved types of boats and equipment, and to teach
fishermen to operate such engines and gear and to use
new fishing techniques. All these problems are not easily
or quickly solved, and, even after progress has been
made in this direction, there often arise other problems
which may be connected with fishery administration and
services or concerned with the storage, processing,
transport, marketing and distribution of fish and fish
products.
Although these and many other problems hinder and
hamper efforts to increase fish production, the facts and
figures of the situation point hopefully to the future. The
world total catch increased by about 60 per cent, from
19,090,000 tons to 33,720,000 tons between 1948 and 1957.
Thus, some of the great potential of fish in the world
supply of food has been realized far more quickly than
many experts dared hope a few years ago. Progress in
fisheries has. been greater in the past 30 years than in
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
GREAT STRIDES IN FISHING (Cont'd)
© Almasy
In the ports of Japan, Geiger counters are still used to check landed fish that are caught In the Pacific
Ocean although no serious cases of radio-active contamination have been observed for the past six years.
the previous 3,000. There are reasons to hope that this
progress will be quickened and it may be that the next
decade will see another substantial increase in the world
fish catch.
A condition essential for the healthy development of
the fisheries of the world, and to obtain the maximum
yield from those fisheries, is an increase in international
co-operation. Much progress has been made in this
direction as is evidenced by the various fishery agreements
and by the joint activities of governments and of various
scientific and technical organizations.
Despite this progress, however, fishing as an industry
is still at the stage reached by agriculture thousands of
years ago. We still hunt fish over thousands of square
miles of oceans and seas where no nation has rights of
individual ownership and where the stocks of fish are
wild. The aim in fisheries must be toward husbandry,
so that stocks of fish can be herded and grazed as a
farmer herds cattle. It is doubtful if we can establish fish
husbandry for certain species, but there are distinct
prospects of success with others, provided nations co-
62
operate in seeking the orderly development of world
fisheries.
Man has the technical ability to overcome all these
problems. The principal requirement is to organize the
technical skills, materials, gear, equipment, etc., in such
a way as to bring about the rapid development of the
underdeveloped fisheries. This can only be done through
international co-operation on an increasing scale. It is
only through such co-operation that we can hope to
achieve the orderly development of world fisheries which
will benefit the fishing industries of all nations and will
lead to great increases in the supply of fish to consumers
everywhere.
This article is a condensation of chapters from a booklet,
"Fish-the Great Food Potential," by Dr. D.B. Finn which
is shortly to be published by the Food and Agriculture
Organization, Rome. The Editors wish to thank FAO for
permission to use this material in advance of publication.
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July-August 1960
ATOMS OVERBOARD!
by George W. C. Tait
Director, Division of Health, Safety and Waste
Disposal, International Atomic Energy Agency
PI
B ^^^ ADioACTivE waste is an inevitable result of
man's exploitation of nuclear fission. Such
wastes will appear in vast quantities if present plans and
hopes succeed in harnessing the atomic nucleus for the
production of a major fraction of man's future needs for .
energy. The thinking person may well ask if there is
any threat ¡to the sea from radioactive contamination
when he considers the common practice of using it as a
catch-all for undesirable waste.
The hazards of radioactivity have been underlined in
the development of man's use of nuclear forces, first as
a dangerous laboratory curiosity and later as an unpa¬
ralleled weapon of destruction. The knowledge of how
radioactivity in the sea can return to man through the
food he eats directs concern to this possibility. Unac¬
ceptable contamination of a major part of man's food is
conceivable if all the radioactivity produced in the fore¬
seeable future were to be dispersed uniformly in the sea.
The intelligent layman looks with some concern to the
scientist, the oceanographer or the marine biologist for
guidance, and to those responsible for the control of radio¬
active wastes for assurance.
The scientist in his turn approaches radioactive waste
disposal from two points of view. He may use his field
of science to investigate the safety of waste disposal or
he may use the threat of waste disposal to promote his
specialty. Both these courses are perfectly legitimate but
the scientist should indicate which course is being follow¬
ed. The oceanographer is concerned with how wastes
placed in any part of the ocean are dispersed and even¬
tually encountered by living creatures. The marine bio¬
logist enquires how these dangerous substances enter the
living organism, are concentrated or diluted as they pass
from one creature to another and eventually reach man.
The oceanographer in searching for the safest methods
of disposal into the sea had first been attracted by the
deep trenches which are found in various parts of the
sea. It seemed a reasonable guess that such depths
should be isolated from the upper waters for long periods
of time. As a result of more recent work this guess
appears to be wrong. The value of the ocean abysses as
Isolated disposal areas is now doubted. Nevertheless
there is considerable evidence that the deeper waters of
the oceans as a whole do not mix rapidly with the upper
layers. Estimates of the time required for mixing vary
over a large range (50 to 2,000 years). Even if the shor¬
ter time was correct there would be an advantage to put
wastes into deep rather than surface waters to delay
their uptake by fishes.
However, the extent and rate of mixing is little under-
Photos © C. O. I., London
ATOMIC 'SEWAGE' from a new British atomic energy establishment at Wlnfrith Heath in Dorset will be disposed of through
the pipe-line shown here under construction. Radioactive liquid wastes. from the centre, five miles inland, will be carried by the
pipe a further two miles on the seabed. The British already have a long experience of disposing of this kind of sewage from
their atom factory at Windscale In Cumberland. Here again a pipe-line carries the wastes two miles out into the Irish Sea.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
ATOMS OVERBOARD ! (Continued)
stood, especially in the deep sea, and oceanographers
hesitate to provide any guidance as to the behaviour of
wastes without much further research. The food chain
and changes in concentration of radioactive material in
passing from micro-organisms in the sea through fish to
man is even less well known and a tremendous amount
of research is called for before general answers can be
found to the result of disposing major quantities of radio¬
active material into the sea.
99.9 % of wastes stored on land
There appears to be little demand on the part of those
responsible for radioactive waste to use the seas as
a general large scale disposal area. This situation is
due to several circumstances. In the first, place there is
no present need. Ninety-nine point nine percent of
wastes being produced are safely put away in permanent
storage. This storage is conveniently near the places of
production and does not raise the very real transportation
and handling problems which would come with large scale
waste disposal into the deep sea. This type of storage has
already been so perfected that its cost is probably less
than that of transportation of the waste to a suitable
place for sea disposal. Finally a not insignificant factor
is that the government scientists and engineers generally
responsible for advising on waste disposal practices are
conservationists at heart, and have little incentive to
recommend doubtful practices. There is little enthusiasm
for large scale future use of the sea.
A large part of this reluctance to turn to the sea is the
importance which is attached to it as one of man's
greatest resources and the fear that if a mistake were
made, it could not be corrected. As a result in planning
large scale disposal for the future most attention is
directed to the land, which appears to be the simplest
and best solution to our immediate problems. The future
looks to the use of favourable geological structures or
fixation in materials resistant to all weathering. Beyond
this, of course, lies the hope of new forms of nuclear
energy, which do not give the tremendous yield of wastes
found with the fission process.
Any reader of the daily papers might well wonder why
the much publicized disposal of radioactive wastes off the
coast of several countries has been overlooked so far in
this discussion. Simply because this sort of thing is
trivial beside what we have just been considering. The
quantities of radioactivity released are so small when
compared with the quantities produced that the discard¬
ing of these wastes can hardly be considered any real
contribution to the world's problems of radioactive waste
disposal.
Public as disposal 'watch dogs'
I't must always be remembered that all things are radio¬
active to some degree. The question then becomes what
degree of radioactivity in trash and garbage is to be
considered the cut-off point beyond which it cannot be
allowed to enter the sea. The writer knows of no one
responsible for the controls of radioactive wastes who
advocates allowing any amounts to enter the sea which
would adversely affect man and his environment. It is
generally accepted that there should be no adverse effect
on the harvest of food from even a small local area of
the sea. The technical problem faced by the responsible
specialist is to set standards and methods of control to
ensure that the radioactivity of wastes entering the sea
never reaches a sufficiently high level to result in pollution
even in a restricted locality (1).
Those responsible for controlling these relatively small
releases of radioactive wastes into the sea generally go
to great lengths to ensure that conditions leading to pollu¬
tion harmful to man cannot occur. It must of course
be recognized that pressure can be exerted to interfere
with the successful carrying out of their work. On the
one hand those who are most concerned with the econo¬
mics of nuclear energy may be tempted to advocate any
techniques which appear to provide the possibility of
cutting costs. This is particularly true at the present
where the calculation of nuclear power costs are very
critical and any small saving in handling wastes might
affect the competitive position of a particular proposal.
For this reason there is much to be said for an organi¬
zation which widely separates the control of radioactive
waste disposal from those concerned with production.
On the other hand there is an unfortunate tendency
of many scientific specialists to be unaware and uncon¬
cerned with the work of their colleagues in neighbouring
. fields. Even scientists are subject to human vanity and
like to think they alone have achieved enlightenment.
As a result, many criticisms of radioactive waste handling,
especially with respect to sea disposal, represent partial
information and cannot stand up to careful analysis.
C. O. I. London
(1) An international panel oí experts on the disposal of radioactive
wastes In the sea, set up by the I.A.E.A. and headed by Mr. Harry
Brynlelsson (Sweden) has recently submitted its report to the Director
General of the Agency. It Is hoped that Its recommendations will
form the basis for an international agreement to prevent radioactive
contamination of the seas.
ATOM-FISHING BOAT, Mary Munro II, alongside the
quay in Whitehaven harbour on a misty morning. Regularly
each month her crew search for radioactivity in the sea off
the Cumberland coast where an atom works discharges
its nuclear fission wastes through a long pipe-line.
In this situation intelligent members of the public have
a useful function and an important responsibility. They
should ask that those responsible for controlling the entry
of radioactive wastes into the sea should justify the.
measures they take. There is no sound argument for
secrecy. On the basis of justification they should support
those responsible both against pressure from, advocates
of laxity and from irresponsible criticisms by those who
have not taken the pains to inform themselves thoroughly
on the overall problem.
Maintaining the seas free from radioactive pollution
should not be costly, but its achievement does call for
consistent determination.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Ne
TV AND CRIME: Do crime films and
TV crime dramas have a great effect on
the incidence of crime among young peo¬
ple? No, according to studies made by
the Department of Audio-Visual Aids,
University of Melbourne, Victoria. Re¬
searchers in mass communication at this
Australian University set out to determine
the impact of television films of violence
on children and adolescents, and to disco-
THE UNESCO
PHILATELIC SERVICE
"Friendship among children the
world over" is the theme of this
stamp one of a series designed by
Czechoslovak schoolchildrne during
a national contest for Unesco. A
3 0 heller denomination, it is
printed ¡n three coloursblue, red
and yellow. It can be obtained
from The Unesco Philatelic Ser¬
vice which has stamps and first day
covers issued by many Member
States to commemorate important
events ¡n the history . of Unesco
and the U.N. (Inauguration of
Unesco's New Headquarters, Hu¬
man Rights Day, World Refugee
Year). As the agent ¡n France of
the U.N. Postal Administration,
Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks
all the United Nations stamps
currently on sale. Information on
items available, their price and the
methods of payment, will be sent
on request by Unesco's Philatelic
Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*.
ver the reasons for the strong and conti¬
nued appeal which '"tension programmes"
have for young people. A report on the
results ¡"Television Crime-Drama" by
R.J. Thomson says that the research pro¬
duced no evidence that seeing a crime film
provokes any criminal or psychopathic ten¬
dencies in the majority of viewers. An ear¬
lier report in the same series, published in
1957, had reviewed the psychological ef¬
fects of the Western film when viewed on
TV.
SELECTED BOOK LIST ON THE SEA
Rachel Carson : THE SEA AROUND US, Oxford Univ. Press, 1951.
R.E. Coker: THIS GREAT AND WIDE SEA, Univ. of North Carolina Press,
1947.
J.J. Chapman: SEAWEEDS AND THEIR USES, Putnam, 1952.
John S. Colman: THE SEA AND ITS MYSTERIES, G. Bell and Sons, 1950.
Jacques-Yves Cousteau & James Dugan: UNDERWATER TREASURY, Har¬
per & Bros., New York, 1959 (see also THE SILENT WORLD, Hamish
Hamilton Ltd., London).
H. Daniel and F. Minot: THE INEXHAUSTIBLE SEA, MacDonald, Lon¬
don, 1955.
J.S. Douglas : THE STORY OF THE OCEANS, Dodd, Mead and Co., 1952.
A.C. Hardy: THE OPEN SEA, its natural history, the world of Plankton,
Collins, London.
T. King: WATER, miracle of nature, The MacMillan Co., 1955.
Pierre de Latil: MAN AND THE UNDERWATER WORLD, G.P. Putnam's
Sons, New York 1956.
J.R. Norman and F.C. Fraser: GIANT FISHES, DOLPHINS AND WHALES,
G.P. Putnam and Sons, 1938.
H. Petterson: THE OCEAN FLOOR, Yale University Press, 1954.
C. Ray and E. Ciampi: THE UNDERWATER GUIDE TO MARINE LIFE,
A.S. Barnes and Co., New York 1956.
F.S. Rüssel and CM. Yonge: THE SEAS, Warne and Co., 1952.
F.P. Shepard: THE EARTH BENEATH THE SEA, Johns Hopkins Univ.
Press, 1959.
D.P. Wilson: THEY LIVE IN THE SEA, Collins, London 1947.
SEAS UNDER THE DESERT:
Recent studies of water resources in
Kazakhstan, in the U.S.S.R., have re¬
vealed the existence of underground
seas lying beneath large expanses of des¬
ert. Nearly 70 of these subsurface,
fresh water lakes have been found and
according to Soviet scientists they are
formed by vast layers of waterlogged
gravel and gritstone resembling a sponge
which if "squeezed" would yield nearly
twice as much water as the Aral sea.
In all, they cover half the total area of
Kazakhstan.
NORWAY'S FLOATING LIBRARY:
After the bookmobile, widely used in the
rural districts of eastern Norway, the first
bookboat is now plying among the islands
of the country's west coast, bringing books
to the fishermen-farmers who live in the
scattered communities in this region. Spon¬
sored by the Bergen City Council, Bergen
Public Library, the State and the Province
of Hordaland, the bookboat carries about
3,000 volumes and calls at 149 places in
the province.
EUROPE'S WORKERS ABROAD:
Textile apprentices from Belgium who
recently spent nine days in Paris on a
UNESCO-sponsored study tour were the
first of over 800 workers of all ages
who will this year travel abroad in
Europe under UNESCO's auspices. A
total of 58 groups, numbering from ten
to twenty workers from 21 different
countries, will take part in study tours,
and Unesco is contributing a total of
§50,000 for their travel. More than
8,000 men and women have so far
benefitted from the Unesco scheme
since it started in 1952. Unesco pays
travel expenses for the various groups
and other funds are provided by
workers' and employers' organizations.
Visits enable men and women to go
abroad not only to see other lands but
to make contacts among people
engaged in the same kind of job.
M.ELP FROM A TO B: Over 3,000
guilders (£300), were collected recently by
girls at a school in Arnhem, Netherlands,
to buy equipment for a small school in the
Himalayan foothills village of Binayak.
They raised it after hearing how the village
people, who live in the mountains on the
borders of India and Tibet, had built their
school by hacking out the solid rock of
the mountainside. The money will be for¬
warded to the school in the form of Unesco
Gift Coupons.
ORIENT OCCIDENT: A NEW
UNESCO ART FILM: Though sepa¬
rated by great distances and by centu¬
ries of history, the Orient and the Occi¬
dent have always met in art. This is
the theme of a new Unesco film,
"Orient-Occident: Highlights of an
Exhibition" which illustrates, through
the medium of ancient sculpture, what
the East and West have in common.
The works it portrays were on view at
an exhibition held at the Cernuschi Mu¬
seum in Paris, early last year. They
range from Greek art to images of the
Buddha from India and the Far East,
illusirate the fundamental unity of art
forms in both East and West and show
the particular contribution made by both
world areas.
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
WAVE
MYSTERY
(Cont'd from p. 37)
THE MIGHTY RIVERS
OF INNER SPACE
So it is only sixteen years since practical methods were
evolved of measuring the height of sea-waves and less
than ten since wave-recorders were fitted to ships, to
accumulate the Information without which further expla¬
nations could never be produced. Yet, once the scientists
got going, it became apparent that the problem was not
nearly as intractable as it had seemed.
The scientists are still trying to find how wind energy
makes the regular wave pattern of a great storm Instead
of stirring the ocean into mere confusion. It is a question
of accumulating data. There are known, storm-centres,
or areas where "master-waves" are generated, but there
are other wave systems, due to secondary causes, and the
visible waves we see at any given time are the result of a
number of component wave-trains travelling at different
speeds and in different directions.
Energy from the Roaring Forties
Those have to be sorted out. This is done by a wave-
analyzer which tells how the energy is distributed bet¬
ween waves of different length. It is an electronic
device and it does very much for the sea what a radio-set
does for electromagnetic waves. It picks out the waves
from the generating-areas as though from different
transmitters and separates them.
They know that waves of different length separate after
leaving a storm area so that the very long low waves,
rising as ground swell on shallow banks, herald the
approach of the shorter steeper swell with most of the
storm energy. It has now reached the stage of refinement
where scientists on the coast of Cornwall or California can
measure the very low swell which has carried energy all
the way from the Roaring Forties of the Southern Hemi¬
sphere.
Methods have been evolved which can distinguish
between what seamen call "sea" and "swell." That is to
say the instruments can tell the difference between 'waves
created by local winds and those originating in storms
possibly thousands of miles away. So, in combination
with the weathermen, the oceanographers can now predict
waves based on meteorological data.
By experiment and theory, the scientists can produce
figures and patterns which are of enormous benefit to
coastal and harbour engineers and to naval architects.
New liners will have "built into them" information, for the
comfort of their passengers and efficiency of running,
which was not available at the end of the war.
Tossed like a Kon-Tiki raft
Already there is a mass of material about wave action
on seacoasts and shoals which will be of value in the
protection of coast-lines which, through the centu¬
ries, have been etched by the action of waves.
That is the surface and the movements which can create
Atlantic rollers 60 feet high, toss a liner as though it were
a Kon-Tiki raft. What of the depths?
The oceans cover nearly three-quarters of the surface
of the Planet Earth and we know rather less about the
geography of this drowned part of our world than we do
about the surface of the Moon. The average depth of
the ocean is about 24 miles but there are "deeps" or
"trenches" which are as deep as 64 miles farther down
than the peak of Everest is up. It is not a "silent world."
With hydrophones, it is possible to pick up jungle noises,
often of creatures we have never seen. And it is certainly
not still; it is in pretty constant movement.
The seas and the climate are inseparable. The oceans
act as a great accumulator or savings bank of heat. The
heat from the sun is stored in the water and Is given off
in times of cold, so that there is a continuous adjustment
of the world's climate. To understand weather, you have
to understand the sea and, the other way round, to under¬
stand the oceans you have to understand the circulation
of the atmosphere.
It is estimated that nine-tenths of the surface currents
(not just the waves) are wind-driven including the Gulf
Stream, which Benjamin Franklin observed so scienti¬
fically nearly two centuries ago, the Humboldt Current
which swept the Kon Tiki raft to Polynesia and the
Kuroshia Current. And even the deep currents are to
some extent influenced by the wind because the surface
water pushed by the winds against the coast is "bent"
downwards to exercise pressures on water layers at lower
depths to get them moving current-wise. It is rather
like on escalator.
More and more is being learned about those deeper
currents. The thing to be remembered is that the water
in the oceans is not all of one density and that lighter
water can lie on top of heavier (because it is colder or
saltier) water like a layer cake. These layers can skid
over, or under each other or move in different directions
to each other.
Gulf stream flows two ways
To study the nature and movement of those deep cur¬
rents instruments have been devised. In a way they
are analogous to those which the weathermen use.
When meteorologists want to explore the upper atmo¬
sphere and study air currents high above the earth, they
send up balloons with transmitting instruments in a
"radiosonde" which signals back information. The ocea¬
nographers who want to study currents far below the sur¬
face of the sea use something similar.
They use two long aluminium tubes which contain
batteries and a simple electronic circuit. It has a sound-
producer like that used in echo-sounding. This Instru¬
ment can be lowered to any precise depth. If you load it
at the surface with enough weight to make it float at a
depth of 2,500 metres, it only needs another gramme of
weight to take it to exactly 2,530 metres. At the prede¬
termined depth it drifts with the current and sends out
pulse-signals. These signals can be picked up by a surface
ship.
Such methods have been used in a "combined operation"
by the British and Americans to study the Gulf Stream. It
was shown that the northward flowing Gulf Stream was
strong at the surface. There was, however, little or no
movement between 4,500 and 6,000 feet but floats released
at 8,200 feet and at 9,200 feet drifted southwardsin the
opposite direction to the surface stream. The speed of
this counter-current was a third of a knot.
Now the plotting of knowledge about the sea is being
intensified. We have had Depth Travel, as Well as Space
Travel. The bathyscaph has gone down to the bottom
of one of the Pacific Trenches. Surface ships make
regular and repeated surveys and gradually we are begin¬
ning to find out things we did not know.
66
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW ON
THE WORLD
Once a month THE UNESCO
COURIER presents to its
readers a panorama of the
modern world. Without being
either too learned or too "popu¬
lar" ¡n its approach, its well-
illustrated articles give a vivid
picture of the endless diversity
of peoples and countries. There
is no facet of the present-day
world on which it does not
touch the sciences man has
developed, the cultures he has
created, the knowledge he has
amassed.
THE UNESCO COURIER, now
in its thirteenth year, does more
than merely satisfy the desire
for information about contem¬
porary problems ; it throws
light on every aspect of human
endeavour, strengthens the links
between the peoples in every
corner of the globe, fosters
international understanding and
advances the cause of peace.
You can help by telling your
friends, colleagues and business
associates or your local libra¬
rian about THE UNESCO COUR¬
IER. It also makes an ideal
birthday or Christmas gift. As
a gift for your friends abroad,
you can subscribe to the French,
Spanish or Russian editions.
A YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION
COSTS ONLY 10/-stg.; S 3.00;
7.00 New Francs or equivalent.
(See list of National Distribu¬
tors, below.)
THE WORLD'S
HIGHWHS
SCIENCE & MANKIND
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
' listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï. Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul. .
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I. Victoria. (A. 13/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C0., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, CCP. 338.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
I 6, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP. 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei I 5 I,
Antwerp.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
1 00 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librarla Alberto Sanchez Veloso
O'Reilly y Villegas, Havana. - Libreria Eco¬
nómica, Pte' Zayas 505-7 Apartado I 13,
Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Paris, 7». CCP. 12598-48
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6).
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asaf AM Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I ; Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Rajkamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permata"
Djalan Nusantara 22, Djakarta
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco. Avenue du Musée. Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 9 1
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.( 1 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
33, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd.. Times House, 135, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
C.G.T. Van Dorp & C (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Willem5tad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
> Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. CM.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass. 7, Oslo. (N. kr. I 0)
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374, 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de Correos 2018,
Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., I 104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46,
Warsaw. 10 (Zl. 50.)
PORTUGAI	 Dias & Andrada Lda.
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. ( I 0/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publication's
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz» I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-481 I. (Fr. S. 7).
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church'
Street, Pretoria ( 1 0/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.( 1 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($ 3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjlga,
Terazije 27/1 I. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
»V
GIANT GROUPER on its way to an Indian
market seems to dwarf the woman carrying
it. Grouper is the name given to southern
species of the sea bass grouplarge vora¬
cious fishes which "come in different
colours" including red, black and blue.
One of the family, the Nassau grouper,
attracts the unwelcome attentions of ene¬
mies by its distinct striped markings. A
camouflage expert, it turns dark when
alarmed and makes for a hiding place.
FAO photo by P. Boucay
**J
'"
OS*
sa
Jfc. *
áh
j-
J A
* x
it
V
]]>
</page>
</document>
