<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064724eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
í¿t loll WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m
SEP
1960
(/3th year)
Price : I -stg. (U.K.)
. 30 cents (U. S.)
0.7 0 NF. (France)
Q>
III
Ml
99o,
igOQOQOOQOOj
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
© Pierre Pittet
WORLD CA
One of the greatest problems of our time is that of food and peoplemore than half
of the world's population is seriously underfed. For the past 14 years, this problem
of population and food supplies has been in the forefront of the work of the U.N.
Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), which has now launched a world-wide
Freedom-from-Hunger Campaign. The first objective of this five-year action
programme which began in July is to bring home to people and governments the
extent and cause of hunger and malnutrition in the world. This first phase will
culminate in a World Food Congress in 1963. Mr. B.R. Sen, Director-General
of FAO, has emphasized that there is no question of hunger being vanquished
during the five-year campaign : "Our aim is to add substantially to man's
knowledge of the problem and of what can be done about it. We want to build a
firm basis for continuing action in the years ahead." (The Unesco Courier will
deal with various aspects of this important world problem in a future issue.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
à WINDOW OHM ON FHI WOIIO
ner
SEPTEMBER 1960
1 3 T H YEAR
Contents
No. 9
COVER PHOTO
Head of an African girl drawn
by Bouba, a 12-year-old boy
from the pilot-school at Pltoa
In the Cameroons. For the
remarkable story of Bouba
and his class-mates and how
they have built a chain of
friendship and understanding
with schoolchildren In
Europe, see pages 4 to 13.
Drawing, Centre d'Art
Africain, Pltoa
PITOA-PILOT SCHOOL IN A CAMEROON VILLAGE
By René Caloz
.8 BOUBA AND JACQUES
Birth of a dialogue between Africa and Europe
13 CHILD AESOPS OF THE CAMEROONS
14 DESERT OR DELUGE AT THE FLICK OF A SWITCH
France builds the world's first ' ecotron '
By Daniel Behrman
16 THE STAIRWAY OF THE GIANTS
Ricefields reaching up to the sky
By Paul Almasy
20 FINE ARTS ON POSTAGE STAMPS
By David J. Jacobs
25 A CENTURY OF «BLACK GOLD'
The story of two million oil wells
By W. H. Owens
30 IN THESE WASTES WHAT VISIONARY PASTS...
Airplane and spade uncover treasures of the Sudan
By W. B. Emery
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational,
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7\ France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Alexandre Leventis
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Célia Bertin
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Yeniamin Matchavarianl
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Scientific and Cultural
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 60.1.150 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Remarkable creative skill and imagination are expressed
in this drawing from the Art Centre at Pltoa (Cameroons)
made by a youngster from one of the bush villages
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
PITOA - PILOT SCHOOL
IN A CAMEROON VILLAGE
by Rene Caloz
PERCHED on an upturned packing case
in the centre of the classroom, Bou-
kar, the little Cameroon boy, hesitatingly read out the
story he had written:
"While I am playing I find a little snake. I hit it with
a stick. My father comes up. *What are you doing?',
he asks me. 'I am hitting this smake.' My father takes
the stick and he hits the snake too."
When Boukar had finished, he looked up from, the paper
from which he had been reading. Judging from the faces
around him the impression he had made, he proudly
began to read it a second time. But the teacher told
him to go back to his place, and called a lijttle girl, Isma,
to come out to the blackboard.
Isma jumped up, took a piece of chalk, rubbed her head
reflectively for a moment, and then began to draw. As
the chalk grated on the blackboard, Boukar gazed
dreamily at the packing case. This old box had become
a kind of tribune on which all the ambitions of a little
world were centered. Each morning the teacher would
ask : " Who is going on the box ?". Only those children
who had been able to make up and write out a short
story on their own were eligible for this honour. The
rest, the majority of the class, were still only able to
describe orally what they had drawn.
At last Isma put down her chalk and turned a roguish
eye towards the teacher, who asked her to explain the
drawing. Looking at the blackboard with her head on
one side, she said: "A woman is walking along the road.
A bird comes along and steals some of her hair. With
the hair the bird makes its nest." Smiling broadly, Isma
turned around as the class roared with laughter.
Both Boukar and Isma go to school in the Cameroon
village of Pitoa. This mountainous, northern region is
inhabited by the Fulbés and the Kirdis, two tribes which
were once enemies. At Pitoa, 200 little Africans from vil¬
lages in the bush live in at the school where they receive
a primary education.
During the past few years, the school at Pitoa has
become a real pilot centre for education in the African
countries thanks to the perception and devotion of its
staff and its teacher-director, Roger Lagrave. Here, like
a bridge spanning differences between centuries and races,
the most up-to-date methods are used to teach children
who have come straight from remote villages in the bush.
In any country, the first day at school makes a big
psychological impression on a child. It is his first real
break with the warm, sheltered atmosphere of home life.
On the African child who has just left the far-off tribal
village where he was born, the effect is even greater.
From one day to the next he is plunged into a totally
strange civilization and way of life.
Added to the impact of this disturbing change are the
feelings created by the long separation from family and
friends. At Pitoa, therefore, the teachers need to use
special methods and even to devise new ones capable of
overcoming these inner conflicts and of opening up young
minds to a different world.
In solving these problems, nothing has worked as
well as painting and drawing. When they reach school,
the children speak only their tribal languages. They
After drawing this picture on the blackboard, Isma explains: "A bird
comes along and takes strands of a woman's hair to make its nest."
quickly and instinctively accept drawing as a means of
expression and communication.
At the very first lesson, the teacher asks the children
to make drawings of anything that comes into the heads.
The first efforts are always clumsy and disorganized a
jumble of things which the child sees around him every
day : gourds, huts, animals, trees, etc. The names of these,
the children quickly learn to translate into French under
the teacher's guidance.
Gradually the drawings become more orderly. As their
skill with pencil and brush grows, the children encourag¬
ed to use their imagination begin to draw scenes from
village life. Graphic expression precedes and then
stimulates oral expression, bringing the first verbs to
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
PILOT SCHOOL
(Cont'd)
enrich a growing vocabulary. They start to make up their
first simple phrasés in French. Only then do writing les¬
sons begin.
Mr. Lagrave, educational director of the Pitoa School,
has noted that by the end of the first term the most
advanced children are able to write their first words in
French. By now a few others are speaking it, but the
majority of the class is still at the drawing stage. By
the end of the first school year most children have started
to write in French.
Drawing and painting have become the key to a new
world. They have helped children, already somewhat
perplexed by the rudiments of the new language, to adapt
their outlooks from those of children in an African tribal
village, while giving them full scope for individual ex¬
pression.
The teachers at Pitoa found to their surprise that when
these children were left to draw on their own sources of
inspiration and were not given any technical advice, they
showed a natural creative aptitude and a sense of colour
harmony even more truly spontaneous than those with
which young Europeans, for example, are apt to surprise
one.
From an early age, European youngsters come under
all kinds of formative influences. The children from the
bush, however, start almost from scratch. They have to
seek everything within themselves, just as did our early
ancestors. With uninhibited powers of inspiration, a pow¬
erful urge to express themselves, a brush and some paints,
they have drawn from within themselves an youthful
African art style that is both original and rich.
This style is expressed in certain, often repeated themes.
There are, for example, the birds of the bushherons,
marabou-storks, ducks and cormorantsall offering
colourful visions which impress themselves on the minds
of youngsters who have spent their childhood along the
banks of Africa's rivers. Here, as in other lands, a
youngster will set down on paper what he knows, and not
just what he sees. In depicting the cormorant he also
shows the fishes it has swallowed and, in admiration for
its angling skill, he sometimes pictures it with several
beaks and long, supple necks.
Ten here is the serpent; the enemy, an ever-present
threat to small bare feet scampering in the bush. So it
is punished in effigy, shown pinned down by that killer
of snakes, the secretary-bird. Or sometimes it becomes
the animal totem, a symbol of taboo. But in all cases,
the harmony of colours transforms these representations
of reality. Thus, from the art centre in Pitoa has flowed
a rich harvest of original and audacious works, full of
suprising power and delightful freshness.
What becomes of these artists whose ages range from
nine to fourteen ? Unfortunately, as is often the case, this
childhood genius fades as maturity approaches. Only a
few of the fortunate ones manage to retain it. The school¬
children of Pitoa will become doctors, teachers and eng¬
ineers. But it has all been worthwhile ; painting has been
the magic charm to exorcise the spells besetting their
childhood, helping them to take the giant leap from the
African bush into the mid-20th century.
When the schoolchild at Pitoa has completed the three
stages of this primary basic education (drawing, spoken
language and writing) he has still not escaped from
his isolation. He knows how to write in French. But to
whom can he write ? He can read. But what will he find
to read ? Unlike youngsters in European countries, for
example, these children of the Cameroons until recent¬
ly had no books suitable to their knowledge and capabili¬
ties other than school textbooks. Thus they came to look
on reading as a purely classroom activity.
To these two problems of isolation and reading material,
the Modern Education Group of the Cameroons has also
found ingenious solutions and has put them into prac¬
tice. These educators provided reading material corres¬
ponding to the educational level and background of this
young public, by producing collections of short stories:
"Fables of the Bush," "Mamadou, the little Shepherd,"
"'At the World's End," which are lively, documentary texts
telling about such things as the millet crop, the mangrove
tree, monkeys, the river, fishing, and so on.
Roger Lagrave went even further and, using some of
the methods developed by the French educator, C. Frei-
net, he got his pupils to help him in writing these new
books. Out of this grew the "African Book Club", whose
publication fund is partly covered by the sale of children's
drawings and also through radio broadcasts.
Each year, the boys and girls in one or more of the
classes set to work on a new book whose preparation is
also the occasion for a concentrated study of the French
language. The themes chosen for these books reveal a
progressive broadening of horizons. The first, "Malik
Child of the Bush," described the life of a typical child
and his family in a Cameroons village. "Two Children in
the Northern Cameroons" told the story of a child as
he left his village and began to experience the realities
of the larger life of his country.
The third book, "Bouba and Jacques" had a special
significance for it brought the children in contact with
another country, France, and a way of life very different
DRAWING THEIR
1 DRAWING is used as a bridge leading to reading and
by the children from the bush who attend the school
Pitoa, Cameroons. First efforts with pencil and brush are usually
a jumble of familiar objectshuts, gourds, trees, animals. From
the names of these, the children learn their first words in French.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
from their own. All the material for this book came from
a pen-friends' exchange between the boys and girls of
Pitoa and those of Costes-Gozon in the Aveyron Depart¬
ment of southern France.
Each week, in the form of questions and answers bet¬
ween a French boy, Jacques, and his African friend, Bouba,
villagers in France and African bush dwellers nearly
4,000 miles away got to know more about each other
(see page 8).
The fourth book in the series, completed this year, is
entitled Nous de partout (We from everywhere). Having
got to know his own country, the child sets out to explore
other parts of the world and discovers that modern tech¬
niques can help to free him from his isolation.
Suggestive of the future possibilities of this admirable
educational venture born in Africa are the words of the
preface to this latest book :
"In gaining its independence, the Cameroons has taken
its place among the nations.
"In this book we would like you to meet some of these
nationsour friends. But this is not a geography book,
and you will not find in it the names of rivers and their
lengths nor the names of mountains and their heights.
Instead, every page shows children, many children and
their ordinary day-to-day lives in these far-off countries.
"They have sent us their school newspapers in which
they have described their life, their work and play, their
problems and their hopes.
"Reading what they have written, we have been very
touched for we have found there our friends, as they
really are, from every continent our friends from
everywhere. For wherever they come from, from hot
lands or from the cold ones, whether they eat wheat, or
millet or rice, they are all our friends and this is
something that no frontiers can change.
"And we need this friendship so that we may work
together to build a vast and a brotherly world. This
friendship makes us very happy."
WAY TO FRENCH WITHOUT TEARS
2 GROWING SKILL of young artists plus freedom to use
their imagination quickly brings a change. Scenes from
village life replace the "jumble" drawings. Vocabularies expand,
and soon the children are able to write down in French the names
of the objects and persons they have depicted In their drawings.
3 HARVEST SCENE with the family at work in the fields
« was drawn by a young child from the bush after attending
school for two months. Through his first drawings he learned
words like father, mother, millet and gourd. Group scenes
introduced verbs, and now he begins writing his first sentences.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
BOUBA AND JACQUES
THE BIRTH OF A DIALOGUE
BETWEEN AFRICA & EUROPE
Over the signature of Bouba, the schoolchildren of Pitoa (Cameroons)
began an exchange of letters a few years ago. with Jacques and the
schoolchildren of Costes-Gozon, a tiny village in southern France. They
wrote of their work, their games, and their everyday life. The letters
became part of the reading and writing programmes of both schools
(See page 5) . Each week they were read, explained, discussed and reco-
pied. In this way the Boubas of Africa and the Jacques of Europe
contributed to a better understanding of each other. Their efforts have
resulted in a delightful and informative little book Notre Ami Jacques
(Our Friend Jacques) published by the Club African du Livre, at Pitoa,
from which tha passages on the following pages have been selected.
Pitoa (Cameroons), October 1.
My dear friend Jacques,
I am very happy to be writ¬
ing to you. My name is Bouba
and my father's name is Cadji.
He grows millet. I chase away
the birds and the monkeys
from his crops and I tend his
herd of goats. I have a sister called Djénabou and a little
brother whose name is Oumar. My mother grinds the
millet, crushes the ground nuts and sweeps out the hut.
I hope you and your parents are well. Goodbye for now
and I hope to hear from you soon.
Your friend: BOUBA.
Costes-Gozon (France)
October 1.
My dear friend Bouba,
My name is Jacques Lacroix.
My father is a farmer. He has
a flock of 30 sheep and four
pigs. My mother looks after
the house, cleans it, prepares
the meals does the washing and helps my father in the
fields.
I have a brother called Maurice and two sisters,
Jeanette and Léonie.
I'm glad I can write to you and I hope you are well.
Your friend: JACQUES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
THIS IS MY HOME
BOUBA: In June, when the school closes I shall
walk down the hill towards my village, very happy to
see my home again.
All around it are young cotton plants, corn and
millet. It has a straw roof which keeps it fresh and
cool. The side which looks out on the road has a veran¬
dah. The second side has a window but as it is unpro¬
tected, it is always drenched during the rainy season.
The third side also has a verandah held up by two open
brick walls. This is where my father quietly sits sewing
his clothes. We also eat our meals there and sleep out
at night during the hot season.
I shall be glad to sleep in the house where I was born.
JACQUES: My home seems to hang on a red and
green hillside: brick-red soil and green alfalfa and
young corn. The house is built of stone covered by
rough-cast plaster. The walls are pink and the tiled
roof is covered with moss. Some grey and white pigeons
circle overhead and with a fluttering of wings land on
the stone-edged pigeon-house.
In another building on the far side of the stone
courtyard are the barn, the sheep-pen, the stable and
the pigsty.
In an open shed leaning against a wall my father
keeps his cart and his binder. In the same shed is the
sling in which we put the ox when it is being shod.
*!**
fönt -Ca. e^rrrvrüO^oXic^.C^uCi^L
BALL AND WHISTLE
BOUBA: We've decided to make a ball. Armed with
knives we go off to the river bank. The sap from the
trees here is like the latex of rubber trees. We make
a gash in a tree and the sap starts to flow. I cover
one of my thumbs with the sap which starts to harden.
To get a thicker layer we add some manioc flour. Then
we let some of the sap run on to Abbo's stomach. The
sap spreads out and solidifies. I go and fetch a hollow
reed stem. I take off the latex from my thumb and
have a small cylinder. With the hollow stem I blow
into it and the latex swells up until it makes a sphere
about eight inches across. To give it a thicker sur¬
face, I spread on it the sap which covers Abbo's sto¬
mach. Finally the skin of the bladder we have made
is nearly half an inch thick. We go back to the village
very pleased with ourselves and in the evening we play
with the ball.
JACQUES: / am guarding the pigs in the chestnut
grove. I pick out a new, straight, smooth branch and
I cut a piece from it about six inches long and about
as thick as my thumb. Halfway down I cut into the
bark just down to the wood. With the handle of. my
knife I tap very lightly on the bark and with a twisting
movement I slide it carefully from the wood. About
half an inch from the end of the bare wood and in the
centre, I cut a triangular notch, and from here to the
end of the wood I cut out a narrow shaving. I wet the
wood with saliva and slide back the tube of bark over
it. Now I cut out of the bark a piece half an inch long
and a quarter of an inch wide above the first hole I
made in the wood. My whistle is ready. I blow it and
keep blowing, blowing, blowing.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
NIGHT FISHING
WITH STICK
AND TORCH
BOUBA: When it has got dark
Nohou, the man with the powerful
voice, cries: "Let all those who have
eaten their fill, who are full of
strength and courage, come fishing
with me; let all those who are still
hungry stay here to wash the
cooking pots of their mothers and
their brides-to-be."
Picking up sticks, matches and
torches of dried grass, we run to
join him.
At the river's edge we light our
torches and wade out until the
water is up to our thighs.
Mamadou and I fish together. A
fish, lured by the light, comes close.
It seems dazzled and stays quite
still. With a quick blow from his
stick, Mamadou stuns the fish. I
grab it easily and put it into a
gourd.
Suddenly I see a big catfish. This
time I hit out and stun the fish.
But my stick breaks in two.
Then I see another big fish and
am just about to grab it when
Mamadou hits my hand. I start
crying and to comfort me, Mama¬
dou gives me half his catch.
HARVEST TIME
BOUBA: In the field the ears of
millet are drooping towards the
ground and the stems are bent. It is
harvest time.
My father gives 15 bowls of millet
to my mother. She grinds it into flour
and makes a meal for the labourers.
My father kills a goat. When these
preparations are finished, my father
goes to borrow some machetes. He
warns the neighbours that there is
work to be done and then he goes to
see the witch-doctor. The next day
work begins. With their machetes,
the men cut the stalks a few inches
above the soil. They lay them out
on the ground in parallel rows. It is
hard work, but the rhythm of a tom¬
tom helps to keep them at it.
We children follow the harvesters,
chewing millet stems as though they
were sugar cane.
Three days later, the women cut off
the ears from the stalks and carry
away the ears in large baskets to the
place where they will be threshed.
JACQUES: The oxen are pulling
the harvester-binder. I grease it well,
put in a good supply of string and
prepare a reserve supply and a spare
blade.
My father leads the oxen. Robert
is in the driving seat; with a lever he
can raise or lower the blade according
to the cut he wishes to make.
The oxen pull hard. The cutting
blade rattles in its frame, the drum
squeaks as it turns, the belts carry
the wheat up to the binder which
gives a bang as each sheaf is tied;
the sheaf carrier tilts as Robert pres¬
ses a pedal, and the sheaves fall.
Mother and I stack the sheaves in
lines. The thistles prick our fingers.
ANGLERS WITH A TRIDENT
JACQUES : When my father and my uncle were
schoolchildren, they would leave home early in the morn¬
ing so as to be able to go fishing before classes began.
Usually about a dozen boys went down to the stream
to fish with a trident.
A few of the boys kept watch in case the gamekeeper
should pass that way. Two others had an iron trident
attached to a long stick. They went carefully towards
the water and when they saw a trout motionless just
above the bed of the stream, their trident flashed into
the water. Impaled by the prongs, the fish fought madly.
But they quickly had it out on the bank and in a twink¬
ling it was hidden in a satchel between the schoolbooks
and the sandwiches.
Then these young rascals went to a place well hidden
by thick bushes and made a fire on which to cook their
catch. How good it tasted.
Sometimes they were late for school and when the
teacher scolded them, they replied, timidly: "We had to
help with the chores at home."
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
MAGIC RIDERS AND CYCLISTS
BOUBA: I went to visit my brother Oumarou, one of the
chief's warriors. Moussa and Zoussoufa told me: "Tomorrow
you will see Djaoro Sanda, the magic horseman."
The next day in the centre of the village Djaoro Sanda is
there beside his horse. A large crowd had gathered to watch
the show.
First Djaoro stuck pointed sticks into the ground in a
straight line. "Hup, hup," he cried to his horse which at
once set off at a gallop. When they reached the first stick,
Djaoro slid under the horse's belly until he was hanging by
his legs. Without slowing down he snatched up one stick,
then another and another until he finally had them all
in his hand. Then he twisted himself back up into the
saddle.
"Bravo! Djaoro Sanda," cried the spectators. Some people,
who will believe anything, say that Djaoro can turn himself
into a panther or a snake without frightening his horse. His
horse is like any other horse, but it has been trained for a
long time by its master.
JACQUES: One Sunday I went to see a motor-cycle cross*
country race. In the afternoon cars began to arrive, pulling
small trailers on which the motor-cycles were fixed.
The circuit was marked out. It went down the side of a
little hill, up another hill, with a sharp turn at the top, and
down into the bed of a dried-up lake. Then it went over a
springboard and back up the first hill to the starting point.
The riders brought their machines to the start line and
when the signal was given they roared off in a cloud of
dust. First away was No. 5 which shot down the hill at full
speed. It went over the springboard, shot into the air and
came down five yards further on. The machines went round
the course ten times and No. 5 was the winner.
THE DAY WE WERE HERDSMEN
BOUBA: My father calls me. "Go into the hut and take
down the stick and the gourd that are hanging from the
roof," he says. "Now go after your big brother," he tells me
"you are going to look after the herd."
I am pleased at the idea of taking care of the animals.
With the gourd in my hand and the stick over my shoulder I
run after my brother and take his place. At the water's
edge our beasts drink their fill. -I cut a stem of wild millet
and make a little flute. While the goats are nibbling at the
young grass, I join the other little herdsmen, who are also
busy making flutes. We blow our flutes together and make
some fine tunes.
Then we send the smallest children back to the village.
"You, Oumarou, bring us some millet flour, and you, Dji-
brilla, some dried fish." We do our cooking and drink the
water in our gourds. In the evening we sing as we go home.
JACQUES: Julian and I have bßen told to watch over the
oxen. We leave them to graze and we run to the cherry
tree. Julian climbs it, cuts off branches loaded with cherries
and throws them to me. We eat lots of cherries and we
even swallow the stones.
An hour goes by and Julian comes down from the tree.
When we go back to the field the oxen have disappeared.
We look for them in the other fields and finally we go back
to the village.
Father is waiting for us on the stairs. "The oxen came back
on their own at full gallop" he tells us severely.
We feel vexed and foolish. We hardly eat any supper and
we don't sleep much that night we both have stomach ache.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
WHEN
GROW UP
BOUBA: I shall raise cows, sheep and
goats. I won't grow any crops, but with
the milk from my cows I shall buy a
big gourd of millet.
With the meat of a goat or a ram
killed each month we shall eat well.
Clothes will be no problem. I shall
take a six-years-old bull to market
and with what it brings I shall buy
fine clothes.
My son 'will guard my sheep, my
daughter will look after the goats and
I shall take the cows out to the pastu¬
res. There I may have to endure rain
and storms, but the delicious, creamy
milk will soon make me forget these
discomforts.
When I grow old I shall employ paid
shepherds. In the shadow of the
"danki", I shall stretch myself on my
sleeping mat, a glass of coffee by my
side. "Bouba has more than a hundred
head of livestock; he is one of the rich¬
est among us," the villagers will say.
When I am 80 years old I shall sell
some of my animals and I shall spend
the money on a pilgrimage to Mecca.
JACQUES' FRIENDS. When I am
20 I shall have a tractor and I shall
use it to work the land. I shall plough
up all the fields. (Roger.)
/ shall be a hairdresser. I shall
cut peoples' hair, beards .that have
grown too long and sometimes... an ear
or two. (Paul.)
Perhaps I shall be the Member of
Parliament for my region. (Alphonse.)
J shall be a postman. I shall go
from house to house delivering letters,
telegrams and parcels. (Antoine.)
PORTRAITS FROM PITOA. All drawings on pages 4.
to 13 are by children from the Pitoa school, Cameroons.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
CHILD AESOPS OF THE CAMEROONS
THE CROCODILE AND THE BULLOCK THE HORSE AND THE DONKEY
The bullock is thirsty and goes to the river to drink.
He goes into deep water. A crocodile seizes him by
the hoof and pulls him towards the bottom. The
bullock pulls hard too .
The crocodile is, very strong. But so is the bullock.
Who will win?
The bullock says to the crocodile: "Cayman !, just
look at the sun."
While the crocodile is looking at the sun, the bullock
gores him with his horn.
The bullock is the winner.
Dairou Issa (Tcholiré School)
The donkey goes into the horse's stable. He says to
the horse:
"I'm stronger than you. Let's have a fight."
The donkey gives the horse a kick. The horse grabs
the donkey's ears with his teeth and pulls hard.
Now all donkeys have long ears. They don't fight
horses any more.
Isma, aged 10
THE FAWN AND THE FLY
The fawn and the fly lived together in the forest.
"Let's play at hide-and-seek", said the fly. "She who wins
will be queen of the forest. You go and hide and I will look
for you." Then the fly settled on the back of the fawn's head.
The fawn hid herself inside a thick bush and called out: "Where
am I?"
"There you are, there you are", cried the fly. "I've won.
Now I will go and hide."
Then she flew back and settled again on the fawn's head.
"Look for me," she caDed. The fawn looked everywhere, but
never found the fly.
At the end of the day the fly came out from her hiding place
and said:
"You never found me, so I am queen of the forest."
Richard Kamga (Gauganté School)
THE MOUSE AND THE BIRD
The mouse and the bird are friends. They decide to build a
house in the bush. The mouse says to the bird: "You go and
collect the wood and I'll go and fetch the grass."
While the mouse looks for the grass a snake catches it and
eats it up. While the bird is fetching the wood a man catches
it and gives it to his child to play with.
The mouse and the bird did not build their house. They are
not even friends now. The mouse lives in the ground. The bird
lives in the sky.
Hamadou Daboré, aged 9
THE CORMORANTS
One day I go with my mother to fetch water from the
river.
I see a cormorant fishing. I take a pebble and throw
it at him.
The cormorant rises with a big fish in its beak. Then
it flies along just skimming the water.
Another cormorant appears. He says to the first: "Wait
for me." Then he dives into the water and comes up
with a fish. He shares it with his friend.
When they have finished eating the fish, the two birds
fly away, singing as they go.
Wabili, aged 9 (Pitoa School)
Texts on this page are taken from Bibliothèque de l'Ecolier Africain,
published by Editions du Groupe Camerounais d'Education Moderne.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE FLICK OF A SWITCH
by Daniel Behrman
H
ow do plants adapt themselves and
survive during a torrid summer in
the Sahara or a long spell of heavy rain in Provence.
Scientists hope that they will soon learn the answers to
some of the puzzling problems of plant behaviour from a
special laboratory, an "ecotron" which is to be built at
Montpellier in southern France.
By simply flicking over a switch they will be able to
obtain precise data on plants growing in "climates"
artificially created in the "ecotron" whose work will
reinforce the offensive launched by science against some
of the worst problems afflicting the world's arid zones
one third of its land surface.
Now in the planning stage with half its total budget of
$1,200,000 already alloted, the ecotron will be the newest
chapter in the four-centuries-old history of Montpellier as
a hothouse of botany. It Will be the laboratory of the
University of Montpellier's Institute of Botany, headed by
Prof. Louis Emberger.
Professor Emberger is one of the world's leading au¬
thorities on plant ecologythe study of relationships of
plants to their environmentand it was he who christened
the "ecotron." Part of its name comes from ecology and
the other part from the cyclotrons used in nuclear physics.
Appropriately enough, the ecotron will enable measure¬
ments of plant behaviour to be made with a precision
usually associated with nuclear physics.
The Institute at Montpellier is already something of a
mecca for scientists from countries in the world's dry belt
who study there under Unesco fellowships enabling them
to specialize in plant ecology.
The "ecotron" will be a powerful weapon in the fight
science is waging against aridity and the misery it en¬
genders for hundreds of millions. Here, a climate will not
only be reproduced With its exact conditions of light,
temperature and humidity (as ecologists themselves say, it
would be ridiculous to spend more than a million dollars
to duplicate what nature offers at no cost), but it will
be "taken apart" so that the ecologist will be able to
learn which of these conditions is essential to plant life.
The plant scientist can turn his findings over to the
agricultural engineer whose task is to raise food produc¬
tion. For example, if soil is over-irrigated a plant often
"transpires" too much and wastes water. At the same
time, too much water can actually lower its absorption of
carbon dioxide in the process of photosynthesis, whereby
plants create living matter from carbon dioxide, water and'
mineral salts.
In other words, the study of how a plant behaves in the
ecotron will allow scientists to determine precisely how
much irrigation water it should receive and how often
thereby both raising its productivity and reducing its
consumption of scarce water.
14
How will these studies be carried out? Recently, we
had an opportunity to take a tour of the Montpellier
ecotron on paper, of course with Profesor Emberger and
Dr. Frode E. Eckardt, who is in charge of its construction.
Once it is completed as a wing of the brand-new
building of the Institute of Botany, the ecotron will
outwardly be a long, low construction of abstract, zigzag
design in the shade of the ancient trees of Montpellier's
botanical gardens, founded in 1593.
Inwardly, it will be a world of its own, so much so that
its staff will have to pass through an "airlock" to go to
work. In special rooms, research workers will change their
clothes, shower, and then put on sterile smocks and, for
certain tasks, gloves and boots. The purpose of these
precautions is to prevent the introduction of insects and
viruses from the outside world into the ecotron.
The heart of the ecotron will be its control room. Here,
a single man with panels of switches and rheostats will be
able to set the weather in the laboratory rooms. To be
exact, he will mainly oversee the setting of the weather
by automation. For example, it will be possible to take
graphs of temperature, humidity and sunlight from re¬
corders in, let's say, central Tunisia and then feed them
into this electronic equipment which will reproduce the
same conditions within a given room of the ecotron.
I
t may very well be one of four rooms
in the laboratory's most highly auto¬
mated section. There, an experimenter will be able to
vary, at will, light, temperature and humidity, and the
carbon dioxide content of the air. Like a stage manager,
he will create a setting where plants can act their parts.
In fact, the lights for these rooms are to be made by the
same firm responsible for stage lighting in Paris theatres
and for illuminating castles in the "sound and light
shows" all over France.
Next to each room will be a small laboratory where
readings can be taken without entering the room. This is
extremely important because the mere presence of a
human being in such an experiment can seriously modify
its conditions.
This is also one of the main respects in which Mont¬
pellier's ecotron will differ from "phytotrons" already in
use in the United States, France, the Netherlands and the
U.S.S.R. There, the growth of plants over a long-term
period is studied in large rooms where the temperature is
held constant. To observe how a plant reacts to a change
in temperature, the experimenter wheels it into a different
room kept at a different temperature. One of the
objectives of the phytotron is to make a highly precise
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
study of the physiology of plants with a view towards
raising yields. Experiments are often conducted on a
large scale.
Montpellier is more concerned with such delicate pro¬
cesses as photosynthesis and transpiration and, in general,
learning how plants react to changes in their environment.
Smaller rooms, in which the climate can be varied, will
be used.
Both in the phytotron and the ecotron, botany is
emerging from what might be called its "hand
craftsmanhip" stage. The scientist will be freed from
such chores as hourly readings which will be registered
and co-ordinated automatically. At the same time, the
ecotron's electronic brain will "remember" experiments on
perforated tape and will be able to duplicate them at any
time.
The ecotron will also include a cold room where tem¬
peratures as low as 5°F can be created, and four green¬
house rooms where plants will "perform" under natural
light while other conditions are varied. Temperatures in
these rooms will be controlled: in the hottest of the four,
they will be "Saharan." In another room, plants will be
subjected to small doses of radioactivity.
^-""^^ÄIl^V^Hii ^ , ¿ *
y rfiàî
fe
Unesco-Aubert de la Rue
The world's arid zones cover one-third of its land surface. Not all of
this area is as badly afflicted as this wasteland in Latin America due
to total erosion of the soil following excessive deforestation and bad
agricultural practices. Today, science has taken the offensive against
some of the worst problems of the arid zones, aided by research carried
out In specialized laboratories like Montpellier's Institute of Botany.
A
ix this will take place only a few
hundred yards away from what Pro¬
fessor Emberger calls "the birthplace of plant ecology."
Opposite the institute in the botanical gardens stands
"La Montagne" created by Richer de Belleval, the 16th
century founder- of the gardens. The "mountain" is a
ridge about 100 yards long and 5 yards high, running from
East to West. On its southern slope, Richer de Belleval
planted sunloving Mediterranean vegetation which thrives
in dry soil. On its shady northern slope, the pioneer in¬
troduced more northern varieties.
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
Today, the rest is almost hallucinating. One side of the
tiny ridge is a Provençal hillside with perfumed rosemary,
spurge and other low sturdy plants baking in the sun.
The other is a thick forest, mysterious and romantic with
ivy winding around massive trunks.
That was the beginning of botany in Montpellier during
the reign of good King Henri IV who wanted every
Frenchman to have a chicken in his cooking pot. Since
then, Richer be Belleval's successors have reigned there in
unbroken line down to Louis Emberger. The list is
studded with the greats of botany. Here, in the early
18th century, Pierre Magnol (who gave his name to the
magnolia) held the chair of botany. Here, Augustin Pyra-
mus de Candolle pioneered a new system of plant classifi¬
cation in the early 19th century and planted a garden still
piously preserved in its original form. Another great link
in this chain of botanists was Charles Flahault who died
in 1945 at the age of 84.
Professor Emberger, the present head, has been fighting
for his ideas almost since the day when he first became
interested in botany as a child in his native Alsace. He
once wrote : "Often we are asked about the usefulness of
an institute of botany in the atomic age. The fact is that
plants have the power to make a synthesis of life. Then
do they not have anything to teach us? We go into
ecstasy over the power of the atom but plants have the
power of life."
T
o help scientists from countries in
the arid zone itself to read the story
of vegetation, Unesco has been offering a series of fellow¬
ships in plant ecology at Montpellier.
Recently, a group of six young scientists made the pil¬
grimage to Montpellier from Iran, Iraq, Jordan, Morocco,
the Sudan and Turkey, and fellowships are now being
awarded to eight more for a two-year course. When we
visited Montpellier, four of the first group had already
completed their stays in which they worked in plant eco¬
logy, including mapping, for periods running from nine
to eighteen months. Their fellowships also covered stays
at a leading soil science laboratory near Paris.
But we did have an opportunity to meet two Unesco
fellows who had stayed in Montpellier for intensive study,
Dr. Ali Zargàri of Iran and Mr. Elmi Taher Amireh. of
Jordan.
Dr. Zargari is a professor of botany at the Higher Tea¬
cher Training College of the University of Teheran and
director of the herbarium at Iran's arid zone research
institute. At forty, he is also the author of a three-volume
work on Iranian medicinal plants which has been honour¬
ed by a royal prize in Teheran.
His work at Montpellier, he told us, has changed his
own viewpoint from that of the "pure botanist" collecting
specimens to that of the ecologist, who is interested in
soil and weather as well as in species of plants. In this
respect, ecology sums up rather happily the goal of Unes¬
co's arid zone programme, to unite various branches of
science into a common front against the desert.
Mr. Amireh told us he was an inspector of horticulture
in Amman. At Montpellier he is studying the water eco¬
nomy of Quercus coccifera, the hardy kermes oak of
Languedoc. On sunny days, he gets up at 4 a.m. to be
at his testing station twelve miles outside the city in the
maquis by 'sunrise. There he measures the plant's eva¬
poration and transpiration, cutting off a sample every
fifteen minutes and then weighing it five or six times at
intervals of one minute. This is repeated at fifteen-
minute intervals until sundown when Mr. Amireh returns
to Montpellier and puts his sample into an oven to learn
its weight when completely dry.
Upon his return to Jordan, Mr. Amireh would like to
attempt similar experiments on local plants to find out
just how much precious water they consume.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE
STAIRWAY
OF THE
GIANTS
by Paul Almasy
Photos © Almasy, Paris
Some 2,000 years ago, the tribes of the Upper Bontok Valley
on the Philippines' island of Luzon completely transformed
their wild mountain fastnesses by a grandiose feat of agri¬
cultural engineering. Taking between 1,500 and 2,000 years
to do so, they had terraced the mountainsides into a series
of ricefields that look (above right) like a stairway for giants.
To.retain these narrow fields they built some 15,000 miles of
high stone walls and laid down innumerable bamboo pipes to
irrigate the rice. Tattooed on arms and chest, peasant
(opposite page) ¡s a descendant of the men who built these
innumerable terraces. These mountain-dwellers, men and
women alike, smoke cigars made from homegrown tobacco.
Above, housewife relaxes with cigarofChurchillian dimensions.
16
In diverse lands and throughout history man,
the settler and the farmer, has often challeng¬
ed a hostile Nature, transforming desert,
jungle or steppe to draw his sustenance from
the soil. Yet rarely has he ever changed a landscape as
profoundly as in the Bontok Valley on the Philippines'
island of Luzon.
Here, in the heart of a wild mountain range, the famous
terraced ricefields of the Ifugaos, spreading over several
hundred square miles, are a green and living testament
to the ingenuity of this people in devising agricultural
techniques a masterpiece of human patience and endu¬
rance.
Describing this region is impossible only pictures can
give an idea of the scope of this achievement one of
history's most remarkable examples of agricultural deve¬
lopment. In the Banaue Valley alone, terraces cover
400 square kilometres and the walls supporting them total
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
some 15,000 miles in length. Archaeologists and historians
who have studied the Bontok ricefields estimate that the
islanders must have worked from 1,500 to 2,000 years to
build the terraces and their systems of irrigation. There
are terraced ricefields in China, Japan and Indonesia^but
these ricefields of the Ifugaos in the Luzon mountains are
by far the biggest in the world, with the highest and the
best-constructed stone walls.
It is believed that a small tribe which emigrated from
Indonesia taught the Ifugaos how to construct ricefields
in terraces. This must have happened some 4,000 years
ago. Remains studied by specialists suggest that the
Upper Bontok Valley took on its present-day aspect only
at the beginning of the Christian era.
We know very little about the Ifugaos who, 4,000 years
ago, took on this gigantic task which the people of the
Philippines call the "eighth wonder of the world." They
probably came from the Asian mainland and they reached
Luzon while seeking a new land in which to settle or after
fleeing from a powerful enemy.
Today, the Upper Bontok Valley and the neighbouring
valleys are inhabited by various tribes, one of them still
known as the "Ifugaos." Their neighbours are the Bon-
toks and the Kalingas. All these mountaineers are excep¬
tionally gifted farmers and they maintain the terraces
of their ancestors with great technical skill. They are
continually improving irrigation systems and ways of
growing rice and raising livestock (their two main occu¬
pations).
There is no better proof of their ingenuity than the
scarecrows they construct to protect their seeds from the
birds. These scarecrows resemble those found in other
lands, but are kept perpetually moving, operated by the
brooks and the many little streams in the region. A
mechanism as ingenious as it is simple transmits the
energy of the streams to the scarecrows through a system
CON'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
STAIRWAY OF THE GIANTS (Continued)
of cords. In some cases, the moving scarecrows may be
as far as 800 yards from the water.
While the Kalinga ricefields are not as spectacular as
those of the Ifugaos and the Bontoks, they are also
remarkably well maintained. The homes and villages of
these mountaineers are among the cleanest and best kept
in the world. Yet it is not uncommon to hear certain
city-dwellers refer to these tribesmen as "savages." It
is a pejorative and unjustified label for people who are
among Asia's most highly skilled farmers and who
have been able to create and to preserve such gigantic
works of engineering.
Its origin may lie in the fact that for centuries, Kalin-
gas, Bontoks, Ifugaos and other tribes were perpetually at
war and, as a sign of victory, the men returned to their
villages with the heads of enemies slain in battle. This
gave them the name of head-hunters. However barba¬
rous a custom it may have been, it certainly was not
unique in the annals of warfare and it has been aban¬
doned for many years.
It is even said that the introduction of baseball and
football among the Luzon mountaineers broke them of
their habit of collecting heads. This seems to correspond
to the theory of an American administrator of fifty years
ago who wrote that head-hunting was not always an
integral part of tribal warfare but, more often, a sport
where two rival teams deliberately accepted the supreme
risks of this combat. At the end of the "match", heads
were counted in the same way as goals at a football match,»
If these mountaineers are still called "primitives" and
"savages" it may be because of the regrettable habit of
certain "civilized" people in thus describing others who
wear only a minimum amount of clothes. The farmers in
the Upper Bontoc Valley have to work in extremely tough
conditions under a blazing sun. They believeand they
are logically correct: that there is no need to wear
trousers and shirts which could only hinder them in their
work. But it is ridiculous to use the term "savages" in
referring to peoples capable of such achievements.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
PM
CENTURIES OF PATIENT WORK went into
the making of these ricefield terraces which climb
up the mountainsides from the valley floors to
heights of nearly 7,000 feet. Hardworking and
skilful farmers, the mountain dwellers of Bontok
are also expert masonsthey need to be with
literally thousands of miles of terrace walls to
maintain. Kalinga village home (right) with its
plaited facade testifies to their skill in yet another
craft. Above right, with his bow and his axe, this
young man of Bontok has a rather forbidding
appearance. These mountain people are, In
fact, very friendly and hospitable to strangers.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
FINE ARTS ON
POSTAGE STAMPS
by David J. Jacobs
EPAYiNG the tax on the delivery of a
letter with a stamp wasn't even
dreamed of when Raphael brushed
into life his lovely Madonnas or when Goya etched his
angry nightmares into seething commentaries on the
ugliness of man. And yet, there, on tiny, gummed and
perforated rectangles, are "The Sistine Madonna" in her
magnificent calm and "Volaverunt", Plate 61 in the Capri¬
chos, showing three crouching witches carrying the
Duchess of Alba through the clouds in three different
directions at once.
These are just two of the more than 1,100 paintings,
prints and drawings that more than 125 governments
have had translated into stamp designs. But why stop
at painting? Sculpture, architecture, music, ceramics,
printing, tribal carvings, weaving, the dance, theatre, lite¬
rature almost every form of art from antiquity to yester¬
day- has been represented on postage stamps from Aitu-
taki to the Virgin Islands.
More than 85 governments have issued about 500 stamps
featuring ceramics. Thousands more have been based on
sculpture a Polynesian club, the "Charioteer From Del¬
phi", an exquisite Ife bronze from Nigeria's Yorubaland,
a head of Nefertiti or a detail from the work of the con¬
temporary Yugoslav, Ivan Mestrovic. A history of archi¬
tecture could be illustrated with postage stamps, from the
cave (Lebanon issued a good example) to the skyscraper
(the new York City skyline appears on a Monaco stamp).
The designers of the first postage stamps never dreamed
of such subjects as an etching of Diirer's mother or a
carving of the great Congo king, Shamba Bolongongo.
But they did turn to the arts from the very beginning
for their motifs. The portrait on Great Britain's Penny
Black of 1840, the world's first adhesive postage stamp,
was based on a carving of Queen Victoria's head designed
by William Wyon for a medal struck in 1837. Another
portrait of Victoria, by Alfred Edward Chalón, became the
basis for many beautiful stamps among the early issues
of Grenada, Queensland and New Zealand.
Some nations based the designs of their first stamps on
the seals and stamps used on deeds, tax documents and
other papers. These were simple ciphers, crests and other
symbols. But most nations, following Britain's example,
used portraits of the rulers. This was an outgrowth of
the ancient practice of using the ruler's head on coins.
From the beginning, stamps have been manufactured
by the makers of money. Early designs of the United
States, for instance, were produced by engravers employed
by banknote printers. They used portraits of Franklin
and Washington which had appeared on notes printed by
the same firm. It was not long before the designers went
beyond the portrait. In 1869, the United States issued
stamps based on historical paintings such as Vanderlyn's
"Landing of Columbus" and Trumbull's "Declaration of
Independence".
And so it is with other nations. As the 19th Century
ended and the 20th began, they were drawing more and
more on their artistic riches. In 1896, Greece issued a set
which included Praxiteles' "Hermes", Paeonius' "Victory",
Myron's "Discobolus'", and a view of the Acropolis and
Parthenon. In 1905, Spain commemorated the 300th
20 CONT'D ON PAGE 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
REMBRANDT MAGNIFIED
The remarkable delicacy and detail of a postage stamp version of Rem¬
brandt's "Persian Wearing Fur Cap "is revealed by the enlargement,
above. Stamp itself, (right) is one of a set showing details of some of
this artist's etchings, issued in 1956 on his 350th birthday anniversary.
P3SÏAILVÂH!
"
v» -jrffit
'S ^&fr WS i
-ât. g i
» ^R^^^HBme 2 !
: 25 JÈÊ*''^^ ¡
\^MÊM& Si
i "[i^mW^^&/Wm\ Èb''»' '
'HttÜ^vy #«
; ; y. yyyy
2I
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
FINE ARTS ON STAMPS (Continued;
HOMAGE TO DA VINCI. "Lady with
the Ermine" was engraved by a Polish artist
from Leonardo da Vinci's painting. It is one of
a number of stamps issued in 1956 to pub¬
licise Unesco's International Museum Week.
ETCHINGS BY DURER. These works by the great German, painter, engraver and
designer, Albrecht Darer praying hands and his motherwere issued by the Saar
in 1955. The remarkable precision of the originals has been carefully preserved.
* -- -~'^r^ -y-y*- - s-S\-y
c
ff^W |P
" y
c;
r
r W^jàJFm <y
<
, [ *
p <
[y
> BLE^% ,'.
f* '
> WW
It
r^r^f
j
J tt*ac*:60**
WV'< '
t.*. H
A GOYA SELECTION. In 1958 a set of
Spanish stamps was issued depicting the works
of Goya. Shown here are "El Pelele" and
"The Drinker", two of the genre works now
in the Prado Museum collection, Madrid.
THREE FACES OF VAN GOGH. Two Dutch engravers and one from France used differing styles to interpret a Van Gogh self-port
Yet in transposing the painting, all three have faithfully reproduced the haunted look which Vincent Van Gogh gave to his own features.
\y '- , ,f\ ., ^y°\yr\r%S-X,'".. *\
VINCENT VGOGH-li
¿OMlRZtGtL-BtJSlAG 11 C
PUBLIQUE HpCAlSE
30F
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
OWM^gPHH
CRAFTSMEN. The Tunisian postal service chose crafts
as the theme for a series of stamps representing embroiderers,
weavers and potters. This one shows the weavers at work.
AN IMPRESSIONIST
Ogata Korin, one of
Japan's most famous ar¬
tists, is honoured by this
Soviet stamp issued in
1959, 'showing a detail
of one of his paintings.
This 17th century artist
broke with tradition and
developed a style dis¬
tinctive by its bold im¬
pressionism, both in
painting and in the
decoration of lacquer.
WORK AND DETAIL. Czechoslovakia has honoured through
its stamps the painter Josef Manes, celebrated for his historical
and genre works. In 1936 a stamp for aid to children reproduced
Manes' "Infancy," showing a midwife presenting a newborn
baby to its father. Left, the complete work; right, a detail.
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
anniversary of the publication of "Don Quixote" by issu¬
ing ten stamps, each based on an illustration by Gustave
Doré of a different episode of the story.
The first stamps of Egypt in 1866, then under Turkish
suzerainty, showed Turkish inscriptions, but the paper
was watermarked with a pyramid. The next year the
Sphinx and pyramids appeared as the central motif. By
1914, Egypt was displaying the Colossi of Thebes, the Pylon
of Karnak and the Rock Temples of Abu Simbel.
Over the years, the postage stamp has assumed addi¬
tional functions, quite apart from the prepayment of a
tax. It commemorates national events, it raises funds for
charity and it disseminates propaganda. The designers
have found the arts a naturaland richreservoir of
ideas. And many governments have found this tapping
of the national heritage a thrifty way of broadcasting to
the world a desirable cultural image.
The hobby of stamp collecting, as old as stamps, has
also tended to influence stamp design. Few products of
the graphic arts are scrutinized so carefully by so many
critical eyes. Advertisements, book and magazine formats,
money, tax forms and thousands of other familiar pieces
of printed paper from menus to market bags are, in a
sense, invisible. We are influenced by them, we read them,
we spend them, we carry home the fish in them, but few
of us are conscious of how they are constructed and
decorated.
Well designed printing does not wish to call attention
to itself. The message is paramount, the messenger un¬
seen. Of course this is true, too, of stamps. To many,
they are just colored blurs on the corners of envelopes.
But millions of collectors the world over study them in
great detail, often preferring stamps that haven't even
performed their function because the cancellations
obscure some of these details.
A
^^ -^^ the catalogues are full of blown-up
illustrations of minute changes in
line, shade or design. Many collectors are concerned pri¬
marily with studying perforations, watermarks, paper,
gum, ink and printing varieties and pay little heed to
design. Some are interested only in cancellations. But
over the years there has been a growing sensitivity to the
elements of design.
It is common practice for many nations to hold annual
contests among artists to determine stamp designs.
Some stamp journals run regular columns on the subject
and one conducts an annual "'Design Derby" in which
thousands of readers vote for the most beautiful and the
most ugly stamps produced each year.
This intense interest in what appears on the face of
a stamp has been even further stimulated by the increas¬
ing popularity of "'topical" or "thematic" collecting in
which stamps are collected by subject, rather than by
country or some other conventional discipline. The topi-
calist chases after butterflies, maps, railroads, ships, water¬
falls, flowers, doctors, dogs, fish, poets, mathematicians,
nudes or whatever else strikes his fancy and also appears
on a sizeable number of postage stamps. About 300 of
these topicalists from more than 20 countries have formed
an organization known as the Fine Arts Unit of the Ame¬
rican Topical Association. The unit publishes a journal
containing detailed and highly informed articles about
works of art depicted on stamps.
Along with this widespread and critical awareness of
stamps has evolved the peculiar art of stamp designing.
Among the handful of steel engravers and the highly
skilled photographers, retouchers, etchers and other tech¬
nicians are the men who have established stamp design
as the rebirth, on a mass level, of the art of the minia¬
turist. They work from designs created for the stamp or
from motifs that were created for other purposes but are
now being used as the theme or a stamp.
The objective is not to reproduce the original, but to
translate it not just into another language, but into
another medium. It is like rendering Dante's "Inferno"
into a comic strip in a Chicago newspaper while still
retaining a suggestion of the spirit of the original. The
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
FINE ARTS ON STAMPS (Continued)
LA LETTRE f" EtïHe:
TRIBUTE TO FRAGONARD. The celebrated French
painter Jean-Honoré Fragonard has been honoured on
stamps issued in Poland and France. In this reproduc¬
tion of "The Letter," French engraver, J. Piel, has captu¬
red the grace with which Fragonard imbued his subjects.
original may have been a fresco from the Cinquecento, a
triptych for an altar, a window on a mosque or a mask
for a tribal chieftan. But the stamp design must be a
vignette, usually in one or two colours, occasionally more,
and it must share its tiny home with the country's name,
the denomination and often, a descriptive legend. It is
sometimes quite remarkable to see how these limitations
are overcome sometimes, even exploited to produce not
only a translation, but a nugget of graphic art with vir¬
tues of it own.
But to many the appeal of the design must remain
secondary to the subject. To see the way the increasing
number of issues based on works of art are grabbed up
is to realize the everdeepening interest in the arts. As
one collector, writing in the journal of the American
Topical Association, put it :
"I never possessed either the means or the wall
space to form a picture gallery in the proper sense.
That is why my choice... fell upon "Pictures and
Painters." Now I have an art gallery in miniature,
embracing... a selection of the outstanding master^
pieces enshrined in the world-famous collections of
London, Paris, New York, Berlin, Vienna, Florence,
Madrid and the like, all reduced to postage stamp
size and displayed upon a hundred or so ordinary
stamp album sheets... I have amassed, in about four
years, rather more than a thousand different stamp
pictures and the cry is 'still they come!'..."
Sculpture and Architecture, he wrote, will come next.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
A CENTURY OF 'BLACK GOLD'
The gigantic oil industry which today
keeps billions of wheels turning through¬
out the world and which, within a
century, has changed the pattern of
life and work for much of mankind,
opening up many new fields of ende¬
avour, sprang from very small begin¬
nings in 1859. Yet, since then, some¬
thing in the region of two million oil
wells have been drilled, occasionally
to as great a depth as four miles.
by W. H. Owens
USIS
The modern oil industry was born just one hundred years
ago at Titusvllle, in Pennsylvania, U.S.A., where Edwin
L. Drake sank the first well ever to be drilled for the purpose of
finding oil. A strike was made at a depth of about 69 feet and
oil gushed forth at the initial rate of eight to ten barrels a day.
LTHOUGH the large-scale exploitation of
crude oil is a fairly recent industrial de¬
velopment, the Earth's "black gold" has
nevertheless been used by peoples in many
different parts of the world for thousands of years. The
Bible tells how pitch, or bitumen, was used for the
waterproofing of Noah's Ark and the basket of the infant
Moses. This pitch came from surface seepages of crude
oil which were bitumenized by the weathering action of
the sun and Iwind. The "eternal fires" around the shores
of the Caspian Sea, which were the object ,of worship in
ancient times, were simply oil and natural gas seepages
which ignited as they reached the air.
Bitumen was an article of commerce in the Tigris and
Euphrates river basin, which is now Iraq, in the days
before Babylon Was built. The Babylonians and
Sumerians, like the Inca rulers of Peru, valued it as a
building mortar. The Chinese used the same sticky, black
substance in their shipbuilding trade to make vessels
seaworthy, and as fuel in their salt works. Among the
many purposes to which crude oil exudations were put
by the Indian tribes of North America and Patagonia was
for medicine and embrocations.
It is interesting to recall that only eleven years before
Edwin Drake drilled his well, oil had been struck
accidentally while borings for brine were being made
along the Allegheny River ih Pennsylvania. This "rock-
ôil" which contaminated the water was skimmed off and
sold in chemists' shops as an embrocation for the relief
of rheumatism, gout and similar ailments.
' The rapid and continuous growth of the modern oil
industry, and the dominant role it has assumed in world
affairs in so comparatively short a time, is without any
parallel in history. This growth has been most striking
since the ¡First World War. In 1914 world production of
crude oil was 55 million tons. In 1938 it was 280 million
tons. Last year's world output exceeded 900 million tons,
and the demand is still growing.
That the present demand for oil is likely to be doubled
within the next twenty years is hardly surprising.
Besides the daily increase in the millions of motor vehicles
(which now consume more than one-third of the world's
supply of petroleum products) and the enormous growth
of aviation, there is the rapid spread of industrialization
and the change to mechanized agriculture throughout the
world. And now the young, but potentially vast,
petroleum chemical industry is producing the raw
materials from which synthetic fibres, synthetic rubber,
plastics, resins, carbon black and fertilizers are made
materials, in turn, of a wide range of consumer goods.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
BLACK GOLD (Continued)
This is why, in spite of the huge output of the world's
producing oil wells, the search for new sources of crude
oil is being steadily intensified. Geological teams are
scattered far and wide hunting for oil in Arctic Canada
and Alaska, in the steaming jungles of Latin-America and
the Far East, in the Australian Bush and on the burning
sands of the Sahara Desert. Exploration for more under¬
water oil is in progress too. There are incalculable
quantities of this sub-ocean oil to be won under the
relatively shallow waters of the Continental Shelf, large
areas of which adjoin some of the richest producing
oilfields, notably in the Gulf of Mexico.
" While oil is produced on a commercial scale in a large
number of countries, there are five main regions in which
the chief proven oil reserves of the world are contained.
These are North America, the Caribbean, the Middle East,
the U.S.S.R. and the far East. The bulk of world
production comes from what have been aptly termed the
two "Petroleum Poles." One is situated around the
Caribbean and the Gulf of Mexico; the other about the
Black Sea, the Caspian and the Persian Gulf.
T
he United States, which is the most highly
developed country so far as oil is concern¬
ed, is still the world's chief producer. In
the past hundred years, the U.S. alone has
provided some sixty per cent of the world's total
cumulative production, and except for a brief period
around the beginning of this century when the Baku
oilfields of Russia had the largest output, she has always
remained in the lead. Today, in spite of the growing
production of other countries, the TJ.S. produces more
than two-fifths of world's total supply. More than half
the forty-eight States are oil producers, and in 1957 just
two of them, Texas and California, together supplied more
oil than the combined output of the Middle East and Far
East.
Venezuela is the world's second largest oil producer and
by far the largest oil-exporting country today. She still
accounts for about ninety per cent of South America's oil
production, although the other countries of that
potentially rich continent and also some in Central
America have recently become the scene of widespread
exploration for the mineral.
Lake Maracaibo, the great sea inlet of Western
Venezuela, Is one of the most successful areas of under¬
water drilling. Very prolific oilfields are worked around
the Lake shores, and in places these extend beneath its
bed where the oil is recovered by means of under-water
drilling from special platforms mounted on concrete piles.
Some of the drilling rigs are several miles out from the
shore and stand in water up to 100 feet deep. Offshore
drilling has also been carried on for many years in the
Gulf of Mexico, where the rich oil-bearing formations of
the States of Texas and Louisiana stretch beyond the
coast swamps far under the sea.
Third place among Jthe world's oil-producing countries
is held by the U.S.S.R.*whose output of crude oil has been
rising rapidly and continuously ever since 1945. A year
ago Mr. Khrushchev announced long-term plans for a
huge production increase from the record 98.3 million tons
in 1957 to around 400 million tons ,by 1972. This would be
achieved mainly, though by no means exclusively, through
the further development of the rich reserves of the Volga-
Ural region.
Russia's oldest oilfield is centred on Baku, on the
Caspian Sea, which is perhaps the earliest ¡known oil area
in the world. But since the Second World War the
Caucasian production has been steadily supplanted by
that of the immensely rich region between the River Volga
and the Ural Mountains, which, it is believed, may contain
as much as eighty per cent of the total Soviet reserves.
Little attempt was made to develop this so-
called "'Second Baku" field until the 1930's,
owing to the remoteness of the region from
the main oil-consuming districts of the
western part of the Soviet Union. But development was
stimulated by the wartime movement of many industrial
plants into the area from the more vulnerable west. It
will be the main centre of Soviet oil expansion in the
future.
When it comes to proved oil reserves, the countries of
the Middle East are in a dominant position with no less
than two-thirds of the world's total. For this reason the
Middle East will become more and more important as the
years pass. Although its total output of crude oil is now
more than ten times the pre-war level, the contribution
of the Middle East to total world production (20 per cent
in 1957) is still disproportionate to its enormous reserves.
But this is expected to be doubled in the next decade.
It is in this fast-changing part of the world that some
of the most remarkable oil developments of thé" present
century have taken place. The first important oil
discovery of modern times in the Middle East was made
in 1908 at Masjid-i-Sulaiman, in Persia a most prolific
oilfield which has since produced over 100 million tons.
That discovery stimulated the oil search in other parts,
and in the years between the world wars new oilfields
were found in Iraq, Bahrein, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait and
Egypt, as well as in Iran itself.
Many of them are exceptionally prolific; for example,
the Burgan oilfield in Kuwait now produces more than
any other single oilfield in the world, and in Saudi Arabia
the average production per well is several hundred times
as great as, for example, in the U.SA. where there are
many large producing wells.
One of the great factors in oil production,
especially in such a region as the Middle
East, is the economic transportation of
crude oil from the wells to the refineries
and ports. The land pipeline systems, linked with the
tanker fleets on the high seas, are the arteries through
which this life-blood of our civilization is distributed.
Pipelines carry crude oil, and also refined petroleum
products, over long distances and across rivers, mountains
and deserts, and pipeline engineering is today a major
activity of the oil industry. In the United States the
pipeline transportation of liquid fuels and natural gas has
reached the highest development, for in that country the
entire oil movement from well to marketing terminal is
often made wholly through linking pipelines.
Until about ten years ago the only direct outlet for
Middle East oil to the Mediterranean was by means of the
26 CONT'D ON PAGE 28
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
OLDEST OIL 'DISTILLERY'
Photos © Paul Almasy
Iraq, one of the largest oil-producing countries in the world is
also the home of what might properly be called the world's
oldest oil "distillery". Its owner he is also its one-man
staff digs holes about six feet deep in the ground and taking
from them the oil-soaked earth, he heats it in his home-made
oven, and thus obtains a crude oil which he sells locally as lamp
fuel. Petroleum, once called "rock oil", is not a new discovery.
Two thousand five hundred years ago, Alexander the Great
was greatly intrigued, when in this same region of Iraq, by the
"eternal fires" which flared up day and night in the desert.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
BLACK GOLD (Continued;
long, forked pipeline from the Kirkuk wells in Iraq to
Haifa and Tripoli. The construction of this pioneer
desert oil routeacross desert, rock, mountain and four
great rivers of Arabia was a considerable feat. At one
time more than 14,000 men were working on the project.
Since the war a number of other large pipelines have
been built across the desert lands, including a second
route from Kirkuk to Tripoli and one from Kirkuk to
Banias, on the Syrian coast. The 1,000-mile pipeline from
the Saudi Arabian oilfields to the Mediterranean port of
Sidon, which cost about £80 million, plays a major part
in supplying oil to Western Europe refineries.
Just how important these desert pipelines are can be
seen by a comparison with the alternative of sea transport.
To carry Middle East oil all the way to Europe by sea
means a round trip of some 7,000 miles between the head
of the Persian Gulf and the Mediterranean end of the
Suez Canal, in addition to the voyage onward from there.
The world-wide movement of oil supplies involves the
operation of large, modern tanker fleets. Today oil is
the most valuable of all seaborne cargoes, and oil-tankers
account for approximately one-quarter of the world's
entire merchant fleet. On any average day of the year
some 15 million tons of petroleum and its products,
valued at well over £100 million, are afloat on the seas.
At the beginning of this century there were only
109 tankers, representing a world tonnage of a little over
half a million, in service. Today the number is more
than 3,000 twice as many as before the Second World
War with a total tonnage approaching 50 millions.
S AFETY is naturally the most important
factor in the operation of oil-tankers.
In the earliest days of the oil indus¬
try, crude oil was shipped in wooden
barrels, and this was a highly inflammable cargo for the
wooden ships of the time. Oil is still a dangerous cargo
to handle, but it is now carried in bulk and the risk of
fire or explosion has been minimized both by the special
design and the safety precautions taken in construction,
and by a rigid system of rules which have to be observed
by the crews. (The crew accommodation, incidentally, is
among the best found in any merchant ship.) In case
of any emergency the cargo compartments of the modern
tanker are equipped with a steam-smothering system
which operates effectively in a matter of seconds.
Everybody knows that petrol, gas oil, diesel- oil,
lubricating oils, kerosine (or paraffin), bitumen and so on
are the products from refined petroleum. But today there
are, in addition, more than a thousand products from the
same raw material which have become part of everyday
life, very often in unsuspected ways.
Among the most important of them are white oils which
are highly purified grades of lubricating oils. These are
used, for example, in the manufacture of popularly-priced
cosmetics, perfumes, hair oil, sun-tan lotions, embrocations
and ointments. Fruit such as oranges are thinly coated
with white oil to prevent them drying up, and eggs are
dipped in it to preserve them.
White oils are similarly used for the preservation of
other foods, for example, cheese, meat and dried fruits.
They also play a part in the manufacture of coloured inks,
flaked soaps, polishes, and in the lubrication of bakery
machinery to prevent bread from sticking to the rolling
slabs.
28
Another group of petroleum products is the petroleum
waxes, which are now used in a great number of
industries. Candle-making is a well-known example.
Cartons for milk and soft drinks, cake boxes and
wrappings for bread and confectionery, are treated with
paraffin wax, which is tasteless and odourless, to keep the
contents fresh. Wax is also used in the manufacture
of polishes of all kinds.
Other petroleum products include white spirit, which is
used in paints and for dry cleaning, and special types of
spirits used for extracting perfumes from flowers, natural
oils from plants and seeds, and glue from bones. Carbon
black a fine powder manufactured from petroleum is
an ingredient of rubber tyres, typewriter ribbons and
carbon papers, and printing and Indian inks. And in the
field of medicine, apart from products already mentioned,
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
petroleum supplies the solvents used in preparing such
life-saving drugs as penicillin and insulin, and in
anaesthetics.
It is in the past few years that the growing range of
synthetic materials produced by the wonders of petroleum
chemistry have begun to play an important part in our
lives. A few substances like artificial silk, synthetic dyes
and artificial fertilizers, of course, have been established
for quite a time now. But the profusion of plastics,
synthetic rubbers, detergents and so on, in the consumer
market is a post-war development.
Today we know of such extremely versatile substances
as polymerized ethylene, or polythene, and polyvinyl
chloride which appear in so many everyday guises in
homes, shops, offices and factories. Detergents, or soap
substitutes, have revolutionized domestic washing and
cleaning. A number of widely used synthetic fibres are
also produced partly or wholly from petroleum, and also
a variety of drugs and certain artificial flavourings.
Indeed, the list is endless.
Yet this is really only the beginning. With one of the
most fascinating and versatile raw materials in its hands,
the oil industry is spending more time and more and more
money on research. More and better plant, involving
heavy capital investment, is being built to implement the
new discoveries of the research teams in many lands.
Although it has achieved so much and bestowed such
benefits on mankind in its first 100 years of existence, the
modern oil industry^embarks now on its second century in
a youthful, pioneering spirit, confident of a future that
promises still greater rewards.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
I
- . _ !
© Almasy, Pans
Part of a bas relief decorating the temple dedicated to Knoum, god of the First Cataract
of the Nile and to Sesostris III and founded by King Tuthmosis 111 (1504-1450 B.C.)
at Semneh in the Sudan on the left bank of the Nile, about 250 miles up river from
Aswan. Today, this temple is threatened with inundation by the Aswan Dam.
30
n the area of the
northern Sudan
which will be
submerged by the waters of the new
Aswan Dam, undoubtedly the most
important sites which will be
destroyed are the series of ancient
fortresses built by the Egyptians
about B.C. 2000 and situated at
strategic points on both banks of the
Nile between Wadi Haifa and Semneh.
The Pharaohs of the 12th Dynasty
built these strongholds to protect the
southern borders of Egypt and to
hold down the subject populations of
their newly conquered dominions in
Nubia.
Some of them were also trading
settlements and dispatch posts to
Egypt of the products of the south,
such as gold, ivory, etc. They are
thus treasure houses of information,
not only on ancient military architec¬
ture, but on the manners, customs
and general conditions of life in colo¬
nial Nubia over a period of nearly a
thousand years.
The exploration of these important
remains of ancient civilization has
been largely neglected because of
their immense size and inaccessibility;
consequently our knowledge of Egyp¬
tian military architecture is extremely
limited. Egyptology is now faced
with the necessity of immediate
research in a subject which, unless
undertaken at once, will be beyond
the reach of a student in less than
four years' time. Once the rising
waters of the new reservoir reach
their specified level of 133 metres,
nothing can save these ancient monu¬
ments, and, built as they are of mud
brick, within a few months not a
vestige of them will remain.
w
W W iTH this know-
7 7 ledge, the Egypt
Exploration So¬
ciety in 1958 undertook, with the
approval of the Sudan Government,
the complete excavation of Buhen,
situated on the west bank of the Nile
opposite the modern town of Wadi
Haifa. Buhen was the largest of the
chain of trading stations and for¬
tresses built by the Pharaohs of
Dynasty 12 (2000 B.C.) to block the
difficult passages by land and river
through the Second Cataract.
It was the G.H.Q. for the admi¬
nistration of the military garrisons
of all the strongholds in the area,
and at the time of its foundation it
was probably the seat of the Egyptian
Viceroy who ruled Nubia in the name
of the Pharaoh of Egypt. At that
time the fortress consisted of an
elaborate series of fortifications built
on a rectangular plan 172 metres
by 160 metres, which enclosed a
town containing domestic habitations,
barrack buildings, workshops, a tem¬
ple and the Governor's palace.
As far as the Egypt Exploration
Society's excavations have gone, they
have revealed a carefully laid out
example of rectangular town planning
with paved arterial roads, each with
its own independent drainage system.
On the river side of the fortress, two
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
N THESE DREAR WASTES
WHAT VISIONARY PASTS REVIVE...
by Professor W. B. Emery
Department of Egyptology
University College, London J. Vercoutter
Aerial photo of the great fortress of Buhen, near Wadi Haifa in the Sudan. The
fortress was built in the early Middle Kingdom, as one of a series of trading posts
and strongholds erected nearly 4,000 years ago to defend the strategic area of the
Second Cataract of the Nile, dividing Upper and Lower Nubia. It has been excavated
and explored by expeditions led by Professor Walter B. Emery of the University of
London. Among details seen in this photo are traces of streets running at right
angles to each other, the earliest ramparts with their circular bastions, the temple
(top centre, closest to the river) and the great gate in the centre of the west wall
facing the desert. Faintly visible too are the outlines of the larger defence system
dating from the reconstruction of the fortress, after its sacking about 1650 B.C.
great gates in the wans lead directly
to stone built quays from which ships
were loaded with the tribute and
products of trade from conquered
Nubia. The contents of tombs
discovered outside the town and the
condition of houses within it give
ample evidence of a rich and even
luxurious standard of living in this
outpost of colonial Egypt.
The elaborate defence system which
enclosed this small town consisted of
a massive brick wall, 4.8 m. thick and
11 m. high, relieved at intervals on
its outer face with projecting rectan¬
gular towers. At the foot of tne
wall was a brick paved rampart with
a fire-step, protected by a loopholed
parapet overhanging the scarp of dry
ditch, about 9 m. wide and 7 m. deep.
The counterscarp on the other side of
the ditch was surmounted by a
narrow covered way of brickwork,
beyond which was a glacis rising from
the natural ground level. Projecting
into the ditch from the scarp were
round bastions with a system of triple
loopholes with single embrasures,
through which archers could direct
a deadly cross-fire which would
completely cover the ditch.
The most strongly fortified part of
the structure was the great gate built
in the centre of the west wall facing
the desert from which came the long
trade roads leading to the mines and
quarries. The gate was closed by
great double doors, beyond which was
a wooden drawbridge which could be
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
pulled back on rollers. The gate and
bridge were flanked by two spur walls
which extended over the dry ditch,
forming a narrow corridor, through
which an attacking force would have
to battle its way exposed to a rain of
missiles from the battlements on
three sides. Even when the storming
party had broken through the gate,
their difficulties would not be at an
end, for they would find themselves
in an enclosed square with exits
giving access to the town only
through narrow roads immediately
under the inner walls of the fortifi¬
cations; thus coming under fire once
again from the defenders.
¡¿OSA* n*s^-ÍO«fc^B*ií*»í>:
T he discovery of
these complex
and elaborate
fortifications at Buhen shows that
the Egyptians of that time were hold¬
ing their newly won territory against
a well organized enemy whose mili¬
tary prowess was by no means
negligible. Strong as they were,
these great defences were not suffi¬
cient to preserve the town, and with
the weakening of Egyptian power
following the Asiatic invasions of
their homeland, the people of the
South stormed and sacked the
fortress about 1650 B.C.
Thereafter it remained a gigantic
and partly burnt ruin for many
years, until the advent of the warrior
Pharaohs of the 18th Dynasty (1555-
1350 B.C.), who after the expulsion
of the Asiatic usurpers in Egypt,
turned their attention once more to
their last possessions in the south.
Buhen was reoccupied and its original
fortifications were rebuilt and streng¬
thened to form a citadel in the centre
of a much larger town with a new
defence system of over a mile in
extent surrounding it. A fine temple
was built by Queen Hatshepsut (B.C.
1495), the town expanded and
apparently remained secure, occupied
by a thriving community, until the
final eclipse of Egyptian power at the
close of the 20th Dynasty (B.C. 1090).
A large part of this great outpost
of Egyptian civilization has already
been excavated by the Egypt Explo¬
ration Society's expeditions, and
valuable new material and knowledge
has been made available for the
historian's research. Two more sea¬
sons of exploration will be necessary
before the whole area is revealed;
but sufficient is now visible to show
that here at Buhen we have a unique
example of Egyptian military archi¬
tecture splendidly preserved.
Remains of bas reliefs covering walls of one
of two temples built inside twin fortresses of
Semneh and Kumma, dating from 1500-1400
B.C. An air survey carried out in the Sudan
has revealed the existence of more than I 00
ancient historical sites which still need to be
at least partly explored, excavated and recorded.
© Paul Almasy, Pans
Elaborate defence system enclosing the
ancient Nubian town of Buhen included
a massive brick wall 36 feet high with
projecting rectangular towers. At the
foot of the wall was a brick paved ram¬
part with a fire-step (inset, right),
protected by a loopholed parapet,
overhanging a dry ditch 30 feet wide.
W B Emery-London Universit/
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1960
L e 1 1 e r s t o t h e Editor
A 'TERRA INCOGNITA'
Sir,
In The Unesco Courier for Feb¬
ruary 1960, (special issue dealing with
the antiquities of Nubia and the need
to save them before they are flooded by
the waters of the ' Aswan Dam), I
found the material published by you of
considerable interest. I must, how¬
ever protest at the small amount of
space given to the antiquities of the
Sudan as compared with those of Egypt...
It is necessary to point out... that the
whole of Egyptian Nubia has been very
carefully surveyed on two occasions.
The first occasion was when carried out
by Dr. Reisner and others when the
Aswan dam was first built and the second,
the survey by Professor Emery in the
1930's when the dam was heightened. As
a result of this, Egyptian Nubia is one
of the best studied areas in the world
from the point of view of archaeology,
and although it is certainly of great imp¬
ortance that everything possible should be
done to save the existing monuments,
the area can in no way compare for
present archaeological importance with
that part of the Sudan that is to be
flooded.
Since Egyptian Nubia has been very
carefully surveyed and excavated it has
little left in the way of new information
to give us. The area to the south of
the frontier in the Republic of the Su¬
dan has only had a few and sporadic
archaeological investigations carried out
and here almost everything is to be
done ab initio. In the northern Sudan
no full archaeological survey has ever
been carried out; several hundred sites
are known and there is a vast amount
of new archaeological information wait¬
ing to be gleaned. There can be no
question at all but that for additions to
knowledge the Sudan side of the fron¬
tier is of the greatest importance.
Dr. Vercoutter himself in the article
you print speaks of Sudanese Nubia as
terra incognita and this is in the most
literal sense of the word true. It is
here in the Sudan that the greatest ar¬
chaeological effort is required; it may
well be that the cost of carrying out
an archaeological survey here will be
less than the enormous sum required
for preserving the monuments of Egypt,
but in view of the extreme importance
of this area for the history and archaeo¬
logy of the whole of the African conti¬
nent it shows a remarkable lack of sense
of proportion to relegate it to one short
article of only two pages of texts in an
issue of your journal of 60 pages. I
very much hope that you can redress
this incorrect balance by issuing a future
number largely concerned with the an¬
tiquities of the Sudan.
P. L. Shinnie
Professor of Archaeology
University College of Ghana
Ed Note: See page 30. Further articles
on Sudanese Nubia are also foreseen.
WHAT ARE WE WAITING FOR 7
Sir,
In your April "'Letters to the Editor"
column, M. L. de Guesnet expresses
doubts about the number of people who
are said to use Esperanto. You pub¬
lish an editorial reply and the subject
now seems to be closed. However, I
don't think that the problem has been
outlined correctly. It is not a question
of knowing how many people speak
Esperanto, but rather ¡how many would
use it if they were sure of finding a
correspondent or if the need to use it
became obvious.
This will not be possible as long as
idealists and dreamers alone learn it and
try to propagate its use. Official organ¬
izations must include it in their
programmes of general education and in
those concerned with the commercial,
touristic and technical fields.
Half a century of international
congresses have proved that Esperanto
is very much alive and capable of re¬
maining so. Today we must make use
of it. Nor is it a question of deciding
if Esperanto is perfect or if, by chan¬
ce, Esperantido, Interlingue or any
future improvement is to be preferred.
These points of view should, I feel,
be acceptable to partisans of any of
these languages. Finally, every nation
should choose one or another of them.
The hope expressed by Unesco hav¬
ing already pointed the way, why
don't we accept it without delay?
Jean Debest
Arcueil, France
MILLIONS MORE MOUTHS TO FEED
Sir,
The isSue of The Unesco Courier
of April 1960 (World Mobilization
Against Malaria) instigates some reflec¬
tions. One thousand million persons
in danger, you wrote. The projected
mobilization against anopheles is meant
to pull them out of the malaria danger,
but, so far as I can see, only to put them
into the hunger danger. What is wor¬
se for parents: to see their children die
of malaria or of a chronic empty sto¬
mach? I wonder if it wouldn't be bet¬
ter to v start a programme of family
planning instead of an irreversible cam¬
paign against the mosquito and its
deadly implications. How long will
the economic advantages you wrote of
in impressive numbers remain an ad¬
vantage ? It would be a horrible pa¬
radox, indeed, if the activities of the
WHO canceled out the activities of the
FAO. These problems are worth
thinking about, so, would it be possible
to dedicate an issue of The Unesco
Courier to the prospects of family
planning, and the ethical problems
which bring the activities of the Unesco
along with them?
P. KIoos
Amsterdam, Netherlands
Ed. note: An issue on the world's
population problem is being planned for
a later date. An issue on the world's
hunger and steps to combat it is fore¬
seen for 1962. See also page 2.
ROOM FOR ALL RELIGIONS
Sir,
As a Christian, as an American, and
as a citizen of the world. I have read
The Unesco Courier for years. When
my wife was alive, I always read the
articles aloud to her. One which
interested her deeply was on under¬
standing between East and West.
I agree with the principle, as set
forth in the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights of the U.N., that
"recognition of the inherent dignity
and of the equal and inalienable rights
of all members of the human family
is the foundation of freedom, justice
and peace in the world."
It is a shame before mankind and a
sin before God that as yet the high
principles of freedom and equality,
subscribed to by so many nations in
the Declaration, are not lived up to
fully by any nation in the world and
are flagrantly violated by some.
The question, then, is how best may
we serve the cause of human freedom?
I feel what The Unesco Courier is
doing to educate regarding other
nations, races, and peoples is very
important. I subscribe to the Courier
because I believe in education for
human understanding international, in¬
tercultural, interracial, and inter-
religious. But I do not believe that
education is enough. We will not
achieve recognition of the rights of
others unless recognition is taken of
the fundamental fact of the Fatherhood
of God, as well as the brotherhood of
man.
As a Christian I believe Christ was
and is unique the Son of God, the
Light of the World, the Prince of Peace.
Yet, as a Christian, I believe, also, that
God revealed Himself through other
religious leaders, Buddha, Mohammed,
Confucius, Moses. The Golden Rule
and many other religious principles are
common to all the great religious.
If due respect were paid to the worth
and validity of all religions, I do not
see why there would be serious objection
to articles in the Courier by out¬
standing Christian thinkers and practical
leaders of the faith for example the
Archbishop of Canterbury, Pope John,
Stanley Jones, Martin Luther King.
Palmer Van Gundy
Los Angeles, U.S.A.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Ne
A.LWARD FOR CALDER 'MOBILE':
The Architectural1 League of New York has
awarded its 1960 Gold Medal of Honour
to Alexander Calder for his "mobile"
sculpture '"Spiral" at Unesco Headquarters
in Paris. Last year, the same work by
Calder was awarded the Carnegie Institute
First Prize for Sculpture, and Joan Miro
received the Guggenheim Prize for his
ceramic walls at the Unesco H.Q.
ARID LANDS ON THE SCREEN:
"Arid Lands" a UNESCO documentary
film describing a problem which afflicts
one-third of the land surface of the
earth, lias been given its première in
Paris. Turning its lens on specific prob¬
lems, the film also shows some of the
solutions offered by science: de-salting
water so it can be used for irrigation,
modern techniques of water prospecting
and harnessing the power of the sun.
The film shows how Unesco's efforts
dating from 1948 have grown into
a major international project, co-ordi¬
nating research and bringing it to bear
on the dry belt running from North
Africa, through the Middle East and
across Asia.
A NTI-'PIRATING' AGREEMENT:
A draft convention for the protection of
performers, recorders and broadcasters was
adopted unanimously by a meeting of legal
experts who met recently in The Hague
under the auspices of the International
Labour Organization, Unesco and the
Berne Union. The new agreement, to be
signed a conference early next year, will
prevent the '"pirating" of performance dues,
which has become more frequent since the
development of new techniques for record¬
ing sound and image .
U. S. AID FOR WORLDWIDE
MALARIA ERADICATION
OUT of one thousand four hundred million people either affected by malaria
or living in areas exposed to it, close to 280 million were freed from the
threat of the disease by the end of last year thanks to widespread eradica¬
tion campaigns. Reporting this to the recent meeting of the World Health Assem¬
bly in Geneva, Dr. M.G. Candau, Director-General of the World Health Organi¬
zation, warned that the WHO Malaria Eradication Special Account was seven
million dollars short of the amount needed for the activities planned for 1960-61.
"With the exception of one country [the United States] which alone has provided
more than 90 per cent of the funds available, actual contributions still continue to
lag far behind good intentions and assurances of support."' Figures released by
the U.S. Government show that for the 1960 Fiscal Year $32 million of special
assistance funds has been programmed for U.S. participation in the worldwide
malaria eradication programme. This includes $3 million for WHO and $2 mil¬
lion for the Pan American Sanitary Organization. The balance is being used
directly to support malaria eradication in 25 countries in the Far East, Near East,
South Asia, Africa and Latin America.
w<ORLD REPORT ON ELEC¬
TRONIC COMPUTERS: Machines can
now control other machines, predict the
weather, memorize all the world's know¬
ledge, compose music, translate languages
and solve in a few seconds problems on
which mathematicians might spend a life¬
time. These remarkable powers of present-
day computers are described in a recently
published Unesco report, "Proceedings of
the International Conference on Informa¬
tion processing" which brought 2,000 elec¬
tronic computer experts from 39 countries
to Paris last year. This 520-page, multi¬
lingual report which gives a complete pic¬
ture of current research in information
processing, is published by Unesco, Paris,
R. Oldenberg, Munich, and Butterworths,
London. Its price is ,$25.00 ; £7-7-0;
100 NF or DM 84.
Clearing House, Unesco, Place de Fon¬
tenoy, Paris T.
CENTRE FOR SAFETY: The In¬
ternational Labour Office recently establish¬
ed an International Occupational Safety
and Health Information Centre in Geneva,
in collaboration with the International So¬
cial Security Association. The Centre will
provide information on various aspects of
safety and health in many fields including
mining, industry, building and civil engi¬
neering, transport, public services and agri¬
culture. Details and information can be
obtained from C.I.S., c/o International
Labour Office, 154, route de Lausanne,
Geneva, Switzerland.
FILMSTRIPS HONOUR DARWIN
& CHEKOV: The life and work of
Anton Chekov, the centenary of whose
birth is being celebrated this year, is
illustrated in a 40-frame filmstrip now
released by Unesco. Its sub-titles are
given in a booklet edited by Ma¬
dame Marie-Madeleine Rabecq, Curator
of the Pedagogical Museum in Paris, in
which a preface describes Chekhov's life
and work. Madame Rabecq is also
author of the commentary for another
filmstrip which is devoted to Charles
Darwin, the publication of whose "Ori¬
gin of Species" in 1859 was marked by
centenary celebrations last year. Full
information on these filmstrips can be
obtained from the Audio-Visual Media
Division, Unesco, Place de Fontenoy,
Paris 7°.
TOP FILM COUNTRIES: For the
past five years, Japan has regularly
been outproducing the U.S.A. and has
become the world's largest maker of
feature films (331 in 1955 and 352 in
1956 compared with 305 and 307 res¬
pectively in the U.S.A.) Even tiny
Hong Kong produces more feature
length films 227 in 1956 than France
and Italy combined. These are but two
of the many surprising facts given in
"Orient A Survey of Films Produced
in Countries of Arab and Asian Culture"
published by the British Film Institute
in London at Unesco's request and
with its help. This 92-page survey, of
which a limited number of copies are
available, can he obtained by writing
directly to the Mass Communication
ATOMS FOR PEACE: A mobile
exhibition illustrating many of the uses
of atomic energy has recently been
touring the principal cities of Mexi¬
co. The display was organized by the
Mexican National Nuclear Energy Com¬
mission with the assistance of the In¬
ternational Atomic Energy Agency
(IAEA) which provided a mobile radio¬
isotope laboratory. This was used by
Mexican universities to initiate young
scientists in basic isotope techniques and
has resulted in several universities de¬
ciding to start regular training courses
in this field. The laboratory, a gift to
the IAEA by the United States, is now
to visit Argentina. IEA's first mobile
radioisotope unit, also a gift from the
U.S.A. has been used for training in
Europe and is now going to the Far
East.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW ON
THE WORLD
Once a month THE UNESCO
COURIER presents to its
readers à panorama of the
modern world. Without being
either too learned or too "popu¬
lar" in its approach, its well-
illustrated articles give a vivid
picture of. the endless diversity
of peoples and countries. There
is no facet of the present-day
world on which it does not
touch the sciences man has
developed, the cultures he has
created, the knowledge he has
amassed.
THE UNESCO COURIER, now
in its thirteenth year, does more
than-merely satisfy the desire
for information about contem¬
porary problems; it throws
light on every aspect of human
endeavour, strengthens the links
between the peoples in every
corner of the globe, fosters
international understanding and
advances the cause of peace.
You can help by telling your
friends, colleagues and business
associates or your local libra¬
rian about THE UNESCO COUR¬
IER. It also makes an ideal
birthday or Christmas gift. As
a gift for your friends abroad,
you can subscribe to the French,
Spanish or Russian editions.
A YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION
COSTS ONLY IO/-stg.; $ 3.00;
7.00 New Francs or equivalent.
(See list of National Distribu¬
tors, below.) Wummmm
Some of the issues shown here may be out of print -fa
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaî. Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I. Victoria. (A. 13/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels. C.C.P. 3 38.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
I 6, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, C C.P. 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgielei 151,
Antwerp.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librarla Alberto Sanchez Veloso
O'Reilly y Villegas, Havana. - Librería Eco¬
nómica, Pte Zayas 505-7 Apartado 113,
Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Arda Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckich, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy. P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Paris, 7". C.C.P. 12598-48
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb fur Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6).
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf All Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Ra|kamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permata"
Djalan Nusantara 22, Djakarta
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco. Avenue du Musée. Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street. Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spalding!.( 1 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.. 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central. Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64. Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück.
33, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, 135, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore. .
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. (10/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
C. G.T. Van Dorp & C- (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass, 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 1 0)
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374, 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a. No. TI-4 9, Apartado de Correos 2018,
Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo. P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. " RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46
Warsaw. I 0 (Zl. 50.)
PORTUGAI	 Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livrana Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724. Pretoria. ( I 0/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-481 I. (Fr. S. 7).
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Raidamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istl-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION. OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church'
Street, Pretoria (10/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.( 1 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($ 3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York. 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Knlga.
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjlga,
Terazij« 27/1 I. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
FINE ARTS
ON STAMPS
A collection of stamps can also be a fine arts collec¬
tion, a veritable museum in miniature (see page 20).
Art from antiquity to yesterday has been reproduced
on stamps in more than 125 lands which have paid
tribute to their past and to their artists. The Nether¬
lands has honoured Rembrandt with a series of his
works, including self-portrait (opposite). Below, repro¬
duction on a Japanese stamp of "Beauty Looking
Back", an 18th century woodcut by Moronobu. Right,
an Ife bronze head represented on a Nigerian stamp.
B rfi Ü Fl
i
]]>
</page>
</document>
