<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064895eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
M
BIRTH OF AN ISLAND
JANUARY
19 5 9
(/2th year)
Price: 1/-stg. (U.K.)
30 cents (U . S .)
50 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
'LE BOURGEOIS GENTILHOMME' on the Screen. Millions of persons who have never had an opportunity to see a play
at Paris's world-famous Comédie Française will soon be able to see one in their local cinema. For the first time, the troupe
of the Comédie Française has consented to have the entire performance of a play speciallyfilmedforthe screen. The play chosen
was Moliere's " Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme". Its premiere showing took place in Paris a few weeks ago as part of "UNESCO
Month," a series of cultural manifestations arranged by the French National Commission for UNESCO on the occasion of the
inauguration of UNESCO's permanent headquarters and the Organization's tenth General Conference (See page 26). Photo
from the film shows famous scene in which Monsieur Jourdain (right) learns to his surprise and delight that he speaks "prose".
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
* , UNESCO
JANUARY 1959
I2T H YEAR
No. I
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 VOLCANOES: MORE USEFUL
THAN DESTRUCTIVE
By E. Aubert de la Rue
6 DESCENT INTO THE FIRE-PIT
Exploring a lake of molten rock
12 RICHES SPEWED FROM
THE WORLD'S VOLCANOES
14 BIRTH OF AN ISLAND
Submarine eruption off the Azores
18 THE TRUE MEANING OF AFRICAN DANCES
By Keita Fodeba
24 PHANTOMS OF THE BIRD WORLD
Unseen by man but not extinct
By John Westbury
26 'UNESCO MONTH" IN PARIS
France assembles a galaxy of cultural events
29 THE ENCIRCLING AIR
An invisible sea around us
By Kenneth Johns
32 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7'
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (I 2 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.132 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads " Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 500 Fr. frs. or equivalent.
COVER PHOTO
Submarine volcanoes are often respon¬
sible for the appearance of new islands
though few remain above the waves for
more than several months. Photographs
show two stages in the development of
one of these "disappearing Islands" which
pushed its way up from the sea floor in
1956 some 200 miles south of Tokyo.
Fumes and steam marking the site of
another volcanic islet in the making can
just be discerned in the background.
(See also "Birth of an Island", page 14)
USIS
As the New Year opens The Unesco Courier enters
its twelfth year of publication. Five years ago it
abandoned, its tabloid newspaper presentation and
appeared for the first time in the present magazine
format. Since then The Unesco . Courier has grown in
stature and readership, and it is now recognized as the
major medium of cultural exchange and of international
education for Unesco. It is in fact the only international
popular magazine of its kind sold -and read not only in
Unesco's 81 Member States but in practically every
country of the world.
The Courier is no|w published monthly in four separate
editions identical in text, pictures and layout: English,
French and Spanish editions published in Paris, and a
Russian edition published in Moscow. . In addition, a
reduced Japanese version appears in Tokyo and a Danish
version in Copenhagen. This year two new, full-fledged
editions are scheduled to be launched: an Arabic edition
for readers in the Middle East and other parts of the
Arabic-speaking world; and a German edition for readers
in Germany, Austria and German-speaking Switzerland.
A notice will appear in due course announcing when the
first number of these editions Will appear.
In its contents The Unesco Courier Will continue to
remain faithful to the goals it has set itself in the past:
to/ serve as "A Window Open on the World" of education,
science and culture through which every thinking man
and Woman can look out on to the broad global horizons
of international understanding for which Unesco is work¬
ing. Each month it will continue to bring its readers
authoritative information and food for thought presented
in everyday language and in revealing pictures. Wholly
non-political, its articles will portray, as in the past, the
life and cultures of different lands, the art and literature,
the science and education of other nations and describe
the work of the United Nations, Unesco and the other
U.N. Specialized Agencies.
At this great moment of advancing history and expand¬
ing horizons, the Editors feel that The Unesco Courier
has its place in every home and in every school.
SUBSCRIPTION INCREASE
IN FRENCH FRANCS
Despite a sharp rise in publishing costs the French franc
subscription rate of The Unesco Courier has not been
increased during the past year. Recent decisions affecting
the exchange rate of the French franc and the repercussions
these have had on production and distribution costs now
oblige us however to increase the annual French franc
subscription rate as of February 1, 1959, to 600 francs,
inclusive of postage. (This price increase is limited to sub¬
scriptions in French francs ; subscription rates in other cur¬
rencies remain unchanged)
Present subscribers in France may, nevertheless, renew
their subscriptions at the current rate provided renewals are
received by February 15.
We trust that our readers in France will appreciate the
fact that this increase in price is imposed by circumstances
beyond our control.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
VOLCÜ
Far more useful
than destructive
by E. Aubert de la RUe
iNCE ancient times volcanoes
have struck terror and wonder
into the heart of man. Yet
there is much more to volcanic
activity than the spectacular
and awe-inspiring eruptions which sometimes cause great
destruction. Comparatively few volcanoes are really dan¬
gerous and many of them are merely "noisy neighbours"
to those Who live nearby causing only a slight nuisance.
The share of good which volcanic force has brought to
the world has too often been obscured by the violent
outbursts of a few highly active cones.
In recent geological times, volcanoes have thrown up a
multitude of islands dotted among the oceans and seas of
the world which have added some hundreds of square
miles to the land surface of the earth. Their real value
to man however, lies in the widely varying uses to which
they can be put. On the continental land masses vol¬
canoes have raised up mountains which have done much
to increase what would otherwise have been a scanty
rainfall. And the peoples of the tropics often have a lofty
volcanic cone to thank for a more temperate climate.
The greatest benefit so far brought by volcanoes,'
however, has been the fertilizing effect of the lava and
ash they eject. The soils formed by the decay of these
volcanic products yield rich harvests in many countries.
This fertility accounts for the amazing density of popula¬
tion in the neighbourhood of many active craters. For¬
getful of past catastrophes and heedless of the dangers
that still threaten them, farmers have settled in large
numbers round Etna and Vesuvius and volcanoes in Cen¬
tral America, Indonesia, the Philippines and Japan, but
they now run fewer risks than their forefathers. In the
past few decades observation posts have been set up
alongside the most dangerous craters, so that an impend¬
ing eruption can be detected and warning given in good
time.
For a long while no attempt was made to harness the
enormous power generated by volcanoes. Even in quite
subsidiary forms it Was put only to such domestic uses
as heating and cooking or was employed therapeutically
in the form of hot mineral springs. Today the remarkable
technical achievements of Iceland and Italy arc- serving
as a spur to the harnessing of geothermal power for use
in industry. In a few years' time, other countries, par¬
ticularly those with few other sources of natural power,
are likely to be drawing more and more on the inexhaust¬
ible power offered by volcanoes.
The number of active volcanoes is not known exactly,
but has been estimated at between 400 and 620. These
figures relate only to eruptions on continents and islands
and not to those which occur on the ocean-floor but which
do not rise above sea-level; the exact locations of some
80 such craters are known, most of them being in the
Pacific.
As a rule, volcanoes are regarded as active if they have
erupted in historic times or if they are fumarolic that is,
if they have a vent from which vapour issues. Also includ¬
ed in this category are some recently discovered cones
situated in remote, deserted regions, about whose past
information is lacking but which are intact and appear
to be of recent formation. Several of the major eruptions
that have occurred since the beginning of the Christian
era have come from craters which for long showed no
sign of life and appeared to be quite extinct. The decep¬
tive nature of this inactivity has therefore to be taken
into account when making a classification of volcanoes.
Account must also be taken of new volcanoes which make
an unexpected appearance from time to time, such as
Jorullo in 1759. and Paracutin in 1943, both in the State
of Michoacan in Mexico, and the cone of scoria the
newest arrival in the volcanic worldwhich rose up in
1957 from the sea near the island of Fayal in the Azores.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
FIERY LAKES
OF SEETHING
MOLTEN ROCK
Among the strangest and
rarest of all the world's
volcanic phenomena are
the lakes of boiling lava in
MhL 0 which innumerable tons of
I^L molten rock bubble and
, fume incessantly. Few
dfíuf^ remain permanently in this
i state, most of them drying
A Hfr up periodically until reacti
fä vated by new eruptions.
7 P^^" The best known of these
Wr^ fire-pits are found on the
J Ê W* * opposite sides of the earth
/ J the centre of the Pacific
« Ocean and in the heart of
/. Y * Africa. Those of the Paci-
\tj * -. fie are Savii in the Samoan
. . .. .- Islands and the great cratery *è '
^r^^T ^%^^ %« * V of Kilauea on the island of
.
wF * . Hawaii in the Hawaiian Na-
i IF i tional Park. Today the
. ^ only large-scale lava lake
^
that is permanently active
is in the volcano of Nira-
. | Hk gongo in the Belgian Con-
« -3 ^M go. (See next page) Fiery
. _ J0 ^^B flow of lava (left) was pho-
j/r ]^m% tographed at night in the
crater of Niragongo's neigh¬
bour volcano Nyamlagira.
At the start of this century
Nyamlagira was the most
active of Africa's volcanoes
and possessed a large lake
of molten lava. From Janu¬
ary 1938 until the end of
1940 it was almost cons¬
tantly in a state of eruption
which culminated in the
collapse of its cone and
central crater. At the same
time its lake of lava dried up
(g) Haroun Tazieff, taken from the
film "Aux Rendez-vous du Diable"
Probably not more than fifty volcanoes above sea-level
can properly be described as in a present state of erup¬
tion. Most . of the others regarded as active are very
intermittently so, and have long periods of quiescence
between eruptions. Cones which are continually aglow
and smoking like those of Stromboli in the Mediterranean,
Izalco in El Salvador, the "Lighthouse of the Pacific"
whose red glow" is visible at night from far out at sea,
and Iahue on Tanna Island in the New Hebrides are few
and far between.
It is accurate enough to say that about 500 volcanoes
are active in varying degrees. They are thus only a
fraction of all the world's thousands of extinct volcanoes.
Some of these are still well preserved while others are so
eaten away by erosion as to be scarcely recognizable,
although the weird and spectacular shapes into which they
have sometimes worn are- characteristic of former volcanic
regions. They stand as reminders of a period of intense
activity within the earth which ended with the dawn
of the quaternary geological period, and show quite clearly
how present-day vulcanicity has declined compared with
that of the past.
Today's volcanoes are not distributed at random but
can be traced along or not far from zones in which the
earth's crust has become dislodged and weakened. They
seldom are found singly but usually in rectilinear or semi¬
circular formations, particularly in the case of island
volcanoes. Some parts of the world, such as Australia
and most parts of Europe and Asia, have no active vol¬
canoes at all, whereas others, such as the two Americas,
the Pacific seaboard and the median ridge of the Atlantic
have a very large number.
The differing degrees of activity shown by volcanoes
depend on the chemical composition of their lava and on
the latter 's temperature and- vapour content, for these
factors determine the fluidity of the lava. Though erup¬
tions may therefore be divided into several classes, there
are two main types.
The first are the effusive eruptions, marked by what is
often a gentle outflow of relatively fluid, dark-coloured
lava. Mauna Loa and Kilauea in Hawaii,
Etna in Italy and most of the basaltic
eruptions usually belong to this type. These
outflows, some of them extending twelve
miles or so, are a danger to crops and
houses but seldom imperil the lives of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
VOLCANOES (Continued)
Photos © Haroun Tazieff
DESCENT INTO
THE FIRE-PIT
OF NIRAGONGO
In September 1958 a Belgian expedition, one of the
scientific research groups set up during the Interna¬
tional Geophysical Year, set out to explore the
volcanic crater of Niragongo which stands in the
3,000 square mile Albert National Park of the Belgian
Congo. Rising to nearly I 1,000 feet and flanked by
two extinct volcanoes, Shaheru and Baouta, it has
boulder and lava-strewn crater walls which drop down
vertically in a series of gigantic steps to a vast lake of
lava hundreds of feet below. Until recent years
it had been regarded as inaccessible because of its
beetling cliffs and the poisonous fumes which rise out
of the pit. In 1958, one of the members of the
expedition was the French volcanologist and geologist,
Haroun Tazieff who in 1948 and again in I 953. had
attempted to reach the lake. The most recent
attempt was successful. Members of the expedition
were lowered by cable to the first terrace 600 feet
below. A second descent of 500 feet brought them
to a ledge from where they were able to observe the
lake of lava at very close range, bubbling and seething
at temperatures varying between 1,000 and 1,200
degrees C. Photos, taken during the 1958 expedi¬
tion, show, above, one of the party about to descend
Into the crater; right, a 600 feet high cliff forming
the first "step" down into Niragongo's giant crater.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
mmmmËËm
E. Aubert de la Rüe
VOLCANIC WASTELAND, stretching as far as the eye can see, is in the dry, barren Bara plain of the Somali Coast.
Stony "crop" covering the soil is composed of innumerable basalt rocks and boulders, the products of past volcanic activity.
peoples settled in their vicinity, who generally have time
to flee before the approaching lava which seldom travels
more than about fifty or at the most a few hundred yards
an hour. The Hawaiian volcanoes have the swiftest flow*
which for short distances and on a very steep slope, has
been known to exceed eighteen yards a second.
To the second type belong the very much more formid¬
able explosive eruptions. Highly viscous lava rises to the
surface of the crater, giving off great quantities of gaseous
products, and in particular water-vapour, which find diffi¬
culty in escaping. Explosions pulverize the lava creating
large quantities of ash and incandescent, semi-solid
lumps which are hurled upwards. The lighter materials,
obscuring the discharge of vapour from the crater, may
be carried far afield by currents of air. The great vol¬
canic outbursts have mostly been caused by this type of
explosion, which commonly occurs in craters that have
been so long dormant that lava from the last eruption has
had time to solidify and stop up the "throat" of the vol¬
cano. A lengthy period of quiescence causes an accumu¬
lation of gases to be trapped in the heart of the crater,
and this explains' the tremendous power generated by
volcanoes. The longer the time elapsing between two
successive eruptions, the more violent is the fresh outburst
likely to be.
In both historic and modern times, a number of volca¬
noes have won tragic fame for their disastrous eruptions.
The eruption of Vesuvius, which in 79 AD. buried Hercu-
laneum and Pompeii beneath its ashes is perhaps the best
known in history. Then there was the terrible explosion
of Tambora, on Sumbawa Island in 1815one of the most
staggering of all times Which claimed 50,000 victims and
cut 4,000 feet off the height of this mountain. In 1886, a
similar explosion literally ripped open the slumbering
volcano of TaraWera in New Zealand forming a fissure
several miles long. The eruption transformed the topo¬
graphy of the area, but claimed few victims in this spar¬
sely populated region. A few years previously, in 1883,
the eruption of Krakatoa in the Strait of Sunda devasta
ted an island, causing 36,000 deaths. Other memorable
catastrophes occurred in Nicaragua in 1835, when the
peak of Conseguina was cut off, the explosion being heard
nearly 1,000 miles away, in Japan in 1888 when Bandai
San lost 1,950 feet of its height in a few seconds, in Gua¬
temala in 1902, when Santa Maria buried a large area
under a pall of ash, and in Martinique in the same year,
When Mount Pelée wiped out the city of Saint Pierre with
its 28,000 inhabitants.
The deadliest form of volcanic activity is the sudden
recrudescence of volcanoes Which have been so long dor¬
mant that they are regarded as extinct and are therefore
left unwatched. The unexpected eruption of Mount
Lamington in New Guinea, which caused 6,000 deaths in
1952, is a recent case in point. Most of the great volcanic
disasters have, in fact, been caused by surprise outbursts
from dormant craters. Nowadays regular observations are
usually made on craters which show intermittent activity,
and a special alarm system is arranged to warn people
living nearby of impending danger. The most dangerous
volcanoes which are surrounded by rich farmland with a
dense population or those Which are situated near towns
and cities, are increasingly watched over by experts.
Vulcanology and geophysics have armed these specialists
with up-to-date detection devices such as seismographs,
geophones, and recording thermometers, as well as
analyses of gas content, gravimetric measurements, and
detection of possible changes in the surface of the ground
by very accurate levelling of the approaches to the
volcano. There have been many successful forecasts of
eruptions, the most famous of which concerned the 1914
eruption of Sakura JLma in the Bay of Kagoshima in
Japan; sufficient Warning was given for the Whole popula¬
tion to be evacuated. Some of the world's best equipped
vulcanological observatories are to be found
on Vesuvius and Etna in Italy and on
Kilauea, in Hawaii, as Well as in Martinique,
Japan and Indonesia. Planes and heli¬
copters are now available, if not to stop the
flow of the lava streams, at any rate to
Cont'd
on
next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
VOLCANOES (Continued)
alter their direction, by bombing the outflow pointsa
method which has often been successfully employed at
Mauna Loa in Hawaii.
Man has found scores of uses for the materials ejected
by volcanoes. From earliest times, volcanic lava, breccia
and tuff, which are usually easy to work, have been used
to build temples and palaces, individual dwellings and
sometimes whole cities. In every age, outstanding works
of art have been created with volcanic substances. Many
primitive peoples were famed for their skill in making
highly decorative objects from carved and polished lava.
The Indians of the high Mexican plateaux and the Andes,
and many South Sea Islanders, including the inhabitants
of Easter Island in the Pacific and the Marquesas, are
noted for such work.
A volcanic material highly prized by the peoples of
antiquity was obsidian, a natural glass, or vitreous lava,
extruded by certain volcanoes. It was universally
employed for making utilitarian objects as well as for
jewelry and ornamentation on account of its brilliance
and iridescence. The few rich deposits of obsidian were
deservedly famous. Those on the Island of Melos were
celebrated throughout the Aegean. Before metals came
into use the products of these deposits were in great
demand for the manufacture of armour and various tools.
In the pre-Colombian era, the inhabitants of the high
Mexican plateaux used the obsidian ejected by some of
their volcanoes for making knives, razors, arrow-heads
and works of art. The most extensively worked deposits
were on the Cerro de las Navajas (Mountain of Knives),
near Pachuca in the State of Hidalgo.
Town built of pumice stone
Since 1946, obsidian has acquired considerable industrial
importance on account of its expansibility. It is used
for the manufacture of perlite, a very light material
rather like pumice stone. Some obsidians have a high
water content which enables them to expand to twenty
times their volume when heated to a high enough tem¬
perature to soften them. The perlite obtained by process¬
ing the obsidian quarried in the West of the United States,
particularly in Nevada, and also in Italy (Ponza Island to
the west of Naples) and Sardinia, is used for the manu¬
facture of light, insulating and incombustible building
materials.
Pumice stone, with its very light, cellular texture, may
properly be described as the natural foam of volcanic
glass; it has many uses in industry and as a toilet
requisite. This variety of lava is in use in a great many
volcanic regions, but the finest quality comes from Lipari
Island in Italy, which produces 50,000 tons a year for
export. The pumice stone found in various parts of the
world is an excellent building material. For instance, the
town of Latacunga in the Andes of Ecuador was built»
entirely of pumice stone, as is also the huge dome of the
church of St. Sophia in Istanbul.
The lavas of present-day volcanoes, unlike those of the
past, are very poor in Workable metals, but the outflows
sometimes contain other useful substances. The volcanoes
of Naples and of Green River in Wyoming U.S.A., for
instance, are rich in potassium. Unfortunately, no cheap
processes have yet been developed for the extraction of
the potassium salts contained in these lavas.
One of the commonest volcanic products is sulphur,
which has been regularly mined from a great number of
craters, temporarily reduced to the status of sulphur-
springs. They are still being worked in some countries,
but volcanic sulphur deposits are small, scattered and
difficult of access and are being abandoned more and
more in favour of sedimentary deposits of sulphur such as
are found in Sicily and Texas.
Volcanoes bring from the bowels of the earth reserves
of mineral matter essential to plant life. They are also
one of the sources of the carbon dioxide contained in the
atmosphere, without which plants would not be able to
grow. Lime, phosphoric acid, potassium and other nu¬
tritive salts are . constantly being drained from the soil
by plants and the run-off of water, but are replaced to
lome extent by volcanoes which replenish impoverished
8
OUNTAIN GROWN
FROM A CORNFIELD
soils by furnishing a regular supply of elements necessary
to cultivation and plant life in general.
The over-abundant showers of ash from some explosive
eruptions naturally bring disaster and ruin for a time
at least. Yet the havoc they wreak is generally confined
to a small area and is of less importance than the
prosperity volcanoes bring to many agricultural districts.
Moreover, their beneficial effect is felt far beyond their
normal radius of activity, for they send up fine dust into
the air to such a height that it is carried long distances
by atmospheric currents.
The fertility of the soil thus formed on the slopes of
volcanoes has always been a magnet to farming commun¬
ities. Observing the infrequency with Which volcanoes
give vent to their destructive forces, the farmers consider
that the rich harvests reaped from land where lava once
flowed fully justify the risks of cultivation in such
relatively dangerous localities. All the disasters of the
past have never prevented man from clinging to land in
the proximity of volcanoes and even the threat of an
imminent eruption is not always enough to make him
abandon soil which gives such flourishing crops.
The slopes of Vesuvius and Etna, famous for their vines
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
On February 20, 1943, a Mexican farmer was ploughing his cornfield
near a village some 200 miles west of Mexico City, in a region of recent
volcanic activity in the western Sierra Madre. Suddenly he saw a spiral
of steam rise from a small depression in the ground, then the earth began
to crack and raise itself and finally a huge column of black smoke rolled
upwardsa new volcano, Paricutin was being born. By next day it had
built up a cone more than 50 feet high. In puffs that occurred every six
Photos © E. Aubert de la Rue
seconds it ejected cinders, ash and bombs of solid rock estimated at 2,700
tons a minute. Within six months the cone (above, right) was 1,000 feet
high. Paracutin provided what was termed "the most splendid firework
show of all time" but the volcano also engulfed villages in a sea of lava.
Top of church tower can still be seen (above, left) above the advancing
lava. Paracutin, which erupted for nearly ten years, was the first volcano in
history to be observed scientifically almost from the moment of its birth.
and orchards, are not the only volcanic sites thus sought
after; the sides of volcanoes in Central America, covered
with rich coffee plantations, and those of Java, the
Philippines and Japan are equally coveted. In the tropics
a host of volcanic islands have been turned into Gardens
of Eden where every kind of tropical fruit is grown. The
Canary Islands, the Azores, the West Indies, Sao Thoma,
Fernando Po and Reunion are but a few examples.
For a long time man had no defence against volcanic
eruptions and his chief feeling about them was one of
helplessness in the face of the irresistible forces they
unleash. Yet for centuries his imagination has also been
stimulated by the possibility of tapping the tremendous
reserves of power locked up in the depths of volcanoes.
Only in relatively recent times, however, has this dream
become an industrial reality. We are not as yet at the
stage of making direct use of the enormous power released
by erupting volcanoes, but at least various countries are
beginning to put some of the secondary forms of volcanic
activity to work for them. With modern equipment it is
possible to sink bores to great depths and thus reach very
high temperatures. Today it is no longer fanciful to
consider the possibility, within the near future, of drawing
off the incandescent gases generated in the underground
reservoirs of volcanoes.
Ideas which not long ago appeared Utopian are now
becoming facts. The natural vapour given off in large
quantities near Lardarello in Tuscany, Italy, has for long
attracted attention because of its special properties and its
industrial possibilities. Italian engineers not only work
these natural steamholes or soffioni, but they are now
drilling down to a depth of nearly 2,000 feet, where the
superheated vapour is captured and directed through
reinforced pipes to steam generating stations, now
producing some 300,000 (kilowatts. In addition, the
soffioni are used for chemical purposes, such as the
extraction of boron, carbon dioxide, ammonia and various
other industrial gases. Research into the uses of geo-
thermal power is being conducted in other parts of Italy,
particularly in the Phlegraean Fields, the Euganean Hills,
at Viterbo in Latium, on the islands of
Ischia and Vulcano and round Sciacca in
Sicily.
The Icelanders too have made extensive
use of the hot springs which abound on
their island as a subsidiary phenomenon
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
VOLCANOES (Continued)
C.N.R.S., Paris
LULL IN ACTIVITY of one of history's most famous volcanoes, Vesuvius, in the Bay of Naples, gave
air-photographer a chance to take this clear shot of its crater. Today Vesuvius is about 3,600 feet
high, but once it may have been twice that height since traces have been found of a very large crater
that was blown away in pre-historic times. After the eruption of 79 A.D. which buried Pompeii, Hercu-
laneum and Stabiae, Vesuvius was less active until the great eruption of 1631. Since then it has never
been really quiet, but when it is at its quietest it is possible to climb up and stand above the crater.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
GIANT WITH
TWIN MOUTHS
Two moods of a twin-mouthed volcano,
Boquerón, off the west coast of Mexico,
captured In aerial photographs. Right, a dense
cloud of vapour and ash spouts upwards as
the volcano erupts. Below, a thin plume of
vapour rises from one of the twin mouths of
the Boquerón crater. Run-off. of molten lava
down to the sea has outlined the contours of
this volcanic island. Mexico is a land of
volcanoes. Starting at its border with the
United States is the beginning of a chain that
is practically unbroken until it reaches the
southern end of South America. The great
Mexican peak, Mount Popocatepetl, which
rises to 17,888 feet, is one of the highest
active volcanoes anywhere in the world today.
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
USIS photos
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
m
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
wW¿
1%-M
«wW** '
countries like-Italy and Iceland in harnessing geothermal
power are encouraging other nations to develop the use
of the inexhaustible power reserves offered by volcanoes.
Photographs on these pages, illustrating some of the
benefits brought by volcanic activity, show : (1) Deposit
of pure sulphur in the sulphur spring on Vanua Lava,
one of the Melanesian group of Pacific islands (2) Tra¬
vertine deposit created by a hot spring in Frenen Somali-
land. Travertine stone from Italian deposits rorms the
principal building material of Rome. (3) Generrtion after
generation of farmers have cultivated the slopes of Etna
in Sicily. Splendid orchards of olive, lemon orange,
fig, and almond trees and vineyards, are nourished by the
rich soil covering the sides of the volcano. (4) Thermal
springs near Lake Rotoruá in New Zealand. The wonder¬
land of hot springs and geysers in this area is a major
tourist attraction. (5) Disused pumice-stone workings at
Latacunga in Ecuador. Nearby is one of the highest
volcanoes in the Andes, Cotopaxi, which rises 19,498 feet.
(6) Quarrying for stonebasaltic rockon the slopes of
Mount Etna. The distribution of basalts is world wide,
often occurring in immense masses. (7) House built of
blocks hewn from pumice in Tlaxcala, Mexico.' Photos
1, 2, 4, 5, 7 (©) E. Aubert de la Rüe 3, 6 (©) H. Tazieff.
I3
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
BIRTH OF
-j**: ^^
X«ÜP
Photos © Les Reporters Associés, Paris
H"
'.
k
im SLAND
© H. Tazieff
For just over one month in 1957
the nine Portuguese islands call¬
ed the Azores, a group 400 miles
long, almost midway between
North America and Europe, be¬
came ten. On September 28 a
submarine eruption took place
just off the island of Fayal and
a volcano emerged from the sea
about 400 yards from the light¬
house of Punta dos Capelinhos.
Its apparition had been prefaced
by slight earth tremors followed
by a violent shock which damag¬
ed the village of Cápelo and
spread panic among the inhabi¬
tants. At the same moment the
sea began to boil, flames and
vapours rose from it and soon a
fierce column of smoke and
cinders shot high into the air.
On October 7, a sudden change
in wind direction carried a rain
of ash and cinders onto the island
of Fayal and partially buried the
now deserted village of Capelo.
Three weeks after it first appear¬
ed the crater of llha Nova
(New Island), shaped like a
horseshoe and giving off a dense
cloud of smoke, vapour and cin¬
ders, had risen over 600 feet
above the waves. (Photos on
these pages show the progres¬
sive stages in the growth of llha
Nova.) After some three weeks
the eruption began to die down
and finally ceased on October
29. The sea made short workof
the cinders forming the cone öf
llha Nova and within a few days
there remained only a wave-
swept rock, shrouded by the
wisps of vapour rising from the
site of the former crater. The va¬
garies of submarine volcanoes
are responsible for the appear¬
ance of such short-lived islands,
which have varying lifetimes
though rarely longer than a few
months. Some disappear only
to reappear once or even several
timesatlaterdates. "Disappear¬
ing islands" of this type have
often given rise to diplomatic
claims by nations seeking to in¬
crease their overseas territories.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
V VJ JJ V/1\XM WillM (Cont'd from page 9)
of volcanism. Since 1930 a system has been in operation
for supplying homes with hot water from springs. At
Reykjavik, the capital, nearly 3,500 homes are now heated
with water at 185° F. The town also has several
swimming-pools maintained at 98° F and public wash-
houses supplied with natural hot water. Villages and
even isolated farms now have their hot water supply
as well. Of special interest is the use by Iceland of hot
springs for the heating of hot houses, where many
varieties of fruits, vegetables and even flowers can be
grown, despite the cold climate.
Elsewhere too, a good deal of research has been devoted
in recent years to the possibilities of using the heat locked
up inside the earth as a source of power. This research
has been carried furthest in California, the State of
Hidalgo in Mexico, the Republic of El Salvador, the district
of Wairakei in New Zealand, famous for its hot springs,
and in East Africa and Japan.
Terrifying and destructive as eruptions may be, they are
a magnificent sight to watch with their dark columns of
ash, their great billows of vapour shot through with
flashes as brilliant as a firework display, their fuming
streams of lava and the blazing craters glowing red
against the night sky. The splendour of active volcanoes
and the strange subsidiary forms they take, such as
sulphur-springs, geyser jets, mud volcanoes and other
varí ¿ties of hot springs attract many tourists.
ISxtinct volcanoes, many of them weather-beaten and
crumbling, are often surrounded by enchanting scenery.
The charm of old volcanic regions such as the Eifel in
Germany, Auvergne in France and the Polynesian
archipelagoes, once thrown up by a long series of eruptions
and now sculpted into weird shapes by erosion are well
.known. The old eroded volcanoes of the Society Islands,
the Hawaiian archipelago and the islands of the Atlantic,
from the Azores to the West Indies, by way of the Canary
and Cape Verde Islands, are equally celebrated.
Geyser & hot spring parks
Extinct craters, where lakes have formed from the
gradual accumulation of rain water, some of them a
perfect circle, are a curiosity of many volcanic sites.
The impressive grandeur of some of these lakes has made
them deservedly famous as beauty spots. But the special
configuration of many old craters also enables man to
make other uses of them. Those which form a natural
enclosure as at Aden in Arabia can serve as reservoirs;
other old craters in Mexico, Patagonia and the Andes, are
prized as farmland, as they afford shelter for crops against
strong winds. Where the explosion of an island volcano
has opened a large breach in its wall, an excellent natural
harbour may be formed if the sea breaks into the crater.
In the past man's chief reaction to volcanoes was fear.
Today as this is replaced more and more by one of
interest, many countries with active or extinct volcanoes
on their territory are taking the trouble to preserve the
surrounding sites in their natural state. Many of the
finest volcanoes have now been converted into National
parks. The United States of America has taken the lead
in the preservations of volcanic sites and has created some
fifteen famous parks, including Yellowstone National
Park with its geysers and pools of boiling water, Greater
Lake National Park in Oregon, the park surrounding
Lassen Peak in California, and others in Hawaii and
elsewhere; in them visitors can observe past and present
volcanic activity in a wide variety of forms. Other
countries also have some very fine volcanic parks.
Thus it can be seen that in addition to bringing havoc
and also being of value to man the world's volcanoes make
first-class recreation centres, for in action they provide
natural spectacles of awe-inspiring beauty and scenery of
tremendous grandeur.
E. Aubert de la Riie, author of this article, is a French geologist
who has carried out numerous surveys and missions in different parts
of the world. In 1953 and in 1956 he went to Brazil on Unesco
technical assistance missions. Since October 1958 he has been
entrusted with a new Unesco mission as chief of a survey of natural
resources in South Chile. He is the author of many works on
geographical and geological questions, the most recent being "L'Homme
et les volcans" (Man and Volcanoes) published by Gallimard, Paris.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
BIRTH OF AN ISLAND (Continued)
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
CHOKED BY A RAIN
OF BURNING CINDERS
Shortly after It emerged from the sea, the volcano of llha
Nova began to shower clouds of dust and cinders on the
nearby Island of Fayal. Great submarine explosions which
rocked the new volcano (left) sent tremendous showers
of debris high into the air from where it was blown inland
by the wind. Houses, crops and pasture land were covered
by a thick layer of cinders, under whose weight roofs caved
in (below). Thousands of acres of land were covered under
debris to a depth of several yards through which streams
fed by torrential rains carved out deep fissures (above),
innumerable fish choked by cinders were washed ashore.
Jovial, Fayal, Azore«
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE TRUE
MEANING
OF AFRICAN
DANCES
by Keita Fodeba
m URING the many tours our troupe has made in
France and other countries, I have noticed
that for most Europeans, the authentic African
dance show corresponds to the single idea they
have formed of Africa from attending a
lecture or seeing, a film.
But this idea is bound to be Wrong, for Africa is a
much larger continent than Europe and more varied. A
film made of any given part of Africa cannot entirely
reflect the essential character of our different regions,
in the way that France Germany or Sweden, for example,
could never become identified to the point of merging
into one psychic entity. Senegal and the Congo are as
different from each other as Finland is from Italy. And
has not modern science endowed the West with, a number
of means of human contact as compared with our so-
called "primitive" countries, where Nature still weighs
heavily on man, often isolating him from his nearest
neighbours? It seems to us consequently tendentious to
try systematically to classify the whole of this vast conti¬
nent by reference to the colour of its inhabitants. The
influence of background upon man is far more important
than that of the degree of pigmentation of his skin. A
thousand historical examples prove this eloquently
enough, be it a question of white, black or yellow races.
Nevertheless, we do not think that the influence exerted
by geographical or social surroundings, however power¬
ful this may be, is alone sufficient to mould man. As
far as we, the black peoples of Africa, are concerned, it
is obvious that whatever may be the degree of assimi¬
lation of foreign cultures as a result of being many times
uprooted, it is still historically too early for us to lose all
our African ethnical characteristics.
Our transplanted brothers have generally been placed
in such political, moral and material conditions, that as
a result of retiring within themselves so
often they have reinforced their psychic
bonds with our continent. Owing to the
dominating effect of conditions of environ¬
ment upon the individual, it would seem
difficult to" speak of a culture of the Negro
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
RHYTHM AND MOVEMENT are media by which the people of Africa express
their feelings in a language of dance as intelligible as speech. Characteristic of
the life of Africa, the dance can become ritual, magic, witchcraft, exorcism, an
expression of freedom, of morals and varied sentiments... for dance is able to
reach to man's instincts and subconscious powers and to express him completely.
Zulu dance. © Paul Almasy, Paris
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
AFRICAN DANCES
(Continued)
World. Yet, to the best of our (knowledge, nowhere in the
world during the long years of their tragic expatriation
have the black races enjoyed social and economic con¬
ditions which were sufficient to destroy utterly their
original ties.
On the one hand, Africa being the land of origin of
the Negroes, we can probably deduce that for a long time,
and wherever they are, they will retain something an¬
cestral which will link them to their African brothers.
On the other hand, when we consider the fate reserved,
generally speaking for the black man in the so-called
"civilized" world, we are obliged, in the present circum¬
stances, to recognize and wish for a certain identity of
aim in culture. "Every culture worthy of the name, must
be able to give and to receive," it is said. And the added
merit of the black cultures will be that they all have the
same legitimate desire to defend the cause of an unjustly
used race.
When drawing up the programmes of the African Ballet
Company, our constant concern is to avoid misleading the
public by presenting a fictitious picture conforming to
the usual preconceived idea. To make Africa and all its
variety known, we have chosen dance, not only as an
excellent means of universal expression but also because,
with us, it is connected with all the other arts.
African dance indeed, far from being the autonomous
art that it is in Europe, is primarily a union of rhythm
and movement. A characteristic phenomenon of our life,
it can become ritual, magic, witchcraft, exorcism, an
expression of freedom, morals and sundry sentiments...
for dance is able to reach to man's instincts, to his sub¬
conscious powers and express him completely.
In all countries of the world, there are as many forms
of dance as there are peoples, customs, cults, traditions
and ethics. The differentiation between the arts in
Europe has progressively raised dance to the status of
ballet by detaching it from the life of the people, of
which in Africa it is a spontaneous emanation. The
developed form of dance, self-conscious and no longer
imitative, collective or religious but a creation in itself,
has existed in Western culture for many centuries.
This progressive tendency to intellectualize the dance,
which seems to be in proper relation to progress, seems
to forget the fact that the arts at the beginning sprang
from necessity, that is to say, they Were created in re¬
sponse to a vital need. Ballet, in its Western conception,
is an original choreographic and musical creation. Our
popular African dances hardly yet correspond to this.
But if ballet is "a form of artistic and cultural expression
developed by man in his endless quest for new means of
expression, in his yearning to create forms Which are
ceaselessly renewed according to his genius and abilities",
African dance as a means of expression and of exterio¬
rization can be identified with ballet. That is the reason
Why we call ourselves the "African Ballet Company" with
the conviction that our songs and dances will have some
significance for all who have correct ideas about life in
Africa.
If, in Europe, dance must necessarily aim at grace and
beauty, be aesthetic as well as expressive of an idea, in
our peaceful African villages, we still learn to sing and
dance just as one learns to talk. Nobody dances for his
neighbour but, instead, to express what he feels, translated
by the rhythm of his movements and his body into a
language which, although different from speech, is no
less intelligible. Moreover in a country where drums can
send messages to great distances, it would be impossible
to dissociate music and dance for the rhythms of sound
and those of the body have the same capacity for
expression. A step evokes a rhythm as much as a song
involves a dance figure.
Photo Ilse Steinhoff, from the film "L'homme contre la jungle"
CIRCUMSTANTIAL DANCES are as numerous and as varied as events in daily life in Africa and they are chiefly character¬
ized by a strong element of Improvisation. Thus, to the rhythms of the tom-toms and the balafons, the whole village will
join in a common celebration for the return of a soldier, a successful hunting trip or the reconciliation of two tribal chiefs.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
/
© Pierre Verger
RITUAL CEREMONIES are nearly always accompanied by dances of symbolic character. Each African dance has a definite
reason behind it. There are traditional dances based on history or ceremonial rites, just as there are also circumstantial
ones which originate in the innumerable aspects of human existence. Photo shows a ritual dance performed in Dahomey.
Neither would it be possible to understand the essential
part played by dance in the life of the African peoples
if one did not bear in mind their conditions of life.
When à body has the lightness and the flexibility of a
"liana", who could prevent it from dancing? When the
economic stage is essentially agricultural, involving few
needs and material worries why not move like a bird or
snake, open like a flower and so be in communion with.
Nature and the mysterious powers which people it and
animate it?
If one remembers these circumstances it is easy to see
why the Africans are, so to speak, the real men of dance.
For the very rhythm of their existence is already an invi¬
tation to dancea simple rhythm in common time, which
can be translated into the following needs:
to work for the community
to enjoy the fruit of common labour
to honour the gods Who protect man during his life
and safeguard him after death
to exteriorize the cause and effect of these activities
by song and dance.
One should not however deduce from this that if our
people rhythmically, stamp the ground in the public place
in the village, they do so unconsciously, like a leaf shak¬
en by the wind. Not one of our dances it performed
without a definite reason. Just as there are traditional
dances based on history or ceremonial rites, so there are
circumstantial dances which arise from innumerable cir¬
cumstances of existence.
In this Way, when the Mandinga civilization was spread¬
ing over a large part of the Continent, the vulture which
usually hovered over the bodies of the fallen, was regard¬
ed as a symbol of bravery and courage. A dance was
dedicated to him, which the more intrepid warriors
solemnly executed after a victory. Today, the Mandinga
tradition has adopted this "'Dance of the Vulture" as a
token of honour and no one has the right to dance-it who
does not deserve to do so through some brilliant fèat of
arms or if he has not been authorized by the Council of
Elders.
A thousand dances of this kind stand out as landmarks
in the history of Africa and help to explain it. In return,
popular tradition has created, through the centuries,
other dances, the character of which is also symbolic, but
which are dedicated to ceremonial rites. Such are those
which, among the peoples of Upper Guinea, mark the
initiation of the child at puberty to the principal duties
of life. First, bewitched by the traditional rhythms, the
initiate is possessed by the devils of his own natural bad
tendencies; he dances until he loses consciousness. He
is brought back to life by the witchdoctor whose exorcism .
then points out the path of good to the child... As for
the circumstantial dances, they are as numerous and
different as the happenings of life and are mainly cha¬
racterized by the large part left to improvisation. In
this way, for instance, to the rhythms of the tom-toms
and balafons, the whole village will celebrate the return
of a soldier, a successful hunting trip or the reconciliation
of two tribal chiefs.
It is, moreover, important to note that a celebration of
which the original character is completely circumstantial,
may be periodically repeated later without in any way
becoming part of the cycle of ceremonial rites. The best
example which illustrates this is certainly that of the
clearing of the land. At the beginning of the rainy
season, the whole village gathers at the call of the drums
to cultivate together, in common, the field of every head
of a family. And at night, by moonlight, this form of
mutual assistance enjoyed without distinction by all the
families, is the occasion for great festivities and joyful
dances.
Yet, although all is replete with art and
poetry, there are still some people for
whom an African folklore performance is
far from being artistic, for the simple rea¬
son that 2,000 years of civilization have
not so far drawn their attention to the
Cont'd
on
next page
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
AFRICAN DANCES (Continued)
When a body has the
lightness & flexibility
of a liana, who could
prevent it from dancing?
existence of genuine forms of culture other than their
own. One can also remember that some civilizations at
thier peak have died out, not having been able to rege¬
nerate themselves by contact with external cultural move¬
ments. The rôle of African performers of the future must
be to bring out the essential, characteristic elements of
our cultures while ¡preserving their originality in our
contacts with the Western world.
How often do we hear the word '"genuine" used at
random to describe folklore performances.
Genuine, in fact, compared to what? To a more or
less false idea which one has conceived about the sensa¬
tional primitiveness of Africa? No! Authentic folklore
is that which truly represents the more characteristic
aspects of the existence it wishes to bring to life on the
stage. Thus, to appreciate the degree of authenticity, it
is necessary to know at least a little about the life which
gave birth to the performance. By giving, a priori, a pre-
logical mentality to the Africans, it is indisputable that
one cannot perceive the intense humanity contained in
their songs and dances.
For us, anthenticity is synonymous with reality. In so
far as folklore is made up of a country's traditions, poems,
songs, dances and popular legends, it can only be the
reflection of the life of that country. And if this life
develops, there is no reason why folklore, which is its
living expression, should not develop too. That is the
reason why the folklore of present-day Africa is as
authentic as that of ancient Africa, both of them being
the real expression of the Ufe of our country at two diffe¬
rent periods in its history.
What makes folklore authentic?
The present tendency of an African folklore company
such as ours must be to display to the whole world
the cultural values of both these two Áfricas; the
traditional and pre-colonial Africa of our forefathers and
the Africa of today which is gradually being impregnated
with Western civilization. Indeed it would be absurd to
confine our folklore only to our own country's past, for no
folklore in the world is entirely pure and free of all
mixture.
Because Arab influence has indelibly marked Spain, this
does not mean that the songs and danges of that country
are not genuine. On the other hand the history of the
dance teaches us how the liturgical, dances of the Middle
Ages differed from the popular French dances of the
period, during which, through various influences, the
latter became the choreographic language of the aristo¬
cracy and gave rise to theatre and court ballet, so nearly
resembling each other as to be indistinguishable. Have
the Basque dances of today remained unchanged in style
and meaning for hundreds of years?
In Africa too, just as there are the dances of our fathers
and our grandfathers, full of majesty and wisdom, so the
younger generations in the villages create today songs and
dances which picture our times, already marked by three
centuries of colonization.
During our last African tour, a musician of the forest
region of Guinea gave us, as a souvenir of his village,
some fine '"maracas" made of coconuts. Yet it is generally
considered that maracas come from South America...
There are a hundred similar examples that we could men¬
tion for the paradox of a certain type of ignorance is that
it considers all objects, instruments, dances and so on,
that the black peoples have brought with them in their
enforced pilgrimages to other continents, have only
become genuine since their exile and because of it.
The essence of authenticity in folklore is not to lose the
original character through external influences. In our
programme of African ballets we have a "Casamançais"
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
song, the words of which are in Portuguese Creole, but
the feeling of which is deeply African because it expresses
one of our oldest proverbs : "Love is like an egg, he who
breaks it is lost". In this way a Creole African song may
perfectly well find its place in an African performance,
Portuguese Creole having become the current dialect of
a large part of Casamance to the south of Senegal. In
the same way one should not be at all surprised to see
half-castes among our performers, singing and dancing in
the usual manner of our villages. For if Western
influence is felt in the economic, cultural and political
life of our country, it is also felt in the field of simple
human contacts and has produced the increasingly large
class of mulattos, considered by Africa as her own children.
During our last Paris season at the Théâtre des Champs-
Elysées, a Press critic seemed to be upset by the fact
that our singer Kandia, one of these traditional African
"griots", sang in a more or less Spanish-Flamenco style.
This journalist was obviously unaware that some African
empires from the 12th to the 15th century, had strong
ties with the Arab countries and were influenced by them
just as Spain came to bear the same Arab stamp.
Kandia has no idea what a Flamenco is but, brought up
to a knowledge of African history he knows that if the
huts in the Sudan (seat of the Mandinga Empire) are
rather Arab in style, it is because they have been inspired
by thet Mosques built by Es Saheli, the architect whom the
Emperor Kongo Moussa, brought back with him from his
sumptuous pilgrimage to Mecca. And it would be absurd
to think that our Sudanese huts were not authentic !
Drums speak with power & magic.
In all countries of the world, art progresses in relation
to the social, economic and political conditions which
determine it. . Thus as well as our pure, unmixed
forms of expression we must present those which have
been influenced by other civilizations. But whatever 'the
form of expression used, African art teaches us to regard
as essential in our societies solidarity, love of virtue and
brotherhood between men.
Nevertheless, the stage being different from life, it is
necessary to resort to a certain amount of stage adapta¬
tion to make ourselves understood by a foreign public.
In our African villages, the same dance may last a whole
night without tiring anyone. The dances are, moreover,
executed in the middle of a ring of spectators who also
take part almost as much as the dancers and musicians.
On the stage new conditions have to be created through
different devices in order to retain the freshness and
reality of the dance and to destroy the monotony which
is quick to arise due to the non-active participation of the.
audience. That " is the reason why we must take our
dances only at their culminating point shorten them and
cut out a thousand details which are not important except
in the public place of the village.
In conclusion it only remains to express a wish which
is dear to our hearts :
May the Africa of tomorrow never lose the secrets of
its songs and dances! May it always be able to dance,
for to Africa dance is life a thousand years having been
only like one long dance with many figures, a real dance
of life which is the message of Africa today! The Afri¬
cans in the cities must not neglect this message nor aban¬
don its meaning to the hazards and vicissitudes of history.
We do not know to what extent dance may play a deter¬
mining role in other societies. But We know that with
all its moral and social context, dance has been the link
which enabled African societies to maintain their cohe-
siveness. We know that only the drums have sufficent
power and magic in their 'voices to speak to Africans in
their original language.
However different the forms and origins of our dances
may be, they nevertheless seem to share the same spirit.
This is the spirit which man never ceases to discover with
wonder in himself. For him there is only one law : conti¬
nual progress, onwards and upwards. In this way, to the
dynamic power of the thought corresponds the dynamic
power of the dance, which is thought embodied.
The article above was adapted from "African Dance and the
Stage" by Keita Fodeba, published in Volume VII, No. 3 of
"World Theatre" (See page 35: "The Only International Theatre
Magazine"). Keita Fodeba was born in French Guinea, and
after leaving university he became a teacher in Saint-Louis,
Senegal. Prior to forming his African Ballet Company in 1950
he travelled throughout Africa to recruit his dancers. He is
now Guinea's Minister of the Interior.
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
PHANTOMS
OF THE BIRD WORLD
by John Westbury
THE CALIFORNIAN CONDOR
One lesson which natural history in¬
evitably teaches the ornithologist and
bird-lover is that it is never safe
to declare, without some qualifying state¬
ment, that a particular bird is extinct simply
because it has not been seen in its custom¬
ary habitat for from 50 to 100 years or so.
A case in point is the Californian Condor.
For nearly a century ornithologists had
considered this bird, one of the "giants"
of the air, to be extinct. The reasons
behind this supposition were sound enough.
The bird, a cliff-dwelling vulture known
also as the "Giant Condor", and found
mainly in California, had not been observ¬
ed (at least by knowledgeable people) since
the 1850's. Slow to reproduce, and un¬
adaptable by nature to man's encroachment
the condor (it seemed) had succombed
under conditions which had changed
amazingly all within the space of a century
or less.
Skeletal remains found near Los Angeles
strongly suggested that the Californian Con¬
dor had made his home in this part of the
world for something like 50,000 years.
Possessing great strength, a wing-span rang¬
ing from 9 to lie feet, and capable of
flying as high as 20,000 feet or more, the
condor seemed fitted by nature to per¬
petuate his species for all time, particularly
as his life span is in the region of a hundred
years. So it was with delight that a report
of "a huge, ungainly bird dwelling in the
Ventural county" was received by ornitho¬
logists a few years ago. An expeditionary
party of scientists and game wardens in¬
vestigated and discovered a number of the
birds living in the primitive wilds north of
Los Angeles. Over 25 were counted then,
but the latest count puts the survivors at
over 60, dwelling in a narrow isolated area
in the mountains, a region seldom visited
by man, which no doubt explains why they
had survived unseen.
Until recent years the American ivory-
billed woodpecker, second largest in the
world, had also been listed in the "believed
extinct" list. For centuries.it had its main
habitat in the ' Singer Tract country of
Louisiana, but lumbermen who laid waste
vast areas of the fine virgin forests here
also destroyed the homes of this attractive
bird. Then it was found in Florida. A
secret and guarded 1,000-acre reservation
was thereupon marked out to enable the
woodpecker to re-establish itself.
Speed saved the notornis
At the beginning of the present century,
New Zealand naturalists began to
believe that their notornis, a very rare
New Zealand bird, was on the verge of
extinction. With the passage of time this
belief was slowly turning into "certainty"
when, a few years ago, the notornis was
rediscovered in the Southland sanctuary. A
member of the "rail" family, this green and
purple plumaged bird is remarkable in that
it cannot fly, though it does possess rudi¬
mentary wings. Yet it is able to run at an
astonishing speed, a factor which no doubt
has contributed to its survival against its
many enemies sparrow hawks, stoats and
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
THE- DODO
THE IVORY-BILLED WOODPECKER
By permission of G. and C. Merriam Com¬
pany, publishers and copyright owners of
Webster's New International Dictionary. THE NOTORNIS
woodhens. It is hoped to breed the bird in
captivity to ensure its survival.
The saddleback, which resembles the
starling, is another bird which was thought
to be extinct in New Zealand. But a few
months ago an expedition led by Dr. R.A.
Falla, Director of the Dominion Museum
in Wellington, rediscovered the saddleback
on South Cape Island, a few miles southwest
of Stewart Island. It derives its odd name
from the chestnut saddle on its back, an¬
other oddity being the bright orange wattles
below its beak.
When it is clearly established that a cer¬
tain species of bird has not been seen over
a long period of time, it is natural enough
for ornithologists to conclude that it has
died out, and sadly to add its name to
those classical examples of extinct birds
the moa, the dodo, the great auk of the
arctic regions, and many others.
The moa, described as an "outsize
ostrich" in appearance was in fact a gene¬
ral name given to several species of flight¬
less birds which lived in New Zealand.
While the smallest species was about the
size of a turkey, the largest was around
12 feet high (i.e. more than twice as tall
as the average man), possessing a small
head, a long bare neck, short or reduced
wings and rounded, loosely-constructed
feathers. Though it could not fly, it could
run with remarkable speed.
Yet this inherent ability did not save
the moa, unless, of course, it still survives
in some remote and inaccessible swamp, a
possibility which few experts will even
consider. To account for its demise, vari¬
ous authorities have put forward theories
which are both plausible and interesting.
Some anthropologists, for instance, suggest
that it was Maori or earlier hunters who
wiped out the moa for they were very
fond of its flesh. An American expert,
studying the basic facts of their disap¬
pearance, has recently concluded that the
moas gradually dwindled in numbers be¬
cause they were unable to resist the tempta¬
tion to feed in dangerous forest swamps
that sucked them down to death. This
theory is supported by the discovery of
the skeletons of moas in the swamplands of
the Pyramid Valley in South Island. Others
say that various cataclysms of nature
earthquakes, floods, brush fires were
largely responsible.
No scientific doubt exists, however, re¬
garding the fate of the dodo, the pigeon¬
like bird found only on the Indian Ocean
island of Mauritius. The expression "as
dead as the dodo," summarizes its fate.
When early Portuguese navigators first
encountered the bird some centuries ago,
they found it was easy prey both for man
and dog, and so gave it the name of "dodo",
from the Portuguese word for simpleton.
For the dodo, three times as large as a
turkey, was so clumsily built that it could
not fly, run or even fight. Bulky, short of
leg, with a long beak and feeble wings, it
was no match for the island's settlers or
for the domestic animals that were intro¬
duced. By the end of the 17th century
the dodo was no more than a memory.
Feathers doomed the auk
Still another flightless bird which nature
seemingly forgot to provide with
adequate protection against its enemies
while on land is the great auk, found in the
northern hemisphere near Iceland, in
Greenland, northern Canada, and off
Newfoundland. Not unlike a penguin in
appearance, and about the size of a goose,
the great auk was killed off mainly for the
sake of its feathers, until it is now said to
be extinct.
A similar fate has befallen two much-
loved American birds, the beautiful passen¬
ger pigeon and the little Carolina parakeet.
The former, a long-failed swift-flying bird,
was once numbered in countless billions in
the mid-western States. Then came the
march of civilization, the destruction of its
meeting grounds and the mass capture of
the bird for food. In September 1914 the
last known passenger pigeon died of old
age in the Cincinnati zoo. Similarly, the
little Carolina parakeet was unable to
reproduce itself .quickly enough to counter¬
act its destruction by its enemies.
It is feared, too, that many other attrac¬
tive birds, among them the Labrador
duck, the heath hen, the Eskimo curlew
and the Laysan rail, are now extinct or
very close to it. Bird-lovers are, however,
hoping that the Eskimo curlew may still
survive on the Argentine pampas or in the
Arctic wilds, for it is a far-ranging migra¬
tory bird. But there is little hope for the
Laysan rail, a native of several Hawaiian
islets. When ornithologists found it the
bird was dying out on these islets through
lack of vegetation (this was being denuded
by rabbits); arrangements were made for
surviving birds to be taken to Midway
Island. Initially their numbers increased,
only to be swiftly decimated by the arri¬
val of. rats brought to the islands by ships
during the last war.
Yet, ornithologists point to the amazing
recoveries made by other birds they had
thought extinct, as a sound basis for hop¬
ing that some at least of these rare birds
may still survive. Before the war the trum¬
peter swan and the roseate spoonbill were
down to a few dozen survivors in their
respective habitats. Now they have been
found in much greater numbers, the form¬
er in the American West and Canada, the
latter in Texas and Florida.
There are others, of course, on the "dan¬
ger" list the cahow petrel still surviving,
if precariously, in Bermuda; the tall whoop¬
ing crane, an annual count of which at
its winter refuge in Texas reveals a steady
decline in numbers; the pure wild turkey
of the northeastern United States; the flam¬
ingo, scarcer than ever in the Bahamas;
and the tiny Bachman's warbler, only rare¬
ly seen these days in the swampy forests
of the southern United States.
While it is true that many species, extinct
or threatened with extinction, owe their
sad fate to man's tendency to kill them for
food, many owe their demise to á changing
civilization new methods of farming, the
destruction of virgin forests, wide-scale
building and all the other paraphernalia
which inevitably follow the changing pat¬
tern of man's progress.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
MONTH'
IN PARIS
Paris, meeting-ground par
excellence of culture and
the arts, was the setting last
November for a succession of
highly successful scientific and
artistic events organized by the
French National Commission for
Unesco on the occasion of
the inauguration of Unesco's
new headquarters and Unesco's
tenth General Conference. The
programme, entitled "Unesco
Month" covered a wide range of
subjects including concerts, plays,
exhibitions and documentary
films from many countries.
Probably the most important
event of Unesco Month was a
three-day International Round
Table in which eight world-
famous scientists, five of them
Nobel Prize Winners, debated the
subject "Man and Scientific and
Technical Progress". Held in the
great conference hall of the new
Unesco headquarters, the Round
Table drew some 2,000 people on
each of the three evening sessions
and was broadcast and televised
to several countries. The Round
Table will be given full coverage
next month.
Unesco Month gave special
prominence to Unesco's Major
Project on East-West mutual
appreciation. While an exhibition
of "The Art of Gandhara and
Central Asia" was organized at
the Musée Guimet with the
co-operation of museum curators
of Pakistan, Berlin and Rome,
another museum in Paris, the
Musée Cernuschi, presented an
exhibition on artistic exchanges
between East and West during
the past 5,000 years.
An important part of Unesco
Month were the Semaines musi¬
cales de Paris (Paris Musical
Weeks) during which concerts
and musical performances were
arranged to complement a series
of discussions by noted figures in
the world of music on the diver¬
sity of musical cultures and parti¬
cularly the mutual influences of
Orient and Occident on musical
Cont'd on page 28
unescc
MUSIC WEEKS. One of the highlights of France's "Unesco .Month" was the long-
awaited series of concerts of modern and classical composers organized in co¬
operation with the International Music Council and in which a galaxy of artists of
international fame had agreed to participate. Photo above shows Ravi Shankar,
one of Asia's most brilliant musicians who played on several occasions, notably in a
U.N.Day concert broadcast in a special hookup between New York, Paris and Geneva
and also featuring the two violin virtuosos David Oistrakh and Yehudi Menuhin.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
FROM STAGE
TO SCREEN
n conjunction with Unesco's
General Conference last Novem¬
ber, the French National Commis¬
sion for Unesco arranged an
impressive list of cultural events
In Paris. France's "Unesco
Month" as it was called, included
special theatrical performances,
concerts, documentary and other
film showings from different lands,
and various exhibitions dealing
with education, science and the
arts. In addition to the premiere
showing of the film "Le Bourgeois
Gentilhomme" (see page 2 and
photo left), the Comédie-Française
offered a gala performance of
Molière's "Fourberies de Scapin,"
while the Popular National Thea¬
tre presented Gérard Philipe
and Geneviève Page (far left) in
Musset's "Caprices de Marianne."
© Musée Guimet, Paris. From Peshawar Museum, Pakistan
HANDS OF A BUDDHA (above) was one of the many
works of art brought together from museums and other
collections in Pakistan, Berlin, Rome and Paris to show
how broad contacts between the ancient civilizations
produced original developments in art. This exhibition
"The Art of Gandhara andCentral Asia" illustrated Unes¬
co's Major Project for East-West mutual appreciation.
Hilding Ohlson, Gustavsberg
SCANDINAVIAN FORM. Scandinavia is recognized today as
one of the world leaders in interior decoration. The originality and
beauty of form and line of Scandinavia's furniture, ceramics, glass¬
ware and lamps was the subject of^an unusual "Unesco Month"
exhibition for which Denmark, Finland, Iceland, Norway and Sweden
sent some of the best of their contemporary handicrafts. Photo
shows examples of the modern lines of today's Swedish pottery.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
development. For the Musical
Weeks, Zurich, Rome, Prague,
Berlin, Brussels and Vienna sent
their most famous orchestras to
Paris, while from Asia came two
great virtuosos: Ravi Shankar of
India and Shinichi Yuise of lapan
who performed for the first time
together on a Paris stage in
a wildly acclaimed performance.
Of the Musical Weeks, Geor¬
ges Duhamel recently said: "It
is with real fervour and hope that
I note that Unesco has announced
the creation of the Paris Musical
Weeks ... If there is one art which
can teach people to know one
another better, to understand and
love their neighbours better, that
art is music . . . Music guides us
into the very souls of other men,
into the hearts of people of other
lands, whereas the ordinary
sources of information often tend
to distort or colour our judgments
of other peoples."
The fourth important event of
Unesco Month was the launching
of a series of International Days
for Documentary Films. Over
120 documentaries from 32 mem¬
ber states of Unesco were shown
to the public in Paris for the first
time. Divided into four chief,
categories (art films; scientific
and technical films; anthropolo¬
gical; and educational films) the
documentaries sought to promote
interest amongst people who are
not regular cinemagoers, and to
show the often unsuspected riches
contained in documentaries of
lesser-known countries.
Other items in the Unesco
Month programme included: an
unusual exhibition at the Institut
Pédagogique National of travel
diaries illustrated with sketches,
paintings and photographs show¬
ing how young French people
who have benefitted from French
travel fellowships see the world;
and an exhibition of 238 water
colours, pastels and gouache
paintings by the great masters
of French art since 1860 assembl¬
ed from various collections in
America and shown in France
for the first time.
Musée Cernuschi
'ORIENT-OCCIDENT, Encounters and Influences Over SO Centuries of Art," an exhibition
at the Musée Cernuschi ¡n Paris, gave striking testimony to the originality of Eastern and
Western cultures as well as to the interaction of their influences. The works displayed
ranged from examples of classical times, such as Greek divinities adopted and transformed by
the artists of Buddhist countries of East Asia down to modern ones showing how the exo-
tism of the East has been analysed by Western artists to serve as the basis for new departures
in the plastic or graphic arts. Whether dating from neolithic, classical, medieval or modern
times, the works assembled at the Musée Cernuschi showed many ways in which the
cultural sensibilities, of East and West have been brought closer together ¡n greater harmony.
Photo, courtesy French National Commission for Unesco
PIERRE AND MARIE CURIE whose discovery of radium towards the end of the 1 9th cen¬
tury did so much to revolutionize theories about the nature of matter and the universe were
honoured in an exhibition held at the Paris Palais de la Découverte. Organized by the French
and Polish National Commissions for Unesco (Marie Curie was born in Warsaw in 1867)
the exhibition told the story of the life and work of this husband-and-wife scientific team.
An identical version of the exhibition was also on view in Poland, The Paris exhibition
is to visit other countries. Photo shows Pierre and Marie Curie at their Paris home.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
An invisible sea around us
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
THE ENCIRCLING AIR
by Kenneth Johns
Over and around us flows an encompassing blanket of
an invisible atmospheric ocean shielding yet forever
moulding the crust of the Earth with its tenuous
fingers of gas and vapour.
This aerial shield, with its yearly tides and complex day-
to-day movements, is all that stands between us and an
environment as harsh as that at the Moon's surface. The
air acts as a vast energy-carrier and, with the aid of the
great heat reservoir of the oceans, moderates the world's
climates. Without this comforting atmospheric overcoat,
the temperature could drop to below the temperature of
liquid air at night and soar to a baking 110° during the
day.
Under these conditions, life would not only be nearly
impossible; it is scarcely conceivable that life as we know
it could ever have begun.
Yet the presence of air alone would not be enough to
make our planet hospitable to life; complex and wide¬
spread global airstreams are essential to distribute heat
and moisture fairly evenly over the surface. Without the
tremendous mass movements of air the Earth would be
divided into zones of extremes. The lands Would be
sterile, rocky continents, seared by unfiltered sunlight
during the day for there could be no clouds, no rain, no
rivers to soften the rugged structure of uplifted primeval
mountains; there would be no alluvial soil to fill the
valleys and no fertile plains to be clothed by the lushness
of plant life.
Only in a thin and precarious band around the coasts
would moisture diffuse in from the seas to combat the
stark glare of the sun. Sunburned deserts would extend
across continents, on both sides of the Equator, and
Tibetan-like tundras, frozen and bleak, would stretch
polewards. The frigid seas would push their iceberg
probes far nearer the Equator than they now do; the
Earth Would toe a parody of a green and pleasant land.
The circulation of the air prevents this cataclysm,
ameliorating conditions over the Earth's surface. At
any moment the energy of the air moving across our
planet is equivalent to the combined energy of seven
million atomic bombs. Yet over a tenth of this energy
is lost every day by friction between the winds and the
ground. Every upjutting blade of grass and tiny ripple
of water takes its toll; a toll that must be constantly
replenished from the sun's radiation.
Thousand miles an hour gales
Although there are two million tons of air free for
every man, wpman and child of the human race,
within a little over a week the great cities of Earth
would be suffocating under motionless clouds of smoke
and exhaust fumes, if the energy lost toy friction was
not forever toeing replaced..
In direct contrast to this choking quiescence, if the
friction between air and surface was eliminated, winds
would rise steadily in strength until rushing, thousand
miles an hour gales would be sweeping endlessly around
the Earth.
Only the edges of the tremendous air movements brush
the lands beneath, where, distorted by local geographical
features, they create the meteorological phenomena we
recognise as weather. Far above, weaving an intricate
three-dimensional pattern across the whole globe, whirl
invisible air-torrents and air-falls which in sheer mass
far outweigh any surface Niagara. Until quite recently,
very few people suspected the existence of such gigantic
upper highways.
Yet even the fantastic strength and speed of these jet
streams is only one facet of the complexity of the upper
air streams.
For two centuries scientific measurement of air condi¬
tions near the Earth's surface was used in attempts to
forecast the Weather, and there |was little or no improve¬
ment in the old cause-and-efïect prognostications handed
down in folk-lore from generation to generation.
Breeding ground of the weather
Then, one hundred years ago, scientists began to look
for reasons rather than surface observations in an
attempt to understand why the weather changed in
such apparently haphazard ways. This was the beginning
of true weather forecasting. By about the turn of the
century meteorologists had a fair insight into the inter¬
play of the tremendous surface forces that, within a few
hours, can change the calm of a hot summer's day into
a maelstrom of destructive gales. Still, even then, the
true breeding ground of the weather the upper air
was beyond the range of the simplest meteorological
instruments.
It was known that air pressure changes accompanied
the mass movement of air associated with storms and
that there was a rotation effect yet these inter-related
happenings seemed to follow no simple, easily defined
track. Sometimes they remained stationary for days
and even back-tracked on themselves. As each rotating
mass a cyclone or anticyclone may be a thousand or
more miles across, this meant that there was no way of
determining exactly where the moving storms would be
twenty-four hours ahead. Even today, this problem is
not completely solved and often causes forecasts to be
completely inaccurate as we know only too well in this
weather-riddled world.
At first sight, the rotating cyclones and anticyclones
tracking across both hemispheres might seem little more
than vague local disturbances when compared with the
great atmospheric rivers that must be called into being
to explain the enormous and never-ending heat transfer
from the tropics to higher latitudes. Between the Equator
and latitude 38, the Earth receives more heat from the
sun than it radiates and reflects back into space, whilst
between latitude 38 and the poles the total loss of heat
is greater than the radiation received.
Warm ocean currents carry some of the warmth pole¬
wards; but this can be accurately measured and is only
a small fraction of the total energy transferred. Now,
modern theory suggests that cyclones and anticyclones,
tiny when compared with the area of the Earth, are the
true controlling features of the atmospheric circulation,
guiding and acting as energy accumulators for the energy
of the prevailing Winds.
The major wind systems are impelled
into motion by the two overpowering forces
of the sun's heat and the earth's rotation.
Without the spin of the earth to funnel the
Cont'd
on
next page
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
THE ENCIRCLING AIR
(Continued)
winds into their prevailing belts there would toe a single
great wind system; hot air rising over the Equatorial
lands and spreading out high above the earth before
chilling and descending over the polar regions.
Even by the beginning of the 1930's, the real nature of
the wide-scale circulation of air around the earth was
still not known although, earlier, it had been suggested
that one of its basic features Was the large masses of cold
air that sweep down from the poles to bring sub-polar
conditions to more temperate climates.
The growing use of aeroplanes boosted meteorology not
only by the increased need for continent-wide hour-to-
hour forecasts along airline routes, but also as a means
of exploring physical changes in the upper air. It was
not long before planes were superseded by radio-sondes
balloon-borne miniature meteorological stations drifting
upwards and reporting back by radio on the temperature,
pressure and humidity of the surrounding air. Tracked,
at first visually and later by radar, their movements
measured wind speeds at different levels.
And then of course the trouble started. The so-called
"classic" theory atmospheric circulation gave a simple but
direct picture showing the air being heated near the
Equator, expanding and rising many miles into the air.
At the same time, dense cold air over the poles dropped
and flowed back over the surface the difference in
pressure maintaining a high, slow-moving blanket of air
from Equator to poles. Superimposed on this stately
turnover were the prevailing easterly and westerly winds
due to the spin of the earth.
Unfortunately, this decisive picture just did not coin¬
cide with the rapidly mounting collection of upper air
measurement.
The more data collected, the more of a muddle the
upper atmosphere seemed. In it was a chaotic turbu¬
lence of upstreams, downstreams, jet streams, west and
east streams all apparently going their own sweet Way.
When hot air falls & cold air rises
With the use of high altitude meteorological rockets
and increased interest in the no-man's-land
between the surface and space, the number of
measurements multiplied enormously; slowly, the grand
pattern of upper air streams began to emerge.
Instead of their being one huge air cell in each
hemisphere, there are three cells.
In the northern hemisphere the cold dry air drops from
stratospheric heights over the North pole and pours
southwards. Swirled towards the east by the spin of the
earth, this blanket extends four or five lobes of cold air
to reach down and intermittently sweep over North
America, Asia and Europe. As a mass of air stationary
with reference to the earth at the North ¡Pole is spinning
once every 24 hours in relation to the stars, its spin shows
up as it moves southwards, the further south the greater
the spin. Outbursts of cold polar air masses can pene¬
trate equatorward up to about latitude 30°. Polar air has
its own inner rotation, and if it intrudes far enough
toward the Equator it may break away to form a separate
MODEL. OF THE ATMOSPHERE. Within the last decade or so
observations, theoretical studies and laboratory experiments all seem
to bear out a new conception of our atmosphere as an air ocean set in
motion by the sun's heat and broken up by the earth's rotation into a
complex pattern of little whirls and big whirls. Though not accepted
30
by all meteorologists the theory has recently been demonstrated in
remarkable fashion by small mechanical models, one of which, cons¬
tructed by Dave Fultz of the University of Chicago, is shown below.
Fultz uses a rotating flat-bottomed pan containing about an inch of
water to represent the atmosphere of one hemisphere. A few drops i
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
revolving cold mass in the surrounding ocean of warmer
air.
In the same way, hot, moist air rises in the tropics and
falls earthwards near latitude 30. This too gives rise to
spinning masses of warm air and these may move north¬
wards into the cooler air, slowly losing their spin.
Both these systems of toubbles hot air in a greater mass
of cool air and cold air in Warm represent a transfer of
potential energy that is transformed into moving energy
as each rotating bubble gradually loses its identity.
The cold air masses are cyclones. The rotating hot air
masses are anti-cyclones. Each acts as a means of convert¬
ing heat into kinetic energy, the power behind the winds.
Where there is a high pressure area, as at the centre of
an anti-cyclone, there is in effect a hill of air pushing the
earth's atmosphere further out into space; a low pressure
area represents a trough. With their rotation, the effect
is of a series of airwaves sweeping around the earth carry¬
ing life-giving rain to the centres of continents.
Outbursts of cold and warm air assume wavelike confi¬
gurations in the middle latitudes. The position and
movement of these Waves may be forecast, giving an idea
of weather trends on a global scale. This method cannot,
however, be used for regional forecasts where so many
surface factors have to be taken into account. The
northern hemisphere's surface air circulation is entirely
different at sea level, the prevailing winds north of lati¬
tude 60 being easterlies diametrically opposite to condi¬
tions existing higher.
Between the polar and tropical air cells, between Cairo
and Paris, lies a region where the vertical air flow is
reversed; hot air falls and cold air rises.
This is not a flagrant reversal of the laws of gravity and
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
thermodynamics. Energy is supplied to this intermediate
air cell by the other two cells and by cyclones and anti¬
cyclones. And With immense energy, almost anything is
possible, including defiance of gravity.
Weather 'spies' in outer space
Whilst this picture is contrary to older ideas, its
essential correctness has been demonstrated by a
fair amount of experimental work. Dye dropped
into a slowly spinning pan of water warmed at the rim
gives a remarkable two-dimensional pattern closely
analogous to the pressure patterns in the earth's atmo¬
sphere. Agreeing both qualitatively and quantitatively
with the equations involving rate of spin and temperature
differences, the model even reproduces the eddies of air
near the base of the atmosphere and the fast moving jet
streams near the top. (See photos below.)
Our knowledge of the movements of the earth's
atmosphere will be enormously broadened when data
from the International Geophysical Year is analyzed and
We have a flow of information from artificial satellites
outside the earth's confusing covering of air to add to our
standard internal measurements.
Perhaps the meteorologists will then know more about
the effects of the millions of tons of carbon dioxide pour¬
ing into the air from chimneys, more of the long-term
weather effects of nuclear contamination, more about
the causes of the ice ages and the two-to-ten-year
drought extending over half the United States.
Perhaps they Will even be more sure
weather.
of tomorrow's
of dye render the patterns of flow in the water visible. The pan is heated
at the periphery (the "equator") and cooled in the centre (the "pole").
Slow rotation gives a simple pattern of circulation (two photos left),
with accelerated rotation it breaks up into a pattern of eddies
resembling cyclones and anti-cyclones of a weather map (two photos
Photos © Dave Fultz. Reproduced from Scientific American
right). From the periphery and the centre eddies move toward the
middle "latitudes" in the pan. "Westerly" currents appear in this
zone, and "easterlies" come into being near the edge (the "equator").
The model even reproduces, the vertical variations in our atmosphere:
at the bottom,' separate eddies; higher up, fast-moving airstreams.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
Ü\TeW SCHOOL OF THE AIR:
Australia is to have a new "'school of
the air" which will broadcast special
radio lessons to correspondence
pupils of the South Australian Edu¬
cation Department who live on
remote sheep and cattle stations
north of Port Augusta. The new
school will make use of the two-way
wireless equipment as in the case of
other Australian "schools of the air".
WINNING THE OPIUM BATTLE:
Successes are reported in the
battle being waged against opium
in Iran where the growing of the
poppy and the smoking of opium
were prohibited in 1955. A recent
report on the campaign by
Dr. William Ossenfort of the
World Health Organization shows
that the number of addicts being
treated daily in Teheran has
dropped from 800 to less than 30.
The effect of controlling the
smuggling of opium from neigh¬
bouring countries has been to
send the price of the drug to 40
times what it was before prohi¬
bition.
SiÍTATESMAN'S UNESCO POST:
Harold E. Stassen, who until recently
held the post of special assistant on
disarmament to the President of the
United States, has accepted a Unesco
appointment as special consultant to
the Turkisn Government to help
in the development of the Middle East
Technical University, opened last
year. Mr Stassen is first going to
Ankara where the Middle East Tech¬
nical University is located. Schools of
administration, architecture and engi¬
neering are already in operation
there. Mr Stassen will assist in the
development of other schools, includ¬
ing a school of agriculture, and
will co-ordinate the university's pro¬
gramme so as to fill the urgent need
for engineers, scientists and techni¬
cians.
LIFESTREAMS FOR A VALLEY:
Climatic conditions in the Ararat
Valley near the Turkish border of
the Soviet Republic of Armenia
make it possible to harvest two
and even three crops of certain
types annually. Due to lack of
water, however, nearly one third
of the land is not cultivated.
Recently large reserves of under¬
ground water and numerous
springs have been discovered in
the area and Soviet scientists are
planning a system of canals and
32
pumping stations which will help
to reduce water consumption from
nearby lake Sevan and turn
marshes into cultivable land.
J.OURISM THROUGH TV: Last
year televiewers across the U.S.A.
from San Francisco to Pittsburgh
made the acquaintance of peasants in
the Pyrenees, joined Parisians in
their everyday activities and visited
the World Fair in Brussels. This
"tourism through TV" was a project
carried out by three American TV
specialists who came to France and
filmed a series of feature programmes
and documentaries. The aim of the
programmes was to improve interna¬
tional understanding, and many of
them were designed specially for chil¬
dren because, as the producers put it,
"children are still free from prejudice
and pre-conceived ideas". The success
of the experiment has shown that it
could well be tried out in other coun¬
tries.
SAVED BY WEATHER SHIPS:
The lives of thirty-four people were
saved in 1957 by weather ships
stationed in the International
Civil Aviation Organization's North
Atlantic ocean network. The net¬
work consists of nine stations
manned by vessels which supply
weather reports for use in mete¬
orological forecasting, search and
rescue services, and navigational
aid to aircraft flying between
Europe and America. The ships'
search and rescue facilities, how¬
ever, are mostly used by surface
vessels: none of the 34 persons
rescued in 1957 were on board
scheduled civil aircraft.
UNESCO EMBARKS ON TWO-YEAR PROGRAMME
WITH LARGEST-EVER BUDGET OF S 26 MILLION
IN 1959 Unesco is beginning a two-year programme with the highest budgel
nearly $26 million in its 12-year history and a mandate from its 81
Member States to concentrate its resources on priority needs in education,
science and culture. The mandate was given and the budget and programme
approved at Unesco's Tenth General Conference during whose month-long
session from November 5 to December 5 the new Unesco Headquarters in
Paris was inaugurated and a new Director-General, Dr. Vittorino Veronese of
Italy was appointed to succeed Dr. Luther H. Evans of the United States. (See
November and December issues of The Unesco Courier).
Foremost among the examples of concentration in Unesco's Programme are
the three "major projects" first approved two years ago by the General Confe¬
rence in New Delhi. These projects aim at expanding primary education in
Latin America, bringing scientific research to the aid of the arid lands in the
dry belt running from North Africa through the Middle East to South Asia and
promoting mutual appreciation of the cultural values of Orient and Occident.
(See The Unesco Courier, December 1958). The Conference voted a total of
$2,310,000 for these three projects during the next two years.
Out of the total budget of $26 million the highest expenditure is for education:
$3,871,000 for the regular programme of the education department. When the
sums provided by the Technical Assistance Programme and those destined for
the primary education project in Latin America are added to this the total
reserved for educational projects in 1959/60 is more than $8 i million.
Some other highlights of Unesco's 1959-60 Programme are:
Awards of fellowships totalling $1,247,000 to artists, writers, musicians,
teachers of journalism, etc.
Aid to Member States in setting up a regional mathematics centre in Latin
America; the creation of libraries in Africa; aid to research in nuclear physics,
the marine sciences and electronic "brains"; assistance in the preservation of
works of art.
International conferences on primary education in Africa, adult education,
electronic computation (over 1,000 specialists are expected to attend a meeting
on the subject in Paris this year); the biological effects of ionizing radiations
and the professional training of journalists.
Technical assistance given by some 300 specialists working in more than 50
countries.
Aid to under-developed countries to develop their mass communication
services ($600,000 available).
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
F,
The Unesco Courier. January 1959
AO OFFICE FOR AFRICA: The
capital of Ghana, Accra, will be head¬
quarters of the new African regional
office of the U.N. Food and Agricul¬
ture Organization. Its creation was
decided by an FAO Conference in
1957. The next session of the Confe¬
rence will discuss the proposal to
create two regional sub-offices in the
north and south of the African
continent.
U RESEARCH GOES TO SCHOOL:
An effort to help bridge the ever-
widening gap between the worlds
of research and the schools is now
being made in Great Britain
through a new publication, "Educa¬
tional Research: A Review for
Teachers and all concerned with
Progress in Education". This publi¬
cation aims to provide comprehen¬
sive and authoritative statements
of the main facts and conclusions
derived from research and thus
provide teachers with the basis on
which to take practical decisions.
Articles in the first issue include:
"A New Look at Intelligence Test¬
ing", "The Wish to Learn-Research
into Motivation" and "The Relative
Effectiveness of Different Methods
of Teaching Reading". The review
prepared by the National Foun¬
dation for Educational Research in
England and Wales, can be obtain¬
ed from Newnes Educational Pub¬
lishing Company, Tower House,
Southampton St., London W. C. 2.,
price 5/6 per issue or annual
subscription (three issues) 16/6.
F(OOD FOR SPACE JOURNEYS:
Scientists of Leningrad University's
Botanical Institute state that micros¬
copic water plants, algae, are likely to
provide an ideal food for the future
traveller in outer space. Experiments
being conducted by the Institute show
that some forms of algae contain more
vitamins than lemons, and others can
produce more fats than many varie¬
ties of oil-bearing seeds.
TOP FISHING COUNTRY: Ja¬
pan not only continued to be the
world's foremost fishing country in
1957 but actually increased its lead.
In 1957, Japanese fishermen
brought home 5,399,000 metric tons
of fish or 18 per cent of the total
world catch. The U.S.A. was se¬
cond with a little over half Japan's
total. These figures are given by
FAO's "Yearbook of Fishery Statis¬
tics" which records that seven
countries Japan, U.S.A., China
(mainland) U.S.S.R., Norway, India
and the U.K. caught more than
one million tons of fish in 1957.
II ISTORY IN A SNOW PIT: By
digging a 50 feet deep pit in the snow
at the Amundsen-Scott South Pole
Station, members of a U.S. team
working there, were able to recons¬
truct a picture of past climatic condi¬
tions of the region. The snow they
TEN YEARS OF UNESCO COUPONS
Cutting red tape to promote
education, science & culture
Ten years ago last month, the purchase of a $2.50 book started what is
today a multi-million dollar international business controlled by 81 coun¬
tries. These countries are Member States of Unesco which in 1948
launched the Unesco Coupon Scheme to help cut the red tape of currency
exchange restrictions in certain fields of foreign trade.
At that time books and periodicals had to take their place in the long queue
of applications for a share of foreign currency available. In many countries
that total was and still is very limited and the needs of students, librarians
and scientists had to compete with other demands from foodstuffs to machinery
and raw materials.
A partial clearance of this discouraging complex of red tape and dead ends
was started in December 1948 when Unesco put into circulation special coupons
which institutions and individuals could buy in their own currencies and then
use to pay for foreign publications on educational, scientific and cultural
subjects.
Since then governments of 22 of Unesco's Member States have agreed to the
distribution of Unesco Coupons for which they pay the Organization in dollars,
French francs, pounds sterling or other monies which Unesco can use in carry¬
ing out its work. Designated distributing bodies then sell the coupons for local
currencies.
In 1950 Unesco Coupons became valid for the purchase of educational films
and scientific materials as well, and four years later the scheme was extended
to include educational and cultural travel. More than 4,000 suppliers in some
30 countries now accept Unesco Coupons. (Coupons can be used to subscribe
to The Unesco Courier). Up to September 1958 Unesco had issued $23,475,000
worth of Unesco Coupons.
Whether used for buying a pocket dictionary or a Geiger counter, a film
on mathematics or a foreign study tour, Unesco Coupons are giving practical
assistance to the development of education, science and culture around the
world.
excavated was melted for their water
supply. It was so hard that it had to
be chipped loose with axes and hauled
to the surface. By studying its stra¬
tification and examining snow crys¬
tals scientists Were able to learn
much about the history of the
Antarctic. Traces of ash, for ins¬
tance, may reveal that a volcanic
eruption took place at a certain peri¬
od and deposits of pollen may provide
a clue to past wind systems.
ASIAN STUDY KITS: As part
of a programme to encourage the
study of Asian countries in United
States schools, the Asia Society in
New York has assembled an expe¬
rimental packet of teaching mate¬
rials designed to supplement text¬
books and other sources. Each kit
includes 17 photographs of repre¬
sentative Hindu, Buddhist and
Mogul art and architecture, a se¬
ries of "people and places" pictures
with captions and pamphlets, refe¬
rence lists, maps and other audio¬
visual materials.
*¡§» UNRISE SEMESTER'S' BIG
SUCCESS: The early morning T.V.
course for university students called
"Sunrise Semester", started last year
by New York University, has broaden¬
ed the scope of its programmes for
the present school year. Last year it
began as a university course en
comparative literature and although
only 117 students registered for the
course at the University, some 120,000
viewers followed the programmes each
morning from 6.30 to 7.30. This year
four different courses will be offered,
and the possibility of an eventual full
four-year college programme on tele¬
vision is being studied.
UNESCO H.Q. ARTISTS WIN
MAJOR AWARDS: Three artists
whose works decorate the main
piazza of Unesco's Headquarters
Joan Miro, Alexander Calder and
Henry Moore are winners of the
three major international art
awards announced since the new
Unesco headquarters was complet¬
ed last year. In November Miro
was named the 1958 winner of the
Guggenheim International Art
Award for his two ceramic wall
designs which stand near Unesco's
Conference Building. Recently the
Carnegie Institute named Alexan¬
der Calder, whose giant mobile
stands at the entrance to the
Conference Building, as winner of
its first prize for sculpture and
Henry Moore, whose massive "Re¬
clining Figure" is placed before the
Unesco Secretariat Building, as
winner of the second prize for
sculpture.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
MAN'S DEBT TO THE WHEEL
Sir,
The wheel (wheel and axle) is one of
the six simple machines, the others
being the lever, pulley, inclined plane,
wedge and screw. Of these the wheel
has been said to be the most significant
invention of man. Certainly it is the
wheel that has played a disproportionate
part in the development of man as
compared with the others. Transportation
without the wheel is, to us, utterly in¬
conceivable. Without it we should still be
paddling down a stream, climbing a
mountain on foot, riding a horse to
distant points or crossing a desert on a
camel. With the vastly enlarged and
expanded means of transportation
afforded by the wheel came a pro¬
portionate increase in trade and
commerce... the contact of peoples one
with another and... the spread of
knowledge which lead to further deve¬
lopment of mechanical means. The
wheel has a very long history in its
own right... Would not The Unesco
Courier do well to devote an entire
issue to the subject?
H. T. McClure
New Albany, Ind., U.S.A
BIBLE TOPS TRANSLATIONS
Sir,
Readers of The Unesco Courier will
perhaps have been surprised to see, in
the issue of April 1958, that the Bible
so often claimed to be the book trans¬
lated into the greatest number of lan¬
guages only took sixth place in the
statistics of published translations, on
the basis of documentation supplied by
Index Translationum. Examination of
the sources of information on which
these statistics are based enables one to
see that simply to add up the transla¬
tions mentioned in the various national
lists can lead to an erroneous interpre¬
tation of the real situation.
Apart from four countries, the publi¬
cations of the Bible Societies have been
completely overlooked, even in countries
like Great Britain and the United States
of America, where Scriptures are
published each year in numerous lan¬
guages.
Moreover, in the case of any author,
each publication of any of his works in
translation, whether book or pamphlet,
counts as a unit in the lists of Index
Translationum. In the case of Lenin,
for example, who comes at the head of
the table brought to our attention for
1956, the figure of 331 does not mean
that the works of Lenin in whole or in
part were translated and published in
331 different languages during 1956, but
simply that in 1956 there were 331
editions of works of Lenin published
(whether whole books or pamphlets) as
either first editions or reprints, the
number of different languages in which
they appeared not being taken into
account. According to the same lists of
Index Translationum, the number of
languages in which translations of
works of Lenin were published that
year was only 14. In the same year
the whole Bible was published in about
60 languages and New Testaments or
portions of the Bible in a further 110
languages. We have therefore no reason
to doubt that this figure for the Bible
remains the highest ever attained by any
book, as far as the number of lan¬
guages in which a work has appeared
is concerned.
Olivier Béguin
General Secretary
United Bible Societies, London
UNBIASED & NON-POLITICAL
Sir,
In my opinion The Unesco Courier
is one of the greatest publications of
our age. It possesses three virtues that
I cannot find in any other magazine.
Its views and news are unbiased, it is
non-political and it refuses to grind the
axe of nationalism. If only the world
press would drag itself from the morass
of sensationalism, party politics and
vested interests, and present the news
to the world in Unesco fashion then
I feel that fear and war would vanish
practically overnight.
I was glad to see a copy of The
Unesco Courier in the Childrens'
Library of this town the other day.
Some adults will never accept the broad
principles of . friendship but at
least our children can help rectify our
mistakes by realising through your
magazine, that the chap in the next
country is not so bad after all.
R. Robertson
Launceston, Tasmania
'MAN AGAINST HIMSELF'
Sir,
Let me tell you that I tremendously
enjoyed (if enjoy is the word) your
"Man Against Nature" (January 1958)
issue. It is one of your best and most
important efforts.
If I may make a suggestion, as a
reader getting into his. fourth "Courier"
year, it is this: let us have another, as
vital and more pressingly urgent issue
"Man Against Himself." Let us start
it with a report on workings and find¬
ings of the permanent investigation
carried out on the Hiroshima survivors.
A recent reader's letter from California
suggested an issue on fallout, and my
suggestion is luckily! not original.
I keenly appreciate your dread of
anything that smacks of politics you
just have to avoid any slammed doors.
Still, a lot can be done to explain and
draw attention to the meaning of
modern war without getting into poli¬
tical hot water. "Man Against Him¬
self like "Man Against Nature", will
be fully in line with Unesco's 'E' for
Education. For further items on such
an issue, we could have: Summary of
WHO's report on dangers of radio
activity; other dangers to our environ¬
ment such as air pollution (Smoke-fog,
combustion-gases), water pollution,
noise. I am certain it would present no
difficulty to fill an issue.
Let me finally congratulate you on
the good work your monthly is doing.
I sometimes wonder if more publicity
could not be given to it; there still
remain many potential readers who
simply do not know what The Unesco
Courier is like. I will confess I used
to be disappointed by a certain naivete
in some of your earlier issues but of
late your grip has become quite sure,
so I certainly remain, your loyal reader.
W. J. Ehrenberg
Wettingen (AG), Switzerland
Ed. Note: An issue on this subject is
now being planned for 1959.
ENGLISH WITHOUT TEARS
Sir,
As a teacher I am very interested in
reading how many countries overcame
the problem of illiteracy. I have found
The Unesco Courier, to which I am
a subscriber, to be the best source of
such information. In the July 1958
issue, a letter asked for information
relating to certain youthful problems.
My colleagues and I are faced with a
similar problem.
Our pupils whose average age is 18
come here for a vocational training in
various trades for a period of ten
months. My colleagues and I, as
teachers of English, are concerned with
making them acquire a suitable working
knowledge of English. We take each
class for ten hours a week in winter
and for six hours a week in summer.
On entering the Centre the standard of
education of the majority of the pupils
is somewhat below the Primary School
standard.
We will be very grateful for and
receive with appreciation, information
about how other countries overcame
such problems, and suitable literature
and advice concerning an interesting
and effective way of teaching English
to our pupils.
Joseph L. Mallia
Government Industrial Training Centre
Marsa, Malta
HE SEEKS SUBSCRIBERS
Sir,
I have always been thinking of writ¬
ing you a letter, in order to thank you
and congratulate you on producing such
an educative and informative magazine.
And, as a token of gratitude, I have
been introducing your magazine to my
friends and to those with whom I make
new contacts, and, I am very happy to
say that, as such, I secure for you new
subscribers.
M. E. Kitabwalla
Mombasa, Kenya
5
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
BINDERS FOR YOUR
COLLECTION OF
Unesco Courier
We offer subscribers a special binder
for their copies of THE UNESCO
COURIER holding 12 issues of the
magazine. Handsomely produced in
halfcloth with the spine in an attractive
blue and the title (in English, French
or Spanish according to the edition to
which you subscribe) and Unesco co¬
lophon embossed in gold, these con¬
venient and attractive binders, costing
$2.50 ; 12/6 stg. ; or 600 Fr. frs, can be
ordered from UNESCO Agents, below.
WORLD
THEATRE
A QJJARTERLT REVIEW PUBLISHED BT VOLUME VII . No 3
THE INTERNATIONAL THEATRE INSTITUTE
WITH THE ASSISTANCE OF UNESCO
THE ONLY INTERNATIONAL THEATRE MAGAZINE
For authoritative and comprehensive comment on all important theatrical productions
throughout the world, from Tokyo to Broadway, from London's West End to Moscow
and from Paris to Belgrade, THE UNESCO COURIER recommends "World Theatre", a
quarterly bilingual (English and French) review published by the International Theatre
Institute (I.T.I.) with the assistance of UNESCO.
The only international theatre magazine, "World Theatre" has been published since I 950
and contains special articles on subjects of international importance and theatre news from
each of the thirty-six member countries of the I.T.I. Issues have been devoted to special
subjects such as Theatre Architecture, New Playwrights, Theatre and Youth, The Audience
and The Theatre of the Nations.
Attractively and copiously illustrated, "World Theatre" is published for the I.T.I, by Elsevier,
Royal Building, SS rue Royale, Brussels, Belgium. Annual subscription: S3. SO; 25/-(stg.);
1,050 Fr. frs. Available in local currencies through Unesco Sales Agents (below).
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C.I. Victoria. (A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 47, rue du Midi,
Brussels, CCP. 338.000. (fr.b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
22, Place De Brouckère, CCP 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151,
Antwerp.
BRAZIL. Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
Mexico 98-B, Caixa Postal 3291, Rio de
Janeiro.
BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon,
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
I 00 Parsons Road P.O. Box 244, Colombo
2. (Rs.9)
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa,
Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado I 13, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris, 7*. CCP. 12598-48.
(500 fr. ; 600 fr. from February I next).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road., Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Rajkamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2 Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv. (£.l./4..)
ITALY. Librería Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 950)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar u|-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (500 fr.).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff. Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. Ti-49, Apartado de Correos
201 8, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniania
Wydawnictw Naukowych PAN, Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgacan 2, Stockholm
16. (Sw.kr. 7.50)
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. (frs. S. 6.50)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E. 1. ( 1 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S3. 00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjïga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade,
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Photo (g) Paul Almasy
The dance plays a profound role in the life of the people of Africa. How profound and important this role is cannot
however be understood fully by isolating it from the everyday life of the people. Thus when a country's economy
is essentially agricultural and involves few needs and material worries why not move like a bird, crawl like a snake
or open like a flower to be in communion with Nature and the mysterious forces which people and animate it? This
is one of a number of questions raised by Keita Fodeba, creator of the African Ballet Company, in an article on the au¬
thenticity of the African dance appearing on page 18. Here French Sudanese villagers are dressed up for a bird-dance.
]]>
</page>
</document>
