<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="065221eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
** ,
' nTK- I
~^m
i
T0^^
m
i*.
;i*r:-sáSS** »
AK I N G
r the jpjvilege
few nations
:
: », >-
*
Vi
Tß*.
"¡P
».
' APRIL
19 5 9
(/2th year)
Price: 1/-stg. (U.K.)
30 cents (U . S.)
60 francs (France)
'^^ Hrafcí'^'-i^aví'&i
r.r , .
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A MODERN
GHWAY
BUILT BY
TEEN-AGERS
> «-I /
im m i
,. >T*W*» ." - áaBP1 1 P V ' ï -»
1l#pW'
Ad II '
VaPp4dMàTT% -* ' . » "J
PaTTaai ^WCl ».aifc- * j. *»"--"^, a> fl /
mw' F À -v . * ;
.* ^. . , a
?:: ^>'/v>*l
**J# 1 "-..-''* Ai
Young volunteers from Asia, Afri¬
ca, America, and Europe have
joined an army of young Yugo¬
slav volunteers to help build a
new international highway which,
will soon cut across Yugoslavia
from north-west to south-east.
Known as the " autoput ", the
motor highway will be completed
next year. Each morning the youth
volunteers, carrying picks and
shovels, set off in singing columns
from their camps bound for the
site of the new highway. Left,
smiling Swedish girl pushes wheel¬
barrow, while a schoolboy from
Zagreb (above) swings a pick on
a* stretch of the road being built
between Ljubljana, and Zagreb.
Last year 60,000 young people
worked on this stretch of road.
Photo» Yuiosl»v Youth Movement
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
Courier
APRIL 1959
I2TH YEAR
No. 4
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 IT'S NEVER TOO EARLY TO LEARN
"Housekeeping" and "baby care" for three-to-sixes
9 MIX-UP OF THE SEASONS
Today's warmer winters and colder summers
By Lucien Néret
10 FILM MAKING: NO LONGER THE PRIVILEGE
OF JUST A FEW NATIONS
By Georges Sadoul
20 YUGOSLAVIA'S «YOUTH ROAD'
Built by young volunteers from four continents
By Bertha Gaster
24 THE DRIVERLESS TRACTOR
Latest thing in mechanized farming
By E.W. Golding
26 KHUJIR: ISLAND CAPITAL ON WORLD'S
DEEPEST LAKE
By Evgueni Veltistov
28 FALLACIES ABOUT AUSTRALIA'S ABORIGINES
By Ronald M. Berndt
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7% France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7'
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (I 2 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.1 35 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do noc necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00; IO/-stg. ; <00Fr.fr». or equivalent.
COVER PHOTO
"Kanal", the story of an encircled
group of combattants who perish In
the sewers during the Warsaw uprising
In the last war won a Cannes jury
award In 1957. Cover shows Teresa
Berezowska who played her first role
in this film. Produced by Andrzej
Wajda, 32, "Kanal" is his second film.
Poland's quality feature film output is
an example of why cinema production
has ceased to be the privilege of just
a few nations. (See also page 16.)
Photo Film Polski
Unknown and unhonoured until recently, the Japanese
cinema industry today leads the world in the pro¬
duction of feature Alms. Before 1951 few were the
persons outside of Japan who had seen a Japanese motion
picture. But in that year, for the first time since 1940,
Japan showed some of its productions at an international
film festival held in Venice, and Rashomon walked off
the premier award an event as unexpected to most
Japanese as it was to many Western observers unacquaint¬
ed with the high standards achieved by the Japanese
film industry.
Since then Japan has won considerable international
acclaim and with 443 films released in 1957, it has become
the first country to jump ahead of the United States in
output. Here are the latest figures for 1957 of the "Top
Five Producers" just compiled by UNESCO:
1. Japan	 443
2. U.S.A 378
3. India 295
4. Hong Kong 217
5. France	 142
It is worth noting that of these "top five" producers,
three are Asian countries.
Although motion pictures are shown regularly for
entertainment in nearly every country of the world it is
only in very recent years that information has become
available on anything approaching a world-wide basis to
indicate the scale of film activity in different countries.
Even today such information is often scanty and
incomplete.
As a UNESCO study, Film and Cinema Statistics,
published a few years ago pointed out: "'When it is
considered that the number of commercial cinemas in
the world is greater than 100,000, that world cinema
attendance is in the order of 10,000 million per year, that
some 2,000 long films are produced every year, and that
the annual turnover of the world's film industry must
be close to 4,000 million dollars, it is surprising, to say
the least, that an activity involving such amounts of
capital, labour and leisure should be so unusually poorly
documented."
Since 1947 UNESCO has been collecting information on
the status of the film industries in different countries and
has issued various publications on this subject. It is with
this material at his disposal, along with data from
other sources, that M. Georges Sadoul, the great French
authority on the history of the cinema, has prepared the
survey published on page 10 which reveals the new and
often unsuspected horizons of the world cinema of today.
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
WE'LL BAKE A CAKE*, announces the teacher, "because Pierre and Robert are five years old today."
She writes the names of the ingredients and the quantities on the blackboard and explains what she has written, because the
children cannot yet read or write. Supervised by the teacher, Jean has lit the stove and now he stirs the mixture
in a saucepan over the gas. For the first time in France, children in a Paris nursery school are learning housekeeping.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
IT'S NEVER TOO EARLY
LEAR
All photos © Gisèle Freund
Three hundred French children, aged from three to
six, are having the time of their lives in a Paris school.
They don't know it, of course, but the eyes of many
educational authorities are watching them closely because
they are taking part in an experiment whose success may
bring a new note to. the whole problem of nursery school
education.
These youngsters are proving every day that "it's never
too early to learn."' In a spacious kitchen and an adjoin¬
ing bedroom they apply themselves earnestly to their
roles as cook or housewife, mother or father. They cook
simple dishes, wash clothes, do housework, make the beds¬
it is all a far cry from the "make believe" of games or
the symbolism, so often unsatisfying, of toys.
The children work in teams of twelve boys and girls.
For a week each team becomes a "family" and takes pos¬
session of the special experimental classroom "apartment"
in miniature. In the kitchen whose walls are painted a
daffodil-yellow, the gas stove is only 18 inches high and
the two sinks for washing have been constructed in such
a way as to render any accidents unlikely. In the second
big room stands a row of small beds where the "older"
children learn the proper way of getting the three-year-
old "babies" to bed.
In this way the children in this nursery school are not
only brought into direct contact with, and have the chance
to handle, real life objects chosen of course with a view
to the height and physical capabilities of the pupils but
the way is also open for them to accomplish all sorts of
home-making and family activities, thanks to their spon¬
taneous urge to imitate their elders and enter the world
of grown-ups.
This is the over-riding purpose of the experiment, and
the French Government is backing the project for a very
good reason: most of these children come from workers'
families in which they have to help mother from a very
early age.
Very few mothers, or, for that matter, even teachers,
realize the extent of the deep-seated changes that take
place in the child during his years in the nursery school
years when his progress
in growth, speech and
vocabulary and control
over his physical actions
is strikingly evident.
When a child enters a
nursery school the only
environment to which he
is accustomed is his home,
his family and friends.
Being plunged into an
entirely new situation
upsets and bewilders him.
If however, the difficul¬
ties of this period can be
smoothed out and the
anguish of separation
overcome, this will be the
starting point of his entry
into the world around
him. The new relation¬
ships he makes will help
him in this period, and
if he is given the right sort of understanding aid he
will begin to grow to adulthood in line with the society
in which he lives.
Thus, the kitchen and the bedroom in the nursery school
are "half-way houses" in which the child is not entirely
in a school atmosphere and where, though removed from
the house where he lives, he nevertheless finds himself in
a family environment which helps him to become one of
the group.
This family atmosphere created in school aims to pro¬
vide the children With an experience in which each new
event is a revelation or source of self-discovery. This is
not a form of "apprenticeship" and the children are not
necessarily expected to retain the things they have learn¬
ed; they may forget them temporarily, only !to reconsoli-
date this knowledge later in the normal course of their
development.
Instead, they have here an entry into the world of
adults, statisfying an urge to be "grown-up", a desire for
independence and a sense of accomplishment. Praised for
his achievements, a child will be helped along the road of
intellectual growth and towards the development of a
healthy personality. This is the atmosphere which the
nursery school kitchen and bedroom seek to create.
Children who have experienced this kind of education
show unbridled confidence and lose such traits as anxiety,
timidity and shyness, aggressiveness and deceitfulness.
Integration into constructive situations forming part of
group activities has led to many cures and a drop in the
incidence of unhealthy symptoms.
The teacher has a vital part to play in a class conceived
on these lines. She must be a highly qualified person,
fully aware of the educational results that are expected
of her and stimulated by the boundless possibilities of an
experiment which throws new light on to the desires, psy¬
chological problems and deep-seated attitudes of children.
What is needed is not a fully-qualified domestic science
teacher, but a good all-round nursery school educator.
The kitchen-classroom, considered as an essential cog in
the educational policy of integration now being developed,
is only one aspect of a form of educational initiation which
stimulates in the child the urge to enter fully into the
world of people and things.
Here is a direct preparation for life... Shall we soon be
seeing six-year-old girls giving advice to their mothers as
they market together? It would not be surprising, and
certainly nothing to complain about.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
arning the
grown-up' way
Each week a "family" of twelve little
boys and girls takes possession of
a special classroom "apartment" in
a Paris nursery school. Here some
things are made on a miniature scale,
but in detail and use correspond
exactly to the real thing. However,
the aim of this experimental pro¬
gramme is not to turn out young
housekeepers, and the children are
not expected to remember the things
they learn. Instead they find them¬
selves in an atmosphere and among
surroundings in which elements of
school and home are combined.
Here they can give full play to their
imitative desires and their urge to
join in the world of adult things.
Top left, Jean beats up the eggs
while René weighs the flour. Above,
the cakes are ready and Pierre tries
to blow out the five candles with
one puff. Right, five-year-old Chris¬
tine maternally cuts the cake for her
neighbour. Left, a carrots. and pota¬
toes cleaning session in progress.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The 'Big Ones' Learn Baby Care
n a large room whose walls are decorated with colourful
children's paintings stands a row of small beds where the
"older" children learn the proper way of getting a boisterous
three-year-old into bed. (Photos above and below.) Photo
left shows Giselle giving the "baby's" diapers a good washing.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. April 1959
IX-UP OF THE SEASONS: WARMER
INTERS AND COLDER SUMMERS
by Lucien Néret
Speaking before the American Chemical Society in
December 1957, the famous physicist Edward Teller
gave a solemn warning about the Increase in the
rate of carbon dioxide gas in the air. According to
Dr. Teller, the carbon dioxide content of the air has gone
up by 2% since the beginning of the Industrial Revolu¬
tion. He said that if the rate of increase reached 10%
the melting of Arctic ice would be speeded, causing the
level of the oceans to rise quite considerably.
The same view had been expressed some three months
earlier by delegates at the International Congress of
Geodesy and Geophysics, meeting in Toronto, Canada.
They stated that by the end of the century the level of
the oceans would have risen by nearly five feet, enough
to threaten many ports and seaside towns.
Adding to these observations, two well-known American
scientists, Professors Maurice Ewing and William L. Donn,
have stated that the gradual melting of the Polar ice¬
caps would lead to condensation of the water vapour which
in turn would produce continuous snow-storms. Such
phenomena, the two specialists believe, might well mark
the beginning of a new ice-age in a hundred years' time.
Both Western Europe and the Eastern part of the United
States would feel the effects of this cataclysm, and a
layer of ice more than a mile thick might form in some
parts of the world.
Such warnings, especially when they are voiced by such
well-known authorities, deserve to be taken seriously and
that is why special attention has been paid during the
International Geophysical Year to glaciological and
oceanographical research.
Over the last ten years specialists have noted a marked
change in meteorological phenomena. Generally speak¬
ing, the average temperature is rising both in the northern
and southern hemispheres a fact which fits in well with
the observed melting of the Polar ice-caps.
But while the winters are getting warmer, the summers
are now cooler. One result is that some of the fast-
flowing glaciers are extending their surface; but there
are other consequences. In England, cricket clubs
complain that their season grows shorter every year;
fisheries experts have noted that the shoals of cod are
tending to move northwards; and in the last few years
the Great Salt Lake in Utah has dried up by half.
H-bomb tests not to blame
Ever since the present series of bad summers began,
public opinion has put the blame on nuclear and
thermonuclear explosions. Most meteorologists,
however, state that, this accusation is completely ground¬
less. They stress that it would take tremendous energy,
exceeding anything man is capable of producing, to exert
an influence on the air circulation and the formation of
anti-cyclones which lead to widespread weather distur¬
bances.
Even a small local thunderstorm would require almost
as much energy as that liberated by about fifteen
hydrogen bombs. Scientists state that the average storm
at sea is equal to the energy of hundreds or thousands
of atomic explosions. To create a full-scale storm artifi¬
cially you would have to let off atomic bombs almost
every second!
Such is the opinion of most meteorologists. There are
exceptions, however, and among them authorities such as
Dr. Horace R. Byers, head of the Meteorological Depart¬
ment of the University of Chicago, and Professor William
H. Parker of the University of Manitoba.
Dr. Byers maintains that each atomic explosion in¬
creases the ionization of the atmosphere and compromises
the electrical balance between the atmosphere's positive
charge and the earth's negative charge,
As for Professor Parker, he has noted "an abnormal
sensitization of the ionosphere." Recalling that the
eruption of the Krakatoa volcano in 1883 was followed by
several disastrous summers, he asks: "Why should not
artificially-produced atmospheric disturbances have
similar effects?"
During the fifth meeting of the special committee for
the International Geophysical Year in Moscow last
summer, I asked several meteorologists for their views on
these theories. All of them expressed a negative opinion.
Weather 'eyes' in the stratosphere
On the other hand, both Russian and American
scientists stressed that the data transmitted by the
artificial satellites has revealed a considerable den¬
sity of meteoritic dust in the vicinity of our planet. They
believe that this dust may play the role of ice-forming
nuclei promoting the condensation of water droplets and
thereby producing the abnormal rainfall which has been
noted recently in various parts of the world.
Observations carried out during the I.G.Y. also seem
to prove a relationship between the appearance of
sunspots and solar protuberances and variations in the
climate. During periods of intense solar activity, special-
its have noted an increased circulation of the air and
temperature variations. It is cooler in the tropics and
warmer in the polar regions. A mass of data on these
phenomena has been collected all over the world during
the I.G.Y.
Once it is sifted we shall know a lot more about the
influence that solar activity exerts on the earth's
atmosphere.
Already artificial satellites have proved to be excellent
instruments of observation, and scientists are now
contemplating sending aloft satellites equipped like real
meteorological stations. Launched in an orbit 3,700 miles
above the Earth, such stations would take about four
hours to travel from one Pole to the other. They would
provide scientists with invaluable information on the
evolution of hurricanes and the formation of cloud
masses.
At this stage, man will have advanced a long way
towards his dream of mastering the climate. Weather-
making has become a necessity of modern living. As the
world population grows and men strive to produce more
and more food, it is important that agriculture should not
be dependent on the whims of the weather.
Up to now man's "weather-making" activities have been
on a very minor scale, such as inducing hail or thun¬
derstorms over a limited area. Now two scientists
Harry Wechsler, in the United States, and Grigory
Avsiuk, in the Soviet Union speak of nothing less than
changing the climate in the Arctic by melting the floating
ice which has formed there over thousands of years.
Technically, the plan could be successful. Its direct
consequence Would be to make the climate warmer and
more humid over an area covering more than 7,500,000
square miles. Since only the ice floating on the sea is
involved, there would be no danger of flooding such as
that mentioned at the beginning of this article. Vegeta¬
tion would appear again in the coldest parts of Siberia
and Alaska, though glaciers might form in the
mountainous areas.
All this, however, is still only a dream.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
FILM MAKING
No longer the privilege
of just a few nations
by Georges Sadoul
U'NTiL about ten or fifteen years ago it
looked as if film making was the privi¬
lege of five or six big nations. Since
then it has been gradually recognized
that, in fact film production has become
*a^ world-wide medium of culture and a fast-expanding
industry in more than fifty countries.
Though more and more films from Asia, the Arab
countries and Latin America began to be shown at
important international festivals such as those of Venice
and Cannes, Karlovy Vary (Czechoslovakia), Sao Paulo
and Berlin, audiences continued for a long time to be
limited and either critical or unimpressed. Between 1947
and 1951 Unesco published reports on the film industry
running to several thousand pages, but relatively few
people explored this mine of information closely enough
to be struck by the growing universality of film produc¬
tion.
After 1950, however, awards made at the festivals of
Venice, Cannes, Karlovy Vary, and Berlin, turned the
spotlight on the Japanese film industry which, since 1925,
has produced more feature films than Hollywood, and on
the Indian cinema with its productions in 14 languages.
And while the West was at last discovering the longest-
Georges Sadoul is a leading authority on the history of the cinema.
Professor at the Institute for Advanced Studies on the Cinema in
Paris and Lecturer at the Institute of Filmology at the Sorbonne,
he is the author of a General History of the Cinema (jive volumes
published) on which he has been working for the past 20 years.
Over 100,000 copies of this work have been printed in eight lan¬
guages. A fifth edition, completely revised and covering the evo¬
lution of the cinema in over 70 countries, is now. in press.
Mr. Sadoul is also the author of a Life of Charles Chaplin and
of The Wonders of the Cinema.
10
established of the Eastern film industries, new national
schools were coming into being. Films of strong emo¬
tional appeal such as The Maimed (Si Pitiang, 1952) by
the Indonesian producer Kotot Sukardi, or those of poetic
beauty like Path of Destiny (Rekava, 1947) by the
Ceylonese producer, Leister Peires, showed that certain
countries had acquired the art of film making almost
simultaneously with their indépendance.
To take in the full panorama of the cinema in the
world today we need to look beyond Europe and North
America to the countries of Asia, the Arab world, Latin
America and the continent of Africa.
Yet how well known is Europe's own film production?
There is much more to it than the works of the main
film producing countries Great Britain, Italy, Germany
the U.S.S.R., France and two of the Scandinavian
countries, Denmark and Sweden, which were already
producing remarkable films between 1910 and 1920.
Just after the Second World War came the revelation
of Central Europe's great progress in the art of film
production. What did we know of Hungarian films before
It Happened in Europe (Radvanyi, 1947) and Talpalatnyi
Fold (Frygies Ban, 1948)? about Polish films before Last
Stage (Wanda Jakubowska, 1948) and Border Street
(Alexander Ford, 1948)? or about Swiss films, until
Lindtberg's Last Chance (1945) made such an overwhelm¬
ing impression with its message of human solidarity?
Yet these films were not the Works of suddenly inspir¬
ed producers. They were the end result of some twenty
to thirty years' research, patient experiment and tentative
groping, and of fruitful international contacts which
helped to set the art of film making on its feet in
countries where the national film industry lacked
independence or the means to develop.
Since 1950, Spain has given us the films of Bardem and
CONTINUED PAGE 12
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier.
Nordisk Tonefilm
SWEDEN is by no means a newcomer to the film Industry. As early as I 9 I 5 and for some ten years
after then, the work of Swedish producers and actors carried this country's productions to the supreme
heights of film art. Following a period of eclipse, the Swedish cinema is today again in the forefront of
world film making. Above, Ingrid Thulin in a scene from "Brink of Life", the work of Ingmar Bergman.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
FILM MAKING (Continued)
Berlengua (Welcome Mr. Marshall, Death of a Cyclist,
Calabuig); Greece, those of Cacoyannis (Stella) and
Kondouros (The Ogre of Athens) ; Yugoslavia, productions
by Pogacic and Striglic; and Bulgaria, the work of Z. Jan-
dov.
How many people know that Finland, with a population
of barely four millions, and having a language that is
practically unknown outside its frontiers, manages to
produce from 25 to 30 feature films a year? Many of these
films, as for example The White Reindeer (Erik Blomberg,
1952) and The Unknown Soldier (Edwin Laine, 1955) set
very high standards. Though the artistic merits of the
Turkish cinema are an unknown quantity, the fact that
in some years the studios at Istambul produce fifty films
or more is not without significance, since quantity is
sometimes the forerunner of quality.
In art there, is never a status quo for very long. A
brilliant school can disappear overnight and just as
easily come to life again.
Between 1915 and 1925 Sweden reached the supreme
heights of film art through the work of producers like
Stiller and Sjöström and actors and actresses like Lars
Hansom and Greta Garbo, and then seemed to flounder
in the doldrums of commercialism. But in 1940, came
a revival and today Sweden is once again in the fore¬
front of world film making, not only thanks to Ingmar
Bergman, but to other equally talented producers, Sjösberg
and Sücksdorf in particular.
Storm over Asian filmdom
If the art of making films can flourish in a country of
seven million inhabitants it can hardly fail to take
root in the ancient civilizations whose populations run
into hundreds of millions. An early masterpiece by the
great Russian producer Pudovkin was given the title
Storm Over Asia. Nowadays Asian countries are sending
their films to the rest of the world, with their own storms,
Idylls and discoveries, their own epics and elegies.
First of the Asian film mäkers was Japan which began
back in 1910 and which was soon followed by China,
Korea and India. Few people know that in 1927 more
feature films (90) Were produced in Shanghai than in
France. Production standards soon reached high levels.
In the film library of Peking, I was able to see several
Chinese films made in the thirties, including The Lost
Horses by Tsai Tsou-sen and The Angels of Mercy by
Yuang Mu tse, which |were every bit as good as the best
Occidental films of that period and which already had
a "neo-realist" flavour.
In China today a score of new film studios are being
built in as many provinces. Though the number of
cinema tickets sold in 1958 2,600,000,000 represents an
average of only four per person, it is still 30 or 40
times higher than' the average for 1945; and the local
number of tickets sold makes China the second or third
cinema-going country in the world, after the United
States of America and the USSR.
As for Japan, both the production figures 1,000 full-
length films in 1928, 443 in 1957, and probably about 520
in 1958 and the audience figures (one thousand million
cinema-goers, an average of twelve cinema tickets per
year per inhabitant) are high; so is the quality. Since
1921, Kinugasa, Nizogushi, Heinosuke Gosho and H.
Shimizu have joined the ranks of the leading film pro¬
ducers of the world. Even today one cannot help being
impressed by the technical perfection, bold approach and
poetic qualities of Jujiro (Kinugasa, 1928), one of the
few Japanese silent films ever to be seen in Europe. This
film is the equal of the finest American, German, French
and Soviet productions of the days of the silent screen.
Since 1950, owing to the well-deserved success of The
Gates of hell (Kinugasa), Rashomon (Kurosawa) and Life
of Oharu, The Gallant Lady (Mizogushi), many people
have gained the impression that most Japanese films,
and certainly the best ones, deal with the Samurai period.
In actual fact, though they are not as well-known in
the West, the majority of Japanese films, including the
best and the most audacious, deal with contemporary the¬
mes. One could almost say jokingly that neo-realism was
born, not in Rome in about 1944, but in Tokyo in 1927,
BRAZILIAN FILMS were on a par with the best European ,
ductions between 1 927 and 1 932. The same qualities they t
showed became evident again in 1950 when Lima Barreto's
striking film "O Cangeceiro" (above) attracted world-interest.
HUNGARY is a leader in Central Europe's post-war production.
"It Happened in Europe" (Radvanyi 1947) came as a revelation
to audiences in many countries, and was followed by other films
like "Professor Hannibal" (above) made by Zoltan Fabu in 1957.
12 CONTINUED PAGE 14
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
lumbia Picture«
FINLAND with a population of four and a half million people
produces something like 30 feature films annually, many high
standard productions such as "Unknown Soldier" (above)
made by Edwin Laine, which won a grand award at Berlin.
Falco Films En
Irawn attention to its film industry since 1950 with
the productions of men like Bardem, Berlengua and Ladislas
Vajda. This children's game of bull-fighting is taken from Vajda's
"My Uncle Jacinto". In 1 957 Spain produced 63 feature films.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
FILM MAKING (Cont'd)
I
JAPAN'S FILM INDUSTRY, unknown and unhonoured abroad until recently, is the world's
leading producer of feature films (500 in I 958). Those on modern themes, like "Crab Fisher¬
man" (above) are even less known in the West than films on the Samurai period.
IN CONTINENTAL CHINA many new film studios
are now being built and cinema-going has shown a
massive increasein .1956 the number of tickets
with the Pro Kino movement, and that, after 1951, neo-
realism has burned with a brighter flame in the Japanese
archipelago than in the Italian peninsula, thanks to
Tadashl Imal (We Are Alive), S. Yamamoto (The Sunless
Square), Kaneto Shindo (The Children of Hiroshima)
Yamamura (Kanikosen) , Naruse (OJcasan) and H. Gosho
(The Four Chimneys). We must remember too that Akiro
Kurosawa, one of the most outstanding of today's film
producers, made not only Rashomon and the Seven Samu¬
rai but also To live and Doomed, in which he treats the
problems of present-day Japan with a depth and under¬
standing worthy of a great novelist or painter.
Every year two hundred films are made in Hong-Kong,
about one hundred in the Philippines, and some sixty in
North Korea. Though neither they nor the fresh, lively
films of the young Indonesian cinema (seventy-five films
in 1956) are scarcely known outside South-East Asia, we
are at least beginning to see something of the films made
in India.
Hindi, Bengali, Tamil, Telugu, Mahrati/ Gujrati, Mala-
yalam, Kanarese... India's films are made in fourteen lan¬
guages. There are three main centres of production. The
newest is inthe South. The one in the West (centred on
Bombay) is the oldest; and it is here that the father of
the Indian cinema Phalké, made his first films back in
1913. The Bombay studios' production includes many high
budget films, the demand for which is now gradually
growing in the Orient and also as far away as Morocco.
On the east coast, Calcutta studios have been a centre
of sparkling, brilliant productions for the past twenty
years. Here, in the country of Rabindranath Tagore,
important films, inspired by masterpieces of contemporary
Bengali literature, have been produced by the New
Theatre led by Devaki Bose and Barua. Their merit was
recognized by a Venice Festival jury as early as 1935.
Nor has the standard of this output dropped since then;
on the contrary it has risen. Two of the greatest of the
modern Indian producers are, in fact, from Bengal: Bimal
Roy (Two acres of land) who started with the New Thea¬
tre movement; and Sajatajit Ray (Father Panchali and
The Unconquered) who won a prize at Venice.
Sajatajit Ray learned a great deal from watching Claude
and Jean Renoir making The River in India; and Phalké,
before making his first Indian film, spent some time train¬
ing with the French firm of Pathé at Vincennes. Inter¬
national exchanges yield valuable fruits, and "old" film
industries can help new ones to find their feet; though
there is no doubt that India, with her wealth of talent,
would inevitably have succeeded in building up an out¬
standing film industry on her own, without knowing
anything about the art of film making in the West.
New cinema industries are springing up in other parts
of Asia as well. The cinema industry in the Union of
Soviet Socialist Republics is multi-national, and all the
main Republics have their own studios at Baku, Tbilisi,
(Georgia), Erivan (Armenia), Stalinabad (Tadjikistan),
Tashkent (Uzbekistan), Alma-Ata (Kazakhstan) among
others all producing films in the languages of their
countries. The film production of the Asiatic Republics
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
»NC^
sold was between ten and twenty times more than
the average for 1 945. Scene above is from the Chinese
film "The White-haired Girl" made nine years ago.
Georges Sadoul Collection
INDONESIAN FILMS typify the work of the young cinema industries which have been
springing up across Asia in recent years, but whose fresh and spirited productions are
hardly known at all outside that part of thé world. "The Return" (above) was made in 1954.
of the U.S.S.R. has been expanding rapidly in recent years
(10 to 20 films per year).
Over a period of eight years (1950-1958) Iran made
ninety films, or five to six times more fhan its entire pro¬
duction during the previous fifty years. There is a curious
reason for this boom. After 1945, two foreign films were
dubbed in Persian a French one First Rendez-vous, with
Danielle Darrieux, and an Azerbaijan comic opera film,
Arshin mal alan, made in Baku. The cinemas showing
First Rendez-vous and Arshin mal alan, between 1946 and
1948, were besieged, simply because these films were
dubbed in a language people understood. Since Persian-
speaking films were obviously a good business proposition,
the production of commercial films began to increase.
This in turn enabled studios to be built, and before long,
as audiences became more demanding, the standard of the
films improved. Among the best of these since 1957 are
The Knightly Vagrant by Mahed Mohseni. The Happy
Urchin by Rafi and, above all, South of the Town by Gaf-
fary. These films bear the imprint of certain French and
Italian techniques... "neo-realism" may soon be making its
appearance in Iran.
The vast film world of Latin America, which begins not
at the Panama Canal but at the Rio Grande, is
practically unknown.
The Mexican film industry, the best 'known and rightly
so, produces an average of one hundred films a year.
These are screened throughout the Spanish-speaking
world and actually have a wider diffusion than Hollywood
productions. Since Portrait of Mary, The Pearl and
Lovesick, producer Emilio Fernandez and cameraman
Gabriel Figueroa, have become world famous, though
there are many other famous names in the Mexican school,
including Galindo, Bracho, Gavaldon, the great Luis
Bunuel, Carlos Velo, and Benito Alazraki.
It is worth remembering that Emilio Fernandez likes to
call himself "El Indio"the Indian. A large part of the
Mexican cinema, including Portrait of Mary and Alaz-
raki's Roots, is permeated with the ancient culture of the
pre-Columbian era. If Eisenstein with Que viva Mexico
(1930) and Paul Strand and Zinnermann with The Wave
and The Alvarado Rebels (1936) gave much to the Mexican
cinema, it was because they, in turn found great riches
in Mexico, with its Indians, its peons, its historic battles,
its ancient monuments and modern murals, and the
wealth of its folklore and traditions.
Between 1927 and 1932 the technique and bold approach
of Brazilian films made them a match for the best Euro¬
pean productions, thanks mainly to Umberto Mauro and
Mario Peixoto. After this the Brazilian film industry
appeared to do little more than produce commercial films
designed to popularize the songs and dances of the Brazil¬
ian Carnival. Then about 1950 it revived again partly
due to the fact that the famous Alberto Cavalcanti went
back, to work in his country for a time.
The success of Lima Baretto's magnificent O Cangaceiro
has since drawn the world's attention again to the exis¬
tence of the Brazilian cinema industry although this was
only one among many other good films it had produced.
CONTINUED PAGE 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
POLAND'S FILM INDUS¬
TRY was little known before
1948 when two Important
films, "Last Stage" and "Bor¬
der Street" were produced.
Yet each year Poland releases
eighteen to twenty films, many
of which like "The Five Boys
of Barska Street" (above) de¬
serve to be better known.
Photo Film Polski
THE TUNISIAN CINEMA
made a promising start in the
field of production with
"Goha" (above) on which
Tunisian film-makers collabo¬
rated closely with the French
producer, Jacques Baratier.
Georges Sadoul Collection
EGYPT Is the major film-
producing country of the Afri¬
can Continent and its films are
shown throughout the vast
Moslem world, from Dakar to
Jakarta. Scene above is from
"The Leech" by Abou Seif.
Georges Sadoul Collection
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
FILM MAKING (Continued)
Georges Sadoul Collection
NEGRO AFRICA remains a "white blank" on the map of
world film production. The short-length film "Mouramanl"
(above) is one of the few films entirely produced by Africans.
No major film has yet been made by Negroes in Africa.
Ceylonese Legation, Paris
CEYLON is one of the countries which entered the ranks
of the world's film makers almost simultaneously with their
accession to Independence. Above is a scene from "Path of
Destiny" made In 1947 and produced by Leister Pelres.
In Argentina, the cinema has already celebrated the fif¬
tieth anniversary of its first productions. During the
1930's, Argentinian films held first place on the markets
of the Spanish-speaking peoples, and though Argentina
has now been supplanted by Mexico, Buenos Aires still
continues to turn out between thirty and forty full-length
films a year. The work of Sazlavsky, Lucas Demare, Hugo
Del Carril and Torre Nilson amongst others, is well up to
international standard.
The production of films in Chile and Venezuela has been
uneven; but The Forgotten Creek, produced by Bruno Ge-
bel near Santiago, and The Sloop Isabel, made by Hugo
Christensen near Caracas, have won favourable comment
at international festivals. Cuba has been producing full-
length films since 1910; and before long Colombia, Pana¬
ma, Bolivia, Uruguay and even Puerto Ricowhere the
film industry has been developing spasmodicallymay
come into the field.
The vast, rapidly developing territory of Latin America
with its teeming millions, will, no doubt add new eye
openers to the film world before the century is out. So
may Australia, which has been producing films for fifty
years; or New Zealand, which, since 1950, already has
several full-length films to its credit.
In the continent of Africa, the only major film-
producing country is Egypt, whose films are shown
throughout the vast Moslem world wherever the language
of the Koran is understood and modern Arabic is used by
press and radio. Thus Egypt's films reach audiences in
two continents, from Dakar to Jakarta, from the Congo to
China. And there are also cinemas showing Arabic-
speaking films in several French towns, in North and
South America and in Africa South of the Sahara.
The Moslem Hollywood
The emergence of Cairo as the Hollywood of the Moslem
world coincided with the second "World War; and
wireless and gramophone records playing in cafés and
squares helped to increase the distribution of Arabic-
speaking films, in which singing and dancing play an
important part. Even fifteen years ago there were towns
in the Middle East where people paid twice as much to
see an Arabic film as to see an American or European one.
Perhaps not all the hundreds of films made in Cairo since
1940 are of a high standard, but no list of the world's best
film producers would be complete without the names of
the late Kamal Selim, Salah Abu Seif and Youssef
Chahine.
Between 1945 and 1950, a few Moroccan films were made
at Rabat; and the Tunisian cinema made a promising
start with Goha on which Tunisians collaborated with a
Frenchman, Jacques Baratier.
Africa South of the Sahara however remains a blank
on the map of film production. Sixty years after the
invention of the cinema, no major film, as far as I know,
had yet been produced, photographed, written and scripted
in their language by African Negroes. Their participation,
in general, has been limited to acting. In other words,
there are 200 million coloured people who have still not
been able to make full use of the cinema to express
themselves; and since statistics show that there are still
regions where, on an average, an African buys a cinema
;ticket only once or twice in twenty years (1), the cultural
influence of the cinema here is limited.
Figures for cinema attendance usually coincide with
illiteracy areasand "hunger areas". Since the end of
the Second World War, however, the geography of the
cinema and the film industry has been changing radically
from year to year. Film making will soon cease to be one
of the most unevenly distributed things in the world. For
fifty countries today perhaps a hundred tomorrow the
cinema represents an important cultural medium and a
rich vehicle of expression.
(1) See Unesco's "Film and Cinema Statistics" (Report N° 1);
"World Communications" (1956); and "Facts and Figures" (1957).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
FILM MAKING (Confd) The Unesco Courier. April 1959
George«
INDIA: THIRD LARGEST
FILM PRODUCER
IRAN has produced fwe or six times more films (90) in the
past eight years than in the previous 50. Some of them
like "South of the To Jl n" (I) produced last year by Gaffary
recall the neo-realisrh of French and Italian productions
TURKEY has an active film industry and its studios In Istan
bul sometimes reach an annual production of more thai
fifty films. "The Empty Cradle" (2) is the work of the Tur
kish producer Baha Gelenbevi. MEXICO'S studios turi
out an average of 100 films each year and these are mor«
widely diffused in theSpanish-speaking world than Hollywood
productions. "The Countrywoman" (3) was made by s
famous team, producer Emilio Fernandez and cameraman
Gabriel Figueroa. INDIA occupies third place in the list
of the world's feature film producers in 1957 with 295 films,
compared with 443 for japan and 378 for the U.S.A. Hong
Kong (217 films) and France (142) came next. India's
multilingual situation is reflected in its films made in 14 lan¬
guages. Scene shown in photo 4 is from "Moral Heritage".
George« Sadoul Collection Basant Film Distributor«, Bomba
18 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
In Yugoslavia
TEEN-AGERS FROM FOUR CONTINENTS
BUILD A MODERN HIGHWAY
Yugoslav Youth Movement photos
GREETING THE NEW ARRIVALS. Between ten and thirteen thousand young people worked each
month from March to November last year on the construction of the 87-miles long Ljubljana-Zagreb sec¬
tion of Yugoslavia's international cross-country highway. During the holiday months their numbers rose
to the peak figure of 18,000 and by the time this section of the highway was completed, some 60,000 volun¬
teers had done their share (out of some 200,000 who made application to participate). Here, at the
Kovenitka Camp, near Ljubljana, "veterans" of the volunteer brigades welcome a group of newcomers.
by Bertha Gaster
There have been hundreds of ways of making roads
in the pastvslave labour, serf and feudal labour,
communal levies, convict labour. But nowadays
the most common way is to do it on strictly commercial
lines. The authorities hire surveyors and engineers,
construction and road gangs, and in due course the road
is made, costing a certain sum. It is a plain, straight¬
forward business affair, and the profit and loss accounts*
are there in two parallel columns for all to see.
But there is also another way to whistle up boys
and girls from the ends of the country, farmhands,
students, secondary school children, waitresses, clerks,
then give them picks and shovels and let them go to it,
singing. By and by they will go home again, leaving a
road behind them, and however trained accountants work
out costs and expenditure, the full profit and loss on that
road will be hidden forever from business eyes.
This is the way Yugoslavia is building her "autoput",
or motor road, the new international highway which by
1960 should be crossing the land from the north-west to
20
the south-east. On November 23 1958 the newest stretch
was formally opened by Marshal Tito, a week before the
scheduled date. It is 140 kilometres (87 miles) long,
linking Ljubljana and Zagreb, the capitals of the Slove¬
nian and Croatian Federal Republics, and joining the
480 kilometres (300 miles) of highway already constructed
in the same way between Zagreb and Belgrade. And a
great part of it was the work of young Yugoslavs come
from all parts of the country in an enormous youth
project which lasted from March to November.
To find out how it was being done I had to go to Otocec,
halfway along the route, where the organizing staff of
the Youth Movement had its headquarters. We drove
from Zagreb through the low rolling hills of Slovenia,
beside rich meadows and wooded uplands and along the
banks of the winding Krkva river, sometimes on the old
road, soon to be relegated to slow farm traffic, sometimes
over a stretch of the newly cemented "autoput".
Otocec itself was a surprise, an ancient manor house
with pinkwashed plaster walls and corner turrets and an
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
arcaded courtyard, standing in a tiny island of flowers
and green gardens along one of the loveliest reaches of
the river. Now the property of the State, it has been
loaned to the Youth Movement for the duration of the
"action". Next year it is planned to turn it into a hotel.
It was José Hardmann, a young lawyer seconded to the
staff organisation handling the job there, who told me
the first part of the story. He was practical. He dealt
with facts and figures. At the beginning of the year
there were eighty kilometres (50 miles) of the new Ljubl¬
jana-Zagreb stretch of highway still to be built. There
was the Youth Movement of Yugoslavia which clamoured
for a share in the building. And from there, through
all the preliminary
planning, it seemed
but a step to the
single wooden barrack
set up by paid la¬
bour on each of the
proposed camp sites,
which were taken over
by the first volunteer
youth brigade arriv¬
ing in the slush and
snow of March to
prepare the ground.
With the exception
of the electrical bri¬
gade,' they were all
untrained, but within
twenty days sixteen
full working camps
or colonies another
was added later had
been built in the
countryside along the
designated route.
Water and electricity
had been laid on at
least one small village
in the neighbourhood
got electricity as a
r e s u 1 t telephones
connected, approach
roads built, wooden
barracks and huts
assembled, tents
pitched, and all stores
and equipment distri¬
buted, from bunks,
benches and tables,
blankets and sheets,
crockery and food,
down to the radio
and first aid installa¬
tions in each small
wireless station and
clinic. The g i r 1 s'
school taken over in
Novo Mesto as a tem¬
porary hospital had
also been fully
equipped and staffed,
though, as the head
doctor told me later
"fortunately, most of our beds have been consistently
empty". On April 1, as planned, the digging began.
José Hardmann also explained the way the scheme func¬
tioned, pointing out on the map the line picked by the
professional surveyors from Ljubljana who mapped out
and designed the road. "Some of it runs straight along
the old Roman road from the north," he said. There
were thirteen professional construction gangs, with paid
labour, stationed along the road, responsible for the later
stages of skilled work such as transporting and mixing
the cement and laying the final coats of bitumen and
cement "particularly hilly parts or curves will be laid
with cobbles to give cars a grip; our icy winters here are
no joke for drivers", said José Hardmann. And in be-
FLAGS OF THE NATIONS fly over the international camp at Kronovo where
I 20 volunteers from abroad were living. These young people came from the United
States, England, Belgium, the Netherlands, Switzerland, Sweden, France, Poland,
Italy, Germany, Tunisia, Morocco and Israel, and worked with their Yugoslav com¬
rades last July. Here, foreign volunteers return to camp after collecting their bedding.
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
tween the first and the last stages, like the filling of a
sandwich, came the young volunteers in their thousands
to dig and clear and level the road and lay the rubble
and shingle foundations.
Thousands is not an exaggeration. The students, secon¬
dary school children and foreign contingents, who came
during the summer holidays, stayed only one month; land-
workers, who came largely in the slack season in May
and June, stayed two. But it was reckoned that there
were between ten and thirteen thousand young people
working on the road each month, rising to the peak figure
of eighteen thousand in the July and August holiday
months, and that when the work was completed in
november, something
like sixty thousand
must have passed
through the colonies,
out of the 200,000
who had put in
applications to come.
I learned some
more from the hand¬
ful of young men
who have been, res¬
ponsible for most of
the organizing work,
forty in 'all, twenty
of them seconded for
the duration of the
project from univer¬
sity and training
schools and first jobs
all of them having
been active in youth
work for a long while
and more from the
boys and girls I talk¬
ed to as I went up
and down the road.
Staff and rank and
file alike wore the reg¬
ulation khaki drill
blouses and slacks of
the brigades, with
the little "titovka"
caps of the Partisans,
flashes on their
shoulders show¬
ing their ranks and
the names of their
brigades.
That loose working
garb soon became a
familiar sight to me
whether in a singing
column with picks
and shovels and fly¬
ing flag, setting off
for the morning or af¬
ternoon shift on the
road six hours, and
a compulsory two
hour's rest afterwards
or in a lorry load
lumbering by on an excursion to Zagreb or Ljubljana
or even further afield; or simply worn by boys and girls
swinging hands as they strolled up and down the broad
streets of the little half-way town of Novo Mesto on their
free day. Even here however, the girls had managed to
introduce a touch of fashion; it was definitely the done
thing, I noticed, for all the girls, unlike the boys, to wear
their trousers half twisted up the leg.
I learned from Dragoslav Petrovic and his friend Milu-
tin Damjanaovic, two eighteen-year-old farm labourers
from one of the Serbian brigades, that it was the local
youth organizations who handled the recruiting end, and
sifted applications to make up each brigade, four com¬
panies of thirty each, 120 in all, with an average of
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Teen-agers build
a highway «.«.»..<.,
Working dress for staff and rank
and file on the Youth Road
is khaki drill blouses and slacks
and the small "titovka" caps,
worn by the youths (right) from
Bosnia, who are trying on the
new boots that have just been
issued to them. For heavy work
like mixing cement on a hot day,
(photo, far right) regulation dress
is abandoned in favour of shorts.
Yugoslav Youth Movement photos
twenty-five girls to each brigade, ages ranging from fifteen
to twenty.
The educational whys and wherefores of a youth project
on this national scale are many historical, social, poli¬
tical, even economic. Historically, the unity of the Yu¬
goslav lands has been bedevilled for centuries by local
rivalries and jealousies, Serb against Croat, Catholic
against Greek Orthodox, submerged Macedonians, dual
nationality border folk, rivalries exploited with cunning
effect, for instance, by the Nazis in the last war; Bringing
COOKHOUSE SESSION. A professional cook is attached to each
camp, but the rest of the cooking and work is done by relays of volun¬
teers like this group from Belgrade shown busily peeling potatoes.
22
the young folk together, Serbs, Croats, Bosnian Moslems,
border minorities, working and playing side by side on
a road which has been given for name the old Partisan
slogan "The Brotherhood and Unity Road" is a step
towards mutual understanding.
Politically, in a socialist country, it mixes up classes
and types, students and farmer boys, factory Workers and
secondary school pupils, living and eating and digging
as one, and learning from each other. Socially it gives
the young people of the more backward parts of the
country a chance to see something outside their own vil¬
lage, learn some of the simple rules of hygiene, and
acquire a few of the elementary skills badly needed in
the national drive towards industrialization and mecha¬
nization.
Young Memic Shemso, for instance, who at twenty had
never been out of his Bosnian village, had learnt a lot
of things. He told me some of them. How to clean a
house. How to make a bed. How to keep a settlement
neat. And he, in common with many others, had taken
advantage of the courses provided for leisure hours to
learn to ride a bicycle and motor cycle. In the first four
months some eleven thousand young men had gone
through bicycle, motor cycle and car courses, as well as
considerable numbers who took the tractor-driving course.
Classes in photography and wireless mechanics were also
available for students and others with higher qualifi¬
cations.
The pretty young waitress serving me at the Otocec
canteen was another example of how different sorts of
training schemes were dovetailed into the main plan.
Franska Basaj, seventeen, is learning to be a waitress
at the school for restaurant workers in Ljubljana, and
she was one of the seven students from the school who
were doing a three weeks' stint at the headquarters'
canteen. "When we go, other students will come", she
explained. "By November everyone in the school will
have had a turn." Franska wasn't sure she was enjoying
it very much. The work was hard and the hours were
long. "It's lovely here, but we don't get enough time to
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
enjoy it. Still, she added philosophically, "it's all good
practice."
There was plenty of evidence of spare time amusements
scattered about the camps; bright modernist designs and
a futurist frieze along the hut walls left by the Belgrade
art students of an earlier brigade; a small model of the
Zornik hydraulic dam in Bosnia modelled in mud and
plaster by a brigade from Zvornik; patterns and slogans
carried out in coloured pebbles decorating the entrances
of the camps and edging barracks and tents. There was
football and sport for those who liked them, though
swimming in the river had been forbidden, to the chagrin
of many, since two brigadists had been drowned. Cul¬
tural activities included occasional visits from theatrical
groups and orchestras, lectures organized and given by
students. Best of all, there were the long evenings round
camp fires with singing and dancing and walking and
talking under the shadow of the pine trees.
And economically did it pay? Funnily enough, said
José Hardmann, it did. Providing voluntary labour in
the form of a Youth Project is reckoned to cost seven
per cent more than by employing strictly commercial
methods with paid labour. But the social value, the edu¬
cational benefits of such "actions" in helping to raise the
general level, has long justified such a loss in the eyes of
the authorities. In point of fact, however, it Was ex¬
plained, since the 5,600,000 dinars which the road costs
comes from a Government loan on which interest has
to be paid, and since there is no paid labour force avail¬
able in the country big enough to do the job in less than
three years, it is calculated that the saving of interest
charges by finishing the work in one year, under the
youth project, thus saving two years' interest, more than
covers the extra seven per cent.
To this must be added the fact that a great deal of the
prefabricated barracks, tents and equipment of the youth
camps will be dismantled and used again in the coming
year on the next stretch of road to be constructed in the
south.
TIME OFF FOR DANCING. There is no shortage of music during off-
duty hours. Many volunteers bring accordions, guitars and other instru¬
ments with them for folk and modern dancing and camp sing-songs.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
DRIVERLESS TRACTORS: THE LATEST
THING IN MECHANIZED FARMING
£S2s*^
by B. W. Golding
Today new methods of mechanization and automation are giving a tremen¬
dous boost to agricultural efficiency, making the farmer's job easier
and more profitable. Better still, they point the way to a solution of food short¬
ages brought on by a massive and ever-accelerating increase in the world's
population.
The whole world depends upon the farmer whether he grows wheat in Kansas,
coffee in Brazil or cotton in Egypt. Since the start of this century, thanks to
the invention of new kinds of farm machinery and the willingness of farmers
to adopt them, agricultural methods have changed out of all recognition.
In the U.S.A., for example, between 1938 and 1958, farmers more than trebled
their ownership of tractors to a total of 4,700,000. Since 1945 they have increased
the number of newer work-saving machinery by 1,200%, investing over 17,000
million dollars in combines, cornpickers, pickup hay balers, field forage har¬
vesters and other machinery. Now, taking another big step from mechaniza¬
tion to automation in the raising of animals and fowl they are copying the
assembly line techniques of industry.
One of the most striking examples is the giant "production line" for eggs
of a U.S. layer-breeder. whose hens are kept in individual cages, feed from a
continuously filled feed trough on one side and drink from a fountain on the
other. They drop their eggs on an inclined wire floor and these roll out through
an automatic counter onto a conveyor belt that takes them to a human sorter
who boxes them. One man can easily take care of 7,000 birds with an output
of 4,000 eggs a day.
Farming, the greatest industry in the world, is now adopting techniques which
have proved their worth in other industries. More and more ways are being
found to use electricity in farming, and research in this field has made pos¬
sible the development of such remarkable devices as the British experimental
automatic farm tractor described in the following article.
24
A farm tractor without a driver,
which sets out from the farm¬
yard, makes its way round the
field where it performs tasks automa¬
tically, and finally comes to a halt
back at its starting point, was seen
recently at Sonning Farm, near Read¬
ing in the South of England.
The demonstration was staged
jointly by the Farm Mechanization
department of the University of
Reading and the British Electrical
Research Association, which has its
rural electrification field station at
Shinfleld, near Reading. The two
groups are collaborating in this and
other research involving the use of
electricity in agriculture and horti¬
culture.
The tractor is a standard model but
it is fitted with special coils of wire
"search" coils which are mounted
at the front of the machine a few
inches above the ground. These coils
pick up signals from a current-
carrying wire which can be laid on
the ground or buried just below the
surface. The current is alternating
and is supplied from a small genera¬
tor, at a low voltage so that there is
no danger of electric shocks being
received by the field workers.
The search coils receive signals
from this directing wire and, through
a controlling circuit, operate the
steering of the tractor by means of
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
The time when a farm tractor
¿m\ m&' * will continue to work unattended
^A * ^ at night while the farmer sleeps
^íár\ is perhaps not so far off as one
might imagine. In Great Britain
the Farm Mechanization Depart
1 P^^^^B^^^fc ment of Reading University has
already developed a system of
WUfl WËTÈSiF' automatic control which enables
f^9[ fl^ JwvKr^l K^J ^B """"^^H mm\. a tractor to carry out pre-selected
mtym PS^*^saÉ A tasks without any human super
vision. At a recent demonstra¬
tion the machine set out from
the farmyard, crossed a road,
: obeying red and green traffic
control lights, passed through
B ' LLflK - ^sS* a gate, then made a circuit of
a field, distributing fertilizer or
I * WT 1 dropping off bales of hay at
ür 1 HI l1
kflr ^B BfA ^B Bfv/ Yl
selected places. Photo left, shows
the driverless tractor being fitted
with auto-controls; far left, a
trial run during research into
^H ^ft wTW1. * ^tt^il the use of automatic controls.
^ fr'n ~Jm*
W* Am m\ Photos Central Office
of Information, London
solenoid-operated hydraulic valves
and a double-acting hydraulic ram.
Movement away from the wire pro¬
duces a stronger signal in one search
coil .than in the other; an out-of-
balance is created and the effect is
to correct the steering to bring the
machine back "on course". In this
way the tractor is made to follow,
closely, the path traced out for it,
while signals passed along the wire
can stop it, or can make it do a num¬
ber of simple jobs. All this is achiev¬
ed without any human supervision;
there is no radio control and no press¬
ing of buttons.
There is a telescoping bumper
mounted in front so that, if the trac¬
tor collides with something, the
engine is shut off by the movement
of the bumper closing contacts in the
electrical control circuit. At the
demonstration, the machine started
out from the farmyard, passed
through a gate, across the roadway
obeying red and green traffic control
lights passed through the field gate
and then made a circuit round the
field distributing fertilizer or drop¬
ping bales of hay at selected places.
It also sounded its horn automatically.
The University and the E.R.A. have
worked out this device as the first
step towards a much fuller system of
automatic operation of machines in
the field. It is only a beginning: a
good deal more research will be need¬
ed to follow out the succeeding steps
which may lead one day to automa¬
tic ploughing, cultivating, harvesting,
seeding, hoeing and other jobs.
At present, the performance is
confined to a very simple routine in
which the machine moves along a par¬
ticular route and performs a number
of pre-selected tasks. Even so, a
considerable saving in labour could
be achieved by dispensing with a
tractor driver when carting silage or
collecting grain from a combine har¬
vester and taking it back to the
farmyard for unloading. Of course,
the tractor has to be fitted With the
search coils and hydraulic controls,
and the directing wire has to be laid
out. But these adjuncts, with the
generator for the controlling signals,
are not very expensive items and the
power needed for the control is so
small that costs are negligible.
Another obvious advantage of a
driver-less tractor is that it can be
used for carrying out noxious or
dangerous operations, such as spread¬
ing toxic weed killers or carting the
radio-active materials which may be
employed if certain techniques now
proposed are adopted.
One can also foresee the develop¬
ment of a self-navigating device
allowing the tractor to move away
from the wire, with perhaps a
magnetic tape record which the
tractor will "play" to itself to guide
its more complicated motions and
conduct it back to its shed for the
night. But need it stop at night?
Could it not go on with its work while
its owner slept?
These may seem fanciful ideas but
there is no reason why automation,
which is becoming so much fashion
in industrial processes, should not be
adopted on the farm. Indeed, there
are very good reasons why it should.
Labour saving in agriculture is
becoming increasingly important in
the more industrialized countries
where farm workers are continually
drifting away to other industries.
And there is a need to allow standards
of living to rise in the countries which
are less developed industrially, by
releasing agricultural workers for in¬
dustrial work. Increased productivity
is the key to advances in this direc¬
tion.
Automatic operation in poultry
keeping by the use of a travelling
"canteen" bringing food to hens in
laying batteries and in pig rearing,
by the use of automatic feeding, air
conditioning and cleaning, have
already been introduced. Automation
in the field is certainly more difficult
to accomplish than in fixed indoor
installations, but its potentialities are
perhaps even greater.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
KHUJIR: ISLAND CAPITAL ON
THE WORLD'S DEEPEST LAKE
THE ISLAND OF OLKHON. ON LAKE BAIKAL: A WINDSWEPT SIBERIAN LANDSCAPE OF BARE HILLS. SAND DUNES AND LOG CABINS.
by Evgueni Veltistov
The island of Olkhon lies in the heart of Siberia, in the
middle of Lake Baikal,the deepest and one of the
coldest lakes in the world. The climate is harsh,
for the Baikal is a tremendous inland sea, nearly
400 miles long and between 15 and 50 miles wide,
surrounded on almost all sides by snowy mountains.
On the island the wind blows ceaselessly, year in year
out, so strongly that even in the heart of winter the snow
never settles on the ground: it is swept away by the wind.
The landscape of Olkhon is also .windswept a sym¬
phony in red and yellow tints with its bare hills, sand
dunes and log cabins.
In winter, the island is joined to the mainland by a road
across the ice. It is a dangerous crossing. Even when
the thermometer registers forty degrees below zero
(72 degrees of frost Fahrenheit) you have to keep a sharp
look-out, for crevasses are apt to appear suddenly in front
of your truck, and the best brakes in the world are useless
on such a skating rink.
Khujir, the island capital, is built on a high bank over¬
looking the lake. You get an excellent view of it as you
approach the island from across the water. The big trays
on which the fish are laid to dry stand out against a
background of yellow sand; you see the plank Walks that
lead up the bank and the salting and curing sheds. Up
on top of the cliff are solid-looking log houses, pine trees
and more sand.
On a sunny day, the whole town shines and sparkles like
the decorations on a Christmas tree, for all the houses
are made of pine-wood from the floor to the roof-top.
Khujir is a fishing village and Lake Baikal provides a live¬
lihood for most of its menfolk. The fishermen are tough
and sturdy and spend their lives on the water. In
26
summer, they cast their nets far out in the lake; in winter,
they go back and forth across the ice, checking the holes
they have cut in the ice by plunging their hands into the
freezing water, until they find that their nets are full of
fish.
Like all small towns Khujir has its chronicler the local
school-master, Nicolai Reviakin. He witnessed the birth
and the development of the town, since he arrived on the
island a quarter of a century ago when the site on which
Khujir now stands was nothing but a wilderness. It was
inhabited by a lone fisherman who had settled there in
spite of the fact that the Shamans (local priests or sor¬
cerers) considered the spot to be peopled by evil spirits.
The Buriats had brought offerings there from time imme¬
morial, and the womenfolk used a roundabout way to
avoid the "Shaman's Stone." But the first fisherman's
example was contagious; others, seeing that the bay was
an ideal place for fishing soon settled on the island.
Khujir has changed a good deal since those early days.
To-day, no one could imagine life there without a school
and a library, a clinic, a sewing centre and a hostel. Yet
twenty-five years ago none of these institutions existed;
and the newcomers had great difficulty in explaining to
the Buriats what a bath was used for and Why you needed
a doctor.
It is still mid-winter and bitterly cold, but the island
tailors are already busy prepararing for the spring season;
at the library people are queuing up for the books, papers
and periodicals Which have just arrived from Irkutsk, the
biggest town in the area; in the afternoon, children play
round the "Shaman's Stone", searching for old coins in its
cracks and fissures; and in the evening the fishermen's
club is thronged with people who come to dance, to listen
to a concert or see a film show.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
In spite of its remoteness Khujir does not feel cut off
from the rest of the country. This is immediately noticed
in the local museum which Reviakin has set up with the
help of the schoolchildren. It is no coincidence that the
museum should be named after Vladimir Obruchev, the
great Russian geologist. In December 1956, the scientist
wrote from Moscow describing his trip to the island in
1889, enquiring about conditions there today, and asking
for samples of local ores.
Soon a regular exchange of correspondence started up
between Moscow and the island. It was cut short unfor¬
tunately by the scientist's death. But good results had
been achieved. The school now has an exhibition room
where various discoveries are on view together with stuffed
animals and a collection of ores. The children of Khujir
write regularly to other schoolchildren in the U.S.S.R.
telling them of their life on Lake Baikal, and
describing the flora and fauna.
No, Olkhon certainly does not feel isolated from the rest
of the world. The island keeps in touch with other parts
of the Soviet Union and even further afield. The local
fishermen send their catch to Irkutsk regularly, and last
year 25 barrels were shipped to the World Fair at Brussels
where tourists from all over the world were able to taste
fish from Lake Baikal.
The little port hums with activity. Two months ago,
despite the intense cold, trucks of all kinds and sizes were
coming and going across the ice; the noise of the power
station on the cliff mingled with that of the workshops
where motorboat engines were being repaired, and with
the creaking of the winch Which, in anticipation of the
summer months, was already extracting great bloks of ice
from the lake for the cold storage rooms.
Khujir is growing fast and so is its population. The
nursery school is now too small and a new one is being
built. Old huts where some of the fishermen used to live
are being replaced by comfortable, modern houses; and
the water supply is being laid on.
Many things still remain to be done, but the fishermen
of Olkhon have begun the job and will see it through.
Official Soviet photos
BARRELS pile up in a cooper's yard. Last year 25 barrels
of fish were shipped from Olkhon to the Brussels World Fair.
ROOF-TOP WORK by carpenters (right), putting the finishing touches to a large house in which four families will live. For
the moment it stands alone on a road leading up to the forest, but soon other houses will rise beside it. Lake Baikal is
the deepest fresh-water lake in the world. Left, a fisherman's wife repairs nets in preparation for the Spring season.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
CURRENT
MISCONCEPTIONS
ABOUT THE
AUSTRALIAN
ABORIGINES
by Ronald M. Berndt
Professor of Anthropology, University
of Western Australia
Most people, through the ages, have regarded those
living outside their normal range of experience not
only as strangers, but as fundamentally different
from themselves. The less association they have with
them, the greater is the margin for distortion. To some
Australian Aborigines, for instance, their not-so-distant
neighbours were "cannibals" or "promiscuous creatures
with no marriage rules". Disparaging others was one way
of emphasizing their own superiority.
Thus a number of Australian tribes referred to them¬
selves by words meaning "men", or "human beings": but
they took it for granted that this status was peculiarly
their own and did not apply to outsiders. They inter¬
preted What they saw and heard of the behaviour of
others in the light of their own preconceived views. In
this way, quite trivial differences were sometimes mag¬
nified until they came to seem overwhelmingly important.
On a larger scale, this is just what has happened in the
case of Europeans coming in contact with Australian
Aborigines as well as with other non-literate peoples. The
obvious differences in their ways of living were so great
that some of the newcomers claimed the Aborigines could
not be regarded as human. Not all of them went as far
as this. Nevertheless, the Aborigines have been popularly
and sweepingly categorized as the most "primitive" people
on earth, and labelled by words like "stone-age".
Certainly some such arbitrary label has been attached
to all sorts of people living in a wide variety of societies,
and scattered all over the world. Perhaps this didn't
matter much as long as people remained "pigeonholed",
so to spealk, with spatial mobility at a minimum; but the
situation to-day has changed so drastically that it has
quite serious implications. Anthropologists, who should
have been the first to point out the insidious character of
such terms, have lagged sadly behind although It has not
always been their fault since, like most if not all scientists,
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
Official Australian photos
they are essentially culture-bound: and in this they do
not differ radically from other members of their society.
Much of the blame here can be laid at the door of the
archaeologists, who in order to fill in gaps in their
archaeological evidence turned to living peoples who
possessed similar technical equipment, or used what
seemed to be the same kind of tools. These were, for the
most part, people who kept no written records; the
Australian Aborigines, among others, were vulnerable on
this score, and did not even realize that they were being
equated with early man. This is not a legitimate
approach. Yet it has survived right up to this day, and
has had an immense bearing on the general use of such
labels.
Although technological complexity is important in our
own kind of society as in many others, . there are other
kinds of cultural complexity which do not necessarily
coincide with this. Simply because the Australian
Aborigines used stone tools, had the minimum of material
objects, did not live in houses, wore little or no clothing,
hunted for and collected their food, we cannot compare
them in more than a superficial way with (for example)
Palaeolithic man. They are "modern men" (*) as we
ourselves are, not representatives of the "Stone-Age", in
the accepted archaeological use of that term.
A vague, emotionally loaded term such as "primitive",
when applied to any contemporary people, has a strong
connotation of "early type", perhaps "stone-age", but
certainly "crude", "mentally backward", and so on. Many
of us to-day prefer to use the term non-literate (not
illiterate or preliterate), to distinguish people like the
Australian Aborigines from those who share a tradition,
( See e.g. S. L. Washburn In E. A. Hoebel, J. D. Jennings and
E. R. Smith's Readings In Anthropology, McGraw-Hill, 1955, p. 108.
or norm, of literacy; even this is not entirely satisfactory.
Yet the bogey of "mental backwardness" or "inferiority"
has persisted from the past and is still with us. As a
catch-phrase, it is often used by members of one group
to downgrade another particularly as applied to people
attempting to adjust to a situation in which the speakers
themselves feel quite at home. People take their own
background of experience and their own way of life very
much for granted; and some of them find it hard to
believe that any "normal" person should have trouble
in acquiring the same familiarity with it.
Too many assessments of intelligence have been made
on just this basis: testing in an unfamiliar situation, often
artificially constructed, against a range of "givens"
relevant to the culture of the person carrying out the test.
And as far as the Australian Aborigines are concerned no
reliable information is available one way or the other.
There is ample material to show that these people can
adjust to changing conditions, under favourable circum¬
stances; and there is nothing, as far as we know, holding
them back mentally.
But, of course, any situation of adjustment which in¬
volves learning a new way of life is fraught with dif¬
ficulties which are not always linked with mental ability.
The Australian Aborigines are responsible people, with
a complex cultural background, and a fully developed
social organization but one that is different from our
own, with differing values and a different outlook on life.
There is nothing embryonic or primitive about them; their
development has merely taken place along different lines.
Traditionally, the Australian Aborigines were semi-
nomadic. The Continent was inhabited by many tribes,
their boundaries not as firmly fixed as has sometimes been
suggested. Each, however, was an autonomous political
unit, although there were some exceptions, notably among
the Wulamba of Eastern Arnhem Land and the "Narin-
CONT'D PAGES 30-31
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
MISCONCEPTIONS
ABOUT AUSTRALIAN
ABORIGINES
(Continued)
Not a primitive 'Stone Age' people;
Not cut off from the outside world
yerl" of the Lower River Murray, South Australia. There
were some large cultural blocs, such as the Bidjandjara
and related groups of the Great Victoria Desert, stretching
across South Australia into Western Australia and Central
Australia. Also there were many languages, and diversity
in a wide range of other aspects as well. When we speak
of the Australian Aborigines as a whole, then we can do
so only in the most general terms. (In other words the
Aranda or Arunta, so well-known from the publications of
Spencer and Gillen, cannot be taken as "typical" Abor¬
igines.)
As far as traditional culture and society are concerned,
misconceptions about the Aborigines are numerous; but
two of these are especially important. One is that Abori¬
ginal society is (or was) static, that ideas and techniques
as well as behaviour patterns had not appreciably changed
over thousands of years. This is linked with the notion
of "primitiveness" already mentioned, with the implication
that their way of life had been somehow arrested in time.
It takes the form of such questions as: "Why didn't they
cultivate the land?" "'Why didn't they have any domestic
animals except the dingo?" "Why didn't they try to exploit
their environment instead of just adapting to it?"
Cultivation of plants
'contrary to nature'
Change, of course, is inevitable in any social situation,
and the Australian Aborigines were no exception. It
does not take outside impact to bring about change,
although this may speed it up. At the same time, in
most Aboriginal societies there was an emphasis on "non-
change", an essential conservatism. This did have certain
far-reaching effectsnotably in circumscribing personal
experience, and discouraging drastic innovation. In part
it stemmed from the basic tenets of their religious tradi¬
tions. Although for general purposes the distinction be¬
tween past, present and future was quite clearly recognized,
the religious view suggested a merging of one with the
other expressed, for instance, in the belief that the
Ancestral Beings Who lived on earth at the beginning of
time are as much alive to-day as they always were, and
will continue to be so.
Further, in their fundamental "world view" man was
part of nature, not opposed to it, and not sharply distinct
from other natural species. (This is, of course, in marked
contrast to our own approach.) The sacred life was of
utmost importance; but, contrary to what is held by some
anthropologists, the division between the sacred and the
profane was not always tightly defined, and women played
a greater part in religious activities than has sometimes
been acknowledged.
Against this background, we can appreciate better the
economic limitations of an environment in which, apart
from the fertile coastal areas, European settlers them¬
selves have not found it easy to exist without considerable
help from outside. Most of the Aborigines believed that
food of various kinds, like water, had been provided for
them by the Ancestral Beings: that their own part in this
lay on the one hand in the everyday tasks of collecting
or hunting for it, and on the other in performing the
rituals which would ensure that the supplies were maint¬
ained. In this view, the cultivation of plants was not only
unnecessary but, one might say, "contrary to nature".
Another source of misunderstanding has to do with
kinship. It has been said that Aborigines are predomin¬
antly interested in this, and that the social arrangements
HALF TRUTHS still exist about the "psychic powers" of the Abori¬
gines, their supposed mental telepathy and ability to work sor¬
cery or black magic. The romantic picture of Aborigines perform¬
ing spectacular dances and ceremonies also persists despite all
evidence to the contrary. Above, meditation over the sacred
boards, most sacred Aborigines' symbol of their desert culture.
30
FAMILY LIFE. It has been said that social arrangements based on
kinship among the Aborigines were rigid and unyielding. In practice,
Australian Aboriginal systems of kinship terms and behaviour associated
with them are fairly flexible. Aborigine, seen here with two of his
wives and their children, has a "Macassan" type bearda relic of earlier
days. In centre, foreground, is his wooden pipe with painted design.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. April 1959
RITUAL CEREMONIES
among the Aborigines are
things about which many
erroneous ideas have grown
up. Present-day reality is
far removed from the stories
that circulate. Except on
rare occasions, naked Abo¬
rigines no longer roam free¬
ly over the tribal lands.
Only in isolated areas can
one find these people living
approximavely as they did
in the past, and then only
a small handful, increasingly
depleted. While in some
places indigenous religion
is still a powerful' force,
rituals are performed less
frequently and with modi¬
fications. Photo shows a
sacred clan emblem being
painted on the chest of
a postulant for ritual at
Yirrkalla, N.E. Arnhem Land.
Photos Ronald M. Berndt
based on it were rigid and unyielding. Yet this is simply
part of the fabric of most social systems, emphasized more
in some than in others. In practice, Australian Aboriginal
systems of kinship terms and the behaviour associated
with them were fairly flexible. As far as choice of a
marriage partner was concerned there was much variation
within a limited range, allowing room for romantic love,
in spite of the emphasis on ideal marriage patterns.
The ghost of "primitive communism" has often been
conjured .Up in connexion with all this. But personal
ownership, and personal rights of distribution, were Well
entrenched; the sharing of food or the rendering of
services nearly always took place on a kinship basis, with
the expectation that they Would be reciprocated in due
course.
Another point about which a great deal of nonsense
has been written concerns the Australian Aborigines'
"instinctive" ability in tracking both human beings and
animals. Statements of this sort do not recognize that
such skills must be learnt and practice in them maintain¬
ed; Aborigines who have been drawn increasingly into
the Western European orbit quickly lose them. Again,
Aborigines, and particularly the men, are accused of being
lazy. The most popular example of this is that When on
a hunting or foraging trip an adult man usually walks
ahead of his womenfolk, who trail behind heavily laden,
while he carries only a spear and thrower. People who
cite this overlook or brush aside the fact that he must be
unencumbered so that he can use his weapons should
the need arise.
To dismiss the Aborigines as "naturally lazy" is to forget
that in their traditional environment, in most parts of
the Continent, they had to work hard for their living
or die. To say that they have "no sense of time" is to
forget that clock-watching is not the only means of reck¬
oning this. They are looked down on as* dirty, living
under insanitary conditions, by those who have seen only
the dilapidated shanties, or the static camps around out¬
back settlements.
In the bush the scene is different. In the necessity of
moving from waterhole to waterhole, from camp to camp.
each new site was abandoned before it had a chance
to become dirty; and any refuse left behind Would be
absorbed easily into the natural environment; as the tins
and old rags, so common to-day, are not. Then again,
there are the half-truths about psychic matters; mental
telepathy; the reading of smoke signals; the power to
work sorcery or black magic; resistance to pain; the
"instinctive urge" to go walkabout, and so on.
But to speak of the traditional societies and cultures
of these people is to speak of the past. The contemporary
scene is very different. There are no Aborigines in the
whole of Australia who have not felt, in some measure,
the impact of the introduced way of living. There are
very few people to-day who roam freely, living a tradi¬
tionally-oriented life: and it is safe to say that none of
them are unaware of Europeans.
Naked Aborigines no
longer roam the land
The Pintubi (so-called Bindaboo) who were recently
"discovered" had been contacted more than 20 years
ago and were not really far, as distances go in Aus¬
tralia, from Mission areas. In Arnhem Land, that 32,000-
odd square mile of Reserve in the Northern Territory, alien
contact has been quite intensive for centuries. Long
before Europeans appeared, traders from what is now
Indonesia had established bases around the coast, and to¬
day Arnhem Land is virtually encircled by mission stations
where most of the people congregate.
South and east, in the coastal cities " where most
Australian-Europeans live, there are comparatively few
people of Aboriginal or part-Aboriginal descent. Only in
isolated areas, such as in North-Western South Australia;
and East-Central Western Australia (where the activities
of the Atomic Energy Commission, and plans to open up
country for pastoral enterprises, threaten to curtail tribal
movements more drastically than in the past), can one
find these people living approximately as they did in the
past and then only a small handful, increasingly deplet-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Their culture swept
into the mainstream
of Australian life
(Continued)
ed through the attraction of settlements of various kinds
on the fringes of this semi-desert country.
Except on very rare occasions, naked Aborigines no
longer roam freely over these tribal lands. While in
some places indigenous religion is still a powerful force,
rituals are performed less frequently and with modifica¬
tions; and this is true for all aspects of their activity. The
romantic picture of Aborigines living in a traditional
fashion, performing spectacular ceremonies and dances,
has persisted in spite of all evidence to the contrary.
There is still a great deal of Aboriginality to be found, but
it is becoming mixed increasingly with introduced
elements.
Change, that inherent quality present in all social living,
has not left the Australian Aborigines untouched. The
picture to-day is of a people spread unevenly across the
Continent and not even now, under outside pressures,
viewing themselves as united. As in the past, although
now in a different setting, there is little interaction be¬
tween those in different parts of the Continent, and so far
little acknowledgement of any common heritage.
The dice are both
loaded and cast
Most of them /live In scattered groups in the poorer
quarters of the cities, or on the fringe of country
towns, pastoral stations, or mission and Government
settlements, incorporated in varying degrees into the Iwider
Australian community. They range from the unsophisti¬
cated to the virtually assimilated, with many in between;
but all have been caught up in the trend toward Euro-
peanizatlon, toward eventual assimilation if not phy¬
sically, then culturally and socially.
Although the policies of the various States and of the
Commonwealth itself differ on a number of points, they
all agree on one basic aim: that these people must be
absorbed into the mainstream of Australian life. Of
course, this will not be achieved by all of them at one and
the same time; but it can be hastened, as is the official
Intention to-day. The outcome, however, is a foregone
conclusion; the dice are too heavily loaded for anything
else to happen.
The greatest misconception has been, and Is, to regard
these contemporary Australian Aborigines, or at least all
but a few, as being primarily Aborigines in the traditional
sense. The majority have grown up under the shadow
of the European; and although in the remoter regions a
modified form of camp life persists, each year sees them
being committed irrevocably to more and more aspects
of European life. Once this process has begun, there is no
turning back...
Misconceptions block our understanding and apprecia¬
tion of traditional Aboriginal life as it Was in the past,
and as it is partly in some areas to-day. And these mis¬
conceptions inevitably have their repercussions In the
present, since they not only influence Government policy
in relation to these people but distort our appraisal of
the total situation.
ABORIGINAL
X RAY ART
Although the materials
and the colours of the
Aboriginal artist are very
limited, he uses the same
principles of line, colour,
balance and spacing of
degign elements present
in all great art. Photo
right, shows Arnhem
Land artist doing one
of the curious "X-ray"
paintings, so called be¬
cause internal as well as
external details are por¬
trayed. Below, "X-ray"
painting of a kangaroo. Photo Ronald M. Berndt
Photo © Unesco. From "Australia Aboriginal PaintingsArnhem Land", in the
Unesco World Art Series. Available in all good bookshops at a maximum price
of $ I 8.00 or ¡a equivalent in other currencies. Also obtainable from New York
Graphic Society, 95 East Putnam Avenue, Greenwich, Conn. U.S.A., and Zwemmer
Galleries, Charing Cross Road, London.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1959
Letters to the Editor
SIZE OF THE «SNOW WHITES'
Sir,
In your February issue, I read with
interest the article on 'the experiments I
am carrying out with several collea¬
gues in my laboratories at the College
de France on changes of physical cha¬
racteristics induced in ducks by injec¬
tions of desoxyribonucleic acid (DNA).
I fully approve of your text, but I am
sorry to say that the relative dimensions
of the four subjects whose photographs
you published were not shown correctly.
The relationship of these sizes is impor¬
tant. The height of the subjects known
as "'Snow Whites" is less, in fact
much less than those of the Peking
breed ducks. This is one of the basic
characteristics of the results which we
have obtained, but it is far from obvious
in your photographs. The photograph
of the Peking breed duck (N° 1) is, for
example, just over one inch too short
as compared to N" 3. Here are the pro¬
portions which should have been shown
for the subjects you reproduced, the
measurements being made from tip of
beak to tip of tail. If Photo 3 is taken
as a standard of measurement, the dis¬
tance beak-tail should have been just
over one inch longer for Photo 1,
.787 inches longer for Photo 2 and, on
the contrary, 3.1 inches shorter for
Photo 4.
M. J. Benoît
Histophysiological Laboratory,
Collège de France, Paris
UNIVERSITY OF THE NATIONS
Sir,
The time has come, I feel, to take
another step on the long and arduous
road of international education: the
foundation of a truly international
university. There is no need to dwell
on the necessity of making science
accessible to all nations and there is no
doubt that this must be a chief aim of
Unesco. It seems to me that there
cannot be many ways more likely to
achieve this effect, or at least to further
it, than the establishment of an Inter¬
national University. By this I mean a
university of the highest standing,
staffed by outstanding scientists of all
countries, for students of any nation,
race and creed, who apply for admission
and are in possession of the necessary
degrees of their respective countries,
i.e. matriculation-papers or similar.
Courses should be given in the main
languages, English, French, Spanish and
Russian, e.g. the degrees won by the
students must of course be fully
recognized by all member-countries. A
useful stipulation might be that the
history of a certain country, or
continent, must never be taught by a
national of the same area.
The organizational effort could well
be directed by a committee of scientists
of high repute working under the
auspices of Unesco. It seems easy to
predict that many member-countries
would agree to sponsor one or the other
institute, i.e. build it, staff it and run it.
Let us say that France might take upon
herself the establishment of a school of
philosophy, Britain the department of
Economics, Russia an Institute of
Mathematics, the U.S.A. Chemistry, etc.
The first International University
might be opened in a small neutral
country, like Switzerland, the idea being
that eventually similar universities would
be founded in many, if not all countries
of the globe. It is recognized that this
is a programme for many years to come
and that achievement will not come
easily. But this seems to be only one
more reason to start now.
Harry Pollak
Nahariah, Israel
Sir,
What we need is a United Nations
University. A school financed by all
the countries on their ability to pay, but
a school where the top crop of the
world, no matter which country they
are from, can come. The students of
this United Nations University would
be citizens of the world.
Robert F. Atkins
Hawthorne, California, U.S.A.
PLACE FOR YOUTH
Sir,
In my own name and in those of
many friends of mine I should like to
back up the proposals of Stan Marks
(Letter to the Editor, December 1958)
concerning a U.N. Youth Council. It
is a great hindrance to the idea of
internationality that many nations are
ruled by politicians whose ages are, on
the average, between sixty and seventy.
Less conservative, youngsters with more
spirit and driving power should be in an
organization as a permanent part of the
United Nations.
Wont de Maat
The Hague, Netherlands
WORKING FOR PEACE-AT HOME
Sir,
In a leaflet distributed at the Brussels
International Exhibition I read: "Since
wars begin in the minds of men, it is in
the minds of men that the defences of
peace must be constructed." (From the
Preamble to the Unesco Constitution.)
It is not only on the international level
that antagonisms exist. Daily life is
full of them. Do you not think that
efforts to smooth out the differences
within a nation, within a social group
or within a family should be linked with
those which you are making on an
international scale? Is it not the state
of mind created by the antagonisms
poisoning their private lives which makes
men tacitly accept the prospect of
armed conflict between nations? And
is not the same fear of being crushed
by others found just as much in the
daily struggle for existence as in a war
between nations?
Do you not think that if, by your
activities, you manage to replace the
latent or active antagonisms of everyday
life by a spirit of mutual understanding
you will uproot the source of warlike
inclinations?
I believe that this great effort to
remove the causes of hostility is one in
which everyone ready to accept social
responsibilities should join. Thus, the
head of a business can bring his
influence to bear on his employees and
on his business competitors, a school
teacher on his class, a lawyer on his
clients and a journalist on his readers.
I am sure that if Unesco initiated such
action it would soon be joined by
thousands of men and women of good¬
will.
M.A. Brodsky
Brussels, Belgium
LITTLE-KNOWN JAPANESE ART
Sir,
As an admirer of Japanese art I
derived great pleasure from your issue
of June, 1958 (Masterworks of Japan's
Stone Age Art). If you could publish
colour reproductions of a good selection
of Japanese colour prints it would
undoubtedly be a revelation to those
people in Europe who known nothing
of this artistic production. I am, of
course, referring to modern prints with
their forceful, glowing colours, although
these may perhaps be too "gaudy" for
the tastes of some lovers of art. In the
exhibition of Japanese art which came
to London directly from Paris there was
not a single example of this work. I
was surprised and disappointed as I
believe this art should be better known
in Europe...
A. Scott
London, England
OUT OF PLACE IN PARIS
Sir,
I shall not be renewing my sub¬
scription to The Unesco Courier for
1959. I made this decision after
reading your November 1958 issue
devoted to the new Unesco Head¬
quarters. I think it is both shameful
and improper that France should have
contributed, through its share of the
Unesco budget, to the construction of
this building, of which the least one
can say is that it is out of place in
Paris... It is distressing to think of the
millions of francs that have been paid
to "artists" for works like that of
Picasso in the Delegates' Lobby, like
Calder's mobile or Moore's "Reclining
Figure". I consider that when an
international organization like Unesco
has the honour to be offered a home
by France in a city like Paris, it should
draw some inspiration from the good
taste of its host rather than to try to
introduce a frigid and lifeless style
which seems to have more in common
with the insane asylum than with art
and which is bound to clash with our
millenary culture and to mar a city as
beautiful as Paris.
B. Amphoux
Paris, France
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
iiOAN AT WORK: A $5,000,000
loan for road construction granted by
the World Bank to the Government
of Salvador is going to mean land,
work, homes and economic be-
. tterment for an area in the south
of the country bordering on the
Pacific. It will be used to construct
a network of 21 branch roads to¬
talling some 200 miles where at
present only earth tracks exist. It
will thus be possible to settle agri¬
cultural and other workers in the
area, thus relieving population pres¬
sures elsewhere and reducing un¬
employment. Land opened up will
be used for stock-rearing and to
grow wheat, rice and vegetables.
ATOMIC NEEDS IN ASIA:
A team of eight scientists recently
returned to Vienna after a five-
week mission to Burma, Thailand,
Indonesia and Ceylon to survey
conditions and possibilities in the
field of nuclear energy. The
survey, undertaken by the Inter¬
national Atomic Energy Agency in
Vienna at the request of the four
countries visited by the mission,
included studies of those s.ectors of
industry, agriculture and general
economy likely to be affected by
the applications of atomic energy.
Also examined were the possi¬
bilities of using isotopes in agri¬
culture, biology and medicine; the
development of reactor projects;
the training of technicians; the
adoption of adequate safety regu¬
lations; and availability of raw
materials.
JLi AST-WEST STUDIES AT OX¬
FORD: Oxford University will this
year be the scene of an experiment to
introduce oriental studies more gene¬
rally in the fields of adult education,
teacher training and student acti¬
vities. The scheme, supported by
the United Kingdom National Com¬
mission for Unesco, is in line with
Unesco's Major Project for encourag¬
ing better understanding between
East and West. It includes special
university courses of lectures on
Asian art, oriental religions and
Asian thought, and lectures on
oriental civilizations given at nearby
teacher training colleges. The
Oxford Museum of Eastern Art is
providing a travelling exhibition of
oriental art, and student activities
include an inter-university con¬
ference, the preparation of an Asian
Film Festival and the publication of
a special edition of a student peri¬
odical devoted to the Unesco East-
West project.
EDUCATION THROUGH ART:
In almost every country in the
world there is now a realization
that education through art is a
subject that transcends narrow
categories of vocational or spe
cialist education, writes Sir Her¬
bert Read in the introduction
to "Education Through Art in
Australia", recently published in
Australia by the Melbourne Uni¬
versity Press. Edited by Dr. Ber¬
nard Smith, a member of the
Australian Unesco Committee for
Letters, this book was stimulated
by the discussions of the Unesco
Seminar on the Role of the Visual
Arts in Education, held at Bristol,
(UJi.) in 1951 and the Unesco Art
Education Seminar, sponsored by
the Australian Advisory Committee
for Unesco and held in Melbourne
in 1954. Leading Australian edu¬
cation officials, art educators
museum directors and psycho¬
logists have contributed to this
publication which will serve as a
guide to creative art education in
Australia.
II.LUMANIA LIQUIDATES ILLI¬
TERACY: Some two decades ago illi¬
teracy was still a mass problem in
Rumania: a 1930 census had shown
an average illiteracy percentage of
38.2, rising as high as from 43% to
56% in certain districts. A 1945
estimate placed the number of the
country's illiterates as four million.
Even after three years of trade union
action for education there were still
over three million illiterates, mosuy
2,800,000 in rural areas. In 1948
Rumania's Grand National Assembly
passed an educational reform law
and the liquidation of illiteracy
became a State affair, crowned with
success during the country's second
five-year plan. Along with the
abolition of illiteracy cultural re¬
sources increased: libraries increased
from 30,000 to 38,000 between 1946
and 1949; volumes increased from
14,544 million to 53,875 million
between 1946 and 1956. The number
of cinemas, theatres, radio sets and
museums showed increases of three
to five times.
TAKING ART TO THE PEOPLE:
A Gallery of Colour Reproductions
of Masterpieces of Fine Art has
been established in Belgrade with
material consisting of repro¬
ductions of collections of old and
modern art given to Yugoslavia
by Unesco. The first exhibition
of reproductions of modern paint¬
ings held last October and No¬
vember was seen by more than
16,000 visitors, including many
schoolchildren and students for
whom lectures on "Trends in the
Art of the 20th Century" were
given. This exhibition is to cir¬
culate in rural areas.
MAINLAND CHINA POPULATION
RISING 10 MILLION A YEAR
The present world population of 2,800 million may rise to between 4,900 mil¬
lion and 6,900 million in the next forty years and there are reasons to believe
that it will already have increased by 100 million at the end of next year. A
disturbing fact is that the growth of population is greater in the less advanced
than in the industrial countries.
Figures such as these highlight the problems created by the rapid increase
in the world's population, and underline the urgency of a recent recommen¬
dation of the United Nations Population Commission that broader studies and
analyses should be carried out.
The Population Commission, which concluded its 10th session in Geneva
recently, suggested that a world conference on population should be convened
by the United Nations in 1964. More accurate census figures will then be avail¬
able as the U.S.S.R. has just carried out its first census since 1939 and India
is to carry out a census in 1961. According to the Commission the birthrate on
the mainland of China is now probably 37 to 42 per 1,000, while estimates of
the deathrate vary from 17 to 21 per 1,000. This indicates an annual natural
increase of roughly two per cent. At this rate the population on the mainland
of China increases by more than ten million a year.
In its report to the U.N. Economic and Social Council, the Commission
regards it "as a grave Iresponsability" to call attention to "the unprecedented
rapidity of the earth's current population increase and to the fact that this
increase may be still more rapid in the near future." The Commission regrets
the lack of trained demographers and points out that the less-developed coun¬
tries have the fewest. In view of the grave issues raised by population growth,
the Commission feels that the services of the United Nations in this field should
be strengthened.
u
z
<
u
z
<
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S DO IT
YOURSELF'
SCIENCE BOOK
(2nd. printing)
Material for making laboratory equipment exists every¬
where the home, around the school itself, in the
junkyard, at the food market, in the garage and in the
countryside, to mention but a few sources. Science
teaching facilities and resources are all around us and just
waiting to be made use of.
In 220 pages the Unesco Source Book For Science Teaching
tells you how to do it. There are directions for making
general pieces of equipment such as balances, heat sources,
filters, pumps, tweezers, ring stands. Experiments and
material for the study of plants are described. Directions
for the study of animals tell how to make a collecting
cage, a wormery, homes for spiders and ants, aquariums.
Astronomy, meteorology, hydrology, machines, mass and
force, heat, sound, light, electricity, and magnetism are
covered by a wide range of simple, inexpensive apparatus
and revealing experiments. More than 300 diagrams
render the use of the volume very easy.
The Unesco Source Book For Science Teaching answers
the needs of teachers all over the world who clamour for
ways to plan and carry out science programmes in which
the subject is experienced and not just learned.
Paper : S 2.50; I2¡6 (stg.); 700 frs.
Cloth : S 3.00; 1 5¡-(stg.); 875 frs.
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment Is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER In any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzal, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C.I, Victoria. (A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 47, rue du Midi,
Brussels, C.CP. 338.000. (fr.b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
22, Place De Brouckère, CCP 285-98 ;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151,
Antwerp.
BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon,
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
I 00 Parsons Road P.O. Box 244, Colombo
2, (Rs.9)
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa,
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado 113, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckach, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box I 20, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris, T. C.CP. 12598-48.
(600 fr.)
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I ; 36a, Mount Road., Madras 2;
Kánson House, 24/ 1 Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi : Rajkamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2 Wel¬
lington Road Ballsbridge. Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35. Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street. Tel-Aviv. (£.l./4..)
ITALY. Librería Commissíonaria San-
soni. Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 950)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. - Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück. 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (600 fr.).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. CM. S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174. Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings,
plass 7. Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall. Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. Ti-49, Apartado de Correos
201 8, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co. .
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniania
Wydawnictw Naukowych PAN, Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724. Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescorädet. Vasagatan 15-17, Stoc¬
kholm, C (Kr. 7.50) other publications:
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. For The Unesco Courier only:
Georges Losmaz. I, rue des Vieux-Gre-
nadiers.Geneve.CCP. 1. 4811 (frs.S. 6.50)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Raidamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu. Istanbul.
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office. P.O. Box 569, London, S.E. I. ( I 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
ey are no
playing house
Youngsters are rarely enthu¬
siastic about letting mother clean
their ears, but baby Philippe
doesn't object. Philippe, a
chubby six pounds, is a baby doll
designed by a French school¬
teacher and made in London, and
he can open and close his eyes
and "eat" and "digest" real baby
food. He is the adopted child
of 300 French children aged
from three to six who are learn¬
ing housekeeping and baby care
in a Paris nursery schoolpart
of a novel French educational
experiment which is trying to
show that "it's never too early
to learn". (See story page 4.)
Photos r Gisèle Freund, Par»
]]>
</page>
</document>
