<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066121eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
\%y*
UNESCO photos
TOOLS FOR THE
SCIENCE TEACHER
Yugoslavia has set up a special centre
at Zagreb for the production of educa¬
tional equipment, including appliances
for science teaching in primary and
secondary schools. Unesco technical
assistance experts, sent to aid Yugo¬
slavia in carrying out its long-term
programme of educational reorganiza¬
tion and development, have helped
the centre to design and manufacture
'multi-purpose' science teaching ap¬
pliances which have lowered the cost
of equipping school laboratories.
Above and left, glass laboratory .
equipment and. a projection apparatus
being made at the Zagreb centre.
For ingenious ways to equip a
school laboratory with less-perfected,
'home-made' equipment, see page 21.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
FEBRUARY 1958
IITH YEAR
No. 2
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 KALINGA, ASOKA & THE AMLAKI FRUIT
4 THE DIVORCE OF SCIENCE & 'CULTURE'
A phenomenon of our time
By Bertrand Russell
5 BERTRAND RUSSELL, KALINGA PRIZE WINNER
6 THE ENIGMA OF SLEEP
A new column: "Science has the answer"
By Gerald Wendt
8 THE RISE OF THE NEW ELITES
Non-governmental organizations at work
By Alfred Metraux
10 SPINA: MYSTERY CITY OF THE ETRUSCANS
By Angelo Frontoni
16 HOW SPINA WAS DISCOVERED
By Prof. Nereo Alfieri
18 ISLAM IN WORLD HISTORY
By Marshall G.S. Hodgson
21 «DO IT YOURSELF' SCIENCE BOOK
Equipping school laboratories from the junk yard
24 'THE EARTH AS A PLANET'
New Unesco Travelling Science Exhibition
25 WHERE TO WRITE FOR PEN FRIENDS
26 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9 Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition, : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States oí America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y.. Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.121 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads " Reprinted Irom THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00 ; 10/- stg. ; 500 French francs or equi¬
valent.
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
COVER PHOTO
THE DISCUS THROWER, a bronze
figure surmounting an Etruscan can¬
delabrum unearthed at Spina, the
long-sought mystery city of the Etrus¬
cans which has at last been discovered
in the marshes of the Po Delta,
on Italy's Adriatic coast. (See page I 0)
© Angelo Frontoni
KALINGA, ASOKA &
THE AMLAKI FRUIT
It is a sad commentary on the educational methods
of the West that most Europeans and Americans
have never heard of the Emperor Asoka. Yet the
German scholar Carl Friedrich Koppen wrote: "If a man's
fame can be measured by the number of hearts who
revere his memory, by the number of lips who have
mentioned and still mention him with honour, Asoka is
more famous than Charlemagne or Caesar". Few
monarchs have been as powerful and none perhaps more
influential morally.
In his time, that is 2,200 years ago, Asoka's dominions
extended across the face of Asia from Afghanistan to
Indonesia. In 255 B.C. he invaded the ancient empire of
Kalinga on the southeast coast of India, and according to
the story that every educated Asian knows, he was so
appalled by the bloodshed and misery that his victory
entailed, that he vowed never again to wage war.
Not only did he dedicate himself to the cultivation of
peace but he embarked upon the mission of improving
the spiritual and material lot of his people. He spread
Buddhism throughout the East, yet there was tolerance
everywhere in his vast empire and any man could
practise his religion without hindrance. It was during
his reign that roads from one end of India to the other
were established. He founded hospitals and public
gardens and reputedly opened the first hospital for
animals in the world. He created a ministry for the.
advancement of backward peoples, and made special
provisions for the education of women.
The legend is told that one day, after having started
life anew as a strict follower of Buddha, he was trudging
on a road as a penniless monk, when a beggar beseeched
him for alms. Asoka had nothing but an amlaki fruit.
He broke it in two and gave the beggar half. When one of
India's most distinguished men of science, the late Sir
Jagadis Chunder Bose, built the Bose Institute in
Calcutta, he took great care to see that the amlaki fruit
was the principal ornament of its cornice.
The legend of Asoka and the amlaki fruit symbolizes
the principle on which science has stood for centuries.
All true scientists see it as their moral duty to give the
world all that they have learned through research to
give the amlaki fruit. This they do in hundreds of
scientific publications and thousands of papers read
annually before learned societies. In their international
gatherings scientists ask no questions about religion, race
or political creed. They accept one another for what they
can add to the sum total of human knowledge.
It was to mark this spirit of Asoka and of the empire
of Kalinga which saw its birth that Unesco in 1952
created the Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of
Science, awarded annually since then in recognition of
the work of leading interpreters of science and as a
means of strengthening the bonds between India and all
other nations on the common meeting ground of science.
The prize fund of £1,000 sterling is a personal donation
of Mr. B. Patnaik a member of the Legislative Assembly
of the Indian State of Orissa, and a director of the
Kalinga Foundation. On January 28, the Kalinga Prize
for 1957 was awarded to Bertrand Russell, 85-year-old
British scientist, philosopher and writer. (See page 4)
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A phenomenon of our time
THE DIVORCE
OF SCIENCE
& 'CULTURE'
by Bertrand Russell
There was a time when scientists looked askance at
attempts to make their work widely intelligible.
But, in the world of the present day, such an
attitude is no longer possible. The discoveries of modern
science have put into the hands of governments
unprecedented powers both for good and for evil. Unless
the statesmen who wield these powers have at least an
elementary understanding of their nature, it is scarcely
likely that they will use them wisely. And, in democratic
countries, it is not only statesmen, but the general public,
to whom some degree of scientific understanding is
necessary.
To insure wide diffusion of such understanding is by no
means easy. Those who can act effectively as liaison
officers between technical scientists and the public
perform a work which is necessary, not only for human
welfare, but even for bare survival of the human race.
I think that a great deal more ought to be done in this
direction in the education of those who do not intend
to become scientific specialists. The Kalinga Prize is
doing a great public service in encouraging those who
attempt this difficult task.
In my own country, and to a lesser degree in other
countries of the West, "culture" is viewed mainly, by an
unfortunate impoverishment of the Renaissance tradition,
as something concerned primarily with literature, history
and art. A man is not considered uneducated if he
knows nothing of the contributions of Galileo, Descartes
and their successors. I am convinced that all higher
education should involve a course in the history of science
from the seventeenth century to the present day and a
survey of modern scientific knowledge in so far as this
can be conveyed without technicalities. While such
knowledge remains confined to specialists, it is scarcely
possible nowadays for nations to conduct their affairs
with wisdom.
There are two very different ways of estimating any
human achievement: you may estimate it by what you
consider its .intrinsic excellence; or you may estimate it
by its causal efficiency in transforming human life and
human institutions. I am not suggesting that one of
these Ways of estimating is preferable to the other. I am
only concerned to point out that they give very different
scales of importance. If Homer and Aeschylus had not
existed, if Dante and Shakespeare had not written a line,
if Bach and Beethoven had been silent, the daily life of
most people in the present day would have been much
what it is. But if Pythagoras and Galileo and James Watt
had not existed, the daily life, not only of Western
Europeans and Americans but of Indian, Russian and
Chinese peasants, would be profoundly different from
what it is. And these profound changes are still only
beginning. They must affect the future even more than
they have already affected the present.
At present, scientific technique advances like an army
of tanks that have lost their drivers, blindly, ruthlessly,
Wadington Studios Ltd., London
without goal or purpose. This is largely because the men
who are concerned with human values and with making
life worthy to be lived, are still living in imagination in
the old pre-industrial world, the world that has been made
familiar and comfortable by the literature of Greece and
the pre-industrial achievements of the poets and artists
and composers whose Work we rightly admire.
The separation of science from "'culture" is a modern
phenomenon. Plato and Aristotle had a profound respect
for what was known of science in their day. The Re¬
naissance was as much concerned with the revival of
science as with art and literature. Leonardo da Vinci
devoted more of his energies to science than to painting.
The Renaissance architects developed the geometrical
theory of perspective. Throughout the eighteenth century
a very great deal was done to diffuse understanding of the
work of Newton and his contemporaries. But, from the
early nineteenth century onwards, scientific concepts and
scientific methods became increasingly abstruse and the
attempt to make them generally intelligible came more
and more to be regarded as hopeless. The modern theory
and practice of nuclear physicists has made evident with
dramatic suddenness that complete ignorance of the
world of science is no longer compatible with survival.
The above is the text of the address (with minor deletions)
delivered by Bertrand Russell, on receiving the Kalinga Prize, at
Unesco House, on January 28, 1958.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
BERTRAND RUSSELL,
KALINGA PRIZE
WINNER FOR 1957
Bertrand Russell the British philo¬
sopher, scientist and writer, who has
been awarded the Kalinga Prize for
1957, was born in 1872, and in the course
of his long career he has written more than
40 books, many of them dealing with
philosophy and mathematics.
In 1950 he received the Nobel Prize for
literature "'in recognition of his many-
sided and significant authorship, in which
he has constantly figured as a defender of
humanity and freedom of thought."
Perhaps his greatest and possibly his most
enduring book is the Principia Mathematica
(1910), in which he collaborated with the
late Alfred North Whitehead (afterwards
professor of philosophy at Harvard
University). Most of Bertrand Russell's
works have been widely translated. In
addition he has contributed to books edited
by others and has written numerous articles
and essays.
In 1944, returning to England after
living for several years in the United States,
he completed the book which has been
described as his "philosophical testament",
Human Knowledge: Its Scope and Its
Limits. Remarking on the enormous sweep
of this work, one critic observed: "All the
central issues in contemporary philosophy,
from the theory of meaning to the nature
of space-time are discussed with... char¬
acteristic incisiveness, technical skill and
imagination."
Lecturer at many universities he began
at the London School of Economics and
Political Science in 1896 Bertrand Russell
has captured the interest and admiration of
audiences from China to Chicago and from
Australia to Uppsala. He has received
awards from many learned societies,
including the Sylvester Medal of the Royal
Society and the Nicholas Murray Butler
Medal of Columbia University. In 1949
he was awarded the Order of Merit (an
exclusive British order, the ordinary
members of which do not exceed 24).
As mathematician and philosopher, he
developed an early interest in interpreting
science for general readers. One of his
earliest books was Essay on the Foundations
of Geometry. In 1903 came his first
important book, The Principles of Ma¬
thematics; in 1919 he published Introduction
to Mathematical Philosophy and in 1923,
The ABC of Atoms. Others of his books
to read: The ABC of Relativity, The
Analysis of Matter, The Prospects of
Industrial Civilization and A History of
Western Civilization.
His radio and TV broadcasts on
philosophic and scientific questions have
added greatly to the wide audience reached
by his writings. It was on one of these
occasions, which also marked his becoming
an octogenerian, that he declared
expressing the outlook of a man who has
spent his life in the search for truth
"I think one of the troubles of the world
has been the habit of dogmatically believing
something or other, and I think all these
matters are full of doubt and the rational
man will not be too sure he is right. I
think that we ought always to entertain our
opinions with some measure of doubt."
The Unesco Courler. February 1958
PREVIOUS AWARDS
1952 Louis de Broglie (France)
First winner of the- Kalinga Prize was Professor Louis de
Broglie, an internationally-famous figure both for research
in theoretical physics and for pioneer achievements In the
popularization of science. A Nobel Prize winner In physics
(1929) and permanent secretary of the French Academy of
Science, Louis de Broglie Is the discoverer of the fundamen¬
tal principles of wave mechanics. Among his books on
science which exist In English: Matter and Light, the new
physics; An Introduction to the Study of Wave Mechanics; The
Revolution in Physics, a non-mathematical survey of quanta.
1953 Huxley (United Kingdom)
Julian Huxley, who won the Kalinga Prize in 1953, was
Unesco's first Director-General (1946-48). He has been
an interpreter of scientific subjects through books, articles,
lectures, radio and films. As secretary of the London Zoolo¬
gical Society (1935-1942) he encouraged educational visits.
He has lectured widely on evolution, the biology of sex, the
social relations of science, and on zoological questions. Books
of Huxley's to read: The Individual in the Animal Kingdom, The
Stream of Life, Essays in Popular Science, Evolution and Ethics.
1954 - Waldemar Kaempffert (U.S.A.)
Winner of the Kalinga Prize in 1954, Waldemar Kaempffert
was for nearly 30 years science editor of The New York
Times, during which time he wrote his Influential two-
column Sunday feature, "Science in Review". One of the
organizers of the National Association of Science Writers, he
had both a profound influence on the quality of science
reporting in the U.S. and on the extensive use of specialized
science writers by American newspapers. He died last year.
Popular books of his to read: The ABC of Radio, Invention
and Society, Science Today and Tomorrow, Explorations in Science.
1955 Pi y Suñer (Venezuela)
An eminent scientist whose works and research in physiology
have won him honours in many countries, Dr. Augusto Pi
y Suñer held the chair of physiology at the University of
Caracas, Venezuela, and was Director of the University's
Institute of Experimental Medicine, when he was awarded
the 1955 Kalinga Prize. A firm believer that scientific
progress must be brought within public understanding,
Dr. Pi y Suñer has devoted many books and lectures to
the popularization of science. Two of his books in
English are: The Bridge of Life and Classics of Biology.
1956 George Gamow (U.S.A.)
A nuclear physicist, George Gamow is known both for his
studies in the field of theoretical physics, particularly In the
application of nuclear reactions to the evolution of stars
as well as for his books for the general public. His special
contribution to the non-scientific world has been through
books in which cosmology and nuclear physics have been
made Intelligible and absorbing to the layman. A trilogy
Birth and Death of the Sun, Biography of the Earth, and
Creation of the Universe brings to the reader in rich prose
and exciting narrative knowledge which the physicists
have discovered of the nature and origin of the universe.
UNESCO Photos
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
U.N. photo
Science has the answer
THE ENIGMA OF SLEEP
by Gerald Wendt
In this issue we present the first of a series of science columns in which matters
of general interest will be dealt with by Dr Gerald Wendt, Science Consul¬
tant of The Unesco Courier in the form of questions and answers. This
month Dr Wendt writes about some of the things people sometimes want
to know about sleep. This science column will appear from time to time.
No. The clock and the
time of night or day, as
such, have nothing to do
with the restfulness of
sleep. But it is true that
the deepest sleep and
the fullest rest come early in the sleeping period. This
has been proved by many experiments involving the
measurement of "brain waves" in an instrument called
Is it true that the
best sleep comes
before midnight ?
an encephalograph, which detects the small electric
currents that are set up by the activity of the brain. .
During the first hour after falling asleep these waves die
down to almost nothing but after two hours they stir again
and gradually come back to normal by the time the sleeper
wakes. Falling asleep has therefore been shown to be a
fast process, but most of an eight-hour sleep is
really a very slow awakening. Normally, of course, this
process of slow awakening takes place after midnight.
Since the exact nature
of the restorative process
in sleep is not understood,
it is also not ¡known
why about eight hours
is usually required to
complete it. At present
this is only an observed fact of nature, though the time
required is somewhat different for different people. It is
well known that Napoleon slept only a few hours at night
6
If Napoleon slept
only four hours a
night, why do most
people need eight ?
during periods of stress or crisis, but it is often suspected
and cannot be denied that he may have taken several
short "naps" by day to bring his total sleep up to perhaps
six hours. Each time he slept he took full advantage of
the first hour or two of sleep, then awakened rapidly and
did not waste his time in the slow process of gradual
awakening. But such a habit-pattern must be acquired
early in life. Any person who has already established an
eight-hour sleep pattern would find it very difficult to
convert his sleeping habits .to .the Napoleonic model.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Do elderly people This is true in tne sense
that older people are not
need less sleep than so active when awake, do
, not tire themselves so
young people do? muCh, and therefore
recover their strength
with less sleep. But the general impression, that older
people do not sleep much has a different cause and is
related to the legend about Napoleon's sleep. They do not
sleep very long at any one time but they sleep more often.
This has been explained by some authorities as a reversion
to the pattern of childhood, or even of infancy. A very
young infant has a rapid alternation of sleeping and
waking. He may wake after only two hours of sleep, then
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
has his milk and goes to sleep again. As he gets older the
periods grow longer and he has only four, two, and finally
only one sleeping period per day. With old age the process
is reversed, the periods grow shorter and very old people
may take four or even six short periods of sleep every
day. Thus it is quite natural that when an elderly person
says he is tired, he means that he wants to sleep soon
but does not mean that he wants to sleep a long time.
In fact, the same is true of eating. Old people cannot
eat much at one time but like to eat often. When an
old man says he is hungry, he wants to eat quickly but
he does not want a big meal. It is a good thing for the
family to understand that with the advance of old age
the life-pattern goes back to that of the early years.
What happens when
a person goes to sleep
slowly and gradually?
Different parts of the
body relax, one after
another, in a definite
pattern, but the process
may be fast or slow
in different people and
at different times. The first step must be the relaxing
of the intellect, the thinking process. After that the
large muscles of the legs and arms relax, then the
smaller ones of the hands and feet, finally the
very small muscles of the face and even the eyelids. This
is followed by a gradual relaxation of the senses. The
first to fade is the sense of sight, then hearing, then the
sense of touch and finally the internal nerves that feel
pain or discomfort. By that time the person is fully
unconscious and so asleep. The sequence is much the
same when a person becomes unconscious through the
action of drugs, including alcohol. The process is reversed
during awakening. Pain is both the most effective pre¬
ventative of sleep and the quickest awakener. It is easier
to awaken a sleeper by touching him than by talking to
him also more of a shock. It is easier to awaken him by
an unaccustomed or sudden noise than by shining a light
on him. But the gentlest awakening is by light, as by
letting in the daylight to a darkened room. After the eyes
are open there is often a short period before the large
muscles are revived and clear thinking does not usually
come until muscles are normal and the sleeper can stand.
If I move about in
my sleep, does it mean
I am not resting well ?
No. Occasional muscu¬
lar movements are normal
during sleep and do not
disturb the sleep pattern
as revealed by the ence-
phalograph. In fact, it has been found that muscles seem
to relax better if they change their position several times
during the eight or so hours of sleep. Sleep without any
movement whatever often results in a "stiff neck" or some
other sign of cramping or muscular fatigue, on waking.
Anyone who has had a
late dinner, or a large one
after the Continental
fashion, with a relaxed
evening following it, sel¬
dom has trouble going to
sleep. But those who
spend an active evening,
or an exciting one, or who
have been mentally active
after their meal, often
find it difficult to relax.
Their first need is to slow down the over-active
brain. This can be done by eating a light meal.
The reason is that the human body does not have enough
Some people seem to
fall asleep better if
they eat before going
to bed ; others say this
causes bad dreams.
Which is correct?
blood to keep all parts in full action at once. There are
three major areas to be nourished by the blood: the brain,
the digestive system, and the working muscles. It is
seldom possible, for anyone, to make good use of any two
of them at the same time. Thus putting a little food
into the stomach sends the blood there and takes it
away from the brain. So thinking or worrying are reduc¬
ed and the relaxed intellect helps in falling asleep.
However, if a heavy meal is eaten at bedtime, the sto¬
mach and digestive muscles have a period of hard work
to do. The sleeper cannot sleep comfortably because the
internal sensory nerves feel this muscle action and do
not relax. In this stage of partial sleep dreams are
common. The result is a nightmare. So a light meal
can induce sleep while a heavy one can disturb it.
In one series of tests,
made at the University of
Chicago, the movements
of the eyeballs were auto¬
matically recorded during
sleep and the sleepers
were occasionally awakened to tell of their dreams, if they
had any. Thus it was shown that eye movements, under
the closed lids, usually accompany dreams. When the
Does one dream all
night or only just
before awakening?
sleepers were awakened during a period of rapid eye move¬
ments they almost always remembered dreaming, but
when the eyes did not move there were no dreams. Judg¬
ing by this test, dreams occur at fairly regular intervals of
about an hour and a half, except during the first few
hours of deep sleep. Dreams are not instantaneous, as is
so often supposed, but dream-action goes on at about the
same rate as normal waking action. The dream is
remembered, only when it occurs just before awakening.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Non-governmental organizations and...
THE RISE OF THE NEW 'ELITES'
by Alfred Métraux
This is an era of great upheaval where
whole societies and deep-rooted
customs are being transformed at a
dizzying pace and in which countless
groups and organizations are at work to
forge a better world for tomorrow. Among
these is a vast array of several hundred
institutions which, though working quietly
and without fanfare for nearly a century,
have achieved remarkable results in the
field of international co-operation and un¬
derstanding.
Known as the international non-govern¬
mental organizations (abbreviated ngos)
they have mobilized enthusiasm and devo¬
tion at the grass-root level, and have built
an immense network of individual bonds
and contacts reaching across one nation to
another around the world. Since the
creation of the United Nations and its Spe¬
cialized Agencies the ngos have thrown the
full weight of their millions of members
behind the cause of peace to which the
U.N. is dedicated.
The objectives of the ngos are almost as
varied as their numbers are great for they
reach out to unite workers in factories and
fields, students in schools and universities,
scientists in laboratories, women in the pro¬
fessions and in the home. Many are con¬
cerned with education; other are devoted
to the struggle for certain human rights;
still others seek to unite the efforts of men
and women in improving the social and
economic conditions of underprivileged
communities.
Thus the non-governmental organizations
have become one of the great instruments
in fostering international understanding.
Through their study groups, their seminars
and international congresses they have
made it possible for large numbers of
people to become active participants instead
of just idle spectators in the great move¬
ments of our time. In a sense, I would
compare the role of the ngos today to that
played by many private organizations early
in the 19th century in the formation of the
Confederation of Switzerland when it was
as divided as are the great States of today.
Anthropologists who have made a study
of the cultural changes taking place in the
so-called underdeveloped countries have
pointed to the highly important and even
paramount role played by religious missions
and organizations in the transformations we
are now witnessing. It is to these missions
in many cases that we owe the first intro¬
duction of modern technology which was
to modify the economy of entire regions,
and the early education and training of
local '"élites" who were later to become
the leaders in the forefront of their
country's progress.
Similar work has been done by many
non-governmental organizations. With the
means at their disposal in their different
domains the ngos too have made their con¬
tribution to the efforts being made for the
rapid industrialization of the lesser-
advanced, poverty-stricken lands. But
anyone who has had anything to do with
technical development programmes be he
an educator, a doctor or an engineer
sent into the field by a government agency
or an international technical assistance ser¬
vice knows that all these efforts will be
wasted time and money unless local men
and women are trained in the areas assisted
so that they are equipped to take over and
to continue the job begun.
This is the real crux of the problem of
technical advancement in the underdeve¬
loped countries. The training of local
leaders in underdeveloped areas is one of
the sine qua non conditions for progress.
No economic aid or education campaign by
itself can raise the standard of living in
these countries unless an opportunity is
provided at the same time for leaders to
emerge from the great mass of the popu¬
lation so that a new "élite" can be formed
alongside the old one still clinging to
traditional ways.
In 1954 Unesco launched the first of a
series of large-scale enquiries into the
problems faced by new African "élites" in
the regions south of the Sahara. These
investigations continued for a period of
four years, until 1957, and have been
followed with deep interest by the non¬
governmental organizations, particularly
those which have leader-training pro¬
grammes for underdeveloped countries.
The emergence of a class of professional
people and technicians in lands which only
a few years ago were qualified as
"primitive" or "archaic" is a social and
cultural phenomenon of paramount im¬
portance. So much so that all studies
made of the social effects of industriali-
AROUND THE WORLD in commu¬
nities which are undergoing industria¬
lization, people are being selected
and trained as leaders. Many of the
non-governmental organizations colla¬
borating with Unesco are helping to
train these new "élites." Right, con¬
gress attended by members of the
C.V.T.C. (A confederation of Christian
Trade Unions in Vietnam, with some
600,000 members). The C.V.T.C. pro¬
vides its members with fellowships
to complete their training in foreign
countries, and is affiliated to the Inter¬
national Conferation of Christian Trade
Unions, a non-governmental organiza¬
tion which has consultative arrange¬
ments with Unesco. Far right, a
lesson for the village elders in West
Africa. An African forest ranger gives
them advice on how to make better
use of trees and local forest products.
C.I.S.C
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
zation and urbanization have highlighted
the preponderant role played by this new
group. And there can be no doubt that
the ultimate success of programmes of
fundamental education, aiming to achieve
the general raising of living standards in
an area, hinges directly on the efforts of
those individuals who make up the "élite".
I should point out that the use of the
word "élite" has been the subject of criti¬
cism in certain circles. It seems to conjure
up the notion of an exclusive, clannish
"club" which has voluntarily set itself apart
from the rest of the population. To the
sociologist, however, the word has a diffe¬
rent meaning. It has none of the deroga¬
tory connotations some people give it; on
the contrary, it suggests not only the
positive idea of excellence or merit in a
specific field of endeavour but also the
capacity to exert influence and encourage
emulation. The word is applied to people
who, because of the position they hold,
lead the community to which they belong
onto a well-defined road of action. It is
thus often synonymous with the word
"leaders" or the French term "cadres".
Lost love of the soil
Many international organizations are
eager to train leaders who will be
equipped to work for the goals they
have set themselves. But such training
poses numerous problems. In February
1947 the non-governmental organizations
(with help from Unesco) began an inquiry
in which all ngos were asked to des¬
cribe their methods of recruiting, the type
of training offered, and particularly the
problems and difficulties encountered.
(The findings of this inquiry are to be re¬
ported to the next conference of ngos in
June)
Some of the difficulties already noted
by the ngos are well known to those who
have had experience with the transition of
a people from one form of culture to
another. When an organization recruits
men or women to be trained as future
leaders of their community, it is quickly
confronted with the great differences noted
in the cultural background and schooling
of candidates. Once this hurdle is over¬
come and the organization arranges to
provide a candidate with the best possible
training (usually at great cost) the student
very often refuses to return home, prefer-
ing the new environment into which he has
become assimilated.
Then there is the problem of readjust¬
ment at home. A young man (the same
holds true for women) who has gone
abroad with the aid of an organization,
finds on his return that he no longer fits
into his community and has become an
"outsider". Sometimes the mere fact of
bringing villagers to a big city spells the
end of their interest in the soil, and is
enough to make them look down their
noses at anything that smacks of village
customs. Whereas many organizations, in
training persons from the underdeveloped
countries for a fuller and richer life, do so
with the idea that the knowledge gained
will be used by these persons for the
greater good of their countrymen, they
find instead that promising leaders quickly
disappear into administrative offices, poli¬
tics or ordinary business concerns.
This problem is considered in many ngo
reports which recognize of course that it
is hardly unnatural for a young person
trained for leadership to feel strong twinges
of anguish at the thought of "burying"
himself in tribal or village work. This
demands an idealism and missionary spirit
that is obviously a rarity. Various solutions
have been put forward as a remedy. One
proposes that better material conditions and
advantages be made available to native-
born leaders ; another perhaps more
important, that continual and closer contact
be maintained by sponsoring organizations
with leaders in order to bolster the morale
of those disheartened or ready to abandon
their work.
It has been observed that leaders trained
in their native country usually prove better
adapted to their missions than those sent
abroad. Then, too, it has been found that
persons who have experienced life in the
industrial world are often inclined to be
British Official Photo
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
much more severely critical and contemp¬
tuous of their own people than strangers.
Hence a special effort is needed to instil in
them patience and tolerance toward their
countrymen.
It is not surprising that many of the
ngo reports received by Unesco speak of
conflicts that have arisen between different
generations, to the dismay and consterna¬
tion of many leaders. The rift between old
and new ways of life is the source of deep-
drawn differences between members of the
same family. Young women in many
countries of the Orient, for instance, today
work in factories but their mothers still
go outdoors swathed in their veils. Many
international organizations are conscious of
this problem and hope to solve it with
tact and patience.
A lesson of real democracy in action
emerges form the replies to the ngo enquiry
into their work with the new "élites".
One ngo states: "Our relations are founded
on mutual understanding and the desire to
face up to the needs of the local environ¬
ment." A women's association in West
Africa reports how both White and Negro
women have joined efforts to work for
healthy surroundings and a richer home
life, and that between its members of
different races there is complete co-opera¬
tion with no trace of any feeling of su¬
periority or inferiority.
The non-governmental organizations have
an immense educational achievement to
their credit. Everywhere schools, study
groups, seminars, have been set up for the
free exchange of ideas and the widening
of mental horizons. Thousands of students
from the less favoured nations have been
educated in Western schools and universi¬
ties, »thanks to their aid. By breaking
down the barriers which formerly prevented
contact between people with sharply differ¬
ing backgrounds, the non-governmental or¬
ganizations are participating actively as well
as effectively in the vast undertaking now
commonly known as Technical Assistance.
Sceptics scoff & shrug
There are sceptics who like to shrug
their shoulders and scoff at what
they consider the naive enthusiasm of
the men and women working for these or¬
ganizations. They have apparently for¬
gotten that it is this same faith in humanity
and in the value of education that has
helped to change the face of the earth. The
industrialization of Africa, of Asia and of
vast regions in the Americas cannot be
achieved in a vacuum. It is precisely be¬
cause this is so that so many international
organizations have set out to prepare the
people of these areas for the new technolo¬
gical age which will soon be upon them
(with all that this implies), so that they are
not crushed by the force of its sudden im¬
pact.
It would certainly be useful if the non¬
governmental organizations one day prepar¬
ed an account of their contribution to the
development of these new societies. They
would no doubt be surprised themselves to
discover the large numbers of leaders of
every kind indebted to them and the scope
of the great changes in traditional life for
which they have been responsible. But no
such survey is likely to be forthcoming in
the near future. Most of the ngos are
more concerned with the work ahead of
them than with a retrospective self-pat-on-
the-back. Such a survey of their achieve¬
ments will probably have to wait until a
historian or sociologist undertakes the job.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
) Prof. Vitale Valvassori, Milan
AIR PHOTOS PIERCE
NATURE'S CURTAIN
Dead for nearly two thousand years,
swallowed up in the swamplands of the Po
Delta, the once-flourishing port and city of
Spina has now been brought to light by the
patient questing of scientists and archaeolo¬
gists, and in particular through excavations
directed since 1953 by Professor Nereo
Alfieri. Mobilized with other instruments
and techniques in the search for the hidden
city was the all-seeing eye of the aerial
camera. Air-photography revealed Roman
remains (above) in the area. Light-coloured
strips forming geometrical patterns mark
emplacements of walls where little or no
vegetation grew. Long diagonal strip, to
right of shadow cast by photographic plane, is
a modern canal. Spina itself (right) has both
modern drainage canals (light-coloured) and
ancient ones (darker-coloured from more
luxuriant vegetation growing in the fertile
soil). Light-coloured rectangles bisected by
the old canals mark the ancient "city-
blocks" of the Etruscan port. Top of opposite
page, treasure trove of objects found in
Spina's burial grounds. Each tomb has
something to tell of a people whose culture,
art and customs have in turn astonished the
most cultured nations of every epoch.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
© Angelo Frontoni,
by Angelo Frontoni
© 1958. Reproduction prohibited
ne of the strangest and most
I puzzling stories of all the
peoples of the Ancient World is
that of the Etruscans. For centuries scholars and
archaeologists have tried in vain to clear up the mystery
surrounding this "riddle race" which, after rising to
prosperity and power on the Italian peninsula, vanished
completely from the stage of history, leaving unsolved
many problems concerning its origin, civilization and
language and its incomparable art.
The history of the Etruscans is like a book which has
been written and then erased." A brilliant and industrious
people, they left evidence of an advanced and flourishing
civilization in many areas of Italy between the plains of
the River Po and the Campagna, dating from before the
rise of, Rome to the early days of the Roman Republic.
Yet our. knowledge of them is still no more than
fragmentary.
Most historians think that the Etruscans originally
came from the East (from Lydia the ancient name for a
district on the West coast of Asia Minor). According to
Varro, the Roman author and antiquarian of the 1st
century B.C., the Etruscans arrived in Italy in the 11th
century B.C., but how they did so is not definitely known.
Those who favour, the theory of their Eastern origin point
to the fact that the oldest of the artistic remains they left
in Italy are in the Oriental style while those from their
middle period show a Greek influence.
The Etruscans, who called themselves Raseni, were
known to the Greeks as Tyrrhenoi (Tyrrhenians) . At first
they were ruled by kings (lars) but they later formed
three great confederations, each governed by a lucumon.
Their principal cities were Arezzo, Bolsena, Cerveteri,
Chiusi, Cortona, Perugia, Roselle, Tarquinia, Veio, Vetulo-
nia and Volterra. When they made their appearance in
Tuscany in the 8th century B.C., the Etruscans already
possessed a rich culture, a fully-developed and expressive
language, and their own philosophy and religion. Their
decline began in the 5th century B.C.; they were defeated
in a great sea battle by the Syracusans in 474 B.C., the Po
Confederation was occupied by the Gauls and the
Campagnan by the Samnites. The battle of the
Valdimonian Lake (309 B.C.) finally extinguished Etruscan
independence.
Since then, the task of tracing their origins, both
geographical and cultural, has been a challenge to men
of science and letters. From early times stories have been
told of a seaport named Spina once the metropolis
of art and culture in the ancient Etruscan Empire. Down
the centuries the greatest of scholars and archaeologists
have searched unsuccessfully for the site of
this city somewhere in the Po Delta on the
Adriatic. Recorded in the literature of Clas¬
sical Greece are references to Spina which
is pictured as a powerful and prosperous
Adriatic port in the days of the old empire
Cont'd
next page
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
SPINA (Continued)
SUNK WITHOUT TRACE
BENEATH A LAGOON
For centuries archaeologists and scholars searched
vainly for the lost city of Spina. In 1956 it was
finally located some three miles to the West of
Comacchio in the Province of Ferrara. In pre-
Roman times part of the land here was above the
level of the Comacchio Lagoon. Later it subsided,
taking with it the remains of the Etruscan city.
and recognized as a significant factor in the Etruscan
influence on Greek art.
Finally, in 1922, searches in the Po region revealed the
existence of a Graeco-Etruscan burial-ground along the
course of the Trebba in the Comacchio lagoon. This in
Itself was a discovery of immense value and it at once
raised hopes that the remains of Spina might also be
unearthed. Excavations in the Trebba Valley continued
until 1935, but although 1,250 tombs were uncovered, no
trace was found of the elusive city. Then, partly because
of the difficulties of working in this muddy, swampy
terrain, operations were halted.
Following the reclamation of the Po region work began
again in 1953 under the direction of the Italian
archaeologist, Professor Nereo Alfieri. Convinced that
Spina had actually existed, he made the search for the
hidden city his life's work. Methodically he followed the
course of the Trebba and then searched in the adjacent
Pega Valley Where he eventually came across another
Etruscan cemetery. This was located on the far side of
a silted-up waterway which had once probably been the
branch of a river perhaps Spina's actual harbour.
This second discovery encouraged Professor Alfieri to
extend his operations around both cemeteries, for the
ancient peoples always fixed their burial-grounds within
sight of their dwellings. . Thus, when the cemeteries were
found to date from the same period the arrangement of
the tombs, the funeral rites and the decorations were
identical in both places the search for the city itself was
pursued with growing optimism.
The discovery of the Pega Valley burial-ground had been
a rich recompense for Professor Alfieri's efforts. But his
ultimate goal was to find the dead city of Spina soothe
search continued.
This tenacity of purpose was rewarded in 1956 when
workers uncovered the first traces of a prize which had
eluded searchers for 2,000 years one of Spina's palafittes
(dwellings built on piles). Professor Alfieri was thus able
to determine the site of the lost city, of which practically
nothing was known, except through casual references to
it by Pliny and Strabo, and whose very existence had so
often been denied. He was also able to fix the age of
this first palafitte (6th century B.C. or somewhat earlier)
from a vase found inside it of unmistakably 6th century
B.C. origin. To uncover the whole of this fabulous city
will take at least twenty years.
As an Adriatic port on the Po delta, Spina was a gateway
to the whole of the then known world. To its quays came
amber, brought down by river from the Baltic lands; it
received and transhipped to the Orient the products of
the flourishing Etruscan metal industry while in return
it received cargoes of Attic pottery, cloth, Oriental
products of all kinds, rare woods from Egypt, perfumes,
rich Phoenician textiles and oil from Palestine. Spina
was a great port and warehouse, the "Genoa" or "Mar¬
seilles" of an increasingly prosperous and flourishing
empire, and a door through which passed the Greek
influence on Etruscan art and culture. Relations between
these two peoples were close and friendly: Greek artistic
influence is manifest in the objects found in Spina's
burial-grounds just as Etruscan Influence on the Greeks
is visible in the examples of pure Etruscan art discovered
in Greek cities in Southern Italy and in Greece itself.
The port of Spina was originally only about two
miles from the sea and was reached by a navigable
channel formed by an arm of the Po, known as the Spineto
or Spino. But the forward advance of the shoreline, by a
process of sanding and silting up, progessively increased
the distance between city and sea. In the 4th century
B.C. they were already 20 stadia apart (three and a half
km., or nearly two and a quarter miles,
working on the Attic stadium of 177.5
metres) and by the Augustan Age (roughly
the start of the Christian era) the village
built over the ruins of Spina was 90 stadia
(16 km. or 10 miles) inland. Pliny the
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
PUMPING OUT TOMB 67
Excavating the tombs in Spina's burial-
grounds has been a difficult business because
of the water-logged state of the soil in this
recently drained swampland. Excavating
teams now work inside open metal caissons
which are sunk around the tombs and then
drained by constantly working pumps (photo,
opposite page). Above, in "Tomb 67" a
broken vase is recovered from its shroud
of mud. The Ancients believed that after
death the soul travelled far through the
underworld and they therefore provided
their departed with all they would need on
the journey. Left, restoration work on
objects found in the tombs. From finds
at Spina, the National Museum at Ferrara
has assembled the most comprehensive
existing collection of Attic black-and-red
pottery from the 6th to the 5th century B.C.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
SPINA (Continued)
DRINKING GOBLET (Cratère) of a style known as "Upper Adriatic"
and dating from the first half of the 4th century B.C. Like all objects
shown on these pages and on pages 16 and 17, it was found at Spina.
'MODERN ART' some 2,400 years old. The form of this wine vessel
(Oinochoe) and the portrait decorating it might easily be the work of a
modern ceramic artist, not one who lived nearly twenty-five centuries ago.
DUCK-SHAPED FLASK (ASKOS) DATING FROM THE 4TH CENTURY B.C. WINGED FEMALE FIGURE DECORATING IT IS
14
"LASA"
© Angelo Frontoni.
AN ETRUSCAN DIVINITY.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
) Angelo Frontoni
BRONZE DANCER HOLDING CASTANETS SURMOUNTS THIS 5TH CENTURY B.C. ETRUSCAN CANDELABRUM. ETRURIA BOASTED A THRIVING METAL INDUSTRY.
ANIMAL-SHAPED FLASKS (ASKOI), USED TO STORE PRECIOUS BALMS AND OINTMENTS. ARE EXAMPLES OF THE POTTER'S ART DATING FROM THE 4TH CENTURY B.C.
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
SPINA (Continued from page I 2)
FREED FROM A SHROUD OF MUD
Elder, who lived four centuries after Spina's greatest
prosperity, had provided a clue to the location of
the vanished city when he recorded that the most
southerly channel of the delta, the Euridano (Vatrenus),
had also once been known as the "Spinetice".
The discovery of Spina is one of the great triumphs of
modern archaeology. It has, for example, provided
confirmation for theories which were largely speculative.
Moreover, the discoveries have dealt a serious blow to the
views of certain archaeologists who declared that the
reason why no Etruscan temples or palaces had been
found was that they were built of wood and terracotta
and their carvings executed in sandstone all of these
being materials unlikely to resist the ravages of time.
The Etruscans were, in fact, great builders (as proved by
the ruins of their massive stone constructions) and they
were the first people in Italy to use the arch, the vault
and the dome.
. The story of Alfieri's search for and discovery of Spina
is one of a never-ending struggle against two stubborn
elements of nature: earth and water. Over the years the
waters had drowned the city and silt had buried it;
nature, with man's help, had also advanced the delta
several miles towards the sea. But as time goes on and
men dig away Spina's muddy shroud, the secrets hidden
In the city for more than 2,000 years will gradually be
revealed. Meanwhile the excavation of its graves enables
us to picture its people and to understand their mode of
life, for each new tomb discovered has something to tell
us of a people whose culture, art and customs have
astonished the most cultured nations of every age.
Daily life is mirrored
in every ancient tomb
Daily life is mirrored in the darkness of the graves
because of the Ancients' belief that death entailed a
long journey by the soul through the underworld.
Thus, even the tomb of a poor man contains some modest
furnishing for the journey in the other world, be it no
more than a bowl for food and drink. Those of the
wealthy are rich with precious urns, offerings and means
of distraction such as dice. In others tools and working
implements reveal the professions or trades the dead had
followed in their lifetimes. There are tombs of great
ladies with trinkets of amber and ivory, mirrors, and vases
of delicate colour and design; children's tombs full of gifts
and toys, including clay dolls with jointed arms and legs.
Through all these relics of the dead we can almost
picture Spina as it once existed alongside its channel to
the sea, its ships, their sails filling to the wind, outward
bound with rare and precious cargoes for the fabulous
city-ports of the East, for Venetia, Umbria, Phoenicia and
Greece. Here are objects evoking the glorious days of
the empire, when Etruria was mistress of the seas, with
a trade so rich that some of its profits were used to build
á splendid treasure-house at the shrine of Delphi in
Greece. Then Spina was abandoned by its citizens* in
their headlong flight from the Gallic invaders, and when
our own era began, Spina's glories had perished; there
remained only a humble village.
Perhaps the secret of the people who gave so much
remarkable art and culture to the ancient -world is waiting
to be discovered in Spina. Many riddles indeed await
solution. For example, small progress has been made in
interpreting the Etruscan language, little of which came
down to us through Greek or Roman writers. Though an
abundance of funerary inscriptions exists (some 800), it
has only been possible to understand the meaning of a
few words. After a great effort, the alphabet written
from right to left, and derived, like all the Italic alphabets,
from the Greek was reconstructed, but we know nothing
more of this language that could tell us about the people
and its civilization so obviously advanced, yet so shrouded
in mystery. Already though, the burial grounds of Spina
have opened our eyes to a vision of art and culture which
have survived the years and even the efforts of man and
nature to efface them from history.
16
ATHLETIC FIGURE, crowning a bronze
candelabrum, carries a discus in the left hand
a work by a 5th century B.C. craftsman.
HOW SPINA
AS DISCOVERED
by Professor Nereo Alfieri
The Pega Valley is a lagoon area some four miles west of
Comacchio in the Province of Ferrara, on the Adriatic
coast of northern Italy. The discovery in this region of the
necropolis and residential quarters of the great city of Spina was
made possible by the use of two distinct excavation techniques.
The unearthing of the cemetery posed a dual problem: first the
actual location of the various tombs, second the adoption of
adequate excavation measures.
From the outset, both a scientific and '"hit-and-miss" method
were applied in locating the tombs. The scientific method
consisted of a methodical study of the historical geography of the
region, that is, a reconstitution of the Po delta as it was at the
time of Spina's glory. This was extremely important for, whereas
the entire plain known as the Pega Valley is now about three feet
below sea level, in ancient pre-Roman times portions of the land
rose above the waters of the lagoon.
In order to determine the precise areas above water at that
remote time, a number of techniques were resorted to: direct
examination of the nature of the soil; a critical analysis of literary
sources of the classical and mediaeval periods, micro-survey
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
MYTHOLOGICAL HERO. This figure is believed to represent
Achilles cutting off a lock of hair to lay on the grave of his friend,
Patroclus, who, according to Homer's Iliad, was slain by Hector.
Khotos © Angelo Frontoni
CLOAKED MAN forms the centrepiece of a
candelabrum, the entire work being cast In
bronze. Etruscans were famed metal workers.
procedures (surveying and analysis of the minutest undulations of
the ground) and air photography. A comparative study of all
these elements combined made it possible to localize the patches
of dry land, or maritime sand dunes, which had existed in the
lagoon area in ancient times. There can be no doubt that only
in these patches was the construction of' tombs possible during
pre-Roman times.
The exact site of the tombs was located by the hit-and-miss
technique of soundings. These soundings were made on the
patches of land, identified as formerly above the water level, by
means of a rod six feet in length thrust into the ground at four-
inch intervals until an obstruction was encountered. In almost
every case this obstruction turned out to be a tomb.
In the search for the city itself the same scientific principles
used to locate the necropolis were employed: identification of the
dry land in' the lagoon during ancient times plus a careful
pinpointing of Roman or mediaeval settlements on these dry
patches. Our investigations were based on what scientists call the
"law of persistent habitation", according to which man tends to
build dwellings where former urban communities existed, even
after these have completely vanished. Thus the lost city of Spina
was likely to be found on a site where Roman or mediaeval
agglomerations had later established themselves. A comparative
analysis of all the archaeological discoveries and of mediaeval
references led me to conclude that the church of Santa Maria in
Pado Vetere (i.e. on the Old Po) built over a pagan temple, was
the most interesting area in our search for Spina. As a matter of
fact, air photographs of the zone, later made by Professor
Valvassori, revealed the outlines of the harbour quarter of Spina
not more than 330 yards from the location of an ancient commu¬
nity named Pieva.
This patient and methodical investigation was perhaps the only
way in which the marshland could have been induced to give up
the secret of the city it had hidden for so many centuries. It may
seem surprising that the most primitive procedures (such as rod
soundings undoubtedly are) were used in combination -with air pho¬
tography, a modern technique. More surprising may appear the
failure to use even more modern techniques evolved in recent
years. New archaeological research methods, for example, have
been successfully applied by professor CM. Lerici, of the Poli¬
técnico of Milan, in locating Etruscan tombs in the Tyrrhenian
region of Central Italy (the area of Tarquinia north of Rome).
Among his methods are: 1) electrical sensitivity prospecting: an
electric current is used to measure the changes in the resistance of
the soil, the charge differing if a tomb or other structure buried
underground is encountered. This method is commonly used by
geologists and other scientists in prospecting for oil, underground
water or minerals and to study sub-soil in dam construction.
2) photographic soundings: the soil is perforated and a special tiny
camera, equipped with an electronic flash, is lowered by cable into
the interior of the tomb. The photographs taken at different levels
reveal the nature of the discovery and the state of conservation of
the objects long before the first pickaxe is used to open up the
tomb.
Lerici's methods, however, were not found applicable in the
case of Spina where the tombs are slab-covered graves almost
flush with the surface of the soil. Electric sensitivity prospecting
was tried in 1954 -without results. A mine detector had some
success since it reacted to the electromagnetic fields in tombs
containing iron objects; but nothing deeper than two feet was
recorded. In Spina we therefore relied on the old hit-and-miss
methods, trusting to the skill and ingenuity of the local labourers
who are unsurpassed when it comes to working in marshland mud.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
iela m
IN WORLD HISTORY
by Marshall G.S. Hodgson
Lecturer and Research Associate in the Committee on
Social Thought, University of Chicago
When Mohammed first preached Islam, in a rather
Obscure part of the Arabian peninsula in the
seventh century C.E., the other major religions had
already penetrated, among them, most of the civilized
lands of the Eastern Hemisphere. Christianity prevailed
in the Mediterranean Basin, Zoroastrianism in Iran,
Hinduism in India and the southeast, Buddhism and
Taoism in the Far East. There seemed little room for a
new religion; and indeed Mohammed did not claim that
Islam was new. He believed he was bringing the same
message from God that Moses and Jesus had brought to
the Jews and the Christians of old: that God alone was to
be worshipped, that His will was to be obeyed as made
known through His prophets, and that at the Last Judg¬
ment the disobedient would be punished and the be¬
lievers rewarded in Paradise.
The Jews and Christians, Mohammed believed, had
corrupted this simple message, and in Islam the purity
of God's truth was restored. In contrast to the na¬
tions around them, the Arabians, pagans till then, were
now offered the uncorrupted truth in their own language
in the Koran. Within Mohammed's lifetime the greater
part of Arabia offered him its obedience as God's Prophet,
and the formerly feuding Arabians were forged into a
strong new society on the basis of Islam.
At its beginning, then, Islam had the appearance of a
reformed version of the Jewish-Christian faith, adapted
to the local needs of the Arabian tribes. It would have
been hard to guess, then, that it was to play so great a
role in the world: first in the creation of a great Middle
Eastern empire, the Caliphate; then, when the Caliphate
broke up, as basis for the most powerful international
civilization of the mediaeval world; and finally in our time
as a world religion which is by some standards the most
widely distributed of all faiths. In the Middle Ages
Muslims believed themselves to be on the way to taking
over the whole world and turning it into a single divinely
guided society. They came nearer to uniting the world
than we usually realize; and the brotherhood of Islam
still provides one of the most active ideals at work among
mankind.
When the Arabian tribes were brought together by
Islam into a single state, they quickly burst the bounds of
Arabia, and within decades found themselves masters of
the Middle East, heirs to half the Roman Empire and the.
whole of the Persian. At first Islam was the badge of
the ruling Arabs; but the subject peoples Christians,
Jews, Zoroastrians, Buddhists were not slow in adopting
the new and dynamic creed, sometimes despite the
objections of the Arabs, many of whom preferred to keep
their privileged faith for themselves.
Within two centuries Islam had become the predominant
religion in most of the lands ruled by the Arab Caliphate,
while the Arabic language had become the common vehicle
of its burgeoning cultural and commercial life. In this
way a great civilization, with its own literary, artistic, and
intellectual traditions, was built around the Muslim faith.
When the Caliphate broke up in the tenth century the
civilization remained, to be carried round the world and
enriched by the various Islamic peoples.
This civilization was now given its social unity no longer
by a single state and a single language Persian soon
became an international cultural language rivalling
Arabic, and in time many other languages became
important locally but by a single system of sacred law.
18
This law covered in principle
every aspect of personal life
etiquette and ritual and be¬
lief as well as points of contract
or of inheritance. Though not
all parts of the sacred law were
equally applied among all
Muslim peoples, it produced
enough uniformity in essentials
to make it possible for a Muslim
from any country to have
citizenship rights throughout
the Dâr al-Islâm, the territory
under Muslim rule.
A learned man from Morocco,
travelling to see the world,
might be made a judge when
he lived for a time in India as
easily as if he were in his own
country thousands of miles
away. At the yearly pilgrimage
to Mecca, Muslims from the
most distant lands met and
might share their concerns.
With such relatively free inter¬
change, Islamic culture, though
it was diverse from country to
country, maintained a common
heritage in all its forms. Thus
in its exquisite grace the Taj
Mahal reflects Indian traditions
differing widely from those of
the Balkans or of North Africa;
but it was as obviously built for
Muslims as any mosque in
Istanbul or Tunis.
The culture which such ef¬
fectively flexible institutions
fostered was worthy of them.
Straddling the crossroads of the
world, the Islamic society was
in a position to gather its in¬
spiration from most of the ci¬
vilizations that had arisen be¬
fore it. It did not fail to do so;
but whatever it learned from the past it made its own,
and generally improved.
Apart from the grand simplicity of the religion itself,
its glory was in its literature, especially its poetry. This
grew out of the classical genius of pre-Islamic Arabia,
which Muslims never ceased to respect, but which in
Islamic times achieved far greater amplitude and variety.
The untranslatable subtlety of Arabic verse and the
versatile sweetness of the Persian poets have inspired local
literatures wherever Islam has gone.
More accessible to outsiders have been the splendours
of its visual arts. In painting and architecture were
mingled the traditions of pre-Islamic Iran going back to
ancient Mesopotamia and those of the Graeco-Roman
world. The lovely miniatures of Persia and India owe
much of their grace to the further addition of a Chinese
influence; the architecture has owed much, here or there,
to Byzantine or Hindu examples. But, above all in
architecture, the strength and precision of Islamic art,
its delicacy combined with uncompromising orderliness,
are fully its own.
\
Projection by A.K. Philbrick,
copyright 1951
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
APPROXIMATE SCALE ON THE HORIZONTAL AXIS
Muslims proved industrious scholars, and notably
indefatigable historians. Above all must be mentioned
their natural science. The Muslims inherited a formidable
body of learning from the classical Greeks philosophy
and logic from Plato and Aristotle, mathematics,
astronomy, and medicine from Euclid and Ptolemy,
Hippocrates and Galen, and the rest. To this inheritance
they joined much of the results of Sanskrit learning
including the use of the zero. They then accumulated
a wealth of further data: astronomical observations which
helped prepare the way for the acceptance of the
Copernican theory, alchemical experiments which much
enlarged the realm of chemistry, algebraic solutions,
geographical data, philosophical problems, botanical
discoveries, medical techniques. The age of creative
Islamic science did not last so long as that of creative art;
.after five or six centuries the Muslim peoples ceased to
produce much that was new. Yet the scientific heritage
did not cease to discipline the minds of cultivated Muslims
everywhere.
In the course of the centuries the Muslim faith, and
with it the Islamic culture, was spread far beyond the old
limits of the Caliphate by the preaching of merchants
and mystics, or by the prestige or force of conquering
monarchs. In some areas, as in China, though many
were converted to Islam the Muslims never gained power.
In most parts Muslim rule spread at least as fast as the
Muslim faith. Islam had been first established in the
Middle East, and Muslim rulers there long made it a point
to carry Islam into the two great populous regions on
each side, Europe and India. India proved the more
vulnerable and by 1300 Muslim rule had been momentarily
extended almost to its southern tip; on the other hand,
by 1529 and again in 1683 the Ottoman Turks were
besieging Vienna in the heart of Europe. In other
directions Islamization was perhaps less romantic, but
more lasting. As can be seen from the map (see page 20),
by 1500 Islam dominated much of northern Africa and of
Central Eurasia, and the coastlines around
the Indian Ocean.
Even where they did not convert or
conquer, the Muslims had an important
cultural influence. Thus in Africa, peoples
which had not yet accepted Islam often
Cont'd
on
next page
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ISLAM
(Continued) One-sixth of mankind
adapted elements of Muslim practice to their own
cultures. In most parts of India even Hindu courts
recognized the excellence of Indo-Muslim culture. Islamic
handicrafts and art objects were eagerly received
everywhere; and in lands as far apart as Western Europe
and China, till the end of the Middle Ages astronomy and
the other sciences were studied in large part from Muslim
masters. It might easily have been supposed that Islam,
from its central position, was destined to unite the Old
World under its own leadership.
In the midst of this expansion the West Europeans,
emerging from relative obscurity, upset all expectations.
In the generation of about 1500 the Europeans proved
themselves masters of the oceans: of the Atlantic and
Pacific, together with a New World which lay between
them; and even of the Indian Ocean, the great highway
of Islamic trade, after a sharp struggle with the Muslims
concerned. During the following centuries, while some
khanates fell before the advancing Russians, elsewhere
the Dâr al-Islâm continued to gain ground in the Sudan
and Turkestan, in India and Malaysia, and even in Europe.
But within the West radical transformations were taking
place, intellectual, social, and economic, which were to
mark an epoch for all mankind. The Europeans, the first
to undergo the effects of these transformations, came to
have a greatly disproportionate power as compared with
other peoples, and especially in the generation of about
1800 this new Western power manifested itself throughout
the world. From the time of Napoleon's expedition to
Egypt the Muslims of the Middle East were faced with the
fact that they would have to go to the European schools
if they were to maintain even a degree of independence;
while at the same time divided India, once a great Islamic
empire, was conquered outright by the British. The
Islamic peoples everywhere found themselves on the
defensive before the once-despised Christians.
During the nineteenth century, Western domination, in
one form or another, spread over the whole world, and
ended by altering radically the circumstances in which
henceforth all peoples must live. The Muslim peoples,
either under direct European rule or under constant
interference by European powers, had to adapt themselves
per force to the European world order, adopting Western
rules of commerce and of citizenship, the new Western
means of transportation and communication, Western
military methods and scientific discoveries.
Gradually they began to undergo like transformations
to those which had already affected the West; and in the
twentieth century, as Western power has receded, they
have taken up (in common with the rest of the world)
the task of forging new destinies for themselves in the
new age, on an equal basis 'with the Western peoples. In
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
country after country new national institutions have been
built up to replace the mediaeval social patterns, and these
new nations have been integrated into a world order
which, in the day of the United Nations, the Islamic
peoples have had a share in forming.
The unity of Islam can therefore no longer be built on
the same basis as in the later Middle Ages; but as a
continuing faith Islam can perhaps find a greater unity
and strength than before. Thus it can be claimed that
when the Caliphate broke up, Islam as an international
civilization became stronger, freed from political
limitations, and expanded more than before; so also it
may be that, now that the particular juridical forms which
tied together the Islamic civilization of the later Middle
Ages have ceased to play their former role, Islam will find
even more effective means of embodying itself.
National diversities can be frankly faced without the
demand for rigid uniformity that sometimes seemed
necessary in the Middle Ages; and with modern methods
of communication Muslims from the farthest parts of the
world, even living in the midst of non-Muslim majorities,
can share together their search for a divinely ordered life.
However this may be, certainly the dignity of membership
in the world-wide brotherhood of Islam is still so
appealing that Islam is actively growing in many areas,
more often as a result of personal contacts than through
the efforts of the missionaries that have been sent out in
recent decades by several Muslim bodies.
Though Muslims Will not play just the same role in the
world's future as they have in its past, their role is bound
to be of great importance if only because they are
established so widely and strategically among mankind.
There are not many more than 350 million Muslims not
more than a sixth of mankind, fewer than Christians and
possibly than Buddhists but they are distributed among
many areas rather than being massed in a single part of
the world. Islam was founded by Arabs, and many of the
lands conquered by the Arab Caliphate came in time to
speak Arabic, which as the language of the Koran
continues to be revered by Muslims everywhere. But
today only a fraction of the whole body of Muslims is
found among the Arabic-speaking peoples.
As can be seen on the map (page 19), there are about as
many Muslims in Indonesia alone as in all the Arabic
countries put together; more than a quarter of the
Muslims of the world are in India and Pakistan and use
the various languages of that subcontinent. Only about
two thirds of the Muslims live in countries where they
form a majority, and these countries are widely scattered;
for instance, Senegal (70 %), Albania (68 %), Egypt (91 %),
Zanzibar (100%), Uzbekistan (80%), Pakistan (86%),
Indonesia (93 %). About a third live in countries where
a strong minority is Muslim, and these countries are even
more widely scattered; for instance, Dutch Guiana (25 %),
Nigeria (33%), Yugoslavia (11%), Lebanon (46%),
Tanganyika (19%), India (11%), Thailand (4%), Fiji
Islands (7 % ) . Sometimes these minorities are of great
importance. Eleven per cent of the population of India
amounts to forty millions, who play a significant part in
Indian life and in the Indian Government; and there are
estimated to be ten million Muslims in China, more than
in all the Arab "Fertile Crescent".
Among the religions, Christianity alone is more
universally found; but the great bulk of Christians is
restricted to Europe and the relatively new and sparsely
settled lands of European speech; Christianity has made
comparatively less progress in regions of other major
heritages. Islam not only dominates the geographically
pivotal Middle East, but has strong footholds in most of
Africa, throughout the Indian subcontinent, in large parts
of the Soviet Union and parts of China, in Malaysia, and
in southeastern Europe.
Thus in the Old World, where the overwhelming
majority of mankind still live, Islam is of major
importance in almost every region; and even in the
Americas there are some Caribbean lands where it forms
an important minority. Where it is not strong, either
migration or missionary work as in America has often
had some effect, so that it is at least represented in small
numbers almost everywhere.
'DO IT YOURSELF'
SCIENCE BOOK
"H ow can I teach science?" asked the
young teacher in an Australian Bush
school. "'There's nothing here to teach
with; no test tubes, no balances, no glass tubes,
neither acids nor alkalis, no material whatever!"
"Quite right,1' agreed the visiting school inspector,
"and there's no air, no soil, no sky, no water, no
rocks, no light, no heat, no sound' and no
energy."
The young teacher was reminded of his
"innocent ex-studentship" experience after read¬
ing the Unesco Source Book for Science Teaching
recently published by Unesco (1). As he put it,
"this book leaves the teacher without any alibi or
any excuse [for not teaching science] except lack
of energy."
It does so by offering practical proof that no
teacher anywhere in the world need be
handicapped because he lacks the "proper"
equipment for presenting science to his class.
Material for making laboratory equipment exists
everywherein the home, around , the school
itself, in the junkyard, at the food market, in the
garage and in the countryside, to mention but a
few sources. Science teaching facilities and
resources are all around us and just waiting to be
made use of. Some examples: gravel pits and
stone quarries (evolution of the earth's surface)
woods (animal and plant life, climate and
seasons); buildings under construction (how
materials are used, technical installations) to
name only a few. Then there are easily-arrang¬
ed school facilities: science corners, aquaria,
animal cages, weather stations and museum
shelves. '
Into 220 pages the Unesco Source Book for
Science Teaching has managed to cram enough
material to satisfy the tastes and needs of
(1) Obtainable through Unesco's National Distribu¬
tors listed on page 25. Price: S2.50; 12/6 stg; 600 frs.
!M^^"'
$m Unesco
Iff source book
mm for science
^ teaching
"z~
vBhhb.
ÈÊUsMtmÊmW^M
«y-« b|k JK
CONTINUED ON NEXT PACE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
'DO IT YOURSELF' SCIENCE BOOK (Continued)
teachers all over the world who clamour for ways to plan
and carry out science programmes in which the subject
is experienced and not just learned.
The greater part is taken up with suggestions for
making science equipment and science experiments with
the simplest of materials from pegs and cotton reels to
bottles and saucepans, from nails and needles, to tooth¬
brushes and vinegar.
There are directions for making general pieces of
equipment such as balances, heat sources, filters, pumps,
tweezers, ring stands. Experiments and material for the
study of plants are described. Directions for the study of
animals tell how to make a collecting cage, a wormery,
homes for spiders and ants, aquariums. Astronomy,
meteorology, hydrology, machines, mass and force, heat,
sound, light, electricity and magnetism are covered by a
wide range of simple, inexpensive apparatus and revealing
experiments. Every item is clearly illustrated.
The prototype for this publication was a small volume,
Suggestions for Science Teachers in Devastated Countries,
written by Professor J.P. Stephenson of the City of London
School, and sponsored by Unesco to meet the needs of
teachers in places where science teaching equipment was
in short supply.
While it proved useful in devastated areas, this book
had an even greater success in regions where there had
previously been little or no equipment, particularly in parts
of Asia and Latin America. Unesco science-teaching
experts sent on missions to these areas were able to make
and to try out the materials and experiments suggested in
the Stephenson book. It was like a snowball of ideas
which rolled around the world gathering new substance on
the way. From Peru to Thailand, experts and local
teachers set to work to find other materials and devise
experiments more suitable for tropical regions.
The work of these field experts, together with the
Stephenson book, has produced an array of simple
equipment and science experiments which has now been
assembled in the present Unesco Source Book for Science
Teaching. The original book of suggestions for science
teachers went through several editions and was translated
into French, Spanish, Chinese, Thai and Arabic. The
new volume has already appeared in English and French
and arrangements are being made for its translation into
Spanish, German, Turkish, Thai, Hindi, Singhalese, Tamil
and Indonesian. This would seem to justify the U.S. re¬
view, Scientific American, in its contention that "Unesco's
little guide will make conscientious science teachers from
Ghana to Georgia happier, and their students more
knowledgeable."
We publish on these pages a few of the 700 or so
experiments made with "'junk shop" laboratory material
which are described in the Unesco Source Book.
How to prove that metals
conduct heat at different rates
Obtain 6 in. lengths of several metals.
The bars should be of approximately
the same diameter. Punch holes in the
side of a tripod that has been made
from a tin can. Insert the metal bars so
that they touch at the centre of the can.
Attach a tack or nail to the outside end
of each bar with some paraffin. Place
an alcohol flame under the tripod so that
it touches the inner edge of each bar
equally. Observe the order in which
the tacks fall from the outer end of the
bars.
How to make projector for
coloured pictures
A projector for coloured pictures can be
made from simple materials as shown in
the diagram. Use a box slightly longer
than the focal length of the lens to be
used. For most lenses the box should
be between 12 and 24 in. Jong- Use a
small candy box as a light shield for the
lens as shown. Connect two lamp
sockets in parallel and put one on either
side of the shield. Use gummed tape to
fasten down the front portion of the top
of the larger box and hinge the rear
portion.
22
Hold picture
upside down
and brinq ir
in ho focus
Place a picture upside down in the
back of the box, focusing by moving it
back and forth until a clear image
appears on the wall or screen in front
of the projector.
Dancing figures with static
electricity
Secure an aluminium soup plate, about
1 in. deep, and a glass plate to cover
Fur or toft leather Glan plate
Aluminium
plate '
Cut figuret
from rmue paper
it. Cut some little doll figures from
thin tissue paper, as shown in the
drawing. You may also cut out some
other figures like boxers. The figures
should be just a little shorter than the
depth of the pan. Put the figures on
the bottom of the pan, cover with the
glass. Rub the top surface of 1116 glass
with a piece of fur or soft leather and
watch the dance.
A static horse race
Cut small horses from a piece of folded
paper so that they will stand on a table.
Fountain pen
Pencil
Paper P"1 out
chips of bolonce
by the pen
Rub a hard plastic comb or fountain pen
with fur and notice that you can pull the
paper horses along the table. With
several horses, you can have a horse race.
A trick with surface tension
Secure a used tin can and make five
holes in it with a nail. The holes should
be very near the bottom of the can and
about one-fifth of an inch apart. Now
fill the can with water and observe that
the water comes from the can in five
streams. Pinch the jets of water to¬
gether with your thumb and forefinger
and you can make one stream from five.
If you brush your hand across the holes
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
in the can the water will again flow in
five separate streams.
should cause the one on the table to
break in two parts.
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
heart while another holds the ends of
the long tubes in his ears. Heart sounds
will be heard very clearly though, of
Y
Making a simple reflecting
telescope
A simple reflecting telescope can be
made from a concave mirror obtained
either from an automobile headlight or a
shaving mirror. The mirror is arranged
in a wooden box of suitable size in such
a way that it can be tilted at different
angles. An upright made of wood is
attached to the box so that its angle may
also be varied. Two short focus lenses
are fixed in corks which are then placed
in a short length of mailing tube as an
eye-piece and attached to the wood
upright exactly at the focal distance
away from the mirror.
Break a stick with inertia
Secure a small stick 7 to 8 in. in
length. If no other stick is available a
lead pencil will do. Fold a newspaper
and place it near the edge of a table.
Place the stick under the newspaper on
the table and let about half the stick
extend over the edge. Strike the stick
a sharp blow with another. Inertia
Some simple experiments on
balance
With a sharp knife cut a slice of some
raw vegetable or modelling clay about
Table
Raw vegetable
or
modelling ctay Pencil
one inch thick. Punch the point of a
lead pencil through the slice until it
protrudes about one inch on the other
side. Insert a dinner fork in the slice
of vegetable as shown in the diagram.
Now place the pencil point on the edge
of a table and adjust the parts until
balance is obtained; then give the long
end of the pencil a little tap.
A simple microscope
Make a single turn of copper wire
around a nail to form a loop. Dip the
loop into water and look through it.
You will have a microscope like the
earliest ones used. Often such a lens
will magnify four or five times. ;
Making a simple device for
listening to the heart beat
Make a stethoscope and have pupils
use it to listen to the heart action. .
A very satisfactory demonstration
stethoscope can be made from a small
funnel, . a glass T-tube or Y-tube, and
some rubber tubing. Slip a piece of
rubber tubing about 8 in. long over the
tip of the funnel. (Any kind of small
funnel will do, such as a glass labora¬
tory funnel or the kind used to ^ fill
babies' milk bottles.) Insert the T-tube
into the other end of the short piece
of rubber tubing, and attach longer
pieces of tubing to both arms of the
T-tube
To use the stethoscope, have one
pupil hold the funnel firmly over his
Funnel
course, pupils will not be able to inter¬
pret them. A physician uses a stetho¬
scope to see if heart action is normal.
This experiment will naturally lead
into a discussion of the heart and its
importance in maintaining good health.
Apparatus to study lenses
All that is needed for an optical bench
is a firm surface, a method of holding
mirrors and lenses, and a convenient
way of measuring distances.
A metre scale laid flat on the bench
serves as the basis of this simple appa¬
ratus. Wooden blocks, with grooves that
just fit over the scale can be adapted
as holders. A layer of cork or soft
cardboard glued on the top makes it
easy to stick pins, such as object and
search" pins, into each block; strips of ,
tin screwed to the side make convenient
lens holders. A groove in the top of
a block helps to keep the lens in
position, and rubber tubing over the tin
increases the grip.
Light sources and screens can be
improvised with card and torch bulbs
fastened to the blocks. It is worthwhile,
to make complete sets of this apparatus
so that individual work on lenses can
be attempted. The groove is easily
made with a chisel after two sawcuts
have been made. Other experiments,
for instance on interference and diffrac¬
tion, can be attempted.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
'THE EARTH
AS A PLANET'
Since July 1, 1957, scientists of sixty-five nations have
been taking part in the International Geophysical
Year an organized global campaign to observe and
measure features of the earth and its vicinity that have
hitherto been beyond man's reach. (See The Unesco
Courier, September, 1957.)
It is to this unprecedented, concerted and concentrated
research effort that Unesco has dedicated its sixth
Travelling Science Exhibition, "'The Earth as a Planet",
which was shown in Paris from December 10 to January 17.
Among the most striking of more than 100 items of
scientific equipment are models of artificial satellites, two
French "Véronique" rockets (see this page) and the nose
cone of a U.S. Viking N° 9 rocket, recovered after a 135-
mile flight into the upper atmosphere.
Miniature radiotélescopes show how the sun's rays can
be observed, and other instruments demonstrate how
scientists study cosmic rays and measure the magnetic
field of the earth. Visitors can reproduce, by means of a
special lamp, the green and red rays of polar lights.
Such practical demonstrations as these and some thirty
exhibition panels bring home to the average man what is
meant by the science of geophysics. In addition graphic
illustration is provided of how the scientists of 65 countries
are collaborating in the work of the IGY, through a
demonstration of the system used to alert stations all
over the world by electrical relay, so as to ensure the
simultaneous observation of phenomena such as solar
flares.
Altogether, fourteen countries have provided the collec¬
tion of apparatus, instruments, photographs and other
illustrations.
This extensive exhibition is divided into seven sections:
solar activity, the earth as a magnet, the upper atmosphere
and the transmission of radio-electric waves, the lower
atmosphere and meteorology, auroral phenomena, cosmic
rays, and IGY research.
Following its showing in Paris, "'The Earth as a Planet"
will shortly begin a tour of some of Unesco's European
Member States.
'VERONIQUE', a French research rocket (right) on view
at Unesco's "The Earth as a Planet" Exhibition, in Paris,
is being used by scientists during the International Geophy¬
sical Year to study the upper atmosphere. A total of twelve
"Véronique" rockets will be launched, five of them during
May, from the research station at Colomb-Bechar in the
Sahara. This long, slender rocket (length 32 ft.; diameter
22in.) weighs 2,960 lb. (with a payload of 132 lb.) when
ready for launching, and 784 lb. after the propellant has
been burned. In its vertical trajectory, the rocket is guided
for the first 200 ft. by cables which are then automatically
detached. In 49 sec. the rocket attains its maximum velocity
of 6,233 ft. per second and reaches a height of 18 miles.
At the end of this powered flight the rocket continues to an
altitude of 136 miles (a total flight time of 250 sec. has
elapsed since takeoff). At this point the nose section separ¬
ates from the body of the rocket and is parachuted back
to earth (at a speed of I 64 ft. per second or 26 ft. per second,
depending on the type of equipment used). Data obtained
during the rocket's flight is either recorded by instruments
which are later recovered from the nose section after this has
been parachuted down, or is transmitted by radio during
flight and picked up by ground-based telemetering devices.
UNESCO - Bablin
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1958
Where to write for pen friends
Lack of space has made it impossible for The Unesco
Courier to continue publishing the many requests it
receives from readers wishing to make pen friends.
All the letters it has received, but which it has been
unable to publish, have now been passed to the Inter¬
national Federation of Organizations for Scholastic
Correspondence and Exchanges (fioces) of 29 Rue
d'Ulm, Paris, which has kindly offered to deal with
these requests. The editor suggests that readers who
wish to make pen friends should write to the organiz
ations listed on this page which are the national affi¬
liates of fioces. Organizations marked (A) particularly
concern themselves with correspondence between
adults. Readers should write directly to organizations
in their own countries where possible. When writing
to foreign organizations an international reply coupon
should be enclosed, and all requests for pen friends
should include sender's name and address (in block
letters) age, status and interests. Readers are asked
NOT to send pen friend requests to The Unesco Courier.
Argentine: Sección argentina de corres¬
pondencia escolar internacional, Aso¬
ciación argentina de profesores de
idiomas, Pueyrredon 821, 6 a.,
Buenos Aires.
Australia: Student's International Corres¬
pondence, c/o The United Nations
Association of Australia (N.S.W.
Div.), 29 Bligh St. Sydney, N.S.W.
Austria: (A) Oesterreichisches Komitee
für internationalen Studienaustausch,
Wallnerstrasse, 8, Vienna I.
Verband der österreichischen Neu¬
philologen, Internationaler Schüler¬
briefwechsel, Zentralstelle für Fran¬
zösisch, Marchetigasse 3, Vienna VI.
Verband der österreichischen Neu¬
philologen, Internationaler Schüler¬
briefwechsel, Zentralstelle für En¬
glisch, Kundmangasse 22, Vienna III.
Belgium: (A) La jeunesse belge à l'étran¬
ger, 11, rue d'Egmont, Brussels.
Brazil: (A) Serviço de correspondencia
escolar internacional, Casa do Estu-
dante do Brasil, Rua Santa Luzia,
305, Rio de laneiro.
Canada: (A) Overseas Correspondence
Dept., United Nations Association in
Canada, Box 204, Markham, Ont.
Federal Republic of Germany: (A) Paeda-
gogischer Austauschdienst, König¬
strasse 61, Bonn.
Finland: Koulumatkailutoimisto, School
Travel Bureau, Korkeavuorenkatu
25 A, Helsinki.
France: Bureau français de CS.I., 29,
rue d'Ulm, Paris-V.
India: (A) Nations' League of Pen-
Friends, 27 Theatre Communication
Buildings, Connaught PL, New Delhi.
Italy: (A) Ufficio di corrispondenza sco-
lastica internazionale, Direzione ge¬
nerale degli scambi culturali, Minis-
tero della pubblica. istruzione,
Piazza Cairoli 3, Roma.
Japan: (A) Association of Pen Friend
Clubs of Japan, Azabu Post Office,
Box No 1, Minato-ku, Tokyo.
Mauritius: (A) Bureau Mauricien de cor¬
respondance scolaire internationale,
Boîte Postale 247, Port Louis.
Mexico: Oficina Mexicana de correspon¬
dencia escolar international, Secre¬
taria de Educación Pública, México,
D.F.
Netherlands: Vereniging voor Interna-
tionaal Jeugdverkeer, 2, Stadhou-
derslaan, Utrecht.
New Zealand: (A) Overseas Correspon¬
dence, The United Nations Associa¬
tion, C.P.O. Box 2209, Wellington.
Norway: Skolenes Brevklubb, Kristian
Augutsgt, 14, Oslo.
Philippines: (A) All Nations Pen Pal
Club, P.O. Box 326, Manila.
Spain: (A) Estafeta Juvenil Internacional,
Frente de Juventudes, Marques del
Riscal 16, Madrid.
Sweden: Centralnämnden för Skolung-
dumsutbytet med Utlandet, Storkyr-
kobrinken 22, Stockholm C.
Switzerland. Echange international de
correspondance. Pro Juventute, See¬
feldstrasse 8, Postfach, Zürich 22.
United Kingdom: (A) International
Friendship League, 21 Wyndham
Road, Birmingham.
International Scholastic Correspon¬
dence, Higher North Hartón Farm,
Lustleigh, Newton Abbott, Devon.
The Modern Language Association,
2 Manchester Square, London W. 1.
National Union of Students, Inter¬
national Correspondence Exchange,
Leeds University Union, Leeds 2.
The Educational Institute of Scot¬
land, 46-47 Moray Place, Edinburgh,
Scotland.
International Scholastic Correspon¬
dence, N. America-Australasia Sub-
Office, P.O. Box 40, Inverness,
Scotland.
United States: Children's Plea for Peace,
World Affair Center, University of
Minnesota, Minneapolis, 14, Minne¬
sota.
Interscholastic Correspondence, Stu¬
dent Forum on International Re¬
lations, P.O. Box 733, San Francisco,
Cal.
(A) League ol Friendship, 4 Ash
Street, Mount Vernon, Ohio.
(A) Letters Abroad, 45 East 65th
Street, New York 21, N.Y.
National Bureau of Educational
Correspondence, A.A.T.F., College
of Wooster, Wooster, Ohio.
Student Letter Exchange, Waseca,
Minn.
World Friends' Club, The Cleveland
Press, Cleveland, Ohio.
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom the English, French, Spanish
and Russian editions of the UNESCO
COURIER can be obtained are listed
below.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Dep¬
artment, Royal Afghan Ministry of Educ¬
ation, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 365 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, 15 rue
du Tilleul. Genval (Brabant). 100 Belgian
francs.
CANADA. University ol Toronto Press,
Baldwin House, 33 St. Georges Street,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
nf Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, I 00 Parsons Road Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kléber, Paris, 16'. C.C.P.
I259B-4B, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen¬
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Raikamal Publicat¬
ions Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby Road,
Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Ojalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P.O. B. 4154, Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Librería Commissionaria San-
soni. Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston,
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Qjiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva.
6.50 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2 rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma)
549, Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724. Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y.
U. S. S. R- Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga
Terazije 27/1 I, Belgrade.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
Ä WOPPING ART WORKS: The
Oxford Museum of Eastern Art, in
England, has found a simple and in¬
expensive way of becoming a centre with
a unique facility for the study of Oriental
Art. It is doing so by assembling a collec¬
tion of 900 35-mm. colour slides of the
most important works from museums in
other lands containing renowned collections
of Oriental art. It is obtaining these slides
by offering to exchange directly 100 slides
of its own works for 100 slides from any
other museum. So far nine museums or
galleries have agreed to "swop" sets. Thus
something quite new has been initiated in
this trade between museums.
H AIR POLLUTION DANGERS : Air
pollution was described as the greatest
and most urgent environmental evil
facing the peoples of Europe, at a
recent conference convened in Milan
by the World Health Organization. The
Conference, the first international
meeting ever to be held on air
pollution, aimed at pooling the
knowledge and experience of many
countries in this field, to fight the
dangers of polluted air. Some facts
highlighted by the meeting : Smoke-
polluted fog in the Thames Valley,
England, in December 1952 is estimated
to have caused 3,000 to 4,000 deaths;
studies in Paris show that motor-traffic
accounts for 30-40 % of the total
pollution and domestic heating for
about 50 %.
Bi»RÜSSELS EXHIBITION STAMPS:
The Belgian postal authorities are to issue
a series of 16 stamps to the value of 100
Belgian francs ($2.00) honouring the United
Nations, on the occasion of the Brussels
Exhibition this year. The stamps will be
valid only for mail posted in the U.N.
Pavilion at the Exhibition. Collectors may
obtain a complete set of the stamps by
writing to unExpo, Pavillon des Nations
Unies, Exposition de Bruxelles, Brussels,
enclosing either a cheque on a Brussels'
bank or an international money order for
the equivalent of 120. Belgian francs made
out to unExpo. Orders may now be placed
for the stamps which will be issued in
April.
YOUNG SCIENTISTS' CHANCE:
The Brazilian Institute of Education
Science and Culture in Sao Paulo has
offered prizes totalling $2,500 to young
Brazilians of not more than 18 years
of age for a scientific thesis on
personal research carried out in chemis¬
try, biology, physics or mathematics.
The contest is intended not so much to
reveal new discoveries as to provide an
opportunity for young people to make
use of their powers of observation in
practical subjects such as radar, plant
growth and electricity.
Jr LENTY TO CHOOSE FROM :
More than 100,000 scientific articles drawn
from publications in 42 countries can now
be made available to scientists in countries
throughout the Middle East by the Library
of the Scientific and Technical Documenta¬
tion Division of the National Research Cen¬
tre in Cairo. Created about two years ago
26
by the Egyptian Government with aid from
Unesco, the Division now handles a
monthly average of 1,350 scientific and
technical reviews in over 20 languages. Arti¬
cles are listed by title, translated into Eng¬
lish or French where necessary, classified
by subject and all this information is pub¬
lished in a monthly bulletin. If a scientist
writes quoting the number of the article
that interests him, a microfilm copy is sent
by return.
DEATH AND DISEASES : In 28
countries and territories comprising 564
million people (one-sixth of the world's
population) mortality from infectious
and parasitic diseases decreased by
50% between 1950 and 1955 according
to recent World Health Organisation
statistics. Of all the diseases, tuber¬
culosis remains in the lead, and
accounted for three-fourths of all deaths
due to infectious and parasitic diseases
occuring after the age of 15. Largest
reduction in mortality from any one of
the diseases (63% less) took place in
regard to whooping cough.
A]RT FOR NEW UNESCO H.Q. :
Four more artists Afro (Italy), Karl Appel
(Netherlands), Roberto Matta (Chile) and
Rufino Tamayo (Mexico) are to be invited
to decorate the new Unesco H.Q. now
under construction in Paris. Their work
will consist of paintings or murals on the
seventh (top) floor of the building. Other
well-known artists who have already agreed
to execute works for the H.Q. are lean
Arp, Alexander Calder, luán Miro, Henry
Moore, Isamu Noguchi and Pablo Picasso.
SMALL FISHLARGE CATCH:
Japan is the world's No. 1 fishing
country, with a total catch of over four
and a half million tons in 1956,
according to the Food and Agriculture
Organization's Yearbook of Fisheries
Statistics. Second largest fish-producing
country is the U.S.A. followed by
China, the Soviet Union. Norway.
Canada, the United Kingdom and
India. These eight countries accounted
for 60% of the total catch in 1956.
The smallest fish herring, sardines,
anchovies make up the largest section
of the world catch by species.
S OVIET WORKERS ABROAD :
Workers from Stalingrad, Minsk, Penza
near Moscow and other U.S.S.R. cities
returned home recently after a tour of
France organized by Unesco under its
workers exchange programme, with aid
from the French National Commission for
Unesco and the French C.G.T. Trade
Union Group. During its stay the party
saw textile, shoe and automobile factories
and visited French workers' homes. In
recent years Unesco has organized group
exchanges with the aid of workers'
organizations, as part of its work for
international understanding and co-opera¬
tion. This was the first time that work¬
ers from the Soviet Union had partici¬
pated in the Unesco scheme.
LOOKING UNDER ASIA: Geo¬
logists from 15 Asian countries met in
Calcutta recently to put the final
touches to the draft of the first
geological map of Asia which is to be
published this year. The importance
of such a map relative to Asia's
economic development is considerable
as a detailed and accurate knowledge
of geological structure is a prerequisite
for Asian countries in the exploitation of
their mineral resources and the creation
of new industries.
AiLL ABOUT WALL SHEETS:
Among the most effective visual aids to
teaching are wall sheets, which may be
used alone or in conjunction with text
books, films, and the blackboard. In a new
pamphlet, "Wall Sheets: their Design, Pro¬
duction and Use", Mrs Helen Coppen,
Lecturer in New Media at the University
of London Institute of Education, and a
leading authority on the use of non-pro¬
jected visual aids in teaching, gives just
about all the useful advice needed to deal
with the practical problems involved in
using this type of material. The pamphlet
can be obtained from its publishers, The
National Committee for Visual Aids in
Education, 33 Queen Anne Street, London
W.l. England; Price 1/6 plus 6d postage
and packing.
H WAY TO EACH OTHER : Fifty
thousand people have visited a Unesco
exhibit, "The Road to Each Other",
which has toured twenty-five cities in
the Netherlands over the past six
months, reports Dr. F. H. Tunissen,
director of the Unesco Centrum in the
Netherlands. The Centre, which has
its headquarters in Amsterdam, has
150 local Unesco committees and
65 youth clubs under it wing. It is also
reaching Dutch audiences with a ten-
minute radio programme every two
weeks and a monthly 50-minute tele¬
vision show. The TV show has
already offered programmes on the life
of children in India and Surinam, and
the next country is scheduled to be
Israel. The Unesco Centre in the Ne¬
therlands draws its support from a
variety of sources, including the Dutch
government, Unesco, private gifts and
also fund-raising campaigns. Among the -
most successful of these has been the
nation-wide sale of a Unesco calendar.
JLiAW AT SEA : An international
Conference on the Law of the Sea is due
to meet in Geneva on February 24, under
United Nations auspices. The conference,
which will last about nine weeks, will
examine such problems as the breadth of
territorial waters, the nationality of ships,
and whether there should be a special
registration entitling a vessel to fly the U.N.
flag and receive United Nations protection.
It will also discuss penal jurisdiction in
maritime collisions, slave trade, pollution of
the sea, and piracy, including piratical acts
by aircraft if these are directed against
ships on the high seas. All member
states of the U.N. and its specialized agen¬
cies have been invited to participate in the
conference, while fifteen non-governmen¬
tal bodies, concerned chiefly with fishing
and maritime questions, have been invited
to send observers.
<
z
<
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
75,000 EDUCATIONAL
OPPORTUNITIES FOR
FOREIGN STUDENTS
A record number of fellowships and scholarships for
foreign studentsmore than 75,000is listed in
the ninth edition of Study Abroad (I), the hand¬
book on international educational opportunities
published annually by UNESCO.
Study Abroad, one of UNESCO'S best-selling publica¬
tions, describes in this edition fellowships and
scholarships offered by governments, foundations,
universities and other institutions in 83 states and
many territories. For the first time, awards are
listed for Bulgaria, Ethiopia, Ghana, Paraguay, Ru¬
mania, Saudi Arabia and the U.S.S.R.
Along with these educational opportunities, the
836 pages of Study Abroad also contain the results
of UNESCO'S fifth survey of foreign student enrol¬
ment around the world. In 1956, the survey shows,
there were an estimated I 50,000 foreign students
enrolled in 74 countries. The United States led
the world with a total of 36,494; followed by France
with 16,877; the U.S.S.R. with 12,300; Argentina
with 10,782 and the United Kingdom with 9,723.
Leader of the Middle East was Egypt with 3,671 and
Japan ranked first in Asia with 3,137.
What do students study when they go abroad ? A
UNESCO survey of 36 selected countries showed
that, of a total of I 14, 145 students, the humanities
still held the lead, in 1955-56, with 26,342 students,
as compared with 24,925 studying engineering.
Medicine ranked third with 20,290, followed by
the natural sciences, 13,034; the social sciences,
I 1,638; and law, 5,907.
StudyAb
m i mi *hm
ihitude
a Tétranger
studios en et
extranjero
IX
1957-58
(I) Price: S2.50; 750 French francs; I 2/6d; (Obtainable from
Unesco National Distributors, see page 25)
Unesco
,;».;, ~ 7
<u
; C
0
'0
u
3
-O .
- i. '
: Q-
V.
IK-
C .
.2'-'
x>-
3
t)
O
. i. .
' o.
- ' -
m*
catalogue;
dé reproductions eh
couleurs de peintures
1860 a 1957
' - ' '.
catalogue of .
colour reproductions ..-.
: Of paintings
I860 to 1957
catálogo, de
reproducciones \
en color de pinturas
1860 a 1957.
unesco paris
CATALOGUE OF COLOUR
REPRODUCTIONS OF PAINTINGS
(4th edition revised and enlarged)
Unesco is systematically building up archives of colour
reproductions of paintings. Copies of all available
reproductions are collected by the Secretariat and,
from these, selections are made by an international
committee of experts for a descriptive catalogue
which is regularly produced in two volumes.
The International Committee (composed of Sir Phi¬
lip Hendy, Mr. Jean Lemayre, Mr. Jean Cassou,
Mr. Sanchez Cauton and Mr. Lionello Venturi) is
guided in its selection by three main criteria: the
fidelity of the reproduction, the significance of the
artist, and the importance of the original painting.
The fourth revised and enlarged edition of the cata¬
logue contains, in Vol. I, 595 reproductions, and in
Vol. II, 992. The reception given to these catalogués
by teachers, students, art publishers, and art lovers
of all kinds has provided convincing proof of their
quality and usefulness..
Vol. I. Prior to I860 (234 p.) 	 S3. 25; 16/ 800 fr.
Vol. II. From I860 to 1957 (364 p.) S4.00; 20/ 1.000 fr.
(Cover of Vol. II is reproduced opposite). Both volumes can
be obtained from Unesco National Distributors, see page 25.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
EP IS THE BEST MEDICINE'
rding to an old English proverb,
ven today how it rests our bodies
is not completely understood. Spe¬
cial studies of the slowing down of
bodily functions are now being made
in experiments using artificial hiber¬
nation to combat severe shock and
exhaustion. (Photo here shows pa¬
tient in a Paris hospital where pio¬
neer work in this field is being car-
' on.) Science today has the an-
s to many of the questions most
le ask about sleep : Is it true that
he best sleep comes before midnight?
Can one really 'dream all night' ? Do
elderly people need less sleep than
young ones? See article page 6.
'can Marquis © Magnum Photos
]]>
</page>
</document>
