<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066148eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ï
,7
MAN
AGAINST
NATURE
rf^JI
fr^ 5^¿*.
{
p^lItvl I
JANUARY
\W ^f"-*^
4A^Hfl
*1 1
19 5 8
(llth year)
Price: l/-stg. (U. K.)
30 cents (U. S.)
5 0 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TT	>*- -»-." "L1^,
^^Stâ^ni
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
-UNESCO
JANUARY 1958
NTH YEAR
No. I
CONTENTS
Cover Photo: Baby Leopard. Once hunted down indis¬
criminately, leopards are now protected in some African
territories, for keeping down wild pigs, baboons and other
crop destroyers. I. U.C.N. Photo
PAGE
3 ARE WE HEADED FOR CATASTROPHE?
By Roger Heim
4 MAN AGAINST NATURE
By Maurice Burton
6 FOSSILS OF TOMORROW
Some living relics among today's animals
By Marguerite Caram & J.J. Petter
9 LAST REFUGE
Where animals no longer walk in fear
15 DEAD AS THE DODO
16 NATURE'S BEST FRIEND: THE SCHOOLCHILD
By Pierre Vernier
17 «FIRE & AXE' FARMING ON THE WAY OUT
By G. Watterson
18 GALAPAGOS : NOAH'S ARK IN THE PACIFIC
By I. Eibl-Eibesfeldt
24 HARMFUL ANIMALS: HIDDEN FRIENDS?
By Jean-Paul Harroy
27 THE TALE OF THE GOLDEN EGG
Threats to Nature's delicate balance
30 THE GENTLE LITTLE GOAT
Arch despoiler of the earth
by Raymond Furon
33 STAMP COLLECTORS' WILDLIFE ALBUM
By C.W. Hill
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
35 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19 Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. A small Japanese version is published in Tokyo
and a Danish version in Copenhagen. The United States of America edition
is distributed by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue,
New York 22, N.Y., Pennsylvania 6-0851. Second-class mail privileges author¬
ized at New York, N.Y. (M.C. 57.1.120 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
credit is given to THE UNESCO COURIER and two voucher copies are sent
to the editor. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00 ; 1 0/. itg. ; 300 French francs or equi¬
valent.
ARE WE HEADED FOR
CATASTROPHE ?
C*\ HARLEs Richet, French physiologist and Nobel Prize
winner, once published a tiny book called L'Homme
stupide (The Stupidity of Man) the caustic title of
which might well give us cause for reflexion. Those of us
to whom it was addressed could still find therein reasons
for humility and a chance for improvement. For the fact
is that mankind is brilliant and yet so stupid.
Brilliant, in being able to produce a number of
exceptional individuals endowed with the spark of creation
and whose genius has made possible the astounding pro¬
gress of today, particularly in the field of science. Stupid,
in being incapable of forethought, except where immediate
and selfish interests are involved, and almost inept in
avoiding major catastrophes. Today, enchained by the
swarm of increasing populations, our planet is being
plundered on an unimaginable scale while mankind races
toward a destiny which it refuses to envisage.
It is not intended here to formulate a one-sided or
philosophical critique of our era or of technical progress,
but rather to look squarely at the things being done
around us, at the facts and figures, on the one hand re¬
calling the chain of causes, and on the other, their
resounding repercussions.
The erosion of the soil has been going on for a long
long time: and yet, relatively speaking, it is a much more
serious threat today than ever before. The ravages of
the goat go back thousands of years: yet the tank and
the bulldozer cause greater destruction and do so with
greater swiftness. The clearing of land by fire has always
been practised in cultivation: yet the introduction of Eu¬
ropean methods of intensive farming has, in some cases,
been even more harmful. Pollution has been a scourge
for aeons: yet the atomic era is bringing it to us in
another form. The stripping of our planet's top-soil, the
deterioration of our capital of renewable resources, the
shattering of the delicate balance of nature... all these
are brutal events of weighty importance which, since they
are all occurring at the same time, are the cause of the
deepest concern.
The notion of the protection of nature has now given
way to that of the conservation of renewable resources.
The earlier notion contained an emotional, sentimental
significance and its goals were disinterested, purely aes¬
thetic, scientific and moral in nature. These are no
longer priority considerations, for today our overpopulated
world is hungry. What is of the utmost importance is no
longer merely the knowledge and study of living species
their surroundings and habitat, or the respect which they
should inspire, or the interest they might arouse, or even
the protection which these species deserve, but rather the
food supply of our rising generations.
The statistics stare us in the face: we must produce
and produce more. Yet the gap between this accelerated
production and world consumption widens every year.
What a terrible price we must pay for this economic
failure... the price of the destruction of what was once
one of life's most beautiful mirages.
Are we then headed for catastrophe?
We have one last chance if the power of education can
overcome the power of ignorance. A rational population
policy, a stop-and-arrest stand against the cancer of
erosion, the adaptation of cultivation to climate and soil,
the preservation of renewable resources all these depend
upon education. It is our sincere hope that this issue
will help Unesco to defend the great cause of the conser¬
vation of nature which it has espoused.
Roger HEIM
Member of the French Institute,
President, International Union
for the Conservation of Nature
and Natural Resources
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
T NATURE
by Maurice Burton
A Belgian meteorologist reports an
increased electrical conductivity
of the atmosphere around his
laboratory at Liège, and suggests that
this may lead, among other things, to
a lessening of atmospheric nitrogen
fixed by lightning flashes, thus depriv¬
ing the earth of one of its natural
fertilizers. This has occurred simul¬
taneously with the testing of atomic
weapons. If his worst fears are realiz¬
ed, then we have added, and quite
unexpectedly, yet one more blow at
the fertility of the soil.
Truly, the conservationists are
fighting a losing battle. Already we
have polluted the rivers, cut down
the forests, cast unwelcome oil on the
waters of the oceans, reduced to dan¬
ger point the number of whales in
the oceans, and brought to a ludicrous
remnant one of the living marvels of
the world, the African Big Game. To
name these is merely to abstract a
few from the long catalogue of blows
which we have irresponsibly aimed at
the thin skin of soil covering the
land-masses, upon which the survival
of the human race is dependent.
One of the suggested palliatives to
offset this catastrophic series of
events is to convert the teeming mil¬
lions of people to eating plankton.
Even Nebuchadnezzar was not brought
so low as this.
To many of us, enjoying the high
standards of living in Western Eu¬
rope, North America and elsewhere,
this may appear to be a picture
unwarrantably overdrawn. Time
alone will prove whether or not it is
correct. If it is not, then the victory
will be owed in great measure to the
small band of conservationists, in
every country, who are fighting this
losing battle, refusing to admit defeat.
And if final victory is won it will add
yet one more instance to the annals
of history of desperate rearguard
actions, with small local successes,
leading eventually to total victory.
It may not be unprofitable at this
point to ask: What does conservation
mean? With it are linked two other
words that are becoming increas¬
ingly heard, "protection" and "pre¬
servation". It is, perhaps, in some
ways unfortunate that these two
words should be better known to the
general public than "conservation",
for they tend to imply restriction of
liberties, prohibition or inhibition of
the rights of the individual to inter¬
fere with the land, and its products,
which history has shown belong first
and foremost to anyone powerful
enough to take them.
Conservation, in its wider view,
means making the best use, by wise
management, of all natural resources.
Expressed thus, the plea for conser¬
vation would be readily accepted by
all but the hopelessly selfish and pur¬
blind. The difficulty arises, as usual,
in the application of the principle,
for where a natural source of wealth,
be it a forest, a species of animal,
a source of water or the use to which
an area of land shall be put, is in
question, there are, and always will
be, conflicting interests. These are of
many kinds, and their impact varies
from one part of the world to an¬
other. The more important are econo¬
mic, political and religious, with sport
as a close fourth. They all have
the advantage of tradition, and they
all offer the prospect of immediate
gain, as against the long-term pro¬
fits, which is very nearly all that a
policy of conservation can offer. The
world is not yet on the verge of
starvation, so it is difficult to argue
anything but the seemingly doctri¬
naire view that the ground is being
cut from under the feet of genera¬
tions unborn. And this, against the
powerful arguments of present gain,
is as the proverbial voice crying in
the wilderness.
Even if it were untrue that the
stakes are as high as world-wide
malnutrition, they would still be
high enough. The present trend in
technology is towards a, higher stan¬
dard of material comfort at less cost
in working hours. Such an end
cannot be other than wholly desir¬
able; but if the leisure so gained is to
be spent in a world bereft of its
amenities we shall have gained the
world but lost the soul thereof. Under
the heading of amenities we have at
the moment a fair yardstick by which
to gauge what it is we stand to lose.
One of the social phenomena of today
is that, as the wild fauna and flora of
the world are shrinking before our
eyes, we see an unprecedented popu¬
larity for films, television and sound
broadcasts, books, lectures and news¬
paper articles on animals and travel.
If the present trend goes on unchecked
the time cannot be far off when there
will be no conspicuous wild animals
to see, and no travel worth the while.
It may be that this very contradic¬
tion is itself symptomatic, that deep
down in the intuitive mind of the
mass of the people is an uneasiness
that something is going from the
world. It may not be an exagger¬
ation, perhaps, to suggest that the
very popularity of these two subjects
arises from the feeling that here is
something that must be enjoyed
before it is too late. If this interpret¬
ation is Incorrect, then we have only
one other to postulate: that people
with leisure find wild life, plant or
animal, or in the form of scenery, a
most desirable asset. Whichever way
we look at it, therefore, there is
potent argument in favour of seeking
to conserve these amenities.
There is, also, in this contradiction
a measure of hope, for it connotes a
PRIMITIVE PEOPLES depended on animal
life for their livelihood but as their weapons
did not have the killing capacity of modern
firearms, the biological balance between man
and his prey remained unbroken. When
reservoir of support for the efforts of
the conservationists, if the means can
be found for rallying it. Already,
throughout the world, governments
are being made more alive to the need
for conservation, although all too
often their pre-occupation with pre¬
sent expediencies precludes their
wholehearted support. Often, too,
the clamour from conflicting interests
deafens them to what, under other
circumstances, would be the clear
voice of reason. For the most part,
then, such victories as have been
gained have been' as the result of
pressure by the International Union
for the Conservation of Nature or by
national or local organizations. These
flourish or wilt according to the
degree of popular education achieved
in any nation, region or local area.
In this education, three things
more especially must be stressed:
1) that the losses among the wild
fauna and flora have been accelerated
within the last century, and that
this acceleration is increasing; 2) that
fundamentally the problem of con¬
servation is biological, using this
word in its widest sense; and 3) that
with the exploration and application
of biological principles loss can be
turned into profit and, what is more
Important, it is possible to have your
cake as well as eat It.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
3 v Í /
I.U.C.N.
hunting becomes a slaughter, however, It
threatens to upset the delicate balance of
Nature. Zebras and antelopes have been
shot down In wholesale numbers in Africa
(above) to the point where certain species
have become extinct. Two examples are
Burchell's zebra (the last one died In London
in 1909) and the Quagga, another member
of the zebra family, striped only on the head
and neck. Quaggas were hunted by the Boers
In South Africa, first for sport and later to
provide' meat for export, and the last one died
In Amsterdam in 1883. The problem is still
with us. In 1953, 380,000 antelope skins
were exported from the Ivory Coast alone.
Within the space available here, it
is not possible to do more than illus¬
trate, in the barest terms, these
three points, as, indeed, it is not
possible to speak except in the mini¬
mum, and probably inadequate, terms
of so vast and deep a problem as
conservation. To do the second of
these in a way that would convey a
real sense of the problem involved
would take us into consideration of
soil erosion and the creation of dust
bowls, the loss of forests and its effect
on the rainfall and water tables, over¬
grazing, over-fishing, as well as the
more localized effects of introducing
alien plants and animals, the killing
off of predators, ill-advised methods
of pest control and the like. On the
three main points upon which the
world as a whole needs instruction
and information, single examples
must suffice.
The first of these can be best ex¬
pressed in the simple arithmetical
expression put forth by Harper and
Allen on the vanishing animals of the
world. They show that during the
last two thousand years, 106 large
mammals have become extinct. Of
these, 33 were lost during the first
1,800 years. During the next 100 years
33 more were lost, and during the last
50 years 40 have been destroyed.
Even this does not take account of the
very large number now either on the
verge of extinction or surviving in
drastically reduced numbers. And it
takes account only of the mammals.
The second illustrates what is
perhaps the greatest difficulty
in conservation, that in dealing
with living organisms, whether plant
or animal, and of whatever size, any
interference produces a chain reaction
the effects of which are difficult to
appreciate except as the result of long
and tedious study. The killing off of
crocodiles seems on the face of it a
desirable thing, and their skins make
a marketable leather. Yet as Cott
has now shown, the repercussions are
likely to be adverse and widespread.
The hippopotamus, also, seems to
serve little purpose, except that of
interest in a large and curiously-built
animal, until we realize that its
excrement, by a chain of ecological
reactions was responsible for the rich
populations of fish in the African
rivers. All these, and many besides,
could be quoted to show how indiscri¬
minate killing, either for commercial
gain, or for the mere lust of slaughter,
is depriving us of amenities or, more
important in the practical values of
the future, of essential food supplies.
The normal effects of human settle¬
ment, make enough inroads without
our adding to them unnecessarily.
For the third point, one cannot do
better than quote what must now be
a familiar example, the story of the
Pribilov seals. These, formerly teem¬
ing in their millions in the North
Pacific, were reduced by sealing to a
dangerously low point. The zoolo¬
gists discovered, in studying the
breeding habits, that each old bull
gathered around him on the beaches
a harem of cows, while the young
non-breeding males gathered in se¬
parate groups at other points on the
beach. There they made a nuisance
of themselves, by fighting and by
challenging the old bulls, causing
casualties among themselves and
among the new-born pups. It was
recognized then, that by thinning out
these bachelor bulls all the skins
necessary for the trade could be
obtained, with an actual benefit to
the species through obviating the
casualties caused by the bachelors.
Today, the Pribilov seals are back to
their former millions and at the same
time a rich crop of furs is being har¬
vested. It should not be impossible
to find similar solutions to other
problems of conservation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THE LION OF ASIA once roamed over the southern part
of the continent from Asia Minor to India. Darius, Xerxes
and other rulers of the Persian Empire caused the image
of the largest of great cats to be carved in the decorations
of the mighty cities they built. Today there are perhaps 250
surviving under protection in the Gyr Forest to the north¬
west of Bombay. Elsewhere they have been wiped out.
THE MOUNTAIN ZEBRA today maintains a precarious foothold
in the mountainous region of Cape Colony, South Africa, where a
hundred or so live in reservations. A century ago they were num¬
bered in millions until they began to be relentlessly hunted down
for their skins. Their low birthrate a female gives birth once
every two yearshas made it impossible for them to recover
from the effects of the wholesale killings which were done.
Drawings taken from Derniers Refuges (Last Refuges), an annotated Atlas of the world's nature reserves prepared by the International Union for the Conservation of
Nature. (I.U.C.N.). © 1956 by Editions Elsevier, Amsterdam and Brussels, and by the I.U.C.N.
FOSSILS OF TOMORROW
by Marguerite Caram and JJ. Petfer
International Union for the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources
Hunted to excess, victims of Man's expansion and
struggle for more living space, prey to epidemics,
prejudices and other destructives forces, wild creatures
are diminishing in numbers. Entire species are disappearing
from the face of the earth. In the 19th century alone 70
species became extinct and in the past 50 years a further 40
have died out. Today the existences of a further 600 are
threatened. One after another they seem destined to join
the long list of animals each of whose names is now no
more than a scientific appelation used by the palaeontologist
and whose only relics are skeletons, reconstituted with
varying success in museums. It is true that in recent years
there has been some heartening progress in wildlife protection
in some countries, where governments have set up conserva¬
tion departments. But, on the whole, if it were not for the
few scientists, nature lovers and economists, who are trying to
save them, realizing their importance in nature's
biological pattern, many animals would quickly Cont'd
be doomed to extinction, and would be fated
to become the fossils of tomorrow.
on
page 8
THE RIGHT WHALE, which
measures between 70 and I 00 feet,
has been almost completly exter¬
minated, although since I 944 (whal¬
ing was reduced during the Second
World War) some increase in its
numbers has been noted in the
Beaufort Sea (northern Canada).
Today the killing of whales is res¬
tricted by international conven¬
tions which fix the maximum catch
in "whale units" for any season.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
THE ONE-HORNED RHINOCEROS from
India, a survivor of prehistoric times, was once
found in all parts of the ancient Indian Empire.
One of the reasons for its progressive exter¬
mination Is the superstition surrounding its
horn which, when ground to powder, is said to
have therapeutic properties. Several hundred
of these beasts still live in the animal sanctuary
at Kasiranga, Assam. Like its Javan relative
the one-horned rhinoceros of the Sunda it
is counted among the world's rarest animals.
© L. Talbot
THE ADDO ELEPHANT whose mighty
herds once roamed the plains of Africa is now
restricted to a special reserve, the Addo
Elephant National Park, to the north of Port
Elizabeth. Elephants are the biggest animals
that walk on four legs, but the Addo elephant
is one of the smaller of the species. Although
there are only about a score of these elephants
in the South African reserve, they did so much
damage "raiding" local farms for food that
the authorities were finally obliged to ring
the elephant park with an electrified fence.
Taken from Derniers Refuges 1956
ï&m*-'
U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service photo by E.H. Haddon
THE WILD BISON of North America, inescapably linked with that adventurous character of our
childhood, Buffalo Bill, barely escaped extinction. Immense herds, millions strong, once grazed
on the great North American Prairie. Despite trading in the hides of these animals, the herds
remained practically intact until about 1870. The building of the trans-continental railway was
like the signing of their death warrant. The story is told in records of the Northern Pacific
Railway: In 1882 this company transported 200,000 buffalo hides; in 1883, 40,000; in 1884,
300; in 1885none! The main industrial value of these victims of the steam engine lay in the
use of their carcasses for making fertilizer. Skeletons were collected along the prairie by hundreds
of tons. Today the American bison lives protected in United States National Parks where there
are about 30,000 head. (Photo above was taken on the National Bison Range, Moiese, Montana).
Across the Atlantic, the European bison, still lives on Soviet and Polish reservations and a recently
noted increase in numbers gives hope that efforts made for its preservation may also be successful.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Fossils of tomorrow
(Continued)
IN the Arabian desert there lives an animal which is believed
to have given rise to a famous legend. It is the handsome
white desert antelope. The smallest representative of
the Oryx group, it is becoming increasingly rare. It has dark
haunches and nearly black legs. Its high, straight, closely set,
parallel horns blend into one when seen in profile; they thus
may have given rise to the unicorn myth. Like the Bedouin,
the animal has become accustomed to an austere existence and
it shares the nomad's waterless
lands which are barely covered
by scant vegetation.
In former times the animal
was found in the whole of the
Arabian peninsula and the re¬
gions north of the Syrian and
Mesopotamian deserts. But it
has always been hunted, pursued
to the accessible limits of its fa¬
miliar haunts. The Arabs of
yesterday hunted it on camels;
those of today pursue it in jeeps
and automobiles. The area fre¬
quented by the Oryx has shrunk
alarmingly since 1884 when
these animals were still to be
found in northern Arabia. Now¬
adays the only known specimens
are in the Rub el Khali desert.
According to some accounts,
only about 100 of these magnifi¬
cent antelopes still exist; other
estimates place their number at
no more than 40. In any case
their chances of surviving are
slim indeed.
The Caribbean monk seal is
about 8 feet long and its
colour shades from grey to
dark brown. It inhabits the
Gulf of Mexico from the coast
of Honduras to that of Jamaica
or Cuba. Already observed by
Christopher Columbus in 1494,
it continued to thrive until about
the beginning of the 18th cen¬
tury.
At that time it began to be
exploited systematically for its
oil. Fishermen were able to take as many as 100 in a single
night and at this rate the "gold mine" gradually became
worked out. The species became rare, and although a few
sporadic killings on a large scale on various Caribbean coasts
were reported between 1875 and 1911, the animal was seen
but fleetingly after 1922. Its very existence is problematical
today, although reports that individual animals or isolated
groups have been sighted by ships are received from time
to time.
There is a group of animals in the highest order of mam¬
mals whose members have a strangely attractive and
rather mysterious appearance. Their large, round eyes,
frequently nocturnal habits and almost exclusively tree-dwell-
8
J.J. Petter.
'GHOSTS OF THE DEAD'. The group of mysterious-looking
animals called lemurs takes its name from the Latin word lémures,
as the Romans called the ghosts of the dead. More or less the
link between insectivores and monkeys, these curious animals
livein theforestsof Madagascar. Above and below, two species of
lemurs, one of them small enough to be h eld in the palm of the hand.
ing existence all add to their mystery. These are the lemurs,
named from the Latin word lémures, as the Romans called
the ghosts of the dead.
This species is more or less the link between insectivores
and monkeys. Ancient writers believed that lemurs had
inhabited a lost continent, Lemuria, which had joined India to
Madagascar and East Africa; their general distribution about
the Indian Ocean could be explained in this way. But the
hypothesis has now been disproved by palaeontological dis¬
coveries. Fossil lemurs have been found in western Europe
and even in North America. The group probably scattered
from a Eurasian centre and reached Africa and Indonesia,
Europe and America.
Today, six genera and some
ten species are found in Indo¬
China, Malaya, Ceylon, southern
India and the African forests.
But the majority of the whole
group ten genera and about
40 species, with many sub-spe¬
cies are strictly confined to
Madagascar. In size, they vary
from that of a mouse to that of
a ten-year-old child. They feed
on insects, small animals and
fruit; their different types of
colouring are often striking; they
have long noses and thin fingers.
Their habitat is the forest
and that is the principal reason
for the danger threatening them.
During the past five centuries,
the forests have disappeared
from nine-tenths of the great
island of Madagascar, and the
rate of destruction is increasing.
The Malagasy burn immense
stretches of brush so that their
livestock may graze on the
young grass that grows up out
of the ashes. People living at
the edge of the forest cut and
burn the trees to plant rice.
Lemurs, despite protective laws,
also become food for a poverty-
stricken population whose diet
lacks proteins.
One of the most remarkable
members of the Lemur fa¬
mily is the aye-aye. It is
as big as a large cat, with dark
brown fur, an almost black tail
and exceptionally long fingers.
As regards classification, it is perhaps the rarest, most extra¬
ordinary member of the group. Zoologists have alloted to it a
family of its own, the Daubentoniidae. It lives in the eastern
coastal forest of the island, and the only threat to its survival
is the disappearance of the forest itself for the people of
Madagascar do not hunt the aye-aye and even dread meeting
one. The animal's rarity and the superstitions attached to
it by the indigenous people have handicapped scientific
expeditions which have tried to obtain specimens.
The only chance for the aye-aye's survival is the establish¬
ment of a reservation on the last remaining stretches of this
eastern forest and the enlarging of the twelve existing reserved
areas. These were set up to preserve some trace of the
island's primitive, natural appearance and are being maintained
only with great effort.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
LASF-RtFUGE
National Parks Association of Japan
IDEAL BREEDING PLACE for the birds, provided on the
rugged seashore in the Sanriku National Park, north-east
Honshu (main island of Japan), attracts great flocks of seagulls.
In almost all countries, there are areas which the International
Union for the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources
calls "The Last Refuges". They are tracts of land which have
been set aside for many different purposes: to prevent the
countryside being spoiled by technological developments and so
losing its true character; to provide places where people can relax
in healthy surroundings; to preserve sample areas for scientific
research; to ensure the survival of rare species of fauna or flora
which would soon die off outside their own environment; or finally,
to keep certain natural beauty spots intact. On the following
pages are several examples of typical reserves in various parts of
the world and some of the rarities of Nature which they protect.
I. U.C.N.
THE ORIGINAL 'TEDDY BEAR' is the koala, a gentle
little animal that lives in tall eucalyptus trees. This marsupial,
was once hunted for its fur and decimated, but is now protected
in Australia, in particular within the sanctuary which has been
established at Philip Island, about 75 miles from Melbourne.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
STRANGE 'FRUITS' & RARE PLANTS. Unusual-looking objects
hanging from a tree (right) in the Rancho Grande Reserve, Venezuela,
are nests of the turpial, a kind of sparrow and a common bird in this
National Park. The Reserve, to the west of Caracas, the capital, has a
three-fold role as a scientific research area, natural protection zone and
centre for educational visits. Rare silversword flowers (below) bloom
among cinders of the Haleakala Crater in Hawaiian National Park
on the island of Maui, one of four main islands of Hawaiian group.
.U.C.N, and U.S. Department of the Interior photos
Photos © B. Schocher, Kontresina
ROYAL EAGLE (right) is not only protected in the Swiss National
Park, where this photo was taken, but throughout Switzerland. Young
one shown here is preparing to fly from the nest. The Swiss National
Park covers an area of about 40,000 acres in the Engadine Valley.
Because all birds of prey are protected here it was feared that they
might increase excessively and decimate the population of smaller
animals, but such has not been the case. Alpine marmots (above),
rodents related to ground squirrels, are also "boarders" in the Park.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
NO FEAR OF MEN
There is no doubt that the largest variety
and number of animals are to be found
on the continent of Africa. Today,
however, these animals are increasingly
concentrated in reserves which govern¬
ments, alarmed by the steady disap¬
pearance of certain species, have set up.
In French African territories, vast regions
have been turned into reserves. A famous
one is that in the Nimba Mountains on
the borders of Liberia and French West
Africa. Madagascar has twelve strictly
protected reserves.
National Parks of the Belgian Congo are
among the finest in Africa and remarkable
scientific studies are being made in them.
The wonderful Albert National Park
(more than 3,000 square miles) was
reserved in 1925 to protect the gorilla and
other rare animals that inhabit it.
South Africa's nature reserves are espe¬
cially popular with tourists. Here, freed
from the threat of being shot or trapped,
animals have in many cases practically '
lost their fear of man. Among the best
known reserves in British African territories
are the Queen Elizabeth in Uganda, the-
Nairobi National Park in Kenya, the
Serengeti in Tanganyika and the extensive
ones in the two Rhodesias.
STRIPED FOR CAMOUFLAGE in forest
shadows but easily seen in the open, the zebra
usually grazes with wildebeests and gazelle
that warn it of danger. Zebras shown here,
with wildebeests in the background roam
the Kafue National Park, Northern Rhodesia.
©Northern Rhodesia Information Department-N. Watt
FASTEST ANIMAL known for running short
distances, the cheetah is a large catthree to
four feet highof the plains of Africa and
Asia. It has been tamed and used for hunting
in India. This specimen was photographed
in the Serengeti National Park, Tanganyika.
© I. U.C.N. Collection
'RIVER-HORSE' is what the name Hippo¬
potamus means, but this African animal is
really related to the pigs, and shares honours
with the rhinoceros as the largest land mammal
next to the elephant. These animals abound
in South Africa's Kruger National Park, an
immense reserve of 8,800 square miles.
© Kruger Park-W. Schack
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
*
Official Soviet photo
STAMPEDING ACROSS THE SNOW as
the photographer's aircraft swoops over them,
wild reindeer on the Lapland Reserve round
Lake Imandra, U.S.S.R., cast long shadows in
the light of the low-hung Arctic sun. Here
live the remains of herds of wild reindeer,
once widely distributed in northern Europe.
E.N.A. photo-archives, U.S.S.R
VALUABLE FUR-BEARERS such as the
beaver were widely distributed in the forests
of Russia two centuries ago, but as there was
little or no control of hunting, some species
were eventually exterminated. The beavers
themselves were almost wiped out. Today,
however, the stocks are being rapidly res¬
tored through the work of national parks.
The reserve in the Voronezh Region (where
these photos of beavers were taken) in parti¬
cular has played an important part in the
recovery of the animals, and has supplied
them to other parks situated in 29 different
regions of the U.S.S.R. The research carried
out in the Voronezh reserve has made
possible the successful breeding and raising
of beavers in captivity. Thus alongside the.
beavers living in their natural habitat there are
others born and raised in the "beaver farm"«
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
RESERVES IN
U.S.S.R. COVER
6,000,000 ACRES
Today there are sixty nature reserves in
the Soviet Union with a combined
area of over six million acres, rep¬
resenting every kind of countryside in the
U.S.S.R. In the North, for example, there
is the Kandalaksha Reserve (including
islands in the White and Barents Seas)
where there is an abundance of eider,
famed for its down, as well as other
valuable birds. To the east, the Pechora-
Ilich Reserve (along the upper reaches of
the Pechora River) contains a complete
cross-section of the rich vegetation found
in this area. This park is the scene of a
remarkable migration each year when
hundreds of elk pass through, in winter,
going south, and in spring returning to
the north. Naturalists here have success¬
fully domesticated the elk.
The sable, prized for its fur, had at one
time become very rare in Russia because
of uncontrolled trapping. Some twenty
years ago the annual number of pelts
brought in had fallen to about 10,000.
Thanks to protective measures, about a .
hundred thousand sables are now being
trapped each year. The Barguzin Reserve
on the northern shores of Lake Baikal has
done- much to revive sable stocks.
Other reserves in the forest zone have
also been instrumental in preserving and
increasing the country's wild life. One
example is the Voronezh Reserve which is
noted for its beaver.
The Khoper Reserve, situated in the
lowlands around the Khoper River (central
area of Russian in Europe) abounds in the
Russian desman, a mole shrew. The
Khoper and Oka Reserves are now helping
to stock other areas with this animal.
There are also several desert reserves.
One, the Badhiz Reserve in southern Turk¬
menistan, has 150 to 200 of the now rare
kulans (wild asses). "
Extensive forest areas are included in
the Tigrovaya Balka Reserve at the
confluence of the Vaksh and Pyandzh
Rivers, to the north of the Afghanistan
frontier. Many Bokhara deer are found
there and sometimes tigers now rare in
Central Asia come from Afghanistan.
At the Crimean Reserve which has an
area of some 75,000 acres, there are over
1,500 red deer. The large concentration
of deer, however, is beginning to have
adverse effects on the rejuvenation of the
forest in this area, for the animals eat the
young saplings.
The Caucasian Reserve, where there are
many chamois, has done much to restore
the Caucasian aurochs which became
extinct locally in the first quarter of this
century. At the Black Sea Reserve near
the mouth of the Dnieper, there are many
species of local and migratory birds.
These are simply a few examples of the
different types of reserves found in the
Soviet Union. Proposals have been en¬
dorsed by the Presidium of the U.S.S.R.
Academy of Sciences to increase the
reserves to about one hundred.
The above facts are taken from a text
prepared for The Unesco Courier by
L. K. Shaposhnikov, General Secretary of
the Commission for Nature Protection,
U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences.
Photo © Dragesco
THE CAMARGUE, a triangular area covering some 60 square miles in the south of
France, is bounded by the delta of the River Rhone and the sea. It is hemmed around
by dikes built a century or so ago in the hope of making possible the tilling of the
marshy soil, at that time criss-crossed by the many arms of the river. Now flooded,
now rising again above water-level, it is a flat, salt-caked expanse, parched and dried,
which attracts multitudes of water fowl and other migratory birds. Two hundred
different species cross it every year, often making stops between the breeding periods
(104 species build their nests there). Hundreds of thousands of birds fly over it on
their way south. In the Camargue there are the nests of two to three thousand pink
flamingos (below). The white egret (above) the heron and the delightful avocet, are
also found there, and migratory aquatic birds of North Europe are frequent visitors.
Photo © Le Campion
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
LAST REFUGE (Continued)
I. U.C.N.
SEA PARROTS, as puffins are sometimes called, are among the many types of sea birds which find sanctuary in north-west France, on the Seven
Islands Reserve which lies at the entrance to the Channel. A careful watch is kept on this sanctuary and as a result birds have been encouraged to
flock there in large numbers during the mating season. Unusual species which make their homes there besides the puffins are the Bassan gannets.
The idea of preserving the wonderlands
of nature for the benefit bf all is an
American inspiration. The United States
set the example by establishing the first
national park in the world, the Yellowstone
Park. Today the U.S. National Parks
System protects an area of over 24 million
acres, including 28 national parks and
79 natural monuments. The parks are
equipped with excellent touristic facilities
and are visited each year by more than
50 million people in search of tranquillity
and relaxation, which means, in some cases,
the parks are suffering from an excess of
popularity. Even in a country which is
fully aware of the value of its great natural
sites, constant effort is required to protect
them. Control of other areas, such as the
national forests and animal sanctuaries
(National Wildlife Refuges) is exercised in
a well-balanced way so as to ensure
rational use of the resources. In the latter,
wildfowl are given every facility to multiply.
Canada was quick to follow the lead of
the United States and it was one of the first
countries to set up a national parks' system.
The oldest Canadian National Park, Jasper,
covers about 4,200 square miles. The pro¬
vincial parks are as rich, and often as
large, as those administered nationally.
Among Latin America's outstanding
reserves are the Rancho Grande National
Park of Venezuela, the Nahuel Huapi Park
in Argentina and the Barrow Colorado Park
in Panama. Mexico is now making
strenuous efforts to prevent its natural
beauties from being despoiled. Reserves,
varying in size and degree of protection,
exist in nearly all the Latin American
republics, including the countries of the
Caribbean region.
Among the best-known reserves and
national parks of Asia and the Pacific area
14
are two concerned almost exclusively with
protecting a single rare species threatened
with extinction: Oedjong Koelon, in In¬
donesia, for the protection of a few dozen
surviving specimens of the one-horned
rhinoceros of the Sunda Isles; and the
Kasiranga reserve in Assam, India, for the
protection of the Indian counterpart of this
rhinoceros, of which less than 500 specimens
still remain.
Japan protects its spectacular national
sites; Hawaii, its exotic vegetation and
fantastic geological formations; Australia,
its remarkable natural features and its
marsupials kangaroos, koala bears, Tas-
manian wolves and devils, and the curious
duck-billed platypus, an aquatic egg-laying
mammal; New Zealand, its rare birds and
magnificent natural scenery, and what
remains of its ancient forests after the havoc
wrought by mammals imported into this
country, where none originally existed.
Despite its small area, Belgium has
several nature reserves chosen to preserve
different kinds of countryside from sand
dunes to the mountain scenery of the
Ardennes as well as a number of bird
sanctuaries.
The Dutch have always been in the
vanguard where the protection of nature is
concerned. Art and nature are combined
in the "'Hoge Voluwe", where the fine Van
Gogh museum stands in about 15,000 acres
of cultivated parkland, with stags, deer and
sheep roaming freely. In other places,
dunes and wooded slopes are conserved and
bird sanctuaries are maintained.
The United Kingdom has both national
parks open to visitors and strict nature
reserves intended primarily for scientific
research. These are used as open-air
laboratories by teams of biologists studying
problems relating to soil and water
conservation, agriculture or pasturage.
In the Federal Republic of Germany,
reserves total between 345,000 and 395,000
acres. The Saar alone possesses over 700
natural sites and nature monuments. The
German Democratic Republic has 210
nature reserves, 350 protected sites designed
mainly for tourist interest, and 10,000
classified monuments.
The problem of preserving the natural
beauties of their lands has for long been a
preoccupation of Poland and Czecho¬
slovakia. Their many nature reserves
include the Tatra Mountains national park,
lying on the borderland between the two
countries.
The Swiss tradition of nature protection
goes back to the Middle Ages; as early as
the 13 th century steps had already been
taken to preserve certain forests, and the
first game preserve dates from 1542. The
Swiss of today regard their National Park
as a heritage which they hope to keep
intact. It was in Switzerland that the idea
of nature protection on an international
scale was first conceived.
Italy has the splendid Gran Paradiso park
boasting a magnificent herd of ibexes.
Wild goats are protected in Spain's reserves;
in Greece men are striving to protect the
former reputed haunts of the gods.
Yugoslavia has set up an impressive
number of protected areas and the
Scandinavian countries are now wisely
planning to safeguard some beauty spots
which, though not in immediate danger,
may eventually suffer from the effects of
population growth and expansion.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
'AS DEAD AS THE DODO'
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
All too often, it is only when- a
species is in an almost hopeless
state, when there is barely a
handful of survivors, that measures are
taken to save it from extinction, through
the creation of reserves and the strict
control of hunting. Sometimes it is
already too late, and Nature has suffered
another irreparable loss.
There are plenty of examples of
animals, known to our not so distant
ancestors, which disappeared before any
measures were taken to protect them.
One of these was the dronte, or dodo, of
Mauritius, a large, heavy bird as big as
a swan, whose main handicap was its
inability to fly and escape from pursuers.
The dodo was a strange-looking bird
with a kind of hood of bare skin partly
covering its broad head; in place of
wings it had only a few blackish
feathers, and its tail was simply a tuft
of grey feathers. It laid a single white
egg on a clump of grass in the forest. It
was not considered edible by the first
men to explore the island, but those" who
followed were less fastidious, and from
1601 to 1644 dodos were slaughtered
wholesale by passing mariners in search
of food, and were eaten fresh or salted.
When the island was colonized, im¬
ported domestic animals completed the
destruction of young birds. By 1712
the people of the island had almost
forgotten that the dodo had ever existed.
Today the only relics of the bird are the
head and foot of a stuffed specimen at
Oxford, a few drawings preserved in
museums and some skeletons. But the
bird has not been entirely forgotten,
for it is still common to say that
something is "as dead as the dodo".
A companion in misfortune to the
dodo was the great auk, also a
large bird much bigger than the
surviving species of auk. Its wings were
only short stumps', it was dark-backed,
white-bellied, brown-throated and it had
a black beak and feet and white circles
around the eyes. Its undoing was partly
due to the fact that it only laid one egg
a year: a greenish-grey egg covered by
an irregular pattern of black and brown
blotches. Even so, it could have sur¬
vived if it had been exploited with some
restraint, but it had already become rare
by the beginning of the 19th century.
Nesting on cliffs in Iceland, the
Faroes and the Hebrides, the great auk
. was hunted for its oil and fat. The de¬
mand for its eggs made its decimation
The Dodo
The Great Auk
inevitable. The last survivors were
killed off in 1844. A few skins have
been preserved along with several ske¬
letons and a limited number of eggs, for
which collectors will pay as much as
£600 apiece.
Until the early years of this century,
the lovely passenger pigeon, native of
the American continent, was famous for
its migrations. The flocks were so
dense that they darkened the sky; birds
alighted in such numbers that tree
branches collapsed under their weight.
Between 16 and 21 inches long, the bird
had grey colouring with a red lustre and
varying shades of blue on its back. The
last passenger pigeon died in the Cincin¬
nati Zoological Gardens in 1914.
Some people blamed its disappearance
on excessive hunting; others claimed a
virulent disease was the cause.
An animal which undoubtedly was a
victim of the hunters was the quagga, a
kind of brown and dark red zebra, with
I. U.C.N, photos
The Quagga
a striped head and neck and white legs
and tail. It lived in the south-eastern
part of Cape province in South Africa,
where the naturalist Burchell came
across great herds in 1812. The Boers
hunted it for sport and also for food.
Between 1858 and 1878 the animals
prized for their meat, and, after 1865,
for their skins became increasingly
rare. By the end of the 19th century
not one was left alive. A few stuffed
specimens still exist in museums.
Down the centuries belief in the
existence of mermaids has been so
strong that instances of their cap¬
ture have been recorded as fact. As we
know, mermaids or sirens only lived in
legend or the imagination of poets.
There were and are, however, various
kinds of aquatic mammals which might
have been mistaken for the semi-human
beings of folklore. One of these was
Steller's rhytina, belonging to the order
of the Sirenia and called, unromantically,
"Steller's Sea Cow".
As much as 24 feet in length, with a
small head on a rather heavy, dark
brown, sometimes white-spotted or
whiti-striped body, it made its home in
the islands along the east coast of Kam¬
chatka, Bering Island and Copper Island.
Slow, defenceless, trusting and edi¬
ble it represented an ideal prey! Two
naturalists, Bering and Steiler, (1741)
discovered it and then in their wake came
sailors, who landed in the islands
slaughtering and exterminating the ani¬
mals with incredible rapidity. Some
men spent eight or nine months on these
shores collecting provisions for the rest
of their voyage.
Within nine years not a single rhytina
remained in Copper Island. After 1763
ships came more rarely to Bering Island,
no doubt because the stock of meat was
running out; the few animals left were
not worth the voyage. The species
became extinct at the end of the
eighteenth or the beginning of the 19th
century.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
NATURE'S BEST FRIEND: THE SCHOOLCHILD
by Pierre Vernier
Whatever befalls in accordance with Nature should be
accounted good", wrote Cicero in the first century
B.C., while sixteen hundred years later Francis Bacon
remarked that "Nature, to be commanded must be obeyed."
But throughout recorded history, and probably long before,
man has been tampering with Nature, upsetting the delicate
balance which governs all natural life by destroying useful plant
and animal species without any forethought for compensating
the upset by readjustments.
In most cases, destruction was unwanton: King Solomon, and
many others after him, could not have known, for instance,
that untimely deforestation causes erosion, and that, in cutting
down the cedars of the Lebanon, the soil would be swept away
and the hilltops would eventually become bare rock.
And it is one of the ironies of Australian history that the
first settlers in Botany Bay rejoiced that five rabbits had sur¬
vived the long journey to Australia in 1788. Another is that
in 1859 a man was fined £10 for shooting a rabbit on the
property of one John Robertson of Glen Alvie, Victoria. Within
a few years, the same Robertson had spent £5,000 in an
unsuccessful attempt to exterminate rabbits on his property. In
a few short decades, the rabbits had invaded and "conquered"
the whole Australian continent.
These and other examples were cited recently by Mr. Tracy
Philipps, Secretary-General of the International Union for the
Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources, as instances of
man's unthinking or untimely interventions in nature's affairs.
Plant a tree & grow up with it
Visiting Paris to attend a meeting of the International
Advisory Committee on the School Curriculum, spon¬
sored by Unesco, Mr. Philipps stressed that the
problem of nature conservation had become increasingly
serious and urgent since the development of modern indus¬
trial society :
"In the world's two temperate zones", he said, "in highly
industrial and densely populated countries like Britain and
Japan, whole new towns are necessarily being created, and
houses and streets, industrial fumes and pollutions are invading
nature and food-producing land and waters. In new surround¬
ings and in new balances of life and nutritions, new viruses and
new epidemics are coming into existence."
To combat unwanton destruction, Mr. Philipps stressed, peo¬
ple must be made aware of the gravity of the problem. "They
must be shown how the earth and the direct or transformed
products of soil and water and trees are our capital, our capital
asset, at the base of the balance of our nature, of our daily
life, of our nutrition and our health.
"This can best be done by starting in the schools. It can
be demonstrated by first-hand observations and such convincing
lessons as, for instance, the treeplanting projects now carried
out by many schools, where each child plants and, so to speak,
"grows up with his tree", learning its nature, its role and its
soil-and-water value for his own life and his community's.
"Our aim and it has been one of the main aims of the
Union since its foundation in 1948 on the initiative of Unesco
and the French Government our aim is that the child should
be made aware of the nature of his relations with his physical
and natural environment which exercises such a powerful in¬
fluence on all living beings, including man. Every child should
learn to recognize those elements in nature which he can accept
and those which he should be afraid of. It is these simple
things, things which he sees every day on his way to and from
school, which should be included in the curriculum and made
to tie up with lessons on hygiene and nutrition."
A start has been made in this direction. Mr. Philipps ex
plained that some, though still inadequate, elements of this
teaching have already been incorporated through the efforts of
the Union and private initiative in the school syllabuses of
nearly thirty countries from Mexico to the USSR, from
Morocco to Malaya, from Germany to the United States and
Venezuela. In most cases, material prepared by the Union in
the form of picture panels and mimeographed "broadsheets"
containing the outline of simple lessons, is distributed to the
schools through the Union's member societies in widely vary¬
ing countries,' in agreement with the educational authorities.
But, as Mr. Philipps stressed, methods and content of the
teaching programmes must depend on the conditions prevailing
in each country. "These conditions," he said, "vary enormously.
For instance, they are very different in a tropical country, where
nature often remains the prime enemy, from, say, New York
where most children are more familiar with automobiles and
washing machines than with wildlife and plants.
"Children need to know that such is the unerring balance
that the extermination of insect-eating birds or of pollinating
bees or even of forms of life which superficially seem harmful,
can strike back and weaken man or expose him in the tropics
to epidemic attack by his ever-threatening enemies, the denuda¬
tions and impoverishment of soils by himself and floods and
fires, and by increase of insects and viruses."
It is therefore left to the teachers in each country to give
their own illustrations of basic principles in examples taken
from local life and problems already familiar to children. In
French West Africa, for example, a lesson-summary prepared
by the local educational authorities on the basis of the Union's
broadsheet explains that in many parts of the territory wind
is a major enemy, "an enemy which dries up the topsoil, and
carries it away to other regions. Plants wilt, they are smothered
or uprooted, and the desert takes over where once man tilled
fertile fields."
Many simple questions are put to the children, such as these
taken from an Italian lesson: "Have you stopped to think what
substances go into the making of the things you use every day?
The bed you sleep in, the toys you play with, the house you live
in, the clothes you wear, the food you eat?" And the answers
bring home the lesson that nature provides all the raw materials,
that natural resources are a capital which must be carefully
tended and preserved now world population is rapidly growing.
'Cherish the hand that feeds us'
ON the request of the UN Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion, the Union has just produced a booklet on the
techniques of nature conservancy for use in schools in
the South and East Mediterranean area, including countries in
the hinterland of these regions. There will be separate editions
for each country, with local examples. The booklet, which
has been asked for by FAO's international commission of the
Arabic-speaking areas, will include an introduction and a pre¬
face contributed by Unesco's Departments of Education and-
Social Sciences, which have had valuable experience in this
field, particularly through the work of the Fundamental Educa¬
tion Training Centre at Sirs-el-Layyan, operated jointly by
Unesco and the Egyptian Government.
Visual media are also used by the Union in its educational
programme. For instance, "See-at-a-Glance" panels for schools
are now touring France, and have already been requested by
the authorities and organizations in Czechoslovakia, Britain, the
United States and Poland, while one of the Union's main picto¬
rial exhibitions was used in a recent Youth Festival in
Moscow.
And the Union's filmstrips "Cherish the Hand that Feeds
Us" and "Precarious Balance" produced with the aid of
Unesco, are being used increasingly by teachers in many lands
as valuable aids to classroom instruction.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
<sfe
tz*z>t^t-r1
"How many times must I tell you not to ill-
treat animals ?"
© Pourquoi Pas ?, Brussels
-u-y?Lr
Tön S M i TS
"All right, so you don't like me. But,
remember, it's yourfault if we become extinct."
© The New Yorker
-xäL
&f3i*-
Drawing by Pouzet
' FIRE & AXE ' FARMING
ON THE WAY OUT
by G. Watterson
Forestry Division, Food and Agriculture Organization
The day of primitive agriculture in the jungle clearing is drawing to an end.
In jungle farming, the trees were felled and the crops were planted. Then
after a few seasons the soil fertility began to fall and by and by, the
jungle cultivator moved on, the forest moved in and the soil slowly recovered its
fertility.
But the impact of modern life is breaking down this traditional pattern of
agriculture which Jias been followed for centuries in the tropical areas of the
world. Once tribal wars and disease laid jungle populations low, so the little
patches of cultivation in the ocean of the trees were small and infrequent.
But modern medicine and suppression of intertribal wars are sending birth
rates up and death rates down. So the jungle areas must support greater popu¬
lations, and the people who live in the jungle are all trying to get more out
of it than they once did. They are not producing only for themselves; they
are producing also for sale in the towns and on world markets. The old
leisurely cycle of cultivation and forest fallow is speeding up. The scars of
cultivations in the jungle are hardly healed up before they are ripped open
again for fresh cultivation. And the people who are cultivating these patches
in the jungle are hanging on to their land a little longer trying to get a little
bit more out of the flagging soil before they move on. Thus coarse grasses are
springing up, stock are coming in and the natural regeneration of the land by
the forest is being stopped altogether.
Deterioration of the soil in the tropical forests has not yet reached a very
serious stage. But, unless early action is taken to counter it, it will be serious
within a very few years. Now is the time for moderately simple action to
avoid the necessity for very drastic measures in, say, ten or twenty years' time.
There are two or three very promising countermeasures being practised
already against this type of forest deterioration. There is the "corridor system"
of cultivation of the Belgian Congo, for instance. In the Congo, the Belgian
Government, as an experiment, is requiring the jungle cultivators to clear their
land in long corridors rather than haphazard patches. This ensures more rapid
natural seeding of forest when the corridor is abandoned and a new one is
opened up for the needs of the village. The authorities are also preventing the
cultivators from overtaxing the soil by regulating the rotation of crops and
preventing the one piece of land from being cropped too long.
Then there is the regeneration of teak forests in association with shifting
cultivation which started in the Far East, where the people are encouraged
to cultivate newly felled forest land for a period of 2-3 years as long as they
plant young teak trees at the same time as they start cropping. When they
move on to new land they leave behind them not bare earth but fresh plantations
of young teak.
There is a common belief that jungle lands are brimming over with fertility
but the falsity of this belief has become very apparent in the past few decades.
If they are to continue supporting vegetation, jungle lands must be managed
carefully and intelligently.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
Photos © Eibl v. Eibesfeldc
REPTILIAN AGE seems to have returned to the earth in these photos of sea ¡guanas basking in
hundreds on the rocks and cliffs of the Galapagos Islands (below). These iguanas, quite unknown
elsewhere In the world, grow to more than three feet in length. Above, a bloodless ''combat" during
the breeding season. Loser (left) adopts submissive posture while victor remains in threatening one.
GALAPAGOS
Enchanted Islands'
CHATHAM-
\jyeafiwatcr Bay
ROUTE °f the "NOMA"
IN THE -.
GALAPAQ05 ISLANDS /^>cCHARLES
191-W. |8Q°W
© 1924 G.P. Putnam's Sons, New York
'GALAPAGOS: WORLD'S END' was the title given by the American scientist and
author, William Beebe, to the account of a two and a half months' trip he made in I 923
to one of the least-visited corners of the world. This map, taken from his book, shows
the position of the island group in relation to South America and route around the Gala¬
pagos Archipelago followed by the yacht Noma in which Beebe and his party travelled.
In December 1831, the naval vessel Beagle left England for a five-year surveying
expedition to South American, Australian and New Zealand coasts and
islands. On board was a young man, just one year out of university,
serving as unpaid naturalist to the expedition. Charles Darwin little guessed, as
he sailed away, that he would bring back scientific material for a theory that
would rock the world. Darwin devoted special study to the animals he found
on remote islands, and on the Galapagos Islands, 600 miles from the coast of
Ecuador, he made some remarkable discoveries. He noted, for example, that
half the plants and birds were different from species in other parts of the world.
About a third of the shore fish and nearly all the reptiles also differed. These
variations helped to suggest to Darwin the theory of evolution set forth in his
Origin of Species. The Galapagos Islands, which proved so fruitful for this
research, had been discovered in 1535, and named from the Spanish word galápago
"tortoise" because of the giant turtles found there. Since 1832, renamed Archi¬
piélago de Colon, they have belonged to Ecuador. The Galapagos are still a
Noah's Ark of strange and unique forms of life, but because these are threatened
by man and his domestic animals, the International Union for the Conservation of
Nature has proposed that one island be set aside as a reserve and that a permanent
station of biological research and conservation be established. Last July the Union
and Unesco jointly sent Dr. I. Eibl-Eibesfeldt, of the Max Planck Institute für
Verhaltens-physiologie, at Seewiesen, Germany, to investigate conditions in the
islands. On the next page, Dr. Eibl-Eibesfeldt describes some of the amazing
birds and animals found on this unique group of "Treasure Islands for Science".
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
GALAPAGOS
(Continued)
Wonders of a Noah's
Ark off the Coast of Ecuador
by /. Eibl-Eibesfeldt
Max-Planck Institut für Verhaltensphysiologie
Sewiesen-Starnberg, Federal of Germany Republic
L
IFTING its gaunt, grey lava
ridges and peaks out of the
Pacific, some 600 miles from
Ecuador, is a group of islands
whose shores are inhabited by some
of the strangest animals in the
world. They are creatures which
have contributed more to the
development of the natural scien¬
ces than all the rest of the fauna
of Latin America put together.
In 1835 they provided Charles
Darwin with many of the facts
from which he drew the ideas
which he later presented in The Origin of Species.
The numerous islands, islets and reefs of the Galapagos
archipelago have a total area of about 3,000 square miles.
All of them were spewed up by volcanic activity and the
highest of their volcanic cones tower over 5,000 feet above
sea level. The flanks of these cones show gaping fissures
from recent eruptions and are seamed and furrowed with
dried-up streams of black lava. The sun-baked lowlands
(the archipelago lies directly astride the Equator) are
covered with a desert growth of cactus and thorn trees
and only in the uplands is found the refreshing sight of
green vegetation.
The Galapagos Islands were never linked to the
continent of South America and all their plants and
animals must originally have drifted to their shores or
been driven there by great storms. On the basis of
existing fauna, this is the only possible explanation for
the scarcity of species on the islands. For example there
is only one species of land snake and only two land
mammals a rat and a bat. If the islands had ever been
connected with the mainland, so rich in animal species,
the situation would certainly be different (1).
Those animals which succeeded in establishing
themselves, developed, for the most part, into highly
individual types and species which are found nowhere
else in the world. Seventy-seven of the eighty-nine
species of birds which breed in these islands are in¬
digenous. The islands are the unique home of sea iguanas.
These creatures, more than three feet long and looking
like prehistoric "dragons,"' lie out in the sun in hundreds
on the spray-blown cliffs and rocks. Among the colonies
of iguanas, flightless cormorants hatch their eggs and
penguins and sea-lions fish busily in the cool waters.
Here, the extraordinary sight of penguins (of Antarctic
origin) and iguanas (denizens of the tropics) living side
by side seems to be the most natural thing in the world.
But what surprises a stranger to the islands most is the
amazing tameness of the animals. Thrushes will fly to
him and alight at his feet, and a hawk, out of mere
-curiosity, will drop down on a nearby boulder, so close
that he can reach out and touch it. None of the
cormorants, sea-lions or sea iguanas show any signs of
fear probably because no large beasts of prey exist.
Certain parts of the island ceased to be like the Garden
of Eden as soon as the most dangerous of all living
creatures man set foot on them. In past centuries
buccaneers and whalers carried away whole shiploads of
Galapagos, as the Spaniards called the giant tortoises,
(1) Readers' attention is drawn to the 1953 Norwegian archaeologi¬
cal expedition to the Galapagos Islands, and the study published
by Thor Heyerdahl and Arne Skjolsvold entitled "Archaeological
Evidence of pre-Spanish visits to the Galapagos Islands", published
in 1956 by the Society for American Archaeology Editor.
20
which soon became a rarity on most islands and in some
places completely disappeared. The arrival of settlers
during the last century only made matters worse, and the
destruction was completed by cats, dogs and pigs that had
run wild. In 1934 the Ecuadorian Government passed a
law forbidding the capture of indigenous animals, and
some islands were selected as sanctuaries. But laws are
of little use unless they are enforced.
In 1954, twenty years after the enactment of these laws,
I visited the islands with an expedition led by Dr. Hans
Hass, of the International Institute for Submarine Re¬
search. I saw what wonderful possibilities the islands
offered for biological research, but I was dismayed by the
amount of damage that had been done to the animal
population, which represents a unique scientific heritage.
I reported the situation to the International Union for
the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources
(I.U.C.N.) and suggested, among other things, that a
Biological Research Station be set up, thus ensuring the
presence of an official supervisory body which alone could
stop the destruction of the animals.
The I.U.C.N. showed great interest in the project (as did
several American institutions) and it approached the
Ecuadorean Government. The Ecuadorean authorities
approved the scheme and asked
I Unesco to send out an expert to
choose a site for the Biological
Station, to make a preliminary
"census" of the animal population
and to suggest any new protective
measures that might be required.
I was entrusted with this mission
and when I left for the Galapagos
Islands in June 1957, I was
accompanied (thanks to the
support of several U.S. organiza¬
tions such as the Pan-American
Section of the International
Committee for the Preservation
of Birds and the New York Zoological Society) by
Dr. Robert Bowman of the University of California and
also by a photographer and artist from "Life" magazine.
In Ecuador we were given every facility by the authorities,
including air transport to the Galapagos group, and the
use of a naval patrol boat. This enabled us to visit
nearly all the islands during our four months' stay.
The first and foremost fact we were able to verify was
that good specimens of every characteristic species of the,
Galapagos Islands still exist. On James Island (also known
as San Salvador, most of the islands having both English
and Spanish names) we discovered a large colony of fur
seals which were said to have become almost extinct. On
Barrington Island, Narborough Island and on the southern
of the two Las Plazas Islands We found large numbers of
land iguanas. We even discovered some on Indefatigable
Island where they were thought to have become extinct.
But on Seymour Island we found no evidence that they
still exist. This island was used as a military base during
the war and the once numerous land iguanas were prob¬
ably exterminated.
The giant tortoises, to which the Archipelago owes its
name, are now extremely rare on most
islands. It is worth noting, however, that
on Chatham an inhabited island a few Cont'd
have survived despite the fact that they on
were thought to have become extinct here paee 23
fifty years ago. We only came across larger
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
"On the small Las Plazas Islands
I found six sea-lions with bat¬
tered skulls (lower photo).
They were rotting in the sun
and had not even been skinned,"
writes Dr. I. Eibl-Eibesfeldt,
author of the article on the
Galapagos Islands. This senseless
massacre was all the more cruel,
because sea-lions are the gent¬
lest of creatures, as Dr. Eibl-
Eibesfeldt has described in an
account of how, for twenty-
four hours, he was the guest of
a family of sea-lions on the
tiny island of Osborne. He
writes : "There were a few
signs of surprise when I moved
Into the middle of the herd, but
no hostility. Just the same, the
leader, an old male, seemed
anxious when he saw me stret-.
ched out there and he came
closer with a rather threatening
air. When I stood up he prob¬
ably decided that as I outclassed
him in height, he would have to
make the best of things and put
up with me.
"Quietly I sat down again and
soon they had all become used
to me. A young female crawled
up to my feet, nibbled at my
shoes, looked at me for a mo¬
ment with round eyes, then
yawned and went to sleep.
However, the rest of the beach
was alive with games which
both young and old seemed to
be playing. They passed stones
to each other, they squabbled,
and the most agile of them
played at hurdling waves In the
surf. I started to throw pieces
of wood at them, which they
caught, threw up in the air
themselves, and tried to catch
again. There are no animals
more playful than sea-lions.
Only the big male proved to
be an exception. Never relax¬
ing his vigilance, he patrolled
out to sea, carefully protecting
his herd.
"Then came sunset, the shadows
of the bushes lengthened, and
the western sky turned a deeper
and deeper purple. One after
the other the animals returned
to the shore, each one heading
for the rock where it usually
spent the night. But when
the animals had found their
accustomed places, one little
sea-lion still remained alone.
It had moved up and down the
beach frantically searching from
one herd to another. But its
mother was not to be found so
the poor little animal climbed
as high as it could, and, raising
itself up, it began to wail and
utter heart-rending cries. Then
to my surprise from out to sea
there came a deep and soothing
call. Galvanized into action,
the little sea-lion rolled and ran
towards its mother who was
also hurrying to the shore. Soon
it reached the shore and for
fully a minute the two animals
stayed there, affectionately rub¬
bing their muzzles, together.. "
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
FLIGHTLESS CORMORANT with stunted wings found on Galapagos Islands, is the largest
cormorant in the world. Parents take it in turn to seek food for their young. They have an un¬
changing procedure (above): the parent returning to the nest always brings a bunch of sea weed
in its beak. The mate always greets returning bird by raising its head and uttering a special cry.
FRIGATE BIRD defends its young as scientist comes close to photograph a nest on Tower
Island. Frigate birds have breast pouches which they can distend with air like huge bladders,
until they are hidden from the front. Scientists have noted that when a ship appears the female
frigate birds fly to it and swarm around the mast; the males, of a less curious nature, stay put.
Photos © Eib! v. Eibesfeldt
0k g¡ -->* -' "**¡&i&T?.à
;ss® ^m
v »^ . 7r 'Im ' .-i '* ' »> »-* "- '' -
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
GALAPAGOS
(Continued,) Giant lizards clash
in chivalrous trials of strength
colonies of tortoises on Albermarle and Indefatigable
Islands.
Our excursion to the tortoise country on the second of
these two islands Was an unforgettable experience.
Setting out With a local guide We first made our way
through the cactus belt. Prickly pears as high as trees
and giant cacti bordered our path. Then at 300 feet above
sea level the vegetation began to change; the cacti be¬
came fewer and fewer and were replaced by trees and
shrubs. Finally we came to luxuriant, damp woods where
there were Scalsia trees With green leafy tops crowning
their straight, slender trunks, and Pisonia trees Whose
reddish trunks were overgrown With fern. Everywhere,
long dark green tufts of moss hung from the branches,
and the wet and slippery soil was covered with ferns. The
Galapagos Islands certainly offer a variety of contrasts.
I know of no other place where a difference of a few
hundred feet in altitude brings such a radical change in
the landscape. A march of
several hours brought us from
the forest belt into a more open
region. Fresh green meadows
with clusters of trees stretched
before us, and there in the
twilight we came across the first
. bleached shells of tortoises that
had been killed.
The Galapagos Archipelago is historically of
great scientific importance, since it was its
fauna and flora which more than anything else
convinced Charles Darwin of the fact of evo¬
lution.
Next morning when we set out
in search of the tortoises we
discovered the track made by a
giant one quite .close to our
camp. It led to a shallow pool
where we found the beast lying
in the water. It was a remark¬
able size some eight feet
around the body and so heavy
that four of us were unable to
lift it. Then we found others,
and at the same time we saw
traces of the hunters who come
here regularly for the sake
of the tortoise fats. However,
tortoises are now so plentiful on
Indefatigable Island that their
future seems assured. When the
time comes for them to lay their
eggs they move down to the
coastal regions, and in the arid
belt, a few miles from the sea, I found young tortoises,
between four and six inches long. Unfortunately these
young ones are an easy prey for the wild pigs which
abound here.
From the zoological point of view and also that of
scenery the most interesting of the Galapagos Islands is
Narborough. Our experiences here made a vivid im¬
pression on our minds. The island has a giant volcano,
its sides marked by flows of lava from recent eruptions,
which rises steeply out of the sea to a height of 5,000 feet.
There is a central crater several miles across, whose sides
plunge steeply to a blue-green crater lake in which a
second volcano in turn enshrines a lake.
But for zoologists the chief attraction is the coastal zone
which is the home of the largest colonies of sea iguanas
anywhere in the islands. Coming across these huge
lizards sunning themselves in hundreds on the cliffs, the
visitor feels he has been miraculously transported to the
reptilian age.
These sea iguanas are only found in the coastal region.
At ebb-tide they climb down from the cliffs and feed on
the sea-weed uncovered by the receding tide. During the
mating season, when the males become aggressive, their
haunts are the scenes of the most curious fights. The
males choose small areas where they Uve with a few
females. If a rival approaches any of these reserved
areas the male "owner" tries to intimidate him, first by
It provides indeed one of Nature's most
clearcut experiments in evolution, and for this
reason, and as a memorial to Darwin's great
achievement, its flora and fauna should be
studied, preserved and safeguarded.
In addition, a great deal of research remains
to be done on the ecology of the archipelago
and on the details of evolutionary change on
its various islands, and any results would be
of outstanding interest, Accordingly, I hope
very much that a permanent Biological Station
may be set up on the Galapagos with a view
to the scientific study and active conservation
of their native animals and plants.
Julian Huxley
erecting his crest and opening his jaws, then by stalking
round his adversary and repeatedly bobbing his head. If
the rival does not withdraw a strange battle begins.
The two opponents rush at each other with lowered
heads and, skull to skull, try to push each other out of
the way. As soon as one of them finds the other is
stronger he gives in and lies fiat in front of the victor in
a submissive posture. The other simply maintains a
threatening posture until the loser retreats. It is like a
knightly tournament of old, the two animals measuring
their strength, but not harming each other at all. In
behaving this way, they must be guided by an instinct for
preserving their species, for if they were really to fall on
one another with their sharp jaws, they would almost
certainly be seriously injured. As it is, the Weaker of the
two animals, usually a young male, thus has the chance
to mature. Chivalrous fights of this kind occur among
many vertebrates.
It is also on the shores of
Narborough Island that the two
rarest birds of the Galapagos
the flightless cormorant and the
Galapagos penguin are found.
The flightless cormorant is the
largest cormorant to be found
anywhere in the world. Its
wings are stunted, showing that
on islands where there are no
enemies, a function can be lost
without detriment to the species.
Similar examples were provided
by the dodo and the great auk.
Now that these birds are extinct,
the flightless cormorant is one
of the few remaining examples
of this phenomenon. I sat for
hours beside the nesting hollows
watching the parents taking
turns to feed their young. The
procedure was always the same:
the bird which went to catch
fish returned with the bunch of
seaweed in its beak and gave it
to the parent on the nest, this
bird greeted its partner by
raising its beak and uttering a
special cry.
Narborough really seems like
an untouched island. Land iguanas swarm in the interior
and because there are none of the domestic animals
which laid waste the other islands, the giant tortoises
have survived here in great numbers. It is therefore vital
that this island be declared a sanctuary, for even short
visits by settlers or fishermen are likely to change things.
For instance, on the small Las Plazas Islands, I myself
found six sea-lions with battered skulls. Those who kill
these tame animals do so for sport.
Apart from supervision, which would be an essential
part of a conservation programme, education is the other
main hope of remedying the situation. This seems likely
to succeed," judging by the reactions of people with whom ,
we came in contact. They were all proud of their islands
even though they did not realize what extraordinary
animals they had around them. For instance, they had
no idea that the iguanas, which to them were such
commonplace animals, were only to be found in these
islands. When such things were explained to them, they
were willing to learn more and seemed ready to help in
the task of preserving these precious species.
The Ecuadorean Minister of Education has promised
his support, and if the Biological Station can be set up
soon, there is every reason to hope that the islands will,
at least in part, be preserved in their natural state.
This article is copyright and may not be reproduced without permission.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Harmful Animals
Are They Not
Hidden Friends?
by Jean-Paul Harroy
Governor of Ruanda-Urundi
Former Secretary-General, International Union for
the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources
"J*
Persfoto, Amsterdam by Lynwood M. Chace
Since prehistoric times certain animals have been
regarded as "harmful" and as such condemned to
relentless extermination by every possible means.
Sometimes the death sentence was justified on practical
grounds. Beasts of prey were hunted down because they
directly threatened man and his domestic animals. No
one could blame our Neolithic ancestors for their
determined and systematic war against the wild beasts
which menaced their existence. Yet, until recently, some
very different reasons have been invoked in condemning
to death animals which in no way represented a threat
to man. Superstitious beliefs which grew up concerning
them or simply their physical appearance repulsive to
men's eyes were sufficient to make them hated and to
provoke the utmost cruelty towards them.
The most obvious example, of course, is that of the
screech owl. Even today it strikes us as an uncanny bird
with its muted flight, night-prowling habits and to our
ears dismal, haunting cries, not to mention those sounds
it emits which are said to resemble the death-rattle. It
has long been regarded as a bird "'of ill omen", and
throughout the Middle Ages, and even up to the end of
the last century in some places, these owls were crucified
on barn-doors in Central and Western Europe as a pro¬
tection against the Evil One.
Yet the screech owl and other members of the owl family
though the chief victims of such superstitions, were also
the first to win rehabilitation. Peasants are shrewd obser¬
vers of the workings of nature. What they saw of the
owl gradually convinced them that whatever its supposed
guilt in the realm of sorcery, it was more than making
up for it in the more practical sphere of agriculture, by
destroying rats, mice and other rodent-ravagers of the
crops.
Thus was born the idea that even where an animal has
been judged as harmful to human interests universally,
there may have been a miscarriage of justice; that a
fuller investigation may reveal it to be a friend of man.
People were beginning to see that judgement should not
be pronounced too hastily.
But this first rehabilitation did not immediately open
the way to the modern theory of natural balance which
maintains that every living creature has its part to play
in the biological complexes biocenoses, as ecologists call
them in which the removal of a single link produces
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January' 1958
National Farks Board by W. F. Schack
effects which are nearly always unpredictable and in the
long run harmful.
Until very recently game-laws of nearly all countries
made wide use of such terms as "noxious" or "harmful ani¬
mals", "'vermin!" and "pests". Laws of this kind still exist
in some parts of the world, for instance in Africa, where
beasts of prey, snakes, crocodiles and a few luckless birds
and mammals can be destroyed by any means whatever,
without possession of a licence. Fortunately, however,
the idea is now growing that the vast majority of such
judgments on animals should be reviewed because they
have been based on superficial evidence.
In this respect, Africa itself has just provided a classic
example of a complete reversal of policy. Until recently
the leopard figured here on the "black list" of harmful
animals and its destruction was encouraged by the au¬
thorities and actively pursued by all those who were able
to do so.
The result was soon felt. Over, vast areas the leopard
became practically extinct. At the same time, wild pigs
and baboons, whose young had previously been decimated
by the leopard, increased so greatly that farmers found
the destruction of their crops by these animals far more
THE OTTERAND THE FISHERMAN
Man frequently seeks to destroy a particular form of wildlife that
he believes to be harmful to his interests, without thinking of conse¬
quences that may arise. In doing so he risks upsetting the delicate
balance which exists between the four essential elements of his life
and nourishment: water, soil, flora and fauna. The otter, for
example, had a bad reputation as a fish robber (1) and in some
countries fishermen began to destroy their rival (2). At first after
the otter had gone there was fishing in plenty (3), but suddenly the
fish started to vanish (4). Why ? The otter had been catching
mostly sick fish which had less chance to escape him. When the
otter disappeared, sickness spread among the fish and destroyed
many. (These drawings are taken from "Precarious Balance", a
film strip prepared by the I.U.C.N. with Unesco's assistance.)
disastrous than the damage previously done in poultry-
yards and sheepfolds by the leopards. Several govern¬
ments, including that of British East Africa, have openly
admitted their mistake and have transferred the leopard
from the category of harmful animals to the list of pro¬
tected ones yet another convincing lesson, encouraging
us to think twice before condemning.
In general, and for good or bad, sentiment still
influences man's attitude to and treatment of animals.
Public feeling aroused all over the world by the fate or a
dog involved in the experiments conducted with an arti¬
ficial satellite is a recent and striking example of this.
Another example is the basic difference of the reaction
to the destruction of what are regarded as predatory
creatures, according to Whether they are vertebrates or
invertebrates. In West Africa the crops are ravaged, to
an extent which is catastrophic for the population, by
flocks of birds, the Quelea Quelea or weaver bird, and
by swarms of locusts. Faced with the famines caused by
this repeated devastation, the authorities have resorted
to measures which unfortunately must be brutal to be
effective for the destruction of Quelea and locusts alike.
Associations and individuals protested strongly against
the mass killing of the birds but no one deprecated the
slaughter of the locusts, probably because people still
think of them as "'the plague of Egypt".
Even so, in the twentieth century, with its rational
outlook and increasingly planned and controlled econo¬
mies, action taken on utilitarian grounds is yearly increas¬
ing at the expense of purely emotional behaviour.
The problem therefore is to determine the pertinence of
these utilitarian aims and strike a balance between them.
When, the original reason for the verdict of destruction
ceases to be the only factor under consideration, it may
be found to be offset; or even more than offset, as in the
case of the owl and the leopardby other factors, favour¬
able to human interests, but previously underestimated
or unrecognized. Unfortunately, the precise importance
of these factors is often revealed only when
the species has been wiped out and the loss
of its activity begins to be felt. Cont'd
A practical illustration of this idea of 0n
striking a balance is given in an excellent next page
pamphlet, "Predator Control. Why and
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
HARMFUL ANIMALS?
(Continued) THINK BEFORE YOU STRIKE TO KILL
How", published by the Conservation Commission of the
State of Missouri, U.S.A., in 1955 (Jefferson City; I. T. Bode,
Director). "For instance," it says, "we might study the
food-intake of a number of coyotes and find that of their
total foods, they killed about $500 worth of poultry and
livestock. But most of the rest of the food was mice
and rats which, if predators hadn't eaten them, would
have ruined $700 worth of crops. The answer seems clear:
we have a $200 profit in those coyotes..."
This theoretical example, incidently, is based on a
proven fact. In 1953 the ranchers of the Toponas district
of Colorado, U.S.A. embarked on a campaign for the
extermination of coyotes. They abandoned it on discover¬
ing that the value of the lambs and calves Whose lives
were thus saved was less than that of the increasing
. damage inflicted on crops
and grazing grounds by the
rabbits and rats which now
began to swarm over the
district.
Which is the best policy:
complete non-intervention,
leaving carnivorous ani¬
mals to do the useful ser¬
vice of killing off sick or
crippled herbivora, or, on
the contrary, the organized
slaughter of a certain num¬
ber of beasts of prey, to
help hoofed animals to
increase in number? So
far, the . biologists working
in national parks and na¬
ture reserves have not yet
agreed which is the best
course to follow.
The otter is considered as
an enemy by most fisher¬
men. Yet in pools where
otters were exterminated
in Poland, for instance
there was a decrease in the
number of fish. Disease now
spread more rapidly since
the disappearance of the
sharp-fanged beasts which
had formerly caught and
devoured any fish weaken¬
ed and slowed down by
infection. In Switzerland,
where the otter had been
classed among the so-called
harmful animals which could be killed during part of the
"close season" for other animals, there was a change of
view and it was proposed to make the otter a "Federally
protected" animal as had been done with the leopard in
Africa.
In Africa, the crocodile is universally detested, but its
status has still not been established to the satisfaction of
ecologists. A recent report of the East African Fisheries
Research Organization listed the useful work done by
crocodiles (destruction of insects, shell-fish, predatory
crustaceans, diseased fish etc.), though it concluded: "It
is a great pity that they also sometimes attack human
beings."
Science is putting more and more effort into weighing
up these pros and cons. On Valcour Island, in Lake
Champlain, U.S.A., a study following a costly operation
to reduce the number of predators, showed that for the
first four years the birds and small mammals increased
in number. So did the popular "game" grouse and hares.
But once this period was at an end, disease became
26
Taken from the film strip "Precarious Balance"
THE RAT AND THE MONGOOSE. In Jamaica, in 1872, the mon¬
goose was brought into the island to kill off the rats which were causing
serious damage to sugar cane plantations. Ten years later the mongoose
had killed off nearly all the rats and, looking for new food supplies, it
started to destroy lambs, kids, pigs, poultry, kittens and puppies. Then
wildlife also began to suffer: the greater part of the island's fauna vanished
into the hungry stomach of the mongoose. Eventually the mongoose
killed so much that its own food supply was scarce and its numbers
declined. The rat, meanwhile, had become a tree dweller and raised
its families in safety. Thus a new balance was established in the midst
of the destruction. And the rats were still there, for in three years
a couple of rats may produce as many as 257,762 descendants.
rampant and the numbers of animals declined rapidly.
Other research has little by little revealed the unsus¬
pected usefulness of some much-abused species. The
black cockatoo, hunted down in Australia because of the
harm it does to shrubs, has recently been recognized for
its value in keeping down' the beetle known as the dendro-
phagous longicorn. This year the shark has been revealed
as a prolific source of batylic alcohol, valuable in the
treatment of certain pathogenic effects of radio-activity.
The porcupine, another enemy of trees with a price on
his head, is now said to be less of a criminal than was
previously thought. The extenuating circumstances in
his favour are that by stripping off the bark of young trees
he carries out a process of "'selection felling" and that in
wintertime he is unintentionally useful to the deer by
scattering the ground with
vegetable refuse which
would otherwise be out of
their reach.
Finally, I should like to
mention two aspects of the
campaigns or policies for
the extermination of
"harmful" species which
may have greater conse¬
quences than the promotors
intend.
One concerns the method
of extermination. In many
cases this is not specific
enough so that in trying to
get rid of real or imaginary
predators, we also destroy
species which are definitely
useful, or seriously disturb
some important natural
balance. Traps and poison
do not discriminate between
harmless species and those
they are intended to kill.
The best-known instance
of this is the large-scale
spraying of chemical in¬
secticides, which sometimes
exterminate an entire en¬
tomological species
leading to the starvation
of insectivorus animals
and are also harmful to
crustaceans, fish, batrachia,
birds and even mammals.
Thus great damage can be
done when only one '"harmful" insect species is attacked.
The other aspect which I feel should be mentioned
relates to those campaigns to eliminate predators as a
protective measure which are over-successful. After the
predator has been eliminated from the biological cycle the
numerical increase which was sought after for certain
species is achieved. But in some cases proliferation is not
impeded by disease. Is success necessarily a good thing?
There is the example of the Kaibab plateau in
north-western Arizona, where, following the extermination
of wolves and pumas, the deer of the plains have increased
to such an extent that hundreds of them are now starving
for lack of pasture. And without becoming involved in
polemics, we might also remind ourselves that our mastery
of the microscopic predators on the human race, since
the time of Pasteur, is now resulting in a staggering and
in many ways alarming increase in the world's population.
Is mankind preparing for itself the fate of the Kaibab
deer? Make no mistake about it, the question "Friend
or enemy?" deserves some serious thought.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
The roof over our head, whether
made of brick, slate or straw, is
an offering of Nature, and so are
the walls that shelter us, and even
the windows that let in the light.
Whether we travel by stage coach or
carriage as in the past, whether by the
"iron horse" or whether in modern
cars, now as then the materials are
furnished by Nature, source of the
iron, and the stone, the coal and the
spark, the sand and the water. But
Nature is a whole, a sum total of self-
adjusting elements that intersect and
depend on one another like the com¬
plicated wheels of a chronometer.
These elements are held in a delicate
balance, more or less unstable, each
factor being linked with all the others.
All that is required to destroy that
balance is one element, one disturbing
agent, one blundering interference.
One fillip is enough to bring the card-
castle toppling and to start a chain of
repercussions that involve a series of
unexpected catastrophes. The com-
I.U.C.N.
FLOURISHING FEATHER TRADE in the early years of this century led to millions of seabirds
being killed in the volcanic and coral islets to the north-west of the main Hawaiian Archipelago.
Since then many varieties of birdspetrels, terns, albatrosseshave been given protection in the
Hawaiian Islands National Wildlife Refuge. Above, a fairy tern on its nest in the National Refuge.
position of a landscape, for example,
is not a matter of chance. It is
decided by the nature of the soil and
the climatic conditions. These con¬
ditions, in their turn, bring about the
appearance of whatever plant, what¬
ever tree and as a result, whatever
animal may find the environment
there suitable for its needs. It all
adds up to form an association in
which the elements are intimately
intricate.
Hippos raise fish crops
The interrelationship of natural
elements is illustrated strikingly
by the role played by insects in
pollination of plants. Certain in¬
dustrial crops are entirely dependent
on this. Without bees, our orchards
would bear no fruit. The olive groves
of Sardinia were sterile for an entire
season after insecticides, spread to
exterminate malaria mosquitos, had
destroyed the bees in the region as
well. The relations between living
beings cannot always be foreseen, they
are often linked in most unexpected
ways. Who, for instance, would think
of linking hippopotami, that live part
of their mysterious existence in African
waters, with fish farming? But they
are valuable auxiliaries, especially in
the case of East African lakes that are
fed a relatively small quantity of
water by their tributaries, where
every plant and animal plays the role
of a regulator. The excrements of the
hippopotami fertilize the water
depths, favouring the formation of
phytoplankton which, for its part,
nourishes the tilapias. These indigen¬
ous fish are widely used by large fish
farming enterprises and supplement
the protein so essential to the peoples
of the African Continent.
Plundering and blundering
Man himself is an element of
Nature. It is normal that he
should draw his own subsistence
from the natural world. The complex
mechanism that is called "natural ba¬
lance" will be seriously
hampered only when Cont'd
human levies on on
natural resources are
mismanaged and
next page
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
THE GOLDEN
EGG (Continued)
MAN THE SORCERER'S APPRENTICE
immoderate. The coexistence of living
beings in a natural state takes place
in accordance with biological laws
governed by their vital needs. But
man, through his ingenuity, dispens¬
ed with the rules that limited his
population. He discovered hygiene
and developed antibiotics, comfort
and means of achieving it. He found
ways of preventing infant mortality
and of prolonging life for the aged.
Consequently, the human population
is growing at a fantastic rate: two
and half billion today, four billion by
the end of this century. It is hardly
surprising that this rising figure
should have serious repercussions
on natural associations.
Dwindling fossil fuels
Among those resources which are
indispensable to man, certain of
them are net renewable. The
exploitation of coal and oil and other
products furnished by the mineral
kingdom cannot be continued indef¬
initely without risking the exhaustion
of the source. On the other hand, ve¬
getable and animal living resources on
which our lives are dependent, will
renew themselves indefinitely on the
condition that moderation and good
sense govern their use. They must be
used as shares and not as the appro¬
priation of capital. The soil is our
basic capital. The well-being of a
country is linked with the few inches
of arable land, formed of decomposed
organic matter, and of soil nutrients.
The farm produce which forms a large
part of our economy depends on the
thickness of this fertile layer, and so
does the food for the livestock which
is also part of the human diet.
Green anchors of the soil
Where man has inherited the
land intact, it is the vegeta¬
tion forests or prairies that
anchors the arable layer to the base
soil. This plant life has protected it
against the violence of the elements
in such a way as to balance the
inevitable losses against the rate of
renewal. . Vegetation also contributes
to the formation of the organic
matter that nourishes the soil and
helps the circulation of water and
nutritive salts. It shelters the earth,
especially in tropical regions, from the
burning force of the sun which would
oxidize organic matter, and render
the top layers sterile. All forests con¬
tribute to the formation and renewal
of humus. Trees hold the hillside
soils and protect the shallow leached
mould from the torrential tropical
eroding rains. One of the most im¬
portant roles played by forests is
in stabilizing the water cycle.
Vegetation facilitates evaporation.
28
The roots then absorb precipitation
moisture, allowing it to filter slow¬
ly through the soil feeding the
underground water tables, and
maintaining them at a high level.
This process of percolation, aided by
the vegetation which keeps the soil
porous and permeable, takes place
gradually. Thus, the forest earth
becomes a reservoir in anticipation of
dry spells. On the other hand, rain
and snow held by vegetation and
filtered through the soil will not swell
floods by their volume, but, purified by
their passage through dead leaves and
humus, will flow crystal-clear into
streams. The trees are thus one of
the surest stabilizers of natural balan¬
ce, controlling the supply of water
under the ground surface as well as
above it, channelling it to rivers and
torrents. They are bulwarks against
spring floods and summer droughts.
Science seeks living relics
Fauna, too, is a valuable resource.
Wild game has played a part in
human economy since ancient
times, and numerous peoples are still
entirely dependent on it for food and
clothing. Our own domestic livestock
can be traced to certain wild species.
In the isolated habitat provided by
certain islands, ancient forms of vege¬
table or animal life have been able to
survive, cut off and safe from the
threat of large types of aggressive
fauna and the competition of intro¬
duced species. These living relics
offer remarkable testimonies to scien¬
ce and have formed a basis for
studies in evolution. Darwin's obser¬
vations on the finches of the Galapa¬
gos Islands inspired him in his
revolutionary deductions. Australian
marsupials have provided a curious
phenomenon of evolution by conver¬
gence, and there is much that remains
to be learned through their study.
The Koala is among these marsupials.
Hunters in pursuit of their fur have
destroyed ten million on these bears
in the short space of half a century.
The loss of such subjects of research
would be an irrevocable mistake.
Death of the land
To increase his crops and acquire
more land to meet the ever in¬
creasing demands of a rapidly
growing population, man clears new
land, denudes it and exposes it to the
intemperate elements, to heat, wind
and storm. Rains wash the soil and
rob it of mineral salts. The terrible
process of erosion sets in. Erosion
costs the United States alone around
four thousand million dollars a year;
in Northern China, vast territories,
formerly forested, have been victimiz¬
ed by its destructive force. They have
become useless expanses of dust and
rock. The inhabitants of these areas
find their only firewood by uprooting
. stumps left in the ground after it has
been cleared. Nevertheless, in the
6th century A.D. the great philosopher
Lâo-tseu had already warned his peo¬
ple against the tragic consequences
that would arise from a policy of
deforestation.
Deserts on the march
Paying no heed to the inevitable
consequences of their actions, the
agriculturist and the herdsman
push ever farther, one seeking fresh
fields, the other new pastures. They
burn the forest for it is the quickest
and most destructive method. They
leave behind exhausted and sterile soil
and desolate landscapes, and they will
push yet farther. This is one of the
causes for the advance of desert land.
Certain writers hold that the Sahara
has encroached upon 300 kilometres
of African land during the past three
centuries. Once the forest has gone
and the earth's green mantle brutally
torn away, the soil is at the mercy of
winds that carry off the valuable top
soil. In the United States, this wind
erosion carved out the "Dust Bowl".
The exodus during the ensuing years
is well remembered. The farmers
were forced to leave the forbidding
regions where there was no longer any
land that would yield crops. Europe
itself, though favoured by a mild
climate, is now beginning to know the
consequences of deforestation. Dust
storms have occurred, notably in the
vicinity of Hanover (Germany) where
30 per-cent of the surface of fields was
carried off by the wind to such an
extent that the roads were sometimes
covered with about 15 inches of
humus and sand. For the same
reasons, other Eastern European
countries are threatened with gradual
transformation into steppes.
Incas' forbidden islands
The old tale of the goose that laid
the golden egg is still to the
point. Peru's chief source of
wealth is guano, a manure deposited
by certain birds on Peruvian islands.
Of these birds, the Cormorant is the
foremost producer of this valuable
resource. Guano Was so important
that even the Incas were Well aware
of its value, and punished by death
any intruder who ventured to these
protected islands without permission.
Virtually abandoned for many years,
the supply of guano replenished itself
until a considerable stock had
accumulated. Finally, in the middle
of the last century, exploitation
started on a large scale. The birds
themselves were looked upon as harm¬
ful to crops and were driven from
their nests by boys specially hired for
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
rCLASS VII LAND
USIS
TREAT THE LAND RIGHT. The U.S. Soil Conservation Service's formula for sound land treatment and use is: Treat the different kinds of land
on a farm according to their individual need or condition; use each kind according to its capability for continued safe and economical production.
Each conservation measure is specifically designed to fit the land on which it is used. Taken on a South Carolina Farm, this photograph, shows eight
different classes of land, each differing from the others in soil or slope, or both. The first four are those suitable for cultivation: (I) Requires good
soil management practices only. (2) Moderate conservation practices necessary. (3) Intensive conservation practices necessary. (4) Perennial vegeta¬
tion-infrequent cultivation. The second four classes of land shown here are those not intended for cultivation, but for pasture, hay, woodland and
wildlife: (5) No restrictions in use. (6) Moderate restrictions in use. (7) Severe restrictions in use. (8) Best suited for wildlife and recreation.
the job. Tne supply was rapidly
exhausted until at last, in 1909, the
Peruvians decided to create a con¬
servation society, "Compania Admi¬
nistradora des Guano", which is now
a member of the I.U.C.N. Among the
typical cases where the natural ba¬
lance is destroyed, those involving the
introduction of a foreign species info
a new environment seem to react in
the most unpredictable ways. In
these cases too, man is the sorcerer's
apprentice. Although often uninten¬
tionally, he introduces a plant or an
animal into an environment where it
is freed from whatever natural enemy
controlled it in its original habitat
and prevented it from reaching
excessive numbers. The first step to
avoid such dangers is to see that the
general public understands the
problems. An enlightened citizen
will more readily respect regu¬
lations when the authorities impose
them and will even encourage them
when necessary. The I.U.C.N. has
assumed this role of educator and
informer as one of its primary func¬
tions. The message must be address¬
ed above all to the young. Towards
this end, the I.U.C.N. organizes or
sponsors international camps for the
study and protection of nature where
young people of diverse nationalities
can exchange ideas and share their
experiences. The first of these camps
was held at Houyet, Belgium, in the
summer of 1952, and it has since
become an annual event, held each
year in a different part of the world.
Nature ignores frontiers
It is essential that the youth of the
universe should realize that all
nations aspiring to prosperity
must recognize the great importance
of conserving their natural resources.
The International Union for the Con¬
servation of Nature has spoken in the
interests of a progressive transition
towards new knowledge and new
understanding for children in primary
scnools, in their relations with their
physical and natural environment.
It has strongly urged that the simple
principles of the conservation of
nature and natural resources be in¬
corporated in primary school pro¬
grammes in urban as well as rural
areas. Nature ignores the political
boundaries set by man. Regulations,
if they are to be effective, often call
for concerted efforts on an inter¬
national scale. This applies, for
instance, to the conservation of marine
species, migratory birds, and to the
prevention of pollution of the seas by
oil residue, a practice that results in
general pollution of coasts and
coastal waters. Bathers complain of
the black sticky residue that spoils the
beaches and clings to the rocks, robb¬
ing much of the charm from their
summer pastime. The fish suffer,
the owners of pleasure-boats are
dissatisfied and the sea birds perish
by the hundreds of thousands.
Unable to fly or to seek food, they are
doomed to die from cold and hunger.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
THE GENTLE LITTLE GOAT:
ARCH DESPOILER OF THE EARTH
Whenever specialists meet to
consider the question of soil
erosion and its effect on food
production the talk always comes
round to a familiar, domesticated
animal the goat. You might well
wonder what connexion there could
be between such an unremarkable
animal and great world problems like
soil erosion and famine.
Consult an encyclopaedia and you
will probably read: "Goat. A ru¬
minant quadruped of the genus
Capra. The common goat is found
in all parts of the world ; it is easy
to feed and valuable for its milk and
meat. Goat-hair is used for weav¬
ing." At first sight the goat seems to
be an outstandingly useful animal,
making an important contribution to
world food supplies.
Now consult some specialists in the
field of natural resources in particu¬
lar those from Unesco, the Food and
Agriculture Organization and the
International Union for the Conserva¬
tion of Nature and Natural Resources
(I.U.C.N.) and ask them their opin¬
ion of the goat. Their unanimous
conclusion : The goat is man's worst
enemy.
It is largely due to the goat that
the whole of the Mediterranean basin
has been stripped of trees. Not
content with grazing the grass, the
goat tears it up by the roots and does
the same with the seedlings of trees
and shrubs, which never have a
chance to grow and spread.
Worse still, the goat will stand on
its hind legs to get at any low bran¬
ches it can reach and even manages
to climb some trees. No hillside is
too steep to daunt this prodigiously
agile creature, and no seedling, even
if hidden under a small stone,
escapes its voracious appetite. By
thus destroying every trace of vegeta- '
Belin-I. U.C.N, photos
THE DESERT MAKER. It is largely due to the goat that the whole of the Mediterranean basin
has been stripped of its trees. Not content with grazing the grass, the animal tears it up by the
roots and does the same with seedlings of trees and shrubs, which never have a chance to grow
and spread. North Africa in particular has suffered from the goat's insatiable appetite. In the
Atlas Mountains its destruction of trees has exposed the earth to erosion by rain and wind.
by
Raymond Furon
Assistant Director,
Muséum d'Histoire Naturelle, Paris
Member of the Académie des Sciences
d'Outre-Mer
tion the goat exposes the naked soil,
especially on hillsides, to rain and
sun which quickly cause violent
erosion.
Much of Spain has been stripped by
flocks of goats and sheep which of
the two animals was the greater
culprit and did the most damage will
never be known and much the
same can be said for the entire
Mediterranean area. Already in Ro¬
man times flocks of sheep and goats
were driven up seasonally into the
wooded mountains, which Were
gradually deforested. In the second
century B.C. no less a thinker than
Cato wrote : "If, owing to lack of
water, you have no natural grass-
grown meadow land, prepare some
dry grazing-ground on the steepest
possible slope." This bad advice was
followed and resulted in the dis¬
appearance of the holly-oak forests
which steadily receded as the ever-
increasing flocks climber higher.
In North Africa the final ruin of
the Berber country was brought about
by the introduction of great flocks of
goats. In Morocco the cedar tree is
now rare, and no young cedars have
been growing up since goats were
established there. In the Western
Sahara the Moors cut down the
mimosas to provide easy feeding for
their goats. A leading botanist, Au¬
guste Chevalier, has described how
these animals, not content with
destroying the vegetation, "literally
graze the soil, to get at the seeds of
grasses and other plants which have
been scattered over the surface and
which might have sprouted during
the next rainy season." The whole of
Africa, from North to South, and
including Madagascar, has experienc¬
ed the same misfortune. In Asia the
limestone mountains of Syria, the
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
Lebanon and Israel have been laid
bare by goats whose ravages can be
traced as far as China.
When expressed in general terms
the tremendous damage done by
goats is always received with a certain
amount of scepticism. Some people
defend the goat and call for an in-
dictement of other guilty parties such
as sheep, rabbits, opossums and all
animals which can do serious harm to
vegetation.
Naturally it is difficult to produce
figures which reveal the damage done
by goats alone, since the process has
been going on for centuries. But, in
the most suitable places for in¬
vestigating the disastrous work of
goats islands we find damning and
irrefutable evidence.
Fodder for the sharks
We know that when the old-time
navigators sailed away in
search of virgin lands and
unknown islands, they always took
with them some domestic animals,
especially goats, and that they left a
few pairs in each newly-discovered
territory. In uninhabited or sparsely
inhabited regions these animals, once
they managed to acclimatize them¬
selves, ended by multiplying beyond
measure. Outstanding examples are
the horses of South America and the
rabbits of Australia. Even more
striking is the story of the goat.
The island of St. Helena, in the
middle of the Atlantic, was discovered
in 1502. It was entirely uninhabited
and covered with forests. In 1513
the Portuguese brought goats there.
Two centuries later these animals
had almost completely destroyed the
vegetation. In 1745 the Governor of
the island complained of their de¬
vastations, forseeing the disappear¬
ance of the last patches of forest and
in particular of a special ebony-tree.
His complaint went unheeded and no
action was taken until 1810, when
the Governor had every goat on the
island destroyed. By then it was too
late ; for lack of protective vegetation
the fertile soil formed from the
volcanic rock had been swept into the
sea by erosion, leaving a naked,
sinister crag.
Charles Darwin in the 19th century
reported that the Juan Fernandez
Islands in the Pacific (from 1704
to 1709 one was the home of a ship¬
wrecked Scottish mariner, Alexander
Selkirk, on whose experiences Daniel
Defoe based his story of Robinson
.Crusoe) had formerly been covered
with sandalwood trees. These had
now nearly all been destroyed by
goats, the only remaining trees being
on some uninhabited islets. The
situation on these islands is today so
serious that when the I.U.C.N. met in
Caracas in 1952 it asked the Gov¬
ernment of Chile, to whom the
islands belong, to protect the re¬
maining vegetation by destroying
all the goats.
In Cyprus the goats carried on the
work of destruction on whatever
remained of the forests after the
depredations of the Phoenicians and
those who followed them.
In the Hawaiian Islands goats have
become such a scourge that children
AGILE AND VORACIOUS, the goat will not only stand on its hind legs to get at any low branches
it can reach, but even climbs into a tree of the right shape and devours its leaves. In Morocco
cedar trees are now rare and no young cedars have been growing up since goats were taken there.
organize drives in which the animals
are chased down to the beaches to be
killed and thrown to the sharks.
All these are specific and document¬
ed examples which admit of no
argument. These are well-known
islands arid their vegetation has been
destroyed by goats and by goats
alone.
Man is also to blame
Responsible people long ago realiz¬
ed that the goat was a dan¬
gerous animal. In 16S6 the
Parliament of Provence in France
decreed that goats were no longer to
be allowed to enter the woods, which
had already suffered heavily. But
public resistance was so stubborn that
the act of Parliament was repealed
in 1731 and replaced by another law,
far less stringent and therefore
ineffectual.
The solution to the problem is a
very simple one: the complete exter¬
mination of goats in the most seri¬
ously threatened districts and the
proper supervision of flocks in areas
(if any still exist) which can still
sustain them without danger.
Many specialists would like to see
the goat become extinct, except in
zoos. This, the ideal solution, is in
fact unattainable because it fails to
take account of certain facts.
The goat behaves not only in
accordance with its nature, but is
also a domestic animal, belonging to
man and wreaking destruction wher¬
ever man leads it. A goat tied to a
stake in the ground can do little or
no harm. A flock of goats in a valley
meadow will do scarcely more damage
than a flock of sheep. But a flock of
goats roaming freely over a mountain
district where the vegetation has
already suffered will end by ruining
it completely. So a way must be
found to limit the rights of the owner
of such a flock and prevent him from
maintaining it at a cost which spells
ruin for the land.
The obvious answer would seem to
be a law or regulation to fit the case.
Laws do in fact exist in some coun¬
tries but are generally not respected
and goats thus ravage the countryside
without any official
efforts being made to
prevent them.
In North Africa, in
the Sahara and in the
territories south of it,
31
Cont'd
on
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
GENTLE LITTLE GOAT (Continued)
flocks of goats are still destroying
vegetation, including new plantations
made by the Forestry Departments.
To bring all the culprits to book would
call for legal action on such a vast
scale that the Administration has had
to forego imposing penalties.
Highlighting the facts about erosion
and the part played by goats has
made no impression whatever on the
people it primarily concerns whether
they be goat-owners, politicians or
senior government officials. From
Madagascar come these striking offi¬
cial figures. About 1936 the Adminis¬
tration introduced Mohair goats into
the south of the Island. There were
a thousand of them in 1937, 23,000 in
1946, 147,000 in 1948, 203,000 in 1949
and 276,585 in 1950. Already the
goats have transformed a number of
areas into desert.
Thrice-proven guilt
What proof do we have that the
extermination of goats would
be a beneficial thing? The
same question has been asked about
the rabbit whose ravages have been
widely verified by agricultural and
forestry experts. When myxomatosis
suddenly reduced the number of
rabbits, the I.U.C.N. made a survey
(Edinburgh, 1956) which proved quite
definitely that vegetation had im¬
proved since their numbers had
declined. In the case of the goat,
three equally convincing experiences
can be cited in Cyprus, Venezuela
and New Zealand.
In Cyprus, at the request of the
Forestry Department, the local Gov¬
ernment passed an "Anti-goat" law
which came into force in 1914 after
its purpose had been widely explained
to the population.
There was no question of exter¬
minating goats by official decree, so
the people were consulted. The Gov¬
ernment promised to pay for the
goats and to provide cultivable land.
In any village where at least ten
owners of land and goats favoured
slaughtering the animals, the local
leader called a meeting of all goat-
owners, explained matters to them
and asked them to vote for or against
the destruction of the flocks. When a
majority agreed, the number of goats
was reduced and the remaining ones
were kept tied to stakes. During the
Second World War submarine action
in the Mediterranean menaced food
supplies by sea and the island had to
become largely self-supporting. The
anti-goat law was strictly enforced
despite many protests. Its good results
are now self-evident. Reafforestation
is proceeding normally and the re¬
duction in cultivable land has halted.
Venezuela's example comes from
the area of the Tacagua river-bed,
which runs between Caracas and La
Guaira. This was once a prosperous
district as can be seen from the ruins
of many farms and mills. In 1934
it had lost all its inhabitants and the
forests had disappeared from its
hillsides. By 1947 the situation was
catastrophic and natural balance had
been completely destroyed. As Pro-
32
fessor Francisco Tamayo explained to
the I.U.C.N. congress in Caracas in
1952, for three quarters of a century
the goats had been at work destroying
everything that had survived the
woodcutters.
Then the Venezuelan Forestry De¬
partment set up an experimental sta¬
tion in the area and began reaffores¬
tation. Its first demand was that all
goats should be banned from the area,
and a law was passed prohibiting the
presence of flocks on any land with a
slope of more than 1/7, and prescrib¬
ing heavy fines and imprisonment for
recalcitrant goatherds.
The Government agreed to buy up
the goats and between 1948 and 1952
it paid for some 16,000 belonging to
77 families living in the area. In
three years there was a great im¬
provement, thanks to reafforestation
and the re-growth over the area of
self-seeding grasses which were no
longer devoured by the herds.
In a report from New Zealand,
written in 1954, Mr. G.G. Atkinson
describes how the Mount Egmont
National Park was invaded around
1920 by goats which farmers had im¬
ported ten years earlier to destroy the
brambles which hindered crop cultiva¬
tion. Campaigns to wipe out the
goats went on from 1926 to 1943 and
altogether over 15,000 were slaughter¬
ed in the National Park. To put an
end to any further danger the farmers
also killed off their goats. Mr. At¬
kinson declares that even a single
goat left at liberty is a national dan¬
ger. Following similar ravages in the
Kermadec Islands ¡(which belong to
New Zealand) the Royal Society of
New Zealand intervened to demand
the extermination of the goats there.
World panic would help
I have said enough to show that
goats are a great danger because
they are one of the chief destroyers
of vegetation and therefore the cause
of soil erosion which threatens man¬
kind with famine. Experience shows
however that efforts to convince
people of this fact have met with no
success. When pressure has been put
on them the reaction has been so
strong that governments have been
forced to give up this method too.
Mr. Tracy Philipps Secretary-
General of the I.U.C.N., has reminded
us that the word "panic" derives from
the name of Pan, the Greek mytho¬
logical goat-legged god of flocks and
shepherds, who it was believed, ran
through the countryside at night,
spreading terror. It would be a good
thing if the people of today (all three
thousand million of them) became
panic-stricken just at the thought of
goats.
I myself believe that our main
effort to arouse people to the danger
of the goat should be made in schools
for here young people do believe what
they hear from their teachers. Thus,
in a few years' time, young men and
women, more aware of realities than
their parents, will be ready to pro¬
pose or accept stringent laws for the
extermination of the goat.
ÏÏÎWSAUSTRAIESÎTANTAPQIÏS
fRÂNÇAISfS
Crested penguins are among the wildlife
depicted on the stamps of French Austral
and Antarctic Territories (Crozet Islands).
Penguins are protected in several reserves,
in particular those of the Kerguelen Islands.
cz.BoaowczvK B.BHANDT
European bison, now greatly reduced in
numbers, is shown with its calf on this Polish
stamp. Now protected in Polish and Russian
reserves, they are showing signs of recovery,
Yugoslavia, where these three
stamps were issued, has done much
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1958
msuù£Si$m
AFRIQUE EQUATORIALE FRANÇAISE
Three stamps issued in France in connexion with the opening
of a travelling exhibition, "Man Against Nature'.', organized by
the Museum d'Histoire Naturelle, Paris with aid from Unesco
and the International Union for the Conservation of Nature.
CQR-R10
RDELKUADOR
m* s/ioo
'^Js^mÉti h
:\ |i6u*NA(.Jt^"i". Y
ISLAS GALÁPAGO S
. Three animals from the Galapagos Islands the sea-lion, a
giant tortoise and an iguanafigure on three of these four
stamps Issued by the Republic of Ecuador to commemorate the
I. U.C.N. -Unesco mission -which visited the islands in 1957.
CfWUSEWHUS, MONTANOS T: <»'. Z
FNR JUGOSL.AVI I A
to protect its wildlife by a special
conservation law passed in 1946
©HP J Y [OC A ABÜ-J. A
and also by the setting up of
national parks and local reserves.
STAMP COLLECTORS'
WILDLIFE ALBUM
by CIV. Hill
The value of postage stamps as vehicles . for all
kinds of campaigns has long been recognized by
both governments and stamp collectors, and one
of the most worthwhile purposes for which special
stamps have been issued is the protection of the world's
living creatures.
As long ago as 1851, the Canadian Post Office issued
a stamp whose design featured a Canadian beaver and
since then hundreds of stamps of many countries have
depicted animals, birds, fish, flowers and insects.
Improved methods of production and the strong
preference shown by modern stamp collectors for
pictorial designs have led certain enterprising postal
authorities, including those of Switzerland, Roumania
and the Soviet Union, to issue stamps on which animals
and flowers are depicted in their natural colours.
Among the most striking of these have been the Yugo¬
slav series which in recent years have shown animals,
flowers and herbs, and fauna of the Adriatic Sea, all
in accurate colour.
Both the United States of America and Canada have
been taking urgent steps to conserve their wildlife and
as part of their campaign several attractive stamps
have been issued. The whooping crane, one of the
rarest birds in the world, is paradoxically one of those
best known to stamp collectors, for a Canadian stamp
of 1955 and an American stamp of 1957 both featured
whooping cranes in their designs. The king salmon
and the pronghorn antelope have also appeared on
American wildlife conservation stamps, while the sad-
looking countenance of a mountain goat and the hard¬
ly less solemn-looking ones of a musk-ox, a walrus
and a moose, are among the animal portraits which
have appeared on the. stamps issued by the Canadian
Post Office each year to mark National Wildlife Week.
Another country which is alive to the necessity for
preserving its wildlife is the German Federal Republic.
Only recently to support International Animal Protec¬
tion Day, the Post Office of the Federal Republic placed
on sale two special stamps. One, bearing the inscription
"Protect the Birds", portrayed a robin, and the other,
inscribed "Protect the Flowers", showed a water-lily in
natural colours.
Real educational value is to be found in the beautiful
stamps of the Portuguese colonies of Angola and
Mozambique, . on which are depicted the exotic birds,
fish and butterflies to be found there. Equally beautiful
are the tropical flowers shown on many stamps of the
Belgian Congo.
Many collectors have forsaken the old method of
collecting the issues of a certain country or group of
colonies. Instead they collect stamps whose designs
illustrate a favourite theme, regardless of the country
of origin or the date of issue. The stamps which depict
the wildlife of the world form one of the most interest¬
ing and attractive themes and the world will be so
much the richer if the message conveyed by such
stamps is studied and accepted by stamp collectors and
non-collectors alike.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
V ERSATILE AS A BAMBOO : The
bamboo tree which has been traditionally
used in Indonesia to make anything from
water containers to musical instruments has
now a new career ahead of it in some of
the country's science teaching centres. It is
one of the many ready-at-hand materials
which are now being used there to con¬
struct low-cost laboratory apparatus. Ham¬
mers, other tools and nails on a modestly
priced list of equipment are being supplied
to schools and with their help and some
ingenuity bamboo sections can be convert¬
ed into pumps and other kinds of apparatus.
This is all part of a new trend in Indonesian
science teaching reported recently by a
Unesco technical assistance expert,
Dr. H.H. Grantham of Canada, on his
return from a mission to Indonesia. Science
teaching methods now stress learning by
doing instead of sitting and listening.
FREE FLOW OF INFORMATION :
Belgium, France, Luxembourg and the
Netherlands have become Contracting
Parties to the Unesco Agreement grant¬
ing duty-free entry to a wide range of
BINDERS FOR YOUR
COLLECTION OF
UNESCO COURIER
Readers often tell us they would
like to keep a bound collection of
their copies of THE UNESCO
COURIER. To meet the needs of
these subscribers we offer a special
binder holding 12 issues of the
magazine. Handsomely produced in
half-cloth with the spine in an
attractive blue and the title (in
English, French or Spanish according
to the edition to which you subscribe)
and Unesco colophon embossed in
gold, these convenient- and attractive
binders cost $2.50; 12/6 stg.; or
600 Fr. frs. They can be ordered from
the UNESCO Agents listed on page 35.
educational, scientific and cultural mate¬
rials. These four countries, which have
been applying the Agreement provi¬
sionally by decree, have now deposited
formal instruments of ratification. This
action by the four countries follows a
52-nation conference which met in Ge¬
neva last month to review application of
the Agreement and encourage wider
adherence to it. Twenty-six countries
now apply the Agreement which grants
free entry to books, newspapers, maga¬
zines, works of art, maps and music
scores.
f^OLOUR REPRODUCTIONS: Art
albums and colour reproductions serve the
plastic arts as gramophone records and ra¬
dio serve music, or the printing press ser¬
ves literature. Few individuals have the
means to purchase original works of art
and, in fact, there are entire peoples whose
only chance of getting to know the art of
the last 100 years is through reproductions.
Unesco has rendered an important service
by publishing in recent years art catalogues
listing paintings for which high quality co¬
lour reproductions are available. The latest
Unesco catalogue lists 992 paintings for the
period 1860 to 1957 and thus brings up to
date a previous volume covering the years
1860 to 1955. The catalogue gives the
artists' dates, places of birth and facts about
the original painting such as catalogue
number, title, medium of the original and
exact size ; the process used in reproduction,
the printer and the publisher and price of
the reproduction. ($4.00; 20/- (stg); 1,000
Fr. fr.)
GUIDE TO STUDY ABROAD:
Volume IX of Study Abroad: Inter¬
national Handbook of Fellowships,
Scholarships and Educational Exchange,
published annually by Unesco is now
available. It gives full details on over
75,000 awards offered in 1957-58,
including where to apply, who is
eligible, field of study, length of
courses, amount of award, etc. This
840-page guide can be obtained from
Unesco national distributors (see page
35). Price: $2,50; 12/6 (stg); 750 Fr. frs.
A MATEUR PHOTO CONTEST: A
photographic competition which is open
to young people in Europe is announced
by the German National Commission for
Unesco in collaboration with "Photokina"
(International Photo and Cinema Exhib¬
ition, Cologne). The competition which
closes on March 31, 1958 is based on the
theme "How We Live", and will comprise
the following photographic subjects: Youth
at work, including school and apprentice¬
ship activities, and young people working
on their jobs; Youth at play, including
organized spare-time activities (sports,
youth clubs, etc.) as well as personal
pastimes and hobbies. Prizes will be
awarded to participants from each country.
All young people up to the age of 25 are
eligible to enter the competition. Photo¬
graphs should be 54 by 1\ inches (13 by
18 cms) in size, black and white, glossy,
or colour prints. For detailed information,
photographers should contact their own
National Commissions for Unesco.
IGY FILM/TV SURVEY: During
the International Geophysical Year film
and TV cameras are busy recording the
many aspects of this world-wide scienti¬
fic research. Because it is difficult for.
any single country to cover the . vast
scope of operations, Unesco is making
a survey of material being prepared in
its Member States, and passing the in¬
formation to TV stations all over the
world so that exchanges of programmes
and films can be made directly. Fifteen
countries have so far prepared films or
have productions in hand. At the end
of the IGY, Unesco will gather TV and
film documentation to prepare a film
record of the international effort as a
whole.
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe to THE UNESCO COURIER today
Fill in this subscription blank and mail It with your cheque or money order
to our local agent in your country listed on page 35
Please enter my subscription for THE UNESCO COURIER
One year $3.00; I 0/-stg. ; 500 French francs Cheque/Money Order
enclosed
Twoyears$5.50;£lstg.;l,000Frenchfrancs Please bill me
Name..
Address..
City... . Country	Profession.,
u
z
<
a.
U
Z
<
u
O
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
AUTHOR-ARTISTS
Sir,
I read the August issue ("Famous
Authors as Artists") of The Unesco
Courier from cover to cover and enjoyed
every page. It's a first-class, unique issue
perhaps the subject can be pursued fur¬
ther. We have a place in a small town
called Swanton, in Vermont. I've arranged
to give our back copies of The Unesco
Courier to the editor of the local news¬
paper in the hope that he may find ideas
and information. The paper covers all the
northeastern section of Vermont, and so'
has a fair coverage. When he finishes
with the copies he will turn them over to
the local library. Again, congratulations
on the August issue.
Rowena Ferguson
Montreal, Canada
Sir,
In the August issue it is stated "...it is
indeed regrettable that no edition of Alice
containing Louis Carroll's own illustrations
is available to the public today." I don't
know whether you are aware that in 1929,
Messrs Dent published in Everyman's Li¬
brary an edition of Alice in Wonderland
(and some other pieces) with the author's
own illustrations. It may be out of print
now, but I have cherished a copy for years.
I enjoy each issue of The Unesco Courier
very much indeed.
Mary F. Moore
St. Annes-on-Sea, England
Sir,
I have read with great interest your issue
of August, 1957. I am interested in
obtaining the works of some of the many
foreign artists who are completely unknown
in this country. I would like to begin
this programme by presenting the work of
Rabindranath Tagore in some of my exhi¬
bitions. I would like to prepare an entire
show about the poetry and drawings of this
great poet who is almost completely un¬
known here in this country...
Harold James McWhinnie
The University of Chicago, U.S.A.
Sir,
I should like to say witli^what pleasure
I read the August issue. It was a delight
to the eyes and left me with a lasting
impression of enriched knowledge. My
own feelings are shared by several of my
friends who are assiduous readers of your
magazine. Nowadays there are so many
undertakings which seem to aim at lower¬
ing and debasing the public taste. The
cultural standard maintained by your ma¬
gazine is therefore a source of comfort and
re-assurance to me. I have, however, had
one small disappointment. As a native of
Geneva I was sorry that you did not deal '
with the works of Rodolphe Toepfer. I
know you have not room for everything,
but I would like to suggest that you devote
some space in a future issue to . this
strange and sometimes little-known author.
His works have sociological aspects
{L'Héritage); anti-militarist ones (See the
indictment against "armed force" in Le
docteur Festiis) and broad international
scope (Voyages en zig-zag: in France, in
Italy and elsewhere) which would certainly
interest you.
J. D. Candaux
Geneva, Switzerland
Ed. Note. Rodolphe Toepfer was, in fact,
referred to in Bertha Gaster's article "Fa¬
mous Authors as Artists", in company with
G. B. Shaw, Winston Churchill, Ibsen,
Anatole France and many other famous
author-artists, of whose works lack of space
prevented more than a mention.
CREATIVE TRANSLATIONS
Sir,
In The Unesco Courier, of June, 1957
("Great Literature of East and West") I
read "Poetry loses much of its charm in
translation..." Statement as rough as that
creates at least one opening for a number
of The Unesco Courier on types and art
of translation. Hop on it! Happens that I
can name a dozen translations that created
as well as the original writer did. The
translation, of course, involves much more
time and study and genius than the original
writer used. As a matter of fact, in many
cases the translater can be placed beside
the writer as a genius of equal credit.
Seems to me, unless someone like you
doesn't point it out, the fact will not be
recognized in this age. Maybe with des¬
perate jobs ahead of all of us, including
surviving at all, it might not matter at. all.
And yet, you are dedicated otherwise.
Don Round
(boalbuildcr, workman, linguist,
student, cynic, old man in ill-
healtli, traveller, seaman)
South Colby, Washington, U.S.A.
VALUE OF SCOUT TRAINING
Sir,
I read with great interest in your October
issue _the article, "High Intelligence Asset
or Liability" by W. D. Wall. I am sur¬
prised he makes no reference to the value
of scout training in overcoming defects of
which we are all aware. The patrol system
gives the young scout an appreciation of
the fact that it is not the stripes which
make him a leader, but his own personal
exampie... The badge system gives him a
-wide background of practical experierice
to counter the narrow specialization which
so often prevents him from fully applying
his knowledge. The Scout Law and the
Scout Promise provide him with a found¬
ation on which to base his life... You refer
to the particular dangers among the "able
members of a developing but still primitive
community educated abroad". In these
places the old scouts do not generally
suffer from unwillingness to do manual
labour. Many come to this country
[England] on scholarships and for some,
a course at Cilwell Park (International
Training Centre of the Scout Movement)
is obligatory. The sight of a general, the
leader of a big business or a high-ranking
civil servant doing the chores in the morn¬
ing is a great shock at first but they
learn a lot.
Rowallan, Chief Scout,
British Commonwealth and Empire,
The Boy Scouts Association,
London, England
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom the English, French, Spanish
and Russian editions of the UNESCO
COURIER can be obtained are listed
below.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Dep¬
artment, Royal Afghan Ministry of Educ¬
ation, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 303 Flinders Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, 15 rue
du Tilleul, Genval (Brabant). I 00 Belgian
francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Baldwin House, 33 St. Georges Street,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, I 00 Parsons Road Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kleber, Paris, 1 6*. C.C.P.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen¬
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co.; 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ I Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I ; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Raikamal Publicat¬
ions Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby Road,
Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posterommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P. O. B. 4 154, Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Librería Commissîonaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall.
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall. Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., I 104 Castillejos, Ouiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, I 6 South Frederick St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. m A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva.
6.50 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2 rue Cook.
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma)
549, Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y,
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
# ».
ENÄ^Kföl
IN THE KINGDOM OF
THE GIANT TORTOISE
The Galapagos Islands, 600 miles from the
coast of Ecuador, are a kind of Noah's
Ark, among whose animals are some which
exist nowhere else in the world. One of
these unique species is the giant tortoise,
after which Spanish explorers named the
islands. In the days of sail, mariners
caught these tortoises by the hundreds
and dumped them in the hold where they
lived without food and water until needed.
Many of the other animals on the Gala¬
pagos, which had no fear of man, have
been slaughtered indiscriminately. In the
past 1 00 years, scientists, of whom the
most illustrious was Charles Darwin,
have gathered a rich harvest of know¬
ledge from this Pacific archipelago. The
disappearance of any of the species
which dwell there would therefore be an
irreparable loss for science. Recently a
joint mission was sent to the islands by
Unesco and the International Union for
the Conservation of Nature to investigate
the present state of the animals and to
suggest ways of protecting them. Photos
show, above, a giant tortoise (some
live to be hundreds of years old) with
a three-year-old specimen placed on its
back for purposes of comparison ; left, a
tortoise "turned-turtle". (See page 18)
© Eibl v. Eibesfeldt
]]>
</page>
</document>
