<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066285eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
EPTEMBER
Messages from space
with solar batteries
/
*r
f
19 5 8
(llth year)
: l/-stg. (U. K.)
cents (U. S.)
francs (France]
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
J WINDOW OH« Off FMI WO« IB
rier
SEPTEMBER 1958
NTH YEAR
No. 9
CONTENTS
8
10
II
16
12
17
18
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
Unesco and Solar Energy research
4 SOLAR ENERGY TODAY & TOMORROW
By Prof. V.A. Baum
7 THE SUN AT WORK AROUND THE WORLD
Exclusive interviews with top men in solar energy research
By Daniel Behrman
(1) FRANCE: PYRENEES' SOLAR FURNACES
(2) U.S.S.R.: 1,300-MIRROR POWER STATION
(3) ISRAEL: FIRST SUN-OPERATED FACTORY
(4) U.S.A.: POWER FROM SOLAR BATTERIES
ARIZONA BUILDS A SOLAR HOUSE
Houses heated and cooled by the sun
MESSAGES FROM SPACE WITH SOLAR BATTERIES
LUNAR LANDSCAPE OF CENTRAL TURKEY
24 THE ROOTS OF PREJUDICE
Conclusion: Eight ways to reduce intolerance
By Arnold Rose
26 WATER COLOURS ON A GRAND TOUR
Unesco's latest travelling art exhibition
By Herbert Read
30 SCIENCE HAS THE ANSWER
By Gerald Wendt
31 IDEAS HIDDEN IN THE BRANCHES
By Georges Fradier
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.128 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads " Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00 ; IO/-stg. ; 500 Fr. frs. or equivalent.
COVER PHOTO
Radio transmitters in most recent Soviet
and U.S. earth satellites are powered
by solar batteries which pick up energy
from the sun's rays as the miniature
moons hurtle through space. Here
second U.S. satellite (6.4 inches dia¬
meter ; 3 1/4 lbs) undergoes special tests
prior to launching last March. The
rectangular objects which are seen on its
surface are the solar batteries. (See p. I 7)
USIS
The history of man's quest for energy resources is
practically that of human progress and civilization.
We are /now beginning to realize how rapidly the
world assets of coal and oil are dwindling. And although
the atomic age has begun we are still far from the
widespread harnessing of atomic energy for industrial and
other useful purposes.
Scientists have therefore turned to other more readily
available sources of energy such as the greater utilization
of direct solar radiation and the energy of the winds, and
even the energy of sea waves for industrial, domestic and
agricultural purposes.
Unesco has given serious attention to the possibilities
of using the unconventional energy sources particularly
in the world's arid or semi-arid regions. As part of its
regular scientific activities and particularly in its Major
Project on Scientific Research on Arid Lands, it has
undertaken a broad review of current research in different
countries. In 1954, Unesco organized an international
symposium in India on wind and solar energy at the
invitation of the Indian Government (see Wind and Solar
Energy, published by Unesco in 1956). In 1955, Unesco
gave financial support to a World Symposium on Applied
Solar Energy held in Arizona, U.S.A., and assisted the
Department of Economic and Social Affairs of the U.N.
in preparing an important study, New Sources of Energy
and Economic Development, published last year (1).
Unesco has only limited funds to support research
projects as such. One of these has been under way in
the past year at the Beersheba Institute in Israel under
the direction of Dr. H. Tabor of the National Physical
Laboratory, Jerusalem (see page 11). In the next two
years, Unesco and the World Meteorological Organization
will undertake the first world survey of solar radiation
distribution,, by mapping its daily and annual variations
and its dependence on altitude and other factors. The
study will be carried out in co-operation with a specialized
observatory and will make use of the data gathered during
the International Geophysical Year. At present there is
no cheap and simple instrument for measuring solar
radiation and thus capable of determining the most
suitable sites for solar energy development. Unesco will
provide funds to develop such an instrument as well as
for testing other solar energy equipment.
In the pages that follow The Unesco Courier describes
a few recent experiments in the direct utilization of solar
energy. A word of caution however is perhaps appro¬
priate. There is no sudden era of solar prosperity just
around the corner. As the Unesco Advisory Committee
on Arid Zone Research recently reported: "'Utilization of
solar energy holds great promise for the arid zones of the
world, but an immense amount of patient and diligent
research is still needed/'
(1) ¡n 1955 The Unesco Courier published a special <¡&-page issue,
(No 8-9), entirely devoted to "The Conquest of the Desert" (Now
out of print).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
SOLAR
ENERGY
TODAY &
TOMORROW
by Prof. V.Â. Baum
Head of the Solar Energy Laboratory,
G.M. Krzhizhanovsky Power Institute,
USSR. Academy of Sciences
POWER STATION IN THE DESERTSoviet
scientists believe that solar power stations can
be used to create oases in the desert. They plan
to install one In a valley near Erivan, capital of
Armenia (drawing, right). It consists of a boiler
on top of a 13 0-foot tower heated by the sun's
rays focussed on-to it by- 1,3 00 mirrors on con¬
centric railway lines at the base of the tower.
These five acres of mirrors will generate 2,500,000
kilowatt hours of electricity annually. Power will
be used to drain valley's swamps, to irrigate its
desert area and to supply electric current for
the use of local farmers. -¿(See article, page I 0.)
U.S.S.R. Official
The great problem of transforming the energy of the
sun's rays into other forms of energy for practical
use has interested humanity for a long time.
Scientists have calculated that the world's resources of
fossil fuels would be exhausted within one or two hundred
years if they were to remain the basic power source.
However, if the growing demand for energy could be
supplied from new, additional sources, first of all, solar
radiation, they could last several thousand years. At
first, solar radiation could serve as an auxiliary source of
energy in districts with a large number of sunny days per
year, and then, given certain conditions, it could become
the main source.
The problem must be tackled by seeking ways of exploit¬
ing this eternal, inexhaustible source of energy, tens of
thousands of times more abundant than current demands.
In ten days, for instance, the earth receives as much
warmth from the sun as we could get by burning all the
known reserves of organic fuel within the earth! However,
this enormous energy has not been exploited directly until
now. Due to uncontrolled natural processes, it is
transformed into low-potential warmth difficult to employ
technically, and is lost in space without working for us.
Only a comparatively insignificant portion of the stream
of radial energy is transformed into the energy of falling
water, wind, or chemical plant energy. It can be said
that so far man only uses these secondary resources,
while direct radiation is only used- in cultivating plants.
This radiation is of very high quality due to the great
temperature of its source, and it can be transformed to
advantage into other forms of energy, such as mech¬
anical, electrical and chemical. Besides, scientists,
engineers and inventors in several countries have built
many experimental solar appliances which have been
tested in operation. Some of them are already profitable
and are being used.
In the past, attempts to use the energy of solar radia¬
tion were made by individual enthusiasts, but in the last
two decades, planned work has been conducted by large
groups of specialists and even by entire laboratories.
Leading scientists have joined this work, the grandiose
prospects of which are so fascinating. Results are discuss¬
ed at regional and international conferences, and exhibi¬
tions of operating solar appliances are arranged.
There have been five national heliotechnical conferences
in the U.S.S.R. since 1939. Heliotechnical conferences
have been held annually in the United States since 1950;
some of them were international in scope. In 1954, there
was an international conference in India, sponsored by
the Indian Government and Unesco. It discussed the use
of wind and solar energy for arid and semi-arid zones. In
this article it is impossible even to list the countries where
such investigations are taking place. It is indicative of
the interest in the problem that more than one thousand
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The - Unesco Courier. September 1958
^^Ët+F* ^frfoM
# FIVE ACRES
OF MIRRORS
ON WHEELS
people from 37 countries took part in a conference in
Arizona, U.S.A., in 1955.
The most recent international conference was held in
June of this year in Mont Louis, France. (See page 7.)
Technically, radiation transforms most simply into
warmth, so that various thermal solar appliances were the
first to appear, such as water distillers, water heaters,
refrigerators, pumps, steam boilers, kitchen heaters, fruit
driers, and high temperature furnaces.
Their operation is based on the well-known fact that
when the sun's rays fall on a object with a blackened
surface they are almost entirely absorbed, and their energy
is transformed into warmth which is used for the desired
purpose either directly or through a series of supplemen¬
tary energy transformations. The amount of warmth de¬
pends on the amount of radial energy absorbed in the
appliance. If high temperatures are desired, the sun's
rays are preliminarily concentrated by mirrors or lenses.
This makes it possible to achieve a temperature of
3,600" C.
In recent years, physicists have demonstrated the
practical application of several wonderful properties of
certain semi-conducting materials to transform radial
energy and warmth into electricity. This made it possible
to construct simple appliances without moving parts,
photocells and therrno-elements, which transform solar
radiation into electricity with a high efficiency.
Of course, only the economically profitable solar
appliances will become widespread. Some of them can
already be recommended for districts where there are at
least 170 to 200 sunny days per year and where there is
a shortage of fuel. Some need improvement and a re¬
duction in cost. The cost could be lowered by producing
them and the special materials for them industrially.
One of the chief difficulties in using the energy of solar
radiation is its inconstancy. At the present stage,
accumulation of energy is technically and economically
practical only in certain cases. It is therefore difficult
at present to use solar appliances in locations requiring a
constant supply of energy. In such cases, solar radiation
can be used in combination with other sources of energy.
The development of cheap ways of accumulating energy
for different purposes is a very important task, and its
achievement could widely extend the field of application
of solar appliances.
In this respect, photo-chemicál methods of transforming
the energy of solar radiation should also be mentioned.
In this case, the. radial energy spent on
the chemical processes in the irradiated
system of matter can perform in the
reverse course of the process either as
heat or as electricity.
Cont'd
next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
USIS
An example of a photochemical process is natural photo¬
synthesis, a process of green plant growth, which from
the energetic point of view consists of a transformation
of solar radial energy into the potential chemical energy
of plant matter. By arranging optimal conditions for
plant growth, the harvest can be greatly increased. There
have been interesting experiments in the United States,
Japan, Italy, and other countries in artificially breeding a
mono-cellular alga, Chlorella, with very high yields,
constituting a prospective source of food, and perhaps of
energy fuel.
So far, matter or systems of matter with sufficiently
high energy efficiency of photochemical processes have not
been formed artificially. Their efficiency is incomparably
less than what could be achieved from plants. If work
in this sphere succeeds, it will solve the problem of
accumulating energy.
Boons to power-poor areas
with a surplus of sunshine
What are the prospects of using solar radiation, and
what part will it play in the near and the distant
future among other sources of energy? It is diffi¬
cult to answer. In a rationally organized economy, each
source will be applied in the sphere most convenient and
profitable, since each has its advantages and shortcomings.
It can only be said with certainty that in the near future
solar radiation will satisfy most demands for energy in
the home as well as for small motors and possibly lighting
in rural communities sparsely inhabited districts where
there are small-scale consumers.
The amount of energy consumed by the population of
the world is enormous. However, it is chiefly expended in
the large cities and industrial settlements, while the rural
population often does not have the possibility of
satisfying its most elementary energy requirements.
The shortage of energy is felt especially in arid and
semi-arid areas, though they have a surplus of solar
energy. Conditions in these areas could be improved
immensely right now by supplying them with such solar
appliances as kitchens, boilers, distillers, and driers. A
solar kitchen, for instance, with a light metal mirror about
one square metre in size, is equal to a 600 watt electric
heater. Food and boiled water could be kept warm for
many hours in thermos vessels. These areas also need
refrigerators operating on solar energy, but available
models must be simplified and lowered in cost.
It might prove expedient in supplying energy to large
oases in desert districts to build large solar heat and power
stations like the one designed at the Helio-laboratory of
the G.M. Krzhizhanovsky Power Institute under the direc¬
tion of the U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences.
The solar photocells now manufactured in the U.S.S.R.,
the United States, the Federal Republic of Germany,
Japan, and other countries are still expensive, and can
only be employed when there are no other means of
getting electricity, and if their cost is no concern. Still,
they are very promising. If their price could be lowered
sufficiently, that would solve the problem of lighting for
most of the districts of the globe. Photocells on 5% to
10% of the surface of a rural roof would light up the
house for an average of six hours daily. This is possible
with the photocell efficiency already achieved.
In the very near future, one-kilowatt solar thermo¬
electric generators will be more profitable than steam
power-and-heating appliances of the same capacity.
They would be of tremendous importance for water pumps
in arid and semi-arid zones. They would release many
people from exhausting, monotonous, and inefficient irri¬
gation labour.
Throughout history, people have been working to
transform nature and improve their conditions.
Transformations are becoming more and more tre¬
mendous. Man advances from small problems of separate
enterprises on a small scale to larger, multi-purpose tasks
of greater and general interest. Doubtless, some time will
be necessary to solve such problems on a cosmic scale.
This will require enormous amounts of power, which
cannot be supplied by any known energy source but that
of the sun.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
THE SUN AT
WORK ROUND
THE WORLD
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
by Daniel Behrman
USIS photos
In 19 54 the United States produced a tiny solar battery which
could operate a pocket-size transmitter containing transistors.
Here an engineer (with solar battery in hand) demonstrates that
his voice can be clearly heard at a receiver some distance away.
Top photo shows details of a larger solar battery. (See p. 17 for
facts about the use of these batteries in artificial satellites.)
IN lands scattered around the world, solar energy is
coming out of research laboratories and into daily life
at a price which the average man or his national
economy can afford to pay.
Today in Africa, Europe or the United States, you can
buy a solar-operated apparatus to heat the water in your home.
In France and in other countries, solar furnaces are opening
up new fields in metallurgical research and in the production
of refractory materials capable of standing the increasingly
high temperatures demanded by modern metallurgy. In the
Soviet Union, costs of operating a sun-powered refrigerator
have been brought down to the point of competing with
classical methods of refrigeration. In Israel, the world's first
factory making use of "solar steam" to produce chemical
products is under construction in the Negev.
These are only a few of the highlights of the applications
of solar energy in the modern world which were revealed at
a recent symposium conducted by the French National Cen¬
tre of Scientific Research. The symposium drew more than
fifty scientists and engineers to Mont-Louis, a citadel built
in the 17th century under Louis XIV in the eastern Pyrenees
and now the home of the world's biggest solar furnace,
designed and operated by Prof. Felix Trombe and a team
of French research workers.
By the end of the week-long symposium, a clear picture
had been drawn of the applications of solar energy in France,
Great Britain, the Federal Republic of Germany, Spain, the
United States, Israel, the Soviet Union and Yugoslavia. As
is often the case in such international meetings, it served to
pull loose threads together and to bring into focus the status
of a vital field of scientific research.
Both during and in between the meetings of the symposium,
it was possible to take a trip around the world of solar energy.
The results of this trip show a tremendous range in the use
now being made of the sun: it runs from cookers which can
fry an egg or grill a steak to laboratory research aimed at
improving turbo-reactors and space-conquering rockets.
Most important of all, this progress offers new hope to those
regions which are the richest in sunshine and, through some
quirk of nature, usually the poorest in other power resources:
the countries in the arid lands covering one-third of the
earth's surface.
Here is what this trip around the world has shown.
The Unesco Courier last month sent its special correspondent, Daniel
Behrman, to the international symposium on solar energy held at Mont-Louis,
in the French Pyrenees. There he Interviewed some of the world's leading
scientists now engaged in solar energy research. His reports on the work
now going on in this field in several countries are published on pages 9, 10,
11 and 16.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
SOLAR FURNACES IN THE PYRENEES
FRESH WATER IN THE SAHARA
Photos courtesy Solar Energy Laboratory, Mont-Louis
STUDY OF METALS capable of resisting working temperatures of today's
jet engines, rocket motors or nuclear reactors calls for furnaces lined with
special heat-resisting materials. One of these materials, zirconium, is produced
on a commercial scale in the world's biggest solar furnace (above) at Mont-
Loüís in the French Pyrenees. Photo shows parabolic mirror (left) which con¬
centrates sun's rays into orifice of solar furnace (centre), creating temperatures
of 3,000° C. Photo, left, shows sun-catcher mirror (40 feet across; 520 indi¬
vidual mirrors) which pivots automatically, when sun acts on photo-electric
cells, to pick up sun at any angle and then reflects rays to parabolic mirror.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
FRANCE
Slowly, almost imperceptibly,
the platform bearing a hand¬
ful of white powder rose until
it reached the focal point of
the parabolic mirror overhead.
Then, before the eyes of
scientists and engineers at the recent Mont-Louis solar
energy symposium, the powder suddenly burst into white
heat brighter than any diamond.
The powder was zirconium oxide with a melting point
of 2,700 degrees Centigrade, and it could not stand up to
the 3,000 degree heat of concentrated sunshine focussed
on it. Nor could the naked eye witness its smelting ; the
onlookers had to use special plates of black glass.
Through these plates, the small heap of powder looked
like a young volcano from another geological era.
"I remember a conference of industrial ceramics
manufacturers in France about ten years ago," said one
of the onlookers, a French manufacturer, as the platform
moved away again to allow the powder to cool. "When
Felix Trombe told that conference he could use solar
energy to produce refractory materials for furnaces, those
present treated it as a joke."
Today, no one is laughing. There is a steady demand
for "solar zircon" produced by the Mont-Louis Solar
Energy Laboratory founded by Prof. Trombe and his
assistant director, Marc
Foex. The mirror used
in the demonstration
was one of a battery of
small solar furnaces
flanking a huge para¬
bolic mirror 30 feet in
diameter and generating
the equivalent of 75
kilowatts.
One firm in Paris has
already purchased seve¬
ral tons of zirconia for
use in manufacturing
furnaces in which spe¬
cial metals are treated,
With this product of
solar energy, one mem¬
ber of the firm explain¬
ed, operating tempera¬
tures of electric furnaces
can now be safely raised
from 2,000 to 2,300
degrees Centigrade.
But this is only. one
aspect of the applica¬
tions of the Mont-Louis
furnace, which can
create a temperature of
3,000 degrees within a
split second. It is now
being used to penetrate
unexplored realms of
metallurgical research.
In the words of General Paul Bergeron, former director
of the French National Defense Scientific Activities'
Committee and one of the founding fathers of the
laboratory, "the solar furnace is invaluable in any field
where purity of materials and resistance to heat is an
important factor." One example is the study of metals
capable of resisting the tremendous working temperatures
of jet engines, rocket motors or nuclear reactors.
Mirror eleven storeys high
Fantastic though it seems set within the walls of a
17th century citadel built 5,000 feet high in the Pyre¬
nees, the Mont-Louis furnace is only a beginning.
This autumn, work will start on a new furnace six miles
away at Odeillo.
Here, solar energy will enter a new phase. The Odeillo
furnace will be operated by a mirror measuring 115 ft.
by 165 ft. thus having an area of 1,793 square yards. Its
size can be visualized more clearly with the help of
another fact: it will form one side of the solar energy
laboratory's new buildings standing eleven stories high.
With this mirror, production of zirconia will go up from
60 kilogrammes a day at Mont-Louis to 2,400 kilogrammes.
Odeillo will be able to produce from ten to twenty tons of
The Unesco Courier. September. 1958
steel daily for it will turn solar heat into the equivalent
of 1,000 kilowatts of electrical energy.
Prof. Trombe, who gave these facts in an interview, is
a tall, lean man in his forties and far more at home tink¬
ering with a parabolic mirror than presiding over an
international symposium. This probably explained the
success of the symposium where tea was brewed in
laboratory beakers and the future of solar energy discus¬
sed in a handsome 17th century room heated by the
crackling logs of a huge fireplace.
Hot water costing nothing
Felix Trombe is interested in the sun as a way of
developing arid lands from every angle, human as
well as economic. Mineral deposits in the Sahara,
for example, could be treated on the spot in solar furnaces.
Workers at these plants would live in houses air-con¬
ditioned by the sun and would raise their own food in
greenhouses. Even lettuce can be grown in the Sahara
in greenhouses, explained Prof. Trombe, because it requires
only one quarter of the water used in normal cultivation.
The solar furnaces in the Pyrenees are only one aspect
of how the French are harnessing the sun. Solar-operated
hot-water heaters are a common sight both in North
"Africa and on the Medi¬
terranean coast of
France. One French firm
manufacturing heaters
in Beziers uses as its
advertising slogan: "Hot
water for nothing." It
produces units which
provide hot water for
homes, hotels, laundries
and even shower-rooms
in factories.
One Paris firm now
has even more ambitious
plans. After installing
individual' hot-water
heaters in France,
Africa, Australia, the
West Indies and various
other parts of the globe,
it has begun to work
on large-scale instal¬
lations. It has already
installed a 1,500-litre
(327 gallon) heater in
the Moroccan national
tobacco factory at Casa¬
blanca.
SOLAR PRINTING PRESS: In 1884 a paraboloid mirror (above) was used
in Paris to print a newspaper by means of solar energy alone. About 1670, a
French scientist, François Bernière, built a solar furnace using huge lenses
mounted on a carriage. Lavoisier later used this same machine to obtain a
temperature capable of melting platinum. For a time in I 9 I 3, a 20-horsepower
"sun engine" was used in Egypt to pump water from the River Nile.
It is now working on
plans for a huge solar
energy unit designed to
supply hot water to 205
apartments in a new
housing development at
Koubra, near Algiers. With solar energy collectors set
on the roof and tanks in the basement, this plant will
have a capacity of 50,000 litres (11,000 gallons) if present
plans are adopted. On sunless Winter days additional hot
water will be provided by normal central heating systems.
Finally, the French are looking into the problem of
distilling saline water for drinking and other purposes
(truck drivers in the Sahara often pay $.25 a quart for
distilled water for their radiators because ordinary Sahara
water contains too many minerals).
What are probably the world's first solar stills manu¬
factured on a commercial basis have been developed by
a firm in Algiers and tested by a French engineer, Cyril
Gomella. One hundred and fifty of these stills, made
of asbestos concrete to stand up to Saharan conditions,
are now in service, producing a total of 1,000 litres (220
gallons) daily. They have brought the price of distilled
water in the Sahara down to one franc per litre a figure
which Mr. Gomella emphasizes is "honest" because it
included the high cost of transporting the prefabricated
elements of the still out into the desert.
From the solar furnaces in the Pyrenees smelting the
metals of the future to a life-giving fresh water supply at
"Bidon V" in the Sahara, the French are making solar
energy an economic reality.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
1,300 MIRRORS
TO OPERATE
POWER PLANT
USSR.
The sun is being put to work in
the Soviet Union to do everything
from producing ice by the
hundredweight to the generation
of electric power both on a scale
suitable for the isolated farmer
and for a major attack against the problems facing dry
regions.
This was disclosed by Professor Valentin Baum, director
of the Heliotechnical Department of the Power. Institute
of the Soviet Academy of Sciences, during an interview
at Mont-Louis.
Here are some of the latest results described by
Professor Baum :
Production of 350 kilogrammes (771 pounds) of ice
daily by a solar refrigerator operating at a cost "com¬
parable to that of other methods."
Widespread use of solar cooking stoves an estimated
600 are now in service which produce the equivalent in
energy of a 600-watt electric hot-plate. A collapsible
solar cooker, used to free scientific expeditions from
dependence upon fuel, has also been developed.
Experimentation and planning for a gigantic 1,200-
kilowatt solar energy plant for use in irrigation and
electric power production.
Development of a new method for converting the
sun's heat directly into electrical energy by eliminating
the inefficient steam boiler and engine.
In an interview, Professor Baum pointed out that
research in the Soviet Union has paid particular attention
to the need for putting dry regions to work. The so-called
arid zones would no longer be arid if we could bring up
fresh water from the soil and this could be done with
the help of solar energy, he said.
There are two sides to the problem. The first is symbol¬
ized by the farmer who needs power to pump water from
his Well and into the irrigation canals of his fields.
Here, Professor Baum's laboratory at Tashkent has
developed the technique of the "thermo-electric
generator." The principle of the thermo-couple is well-
known when two different metals are heated, an electric
current is produced and it is widely-used in measuring
high temperatures.
Soviet scientists took a parabolic mirror measuring two
metres (6* ft.) in diameter and heated a specially-design¬
ed thermo-couple. Despite the relatively small area of
the mirror, it produced 40 watts in electric energy.
"Our experiments have shown that, with the use of
semi-conductors, we can create a one-horsepower thermo¬
electric generator," said Professor Baum. "This would be
much more efficient than a steam engine of the same
power operating on solar energy."
On a far greater scale are the solar power stations
which Professor Baum believes could be used feasibly to
create oases in the desert. One such power station has
been planned at Tashkent and its components have
already been tested.
It consists of a boiler on top of a tower 40 metres (131
feet) high and heated by the sun's rays focussed on-to
it by 1,300 mirrors on concentric railway tracks at the
base of the tower. The mirrors with a total of 19,500
square metres (five acres) would generate 1,200 kilowatts
of high . pressure steam.
Prof. Baum designed this plant for use in a valley
near Erivan, the capital of Armenia, where it could be
put to work with extreme efficiency. One-third of the
valley is swamp, one-third is dry and, finally, one-third
consists of farms requiring power. The solar power station
could be used to drain the swamps, irrigate the dry land
and feed power to the rest of the valley.
10
Official Soviet photos
SOVIET SCIENTISTS are putting the sun to work in dozens of ways
from the production of ice by the hundredweight to the generation of
electric power in installations designed for individual consumption and
larger ones for public use. Above, bar. held at focal point of a Soviet
solar parabolic reflector melts away in the intense heat. Below, experi¬
mental model of mobile reflector. When batteries of these are used,
sufficient concentrated heat is generated to produce high pressure steam.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
THE WORLD'S FIRST SUN-
OPERATED INDUSTRIAL PLANT
ISRAEL
The world's
first industrial
plant operat¬
ing on solar
energy is now
under cons¬
truction in Israel at ancient Beershe¬
ba, the home of the Negev Institute
for Arid Zone Research.
This is one of the applications of
the solar energy programme which
Israel is now carrying out on a broad
front described by Dr. Harry Tabor,
director of the National Physical
Laboratory in Jerusalem and one of
the fifty scientists and engineers who
participated in the Mont-Louis Solar
Energy Symposium.
A lean, alert man who obviously has
little use for the "science fiction"
approach to solar energy, Dr. Tabor
methodically traced, in an interview,
the practical steps which his sun¬
baked country is taking to put the
sun to work.
"We are trying to answer four ques¬
tions at the Negev Institute", he stat¬
ed, and then he ticked them off :
Can we use solar energy to cool
houses ?
Can we use solar energy to gene¬
rate steam for a factory ?
Can we use it to run a small
power unit for farmers ?
What are the long-term pros¬
pects of building a solar power sta¬
tion ?
These immediate economic concerns
have led Israeli scientists to concen¬
trate on the most efficient ways of
collecting the sun. In this respect,
other participants at the Mont-Louis
symposium agreed, they are among
the world's pioneers, while Dr. Tabor
himself is one of the men responsible
for developing a new type of collector
which doubles the solar energy col¬
lected for a given surface.
Here, a word of explanation is need¬
ed. The world's solar energy specia¬
lists can be divided into two groups :
men working in high temperatures
who use parabolic mirrors to focus the
sun in the same way as a burning
glass, and scientists interested in
using the sun's heat for low-tempe¬
rature applications such as the
heating of water. In this second
category, the "powerhouse" is a col¬
lector and consists basically of a
black plate which absorbs the sun's
rays and pipes which carry away
water heated beneath the plate.
What Dr. Tabor has done is to
develop a plate which is both "black
and white". That is, it absorbs the
sun's heat as effectively as an ordi¬
nary black plate, but its wasteful
emission of energy is almost as low
as if it had been a perfect reflector.
This new type of collector is capa¬
ble of producing low-pressure steam
without the use of mirrors. It is to be
used in a chemical factory now under
construction at Beersheba which will
Israel National Research Council
FUEL-POOR BUT SUN-RICH, Israel has embarked on a broad programme of solar energy
research including the development of steam for industries and the production of small power
units. At the Negev Research Institute, Israeli scientists have built the new type of solar energy
collector unit shown above. This consists of simple curved mirrors which reflect heat upwards to
collectors fixed overhead. Use of black surfaces cuts heat losses by about four fifths, enabling unit to
compete with more expensive systems. Five hundred units will save about 500 tons of fuel oil a year.
produce fertilizer and insecticides
with ths help of steam provided by
300 square metres of roof collectors.
Refrigeration and air-conditioning
are other tempting goals for the
scientists working in solar energy.
They do not offer the same problem
presented by solar heating, which is
that the least amount of sun is avail¬
able when you need it most.
Packaged power
for the farmer
Here, stated Dr. Tabor, the Negev
Institute has managed to bring
the price of solar cooling down
to the point where it is only twice as
expensive as electric refrigeration.
The "running costs" of a solar refri¬
gerator or heater consists of paying
off its original price and that is why
the scientist in this field is forced to
think as a businessman. In 1959, he
said, Israel hopes to test more econo¬
mical systems of running a' solar
cooler.
One of the most tempting prospects
of all in the uses of solar energy is
the small power plant which could
bring the machine age to the aid of
farmers living in regions where the
cost of fuel has kept machine power
away. Unfortunately, the problem is
not as simple as it sounds.
There are two stumbling blocks.
The first one is the tremendous loss
of efficiency which always occurs when
you convert heat into mechanical
energy with a steam engine. The
second is the problem of moving the
collector so that it can track the sun
all day long. This involves either a
photo - electric device known as a
"heliostat", or constant supervision
and both are expensive.
A new mirror-type collector deve¬
loped at Beersheba is so efficient
that it has to be moved only once a
week to catch the sun properly.
Thus, one stumbling block has been
removed.
"What we are looking into now is
a small turbine operating at 150
degrees centigrade and using not
steam but a heavy fluid of high mole¬
cular weight", Dr. Tabor added.
The Negev Institute is now aiming
at a 10-H. P. solar "power package"
which Dr. Tabor believes may be able
to compete with Diesel plants par¬
ticularly in maintenance costs.
Regarding the prospects of large-
scale power installations, Dr. Tabor's
attitude is one of "reserved optimism".
"Any large solar power installation
means an extensive site", he explain¬
ed, "but we have huge chunks of the
Negev which are not good for any¬
thing else."
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ARIZONA
BUILDS
Ä ÇOT. HP
HOUSE
Not so many years from now, houses around the world
may be heated (or cooled) by a furnace situated
some 93 million miles away. Scientists have already
demonstrated convincingly that practical, full-scale sun-
heated houses can be built and made to work successfully
both in hot-weather countries and chillier northern climes.
For example, a pre-view of the comfortable existence
that awaits people when central heating will come by
courtesy of the sun has been provided since last April at
a house built in Phoenix, capital of the sunny state of
Arizona, in the U.S.A.
Outwardly the house doesn't look too different from
ultra-modern styled dwellings (in a fairly high price
range) that are being built in many parts of the U.S.A.
today. But there are plenty of new notes and new ideas
in the internal construction.
Its completion this year climaxed a project which began
when the Association for Applied Solar Energy and the
Phoenix Association of Home Builders planned an archi¬
tectural competition for the design of a new and unique
solar house which was to provide three things: archi¬
tectural distinction, a solar energy collection area suf¬
ficient to meet all the heat requirements of the house and
its swimming pool throughout the year, in the kind of
weather normally experienced in Phoenix and, finally,
sunshine control to reduce the amount of energy needed
to cool the house in the summertime.
In this competition, architects and designers throughout
the world (126 entrants from 13 nations finally competed)
set to work to solve the problems of "living with the sun",
including summer cooling as well as winter heating.
Winner of the competition was an architecture student
at the University of Minnesota, Peter R. Lee. The entire
project, from the mailing of the competition programme
to some 1,600 architects in 42 countries to the opening of
the completed house, built to Lee's designs, was carried
out in only eleven months.
Solar heated houses have been built in various places
since about 1939, but their designers have been beset by
two problems: How to compete economically with conven¬
tional heating systems, at least in installation costs ; and
how to provide heat when the sun doesn't shine.
Methods used in the past to provide solar house-heating
have ranged from the simple installation of a large
window wall facing south (to give supplementary heat)
to installing large collectors on the roof for heating water
in a conventional central heating system with circulation
through pipes and radiators. The storage of collected
heat has also been accomplished with pebble beds or by
the use of certain chemical salts that absorb heat when
changing from a crystal to a liquid state.
The Phoenix house shows a new trend and a new idea
in solar heating. The trend is to use water both to
transfer the collected heat to a storage tank and also
as the medium to retain the heat. Water is the lightest
of the heat storage materials so far- employed. Its heat
storage capacity ranks between rocks or pebbleswhich
are the lowest and salts, which hold the most British
thermal units per cubic foot.
12
An outstanding architectural feature of the house and
a new idea in solar heating design is its energy collection
system. This is composed of a series of 68 louvers, or
aluminium shells, mounted in 17 parallel rows between the
steel roof beams.
Resembling the wings or control surfaces of an aircraft,
these aluminium shells are covered with fibre for insu¬
lation. Blackened copper tubes set in a blackened copper
sheet are placed over the fibre. The copper absorbs heat
from the sun and transfers it to water which circulates
through the tubes. Transparent sheets of plastic are
placed over the copper and these allow the sun's energy
to get through, but prevent the long heat waves from
radiating back out to be lost. This is the same princi¬
ple on which a greenhouse operates.
All the heat collectors are arranged louver style over
the house's patio and central court. They are rotated by
a clock-operated motor to face south during daylight
hours in the heating season (in Phoenix, October to mid-
April) and can be adjusted so that they are always nearly
perpendicular to the sun's rays. During the summer, the
collectors are flipped over so the aluminium shells reflect
SUN SAND AND SKY set the decor for the Solar House built at
Phoenix, Arizona. Nearly 600 yards of material were used to curtain
the extensive glass areas (as in living-room, above, left) which form two
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
AIR RETURN DUCT
AIR SUPPLY DUCT
WATER PUMP
STORAGE TANK
CROSS-SECTION THROUGH THE SOLAR HOUSE
USIS photos
heat away from the house and provide shade below.
Fifteen of the seventeen rows of collectors are used to
provide heat for the house and swimming pool while two
rows are reserved to heat the domestic water supply,
which is stored in a 50 gallon tank apart from the house
heating system.
Water, warmed in the copper pipes concealed in the
roof heat collectors, is carried to a 2,000 gallon storage
tank. When this water is needed it circulates through
the coils of a forced-air system, warming the air in the
house. The system in the Phoenix House does not make
use of an auxiliary furnace to provide heat when the sun
does not shine. Instead, it makes use of a heat pump an
air-conditioning device which can extract heat from the
outside air when there is not enough solar heat.
Thus, if the water in the storage tank cools after several
sunless days, the heat pump comes into action to warm
the house air. The residual warmth of tank water is
used to pre-heat air round the heat pump's external coil.
In other words, these pumps need electricity to operate,
but obtain their heat from the warmth remaining in the
storage tank and the swimming pool. When cooling in
summertime, the heat pump reverses itself and acts like
a conventional air-conditioner. This time, water from
the storage tank, cooled by the aerated swimming pool, is
used to precool air round the pump's external coil.
Cost of the Phoenix solar heating equipment is esti¬
mated to be about #4,000 more than conventional heating
equipment would have cost. However, the cost of heating
and cooling the house (close to 2,000 square feet) is placed
at $450 a year, compared with $1,000 when using conven¬
tional equipment.
The purpose of the Phoenix Solar House is to stimulate
public interest in the use of the sun's energy for man's
benefit in his living conditions. The lessons learned from
its operation will be useful in designing houses of every
price level and for more northerly areas, where the sun
can supply only a part of winter heat requirements.
Proof that such systems of solar house heating are
practicable in cooler climates than that of Arizona has
been given by a series of experimental houses erected by
the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. The latest
of these was completed at Lexington in March. (See
following pages.)
I I III
_wU-wL-wl_pl--
ljlj!|!||
sides of virtually every room. Concrete masonry screen walls to
shade the sides of the house <Vom the sun are seen (centre photo)
flanking oneof the two patio"outdoor living rooms". Ultramodern kit-
Photos © Almasy, Paris
chen has an "island" containing sink and dishwasher(located to command
a view of the nearby mountains) and its equipment includes an electronic
oven, a built-in refrigerator and electric cooking range (above, right).
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
HOUSES HEATED
(OR COOLED) BY
THE SUN'S RAYS
Earlier this year a team of archi¬
tects and engineers from the
Massachusetts Institute of Techno¬
logy, in the United States, put the
finishing touches to a unique full-
scale sun-heated house at Lexing¬
ton, near Boston. This sleek,
two-storey, three-bedroom
house is officially called "M.I.T.
Solar House IV" for it is the
fourth in a series that M.I.T. has
built over the past 20 years to
study ways of obtaining practical
house-heating from solar energy.
Using the results of this research,
M.I.T. built the latest house to
demonstrate that enough facts
and equipment are now available
to combine a reliably engineered
solar heating system with a house
designed for comfortable sub¬
urban living in a northern clime.
The entire solar heating system
is thermostatically controlled and
completely automatic in opera¬
tion. The house owner simply
has to visit the basement instru¬
ments room (right) twice in the
year (in the spring and autumn)
and turn the valves (at right) either
to provide cold air during the
summer or to obtain warm air in
the winter. (Instruments on left
are solely for engineers who will
take data from the house). Pro¬
fessor Anderson, chairman of the
committee under whose auspices
the house was built, calls it "the
wedding of the special engineer¬
ing requirements of a reliable
solar heating system with the
architectural demands of modern
living". Top photo, corner of the
living room in "Solar House IV".
Behind sloping wall at left is 640
square-foot solar heat collector.
Photos : Office of Public Relations,
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
COPPER TUBES UNDER
BLACK- SURFACED
SHEET ALUMINUM
CLASS
vXX COLLECTOR
¡N\ FACE
TANK
COIL ^ATER
co.l'Co^'t.om1Nc FuRnace
M.I.T. SOLAR HOUSE
SNOW-COVERED ROOF
SUN-WARMED PARLOUR
Most striking feature of the M.I.T. Solar
House In Lexington is the solar collector
with which the sun's energy Is trapped
for heating use. Photo, above, shows
this collector, a sloping roof wall consist¬
ing of 640 square feet of glass, two layers
thick, over a similar area of thin alu¬
minium sheet, painted a heat-absorblng-
black. While the aluminium sheet ab¬
sorbs the solar energy, the glass works
as it does in a greenhouse It lets in the
sunshine, but keeps the longer waves
of heat energy from escaping again. To
store this energy for use, water Is circu¬
lated through copper tubes attached to
the aluminium sheet and is thus heated.
This hot water is stored, in turn, In a
1,500 gallon basement tank. To heat
the house, water from this tank Is
pumped through a heat exchanger,
which functions like an automobile
radiator, to transfer heat from the water
to a stream of air. This warm air is
then forced through ducts to heat the
living spaces. (See diagram, left). A
small auxiliary oil furnace is used for
heating if a series of sunless days occurs.
In summer, water in the basement sto¬
rage tank Is refrigerated so that forced-air
system can be used to cool the house.
Photos Office of Public Relations,
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
POWER FROM SOLAR BATTERIES
AND DRAWBACKS
USIS photos
MULTIPLE LENSES (left) concentrate
sunlight to "feed" a solar furnace at the
California Institute of Technology. Fur¬
nace Is used for high temperature tests of
Jet Age materials, those, for example,
required for rockets and earth satellites.
Right, forty-eight cells on the lid provide
current for world's first sun-powered
radio-phonograph which was demonstrated
in New York last year. The 48-cell solar
battery for this portable transistor unit
will operate on artificial light when the
sun is not shining. Standby batteries pro¬
vide current when no light is available.
U.S.A.
Only a few years ago, solar
energy was the pampered, spoon¬
fed darling of scientists working in
laboratories behind closed doors
closed not so much for the sake
of secrecy but for protection
against the usual form of humour reserved for research
off the beaten track. Today, it is a healthy child doing
very well in the hard-headed world of industry in the
United States.
This was brought out by American participants at the
Mont-Louis symposium. Dr. Frank Edlin, a consulting
engineer in the engineering department of Du Pont de
Nemours at Wilmington, Delaware, reported, in an inter¬
view, on the results of a Du Pont survey of the uses of
solar energy in the United States. No less than 5,000 solar
hot-water heaters have been sold in the United States,
mainly in Florida, Texas, Arizona and California.
An even more spectacular illustration of the market
for solar energy is the "silicon photovoltaic cell" developed
by the Bell Telephone Company several years ago. At
present, thousands of cells a month are being produced
in the United States. Their two main uses are in powering
transistor radio sets and in lighting beacons, buoys and
other aids to navigation. In some cases, up to 3,600 cells
are used.
They are popularly known as "solar batteries". Each cell
consists of a slice of single crystal of silicon. When the
sun shines, it converts from 8 to 14 per cent of the sun's
energy into electricity a much higher efficiency rate than
in other methods. This electricity is fed into an ordinary
storage battery to run the beacon or the radio at night.
The solar-powered silicon cell has one main advantage:
it requires very little maintenance. No one knows as yet
how long it will last but the estimate is "'dozens of
years." Its main disadvantage high cost is disappear-
16
ing rapidly. At present, the price of a cell measuring one
square inch has been brought down to S 3.
Why is Du Pont interested in hot water heaters and
silicon cells to the point of carrying out a survey of the
use of solar energy in the United States ?
"We don't sell solar energy appliances, but we are
interested as suppliers of material," explained Dr. Edlin.
"It's the same with nylons we manufacture the yarn
and we've made thousands of experimental stockings but
we've never sold a pair."
Plastic panes for the greenhouse
Du Pont is almost synonymous with plastics and
plastics have a tremendous future in solar energy,
Dr. Edlin pointed out. One of the biggest economic
question marks in the use of solar energy is the cost of
the glass in an appliance's collector. Plastics, Dr. Edlin
explained, have several advantages: they are cheaper,
they can be more easily shaped for special requirements
(such as parabolic mirrors) and they are less fragile.
Du Pont is now manufacturing one weather-resistant
clear plastic known as mylar and is experimenting with
another. This material is already used for greenhouses,
but it will open up new vistas in solar energy and that
is why Du Pont sent Dr. Edlin and its chief consulting
engineer, Mr. R.C. Ficke, to Mont-Louis.
The use of the sun to "weather-condition" homes has
been developed to such a point that, today at Lexington
in the U.S.A. there is a solar house for sale. The house
was developed by Prof. H.C. Hottel of the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology at Cambridge. It is a two-story
home with one-half of its roof the south side covered
with solar-energy collectors which take care of its heating
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
and hot water requirements. It has an auxiliary oil fur¬
nace for emergencies. (See page 14).
Dr. Thomas A. Unfer, a young scientist who has been
working with Prof. Hottel, told the symposium at Mont-
Louis of research in "selective surfaces" for solar energy
collectors. By coating an aluminium plate with copper
oxide, losses from emission are reduced from 95 % to 10 %
and twice as much water can be heated with the same
collector surface.
Another centre of solar energy research in the United
States is the University of Wisconsin at Madison, repres¬
ented at Mont-Louis by Prof. Farrington Daniels and
Prof. John A. Duffie. Prof. Duffie has been working on
solar refrigeration and air-conditioning and, he declared
in an interview, it appears "reasonably attractive1' when
combined with a space heating system (in order to
amortize the original investment in collectors as much as
possible).
Prof. Daniels has been working for the past decade to
bring the costs of a solar power unit down to the point
where it can be used to help non-industrial countries. His
research, financed with a grant from the Rockefeller
Foundation, has led him to look into all low-cost
possibilities and plastics are one of them.
Prof. Daniels, who has worked extensively in India, does
not think in terms of bath heaters or refrigerators but
of bullocks. "I've seen bullocks raising water to irrigate
land and then eating up most of the crops they had
irrigated," he pointed out. He has conducted extensive
experiments with small steam engines and, he admitted
frankly, he is still looking for one efficient and simple
enough to meet his requirements.
Prof. Daniels is basically a chemist, and is also conduct¬
ing research on chemical ways of storing the energy
of sunlight which would not be limited by the laws of
thermodynamics governing steam engines. "Nature does
it with plant synthesis," he said, "so we know that it
can be done."
MESS AGES
FROM SPACE
WITH SOLAR
JS A«, JL JL Its j\ JL £a kl
Soviet Sputniks and American satellites are trans- :
mitting important data on conditions in space as
well as in the upper reaches of the earth's atmo¬
sphere thanks to power picked up directly from the sun.
Unlike the earlier artificial satellites, the latest ones
launched during the International Geophysical Year
are now equipped with solar batteries which means
that scientists now have an efficient means of receiving
information from the satellites for years to come.
Though the life of these solar batteries has not yet
been determined, some scientists believe that they will
last about ten years, others hint that they may be
charged indefinitely by the sun.
The first Soviet and American Sputniks were
equipped with standard, though specially sensitive
batteries (working on a mercury principle) to supply
the needed electricity for their transmitters. But after
several weeks their power was exhausted and they
ceased operating. Thus one transmitter of the second
U.S. satellite faded out in less than three weeks.
Both the American and Soviet solar batteries now
hurtling through space consist of wafer-thin silicon
cells smaller than the size of common razor blades.
(The cells in American batteries are l/400th of an inch
thick). Each cell contains two layers of silicon of
different electrical properties so that when sunlight
strikes a cell, electrons move from the first layer
(positive) to the second (negative), creating an electric
current.
The second U.S. satellite, launched on March 17,
1958, has six solar batteries spaced on its surface
' (diagram below) so that at least one of them is in
direct sunlight except when the satellite finds itself
in the earth's shadow. (Because of its distance from
the earth, it is estimated that it will not be in the
shadow period 85% of the time).
The third Soviet satellite, sent up on May 18, 1958
(it carried a ton of scientific equipment and measuring
instruments) has nine solar battery sections Four are
installed on the front end plate, four on the side
surface and one on the back end plate. This arrange¬
ment ensures normal working irrespective of the
Sputnik's orientation in relation to the sun.
SECTION "A-A*
BATTERY-POWERED
TRANSMITTER
INSTRUMENTATION
PACKAGE
BATTERIES
CRYSTAL
-SOLAR -POWERED
TRANSMITTER
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
LUNAR LANDSCAPE OF
PINNACLES & TOWERS
Strangely-shaped rock towers and pinnacles stud countryside around
Mount Argaeus, Asia Minor's highest peak, which rises 12,848 feet
on the Cappadocian Plateau of Central Turkey. In prehistoric times
the mountain erupted, spewing ash and lava hundreds of feet deep
across the land. Rains and melting snows created valleys and river¬
beds, and wind and water slowly carved the volcanicdebris intothousands
© Marc Riboud-Magnum Photos
of pyramids and cones. For thousands of years men have made their
homes in these rock shapes. Macan (above) is one of half-a-dozen
villages half-hidden in this lunar landscape. First cone dwellers hacked
out homes from the soft rock. Many carved entrances high above
ground to protect themselves from attack. Double towered cone
(opposite page), no longer inhabited, has many rooms on different levels.
18 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
STONE CAPS WORN
AT RAKISH ANGLES
The whims of nature have rarely produc¬
ed stranger sights than those in the
cone-land of Cappadocia. As wind and
water have carved out valleys and river
beds, they have also left cones and
pyramids standing in space, sometimes
with stone caps of a different, more
resistant material. (I) Rock hats on
these cones, already at a rakish angle,
will one day tumble off and the un¬
protected cone will crumble away.
(2) A two-storey dwelling, now un¬
inhabited, whose weather-worn walls
have opened up like a honeycomb.
(3) A cloistered community grew up in
Cappadocia between the fifth and
twelfth centuries. Holy men excavated
tombs, shrine and even large churches
out of rock. Farming family now lives
in this mushroom-shaped cone which
Christians of medieval times used as a .
chapel. Columned room (on right of
dwelling) is thought to have been
carved as a tomo. (4) Rock pyramids
in the Goreme Valley stand in serried
ranks like some army poised to strike.
(5) Towering spires dwarf a farmer's
wife and her donkeys near one of the
oasis-like cultivated patches which dot
the floor of the valley near Urgup.
© Marc Riboud-Magnum Photos
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
.? C> >V tÂ
"ji**
ttÛi
'isflP^' '
VaWn't
*«-
" ._JÎ
"-Vfc.'
U* *
*$¿¿ V
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
CAPPADOCIA: COUNT R Y
OF THE CONE DWELLERS
rrrr-i AKE the first turning on the left, pass two mina-
I rets and a tower, go round the pyramid on the
right and make straight for the cone with the
stone cap leaning to the left." This is the type of street
direction a visitor would need to find his way around
ürgüp, a Turkish village set in one of the strangest
landscapes this side of the moon.
For ürgüp is in the heart of a country of volcanic
towers, a fabulous land of some two or three hundred
thousand stone cones, in the centre of the Cappadocian
Plateau of Turkey. Kayseri formerly Caesarea, a com¬
mercial centre from Roman times is the nearest town.
Ankara is some 200 miles to the northwest. Here nature
has taken a fling at proving that anything is possible
and man has countered by demonstrating that no matter
what nature contrives, and however improbable, he can
make some use of it.
This is the situation today. But the beginning of the
story of Ürgüp is in prehistoric times when Mount Argaeus
(Erciyas Dagi), the biggest mountain peak in Asia Minor
exploded violently covering a forty-mile area around its
base with ash and lava hundreds of feet deep. At first
the triangular volcanic plateau was a smooth molten mass
but as the lava cooled, large cracks, fissures and ravines
appeared, and the process of erosion began.
Melting snows, rains and wind then took a part in
sculpting the weirdest landscape the human eye has ever
seen outside of the lens of a telescope focussed on the
moon. Pyramids, towers, spires, cones, minarets and
needles of rock in a brilliant phantasmagoria of colours
ranging from blinding white to bright yellows and softest
rose were left jutting skywards in haphazard confusion.
Handiwork of a drunken architect
Some towers, polished smooth by grit-laden winds, stand
so high that they have as many as ten floors; others
are man-size. Some have comical caps of rock
substance, more resistant to the weather than the main
cone, which sit coquettishly on top. Others have been
worn down to the shape of a Cleopatra needle. And lest,
if even in this, there might be some semblance of- sym¬
metry, the hand of some drunken architect seems to have
pushed this one slightly left, that one over to the right,
placed these cones leaning towards each other like people
in deep conversation and set these others standing stiffly
apart.
If the first tribes wandering across the desert land saw
this strange incomprehensible rockland as a challenge
they also seized on it as an opportunity. For more cen¬
turies than are recorded in history, men have made their
homes in this woodless land by digging into the rock
shapes and enjoying the safety offered by dwellings with
a life span beyond human reckoning. Yet even the rocks
do not last forever because once the caps fall off, the
shape of the cone starts changing, giving a constant
impermanency to the bizarre skyline.
What is known of ürgüp has been compiled from what
the previous generations have left behind them. Some
time about the 4th century A.D., a community of Cénobite
monks discovered the advantages offered by this rock
land for the preservation of the seclusion demanded by
their order. Side by side with the humble farmers who
tilled the valleys, they established themselves in the cone
village of Goreme a few miles from ürgüp.
With considerable ingenuity they dug out living quar¬
ters, sometimes at ten different levels in the same cone,
reaching the entrances by rope ladder or by a central
inside chimney niched to provide hand and footholds.
22
Ground level doorways they sealed with large stone wheels
which rolled on carefully cut grooves.
These monks left a rich heritage for the archaeologist.
They built dozens of small chapels in the cones, mainly
following the Byzantine form of architectural construc¬
tion and covered the walls and ceilings with brilliant
paintings depicting the iconography of the Christ, Mary
and the Saints. In the earlier chapels probably built
about 400 A.D. the paintings were done in simple wash
on the stone face.
Kilroy was herein 1650
More elaborate work was done from the 8th to 11th
centuries when artists had learned the art of using
tempera which is more resistant to the ravages of
time, though not, unfortunately, to the vandalism of
sightseers. Thus many of the paintings have been
mutilated almost beyond recognition by visitors who,
wishing to leave their mark on time, have scribbled their
autographs on the walls. One autograph defacing a
well-nigh priceless fresco has been identified as dating
back to 1650.
The departure of the monks, following the decline in
the Christian monastic communities in the 14th century,
brought another era to the rock country. The villagers
were not slow to put the former chapels and living quar¬
ters to practical use. Windows were walled up and former
sanctuaries became pigeoncotes so that there would be a
, reliable supply of guano to supplement the chemicals of
' the volcanic soil. Cells became store-rooms, and, not to
be outdone by the monks in artistic effort, the villagers
decorated the outside of crofts and barns with figures of
animals and geometric patterns.
Blessed with an abundance of food products grapes,
melons, apricots, pears, apples, walnuts and certain types
of cereal all grow in profusion the villagers of the cone
country have little reason to go far afield. Their main
product is a sweet wine absorbed easily by the surround¬
ing provinces, though ürgüp itself has vats that can
hold up to 3,000,000 litres (790,000 gallons).
As a result, changes have come slowly to this outlandish
place. Though thé richer members of the community
sometimes build housefronts and install wooden doors to
give the appearance of ordinary dwellings, they show no
desire to alter their cave houses behind, and a step over
the threshold is a step back across the centuries.
Spring-cleaning with hammers
While the people of Urgüp may now wear Western
dress in their homes probably the same shelters
their ancestors carved out of the untouched rock
the stairways, floors, ceilings and walls are of stone. The
divans they sit on and probably sleep on, are of stone,
and the fireplace without a flue is of the same basic
material.
When spring-cleaning time comes round, the women
use hammers to chip off the accumulation of grime
incidentally enlarging the chamber each time and then
complete the annual renovation with whitewash applied
With a twig brush.
Should the family needs change and living space
become cramped, one can always cut out another room
and if the cone is not large enough to allow this, then
there is always another round the corner. And who could
wish for more than a home that is cool in summer, warm
in winter, rent-free and well-nigh indestructible.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
Josephine Powell, Rome
TROGLODYTE HOMES OF THE 2 0TH CENTURY
In cave houses of Cappidocian villages like Uchisar (below) stairways, floors and even divans are of stone, but one advantage of these modern troglodyte
dwellings-is that they are cool in summer and warm in winter. Smoke from their flueless chimneys blackens the rooms, so once a year the people
chip away the begrimed layer on ceiling and wallsthus enlarging the room each time. A coat of whitewash then completes the "spring cleaning."
Below, left, a young woman, balancing atop a woven basket, uses a bundle of twigs to whitewash the ceiling. Above, view through window space
shows thickness of cave house walls. Women are busy at their looms, weaving carpets. Some carpets take as much as two years to complete.
© Marc Riboud-Magnum Photos,
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE ROOTS OF PREJUDICE
Eight practical steps to reduce intolerance (bias)
by Arnold M. Rose
(4)
In this issue we conclude the serialization begun in June of "The Roots of Prejudice",
published by Unesco in its series "The Race Question in Modern Science." In the present
article Professor Rose explains how prejudice arises from imaginary fears in the minds of
certain people. He then goes on to examine prejudice particularly in its more extreme
forms as the "expression of a warped personality." The author concludes with a list of
eight practical steps that can be taken to help reduce prejudice.
© by UNESCO. Unauthorized reproduction prohibited.
Frustration explains the force behind prejudice. But
it does not explain why certain minority groups are
chosen as scapegoats. To explain this, psycholo¬
gists help us out with another theory the "symbolic"
theory. This theory is based on the important fact that
one thing can stand for something else in the uncons¬
cious mind. People often find themselves liking some¬
thing, certain foods or some scenery, for example,- without
knowing why. If such feelings could be traced back
to their origin, it would be found that these new foods
or new scenery "remind" people of some pleasant expe¬
rience in their past. There need not be any real
connexion at all. The unconscious mind is always
making connexions so that one thing will substitute for
another.
There can also be substitutes, or '"symbols" as the
psychologists call them, for things disliked. Probably
everyone has. had the experience of disliking semething
at first sight, without any reason for doing so. The
unconscious mind made a symbolic connexion there, too.
Now, the question is: why are certain minority groups
disliked by so many people? Obviously, they must be
symbolically connected with something very important to
many people. Such things would include an interesting
life with new opportunities, money, a belief in being
kind and just to others, family life and sexual satisfac¬
tion, good health, and so on. Toward all these things
most people have mixed attitudes; we like them, but we
also dislike them. We may be a little afraid of some of
these things, or we may wish to rebel against them. But
we cannot say so: it is not proper to dislike these
important things. So the dislike becomes unconscious,
and can be expressed only through a substitute. Minority
groups become substitutes for important things in the
culture with which they have deep psychological and
historical connexions.
What man fears he hates
Let us take an example of how this works for one type
of case. All of us have had the experience once in
a while of disliking a thing that is good for us. Most
of us have kicked up our heels at our parents, at our
church, at practices that are said to be healthy and so
on. That seems to be a natural human way of behaving,
if it happens only once in a while. But some people will
not admit that they would like to rebel, and these are
usually the ones who would most like to do so. They
pretend that they adore their parents at all times, that
they always have "pure" feelings about sex and religion
and so on. Since this is not really the case, they have
to give vent to their, rebel feelings in some way. And they
do so by having prejudices against minority groups.
It is not only a matter of disliking the objects of pre¬
judice; it is also a matter of fear. When people hate
something strongly, they are usually also afraid of it. It
is of course sensible to hate and fear certain things, but
24
when the danger is imaginary there is something wrong
with the person who hates and fears. That is the
situation when there is prejudice against minority groups.
Most of the fears connected with prejudice are imaginary,
even though they seem real enough to those who have
them.
Take, for example, the fear of large numbers. Many
people who are prejudiced against Negroes, or any
other minority group, say that there are so many
Negroes. They are afraid they are going to be "over¬
whelmed" or "dominated" by Negroes. If these people
are asked: "'What percentage of the people in this
town are Negroes?" they usually give a falsely high
number. The real facts are available to them if they
wished to know them. But prejudiced people seem
to wish to hold on to fears about the large numbers of
Negroes.
Another fear is that minority groups have too much
power. Prejudiced people say that Jews own the big
banks and run the government. Even a little investi-»
gation will indicate that this is not so. As a matter
of fact, in some countries Jews are kept out of the
banking business and out of many government posts
because of prejudice. There are no Jews in many of
the biggest and most powerful industries.
There is the fear that members of the minority many
be spying for foreign governments. For years before
the World War II many Americans were afraid of Japan¬
ese spies. When the war came, hundreds of Japan¬
ese-Americans were arrested because they were sus¬
pected of spying. There were many rumours of
various kinds of secret work for the Japanese Govern¬
ment. But when it was all investigated, not a single
Japanese-American was discovered to have been help¬
ing the enemy. The Japanese Government knew about
Americans' prejudice and hired only white Americans
as spies.
It is wise to be afraid of some things. But the fear that
goes with prejudice is always harmful, because it is a fear
of something imaginary.
We can now bring together the ideas dealt with in this
section: Why do people learn prejudice and hold it so
strongly that they do not wish to give it up?
It is not because people naturally dislike any person
who looks different, behaves differently, or speaks in
a different manner from themselves. In fact, people
pay attention to differences only when they have pre¬
judices first. Then they hold themselves apart and
despise or hate the differences of the other people.
It is not because prejudiced people have had unplea¬
sant experiences with minority groups. Some have,
and some have not. Those who have had unpleasant
experiences with minority groups have also had un¬
pleasant experiences with other people. They remem¬
ber some unpleasant experiences because they are
already prejudiced.
In part, people have prejudice because they are frus-
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
trated and unhappy in a general way. Depression,
unemployment, and low wages are among the main
causes of frustration for a country as a whole, but
there may be other causes. There are many things
which cause fear and anxiety among large numbers of
the people. When people do not understand the cause
of their frustration, or feel that there is nothing they
can do to stop it, they look for a scapegoat. Certain
kinds of politicians gain popularity by naming the
Negroes, the Jews or some other group as the scapegoat.
People are willing to use these groups as scapegoats
because the groups have become symbols of other
things they dislike. They cannot openly show their
dislike of these other important things, since they
would regard that as improper or foolish. Also, they
like or admire the other thing at the same time as
they dislike it. So they switch all the dislike over to
the symbol the minority group.
Fear of imaginary dangers is an important part of
prejudice. One of the reasons why prejudiced people
dislike or hate minority groups is that they imagine all
kinds of fearful things about them.
A number of students have sought to explain prejudice
as a type of mental disease. Some mental disorders can
be traced to inadequacies in personality development, and
prejudice is regarded under this theory as resulting from
a particular kind of mis-development. Prejudice arising
from this source is quite non-deliberate and cannot be
eliminated by rational appeal or the application of laws.
Most studies of this aspect of prejudice take the form of
a comparison between groups of prejudiced and unpre¬
judiced persons, based on a number of questions about
personality characteristics and personality development.
The items where significant differences appear are then
integrated into a clinical picture of the "prejudiced per¬
sonality".
One study, by Frenkel-Brunswik, Sanford, and others,
at the University of California, is based on a detailed
comparison between the personality traits of known anti-
Semites and the personality traits of known non-anti-
Semites. By comparison, the typical anti-Semite was
found to be a compulsive conformist, exhibiting anxiety
at the appearance of any social deviation. He appears to
be a person with little insight into himself, who projects
his own undesired traits on to other people, so that he
blames people against whom he is prejudiced for traits
which are characteristic of himself. He has a tendency
toward stereotyped thinking and is unimaginative. He
tends to-, have unconscious inferiority feelings centering
mainly in a feeling of sexual inadequacy. He expresses
strong filial and religious devotion, but unconsciously
manifests hatred of parents and indifference to moral
values. He exhibits an aversion for emotionality but
unconsciously has a feeling of inferiority toward it. He
is prone to aggressive fantasies.
Anxiety, insecurity breed anti-Semitism
Another study was conducted in New York City by
Jahoda and Ackerman. They secured detailed reports
on 50 patients who had expressed anti-Semitism
while undergoing psychoanalytic treatment, and tried to
determine what role, if any, anti-Semitism played in their
unstable mental make-up. It appeared that anti-Semitism
resulted from some distortion in personality structure and
fulfilled certain needs. Anxiety and lack of security in
group membership are among the principal traits of anti-
Semites. Fearing attacks on their integrity as individuals,
these persons counter-attack against Jews, the hand¬
iest object. The anti-Semitic personality type in
this study, too, has an overwhelming desire to conform, to
appear '"respectable" and to attach itself to dominant
organizations, and is characterized by outward submissi-
veness and inward aggressiveness.
Hartley made a study among college students of the
personality traits of the prejudiced person. His summary
of the characteristics of the intolerant personality fol¬
lows: "unwillingness to accept responsibility; acceptance
of conventional mores;, a rejection of serious groups; re¬
jection of political interests; a desire for groups formed
for purely social purposes and absorption with pleasure
activities; a conscious conflict between play and work;
emotionality rather than rationality; extreme egotism;
compulsive interest in physical activity, the body and
health. He was likely to dislike agitators, radicals, and
pessimists. He was relatively uncreative, apparently
unable to deal with anxieties except by fleeing them."
These studies of prejudice as the expression of a warped
personality have certain weaknesses when considered by
themselves. But when taken in connexion with other
factors underlying prejudice, they add much to our under¬
standing. They probably are most useful in explain¬
ing extreme case of prejudice.
Shatter stereotypes with facts
We have thus seen that prejudice is indeed a complex
thing. There are background factors and immediate
factors which account for its presence in any
individual or group of people. This complexity makes it
difficult to eliminate prejudice, as action taken against
one root does not necessarily affect the other roots.
Perhaps we can best summarize our findings by suggest¬
ing what .kinds of action will contribute toward a reduc¬
tion of prejudice. These are not listed in order of import¬
ance but simply according to convenience of presentation.
1 One thing would be an intellectual appreciation by
prejudiced people of the fact that prejudice harms
them, financially and psychologically. Involved in this
is a recognition that the gains that seem to come from
prejudice are to some extent temporary and illusory.
These gains, which can be classified as economic, politi¬
cal, sexual and prestige, sometimes divert the preju¬
diced person from more satisfactory and more perma¬
nent gains. Prejudiced people need to be shown how
they are exploited because of their prejudice.
2 A second activity helpful in diminishing prejudice
would be the provision of accurate information about
the minority groups against which there is prejudice.
This should include facts which break stereotypes, and
explanations of the causes that give rise to differences
between minority and dominant groups. Facts of this
type are learned not only through books, newspapers
and speeches, but through personal contact on a
friendly and equal basis.
3 One of the most important traditions to combat is that
of racism. This can be attacked not only when it is
applied to minority groups, but also whenever biological
explanations are applied to any social phenomenon.
4 Legislation which penalizes discrimination reduces the
occasions on which prejudice is made to seem proper
and respectable, as well as eliminating some of the
worst effects of prejudice. Legislation against dis¬
crimination is thus one of the most important means
of breaking traditions of prejudice.
5 A tradition on which prejudice is based can be main¬
tained only by being transmitted to children. If the
transmission of prejudice through the home and play
group can be counteracted by the school and church
while the child's mind is still flexible, prejudice cannot
long survive. Also, if the public can be led to consider
that manifestations of prejudice are shameful, many
parents will refrain from displaying their prejudice in
front of their children. Where this happens, children
are less likely to acquire prejudice.
6 Direct efforts to solve major social problems will not
only divert people from prejudice, but will remove some
of the frustrations that create a psychological tendency
towards prejudice. The most important single step of
this type is the provision of economic security.
7 Demonstration that many of the fears about minority
groups are imaginary might help to dispel those fears.
There is probably a need to inculcate a more thorough
understanding of the fact that fear or hatred of a
minority group is a mere substitute for real or hatred
of some other object, towards which people are unwill¬
ing to express their true attitude. A general program¬
me of mental hygiene needs to be developed to get
people to be honest with themselves.
8 Any effort to develop healthier and saner personalities
will diminish prejudice. Such efforts usually require
the guidance of psychiatrists.
A concerted programme which included all these acti¬
vities would, in a generation or two, at least greatly reduce
prejudice. But many of these activities are difficult to put
into practice. Further scientific research is needed to
indicate just how important each of these factors is, and
how they can be manipulated most easily. Both re¬
search and action aimed at diminishing prejudice are un¬
der way in several countries. The future, is hopeful if
even a small group of people in each country is organized
to eradicate this most serious blight on all civilization.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
WATER COLOURS
ON Ä GRAND TOUR
by Herbert Read
STILL LIFE WITH PIPE, by the Italian painter, Gino Severini (born 1883). New York Graphic Society.
Great works of art are notoriously bad travellers.
Not so their sturdy stand-ins, the high quality
reproductions that make up the Unesco Tra¬
velling Art Exhibitions. These intrepid voyagers
pass happily from continent to continent, from hot climate
to cold, from green lands to desert, giving the great
masterpieces of the world a previously inconceivable mobi¬
lity and universality.
The first exhibition was assembled in 1949 from fifty
quality reproductions of the work of artists from 1860 to
the present time. Five sets were made and the object was
to send them to stimulate interest in world art in countries
that have little economic possibility of obtaining significant
collections of their own. Brazil was host to the first dis¬
play. After an astounding success in Rio de Janeiro, the
exhibition toured the smaller towns. It was then scheduled
to go to adjacent lands in Latin America, but the Govern¬
ment of Brazil set a precedent, and thereby started an
26
unthought on sideline, the selling of exhibitions, by asking
Unesco for permission to keep the collection. The same
fate awaited many of the others, which have found perma¬
nent homes in countries, not necessarily culturally im¬
poverished, who have realised that the exhibitions fill a
gap in their artistic life.
Since these early days five further exhibitions have gone
on their way and been enjoyed by some 74 countries. The
themes dealt with are: Paintings Prior to 1860, The Works
of Leonardo da Vinci, Japanese Woodcuts, Two Thousand
Years of Chinese Painting and Persian Miniatures.
A seventh Exhibition is now ready. It consists of 20
identical sets of 72 framed reproductions of water colours
dating from the 4th century onwards. It already has world¬
wide bookings. On the following pages we publish an arti¬
cle on the water colours specially written for the exhibition
by the noted British art critic, Sir Herbert Read.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
In a general sense, water-colour is one of the most
ancient methods of painting it was used in Egypt in
remote times for the decoration of papyrus rolls, and
in a similar way the sacred books of the Middle Ages in
Europe were illuminated with pigments mixed with
water and gum. Such early forms of the art, however,
have very little in common with water-colour painting
as it has developed in Europe since the eighteenth cen¬
tury. More comparable, from a technical and aesthetic
point of view (the aesthetics of the art, as we shall see, are
inseparable from the technique), is the early development
of the art in the Far East. The art cannot, of course, be
older than the invention not only of paper, but of the
soft-hair brush (camel hair or hare's fur) and tradition
attributes this invention to Mêng T'ien, who died about
210 B.c. Paper was not invented until about three cen¬
turies later. A scroll in the British Museum, The admoni¬
tions of the instructress, bears the signature of Ku K'ai
Chih (circa a.d. 344-406) and may be a Chin dynasty copy
of an earlier painting. One scene from this scroll illus¬
trates a hunter in a landscape and this particular
painting may be regarded as the prototype of the art as
it was to develop in Europe many centuries later.
Chinese water-coulours always remained strictly sub¬
ordinate to calligraphy even Confucius lays down
a law on this point ('Applying colours comes after
the groundwork'). In Western terminology most Chinese
paintings on paper should be classified as tinted drawings
rather than as water-colour paintings. But the modern
European tradition developed from the tinted drawing it
was the practice of painters from the fourteenth century
onwards to make preliminary sketches in ink, reinforced
by washes (usually of the same colour). An early example
is a wash drawing in the Louvre by Taddeo Gaddi (circa
1300-1366) which is a preliminary study for the fresco of
The presentation of the virgin in the Baroncelli Chapel,
Santa Croce, Florence, For the next four centuries the
technique remained ancillary to the arts of tempera and
oil painting, and though such artists as Rembrandt and
Rubens produced water-colour drawings of great beauty,
it was only Dürer who used the medium as an end in
itself his landscapes in tinted water-colour anticipate
the fully developed art of the eighteenth century.
The art of water-colour as we ¡know it had an inde¬
pendent origin, as a miniature art within the capacity of
travellers, topographers and illustrators of books on
natural history. Pisanello's studies of birds (second quar¬
ter of the fifteenth century) may be taken as an early
prototype and these are scientific records rather than
works of art. Then in the sixteenth century the medium
began to be used to record the discoveries of the early
explorers John White, who sailed with Raleigh, drew
Indians in their various occupations, birds, plants and
fishes. There were other topographical artists of this
period in France (Jacques Le Moyne, for example) and
in the Netherlands. An artist of this ¡kind, Wenzel Hollar,
came from Bohemia to England in 1635 and began to
make tinted drawings of scenes in London and its neigh¬
bourhood. Hollar inspired Francis Place, a native of
York, to make similar drawings of his city and its sur¬
roundings, and from that moment we can trace the conti¬
nuous development of the English water-colour school
a tradition of landscape based on topography, from Hollar
and Place through Samuel Scott and the Sandbys, Rooker,
Hearne and Dayes, to Girtin and Turner.
The medium was also used skilfully by the Tudor and
Stuart miniature portrait painters, notably by
Nicholas Hilliard (1537-1619) and Samuel Cooper
(1609-1672). But here again the European artists had
been anticipated by the Chinese artists as we may see in
the portraits by Yen Li Pen and Liang K'ai included in
the exhibition.
From the middle of the eighteenth century water-colour
painting became the most characteristic art of England,
and even this country's greatest oil painters, Gains¬
borough, Constable and Turner, found in it an essential
medium of expression. This efflorescence of the art lasted
barely a century, but in that relatively
short period artists like J. R. Cozens, Fran¬
cis Towne, Thomas Girtin, J. S. Cotman,
Peter de Wint and David Cox gave to the
art, not only its highest perfection, but also
a distinct aesthetic.
GENTIL BERNARD and ROUSSALKA, by French
painter Georges Rouault (1871-1958). Guy Spitzer, Paris.
Cont'd
on
next page
-27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
WATER COLOURS
ON TOUR (Continued)
PORTRAIT, a work by the French
painter Jacques Villon (born 1875).
Daniel Jacomet et Cie, Paris.
KINGDOM OF THE BIRDS,
by the Swiss painter Paul Klee
(1879-1940). Benteli Verlag, Berne.
An art can have a distinct aesthetic only if it has
distinct materials, a distinct technique and a distinct
aim. The materials of water-colour painting are trans¬
lucent pigments, applied with a soft brush to a ground
of white paper. Each of these materials has its special
characteristics the colours must be pure, the brush
must be well-made of the finest hairs, the paper must
have its own-sensuous quality, for very different effects
can be obtained according to its roughness or smoothness,
its degree of permeability and its whiteness. The tech¬
nique of applying the colours to the paper will vary
from artist to artist, but as compared with tempera or
oil painting, great sureness and precision is required, for
there is no possibility of overpainting or retouching. The
art gets its most distinctive quality from its necessary
spontaneity, and in this respect may be compared with
the calligraphic art of the Far East. The aim, as in any
other type of painting, is to create a harmonious compo¬
sition in colour on a two-dimensional surface, but until
comparatively recent times the medium has been applied
almost exclusively to the depiction of landscapes. This
is because the subtlety of the medium allows for the
rendering of nuances of tone and colour beyond the
range of tempera or oil.
Amateurish blots, clots & speckles
This capacity of is brought out in remarks
of Ruskin on one of the later masters of the English ,
water-colour school, Copley Fielding: "Water-
colour, under the ordinary sketcher's mismanagement,
drops and dries pretty nearly to its own fancy, slops over
every outline, clots in every shade, seams itself with unde¬
sirable edges, speckles itself with inexplicable grit, and
is never supposed capable of representing anything it is
meant for, till most of it has been washed out. But the
great primary masters of the trade could lay, with unerr¬
ing precision of tone and equality of depth, the absolute
tint they wanted without a flaw or a retouch ; and there is
perhaps no greater marvel of artistic practice and finely
accurate intention existing, in a simple kind, greater than
the study of a Yorkshire waterfall, by Girtin, now in the
British Museum, in which every sparkle, ripple, and cur¬
rent is left in frank light by the steady pencil which is at
the same instant, and with the same touch, drawing the
forms of the dark congeries of channelled rocks, while
around them it disperses the glitter of their spray.
"Then further, on such basis of well-laid primary tint,
the old water-colour men were wont to obtain their effects
of atmosphere by the most delicate washes of transparent
colour, reaching subtleties of gradation in misty light,
which were wholly unthought of before their time. In
this kind the depth of far-distant brightness, freshness,
and mystery of morning air with which Copley Fielding
used to invest the ridges of the South Downs, as they
rose out of the blue Sussex champaign, remains, and I
believe must remain, insuperable, while his sense of
beauty in the cloud-forms associated with higher moun¬
tains, enabled him to invest the comparatively modest
scenery of our own island out of which he never travel¬
led a charm seldom attained by the most ambitious
painters of Alp or Appenine."
This remarkable passage manages to detail, not only
all the characteristic virtues of the water-colour medium,
but also its characteristic shortcomings. There is no
doubt that the English school, particularly in Girtin and
Turner, reached a perfection in this art which has never
been excelled, and Ruskin, in Modern Painters, extolled
the art with an insight and an eloquence that also have'
never been excelled. But Turner, by his technical virtuo¬
sity and overwhelming achievement, virtually brought the
art to an end only Cotman, seven years his junior, was
strong enough to maintain an independent style: one
might say, to maintain the tradition which Turner was
destroying. For Turner, in his last phase, left far behind
the topographical aims with which the art had originated.
Always, as Ruskin had noted, primarily concerned with
the light and colour of the scenes he depicted, he now
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
became absorbed with the elements themselves, freed from
their incidental relation to physical objects. Writing
about the late transparent water-colours of Venice and
Switzerland, Laurence Binyon says truly that "the ele¬
ments, in their energy and radiance, mean more and more
to Turner, the works of man less and less. At first sight
it is the miracle of the colour, the luminousness, the
indescribable delicacy, that holds one ; but soon one mar¬
vels more at the amazing science behind it, the evocation
of complex forms, however submerged in aerial hues, the
fullness of the distances. It is the same with the alpine
scenes, where the mountains retain their sculptured
form yet seem built of light and air ; the lakes are unfa¬
thomable, the valleys recede into an infinite distance. The
design is all in depth ; whorls of curving cloud lead the
eye on and on into a vibrating mystery of light, which
unifies the whole fabric of earth and air and water.
Never, had painting communicated with such subtlety and
power the sense of infinity. For it is not merely the sense
of infinite recession that it gives, the attraction of a final
peace, such as we find in the Umbrian painters ; it is space
conceived as something living, as a power which draws
our spirits into itself but also wells out in impalpable
radiance from the picture and absorbs and envelops our
minds."
Turner : unrivaled by latter-day artists
When we survey the century that has passed since
Turner's death, we can discern no use of the
medium by any painter of any country in the world
that can compare with such intensity of vision and mas¬
tery of expression. Only Cézanne comes into comparison,
and Cezanne's water-colours are essentially preparatory
exercises for his paintings, quick notations of form and
contour of great delicacy that perhaps express an ideal
which he had hoped to achieve in his oil paintings. But
from his letters it is evident that he never regarded water-
colour as more than a convenience ; only towards the
end of his life, when he was finding the effort demanded
by oil painting too exhausting, did his water-colours
become a self-sufficing medium of expression.
Apart from Cézanne, there have been perhaps only two
significant developments of the artone which might be
said to exploit the freedom of Turner's last phase, without
his sense of infinity; the other using the medium in a
manner which would never have occurred to Turner or
any of his predecessors to convey symbolic images. Gau¬
guin, with some help from medieval illuminations and
Japanese coloured woodcuts, might be said to have revived
the symbolic mode, and he has been followed by Kan-
dinsky, Klee and Miró. The other mode, which we now
call expressionist, has had a continuous development
beginning with Van Gogh and extending to Nolde,
Kokoschka, Rouault, Soutine and Sutherland. There are
several artists who do not fit into these general categories
impressionists like Jongkind, Steer and De Pisis who
continue the tradition of Constable or Girtin; and others,
like Turner himself, who transcend all categories nota¬
bly Picasso. The art has lost what gave it its distinctive
aesthetic its desire to render the subtlest effects of atmo¬
sphere; but what it has lost in subtlety it has gained
in power. But this power, in a Rouault or a Nolde, usually
demands the addition of body colour, and once the
translucency of the medium is sacrificed, the medium
itself has been transformed. Artists like Klee and Miró
have used the medium for new effects, subtle in a psycho¬
logical rather than an atmospheric sense ; but finally it
is an essential attitude of mind or spirit that is lacking
in the modern artist the quality which in Chinese
aesthetics is called Ch'i yün. "Ch'i yiin", explained the
eighteenth-century painter Chang Kêng, "may be express¬
ed by ink, by brush-work, by an idea, or by absence of
idea... It is something beyond the feeling of the brush
and the effect of ink, because it is the moving power of
Heaven, which is suddenly disclosed. But only those who
are quiet can understand it."
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Science has the answer
WHAT IS THE CAUSE
OF TIDAL WAVES?
by Gerald Wendt
The primary causes of tidal waves are large earthquakes.
Out at sea such waves are hard to detect because,
though they travel at a speed of about 400 m.p.h.,
they are only a few feet high. The distance from the crest
to the trough is some 15 miles long, and the wave period
takes several minutes to pass by. When the tidal wave
reaches the shallow Water near a land mass, however, the
front is slowed down and the fifteen miles of water piles
up to form a steep-fronted surge that can wreak
tremendous havoc as it hits the land. \
In the Krakatoan earthquake, which occurred between
Java and Sumatra towards the end of the 19th century,
there were enormous casualties because the earthquake
took place in shallow water close to the land and waves
as high as 100 feet piled up and swept inland.
In the Pacific area where tidal waves cause tremendous
havoc, ordinary earthquake phenomena are not easy to
observe since many parts of the ocean are extremely deep.
But a series of seismograph stations set up to detect
'quakes in the area can give advance warning of tidal
waves.
The sound waves produced by earthquakes travel
through the ground at a speed of about 5 miles a second
that is, much faster than tidal waves. When seismograph
stations record large 'quakes, the exact arrival time of
the beginning of the ground waves are compared, and
from these the position of the earthquake can be calcul¬
ated. Since tidal waves travel at roughly 400 miles per
hour, it is relatively easy to predict their time of arrival
at places where damage may be expected.
Why is sea-water salt and how does it retain its saltiness ?
When the hard rooks of the earth's crust are thrust
up to form mountains they are exposed to the
weather and thus to the chemical action, of water,
oxygen and carbonic acid from the air, and to alternate
heating by the sun and cooling by frost and ice. They
slowly crumble, which speeds the chemical action and
permits the atta&k by plants also. The result is disintegra¬
tion into gravel, sand and ultimately soil. Most of the
products of this decomposition are solid materials that
remain near by or tumble down the brooks and rivers.
But others dissolve in the rain-waters and remain invi¬
sibly in the waters of the rivers. Thus all "fresh" water
except pure rain-water contains a small but definite
quantity of these dissolved '"salts". Water that is called
"hard" contains relatively large quantities.
All rivers run to the sea and carry the salts with them.
In the course of the millions of years of geological time
the salt has accumulated in the sea because evapora¬
tion 'from the surface takes only pure water and leaves
the salt behind. As- the rain falls and returns to the
sea in rivers it brings more salt with each cycle. Thus
the saltiness of the sea is slowly but steadily increasing.
The fresh water from the rivers does not dilute the ocean
and make it less salty because just as much water
evaporates as the rivers pour in.
The level of the sea remains constant and so the salt-
content slowly increases in the course of the centuries.
At present the salt content of sea-water amounts to 35
parts per thousand. This means that one metric ton
(2,000 pounds) of sea-water contains 70 pounds of salts.
With only minor variations due to local conditions, it is'
the same in all the oceans, the world over.
Why does the moon exercise an influence on phenomena of life on earth ?
The centrifugal force of the moon is just sufficient to
maintain it in its orbit and at a distance of about
two hundred and fifty thousand miles from the
earth. But neither the moon nor its centrifugal force
have any direct influence on any phenomena of life on
earth.
However, the moon and the sun, too have a direct
and important bearing on the various "tides*' which occur
on our planedthe movements of the magma, or fluid
strata under the earth's crust, the tides of the oceans,
seas and lakes, and also the atmospheric '"tides" which
cause variations in height of the ionosphere. All these
tidal movements have different but very indirect conse¬
quences on earthly phenomena. Another, and by no
means negligible contribution on the part of the moon
is that it periodically lights our night sky.
But apart from this the moon plays no part in any
phenomena of life on earth. And all theories tending
to prove that its rays influence the destinies of human
beings are without foundation, for no such mysterious
radiations have ever been detected by astrophysicists.
What would happen if the earth's ice caps melted completely ?
It is a fact that glaciers are receding in all parts of the
earth, which indicates a slight warming of the average
temperature. But it has not yet been established that
the polar ice-caps are also melting. This would require
an extended series of measurements of the thickness of
the polar ice, which have not been made. But this is one
of the objectives of the present International Geophysical
Year.
The thickness of the ice on the Antarctic Continent is
especially important since about 90 per cent of all the
earth's snow and ice is there. It has been estimated to
be between 2,000 feet and 8,000 feet thick on the average.
At some points it is certainly 10,000 feet thick. If all this
30
ice should melt, the level of the ocean would rise at least
85 feet and possibly 400 feet, which, would indeed submerge
most of the great seaport cities.
A Californian expert, Professor Robert P. Sharp, has
estimated for the American Geophysical Union that the
average of the Antarctic ice is in excess of one mile'
and that its complete melting would raise the sea-level
all over the earth toy 200 feet. He calls this ice "something
of a Sword of Damocles hanging-over the' heads of all
peoples living close to the sea." However, he also advises
a relaxed attitude toward this possibility. It cannot
happen fast. "Conceivably1", he says, "it might happen
in 10,000 to 20,000 years."'
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
à
IDEAS HIDDEN
IN ROOTS AND
BRANCHES
by Georges Fradier
With pieces of leather, straw, felt, etc. Mrs. Arjun Ray has created
strange pictures, statuettes, which at first seem to be made of porce¬
lain, but which are really shells... and especially pieces of wood, the
most beautiful of all her work. You cannot really call it sculpture.
The sculptor chooses his medium, then, after a good deal of effort, he
creates a form. No one save he can foresee what its shape will be;
he aleone decides. Here, on the contrary it is the wood which decides.
A wealth of forms and patterns lie hidden in these twisted roots and
dead branches. The artist has merely helped to bring them to life.
A few years ago, when a collection of essays, richly
illustrated with children's drawings and paint¬
ings, was published by Unesco under the title, Edu¬
cation and Art, a schoolteacher friend from the Alps
wrote to me to say how absorbing he had found this
beautifully presented volume. "But let us not fool our¬
selves," he added at once. "I have nothing against
children dabbling with paints and having fun expressing
themselves freely. The trouble is that by the time they
reach ten or eleven it's all finished. Their feeling for
colour and their imagination have flown out of the
window.
"I admit that it's not the same in the big cities where
children can get a fresh start at that age. They have big
museums they can go to and, provided someone is in the
least bit interested in showing them, they can be in¬
troduced to the world of art and its pervading atmosphere.
But where I live there is just nothing that even faintly
resembles the world of painting or sculpture.
"And I don't think that people are born with such a
thing as an artistic sense. At any rate the old people up
here, who have never had any initiation into art, spend
their whole life without ever noticing the majestic beauty .
of our scenery. When I point out to my pupils how beau¬
tiful the pine trees are they merely shrug their shoulders
and say : 'Yes, but with the cost of transport timber is
hardly worth selling any more'."
I have waited until now to answer my friend's letter.
Not that I have discovered any new method of solving his
problem that would be hailed by educators and art autho¬
rities. It is simply that I have met an artist who, I think,
could inspire even the most rough-and-tumble child with
a feeling for beauty and taste for creative work.
This artist is a woman, and she is a practical person
not a theorist. She has neither degrees nor diplomas.
She is the wife of an important Calcutta architect, with
children of her own and a large household to run. When
she speaks of her work it is in a shy, diffident manner :
"I don't even know if it's worth anything," she says.
By "it" she means strange art objects made of leather,
straw, felt or cloth, figurines which at first seem to be
made of porcelain but which are really shells... and espe¬
cially pieces of wood, the most beautiful of all the works
produced by Mrs. Arjun Ray. Sculpture is really not the
word for them. The sculptor chooses his medium himself
and after a good deal of work creates a form, which only
he decides on and elaborates, Here, on the contrary, it
is the wood which decides.
A twisted root, a dried-up branch. In each of these a
form and pattern liées hidden. One needs only to spot it,
and then help it a little so that it springs to life.
One figurine is called "After Me Cometh One." Mrs. Ray
did not get up one morning saying "I'm going to do a
statuette of St. John the Baptist." She found a branch
lying on the grass split at one end and shaped like a
trident at the other. She picked it up, and saw in it the
image of an ascetic prophet, arms raised skyward. Some¬
one else probably would not interpret it in the same way
as she did. At any rate, on returning
home, Mrs. Ray scraped off bark in places,
removed a knot in the wood, deepened
a notch and accentuated the outline. And
there, suddenly, was the prophet, clad in a
goat skin, "crying in the wilderness."
Cont'd
on
next page
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Polished, varnished and impregnated with oils (to pro¬
tect them from insects and humidity) but never painted,
the pieces of sap-wood, bark or root, become true works
of art once mounted on a base.
Anyone, irrespective of his age or educational back¬
ground, will recognize them as '"living" shapes:" two
wrestlers struggling desperately together, a screaming
monster, the great hand of Peace. Yet without Mrs. Arjun
Ray these same persons would never have seen anything
more than twisted roots and brambles and branches of
deodar, cedar and gardenia.
It seems to me that my teacher friend might draw a
useful lesson from the work of the lady in Calcutta.
I repeat, there is nothing novel about what she has done.
But a lesson need not be an original revelation to be
useful. A sense of form stems from things seen rather
than from notions acquired. Or to put it another way,
sense and taste for form depend first of all on knowing
how to look at things. Paul Valéry once wrote: "Examine
all things on earth as though you had never seen them
before." Mrs. Arjun Ray sees a frail dancer in a broken
twig which a dozen people have passed by without a
thought. In much the same way a painter sees limitless
patterns of shape and colour in a simple composition
of objects which the layman vaguely describes as "a
window, a table and a flower pot."
Where is there a child between four and six who does
not inspect everything around him with infinitesimal
attention and interest? Not of course in as sophisticated
and learned a fashion as does the painter, but the con¬
ception at least is the same. All children are sensitive to
the suggestion of form, and their world is rich in images
and metaphors. A pebble is always something more beau¬
tiful than a pebble ; a leaf is like silk, or like a face, or
like a butterfly. The child collects scraps of old paper or
old buttons just as he does sea shells or birds. Gravely
and matter-of-fact, grownups put everything into cate¬
gories and classes: "This is mineral so and so, that is
mountain so and so. This is clean; that is dirty". But
the child's mind says: "It's like..." A lion. An angel. A
shoe "It's like...": the very first beginnings of graphic art.
And one might well ask oneself whether the role of the
teacher in this field only, obviously should not be to
permit their 10- and 12-year-old pupils to continue their
game of make-believe by permitting them to go on search¬
ing for images without shame. Let them keep their vision
of a world which is profoundly fascinating because of its
infinite variety, and because everything around us is worth
seeing, and each thing in turn suggests another, indeed a
thousand other things. To allow children to escape for
as long as possible from the impoverishment which
characterizes adults whose view of life is limited to things
useful, conventional and efficient is to remain an artist.
By learning to see, to feel and imagine, children learn
to detach things from their surroundings. The strollers
who did not notice the twig from which Mrs. Arjun Ray
produced the figure of a dancer cannot fail to recognize
the finished work: the dancer stands gracefully poised,
ready to spring to life. True the artist has added a few
touches to the guava branch, revealing what she could
already see. But what really brings the dancing girl to
life is that she stands out alone on an empty background.
To use a rather worn simile: on a wall covered with pic¬
tures, each one is invisible.
I suggest, therefore, that my friend from trie mountain
school should get his pupils to display in class once or
twice a week the natural "treasures" picked up during a
walk, polished and "brought to life" by some minor altera¬
tion. At first they will believe that the form or pattern
is due chiefly to chance. But, gradually, they will come to
understand that no thing of beauty whether it be a
branch, a fir tree, marble or precious stone is really
beautiful until our eyes have "learned to see" it. There
is enormous scope for children in this "game".
Mrs. Arjun Ray does not work only with dead wood.
She uses feathers, shells, and even pieces of coal; a touch
here, a slight twist there and the image springs to life.
And she marvels: "What a wealth of ideas, forms and
shapes lie hidden amid the trees and shrubs around us !"
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1958
Letters to the Editor
ASIAN SUBJECTS-A BORE...
Sir,
You have published some extremely
interesting numbers which deserve
congratulations, but there have been
far too many dealing with India. There
are other places in the world besides
Asia.
R. de Cotignon
Paris, France
...OR SOURCE OF SELF
KNOWLEDGE ?
Sir,
In making better known the culture
of the East among other cultures
you are not only bringing different
peoples ' closer to one another, but also
opening up to Western nations the
deepest well-springs of their own
civilization.
A. Chatillon
Lausanne, Switzerland
AIR DENSITY 500 MILES UP
Sir,
Last November you published an
article entitled "A Soviet Scientist Looks
At 'Sputnik'," in which the author,
K. Staniukovich writes: "The density of
air at an 'altitude of 500 to 550 miles
is so small that it evidently does not
exceed 10 to 18 grammes per cubic
centimetre." This figure is just about
the density of lead and of platinum.
What it should have said is 10 to 18
grammes per cubic metre, in other
words about one million times less.
M. H. Friedel
Paris, France
'DIGESTS' & FIGURES
Sir,
The Unesco Courier covers subjects
which are so vast that they have to be
reduced to a sort of "digest" or present¬
ed as statistics. As a result your
magazine is perhaps of great use to
people who do not make a point of
reading specialist articles published by
the daily press or to those who read
few or no books at all. The subscription
price is reasonable, and in several issues
you have published reproductions of
ancient works of art in places we would
normally be unable to visit. However,
if I wish to improve my mind through
reading I feel I can do better by going
along to my local library.
S. Delessert
Dully, Switzerland
GREETINGS FROM MOLDAVIA
Sir,
I am the village schoolmaster of
Nagoriany in the Moldavian Republic
of the U.S.S.R. While visiting Kichinev
I was able to buy a copy of The
Unesco Courier to which I had been
attracted by its striking appearance. On
reading it I found its contents to be
just as interesting and attractive as its
cover and its presentation, and I noticed
that the opinions of readers did not
always concur with those of Unesco
or of the editors of the magazine.
We are very keen to contact schools
in other lands, to exchange knowledge
and ideas with them, to get to know
our foreign colleagues really well and
to develop mutual confidence, hoping
that wisdom throughout the world will
bar the road to collective suicide.
Victor Kassianenko
Rychkany Post Office
Nagoriany Village School
Soviet Socialist Republic
of Moldavia, U.S.S.R.
HIGHER STANDARDS PLEASE
Sir,
I should like to congratulate you on
the care and objectivity which goes into
the production of The Unesco Courier.
Quite rightly you adopt a position which
is above all the political problems
dividing the world, so that you see the
world only from the humanistic view¬
point. Well done! It enables people of"
all nationalities, religions and races to
recognize the things that bring them
closer together and reminds them that
they must make a common front to
overcome all the problems facing them.
Your issues deal with problems of
the greatest interest and, above all, your
special numbers like "The Conquest of
the Desert" and "Twenty-five Centuries
of Buddhist Art and Culture" give one
a precise view of certain problems.
However your treatment of some
other questions is too superficial and
leaves us with a thirst for more facts
about the problems you have dealt
with a thirst that you alone with your
world-wide documentation can satisfy.
I know that some of your readers
would protest at the idea of raising the
intellectual and scientific level of your
magazine, and would accuse you of
failing to remain in the realm of
popular understanding. But I believe
it is preferable for the diffusion and
influence of The Unesco Courier to
raise rather than to lower its level. It
is through contacts with highminded
ideas that human minds are exalted.
What I am really sorry to see is
your magazine looking like some small
popular publication when it should
remain as a review devoted to the study
of the urgent human problems which
face humanity today.
Pierre Ouette
Courbevoie, France
INTERNATIONAL COOKING
Sir,
I am president of a small club the
United Nations Youth Fellowship
which is a junior branch of the U.N.
Association in Adelaide. Our 150
members include many nationalities,
including Europeans and Asian students.
We have had little contact with similar
U.N. youth groups in other parts of
the world. Perhaps we might be able
to compare our activities and interests
through The Unesco Courier. Has
there been an issue of The Unesco
Courier on international cooking and
ways of eating yet? I'm sure we have
much to learn here in Australia on that
subject.
A.C. Adams
North Adelaide, South Australia
Ed. Note : See The Unesco Courier,
April 1957 ("The Food We Eat") which
included recipes from an international
cookbook published by the U.N. Nursery
School, Geneva.
FOR HUMAN SOLIDARITY
Sir,
By giving us useful and detailed in¬
formation about different peoples, your
magazine broadens our outlook on the
world. We often think only in terms
of a single civilization our own but
The Unesco Courier puts us into
contact with others. It also enables us
to keep abreast with questions of
particular interest to the modern world.
You are achieving a great deal, for
you bring home to us the real meaning
of human solidarity...
Madeleine Catella
Lyons, France
ESSENTIAL PUBLICATION
Sir,
Let me offer a word of profound
appreciation and gratitude for The
Unesco Courier. I have arranged to
have it supplied to this office as an
essential publication. And my successor
(on my retirement), Stuart Jackman,
will continue the arrangement.
Leonard Hurst
London Missionary Society
ENCYCLOPEDIA'
Sir,
I have been a regular reader of your
magazine since 1953 and I have
consistently admired its class and
appearance. All the issues I have read
and kept since that time now constitute
a kind of supplementary encyclopedia
of the scientific, cultural and phil¬
anthropic activities of the nations. I
was particularly struck by the issue of
May, 1958 ("World Health: Ten Years
of Progress".) It showed not only the
technical difficulties arising out of
public health problems around the
world, but also brought home strongly
to me the reasons why nations must
unceasingly link their efforts to track
down and wipe out epidemics on every
continent.
J.M. Robillard
Montreal, Canada
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
For reasons beyond our control
the schedule of publication of
THE UNESCO COURRIER has
been considerably delayed. We
ask our readers' continued
indulgence and hope that
the normal date of delivery
will shortly be re-established.
lANDIER 'TALKING BOOKS':
A project designed to give blind
readers handier "'talking books" and
up to ten times as many as they now
have by reducing production costs per
book is being investigated by the
United States Library of Congress,
which is now studying the production
of 8 1/3 rpm. recordings and record
players. Record players would be
smaller, lighter and more durable
than present ones and smaller records
could be mailed more easily. Records
for each book would be reduced by
three-quarters. Hemingway's For
Whom the Bell Tolls would require
only six records instead of 22 as today.
TRAILING THE LOCUST: A
combined Food and Agriculture
Organization-UNEsco team left
Europe recently to study the
ecology of locusts in the Sudan
and the Chad Territory, in Africa.
This was the first of a series of
similar expeditions scheduled for
1959 and 1960 which will cover the
whole locust-infested area spread¬
ing from Morocco to India, through
Africa and the Middle East. The
present team consists of George
Popov, an expert on locusts from
the United Kingdom (appointed by
the FAO) and Charles Rosetti, a
Swiss plant ecologist (nominated
by Unesco). Together with Sud¬
anese assistants they will study
relations between vegetation, cli¬
mate and soil and the proliferation
of locusts.
TiWENTY-NINE FOR FREE FLOW
Austria has become the 29th country
to join a Unesco-sponsored inter¬
national agreement exempting books,
newspapers, magazines, works of art
and music scores from import duties.
Also exempt are newsreels, educational
films, sound recordings and scientific
equipment if consigned to approved
institutions. Besides lifting import
duties, the agreement grants import
licences and foreign exchange for
books needed by public libraries. The
agreement forms part of Unesco's
programme to promote the "free flow
of ideas."
ASIA IN THE CLASSROOM :
Several thousand schoolchildren in
the United Kingdom have recent¬
ly been hearing special talks on
Asian countries sponsored by the
Council for Education in World
34
Citizenship. These lectures were
organized in co-operation with the
U.K. National Commission for
Unesco in connexion with Unes¬
co's Major Project to encourage
East - West understanding. The
talks dealt either with one of four
Asian countries China, India,
Indonesia and Pakistan or with
the changing situation in Asia ge¬
nerally, and were given by experts
who had lived in the countries as
well as by members of the staffs
of Asian embassies.
H ANDLING ISOTOPES SAFELY:
Safety recommendations for persons
handling isotopes have been drawn
up by experts from ten countries invi¬
ted to Vienna by the International
Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) of the
United Nations. These recommen¬
dations cover packaging, transport,
use and disposal of radio-isotopes
based on knowledge about the effect
on health of varying degrees of ra¬
diation and permissible radiation
levels. The IAEA is to work out health
and safety codes for a wide range
of operations in the atomic field and
its work is being co-ordinated with
that already carried out by other in¬
ternational organizations, particularly
the World Health Organization and
the International Labour Organi -
zation.
NOW EIGHTY STRONG: The
Federation of Malaya has now
joined Unesco, bringing thß total
number of Member States to 80.
The Federation has taken part in
Unesco's work for the past four
years as an Associate Member State.
After proclaiming its independence
in August 1957, it applied for
membership of the United Nations
and was admitted on September 17.
The Federation of Malaya produces
about half of the world's natural
rubber and a third of its tin.
Almost half of its six million
people are Malay, more than two
and a quarter million are Chinese
and nearly 750,000 are Indian or
Pakistani.
Jr\ WOMAN'S NATIONALITY :
A United Nations Convention on the
nationality of married women and
' under which a wife may retain her
nationality irrespective of marriage
or divorce, or change of nationality
by her husband, became effective last
month. New Zealand was the latest
country to sign it early in July. It
had previously been ratified or acced¬
ed to by Ceylon, Cuba, the Dominican
Republic, Ireland, Israel, Norway,
Sweden and the United Kingdom.
RIVER-BORNE MUSEUM: People
living in provincial cities along the
banks of the Vistula River in
Poland who have little opportunity
of travelling to Warsaw and seeing
its big museums are now receiving
visits from a floating museum. A
pleasure steamer, the "Golden
Duck" has been specially equipped
to house some 200 items from the
Warsaw Museum of Popular Art
and Culture on Africa, Indonesia,
Qceania and the Americas. Pho¬
tographic panels illustrating the
life, customs and architecture of
these areas have been installed on
the upper deck of the ship, while
the exhibition itself, arranged on
the lower deck includes weapons
from Africa, statuettes carved by
Eskimos, dancing masks from
Africa and marionettes used in
Indonesian shadow plays.
Si»POTTING BIRDS BY RADAR:
Radar is most likely to become an
invaluable tool for ornithologists
studying migration habits of birds,
according to Dr. David Lack, a Bri¬
tish scientist. Radar echoes from
birds were first identified during the
war at listening posts working on
aircraft interception in southern Eng¬
land. For security reasons these
findings were not revealed, but Swiss
scientists independently made similar
discoveries and published their
findings. In recent experiments
high-flying and mist-concealed flocks
of migrant birds which would nor¬
mally have passed unnoticed have
been detected. Dr. Lack predicts that
radar may prove as important in
research on bird migration as the
sound spectrograph has proved in the
study of bird-song.
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe today to
THE UNESCO COURIER
Fill in this subscription blank and mail
it with your cheque or money order
to our local agent in your country
listed on page 35
Please enter my subscription for
THE UNESCO COURIER
D One year 83.00; 1 0/-stg. ; 500
French francs Q Cheque/Money Order
enclosed
D Two years $5.50; £1 stg.; 1,000
French francs
Name	
Address 	
City	
Country....
Profession..
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
AN IMPORTANT SURVEY
OF THE ROLE OF THE
EXECUTIVE IN THE
MODERN STATE
At a moment when the people of France
are being asked to pronounce themselves
on a new Constitution, the current issue of
UNESCO's International Social Science Bul¬
letin (Vol. X, N° 2) will interest readers
with its timely survey on "The Role
of the Executive in the Modern State".
The issue is based on a series of studies
carried out last year by UNESCO'S Depart¬
ment of Social Sciences in six countries :
France, Canada, U.S.S.R., U.S.A., United
Kingdom, and Yugoslavia. An extensive
amount of supplementary information
was collected from correspondents in
nine additional countries, which has
resulted in a clear and detailed presen¬
tation of the current political scene.
The major section of the issue is devoted
to separate surveys on each of the six
countries studied, revealing the great
diversity of background and the impos¬
sibility of generalizing on the role of the
executive in contemporary society. In
a preliminary article, Professor Jean Mey-
naud, of the University of Lausanne and
the Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes,
Paris, examines the commonplace remark
that "parliamentary assemblies are ill-
suited to the new responsibilities assumed
by 20th century governments and that
the larger share of these responsibilities
has devolved upon the executive branch."
He reviews the executive's tasks and res¬
ponsibilities, his relation to the govern¬
mental system and to the administration,
his reaction to pressure groups and poli¬
tical parties, and examines the delicate
topic of the reform of the executive.
INTERNATIONAL
SOCIAL SCIENCE
BULLETIN
\
The Role of the Executive
in the .Modern Slate
VOL. X. Xo. », mo .TniTft
PUBLISHED CltJAkTKKl-Y Hill)
IA1 PRÍCF.: H.nu: lV-[u<;; ,oulr (
The International Social Science Bulletin
appears quarterly in English and French,
its contributors being recognized spe¬
cialists in the fields of scientific interest
chosen as the subject of each issue. It
can be obtained from booksellers or directly
from UNESCO distributors listed below
at a price of U.S. $1.00; 6/-(stg); or
300 F. frs per issue. Annual subscription
rate: U.S. $3.50; 2l/-(stg); 1,000 F. frs
(these rates apply only until Jan. I. 19 59,
when an increase will go into effect).
Titles of some recent issues of the Social
Science Bulletin : THE NEGRO IN THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA (Vol. IX,
N° 4); SOCIAL CONSEQUENCES OF
AUTOMATION (Vol. X, N°l); DISAP¬
PEARING CULTURES (Vol. IX, N" 3).
GUIDE TO UNESCO
PUBLICATIONS
The second revised edition of the Check List of
Unesco publications has now been published.
Free copies can be obtained from UNESCO'S
National Distributors or by writing to UNESCO
Sales Section, Place de Fontenoy, Paris. The latest
Check List contains alphabetical lists of the fol¬
lowing: (a) Titles of all UNESCO publications in
English available for sale as of April I, 19 58.
(b) All UNESCO periodicals currently published.
(c) Current series or collections of Unesco
publications, (d) Currently available UNESCO
publications in French or Spanish of which there
has been published no equivalent English edition.
1j n e s c o
UNESCO check list
2nd nwiwd ««Hon 1951
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. - Panuzai, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria. (A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 47, rue du Midi,
Brussels, C.C.P. 3 38.000. (fr.b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16 rue Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151,
Antwerp.
BRAZIL. Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
Mexico 98-B, Caixa Postal 3291, Rio de
Janeiro.
BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
CANADA. The Queen's Printer, The
Superintendent of Publications, Ottawa,
(Cn .)
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, I 00 Parsons RoadColombo 2. (Rs. 9)
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section 1,-Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado I 13, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box I 20, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. U nesco Sales Section,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris, 1'. C.C.P.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
(500 fr.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I ; 3 6a, Mount Road , Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ I Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I ; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Raikamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, I 6 South
Frederick St., Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
3 5, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street. Tel-Aviv. (£.l./4..)
ITALY. Librería Commissionaria San-
soni. Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 950)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (500 fr.).
MOROCCO. Paul Fekete. 2, rue Cook,
Tangier.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7. Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. 49, Apartado de Correos
201 8, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., I 104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniania
Wydawnictw Naukowych PAN, Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724. Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. - AÍB CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm
16. (Sw.kr. 7.50)
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. (frs. S. 6.50)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E. 1.(1 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
&,#*>
&W&
£?£?%*
«wft
tjl-
]]>
</page>
</document>
