<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066321eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
o\^
ÜP
m
Ëw s\
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Je?
Air
PCS
Bfcä
-.
.*M ; (
J7
>ï '
>*'
4S
f~ v*V tí
* z
<Ä
,
R
:r W
- .'r (.
-&,
r$5«£
\ *^**!¿
:á¿^ téSfe, %
A time to live... 37 Brazil
In the 18th century, the Brazilian economy
was dominated by gold and diamonds. The
exploitation of gold and other mineral
deposits led to the development of the
Minas gérais ("general mines"), the name
of the State in southeastern Brazil which
is still the country's chief mining region.
Today Brazil is the world's fourth most
Open-air gold mine
important gold-producing country. The
open-cast Serra Pelada mine, above, is
located 400 km south of Belém, which lies
at the mouth of the Amazon and is the
capital of Para State. Some 20,000 workers
exploit the mine, which produces a ton of
gold each month.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the world
Editorial
IN modern times the art of writing has assumed such importance
that literature today seems inseparable from the written word.
Even though many cultures are known to be articulated around,
and transmitted by, the spoken word, there is still a strong inclination
in contemporary thinking to discount oral literature as the expression
of folklore, which is often regarded with a certain condescension.
In the present issue of the Unesco Courier we hope to correct
this false vision of the relationship between the spoken and the written
word.. To see. these modes of expression as locked in a fundamental
antagonism, both as forms and as aspects of different civilizations,
today increasingly seems to be an inadequate, overschematic analysis
of the situation. As Paul Zumthor shows in his introductory article,
there has never been a watertight barrier between the two forms
of expression; exchange has been constant. Even in the literature
and sensibilities of the Western societies which have been the most
active in raising the status of the written to the detriment of the oral,
traces of the interdependence of oral and written are far stronger
than might appear at first glance. And in the West, for all its fascination
with the written word, the once-stifled voice may be making a come¬
back at this very moment.
To show thé force of the spoken word, we highlight a number
of major texts which are botlfnationarepics and poems of universal
significance. The origins and destiny of each of these works form
original variants of the relationship between the spoken and the writ¬
ten word, but they are all primarily texts in which a people can find
its roots and identify itself, or else as in the case of the Chronicle
of Michoacán the final testament of a civilization.
Elsewhere in the issue, in the field of Arabic, Japanese, Basque,
Chinese and Indian cultures, we have tried to convey through specific
examples, synopses of stories and poems, and personal reminiscences,
the spiritual attraction and inspirational force of works which, trans¬
mitted by word of mouth and in many cases relayed by writing or
image, live on and echo in the minds of individuals and beat in the
hearts of communities.
But this spiritual treasure, which belongs to the heritage of hu¬
manity, is under threat. Unesco is contributing to its preservation,
especially since it is a vehicle of identity. Essential though it is to
record this heritage on tape or in writing, such measures do not go
far enough. The ultimate goal must be a redefinition of the concept
of cultural communication which recognizes the creative value of the
spoken word in every community.
Cover: Photo Michel Claude, Unesco
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
August 1985
38th year
^
0¿
Photo Richard Frieman © Rapho, Paris
$1 . frsdr
4 The living voice
by Paul Zumthor
9 The Kalevala
The birth of Finland's national epic
by Lauri Honko
11 The land of heroes
12 The Kalevala and the flowering of Finnish art
by Heikki Kirkinen
1 5 The Chronicle of Michoacán
Testament of a people
by J.M.G. Le Clézio
17 The Lay of Igor's Campaign
by Igor Shkliarevsky
19 Shaka the Great
by Mazisi Kunene
21 The glory of the spoken
by Salah Stétié
24 The Tale of the Heike
Japan's long-running medieval saga
by René Sieffert
26 Who's Who in the Mahabharata?
by Lokenath Bhattacharya
28 Liu Jingting, prince of story-tellers
by Yao Zhenren
30 Tibet's Ge-sar epic
by Mireille Helffer
32 The love-story of Hir and Ranjha
by Hakim Mohammed Said
33 Basque literature and the oral tradition
by Juan Mari Lekuona
34 Unesco Newsroom
2 A time to live...
BRAZIL: Open-air gold mine
Published monthly in 32 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
German Persian Korean Bulgarian
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French,
Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N° 8 - 1985 - OPI
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The living voice
by Paul Zumthor
NO one today questions the impor¬
tance of the part played by the voice
in the preservation of human soci¬
eties, although it was long discounted by
historians who paid little or no attention
to anything but the written word. What
is known as the oral tradition of a social
group is a system of vocal communications
bound up with attitudes that are more or
less rigidly codified, the prime function of
which is to ensure the continuity of a con¬
ception of life and the experience of a
group without which the individual would
be a prey to the vicissitudes of his solitary
state, if not to despair.
This seems obvious enough if we are
thinking of primitive civilizations or some
of the marginal cultures of the world today.
But it is harder for us to realize that our
own rational, technological culture of the
late twentieth century is imbued with oral
traditions and would find it hard to survive
without them.
In this article I shall consider only one
aspect, that of "poetry" in the broadest
meaning of the term, that is, an art which
arises spontaneously from language and
the perpetuation of which is a constant of
history, so much so that it could be called
one of the factors by which man can be
defined. But while everyone thinks it
natural that African or Amerindian ethnic
groups should have their own treasure-
house of poetry which is maintained by
oral tradition, we have to strain our imag¬
ination to detect more than traces of such
poetry in our own civilization a still active
presence, when the stage of moribund folk¬
lore has been passed.
Statistics show that ten thousand songs
a year were being composed around the
year 1980 in France alone. Allowing an
average of three minutes for each song,
that makes five hundred hours' listening,
or one hour and twenty minutes every day!
Even if we do not count failures the
effects of selection before the works are
performed there is still a considerable
mass of them. I use the word mass delib¬
erately, because this is clearly a phenom¬
enon of "mass culture", the main form of
poetry that is alive and functional at a
group level in the 1980s. There is no reason
to suppose that France is exceptional in
this respect.
We have to make an effort to admit that
this is so. For love of the "live" word died
out long ago in our Western societies,
being gradually excluded from the interests
of intellectuals and also from our "basic
personality." Owing to a prejudice that has
been part of Western mentality and tastes
for centuries, we are unwilling to accept
what is produced by any art derived from
language unless it is in written form. The
one exception we make is for the theatre.
This is why we find it difficult to acknowl¬
edge the aesthetic validity of anything
which, in intention or in fact, is not written
down. In the last five or six centuries all
the countries of Europe first, next those
of America, then starting from different
premises those of Asia, refined the tech¬
niques of writing to such a degree that our
sensibility automatically rejects what
seems to be the immediacy of vocal
expression.
Is this merely a matter of historical cir¬
cumstances that affect only the surface of
things, or is it a shift in hidden structures
that govern our perception and our
thinking? The Canadian Marshall
McLuhan examined this question as early
as 1962, and in The Gutenberg Galaxy, a
book that attracted much attention,
opened up a path for sociological and phil-
"Through the voice, the word becomes
something that is exhibited, a gift (...) In
extreme cases, the meaning of the words
ceases to matter and the voice of itself
captivates us because of the self-mastery
It indicates, as the Ancients taught us with
the myth of the Sirens." Above, mosaic
from the Bardo Museum, Tunis, illus¬
trating the story of Odysseus and the
Sirens, a famous episode in the Greek
poet Homer's epic The Odyssey. The
Sirens were mythical creatures, half-bird,
half-woman, who lured sailors to destruc¬
tion by the enchantment of their singing.
Homer tells us that Odysseus escaped
this danger yet heard their song by stop¬
ping the ears of his crew with wax and
having himself tied to the mast so that
he could not steer the ship off its course.
osophical reflection which has been effec¬
tively prospected by a number of research
workers since then. As we know, the prin¬
ciple they observe is that a message is more
than what appears to be its content. It has
another content, which is latent and which
stems from the very nature of the medium
by which it is transmitted. The introduction
of writing into a society and its subsequent
adoption by everyone therefore entails a
mutation in the mental, economic and
institutional spheres. Thus, in McLuhan's
view, two types of civilization that of oral
culture and that of written culture con¬
front each other. In a world based on oral
expression, man, who is directly in touch
with the cycles of nature, interiorizes his
experience of history without conceptual¬
izing it. He perceives time in the circular
patterns of a perpetual return, and con¬
sequently his actions are inevitably deter¬
mined by group norms. But the practice
of writing implies disjunction between
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
thought and action, an abstraction which
weakens the very power of language, the
predominance of a linear conception of
time, individualism, rationalism and
bureaucracy.
Research workers today hold that a
dichotomy of this nature cannot be main¬
tained except in a very general way, in
theory, and only insofar as it throws a con¬
trasting light on concrete reality, which is
nearly always situated in a median position
between extremes. The latter reveal dif¬
ferences which, as a rule, are actually only
differences of degree, since every cultural
situation has a different proportion of the
various characteristics concerned.
Yet these differences, slight though they
may be in practice, are categorical rather
than historical in nature. In most societies
men of the spoken word and men of the
written word are to be found side by side
and working together, in any period of
history. It is true that some civilizations
have known nothing of the written word
at least that is what we are told. But per¬
haps these civilizations have been less
numerous than one might think. For what
is writing? Symbolic marks, masks, tat¬
tooing and the various social emblems
are they writing or not? And other things
could be added to this list.
With these reservations, it is possible to
suggest a general typology of "situations
of orality". There are many such situ¬
ations, and the distinction between some
of them is unclear, but broadly speaking
there are four kinds:
primary orality, which has no contact
with any kind of writing;
mixed orality, which exists alongside
writing in a sociological context in which
the influence of writing is partial, external,
and slow to take effect;
secondary orality, which is actually
reconstructed from writing (the voice
utters what has been written or what has
been thought out in terms of writing) in
a context in which the written word takes
precedence, in both action and imagina¬
tion, over the authority of the voice;
mediatized orality, which we experi¬
ence today through the radio, gramophone
records and other media.
The only context in which primary oral¬
ity has flourished is in archaic communities
which have long since vanished. Even
today it is found here and there in the
tropics, among "primitive" cultures which
are dying out. The vestiges of primary oral¬
ity that ethnologists have found mean little
to us except as evidence touching evi¬
dence it is true, but incomplete and prob¬
lematical. Mixed and secondary orality
break down into an infinite number of
shades of meaning, as many as there are
degrees in the dissemination and use of
the written word, depending on the diver-
Considered by the ancient Egyptians to
be of divine origin, writing was reserved
to a privileged caste, the scribes. Below
left, Old Kingdom (Vth Dynasty, c.2494 to
c.2345 BC) painted statue of a seated
scribe, Louvre Museum. The nomadic
Tuaregs of Africa still use a traditional
form of writing, the tifinagh, but their his¬
tory and their literature are rooted in the
oral tradition. Below right, a Tuareg singer
from Algeria with an imzad (a single-string
violin). Tuareg women are the guardians
of the collective memory of their people
and their songs recount the feats of their
ancestors.
sity of societies and levels of cultures.
Mediatized orality is found today side by
side with the third or the second form of
orality, and even with the first, in a few
remote regions.
Typically, primary orality is character¬
istic of a civilization based on the voice.
The latter is a fundamental dynamic force,
whose function is both to create and to
preserve common values. A number of
books have been published on this role of
vocal activity, especially in African tra¬
ditional cultures. But the phenomenon is
universal. The difference between the
poetic forms produced in this way and writ¬
ten poetry is that the former do not provide
either those who hear them or historians
with material that can be slotted into water¬
tight lists and categories. When an eth¬
nologist records such poetic forms,
whether he intends to publish them in a
book or not, the very fact that he has
recorded them in a sense modifies the
nature of what has been recorded, just as
a photograph of a person is not the same
as his face.
Even if writing is widely practiced in a
society, primary orality remains alive in
that society, and may evolve for a con¬
siderable time in accordance with its own
laws. Again a good example of this can
be seen in Africa, which has experienced
this kind of thing at least twice in the course
of its history first with Islamization and
the introduction of the Arabic alphabet
among the educated section of the pop¬
ulation, in the tenth century, and then with
colonization, in the nineteenth century.
More generally speaking, today, where a
community has both a national language
with a written form and local languages
or dialects which exist only in an oral form
E
3
0)
tfí
S
tu
>
O
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
"The partition that appears to separate
oral poetry from written poetry (...) has
never been watertight (...) Many tales,
poems and songs which were written
down (...) became part of the oral tradition
and in some cases have remained so
much a part of it that their origin has been
lost sight of." Martín Fierro, by José Her¬
nandez, one of the great national poems
ofArgentina, published In 1872anda clas¬
sic of Hispano-Amerlcan literature, is a
masterpiece of the literature of the gau¬
chos. This written work, which is both
erudite andpopular in inspiration, quickly
became part of the repertoire of the pay-
adores, the wandering singers of the Rio
de la Plata, who improvised poems to the
accompaniment of the guitar. Left,
drawing of the gaucho Martín Fierro by
the contemporary Argentine artist Juan
Carlos Castagnino.
"Some civilizations have known nothing
of the written wordat least that Is what
we are told. But perhaps these civiliza¬
tions have been less numerous than one
might think. For what is writing ? Symbolic
marks, masks, tattooing and the various
social emblemsare they writing or not?
And other things could be added to this
list." Below, symbolic bark-painting by
the Australian aboriginal artist Daodi tells
us how the "man-crocodile" and the
"man-lizard" first succeeded in produc¬
ing fire and how the "man-crocodile" sub¬
sequently stole it (see the Unesco Cour¬
ier, January 1980).
or are no longer written, tension often
arises between a written national litera¬
ture, an oral poetry that employs a patois
to some extent, and attempts made by
regionalist movements to bring in a literary
(and therefore written) version of the local
speech.
In France, in the last century and a half,
the example of Occitan has shown the
extent of the various implications of such
a development; but great tracts of Africa,
Asia and even America are in the same
situation today, with more dramatic
effects.
Besides, the fact that tales or poems (or
even poetical genres as such) which have
hitherto been part of the oral tradition are
committed to writing does not necessarily
mean the end of that tradition. A two-tier
system may emerge we may have a ref¬
erence text (or textual model) which may
give rise to a body of written works, and
also to various oral versions that continue
to be produced at different times and
places. The history of European cultures
(perhaps from the time of ancient Greece)
provides plenty of illustrations of this pro¬
cess. When Elias Lönnrot published the
Kalevala in 1835, the oral tradition con¬
tinued to flourish so vigorously that a sec¬
ond Kalevala, published fifteen years later,
was twice as long as the first! Other exam¬
ples are the Russian byliny, the Anglo-
Scottish ballads, the Spanish Romancero
and the Japanese Tale of the Heike.
The African Shaka cycle is a noteworthy
case in our own day. Shaka, who founded
the Zulu empire at the beginning of the
nineteenth century, became the hero of
epics which are today part of the oral tra¬
dition. But a novel based on these epics
was written in 1925, and from it emerged
a pan-African literary tradition to which
we owe a number of important works in
English, French and even in the vernac¬
ular, which have been produced in a wide
variety of regions, from the Republic of
South Africa to Zambia, Congo, Guinea,
Senegal and Mali.
It sometimes happens that oral poets are
influenced by certain stylistic usages or
thematic trends that belong to the written
tradition. Such mutual influences are the
rule today; but the partition that appears
to separate oral poetry from written poetry
that is part of the literature has never been
watertight, and in many cases it has not
kept the two apart. Many tales, poems and
songs were written down and based on a
substantial literary tradition but, either
because their authors intended it to be so
or because of some accident of history,
became part of the oral tradition and in
some cases have remained so much part
of it that their origin has been lost sight
of. This was true of most of the "popular"
or folk songs of Europe and America.
On the other hand, of course, some of
the world's greatest writers have linked up
with an oral "popular" tradition from
which their art has derived part of its
power. When a work produced in this way
belongs to the past, it is therefore some¬
times marked by an ambiguity which his¬
torians and specialists in poetics find very
difficult to resolve. Well-known examples
are the Russian The Lay of Igor's Cam¬
paigners German Song of the Nibelungen,
and probably most of our medieval
"literature".
Yet even when such admixtures appear
to be inextricable a real difference remains,
which cannot be eradicated. One text may
be intended to be absorbed visually (as a
rule, by one person and in silence) by read¬
ing; another may be intended to be heard
(so that the listener will hear sounds, which
means, as a rule, that it is to be heard by
a group of people). The first text is a tan¬
gible thing a sheet of paper or a book.
The second is a vocal action. If we con¬
sider as I think we should that a work
attains its consummation, its peak of per¬
fection, the form which shows us its inner¬
most nature and the original intention of
its author (not necessarily consciously felt,
but determinative) at the moment when
it is communicated to another person, then
we have two entirely different works,
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
according to whether the text is read or
spoken; and this is so if the same text is
both read and spoken. It becomes two
works, which have only the form of the
words in common. Half a century after the
death of Dante, the Divine Comedy, which
was intended to be read, was on the lips
of the ordinary people of Florence, who
sang its terzine as they walked along the
streets. Was it the same work? Of course
not.
Written works have their own values,
on which European and American critics
have concentrated in the last twenty years.
But the voice brings to the fore other val¬
ues, which in the course of a performance
become part of the meaning of the text
that is being transmitted. They enrich it
and transform it, sometimes making it
mean what it does not say. For the voice
is more than speech". Its function is greater
than that of conveying language. It does
not convey language; rather language is
conveyed through it, and the physical exist¬
ence of the voice hits us with the force
of a material object. The voice is a thing;
its qualities can be described and meas¬
ured tone, timbre, range, height, regis¬
ter. Most civilizations have attached a sym¬
bolic value to each of these qualities, and
in everyday relations between persons we
judge people by their voice and (with a
bad conscience sometimes) we apply this
judgment to the value of what they say.
If I am listening to oral poetry, such
considerations determine my aesthetic per¬
ception. And more than that there can ^
"In those days when writing was virtually
. non-existent in parts of Africa, the task
ofmemorizing and recounting history had
to be entrusted to a particular social
group. It was thought that the successful
transmission of this history required a
musical background, and so the oral
transmission of history was confided to
trie griots, the musicians' caste,(...) which
thus became the repository of the col¬
lective memory of the peoples of Africa.
Griots are also poets, actors, dancers and
mimes and they introduce all these arts
into their performances." [The Sene¬
galese griot Lamine Konte, during a
recent interview with French journalist
and musicologist Marc Kerjean] Above,
the Kama-blon, the sacred hut of Kan-
gaba, Mali, the roof of which is cere¬
monially rebuilt every seven years. This
ceremony is the occasion fora greatgath¬
ering to hear the griots recount the gen¬
esis of Mall and to recall the exploits of
the epic figure king Soundiata Keita.
Within the framework of one of its major
programmes, Unesco Is actively working
to help preserve the non-physical ele¬
ments of the world's cultural heritage. In
Mali, a pilot project has been launched
which aims to revitalize the knowledge
embodied in the oral tradition so that it
can contribute to the development of
communities of whose cultural expres¬
sion it is a key element.
Lat Dior (1842-1886), king of Cayor (in
present-day Senegal) fought to the death
against the colonial invaders. His heroic
exploits, long part of his people's oral
tradition, have now been recorded in the
written history of Africa. Below, Lat Dior
as portrayed on a modern Senegalese
postage stamp.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
be no doubt that the voice is an archetypal
form in the human unconscious, a pri¬
mordial, creative image, a force and a con¬
figuration of characteristics that predispose
each of us to particular experiences, feel¬
ings and thoughts. When we hear poetry
spoken, this force is. reactivated in us, in
a more or less confused way, but some¬
times with gi eat violence (as in the case
of certain rock music festivals). A human
form is there, and speaks to me, being
represented by the voice that emanates
"The come-back of the voice Is not only
due to media technology. Through the
media (...) we are witnessing a reawak¬
ening of the vocal powers of mankind,
after a period when public opinion had
devalued them." Below, people walking
around listening to portable cassette-
players are an everyday sight today.
from it. Through the voice, the word
becomes something that is exhibited, a gift
that is virtually eroticized, and at the same
time an act of aggression, a determination
to conquer the other person, who submits
because of the pleasure he derives from
hearing it. In extreme cases, the meaning
of the words ceases to matter, and the voice
of itself captivates us because of the self-
mastery it indicates, as the Ancients taught
us through the myth of the Sirens.
At least, all this was true in the past.
Is it true in 1985? Certainly, there are still
many traces of this sort of thing. Many
of us feel nostalgic, others want to retrieve
values that may have been lost, by chal¬
lenging the power of the ever-dominant
written word. Since the beginning of this
century there has been a movement for
poets to recite their poetry. Yet the fact
is that today the poetic voice comes to us
mainly in its mediatized forms and this
leads to ambiguity. The time when we hear
a poem (when we are listening to a record
or the radio or watching television) is the
moment when the "work" is created. But
the medium has been displaced; it now
occupies a space slightly removed from
both the written word and the voice. Elec¬
tronic media are comparable with the writ¬
ten word in three ways:
they do away with the presence of
the speaker;
' they have nothing of the purely pres¬
ent nature of a recital, for the vocal mes¬
sage that they transmit can be repeated
indefinitely in exactly the same form;
owing to the manipulation made pos¬
sible by highly sophisticated recording sys¬
tems, they tend to obliterate the spatial
associations of the live voice, and artifi¬
cially reconstruct the environment in which
it is used.
However, the media differ from writing
in one vital respect: what they transmit is
heard, and therefore cannot be read (apart
from the television or film image), that is,
it cannot be deciphered as the codified
signs of language can. This explains the
belief, widely felt in recent years, that the
triumph of the media is a kind of revenge
taken by the voice after centuries of repres¬
sion under the dominance of the written
word. This is true, but the come-back of
the voice is not only due to media tech¬
nology. It is through the media, and per¬
haps by virtue of the false idea that most
people entertain of them today, that we
are witnessing a reawakening of the vocal
powers of mankind, after a period when
public opinion had devalued them. Evi¬
dence of this reawakening can be seen in
many spheres, from the indifference of
many young people to the pleasures of
reading and the revival of the art of singing
throughout the world in the 1950s, 1960s
and 1970s.
What does all this add up to, in the long
run? At all events, what we have com¬
pletely lost with the advent of the media
is bodily presence the authority, the
warmth and the visible volume of the body,
of which the voice is but an extension. And
this produces in the person to whom the
medium is addressed (and perhaps also in
the person whose voice is transmitted by
it) a special kind of alienation, a disin¬
carnation of which he is probably not com¬
pletely aware, but which is certainly to be
found somewhere in his unconscious. We
may well wonder what inner disturbances
are now being produced, unknown to us,
by such repression.
It is, I think, inevitable that the live voice
should experience a pressing need to speak
out once more, to use an expression whose
full meaning should be restored. And this
is probably the best way to ensure the sur¬
vival and the renewal of the traditions of
the living poetic voice, which are in such
jeopardy today.
PAUL ZUMTHOR was born in Geneva, Switz¬
erland, and now lives in Montreal, Canada. A
specialist in medieval literature, he has for many
years made a particular study of oral poetry in
the contemporary world. He is the author of
many works, including Essai de Poétique Médi¬
évale (Essay on Medieval Poetry, 1972) and
Introduction à la Poésie Orale (Introduction to
Oral Poetry, 1983).
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The birth of Finland's national epic
I HO f%CIf©l/CIfCI by Lauri Honko
THE origins of epics based on folk
poetry are usually clouded in mys¬
tery. We can only guess at the gene¬
sis of such treasures as the Mahabharata,
the epics of Homer and Virgil, Beowulf,
the Nibelungenlied and the Edda. The Kal¬
evala, the national epic of Finland, which
was first published in 1835, is an interesting
exception.
We know that the Kalevala (Kalevala
is the name of the mythical land in which
the epic is situated) was compiled and
edited by Elias Lönnrot (1802-1884) , a doc¬
tor who for twenty years was district phy¬
sician in Kajaani, in north-eastern Finland,
and who later became professor of Finnish
language and literature at the University
of Helsinki.
We know, line by line, the sources of
the Kalevala, those folk poems that Lönn¬
rot collected during the eleven journeys
he made to the eastern and northern prov¬
inces during the period 1828-1844, as well
as poems recorded by dozens of other col¬
lectors which were included in the second
and final edition published in 1849.
We also know Lönnrot's working me¬
thods; his compilation work is illuminated
by his travel accounts and newspaper arti¬
cles, by the method he used in handling
his poetic raw material and by the five
editorial phases which preceded the final
published version. Since the original
recorded poems have been preserved and
published (1908-1948) in the thirty-three-
volume Suomen Kansan Vanhat Runot
(Ancient Poems of the Finnish People),
and since other documentary evidence
abounds, we are able to follow in the foot¬
steps of the compiler of the epic. It is as
if we were looking over his shoulder as
he sat working at his desk.
The story of the genesis of the Kalevala
began in the 1760s. It was then that Henrik
Gabriel Porthan, professor at the Turku
Academy, began publishing his treatise on
Finnish poetry {Dissertatio de Poesi Fen-
nica, 1766-1778). It was not until Porthan's
day, and largely thanks to him, that it was
realized that folk poetry, maintained in
oral tradition, was a more valuable part
of the Finnish-language literary heritage
than any previous Finnish literature, which
had been predominantly religious and eco¬
nomic in nature.
A second turning point came with the
treaty of Hamina (1809) which severed the
ties between Finland and Sweden (which
went back nearly seven centuries) and
attached her as a self-governing Grand
Duchy to the Russian Empire. The far-
advanced assimilation with Sweden was
broken, doors were opened towards the
Finno-Ugric tribes in eastern Europe, and
the first Diet planted in the minds of Finns
an image of a Finland which was more than
a few provinces belonging either to Sweden
or to Russia. ^
Caricature drawn in 1847 depicts Elias
Lönnrot, the author/compiler of the Kal¬
evala, tirelessly travelling the country In
search of the ancient songs of his people.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
There are no known pictures of the great
singers interviewed by Lönnrot, and it
was not until the 1890s that photo¬
graphers and artists began to retrace his
footsteps. In 1894, I.K. Inka, the pioneer
of Finnish photography, made a journey
to north-eastern Karelia from which he
brought back some wonderful portraits
and landscapes. Photo shows Inka (right)
and his travelling companion K.F. Kar-
jalainen (left) with peasants from the
region during a halt on the shores of Lake
Kuittijärvi.
^ This resulted in an identity crisis. The
educated, Swedish-speaking minority had
to decide whether to turn towards Russian
culture or to identify themselves with the
language and underdeveloped culture of
the majority. They chose the latter course
even though it entailed a dramatic change
of language and the difficult task of build¬
ing a new identity. The Finnish language
had to be raised from its state of deg¬
radation and made into a. language of cul¬
ture. A Finnish-language literature had to
be built and material collected for a new
kind of Finnish history.
In the autumn of 1822, three students
enrolled at the Turku AcademyJ. V.
Snellman, J.L. Runeberg and Elias Lönn¬
rot. At the time no one could have foreseen
that Snellman was destined to become the
main ideologist of the national movement,
Runeberg the most important Swedish-
speaking poet in Finland and Lönnrot the
compiler of the Finnish national epic.
Elias Lönnrot represented the common
man in this group. He was a poor tailor's
son whose schooling was frequently inter¬
rupted for want of money. His talent
helped him to get ahead, his diligence
encouraged him to undertake great proj¬
ects at which others would have balked
and his unassuming manner won the
respect of both learned men and ordinary
people. His natural make-up and social
background coupled with his training as
a doctor gave him an understanding of and
an insight into the lives of ordinary people
and helped him to withstand the rigours
of his strenuous journeyings.
His interest in folk poetry aroused by
Reinhold von Becker, his teacher in the
Finnish language at the Turku Academy,
Lönnrot began his collecting expeditions
in 1828. These took him first to Finnish
Karelia and then to Archangel Karelia
beyond the border, where the Karelian
dialect was very close to Finnish.
What did Lönnrot find on his journeys?
He found poems, their singers and the
living environment in which the poems
formed an interlude to daily toil and the
high point of festive occasions. The var¬
iants known from collectors' manuscripts
now became a living stream of poems flow¬
ing from the lips of tens and later hundreds
of singers. In a word, Lönnrot stepped into
a world of living epic poetry and his mind
recorded not only the content of the poems
but also the whole varied but strictly
restricted verse language in which that
poetry lived. Without his mastery of that
language the peculiar genesis of the Kal¬
evala would not have been possible.
Lönnrot collected approximately two
thousand variants of poems, all in all some
forty thousand lines of poetry sung in the
ancient Finnish metre. This constituted
only a fragment of his collection in its
entirety since he also recorded fables,
riddles, proverbs and dirges as well as
material connected with local mores and,
above all with the language.
Lönnrot's journeys were comparatively
short, of only some weeks', at most
months', duration, and most of his time
was spent in travelling from one place to
another. He appears not to have stayed
long in any one place and it seems that
he did not record the entire repertoire of
any singer of note. There is no evidence
that Lönnrot was deeply interested in the
context in which the poems were per¬
formed or in the lives and fate of the rune
singers. As a rule he did not even record
the names of the singers in his notebook.
Thus there remained a considerable cul¬
tural distance between Lönnrot and the
rune singers.
The fact that Lönnrot did not identify
with any area or community that he
encountered was both understandable and
important understandable in that Lönn¬
rot was not primarily interested in modern
folk life but in the ancient Finnish society
of which it still possibly bore traces; impor¬
tant in the sense that he was freer to create
a poetic world of his own which repre¬
sented the entire tradition as conceived by
himself and not a system of tradition as
conceived by one singer or a single family
of singers.
Judged by the norms of our day, the
methods he used might be considered
unscientific; yet Lönnrot knew subcon¬
sciously that he needed time for the process
of integration to take place. In his relations
with the most important singers he met
Lönnrot maintained the attitude of an
apprentice almost to the end, until the first
edition of the Kalevala was published.
From the point of view of general com¬
parative epic research the question of the
authenticity of the Kalevala is very in¬
teresting. How well does the epic reflect
the folk poems preserved in oral tradition,
that is, how genuine is it as a folk poetry
epic? What were Lönnrot's goals in com¬
piling the Kalevala and how well did he
attain these goals with the poetic material
at his disposal? The endeavours of tra¬
ditional singers to combine tales of Väin-
ämöinen, for instance, have produced a
few minor epic cycles, which could be
called folk epics, but which are less than
a thousand lines long. There is no reason
to believe that the situation had been any
different in former centuries or that the
poems had originally been part of larger
entities. Thus the entity and structure of
the Kalevala represent Lönnrot's solution
to the problem upon which he may have
deliberated most during the compilation
what was the time sequence of the events
described in the narrative poems? His
interpretation involved no reconstruction,
only creative form-giving.
Study of the verse material reveals that
the proportion of Lönnrot's own com¬
positions is very small, three per cent
according to one calculation. Thus he man¬
aged with lines that he and other collectors
had found; this means that, if the criterion
is the authenticity of single lines, the Kale¬
vala is a very genuine folk poetry epic.
How about the remaining ninety-seven
per cent? Did they come straight from the
original poems? Some fifty per cent of the
Kalevala verses have been changed by
Lönnrot either in spelling, language or
verse. From the beginning of the Kalevala
process Lönnrot had been of the opinion
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
that differences in dialect or other incon¬
sistencies must not be too disturbing for
the reader, since the public consisted not
just of scholars but the whole nation. Four¬
teen per cent of the verses have no identical
equivalent in the poems but were com¬
bined from popular elements by Lönnrot.
Finally, thirty-three per cent of the lines
are exactly as found in the original
recordings.
The statistics show that Lönnrot never
aimed at poetic freedom where individual
lines were concerned. The liberties he took
lay elsewhere. Due to his working methods
the Kalevala contained few of the longer
sequences of lines to be found in the ori¬
ginal variants. Thus the context of most
lines had changed, not necessarily to a less
genuine one, but to a different one from
that in which they were found in oral tra¬
dition. This also means that the poems
have no place of origin, since lines from
variants found in different regions are
intermingled. This technique contributed
to the emergence of a pan-Finnish and not
a regional epic. Whether or not this was
Lönnrot's conscious aim is not clear, for
the actual function of this freedom was to
give form to the plot.
Lönnrot also tried to find a geographi¬
cally defined place for his vision and found
it south of the White Sea, where, according
to one contemporary view, the Finns could
have originated. As regards time, this idea
presupposed a time span of almost one
thousand years. In outlining this quasi-sci¬
entific view of antiquity Lönnrot ended up
developing a fuller insight into the world
of the Kalevala than we can imagine. As
a scholar he wanted to take account of all |
'The land of heroes'
THE Kalevala is a vast anthology of the Finnish popular
poetic tradition. In its definitive version it consists of fifty
poems, totalling 22,795 lines, painstakingly collected
between 1828 and 1849 by Elias Lönnrot from the mouths of
folk singers from Karelia, a remote district in northern Finland
where the traditional songs of the Finnish people had retained
all their original purity and freshness.
Ancient Finnish poetry did not rhyme, but it made great use
of alliteration and, above all, of "parallelism"; each thought or
topic had to be repeated in different terms in two or three con¬
secutive lines. These stylistic devices, which are often to be found
in the oral tradition, imbue the Kalevala with a bewitching fluidity,
as witness the following lines from the first poem of the epic.
They describe how two singers would recite a poem, sitting face
to face, holding hands and rocking gently backwards and forwards,
each reciting alternate lines.
Beloved brother, dear companion,
Dear comrade of my youth,
Come straightaway sing with me,
Since we are reunited,
Come close and sing with me (...)
Stretch out your hand to my hand,
Entwine your finger with my fingers,
Come sing our finest songs
Come spin our finest tales (...)
Then follows an account of the creation of the world and the
introduction of the great heroes whose exploits, loves and hates
make up the framework of the epic. These are the native sons
of Kalevala, the "land of heroes", the mythical cradle-land of
the Finnish people.
Reminiscent of the ancient pagan deities, these larger-than-life
characters with supernatural powers fight for possession of a mag¬
ical object, the Sampo. A mill or lid with miraculous powers,
the Sampo was made for Louhi, mistress of Pohjola, a cold
northern region, land of magicians and of darkness.
To Pohjola go three aspirants to the hand of Louhi's beautiful
daughter Väinämöinen, an aged bard whose wisdom is his
strength and who can charm the elements with his words, Lem-
minkäinen, valiant warrior and fickle seducer, and the dynamic,
enterprising blacksmith Ilmarinen.
After welcoming him to her castle, Louhi, mistress of Pohjola,
makes the following proposition to Ilmarinen:
"O mighty Ilmarinen,
Eternal blacksmith,
Canst thou forge a Sampo? (...)
My daughter shall be thy payment,
The recompense for thy labours."
In this fashion did Ilmarinen
The blacksmith, reply to Louhi:
"Yea I can forge a Sampo.
With feather of swan,
With milk of cull cow,
With grain of barley
And a tuft of lambswool,
I can fashion the ornate lid.
Did I not hammer out the sky,
Forge from nothing, not the merest scrap,
The great cover of the heavens?"
Thus Ilmarinen made the Sampo and married "the maid of
Pohjola". But after the death of his wife, the Sampo, for pos¬
session of which a furious struggle had erupted between the peo¬
ples of Kalevala and Pohjola, was broken in the course of a violent
sea battle. Its remnants brought happiness and prosperity to the
people of Kalevala, but, from that time on, their chieftain Väin¬
ämöinen had constantly to guard them against the vengeful sor¬
ceries of the mistress of Pohjola.
These two great adventures are interspersed with countless
mythological and traditional episodes, such as the theft of the
sun, of the moon and of fire, as well as other parallel intrigues
involving such vital and engaging personalities as the unfortunate
Kullervo, condemned to a life of slavery to satisfy the hatred
and desire for vengeance of others.
In the final poem, Väinämöinen yields pride of place to a
Messiah-like hero, born miraculously of a virgin, and disappears,
leaving to the Finnish people the echoes of his kantele, his world-
renowned harp.
Bronze medal by the Finnish artist Pekka
Pitkänen has been struck this year on the
initiative of the jubilee committee for the
150th anniversary of thepublication of the
first edition of the Kalevala. // Is being
awarded to persons who have helped to
make Finnish culture more widely known.
The jaws and teeth of a pike featured on
one side of the medal are a direct allusion
to the epic. They were used by Väinä¬
möinen, the central figure of the Kalevala,
to make the first kantele, the harp which
is the national instrument associated with
Finnish lyric poetry.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
the research findings that could throw light
on the Finns' past; as a poet he wanted
to recount the past in the words of a folk
poem, as if calling the folk singers, the first
receivers of the poetic messages of the past,
to bear him witness. For him the ancient
times of Kalevala were a phase in history.
Seen from this standpoint it is easier
to understand the astonishing fact that at
'times Lönnrot speaks of the Kalevala as
a source of scientific research which sheds
light on life in the ancient society. This
indicates that he underestimated the sig¬
nificance of his own input and overesti¬
mated the value of the Kalevala as an his¬
torical and ethnographical source.
No poet can announce in advance that
he is going to compile a national epic. The
decision as to whether a work is a national
epic or not is made by the reading public.
Nevertheless, expectations were high with
regard to the Kalevala and the first
speeches hailing it as a national epic were
made even before it reached the book¬
shops. No one had cause to regret making
these speeches and very rapidly, both at
home and abroad, the Kalevala came to
be recognized as a valuable addition to
both Finnish and world literature. The
builders of the new Finnish national iden¬
tity drew new belief in the future from the
epic which seemed to restore to the nation
both its literature and its history.
This enthusiasm focused naturally on
the future and not on the past. The epic
was commented on and translated even
before people had had time to study it in
depth. In fact there was no need to know
what the Kalevala contained, only what
it was.
It was not until the mid-1870s that
critical folk poetry research began and the
Kalevala was rejected as a source and orig¬
inal recorded poems began to be studied.
Kalevala research became part of research
done on Finnish literature and general epic
literature.
The Kalevala as a symbol of national
identity, however, belongs to the history
of Western thought and to cultural history.
The message that Elias Lönnrot wanted
to convey to the nation with the epic is
to be found in the mystery of the Sampo.
In Lönnrot's hands this magic object,
which mills all material wealth and which
is fought over by the people, is transformed
in the Kalevala into the symbol of man¬
kind's cultural development.
LAURI HONKO, of Finland, is professor of Folk¬
loristas and Comparative Religion at the Uni¬
versity of Turku, Director of the Nordic Institute
of Folklore and president of the Finnish Lit¬
erature Society and the International Society
for Folk-Narrative Research. He is the author
of several books on ethno-medicine, folk reli¬
gion, lamentation poetry, and the methodology
of research into folk traditions.
The Kalevala
and
the flowering
of Finnish art
by Heikki Kirkinen
THE Kalevala was born in the Euro¬
pean atmosphere of National
Romanticism stimulated by the
struggles for national autonomy. At the
time it was published Finland was a Grand
Duchy of the Russian Empire. The official
language was Swedish, a heritage of more
than six centuries of Swedish rule before
Russia invaded Finland in 1809. In none
of the schools was Finnish the language
of instruction and few educated people
understood Finnish. Over eighty per cent
of the population of one and a half million
were Finnish-speaking, but Finnish lit¬
erature consisted mainly of religious prose
and hymns.
At first the Kalevala was much admired
but little read. The 500 copies of the first
edition, published in 1835, took twelve
years to sell. During the nineteenth century
eight editions of the Kalevala were pub¬
lished, whereas in this century there have
been over sixty editions, including six in
the Soviet Union and four in the United
States.
The poetic beauty of the Kalevala, its
dramatic elements and its depiction of pop¬
ular yet mythical characters have always
been a source of inspiration to artists and
poets.
The themes most favoured by artists
have been the creation of the world, the
evidence of the magical powers of the great
sage Väinämöinen, the forging and theft
of the luck-bringing magical object the
Sampo, the adventures, death and revival
of the faithless lover Lemminkäinen, and
the tragic fate of Kullervo, who had been
raised as a slave.
During the 1850s, the first paintings and
sculptures on Kalevala themes were in the
Romantic style and were the work of Swed¬
ish artists. R.W. Ekman created idealized
images of Väinämöinen and other Kalevala
scenes, whereas J. Takanen used the
refined lyricism of neo-Classicism in his
sculptures. The stylistic schools of Italy and
France also had an effect on Finnish, which
began to shift from Classicism to Realism.
Up to the 1890s, then, Kalevala art, like
Finnish culture in general, was searching
for its own individual forms of expression.
The same search was also evident in
literature and music. Themes taken from
folk poems or the Kalevala were already
present in the Swedish-language literature
of the early nineteenth century, but full-
scale cultivation of the Kalevala spirit in
literature began later. The year 1869 saw
the performance of Z. Topelius' play Prin-
sessan av Cypern (The Princess of Cyprus),
which combined the adventures of the
Kalevala heroes and the world of ancient
Greece. The overture composed for it by
F. von Schantz is one of the first com¬
positions for an orchestra in the mood of
the Kalevala.
Aleksis Kivi, who was to become the
Finnish-language national writer, won the
best play award with his Kullervo, but con¬
servative critics demanded changes and it
was not performed until 1885. The lan¬
guage and metre of the Kalevala was a
stimulus to Kivi's poetry, although his
prose works are classed as Realism. H.J.
Erkko and many other poets favoured Kal¬
evala themes, but on the whole the rise
of political and language issues temporarily
weakened interest in the Kalevala.
A turn in the tide of cultural devel¬
opment occurred in 1885 at the time of
the fiftieth anniversary of the publication
of the Kalevala. That year saw the pub¬
lication of J. Krohn's Suomalaisen Kir-
jallisuuden Historia (History of Finnish Lit¬
erature) in which the Kalevala occupied
a central position.
After a period of maturation the Kal¬
evala and the cultural tradition behind it
reached a peak as sources of national cul¬
ture between the 1890s and the achieve¬
ment of independence in 1917. During this
period Finnish culture became interna¬
tionally known, both in Europe and Amer¬
ica, thanks largely to artist Akseli Gallen-
Kallela (1865-1933), composer Jean Sibel¬
ius (1865-1957) and poet Eino Leino (1878-
1926).
Gallen-Kallela, who had studied in
France, started out as a Realistic painter,
but after spending a long honeymoon in
Karelia in the traditional folk-song regions,
he developed a new style of depicting the
Kalevala, bringing decorative and sym¬
bolistic elements as well as monumental
ruggedness into a realistic representation
of Nature and the mythical heroes.
The Paris World Exhibition in 1900
brought Finnish culture and the Finns'
desire for independence to international
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Photo-portrait of the blind kantele-player
Stefan Jänis, taken in 1915 in the village
of Hanhiselkä, to the north of Lake
Ladoga. The kantele, or Finnish harp, was
traditionally used to accompany Finnish
lyric poetry.
consciousness. Gallen-Kallela painted four
Kalevala-inspired frescoes for the Finnish
pavilion whose monumental art and ide¬
ological message created a world sensation.
Finland had created her own culture and
was defending it, as if it were the luck-
bringing Sampo, against the attacks of
Mother Russia on Finnish autonomy. This
message was further confirmed by Sibelius'
symphonic poem Finlandia, which was also
performed at the World Exhibition.
Sibelius studied in central Europe, but
he had early grown attached to the mood
of the Kalevala. He visited the great rune
singer Larin Paraske to learn the way the
traditional folk poems were sung. He also
made several trips to Karelia. In 1892 he
conducted the first public performance of
his Kullervo symphony, which demon¬
strated that he had penetrated deep into
the mythical spirit of the Kalevala with his
original tone language. This impression is
reinforced by his Karelia and Lemmin-
käinen suites.
Eino Leino was of Karelian origin and
had been inspired by the Kalevala when
still a student. He developed its themes
and stylistic devices in his poetry in the
spirit of neo-Romanticism, Symbolism and
hero-worship. One of his earliest poems,
Tarina Suuresta Tammesta (A Tale of the
Great Oak), was a symbolic description
of the growth of the Finnish nation from
the shade of a foreign power into light.
The Kalevala blossomed out in his col¬
lection Helkavirsia, published in 1903. In
a sophisticated adaptation of the folk poem
metre he depicts the mythical characters
in his ballads as reflections of the ideo¬
logical trends and goals of his own time.
The poems convey the bitterness of threat
and revenge but also the spirit of love. The
second Helkavirsia series expands the
themes to general humanistic and even
cosmic visions of the liberty of the human
spirit and the limits of life.
Finland won her independence in 1917
in the turmoil of the Russian revolution.
The great dream had come true and thus
began a new phase of material and cultural
reconstruction. Typical of the works of the
first young artists of the independent
nation to be inspired by the themes and
moods of the Kalevala were the sculptures
of W. Aaltonen, the lithographic illustra¬
tions of the Kalevala by M. Visanti, U.
Klami's orchestral suite Kalevala and L.
Madejota's composition Väinämöisen
Soitto (Väinämöinen Playing). The cele¬
bration of the centenary of the Kalevala,
in 1935 , was the climax of the consolidation
of the position of the national epic.
In the aftermath of the Second World ,
War Finland lost part of the Kalevala
regions of Karelia, settled the evacuees in
Finland and began developing a modern
industrialized society on a democratic
basis. Artists began to experiment with the
use of modern stylistic devices in the treat¬
ment of Kalevala themes. U. Alanko
painted a cubistic Aino figure and J. Sie-
vänen an abstract figure of Lemminkäi-
nen's mother. T. Sakki won a Kalevala
sculpture competition with his wave line
sculpture depicting the rhythmic metre of
the Kalevala.
Reading room in the Folklore Archives,
Helsinki. This Institution which special¬
izes in the collection, study and publi¬
cation of the oral heritage, contains over
3 million manuscripts and some 10,000
hours of sound recordings. The Archives
form part of the Finnish Literature Soci¬
ety, an extremely active research centre
founded in 1831. The Finnish folklorlst
Urpo Vento was director of the Folklore
Archives from 1964 to 1972.
I
M
hmiw; */f//..
I
¿
©
Photo-portrait of the famous woman
singer Larin Paraske, better known as
Paraskeva Nikitin, taken in 1892. Some
32,000 lines from her rich repertory of
verse were recorded.
In poetry the impact of the Kalevala
was at first an unfocused striving to find
the riches of the Finnish language through
new forms; there was the juxtaposing, of
the themes of the Kalevala with those of
modern times as well as the use of the
metre of the Kalevala in modern poems.
L. Viita introduced it into the rugged
rhythm of Betonimylläri (Concrete Mixer)
and S. Selja into her sensitively feminine
mood poems. M. Rossi wrote a delicate
lullaby in Kalevala metre and A. Tur-
tiainen used it in his idealistic social poems
Leivän Sampo (The Bread-bringing
Sampo), dedicated to metalworkers.
The renaissance of the Kalevala in the
arts culminated in the works of P. Haaviko.
His collection Kaksikymmentä ja Yksi
(One and Twenty, 1974) uses both the
Kalevala metre and modern verse forms
in portraying a phantasy of some Finns
journeying through Russia to Byzantium
to steal the Empress's money-making
machine, the Sampo. After concentrating
on modern themes for a while he created
Rauta-aika (The Iron Age, 1982), which
is a profound and individual analysis of
the main events in the Kalevala. Kalevala
themes have also been used in plays and,
this year, the one hundred and fiftieth anni¬
versary of the Kalevala, the whole epic will
be portrayed on stage in Karelia.
All in all, the Kalevala and Kalevala-
style folk poetry have undergone a revival
in Finnish cultural life. They have inspired
the Finns to express their own tradition
in a modern language in nearly all fields
of culture.
HEIKKI KIRKINEN, of Finland, is professor
of history at the University of Joensuu. His
research field is the cultural history of Karelia
and Russia. He was Rector of the University
of Joensuu from 1971 to 1981, and in 1984-
1 985 he is an associate professor at the Centre
of Finno-Ugrian Studies of the University of
Paris.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
¿2 / v
zon be Li
Cpimoîifjf » rrtcw L toon
ft- - F .-¿y. - ,'s '
ÉÎ
©s
II
JO (a
-C Q)
O ç
-JÜJ
(TI r;
5«
Presentation to the Viceroy of New Spain
of the Chronicle of the Ceremonies, Rites,
People and Government of the Indians of
the Province of Mechuacán ("The Chron¬
icle of Michoacán"). In the preface, the
anonymous Spanish cleric who compiled
the Chronicle declared that it was pre¬
pared by the elders of the city of Mechu¬
acán "and by myself, in their name, not
as author but as interpreter". This illus¬
tration and the others accompanying this
article are facsimiles of a document dat¬
ing from 1541 which is preserved in the
Escorial Palace.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
In the sixteenth century, Michoacán, which in the Náhuatl
language means "the place offish", was the name of the
Indian town of Tzintzuntzan, the capital of the Porhepecha.
We should know nothing about this vanished civilization of
Central America were it notfor the Chronicle of Michoacán,
which can rightly be said to be its testament. The book was
written in Spanish around 1540; it describes the history of
the Porhepecha people, their beliefs and theirfaith, and gives
the names of their gods and heroes. It was written at the
request of the viceroy of New Spain, by an unknown scribe,
to whom the last Porhepecha nobles dictated it when their
civilization was nearing its end. It is a purely Indian work,
and its verbal and poetic power is such that it stands with
the greatest epics of world literature. The French writer
J.M.G. Le Clézio has published a French translation of the
Chronicle of Michoacán (La Relation de Michoacán, Gal¬
limardpublishers, Paris, 1984). In thefollowing text he evokes
this legendary tale of the one-time glory of the Indians.
The Chronicle
Testament of a people
of Michoacán
by J.M.G. Le Clézio
THE great stories of history tell us
about beginnings: the creation of
the earth, its first inhabitants, and
the coming of the gods and of the beings
they created. They recount these events
simply, as if the world extended no further
than a particular land that was bound up
with a particular people, and beyond its
frontiers there was a different kind of life;
a different time, too, unreal and fraught
with danger, as dreams are.
Examples of such stories are the first
tales of the Iranian people, the epic of the
giant Gilgameth, the founding of the peo¬
ple of Israel, and the Greek and Scan¬
dinavian legends. These sacred texts are
the foundations of history. They show how
the emergence of a nation, a language, a
religion or a government is related to the
most ancient of myths. They also tell us
of the primal creation of the world, for
they show us how places were given names.
By naming mountains, rivers, springs and
forests, men rescued them from non-being,
and found in them the rudiments of what
were later to be towns and temples. This
appropriation of the earth is the real source
of history, a magical invention of the
moment when men and the gods met.
The Chronicle of Michoacán is one of
the few texts the books of the Chilam
Balam of the Mayas of Yucután and the
Popol Vuh of the Quiche Mayas are
others which tell us about these begin¬
nings. Thanks to the Western system of
writing, it catches the verbal magic of the
fabled past of the people of Michoacán
when, after centuries of wandering amid
tribal warfare, there came the first signs
of the destiny of a nation which played
a vital part in the civilizations of Central
America.
Yet in this case the writing is of
secondary importance. It merely transmits
a message to posterity, and it gives the text
its strange, almost dreamlike quality that
of the testimony left by a people before
its death and of which we understand very
little. The anonymous sixteenth-century
writing, which is jerky and full of redun¬
dancies, and the naive illustrations a
combination of Indian symbols and the
tradition of illuminated manuscripts dear
to the monks of the Renaissance are the
ultimate attempt to halt the flight of time
and to preserve an evanescent glory. The
writing is the work of a copyist; it may
be a translation of texts written in the
Porhé language, compiled by an obscure
monk who reconstituted in Spanish the
message of the last priests of Michoacán,
in some cases dictated to them by Don
Pedro Cuinierengari, the son ofaPetamuti,
as the priest-historians of the court of the
Cazonci, or sovereign, were called, and
a witness of the last days of the reign of
the Porhepecha.
What disturbs and moves us is the sacred
character of this profoundly Indian book.
This legendary story, handed down from
generation to generation by petamuti
priests, is a solemn tale, with the same
oratorical beauty as that of the religious
and military colleges of Tenochtitlán (Mex¬
ico City), which Bernadino de Sahagún
(1500-1590) used when writing the "Gen¬
eral History of the Things of New Spain".
But it also reminds us of the epics that
survive today among peoples that have no
written language the Tule of San Bias,
the Inuit of Greenland , the Dogon of equa¬
torial Africa, and the Tiwi of Oceania.
The Cazonci, or sovereign of the Por-
hepechas, seated on his throne in pres¬
ence of the Url, the representatives of the
main guilds of the kingdom (artists, fish¬
ermen, hunters, etc.).
One of the most powerful and most
orderly kingdoms in Indian America, that
of the Porhepecha, was whole-heartedly
dedicated to the supernatural forces that
brought it into being, and was unable to
survive the fall of its gods. Only the rep¬
resentatives of Curicaueri, the god of fire,
and Xaratanga, the moon goddess, had any
power in this hierarchical religious society.
But the faith that was the strength of men
in the early days of the Conquest, when
the two Chichimec brothers Uapeani and
Pauacum, the founding heroes, wandered
with their warriors in search of a promised
land and a dwelling for their gods, the faith
that inspired Tariacuri, the founder of the
empire, and his nephews when, village by
village, they conquered the domain of Cur¬
icaueri, their master this same faith now
rendered the Porhepecha powerless in
their superstitious fear of omens, and con¬
demned them to annihilation.
Stricken in its vitals, with its temples
in ruins, its gods overthrown and, worst
of all, the one incarnation of their god
Curicaueri, the Cazonci Tangaxoan Tzintz-
icha, fallen and enslaved by the Con¬
quistador Ñuño de Guzman, the Porhe¬
pecha Kingdom was unable to put up a
fight. The men of this warlike people were
struck motionless by a holy dread, and
fighting was out of the question. "Where
are they from, these newcomers, if not
from heaven?" said the Cazonci to his
nobles. "People say that these stags
(horses) that they bring with them come
from the place where the sky meets the
sea. Who can they be?"
The Indians sent these new gods offer¬
ings by way of greeting. The Cazonci sent
skins with colours from the four corners
of the world, as he would have done to
their own gods. And he ordered gold to
be placed in the middle of the court for
the chief god, Hernán Cortés.
But the Indians were soon to realize
that these "gods from heaven", the ter¬
rifying messengers from the other world,
had not come to bring the answer to their
prayers and receive their offerings; they
had come to fulfil the doom-laden sayings
of the oracles.
The news of the destruction of the
opposing empire of Tenochtitlán brought
no solace to the Cazonci; it perturbed him
even more. "Who are you?"he asked Mon¬
tano, the first Spaniard to set foot on his ^
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The priests who offer up incense in the
temples, the curitlechas, gathered round
the High Priest, or Petamuti, who bears
the insignia of his ranka lance and a
gourd set with turquoise. "And they
declared that they bore the whole nation
on their shoulders."
territory. "Where are you from? What are
you seeking? For we have never heard tell
of men such as you, nor seen such men.
Why have you come from such distant
lands? Is there neither food nor drink in
your native land, that you have come to
make the acquaintance of peoples
unknown to you? And what had the Mex¬
icans done to you, that you annihilated
them when you were in their city?"
The apprehensive questions of the Por¬
hepecha people were soon to be answered.
Motionless and powerless, the men stared
at these new gods. Already the old gods
Xaratanga, Curicaueri, the mother Cuer-
auaperi, Hurendequauecara, the guardians
of the grottoes and the mountains, the
spirits of the springs and the lakes, the gods
of the four corners of the earth and of
hell had all returned to nothingness The
newcomers wanted gold, the "excrement
of the sun", the symbol of divine power.
Their lust for gold was not sated by the
spoils of war handed over to them by the
Cazonci; they wanted more and more, so
they sacked the temples and profaned the
tombs of the most illustrious kings.
The impregnable frontier city, Taxi-
maroa, had already been reduced to ashes
by the new victors. Disease influenza,
smallpox and measles decimated the
inhabitants and wiped out villages. Fore¬
seeing the terrible fate that awaited him,
in the solitude of the end of the world that
the gods had deserted, the last king of the
Porhepecha could not hold his peace.
"They are coming," he cried. "Must we
therefore die?"
Already Timas, the captain of war of
the Cazonci, knew that death was the only
way. "My lord, order copper to be
brought, and we shall put it on our shoul¬
ders and drown ourselves in the lake; so
we shall reach our end more quickly, and
join those who have already died."
With the fall of the gods the empire
of the Porhepecha came to an end. The
newcomers first destroyed the enemies
they feared most, just as they had done
at Tenochtitlán: the statues were cast down
from the temples and lay crumbled into
dust, before the eyes of the Indians. "Why
are the gods not moved to wrath? Why
do they not curse these men?" But the gods
remained silent. Defeated without even
offering any resistance, they had left their
dwelling places and their temples and had
gone back to the mysterious realms from
which they had come, under the earth in
volcanoes, at the bottom of lakes or in the
depths of the forest, in the warm lands
where perhaps they were born.
With the fall of the gods of the Por¬
hepecha another kind of conquest of
Michoacán began, a conquest in which the
goal was not the glory and power of the
ancient Chichimec gods, but possession of
the land, power over men, and gold.
Everything vanished when these con¬
querors approached, everything grew
silent, as the soothsayers had prophesied.
On the banks of a river, at the ford of
Nuestra Señora de la Purificación (prob¬
ably near the town of Purnandiro, on the
frontier of what is now the Mexican State
of Guanajato) in the year 1530, the last
Arrival of the first Spaniards in Michoa¬
cán. In his residence at Tzintzuntzán, on
the shores ofLake Pátzcuaro, the Cazonci
Tangaxoan orders gifts of food, copper
axes, jars of wine and hides of every col¬
our to be taken to the strangers who were
thought to be gods, for "from whence
could they have come, if not from the
heavens?" At his feet can be seen the
round plaques ofgold and the half-moon-
shaped sheets of silver in their greed for
which the conquistadores would pillage
the kingdom.
Cazonci was tortured and slain by the con¬
quistador Ñuño de Guzmán , after a parody
of a trial. So ended the glorious line of
the Uacusecha, the Eagles, who had built
up the empire, and also the reign of the
god Curicaueri, whose last incarnation on
earth the Cazonci had been. Another form
of speech, another conquest were about
to begin, covering over the silence of the
Indians.
All that is left today as a legacy, thanks
to the anonymous Chronicle, is the mem¬
ory of that greatness, the legend, both
touching and true, of a past era, when
poetry and history were one, and when
the kingdom of men was like the dwelling
place of the gods.
JEAN MARIE G. LE CLEZIO fe an essayist
and novelist of Franco-Mauritian origin. In addi¬
tion to his translation from Spanish into French
of the Relación de Michoacán (The Chronicle
of Michoacán, 1984), his many published works
include French translations ofMayan texts, such
as The Prophecies of Chilam Balam (1976), and
novels such as Le Chercheur d'Or (The Gold-
Seeker, 1985). Since 1 973 he has made several
trips to Mexico and is a part-time research
worker at the College of Michoacán.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Lay of Igor's Campaign
by Igor Shkliarevsky
THE barbarian hordes flooded across
the steppes, breaking like waves
against the wooden walls of the cit¬
ies of ancient Russia.
From his post atop the ramparts the
sentinel raised the alarm: "The Khazars!"
His son in turn cried out: "The Pech-
enegs!"
His grandson echoed: "The Polovtsy!"
And again and again their descendants
would take up the cry. Such was the nature
of things...
With no roof but the sky, no shelter
but the light of day, southern Russia was
a tempting, easy prey. Unwelcome guests
One of a series of engravings by the
Soviet artist Vladimir Favorsky (1886-
1964), Lenin Prize winner in 1962, illus¬
trating a re-edition of The Lay of Igor's
Campaign issued in 1954. It depicts a
scene towards the end of the poem when
Prince Igor's wife Yaroslavna begs the
powers of heaven to bring Igor back to
Russian soil:
Yaroslavna weeps in the early morn
On the walls of Putivl wailing:
"Wind, O wind!
Why blow, my lord, such a stormy
blast?
Why do you bring on your wings so
light
Pagan arrows down on my lover's
host?
Were you not sated with blowing
High up under the clouds,
And with rocking ships upon the blue
sea?
Why have you scattered my joy, O my
Over the feather grass?" lord'
hammered at the gates of Pereyaslav, of
Chernigov, of Kiev with their heavy sling-
stones. Burning arrows flew. Walls
crumbled. A grassy shroud covered and
recovered the charred ruins.
Nor was the suffering any the less when
inflicted by kinsmen, when the people of
Novgorod marched against Kiev, or the
people of Kiev took up arms against Cher¬
nigov.
For brother spoke to brother
Saying,
"This is mine,
And that, too, is mine!"
And the princes began
To call small things great,
To forge feuds
Among themselves...
to the despair of chroniclers over the cen¬
turies...
Whose was the hand that recorded The
Lay of Igor's Campaign? Did he live to
be an old man? What happened to him
after he had written The Layl Nobody
knows, but he was certainly a man of rare
courage, proclaiming out loud what others
dared but think. For a prince has his armies
and his ramparts, but a poet is without
defence...
He foretold the misfortunes that would
strike the land of Russia over many cen¬
turies. With a prophetic ear to the ground
he heard the muffled, drumming hoofbeats
of the Mongol horsemen, whose thirst for
conquest could have dried up whole rivers.
He could not know that far across the
steppes Genghis Khan was forging his
empire, but he had the political intuition
of a great poet.
A heavy sense of brooding anguish per¬
meates The Lay of Igor's Campaign. The
Russian town of Glebov has been sacked,
its defenders hacked to pieces. As though
a fiery brand from Glebov in flames had
set light to his raiment, Igor Svyatoslavich,
Prince of Novgorod, burns with shame.
The state of the roads at winter's end has
prevented him from joining the other Rus¬
sian princes who have taken up arms
against the Polovtsy.
Igor is racked with fear that the princes
will doubt the sincerity of his will to join
the expedition. He is tortured by his ambi¬
tion and his desire to prove his valour and
to make amends for failing to answer the
call of the motherland. Hastily he prepares
to venture forth alone on the Polovtsian
steppe.
At dawn on the day of battle the enemy
seemed to Igor's men like a great forest
advancing upon them. The enemy leader
Khan Konchak had mustered all his troops.
Another chronicler recounts that the
princes could still have forced their way
through the enemy and galloped to safety,
but they would not desert their foot-
soldiers and common men-at-arms. Igor
ordered the horsemen to dismount and
fight on foot.
This defeat of a prince of Novgorod,
which was to be of little consequence in
the history of Russia, is transformed by
the poetic genius of the author into a great
moral victory. A great poetic epic is born.
Plains, forests, steppes, the whole Rus¬
sian landscape becomes a living presence
in The Lay of Igor's Campaign. Stretching
out to the horizon can be seen the rapids
of the Dnieper, the sandbanks of the Don, ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
il fcá m my
il
t "* Ä
^H j^H ^^k ^|
Left, fwo scenes from a performance at
Moscow's Bolshoi Theatre of Prince Igor,
Borodin's famous opera inspired by the
great epic of ancient Russian literature
Slovo o Polku Igoreve (The Lay of Igor's
Campaign). Written during the 12th cen¬
tury and rediscovered six centuries later,
The Lay recounts an incident that was of
only minor importance in Russian his¬
tory Svyatoslavich's ill-fated expe¬
dition against the Polovtsy in 1185.
Despite doubts that have been expressed
by some as to its authenticity as a medi¬
eval document, this epic poem, some
3,000 words in length, is universally rec¬
ognized as a masterpiece of world lit¬
erature. For the Soviet expert on Slav cul¬
ture Andrei Nicolayevich Robinson, the
originality of The Lay lies in its rich sym¬
bolism and its powerful nationalist under¬
current. He writes: "The Lay of Igor's
Campaign occupies the middle ground,
in the geographical, historical and poetic
senses alike, between the epics of West
and East, and also between two periods,
the archaic (pagan) and the feudal (...) The
poetic originality of The Lay derives in
part from its author's use of ancient Rus¬
sian folk poetry (...) The basic symbols
of the heroic poetry of the Middle Ages
can in many instances be traced back to
a distant myth-making epoch character¬
ized by an animistic attitude to nature and
its interaction with human beings (...)
Through the force of his poetry the author
of The Lay tried to take a stand against
the feudal division of Russia (...) The
inspired idealization of reality in the lyrical
epic, combined with an uncharacteristic
criticism of that reality, are recognizable
in a large perspective as that civic sense
which is an important feature of Russian
literature."
grass-covered kurgans (burial
mounds), the wooden walls of Novgorod,
Polotsk and Kiev the entire expanse of
twelfth-century Russia. Above this
expanse, like a man with winged sandals,
his face reddened by wind, soars the author
of The Lay.
The original manuscript of The Lay,
discovered by Count Alexei Musin-Push-
kin (1744-1817), perished in the burning
of Moscow in 1812. The words of The Lay
writhed in the flames like living things. A
little of the soul of Russia perished with
them. All that remained was the copy made
by Musin-Pushkin for Catherine II, as well
as the poignant saying: "Manuscripts never
burn completely".
Doubt has been cast on the authenticity
of the text, yet the more one reads The
Lay the more evident it becomes that even
a poet of the stature of Pushkin could not
have composed it. How could anyone have
imitated the language and rhythms of the
twelfth century or captured with such
immediacy the excitement of the hap¬
penings of the period.
If The Lay was really written early in
the'eighteenth century, how are we to
explain the author's hostility to the Polov¬
tsy, six hundred years later? Only a con¬
temporary who had witnessed their incur¬
sions and who had known the smell of fire
and blood in the air could be capable of
such intensity of feeling. The Polovtsy have
long disappeared, fused in the great melt¬
ing-pot of peoples. Even during the twelfth
century, in times of truce and peace, blood
links had been forged between the Russian
princes and the Polovtsian khans. As The
Lay itself tells us, marriages "between
steppe and forest" were not unusual.
Behind the anonymous author of The
Lay an entire people stands revealed. The
poet has achieved a great exploit. Tau
tening his genius like a bow, he let fly
across the centuries the courage-tipped
arrows of his thoughts. In this poem, now
eight centuries old, all is movement, all
is life the fighting men, the clouds above,
the birds, the wind, the grass and the
words. The Lay is an integral part of our
language. It is in the air we breathe and
in the blood that flows in our veins. It
teaches us to love our country, but also
to maintain a wide perspective, to be for¬
giving and to respect other peoples.
IGOR IVANOVICH SHKLIAREVSKY, of the
Soviet Union, is the author of fifteen volumes
of poetry and a book of short stories entitled
The Shadow of a Bird. He has also translated
into modern Russian such important classics
as The Lay of Igor's Campaign and The Saga
of the Battle of Mamaev.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Shaka
by Mazisi Kunene
IN the African world the family is an
all-inclusive social phenomenon
involving a large number of individuals
who may be linked by a common ancestry.
The ideals that are celebrated within such
a large family unit are those that emphasize
continuity, participatory activities and ful¬
filment through wider circles of relations.
The implication of these factors on the
nature of the literary idiom and form can¬
not be over-emphasized. They mean that
literature, as a social product, must be
celebratory and public, and above all focus
on group participation and performance.
Literature, if it is to be meaningful in such
a society, must utilize the oral language
and group action (drama, song, mime,
dance) to heighten its meaning.
Looking at Zulu literature in particular,
it is important also to emphasize that the
heroic poem or epic is integrally linked to
events as they happen in society. Its focus
is on the extent to which such events exem¬
plify the social ethic. The very process of
selecting what to celebrate is a serious one
which engages the poet's integrity and
intellectual perception. The poet in this
sense is viewed as a thinker, as the high
priest whose status is inviolable.
His poetic statement must incorporate
the highest social truths. He not only
reports events, but, after careful selection,
uses them to affirm the ideals of the society.
There is nothing deeply personal in his
praise for the hero. His statements of
approval or disapproval celebrate the per¬
manence of the social order. He is a per¬
former whose utterances must always be
directed at a public audience, a philoso¬
pher who must link the particular with the
universal, and a historian whose know¬
ledge of detail must be attested by a highly
attentive and critical audience.
What political factors led to the major
heroic period that brought about the
flowering of the Zulu heroic epic?
From about the middle of the seven¬
teenth century, the African peoples in
southern Africa went through a period of
extensive land crisis. This was due to pop¬
ulation growth which led to crowding in
that part of the continent, to the mounting
pressure arising from colonial wars and
slave raids by the Portuguese and the
Boers, and to the fact that the economic
life of the African people centred on ani¬
mal husbandry and agriculture. The impact
the Great
The legendary exploits of Shaka (1786-
1828), founder of the Zulu empire, gave
rise to a number ofepicpoems which rank
among the finest in the literature ofsouth¬
ern Africa and are still a source of inspi¬
ration to many African writers. In his dra¬
matic poem Shaka, which he dedicated
to "the Bantu martyrs of South Africa",
the philosopher-poet and former Presi¬
dent of Senegal, Leopold Sedar Senghor,
put these words into the mouth of the
famed warrior-chief:
"It is not hate to love one's people.
I say there is no peace under arms, v
no peace under oppression,
No brotherhood without equality. I
wanted all men to be brothers."
Above, Shaka portrayed by the Sene¬
galese artist Alpha Diallo.
of these factors was to destabilize the whole
region. It was a period during which many
national States emerged, each boasting an
heroic leadership by a particular individual
or family. One of these was the Zulu State.
At first it was a small State, often forced
to pay tribute to more powerful States such
as the Ndwandwe. At other times it was
part of a loose confederacy. Its decisive
period came with the emergence of Shaka
as its political leader. Through outstanding
military genius and astute political
leadership, he subdued and integrated
many once-powerful States within just over
a decade, from 1815 to 1828.
Shaka not only initiated unique styles
and methods of warfare, he also evolved
a type of leadership that sought to reinstate
the social law, which had been violated
by selfish leadership. This social law was,
according to Zulu thought, embodied in
the Sacred Codes of the Ancestors.
Shaka's leadership was patterned on the
idea of service in which the leader himself
took equal risks with the rest of the pop¬
ulation. One of the greatest doctrines that
characterized the Zulu State became that
of selflessness in rendering service to the
community. This was coupled with the
notion of merit as a criterion for leadership
at all levels.
An analysis of the impact and the influ¬
ence of the Shakan epic is inevitably an
analysis of the transformation of Zulu soci¬
ety and its affirmation of the Law of Self¬
lessness. While in other societies this may
be viewed in moral terms, in Zulu society,
influenced by Shaka's ideas, it became a
law. Punishment for disobedience of this
law ranged from ostracism by the com¬
munity to, in extreme cases, death.
It is natural that the Shakan heroic epic
should have celebrated these virtues. The
celebration was woven around a specific
series of events; it ceased to be a didactic
and moralistic statement. The poetic style
underwent a dramatic change to convey
a sense of urgency. A new technique
evolved that was deeply concerned with
projecting the social message. The very
selection of metaphors and symbols is tes¬
timony of a society concerned with high
achievements and high goals. Courage and
initiative were relevant not only to wartime
situations but to all social occasions.
Thus the first part of the Shakan heroic
epic is a cosmic address to all forces, real
and imaginary. The hero is depicted as
breaking through all obstacles. He is pos¬
sessed with the spirit of his forefathers,
symbolized in Ndaba. He is the will of the
Ancestral powers. He is ferocious in battle;
he has subdued nation after nation. He
has attained his fame, the poet says,
through his wisdom and his skill on the
battlefield.
Wild one! Restless power, son of Ndaba
You who were the whirlwind of the Mbe-
lebele brigade
Who raged among the vast villages ofmen
Until morning they tumbled down one
after another.
You whosefame spread effortlessly, great
son of Menzi!
Shaka the Invincible, who is not subdued
like water
Great battleaxe that flashed over others
by its sharpness
Shaka! I fear to call you by name
Because you were the ruler
Who counted multiple feats of battle
Whistler who responded like a lion
You prepared for battle in the thick of
the forest
You were the madman who was the spec¬
tacle in the eyes of men! ^
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Descendants of the Nguni people, the
Zulus were given their name by their war¬
rior-king Shaka. In a famous book on
Shaka, the well-known author Thomas
Mofólo (1877-1948), of Lesotho, who
wrote in the Sotho language (belonging
to the Bantu linguistic group), recounts
thata soothsayer suggested to Shaka that
he should rename his clan. Looking up
to the stormy sky above him, Shaka cried
out " Zulu! Amazulu!" (The sky! The clan
of the sky!). Then he spoke to his men,
saying: "Today you have vanquished all
your enemies and this is why I have cho¬
sen for you a worthy name. " Left, a kraal,
or village, similar to those in which Shaka
and his contemporaries would have lived.
A kraal usually houses a familygroup and
consists of a number of huts arranged
in a circle around an enclosure for cattle.
In the elaborate poetic restatement and
dramatization of Shaka's life the numerous
episodes are carefully selected for their
national and public significance. They
serve not only as points of historical ref¬
erence but also as affirmations of com¬
mitment to public service. The leader has
acquired the right to leadership, not by
virtue of his birth, but through communally
approved social actions.
Throughout the epic there is no ref¬
erence to Shaka's personal appearance.
Instead, events assume a primary symbolic
significance; their meaning, scope and vari¬
ety are built up in a series of dramatic
statements. Whereas pre-Shakan poetry
had concentrated on the person of the
leader, the poetry of the Shakan period
ignores the leader and concentrates on the
event. Persons are only mentioned in order
to stress socially significant events.
It is unfortunate in a sense that
evaluation of this great heroic epic is today
based purely on recorded material. The
heroic epic of the Shakan era was never
meant to be read but to be verbalized,
acted, dramatized and heightened in
meaning through public performance. The
highly skilled use of ideophonic sounds,
for instance, is lost on the silent page. What
we read therefore is only a skeletal part
of the epic. Besides, the epic must be per¬
formed before an active and appreciative
audience; its "private" form cannot fully
convey its public meanings.
It should not be assumed that the Shakan
heroic epic is a piece of archaic literature.
Ever since its inception it has exercised
enormous influence on Zulu literature.
Virtually every African child in South
Africa is taught to recite one or more
excerpts from it, and by virtue of its highly
sophisticated style, it has influenced the
compactness of the Zulu poetic idiom and
guaranteed that performance of the heroic
poem shall not die. Many public gatherings
in modern South Africa feature perform¬
ances by poets who model their public mes
sages on the heroic epic of the Shakan
period.
Since the advent of Christianity, some
communities have taken to public dram¬
atizations of the achievements of Jesus
Christ, which are invariably modelled on
A military genius of the highest order,
Shaka created the powerful fighting
machine that would later offer stern
resistance to colonial occupation. He
divided the army into regiments based on
age groups and distinguished by special
markings on their shields and various
combinations of headdress and orna¬
mentation. His soldiers went barefoot,
"because sandals prevented them from
marching fast" (Mofólo); they were
equipped with large shields and armed
with shortstabbing assegais which meant
that they had to fight at close quarters.
the Shakan epic. This is not to say that
before the Shakan epic there was no pow¬
erful Zulu heroic poetry; there was. But
never had there been a heroic epic as elab¬
orate, as powerful, as idiomatically com¬
plex or as intrinsically geared to the public
event. The Shakan epic has permeated all
subsequent poetry to the present day. Its
impact has even been felt in poetry com¬
posed for children. All Zulu literature
since that time has specifically focussed on
the event rather than the individual.
Many Zulu poets whose works today are
in written form have taken the great heroic
verses of the Shakan period as their model.
The influence of these verses on the work
of Vilakazi, the outstanding modern Zulu
poet, is particularly evident in his suc¬
cessful volume Amal'ezulu. My own epic,
Emperor Shaka the Great, was deeply influ¬
enced by the idiom and style of the Shakan
epic. Indeed, I consider Magolwane and
Mshongweni, the great Zulu poets of the
Shakan era, as my true masters. The com¬
bination of the Shakan heroic idiom with
the discipline of converting oral literature
into written form has created a new and
original challenge to a type of poetry that
had become precise and technically cor¬
rect, but dead.
-X^* &$
MAZISI KUNENE, of South Africa, is a pro¬
fessor in the Department of Linguistics at the
University of California Los Angeles (UCLA)
where he teaches African literature and African
languages. He has written several volumes of
poetry in his mother tongue, Zulu, many of which
remain unpublished owing to the situation in
his country. His published works include the epic
poem Emperor Shaka the Great (1979) and two
anthologies, Zulu Poems and Ancestors and
the Sacred Mountain (1980). He was for many
years an African National Congress repre¬
sentative in Europe and the Americas.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
/
The glory of the spoken
by Salah Stétié
ARABIC is a verbal reality, and some¬
thing more an act. Before they were
embroidered in golden letters on the
walls of the Ka'ba, then the temple of three
Meccan divinities, the seven orten? great
odes of pre-lslamic Arabia, the celebrated
Muallaqat (literally "suspended", in allusion
to the way in which they were disposed on
the walls of the sacred precinct) had long
been an intense oral experience, the glory
of the poetic discourse whereby the cultural
identity of each tribe was redefined, revi¬
talized by the word of the poet and poised
to challenge, not without pride and panache,
other tribal identities assembled around their
own messages.
A major verbal feat, indeed, was the Qas-
idah, the great inspired poem, whose theme
was nevertheless rigorously pre-established,
and which was the banner of the group and
the impressive expression of its existential
challenge. It was for each spokesman, and
the tribal bard was in a sense the admirable
spokesman of his community, to bring to a
pitch of excellence a subject prescribed by
a rhetorical game whose roots ran deep.
For memorative and commemorative
populations, the Qasidah was an act of
remembrance.
Every year in jâhilite ("pagan" or "igno¬
rant") Arabia before the coming of Islam, from
the four corners of the peninsula and beyond
the shadeless horizons people came to Suk-
Ukaz, the market or fair of Ukaz, where they
stayed, exchanging on the public square,
through the mediation of poets who held
tumultuous, ecstatic audiences spellbound,
verses impregnated with frenzy and wisdom,
"/ firmly believe that the first, the most
ancient language was born in resistance
to the desert (in resistance to all deserts,
however they may be defined), and that
it was born as a primitive enterprise for
safeguarding and salvation.
desire and serenity, triumph and invective,
with despair and the greenness of hope, with
a lover's attachment to a mare or she-camel,
or with the tearful refusal to accept the loss
of a woman or girl who was the acme of
presence before being transformed into utter
nothingness. All this, the glory of the spoken,
the fabulous opera of the word, was enacted
against the splendid and virtually unadorned
backcloth of the desert: sand and wind, solar
oven, arena for vast, formless protagonists.
The utterance of man is here the only form;
the word empowers him to confront the
elemental.
I firmly believe that the first, most ancient
language was born in resistance to the desert
(in resistance to all deserts, however they
may be defined), and that it was born as a
primitive enterprise for safeguarding and sal¬
vation. The working of primordial magic, a
talisman, a form of sacrament. This and other
reasons attest to the antiquity of Arabic,
which is one of our mother languages and
which, before Massignon'11 but largely due
(1) Louis Massignon (1883-1962), French Orientalist,
author of major works on Islamic mysticism.
to him, is better known as an immemorial
matrix. The immemorial is also memorial.
The Arabs, inventors of genealogical chains,
recited. The others, the descendants of Abra¬
ham, the Jews and the Christians with whom
they lived in familiar proximity were, solely
through their use of the written text, suffi¬
ciently exceptional to be defined by this
unique and enigmatic characteristic as "Peo¬
ple of the Book". One day the Arabs too
would fall into the same category when they
received, through the Muhammadan reve¬
lation, the supremely sacred deposition of
the Book.
But so deep was the groove traced in them
by archetypal pure orality, that it was by ear
that the illiterate Muhammad apprehended
the Book dictated by the Angel Gabriel and
entrusted to him, the Prophet, to be com¬
municated to men. This Book he would him¬
self transmit by recitation, sequence after
sequence, verse after verse, surah after
surah, with those astonishing silences
between one verse and the next, which seem
intended to highlight the miraculous way in
which the word erupts in the circus of sound;
yes, verse after verse, silence after silence,
surah after surah, the Prophet verbally trans¬
mitted the spoken message to those who,
in their turn, would transmit it until scribes
and writers, those who knew and practiced
the art of writing as well as the science of
sacred conservation, commit the word of God
to writing.
And so the Qur'an would retain for eternity
the sign that it is deeply rooted in orality:
Qur'an, that is, "reading". The Qur'an cer¬
tainly gave to writing, in the Arabo-lslamic
world, its patent of nobility. It is the meta-
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Immensely popular throughout the Arab
world, the Hilali Saga Is an epic poem
which recounts the historic migration of
the Banu Hilal, a nomadic Arab people
whose travels took them from the Arab
Peninsula to Egypt and the Maghreb. The
epic is thought to have been composed
around the 11th century, but certainly not
later than the 14th century since the Arab
historian and traveller Ibn Khaldun (1332-
1402) quotes a number of verse passages
from it in his writings. A variety of written
versions of the Hilali Saga are current
throughout the Arab world, but oral ver¬
sions transmitted by narrator poets or
singers have all but vanished. French
researcher Lucienne Saada of the CNRS
(Centre National de la Recherche Scien¬
tifique), Paris, has recently published a
French version of the Saga as she heard
it from the lips of Mohammed Hisni, a
story-teller from Sfax, Tunisia. This ver¬
sion consists of some 3,700 lines of verse
interspersed with long sequences of nar¬
rative prose. Above, this painting on glass
by an anonymous 19th-century artist
depicts Jazia, one of the great heroines
of the epic.
physical and physical articulation which
takes the entire cultural process from one
phase to another with its visible dynamism
and invisible potential. Beginning with the
Qur'an the Mother of which, the absolute
matrix, pre-exists in all creation and in every
formulation or emanation of existence, eter¬
nally established spirit and letter, in the very
eternity of God the text acquires density,
and orality, without ceasing to be creative
fervour and multiplicatory fermentation, Is
entrapped, as it is refined, in the symbolic
snares of the page, line after line. After the
Greek library, the Arab library, heir of all
those which preceded it but pregnant and
fertile in its own right, would become one
of the richest and, when ransacked, would
give birth to many another library according
to the law whereby a constellation is formed.
Why should we deny Borges'2», to cite only
him, the right' to be the descendant of Mai-
monides and Averroes, since he considers
himself to be such? He has also often rec¬
ognized his debt as a story-teller to the Thou¬
sand and One Nights.
Narrative too is above all a verbal fact. The
story and the novel came much later, ben¬
efitting from the qualitative and quantitative
contribution of printing, as they established
themselves as distinct forms. In Arabic nar¬
rative the story comes from a mingling of
remote times and places. The Arab world
established itself on the dust of the oldest
empires in which Sumer and Babylon min¬
gled, as well as that which came one day
from Athens and Alexandria, and that which
came from Central Asia and China, and that
which came from India and Persia, and
stories and legends which circulated on the
shores of the Mediterranean before Islam.
In addition to the ferment, on the Arabian
peninsula itself, of men and jinns, spirits and
ghouls and all kinds of strange fancies and
often cruel imaginations mingled in prodi¬
gious disorder in the vast empty phantas¬
magoria of the desert. The oral tradition of
the Arab tale Is at the confluence of all these
influences and all these interferences.
And so it is not unduly surprising to find,
for example, in the Kalila and Dimna of Ibn
al-Muqaffa' (c.720-c.756), beside the old
Indian backcloth of animal stories by Bay-
daba (the Bidpai of the Europeans) such and
(2) Jorge Luis Borges, Argentine writer born in 1899;
author of poems, short stories, novels and essays.
"Yes, verse after verse, silence after
silence, surah after surah, the Prophet
verbally transmitted the spoken message
to those who, in their turn, would transmit
it until (...) those who knew and practiced
the art of writing as well as the science
of sacred conservation could commit the
word of God to writing. And so the Qur'an
would retain for eternity the sign that it
is deeply rooted in orality: Qur'an, that
is, 'reading'. The Qur'an certainly gave to
writing, in the Arabo-lslamlc world, Its
patent of nobility." Above, detail of the
Ka'ba, the most holy shrine of Mecca. The
Ka'ba is covered with a Kiswah, or ves¬
ture, made of black cloth with gold let¬
tering, which is renewed every year.
such an evocation from Aesop or some other
fabulist, possibly Chinese, whose name has
disappeared, to the advantage of a "story"
whose meaning still enriches us. Nor is it
surprising that in the Thousand and One
Nights, beneath the characteristics of Sind-
bad the Sailor and in many of his adventures
it is possible to make out an episode from
the Odyssey, the ingenuity and mischievous
wisdom of Ulysses. Even more enigmatically
and more profoundly in the vortex of time,
it is perhaps possible to recognize In stories
which are set in rediscovered and lost places,
forbidden thresholds, magic uncrossable
frontiers, living and reviving springs, mi¬
raculous trees, offensive or defensive génies,
yes, in these stories which trace the extra¬
ordinary history of the Babylonian quest of
Gilgamesh In search of his friend En-Kidu,
perhaps it is possible to recognize some fun¬
damental features of the collective Semitic
imagination of which we are all, thousands
of years later, to a greater or lesser degree
the heirs.
Even today the theme of the initiatory jour¬
ney is a recurrent theme of the contemporary
Arabic novel. Thus, between the oldest store
of legend which gave rise to the myths of
an antiquity which disgorged its substance
in other myths through the mediation of sto¬
ries transmitted orally from generation to gen¬
eration and the inspiration of some of the
most significant writing today, there is a link
which nothing has snapped, neither the mod¬
ification of structures of thought nor the evo¬
lution of men in history. It must be admitted
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
that the Orient remains a place of unique
magnetism for all those for whom man is,
at some point in himself, wounded by the
invisible. Man, says the Orient, isalso
invisible. Whence it follows naturally that the
apparent history of men and of their civili¬
zations is only an equivocal and illusory
advance from an absolute anchoring point,
a central well in which the eternal is mani¬
fested, if it reaches the surface, and if one
cares to slake one's thirst in it. In many sto¬
ries, legends and episodes of Oriental mys-
tagogy there is a well. A well or a waterhole.
It is often there that the ghouls, the voracious
ogresses of the old Arab tales, wait for their
prey the wretched man to whom, like the
sphinx over whom Oedipus triumphed, they
ask the absurd question which will cause him
to die.
I shall only cite as examples two sacred
wells: it was into a well that Joseph was cast
by his brothers, and it was at the well of
Zemen, miraculously opened for the thirst
of the child Ismael, that the pilgrims of
Mecca slaked their thirst at the end of their
pilgrimage.
But let us return to poetry. Borges affirms
that if, according to Greek tradition, Homer
was blind, this was a way of stressing the
priority of the lyrical, that is the musical and
the verbal, over the visual. There is in the
purely verbal a power of concentration that
limits the imaginative content inevitably con¬
fined within the very frontiers of the image.
The system of images of classical Arabic
poetry seems to me, even when unexpected,
unusual and precious, strangely con¬
stricted firstly by a deliberate codification
of themes, signs and symbols, then by a
quasi musical décantation of an ontological
experience in which everything is perceived
In reference not only to the constellations of
the language according to a mode which is
already almost Mallarmean, but also, some¬
what mysteriously, by allusion to some orig¬
inal shaking of the sensibility, on a cosmic
scale, of which the poet's own sensibility, put
into words, would only be an epipheno-
menon.
Thus the archetypal and the highly singular
combine at the level of the collective uncon¬
scious in classical Arabic poetry. This does
not fail to accentuate the abstracting effect
of this poetry, through a corporality. which
is often insistent through the evocation of the
most natural and, if required, of the most
denuded and raw. The projection of the word
in a declamatory orality strongly marked by
the rhythms of short and long syllables, not
so much compensates for this as, on the
contrary, and paradoxically, broadens it con¬
centrically. The Arabic chant is incantation;
it is that above all, like magic. One could even
go so far as to say that the Qasidah is a
blueprint for a universe. It is centration, it is
the equivalence of a universe grouped
around its leading impulses, love and nos¬
talgia, destruction and glory, desire and its
exaltation in phantasm, the exaltation of the
festival as an expression of community,
space and the known yardstick of space: this
highly strung horse, that she-camel as young
and beautiful as a beautiful young girl, which
are for the poet one of the possible names
for his identification with his most intimate
solitude, horse, mare or she-camel being for
him a confidence granted to himself, destiny
of his becoming, diverted magnification of
a more secret identity. I add that if space
is everywhere present in the Qasidah, time,
yJ ^fc_- ~^ ** *-"V*" if i
©
The book Kalila and Dimna, a celebrated
collection of moralistic animal stories, is
a translation by Abd Allah Ibn al Muqaffa
(7th century AD/2nd century of the Hejira)
of the Indian Fables of Bidpai. Above,
illustration from a 15th-centuryArab man¬
uscript of an episode from Kalila and
Dimna in which the lion falls into the trap
prepared for him by the hare.
that eternal point, without being really absent,
only presents itself in the light of a time-
lessness without figurative form: it is, essen¬
tially, that which was, far more than that which
is or that which will be; it is a fixed reference.
Thus the orality of the Qasidah is, invisibly,
one of the arches of its ontological structure
and, confronted with the space crystallized
in the imaginary world of the word, it is the
temporal dimension of this word. Hardly a
simple orality, then. Orality on another level.
The Arabs, before becoming the people of
the Book, had thus foreseen what one day,
much later, Joë Bousquet'31 would admirably
formulate in another language after a quite
different experience: "Poetry is the word of
the word."
Did Labid (560-661?), a poet who lived at
the meeting point of two ages and was con¬
verted to awakening Islam, have this intui¬
tion? His celebrated Mu'allaqa opens with
the following lines on which Jacques
Berque''" has made this comment: "The
return to the mass is also a return to the
original."
Now that they are gone the houses of Nina
The halting places and the places of sojourn
Rijam and Ghawl return to the permanences
like the slopes of the Rayyan
whose imprint is denuded to the mass
as the stone contains an inscription.
Berque notes that: "The birth of the poem
coincides here with the dynamic of its con¬
tents. Circularities."
(3) French poet (1897-1950)
(4) Jacques Berque, born 1910, French sociologist and
Orientalist. A specialist in Arab culture.
SALAH STETIE, Lebanese ambassador to The
Netherlands and formerly for many years his
country's representative at Unesco, is one of
the leading contemporary poets and essayists
of the Arab world. His works include three books
that deal more particularly with aspects of Arab
culture, Les Porteurs de Feu (The Bearers of
Fire, 1972), La Unième Nuit (The First Night,
1980) and Firdaws (1984), a study of Islamic
gardens.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Tale of the Heike
Japan's long-running medieval saga
by René Sieffert
The chief of the Heike clan clasps in his
arms the wife of his worst enemy... This
scene is from a television series made
in Japan during the 1970s and adapted
from a "cloak and dagger" novel, Shin
Heike Monogatari, which the author, Eijl
Yoshikawa (1892-1972) built around the
characters in the Tale of the Heike, one
of the most popular works in Japanese
literature.
IN the 1 320s, "monks with the biwa" began
to appear on the highways and byways
of Japan. (The biwa is a four-stringed lute
which reached Japan from the Middle East
by way of China.) Most of them blind, wearing
monks' robes, they travelled from village to
village, from castle to castle, chanting the
exploits of the heroes of the great conflict
which in the 1180s had opposed two impor¬
tant clans of the Imperial House, the Talra
and the Minamoto, in an implacable struggle
for power.
They were in many ways similar to the
rhapsodists, the reciters who spread the
Homeric epics through Greece, judging from
the countless variants and interpolated epi¬
sodes which feature in the hundreds of
known manuscripts of the chief of these epic
stories, the Heike Monogatari ("Tale of the
Heike"). The shortest version is in six
"books" (maki or rolls), the most extensive
in forty-eight.
The strange thing is, however, that this
epic, apparently a monument of oral liter¬
ature, emerged in Japan after some five cen¬
turies of highly developed written literature
which produced among other.masterpieces,
the Man yô-shû, an anthology of largely
scholarly poetry (8th century), and the Genji
Monogatari, a veritable psychological novel
which might be called "Proustian" had it not
been written almost a thousand years before
A La Recherche du Temps Perdu.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
However, the paradox is only apparent.
It seems to be accepted that there was orig¬
inally a written text of the Tale of the Heike,
a kind of chronicle whose author is unknown
although various names have been proposed
over the centuries, usually those of monks.
This original Heike, in three books, was prob¬
ably the third part of a trilogy, the first two
parts of which have survived almost in their
original form.
This Is an original instance, In a country
with an advanced civilization, of the formation
of an oral, popular epic literature on the basis
of a written work. Furthermore, this came
about near the capital, in a part of Japan
where there was a high rate of literacy.
Courtiers, administrators and monks from
big monasteries displayed rare curiosity
about and interest in what we should today
call the "popular arts" or "folklore". In a pro¬
fusion of stories, chronicles, essays and diar¬
ies, they have left us descriptions of the way
in which the new culture developed and took
root, largely through the diffusion of epic sto¬
ries. They also recorded In writing the suc¬
cessive forms of the texts. Thus we can follow
more or less from the fourteenth to the end
of the sixteenth century the chequered fate
of what was to become the quintessential
Book of Japanese national culture until the
last century.
At the end of the sixteenth century, a
"definitive" printed version appeared of this
work which had until then been collective and
malleable. It circulated in a society in the
throes of explosive urbanization, becoming
the all-time best-seller of Japanese publish¬
ing, Japan's most imitated book and the one
best adapted to new forms of expression,
especially the theatre.
One of the first printed editions of the Tale
of the Heike was published at Nagasaki in
Latin characters to help Iberian missionaries
learn the Japanese language. The choice is
significant. What better model could be imag¬
ined for those wishing to preach the gospel
to the greatest number than this text known
to everyone, literate and illiterate.
For the "Heike monks" or Heiké-hôshi,
continued their itinerant activities as musi¬
cians and reciters, as they still do today. In
the last few years, recordings have been
made of stories told by the last chanters of
heikyoku (epic song), which are not more
or less arbitrary reconstitutions but reflect a
way of story-telling transmitted from master
to pupil since the Middle Ages.
And through a new paradox in its history,
this form which the modern media once
seemed to dismiss out of hand, is today expe¬
riencing thanks to the media and to Japan's
rapidly developing leisure civilization an
unexpected revival and extraordinary pop¬
ularity: a single singer, through a recording
or a TV performance can today reach an
The Tale of the Heike Is an epic based
on an actual historical struggle for power
in Japan between the Taira (Heike) and
Minamoto (Genji) families during the sec¬
ond half of the 12th century. After an irre¬
sistible rise to power, the Heike family
held absolute sway until the death in 1181
of their leader Taira no Kiyomori. The
Genji finally succeeded in crushing their
rivals and their leader, Minamoto no Yor-
itomo (1 147-1 199), established himself as
Shogun of Kamakura. Below right,
painted wood statue of Taira no Kiyomori
preserved in a Buddhist temple in Kyoto.
Below left, statue of Minamoto no Yori- x
tomo in a Shinto temple.
audience a hundred or a thousand times
bigger than that which his predecessors
could hope to reach in a lifetime.
Furthermore, these survivors of an art
thought to be moribund (thirty-odd years ago
there were only three or four singers left)
have not only found successors who will carry
on the tradition in far more satisfactory mate¬
rial conditions, but more and more young
people are studying under their supervision,
just as others attend schools run by rió actors
(some two million active amateurs at present)
or Indulge in the pleasures of haiku (ten mil¬
lion), flower arranging and other classical
Japanese arts.
This brief account of the extraordinary fate
of the Japanese epic and the continuous
exchanges between the written and the oral
of which it is the focus, may overlook the
essential fact that all forms of Japanese lit¬
erature and the performing arts have con¬
stantly borrowed from it for seven centuries.
The classical nô, jôruri (bunraku) and kabuki
theatre as well as the novel, with the very
recent vogue for cloak and dagger stories
draw on the epic cycle for themes, characters
and inspiration. More than anything else the
constant use of the epic in advertising in the
media is a sign of its unfading popularity.
	
RENE SIEFFERT, of France, is a professor at
the Institut National des Langues et Civilisations
Orientales, Paris, where he is director of the
Centre d'Etudes Japonaises. He has translated
and published several French translations of
the classics of Japanese Literature including
Le Dit des Heike (Tale of the Heike, 1976), La
Tradition Secrète du Nô et Une Journée de Nô
(The Secret Tradition ofNô Theatre and A Day
ofNô, 1960), Le Dit du Genji (The Tale of Genji,
1979, new edition 1985) and Les Contes des
Provinces de Saikaku (Tales from the Saikaku
Provinces, 1985).
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Who's Who
in the Mahabharata?
by Lokenath Bhattacharya
JARATKARU or Jamadagni? Or was it
Jayadratha, or Jarasandha? There are
so many names beginning with J in the
Mahabharata that I confuse them. Who was
who? Who did what?
A group of trekkers and pilgrims, just
arrived at Bhaironghat after covering on foot
the nine-kilometre distance from Gangotri
near the source of the Ganges, we had
crowded into the only tea-stall at the halting-
place before embarking the next morning on
the two-day bus journey to Rlshikesh from
Lanka, on the other side of the Ganges.
It was already evening and shivering cold,
and the mountains all round, at that altitude
of about 3,000 metres, stood like giant seh-
tries obstructing the view on every side. The
singing-ringing-roaring river down below
drowned our whispers like so many noth¬
ingnesses in an all-engulfing ocean of
silence.
Our chit-chat, to pass the time as we fought
against the cold with chipped cups of hot tea,
had started with a casual question: who was
the king whose name began with J and who
conducted that great sacrifice in the course
of which the Mahabharata story was
recounted for the very first time by a sage?
While we were making wrong guesses, the
answer came from the owner of the tea-stall,
a middle-aged man of great simplicity, whose
face, smile and voice had a touch of the age-
old India. No, he said in a Hindi which we
Bengalis, South Indians and others of the
group had no difficulty in grasping no, it was
Janamejaya, King Parikshit's son, who, in
the course of a sacrifice conducted by him,
requested the sage Valsampayana, a leading
disciple of Vyasa, the author of the epic, to
narrate the story.
j And Jaratkaru? Well, he was the father
of the sage Astika who intervened to save
the life of the serpent Takshaka when Jan¬
amejaya, while making his great sacrifice of
serpents, was determined to persecute the
serpent race.
Then the tea-stall owner took up one by
one the other Js we had mentioned Jamad¬
agni, Jayadratha, Jarasandha, and so on
and described in detail who they were or what
they did.
Time passed as we sat enthralled, imag¬
ining ourselves to be the assembly that had
gathered in the court of Janamejaya, with
the tea-stall owner, an unlettered man, a
replica of the sage Vaisampayana. In a cor
ner of the stall, in the dim light of the lamp,
the silhouette of a man, perhaps a sadhu
(holy man), could be seen standing on one
leg. We were told that he had taken a vow
to remain standing in that posture for one
full year without interruption and that he
would have completed the year on the next
day. Looking like a figure from the Mahab¬
harata, he fitted well into the surroundings
and as a backdrop to our discourse. Trans¬
posed into a space without time, we felt pos¬
sessed by the truth of the saying that what
is not in Bharata (the Mahabharata) is not
in Bharata (India). Just as we carry the
Ganges in our veins, so the battleground of
Kurukshetra, the scene of the eighteen-day
war between the Kauravas and the Pan-
davas, lies in our heart. And that battle is
our inner battle with ourselves. And doesn't
the Mahabharata story almost start with the
Ganges? Wasn't it Ganga the goddess who,
in fulfilment of a curse, assumed human form
to become the wife of King Santanu, to whom
she bore eight sons, the youngest of whom
was Bhishma?
The Mahabharata is a story told to be
heard which continues to be told and heard
by countless millions throughout the length
and breadth of the country during festive
occasions, dramatized in performing arts
such as Kathakali or Yakshagana or the pup¬
pet plays of different regions. No one,
whether educated or illiterate, Is immune to
its overwhelming attraction and Impact. Chil¬
dren learn it at their grandmother's knee, and
village evenings are enlivened when, their
day's work done, villagers gather in the tem¬
ple or under a tree to listen to these stories
being read. Even to this day, in cities like
Calcutta, busy market-places are magically
transformed in the evening when people
gather in clusters in any open space they
can find and listen as someone recounts and
explains an episode from the Mahabharata.
The orality of the Mahabharata has a
sanctity all its own. How many could read
it in India where the literacy rate is around
37 per cent? But ask any passer-by who
Arjuna was, for example, and listen to all he
has to say.
The name of Arjuna brings back another
memory. As a child, on a visit to Maha-
balipuram with my father, I remember making
some stupid remarks about the famous rock-
sculpture known as Arjuna's Penance.
Seeing Arjuna standing there on one leg,
much like the sadhu we later came across
in the tea-stall at Bhaironghat, I laughed at
The great Hindu epic, the Mahabharata
provides the inspiration for Pandavani, a
form of oral literature current in a wide
area of central India. Teejan Bai (right),
one of the best-known contemporary Pan¬
davani singer-narrators, belongs to one
of the two main streams of Pandavani,
the Kapalike school. The performer
recites and sings several episodes from
the epic whilst playing the tambura, a
long-necked, three-string lute with a
sound-box made of half a gourd covered
with the skin of a salamander. The Instru¬
ment is usually made by the performer
himself or herself. The performer is
accompanied by two tambourplayers and
a harmonium player. A second singer
maintains a dialogue with the principal
singer and beats out a rhythm on the
Changuri, a kind of tambourine.
what I then considered to be the futility of
making so much fuss about a person who
had perhaps never existed. My father's
rejoinder was prompt and sharp. If Arjuna
does not exist, who does, you or I? We come
and go; Arjuna remains. He has a vital exist¬
ence in us and lives in our imagination. He
is much more real than the so-called reality
of the factual world.
Composed several thousand years ago,
the Mahabharata possesses in a supreme
manner all the characteristics of a true epic,
and remains an unfailing source of spiritual
strength to the people of India. Generations
of gifted writers have added a mass of mate¬
rial to Vyasa's original, giving the work its
present form of ninety thousand couplets,
which makes it by far the longest epic in the
world. All kinds of historical, legendary, geo¬
graphical and philosophical material has
been added to the original over the centuries.
To writers in these fields, especially when
printing did not exist, the Mahabharata was
like a national library, inclusion in which was
a token of their enrichment of the national
heritage. The immediacy of its grandeur lives
in the hearts of men, more than in a
book.
LOKENATH BHATTACHARYA, of India, is
director of the National Book Trust, New Delhi.
He is the author of several works including The
Prose Poems of Lokenath Bhattacharya (1972)
and The Drum of the Guru (1979).
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Liu Jingting,
prince of story-tellers
by Yao Zhenren
LIU Jingting (1 587-1 670), the originator
of the modern art of Chinese story¬
telling, lived during the tumultuous
period of Chinese history when the Ming
Dynasty was supplanted by the Qing
Dynasty.
A native of Taizhou, Jiangsu Province,
Liu's original name was Cao Fengchun.
When he was fifteen, he had a brush with
the law and fled to escape punishment. He
travelled to the Xuyi area, where he became
an apprentice story-teller in order to earn a
living, eventually embarking on a career
which was to last over sixty years. One day,
distressed by his misfortunes and probably
in an attempt to shake off his pursuers, he
changed his name to Liu Jingting. He was
a man of plain features, and since he had
black moles on his face people nicknamed
him "Pockmarked Liu".
He sought advice from an elderly and
respected scholar, Mo Houguang, who had
made a profound study of the theory of story¬
telling. Mo held that apart from basic skills,
a good story-teller should first of all familiarize
himself with the lives of all social groups, be
conversant with different dialects, know the
customs and habits of different parts of the
country, and absorb all kinds of trivia. Even
more important, Mo said that the story-teller
should live each part man, woman, hero
and clown in a story instead of simply acting
as a mouthpiece for the characters. In addi¬
tion he should imitate the characters' ges¬
tures and emotional expressions so that he
could draw his audiences into the world
depicted in the story. Mo's ideas were quite
similar to Western theories of realistic drama
in the nineteenth century. After arduous
study, Liu finally understood the quintess¬
ence of story-telling and was able to move
his audiences even before he uttered a single
word.
He travelled to Yangzhou, Suzhou, Hang-
zhou and other places to make a living as
a performer. Finally he came to Nanjing,
known then as the capital of six dynasties,
where he began to win overwhelming admi¬
ration from audiences who were entranced
by his brilliant artistry.
Contemporary descriptions give some idea
of his outstanding performing manner. Zhang
Dai, a scholar of the late Ming Dynasty,
depicted Liu telling the Water Margin story.
"At the climactic point of the story, thun¬
derous shouting and brawling breaks out,
Discovered in a Han Dynasty tomb at Tian-
wei, Sichuan Province, this dancing fig¬
urine, drumstick in hand and a big smile
on his face, creates a vivid image of the
art of popular story-telling. It dates from
the later years of the Eastern Han Dynasty
(second century BC) and is now in the
collection of the Chinese History
Museum. Similar wood or pottery figu¬
rines have been found in other parts of
Sichuan and Jiangsu Provinces.
Wang Shaotang (1889-1968), descendant
ofa family ofstory-tellers from Yangzhou,
began his own story-telling career at the
age of 12 and perfected his art during his
60 years on the stage. His original inter¬
pretation of a story called The Water Mar¬
gin was so popular that people began to
call his oral version The Water Margin of
the Wang Family. In 1959, an 800,000-
word book was published, entitled Wu
Song, which was based on Wang's inter¬
pretations of popular stories.
and the whole house seems to be shaking
and collapsing. When Wu Song gets into the
wine-shop and finds nobody inside, he lets
out a mighty roar, making all the empty pots
and urns inside drone in resonance."
Another writer also described a Liu per¬
formance: "From time to time, his voice
changes from thunderous booming to melo¬
dious murmuring; his expression changes
from tears to laughter. The characteristics,
voices, behaviour and gestures of each role
are so vividly rendered that his listeners feel
as if they are in the story with the characters
while the story-teller has silently faded away
from the scene."
Liu became widely renowned as a master
story-teller and for about three years became
deeply involved in the political and military
affairs of the Southern Ming régime. Around
the sixteenth year of Emperor Chongzhen's
reign (1 643), he was invited by the then-pow¬
erful military governor of Wuchang and Mar¬
quis of Ningnan, Zuo Liangyu, to perform at
his army headquarters. Subsequently he
began to serve as a close aide to the gov¬
ernor, helping to mastermind plans and draft
documents.
These were palmy days for Liu. However,
after Zuo Liangyu's causes were lost and the
Southern Ming Dynasty collapsed, he had
to return to the street and to story-telling. He
wrote and circulated an epic about Zuo, at
a time when "current affairs" story-telling
seemed most likely to appeal to audiences.
His story was not just an account of what
he had seen and heard; it was mainly an
expression of deep grief over the fall of a
nation and the break-up of countless families.
In the first year of Emperor Kangxi's reign
in the Qing Dynasty, Liu Jingting, then a grey-
haired man in his late seventies, came to
Beijing by way of Tianjin. But his old age
apparently did not dim his lustrous talents;
he could still vividly portray the valour of war¬
riors as well as tender feelings between
young lovers.
Sadly, Liu led a miserable and dreary life
In old age. It is said that he died of frost¬
bite and starvation, but even today nobody
knows exactly when and where this master's
story ended.
YAO ZHENREN, of China, is editor and head
of the art department of Literary and Art Study,
a magazine published by the Chinese Art Study
Institute.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
»7
I
¿i.
1
imi
tülE
ÉïV mm.
1 1
\ 1Mflr ' ní/a
Ufe- ^_ / / /f í \
tk
The on/y known portrait of the famous
17th-century story-teller Liu Jingting. It
is the work of Wang Su, an artist of the
late Qing Dynasty. This radiant portrayal
of Liu, with his flowing grey hair, square
headdress and fan, and costume typical
of the period, almost exactly matches the
description written by Zhang Dai, a
scholar of the late Ming Dynasty, in an
account entitled Recalling the Dream at
the Tao'an Hut.
* *-'
cy
S
o
©
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Tibet's Ge-sar epic
by Mireille Helffer
Recent Tibetan wood-cut depicting Ge-sar as the warrior-god.
FROM the land of the Burushaski in the
west to Mongolia in the east, In all the
regions where Tibetan civilization pre¬
vails, the oral as well as the written tradition
has preserved the name of a hero, Ge-sar,
whose exploits fill an epic cycle (sgrung)
which has many ramifications.
The name "Ge-sar" of course brings to
mind the title of the Caesars In the Medi¬
terranean world and Byzantium. But there
may also have been a historical Ge-sar,
whose existence is doubted by Tibetologists,
although coins recently discovered show that
there was in the ninth century a certain
Phromo Gesaro, who is thought to have been
one of the sovereigns of Gandhara (in what
is now northwestern Pakistan). Chinese and
Tibetan documents also mention a Gru-gu
Ge-sar, possibly a reference to the Turkish
tribes of Central Asia, and a Ge-sar of Gling,
who was connected with the kingdom of that
name to the east of Tibet. The latter term,
Gling, could be understood as an abbrevia¬
tion of 'Dzambu-gling, which means "the
world" in Tibetan.
In any case, the Ge-sar of the epic appears
in turn as a king of armies, a universal sov¬
ereign who overcomes the demons of the
points of the compass, and a god of war to
whom worship is paid, and even a Buddha.
The many episodes that illustrate the
exceptional qualities of Ge-sar include the
miraculous birth of the hero, who was the
son of a celestial father and a mother who
was the daughter of a divinity of the under¬
world; his unhappy childhood; his accession
to the throne of Gling and his marriage, after
a horse-race; his victorious combats with Klu-
btsan, the demon of the north, Gur-dkar king
of the Hor, Shing-khri king of the Mon, and
Sa-tham king of the 'Jang.
In addition to these main episodes there
were others, in an order that is not clear
the conquest of the Stag-gzig, Kashmir,
China, and the four great and eight small
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
castles, and indeed of the eighteen castles,
and the descent into hell.
We have manuscript or wood engraving
versions of most of these episodes, which
take up tens of thousands of pages. A printed
version, which is in Mongolian but is based
on a Tibetan original, appeared in Beijing in
1716. And around the middle of the nine¬
teenth century Tibetan scholars contributed
much to the development of Ge-sar and the
production of a version of the epic.
Tibetans today are again becoming inte¬
rested in the man they regard as a national
hero, and their interest has been stimulated
by the many re-editions brought out in India
and Bhutan as well as In the People's Repub¬
lic of China.
The dissemination of the epic in written
form did not put a stop to the oral tradition,
which remained alive thanks to the singers
of epics who were known as sgrung-mkhan.
Some of these singers were thought to have
been possessed by one of the characters
of the epic; sometimes they went into a trance
and maintained that they knew the epic
without having learned it, by direct inspi¬
ration. Others took lessons from teachers;
and yet others, who were mere amateurs,
used books that they had obtained or that
someone had read to them.
If we examine the sound recordings that
have been made in the last forty years, we
can see that those who sang the praises of
Ge-sar, whatever training they had had and
wherever they came from, alternated prose
tales, rapidly recounted, and strophic songs
composed of lines containing seven or eight
syllables, in which, in accordance with immu¬
table conventions, the characters introduce
themselves, state where they are, and des¬
cribe the situation, pronouncing many
adages.
Few sgrung-mkhan now sing the praises
of Ge-sar in Mongolia and Bhutan, but there
are quite a number of them in Ladakh, and
according to information obtained in August
1984 they had recently held a meeting at
Rtse-thang, in the Autonomous Region of
Tibet. One of the twenty participants, who
attracted special attention was an illiterate
young woman of twenty-five, a native of
Byang-thang. She knew by heart some sixty
chapters of the epic, which she had learned
from her father, who had died in 1968.
This confirms, if any confirmation were
needed, the vitality of the epic of Ge-sar in
the Tibetan context, and gives us reason to
hope that a systematic study of the ways in
which It has been handed down can be
undertaken in the near future.
MIREILLE HELFFER, of France, is a director
of research at the Centre National de la
Recherche Scientifique , Paris. An ethno-musi-
cologist and a specialist on the music and mus¬
ical notations of Tibetan Buddhist ritual, she is
the author of Les Chants dans l'Epopée Tibé¬
taine de Ge-sar, (The Songs of the Epic of Ge-
sar, 1977) and has made two records, Castes
de Musiciens au Népal (Musicians' Castes in
Nepal) and Ladakh, Musique de Monastère et
de Village (Ladakh, Music of Monastery and
Village).
The Tibetan srung-mkhanfep/c singer)
Rin-chen Dar-rgyas, photographed in
1956.
'V ?* Vu
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The love-story
of Hir and Ranjha
by Hakim Mohammed Said
PAKISTANI culture has known writing
from a remote past, and its oral tra¬
ditions were committed to writing at
different periods, although the mode of their
transmission has always been oral. Each of
the four provinces of Pakistan (North-West¬
ern Frontier Province, the Punjab, Sind and
Baluchistan) has a number of folk-stories
which have been transmitted from generation
to generation in this way. Expressed in
poetry, almost all of them were meant to be
sung to the accompaniment of local musical
instruments.
Hir and Ranjha is a favourite folk-story of
the Punjab, a vast fertile plain watered by
five rivers (the Indus, the Jhelum, the
Chenab, the Ravi and the Sutlej). Sir Richard
Temple, an authority on the legends of the
Punjab, wrote that "Hir and Ranjha are com¬
monly said to have flourished 700 or 800
years ago, but some other scholars assign
them to the time of the Moghul emperor Akbar
the Great, in the sixteenth century AD." The
version which is regarded as a classic was
composed by the poet Waris Shah in 1766
in Punjabi, one of the mother-languages of
Urdu, the national language of Pakistan.
The story, according to Waris Shah's ver¬
sion, is simple, symbolic and dramatic. It
opens with the following line:
Praise be to God who made love the foun¬
dation of the world.
The poet refers to the sacred relationship
between God and man based on love, and
glimpses of this humanized philosophy are
seen throughout the long narrative, which
may be summarized as follows. "Takht
Hazara was a pleasant place on the banks
of the River Chenab. The chief land-owner
of the place had eight sons. He loved his
youngest son Ranjha the most, so Ranjha's
brothers hated him. On his father's death,
Ranjha's brothers turned him away. He jour¬
neyed through wild forests and wastes and
came to the River Chenab. He found a barge
on the bank but the boatman refused to let
him in. To kill time Ranjha played his flute
which attracted the boatman, who allowed
him onto the barge where he soon fell asleep.
A little later he was awakened by a noise
and to his great surprise he found a beautiful
maiden by his side. She was Hir, the daughter
of the chief of the Sial family of the town of
Jhang. When she stepped on the barge she
was furious to see this stranger, but when
she took a close look at Ranjha she fell in
love with him.
"She took him home and by some con¬
trivance persuaded her father to employ him
as a herdsman. She met him daily when he
went out into the forest to graze the herd.
Their clandestine meetings were soon dis¬
covered, Ranjha was banished, and Hir was
Hir and Ranjha, heroine and hero of a
traditional Pakistani love story that orig¬
inated in the Chenab Valley of the Punjab,
probably during the 16th century, as vis¬
ualized by Ustad Allah Bux, a well-known
contemporary Pakistani artist.
given in marriage to Saida, to whom she had
been betrothed while still quite young. Saida
belonged to a family of Rangpur. Hir was
not happy living with her husband and missed
Ranjha badly.
"Ranjha left Jhang, disguised himself as
a beggar, and went to Rangpur. On his way,
he visited a Hindu guru and begged for his
help. The guru blessed him. Ranjha came
to Rangpur and somehow managed to get
in touch with Hir. After a time they escaped,
but they were pursued, caught, and brought
back. They were taken before a judge who
ordered Ranjha into exile.
"Unfortunately, immediately after this inci¬
dent Rangpur caught fire. The people attrib¬
uted this misfortune to the forced separation
of lovers. Ranjha was called back and Hir
was handed over to him. They went back
to Jhang to Hir's home. But Hir's family had
taken it as a disgrace. The family planned
a stratagem. Ranjha was asked to go home
to make preparations for his formal marriage
to Hir. Meanwhile Hir was told that Ranjha
had been murdered, whereupon she fell
down unconscious. While in this state she
was given a poisonous drink and she died.
A messenger was sent to Ranjha to inform
him of her death. He came and was straigh¬
taway taken to her tomb. The shock was
unbearable and he fell dead at the tomb of
his beloved."
This story, reminiscent of that of Romeo
and Juliet, has.a symbolic and esoteric sig¬
nificance. It is a protest against the ills and
vices of the feudal system prevalent at the
time it was written by Waris Shah. Hir is a
symbol of protest against the exploitation of
women. Ranjha symbolizes protest against
the social system and the inefficient insti¬
tutions of his time.
The story of Hir and Ranjha is still as pop¬
ular as ever. Dr. Mumtaz Hasan has noted
how "Buffaloes and cowherds are still the
same in the old Punjab where wandering
minstrels to this day sing the familiar poem,
just as the bards of ancient Greece used to
sing Homer. And when the ploughmen gather
together in the village Dara (meeting place)
at the end of the day's toil, it is remarkable
how readily they turn to Hir and Ranjha to
soothe and refresh their tired spirits. A man
who can recite Hir well is always in demand.
Nor is the popularity of the poem confined
to villages. City audiences take just as much
delight in Hir recitations broadcast by
radio."
HAKIM MOHAMMED SAID, of Pakistan, is
president of the Hamdard Foundation and edi¬
tor-in-chief of the Foundation's magazine Ham¬
dard Medicus and editor of the Urdu edition of
the Unesco Courier.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Basque literature
and the oral tradition
by Juan Mari Lekuona
THE oral and the written tradition are
intimately Intermingled in Basque lit¬
erature. For those who know it well,
there is not a shadow of a doubt that Basque
literature is as rich and varied as that of any
other people, that it is just as fertile in original,
authentic literary forms, and that the oral
tradition is the vector of the essence of
Basque culture.
Coupled with this keen awareness of the
oral tradition is a realistic appreciation of writ¬
ten literature, which is seen as being a late¬
comer, neither very abundant nor fully rep¬
resentative, yet, at the same time, essential
to the very survival of the language and to
its adaptation to the demands of modern life.
Although this state of affairs is today widely
recognized, this was not always the case and
a glance back at the past may help us to
appreciate better the present complemen¬
tarity of these two forms of Basque literary
expression.
Under the impetus of the Renaissance
and the religious trends of the time, the six¬
teenth and the seventeenth centuries wit¬
nessed the publication of the first texts in
the Basque language. The output was very
small and was virtually confined to the north¬
ern or French-Basque region, as it was
called; this region was socially less devel¬
oped than the Spanish-Basque area where,
at the time, published material was virtually
limited to catechisms for parish use.
At that time oral expression was pre¬
dominant. Books containing religious texts
and texts for religious instruction were usually
read aloud in church to the congregation. In
preparing these books, their authors, bearing
in mind the instructional purposes to which
they were to be put, deliberately adopted the
forms and styles of oral literature.
These texts, which were both written and
spoken, became part of the collective mem¬
ory, colouring even popular forms of expres¬
sion; they were transplants grafted, as it
were, on to the language by educated reli¬
gious minorities.
The first written collections of oral texts,
gathered in both of the Basque regions and
consisting of old songs, refrains and popular
sayings, also date back to this period. Apart
from their inestimable value in tracing the
linguistic and literary development of the lan¬
guage, these collections also bear witness
to the vigour of the poetic forms and the
quality of the literary tradition from the Ren¬
aissance to the Baroque period.
During the two following centuries the links
between oral and written literature underwent
a transformation in the southern provinces
of Guipúzcoa, during the eighteenth century,
and Vizcaya, during the nineteenth century.
Literature flourished and the production of
published works outstripped that of the north¬
ern region.
The increase in the proportion of non-
religious books, accompanied by a rise in
the cultural level and a more pronounced
taste for the classics in the creation of oral
works, led to a new relationship between the
two forms of literature. Written literature was
obliged to turn to oral forms as the prime
source of literary structures and techniques,
whilst the oral tradition, particularly during
the Enlightenment, had to conform more and
more to the rules of written literature if it was
not to lose its topicality or even to disappear
altogether.
It was at this point that written transcrip¬
tions of oral literature began to appear. These
publications, ranging from fly-sheets of
poems by popular poets to magazines, peri¬
odicals and collections of folk tales, were
written versions of what was formerly trans¬
mitted by word of mouth. Forced to adaptx
to the rhythms, the norms and the mech¬
anisms specific to written literature, oral cre¬
ation was obliged to become more precise,
to adopt more complex structures. In so doing
it gave birth to a special branch of Basque
literature, born of the oral tradition but pre-
Taken in 1936, at Rentería, in the Basque
province of Guipúzcoa, this photo shows
a group of the finest Bersolaris (improv-
isers of poems) of the day, gathered
together to pay tribute to one of their num¬
ber, the renowned Txirrita (seated centre,
with walking-stick).
served and brought up to date in the written
word.
Those forms that could be safeguarded
in written form gradually declined, finally dis¬
appearing during the twentieth century.
These included ballads, romances, coplas,
lyric songs, choral and festive compositions,
short plays and other quasi-theatrical forms
which together had made up traditional lit¬
erature.
Modern life has led inexorably to the adop¬
tion of writing as the means of expression
and of preservation of literary works. Yet, in
the Basque language, written output has not
yet achieved the volume, the quality or the
popularity necessary for it to fulfil the func¬
tions that are attributed to literature in the
societies of today. The oral tradition remains
an inexhaustible source of means of expres¬
sion which still has a base broad enough to
allow the universal to be derived from the
particular and to embody the complexity of
the modern world as perceived by the col¬
lective personality.
Thus the twentieth century has witnessed
the forging of a new interdependence
between these two literary traditions. It is
clear that Basque literature can no longer
escape the written form and that it must seek
to achieve the level of the best national lit¬
eratures around it, taking quality as its only
criterion. As knowledge of it grows deeper,
Basque oral literature will become an essen¬
tial reference point for the creation of a mod¬
ern national literature.
In the period just before the Spanish civil
war, the lack of popularity of erudite, minority,
lyric poetry, as compared with the success
of improvised verse, popular theatre and folk
narrative, indicated the need for a redefinition
of cultural policy and a search for a rap¬
prochement with majority forms of expression
more firmly rooted in oral literature.
This trend was maintained in the post-war
period. The oral style, with its functionalism
and its specific rules, became a field of
research for writers seeking to create a new
aesthetic form which would enable them to
make the transition from the specific to the
universal on the basis of the fundamental
elements of their own cultural truths.
JUAN MARI LEKUONA Is professor of Basque
literature at the University of Deusto, Bilbao.
He is a specialist on Basque oral literature on
which he has published a major study, the fruit
of twenty-five years of research. He is also the
author of two volumes of poetry, Muga Beroak
(Deep Frontiers) and llargiaren Eskolan (The
School of the Moon).
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Newsroom
The Unesco Collection
of Representative Works
A new edition of the
Unesco Courier
We are pleased to announce the launching of
a Thai edition of the Unesco Courier, published
under the auspices of the Thai National Com¬
mission for Unesco. The first number appeared
in January 1985, bringing the total number of
different language editions of the Unesco Cour¬
ier up to 32, in addition to the quarterly Braille
selection.
Since its inception in 1948 the Unesco Pro¬
gramme for the translation of literary works has
sought to contribute to a broader international
appreciation of the world's literary heritage by
promoting the translation and publication,
mainly in English or French, of representative
works of literature written in the less widely
known languages. In addition to scholarly edi¬
tions of basic philosophical, religious and his¬
torical texts, the "Unesco Collection of Rep¬
resentative Works" includes anthologies of
national literatures, epics, sagas, legends,
fables and romances, drama, novels and short
stories, as well as many works of poetry. A
selection is given below.
African Series
Anthem of the Decades (A Zulu Epic) by Mazisi
Kunene. Translated by the author. London,
Ibadan, Nairobi and Johannesburg, Heine-
mann, 1981. Emperor Shaka the Great (A Zulu
Epic) by Mazisi Kunene. Trans, by the author.
London, Ibadan, Nairobi, Lusaka and Johan¬
nesburg, Heinemann, 1979.
European Series
Curial and Guelfa. Trans, from Catalan by
Pamela Waley. London, Boston and Sydney,
George Allen and Unwin, 1982. (Fifteenth-
century chivalry novel)
Hrolf Gautreksson (A Viking Romance) (Ice¬
land). Trans, by H. Pálsson and P. Edwards.
Edinburgh, Southside, 1972; Toronto and Buf¬
falo, University of Toronto Press, 1972.
Unesco Courier
readers' clubs launched
The Unesco Courier has decided to establish
a network of readers' clubs in as many countries
as possible. Exhibitions, which may be org¬
anized with technical assistance from Unesco
headquarters and the Unesco Courier, and dis¬
cussions of topics receiving coverage in the
magazine are among a wide range of club ac¬
tivities envisaged with the aim of stimulating a
dialogue between cultures. Unesco Courier
readers' clubs already exist in Bulgaria and
Egypt, where they have been established within
existing unions of writers and artists, and in
Tamil Nadu, where they have autonomous sta
tus. In the Soviet Union the Russian edition has
agreed to form readers' clubs as part of existing
cultural associations, and in the Republic of
Korea efforts afe being made to launch clubs
within local Unesco associations in colleges,
schools and universities. The Swahili and Dutch
editions of the magazine are attempting to cre¬
ate Unesco Courier clubs as part of the Unesco
Associated Schools project. Readers seeking
further information should write to: The Editor-
in-Chief, The Unesco Courier, Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Latin American Series
Flower and Song (Poems of the Aztec Peoples)
(Mexico). Trans, and introduction by Edward
Kissam and Michael Schmidt. London, Anvil
Press Poetry, 1977.
Oriental Series
Translated from Bengali (Bangladesh)
Uddin, Jasim. Gipsy Wharf (Sojan Badiar
Ghat). Trans, by Barbara Painter and Yann
Lovelock. London, Allen and Unwin, 1969;
New York, Pegasus Bobbs-Merrill, 1969. (Nar¬
rative poem)
Translated from Chinese
Anthology of Chinese Literature from Early
Times to the Fourteenth Century. Comp, and
ed. by Cyril Birch. Associate editor Donald
Keene. New York, Grove Press, 1965; London,
Penguin Classics, 1967.
Translated from languages of India
The Mirror of the Sky (Songs of the Bauls from
Bengal) (Bengali). Trans, with introduction and
notes by Deben Bhattacharya. London, Allen
and Unwin, 1969. (U.S. edition published as
Songs of the Bards of Bengal. New York, Grove
Press. 1970.)
The Parrot and the Starling (Hindi). Trans, by
K.P. Bahadur. Delhi, Varanasi and Patna, Moti-
Ial Banarsidass, 1977 (Folk tales).
The Wisdom of the Tamil People (As Illustrated
by Translated Selections from their Ancient Lit¬
erature) (Tamil). Trans, by Emmons E. White.
New Delhi, Munshiram Manoharlal Publishers
Pvt. Ltd, 1975.
Translated from Japanese
Tale of the Disorder in Hogen (Hogen Mon¬
ogatari). Trans, by W.R. Wilson. Tokyo, Sophia
University, 1971 (Historical novel).
Translated from languages of Pakistan
Waris Shah. The Adventures of Hir and Ranjha
(Hir Ranjha) (Punjabi). Trans, by Charles Fred¬
erick Usborne; ed. by Mumtaz Hassan. London,
Peter Owen, 1973. (See article page 32).
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 68 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 1 20 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
52 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun¬
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply official
endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/
or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris: (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan
48100, U.S.A.: (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc.,
111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.: (4) Bell and Howell
Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whltcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Roy Malkln
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seilchiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tlwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul).
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene
Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen Helsinki)
Swedish: Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-
in-Chief in Paris.
34
BRODARD GRAPHIQUE, COULOMMIERS - Dépôt légal C 1 - Août 1985 - IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed In France)
PHOTOCOMPOSITION/PHOTOGRAVURE DAWANT - 13, rue des Arquebusiers - 75003 PARIS.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published
This book, the first of its kind,
reviews the growth of sociology and
social anthropology in Asia and the
Pacific, showing how these
disciplines have developed and the
directions they are taking. Reports
on 12 countries provide:
concise descriptions of the origin
and development of each discipline;
the influence of schools of
thought from abroad;
the relationship between
sociology and social anthropology
and between these two disciplines
and the other social sciences;
research trends in each country.
Sociology and
Social
Asia and the
Pacific
Edited by Professor Yogesh Atal,
Unesco's Regional Adviser for
Social and Human Sciences in Asia
and the Pacific. Country reports by
noted sociologists from Japan,
People's Republic of China,
Republic of Korea, Thailand,
Indonesia, The Philippines,
Singapore, India, Pakistan,
Bangladesh, Australia and New
Zealand.
Co-published with Wiley Eastern Limited
(New Delhi, Bangalore, Bombay, Calcutta,
Madras, Hyderabad).
150 French francs
Unesco ISBN 92-3-102172-9
Wiley Eastern Limited ISBN 0-85226-041-5
Wilay Eastem/Unesco
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 1 75,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-101 1, Vienna. BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. - BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2 182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1 M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague
1 ; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 1 1 - 27 Prague 1 (Permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, CCP. 12598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D 5300 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport - ABT, P.O.B. 149 -
H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraett 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP>; 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 188 Enghlab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 131 58, P.O. Box 1 1 365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water. Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 1 1 3. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd.,
Quran House, Mfangano Street, P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd,
POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod. Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 - 9494 Schaan.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service,
Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Potchowk.'Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
. ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1 104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1 1 77 Sentrum - Oslo 1 , Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional
Office for Book development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi
Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES.
National Book Store, Inc. 701, Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra
Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road,
Singapore 2261 . SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern
Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH
AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl,
Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 1 6. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchätel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam,
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1 715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. TURKEY. Haset Kitapovi A.S.,
Istiklàl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 1 22 King's Cross Road,
London WC IX 9 DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor, Ml 48106. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121200. YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, P.O. Box 4227, Aden. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, Mica 30/1 1, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/1 1 , Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Lokenath Bhattacharya
Heikki Kirkinen
Mazisi Kunene
J.M.G. Le Clézio
René Sieffert
Salah Stétié
Paul Zumthor
Ho*ik (k^r
's^ms
mSSt wttKR
I I
m m
i
l^J^-iAr
4^
4^'
]]>
</page>
</document>
