<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066614eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
39 Bolivia
Round numbers
This pupil at school in the Bolivian town of
Corocoro is learning arithmetic with the aid
of an abacus designed by her teacher who
has used old bottle tops as counters. In the
rural areas of Bolivia, where the United
Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) is
helping the government to spread formai
education as widely as possible, teaching
aids are in short supply and are mostly made
by the teachers themselves. The abacus is
one of the oldest counting devices known to
man. Its name is thought to derive from the
ancient Phoenician word abak describing
sand strewn on a surface for writing.
wU
u.
Ü
Z: J
ë,
Cri ;0
o
Õ. r:c[l.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
 The Courier
A window open on the world
Editorial
TEE origins of war are intermingled with the origins of
mankind. Indeed, history was for long summarily reduced
to little more th an a c talogu  of a series of conflits. There
was not only one"Hundred Years War", but centuries of waste of
human lives.
The desire for peace, however, is just as ancient as the instinct to
destroy, and the vision of a united planet had haunted mankind
long before it assumed definite shape at a Conference in London in
1945, when men and governments decided to give it a new meaning.
Scarcely had men emerged from the bloodiest of human confIicts
than they suddenly seemed to become aware of the unity of their
species, proposing to create what the French poet Paul Eluard
called"Man with the face of man". They wished to turn values
upside down.
This was no longer the isolated cry of a poet, a prophet or a
visionary preaching to an indifferent world, but the commitment of
men and women speaking different tongues but a common lan-
guage :"Since wars begin in the minds of men, it is the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be constructed". * More than an act
of faith, the words of Archibald MacLeish spell out the lesson
learned from a grim and horrifying reality. Crimes against human-
ity'had been committed by men who knew how to read. Medical
doctors, in the name of science, had used women and children as
guinea pigs, as fuel. Men of taste had provided a theory for this
carnage and encouraged it, just as they had ordered Heine's poetry
to be burned. And so, in 1945, on the banks of the Thames,
governments affirmed that education, science and culture should
no longer be a law unto themselves, nor a servant for Caesar.
How do things stand now ? Such an objective is not achieved
from one year to the next, nor from one plan to the next. Even
today, on the fortieth anniversary of the signing of Unesco's
Constitution, we still have to fight against"that ignorance of each
other's ways and livets [which] has been a common cause, through-
out the history of mankind, of that suspicion and mistrust between
the peoples of the world through which their differences have ail
too often broken into war."*
This is why, at a time when the United Nations system as a whole
is undergoing a searching re-appraisal, it was decided that this issue
of the Unesco Courier, should commemorate not the customary
anniversary (4 November 1946, the date on which Unesco's Con-
stitution came into force) but the birth, with the signing of the
Constitution on 16 November 1945, of the Unesco ideal and the
efforts of the men and women whose passionate commitment made
possible this expression of belief in mankind and hope for the
future. If anniversaries are occasions for reftection, may this
anniversary be an occasion for us to meditate on this message, too
often ignored or lost sight of, from the founding fathers.
* Thé PreamNe to Unesco's Constitution
COVER : Gouache by the American artist Alexander Calder (1898-1976),
from the book Calder à Saché, published by Les Editions du Cercle d'Art,
Paris, 1975. &commat; Cercle d'Art, Paris-ADAGP
Editor-in-Chief : Edouard Glissant
October 1985
38thyear
This issue of the Unesco Courier is special on two counts. Firstly, it
celebrates the fortieth anniversary of the signing in London, on 16th
November 1945, of the Constitution of Unesco. Secondly, within the
framework of the programme of innovation and modernization now being
implemented throughout the Organization, it is the first fully computerized
issue of the English, French and Spanish editions of the Unesco Courier to
be prepared entirely within Unesco up to the final photogravure and
printing stage. To mark this occasion we are happy to have obtained the
collaboration of the Assistant Director-General, of the General Activities
and Programme Support Sector, Mr. Henri Lopes, as guest editorialist.
5 Birth of an ideal
by Howard Brabyn
6 The precursors
8'Thetifeofthemind'
Clement Attlee, Ellen Wilkinson, Jaime Torres Bodet, René Cassin
10 The San Francisco Conference
Harry S. Truman, Andrei Gromyko, Ezequiel Padilla
14 The mood of Britain, 1945
by Asa Briggs
21 Putting thé'S'in Unesco
24 Early days
by Julian Huxley
27 Can we educate for world peace ?
by Archibald MacLeish
28 The application of science and art
29 Finding a home for Unesco
32 Foundations
Photo story
2 A time to live...
BOLIVIA : Round numbers
1
PuMshed monthty in 32 languages English ItaUan Turkish Macedonian Finnfsh Selection in Brasille is published
by Unesco Pfench Htnd) Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish quartedy in Engtish, French,
The United Nations Educational, Spanish Tamil Catalan Stovene Basque Spanish and Korean
Scientific and Cultural Organization Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thal
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. Gertnan Persian Korean Butgarian) SSN 0041-5278
N°10-1985-CPD-85-1-427AArabie Dutch Swahili GreeX ? 10 1985CPD-85-1-427A
"pa---...... c-s ; nh
ARCHIVS 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
La Place (195O), sculpture in bronze (17 x
64 cm) by the Swiss-born artist Alberto
Giacometti (1901-1966).
Photo Mirko Lion @ ADAGP 1985
Peggy Guggenheim Collection,
Venise (R. Guggenheim Foundation)
The Governments of the States Parties to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare :
That since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be constructed ;
That ignorance of each other's ways and lives has been a common
cause, throughout the history of mankind, of that suspicion and
mistrust between the peoples of the world through which their
differences have all too often broken into war ;
That the great and terrible war which has now ended was a war made
possible by the denial of the democratic principles of the dignity,
equality and mutual respect of men, and by the propagation, in their
place, through ignorance, and prejudice, of the doctrine of the
inequality of men and races ;
That the wide diffusion of culture, and the education of humanity for
justice and liberty and peace are indispensable to the dignity of man
and constitute a sacred duty which all the nations must fuifil in a spirit
of mutual assistance and concern ;
That a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to
fail, upon the intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
For these reasons, the States Parties to this Constitution, believing in
full and equal opportunities for education for all, in the unrestricted
pursuit of objective truth, and in the free exchange of ideas and
knowledge, are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the
means of communication between their peoples and to employ these
means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and
more perfect knowledge of each other's lives ;
In consequence whereof they do hereby create the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization for the purpose of
advancing, through the educational and scientific and cultural rela-
tions of the peoples of the world, the objectives of international peace
and of the common welfare of mankind for which the United Nations
Organization was established and which its Charter proclaims.
Preamble to the Constitution of Unesco,
London, 16 November 1945
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Birth of an ideal
by Howard Brabyn
UNESCO, the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization, w uld
almost certainly never have corne into
being, at least in its present form, had it
not been for the very special conditions
that existed in London during the Second
World War.
With great tracts of Europe occupied
by Axis forces, Britain's bomb-scarred
capital was the temporary home of seven
Allied Governments-in-exile and of
General de Gaulle's Free French Com-
mittee, of statesmen, diplomats and
generals, of intellectuals and refugees,
and of ordinary men and women corne
from ait corners of the earth to fight for
freedom. It was a microcosm of a world in
ferment.
Although the overriding common pur-
pose was the winning of the war, the
presence in London of so many able men
and women from so many countries also
engendered an intellectual ferment which
was to leave a permanent mark on the
post-war wor) d. Among these men and
women were the education ministers of
the Allied Governments in exile who at a
critical point in the struggle against the
Axis Powers had the vision and the cour-
age to plan ahead for the task of recon-
structing their educational Systems after
the war was over.
As Gian Franco Pompei (President of
the Executive Board of Unesco from
1968 to 1970) was to write later : (l)
"We recall with admiration that on 16
November 1942, in a London then halfin
ruins, Richard A, Butler, President of the
Board of Education of England and
Wales, invited his colleagues from the
Allied Powers in exile, Belgium, Czecho-
slovakia, France, Greece, Netherlands,
Norway, Poland and Yugoslavia, to meet,
not just to discuss the problems of the
moment, brut also to plan the establish-
ment after the war of a permanent orga-
nization for co-operation in the field of
education."
The invitation was enthusiastically re-
ceived and the first meeting of the Con-
ference of Allied Ministers of Education
(CAME) took place at Alexandra
House, London, three years to the day
before Unesco was born. Au the coun-
tries invited were represented by their
ministers of education or their deputies.
Although it spoke of educational needs
in the post-war world, the letter of invita-
tion made no spécifie mention of the pos-
sibility of creating a permanent interna-
tional educationa) organization. Yet, as
Denis Mylonas points out in his remark-
able study La Genèse de l'Unesco (The
Genesis of Unesco) (2), only two months
later, during the second plenary session
of CAME, this possibility was mooted by
the Belgian delegate Jules Hoste in a
document he had prepared concerning
the intellectual relations between the Un-
ited Kingdom and Europe in which he
expressed the hope"that these relations
which had been developed and institu-
tionalized within the framework of the
International Institute of Intellectual Co-
operation (see page 6) would be vigorous-
! y renewed in more practical form after
the war".
Meanwhile, a number of independent
British and international organizations,
including the London International
Assembly (founded in 1941), the Council
for Education in Wor/d Citizenship, the
British Association for the Advancement
of Science and the Association of Uni-
versity Teachers, spurred on perhaps by
their contacts with the many European
intellectuals in exile in London, were ex-
amining various aspects of the future of
education in Europe in the post-war
world.
The personal prestige of their mem-
bers, among whom were numbered such
men as Lord Robert Cecil, Henri Rolin,
René Cassin, Jan Masaryk, Gilbert Mur-
ray and Julian Huxley, added great
weight to their deliberations which,
almost without exception, stressed the
need for an international educational
organization or organizations of one form
or another and which were to have great
influence on such governmental orga-
nizations as CAME.
Denis Mylonas describes how :
"in May 1943, during the fourth plenary
session of CAME, an ad hoc committee
was formed to study a joint report (Educa-
tion and the United Nations) drawn up by
a joint committee of the London Interna-
tional Assembly and of the Council for
Education in World Citizenship, This re-
port proposed, among other things, the
'création as soon as possible'of an inter-
national organization for education (.,,)
The ad hoc committee considered that the
creation of such an organization would be
premature,"
Nevertheless, only a month later, in
July 1943, delegates attending the fifth
plenary session of CAME were talking of
their own Conference as"containing the
seed of an international educational orga-
nization".
Indeed, in the nine months of its ex-
istence, CAME had vastly extended the
scope of its activities. It had created com-
missions on cultural conventions, on
books and periodicals, on scientific mat-
ters, and on films and audio-visual media,
as tell as committees or sub-committees
on history, the restitution of scientific
equipment and on the restitution of
works of art. To these would be added
later further commissions on the protec-
tion and restitution of cultural objects
and on school equipment, and another to
enquire into the special educationat prob-
lems of liberated countries, finance and
drafting committees, committees on
emergency assistance for teachers and on
the re-education of children who had
been subjected to nazi-inspired educa-
tion, a technical sub-committee to the
scientific commission, and sub-commit-
tees on educationat broadcasts and on an
international film centre. Just by looking
at the titles of these commissions, com-
mittees and sub-committees, we can see
emerging the hazy outlines of many of the
important programmes with which Un-
esco is still very much concerned today.
Meanwhile, world interest in the activi-
ties of CAME was growing and towards
the end of 1943 the delegates decided that
the time had corne to enlarge the Confer-
ence by giving full delegate status to those
countries until then represented only by
observers. By now the concept of the
creation of an international organization
was fully accepted, and in its letter of
invitation to the US Government the
Conference declared that among"the ob-
jects of the reconstituted Conference
would be to consider plans for the forma-
tion of a permanent organization, at first
confined to the United Nations3, but
eventually to be placed on an internation-
al basis with the object of promoting co-
operation in educational matters in the
post-war period".
The United States Government
accepted this invitation with alacrity and
enthusiasm. In its reply it acknowledged
"the important preliminary work done by
the Conference of Allied Ministers of
Education"and recognized it as"a useful
agency for the further emergency de-
velopment of international co-operation
CONTINUED PAGE 12
(1) ln the Minds of Men, Unesco, 1972
(2) La Genèse de l'Unesco : La Conférence des Ministres
Alliés de l'Education (1942-1945), by Denis Mylonas.
Bruylant, Brussels, 1976.
(3) Here the term United Nations refers to those nations
that had signed the Declaration by United Nations on 1
January 1942 ; the United Nations Organization did not
then exist.
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The French philosopher Henri Bergson
(1859-1941)
The Polish-born French physicist Marie'
Curie (1867-1934), famous for her work on
radioactivity and twice winner of the Nobel
Prize (1903 and 1911),
The precursors
*W F thé Conférence of Allied Ministers
of Education (CAME) was to play
the unusual role of mother and
midwife at the birth of Unesco, the new
baby that was born on 16 November 1945
could trace its antecedents back some
twentv vears to an emanation of the
League of Nations, the International In-
stitute of Intellectual Co-operation. and
an institution which started out as an
autonomous, non-governmental organi-
zation. the International Bureau of
Education.
lnternationallnstitute of lntelleetual Co-
operation (flic)
! n 1922. foUowing a proposa) made by the
French statesman and Nobel Peace Prize
winner Léon Bourgeois, the League of
Nations estab ! ished an International
Commission for lntellectual Co-operation
(ICIC) which was composed of twelve
members and which was to be responsible
for international questions relating to in-
ternational co-operation.
The Commission was made up of an
impressive array of great thinkers inclu-
ding, for example, Henri Bergson, its
first president, Marie Curie, Albert Ein-
stein and Gilbert Murray. With the
woefully inadequate financial resources
made available to them, however. they
could do iittte more than exchange) etters
and come together for an annual session
of discussion to which there was virtually
no follow-up.
In reply to president Henri Bergson's
6
CL'
LU
oi
- 6
"
E
- 6
w
(Ç)
o
Õ. r:c
Ci.
"'
eL
ro
15'"
E
15
LU
ç
o
Õ. r:c
[l.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Albert Einstein (1879-1955). The great
physicist played a leading raie in the work
of the Internationallnstitute of Intellectual
Co-operation.
The Swiss psychologist Jean Piaget
(1896-1980) was Oirector of the Interna-
tional Bureau of Education from 1929 to
1968.
plia for help, the French Government
offered to create in Paris and to finance
an International Institute of Intellectual
Co-operation, and, in 1926, with the bles-
sing of the Assembly of the League of
Nations, the IIIC came into being.
Properly financed and staffed by a
permanent Secretariat, the IIIC breathed
new life into international intellectual co-
operation. The Institute established
seven sections which dealt with : general
affairs, relations between universities,
libraries and scientific unions, juridical
questions concerning intellectual proper-
ty and the conditions of intellectual
labour, translations and the exchange of
literary works between nations, museums
and artistic relations, and information
and relations with the press and other
media.
We begin to see the embryonic outlines
of things to corne.
International Bureau of Education
(IBE)
After thé First World War, although indi-
vidual educationists and intellectuals
called insistently for an international
organization to promote co-operation
between countries in education, govern-
ments tended to guard jealously their
right to unqualified contre ! over the
education process within their bound-
aries. Indeed, the League of Nations ex-
pressly limited the educationa) activities
of the IIIC to theoretical pedagogical
matters and declared that it should"ab-
stain from activities concerning educa-
tional questions which belong to the
realm of the sovereign Member States."
This, however, merely had the effect of
encouraging independent action and, in
1925, the International Bureau of Educa-
tion was founded in Geneva as a non-
governmental organization. This was
made possible through the sponsorship of
the Jean-Jacques Rousseau Institute of
the University of Geneva. Despite the
support of this prestigious body, the IBE
soon found itself hampered by lack of
funds and, in 1929, it became a mainly
intergovernmental organization when a
number of States met in Geneva to draw
up and sign a new constitution. However,
the reformed IBE still remained indepen-
dent of the League of Nations.
The main objectives ofthe IBE were to
act as an information clearing house for
aH matters connected with education, to
gather information concerning both pri-
vate and public education, and to under-
take scientific and statistical research in
the educationai field.
During the Second World War the acti-
vities of the IBE were severely curtailed.
Its efforts were concentrated on the
humanitarian work of supplying"intel-
lectual aid"to prisoners of war of ail
nationalités. AItogether it sent some
600, 000 volumes of scientific and literary
works to prisoner of war camps.
With the emergence of Unesco it be-
came clear that the new organization was
better placed to carry out many of the
functions of the IBE, and in 1947 a pro-
visional agreement was drawn up be-
tween the two bodies for their future
unification. In 1968, under the terms of a
new agreement, the old IBE ceased to
exist, its functions being fully assumed by
Unesco. A new IBE was established in
Geneva, under the aegis of Unesco, as an
international centre for comparative edu-
cationa) studies. N
. ! a
<t ;
û.
g
"
â
""
V
Üo"'"'
<&lt; :
&commat;
o
Õ. r:c
CL
'"ai
c
0
[l.
. ;"
o
1 ;),.,
Q)
>&lt; :
0
o
Õ. r:c
[l.
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
,,
The life of the mind
Clement Attlee (later Earl Attlee, 1883-
1967)
"In the new world order towards which
we are moving it is essential that we
should have appropriate machinery to
deal with each of the major fields of
human activity (.,,) However we cIassify
the principal elements in the public life of
the world it would be impossible to ex-
clude from our classification that large
and significant field of activity which can
be described broadly as the life of the
mind. This covers not only the special
field of education in ail its branches and at
ail its stages, it includes the whole intel-
lectual realm with its'many goodty states
and kingdoms', the sciences, the humani-
ties, the fine arts, research for the
advancement of knowledge and the
who) e vast territory in which ideas are
disseminated. The field of educational
and cultural relationships is surely one of
the richest and most significant in the
internationallife of the world, We cannot
be content until our new world organiza-
tion provides for the fullest and most
beneficent development of these re-
tationships. Do not wars, after ale, begin
in the minds of men ?"
Clement R, Attlee
Prime Minister of the United Kingdom
London, 1 November 1945
Below and on the opposite page we present extracts from four
speeches made during thé"Conférence for the Establishment
of an Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization of the
United Nations", held in London from 1 to 16 November
1945.
Ellen Wilkinson (1891-1947) addressing a
peace rally in Trafalgar Square, London
"We are met at the end of the greatest
war in history, against the background of
two continents with their attendant
islands, across which the fires of war have
raged. Even now the embers stiiï glow,
and here and there the flames stiH fticker.
AU of us here-all the nations that we
represent-have taken some part in this
great struggle. AU have ranged them-
selves under the flag of freedom and
against aggression and oppression. Many
of us have drunk together from a com-
mon cup of sorrow and sacrifice. Now we
are met together ; workers in education,
in scientific research and in the varied
fields of culture. We represent those who
teach, those who discover, those who
write, those who express their inspiration
in music and art. We have a high respon-
sibility, for entrusted to us is the task of
creating some part-and not the least
important part- {) f that structure of the
United Nations on which rest our hopes
for the future of mankind. It is for us to
clear the channels through which may
flow from nation to nation the streams of
knowledge and thought, of truth and
beauty which are the foundations of true
civilisation."
Elles Wilkinson
President of the Conference
Minister of Education, United Kingdom
London, 1 November 1945
8
a
d
0
'". 
[l.
e ;c :o1 ; 5>-"'"
Ô
. r:cû.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Jaime Torres Bodet (1902-1974), is here
seen (third from left) during his term as
Unesco's second Director-General (1948-
1952) with a group of exchange students.
"We believe that the intellectualism of
the eighteenth century and the material-
ism of the nineteenth should give place in
the twentieth to the conception of a true
and balanced integration of man. That is
why-while the education of the intellec-
tua) faculties was the chief concern of
those systems which are now obsolete,
and while the education of the will has
resulted in extremes of imperialism that
we condemn-the horizons now open to
our view will demand of us a form of
education aiming at international co-
operation through the medium of truth,
virtue in aM its significance, and
democracy."
Jaime Torres Bodet
Delegate of Mexico
London, 2 November 1945
"Our duty wi)) be more completely de-
fined when our charter has been adopted
by ai) the United Nations, and when, on
what 1 hope may not be a far distant day,
we have the great Soviet Republic in our
midst (..,), We shaH never lose sight of
the fact, so adequately expressed at the
opening of our deliberations, that it is not
the sum of knowledge that is to be the
distinguishing mark of the activities of
our future Organization, but the develop-
ment of culture. One of our great authors
has said :'Science without conscience is
but the ruin of the sou\.'We can say :
'Know) edge without morality can only
result in barbarism,'We who know that
there can be no democracy without cul-
ture, will direct our efforts towards
adding something else to knowledge : a
great ideal, a ctear vision of the great
problems to be solved in the cause of
international peace and, lastly, and
perhaps most important of ale, the mas-
tery of self."
René Cassin
Delegate of France
London, 16 November 1945
René Cassin (1887-1976) photographed in
London during the Second World War
ouN
N
'"
<1>c :
: J
o
Õ. r:c
[l.
"'. 
N
[l.
oic :
>-
"
'"
Qi
o
õ. r:c
[l.
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
'"
: ij
û.a
oic
o
1ñ>-Q)
'"
Ccg
o
Õ. r:c
[l.
Stamp commemorating the signature of
the Charter of the United Nations at San
Francisco on 26 June 1945 shows the
Memorial Opera House, where the signing
ceremony took place, and the UN emblem.
On 25 April 1945, crowds line the outside
of the San Francisco Memorial Opera
House as delegates enter the building for
the opening session of the United Nations
Conference on International Organization
(UNCIO) at which the Charter of the United
Nations was drafted.
The Second World War was nearly over when thé United
Nations Conference on International Organization (UNCIO)
convened in San Francisco on 25 April 1945 to complete the
work, started long before, of drawing up the Charter of the
United Nations. This Charter was signed by heads of delega-
tions on 26 June with the understanding that it woult corne into
effect (and that the organization would officiallly corne into
existence) when it had been ratified by China, France, the
United Kingdom, the United States of America, the Union of
Soviet Socialist Republics and by a majority of the other
signatory States. This condition was met on 24 October which
is therefore the birthday of the United Nations, celebrated as
United Nations Day. Opposite page, brief extracts from three
addresses given at the final plenary session of the Conference.
10
The San Francisco
Conference
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
President Harry S. Truman (1884-1972)
speaking at the 16th plenary session of the
San Francisco Conference, on 26 June
194'
Andrei Gromyko, then Soviet ambassador
to the United States, signs the Charter.
" (,.,) That we now have this Charter at ail
is a great wonder. It is also a cause for
profound thanksgiving to Almighty God,
who has brought us so far in our search
for peace through wor) d organization.
There were many who doubted that
agreement could ever be reached by
these fifty countries differing so much in
race and religion, in language and cul-
ture. But these differences were ait for-
gotten in one unshakable unity of deter-
mination-to find a way to end war. Out
of aM the arguments and disputes, and
different points of view, a way was found
to agrée. Here in the spotlight of full
publicity, in the tradition ofliberty-toving
people, opinions were expressed openly
and freely. The faith and hope of fifty
peaceful nations were laid before this
world forum. Differences were over-
come. This Charter was not the work of
any single nation or group of nations,
large or smala, It was the reluit of a spirit
of give and take, of tolerance for the
views and interests of others. It was proof
that nations, like men, can state their
differences, can face them, and then can
find common ground on which to stand.
That is the essence of democracy ; and
that is the essence of keeping the peace in
the future. By your agreement, the way
was shown toward future agreement in
the years to corne (..,)"
Harry S, Truman
President of the United States of America
" (..,) The small nations, who have dis-
played in this Conference a great sense of
responsibility, noble co-operation and
dignity, are destined to fulfil a great mis-
sion : to tend with devotion and courage
the sacred fire of Law. They will not be
alone in this luminous task, for the com-
mon men of aïï nations, great and small,
hold the same aspirations and have the
same faith in a common destiny.
Whenever the cause of justice will raise
its banner, the peoples, great and small,
shall cry with the same conviction, shall
act with the same strength (...) Our faith
must rest, not on the great or the small
nations, but upon the common men of ail
nations. A) t peopies, large and smalt,
fully know that the world cannot bear the
terrible stress of another total war with-
out turning back to the dark âges. There
is, therefore, a peremptory necessity to
live in peace. Let us have reciprocal con-
fidence, let us have the full measure of
our goodwill (..,)"
The Honourable Ezequiel Padilla
Chairman of the Delegation of Mexico
" (...) In the course of the work of the
Conference there were some difficulties
and differences of view between separate
delegations on these or other questions.
However, one should be surprised not at
the existence of these difficulties and not
at the existence of different viewpoints
between separate delegations on these or
other questions, but at the fact that, as a
result of the work of the Conference, ail
the main difficulties were overcome, and
we succeeded in fulfilling successfully the
tasks before the Conférence. We pre-
pared a document which should become
the basis for the actions of the Interna-
tional Organization-its constitution.
Naturally, the very best and most perfect
Charter in itself is not yet a guarantee that
its provisions will be carried out and en-
sure the preservation of peace. In order
to achieve this important and noble task it
is also necessary, in addition to the ex-
isting Charter, to have the unity and co-
ordination of actions of members of the
International Organization, and first of
an the unity and co-ordination of actions
between the most powerful military
powers in the world. It is also necessary
that aU members of the International
Organization should try to settle aU dis-
putes by peaceful means in the spirit of
co-operation and goodwill (..,)"
The Honourable Andrei Gromyko
Acting Chairman of the Delegation of the
USSR
The Mexican jurist Ezequiel Padilla (1892-
1971), Ministerof Foreign Relations (1940-
1945).
11
<J>,
c :'
. Q
.,
z
7
ë). r : c
[l.
C
'"
c :
o
Z
G
"
: J
o
Õ. r:c
[l.
0
Z
a
<J>
c :
. Q
...
z
t
û.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Birth of an ideal
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 5
in educational and cultural reconstruc-
tion". It also declared that"the govern-
ments collaborating in the Conference
should take steps, with other interested
governments, to seek the best means for
establishing a United Nations agency for
educational and cultural reconstruction,
organized and administered along demo-
cratic Unes".
Thus, by April 1944, the United States
was represented at the Conference in
London by a strong delegation which in-
ctuded J. William Fulbright and a man
who was to play an important role in the
preparation and drafting of the constitu-
tion of Unesco-the poet and Librarian
of the American Congress Archibald
MacLeish.
The American delegation had arrived
with already well-formed proposais for a
"United Nations Organization for Edu-
cationat and Cultural Reconstruction"
and these were discussed at two special
"enlarged"meetings of the Conference
and a tentative draft constitution was ela-
borated. After discussion of this draft at
the tenth plenary session of CAME, at
which the Conference accepted a minor
but significant amendment proposed by
the chairman of the Scientific Commis-
sion, it was sent by the Chairman of
CAME, Richard Butler, to the govern-
ments of al) members and associate mem-
bers of the United Nations, as well as to
institutions with links with the United
Nations, for consideration and comment.
The amendment mentioned above
proposed the addition to a paragraph
concerning the exchange of information
on problems of education and culture of
the words"including scientific research".
Innocuous enough on the face of it, the
addition of this phrase was an indication
of the pressure that was building up to
extend the importance of science in the
activities of the proposed new
organization.
Reactions to the United States propos-
ais were generally favourable, but were
to be influenced by the outcome of the
Dumbarton Oaks Conference, held in
Washington from 21 August to 7 October
1944, which was to pave the way for the
creation of the United Nations Organiza-
tion during the following year at the San
Francisco Conference. The Dumbarton
Oaks Conference had given cautious
approval to the concept of an educational
and cultural organization, but everything
would dépend on the Conference at San
Francisco at which the Charter of the
United Nations was finally to be adopted.
Work at the London Conference came
virtually to a standstill, the general feel-
ing being cleariy expressed in a declara-
tion in March 1945 by Richard Butler,
chairman of CAME, that"the creation of
a United Nations Educational Organiza-
tion should have the closes possible con-
nexion with any organization created by
the San Francisco Conférence",
The eagerly awaited United Nations
Conference on International Organiza-
tion opened in San Francisco on 25 April
1945, and when it closet, two months
later, it had not only agreed the Charter
of the United Nations Organization
(which came officially into force on 24
October 1945), but had also approved a
French recommendation"that govern-
ments should convene within the next few
months a general conference to draw up
the statute of an international organiza-
tion on cultural co-operation". It also
recorded an addendum by the United
States delegation, speaking in support of
the French proposai, mentioning"the
plans of the Conference of Allied Minis-
ters of Education to call in the near future
a United Nations conference for the
establishment of an international orga-
nization on education and cultural co-
opération. The Government of the
United Kingdom had been requested to
convene such a conférence,"
The way ahead was now clear for the
creation of the new specialized agency of
the United Nations, and on 12 July 1945,
following the nineteenth plenary session
of CAME, British minister of education
Richard Law issued a press release
announcing that"A conference is to be
held in London on November 1 next, to
consider the establishment of a United
Nations Educational and Cultural
Organization".
On 3 and 4 August 1945 invitations
were despatched to the governments con-
cerned, the French Government being
specially associated with the British Gov-
ernment as inviting power. A working
committee to prepare the Conference
was established, and on 1 November 1945
the Conference for the Establishment of
the United Nations Educational and
Cultural Organization began its work at
the Institute of Civil Engineers, one of
the few buildings in London large enough
to house such an important meeting that
had not been damaged by bombs.
The Conference started out to estab-
lish Uneco ; it ended up establishing Un-
esco, For some time past a number of
eminent scientists, including, in particu-
lar, Joseph Needham and Julian Huxley,
had been pressing for the inclusion of
science in the title of the new organiza-
tion (see page 21), In her opening speech
on the first day of the Conference, the
chairman of the Conference, Ellen Wil-
kinson, had announced the intention of
the British delegation to propose the in-
clusion of science in the organization's
title. During the third plenary session,
the Chinese delegate, Hu Shih, declared
his support for the British proposition,
and by the end of the Conference Unesco
was firmly established as the name of the
new organization. There can be little
doubt that the events of August 6 and 9 at
Hiroshima and Nagasaki, still fresh in ail
their horror in delegates'minds, had con-
siderable bearing on this decision.
The Conference took place in an
atmosphere quite remarkable for its
sense of urgent purpose, of determina-
tion to succeed in what was seen as a task
of crucial world importance, and of refus-
ât to allow minor differences to stand in
the way of the main objective.
The tone was set from the outset by the
US delegate Archibald MacLeish. In a
speech in which he seconded Léon
Blum's motion that Ellen Wilkinson, the
new British Minister of Education, be
elected President of the Conference, he
declared :
" (,..) The achievement of greater and
more effective international co-operation
in the field of education, as in the fields of
culture generally-of science and the
arts-is the immediate purpose of this
meeting, But that purpose has behind it a
greater and even more moving objective-
the common understanding of the masses
of the people in this world (.,,)
The univers al languages of communica-
tion have always existed in the sciences
and in the arts and in the language of the
human spirit, Human science has prQ-
vided those universal languages with in-
struments, in the last few years, by whiçh
men can speak to men across the frontiers
of the world, by which the peoples of the
world may speak and answer (.,,) What
remains to do is what we have been called
here to accomplish : to crea te a social in-
strument through which these instruments
of communication, these universal lan-/co/ ? ! My ! <caf<OM, f/ : g MMpr ! a//a/ !-
guages, may be put to the service of the
common hope for peace (.,.)"
The Conference achieved this goal
with remarkable unanimity and des-
patch. At three o'clock in the afternoon
of Friday 16 November 1945, the Presi-
dent of the Conference, Ellen Wilkinson,
opened the tenth plenary session at which
delegates formally signed the Final Act,
the Constitution of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization, and the Instrument Estab-
lishing a Preparatory Educational, Scien-
tific and Cultural Commission,
Once again Archibald MacLeish found
the right words to sum up the feelings of
all the delegates at the close of the Con-
ference :
H J 1 think, speaking in all frankness,
that some of us who came to this Confer-
ence came with narrower ideas of what this
Organization was going to be than the
ideas with which we leave it, Some of us
thought it was to be an international orga-
nization for this or for that or the other
piece of the whole objective ; but 1 think
not one of us knew we should be construct-
ing here a great and powerful instrument
for the broadest possible purpose, which is
the purpose of the common understanding
of men for peace (...)".
HOWARD BRABYN is editor of the English edi-
tion of the Unesco Courier.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
13
f !
.-J..
v- :'
"
. 
g
L !J
'>
(5
õ
J
0
o
: g
û.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The mood of Britain, 1945
by Asa Briggs
"The air of England has a curious quality. We ais com-
plain about it one way or another when we come to it-the
physical air of England-but, oddly enough, we can ail
live in it, no matter where we come from. It is a mild air, it
is a medial air, it has no extremes about it, and we can ail
livre here. And what is true of men physically is true of
men's ideas. This air has always been hospitable to ideas ;
it has always been hospitable to freedom ; and we are men
who love freedom."
Archibald MacLeish, 16 November 1945
THE word"revolution"was some-
times used in Britain to describe
the transformation of ways of
life and, equally important, of attitudes
since the beginning of the Second World
War. The scientist Julian Huxley, who
was to become Director-General of Un-
esco in 1946, had published a volume of
essays in 1944 with the title On Living ira a
Revolution which caught the mood. Of
course, not everyone shared the sensé.
There had always been people who were
unwilling to chart plans for"reconstruc-
tion"untillong after the War had been
won, and there were some who in the
year of victory stressed continuity rather
than change, fearing change rather than
welcoming it.
Huxley, we ! ! known to the war-time
public through his broadcasts in the
BBC's immensely popular programme
the Brains Trust, in which everything was
discussed except the War, had no doubts.
The first of his essays, written as early as
1942, described how'there had already by
then been"a re-thinking of old prob-
lems"and a"transvaluation of values"in
Britain since the War began. Social ser-
vices were being extended, old clashs di-
viding lines crossed, and planning was
being taken for granted. Economie man
had given way to"social man". After the
War was over people would not want to
return to the ways of 1939."As a result",
he concIuded,"we now live in quite a
different world."
Huxley had made his reputation as a
writer on biological évolution. He con-
c) uded quite deliberately, however, in his
essays that only the word"revolution"
was adequate to cover what had been
happening not only in people's minds but
on the world stage. It was a world revolu-
tion which he contemplated, not just a
"revolution"in Britain. Certain trends
within the revolution were"inevitable"
and"universal". One was towards"a
more conscious social purpose". Another
was towards"a fuller utilization of the
resources of backward countries". The
question was one not of trends but of
methods,"The chief alternatives depend
on whether the revolution is effected in a
democratic or a totalitarian way."
Nothing could have been more demo-
cratic than Britain's general election of
July 1945 which displanted Britain's great
war leader, Winston Churchill, and
which brought the Labour Party into
power with a massive over-all majority of
146 seats in the new Parliament. In one of
the most readable of Britain's contem-
porary diaries Harold Nicolson, who lost
his own seat, wrote simply"Churchill is
out and Attlee has a clear majority ! No-
body foresaw this at aIl."Y et there were
people who foresaw it and had foreseen it
for some years as the logical outcome of a
"people's war"and the deveiopment of a
"citizens'army"which had been encour-
aged to think,"This is the dawn of a new
day", dectared the new Minister of
Labour with unsurprising enthusiasm,
"and in the light of it we are going to
march forward to those things of which
we have dreamed for years past."
It is easy in retrospect to analyse the
remarkable social and political conjunc-
tions of 1945 in a more sophisticated
fashion than was possible in 1945,
although even in the immediate after-
math of the election its first academic
analyst, R. B. McCallum, was at pains to
insist that even if it might be called a
revolution it was as well to avoid the
word,"Revolution is a cant word of the
day and is applied to almost any move-
ment of human affairs."
Certainly there was no element of force
or coercion in the domestic politics of
1945 ; the verdict was free. Nor was the
Conservative Party overwhelmed in
terms of the total number of votes cast
nationaux. In fact, Labour was in a
minority of 47, 8 per cent and the Con-
servative Party was to return to power,
once more under Churchill, in 1951.
Above all, the Labour Party itself was
less radical in 1945 than Conservatives
claimed during the heat of the general
election campaign ; it was wooing a broad
spectrum of the electorate, and many of
the policies it propounded had been
forged as part of a war-time national con-
sensus in which different parties shared
and to which they all contributed.
Moreover, it inherited rather than de-
signed the planning controls deemed
necessary to implement them. The eco-
nomy was to be"mixed","Labour will
plan from the ground up", its election
manifesto La6our Face the Future stated,
"giving an appropriate place to construc-
tive enterprise and private endeavour in
the national plan."
There was a reasonably broad consen-
sus on foreign policy in 1945 with the only 
On 8 May 1945, the day the Third Reich 
capitulated and peace returned to Europe
after 5 years and 8 months of bloody war, 
prime minister tMnsfon Churchill and 
members of his cabinet received a raptus-O
ous welcome as they appeared on the bal-
cony of the Ministry of Health in London. 
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ion May 1940, Winston Churchill (1874-
1965), statesman, author and orator, be-
came prime minister of the wartime coali-
tion government that was to lead Britain to
vlctory in 1945. ln the darkest days of the
Second World War he rallied the people of
Britain behind him and, concentrating his
boundless energy on the conduct of the
war, oecame one of the principal
architects of the Allied victory. Swept out
of office in the Labour election landslide of
July 1945, he became prime minister again
for another four-year term from 1951-1955.
The author of a number of books, includ-
ing a biography of his famous ancestor,
Marlborough : his Life and Times, and a
six-volume history of The Second World
War, he was awarded the Nobel Prize for
Literature in 1953. Above, a smiling Chur-
chill gives his"V for Victory"salute.
 critics on the far left and far right. Much
was made of the need to continue the
alliance of"the Big Three"-the United
States, the Soviet Union and Britain. Ali
the main parties supported the idea of a
new international organization"with
teeth" ; the teeth, in particu) ar, mattered.
It seemed more important also to create
machinery that would work than to im-
pose a quick peace ; peacemaking was
approached as a process, not an event.
Finally, in the making of peace, it was
maintained, attention had to be paid to
economic and social issues as tell as to
political and diplomatie concerns. As the
authors of Patterns of Peacemaking, a
much praised book of 1945, put it,"The
last war slogans of'homes fit for heroes'
and'a wond safe for democracy'were
modest hopes compared with the aspira-
tions for social security, freedom from
fear and want, full employment and
world peace which have been generated
by this war."
Education was considered to be a
necessary agent not only in purging Ger-
many and Italy from the grip of Nazism
and Fascism but in bringing people of the
world together, and Huxley participated
in a London conference held in 1944 to
consider new international machinery de-
signed to extend the work of the Interna-
tional Institute of Intellectual Co-oper-
ation, a body associated with the League
of Nations, and at the founding Confer-
ence of Unesco in London in 1945, One
<II."as[l.
ui<II
e
J : :
(Q)
. <=[l.
of the most important reforms in Britain
carried out during the War itself had been
an Education Act of 1944, and there were
several meetings of Allied Ministers of
Education from European governments
in exile in London which considered the
international implications of educational
advance.
It was usually recognized too, that
education and science went together. The
winning of the Second World War had
depended on trained scientists-it was
sometimes called"the physicists war"-
with some of the ablest scientists working
in laboratories and"Iittle back rooms"on
electronics, radar and nuclear power. Sci-
entists were the first to appreciate,
however, that scientific discovery was in-
ternational rather than national in char-
acter and that the effective use of science,
which was to pose difficult moral prob-
lems in the 1950s and 1960s, depended on
advances in the social as well as the natu-
rat sciences.
Education and science did not figure,
however, in the list of maj or public preoc-
cupations in Britain which were identi-
fied in a pre-election public opinion poli
in June 1945, Housing came first, full
employment second, and social security
third. And by then as many as 84 per cent
of the persons questioned, large numbers
of them new voters, had made up their
minds as to how to vote.
There were echoes of the First World
War slogan"homes for heroes"in the
placing of housing first, and full employ-
ment had been identified as a major goal
of national policy in 1944, one of the
Government's"primary aims and re-
sponsibihties". Social security had been
the theme of the most popular of all
war-time reports, that of the Liberal Wil-
liam Beveridge, who went on in 1944 to
write Full Employment in a Free Society,
The name of Beveridge became one of
the best-known in the country, but, hav-
ing won a war-time by-election he lost his
seat at the general election in 1945. The
plan was more important than the man.
Beveridge was to criticize the use of the
term"welfare State". Yet it was such a
State which the Labour Government of
1945 set out to create-with a compre-
hensive national health service figuring
prominently as an extra plank in its prog-
ramme. The day it was brought into
effect, 5 July 1948, was treated as another
D-Day and compared with the Allied
landings in Normandy in 1944, and
Labour was at pains to insist that it was a
model for others to emulate.
It was to prove difficult in practice to
reconcile the demand for such an active
and greatly extended social policy with
the economic facts of life which Britain
faced in 1945, If there was sunshine in the
sky, there were lots ofclouds. Huxley had
written little in his essays about economic
problems, although he had been associ-
ated with Political and Economic Plan-
ning, an important cross-party opinion
group, since its foundation in 1931. He
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
believed in the possibilities of planning
without devoting sustained attention to
the most appropriate methods of carrying
it out. Nor had most of the Labour lead-
ers very clear ideas either.
In fact, Britain in 1945 faced very se-
rious economic probtems. short-term as
we) I as long-term, which severely limited
its choices and made it difficult to pursue
long-term goals. On the day of the
Japanese surrender in August 1945, J. M.
Keynes-by then a main influence on
economic policy-making-warned that
Britain faced an"economic Dunkirk"as
serious as the military Dunkirk five years
before.
Existing foreign investment had been
dissipated to pay for the War, there was a
heavy new foreign debt. and there had
been a serious destruction of shipping on
which a crucial export drive depended.
Many materials and foodstuffs were in
shorter supply than they had been during
the War. and rations were to fall lower
after 1945 than they had been in the
darkest years of the War. The abrupt
ending of American Lend/Lease was a
severe blow to an increasingly vulnerable
economy. and an indispensable Amer-
ican loan was securcd onl on difficult
and controversial tcnns, 1 n Ci' ! lSequènce,
the country remamed in thé snp of
austerity. Indeed. bread. which had nev-
er been rationed dring the \Val, was to
be rationed in lC) J (l,"That wc shoule !
have to do snch an nnpopuiar thing".
wrote the ChanceJlor or the Fxchequer.
"illustrates ViVId ! y the urgent, hn ! ! ages of
the post-war venais,'
Thé words"shoIlage ; md"crisis"
were to be two of the mo-, t used words of
the ! ate 1940s. \\hen thé queue became a
major nationai peacenme institution.
"Economie man"had not been sup
p) anted by"sociat mart'as Huxley had
suggested. The new : \\ (Jmcmmcnt had ta
deal not onlv with"èeOnOInlC man"in the
shape of tradition cntrl !) ltflCurs. des-
perate ! y struggling to restore theit
businesses, or ml ! 1agcrs of newl)'
nationalized industries.) ike cuat and the
rai) wavs. but with'SpIVS" (a ne'\\'wl, rd)
who dealr shadih in uripr (Ct.'lÌt : liL : dl\'
suhstan'ia ! biack rnarkets D'ère '. e ! e
solin to hc. : m.'rt'carl," ! Il' ahout SPI\',
than, fìh () ut any t"d.-h ! : r",, 1 1. ct, ri1J1. 1 th\rhaut n, , lr, _r snt,; crv m.'ïl. w
were tau tlgure. P1U1"i : ! I", : l\li\ : 11 EnId]
films. many of them cornuJv films, \\'flldl
ion November 1940 the city or Coventry
bore the brunt of a massive attack by Ger-
man bombers aiming to destroy the air-
craft and armaments factory complex on
the city's outskirts. Bombs destroyed
some 70, 000 houses and the 14th-century
Gothic cathedral of S1. Michael, above.
17
ro
Q.
ui'"
'"
5-
i
É
n,
o
Õ. r:c
[l.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
 had been given a new lease of lifte during
the War and which evoke the mood of the
War and the immediate post-war years
more quicktv than plays. noyels or
poems.
! n cvoking thé mood of Britain in 1945
it would be misleading to concentrate
entirelv on the économies either of indus-
try or of consumer austerity. One enect
of the War had been to stimu) ate a hveiy
interest in the arts. including music. and
the interest was enhanced after the end of
the War.. A COill/cil for the Encourage-
meut of/Husic and the Arts had been set
up during the War. and in 1946 this body
gave wav to the.-I thé, COl/nci ! with an
annual Government grant at its disposa.
modes ! thoush this was b\ the standards
of some other European countries."I do
not betieve it is vet reahzed \\hat an im-
portant thing has happened", wrote
Keynes. who was even more interested in
the arts than in the dip ! omacv of the
Anglo-Ameriean 1. oan."State patronage
of the arts has crept in."
Keynes made the remark in a BBC
broadcast. and it vas often through the
BBC. which had providcd both an inspir-
ing and a consoling influence for the peo-
ple of occupied Europe during the War.
that the culture of the nation was most
universaiïy expressed. ! t was a sign of the
times that Sir William Haley, the BBC's
Director-Genera). planned the start of a
new Third Prorgamme which would pre-
sent the best not oniy in British but in
European culture. For him-and for his
colleagues-the community was"a
broadly-based cultural pyramid aspiring
slowly upwards". The pyramid would be
served bv three main Programmes.
"differentiated but broadh overlapping
in levels and interest. each Programme
leading on to the other. the listener being
induced through the vears increasingly to
discriminate in favour of the things that
are more worthwhile".
This was a verv British conception. So
too was the phi ! osophy that"each Pro-
gramme at any given moment must be
ahead of its public, but not so much as to
lose their confidence"."The listener",
Hatev maintained,"must be lcd from
good to better by curiositv. liking and a
gn) \\th of understanding. As the stan-
dards of the education and culture of the
During the Battle of Britain London was
the target of violent and highly destructive
bombing attacks by the Luftwaffe, The
bombing of London continued intermit-
tent/y throughout the war culminating in
1944 with the launching of V1 and V2 pilot-
less planes and rockets against the capi-
tal. Above, to escape the bombs many
thousands of Londoners slept each night
in London Underground stations. Right,
Shelter Scene (1941), one of a series of
drawings by the famous sculptor Henry
Moore who was an officiai war artist from
1940 to 1942,
on
"'-
F
Q
'"
E
o
Si
fui :
t8
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
community rise, so should the pro-
gramme pyramid rise as a who) e."
It was an essential feature of the mood
of 1945 that there was optimism about the
cultural pyramid. Social security reform
was based on a sense of solidarity. Much
other reform presupposed that"the
education and culture of the community"
would"rise as a whole"in conditions of
peace. Economists might be pointing to
the inherent difficulties in the British eco-
nomy ; sociologists, a smatler band, were
pointing instead to increased social
mobility and to higher levels of social
aspiration.
Britain's Labour Foreign Secretary,
Ernest Bevin, a trade unionist by com-
mitment and career, had warned of the
dangers of"poverty of désire", That
poverty, it was hoped, would now dis-
appear as completely as poverty affecting
the body. The hope was to reach its
pinnacle at the time of the Festival of
Britain, in 1951, which seemed to follow
naturally from the Allied victory six years
earlier, and, characteristically, it was ex-
pressed as a public as weiï as a private
hope."1951", the Director-General of
the Festival promised,"shall be a year of
fun, fantasy and colour, a year in which
we can, while soberly surveying our great
past and our promising future, for once
let ourselves go."
Science had its place in the new picture
atso. Two of the features of the Festival
were displays of jet engines and penicil-
lin, the one transforming travel, the other
medicine. There was a Dome of Dis-
covery, and most of the visitors to Lon-
don during the Festival went there first.
Many of them came from outside Britain,
although in retrospect this was a period of
severely restricted travel and people had
to depend on rationed newsprint and
broadcasting to find out what was hap-
pening in other parts of the wor) d.
The BBC was broadcasting to the
world in 1945 and, as the War ended,
there was considerable interest in Britain
in the world outside Europe. It was still
considered likely in May 1945 that the
war against Japan in the Far East would
continue into the unforeseeable future,
and once that war ended the political
problems of Asia were forced into the
newspaper headtines.
Inevitably issues of empire confronted
a British Government which inciuded a
strong anti-imperial element and which
wanted to settle them as quickly as pos-
sible. Already in 1945 the word most
generally used to describe the inherited
empire was"Commonwealth", and the
Labour Government always spoke of it in
this way ; it had no sympathy with
attempts by other imperial powers, as it
saw them, to put back the dock of empire
to 1939, In particular, the Government
was anxious to speed up the process of
implementing India's independence and
to try to introduce welfare State policies
in Africa.
There was a further strand in the think-
ing which related to Huxley's sense that a
worldwide revolution was in the making.
Great emphasis was placed on"develop-
ment"even though the economics of de-
velopment were expounded in such a
fashion that the advantages of tropical
development in Britain were stressed
more than its advantages to the people
who still had not won their political inde-
pendence. There was a sense that the
whole world was a great underdeveloped
estate.
The biggest changes in the world scene
were to become fully apparent only after
1947, when the Indian sub-continent secu-
red its independence, and there was to be
more than one crisis before the world
map was redrawn. There were few people
in 1945 who could have foreseen the fu-
ture speed of change, and it was other
actors in the drama, not the British, who
were to determine that. Britain had with
its Allies won the War, but it had lost
power in the process. It took time and
more than time to appreciate that, and
again it was people outside Britain, not
inside it, who were best able to judge the
conséquences, t
ASA BRIGGS (LORD BRIGGS) is a dis ting-
uished British social and economic historian who
has been Provost of Worcester College, Oxford,
since 1976 and Chancellor of the Open Universi-
ty since 1978. He is the author of many published
works, including A Social History of England
(1983), and a History of Broadcasting in the
United Kingdom, the fourth volume of which,
Sound and Vision, appeared in 1979. He was
made a life peer in 1976. His latest book is The BBC :
The first fifty ears ('Oxford University Press. 1985).
19
o
: ë
o
., jc :
'"
"
iE o.
us
. r : c'L
j
0
0
3
g
t-
8
c :
o
fj
0
il
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Putting thé'S'm Unesco
OF the many factors which com-
billet in 1945 to bring about the
creation of Une co the most
important were undoubtedly the historic-
al climate of the day and the overwhelm-
ing political wi ! ! of aH nations, after the
mort destructive war ever, to establish
mechanisms for the preservation of
peace.
A third crucial factor, the importance
of which has often been under-estimated,
was the contribution of individuel men
and women who, driven on by pas-
sionately held personal convictions, left
an indelible stamp on the infant Organi-
zation ; outstanding among them were
"the men who put the S in Unesco".
In fact, the original letter of invitation
which resutted in the establishment of
CAME (Conference of Allied Ministers
of Education) spoke only of educational
questions, although the ministers'discus-
sions rapidly broadened to cover a wide
range of cultural and some scientific
topics. At the end of 1943, when it was
proposed to widen membership of
CAME, the Conference was stiU talking
in terms of creating a permanent interna-
tional organization"with the object of
promoting co-operation in educational
matters" (UNEO ?),
When the United States became
associated with CAME, the US delega-
tion arrived with a plan for a United Na-
tions Organization for Educational and
Cultural Reconstruction (UNECREC ?),
while by January 1945 the US State De-
partment was referring to the creation of
a United Nations Educational and Cultu-
ral Organization (UNECO ?), and it was
The destruction of Hiroshima and Nagasa-
ki by atom bombs in August 1945 made the
consequences and uses of scientific re-
search the focus of intense concern, re-
Mecfed in the debates which led to the
creation of Unesco and defined the scope
of Its activitles. Left, the mushroom cloud
over Nagasaki, 9 August 1945.
an organization with this provisional
name that the Conference of November
1945 set out to estabtish.
It was against this background that,
behind the scenes, a number of scientists
were fighting desperately for the inclu-
sion of Science both in the title of the
organization and in the content of its
programmes.
The fight was spearheaded by Joseph
Needham, head of the British Scientific
Mission in China, ably seconded by Ju-
lian Huxley. The documents reproduced
below give an insight into the course of
the struggle and into Needham's obsti-
nate, and finally successful, single-min-
dedness.
On 29 December 1943, Needham outlined
for the/irst time his conception of an
International Science Co-operation
Service :
1 would like to indicate, in just a few
words, what 1 feel is necessary in post-war
International Science Co-operation. 1 be-
lieve that the time has gone when enough
can be done by scientists working as indi-
viduals, or even as organized groups in
universities, associations, etc., within in-
dividual countries, and contacting each
other across national boundaries, as indi-
viduals. Science and Technology are now
playing, and will increasingly play, so
predominant a part in ait human civiliza-
tion, that some means whereby science
can effectuaHy transcend national bound-
aries is urgently necessary. The Science
Co-operation Offices which have already
been set up in the capitals of the United
Nations are a piece of machinery which
ought to continue after the war. The need
for contact can be met neither by institut-
ing"scientific attachés"at ail Embassies,
for that would be too subject to diploma-
tic formalities, nor by sending from one
country to another industrial scientists
whose loyalty is to particular commercial
interests, for then their advice is likely to
be neither disinterested nor unbiassed.
What 1 should like to see is some kind of
International Science Co-operation Ser-
vice, whose representatives in ail lands
would have semi-diplomatic status and
full governmental facilities in com-
munication and transportation, but who
would be drawn from either governmen-
tal or academic laboratories-to which
after their period of service they might
return-and would therefore be free
from commercial entangtements. One of
the immediate aims of such an Interna-
tional Service would be the conveyance
of the most advanced applied and pure
science from the highly industrialized
Western countries to the less highly in-
dustrialized Eastern ones ; but there
would be plenty of scope for traffic in the
opposite direction too.
Needham developed these ideas in three
detailed memoranda which he sent to a
large number of diplomats, politicians
and men of science in the Allied countries,
following up this initiative by personal
contact with important personalities in the
United States, Britain and the Soviet Un-
ion. From them he learned of the proposai
for a United Nations Educational and
Cultural Organization and he immediate-
ly saw this as suitable vehicle into which to
integrate his International Science Co-
operation Service, It was in his third
memorandum, entitled"The Place of Sci-
ence and International Scientific Co-
operation in Post-war World Organiza-
lion"and dated 15 March 1945, that the
name"Unesco"appeared for the first lime in
a published document (see extract from
Needham's own summary to Memoran-
dum 11 belon),
SUMMARY
1) An International Science Co-opera-
tion Service (ISCS) has been proposed. It
is shown that there are immense tasks for
the benefit of humanity in the rapid ex-
pansion and dissemination of knowledge
lying before such an organization. Espe-
cially in rendering assistance to scientists
and technologists in the more outlying
parts of the world, there is much which is
not being done, and which could not be
done, by any other agency. 
21
'"
Na[l.
aic :o
""
0
o
Õ. r:c[l.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
 2) The United Nations Educational and
Cultural Organization (UNECO), now
being planned, could embody the
machinery proposed above, subject to
certain conditions being met. It would be
desirable to inclure the word"Science"
in th title, so that it should be named
UNESCO, and to ensure that its constitu-
tion covers international interchange in
Applied as we ! ! as Pure Science.
There was at first some opposition to
Needham's proposai as the following ex-
tracts from a letter dated 11 May 1945
from a British Foreign Office officiai to a
colleague in the Ministry of Production
demonstrate :
(...) We have already had copies of Dr.
Needham's remarks from several
sources. Insofar as his anxiety about the
position of science in the proposed Un-
ited Nations Organization for Education-
al and Cultural Co-operation is concer-
ned, 1 can assure you that the daims of
science will certainly not be overlooked
when the new organization begins its acti-
vities (..,) Dr. Needham's observations
were reported to the Executive Bureau of
the Conference of Allied Ministers of
Education by the Secretary of its Science
Commission, Dr. J. G. Crowther. There
was a general feeling against incIuding
the word"science"in the title of the
organization on the ground that it implied
a distinction between science and culture,
which not merely the English language
but British usage would not sustain (...)
Meanwhile, Julian Huxley had been
pressing the case for science behind the
scènes. On l4th August 1945 he wrote a
letter (see opposite page) to Philip Noel-
Baker at the British Foreign Office in
which he summarized the main points of a
ion the forefront of the drive to Include sci-
ence ln Unesco's activities was the British
blochemlst, slnolaglst and hlstorlan of sci-
ence Joseph Needham (b. 1900), below.
conversation the two men had had earlier
in the day and fram which the following
extracts are taken :
(...) a number of scientific men are con-
cerned that the proposed new cultural
and educationa) organization of the Un-
ited Nations should be more definitely
scientific than now appears. Culture does
Hof cover aU of science, any more than
science covers ai) of culture. To use an
Americanism, we want to put the S in
UNESCO. This, it seems to us, could be
achieved (1) by inserting"Scientific"in
the tille, (2) by having the organization
essentially tripartite, one section dealing
with education in the narrow sense, the
second with culture in the sense of the
humanities and arts, the third with sci-
ence, pure and applied (..,) Unesco
should have definite positive functions in
ait sections-in education in actually pro-
viding certain types of educationa) faciH-
ties, in culture in positive stimulation of
e. g. the arts, and in science in just such
functions as you outhned (...)
Even when the Conference which was io
establish Unesco began on 1 November
1945 the battle was not won, ln his speech
of welcome to the delegates the British
prime minister, Clement Attlee, spoke at
some length about education and culture
but said not a word about science, Never-
theless, the mushroom c/ouds over
Hiroshima and Nagasaki had made sci-
ece an c ; e/ ! f ;/ : c eeayc/ ! fAe &M ! ; Mgnce d sci ntifi r search the burning
question of the day and in her opening
speech, Ellen Wilkinson, British minister
of education and President of the Con-
ference, dec/ared :
Though Science was not included in the
original titte of thé Organization, the
British delegation will put forward a
proposa ! that it be included, so that the
titre would run"Educational, Scientific'.
and Cultural Organization". In these
days, when we are hall wondering, perhaps
apprehensivety, what the scientists will
do to us next, it is important that they
should be linked closely with the humani-
ties and should feel that they hâve a res-
ponsibility to mankind for the result of
their labours. 1 do not believe any scien-
tists will have survived the world cata-
strophe, who will still say that they are
utterly uninterested in the social implica-
tions of their discoveries.
These words of Ellen Wilkinson summed
up the anxieties felt by a majority of the
delegates and on 6 November 1945, dur-
ing the third session of the First Commis-
sion of the Conference (whose task it was
to decide on the title of the Organization,
to draft the preamble to the Constitution
and to define its objectives and principal
functions),"S"for Science was finally
incorporated into the title of the new body
henceforth to be known as The United
Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultu-
ralOrganization..
22
! I
[l.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
c
o
"0C
o.... J
ai<. >
ð
O
Q
"0
o
a :
. 2
15
: J
[l.
ô
o
õ. r:c
[l.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Early days
bu Julien Huxley
In this extract from the second volume of his auto-
biography, Memories II (1973), published here by kind
permission of George Allen and Unwin Ltd., the late Sir
Julian Huxley evokes the exciting period from his
appointment in March 1946 as successor to Sir Alfred
Zimmern as Executive Secretary of the Preparatory
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Commission to his
early days in Paris as the first Director-General of
Unesco.
Text 1 copyright. Reproduction prohibited
TEE offices of the Commission
were in Carlos Place. The first
- M. time 1 entered its portais in my
new capacity, 1 was very nervous, as if 1
were both a Headmaster and a boy enter-
ing school for the first time. However,
Mrs Brunauer (l) knew the ropes and 1
soon found my feet in this strange job.
Once 1 had settled down, 1 feint that 1
should try to clarify my own ideas about
the ro ! e ofthe Organization. So 1 took a
fortnight off and went once more to stay
with Ronald Lockley (with whom 1 had
made the film The Private Life of the
Cannent on an island off the Pem-
brokeshire coast) ; he was now occupying
a farm on Dinas Head, also in Pem-
brokeshire. There, in the intervals of
walks and talks, exploring the promon-
tory and basking with my host in shel-
tered nooks overlooking the bird-
haunted sandstone cliffs, 1 wrote a sixty-
page pamphlet entitled Unesco, Its Pur-
pose and Its Philosophe (see page 28).
In this, besides stressing its obvious
duties in promoting cultural exchanges
and giving help to the educational sys-
tems of backward (or, as we say now,
"underdeveloped") (2) countries, 1 main-
tained that it could not rely on religious
doctrine-there was strife between diffe-
rent religions and sects-or on any of the
conf) icting académie Systems of philo-
sophy. Unesco, 1 wrote, must work in the
context of what 1 called Scientific Huma-
nism, based on the established facts of
biological adaptation and advance,
(1) Mrs. Brunauer, of the USA, had been assistant to
the previous Executive Secretary, Sir Alfred Zimmern.
(2) With changing times and circumstances these coun-
tries are now referred to as the"developing"countries.
brought about by means of Darwinian
selection, continued into the human
sphere by psycho-social pressures, and
leading to some kind of advance, even
progress, with increased human control
and conservation of the environment and
of natural forces. So far as Unesco was
concerned, the process should be guided
by humanistic ideals of mutual aid, the
spread of scientific ideas, and by cultural
interchange.
This was presented to the Commission
and was ordered to be printed as an offi-
cipal document. But one Saturday, when 1
was about to go to Oxford to look for
possible staff, 1 heard that Sir Ernest
Barker, the historian, who had been
appointed to the Commission in view of
his work on the Committee of the
League's Institute of Intellectual Co-
operation (see page 6), was to be present
at the meeting which was to discuss Un-
esco's role in philosophy. He and 1 had
previously quarrelled over my attitude to
established religion when 1 was Professor
of Zoology at King's College, London, of
which he was Principal, and 1 scented
trouble, rightly suspecting that he would
attack my pamphlet.
As an ardent churchman, he argued
forcibly against Unesco's adopting what
he called an atheist attitude disguised as
humanism, and got the members to agree
to state, when circulating my document,
that it expressed merely my personal
views, not those of the officiai Commis-
sion.
Looking back, 1 think he was right.
Though Unesco has in fact pursued
humanistic aims, it would have been un-
fortunate to lay down any doctrine as a
basis for its work. Further, a purely
. humanist tone would have antagonized
the wodd's major religious groups (...)
Meanwhile, there was the difficult
business of recruiting staff : this 1 had to
begin, whether or not 1 was eventually
appointed Director-General. Some 1
appointed directly, like Joseph
Needham, the eminent Cambridge
biochemist, who was also interested in
Chinese culture and in the history of sci-
ence ; and John Bowers, who was recom-
mended to me by a war-time colleague
for his first-hand experience of an under-
developed country's basic needs.
One virtually appointed himself-with
excellent results. 1 had to find someone to
take charge of the Libraries section.
Desmond Bernât had recommended an
English woman librarian, but 1 was not
sure of her competence, and asked Ed-
ward Carter, my Hampstead neighbour
(and Librarian of the Royal Institute of
British Architects), for advice. His re-
sponse was simple-"Why not me ?" (..,)
Edward was excellent, especially in
getting Unesco to set up good modern
libraries in underdeveloped countries.
Later, 1 was to see the one in southern
Nigeria, and be delighted to find that it
was not only housed in a fine building (as
was to be expected from a man interested
in architecture), but also well-stocked,
and with many readers in its spacious
rooms.
Others were recommended to me by
friends. Thus Sir Kenneth Clark recom-
mended the young Australian, Peter Bel-
lew, as head of the Fine Arts section (.,,)
Still others were wished on me by their
Governments. While the Preparatory
Commission was still in London, Julien
Cain the charming and learned head of
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
the Bibliothèque Nationale in Paris,
came over with a young man called Jean
Thomas, who was officially recom-
mended by the French authorities as my
Deputy. It was understood that, in return
for waiving the right to nominate the top
man, France should be the home of the
Organization and one of its two deputy
Director-Generals should be a French-
man. Thomas and 1 got on excellently
throughout my term of office, while
Julien Cain became an influential mem-
ber of the Executive Board. He and his
gifted wife (she had once acted as Paul
Valéry's secretary) became close friends
of Juliette (3) and myself,
Professor Pierre Auger was also re-
commended by the French, for a post in
the Science Department. He was an ex-
cellent physicist, balancing the bio-
logically competent Needham, and even-
tually succeeded him as Head of the
Department.
Alva, sociologist wife of the celebrated
Swedish economist Gunnar Myrdal, took
charge of the Social Sciences Division,
and 1 myself asked John Grierson, the
pioneer of documentary films, to look
after the Cinema section of the Arts De-
partment. Flora McGlade (always known
as Mac) was already in my office, having
been Zimmern's assistant on the Prepara-
tory Commission. She stayed as one of
my secretaries aH through my time at
Unesco. 1 also kept Friedl Rothschild,
who had worked for me at P. E. P., (4) but
soon had to add others to my personal
staff : Mrs Paulette Matthews, as a second
The British sclentlst, p/ !//osopherand edu-
cator Julien Huxley (18871975) wus Un-
esco's flrst Dlrector-General (1946-1948).
secretary to deal with the flood of officiai
correspondence ; and Claude Berkeley,
cousin of the composer of the same name,
as my personal assistant, constantly
called on to deal with complaints, and to
prepare for the visits and travels 1 had to
undertake.
Alfred Métraux took charge of most of
the work in Anthropology and Sociology,
while Guy, his younger brother, after
working in various sections, later became
the very efficient Secretary of the Com-
mission dealing with Unesco's History of
Mankind,
Emilio Arenales, nominated by Guate-
mala, was very useful in dealing with
Latin American countries in general ;
with Manolo Jiménez for Mexican affairs
and for dealing with internai procedure.
Then there was Dr Irina Zhukova,
Russian by birth, who worked in the Phy-
siological section of the Science Depart-
ment, with special responsibility for
liaison with WHO, the World Health
Organization (.,,)
So 1 could run on. 1 secured another
Frenchman, Michel Montagnier, to deal
with arrangements for Conferences,
which he did with great efficiency ; a
Swiss, André de Blonay, to cope with the
affairs of national delegates, especially
during General Conferences ; while a
Chinese Professor, Dr Kuo, was made
Head of the Division of Education.
Later in the year an American, Walter
Laves, was nominated by the USA to
deal with questions of internat adminis-
tration. These, unfortunately, often 
25
(3) Joliette Huxley, née Baillot, Julian Huxley's wife.
('1) Political and économie Planning, a Bhtish indepen-
dent cross-party opinion group.
i: J
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
 caused trouble-there were jealousies
between different Divisions-and once, 1
remember, 1 had to intervene between
one Division and the staff responsible for
preparing Unesco's budget. The Division
Head thought that the Budget men
should corne to his office, while they
expected that everyone, even Assistant
Director-Generals, should corne to them
at their request. 1 eut the Gordian knot by
inviting both parties to rneet in my own
office.
But much more taxing than such
squabbles was establishing the pro-
gramme for the coming year. This,
together with an estimate of its cost, had
to be laid before the next General Con-
ference, which could in theory (and
sometimes did in practice) eut out some
item, refuse to grant necessary finance,
or even press for new items to be
included.
This task was made more difficult by an
anomaly in the relations between the Ex-
ecutive Board and the Director-General.
Under the original constitution, the
Board was given a hand in framing the
programme, in consultation, of course,
with the Director-General. This led to so
many disagreements, and such waste of
time, that in 1948 the arrangement was
altered : from then on, the Director-
General had sole responsibility for pre-
paring the Programme, while the Board
could only offer comment or criticism.
This is merely one example of the way
in which everything had to be impro-
vised, and arrangements made to patch
up the differences of interest between
various Divisions, the Director-General
and the Board. These were perhaps in-
evitable in a new organization-indeed a
new kind of organization, for its scope
was very much wider than that of the
original League's Institute of Intellectual
Co-operation. At any rate, they gave me
plenty of headaches during my term of
office (..,)
Headaches, yes, but also interest, and
indeed excitement-the excitement of
being in charge of a vast new internation-
al experiment, a stimulus which kept me
going through the gruelling two and a half
years of my tenure of office.
Once 1 started work at Unesco's head-
quarters in Paris, 1 had to deal with the
Executive Board over aU major prob-
temps. In 1947, the Board numbered only
eighteen members. These were chosen
from the delegates of member-states, al-
ways one from the UK, France and the
USA (and a Soviet delegate when the
USSR joined Unesco), one from the
country where the next conference was to
be held, and representatives of other
countries to make up its number.
In 1947, it included some very disting-
uished men-John Maud (latter Lord
Redcliffe-Maud) from Britain, Archibald
MacLeish from the USA, Pierre Auger
(soon to became head of Unesco's Natu-
rat Sciences Division), Dr. Photiades
from Greece, Professor Paulo E. de Ber-
rêdo Carneiro (later Chairman of the In-
ternational Commission for a History of
the Scientific and Cultural Development
of Mankind), Sir Sarvepalli Radhakrish-
nan, statesman and philosopher from
India, Ronald Walker from Australia,
etc. (..,)
The original principle was that Board
members should be men distinguished in
education, the sciences and the arts, from
different regions, but voting as indi-
viduals, not as representing their own
country. It was a fine idea, but it did not
work out. Board members were almost
always distinguished, but they usually
voted in favour of measures approved by
their Governments. So eventually they
became representatives of their own
countries, as tell as specialists in some
field of Unesco's work.
Another difficulty arose over Unesco's
budget. The Board was originally em-
powered to propose a budget sufficient to
carry out the programme submitted to
each Gênera ! Conférence. This led to
many squabbles, members of the Board
too often making proposais that would
benefit mainly their own country or re-
gion. They had the duty of consulting the
Director-General, but frequently the
consultation was mere) y formai.
This system was quite iDogicat, and
during my term of office the Director-
General became responsible both for the
details of the programme, and for pre-
senting the budget estimate. Of course,
he had to consult the Board and take into
account any comments or objections they
might make, but the unworkable system
of divided authority was scrapped (.,,)
It had been laid down by the London
Conference (S) that Unesco could seek
help in technical matters from non-
governmental International Agencies
concerned with subjects within Unesco's
purview ; and, if necessary, aid in the
creation of new ones. It was on
Needham's advice that ICSU, the Inter-
national Council of Scientific Unions, be-
came the first of such bodies to be
attached to Unesco. We provided it with
rooms in Unesco's headquarters in Paris,
and salaries for its staff : previously, the
Cambridge professor who was its secret-
ary-and sole executive-had to dictate
aH its correspondence in his College
rooms !
The ICSU gave Unesco much valuable
advice--on the peaceful uses of atomic
energy, on regional centres for scientific
co-operation and exchange of know-
ledge, on the calling of international sci-
entific congresses, and on liaison with
other International Agencies concerned
with science, such as FAO for agricul-
tural science and applied ecology, and
WHO for medicine, physiology and so-
cial we) !-being.
(5) United Nations Conference for the Establishment
of an Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization,
London. 1 to 16 November, 1945.
Soon after, 1 had a surprise visit from a
wealthy American art-lover, a trustee of
the Buffalo Art Gallery, and agreed to
recommend that an International Com-
mission on Museums should be attached
to the cultural section of Unesco. Thanks
to its advice (and that of other interna-
tional bodies concerned with the arts),
Unesco has done valuable work since
then, both in giving financial aid to gal-
leries and museums, and also in pub-
lishing and distributing excellent repro-
ductions of little-known paintings, sculp-
tures and architectural achievements
from various countries, especially repro-
ductions which could be used in schoo) s.
In the hot summer of 1947, we also set
up an International Theatre Institute (for
drama, opera, films and ballet) at the
insistence of Jack Priestley, an American
called Kuntz and John Grierson. The
committee responsible for this comprised
many well-known names in dramatic
circles, such as the French producer and
actor Jean-Louis Barrault, Sir Tyrone
Guthrie from England, and Lillian Hell-
man from the USA (...)
The Commission moved to Paris in late
November, 1946, and we and other dele-
gates had our offices in the former Hotel
Majestic, where the Peace Conference
was held after the First World War. Dur-
ing the Second World War, it was com-
mandeered by the Germans, and my offi-
cipal room had the"distinction"of having
been the office of the notorious Nazi
Commandant of Paris. Thus my occupan-
cy visibly symbolized the transition from
war and racialism to peace and cultural
co-operation.
The full Executive Board was now in
daily session, discussing not only Un-
esco's terms of reference and its immedi-
ate activities, but also whom to nominate
as Director-General.
Archibald MacLeish, the distinguished
American writer and poet, who was also
Librarian of Congress, had written a bril-
liant preamble to Unesco's Constitution,
in which he had stressed Unesco's role in
promoting Peace-"Peace through Edu-
cation, Peace through Science, Peace
through Culture, Peace everywhere in
the hearts of men"-a starry-eyed hope
rather than a guide to practica ! action.
The USA wanted him as Director-
General, but he declined, saying he could
not spare the time from his real work in
literature. The British delegate, Sir John
Maud, put forward my name, and there
were one or two other candidates (...)
Eventually John Maud came to tell me
that 1 had been duly elected, but for two
years only, in place of the constitutional
five (..,)
Looking back today, 1 am grateful for
having been appointed, but also grateful
that 1 did not have to serve for five years :
it would have been too geat a strain (in-
deed one later Director-General found
the job too much for him and had to
resign in the middle of his term). N
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Can we educate for world
peace ?
Extracts from the opening remarks by Archibald MacLeish
during a radio discussion with Dr. F. L. Schlagle, President of
the U. S. National Education Association, Mr. HerbertEmmer-
ich, Director of the Public Administration Clearing H ouse, and
Dr. Francis Bacon, member of the Educational Policies Com-
mission of the National Education Association, broadcast on 12
December 1945, one month after the establishment of Unesco.
"Of course we can educate for world peace.
l'd be willing to go a great deal farther than
that, l'd be willing, for my own part, to say
that there is no possible way of getting
world peace except through éducation.
Which means education of the peoples of
the worid. AU you can do by arrangements
between governments is to remove the
causes of disagreement which may become,
in time, causes ofwar. But peace, as we are
ail beginning to realize, is something a great
deal more than the absence of war. Peace is
positive and not negative. Peace is a way of
living together which excludes war, rather
than a period without war in which peoples
try to live together.
"But the difficulty with this kind of dis-
cussion is not the answers. The difficulty is
the questions. And the trouble with the
questions is that they are put-have to be
put-in words which have lost their fresh-
ness and their reality of meaning (,..)
"The real problem (,.,) is one that goes a
lot deeper. It has to do with the effect on the
human mind of words tike'international
understanding'and'éducation'and'cul-
ture' (..,)
"Before we can talk intelligently and
meaningfully, therefore, about questions
like education for peace, or the creation of
international understanding, we have got to
find the abrasives which will scrape these
words down to their living meanings again.
For some reason which 1 have never been
able to understand, people are quite willing
to believe that anything you caU'écono-
mies'is real and that you call'politics'is
US poet and Librarian of Congress Archi-
bald MacLeish (1892-1982) was Chairman
of the Committee which drafted the Pre-
amble to Unesco's Constitution.
exciting, but that anything you refer to
under the general words which describe the
life of the human mind is necessarily dull
and stale and unrealistic and fuzzy (..,),
"Actually, in the world we live in, which
is very different from the world we think we
live in, the relations of peoples to each
other in terms of the things they think and
the things they believe and the things they
hope, in terms, that is to say, of their mental
processes, of the things that distinguish
them as men, are far more vivid-make, to
be brief, far more sense than the economic
and political arrangements between gov-
ernments which capture the front pages of
our minds as weU as of our newspapers (,.,)
"I am not belittling the tremendous im-
portance of economic solutions for econo-
mie difficulties and political cures for poli-
tical mistakes. 1 am saying that thèse things,
important as they are, are far less important
than the creation of a world of words and
images and mutual knowledge within whieh
people may talk to each other.
"What we tried to do in London was to
invent an international instrument which
could help us aU to create that world by the
use of aU the channels of communication-
education and radio, press and scholarship,
motion pictures and music, journalism in ail
its forms and living, enduring arts. If the
question you are discussing is the question
whether our international instrument will
work, 1 am going to ask my cotleagues
Emmerich and Schlagle to put me down as
voting Yens."
27
M i
IQ-'
S.
I
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The application of science
and art
*W T NESCO cannot be highbrow and
confine itself solely to"pure"sci-
ence, and"fine"art. It cannot do
so, because it must concern itself with the
whole of humanity, not only with the spe-
cialists, the highly educated élite, or the
privileged few, and is expressly charged
with advancing the ideals of equality of
educational opportunity ; and this is not
possible if Unesco's concern with science
and art is confined to the encouragement of
the scientist and the artist and to the learned
study of their achievements. It cannot do so
for another reason-because its Constitu-
tion lays upon it the duty of advancing the
common welfare of mankind. For the
advancement of human welfare depends in
the main upon the right application of sci-
ence-physical, biological, psychological
and social-and also, in the sphere of emo-
tional and spiritual satisfactions, upon the
application of the arts.
Unesco must therefore concern itself
with the widest extension and the fullest
application both of the sciences and of the
arts. It has, of course, neither the right nor
the wish to deal with the detailed problems
of nutrition and agriculture, medicine and
health, to however great an extent they
depend on the applications of science,
since, to cope with them, other Agencies of
the United Nations have been created.
With the scientific bases of these questions,
however, it must concern itself and must
therefore establish a proper liaison, with
clear delimitation of functions, between it-
self and the FAO [Food and Agriculture
Organization of the United Nations] and
the World Health Organization. The same
holds for those applications of the sciences
which, because of their importance for
labour welfare, fall to be dealt with by the
ILO [International Labour Organisation],
and of those which, because of their military
importance, fall within the province of the
Atomic Energy Commission of the Security
Council.
Further, it is clear that practical problems
of economics and of social structure and
welfare, in so far as they are to be dealt with
by an international body, must be the con-
cern of the Economie and Social Council ;
while certain sectors of social anthropology,
such as culture-contact between more and
less advanced cultures (which include prob-
lems not only of applied science but also of
art and literature and of education), will be
the primary concern of the Trusteeship
Council and of the section of the Economie
and Social Council dealing with non-self-
governing peoples.
This overlap, however, far from de-
barring Unesco from concerning itself with
the applications of the sciences and the arts
in general, makes it aH the more imperative
that it should do so, and should do so in a
particular way. These other Agencies and
organs ofthe United Nations which we have
mentioned are concerned with particular
fields or problems some larger, some more
speciaHzed. Unesco alone is charged with
the comprehensive task of studying and
promoting al) the higher activities of man
and their applications, and of doing so in a
co-ordinated way, subject to a definite set
of purposes.
What Unesco can do in this vast sphere of
the practical application of creative know-
ledge and art is, accordingly, to study the
problems in correlation, to endeavour to
promote the best methods of translating
theory into practice, and to give guidance as
to right application. The terms best and
right are not used merely in the technical
sense of most immediately efficient, but as
definitely implying value-judgement. It is
possible to exploit new agricultural
methods in a way that is in the long run
technically disastrous to agriculture itself,
by causing soil exhaustion or erosion, but it
is also possible to do so in a way which is
technically sound but socially wrong-by
causing over-population, for instance, or by
ruining natural beauty or causing the ex-
tinction of striking or interesting species of
animais and plants, or by creating a depress-
ed agricultural class with unduly low stan-
dards of living. Similarly, it is possible to
devote too much attention to exploiting the
discoveries of mechanical, physical and che-
mical science, to the grave detriment of
interest in the arts and appreciation of the
value of beauty in everyday life and of
artistic creation as a human activity ; while a
contrary effect is also ait too readily pos-
sible, when religious prejudice or cultural
obscurantism puts obstacles in the way of
scientific research and new knowledge, or
their beneficent applications.
Again, there are fields with which other
Agencies are not expressly or immediately
concerned. No other United Nations Agen-
cy deals with the important question of
seeing that the arts are properly and fully
applied, or that provision is made for satis-
fying man's need for aesthetic enjoyment,
whether of scenery and natural beauty, of
the everyday furniture of life, of buildings
and cities, or of great works of art and music
and Hterature. Nor is any other Agency
concerning itself with such important ap-
plications of the sciences as the disciplinirig
of the mind to produce so-called mystical
experience and other high degrees of spir-
itual satisfaction ; or with the application of
psychology to the technique of government,
or to preventing the abuse or the exploita-
tion of democracy.
Thus in this general field Unesco should
pursue three main objectives. First, it
should discover what applications of science
and art are not being considered by other
United Nations organizations, and then
pick out from among them those it thinks
most important to promote or to study.
Secondly, it should study the practical ap-
plications of science and art as a particular
social problem, to discover what are the
reasons which prevent, frustrate or distort
them, what are the effects of undue speed or
undue delay. Such a study should be of
considerable help in promoting the technic-
al efficiency of this process-a problem
which will become steadily more pressing
with the increase of scientific knowledge
and of social comptexity. And the third
objective, the most difficult though perhaps
also the most important, is to relate the
applications of science and art to each other
and to a general scale of values, so as to
secure a proper amount and rate of applica-
tion in each fietd. If such a task were satis-
factorily carried out, and if its findings were
acted upon, this would constitute one of the
most important contributions towards dis-
covering and pursuing the desirable direc-
tion of human evolution-in other words,
true human wetfare. t
Julian Huxley
Extract from Unesco Its Purpose and its Philo-
sophy. This document was written by Julian Hux-
ley during a fortnight's holiday taken in 1946
shortly after his appointment as Secretary-
General of the Prepara tory Commission.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
From premises in Grosvenor Square and
Be/grave Square in London, Unesco
moved to the Hote/Majestic in Paris in
1946. Photo shows a sa/on at the Majestic
transformed into a conference room.
Finding a home for Unesco
D URING 1945, the question
arose of where the proposed
new Organization was to be
situated. A number of countries had ex-
pressed their desire to provide a home for
the Organization, but France, which still
housed the Internationat Institute of In-
tellectual Co-operation (IIIC, see page
6), an offshoot of the former League of
Nations, pressed her daim with particu-
) ar forcefulness.
The French representatives in London
seem to have interpreted a certain rets-
cence about Paris as the location of the
Organization on the part of the British
Government as a desire to see Unesco
situated in London. This, however, was
far from being the case.
In common with many other countries,
Britain was concerned about the French
desire to prolong the life of the IIIC,
which the French believed should pro-
vide the Secretariat for Unesco. Most
other governments were anxious to make
a complete break with the institutions of
the old League of Nations. When this was
accepted by the French Government, the
way was clear for Paris to become the
home of Unesco headquarters. The docu-
ments reproduced below illustrate the
final stages in the process which led to
agrément on Paris as the seat of Unesco.
Extract from a Foreign Office memoran-
dum dated 30 June 1945,
(...) 1 doubt very much whether we shaH
wish to have an organization permanently
on our hands in London, and in these
circumstances it seems to me important
that we should assure the French that
these plans (*) are in no way designed to
rush Allied nations into decisions which
do not take proper account of French
interests (...)
(') The plans rcfcrrcd to werc for the convening in
London of thé Conférence which was to establish
Unesco.
29
o"N'"
Gc :
7
o
õ
&1
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
FINDING A HOME FOR UNESCO
Letter fram Léon Blum, chief French de-
legate to the Conference for the Establish-
ment of an Educational and Cultural
Organization (London 1 to 16 November
1945), to Clement Attlee, prime minister
of the United Kingdom,
Claridge's
Brook Street, W. l.
Sunday 4 November
My dear friend,
You will remember that, last Wednes-
day, when ï arrived at Downing Street, 1
had just left our friend Ellen Wilkinson.
You will no doubt also recall that with
regard to a subject close to our hearts in
France-thé location in Paris ofthe future
educational and cultural organization-
she had assured me that we should not
lack British support, unless there should
be opposition on the part of the United
States. 1 spoke about this in the most frank
and open manner with the head of the
American Delegation, Mr. Archibald
MacLeish, and have, in my turn, been
able to assure Ellen Wilkinson that the
opposition in principle that she seemed to
fear does not exist. The American Gov-
ernment has taken no advance décision.
The Delegation has its hands free and, in
Mr. MacLeish's opinion the French re-
quest would be heard sympathetically by
his colleagues.
Please forgive me for keeping you
posted about this matter, apparently
minor, yet in reality rather important.
Your faithful friend,
Léon Blum
Perhaps ï shall be fortunate enough to see
you again for a moment or two before you
leave. ï am taking the liberty of sending
you a copy in French of a book 1 wrote in
one of the first of my prisons, the English
translation of which is now being com-
pleted by William Pickles.
Confidential telegram sent on 10 Novem-
ber 1945 by the British Foreign Office in-
forming the French authorities that their
offer to pro vide Unesco with a seat in Paris
had been accepted.
Reply fram Mr, Attlee to M, Léon Blum,
10, Downing Street,
Whitehall.
7th November, 1945
My dear friend,
Thank you for your letter of Novem-
ber 4th. As you know, the British attitude
to the question of the siting of the Educa-
tional and Cultural Organization is at pre-
sent under consideration ; and 1 hope my
colleagues will be able to let you know our
views shortly.
Thank you also for sending me a copy
of your book"A l'Echelle Humaine". 1
shall always value it and the friendly in-
scription which you have written in it.
It was a great pleasure to meet you
again after a) i thèse years.
Yours ever,
C. R. Attlee
Extract from the Final Act of the United
Nations Conference for the Establishment
of an Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organisation.
After consideration of these drafts and
proposais the Conference drew up a Con-
stitution establishing an Educational, Sci-
entific and Cultural Organization and an
Instrument establishing a Preparatory
Educational, Seientific and Cultural
Commission. The Conference also
adopted the following Resolution :
"The seat of the United Nations Educa-
tional, Scientifie and Cultural Organiza-
tion shall be in Paris.
"This Resolution shall not in any way
affect the right of the General Conference
to take décisions in regard to this matter
by a two-thirds majority."
30
C
o
DC
O
Jc :
o... J
""
: ;
o
Q
8
"
CI :
. 
: c
=>
[l.
Q
o
õ. r:c
[l.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
-
1
: ;,
: i
3
Script of a radio broadcast early in 1946
du ring which Léon Blum presented ta the
French people the new organization which
had just been created in London. As head
of the French delegation ta the Conference
which established Unesco, Léon Blum had
successfully argued that the seat of
Unesco should be in Paris.
ion 1936 the French writer and socialist
leader Léon Blum (1872-1950) became pre-
mier of the first Popular Front go vemmen
supported by a coalition of parties of the
loft which broke up in 1938, the year in
which this photo was taken, A supporter of
a firm policy against Hitler, Léon Blum was
arrested in September 1940 and while in
prison wrote a book, A l'Echelle Humaine
(For Ali Mankind), in which he expounded
his humanist conception of socialise and
urged his party to resist. Deporfed'fo
Dachau and then Buchenwald in 1943, he
was liberated in 1945, ln 1946 he formed an
all-socialist government which brought in
the institutions of the Fourth Republic,
Extract fÚJlI1 Il radio broadcast made bv
/1'1. LéO ! 1 Blum carlv i ! 1 1946.
U-NES-CO
Do not forget these three exotic-sounding
syllabes.
L-NES-CO-perhaps you have already
heard them somewhere. You will certain-
ty hear them repeated often in the future.
These three exotic-sounding syllables are,
as you have already guessed, made up of
the initiais of a rather long name.
The United Nations Educational, Scien-
tific and Cultural Organization,
Unesco is one of the sections, one of the
departments of the International Com-
munity, founded by the United Nations in
the midst of war, at Dumbarton Oaks and
at San Francisco.
What is of particular interest to aIl
citizens of France is the tocation and the
purpose of Unesco.
ifs headquarters ?
During the Conference for the estab-
lishment of Unesco which was held in
London at the end of last year, the French
Delegation managed to ensure that its
headquarters woutd be s'ted ir paris. khis
decision did not make a great impact at
the time, and 1 regret this because it was
an important décision. The representa-
tives of over 40 nations, gathered together
from every continent, agreed in the opin-
ion that the Paris of the Liberation re-
mained the natura ! centre ofinternationat
culture and spirituality. The Preparatory
Commission is still in London, but the
installation of Unesco in Paris will begin
next autumn. The Hotel Majestic, made
available by the Government of the Re-
public, will be Unesco's provisional head-
quarters.
lis purpose
The London Conference defined Un-
esco's purpose at the highest spiritual
plane. The United Nations, determined to
create and organize a peacefu ! wortd, are
aware that the foundations of Peace are as
much psychica), sentimental, and spir-
itual, as poiitica !, économie and social.
The spirit of Peace is one of the conditions,
one of the eiements of Peace. thé spirit of
Pence pre-supposes mutual knowledge
and understanding between peoples ; it
implies the co-operation and solidarity of
ail States in the wide fields of éducation,
ScientijÏc knowledge, and General culture
(H.).
en
ce ;
(L
ro
i5
"
E
i5
w
', ;  :)
"Nro
o
-"
c
"
0 :
o
: g
[l.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Foundations
32
1
2
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Inaugurated on 3 November 1958, Unesco
House was built on a site previously occu-
pied by a cavalry barracks to the rear of the
Ecole Militaire, on a three-hectare site
made available by the French Govern-
ment. Photos 1 and 2 show the progres-
sive demolition of the last remaining bar-
rack buildings, top right hand corner of
site, and early stages in the construction
of Unesco's new home. Plans for the new
buildings were prepared by three great
contemporary architects : Marcel Breuer
(United States), Pier Luigi Nervi (ltaly) and
Bernard Zehrfuss (France), and approved
byan international panel whose members
included Le Corbusier (Charles-Edouard
Jeanneret) and Walter Gropius, the foun-
der of the famous Bauhaus school of de-
sign, art and architectura. Photos 3 and 4
show the Conference building during
construction. This fine structure has fluted
walls of unequal height which slope
outwards, supporting the extremities of
the roofing. This sloping roonng, set on
two asymmetricallevefs, rests at its centre
on a row of six concrete pillars. Photo 5,
over a hundred tons of concrete were
poured in the construction of the soaring
portico which marks the entrance on the
southwest-facing façade of Unesco head-
quarters and which has been described as
"a triumph of imaginative engineering".
Photos 1, 2 and 3. R. Szczesnowicz, Unesco
Photo 4. Unesco
Photo 5. &commat; G. Bozelec
33
3 4
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Unesco officially became fully operational
on 4 November 1946, when Greece be-
came the twentieth State to deposit the
instrument of ratification at the Foreign
Office in London. It was on this date, the
fortieth anniversary of which will be
commemorated by the Unesco Courier
next year, that a great ideal became a prac-
tical reality, The First General Conference
of Unesco opened in Paris on 20 Novem-
ber. Above, the inaugural session of the
Conference which was held in one of the
great amphitheatres of the Sorbonne.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office :
Unesco. 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year : 68 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France) : 120 French francs. Binder for a year's is ues :
52 FF
The UNESCO COURIER IS published monthly.
individuai rticles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads ; ; Reprinted tram the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannat be re urned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessahty represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun-
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply officiai
endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and
ormicrofiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7PiacedeFontenoy. 75700
Parts :(2) University Microfilms (Xerox) Ann Arbor. Michigan
48100. U. S. A . (3) N. C. R. Microcard Edition. Indlan Head. Inc.
111West40thStreet. NewYork. US. A. : (4) Bell and Howell
Co., Old Mansfieid Road. Wooster. Ohio 44691. U. S. A
Assistant Editor-in-chief : Olga Rödel
Managing Editor : Gillian Whitcomb
Editors :
English : Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Roy Malkin
French : Alain Lévéque (Paris)
Neda es Khazen
Spanish : Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian : Nikolal Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic : Sayed Osman (Paris)
German : Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese Selichiro Ko]ima (Tokyo)
Italian Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi : Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil : M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew : Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian : Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch : Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese : Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish : Mefra IIgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu : Hakim Mohammed Saïd (Karachi)
Catalan : Joan Carreras 1 Mart (Barcelona)
Malaysian : Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean : Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili : Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, S ! ovene : Vito-
mir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese : Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian :Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek : Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala : S. J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish : Marjatta Oksanen Helsinki)
Swedish : Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque : GurutzLarranaga (San Sebastian)
Thai : Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Braille : Frederick Potter (Paris)
Research : Christiane Boucher
Illustrations : Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Georges Servat
Promotion : Fernando Amsa
Special projects : Peggy Julien
Aloi correspondence should be addressed 10 the Edilor-
In-Chlet ln Paris
BRODARD GRAPHIOUE. COULOMMIERS Depot legal C1-Octobre 1985-IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Pnnted ln France)
34 PHOTOCOMPOSITION Ateliers de 1 Unesco. MONTAGE M ! croCompo'17 rue Beranger-75003 PansPHOTOGRA VURE Dawant-13 rue des Arquebusiers-75003 PARIS.
Photo Unesco/Eclair Mondial
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just Published
In the industrially developed world
many of today's most urgent problems,
such as environmental pollution,
nudear power, and unemployment
caused by technological innovation, lie
on the frontiers between science and
technology. By contrast, Third World
countries are faced with the problem of
too few scientists, too little research,
and insufficient funds for technological
development. In Science and
Technology in World Development,
Robin Clarke examines the
relationships between science,
technology and society in both the
developed and the developing
countries. He believes that a global
view is essential because of the close
links that aid and trade have forged
between rich and poor countries. Only
then can we see how research has
ignored key issues for Third World
development, and concentrated on
matters relevant only to the rich and
priviteged.
PubHshed by the Oxford University Press in
association with Unesco.
Sold throughout the world by the Oxford
University Press
PaperbackjE4. 95 in UK (Also available in
hardback)
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below ; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58AGipps Street, Co'iing-
wood Victoria 3066 : Publications : Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd
P. O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals : Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P. O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent :United Nations Association f Australia, P. O. Box175,
5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AU5TRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A1011. ViennaBAHAMAS. NassauStationersLtd. PO Box
N-3138. Nassau BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R. K. MissionRd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3.-BARBADOS. University of the West fndies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P. O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM."Unesco Courier"Dutch edition ly :N. V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-1 8, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition a d general Unesco publications
agent :Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 8russes, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P. O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street. Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H lM7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P. O Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS."MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P. O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLQVAKIA.-S. N. T. L., Spalena 51-11302, Prague
1 ; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O. B. 790-111-27 Prague 1 (Permanent
dispJay) ; Zahranicni l teratura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1 For
Siovakia only :Alla Verlag.-Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6, 893
31 Bratislava-CSSR. OENMARK. Munksgaard Export OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K
EGYPT (AftAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency forUnesco, P. O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF 00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7 place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Pans. C. C. P. 2598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig orfrom Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G. D. R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANT. For the Unesco Courier {German.
EngHsh, French and Spanish éditions) : Mr. H. Bau, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D 5300 Bonn 3.For
other Unesco publications : Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scienttfic maps only :Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P. O.
Box195, Accra ;Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P. O  Box 7869,
Accra ;The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra ;The University
Bookshop of Capte Coast ;The University Bookshop ouf Legon,
P. O. Box 1, Legon. GREAT BRtTA) N. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial M nsion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Infirmation Services, Publication C tre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura. Bushimport ABT, P. O. B.149-
H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELANO. Snaebj6rn Jonsson & Co.,
H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038 ; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13 ; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2 ;
59 41/1 BashirBagh. Hyderabad 500001 IAPI ;80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road. Bangalore-560001 ; 3-5. 820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016 ; Scindia House, New Delhi ;
Publication Unit, Ministry ofEducation and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New De ! h ! 110001
INDONESIA. Bhratara Pubtishers and Bookse !'ers. 29 Je. toto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta ;Indira P. T., JI Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P. O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran ;Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco-1188 Enghlab As.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158, P. O. Box 11365-4498,
Teheran. RAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B. C.
Bookstore Ltd., P. O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. licosa (libreria Commissionaria S nsoni, S. p. A. J
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552,50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P. O. Box 366, 101
Water. Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 113. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P. O. Box 30571, Nairobi ; Africa Book Services Ltd.,
Quran House, Mfangano Street, P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P. O. Box
Central 64, Seou). KUWA) T. Thé Kuwa't Bookshop Co., Ltd,
POB 2942, Kuwait ;for the Unesco Courier ; Farafa !) a Press
Agency, P. O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P. O. Mazenod. Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P. O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan Trust Reg. P. O. B. 5 9494 Schaan.
UBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P. O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Bruck,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service,
Head Office. P O. Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3.MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-11 MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, VaHetta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library. 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B. V., Joan Muyskenweg.
22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P. O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N. A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at : Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland ;130, Oxford Terrace. P O. Box 1721 Christchurch :
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton ; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street. Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife ;The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P. O. 286 ; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka ;The University Bookshop of Lagos :The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P. O. B. 1177 Sentrum. Oslo 1, Narvesen A/S ; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P. O. B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6 ; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindern, Os ! o 3
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-I-azam, P, O
Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional
Office for Book development in Asia and the Opacifie, 39 Delhi
Housing Society, P. O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES.
National Book Store, Inc. 701, Rizal Avenue, Manila 0, 404.
POLAND. Orpan Import, Palac Kultury 1 Nauki, Warsaw ; Ars
Polona : Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No, 7. 00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal. rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, PO. Box
48, Mahé ; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P. O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra
Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road,
Singapore 2261 SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBUC. Modem
Book Shop and General, P. O. Box 951, Mogadiscio, SOUTH
AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single copies only :Central
News agency, P. O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P. O. B.
244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P. O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. A publications A/B. C. E. Fr ! tzesKung !.
'Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
'Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier : Svenska FN Förbundet.
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 5-104 65, Stockholm ; Wennergren
Williams, Box 30004. 5. 104, 25 Stockholm : Esselte
Tidskriftscent-ralen. Gamla Brog tan26, Box 62-101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Ali publications : Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. L brairie Pavot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, C. C. P. 12. 236. Librairies Pavot also in Lausanne. Basie,
Berne. Vevey, Montreux, Neufchâtel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P. O. B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THA) LAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40 42 Charoen Krung Road.
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P. O. Box 402 ; Bangkok :Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok ;Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National CommisSÎon for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W. I. TURKEY. Haset KitR : ; :' : : vi A. S.,
Istiklâl Caddesi, NO 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P. O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H. M. Stationery Office, H. M. S. O., P. O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT. and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol ; for
scientific maps only :McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC 1 X 9 OS. UNITED STATES : Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N. Y. 10017. Orders for books &
Periodicals : P. O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor, MI 48106. U. S. S. R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121200. YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, P. O. Box 4227, Aden. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mtadost. N'ca 30/11. Zagreb ;Cankarjeva Z lozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana : Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd.. P, O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
