<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066617eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^^^ ^^^ ^^B^^^^M SEPTEMBER 1985 - 7 French francs ^B
TheCourier
MIGRANTS
Between two worlds
^BoK^^D^* BW "%" ' i vJttftJaBMga^MBfcBW^SjroSEsÉRSJ^B^
9BÜF V . . ?^MK^8BJeaag^i^^
^hl bW " '-'lâM ^Kl
I.; 3§ 9
.'jSflSFk. JSf/T'- m ¿JBB^B^B^B^BB bv
'?* B^BJT^^^^^Pjt^^^^^^B^BBW ¿3^sy
1
^^^~
1
^^L
1
1
[
B^B^BTBBt=£v^:^M B^B k9
j Wk
1 Bb
#fe^^""Ä'l^ jB-.
I H
r'^VV"'* _¿^bMb1Sbh ^^^bzb^b^b^bhB^^^b^b^bh B
í5¿7 K/ rXy*<-ijn*h.Jíiírt M;^
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live
Photo © G. Hyvert, Paris
38 Haiti
The restoration of Sans Souci
Built in the early 19th century by Henri
Christophe (1767-1820), who in 1811 pro¬
claimed himself sovereign ruler of the king¬
dom of Haiti, the imposing palace of Sans
Souci is one of the earliest symbols of
Haitian independence. The palace, sur¬
rounded by gardens which covered
8 hectares at the height of their splendour,
was pillaged after Christophe's death, and
later seriously damaged in an earthquake.
In 1973 Haiti launched an emergency pro¬
gramme to halt the deterioration threaten¬
ing Sans Souci and other parts of its cultural
heritage and to create a national
historic park. Today Unesco is co-operat¬
ing with the Haitian Government on a proj¬
ect, financed by the United Nations Devel¬
opment Programme, to preserve Sans
Souci, the Citadel Laferrière, which was
built to protect Haiti against attack by
colonial forces, and Les Ramiers, a for¬
tification above the citadel. Above, recon¬
struction work being carried out on the
main avenue at Sans Souci in June 1985.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the worid
Editorial
FROM the very earliest times, men have moved from place
to place. In tribes, clans, families or other groups they fled
from natural catastrophes or the horrors of war in search
of food, shelter and peace. The human sediments left by the great
early tides of migration shaped the face of continents, regions
and countries, and in later times, slaves captured by conquerors,
refugees from terror, impoverished victims of hard times or sys¬
tems, all made their contribution to the inexhaustible wealth of
universal culture, a whole which is greater than the sum of its
parts.
In today's world of societies developing at different rates and
separated by growing inequalities, international migrations still
obey the imperatives of survival, but more than ever before they
are triggered by the need to find work. Millions of persons, obliged
to leave their homeland not so much in quest of higher material
gain as simply to find a job of any kind, naturally look towards
the industrialized countries (where they are assigned tasks which
workers in these countries are loath to perform). Legal or illegal
entrants, alone or accompanied, they are more intent on an even¬
tual return to their country of origin, than on settling in an adopted
country. They live between two cultures, subject to controls which
may be legal or arbitrary, sometimes victims of discrimination,
aggression or unemployment. They defend their right to earn
a living and the right to preserve their identity, or try to adapt
to another culture which in turn feels that its integrity is being
threatened.
This issue of the Unesco Courier reflects Unesco's longstanding
interest in certain aspects of the problem of international migra¬
tion, especially language teaching and vocational training for
immigrants and education for their children. The various dimen¬
sions of the migration phenomenon in our time underline the
complex realities of the problem: the integration of migrant wor¬
kers in the host society; the reactions of the indigenous population
of the host society to the presence of foreigners who are sometimes
seen as competitors on the labour market and whose customs
are generally ill accepted; the impact of rural-urban migration
on the structure and functioning of families left behind; the impact
of rigid school systems on the "parallel" culture of the children
of immigrants; the problems of readaptation of migrants to their
countries of origin when they return after living different lives
abroad.
These are some of the many facets of a problem which today
is a matter of preoccupation in all countries. It is hoped that
analyses of the situation presented here (which even when they
underscore its economic and social effects are made from a pro¬
foundly humanitarian standpoint) will not only constitute a step
forward in understanding this phenomenon but will also contribute
eventually to the definition and implementation of appropriate
strategies of action which will reconcile respect for the rights and
dignity of migrant workers with the legitimate interests of the
receiving countries.
Cover : Physiognomic Blitz. Aquarelle (1927) by Paul Klee, private col¬
lection. New York.
Photo ©' S.P.A.D.E.M., Paris
Editor-in-chief : Edouard Glissant
September 1985
38 th year
Migrant workers :
a world phenomenon
A challenge for the schools
by Georges Vignaux
10 City lights
The impact of rural-urban migration
by Yogesh Atal
12 A Unesco approach to international migration
by Ronald G. Parris
16 BETWEEN TWO CULTURES
France
The dilemma of the North African worker
by Abdallah Buhamidi
1 8 Trie Federal Republic of Germany
Integration or repatriation ?
by Gisela Apitzsch and Norbert Dittmar
21 United Kingdom
The struggle against discrimination
by Robert Miles
24 North America
Men for all seasons
by Anthony P. Maingot
26 The Gulf States
A delicate balance
by Elisabeth Longuenesse
28 Scandinavia
How to be a good host
by Carolyn Swetland
30 The psychology of migrant workers
by Ana Vâsquez
33 Return ticket
The problems of going back
by Eric-Jean Thomas and Catherine Wihtol de Wenden
2 A time to live...
HAITI : The restoration of Sans Souci
Published monthly in 32 languages English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish
by Unesco French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish
The United Nations Educational, Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque
Scientific and Cultural Organization Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. German Persian Korean Bulgarian
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French,
Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N° 9 - 1985 - OPI
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The following article reviews some of
the main trends in international
migration and in policies relating to
them in the decade following 1974 when
a World Population Plan of Action was
adopted at the World Population
Conference organized by the United
Nations and held in Bucharest
(Romania). It focuses attention on
migrations of labour, illegal or
undocumented migration, refugee
movements and migration for permanent
resettlement. The article has been
extracted from a United Nations study
prepared in connexion with the
International Conference on Population,
1984.
IN Europe the virtual stoppage of the
recruitment of foreign workers by the
industrialized market-economy coun¬
tries, which was only incipient in 1974, has
continued, leading to a net reduction in
the size of the foreign labour force still
present in the main labour-importing coun¬
tries, from some 6.5 million foreign work¬
ers in 1974 to 6.2 million around 1980.
Since in many of the receiving countries
of Europe children born of foreign parents
are considered non-nationals, even in the
absence of net immigration an increase in
the foreign population would be expected
because of natural increase. Yet the net
gain recorded falls short of natural
increase, implying that net emigration has
occurred, probably in the form of return
migration to the countries of origin.
At present, most of the receiving coun¬
tries still claim not to be countries of immi¬
gration for permanent resettlement. Their
policies are aimed, inter alia, at stabilizing
the size of the foreign population in their
territories and at ensuring a certain degree
of integration between the foreign minor¬
ities and the national majority, while at
the same time allowing the former to keep
their cultural identity.
Stabilization is to be achieved by pro¬
moting the voluntary return to the sending
countries of foreign workers and their
dependents and by the naturalization of
those who are well adapted to their new
environment. Integration is to be pro¬
moted, inter alia, by ensuring parity
between foreigners and nationals in such
fields as terms of employment, social and
health services, and housing, by providing
special training (notably in the local lan¬
guage) for workers and their dependents,
by combatting discrimination and pre¬
judice against foreigners and by creating
an environment conducive to the normal
development of family life.
Hence, measures related to family re¬
union and to the education, training and
employment opportunities of dependents
of foreign workers are key elements in the
promotion of integration. Yet, although
immigration for the purpose of family re¬
unification is allowed by all the former
labour-importing countries, it is still sub¬
ject to a number of restrictions and, in
general, work permits for spouses and
older children are not easily available.
Migrant workers: a
In contrast with the evolution of immi¬
gration in Europe since 1974, the oil-
exporting countries of Western Asia and
the Libyan Arab Jamahiriya continued to
admit sizeable numbers of foreign workers
at least up to 1980. It has been estimated
that between 1975 and 1980 the total num¬
ber of foreign workers in the main labour-
importing countries of the region increased
from 1.8 to 2.8 million. The total foreign
population in those countries was esti¬
mated to be 3.5 million in 1975 and is likely
to have increased less rapidly than the
number of foreign workers since then.
Given the relatively small size of the
national populations of the Western Asian
labour-importing countries, although the
total number of foreign workers present
in their territories is smaller than that in
Europe, it often constitutes a very large
proportion of the local labour force. Partly
for this reason, in recent years the receiving
countries have tended to adopt measures
that regulate immigration and labour
recruitment more strictly, that discourage
the immigration of family dependents and
that enforce, as much as possible, the rota¬
tion of labour. These measures include the
promotion of such novel labour-importing
mechanisms as the so-called "turn-key
project" by which a foreign company, con¬
tracted to carry out a certain project, pro¬
vides every input, including the manpower.
Lastly, although data for more recent
periods are not yet available, it is likely
that the oil glut experienced by the world
economy since 1982 and the ensuing
decline in oil prices may have had a neg¬
ative effect on immigration levels to West¬
ern Asia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Day and Night (1938), a woodcut by the
Dutch artist M.C. Escher (1898-1972)
world phenomenon
In Africa, available evidence suggests
that seasonal migration is relatively more
common in Western Africa than in other
sub-regions and that the Ivory Coast, the
Gambia and Senegal continue to attract
migrants from neighbouring countries,
among which Chad, Ghana, Mali, Togo
and Burkina Faso appear to be the main
sources of emigrants.
Labour migration is also characteristic
of the southern region, where short-term
movements (of six to eighteen months
duration) of young males to the mines and
industrial complexes of South Africa (and
until the mid-1970s to Zambia and Zim¬
babwe) predominate. Yet the level of
labour migration to South Africa has
declined substantially during the last dec¬
ade, falling from an annual intake of some
300,000 foreign workers in 1970 to less than
200,000 in 1981. Foreign workers in South
Africa are recruited under agreements
between the employing organization and the
Governments of supplying countries, their
repatriation is assured upon completion of
the contract period, and while in the Repub¬
lic they are forbidden to change place of
residence or employment.
In terms of policies, few African coun¬
tries have recognized explicitly a need for
foreign labour and even less have adopted
measures to promote actively the immi¬
gration of foreign workers. In fact, many
countries have expressed the desire to
become self-sufficient in terms of labour
needs, especially in regard to skilled per¬
sonnel. Yet, as long as needed skills remain
scarce, most countries are willing to allow
the temporary presence of foreigners hav¬
ing those skills.
Although Canada and the United States
are better known as countries admitting
permanent immigrants than as importers
of foreign labour, they nevertheless admit
considerable numbers of persons for tem¬
porary employment. Thus, during 1976-
1979, the United States admitted an annual
average of some 91,000 temporary work¬
ers, trainees and exchange visitors (a figure
that excludes all immigrants admitted as
permanent residents) and in 1981 Canada
reported that it had granted about 113,000
work permits, 84,000 valid for less than
a year.
In other parts of the continent, legally
sanctioned labour migration is the excep¬
tion rather than the rule. Very few coun¬
tries have policies that actively promote
the immigration of labour. During the
1970s, Venezuela admitted a significant
number of migrants for employment, while
the Dominican Republic served as host to
many temporary workers from neigh¬
bouring Haiti. Yet, most of these legally
sanctioned flows were accompanied by par¬
allel flows of clandestine migration.
No region of the world is exempt from
illegal or undocumented immigration. Eco¬
nomic disparities between countries, cou¬
pled with the general tendency of receiving
States to restrict the possibilities for legal
migration have often given rise to migra¬
tion flows that are not legally sanctioned
by the receiving countries. In the context
of the existing world order, where only
relatively few countries still encourage or
allow immigration, illegal movements are
likely to continue.
In the Americas, labour migration flows
of considerable magnitude occur, largely
without the explicit approval of the receiv¬
ing States. Illegal or undocumented migra¬
tion is typical of this region. Although
there is little solid evidence on the mag¬
nitude of these flows, it seems likely that
they have increased during the past dec¬
ade. Countries such as Argentina, Canada,
Costa Rica, the Dominican Republic, Pan¬
ama, Venezuela and the United States
have all been known to be the destination
of sizeable numbers of undocumented
migrants who originate in an ever more
varied set of countries.
The policies adopted by countries in this
region to cope with illegal immigration
cover the full range from laissez-faire to
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
} the adoption of regularization drives that
aim at legalizing the status of the migrants
concerned. Deportation or the "voluntary
return" of illegal migrants is the typical
mechanism used to control migration,
although some countries have also adopted
stricter border controls or stiffer employ¬
ers' sanctions to deter the further illegal
influx of migrants for employment.
Undocumented immigrants are also
common in Europe, where the restrictive
admission policies adopted since 1973 have
led many job seekers either to enter a coun¬
try illegally or to enter it legally and accept
employment illegally. In order to control
illegal immigration and prevent its con¬
tinued increase, the former labour-import¬
ing countries have resorted to a wide vari¬
ety of measures, including more careful
border controls, stricter admission require¬
ments, steeper penalties for traffickers and
employers of illegal immigrants, and regu¬
larization schemes.
It is now impossible to assess reliably
either the success of these measures or the
current size of the illegal population. It
must be noted, however, that immigrants
whose status is not legal are not only pres¬
ent in the former labour-importing coun¬
tries, but also in the traditional countries
of emigration. Thus, Greece, Italy and
Spain have reported that they are hosting
substantial illegal populations, a situation
that aggravates the problems these nations
face in reintegrating their own returning
citizens.
Undocumented aliens are also known
to exist in many of the labour-importing
countries of Western Asia, where migrants
have been attracted by better economic
opportunities. In other parts of Asia, eco¬
nomically prosperous States or areas, such
as Hong Kong and Singapore, have also
acted as magnets for illegal flows, while
in certain regions of India economic and
political motivations have led to the exist¬
ence of large populations of migrants
whose legal status is now clear.
In Africa, the relatively recent estab¬
lishment of sovereign States whose bound¬
aries do not always coincide with tradi¬
tional ethnic divisions has often led to
undocumented flows of persons arising
from what used to be traditionally
unimpeded population movements. In gen¬
eral, policy responses to these movements
have been liberal and migrants have been
able to stay and work in the receiving coun¬
try. However, in recent years some States
have resorted to deportation measures that
often contravene basic human rights.
The importance of refugee movements
has increased considerably during the past
decade, partly because of the growing
number of both countries and persons
involved and partly owing to the political
ramifications of these movements. While
in 1974 the Office of the United Nations
High Commissioner for Refugees
(UNHCR) reported that there were
slightly more than 1.8 million refugees in
the world (excluding Palestinians), by the
end of 1981 this number had risen to nearly
6.8 million (again not counting the nearly
1.9 million Palestinians overseen by the
United Nations Relief and Works Agency
for Palestine Refugees in the Near East
(UNRWA)).
Given the nature of refugee movements,
the figures quoted are only approximate,
but they nevertheless indicate orders of
magnitude. In fact, the 1981 figure
excludes nearly two million refugees who
have been permanently resettled in third
asylum countries and the many others who
have been successfully repatriated to their
home countries. Despite the considerable
effort made by developed countries in
resettling refugees, the vast majority are
still being hosted by developing countries
which are commonly the countries of first
asylum. In Africa alone, the number of
refugees increased from one to nearly three
million between 1974 and 1981, while in
Southeastern Asia by the end of 1981 there
still remained about 3 million refugees
awaiting resettlement in third countries.
In general, the policies adopted by Gov¬
ernments to deal with refugees have been
strongly shaped by humanitarian consid¬
erations. In response to the growing num¬
ber of refugees world-wide, many devel¬
oped countries have made special efforts
to increase their refugee intake. However,
since most of these countries have rarely
received direct refugee arrivals, their posi¬
tion as third countries of asylum has
allowed them to select refugees for admis¬
sion, with the result that the criteria on
family reunification and skills used in the
selection have been detrimental to the
resettlement chances of the vast majority
of refugees who lack family ties in the
developed world and are mostly unskilled.
Countries receiving large numbers of
refugees directly have resorted mainly to
two types of strategy: (a) the creation of
"temporary" refugee camps whose basic
necessities are satisfied with the help of
the international community and (b) the
Major International Labour Migration Flows of the Past 20 Years
Path of major migration flow
Major receiving countries
Note: All flows are continuing at substantial levels except flows into Europe,
Ghana, and Nigeria.
Source: Population Reports, September-October 1983, The Johns Hopkins
University, Baltimore, USA
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
resettlement of refugees in rural areas
where they are provided with land and are
encouraged to become self-sufficient.
International aid has also been sought in
the latter case so as to integrate the refugee
in the overall development process. Reset¬
tlement strategies have been common in
Africa, while temporary refugee camps are
typical of Southeastern Asia, a region that
has been the main source of refugees for
resettlement in third countries.
The role played by the United Nations
system in providing aid, safeguarding the
physical safety and basic rights of refugees,
and working towards permanent solutions
to their plight cannot be overstressed.
UNHCR has been successful not only in
eliciting support for resettlement pro¬
grammes, but also in aiding the many thou¬
sands of refugees for whom voluntary repa¬
triation has been possible. The support of
the international community for the activ¬
ities of the United Nations system in regard
to refugees testifies to the importance of
these activities and highlights their con¬
tinued necessity.
Finally, regarding migration for per¬
manent resettlement, mention must be
made of the recent trends in migration to
and from the traditional countries of'immi
gration: Australia, Canada, New Zealand
and the United States. During the decade
1971-1981, only in the United States did
immigration levels grow steadily (largely
because of the admission towards the end
of the decade of sizeable numbers of ref¬
ugees, an immigration category that is not
yet subject to quotas).
The recent adoption by Australia, Can¬
ada and New Zealand of new immigration
laws that allow a better adaptation of immi¬
gration levels to national needs led to a
reduction in the number of admissions, in
spite of the larger intake of refugees that
they all approved. In fact, the data on
emigration from New Zealand reveal that
the country experienced a negative migra¬
tion rate during 1976-1980. These devel¬
opments suggest that, in terms of the tra¬
ditional countries of migration, the number
of places available for future migrants are
not likely to increase.
The decisive moment between past and
future, unemployment and work, hope
and fear
Source : Review andAppraisalof the World Population
Plan ofAction, United Nations document E/CONF.76/
PC/10, 2 December 1983.
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
A challenge for the schools
by Georges Vignaux
THE place where, essentially and his¬
torically, necessary change occurs
is the school. That is where migrant
children are subjected to their crucial first
experience of adjustment to a different
culture and, conversely, where the children
of the host country come into contact with
their otherness and their differences, which
prompts them to reconsider and to under¬
stand their own culture.
Many conflicts can arise in the migrant
child as a result of minority practices that
can identify him and make him visible as
a member of another community (clothing,
diet, personal background, etc.). Unfor¬
tunately, certain underlying cultural
assumptions will then act as kinds of "basic
concepts", axiomatizing images of the
world, codes and conventions that are leg¬
itimated by family consensuses and per¬
ceived by the child as. being at variance
with the very rules, implicit or explicit, of
the school, itself the expression of a major¬
ity consensus.
But the school is not only the "reflec¬
tion" of a national consensus; it also aims
actively to integrate and cast all children
in the same mould. Thus, inevitably, there
is often not so much ignorance as rejection
of their differences.
Yet each of us, each child, needs these
personal and collective differences, if only
to locate and perhaps dedramatize his posi¬
tion on a continuum of images, stereotypes
and prejudices ranging from the nearest
to the most remote. Thus those relegated
to the fringes of society draw upon people's
attitudes to social relegation their own
and those of others. All these attitudes can
only serve to widen the gap between how
the child perceives his social status and how
he experiences his cultural identity. Thus
school can serve as much to materialize
these exclusions, by giving them form and
typology, as to relativize them. This can
happen on two general levels: those of
expression and guidance.
Young Swedes and the children of Turk¬
ish migrant workers learn carpentry in a
school at Göteborg, Sweden.
The acquisition of expression involves
first of all the forced learning of a dominant
rhetoric, that of the host country and its
language, which is the language of know¬
ledge since all subjects will be taught in
it. Very early on, therefore, the migrant
child comes to compare two languages:
that of the school and that of the family,
the latter being necessarily diminished in
value relative to the former. In a great
many cases this linguistic handicap will be
further aggravated by the absence of family
support. If the migrant child succeeds in
overcoming it, he will have to pay the price
in terms of a rift between himself and the
family cultural environment, which he will
now regard as being antagonistic towards
the surrounding model.
With regard to guidance, as a result of
the standards applied in the school (age-
limits, "backwardness", so-called special¬
ist courses etc.), even the best intentions
in the world can turn out to be terribly
selective here. Teachers and counsellors
often arrive at a certain, perception of the
family and social environment which will
lead them to treat the children as special
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
In a class comprising 30 per cent of Immi¬
grant children In a co-educational State
school at La Seyne-sur-Mer in the south
of France, an experiment was carried out
In 1983 to foster greater mutual under¬
standing among the children and to
encourage the young North Africans to
take greater pride in the achievements of
Arabic culture and language. Combining
imaginary and real-life incidents, the
pupils wrote a story about their town
in French and Arabic and Illustrated It
with their own drawings and photos.
cases. As they are moved from one course
to another and from one institution to
another they will very soon be victims of
relegation, this time to the educational and
administrative fringe.
Thus for the migrant child school proves
to be essentially a place where differences
are recognized, distinctions are drawn and
exclusion occurs. The selection systems it
involves rely on explanations and, con¬
versely, these explanatory systems, which
are gradually internalized by the children
concerned, will further the development
in them of paradoxical processes of self-
selection and self-elimination ("I am not
good at school because I am different. . . and
the same applies socially...").
The educational fate of migrant children
can thus be sealed as a result of the subtle
processes whereby they are transferred to
specialist courses, vocational or not, and
their concentration in certain establish¬
ments. Their place of education is as much
a reflection as a result of their physical
location within society (overcrowded
schools in some urban areas). Thus it might
even be claimed that the environment is
fully responsible for under-achievement,
thereby ignoring the ill-preparedness of
teachers for the intercultural problems con¬
fronting them.
Every educational institution is based on
a profound elitism which can only lead to
the exclusion of a substantial percentage
of pupils. This fate is, of course, also that
of children from the under-privileged sec¬
tions of the host society, but the con¬
sequences are necessarily more serious
among migrant children in terms of the
ways in which they perceive their own iden¬
tity. They will resent this selection more
than others as a kind of social rejection,
a return to the same jobs as their parents
or, quite simply, as a sign that they are
being consigned to the ranks of the unem¬
ployed.
School, which they experience as a place
of obligations and constraints, will soon
seem alien and even hostile to them
because they see it as leading them into
a dead end symbolizing a society in which
they cannot see their place. Academic fail¬
ure thus reflects a more general social fail¬
ure generating strategies of despair.
Cultural dysfunctions gradually engen¬
der social maladjustment. "Illegitimate
offspring" of a society in which they believe
they have no place, from countries which
are no longer theirs, these migrant children
will then demand the visibility they once
feared. Their social dis-identification leads
them necessarily to adopt more conspic¬
uous fringe behaviour patterns (formation
of minority groups) or to re-identify with
a mythical native culture which will never
iii^D^I
tf '"Vi^xUl
i^^ S^J>'
vtT
111 7 i i íAIUJA
te Soif
be that of the family. Symbolic crises
develop as ethnic aspirations grow. These
crises express a search for strategies of self-
improvement and self-justification as much
as they reflect the failure of integration in
a school environment which is not pre¬
pared to receive these children with the
respect that they and their families want.
The answer lies in educational diver¬
sification. Various kinds of culture-based
or technology-based courses designed to
be equivalent must be grafted onto a com¬
mon core of basic education. The present
mistake of selective streaming, inevitably
leading to failure at school and in society,
must not be repeated. Hence the impor¬
tante of a cultural re-moulding of ele¬
mentary and pre-elementary education.
Teacher training, analysis and thinking
about methods must concentrate on these
points. All children, not only immigrants,
must be offered common educational facil¬
ities that will provide them with freedom
of choice later on. Recognition of cultural
diversity also implies recognition of dif¬
ferences in rates of progress and adjust¬
ment and hence a re-evaluation of present
modes of enforced "hierarchization"
between types of teaching and curricula.
It is thus important that all children
should enjoy a free interplay of linguistic
expression which is crucial to cognitive,
intellectual and, particularly, technical
development. In this sense, the establish¬
ment of conditions to ensure respect and
understanding not only between cultures
but also between modes of expression in
language, literature and technology, must
go hand in hand with efforts to define and
develop intercultural education.
No culture can be identified with a closed
system of values and behaviour, even if
it is necessary, at certain stages of history,
for it to act as if this were the case. On
the contrary, all cultures can only be nour¬
ished by contact with others that are close
and by contrast with those that are distant.
Schools can help to promote understanding
of this "natural" living process. This is,
perhaps, one of their fundamental roles.
This article is adapted from a report entitledThe
Education of Migrant Children: Problems and
Prospects, prepared by Georges Vignaux for
the 13th session of the Standing Conference
of European Ministers of Education, held in Dub¬
lin from 10 to 12 May 1983.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
City lights
The impact of rural-urban migration
CO
0.
i
©
THE phenomenon of migration is a
major factor in social change. It
affects not only those places that
receive migrants, but also those that send
them. In one type of migration, a member
of the family migrates temporarily to a
different place, moves between the place
of origin and the place of migration, and
treats the former as the reference point
to which he ultimately plans to return.
Migration from a rural to an urban area,
which is usually motivated by the need to
find work, makes heavy demands on the
members of the family back home. It
means that women have to undertake cer¬
tain tasks they did not previously perform
and thus involves a rearrangement of the
family time-table. It influences the social¬
ization pattern of children and may result
in a series of psychological problems. It
affects social life within the family as well
as relations outside.
The effect of these changes varies from
family to family and from culture to cul¬
ture. Response to male migration is dif¬
ferent in families in which the son has
En route for the city. For ruralpopulations
the great urban centres hold a natural
attraction which is magnified by the
hopesometimes justifiedthat in the
city their menfolk will find work enabling
them to improve the living standards of
the families they leave behind.
migrated from those in which the father
has migrated. In families in which the
migrant has the dual status of son and hus¬
band the impact of his migration is felt
differently.
A cross-cultural study of migration has
indicated that migration increases family
income, raises the standard of living some¬
what and adds in varying proportions to
the responsibilities of female family mem¬
bers. Some urban elements enter into the
inventory of the material culture of the
home.
Contrary to common belief, migration
and exposure to modernity may serve to
cement the bonds of kinship and to rein¬
force tradition. It is through the network
of kinship that people move into the city
and, once there, they continue to move
in the kinship and village circle. Back
home, the degree of dependence on kins¬
men increases with the departure of the
male to the town. The authority structure
changes very little; the patriarchal ethos
is pervasive. Family reunions generally
coincide with religious festivals and cer¬
emonial occasions and it is still the husband
who takes major decisions or gives the seal
of his approval, and in his absence the
other senior male members of the family
act as guardians.
Such a situation is understandable since
migration is a temporary phenomenon that
requires only ad hoc arrangements. These
are all withdrawn with the return to "nor¬
mality". However, such migration exposes
women to a wider world of work and expe¬
rience in the management of household
affairs that are in normal circumstances
looked after by men. Longer periods of
absence of husbands create a situation in
which women begin to assume greater
responsibilities and take decisions on mat¬
ters that cannot wait.
This said, the fact remains that men do
not migrate to improve the status of
women. They do it for the overall improve¬
ment of the family's standard of living and
to enhance its status within the traditional
structure. Seen in terms of long-term con¬
sequences, the suffering due to separation
caused by migration is actually an invest¬
ment made by the parents to provide a
better future for their children. The status
of the parents may not change much, but
their sons may have an education, and thus
get a better job, and their daughters may
marry well.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
by Yogesh Atal
Migration to metropolitan centres causes
problems both in the cities and in the fam¬
ilies that remain in the village. It does not
immediately affect the status of migrants.
Realizing this and also accepting the inev¬
itability of the pulls and pushes that lead
ineluctably to migration, we need to devise
a suitable strategy to channel the move¬
ment of men. Studies carried out so far
suggest that we should think more about
the desirability of providing incentives
which would keep people in the rural areas,
such as the development of large villages
or small towns to which people could
move, but without moving very far. The
process would become decentralized with
suitable infrastructures being established
in the various regions of a country to ensure
the balanced economic growth necessary
for the elimination of rural poverty.
This text has been taken from the epilogue to Women
in the Villages, Men in the Towns, a book published
by Unesco in 1 984 as part of a series entitled "Women
in a world perspective".
WOMEN ALONE. A recent study of Indian
rural families from which at least one male
had temporarily migrated to Delhi showed
that 75 per cent of the families lived prin¬
cipally on remittances received from their
menfolk. Most of the cash was used for
the purchase of food and clothes; some
of it was spent on medicines and the edu¬
cation of male children.
*\ -- . »^-
"5^*--*
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
A Unesco approach
to international migration
by Ronald G. Parris
INTERNATIONAL migration,
whether permanent, temporary or sea¬
sonal, legal or illegal, organized or
spontaneous, is inherently characterized by
varying levels of confrontation between
different social systems and cultural tra¬
ditions and has occurred within differing
historical and structural contexts (reli¬
gious, political, economic, the result of war
and natural disasters).
These phenomena have long received
the attention of Unesco, beginning as early
as 1949 with studies ranging from the ques¬
tion of cultural assimilation and the edu¬
cation and training of migrant workers and
their families to the problems associated
with their return and re-adaptation to their
countries of origin.
Resolution 1.142, adopted at the Seven¬
teenth Session of the General Conference
in 1972, called upon Unesco to launch a
specific programme of action on behalf of
migrant workers and their children. Activ¬
ities undertaken to implement this reso¬
lution have included studies of the various
dimensions of migration, wide dissemi¬
nation of their results and the sponsoring
of Meetings of Experts to evaluate these
research findings and to offer recommen
dations for the attention of Member States.
The major orientation of these actions
has been that migration should be con¬
sidered not simply as a labour problem but
as a social, cultural and political process
of intricate dimensions. One practical
objective remains that of encouraging
States to choose and implement appro¬
priate policies in the economic as well as
political and cultural domains that could
lead to the definition of a genuine charter
for immigrants. Such a charter could be
based on the principle of equality of treat¬
ment of immigrants with the local pop¬
ulation, while recognizing the relevance of
making particular distinctions, where spe¬
cific needs exist (for example, language and
skills training) and the importance of the
formation and protection of the cultural
The basis of the apartheid economic sys¬
tem in South Africa is cheap blackmigrant
labour. Millions ofAfricans are denied the
right to live permanently with their fam¬
ilies, which are left in the rural areas or
Bantustans. Many African children see
their fathers only once a year and are
brought up by the womenfolk alone.
Photo shows a family in the "independent
State" of the Transkei in the Republic of
South Africa.
identity of individuals and groups as a
' right.
More recent Unesco programme activ¬
ities have focused on the education and
training of immigrants and the impact of
migration on the social structures of
selected countries, particularly on racial-
ethnic relations. Research has also been
undertaken on the patterns and conse¬
quences of rural-urban migration in Africa,
Asia and Latin America and the mech¬
anisms of. adaptation of migrant workers
to urban life.
In his everyday life, the experience of
the migrant worker is generally one of cul¬
tural alienation, isolation, ambivalence
and rejection, which forces him into social
universes that are generally disconnected
and conflictual. The migrant worker is in
a "nomansland, which is neither that of
his country of origin nor that of his country
of employment," resulting often in the des-
tructuring of the very family group and
immigrant community that he needs to
sustain him. Everyday life is typically orga¬
nized around two poles: his family and
fellow countrymen, in a cultural environ¬
ment resembling or at least drawing on
elements of the culture of the country of
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
^ origin; and his work and public life, in a
culture unfamiliar to him.
This cultural divergence or dichotomy
finds expression in the gradual acquisition
by the migrant of two autonomous lan¬
guage tools: the mother tongue, which pri¬
marily serves him for private use with fam¬
ily and friends ("language of affect") and
a specialized administrative language of the
country of employment, devoid of affective
connotation and representing "the lan¬
guage of power or domination." Inter¬
related with this linguistic dichotomy is the
division of his daily life into two discon¬
nected universes: the universe of work and
that of the cultural ghetto.
The isolation and alienation identifiable
in the general migrant population assume
even more significance when female
migrants are considered. Sex differences,
rather than obscuring the alienation the
migrant experiences qua migrant, tend to
exacerbate the problems of cultural adap¬
tation female migrants have to overcome.
The reproductive behaviour together with
the productive functions of female
migrants constitute the core elements of
their experiences in the countries of
employment and represent the context for
assessing the effects of migration on their
identity, status and cultural behaviour both
inside the family and in the world of work.
The socio-cultural conditions encoun¬
tered by migrant workers and their families
and the patterns of migratory flows them¬
selves take as a point of departure the
international economic, political and
demographic structures that generate
them. These factors include, in particular,
the demand in the more industrialized
countries for cheap manpower and the
need of the labour-surplus countries to sell
their labour power. Deteriorating demo¬
graphic patterns in some of the more indus¬
trialized countries also play a role.
It is also important to consider the par¬
ticular terms and conditions of recruitment
and employment of migrant workers (for
example, organized bilateral agreements,
spontaneous undocumented movements),
Twoyoung Mexican women illegallycross
the Rio Grande del Norte (or Rio Bravo),
which forms the frontier with the United
States, between Ciudad Juárez in Mexico
and El Paso, Texas.
for these too play a role in the socio-
cultural experiences of migrant workers
and their families, including their access
to the institutions and services of the
receiving countries.
For these reasons, the approach to the
problem of migration must be holistic. The
situation of the migrant worker must be
considered in its various dimensions, for
his culture, education and training are all
interrelated with the economic and polit¬
ical factors affecting his labour or employ¬
ment, and these, in turn, should be ref¬
erenced to the racial-ethnic and class
systems of the receiving countries. It is
necessary to keep in mind the effects of
his presence on these systems and the prac¬
tices and policies employed which, by
design or chance, keep him in a state of
economic domination and cultural limbo.
And when considering the problem at the
level of the economy, it could be asserted
that migration,' whether spontaneous or
organized, fails to correct the underlying
weaknesses of the socio-economic struc¬
tures of either the receiving countries or
the countries of origin, while remaining
a structural component of the world
economy.
Institutional discrimination, racial and
ethnic prejudice are common features of
the societies to which the migrants go.
Racial and ethnic prejudice is often mani¬
fest in the terms and conditions of entry
and in official immigration policies, in the
daily practices on the job and in the class¬
room and in indigenous attitudes and daily
contacts between migrant workers and the
local population. In some cases, racial
strains lead to racial violence. The migrant
worker, at first an economic object, soon
becomes a racial-ethnic object.
Leaders in the receiving countries, who
declare themselves in favour of immigra¬
tion, so long as it is limited to certain coun¬
tries of origin, or in favour of extending
civic rights and privileges only to those
immigrants whose "cultural traditions"
more resemble or are more likely to be
compatible with their own, hence making
these immigrants more assimilable, are,
like the more direct opponents of coloured
immigration, declaring a case for racism.
Under present conditions of economic
crisis and unemployment, many receiving
countries re-define the presence of immi-
With Unesco support, the Association
Africaine des Femmes de l'Espace 93 at
Bobigny in the northeastern suburbs of
Paris organizes educational activities
designed to encourage the wives and
daughters ofmigrants toparticipate In the
social life of the host community. Dress¬
making, sewing, knitting, crochetwork,
painting on cloth and dyeing feature
among the range of manual activities
available. Left, the sewing room. Unesco
has offered similar contracts to four
migrant workers' associations: two in
France, one in Switzerland, and one in
Belgium.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
grants and migrant workers as threatening
the livelihood and survival of the indig¬
enous population or even as an explanation
for the economic ills themselves. Greater
social controls are usually demanded,
including calls for their expulsion and
repatriation.
Examples abound everywhere. Recent
official policy in Nigeria, after the falling
off of oil revenues, has been that of forcible
expulsion of immigrants, particularly illicit
workers. In France, a political party has
been consolidating its political position by
associating immigration with unemploy¬
ment, provoking a vigorous response in
the form of an anti-racist movement mobi¬
lized under the fraternal slogan "Touche
pas à mon pote" ("Don't touch my pal")
which has been relatively successful in cap¬
turing the attention of public opinion and
articulating the opposition of diverse
groups opposed to racism and the scape-
goating of immigrants. The response of
Asian and Caribbean immigrants in Britain
to racial violence and discrimination has
been increased collective organization and
participation at the community level as well
as a marked involvement in trade union
activities.
Finally, what then is the legal status of
immigrants and migrant workers in the
countries of employment? This is a prob¬
lem with which Unesco has also been con¬
cerned. Experience has shown that like
their socio-economic status, their legal sta¬
tus is generally precarious, often depend¬
ing on the discretionary powers of the
administrative authorities. Their legal sta¬
tus could be subjected to reassessment dur¬
ing periods of economic downturn.
This has been the case, for example, with
Asian and Carribean immigrants in Brit¬
ain, where a series of Immigration Acts
beginning with the Commonwealth Immi
gration Act, 1962, have strictly circum¬
scribed the conditions of entry and also
the right of admission of family depend¬
ents, including spouses. This is true also
for some of the labour-importing countries
in West Asia, which have instituted their
own measures of control. The extension
of civic rights to immigrants is closely
guarded. The right, for example, to vote
remains a controversial point of issue in
several of the receiving countries.
RONALD G. PARRIS is a specialist on deve¬
lopment in Unesco's Sector of Social and
Human Sciences. He is a former professor of
sociology at New York University and at Van-
derbilt University, and Dean of the School of
Arts and Sciences at Virginia Union University,
in the United States. He is the author of several
publications on the problems of migration.
Migration within Africa
IN sub-Saharan Africa there are two
major patterns of international labour
migration.
The first and most important is in West
Africa, where in nine countries about 2.8 mil¬
lion people were living outside their country
of birth in 1975. Long-distance migration in
West Africa has a lengthy history, beginning
with the movement of entire villages or clans
to avoid war or famine. Later, colonists
brought labourers, often by force, to Ghana
and the Ivory Coast. Now unequal job oppor¬
tunities within the region, drought, and the
open-border policies of most countries sus¬
tain voluntary migration. Moreover, with birth¬
rates now above 45 per 1,000 in all West
Africa, the number of migrants is likely to
grow. Return migration and circulation
among countries is common.
Most of the migrants come from rural areas
and the lower-income, land-locked countries
such as Burkina Faso (formerly Upper Volta)
and Mali. In 1975 as much as 17 per cent
of the population of Burkina Faso was living
elsewhere. The destinations of the migrants
have changed over the last three decades,
depending on the relative prosperity of the
coastal regions and on their immigration pol¬
icies. Ghana, the most popular destination
in the late 1950s and early 1960s, gave way
to the Ivory Coast and Nigeria after the Ghan¬
aian economy deteriorated and, in 1 969, the
Villagers in Mali making for the town in
search of .work and better living condi¬
tions hitch a ride on a truck laden with
calabashes.
Government expelled all aliens without res¬
idence permits. In 1983 there was a similar
expulsion from Nigeria.
The other, much smaller migration flow in
sub-Saharan Africa is into South Africa. For
nearly a century mines in South Africa have
recruited workers on short-term contracts
from neighbouring countries. The flow of
international migrants amounts to about
250,000 a year, and recently the number has
remained fairly constant. The origin of the
migrants has changed, however, with fewer
coming from Malawi and Mozambique and
more from Botswana, Lesotho and Swazi¬
land.
Source : Population Reports, Special Topics, Number
7, September-October 1983. Johns Hopkins Univer¬
sity, Baltimore, USA.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
BETWEEN TWO CULTURES
France
The dilemma of the North
African worker
by Abdallah Buhamidi
IMMIGRATION from North Africa to
France is nothing new; it started with
the men who came to fight with the
French forces in the First World War. But
the biggest influx took place more recently
and dates back some thirty or forty years.
Most of the immigrants came after the
Second World War, to help rebuild the
French economy. They provided man¬
power that was plentiful, adaptable and
cheap; the problem of social and cultural
adaptation did not arise.
Neither they nor their French hosts
envisaged long-term coexistence. The
French economy was interested in these
men and women solely as a source of
labour, and the immigrants intended to go
back home as soon as they had saved
enough to give their families, which most
of them had left behind, a better life.
Today this may still be the case for some
600,000 immigrants whose families have
remained in their country of origin. But
for the majority, the situation is no longer
entirely the same, even though most of
them have not abandoned the idea of going
back one day.
In fact a number of recent developments
are causing immigrants from North Africa
to reconsider the question of going home.
As a result of the economic crisis they are
victims of unemployment. The current dif¬
ficulties on the labour market are hitting
them harder than the indigenous popu¬
lation or even other immigrant groups.
Except when the work to be done is
arduous, dangerous or dirty, immigrant
workers are the last to be hired. However,
when firms run into difficulties, reorganize,
and decide to reduce their workforce, they
are also the first to be fired, unless they
are offered the chance of taking early
retirement, possibly accompanied by a
financial inducement to return to their
country of origin.
For the present crisis is not merely short-
term or cyclic. It affects the country's eco¬
nomic structures, which are having to be
adapted to meet the demands of foreign
competition. The necessary modernization
calls for technological competence of the
highest order. The days of unskilled
labour, however cheap, are over.
Furthermore, many of the first arrivals
have now reached the age of retirement
(early or otherwise), and for them the
problem of going back home is com¬
pounded by the question of their children
and their children's future. For the fact
is that, although many have never aban¬
doned the idea of returning home, they
have always postponed it until their chil¬
dren who were either born in France or
came as soon as their father was in a posi¬
tion to give them a home finished their
education.
As they grew up in France, these chil¬
dren acquired attitudes, modes of thought
and a way of life that have made most of
them foreigners in their country of origin,
to which they would find it extremely dif¬
ficult to adapt. The parents too, while they
are foreigners in France, have also grad¬
ually become foreigners in their own coun¬
try.
In such conditions, is it possible to go
back?
The experiences of people who have
made the attempt are very instructive,
although they are so recent that it is dif¬
ficult to draw any general conclusions from
them.
Readaptation to the country of origin
is not a simple matter, either for those who
have made a success of their return or for
those who have encountered difficulties,
especially since the "returnees" are often
ill prepared for the situation.
The most successful cases seem to be
those who adapted best to life in France,
where they acquired knowledge and voca¬
tional skills which made it easier for them
to fit back into the social and working life
of their country of origin.
It has also been observed that the immi¬
grants' children who have achieved the best
results in French schools are those who
have maintained the closest ties with their
original culture and with the chief vehicles
of that culture, their parents. The problem
of the social and cultural adaptation in
France of North African immigrants and
their children is thus closely linked in a
complex interaction with the problem of
identity.
The children of the Mekong
Aquiet street in the Paris suburb of
Asnières. A sign above a door bears
the unexpected words "Les Enfants
du Mekong" ("The Children of the Mekong").
The house is a hostel inhabited by some 1 5
young Asians aged between 1 6 and 20. Dur¬
ing working hours the hostel is empty; every¬
one is at a literacy class or at school. But
in the evening or at mealtimes it is like being
in a big family, with Monsieur Péchard the
director, whom everyone calls "uncle", Oli¬
vier the group leader, who might be an older
brother, and the Vietnamese mothers who
do the cooking.
"We organize a lot of sponsorship," says
Monsieur Péchard. "We give the sponsor the
name of a child in a camp in Thailand and
he agrees to send that child a small sum
of money through us each month. It is also
possible to sponsor a young person in
France, like the young people in this hostel,
either by paying for all or part of his keep
or, preferably, welcoming him into the family
at weekends or on holidays. All degrees of
participation are possible."
In this way whole families are welcomed
by specially formed groups, often in a parish,
a movement of some kind, or a school. Some
try to find housing for these families, others
help them with scholastic formalities or teach
French to those who have. just arrived. A
whole network of solidarity is being created
in which each person does what he or she
can.
Source : Peuples du Monde N° 1 84, Paris, June 1 985.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Painter Rachid Khimoune's interest in
Arabic calligraphy and geometric man¬
hole cover designs has Inspired an un¬
usual artistic experiment. He makes casts
of the covers and reproduces them on
large canvases into which he incorpo¬
rates pages of writing. "The street is the
immigrant's lot, " he says. "I find the same
arabesques there as I do In Muslim art."
Integration difficulties were a logical
result of living in a community which was
regarded solely as a source of labour and
which was relegated to the fringes of the
host society and its culture. Integration was
not encouraged. Apart from these diffi¬
culties, the problem of the adaptation of
North African workers was distorted by
an enormous misunderstanding which tran¬
scended the simple question of adopting
the laws and customs of the host country
and which made any possible integration
dependent on repudiation of one's self.
The values so dear to North African
immigrants and their culture, perceived in
France in terms of clichés divorced from
the historical context common to the two
shores of this part of the Mediterranean,
had no chance of asserting themselves
against those of the host country.
The rejection of certain forms of expres¬
sion of this immigrant community has been
attributed to the fact that Arab Muslim
culture is very different from European
culture. This explanation is not fully sat¬
isfactory, since in other circumstances the
two cultures have several times proved to
be fully complementary and perfectly com¬
patible.
At a very early stage, the values of which
the parents were the bearers were rejected
not only by the host society but also by
their own children, who attributed their
difficulties to their cultural identity and
therefore to their parents.
Through the school and the acquisition
of a working knowledge of the language,
"He is the son of Immigrants, adrift
between two cultures, two histories, and
two languages... inventing his own roots,
forming his own attachments," wrote
Algerian writer Mehdl Charef in his novel
Le Thé au Harem d'Archi Ahmed, which
he successfully adapted for the screen
In 1984. Cultural ambivalence can be a
bitter experience for second-generation
immigrants, banishing them to the fringe
of two worlds, but it can also be a source
ofcreativity. Novelist Leila Sebbar, above,
is the daughter of an Algerian father and
a French mother. She draws inspiration
for her work in the confluence of two rich
civilizations.
even the less gifted children soon gained
access to a code for understanding the host
society which was a closed book for their
parents, who thus lost their status as socio-
cultural initiators the basis of their
authority and its "legitimacy".
Because of their ambiguous attitude to
their own identity, the parents contributed
involuntarily to the deterioration of their
relations with their children. Anxious to
resemble the dominant model through the
educational and social success of their chil¬
dren, they overvalued that model to the
detriment of their own cultural values, to
which their children should have referred.
Caught up in this contradiction, the chil¬
dren harboured a negative image of them¬
selves and linked this disparaged identity
with their failure, which they saw as pre¬
ordained. This situation created conflict
within the family and jeopardized its co¬
hesion as a group. The father was the first
victim and then by way of reaction the
children, who in such circumstances were
bound to do badly at school. In these con¬
ditions many young people have rejected
their culture of origin, while failing to
acquire access to the host culture or to
achieve the qualifications necessary to
achieve a satisfying social and professional
life, still less the integration dreamed of
by their parents.
"In the past we thought of going back to
Algeria one day. Now we know we'll stay
here," says sculptor Mohand Amara.
Going back was once the dream of many
Immigrants, but is it possible for their
children? Many immigrants are only par¬
tially integrated in the host society, but
no longer feel they belong in their society
of origin, which also regards them as out¬
siders.
The contribution made to. the French
economy and culture by immigrants from
North Africa has been far from negligible.
Thanks to their constant comings and
goings between the two shores of the Med¬
iterranean, North African immigrants have
become an organic link between France
and the Maghreb, participating in the com¬
merce between the two cultures.
Through its contact with immigrant chil¬
dren, the French educational system is re¬
examining its methods in such a way that
many French children, hitherto excluded
because of their non-conformism from the
traditional channels of knowledge and
instruction, will certainly benefit.
Mention should also be made of the
growing number of writers and artists
(especially musicians, painters and film¬
makers) whose specific modes of expres¬
sion are making a mark on French cultural
trends.
One of the greatest benefits which
i France is reaping from the presence of
North African immigrant workers is
undoubtedly an awareness, still in its
infancy, of her pluralistic identity, the
; source of all her riches, symbolized by the
slogan chanted during a recent anti-racist
demonstration: "First, second, third,
fourth generation, we are all the children
i of immigrants." '
ABDALLAH BUHAMIDI, of Morocco, is a psy¬
chologist and guidance counsellor with the
Paris-based association Jeunesse, Culture, Loi¬
sirs et Technique. He is also director of the
association's specialized guidance service.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
BETWEEN TWO CULTURES
The Federal Republic of Germany
Integration or repatriation?
by Gisela Apitzsch and Norbert Dittmar
THERE are about 4.5 million for¬
eigners living in the Federal Repub¬
lic of Germany and West Berlin of
whom Turkish nationals form by far the
largest group, accounting for 35 per cent
of the total.
As a result of the current economic
situation the legal requirements affecting
foreigners are being applied in a more
restrictive manner and this has made their
situation more precarious and has also
made it more difficult for them to plan for
the future. Only a fraction of these
migrants enjoy legal security. Although 2.9
million foreigners have been living in the
Federal Republic for more than eight years
and thus fulfil the most important condition
for obtaining a residence permit which
would protect them against expulsion in
the case of long-term unemployment or
dependence on social security, only 3.2 per
cent are in possession of this precious doc¬
ument.
In order to clarify the present situation
of foreign communities from countries out¬
side the European Economic Community
(EEC) in general, and of the Turkish com¬
munity in particular, it is necessary to
retrace the policies concerning foreigners
adopted over the past few years.
Uncertainty about the future seems
etched Into the features of these foreign
workers in the port of Hamburg. Facing
them was the prospect of massive redun¬
dancies in the city's shipyards.
The ban on recruitment of foreign work¬
ers decreed in 1973 and a regulation of
the Bundesanstaltfür Arbeit (Federal Insti¬
tute of Labour), which came into force a
year later, concerning the granting of work
permits for foreigners stipulated that an
interruption of residence in the Federal
Republic could result in loss of employ¬
ment. To avoid this problem many migrant
workers tried to arrange for their families
to join them in the Federal Republic.
As a result, during the years of economic
crisis, the age and employment compo¬
sition of the foreign population underwent
a fundamental change. Whereas the num¬
ber of foreign workers living in the Federal
Republic in 1978 tallied almost exactly with
that in 1973, the number of foreigners in
employment had actually gone down by
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
28 per cent. The number of children under
the age of sixteen increased by about 25
per cent, passing the million mark in 1976.
In the following years the authorities
pursued a dual strategy: on the one hand
encouraging return to the country of ori¬
gin, and on the other promoting the inte¬
gration of migrants. As late as 1978 a prac¬
tice was introduced whereby foreigners
who fulfilled certain conditions, such as
having satisfactory living quarters and a
basic knowledge of the German language,
could be granted an unlimited residence
permit after five years of uninterrupted
stay and the right of residence after eight
years. In 1979 the general ban on employ¬
ment for spouses who had joined their
partners at a later date was lifted in favour
of a four-year waiting period. Since then
adolescents joining their parents later have
usually been granted full access to the
labour market after a maximum two-year
waiting period with the proviso that pref¬
erence should be given to nationals
of the Federal Republic and the EEC
countries.
These improvements in the situation of
the children of immigrant workers were
supported on the grounds that their dis¬
advantaged position at school and at work
might prove a threat to social stability and
that the members of this "second gen¬
eration" could be considered as a potential
source of skilled labour to meet shortages
expected in the late 1980s.
1979 was a key year for integration strat¬
egies, and a number of in-school and out-
Turklsh women photographed at the Fed¬
eral Republic of Germany's recruitment
office in Istanbul, before the 1973 ban on
the recruitment of foreign workers. Those
who spoke German, had a relative work¬
ing in the Federal Republic or had already
worked abroad stood a better chance of
getting a job.
of-school training programmes were ini¬
tiated. Perhaps the most important of these
was a programme of Measures for Job-
preparation and Social Integration of
Young Foreigners (MBSE). The MBSE is
a full-time, ten-month programme whose
primary aim is to provide adolescents with
an integrated course combining practical
job preparation, language teaching and
general education. The vast majority of
participants (95 per cent) are Turkish
youths. The initial intention was that the
programme should be offered nationwide
and be extended to offer 20,000 places.
However, a continual reduction has taken
place since the programme was established
in 1980, and in the year 1983/84 only 6,500
adolescents were able to benefit from it.
By the early 1980s, the tendency to
regard integration policy as a means of
limiting the number of foreigners grew
stronger. Opportunities for families to be
reunited have been drastically curtailed.
Since December 1981 only children below
the age of 16 (as compared with 18 pre¬
viously) have been allowed to join their
parents, and a stricter interpretation of the
regulations concerning living quarters fre¬
quently makes it impossible for married
couples or for parents and their under-age
children to live together.
One of the basic aims of policies con¬
cerning foreigners under the Government's
Urgent Measures Programme was the facil¬
itation of repatriation. Foreigners from
non-EEC countries who left the Federal
Republic or West Berlin between October
1983 and September 1984 could ask for
50 per cent of their pension contributions
to be paid back to them and the usual two-
year waiting period was waived. According
to information from the Regional Insur¬
ance Offices one-fifth of all Turkish nation¬
als living in the Federal Republic took
advantage of this offer even though they
lost the employers' contributions and had
to forgo all claims on a pension as well
as the possibility of returning to the Federal
Republic in the future.
Although the Federal Government has
an interest in reducing the number of for¬
eigners living in the Republic, the economy
is still dependent to a certain extent on
foreign workers. They account for 28 per
cent of the work force in foundries, 25 per
cent in the mining industry, 20 per cent
in the textile industry, 16 per cent in the
car industry and 14 per cent in the building
sector. In these areas, as well as in the
artificial fibre industry, in cellulose pro¬
duction and in heating and refrigeration
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
it would be well nigh impossible
to replace foreign workers by unemployed
nationals of the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many, since their qualification patterns are
unsuitable.
About half the unemployed nationals of
the Federal Republic are qualified in areas
in which hardly any foreign workers are
employed. Moreover, for health or age
reasons, two-thirds of them could not take
over jobs with a high level of stress, and
one-fifth of them are looking only for part-
time employment. Thus, even though
many nationals of the Federal Republic
consider foreigners to be a contributory
factor to the unemployment situation,
ousting them from the labour market
would in fact do little to improve it.
More than 95 per cent of foreign workers
are employed in production (one in six
production workers is a foreigner). In West
Berlin, where the proportion of foreigners
(12 per cent) is higher than anywhere else,
one in every four workers comes from one
of the former countries of recruitment, half
of them being from Turkey. Foreigners
also form a high proportion of the work
force in towns in the industrial area of the
Ruhr and in Frankfurt-am-Main, Offen¬
bach, Stuttgart, Mannheim and Munich.
Foreign workers have been much more
badly hit by unemployment than nationals
of the Federal Republic. Whereas at the
end of 1983 there was a total of 9.5 per
cent of registered unemployed, the rate
amongst foreign workers was nearer 14.9
per cent. Turkish workers were the most
severely affected with an official unem¬
ployment rate of 18 per cent.
- Foreign families are worried not only
about uncertain employment prospects,
and consequently about the right of res¬
idence, but also about the uncertain future
facing their children.
Foreign children form a significant part
(845,000) of the school populationone
in every twelve pupils is of foreign origin.
In towns with a high foreign population
some 25 to 30 per cent of the pupils in
primary and secondary schools are of for¬
eign origin, with Turkish pupils forming
the largest single group (53 per cent).
The opportunities for social progress for
these children are minimal 20 to 25 per
cent play truant, some 50 per cent of for¬
eign school-leavers fail to obtain a certif¬
icate of education, and only very few of
them continue their education beyond sec¬
ondary level.
Since responsibility for education lies
with the regions and not with the Federal
Government, there is no homogeneous
educational policy in the Federal Republic
of Germany. Each local authority puts its
own interpretation on the guidelines estab¬
lished by the Conference of Education
Ministers. Yet despite certain local dif¬
ferences to which this leads, a number of
common factors can be observed: the
native language and culture of foreign chil¬
dren is hardly taken into account in regular
courses and native language teaching rarely
figures on the time-table where classes are
mixed; there is a shortage of teachers who
are adequately prepared for teaching
involving foreign children; there is a grow¬
ing tendency to segregate foreign pupils.
A "mixed" class of Turkish and German
children at a school in Duisburg, in the
Federal Republic of Germany
Even though the educational aspirations
of foreign pupils have been shown to be
no lower than those of nationals of the
Federal Republic, 75 per cent of foreign
adolescents receive no education beyond
secondary level and no specialized job
training. Inadequate knowledge of the
German language goes a long way to
explaining this situation.
However, in order to enable at least the
following generations to acquire an eman¬
cipated status in their host country and to
ensure the peaceful co-existence of mem¬
bers of differing ethnic and cultural back-
gounds, more must be done than simply
to lament migrants' lack of readiness to
go through a process of acculturation.
What is needed and this also in the inter¬
est of the majority of the population is
a turning away from the employment of
foreign workers on the basis of short-term
economic interests and a re-thinking of
employment policies by those to whom
political responsibility is entrusted.
GISELA APITZSCH, of the Federal Republic
of Germany, is a research assistant at the Free
University of Berlin. She has been engaged in
a research programme on "Strategies in Inter-
cultural Communication", and is the author of
several articles on the problems of language
acquisition and communication among
migrants.
NORBERT DITTMAR, of the Federal Republic
of Germany, is professor of sociolinguistics and
second-language learning at the Free University
of Berlin. He is the author of several publi¬
cations, including Sociolinguistics, A Survey of
Theory and Methods (1976). He is currently
engaged in a project on cross-linguistic second-
language acquisition by Italian, Polish and Tur¬
kish migrants.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
BETWEEN TWO CULTURES
Indian workers in a garment factory in
Wolverhampton, England
United Kingdom
The struggle against
discrimination
by Robert Miles
THERE has been an Asian and Car¬
ibbean presence in Britain for sev¬
eral centuries, reflecting British
colonial history. Many British towns and
cities, particularly seaports, contain Asian
and Caribbean communities which have
been established for three generations or
more. Their origin often lies with travelling
salesmen from the Indian sub-continent or
with seamen recruited in the colonies.
These communities formed the base for
the migration that developed in the 1950s
in response to the demand for labour in
certain sectors of the British economy. As
happened elsewhere in Western Europe
after 1945, the expansion of the capitalist
economy exhausted the supply of labour
within the national boundary and employ¬
ers were forced to recruit workers from
elsewhere.
The majority of those recruited after
1945 were from colonies and ex-colonies,
and they arrived in Britain with British
citizenship. Comparable circumstances
existed in the case of certain migrant
groups to France and the Netherlands.
These colonial migrants arrived with the
right to settle and work, and with full polit¬
ical and civil rights. However, this position
of legal equality has not led to their attain
ing a position of economic and social equal¬
ity with the indigenous population.
Most New Commonwealth migrants who
came to Britain before 1965 did so in order
to fill positions in the labour market
vacated by indigenous workers. These
were mainly manual jobs, and particularly
semi- and unskilled manual jobs. They
were also often low-paid and involved poor
working conditions and/or shiftwork.
Migrants were concentrated in textiles,
food production, automobile construction,
metal manufacture, transport and the
National Health Service.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
% WÊ^--
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Although the majority of migrants in this
early period were men, the migration from
the Caribbean did include a large pro¬
portion of women who came in order to
work in their own right. Since the mid-
1960s, almost all the New Commonwealth
migrants have been the wives and children
of those who came in the earlier period,
and many of them have entered the labour
market as is their right.
Thus, in 1981 , 89.9 per cent of Caribbean
men of working age and 69.9 per cent of
Caribbean women were employed, com¬
pared with 90. 6 per cent of indigenous men
and 63.5 per cent of indigenous women.
The respective figures for Asian men and
women were 85.6 per cent and 41.4 per
cent. The much smaller proportion of
Asian women employed is partly explained
by cultural factors.
The position of these migrants in the
labour market in the 1980s has not changed
noticeably from the situation that existed
during the early period of the migration.
A national survey published in 1984
showed that, amongst the indigenous male
population, 42 per cent were employed in
professional and non-manual occupations,
and 58 per cent were employed in manual
work. The respective figures for Asian men
were 26 per cent and 73 per cent, and for
Caribbean men, 15 per cent and 83 per
cent.
Concerning manual work, men of Car¬
ibbean and Asian origin remained over-
represented in semi- and unskilled jobs,
compared with 16 per cent of indigenous
men.
Workers of Caribbean and Asian origin
in Britain are, therefore, predominantly
manual workers and are significantly over-
represented in semi- and unskilled manual
work. The migrant of the 1950s was
recruited to these positions. But an expla¬
nation is required for the fact that migrants
and their British-born children remain
largely confined to these same sectors.
Language problems have not been irrel¬
evant, and some of the migrants lacked
formal qualifications, but these factors less
easily explain the position and experience
of the migrants' children.
In the case of the latter, the question
of achievement within the British edu¬
cation system arises, especially for West
Indian boys. Yet even where people of
Asian and Caribbean origin speak good
English and have equivalent qualifications,
they are commonly employed in inferior
positions. A number of studies conducted
since the mid 1960s have shown that dis¬
crimination plays a crucial role in deter¬
mining their position in the labour market,
despite the fact that such discrimination
is illegal.
West Indian and Asian migrants and
their children (particularly young men of
| Caribbean origin) have been particularly
"-. vulnerable to unemployment. In the early
¡ 1960s, unemployment amongst New Com-
I monwealth migrants was higher than
~ amongst the indigenous population, but it
§ A Bangalee mother in London takes an
£ English lesson in her home.
Audio-visual aids are used to help these
Pakistani children learn English at their
school at Bradford in northern England.
fell during the 1960s, with the exception
of the recession of 1967/68, and by the end
of the decade was at about the same level.
However, over the past fifteen years,
unemployment amongst both migrants and
their children has increased faster than
amongst the indigenous population.
Within the Asian and Caribbean popu¬
lations, unemployment rates have been
even higher for young West Indian men
and for Pakistani and Bangladeshi women.
The aforementioned 1984 study showed
that 25 per cent of Caribbean men and 16
per cent of Caribbean women, and 20 per
cent of Asian men and women were unem¬
ployed, compared with 13 per cent of indig¬
enous men and 10 per cent of indigenous
women. In the 16-24 years age range, 44
per cent of Caribbean men and 38 per cent
of Caribbean women, and 30.5 per cent
of Asian men and 38.5 per cent of Asian
women were unemployed, compared with
26 per cent of indigenous men and 20 per
cent of indigenous women.
This higher level of unemployment is
due in part to the fact that Asian and Car¬
ibbean workers are over-represented
amongst those engaged in semi- and
unskilled manual work for low wages. Peo¬
ple doing these jobs are more likely to
become unemployed, partly because it is,
these sorts of manual jobs that are increas¬
ingly being replaced by machinery. But this
is far from being the only factor.
Asian and Caribbean people are more
likely to be unemployed whatever their job
level, and they are also more likely to be
unemployed due to dismissal from work.
These facts suggest that discrimination is
an important part of the explanation.
Discrimination confines migrants to par¬
ticular positions in the hierarchy of wage
labour, but in a way which is not always
evident to the victims; studies show that
people of Asian and Caribbean origin
underestimate the extent of discrimination
against them. Moreover, immigrants are
also subjected to incidents of violence. A
Home Office report published in 1981 con¬
cluded that there was a minimum of 7,000
attacks a year and that people of Asian
origin were fifty times more likely to be
the victim of an attack than people of Euro¬
pean origin. People of Caribbean origin
were thirty-six times more likely to be vic¬
tims of such attacks. The research team
concluded that "It was clear to us that the
Asian community widely believes that it
is the object of a campaign of unremitting
racial harassment which it fears will grow
worse in the future". These attacks take
\ place in certain urban areas, especially in
the big cities.
The vast majority of colonial migrants
to Britain and their British-born children
are part of the working class. In many
respects they share all the disadvantages
and problems of the working class, and
they are involved in traditional forms of
working class political organization and
behaviour. Overall, workers of Asian and
Caribbean origin are more likely to belong
to a trade union and to vote for the Labour
Party than are indigenous workers. They
have also played a prominent part in trade
union struggles, although the trade unions
themselves are often characterized by dis¬
criminatory practices against immigrants.
The political consciousness of these work¬
ers overlaps to a significant extent with the
political consciousness of the rest of the
working class.
The activities of self-help groups, com¬
munity schools, parents' groups concerned
with their children's experience in the edu¬
cation system, self-defence groups and
many others are all part of the complex
political reaction of colonial migrants and
their children to the specific problems that
they face in Britain and are an important
part of the continuing struggle for racial
equality there.
ROBERT MILES, of the United Kingdom, has
been lecturer in sociology at the University of
Glasgow since 1978. He is the author or co¬
author of several publications including Labour
and Racism (1980), Racism and Migrant Labour
(1982), and White Man's Country: Racism in
British Politics (7984).
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
BETWEEN TWO CULTURE S
North America
Men for all seasons
by Anthony P. Maingot
THE history of the exploitation of
migrant workers in general and in
North America in particular is too
well known to warrant repetition. It has
provided the plot of more than one major
novel and the workers' plight has been
portrayed in all its pathos in more than
one film. That plight tends to be a com¬
bination of substandard wages and living
conditions and a high degree of job in¬
security. More often than not these con¬
ditions have been associated with the agri¬
cultural sector in labour-intensive agro-
industries.
Because such substandard programmes
continue to exist it might be good to look
at some cases where the use of migrant
labour in agriculture has worked well for
the migrant, his family and community as
well as for the employer. It might be pos¬
sible to derive some lessons from a review
of such cases. It is fortunate, therefore,
that we now have good data on two agri¬
cultural programmes utilizing migratory
labour, one in the State of Florida and the
other in Canada.
The 8,000 migrant workers in the Florida
sugar industry are in a way all that is left
of the original bracero (strong arm) pro¬
gramme that started in 1942 and at its
height brought more than 420,000 workers,
mostly Mexican, to work in US agriculture.
Only one part of that large migrant worker
scheme of the 1940s remained intact: the
so-called H-2 programme (from the cat¬
egory of visa granted to temporary work
ers) bringing British West Indians to work
in the Florida sugar cane industry. Estab¬
lished in 1943, it continues up to today.
The story of the success of this H-2 pro¬
gramme is the story of a felicitous match
between nature and economic circum¬
stances in Florida and the cultural ori¬
entations of British West Indians.
Florida cane is grown under conditions
which do not allow full mechanization.
Such a cane culture is not suited to the
use of cane cutting machines; it needs
skilled and dependable manual labour.
Here nature shapes economics, for if a
machete-wielding man in Florida is to com¬
pete with a harvesting machine in Hawaii,
he has to be skilled. But cutting cane man¬
ually is nasty, back-breaking work that no
West Indian Immigrants in Canada
WEST Indians who migrate to Can¬
ada today are generally better edu¬
cated than their predecessors and
more at home in modern metropolitan com¬
munities. However, in spite of the fact that
most of them come from the countryside and
small towns and have no experience of big
city life, they do not go to the rural areas
of Canada. They are attracted to the large
urban centres of Toronto, Montreal, and Van¬
couver.
Having left their native land for economic
reasons, and with the expectation of eco¬
nomic advancement in their adopted home,
they are ill-prepared to face the reality of
Canadian attitudes towards immigrants. But
West Indians, as well as facing the same
problems as immigrants of whatever race or
origin, are also victims of greater hostility
because of their colour, especially when they
try to obtain housing and employment. Hav¬
ing experienced a marginal existence in the
Wegt Indies, and finding that his basic cultural
and'human values are not recognized in Can¬
ada, the West Indian immigrant often expe¬
riences serious identity problems.
Attempts by West Indians to be accepted
through adapting themselves to the dominant
culture have, with few exceptions, not suc¬
ceeded. Many West Indians are actively par
ticipating in movements which are seeking
to change the present situation in which they
face varying degrees of prejudice and dis¬
crimination. These individuals and groups
are joining forces with Canadian-born blacks,
South Asians and other disadvantaged group
in an effort to eliminate discriminatory prac¬
tices which restrict their full participation in
Canadian society.
The Haitian community in Quebec con¬
stitutes a special case in this respect. First
óf all it has to face the problem of illegal or
clandestine immigrants who wish to leave
Haiti at all costs and cannot receive aid from
the Government when they arrive in Canada.
In the early 1960s, the Haitian diaspora
consisted of highly educated individuals,
mostly professional people, until the political
situation in Haiti gave rise to an entirely dif¬
ferent kind of exodus, especially from the
rural areas of the country. In addition,
because of their physical characteristics and
the African sonority of their mother tongue,
the Haitians quickly form a group which the
officials of the Immigration Ministry describe
as "visible". So far, however, Haitians have
not sought to confine themselves to a ghetto
or to form groups centred on immigrant asso-,
dations.
The evidence suggests that the Haitians
have not encountered major obstacles to
their adaptation to the society and culture
of Quebec either from the two national major¬
ities or from the other groups, in spite of the
universal feeling that the "Creoles" are going
through a difficult period in Quebec. A "third
culture" is beginning to emerge in the Haitian
community, a kind of intermingling born of
the social differences between young Hai¬
tians and their contemporaries in Quebec.
This third culture is formed largely of dis¬
parate, anarchic elements, taken at random
from American and English-speaking West
Indian "négritude". It can easily be imagined
that such influences, added to the pro¬
nounced oral character of Haitian culture may
separate the young generation from the main
trends and currents of life in Quebec and
create an impression of lack of commitment
and marginalization.
Sources : "The West Indian Family in Canada: Prob¬
lems of Adaptation in a Multiracial, Multicultural Soci¬
ety" by Wilson A. Head, in Multiculturalism, vol. Ill No.
12, 1979; and "Questions de Culture: Migrations et
Communautés Culturelles, Institut Québécois de
Recherche sur la Culture.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
one in the world engages in unless the
rewards are real, as indeed they have been.
To be sure, the major element of this
reward is monetary the difference
between what the workers make abroad
and what they would! have made staying
home. But there is another incentive which
explains the popularity of the H-2 pro¬
gramme: the worker is not locked into the
"cane culture",, i.e. the complex and
demeaning life style associated with the
sugar plantation which affected not just
the worker but his whole family. Certainly
the companies' stance toward labour
reflects self-interest, not altruism nor a
particular fondness for West Indians.
Here again the reason for the situation
is economic, since the traditional source
of abundant and thus cheaply available
labour does not exist. It has not been dif¬
ficult, therefore, for the U.S. Department
of Labor to provide certification for this
programme: every effort to recruit local
labour has so far failed. This is where both
economics and culture come in, because
the necessary labour is available in the
West Indies where migration and work
abroad have long been integral parts of
the area's cultural orientations.
An interesting cultural aspect of this
migration is that even before the dawning
of the trade union movement West Indians
tended to organize for improvement.
Today these workers who come for the
five-month season are represented through
their union, the British West Indian Cen
tral Labour Organization. Additionally,
being citizens of small but proudly dem¬
ocratic States such as Jamaica, Barbados,
and St. Vincent, they possess the advan¬
tage of having the support and vigilance
of their Governments which, no doubt, are
keenly aware of the contributions the earn¬
ings of these workers make to the balance
of payments and hard currency situation.
The joint effort in favour of workers'
rights has paid off. Apart from subsidized
room and board, they get a 50 per cent
subsidy for travel to the job, and upon
completion of contract, free travel back.
Workers receive a medical exam before
travelling, and are covered by their own
group hospitalization insurance as well as
State-mandated workers' compensation
for job-related injuries. The goal in nego¬
tiating these subsidies is of course to fulfil
the whole purpose of migratory work:
sending much of the earnings back home.
In a fundamental way, work in the Flor¬
ida sugar industry helps to reinforce their
status back home rather than replicating
the terrible wastage of human lives so typ¬
ical of the history of the sugar plantation.
An interesting comparison can be made
with West Indian farm workers in Canada,
where the programme was established
much later than in the USA. First came
the Jamaicans in 1966, followed in 1976
by workers from the eastern Caribbean and
Mexico. By 1982 there were some 6,000
working on fruit, vegetable and tobacco
farms. Over half of these were Jamaicans.
In Canada as in the United States the eco¬
nomic rationale is the same: the inability
to recruit sufficient native workers.
As distinct from Florida, however,
where only eight large growers are
involved, in Canada the farm workers deal
with small farmers; in 1982, 782 employers
participated. The hourly wage in 1983
ranged from $3.50 to $4.80 per hour. As
in the case of those going to Florida, nearly
all had jobs back home when recruited.
However, those going to Canada tend to
come from a different labour pool: over
half were skilled or semi-skilled workers.
As is to be expected, West Indians indi¬
cate that they travel for the increased pay,
yet fully 22 per cent of those in Canada
indicated that they had travelled for the
experience of being overseas.
Although clearly a very small part of the
overall flow of migrant farm workers, espe¬
cially into the United States, the cases
described illustrate the fact that this type
of work does not have to be exploitative
and degrading to the workers to be bene¬
ficial to the employer. Work in agriculture
does not have to be associated with the
wasting "plantation syndrome."
ANTHONY P. MAINGOT, of Trinidad and
Tobago, is professor of sociology and director
of the graduate programme in International Stu¬
dies at Florida International University, Miami,
USA.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
B E T W E E N TWO C U L TU RE S
The Gulf States
A delicate balance
by Elisabeth Longuenesse THE demographic situation in the
Gulf States (the six members of the
Gulf Co-operation Council Saudi
Arabia, Kuwait, Qatar, Bahrain, United
Arab Emirates, Oman) is unique: in 1980,
of a total population of some thirteen mil¬
lion, it was estimated that over four million
were foreigners, while of a total working
population of some four million three
hundred thousand, about two million five
hundred thousand were foreign workers.
Whereas in Saudi Arabia, which is the
largest of the Gulf States and whose pop¬
ulation constitutes two thirds of the total,
non-Saudi workers accounted for less than
50 per cent of the total working population
in 1980, the proportion of foreigners in the
small Gulf Emirates has reached such lev¬
els that social and cultural imbalances are
getting out of hand. In Qatar 85 per cent
and in the United Arab Emirates 90 per
cent of workers are foreign and three-quar-
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Philippine workers on a construction site
in Riyadh, the capital of Saudi Arabia.
ters of the total population are non-citi¬
zens. In Kuwait over 75 per cent of the
workers and nearly 60 per cent of the pop¬
ulation are non-Kuwaiti.
The situation in Oman and Bahrain
seems to be better balanced. This is
because Oman still has a large rural pop¬
ulation, whilst there has been a relative
decline in immigration to Bahrain, al¬
though this trend is now being reversed.
Since the policy of importing labour
from abroad is of relatively recent origin,
most of these workers are unaccompanied
men and this strong male predominance
has given rise to a very serious population
imbalance. Only in Kuwait and Bahrain,
where immigration has a longer history,
has a better balance been achieved thanks
to the gradual arrival of families and the
subsequent creation of families on the spot.
The immigrants can be divided into three
main cultural groups: the Europeans, who
form a privileged minority and whom we
mention only for the record, the Arabs,
still by far the most numerous, and the
Asians, who have been constantly growing
in number since the mid-1970s.
Unlike immigrant workers in Western
Europe, those in the Gulf States are to
be found in all branches of activity and
at all levels of skill. This is true for all
nationalities, although the pattern of qual¬
ifications is not the same for all of them.
The employment of indigenous workers is
marginal in virtually all sectors except the
administration.
The conditions under which immigration
takes place vary considerably. Strictly
speaking, the prospective immigrant must
have an employment contract before an
entry visa can be granted, unless he man¬
ages to get a job while visiting relations.
There is, however, a lot of illegal immi¬
gration and the status of illegal immigrants
is very precarious. They are at the mercy
of the expulsion measures which the
authorities apply from time to time, but
since they provide a margin of flexibility
for the labour market they are usually tol¬
erated in practice. Owing to the absence "
of local manpower, to the obligation for
a foreigner to have a work permit before
entry, to the fact that foreigners cannot
easily change jobs, and to the prohibition
on foreigners remaining in the country if
they become unemployed, the labour mar¬
ket is extremely rigid.
Apart from illegal immigration there is
another practice which helps to ensure a
supply of marginal, day-to-day manpower.
This consists of the importation of workers ,
quite legally, by someone who is himself
the owner of one or more small businesses.
If he succeeds in obtaining entry visas for
workers in excess of his own needs, he
either throws them on the labour market
to fend for themselves or hires them out
to other employers on a daily basis, retain¬
ing a percentage of their wages for himself.
Foreign workers have no means of
organizing to defend their rights. Trade
unions are forbidden except in Kuwait and
Bahrain where foreigners have the right
to join a union after five years with the
same employer but are not allowed to take
part in elections. So the worker has no
recourse against any possible exploitation,
particularly since in many instances he will
have incurred heavy debts to gain entry
into the country in the first place. Even
if he obtains regular employment it may
be several months before he can save any
money to send to his family.
The vast majority of immigrants remain
on the fringe of society, housed, at worst,
under canvas on the outskirts of towns and,
at best, in collective apartments. More
often they live crowded into dilapidated
UA
0.
©
This group of four teachers in the court¬
yard ofa SaudiArabian school comprises
an Egyptian, a Jordanian, a Palestinian
and a Syrian.
houses in old quarters that have been aban¬
doned by the indigenous inhabitants.
Nearly a third of foreigners resident in
Kuwait were born there, but only 16 per
cent have been living there for more than
ten years, since the majority of the second
generation consists of youngsters less than
ten years old. Already in 1975, 126,500
of the 234,000 children attending school
in Kuwait were foreign. Nevertheless, the
existence of a core, albeit still small, of
older, well-established immigrants has had
an integrating influence on the newer
arrivals.
Life is certainly easier for the worker
who is accompanied by his family, but he
is liable to be more severely affected by
any discrimination to which he may be
subjected. Certainly, he enjoys some of
the advantages of an oil-rich society such
as free medical care and free schooling for
his children (provided that they were born
in Kuwait or their parents have been living
there since 1970 and, above all, that they
don't fall behind in their studies). How¬
ever, scarcity of services and the priority
given to Kuwaiti citizens often oblige the
foreign worker to have recourse to the
private sector. In many cases he is saddled
with an exorbitant rent while access to
subsidized housing or house ownership on
easy terms and grants and allowances of
various kinds are reserved to citizens who
also receive higher wages for similar work.
These frustrations contribute to the
building up of a climate of tension which
may develop into mutual hostility. Asian
immigrants seem to provoke most of the
negative reactions, at least in the press
which blames them for the growth in the
crime rate (not supported by the facts) or
which expresses fear of loss of cultural
identity should they become numerically
predominant. It is true that if immigration
from Asia continues, even at a lower rate,
the question of integration will eventually
be posed in terms of recognizing national
"minorities" that will have become major¬
ities.
ELISABETH LONGUENESSE, French socio¬
logist, is a research assistant at the Centre
National de la Recherche Scientifique, in
France. She worked for several years at the
Centre for Study and Research on the Contem¬
porary Middle East, at Beirut, Lebanon.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
BETWEEN TWO CULTURES
Scandinavia
How to be a good host
by Carolyn Swetland
HOW are migrants adapting to life
in the Scandinavian countries? To
understand the problems of adap¬
tation that migrants face it might be better
to turn the question round and ask: How
are Scandinavians adapting to the presence
of migrants?
Scandinavians tend to think of migrant
workers as being people from Third World
countries, whereas in fact migrant workers
coming from other Scandinavian countries,
Europe and North America are far more
numerous.
During the economic upswing in Europe
during the 1960s Third World migrant
workers were encouraged to come to the
Scandinavian countries by open-door gov¬
ernmental policies aided by active labour
recruitment by private employers. Many
workers came from India, Pakistan and
Bangladesh, with Pakistani's now forming
the largest group (about 7,500).
Just as labour was recruited when it was
needed, so its entry was halted when it
was not. Norway was the last Scandinavian
country to call a halt to immigration (in
1975), but it did so with certain dispen¬
sations which permitted free movement of
labour within the Scandinavian countries
and provided certain special preferential
arrangements for North Americans.
Thus, until some five years ago the Third
World migrant was perceived as an eco¬
nomic element, but now he has become
an ethnic element. Coming from the Third
World and still attached to it in the eyes
of both officials and the public, he is a
"Third World problem" and, in a certain
sense, he is supposed to remain one. An
Indian immigrant, now a school psychol¬
ogist, was asked to provide some migrants
for a radio programme (the broadcasting
station was government owned and con¬
trolled). When he suggested himself as one
of them he was told: "Not you! You are
a successful migrant!"
The ban on Third World immigration
and the arrival of wives and children
changed the situation. The unaccompanied
male worker who, it was assumed, would
eventually return home when no longer
needed, had become a family man appar¬
ently there to stay. This not only affected
the structural situation in the Scandinavian
countries, but also attitudes towards immi¬
grants.
Structurally the Scandinavian States
define the migrant community as an ethnic
minority, their culture as a minority culture
Cover of Immigranten - The Immigrant,
a bilingual (Norwegian-English) quarterly
produced and published by the Immi¬
granten Collective, Oslo. "Norway is not
only for the Norwegians" proclaims the
poster carried by the little girl.
THE IMMIGRANT
>i. j ^im jh. »,-
z*PL
I
©
" <
and their language as a minority language.
They have created various institutions
exclusively concerned with migrants, such
as housing institutions, separate employ¬
ment offices and separate youth clubs, and
subsidized migrants' own organizations as
well as mother-tongue and two-culture
classes in schools and so on. Under this
policy of cultural pluralism, as it has come
to be called, ethnic differentiation has not
only been endorsed, but also encouraged.
What has been the outcome of this dif¬
ferentiation?
Once the migrant becomes eligible for
it, family housing is normally available
either in the older sections in the centres
of Scandinavian cities or, more recently,
in new suburban housing areas in the out¬
skirts. These areas are not limited exclu¬
sively to migrants, but in practice a high
percentage of migrant families live in them
since they are directed there by the housing
institutions to which they have to turn for
help in finding accommodation. It is not
uncommon to find that as much as 85 per
cent of the population of these areas con¬
sists of immigrants with the remaining 15
per cent being made up of Scandinavians,
including a number of Scandinavian girls
who have married migrants.
The phrase "once the migrant becomes
eligible for it" calls for some explanation.
In Norway, for example, there is a curious
ruling that an immigrant cannot bring his
wife until he has family housing, and he
is not eligible for family housing unless his
wife is there!
Separate employment offices for
migrants result in the sifting and control
of re-employment opportunities, job pref¬
erences and training programmes.
Migrants working on North Sea oil rigs are
a special case. Since the rigs are classified
as "ships" they are not subject to the
labour legislation that prevails on land.
Spaniards working on them are often
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
''- \ 1. :'f. ' W
recruited in Rotterdam, taken out directly
by boat and never set foot on Norwegian
soil. As a result these workers do not figure
in Norwegian labour statistics.
State subsidization of migrants' own
organizations led to the destruction of the
original single-organization system which
for a time offered a united front in defence
of migrants' interests. In Norway, for
example, the plurality of subsidies has
resulted in twenty-six separate and distinct
Indian organizations receiving State funds
for a total Indian population of a little over
two thousand. Ethnic youth clubs are also
given financial support.
The policy of cultural pluralism may give
the impression that all cultures are free
to flourish on an equal basis in the Scan¬
dinavian countries. But is this the case in
the schools?
The debate on the pros and cons of
mother-tongue teaching in schools is far
from being resolved. Without exception
the migrants' own organizations demand
mother-tongue teaching. Migrant parents
demand proficiency in the language of the
host country.
The State and local authorities make
proposals that chop and change from year
to year. A two-teacher, two-language, two-
culture class system is established for
grades 1 to 9. Two years later it is restricted
to grades 1 to 3. A series of changes and
new proposals that were later withdrawn
provoked one migrant father, himself a
Immigrant girls in Norway. The first signs
of adaptation to a culture which will soon
confront their own?
two-culture class teacher, to voice the opin¬
ion of many migrant parents when he
declared: "We want an end to experi¬
mentation in the teaching of migrant chil¬
dren."
Throughout all this the goal presumably
remains the same to educate migrant chil¬
dren in such a way as to place them on
an equal footing and to make them com¬
petitive with indigenous children when
they leave school. However, to be com¬
petitive with Scandinavian children the
migrant child has to know three languages.
Even a Swede, a Dane or a Norwegian
has to learn English in addition to his
mother tongue if he is to obtain anything
other than a menial job. Learning the lan¬
guage of the country in which he lives and
works, when that language is itself a minor¬
ity language, does not take the migrant
child very far. It could even be argued that,
apart from acquiring a minimum of nec¬
essary phrases in the language of the host
country, the migrant would do better to
become proficient in English.
No matter how well intentioned the
thinking behind it may be, cultural plu¬
ralism has differentiation as its starting
point and defines the migrant on an ethnic-
minority basis. And it is the host country
that defines what a minority culture is.
Today's man is a migrant. If he is treated
as a member of a minority when he arrives
in a white industrialized country, it is
because he has been ethnically labelled.
That he is part of a minority group in a
particular host country is one thing. For
him to be treated as a member of a minority
is another.
The Third World migrant, often a for¬
mer colonial subject, no longer sees him¬
self as he was taught to, that is to say, with
reference to the white industrial world, to
the white model. His models are changing.
The trouble lies in the fact that the former
model seems to be unaware of this change.
A migrant, as opposed to a man who
has never moved, is a highly adapted and
adaptable person. He has to be. In order
to survive he has had to learn the ins and
outs of other nations' cultures, languages,
income tax and social security systems. The
problem of adapting does not rest, and
never has rested with the migrant.
CAROLYN SWETLAND, Norwegian anthro¬
pologist, is a specialist and lecturer on migration
problems. She is the author of several studies
and articles including "The Ghetto of the Soul"
(Unesco, 1978) and "Migrant Workers, Lan¬
guage and Culture: Ethnolinguistic Models"
(Unesco, 1981).
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The psychology of migrant
workers
by Ana Vásquez
WHAT is there in common
between Joâo, who had to leave
his wife and children back in
Portugal in 1978, and Mohamed, the North
African shepherd, who only arrived in
Europe a year ago? Does Mirjana,
Mohamed's twenty-five-year-old wife,
have the same feelings and make the same
These two recent (1985) works by the
French sculptor Arman stand in the fore¬
court of Paris's Saint-Lazare station and
mightbe seen as a monument to rail trans¬
port, but they could also be interpreted
as a comment on time-dominated big-city
life (left, L'Heuçe de Tous, "Everyone's
Time") and on the improbability ofescape
(right, Consigne à Vie, "Left Luggage
Office for Life").
plans as Maria, who is going on forty? Over
and above the raw data of the figures illus¬
trating the trends and scale of the migration
problem, what we are interested in finding
out is how human beings cope with their
transplantation and what upsets it causes.
In the first place it should be remem¬
bered that migrants' attitudes, experiences
and plans vary from one period to another.
For example, they will not have the same
outlook if they are only just preparing to
leave their own country as they will if they
have already spent five or ten years as
"foreigners" in another country. Hence,'
in psychological terms, a distinction can
be made between several key stages in the
actual experience of migration.
This is the standpoint from which the
analysis attempted here has been carried
out. It is exclusively concerned with men
and women emigrating to Europe. A host
of studies have shown that people emi¬
grating to the Americas leave their country
of origin for good, whereas those who go
to work in the leading industrial countries
of Europe visualize their stay as tempo¬
rary. The migrant's psychological situation
differs significantly in these two cases.
It is more harrowing for people to leave
their own country when their self-confi¬
dence has been undermined by the expe¬
riences they have gone through. Migrants
leave because they earn a poor living or
because they are unemployed. They are
accordingly placed in a position where they
are dominated, with all the demeaning con¬
sequences that implies. Leaving entails a
twofold effort. The first is psychological;
it entails an effort to overcome loss of self-
esteem and to look forward to the prospect
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
of vocational training or a fob abroad. The
second is material and entails finding ways
and means of making the journey.
Strongly influenced by the images con¬
veyed by the media and by the stories told
by people who have returned home, which
always tend to exaggerate the "wonders"
of foreign countries, migrants have an
idealized picture of the country to which
they are so keen to go. The "credibility
gap" between the country they dream of
and the real-life situation they will find
there causes their first traumatic experi¬
ence. This is compounded not only by their
living and working conditions but by their
meagre knowledge of the language of the
host country, behaviour patterns in large
industrial cities, administrative formalities
which they do not understand, and even
mechanical appliances which they look
upon as traps. Above all, however, a trau¬
matic situation is created by the discrim¬
inatory, if not overtly racist, attitudes to
which they are exposed. As they feel ill
at ease and anonymous in an unfamiliar
situation which they are unable to control,
the view they have of themselves is utterly
confused.
Admitting to the resulting disappoint¬
ment and sense of disarray would be tan¬
tamount to acknowledging failure, but that
is something the migrants cannot afford,
since their only strength lies in their desire
Members of a Turkish migrant family
browse before an array of TV screens in
a store In the Fed. Rep. of Germany.
to make a success of the plans they have
made. In many instances, therefore, they
develop defence mechanisms in order to
cope more easily with the difficulties con¬
fronting them.
Consequently, they withdraw into them¬
selves and into their community, since they
only feel at ease among their own people
and tend to idealize their country of origin.
This is reflected in the importance they
attach to certain features that seem to have
no bearing on the success or failure of their
emigration plans, such as loyalty to their
own folk or appreciation of traditional fam¬
ily cooking, or in their readiness to forget
the unemployment and poverty in their
country of origin.
Migrants also tend to become more frag¬
ile and to display somatization patterns;
when they are ill, they suffer from a range
of symptoms which are difficult to identify
and which may even give rise to certain
forms of mental pathology.
After a period of time which varies from
case to case, the migrants manage to over¬
come these initial stumbling blocks and
embark on a process of transculturation.
From the psychological standpoint, the
main feature of this stage lies in the con¬
flicts they experience whenever they have
to compare their habitual practices, norms
and values, in other words their original
culture, with those of the host country.
In their country of origin, the extended
family and the community deal with many
aspects of everyday life which are handled
by institutions in the industrial countries.
For example, the social security, family
allowance and day nursery systems require
information that has to be provided on
special sheets or forms within prescribed
deadlines. This is something foreigners find
hard to grasp.
Moreover, urban time and space are also
regulated. Even in the places where they
live, migrants are subject to constraints
which they regard as infringements of their
personal freedom. They cannot perform
certain religious or family ceremonies such
as the "sacrifice of the sheep", because
the smell and the noise will inconvenience
their neighbours; nor are they allowed to
make a noise after certain hours.
The organization of time in industrial
cities is particularly demanding: everyday
life is compartmentalized, with set times
for meals and leisure pursuits, and people
have to hurry from place to place. The
comments made by migrants point to the
difficulties they face in adapting to the new
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
as when they claim "The people
here rush around all the time, it's exhaust¬
ing", or "At the factory your every move
is watched and you're even timed when
you go to the toilet", or else "I am under
pressure because you always have to be
in a hurry. By the evening, I'm so ex¬
hausted that I feel as if I've had all the
stuffing knocked out of me".
Social relationships, especially between
men and women, are baffling and cause
tensions. Gestures that are meant to be
polite are taken for impudence, and signs
of friendship are misinterpreted. After
some bewilderment which prompts them
to withdraw into their shells, migrants
reach the point where they try to com¬
prehend these behaviour patterns and to
compare them with their own. Then they
slowly embark on a process of change
which eventually comes to affect significant
aspects of their personality , and cultural
identity.
After a while, when they meet newly
arrived compatriots, they realize how they
have changed when, for example, they feel
embarrassed by the newcomers' "noisy
behaviour in the street" or by "the way
they look at women". But even though
the migrants adopt some of the norms of
the host country; they are still "out on a
limb" as it were, torn between their deep-
rooted and unconscious attachment to their
At this spectacular naturalization cere¬
mony at the Hollywood Bowl in 1954,
7,600 people from 68 countries became
citizens of the United States.
native culture, which they do not wish to
betray, and their newly acquired outlook,
which they feel to be more suited to the
continued fulfilment of their plans.
"I should like to open a grocery store
in the village, but I haven't managed to
save enough money yet. I've been in Paris
for fifteen years.... What worries me most
is that my son wants to stay here, my
daughter would like to go on with her stud¬
ies... and even my wife is not all that keen
on going back." These comments by a
migrant worker reflect a situation that has
become fairly widespread and arises when,
after a period of time, the members of the
family start to question the dream of going
back home.
The teenagers speak and write badly the
language of the country of origin , and have
few real ties with the mythical land which
is meant to be "home", especially since
their friends are "over here". Women
sometimes without even realizing it find
that they enjoy greater social independ¬
ence. They often dread going back to a
situation in which they would again be
compelled to live under the thumb of the
family.
Such uncertainty can be distressing, for
emigrants feel that they have endured all
kinds of ordeals because they were going
to succeed and return home. Hence, giving
up the idea of returning is tantamount to
making a far-reaching appraisal of the very
meaning of their lives.
They have to ask themselves whether
they are going to stay and become inte¬
grated. However, in some European coun¬
tries the adoption of such a course is to
some extent a gamble, given the extent
of discriminatory and even aggressive reac¬
tions towards immigrant workers and their
children.
What choice lies open to them? The
uncertainties and the issues we have
described form the backdrop to the lives
of migrants and place them and their chil¬
dren in a kind of nomansland which often
prevents them from making and carrying
out long-term plans.
ANA VASQUEZ, French psychologist of
Chilean origin, is currently engaged in research
with the Centre National de la Recherche Scien¬
tifique, in France. She formerly taught edu¬
cational psychology at the University of Chile
and is the author ofsome 30 studies and articles
on the psychological problems ofdisplaced per¬
sons and the processes of transculturation.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Return ticket
The problems of going back
by Eric-Jean Thomas and Catherine Wihtol de Wenden
THE flows of migration to the West¬
ern countries which took place after
the Second World War, and espe¬
cially from the 1960s onwards, differed
from earlier migratory movements in that
they were primarily intended to be tem¬
porary.
In the wake of those immigrants who
took their families and left their homeland
to conquer a new world, the immigrants
of the 1960s scarcely entertained the idea
of settling in the host country on a per¬
manent basis. Their intention was to find
better paid jobs, to put some money aside,
and then to go back and turn their savings
to good account.
The clampdown on immigration decided
by the industrialized countries after the
1973 oil crisis had the unexpected effect
of increasing the immigrant population res¬
ident in those countries and prolonging
their stay. At the same time, there was
a significant decline in the number of sea¬
sonal returns coinciding with vacation
periods.
This paradoxical situation stemmed from
the fact that restrictions on immigration
initially applied only to the workers them¬
selves who, since they expected more strin¬
gent regulations to be introduced, did their
utmost to bring their families over to join
them. As a result, many migrant workers
postponed their return home indefinitely,
and, afraid that they might not gain re-
admittance to the host country, refrained
from returning to their country of origin
even for a temporary visit.
For example, between 1974 and 1982,
an estimated 100,000 Portuguese returned
home, whereas some 200,000 emigrated
during the same period. The same phe¬
nomenon also occurred in other sending
countries with different economic struc¬
tures, such as Finland, where the number
of returns home fell by 7 per cent in 1982.
A study on Turkey carried out in 1980
showed that the return phenomenon had
been reduced to a mere trickle.
For this reason, some European receiv¬
ing countries, including France and the
Federal Republic of Germany, have
attempted in the last decade to introduce
policies aimed at encouraging immigrants
to return home. These policies raise ques¬
tions of principle which were irrelevant in
Egyptian migrant workers returning home
after two years in Iraq
the liberal climate of international migra¬
tions which still prevailed at the beginning
of the twentieth century.
The idea that States had the right to
encourage immigrant workers to return to
their countries of origin in a situation
where labour was surplus to requirements
slowly emerged between the two World
Wars. Today, no European State can take
peremptory measures for the collective
expulsion of migrants. It is widely accepted
that the loss of residence entitlement,
which entails the loss of acquired social
benefits, should give rise to compensation.
As a result, there has been a gradual
recognition of a right associated with the
return process, which is no longer rejected
either by immigrants or by the trade
unions, which are now more concerned
with negotiating the amount of compen¬
sation to be paid. In a context of economic
crisis, workers who are nationals of the
host country sometimes protest against the
discriminatory nature of such a right which
does not apply to them and which gives
them the impression that immigrants are
favoured when it comes to leaving their
jobs.
This thinking about the return process
gradually began to spread in the receiving
countries when they closed their frontiers
to foreign workers. In a sense it was
because immigrants were no longer leaving
that the host countries "invented" the idea
of giving them money to encourage them
to return to their own countries.
The fact is that policies to incite immi¬
grants to retufn raise questions of legality
both for the countries which carry them
out and, increasingly, for the countries of
origin. In the host countries, providing
assistance for return to the countries of
origin is theoretically supposed to reassure
public opinion which is anxious about the
immigrant problem, but in practice it is
a costly, not very effective, and sometimes
even damaging exercise. It may well be
asked what purpose it serves, apart from
having symbolic implications and serving
as a bargaining counter between the States
concerned.
To what extent does the return of the
migrants benefit the countries from which
they emigrated? In fact, although their
return may appear, at first sight, to be an
advantage for the country of origin, a num¬
ber of recent studies have shown that this
is by no means always the case.
In terms of vocational training, the mar¬
ginal status of foreign workers in the host
country is little incentive for them to
improve their qualifications. The govern¬
ments of the host countries have clearly
recognized this, since those which attempt
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
to promote the return of immigrants have
introduced a variety of measures to
improve the job qualifications of would-be
returnees in line with the requirements of
the countries of origin.
However, these intentions are not
always easy to fulfil, especially since the
immigrant workers are reluctant to take
time off work for vocational training,
thereby foregoing immediate financial
gain. The problem is further compounded
by the fact that most of the prospective
returnees are unskilled workers.
Lastly, it must be stressed that on-the-
job training in factories and other work¬
places is primarily geared to the needs of
the industrial society of the host country
and will be of little value to the country
of origin.
In terms of financial input to their coun¬
try of origin, regardless of whether the
immigrants return as "failures" or "suc¬
cesses", they will try to acquire a social
and economic status higher than that they
enjoyed when they left. The vast majority
of the "returnees" aspire to be self-
employed and put their savings into those
sectors of the economy in which they are
most likely to achieve this status.
In agriculture, unless they have a well-
thought-out plan, they often use their sav¬
ings to purchase more or less unproductive,
land and equipment that cannot be easily
serviced.
The purchase or construction of a house
is one of the main purposes for which they
use their savings. However, such an invest¬
ment can hardly be said to be productive
and may entail a high social cost in urban
areas.
The tertiary sector of the economy, espe¬
cially small independent businesses, is the
big magnet for their savings. Such small
businesses, of which one-man taxi services
are typical, are notoriously unproductive
and are liable to have parasitic effects on
the economy of the country of return.
Lastly, savings are often channelled into
the purchase of consumer goods. As a rule
this has an adverse effect on the economy
This work by the Belgian artist René
Magritte ( La Maison de Verre, 1939) could
be seen as the depiction oía man eternally
looking back to his past or dreaming of
a return to his homeland.
in that it stimulates domestic demand for
imported goods.
Studies carried out so far do not suggest
that any change in social and political atti¬
tudes is intrinsic to the migration process.
For if emigration gives rise to specific polit¬
ical or family behaviour patterns different
from those of the country of origin, con¬
siderable caution must be exercised before
concluding that such patterns will survive
after the migrants have returned home.
Finally, it must be emphasized, firstly,
that the percentage of immigrants return¬
ing home is extremely small and that until
recently the countries of origin displayed
little interest in the problem. Secondly,
although the structural effects of the return
of immigrants are by no means clearly
grasped, they are limited and, in general,
have a disturbing impact on the economy
of the home country. Thirdly, it is becom¬
ing clear that policies to encourage
migrants to return can only be put into
effect by the host countries as a result of
far-reaching concerted action with the
countries of origin.
The return of immigrants can only
become a reality and be a source of profit
to the emigration countries if negotiations,
which will have to be bilateral, at least in
the early stages, lead in the long run to
concerted action between these countries
and the immigration countries.
ERIC-JEAN THOMAS, of France, is a lawyer
with the Paris Court of Appeal and teaches at
the University of Paris. He is the author ofmany
studies on the legal aspects of migration. He
was director of a comparative study entitled
Immigrant Workers in Europe: their Legal Sta¬
tus, published by Unesco in 1982.
CATHERINE WIHTOL DE WENDEN, of
France, is engaged in research with the Centre
National de la Recherche Scientifique and is
a consultant with the Organization for Economic
Co-operation and Development (OECD). She
has published many articles on the political
aspects of migration, including a work entitled
Les Immigrés dans la Cité (1978).
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 68 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 120 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
52 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun¬
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply official
endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/
or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan
48100, U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc.,
111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell
Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Roy Malkin
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broïdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul).
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene: Vito-
mir Sudarski (Beigrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen Helsinki)
Swedish: Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-
in-Chief in Paris.
34
BRODARD GRAPHIQUE, COULOMMIERS - Dépôt légal C 1 - Septembre 1985 - IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
PHOTOCOMPOSITION/PHOTOGRAVURE DAWANT - 13, rue des Arquebusiers - 75003 PARIS.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Two Unesco books on migrant workers
LIVING
Ita-nHD
CULTURES
The Socio-Cultural Situation
of Migrant Workers and their Families
Living in two cultures presents a collection of
studies on the social and cultural situation of
immigrants in Europe and the United States.
The first part is concerned with the conditions,
nature and effects of official language training
programmes for migrant workers and their
families. The second part addresses the partic¬
ular problems faced by female migrants and how
the characteristics of the old culture affect their
adaptation to the requirements of the new.
1982 325 pages
ISBN 92-3-1018669-8
140 French francs
Co-published with Gower Publishing Co. Ltd,
who have exclusive sales rights in the United
Kingdom.
Immigrant workers in Europe: their legal status
shows how the status of immigrant workers is
determined with reference to the economic,
political and social conditions peculiar to each
host country and, particularly, how the legal
machinery controlling immigration affects the
future of migrants. Chapters discuss the specific
situation in Belgium, France, the Netherlands,
the Federal Republic of Germany, Sweden and
Turkey.
1982 245 pages
ISBN 92-3-101867-1
50 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 1 75,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-101 1 , Vienna. BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague
1; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 1 1 - 27 Prague 1 (Permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1 , SF-001 00
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2, -
01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de ('Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport ABT, P.O.B. 149 -
H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 31 4/1 486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 188 Enghtab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158, P.O. Box 11365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Vis Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water. Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 1 1 3. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd.,
Quran House, Mfangano Street, P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd,
POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod. Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.'
Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 - 9494 Schaan.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service,
Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1 1 18, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1 177 Sentrum - Oslo 1, Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional
Office for Book development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi
Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES.
National Book Store, Inc. 701, Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra
Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road,
Singapore 2261. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern
Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH
AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier [single copies) only: Central
News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue -Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
1 1 , CCP. 1 2-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Pamt,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. TURKEY. Haset Kitapovi A.S.,
Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC 1 X 9 DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 1001 7. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor, Ml 48106. USSR.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121200. YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, P.O. Box 4227, Aden. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, Mica 30/1 1 , Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
m
Y
K
'fit
ï?
Twenty million migrant workers
Estimates of the number of migrants in the world vary widely,
partly because of the difficulty of obtaining reliable statistics from
some areas and partly because of discrepancies in the definition
of migrants. Leaving aside refugees, tourists, pilgrims and
nomads, the major distinguishing feature of migrants is that they
move to a country of which they are not nationals for the purpose
of employment. On the basis of the definition of migrants as
"persons not possessing the citizenship of their country of employ¬
ment", the International Labour Office estimates the number of
economically active migrants in today's world as at least 19.7
to 21 .7 million. Above, a cosmopolitan scene at the Notting Hill
carnival. London.
]]>
</page>
</document>
