<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="067988eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
Mediterranean
worlds
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
951
*m
im
Ui
w
A time to live....
40 The Arab Republic of Egypt
The life of the street
The Mediterranean is a region with a tradition
of urbanization stretching back to very early
times. From Byblos to Barcelona, from Kai-
rouan to Dubrovnik, from Istanbul to Cairo,
towns and cities proliferated and became an
essential feature of the landscape and of social
life. In the Mediterranean city the home is a
haven of privacy, in sharp contrast to the web
of alleyways, streets and squares which pro
vide the setting for public life. Especially for
the menfolk, the street is a theatre for the
drama of self-presentation, a place for relaxa¬
tion and work, where the barber shaves his
customers, and children do their homework or
play beneath the watchful eyes of the women
who knit or sew. Photo shows a street scene in
the old city of Cairo.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the wortd
Editorial
The Mediterranean, which the Romans sometimes called
Mare Nostrum ("Our Sea") or Mare Internum ("Inland
Sea") is one of the great crossroads of history. The land
bridges formed when its water level fell during the Ice Ages were
crossed by the early hominids from Africa, and later some of the
world's oldest cities such as Byblos in the Lebanon and Cadiz in
Spain grew up on or near it. Its shores gave birth to outstanding
civilizations whose influence spread far and wide, helping to shape
many features of the modern world. From the Greco-Roman and
Christian heritage arose the civilization of Western Europe and the
vast Byzantine-Orthodox world which would stretch beyond the
Urals. And Islam, born on the periphery of the Mediterranean,
would develop brilliantly throughout the region, as far as such
European countries as Spain where it left a profound imprint.
But the existence of a diversity of civilizations that were in some
cases mutually hostile did not prevent the emergence over the
centuries of a distinctive "Mediterranean" way of thinking and
living born of the long interpénétration ofcultures and rooted in the
geographical realities of the Inland Sea.
This issue of the Unesco Courier is an attempt to chart the
essential features of the Mediterranean ethos. In the lead article,
one of the world's great specialists in Mediterranean studies, the
French historian Fernand Braudel, paints a general historical por¬
trait of the region, while other specialists look at such major aspects
as the habitat, urban civilization and marine ecology.
But steeped though it is in ancient history, the Mediterranean
basin is a region whose European, African and Asian constituent
parts are today in the throes of change, a region where conflicts
involving democratization, development and national and cultural
identity often arise in acute form and where the industrial world and
the developing world coexist, often within a single country (to the
point that some consider the region to be the Third World of
Europe). On the one hand it is, perhaps, a region of friction and
imbalance; on the other it is fertile terrain for the mutual
knowledge and collaboration between different worlds that Unesco
and the United Nations system as a whole seek to encourage, a fact
which explains Unesco's profound and longstanding interest in the
region.
Ever since Homeric times and the ancient Egyptian "Book of the
Dead", the Mediterranean has also been an area of intense literary
creativity. As a symbolic and admittedly inadequate tribute to this
flowering we also present in this issue a garland of texts and poems
by Mediterranean writers past and present.
Cover: Photomontage by Georges Servat
Editor-in-Chief: Edouard Glissant
December 1985
38th year
4 The Mediterranean: Land, Sea, History
by Fernand Braudel
13 Transformation and tradition in Mediterranean Europe
by Salvador Giner ''
21 Unesco and cooperation in the Mediterranean
23 A region in search of itself
by Paolo Apolito
27 Public spaces and private faces
Patterns of urban living
by Maurice Aymard
36 Profile of an inland sea
by Ramón Margallef
39 An Action Plan for the Mediterranean
40 A cultural crossroads
by Giovanni Dotoli
42 The birthplace of submarine archaeology
by Selim Morcos
A time to live...
Egypt: The life of the street
Published monthly in 32 languages English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish A selection in Braille is published
by Unesco French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish quarterly in English, French,
The United Nations Educational, Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque Spanish and Korean
Scientific and Cultural Organization Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. German Persian Korean Bulgarian
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek ISSN 0041-5278
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
N° 12-1985-CPD-85-3-429A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The Mediterranean:
Land,
by Fernand Braudel
Sea,
History
WHAT is the Mediterranean? A
thousand things at once. Not one
landscape, but landscapes with¬
out number. Not one sea, but a succession
of seas. Not one civilization, but a number
of civilizations, superimposed one on top of
the other. To travel in the Mediterranean
region is to find the Roman world in Leba¬
non, prehistory in Sardinia, Greek cities in
"In both Its physical and Its human
setting, the Mediterranean crossroads,
the Mediterranean patchwork, leaves a
coherent Image In the mind as a system
In which everything mingles and Is then
recast to form a new, original unity."
Below, vines growing on stony ground In
the South of France.
Sicily, the Arab presence in Spain, and
Turkish Islam in Yugoslavia. It is to reach
far back in time, to the megalithic buildings
of Malta and the pyramids of Egypt. It is to
encounter ancient things that still live on in
juxtaposition with the ultra-modern: beside
the deceptive immobility of Venice are the
heavy industries of Mestre; beside the
fisherman's boat, which is like the bark
sailed by Ulysses, are huge tankers, and
trawlers that ravage the sea bed. It is to
plunge into the archaism of insular
societies, and at the same time to wonder at
the extreme youthfulness of very old cities
which are exposed to all the winds of culture
and profit and which for centuries have kept
watch over the sea and lived on its
resources.
All this is because the Mediterranean is a
very ancient crossroads on which, for
thousands of years, everything has con¬
verged men, beasts of burden, vehicles,
merchandise, ships, ideas, religions and the
arts of living. Even plants. With the excep¬
tion of the olive tree, the vine and wheat
which were growing in the region at a very
early stage almost all the plants that we
think of as Mediterranean originated far
from the sea. If Herodotus, the father of
history, who lived in the fifth century BC,
were to return to earth and join the tourists
of today, he would face many surprises. I
imagine him, wrote the French historian
Lucien Febvre, "revisiting the places he
knew in the eastern Mediterranean. How
astonishing it all is! He cannot remember
ever having seen these golden fruits hanging
on dark-green bushes orange-trees,
lemon-trees, tangerine-trees. Why, they
were brought from the Far East by the
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
You must take a well-cut oar andgo on tillyou reach a
people who know nothing ofthe sea and never use salt
with theirfood, so that our crimson-painted ships andthe
long oars that serve those ships as wings are quite beyond
their ken.
Homer
(9th century BC)
"The reason for the folds and fractures In
the Mediterranean, for the Juxtaposition
of sea depths and mountain peaks, Is a
restless and still seething geology, the
effects of which have not been effaced by
time." Above, view of Stromboll, one of
the Aeolian Islands In the Tyrrhenian Sea
north of Sicily. The Islands are so called
because In Antiquity they were thought to
be the home of Aeolus, the lord of the
winds. Crowned with a plume of smoke,
the volcano which forms the island Is
constantly active.
Arabs! These strange, oddly-shaped spiky
plants and flower stalks with their outland¬
ish names cactus, agaves, aloes and prick¬
ly pears he never saw such things in his
life. Why, they are from the Americas! And
these tall trees with light-coloured leaves,
which yet have a Greek name, eucalyptus
he never saw their like. Why, they come
from Australia! And the cypresses, which,
like the other trees, he has never seen, are
Persian. So much for the setting. But the
simplest meal brings him more surprises
the tomato from Peru, the egg-plant from
India, the pimento from Guyana, sweet
corn from Mexico, rice the gift of the Arabs,
not to mention the bean, the potato, the
peach-tree, a native of the mountains of
China which became Iranian , and tobacco . "
Yet all these things are now part of the
Mediterranean scene. "Today it would be
impossible to imagine the Riviera without
orange-trees, Tuscany without cypresses,
or vegetable stalls without pimentos."
And if we were to draw up a list of the
peoples of the Mediterranean those born
on its shores, the descendants of the men
who, in far-off days, sailed its waters or
cultivated its soil and terraced fields, as well
as all the new-comers who invaded it in their
turn would we not have the same impress¬
ion as we had when we catalogued its plants
and fruit?
In both its physical and its human setting,
the Mediterranean crossroads, the
Mediterranean patchwork, leaves a co¬
herent image in the mind as a system in
which everything mingles and then is recast
to form a new, original unity. How can this
undeniable oneness, this profound essence
of the Mediterranean, be explained? Sever¬
al approaches will be needed. The explana¬
tion lies not only in nature, which has
played a significant part, nor only in man,
who has obstinately bound all together; it
lies in both the blessings of nature and its
curses, which are equally abundant, and in
the manifold labours of man, both past and
present; in other words, it lies in an endless
succession of chances, accidents, and re¬
peated successes. (...)
On a map of the world the Mediterranean
is a mere slash in the earth's crust, a narrow
spindle stretching from Gibraltar to the
Isthmus of Suez and the Red Sea. Frac-
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
^ . , _r
-** ~""~ :~~Á "-~t^ It,
** ' f -, T?""^"? -» .
"Nature, history, and the quintessence of
Ufe differ from north to south of the sea....
In the direction of Europe and Its peninsu¬
las rises the screen of mountains.
Southwards, with the exception of the
tree-entwined djebels of northern Africa,
there is the desert, a sea of rocks or sand;
andbehindlies the Sahara, the vastness of
Black Africa and, extending beyond It, the
deserts ofAsia...." Above, expanse of salt
androck in the Mzab region ofthe Algerian
Sahara.
WhereverI travel Greece wounds me.
On Pelion among the chestnut trees the Centaur's shirt
slipped through the leaves tofoldaround my body
as I climbed the slope and the sea came after me
climbing too like mercury in a thermometer
till wefound the mountain waters.
On Santorini touching islands that were sinking
hearing apipeplay somewhere on thepumice stone
my hand was nailed to the gunwale
by an arrow shot suddenly
from the confines ofa vanishedyouth.
George Seferis
(1900-1971)
Move onward, little she-goats, onward, once-happyflock!
No more shall I, stretched out in some green dingle here,
Watch you poisedfaroffon the bushy brows ofa hillside.
No more singingfor me, no takingyou to browse,
My little goats, on bitter willow and cloverflower.
Virgil
(C.70-C.19 BC)
tures, faults, subsidence and folds in the
Tertiary period produced extremely deep
basins and, as a counterpart to their depths,
endless garlands of young, high mountains
with jagged outlines. Near Cape Matapan is
a depression 4,600 metres deep, which
could easily cover the loftiest peak in
Greece, 2,985-metre-high Mount Olympus.
These mountains jut out into the sea,
sometimes narrowing it down to a corridor
of salt water: at Gibraltar, in the Straits of
Bonifacio, in the Straits of Messina with
their swirling whirlpools of Scylla and
Charybdis, and along the Dardanelles and
the Bosphorus. Here, the sea is nothing but
rivers, or merely inlets.
These inlets, straits and mountains ar¬
ticulate liquid space. They delineate auton¬
omous realms: the Black Sea; the Aegean;
the Adriatic, which was long the possession
of the Venetians; and the much larger Tyr¬
rhenian Sea. This division of the sea into a
series of basins is the mirror image of the
division of the land into separate tracts: the
Balkan peninsula, Asia Minor, Italy, the
Iberian peninsula and North Africa.
Yet through this picture runs a line with¬
out which it is impossible to make sense of
the history of the Mediterranean from the
age of the Greek and Phoenician settle¬
ments until modern times. Geography and
history conspired to trace down the middle
a frontier of shores and islands which runs
from north to south, dividing the sea into
two hostile worlds. If we follow this fron¬
tier, from Corfu and the Strait of Otranto,
which half cuts off the Adriatic, as far as
Sicily and the coast of what is now Tunisia,
to the east of it we are in the Orient, to the
west, in the Occident, in the full, classical
sense of these terms. It is not surprising that
this frontier is the great line where battles
were once fought Actium, Preveza,
Lepanto, Malta, Zama and Djerba. (...)
The reason for the folds and fractures in
the Mediterranean, for the juxtaposition of
sea depths and mountain peaks, is a restless
and still seething geology, the effects of
which have not been effaced by time. It
explains why the sea is scattered with is¬
lands and peninsulas, the remnants of land
masses some of which have been buried
beneath the sea and others torn to shreds; it
explains why the jagged mountains have
not yet been extensively eroded; and it
explains why there are earthquakes and
fiery volcanoes which often grumble, fall
asleep, and dramatically reawaken.
Geology explains why there are so many
mountains in the Mediterranean region.
What a procession of recent mountains!
lofty, angular mountains that pierce the
skin of the Mediterranean countryside like
a stony skeleton the Alps, the Apennines,
the Balkans, the Taurus, Lebanon, the
Atlas, the Spanish mountain chains and the
Pyrenees! (...)
Yet some parts of the Mediterranean
coast are not mountainous. In the north, the
coast of Languedoc as far as the Rhône
delta, and the low-lying coast of Veneria on
the Adriatic. But the main exception to the
rule is in the south the long, extraordinari¬
ly flat, almost featureless littoral which
stretches from the Tunisian Sahel to the
Nile delta and the mountains of Lebanon.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
"The Mediterranean Is honeycombed with
sea and land routes....llnked together. All
these routes form a system for the
movement of traffic. This system, I think,
Is the last element In our understanding
of the Mediterranean, which Is, In the full
sense of the term, space-movement."
Top, fragment of a marble group (1st
century BC) unearthed at Sperlonga (Ita¬
ly), possibly depleting the helmsman of
Ulysses' ship; above, rigging of an Egyp¬
tian boat depicted In a detail of a bas-
relief from Luxor (middle of the 2nd
millennium BC); right, a felucca on the
Nile In modern times.
On these endless, monotonous coasts, the
Sahara is in direct contact with the Inland
Sea. Seen from an aeroplane, two huge flat
surfaces the desert and the sea lie edge
to edge; their colours clash, one ranging
from blue to violet and even black, the
other from white to ochre and orange.
The desert is a strange world which brings
to the seashore the depths of Africa and the
restlessness of the nomadic life. Its ways of
life are quite unlike those of the mountain
regions. This part of the Mediterranean is in
opposition to the other, and is constantly
insisting on its place. Nature paved the way
for this duality, which might even be called
a congenital hostility. But history has mixed
the different ingredients, just as salt and
water are mixed in the sea.
And so when he listens to the Mediterra¬
nean concert, Western man should not only
hear the voices which are familiar to him;
there are other voices which he does not
know, and the keyboard is meant for two
hands. Nature, history, and the quintess¬
ence of life differ from north to south of the
sea and whether one is looking northwards
or southwards. In the direction of Europe
and its peninsulas rises the screen of moun
tains. Southwards, with the exception of the
tree-entwined djebels of northern Africa,
there is the desert, a sea of rocks or sand;
and behind lies the Sahara, the vastness of
Black Africa and, extending beyond it, the
deserts of Asia.(...)
Essentially, it is the climate that gives
unity to the Mediterranean. It is a very
special climate, which changes little from
one end of the sea to the other, and unites
different types of scenery and ways of life.
For it is virtually independent of local
physical conditions, shaped by two external
influences, the Atlantic Ocean to the west
and the Sahara to the south. Each of these
giants leaves its dwelling at regular intervals
to conquer the passive sea, whose mass of
lukewarm water makes it easy for each of
them to intrude.
Every summer, the dry, scorching air of
the Sahara covers the whole of the sea and
much of the land to the north. It creates the
glorious Mediterranean skies, the brilliant
spheres of light and the star-studded night
skies which have no like anywhere else.
This summer sky is only clouded over dur¬
ing the short period when the sand-laden
south winds rage the Khamsin or the
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Those who, on the eve ofadolescence, orafter having
been tossed aboutfora long time constantlyperceive
certain signals which remind them, even in the midst of
the waves, oftheir sweet homeland. Then they return
straight home withoutgoing astray or losing time, or else,
most often, either because they lose their way infog or
insist on staring at the stars whichplunge into the sea, or
because they are delayed by certain seductivepleasures
the momentforgood navigation eludes them, wander
hitherand thitherand often even risk shipwreck.
St. Augustine
(354-430 AD)
Drinking the sun ofCorinth
Reading the marble ruins
Striding across vineyards and seas
Sighting along the harpoon
A votivefish that slips away
Ifound the leaves that the sun 'spsalm memorizes
The living land thatpassionjoys in opening.
Odysseus Elytis
(born 1911)
sirocco, Horace's "Plumbeus Auster", grey
and heavy as lead.
For six months, while it is under the sway
of the Sahara, the Mediterranean is a tourist
paradise, with its sea sports, its crowded
beaches, and its blue, still water glistening
in the sun. But this is a time when animals,
plants and the parched earth are longing for
rain, for the water that is the richest of all
prizes. From April till September, the pre¬
vailing north-east winds, the Etesian winds
of the Greeks, bring no relief, no real mois¬
ture to the furnace of the Sahara.
When the Ocean asserts itself, the desert
gives way. In October, the oceanic depress¬
ions, swollen with moisture, begin to move
in procession from west to east. Winds from
all quarters assail them and drive them on to
the Orient. The sea darkens, and becomes
as grey as the Baltic, or, buried beneath a
powder of white foam, looks as if it is
covered with snow.(...)
All in all, it is a strange climate, and one
that is hostile to plant life. The rainfall is too
heavy in winter, when the growth of vegeta¬
tion is halted by the cold. When the hot days
come, there is no water left. And so, if the
Mediterranean plants are scented, their
leaves covered with down or wax and their
stems with thorns, it is to protect them
against the dryness of excessively hot
weather, when only the cicadas are alive.
And if the wheat harvest is so early in
Andalusia in April it is because the
wheat is obedient to its environment and its
ears ripen quickly.
Visual beauty masks the treachery of
Mediterranean geology and climate. It
makes it too easy to forget that the
Mediterranean has not been a paradise bes¬
towed freely on man for his pleasure. Here
everything has had to be made, often with
greater difficulty than elsewhere. The
wooden swing plough only scratches the
surface of the shallow, friable soil. If it rains
too hard, the crumbly soil pours down the
slopes like water. The mountains obstruct
movement and occupy too much space, so
that the plains and fields are often mere
strips or handfuls of earth, beyond which
rise the steep paths that are so hard for man
and beast alike to climb.
And those plains that are of any size were
long crossed by meandering streams. Man
had to conquer the plains from hostile
marshes, protect them from destructive riv¬
ers swollen by the pitiless winter, and ban¬
ish malaria. Brackish water had to be puri¬
fied before the plains could be used for
agriculture. Then fresh, pure water had to
be brought for irrigation. (...)
Even today, in all the uplands of the
Mediterranean in Italy, Spain, Provence
and Greece festivals are held, in which
Christian beliefs and the vestiges of pagan
creeds are associated with work. But the
landscape itself, as much as folklore, bears
witness to these archaic ways of life. And
what a witness it is! It is a fragile landscape,
Air view of Herodion, the monumental for¬
tress built south of Jerusalem by Herod
the Great (73-4 BC). Excavations have
brought to light the building's four towers
and the ruins ofthepalace within the walls.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
shaped entirely by human hand: the ter¬
raced crops and low walls that forever need
to be rebuilt, the stones that must be
brought up the hillside on the backs of
donkeys or mules before they are put in
place and consolidated, the earth that must
be carried in baskets and piled up behind
the wall. And remember, no cart hauled by
animals can be used on these steep slopes;
olives and grapes are picked by hand and
transported on the backs of men.
Today, as a result, this once cultivated
land is gradually being abandoned. The life
is too arduous and the profits too low. Even
the famous hills ofTuscany are slowly losing
their distinctive features; the low walls are
disappearing; olive trees over a hundred
years old are dying, one by one; no wheat is
being sown; and the slopes which have been
cultivated for centuries are returning to
grass and pasture or to nothing.
Another sight that is disappearing before
our eyes, but only began to do so recently, is
transhumance, an age-old phenomenon in
which mountains were associated with the
plains and the towns on them; this was a
source of both conflict and profit.
In the past, the movement of flocks of
sheep and goats between the summer pas¬
tures in the uplands and the grass that re¬
mained in the plains during the winter
months took streams of sheep and
shepherds back and forth between the
southern Alps and La Crau, between the
Abruzzi and the plateau of Apulia, between
northern Castile and the southern pasture-
lands in the region of Estremadura and La
Mancha, whence came Don Quixote.
Today this movement still goes on,
though on a much smaller scale. But in
many cases it has been replaced by road or
rail transport. (...)
All life must find its equilibrium. Other¬
wise it is doomed to disappear; this is not
the case of Mediterranean life, which is
sturdy and tenacious. (...)
Mediterranean life is hard and often pre¬
carious. In the final analysis, the balance is
often weighted against man, condemning
him to eternal frugality. A few hours or days
of feasting must be paid for by years, life¬
times of bare subsistence. The historian and
the tourist must not be over-impressed by
the urban successes, by the wonderful old
cities of the Mediterranean. Towns and
cities accumulate wealth, and consequently
they are exceptions; they are privileged
cases, especially in view of the fact that
before the industrial revolution almost 80 to
90 per cent of the population lived in the
countryside.
By and large, the life of the Mediterra¬
nean revolves around three things the
olive-tree, the vine, and wheat. "Too many
bones and not enough meat," as the French
geographer Pierre Gourou has jokingly re¬
marked. (...)
Of the three basic crops, oil and wine
(which are exported to countries outside the
region) have almost always been successful.
The only problem is wheat, but what a
problem! And the problem of wheat entails
that of bread and its consumption as a ne¬
cessity of life. What sort of wheat will it be
made of? What colour will it be? How much
will it weigh, since it is sold everywhere at a
Avlcenna (Ibn Slna) Is one of the greatest
names In Islamic science and philosophy
(980-1037). His Influence permeated the
whole of Islam and penetrated Europe
through Muslim Spain, al-Andalus, where
It remained a force for centuries. Imagi¬
nary portrait of Ibn Slna, above, Is an
Illustration from "Authentic Portraits and
Lives of Illustrious Men, Greek, Latin and
Pagan", by André Thévet (Paris, 1581).
fixed price although its weight varies?
Wheat and bread are the perpetual bane of
the Mediterranean; they are the decisive
figures in its history, a constant source of
preoccupation for the great. What will the
harvest be like? That is the important ques¬
tion asked in every exchange of letters,
including letters between diplomats,
throughout the year. (...)
The Mediterranean is honeycombed with
sea and land routes, so that the towns
small towns, medium-sized towns, and
great cities are linked together. And all
these routes form a system for the move¬
ment of traffic.
This system, I think, is the last element in
our understanding of the Mediterranean,
which is, in the full sense of the term, space-
movement. Movement adds its gifts ~to
those that form the basis of Mediterranean
life and are bestowed by the nearby space,
whether on land or sea. If movement be¬
comes faster, its gifts increase in number,
with visible consequences. For centuries,
Tuscany has been perhaps the most beauti¬
ful countryside in the world. Is not this
because the Florentines eat Sicilian wheat,
so that rural Tuscany has been able to spe¬
cialize in growing vines and olives. From
the fourteenth to the sixteenth century,
Venice was the richest city in Italy and
perhaps in Europe, certainly the richest in
the Mediterranean. She was at the centre of
the most extensive communications system
of the time, a system that extended over the
whole sea; she was the greatest purchaser of
the pepper and spices that came from the
Levant, or at least from the Indian Ocean to
the trading ports of the Levant; most impor¬
tant of all, she was the greatest retailer of
these precious commodities to the West,
and particularly to Germany, the greatest
consumer in Europe. In a sense Venice
confined the German merchants in the
great building known as the "Fondaco dei
Tedeschi" , just as the Islamic countries con¬
fined the Venetians themselves in the fon-
duks of the Levant. (...)
So it can be seen that the Mediterranean
routes increased enormously the space at
the disposal of the cities and merchants of
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
the Inland Sea. Yet it was a man of the
Mediterranean, Marco Polo, who revealed
the existence of distant China to his contem¬
poraries when he returned to Venice in
1296. Another, Christopher Columbus, dis¬
covered America in 1492. Italian merchants
dominated the trade fairs of Champagne in
the thirteenth century, and two centuries
later those of Lyons, around which for a
time the whole fortune of Europe soberly
revolved. (...)
A greater Mediterranean, then, lies
around the Mediterranean in the strict
sense and acts as a sounding board for it.
Nor is it only the economic life of the Inland
Sea whose repercussions are felt far away;
the same is true of its civilizations and of its
cultural movements with their changing col-
" ours. Florence is the centre from which the
Renaissance spread. The baroque arts,
which came from Rome and from trium¬
phant Spain, spread throughout Europe,
including the Protestant countries of the
north. Similarly, the mosques of Istanbul,
particularly the mosque of Suleyman, were
copied in countries as far distant as Persia
and India. (...)
Today we can recapture that splendour,
both in spirit and in fact, when we sail down
the Grand Canal, the world's finest thor¬
oughfare, or stand in the Piazza San Marco,
the world's finest square. But the splendour
was only possible because profits were
made from other people in distant lands.
For it took more than the exploitation of the
nearby countryside and the activity of the
little satellite ports in the Adriatic to
achieve such splendour. It needed the con¬
tribution of far-distant trade and of the
outposts which the Mediterranean scat¬
tered, through Islam, all the way to the Far
East. When the Doge of Venice weds the
sea at the feast of the Sensa, on Ascension
Day, standing before the church of San
Nicolo dei Mendicoli, it is not only a great
and magnificent spectacle, or a symbol; it is
a reality, for in wedding the sea he weds the
greater Mediterranean, the perennial
source of wealth.
The decadence, crises and difficulties of
the Mediterranean result from break¬
downs, shortcomings and disruptions in the
traffic system which goes through, beyond
CD
©
O
ê
Gl
and around it, and which for centuries over-
enhanced its status. Vasco da Gama's
voyage in 1498 was the first blow struck by
fate at the Mediterranean. Yet it survived
that trial. Decadence did not really set in
until 1620, when the English and Dutch
made inroads into the Mediterranean and
seized its distant trade outlets. That was a
long-term disruption. Was it definitive?
Even much later on, after centuries of re¬
cession, the opening of the Suez Canal in
1869 did not fully restore prosperity, let
alone pre-eminence, to the Mediterranean,
for by then England held absolute sway
throughout the world. There was no ques¬
tion of the Mediterranean, which had been
seized by foreigners in the sixteenth cen¬
tury, being given back to those who lived on
its shores.
Covering from six to ten millennia, in a
dislocated, inconsistent world as vast as its
human resources, a world that has been
studied exhaustively by archaeologists and
historians, the history of the Mediterranean
is a body of knowledge that cannot reason¬
ably be reduced to a synthesis. The
Mediterranean .past consists of an accu¬
mulation of layers as thick as the history of
distant China.
Let us look first at its civilizations.
"Over and above its present political
divisions, the Mediterranean consists of
three cultural communities, three huge,
thriving civilizations, three major modes
of thinking, believing, eating, drinking
and living.... First of all the West... or
perhaps we should say the Roman
world.... The second world Is another vast
expanse, that of Islam, which begins In
Morocco and extends beyond the Indian
Ocean to Indonesia and the Philippines....
The third civilization... Is the Greek world,
the Orthodox world." Above, from left to
right, mosque scene from the Maqamat
("Assemblies"), a collection of tales by
al-Harlrl (1054-1122), one of the first
masters of style In Arab literature. Illus¬
tration Is taken from a 12th-century Arab
manuscript by al-Wasitl; the centaur Chi¬
ron Instructing Achilles, as depicted In a
Roman fresco from Herculaneum (c. 1st
century AD), now In the National Mu¬
seum, Naples (Italy); The Marriage at
Cana of Galilee, a 14th-century Byzantine
painting from the church of St. Nicolas
Orp at Salonika (Greece).
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Sea, autumnal sweetness, isles bathed in light,
diaphanous veiloffine rain which covered the immortal
nakedness ofGreece. Happy the man, I thought, to whom
it was given to sail in the A egean Sea before he died. . . .
Nowhere else does one pass so serenely and so easily
from reality to dream. Thefrontiers wither away and the
masts ofthe oldest ship shoot up branches and bunches of
grapes. It could be said that here in Greece the miracle is
the inevitableflowerofnecessity.
Nikos Kazantzakis
(1883-1957)
If we are to give the reader a rapid over¬
view, we must select a guideline. Ana the
best way to do this is to look carefully át the "
Mediterranean as it is today, to try to define
the essential factor in its life and in its visible
equilibrium as it is now and probably as it
was at different points in the past. This
crucial element can be quickly and une¬
quivocally determined. Over and above its -
present political divisions, the Mediterra¬
nean consists of three cultural communities ,
three huge, thriving civilizations, three ma¬
jor modes of thinking, believing, eating,
drinking and living. (...)
Actually, these civilizations are the only
lasting forces that can be traced without
interruption throughout the vicissitudes of
Mediterranean history.
Three civilizations, then. First let us look
at the West, or perhaps we should say
Christendom, an old word overburdened
with meaning; or perhaps we should say the
Roman world, since Rome was and rerhains
the centre of the old Latin universe, later
the Catholic universe, extending as far as
the Protestant world, as far as the Atlantic
Ocean and the North Sea, to the Rhine and
the Danube, along which the Counter-Re¬
formation built its baroque churches, like so
many watchful sentinels; and as far as the
lands beyond the Atlantic, as if the destiny
of modern Rome had been to keep within
its sphere the empire of Charles V, on which
the sun never set.
The second world is another vast ex¬
panse, that of Islam, which begins in
Morocco and extends beyond the Indian
Ocean to Melanesia, Indonesia and the Phi¬
lippines, which were partly conquered and
converted by Islam in the thirteenth century
AD.
The third civilization is not immediately
discernible in our day. It is the Greek
world, the Orthodox world. It covers, at
least, the whole ofwhat we know as the
Balkan peninsula, Romania, Bulgaria,
almost all of Yugoslavia, and Greece itself,
where so much reminds us of the past and
ancient Hellas seems to come back to Ufe;
and of course it also covers the vast
stretches of Orthodox Russia. But what is
its centre? Constantinople, you may say,
which is the second Rome, and Santa
Sophia at its heart. But since 1453 Constan¬
tinople has been Istanbul, the capital of
Turkey: '
Turkish Islam, which owned the whole of
the Balkan peninsula, in the days of its
grandeur, kept its morsel of Europe! And
another centre doubtless played its part .
Moscow, the third Rome. But Moscow,
too, ceased to be a centre of Orthodoxy.
One might perhaps say that the Orthodox
world today is fatherless.
What better guide could there be than
civilizations? They traverse the passing
ages, they endure. While the film of history
is being made, they remain imperturbably
in position.
This immobility implants civilizations in a
far more distant past than is at first
apparent, and the ages through which they
have lived become an intrinsic part of their
nature. The Roman world did not begin
with Christ. Islam did not begin in the
seventh century, with Muhammad. And the
Orthodox world did not begin with the
foundation of Constantinople in 330. For a
civilization is continuous in nature, and
when it changes, even as profoundly as by
the adoption of a new religion, values in¬
herited from the past are part of it; they
survive through it, and continue to form its
substance.
Take the case of Greek civilization. It
arose and began to take shape around the
eighth century BC, following devastation
and invasions which had brought Greece
down to the nadir of history. Today it is still
alive. At the least, it has lasted for three
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Historical absolutism, in spite ofits triumphs, has always
come up against an invincible exigence ofhuman nature,
ofwhich the Mediterranean, where intelligence is sister to
the harsh light, keeps the secret.
Albert Camus
(1913-1960)
"From the 14th to the 16th century,
Venice was the richest city in Italy and
perhaps In Europe, certainly the richest In
the Mediterranean. She was at the centre
of the most extensive communications
system of the time, a system that extend¬
ed over the whole sea; she was the
greatest purchaser of pepper and spices
from the Levant, and above all the great
est retailer of these precious commodi¬
ties to the West... " Below, detail of a plan
of Venice by Jacopo de' Barbari (1440-
1516). In left foreground, the Island of
Giudecca with, at right, the island of San
Giorgio. In background, the Doge's pa¬
lace and the cupolas of the basilica of
St. Mark.
millennia. How many mishaps, catas¬
trophes and disasters have marked its long
journey! Greece and the Hellenistic world
fell to the Roman legions. But when Con-
stantine founded Constantinople, in 330
AD, the vanquished Greeks emerged from
their long period of subjection, the prison in
which they had been held for four or five
centuries. That was the beginning of a
Christian Empire as extensive as the Ro¬
man Empire. And in 395, when the Roman
Empire split into two parts, a "pars orien-
tis", which was ' to become the Greek
Empire of Byzantium, and a "pars
occidentis", which was to fall under the
hammer-blows of the Barbarians, Greece
revived, in all her power. Under this im¬
petus she survived for almost a thousand
years, until the Turkish conquest, in 1453,
which seemed once more to call everything
in question. But in the nineteenth century,
with the help of the Russian Orthodox peo¬
ples and of Europe, a veritable crusade
liberated the Christian peoples of the Bal¬
kans one after the other.
What we have just said about the Ortho¬
dox world is also true, mutatis mutandis, of
the two others Rome and Mecca. Theo¬
retically, in the case of Rome the starting
point is the birth of Christ. In the case of
Islam, it is the flight of Muhammad from
Mecca to Medina, on 16 July 622. But the
Western world is really only the continua¬
tion of the Latin world, whose language,
spirit, law and much else besides it took
over. And while Islam was indeed originally
Arabia, a land of deserts traversed by cara¬
vans with a long history behind it, it is above
all the countries that were so easily con¬
quered by horse- and camel-borne Arab
troops Syria, Egypt, Iran and North Afri¬
ca. Islam appeared in the main the heir to
the Middle East and to a number of cul¬
tures, economies and sciences of an earlier
day. The heart of Islam is the confined
space between Mecca and Cairo, Damascus
and Baghdad. It is too often said that Islam
is the desert and the image is a fine one.
But it should also be said that Islam is the
Middle East. This means that it is also the
heir to the untold wealth of ages.
FERNAND BRAUDEL, French historian, was
honoraryprofessor at the College de France and
a member of the French Academy. He was ad¬
ministrator of the Maison des Sciences de
l'Homme, in Paris, andservedaspresidentofthe
sixth section of the Ecole Pratique des Hautes
Etudes from 1957 to 1972. His first major work,
The Mediterranean and the Mediterranean
World in the Age of Philip II, playeda seminalrole
in the emergence ofa new schoolofhistoriogra¬
phy. In 1979 he published a 3-volume study,
Civilisation Matérielle, Economie et Capitalisme,
XVe-XVIIIe Siècles (published in English by Col¬
lins, 1981-82 as Civilization and Capitalism,
1 5th-1 8th Century). His study of French history
entitled Identité de la France is scheduled for
publication by Arthaud-Flammarion, Paris, in
1986. The present article has been extracted
from La Méditerranée, l'Espace et l'Histoire
(Flammarionpublishers, Paris, 1985), which was
first published in 1977 by Arts et Métiers Gra¬
phiques, Paris.
As this issue was going to press, the editors of
the Unesco Courier were saddened to learn that
Fernand Braudel had died in Paris during the
night of 27-28 November.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Transformation
and tradition
in Mediterranean Europe
by Salvador Giner In the Mediterranean region, traditions
die hard and are reflected in a wide range'
of Institutions and activities, from the
family and social customs to economic
systems. At Hama (Syrian Arab Republic)
magnificent traditional water-wheels, be¬
low, are still used to raise water to the old
houses with f/ie/rmoshrablyyahs (projec¬
ting oriel windows with a wooden lattice).
UNTIL not so long ago, the coun¬
tries of Southern Europe seemed
to be stranded half-way between
the more developed nations and the less
advanced nations. In recent decades,
however, the whole area, has embarked
on a process of political, economic and
cultural integration into the rest of
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
MEDITERRANEAN CITIES
10,000 pop.
500.000 pop.
5,000.000 pop.
LIBYAN
ARAB
JAMAHIRIYA
Map © Plan Bleu pour la Méditerranée. Source: U.N. Demographic Yearbook, 1981
Colour page opposite
Between the 7th and the 9th century, Arab
Muslim civilization spread westwards
along the shores of the Mediterranean
from the Near East to the South ofFrance,
through North Africa, southern Italy,
Spain and Portugal. In the Iberian penin¬
sula it left an enduring mark on Western
Christian civilization. The Mozarabic art
of illuminating manuscripts is one of
many examples of this symbiosis (the
Mozarabs were the Christians ofmedieval'
Spain who adopted certain Arab customs'
during the period of Muslim domination).
Photo shows a page from a Mozarabic
manuscript of the Commentary on the
Apocalypse by Beatus of Llebana, an
8th-century Asturian monk whose work
was often copied and illuminated in later
centuries. This manuscript was illumina¬
ted In 1047 by the painter Facundo for
Ferdinand I of Castile and his wife
Sancha.
The Mediterranean basin has a long histo¬
ry ofurbanization and is todaygirdledbya
dense network of urban settlements
ranging from small towns to great cities
such as Cairo, Barcelona, Rome, Athens,
Valencia, Istanbul, Marseilles, Alexandria,
Damascus and Algiers. A rapid exodus
from the countryside has led to anarchic
urbanization and widespread shanty-
towns on the outskirts of towns and cities.
Europe, as if Portuguese, Spaniards, Ita¬
lians and Greeks had decided to return on
equal terms to a home which after all is
theirs. Their reintegration into Europe at
a particularly creative moment in its his¬
tory has enriched and revitalized the col¬
lective life of all Europeans. But the
homeward path has been a difficult and
tortuous one.
After a remarkable flowering in the
Middle Ages and an extraordinary Re¬
naissance, the peoples of Southern
Europe experienced a profound reversal
in their fortunes. The Hellenic world had
already fallen victim to Ottoman expan¬
sion, which also seriously affected the
great maritime centres such as Barcelona
and Venice. Although the Atlantic
façade, including the ports of Lisbon and
Seville, would continue to benefit from
imperial and overseas trade, the econo¬
mic decline of the Mediterranean and the
growing prosperity of the North, com¬
bined with the wars of religion, began in
the sixteenth century to shift the centre of
gravity of European history towards
countries further from the south.
Although many features of the modern
world rationalism, science, capital¬
ism have their historical roots in South¬
ern Europe, the ankylosis which afflicted
the region during the seventeenth and
eighteenth centuries, a decisive period,
had a crucial impact on its precarious
participation in the great transformation
brought about by the industrial revolu¬
tion. The latter, which started in England
14
and soon spread through Belgium, the
Netherlands and northern France, en¬
countered very serious difficulties in tak¬
ing root in Southern Europe. In one of
the paradoxes that are so common in the
history of this part of the world, some
regions, such as Piedmont and Lombardy
in northern Italy and Catalonia in north¬
eastern Spain, succeeded in carrying out
their own industrial revolutions, led by
the enterprising and farsighted local
bourgeoisies of Turin, Milan and Barce¬
lona. But these islands of prosperity and
modernity could not totally transform the
societies of which they were part, so that
they long remained isolated in a world
that must have seemed backward, poor
and, perhaps, relatively uncivilized to
any traveller coming from the north.
Nevertheless, many of the inhabitants
of these countries soon realized that they
were in a tragic situation. As European
peoples they found it incongruous and
even unjust not to participate fully in the
great movement of modernization in
which their neighbours beyond the Alps
and the Pyrenees were engaged. Efforts
to join in this movement were made in the
eighteenth century both in the Iberian
peninsula and in Italy.
It was thus that Southern Europe be¬
came the first part of the world to experi¬
ence an agonizing longing for modernity
and rapid change that would enable it to
catch up with the developed countries.
What was later to become a movement in
which poor or "undeveloped" or "devel
oping" countries (the word backward be¬
came nothing short of taboo) aspired for
their transformation into" "developed",
industrialized, in other words rich coun¬
tries actually began in Southern Europe.
Thus the struggle between modernizing
and conservative forces, between city and
countryside, between the economic in¬
terests of the powerful and the emerging
urban proletariats, which unfolded in
Southern Europe between the middle of
the nineteenth century and the late 1960s,
presents some analogies with what is hap¬
pening today in many countries else¬
where in the world.
During most of the nineteenth century
there was slow, uneven progress towards
a bourgeois parliamentarian society in
the Iberian, Italian and Balkan peninsu¬
las. This process was dominated by oli¬
garchical governments, military coups
d'état and régimes of varying degrees of
despotism. Political life was dominated
by patronage, favouritism and
bureaucratic parasitism. The emerging
industrial bourgeoisies, especially in
Spain and Italy, struggled in vain to im¬
pose a European-style parliamentary sys¬
tem within profoundly agricultural
societies in which the interests of great
landowners either predominated or were
very strongly represented. At the same
time, constant and sometimes violent
repression of the working classes in these
countries led to growing political and
ideological polarization and endemic
class confrontations. The liberal political
CONTINUED PAGE 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
:
í JAVO
Surgut;*, áUffta«
i ra !PI
1 1 i
-* ^FÏI^î^B
LwBM Êm) 1 J
L
-1 i |
Jl
§ 1
, n
' a
.h a
it !
r
t
!* I I
s*~"^
m 8
Ü,
6»'
j
jíOiiAtjdot
!
j ' | o f % ! c ' *
¡1 r-2 YAYa
HIB
tri' .
1 * mm
? 1 111
III
1
fu frrn/fr
ÜB
"V-
m il Üb Hi it
1
1 1 l .
Ltrrinu < mît'
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
a.
o
S
©
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 14
formula which triumphed in northern
Europe failed in the south. There seemed
to be no place for tolerance, political
pluralism and peaceful rule by the
bourgeoisie, tempered by an opposition
of trade unions and the Left to which
concessions could be made. The political
formula which had brought relative
prosperity and equilibrium to the ad¬
vanced capitalist countries in central and
northwestern Europe seemed to have
failed completely in the countries of the
south.
At the end of the nineteenth century it
seemed as if the progress of industrializa¬
tion and the consolidation of bourgeois
parliamentarian régimes in several
Mediterranean countries would even¬
tually bring these countries closer to the
models of the advanced European coun¬
tries. However, a series of unexpected
reverses sharpened confrontations be¬
tween the different groups and deepened
the fissures which divided these societies.
In spite of attempts to establish republics
in Portugal, Greece and Spain and the
creation in Italy of a parliamentary sys¬
tem open to the socialists, the First World
War exacerbated the internal contradic¬
tions in these countries. Moreover, Euro¬
pean that they were, they had embarked
on, or were destined to embark on, a
series of disastrous colonial wars that di¬
vided them even further: the Spanish war
with the United States in Cuba and the
Philippines in 1898, the later Italian cam¬
paigns against various African countries,
and the Portuguese wars in Africa.
In the decades following the European
Great War which ended in 1918, all these
countries embarked upon various forms
of fascism. Fascism was a Mediterranean
Colour page opposite
Above: a landlocked sea, the Mediterra¬
nean has always been open to the world
beyond Its shores. Three great civiliza¬
tions born in the region those of Western
Christianity, Islam and Byzantium car¬
ried their message far afield. The Mediter¬
ranean has had Its great travellers and
geographers such as Strabo, Ibn Battuta
and AI Bakri, and two explorers from the
Mediterranean basin extended the boun¬
daries of the world known to their Euro¬
pean contemporaries. In the 13th century
the Venetian Marco Polo gave Europeans
their first Information about central Asia
and China and In the late 15th century the
Genoese Christopher Columbus made his
epic voyage to America. Photo shows the
pepper harvest, a miniature from a 15th-
century manuscript ofThe Book of Marco
Polo.
Below: in the Mediterranean, death Is sur¬
rounded by a ritual designed to soften Its
Impact on those who mourn. Photo shows
a scene ofmourning at the tomb ofa Casti¬
llan knight, Sancho Sáez de Carrillo (late
13th century) now In the Museum of Cata¬
lan Art In Barcelona.
political invention. It was a way of sup¬
pressing popular revolt and imposing
peace through rule by a single party allied
to the upper classes, afraid of losing all
they possessed in the event of an im¬
agined proletarian revolution. Fascism
was, therefore, a retrograde movement
aimed at neutralizing the working classes
by demagogy or terror. It originated in
Southern Europe although, paradoxical¬
ly, it was in the north, in Germany, that it
found its most violent and extreme ex¬
pression.
In the Mediterranean countries of
Europe, really democratic intervals were
few and far between, and consisted of
republican or radical experiments which
the dominant classes, allied with the
military or with semi-fascist or frankly
fascist parties, did not allow to succeed.
Nevertheless, during the same period the
forces of social change were already on
the move. The day would come in all
these countries when the dictatorial, anti¬
democratic régimes would become use¬
less and inadequate for an area of the
European world that had been complete¬
ly transformed.
To some extent the transformation of
the Mediterranean was obscured by these
régimes, which gave too backward an
impression of the societies they encom¬
passed. Italy, and to a lesser extent Spain,
were already minor industrial powers in
the decades before the First World War.
Large-scale industrial enterprises were
created in both countries under the aegis
of fascism, with State capital compensât- N
ing for the lack of private investment.
In the 1950s Italy, which had been
liberated from fascism by the Allies in
1945, became the first country to experi¬
ence what came to be called an "econo¬
mic miracle". The Spanish "economic
miracle" took place in the following de¬
cade, beginning in 1959. During this
period, and to a lesser degree later on,
these countries experienced spectacular
industrial growth rates which were sur¬
passed only by those of Japan. The same
years saw an increasingly rapid decline in
the numbers of people working on the
land, without any drop in agricultural
production. A veritable "deruralization"
was beginning to take place in all these
societies, although the phenomenon was
much less pronounced in Portugal. Cities
grew more quickly than ever before in
European history, and were unable to
absorb the massive influx of new immig¬
rants. Urban growth was particularly ex¬
plosive in Spain. The populations of
Milan, Turin, Barcelona, Madrid, Bilbao
and Athens doubled or tripled in two
decades. In their endlessly sprawling sub¬
urbs shantytowns proliferated on a scale
that dwarfed the bidonvilles of Paris.
Two other phenomena tourism, and
the economic growth and prosperity of
Europe in the 1960s coincided with this
massive migration from the country to
the cities and from agriculture to indus¬
try, and helped to avert an explosive poli¬
tical and social situation in these coun¬
tries. European economic expansion,
which continued virtually until 1974,
- m a a-T-t£ 1 >. = /
Immense In area, like Its neighbours
Algeria and Egypt, the Libyan Arab Jama-
hlrlya has one of the lowest population
densities In the world (only 2 Inhabitants
per Km2). Its per capita Income, on the
other hand, Is one of the highest In the
Mediterranean basin, higher than that of
Spain and Italy, essentially because of
the revenues from its enormous oilfields.
The percentage of the labour force en¬
gaged In agriculture Is low and that
employed In the services sector Is high.
Photo shows the head of a Medusa from
Leptis Magna, the Phoenician, Carthagi¬
nian and Roman city whose ruins stand
near to the Libyan capital of Tripoli.
absorbed an enormous quantity of man¬
power from Southern Europe. Millions
of Greeks, Spaniards, Yugoslavs, Turks,
Portuguese and Italians crossed the Alps
and the Pyrenees to look for work. The
money they sent back to their families
strengthened the currencies of the receiv¬
ing countries and increased the purchas¬
ing power of the recipients, thus stimulat¬
ing the domestic markets of these coun¬
tries. The advantages for the host coun¬
tries (the Federal Republic of Germany,
Switzerland, the Netherlands and
France) were, of course, even greater,
since they obtained /docile, cheap,
healthy workers in the prime of life.
For the countries of the south, tourism
was also an unexpected source of income
and one which, for the first time, bene¬
fited people of all conditions and not only
the ruling class. Mass tourism breathed
new life into the manufacturing and con¬
struction industries, led to an increase in
the number of mechanical workshops,
provided seasonal employment for
thousands of unskilled young people,
contributed to the development of
national airlines, helped to finance the
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
construction of motorways and airports
and accelerated changes in mentality
which had already been initiated by other
historical forces.
The fact is that by the mid-1970s, if not
before, these countries had changed. Of
course, visitors could still see not only
traces of the past but scenes from a pre-
industrial era of a kind which it is still easy
to find today in Portugal, in some parts of
Andalusia, in rural southern Italy, in
Apulia and Sicily, in many of the Greek
islands and in the inland mountain re¬
gions of Greece. Even if the numbers of
telephones, cars and electrical household
appliances per head of population are still
lower than elsewhere in Europe, the in¬
teresting fact is that they are gradually
catching up. Other figures, such as the
percentages of students at universities,
family size (and also, unfortunately, the
statistics for unemployment and delin¬
quency) are growing closer, if not equal,
to those for the rest of Europe. Although
the two Europes are still not fully com¬
parable, the gap between them in these
respects is now so narrow that it is im¬
possible to maintain that they are des¬
tined never to meet.
From 1974 onwards, with the fall of the
reactionary régimes in Greece and Por¬
tugal and the crumbling of the Franco
régime in Spain which began in the fol¬
lowing year, the eyes of the world were
on the Mediterranean. Italy, which had
enjoyed a liberal constitution since 1948,
This table reveals a general decline in the
agricultural labour force in Mediterranean
countries in recent decades, combined
with an increase in the percentage ofper¬
sons employed in industry, and In the ser¬
vices sector (which includes tourism, one
of the region's main sources of Income).
Also apparent are marked differences
between the northwest Mediterranean
countries and Israel (whose figures bear a
strong similarity to those of the Industria¬
lized countries) on the one hand, and the
countries of the southern and eastern
Mediterranean (closer to the developing
countries), on the other.
seemed to be the only country in the
region to have escaped dictatorship. In
addition, the violence of the recent civil
wars in Greece and Spain seemed to have
irremediably polarized their populations
into hostile camps, and the colonial wars
in which Portugal was engaged did not
augur well for a reasonably peaceful tran¬
sition to democracy.
But to universal surprise this is exactly
what happened. After several unsuccess¬
ful attempts, a democratic movement
within the Portuguese armed forces car¬
ried out a military coup d'état on 25 April
1974 and placed power (or, initially at
least, a large share of it) in the hands of
freely elected political parties. In the
same year the Greek colonels embarked
on a venture in Cyprus, the failure of
which discredited them with their dwind¬
ling number of supporters. In Spain the
dictator's death, after several years dur¬
ing which the régime had intensified its
repression of a number of popular move¬
ments (workers, students, professional
people) was followed by a final man¬
oeuvre to save the régime; but the latter
gradually lost credit from 1976 onwards.
A series of referenda and general elec¬
tions led to a de facto democratic situa¬
tion in 1977 and the proclamation of a
democratic constitution in the following
year. At the beginning of the 1980s the
West Mediterranean European countries
were not only enjoying liberal democratic
régimes but had progressed from a stage
of political transition to one of democra¬
tic consolidation.
One must proceed with caution and
even with a certain degree of scepticism
when considering the old societies of
Southern Europe. It cannot be denied
that these nations, heirs to ancient civi¬
lizations and participants in a long and
glorious history, are again showing signs
of great vitality. This is clearly indicated
by their recent economic expansion and
their participation in the technological
revolution, in which, not without difficul¬
ty, they are playing an ever more impor¬
tant role. At the same time their creativ¬
ity in the arts and sciences and in the
fields of culture and university education
is attaining ever higher levels. But their
situation does not justify unmixed
optimism.
Because they have not yet achieved the
level of industrial productivity and tech¬
nological rationalization of other coun¬
tries, the Mediterranean countries of
Europe are far less well equipped to cope
with the economic recession and financial
and employment crises of the 1980s.
Their socio-economic structures, i.e. the
pattern of distribution of private wealth,
were still relatively antiquated when the
period of rapid prosperity in the West
began to run out after 1973.
Moreover, unemployment, which
affects the middle classes and university
graduates as well as the working class, is a
more serious problem in Southern
Europe than in the North. When the
economic crisis hit the South the welfare
state was far less developed there than in
the North, and it is very difficult to ex¬
pand welfare services and improve the
quality of benefits in times of penury. In
Western Europe the development of the
vast apparatus of the welfare state free
education for all, free medical services,
unemployment and retirement ben¬
efits occurred during the prosperous
years which followed the Second World
War.
As if this were not enough, Southern
Europe is also one of the world's most
traditionalist regions. This is not always
in contradiction with its renewed vitality,
since innovation is an essential part of the
European cultural, technical and ideolo¬
gical tradition, but it can be an obstacle to
progress in times of crisis. Administrative
corruption and political patronage are
not a monopoly of the Mediterranean
countries but in these countries they
often reach proportions that in the Euro¬
pean political and cultural context are
intolerable. Nevertheless, in a growing
number of cases the courts of law are
functioning normally and prosecuting
offences of this kind, thus proving that
modernization is also making an impact
in this difficult field.
But the traditionalism of Mediterra¬
nean Europe also has less encouraging
aspects. Southern peoples are, for
instance, still deeply attached to their
ethnic groups, nationalities, regions and
localities. In order to relax the tensions
that such feelings could generate within a
democratic framework, Spain has be-
PERCENTAGES OF THE LABOUR FORCE
Agriculture Industry Services
1965 1981 1965 1981 1965 1981
Spain 34 14 35 40 31 46
France 18 8 40 39 42 53
Italy 24 11 42 45 34 44
Yugoslavia 57 29 21 35 22 36
Greece 51 37 22 28 27 35
Turkey 74 54 11 13 15 33
Syrian A. R. 53 33 20 31 27 36
Lebanon 28 11 25 27 47 62
Israel 12 7 35 36 53 57
Egypt 56 50 15 30 29 20
Libyan A.J. 42 19 20 28 38 53
Tunisia 53 35 20 32 27 33
Algeria 59 25 14 25 27 50
Morocco 60 52 15 21 25 27
This land which is like the head ofa mare
Which has gallopedfrom distantAsia
To plunge into the Mediterranean,
This land is ours. . . .
Nazim Hikmet
(1902-1963)
Source: World Development Report, 1985. World Bank
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
come a semi-federal state with extensive
powers granted to minority nationalities
such as the Basques and the Catalans.
Italy has also introduced an extensive
system of regionalization in order to put
an end to the endemic centralism of the
past. Italy was one of the signatories of
the Treaty of Rome which set up the
Common Market, and one of the promo¬
ters of the European Community, which
is not only economic but aspires to the
eventual creation of a single political area
for all the citizens of Western Europe.
The vast majority of Spaniards, Portu¬
guese and Greeks are enthusiastic Euro¬
peans whose admission to the Commun¬
ity was hindered because of their dictato¬
rial régimes. After excessive delays the
Greeks joined the Common Market in
1981 and Spain and Portugal will do so in
1986. This is much more than a symbolic
event. It is a return to the family fold of
peoples whose recent tragic history kept
them apart from the rest of Europe. This
return will be crowned with success pro¬
vided the new Europe does not withdraw
into itself and becomes a force for peace
and solidarity with other nations. It is not
too much to hope that the Mediterranean
countries, which are much closer in many
respects to the less privileged nations of
the world, will oblige the rest of the conti¬
nent to reach out to a world that demands
fraternal, efficient collaboration from
Europe as a whole.
SALVADOR GINER of Spain, is Reader in
sociology and social anthropology at Brunei
University, London. He has also taught at the
Universities of Barcelona, Puerto Rico, Reading
and Lancaster, and has been a visiting profes¬
sor at Yale. He is currently vice president of the
Spanish Sociological Association, and a mem¬
ber of the executive committee of the Internatio¬
nal Sociological Association, which collabo¬
rates with Unesco. A number of his works have
appeared in English, including Sociology, 1972.
He is also the co-editor of Contemporary
Europe: Social Structure and Cultural Patterns,
7975.
.
<
z
<
©
Top, new cars parked near the Alfa Romeo
plant in Milan, Italy. Industrialization, more
advanced in the countries ofthe northwest
Mediterranean than elsewhere in the re¬
gion, is the most visible aspect of the mo¬
dernization process. In the rural areas, tra¬
ditions and a certain inertia are much
stronger, and development is inhibited by
the aridityprevalent in the southern part of
the basin. Above, land irrigated by water
from the Bin El Ouidan dam, In Morocco.
Agriculture is still centred on traditional
crops such as the vine, the olive and
wheat. Left, wheatfields south of Palermo,
in Sicily.
<
''.
*
is
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Unesco and cooperation
in the Mediterranean
ALTHOUGH the Mediterranean re¬
gion straddles three continents and
englobes many different countries,
Unesco recognized the specific nature of its
problems early on and has made a growing
contribution to solving them.
The major work carried out by Unesco in
the study and development of arid zones
began around the Mediterranean. The idea
of an action programme in this field was
adopted at Unesco's third General Con¬
ference, held in Beirut in 1948. The first
international symposium on arid zone hyd¬
rology was held at Ankara in 1 952, and this
important scientific meeting was followed
by many others, including symposia on
plant ecology (Montpellier, 1953); on the
protection of nature in the Near East
(Beirut, 1954); on plant-water relationships
(Madrid, 1959); on climatic change (Rome,
1961); and on land use in a Mediterranean
climate (Heraklion, 1962).
Studies carried out over more than four
years led to the publication in 1963 by
Unesco, in collaboration with the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United Na¬
tions (FAO) of a Bioclimatic Map of the
Mediterranean Zone. This was followed in
1 969 by a Vegetation Map of the Mediterra¬
nean Region, which is still the best basis for
assessing the region's highly distinctive
ecological conditions.
The tradition of these activities is today
Islands abound In the Mediterranean, from
the small and the medium-sized (such as
Malta and the Islands of the Aegean), to
such large islands as the Balearles, Corsi¬
ca, Sardinia, Sicily, Crete and Cyprus. On
some of them, landscapes and regional
ways of life have been better preserved
than on the continental landmass, and
form a field for study and conservation in
which Unesco Is active. In 1980, for exam¬
ple, the Director-General of Unesco, Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, launched an In¬
ternational campaign to safeguard the
sites and monuments of Malta. Opposite
page below, the citadel of Victoria on the
Maltese Island of Gozo. Opposite page
above, the ruins of the odeion (theatre) at
one of the oldest cities in the Mediterra¬
nean, Paphos in southwest Cyprus.
being maintained by Unesco's interdisci¬
plinary research programme on Man and
the Biosphere (MAB). This programme,
launched in 1971, broadens the range of
Unesco's Mediterranean activities, which
reflect the strong determination of all
Mediterranean countries to cooperate in
safeguarding their common heritage.
The Mediterranean region is a privileged
area for certain major research themes of
the MAB programme, whose ultimate
objective is to provide a scientific basis for
the rational management of natu rar re¬
sources and lasting harmony in the rela¬
tionship between man and his environ- x
ment. Mechanisms for concerted action by
Mediterranean countries have been elabo¬
rated at a number of meetings held in con¬
nexion with the implementation of the MAB
programme. One of the most important of
these meetings was the MAB Mediterra¬
nean Scientific Conference, which was
held at Montpellier in 1976 and was
attended by all MAB national committees
from countries bordering the
Mediterranean. A number of subjects of
common interest were examined, including
the effects of fire on Mediterranean eco¬
systems, the impact of grazing in marginal
zones, management methods for deltas
and irrigated zones, the development of
catchment areas and the fight against
erosion.
One major MAB research theme con¬
cerning the Mediterranean is a project relat¬
ing to the ecological effects of human activi¬
ties on lakes, streams, deltas, estuaries
and especially coastal areas, where the
combined effects of tourism, urbanization
and industry often cause considerable
damage.
Other MAB studies are aimed at deter¬
mining the optimum social, economic and
environmental conditions for the balanced
development of ecosystems on the smaller
Mediterranean islands, given their fragility
and marginal nature. Integrated manage¬
ment exercises have been carried out on
the islands of Skiathos and Skopelos
(Greece), Salina (Italy) and Kerkennah
(Tunisia). A development plan is being pre¬
pared for the Greek island of Chalki and an
intersectoral model programmed on a mic¬
ro-computer has been worked out for the
Maltese island of Gozo.
One activity stemming from this project
has been the establishment on a number of
smaller islands of simple experimental sta¬
tions operated by the local authorities. The
role of the stations is to make concrete
proposals for the wise use of available
natural and human resources and to de¬
velop techniques for, notably, energy pro¬
duction, the treatment and recycling of
waste, and aquaculture.
An international symposium on develop¬
ment problems in the smaller Mediterra¬
nean Islands, held in Ibiza and Formentera
(Balearic Islands) in October 1 985 has led
to wider cooperation in this field between
the countries concerned.
The MAB programme in the Mediterra¬
nean region currently includes about a
dozen country projects in such fields as
forest ecosystems, the development of
coastal areas, the desert ecosystems of
North Africa, the study of parasites affect¬
ing agricultural systems in delta regions,
and regional exchanges of ecological infor¬
mation.
Through its Intergovernmental Océano¬
graphie Commission (IOC), Unesco plays
an active role in the Action Plan for the
Mediterranean launched by the Mediterra¬
nean countries in 1975 under the auspices
of the United Nations Environment Pro¬
gramme (UNEP). Its work includes carrying
out pilot projects on the continuous moni¬
toring of oil and hydrocarbon pollution and
on the coastal transport of pollutants;
studying the role of sediments in pollution;
measuring the contribution of rivers to pol¬
lution; modelling marine ecosystems; and
organizing reference collections of
Mediterranean marine flora and fauna.
Other interesting examples of coopera¬
tion between Mediterranean countries
could be cited, notably as part of Unesco's
International Geological Correlation Pro¬
gramme through which, in collaboration
with the International Union of Geological
Sciences, studies are being made of the
desiccation of the Mediterranean during the
Miocene and Pliocene eras, the strati-
graphical . correlation of the
Mediterranean's ancestor, the Tethys, dur¬
ing the Neogene era, and the analysis of
sea-levels in order to forecast short-term
variations in them.
The Mediterranean region where, broad-
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ly speaking, the African tectonic plate col¬
lides with the Eurasian plates, is a zone of
intensive seismic activity marked by re¬
latively frequent and serious earthquakes.
Under Unesco's auspices, cooperation has
been instituted for studying the probable
location of earthquakes and precautions
that could limit their effects. A programme
for the reduction of seismic risks in the Arab
region is currently being carried out with the
financial support of the Arab Fund for Eco¬
nomic and Social Development and the
Islamic Development Bank. Unesco's
assistance has also been sought by the
French Geological and Mining Research
Bureau for the preparation of a seis-
motectonic map of the Mediterranean
basin. The Mediterranean is also one of the
three major regions which are the subject of
a joint Unesco-UNEP study on theestab-
lishment of a volcanic eruption alert
system.
The ancient city of Tyre (Lebanon) is an
archaeological site of major importance.
In 1979, the United Nations Security Coun¬
cil declared Tyre to be an endangeredpart
ofthe worldheritage, and in 1980 Unesco's
Executive Board appealed for it to be pre¬
served. In 1982 the Director-General of
Unesco again intervened on behalfof this
prestigious site, In the protection of which
a non-governmental organization, the In¬
ternational Association to Save Tyre, Is
playing a leading part. Below, remains of
Greek columns at Tyre.
In the cultural field, Unesco has spon¬
sored research into the renovation of his¬
toric sites in the Mediterranean, notably the
historic centres of Kastoria in Greece and
Palermo and Otranto in Italy. It is also active
in the preservation of the Casbah of Algiers,
in the establishment of national museums
in the Libyan Arab Jamahiriya and in Egypt
(Aswan and Cairo), and in the protection of
the archaeological site of Jerash in Jordan.
Major international campaigns have also
been launched by Unesco to save a num¬
ber of prestigious sites in the
Mediterranean, including the Medina of Fez
(Morocco), the Medina of Tunis and the
ruins of Carthage (Tunisia), the Acropolis of
Athens (Greece), historic sites and build¬
ings in Malta, monuments and sites in Mon¬
tenegro damaged in the 1979 earthquake,
the historic quarters of Istanbul (Turkey)
and the archaeological site of Tyre (Leba¬
non). Since it was ravaged by severe flood¬
ing in 1 966, the city of Venice has been the
focus of an interdisciplinary campaign to
save not only the city itself and its monu¬
ments but all the lagoons on which it
depends.
As part of its programme on intercultural
studies, Unesco pays special attention to
the Mediterranean area as a cultural cross¬
roads. A series of specialist meetings on
Mediterranean cultures began in Malta in
1978. In accordance with a recommenda¬
tion of the World Conference on Cultural
Policies (MONDIACULT) held in Mexico
City, the establishment of a Liaison Office
for Mediterranean Cultures was envisaged
in 1982. In addition, several Mediterranean
countries have undertaken to establish a
number of specialized Mediterranean cen
tres Handicrafts Centre in France, a
Submarine Archaeology Centre in Athens,
a Community of Mediterranean Universi¬
ties at Bari (see page 40), a Centre of
Andalusian Studies in Beirut, a Plastic Arts
Centre in Tangiers, and an Architecture
and Town-Planning Centre in Istanbul.
These centres, whose activities will be
coordinated and supported by Unesco,
should provide an efficient structure for the
promotion of intercultural studies in the
Mediterranean region.
Cooperation between the States with a
Mediterranean seaboard is thus institu¬
tionalized in many fields. It is to be hoped
that in spite of, or perhaps because of, past
conflicts, perception of their geographical
solidarity, economic complementarity and
cultural affinities will encourage the
Mediterranean countries to extend their
cooperation to other fields within the com¬
petence of Unesco and of other United
Nations bodies.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Photo Dan Dubert/Unesco
A region
in search of itself by Paolo Apolito
Above, a Syrian boystands beside a stone
statue adorning an underground mauso¬
leum atPalmyra. Theyare dividedbysome
twenty centuries but joined by the kind of
family resemblance that survives in the
history ofnations swayed by invasion and
conquest.
APART from questions of strategy, is
it possible today to form a mental
image of the Mediterranean as a
whole, to talk in terms of a "Mediterranean
entity"? It is reasonable to suppose that
Mediterranean countries on the road to
"development" or "revolution" do not re¬
gard the "Mediterranean" as a region com¬
mon to them all, but look instead to the
centre of modernization or revolution. In
other words, they look beyond the
Mediterranean, to the West, to socialism,
or to pan-Islamism.
What, then, is left of the Mediterranean
besides the geographical expression? In my
opinion, not much more than a Utopian idea
(but is this utopia attainable?). In recent
years, intellectual minorities in some coun
tries have begun or begun again to talk
about the Mediterranean. In most countries
of the region, this has coincided more or less
with the crisis of the "diffusionist" model of
development according to which develop¬
ment and modernization spread constantly
and gradually, like an oil stain, slowly per¬
meating from a centre the industrialized
regions towards outer regions which are
in contact with the centre, or rather are
influenced by it. Sooner or later, indus¬
trialization gives rise to social and cultural
changes which bring the outer regions to the
same level of civilization as the centre a
level which of course is measured according
to criteria set by the centre and thus brings
the state of underdevelopment to an end.
Italy's policy towards her southern regions,
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
|:£tihm
R isen the sea wind,
now that night comes,
away to the nets.
The wind*sflight
has covered withfog
the whole sweep ofthe sky.
The eyes ofthe night
play blind man 's buff
with thefirst crickets.
Salvador Espriu
(born 1913)
The sea
smilesfar away,
Teeth offoam,
lips ofsky.
Whatareyou selling, o troubled
girt with breastsfree in the air?
Sir . I am selling the water
ofthe seas .
Federico García Lorca
(1898-1936)
for instance, has been based on this model
for decades.
But at the end of the 1960s and especially
in the 1970s it became clear that this model
took no account of what was actually hap¬
pening in the developing countries, and it
was replaced by new interpretative models,
none of which, however, was entirely satis¬
factory.
If the diffusionist model had worked, the
Mediterranean as the focal point of influ¬
ence from a number of economic centres,
would have lost its distinctive historical and
geographical features to an all-embracing
industrial society.
Things turned out differently, however,
and the result is that the Mediterranean, in
the view of the intellectual minorities men¬
tioned above, is coming back into its own as
an area with a common history. The outer
regions are slowly abandoning the attempt
to identify themselves with centres which
they have long vainly sought to emulate,
and are looking elsewhere for their identity.
In the Mediterranean, development can
obviously follow a variety of directions. It is
coming to be recognized that this is a region
of common or contrasting civilizations. (It
must be emphasized that this is as yet a
minority view).
Then the idea emerged that the
Mediterranean is a kind of hinge between
North and South, between the industrial¬
ized world and the developing world. Both
"... the complex of mentalities and social
behaviour which may be described as
'tradition' and which has been a formi¬
dable obstacle to all attempts at econo¬
metric planning." Above, view of Pocltel],
a Yugoslav town near the Adriatic coast.
worlds are represented in the
Mediterranean; economically, culturally,
historically and geographically they are
very closely related. These relationships
could form the basis of a new kind of bal¬
ance between the continents of Europe and
Africa and, to some extent, Asia. This is not
an original idea, but it is the only one so far
that seems defensible and even reasonable.
From the standpoint of a purely "econo¬
mist" logic of development, political con¬
cepts such as "cultural region", "identity"
and "historical depth" are considered to be
irrelevant, if not positively dangerous.
According to this view, only economic and
statistical parameters should be taken into
account.
But sociology based on indices and para¬
meters has proved to be short of ideas. As
the economic historian Paul Bairoch has
written, "the early 1970s saw the beginning
of a period of disillusionment with develop¬
ment policies in both the 'capitalist' and
'socialist' camps (to use over-simplified
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
"Some aspects of Mediterranean society
have exertedsuch pressure that they have
restricted the effectiveness of this (Wes¬
tern) development model. " Above, the vil¬
lage of Alberobello In southern Italy.
terms). There have been many failures and
semi-failures in both camps, but few succes¬
ses". National bourgeoisies (which Franz
Fanon had already denounced as incom¬
petent) and bureaucratic and military castes
had all employed similar procedures,
theoretically dependent on scientific mod¬
els whether capitalist or socialist which
were based on situations that already be¬
longed to the past and attached absolute
value to economic factors. Cultural prob¬
lems were seen as the province of moraliz¬
ing anthropologists, and the aim of both
camps was the rapid achievement of mas¬
sive industrialization.
Implicit in the development model that
almost everyone accepted is a backward-
looking, ethnocentric philosophy of history
which is more effective when it is repre¬
sented as economic pragmatism. The Ita¬
lian historian Rosario Romeo has given a
good description of this kind of philosophy,
which "proceeds from the tacit assumption
that there is a kind of normal or exemplary
historical process that coincides with the
history of Western countries, which
attained national unity early on and then
went on to construct the edifice of political
and economic freedoms which have led to
the apogee of the modern industrial demo¬
cracies. But the histories of other countries
are seen as tainted, to a greater or lesser
degree, by distortions and backwardness,
and are to be assessed in terms of the extent
to which they deviate from the history of the
countries of the North Atlantic region".
(Europa e Mediterráneo: una prospettiva
storiografica, 1984)
The norm changes from time to time:
besides referring to the history of the West¬
ern countries, it requires that statistical
figures and tables should take precedence
over all other considerations, that the
centre of the economic system should be
copied whatever the cost, and that the
strategical motive force of development
should be an altar on which the rest of the
economy must be sacrificed. Apart from the
ethnocentric and culturally imperialistic na¬
ture of this philosophy, the result is that
reality is reduced to a few categories and
thereby impoverished.
However, certain aspects of Mediterra¬
nean societies have exerted such pressure
that they have restricted the effectiveness of
this development model. A good example
of this is the complex of mentalities and
social behaviour which may be described as
"tradition" and which has been been a for¬
midable obstacle to all attempts at eco
nometric planning. More precisely, the
tradition-modernity dialectic has developed
in a different way from what was expected.
Whereas it was thought that tradition would
slowly disappear as a result of the powerful
stimulus of modernity, it was perceived that
in fact "tradition and modernity... relate to
each other through a variety of comprom¬
ises and mutual adjustments, with the out¬
come varying greatly from one place to
another". (Peter Berger, Pyramids of
Sacrifice)
For decades, the racist variety of positiv¬
ist anthropology took the lead in maintain¬
ing that the nordic "races" were the best
equipped for success in the modern, indus¬
trialized world, relegating the Latin coun¬
tries and the Mediterranean region to limbo
because of their supposed inability to over¬
come their anachronistic backwardness.
Between the wars, historiographie para¬
digms were propagated which, while they
put an end to racist anthropology, provided
new arguments to emphasize the superior¬
ity of certain countries over others.
In the words of Rosario Romeo, "The
new 'scientific' history of the quantitative
and 'serial' historians, like the old anthro¬
pology of the positivists, may conceal an
ideology whose aim is to assert the super¬
iority, conferred by destiny, of the Atlantic
countries over the others... The same pur¬
pose is served by a political historiography
on which ideology exerts such a strong
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Ifall the trees in the earth were pens, and the sea, with
seven more seas to replenish it, were ink, the writing of
Allah's words couldnever befinished.
The Qur'an
"... tradition and modernity relate to each
other through a variety of compromises
andmutualadjustments, with the outcome
varying greatly from one place to
another." Below, street scene at Korçë in
Albania.
pressure that in some cases it leads to the
violation of the elementary rules of conduct
of the historian's profession. In this way,
countries not on the Atlantic are relegated
to the margins of the world's historical de¬
velopment and, by implication, destined to
remain there. The common consciousness,
in which so many of the racist prejudices
that have been overcome at the cultural
level come to life again, combines with the
kind of historiography described above to
suggest that the attitudes required by mod¬
ern mass industrial society are largely in the
possession of the Atlantic nations, and that
consequently other nations should aim to
acquire, as far as possible, the attitudes,
values and techniques of the latter". The
various development sociologies continue
to affirm, by implication, the impossibility
of reaching the level of the models of de¬
veloped societies that they themselves pre¬
sent as examples.
One of the most decisive contributions to
the downfall of this philosophy was the
comical recent "discovery" that the heights
of development, which it was natural for the
Western, Atlantic countries to scale, had at
last been reached by Japan, a country which
belongs to neither of these categories.
If the Japanese success story teaches us
anything, it is that the last word has never
been spoken in history, that models, norms,
parameters and ideologies are never defini¬
tive in the world of men, a world that is less
closed today than in the past if ever it was
so.
The Mediterranean, of course, is not
Japan. In the Mediterranean region severe
economic stagnation is accompanied by a
dangerous potential for political explo¬
sions. The coming together of civilizations
seems increasingly Utopian in a deeply di¬
vided region. The difficulties are enormous
in a world where it seems that the strong are
growing stronger and the weak weaker. But
this is precisely why the solution is not to be
found in economics only; it must be sought
in a broader context, reaching to the very
heart of civilizations, and reviving pride in
their identity.
The problem faced by the Mediterranean
is how to vanquish its inferiority complexes
so that it may again become a centre of
attraction, continuing its history, which is
far from ended, and reviving the Utopian
dream. We must start talking earnestly
about the Mediterranean again, and lay the
first stone in the construction of a boundless
future.
PAOLO APOLITO, of Italy, is professor of cultu¬
ral anthropology at the faculty of letters of Saler¬
no University. His major research field is that of
cultural change in traditional societies, and he
has also studied the evolution ofmagic, festivals
and ritual. Among his published works are
Lettere al Mago ("Letters to the Magus", 1981)
and II Popólo del Totem ("The Totem People",
1985).
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Public spaces and prívate faces
Patterns of urban living
by Maurice Aymard
-. tí&á
The separation of the family cell from the
outside world is an important feature of
traditional domestic architecture in the
Mediterranean, and in some mountainous
parts of the region the protective function
of the dwelling even tookprecedence over
all others. Above, In the valley of Göreme
in Cappadocia (Turkey) communities
numbering thousands found refuge over
the centuries in a complex of churches,
monasteries and dwellings hewn out of
the living rock. Turkey and Unesco have
launched an appeal for international soli¬
darity to preserve the site of Göreme and
safeguard it from the effects of erosion.
WHERE do Mediterranean people
choose to live? Never alone, al¬
ways in a group, regardless of its
size or wealth. In the Mediterranean, it
takes only a thousand people scraping a
poor living off the land and trading in its
produce to create an urban unit and infuse
into it the vital forces of cohesion and oppo¬
sition. Elsewhere, twice that number would
amount to no more than a village.
From the simple township to the major
conurbation, there are all the levels of a
hierarchy which is complex because it is
based not only on population figures, eco
nomic activity or accumulated capital, but
also on history, the architecture of build¬
ings, prestige, political and administrative
activities (which define élites), intellectual
life, and an intangible element that makes
one city more of a city than another.
Major towns and cities enjoy looking
down on smaller ones as mere villages, and
their inhabitants as unpolished rustics.
Nevertheless, even the smallest village
appears as an urban microcosm in the sense
that the group is the core of all social life.
The word city, in the Mediterranean basin,
refers to all these different strata of urban
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
life, each of which is formed on the same
model.
The town, as a theatre for trade and
communication, leisure, and all aspects of
social life, is clearly distinct from the coun¬
tryside, which is a place of work, animal life
and the production of material goods. It is
not a simple, homogeneous place into
which anyone can walk and automatically
become a city- dweller. On the contrary, it
is a dense pattern of interwoven spaces
arranged in accordance with an unwritten
yet carefully respected order whose consti¬
tuent rules, apparent at every level of urban
life, define the complexity of a culture.
Modern town planning was born in the
Mediterranean, in fifth-century Greece,
with Hippodamos of Miletus, who invented
the grid layout. It has triumphed during
every era of cultural standardization,
whenever the systematic reproduction of an
established model, acclaimed as superior,
has taken a kind of revenge on spontaneous
development: in Hellenistic Greece, in
Rome, during the Renaissance and the
Baroque period, and in the contemporary
world.
More than the functional needs pro¬
claimed by Haussmann centuries later, it
proclaims the total transparency of in¬
habited space, and is, essentially, an urban
ideal in which order reigns over darkness
and the human mind is the dominant force.
Yet even in propitious circumstances, such
attempts at organization are checked by the
outer walls of the basic unit: the home. The
home is a haven for fundamental distinc¬
tions, the foremost being the separation
between public and private life, followed by
others that situate every man, woman and
child with respect to others around him
and to the world as a whole.
The home can be quite simple, even
rudimentary, comprising no more than a
room three metres square, with a door for
its sole aperture. Such dwellings were found
in archaic Greek cities, throughout the
Maghreb, in Sicily, and in the bassi of
Naples. Such are the homes of the poor to
this day. However, Mediterranean man en¬
larged his home at the earliest opportunity,
annexing an enclosed space (the Arabic
zareba), building around an interior court¬
yard (the atrium or cortile of patrician re¬
sidences), secluded from the indiscreet
glances of passersby. This type of construc¬
tion is horizontal rather than vertical.
However, with the Roman insulae, vertical
construction, as it appears in today's hous¬
ing blocks, began to superpose distinct
areas of space.
For the home always serves the same
purpose; it unites the family and its material
possessions (including animals) under one
roof, but it also separates the family from
the outside world, and safeguards the para
mount value: the honour of the family
group and its head. This explains the prop¬
itiatory rites governing the construction of
the home. It also explains the sanctity of the
threshold a frontier between interior and
exterior, a barrier against evil forces. It
cannot be crossed by all and sundry, and
those who do cross it must obey certain
rules of etiquette. The bride is carried over
it by a relative, after receiving the custom¬
ary offerings intended to ensure her ferti¬
lity; the guest may cross it only if he is
invited by the head of the household, and
only when he has offered a gift.
Beyond the threshold new distinctions
immediately arise. The inside of the home is
parcelled out and organized in the same way
as the outside world from which it is
severed. It is the domain of family and
privacy only because it is the sphere of the
woman in her reproductive role and as a
provider of nourishment. It is the place
where the essential biological functions of
feeding, resting and procreating are per¬
formed. Man's presence within this sphere
is strictly limited. He is excluded from it by
day, for his business is elsewhere, either at
CONTINUED PAGE 32
Blue clods blue with stridency
And, crazy vibration, melts, erases andmingles.
Thus the sea is created, second nudity. . .
Abdelmajid Choufi
(born 1939)
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The family house, often with rooms
groupedarounda central courtyard, is the
basic unit of Mediterranean towns and ci¬
ties, where its walls insulate the private
world of an intensely closed family life.
Outside, squares, streets and markets
form a theatre for the public activities ofa
zestful community life. Above, the cattle
market In a North African town. Above left,
tightly packed houses in a Sicilian village
south of Palermo.
Barriers visible and invisible mark off the
territory of the menfolk from that of the
women in traditional Mediterranean towns
and cities. The squares and pavement
cafés where men gather to talk and take
their place In the community are modern
descendants of the Greek agora and the
Roman forum. The women's realm, right,
Is traditionally in the privacy of the home,
bounded by the sacred threshold.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
In Roman and medieval times a rich intel¬
lectual, spiritual and Institutional heritage
was transmitted to Atlantic Europe from
the Mediterranean world. Its components
Included monotheistic religion and (until
the Reformation) a form of religious orga¬
nization dominated by Rome; language,
law and State institutions; the prestige of
the written word which inspired the medie¬
val copyists; and scientific instruments
for measuring time such as the sun dial
and the water clock. Right, detail from a
16th-century Ottoman manuscript shows
astronomers working atan Istanbulobser¬
vatory. Below, detail from Raphael's fres¬
co The School of Athens in the Vatican,
Rome. The fresco shows Plato and Aris¬
totlesurroundedbyphilosopherspastand
present.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Facts and figures
The total area of the 1 8 countries bordering on
the Mediterranean is slightly over 8.5 million
sq. km. The largest country is Algeria with an
area of almost 2.4 million sq. km., followed by
the Libyan Arab Jamahiriya (1 .7 million), and
Egypt (I million), although much of these
areas consists of desert. The areas of other
Mediterranean countries vary between
100,00 and 500,000 sq. km.
The estimated total population of these
countries is 350 million. France and Italy have
the highest population (about 55 million
each), followed by Turkey and Egypt with
about 45 million each. The countries with the
lowest population are Malta (350,000) and
Monaco (25,000).
Between 1950 and 1980, the demographic
growth rate of the north Mediterranean coun¬
tries ranged between 22 per cent (Italy) and
37 per cent (Yugoslavia). During the same
period the rate for Algeria and Tunisia was
116 per cent, 125 per cent for Morocco and
157 per cent for Syria. In the most developed
Mediterranean countries the percentage of
inhabitants aged under 15 ranges from 21 to
26 per cent (22 per cent for France, 25.7 per
cent for Spain). In the other countries the
corresponding rate ranges from 37 to 49 per
cent, i.e. almost twice as high (42 per cent for
Tunisia, 44 per cent for Egypt, 47 per cent for
Algeria and 48.8 per cent for Syria). These
figures point to a swing in the coming decades
both in numbers (from the currently more
populous northwest towards the southern and
eastern Mediterranean) and in composition by
age, with elderly populations in the north and
youthful or very youthful populations in the
south.
Apart from Malta with 1,100 inhabitants per
sq. km., population densities vary from 260
persq. km. in Lebanon to 2 in the Libyan Arab
Jamahiriya (one of the lowest in the world)
and slightly more than 8 in Algeria (also be¬
cause of the desert). Egypt is a special case,
with 44 inhabitants per sq. km. in the country
as a whole, but 1 ,000 in the Nile valley and
delta.
According to World Bank statistics none of
the Mediterranean countries belongs to the
category of least developed countries (annual
per capita income of less than $200). Most of
them belong to the middle income category.
They range from Egypt and Morocco ($700
and $760, respectively, in 1983) to Greece
($3,920). Five countries had a per capita in¬
come exceeding $4,500 in 1983: Israel
($5,730), Spain ($4,780), Italy ($6,400), the
Libyan Arab Jamahiriya (an oil-producer,
$8,480), and France ($10,500). The latter are
comparable to countries such as the United
States ($14,400) and Switzerland ($16,300).
The Mediterranean countries are not
afflicted with famine, although the food situa¬
tion is quite serious in some of them, such as
Egypt, where a large proportion of the popula¬
tion is undernourished.
Several countries in the Mediterranean
basin (led by the Libyan Arab Jamahiriya and
Algeria) are oil and gas producers, but their
deposits are smaller than those of the Middle
East. The region is not very rich in mineral
resources. Its share of world mineral produc¬
tion excluding energy products is about 6 per
cent in value terms. It holds a favourable
position in the production of phosphates (Mor-
POPULATION GROWTH IN MEDITERRANEAN
COUNTRIES 1950-1983
POPULATION 1950 1960
1950 /o
1960 1970 1970 1980 1983
IN THOUSANDS 1960 /o 1970 k
Spain 28,022 8.73 30,469 10.86 33,779 10.72 38,200
France 41,758 9.46 45,707 11.07 50,768 5.38 54,700
Italy 46,769 5.93 49,542 8.31 53,661 6.04 56,800
Monaco 20 25.00 25
Malta 312 5.45 329 326 5.21 350*
Yugoslavia 16,346 12.58 18,402 10.70 20,371 9.47 22,800
Albania 1,243 31.94 1,640 30.24 2,136 26.40 2,800
Greece 7,566 10.06 8,327 5.60 8,793 9.18 9,800
Turkey 20,809 32.20 27,509 26.68 34,848 28.85 47,300
Cyprus 494 15.99 573 5.41 604 2.65 620*
Syrian Arab Rep. 3,495 30.50 4,561 37.21 6,258 43.82 9,600
Lebanon 1,390 34.53 1,870 32.03 2,469 9.36 2,600
Israel 1,258 68.04 2,114 40.92 2,974 31.14 4,100
Egypt 20,461 26.25 25,832 29.02 33,329 19.42 45,200
Libyan A.J. 1,029 31.10 1,349 47.66 1,992 50.60 3,400
Tunisia 2,940 28.50 3,778 35.71 5,127 24.83 6,900
Algeria 8,753 23.39 10,800 32.69 14,330 31.89 20,600
Morocco 8,953 30.01 11,640 33.33 15,520 30.15 20,800
MEDITERRANEAN
TOTAL 211,598 15.52 244,442 17.54 287,305 15.62 346,595
WORLD
TOTAL 2,512,000 20.50 3,027,000 21.51 3,678,000 18.65 4,600,000*
Sources : United Nations Statistical Yearbooks
World Development Report, 1985. World Bank
* Plan Bleu
POPULATION DENSITY
l^B Over 100 inhabitants Km?
|g From 40 to 100
\^2 From 20 to *0
I 1 Less than 20 Source : The Times Adas of the World
andocco and Tunisia), alumina (France
Greece), and mercury (Spain).
The Mediterranean is the world's leading
tourist region. Out of 250 million international
tourists, between 80 and 100 million practi¬
cally one in three visit the Mediterranean
each year.
Source : Perspectives sur le Bassin Méditerranéen
(Développement et Environnement) -Plan Bleu pour la
Méditerranée, 1985.
According to World Bank projections
(1985 estimates), the total population of
the Mediterranean basin in 2025 will be
between 550 and 600 million persons. The
same projections show Turkey and Egypt
as the mostpopulous nations (each with a
population around 100 million), followed
by Algeria and Morocco (each with some
60 million inhabitants).
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 28
work in the fields, or in the city, in the
square, at the café, at meetings with other
men. In summer, it is even considered nor¬
mal for him to sleep out of doors on
occasion.
If the home prospers and becomes large
enough to entertain guests, it is divided into
two parts, one for receiving, the other for
the women the gynaeceum of classical
Greece, the women's apartments as
opposed to the men's area, the andron; the
sacred, forbidden harem of the Islamic
world. Even nomads' tents are partitioned
in this way. The barrier, representing a
strict dissociation between men's and
women's tasks, is functional. It is also laden
with symbolism.
By its very nature, the city as a:.space
where man must appear in public is disting¬
uished from two others. The first of these is
the home, which is a place for relaxation
and sleep, but which is also the woman's
Twice a year, on 2 July and 16 August,
thousands of spectators throng the mag¬
nificent shell-shaped Piazza del Campo
in Siena (Italy) to watch the Corsa del Palio
(Race for the Palio), a race of medieval
origin in which horses and riders repre¬
senting different wards of the city (con-
trade) compete for a silken banner or Pa¬
lio. Brilliant displays ofpageantryare held
before the race and excitement mounts to
fever pitch as the horses hurtle round the
cobbled square at breakneck speed. Be¬
low, the Piazza del Campo on Palio day as
depicted in an anonymous 18th-century
painting.
domain: closed, private, forbidden and to
be protected. The second is the country¬
side flat and empty, reserved for work
and nature. Thus, the city is a place for
action not involving work: ritual and festi¬
val, gesture and drama, leisure and games.
In considering the city as a place for
ritual, it is interesting to note that not one of
them lacks either a founder real or mythi¬
cal, hero or saint or a political and reli¬
gious centre, or a wall which unequivocally
separates it from the countryside and, like
the Roman pomerium, places it under di¬
vine protection. There is no city without an
easily comprehensible scheme: that of its
layout, when regular, that of its cardo and
decumanus, intersecting at right angles;
that of its axis of development; that of the
roads which were responsible for its found¬
ation, lead to its gates, and link it to other
cities across fields, desert or sea; that of the
orientation of its churches or the direction
in which prayers are offered. Every town
derives its meaning and special flavour from
a system of landmarks.
Whether they were designed geometri¬
cally or grew spontaneously, cities have
been organized for communication, for the
exchange of signs and symbols more than
for the exchange of goods. The street, that
narrow, encumbered passage which the
houses on it always seek to annexe as a
courtyard, is rarely the main scene of such
exchanges. It is a place where, given a few
chairs, the barber will shave his customers,
children will do their homework, or play
under the watchful eyes of women who sit
nearby sewing or knitting. The true centre
of urban life is the square, the destination of
CONTINUED PAGE 35
Colour page opposite
Above: the Interpénétration of cultures
and religions In the Mediterranean Is
often reflected In styles of monumental
architecture. The Great Mosque of Cordo¬
ba Is a famous example: a Christian
church was built within It after the city
was conquered by the kings of Castile.
Photo shows the Christian basilica of St.
Sophia In Istanbul, Turkey, a classical
example of the Byzantine style which had
widespread Influence In the Christian
West and In the Islamic East. After the
Turkish conquest In 1453, It was used as
a mosque and endowed with a mihrab
(the niche Indicating the direction of
Mecca) and four minarets.
Below: central nave of the Great Urn-
mayyad Mosque in Damascus, Syria, one
of the foremost sanctuaries of Islam (8th
century). It was built on the site ofa Chris¬
tian church and contains Byzantine mo¬
saics from an earlier period.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
f
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 32
the chaotic movement that flows through
the narrow alleys. Always better defended
from intrusion by individuals when there is
a strong sense of community, the square is
the public domain par excellence, and it has
been a fixture of Mediterranean town plan¬
ning since the Greek agora and the Roman
forum.
Consider, for example, the Plaza Mayor,
that inevitable, often sumptuous feature of
Spanish cities; the narrow squares that clus¬
ter around the ports of the Greek islands;
the Piazze della Signoria or Piazze del Com-
une of middle Italy; the Plaka the main
square of Dubrovnik, which stretches from
one gate of the city to the other, dividing the
city in -two. The square is the place for
holding meetings and discussions, assemb¬
ling citizens, organizing mass demonstra¬
tions, taking momentous decisions, and car¬
rying out executions.
Originally simply a meeting place, the
square soon became lined with porticoes
and arcades, providing shelter from sun and
rain. In most cases, it ceased to host mar¬
kets; instead it gathered around it the chief
religious and secular buildings, to which it
acted as an antechamber and proscenium,
as in the case of the temple of Rome and
Augustus, the curia, the cathedral, and the
ancient palace of the podesta.
It reflects its city's material and political
success. As the city expands, it diversifies.
The main square stands at the head of a
complex hierarchy that mirrors the social
order. There is a square for each neigh¬
bourhood, one for each ethnic and religious
community. There is also a square for each
function, market, cult, assembly or festival.
There are squares the size of streets, such as
the corsi, lined with the homes of the
prosperous and luxury shops, where pa¬
rades and solemn processions pass. Each
square also has class overtones; it is aris¬
tocratic or of the people.
The original destiny of Islamic cities
favoured a different utilization of space,
fragmenting the functions of the main
square. The only places where men can
assemble in the centre of the city are the
mosque and its courtyard, which are sur¬
rounded by madrasahs, hans, and baths. It
is here that decrees are announced and
prayers are intoned in the name of the ruler.
Commercial activity took root in the suqs
and bazaars. Other squares, perhaps the
largest, formed at the gates of the cities,
where travelling caravans entered and
camels were unloaded.
Alleyways, streets and squares form a
setting for leisure activities. The group puts
Colour page opposite
At home in the Mediterranean since neo¬
lithic times, the olive tree, the vine and
wheat form a classic trio and until quite
recently were the region's basic source of
nourishment. Their importance is shown
by their role In Christian holy ceremonies:
bread and wine at the sacrament of the
Last Supper, and holy oil for extreme unc¬
tion. Photos show ears ofcorn, a bunch of
grapes and an olive branch, carved on a
bas-relief In the temple of Ramses II at
Hermopolis in Egypt.
New corn, I am yourfaithful lover
Who longed to win you.
Good are the days when yourgrainforms
when you grow higher than a man,
andyour ears unfold.
Howgracefulyou are onyourstalk!
Ben Quzmán
(12th century)
on a performance and observes itself per¬
form. Men come there to talk and linger,
not to work. They have spent their night
fishing or their day tilling the fields, or else
like so many men in the Mediterranean they
only work irregularly, a few days each year,
and are waiting for some hypothetical job to
turn up. In recent years, it has become more
common for them to spend their working
years in the United States, the Federal Re¬
public of Germany, Venezuela, or Austra¬
lia, returning to spend the rest of their days
among their own. N
The city can thus impose its own pace,
which differs from the monotonous and reg¬
ular routine of the working day. It is discon¬
tinuous, it consists of words and silence, of
the lengthy discussions that precede every
decision, accompany every transaction, and
surround every event. It is the pace of the
stroll, of slowly savoured ouzo. Men do not
go into a café to drink but to take their place
in a society of men. It is the pace of the
game, which occupies such an important
place in the lives of the Mediterranean peo¬
ples. Its significance is manifest in the card
games depicted in a famous painting by
Cézanne and a memorable scene by Pagnol,
in the checkerboard squares traced on the
flagstones of the forum in Rome, in the
knucklebones and dice that have symbol¬
ized chance since the time of Caesar.
Games are played everywhere: in the
street by the poor, but more often in public
places, in cafés or on terraces, or else,
where social stratification exists, in clubs
and circles. Every Andalusian town and city
has its "labourers' circle", every Sicilian
town has at least one circle of "galantuomi-
ni", an institution that may undermine so¬
cial solidarity, but gives its members an
opportunity to meet their equals, get to
know them and challenge them in games
that invariably entail betting.
Of course, there are the business centres
such as Barcelona and Genoa, caught up in
the flow of international economic affairs
which they controlled in the past. But these,
in a way, are the exceptions. Everywhere
else, the values of leisureliness still hold
sway, just as they did in the Athens of
Pericles at the height of the city's import¬
ance as a centre of crafts and trade: work is
for other people. The only activity that has
an acknowledged place in all cities com¬
merce, the exchange of goods tends to go
on at a leisurely pace. What's the point of
making a deal too quickly? Buying and
selling, winning and losing are subsidiary to
the pleasure of bargaining, to the pro¬
tracted discussion that is broken off and
then resumed, concluded only when the two
participants congratulate one another on
having played the game so well.
But living under observation by others,
however important it may be, cannot be a
completely satisfying goal. The show would
stop for want of a purpose if it did not
engage the community as well as the indi¬
vidual. It calls for those major perform¬
ances which mobilize the group in its en¬
tirety, enabling its members to test and
demonstrate its cohesion, to express and
verify that cohesion, to feel its power, and
draw renewed confidence from it. Such per¬
formances mark the great moments of so¬
cial life. Condemnation by the moralists of
the Roman empire of the theatre, circuses,
chariot races and gladiatorial combats of
Antiquity, even when justified on account
of their decadence, has caused us to lose
sight of their religious origin and signifi¬
cance. Today, virtually everywhere, group
performances are related to sport; bullfight¬
ing in Spain, and the major religious and
civic festivals still celebrated in certain Ita¬
lian cities are two examples. In all cases,
these performances are staged with men , by
men and for men.
MAURICE AYMARD, French historian, is direc¬
tor ofstudies at the Ecole des Hautes Etudes en
Sciences Sociales andassistantadministratorof
the Maison des Sciences de l'Homme, in Paris.
For the past 20 years his research has mainly
focused on the history ofmodem Italy. The pre¬
sent article has been taken from La Méditerra¬
née, l'Espace et l'Histoire, (Flammarion pub¬
lishers, Paris, 1985), which was firstpublished, in
an illustrated edition, by Arts et Métiers Gra¬
phiques, Paris, in 1977.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Profile ofan inland sea
*.^i
I lili lili II I I I
iinniii
THE Mediterranean is sometimes de¬
scribed as a scale model of the world
ocean which facilitates the study of
important ocean phenomena. This is partly
true, as in the case of the analysis of inter-
oceanic exchanges or the formation of cold
waters, but on the whole, because of differ¬
ences of scale, attempts at extrapolation to
other oceans have not been successful. Be¬
cause of its size and situation, the
Mediterranean has a physiognomy and
dynamic of its own which do not occur
elsewhere, even in seas of comparable size.
It is too frequently asserted that the
Mediterranean is a dying if not dead
sea. I do not agree. True, there is justified
concern for its future on account of the risks
from pollution, but I do not think that the
solution is to cry wolf. The most responsible
and realistic solution to this real threat is to
develop new lines of research.
The Mediterranean ecosystem could be
described as a "machine" that generates its
own organization. In the Mediterranean, as
in any marine environment, all living
creatures, from micro-organisms to the big¬
gest fish and cetaceans, form part of an
extraordinarily complex chain. The system
is based on the producers, which use solar
energy to achieve a synthesis of living mat¬
ter from the mineral world. These produc¬
ers consist chiefly of micro-algae known as
phytoplankton. Starting with them, a food
chain is formed in which each link nourishes
the next. Phytoplankton, the "grassland" of
the sea, are consumed by small animals
the herbivorous Zooplankton which are in
turn consumed by carnivorous Zooplankton
AVERAGE ANNUAL PRECIPITATION
yïlpmiiBii«, . y " i
'/ V. M /
in
m Over 1 ,000 mm per year
'HillllHI, From 500 to 1,000 mm
lllllli: From 300 to 500 mm
1 I I I From 200 to 300 mm
I I Less than 200 mm Source: The Times Atlas of the World
which provide food for various species both
on the surface and lower down. Finally,
much of the animal waste is later restored to
the system by bacteria which transform it
into mineral elements, thus completing the
cycle of matter.
In the Mediterranean the functioning of
this "machine" or ecosystem depends close¬
ly on the unique geophysical conditions pre¬
vailing there. The extraordinarily heter¬
ogeneous and complex configuration of the
basins which constitute the Mediterranean
indicates that the sea has had a highly event¬
ful history, our understanding of which has
been greatly increased by a number of
geological and geophysical expeditions in
the last decade. One major event in this
history was undoubtedly the "Messinian
crisis" which occurred between five and six
million years ago, when the Mediterranean
was transformed into a huge "dead sea",
and all the water entering it from the neigh¬
bouring oceans evaporated, creating enor¬
mous deposits of salt which are now buried
under sediment. Such was the scale of this
crisis that it helped to modify the salinity of
the world ocean, providing a good illustra¬
tion of the interdependence of the
hydrosphere.
This tendency to evaporation persists to-
Between rainy Europe and the deserts of
Africa and Asia, the Mediterranean world
is unified first by the sea Itself, and then
by Its climate, typified by wide contrasts
In rainfall and the concentration of rainfall
In winter.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
by Ramón Margallef Estimated at 5,700 million tonnes in 1982,
the petroleum reserves of the Mediterra¬
nean basin amount to more than 6% of
the world total. Refineries are numerous,
and Italy, for example, has a capacity of
200 million tonnes. There is a substantial
tanker fleet, with Greece alone account¬
ing for some 44 per cent of total capacity.
Although less serious than pollution
originating on land, pollution linked to the
exploitation and transport of hydrocar¬
bons remains considerable. The amount
of oil discharged into the Mediterranean
each year ranges from 500,000 to one
million tonnes, only some 10 per cent of
which Is due to accidents at sea. Below, a
tanker sails past St. Mark's Square,
Venice.
Uli 1 1
T -_
I I
Mill I I ¡J
day and is one of the essential features of
the Mediterranean's hydrological régime.
The Mediterranean (including the Black
Sea) has a surface area of 2.96 million km2
for a volume of 4.24 million km3. Its aver¬
age depth is 1,429 metres, with the max¬
imum of 5,000 metres occurring in the Io¬
nian basin, which lies to the south of Italy
and Greece. One feature of the profile of
the Mediterranean is the shallow depth of
the ridges separating the chief basins 40
metres in the Bosphorus, 400 between Sicily
and Tunisia, 320 in the Straits of Gibraltar,
the sole link between the Mediterranean
and the ocean.
The hydrology of this sea which is almost
entirely enclosed has been the subject of
considerable research. At first sight the ba¬
lance is negative, since evaporation greatly
exceeds precipitation and inflows from
rivers. According to current estimates, eva¬
poration causes an annual loss of 1 ,000 mm
or nearly 2,900 km3 of water. Average
annual precipitation amounts to 310 mm,
which is low compared to the estimated
world average of 970 mm. Even if we take
into account precipitation throughout the
catchment area, which amounts to 550 mm
per year only a third of which reaches the
sea total precipitation does not exceed
500 mm per year. Thus there is a massive
shortfall, and it is not necessary to be a great
mathematician to see that without a com¬
pensatory phenomenon of some kind the
Mediterranean would dry up completely
within 2,000 years, as indeed happened dur¬
ing the Messinian crisis.
A compensatory mechanism is, there¬
fore, essential. It is provided by the Atlantic
Ocean but is not limited to a mere inflow of
water. Broadly speaking, it can be said that
the Mediterranean converts water coming
in from the Atlantic into typically
Mediterranean water, some of which re¬
turns to the Atlantic in the lower layers of
the Straits of Gibraltar. On the other hand,
the water which enters the Mediterranean is
surface water. It is less salty than Mediterra¬
nean water (about 36 g of salt per thousand)
and its volume is from twenty to forty times
greater than that of the evaporated water.
During the summer months this surface
water is subj ect to a high rate of evaporation
and consequently its salinity increases, but,
as a result of its high temperature, not its
density. During the winter, as it cools, its
density increases and it descends to a lower
level where it acquires the typical character¬
istics of Mediterranean water (T= 13°C, 38g
of salt per 1,000). This water, which subse¬
quently emerges in the lower layers of the
Straits of Gibraltar, spreads out in a sheet
into the Atlantic, as far as the Azores and
the Bay of Biscay. Consequently, when the
volume evaporated has been replaced, the
deep outflow is almost equal to the inflow,
thus ensuring a slow but steady renewal of
the water of the Mediterranean (according
to specialists it takes 180 years for the total
volume of water in the Mediterranean to be
renewed). Above all, this reciprocal ex¬
change with the Atlantic Ocean helps to
maintain salinity and prevents the
Mediterranean from being transformed
once more into a dead sea. It also creates
major turbulence phenomena in the Albor-
án basin between Spain and Morocco.
While the water dynamics described
above play an essential role in ecosystems,
other, sometimes more important mechan¬
isms intervene in the control of biological
cycles. Phosphorus, for example, which is
present in water in the form of phosphates,
is used in the synthesis of living matter by
phytoplankton, thus acting as a limiting
factor in biological productivity. Calcula¬
tion of the phosphorus balance in the ^
However longfortune may smile in aforeign country, the
lotus eater neverforgets his happy land, the verdant
wilderness in the InlandSea, the home ofa hundred
thousand souls,fallen like olives in the heat ofthe sun, a
hundred thousand souls and bodies oflight andfire, men
and womenfedonfruitandgrilledfish, quietly active,
dreaming and ready to seek distraction, sober and
voluptuous, hospitable in theirmysteryJealous ofthe
patch ofsand snatchedfrom the ancientFloodasfrom the
fever ofthe New World, as thefounders wished.
Kateb Yacine
(born 1929)
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Mediterranean reveals that elements are
recycled. By measuring the inputs pro¬
vided by water from the Atlantic, rains and
rivers and the outflows to the Atlantic,
losses in depth, withdrawals through
fishing, etc., the amount of phosphorus
theoretically available has been estimated
at about 500,000-600,000 tons per year.
Primary production, as far as it can be esti¬
mated at present, needs four times the
amount theoretically available. Thus the
speed of the biological cycle is higher than
that of the hydrological cycle. This confirms
that the same atom of phosphorus is used on
an average several times a year in the biolo¬
gical cycle.
This brief study of phosphorus also re¬
veals that the mechanisms responsible for
the recycling of nutrients form a safety de¬
vice which is continuously washing and
clearing the sea of accumulated waste. In a
sense the Mediterranean is withstanding
pollution better than other enclosed seas
such as the Baltic. However, this does not
mean that the mechanisms involved are
capable of coping with excess of all kinds.
No natural process can deal with an over¬
load that keeps growing indefinitely.
However, the mechanisms which restore
surface fertility are of limited efficacy.
Compared to other seas, the Mediterranean
is not very productive. Experts call it an
oligotrophic sea. By analogy with certain
terrrestrial ecosystems it could be said that
the Mediterranean corresponds to certain
semi-desert arid zones.
The relative poverty of the Mediterra¬
nean is reflected in the high transparency of
its waters, as a result of which it has been
described as a sea for tourists rather than
for fishermen.
In fact there are two main ecological sea¬
sons in the Mediterranean. A six-month
period from May to October is marked by a
significant rise in the temperature of the
surface waters, which may reach 25° or even
27°C. During this period these waters are
very sharply stratified, being separated
from the underlying cold layers by a very
pronounced thermal discontinuity known
as "thermocline". Save in rare circum¬
stances (local inshore mixtures or nutrient
salts brought down by rivers) fertilization is
out of the question. The transfer of nut¬
rients takes place downwards, by
sedimentation.
The second season, between November
and April, is described as "productive". As
the surface water cools, it sinks and is re¬
placed by water from lower down. The
homogenization of temperatures (in the re¬
gion of 13°C) all through the vertical profile
facilitates the mixing of the waters and
promotes a return of nutrients to the surface
and the development of phytoplankton.
A fisherman carrying strings of fish is
depicted In this mural dating from the
first half of the second millennium of the
pre-Christian era. It was discovered at
Thera (the Island of Santorin in the
Aegean Sea) and Is preserved In the
Archaeological Museum, Athens.
Currently available data (which are
admittedly far from complete) indicate that
the annual production ofZooplankton in the
Mediterranean amounts to about 8 g of
carbon per square metre. This is more than
enough to feed the higher links of the
trophic chain, especially pelagic fish and
cetaceans. But information is still scarce.
Mediterranean fisheries take about 40 mg
of carbon per square metre per year, some¬
times ten times more in certain zones of the
western basin. This is of course an excellent
yield in the light of what is known about
primary and secondary production levels.
Finally, I should point out that, according
to a general law of ecology, oligotrophic
ecosystems, while remaining at a relatively
low level of productivity, display far smaller
fluctuations over time than those observed
in more productive ecosystems. These fea¬
tures are, I believe, the chief characteristics
of the pelagic ecosystem" of the
Mediterranean.
FISHING
IN THE MEDITERRANEAN
Tonnes of fish taken
1968 1980
Spain 83,197 146,606
France 39,857 46,800
Italy 296,952 352,631
Monaco
Malta 1,300 1,023
Yugoslavia 30,061 34,968
Albania 4,000
Greece 55,815 75,745
Turkey 33,287 41 ,405
Cyprus 1,354 1,304
Syrian Arab Rep. 800 976
Lebanon 2,500 2,400
Israel 6,864 3,702
Egypt 13,560 19,939
Libyan Arab Jamahiriya 5,000 4,803
Tunisia 14,537 60,154
Algeria 18,200 38,878
Morocco 10,578 27,316
TOTAL 617,692 858,650
RAMON MARGALLEF, of Spain, has been pro¬
fessor of ecology at the University of Barcelona
since 1967. He is a specialist in the ecologyofthe
primary producers of marine and freshwater
plankton and in theoretical questions related to
the complexity of ecosystems and their develop¬
ment. The present article has been extracted
from a more detailed study of Mediterranean
plankton which has appeared in the French
scientific periodical La Recherche (September
1984).
Source : FAO, Rome
In 1980, the official fish catch In the
Mediterranean was 858,650 tonnes, or 1
per cent of the world total. The quality of
the species taken Is such that the percen¬
tage In terms of commercial value Is far
higher. The Mediterranean Is rich In fish
species, which number from 450 to 500
(as opposed to 170 In the Baltic), some
120 of which are fished. In tonnage more
than half the catch usually consists of
Clupeldae (anchovies, sardines, etc.),
followed by mackerel. Shellfish and
molluscs constitute just under 15 per
cent (by weight) of the total catch.
Perspectives sur le Bassin Méditerranéen (Développement et
Environnement)-Plan Bleu pour la Méditerranée, 1985
An Action Plan
for the Mediterranean
It is with regard to the Mediterranean Sea itself
and its protection that the common interest of
the countries bordering on it is greatest and
the need for their cooperation most striking. At
a meeting held in Barcelona in 1 975 under the
auspices of the United Nations Environment
Programme (UNEP), these countries adopted
a Convention for the Protection of the
Mediterranean Sea against Pollution, with
four technical protocols concerning the pre¬
vention of pollution by dumping from ships
and aircraft, the fight against pollution by hyd¬
rocarbons and other harmful substances, pro¬
tection against pollution originating on land,
and specially protected areas.
An Action Plan for the Mediterranean was
also approved. It is financed jointly by the
signatory States and by the European Econo¬
mic Community. In addition to legal activities
relating to the implementation of the Conven¬
tion and its protocols, the Action Plan includes
scientific research and monitoring pro¬
grammes relating to marine pollution as well
as economic and social planning com
ponents. The latter consist, firstly, of a pro¬
gramme of specific activities in what are
deemed to be priority areas (soil protection,
water resource management, human set¬
tlements, tourism, aquaculture and renewable
energy sources) and secondly, an exercise in
reflection and forecasting the Blue Plan
whose aim is to offer guidance for govern¬
ments according to different potential de¬
velopment scenarios.
Thus, for nearly ten years now, 1 7 of the 1 8
countries bordering on the Mediterranean,
setting aside the political differences existing
between some of them, especially in the east¬
ern Mediterranean, have jointly faced the
threat to their common environment. These
countries are Spain, France, Italy, Monaco,
Malta, Yugoslavia, Greece, Turkey, Cyprus,
the Syrian Arab Republic, Lebanon, Israel,
Egypt, the Libyan Arab Jamahiriya, Tunisia,
Algeria and Morocco. Albania sent a delega¬
tion for the first time to the meeting of
contracting parties held at Genoa in Septem¬
ber 1985.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
A cultural crossroads
by Giovanni Dotoli
«**
O
/
The Mediterranean can be seen at right of
this map of the worldproduced in 1154 by
the Hispano-Arab geographer al-ldrisi
(C.1100-C.1166). In accordance with a
convention of Islamic cartography at that
time, the south is shown at top of map.
THERE was already a flourishing civi¬
lization in the Mediterranean area
3,000 years before the Christian era.
Each of the regions of the Mediterranean in
turn has been a source of influence, each
has made an outstanding contribution to
the development of mankind. The sole
point of reference has always been the
material and spiritual progress of mankind.
From one era to the next, these successive
polarizations created a ferment of intellec¬
tual activity and a body of convergences
that make the Mediterranean tradition a
unique example of cultural identity.
The Mediterranean is a crossroads of
history uniting three continents Africa,
Europe and Asia, that is to say the entire
known world at the Renaissance in a pro¬
cess of reciprocal exchanges, a circular
movement which enabled each of the many
centres which emerged to absorb some¬
thing of the other.
The unity to which the Mediterranean
tends is inscribed in its long history and has
been sought many times in different parts of
the region. All the peoples and cultures
which today coexist in the Mediterranean
basin call for recognition and respect. In a
sense the Mediterranean peoples are at
once Arab, Greek, Hebrew and Latin. And
the history of the world would be quite
different without the contributions of these
peoples to science, medicine, literature,
law, religion and politics. It is therefore jus¬
tifiable to speak of a Mediterranean human¬
ism centred on the person, the basis of
every assertion of human rights.
Today the Mediterranean is seriously
threatened as a beacon of civilization
whose special feature is unity in diversity.
Urgent action is required if the Mediterra¬
nean basin is to be saved from grave cultur¬
al, economic and political damage.
Unless they commit themselves to active
collaboration, the Mediterranean countries
will be condemned by the kind of economic
relations that prevail in the world today to be
mere market outlets for the costly, unsuit¬
able products of an alien technology.
But if they overcome their prejudices and
realize that no one can succeed alone, the
Mediterranean countries, with their extraor¬
dinary economic situation, will be able to
surmount their handicaps rapidly and-
benefit from an interdependence recog¬
nized as indispensable.
In the conviction that cooperation is the
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
best way to halt this decline a Conference
on Scientific Cooperation between
Mediterranean Universities was held at
Bari (Italy) on 1 9 and 20 May 1 982. The aim
of the conference was to initiate an integra¬
tion process for Mediterranean peoples by
analysing the possibilities for cultural and
scientific collaboration. The following prop¬
osals were adopted:
- to establish training programmes in
conformity with the special cultural features
of the countries in the region and their
specific needs;
- to set up research groups concerned
with the protection and development of the
man-made and natural environments;
- to establish a data bank for education
and research;
- to create an information centre on the
activities of each university;
- to initiate training programmes in the
fields of energy, biotechnology, agro-food
production and hydrology;
- to prepare a map of existing Imbalances
in the fields of health and the environment;
- to set up intervention centres for the
protection of the cultural, artistic and natu¬
ral heritage and the defence of minorities;
- to draw up an inventory of the common
heritage of popular traditions;
- to establish a linguistics centre;
- to expand collaboration in music, the
visual arts, literature, archaeology and
town planning;
- to create university chairs related to
Mediterranean studies;
- to provide information about the norms
governing the activities of the various re¬
search institutions.
On these foundations the Community of
Head of a statue commemorating Ibn
Rushd (Averröes) In his native city of
Cordoba. This 12th-century Hispano-
Arab philosopher Is one of the most
Illustrious Intellectual symbols of co¬
operation and understanding among the
countries of the Mediterranean. Born in
Andalusia, he achieved a synthesis of
classical Greek philosophy (especially
Aristotelian theories) and Islam In a body
of work which profoundly Influenced the
thought of the Christian West.
Mediterranean Universities, whose mem¬
bers include some hundred universities
and research centres, was created in 1 984.
Its objectives are to reassert the role of
culture and scientific and technological re¬
search in solving the difficult problems sur¬
rounding the development of Mediterra¬
nean countries, and to promote scientific
cooperation between universities by using
the competence and resources of each of
them while respecting the specificity of the
different nations to which they belong.
The Community is not an isolated in¬
itiative. It forms part of a network of special¬
ized centres created by Unesco in different
countries in the region under the authority
of a general coordinating bureau.
In this way some of the conditions are
being met for the sustained and orderly
growth of Mediterranean countries, whose
unity and diversity are a source of strength
and fortune.
GIOVANNI DOTOLI, of Italy, is professor of
French language and literature at the University
of Bari, and general co-ordinator of the Commu¬
nity ofMediterranean Universities, of which he is
a co-founder. He has launched and directed
literary magazines and book series, including a
number of international co-publications. He has
taken part in many international seminars and
was rapporteur of a meeting on Mediterranean
writing organized by Unesco at Hammamet (Tu¬
nisia). He is the author of 16 books and many
essays on French and Italian literature, and as¬
pects of European and Mediterranean cultures.
Education: two Unesco programmes
A team of young Greek film-makers wishing to
develop educational television and interested
in what is going on in this field in other coun¬
tries has decided to participate in an ex¬
change project for educational films entitled
AVINTER. Turkey has introduced an innova¬
tive programme of cooperation between in¬
dustry and secondary education. How is it
organized and what are its results? A compa¬
rative study carried out by the Hungarian
National Institute of Education is evaluating
experiments of this kind in Mediterranean
countries. What are the consequences of in¬
troducing new technologies for the training
and further training of teachers? The Universi¬
ty of Bucharest recently organized a meeting
of specialists and is preparing a comparative
study on this question. The Bulgarian Institute
for Research in General Education is coordi¬
nating a project on the use of educational
games in schools. The Serbian Institute for
the Promotion of Education, in Yugoslavia,
has launched a pilot project concerning the
introduction of methods of self-instruction in
primary schools. The results are promising
and were recently analysed at a meeting of
specialists held in Yugoslavia.
These are some of the activities included in
the programme of Co-operation in Research
and Development of Educational Innovation
in Southeast Europe (CODIESEE) in which,
under Unesco auspices, Bulgaria, Greece,
Hungary, Romania, Turkey and Yugoslavia
are taking part. The programme, which has
just been extended to Spain, Italy, Malta and
Portugal, enables participating institutions to
exchange information and carry out joint re¬
search through seminars, meetings of spe¬
cialists, joint research projects and study
visits.
The research themes of the CODIESEE
programme are selected by a coordination
group which meets every two years at
Unesco's invitation. One of the participant
institutions is responsible for the scientific and
administrative coordination and direction of
the selected projects. The role of Unesco,
which provides technical backing and a mea¬
sure of financial support, is essentially that of
a catalyst. The success of the programme is
largely due to the willingness of the participat¬
ing bodies to cooperate in the search for
solutions to their common problems.
One of the biggest Unesco field operations
in education is the joint programme carried out
in cooperation with the United Nations Relief
and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in
the Near East (UNRWA). Cooperation be¬
tween Unesco and UNRWA began in 1950
and is the subject of an agreement between
the two organizations. Its purpose is to de¬
velop primary and preparatory education for
Palestine Arab refugee children, to contribute
to the training of teachers, and to provide
vocational and technical training facilities and,
to a limited extent, secondary and university
education for Palestine Arab refugees.
UNRWA is responsible for administering
the educational programmes for Palestine
Arab refugees, while Unesco assumes tech¬
nical responsibility. Unesco's action consists
mainly in the initial and further training of
teachers, the improvement of school build¬
ings, laboratories and scientific libraries and
the publication of school textbooks and
teaching materials.
A few figures will give an idea of the scale of
the Unesco-UNRWA programme. In 1983-
1984, 241,237 young Palestine Arab re¬
fugees were enrolled in UNRWA-Unesco
primary schools in Jordan, the West Bank, the
Gaza Strip, Lebanon and the Syrian Arab
Republic, the teaching staff numbered 5,985.
The corresponding figures for UNRWA-Un¬
esco preparatory schools were 101,800
pupils and 3,274 teachers. The number of
university grants awarded under the UNWRA-
Unesco programme ranged from 1 43 in 1 950-
1951 to 1,088 in 1967-1970, levelling out at
approximately 350 fellowships per year from
1973-1974 to 1983-1984.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
The birthplace
ofsubmarine archaeology
by Selim Morcos
THE waters of the Mediterranean
are the world's richest in terms of
the ancient artifacts and structures
that lie beneath them.
In ancient times, the Mediterranean
played a major role in communication
between its people, many of them sea¬
farers, throughout a succession of civili¬
zations, distinct from but influenced by
each other. Ships bearing cargoes and
passengers plied the sea lanes from port
to port. In the early days of navigation,
casualties were very high. As a result, the
shallow inshore waters are dotted with
shipwrecks. Moreover, in many places
the shoreline has been subjected to natu¬
ral processes such as subsidence and coas¬
tal erosion which have led to the sub¬
mergence of many of the ancient har¬
bours, and to the disappearance of fine
examples of old maritime structures and
buildings.
The presence of these extraordinary
riches combined with other factors to
make the Mediterranean the natural
birthplace of underwater archaeology, a
new field of investigation that was gra¬
dually opened up by the development of
diving techniques during the Second
World War, assisted by modern technol¬
ogy in submarine surveying, photography
and submersibles.
Underwater investigation is favoured
in the Mediterranean by the fact that the
water temperature makes diving agree¬
able during most of the year, while the
transparency of the water and the clear
sunny weather enhance the penetration
of sunlight and increase visibility in re¬
latively shallow depths.
Many of the early finds were made by
sponge divers or fishermen. In fact,
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Left, submarine archaeologists photo¬
graph and map the wreck ofa Bronze Age
ship that sank off the southern coast of
Turkey In the 14th century BC or earlier.
The shipwreck Is the oldest ever exca¬
vated.
sponges are widespread in the warm wa¬
ters of the eastern Mediterranean, at
depths of less than sixty metres; and
sponge diving is one of the oldest profes¬
sions in the Aegean.
It was a fisherman who made one of the
first discoveries, in 1832, when he found
in his nets a beautiful bronze statue of
Apollo from 460 BC, while Turkish
sponge divers discovered one of the old¬
est shipwrecks ever investigated (1200
BC). The latter was excavated by Peter
Throckmorton and George Bass between
1958 and 1960. Its one-ton cargo of cop¬
per and bronze ingots shed new light on
Phoenician seafaring in the Bronze Age
and on trade and metallurgy in that
period.
Greek sponge divers discovered the
famous shipwreck at Mahdia, Tunis, in
1907. Five costly expeditions between
1908 and 1913 led to the most brilliant
early success in submarine archaeology,
resulting in the recovery of a cargo of
works of the finest Greek art. The trea¬
sures of Mahdia now occupy five rooms in
Alaoui Museum, Le Bardo, Tunis. Of
particular interest is a magnificent 1.25-
metre-high bronze statue of a young man
personifying Eros, the god of love, by the
sculptor Boethios the Chalcedonian.
Excavations at Mahdia continued until
after the Second World War, providing a
vivid demonstration of, and testing
ground for, diving techniques. It was at
Mahdia in 1948 that the newly invented
aqualung was applied for the first time in
submarine archaeology, by a French
team led by Jacques-Yves Cousteau and
Philippe Taillez who carried out scientific
investigations and raised more cargo to
the surface using a water jet to remove
mud. Later, members of the Tunisian
Club of Undersea Studies, using an air¬
lift, a kind of powerful underwater
vacuum cleaner they had designed for
themselves, removed mud and unco¬
vered the twenty-five-metre keel which
suggested the ship was about thirty
metres long. Other wooden parts offered
valuable information on Roman ship con¬
struction, and as a result a plan was made
of the ship.
When studying wrecks, archaeologists
seek to analyse the cargo and investigate
the construction of the hull, since this
contributes to our understanding of
trade, economy, ship-building and mari¬
time history. Two characteristics of
ancient wrecks are rarely encountered in
land archaeology: the collection in one
place of many objects that were in use at a
specific time and the fact that they suf¬
fered no alterations by human interfer¬
ence since the time of the wreck. Each
wreck is "a miniature Pompeii that
vanished tragically at a precise point in
time," pioneer submarine archaeologist
Honor Frost has said.
Submarine archaeology is, in fact, not
a search for souvenirs, but a scholarly
pursuit or search for knowledge. Many of
the wrecks discovered in the Mediterra¬
nean were carrying cargoes of amphorae,
the classical containers used for trans¬
porting fresh water, wine, olive oil, grain
and other commodities, The tonnage of
the ship can be estimated from the total
number of amphorae. The shape of and
inscriptions on amphorae provide clues
as to the date and place of manufacture.
Their position in the cargo, at the bottom
or on deck, may also cast light on the
route of the ship.
One interesting example of trade
emerged from an eleventh-century wreck
at Serçe Limani in Turkey, which was
excavated by George Bass between 1977
and 1979. The cargo included three tons
of broken Islamic glass representing the
remains of 10,000 glass vessels. Bass won¬
ders if this ship was Islamic because of the
contradictory evidence revealed by the
cargo. A secondary cargo of wine was
carried in amphorae marked with Byzan¬
tine Christian inscriptions. Islamic gold
coins were intermingled with Byzantine
copper coins. Official Islamic glass
weights were found side by side with offi¬
cial Byzantine lead seals.
Until the advent of submarine
archaeology, few examples of ancient
ships were known. They included a Ro¬
man ship (220-160 BC) found behind the
Stock Exchange in Marseilles and the
"solar boat" (2600 BC) discovered in
1954 in a pit near the Khufu (Cheops)
Pyramid, south of Cairo. Then awareness
that a large number of ancient wrecks lay
on the sea-bed suddenly heightened the
interest of specialists and the public in
wooden ship architecture, which had
faded when sailing ships were replaced by
steam ships. Many revealing lessons have
been learned from sunken hulls. From
thorough study of the hull of a ship at
Yassi Ada in Turkey, dating from the
time of the emperor Heraclius (610-641
AD), George Bass was able to conclude
that the hull was built partly by the mod¬
ern "skeleton first" method, and partly
by the Greco-Roman "shell-first"
method. From this he deduced that the
modern method of constructing carvel-
built hulls evolved from the older Greco-
Roman method at some point during the
late Roman period.
Five varieties of timber were used in
the construction of the Roman ship found
behind the Marseilles Stock Exchange.
The keel was of cypress and all the rib¬
bing of pine. Certain varieties of wood
were used for the longitudinal elements,
and others for the transversal elements,
thus confirming the texts of ancient wri¬
ters on the qualities, uses and sources of
different varieties of wood.
Another field in which submarine
archaeology is active is the discovery and
exploration of lost harbours and sub¬
merged cities. In 1910 Gaston Jondet dis¬
covered, west of Alexandria, completely
submerged at a depth of about 8.5metres,
the piers of an entire seaport of a colossal
scale which dwarfs many present-day har¬
bours. The find aroused considerable in¬
terest because of the massive size of the
submerged masonry and the skilful
method of its construction. This was the^
A huge statue of the Egyptian goddess
Isis (7 metres long and weighing 25 tons)
was discovered on the sea bed In the
harbour of Alexandria In 1961 and sal¬
vaged the following year. It Is thought to
have adorned one of the Seven Wonders
of the World, the ancient lighthouse of
Alexandria which was built In the 3rd
century BC. The statue can be seen today
In the gardens of the catacombs of
Kom-el-Chogafa In Alexandria (below).
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
gj jr;
The remains of a Roman ship were
discovered near the Marseilles Stock
Exchange In 1974. Photo shows workmen
preparing for the delicate operation of
transporting the wreck to the city's His¬
tory Museum.
first detailed survey of an ancient
harbour.
From 1931 to 1934, Père Antoine
Poidebard made an elaborate survey of
the Phoenician harbour of Tyre. Later,
Honor Frost and others studied several
old ports in the east Mediterranean such
as Arwad, Tyre, Sidon, Caesarea and
Athlit. In 1958-59, the British oceano-
grapher and marine archaeologist Nicho¬
las Hemming led a Cambridge University
expedition to the sunken Greek port of
Apollonia (Susah) on the Cyrenaican
coast of Libya. Built on a Phoenician
plan, the port was a two-harbour city.
The outer harbour received trading ships
while the inner harbour was fortified to
protect the city. The two harbours were
connected by a narrow channel flanked
with long walls to defend the inner har¬
bour against invaders.
The Romans made great progress in
harbour construction. Robert Günther,
an Oxford don, surveyed the elaborate
Roman ports of the Bay of Naples be¬
tween 1901 and 1903. Later, the French
diver Philippe Diolé visited many Roman
ports in North Africa, and devoted par¬
ticular study to Caesarea, the most im¬
portant military harbour between Carth¬
age and Gibraltar, which is now known as
Cherchel in Algeria.
O Tyrus, thou hast said, I am ofperfect beauty. Thy
borders are in the midst ofthe seas, thy builders have
perfected thy beauty. They have made all thy ship boards
offir trees ofSenir: they have taken cedars ofLebanon to
make mastsfor thee. Ofthe oaks ofBashan have they
made thine oars; the company ofthe Ashurites have made
thy benches ofivory, brought out ofthe isles ofChittim.
Fine linen with broidered workfrom Egypt was that which
thou spreadestforth to be thy sail.
The Holy Bible
Lighthouses were often constructed as
aids to navigation. When Alexander the
Great reached Alexandria, he con¬
structed the Eastern Harbour by linking
the island of Pharos to the mainland with
a narrow causeway, the Heptastadium.
The entrance to the Eastern Harbour was
so narrow that the lighthouse of Alexan¬
dria was constructed under Ptolemy II in
the third century BC. One of the seven
wonders of the world, the lighthouse was
a three-story structure probably rising to
a height of 120 metres. It survived until
the fourteenth century, when it was des¬
troyed by earthquakes. The coastal re¬
gion of Alexandria has also undergone
subsidence, and many buildings around
the old Eastern Harbour have been lost
to the sea. In 1961, an Alexandrian
amateur diver, Kamel Abu Al-Saadat,
discovered a massive statue of the god¬
dess Isis, weighing about twenty-five
tons. It was brought to the surface in
1963. In 1968, Honor Frost undertook a
Unesco mission to Alexandria on the in¬
vitation of the Egyptian Government.
After several d^ves on the site of Pharos,
she identified, with the help of Kamel
Abu Al-Saadat, seventeen different ob¬
jects. She believes that the large statue of
Isis and the other items are almost cer¬
tainly remains of the famous Pharos.
But underwater archaeology in the
Mediterranean today is not only con¬
cerned with such comparatively "recent"
monuments as the lighthouse of Alexan¬
dria. One of the most important new
developments is the study of very early
human settlements on the continental
shelf.
During the Ice Ages, huge ice sheets
covered Antarctica and large areas of the
northern hemisphere. Because a large
amount of seawater was frozen in the ice
caps, the sea level dropped by as much as
100 metres, thus exposing a wide area of
the continental shelf. This area, sloping
gradually beyond the present shoreline of
continents and islands, became available
as a living space for early man, and as
land bridges between continents and
islands.
The discovery of fossil bones and other
evidence by anthropologist Richard
Leakey and his colleagues has led to the
belief that manlike creatures (East Africa
man) existed in Africa around 1.5 million
years ago. These early men moved gra¬
dually into Asia and Europe over the land
bridges created during the Ice Age, and
particularly through the Isthmus of Suez,
the southern end of the Red Sea, between
Tunisia, Sicily and Italy, and between
Morocco and Spain. Until now there has
been no direct evidence from below the
sea of human use of these land bridges
(today sea straits), in spite of research
carried out on caves below sea level in
Gibraltar and Malta. However, in the last
ten years, research by Nicholas Hem¬
ming and other expeditions in the eastern
Mediterranean, have found for the first
time convincing evidence, mainly Stone
Age relics, on the continental shelf which
was inhabited and exploited by Stone
Age people to a depth of ten metres
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
below the present sea level, from at least
40,000 BC until the beginning of the
Bronze Age in the Middle East, about
6,000 years ago.
Today underwater archaeology is an
increasingly popular pursuit. But its very
popularity and success have brought
problems. The development of the
aqualung has given the professional
archaeologist a powerful tool; on the
other hand, it has also provided access to
amateur divers, many of whom admitted¬
ly are aware of the importance of the
great heritage lying beneath the sea.
However, some of these divers are also
fond of beautiful, rare objects and sou¬
venirs. Worse still, the existence of a
market for algae-encrusted antiques from
beneath the sea has attracted looters and
racketeers.
Even if objects of archaeological value
are presented to local museums, some of
their scientific value is lost, because they
are removed from their context. Old
stone or metal anchors, for example,
could give valuable information on mari¬
time routes if their distribution is proper¬
ly plotted. Souvenir hunters can disrupt
these studies.
The expansion and improvement of
harbours and old cities such as Alexan¬
dria, Athens and Naples have also re¬
sulted in severe losses. This man-made
destruction is intolerable and calls for
urgent remedy and an acceleration of
survey work, recording and study.
One big dilemma facing archaeologists
is what to do with the material they sal¬
vage, especially if they are dealing with a
bulky shipwreck or hundreds of amphorae.
Conventional museums tend to relegate
such material to their store-rooms or
backyards. A more innovative but costly
approach is to establish special museums
such as the Bodrum Museum of Under¬
water Archaeology in Turkey, which was
created in the late 1950s and now displays
the finds of five scientifically excavated
ancient shipwrecks.
SELIM MORCOS, Egyptian oceanographer, isa
senior programme specialist in Unesco's Divi¬
sion of Marine Sciences. Before joining Unesco
in 1973, he taught at the University ofAlexandria
where he carried out research on the exchange
of sea water between the Mediterranean and
Red Seas. He is interested in the history of
oceanography and in underwater archaeology,
on which he has written the only book in Arabic,
"Sunken Civilizations, the Story of Submarine
Archaeological Discoveries".
The ancient seaport of Apollonla on the
Libyan coast today lies half underwater,
either because of land subsidence or a
rise In sea level. While surveying a
submerged Roman Piscina or fish preser¬
vation tank atApollonla, divers found this
well-preserved marble torso and head of
a faun, now In the Archaeological Mu¬
seum at Cyrene, Libyan Arab Jamahiriya.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Mediterranean voices
Asyou set outfor Ithaka
hope thejourney may be long,
full ofadventure, full ofdiscovery. . .
Hope thejourney may be long.
May there be many a summermorning
when with whatpleasure, whatjoy,
you enter harboursyou're seeingfor thefirst time.
Keep Ithaka always inyour mind.
Arriving there is whatyou 're destinedfor	
Constantine Cavafy
(1863-1933)
Theplain ofwater ripplingfalls.
Still secret the sun
bathes in its urns.
Waterwave incarnadine.
With sudden gentle eyes
opening on the bays.
The submerged shadow ofthe rocks dies.
Giuseppe Ungaretti
(1888-1970)
Nowyou are on the edge ofthe Mediterranean
Beneath the lemon trees thatflowerallyear long
You go sailing withyourfriends. . .
We watch with terror the octopuses ofthe depths
Andamong the algae swimfish images ofthe Saviour
Guillaume Apollinaire
(1880-1918)
The cries ofHeracles the Mighty
resound in the bay.
Hey, they're taking the bulls away,
theproudfighting bulls!
With theirforeheads like whirlwinds
andsplintering horns .
Roaring ofthe sea and the wind
ofthe saltmarshes.
Opening a new way
to the shores,
Hercules advances, the stealer ofbulls
ofthe saltmarshes.
Rafael Alberti
(born 1902)
Correction
We regret that, on page 18 of our November issue devoted to Victor
Hugo, the captions referring to the colour photos appearing on page 22
were inversed. The upper photo on page 22 depicts Le Rocher Ortach
and the lower photo shows La Tour des Rats.
You sleep dense beauty ofsummer
o blinding immensity
brightness on brightness in the brightness
abyss on abyss in the abyss
all the cries ofall the shipwrecked mingle in you
and soothed today inyour vain diamantine harmony.
Dusan Matic
(1898-1982)
Justas then, today, I am stilled byyourpresence,
sea, butthink myselfno longer worthy
ofthe solemn warning
thatyou breathe. You werefirst to tell me
that the tinyferment
ofmy heart was simply an impulse
ofyours; that in my depth ofbeing
there wasyourperilous law. . .
Eugenio Móntale
(1896-1981)
Acknowledgments
Extract from Homer (page 5) is taken from E.V. Rieu's translation of the
Odyssey, published by Penguin Books Ltd. Extract from Virgil (page 6) is
from The Eclogues, The Georgics, translated by C. Day Lewis (Oxford
University Press, 1983). Extract from the Qur'an (page 26) is taken from
the translation by N.J. Dawood, published by Penguin Books Ltd. Extracts
from the poems "Ithaka" by Constantine Cavafy (this page), "In the
Manner of G.S." by George Seferis (page 6), and "Drinking the Sun of
Corinth" by Odysseus Elytls (page 8) translated from the Greek by
Edmund Keeley and Philip Sherrard and published in Voices of Modern
Greece, Princeton University Press, 1981. Extract from the poem
"Silence in Liguria" by Giuseppe Ungaretti (this page) translated from the
Italian by Michael Fineberg.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco. 7, Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 68 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 1 20 French francs Binder for a year s issues:
5! FF
The UNESCO COURIER i» pubktned monthly,
individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Repnoted tram the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date ol issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed anieles reprinted must
(Mar authors name. Non-copyngbi photos will be supplied on
reouest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage Signed «deles ««press the opinions ol the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions ol UNESCO or those
of the editors ol me UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines aie written by the Unesco Courier staff The ooun-
Panes on maps published in the magazine do not imply official
endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations
The Unesco Courier is produced m microform (microfilm and
or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700
Paris: {2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor. Michigan
48100. USA : (3| NCR Microcard Editen, Indian Head. Inc.
in West 40th Street. New York. USA.: (4) Bell end Howe«
Co.. Ok) Mansfield Road. Woosler. Oho 44691. U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Roy Malkin
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Jorge Enrique Ado urn
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayad Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander BroîdO (Tal Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morran (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedlcto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Metra llgazer (Istanbul).
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Aziz ah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Pa Ik Syeung.Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
¡Dar-es-Salamj
Croato-Serb, Macedonian. Serbo-Croat, Slovene: Vrto-
mir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shan Guolen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgtou (Athens)
Sinhala: S J Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: M at) ana Oksanen Helsinki)
Swedish: Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurulz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savilri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustration*: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special project«: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-
in-Chief in Paris
BRODARD GRAPHIQUE, COULOMMIERS - Depot légal Cl - Décembre 1985 - IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
. , PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de lUnesco, MONTAGE : Micro-Compo - 17, rue Béranger - 75003 Paris, PHOTOGRAVURE : Dawant - 13, rue des Arquebusiers 75003
T-O Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Index 1985
January
WATER AND MAN (G. Voropayev). Nature's water wheel. Erosion, drought and
deserts. Drought over Africa. The menace of desert advance. Mining fossil
water. Unesco's International Hydrologlcal Programme. Acid rain. Cities
athlrst Washing dirty water. Waterlords of ancient Sri Lanka. The deadly snails
of Dongfeng (Zhang Blhua)
February
UBRARIES AND ARCHIVES. The memory of mankind (J.L. Borges). Librarles
and archives for tomorrow (J.S. Parker). Legal status of national archives (C.
Kecskemet!). African archives and the oral tradition (A.A. Mazrul). The "Ar¬
chives agreement" (LS. Senghor). Unesco's library and archives. The Vatican
library (A.M. Stickler). The Monte del Paschi archives (P. Baruccl). Grassroots of
the pampas (C.A. Garcia Belsunce). The computer revolution (R.M. Dougherty).
History off the record (E. Franz). Sense and censorship (P. Hanak). The Lenin
Library. The new science of bibliology (A.-M. Blanchi). A "What's What" of
libraries and archives.
March
THE URBAN EXPLOSION. International competition for young architects. Ar¬
chitecture and the city (K. Tange). A city for the year 2000 (O. Niemeyer). The
metamorphosis of Cairo (H. Fathy). Unesco and the conservation of old Cairo.
The urban explosion. The outlook for urban man. A back-to-the-earth approach
to housing (J. Dethler)
April
WOMEN OF THE MEDITERRANEAN (N. Göle). Latin American woman (L.
Futoransky). Women under apartheid (C. Flepp). Johan Sebastian Bach (A.
Basso). Niels Bohr (J. Gribbin). In defence of folklore (J.P. Gulbbert). Unesco
and the preservation and protection of folklore. Bartolomé de Las Casas (S.
Zavala). Cartagena de Indias (R. Duran).
May
FORTY YEARS AFTER THE END OF WORLD WAR II. Peace and human values
(A.-M. M'Bow). Why war? (A. Einstein). Cultural persecution (F.V. Grunfeld).
Strange hiding place (A. Malraux). The art of concealing art (H. Plenderleith). Art
under siege (B. Piotrovsky). Can we save civilization? (Y. Kirshln). The forgot¬
ten resistance. A time-table for peace (G.N. Sato). Unesco: the birth of an ideal.
A new hope In the nuclear age (L. Thomas). Nuclear winter. Unesco and peace
research.
June
YOUTH 1985. In search of the present (E.Khaliffé). That first job. World
Congress on Youth. Unesco Courier International survey. A day In the life of....
Spotlight on youth. Streets apart (M. Fall). Africa's generation gap (B. Ly).
Chinese youth (Tang Ruoxln). A truce for children (H. Ahrweiler)
July
WHAT'S NEW IN ARCHAEOLOGY? (C. Renfrew). Let the past serve the future
(0. Odak). Science unlocks the secrets of the past (T. Hackens). El templo
mayor (E. Matos Moctezuma). From the Throne of Stone (B.A. Lltvinskiy, I.R.
Plchikiyan). Moenjodaro (S.A. Naqvl). My life as an archaeologist (Guo Zhan).
August
THE SPOKEN AND THE WRITTEN WORD. The living voice (P. Zumthor). The
Kalevala (L Honko; H. Klrklnen). The Chronicle of Mlchoacán (J.M.G. Le Clézio).
The Lay of Igor's Campaign (I. Shkliarevsky). Shaka the Great (M. Kunene). The
glory of the spoken (S. Stétié). The Tale of the Heike (R. Sieffert). The Mahabha-
rata (l_ Bhattacharya). Liu Jingtlng, prince of story-tellers (Yao Zhenren).
Tibet's Ge-sar epic (M. Helffer). Hlr and Ranjha (H.M. Said). Basque literature
and the oral tradition (J.M. Lekuona).
September
MIGRANTS. A challenge for the schools (G. Vignaux). City lights (Y. Atal).
Unesco and international migration (R.G. Parrls). Between two cultures: France
(A. Buhamldi); the Fed. Rep. of Germany (G. Apitzsch, N. Dittmar); United
Kingdom (R. Miles); North America (A.P. Maingot); the Gulf States (E. Longue-
nesse); Scandinavia (C. Swetland). The psychology of migrant workers (A.
Vasquez). Return ticket (E.-J. Thomas, C. Wihtol de Wenden).
October
UNESC0 1945, BIRTH OF AN IDEAL (H. Brabyn). The precursors. The life of the
mind (C. Attlee, E. Wilkinson, J. Torres Bodet, R. Cassln). The San Francisco
Conference (H.S. Truman, A. Gromyko, E. Padilla). The mood of Britain, 1 945 (A.
Briggs). Putting the 'S' in Unesco. Early days (J. Huxley). Can we educate for
world peace? (A. MacLelsh). The application of science and art. Finding a home
for Unesco.
November
VICTOR HUGO. A 'modem' poet? (J. Gaudon). Hugo's life and times (E. Blewer).
A novelist and his century (V. Brombert). The sack of the Summer Palace (V.
Hugo). African first nights (J. Théphany). The showman poet (R. Char). Hugo in
China (LI Meiying). The Jean Valjean of writers (Y. Yevtushenko). A living
presence in Brazil (J. de Souza Rodrigues). At home with Hugo (R. Darío).
Caramba! (S. Sarduy).
December
THE MEDITERRANEAN (F. Braudel). Transformation and tradition In Mediterra¬
nean Europe (S. Giner). A region In search of itself (P. Apollto). Unesco and
cooperation In the Mediterranean. Patterns of urban life (M. Aymard). Profile of
an Inland sea (R. Margallef). The Action Plan for the Mediterranean. A cultural
crossroads (G. Dotoli). The birthplace of submarine archaeology (S. Morcos).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept-, P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 175,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-1011, Vienna. BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R,K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88. Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM".
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-1 13 02, Prague
1 ; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 1 1 - 27 Prague 1 (Permanent
display}; Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy. Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier {German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D53O0 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport - ABT, P.O.B. 149
H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 1 3; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 1 0001 .
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 1 88 Enghlab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 1 31 58, P.O. Box 1 1 365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water. Lane. Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 113. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd.;
Quran House, Mfangano Street, P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd,
POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod. Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 9494 Schaan.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service,
Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.. 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prekashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V.. Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200,'Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 1 30, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1 72 1 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1 104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1 , Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional
Office for Book development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi
Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES.
National Book Store, Inc. 701, Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-'Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmtescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National 8ookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mané; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mané. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra
Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road,
Singapore 2261. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern
Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH
AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1 1 18,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl.
Regeringsgatan 12, Sox 16356. 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 1 50 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62-101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
1 1 , CCP. 1 2-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. TANZANtA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Kmng Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. TURKEY. Haset Kitapo/i A.S.,
Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC IX 9 DS. UNITED STATES. Ünipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 1001 7. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor. Ml 48106. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121 200. YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, P.O. Box 4227, Aden. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, llica 30/1 1, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/1 1, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
V '
A city wedded to the sea
For centuries Venice was mistress of the Mediterranean, her supremacy symbolized in
magnificent ceremony wedding her Doge (duke) to the sea. Venetian painters often recorded
this alliance between city and sea. chronicling the city's activities and the distant voyages of
her ships. Photo shows a detail of The Departure of the Betrothed, one of a series of scenes
illustrating the legend of St. Ursula executed by the Venetian painter Carpaccio |c.1465-c. 1525, .
]]>
</page>
</document>
