<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068057eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
SEPTEMBER 1957 Price: 9d. (U. K.)
25 cents (U. S.)
40 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
History's greatest science research project
OPERATION GLOBE
Each of the 2,500,000,000 persons on earth lives in a local culture that is dis¬
tinctive in. its dress and social customs, in its habits of living and thinking, in its
government and politics. Until recently most cultures regarded all others as strange or
even inferior. A visitor from a far planet would be fascinated by this remarkable
diversity. Yet he would be equally impressed by what men have in common, the
essential humanity that is often not visible to us across the geographical and cultural
barriers.
The diversity of human cultures is paralleled by a striking diversity in the environ¬
ment, in the climate, the terrain and the soil. Mountains and plains, deserts and
humid forests, icy winters and the blazing sun, rivers and the many arms of the sea are
contrasting scenes that offer different foods and clothing, from rice to blubber, from
grass skirts to polar parkas. Plants and animals vary with the environment, and man
adapts to them all.
But the vast variety of scenery has an underlying unity too. It all derives from the same materials and forces
that compose our world the same rocks and waters, the power of the sun, the rotation and revolution of the earth
itself, the tilt of its axis, the weight of the continents, the heat of the deep plastic interior, the rushing rivers, great
ocean currents and the winds that brush the sky. Acting through the ages, they have shaped our geography as the
latter has shaped our lives. For both Man and Nature, the essential unity is hidden in the many forms.
It is the function of science to observe the myriad things and events that comprise the universe and to
discover the relations between them, to explain their causes, as we say. Thus science has evolved new concepts
and basic laws which again simplify and unify the diversity of nature. All the numberless materials of the earth
are composed of a small number of chemical elements whose atoms are in turn simple combinations of protons and
electrons. Gravitation accounts for the motions of the planets and the fall of an apple. The principle of evolution
explains the development of all the species of plants and animals from simple primitive forms. Relativity is a
unified concept on a cosmic and superhuman scale.
All this leads to understanding. The unknown becomes known and the complex becomes simple. From this
point of view it is obvious that we all live on one world, one celestial globe that is our common heritage. Each
man may see only his own acre but the combined view of the human race, in the form of organized science, sees it
whole. The individual sciences of astronomy, geology and geophysics, geography and oceanography, climatology
and meteorology, to list only a few, have made this world comprehensible, have enabled us to foresee the course
of natural events such as the seasons and the weather.
However, compared with the mystery of nature we know but little now. We live at the bottom of a great
ocean of air and cannot truly see the sun and the stars because so much of their light is absorbed by the atmo¬
sphere and never comes down to us. Cosmic rays and millions of swift meteors are altered or destroyed high
in the sky where we have no observatories. Weather can be predicted a few days in advance, though none too
well, but the complexities of the atmosphere prevent accurate forecasting for weeks or months ahead. Currents on
the surface of the ocean, like the Gulf Stream and the Japan Current, determine much of the earth's climate; but
there are deep currents too that are equally important, though they are as yet unmapped. A whole vast continent,
probably full of precious resources, lies about the southern pole, almost unexplored. Electronic and magnetic
storms rage above and around the earth, visible as the aurora borealis and the aurora australis, but a challenging
mystery in their effects on human communications by radio and even by wire. Science cannot be content with
our present ignorance of our planet. All our past experience shows that more knowledge will solve these many
mysteries too, will bring understanding and then add still more resources for man's use.
What remains to be explored is global, not local. None of the problems that have been mentioned can be
investigated in the laboratories or from observatories of a single country. The winds on high, the rivers in the sea,
the forces of gravity and magnetism, the radiations that bombard the earth from outer space, know nothing of
national frontiers. If they are to be understood it must be by the joint action of many nations. Co-operation
among scientists across national borders is not uncommon, but what is required now is a large number of
observations of the same phenomena made at the same moment at many points on the earth. It amounts to
this: that humanity as a whole must now study the planet as a whole.
For the first time in history this is now possible. The nations of the earth are joined together in the United
Nations. Their studies of the weather and climate are centered in the World Meteorological Organization. The
advancement of science as such, and international co-operation in science especially, are one of the functions of
unesco. Whatever political differences still separate the nations, the ten years of unesco have created a cordial
unity among all the nations in the pursuance of science, education and culture. So the time is now ripe for such
a world-wide study.
Thus a new age is opened by the International Geophysical Year, to which this issue of the unesco courier
is devoted. How it will change our concepts of the universe and our understanding of the forces that play upon
and within the earth will not be known for several years. What benefit will accrue to mankind from the new
knowledge will develop in future decades. But the new age begins with the concerted action of many peoples and
by the carefully organized researches of many thousands of scientists the world over. For the first time the peoples
of the earth have joined to study their common and fundamental scientific problems together.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
DOW OPCN ON TMI WQI1«
rier*
10th YEAR Special Issue:
SEPTEMBER 1957 THE INTERNATIONAL
GEOPHYSICAL YEAR
No 9
page
CONTENTS
2 OPERATION GLOBE
3 MAN OF 'THE YEAR'-THE SCIENTIST
4 THE WHY AND HOW OF I.G.Y.
5 THE NOT SO SOLID EARTH
9 FLAG OF SCIENCE ON THE 6TH CONTINENT
I 6 ZERO HOUR FOR THE WEATHERMAN
20 WARNING ! SPECIAL WORLD ALERT
22 OUR GREAT OCEAN RESERVOIR
24 UNESCO AND THE I.G.Y.
26 WHERE THE SKY IS BLACK
28 METEORS: TINY WANDERERS THROUGH SPACE
30 MAN-MADE SATELLITE
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9 Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (I2 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. A small Japanese version is published in Tokyo
and a Danish version in Copenhagen. The United States of America edition
is distributed by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 1 52, West -42nd
Street, New York 36, N.Y., Pennsylvania 6-085 I. Second-class mail privileges
authorized at New York, N.Y. (M.C. 57.I.II6 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
credit is given to THE UNESCO COURIER and two voucher copies are sent
to the editor. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $2.50 ; 8/- stg. ; 400 French francs or equi¬
valent.
AFTER NOVEMBER I, 1957 : $3.00 ¡ 10/- stg., 500 frs.
COVER PHOTO
Most ambitious project of the
International Geophysical Year
will be the launching of an arti¬
ficial satellite carried by a giant,
three-stage rocket to a height of
300 miles and hurled into space
at 18,000 m.p.h. Here, Viking
rocket (first-stage) is fired with
third-stage rocket to test high
altitude separation methods. The
rocket reached a peak velocity
of 3,500 m.p.h. ' USIS
MAN OF THE YEAR'
-THE SCIENTIST
Even its name needs explanation. It is more than a
year: eighteen months, from July, 1957, through
December, 1958. It is more than geophysical. The
prefix geo comes from the ancient Greek word for the
earth, and identifies the earth sciences of geology,
geography, geodesy and geophysics. But the Year's pro¬
gramme also involves astronomy, meteorology, oceano¬
graphy, glaciology and other sciences that contribute
physical studies of the earth and of its environment in
space. It is also rather more than international, for the
66 nations that are participating in it include almost all
countries that are capable of such scientific effort. It is
a world venture.
The Year is certainly more than a period of time. An
immense amount of research will be done high in the sky,
deep in the sea and on all the continents by more than
5,000 scientists at an estimated cost of some $500,000,000.
The Year is in fact an organized global campaign to
observe and measure features of the earth and its vicinity
that have heretofore been beyond man's reach.
The investigations fall into three major groups.
Most remote from the thin skin of the planet where
men spend their lives are the studies of the upper
atmosphere. There are electrons and radiations from the
sun, the "'shooting stars" that burn and fall to earth each
day. There the sun's rays are filtered and electrically
charged atoms form a mirror for the reflection of radio
waves. Least understood are the cosmic rays from outer
space. Here is the outermost frontier of our planet that
must be mastered before man can sail through it and
embark on spaceflight.
The second field of investigation is that ever-changing
mixture of air and water in which we are immersed, the
lower atmosphere. Its daily variations are the weather,
determined by the sun's rays, by the evaporation of water
from the oceans, thus by the temperature of the ocean
waters and of glaciers and ice-fields. Differences in
pressure force the flow of air from high to low. Hence
the winds and the storms, impeded by mountains, lifted
on high when there is no place else to blow, and cooled
and stripped of moisture as rain or snow.
But the underlying causes of climate and weather
changes are complex. They depend on changes in the
sun's radiation, on the available water, and on unpredic¬
table high winds in the upper atmosphere. Weather is
notoriously local but its causes are global. It will remain
a favourite but fruitless subject of conversation in every
village until researches on the sun, the upper atmosphere,
the ocean currents, the ice-fields of the Arctic and
Antarctic, and simultaneous observations of air conditions
at different heights and at thousands of points on earth
and on the sea have been made during the Year. Better
understanding of the atmosphere will at last permit
reliable forecasting of the weather for weeks and perhaps
months ahead and of climatic changes for centuries into
the future.
The third major interest during the Year is the solid
earth itself. Today only one area remains unexplored:
the great Antarctic continent, nearly twice as large as
Europe. It will be explored not so much to map its
possible wealth nor for prospective human habitation but
because its colossal ice masses have a profound influence
on the world's weather.
But far more vital will be studies of the earth's interior
as a basis for earthquake and volcanic predictions, for an
understanding of the earth's magnetism and the strange
variations in the force of gravity at different points.
Such studies involve seismology and geology and the
fundamentals of geophysics as a whole.
The largest benefit, however, will accrue not from any
of these investigations in themselves but from the corre¬
lation between results from different sciences and appar¬
ently unrelated researches. There has never before been
such a concerted and concentrated attack on the frontier
of our ignorance. It will seem a different world when
the Year is over.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE WHY ÄND HOW OF I.G.Y.
Life Magazine 1957
INTERNATIONAL HEADQUARTERS for the I.G.Y. is situated at Uccle, Belgium. Here, Special I.G.Y. Committee
of eminent scientists meets frequently, sends out its suggestions and progress reports. Members of Special Committee
shown here are, from left Vladimir Beloussov of U.S.S.R.., Lloyd V. Berkner of the U.S. (Vice-president of committee);
Marcel Nicolet of Belgium (Secretary General); Jean Coulomb of France, Sidney Chapman of Great Britain (President).
Twice before this Year there were
limited programmes of interna¬
tional co-operation to study
geophysical phenomena. Both were
known as Polar Years because their
primary purpose was the understand¬
ing of Arctic weather. The first was
75 years ago, from August 1882 to
August 1883; the second fifty years
later, during the same months of 1932
and 1933.
Twelve nations maintained fourteen
observation posts in the Arctic area
during the First Polar Year and 34
farther south at which hourly records
of the meteorological and magnetic
conditions were made and the North¬
ern Lights, the aurora borealis, were
systematically observed.
The Second Polar Year included
observations in the Antarctic, and its
scope was extended to include the
study of ionization in the upper
atmosphere and its effects on radio
communication over most of the earth.
Both poles had then been reached by
explorers and the scientific equipment
available was far superior to that of
fifty years earlier.
In the years since then both the
need for geophysical knowledge and
the means for acquiring it have grown
mightily. Planes, radar, radio-tele¬
scopes, sound-wave reflection and
remote-control electronic systems, to
say nothing of high-altitude rockets,
are among the new tools for research
that have been perfected during the
course of the past two decades.
This led Dr. Lloyd V. Berkner, presi¬
dent of the Associated (American)
Universities, Inc. and a former presi¬
dent of the American Geophysical
Union, to propose in April, 1950, that
the interval between Years be cut
from 50 years to 25 and that the Third
Polar Year be planned for 1957-58.
In October 1951, the proposal was
referred to the International Council
of Scientific Unions, the logical organ¬
ization to launch the entire project
since it is the central body that
comprises nearly all the individual
international scientific unions, thus
represents all the sciences as well as
the interested nations.
In 1952 the International Council
broadened the scope of the project by
giving it its present name and estab¬
lished the Special Committee for
the International Geophysical Year.
When the Committee was assured of
financial support for its initial ope¬
rations by unesco it proceeded to
organize the ambitious project and
established a permanent Bureau to
act as executive headquarters. It
is located in Belgium at Uccle, a
suburb of Brussels, and is headed by
Prof. Sydney Chapman of Queen's
College, Oxford, as President, Dr. Lloyd
V. Berkner of the United States as
Vice-President, and Prof. Marcel Nico¬
let of Belgium as General Secretary.
They were later joined by Prof. V. V.
Beloussov of the U.S.S.R. and Prof. J.
Coulomb of France. Vice-Admiral Sir
Archibald Day has been appointed as
Co-ordinator of I.G.Y. Operations.
However, most of the costs of the
actual researches are borne by the
co-operating governments and in part
by the various national and inter¬
national scientific societies and by
individual universities and research
institutions. The amounts of the
national expenditures are not gener¬
ally available but an instance is the
planned expenditure of $80,000 to
$90,000 by Iran on geophysical data in
the Near East. The U.S. Congress has
appropriated $39,000,000 to the Nation¬
al Academy of Sciences for the expen¬
ses of the U.S. programme. This is
apart from the additional expenses
involved in the exploration of the
Antarctic Continent and in the
launching of an artificial earth-satel¬
lite for high-altitude observations.
The magnitude of the programme in
each country depends on its own
financial support, and is supervised by
a national committee. The chairmen
of these committees are organized as
an Advisory Council for the planning
of the world programme. An official
Reporter has also been appointed, one
for each of the thirteen major fields
of study, to co-ordinate the work
within each specialty but on a world
basis. Finally, an Advisory Committee
on Publications will supervise the pre¬
paration of the "Annals of the Geo¬
physical Year" which will be publish¬
ed by the Pergamon Press after the
close of the Year.. Sir Harold Spencer-
Jones, Britain's former Astronomer
Royal, is to be Editor-in-Chief.
Articles in this issue on the International Geophysical Year were written by Dr. Gerald Wendt, science consultant
to the Editor of The Unesco Courier and Special Editor of the present issue. Formerly a professor of chemistry
at the University of Chicago and Dean at the Pennsylvania State College, Dr. Wendt has devoted recent years to
the interpretation of science and its social consequences In public lectures, on the radio and by television. He
has been Director of Education at the World's Fair in New York, Science Editor of the American weekly, Time,
and Editorial Director of the monthly, Science Illustrated. For three years (January I 952 to December 1954) he
was Head of the Division of Teaching and Dissemination in Unesco's Department of Natural Sciences. His articles
on science in The Unesco Courier and Unesco Features have been translated into many languages and reprinted
all over the world, in particular those he wrote for the special Issue of The Unesco Courier, "The Promise of
Atomic Power", dated December 1954. He is now president of the Unesco Publications Center in New York.
GERALD WEIMDT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
MEASURING
THE EARTH
FROM THE MOON
AND STARS
During the International Geo¬
physical Year teams of spe¬
cialists will be exploring the earth
on every level, from the upper
atmosphere to the groundand
below its surface. Art of photo¬
graphing the earth from rockets
has now been developed to a
high degree. Photo (I) was taken
from a height of 101 miles. It
reveals about 300,000 square
miles of New Mexico, Arizona,
California and the Mexican pro¬
vince of Sonora. To clear up
doubts about the exact size and
shape of the earth, scientists will
be using a remarkable instrument,
the Markowitz Moon Camera (2)
which takes photographs of the
moon against a background of
.fixed stars (3). These cameras
will be operating from twenty
stations during I.G.Y. Results will
enable points on earth's surface
to be fixed with a higher preci¬
sion than ever before. From
Moon Camera photographs, dis¬
tances between continents, now
known to within 100 to 130
metres, can be calculated with an
average error of only 30 to
35 metres. Still more accurate
measurements are expected from
observations of the artificial sa¬
tellites. (See page 32)
USIS photos
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THE NOT SO SOLID EARTH
In the scientific attack on so complex a problem as the
complete understanding of the earth, the first step
must be to separate it into smaller problems and to
approach them one by one. The Year does this first of
all by eliminating all human and biological questions,
important as they are. This is a Geophysical Year and
only the physical sciences are involved. But even from
that restricted point of view, the earth has three major
aspects.
First, it is a celestial object, a planet rushing through
space at a velocity of 18.50 miles per second in its annual
orbit around the sun that is some 93 million miles away.
It constantly encounters radiations, particles and meteors
which add thousands of tons to its mass every year and
have a profound effect upon the upper atmosphere as
they impinge upon it.
Second, it is an almost spherical mass of 6,600 million -
million million tons (in figures: 6.6 followed by 20 zeros),
that as a whole is 5.5 times as dense as water. The globe
has a diameter of 7,920 miles. It is composed of three
major layers: a central core, 4,300 miles in diameter, that
may be metallic and probably is fluid, surrounded by a
magma, 1,800 miles thick of compressed rigid rock, and
around this the thin crust, only about 20 miles thick, that
is made up largely of rocks that have descended from the
surface after chemical action by the sea and by air.
And the third aspect of the earth is known in common
speech as the surface, between the globe and the sky, the
abode of life and the scene of history. It extends over
197 million square miles. Strictly speaking, it is not a
simple surface but a complex of three separate interfaces,
one where earth meets water on the sea bottom, another
between the sea and the air, and a third where the dry
land is itself exposed to the atmosphere. This is the
smallest of the three and covers only about one fourth of
the entire area. Here most of the geophysical studies of
the Year are concentrated in terms of geography and
geodesy, Antarctic exploration, weather studies and the
exploration of the great heights. They are closest to
man's common life and natural interest.
Sixty million lbs. per sq.in.
But logically it is the solid earth that is the base of
geophysical science. It is also the least explored.
The deepest mine goes down about 10,000 feet, less
than a tenth the thickness of the crust. Oil wells, how¬
ever, have penetrated to more than twice that depth, to
22,000 feet, nearly one-fifth of the way to the underlying
magma. The materials thus penetrated are the familiar
surface rocks. Such borings, however, do give direct evi¬
dence of heat in the interior. In deep mines the tempe¬
rature rises about 54°F per mile of depth. If this rate
continued, the temperature at the centre o-f the earth
would be above 200,000"F. But it is practically certain
that the rate of increase is much less farther down so that
the temperature of the centre is estimated to be between
3,600 and 11,500°F. Exact knowledge is lacking.
Under surface conditions such temperatures would be
adequate to melt or liquefy most materials. But the
distinction between solid and liquid becomes less definite
under the high pressures of the earth's interior that result
from the enormous weight above. Here again no direct
measurements exist but indirect calculations that gave
astonishing results have. been made by Prof. K.E. Bullen
of the University of Sydney in Australia. The pressure at
the bottom of the Pacific Ocean is known to be about
800 atmospheres, one atmosphere being the normal weight
of the air pressing on the earth's surface at sea-level
(15 pounds per square inch). Only 200 miles down in the
earth's mantle below the crust the pressure is already
100,000 atmospheres, equal to the highest pressure ever
produced in a laboratory. But at the base of the mantle
1,800 miles down, the pressure is more than a million
atmospheres and at the centre of the earth nearly four
million. It is difficult to imagine the condition of any
form of matter at a temperature of perhaps 10,000 °F and
under a pressure of 60 million pounds per square inch.
Antarctic 'ice-quakes'
Certainly the density is much higher than at the
surface. Professor Bullen has estimated that the
rocks just below the crust have a density oí 3.3
grammes per cubic centimetre, compared with water at
one gramme per cubic centimetre (or 62.3 pounds per cubic
foot). But the density increases to 5.5 at the bottom of
mantle, then jumps suddenly to 9.5 at the top of the core
and increases gradually to 11.5 within the core. This is
close to the density of metallic lead at the surface (about
700 lbs. per cubic ft.).
Most of our knowledge of the earth's interior has come
from the careful study of earthquakes and the many lesser
vibrations that reach the surface from disturbances
within. Nearly all are based on the continuous records of
earth vibrations made at many points on earth by an
instrument called a seismograph, from the ancient Greek
word, seísmos, for an earthquake.
It is by the analysis of seismograph records from differ¬
ent stations that the location of the 'quake itself is deter¬
mined. The rate of travel of the shock wave through the
earth's interior also gives important information on the
composition of the magma and the core. For instance
pressure waves, in which the motion at each point is in the
same direction as that of the wave, pass through the
central core, though they are deflected somewhat. But
secondary waves, in which the motion of the individual
particles is cross-wise, or perpendicular, to the direction of
the wave, do not pass through the core. The resulting
"shadow" of these waves on the opposite crust is both
major evidence for the existence of the core and an indica¬
tion that it is fluid rather than solid and may be compos¬
ed of molten iron and nickel.
In the seismological programme of the Year earth
tremors will be measured by expeditions and special sta¬
tions at points where observations are usually unobtain¬
able, for instance in the Antarctic and on remote equa¬
torial islands in the Pacific. This is to get more accurate
information on seismic events in those areas and thus on
the earth's interior. This, in turn, will reveal more about
TELLTALE TREMORS. Most of our knowledge of the earth's
interior has come from studies of waves set up by earthquakes and
from other vibrations recorded by seismologists. To obtain still more
accurate information, earth tremors that occur during the I.G.Y. will
be measured in places where observations are usually unobtainable in
the Antarctic and in remote Pacific islands. Typical seismogram (above)
is of earthquake on Kamchatka Peninsula in Siberia, whose phases
reveal three main types of seismic waves: Primary (P), secondary (S)
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Seotember 1957
ourtesy "Scientific American" © I 955
X-RAYING THE
WORLD WITHIN
Waves set up by earthquakes travel
through the whole interior of the
earth and as they travel from their
source their paths are bent and
shaped by the shells of the earth's
internal structure. By Interpret¬
ing the story they tell when re¬
ceived on the surface, the seismo¬
logist, in effect, "X-rays" the earth.
In upper diagram solid lines rep¬
resent primary shock waves and
dotted lines are secondary waves
formed by reflection. The only
primary waves that can get into
"shadow" zone on opposite crust,
shown in upper right, are those
which enter earth's Inner core
and are sharply bent. Cross
section of earth (lower diagram) is
divided into distinct layers through
which seismic waves travel at dif¬
ferent speeds. Outer core is indi¬
cated by lighter tone of shading;
inner core by darker tone. Layer
marked by A is earth's thin crust.
the nature of magma and the core and of a number of
intermediate layers that are now ill-defined.
In another phase of the programme the faint vibrations,
called microseisms, will be studied so that seismographs
can later bë used to detect and locate small disturbances
that are not full earthquakes. Finally, in the Antarctic,
seismic measurements on man-made explosions in effect
ice-quakes will be used to measure the thickness of the
otherwise impenetrable ice layers.
The Reporter for the seismology programme is Prof. V.V.
Beloussov of the Soviet Union.
At first thought gravity would seem to be one of the
most constant forces of nature. To be sure, its actual
cause is unknown and so is the means by which it acts at
a distance except in the esoteric terms of Einstein's
relativity theory. But it is very simply a pull exerted
mutually by any two masses of matter upon each other
which is proportional to the product of the two masses and
inversely proportional to the square of the distance
between them. This is simple, accurate and perfectly
constant for the pull of the earth as a whole, as it is for
any astronomical body.
But on the surface of the earth there are complications
and the force of gravity is not uniform. For one thing,
the earth is not a true sphere. Because it spins on its axis
it is deformed into an "oblate spheroid", hence flattened
like many an orange. For this reason a man standing at
sea level at one of the poles would be 13 miles nearer the
earth's centre than if he stood at the equator. Without
changing his mass he would be heavier because at less
distance from the centre the force of gravity is somewhat
stronger.
There is also a direct complication from the rotation of
the earth. Near the equator the rotational velocity is
about 1,000 miles per hour. The resulting centrifugal force
counteracts the pull of gravityin effect reduces it.
Furthermore the oblate spheroid is by no means mathe¬
matically smooth. If the earth is shaped like a flattened
orange, it is like a battered one, with bulges
and depressions quite apart from the
mountain heights and ocean deeps. The
major undulations in the earth's shape
again modify the force of gravity at the
surface and this time with a sideways pull
Cont'd
on
next page
Courtesy "Scientific American"
and surface waves which appear in upper 20 miles or so near earth's
surface. The rate of travel of the shock wave through the earth's
interior gives vital information on composition of its mantle and core.
Secondary waves do not pass through core. Separate lines are actually
part of a continuous spiral trace going from right to left on a circular drum.
First disturbance recorded is P wave shown by number I. Then follow the
multiply reflected P waves at 2 and 3. S waves begin at point 4 follow¬
ed by multiply reflected waves at 5,6 and 7. Surface waves start at 8.
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
NOT SO SOLID
EARTH (Continued) DO CONTINENTS DRIFT LIKE ICEBERGS?
so that a plumb line does not point always to the true
centre but at an angle. This means that a supposedly
vertical line does not point to the zenith among the stars
but off to one side. Obviously this interferes with the
accurate long-distance surveying that is called geodesy.
The result of this, in turn, is that world maps are incorrect
because the distances between continents and islands aré
not accurately known.
There are also changes in the force of gravity at some
points which may indicate a slow vertical movement. It
is suspected that the Hawaian Islands have thus been
lifted several inches. This indicates an "earth-tide" simi¬
lar to the tides of the ocean but affecting the great rock
mantle. They are not yet understood but a schedule of
continued measurements of gravity may reveal broad up-
and-down movements as if the earth itself were plastic.
Pull of gravity less over oil deposits
Finally, there is a practical use for gravity measure¬
ments. When large bodies of minerals are present
under the surface they can reveal their presence by
their effects on gravity when they differ in density from
the average rock. Petroleum, for instance, is light and
reduces the local pull of gravity. Metallic minerals are
often much denser than the usual rock and so increase
gravitation. Both oil and mining companies now regu¬
larly prospect underground by measuring the gravity at
the surface. Many of their data are being turned over to
the Year.
The purpose is to make accurate measurements of the
force of gravity at as many points on earth as possible.
This can be done by measuring the time of swing of a
pendulum, but the usual gravimeter is merely a supersen¬
sitive spring-scale in which the earth's pull on a small
weight is indicated by the stretching of a fine wire of silver
or of nickel-steel. There are already hundreds of base
stations scattered over the earth that have made many
hundreds of thousands of gravitational measurements,
including 4,000 points at sea. But it is part of the pro¬
gramme of the Year to extend these stations and to take
advantage of special expeditions, such as those to the
South Pole. With gravity measurements dotted all over
the earth, the earth's actual shape can at last be comput¬
ed. Then it will be possible to obtain exact figures for the
earth's various diameters and for its circumference.
Thirty nations are co-operating in the gravity pro¬
gramme. The Co-ordinating Reporter is Father Lejay,
Director of the International Gravimetrical Office in Paris.
Closely related to the purposes of the gravity studies are
the completely different methods for measuring the exact
position of points on the surface of the earth in terms of
latitude (the north-and-south dimension) and of longitude
(the east-and-west dimension). These are actually mea¬
surements of angles. In the case of latitude it is the angle
between the vertical line from the centre of the earth to
any given point on the surface and the true north-and-
south line which is the axis of rotation of the earth. In
the case of longitude it is the angle between the vertical
line and one drawn through the zero meridian, which
passes through Greenwich Observatory in England.
It takes but a little geometry to see that these angles can
best be measured on the sky. For instance, the vertical
line from the centre to any surface point can be extended
upward and then indicates the zenith, the overhead point,
on the sky. The angle between the zenith and the North
Star then gives the latitude. Thus practical navigation on
the sea and in the air is always done by reference to the
sun by day or to the stars by night. Since the sky has
been so accurately photographed and mapped, almost any
star will do for reference and special stars have been
selected for use in the navigational charts.
But high accuracy is now needed. There is some reason
to think, for instance, that some islands and even the
major continents are like icebergs, in a sense floating on
the magma below, and that they have changed their
positions radically in the course of geologic time. If they
are sliding about then accurate determination of their
latitude and longitude would reveal some slight motion
within a few years.
A new and very precise photographic technique has now
been developed which will locate the position of the moon
against a background of stars at accurately measured
times. Such photographs, taken at more than twenty
different observatories during the Year, will improve all
figures on latitude and longitude and will also give the
basis for noting possible changes of location as time
goes on.
The Reporter for the geodetic measurements of latitude
and longitude is Prof. Danj on, Head of the Paris Obser¬
vatory.
It was easy to think, in former days, that the earth as a
whole is a permanent magnet, much like an iron bar
magnet, with its magnetic poles at the poles of the earth.
This would require that the magnetized atoms inside the
earth be permanently arranged side by side with the poles
pointing north and south. But at the temperature now
known to prevail below the surface, any such permanent
arrangement is impossible. Besides, the magnetic pole is
not at the geographic North Pole but several hundred
miles distant on the Arctic coast of Canada. In addition,
the magnetic pole has wandered over the earth far from
the North Pole, even into the South Pacific, in previous
geological eras. And finally, there are very few places on
earth where the compass points true north, or even points
to the magnetic pole.
Almost all compass readings need correction to give true
north. The amount of deviation has been measured over
almost the entire earth's surface and, for the benefit of
mariners, with especial care over all the oceans. The
study of the world magnetic map indicates that there are
two independent components of the magnetic field, with
separate causes. The major one is somehow connected
directly with the earth's rotation and, if acting alone,
would point all compasses to the North Pole.
But there are also secondary sources of magnetism
produced by some quite different mechanism, which vary
irregularly over the earth and change with time, even in
the course of a few years, or sometimes months. This
secondary or "residual" magnetic field seems to produce
magnetic eddies that are in general wandering westward
and, at the present rate, will circle the earth in 1,600
years. Their net effect is to produce the magnetic
deviations from true north in the main field and to
necessitate ever-new mapping of the earth's whole
magnetic field. New accurate figures are an important
objective of the Year. The actual cause of both the major
and the residual magnetic fields is unknown.
Electric currents from outer space
Superimposed on the slow variation of the total magne¬
tic field over the course of years is a much smaller
variation so small that it would not be noticed on a
compass. It involves only about two percent of the total.
But it is properly called a fluctuation because it varies so
swiftly that instruments capable of measurements in
hundredths of a second are required to study it. These
fluctuations probably do not originate in the earth but on
the sun. They increase in number and intensity with the
number of visible sunspots. Such spots indicate gigantic
electrical and magnetic storms on the sun's surface which
eject radiations of some sort. When they strike the
earth's upper atmosphere, it is supposed that they cause
ionization, i.e. electrification, and winds which result in
broad electric currents at great heights and these, in turn,
affect the magnetic field at the earth's surface.
At present there are about 80 completely equipped
magnetic observatories in the world, most of them in
Europe and Japan in the temperate zone where fluctua¬
tions are least. During the Year a large number of addi¬
tional magnetic stations will be established across North
America and Alaska, on the Paciiic Islands, on the Antarc¬
tic Continent and in the Arctic areas of Canada and the
Soviet Union. The hope is that the causes of the rapid
fluctuations will be discovered and that information will
be gathered to solve the underlying mystery of the earth's
magnetism. Dr. V. Laursen of the Meteorologisk Institut,
Charlottenlund, Denmark, is Reporter for the geomag¬
netism programme.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
THE FLAG OF SCIENCE
ON THE 6TH CONTINENT
c
1 G. Y. STATIONS
United
States B Chile
es
Great
Britain
Soviet
Union
1*1 Japan
New
Zealandm
ii France i
mm
Norway
FT*
Argentina II Belgium
a« Australia ptfluiiui
MMflllU
Spain
Based on map published in "Natural History" V) I 957
THE 'ICE BOX* OF THE WORLD, as Antarctica has been called,
greatly influences climate of all countries. During I.G.Y. twelve
nations will investigate this mountainous land mass of 6,000,000
square miles (much larger than all of Canada) most of which is a vast
plateau averaging 6,000 feet in height, capped by the world's greatest
ice-sheet. Something like 90% of the total ice-cover of the world
lies on the southern continent. Studies of the possible shrinkage in
the Antarctic ice are of vital interest to mankind for if all this enormous
¡ce-sheet melted it would raise the average sea-level all over the
world by nearly 200 feet. For the first time more than 6,000 men
will be ranging over a continent still no more familiar to us than the
visible side of the moon. Map shows locations of principal I.G.Y.
stations with flags of nations manning them. Objectives of all
nations are the same: to determine how Antarctic influences world
conditions in respect of weather, water balance, glaciers, ocean
currents, etc, and to make joint geophysical measurements with
respect to world's magnetism, cosmic rays, the aurora and
other phenomena of the upper air and of the earth's interior.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
SIXTH CONTINENT w
PICTURE FROM THE PAST (below) shows Sir Ernest Shackleton's
expedition ship ( I 908- 1 909) trapped in South polar pack ice. Threat¬
ened by gigantic iceberg pushed by deep ocean currents, ship was saved
by timely blizzard which deflected iceberg's course. Human endurance
and heroism finally triumphed over the white wastes in 1911 when
Amundsen and, 35 days later, Scott, reached South Pole. Right, South
Pole photographed today from plane which carried equipment and
supplies for the scientific observation station that has been set up there.
1957, Pictorial Press Ltd, London US1S
A unique feature of this age, beginning with this Year,
is that one whole continent is inhabited only by
scientists. They came from twelve nations with no
purpose of conquest or possession. They share their data
and discoveries, their equipment and supplies, and
perchance their hardships, with the men from other lands.
Characteristically, for instance, an American, Dr. Gordon
D. Cartwright, is working at the Soviet observatory at
Mirny while on the other side of the continent, a Russian,
V. Rastorgouiev, has a place at Little America. Even the
former tension between Great Britain and the governments
of Argentina and Chile, all three claiming the area between
South America and the South Pole, has now been resolved.
Instead, the three nations are maintaining some two dozen
scientific bases side by side.
Antarctica is as international now as science itself. It
is a true landmark in history as well as in geography.
Indeed its name has become an anomaly. It implies the
opposite to Árctica, which does not exist, for the North
Pole is 10,000 feet deep under the Arctic Ocean. This
magnificent new continent deserves a name of its own.
For the present it is in truth, if not in name, Science Land.
It is new only to man. The great rock shield that
underlies East Antarctica is very ancient. The high
mountains of West Antarctica have been uplifted and
folded through geologic ages. There is coal in some of
their strata to prove that this was tropical swampland at
one time. The continent is a vast area of nearly six million
square miles, approximately circular and 3,000 miles in
diameter nearly twice as large as all Europe, almost as
large as South America. It has majestic mountain ranges
more than 15,000 feet high. The South Pole itself is on a
plateau some 10,000 feet above sea level, the extent of
which is not known because only a small part of it has
ever been seen, even from planes. There is a rugged
mountainous peninsula, nearly 1,000 miles long, reaching
northward toward the Andes of South America and
perhaps an extension of them.
Antarctica has all the variety of any continent but over
it all is the endless monotony of the age-old ice sheet, in
places 10,000 feet thick. The ice covers almost every inch
and extends out to sea. In the great bay that is called the
Ross Sea, the ice shelf is 600 to 1,000 feet thick and extends
400 miles from the shore over an area 500 miles wide. It
10
moves steadily seaward at the rate of about four feet per
day. Beyond this Shelf Ice, pack ice covers the sea for
hundreds of miles in all directions although from the
Pole all directions are north.
Except for the end of the long peninsula that is known
in the British Commonwealth as Graham Land and in the
United States as the Palmer Peninsula, the entire continent
lies within the Antarctic Circle so that for six months of
the year none of it sees the sun and for the other six
months the sun circles around, low in the sky, without
setting. During the dark winter (June and July) the cold
is intense. A record of 83 °F below zero has been measured
on the Shelf Ice but temperature on the high polar plateau
has reached as low as 100°F below zero. Under the steady
summer sun (December and January) there are days when
the snow near the coast becomes wet irom melting.
The short, inadequate summers forbid the growth of
flowering plants. Only two are known and they are rare,
a species of grass and a pink. But the exposed rock areas
are sometimes covered with the browns and greens of
lichen and moss. The lichen is on the extreme limit of
life for it persists in spite of low temperature, can be
thoroughly dried by the cold and yet not die, and it is
almost independent of nutrients from the ground. The
only animal life that such vegetation supports is also of a
low order and includes insects like the wingless mosquito,
midges and mites.
But if the icy surface is a desert, marine life is plentiful.
The cold sea is rich in plankton. Indeed, the Antarctic
has been called the most productive sea in the world,
perhaps because of the continuous upswelling of waters
from the deep, bringing up plant nutrients. Feeding on
the plankton are huge numbers of "red krill", a type of
shrimp that, in turn, is the food for many fishes, for seals,
and for the large population of whales. Both the stately
Emperor Penguin and the smaller, agile Adelie Penguins
dive into the sea for their food but have their breeding
grounds on the ice. They are distinctive of the Antarctic
and fossil discoveries indicate that they may have evolved
from land birds that lived there during the long ages, long
ago, when the climate was mild.
Much remains to be discovered with res- Cont'd
pect to Antarctic life, both plant and ani- on
mal, but it will be incidental to the page 1 3
Year's expeditions. The basic, biological
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
Australian Official Photograph
SECRETS OF ANTARCTICA are now being discovered more ra¬
pidly as Nature's resistance is overcome with aid of modern machines
such as huge ice-breakers, airplanes, helicopters and electric snow
ploughs. Above, Antarctic expedition ship dwarfed by majestic, snow
covered mass of Mount Ohlson. Below, right, helicopters for carrying
personnel and supplies to advanced bases and tracked vehicles for
transporting building materials and instruments have made possible
a new era in polar travel though dog teams (below, left) are still of use.
1957 Roger Kirschner French Polar Expeditions Soviet Antarctic Expedition
British Official Photograph
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
y
1
LIFE AND WORK
IN AN ICE AGE
Australian Official photos
Antarctica is the coldest and windiest region of the whole globefar colder than the Arctic. The
air above it lies over a massive continent, glacier-bound, literally in an ice age; and temperatures of
100 degrees F below freezing can result. Surface winds, funnelled down the glacial valleys from the
interior can beat north at speeds of 1 00 miles an hour . These are the rigorous conditions in which
men who staff Antarctic weather and other observation stations live and work. Above, howling
winds sweep one of research stations maintained on Heard and Macquarie Islands. Below, left,
biologist disects a large, red deepsea crab, and right, meteorologist takes instrument readings.
I 957 Camera Press, London
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
SIXTH CONTINENT
(Continued)
ODYSSEYS OF THE WHITE WASTES
problem concerns the adjustment of the animals to the
extreme cold, the adjustment of their metabolism and
the properties of the fats that insulate their tissues. The
breeding grounds of the Emperor Penguin and of the seals
too are unknown. Both the birds and the seals should
be tagged to determine their migrations. Aerial photo¬
graphs are needed to count their numbers. Their diving
habits and underwater life also offer many mysteries. But
the geophysicists will have their eyes on the great drama
of the skies, the forces of nature and the geologic deeps.
The first man to suspect the existence of the great cold
continent was the famous British explorer of the Pacific,
Captain James Cook, but his attempts to penetrate the
barrier of pack ice failed in both 1773 and 1774. He was
within 1,200 miles of the South Pole when he turned
back after sailing completely around the continent. It
was in 1820 that the land was first clearly seen, either
by the American Captain Nathaniel Palmer or by the
British Captain Edward Bransfleld, both of whom,
having sailed south from the South Shetland Islands (500
miles from the tip of South
America), saw the mountains of
the long north-reaching penin¬
sula. Neither landed. In the
same year the Russian Admiral,
Fabian von Bellinghausen, sailed
half-way around the 'continent,
discovered the large Alexander I
Island, and saw vast ice masses WE}
which probably were on the
mainland.
It was not until 75 years later,
in 1895, that anyone landed on
Antarctica and two years later
a Belgian vessel, the Bélgica,
first spent the winter in its ice.
One member of that expedition,
and the first scientist to report
on Antarctic phenomena, was
the American meteorologist
Henryk Arctowski who, at 86, is
still living in Florida (U.S.A.).
But the first extensive
exploration and scientific study was made in 1901 to 1904
by the British National Antarctic Expedition under Captain
Robert Falcon Scott which explored the high plateau west
of the Ross Sea and reached to within 463 miles of the
South Pole. In the same years both a German and a
Swedish expedition made scientific studies near the shore.
In the next year, 1905, the American explorer, Robert E.
Peary, came within 200 miles of the North Pole and on
April 6, 1909, he reached it. But three months earlier, on
January 9, a British expedition led by Sir Ernest
Shackleton, came within only 97 miles of the South Pole,
high on the 10,000 foot plateau, before being forced back
by blizzards and lack of food. His failure and Peary's
success at the opposite pole led to a second British
expedition under Robert Scott which finally reached the
South Pole on January 18, 1912. Scott and his four
companions perished in a blizzard on the way back but
their scientific records and collections were found when
Spring came. They were not the first men at the pole.
That distinction belongs to a Norwegian party, led by
Roald Amundsen, who used dog teams and skis with
Norwegian expertness and made a relatively rapid dash
to reach the Pole on December 14, 1911just 35 days before
Scott's party arrived there.
Both of Scott's expeditions were sponsored by the British
Royal Society and the Royal Geographic Society and
produced volumes of scientific observations which were
more important, in the long run, than reaching the pole.
Simultaneous weather observations were made at widely
separated points, which permitted the first weather charts
of the region. Magnetic and electrical measurements and
the sounding of the upper air also set the pattern for the
intensive work that is now to be done by a broad and
continuing international effort during the Year.
In 1926 the American aviator Richard E. (later Admiral)
Byrd and Floyd Bennett flew from Spitzbergen to the
North Pole and return, a distance of 1,360 miles. In April
of 1928 the Australian, Sir Hubert Wilklns, flew 2,100 miles
from Point Barrow, Alaska, to Green Harbor, Spitzbergen.
They proved that there is no continent in the Arctic but
they also opened a new era in polar studies. On Novem¬
ber 29, 1929, Admiral Byrd and Bernt Balchen flew from
their base at Little America to the South Pole and back.
The airplane had become indispensable for photographic
reconnaissance, for transportation of supplies and person¬
nel to advanced bases and for rescue missions. An Ame¬
rican plane landed and returned from the South Pole itself
on November 1, 1956, and more than 700 tons of supplies
have been landed at the Pole by airliit for the construction
of the South Pole Station. The lowflying and slower heli¬
copter is almost equally valuable when operating from
shipboard to explore paths through the ice and in landing
supplies.
So also the diesel-powered tractor has replaced the dog-
team, the ponies and man-power for surface transporta¬
tion and has made possible the use of immense quantities
of building materials, scientific instruments and supplies
for comfortable and healthy
living. In addition, the power
of the ships that must penetrate
the ice barriers has grown from
the 200 horsepower of Admiral
Byrd's first ship only 25 years
ago to the modern ice-breaker
with ten diesel engines capable
of producing 21,000 horsepower.
Even more striking is the change
effected by radio-communica¬
tion which permits contact bet¬
ween advance parties and their
base, between bases thousands
of miles apart, and even with
the outside world and home by
means of radio-telephone con¬
nections. Finally, the science
of nutrition has made such
advances that scurvy and other
deficiency-diseases, once the
scourge of explorers, are now
unknown. "'The Continent is
rapidly approaching the period when long-term habitation
will become possible", writes Paul E. Siple, the chief
scientist at the South Pole Station of the U.S.A.
Ten nations have established bases on Antarctica:
Argentina, Australia, Chile, France, Japan, New Zealand,
Norway, the U.S.S.R., the United Kingdom and the United
States. They are being joined by Belgium, and perhaps
Spain. The greatest concentration of research stations,
primarily devoted to meteorological studies, is on the long
Palmer Peninsula (or Graham Land) which is almost
directly south of the tip of South America and of the
Falkland Islands. Here the United Kingdom has ten
bases, Argentina eight and Chile six, all closely co¬
operating. Just to the east of it is the Weddell Sea that
cuts into the continental shoreline to a depth of some
600 miles and over an east-west spread of nearly one
thousand miles.
On its shores are an Argentine base, one of the U.S.A.,
and the base of the British Royal Society. Almost
opposite the Weddell Sea, and thus south of New
Zealand, is the Ross Sea which, under its ice cover
reaches to within 750 miles of the South Pole. From
it, Scott, Shackleton, Amundsen and Byrd all made
their famous explorations. On its eastern shore is
the main U.S. base, Little America, and to the west, on
McMurdo Sound, is the U.S. Air Supply Base and the New
Zealand scientific station. At Cape Adare, where the Ross
Sea joins the Ocean, is a station that is operated jointly by
New Zealand and the United States. Along the coast at
intervals westward from Cape Adare are the bases esta¬
blished by France at Pointe Geologie; the U.S.A. on the
Knox Coast; the U.S.S.R. at Mirny;
Australia on Enderby Land south of the
Indian Ocean; Japan and Belgium on the
shore of Queen Maud Land south of Africa;
and finally the Norwegian station near the
eastern limit ai the Weddell Sea. The
U5IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
SIXTH CONTINENT
(Continued)
ICE 5,000 FT. THICK, TEMPERATORES 60 BELOW
Soviet Union, France and the U.S.A. have established
stations inland.
The objectives of all the nations are the same: to
determine the influence of the Antarctic on world condi¬
tions with respect to weather, water balance, glaciers,
ocean currents, etc., and to make joint geophysical
measurements from this vantage point at the bottom of the
world with respect to the earth's magnetism, cosmic rays,
the aurora and other phenomena of the upper air and of
the earth's interior.
Ambitious Soviet
polar programme
These objectives are listed in a special report on the
Soviet participation written for the unesco courier
by Evgueni Tolstikov, Deputy Director of the North¬
ern Maritime Route and a Hero of the Soviet Union.
In undertaking the Antarctic studies, Soviet scientists
established a number of projects. Among them are:
1. The study of the influence of atmospheric phenomena
in the Antarctic region on the general circulation in the
world atmosphere.
2. The study of the basic circulation of the Antarctic
waters and its relation to all other ocean currents.
3. Elaboration of the physical geography of the Antarc¬
tic and detailed study of its glaciers.
4. Study of the characteristics of geophysical pheno¬
mena in the Antarctic.
In accord with these projects and in agreement with the
International Committee for the Geophysical Year, the
Soviet expedition is planning a series of researches at the
Observatory at Mirny and at two stations in the interior,
together with two intermediate bases, Pioneerskaia and
Komsomolskaia, and the "'Oasis" station. Researches for
contour mapping will be undertaken by planes and by
tractor trains.
A large group of Soviet scientists and specialists will
take part in the Antarctic researches in meteorology,
atmospherics, actinometry, geology, geography, glaciology,
magnetism, seismology, ionospherics, the aurora, cosmic
rays, earth movements and gravimetry.
Venture to the 'Pole
of Inaccessibility'
Special structures have been built at the Observatory at
Mirny to house modern equipment which will operate
on full schedule for the Geophysical Year. At the
same time major studies will be made in Antarctic waters
by the diesel-electric ship "Ob" and in part by the "Lena,"
which are specially equipped for a great variety of resear¬
ches in meteorology, actinometry, oceanography, hydro-
biology, maritime geology and geophysics.
While these researches have hardly begun, much inter¬
esting information has already been obtained. For
instance, measures of the ice at Mirny have shown a
thickness af 250 to 650 feet. But under the ice there is no
land; beneath is only water down to the sea bottom,
500 feet below sea level. Mirny station is situated partly
on some small islands and partly on the ice. It is interest¬
ing to note that 60 miles south of Mirny where the surface
of the ice sheet gradually rises from the sea to a height of
4,000 feet, the ice has a thickness of 5,000 feet. There too,
under the heavy layer of ice, is the bottom of the sea.
Meteorological observations have shown that the area of
Antarctica, where Mirny is located is characterized by
violent winds. In the course of the year there are 262 days
with very high winds and 23 days when the wind was of
hurricane strength. These storms are especially frequent
14
in winter. Observations at Pioneerskaia, gave us our first
real information on the rigours of the climate in the inte¬
rior regions. The average temperature of the air in the
coldest month is -62°F while that of the least cold month,
December, is -8°F. Since there is never a real calm at
Pioneerskaia and since the average wind velocity is 20 to
25 miles per hour, it is easy to imagine the difficulties
under which the scientists must work in the Antarctic. It
must be said, however, that the difficulties and hardships
of the men will only be compensated when the scientists of
the entire world who are participating in such researches
can combine all their efforts. Those of each country
taken separately, without the data from the observations
of other countries, would not be in a position to solve the
problems that are presented by the International Geophy¬
sical Year.
The Soviet scientists now maintain continuous radio
contact with the Antarctic expeditions of the other
countries, mutually exchange the results of their scientific
observations, and consult each other on the interesting
questions that arise. Such bonds are established with the
expeditions of France, Australia, the United Kingdom and
the United States. (The stations in the interior, mention¬
ed by Mr. Tolstikov, are to be established at two important
points. One is at the South Magnetic Pole which, as in
the north, is many hundred miles from the geographic
pole. The other is at what is now called the "Pole of
Inaccessibility", the centre of the great mass of East
Antarctica, the remotest point, about 1,000 miles from the
nearest coast).
Robot weather station
reports twice daily
The British programme has many aspects. Largest is
the Falkland Islands Dependencies Survey which has
been making surveys and polar researches on the
islands south of the Falklands and on Graham Land (the
Palmer Peninsula) for some years and now operates ten
permanent stations in that area. These stations, equipped
for the scientific studies included in the Year and especially
for weather observations, will lay a firm foundation for
the more temporary and often more spectacular ventures
around the rim and in the interior of the continent.
Argentina and Chile, with 14 stations of their own on the
Peninsula, co-operate closely with the British.
Nearer the pole by 600 to 800 miles and on the
eastern coast of the Weddell Sea at Halley Bay, the
Royal Society has established its own observatory, manned
by 18 men, for precision measurements in geophysics and
especially for the study of geomagnetism, electrical condi¬
tions oí the upper atmosphere and radioastronomy. The
station lies close to the belt of maximum auroral activity.
Reminiscent of the heroic expeditions of Scott and
Shackleton will be the British Trans-Antarctic Expedition
and the New Zealand Trans-Antarctic Party, led respec¬
tively by Dr. Vivian E. Fuchs and Sir Edmund Hillary,
conqueror of Mt. Everest. From Vahsel Bay at the base
of the Weddell Sea the British party will climb by track
vehicles and dog sled to the South Pole and, continuing,
will cross the continent at its narrowest point to McMurdo
Sound on the Ross Sea, a distance of about 1,800 miles.
The New Zealand party will travel in the opposite direction
to a meeting point. This mobile expedition is not
primarily scientific, but topographical, meteorological and
geological observations will be made and the ice thickness
will be measured every 20 to 30 miles.
Australia established a base three years ago at Mawson
on the rugged coast directly south of the tip of India. A
staff of 24 men is at work with elaborate equipment for the
measurement of the aurora, cosmic rays, meteor-tracking
to measure winds in the upper atmosphere, geo-magnetic
fluctuations and ice-thickness. Mawson base has two
airplanes to maintain contact with the smaller Davis base,
400 miles to the east where geological and meteorological
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
Soviet Antarctic Expeditions
A MAIN STREET
CALLED LENIN
Soviet engineers have set up a town
site at Mirny ("Peaceful" in Russian)
at the foot of the massive Helen
Glacier which leads into the interior
towards the "Pole of Inaccessibility",
the most difficult part of Antarctica.
Right, N° 5 Lenin Street, as the main
street of the station has been named.
An automatic telephone station has
been installed in the right wing of the
building which is temporarily heated
by metal stoves. Soviet preparations
for the I.G.Y. in the Antarctic have
been going on since 1955 when two
ships arrived at the Mirny site and
disembarked advance party and stores.
measurements will be supplemented by an all-sky camera.
Australia also maintains a station on Macquarie Island a
thousand miles north of Antarctica and south of the Aus¬
tralian island of Tasmania. A robot weather station on
the Windmill islands automatically reports its observations
twice daily by radio to Australia direct.
The United States has established five major stations,
plus the station at Cape Adare operated jointly with New
Zealand and a station for meteorology and air supply base
on McMurdo Sound. The large station at Little America
on the eastern shore of the Ross Sea includes 25 scientists
and serves as a base for two stations in the interior. One
with 9 scientists is at the South Pole; another with 15
scientists is at an altitude aï 5,000 feet in the mountains
of Marie Byrd Land some 650 miles east of Little America,
an 18-day trip by tractor-train. The two others, with 14
scientists each, are on the ice at the base of the Weddell
Sea and on the Knox Coast directly opposite, 2,000 miles
distant. All five stations are equipped for researches in
meteorology, geomagnetism, glaciology, physics of the
ionosphere and studies of the aurora and airglow. All
except the base on the Weddell Sea ice will undertake
seismological research, and the station on the Knox Coast
is a major one for studying cosmic rays.
Extensive traverses totalling nearly 5,000 miles will be
made from three stations for extended measurements oí
the ice thickness and the contour of the rocks beneath,
measurements of ice flow, of the gravitational field, of
magnetic fluctuations and of atmospheric conditions. The
station at Little America "also operates the Antarctic
Weather Central where weather observations are collected
and analyses and forecasts are broadcast ior the use of
all the nations operating on the continent. The station
at the South Pole has been named the Amundsen-Scott
Base in honour oí the only two men who have reached
the pole by surface transport. It was dedicated on
January 24.
France established a station at Pointe Geologie in Adelie
Land, south of Eastern Australia, in 1949-'53 which has
again been occupied during the Year together with a
smaller station some 300 miles inland toward the South
Magnetic Pole.
The Norwegian station east of the Weddell Sea is on the
zero meridian of longitude the meridian of Greenwich
and was established in March 1957.
The Japanese and Belgian stations will be on the relati¬
vely unexplored coast that faces Africa, between the
Australian base at Mawson and the Weddell Sea, and they
complete the ring of stations spaced around the continent.
The materials for Japan's station at Showa were unloaded
under difficult conditions in February 1957. It is the first
Antarctic activity of Japan since 1912 when Choku Shirase
made a voyage of exploration.
Belgium is the most recent participant in the Antarctic
programme and will make its first entry late this year.
The Belgian government has allocated 40 million Belgian
francs to the expedition.
As the sun veers southward in September and reappears
over Antarctica's northern horizon, the springtime of the
epochal Year dawns on the cold continent and a season of
feverish activity begins. Before it sets again in March
much of the mystery of the Antarctic will have been
transformed into sure scientific information and this in
turn will solve many a problem in the understanding of
the forces that govern this mysterious planet.
SNOWED UNDER AT
THE POST OFFICE
Largest part of Britain's I.G.Y. Ant¬
arctic activities stems from the
Falkland Islands Dependencies Survey
which has been conducting both
surveys and polar researches in
islands south of the Falklands and on
Graham Land for some years. It has
ten permanent stations in the area
equipped for scientific studies included
in the Year, but especially for weather
observation. Right, Marguerite Bay
Base at Stonington Island where
eleven British scientists were maroon¬
ed for over two years. Building with
wire-braced chimneys peeping
through snow is party's "Post Office".
C.O.I. London
«r£^-<
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ZERO HOUR (MIDNIGHT)
FOR THE WEATHERMAN
WMO/OMM
T 1.12.001
Nothing is so effective in creating the fascinating
human diversity of races, cultures and ways of life
as the infinite range of local weather that is called
climate, irom that of the frozen Arctic tundra to the
tropics, from the rain forest to the desert. So the geo¬
physical sciences that touch us most closely are those that
study the weather and the climate.
Yet few people are aware that meteorology is not the
science of meteors but of weather. It seems a misnomer.
However, the word "meteor" comes from the ancient
Greek and means "high in the air" and originally included
all phenomena above the earth's surface, clouds as well as
the aurora and the "shooting stars" to which the word is now
limited. And what is more,
"climate" has changed its
meaning too, for originally it
referred only to the incline
(which has the same Latin
root) of the sun's rays at
various locations, whereas
now it refers to the relation
of the long-range weather
to the ground beneath. Me¬
teorology and climatology
are the geophysical sciences
with direct human appeal,
as distinct from the scien¬
tific and scholarly.
They are primarily con¬
cerned with the lowest layer
of air called the tropo¬
sphere which is close to
the earth and extends
upwards perhaps ten miles.
It is warmed by heat
radiated from the ground
and is compressed by the
weight of the air above
it which is about a ton
per square foot at sea
level. Here and there it is
saturated with water evapo¬
rated from the ocean which
condenses to form visible
clouds. It is in constant
turmoil, rising upward as it
is heated, dropping its moi¬
sture as rain when it is
cooled, flowing in swift
winds where differences of
pressure develop, swirling in
vast storms a thousand mi¬
les in diameter or whistling in violent whirling tornadoes,
hurricanes and typhoons when its energy is concentrated.
Man has always been at the mercy of the weather and
cannot control it. Indeed, it is beyond his understanding
because, as has been learned only recently, the circulation
of the lower atmosphere is partly dependent on the great
winds of the layer above, the cold stratosphere where the
air is too thin to support life or even the burning of a
candle. Meteorological researches of the Year will thus
include conditions in the stratosphere to a height of about
20 miles, as high as weather ballons can rise without burst¬
ing. But above that lies the ionosphere, the study of which
requires quite different devices and methods, a different
committee of the Year, and another article in this issue.
Adequate weather forecasts for a day or two into the
future have long been based on measurements and records
of the temperature, pressure, humidity, rainfall and the
direction and velocity of the wind, taken at weather sta¬
tions on the land and on ships at sea. The location of
existing storm centres was thus established and the direc¬
tion and speed of their movement could be predicted. But
predictions based only on the lowest layer of air, in contact
16
with the ground or sea, were not wholly reliable nor could
they extend more than a few days into the future. In
recent years weather analyses and 'forecasts have been
based on the movement of major air masses at high alti¬
tudes which profoundly influence air circulation at the
surface.
For this reason the weather balloon has become an im¬
portant observing instrument. Many are released as pilot
balloons to reach altitudes of five to ten miles where tha
direction and speed of their drift can be followed optically
from the ground stations. Others, called radio-sondes, carry
instruments to measure temperature, pressure and humidi¬
ty which are recorded or reported to ground by radio. A
third type is designed to
measure wind velocity. These
balloons are made of natu¬
ral or synthetic rubber, and
when properly handled and
inflated with hydrogen or
helium can climb to an alti¬
tude approaching 20 miles,
where the air pressure is
only one fiftieth that at sea
level and the balloon ex¬
pands under its own pres¬
sure until it bursts. Low
temperature is a major
cause of bursting, as the
rubber becomes less plastic.
Temperatures of -40°F and
even of -110°F are encoun¬
tered at such altitudes,
especially in the Arctic and
Formulaire N» 1 : Observations synoptiques en surface IQY/AGI
Région I : Afrique. StaUons : 64 400 - 65 592
6-10 JAN. 1957
MILLIONS OF OBSERVATIONS will be recorded at the Special
Meteorological Data Centre set up by the World Meteorological Orga¬
nization in Geneva during the I.G.Y. To publish them would require
about 1,000 volumes of 1,000 pages each. A cheaper and simple
solution has been found in the microcard (above) of less than postcard
size on which nearly 50 of the original report forms can be reproduced
photographically. Complete collection of meteorological reports
received during the I.G.Y. will be compressed into 20,000 microcards.
Antarctic, where special
weather stations are estab¬
lished for operation during
the Year.
Obviously data obtained
at any one station, no mat¬
ter how accurate or complete
are of little significance
until they are combined with data from the entire globe,
all of them taken at the same hours and taken every day.
Only in this way can the large air masses be identified
and their movements followed. Essential to the weather
studies of the Year, therefore, is the Meteorological Data
Centre operated by the World Meteorological Organization
(wmo) at Geneva, Switzerland, wmo is a specialized
agency of the United Nations as Unesco is which was
established with the purpose of co-ordinating, standardiz¬
ing and improving meteorological observations throughout
the world. It regularly publishes the quarterly wmo Bul¬
letin and for the purposes of the Year has published two
authoritative books, one a general survey of the meteoro¬
logical programme and the other a complete list of the
several thousand weather stations of the world that will
take part in it. The books can be obtained at wmo head¬
quarters, Campagne Rigot, Avenue de la
Paix, Geneva, for 10 and 8 Swiss francs, res¬
pectively.
The number of stations that will make
weather observations daily at six-hour in¬
tervals, beginning at O hours (midnight),
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Seotcmber 1957
AT WORK ON THE WEATHER. For many years meteorologists have been trying to obtain an ever
more complete picture of the global circulation of the atmosphereknowledge on which really reliable long-
range weather forecasting must depend. Much light has been thrown on this problem in recent years through
soundings of the upper atmosphere by the radio-sonde a small radio transmitter which signals atmospheric
pressure, temperature and humidity as it is carried aloft by a hydrogen-filled balloon (right). Three hundred
additional radio-sonde soundings will be made daily during I.G.Y. Above, observations of extraordinary meteo¬
rological phenomena, like this lenticular cloud formation on a storm-swept Antarctic island, help in valuable
long-range weather forecasting. Below, left and right, meteorologist analyses weather chart and a radar operator
picks up a far distant swirling hurricane on the scope of his set. This new radar equipment will enable meteo¬
rologists to study an entire weather front or to magnify and analyse a small portion of an approaching storm.
Meteorologie Nationale. Paris
WMO USIS
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ZERO HOUR (Continued)
THE WORLD-WIDE EXTENT OF I.G.Y.- THOU
UNITED -¿,
KINGDOM^a^
Map courtesy of "New York Times" © 1957
Greenwich Mean Time, is now over 2,100, selected from a
much larger number of available stations in order to repre¬
sent as evenly as possible all areas of the earth. They are
located from pole to pole in 93 different countries, and in¬
clude remote islands in the oceans and ships at sea. There
is an especial concentration of stations in five north-south
or meridional bands, as shown on world map above.
In addition, some 650 stations are equipped with radio¬
sonde and radio-wind equipment for study of the upper
atmosphere. They are expected to carry out two radio-sound¬
ings (for temperature, pressure and humidity) and four
radio-wind observations daily. A total of 700 stations will
also measure the intensity of the radiation received from the
sun in terms of direct sunshine, diffuse skylight, long-wave
and short-wave (ultra-violet) radiation. Finally, about 100
stations will make frequent measurements of the ozone in
the atmosphere at various levels.
This is obviously the most extensive of all the programmes
to be undertaken during the Year. It involves many
thousands of technical experts and will grind out many
millions of individual measurements. These will all be sent
to Geneva and coded for reproduction on microcards which
can later be studied. It will be some years before the analysis
of the cards can distill from them the useful information
that may well revolutionize present concepts of atmospheric
18
energy and circulation and may permit more precise long-
range weather forecasts .
In scholarly terms the Special Committee for the Inter¬
national Geophysical Year has listed the following major
problems to be solved by this study: Redistribution in the
atmosphere on a planetary scale of momentum, absolute vor-
ticity, entropy and the various forms of energy.
Large-scale influence of friction and surface topography
on the balance of these factors.
Heat and momentum exchanges between the atmosphere
on the one hand and the continents and oceans on the other.
Flow patterns in the lower latitudes, including the inter¬
actions between the circulations of the two hemispheres and
between the tropical and extratropical circulations.
Distribution of precipitation, especially over the oceans
and distribution of evaporation at the earth's surface in
relation to large-scale world situations.
Horizontal and vertical distribution of ozone and of water-
vapour.
Heát balance and the radiation balance of the atmosphere
in relation to the general circulation.
The electric field in the atmosphere on a planetary scale
and its variations in terms of weather systems.
In plainer language, what is involved here is not merely
the mapping of the air movements but the transport by the
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
SANDS OF STATIONS WILL DOT THE GLOBE
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
air of heat, water, electricity and other forms of energy from
place to place on earth, from the hot tropics to the temperate
and polar zones, from the upper layers, where sunshine
strikes, to the lower, from the oceans to the land. Weather
is the result of such transportation and the winds that bring
the weather are themselves impelled by air pressure, which
represents energy.
In still plainer language, what is sought is the answer to
such questions as: Where and how are the winds generated?
What is the origin of the great vortex movements, from
rainstorms to hurricanes and typhoons? Are periods of warm
and of cold weather related to the energy received from the
sun or are they variations in the local energy balance cold
at one point being balanced by heat at another? What is
the effect on the atmospheric energy of the vast Antarctic
cold area? What is the effect of the temperature of the ocean
and of ocean currents? What is the weather map in the
stratosphere, where there is no water and no clouds but the
winds blow strong, and what is the effect of stratospheric
winds on the weather below? Does the earth radiate as much
energy into space as it receives from the sun, thus maintain¬
ing a balance, or is the earth slowly warming so that the gla¬
ciers are melting and the climate all over the earth is chang¬
ing slowly?
Many of these questions cannot be answered by meteorology
alone but involve observations in glaciology and oceanography
and especially the phenomena of the upper atmosphere that
will be separately studied by means of rockets and the physics
of the ionosphere, as detailed in a later article.
In order to tie together the lower and upper atmosphere
observations and to obtain a simultaneous report from diffe¬
rent sciences, the Special Committee has established a special
calendar for the 18 months of the Year which sets individual
days and ten-day periods, known as World Days and World
Meteorological Intervals, during which all observations will
be increased in number and special tests, such as rocket
launchings, will be made. (See pages 20 and 21).
If the occurence of spots on the sun i.e. electrical and mag¬
netic storms, could be predicted, a World Interval would
certainly be scheduled for that period because the electrical
conditions in the upper atmosphere are then profoundly
changed. Sunspots and electrical storms will very probably
increase during the Year, however, and provision has been
made for a Special World Interval whenever they do appear.
A short article can do no more than sketch the meteorolo¬
gical activities during the Year. Enough has been said to
show that the complexity of the investigations will match
the complexity of the causes of weather. They are hidden
today and as turbulently mixed as the storm winds them¬
selves. This geophysical year promises to unravel most oí
the confusion and permit much better weather forecasts.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE GRASSHOPPER, as this robot weatherstation is called, is
dropped by parachute in isolated areas from where meteorological
reports would be of greatest value in forecasting the weather.
On reaching ground, grasshopper detaches itself from the
parachute, erects itself on six legs, takes weather information
direction, temperature, barometric pressure and humi¬
dity these observations automatically into morse
and transmits them by radio at a speed of 17 words a minute.
It operates on batteries which will power it for 60 days.
20
WARNING! SPECIAL
WORLD ALERT:
AGI-SSSSS-SWI
One of the key principles of the I.G.Y. is the simultaneous
observation of the same or related geophysical phenomena
at all points on the world network. So a special I.G.Y.
Calendar of Regular World Days and World Meteo¬
rological Intervals (right) has been drawn up so as to concentrate
and conserve the energies of the thousands of observers during
their long watch of 18 months.
The Regular World Days occur twice a month, two days
together at each new moon and a single day at quarter moon.
These days are set apart for intensive observation of all kinds.
Then every quarter comes a period of ten days during which the
meteorologists will be especially active in mapping the world¬
wide trends of wind and weather at each equinox and solstice.
These are the World Meteorological Intervals.
High on the list of key stations of the I.G.Y. are the solar
observatories. For if watchers are to obtain a world coverage
of the effects of eruptions on the sun in such diverse fields as
the onset of radio fade-outs, deviations of the magnetic compass,
world-wide interruption of radio-communication following
magnetic storms in the upper atmosphere and possibly enhanced
displays of the aurora in the Arctic and the Antarctic, then they
must be warned in advance.
Thirty-eight solar observatories, girdling the earth, are lined up
for intensive observation of the sun. An elaborate system of
radio and telegraphic communication has been worked out to
give upwards of 800 stations, equipped to observe the numerous
phenomena which accompany magnetic storms, timely warning
of such special events on the sun, so that scientists manning them
may be on the alert.
These warnings are known as World Alerts, and the job ot
issuing them has been assigned to the powerful radio transmitter
at Fort Belvoir near Washington, on the basis of information
received by radio from Paris, Moscow and Tokio. A team of
trained predictors of solar disturbances has been assembled at
Fort Belvoir.
A World Alert is issued four to six days ahead of an expected
disturbance on the sun at or near the centre of the sun's disc.
If the disturbance continues to look important, then the day before
its expected advent the Central Warning Service at Fort Belvoir
flashes the pre-arranged signal "AGI-SSSSS-SWI", (meaning
Année Géophysique Internationale Warning Special World
Interval) indicating that a special Interval of several days will
be observed.
In this way, observers up and down the world can conserve
their energies for periods of maximum solar-terrestial activity,
and then go all out towards constructing a real world picture of
the event, not only in relation to the geographical map of the
world, but also in relation to the events which are taking place
high above the earth's surface.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
July 1957
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
1 2 3 (a) 5 6
7 8 9 10 11 12 13
14 15 16 17 18 19 20
21 22 23 24 25 (26) (27)
28 29 30 31
October 1957
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
12 3 4 5
6 7 8 9 10 11 12
13 14 15 16 17 18 19
20 21 @[23](53) 25 26
27 28 29 30 31
January 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
1 QQ
5 6 7 8 9 10 11
12 13 14 15 16 17 18
©® 21 22 23 24 25
26 27 28 29 30
April 1958
31
Sun. Mon Tue. Wed. Thu . Fri. Sat.
1 2 3 4 5
6 7 8 9 10 11 12
13 14 15 16 17 (<») n
© 21 22 23 24 25 26
27 28 29 30
July 1958
Sun. Mon . Tue. Wed. Thii. Fri Sat
12 3 _4 5
6 7 8 9 10 11 12
13 14 «o© 18 19
20 21 22 23 24 25 26
(27) 28 29 30 31
October 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
12 3 4
5 6 7 8 9 (jq)(n)
[22JIT3; 14 15 16 17 18
19 20 21 22 23 24 25
26 27 28 29 30 31
August 1957
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
1 2 3
4 _5_ 6 7 8 9 10
11 (TS) 13 14 15 16 17
18 19 20 21 22 23 24
15)<26) 27 28 29 30 31
November 1957
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
1 2
3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10 11 12 13 @ 15 16
i
17 18 19 20 (2p(22) 23
24 25 26 27 28 29 30
February 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
1
2 3 4 5 6 7 8
9 © 11 12 13 14 15
16 17 ©© 20 21 22
23 24 25 © 27 28
May 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
1 2 3
4 (7) 6 7 8 9 10
11 12 13 14 15 16 17
(18) (]9) 20 21 22 23 24
25 26 27 28 29 30 31
August 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
1 2
3 4 5 6 (7) 8 9
10 11 (Î2) 13 (if)© 16
17 18 19 20 21 22 23
% 25 26 27 28 29 30
November 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
1
2 3 (4) 5 6 7 8
9 ©(vT) 12 13 14 15
16 17 © 19 20 21 22
% 24 25 26 27 28 29
September 1957
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
(j) 2 3 4 5 6 7
8 9 10 11 12 13 14
15 16 17 18 19 20 21
22 (23)© 25 26 27 28
December 1957
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
12 3 4 5 6 7
8 9 10 II M 2 (J 3) 14
15 © 17 18 19 20 (21)
(22) 23 24 25 26 27 28
29 30 31
March 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
2 3 4 5 6 7/
9 10 11 12 13 14 15
16 17
24
18
25
19
26
(2Q)
27
(21) 22 j
23 29
30 31
June 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat
12 3 4 5 6 7
JJ_(9)10 11 12 13 14
15 16 18) 19 20 21
22 23 (24) 25 26 27 28
29 30
September 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
1
7 8
2
9
3
10
4
11
5©
@15
21 22
16 17 18 19 (5o)
23 24 25 26 27
28 29 30
December 1958
Sun. Mon. Tue. Wed. Thu. Fri. Sat.
12 3 4 5 6
7 8 9 (T^)(VJ) 12 <3)
14 15 16 Qf) 18 19 20
21 22 23 24 25 26 27
28 29 30 31
World Meteorological Interval 20 21 22
J23 24 25 26 27 28 29
Regular world day (ÍT)
Regular world day at new moon(lO)
Unusual meteoric activity 8 (but not world day)
Regular world day with unusual meteoric activity(]7)
Day of total eclipseR^I
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
OUR GREAT OCEAN RESERVOIR
A THOUSAND AND ONE SECRETS LOCKED IN WATER, CLOUDS & ICE
Tf MP "C APR '57
I
Woods Hole Océanographie Irstitute
ANATOMY OF THE ATLANTIC was studied by research ship Crawford, from Woods Hole Océanographie Institute
(U.S.A.), in 1957. Here, oceanographer shows vessel's track chart across Atlantic. Superimposed on left is chart of
deep-water temperatures between Africa and South America. Island of St. Helena, topping a high mountain peak in
the mid-Atlantic submarine range contrasts sharply with depths of 15,000 feet surrounding it. At this latitude bottom
waters are close to freezing point and only In top 200 metres are ocean waters near the temperature of the atmosphere.
The Immensity of this earth is best appreciated by the
men of the sea. From the air it seems small; on
the land the expanse is always limited. But the
sea is continuous and endless. The continents are only
islands in it. Altogether they cover only 57 million
square miles. But the ocean area is 140 million square
miles two point five times the land area. And ten percent
of the land, six million square miles, is covered with ice
that is slowly crawling back to the sea. Almost three
quarters of the earth's surface is water or ice.
The volume of water, is even more impressive. In
human terms a cubic mile is enormous, for a box one
tenth of a cubic mile in size could easily contain the
entire human race though not comfortably. Yet a cubic
mile would hardly seem a drop in the world's total of
350 million cubic miles of water. While most of the
water is in the great ocean reservoir, of course, about 25
million cubic miles of it is in circulation elsewhere at any
moment, making the grand tour up into the skies by
evaporation, then falling as rain or snow and returning
to the ocean via the rivers. The atmosphere probably
contains about 3,600 cubic miles in the form of vapour
and clouds. The surface rivers and lakes hold about 55,000
cubic miles. The amount hidden in underground rivers
and reservoirs is several hundred times larger and has
been estimated at 20 million cubic miles.
But aside from all these mobile forms, there is still
about one percent of all the earth's water that is detained
in its circuit, frozen, perhaps for centuries, in the form of
22
glaciers and the massive ice cover of Greenland and
Antarctica. How much this is nobody knows because the
thickness of the Antarctic ice has been measured at very
few points. Estimates of the average thickness vary from
2,000 to 5,000 feet but at some points it is certainly 10,000
feet thick. One of the most interesting results of the
Year's researches will be the answer to this question. De¬
pending on the thickness, the total volume of Antarctic
ice is between 2.4 million and 6 million cubic miles.
If all this ice were permanently frozen in place, it
would matter little to human thought or plans. But it is
in constant exchange, always growing with snowfall yet
always flowing to the sea in glaciers or breaking from the
Shelf Ice as icebergs and in sheets that may be several
hundred miles in extent and hundreds of feet thick. Part
of the snow is blown to sea by high winds. Above all, a
rise in temperature causes melting. If it were all melted
and ran to the sea the level of the oceans all over the
world would rise by 60 to 200 feet. Most of the world's
great seaport cities would be inundated. A report to the
American Geophysical Union calls the Antarctic glaciers
"something of a Sword of Damocles hanging over the
heads of all peoples living close to the sea".
It could happen but not soon and only very slowly
conceivably in 10,000 to 20,000 years. In fact, during most
of the world's history the earth was probably free of
glaciers. But in the past million years there have been
four great ice ages when the average temperature was
some ten degrees cooler so that ice accumulated and
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
covered a million square miles each in Europe, Siberia
and North America. As the ice piled up on the land, the
level oí the sea dropped to some 300 feet lower than now.
In about 3,000 B.C. the climate was warmer and drier
than now and sea level was apparently about six feet
higher than now. Then the glaciers grew again and
reached a maximum in the 18th century. Since then the
glaciers have been receding and the sea level is rising at
a rate of about 2.5 inches per century. Since the temper¬
ature of the earth is variable, the glaciers come and go
and even the "'ageless and eternal sea", rises and falls
again. Man is powerless to control such vast forces but
he has the ability to understand them and to foresee their
effects. This is part of the task of the sciences of glacio¬
logy and of oceanography during the Year.
Accordingly the Antarctic studies during the Year join
with those in the Arctic and with glacier studies through¬
out the world to determine the life history of the ice,
including its rate of formation, its age, and the shifting
balance between its growth and Its melting. Extended
studies are under way by both Soviet and American
scientists encamped on floating ice islands to measure
their drift and observe their fate as well as to measure the
temperature, depth and circulation of the Antarctic and
Arctic seas.
As for many years, since 1912, the International Ice
Patrol will continue its investigation of icebergs in
the North Atlantic for the direct benefit of mer¬
chant shipping but also to obtain weather data. So gla¬
ciology, oceanography and meteorology merge their sur¬
veys of ice, water and clouds for the purposes of better
forecasting of oceanic conditions and especially of anti¬
cipating their changes in the course of years.
Oceanography itself is a many-sided science that inclu¬
des the geological study of the sea bottom and the geo¬
graphy of its submerged mountain ranges and deep tren¬
ches, the variation of the saltiness, chemical composition,
and temperature of the waters, the mapping of the great
movements of the ocean currents both at the surface and
in the deeps, and the study of marine life, both plant and
animal, polar and tropical, at the surface and in depth.
During the Year, however, it is the ocean itself that will
be especially studied, not its life.
The surface currents of the oceans have a direct effect
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
on the climate and the weather of the continents as the
warm tropical waters flow toward the poles, both north
and south, and are driven eastward both by winds and by
the rotation of the earth. Thus the Gulf Stream In the
Atlantic and the Japan Current in the Pacific warm the
western areas of both America and Europe.
But cold water from the Polar regions flows toward the
tropics in the ocean depths. The British research ship
Discovery II has recently tracked the deep currents by
using a float made of sealed aluminium tubing which is
heavier than water at the surface, but can be adjusted to
the density of the compressed seawater at any depth and
can be effectively suspended at different underwater
levels. It drifts with the submerged currents, sending out
sound signals which permit the ship to follow it on the
surface. In the Gulf Stream there is a strong northward
movement at the surface and little movement at depths
of 5,000 to 6,000 feet, but at depths between 8,200 and
9,200 feet the movement is southward. At one point the
deep float travelled 23 miles in 66 hours. Even 18 inches
from the bottom there is noticeable flow to the south.
Thus the ocean "turns over" at a slow pace. The com¬
plete top-to-bottom exchange may take from 150 to 1,000
years, bringing the surface plant life to the lower levels
and mineral nutrients to the top. It is possible that the
fluctuations may be responsible for severe changes in the
climate on land. The "age" of the deep waters I.e. the
years since they were at the surface is measured by
bringing up samples irom far below, releasing its dissolved
carbon dioxide by means of acid, then determining the
ratio of the three forms, or isotopes, of carbon in the gas.
As the radio-active isotope gradually disappears with the
years, the ratio shows how long each sample has been
submerged.
Knowledge of the deep currents will also become in¬
creasingly important if the practice of disposing of radio¬
active wastes from nuclear power plants becomes general
in the atomic age. It is by no means certain that such
materials will long remain where they are dropped. So
it is also important to know the nature of the ocean
floor. It has usually been assumed to be a thick layer of
sediments but there are certainly large areas
of bare rock. Samples are gathered by Cont'd
dropping a core-tube to within a few feet of
the bottom, suspended on a heavy cable, then
releasing a heavy lead weight which drives
the core-pipe into the soft sediment. With a
'AGE' OF OCEAN WATERS at great depthsthe years since they
were at the surfacecan now be measured by studying content of
radio-active isotopes to determine the "turn over" or complete top-
to-bottom exchange which may take from 150 to 1,000 years and
whose fluctuations may be responsible for severe changes in climate
Woods Hole Océanographie Institute photos
on land. Above, right, lowering a water sampler from U.S research,
ship, Crawford, to obtain specimens from the depths. Thousands of
observations of temperature, salinity, oxygen content etc., will be
made during the I.G.Y. by ships of many nations. Above, left, techni¬
cian unhooks a "Nansen bottle" used for collecting submarine water.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
OCEAN RESERVOIR (Continued)
tube, about 3 inches in diameter,
samples 100 feet in thickness have
been obtained but more recent devices
take wider samples a° less thickness.
Columbia University's research vessel,
the Venia, has taken samples from
the ocean bottom 13,000 feet beneath
the surface. Microscopic study of the
materials in the samples and of their
arrangement in depth reveals their
geological history.
Another ocean-bottom device mea¬
sures the heat that flows to the sea
from the relatively thin crust of the
earth under it. Because of the vast
extent of the oceans this is an
important element in the heat balance
of the earth. It is the only major
source of energy that does not
originate on the sun.
The largest task of the oceanogra-
phers is to map the geography
of the sea bottom over its entire
area, which is 70 percent of the area
aï the earth. It is not flat but, like
the land area, has long chains of high
mountains, most of them wholly
submerged though some extend above
the surface as islands in the sea.
There is one such range 8,000 miles
long, running north and south in the
Atlantic between Europe-Africa and
the two Americas. Its peaks are
10,000 feet above their base on the
Atlantic floor. Another such ridge
runs from Japan south to Antarctica
and that continent is also joined to
South America by an undersea ridge
which projects above the surface to
form the South Sandwich, South
Orkney and South Shetland Islands.
But there are also long deep trenches
that cut into the sea bottom to a
depth of several miles. The deepest
is southwest of the island oí Guam,
more than 34,000 feet below sea-level
at the lowest point yet measured.
If the earth's highest mountain,
Mt. Everest in the Himalayas, were
based on this trench, it's summit
would still be 5,000 feet below sea
level.
Large areas of the sea, however,
have not been mapped and surprises
may appear during the Year as
vessels of many nations continue with
the modern technique of echo-
sounding which measures the depth
by the reflection of sound-waves irom
the bottom. Earlier this year, for
instance, the Lamont Geological
Observatory of Columbia University
announced the discovery of a "rift"
in the sea-bottom that is 45,000 miles
long and coincides with the major
undersea earthquake zone along its
entire length. It averages 20 miles
in width and 7,500 feet in depth. It
is bordered by mountain ridges that
average 6,000 feet in height and about
75 miles in width.
The sea is the source aï all rain
and no certain understanding of the
world's weather is possible without
much better knowledge than is now
available of the controlling factors in
the sea. The relatively unspectacular
explorations of the ocean deeps,
showing only a white research yacht
slowly cruising along, far from the
major traffic lanes, are nevertheless
one aï the most important features
of the Year.
24
UNESCO AND THE I.G.Y.
The Department of Natural Sciences of unesco has no laboratories,
observatories or scientific equipment, conducts no researches,
and cannot take an active part in th« Year. Its function is to
advance world science, primarily by means of existing international
scientific organizations such as the Scientific Unions that are organiz¬
ed into the International Council of Scientific Unions and the Inter¬
national Council of Medical Sciences. It stimulates international co- '
operation in the attack on problems that are regional or world-wide.
For example, its Advisory Committee on Arid Zone Research has
effectively unified the programmes of the 37 nations that are handi¬
capped by deserts or arid lands. Humid tropics, marine biology and
the use of radio-isotopes are similar projects.
Unesco has for the past ten years allocated an annual subvention
of around $180,000 from its own limited budget to support the meetings
and the headquarters of the International Council of Scientific Unions
(I.C.S.U.), which are now in London (1). The council established, the
Special Committee on the International Geophysical Year which did
its original organization and planning partly on subventions from
unesco, listed below (larger funds were later supplied by many other
scientific organizations and governments) :
$1,400 for the organization of the first meeting of the Committee
at Brussels in October, 1952.
$1,000 for the first preparatory work on the Year in 1953.
$2,000 for the second meeting of the Committee at Rome, October
1954.
$20,000 for the establishment of the permanent Committee head¬
quarters, for the work of the Committee and maintenance
of its headquarters in 1955.
$15,000 similarly for 1956.
$50,000 for the biennium 1957-58.
However, education in science is also an important unesco function.
This issue of the unesco courier, devoted to the International Geo¬
physical Year, is only one aspect of unesco's educational support.
Another is the newest of unesco's famous travelling science exhibi¬
tions, dedicated entirely to geophysics and to the scientific activities
of the Year, which will tour almost the entire globe in 1957 and 1958.
These exhibitions are enormously popular educational displays that
travel from country to country at the invitation of the member states
of UNESCO.
Unesco's international fellowship training programme in science has
also provided and financed eight fellowships to augment the supply of
competent experts needed by the Year's widespread activities. Fellows
have been appointed from Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, Egypt, Pakistan,
Peru, Thailand and Yugoslavia. They have been in training during
the past year at the Institute of Meteorology, Charlottenlund, Den¬
mark ; The California Institute of Technology ; The U.S. Weather
Bureau, Washington ; The U.S. National Bureau of Standards,
Washington ; The University of Colorado U.S.A. ; The U.S. Coast and
Geodetic Survey ; The Carnegie Institution of Washington.
In addition to the grants made by unesco, the Special Committee for
the International Geophysical Year has received annual grants from
the I.C.S.U. since 1952, and more than ten countries have made indivi¬
dual contributions varying in size from several hundreds to several
thousands of dollars.
(1) The members of the International
Council of Scientific Unions are : Inter¬
national Astronomical Union ; Internation¬
al Union of Biological Sciences ; Inter¬
national Union of Pure and Applied Che¬
mistry ; International Union of Crystallo¬
graphy ; International Union of Geodesy
and Geophysics ; International Geogra
phical Union ; International Union of the
History and Philosophy of Science ; Inter¬
national Union of Theoretical and Applied
Mechanics ; International Union of Pure
and Applied Physics ; International Scienti¬
fic Radio Union ; International Mathema¬
tical Union ; International Union of Phy¬
siological Sciences ; International Union
of Biochemistry.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Scotcmber 1957
A GIANT EAR
'LISTENS IN'
TO THE STARS
Radioastronomers at Jodrell Bank, Cheshire,
England, have begun delving into the secrets
of outer space with the giant, 250-foot,
dish-shaped radio telescope (left) completed
recently for Manchester University after five
years of construction.
Designed to explore natural radio signals
coming from outer space, the radio telescope
will enable scientists to "listen in" to cosmic
events that took place millions of years ago
and to reach out into space to distances of
1,000 million light years or more far beyond
the limits of observation of the greatest
existing optical telescopes.
The mammoth radio telescope (total weight
2,000 tons) went into operation in August,
and Professor A.C.B. Lovell, professor of
radioastronomy at Manchester University,
who is in charge of it, reported that in two
hours it provided information that would have
taken a month to collect with any previously
existing receiver. After these initial tests,
the new telescope will play a part in Britain's
contribution to the I.G.Y.
Pressure on a series of buttons brings this
enormous mass of steel into action, slowly,
almost imperceptibly (maximum speed one
mile per hour) sweeping the heavens while
following a star in its course. Electronic
computors do all the calculations required to
keep the 62 >/2 foot aerial inside the bowl
pointing at the star wherever it moves in the
sky, taking into account the movement of the
earth around its axis and around the sun.
Originally designed to survey unknown parts
of the sky by intercepting the faint radio
signals emitted by celestial bodies like the
stars, the sun and distant galaxies, the radio
telescope will also be used during the I.G.Y.
to send radio pulses to the planets and the
moon and receive the echos that "bounce"
back. By I 960 with the aid of this instrument
scientists will have learned a great deal about
conditions that existed in the universe mil¬
lions of years ago.
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom the English, French, Spanish
and Russian editions of the UNESCO
COURIER can be obtained are listed
below.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Dep¬
artment, Royal Afghan Ministry of Educ¬
ación, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 303 Flinders Street, Melbourne,
C I, Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C'., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15 rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). 80 Belgian francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Baldwin House, 33 St. Georges Street,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, 100 Parsons Road Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kleber, Paris. I 6\ C.C.P.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Achens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Ntcol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcucta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mounc Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi: Raikamal Publicat¬
ions Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby Road,
Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.CT. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P.O. B. 4154, Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.. Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174. Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall.
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi- and
35 The Mall, Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Ouiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Friezes, Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgacen 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot. 40 rue du Marché, Geneva.
5.20 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2 rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
cional Bookshop, 551-3 Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724. Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569. London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 152 West 42nd St, New York,
36, N.Y,
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjlga
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
WHERE THE SKY
IS BLACK
There is an eerie fascination in the
high ionosphere. It is 50 to 250 miles
above the earth, higher than man ever
dreamed of reaching until the recent devel¬
opment of rockets. Nothing can live
there because the air is too thin only one
ten-millionth as dense as on the earth.
There can be no sound. The sky above
is black because there is nothing to break
up and reflect the sun's rays. But the
black sky glitters with brilliant stars, and
the sharp beam of the sun if one could
look at it would burn like a rod of white-
hot metal, yet is embroidered with grace¬
ful solar flares and the shimmering lace of
the corona.
The aurora is ever present, by day as by
night, weaving electronic rays into gorgeous
designs over the poles, waving majestic dra¬
peries of light hundreds of miles high and
thousands wide. Millions of meteors from
the depths of space flash into burning dust
on all sides, like fireflies on a Spring night.
Unseen and unheard is a turmoil of radio
waves from distant stars and from clouds
of cold gas between the stars. And finally
cosmic rays, projected from unknown explo¬
sions somewhere deep in the black sky,
pierce through any obstacle only, sooner or
later, to crash head-on into the nucleus
of some lone atom and thereby create a
whole shower of secondary rays that repeat
the collision miles and miles below as they,
in turn, dash earthward.
There in the black ionosphere is the dra¬
ma of cosmic energy, variegated and mani¬
fold, impinging on the tenuous halo of the
earth, with no man to see it. But the irre-
C. T K. Bratislava
MOUNTAIN OBSERVATORY in the High
Tatra range, Czechoslovakia, is making special
cosmic ray studies for I.G.Y. Another obser¬
vatory is perched on Mount Lomnitze (8,000
-feet high) seen in background. Cosmic rays
are also being studied in Central Europe's
deepest mine, at Pribram, Czechoslovakia.
26
sistible fascination is that without being
there, without the supersenses that would be
needed to detect these rays and radiations,
man nevertheless can know them through
the instruments he devises and the mathe¬
matics that makes them subject to reason.
The first inkling of all this complexity
came when it was discovered that radio
waves are reflected from something in the
sky so that they do not escape into space
when they pass the horizon but bounce
down again to reach distant receivers in
spite of the curvature of the earth. A
simple measurement of the time required
to reach the reflector and return to earth
showed that the reflecting layer is 60 to
90 miles above the ground. This discovery,
made in 1925, explained how wireless
messages can be sent across the ocean and
made possible the sending of radio broad¬
casts beyond the horizon. It also proved
that there is an electrified layer in the thin
air at that height which contains free elec¬
trons that are set into oscillation by the
radio wave. It absorbs the energy of the
wave so that it does not pass on but the
electron oscillation generates the same
wave-length and part of the new wave
returns to the ground.
This simple mechanism of reflection
means that large numbers of free electrons
and of electrically charged molecules, called
ions, are present in the upper atmosphere.
It is now known that there are three major
layers of ionized air which reflect radio
waves of different frequencies. The one
mentioned is known as the E layer. Above
it, at a height of about 90 to 150 miles, is
the F-l layer and still higher is the F-2
layer. The E-layer normally has 120 elec¬
trons per cubic millimetre, the F-l layer
220, and the F-2 layer 450. Ions are there¬
fore the outstanding characteristic of the
upper atmosphere so that it is properly
known as the ionosphere.
Storms in outer space
cut world communications
The ions are formed by the detachment
of electrons from atoms and mole¬
cules of ordinary oxygen, nitrogen
and other gases in the air when they are
bombarded by radiations from the sun, by
particles from outer space, even by passing
meteors. The chief source is the ultra¬
violet light from the sun which is intense
at that height but never reaches the surface
of the earth itself. The number of ions
at any moment is therefore dependent
on the amount and the type of radia¬
tions received from outside the earth.
Thus the ionosphere is a sort of sen¬
sitive skin for our planet, receiving and
responding to external influences. And
because the ionization can be observed from
the surface, by radio reflection, by radar,
and often optically too, it acts as a sort
of relay station to report external events
to puny men far below on the ground
whose senses are inadequate but whose
instruments, added to those senses, can feel
the skin of the planet and can thereby
learn what goes on hundreds of miles
high in the sky at the spherical border of
space. This is the function of what is
AURORA BOREALIS
called the physics of the ionosphere, one
of the major activities of the Year.
Below the ionosphere is the stratosphere
with air dense enough to support radio¬
sonde and other light balloons. The
highest unmanned balloon has risen to
about 30 miles. This is the frontier of
weather studies, as described in another
article in this issue. Recent rockets have
entered the ionosphere but none has as yet
gone through and beyond it. But above
the ionosphere is the unknown exosphere
where even ions are few and far between.
This will be the playground of the artifi¬
cial satellite, careering freely through space
by virtue of its velocity and held captive
only by gravitation, the one earthly force
that extends outward without limit.
The ionosphere is restless, more so than
any layer below, more restless than the
sea, because its ions are sensitive and very
light. It rises and falls in majestic tides
with the passage of the sun and- the moon.
The ionization grows by day and wanes by
night as the sunlight comes and goes. It
is stronger in winter than in summer. A
passing meteor may increase the ionization
locally a thousand-fold, as is described in
an article that follows. Each of these has
its effects on the transmission of wireless .
messages and of radio broadcasts. But
still more impressive are the major turbu¬
lences that are known as storms. They
may be real storms in the sense of violent,
high-altitude winds. They may be res¬
ponses to storms on the sun which spew out
vast fountains of swift particles and put the
ultra-violet radiation into spasms. Cer¬
tainly the ionization is affected by the solar
eruptions that cause the aurora borealis and
the aurora australis (Northern and Southern
Lights) and it varies regularly with the
eleven year cycle "of sunspots.
A consequence of all this turmoil on
high is the variation of the magnetic field
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
was photographed at Kiruna, northern Sweden, by all-sky camera (above,
left) which took in auroral displays from horizon to horizon by means of
curved mirror that reflects sky's image onto film.- Small white dots above
camera are pilot lights which determine aurora's position in both azimuth
and altitude. During I.G.Y. observing stations will be clustered for the
first time about both magnetic poles in zones of maximum auroral activity.
Photos courtesy Uppsala Ionosphere Observatory, Sweden
of the earth and the "magnetic storms" on
the surface which disrupt even ordinary
telegraphic and telephonic communication.
This is presumably because a layer of ions is
a conductor of electricity and a movement
of ions is an electric current. Every electric
current generates a magnetic field, whether
it flows in a wire or flows free. So iono¬
spheric winds could well produce enough
magnetism to magnify or counteract the
earth's own magnetism or to change its
direction somewhat, and thus to affect every
compass on every ship and plane.
Aside from such practical matters, it is
the task of ionospheric physics during the
Year to relate these various causes and
effects to each other and to deduce a single
consistent picture of events in the iono¬
sphere and their effects on human affairs.
This means that sunspots and solar flares
must be observed at the same instant as the
earth's magnetism is measured at as many
points as possible on the earth's surface.
The aurora must be observed in relation
both to the solar flares and to magnetic
variations. Measurements of the ioniza¬
tion in the various layers of the ionosphere
must also be tied to the other variations,
whether sunspots are involved or not. Iono¬
spheric physics and meteorology are there¬
fore both vitally concerned in the World
Days and the World Intervals when special
efforts will be made to obtain simultaneous
measurements all over the world. By this
time it is obvious that such world pheno¬
mena can be effectively studied only by
world-wide co-operation among scientists of
many nations and that to geophysics an
occasional period such as the present Year
is a necessity.
Since the major source of influence on
the ionosphere is the sun, it will receive
primary attention in the observatories that
are equipped for solar studies. Both the
magnificent eruptions of flares that spurt
hundreds of thousands of miles into space
from the face of the sun and the trembling
variations in the sun's much fainter corona
can now be observed on any clear day
without waiting for a total eclipse to make
them visible. This is the accomplishment
of the coronagraph, a telescope so equipped
that it blocks out the brilliant face of the
sun completely and precisely, as an
eclipse does, and thus permits the surround¬
ing flames and luminous clouds to be pho¬
tographed. Combined with a spectograph,
which can detect the separate light from
individual chemical elements on the sun,
and with a motion picture camera to record
action, the sublime drama is already record¬
ed on film. The timing of such solar
events with related effects in the ionosphere
will be a major feature of the Year.
Gorgeous celestial ballets
at the ends of the earth
The aurora is almost certainly the
consequence of a shower of particles
from the sun, probably electrons
and possibly protons (the nuclei of helium
atoms) too. As they approach the earth
these charged particles are deflected
toward the magnetic poles of the earth
and strike downward to ionize the upper
air. With this much known, the exact
course of events in the aurora is still
unknown: the explanation of the gor¬
geous "curtains", the '"draperies", the
"rays" and the "arcs", the location about
the poles, and the relation of the
northern to the southern lights. For the
first time a series of observing stations will
be clustered about both the magnetic poles
in the zones of maximum auroral activity.
Radio contact has already been established
between the stations at the two ends of the
earth in order to link the two celestial
ballets which cannot be seen at the same
time from any point on earth. There is
every reason to suppose that even more
particles are showered on the earth by day
than by night, which is to say that more
can be expected on the side of the earth
that faces the sun than on the back side.
Yet the aurora is not visible by day.
Efforts will therefore be made to track the
aurora by radar and radio reflection during
the daylight hours.
The radio-telescope, (see page 25) which
has undergone rapid development in the
past few years, will also do its share not
only in "listening" to the sun but
in detecting variations in the radio-waves
from distant stars as related to change in
the ionosphere.
The greatest mystery of the skies, how¬
ever, are the cosmic rays. They are compos¬
ed of the smallest of nuclear particles and
reach the earth with energies measured in
millions of millions of volts. With this
high energy they are less affected by the
earth's magnetic field than the particles
which cause the aurora. But the actual
particles from space seldom reach the
lower atmosphere. These primary rays
collide with atomic nuclei in the iono¬
sphere or in the stratosphere to produce
showers of secondary rays, composed of
atomic fragments, which themselves have
higher energies than any man-made parti¬
cles. The properties of the primary parti¬
cles can be deduced from the secondary
ones in the showers but their origin cannot.
It is not known from whence they come.
It is possible that they or some of them
originate on the sun or that their passage
to earth is strongly influenced by the sun.
This again means correla¬
tion with many other
ionospheric observations.
But cosmic rays are re¬
latively rare and do not
cause any mass effects ;
next page
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
WHERE THE SKY
IS BLACK (Continued)
they must be studied individually. And be¬
cause they change their nature as they
crash downward, they need to be measured
and identified at different altitudes. They
have been caught on mountain tops, under
the surface of deep lakes and in the depths
of a few mines. Balloons have been used
to study them to the reachable heights. But
all this is too low and a cosmic-ray counter
is needed that can ascend into the iono¬
sphere. For this reason rocketry has
become an invaluable instrument. It is a
poor rocket these days that cannot climb
50 miles into the lower ionosphere and
they have been sent up higher than 100
miles. During the Year rockets will be
increasingly used to make brief excursions
into these high levels and to bring back
cosmic ray data. But more hope for
valuable cosmic-ray information is borne
by the artificial satellite which will cruise
even beyond the ionosphere for a period of
weeks, as described in the final article of
this issue.
The Soviet Union and the United States
have developed rocketry to a high degree.
The disadvantage of the rocket is that it
makes a vertical penetration of the iono¬
sphere at a single spot and does not remain
more than a brief moment at the top of its
trajectory. Nevertheless important data have
been collected. In a recent paper in the
Journal of the British Interplanetary Society
S.M. Poloskov and B.A. Mirtov of the
U.S.S.R. describe a method of obtaining
samples of air and of measuring wind
velocities at altitudes of 50 miles and above
by fitting a rocket with a series of mortars
inside the shell which explode at prede¬
termined altitudes and eject vacuum bottles
to "some distance" from the rocket itself,
hence from its combustion gases, where
their valves open to collect samples of the
air to be parachuted down for recovery and
analysis.
Similarly, other mortars in the rocket
eject cannisters containing 33 pounds of
smoke-forming materials which are explo¬
ded at a distance from the rocket to form
large smoke-clouds. Five such cannisters
are exploded at different altitudes but the
speed of the rocket makes them appear
almost simultaneously in a vertical pattern
which can be accurately measured from
the ground with telescopes to determine
their altitude and the speed of their motion
with the ionospheric winds. Such obser¬
vations have confirmed that these winds
are of high velocity, always of the order of
200 to 300 feet per second, or about 150
miles per hour. The direction of the
observed winds is from east to west in
summer and from north to south in
winter.
Another method for estimating iono¬
spheric winds is by the study of meteors.
These tiny wanderers through space, prob¬
ably the debris of comets or ejected from
comets during their passage around the sun,
enter the ionosphere by the hundreds of
millions daily, most of them mere specks
of dust. They have had little scientific
study except for the larger ones that survive
the fall through the atmosphere and strike
the earth. But scientists of the Soviet
Union have set up a comprehensive pro¬
gramme for their study, which is described
in the following article by Dr. V. V.
Fedynsky. a distinguished member of the
U.S.S.R. National Committee for the
International Geophysical Year.
28
METEORS
Tiny wanderers
through space
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
Meteors, visible to the naked eye as shooting-stars,
blaze up and go out at a height of from 70 to
35 miles above the surface of the earth when iron
or stone particles meteoric bodies from interplanetary
space collide at a high velocity (from seven to 45 miles
per second) with the atmosphere. The meteoric body is
heated to a temperature of several thousand degrees
and becomes highly incandescent; a column of ionized
gas, the meteoric trail, is formed about it.
The diameter of the trail is several yards, and its
length is usually from 15 to 18 miles. As it gradually
disperses, the meteoric trail introduces electrically
charged particles into the E layer of the ionosphere,
thereby changing its composition. This trail can easily
be registered by radar. By eye observation, and also
with the help of radar, it is possible to follow the
displacement of the meteoric trail, and thus to deter¬
mine the direction and velocity of the wind at a height
of 60 miles. From the height and velocity of a meteor's
flight, and also the intensity of the light it emits, it is
possible to calculate the pressure, density and temper¬
ature of the upper layers of the air in the region of
its flight.
The programme for the observation of meteors in the
U.S.S.R. was drawn up at international scientific
the mechanics of the emission of energy by meteoric
bodies when they come into collision with the atmo¬
sphere. In order to do this, visual registration of the
meteors by unaided eye observation, and also with
short-focus binoculars of large field of view, will be
practised in conjunction with the radar observations of
meteors. Amateur astronomers who are interested in
astronomy but do not make a profession of it will thus
take part in scientific research.
Bright meteors will be photographed with cameras of
high light-gathering power. Photographic observation
of meteors can only be carried on when the sky is
dark and clear, best of all in the south. In the U.S.S.R.,
such observations have been carried on for a long time
now by the Astronomical Observatory of the Tadjik
Academy of Sciences in Stalinabad, and the Astro-
physical Laboratory of the Institute of Geophysics of
the Turkmen Academy of Sciences in Ashkhabad. By
the beginning of the Year these observatories will have
received more powerful meteoric photographic appar7
atus and set up observation points in the mountains
outside the cities mentioned above. The Astronomical
observatories of the Kiev and Odessa Universities in
the Ukraine have again organized the photographic
observation of meteors.
Hundreds of millions of meteors most of them mere
specks of dust enter the earth's atmosphere every day
and burn out in the ionosphere which acts as a shield
against this meteoric bombardment. They have had
relatively little scientific study except for the larger ones
that survive the fall through the atmosphere But scientists
of the Soviet Union have set up a comprehensive program¬
me for observing meteors during the I.G.Y. linked up
with similar studies in other countries. Opposite page,
(top photo) very bright meteor, visible to the naked eye as a
"shooting star", recorded by the Stalinabad Astronomical
Observatory. Snake-like form of a meteoric train seen at
Penza in. central Russia (bottom photo). The wind at the
height of 40 to 55 miles where it was observed varied in
direction at different levels, thus bending the train to form
a figure "3". Left, meteor "patrol" at Stalinabad with
cameras to photograph meteoric activity during the I.G.Y.
U.S.S.R. official photos
conferences in Leningrad and Manchester in 1954, at
which Czech and British scientists made suggestions
on the study of meteors during the International Geo¬
physical Year. The Soviet observations will be carried
on parallel with observations in Czechoslovakia, the
German Democratic Republic, Great Britain, the United
States, Canada and other countries.
First in importance is to keep a constant check on the
number of meteors and the nature of the ionized track
they leave behind them. This work is to be done by
radar installations in Kazan, Kharkov, Stalinabad, and
Tomsk. Meteoric activity is to be registered day and
night on all days set for universal geophysical
observation, that is : during the World Meteorological
Intervals, during the World Days, and on the Meteor
Days when the earth comes into collision with large
meteoric showers. Observations are also needed on such
ordinary days, immediately preceding or following these
intervals, as are required for comparison. In all, the
radar installations are to be working about 100 days a
year. This will provide sufficiently complete data on
the earth's collisions with meteoric matter in cosmic
space. It will give a clear enough idea of the nature
of the action of meteors on the ionosphere and on the
connexion between meteoric ionization and the anomal¬
ous audibility of radio broadcasts and visibility of
television broadcasts.
It is important to compare the intensity of ionization
with the luminosity of meteors in order to determine
In order to determine the altitude and velocity of a
meteor's flight, the meteor must be photographed with
two cameras set up from 12 to 25 miles apart. At one
of these points the apparent velocity of the meteor's
flight must be determined with the aid of a rotating
shutter of the "windmill" type. The obturator covers
the lens of the camera from 30 to 50, and even 100 times
a second. The trail of a meteor photographed through
an obturator shows as a broken line. A double photo¬
graph of a meteor (combined print of two photographs
of the same meteor taken from different places), makes
it possible to calculate the height, velocity and slowing
up or tne meteor, as well as its magnitude. Having all
these data, it is not difficult to determine the physical
properties of the upper layers of the atmosphere along
the path of the meteor the density, pressure and
temperature of the air.
The winds in the ionosphere can easily be observed
with the aid of radar. To do this, observations are
made of the shifting in the position of the meteoric
trail which produces radio echoes. The trains of very
bright meteors can also be observed visually through a
telescope, or successive photographs can be taken of
them which register their movement in space. Observa¬
tion of the movement of meteor trails is to be carried
out in Ashkhabad and Stalinabad.
The above article is based on a special report prepared for THE
UNESCO courier by Dr. V.V. Fedynsky, a member of the U.S.S.R.
National Committee for the I.G.Y.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
MAN-MADE SATELLITE
the first step into outer space
The most ambitious project of the International Geo¬
physical Year and the most imaginative project in
the history of science will reach out into space,
possibly as far as 1,800 miles above the earth's surface,
to observe and report on conditions there. The launching
of a 20-inch sphere, filled with electronic instruments and
transmitters to a total weight of about 22 pounds, and
setting it into an orbit around the earth at a velocity of
approximately 18,000 miles per hour will be an incom¬
parable achievement-^-not because it is spectacular, but
because it is precisely planned, mathematically predicted
in advance, and because it requires the use of many
fabulous devices that have been perfected only recently,
a focussing of many sciences and the integrated co-opera¬
tion of thousands of experts.
No one man will get the credit or make the first voyage
into unknown space, as Columbus did, or Magellan. This
present explorer 'will be a superhuman electronic brain
that will go where no- man can go, yet will do man's
bidding, investigate and report continuously to its creators
LONG-PLAYING ROCKET. Earth satellite tobe launched from the
United States will be used by I.G.Y. scientists in two basic ways. First
it will provide a target to be trackedby radio and opticallyfrom the
ground. Second it will collect, memorize and transmit to the earth
data on the upper regions through which it passes. Opposite page,
(upper photo), cylinder containing electronic equipment is inserted in
outer shell of satellite. Closely packed instruments represent almost
half its total weight of about 22 pounds. These are revealed (lower
photo) as satellite model is lifted out of its plastic shell. In fore¬
ground are removable plastic antennas. Above, the miniaturised ins-
30
USIS photos
truments which will make the first sustained observations in space.
It is for this reason that satellite has been labelled the "long-playing
rocket". (I) Pressure gauge will tell if meteorite pierces metal shell of
satellite. (2) Meter will measure intensity of sun's ultra-violet rays.
(3) Solar cell (on left) will harness sun power to produce electrical
impulse as satellite emerges from darkness into daylight on each succes¬
sive orbit, resetting memory unit that stores data for transmission to
earth. Erosion gauge (right) will record any damage to shining,
golden surface of sphere by meteorites. (4) "Minitrack" radio trans¬
mitter, equipped with mercury batteries, has range of 4,000 miles.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
and masters far below, glide through silent space for a few
weeks, then end its meteoric career in a brilliant flash.
Why ? Because man wants to know. Every boy in
every land throughout the ages has gazed on the clouds
and blue sky, and on the stars at night, and has wonder¬
ed what is beyond. During the centuries of ignorance
and mysticism men filled the heavens with visions.
Then, with increasing knowledge, the air became a mate¬
rial substance and the blue of the sky lost its reality to
become only an optical effect of refracted light, and
beyond that nothing, cold, empty space interspersed
with remote stars and galaxies. But that was a passing
stage.
Because men have ever wanted to know more which is
their chief distinction from the
animals space is no longer cal¬
led empty. The atmosphere
gradually thins out; it has no
surface like that of the ocean.
There is enough of it even a
thousand miles up to give a
slowing friction to the propos¬
ed satellite. There are enough
particles of solid matter cruising
independently through space to
show the instant flash of a me¬
teor, heated by this friction of
our air and burned to dust,
almost anywhere and at any
hour of night and millions of
them, in all, every 24 hours.
There are the rays called '"cos¬
mic" to imply that they come
from remote regions of the uni¬
verse, though no one knows
from where. They are minute
fragments of atoms, fragments
of atomic nuclei, and "funda¬
mental" particles that are still
smaller, all of them crashing
into the top of the atmosphere
with incredible energy. Then
there are the tremendous
showers of electrons that are
ejected from the sun during its
colossal storms and are pro¬
jected to us across 93 million
miles of space. And there is
sunlight itself. All these im¬
pinge upon the earth in a
constant barrage but only the
dumb, helpless atoms of the
outermost air receive their
impact and message.
The proposed satellite will be
a temporary observatory for
them all, limited in its powers
as in its existence, but far more
than earthbound man has ever
before used. It will police the
topmost sky. What it discovers
and reveals to science will no
doubt be fragmentary, and will
bring more questions than ans¬
wers, but it is an essential step
toward the eventual conquest of
space.
Both the United States and
the Soviet Union have an- '
nounced plans for launching
earth satellites but the United
States has given full detailed
publicity to its programme so that this article is devoted to
the American project. The launching site is at Cape
Canaveral on the long Florida peninsula that extends the
Atlantic coast of the United States into the Caribbean Sea.
The satellite itself is small but the rocket system to lift it
on high and to give it an adequate velocity in its orbit is
massive. Its total length is 72 feet, composed of three
stages. The design, construction arid launching of the
rocket is in the hands of the U.S. Naval-Research labora¬
tory which is spending $110 million on the project. The
large first-stage rocket will have a thrust of 27,000 pounds
and will propel the entire vehicle upwards with a gradual
inclination of the path eastward over the Atlantic Ocean.
When its fuel is exhausted the first-stage rocket will drop
off into the sea and the second-stage motor will be ignited.
This will drive the remaining vehicle to an altitude of
about 140 miles and it will then coast, without power, an¬
other 700 miles on an inclined path to reach the desired
altitude of between 250 and 300 miles. At this altitude
the nose cone that protects the sphere of the satellite itself
will be dropped, a pinwheel array of small jets will spin
the vehicle to stabilise its flight, and then the third-stage
rocket will give another burst of power to propel the
satellite into its desired orbit at a velocity of 18,000 miles
per hour.
At this speed the centrifugal force of Its horizontal mo- .
tion around the earth will be sufficient to counteract the
force of gravity at that altitude so that it will continue to
circle the earth in its orbit exactly as the moon does at a
much greater distance of 250,000
miles. If the satellite were per¬
fectly launched it could attain a
circular orbit. But such accurate
control is not possible and the
actual orbit will probably be an
ellipse and the distance of the
satellite from the earth will
vary from 2-300 miles to 800-
1,500 miles. The orbit will not
be exactly to the east, parallel
to the earth's equator but at
an angle with it so that its
position as it goes round the
earth will vary from 35 degrees
of latitude north of the equator
to 35 degrees south of it. Thus
in its various circuits a band
about 70 degrees wide will be
covered by the satellite and
scientists of a large number of
nations will be able to observe
and measure it.
At a velocity of 18,000 miles, it
will not bè able to encircle the
earth in an hour, for the cir¬
cumference of the earth is
24,000 miles. It will pass
completely around the earth In
approximately one and a half
hours.
The most important informa¬
tion to be furnished by the sat¬
ellite will come from tracing its
orbit. Its position will be
carefully measured and timed
from many points on the earth's
surface and its orbit will then
be precisely calculated. The
first problem will be to find the
satellite in the sky early in its
flight. This cannot be done by
the accurate cameras that will
later fix its position because
such cameras can cover only a
small portion of the sky and
must be aimed in advance at an
area through which the satellite
will later pass. The original
location of the satellite and a
preliminary calculation, of its
orbit will be done by timing of
the radio-waves that are cons¬
tantly emitted from the sat¬
ellite. Radio receiving stations
will be situated along its path
to detect the direction from
which these signals come.
This system is known as Mi-
nitrack. Each minitrack station will have two sets of re¬
ceivers, 200 metres apart on the ground. The difference in
the time required for a signal from the small transmitter
in the satellite to reach the two receivers will give a fairly
accurate measurement of the location of a satellite in the
sky One set of two receivers will measure its position
in the east-west direction and the other set its position
in the north-south direction. Such stations will be located
at Washington D.C. and Savannah, Georgia, in the U.S.A. ;
at Havana, Cuba ; at Antigua in the British
West Indies; Quito, Ecuador ; Lima, Peru ;
Antofagasta, Chile ; Santiago, Chile ; San Cont'd
Diego, California, U.S.A. ; and one in Aus- on
tralia. nixt page
It is possible, however, that the radio-
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
MAN-MADE
SATELLITE
(Continued)
FLYING OBSERVATORY 1 ,200 MILES HIGH
transmitter within the satellite will somehow fail to
operate. In that case the minitrack stations would be
useless. To guard against this contingency large numbers
of volunteer sky searchers, scattered all over the world,
will be on duty with powerful binoculars to locate it.
With groups of such binoculars at many points, a large
region of the heavens can be covered and the satellite can
be kept under observation. Thus the orbit can be approxi¬
mately established even without the radio-transmitter.
When the orbit has been approximately established by the
minitrack measurements of the binocular observers, pre¬
cise observations of its positions will be made by a series
of special "'Schmidt" cameras that are provided with
timing devices so accurate that they will measure the
instant of taking the photograph of the sky within a
thousandth of a second. Such optical observing stations
will be established in New Mexico and Florida in the
U.S.A. ; and Bloemfontein, South Africa ; Mauna Loa,
Hawaii ; Tokyo, Japan ; Curacao, Netherlands Antilles ;
Cadiz, Spain; Tehran, Iran; Arequipa, Peru; Villa Dolores,
Argentina; and in India and Australia.
The reason for the high accuracy of the orbital observa¬
tions and calculations is not merely to establish the
orbit itself but to observe its small irregularities and
changes in the velocity of the satellite. These will give
important further information. A gradual reduction of
velocity is expected as a result of the friction of the thin
upper air. Very little is now known of the density of the
air at that height but the geometry of the satellite's orbit
and observations of its flight will permit calculations of
the air density.
If the composition of the earth were quite uniform its
gravitational . pull, or gravitational field, would also be
uniform. In that case the orbit of the satellite would be
a simple, regular ellipse.. But irregularities in its orbit,
knov/n as perturbations, will undoubtedly be observed by
the use of accurate Schmidt cameras. Such variations in
the orbit will permit calculations of the distribution of
mass within the earth and these, in turn, should yield
information on the composition of the earth's crust. This
may prove to be one of the most valuable results of the
whole project.
But there is more. The earth is not a sphere but is
flattened at the poles into the oblate shape of a spheroid.
The exact magnitude of this distortion needs to be known
to permit accurate determinations of latitude and
longitude. Here too knowledge of the exact path that the
satellite takes will give valuable information.
Finally, the orbital measurements will also give informa¬
tion on the electrical conditions of the upper atmo¬
sphere, i.e. on the number of ions, or electrical charges,
in the air. This requires a double observation of the orbit :
one by the Schmidt cameras, the other by the radio signals
that come from the transmitter in the satellite. If the
upper air were not electrified the radio signals would
come to earth in straight lines. But when they go through
electrified layers they will be bent, or refracted, much as
a beam of light is refracted when it passes from air to
water or passes through the glass in a lens. Thus when
the angle of the radio beam is accurately measured, it will
not be correct, because of this refraction. But light waves
are not bent, or refracted, by electrical charges. So the
altitude of the satellite as measured by the optical cameras,
will be correct. The difference between the optical
measurement and the radio measurement will indicate the
RADIO SIGNALS will be used to track artificial satellite as it sweeps
over the earth at 18,000 miles per hour. Drawing, right, shows
arrangement of supersensitive ground receivers, called Minitrack, which
will be located in a chain in the United States and South America to
pick up signals from satellite's miniature radio transmitter. (See map,
32
VJ wiS
USIS photos
pages 18/19). Accurate tracking of satellite from the ground offers
a unique opportunity for a closer study of the shape of the earth.
Scientists have developed a variety of equipment for launching and
tracking the satellite. Left, telemeter antenna at a satellite launching
area used to monitor test performances of rocket launching vehicles.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1957
ELEVEN-TON
ROCKET FOR
22-LB. SATELLITE
The earth satellites In the I.G.Y. pro¬
gramme of the U.S.A. will be launched
from a huge, three-stage rocket called
the Vanguard (upper left), 72 ft. long
and weighing I I tons (satellite it will
carry weighs about 22 lbs). Idea of Its
size is given by human figure drawn in
proportion alongside. Drawing, lower
left, shows the stages in the flight of the
Vanguard rocket vehicle. The first-stage
rocket propels the vehicle from the
launching point (I) to an altitude of
36 miles (2) and then falls away back
to earth. The second-stage rocket now
takes over and carries the vehicle, first
under power and later on coasting flight,
to a height of about 300 miles. The
second-stage separates and the third-
stage now boosts the speed to 18,000
miles per hour at which point the
satellite is launched into its orbit. At
(4) third-stage rocket falls away.
USIS photos
amount of refraction by the electrical ions and will permit
a calculation of the electrical charge characteristics of
the thin air in the ionosphere.
These are all items of information that can be obtained
from the ground by the observation of the satellite's orbit.
But the satellite itself contains instruments for making
observations which will be automatically reported to the
ground by radio while it is in flight. Both the space
inside the small sphere and the permissible weight are
very limited. But among the experiments that the satellite
may conduct are a number that are of great interest to
men of science.
The most important is the measurement of the invisi¬
ble energy that reaches the earth from the sun. It
is not visible to human eyes because the light¬
waves are too short. They are shorter than those of
purple or violet light, hence are ¡known as ultra-violet.
Much of the radiation can hardly be called light at all,
with waves as short as those of the penetrating X-rays.
This radiation is absorbed in the upper layers of the
atmosphere where it is transformed, causes ionization and
the strange luminous effect that is called airglow. Even
tually the energy is either reflected into space or reaches
the lower atmosphere where it affects the weather and
the climate. The satellite gives a unique opportunity
to study this energy at the edge of space, before it has
been absorbed and transformed. What is more, this
flying observatory is expected to stay aloft for at least
two weeks and will measure the variations of the solar
radiation during all its flight. If in this period there
should be a solar flare, a great outburst of energy
from a "sunspot", the data provide by the instruments in
the satellite "would be of the greatest possible scientific
interest", says the U.S. National Committee.
Another primary function of the satellite is to explore
the motion of electrical charges in the air at that height,
and the flow of thin but very large electric currents. It
is supposed that these are responsible for the rapid
fluctuations of the earth's magnetism. Since the satellite
will be cruising over a very large part of the earth's surface
every day and, in its elliptical orbit, will vary in height
from 200 miles to 1,200 miles, it will make
an overall map of electrical conditions and
presumably will furnish clues to the origin
of "magnetic storms." It would be of
great practical value to understand these
storms enough to permit predicting them.
Cont'd
on
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A GIRDLE ROUND THE
EARTH IN 90 MINUTES
Scientists in the Soviet Union have announced that they will
launch at least one artificial earth satellite during the Interna¬
tional Geophysical Year. Of spherical form, the Soviet satellite
will be carried aloft in the nose of a multi-stage launching vehicle.
Once propelled into its orbit, the satellite will girdle the earth
at altitudes varying between 120 and 300 miles at a speed of
between 15,000 and 18,000 miles per hour. This speed will
bring it around the globe every 90 minutes so that in 24 hours
it will make 16 complete circles. Recording instruments in
the satellite will make observations which will be radioed to
specially equipped ground stations. The rocket which will
launch the satellite into its orbit will be similar to the one
shown here, which has been specially designed for studies in the
upper atmosphere. Left, Soviet rocket being launched and
(below) after its return to earth with parachute still attached.
Official Soviet photos
MAN-MADE SATELLITE (Continued)
Cosmic rays are another mystery which has never been
investigated at a level above the atmosphere where they
are still unaffected by collision with earthly atoms. The
satellite will contain a counter for these rays to measure
their total number. After two weeks of such counting over
a wide area of the earth the results are expected at least
to be of sufficient importance to justify more elaborate
study of cosmic rays by later satellites.
Information on the total heat received from the sun
and on its variation, which is the fundamental factor in
weather phenomena, will also be valuable in an under¬
standing of the major weather changes and possibly in
the prediction of future hurricanes and typhoons. Also
the satellite will observe the cloud cover of the earth
continuously and on a world-wide scale, thus providing
another basis for weather studies.
Finally, there will be many routine observations of minor
significance, such as a microphone system to record the
number of collisions with tiny meteorites, pressure
measurements to record any leakage in case of a puncture,
34
and observations on corrosion and the temperature of the
shell of the Satellite.
The date for the launching of this superb experiment,
this supreme test of man's present command of his world
and its forces, this first small venture to the borders of
cosmic space, has not yet been set. But it will be in 1958,
a year which will go down in history for that reason, just
as 1939 will forever be remembered for the first observed
fission of a few single atoms of uranium in a peaceful res¬
earch laboratory in Berlin. The superhuman but captive
explorer will not survive to be shown to future generations
in a museum of science. In a few weeks two to four
probably, six perhaps the friction of whatever air there
is so high up will slow it down, decrease its centrifugal
force so that gravity will slowly pull it downward, then
faster into thicker air and more friction and higher
temperature until every speck of it is vaporized and burns
into dust. The man-made moon will end as a meteorite
and disappear in a flash of brilliant light, a blaze of well-
earned glory.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
MAN MEASURES
THE UNIVERSE
Since the announcement in the May,
I 957 issue of The Unesco Courier that
copies of Unesco's pamphlet, "Man
Measures The Universe", could be
obtained free of charge by subscribers,
some 5,000 readers have requested
and received copies of it. As stocks
are now exhausted we regret that no
new requests can be met. The pamph¬
let describes in detail Unesco's fourth
travelling exhibition, "Man Measures
the Universe" which is now visiting
Danzig, after being on view in Paris,
Liège, Brussels, Ghent, Madrid, The
Hague, Warsaw and Cracow. After its
Polish tour the exhibition will go to
Czechoslovakia in December. When it
closes at the end of the year it will have
been viewed by some 500,000 people.
s WISS & SWEDISH SWOP JOBS:
Eight girls employed by co-operative
stores in Zurich have been studying dili¬
gently after the day's work for the past
year, learning Swedish. And now their
chance has come to use the new words,
for recently they set off for a year's work
in Stockholm. The Swiss girls, whose ages
range from 19 to 24, are well prepared
for their new jobs in grocery shops of the
Swedish Co-operative Federation, for they
have also studied Swedish trade instruc¬
tions, price lists and commodity lists.
Meanwhile, six Stockholm girls have been
studying German in preparation for taking
up jobs in Zurich as one-year "guests" of
the Swiss Co-operative Federation. These
exchanges are sponsored by the Interna¬
tional Co-operative Alliance under a plan
initiated by Unesco to enable men and
women in many walks of life to work
abroad at their own trade for periods of
three to twelve months. The over-all plan
for the exchange is operated through inter¬
national trade unions and co-operative or¬
ganizations working with Unesco. It is li¬
mited to persons in European member states
of Unesco. Applications are received by
the worker's own co-operative or trade
union. Unesco pays for travel between
countries.
NUCLEAR POWER AT HOME:
Power from the atom will soon provide
electricity for towns and villages in
France's chateau country. Work has
already started on the site of a new
nuclear power plant to be constructed
near Chinon in the Loire Valley. The
plant, which is to start operating in
1959, will be the first -in France to
produce "nuclear" current for domestic
and industrial purposes. Another station
is in the south-west, but it provides
energy for research purposes only. The
Loire site was chosen for the new plant
because the Valley has no hydro-electric
resources.
l^ITY UNDER A CITY: An ancient
city wall, 3,300 years old, has been dis¬
covered at Chengchow by an archaeolo¬
gical team now exploring the site. This
is the oldest city wall found in China and
has been dated to the early Shang dynasty
(1700 BC to 1200 BC). Most parts of the
city wall (between 13 and 55 feet wide)
as well as the ancient city itself lie buried
beneath Chengchow city. Over 10,000
ancient buildings and relics have been
found around the buried city in the past
three years, including tombs, workshops,
tools, weapons and works of art.
UNESCO AIDS YOUTH TRAVEL:
A world-wide programme for educa¬
tional travel by selected members of
youth groups this year has been put into
operation by Unesco. Forty young
people of 32 countries will go abroad
in the 1957 operation of the unesco
Youth Travel Grant plan, many of
them on long journeys, for study of
out-of-school educational methods for
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe to THE UNESCO COURIER today - $ 2.50; 8/-;
400 francs per year (12 Issues)
Fill in this subscription blank and mail it with your cheque or money order
to our local agent in your country listed on page 25
Please enter my subscription for THE UNESCO COURIER
One year $2.50; 8/-; 400 French francs Cheque /Money Order enclosed
Two years $4.50;I6/-; 800Frenchfrancsü Please bill me
Name..
Address	
City Country	Profession..
youth. This year's programme includes
travel for study in Europe, Africa,
Southeast Asia, the Far East, Australia,
the West Indies, Central and South
America and North America. Some of
those travelling under the plan will go
to international work camps and to
holiday camps. Others will study Red
Cross youth organizational work,
student movements, youth hostels, young
worker activities, youth legislation and
governmental programmes for youth.
Youth organizations will receive the
travellers, for training periods of from
3 to 12 months. Those selected hold
responsible posts in their organizations,
and are to use in their own countries
the knowledge and experience gained on
their journeys. They range in age from
20 to 30. Their study travel is from
region to region not merely to near
countries and their transportation is
paid in full or in part by unesco.
J.VORY TREASURE RESTORED:
How the priceless collection of ancient
ivory art objects of the Sakiz Treasure of
Iran was saved through scientific restora¬
tion was recently described by a Unesco
expert who worked for six months in the
Museum of Teheran on these relics from
Kurdistan, believed to be more than
2,500 years old. Friedrich Smoorcnburg,
Dutch specialist, who had been assigned by
Unesco to assist the Iranian Government in
the restoration work, reported that about
100 pieces of ivory, mostly in plate car¬
vings, could not have lasted more than
another year. Buried for 2,655 years, the
ivories had been reduced to calcium which
under slight pressure would become dust.
Now, after treatment with humidity and
carbonic acid, the pieces have become
strong and hard again. And by the use
of a cellulose compound as an adhesive,
the elements of the plates and the few
sculptures have been joined together to
form the ancient designs. They are now
protected with paraffin. The ivories were
part of a chest-full of treasure including
gold and jewels which was discovered by
shepherds a few years ago.
FORTHCOMING
PRICE INCREASE
The Unesco Courier announces with
regret that in view of ever-increasing
production costs it will no longer be able
to avoid a slight increase in price. On
and after November I, 1957, the an¬
nual subscription rate will be increased
to:
S3. 00 l0/-stg. 500 frs
and the price per copy will go up to
30 cents [/-stg. 50 frs
All subscriptions received before
November I, 1957 and accompanied
by payment will be accepted at the old
rates, including renewals for subscrip¬
tions whose expiration falls in the
12 months following November I,
1957. Renewals for unexpired sub¬
scriptions can be accepted only for a
maximum period of one year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
FLAMING GASES
SPEWED OUT
FROM THE SUN
On July 3, 1957third day of the Interna¬
tional Geophysical Yeara gigantic flare
occurred on the sun. (Solar flares are ex¬
plosive events which spew out gaseous
matter into space, sometimes rising to a
height of half a million miles at a speed of
500 miles a second). The event was pho¬
tographed at the Meudon Observatory near
Paris, by a method which eliminates all
the light radiations from the sun except
one, in this case the H-alpha hydrogen line,
by which the photographs were taken. Top
photo, taken at 7.22 hours (Universal Time)
shows start of flare on right. Second,
taken 40 minutes later, reveals state of flare
just after its maximum phase. Meudon
Observatory, chosen as world centre for
collection of solar observations concerning
chromospheric flares and the sudden dis¬
appearance of solar flare prominences dur¬
ing the I.G.Y., will receive reports from
some 50 stations in all parts of the world.
Photos Meudon Observatory, France
]]>
</page>
</document>
