<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068051eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
*<Ç|
aw?
h§
1 ^fe
Vi -»{
if^fli -
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
'
K*»!7.. j^> JBI
&- "^5
IM *'*
« *:
Vwr.
'*
*- . ^<3&
SP
fiST^
v "-i
s%m*>
*^>
**$£
L*W
^
..&
V V
3
bbbbhbbbbbpP*
'W .V**.'
va^SSfc.
!S»
A«.'.ft*
F« »»"*' » ii g?-: **>
«r-
PRIEST. Detail of stele at
Bonampak, Chiapas, Mexico.
Mayan art. (© Gisèle Freund)
jÈpL_ ' _ t~ -*v ^l.yjiàmw'
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
^"" A WINDOW
Cour
DECEMBER 1957
I OTH YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 THE UNESCO WORLD ART SERIES
4 BONAMPAK: PAINTED WALLS OF THE MAYAS
Mexico's Pre-Hispanic paintings
By Yvonne Tabbush
12 ICON PAINTINGS
The triumph of ancient Russian art
By Victor Lasareff
16 RUBLEV AND THEOPHANES
Two great Russian artists
By Mikhael Alpatov
19 SPECIAL COLOUR PAGES
Six pages, including front and back covers, of full colour
plates of masterpieces from Mexico, the U.S.S.R., Ceylon
& Czechoslovakia
23 SHRINE OF ART ATOP THE LION'S ROCK
Temple paintings from Ceylon
By Dr. S. Paranavitana
30 GOLDEN AGE IN CZECH ART
Sculpture, painting & manuscripts of the Middle Ages
By Vladimir Novotny
37 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
38 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
The colour pages in this issue have been made possible thanks
to the co-operation of the New York Graphic Society, publishers
of the Unesco World Art Series. They were specially printed
in Milan, Italy, by Amilcare Pizzi. All illustrations in the
issue which have been taken from Unesco Art Albums are
copyright and may not be reproduced without permission
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9 Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
Ronald Fenton
Alexandre Leventis
: Jorge Carrera Andrade
: Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. A small Japanese version is published In Tokyo
and a Danish version in Copenhagen. The United States of America edition
is distributed by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue,
New York 22, N.Y., Pennsylvania £-0851. Second-class mail privileges author¬
ized at New York, N.Y. (M.C. 57.1.1 19 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
credit is given to THE UNESCO COURIER and two voucher copies are sent
to the editor. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00 ¡ I 0/- stg. ; 500 French francs or equi¬
valent.
COVER PHOTO
MICHAEL THE ARCHANGEL, de¬
tail of a large, early 1 5th-century
wooden Icon. For its colour and
composition it is considered one of
the masterpieces of the Moscow School
of painters. Now in the Archangel
cathedral of the Kremlin, Moscow.
Unesco Album "U.S.S.R."
THE UNESCO WORLD
ART SERIES
The UNESCO WORLD ART SERIES is a unique publishing
venture, jointly launched in 1954 by New York Graphic Society
and Unesco with the co-operation of the various governments.
It has resulted to date in the publication of ten books considered
by authorities as among the most faithful art reproductions ever
issued. Each book contains 32 high-fidelity extra-large colour
plates, mostly 15 by 11 inches (38 by 28 cm), plus several black
and white illustrations in the text. The page size is 18-4 by
13 inches (14 by 33 cm). Each volume is published in five
languages, and often a sixth that of the country of origin.
The price per volume is $16.50 (U.S.A.) Colour plates from any
books may be purchased individually : price, $2.00 each.
New additions to the series
CEYLON : Paintings from Temple, Shrine and Rock
U.S.S.R. : Early Russian Icons
Previously published
INDIA : Paintings from Ajanta Caves
EGYPT : Paintings from Tombs and Temples
AUSTRALIA : Aboriginal Paintings - Arnhem Land
YUGOSLAVIA : Mediaeval Frescoes
NORWAY : Paintings from the Stave Churches
IRAN : Persian Miniatures - Imperial Library
SPAIN : Romanesque Paintings
MASACCIO : Frescoes in Florence (Not part of the series)
To appear shortly
MEXICO : Pre-Hispanic Paintings
CZECHOSLOVAKIA : Romanesque and Gothic Illuminated
Manuscripts
JAPAN : Ancient Buddhist Paintings
Unesco world art series - International Agents: Argentina:
Carlos Hirsch, Buenos Aires; Canada: Burns and Mac-Eachern,
Toronto; Denmark: G.E.C. Gad, Copenhagen; England: The
Zwemmer Gallery, London; Finland: Akademiska Bokhandeln,
Helsinki; France, Belgium, Luxembourg: Etablissements Braun
et Cié, Mulhouse-Dornach, Haut-Rhin, France; Germany: R. Piper
and Co., Munich; Holland: Meulenhoff and Co., Amsterdam;
Italy: Silvana Editoriale d'arte, Milan; Spain: Sociedad General
Española de Librería, Madrid; Sweden: Importbokhandeln,
Stockholm; Switzerland: Office du Livre, S.A., Fribourg; Uru¬
guay: Ibana, Montevideo.
volumes also available directly from New York Graphic
Society, 95 east putnam avenue, Greenwich, conn., u.s.a.
Please do NOT send your orders to Unesco.
(Discounts for Members of Educational and Cultural Organizations
available from National Distributors)
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Agréât name has been added to the art lover's vocabulary
within the past ten years Bonampak, home of the most
important vestige of Maya painting yet discovered.
Bonampak, meaning "painted walls", is the name given a
unique temple in the heart of the Mexican jungle by the late
Dr. Sylvanus G. Morley, authority on Maya culture. The
murals," which cover the walls of three rooms making up the
temple, have been hailed as the finest pre-Conquest paintings
on the American continent and are considered to rival in
brilliance the famous. wall decorations of the early Egyptians
or the cave paintings of Ajanta in India. Done during the
earliest Maya empire (317 to 978 A.D.) the paintings
constitute one of the most significant discoveries in the long
history of Maya research.
Like many archaeological finds in the past, Bonampak owes
its recent discovery to an accident.
In the spring of 1946 a photographer named Giles
G. Healey was commissioned to make a documentary film on
"The Mayas through the Ages" to include both Maya
antiquities and the living descendants of the ancient Mayas.
Healey went to Yucatan and the Guatemalan highlands where
\_/~~\ / " ^v__s-i
\j \ \ «=*!,
) GOLFO DE M \
\ ( MEXICO
\ v
v ° \ n
J^^Z
^^*ON*MPAK kr~]j
^
OCÉANO ^"^V/ *~
PACIFICO ^	CrU7Ï
he filmed Indians still speaking Maya languages and dialects
but all of whom have absorbed Occidental culture in varying
degrees. He then decided to penetrate the virtually unexplored
Chiapas jungle near the Guatemalan border of southeastern
Mexico to secure motion pictures of a rapidly vanishing tribe
of Indians, known as the Lacandons, purported to be the last
pagan descendants of the great Maya civilization of twelve
centuries ago, and who had had practically no contact with
the outside world.
In the dense tropical forest of Chiapas, Healey encountered
a group of the long-haired, white-robed Lacandons. He soon
observed that at recurring intervals the men vanished into
the bush and remained absent for several days. He believed
that they were practising an attenuated form of the ancient
Maya religion as described by historians at the time of the
Spanish Conquest, and that they made periodic pilgrimages
to worship in ancient temples of their ancestors. He
persuaded two of the Lacandons whose friendship he had
won to lead him to this, area deep in their country.
On May 13, 1946, he reached a group of ancient Maya
temples hidden in the jungle. As he entered one temple,
virtually buried in the trees and thickets that had grown
through its crumbling masonry, he suddenly came face to
face with an extraordinary sight: a series of painted murals
covering the walls of three narrow high-vaulted rooms from
floor to ceiling. Despite the layer of lime, deposited by
moisture which had trickled down from the limestone roof for
centuries, the paintings were amazingly preserved.
Healey realized that he had made a spectacular discovery
for never before had a structure with rooms entirely covered
with murals been found in the Maya area. He immediately
reported his discovery to the authorities in Mexico City and to
the Carnegie Institution of Washington. Just four months
before him, two Americans, John Bourne and Carl Frey, had
been guided to Bonampak by chicle gatherers working in the
region, but though they had visited the ruins
of the ancient Maya site and examined several c ,,
temples and carved stone slabs strewn on the
ground they had missed the building with the
magnificient murals. Though only a hundred
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
UNESCO Album "Mexico"
DETAIL OF A FIGURE painted in the second room of the Bonampak temple. This same figure can be identified in the section of the mural
reproduced on page 7, second to right of the reclining Indian immediately above the doorway. Note the hieroglyphics over the figure's right arm.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
BONAMPAK
(Continued)
What the Mayas really looked like
revealed by first true picture in colour
yards away, it was buried by so much foliage and underbrush
that it had completely escaped their notice.
This is how Healey described his great discovery:
"These temples were beyond anything an archaeologist or
explorer could have imagined. It took days to get to these
ruins on foot through rivers, jungles, and over hills where
one climbs until absolutely exhausted. Sometimes I became
so utterly worn out in following the Lacandons that I thought
I would collapse.
"The greatest thrill of all came when the Lacandon Indians
led me into a temple made up of three rooms. Each room
was painted with frescoes from the floor to the ceiling. A
parade of Maya priests or chieftains is painted on the wall,
flanked by their attendants holding fans and umbrellas, and
with their musical attendants blowing on long horns, beating
drums, and playing flutes.
"The more important
personages are painted in
their full regalia, show¬
ing great detail of em¬
broidery, jewel insets,
feathered headdresses,
and so on. The fabric
designs show great skill
both in weaving and in
the use of native dyes.
"Handsome feather
plumes are worn by the
notables. For the first
time we had a true
picture in colour of what
the ancient Mayas actual¬
ly looked like. Books and
books have been written '
about them with only a
slight indication of what
they looked like and
wore... and here on this
wall was revealed for the
first time authentic evid¬
ence of the glorious
Mayas of the first em¬
pire period... Here is the work of the great, almost incre¬
dibly skilful mural painters, who lived and worked centuries
before Michelangelo...'"
Painting was a fine art among the ancient Mayas and
reached a high degree of excellence. Like the Greeks and
the Egyptians, the Mayas painted their stone monuments and
stone sculpture. Many vestiges of colour on stone still exist in
Mexico and Guatemala.
Painting was also used in the decoration of ceramics and
in illustrating codices, and frescoes in wall decoration. But
until the discovery of Bonampak very little was known of
early Maya wall painting. Except for the traces of a fourth-
century fresco found at Uaxactun, Guatemala (the oldest
known Maya monument) only a few fragments of Late Period
Maya wall paintings have been found at religious centres
such as Chichen Itza, Palengue, Tulum, Yaxchilan, Chac-
multun and Santa Rita Corozal.
When the world heard of the discovery of the Early Period
Bonampak paintings the news, therefore, electrified archaeolo¬
gists and art historians.
Unesco photo by Mario Dolfi
FRONT ENTRANCE of Bonampak temple after the jungle trees and thickets
had been partially cleared, shows the doorways of three rooms containing
the murals. The façade of the building reveals stuccowork and niches above
the entrances, of the temple; the central one contains fragments of a statue.
Expeditions were dispatched to Bonampak to survey the
site, the most important members being artists whose task it
was to make copies of the' originals. During 1947 and 1948
the slow work of copying the murals in colour proceeded.
Two artists, Antonio Tejeda of Guatemala and Agustín
Villagra of Mexico, working under the auspices of the Car¬
negie Institution and the National Institute of Anthropology
and History of Mexico, each made a set of copies. It is
chiefly through these copies that until now the treasures of
Bonampak have been known to art lovers and the public
generally.
Last year, Unesco and the Mexican Government organized
a special expedition to Bonampak to take full colour
photographs of the murals. These colour photographs will
shortly appear in the unesco world art series in an album
entitled Mexico : Pre-
Hispanic Paintings, pub¬
lished by the New
York Graphic Society
in collaboration with
Unesco.
One colour photo¬
graph from this forth¬
coming album publish¬
ed for the first time,
appears on the back
cover of this issue.
After a tour of the
country's chief archaeo¬
logical centres, including
Chichen-Itza where they
photographed the frag¬
mentary murals in the
Temple of the Warriors
and the Temple of the
Jaguars, and Teotihuacan
near Mexico City where
they took colour photos
of the existing paintings,
the members of the
Unesco expedition set
out for Bonampak from
Tenosique, the last main outpost. A government plane set
them down on a small clearing in the forest originally built
for chicle prospectors, about 20 miles from Bonampak. Seven
guides with 17 mules loaded with electric generators for their
floodlights, medical supplies, food end hammocks had left
Tenosique 15 days earlier. The expedition then made the
rough two-day trek through the jungle to the land of the
"painted walls".
Previous expeditions had found that the application of
kerosene to the calcite layer covering the murals rendered it
temporarily transparent. This discovery was of great aid to
the Unesco photographic team. But since the transparent
effect lasted only a few hours work proceeded slowly and with
difficulty under the trying humid tropical climate.
Bonampak is located near the Lacanjá River, a tributary of
the Usumacinta River which forms the boundary between
Mexico and Guatemala. Nine temples rest on
the terraced slopes of a hill. Long staircases
lead to the entrance of the buildings which face
a large square surrounded by platforms.
r page 10
There is no evidence that Bonampak is the
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
^*J \gy ;
"The Ancient Maya" by Sylvanus G. Morley. I 9 56 edition
Arraignment
of prisoners
Drawing, left, shows view from back of second room of the
Temple of the Murals looking toward entrance. Room Is
covered with paintings from base of a platform to top of
sloping ceiling. Detail is reproduced below from copy painted
by Guatemalan artist Antonio Tejeda. Scene has been Inter¬
preted by Maya experts as showing the arraignment of prisoners
on a step-terraced structure. Most Important personages
are grouped on upper part of structure. In centre Is a per¬
sonage clad in a jaguar jerkin and wearing a large jade pectoral.
A sweeping panache of long quetzal feathers attached to his
headdress attests to his high rank. Flanking him are person¬
ages wearing jaguar skins and jaguar or other animal heads
as helmets. Two women are also present on right. Seated
on the steps are nine men, apparently captives, awaiting
decision concerning their fate. At foot of reclining figure Is a
human head, but paint of mural Immediately to right has
scaled off and this area may originally have shown the body.
Carnegie Institution of Washington
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
BONAMPAK (Continued)
POMP AND CEREMONY, occupying all four walls of the first room
of the Bonampak temple, reveals Maya pomp and pageantry. Irregular
shape of mural is due to the fact that the room is vaulted, the triangular
and quadrangular pieces joining together at the top of the vault as
shown in drawing, above left. Upper portion shows preparations
for ceremony. To left are 14 persons, all clad in long white cloaks,
against a red background. Two of them in the centre address the
group while an attendant, holding a child, turns to receive instructions
Painting copied by Agustín Villagra, Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia, Mexico
TRUMPETS AND MASKED MEN, detail from lower left strip at
top of the page, which has been copied by the Mexican artist Agustín
Villagra. It shows part of the twelve-man orchestra. "Trumpets like
8
those on left were probably of wood and rotted away long'ago for never
have any been unearthed In Maya excavations. Scholars believe the ma¬
sked figures with alligator heads, crab claws, etc. represent Maya deities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
**fc
Ml i
1 J£& Êk Ê.
A. IjL...XI_JL AJÍ	á-ü JB Jf JL
Painting copied by Antonio Tejeda
Carnegie Institution of Washington
from a figure seated crosslegged in triangular section. In far right
panel, three personages are being robed. One on right is nearly ready
and has on his jaguar skin, bracelets, ear-plugs, anklets, all coloured
green to represent jade or quetzal feathers. His great, inverted U
m eer^ES
quetzal-feather backpiece Is In position. In lower strip the three
men are fully dressed and stand In the centre of the scene as the pro¬
cession advances towards them with blowing of trumpets, beating of
drums and shaking of rattles. Scene has a striking blue background.
f.r./-'!- ?£-
MAYA BATTLE SCENE, from a mural In the second room, indicates
that the warriors of Bonampak used the spear as their principal weapon.
Here the men, arrayed in magnificent costumes, jewellery and paint,
Painting copied by Antonio Tejeda, Carnegie Institution of Washington
are apparently carrying out a raid on an enemy camp. Combat scenes
such as this one occupy three walls of this room and have led experts
to revise the old conception that the Mayas never engaged in warfare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
BONAMPAK
(Cont'd from p. 6)
Strikingly carved
stone reliefs and
a stele weighing four tons
ruin of an ancient town or city. Like other Maya
archaeological sites it was probably a religious centre to
which the Maya resorted only for ceremonies, the inhabitants
living in small groups, probably only of family size, scattered
over the countryside.
Although famous for its murals, Bonampak is also
remarkable for its well preserved and finely carved stone
reliefs. The site contains significant carved lintels and three
highly revealing carved record stones or. stelae one of which
bears the Maya hieroglyphic date 9.17.15.00 (785 A.D.). In
the centre of the square is a great stele, unfortunately broken,
16 feet high, 8 feet wide (5 by 2i metres) and weighing at
least four tons.
The three rooms containing the murals appear to depict
the holding of a religious ceremonial, the robing of priests or
personages of high rank, an orchestra procession, a raid to
obtain victims for a sacrifice on the stairs of a temple, a
dance in magnificent costumes, and a bloodletting ceremony
by a high priest accompanied by a woman and a child.
Headdresses of dazzling colour
tall as the men who wore them
Much of» the painting is on the sloping overhead stone
surfaces of the roofing and shows remarkable skill in
perspective on the part of the Maya mural artists. The
paintings are executed with extreme realism. The faces of
certain of the figures can be recognized from room to room
as they recur in different parts of the story. The artist has
skilfully conveyed different moods for different scenes: bodies
and facial expressions are relaxed during the. preparation of the
ceremony; they seem ferocious during the raid; during the
sacrifice one can almost feel the cold, forbidding atmosphere.
Sylvanus Morley has said, "some of the figures in the
Bonampak murals exhibit a degree of naturalism which
Western European art did not achieve until several centuries
later."
Probably the most overpowering effect of the murals is the
magnificence of costuming and colour. Healey's first
description was hardly exaggerated. One is dazzled by the
colourful headdresses of delicate featherwork as tall as the
principle figures wearing them, and by the variety of materials
used: featherwork, cut stones, furs, intricate woven fabrics.
In delicacy of execution and in sensitivity and purity of line
these paintings are truly remarkable.
The murals also offer us one of the most detailed sources
of information on the pattern of Maya life. Better than ever
before they reveal the musical instruments, dances, costumes,
weapons and family groupings of the early Mayas. They
seem to contradict the old conception that the Mayas nevei
engaged in warfare or resorted to human sacrifice since scenes
of both are found at Bonampak. The murals also indicate
that the position of women in the life of the community was
more important than had generally been supposed. As Maya
authorities point out, probably no other site has added so
much to our general knowledge of the Maya people. With
the publication by Unesco of the full colour photographs of
the Bonampak murals, art historians will no doubt give an
even higher place in the history of art to the great civilization
of the Mayas.
10
Carlos Prieto, from "Bonampak"
by Agustin Villagra, 1949
ONE OF THREE LINTELS with hieroglyphic blocks found over the
doorways of the Temple of Murals. AM three of them show, the
capturing of prisoners and are thought to date from about 790 A.D.
Giles G. Healey, from "Cités
Maya" by Paul Rivet 19 54
GREAT SCULPTURED STELE, measuring five by two-and-a-half
metres, found broken In several pieces in the plaza of the Bonampak
acropolis. Detail of the head is reproduced on the inside front cover.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
Maya acropolis
on terraced hill
Right, a map of Bonampak, surveyed
and prepared by K. Ruppert and
G. Stromsvik, members of the
second Carnegie Institution expe¬
dition in the winter of 1947. Bo¬
nampak is a small, carefully laid
out, compact site, with a plaza
measuring about 90 by 110 metres.
Surrounding it on three sides are
low mounds, the remains of terraces
and small structures. The fourth
(south) side is delimited by a hill
43 metres high, artificially terraced.
Here the nine temples of Bonampak
are located. Temple of the Murals
is encircled. Below, a sculptured
stone, with delicately incised relief
figures, which was found nearby.
From "Bonampak" by Rupert Thompson &
Proskouriakoff, Publication 602, Carnegie
Institution, Washington, 19 55
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Icon paintings:
THE TRIUMPH
OF ANCIENT
RUSSIAN ART
by Victor Lasaren
Corresponding Member of the Academy
of Sciences of the U.S.S.R.
ryiHE Russian icon ranks among the most
I remarkable artistic revelations of the
20th century. In the previous century
even those collectors who specialized in the
works of the mediaeval Russian school of
icon painting did not suspect what beauty
lay concealed in them. The old icons were
hidden under metal settings or under
numerous layers of overpainting, which
completely altered their original appearance.
When, in the 1900's, the cleaning of icons
was first undertaken, it was discovered that
the mediaeval paintwork had been
admirably preserved beneath the retouch¬
ings and the overpainting and had acquired
the firmness and close texture of bone. The
removal of the dark varnish and retouchings
from the large Novgorod icons resulted in
a veritable revelation, and this new and
magnificent branch of art, hitherto known
to few, soon found enthusiastic votaries
among collectors and artists alike.
The museums likewise began actively to
acquire icons, as a result of which the
Tretyakov Gallery in Moscow and the Rus¬
sian Museum in St. Petersburg rapidly be¬
came real treasure-houses of mediaeval Rus¬
sian painting. Unfortunately, galleries in
the West did not extend their collections to
include good Russian icons, and Russian
icon painting has thus remained unre¬
presented in them or is represented by
such inferior and fortuitous specimens
that they could perfectly well be dispensed
with.
The public at large did not come to
realize the aesthetic value of the icon until
12
UNESCO Album "U.S.S.R."
1913, following the Moscow Exhibition of
Mediaeval Russian Art, at which a
considerable number of first-class icons of
the 15th and 16th centuries were displayed.
For those who visited the exhibition it was
as though a bandage which had prevented
them from seeing the true face of Russian
painting had suddenly fallen from their
eyes. In place of dark, gloomy icons
coated with a thick layer of varnish they
beheld glorious works of art which would
do honour to any people in the world.
The cleaned icons were radiant with
colours as bright as precious stones ; they
blazed with the flame of cinnabar ; they
caressed the eye with their subtle shades
of pink, violet and golden yellow ; they
gripped the attention of the onlooker by
the rare beauty of their snowy white and
clear blue tones. And at once it became .
obvious to all that this was no ascetic, grim,
fanatical art-form ; that in it the living
creativeness of the people was vividly
reflected ; that its radiance and a certain
peculiar clarity of form related it to the
painting of classical antiquity ; and that it
deserved to be regarded as one of the
supreme manifestations of the Russian
national genius.
The most important discoveries in the
field of old Russian painting were made in
the years following the Soviet Revolution.
As early as October 5, 1918, a decree of
the Council of People's Commissars, "On
the Registration, Cataloguing and Protection
of Monuments of Art and Antiquity", was
published. The personal instructions of the
founder of the Soviet State, V.l. Lenin,
played an important part in this matter.
The great works of the mediaeval
masters, which had previously been
concealed in churches and monasteries,
where they had been repeatedly subjected
to alteration and repainting, became the
object of thorough scientific study and
restoration. Dozens of expeditions were
organized, to Novgorod, Pskov, Kiev,
Zvenigorod, Vologda, the Monastery of the
Trinity and St. Sergius, Tver and Yaroslavl,
to the North and to the cities of the Volga.
These expeditions were organized in
accordance with'a carefully worked out
plan ; highest priority was given to the
cleaning of works of outstanding impor¬
tance which might possibly throw light on
the central problems of the history of
mediaeval Russian painting.
It was now possible to replace the
dilettante concept of "manners" (i.e.,
different manners of painting) by the
scientific concept of '"schools". By follow¬
ing this course it became possible to
establish the dividing lines between the
Novgorod and Moscow schools, the pro¬
ductions of which had constantly been
confused by earlier investigators ; the
schools of Pskov and Tver arose again from
non-existence ; Theophanes the Greek,
Andrei Rublëv and Dionisius became
perfectly concrete figures. Of particular
importance was -the discovery of a series
of works of the 12th and
13th centuries, thanks to
which the earliest period of
Russian painting appeared
in a completely new light.
Cont'd
on
page 14
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
St. PETER LEADING
THE WAY TO PARADISE
The art of the icon is one of Russia's most significant contri¬
butions to the history of world art. For 800 yearsfrom
the I Ith to the 18th centurythis art-form preserved its
inherent vitality and energy. It began when ancient Russia
adopted Christianity and Kiev received her first Byzantine
artists, with whom local craftsmen collaborated. Icon
painting was thus the legitimate successor to Byzantine art
moulded in a new, national form, and once it attained full
maturity it became completely self-contained. Among the
earliest Russian icons known to us are those of the Novgorod
School such as the painting of St. George (opposite page)
dating from about I 170, and now in the Cathedral of the
Annunciation, in the Kremlin. St. George, one of the favour¬
ite subjects of the Novgorod ¡con painters, is depicted as
patron of Prince George Andreevich of Novgorod. Supreme
achievements in the field of icon painting were made by the
masters of the Moscow school, headed by the great Andrei
Rublëv (c. 1370-1430). In 1408 Rublëv and his friend,
Daniel Tchernyi, decorated the Cathedral of the Assumption
in Vladimir. They chose as their subject "The Day of Judg¬
ment", but unlike the treatment given to this theme by most
mediaeval artists, Rublëv's interpretation has nothing dread
or awesome about it. Left, a group from the fresco on the
south side of the Cathedral nave depicting St. Peter leading
the blessed to Paradise. Above, a detail from this group.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Icon paintings
(Continued)
In 1929-1930 an exhibition of Russian
icons was held in Germany, Britain and
America and attracted general attention.
It was this exhibition which first brought
mediaeval Russian painting to the notice
of western Europe. From that moment the
Russian icon, which Matisse had been one
of the first to appreciate in the West, had
entered the broad international arena.
The sources of Russian icon painting
date back to the 10th century, when ancient
Russia adopted Christianity and Kiev
received her first Byzantine artists, under
whom local craftsmen were trained. Thus
arose the Byzantino-Russian workshops
which adorned with mosaics, frescoes and
icons the celebrated Churches of Kiev,
including the Church of the Tithe (989-
996) and the Cathedral of St. Sofia (1037-
1067). These studios were centres not only
of Byzantine iconography but also of the
Byzantine manner of painting. However,
as always, the pupils very soon began to
diverge from their teachers and, under the
influence of the exigencies of Russian life,
to raise and to solve new problems.
In this way the national characteristics
of Russian painting began to take shape,
a process which we are able to follow only
through study of the frescoes, not the icons,
for no Russian icons of the 11th century
have come down to us. Nevertheless,
Kievan Russia already possessed its own
celebrated artists.
Fiery tastes of Novgorod
As centrifugal tendencies grew stronger
and the Kievan State declined, local
feudal centres began to arise, and,
along with them, local schools of painting.
With three of them, those of Novgorod,
Vladimir-Suzdal and Yaroslavl, are asso¬
ciated the oldest Russian icons known to us,
dating from the 12th and 13th centuries.
The most outstanding productions of the
Novgorod school of icon painting were
created towards the end of the 14th and in
the 15th century. The Novgorod artists
avoid the complicated, intricate symbolic
subjects which are so widespread in later
Russian icon painting. The themes treated
by them are simple and lucid ; their
lightly constructed compositions are clear
and easily comprehended, and the main
outlines of the subject. are not obscured by
obtrusion of secondary episodes. The
Novgorod icon is distinguished above all by
its colouring, in which the predominant
element is fiery cinnabar. It is these
colours, unforgettable in their brilliance
and chromatic tension, which reflect prob¬
ably more fully than anything else the
taste of the people of Novgorod.
The supreme achievements in the field
of icon painting were made by the masters
of the Moscow school, headed by the great
Andrei Rublëv (c. 1370-1430). As from
the 14th century, Moscow began rapidly to
move forward to the front place among
the Russian states, taking the lead in the
struggle against the Tartars. After the
famous battle of Kulikovo (1380), at which
the Russians dealt the Golden Horde a
crushing blow, the political importance of
the Moscow principality was vastly increas¬
ed. This 'battle, which demonstrated to
the Russian people the importance of their
national unity, contributed to the awakening
of their national consciousness. So were
14
m
THE VIRGIN OF THE DON, a work of the Novgorod school of icon painters in the late 1 4th cen¬
tury, is said to have accompanied the great Prince of Moscow, Dimitri Ivanovich of the Don, in the
battle of Kulikovo in 1380 when the Russians dealt the Golden Horde a crushing blow. It also
figured in other Russian campaigns against the Tartars in 1552 and 1591. Authorities in the past
ascribed the work (now in the Tretyakov Gallery, Moscow) to Theophanes the Greek (one of the
most outstanding artists in Russia during the late 14th and early 15th centuries) but following
more recent research it is now believed to have been painted by a Novgorod follower of Theophanes.
created the necessary conditions for a gene¬
ral flowering of culture.
Moscow painting made full sense of the
artistic heritage of Byzantium. In 1344 the
Metropolitan Theognostus invited Greek
masters to decorate with murals the walls
of his cathedral ; in 1395 at the latest the
celebrated Theophanes the Greek arrived
in Moscow, where he was to remain until
his death. In Moscow, finally, there were
Greek icons and much church plate of
Byzantine origin. In the works of Andrei
Rublëv the aesthetic ideals of the Moscow
school received their most complete
expression. For the loftiness of his human
ideal, for the moral purity and profound
poetry of the figures, for delicacy of purely
musical rhythm, for perfection of chromatic
relations, Rublëv has no equals. His icons
are full of an irresistible charm, and his
painting of The Trinity (see page 17) is
one of the great masterpieces of the world.
The golden age of Russian icon painting
was the 15th century, which constitutes a
clearly marked historical stage. For this
reason the monuments of this period may
serve as the basis for a characterization of
Russian icon painting as a whole.
Some students of mediaeval art are still
inclined even today to regard Russian icon
painting as a mere branch of Byzantine. It
would of course be naive to deny the
derivation of the Russian icon from the
Byzantine. Iconography and all the basic
technique of painting were inherited by
Russian artists from their Greek compeers.
But very soon, and that at the early stages
of development when survivals of the
joyous pagan attitude to life were still
strong, profound changes took place in
Russian painting, leading to the birth of a
new art which diverged more and more
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
decidedly from that of Byzantium. This
evolution first became apparent in an.
attenuation of Byzantine asceticism, as well
as in the creation of completely original
iconographie types. It showed itself also
in the growth of the cult of local saints,
which absorbed many elements of
Russian life, and in the continuous
intrusion of national ethnic types into icon
painting. It showed itself finally in the
brightening of the palette, which acquired
extraordinary brilliance and joyousness as
well as in the steady growth of the impor¬
tance of line, notably of the outline, so
highly valued by the Russian icon painters.
Then, gradually, the Russian icon became
the great national art-form of mediaeval
Russia. It was in the 15th century that
this lengthy process attained, so to speak,
its logical culmination.
In the Russian icon one is struck by the
peculiar combination of abstract conception
with intense emotional quality. It might
have been expected that, given a strongly
abstract approach, there would be no
possibility of creating a joyous emotion¬
al art capable of arousing ordinary
human feelings. In fact, however, Russian
15th-century icon painting is radiant and
lighthearted. It is equally removed from
gloomy Byzantine contemplativeness and
from the exaggerated expressiveness of
Gothic art.
When the modern spectator looks at old
icons, they usually seem to him to be so like
one another that he is unable to see much
difference between them, especially in the
case of icons which depict the same subject.
This is due to the extraordinary persistence
of the majority of iconographie types in
Byzantine and old Russian art. These
types were hallowed by ancient tradition.
They were regarded as historically true
renderings of the events with which they
dealt. Moreover, many of these iconogra¬
phie types were attributed to the brush of
this or that saint or hermit. It was to this
that they owed their persistence.
For the men of the past all these re¬
presentations of the Annunciation, the
Nativity, the Crucifixion, and so forth,
were exact representations of sacred
events. For this reason, the more care¬
fully such a scene was copied from
existing representations, the greater was
its value in the eyes both of the artist
and of the contemporary spectator.
The consequence was that copies of certain
miraculous icons held their ground for
more than a thousand years. Despite
similarity, at times extraordinarily close,
no single icon is an exact copy of another.
Dozens of representations of St. George,
of the Pokrov and of various Gospel
scenes have come down to us ; but
to look for two absolutely identical
pictures would be wasted effort. Of
course, the Russian master followed tradi-
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
tion. He was bound by it to no small
extent. But in the 15th century it was
never felt to be a fetter on his creative
powers. He operated fairly freely with the
iconographie types inherited from earlier
generations. By altering the rhythm of the
composition, the outlines, the distribution
of colour and the psychological nuances, he
succeeded without difficulty in giving a new
note to each of the works which he created.
It was probably in the colouring that the
Russian icon painter revealed most clearly
his individual tastes. Colour is the real
soul of 15th-century Russian icon painting.
For the Russian, as for the Netherlands'
artist, paint was a precious material, no less
precious than smalt. He revelled in the
beauty of its pure, simple colours, which he
applied in combinations of astonishing
resonance. When he carried colour to its
extreme degree of tension, he achieved a
quite unique colour system, strong, bright
and confident, unlike the severe and much
darker colour range of the Byzantine icons.
No less essential as a means of expression
in the hands of the Russian icon painter
was line. His mastery of line was com¬
plete. He could render it soft, clastic,
flowing, angular, monumental and calligra-
phically precise. He attributed particular
importance to the outline, which in Russian
icons is characterized by such great terse¬
ness that it recalls the concise outlines of
the figures on Greek vases.
UNESCO Album "U.S.S.R."
THE SAVIOUR is part of the deesis (set of ¡cons
representingjesus, the Virgin and St. John the Baptist)
painting by Andrei Rublëv. An icon painting on wood
dating from about 1400 and previously in the cath¬
edral of the Dormition at Zvenigorod, it is now part
of the collection in the Tretyakov Gallery, Moscow.
fa-5*i&;
UNESCO Album "U.S.S.R."
ARCHANGEL, a late I 2th-century wooden ¡con, formed
part of a half figure deesis from an altar screen. Stylisti¬
cally it is closely related to a group of works which has
been associated with the workshop of the "Greek Petro-
vich" (one of the artists who brought Byzantine art to
Russia). It is now in the Russian Museum, Leningrad.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Two Great Russian Artists : Rublëv and Theophanes
Soviet art critics are today making a
thorough study of the works of
Theophanes the Greek and Andrei
Rublëv, the two most outstanding artists of
the 14th and 15th centuries in Russia.
Until recently, very little was known about
them and most information was based more
on fiction than on fact. The works of
Rublëv, for instance, were formerly attri¬
buted to the Novgorod school of painting,
an error arising from the fact that until
recently no other schools of 14th and 15th-
century Russian painting were known.
Although much still remains to be disco¬
vered about their lives, their works can
now be as surely identified as those of the
ancient Greek sculptors Phidias and Myron
or the Italian painters Masaccio and Fra
Angélico.
The true greatness of Theophanes and
Rublëv has been revealed to us largely by
Soviet restoration experts who have restored
the frescoes of cathedrals in Novgorod,
Moscow, Vladimir and other towns. Soviet
art critics have contributed to a better
understanding of the art of these masters,
explaining it as an expression of the great
period of Russian history when the Tartar
yoke was thrown off and the unification of
the country began.
Theophanes the Greek came from Byzan¬
tium, arriving in Russia at the* end of the
14th century. His work .unquestionably
resembles that of the Byzantine masters of
the 14th century, but his highly original
creative efforts place him beyond the
bounds of Byzantine art.
One cannot resist drawing a comparison
between Theophanes and another great
Greek artist, Dominico Theotocopuli, called
16
by Mikhael Alpafov
Member of the Fine Arts
Academy of the U. S. S. R.
El Greco. El Greco received his first
training on his native isle of Crete ; later
he studied in Venice, but his long stay in
Toledo, his adopted home, made of him a
typical representative of Spanish art. In
similar fashion Theophanes' genius came
to full flowering in Russia.
The stern, passionate nature of Theo¬
phanes' art is clearly demonstrated in his
icon of the Virgin in the iconostasis of the
Blagoveschensky cathedral in the Kremlin
at Moscow, painted in 1405. Here the ar¬
tist tempered the force of his passion,
given full rein in the Novgorod frescoes, but
his hand is clearly discernible in the blue
draperies enveloping the Virgin, in the soft
drawing of her features, and in the prayer¬
ful attitude of her extended hands.
It is known that Rublëv worked with
Theophanes in the Blagoveschensky cathe¬
dral. By right of seniority Theophanes'
name comes first in the chronicles. So
different is Rublëv's work from that of
Theophanes that some critics have called
them representatives of opposite schools of
art: Theophanes of the "picturesque style",
Rublëv of trTe "graphic or icon style".
As, a matter of fact, Rublëv is as fine a
painter and colourist as Theophanes, but
the poetry with which he imbues his art is
of an entirely different order. The art of
Theophanes is ardent, impassioned, drama¬
tic, full of movement, contrast, and psy¬
chological tension. The art of Rublëv is
mild and expresses exquisite lyricism, spi¬
rituality and harmony.
The most mature and most famous work
by Andrei Rublëv is his "Trinity". At first
this icon adorned the iconostasis of the Tri¬
nity cathedral at the Monastery of the Tri¬
nity and St. Sergius near Moscow. At
present it is one of the most valuable
acquisitions of the mediaeval Russian
collection of the Tretyakov Gallery.
In his '"Trinity" Rublëv uses the Biblical
legend of the appearance of the Godhead
to man. The Godhead is incarnated in the
lovely forms of three youths.
With the laconism of genius the artist
conveys the finest nuances of expression as
these three youths converse together ; he
tells us they are united in love, that the
will of each is subordinated to that of all,
and that all three are saddened by a
contemplation of the sufferings awaiting,
one of them. The greatest charm
of the colouring is the purity and
brightness of the tints, especially of the
light blue. These gleaming tints are in
complete harmony with the lucid, balanced
composition of the icon.
Theophanes the Greek and Andrei Rub¬
lëv were contemporaries of the Italian
and Flemish artists of the early Renais¬
sance. The work of both masters, repre¬
sentative as it was of mediaeval Russian
painting, differs greatly from that of the
founders of the realistic school in western
Europe. Modern criticism, however, has
admiration for the artistic achievements of
both schools. In the Soviet Union, An¬
drei Rublëv is particularly beloved. By a
decree of the Soviet Government, the An-
dronikov monastery in Moscow where
Rublëv was buried in 1430, has been
turned into the Rublëv museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
..~"S7 V ' m
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
] ' " * ' ' ' ' ' ' . i
; ^ .- . ?
¡R 7-x' . 'if ï
V
i*
£W ' t
I^^SHn^^B Hb ^ >*
1 ^Qr Bf Sj\ i
'W ^íí
/íj|j y\Ä-
/ ;$L¿A ''//»>
^m^fcjj-r' 4 '
v'*' ~- ^í- '^SK*1*»
UNESCO Album "U.S.S.R."
HIGHEST EXPRESSION of mediaeval Russian ¡con painting is found in The Trinity (above) and detail (left) painted about 1411 by Andrei Rublëv,
in whose works the aesthetic ideals of the Moscow school of painting came to full flower. At first this icon was kept in the cathedral of the Trinity
at Zagorsk, near Moscow. Regarded as one of the world's great masterpieces, it is now a treasured item in the mediaeval Russian collection of the
Tretyakov Gallery, Moscow. Opposite page (far left), detail from The Virgin (See also p. 18) by Theophanes the Greek, who came to Russiafrom Byzan¬
tium in the 14th century. The true greatness of Theophanes and Rublëv has been revealed to us largely by Soviet restoration experts who have
worked on the frescoes of cathedrals in Novgorod, Moscow, Vladimir and other towns, during dozens of research and restoration expeditions.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Great Russian
Icon Painters
(Continued)
	T - T.. . -»T-*"
1
Up** . L _Mg|
mmum^
1
' "** tWWm i
i
JÍlaafl
54 mW* À\\
m> -* Am
1
t
i Am
I
p
p
VH
1
1
Id B^^^^H PWj
UNESCO Album 'USS.R."
TWO ARTISTS, SAME SUBJECT. These paintings of the
Virgin show how two of Russia's great artists gave individual
expression to the same subject. Above, The Virgin from the
Cathedral of the Annunciation, in the Kremlin, painted by
Theophanes in 1405. Left, Virgin painted by Rublëv when he
decorated the Uspensky Cathdral, in Vladimir, in 1408. True
beauty of old Russian ¡cons was hidden under metal settings or
layers of overpainting. When their cleaning was first undertaken
it was found that the mediaeval paintwork had been well preser¬
ved and had acquired the firmness and close texture of bone.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
mmm) %wm
ST. GEORGE. Novgorod School. First half of XVth century.
Tretyakov Gallery, Moscow. (Unesco, Album "U.S.S.R.")
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
THE ENTOMBMENT. Northern School. Last
quarter of XVth century. Tretyakov Gallery,
Moscow. (From Unesco Album "U.S.S.R.")
PRINCE SIDDHARTA, the Buddha-to-be, exhibiting his skill in archery.
Dambulla Cave temple. XVIIIth century. (From Unesco Album "CEYLON")
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ENTRANCE INTO JERUSALEM. Page of an important I Ith cen¬
tury manuscript, the Codex of the Gospel Book of the Coronation,
bound in the 14th century, and a rare example of the earlier
use of metal and precious- stones in Middle Age binding. In St. Guy
Capitulary Library, Prague. (Unesco Album 'CZECHOSLOVAKIA')
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
EARLIEST REMAINS of pictorial art in Ceylon are the figures of
women depicted as rising from clouds painted in a rock pocket at Sigiri
(see next page). They date from one of the great periods of Sinhalese
art (4th and 5th centuries) about which early Chinese historians spoke
in raptures. By their originality and their capacity for depicting the
UNESCO Album "Ceylon"
human form, the Sigiri paintings stand isolated from later works, but
resemble the famous contemporary Ajanta paintings in India. This
golden-coloured damsel is one of 21 on the rock once supposed
to have been decorated with 500 "golden-coloured ones". Gazing
at a sapu flower in her right hand, she holds water lilies in her left.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
^"*»r
RIÑE OF A
OWNING THE
LION'S ROCK
by Dr. S. Paranavitana
Professor of Archeology, University of Ceylon
W
VtëZmA
The elements of civilization were first introduced into
the Island of Ceylon, some five centuries before the
beginning of the present era, by an Aryan-speaking
peoplethe forefathers of the modern Sinhalesewho
came from Northern India and settled down there. When
the missionaries despatched by the great Indian emperor
Asoka preached the doctrines of Buddhism in the middle
of the third century B.C., the early Sinhalese had spread
themselves over almost the entire area of the Island and
founded a dynasty with its capital at Anuradhapura, in
the centre of the northern plains. The adoption of Bud¬
dhism by the Sinhalese marked the beginning of a period
of great building activity, designed to serve the needs
of their new faith, which gave an impetus to the growth
of the arts, including sculpture and painting.
Anuradhapura remained the capital of Ceylon for over
a thousand years. For a brief period of eighteen years
in the 5th century A.D. Sinhalese royalty moved its seat
to Sigiri, a city built with an impregnable rock fortress
as its central feature, situated some forty miles to the
south of Anuradhapuraan interlude which marked an
epoch in the history of painting in Ceylon.
Often during the first millenium and a half of their
history, the Sinhalese had to contend for the possession
of the Island with Tamil invaders from South India and,
in the first decade of the 11th century A.D., the greater
part of Ceylon was subjected to the mighty Chola empire.
24
When the Sinhalese regained their independence after
three-quarters of a century, the old capital Anuradhapura
was abandoned in favour of Polonnaruva, which was
the headquarters of the Chola rulers. In the 12th cen¬
tury, Polonnaruva witnessed a brilliant period, note¬
worthy for its political and military achievements, as
well as for the fostering of the arts. But this later efflor¬
escence of Sinhalese culture was of short duration and
was followed, in the third decade of the 13th century,
by the collapse of the ancient monarchy.
The history of the next three centuries is a tale of steady
decline. Those regions of the Island where the Sinhalese
achieved their greatest triumphs in architecture and art
became gradually depopulated and the seat of govern¬
ment was shifted at different times to various places in
the Western and Central districts. On the arrival of the
Portuguese, early in the 16th century, the Sinhalese
king had his abode at Kotte, close to modern Colombo.
The struggle with the Portuguese compelled the Sinha¬
lese to shift the seat of government to Kandy, which
had a natural defence in the mountains surrounding it.
In the meantime, Buddhism, the national faith which
provided the inspiration for most of the artistic achieve¬
ments of the Sinhalese, had sunk to a very low ebb.
There was a revival in the 18th century, when a number
of religious edifices were built anew and many ancient
shrines were restored, in the embellishment of which the
services of the painter were pressed into service.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
Time has dealt severely with the vast quantity of paintings
which must have been produced during a period of over
two thousand years in Ceylon. The frescoes on the
walls of palaces and shrines have disappeared with the collapse
of thoses edifices. Paintings executed on wooden boards and
cloth, belonging to a date prior to the 18th century, are
no longer to be found, save for a few covers of ola (palm-leaf)
books, for such materials have a limited duration of life in
a climate like that of Ceylon. We have, therefore, from early
times, only such paintings as were in positions sheltered from
the weather and beyond the reach of destructive human hands.
The earliest remains of pictorial art in Ceylon are found
in a rock pocket at Sigiri, in the Mátale District, and can
be authentically dated as belonging to the 5th century. On
the summit of this well-nigh unscalable rock, which rises
600 ft. above the level of the surrounding plain, a Sinhalese
king, Kassapa I (circa 473-491 A.D.), fixed his abode so that,
as the chronicler informs us, he might be safe from his
enemies who were determined to mete out justice to him
for having murdered his father to secure the throne for
himself.
Hugging the perpendicular, and in some places overhanging
faces of the rock on the western and northen sides, a pathway
has been constructed, giving access to the summit. Halfway
up this pathway, on the northen side, is a plateau on which
has been built, in brick masonry, the forepart of a colossal
figure of a seated lion, projecting out of the rock face. A
flight of steps through the body of this lion has solved the
problem of taking the pathway above a perpendicular
stretch of the rock face. The figure of the lion has given
the rock the name by which it has since been known: Sigiri
means "Lion's Rock".
The pathway was protected at its outer edge by a brick
The colossal figure of a seated lion projecting
out of the cliff face has given the name "Sigiri"
(The Lion's Rock) to the enormous mass of
stone rising 600 feet from a plain in the Mátale
district of Ceylon. Here, in the 5th century a
parricide king, Kasappa, took refuge from his
enemies and built a handsome palace. The
tempera paintings of women similar to those
which still exist in an almost inaccessible rock
pocket at Sigiri may also once have covered a
large area of the western face of the Sigiri rock.
wall averaging eight feet in height and coated with lime
plaster so highly polished that, even today, after the lapse
of fifteen centuries, one can see one-s reflection in it. Hence,
the wall is appropriately known as Kadapat-pavura, "Mirror
Wall". Sections of the pathway that were open to the sky
have long since collapsed, but a good stretch, sheltered by
the overhanging rock, is still in a fairly good state of pre¬
servation. The rock pocket in which the frescoes are now
seen is at a height of about forty feet above the floor of this
pathway, generally referred to as the Gallery, on the western
face of the rock.
In olden days, there was no means of access to this rock
pocket, and the presence of the figures of women painted at
the place has to be explained as due to the fact that, formerly,
there were such painted figures over a very large area of the
western face of the rock, and that these only have been
preserved due to their being sheltered from the sun and rain.
Patches of plaster in the crevices of the rock outside the
pocket support this view, which is also confirmed by refer¬
ences in the graffiti on the Mirror Wall to five hundred
"golden-coloured ones" on the rock, whereas we have today
only twenty-one. figures. These graffiti also refer to figures
which could be touched by the hand as one proceeded along
the gallery and to a painting of a lady holding a flute in her
hand. No such paintings are to be seen now;
we have, therefore, to conclude that, in olden
days, there were many more figures than are
preserved at present.
The figures of women, somewhat less than
UNESCO Album "Ceylon"
SUDDHAVASA BRAHMAAn inhabitant of the Pure Worlds
(above) adoring Buddha. From a painting on the walls jaf a relic-
chamber (c. I Ith century) In the Mahiyangana Dagaba, a stupa or relic
mound, in the Uva Province, and one of Ceylon's most venerated
Buddhist shrines. Now in the Anuradhapura Museum. Below, a female
figure from frescoes at Sigiri with hands in a conventional dance pose.
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
Buddhist artists have never tired of recounting in paint and
stone the jataka storiestales of Buddha's previous lives
before he attained Enlightenment. A favourite subject is
the temptation of Buddha by his great enemy, Mara, chief of
demons, who is often represented as attacking Buddha with
innumerable hosts of demons and monsters (below). Buddha
resisted the temptations of Mara and finally vanquished the
evil one whose downfall is depicted (bottom of opposite page)
with him being thrown from his elephant. Both these 18th-
century paintings are in the Dambulla cave temple in the
Mátale district. Another 18th-century Jataka painting (left)
from a cave temple, Degaldoruva Vihara, near the hill-capital,
Kandy, shows Prince Vessentara (the last but one of Buddha's
incarnations) riding in state upon a white elephant. This
treasured beast had the power of bringing rain, but the
prince, practising "the perfection of giving ", presented it to
another ruler, so angering his people that he was banished.
Reproducedfrom "Mediaeval Sinhalese Art" by Ananda K. Coomaraiwamy
3 - - - --
Photos UNESCO Album "Ceylon"
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO Album "Ceylon'
EARTH-GODDESS, (Mahi-Kanta) painted on the ceiling of the cave temple at Degaldoruva, near Kandy. The goddess is bearing
witness to the Buddha's right to occupy the diamond throne at the foot of the Bodhi tree where he found Enlightenment. This
18th-century work dates from the period of the Buddhist revival in Ceylon when many ancient religious shrines were restored.
Reproduced from "Mediaeval Sinhalese Art" by Ananda K. Coomaraswamy
ROYAL RAIMENT. Sinhalese drawing of Sri Vikrama Raja Simha (last of the line of 18th-century Kandyan kings who were
great art patrons during the Buddhist revival) attended by his ministers. The king wears a shirt, tunic, cape, trousers, and
sandals, earrings, necklaces and pendants, and bears a lacquered arrow. Attendants hold pearl-fringed umbrellas and royal fans.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
(Cont'd from p. 25)
life-size, are depicted in three-quarter profile as rising from
clouds, being cut off below the waist. Some are in pairs, a fair-
complexioned lady being 'attended by a dark-hued one, while
others are single figures. The golden-coloured ones are nude
above the waist, while the dark damsels are wearing breast-
bands. All are wearing jewellery in profusion, and have ela¬
borate coiffures. Some of the women hold trays of flowers
in their hands; others are holding or scattering flowers.
Some figures hold their hands in conventional dance poses.
The faces are oval in shape, with sensuous lips, while the hands
are delicate and expressive. The figures may be taken as
representative of feminine types common among the upper
classes of Sinhalese society in those days.
On grounds of style, the fragmentary remains of frescoes
in a cave at Hindagala, about six miles to the South-East of
Kandy, can be attributed to a period co-eval with, or some¬
what later than, those at Sigiri. Nothing is known about the
history of this ancient Buddhist monastery. There are inscrip¬
tions of the 6th or 7th century on rocks at the place, but
they do not mention its ancient name. The painting depicts
the Buddha surrounded by figures, presumably divine, in atti¬
tudes of adoration. As the Buddha is shown twice in the
same scene, it is clear that the method of continuous narration
has. been adopted by the artist.
The walls of the relic-chambers of some stupas in Ceylon
appear to have been covered with paintings which, of course,
would not have been seen by human eyes after the chambers
were sealed. A monument which has yielded fragmentary
remains of this type of fresco is the Mahiyangana Dagaba, a
stupa or relic-mound, in the Uva Province, one of the most
venerated of Buddhist shrines in Ceylon, which, in its historic
form, dates from about the second century B.C. But the
relic-chamber containing the paintings, opened in 1950,
belonged to a subsequent period of restoration, several cen¬
turies later. The plaster with the paintings had peeled down,
but many of the larger fragments were collected and carefully
joined together. The scene represented is the defeat of Mara,
the Evil One, by the Buddha, and the adoration of the Buddha
by heavenly beings after the victory. It is interesting to find
the sectarian gods of Puranic Hinduism, Siva and Vishnu,
among the celestial beings paying homage to the Buddha.
Inner sanctum for
Buddha's life scenes
Pictorial remains in a rock shelter called Pulligoda-galge,
near Dimbulagala in the Tamankaduwa District of the
North-Central Province, consist of four haloed divinities
seated on a carpet, probably the remnant of a large composition
in which gods were depicted as adoring the Buddha. This
painting has been ascribed to the 7th century by V.A. Smith,
but the fact that the deities are provided with haloes and the
general character of the drawing would indicate a much later
date. In caves on the adjoining hill of Dimbulagala, there
were, before a fanatic recently obliterated them, fragmentary
remains of paintings of the first half of the 12th century; the
same date appears to be reasonable for the frescoes at Pulli¬
goda-galge.
The paintings on the walls of the shrine anciently called
Tivamka-patima-ghara, at the mediaeval capital Polonnaruva,
dating from the reign of Parakramabahu I (1153-1186 A.D.)
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
or the decades immediately following, are, next to those of
Sigiri, the most important monuments of pictorial art which
Ceylon possesses. They prove that the classical tradition of
Indian painting, represented at Ajanta and Bagh, was kept
alive in Ceylon after it had lost its vitality in India itself.
These paintings have suffered badly from neglect since they
were first brought to light over half a century ago, but what
remains today is impressive enough.
As is to be expected of paintings in a building dedicated to
religion, their subjects are of an edifying nature, and the
artists seem to have followed a set scheme in. the decoration
of the walls. Scenes illustrating the previous lives of the
Buddha, while he was yet perfecting the virtues which led to
the final attainment of Supreme Wisdom the Jataka Stories,
as they are known among the Buddhists are painted on the
walls of the vestibule; the inner sanctum was reserved for
scenes depicting episodes in the life of the Buddha after the
Great Awakening.
. Almost every shrine at Polonnaruva of the Xllth century
contained frescoes on the walls; even the exterior was
brilliantly painted with floral designs, as may be judged from
traces yet visible. Apart from the frescoes in the Tivamka
shrine, however, the only noteworthy example of a painting
at Polonnaruva is the figure of a bearded old man in the
rock-cut shrine at the Gal Vihara monastery. The centre of
the rock wall at the back of the cave is occupied by a Buddha
image in high relief.
Ancient works inspire
cultural renaissance
The classical school of Sinhalese painting seems to have
ceased to exist after the fall of the Polonnaruva king¬
dom. At any rate, we do not possess any examples of
its work after the 13th century. It is from the 17th and 18th
centuries that we have, once again, examples of the work
of a school of indigenous painters. This school does not seem
to have had its roots in the artistic traditions which created
the masterpieces of Sigiri and Polonnaruva.
The subjects painted by Kandyan artists, on the other hand,
have much in common with those of earlier masters. The
representations of Jataka Stories were as popular then as at
any other epoch in the history of Buddhism.
Paintings of this school are found today at Degaldoruva
near the hill-capital, Kandy, at Dambulla in the Mátale District,
an impressive cave temple dating from pre-Christian times, but
redecorated in the 18th century, and at Ridi Vihara and
Kaballalena, shrines of similar historical character in the
Kurunagala District. Artists of this school were employed to
paint shrines built in the Maritime Provinces in Dutch and
early British times; for instance, Mulgirigala in the Hamban-
tota District and Telvatta in the Galle District.
It will thus be seen that there was considerable artistic acti¬
vity among painters in Ceylon during the course of its history
of over two thousand years, and that the old masters, mostly
anonymous, have succeeded in creating works of a high aesthe¬
tic standard. These ancient works of art have had and still
have a profound influence on the artists of present-day Ceylon,
who are striving to bring about a cultural renaissance in the
Island. The splendid colour reproductions of selected
examples from the pictorial art of ancient Ceylon, which
Unesco is now making available to lovers of art throughout
the world, will undoubtedly result in gaining for them a far
greater circle of admirers than they have ever had.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
One of the least-known chapters in
the history of European painting
is the one written from mediaeval
times up to the Renaissance in lands
which are today encompassed by the
frontiers of Czechoslovakia. The Ro¬
manesque and Gothic art treasures of
Czechoslovakia have been carefully pre¬
served in its museums, castles and ca¬
thedrals but until recently they had never
been displayed outside its borders.
This year, for the first time, they were
shown abroad at an exhibition of ancient
Czech art at the Musée des Arts Déco¬
ratifs in Paris. The treasures assembled
in Paris included paintings, sculpture,
richly illuminated manuscripts dating
from the early Middle Ages down to the
Renaissance, rare examples of jewellery
and unusual prehistoric artifacts. It was
more than a unique exhibition; it was the
revelation of an art development practic¬
ally unknown to the world.
Particularly revealing was the art of
the 14th and 15th centuries which
marked a high point in the development
of Czechoslovak art.
However, in the old Czechoslovak
lands, as elsewhere, Gothic art did not
originate spontaneously. All great
artists have not only precursors but also
those who continué their work, and each
one builds on the achievements of
others. Prior to Gothic art there had
been a rich and complex evolution going
back to the earliest times. The country
stood at an important cross-roads of
Europe and this had a direct influence
on artistic development through the
contacts it facilitated with nearby lands.
These contacts began in very early
times. Recently, for example, traces
have been discovered of Christian cul¬
tural penetration in the 8th century.
The latest excavation of the foundations
of pre-Romanesque buildings and the
frequent discovery of large edifices, iden¬
tified as monasteries and churches, and
of houses in Prague all demonstrate the
importance of the initial period of Me¬
diaeval art in Czechoslovakia as well as
its astonishing wealth.
Though Romanesque art may. have
developed hesitantly in terms of figura¬
tive sculpture, the art of illuminating ma¬
nuscripts was already well established by
the end of the first millenium and its
masters went on to produce some extra¬
ordinary works.
As the Gothic period began the new
art found here a fertile soil for its deve¬
lopment. The representation of the
human form became of prime impor¬
tance,, inspiring masterpieces which
revealed a progressive emancipation from
the Byzantine influence.
With the development of Gothic art
during the 14th century and until the
revolt of the Hussites, religious ideas
themselves became more humanized.
The first Madonnas, dating from this
period, already reflect the artists' urge
to express the passions and emotions of
their fellow men.
This same artistic feeling radiates
from the countenance of the Virgins,
which found their most graceful expres¬
sion in the "Beautiful Czech Madonnas."
Yet it is also found in many other com¬
positions and notably in the magnificent
works of Theodoric, a master painter at
the court of Charles IV, whose paintings
are imbued with this spirit.
The Golden Age of Czech art indeed
owes much to Charles IV. The
son of King John of Luxembourg
(known as John the Blind), Charles was
brought up at the French Court in close
contact with great European humanists.
He built the castle of Karlstein close to
Prague and for its decoration he ordered
many paintings and frescoes. The walls
of the chapel at Karlstein The Chapel
of the Holy Crossare decorated with
Theodoric's paintings representing the
heads of saints.
Another great painter of this period
was the Master of Trebon (his real name
is unknown). Several of his works,
including The Entombment, Christ on
the Mount of Olives and The Resur¬
rection, rank among the outstanding
masterpieces of European mediaeval
painting. With a masterly use of shad¬
ing he has given them a plastic quality,
infusing into his scenes remarkable
effects of depth, breadth and intensity.
In the first half of the 15th century,
artists continued to draw inspiration
from the traditions of the previous epoch,
but added some new characteristics such
as landscapes in which the influence of
Dutch painters was apparent. At the
end of the 15th century and at the start
of the 16th, the Gothic style was losing
its vitality as the dawn of the Renais¬
sance began to shed its immortal light.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
Josef Ehrn, Prague
THE MADONNA OF STRAKONITZ (detail) is one of the "Beautiful Czech Madonnas" which mark the zenith of Czech art in both sculpture
and painting and the full development of its originality. Dating from the middle of the I 4th century, it is carved in wood like most of the Madon¬
nas of this period. Originally in the church of St. Procopius at Strakonitz, it is now in the National Gallery, Prague. Masterpieces displayed at the
Musée des Arts Décoratifs, Paris, this year, revealed for the first time outside Czechoslovakia the wealth of this little-known art.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
CZECH ART (Continued)
KNEELING SHEPHERD, an early 16th-
century wooden statue from the church of
St. James at Levoca In Slovakia. This is not
the work of a Czech sculptor. It was carved
by Master Paul of Levoca, the most outstand¬
ing of the Late Gothic artists of Slovakia
whose stylistic conception markedly influenced
the development of 16th-century Slovak art.
Tibor Honty, Prague
THE VIRGIN AND CHILD, a wooden
statue (c. 1390) from the church of St. Bar¬
tholomew (famed for its soaring, 337 ft.
spire) at Pilsen in Bohemia. Recent research
has Identified it as the work of the finest
of the Czech sculptors of that period.
National Gallery, Prague
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1937
National Gallery, Prague
THE APOSTLE (DETAIL). MID-UTH-CENTURY WOOD STATUE FROM CHURCH OF ST. JAMES AT BRNO. NOW IN BRNO'S MORAVIAN MUSEUM
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
mlmmâmmàm
imam tints mtus fir
ïfitotîotîmiitfnitrî
*r-faJ&fytto imtoitirmrmt
tiimmnttrmmvm
tofl qui troptât tt
iômttiinin Vitó
Iâ6 fOfttfftr CVttlOltCf
rdticr tonnas nttis
|itoffmt-6iapamer-
iOfâmomits Jtr
'ftttfliKft*
Oltrpitf
V_>\amrrorá
avattvfiîoimt
tiamüspfttmife
imams mimar
cjb mtirptajamar
^pt.MrtammGil
mm- «Dmami fo
]triyi4îVu
limita
íunrxim
iiîimfvmjmrsv
movatmttimuttt
iingflûimmiimJ
tfrnaian ftiftipor
vounntpttiftiipii
nomits-vrwtivf
trfimifaganmô
itmisattstw/
Ï4
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Unknown treasure
In the Middle Ages illuminated manuscripts
were among the greatest artistic treasures of
Bohemia and Moravia. Recently, when some
of (the most remarkable of these manuscripts
dating from early mediaeval times to the Re¬
naissance were exhibited at the Musée des Arts
Décoratifs in Paris, they could truly be described
as "unknown treasures". The forthcoming
publication of the album, Czechoslovakia - Ro¬
manesque and Gothic Illuminated Manuscripts In
the Unesco World Art Series will bring these
treasures within the reach of all countries. On
these pages we reproduce three of the manu¬
scripts which will appear In colour in the Unesco
Album. (A fourth manuscript is reproduced in
colour on page 22 of this issue):
The Annunciation (opposite page) is from the
missal of the Bishop of Olomouc, probably John
of Streda. The Bishop is depicted kneeling at
the feet of the Virgin. In the centre of the
bottom margin are shown the arms of the
Bishopric of Olomouc. The missal (c. 1364),
is now In the St. Guy Capitulary Library, Prague.
The Embrace of Christ and the Holy Mother
(below, left) is from the famous Passional of
the Abbess Cunegonde and is now in the Uni¬
versity Library, Prague. It was copied and illu¬
minated about 1320 for Cunegonde, daughter
of a King of Bohemia and abbess of a Prague
convent. Her death in 1321 interrupted the
work and the manuscript remains unfinished.
Genealogy of Christ (below, right). Page of a
gospel book which was originally in the Vys-
cherad Capitulary Church, Prague. It is now in the
Library of the National Museum, Prague. This
work, probably executed for the coro¬
nation of King Vratislav in 1085, is also refer¬
red to as the Gospel Book of the Coronation.
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
CHURCH DIGNITARY executing a manuscript. Painting by the master
painter Theodoric who, as royal artist to the Emperor Charles IV, worked
for ten years (1357-1367) at Karlstein Castle, where the panel remains.
quAjifcniufmjríiuí
¿fcrntyttfrofiairti
Ufrntttbttiuyci
töinftstfamiiifem)
ttfentfWflWttrafo
uttftótmoulttttrí
ttpHtftuutfmeutn
fmetfll0u*ffl4tftai
rat»)»
^i-^â ^ a\Mm f mm) mtommÊm\^*^^Â^^ *t% i
gttt-jdtn premaní pi
ftytib/ttttiititftfittni
ôuttujtrfoamâsoi
taw (MJdTtftmnon
tatra&rtU0tâiU'$4i
W^rmmtrrmmmmw' W mymrm^^mwmjm^^mt ^mr ^m^r
Wilma qwdfztáats
^tfintt mout mttru
mftrttttuHicdfltttfl
rejtmaoquÄmfmi
âbytttttumetttft'iti
tin*latumCuitó
mdatiimttdtiinp
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
CZECH ART (Continued)
*'
THE RETABLE OF ST. GEORGE (c. 1470). Detail of the central panel of a Triptych representing
the Dormition of the Virgin. This Tryptich was originally in the church of the Benedictine Monastery
at Hradcany and is now in the National Gallery, Prague. It is attributed to a painter, simply identified
as the The Master of the Retable of St. George, one of the greatest late I Sth-century Czech artists.
VOTIVE PAINTING of John Ocko of Vlasim, Archbishop of Prague. Left, the Emperor Charles IV
(detail of the upper section of the panel). Right, Saint Ludmilla (detail of the lower section). This
panel is originally believed to have come from the chapel of Roudnitz Castle, the former residence of
the Archbishops of Prague. It is now in mediaevel art collection of the National Gallery, Prague.
Photos National Gallery, Prague
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1957
Letters to the Editor
GREAT LITERATURE
Sir,
As a schoolmaster in a secondary
school, may I thank you and your staff
for your excellent production... Of
particular interest to me has been the
topic of your June, 1957 number
("Great Literature of East and West").
I would, however, like to see the
activities in this field widened to
include the publication of books,
suitably edited for use in schools, on the
literature of each country in the
Organization. So much valuable under¬
standing of another's country can be
obtained through its literature, and I
feel that the foundations of this under¬
standing should come during one's
school life. Whilst I admire the work
of Unesco in this field, I am
disappointed to see it only at adult
level, and I wonder if work is being
done, or can be done, to cater for that
essential age, early adolescence.
John H. Hemsley
Leicester, England
Ed. note: Budgetary considerations at the
present time limit the Unesco Translations
Programme to the areas described in the
June issue. However in its 1958 pro¬
gramme Unesco will sponsor the prepara¬
tion of books suitable for schools, on
the important elements in the culture in
its Member States, particularly for school
libraries of other countries. Unesco is
also studying the production of booklets on
the different aspects of civilizations in
East and West, designed for readers
of secondary school educational level.
CHILD CARE IN DAHOMEY
Sir,
In "A Woman's Life in an African
Village" (May, 1957) Claudie Hauferlin
wrote: "So many names here recall
that infant mortality is the great
scourge of the countryside"... and later,
in the same article: "I seldom hear
children cry... A child's mother feeds
him when he is hungry and puts him to
sleep when he is tired, and he doesn't
seem any the worse for it." Perhaps
this applies to those who survive. But
what about the many others... why have
they died? Don't you think it would
be a good idea to change the method
and to try to give Dahoman mothers a
few ideas about child care?
Madame Gretz
Paris, France
Ed. note: Replying to our reader,
Claudie Hauferlin has written, in part:
"I wished to emphasize the care and
attention that Dahoman mothers show in
the upbringing of their children. This does
not mean that the upbringing takes place
in an environment in which rules of
modern hygiene are observed. The
question of hygiene is something quite
different. My aim was above all to show
that the African mother satisfies the
desires of the child at the time it expresses
them. I believe, by the way, that this is
a form of education whose beneficial
effects on the development of a child have
been recognized. As regards the spreading
of our ideas about bringing up children, it
is true that some of these could usefully
be introduced into rural communities, in
particular the rules relating to food,
hygiene and the protection of children
against certain infections. This, of course,
raises the problem of transforming African
societies, i.e. the provision of capital and
of trained personnel. Such questions are
beyond the scope of the article which
simply aimed to show the aspects of a
woman's daily life.
SOUND LIBRARIES FOR ALL
Sir,
From your issue on "Great Literature
of East and West" (June, 1957) I was
pleased to learn that Unesco is
arranging the translation and publication
of books... Consideration of this fine
undertaking prompts me to propose
the setting up of international
sound libraries in which tape-recorders
equipped with earphones would be
installed. All the works of international
literature, recorded and thus conserving
all the charm of their original languages,
could be collected there. Visitors would
have the choice of the best that exists
poetry, music and, in fact, everything
which beautifies each part of the world.
Would not this be a window opened on
universal culture ? Book publishing is
an expensive business and hundreds of
thousands must be sold if a deficit is to
be avoided. Sound-recording is a rapid
process and the use of a tape recorder
is not costly. The creation of free
centres of universal literature, accessible
to millions of people, would provide a
rapid solution to the problem a better
solution than the building up of
individual libraries. International Pub¬
lic Sound Libraries in each of the
world's capitals that should be a
slogan for Unesco.
V.P. Basharin
Moscow, U.S.S.R.
40 JUMPS THROUGH
THE UNIVERSE
Sir,
With its issue of May 1957 The
Unesco Courier marked still another
success. "Forty Jumps Through the
Universe" (An imaginary journey
through space into the worlds of the
infinitely large and the infinitely small),
is an absorbing and instructive article.
Raymond Bossy
Geneva, Switzerland
Sir,
The article by Kees Boeke (author of
"Forty Jumps") is one of the most
fascinating and interesting which it has
been my privilege to study...
C.B. Combe
Randwick, N.S.W., Australia
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom the English, French, Spanish
. and Russian editions of the UNESCO
COURIER can be obtained are listed
below.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Dep¬
artment, Royal Afghan Ministry of Educ¬
ation, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 303 Flinders Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, 15 rue
du Tilleul, Genval (Brabant). 100 Belgian
francs.
CANADA. University ol Toronto Press,
Baldwin House, 33 Sc. Georges Street,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
nf Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, 1 00 Parsons Road Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section 1,-Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kleber. Paris, 16'. C.C.P.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G..
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens,
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mounc Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I ; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Raikamal Publicat¬
ions Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby Road,
Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission lor
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P.O. B. 4154, Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Librería Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central. Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhouc, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road. Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall.
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Ouiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. A'B CE. Fritzes, Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
RSmistrasse, Zurich.
Payor, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva.
6.50 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete. 2 rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panic, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma)
549. Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724. Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569. London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y,
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga
Terazij« 27/1 I, Belgrade.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
ilJNESCO BOOKS IN MOSCOW:
Unesco publications displayed recently in
the Soviet State Library of Foreign
Literature in Moscow attracted considerable
attention. They included publications
issued by Unesco itself, and those produced
by other organizations with Unesco's
assistance. U.S.S.R. public interest in the
work of this U.N. Agency has greatly
increased since Russian editions of The
Unesco Courier and the Unesco Bulletin
For Libraries appeared this year. The
recent exhibit in Moscow has brought many
requests to the Library of Foreign Literature
for other publications.
HEALTHY DISH WITH FISH:
Several hundred people in the village of
Nongkhorn in the Ubol province of
Thailand are taking part in an
experiment which may have a radical
effect on the diets of this protein-starved
region of the country. Supervised by
nutritionists of the Food and Agriculture
Organization, 150 families receive a
daily ration of 15 grammes of fish meal
to supplement their meagre protein
intake. Simple recipes, supplied by
the Government's Health Department,
explain how. to use the fish flour in
curries, fish pastes and vegetable dishes.
If the experiment is successful the
Department of Fisheries will supply the
flour at a low cost to all villages in the
province. The project is being carried
out by trainees of the Thailand-UtiESCO
Fundamental Education project who will
eventually qualify as social and
educational workers.
íVeW HOME FOR A MODEL
LIBRARY: Work has started on a new
building to house the Medellin Public
Library, the pilot-project created in 1954
by the Government of Colombia and
Unesco as a model for other Latin
American libraries. When completed next
year the library will be one of the most
up-to-date on the Continent. Need for new
premises followed the Library's rapid
expansion. From October 1954 to April
1957 a million books were loaned to readers
in Medellin and nearby rural areas. The
Library has over 36,000 volumes and some
26,000 members and issues about 23,000
books monthly. Its cultural activities'
programme includes concerts, lectures,
group discussions, story hours, drawing and
singing courses for children, language and
film clubs, exhibitions and TV viewing.
LESS MATERNAL MORTALITY:
A decrease of between thirty to ninety
per cent in maternal mortality has taken
place in the last 20' years, according to
a recent report of the World Health
Organization, covering 49 countries and
territories. The lowest maternal death
rate is recorded in the United States,
where it is 0.5 per 1,000 live births for
the population as a whole. The
decrease is most spectacular in countries
undergoing rapid development. In
Ceylon, for example, the drop has been,
from 20.5 to 4.1 per 1,000 live births
during the 20 years under review.
.Indian frescoes for France:
As a contribution to Unesco's Maj'or
Project for increasing understanding
between East and West, an exhibition of
32 reproductions in colour of the famed
frescoes in the Ajanta Caves in Southern
India will soon be touring French cities.
Inaugurated recently in Paris, the exhibition
was organized by the French National
Commission for Unesco and the Federation
of Friends of Unesco Clubs in France, and
is intended to provide an introduction to
Indian art of the 5th and 6th centuries, of
which these frescoes provide very fine
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe to THE UNESCO COURIER today
Fill In this subscription blank and mail it with your cheque or money order
to our local agent in your country listed on page 37
Please enter my subscription for THE UNESCO COURIER
D One year
enclosed
$3.00;l0/-stg.; 500 French francs Cheque /Money Order
O Two years $5.50; £1 stg.; 1,000 French francs Please bill me
Name	
Address
City		Country	Profession	
examples. The reproductions are selected
from the album "Paintings from Ajanta
Caves", in the Unesco World Art Series.
HOW TO PROTECT AGAINST
RADIATION: Physicists, chemists and
engineers from countries in Europe and
the Eastern Mediterranean region re¬
cently attended an international course
in protection against atomic radiation
arranged by the World Health Organiza¬
tion and the Belgian Government, at the
Centre of Studies for Applications of
Nuclear Energy, at Mol in Belgium.
The course included instruction in the
general principles of health physics,
protection of workers at reactors and
radio-chemical laboratories, monitoring
methods and dosimetry. It also dealt
with safety measures in uranium and
plutonium factories, hazards and prob¬
lems connected with the selection of
reactor sites, waste disposal and safety
factors in laboratory design.
*SuNRISE SEMESTER': New York
booksellers recently had unprecedented
demands for Stendhal's novel The Red and
the Black following the selection of the
book for the opening session of a televised
college course on Comparative Literature,
sponsored by New York University. The
course, entitled "Sunrise Semester", consists
of 76 half-hour sessions given at 6.30 a.m.
each weekday, and students officially
registered for it will receive a final
examination at the University which will
count towards their degree. So far, some¬
thing like 120,000 New Yorkers are said to
be viewing the programme.
IT'S UP TO THE TEACHER:
Some of the teachers attending a recent
international seminar at Lake Maggiore,
Italy, were unpleasantly surprised to see
how their countries were represented in
school books used in other countries.
They were meeting to discuss "The
teacher's contribution to international
understanding" , at a seminar organized
by the Unesco Institute for Education
in Hamburg, the Italian National
Commission for Unesco and "Umani-
taria", the Italian adult education
organization. Each teacher brought
along history, geography and foreign
language textbooks from his school, and
these books were compared and
discussed. While agreeing that text¬
books should be revised in a spirit of
international understanding, participants
felt that the real task lay with the
teacher. It is his personal attitude
towards other countries which in¬
fluences his pupils more than the
objective facts he might impart.
*
CORRECTION
In our last issue, the name of Arthur
C. Clarke, author of "The Challenge of the
Spaceship" was given incorrectly as Arthur
Clark. We regret this typographical error.
u
Z
<
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
CATHERINE
KARLSTEJN.
st of wooden
statue at Karlstejn
castle, Czechoslo¬
vakia. About 1400.
(Photo Josef
Ehm, Prague)
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
&"*.
fk
J¡,*. li -
¡ft '
M
S^^^MT
,*r- '
A'Jc»
./-. &
**«
vi^.
í#í:
4^5 ïj&
/«V?
>»-
» ** i'à
'»" '
0Fi WALL PAiNTOfJS
F. BONAMPÁ"
JM "MEXICO
]]>
</page>
</document>
