<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068337eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
«'
<+. *
&W
4 <P	
*v&
..» j
*
^S**»
V
X
THE NEW WORLD
OF THE OCEAN
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live . . .
42 Benin
Village on stilts
In Ganvié, a lagoon village in the coastal region of Benin, dugout canoes ply between thatched-roof
dwellings built on piles in the water. One of Africa's smallest States, Benin consists of a long wedge
of territory extending some 675 kilometres from the Niger, which forms part of its northern frontier,
to the Atlantic where it has a 125-kilometre seaboard. The land rises from the narrow coastal strip to
a swampy, forested plateau and then to highlands in the north. With an estimated population of
some 3.5 million, most of whom live in the hot, humid southern third of the country, Benin takes its
name from a kingdom that flourished in the West African forest region between the 14th and 17th
centuries.
©
Ï
S %
;
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the world
Editorial
FUELLED by the sun, the ocean is the powerhouse of
the earth; the source of all life, it is a huge heat
exchanger that regulates our climate, it is a source of
food, minerals and energy, it offers the cheapest form of
transport available to us, and, last but not least, with its
restless, ever-changing beauty it seems to have been de¬
signed for the delight of mankind.
Today, scientists and world leaders are looking more and
more to the ocean from which we came as a reserve from
which to meet the needs of a growing world population. If
the potentially huge resources of the ocean are to be proper¬
ly exploited for the benefit of all mankind, a major interna¬
tional co-operative effort involving scientific research, eco¬
nomic assessment and the institution of acceptable control
mechanisms is required. It is with these problems that this
issue of the Unesco Courier is chiefly concerned.
In all this Unesco has a major role to play. For years
Unesco's Marine Sciences Division has been working to
strengthen the research institutions and training capability of
developing countries through programmes such as COMAR
(Major Interregional Project on Research and Training
leading to the Integrated Management of Coastal Systems).
The Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission (IOC),
founded twenty-five years ago under the aegis of Unesco,
has been concerned with such tasks as the planning, promo¬
tion and co-ordination of co-operative international re¬
search, for example, in the fields of ocean dynamics and
climate, and the preparation of the General Bathymétrie
Chart of the Oceans. With the adoption in 1982 by the
General Assembly of the United Nations of the Convention
on the Law of the Sea, the responsibilities of the IOC are
destined to be greatly increased.
It is a startling fact that in many respects we know more
about the moon than we do about the vast mass of water that
covers over two-thirds of the surface of our planet. Now
more than ever before the time is ripe for a combined
international exploration of "the last frontier".
Front Cover: Earth, the "Blue Planet", photographed from Apollo
11, the spacecraft that first took men to the moon.
Back Cover: Detail from a relief map of the ocean floor showing the
huge expanse of the Pacific Ocean
Editor-in-chief : Edouard Glissant
February 1986
39th year
Photo Drachoussoff © A.A.A. Photo, Paris
4 Blue planet
Unique in the solar system, only the earth
has rain, rivers and oceans
by Howard Brabyn
7 The restless currents
8 A fortune on the sea bed
9 Time and tide
11 Charting the ocean floor
by Dale Krause and Jacques Richardson
14 A world map of the sea depths
16 Glossary
18 The nature and purpose of marine science
23 Satellites scan the ocean
Modern technology in the service of oceanography
by D. James Baker
26 Twenty-five years of research
The Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission
28 The challenge of the new ocean regime
by Mario Ruivo
30 Highlights of the Convention
on the Law of the Sea
32 Living treasures of the deep
Marine flora and fauna can provide food,
medicines and information about the origins of life
by Vitali Voitov
34 World fisheries face growing demand
37 Year of peace: 2
2 A time to live ...
BENIN: Village on stilts
Published monthly in 32 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish A selection in Braille is published
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish quarterly in English, French,
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque Spanish and Korean
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
German Persian Korean Bulgarian ISSN 0041-5278
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
No 2 - 1986 -CPD -86-1 -431 A
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
©
Blueplanet
Unique in the solar system,
only the earth has rain,
rivers and oceans
by Howard Brabyn
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The enormous surface area of the world
ocean is revealed by this map, known to
map-makers as a homolographic, equal-
area projection.
OUR ancestors made a major, if
understandable, mistake when
they named our planet "Earth".
They believed that, with the exception of
some comparatively small bodies of wa¬
ter such as the Mediterranean and the
Black Sea, the surface of our world con¬
sisted almost entirely of rocks and soil.
They knew, of course, of the existence
of other waters but believed them to be
part of the river Oceanus which encircled
the world and from which sprang all other
rivers and seas. Even as late as the six¬
teenth century, the great Flemish geog¬
rapher Gerardus Mercator (1512-1594),
the father of the science of cartography,
believed that the earth was about equally
divided between land and water and that
there was a vast undiscovered land mass
in the southern hemisphere to balance
the great expanses of Europe, Asia and
North America that lie within the north¬
ern hemisphere.
The Ancients would have been
astounded to learn that water covers 70.8
per cent of the surface of the earth and to
see the satellite photographs that confirm
the excited words of twentieth-century
astronauts as they watched the wonder of
earthrise from the arid, barren expanse of
the moon: "Our planet is blue! Our
planet is beautiful!"
The earth, in fact, is uniquely favoured
among the planets of the solar system. It
alone has a surface temperature that per¬
mits water to exist in all three forms
liquid, solid and gas; it alone, as far as we
can tell , has rain , rivers and oceans. To be
strictly accurate we should say ocean,
since what geographers conventionally
define as the Pacific, Atlantic, Indian,
Arctic and Antarctic oceans in fact con¬
stitute a single body of salt water from
which the continents emerge like islands.
This vast, endlessly churning volume of
liquid was the source of life on earth and
remains essential to its continued ex¬
istence. Acting as a huge heat reservoir it
moulds our climate, levelling out the ex¬
tremes of temperature that would other¬
wise prevail over the earth, creating de¬
serts and frozen wastes. It is a major
source of food and a potential source of
valuable minerals and energy. It is a high¬
ly efficient waste disposal unit and pro¬
vides the least expensive form of trans¬
port known to man. Its margins are man¬
kind's favourite playground and its gran¬
deur and beauty have inspired poets
throughout the ages.
Nobody really knows for certain how
the oceans were formed. Some scientists
believe that the water came from thick
clouds that surrounded the earth and
that, as the earth cooled, rain fell from
the clouds in a continuous downpour last¬
ing hundreds of years. However, the
newly-formed earth of 4,500 million
years ago was very different from the
earth we know today. It may have been a
much larger planet with a molten core of
rock and a vast atmosphere of cosmic
gases. Because such volatile gases as
neon and xenon are extremely rare in our
present atmosphere as compared with the
cosmic mix, it is generally thought that
this early atmosphere was stripped away,
perhaps during a period of higher heat
output from the sun, and that our present
atmosphere and surface waters derive en¬
tirely from the earth itself.
However, if water, which has a
molecular weight of eighteen, which is
less than the atomic weight of neon, had
been suspended in the atmosphere, it too
would have been swept away. Many sci¬
entists therefore believe that the water
must have been tied up in compounds,
perhaps hydrated silicates, until the earth
had formed. Water would then have been
released in liquid form as the rocks
cooled some time during the first
thousand million years of the earth's his¬
tory.
Although we may still have doubts
about its origin, we have learned a great
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The composition of sea water
deal about the ocean of today. The statis¬
tics are impressive. It has a volume of
1,370 million cubic kilometres and a sur¬
face area of 361 million square
kilometres. It accounts for just under
98.8 per cent of the total hydrosphere,
the remainder being made up of ice (1.2
per cent), and water in rivers and lakes
(0.002 per cent) and the atmosphere
(0.0008 per cent).
The average depth of the ocean has
been estimated at 3,790 metres, consider¬
ably greater than the average elevation of
the land above sea level, which is 840
metres. The point of maximum depth of
the ocean is to be found in the Mariana
Trench , between the islands of Guam and
Yap, some 11,000 metres below the sur¬
face öf the Pacific. If Mount Everest were
to be placed in the Trench, its summit
would be about two kilometres below the
ocean surface.
Locked up in all this water is a great
variety of salts and minerals in solution.
In fact, sea water contains all the ele¬
ments that make up the minerals in the
earth's crust. At one time it was thought
that the salinity of the modern ocean was
due to salts derived from rock weathering
and transported to the ocean by rivers.
This would mean, however, that the
salinity of the ocean was steadily in¬
creasing, whereas calculations have
shown that the ocean probably acquired
its modern characteristics between 1,500
million and 2,000 million years ago and
that, for at least 100 million years, the
oceanic system has been in a steady state
with a fixed chemical composition. This
implies that inflow and outflow of ele¬
ments must be basically in equilibrium
and that dissolved elements carried to the
ocean in rivers and in rain must precipi¬
tate from ocean water or be cycled back
through the atmosphere by evaporation
to fall on the continents.
The atmosphere and the ocean are in¬
extricably linked. The wind, in combina¬
tion with the heat of the sun and the
rotation of the earth, powers the mighty
ocean currents, moving huge volumes of
water in giant whirlpool motions that ro¬
tate clockwise in the northern hemi¬
sphere and anti-clockwise in the southern
hemisphere (see box page 7). These cur¬
rents carry staggering amounts of water.
It is estimated, for example, that the Gulf
Stream, an "ocean river" some eighty
kilometres wide and 450 metres deep,
propels more than 4,000 million tons of
water a minute.
Movement of deep-ocean waters is
governed primarily by variations in
temperature and salinity. Cold water is
heavier than warm water because it con¬
tracts as it cools (although, unlike other
liquids it expands when it solidifies into
ice) and tends to sink. Salt also makes
water heavy and although salinity in the
CONTINUED PAGE 9
The constituents of sea water include dissolved inorganic sub¬
stances (mineral salts), dissolved gases and dissolved organic
substances. Water is, in fact, the most powerful solvent of all liquids
and all the natural elements can be found in sea water. The most
common of these elements are chlorine (55 per cent) and sodium
(31 per cent) which combine in the ocean to form sodium
chloride common table salt. Of all these elements only sodium
chloride, magnesium and bromine are at present being extracted in
significant amounts.
In the open ocean the salinity of water varies only between very
narrow limits, average salinity being about thirty-five parts of salt to
a thousand parts of water.
There are two rather curious parallels between sea water and
the liquids of the human body: the ocean covers 70 per cent of the
surface of the globe 70 per cent of the human body consists of
water; a comparison of the composition of sea water and human
body fluids shows that the proportions of the elements are largely
the same.
57 OF THE ELEMENTS THAT MAKE UP
THE "SALT" OF SEA WATER"
(In order of their abundance)
Chlorine Lithium Uranium Cadmium
Sodium Rubidium Nickel Tungsten
Magnesium Phosphorus Vanadium Xenon
Sulphur Iodine Manganese Germanium
Calcium Barium Titanium Chromium
Potassium Indium Antimony Thorium
Bromine Zinc Cobalt Scandium
Carbon Iron Cesium Lead
Strontium Aluminium Cerium Mercury
Boron Molybdenum Yttrium Gallium
Silicon Selenium Silver Bismuth
Fluorine Tin Lanthanum Niobium
Argon Copper Krypton Thallium
Nitrogen Arsenic Neon Helium
Gold
Chlorine
Sodium
Other
JÉ
o
>-
ï
ID
2
C I
I
cu ^ >^
E ^ jS
^ s"^ _s^
¿i j**1 r
c: jt
1 H
	
^y S^
E / ^ /^
b S s ¿<
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
B
The restless currents
The waters of the ocean never stop moving. Most of us think of this
motion in terms of the waves and tidal movements that we can
observe for ourselves whenever we go to the coast. Less im¬
mediately apparent to the casual observer, however, are the great
ocean currents, well-defined streams that flow over parts of the
ocean in never-ending cycles.
Ocean currents are caused by a combination of three major
forces: the heat of the sun, the rotation of the earth and the
friction-force of the winds.
As the earth revolves round the sun it rotates on its own axis in
such a way that the direct rays of the sun strike the seas near the
equator, heating them up much more than the polar seas. As the
surface water at the equator heats up it expands, raising the sea
level at the equator almost imperceptibly but enough to create a
"slope". The water at the equator, therefore, tends to run
"downhill" towards the Poles.
Cold water is heavier than warm water, because water contracts
as it cools, and the colder water of the polar regions sinks beneath
the inflowing warm water from the equator and spreads slowly back
along the bottom towards the equator.
The rotation of the earth also has another curious effect on the
waters of the ocean and indeed on any moving object, such as a
ballistic missile, an artillery shell, or even a ball that is thrown,
although in the case of the ball its trajectory would be so short that
the effect would be imperceptible. This "Coriolis effect" as it is
called, after the French mathematician Gaspard Gustave de
Coriolis who first described it, causes such objects to be deflected
somewhat to the right in the northern hemisphere and to the left in
the southern hemisphere.
The winds too have a major influence on currents. The Trade
Winds, which blow steadily from the north-east, in the northern
hemisphere, and from the south-east, in the southern hemisphere,
towards the equatorial regions, are the force which powers the
great westward-moving currents just north and south of the
equator. But these winds too are subject to the Coriolis effect which
causes them to curve north and south away from the equator and
to circle back in the higher latitudes, driving the surface waters
before them from west to east.
The effect of all these factors combined is to set and keep in
motion the gigantic eddies of circling waters that make up the main
surface currents of the ocean.
Caused by the rotation of the earth, the
"Coriolis Effect" deflects winds and cur¬
rents to the right in the northern hemi¬
sphere and to the left in the southern hemi¬
sphere.
©
«J
CD
to
Ol
Ê
E
Also affected by the spin of the earth and
by heat from the sun, wind belts drive the
waters of the ocean; in the tropics the
Trade Windspush them westward towards
the equator, and in the higher latitudes the
Westerlies drive them in the opposite
direction.
A combination of three forces the heat of
the sun, the Coriolis Effect and the
winds causes the ocean currents to cir¬
culate clockwise in the northern hemi¬
sphere and anti-clockwise in the southern
hemisphere.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
A fortune on the sea bed
MANGANESE nodules occur mainly as a deposit in the deep
sea. These potato-shaped concretions are rich in man¬
ganese oxides and are present on most of the floor of the
deep ocean. However, their composition varies widely from place
to place, and only in a few areas do they contain sufficient
manganese, nickel, copper and cobalt, and other metals of possi¬
ble economic value, to be of interest. A combination of about 1 3 per
cent nickel, cobalt and copper, the most valuable metals, is re¬
garded as making the nodules an economically viable resource.
The main area where nodules of this grade occur in good
abundance is the north-eastern equatorial Pacific; this area has
been the subject of most research work. However, nodules of
similar composition occur in parts of the southern and western
Pacific and also in the central Indian Ocean, where Indian research
scientists are undertaking much work on them.
For a long time, high-grade nodules were thought to occur only at
great distances from land, but exciting discoveries have been
made recently within the two hundred-mile Exclusive Economic
Zones of some of the small developing island nations of the South
Pacific. These deposits belong to the adjacent islands themselves
and, if they were commercially recoverable, the island peoples
would benefit. This possibility has prompted the United Nations to
set up a development programme to organize further exploration in
these areas on behalf of the islands.
Another deposit, similar to manganese nodules, which has been
receiving much attention recently in the Pacific, is the so-called
cobalt-rich manganese crusts. The crusts are similar in their
overall composition to manganese nodules but are richer In cobalt,
up to 2 per cent, and lower in nickel and copper than the highest
grade nodules. Cobalt is a strategically valuable metal and only a
limited supply is available from mines on land, so these marine
deposits may provide an alternative future source of the metal.
Unlike nodules, which lie loose on the sea floor, crusts occur as
coatings on rock outcrops and can be up to several centimetres
thick. They occur at much shallower depths than most nodules,
which are richest below 4,500 metres, and the highest grade
deposits are present at less than 2,000 metres deep. In the Pacific
Ocean, depths of 2,000 metres are usually associated with sea-
mounts, sunken mountains that rise from the deep ocean floor and
which are often grouped into chains. Sometimes, one or more of
these seamounts breaks the surface to become an island, and
where this happens the deposits on the submerged part of the
island and on adjacent seamounts within the two hundred-mile
Exclusive Economic Zone belong to that island.
This discovery, like that of high-grade nodules near some is¬
lands in the Pacific, is stimulating a lot of work on cobalt-rich crusts.
Nowhere is this more so than in the Hawaiian Islands, where the
islands themselves are just the peaks at one end of a long
submarine mountain chain stretching across more than 1,500
kilometres of ocean all the way west to Midway Island.
David Cronan
Reader in marine geochemistry
Imperial College of Science
and Technology, London
Reproduced from a longer study
by courtesy of New Scientist magazine, London
h>&Z®
w.
3 . "5
»
, I
)
i
8
« ' \s , s >
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Time and tide
Tides, the periodical rise and fall of the waters of the ocean, are due
to the gravitational pull of the moon and, to a lesser extent, of the
sun. At most seaside places there are two tides a day, the average
time interval between two successive high waters being twelve
hours and twenty-five minutes.
When the moon is directly over any point in the ocean, it pulls the
water towards it causing a "doming up" of water under the moon.
On the side of the earth opposite to this point, however, the
centrifugal force generated by the rotation of the earth will exceed
the attractive pull of the moon, causing the water of the ocean to
tend to dome outwards. Thus high tides will occur at the same time
on opposite sides of the earth, rather than a high tide on one side
and a low tide on the other.
Low tides occur at points ninety degrees away because water is
flowing away from these areas towards the areas of high tides. In
other words, there is a horizontal flow from every point of the ocean
towards the points directly under or directly opposite the moon.
The gravitational pull of the sun, which is less than half that of the
moon, somewhat complicates matters. When there is a new moon,
the moon is situated between the earth and the sun so the
attraction of the sun and the moon reinforce each other. Two weeks
later, when the moon is full, it has moved round to the opposite side
of the earth to the sun so that the earth is between them and once
again they are pulling on the ocean, this time in opposite directions
but along the same axis. At these times the earth experiences its
highest tides, commonly known as spring tides.
At the quarters of the moon, when the sun and the moon are at
right angles to each other in relation to the earth, their respective
gravitational pulls tend partly to counteract each other. At these
times the tides, commonly called neap tides, are neither so high
nor so low.
The moon travels in an elliptical orbit in relation to the equator,
swinging back and forth over the northern and southern hemi¬
spheres. In some parts of the earth this inclination of the moon's
orbit, coupled with the fact that the axis of the earth is tilted in
relation to its orbit round the sun, produces diurnal tides (tides
occurring at intervals of twenty-four hours and fifty minutes) rather
than the semi-diurnal tides (tides occurring at intervals of twelve
hours and twenty-five minutes) described above. Semidiurnal tides
predominate in the Atlantic, whereas diurnal tides are found on the
coasts of Alaska, the Philippines and China.
At the times of new and full moon, the
earth, the moon and the sun are in line and
reinforce each other's pull on the oceans
on earth, causing the spring tides the
highest and the lowest tides of the lunar
month.
%
-c
"J>-* I.'
Spring Tides
During the first and last quarters of the
moon, the sun and the moon pull at right
angles to each other, causing the neap or
weak tides.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 6
open sea remains fairly constant at
around 3.5 per cent, water near freezing
ice will be heavier because extra salt is left
behind in the freezing process. As this
heavier, saltier water sinks it begins to
move along the ocean floor in the oppo¬
site direction to the surface current above
it.
It is this mechanism that is responsible
for the renewal of virtually enclosed
bodies of water such as the Mediterra¬
nean where salinity is high due to high
rates of evaporation. This increases the
density of the surface water which sinks
and begins to flow westwards through the
Straits of Gibraltar and out into the
Atlantic. Passing above this submarine
current, lighter water from the Atlantic
flows in to replace it.
The other great forces that act upon the
movement of the ocean are the attracting
force of the sun and the moon and the
centrifugal force resulting from the orbit¬
al movement of the earth round the sun
and the moon round the earth; these
cause the rhythmic movement of the wa¬
ters of^the ocean which we call tides (see
box this page). These same forces actual¬
ly move the earth itself and the atmos¬
phere as well, although the rise and fall of
the continents is so small as to be imper¬
ceptible.
Theocean has a powerful effect on
climate! Compared with the land, the
ocean heats slowly in summer and cools
slowly in winter, so its temperature is
much less variable; because of its huge
size it has a moderating effect on land and
air temperatures and helps to iron out
temperature extremes.
Curious as it may seem, the ocean floor
is much younger than the ocean it under¬
lies (the oldest sediments found so far by
deep-sea drilling are from the Upper
Jurassic period and are only about 150
million years old) and is continually being
added to by extrusion of new, initially
molten basaltic rock rising from the man¬
tle. As the upwelling molten rock solidi¬
fies on reaching the ocean floor it is
magnetized in the direction of the earth's
prevailing magnetic field. Magnetic pat¬
terns are established which can be dated
by reference to the time-scale of
geomagnetic reversals which occur at
irregular intervals of a few hundred
thousand years. Our knowledge of the
geology and topography of the ocean
floor has made giant strides during the
past twenty years, thanks largely to tech¬
nological advances which have made
possible improved bathymétrie and sub¬
marine geological mapping (see article
page 11).
The mineral resources of the sea bed,
unlike those contained in the overlying
waters, tend to occur in localized deposits
on top of and within the rocks and sedi¬
ments of the ocean floor. These potential
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
^ riches include: surface deposits such as
heavy metals, diamonds, sand, oyster
shell and gravel, and the much-publicized
nodules of manganese and phosphorite
that have formed by precipitation from
sea water; subsurface deposits, such as
coal and iron ore, which have been mined
since as early as the beginning of the
seventeenth century by tunnelling from
the land; and fluid and soluble minerals,
such as oil, gas, sulphur and potash,
which are extracted through boreholes.
At present oil and gas represent around
90 per cent in terms of value of all miner¬
als obtained from the oceans. As recov¬
ery techniques improve this situation is
likely to change rapidly and it was largely
in an attempt to ensure an equitable
share-out of what looks like being a new
minerals bonanza that the United Na¬
tions Convention on the Law of the Sea
was drawn up (see page 30).
Although all the chemical elements are
present in sea water itself, only magne¬
sium, bromine and sodium chloride
(common salt) are now being extracted in
significant quantities. The other resource
which is increasingly being extracted
from sea water is water itself fresh
water. Rising demand for fresh water and
improvements in technology are making
desalted water competitive in ever larger
areas of the world.
The ocean is a provider of food to eat as
well as of water to drink. Over the past
decade total catch from the sea has aver¬
aged 75 million tons (see box page 34).
Our present fishing methods, however,
are inefficient. We overfish certain spe¬
cies to the point where they are in danger
of complete extinction and reject others
which are equally valuable as a source of
protein. It has been estimated that with
efficient harvesting of all the fish of the
Relative sizes of the planets, arranged in
order of distance from the sun (but not
according to their respective distances
from each other).
sea, the ocean could provide a sustained
yield of around 2,000 million tons of food
annually.
The Japanese in particular are actively
developing methods of "fish-farming"
which hold great promise. Fish will re¬
main in an area convenient for fishing if a
food supply for them is artificially
created. For instance, by inducing up-
wellings of the nutrient-rich bottom
layers of ocean water, similar to the
naturally occurring upwelling that sus¬
tains the huge anchoveta fisheries off the
coast of Peru, the potential yield of the
ocean could be increased perhaps as
much as tenfold.
The ocean's potential as a source of
energy which can be harnessed to meet
man's needs is still largely hypothetical.
Only in a few places is it economic to
harness the energy locked up in the
world's tides. Only one large tidal power
plant has been built at La Ranee, in
France and there are thought to be only
about twenty-four potential tidal power
sites in the world. Research is continuing
on the extraction of the energy stored in
waves, but this is still at the early ex¬
perimental stage.
Greater hopes are placed in exploiting
the temperature differential between the
surface and the lower layers of the ocean
to generate electricity by means of a pro¬
cess known as Ocean Thermal Energy
Conversion. Experiments with this tech¬
nique undertaken by French researchers
have proved technically successful, but as
yet the technique remains uneconomic in
practice.
As man turns back again to the sea, the
source of all life, in an attempt to draw
even more heavily on its resources, he
will have to tread warily if he is not to
destroy it entirely. There was a time when
we could dump into the ocean the sewage
and other effluents and wastes from
homes and industry safe in the knowledge
that they would be rapidly dispersed, di¬
luted and degraded. But with the rapid
growth of world population and the con¬
centration of people in coastal areas,
both for industrial and recreational pur¬
poses, combined with the sheer bulk of
the material to be disposed of and the
inclusion in it of new, non-biodegradable
waste products, this is no longer possible.
Furthermore, lead in exhaust emissions
from cars and wind-borne toxic DDT re¬
sidues as well as agricultural fertilizers
and pesticides of all kinds are finding
their way into the ocean to add to the
pollution from oil spills, from radio-ac¬
tive fallout and from dumped radio-ac¬
tive wastes.
The ocean has been called "the last
frontier". We are rapidly acquiring the
basic knowledge and the technology
which will enable us to harvest the untold
riches of the sea; with the Convention on
the Law of the Sea we have the embryo of
a legal and institutional framework with¬
in which to reap this harvest to the best
advantage of all mankind and to correct
past errors due to ignorance, neglect and
greed.
HOWARD BRABYN, of the United Kingdom, isa
Paris-based writer and journalist with a special
interest in the popularization ofscience. He was
formerly Editor of the English edition of the
Unesco Courier.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Charting the oceanfloor
by Dale Krause
and Jacques Richardson
Portuguese nautical chart of the Atlantic
Ocean drawn on parchment by Pascoal
Roiz in 1633.
T
| HE tale of Aeneas, legendary hero
of ancient Greece and Rome, is
one of hazardous voyages back
and forth across the Mediterranean Sea,
between the Eurasian land-mass and
Africa. In his turbulent wanderings from
Troy to Carthage to Latium (Italy),
Aeneas is constantly in peril from the
hidden dangers of travelling over deep
waters. He loses his father, Anchises, as a
result of intemperate weather inevitably
attributed to the mystery of the ocean's
depths. The sea is thus an enigmatic en¬
vironment, threatening and incompre¬
hensible.
And so it remained until the great
marine explorations of the fifteenth to
nineteenth centuries. Only relatively re¬
cently have we begun to understand,
measure, evaluate and demystify what
lies in the salty deep of the world ocean.
We now know that although our planet
is made up essentially of soil, rock and
sand (in either solid or molten form),
r-
*
<
©( 4
-V
v.
»j£
I fyy-
E '-**.
*
i
k¿ 4
*
Ct-
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The earliest Surviving European Sea Chart, Photo taken tram The Drama of the Oceans © Abrams,
fne Carta Pisana (above) depicts the entire NewYork
Mediterranean. It is hand drawn on a
sheepskin and dates from about 1275.
Peoples with no tradition of the written
word used ingenious methods of pro¬
ducing navigation charts and maps.
Drawings show (above left) a Micronesian
navigation "chart" consisting of a lattice¬
work of sticks showing the relative posi¬
tions of the islands of the Marshall Islands
group, and (above right) an Eskimo "map"
carved from wood recovered from the sea.
Echo-sounders are used to chart the topo¬
graphy of the ocean floor. Left, a marine
scientist at work at an echo-sounder re¬
cording unit aboard the British research
ship Discovery.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
nearly 71 per cent of its surface is covered
by the sea. Of the remaining 29 per cent
of terrestrial or land formations, one-fifth
of all the continents are submerged as
"continental shelves". It may not seem
significant at first glance that 20 per cent
of the continents are under water, but this
represents a territorial land-mass equal to
that of Africa. This was not understood
by the ocean's first users (prehistoric man
and some of our less remote ancestors),
who perceived a sheet of water as a join¬
ing or interruption of two or more pieces
of land unaffected by what lay beneath.
As man's activities in fishing, sailing
and navigation, transport and the move¬
ment of navies became more far-ranging
and complex, it became necessary to
learn more about what lay beneath the
water. The explorations of Phoenician,
Indian, Chinese and Arab sailors pro¬
duced the first simple maps of the ocean.
The oldest existing chart of the sea, in the
form of a clay tablet, dates from the
Babylonian period of 4,500 years ago.
The Micronesians, using twigs and shells,
produced charts of the Pacific Ocean.
Gradually, our "road maps" of the sea,
or sailing charts, became more detailed
and complicated. Mariners recorded not
only depths, but also the locations of
obstacles such as large rocks, shoals and
reefs. They noted local and regional cur¬
rents, seasonal temperatures and salt
content. They compiled atlases of the
shapes of coastlines, islands, harbours,
river estuaries and deltas, beaches and
coastal vegetation, as well as catalogues
of fish and other inhabitants of salt water.
And when the first international meeting
of hydrographers (mappers of the sea)
was held in Belgium in 1853 to try to
understand the effects of the ocean and
weather on one another, it gave birth to
the new science of oceanography.
But it was not until the undersea man¬
oeuvres of navies during the principal
wars of the twentieth century that curios¬
ity and need drove governments, pe¬
troleum and mineral explorers, and uni¬
versities to begin a systematic study of the
shape and substance of what lies under
the ocean's waves. Thus blossomed the
disciplines of marine geology and
bathymetry (measuring ocean depths) to
provide the new knowledge that is indis¬
pensable if we are to use the sea intel¬
ligently and preserve its resources as far
as possible for future generations.
The sea bed that was once thought to
be flat is, we know now, anything but an
endless plain. The continental slopes that
drop gently from the continental shelves
are marked nearly everywhere by sub¬
marine canyons, large troughs that have
been eroded by dense currents of com¬
bined sea water and mud; these form as
earth-slides at the tops of the canyons and
wear away courses or paths much as sand¬
paper smooths down wood. Submarine
earthquakes, modern volcanoes and
eruptions of red-hot magma (lava) con-
Main types of minerals on the sea floor
Type of Materials Geological
deposit or elements setting
Construction Pebbles, quartz Coast and shelf
materials and carbonate
sand, shells
Placer Iron Coast and nearshore
deposits Gold
(sand Platinum
and gravel Tin
containing Diamonds
heavy Rare earth
metals) elements
Zirconium
Titanium
and others
Hydrocarbons Petroleum Mainly passive
Gas continental margins
and certain basins
Hydrothermal ore Iron Fracture zones,
deposits Manganese spreading centres,
Copper certain basins
Zinc
Lead
Silver
and others
Manganese Manganese Deep sea
nodules Iron
Cobalt
Nickel
Titanium
Molybdenum
and others
(4,000 metres)
Phosphorites Phosphorus Coastal (locally
Uranium continuation of
Rare earth land resources)
elements and nearshore:
and others submarine plateaux
After P. Rothe, "Marine Geology: Mineral Resources of the Sea",
Impact of Science on Society. Nos. 3 / 4, 1983
stantly shift the contours of the sea bed
along the central ridges of the ocean
basins.
Research carried out between the
1930s and the 1950s in the Pacific Ocean
basin revealed hundreds of undersea
mountains (called seamounts), mostly
old volcanoes, measuring 3,000 metres or
more in altitude above the floor of the
sea. Some of these are shaped like cones
with their topmost peaks missing; they
are called guyots or tablemounts. These
flat-topped ancient volcanic summits
have had their tips worn away over time
by wave action and they may rise to with¬
in 100 to 1 ,600 metres of the surface of the
ocean. During the Cretaceous period
(roughly 100 million years ago) they be¬
came inhabited by organisms similar to
those that built shallow-water reefs or
masses of coral in the Pacific, Carib¬
bean and other oceans. The guyots, and
seamounts in general, have sunk as the
earth's crust beneath them has cooled.
Techniques used to measure depth be¬
gan with "sounding" using a fibre or
wire cable marked periodically with
metallic or other weights, dipped and
raised continuously to estimate the sur¬
face-to-bottom distance. The method is
unreliable because of the irregularity of
the sea floor, movement of the ship and
currents running beneath the surface of
the ocean.
Echo-sounding and sonar, invented to
meet naval needs during the two World
Wars, use a pulse or beam sent mechani¬
cally or electronically from a vessel to the
bed of the sea, where it is reflected and
then recaptured by the emitting vessel.
The total time elapsed during the pulse's
round trip is translated into distance, giv¬
ing a "fix" on the target of the sound
signal. A chart is produced by this process
so that a printed memory or record can be
kept of the depths along the course fol-^
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A world map
of the sea
depths
The fifth edition of GEBCO (General
Bathymétrie Chart of the Oceans) con¬
sists of nineteen sheets. Sixteen of the
charts cover the world from 72 degrees
north latitude (at the northern tip of Nor¬
way) to 72 degrees south latitude (the
Bellingshausen Sea of Antarctica), with
a scale of 1:10 million at the equator.
There are two polar sheets, or polar
stereographic projections, of scale 1:6
million at 75 degrees latitude, and a
world sheet reducing all the eighteen
other sheets printed on the scale of 1 :35
million. There is a guidebook for all
these charts.
National hydrographie offices in
eighteen Member States of the Interna¬
tional Hydrographie Organization are
responsible for upkeep of the basic
data, a set of sixty-five "master sound¬
ing sheets". The Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission at Unesco,
together with three major non-gov¬
ernmental scientific bodies as well as
the French Institut Géographique
National and the Scott Polar Research
Institute in Cambridge, are charged with
providing the scientific details to be en¬
tered on the GEBCO charts.
Interested teachers, researchers,
fisheries specialists and others may
order the GEBCO series, boxed and
accompanied by a supporting descrip¬
tive volume, at a cost of US $120 from:
Hydrographie Chart Distribution Office,
Department of Fisheries and Oceans,
1675 Russell Road (Box 8080), Ottawa
K1G3H6, Canada.
Part of the eastern Pacific Ocean sea floor
and of the west coast ofSouth America are
depicted on the portion of the fifth edition
of the General Bathymétrie Chart of the
Oceans (GEBCO), reproduced here in
black and white. The sea floor In this re¬
gion is about 4,500 metres deep and is
moving slowly towards South America ata
rate of almost 9 centimetres a year. The
7,000-metre-deep Peru-Chile Trench is for¬
med at the margin of the continent, where
the sea floorplunges down into the interior
of the earth and slowly melts. GEBCO was
prepared by marine scientists from many
countries and was published by Canada.
The work was carried out under the aus¬
pices of Unesco's Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission (IOC) and the
International Hydrographie Organization.
14
#
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
ECUADOR COLOMBIA
ÍT?
lowed by a vessel. Shortcomings of this
method include errors in data resulting
from under-sea obstacles and variations
in the speed of sound through water
(caused by differing salinity, tempera¬
tures and depth).
The systematic compilation of depth
charts, called the General Bathymétrie
Chart of the Oceans (GEBCO), dates
from the time, early in this century, when
Prince Albert I of Monaco realized that
the best possible maps of any surface,
undersea as well as on land, are a critical
tool in good management of the re¬
sources and environment of the sea. Pub¬
lishing GEBCO the first time was fairly
easy: in 1903 knowledge was so scanty
that the job took only seven months to
complete. As the next three editions were
researched and compiled, oceano-
graphers became aware of massive relief
features found on the sea floor, for exam¬
ple, the spine-like mid-ocean ridges of
the Atlantic and the Pacific. They did not
understand that geological processes
gave rise to, then changed, these large-
scale features.
The current (fifth) edition of GEBCO
has been compiled under the aegis of the
Unesco-based Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission and of the
International Hydrographie Organiza¬
tion, and was made possible by new re¬
search in geology and geophysics that has
enabled scientists everywhere to estimate
trends in the shape and materials forming
the sea bed. The huge amount of depth
data, collected for the most part since the
1950s, has been integrated into the fifth
edition of GEBCO. This was published in
1982 by the Canadian Hydrographie Ser¬
vice after seven years of exhaustive com¬
pilation compared to the seven months
required for the first edition eighty-three
years ago.
The latest edition of GEBCO, like its
earlier versions, is both a major improve¬
ment over the previous charts and a signi¬
ficant contribution to scientific know¬
ledge; it is a scientific synthesis of all
océanographie and hydrographie inves¬
tigations stretching over more than a cen¬
tury. To a geologist, poring over GEBCO
is like reading an exciting book on the
history of ocean basins and continental |
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
margins and on the geological processes
that formed them.
GEBCO was drawn up by geological
oceanographers from millions of depths
soundings. Although this number seems
large, it must be remembered that the
ocean has a total area of some 360 million
square kilometres. Thus the number of
soundings is generally insufficient to por¬
tray accurately the bathymetry of the
ocean floor by using a purely geometrical
joining up of depth points. So the science
of geomorphology is used to interpret
scattered data, combined with some de¬
tailed studies, in order to obtain reliable
bathymétrie contours at the GEBCO
map scale. Depth soundings near conti¬
nents are usually more numerous.
The basic data for GEBCO were
gathered by ships using single-beam
echo-sounders. In recent years, a new
sounder, using fifteen beams side by side,
has come increasingly into civil use as a
scientific instrument. This "swath-sound¬
er" uses a computer to integrate sound¬
ings and produces a detailed contoured
strip-chart of the deep sea floor that is a
few kilometres wide.
The high quality of GEBCO's fifth edi¬
tion can be judged from a detailed swath-
sounding record made by the Federal
Republic of Germany's research vessel
Polarstern in the Atlantic Ocean between
Europe and South America late in 1984.
Only two differences were found: an un¬
discovered seamount off Brazil, and a
correction to the measurements of a sub¬
marine canyon off southern Argentina.
At the next stage above purely naviga¬
tional charts, bathymétrie maps like
GEBCO and its larger-scale cousins
(such as the Bathymétrie Chart of the
Mediterranean Sea) are the basic portraits
of the sea floor for both general and
geological uses. There are also special¬
ized charts of the sea bed produced from
geological and geophysical data showing
sediment and rocks, magnetic and gravity
fields, sediment thickness and so on.
Multi-beam echo-sounders can be turned
to "look sideways" in order to produce
shaded images of the sea floor; these
resemble photographs.
Information for specialists can be
synthesized into geological charts, as has
been done in the ocean sheets of the
Geological Atlas of the World, a twenty-
two-sheet array produced by Unesco and
the International Commission for the
Geological Atlas of the World (also com¬
piled by geologists from all over the
world).
Since the early 1970s, more and more
nations have become vitally interested in
the ocean and its resources a curiosity
stimulated by the eight years of intensive
negotiation to draft, by 1982, a Conven¬
tion on the Law of the Sea.
Over many years, carelessness and
mismanagement have led to depletion of
some species of fish and other seafood in
waters that had been rich and productive.
The search for petroleum under the seas
and its production took explorers far
along the continental shelves, virtually
everywhere. While the new energy
sources are welcome, the ensuing pollu¬
tion problems, including oil spills peri¬
lous to flora and fauna, are much less so.
A variety of useful metals and other
minerals are now within our reach and
some nations consider many of these eco¬
nomically significant for the future and
are planning their extraction from the sea
bed. Good bathymétrie charts and geolo¬
gical maps are essential tools for such
study, exploitation and conservation of
the natural resources of the ocean. H
DALE KRAUSE has been head of Unesco's
Division of Marine Sciences since 1973. A spe¬
cialist in marine geology and tectonics, he has
led océanographie expeditions in the Pacific and
Atlantic oceans.
JACQUES RICHARDSON was head of Un-
esco's Science and Society Section from 1972 to
1985. He edited Managing the Ocean: Re¬
sources, Research and Law, a book co-pub¬
lished last year by Unesco and Lomond Publica¬
tions, Inc., Maryland, USA.
Right, this example of a geological map of
the sea floor is taken from sheet 21 of
Unesco's Geological Atlas of the World
which covers the Indian Ocean.
The centre line of the symmetrical
stripes marks the axis of the mid-ocean rift
where the sea floor is moving apart at a
rate of about 1 to 2 centimetres a year.
Molten lava wells up along this crack and
becomes new sea floor as it cools. Thus
the age of the sea floor increases progres¬
sively the farther it is from the ridge. The
age ofthe sea floor isshown on the map as
stripes (coloured on the original sheet)
and ranges from zero, where the sea floor
is currently forming, to over a hundred
million years south-west of Madagascar.
Among other features shown on this
geological map are: the location of geolo¬
gical faults (heavy black lines); the kinds
of rock found in drill cores taken from the
sea floor; contours showing the thickness
of sediment that has slowly deposited on
top of the cooled lava; the location of
earthquakes (black dots, red on the origi¬
nal sheet); and the location ofactive volca¬
noes (triangles). Land appears dark grey
as reproduced here.
This geological map of the Indian Ocean
was prepared by marine geologists under
the auspices of the Commission for the
Geological Atlas of the World. The Atlas
consists of22sheets6small-scale maps
covering the oceans and 16 larger-scale
maps covering the continents. The Atlas is
a major scientific contribution to human
knowledge because it summarizes the
geology of the entire earth. It was made
possible by the hard work of land and
marine geologists from all over the world,
co-operating within Unesco. The Atlas is
published by Unesco and is available
through Unesco sales agents.
Glossary
Bathymetry Measuring the depths of the sea, including the
slopes descending from the continents and probing the shape of
the ocean floor
Contour In mapping, an imaginary line joining all points having
the same height or depth
Cretaceous A geological period extending from about 135 mil¬
lion years to 65 million years ago
Geology Study of the rocks, soils and minerals of our globe's
structure and history
Geomorphology Study of the geological evolution of land-forms
Geophysics Study of the forces of nature at work (heat, gravity,
magnetism, radiation, weather and climate, volcanoes and earth
quakes) and how these affect the structure and the evolution of the
globe
Guyot Flat-topped submarine mountain also known as a table-
mount
Seamount A cone-shaped submarine mountain rising from the
deep sea floor
Sonar SOund NAvigation Ranging, the detection of submerged
objects by the sensing of reflected sonic and sub-sonic waves (a
sub-sonic wave is inaudible to the human ear)
Tectonics Geophysical processes whereby the earth's crust
constantly shrinks and shifts, thus causing faults, rifts, earth¬
quakes and volcanic eruptions
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The nature andpurpose
ofmarine science
OCEAN science is concerned with
the investigation of the world
ocean, its biota and its physical
boundaries with the solid earth and
atmosphere. It is no different from any
other scientific field in its use of the scien¬
tific method, in which careful description
leads to the formulation of hypotheses
and their testing by experiment.
As in other earth sciences, the testing
of hypotheses can only occasionally be
accomplished by the conventional sort of
laboratory experiment where the impor¬
tant variables are under the ex¬
perimenter's control. More commonly a
"geophysical experiment" must be
undertaken, where the experiment is per¬
formed by nature and the scientist is
limited to observing its various phases at
different times and locations.
Scientific problems in the ocean tend to
involve more than one discipline, so that
their solution often calls for collaboration
among scientists with different experi¬
ence and skills. And because of the large
dimensions of many oceanic processes
and the fact that their occurrence and
location are seldom coincident with the
limits of national jurisdiction, ocean sci¬
ence depends heavily on international co¬
operation.
Different countries assign different de¬
grees of importance to marine research.
While the industrialized maritime coun¬
tries are generally the major investors in
these activities, some developing coun¬
tries have also assigned high priority to
ocean studies. In recent years the number
of marine scientists, institutions and re¬
search vessels has increased considerably
in many countries, including those of the
tropical and sub-tropical zones. Never¬
theless, ocean research continues to have
a low priority in many States, in part
because of the lack of awareness of the
need for, and benefits of, such research
for overall economic and cultural
development.
There appear to be compelling reasons
now for giving increased priority to the
support of basic marine science and its
application to ocean use and man¬
agement. The main reason is that an ever-
expanding world population is placing
increasing pressure on all the resources of
the planet and this growing need for food,
minerals and energy cannot be fully met
from the land. Thus demands on the
ocean will increase as land sources are
depleted and as their increased cost
makes ocean exploitation economically
feasible. But rational use of the ocean
and its resources will depend heavily on
scientific knowledge, which in many
cases does not at present exist.
There is a broad spectrum of kinds of
research, ranging from the most fun¬
damental with widespread relevance but
no obvious short-term application to that
with immediate, specific application but
with little relevance to other problems.
The time-scale of pay-off varies greatly
and it is usually difficult to predict just
when the application of research findings
will become feasible. It is important to
remember that applied research draws on
the reservoir of scientific knowledge, and
it is often the case that problems of im¬
mediate concern cannot be solved with¬
out additional research of a very fun¬
damental character.
For example, the growth in scientific
manpower and facilities and their exten¬
sions to new locations will in the long run
permit a better scientific coverage of
many regions previously neglected due to
their remoteness from traditional centres
of scientific activity. But it would be un¬
fortunate if this effort were to be limited
to specialized measurements for fisher¬
ies, or for petroleum or mineral develop¬
ment on the continental shelf. Until the
present gaps in our basic information on,
for example, ocean circulation and major
ecosystems are filled, it will be very diffi¬
cult to use these resources wisely or to
predict the consequences of harvesting
them.
The Convention on the Law of the Sea,
accepted by many countries in 1982,
assigns much of the world ocean to exclu¬
sive national economic zones where
coastal States have jurisdiction over the
exploitation of resources. The wise use of
these resources, both living and non¬
living, will require scientific knowledge
that is often not now available. Thus the
new Law of the Sea serves to increase the
need of coastal States for scientific re¬
search in these offshore regions.
This is true for all coastal States, re¬
gardless of their level of development,
but becomes particularly important when
their coastal inhabitants depend directly
on food from the sea and when alterna¬
tive sources of food and other resources
ashore are very limited. The need to
understand océanographie processes
within a few hundred kilometres of the
coast is thus widespread and provides
strong justification for enhanced interna¬
tional co-operation in ocean research.
Perhaps the most imperative reason for
such collaboration is the mismatch be¬
tween the dimensions and locations of
oceanic processes and phenomena and
the national boundaries that are imposed
on the ocean system. In some regions, for
example the Gulf of Guinea or the Carib¬
bean Sea, the ocean circulation and the
distribution of fish are common to the
several bordering countries and their in¬
vestigation can only be effectively accom¬
plished through regional collaboration.
Finally, it should be observed that the
dimensions of some ocean phenomena
vastly exceed the national domains of
affected countries and it is not uncom¬
mon for local events to be driven by
processes operating in distant parts of the
ocean. A classic example is El Niño, a
phenomenon in which the fisheries of the
coastal waters of Peru and Chile may be
affected by an ocean circulation pattern
across the entire equatorial Pacific and by
atmospheric conditions over the entire
planet. This emphasizes the need for col¬
laboration at the global level to provide
the necessary insights into the atmos¬
pheric and oceanic causes of changes in
both local and large-scale climate.
This article is extracted from Ocean Science for
the Year 2000, a report on an inquiry by the
Scientific Committee on Oceanic Research and
the Advisory Committee on Marine Resources
Research for the Intergovernmental Océanog¬
raphie Commission and Unesco, published by
Unesco in 1984.
COLOUR PAGES
Opposite page, detail from a relief map of
the ocean floor showing the submerged
"spine" of the Atlantic Ocean fne mid-
Atlantic Ridge.
Photo © Hachette/Gu/des Bleus, Paris. Detail from Carte du
Fond des Océans, by Tanguy de Rémur
Page 20, specimens of marine life form a
pageant ofastonishing varietyandbeauty.
Clockwise from top left: (1) The Moorish
idol {Zanclus comutusj is an Indo-Pacific
tropical fish that grows to be 22 cm long.
(2) A nautilus. Its spiral-shaped shell con¬
tains a number of chambers. It adds anew
chamber to its cell each time it outgrows
an old one. (3) Delicate tracery of coloured
markings dot the arms of a bevy of star¬
fish. Most starfish have 5 arms although
some have as many as 50. (4) Seafloor
landscape of multicoloured corals and
sponges.
Photos 1 and 3, Myers © A.A.A., Paris
Photos 2 and 4, Syllebranque © A.A.A., Paris
Page 21, view of the 400-kilometre-long
barrier reef, the world's second largest
after the Australian Great Barrier Reef, that
encircles New Caledonia in the southwest
Pacific.
Photo Syllebranque © A.A.A. , Paris
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
fcH^jJF'
fr, , t v"\
.p^^wïâ --* £
i
is-
ihV
v^
'-^'
W-,
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
MEAN SURFACE TEMPERATURE FDR JANUARY 1979
FROM KERS 2 AND MSU DATA
M\
! -t-í- 22
DEGREES KELVIN
263 273 283 293 303 313 HASKINS AND HUS:
l
SEASAT SMMR UflTER VAPOR
JULY 7 - OCTOBER 10. 1978
GRAMS'CENTIMETER'
SEASAT ALTIMETER UAVE HEIGHT
JULY 7 - OCTOBER lOi 1978
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Satellites scan the ocean
Modern technology
in the service of oceanography
by D. James Baker
WHEN I entered oceanography
in the early 1960s, rapid strides
were being made towards de¬
scribing and predicting ocean behaviour.
The first expedition in whióh I partici¬
pated spent six months in the Indian
Ocean helping to measure the currents
and winds in the equatorial regions there.
But the technology and the research ships
available to us at that time had serious
limitations. The ship we used was the
Argo, a former submarine rescue ship
deeded from the United States Navy to
the Scripps Institution of Oceanography
and our equipment was largely devoid of
electronics. Our officers used celestial
navigation, dead-reckoning and local
measurements. The difficulty of obtain¬
ing any kind of global view or photograph
of conditions at any one time over a large
area of the Indian Ocean was painfully
obvious.
Today, our instruments are much more
sophisticated, largely because of the re¬
volution in micro-electronics and com¬
puters, but the limitations of measure¬
ments from ships are still with us.
Measurement of the ocean from satellites
promises to liberate us from many of
these shipboard limitations. Navigation
by satellite, a technique that uses satel¬
lites and on-board receivers and com¬
puters, is commonplace for research
ships and commercial vessels. Accurate
positioning is available at two hourly in¬
tervals in most regions of the world and in
any weather conditions. We are also now
beginning to use other satellite data to get
photographs of the behaviour of the
oceans its temperature, the shape of its
The SEASAT satellite which produced the
global measurements of water vapour,
wind speed and wave height illustrated on
colour page opposite. Drawing shows
SEASAT in polar orbit over Alaska.
surface, its waves and its chemical and
biological properties.
The ocean is a subject of intense in¬
terest to the applied scientist for a variety
of reasons. Whereas in the past increas¬
ing energy and food requirements could
be met by expansion of frontiers, use of
chemicals for fertilizers and pesticides,
and by using available reserves of gas and
oil, we are today being confronted by the
finite dimensions of the world. We are at
the point where we affect both regional
and global climate. We are a factor in the
COLOUR PAGE OPPOSITE
Top photo shows the first global map ever
put together of the surface temperature of
the earth. The temperatures shown on the
map correspond to those ofJanuary 1979.
The colour scale shows temperature ex¬
pressed in degrees Kelvin (a temperature
expressed in degrees Centigrade is equal
to the temperature in Kelvins less 273.15.
For example, the light yellow band at
centre of the colour scale shown beneath
the map Is approximately equal to zero
degrees Centigrade). Since the cold polar
regions coveronlya smallpartof the globe
relative to the warm equatorial regions, the
mean surface temperature of the earth is
clearly dominated by the temperatures in
the tropics. The map shows several cold
regions, such as Siberia and northern
Canada, and a hot Australian continent
during the southern hemisphere's sum¬
mer. The effect of the GulfStream is clearly
seen off the eastern coast of the United
States (the temperatures there are cooler
than at comparable latitudes on the eas¬
tern side of the Atlantic Ocean). Maps such
as these are used to establish the basic
parameters ofglobalair/sea interaction for
understanding climate.
Photo courtesy of M. Chachine, NASA/Jet Propulsion
Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena
Lower photos Illustrate global mea¬
surements of water vapour, wind speed
and wave height made by the SEASAT
satellite between 7 July and 10 October
1978. The water vapour in the atmosphere
affects the earth's surface radiation ba¬
lance and, together with wind speed, is
important for studies ofclimate. As expec¬
ted, most water vapour is found in the
tropics, where evaporation is high. The
wind speed is measured by inference from
the shape of the waves, which in turn Is
measured by altimeter. The modern alti¬
meter is a radar device that sends down a
pulse from the satellite which is reflected
back to the satellite. The time it takes to go
from satellite to ocean andbackagain tells
us how far the sea surface is from the
satellite and hence the shape of the sur
face under the satellite track. From the
surface shape the waves andgeneral topo¬
graphy of the surface can be determi¬
ned. The wind speed and wave height
show the strongest Intensity in the
southern oceans, particularly south of
Australia. These measurements illustrate
the importance of satellite measurements
for such data, since this is a region gen¬
erally devoid of ships that can take direct
measurements. For the first time we now
have measurements of wind and waves in
this region.
The altimeter can measure more than
waves since variations in the sea 's surface
height are also caused by ocean currents.
For example, the Gulf Stream has varia¬
tions of height across its width of about
one metre. Such variations can be mea¬
sured by the satellite altimeter and pro¬
mise to provide global pictures of ocean
circulation as well as waves. This is one of
the most exciting possibilities of the new
satellite data.
Photos courtesy of D. Chelton NASA/Jet Propulsion Laboratory,
Pasadena
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
^ global cycles of carbon, nitrogen, phos¬
phorus and sulphur because we produce
significant amounts of these chemicals
and dump them into the air and the sea. It
is essential that we understand how the
overall ocean-atmosphere system works
if we are to live successfully with global
change. We have to understand the cyc¬
ling of energy, waste and essential che¬
micals through the atmosphere, land and
oceans.
The oceans regulate the climate and
make it more predictable. The slow varia¬
tions of ocean currents which affect the
transfer of heat to the atmosphere could,
in the view of many experts, provide a
mechanism for predicting the climatic
changes in the atmosphere. But in order
to understand these variations of ocean
currents we need to understand the
general circulation of the ocean, how the
currents are driven and how and why they
change. Another largely unknown factor
in the climatic system involves the role of
sea-snow and sea-ice. Both of these are
quantities that can be measured and mon¬
itored by satellite.
The distribution and cycling of nut¬
rients is also important to the "habitabi-
lity" of our planet. The nutrients are re
lated to the biological productivity cycle
through the atmosphere, rivers, coastal
zones and the deep ocean. The continen¬
tal shelf is a critical area. Most of the
world's fisheries occur here, much of the
world's petroleum production may be in
these areas in the future and it is here that
most of man's pollution enters the ocean.
The shelf is a direct source of food for
humanity and the pressures on this food
supply are increasing rapidly. We must
know what is happening here and we
must be able to understand the mechan¬
isms that control the transport of these
nutrients from terrestrial sources to
oceanic sinks. To do this we must be able
to understand the interactions between
physical and biological processes in the
oceans. Large-scale satellite views of nut¬
rients in the ocean are necessary for this
understanding.
Changes in the amount and timing of
global rainfall are critical for farmers.
The green revolution has shown dramati¬
cally how genetic engineering can pro¬
vide farmers with exactly the right kind of
crops for a maximum of productivity if
the water resources are known. Thus
rainfall is critical, but we must know it
globally. The problem is not yet solved;
j -jjjr£3&g?9*¡7'"'" ' J Jküü
'Ï	
©
.¿***
in fact, the natural rainfall patterns over
the globe are only marginally predictable
by the use of climate models now avail¬
able. Global rainfall is another parameter
that we can measure by satellite.
For the oceanographer, ships are
essential. There is no other way to get
samples of water, chemicals or biological
organisms from the sea. But ships alone
cannot give us an overall view of the
ocean. A typical research ship travels at
about ten knots; at that speed it takes
about ten days to make a single crossing
of the North Atlantic. It can therefore
take months to complete a careful survey
of any large region, and in that time the
state of the ocean can change drastically.
From ships and from the relatively few
buoys that are moored in the ocean for
weather measurements and for research
purposes, we get an average view of the
ocean's properties (for example its
temperature and salinity) and of near-
surface weather. This average view is im¬
portant, but we have to recognize that the
ocean is continually changing. It does not
change as fast as the atmosphere, but it
does behave in a similar way. The atmos¬
phere changes its weather in a few days
and its climate varies from year to year.
The ocean's "weather", that is, the cur¬
rents and temperatures, changes over
periods of a few weeks instead of a few
days. The ocean's "climate" also changes
from year to year.
But how do we get an overall view of
the ocean? Our instruments have to be
placed in a position away from the earth
in order to see it all at once. Satellites are
the only way. Typically satellites receive
their power from the sun, and they are
classified as either passive or active. The
passive satellites receive the radiation
that comes from the earth and attempt to
interpret it; the active satellites illumin¬
ate the sea with specified radiation and
observe the reflected pulses. We now
have satellites that can measure the shape
of the ocean's surface, the surface
temperature of the ocean, the wind speed
near the surface, the extent of the polar
ice, the surface chlorophyll and a variety
of properties in the atmosphere.
From these instruments we get a global
view either an image of almost half the
earth at a time from a satellite in geosta-
Above, the US research ship Anton Bruun,
which took part In the International Indian
Ocean Expedition. Before being refitted
for ocean biology research and renamed
in honour of the famous Danish oceano¬
grapher, it was the US presidential yacht
Williamsburg.
Left, the Argo, the research vessel of the
Scripps Institution of Oceanography, San
Diego, California.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
ON- 90E QÇ09
tionary orbit, or from a series of tracks of
"low earth orbiter satellites" which travel
closer to the earth and repeat their orbits
about every ninety minutes. Thus we
have at our disposal a new and remark¬
able series of pictures of the ocean and
the land, and this new imagery has dra¬
matically changed the way in which we
view the ocean, allowing us to plan for
new research programmes. We now see
the possibility of describing and under¬
standing some of the important cycles of
climate, of nutrients and of other en¬
vironmental factors that affect global
habitability.
Enormous quantities of data have been
collected since the early 1960s, when
satellites first came into use, but it is only
in recent years that satellite pictures that
can be used for real scientific understand¬
ing of the ocean have become available.
The four photographs on page 22 demon¬
strate the power of these new techniques.
Encouraged by this technological
advance, a number of scientists have
proposed the establishment of an interna¬
tional Global Habitability Programme
aimed at improving our understanding of
the climate and the global cycles. The
central elements of the programme
would be satellite measurements by many
nations and shipboard and land-based
measurement and modelling of the
ocean, the earth and the biosphere. Us¬
ing satellites, ships and computers, en¬
vironmental scientists have the technolo¬
gy to carry out the required research. In
addition, their theoretical tools have ad¬
vanced to the point where the integrated
study of the global system is becoming
feasible. With scientists working together
internationally it is possible that rational
management of the earth and its re¬
sources may be achieved.
D. JAMES BAKER, of the USA, is Dean of the
College of Ocean and Fishery Sciences and
professor of Oceanography at the University of
Washington Seattle. He is a member of the
Board on Ocean Science and Policy and the
Climate Research Committee of the US National
Academy of Sciences as well as of the Earth and
Space Sciences Advisory Committee of the
National Aeronautics and Space Administration.
He is the author of many articles on the general
circulation of the ocean, the role of the ocean in
climate variation, and ocean technology. This
article is extracted from a longer study first pub¬
lished in the Unesco science magazine Impact oí
Science on Society.
Satellite image ofa cyclone over the Indian
Ocean
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Twenty-five years of research
The Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission
TWENTY-FIVE years ago, international co-operation in
marine science was in its infancy. Although serious scientific
investigation of the deep oceans had begun almost a cen¬
tury earlier, when, on a cold grey December day in 1 872, the British
corvette HMS Challenger set out on an historic three-and-a-half-
year round-the-world océanographie exploration cruise, interna¬
tional océanographie research as we know it today did not com¬
mence until after the Second World War.
The Challenger brought back valuable information on ocean
temperatures, ocean currents and the depths and main contours of
the great ocean basins, and other governments were quick to
mount similar expeditions.
These, however, were individual, unco-ordinated efforts and,
rather surprisingly, it was not until the 1 950s that marine scientists
and governments came to realize that, if ocean properties were to
be adequately measured, the measurements would have to be
made in many places simultaneously.
The success of the first truly international co-operative venture
the investigation of the Atlantic Polar Front in 1958, within the
framework of the International Geophysical Year demonstrated
what could be achieved through international co-operation. It also
demonstrated the need for some form of international organization
to which governments would be prepared to give their
wholehearted backing.
It was in this context that an Intergovernmental Conference on
Océanographie Research, held in Copenhagen in 1960, recom¬
mended the establishment, within Unesco, of the Intergovernmen¬
tal Océanographie Commission, more familiarly known as the IOC,
which it charged with the task of promoting "scientific investigation
with a view to learning more about the nature and resources of the
oceans through the concerted actions of its members".
During the twenty-five years that have elapsed since that
momentous meeting the IOC has grown both in numbers and in
stature. The forty oriqinal Member States have swelled to 113
and the Commission itself has gained recognition as the world
leader in international oceanographical research.
A major turning point in the life of the IOC came in 1 969 with the
establishment of the Key Long-Term Expanded Programme of
The route taken by HMS Challenger during
her historic océanographie research
cruise, 1872 to 1876.
v &"
10/74^1- ITS
HAWAIIAN I.
MANILA'. MARIANA I.
MARIANAS TRENCH
I
»S 1 Mt UM - I,
DEEPEST POINT ONV,
>'. EARTH'S
9 '' CAROLINE I. SURFACE .'
4/74
MELBOURNE
12/74, U
TONGATABU
7/74
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Oceanic Exploration and Research (LEPOR) which was to deter¬
mine the main thrust of the Commission's activities for years to
come.
An event of equal importance for the IOC, and indeed for the
world, was the signing in 1 982 of the United Nations Convention on
the Law of the Sea, which is expected to extend the scope of the
IOC's responsibilities very considerably.
Throughout its twenty-five years of existence the IOC has been
taking innovative initiatives that have helped to push back the
boundaries of océanographie knowledge. These include: a new
approach to the relationship between the marine environment and
the living resources of the sea; the preparation of specialized maps
of the ocean, in particular bathymétrie (ocean depth) charts, maps
of the sea bed and of its geological and geophysical characteris¬
tics; the setting up of two international experiments on the rela¬
tionship between the ocean and the atmosphere; the global inves¬
tigation of marine pollution; the establishment of a system of
collection, classification, exchange and analysis of ocean data;
and, the elaboration of a comprehensive plan for a Major Assist¬
ance Programme to Enhance the Marine Science Capabilities of
Developing Countries.
During the past quarter of a century the objectives of the IOC
have remained fundamentally the same, although they have been
broadened and clarified. The Commission's aims today could be
summed up as being:
to identify problems the solutions to which require international
co-operation in ocean research;
to develop scientific investigation of the oceans and the related
services such as international océanographie data exchange and
ocean observing systems;
to strengthen the marine scientific and technical capabilities of its
Member States through training, education and mutual assistance.
The silver jubilee of the IOC, which was celebrated during the
thirteenth session of the Assembly, held in Paris from 12 to 28
March 1985, provided a special opportunity for a critical review of
the Commission's work and the formulation of guidelines for future
activities.
The governing body of the IOC is its Assembly which meets once every two
years. An Executive Council consisting of thirty-three Member States
exercises overall supervision of the implementation of the Commission's
activities. The day-to-day running of the IOC is the responsibility ofits chief
executive officer, the Secretary of the Commission. Unesco provides most
of the staff and Secretariat services and close co-operation is maintained
with the Division of Marine Sciences of Unesco on projects of mutual
interest. The Commission also functions as a joint specialized mechanism
for discharging certain of the responsibilities, in marine scientific and
technical affairs, of the five UN OrganizationsUN, Unesco, FAO, WMO
and IMOmembers of the Inter-Secretariat Committee on Scientific Pro¬
grammes Relating to Oceanography.
A researcher prepares to lower a net
designed for taking plankton samples.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The challenge
of the new ocean regime
IN considering the consequences of
the signature, by over 150 nations, of
the United Nations Convention on
the Law of the Sea, the words of the
Portuguese poet who said that "today is
the first day of the rest of your life" come
to my mind. Indeed, this historic event
marks the beginning of a new relationship
between mankind and the oceans. It rep¬
resents to some extent the culmination of
a long process of universal negotiation
among States. It is also the beginning of a
phase of international co-operation
aimed at the achievement of the objec¬
tives of the Convention, as well as the
dreams and aspirations behind its
provisions.
The new ocean regime is a develop¬
ment with far-reaching consequences for
the conduct of ocean affairs at the nation¬
al and international levels. It is also a
symbolic event in that it reflects the im¬
portant changes that have been shaping
the world community since the Second
World War (characterized mainly by the
process of decolonization and national
self-determination) as well as by the drive
for a more just and equitable economic
order built on a foundation of peaceful
and friendly relations between countries
regardless of their political and economic
systems.
Among the many features of the new
ocean charter that constitute innovations
with respect to the 1958 Convention on
the Law of the Sea, mention should be
made of the regime for marine scientific
research and the transfer of marine tech¬
nology. This innovation is derived from
the growing perception by States of the
value of science and technology, first to
economic and social development and
secondly as sources of power and an ele¬
ment of the independence of States in the
modern world. Science is a fundamental
component of a technological civiliza¬
tion. Scientific activities generate the in¬
formation required for many kinds of
economic activity. Without scientific
data, modern States, government admi¬
nistrations and industrial management
could not perform their functions effec¬
tively or achieve their goals.
The Convention includes a compre¬
hensive regime for the conduct of inter¬
national marine scientific research and
the transfer of knowledge and tech¬
nology. Some principles and rules estab¬
lish the duty of States to co-operate
directly with each other or through the
appropriate international, regional or
sub-regional organizations.
The rights accorded to coastal States
and the corresponding duties of States
engaged in research for granting or re¬
fusing their consent to research to be
conducted in their Exclusive Economic
Zones create favourable conditions for
the participation of local scientists in re¬
search activities, training, access to re¬
quired knowledge, and so on. It should
be noted in this context that, besides
references in the Convention to "regional
centres", to be established or reinforced
for the promotion of marine scientific
research and technology and related
training and transfer of knowledge, men¬
tion is also made of national centres to be
created at the local level for the same
purpose. The functions assigned to this
type of institution and the need for
further elaboration of the concept of re¬
gional centres reflect the concern for
participation by, and the aspiration for
real partnership among, developing
countries in scientific and technological
international marine programmes and
activities in the future.
Pending the ratification and entry into
force of the Convention, and to facilitate
the progressive implementation of the
new regime by States, a major require¬
ment is the improvement or the establish¬
ment of the necessary institutional
arrangements. During the Conference on
the Law of the Sea, a detailed discussion
on institutional aspects was deliberately
left aside and was only dealt with in
general terms in connexion with specific
articles. Neither was there any mention
by name of the appropriate inter¬
governmental organizations, except in a
few cases, so as to avoid extra difficulties
resulting from the definition of compe¬
tences in various aspects of oceanic
affairs within the United Nations system.
Steps have already been taken, or are
under way, by a number of organizations
to adapt themselves to the new demands
and to prepare themselves to be able to
fulfil the functions assigned to "compe¬
tent international organizations" in the
Convention.
Following this trend, Unesco, through
The headquarters of IOCARIBE, the Carib¬
bean Region branch of the inter¬
governmental Océanographie Commis¬
sion, in Cartagena, Colombia. It Is located
in the house of the Marquis of Valdehoyos,
a wealthy merchant of the 18th century.
Recently restored, it is one of the many
fine examples of colonial architecture In
the old town of Cartagena.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
by Mario Ruivo
the Intergovernmental Océanographie
Commission (IOC), initiated a study of
the implications of the Convention in
which its articles were taken as indicators
of problems requiring solution through
international co-operation in the fields of
ocean science and services and related
training and education. The aim is to
strengthen the Commission's pro¬
grammes and undertake the structural
adjustments needed, including, eventual¬
ly, improvements in the statutes of the
Commission.
As an immediate step the IOC has
established a new category of regional
subsidiary bodies the regional Sub-
commissions the first of which has just
been created for the Caribbean and adja¬
cent regions (IOCARIBE) as a successor
to an association of the same name. It is
expected that such sub-commissions will
progressively replace the existing IOC
Regional Programme Groups responsi¬
ble for the promotion and co-ordination
of marine scientific research and related
activities, including the building up of
regional centres and the establishment of
co-operative networks.
Institutional adjustments can also be
observed at the national level. In fact,
traditional administrations, established
usually on a strictly sectoral basis (for
example, fisheries, the merchant navy)
are confronted with difficulties in coping
with the new problems resulting from the
multiple use of the oceans and their in¬
teractions. To deal with these difficulties,
two trends can be identified: one is to¬
wards the establishment of a sectoral
administration dealing with ocean affairs
as a whole (the establishment of Minis¬
tries of the Sea, in certain countries, falls
into this category); the other is based on
the full use of the existing sectoral admi¬
nistrations operating under a high-level
national body having the power to formu¬
late national policy in ocean affairs and to
co-ordinate its implementation (this is
the case, for example, of the Department
for Ocean Development established in
India).
In the more specialized field of marine
scientific research a general trend, which
has been encouraged by the IOC, is the
establishment or the strengthening of
marine science co-ordinating bodies,
namely National Océanographie Com¬
missions, formed by representatives of
departments of State, universities, and
other institutions deeply involved in
Built from a design and study carried out
under Unesco supervision, the research
vessel Mukhtabar Al-Bihar was first
commissioned in Doha, Qatar, on 9 No¬
vember 1982 (above). The same design
and study were used to build a sister ship
for Algeria, Benyahia (top) which recently
became active in the Mediterranean.
marine scientific research and applica¬
tions. Such bodies are intended to mobil¬
ize the available relevant national re¬
sources and to act as focal points for
international co-operation, including
liaison with the IOC.
The pre-eminence given in Unesco's
second Medium-Term Plan (1984 to
1989) to the activities of the Organization
and, in particular, of the IOC and Un¬
esco's Division of Marine Sciences with
respect to the oceans and their resources,
and the efforts to strengthen the Commis¬
sion as a major instrument for the realiza¬
tion of the programme especially in
connexion with the Comprehensive Plan
for a Major Assistance Programme to
Enhance the Marine Science Capabilities
of Developing Countries should be re¬
garded in the context of the broad institu¬
tional process under way.
It is therefore essential that non-Gov¬
ernmental scientific institutions con¬
cerned, such as the Scientific Committee
on Oceanic Research (SCOR), also
undertake a parallel effort of adjustment
to the new conditions in order to become,
as far as possible, universal and to reflect
the views and aspirations of the world
scientific community. For historical
reasons, many such organizations still
consist predominantly of representatives
or scientists of developed countries. In
fact, scientists too must learn to adapt to
the new rules of the ocean game. The new
ocean regime offers the potential for ex¬
pansion of scientific research in the ocean
through the active participation of scien¬
tists and institutions of all countries, both
developing and developed, in a spirit of
equal partnership.
MARIO RUIVO is Secretary of the Unesco-
based Intergovernmental Océanographie Com¬
mission. A marine scientist specializing in the
management of living resources, he was former¬
ly director of FAO's Division of Fisheries and
headed the Portuguese Delegation to the United
Nations Conference on the Law of the Sea. This
article is based on a longer study first published
in the Unesco science magazine Impact of Sci¬
ence on Society.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Highlights of the Convention
on the Law of the Sea
Adopted on 30 April 1982 by the United Nations Con¬
ference on the Law of the Sea (by 130 votes to 4, with 17
abstentions) after more than eight years of preparatory
work, the Convention on the Law of the Sea lays down
rules for all parts and virtually all uses of the oceans. While
a large part of the Convention deals with the international
areas of the sea, there are important provisions recog¬
nizing the jurisdiction of States in a number of areas. The
Convention will come into force when it has been ratified
by sixty States, but a number of States have already altered
their own national legislations to bring them into line with
its provisions. Below, some of the key features of the
Convention.
Coastal States would exercise sov¬
ereignty over their territorial sea of up to
twelve miles in breadth, but foreign vessels
would be allowed "innocent passage"
through these waters for purposes of
peaceful navigation.
Ships and aircraft of all countries would
be allowed "transit passage" through
straits used for international navigation, as
long as they proceeded without delay and
without threatening the bordering States.
States alongside the straits would be able
to regulate navigation and other aspects of
passage.
Archipelagic States, made up of a group
or groups of closely related islands and
interconnecting waters, would have sov¬
ereignty over a sea area enclosed by
straight lines drawn between the outermost
points of the islands. They would have
sovereignty over these archipelagic
waters, while ships of all other States would
enjoy the right of passage through sea
lanes designated by the archipelagic State.
Coastal States would have sovereign
rights in a 200-mile exclusive economic
zone with respect to natural resources and
certain economic activities, and would also
have certain types of jurisdiction over sci¬
entific research and environmental preser¬
vation. All other States would have freedom
of navigation and overflight in the zone, as
well as freedom to lay submarine cables
and pipelines. Land-locked States and
"States with special geographical charac¬
teristics" would have the right to participate
in exploiting part of the zone's fisheries
when the coastal State could not harvest
them all itself. Delimitation of overlapping
economic zones would be "effected by
agreement on the basis of international
law.. .in order to achieve an equitable solu¬
tion". Highly migratory species of fish and
marine mammals would be afforded spe¬
cial protection.
Coastal States would have sovereign
rights over the continental shelf (the na¬
tional area of the sea bed) for the purpose
The scene at United Nations headquarters
in the afternoon of Friday 30 April 1982,
when the Convention on the Lawofthe Sea
was adopted by 130 votes to 4, with 17
abstentions.
tsn
of exploring and exploiting it without affect¬
ing the legal status of the water or the air
space above. The shelf would extend at
least to 200 miles from shore, and out to
350 miles or even beyond under specified
circumstances. Coastal States would share
with the international community part of the
revenue they derive from exploiting oil and
other resources from any part of their shelf
beyond 200 miles. Delimitation of overlap¬
ping shelves would be on the same basis
as for the exclusive economic zone. A
Commission on the Limits of the Continen¬
tal Shelf would make recommendations to
States on the shelf's outer boundaries.
All States would enjoy the traditional free¬
doms of navigation, overflight, scientific re¬
search and fishing on the high seas. They
would be obliged to adopt, or co-operate
with other States in adopting, measures to
manage and conserve living resources.
The territorial sea, exclusive economic
zone and continental shelf of islands would
be determined in accordance with rules
applicable to land territory, but rocks which
could not sustain human habitation or eco¬
nomic life would have no economic zone or
continental shelf.
States bordering enclosed or semi-
enclosed seas would be expected to co¬
operate on management of living resources
and on environmental and research poli¬
cies and activities. Land-locked States
would have the right of access to and from
the sea, and would enjoy freedom of transit
through the territory of transit States by all
means of transport.
States would be bound to use "the best
practical means at their disposal" to pre¬
vent and control marine pollution from any
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
source. The text defines which categories
of States (coastal States, port States and
flag States) would be responsible for pre¬
venting pollution and punishing polluters,
particularly when pollution originated on
board vessels, and what kinds of enforce¬
ment action were allowable. States would
be liable for damage caused by violation of
their international obligations to combat
marine pollution. They would be bound to
co-operate globally and regionally in formu¬
lating rules and standards of environmental
protection, and would commit themselves
to promote technical assistance to develop¬
ing countries in this area.
All marine scientific research in the ex¬
clusive economic zone and on the con¬
tinental shelf would be subject to the con
sent of the coastal State, but those States
would be obliged to grant consent to foreign
States when the research was to be con¬
ducted for peaceful purposes and fulfilled
other criteria laid down in the Convention. A
coastal State could deny permission for
such research or insist on its cessation, but
only under circumstances defined in the
Convention; in the event of a dispute, the
researching State could require the coastal
State to submit to international conciliation
on the ground that it was not acting in a
manner compatible with the Convention.
States would be bound to promote the
development and transfer of marine tech¬
nology "on fair and reasonable terms and
conditions". This would be done with
proper regard for all legitimate interests,
including the rights and duties of holders,
suppliers and recipients of technology.
States would be obliged to settle by
peaceful means their disputes over the in¬
terpretation or application of the Conven¬
tion. When they could not agree on the
means of settlement, they would have to
submit most types of disputes to a compul¬
sory procedure entailing decisions binding
on all parties. They would have four
options: an International Tribunal for the
Law of the Sea, to be established under the
Convention, the existing International
Court of Justice, arbitration and special
arbitration procedures. Certain types of dis¬
pute would have to be submitted to con¬
ciliation, a procedure whose outcome is not
binding on the parties.
/
/
\
\
/
\
/ International
l Sea-Bed Area
:':/ Limit of territorial sea
~:\ over which a coastal State
has sovereign powers
\
\
\
\
The International Sea-Bed Area
The longest part of the Convention concerns the future regime
for exploring and exploiting the bottom of the deep ocean in
areas beyond the continental shelf of any State.
Of main economic interest in this area at present are polymetal-
lic nodules lying on or just below the sea-bed at great depths,
composed of manganese, copper, cobalt and nickel, although
the Convention extends to all resources of the area, including
any which may be discovered or which may become economi¬
cally exploitable in the future.
The Convention would establish a "parallel" system for explor¬
ing and exploiting the deep sea-bed. Under this system, all
activities in the area would be under the control of the Interna¬
tional Sea-Bed Authority, which would be authorized to conduct
its own mining operations through an organ called Enterprise.
At the same time, the Authority would contract with private and
State ventures to give them mining rights in the area so that
they could operate in parallel with the Authority. The resources
of the area would be managed as a "common heritage of
mankind".
Limit of Exclusive i
Economic Zone
/
\
/
Of all the minerals known to exist in and
under the seas the most valuable at the
moment is oil. About one fifth of total pro¬
duction comes from the continental shelf
within 200 miles of the coast of about 75
countries and under relatively shallow
water. Many such areas have not yet been
tapped and vast reserves are suspected
under much deeper water.
Nodules rich in nickel, manganese, copper
and cobalt are the most valuable resource
now known in the International Sea-Bed
Area.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
_Ä
VC
%V'
lOJUÏl
(«WT^T^S»'
.few
5 **
©r v
Ö»>:
ft
*n
K x -
¿r
feMäj_<
[jB
N. *
Krii iiiTT" y»o
Living treasures ofthe deep
Marineflora andfauna canprovidefood,
medicines and information about the origins oflife
by Vitali Voi'tov
Above, watercolour dating from around
1546 shows the 700-ton Mary Rosa, which
sank off the coast of southern England in
1545. The 40-metre vessel, Henry VIII's fa¬
vourite warship, was discovered by ma¬
rine archaeologists in 1967 and raised
from the sea-bed on 11 October 1982 after
15 years continuous work on what has
been describedas "the world's mostambi¬
tious underwater archaeological opera¬
tion."
BURIED in the silt of Vigo Bay, off
the Atlantic coast of Spain, lie a
dozen or more Spanish galleons
whose rotting timbers spill out gold, the
spoils of the conquistadores destined to
fill the coffers of the King of Spain. Gold
and silver ingots to a value of some three
hundred million dollars rest on the ocean
floor off the northeast coast of Brazil.
Untold treasures lie concealed beneath
the coastal waters of India, Sri Lanka and
that former hunting-ground of pirates,
the Caribbean Sea.
No one can estimate the total value of
this sunken treasure, nor of the pearls
that for centuries men have dived to re¬
cover from the waters of the Gulf to
embellish the robes of kings and
courtiers.
Yet these sunken, gleaming bars of
gold and silver, so many monuments to
human greed masquerading under a
cloak of romantic myth and adventure,
pale to insignificance when compared
with the fabulous living treasure that the
ocean has to offer. For the sea, in which
life first evolved, contains all the major
animal groupings, from simple protozoa
to highly complex mammals.
Of all the living resources of the ocean,
the one that has been exploited the
longest by man is its renewable treasure
of fish and other edible forms of marine
life. Today the total world catch of fish
amounts to some seventy million tonnes a
year and provides around 24 per cent of
the animal protein necessary for a ba¬
lanced diet (see box page 34). Until com¬
paratively recent times the supply
seemed to be virtually inexhaustible, but
with improvement in fishing techniques
and increasing pressure on food supplies
some species of fish have been over-ex¬
ploited to the point of virtual extinction.
If we are to preserve this living treasure
there must be planned exploitation of the
bounty of the ocean.
The exploitation of marine organisms
for their medical, curative properties also
has a long history. Records show that the
CONTINUED PAGE 36
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
<:. -^
h
	
P D
l'
ü
,.
^
Tne 6,300-ton Soviet research ship Acade¬
mician Mstislav Keldysh. Named after a
former president of the USSR Academy of
Sciences, it has a top speed of 16 knots
andan operating range of 20,000 nautical
miles.
The Soviet research mini-submarine
Pisces VII which, with its sister sub Pisces
XI, played an important role in extensive
Soviet océanographie expeditions in the
Pacific, Atlantic and Indian Oceans from
1982 to 1985.
The two-man research mini-submarine Al-
vin in which US researchers first investi¬
gated hydrothermal vent-hole communi¬
ties living on the ocean floornear the Gala¬
pagos Islands. At depths of around 2,700
metres, where sunlight cannot penetrate,
they found communities of giant tube
worms (some as much as 2.4 metres long)
clustered around the vent-holes and living
in symbiosis with strange bacteria that
convert the chemicals spewing out from
the vent-holes into a form of food on which
the worms live.
ï
z
©
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
sunlight
Almost all life In the sea is dependent on
sunlight, which Is directly converted Into
food by microscopic plant-like floating or¬
ganisms (phytoplankton). Phytoplankton
In turn Is eaten by animal-like plankton
(Zooplankton). The plankton supports a
succession of actively swimming preda¬
tors (nekton). Organic debris rains down
(dots) and provides food for animals at
lower depths. Near-shore organisms are
supported by land drainage. Coastal
upwelling (upward arrows) provides the
phytoplankton with nutrients released by
decomposition of organic matter on the
bottom. (Organisms not drawn to scale.)
subtidal zona
World fisheries
face growing demand
Most traditionally acceptable species of fish are now fully exploited
and many are over-exploited. As a result, the rapid growth in the
world catch witnessed in the 1950s and 1960s has given way to a
much slower rate of increase. The total catch has averaged around
seventy-one million tonnes during the past decade, although the
catch of food fish has continued to increase by about 1 per cent per
annum. Excluding aquaculture, the final yield from currently ex¬
ploited species is unlikely to be much more than 1 1 0 million tonnes.
Production could eventually be increased above this limit,
however, by catching so-called unconventional species such as
the shrimp-like Atlantic krill, lantern fish, oceanic squid and small
pelagic (open sea) fish.
Fisheries in many developing countries are already a vital
source of food, employment and income. The changed circum¬
stances of marine fisheries and advances in aquaculture and
inland fisheries make it essential, however, to persuade countries
accustomed to devoting the bulk of their national resources to
agricultural development and the pursuit of industrialization that
fisheries are also of considerable value to them.
Fisheries contribute about 6 per cent of the world supply of
protein and about 24 per cent of its animal protein, if allowance is
made for the use of fishmeal in animal feeds. On a regional basis,
the percentage contribution of fish to animal protein in the diet is
greatest in Asia. In southeast Asia, for example, 55 per cent of the
animal protein consumed is derived from fish. In Africa, the figure is
1 9 per cent. Such regional statistics reveal little of the true contribu¬
tion made by fish to food supplies in developing countries; in some
communities, often the poorest, it may be the only source of
"meat". This dependence on fish is made all the more important
because the growth in demand, which is expected to double by the
turn of the century, is likely to be greatest in the developing world.
It has been estimated that the fisheries provide employment,
some of it part-time, for about sixteen million fishermen in develop¬
ing countries. Many more people are engaged in associated
activities, such as processing and marketing. The greater part of
this work force is associated with small-scale or artisanal fisheries.
Taking into account dependents, tens of millions in the Third World
must rely completely, or in a major way, on fisheries for their
livelihood. H
phytoplankton Zooplankton
Coral of the Great Barrier Reef, off Cairns,
Queensland, Australia
Excerpted from: Fisheries Development in the 1 980s,
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Rome
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
flying fish
dolphinfish
r^*^
lantern fish
<^<2^g^
toothed shark
^f, j-* *zl-J~ hatchetfish
¿^ /anglerfish
V
_^
>^wj^ 'éç?
r/^. fci- JmÊM
w& ^^^J
#
A brown sea perch photographed by
Soviet researchers in the Tadjoura Rift,
Gulf of Aden
glass sponges
qrenadier
a sea urchin
_ _ ..__ e
ocean bottom
A Bahrein!pearl-trader
displays his wares.
Below, a fine specimen of a coelacanth. It
is known as the "fossil-fish" because until
a living specimen was netted in the Indian
Ocean during the 1930s experts believed
that it had become extinct about seventy
million years earlier.
This greatly enlarged photo reveals the
beauty of the "peacock's tail" of the
common algae.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 32
Ancient Egyptians and the peoples of
Mesopotamia used extracts obtained
from seaweed, certain molluscs and the
tissue of venomous fish for medical pur¬
poses. Research into the possible medical
properties of marine organisms continues
throughout the world today. In the
USSR, for example, advanced research is
being carried out by the Institute of Sci¬
entific Research on Oceanography and
Marine Pisciculture.
The marine organisms that hold out the
greatest promise for medicine are mol¬
luscs (substances that can be used to reg¬
ulate the circulation of the blood have
been extracted from certain species), sea-
urchins, asteriidae (starfish), beroida
(comb-jellies), sea-anemones and certain
species of fish.
Already preparations extracted from
myxinii, a sub-order of fish (slime eels
and hagfish) found in the Pacific, are
being used as heart stimulants capable of
restoring normal functioning of the car¬
diac muscle, and a product obtained from
the tissues of the ostracion (box-fish or
coffer-fish) has proved its worth as a
powerful local anaesthetic. Study of cor¬
als seems likely to produce spectacular
results. Corals contain active substances
which can affect the functioning of the
heart and blood vessels, regulate metabo¬
lism, increase arterial pressure and pre¬
vent thrombosis and cerebral congestion.
The rarer creatures of the ocean also
form a living natural history museum, a
treasure-store of knowledge which we
have only begun to explore and which
holds the keys to the origins and evolu¬
tion of the flora and fauna of the oceans.
Imagine, for example, the astonish¬
ment of South African ichthyologist
J.B.L. Smith when, in 1938, asked to
identify from a sketch an unknown spe¬
cies of fish recently netted in the Indian
Ocean, he found himself looking at a
drawing of a "living fossil", a coelacanth,
a fish with large coarse scales and four
limb-like fins that is thought to be the
ancestor of four-legged terrestrial
vertebrates.
The fossil record shows that the coela¬
canth, a member of the crossopterygii
sub-order, dates back some 30U million
years and scientists had long believed it to
have been extinct for fifty to seventy mil¬
lion years. Smith began to search for
further specimens, but it was not until
1952 that other coelacanths were netted
off the Comoros Islands.
The discovery of the coelacanth
spurred scientists on to search for other,
perhaps unknown, creatures that might
exist in the ocean depths. Their efforts
were rewarded when, in 1952, the Danish
research ship Galatea fished up a neopili-
na from a depth of 3,580 metres in the
Pacific off the coast of Costa Rica. The
neopilina is a primitive marine mollusc
previously thought to have become ex¬
tinct some 350 million years ago. It forms
the link in the evolutionary chain be¬
tween marine worms and molluscs.
Also during the 1950s, Soviet scientists
aboard the research vessel Vityaz
brought up from the depths (10,500 met¬
res) of the Kuril-Kamchatka Trench a
number of worm-like creatures, one of
which proved to be of a hitherto unknown
type having no digestive tube.
To these remarkable discoveries must
be added those made in 1977 by United
States researchers on the floor of the
Pacific. Diving to depths of some two and
a half kilometres, near the Galapagos
Islands, in the mini-submarine Alvin,
they found themselves in an area where
the water temperature was as high as 17
degrees centigrade. When they returned
to the surface they found that the water
samples they had taken smelled strongly
of hydrogen sulphide. The water had
clearly seeped into cracks in the ocean
floor, circulating deep into hot rock and
leaching out chemicals from the rock be¬
fore emerging again heated up to an ex¬
tremely high temperature.
Hydrogen sulphides are toxic to higher
animals, but specific bacteria are immune
to its poisonous properties and, indeed,
base their metabolism upon it. Thus, in
the abyssal deeps of the ocean these bac¬
teria form the first link in a food chain
which supports thriving communities of
submarine creatures giant tube-worms,
clams, snails and sulphur-coloured
mussels.
Down in the almost total darkness of
the ocean depths, where the sun's rays do
not penetrate, life is based not on photo¬
synthesis which is powered by energy
from the sun, but on a process called
chemosynthesis which is fuelled by the
chemical energy in inorganic compounds.
Herein, perhaps, lies the secret of the
origin of life on this planet.
The ocean belongs to the whole of
humanity. It is the last frontier whose
exploration and exploitation is the con¬
cern of all the nations. It has already
yielded up many of its secrets, but many,
many more remain to be unveiled.
VITALI VOITOV, of the USSR, is a geographer
who has taken part in some forty research ex¬
peditions in the Pacific, Atlantic and Indian
Oceans. He is the author of 160 books and
scientific studies on oceanography, many of
which have been translated into English, French,
Italian and German. They include/The Research
Ship Vityaz; Prospects for Océanographie Re¬
search (written in collaboration with A. Monine,
corresponding member of the USSRAcademy of
Sciences); The Mystery of the Bermuda Tri¬
angle; and The Bounty of the Ocean.
V HT />
3 I
©
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Year of peace: 2
^^^^^^
The fortress of the Slovenes
Slovenj Gradee, a little Slovenian town of
8,000 people in northwest Yugoslavia, lies
at the crossroads of Central Europe, the
Baikans and the Mediterranean. It has a
long history. A Celtic, then a Roman colony
in ancient times, it owes its name "the
fortress of the Slovenes" to the presence
of Slavs there since the tenth century. Dur¬
ing the Second World War, this moun¬
tainous, forested site was the scene of
fierce fighting between partisans and the
Nazi occupying forces. The last battle in the
European theatre actually took place at
nearby Poljana on 15 May 1945, a week
after the armistice had been signed.
As a result of all its sufferings, Slovenj
Gradee today wishes to be a centre of
peace and understanding between cul¬
tures. Among its honorary citizens are two
internationally renowned sculptors, Henry
Moore (born 1898) and Ossip Zadkine
(1890-1967).
In 1965, the United Nations sponsored a
series of international exhibitions in the
vast modern gallery at Slovenj Gradee, and
in 1985 the little town organized an exhibi¬
tion of woodcuts to celebrate the fortieth
anniversary of the foundation of the United
Nations. One of the most striking exhibits
was the work of a local naive painter, J.
Tisnikar, an employee at the municipal hos¬
pital. The director of the hospital, a commit¬
ted pacifist, also took part in the event by
sponsoring a round table of specialists on
medicine for peace.
From 11 to 14 November 1985, a meet¬
ing of writers and journalists from nine
countries was held at Slovenj Gradee
Pi
under the auspices of Unesco and the Un¬
ited Nations. At the end of the symposium,
entitled "Pen for Peace", all the participants
stressed that real solidarity can exist be¬
tween nations, transcending simplistic poli¬
tical divergences, and that the writer in all
circumstances should seek the truth, which
is not the exclusive apanage of any indi¬
vidual, society, or State. Unesco was also
asked to encourage the translation and
publication, in the major world languages,
of anti-war literary works from small
countries.
Bogdan Pogachnik
The PEN Club and peace
The PEN Club groups between 10,000 and
1 1 ,000 writers from all over the world and
has 83 Centres in 57 countries. In 1983 it
created a Writers for Peace Committee to
define the responsibilities of writers and
decided that each year 3 March would be
celebrated as Writers for Peace Day. All
PEN Centres pledge to hold a meeting on
that day and to examine the problems that
arise in their respective countries. A meet¬
ing of this kind was held last year at Tel Aviv
in which Israeli and Arab writers took part. It
gave rise to lively exchanges of opinion, but
was also highly constructive.
Under the aegis of the chairman of this
special Committee, a meeting was also
held at Bled in Yugoslavia on the theme of
the myth of the hereditary enemy. It cannot
be denied that literature has created or
contributed to the creation of myths of this
type. The participants considered that it
was time to react and to explode this myth
once and for all by studying how it has been
formed through literature which remains
one of the great vehicles of contemporary
sensibility. The work of this meeting was
considered to be so important that the
Committee has suggested that the United
Nations publish a book on this theme in
1986 on the occasion of the International
Year of Peace.
The theme of the 48th International PEN
Congress, held in New York from 1 1 to 17
January was imagination of the State, im¬
agination of the writer. Later this year, a
meeting will be held in Hamburg on the
theme of contemporary history and its
image in literature.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office :
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 78 French francs. 2 years (valid only In France):
144 French francs. Binder for a year's issues : 56 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an International reply coupon covering postage. Signed ar¬
ticles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER. Photo capitions and headlines are written
by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published
in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produ¬
ced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by : Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xe¬
rox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (30 N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief : Olga Rodel
Managing Editor : Gillian Whitcomb
Editors :
English :
Roy Malkin
French : Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish : Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian : Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic : Sayed Osman
Braille : Frederick Potter
Research : Christiane Boucher
Illustrations : Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Georges Servat
Promotion : Fernando Ainsa
Special projects : Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-
Chief in Paris
Non4Headquarters editions
German : Werner Merkll (Berne)
Japanese : Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian : Mario Guidorti (Rome)
Hindi : Rajmanl Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil : M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew : Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian :
Dutch : Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese : Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish : Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu : Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan : Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian : Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean : Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili : Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene :
Bozidar Perkovic(Belgrade)
Chinese : Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian : Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek : Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala : S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish : Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish : Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque : Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai : Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
38 IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C 1 - Février 1986 - Commission paritaire N° 27.253 - Diffusé par les N.M.P.P.
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de l'UNESCO - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.l. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
&S2S*»»*"*
Mediterranean
Volume*
J-" ', ^%.
t^mv&:
Fishes of the North-eastern Atlantic and the
Mediterranean is an important new refer¬
ence work which describes the main tax-
onomic features and biology of all the
known marine fishes of the north-eastern
Atlantic and Mediterranean region a total
of 1,256 species from 218 families. Twenty
years in the making, the guide has been
prepared by an international team of spe¬
cialists (with contributions from over 70
authors) and is being published by Unesco
in 3 volumes over the period 1984-1986.
Volume I is now available.
Preface, Foreword and User's Guide are
in both English and French. The main text
is in English only. Common names of each
species are given in various languages, as
known.
FNAM will be of great value for many
years to come to workers in many disci¬
plines, such as marine biology, oceanogra¬
phy and fisheries science, as well as to those
concerned with the marine aspects of
zoogeography, physiology, embryology
and parasitology. All libraries and labor¬
atories, museums and universities will need
a set on their shelves.
FNAM can be purchased with local cur¬
rency through academic booksellers
worldwide (see list of suppliers of Unesco
publications below). Local prices may be
obtained from your bookseller. However
three sample prices for Volume I are as
follows:
250 FF at the
Unesco Bookshop
7 Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris
United Kingdom: £37.50
HMSO
P.O. Box 276
London SW8 5DT
United States $63.50
(plus relevant sales tax),
Unipub
P.O. Box 1222
Ann Arbor, MI 48106
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 175,
5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-101 1, Vienna. BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. - BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L, Spalena 51-1 1 3 02, Prague "
1; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 1 1 - 27 Prague 1 ¡Permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57. D 5300 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd.. P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport - ABT, P.O.B. 149 -
H-1 389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 BashirBagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 188 Enghlab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158, P.O. Box 11365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water. Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 1 13. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd.,
Quran House, Mfangano Street, P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd,
POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541 , Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod. Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 - 9494 Schaan.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück.
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service,
Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichin, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN 8.V.. Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office.
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1 721 Chnstchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1 104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of He; The University
ßookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1 , Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindern, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional
Office for Book development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi
Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES.
National Book Store, Inc. 701, Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-'Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra
Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road,
Singapore 2261. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern
Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH
AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News agency, P.O. Box 1033. Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1 1 1 8,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl,
Regeringsgatan 12. Box 16356. 10327
"Stockholm 1 6. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 1 50 50 S- 1 04 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscenwalen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rámistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
1 1 , CCP. 1 2-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dares-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. TURKEY. Haset Kitap^i A.S.,
Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219. Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC IX 9 DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor, Ml 48106. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow. 121200. YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, P.O. Box 4227. Aden. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, Mica 30/1 1, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/1 1, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
*/*
£'// ' ' - * A
]]>
</page>
</document>
