<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068623eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
KO-51 Í loi. j\
APRIL
19 56
(9th year)
Price : 9d. (U. K.)
40 francs (France)
inLLERS
OF THE
NSECT
WORLD
The Big Five
of ancient
and modern
'Plagues'
¿
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
BEAUTIFUL, BUT...
Houses of the Banana tribesmen in French
Cameroons are built on stilts above a
swamp teeming with mosquitoes. Village
is one of some 200 scattered throughout
a forest area where ways of fighting
malaria are tested by an Anti-Malaria
Experimental Centre. (See page 22)
WHO - Pierre Pittet
m*'
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
N° 4 - APRIL 1956
9th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
By Dr. M.G. Candau
5 KILLERS OF THE INSECT WORLD
By Dr. B. de Meillon
9 A LITTLE BLACK GNAT
It threatens 19 million people with blindness
10 IN THE 'VALLEY OF THE BLIND'
By Anthony Lavers
12 THE SLEEP THAT KILLS
By J. Ford
15 THE TERROR OF PLAGUE IN THE MIDDLE AGES
By Dr. Georges Barraud
FLEAS, RATS AND MEN
Links in a deadly chain
18
22
BLACK DEATH' LURKS UNDERGROUND
THE FEVER OF THE THREE DEMONS'
Malaria's staggering toll of death and Infirmity
25 THE LAST REFUGE OF YELLOW FEVER
By Dr J. Austin Kerr
27 QUERIES FROM THE INSECT WORLD
28 HOW FAR DOES A FLY FLY 7
Radio isotopes provide an answer
By Dale W.Jenkins
30 DISEASE KNOWS NO FRONTIERS
The story of quarantine
By Dr. Neville M. Goodman
32 THE UNWANTED TRAVELLERS
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leyentis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not copyrighted may be reprinted from THE UNESCO
COURIER but must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted
from UNESCO COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's
name. Prints of non-copyright photos are available on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE UNESCO
COURIER
Annual subscription rates of THE UNESCO COURIER : 8/-;S2.S0or 400
French frs or equivalent.
(MC. 56. 1. 101 A)
COVER PHOTO
It is no longer necessary to cremate the
bodies of plague victimscurrent practice
in the past. Bodies are usually buried by
special squads provided with parapher¬
nalia like masks, protective garments
and sometimes boots, rubber gloves or
stout canvas mittens.
Institut Pasteur, Paris
HP
here are many diseases that cannot spread unless
m . carried by insects. They are among the most
ancient afflictions of mankind, and have played their part
in shaping his history. Malaria has influenced the rise
and fall of civilizations, epidemics of plague and of yellow
fever have again and again decimated populations in the
old and the new worlds, while outbreaks of louse-borne
typhus have often determined the outcome of military
campaigns. Sleeping sickness and a less well-known
.disease, onchocerciasis, have held back progress in Africa.
These and a score of other diseases carried by flying
and crawling insects have enfeebled whole sections of the
human race, depopulated fertile food-producing tracts,
and held down man's levels of living particularly in the
tropics but also in temperate climates. Despite the strides
that have been made in our own day towards the control
of many of these scourges, there is scarcely one which
does not still represent an actual or potential danger to
large numbers of human beings.
Most of these diseases have been known and feared
for centuries, but it was not until about 60 years ago that
scientists began to suspect the part played by insects as
carriers. It was only in the early years of the present
century that painstaking research established with certainty
the action of many different species of insects such as
mosquitoes, tsetse flies, sandflies, fleas, lice, as well as
of ticks and mites in transmitting many pestilences.
In the first flush of enthusiasm following these discoveries
it was thought that, once the carrier was known, any disease
would be virtually conquered. Indeed, in a relatively short
time yellow fever was banished from most of the cities
of the Americas, the incidence of malaria was reduced
particularly in the towns and in the more temperate zones,
and certain other diseases were successfully attacked.
Rapid progress, however, became possible only after
the discovery during the last war of the "residual"
insecticides, of which the best known is (Cont'd on
probably DDT. The special character of these .
chemicals is that they remain deadly for periods
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
(Continued from previous page)
ranging up to several months after application One
of their first triumphs was to strangle the threat of
typhus epidemics during and after the war. Next,
they proved amazingly effective when correctly used
to control malaria, even in the sparsely-settled rural
districts. There is scarcely an insect-borne disease
against which these new chemicals are not being
used today with greater or less effect.
But again disappointment has followed too opti¬
mistic hopes. First the common housefly, and now
some mosquitoes as well as lice, cockroaches and
bed-bugs in certain areas, have shown that, after a
few years of exposure to the action of these killers,
they can develop resistance which protects them from
fatal effects. In the case of the housefly this hap¬
pens rather quickly, and these chemicals have there¬
fore become of little value. With the mosquito,
however, the insecticide can be used effectively for
several years, during which period an all-out cam¬
paign is able to eradicate diseases like malaria so that,
if the mosquitoes should, in time, develop resistance,
there is no malaria left for them to carry.
Another and very serious difficulty is that many
insect-borne diseases appear to exist more or less
permanently among wild animals which thus provide
a reservoir of infection that may suddenly spread to
start epidemics among domestic animals and humans.
Yellow fever is known to be firmly entrenched in
the jungles among monkeys and other animals ;
plague smoulders in many places among wild rodents
whence it can easily spread to the rats that live with
men ; the trypanosome that causes sleeping sickness
exists permanently in wild game in Africa and is
carried to men and cattle by the tsetse fly. There
are many other examples among diseases caused by
viruses and "rickettsiae".
It would be a serious mistake to underestimate
these ancient enemies of mankind. It is already
clear that the residual insecticides, powerful weapons
though they be, do not provide the final answer
to the disease-carrying insect. Nor is there at present
any prospect of eradicating those diseases that have
become permanently established among the domestic
and wild animals. There they remain, a constant
threat calling for constant watchfulness.
World Health Day on April 7, this year will,
I hope, serve to make people everywhere realize that,
although the insect-borne diseases are being increas¬
ingly held in check, they are not yet conquered. To
achieve that final victory man will need all his intel¬
ligence and resourcefulness. Above all, he will need
to act in concert, for this group of diseases is one of
the greatest challenges to international health action.
Dr. M. G. Candau.
Doctors in Cairo. Egypt, at special ophthalmology course.
WORLD NOW HAS
1,200,000 DOCTORS
There are now 1,200,000 physicians in the world according
to a recent survey of the World Health Organization;
which also reveals that between 50,000 and 60,000 new
doctors graduate each year from some b00 medical schools in
85 countries. The WHO report points out that this is not enough
in view of the world's health needs and the inequality of dis¬
tribution of doctors in different countries.
There are only 14 countries, it states, fortunate enough to
have one doctor to serve every thousand inhabitants or less.
But there are 22 countries where only one doctor is available
for 20,000 people or even more. Between these two extremes,
the figures vary greatly for the rest of the 124 countries and
territories which make up today's world. In addition, the
report adds, many doctors are engaged in teaching, research,
administration and other duties which are not directly concern¬
ed with the care of patients, and this must be taken into
account when looking at the statistics. The report also
confirms previous findings that rural areas are under-manned
while cities often have too many medical practitioners.
The WHO study underlines the "definite, immediate need for
planning the construction of medical schools" in many parts
of the world. It shows that while nine countries have one
medical school for less than one million of population, there
are 13 countries with only one medical school for 9 to 17 million
people. Distribution of doctors and medical schools by continent
is shown below.
DISTRIBUTION OF DOCTORS AND
MEDICAL SCHOOLS BY CONTINENTS
Areas Population
Number
of
medical
schools
Popula¬
tion per
medical
school
Number
of
physi¬
cians
Popula¬
tion per
physi¬
cian
Annual
number
of
medical
grad¬
uates
211,851,000
233,872,000
120,731,000
1 ,370,961 ,000
83,112,000
614,831,000
13,910,000
14
122
51
152
13
237
6
15,132,000
1,917,000
2,367,000
9,020,000
6,393,000
2,594,000
2,318,000
23,253
247,220
48,202
201 ,502
16,970
643,144
12,083
9,111
946
2,505
6,804
4,898
956
1,151
855
8,930
3,733
11,582
859
27,177
753
North A. Centr.
South America .
East. Med	
2,649,268,000 595 4,453,000 1,192,374 2,222 53,889
Director-General, World Health Organization
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courter. April 1956
KILLERS OF THE They once C0||Pere[i wl10le armies
INSECT WORLD Science now has them on the run
In the history we learned at school battles were won by
the brilliant tactics of generals, marshals and admir¬
als and sometimes by the special interposition of
Providence. Today, however, we have come to recognize
that generals were often relatively unimportant.
In many cases, the real victor is shown to have been
epidemic disease. Among the most important of these
diseases is louse typhus which has decided the course of
many battles and campaigns. In 1632 for example, Gus-
tavus Adolphus and Wallenstein prepared for battle near
Nuremburg, but before the slaughter could begin both
armies had to flee before the ravages of typhus.
There does not seem to be very much doubt that Napo¬
leon's worst enemy was General Disease, among whose
ablest henchmen was the louse. When Napoleon prepar¬
ed for his advance into Russia in 1812 he mobilized about
half a million men. In June of that
year typhus began to appear and by
July, after Ostrowa, there were
80,000 ill.
When the retreat from Moscow
began there were less than 100,000
troops fit for service. Another 80,000
sick were left at Smolensk in Novem¬
ber and when Vilna was reached in
December the army had dwindled
down to 20,000 men.
It is not necessary to dwell on the
horrors the sick had to endure in
Vilna. By the end of June 1813 only
3,000 remained alive !
During the course of, and after, the
by Dr. B. de Meillon
South African Institute of Medical
Research, Johannesburg
WHO - Marc Riboud
CHANCE OF SURVIVAL for these Iranian children is only fifty per-cent half the babies born
in their village die in infancy or childhood. Many deathsboth infant and adultare caused by
insect-borne diseases in this part of Iran. (See next page for a story on how the people of
Farimaneh in Iran, fought back against insects that bring sickness and death to their village.)
first world war millions of people
died from typhus, many more indeed
than were killed by bullets.
Ten years before his Russian cam¬
paign, Napoleon had been severely
defeated by the mosquito. In 1801
when his brilliant Italian campaign
was at an end and he had defeated
the Austrians and concluded the
treaty of Marengo, he decided to
occupy the island of Haiti and from
there strengthen the forces in Loui¬
siana on the mainland of America.
He therefore despatched Leclerc
with 30,000 troops for this purpose.
Haiti was at this time ruled by that
tragic figure Toussaint Louverture
who, ironically enough, had shortly
before helped the French drive the
English out of the island.
Toussaint, with his ill-trained and
badly equipped army, decided to
defend his homeland. For the Haiti¬
ans the situation appeared hopeless,
especially when Toussaint was cap¬
tured. But when all seemed lost, a
little black and white mosquito, car¬
rying yellow fever, began to take a
hand in affairs and by 1803 Leclerc
had lost 23,000 of his troops. He was
forced to evacuate the island, and
the Republic was saved. (See the
UNESCO courier, N° -2, 1954.)
In 1885, de Lesseps, the
creator of Suez, set out to - (Cont'd on
cut the two Americas in page 7)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
- ^.~*w^r^
IRAN'S VILLAGERS HELP
THEMSELVES TO HEALTH
The people who live in the Sabzevar district of Iran are
plagued by insect-borne diseases malaria, typhus and
trachoma, a blinding eye disease to name only the most
common. Villagers had always accepted these sicknesses
fatalisticallyuntil last year, when the Iranian Govern¬
ment began disease control operations in their area.
A health and sanitation team which. included WHO per¬
sonnel began to work in 22 villages where the incidence
of disease was highest, and the idea of health precautions
and better hygiene gradually caught on. In Farimaneh,
where sanitation work started, a health council was set
up, the water supply was improved and cleaned, the
six existing latrines were increased to 63 and rubbish
was dumped in pits dug outside the village. These and
other co-operative activities removed the most obvious
threats to health. Photos show: (I) A "shot" öf BHC
powder deals with typhus-bearing lice (2) Streets were
soon cleared of rubbish and swept clean (3) Wall posters
put up to encourage youngsters to be health-con'scious.
-~*s
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
KILLER
INSECTS
(Contd) THEY MOULDED THE DESTINY OF NATIONS
half. The expedition was a failure largely because of the
ravages of yellow fever, and de Lesseps, who had once
been hailed as the greatest conqueror of nature and who
had received honours from kings, governments and scien¬
tific bodies, returned to France a broken man and died in
comparative poverty.
A few years later the Americans began to work on the
Panama canal and they too nearly had to abandon the
project because by 1905 yellow fever was again taking a
great toll.
It was at this juncture that a U.S. Army surgeon, Gene¬
ral Gorgas, took charge of the health of the expedition.
By 1914, when the canal was completed, the death rate
was lower than that of any American city or state.
Such is the impression that this disease made on the
minds of men that it has inspired at least one well known
legend, that of the "Flying
Dutchman", which is
thought to refer to a ship
stricken with yellow fever
and refused entry into port,
and one equally well-known
poem, Coleridge's "The An¬
cient Mariner". When this
sole survivor tells the wed¬
ding guest:
/ looked upon the rotting
[sea
and drew my eyes away;
I looked upon the rotting
[deck,
and there the dead men
[lay...
he is probably describing
an epidemic on board ship
in the calms of the Carib¬
bean Sea.
In Africa today the popu¬
lation is estimated to be
135 millions... yet it has
been calculated that there
is room for nearly 2.000
millions. Why is it that
this vast continent is at
present only carrying 7%
of the possible total?
There are many answers
to this question but the
chief among them is un¬
doubtedly an insect-borne
disease, and of the numer¬
ous diseases of Africa none
has played a greater part
in the past than sleeping sickness of man and nagana of
cattle, both carried by tsetse flies.
It seems highly probable that Africa earned its name
of "The Dark Continent" because of the tsetse fly. Early
Arab and Portuguese travellers were considerably hamper¬
ed and disaster often overtook them. Indeed the
gradual withdrawal of the Arabs from the interior to the
Eastern coastal belt was certainly due to the tsetse fly.
Up to the year 1880 human sleeping sickness was
almost completely confined to West Africa and known
under a variety of names. Many Negro slaves imported
into places as far apart as the West Indies and Marti¬
nique were known to suffer from a kind of lethargy and
melancholy. This was attributed to homesickness and
the afflicted person was supposed to be dreaming of his
homeland.
Early historians remark with interest that even the
whip could not awaken them from their dreams. Longfel¬
low in his "Slave's Dream" written in 1842, most probably
describes a case of sleeping sickness:
Bes'de the ungathered rice he lay
His sickle in his hand;
His breast was bare, his matted hair
Was buried in the sand.
He did not feel the driver's whip;
Nor the burning heat of day...
CARLOS
CHAGAS
AND THE
CONE-
NOSED
BUGS
Copyright J. Pinto
Some 45 years ago, Carlos Chagas, a Brazilian scientist, made
medical history by the method he used to discover a disease
which now bears his name: "Chagas disease", a fever which can
cause severe and often fatal damage to the heart. Chagas achieved
the still unequalled distinction of having found the cause of a disease
before the disease itself. In 1909 while doing anti-malaria work in
Brazil, Chagas became interested in the large and voracious blood¬
sucking bugs with cone-shaped noses which infested local mud huts.
Laboratory tests showed these bugs were carrying microbes similar
to the African trypanosomes which cause sleeping sickness. Chagas
next found that these microbes could cause disease In laboratory
animals. Returning to the place where the bugs had been found,
Chagas discovered a cat with similar microbes in its blood and then,
in the same house, a young girl suffering from fever. He clinched
his important discovery by finding the ¡microbes in her blood also.
Since 1880 sleeping sickness has spread east over most
of central Africa as far as the Great Lakes and south
into Portuguese East Africa and Bechuanaland.
Increased travel and the gradual opening up of the
continent has undoubtedly played a large part in aiding
the distribution of the disease. Stanley (of "Dr. Living¬
stone, I presume" fame) is regarded with great suspicion
in this respect. In 1887 he started off on an expedition
to rescue Eduard Schnitzer, better known by the romantic
name of Emin Pasha, and Stanley's porters from the
Lower Congo are said to have brought the disease to the
Great Lakes where it was previously unknown.
Among all the diseases to which man is subject malaria
is without doubt one of the most important. If you take a
map of the world and draw a line along 60 degrees north
latitude, and one along 30 degrees south latitude you will
have a wide belt in which
malaria occurs. Some areas
in this belt are free from
the disease, but on the
whole it is fairly evenly
spread between these two
lines of latitude.
Within this vast area
millions of people die from
malaria, many more suffer
from the weakening effects
of the disease, countless
hours of work are lost and
the direct and indirect
influence on production
would stagger the imagina¬
tion if it could be calculat¬
ed with any certainty.
Through malaria civiliza¬
tions have been wiped out,
successful colonization
prevented, and large tracts
of fertile land have been
depopulated.
Bubonic plague, trans¬
mitted from rat to man by
fleas, has also done much
to decimate populations
and it is said that the
great pandemic, known as
the "Black Death" which
started in the 14th century
and raged for four hun¬
dred years, killed twenty-
five minion people in Eu¬
rope alone. (See page 15.)
There are, of course,
many other insect-borne diseases than those I have
mentioned, such as filariasis, relapsing fevers, leishma¬
niasis, rickettsial fevers, virus diseases and so on which,
though perhaps less spectacular, have nevertheless pro¬
duced their quotas of death and illness. Many of them
still present problems of great importance today.
The reader may well ask what has been done about all
this? Many of these diseases are now under partial or
complete control in many countries. How has this been
achieved? What is the overall technique which has led
in many cases to success and will it be applicable in the
future?
The vector-borne diseases depend for their existence on
three things, namely, 1. the host, e. g. man, and often in
addition some other animal, 2. the parasite, e. g. Plasmo¬
dium, 3. the vector (or carrier of the parasite) e.g. the
Anopneles mosquito. Break this chain anywhere and
the disease ceases to reach man. In the early days em¬
phasis was laid on the host or the parasite. This was
largely due to lack of knowledge of the vector.
Man on the other hand was readily available. He was,
and still is drug conscious. At a word he will open his
mouth and swallow a pill! Mass application of drugs,
however, presents great administrative difficulties and
has rarely been entirely successful on its own. Ir
Also really effective drugs exist for only a few ' * on
diseases and they are generally costly. next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
KILLER
I NSE CTS
(Cont'd) CLUES FROM SCIENCE'S 'ROGUES' GALLERY'
With the coming of the 20th century and the great
discoveries of pioneers like Manson, Ross, Grassi, Nicolle
and Reed, emphasis became focused on the disease
carriers themselves and their study was intensified
through the years, resulting In marked and often pheno¬
menal success in disease control. How has this been
achieved?
The first problem in the study of any creature is its
identity. Things must be identifiable before we can study
them, write about them and exchange views about them.
The naming and identification of the insect vectors has
in this way played a very significant role and lies at the
very foundation of the study of their habits and ecology.
Case of mistaken identity
Discoveries relating to the . identity of a certain
carrier of malaria, namely, Anopheles gambiae in
Africa, enabled malariologists to recognize the
species and its potential dangers when it was accidentally
introduced into South America.
The species having been identified it was a simple
matter to read all that was known about it, to carry out
further work and finally to single it out and strike at its
weakest point.
In the early days of malaria control in South Africa a
puzzling situation was discovered. The vectors of mal¬
aria had been identified as Anopheles gambiae and
Anopheles funestus. Furthermore it was found that
they were largely house-frequenting and preferred biting
man to any other animal.
The method and site of attack on them appeared
obvious, namely, with insecticides in human habitations.
However, further work showed that large numbers of
funestus could be captured in holes in the ground, under
stones, in crevices in river banks, under vegetation etc.
Further, they were also found in areas where malaria
occured only sporadically or not at all. What was to be
done with this huge insect population, how were they to
be controlled, was it a practical proposition, could it be
financed and above all was it necessary?
The problem, however, was quite easily and neatly
solved when it was discovered that these out-of-door
customers were not funestus at all but another species
which was not a disease carrier but which resembled
funestus so closely in the adult stage that they were to
all appearances identical. Discovery of their larval an-J
egg stages provided the key because they were different
and easily recognizable. The correct naming of carriers
is the basis of an understanding of the whole problem
of insect-borne diseases.
Once a carrier is properly labelled and can be recog¬
nized under all circumstances the next procedure is to
find out all about it. What are its requirements,' how
does it live, why is it a carrier, and so on?
Exterminated by air attack
Answers to these questions are of vital importance
as they often yield the answers to control. It is
rare for one single line of attack to emerge from
such studies. Usually many vulnerable points are revealed
and it is then a matter of expediency, costs, local condi¬
tions and so on as to which methods are applied.
A method which is successful or promising in one area
may be a relative failure in another because local condi¬
tions are not applicable. In Zululand, for instance, the
tsetse fly Glossina pallidipes was exterminated largely by
aerial spraying of insecticide. The area was compara¬
tively small, there was little likelihood of reinfestation,
the cost was high but economically worth it. The method
is obviously only applicable under these conditions and
cannot be applied indiscriminately all over Africa.
It is in this search for knowledge about the economy,
habits and requirements of the carriers of disease that
much work still remains to be done. Nowhere is this
better illustrated than in the control of mosquitoes. At
least twice in the history of malaria control a feeling
has been apparent that the problem was solved.
Firstly, when the carriers were found to be Anophelines
the answer appeared to be simple: destroy them and the
disease will disappear. It did not take long to discover
that this was not so easy. The second occasion arose
when the modern insecticides like DDT became avail¬
able. But instead of putting an end to work on the
carriers this insect ki.ler has served as a great stimulus to
research and in many instances revealed how ignorant we
are in many ways of disease carrier biology.
It is fairly safe to say that more research is being done
today than ever before because of the gaps that have
been revealed in our knowledge through studying the
effects of DDT. The emphasis today, of course, is still
on the residual insecticides and their names are on
everyone's lips.
Biologists, however, have not forgotten that many eco¬
logical 'factors, including the habits of man, have to
combine in a particular manner before the complicated
series of events wh'ch lead to successful transmission and
maintenance of a. vector-borne disease, takes place.
Sometimes it is cheaper and easier in many cases to
bring about a change in these nice.y balanced events. In
many cases it is definitely desirable. Teaching people
to use soap and water and to keep themselves clean is
obviously a better method of controlling louse-borne
typhus than continual use of DDT. Again, teaching peo¬
ple to water their cattle at places that have been made
safe from the tsetse fly is obviously a neater and cheap¬
er method of preventing sleeping sickness than large-
scale aerial spraying or bush and forest clearing.
Might set the clock back
In certain parts of tropical America the insects which
carry malaria have been found to breed exclusively
in certain plants which live on forest trees. Success¬
ful control has been achieved by deforestation and
subsequent use of the land for agricultural purposes.
Where slopes are too steep for vegetable growing, use¬
ful timber is grown which can be cut easily before the
mosquito-haunted plants establish themselves. Further
research, this time on the ecology of the plants them¬
selves, may show that they will grow only on certain
trees. It may be possible to rea-fforest with trees that
the plants don't like.
Such methods which may be called ecological or bio¬
logical, are often so simple and obvious it is hard to
believe that they are the result of many years of pains¬
taking research. The future of the control of insect-
carriers of disease has never appeared to be brighter than
at present but there is no reason for complacency. Fur¬
ther research is urgently required and must be main¬
tained at a high level.
Modern insecticides have tremendous advantages and
have proved a great blessing to mankind but if they tend
to halt further biological and ecological research, of which
there is already evidence in some countries, they might
easily set the clock back.
The living organism is not a machine but a resilient,
pliable and variable entity. It has survived aeo^s of
time because of this and is not easy to put aside or destroy.
Resistance to the residual insecticides (see page 29) is
being reported more frequently as time passes, their long-
term effects on man himself are not properly known and
their manufacture is costly and a drain on our resources.
The aim in the future, in my view, should be to find
ways of controlling insect-carriers by ecological methods.
They will prove to be the cheapest, the most lasting and
in the long run the most effective.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
WHO Match
A LITTLE BLACK GNAT
Threatens 19 million people with blindness
A tiny black fly (above, left) threatens something like I 9 million people in large areas of Africa and Latin America with a
disease called onchocerciasis (pronounced on'-ko-ser-ky'asis). When this gnat bites a human being, tiny parasitic worms enter
the human body. They first cause painful lumps, then invade the tissue of the eyes, bringing total blindness. In the
Chad, (French Equatorial Africa) insecticides are sprayed by helicopter (above, right) over gnat-infested areas. Disease
is already so widespread that tragic replicas of Breughel's painting "The blind leading the blind" are often seen (below).
Mater
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
BLACK GNAT
	 (Continued) 	
in the Valley of the Blind'
Through an Irishman's pluck and
perseverance a province of.
Kenya, Britain's East African
colony, has been rid of its most
dreaded scourge the tiny flies which
brought blindness to thousands of
middle-aged African men and women.
The scientist who solved one of the
most intriguing medical problems
which had defied scientists for over
30 years is genial, burly James Patrick
McMahon, a 50-year-old Kenya
Medical Department entomologist
who le'ft Dublin for army service in
1922, and came to Kenya in 1929 to
join the Medical Service.
Insects fascinate Mr. McMahon and
in Myanza Province, the vast col¬
lection of African tribal lands fring¬
ing Lake Victoria, he found them in
numbers and variety to exceed his
most cherished expectations. And,
in particular, one tiny species of fly,
known as Simulium Neavei, caught
his attention. The fiy carried the
microscopic worm which causes the
disease called river blindness.
When the fly bites human beings
it transmits the worms which
multiply under the skin, working
their way towards the eyes. If the
disease is not halted, by middle age
they destroy the eye tissues and bring
total blindness.
Finding the adult fly was easy
enough. In some areas there were
concentrations of thousands in every
glade. But to kill it, science
had to know where and how it spent
the larva and pupa stages.
River blindness onchocerciasis to
medical workers is confined in
Kenya to the hilly regions of Nyanza
Province. The highlands are inter¬
sected by hundreds of mountain
streams. Where there was running
water the concentration of fly was
strongest and the incidence of blind¬
ness among African villagers most
prevalent.
Medical men baffled
For this first attempt to solve a
problem which had baffled
dozens of medical workers, Mc¬
Mahon chose an area dubbed "The
Valley of the Blind", where one out
of every six tribesmen had lost his
sight, and 90 per cent of the- popu¬
lation in some places was infected.
World War II put an end to the work,
but McMahon resumed it in 1946, by
then convinced that the fly somehow
bred in rivers.
He therefore tried "dosing" rivers
with a DDT solution. It worked, and
subsequent tests in the "Valley of the
Blind" showed that the fly had been
eradicated from that district. The
riddle of the fly's life cycle remained
unsolved, but McMahon now had an
effective weapon against his enemy,
and he was quick to use it.
The main river blindness area was
in uie norchern districts of Nyanza.
Mr. McMahon began an 18-month
survey to determine the exact area of
infection before the work of fly eli-
10
by Anthony Lavers
mination began. It covered an area
of 6,000 square miles and narrowed
the infection focus down to 1,000
square miles.
Steep mountain valleys, dense for¬
ests and thick bush were the survey's
main obstacles. The teams had to
hack 400 miles of trails through the
forests and strip the bush from the
banks of hundreds of streams and
brooks, most of them unmapped.
Snakes were as common as pigeons in
London's Trafalgar Square, and en¬
counters with buffalo Africa's most
dangerous big gamewere part of the
daily routine. But the greatest dan¬
ger lay in getting lost in dense jungle.
This happened several times, cul¬
minating with the disappearance of
an African worker who tried to make
a short cut back to camp. He died
Copyright Camera Press.
HUNTER AND HUNTED : Mr. J. P.
McMahon, the man who solved the river
blindness problem in Kenya, examines a crab
bearing the larvae of the black gnat which
carries the blinding disease.
of shock and exhaustion and his
body was discovered two days later.
When the survey was complete, each
team had walked some 3,000 miles
through some of Africa's toughest
country.
Dosing the streams in the affected
area was followed with partial
success in 1947. In the meantime
McMahon continued his search for
the larvae's habitat. Nearly all spe¬
cies of fish, crabs and insects found
in the North Nyanza rivers were
examined. Streams were dammed
and diverted. At one stage McMahon
considered hiring a diver's suit to
explore the river beds personally.
Then came encouragement. An¬
other Kenya scientist, Dr. V. D. Van
Someren, found the larva of a fly si¬
milar to Simulium Neavei attached to
a mayfly nymph. He told McMahon
of his discovery, and the indomitable
Irishman again plunged quite liter¬
ally into the search.
He returned to the southern high¬
lands and searched every square foot
of a river running through a badly
infected area. The fact that he ran
a grave risk of contracting a disease
for which there is no cure did not
deter him. He and his African assist¬
ants spent weeks waist-deep in water
and once more the results were nil.
Other entomologists might well
have pigeonholed the river blindness
problem as just another African
medical mystery. But McMahon and
his team simply moved' downstream
to another and bigger river. And
there they met success.
Into the crab's hideout
Wading through the shallows,
the team pulled out hundreds
of crabs of a hitherto unexa¬
mined species. Nearly all of them
carried both larvae and pupae of
Simulium Neavei, McMahon knew he
had slammed the door on the river
blindness ghoul which haunted
thousands of African homes.
Soon the Nyanza medical authori¬
ties launched the final drive to
exterminate Simulium Neavei. When
the last of North Nyanza's 170-odd
rivers had been given their last dos¬
age of DDT mixture last year, the
experts felt reasonably certain that
river blindness will never again
afflict this peaceful and fertile corner
of Kenya.
More than one and a quarter tons
of pure DDT were used in treating
each of the rivers and tributaries at
fortnightly intervals over a three-
month period. The whole project,
including the preliminary survey
work and mapping, had kept Mr. Mc¬
Mahon and his team of four Euro¬
pean and 40 African helpers working
fulltime for four years.
The dosing programme has been
overwhelmingly successful. Eight
years ago an area was treated where
36 per cent of the children below the
age of six were found to be infected
with river blindness. In 1953 a medi¬
cal survey showed that not a single
child in a similar age group had con¬
tracted the disease.
James McMahon is now turning his
talents to other medical problems. The
elimination of malaria and other
tropical ills have still to be achieved.
But the Government of Kenya did
not forget his victory, and the 1955
New Year's Honours List announced
the award of the Order of the British
Empire to Mr. J. P. McMahon, senior
entomologist, Nyanza 'Province, for a
"discovery of very great importance
to science and medicine." His pioneer
work in solving the fly's life cycle
problem, the citation added, was
"carried out at considerable risk of
infecting himself."
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
DESERTED VILLAGE In French Equatorial Africa (left) is one of
many abandoned by people who lived in an area heavily infested by
the black gnats whose bites cause a blinding disease. Many of the
Match.
middle-aged inhabitants were already blind. Here and in other
large areas of Africa, a blind man being led by a youngster whose eyes
have not yet been affected by the disease is a common sight (right).
DISEASE OF DIRTY HANDS. One of the oldest known diseases
and still one of the most widespread is trachoma. If left untreated
trachoma causes blindness. It flourishes where elementary hygiene
does not exist and has thus been called "the disease of dirty hands".
WHO and UNICEF
It is spread by flies in countries where flies are so numerous that
people become indifferent (left). Anti-trachoma campaigns are
carried out with aid from WHO and UNICEF. Right, "nurses" of school
health committee apply anti-biotlc ointment at Sanafir, Egypt.
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The sleep that kills
by J. Ford
Director, East Africa Tsetse and Trypanoso¬
miasis Research and Reclamation Organization
From the southern edge of the Sa¬
hara Desert to Zululand in the
Union of South Africa the peo¬
ples of tropical Africa are afflicted by
a number of diseases carried by
tsetse flies (Glossina).
These insects infest -about four and
a half million square miles of land.
In much of this vast area (half as
great again as that of Australia)
their bite may infect man with a mi¬
nute protozoan organism, a trypano-
some, which produces the fatal sleep¬
ing sickness. Over all of it tsetse
flies transmit other trypanosomes
which are fatal to cattle and other
domestic animals.
This means that the African, even
if he is fortunate enough to live in
an area free of sleeping sickness, may
be deprived of much needed animal
protein in his diet, while his agricul¬
tural activities suffer both from lack
of fertilizing manure and of draught
animals.
Further, there is, naturally, a ten¬
dency for the human population, with
its cattle, to crowd into the relatively
small areas which are free of tsetse
fly. The result is that the land is
overworked and over-stocked and
suffers accordingly.
In short, the tsetse fly, through the
diseases it transmits, affects directly
or indirectly, the whole economy of
tropical Africa and there can be no
doubt that the poor situation of the
African can be attributed very large¬
ly to this terrible scourge.
There are twenty-three known
species of tsetse fly, some living in the
rain forest, some in the vegetation
fringing laikes and rivers, others in
the woodlands and bush of drier
Photos from French Cameroons on these
pages show some aspects of research
into sleeping sickness caused by the tsetse
fly and treatment that Is given to the victims
of this dreaded disease. (1) In the second
stage of the disease the sick man becomes
weak, anaemic and more and more emacia¬
ted. He begins to sink into a coma which
becomes so deep that he dies of exhaustion
and starvation. (2) Villagers wait to be
weighed and vaccinated. (3) A young
mother and her baby are given injections of
lomidine. (4) An entomologist classifies
and counts pupae of tsetse flies brought
by insect catchers. (5) At the research
station of the pilot project In Yaounde,
guinea pigs are strapped to cages filled
with tsetse flies. The flies feed off the
guinea pigs until they are needed for dis¬
section and analysis.
WHO - Pierre Pittet
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956.
r. *'iß^P
areas, but all requiring the shade of
trees or bush to survive.
They vary in size from that of a
large blue-bottle to about that of a
common house fly and all feed only
upon the blood of animals.
Many of these animals, the wild
game of Africa, carry in their blood
the parasitic trypanosomes which to
them are harmless. When the tsetse
fly feeds it may suck up these try¬
panosomes, which develop in it so
that it becomes itself infected and
infective.
In the normal course of events it
is likely to feed again only on wild
animals and no harm is done, but to
man or to cattle its bite may bring
death.
Just as there are several kinds of
tsetse fly, so there are several kinds
of trypanosome.
Two species cause sleeping sickness
in man. In West Africa, the Congo
and as far East as Lake Victoria the
disease is generally in the form
known as Gambian Sleeping Sickness.
It is transmitted by tsetse flies living
along rivers so that dangerous foci
tend to develop where the people go
to draw water or to bathe.
Although these riverine tsetse may
feed very largely on reptiles, there is
much evidence that man himself is
often the only host of the trypano¬
some of Gambian Sleeping Sickness.
In the afflicted territories millions
of people are subject to the risk of
this disease and in the past there
have been appalling epidemics, for
example, in Uganda between 1896 and
1906 when it was estimated that
200,000 people died.
The other form of the human, dis¬
ease, Rhodesian Sleeping Sickness,
is largely confined to East and Cen¬
tral Africa.
Here there is much evidence sug¬
gesting that the wild game form an
important reservoir of the disease
which is largely carried by a tsetse
infesting vast areas of dry woodland
and not confined to rivers. The Rho¬
desian Disease is more acute than the
Gambian and, untreated, kills much
more quickly.
Some twenty-five years ago a drug
(Bayer 205 or Antrypol) was produc¬
ed in Germany which could cure the
early stages of both diseases and
somewhat later the Americans discov¬
ered another drug (Tryparsamide) ef¬
fective in more advanced cases of the
Gambian disease.
During the war other drugs (diami-
dines, especially pentamidine) were
developed in the United Kingdom
which not only provided a useful cure
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE SLEEP THAT KILLS
	(Continued)	
in the early stages, but also showed
marked prophylactic effects against
the Gambian disease.
But it is only very recently that yet
another group of drugs has been pro¬
duced which offers hope to sufferers
in the later stages of Rhodesian
Sleeping Sickness.
Because in Western Africa the
tsetse carrying sleeping sickness come
much into contact with the human
population, the human problem re¬
ceives more emphasis than the prob¬
lem of cattle trypanosomiasis.
Mass diagnosis
The French, Belgian and British
Governments of the West Afri¬
can territories maintain large
sleeping sickness services, which,
increasingly during the last few
years, have succeeded in reducing the
incidence of the disease to very low
. levels.
Something of the scale of their
operations may be judged by noting
that in French West Africa some
four-and-a-half million people are
examined annually. In Nigeria, of
four million people examined between
1931 and 1943, 11 % were infected.
This "mass diagnosis" and treat¬
ment of infected cases resulted in a
marked decline in the infection rate
which in 1950 was only 0.37% in over
800,000 people examined.
The East and Central African areas
infested with Rhodesian Sleeping
Sickness present a different kind of
problem.
Partly because the disease is more
acute and so more dangerous, partly
because most of the area involved is
not, in any case, suited to dense
settlement, far fewer people are in
danger of infection.
The practice, therefore, is either to
remove people entirely out of the
tsetse-fly belts, or, where this is im¬
practicable, to gather them into
"sleeping sickness settlements" in
which, by combined efforts in agri¬
culture they can create islands of
land in which, because the trees have
been cut down, the tsetse cannot live.
Vast empty spaces
Bad though the effects of sleeping
sickness may be, it is possible
that if we could fully understand
the whole situation created by the
presence of tsetse flies, we might
well conclude that cattle trypanoso¬
miasis is an even greater hindrance
to African welfare and development.
Undernourishment and deficiency
diseases are now recognized to pro¬
vide perhaps the greatest barriers to
African progress and these might
well be overcome if the vast areas
now denied to cattle by the tsetse
could be reclaimed.
Up to about 1945 there were only
two basic methods of eliminating
tsetse flies, although there were a
variety of ways in which they could
be applied. These were either to kill
off the wild game animals which pro¬
vide the tsetse fly with its food or to
cut down the forests and woodlands
which provide its home.
In recent years, however, first DDT
and later other insecticides have
added a very valuable weapon against
the tsetse fly, but the battlefield is
vast and progress is slow.
A great deal of research into the
problem has been and is being done,
largely at the expense of the metro¬
politan governments administering
tropical Africa and there are only
one or two insects such as the mal¬
aria carrying mosquitoes, about which
more is known than about the tsetse.
Why, with so much knowledge, can
we not go faster?
The reasons these methods are not,
and cannot be, applied rapidly are
two. First, the vast size of the areas
involved, areas sometimes of 100,000
square miles or more, prevents them
being tackled as single units.
The second reason is that unless an
area so reclaimed can be occupied by-
forms of land utilization which per¬
manently make them unfit for the
tsetse flies to live in, these insects will
invade once more from other areas.
Research is directed towards the
prevention of disease in man and
stock and the reduction of cost of
reclamation of land from the tsetse
fly.
But the end lies with the African
himselfby using intelligently and
vigorously the new knowledge that is
being given to him, to occupy pro¬
ductively Africa's vast empty spaces.
LIVINGSTONE GAVE HIM
THE MISSING CLUE
ON one of his journeys into Cen¬
tral Africa, David Livingstone ar¬
rived one day in 1857 at the
confluence of the river Tamunak'le.
There he came up against a barrier he
could not cross. "We were informed,"
he wrote, '"that the fly called tsetse
abounded on its banks. This would
have brought our wa¬
gons to a standstill in
the wilderness, and we
were reluctantly com¬
pelled to retrace our
steps." Like others
before him, Living¬
stone was stopped by
the tiny yellow-barred
blood - sucking insect
which is today con¬
sidered one of the
greatest scourges of
man and animals in
tropical Africa. "Its
peculiar buzz once
heard," he said, "can
never be forgotten by
the traveller... When
cattle are bitten, they SIR DAVID
become ill in a few
days, then gradually
weaken, and it is perhaps months later
before they die."
The story of the discovery of the
cause of sleeping sickness begins with
this description by Livingstone of the
tsetse fly. In 1895 a fatal cattle dis¬
ease called nagana was raging in
North Zululand. An Australian-born
British Army doctor, Major David
Bruce, who had shown which organism
caused Malta fever, was called in.
Setting up a laboratory in a wattle and
daub hut, he examined blood samples
from sick animals and spied a "rapidly
moving object... lashing about among
the red corpuscles." This he soon iden¬
tified as a trypanosome, a parasite
known to cause disease in animals. He
assumed it was the cause of nagana.
But how did the trypanosome get into
the cattle's blood? He then recalled the
books by Livingstone and other tra¬
vellers. Might there be a link? He sent
down two oxen into the tsetse fly-infest¬
ed plains nearby. They caught nagana
and their blood swarmed with trypa-
nosomes. After endless experiments
Bruce conclusively proved that the
tsetse fly disease and nagana were the
same. So far though no one suspected
that human sleeping sickness and na¬
gana might be linked through the
tsetse. When a sleeping sickness epi¬
demic flared up in
Uganda in 1902 Bruce
joined two other scien¬
tists near Lake Victoria
where 20,000 Africans
were dead or dying.
Soon he found that not
only did the trypano¬
some cause sleeping
sickness but that it was
carried from man to
man by the same insect
that carried nagana
from beast to beast.
By collecting specimens
of tsetse flies from all
over the territory
(where they were called
kiou) Bruce marked
BRUCE out a tsetse location
map. It agreed exactly
with the distribution of
sleeping sickness in the same region.
Still unsatisfied, he. put tsetses in
muslin cages, fed them on sleeping
sickness patients and then let them feed
on healthy monkeys. The monkeys
caught the disease. He took tsetses
from sleeping sickness areas and fed
them on healthy animals. Again the
animals developed the disease symptoms.
Although there are many varieties of
tsetse fly and trypanosomes, Bruce had
discovered the cause of sleeping sickness
and the way it spread. For his work
he was later knighted. He did not
find a cure but he suggested ways of
preventing infection, recommending the
killing of wild game which act as
"reservoir hosts". And it was he who
persuaded a Uganda chief to move his
people 20 miles back from a lake shore
in the tsetse infested country in 1902
thus saving their lives. Much was still
to be done and is still to be done, but
Bruce had opened the way for effective
attacks on the scourge of the tsetse.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
THE TERROR OF PLAGUE
IN THE MIDDLE ACES
«¿flu *t'.
fen
Dr. Georges
B a r r a u d
***.** -*<*
ARMIES OF THE
PAST were often de¬
cisively defeated by
plague. Here, King
Louis IX of France
(St. Louis) is shown
during his ill-fated
campaign In Egypt
(I 249-50) helping to
bury more than
1, 000 French sol¬
diers struck down by
a plague epidemic.
(In this engraving,
French soldiers are
anachronistically de¬
picted in 17th cen¬
tury garb). St. Louis
himself died from the
plague after arriving
in Carthage In 1270.
Bibliothèque Nationale,
Paris.
For four centuries the West lived in terror of great
plague epidemics. The first and certainly the most
devastating struck Europe in the 14th century. It
took the form of a pneumonic plague, attacking the lungs
and causing hemorrhages under the skin which made its
victims turn black. From this hallucinating sight came
the name "Black Death".
In less than three years from 1348 to 1350, the "Black
Death" killed 25 million people in Europe and some
75 million throughout the world estimated at half the
population of the globe at that time. From then on the
plague was an ever-present menace in Europe although
its ravages progressively decreased, except for serious '
outbreaks in Milan in 1628, in Lyons in 1638, the "Great
Plague" of London in 1665 and that of Marseilles in 1720.
In Italy, epidemics had occurred as early as 980 A.D. in
the Este States and in particular at Modena in 1006 and
1065; they reappeared only in 1311, when not merely the
whole Italian peninsula but France, Spain and Germany
were seriously affected.
At that time, all diseases were ascribed mainly to astro¬
logical causea to the influence of constellations regarded
as benign or hostile and unfavourable. Some people,
however, also blamed malignant vapours which rose from
stagnant water after heavy rain followed by a heat wave.
The pestilential miasmas came, it was said, from the
bowels of the earth ; and the proliferation of insects as
well as rats was regarded not without reason as an evil
omen foreshadowing plague. Thus in 1120 we find the
Bishop of Lyons actually going so far as to excommunicate
all the insects in his Diocese ! In like fashion, we also
find the authorities of Autun, Mâcon, Lyons and
Troyes subsequently issuing edicts condemning (Cont'd on
rats, caterpillars, slugs, and even weevils, next page)
Finally, if we are to believe the account of
i"Ä
It .~¿ ^Ä^OI
n^'M
MmWimW ^Mhfe^M^^I
aKIl m
HHIr¿<ÉSmmm MÊL Ummmmi
Institut Pasteur, Paris.
"GARB FOR DOCTORS and other persons who visit plague victims.
The mask and eye-pieces are of glass and the long nose is filled with
perfumes" reads the 17th century description of costume (left) designed
by the personal physician to Louis XIII of France. Masks and robes worn
by modern doctors to protect themselves from Infection still retain
something of the nightmarish aspect of their ancient counterparts.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
PLAGUE
(Cont'd; 'Heralded by comets, shooting stars and floods'
the historian, de Thou, an actual "'trial" of rats opened
at Beaune, in 1530. The rodents were formally charged
and were even defended by a lawyer. Needless to say,
the accused never appeared in court.
During the second half of the 13th century, the first
treatises on plague and how to deal with it appeared.
Pierre de Dumouzy, a doctor at Rheims, who wrote the
first of these, spoke, even at this early date, of germ-
carriers "'who can transmit infectious germs, even though
they themselves may not be ill... Such are those who have
eaten garlic and no longer smell the odour with which
they infect others."
Dumouzy advised against physical exercise, baths and
massage in times of plague, and advocated light nourish¬
ment, prepared' dry with vinegar. He completely banned
the eating of fruit. He recommended drinking light, clear
wine, thinned with water that had flowed over pebbles,
been boiled or even been distilled in a silver or glass still.
Aromatic disinfectants were essential ; incense, aloes and
myrrh were to be burnt in the rooms ; and doctors and
priests approaching the plague-stricken had to be careful
to carry camphor and a ball of amber in their hands.
Moderation in all things was to be the rule, and chastity
a safeguard against contagion. Above all, the patient
must keep up his spirits and follow a reconstituting re¬
gime, living a joyful and care-free existence. This medical
advice, which on the whole is not so out of date as mignt
seem, was far superior to the prescriptions ordering bleed¬
ings and purges or the taking of theriac or treacle those
classic but highly complex remedies of yore.
It was only two centuries afterwards that anti-plague
pharmaceutical preparations, as picturesque as they were
absurd, made their first appearance. But the fact is that
plague was regarded essentially as a manifestation of
God's wrath, a supernatural scourge designed to punish
man for his sins and crimes. As La Fontaine wrote in the
17th century it was:
"Un mal qui répand la terreur,
"Mal que le Ciel en sa fureur
"Inventa pour punir les crimes de la Terre" (1).
Arrows shot in the air
Thus, in a treatise published in 1629 Jean Fabre of
Toulouse, wrote: "It is sent of God; the angels often
receive God's commandment to distil the same poi¬
son. The demons too; witches and magicians, also may,
by Divine permission and with the aid of the demons
whom they serve, become in truth instruments of the
plague."
Since the plague was considered of Divine origin, it was
natural that it should be heralded by "comets, shooting
stars, earthquakes and floods", and other strange pheno¬
mena which, according to Fabre again, were "the real
precursors and foreshadowers of the plague."
It was equally logical to invoke against it the inter¬
cession of the Saints. Between the 7th and the 12th cen¬
turies, protection was usually sought from St. Sebastian,
the martyr of the arrows, since arrows were regarded as
capable of spreading the plague. From the 13th century
onwards, however, St. Sebastian was gradually replaced
by St. Roch, who had himself contracted the plague in
Italy. Always represented pointing at his bubo, (or pla¬
gue boil) he was the great "healer" of plague in the 15th
and 16th centuries.
The great epidemic of "Black Death", thought to have
originated in Mongolia in 1346, had been prepared and
facilitated by a series of atmospheric disturbances, fa¬
mines and particularly floods, which are believed to have
taken 400,000 lives. In less than a year the great plague
is said to have claimed as many as thirteen million vic¬
tims in Northern China alone. It spread to the West by
way of Baghdad, Syria and Constantinople, where it raged
for several months.
"The disease was incurable," wrote the Emperor Can-
tacuzene. "'Neither mode of living nor bodily strength
was proof against it. Strong and weak were struck down
alike; and death spared those tended at great cost no
more than those who were bereft of help... Saddest of
all was the way the plague sapped its victims of courage.
At the first symptoms, they lost all hope, took to their
beds and shut themselves off, as it were, from the world.
This moral prostration made them rapidly worse and
speeded the hour of their death: No words can be found
to describe this disease. All that can be said is that it
had nothing in common with the ills by which man is
ordinarily afflicted, and it was a punishment sent by God."
By way of Greece the scourge passed to the Mediterran¬
ean islands, in which two-thirds of the population were
struck down. In Italy, even more victims were claimed;
100,000 died in Florence, and as many in Venice ; at Bo¬
logna and Ferrara there were 2,000 deaths each day. The
epidemic swept across the Balearic Islands into Spain,
and across Switzerland into Austria and Germany, where'
it brought death to 1,250,000 people, including some
125,000 Franciscan monks.
Processions of flagellants
In France it made its first appearance in a Carmelite
monastery at Avignon, and within a few months it
carried off 150,000 persons. Having decimated Prov¬
ence, it ravaged Paris, the Eastern provinces, and parti¬
cularly Burgundy, where the following grim couplet was
composed:
"En mil trois cent quarte huit
"De cent ne demeurait que huit." (2)
England's turn came next: In London 100,000 persons
died. Then, Norway, Denmark, Iceland and even Green¬
land were decimated. All in all, it is said that the "Black
Death" of the 14th century carried off between 30 and 40
million people in Europe alone.
As an attempt to overcome this epidemic and appease
the Divine wrath, a wave of frightened mysticism swept
over Christendom. In many countries, processions of
flagellants were to be seen throughout the land, half-
naked, intoning religious hymns, and chastising them¬
selves with whips to which crosses of iron were attached.
Finally the various kings, and even the Pope, forbade
these people to enter their realms, for they engaged in
every sort of pillage.
It was commonly believed that wells and fountains had
been poisoned and popular anger was aroused against the
Jews who were held responsible for these disasters. The
Jews were hounded everywhere and large numbers were
burned alive, especially in the German-speaking countries.
To put an end to these horrible massacres, Pope Clement
VI issued two Bulls declaring the Jews innocent. But
despite this it was only in Poland that the Jews Anally
could find refuge, with King Casimir the Great, who gave
asylum to whole Jewish colonies.
Fig & pistachio poultices
When the great plague epidemic broke out in Avignon
in 1348, the physician-surgeon Guy de Chauliac
began to treat tumors by "ripening" them with
fig and pistachio poultices and then lancing them with
a hot knife.
Large quantities of incense and camomile leaves were
burnt in public squares and in houses, and rooms were li¬
berally washed with rosewater and vinegar. Doctors
began to wear long loose clothing and long gloves, protect¬
ing their nose with a sponge soaked in vinegar containing
clove and cinnamon powder.
But it was especially in Italy that the most effective
public health measures were developed. In 1374, people
and merchandise either infected, or even suspected of
infection, were forbidden to enter Venice. Patients were
isolated in special places outside the towns and
the declaration of plague cases became compul- (Cont'd on
sory. In 1377 the Republic of Ragusa initiated page 20)
the first system of quarantine. All suspected
(1) A malady that spreads terror, a malady which Heaven in its
fury invented to punish the crimes of the Earth.
(2) In thirteen hundred forty eight, of one hundred remained but
eight.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
ALEXANDRE YERSIN
CC I ^ he day you i see rats fall dying
I from the roofs, leave your
homes !" advised the Bhaga-
vata Purana, a sacred Hindu poetical
work written in Sanscrit centuries ago.
It was good advice and was still being
followed in the 19th century according
to a British observer who watched the
people of Marwar abandon their homes
during the Pali plague of 1836-38.
People in the Chinese province of
Yunnan, scene of many outbreaks, were
well aware that death among rats was
a warning of worse things to come.
During an epidemic at Chaochow in
1792, a poet, Shih Tao-nan wrote a few
days before he himself died from the
plague :
"Few days following the death of rats,
Men pass away like falling walls." .
It is thus easy to understand why the
idea arose that plague was not a disease
of rodents in general, but of rats in
particular and that slogans like "'No
rats no plague" were widely accepted.
Just the same, the inhabitants of
Central Asia, birthplace of great plague
epidemics of the past, had, known for
generations that a fatal, infectious
disease periodically attacked the Sibe¬
rian marmots and that it was apt to
spread to man. They had, in fact, taken
surprisingly adequate measures to pro¬
tect themselves against this danger.
The infection carried by the marmots
and among the human beings who had
come in contact with them seems to
have first been identified with plague in
1895 by two scientists, Bjeliavski and
Rjeshetnikoff.
Solved marmot mystery
But the evidence collected by these
two observers was not supported
by laboratory examination, and it
was only ten years later that bacterio¬
logical proof of the existence of human
plague in Tansbaikalia was obtained. In
other parts of the world, wild rodents,
quite apart from rats, were first sus¬
pected and later proved to suffer from
plague and to be able to transmit it.
It is generally recognized that the
plague bacillus was first discovered by a
French Army doctor, Alexandre Yersin,
although some authorities credit a Japa¬
nese scientist, Shibasaburo Kitasato with
FLEAS, RATS
AND MEN-
LINKS IN A
DEADLY CHAIN
this achievement. Yersin who was one
of Pasteur's pupils, had an adventurous
career. A laboratory research worker
by training, he set out for the Far East,
became an explorer in Indo-China and
found himself in Hong-Kong during the
bubonic plague epidemic of 1894. It
was here that he made his great dis¬
covery which he recounted as follows :
"'Before being buried in the cemetery
the bodies were left for an hour or so
in a kind of cellar. They were already
in coffins and covered with quick-lime.
Institut Pasteur, Paris.
Plague bacilli seen through a microscope.
One of the coffins was opened and I
removed some of the lime. The bubo
(plague boil) was unmistakable ; in less
than a minute I had removed it and I
went up to my laboratory. I quickly
prepared a specimen and placed it
under the microscope. At the first
glance I made out an absolute swarm of
microbes all alike. They were like
very tiny rods, thick, with rounded ends
and not very well coloured..."
After having identified this bacillus in
both rats and men, Yersin was able to
affirm : "'The plague is a contagious and
inoculable disease. It is probable that
rats form the main reservoir."
The early plague investigators in
Hong Kong, however, were obsessed
with the idea that bubonic plague was
LT. COLONEL P. L. SIMOND
primarily a gastro-intestinal infection,
and it was not until 1901 that rat des¬
truction was started there, even though
this had been recommended by Yersin
as early as 1897.
How this question was cleared up by
two scientists, M. Ogata, and P.L Si-
mond working independently is told in a
monograph on plague by Dr. R. Pollit¬
zer, published by WHO.
Working in Formosa. Ogata assumed
that the plague was an insect-borne
infection and suspected rat fleas in par¬
ticular. "'One should pay attention to
insects like fleas", he wrote, "'for as the
rat becomes cold after death, they leave
their host and may transmit the plague
virus direct to man". After inoculating
mice with a mixture obtained by grind¬
ing up fleas collected from plague rats,
he obtained positive results and was
able to prove that the fleas had actually
absorbed plague virus.
Discoveries ridiculed
SIMOND, a French surgeon working in
India, was quite unaware of
Ogata's findings when he began his
own investigations in 1897. He found
that when healthy rats were placed near
infected ones (without there being any
direct contact) the healthy ones contract¬
ed plague. Under exactly the same
conditions no infection was transmitted
as long as both animals had been freed
from fleas beforehand. "On that day,
June 2, 1898", wrote Simond later, "I
experienced an indescribable emotion at
the thought that I had just solved a
mystery that had haunted mankind since
plague first appeared in the world."
Though the findings of Ogata and
Simond were at first ignored or even
ridiculed, their scientific accuracy was
soon established. Further investigations
carried out in all areas where plague
became rampant at the end of the 19th
and in the early 20th centuries showed
that the plague bacillus is constantly
present among the rodents, being spread
from animal to animal not directly but
through their blood-sucking fleas.
They also showed that the danger of
the disease spreading to men arises as a
rule only at times when the infection
among the rodents becomes so wide¬
spread that many animals die and thus
their fleas are driven by hunger to
attack other than their usual hosts, par¬
ticularly man.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
PLAGUE (Continuée/)
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
1 BLACK DEATH '
LURKS
UNDERGROUND
A small brown, furry animal, too common in
India to attract much notice has suddenly
become the central figure in a research project
of international significance. The Tatera in¬
dica, as this wild rodent is known to zoologists,
has become important because of the role it
appears to play in spreading and perpetuating
a dread diseasebubonic plague, the "Black
Death", Evidence linking this seemingly
harmless rodent with plague has been collected
by scientists in Uttar Pradesh, India, where
in 1947, more than 50,000 people died of
plague. Latest research suggests that the
Tatera indica, harbours the disease between
outbreaks in its underground burrows.
Some of these wild rats have a higher
resistance to plague and survive outbreaks
which kill off most others, including house
rats. They then carry the plague bacilli in
their blood and spread infection through
their fleas. Laboratory tests, on 5,000 wild
rats and several hundred guinea pigs showed
researchers that Tatera indica was, in fact,
the plague reservoir in Uttar Pradesh. Photos
tell how research "convicted" this wild rat as
a dangerous harbourer of plague. ( 1-2) When
grass is burned away rodents' burrows and
"footpaths" are revealed. (3-4) As burrows
are dug out a frightened rat tries to escape.
(5) Before it can get away a pair of rat
forceps have it firmly by the ear and tail.
(6) Villagers lend a hand in baiting rat traps.
(7) Rat is numbered and released exactly where
it was caught. Later catches of marked rats
show extent of their movement in village. (8)
Guinea pig is injected with organic matter
from rats suspected as plague carriers. (9) If
rodents were infected a plague abscess appears
at the ¡nnoculated spot on guinea pig's back.
WHO Pierre Pittet.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
PLAGUE
(Cont'd from
page 16)
FORTY DAYS IN
THE LAZARET
cases were isolated for thirty, and later forty days in
sunny and well-aired "lazarets".
Marseilles followed this example in 1383 and Venice
drew up a whole series of model health regulations. By
1438 Venice had appointed health directors who controlled
the cleanliness of the water supply. In 1485 the city de¬
signated a special magistrate for public health who was
endowed with wide powers and duties.
In 1418, during the Hundred Years' War, the plague re¬
appeared in Paris and "'in less than five weeks killed off
more than 50,000 persons". At the end of the 15th cen¬
tury the discovery of the New World extended European
medical knowledge. Doctors now faced new diseases, such
as syphilis and yellow fever which caused terrible havoc
among the Spaniards, along with plague and typhus.
During the siege of Milan, in 1522, the French army
commanded by Admiral Bonnivet was attacked by a for¬
midable epidemic of plague which is said to have claimed
between 40,000 and 50,000 victims.
In Rome, in 1527, "there was no street that was not
heaped with plague-victims, dead or dying, and people
imploring Death to put an end to their sufferings." To¬
wards the, end of July 1528, the French army encamped
before Naples, was decimated by an epidemic (probably
typhus) which in less than a month reduced it as a
fighting force from 25,000 to less than 100. This was the
end of the proud army of Francis I which, as the King's
historiographer, Martin du Bellay, wrote, "had dominated
Italy, the Romagna and the Kingdom of Naples".
In the following century, the plague broke out once
more, this time among the armies of the Thirty Years'
War, causing 18,000 deaths -at Nuremberg in 1634. At
Stuttgart, typhus and the plague held sway for five years,
from 1634 to 1639 ; while at Augsburg, a town of 10,000
inhabitants, 30,000 died between 1625 and 1628.
The whole of Germany was scourged alternately by
typhus and the plague, spread by rats and fostered by
famine, for "the crops in the fields had been entirely
eaten up by mice." These disasters drove the people to
outright acts of cannibalism ; and attempts to conjure
them away led to a wave of religious fervour. Vows were
made and processions and pilgrimages took place espe¬
cially to Oberammergau, where in 1634 the plague carried
off 84 out of 400 inhabitants. This period saw the be¬
ginning of the "Passion Plays" which are now performed
every ten years in this little village of the Bavarian Alps.
A few years later, in 1657, a Jesuit priest named Atha-
nasius Kirche, announced . that the epidemic of plague
Plague "seasons" in different parts of the world
circles indicate the number of months ranging
then raging in Rome was caused by worms so small and
elusive that they could not be perceived by the senses.
When viewed under the microscope, he said, they resembl¬
ed objects no larger than atoms. He noted that he had
found these small worms in the blood of plague-victims
and in the pus of buboes, and that they multiplied in
the system exceedingly rapidly.
This forerunner of microbiology believed that the
worms were carried by the air, clothing and other objects
with which the sick had been in contact, and even in fact
by animals. These prophetic views which preceded Pas¬
teur's theories by two centuries naturally strengthened
the belief that plague was contagious.
In the early middle
ages Christians called
on St. Sebastian to
protect them from
the plague, which
they regarded as a
form of divine pun¬
ishment. From the
1 3th century on¬
wards they appealed
to St. Roch who had
himself contracted
the plague in Italy.
These statuettes from
a Paris church depict
St. Roch snowing his
plague boll to a doc¬
tor garbed In a hood
and lobe to protect
him ygainst infection.
Institut Pasteur, Paris.
Carnavalesque costume
and a disinfecting beak
Treatment of the disease was mainly governed at the
time by an aphorism which had been jokingly baptiz¬
ed "the electuary of the three adverbs" cito, longe,
tarde that is, "early to leave, far away to finish, late to
return." The doctors who braved contagion had adopted
a special costume, designed in Paris in 1619, comprising a
long smockfrock of oiled and waxed cloth together with
oiled and waxed taffeta gloves. Louis XIII's doctor im¬
proved upon the costume to an almost carnivalesque
degree with a leather shirt and breeches of leather, high
riding-boots, a full-length coat and gauntlets. The head
was completely encased in a leather headpiece with glass
protectors for the eyes, while the nose was protected by
a sort of large beak filled with disinfectants to inhale.
In France, the first special hospital for the plague-
stricken was instituted in 1474 at Lyons. Paris, where
68,000 victims had died at the Hôtel-Dieu hospital during
the single epidemic of 1562, established a plague-hospital
only at the beginning of the 17th century.
When a terrible epidemic broke out in Lyons in 1628, a
health bureau went into operation and was remarkably
successful in checking the scourge. From the outset, one
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
are shown on this map. Shaded sections within the
from one to twelve when cases of plague occur.
hospital equipped with only 200 beds for contagious cases,
accommodated 4,000 patients by crowding four or five
persons into a single bed.
The declaration of all suspect cases was made compul¬
sory, "health passports" called bullettes were issued, and
any failure to observe the draconian regulations set up
was punished by death. Organized "disinfection teams"
worked methodically, fumigating houses and buildings
with sulphur, and subjecting all persons released from
quarantine to drastic antiseptic cleansing. As a result,
the epidemic was throttled in less than six months.
A century later the plague reappeared in Marseilles
where unlike Lyons, no health bureau existed. The epi¬
demic devastated the city, raging for years at a cost of
40,000 lives. Many inhabitants fled to Lyons and these
plague-spreaders gave the Lyons health bureau another
opportunity to prove its worth. Its director, named Goif-
fon, mobilized his health forces, applied all the prophy¬
lactic measures that a century of .tests and experiments
had perfected and saved his city from disaster.
From then on the advantages of disinfection and
"deratting" needed no more proving. Although, at the
end of the 18th century, the plague levied a heavy tribute
on the French Army in Egypt and decimated Napoleon's
troops at Jaffa, its ravages were more or less confined at
that time to Eastern Europe and Asia Minor ; and hence¬
forth it did not range beyond Asia and Africa. It was
only at the end of the first World War that a slight
epidemic struck in the suburbs of Paris but was imme¬
diately checked. Of the 137 cases observed only 4 % or
so died. Three centuries earlier the plague would have
carried off millions of people.
Thus, sanitary measures applied swiftly and methodic¬
ally to patients as well as to rats and fleas, have succeeded
in ridding Europe at least from this terrible scourge which
as La Fontaine put it in Louis XIV's time "was able to
enrich Acheron in a day."
The above article is taken from Clio en Epidaure by Dr. G.
Barraud, a book devoted to medicine and humanism in ancient
times, by permission of the publishers, Editions Sipuco, Paris.
'PLAGUE SPOTS'
AROUND THE WORLD
DURING the Great Plague of London in
1665 a chronicler of the time wrote
with grim humour : "Mr. Garancières
saith the Plague is the easiest disease in the
world to cure, and soe said Mr. Stoakes, the
Apothecary... but hee is dead since."
A modern medical writer was recently able
to state, "We have vanquished plague as an
epidemic scourge." But the same writer went
on to warn: "The reservoir of the disease
remains because it is not in man himself,
and to expect its eradication is Utopian."
This is exactly what Pasteur foresaw in 1881
when he said: "Plague is a virulent disease
endemic to certain countries. In all these
places its virus must exist and is ready to
become active immediately suitable condi¬
tions of climate, poverty or famine appear."
In the past half century plague has killed
more than twelve and a half million people
(according to Dr. R. Pollitzer, author of a
World Health Organization monograph on the
disease). Half these victims died between
1898 and 1908, and a further quarter in the
next ten years. After a temporary increase
during the war years (1939-1946) the death
rate has again dropped.
Until 1912 it was believed that plague was
essentially a disease transmitted to man by
the domestic rat (through fleas). Today we
know that there are also enormous reservoirs
of the disease among some 200 species of
wild rodents. These exist in areas of Central
and Western Asia, a vast territory of South
Africa and some parts of Latin America.
One of the world's great areas of wild
rodent plague is in a huge territory
covering some 15 states in the western
part of the United States. Here ground squir¬
rels and prairie dogs form the main reservoirs
of infection. But there have been practically
no cases of human plague in the region since
1924 for these wild rodents live far from
human dwellings and their fleas fortunately
do not bite men.
The danger however lies in the wild
rodents or their fleas coming in contact with
the common house rat which would set off
a chain reaction of infection threatening
human beings. U.S. health authorities are
aware of this danger and along with whole¬
sale wild rodent extermination have created
safety zones with rodent-free belts around
human settlements.
Scientists have discovered in recent years
that seasons, climate and temperature also
play an important role in accelerating or
reducing the spread of infection. The death
rate of flea-infected rats has been found to
be high when temperature and air humidity
are moderately high. When such a favourable
climatic period ends, instances of rat plague
become few and far between and human
plague ceases until suitable climatic conditions
once more, usher in a new plague season.
Map shows world's plague areas between
1900-1952. Shading in circles indicates length
of plague season sometimes all year round.
Map copyright 1952, The American Geographical Society The
Geographical Review, Vol. 42. N- 4, 19 52.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
'THE FEVER OF THE THREE
}
*
h m
^^*jT tm ft ""**.
. ,^_
1
mam.
ANOPHELES MOSQUITO
WHO
Malaria was given its name directly from the Italian
"mala" and "aria" literally "bad air". It is a
stubborn disease: slow to kill, quick to incapacitate
and hard to cure.
It exists widely in populated areas where average tem¬
peratures reach 60° F. Since 1920, malaria has been found
as far north as Archangel, and as far south as Cordoba in
the Argentine. It occurs at mountain altitudes as high as
8,000 feet, and around the Dead Sea, some 1,300 feet below
sea level.
Of the 300,000,000 estimated malaria sufferers in the
world, before present control methods were used, 3 million
died each year. Malaria raises mortality, reduces ferti¬
lity, increases stillbirths. Malaria kills only 1% of those
who contract it, but reduces the productive capacity of the
other 99 %, and causes heavy financial and economic loss.
Malaria is spread by certain types of mosquito. The
mosquito absorbs the parasite when it bites and draws
blood from a malarial subject. After developing inside
the stomach of the mosquito, the
parasite is re-injected by the
insect into the blood stream of
another human being.
The world's oldest recorded
disease, malaria is referred to in
ancient Chinese, Chaldean and
Hindu texts. Hippocrates men¬
tions it, and Chinese mythology
tells of the fever "of the three
demons: one armed with a ham¬
mer, the second with a pail of
water, the third with a stove"
forceful symbols of the bouts of
headache, chills and fever that
characterize the disease.
The Romans offered prayers
and sacrifices to "Dea Fibris"
The Goddess of Fevers in the
hope of escaping infection. They
associated swampy areas and
even mosquitoes with the disease
and built drainage canals as an
early form of malariology. By
100 A.D., Columella in "De Re
Rustica", advised against build-
UNICEF
MOSQUITO PATROL visits this Costa Rican village
twice each year to spray houses and farm buildings with
DDT insecticide. Malaria control campaigns in most
parts of the world are being aided by the World Health
Organization and the U.N. Children's Fund (UNICEF).
ing near marshes "that breed animals armed with
mischievous stings whereby diseases are often contracted."
Fifteen centuries later, in 1632, Spanish explorers and
colonists brought back from Peru the bark of the "quina¬
quina" tree. The quinine it provided was called "cinch¬
ona" in honour of the Spanish Countess of Chinchón
celebrated as the first known case of malaria cure. For
centuries after, the value of the medicine was obscured
because of the confusion between the quina-quina bark
and that of similar trees, and by quacks hawking bogus
"cinchona" throughout Europe.
One of the earliest malaria control projects based on
the discoveries of Sir Ronald Ross, of Great Britain, was
the clearing of the disease from Staten Island in New
York harbour, during 1901.
Throughout the first World War and since, the repres¬
sion of malaria was widely practised by eradication of the
mosquito in the larva stage usually by drainage works
and with oil sprayed on ponds and breeding places.
Spray killing of the adult mos¬
quitoes rather than of the lar¬
vae began in South Africa In
1935, with oil extracts of pyre-
thum. This same prophylaxis
was used during World War II.
In 1940, the potentialities of
DDT as a fly and insect killer
were realized by a Swiss chemist,
Dr. Paul Müller. Since then,
DDT, together with other insecti¬
cides such as dieldrin, has
become the supreme anti-malaria
weapon of man it does not kill
mosquitoes more efficiently than
pyrethum, but it does continue
to kill them months after it has
been applied to a given surface
on which they alight. Therefore,
repeated sprayings of the in¬
teriors of homes and buildings,
where mosquitoes prey on hu¬
mans, result in killing the insect
vector before he can re-infect
another person, thus interrupting
the transmission cycle.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
MEETING THE CHALLENGE. This Is
how the challenge of malaria is being met at
the Anti-Malaria Experimental Centre near
Yaounde, French Cameroons, set up by the
French Government with the aid of WHO
and the U.N. Children's Fund. (Photos I
and 2) Doctor's hands feel a child's spleen.
Repeated attacks of malaria cause an enlarge¬
ment of the spleen and such examina¬
tions give an Idea of the amount of malaria in
a given area. (3) Insect collector at work In
local swamp. (4) An African laboratory
worker examines blood slides from villages.
WHO - Pierre Pittet
SIR PATRICK MANSON
he detective
work that
exposed the
mosquito as the
culprit respon¬
sible for malaria
is one of the
great chapters in
the history of
science. Scien¬
tists of many nations have participated
in the search. A possible connexion
between mosquitoes and malaria was
actually made by the ancient Hindu,
Susruta. In 1880, Charles Laveran, a
French army surgeon stationed in Al¬
geria, discovered the malaria parasite in
human blood (he won the Nobel Prize
in 1907). A year earlier, Sir Patrick
Manson, the great Scottish microbiolo¬
gist then working as a young doctor in
China, had discovered the role of mos¬
quitoes in the transmission of another
ON THE MOSQUITO'S TRAIL
T
tropical disease called filariasis which
led him to propound the theory that
mosquitoes transmit malaria. It is said
that Manson proved it was the Ano¬
pheles mosquito, by allowing his son to
be bitten by an
infected mosqui¬
to and to come
down with the
disease. The con¬
clusive incrimi¬
nation of the
mosquito, how¬
ever, came as a
result of five
years of pains¬
taking work in
India by Sir Ron¬
ald Ross, one
of the most emi¬
nent and versatile of modern patholo¬
gists, who received the Nobel Prize for
his investigations in 1902. On Aug¬
ust 20, 1897 (later called "Mosquito
SIR RONALD ROSS
Day") he identified the malaria parasite
inside the Anopheles stomach. A year
later Ross had established the entire life
cycle of the parasite. His work opened
the way to malaria control through the
eradication of mosquitoes in the larva
stage. Ross recognized that it was
"Manson's theory, and no other, which
actually solved the problem" of the
mosquito transmission of malaria.
Working separately in Italy, Prof.
Giovanni Battis-
,***&
GIOVANNI GRASSI
ta Grassi bril¬
liantly demon¬
strated the mos¬
quito's role in
1898. The gen¬
eral problem
was advanced in
its various stages
by pathologists,
clinicians and
hygienists from
other countries.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
'We don't count
the deadwe
just bury them'
UNICEF
Malaria as every self-respecting
Dahomey fetichist knows is
simply a stone planted in the
heart by an angry god. All the same,
ramer than risk a contest with the
white magic of DDT supplied by the
U.N. Children's Fund (Unicef), the
black magic priest-professors of the
fetichist school, in the fisherman's
village oí Houedome, on the Porto-
Novo lagoon, marshalled their female
pupilsaged two to fifteento greet
the visiting anti-malaria team with
drums and dances (Photos 2 and 4).
To reach this picturesque island
settlement, built on stilts in the
delta area of the Oueme river, the
health team, together with their
equipment and supplies, were ferried
across in hollowed-out log canoes (1).
The team's itinerary from the
mainland to Houedome and other
island villages in the Aguegues
district, took them through blue
lagoons edged by tall waving reeds
and across emerald-green flood p^ain
pastures. Here local tribes live by
spearing fish and breeding hardy
brown cattle penned inside man-
made enbankments. Such slow-
moving delta waters offer ideal con¬
ditions for mosquitoes and almost
half of Dahomey's 1,500,000 popu¬
lation living along the coastral strip,
is exposed to the constant threat of
malana. In the words of Houedome's
headman, when questioned on the
malaria mortality rates among
children: "We don't count them we
just bury them."
Protection of these people by anti-
mosquito spraying with DDT or
dieldrin, is part of a general drive
against malaria launched by the
French Health authorities in French
West Africa and in Togoland, and
towards which the Unicef has con¬
tributed $ 1,268,000 since April 1952.
The people of Houedome and other
settlements of the Aguegues area, will
be among the 400,000 people due to be
protected against malaria in Da¬
homey, this year.
According to the fetichists, the
explanation will be that fewer stones
have been planted in the hearts of
those that offend the godsHebipsso
the Thunder, Sakpate the Smallpox,
Dan the Rainbow and Ogoun the
Almighty.
But just to make sure they too will
benefit by this reprieve, the prancing
cotton-draped bead-covered trainee
witches o'f Houedome, politely invited
the team of "white magic" practi¬
tioners to spray DDT over the
matting walls of their own academy
of black magic (3).
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
THE LAST REFUGE
OF YELLOW FEVER
by Dr. J. Austin Kerr
Rockefeller Foundation
YELLOW fever will invade Mexico within the next few months
probably, and almost certainly within a year. This prediction has
just come from Dr. Fred L. Soper, director of the Pan American
Sanitary Bureau, regional office of the World Health Organization in
Washington. Official notification has been received from the Govern¬
ment of Guatemala that dead and dying monkeys are now being found
around Lake Izabal and there is evidence of the presence in the region
of the yellow fever virus. Yellow fever is now only 75 or 80 miles from
the Mexican-Guatemalan border and 800 miles from the U.S. border
where the whole southern third of the nation is classified as a' yellow
fever "receptive area".
In December 1954, Dr. Soper had already warned: "Yellow fever is
not a 'dead duck', it has not been conquered, it has not been eliminated
as a permanent threat to the United States. It has recently come back
to nearby countries where it had been unknown for decades. Yellow
fever seems of little international importance or concern until it
suddenly appears in a port city as it did in the summer of 1954 in
Port-of-Spain, Trinidad. Then the picture changes overnight and in¬
terest in the disease as a public health menace is rekindled."
Although yellow fever in cities (carried by Aedes aegypti mosquitoes)
has been practically eradicated from most of South America and parts of
Central America, another type of the same disease known as jungle
yellow fever still exists in tropical jungles attacking monkeys which keep
the virus alive. A wave of this jungle yellow fever has been moving
slowly but steadily up through Panama and Central America since 1948,
reviving old memories of the devastating epidemics that preceded the
building of the Panama Canal. The wave reached the north-west corner
of Honduras in September 1954. The threat now is that a jungle in¬
fected person reaching a port city may spread the disease to Aedes
aegypti mosquitoes, starting a chain reaction of urban yellow fever.
One the five great pestilential
diseases from which mankind
suffers, yellow fever, is transmitt¬
ed to man by certain mosquitoes.
It is a tropical disease, primarily of
the shores of the Atlantic Ocean. At
its greatest extent yellow fever spread
from the Belgian Congo to Spain,
France and England in the Old World,
and from Buenos-Aires, Argentina, to
New York, Boston and even Que¬
bec, in the New World. The
disease did make some excursions
to the Pacific Coast of the American
tropics, but it has never been present '
on the East Coast of Africa.
This disease is the "yellow jack" of
history. It is a disease of cities, trans¬
mitted from man to man by the Aedes
aegypti mosquito. The disease was
first diagnosed in the Americas but it
well may have originated in Africa.
Yellow fever is caused by a virus.
The organism is very much smaller than
an ordinary bacterium or germ, and is
transmitted to man by the mosquito.
No mosquito is ever hatched infec¬
ted. It has to acquire its infection
from some infected person or jungle
animal after it hatches.
In 1918 the Rockefeller Foundation
became much interested in yellow fever
and undertook to eradicate it from the
face of the earth. A careful appraisal
of the situation at that time resulted in
. the conclusion that the disease could be
eradicated from the earth in 10 years
at a cost of $5,000,000. Much work
was done, much very successful work,
and in 1925 it was thought that the era¬
dication of the disease was in sight.
But the next year there was a set-back.
Again, in 1928, the goal seemed to be
in sight but in that year there was a
more severe set-back in the form of an
epidemic of more than 1,000 cases in
the city of Rio de Janeiro. In the next
few years the development of in-
CARLOS JUAN FINLAY
The first scientifically based
suspicion that mosquitoes might
be guilty of spreading disease
came In 1881 from Dr. Carlos
Finlay of Cuba. He propounded
the theory that the tiger
mosquito (Aedes aegypti) was
responsible for transmitting
yellow fever. -His theory was
confirmed in 1901 by Walter
Reed of the U.S. Army, in Cuba.
The Wellcome Historical Medical
Museum, London.
creasingly effective measures for the
control of Aedes aegypti so greatly
reduced the amount of yellow fever that
it was possible in 1932 to recognize
that yellow fever was occurring in the
complete absence of this particular
mosquito.
The name given to this form of the
disease was jungle yellow fever. It has
since been recognized to be widespread
in South America and in Africa, where
it exists permanently in the tropical rain
forests of the Amazon Valley and of
the Congo River Basin. From time to
time epidemics of the disease burst out
of these huge central reservoirs.
Jungle Yellow Fever is transmitted to
man by the bite of a jungle mosquito.
The species of mosquitoes present in the
American and African tropical forests
are very different in name but not
really different in their habits. Both
kinds live in the leafy canopy, or top
layer of the forest rather than down at
the ground level where man spends
most of his time.
The distribution of the Aedes aegypti
mosquito nowadays is very much more
restricted than it used to be because of
the presence in all large cities of a
supply of piped water, which we take
for granted. The mosquito is gone
from the temperate regions but it does
remain in the tropical and subtropical
regions.
From many of the seaports of tropical
America, the mosquito has been eradi¬
cated ; in most of the others it is rather
scarce. However, it still remains wide¬
spread in the southern U.S.A.
The confirmation by Walter Reed,
and his co-workers, of Carlos Finlay's
theory that yellow fever was transmitted
by the Aedes aegypti mosquito made it
possible to eradicate yellow fever from
Cuba in 1901 and from the Panama
Canal Zone a few years later. With
the perfection thirty years later of the
techniques for eradicating Aedes aegypti
from cities, towns, villages and rural
houses" in the Americas, it became
possible to protect the residents of those
non-jungle areas against the disease.
Where there were no mosquitoes there
could be no yellow fever.
Quite a different situation exists
regarding jungle yellow fever, for it is
manifestly impossible to control the
jungle mosquitoes which transmit the
disease to man and it always will be.
Reliance has to be placed on individual
protection by vaccinating against
yellow fever the persons who have to
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
YELLOW FEVER
	 (Cont'd) 	
enter the forest and run the risk of
contracting the disease.
One of the great mysteries of modern
medicine is the fact that yellow fever
is not present, and never has been
present, in India or in any other place
in the Orient.
As a matter of fact it has never been
recognized on the coast of East Africa,
so that it would appear that the barrier
to the eastward spread of the disease
lies somewhere inland from that coast.
The yellow fever mosquito (Aedes
aegypti) is widespread in the tropical
portions of the Orient and among the
islands of the Pacific. Furthermore,
this whole area is rich in species of
mosquitoes which are first cousins of
Aedes aegypti.
More important still, some of these
species have been shown in the labora¬
tory to be capable of transmitting the
disease experimentally from monkey to
monkey.
Howler monkeys fell
dead from the trees
IN the Americas there have been two
episodes in recent years which have
been of great interest and impor¬
tance. The first of these was the epi¬
demic of yellow fever which began in
Panama in 1948. In succeeding years
it spread northwards through Costa
Rica, Nicaragua and Honduras causing
cases and deaths each year through
1954, when it burned itself out.
This epidemic was accompanied by
a fantastic mortality of howler and
spider monkeys in the forests of Central
America. In many places the stench
of dead monkeys in the forests was
overpowering.
With the human population well
vaccinated and with Aedes aegypti well
under control in the port cities and other
centres of population, this epidemic was
of relatively little economic importance.
Not since 1925 had yellow fever
previously been diagnosed in Central
America. In that year some cases
occurred in Mexico ; and they are
considered to have been urban cases
transmitted by Aedes aegypti.
In 1920 there is a well authenticated
history of heavy mortality of howler
monkeys in the forests of Honduras.
And in 1882 there is also a very clear
story of an epidemic of yellow fever
in man in the forests of the Guate¬
malan Peten. At the time of the epi¬
demic howler monkeys were observed
to fall dead out of trees by people still
living today.
The second epidemic in recent years
occurred in 1954 in Trinidad, British
West Indies, where yellow fever had not
been diagnosed for 40 years.
By great good fortune, a virus
research laboratory which had been set
up in Port-of-Spain isolated a virus from
a forest labourer who was sick with an
insignificant fever. The virus was
identified as that of yellow fever.
In the succeeding few months, numer¬
ous other strains of yellow fever virus
were isolated in Trinidad from men,
monkeys and mosquitoes. It is prob¬
able that the warning given by the first
virus isolation prevented an epidemic in
the island's aegypti-infested areas.
It is good to know that a disease
which was once one of the great pesti¬
lences of mankind has now been brought
under effective control. In cities the
disease is best controlled by eradicating
the mosquito which transmits it.
Elsewhere, vaccine is available for
everybody who has occasion to enter the
MAJOR WALTER REED
His work was among the most
important in history of medical
research. In I 900 he led group
of U.S. Army doctors to Cuba
to study yellow fever. At end
of series of heroic experiments,
with soldiers and doctors volun¬
teering to be injected with the
fever germs, he proved that
the tiger mosquito caused
yellow fever, and made future
control of the disease possible.
The Wellcome Historical Museum,
London.
jungle and there come into contact with
the disease.
Great though the accomplishments
have been, there is still much to be done.
There should be no complacency in face
of the fact that yellow fever virus is
solidly entrenched, and always will be,
in two enormous tropical areas the
rain forests of the Amazon and Congo
River Basins.
The eradication of Aedes aegypti
from the entire New World is a practical
goal toward which the World Health
Organization is working hard. Eradi¬
cation seems feasible also in certain
areas in Africa and Asia, but precise
information on certain habits of the
mosquito is necessary before a final
decision can be made in regard to
continent-wide eradication in the Eas¬
tern Hemisphere.
OLYMPIC RACES
FOR LICE
THE louse is an adventurous
vagabond by nature" that is
the considered opinion of Dr.
Maurice Mathis of the Pasteur
Institute of Tunis, where Charles
Nicolle discovered the transmission of
typhus fever by the body louse in
1909.
Dr. Mathis, author of a book on
the Life of the Louse,- has written
extensively about the habits of this
highly repulsive parasite and this is
what he has to say about the louse
as a Marco Polo of the insect world :
"'Despite its size and its extremely
inadequate means of locomotion, the
louse likes to travel. A scientist, G.
Nuttall, has investigated the prowess
of the louse as a traveller by organiz¬
ing 'louse races'.
'"Selected lice ran over horizontal
and vertical courses and paths at a
45 degree angle. The race tracks
themselves were composed, in turn, of
black stain, smooth cloth, rough cloth,
or one or two hairs. In other words,
Nuttall organized a rather strange
form of Olympic Games.
"Here are the records of a few
champions :
Body Louse Events
1. 12 inch flat race: 49 sec.
2. Same distance on black satin at
45 degree angle : 2 min. 53 sec.
3. Same distance on rough cloth at
45 degree angle: 2 min. 51 sec.
Head Louse Events
Vertical climb on a hair 8 inches
long : 1' 25", a record set by a female.
The best time clocked by a male over
the same distance was 25" longer.
Downhill Schuss
Record held by a male over the
same distance as the vertical climb :
2' 46". But the champion, after a
day of fasting, refused to run the same
course in less than 8' 57". He then
proceeded to play the prima-donna by
refusing to run at all even after
careful feeding.
Open Events
In all races in this category, the
body lice were beaten at every turn.
Over one distance, the best head louse
registered 5' 54" as compared to 8' 12"
for the champion body louse.
Best Hour's Run
The records, as reported by A.D.
Peacock, are :
1) On a horizontal surface : 4 feet,
7 inches.
2) On a vertical surface : 11 and 1/2
inches.
'"These experiments were not car¬
ried out for the sake of amusement.
They enable us to understand how
lice travel from one individual to
another. The times and distances
recorded by the average louse give
us the key to all possible forms of
contamination by lice, especially in
crowded dormitories."
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
Queries from the insect world
Are insects sick with
the diseases they carry ?
Does an insect carrying a human
disease get sick itself? Is the
Anopheles mosquito, whining through
the hot darkness, as sick as the person
from whom it got the malaria parasites
it is loaded with? The malaria para¬
sites will be multiplying in its stomach,
then boring through the stomach walls,
developing and dividing in the abdo¬
minal cavity, swarming through the
body, and finally reaching the salivary
glands, from which they are ready to
penetrate with the mosquito's saliva
into the next person it bites.
This seems to be a lot for a-mosquito
to carry, and yet it does not appear to
suffer much from such an invasion.
Laboratory observations on mosquitoes
infected with malaria have shown that
there is little difference, if any, between
their life span and that of non-infected
mosquitoes. Other diseases, like yellow
fever, often lethal to man, seem to have
no harmful effect at all on the mos¬
quitoes infected with them. The Aedes
aegypti carrying yellow fever is a healthy
creature, though the virus of the
disease is found throughout its body.
Can mosquitoes
get elephantiasis ?
It is only when carrying diseases like
filariasis that mosquitoes suffer
heavily and even die. Filariasis is the
name given to an infection with tiny
parasitic worms called filariae, and is
the basic cause of the condition known
as elephantiasis. When sucking blood
from an infected person, à Culex fati-
gans mosquito may receive such a mas¬
sive infection that it cannot survive the
resulting damage to tissues and disrup¬
tion of its organs.
Other insects can also be killed by
germs pathogenic to man. The rat
flea which spreads plague may die when
its gut gets blocked with a massive
multiplication of the plague bacteria.
But these are exceptions. On the
whole, insects are not sick from the
disease they carry to man and, if they
are, they seem to suffer only from the
mechanical effects of massive infection.
How can a
killer save lives ?
IT has been estimated that five million
deaths and 100 million illnesses were
prevented by the use of DDT for con
trolling insect carriers of disease bet¬
ween 1942 and 1954.
What are *Q' fever
and scrub typhus ?
Among the diseases spread by insects
are several caused by tiny orga¬
nisms called Rickettsiae. They can bare¬
ly be seen under an ordinary micro¬
scope, and thus fall between the larger
bacteria and the smaller, sub-micro¬
scopical viruses. For example, a Rickett¬
sia is responsible for classic typhus fever
which in the past has killed millions of
people during raging epidemics in differ¬
ent parts of the world. It is transmitted
by the body louse. Murine typhus, a
similar but much less common disease
is harboured in rats and is transmitted
to man by the rat flea.
Scrub typhus, also known as Japanese
River fever or tsutsugamushi fever, is a
rickettsial disease of man in the Far
East, transmitted from wild rodents by
a small mite. Q-fever, which causes a
pneumonia-like disease in man, is often
carried by ticks between domestic ani¬
mals, from which man obtains the
disease by the airborne route.
Do ticks ever
attack human beings ?
Rocky Mountain spotted fever in the
United States, and boutonneuse
fever seen around the Mediterranean,
are sicknesses that man catches from
ticks which infest dogs. Tularemia, an¬
other rickettsial disease of man, is perpe¬
tuated in nature by ticks infecting rab¬
bits and other small wild animals. It is
interesting to note that ticks also trans¬
mit certain blood diseases, resembling
malaria, amongst domestic livestock and
cause enormous economic losses. Fortu¬
nately, this group of diseases is not
transmissible to man.
What insect-borne
disease resembles polio ?
The tick pest is also responsible for
infection in man of a group of
viruses which cause encephalitis (inflam¬
mation of the brain). Foresters and
rural folk in central and south-eastern
Europe are not infrequently infected
with this disease, which may somestimes
be confused with poliomyelitis. It appar¬
ently finds its reservoir in wild life and
is transmitted to man through tick-bite.
Although it is probable that meningo¬
encephalitis (to give it its full name) has
existed for many years, it was not until
1946 that it was recognized in Slovenia
as a form of meningitis. In 1953 serious
epidemics occurring simultaneously in
Yugoslavia and in Austria created wide¬
spread medical interest in this disease.
No specific cure has yet been found.
The existing antibiotics have no effect.
Recovery in paralytic cases, however, is
somewhat more frequent in meningo¬
encephalitis than in polio, and the pro¬
portion of deaths from this disease is
somewhat less than in polio : 4.6 %
deaths in meningoencephalitis as against
6.8 % in poliomyelitis.
What causes
' Oriental sore' ?
Leishmaniasis, a disease in man
caused by a protozoa (one-celled
parasite), causes "oriental sore" and
"kala-azar" amongst large numbers of
the poorer population groups in the
Mediterranean and South-east Asian
areas. Certain species of small flics
transmit this disease, and one of its
reservoirs is the dog, although man-
to-man transmission by the fly is the
usual chain of infection.
How fast can
mosquitoes bite ?
In Canada, in some of the badly
infested northern areas, as many as
280 mosquito bites a minute have been
counted on a bare forearm. At this rate
a naked man would theoretically be
drained of his blood in one hour and
45 minutes.
Is myxomatosis
also carried by insects ?
Careful investigations in Australia
have shown that myxomatosis is
spread from rabbit to rabbit by the bites
of a number of insects. The most im¬
portant is thought to be a species of
anopheline mosquito which goes down
into rabbit burrows to shelter from the
heat and dryness of the summer days,
and prefers biting rabbits and other
grass-eating animals. Further carriers
of the disease are some other species of
mosquito, certain blackflies (simulium)
as well as rabbit fleas and lice.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Radio-isotopes now answer the question:
HOW FAR DOES A FLY FLY ?
by Dale W. Jenkins
National Research Council, USA
If babies or young children in any country were being blinded or killed by human
enemies no effort would be spared to put the enemy out of action. Yet flies, which
do exactly these things, are treated merely as a nuisance and not as a deadly menace
capable of transmitting dysentery, diarrhoea, severe eye inflammations, typhoid
fever, cholera and many other diseases. Little progress is, in fact, being made in the
control of diseases caused by flies in most of the world. One reason is that too much
faith has been placed in insecticides while the real basis of fly controlsanitation-
has been neglected. Today, with radio-isotope "tracers" we have a new weapon to
fight insects which bring disease. In the article below, Dale W. Jenkins, one of the
delegates to the Geneva Conference on Atoms for Peace, describes the new fields
opened today by "tagging" insects to follow their activities more easily.
Nuclear energy has provided a valuable new tool
has permitted real progress in studying dif¬
ficult entomological problems. The exact part
played by insects in the dissemination of certain diseases
is still obscure, and use of radio-isotopes provides a means
of clarifying some of these relationships. Labelling of
medically-important insects with radio-isotopes was ini¬
tiated in 1949 by the author and others. Since that
time extensive studies have been carried out, using this
technique on a variety of insects.
Radio-isotope tagging is an effi¬
cient method since it permits positive
marking and identification of large
numbers of insects with a minimum
of labour and cost. For example it is
of importance, if control methods are
to be efficient and effective, to know
how far such insects usually travel
("dispersal range" is the technical
term), since this helps us to under¬
stand their role in spreading an epi¬
demic.
Various species of mosquitoes have
been labelled by growing the larvae
in radio-active solutions of phospho¬
rus 32, Strontium 89, and thorium,
and releasing the radio-active '"mark¬
ed" adults in large numbers. The
dispersal of 10 species of tropical and
arctic mosquitoes has been studied by
various investigators who have found
dispersal ranges of from 1 to 34 km.
The yellow fever mosquito in Nigeria
was found to disperse up to 1.2 km.
Dispersal and flight range (the
maximum distance which can be
travelled) of houseflies have been
subjects of study for a long time and a variety of marking
techniques have been used. Most of these studies showed
effective dispersal of 2 km or less. A number of studies
of dispersal of the housefly have been carried out using
phosphorus 32 and effective dispersal ranges were found
to be 1.6 to 13.6 km with maximum dispersal up to 32 km.
Dispersal studies have also been carried out using radio¬
active blowflies, screw-worm flies, eyegnats, blackflies,
and cockroaches.
Radio-isotope tagging has also helped to find out the
total number of one kind of insect there is in a given
area, how long certain disease-carrying insects live, and
how many offspring they have .
Studies of the disease-carrying role of insects, using
radio-isotope marking during epidemic outbreaks, have
not been made, but several preliminary experiments of
this type have been carried out. In a city in the Crimea,
houseflies were studied in their relation to carrying
diseases from outdoor privies. Radio-active flies were
collected in traps in kitchens in houses 30 metres from
the outdoor privy. In Texas, radio-active fruit flies were
found by the US Public Health Service in houses 320 me-
28
tres away from privies containing phosphorus 32 baits.
A large number of fruit flies which were found in houses
had at one time or another frequented privies. These
results should be borne in mind in relation to outbreaks
of dysentery and poliomyelitis.
Another very promising and fertile but unexplored
field awaits investigators using radio-isotopes in studying
disease transmission by insect carriers. If the organisms
which produce a given disease can be
tagged, many experiments are possible
in tracing them through the insect
carrier and determining the sites and
numbers of disease organisms which
are disseminated.
A large number of disease-produc¬
ing organisms have been labelled
with various radio-isotopes. These
include bacteria causing plague and
tuberculosis, dysentery, influenza and
other viruses, trypanosome sleeping
sickness, malaria, and also a variety
of nematode (thread-like) worms.
Use of radio-isotopes offers a
technique for studying medically-im¬
portant insects from the point of
view of their ability to carry disease,
their feeding habits, and the dissemi¬
nation and numbers of organisms, or
size of infective dose of organisms
that they can introduce.
The habits, life histories, and
disease-spreading role of many impor¬
tant body parasites living on animals
are not fully known. Ticks, mites,
lice and other medically important
parasites of this kind have not been
made radio-active and this is a most hopeful field of
investigation. Use of this technique should provide
needed information on the length of time such parasites
remain attached to their hosts under natural conditions,
whether they change to other hosts, where they are
located while unattached, longevity, dispersal, and popu¬
lation size. Tagging of the parasites is simple since the
creature on which they live can be made radio-active as
desired.
White rats and rabbits, for instance, were injected with
phosphorus 32 so that mosquitoes would take up 1,000
c p m (Geiger counts per minute) of this isotope per blood
meal. Similar results were obtained by other workers.
Phosphorus 32 has been used to find out just how much
blood fleas and mosquitoes take up at a "meal".
Control of insect disease carriers provides a constant
challenge, since almost every effort by human beings
results in a counter-move by the insects. The widespread
use of newer residual insecticides has resulted in the
development of resistance, which requires use of greater
quantities of more effective new insecticides.
Radio-isotopes provide a tool for furthering basic
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
THE POISONER IN
YOUR HOME. Of all
the world's insects, the
one most intimately asso¬
ciated ' with man is the
common house fly which
shares his home. Because
of Its capacity to spread
disease and Its ready appe¬
tite for both filthy and
clean foods and its
unpleasant habit of moving
back and forth between
them It is, in fact, one of
man's deadliest enemies.
Modern insecticides were
thought to be weapons
which could control If not
completely eradicate the
fly. (Photo, opposite page
shows flies killed by ten
milligrams of DDT In six to
eight hours). But health
authorities now report
that flies are rapidly deve¬
loping a resistance to insec¬
ticides to a degree that
makes them Ineffective as
a single means of control.
WHO
research on control of disease-carrying insects and disease
organisms. More than thirty different insecticides have
been radio-actively labelled. Radio-isotopes have already
been of great use in studying the site of entry, mode and
site of physiological action, and generally what happens,
to an insecticide when it gets inside an insect. Radio¬
isotopes have also been used in studying the resistance
to insecticides of certain insects.
Assessments of the area covered by airplane sprays of
insecticides and other materials have been made by the
author using radio-active gold. This technique has
several advantages over dye tracers in assessing the
results of airplane spraying of insecticides. These are,
greater accuracy, shorter time for assessment, fewer staff
required, and ability to measure depositions on vegetation
and uneven surfaces. This technique should be utilized
in assessing the efficiency of generators of insecticide fog
and smoke and other methods of insecticide dispersal.
Radiation from certain radio-isotopes and X-rays is
also proving valuable in controlling or killing insect
disease-carriers, disease organisms, and parasites. Large
stores of highly radio-active reactor wastes may be made
available in the future which have great potential value
for this purpose. Eradication of the screw-worm flies
was accomplished in Curacao- and is being planned in the
south-eastern United States. Many papers have appeared
on X-irradiation of fruit flies and other insects.
Radio-isotope radiation offers a possible means of
killing or arresting development of disease organisms in
the animal host body due perhaps to the large uptake of
metabolically active elements by these organisms. Inges¬
tion of phosphorus 32 by mosquitoes arrested development
of malaria parasites during the oocyst stage.
Red blood corpuscles carrying malaria parasites were
shown to take up more phosporus 32 than normal cells,
probably due to a more active rate of metabolism. Two
varieties of radio-iron have also been used in studying
malaria. Three species of trypanosome protozoans caus¬
ing sleeping sickness became non-infective or were killed
when treated with radiation from radium and X-ray.
Numerous studies using radio-isotopes have been carried
out in attempts to control or reduce infections due to a
variety of bacterial and viral diseases, and this field holds
great promise.
Super race of insects
developing
Asuper race of insects resistant to all types of insecticides
is developing in many countries, a World Health Orga¬
nization report now reveals. Thirty two countries have
reported insect resistance to DDT and other new Insecticides,
and approximately 35 species of insects are already involved.
A number of these insects spread some of the world's most
dangerous epidemic diseases.
Various types of malaria-bearing mosquitoes show immunity
to DDT in some areas of Greece, Lebanon, Indonesia, Saudi
Arabia, Panama, and Mississipi (USA). Body lice spreading
typhus can no longer be controlled by DDT In Korea, and five
other countries report that satisfactory control is becoming
difficult. Fleas which are responsible for plague are manifesting
resistance in certain parts of South America.
Worse still, there has recently come from Trinidad information
that a strain of mosquito which spreads yellow fever has shown
itself to be extremely resistant to DDT. (Trinidad had an out¬
break of yellow fever 2 1 months ago.) As to flies their destruc¬
tion with DDT and other chemicals is no longer possible in almost
all countries where these materials have been used In recent
years. Resistance of cockroaches and bedbugs is also well estab¬
lished in many countries.
"Should the degree of resistance in insects transmitting diseases
such as malaria, yellow fever, plague and typhus reach the point
where control by the available insecticides is no longer possible,
disastrous results from a health viewpoint will Inevitably occur
in many parts of the world", WHO director M.G.Candau recently
Informed a World Health assembly In Geneva.
Although new insecticides are available they are too few and
too limited In efficiency to have a significant effect on events.
An extraordinary fact is that no scientist today can yet say
with certainty "what causes death when insects are exposed
to insecticides" and what the biochemical and physiological
bases of resistance really are. A survey of the research on resis¬
tance is at present being carried out by WHO.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
DISEASE KNOWS NO FRONTIERS
Man's first concept of disease was
that it was a punishment of
the gods. This attitude is still
found among primitive peoples and
traces of it can be detected even in
our own sub-conscious minds.
The Greeks made the first great
step forward in this as in so many
other fields when Hippocrates and"
his followers began to consider dis¬
eases as natural phenomena which "
could and should be studied like any
other occurrence in nature. The very
title of his most famous work, "Airs,
Waters and Places" shows his rational
and scientific approach.
It was then quickly realized that a
large group of diseases, which we now
call epidemic, infectious or conta¬
gious, could be spread from person
to person, community to community
and country to country.
We know, for instance, that the
man who introduced the Black Death
(bubonic plague) into England in
1348, landed at Weymouth, then called
Melcombe Regis, and we know the
farm where he spent the first night
on his way to London and infected
his first contact. We also know the
name of the Negro who is supposed
to have introduced smallpox into
Mexico in 1520, thus being respon¬
sible for perhaps three and a half
million deaths.
The next step was for communities
to attempt to isolate themselves from
infection or to isolate the infected
area, by various means such as
establishing cordons sanitaires and
preventing all ingress or egress.
This policy failed even with the most
barbarous penalties such as "break¬
ing the head of a man who attempts
to escape, as an example to his
neighbours".
'A box of old cloathes'
Even under medieval conditions,
complete isolation was a practi¬
cal impossibility, though one
striking exception occurred when the
village of Eyam, in Derbyshire, Eng¬
land, infected with plague from a
"box of old cloathes" which arrived
from London on September 3, 1665,
voluntarily isolated itself for thirteen
months, by which time 259 out of
the 350 or so inhabitants had died.
In the fourteenth century, the
Republic of Venice, often infected
with plague from its trade with the
Levant, conceived the idea of holding
the crews, passengers and goods of
ships coming from infected countries,
in isolation for a limited period, to
cover' as we should now say the
incubation period of anyone infected
and to allow disinfection of goods by
exposure to sunlight or other means.
This period was arbitrarily fixed at
forty days said to be derived from
the time Jesus spent in the wilderness
and hence these measures came to
be called "quarantine" from the Ita¬
lian quaranta, i. e. forty.
30
by Dr. Neville M. Goodman
This idea caught on, and similar
systems of quarantine were adopted
by the ports of most maritime coun-
. tries over the next three centuries or
so; the introduction of infection was
thus sometimes prevented and at
least it showed that the authorities
were taking action.
But by the nineteenth century,
with the great expansion of trade and
travel made possible by the steam¬
ship and railway, these quarantine
systems had become an intolerable
nuisance. They varied from port to
port and were arbitrary, vexatious
and often cruel; they obstructed
travel and trade; they were very
costly; and they gave limitless oppor¬
tunity for bribery and corruption.
78 miles in 4 months
An excellent example of folies
quarantainaires was the case
of the Matteo Bruzzo, an Italian
ship with 200 passengers which left
Genoa for Montevideo on September
30, 1884. Cholera broke out on board
on arrival at Montevideo and the
ship was refused pratique there and
at Rio. It returned to Italy and
performed its quarantine at the island
of Pianosa near Elba. The ship
finally put in at Leghorn and the
passengers disembarked, having taken
nearly four months to travel from
Genoa to Leghorn, a distance of
78 miles.
Eventually the representatives of
twelve European countries met in
Paris in 1851 to try to bring about
some order and uniformity in qua¬
rantine measures, and from this con¬
ference the whole modern apparatus
of preventing the spread of disease
across frontiers indeed all interna¬
tional co-operation in the field of
health may be said to have sprung.
For the next seventy years in fact,
international health was quarantine.
It took, however, another ten inter¬
national Sanitary Conferences spread
over fifty years before the first effec¬
tive convention was signed in 1903.
This dealt with cholera, plague and
yellow ïever, to which were added
in later conventions, smallpox and
typhus together sometimes known
as the "quarantinable diseases" or
"Big Five". (In 1952, louseborne re¬
lapsing fever was added to the qua¬
rantinable diseases.)
The next step was the creation of
international bodies to settle disputes,
prepare new conventions in the light
of advances in medical knowledge
and, above all, to receive and transit
information of outbreaks of disease,
since early and accurate information
is essential to effective quarantine.
These were the Pan American
Sanitary Bureau (Washington 1902)
and the International Office of Public
Health (Paris 1907). Later the Health
Organization of the League of
Nations (Geneva 1923) and, during
the last war, unrra also helped.
Finally, about 1948, all these bodies
and their work were absorbed into
and taken over by the World Health
Organization, which is today the
only international authority on qua¬
rantine matters.
The actual work of "quarantine"
is carried out by the central and
local health authorities and the sea
and airport authorities of each
country. International traffic by
land is seldom the subject of health
measure: control is too difficult and
results are hardly worth while.
This is done under governmental
regulations which must conform to
the international codes, conventions
or regulations to which the country
Collecting and distribution centre of
epidemiological information.
WHO HQ Geneva.
Other centres.
Wireless stations transmitting WHO
bulletins.
Daily world-wide bullletins issu¬
ed by WHO, Geneva.
Weekly bulletins of the Singa¬
pore Epidemiological Intelligence
Station.
Weekly bulletin of the Alexan¬
dria Regional Office.A
is signatory. The code in operation
since 1952, accepted by some 90
countries, is contained in the Inter¬
national Sanitary Regulations.
The role of who is twofold: on the
one hand to draw up, interpret,
administer and, when necessary,
amend the International Sanitary
Regulations, which it does through a
Technical Committee on Interna¬
tional Quarantine (Chairman, Dr.
M. T. Morgan, United Kingdom); and
on the other to receive, collate and
distribute information on the occur¬
rence of these pestilential diseases.
This is done by the who staff at its
headquarters in Geneva and in three
main sub-centres, at Singapore,
Alexandria and Washington.
Some 7,000 reports are sent in each
year by national health administra¬
tions of 170 countries and territories,
and the information thus received is
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
broadcast daily in English and
French from Radio Nations at Geneva
and the other centres: by arrange¬
ment with other stations, these mes¬
sages are rebroadcast over a wide
area. This is supplemented by tele¬
grams and a printed bulletin, the
Weekly Epidemiological Record. It
should be mentioned that who's Epi¬
demiological Information Service is
not limited to the six major pestilen¬
tial diseases, and in a montly Epide¬
miological and -Vital Statistics Report
the occurrence and trends of other
infectious diseases such as poliomye¬
litis, influenza, diphtheria and scarlet
fever are reported and analysed. In
addition, other cognate work is un¬
dertaken, such as revising the Inter¬
national Certificates of Vaccination,
and de-ratting certificates for ships.
Annual reports /aré also collated
on the health condition of the Mecca
Pilgrimagealways a potential source
of danger, since up to half a million
pilgrims coming from every part of
the Old World are crowded annually
for a few weeks into the Holy Places
water, that plague was spread by
fleas of the black rat and yellow
fever by a particular mosquito; and
when, later, effective control mea¬
sures, using modern insecticides and
immunizing inoculations had been
developed against these diseases,
agreement could be reached on more
rational measures.
Instead of shutting up people in
isolation for arbitrary periods if
they were suspected of coming from
infected places, today the emphasis
is on getting their co-operation and
warning them (and their doctors) if
they fall ill after arrival of the possi¬
bility that they may be suffering
from one of these diseases.
Thus, the passengers on a ship
coming to London from Calcutta,
where smallpox is prevalent, without
any suspicious cases having occurred
during the voyage would not normally
be subject to any restrictions. But
if a case of smallpox occurred on
board, vaccination would be offered
on arrival if that had not already
Information on epidemic diseases is continuously collected from all parts of the world by the
World Health Organization headquarters in Geneva, and re-transmitted to all health authori¬
ties. Map shows the radio-telegraphic network that makes this service possible.
in Saudi Arabia. This made the Pil¬
grimage a frequent source of world¬
wide epidemics of cholera in the
nineteenth century.
Thus who is enabled to keep its
finger on the epidemic pulse of the
world and to keep its member coun¬
tries informed of the patient's condi¬
tion. By reducing the international
spread of disease and, on the other
hand, by preventing excessive or
hysterical restrictions on health
grounds, who is favourably affecting
the lives and health of all of us.
Finally, something may be said of
the trends and tendencies of quaran¬
tine practice today. Originally, qua¬
rantine measures were arbitrary and
empirical, since little was known
about tlie way these diseases spread.
Once it was established that, for
instance, cholera occurred primarily
from the excreta! contamination of
been done and everyone would be
put under "surveillance" i. e. notified
to the Medical Officer of Health of
their destinations and told to see him.
When the risk is less, and formal
"surveillance" is not considered
necessary, perhaps, for example, if
the case had been discovered at the
beginning of the voyage and no other
cases had occurred, passengers might
only be given a yellow warning card,
urging them to call in a doctor at
once if they fell sick and to show him
the card which would alert him to
the possibility of smallpox.
Another factor in modifying qua¬
rantine practice has been the intro¬
duction of air travel whereby a man
may arrive from a distant country
well within the incubation period of
the diseases prevalent in the country
of departure.
To examine him on arrival would
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
be fruitless, since the signs and
symptoms of disease would not yet
have appeared. To isolate him until
the incubation period was over would
be intolerable and would stultify the
whole purpose of air travel. But,
according to circumstances and the
diseases in question, he can be immu¬
nized sufficiently long before his
departure to prevent him starting
an epidemic in the country of arrival.
Thus "quarantine" measures have
become steadily more rational and
less restrictive, and the well-immuniz¬
ed traveller has little to fear. The
ultimate aim, of course is to abolish
the need for any restriction, by
stamping out these diseases them¬
selves in the areas in which they are
endemic. This is a long-term policy
though given the money, effort and
co-operation of the countries concern¬
ed, it could be done.
To sum up, governments began to
co-operate in health matters about
100 years ago, not from idealistic mo¬
tives but because hard-headed busi¬
ness men and officials decided that
agreement must be reached with the
doctors on the maximum measures
which could be applied everywhere to
keep epidemic diseases from spread¬
ing from one country to another, and
that these measures must be accept¬
ed in every country.
'Wens and excrescences'
That it took more than 50 years
to achieve this was due to lack
of definite knowledge on how
these diseases were spread, as well as
to international political rivalries.
Once agreement had been reached, it
was necessary to create international
bodies to oversee the working of the
conventions embodying the agree¬
ments, and the creation of the World
Health Organization permitted for
the first time a single world-wide in¬
ternational authority to become res¬
ponsible over this whole field.
Advances in medicine and in com¬
munications have allowed the original
conception of quarantine as a kind of
sanitary police and prison system to
be modified in the direction of
greater freedom combined with great¬
er safety, based on the co-operation
of the public though the powers are
still there should they be needed.
The philosophy written into the
International Sanitary Regulations
now in force is to give the maximum
security against the importation of
these diseases with the minimum in¬
terference with world traffic. The
success achieved in the first three
years of application of the Interna¬
tional Sanitary Regulations augurs
well for the future.
To have been associated with this
work, as with other accomplishments
in the international health field,
brings appreciation of the words
written by John Donne 300 years ago:
"To be no part of any Body is as to
be nothing. For the greatest Persons
are but great wens and excrescences
except they be so incorporated into
the body of the world that they con¬
tribute something to the sustentation
of the whole."
This article originally appeared in an
unabridged form in Unilever's magazine
"Progress".
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The unwanted travellers
The march of civilization, with ever
*- faster travel by ships and
aircraft, has also helped the disease-
carrying insects to colonize new ter¬
ritories and launch fresh epidemics.
To stamp out the intruders often
takes years of tedious struggle.
npHERE is one kind of aircraft pas-
senger, which does not appear in
the passenger lists and often escapes
the sanitary control authorities.
These are insects which may lodge
in the cabin of the aircraft or in the
luggage hold or be taken in on the
clothes of passengers or even on
flowers which may be presented to
them. Most often they are mosqui¬
toes, flies, fleas, lice, sometimes ticks,
beetles, cockroaches, Colorado beetles,
and still others whose presence is
always disagreeable but may also be
dangerous for man, livestock and
agriculture.
np he behaviour of insects in aircraft
in flight has been closely observ¬
ed. Altitude, changes in air pressure
and temperature during long flights
do not permanently affect the insects.
They live in aircraft for as long as
they can exist without nourishment;
that is, of course, if they cannot find
what they need in the aircraft itself.
Certain insects have been known to
lay their eggs on the outside of
aircraft on the wings, the fuselage,
the rudder and even on the propellers!
These eggs were found to be still
there at the end of the journey:
neither the wind nor the altitude nor
yet changes in temperature had
affected their capacity for survival.
On one single plane thousands of
larvae emerged from the eggs and
swarmed over the surface of the air¬
craft. Strict surveillance of aircraft
and airports is absolutely essential.
Tr was undoubtedly on board a fast
boat that the malaria-carrying
mosquito, Anopheles gambiae, cross¬
ed from West Africa to Brazil in 1930.
This mosquito is particularly danger¬
ous since it is essentially "domestic",
prefers biting human beings, and
breeds easily near human habitations.
In 1931, a campaign was organized at
Natal (Brazil), which was the point
of entry of Anopheles gambiae, and !
as a result the mosquito was cleared
from that port. However, it found
terrain favourable to its development
in the interior of the states of Rio
Grande do Norte and of Cesra. The
ASIA'S FIRST
PENICILLIN FACTORY
Penicillin, a vital arm In the battles against
disease and epidemics, is still missing or is in
short supply on many of the fronts where the
world war for health is being waged. Peni¬
cillin production, however, is now being in¬
creased through aid given by the U.N., the
World Health Organization (WHO) and the
U.N. Children's Fund (UNICEF). Asia's first
penicillin factory, set up with help from these
organizations at Pimpri, near Poona, India,
has increased its production to 1,000 pounds
per month, since it began to operate in
March 1955. Thirteen Indians have so far
been trained abroad and have now become
the key staff at the plant. Technical Assistance
funds were used to provide international
result was a murderous epidemic of
malaria lasting up to 1938 when a
special control service was organized
in that region of north-east Brazil.
Thanks to its efficient organization
and abundant resources it was able
to eliminate these mosquitoes from
Brazil in about two years.
A nopheles gambiae inhabits the
whole of tropical Africa and it
periodically invades certain temperate
zones and spreads malaria there. In
1942, for example, probably as a result
of military movements, these mos¬
quitoes invaded Upper Egypt and the
number of cases of malaria in 1942-
1943 was estimated at 140,000. Ener¬
getic extermination measures under¬
taken in 1944 led to the complete
disappearance of the species by
February 1945. Such examples of
eradication of a species of mosquito,
personnel to guide the project, supervise,
the construction and erection and develop
the operating techniques. Above, a locally-
trained technician makes a biological test in
laboratory of potency of the penicillin pro¬
duced. WHO and UNICEF also recently
joined hands with the Government of Yugo¬
slavia in modernizing and expanding the only
penicillin processing plant in this country.
Left, girls bottling penicillin in a sealed,
sterilized glass cabinet at the Zemun plant
near Belgrade, Yugoslavia.
UNATIONS
carried out on a large scale and at
great cost, effectively demonstrate
what may be the consequences of the
accidental introduction of an insect
carrier of disease.
npHE regular deratting of ships, and
the rational use of insecticides on
board ship and aircraft, or for pas¬
sengers and their luggage, have prov¬
ed to be effective in preventing any
epidemic of pestilential disease in the
past 25 years.
This is the aim of the World Health
Organization International Sanitary
Regulations which, on the basis of
up-to-date epidemiological and other
information, lay down the preventive
measures which should be taken,
while at the same time reducing to
the strict minimum any inconve¬
nience or delay caused to interna¬
tional passengers or goods traffic.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1956
Letters to the editor...
Sir,
The unesco courier has been a tre¬
mendous benefit to me, increasing my
knowledge and understanding of the cul¬
ture of other people. I would be so
pleased "if you could put me in touch with
the readers in other lands who may like
to make an exchange of some of the pri¬
mitive native art of their own countries
for some original aborigine bark paintings
from Arnhem Land. With very good
wishes.
Oscar Edwards.
Sydney, New South Wales,
Australia.
editor's note : In issue N° 11, 1954, the unesco
courier published an article on Australian abo¬
rigine paintings from Arnhem Land : "An art
on bark and stone", together with full colour
reproductions.
Copyright A. Billeaut
A MYSTERIOUS, SPINNING «ELECTRIC EGG'
A gleaming metal egg which whirled round at top speed and theH stood on end intrigued
visitors at a Unesco travelling science exhibition, "Energy And Its Transformations", which
opened in Paris on March I. The mysterious behaviour of the egg is easily explained as an
application of electromagnetic energy. Four induction coils are placed in a square pattern
beneath a concave sheet of glass, in the centre of which is the aluminium egg. Electrical
currents with a difference In phase of ninety degrees are passed through the coils. The egg
becomes the centre of induced currents which create a torque (two equal and parallel forces
acting In opposite directions). The egg begins to turn until, under the action of centrifugal
force, It slowly becomes Inclined, When it is turning with sufficient speed, the egg rises
on end and continues to spin round and round. The "electric egg" is one of many fascinat¬
ing exhibits In the travelling exhibition which will shortly leave for a three years' tour of
cities in the Far East. Four earlier Unesco science exhibitions have been viewed by nearly
2,000,000 people in 32 countries during the past five years.
Sir,
Couldn't you devote one of your issues
to the question of religious tolerance which,
as you must be aware, does not exist in
many countries, even in those referred to
as "'civilized"? Also, could not unesco
launch a campaign for the abolition of that
medieval anachronism the death penalty?
Strasbourg-Ncuhof, J.-P. Thomas.
France.
Sir,
In your June, (U.S.A.) 1955, issue
(European, N" 6, 1955) you published an
article by Lucien Bernot and Rene Blan-
cart, "What a French Village Thinks of
the Foreigner". The questionnaire used
by the unesco research team listed Jews
as one of the "peoples" investigated.
As you probably know there is consider¬
able question in the minds of anthropo¬
logists regarding this designation of Jews
as a '"people". Most social scientists, of
course, classify Judaism as a religion; Jews
however, who are citizens of various coun¬
tries, are considerd to be French, British
or Americans as the case may be. Under
the circumstances, the grouping utilized by
the research team seems to leave something
to be desired. It would probably have
been more accurate also had the list
included such categories as Catholic and
Protestant in addition to Jews. This
would have permitted comparison of
respondents' attitudes towards different
religious groups.
Marc Vosk.
Director, Div. of Scientific Research,
The American Jewish Committee,
New York 16, N. Y.
Sir,
Reading the February 1956 issue of your
magazine (U.S., April) I found the article
on the earthworm excellent. This is a
humble yet surprising creature and I
think the article must have interested all
your readers. I personally would have
liked to see a rather more complete study.
Boulogne, Guy Fort.
Seine, France.
Sir,
With each issue of the unesco courier
I am more impressed with the work of
unesco and more encouraged in the never-
ending struggle for making this world a
better one for all mankind. This maga¬
zine is required reading for all students in
Music Education at Southern Illinois Uni¬
versity. Thank you for your wonderful
work.
Carbondale, Robert Forman.
Illinois, U.S.A.
Sir,
I am glad to have "met" the unesco
courier. It is the best and most urgently
needed paper I ever read. At my school
I am going to try to form a study-group
among the teachers to discuss the articles.
Bjorkfors, Espinara, Gustav Wïkstrom.
Sweden.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom
o.'UTCASTS NO LONGER:
Growing confidence in new anti-
leprosy drugs and the fact that
leprosy sufferers are no longer
treated as outcasts means that
fewer people conceal their dis¬
ease and more are seeking treat¬
ment in World Health Organi¬
zation (who) -assisted cam¬
paigns, who which has been
aiding leprosy control work in
12 countries during the past six
years is now to extend this help
to six other countries. In 1942
estimates of the number of le¬
prosy victims in the world rang¬
ed from between two and seven
million. Revised figures place the
number today at between ten
and twelve million. This does
not mean that leprosy has in¬
creased, but simply that more
cases are known about. It is a
myth that leprosy is highly con¬
tagious. Risks of contracting it
are smaller than those associat¬
ed with tuberculosis.
H SCHOOLS IN THE
SNOW : Many French city
schoolchildren have been
gaining health and vigour
this winter from "snow
classes", first started as an
experiment in winter sports
centres two years ago. Morn¬
ing classroom lessons, after¬
noon ski instruction, evening
homework, then games and a
long night's rest make up the
day's programme. Teachers
report a striking improve¬
ment in both the work and
the morale of the children.
Most of the cost of sending
classes to the mountains is
paid by the Ministry of Edu¬
cation and local authorities.
1_.UBAN CRITICS CON¬
CUR : The Unesco film "World
without End" has been selected
by the Cuban Association of
Theatre and Cinema Critics as
the best film of 1955 in the cate¬
gory of non-commercial docu¬
mentaries. The international
selection of the best films of the
The Subscription Dept of
the UNESCO COURIER
wishes to remind readers
that it can guarantee to
service subscriptions without
interruption only if renewal
remittances are made imme¬
diately upon receipt of noti¬
fication of expiry.
tribute to the Lumière Brothers
who organized it in Paris in
December 1895. (See the Unesco
Courier, No 1, 1955.)
H ATOMS FOR ASIA : As
soon as atomic power stations
can be built economically
enough to produce . cheap,
power, the tremendous possi¬
bilities of atomic energy can
be used to improve living
standards in under-developed
countries. Though this is
not likely to happen for
another decade or so. long-
term planning is already in
progress. Recently a com¬
mittee of the U.N. Economic
Commission for Asia and the
Far East met in Bangalore,
India, to discuss the role that
atomic energy may play in
Asian countries. It discus¬
sed how technically advanced
countries at present engaged
in atomic research and deve¬
lopment can eventually help
other nations to train tech¬
nicians to prospect for radio¬
active minerals and how
information on the latest
nuclear techniques can be
exchanged.
IIHJRAL SCIENCE CEN¬
TRES: India is to set up a net¬
work of rural science centres
which will advise people in vil¬
lages and small communities on
the practical application of
science in everyday life. Centres
will operate as laboratories for
applied science where secondary
school pupils will receive train¬
ing and practical experience.
The centres are being planned
on the basis of successful results
obtained at an experimental
centre in New Delhi State.
SOIL DOCTORS : Since
1954 a land rehabilitation
team has been working in an
erosion-wrecked section of
Jamaica to improve living
standards in a mountainous
area of some 55,000 acres
where 60,000 persons must
cope with the problem of
wasted land. The team will
shortly be joined by Dr. G.J.
Kruijer, a Dutch sociologist,
who is being sent there by
Unesco under the programme
of assistance to its member
states in fields not normally
covered by the U.N. Technic¬
al Assistance programme.
II
year was made by the Associa¬
tion to commemorate the 60th
anniversary of the first public
LUNGRY FOR MUS¬
EUMS: Public interest in mus¬
eums is growing in Hungary
where during the past two years
more than five million people
tions. Budapest has now twenty
museums (twice the pre-war
figure)' while every provincial
town of any importance has its
own collection, generally devoted
to regional, archaeological, his¬
torical and folklore exhibits.
H PAKISTAN'S 'SCIENCE
HOUSE' : The foundation
stone of a national science
institute which will even¬
tually house a library of
some 250,000 scientific works
was laid recently at Lahore,
in West Pakistan. Called the
Ismail Aiwan-i-Science (Is¬
mail Science House) after
the benefactor of the project,
it will provide a meeting
place for scientists and will
give Pakistan its first com¬
prehensive scientific library,
now being planned in con¬
sultation with Unesco.
M. RAINING REFUGEE
TEACHERS : Unesco experts
and Arab instructors are draw-
in» up curricula for two new
teacher training centres, one for
men and one for women, which
have been opened in Jordan by
the United Nations Relief and
Works Agency (Unrwa). The
centres will train teachers in
up-to-date methods suited to
Unrwa's educational programme
for Arab Refugee Schools, over
300 of which have been set up
in Jordan, the Lebanon, Syria
and the Gaza area. (See the
Unesco Courier, No 7, 1955
"Schools in the Sand".)
H PLANNING AT PHNOM-
PENH: Four countries
bodia, Laos, Thailand, and
Vietnam are to join efforts
to rid the Indo-Chinese pen¬
insular of its most expensive
and debilitating disease ma¬
laria, it was announced at a
recent conference in Phnom-
Penh, Cambodia, sponsored
by the World Health Organi¬
zation. Delegates proposed
to set up an Anti-Malaria
Co-ordination Board with
who providing technical ad¬
vice. No . country, said the
delegates, could be safe from
malaria if its neighbours har¬
boured the disease, since
"mosquitoes recognize no ter¬
ritorial or political bounda¬
ries".
Hi
moving picture show and as a have visited the various collec-
34
LISTORY IN WOOL: The
famous Bayeux Tapestry which
attracts some 50,000 visitors to
Bayeux Museum in northern
France each year. will, soon be
seen by a far wider public. A
documentary film in colour has
been made of the tapestry, in
French and Spanish versions,
which will be shown throughout
the world. A wool-embroidered
canvas 231 feet in length, the
tapestry was completed about
the year 1092, and shows differ¬
ent stages in the conquest of
Britain by William, Duke of
Normandy.
T.V. GOES BACKSTAGE:
Television has found a "be¬
hind the scenes" job in the
Vienna State Opera House,
which re-opened last Novem¬
ber. It is helping the con¬
ductor of the choir, back¬
stage, to take his cue from
the orchestra conductor, in
front. As in many opera
houses, the Vienna Opera
cho'.r is behind the stage and
invisible to the audience. A
miniature television camera
fitted into the prompter's
box, facing the orchestra, re¬
lays the conductor's move¬
ments to a screen installed
behind the stage where choir¬
master and singers await
their cue.
SPECIAL BINDER
FOR THE "UNESCO
COURIER"
Special binders in which
readers can keep their year's
collection of issues of the
UNESCO COURIER will
slnitiy be available. Watch
for special announcement
with full details next month.
A,LFRICA'S FIRST CY¬
CLOTRON: A cyclotronan
atomic particle accelerator
which recently began operating
near Pretoria, in the Union of
South Africa, will produce short-
life radio-isotopes for use in in¬
dustry, agriculture and medicine.
These isotopes cannot normally
be imported from Europe or the
United States owing to their
short lifespan. The cyclotron
Africa's first will also be used
to train South Africa's nuclear
physicists.
WELCOME TO GER¬
MANY: A varied programme
for youth groups from abroad
visiting Germany this sum¬
mer is offered by the Ger¬
man Association for Inter¬
national Youth Exchange, in
Bonn, German Federal Re¬
public. Some well-equipped
residential centres are re¬
commended by the Associa¬
tion which also supplies in¬
formation on study tours and
arranges school exchanges
and holidays for members of
youth groups as paying
guests in German families.
o
z
<
a:
r
ci
<
z
<
o
a?
O
uj
U
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Vacations Abroad
Vacances à l'étranger
Vacaciones en el extranjero
The I 956 edition of this annual Unesco handbook, now available,
gives details in English, French and Spanish of nearly 950 summer
courses, study tours, work camps, youth and student centres,
hostels and holiday camps, of Interest to persons wishing to
combine educational experience with travel abroad during their
vacations in 1956. These activities take place in 57 countries
in Europe, Asia, Africa and America. There is also a section on
vacation scholarships open to participants in summer schools.
Vacations Abroad can be obtained from the Unesco national
distributors listed below. Price: SI; 5/-; 250 francs.
An extra-special issue :
BUDDHIST
ART
* 2,500 years of art and
culture.
* Buddha's influence on the
thought of Asia.
Don't miss this issue. Subscribe today
to the UNESCO COURIER
Annual subscription rate 8/-, $2.50 or
400 French francs
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's National distributors from
whom the English, French and Spanish
editions of the UNESCO COURIER
can be obtained are listed below.
AUSTRIA. Wilhelm Frick Verlag. 27
Graben, Vienna I.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, I 5. rue du Tilleul. Genval (Bra¬
bant). (UNESCO COURIER only)
Librairie Encyclopédique, 7, rue de
Luxembourg, Brussels IV.
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei, 151,
Antwerp.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090, Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, Colombo 1.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. M.E. Constantinides, P.O.
Box 473, Nicosia.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6, Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
Ave-
Paris
Ave-
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, 19,
nue Kleber, Paris, I6\ C.C.P.
12598-48.
Sales & Distribution Division, 1 9,
nue Kléber, Paris, 1 6'.
GERMANY. R.. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bom¬
bay I ; I 7, Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta
13. 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Jakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road, P.O. Box 4101, Tel-
Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99,
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings,
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.. 6, Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26, Kings-
way, Valletta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Ni-
jhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 1 00, Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop. P.O. Box
I 74, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stprtings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60, The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35. The Mall. Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl-
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5.
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2, rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 551-3, Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London. S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, National Agency for Internatio¬
nal Publications, 500, Fifth Avenue, New
York 36. N.Y.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga.
Terazije 27' I I, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
WHO - Pierre Pittet
BIG MENACE IN
A TINY SPACE
The tsetse fly shown much enlarged here is actually only half an inch long, its
wingspread one inch. The proboscis, the fine tube with which it punctures the skin
to suck blood, is the thin line seen between the two "feelers" or palps. The
dreaded tsetse fly produces the sleep that ends in death. Slayer of cattle, killer
of men, it is one of the great scourges.of tropical Africa. In over four and a half
million square miles of Africa the bite of the tsetse fly may infect man with a
minute organism which produces the fatal sleeping sickness, or may transmit
other organisms fatal to cattle. But today it is slowly being driven from its empire
area half as great again in extent as the continent of Australia. (See page 12)
]]>
</page>
</document>
