<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068829eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
H O , St. \ . i -o U . fir.
Strange spirals in
a Viet-Nam pagoda
(See page 29)
V..-U
ï*A	i X >/
OCTOBE
1956
(9th year)
Price: 9d. (U. K.)
francs (France)
7-/
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Sicily's
one-horse
'jeep'
The maid-of-all-work for Sicily's
farmers is a one-horse cart called
carretto which, because it is
perfectly adapted to the rugged,
mountain terrain of' the island,
has been dubbed "a one-horse
jeep." It offers a unique example
of Sicilian craftsmanship, love of
music and decorative art asso¬
ciated with ancient tales of
chivalry. (See story page 24)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
OCTOBER 1956
9th YEAR
N° 10
CONTENTS
PAGE
3
4
EDITORIAL
ASIAN ARTISTS IN CRYSTAL
Eastern inspiration joins Western workmanship
IS TWO WORLDS FACE TO FACE
Dialogue across the Atlantic
By Antony Babel
17 OUT, OUT, DAMNED SPOT
What did people do in the days of no dry-cleaning ?
By Anna Sommer Lenn
21 OBESITY : A SLOW FORM OF SUICIDE
By Gerald Wendt
22 SANTINIKETAN: ABODE OF PEACE
By Guy Wint
24 THE SICILIAN «CARRETTO'
Artistic pride of peasants yesterday and today
Fly Lucio Attinelli
27 VIEWPOINT ON BUDDHIST ART
A controversy at the "crossroads of civilization"
By Grégoire Frumkin
29 PAGODA OF THE GOOD MOTHER
Super joss-sticks to honour a sea goddess
32 FESTIVE GREETINGS FROM UNICEF
New Year cards to help the world's needy children
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19 Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leve.ntis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not copyrighted may be reprinted from THE UNESCO
COURIER but muse be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted
from UNESCO COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's
name. Prints of non-copyright photos are available on requesc.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE UNESCO
COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE UNESCO COURIER : 8/-; $2.50 or 400
French frs or equivalent.
(MC. 56. 1.106 A)
The Unesco Courier
COVER PHOTO
Long spirais of incense form an abstract
design of strange beauty as they hang
from a pagoda roof in Cholon, the
Chinese quarter of Saigon. The spirals
of incense, once lit, smoulder away
for months at a time. They are offer¬
ings made by well-to-do Chinese to i
patron goddess of travellers and sailors
(See page 29)
Copyright |. D. Lajoux
The crisis of our times is a crisis of cultures as well as
of economics and politics. "What happens to the
values of art, science, literature, philosophy and
religion, affects and is affected by what happens to the
material conditions of life and the international relations
of nations.
No one today would any longer want to entertain the
notion of a culture confined to a particular section of
mankind or to a single nation with the civilizations beyond
dismissed as mere superstitions or anachronisms. The
problem of international understanding today is a problem
of the relations between cultures, for from such cultures a
new community of mutual respect will finally emerge.
unesco itself is a sign and acknowledgment of the
important use to which the instruments of education,
science and culture can be put in advancing peace and the
welfare of man. Since its foundation, unesco has
concerned itself with the multitudinous problems raised
both by the legitimate diversity of cultures and by the
necessity for mutual relations between them. In fact the
need for better understanding and mutual appreciation
between different peoples of one another's cultures was
recognized by the founders of unesco, and its encourage¬
ment placed by them among the major objectives of the
Organization.
In 1949, unesco initiated a series of studies and enquiries
on the state of indigenous cultures of the various peoples
of the world and on the relations existing between these
cultures. It published two thought-provoking volumes on
Humanism and Education in East and West, and on the
Interrelations of Cultures. In 1954 it sponsored two
international forums in Europe and South America on the
contributions of the New World and Europe to cultural
life. (See page 15)
Today the vast problem of the cultural relations between
peoples is receiving increasing attention both by unesco,
as an international agency, and its member nations. Of
three major projects which the next session of unesco's
General Conference will be called upon to approve in New
Delhi in November, one is "the promotion of mutual
appreciation of Eastern and Western cultural values."
It is clear that many nations of the East believe that the
world as a whole can benefit from a greater appreciation
of the elements of their cultures. Also clear is the fact
that this belief is readily accepted by Western nations, in
varying degrees. But because the engines of cultural dif¬
fusion are forcing the flow largely from West to East,
chiefly in the form of scientific and technological know¬
ledge and ideas, two harmful effects are produced. The
more obvious is that the East is not presented with suffi¬
cient fullness to the West in any form whatever. Less
obvious but equally important is the fact that Asian and
other nations get a seriously distorted idea of the total
Western culture. These fragmentary, or distorted notions
either create or add to many contemporary problems.
In its March 1956 issue, the unesco courier discussed
one aspect of this problem under the title "Are our
children learning history with a slant?" (U.S. edition May
1956). A portion of the present number is devoted to a
unique example of artistic co-operation combining Eastern
inspiration and Western craftsmanship.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Malinaothe village
of peaceful people
Manuel Rodriguez, a Filipino artist,
with a light touch and a natural gift for
illustrative drawing, portrays "The
Village of Malinao" the village of
peaceful people. His drawing (bottom
of this page) Is a succession of
simple scenes typical of village life
in his country the market place, the
pounding of rice, the flower vendors,
the village huts, the slow-footed cara¬
bao, and the roast pig on the day of
the feast. It has been engraved as a
continuous frieze on the handsome,
1 0-inch diameter decorated bowl (oppo¬
site page). Manuel Rodriguez' work
has a touch of journalism and of hu¬
mour and he is at his best when depict¬
ing the simple life of his own country.
A unique form of co-operation between artists
of the East and craftsmen of the West .has
produced a remarkable collection of works
of art in engraved crystal. Asian artists prepared the
drawings; American designers captured the mood of the
drawings in the crystal forms, and American draftsmen
interpreted the drawing in engraving the crystal.
In all, 36 pieces were prepared and executed by an Am¬
erican producer of fine crystal (1) which conceived the
collection as a contribution to the art of glass. "Asian
Artists in Crystal" has been on exhibition in the National
Gallery of Art, Washington, and the Metropolitan Museum
of Art, New York, this year. Now it is touring the coun¬
tries in the Far and Near East, from which the drawings
were obtained, under U.S. Government sponsorship.
In 1954 and 1955, Karl Kup, Curator of Prints and of
the Spencer Collection at the New York Public Library,
visited 16 countries to seek out and work with artists
whose style and manner would lend themselves to glass
engraving. Writing of the Asian artists he says: "Their
paintings, their drawings and their sculpture quite natu¬
rally follow established cycles of subject matter : their
manner of rendering is indigenous, almost intuitive. In
Korea, symbolism still attracts contemporary painters ;
(1) Steuben Glass Inc., New York.
in China mood, thought and poetry are more important
than subject matter; in the Philippines there are traces
of Western influence; in Viet-Nam and Indonesia, a strong
leaning toward colourful themes of folklore. The themes
of Angkor Wat, the textile patterns of Central Java and
the Festival of Hindu Bali: all these I found in drawings
of contemporary men and women of Southeast Asia.
"Later, as I proceeded toward Thailand, Burma, India
and Ceylon, I found religion, Buddhist and Hindu, to be
the mainspring of inspiration. There were exceptions, of
course. In Pakistan, Turkey and Egypt one sensed the
artists' nearness to Western conceptions and expressions."
The merit of the original drawing lies with the indivi¬
dual artist, but the masterful craftsmanship of the glass
blower and the glass engraver must be apparent if uni¬
formity of excellence is to be attained. A successful colla¬
boration would be impossible without the guiding hand
and spirit of the glass designer who interprets the artist's
drawing and designs the glass form which will result in
a lovely and integrated whole. In this collection the
designers have tried to capture the mood of the original
drawing and to evoke religious, racial and geographic
influences.
On the following pages The Unesco Courier presents
some of the outstanding works of "Asian Artists in Crys¬
tal". (All photos courtesy Steuben Glass Inc.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
ASIAN ARTISTS (Continuée/;
The floating
village
In Viet-Nam, a heavily
populated land studded
with rivers and rivulets,
generations of families
are born, raised and die
on the covered sampans, /
or dinhs anchored like «
floating villages off the
stilted wooden walks to some fertile shore. In the boats, ingenious
builders have incorporated rooms for the ancestral shrine, for the
family elders, for the kitchen. Nguyen-van-Long, designer of "The
Floating Village" which has been engraved on a crystal vase, is a
drawing teacher at a Saigon Fine Arts School. He is an admirer of
the French impressionists whose style has influenced his own work.
Nang Fa, Siamese angel
Bhima, an uncouth warrior and powerful
magician, is a hero from the Indonesian shadow
plays in which flat, cowhide puppets act tales
from the great Hindu epics, the Ramayana and
the Mahabharata. In the adventures of Bhima,
a tale of feud between two princely houses,
the strength of the righteous and their ulti¬
mate victory is so great that rivers stand still,
the sun pales and mountains tremble. Here
is Bhima's epic battle with a deadly snake.
Raden Basoeki Abdullah, the artist, (Raden
means "prince") though inspired by such
Western painters as Rembrandt and Ve¬
lasquez, also draws richly on the folk-
. lore and imagination of both Java and Bali.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ASIAN ARTISTS (Continue^
Aft*.*«
L->
$
l*1^
¥?
~i
The fabulous unicorn
Fabulous beast of great strength, the unicorn made its
first pictorial appearance into the world in the ancient
civilization of the Indus Valley, in the Pakistan of today.
Sheikh Ahmed, a Pakistani artist and director of art in the
Department of Public Relations of the Government of the
Punjab, chose it as the subject for his contribution to
"Asian Artists in Crystal". He based his drawing on a
seal dating from the third millenium B.C. found in an an¬
cient Indus Valley city. Sheikh Ahmed, a trained automobile
and aircraft engineer, gave up a technical career for art.
Sniffing the breezes
"Sniffing the breezes" or Shemm-en-neseem, is an age-old
custom in Egypt on the first day of Khamaseen in the Spring
when the air is balmy and fragrant. People ride or walk
to the country to take the air, and Spring, a beautiful time
on the banks of the Nile, is the time for lovers. Hamed
Abdalla, one of Egypt's most modern painters, whose draw¬
ing has been engraved on rectangular crystal blocks,
9 l/2-inches high, is self taught. He says: "like the orien¬
tal and folkloristic artist and unlike the occidental, I paint
nature as I see it with my mind, not as it 'looks' to the eye."
r*%
?y?{MK x
risaä
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Balinese funeral
a joyous occasion
Balinese funerals are occasions for joy rather than sorrow. The
soul travels to Indra's heaven where life is as beautiful as in Bali,
as the saying goes, but without illness and without worry. So there
is reason to celebrate. Food is prepared, palm leaf offerings made,
and the funeral tower holding the body is decorated with the fan¬
ciest of coloured papers. Young men vie with one another to carry
the burden and as the flame touches the body, the orchestra strikes
a jubilant tune. Made Djate, a Balinese artist, has conveyed the
spirit of joyfulness in his drawing now engraved on a 19-inch high
vase with ornamental cover. Quite early in life Made Djate became
an apprentice in the art of making Wayang puppets for the tradi¬
tional shadow plays of Indonesia. (See "The Unesco Courier",
3-4, I 955; U.S. June). Today he draws from the daily life of Bali.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ASIAN ARTISTS (Continued)
Zl It
Tray of delights
Fruit, cakes and other delights are heaped around the elaborate
and indispensable coffee urn in "The Turkish Tray", a humorous,
semi-abstract rendition of a Turkish folk art motif. Now gracing
an elliptical form with ornamental stopper, it was engraved from
a drawing by versatile Turkish artist, Bedri Rahmi Eyuboglu, who
is professor at the Academy of Fine Arts in Istanbul. Bedri Rahmi,
as he calls himself, works in his studio over designs for textiles,
murals, ceramicsand in his spare time paints to his heart's content.
With his wife, Eren, an accomplished painter in her own right,
and others, he founded the "New Group" of Turkish painters.
Burmese royalty
Traditionally an object of veneration and a symbol of strength and
royalty, the elephant of Burma is an ancient theme for Burmese
designers and illustrators. In U Ohn Lwin's drawing for a covered
urn with ornamental finial, a member of the royal family of Burma
is seen riding a handsomely caparisoned elephant under an umbrella
held by a servant, while the oozie or driver sits in front. U Ohn
Lwin who studied art by himself, believes that water colour is the
truest Burmese style of art expression. No experimenter with
what the West calls "modern" art, he prefers tradition, to
record the life of his people and to be understood by them.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
The lone bamboo
"To learn to draw a bamboo, take a branch and cast its shadow on
a white wall on a moonlight night", wrote Küo Hai, the Chinese
landscape painter, almost a thousand years ago. Here, Ma Shou-
Hua, a distinguished Chinese administrator who turned to painting
for recreation and self-expression, has made a poetic interpretation
of the ancient Chinese theme, "The Lone Bamboo in All Its Grace¬
fulness". The bamboo is this artist's favourite subject. He has
observed its gracefulness in rain and shine, in wind and calm. He
has painted bamboo in groups and in groves; as a single tree, a
branch, a leaf. His works have been seen all over the world.
The eternal Eve
The design for "Eve", says the Egyptian artist, AI Hussein Fawzi,
springs from an ancient legend in which the eternal Eve pierces
with an arrow the heart of her beloved, flying above in the guise
of a hawk. In his illustration of this tragic tale, the delicately
modelled form of the woman, bow in hand, sits brooding beside
her victim in the light of the setting sun. Above, a flock of hawks
wings its way into the dusk. After graduation from the Cairo
Academy of Fine Arts and studies in Paris, AI Hussein Fawzi return¬
ed to Egypt in 1932 to become instructor of engraving at the Aca¬
demy of Fine Arts. His work is best known for its illustrative quality.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ASIAN ARTISTS (Continued)
Visvantara the unselfish-
The unselfishness of the Bodhisattva Visvantara in giving away his
wife is described in one of the Jataka stories, a series of charming
folk tales of the Buddha's deeds of charity and benevolence to all
creatures in his previous existences. (See "The Unesco Courier",
"Twenty-five centuries of Buddhist Art and Culture", June 1956;
U.S., August). Here, it is depicted by one of Asia's great artists,
George Keyt, a Sinhalese painter, poet and translator of his country's
classical literature. His murals on the life of Buddha in the Gotami
Vihara Temple near Colombo have been called "perhaps the
most outstanding contemporary expressions of Sinhalese painting."
Bodhisattva: a future Buddha
Engraved upon a crystal stele, this Bodhisattva is as graceful and
slender as its bronze prototype which was cast in the seventh century
and is still standing in the Horyuji Temple in Nara, Japan. The
Bodhisattva, a future Buddha on his way to enlightenment, has been
subtly drawn by Kiyoshi Saito, Japan's foremost contemporary
printmaker, who has emphasized the mysticism and gentleness of
the holy man's' meditation. Saito wandered among the temples of
Nara, sketching and drawing and then transposed his drawing of the
Bodhisattva upon wood, cut the block and pulled the print. He
used the grain of the wood to suggest the statue's age and fragility
1
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Gopis in the grove
Jamini Roy of India is a master in the realm of Asian art who,
since I 921, has devoted himself to the study of Hindu thought
and Bengal folk art. Here, he has illustrated one of the
stories of the Hindu god Krishna. The playful and capricious
Krishna had promised to dance with the gopis (milkmaids) of
Vrindavana, but on the night of the festival Krishna was
not to be found and though the gopis searched everywhere
the promised meeting was never fulfilled. (Jamini Roy has
given two works to the United Nations Children's Fund to
reproduce this year on its greetings cards. See page 32)
Fleet-footed gazelles
Running gazelles, woven into a continuous band of design,
form the motif chosen by Alfred Baccache of Syria for engrav¬
ing on crystal. His theme is one that is familiar to travellers
on the more remote highways of Syria who may sometimes
glimpse herds of the small, fleet animals. Here, flowing,
horizontal lines convey the fugitive grace of the animals in
flight. The charm of "Gazelles" is enhanced by its simplicity.
Although Alfred Baccache had no formal training in
the fine arts, he took to painting and sculpture so successfully
that he quickly made a name for himself in many countries.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
ASIAN ARTISTS (Continued)
JlM
A.,:;Mî?s. - .*^j \
(
m^Srá ' n*à\LmW
Jfluiâï» a1-1*1*-111- |:"' KlBl
l^v*? ' 3Eî.f-?A -v ' ^"»^M
fr > ' < ~&IS>V&¿' $.- : :<m *
**vln*^j§]0fità*> *'-ÀL.%^&\h
riitijor^. j^ffb^jnl
W ! f^- #h fM
W?GPm^-£v$i&ïï\im\\
wÈWWiî* A^mU''HÍU'M
^,#r:,,-**v -ÜpÜlta
Festival of Krishna and Radha
On festival days pilgrims from all parts of India flock to Matura
on the Jumna River, birthplace of the Hindu god Krishna
and scene of many stories about him and his beloved Radha.
Here, where the melody of the young Krishna's flute, plaintive
and tantalizing, was once heard across the fields, the people
honour him with dances, performances and processions.
This joyful occasion has been depicted by Rama Maharana,
who belongs to the caste of traditional painters of temple
murals. This artist, who lives near the sacred Indian city
of Puri, paints on canvas of hand-loomed sari cloth,
impregnated with tamarind seed paste and surfaced with chalk.
Harana in Manila
Anyone having a sweetheart in Manila may "harana", that is,
serenade the lady of his choice. Accompanied by a band of
musicians and an enthusiastic host of friends and accomplices,
the young man leads the serenade just as the sun is falling
into Manila Bay. The gay, romantic scene, drawn by Arturo
Rogerio Luz, a young Filipino artist, in a simple, semi-abstract,
angular style, has been engraved on a dome-shaped, I 1-inch
high stele. Arturo Luz says of his painting: "It is my desire
to combine the oriental and occidental elements that make
up the life around me, to find what makes that life unique,
and then to express it simply, in paint, line or watercolour."
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
When Europe styled itself the "Old World", it did so
for reasons of chronology: it had discovered and
occupied a land that was completely unknown.
But today there are people who use the phrase with an
entirely different connotation. The Old World to them is
an exhausted, worn-out continent which has run its
course and now stands crouched over its own tomb.
Meanwhile, facing it, a New World has arisen, full of
vigour, throbbing with vitality and of unlimited promise.
Neither Europe nor America form complete, homogen¬
eous blocs; each in fact is infinitely diversified. The
European continent, though small in size, is so composite
and so charged with history that it has been incapable of
forming a coherent whole. The difficulties encountered
by those favouring an integrated Europe make this
abundantly clear.
The New World too is a veritable mosaic. Within the
Anglo-Saxon, Spanish and Portuguese Americas there are
countless areas marked by French, Irish, Italian and Ger¬
man influences, to cite only a few, and overlooking for the
moment the role of the American Indians and the Negroes
of Africa. Furthermore, the problems dividing Latin
America and the United States are no less serious than
those which must be solved between the two sides of the
Atlantic. Culturally, the South American countries have
closer ties with the Iberian peninsula than with the United
States. It is this internal diversity within each of the two
worlds which renders a study of their similarities and
differences so difficult.
For many years, Europeans believed that America had
no history. Certain Americans it is true recent immi¬
grants not yet firmly rooted in their country of adoption
sometimes helped to strengthen that illusion. But that
period is past. Everywhere an effort is being made to
unroll the past, to unearth the civilizations of the pre-
Columbian eras. New York points to its kinship with New
Amsterdam, Mexico looks back to its ties with the Aztecs
and the Mayas, Brazil takes pride in the Baroque churches
of its colonial period...
The influence of European thought and European art
and religion on the New World makes a fascinating subject
for study. European culture, when transplanted abroad,
underwent many modifications in the course of time. It
developed its own peculiar characteristics, with some
notions exaggeratedly overdeveloped, others degenerating
quickly, and some merely adapted to the new environment.
Thus the American language has diverged from English,
Brazilian now reveals subtle differences with Portuguese,
while Romanticism in South America and the positivist
philosophy in Brazil or Chile are far removed from their
European models.
The literatures of the two Americas were once no more
than extensions of European literature; today they are
not only independent but, having reached maturity, are
inspiring certain literary trends in the Old World.
European architects, headed by Le Corbusier, have made
a by no means negligible contribution to architectural
development in the two Americas; now their ideas, trans¬
formed into new and original designs, are making their
way back to Europe.
Events such as these, though particularly striking today,
are in no way new. They have repeatedly occurred
throughout the centuries. But there is no need to exag¬
gerate their importance. Is there any real justification,
for instance, in saying (as some have in Brazil) that the
Baroque style was originally inspired by the tortuous roots
and branches of the vast Amazon forests? Nonetheless it
does remain true that an intellectual give-and-take
developed from the start between both sides of the
Atlantic, with the role of America becoming more sharply
defined as political and spiritual independence were pro¬
gressively achieved.
One of the most striking features of a number of Latin
American countries today is their determination to esta¬
blish the link between themselves and their pre-Colum¬
bian civilizations. It is a pity that so much of what these
civilizations once contained was destroyed by the Conquest.
Paul Rivet, the French authority on ancient American
civilizations, defends the thesis of an"Indo-Mediterranean
humanism" derived from a combination of European and
native cultures. Other authorities however, like Paulo
Carneiro of Brazil, believe that the current "return to the
past" is little more than a vogue of fashion and the cult
of the native a figment of modern imagination. Whoever
is right, there is no escaping the attachment of many
Latin American nations today to the roots of their
pre-Columbian past.
The New World is also growing increasingly aware of its
debt to Africa, even where racial prejudice and segregation
still persist.In certain countries (Brazil for example) the
problem of Negro-white relations seems practically solved.
Certainly no one can deny that the Negro has made his
contribution to America both during the slavery era and
since emancipation.
Then, too, there is the contribution which is quite
important in more than one region of the Americas of
inhabitants from China, Japan and the Near East. Thus
Europe cannot help but admit that it has no exclusive
claim to the settling of the American continent.
Between the Old and the New World relations are far
too often dominated by a complex of inferiority. Even
America does not escape this when it views Europe's
extraordinary contribution to civilization.
But the complex is at present greater on
the European side of the Atlantic. Europe
feels humiliated after the two wars which
ripped it asunder and which it could not
have brought to an end if indeed it really
Cont'd
next page
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
TWO WORLDS
FACE TO FACE
(Continued)
ended them without the intervention of America. Europe
also ponders the material aid which the United States has
given and continues to give it. Europe is alarmed at the
world's economic instability, by the growing industrial
power of the United States and its gigantic technical civi¬
lization... by certain trends in America which may ultim¬
ately result in a dangerous limitation of freedom to
thought and opinion.
Europe and even Latin America often accuse the United
States of inundating them with a low-type literature, with
a kind of pre-digested intellectual (or so-called intellec¬
tual) fare, commercialized films, and soulless mechanical
devices. In my opinion, we are
not wrong to defend ourselves
against things of this kind, but
we are often unjust in believing
that is all the United States
has to offer us.
We are unjust when we
ignore the spiritual and non-
material side of life in the
United States despite the fact
that it has been developing and
penetrating the nation in depth;
when we ignore the highly ori¬
ginal efforts which have led to
a renewal of art and literature
in that country. Why do we
keep looking only at what the
United States does in the
practical and technical sphere
and forget that there are large
numbers of scientists who de¬
vote their lives to nothing but
pure and disinterested res¬
earch activities?
Europe is also over-inclined
to neglect Latin America as
a whole, its efforts, its struggles
and its material and spiritual
achievements. ' How many of us
in Europe have even an inkling of the obstacles which the
painting, music and films of Mexico and Brazil had to
overcome before there was any response whatever from
the Old World? This is only one of many examples.
But the problem is by no means one-sided. Americans
do not find it easy to understand Europe. True, they
know our continent a little better as a result of the
contacts made during the last wars, the troops stationed
on our soil, the influx of tourists, our fashion trade, and
the increasing exchange of scholars, teachers and students
as well as the translation of representative works of
European thought. In addition, European emigration
which followed recent political events has contributed to
and even helped to inspire the new growth of intellectual
life in the New World.
Many Americans gladly point out that, despite certain
appearances to the contrary, Europe's influence in the
intellectual world is actually increasing. This is parti¬
cularly gratifying in view of the great numbers of Ameri¬
cans who believe, as I have already said, that Europe is
doomed to internal strife, decadence and probably death.
It is time America stopped believing as it has for so
long that Europe's role in the world,' is henceforth
reduced to that of former Greece, that is, a sort of
museum or library to be tapped at will but devoid of any
activity of its own. That is a role which Europe has never
accepted. America is only now beginning to recognize its
error of judgment. In reality, the Old World, politically
and materially weakened though it be, is more active
than it has ever been in the intellectual field. Its
creative powers remain unimpaired and its living con¬
tribution to contemporary civilization continues.
The New World;
' Is Europe doomed to
strife, decadence and
certain death?
The Old World:
'Do human values
take second place in
America ? '
The American side of the Atlantic also finds it hard
to understand Europe's intellectual torment. Its endless
searching and discussion is criticized readily as "Byzan¬
tine". In the eyes of some Americans, the Old World
seems like Byzantium arguing over the sex of the angels
while the enemy is hammering at its gates. And yet,
this desire for deep investigation, this inquisitiveness, is
the very essence of intellectual vigour.
These are but a few aspects selected at random from
amongst hundreds of others of the lack of comprehension
and the misunderstandings which separate the New from
the Old World, and in many instances the United States
from both Europe and Latin America.
Is such lack of comprehension inevitable? and is this
kind of misunderstanding irrefutable? The answer must
be "No", for it behoves thinkers and men of action alike
to work for the Old World and to reinforce the ties which
unite them.
But if this is to succeed, the exchange of ideas and
minds across the Atlantic must be a two-way bridge with
each continent offering the other the best and most
valuable elements it possesses. I am quite aware that
exchanges and cross-fertilization of this kind are fraught
with a terrible danger; they may well lead to dreary uni¬
formity. We already suffer from this in a number of
domains, and particularly in
architecture.
How much difference is there
between certain sections of
Montreal, New York or Rio de
Janeiro and the reconstructed
parts of some of the cities
devastated by the war, such as
Frankfort or Berlin? The
danger should not be under¬
estimated; it should be taken
seriously, for there is no doubt
it can be eliminated.
Despite the cries of certain
alarmists, the civilizations on
both shores of the Atlantic are
not diametrically opposed but
in fact complementary. They
are developing In the same
intellectual climate, condition¬
ed by Christianity which, in its
two branches and under the
influence of Greco-Roman cul¬
ture, has produced Western
civilization. This element is a
living force even for those who
deny any religious belief.
The American sociologist
Pitrim A. Sorokin, professor
at Harvard Unisersity, who began his career in Europe
and then continued it in America, and thus knows both
civilizations since he is a product of both, has laid great
stress on the points of convergence of the New and the
Old World. His conviction is that "'despite three or four
centuries of geographical separation, there has for a long
time been, and still is, only one culture, namely Western
or European-American culture, all the features of which
are identical on either continent. Being fundamentally
a single unit, this culture is as old on one continent as it
is on the other; it is no younger in America than it is
in Europe. For the same reason, it evolved in either
place in the same direction, passing through the same
phases and developing the same trends."
Moreover, the problem of intellectual relations trans¬
cends the boundaries of the two continents. Qur
Western civilization cannot be isolated from the rest of
the world. It must form an integral part of a community
in which each nation contributes its original share to a
new humanism of tomorrow, so that each element is
subtle and differentiated to reflect the universe itself.
A provocative volume, "The Old and the New World" has just been
published by unesco in its series Unity and Diversity o] Cultures (price:
$4.00; 21/-; 1,000 francs). It contains the addresses and discussions of two
International Forums organized by UNESCO in 1954 in Geneva and Sao Paulo
during which scholars discussed the cultural and moral relations between
Europe and the New World. The above text is an edited and abridged
version oí the address by Mr. Babel, chairman oi the International Forum
committee of Geneva.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
OUT, OUT,
DAMNED SPOT !
What did people do in the
days of no dry-cleaning ?
by Anna Sommer Lenn
Drawings by Ulrich
Copyright Unesco Courrier
You, when you read of the blue
and white habiliments of me¬
diaeval pages, may conjure up a
vision of castles, crusades and pale
ladies in peaked hats. The slashed
satins and gorgeous brocades of the
Renaissance no doubt put you in mind
of Leonardo, Lorenzo, and black¬
hearted Borgias. Powdered dandies
and belles in sky-blue taffeta and
apple-green velvet probably send you
into a reverie of Revolutions.
Not me. As a practical housewife
and any woman who is the single-
handed chatelaine of a 7-room house
and a family of 4, has to be either
practical or a drudge I behold in my
mind's eye something else. Spots
from a venison pasty on a knightly
tunic. Gravy from a roast pheasant
on a Medici bosom, or, ugh, brown
driblets from the newly fashionable
cup of chocolate on an 18th century
waistcoat or hooped skirt. I see
velvet trains rustling over stone
floors strewn with rushes and greasy
bones from the last meal; the pea¬
cock-blue satin shoes of 15th century
Venice treading on slimy cobble¬
stones; champagne-coloured knee
breeches stained by saddle leather.
Od's Bodikins, what did they do in the
days of no dry-cleaning?
Granted that other eras were not
so fastidious as ours, that perfumes
masked body odours, that sewage
stood in the open streets, and privies
were noisome holes. You can picture
the gentry of these periods wearing
undergarments unclean because not
seen, but can you imagine the cele¬
brated Duchess Isa¬
bella d'Esté dancing
in a spotty gown, or
Sir Walter Raleigh
discarding his cloak
because it was fouled?
Cont'd
next page
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Out, damned spot
(Continued) Ancients had secret of soapless detergents
Clothes were not easily come by,
even among the wealthy. All stuffs
were hand-loomed until 1787. Weeks,
often months, of handwork went into
the making of a garment of quality.
Lucrezia Borgia had a dress that cost
15,000 ducats. Gentlemen of the court
of the French king, Charles IX, dressed
in hose costing £60 to £100 the pair.
Clothes like these were not thrown
away like paper napkins. On the con¬
trary, festive robes and mantles were
often passed on from parent to youth.
Ergo, visible and disfiguring soil
must have been attacked in some way.
How? The question does not seem to
have plagued the writers of books on
costume, the history of dress, decora¬
tive arts, modes and manners, house¬
hold arts, almanacs, books of curious
facts and where else would you have
looked? I read through several li¬
brary shelves of this material without
discovering a clue. The encyclopaedias
offered some information after you
found the spoor, but they had nothing
so direct as "Spots and Stains anti¬
que methods of removing," or "Clean¬
ing Clothes history of."
I consulted the Curator of Decora¬
tive Arts of a large and famous
western museum, noted for its collec
tion of costumes of bygone eras. The
Curator confessed the question had
never kept her awake at night and
said she could not help me. I popped
in and out of dry-cleaning shops. A
few proprietors were aware of the
fact that their trade dated from the
first half of the 19th century, but could
tell me no more. I wrote to the Na¬
tional Institute of Dry Cleaning.
"For years we have been looking for
answers to the questions you propound,
but have found very little," replied the
Institute. "See if you can find some
old-time recipe books."
'Witch's brew' of cleansers
The first disclosures came to light
among formulas for 12-egg cakes
and how to dye Grandma's me¬
rino shawl, in such yellowed volumes
as Wright's "Book of 3,000 Practical
Recipes" (1840-1850), Thomas Love's
"Practical Dyer and Scourer" (1852),
and Youman's "Handbook of House¬
hold Sciences" (1866).
Next I turned to San Francisco's
Sutro Library with its rare collection
of genealogical books and papers. It
was the first time the library ever had
had a request on this subject, and its
librarians went to work like blood¬
hounds on fresh scent. One library
sleuth discovered the existence of "a
profitable boke declaring dyvers ap-
prooved remedies to take out spottes
and stains. Taken out of Dutche and
by L. Mascall, 1583." More
facts, buried in two century-old diction¬
aries of antiquities, were unearthed by
San Francisco's Public Library.
In time I had a list of cleansing
agents used by peoples from the an¬
cient Egyptians to the Victorians, a list
that sounds like a veritable witch's
brew. Not eye of newt or toe of frog,
but ox gall, soapwort, hollow bones,
decomposed urine, pig dung, sheep ma¬
nure, egg yolk, boiling milk, spring
water, nitre (saltpetre) hot bran, fuller's
earth, cowherb, gum arabic, honey,
logwood chips, soap berry, soap bark,
potash, pearlash, bean meal, Paris
White or French chalk, barley leaven
and glue water. These were the spot
removers, detergents, water softeners,
and dirt solvents of our ancestors!
When Caesar's wife decided her lord's
second best yellow woollen toga was too
soiled to wear to the Forum that day,
she would dispatch it to a fullery or
fullonica, the clothes cleaning esta-
olishment of ancient times. Here the
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
garments were trodden by the feet of
fullones (fullers or laundrymen), stand¬
ing in vats of water-alkali mixture.
The cheapest and most widely used
laundry alkali was the decomposed
urine of men and of animals, an in¬
gredient which had a soapy effect on
dirty woollens. So necessary was urine
to the Roman way of life and to
the laundering of the universally
worn woollens, that vessels ' for its
collection stood on almost every street
corner. Down the centuries this un¬
appetising cleanser was used ; as late
as 1799 we read of it as "old lant",
collected by servants in England.
Fuller's earth, of which there are
numerous varieties, derives its name
from the fullers who used the powdery
clays to absorb grease and grime from
clothes. Pliny recommended that clo¬
thes be washed in the Sardinian variety
of Fuller's earth. The Greeks favour¬
ed such earths as Cimolite, and those
from Selinus and Chios. After the
scouring process, the clothes of the
ancients were often brushed and card¬
ed with the skin of a hedgehog, or
with thistle plants, to raise the nap.
In Biblical times a fuller's field was
located outside the wall of Jerusalem
where cleaned garments were spread
to dry after being washed in copper
tubs. ("For he is like a refiner's fire,
and like fuller's soap."Mai. 3.2; "And
his raiment :.-;came shining, exceeding
white as snow; so as no fuller on earth
can white them" Mark 9.3).
Englai. . for centuries had the
. world's largest supply of fuller's earth
in its Cretaceous beds (chalk depo
sits). When Henry VIII's damask sur-
coat became too encrusted by his ar¬
dours as a trencherman, a Palace
servant would rub the cleansing earth
into the spots. Shakespeare, in his
play about old Hank, mentions fullers
(1.2.33) who have since joined the lim¬
bo with such artisans as fletchers (bow
makers), wainwrights (waggon builders)
and sawyers (sawers of timber).
Centuries before the advent of auto¬
matic dish washers and washing ma¬
chines, the ancients had the secret of
soapless detergents. In every country
from Egypt of the Rameses to the
lands of the Incas and from China to
France, there grew members of a fa¬
mily of "soap" plants. The roots or
bark or berries of these plants exuded
a mucilaginous liquid which produced
a lather in water.
Gudewyfe used Bouncing Bet
In these natural detergents, the most
delicate silks could be washed with¬
out damaging the material or
mingling the dyes. Egypt had soaproot
(gypsophylia struthium) ; Spain, the
so-called Spanish soaproot. China had
soapberry which is still used today for
laundering among the poorer classes;
the West Indies had shagbark or soap-
bark. In Mexico the Indians used a
soap root which is still found as far
north as California and Colorado. In
the countries of Europe, soapwort, also
known as fuller's herb or (in England)
Bouncing Bet, was the most commonly
used member of the saponin family.
Soapwort (saponaria officinalis) was
a pinkish herb that grew wild by every
European roadside, in thickets, and by
the banks of streams. As far back as
the Middle Ages, the Gudewyfe used
an extract of Bouncing Bet's leaves
and roots to cleanse grease spots from
woollens, linens and cottons. In the
Castle they used it on the silks and
velvets that came from the Orient.
As clothes became more intricate
in cut, design, and ornamentation,
housewives found it expedient to
rip them fuily apart for a thorough
dunking in soapwort lather. Section by
section, each garment was cleaned, and
the sections laboriously pinned to fin¬
ishing boards, so that shrinkage and
loss of shape could be held to a mi¬
nimum. The drying of the pinned
sections was hastened by rubbing
with clean cotton cloths, or by placing
the pinned sections in a hot stove
room. Later the sections were stitched
together again by hand. (No sewing
machines until 1841 !)
The dust and mud of horseback tra¬
vel in, say, Chaucer's time, were treat¬
ed by first allowing the garments to
dry on the immemorial clothesline.
They were then vigorously beaten
with a smooth stick or "beetle," the
name of the mediaeval pestle or paddle
board with which women pounded
linens on the banks of steams. After
that, the housewife went to work on
the garments with the detergent of
her choice Bouncing
Bet, urine, or perhaps
nitre. The use of nitre
as a cleanser is men¬
tioned by Pliny and
in the Old Testament.
Cont'd
next page
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
OUT, DAMNED SPOT!
(Continued)
"For though thou wash thee with
nitre and take thee much soap, yet
thine iniquity is marked before me,
saith the Lord God." (Jer. 2.22.)
Another old-time antidote for dirt
was ox gall, the actual bile of a
bullock, mixed with boiling water.
This was considered fine for grease,
particularly the axle and waggon
grease that begrimed clothing as civi¬
lization took to carriages. Garments
were sponged with ox gall solution,
then with spring water. They were
then treated with "glue water"' and
dried before a fire. "'Glue water," no
doubt, acted as starch or sizing, to
restore body and texture to the ma¬
terial. Honey and gum arabic seem
to have served the same purpose.
After spots were removed with ox
gall solution, fine, damp sand was
beaten into the cloth, followed by a
good stiff brushing. Two or three
drops of olive oil on a soft brush were
often passed over the fabric to bring
back the lustre.
Still another approved remedy for
dirty woollens was a strong solution
of logwood chips in water, with a
small quantity of gum arabic. The
logwood chips acted as detergent, and
the gum arabic as sizing. The gar¬
ment was dried in the shade and
brushed in the direction of the nap.
Hot bran, rubbed or brushed into
furs, was a time-honoured way of
cleaning the skins of animals, the
heated particles being grease-absorb¬
ent. Warm pig dung and fresh sheep
manure were prized as spot removers
20
even as late as the early 19th century.
From the Dark Ages until Victorian
times, the housewife tackled dirty
clothes via yet another method:
"bucking," a mediaeval term derived
from (1) the beech tree which produc¬
ed a desirable wood ash or lye for
laundering purposes, and (2) from
"bouken," akin to Low German "bue-
ken," i.e. to soak, steep or boil in lye
or suds. Linens were soaked in a
simple solution of lye from beech or
fir ashes, hollow bones, and boiling
water. The garments were then rins¬
ed, soaked again, then spread flat to
bleach in the sun.
Oxgall and soapwort were out
The ubiquitous Pliny also gives us
an early history of soap. "Sapo,"
he relates, was a Gallic inven¬
tion, introduced to the Romans by the
conquering Gauls and Germanic
tribes. It was a soft concoction of
goat's tallow and causticized wood
ashes or potash ("pot" for the iron pot
in which the ash was evaporated).
Pliny was evidently not aware that
the Phoenicians, Egyptians, and
other Biblical peoples, knew diverse
forms of soap. The soaps of the Old
Testament were a crude substance
compounded by fullers from vegetable
alkalis, while the Egyptians combined
Trona, their native soda which is a
cousin of California borax, with ve¬
getable oils or tallow. The Greek
physician Galen, of the second cent
ury, wrote of soap as a specific for
certain ailments.
However, as late as the Middle Ages,
soap was strictly a luxury item, used
sparingly by persons of wealth as a
cosmetic (in Pliny's time chiefly as
a hair pomade) or as a medicament.
Not until the 16th century was soap
widely used for general cleansing and
scouring. By that time it had been
discovered that soap could be hard¬
ened by treatment with salt. For
centuries it was moulded in a spheri¬
cal shape rather than in the flat bars
of today, and for most of those cen¬
turies, it had a strong animal smell.
Until the early 19th century, the mak¬
ing of soap was still a household task.
In the early 1800's, scientists like
Michael Faraday in England, and
Karl Reichenbach in Germany, blew
the whistle on soapwort, pig's dung,
fuller's earth, urine, ox gall and simi¬
lar cleansing agents.
Experimenting with coal-tar (Fara¬
day) and petroleum (Reichenbach),
they rang in the era of cleansing with
naphthas. Dry cleaning is said to
have been born when a careless serv¬
ing maid upset a turpentine lamp on
a table cloth which became miracu¬
lously bright and clean. The first
dry-cleaning ("nettoyage à sec") es¬
tablishment was opened in 1845 in
France by a M. Jolly Belin.
Not long thereafter the bell tolled
for Liebig's classic pronouncement: a
civilization is measured by the amount
of soap it uses. Dry-cleaning super¬
seded soap as the yardstick.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
OBESITY: A SLOW FORM OF SUICIDE
by Gerald Wendt
Thin people are much more numerous than 'fat
ones. Undernourishment is still a world prob¬
lem ; overeating is not at least not yet. But
conditions are changing. The U.N. Food and Agri¬
culture Organization has reported a marked increase
in the world's food production in recent years.
As the prosperity of the underdeveloped lands im¬
proves, life will be easier, sedentary occupations will
increase, and many people will attain that "mark of
wellbeing", an ample girth. The jolly fat man has
always been a popular figure. Less admired, but more
envied are the well-fed businessman, the rotund
potentate, the successful politician. In the Western
world especially, they have long been symbols not
only of wealth but of health.
It is true that undernourishment and malnutrition
are the real penalty of poverty. They bring on many
serious diseases, such as tuberculosis, which thrive on
weak and wasted bodies. It is also true that 'tubercu¬
losis is only one-fifth as common among overweight
people as among those of normal weight. Further¬
more, the suicide rate is much less among fat folk.
Nevertheless, being too fat and heavy is itself a slow
form of suicide, for the death rate is far higher
among fat people than among lean. They are four
times as likely to die of diabetes and their death rate
from inflammation of the kidneys, or Bright's disease
(chronic nephritis), apoplexy (cerebral hemorrhage)
and heart failure (coronary disease), is about twice
the normal. Accurate life insurance statistics in the
United States show that with as little as 10 percent
overweight the mortality raté is 20 percent higher
at 20 percent overweight it is more than 40 percent
higher ; and at 25 percent the mortality rate is nearly
75 percent higher than normal.
Medieval 'central-heating'big meals
Put in another way, and less accurately ; out of
ten lean men at the age of 30, eight will reach
the age of 60, five will reach 70 and three will
survive to the age of 80. But if the ten men are fat
at the age of 30, only six will reach 60, three will
reach 70 and one may reach 80.
What is the cause of overweight ? The answer is
simple : eating too much. Every ounce of weight has
entered through the mouth. Overeating is, quite sim¬
ply, putting more fuel into the mouth than the body
uses for energy. The excess food above the energy
need is inevitably stored as fat. The body has no
means of rejecting the excess once it has entered
the mouth. If overweight is to be avoided it must be
done before that pointby good sense.
This is neither as simple nor as easy as it sounds.
There is first the question of how much food is too
much. This differs for different people because it
depends on how much food is needed for energy pro¬
duction. It is easier to overeat in the tropics than
in a cold climate because in cold weather much food
is burned just to keep the body warm. The meals of
medieval days in Europe were enormous because the
houses were always cold. Everywhere meals should
be lighter in summer than in winter for this reason.
People who move from cool countries to hot ones
easily grow fat unless they reduce their food intake.
Even more important is the amount of work done.
Hard physical labour requires energy, which can be
obtained only from food. A labourer in the fields or
in industry may eat twice or even three times as
much as an office worker without growing fat. But
when he grows too old for work, his weight increases
rapidly unless he also changes his eating habits.
In the cities the young athlete can eat well but
when he stops his exercise he should reduce his diet
too, since from the body's point of view exercise is
work. For this reason the man or woman who does
no manual work and yet has an appetite for good
eating should maintain a schedule of physical exer¬
cise to counteract and use up the excessive food. In
one sense this is automatic because the heavy person
gets exercise just by carrying and propelling the
excess weight. One who weighs 200 pounds does twice
as much work in climbing a flight of stairs or a hill,
for instance, as one who weighs only 100 pounds.
This sets some limitation on the ultimate gain in
weight. But it is usually wiser and healthier to take
pleasant exercise at a normal weight than to do the
enforced labour of carrying 100 pounds of unne¬
cessary weight wherever one goes. This is only the
first penalty of overeating. It is followed by a se¬
vere strain on the heart and often by heart failure.
Pregnant women 'eat for two'
There is thus no absolute answer to the question
of how much food is too much. It depends on
the activity of the person. But whenever one's
body weight rises above normal there is no escaping
the verdict that one is eating too much. For in¬
stance, pregnant women often eat far more than they
need to in the thought that they must feed the de¬
veloping infant too. This is true but it is balanced
by the fact that the pregnant woman usually greatly
reduces her work or exercise. Thus she gains far
more weight than is accounted for by the infant. As
always, such gain in weight indicates overeating.
There remains the question as to why people
overeat. More is involved than just good sense and
more than just hunger too. It is a matter of conti¬
nuing appetite after hunger is satisfied. Dr. Jean
Mayer of the School of Public Health at Harvard
University (USA) and the son of a famous French
physiologist has recently discussed several causes.
Neurotics need to nibble
One cause is certainly hereditary, for there are
many strains of domestic animals which are bred
and grown because their appetite is never satis¬
fied and they grow fat. Another cause is the result of
an injury of some sort. Overeating results in some ani¬
mals upon the removal of two small centres in the
mid-brain. A certain type of tumour in the pituitary
gland also causes obesity in mice. Both hormonal
treatments and castration are known to cause obesity.
But in human beings it is more often psychic
injury. A sudden insecuritylor the removal of a
long-standing insecurity may be connected with the
beginning or the ending of overeating. To forget
their troubles some neurotics are as addicted to eating
as others are to alcohol. Often the nibbling of sweets
between meals is due to nervous tension.
But the major cause is environmental or social.
The availability of ample food after years of priva¬
tion is a strong psychological temptation, especially
when it is prominently displayed and advertised.
Finally, there is the esteem in which overweight per¬
sons are held in many lands on the outmoded and
false idea that fat is a mark of health and success
in life. Not so, say the scientists and the physicians,
obesity is a major malady of civilization.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
IN building up its new educational system during the last
century, India copied the universities of the V/est,
especially the newer universities of Britain. India's
universities have multiplied and new ones are still being
founded. Critics of education have pointed out their
obvious faults. Nevertheless they have served the nation.
From them have come the political leaders who won India's
freedom, the administrators who conduct the country's
affairs in a modern way, and some of the businessmen
who are transforming it economically.
During the same time India developed one eminent
institution which v/as quite distinct from all these others,
and which, though also borrowing from the West, is
particularly Indian. This is Visva-Bharati, known more
familiarly as Santiniketan, or the Abode of Peace.
Santiniketan, which is not far from Calcutta, was created
by the Tagores, that remarkable mercantile family of
Bengal in which for more than a century great wealth and
great artistic and intellectual eminence have gone side by
side. The school at Santiniketan which was to grow into
the university of today was founded in 1863 by the father
of Rabindranath the poet. But it was Rabindranath
himself who created it as it has existed in our day.
By its very nature Santiniketan is a criticism of the
orthodox Indian universities. It is a protest against their
size, against their soullessness, against the ugliness of many
of their buildings, against the gradual falling away from
the old invaluable Indian tradition of the devoted
relationship of pupil and teacher. Rabindranath Tagore
regarded education as an art, and also he thought that
education proceeds best through art and through religion
as understood by the poet and the artist.
The guiding principle of Santiniketan is described in a
celebrated pronouncement by Rabindranath. "The
highest education", he wrote, "is that which does
not merely give us information but makes our life in
harmony with all existence... Let us have access to the
life that goes beyond death and rises above all circum-
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
stances, let us find our God, let us live for that ultimate
truth which emancipates us from the bondage of the dust
and gives us the wealth, not of things but of inner light,
not of power but of love."
At Santiniketan, all the subjects which were taught in
the Western-style universities could be studied but the
method of study was to be Indian, or at least Indian as
interpreted by Rabindranath Tagore. The lecture room
and the examination hall did not dominate; instead the
teacher taught the pupil through a personal relation. The
imagination was cultivated as well as criticism. And in
addition many subjects not taught in the Western-style
universities were offered at Santiniketan, among them
Indian dancing and music and contemporary Indian poetry.
The result, it was claimed, was a better balanced per¬
sonality. Those educated at Santiniketan felt themselves
nurtured in an Indian
tradition through a live,
developing tradition, not
an ossified one and they
did not suffer the same
sense of cultural expatria¬
tion as did some of the
graduates of Allahabad or
Madras or Bombay.
Reading Tagore on
education it is impossible
not to be reminded again
and again of Plato ; and
walking through Santini¬
ketan it is easy to feel that
one is visiting an academy
not of the modern world
but of Periclean, Athens.
In Santiniketan there is the
same mixture of humanism
and theism as in Plato ;
there is the combined
worship of beauty and
exactness of thought. The
dominant impressions
which the visitor brings
away are of an elegance
alike of spirit and of exter¬
nals, of simplicity, of
decent and graceful leisure,
and of abundant youth,
but youth which is any¬
thing but raw or callow.
Some visitors have of
course felt that such an institution was too precious for
the strenuous and earthy contemporary India, with all its
urgent problems of social and economic reform. Perhaps
in its earlier days the criticism was partly fair. Even
Gandhi was inclined to share the doubt. But Santiniketan
has moved with the times and has been adaptable. That
is a sign of its strength. Rabindranath Tagore, who had
resided continuously in the institution during his declining
years and who, with his magnificent head, dress, and
manner of speech and movement, was in those days one
of the most impressive sights which India could offer died
during the war.
Soon after India became independent, Santiniketan was
reorganized. It has been incorporated as a statutory full-
fledged university, with a much wider curriculum, offering
courses to meet the needs of the new India. But em¬
phatically it has not lost its special nature, or become a
replica of other universities. It has preserved its auto¬
nomy, its traditions, its spirit, and its special customs,
its insistence on the living personal relation of teachers
Saruinikecan University
TEACHER AND FRIENDS: Education at Santiniketan is not
based on the principle that a university is a hierarchy, but on
the view that student and teacher should live in relations of
companionship and common dedication to their ideals. Lecture
room and examination hall do not dominate in this university.
The Unesco Courier
and pupils, its cultivation of the harmonious corporate life.
Today Santiniketan is at once school, university, research
institution, and international centre. The school is co¬
educational; boys and girls live in separate hotels but share
the same class-rooms, kitchens and playgrounds. In the
university, nearly all the ordinary subjects may be studied;
but, following a tradition established by Rabindranath,
students are encouraged to combine "light-bearing"
subjects those inviting study for their own sake with
"fruit-bearing ones" those which have practical use¬
fulness. "Fruit-bearing" is very much in the centre of
the research programme of the institution. At the
neighbouring centre Sriniketan, some of the most stimulat¬
ing work in modern India has been done on the sociology
of peasant life and on methods of rural education. The
man or woman who obtains part of his education in the
College of Music and
Dance is urged in due
course to move over to
Sriniketan and study his
countrymen working at
their humbler tasks.
Because of its inter¬
national reputation, San¬
tiniketan soon attracted
scholars from the outside
world. It became, and
has remained, one of the
most cosmopolitan places
in Asia. This has been
reflected in journals and
annals which are pub¬
lished by the institution.
What can Santiniketan
give to India, and to the
world, in the corning
decades? Perhaps it will
serve best by continuing
to proclaim the same
principles as in the past
especially the principle
that a university is not a
hierarchy, and that student
and teacher should live
not in relations of sub¬
ordination but of com¬
panionship and common
dedication to their ideals.
If Santiniketan continues
steadfast to this, it wi 1 do
much. But nohealthy institution stands still. Santiniketan
will inevitably grow and change. One of its most interesting
ventures at the moment is the systematic training of
teachers intended for the villages. More will probably
be heard of this in the future; it is a development which
would certainly have delighted Rabindranath Tagore's
friend, Mahatma Gandhi.
In the twentieth century world of volcanic upheavals,
Santiniketan has remained true to its name. It is an abode
of peace. Its Chancellor, Jawaharlal Nehru, has declared
the resolve of his Government that everything shall be done
to enable it to grow and prosper according to its own
nature. "I have Santiniketan very much in my mind",
he said recently, "and feel that it is our national duty which
Rabindranath Tagore entrusted to all of us to make it
possible for this institution to prosper." Scholars outside
India share Mr. Nehru's feeling, and some may be inclined
to add that the responsibility for Santiniketan's welfare has
now become a world-wide one which they would have
great pride in undertaking.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE SICILIAN CARRETTO
by Lucio Attinelli
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Photos Copyright Attinelli
3R
On a return visit to Sicily recently,
after a long absence, I found myself
looking at everything on the island
with a new eye. Things which had
once been so much a part of my
everyday life that I hardly noticed them now
struck me with astonishment.
Among them was a vehicle which in any
other place would hardly attract a second
glance the cart of the peasant farmer. But
in Sicily the farm cart, the carretto, adorned
with beautiful paintings and carved decora¬
tions would make any visitor stand and
stare.
With its brilliant colours and rich carvings
it suggests an object fit for festivities and
religious occasions in the countryside. These
carts however, are used day in day out by the
Sicilian carritteri (carters) for the lowliest
tasks carrying fruit and vegetables, trans¬
porting pottery and building materials and
even manure.
For such humble work the cart has
obviously no need of the rich and very
expensive decorations which embellish it.
Colourful, lively and extraordinarily forceful
in their simplicity the decorations, are the
SYMPHONY IN COLOUR
composed of carvings, paint¬
ings and ornamental designs
covers entire surface of the
"carretto" giving it the appear¬
ance of a vehicle reserved for
ceremonies and processions.
But these festive-looking carts
are used for everyday trans¬
port along the twisting stony
roads of the Sicilian mountains.
expression of a genuine folk art for. which the
cart itself is simply a convenient canvas.
Designed to be pulled by a single horse, the
Sicilian cart differs little in construction from
other carts, apart from its exceptionally large
wheels (about 55 inches in diameter).
The unusual size of the wheels is dictated
by the character of Sicilian roads which twist
and turn along the coastline or. up steep
mountain slopes. Often stony and almost
impracticable, the roads were once the links
between the main towns on the island. Even
today there are paths that only the carretto
can safely take, adapted as it is to any type of
ground by its particularly strong construction.
The carretto consists of the cascia or body,
resting on the fusu or. axle-tree, which is
strong enough to stand up to anything. The
vehicle is easy to manoeuvre and can take any
turning or even swing right round in its own
length. Each cart is unique, made specially
to order according to the needs and tastes of
the purchaser.
The carts are built by a small team of spe¬
cialized craftsmen: the master carradore, who
selects and works the wood; the firraru, or
smith, who makes the metal parts, working
them with real artistry in designs of rabischi
The Unesco Courier
(arabesques) in which an Arab influence is to
be seen; and the master-painter, who decor¬
ates the panels and signs the finished work.
Little is known about the origins of the
carretto or whether it was exactly the same,
in olden times, as it is today. Writers may
deliberately have said nothing about it because
they looked on it as a product of folk art and
of only minor interest.
According to the Sicilian historian, G. Pitre,
however, there is a document at the Univer¬
sity of Palermo, approved by King Frederick II
in 1330, which contains a description of a
carretto of the period which is similar in
many respects to the vehicle of today.
A French traveller, Elisée Reclus, writing
an account of Sicily in 1865, referred to the
carretto and said it might almost be regarded
as a work of art, when compared with French
carts. A few years later, in 1881, the muni¬
cipal authorities at Palermo were officially
invited to send a carretto to the Milan Trade
Fair as an example of Sicilian craftsmanship.
This made such an impression that Sicilian
cart builders received orders from as far afield
as America.
The most interesting thing about the
carretto is its de¬
coration an ex¬
traordinary prof¬
usion of carvings,
paintings and or¬
namental designs
covering the en¬
tire surface of the
vehicle with a
symphony of co¬
lour- The paint¬
ing and carving is
done by crafts¬
men who have
never studied
drawing or de¬
sign; their art is
thus untutored
but entirely spon¬
taneous and free
from the shackles
of convention.
Very often, the anonymous craftsman who
does the unsigned carving is the master
woodworker, or carradore, who, to lighten the
vehicle, rapidly chisels designs in high or low
relief, and though the artisan does not set out
to produce a work of art the result is remark¬
able, and unexpectedly expressive.
There is a strong resemblance between the
style of these carvings and the distinctive type
of architecture which reached its apogee in
Sicily about the twelfth century. This style
is a fusion of apparently incompatible archi¬
tectural formsByzantine (585 to 826 A.D.) ;
Arab (826 to 1060) and finally Norman,
brought in with the conquest of Sicily by
Roger de Hauteville in 1089. The style finally
came to be known as "Arabo-Norman" or
"Siculo-Norman."
The panels of the carretto are adorned with
paintings about whose origins little is known,
except that they go back far into the past.
The style of the pictures and the manner of
their painting are simple and direct. The
artists seek to produce their effects without
worrying too much about pers¬
pective, but the details of their
paintings are always extremely
precise.
The paints used are in bright,
Copyright Attinelli
Cont'd
next page
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Sicilian
'carretto'
(Continued)
BY WINGED HORSE TO THE
MOON: Heroic legends and tales of
chivalry provide many subjects for
decorative designs on Sicilian carts.
Right, Astolfo, a character from the
epic "Orlando Furioso", written by the
Italian poet, Ludovico Ariosto and
published in 1516. Painting (right)
illustrates episode in which Astolfo flies
to the moon on his winged horse.
Below, subjects Tor wheel decorations
include fruit, flowers, signs of the Zo¬
diac and one of the knights of Roland.
contrasting tones. The primary colours red, blue
and yellow nearly always predominate and the effect
of the whole decoration is one of striking vividness
and beauty.
The source from which the subjects of the pictures
are drawn is another surprise. The main themes are
the heroic legends of Charlemagne's knights and the
tales of chivalry, in particular, the Chanson de
Roland, the Paladins of France, the Knights of the
Round Table and other epics of the Middle Ages.
The Sicilian people are so attached to these legends
that even today some streets and certain places in the
vicinity of Palermo still bear names taken straight
from the tales of chivalry. Here, a headland is nam¬
ed after Roland, there both a mountain and a river
bear the name of Oliver; elsewhere a castle and a
village are called "Montauban"; in Palermo itself
Ass?=sora:o Turismo. Palermo
Copyright Rico
there are streets named after. "Argante" and "Guer-
rin," and there is also a "Court of the Paladins."
That the tales of chivalry are so well and widely
known in Sicily probably owes something to the
wandering Sicilian troubadours, the Cantastorie whose
tradition is still alive, especially in the villages of the
interior. To enhance the tales they told, the trouba¬
dours illustrated these legends with crude paintings
depicting the principal characters and scenes in a
kaleidoscopic profusion of bright colours.
The paintings on the carretto inevitably suggest a
connexion with these illustrations, and it is likely that
the Sicilian peasants, enamoured as they were of the
tales of chivalry, liked to have them reproduced on the
panels of their carts which were part of the very
fabric of their lives.
This form of folk art, the techniques and secrets of
which are handed down from father to son, is still as
vital and as fresh as ever- A recent dramatic event
has given proof of this, for lately carts have even been
produced with paintings showing scenes from the life
and adventures of Sicily's bandit, Salvatore Giuliano !
Music of bronze axles
tuned to peasant songs
Strange as it may seem, the Sicilian carretto also
provides an unexpected example of the islanders'
pervading love of... music. The axle bearings are
not made of iron or steel but are cast in a grade of
bronze ordinarily used for bells. Although they are
thus more expensive and do not last as long as other
bearings, the Sicilian farmer prefers them since the
turning wheels produce a pleasant metallic sound
which provides an accompaniment to their nostalgic
songs. The songs, too, are evidence of the tenacity of
Sicilian tradition, for they are directly derived from
the funeral elegies or "plan" of the ancient Provençal
troubadours.
Today the motor car has almost "honked" the
carretto out of existence. But the cart itself is only
one aspect of the artistic temperament of the Sicilian
people. Their folk art remains a moving force, rich
in energy and vitality which will surely find outlets in
other forms we may little foresee today.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
VIEWPOINT ON
BUDDHIST ART
by Grégoire Frumkin
Many comments have reached us following
the publication of the June issue on "Twenty-
five centuries of Buddhist art and culture"
(U.S. August). Amongst the points raised,
perhaps the most interesting are those of M.
Grégoire Frumkin, a Swiss scholar from Ge¬
neva, whose views on the Greek, Roman
and Indian influence in Buddhist art clarify
the differences which still exist amongst
art historians on this controversial subject.
Our readers, we feel sure, will find
Mr. Frumkin's remarks highly stimulating.
Afghanistan has been called "the crossroads of civi¬
lization". Its role in spreading Buddhist art has
also made it a crossroads of conflicting interpreta¬
tions or theories and of preconceived ideas at times
tainted by nationalistic bias. In the controversies which
have raged, one school has exalted the role of Greece and
Rome, others that of India.
The issue may seem clearer if we attempt to distinguish
between the following points: on the one hand the origin
of Buddhism, the role of Buddhism and the dissemination
of Buddhism; and on the other hand the origin of
Buddhist art, the origin of images of Buddha, and the
spread of Buddhist art.
There can be no denying the Indian origin of Buddhism.
Emerging in India in the 6th century B.C., it vanished
from that land by the end of the 12th century under the
impact of Islam and the prolific growth of Hinduism.
Its essence, however, still survives in the concept of spi¬
rituality through poverty, in the respect shown for human
and animal life, and in the idea of non-violence, all of
which have endured through the ages to find their 20th
century expression in the teachings of Gandhi.
The Western reader should
remember that the moral pre¬
cepts of Buddha (c. 560-480 B.C.
which made him a contempo¬
rary of Confucius, Lao-Tse, the
Hebrew prophets of the Baby¬
lonian captivity, Pythagoras,
Heraclitus and Solon), were
to become the heritage of a
large part of humanity. Earlier,
by five centuries, than the Ser¬
mon on the Mount, his medita¬
tions on the existence, origins
and removal of suffering, led to
the glorification of pity, of
charity towards others and of
universal brotherhood. Asia's
history shows how often Bud¬
dhism had a beneficent in¬
fluence on the mentality of
barbaric peoples. Bound up
as they are not to say enslav¬
ed by material progress, West¬
erners cannot hope to under¬
stand Ihe Asian peoples without
a knowledge of their spiritual,
material and political history.
Buddhism took root chiefly in
the 3rd century B.C., under the
Indian king Asoka of the
Maurya dynasty. How many
Westerners have heard of this missionary-king who put
the moral teachings of Buddhism into practice? Once a
bloodthirsty and belligerent warrior, Asoka became an
apostle of charity and peace under the influence of
Buddhism. Because of Buddha and Asoka, the world's
debt to India is great.
Under Asoka's reign, Buddhism began to spread
throughout Asia, especially across what are now Pakistan
and Afghanistan, reaching Turkestan and China some
centuries later. A short historical outline will give a
better idea of the way in which this peaceful penetration
took place.
After a first Persian invasion under Darius I (521-486
B.C.), Northern India was again invaded, during the
second half of the 4th century B.C., by the armies of
Alexander the Great ; for the first time, Hellenism, which
had already taken root in Asia Minor, came in contact
with India. Alexander's empire stretched from Greece and
Egypt across Syria, Mesopotamia and Afghanistan to
Western India ; its southern limits were the Persian Gulf
and the Arabian Sea and, to the North, it was bordered
by the Caspian Sea and by Scythia. Alexander, who had
. become very orientalized, never
had any direct influence in
Hellenizing his vast empire,
although its very existence was
to encourage the spread of
Hellenism throughout Asia for
centuries.
Among Alexander's notable
successors was Seleucos, whose
empire stretched from Syria to
what is now Pakistan. In the
North, it included Transoxiana,
the country on the far side of
the River Oxus (now Soviet
Turkestan). It was a Hellenic
state in a mainly Iranian coun¬
try. India, however, became in¬
dependent in 306 B.C. under
Chandragupta (Sandrakottos in
Greek), grandfather of the
Buddhist king Asoka, although
it remained in close contact
with the Greco-Persian empire
of the Seleucid dynasty.
TWO CIVILIZATIONS,
once met in Afghanistan,
which at one time decorate
and plaster medallion of
discovered during excavati
Photos Musée Guimet, Paris
Indian and Greco-Roman,
Ivory plaques (top of page)
d some nobleman's furniture,
Greco-Roman style were
ons at Begram, near Kabul.
At that time,
national atmos¬
phere" prevailed
in all this vast
region, with cul¬
tural and eco¬
nomic exchanges
an "inter-
Cont'd
next page
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
VIEWPOINT
(Continued) _
GRECO-ROMAN OR INDIAN ?
taking place between India, Persia, Parthla, Syria, and
Mesopotamia, and also with the vast territories of Central
Asia and Siberia. The influence of Greek and, later, of
Roman civilization was very much in evidence.
Towards 250 B.C., Bactria, which included the territo¬
ries between the Hindu Kush and the Oxus (and even
beyond), attained independence under Hellenic kings and
generals. The coins found there Greek, barbarian, Sas-
sanid, Hindu, Buddhist and, finally, Moslem, provide a
fragmentary but impressive glimpse of the history of the
West in Asia:, the tribulations of a centre of Hellenism,
cut off from the West and stretching as far as India.
During the first half of the 2nd century B.C., the Bac-
trian Greeks dislodged the Indians and established them¬
selves in north-west India. Towards the middle of this
century, one of their rulers (one of the Greco-Indian
basileis-maharajahs) named Menandros (Milinda to the"
Indians), was converted to Buddhism. Menandros suc¬
ceeded in extending the borders of his kingdom as far as
the Ganges, thus achieving the dream of Alexander.
In Bactria itself, the Greeks were supplanted about
130 B.C. by the Scythians or Parthians, who quickly
became assimilated. They were driven out in their turn,
however, by the Kushana, a tribe of Chinese origin, about
the beginning of the Christian era. The Kushana also
became assimilated and Hellenized. Officially they em¬
braced Buddhism, but the old religions continued to be
practised simultaneously with the new. In the 2nd cen¬
tury A.D., under their great king, the "basileus-basileôn"
Kanishka, whose empire stretched from the Aral Sea to
the Erythrean Sea, including a large part of India, came
a flowering of the arts within a framework of Indian,
Greco-Roman, Iranian and Chinese cultural elements.
Buddhist art certainly sprang from Indian roots, and
spread with the Buddhist religion. During the first centu¬
ries of its existence, however, any image of Buddha was
forbidden. Thus the impressive monuments of Sanchi,
that masterpiece of Buddhist art of the 1st century A.D.,
do not include a single image of Buddha, who was then
represented by such symbols as an empty throne, a para¬
sol, and a saddled, riderless horse. Buddhist art had
developed in the 2nd and 1st centuries B.C., especially in
Gandhara, a Hellenized region between the Oxus and
the Indus (straddling what are now Afghanistan and
Pakistan), and, above all, in the Kabul River valley and
the Peshawar area as far as the borders of Taxila. Des¬
pite the absence of the image of Buddha, Indian art, like
that of Gandhara at the time already showed a strong
Hellenic influence.
The Greeks called him " Boddo "
A coin of the Kushan king Kanishka shows an impor¬
tant change in the evolution of Buddhist art an
image of Buddha with the inscription "BODDO" in
Greek characters. This is one of the oldest, if not the
oldest image of Buddha which has come down to us. The
Kushan period marks the flowering of what is known as
"Greco-Buddhist" or Buddhist "Greco-Roman" art or
sometimes as "Gandhara art" a stage in artistic deve¬
lopment which has been revealed through a host of
statues and reliefs showing Buddha in the guise of Apollo.
Gandhara was a religious and commercial crossroads
which explains the remarkable discovery made at Begram,
Kanishka's summer capital (some 40 miles north of
Kabul). Hundreds of coins, and also a whole store of
classic works of Greco-Roman Buddhist, Indian, Roman
and Chinese art were uncovered here. Greek medallions
showing Dionysius, satyrs and maenads were found side
by side with Chinese lacquer objects, Greco-Roman
bronzes and glassware, and sculptured ivories of undoubt¬
edly Indian origin.
While the Gandhara Buddhist art was developing in the
1st and 2nd centuries A.D., an impressive flowering of art
was seen in the Indian town of Mathura, between Delhi
and Agra. Images of Buddha dating from this time have .
also been found here, this time a typically Indian Buddha,
not the Greco-Roman one of Gandhara. And this has
led to the problem so hotly debated by art historians;
did the image of Buddha first appear in the Hellenic
territoriesGandhara. or Bactria or at Mathura? Did
the Apollonian Buddha become Indianized on reaching
Mathura, or did the Indian Buddha become Hellenized
on reaching the Hellenic provinces? An alternative possi¬
bility is that the image of Buddha was created indepen¬
dently and simultaneously in the two places.
The last of the theories was advanced in the unesco
courier in which it was asserted that the artists of Ma¬
thura took as their model, not the Apollonian Buddha of
the Gandhara, but statues of the primitive genii of the
ancient, pre-Buddhist cults (the unesco courier, June
1956, p. 14). This rather obscure theory, which seems to
link the Mathura Buddha with the pre-Aryan (Mohenjo-
Daro) civilization of the Indus valley has by no means
been proved scientifically. Similarly, doubt may be
expressed about the interesting discovery made at Had-da,
Afghanistan, in 1926, of what are probably later figures.
Are they Greek, Greco-Roman or, as the unesco courier
states (p. 49), Roman?
The discussion seems sometimes to be based on a spirit
of "nationalization" a nationalization of what took place
2,000 years ago. However, if looked at, as here, in terms
of the cultural exchanges which occurred in these areas,
such questions lose something of their sting.
The/ deified men and humanized gods
Without, therefore, attaching more importance to the
question than it deserves, we think it likely that
the first statues of Buddha were fashioned by
Greco-Roman artists (leaving aside the question as to
whether this happened in Gandhara or in Bactria).
A kind of taboo appears to have prevented the Indians
from fashioning images of Buddha for about 500 years.
Similar cases are to be found, incidentally, in Persian
Mazdeism, Judaism, primitive Christianity and Islam. As
Buddha, who did not consider himself of divine nature,
stressed his teaching and not his person, an impersonal,
spiritual art was more in accordance with Buddhism than
an image of its founder.
Anthropomorphism was, on the other hand, familiar to
the Greco-Romans, who deified men and humanized
their gods. There are many examples of borrowings and
of "'nationalization" in the matter of images of gods:
statues of the goddess Astarte have a resemblance to Ar¬
temis ; to the Greeks, Jehovah was a god like Zeus, and
the Sassanid Persians represented Apollo in Persian cos¬
tume. Finally, the first statues of Jesus have some ana¬
logy with the prototype of Buddha. Although spiritual
values may have suffered in this transition from symbo¬
lism to representational art, Buddhist religious and Bud¬
dhist secular art were thereby enabled to flourish.
For Westerners, imbued with classical culture, ancient
art and thought had their fountain-head in Greece, law
being the child of Rome. Greece was more familiar to
them than India the furthest point reached by Alexan¬
der's Western armies. Central Asia? Lying beyond "outer"
Iran, it seemed to them too far-off. "Near East", "Middle
East" both terms illustrate European ethnocentricity.
In fact, the civilizations which contributed to the deve¬
lopment and dissemination of Buddhist art were many.
Gandhara, especially was an intermediary between the
Near and Far East, between Occident and Orient.
The famous Buddhist monastery of Bamiyan in the
Hindu Kush range, where Buddhist thought was allied to
Greco-Roman, Sassanid Persian and Indian art, was an
important stopping-place on the road from India to
China. As numerous archaeological remains still show, all
the tribes living between "outer" Iran and the steppes of
Turkestan on the one hand, and China on the other, came
under the influence of Buddhism. This was the meeting
place of currents of civilization coming from the four
points of the compass.
Some civilizations are better-known to us than others.
Thanks to the efforts of Soviet archaeologists, our know¬
ledge of the cultural past of territories beyond the Amu-
Darya is rapidly increasing, though much still remains to
be discovered. Little by little, the importance of local cul¬
tures associated with Greco-Roman contributions is being
brought to light. Chinese archaeology has most certainly
some interesting surprises in store for us. In this work,
Indian, Soviet or Chinese chauvinism would be as regret¬
table as any European-centred prejudice.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Copyright J. D. Lajoux
PAGODA OF THE GOOD MOTHER
Finest and richest pagoda of Cholon, Saigon's Chinese quar¬
ter, is the Pagoda of the Good Mother built and maintained by
people from Canton in South China to honour their sea god
dess who protects sailors and travellers. Here, an old woman
burns joss-sticks she has bought in the pagoda or in the local
bazaar. When lit they will be planted in a special copper bowl.
(Continued on next page) 	
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
PAGODA (Cont/nuec/;
OFFERINGS
THAT BURN
FOR MONTHS
In more than a score of
pagodas of Saigon's "China¬
town ", people of Chinese birth
or ancestry honour divinities
on whose protection and good¬
will they count. People who
trace their origins back to
Canton on the South China
coast have a particular guard¬
ian to watch over thema
goddess of the sea who is
sometimes called "The Good
Mother" and sometimes, "The
Celestial Empress".
Chinese of other religious
beliefs also frequent the pagoda
of the people of Canton in
Saigon and Buddhists celebrate
their most important festivals
there. But the chief deity of
the pagoda is the protectress
of fishermen, travellers and
sailors, who is said to have
been born more than a thous¬
and years ago. Many stories
are told of her appearance in
the midst of tempests to save
mariners from certain death.
In the courtyard of the
pagoda are huge braziers. In
these, people solemnly burn
paper money and paper clo¬
thes during the three days of
anniversary celebrations for the
goddess, thus assuring cloth¬
ing and money for the Good
Mother for the next twelve
months. In return they hope
to receive her gratitude and
protection.
Throughout the year people
come to the pagoda to burn
joss-sticks and, on the assump¬
tion that the more they offer,
the greater will be their re
ward, wealthy Chinese bu
huge spirals of incense which
are then hung from the roof
where they smoulder away
slowly for months. Copyright J. D. Lajoi
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
AKING A SUPER JOSS-STICK
The tremendously long coils suspended from the roof
of the pagoda are a mixture of clay and incense. To con¬
struct them, workers begin by coiling the paste on a
wicker tray, first placed on the ground and later,
when the centre of the coil is finished, on trestles. Fi¬
nally the coils are sewn together (Below, right).
When dry the coil is stretched and placed on frame.
Some of these "super joss-sticks" burn for months.
Q>39 7'JJ-f I
/7 V
Photos Copyright Jean Garcer.ot
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Fine Lady On A Black Horse by Jamini Roy Masquerade In India by Jamini Roy
Festive greetings from Unicef
ccAll I need in life is a simple earthen pot for food and a straw mat to sleep on",
says Jamini Roy. But this Indian painter (see also page 13) realizes that sick
and hungry children need more medicines and food to put in the pot. That is
why he has given to the United Nations Children's Fund (unicef) two of his works which
they are offering for sale in reproduction on their 1956 greeting cards.
The two cards reproduced on the top of this page are examples of Roy at his best
with his toy-like figures with immense almond eyes done in jewel-bright colours.
Originally a portrait painter, Roy withdrew from conventionalism in 1921 and began
to draw inspiration from Hindu thought and the basic elements of Bengal folk painting.
Two other outstanding artists have also donated original works for the benefit of
unicef whose cards are a reminder of the work it has been carrying out among millions
of the world's children and of the need for continued contributions to its fund. One
of them is the Rumanian-born artist, Saul Steinberg, who has designed this year's official
U.N. greeting card, "'Bridge to Peace" his imaginative concept of the world spanned
by bridges uniting all civilizations and cultures.
The third artist represented in this year's collection is the American, Joseph Low.
who has designed five cards, three of which are shown here, depicting "Festival Times
Around the World". All the cards express the season's greetings in the five official
languages of the U.N. Each of the three series costs $1.00 for a box of ten cards. In¬
formation as to where these cards are available can be obtained from all U.N. Informa¬
tion Centres.
The U.N.Bridge To Peace by Saul Steinberg
Festival... South America by Joseph Low
32
Ferris Wheel... The Mediterranean (Low) Punch and Judy... North Europe (Low)
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Letters to the Editor
Sir,
Being a citizen of India, I was particu¬
larly interested by the article "Asian His¬
tory Through Western Glasses" in your
timely U. S. issue of May 1956. (European
March) As a U.S. resident for seven years
I have seen a growing interest being taken
in Indian history, past and present, which
has been presented to the American
public both objectively and with bias.
However, a greater percentage has been
quite fair and objective.
The article suggested more use of films
and filmstrips in schools. Almost every
school in the U.S.A. has projectors, and
the total audience approaches one billion
annually. Films (on India) shown to school
children and adult groups are mainly pro¬
duced by the Government of India, inde¬
pendent producers and religious groups.
As their purposes are different, so is their
interpretation of India.
Recently I saw a film produced by a
religious group in America. Superficially,
most of these films give the impression of
being documentary because all the footage
is shot in India, and all the people in¬
volved are Indians. These facts do not
make them documentary films, because
film production is a selective process, and
is influenced by the attitudes of its script
writer and director, and the degree of their
understanding of Indian culture. Some of
these films are excellent, but others are
nothing more than superficial records of a
people observed from far off. While a
great effort is being made to present Asian
life to Western audiences through films,
now is the time for all producers to consi¬
der how this could be done as objectively
as possible.
Kantilal Rathod
Syracuse, N.Y., U.S.A.
Sir,
Why is the Microfilm Unit mentioned in
The Unesco Courier (May, 1956 : U.S.
July) beginning its activities in Paraguay?
Surely the most urgent task is to microfilm
serious, out-of-print books and learned
periodicals in places like London, which
would be a sitting target for a hydrogen-
bomb, and keep the films in comparatively
safe places like Paraguay. I suggest that
the Unit be sent first to the British Mu¬
seum Reading Room or the Bodleian at
Oxford.
Daphne Hereward
University of London.
Editor's note: As a direct step towards
the microfilming of important books and
publications in the world's great collections
and the preservation of at least the sub¬
stance of their contents in time of war,
unesco prepared an international conven¬
tion for the protection of cultural properly
which was signed by 50 states in May 1954.
(See the unesco courier N° 7, 1954 ; U.S.
September) This convention, which pro¬
vides for the protection of museums,
libraries and other depositories of valuable
documents, came into force on August 7,
1956. The actual work of microphoto-
graphy is beyond UNESCO's financial
resources so it has encouraged member
states to take action themselves in much
the way Miss Hereward proposes. It has
also examined the possibility of setting up
depositories of microfilms in "safe" coun¬
tries. The mobile microfilm unit referred
to in the unesco courier was set up at
the request of member states to help them \
preserve and reproduce their archival and
documentary collections. From Paraguay
its work will be extended to other Latin
American countries where collections are
endangered by neglect and climatic condi¬
tions, and where no facilities for micro¬
filming exist. Technically, if not financially,
the British Museum and the Bodleian
Library have good existing resources to
carry out major microfilm projects.
Sir,
Your magazine is interesting, but my
friends and I feel it has not maintained its
former high standard perhaps because it
is being aimed at a wider public. We feel
it should, at all costs, avoid copying the
majority of weekly publications... which
manage to satisfy their readers with articles
that are lacking in value and importance.
Sir,
I am sure there is much that is interest¬
ing and fascinating to be told about
UNESCO's work, but that which you find
to say is far below the adult level of
intelligence.
M. Marct
Paris.
Sir,
My level of understanding is too low for
a scientific publication like yours which
uses technical terms and erudite expres¬
sions that are quite beyond me. I must
admit that certain issues have interested me,
but if one suffers from brain fag from
reading a publication, thus adding to the
mental tension induced by one's work, it
is better to do without it. Such is the
case for me.
Marie Josephe Le Fur
Paris.
Sir,
The unesco courier is a great help to
me in my career as a school teacher, and
is a continual source of valuable informa¬
tion. I feel that in reading your excellent
magazine we are in some way drawing
closer the bond of friendship between
nations, and that by acting on the prin¬
ciples set down in the Declaration of
Human Rights we may in some way
contribute to universal peace and under¬
standing.
Judith Mates
East Glenelg,
South Australia.
Sir,
Your periodical has been a well of
information for me for use in my teaching.
I have familiarized my students with the
fine work your Organization is doing.
Nettle Goldstein
Jacques Martin
Paris.
Miami Beach,
Florida, U.S.A.
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's National distributor! from
whom the English, French and Spanish
editions of the UNESCO COURIER
can be obtained are listed below.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 303 Flinders Street, Melbourne,
Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C"., Spengergass 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15 rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). 80 Belgian francs.
CANADA. University ol Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244. Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUSA. Libreria Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kleber, Paris, 16".
CCP. 12598-48, Unesco Bookshop,
Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bom¬
bay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta
13; 36a, Mount Road. Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Jakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission lor
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P. O. B. 4154. Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San¬
son!, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99,
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Olfice Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokh'ornet. Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall. Pishawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc.. 1104 Castillejos, Ouiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16 South Frederik St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämiscrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva.
5.20 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2 rue Cook.
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit. Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 551-3 Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London. S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 152 West 42nd St. New York,
36, N.Y.
Columbia University Press. 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. (except
periodicals).
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjlga.
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
By THEIR OWN HAND: The
highest death rates from suicides in both
sexes are found in Japan, Denmark, Austria
and Switzerland and the lowest are reported
in Ireland, Northern Ireland, Chile,
Scotland and Spain. Within the United
States the rate for the white population
is almost three times that of the non-white
population. These facts emerge from the-
first statistical survey of suicides as a cause
of death compiled by the World Health
Organization. The survey, covering the
period from the beginning of the century,
shows that between 71,000 and 72,000 men
and women die by their own hand each
year in the 25 countries studied which have
a total adult population of 400 million.
Everywhere men are more prone to suicide
than women. Total mortality has re¬
mained more or less stable in the past
50 years except around 1930 at the time
of the great economic depression.
LAW OF THE SEA: The first step
towards replacing the vast network of
laws concerning the sea by one or more
international conventions has been made
by the U.N. International Law Com¬
mission which has now completed a
seven years' study and codification of
the laws. Among other questions, the
Commission's report, which is to be
discussed by the U.N. General Assembly
this year, deals with the limit of terri¬
torial coastal waters, the right of
passage of foreign ships in these waters
and the rights and duties of coastal
states, the nationality of ships, juris¬
diction in maritime collisions, pollution
of the sea and piracy. It proposes the
calling of an international conference to
give effect to the rules now formulated.
ILIK'S TV ROUNDUP: What are
TV programmes like in Japan? What sort
of sets do they use in the Soviet Union?
How do French schools use TV? These
and many similar questions were answered
recently for British televiewers by the first
programme on the impact of TV on coun¬
tries throughout the world. Produced by
the B.B.C. in co-operation with unesco
and TV stations in 13 countries, the pro¬
gramme examined the history, current de¬
velopment and future prospects of a
medium of entertainment and information
now reaching 50 million receivers.
'BIGGEST EVER' CO-OPERA¬
TION: Since 1950, 78 countries have
given a total of $142,000,000 to the
U.N. technical assistance programme
for aid to underdeveloped countries.
These funds, the U.N. Technical
Assistance Board reports, have been
used to help 131 countries and terri¬
tories. Experts from 77 countries have
taken part in the programme and 105
countries have provided training facili¬
ties. "Never before", says the report,
"have the resources of so many coun¬
tries been mobilized for a world-wide,
co-operative enterprise."
MrAQ TEACHES WITH TV:
Thousands of people crowding round
community receivers to watch the opening
telecast of the first permanent TV station
IMPACT
of Science on Society
A quarterly bulletin of science
and its social relations ; stu¬
dies on the impact of science
on society ; reviews of impor¬
tant scientific publications.
Some recent articles : Medi¬
cal and Social Problems of
Aging, by R.E. Tunbridge ;
Science and the Changing
Face of Industry The So¬
cial Phase, by Alexander King ;
Warning and Promise of
Experimental Embryology, by
H.V. Brondsted ; Design and .
Chance in Discovery and
Invention, by René Taton ;
Man's Responsibility to his
Genetic Heritage, by Mogens
V/estergaard.
In the latest issue.
Volume VII N° 3 :
-k Ten Years of Science at Unesco by
~k The Social Character of Technology
Fifty Years of Medical Research by A.
Annual subscription : $ 1.75 ; 9/6d.
Send your subscription to the Unesco Sales Agent
in your country. See list page 34.
Marcel Florkin ;
by Tom Burns ;
C. Allison.
in the Middle East caused traffic jams in
the streets of Baghdad. Telecasts from
the new station, which was opened by King
Feisal of Iraq, are primarily educational
two half-hour sessions for schools each
morning and adult educational and cultural
programmes in the evening. The station
at present covers Baghdad and its suburbs,
but its range will be increased by a high
power transmitter now being built. The
station is to have an outside broadcasts van
and will receive films regularly from the
British television services.
WFUNA IS TEN: The World Fede¬
ration of United Nations Associations
(wtuna) recently celebrated the tenth
anniversary of its foundation during its
annual General Assembly in Geneva.
Among the leading world figures who
addressed the Assembly on wfuna's
contribution to the work of the U.N.
were Mrs. Eleanor Roosevelt, Earl
Attlee, M. Jules Moch, French repre¬
sentative on the U.N. Disarmament
Commission, Dr. Ralph Bunche, U.N.
Under Secretary, and Dr. Homi Bhabha,
President of the U.N. Conference on
Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy.
.TRESS MESSAGE PROBLEMS:
The international flow of news is today
being hampered by high and discrepant
charges made for sending press messages
by cable or radio. Similar services vary
from country to country by over 300 per
cent and it sometimes costs twice as much
to send news in one direction as it does in
the reverse. Many countries, notably in
Africa and Latin America, lack adequate
news transmitting facilities. Forty-five, for
example, have no national news agencies.
These facts are brought out in a world¬
wide survey, "The Problems of Trans¬
mitting Press Messages" (1), jointly pre¬
pared by the International Telecommuni¬
cation Union (itu) and unesco for the
U.N. Economic and Social Council. Now
published as a brochure, it gives detailed
facts from over 80 countries and provides
a comprehensive picture of press rates and
communication facilities throughout the
world. It includes UNESCO's proposals
for greater rate reductions and the expan¬
sion of communication networks to broaden
news coverage in countries now inadequa¬
tely served.
(1) unesco, Paris, 1956. 95 pp. Price:
S 1,00; 5/-; 250 francs.
MANKIND AGAINST KILLERS:
The dramatic story of man's patient
efforts to understand and master pesti¬
lential diseases is told with skill and
simplicity in "Mankind Against the Kil¬
lers" (2) a timely book written by
James Hemming, a member of the
Unesco National Committee for the
United Kingdom. It takes the reader
on an adventurous exploration into his¬
tory and behind the scenes in crucial 'à
scientific experiments and gives a gra- <
phic account of the work of the World °~.
Health Organization whose programma ^
for the control of malaria, tuberculosis <
and other diseases have benefited one ^
sixth of the world's population since this o
U.N. agency was created ten years ago. §
(2) Longmans, Green and C"., Ltd., o
London - New York - Toronto, 1956. a."
231 pp. Price 15/-. 5
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
ANNOUNCING
A SPECIAL
NEW YEAR GIFT
Our January 1957
Issue
(Published Dec.)
TEN PAGES OF FULL
COLOUR PLATES OF
ANCIENT MASTER¬
PIECES OF WORLD
ART
An extra-special
52-page issue devoted
entirely to the art of
IRAN
SPAIN
ITALY
SINGLE COPY PRICE :
50 cents, 2/-, IOOFr.fr.
Subscribers will receive this
special number at no extra
cost. SUBSCRIBE NOW.
Send a gift subscription
to your friends.
Annual rate :
$ 2.50; 8/-; 400Fr.fr. WOÊBÊ mWm
NEXT MONTH'S ISSUE
will mark the I Oth anniver¬
sary of UNESCO's creation
with an account of its contri-
butions to education, science,
culture and the arts.
'PRINCE BAYSUNQUR MIRZA WATCHING A BATTUE',
a 15th century Persian miniature reproduced from the "Shahnameh",
the Iranian epic written by Firdausi. The manuscript and its mag¬
nificent illustrations are now in the Imperial Library, Teheran.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Eastern inspiration
Western workmanship
"Returning Home", the pastoral design engraved on this flask-shaped vase was drawn
specially by the Indian artist, Phani Bhusan (inset) for a unique project in which Oriental
artists and Occidental craftsmen combined their talents to produce an unusual collec¬
tion of art on engraved crystal. Artists In the Far and Near East prepared the drawings,
American designers created the shapes of the glass and American artisans Interpreted
the drawings on the crystal forms. (See "Asian Artists in Crystal", page 4)
Steuben Glass Inc., New York
]]>
</page>
</document>
