<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068909eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
a m
LAND
OMf
N*0 M
eL
'frftgr* ^»'«
V
« ^
*-#
rT*.
O
«^
SEPTEMBER
1956
(9th year)
Price: 9d. (U. K.)
40 francs (France)
m
i /p¿2^
^4
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
SOVIET HOMAGE TO
NATIONAL HERITAGE
Museum attendance in the U.S.S.R. reflects enthu¬
siasm and respectsometimes bordering on religious
fervour felt by Russian people for things pertaining
to their national heritage. Above, old woman
focusses spectacles to read title of painting in Tretiakof
Art Gallery, Moscow, one of whose halls is seen in
photo, left. Soviet Union now has about 1,000 mu¬
seums. Hermitage (top photo) housed in former
Winter Palace of the Czars at Leningrad, boasts one
of the world's finest art collections. (See page 28)
Soviet Information Office
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
INDOW Orín ON TMI WOILO
ner
SEPTEMBER 1956
9th YEAR
N° 9
CONTENTS
PAGE
3
5
EDITORIAL
EDUCATE, ENTERTAIN, ENRICH
The three E's of the modern museum
By Molly Harrison
7 TOMORROW'S MUSEUM TODAY
Bold new designs oust the Greek temple
9 A PLACE OF HEALING FOR THE SOUL
Museums down the ages
By Francis H. Taylor
10 DIGGING UP HISTORY FOR THE SHOWCASE
Museum pioneers of modern archaeology
By Sir Leonard Woolley
13 OUT OF BOUNDS TO VISITORS
The busy world behind the glass cases
15 BACKSTAGE AT NEW YORK'S BIG FREE SHOW
By Isabel Mount
18 WORKS OF ART AT THE DOCTOR'S
22 A STRIPED POSTER SAYS «COME INSIDE'
International Campaign for Museums
23 BROWSING IN THE METRO MUSEUM
A new pastime for Parisians
25 THEY STAY CLOSE TO THE PEOPLE
A look at local museums
By Grace Morley
27 HAUNTING MUSEUMS HIDDEN IN THE JUNGLE
Mysterious graveyard statues of Indo-China
By Frantz Laforest
28 LEO TOLSTOY IS ALWAYS AT HOME
Soviet homage to famous men
30 "ANIMAL, VEGETABLE, MINERAL?"
Museums' telecast with 5,000,000 fans
By Paul Johnstone
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19 Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not copyrighted may be reprinted from THE UNESCO
COURIER but must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted
from UNESCO COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's
name. Prints of non-copyright photos are available on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles uxpress the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE UNESCO
COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE UNESCO COURIER : 8/-; $2.50 or 400
French frs or equivalent.
(MC. 56.1.105 A)
The Unesco Courier
COVER PHOTO
Ancient pieces of wood sculpture "under
treatment" in the restoration workshop
of Central Laboratory of Belgian Museums,
Brussels. Infra-red rays from lamps are
used to melt a special mixture of wax
and resin which will impregnate wood,
protecting it from dampness and des¬
troying infesting worms. (See page 18)
Copyright Central Laboratory of Belgian Museums
Not so long ago museums were still, as one museologist
has put it, "sidings on whose rails treasure-laiden
trains had halted for ever." Curators had still not
thrown off the collecting and hoarding mentality which
wealthy travellers and lovers of the arts bequeathed to
public museums of the 19th century along with their
collections of treasures. A museum's greatness was
measured in terms of how many objects it contained, so
every inch of space was used and the museum became a
vast necropolis, its walls, from floor to ceiling covered
with paintings, its rooms crammed with statues and
showcases. It was a dusty, tiring place, to be visited from
a sense of duty or "done" as the tourist "does" ruins and
other ancient curiosities marked with an asterisk in the
guide book.
Even today there are local, regional and even national
museums which seem dedicated to the sole task of conser¬
vation. But in most cases a new wind has been blowing
out the cobwebs from the dusty cemeteries of yesterday.
Flexibility and movement are the new watchwords which
have replaced rigidity and inactivity. The museum has
begun to speak the language of our time.
This change came about when it was recognized that
the justification of a museum's existence must be measur¬
ed by its capacity to serve the needs of the people and by
its ability to put at their disposal the vast accumulation of
human experience and help them develop their taste and
judgment. The recent reconsideration of the whole
function and purpose of museum work has been based on
the premise that museums are education and not simply
ancillary to it.
Sir Harry Lindsay, Chairman of the Council of the
Royal Society of Arts in Great Britain, once declared: "If
only I had been trained properly when I was a child, I
should not only like what I know, I should not only know
what I like; but I should also know why I like what I
like." One of the great achievements of the modern
museum is that it has proved to the hilt its capacity to
interest and instruct young people, for it is at the same
time book, spoken word and image; it is the living past.
In the museum the word "education" takes on its original
etymological sense: "E-ducare" "to lead out", and so to
foster, to encourage, to cultivate.
But the museum can do still more. "It is", says
M. Georges Salles, Director of French National Museums,
"one of the places where contacts, exchanges and under¬
standing between different peoples can most easily be
established. It is this power of the museum to act as a
unifying force, as well as its role as a cultural community
centre, that is being emphasised by the UNESCo-sponsor-
ed International Campaign for Museums and its special
Museums Week in October.
As a contribution to this campaign, The unesco
courier in this issue has opened a window on the
wonderland of museums, a world in which young people
can see the shape of things to come outlined more clearly
in the light of things past, and where men and women
can find a sense of continuity and balance amid the speed
and pressure of modern life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
SAO PAULO
ART ADVENTURE IN A
FAST-GROWING CITY
An art museum which offers dancing lessons and classes in gardening, photography or interior
decoration may seem a bit out of the ordinary run of museums. But these and many other acti¬
vities at Sao Paulo's Art Museum, Brazil correspond exactly to the spirit and needs of South America's
probably the world'sfastest growing city. As its director describes it, the Museum is a
place "where works of art form part of a living atmosphere, where antiquity is the seed of a desire
to understand and appreciate art as a living force in the present day and a necessity of life." That
is why it forms the centre of a school for the teaching of art and various related subjects which
might, at first glance, appear to be outside the range of art in the strict sense. Young people
find in the museum pleasant, familiar surroundings calculated to arouse curiosity and interest
where they are provided with good film shows, concerts of classical and modern music, and easy
lectures on art history. The fine collection of works from different centuries in the striking main
hall (I) helps to give young people a sense of history and a respect for the past while teaching them
to appreciate works by such modern artists as Matisse, Chagall and Brancusi. Concerned with
all the bearings of artistic life on practical activities the museum now has twenty classes which
teach photography (2), dancing (3), modelling and drawing (4), cinematography, engraving, indus¬
trial design, gardening and many other subjects. The Museum has organized Sao Paulo's first
young people's orchestra (5) which gives regular concerts of classical and contemporary music.
I) Copyright Roberto-Maria, Sao Paulo.
2-5) Copyright P. C. Scheir, Sao Paulo.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
The three E's of the modern museum:
EDUCATE, ENTERTAIN, ENRICH
by Molly Harrison
Museums, as we know them, have their origins in
a combination of love and self-interest. The wealthy
traveller of earlier centuries who established the
nucleus of our modern collections loved .beautiful and
unusual objects and he was fortunate in being able to pur¬
chase the things he liked and wanted. His taste was per¬
sonal, he indulged it to the full and his influence is still
felt in many of our European museums today.
The wealthy personal collection is, however, less and less
a possibility in our modern world and economic and poli¬
tical developments are steadily altering the nature, the
financial support and, in many cases, the purpose of mu¬
seum collections. Increasingly they are being taken over
by public bodies and maintained and developed from pub¬
lic funds. Public money implies support and public use:
it is perhaps timely that we take a new look at museums
for many of them are, in the fullest sense, ours.
What are they? Temples of the Muses to the fifth
century Greeks, but they have travelled far since then.
Their facades, encrusted with doric and ionic, seem to
hanker longingly for the past, but the atmosphere inside
sometimes lacks much that the Greeks thought important
in life.
Museums show things. That may seem to the layman
an easy, innocuous and almost automatic thing to do, but
the showing of things is fraught with problems, many of
which divide the museum profession with an acerbity
undreamed of by laymen. We museum directors and cura¬
tors are on the whole an enthusiastic and devoted band
for surely no one would dream of undertaking such work
unless he enjoyed it. We represent many different points
of view but for all of us the problems are great and they
increase. What are they ?
Firstly, museum material is fascinating material and
much of it is unique. Most modern men and women
cannot, or do not want to fit such things into their daily
living and so there is perpetually the danger of an em¬
barras de choix, the risk that museums may acquire too
much and far more than their founders or the architects
of their buildings originally conceived of. The problem
therefore arises of what do we do with it how much do we
show? Collecting is a habit of mind as well as of body
and of purse and it is almost an occupational disease,
which museum officials tend to acquire in the same way
as hairdressers fall to fibrositis, miners to silicosis and
tennis champions to damaged elbows.
We differ considerably in our ways of warding off our
incipient collecting mania. It is a recent problem ; an
earlier generation of museum officials felt it essential to
show everything and their collections were nothing more
than an assembly of curiosities. Of recent years the
cobwebs have largely been swept away in most museums
and the back tooth of an Indian elephant is no longer
shown alongside a piece of Mexican embroidery, a Fabergé
clock and the horns of a reindeer from Finnish Lapland.
We try to display things around some intelligible theme
and to avoid the mistake of failing to show anything be¬
cause we show too much. Some fear that this trend has
almost gone too far and that two important elements in
enjoyable museum visiting wonder and delight may
well be lost if our objects are too coldly displayed and
carefully segregated. As in most spheres, balance, and
proportion are difficult to achieve but as always they
are vitally important.
Again, enthusiasm for their collections causes many
museum people to think of an ideal museum as being a
large building, imposing and arresting, as befits the im¬
portance of what it contains. Others think . differently
and fear that potential visitors may feel dwarfed and iso¬
lated in great halls. It may be that a number of small
museums, in place of one large one, would be more invit¬
ing to the public, who would tend to visit them in a more
relaxed and receptive frame of mind. Of course there is
no final answer to this problem of size in museums, for
individual, regional and national characteristics and op¬
portunities differ so greatly ; so thought remains divided
and practice varied.
A more knotty problem and one around which fur flies
thick arises from the fact that most museum material
is valuable and irreplaceable. It must, of
course, be assembled and cared for with
the greatest skill ; acquisition and con¬
servation are the primary responsibilities
of museums, for unless the exhibits are
there and in good condition there is no
Cont'd
next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A MODERN MUSEUM
(Continued) The Muses would almost feel at home
museum. A collection, however, is not an end in itself
r.nd unless the objects are seen and enjoyed by people
there is no worthwhile museum. So a second problem
hits us, far more difficult than that of how much we
shall showto whom do we show?
We have to choose, to select, for no museum can be all
things to all men. That which is significant and delight¬
ful to a university professor, a research scholar or an ad¬
vanced student will not mean anything at all to Hans
Schmidt, John Brown or Pierre François or their wives,
daughters and sons. We are compelled to decide our par¬
ticular function, but the decision is rarely a personal one,
for the nature of our exhibits, the extent of our collection,
the locality in which we work and the structure of the
society in which we live all these and other factors de¬
termine to a considerable extent to whom we show our
exhibits and to what purpose.
Increasingly it is being realised in the museum world
that museums are not an end in themselves, that though
our work may be entirely with things it is only justifiable
if in the end we are working for people. For their enligh¬
tenment, enjoyment, understanding, development, educa¬
tion it matters little that our words vary. Our differen¬
ces here are perhaps largely a question of pace: some wish
to hasten the fostering of truly popular interest in mu¬
seum material, believing that the modern world has sore
need of what museums stand for and that there is no
time to lose. Others, more cautious perhaps or more spe¬
cialist, seeing clearly the dangers of attempting to make
objects of supreme quality too readily accessible to persons
as yet ignorant of them, tend to look askance at populari¬
zation. There is room for many differences of emphasis
but we are all imbued with a similar belief that museums
are vitally important institutions, essential to our time.
Museum material is, however, often difficult material
and much professional discussion centres around the
problem of how to make it understandable. Technical
matters impinge here what kind of show case? Do we
have to have them at all ? How do we light our objects
so that they can be seen to best advantage, by night as
well as by day ? What style, size and detail of label is
best ? What publications do we issue ? and why ? What
ventilation, what heating system, what hours of opening
can best serve the interests both of the valuable object and
of the valuable visitor ?
These are perennial matters, debated in season and out
whenever museum officials meet together, matters which
are certainly never capable of final solution. That tall,
indeterminate young man and his girl-friend, that solid
bourgeois and his family, all spending an hour of their
spare time in their local museum, would be astonished if
they could know how much thought, effort, argument and
trouble have gone towards helping them to understand, as
well as to enjoy, what they are seeing. Showing our exhi¬
bits is more involved than they might think.
Are they keeping pace
with a changing world ?
Anew trend in museum thinking has made rapid
strides in recent years, a trend which fits well into
the pattern of thought of the post-war years: much
museum material is international, the product, with varia¬
tions, of all mankind and belonging to all mankind.
Museum material is, therefore, potentially a unifying
force and many ways have been tried of incorporating,
even among purely local or national material, an impli¬
cation affecting the unity of mankind.
Unesco, through its Museums and Monuments Division
has done much to foster international co-operation bet¬
ween museums, and the International Council of Mu¬
seums, a professional, non-governmental body, was found¬
ed to further the same ends. In the critical condition of
the modern world we cannot afford to neglect any media,
any techniques, which can help men to speak to one an¬
other and to interpret their thoughts across barriers of
nationality, race or creed.
Museums are definitely on the up and up. There is
new thought afoot, renewed professional activity and in¬
creased public response yet no one in his senses could
possibly be content.
The world is changing and museums are changing with
it but are they keeping pace? Do more people in the
world appreciate things of beauty and worth than, say,
a century ago? Do people make more good things than
they did? Most people have more leisure than in the past
do they spend it in more fulfilling ways? Are imagi¬
nations as vivid, is perception as acute, are tastes as per¬
sonal and is thought as individual as it was? Are more
people happier, leading richer lives, than was the case
when the objects now displayed in our museums were a
part of daily life, made, used and misused by ordinary men
and women ?
There seems to be little cause for complacency. Museums
do, indeed, interpret life, but they do not always do so
with a clear voice and their message is not always wel¬
come. One senses sometimes an atmosphere of disappoint¬
ment, disillusion, frustration. Why? Of course the fault
lies, as it always does, on both sides. There is no perfect
museum, just as there is no perfect visitor. Can one, in
general terms, list their respective inadequacies, as each
appears to the other ?
Curators look and listen
Exhibits go a-journeying
To many visitors many museums still seem to be too
big, too full, too grand, too rich. Museums often
expect too much in understanding, in appreciation,
in physical staminai and so they fail in many cases to
become a part of everyday life. They seem too special¬
ized, often too erudite and it is difficult for the man in
the street to see the connexion between one display and
another. Their basis seems to be too exclusively in the
past, they seem not to relate the objects they cherish and
display to what that tall young man does in his working
hours, or that solid bourgeois' equally solid wife uses in
her kitchen.
To many museum officials, on the other hand, the ordi¬
nary visitor often seems profoundly stupid. He is either
inert, using nothing of the self that goes so keenly next
day to a football match or a cinema ; or he is greedy,
trying to see too much in too short a time. Being of the
twentieth century, he "has no time to stand and stare,"
and often rushes past things which would speak to him
vividly if he would but pause and really look at them. He
is superficial, because he is often too lazy to think. Feeling,
too, often seems difficult to him ; his channels of appre¬
ciation have been blocked, his senses atrophied and his
enthusiasms dulled by much that happens to him outside
and he cannot relax enough to find renewal.
So the scene is variegated hopeful at one moment,
frustrating at another, enthusiastic here discouraging
there... but no one can doubt that things are on the move,
that the museum world is alive and, in places, almost
kicking. Directors and curators are no longer the hermits
they once tended to be, they are often out of their build¬
ings talking, listening, lookingas much as they are in
them and this is a symbol of increasing museum influence
among the community.
Exhibits, too, even very precious ones, are taken out of
their cases and sent a-journeying to an extent which
would have seemed the height of folly a generation ago.
National museums lend to provincial ones and to one an¬
other, many museums lend things to schools, to churches,
even to shops. And in some places "shop things"
everyday objects made and used by everyday men and
womengo into the museum and take their place along¬
side venerated objects from previous centuries. There is
a va-et-vient which spells health and vitality and growth
museum is gradually and painfully becoming a
cultural community centre, a place where interests start
suddenly to life for some and find their delighted fulfil¬
ment for othersan indispensable element in the whole
rich pattern of modern life. The Greeks and their Muses
would almost feel at home.
MOLLY HARRISON has been Curator of the Geffrye Museum, London
since 1941. She previously taught in schools in Great Britain and from 1953 to
1955 she was a member of the Council of the Museums Association. Molly
Harrison has written many articles and reviews on art and museography.
Her publications include "Museum Adventure", "Picture Source Books for
Social History" and "Learning Out of School".
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
TOMORROW'S MUSEUM TODAY
The working partnership between museum curator and architect has been better defined in recent
years and boldness of conception has marked the striking progress made in museum architecture. Bold
and brilliant innovations have appeared in structural design, choice of materials, lighting, air
conditioning and in the design of display rooms and the provision of educational facilities. Plans of the projected Fine Arts Museum in Le Havre,
France (the former building was destroyed during the war), for example, reveal a treatment providing great flexibility of interior space, the
advantages of which architects have been able to show to museum curators. A sunscreen of specially treated aluminium will be fixed over the
building. Above, model of the Le Havre Museum (now under construction). Below, artist's impression of the Pre-Columbian exhibition hall.
Musée des Beaux-Arts, Le Havre
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Copyright Franco Albini, Milan
1
J
SPIRAL STAIRWAY
TO THE HOLY GRAIL
A museum of unique design which was built under the courtyard of the Archbishop's
Palace In Genoa, Italy, is to house religious treasures from the nearby cathedral of San
Lorenzo. It consists of a series of circular rooms "tailored" by the architect to "fit" the
permanent collection of gold and silver objects formerly locked away in cupboards in
the Cathedral sacristy. Visitors descend into the museum, which resembles a crypt
or catacomb, down a spiral staircase. San Lorenzo's treasures are now easily accessible
to the public and can be quickly taken into the Cathedral for religious ceremonies. Upper
photo shows models of the three main rooms. A smaller room enshrines the Holy Grail, a
Roman glass vessel of the first century A.D. which according to tradition received the Blood
of Christ. Lower photo shows largest room seen through aperture giving access to it.
RAMESES II
CALLED IT:
If the term "museum" strikes
terror in the heart of the average
layman, it is as nothing compar¬
ed to the sense of panic which its
sound produces in the poor innocents
who spend their lives rationalizing its
very -existence. Going back into the
far reaches of time, the word '"mu¬
seum" has succeeded in meaning
nothing vital to anyone in particular,
yet at the same time it has strangely
meant all things to all men.
Through a metamorphosis lasting
many centuries it has emerged from
the simple designation of a temple of
the Muse to be the encompassing
catch basin for all those disparate
elements of hereditary culture which
are not yet woven into the general
fabric of modern education. And
since education has been defined as
"the art of casting artificial pearls
before real swine," it is only natural
that museum workers should have
concerned themselves with the elabo¬
rate furnishing of the trough at the
expense of the digestive capacity of
the feeders.
Museums came into being at a very
early date. There are records of
Egyptian kings who formed collec¬
tions of votive offerings to placate the
gods. Rameses II was the proprietor
of a large library of papyri at Thebes,
above the entrance of which was
carved the hieroglyphic incription,
"A Place of Healing for the Soul."
Centuries later, at the lower end of
the Nile, Ptolemy Soter founded the
Great Museum of Alexandria, the
fountainhead of later humanistic
study. This was not the museum of
sterile objects we know today, nor yet
a temple, but rather a Platonic grove
or academy in which were gathered
about the famous library the leading
intellects of the day.
Socrates spurned sculpture
The role of the collector in the an¬
cient world is steeped in legend¬
ary speculation and coloured
with political oratory. The idea of a
public collection, or in fact any collec¬
tion at all, was unknown to the early
Greeks, whose creative impulses were
so balanced, and whose spiritual
contentment and harmony so complete
that they were never conscious of the
intellectual processes involved in the
creation of a work of art itself.
Beauty to the Greek of classic
times was an accepted fact and,
paradoxically, he despised the factors
that produced it. Socrates, originally
a sculptor, gave up the calling as low
and ignoble, and in Plato's "Republic"
the artist was looked upon as the
lowest order of citizen. He was con¬
sidered a common labourer or decora¬
tor. Since the Greeks, therefore, had
few opinions of art and even fewer
theories, they obviously could not be¬
come collectors in the sense in which
we use the word today. For the col¬
lector is first and last a theorist of
taste upon whose acceptance or re¬
jection of fashionable judgements the
art market fluctuates, up or down,
with startling inconstancy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
'A PLACE OF HEALING FOR THE SOU L'
by Francis Henry Taylor
The work of art remained, then,
until the time of Alexander, either an
oblation to the gods or part of the
public wealth to be guarded in the
treasury of the temple and reckoned
in terms of its monetary or material
value.
As the over-expanded empire of
Alexander the Great crumbled of its
own weight and succumbed to oriental
influences, there developed a nostalgia
for the purity of Athenian civiliza¬
tion. The Hellenistic monarchs of
the Near East began to collect syste¬
matically and reverently the ruins
and fragments of the classic age, and
one may well say that the true fathers
of European collecting were Attalus
and Eumenes II, kings of Pergamum,
outrivaled only by the reigning
houses of Antioch and Alexandria.
Cicero castigated Caesar
Collecting, both public and priv¬
ate, came into its own with the
prosperity of the Roman Em¬
pire. It was incumbent upon every
citizen of rank to be a collector. An
entire quarter of Rome was devoted
to art dealers and galleries, much like
New York' s Fifty-Seventh Street.
Latin literature is filled with the
exploits of art dealers, of their forge¬
ries and swindles, of their ennoble¬
ment and of the fantastic auctions of
Caligula, who forced his retinue to
bid against each other for the fruits
of his military plunder. Cicero ful¬
minated against the rapaciousness of
Caesar and Sulla in stripping the
colonies of their artistic wealth.
The Middle Ages open another
vista in the retrospect of the "mag-
piety" of mankind. Collecting con¬
tinued, but for another purpose. As
the lamp of classic learning flickered
out in the dark night of barbarism,
the Church became at once the sym¬
bol and repository for our intellectual
heritage. Yet the number of objects
preserved in the collections of the
medieval palace or cathedral treasury
are negligible. They were the occa¬
sional gifts of visiting sovereigns, or
conscience tributes paid to patron
saints in expiation of accomplished or
anticipated sin. It was in the mon¬
astery alone that the work of art
was estimated for its own sake.
Whether in regard to the illumination
of a sacred text or the intricacy of a
gold-enameled reliquary, such pre¬
lates as the Abbot Suger of Saint-
Denis or Bishop Bernward of Hildes¬
heim displayed a connoisseurship that
might humble the most impeccable
curator of the present day.
To understand the formation of the
great Renaissance collections and
their implications for those of us who
have to show them and dust them
off, it is necessary to digress into the
distinction between the humanism of
Italy and that of the graver nations
of the North. For in this distinction
lie the differences of viewpoint that
in later centuries were to segregate
the museums of art from similar ins¬
titutions of history and science.
Throughout the quattrocento, col¬
lections of antiques were gathered to¬
gether either to furnish formal aca¬
demies of art, as in the case of the
Medici Gardens, or as the properties
of artists' studios. The ateliers of
Bertoldo, the master of Michelang¬
elo, and the Squarcione in Padua were
rich in fragments of the past. Dona-
tello made constant studies from the
antique, while Lodovico Conzaga,
Bishop of Mantua, formed a collec¬
tion of plaster casts probably no
better than those which are gathering
grime in our museum basements.
The Italian, very much like Ameri¬
cans and Europeans today, was living
for the pleasures of this world, having
only a slight concern for religion and
ethics. He admired art for its own
sake, and more than that, he accepted
it as part of his daily life. The art
of Italy has ever sought to reconcile
the human with the humanistic for
there the art gallery of today was
born even to the extent of bringing
into common use the Italian word
gal.eria to designate its purpose.
The scientific museum, on the other
hand, is the product of a curiosity
and literalness that are purely Teuto¬
nic, and it grew out of the hereditary
accumulations of the petty German
rulers. These collections, like the hu¬
manism of the North, were more con¬
cerned with the dawn of science and
social regeneration than with beauty.
The intellectual movements here were
essentially religious ; they developed
a rational spirit of enquiry which
helped, in many ways, to bring about
the Reformation.
A phoenix from the Bishop
The collections themselves compris¬
ed gifts of all sorts, sea shells,
fossils, stuffed alligators, mine¬
rals, works of gold, silver and glass,
as well as a hodgepodge of painting
and statuary. The Archduke Al-
brecht of Bavaria possessed, for
example, 3,407 objects which included,
in addition to 780 paintings, "an egg
which an abbot had found within
another egg", manna which fell from
Heaven in a famine, a stuffed ele-
pnant, a hydra and a basilisk.
The Elector of Saxony, Augustus I,
was possibly more fortunate, for his
collections included "a series of por¬
traits of Roman Emperors from
Caesar to Domitian, said to be copies
of originals done by Titian from the
life." To this very remarkable array
were added in 1611 a unicorn and a
phoenix which were presented to him
by the Bishop of Bamberg. Even as
late as our own times Mark Twain
records that it was possible to see in
the sacristy of Cologne Cathedral an
elaborate reliquary containing the
skull of a child, labelled "Head of
Saint John the Baptist at the age of
twelve years."
These objects were gathered toge¬
ther into what was known as the
Wunderkammer. Julius von Schlosser
has shown that the differences in
temperament between the North and
South are inherent in the conflicting
meanings of those two words, Wun¬
derkammer (wonder chamber) and
gallería (the formal gallery). More¬
over the passion for classification
and spinning a priori theories from
artifically established premises had
already begun to assert itself at a
very early date. It set a standard for
unintelligibility which has remained
in vogue until the present day, and
which has done more to keep the
public out of our museums than any
regulations issued by trustees or gov¬
ernmental bureaucracies have ever
succeeded in doing.
Rival royal collectors
There is a strange irony in the
fact that the art galleries of the
world, filled with works of art
originally collected by the brilliant
open-minded humanists of the Italian
Renaissance, are being made a battle¬
ground for conflicting attributions of
iconography and authorship by schol¬
ars trained in the tradition of know¬
ing everything about a work of art
except its essential significance.
By the end of the sixteenth century
the future pathway of museum deve¬
lopment was clearly marked. Political
factors, moreover, were to determine
the successive ' steps by which this
path was to be followed. For, as the
economic crises of the seventeenth
century made it necessary for the
High Renaissance collectors princes,
dukes, merchants, and cardinals to
dispose of their treasures, nationalism
and the conception of absolute mon¬
archy had brought about another
use to which these collections could
be put. The Hapsburgs in Austria,
the Netherlands, and Spain found
themselves in open competition with
the English Stuarts and the Bourbons.
It was obligatory for the Roi Soleil to
shine not only in his own brilliance,
but also to cast the reflection of his
authority upon the accumulations of
the wonders of the past. This was the
philosophy of collecting until the
French Revolution, when the idea of
the public institution virtually the
only one we know today was born.
FRANCIS H. TAYLOR Is Director of the Wor¬
cester Art Museum, Massachussets, U.S.A. and
Director Emeritus of the Metropolitan Museum of
Art, New York. He is the author of "The Taste
of Angels: a history of art collecting from Rameses
to Napoleon" and numerous monographs and
articles on art and archeological subjects. The
article on this page is taken from a paper prepared
by Dr. Taylor under the title "Babel's Tower: The
Dilemma of the Modern Museum" for the Fourth
International Conference of Museums held in
Switzerland, in July 1956.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Today's archaeology was
pioneered by museums
DIGGING UP
HISTORY FOR
THE SHOWCASE
by Sir Leonard Woolley
ROYAL TOMBS at Ur and other sites of ancient Sumerian civilization
in present-day Iraq were excavated in the early I920's by expeditions
financed by Western museums. Excavators at Ur (above, left, digging
out tablets) were from joint expedition of the British Museum and the
Museum of the University of Pennsylvania, directed by Sir Leonard
I
N the old days, which after all are not so very old, say,
sixty years ago, the museums of the Western world
played the principal part in archaeological excavation.
Th& reason for this was simple. Museum directors
needed material to fill their glass cases. Generally speaking
the objects of the sort wanted were to be found in countries
whose people and governments were but little concerned with
the artistic' or scientific importance of antiquities; sometimes
they allowed the free export of such things ; sometimes they
PRIDE AND INTEREST of Near and Middle East countries In their own past history and
cultural monuments have been stimulated by rich finds made in their soil, and have led to deve¬
lopment of national antiquities services and museums. Above, statuettes from temple of Ishtar,
goddess of love and fertility, at Mari, Syria, on display at Damascus Museum, where a great
exhibition grouped priceless antiquities, works of art and documents found in Syria in 1952.
conceded to the excavator half of the objects he found and
kept the other half themselves; sometimes, either from patriotic
motives or 'because they had exaggerated ideas about the
financial value of antiquities, they forbade export altogether;
but the law was not easy to enforce, and often the officials
winked at breaches of it.
Turkey in the days of Sultan Abd el Hamid was a case in
point. When in the early years of this century David Hogarth
dug at Ephesus he found deep down in the mud and water
that hid the ruins of the altar of "Diana
of the Ephesians" a number of gold orna¬
ments and precious figurines carved in
ivory. One evening towards the close of
his season, as he was working over his
catalogue, the Government Inspector
attached to the expedition came and
asked him which, and how many of the
treasures he proposed to take back to
England. As Hogarth had signed an
undertaking to hand everything over to
the Turkish Government he was aston¬
ished at the question and replied that
he was of course taking nothing; the
inspector was equally astonished, and
also very angry that he was not going to
receive the bribe that he had expected.
But not all archaeologists were so
conscientious; thus, nearly all the small
objects unearthed by the German exca¬
vators at Sinjirli found their way to
Berlin. How the famous head of Queen
Nefertiti got there has never been
explained. The German mission digging
at Tell el Amarna discovered it, and at
the season's end the finds were duly
examined and divided by the Egyptian
Government inspector; the excavators
said that he allotted the head to them in
the ordinary way, the inspector declared
that he never even saw it and had he
Copyright Museum of Dasmascus
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Taken from "Digging up the Past" and "Ur : The First Phases" by Sir Leonard Woolley, copyright Penguin Books Ltd.. London and New York
Woolley. Most interesting treasure from Ur now in the British Museum
is the "Standard of Ur", a work in mosaic which when found was nothing
more than minute bits of stone and shell lying loosely in the soil. Months
of delicate restoration revealed Sumerian representations of War
and (above, right) a victory banquet. Top row of figures are feasting
Sumerian captains wearing sheepskin kilts and being entertained by
woman singer and lyre player. Centre and lower rows show servants
carrying in food and soldiers bringing spoils and a bound prisoner.
Such rich discoveries encouraged other museums to enter the field.
By 1933 eleven Western museum expeditions were at work In Iraq.
done so would never have let it go. Scandal says that the
lovely head was shown but shown under an effective disguise
of plaster-of-paris; but whatever happened, Nefertiti went to
the Kaiser Friedrich's Museum, and Cairo refused to licence
any more German excavations in Egypt.
But of course most of the objects acquired by museums
from their own diggings were got legally, conceded to them
by the government concerned. Egypt, for example, (and
Egypt was one of the first countries to organise its antiquities
service) allowed expedi¬
tions to keep half of the
things they found; it was
a very sensible arrange¬
ment, whereby the for¬
eign museums were en¬
couraged to dig and the
Egyptian National Mu¬
seum amassed a vast col¬
lection of treasures with¬
out having to spend a pen¬
ny on excavation.
This possibility of build¬
ing up a national collec- 	
tion "on the cheap" was
one argument in favour
of the law dividing finds equally between the two parties, and
a further advantage was that the dispersal of Egyptian anti¬
quities and their exhibition in foreign museums was wonder¬
fully good propaganda; people in other lands who saw these
treasures of art and antiquity acquired a profound admiration
for Egypt as the birthplace of an ancient civilization, so that
Egypt won a preeminent position in men's minds.
In proportion as the museums of Europe and America were
able by their exhibits to impress upon their public the interest
and the importance of the history which those antiquities
illustrated, the greater grew the demand for additions to the
collections or for their expansion so as to include objects
from other countries which had in the past influenced the
growth of culture.
UNESCO and its International Committee on Monuments, Artistic
and Historical Sites and Archaeological Excavations have always
sought to improve international co-operation in such matters as
access to archaeological sites and the proper study of remains and their
preservation. A series of International principles applicable to archaeo¬
logical excavations has now been formulated and will be presented
for approval to UNESCO'S General Conference in New Delhi in No¬
vember. While recognizing that the regulation of excavations is
primarily for the domestic jurisdiction of each state, UNESCO proposes
to its member states that this principle should now be harmonized
with that of a liberally understood and freely accepted co-operation.
But it was realised that the need could not be met by the
mere purchase of antiquities; things bought from dealers
might be intrinsically important, but their historical contribu¬
tion was small; only the objects found in the course of
scientifically controlled excavation could be considered to have
real documentary value. So it was that more money became
available for excavation and more missions took the field
and nearly all of them were sponsored by museums.
This is very well illustrated by the case of Iraq. After
the first World War the
British, finding themselves
in control of the country,
abrogated the old Turkish
law whereby all antiquities
remained the property
of the government and
introduced the principle
of equal shares between
government and excavator,
and at once the museums
saw their opportunity.
In 1922 there were two
	 missions working, one at
Kish and one at Ur; the
results they obtained were
so important for ancient history and the objects which they
were allowed to take home were so fine and so numerous that
in 1933 there were eleven expeditions in the field, all of them
representing museums of the western world.
This archaeological activity aroused world-wide interest in
Iraq, which was for the country's good, and incidentally
brought in a lot of much-needed foreign money; another
result was the foundation of an Iraq National Museum. When
in 1922 the government's share of objects from the two
expeditions was brought to Baghdad there
was no museum to house them and they were
simply laid out on rough trestle tables in a
government office. Then, as more came in
each year, Miss Gertrude Bell, the British
Cont'd
on
next page
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
DIGGING UP HISTORY (Continued)
archaeologist, took over an old building which served the
purpose for a time, and finally a real museum was built in
'which could be properly exhibited the finest collection of
Mesopotamian antiquities in the world.
But a museum requires a staff, a staff of experts in various
branches, and while at the outset foreign officials had to
undertake the task of guidance, in due time Iraquis, trained
in scientific methods, could form an independent service and
fulfill all the many duties that museum charge entails.
I well remember the government Inspector coming to Ur
at the close of our 1928 season and asking me what was the
best object I had unearthed. I showed him something and
he looked blankly at it and enquired what it was. I told him
that I didn't know. It had undoubtedly been a large and very
fine piece of mosaic, but as its background of wood and
bitumen had decayed and the minute bits of stone and shell
had been lying loose in the soil the only means of lifting it
out which I could devise had prevented my ever seeing it,
since it had had to be
treated half an inch at a
time; what I had now
was an ugly lump of
muslin, wax and dirt,
and I really did not
know what could be
made of it. It would
need months of work
and if the work were
successful it would, I be¬
lieved, prove to be the
best object of the year;
but then nobody could
be sure of success.
The inspector said that
there was nobody
connected with the Iraq
Museum who could pos¬
sibly undertake a job of
that sort; I must keep
the thing and the Iraq
Government would take
in its place the next-best
object, something that
did not need elaborate
treatment. Well, I did
put in months of work,
and the "Standard of
Ur" is the most interest¬
ing of all the treasures
from Ur now in the
British Museum. But
today the Iraq Museum
would tackle such a task
itself and would there¬
fore keep its treasures.
It was the museums of
the world that opened up
Iraq as an archaeolo¬
gical centre, and undoub¬
tedly they were enabled
to do so by the fact that the law allowed them to keep so
much of what they discovered. When in 1934 a new Anti¬
quities Law was passed and the old generous terms were
changed, the foreign excavations, almost without exception,
closed down; digging had ceased to pay, from the museums'
point of view. Egypt also modified its old terms and was no
longer a fruitful field for museum expeditions. Turkey main¬
tained its old exclusive Antiquities Law, justified by the fact
of there being fine museums with scientific staffs for mainte¬
nance and also for excavation. The good work done by
Western museum missions in developing the interest of so
SIR LEONARD WOOLLEY has spent over half a century "digging up
history". From 1907 to 1911 he was with the Eckley B. Coxe expedition
at Nubia in the Sudan and until 1914 was in charge of the British Museum
Excavations at Car*chemish, on the Euphrates. From 1922 to 1934 he
conducted the excavations at Ur in Mesopotamia for the Trustees of the
British Museum and the Museum of the University of Pennsylvania. His
many works include : "Ur Excavations", "Ur : The First Phases",
"Ur of the Chaldees" and "A Forgotten Kingdom".
Copyright Iraq Museum
IVORY MASTERPIECE discovered in Iraq under ruins of Nimrud, Assyrian
capital in the I Ith and 9th centuries B.C., is a plaque showing in a relief a lioness
attacking a man in a lotus field. Inlaid with lapis lazuli, cornelian and gold,
it is one of many important findsinscribed clay tablets, ivory works of art
and potterymade at Nimrud In I 952 by expedition of British School of
Archaeology ¡n Iraq, which were later exhibited in the Iraq Museum, Baghdad.
many peoples in their own past history and cultural monu¬
ments now turned against them in so far as they were now
no longer able to dig, as in former days, for the enrichment
of the Western museums.
But digging goes on. In some parts of the world conditions
still make it possible for museums to play the major part in
such work; but generally changed circumstances have brought
in a change of policy (not to say a change of heart) as
regards archaeological excavation. Today most foreign mis¬
sions working in the field do so under the aegis and largely
at the expense of scientific bodies which are interested in the
increase of historical knowledge, and not in the acquisition of
objects by the museums of their own countries; they are
satisfied that the greater part of the objects found, or all of
them, should remain in the country owning the site, provided
only that they are preserved in a properly organised museum
where they can be studied by scholars; what they do reserve
for themselves is the right to publish the results of their work
and thereby to gain the satisfaction and the credit of having
made a contribution to
scientific knowledge.
Clearly this is a more
altruistic attitude than
that of the museum
which promoted excava¬
tions with an eye to the
empty shelves in its glass
cases, but the present
system could not have
been introduced if the
old policy of museum
acquisitions had not pa¬
ved the way for it.
Those exhibits aroused
the interest of the public
which, in the end, pays
for the work now being
done. Granted that in
the past precious treasu¬
res were allowed to leave
the lands of their origin,
that is the price which
those lands have had to
pay for the recovery of
their own past history
through the generous
expenditure of other
people's money and for
the possession of rich
collections of antiquities
unearthed by members
of foreign archaelogical
expeditions.
Yesterday Iraq might
have complained that the
unique bronze gate-fit¬
tings of Balawat were in
the British Museum; to¬
day an expedition financ¬
ed by the British Institute
of Archaeology in Iraq
and supported also by museum contributions has been
able to hand over to the Iraq Museum a new set of bronze
gate-fittings found at Balawat, no less important artistically
than the original ones from this site, but scientifically more
important because, coming from properly controlled diggings,
they have all the value of known historical associations.
A SPECIAL DOCUMENTARY FILM on today's museums Is
being produced by UNESCO, collaborating with French TV, in
connexion with the International Campaign for Museums. (See
page 22 for a round-the-world review of this campaign).
Intended for TV screening, the film will be a montage of film
extracts from Asia, Europe and the Americas showing work of
museums (with emphasis on their educational role), and illustrating
the latest presentation techniques. UNESCO is also producing
a filmstrip showing how these techniques transform museums
from "storehouses" to places of interest and enjoyment.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
OUT OF BOUNDS TO VISITORS
Reinach and Ethnographical Museum, Neuchatel
The busy world behind the exhibits
A museum is like a theatre with a revolving stage, each exhibition
hall representing a different scene and decor. And behind the scenes
of the tremendous "show" put on by a large, modern museum there
is an industrious little city whose laboratories, store-rooms, offices,
workshops and other services sometimes cover nearly as much floor
space as the exhibition halls "out front". Here, in an area which is
"out of bounds" to visitors, technicians, scientists, artists, craftsmen and
others study, classify, plan and prepare (or repair) the exhibits. The
public has little or no Idea how much effort and skill goes into the
creation of an exhibition like that put on recently by the Neuchatel
Ethnographical Museum, In Switzerland, under the title "Brazilian
Arts". For the "Bumba-meu-boï" dance scene (upper photo) hundreds
of hours went into the moulding and painting of the manikins (lower
photos) and the preparation of the colourful costumes they wear.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Out of bounds to visitors (Continued)
There is an art gallery at the Louvre In Paris (I) which visitors never enter. It is the store
room where the Museum keeps its reserve of paintings, classified and hung on huge, mobile frames.
Paintings in foreground are by Dutch artists. Although the Louvre covers 49 acres, it is still not big
enough to display all its vast collection. Another part of the Museum not open to the general public
comprises five rooms housing magnificent collection of over 75,000 drawings. Collection was founded
in time of Louis XIV when Colbert obtained thousands of drawings. Scholars or students armed with
magnifying glasses (2) are able to Inspect these drawings, thirty-five thousand of which are by Italian masters.
Masterpieces are made to order In a long, curving workshop (3) in Paris, where craftsmen carry out an
unusual museum activitythe reproduction by plaster casting of statues and reliefs exhibited in France's
national museums. Most of the castings produced, ranging from life-sized versions of the Victory of
Samothrace to busts of Napoleon Bonaparte, are purchased by schools, universitiesand artists. Photos
show (4) gelatine mould being filled with liquid plaster (5) original sculpture of the head of Sapho
(on right) with a plaster reproduction and (6) a series of Greek warriors. Larger castings are first
made In several pieces, as in case of this classical statue of a discus thrower (7) and then assembled.
Photo story copyright Louise de Béa
í "
!^^^^^^B
L/ il
¡ i
n
I J?
ÜBT -fc^
mV Vfl ^1
i fi
B** ~~~""*
^ 1--= --
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
BACKSTAGE AT NEW YORK'S
BIGGEST FREE SHOW
by Isabel Mount,
American Museum of Natural History
Some time ago, when a popular
American magazine announced
that it was soon to run a two-
part article called "The Biggest Free
Show in New York", guesses as to its
subject ranged all the way from the
view from one of the city's skyscrap¬
ers to Washington Market at dawn.
Actually the city's "biggest free
show" turned out to be a rambling
collection of Romanesque-style build¬
ings on Manhattan's busy upper
West Side. To the casual eye, accus¬
tomed to the more usual steel-and-
glass facaded attractions with which
New York City abounds, the quiet, ivy-
covered red granite
buildings may have
seemed an odd choice
for first place on the
tourist's itinerary. But
to the two million
people who visit the
American Museum of
Natural History each
year, the choice must
have been a natural one.
For within the
Museum's walls are hous¬
ed the results of more
than eighty-five years of
exploration and research
by leading American
scientists. Fifty - eight
exhibition halls, covering
thirteen and a half acres
of floor space, are filled
with some of the world's
finest collections of birds,
mammals, reptiles, fos¬
sils, minerals and gems,
fishes, insects and eth¬
nological objects. A visi¬
tor can view animals,
minerals or artifacts
from practically every
corner of the globe.
It soon becomes clear
to the discerning sightseer, however,
that there is more to a "show" like
the American Museum than is appa¬
rent on the surface. Attendants are
frequently asked, "'How does all this
come about?" "What goes on 'behind-
the-scenes'?"
There is a great deal more to the
Museum than the average visitor sees,
another twelve acres to be exact. It is
in this "behind-the-scenes" area,
peopled by more than 600 scientists,
technicians, administrators, artists,
craftsmen, attendants and office
workers, that all the American Mu¬
seum's exhibits are planned and
constructed.
The first steps in the development
of a Museum exhibit are sometimes
taken many years before actual
construction is begun. The idea may
originate in a busy laboratory, or it
may germinate thousands of miles
from New York City during one of
the institution's field trips. In either
case research by one of the Museum's
scientists is usually the starting point
for a display designed to share na¬
tural history secrets with the public.
The scientist who is planning an
exhibition must first decide how he
wants to tell the story of his research
and what he wants to include in that
story. Then a synopsis of his ideas is
cleared with the administration, and
a concerted effort is made to ensure
that the new display will make the
greatest possible impact on the many
different people who will see it.
Next in the line of progress of the
exhibit is the Museum's Planning
Copyright Swiss National Museum
FOR THE RECORD: Photography is now considered one of the essential
"behind the scenes" activities in large modern museums. Jobs for the photo¬
grapher are many and varied making complete film records of certain collec¬
tions, preparing illustrations for catalogues, producing filmstrips of exhibits.
Above, photographing sculpture at the Swiss National Museum, Zurich.
Department. Here the scientist dis¬
cusses the subject matter he wishes
to show with architects, artists and
designers. And here basic scientific
theory is translated into visual inter¬
pretations that will interest, amuse
and instruct those two million yearly
visitors. Blueprints are drawn up,
and if necessary, models are made.
More discussions are held. Colour and
lighting are studied and their most
advantageous use debated. Then,
final plans for a new exhibit, com¬
bining modern display techniques with
the most recent advances in scientific
knowledge, are put on paper and
construction of the exhibit is begun.
At this stage, the project is ready
for the hands of those special artists
and craftsmen usually found only in
a Museum of this kind : background
painters, leaf and flower makers,
model builders, sculptors, tanners and
taxidermists. Because many of the
materials shown in the Museum's
famous habitat groups (authentic
recreations of a scene at a particular
site at a specific time of the day)
cannot be preserved, artificial leaves,
flowers, trees, bushes, fruits, berries,
and at times even rocks, must be
made in the Exhibition Department.
Among the most highly specialized
and gifted artists to work on an exhi¬
bit of this sort is the background
painter. It is his job to lead the eye
to believe that the painted objects on
the background are as real as the
actual objects in the foreground. The
curved background on which he works
adds to the feeling of depth, and
perspective and reality,
but requires exceptional
talent for execution.
Using sketches and pho¬
tographs made at the
scene to be reproduced
he must have a natural¬
ist's eye and an artist's
talent with a brush.
When an animal is to
be used in a display
additional problems are
created. The familiar
"stuffed" animals still
found on mantels all
over the world have a
stiffness that destroys a
habitat group's illusion
of reality. So, a different
but far more complicat¬
ed method is used. In
this process, originated
by the late explorer-
sculptor Carl Akeley, and
developed by those who
followed him, a clay
figure reproducing the
animal even to the
detail of its muscle
structure is modeled by
a sculptor. From this
clay model a manikin
with a light, thin shell is made by
several intermediate stages and the
preserved skin is fitted over. The
result is amazingly realistic.
While the Department of Exhibi¬
tion is working on the contents of the
display, the construction personnel of
the Museum are busy building the
structure to house the exhibit. Metal
workers, masons, electricians, carpen¬
ters execute the plans drawn up by
the architects and designers.
Little by little, each man's work
reaches completion and the parts of
an exhibit finally blend into a whole.
Many people have shared in the deve¬
lopment of the idea since the scientist
originally set his thoughts to paper.
Many hands and talents have been
used in its completion. Now the
exhibit is ready for the millions who
will see and be entertained by it, and
who it is hoped will learn a great deal
from it. Now it is ready to teach man
more about the world he lives in.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
OUT OF BOUNDS TO VISITORS (Continued)
HOW TO BUILD A DINOSAUR. Gorgosaurus, one of the largest
and most vicious dinosaurs and king of beasts some 75 million years
ago, went on display recently at the Chicago Natural History Museum
together with Lambeosaurus, his victim, also a large dinosaur but
vegetarian in habits and probably a gentler creature. Museum palaeon¬
tologists worked for 1 8 months to prepare the fossil skeletons of
Chicago Natural History Museum
these two giants as an exhibit showing "Gorgo" looking down upon
the dead Lambeosaurus. Gorgosaurus, whose skeleton was excavated
near Edmonton, Canada, is 26 feet long, has a head rising to a height
of I 5 feet and in life is believed to have weighed about six tons. Inset,
a specially built steel construction for Gorgosaurus skeleton which
eliminates the need for vertical supports and also maintains balance.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
PALAEONTOLOGISTS* PUZZLE at the Chicago Natural History
Museum consisted of seven large crates containing giant dinosaur
skeleton. The skull alone weighed 205 pounds and was 42 inches long.
PEEK PREVIEW for young museum visitors of Gorgosaurus tower¬
ing over wall behind which the striking exhibit is being prepared
Skeleton was museum's most important acquisition in recent years
GORGOSAURUS : TERRIFYING
OVERLORD OF BEASTS SOME
75 MILLION YEARS AGO
WELDER AT WORK putting into place metal discs which separate
vertebrae of Gorgosaurus. Only seven skeletons of this kind of dinosaur
have ever been found. Museum reconstruction was an arduous task.
DUCK-BILLED DINOSAUR, the Lambeosaurus, whose skeleton
was found in Canada in 1922. Museum stored it in plaster for years,
awaiting a suitable installation. Months were needed to remove plaster.
Photos Chicago Natural History Museum
MODERN MAMMOTHS, famous fighting African elephants mounted
by late explorer-sculptor, Carl Akeley, whose technique gave strikingly
realistic effect, now have new neighbours the dinosaurs (in rear).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
OUT OF BOUNDS TO VISITORS
(Continued) 3 Works of
rt at the doctor's
Some of the most important but less well-known
of museum activities go on in "hospitals" where
works of art are cared for and restored and In
laboratories where new scientific treatments are
continually being devised and improved. These
hospitals and laboratories have their specialists for
all kinds of works of artpaintings, sculpture, draw¬
ings, ceramics, engravings, mosaics and for different
materials used by artistscanvas, marble, wood,
stone, bronze, textiles. To make a diagnosis of a
"sick" masterpiece, and decide on Its treatment,
experts need to know a great deal about it, from its
origin and history down to materials and methods
used by its author. Photos here were taken at one
of world's best equipped centres for the care of
works of art, the Central Laboratory for Belgian
Museums, Brussels. (I) "Surgeons" at work on
series of sculptures in wood. Specialist working in
foreground is removing overcoatings of paint which
cover original colouring of Roman sculpture of Christ
from church at Gretz-Doiceau, near Louvain. In rear
of workshop (on left in photo) is an electric immersion
tank. (3) Close-up of tank showing a painted wooden
statue undergoing treatment in a mixture of heated
wax, resin and paraffin to preserve it and to destroy
infesting parasites. (2) Special workshop for care
and restoration of paintings. Distinguished "invalids"
shown In photo Include: Memling's "The Mystic Mar¬
riage of St. Catherine" (far left) ; Thierry Bouts' "The
Judgment of Othon" (one part on trestles and the
rest upright behind); and a work by Rembrandt (on
easel in rear). One of most delicate and arduous
restorations undertaken in this laboratory, which
Is directed by M. Paul Coremans, was on "The Adora-
18
tion of the Lamb", the famous triptych from the
Cathedral at Ghent. This operation, in which Unesco
was associated, lasted for two years. Works of art
from museums in all parts of Belgium come to the
Central Laboratory, and churches and private collec¬
tors in Belgium and other countries make use of its
services. Another of the world's Important restora¬
tion laboratories is the Istituto Centrale del Restauro
in Rome which Unesco selected as the site for the
International Centre for the Study and Preservation
and Restoration of Cultural Property. The world's first
restoration centre was set up by the Berlin Museum
in I 898 and the one In the British Museum in 1919.
Copyright Laboratory of Belgian Museums and Presse Univers
BVi'íl'l Km ^Q
i w 3Sr
m!û% mm
fr *
¥ /km'
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
^
i
X-RAYS PROBE
A RUST CRUST
Merovingian buckle unearthed at Namur, Belgium, in
1908 was so deeply encrusted with rust (far left) that
any possibility of cleaning it successfully seemed out
of the question. It remained in this state until last
year when It was sent to the Central Laboratory of
Belgian Museums, Brussels, where an X-ray photo
(centre) revealed the true state of the iron base and
silver decoration under the rust crust, thus showing
restoration was possible. Left, buckle after cleaning.
Copyright Central Laboratory of Belgian Museums, Brussels
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
OUT OF BOUNDS TO VISITORS (Continued)
Modern restoration techniques
rejuvenate Leonardo's 'Last Supper'
The restoration of a fresco painted many centuries ago and
since then exposed to the attacks of time, damp and dust
is a delicate operation requiring long and careful work by
experts. One of the best-known restoration services is that of
the Uffizi Gallery, Florence, Italy, where specialists (right)
are shown at work on a fresco painted in the church of the
ancient hill town of Cortona, Italy, by Fra Angélico, the Domi¬
nican priest who died In Rome just over 500 years ago. Never,
however, has the restoration of a major work of art aroused so
many passions or produced so much controversy as that of
Leonardo da Vinci's the "Last Supper" (far right) which he painted
on the wall in the little refectory of Milan's Santa Maria delle
Grazie in 1497. Even in Leonardo's own lifetime the wall
began to show patches of dampness and, thereafter, down the
centuries, critics, artists, scientists and restorers studied the
problem but never reached complete agreement either on the
techniques used by Leonardo, or on what was causing the damage
or again on which restoration method should be employed. Well-
meaning restorers "bandaged" the cracks with plaster and
retouched the masterpiece. At least six other artists overlaid
Leonardo's work. By 1908 it was shown beyond doubt that
the "Last Supper" was a distemper work and that the damage
was simply being caused by the dampness. A heating system
installed behind the wall eventually eliminated the mildew, and
the colours once more adhered firmly to the plaster. In 1943,
a bomb fell on the refectory and though the mural remained
intact under sandbags protecting the north wall, it was left like
this for two years. When the sandbags were removed a
crust of white mold covered the painting, even a touch dented
the surface and there seemed to be no way of removing the
mildew without flaking off the picture as well. Italian restorers
then injected quantities of a new shellac which was colourless,
waxless and impervious to moisture and within a year the mould
had dried up and the painting remained. After this, a brilliant
restorer, Mauro Pellicioli, went to work with a surgeon's scalpel
and a fine brush for three years and gradually removed the paint
of former restorers to lay bare the areas where Leonardo's
original paint still remained. In places where restoration paint¬
work was covering bare plaster it was left. Today restored to
an approximation of its original purity, the "Last Supper" Is
again revealed as the marvel of light, form and movement that
must have amazed the contemporaries of Leonardo da Vinci-
Uffizi Art Gallery, Florence and Pinacoteca di Brera, Milan
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Secrets of Rembrandt
and Mozart revealed
Using special instruments and scientific
techniques museum experts nowa¬
days "look inside" paintings to dis¬
cover and record things which cannot be
seen with the naked eye or through a
magnifying glass. As a preparation for
restoration or to help determine a paint¬
ing's authenticity, X-rays and ultra-violet
rays are widely used. Earlier this year,
for example, the first complete X-ray
photograph was made of one of Rem¬
brandt's great works, "Julius Civilis Giving
Oath to the Batavians" and was displayed
alongside the work itself at a Rembrandt
anniversary exhibition organized by the
Stockholm National Museum. The work
portrays a group of men taking an oath
on their swords, and experts have long
been puzzled by the outline of an "owner¬
less" sword in the picture. It was hoped
that the X-ray photograph (far left) would
reveal the missing owner of the sword.
Instead of showing a hidden figure the
radiograph brought to light a second
sword, thus adding another mystery to
the painting. Specialists at the Louvre
Museum, Paris, use similar methods, have
developed other special techniques. Photos
(left), show portrait of Mozart at the
Louvre under X-ray examination which
revealed painter's signature and other
hitherto unknown facts. One Louvre tech¬
nique of great assistance to archaeologists
consists of coating illegible inscriptions
with phosphorescent powder and afterwards
photographing them by ultra-violet rays.
Copyright Stockholm National Museum and Louise de Béa, Paris
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL
MUSEUMS WEEK A STRIPED POSTER SAYS 'COME INSIDE'
Wherever you may happen to be this autumn
your eye is likely to be caught by a poster
with a bold black curlicue superimposed on
bright stripes of yellow, red and blue. That poster
will be like an international flag flying in the four
corners of the world all through the second week
of October, 1956. It signals Museums Week, the
International Campaign for Museums sponsored by
unesco, and taken up by one after another of the
member nations.
Each country knows the value of museums,
"symbols", as Mr. Stephen Thomas, Chairman of
the U.S. Committee for the International Campaign,
has said, "of culture and knowledge dedicated to
the use of the people." For the scholar and
student, the object matter stored and provided for
his research and study; for the teacher and educa¬
tionalist, the concrete and vivid adjunct bringing all
forms of education to life; for the child, the spark
lighting first wonder and curiosity; for the ordinary
citizen, that value of a museum most often for¬
gotten, least mentioned, and perhaps most impor¬
tant of allpleasure, delight, the joy of knowledge
and beauty drawn for him from
all the corners of the world.
MtJtMIt-iMI iEach country, therefore,
according to its capacity, is
making an effort to bring these
values home by building some
sort of programme around
Museums Week this October.
Some cannot manage much,
but even those with few
resources are planning to
display the unesco poster and
leaflets, and organize a com¬
petition for children's drawings
as part of the big international
competition sponsored by
unesco, as well as arranging for
special lectures and radio talks.
The importance of museums
to the national life of a country
can be seen from the number
of new museums, or new
galleries in existing museums,
which will be opened in the
course of Museums Week.
They will include a school
science museum in Ceylon, a
new Science Museum in Buda¬
pest, a new art section and a
new archaeological section in the Jerusalem Mu¬
seum in Israel, the foundation of a children's mu¬
seum in Hungary, and two new museums in India,
one of them being founded on the spot where the
revelation of Gautama the Buddha's religious voca¬
tion took place.
Some countries, like Greece, Japan and the Ne¬
therlands, are marking the occasion by publishing
guides and much-needed catalogues; others are
showing new acquisitions. In the United States, for
instance, where over two hundred museums are
taking part in the campaign, the Metropolitan
Museum of New York is opening a new gallery for
its collection of armour, while in Italy, a Marconi
hall will be inaugurated, complete with manuscripts,
instruments, and other objects of interest. Others
again, are organizing special exhibitions. In Bolivia
there will be a display of archeological material from
Peru and north Argentina in the museum at La Paz.
Hungary is holding a Rembrandt exhibition, and
Iraq, remembering the needs of villagers and Be¬
douins, is sending round a travelling exhibition of
antiquities which is based on the theme of "Writing
its invention and development".
The use of the museum to emphasize community
INTERNATIONAL
CAMPAIGN
FOR MUSEUMS
services and promote international understanding
is stressed in a number of American displays. The
Cleveland Museum of Art has organised a big exhi¬
bition entitled "Art, the Universal Language", and
with the co-operation of widely assorted bodies
another American museum, the Canton Art Institute
in Ohio, is arranging sets' of children's drawings to
be exchanged for similar sets from Mexico City,
Japan, Israel, and Ave South American countries.
Countries are borrowing ideas from each other.
There must be many who remember the charm of
the mid-day concerts held in the National Gallery
in England during the war. A large number of
museums are organizing concerts as part of Cam¬
paign Weekin particular both France and Poland
are inaugurating the whole Campaign Week with a
performance of Darius Milhaud's "Cantata", the one
at the Louvre in Paris, the other at Warsaw, where
the National Museum is being reopened for the first
time since the War. Receptions are being held at
the Louvre and the old Hotel de Lauzan in Paris,
while London is starting the week off with a big
reception at the National Gallery held under the
auspices of the Queen Mother.
For some years the Louvre
has made a practice of illu¬
minated displays at its Friday
night openings, and visitors
from all over the world have
gone home to talk about the
wonder of the Winged Victory
gleaming white against black
shadow, and the sudden beauty
of a small Egyptian figurine
lit up like a jewel. A number
of museums have taken a leaf
out of the Louvre's book, and
are celebrating Museums Week
by opening at night. Bolivia is
running evening opening from
8 to 12 p.m., as well as flood¬
lighting the museum; so is
Japan, and also the Arnhem
Museum in Holland.
. IMUIMlti.MII. 111.. »11 -it-
HV WMUK-im OF I NKSCll
19 3 6
Many museums have consi¬
dered the Biblical injunction
"Cause them to come in". A
number of them, as in Greece,
Israel and Japan, are institut¬
ing free entrance to their mu¬
seum for that week ; special
stamps, special post-cards, illu¬
minations, all play their part. In Paris there is a
museums display from the provinces displayed in an
underground station (see opposite page) ; in Ame¬
rica shop-windows are being used. In some places
school-children are being taken to special displays;
in others special displays are being prepared and
taken to school-children.
The brightly striped poster with its black curlicue
will be everywhere the second week in October. It
signals Museums Week. It signals, to every passer¬
by, an added richness in his life which, maybe, he
has refused, maybe, overlooked; and maybe, will
now accept.
MUSEUM
The International Review for Museums, published by
UNESCO
Annual subscription (4 Issues) . S5.00 21/- 1.000 fr.
Each number	 S 1.50 6/- 300 fr.
Enquiries and subscriptions should be sent to: Sales
Division, UNESCO, 19, avenue Kléber, Paris (XVI
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
A n ew pastime for Parisians
BROWSING IN THE
METRO MUSEUM
Unesco - A. Vorontzoff
Probably the last place in the world anyone might recommend
for browsing through treasures of art or history is the
Paris Metro especially the bustling Opera station. And
yet, all during the month of August, Metro travellers turned
their backs on the underground trains roaring by their trains
to spend a few minutes among the cave paintings of the Perigord
or conch-shell collections from the South Seas.
This underground exposition which brought a cross-section of
more than 100 French museums into 23 showcases in the Opera
station of the Metro was part of the International Campaign for
Museums which has been launched on a world-wide basis with
Unesco's sponsorship.
The idea took root a few months previously when the Paris
Metro system offered its showcases in the Opera for one month
to a Paris science museum, the Palais de la Découverte. M. An¬
dré Léveillé, Director of the Museum, suggested that the show¬
cases be used in connexion with the international museums
campaign and the Metro authorities agreed.
So at the beginning of August, museums went into the Metro.
The exhibition was intended to draw the attention of hurried
travellers for a few minutes in between trains... but it went a
great deal further.
On almost any afternoon in August, the Opera station was
visited by the same species of easy-going browser who enjoys
spending an afternoon in the Louvre or wandering along the
book-stalls on the banks of the Seine.
A business man in his late fifties admitted that he had made a
special trip to the Opera station to see the exposition. "'I noticed
it a few days ago from my train, so I decided to take the
afternoon off and see it in a leisurely way," he told the reporter.
He explained that he was interested mainly in natural history
and he was brimming with suggestions for museums. "'I'd like
to see a museum show us the bird life around our cities so that
we could identify it," he said. "When we Parisians go to the
country and see birds, we don't know what they are... all we're
familiar with are sparrows and pigeons."
Nearby, a wizened little man with a huge cardboard box
strapped to his back was peering intently at a beautiful ivory
vase from a Dieppe museum. "I love old objects," he said
to a reporter. "But I'm afraid I don't have any time to talk
to you... I can't let more than two trains go by."
One woman visitor had been particularly impressed by her
discovery of a letter signed by George Sand, part of the exhibit
devoted to museums in the centre of France. She was taking
plenty of time to go round the showcases. She had read about
the exhibition in the newspapers and she had made a special
subway trip to the Opera station to see it.
The exhibition itself offered something for just about every
Metro user. Its first three showcases formed a pocket science
museum, exhibiting locomotive models, a gay-
plumed toucan, marine life, and mineral speci¬
mens. One of the mineral exhibits was a sample
of Montmartre gypsum, quarried only a few hun¬
dred yards away from its underground showcase.
Cont'd
next page
The guide in a small, grey box
Visitors to the American Museum of Natural History in New York nowadays carry a
guide around with them slung on their backs. No "Old Man of the Sea", the guide
In question is simply a tiny radio receiver, housed in a grey-coloured box and
weighing less than a pound. Known as the "Gulde-a-phone" it is the newest thing in
museum education, enabling museum visitors to hear carefully prepared lectures about
groups of birds and beasts as they walk around the exhibits.
Each of the exhibition halls equipped for Its use contains a closed wire loop that acts
as an aerial. Recordings of the lectures are played from a control room, the electrical
impulses are carried to the hall and broadcast from the wire loop. The receiver picks
up the impulses, amplifies them, and the visitor hears the talk through a single earphone.
As each hall talk progresses, the sound of a bell tells visitors when to move on to the
next group. At the end of the tour, which takes twenty minutes for each hall, the talk
begins again for new visitors or for those who may have missed part of it.
Recently the sounds of nature have been put on the recordings. The roll of the surf
on a Pacific atoll, the screaming of seablrds on Australia's Great Barrier Reef, the roars
and coughs of a family of lions, the trumpeting of African and Indian elephants, the cry
of the puma, the gurgling of a New Hampshire brook, the sounds of a Georgia swamp
at midnight, the shrill whistle of an Arctic blizzardall these and many other background
effects have added considerably to the lectures.
The Guide-a-Phone was introduced and developed in the United States after a trustee
of the American Museum had seen a similar device used in a small art museum in Amster¬
dam to explain paintings without the use of loudspeaker or guide. It does not replace
museum labels but acts as a supplementary device to make assimilation of facts about
exhibits more profitable and enjoyable than ever before. Now other American museums
are taking up the idea. American Museum of Natural History, New York
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Unesco photos - A. Vorontzoff.
METRO MUSEUM (Continued)
Then, for the 35-franc price of a Metro
ticket, the exhibition took travellers on a
tour of the museums of France. Cham¬
pagne had ancient champagne bottles, of
course, while Alsace displayed a section of
Griinwald's famed Issenheim altarpiece
from Colmar.
Wooden ships and iron men sailed into
the Opera station in the Brittany show¬
case with a few souvenirs of Surcouf, the
French privateer, and an old flintlock.
In a showcase devoted to ethnography,
a sarcophagus from Oceania stood along¬
side the mask of a Congo witch-doctor and
a delicate lapanese print. Renoir and
Picasso were represented in the Provence
exhibit which centred on a photograph of
the sun beating down on the old Roman
arena at Aries. In front of this showcase,
there even seemed to be a hint of lavender
and scrub pines in the tired Metro air.
The Perigord region was represented
by objects from the Stone Age discovered
in its caves. And the Loire Valley stayed
in character with a silver "'tastevin" (the
cup used for wine tasting) and one of the
old books of learning ridiculed so
sublimely by Rabelais.
Metro users lingered over the exhibition
and came away enthusiastic. A white-
haired lady said she thought the display
should be made a permanent one. One
of the most avid admirers was the
plainclothes policemen assigned to keep
watch over the objects displayed (their
estimated worth is more than 10,000,000
francs$28,000 or £10,000).
"Take that conch-shell in the natural
history window", he told a reporter. "I'm
interested in zoology, so I took its name
yesterday and, when I got home last night
at midnight, I looked it up. I never
thought I'd be able to go to a museum
on this job."
FROM SPORT TO WINE MAKING
A look at some unusual European collec¬
tions. Above, tournament scene a
maquette In a travelling exhibition on the
history of physical culture prepared by
the National Museum, Cracow, Poland.
Right, ladder of super dumb-bells in the
Sports Museum, Stockholm. Below, the
ancient wine-presses and huge casks in
the Hotel des Ducs which houses the Bur¬
gundy Wine Museum, in Beaune, France.
National Museum, Cracow; Copyright P. Almasy;
and G. Franceschi, copyright Musée National des
Arts et Traditions Populaires, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
CEREMONIAL MASKS from different African regions form part of
unique collection in museum of Dundo, in Luanda region of Angola,
whose people, the Quiocos, are famous mask-carvers. Museum at
Taken from £/ Arte Negro by José Ocorio de Oliveira, published by Indice, Madrid, 1956.
Dundo, probably Africa's largest ethnographical museum, was founded
by Angola Diamond Company and has become a widely-used centre
for studies of African art and culture. It is considered unique in its field.
They stay close to the people
by Grace L. Morley
Amuseum has been called "a window on the world."
That it often is when it brings together the art or
science of the world at large for exhibition and
explanation in its own halls. But it can also interpret its
local scene or a limited subject, if used like a high-
powered lens to bring into clear focus and strong relief
characteristics and important features. Examples are
local museums everywhere and museums devoted to a
single theme.
Variations in museum development and programme,
however, are infinite, as a recent 70,000 miles round-the-
world trip to survey nearly 100 museums in 40 cities of
Africa, Asia, Latin America and Australasia revealed. Yet
despite the greatest diversity in aims and local conditions
and the contrasts in organization and programme, the
contribution museums make to contemporary society
stands out clearly.
Perhaps the most interesting examples of museum ser¬
vice to the local community are among those found in
British East and Central Africa. Museums here have
prehistory, natural science and ethnology collections, on
which an imposing amount of scholarly publication is
. based, but their exhibitions are planned to help directly
the local populations. For the foreigner from Asia or
Europe seeking to learn quickly about the people and the
country, they are the usual short-cut to knowledge, be¬
cause of their direct visual communication. But for the
African, who now uses them most, they have a broader
function: they provide a link with his own recent past
and they furnish an insight into the contemporary scien¬
tific world, drawing on it to help him in his daily life.
In the Rhodes-Livingstone Museum of Northern
Rhodesia daily concerts of African music on tribal
instruments, ceremonial costumes and traditional crafts
which have so largely disappeared as urban culture
spreads, represent for the African his ancestral arts and
traditions, honoured in a way to encourage his own
pride in them. The Zanzibar museum has exhibits on
the history and products of the island and models that
illustrate the best way to arrange farm buildings for
health and convenience, while the National
Museum in Bulawayo has health and
hygiene exhibits, designed to teach visually,
as well as sculpture from Zimbabwe and
costumes of the region. In Nairobi the
Corydon Museum presents vividly the
Cont'd
next page
TEACHERS' CLASSES and art
courses for more than 40,000 chil¬
dren drawn from Hawaii's schools
are chief features of The Honolulu
Academy of Arts' applied educa¬
tional programme. This art mu¬
seum In remote Hawaii is associa¬
ted with Honolulu's Bishop Mu¬
seum whose vast and world-
famous collections Illustrate folk¬
lore and culture of Pacific peoples.
Sato, Honolulu Academy of Arts
UP-TO-DATE SETTINGgreen,
grey and white colour scheme and
neon-lighted showcasesenhances
striking effect of ancient Congo art
In Museum of Native Life at Leo-
poldville, Belgian Congo. By pre¬
serving this old art, museum en¬
ables young artists to draw Inspi¬
ration from traditional cultures.
Lamote, Musée de la Vie Indigène
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Close to the people (Continued)
story of prehistoric man in that region where he deve¬
loped early and left much evidence of his life, and com¬
pletes it by relating it to prehistory elsewhere. It has a
section on Bushman painting, and others on natural
sciences, but it also has exhibitions on timely subjects.
Important as is this function of interpreting the en¬
vironment, of serving as a teaching medium on science,
natural history and applied sciences, and as a link with
the industrialized life which is making such rapid pro¬
gress in the country, the museum as a preserver and in¬
terpreter of the traditional past probably has its most
important role to play in Africa's rapidly changing society.
Guardians of the Maori treasures
Museums in New Zealand, which have collections of
Maori arts and ethnology and architecture, likewise
have meaning for the original inhabitants of the
country, and bridge to some extent the long step from a
pre-European period to the present. Several of the
museums act as official custodians of Maori meeting"
houses, canoes, and other treasures which still retain
symbolic significance for the people, and they also accept
from Maori families guardianship of family ceremonial
treasures which, on occasion, are borrowed back for use
at some family function. The result is that the museums
are living places of pilgrimage and a part of the life and
pride of the Maoris.
Ethnological collections have importance in Africa and
New Zealand because of their meaning for the people
themselves, but in many places museums of ethnology
and those with collections of the related material of folk
and popular arts are valued sources for artists in develop¬
ing a national style and adding to national culture.
The Museum of Popular Arts in Lima has collected and
put attractively on exhibition fine examples of ceramics,
wood, metalwork and textiles from various parts of Peru.
Peruvian painters study them as well as local pre-
Columbian material, just as Mexican artists, in develop¬
ing their distinctive art, drew on their folk arts and
Aztec and Maya archaeology.
Humorous scenes from daily life
For the same reason, in Dacca, East Pakistan, a region
especially rich in popular arts, the new National
Institute of Art has provided exhibition space for
a museum of popular arts on a small scale, deliberately
planned to aid the young artists being trained there to
remain in contact with the arts of their own tradition
even while learning to take their place in the contem¬
porary international world of art. The toys of Bengali
children, the covers on which women stitched and quilted
geometric patterns or quaintly humorous scenes of daily
life in bright colored silks, the ceramics and brass work
used in the villages, all reflect a long tradition of decora¬
tion and have meaning in terms of contemporary design
for the life of Pakistan today. On the other hand, the
Museum of the Indian in Rio de Janeiro collects and
exhibits the popular arts of the peoples of the Amazon
and of other distant regions of Brazil, not yet much
touched by urban life, primarily to inform Brazilians
about the richness of the cultural patterns in their own
country and so bring it into the whole country's life.
Another example of a museum that remains close to
the people, but in a quite different fashion, is the Mu¬
seum Albert Sarrault in Phnom-Penh, Cambodia. It has
a great collection of Khmer sculpture including many
statues of the Buddha, and some of them are still vene¬
rated. The clusters of praying faithful here and there
in the shady halls of the great museum give a reality and
a sense of relation to life.
Everywhere museums respond in some fashion to local
needs and conditions. Those described here only a
few of the striking and unusual forms museum adapta¬
tion has taken in widely separated places are eloquent
evidence of museum use and usefulness.
DR. GRACE McCANN MORLEY has been director of the San Fran¬
cisco Museum of Art since 1934, prior to which she was Curator of the Cincin¬
nati Art Museum Ohio. Between 1946 and 1949, while on leave from the
San Francisco Museum of Art, she was Consultant for Museums to the
Unesco Preparatory Commission and later became Head of UNESCO's Divi¬
sion of Museums. She has written many articles on contemporary art and
Latin American civilizations and her books include, Le sentiment de la nature
en France dans la première moitié du xvm« siècle.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Haunting museums
hidden in the jungle
by Franfz Laforest
SOUTH East Asia was the meeting
place of the civilizations of Outer
India and South China which,
superimposed on a vast pre-Aryan
and pre-Indonesian culture, produced
one great cultural entity embracing
all Asia of the monsoon area. The
coasts of India, Indo-China and
South China were the bases from
which these civilizations, taking on a
maritime character, extended their
cultural influence as far as Madagas¬
car and many of the islands in the
immense expanse of the Pacific Ocean.
One of the
most interesting
aspects of the
cultural unity
which was esta¬
blished between
several races,
from Eurasia to
the outer fringes
of Polynesia, is
the expansion
of Megalithic
culture whose
monuments are
associated with
a complicated
magico-religious
cultural pattern
about which we
still know very
little indeed.
The megaliths
appear to be
closely con¬
nected with the
various forms
of agrarian
"worship" : sun
worshipping,
phallic or erotic
worship (sym¬
bolizing the fer¬
tility of the
soil), and hu¬
man sacrifice, and the stones erected
had a definite funerary purpose.
Many of them are associated with the
souls of the dead, or were intended
as commemorative monuments.
Apart from various forms of archi¬
tecture such as terraces, truncated
pyramids, staircases and tiled walks,
several types of megalith are in
evidence, in an area stretching from
northern India, to Easter Island in
the Pacific. The best known are the
human or animal representations, of
which remarkable examples exist in
the islands of the Marquesas, in Su¬
matra and on Nia Island off the coast
of Sumatra.
In most of the countries, non-
representational stones erect or
horizontal antedated stones of a re¬
presentational character. Several
morphological types of very curious
megaliths still puzzle archaelogists.
Vertical stones and horizontal ones
placed side by side which are found
over an area from northern India to
the Gilbert Islands, appear to sym¬
bolize men and women. Stones laid
WOODEN PHANTOMS, these mysterious
statues stand In hundreds amid the tombs of
certain Bahnar cemeteries In Indo-China, like
mouldering exhibits in a jungle museum. Eaten
by weather and decay and Invaded by the
forest growth, they will eventually disappear.
Raoul Coutard, copyright Laforest Mission
horizontally on smaller stones would
seem to be "seats for the souls of the
dead", or sacrificial altars.
On Nias Island, various megaliths
encircle regular seats and benches
bearing beautifully sculptured human
or animal heads. But the most
remarkable groups of megaliths are
those constituted by whole fields of
enormous jars carved in stone, found
in Laos and on Celebes Island; some
of these are as much as ten feet high
and five feet broad. Near the jars lie
a great many stone discs, weighing
several tons
and measuring
as much as four
feet in diameter.
Did these serve
as lids or
covers?. The
megaliths, i t
would seem,
were for fune¬
rary purposes.
Where social
conditions and
geographical
environ-
ment dictated,
wood was used
as raw material
by the "sculp¬
tors of gods",
before, along
with, or after
the use of stone
as, for instan¬
ce, in the "'tot¬
em", pillar or
tomb statues of
Outer India and
Oceania. These
different sculp¬
tures often stem
from the same
creative idea,
and from icono¬
graphy similar to that which is
widely found in Megalithic culture.
It is believed that at the end of the
Neolithic age in South East Asia the
great stone working techniques were
abandoned, the introduction of metal
implements encouraging the develop¬
ment of wood-working. The use of
wood contributed, in any event, to the
construction of a large ocean-going
fleet, which was a dynamic factor in
the development of many commu¬
nities and set on foot a great move¬
ment of trading and exchanges.
Continuity of tradition in wood
statuary occurs again with the Nagas
of Assam, the Proto-Indo-Chinese of
the mountains of Indo-China, the
Dayaks of Borneo, and in certain
islands of Micronesia, Indonesia,
Melanesia and Polynesia.
This statuary reflects the same
preoccupation with the supernatural.
It is, in particular, associated with the
worship of the dead. Even quite
recently the Jarai and Bahnar of the
Annamese mountains surrounded
their tombs with many sculptured
statues in human and animal forms.
This art of "detached" sculpture is
imbued both with a spirit of realism
which might have stemmed from
Hindu art, and with a "harmonious
archaism", a planned adherence to a
style which is very akin to the art
of Melanesia.
Certain Bahnar cemeteries which
have been abandoned to the whims of
nature offer a striking spectacle.
Hundreds of statues, covered with
moss, weathered by rain and shackled
, by tree roots, stand erect in the
depths of the luxuriant forest.
Tombs, now in ruin, are surrounded
by four small megaliths, and by
mysterious figures. The "thinkers",
at the corners, recall the korwars, of
Melanesia. Are these statues "com¬
panions" for the souls of the dead?
Some, highly erotic in character,
represent couples locked in an em¬
brace. Do they symbolize a rebirth,
or a survival?
These fascinating ana naunting
museums are filled with wooden
phantoms which, eaten up by weather
and decay, and imprisoned by the
forest growth, will eventually dis¬
appear, taking their secret with them.
The megaliths, however, will long
survive, as inscrutable relics of a
glorious past.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Pilgrimage to
Dostoïevski street
The surroundings and atmosphere In which Fyodar Dostoïevski
worked have been faithfully reconstituted in the Moscow house
(in Dostoïevski Street) where the famous writer once lived.
Top photo, Dostoevski's spectacles and pen among other
personal objects. Centre, his portrait watches over the writing
desk. Below, Soviet citizens pay a visit to the "home museum".
LEO TOLSTOY
IS STILL AT
HOME TO HIS
VISITORS
Among the Soviet Union's thousand or so museums there
are none more "alive" or more carefully looked after
than the one in Tolstoy's house at Yasnaya Polyana,
some sixty miles south of Moscow on the Kursk road. To
reach it from Moscow, the visitor follows the motor highway
which passes through forests filled with "dachas", or villas,
through whose open gates he may catch a glimpse of Russian
families at home, some preparing food and others in the
garden, often planting sunflowers.
The road passes through many vil¬
lages where in summer the peasants play
cards on benches beneath the shade of
the poplars which let drop a fine dust of
pollen known locally as "summer snow".
At this time of year, hammocks are
slung between the trees and campers'
tents are pitched on the grass. T.V.
aerials contrast . strangely with the
"isbas," the gay, carved wooden huts
whose style is exactly as it was half a
century ago, and on whose roofs they
are mounted.
Beyond Tula and its lake, which look
just as they were described in the older
editions of Baedeker, is Yasnaya Polyana
and the Tolstoy Museum in what was
once Count Leo Nicolaievitch Tolstoy's
estate and park. The trees were planted
200 years ago and the houses built by
Tolstoy's grandfather, who appears in the
writer's work as Prince Volkonsky are
about 150 years old.
The deserted forest glade, the old
tennis court, the orangery, the pond
covered with water-lilies and lentisks just
as it was when the Tolstoy family bathed
in it, and the "nightingale walk" where today, too, the birds
sing in their thousands all combine to produce a feeling that
time has stood still here and that the life of half a century ago
continues.
"The Soviets have an unrivalled gift for bringing the past
to life and glorifying it when they wish", said a foreign diplo¬
mat in Moscow, recently. The secret of this success is
perhaps best explained by Alexander Ivanovitch Popovkin,
the curator of the Tolstoy Museum, an elderly man who
reminds one of "Anatoli", a character in "War and Peace".
"'To bring a museum to life", he says, "calls for great
reverence, affection, and attention to detail." Popovkin
Leo Tolstoy in the park
of his estate two years
before his death in 1910.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
has devoted himself to his own task so single-mindedly
that he appears to have forgotten everything outside it.
Though he knows everything that has been written, the
world over, about his hero, his own world seems to stop
short at the bounds of the Tolstoy estate, which he manages
in the manner of some stewards of bygone days.
The same attitude is widely found among curators in the
Soviet Union, whether at the Lenin, Chekhov or Dostoievski
museums, at the Hermitage in Leningrad, or at the museums
of Erivan in Armenia, Tiflis in Georgia, at Kiev, at Odessa
or in other places. Everywhere curators seem to have the
same devotion to an individual, the same worship, not so
much of history, as of a personal representative of national
culture.
The Union of Soviet Socialist Republics is a country where
the cult of the museum is akin to a religion, in which the
past seems to be incorporated in the present, and the whole
combined in the purpose of preparing the future. This is no
exaggeration. In small villages of the Ukraine, for exam¬
ple, peasants can be seen queueing up on Sundays to visit
their local museum and ignoring the cinema. In 1942 the
peasants of Peterhof, near Leningrad, preferred to die rather
than to tell Goering's treasure hunters where they had
buried the statue of Catherine the Great in the park of the
Tsars' summer palace.
A clock marks the death hour
When visiting that park last year, one traveller was struck
by the emotion which some former émigrés, returning
as tourists to the U.S.S.R., betrayed at the sight of the
palace and gardens, which had been reconstructed exactly as
Peter the Great himself had planned them. On the spot
where, less than ten years previously, a bloody battle had been
fought, everything was now once more what it had been in
the past. Peter's city Leningrad and its museums, which
had suffered so cruelly during the war, had been rebuilt, lov¬
ingly and faithfully as had the churches of Nizhni Nov¬
gorod, Kazan and Vitebsk.
Reverence for the past and an attention to detail are every¬
where in evidence in Tolstoy's house where the hands of
the clock still point to five minutes past six the time, in the
morning, when Tolstoy died, At the top of the wooden
staircase, which Turgeniev and Gorki climbed so often be¬
hind Sophia Ivanova, the writer's wife, are the living rooms.
Tolstoy's bedroom has been left exactly as It was on the day of his
death. Hundreds of thousands of Russians have visited it since then.
Soviet Information Service photos
In this room, furnished with almost monastic austerity, Tolstoy wrote
his two greatest works, "Anna Karenina" and "War and Peace".
There is the table set, with the bell to summon the servants.
Among the pictures is a portrait of Tolstoy's eldest daughter,
Tatiana, who died in Italy in 1950.
In Countess Tolstoy's boudoir and in the writer's study,
nothing has been touched since November 17, 1910 when
Leo Tolstoy put out his candle one night, after laying his
pen on a sheet of paper and placing a marker at page 54 of
"The Brothers Karamazov". So many other personal ob¬
jects are here a little ivory abacus, the black leather divan
on which Tolstoy was born and which stood behind him in
the room where he worked, the dictaphone presented to him
by Edison, and a piece of Siberian stone, given him by a
group of workers after he had been excommunicated as a re¬
sult of the "Resurrection" scandal. "'Nothing will arrest thy
fame" were the prophetic words which the workers had had
engraved on this stone.
The emotional effect of the objects in Tolstoy's bedroom
seems even greater. On the night table, a half consumed
bottle of Vichy water; under the pillow, a used notebook; and
again a snuffed out candle. At the foot of the .bed is a
cushion, embroidered by his sister, a nun who, after unkind
treatment at the hands of her brother, made a point on her
return to the convent of sending him this dedication in lace:
"From one of the 700 'idiots' of our Congregation."
Invaded by a felt-shod crowd
IN the wardrobe, are clothes which illustrate one of those
paradoxes that marked the path through life of this com¬
plicated man. Under the peasant clothes he affected, he
wore shirts made for him by the English firm of Shanks and
Co. in Moscow, and his pyjamas came from the shop called
the "Carnaval de Venise".
The library, with its 25,000 volumes; the desk of the sec¬
retary, who is still alive; the portrait of Tarpán, Tolstoy's
favourite horse; the room like a monk's cell in which he
wrote "Anna Karenina" visitors pass from one personal
souvenir to another and reach at last the nightingale-filled
garden where Sophia Ivanova bred adders and exterminated
cats. She died in 1919.
On every opening day, the Tolstoy Museum is silently in¬
vaded by a felt-shod crowd. "'They make no noise at all
and they never damage anything," says the curator, "although
they have been coming in hundreds of thousands, and ever
since Tolstoy's death in 1910."
And yet in this House of old Russia, all these living people
with the wonder written on their faces, seem far less real
than the presence of Leo Tolstoy himself.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
MUSEUM V. EXPERTS. Panel of specialists
stares hard at 35,000 year-old-skull of woolly rhl-'
noceros, one of the unusual museum objects they
are asked to identify on popular B.B.C. telecast.
Copyright CO. I., London
Museums' telecast
with 5,000,000 fans
' ANIMAL, VEGETABLE, MINERAL ? '
by Paul Johnstone
Archaeology has never been so popular as it is in
Britain today. Archaeological discoveries are head¬
line news and the more important excavations have
crowds of interested visitors. University extension courses
and adult education classes in archaeology are hopelessly
over-subscribed. More volunteers than can possibly be
used wait to take part in digs. Serious books on the sub¬
ject printed in cheap editions sell in vast numbers.
This tendency has existed for some time but its most
striking encouragement has come in the last three years
from a television programme called "Animal, Vegetable,
Mineral ?". In this programme, three experts are con¬
fronted by a selection of unusual objects from a museum,
which they are asked to identify. The chairman, who sees
fair play, is a lecturer in archaeology at Cambridge Uni¬
versity, and a different museum supplies the objects for
each programme.
The critics gave the programme a cold welcome when
it started. Professors and fossils seemed an unlikely
source of entertainment, they said. Of what possible
concern could it be whether a bronze razor was B.C. or
A.D. But the public thought otherwise. There was a sense
of wonder at the uncanny skill of a man who could take
one look at a carved wooden idol and say which island in
the Pacific it came from, or date a stone tool by its shape.
There were the wild guesses viewers themselves made,
until told the answers, and then the drama of the gradual
approach of the experts, clue by clue, to the same.
Finally, there was the good talk. Good talk is a rarity
on television, but here it has every chance. The experts
do not have to rehearse, look at cameras, take cues or
undergo any of the normal tiresome restraints of appear¬
ing on television. They just have a good dinner together
and then sit round discussing a number of interesting
objects as they are passed from hand to hand, while the
cameras eavesdrop on their conversation.
Expert was right about the rapier
Today the programme has had one of the longest runs
of any on British television and evidence of its
popularity is the size of the audience some five
million people who "watch it regularly. Its two principal
performers are probably the best known academic figures
in the country. Dr. Glyn Daniel, the chairman, was
awarded in 1955 the annual silver medal of the Television
Society of Great Britain. Sir Mortimer Wheeler, the most
frequent member of the panel, was in 1954 elected Per¬
sonality of the Year by the Television Producers' Guild.
The museums too, some of which may have annual
attendance of only a few thousand, are delighted that
audiences of such size should see their treasures and lis¬
ten to some of the greatest authorities in the country talk¬
ing about them. Between fifty and sixty have now con¬
tributed to the programme and many have reported in¬
creased attendances after the programme, with numerous
enquiries for the objects seen on the screen.
But there is one aspect of the programme which mu¬
seum curators regard with a certain caution. A number
of times their identification of objects has been ques¬
tioned by the experts and subsequently altered. A typical
instance was a beautiful rapier which a museum said was
Spanish, early 17th century. When it was handed during
the programme to Sir James Mann, perhaps the greatest
expert on arms and armour in the United Kingdom,
30
he soon declared the hilt to be 18th Century, the blade
late 17th century, and the name of the maker inscribed
on it, by which the museum had dated it, to be a forgery.
Investigation after the programme proved him to be right
and the rapier now has an altered label in its showcase.
Curators of course, especially in smaller museums, can¬
not possibly have the specialized knowledge to check all
their collections themselves or the time to consult other
authorities except about the more important pieces. They
have therefore found the programme useful too for getting
a line on objects they cannot identify themselves. The
answer may come from the panel or from viewers.
¡Grandma's peeler and Viking's thimble
!
I
For instance there can only have been one or two
people in the whole country who could have helped '
one puzzled curator over a mysterious carved piece
of bone found with other Viking objects in Norfolk. For¬
tunately one of them was watching and was able to
inform the museum that it was an early type of Scan¬
dinavian thimble. On the other hand innumerable letters
were received about a 19th century mechanical potato
peeler. This was used for peeling apples, not potatoes,
many viewers declared, because they could remember
their grandparents using just such a machine for that
purpose.
The programme has had other repercussions too. A
national newspaper, conducting an enquiry into the
effect of television on reading habits, discovered from
librarians that this programme more than any other had
widened people's choice of books and encouraged their
reading of archaeological books.
Other papers have reported that volunteers at exca¬
vations and pupils of adult education and extra-mural
classes largely ascribe the awakening of their new interest
to the programme.
Then the Manchester Museum reports that casual finds
brought to them for identification and dating have more
than doubled since the programme started.
Finally the programme has considerable possibilities for
closer international understanding. Already museums from
Denmark, the United States, Ireland, Australia, France,
and Switzerland have safely and successfully contributed
articles from their collections to the programme and
visiting experts from America, Canada and Denmark have
appeared on the panel.
Similar types of programmes already exist or are
planned in France, the Netherlands, Denmark, Switzer¬
land and the United States. The first transatlantic
exchange programme, in which American experts, on
film, were seen discussing a group of objects immediately
after their British colleagues, in the studio, had done the
same, was a definite success.
Now we are planning to televise a programme of British
experts in a Dutch museum with a Dutch Television unit
sending the picture back via the Eurovision link to
Britain. This programme, which is planned for
November 1956, should be unique in various ways. It
will be the first time the programme has actually origi¬
nated in a museum in a country outside Britain.
We are also hoping to televise programmes from
museums in Belgium, France, Italy and Denmark. The
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
programme from Denmark, we hope, will coincide with
the celebration of the centenary of the Danish National
Museum at Copenhagen in May 1957.
In the meantime we have developed another version of
the programme in which, instead of objects, details from
famous paintings are given to the experts to identify.
The viewer is first shown the whole of the picture, with
a detail marked in, and told what the picture is and by
whom. The experts are then shown the detail only, very
much enlarged, and asked to identify it.
We have already shown details from the National
Gallery in Washington and the Metropolitan Museum of
Art, New York, as well as British galleries. We have also
successfully applied the principle to architecture, giving
the experts details from famous buildings to identify.
But perhaps the most remarkable programme of the
last year was the occasion when the objects were provided
by the National Museum at Prague. They were after
wards put on display for ten days at the British Museum.
These international contributions are very vital to the
programme, for as it reaches its fifth vear with its
popularity apparently undiminished, it becomes more
than ever necessary to turn to other countries to maintain
the interest and appeal of the material that is shown.
Clearly the possibilities for using television in this way
to increase mutual understanding and appreciation of
other countries' art treasures and history are considerable
and it never ceases to be a subject of wonder and pleasure
to me that I should have had the privilege of starting
this programme and seeing it develop so remarkably.
Paul Johnstone launched the "Animal, Vegetable, Mineral ?" TV programme
in 1952, a year alter transferring to TV from the BBC. Overseas Service.
Other programmes which he has produced include "Hidden Treasure" which
takes televiewers on a treasure hunt of art and archaeology, "Modern Uni¬
verse" which illustrates man's discoveries, and "Up-to-date", a modern près,
entalion of historic events like the Battle of Hastings and the Great Plague.
COLLECTIONS IN THE KEEP
One of the largest provincial mu¬
seums In Britain is housed in the
Keep of the Norman Castle overlook¬
ing the ancient city of Norwich In
Norfolk. Over 1,000 people visit It
everyday. Photos on this page show
some of the many reasons for which
both the general public and special¬
ists use Norwich Museum. Above,
museum teacher and demonstrator
points out features of Museum's
Norman architecture to visiting school
children. Fearsome looking dragon
as " Snap " was used in
local civic processions from 1451 to
1835. Left, curator of another British
museum photographs some of the
600 teapots In the collection to illus¬
trate a book he has written on York¬
shire pottery. Right, two specialists
reconstruct ancient pottery they
found on site of Anglo-Saxon town
of Theodford (now Thetford) which
is some 30 miles from Norwich.
Copyright CO.I., London
P? /utà
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
see them
/Wj*y
The Saturday Evening Post, U.S.A.
"Watch this I wired it for sound !"
The Saturday Evening Post
'Never mind how he got in there! Get him out!"
Natural History, U.S.A.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the editor
Sir/
I am impressed by the interest and authority of the
material you publish, but I have not yet seen many
articles about Negro countries. There is so much to tell
about the development and the past history of these
peoples about whom usually so little is known in Europe.
We may know how India in particular and Asia in
general fit into the picture of world history, but countries
far removed from the tropics should also know what life
is like there.
Perhaps by collaborating with the Institut Français
d'Afrique Noire (French Institute of Negro Africa) which
has made a long study of African art, the unesco cou¬
rier, a cultural magazine in the broadest sense of the
term, could introduce its readers to Negro Africa (French
West Africa, Equatorial Africa, Madagascar, etc.). I am
sure that your readers are curious to know why witch¬
doctors, fetishists and other similar things exist.
I am not suggesting this for chauvinistic reasons, but
because of my constant desire to see culture being spread
(the aim of your magazine if I am not mistaken). The
publication of articles describing the cultural, economic,
artistic and social life in these countries would show
readers of the unesco courier the speed with which the
peoples have "evolved" in the Occidental meaning of
the term.
Sergeant Ibrahima Doumbduya,
La Redoute, Algiers,
North Africa.
Sir,
The unesco courier is so good that I am recommend¬
ing it as widely as I can as being far and away the best
value for the general reader's money even at the new
rate I
There is one feature I would like to see added, and
that is notices they need not be extensive reviews
of books, particularly of books good for giving to young
people. I am sure such a feature would be welcome to
many readers and very useful.
John A. Ritchie,
Upper Hutt, New Zealand.
Sir,
The unesco courier is worth more than the subscrip¬
tion we pay for it. Very often we read the articles in
our Sunday morning meetings and then discuss them.
But, however cheap it may appear to subscribers of other
countries of the world, here in India the former rate was
more tempting to the intending subscriber. I think the
inclusion of a few pages of advertising would consi¬
derably help towards meeting the loss incurred by the
lowering of the rate. Advertisements to attract tourists
can be drafted so as to help the cause of international
understanding. Therefore I request you seriously to
consider the proposal.
N. G. Gudi,
P.O. Shirahatti,
District Dharwar,
India.
Pen friends wanted
Georges TRUCHET, 28. of 8. rue Clairaut, Paris. 17e. France. Hobbies: Yoga
and photography. Wishes to correspond in English or French with an Indian or
Japanese reader.
Sakea TANAKA, 23, of Futabasoen Apartment, Nagailce-cho, Abeno-ku, Osaka,
Japan. Reads the Spanish edition of the UNESCO COURIER. Understands English,
French, Spanish, German, Swedish. Finnish and Russian.
Charles McCANN, 30, of 5, cours Maréchal-Foch, Aubagne, B.-du-R.. France,
wishes to correspond in French, English, Russian, German and Spanish.
Takujo YASUMOTO. 17. of 28 Keya-Choo. Fukui-City, I. Japan. Interests:
music, foreign currencies, reading, and sports. Collects stamps, postcards, maga¬
zines, newspapers and national flags of all countries. Writes English.
Régine HELLER, 22, kindergarten teacher, of Wuppertal Elberfeld, Moritzstr. 6,
Germany. Interests: literature and music. Corresponds in English or German.
Enrique J. FALCO, av. Gral. Flores 583, Las Piedras Canelones, Uruguay,
seeks a correspondent from "any country, and of any religion or race". Interests:
sport, good books, stamp collecting and rare objects. Wishes to correspond in
Spanish, French, Italian, English or Portuguese.
Emmanuel Oludele AKINWUNMI, 32, of 49, Victoria Street, Lagos, Nigeria.
Writes English. Interests: Scouting, picture collecting, geography, swimming and
boating.
Robert RAMIK, 20, of Fakulta electro, Karlovo nam. 13, Prague II, Czechoslo¬
vakia, wishes to correspond in English. Can also read French and Spanish. Inte¬
rests: classical music and art. Collects postcards.
M. JOSEPH, of 16, Rue Bois des Moines, HoufTalize, Belgium. Wishes to
exchange ideas especially on the ways of life and customs of different peoples
and to exchange illustrated magazines and picture postcards.
RAJESHWARI. an 18-year-old girl, of Jodhpur, India. POB-100. Interested
in the way of life of other peoples, she seeks correspondents in any part of the world.
Marcelino Francisco MIRANDA, of Villa Nueva de Guaymallen. Mendoza'
Argentina. Seeks correspondents in Asiatic and African countries. Write English,
French and Spanish. Hobbies: philately, reading and sports.
Cassim KHARWA, university student, of P.O. Lennoxton, Newcastle, Natal,
South Africa, wishes to correspond with girl students in the United Kingdom,
Ireland, Italy, Turkey, Greece, Persia, France and Sweden. Interests: general.
Language: English.
Sandor BEKESI, 36, of Budapest, I, Attila-utca 103/3/3, Hungary, bed-ridden for
the past 18 months following an accident, wishes to correspond in English, French
or German. Interests: ways of life and cultures of other peoples, art and architec¬
ture, post-card and picture collecting.
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's National distributors from
whom the English, French and Spanish
editions of the UNESCO COURIER
can be obtained are listed below.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 303. Flinders Street, Melbourne,
Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C°., Spengergass 39, Vieuna V,
BELGIUM. Louis de Lan noy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15, rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). 80 Belgian francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090, Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6, Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19, Avenue Kléber, Paris, 16a.
CCP. 1 2598-48, Unesco Bookshop,
Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G..
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bom¬
bay I; I 7, Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta
13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Jakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P. O. B. 4154. Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Case I la Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99,
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6, Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26, Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100, Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. CM.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60, The Mall.
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35, The Mall. Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Ouiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16, South Frederik St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgacen 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5,
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva.
5.20 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2. rue Cook.
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 551-3, Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center. 152 West 42nd St, New York,
36. N.Y,
Columbia University Press, 2960, Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. (except
periodicals).
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
D'AM BUILDERS' DOMAIN: A hy¬
draulic laboratory built by the Government of
India with aid from unesco is now being used
for teaching and research at the Indian Insti¬
tute of Technology, Kharagpur. It was plan¬
ned by Dr. Otto Walch of Germany, who has
just completed a four-year mission to India
under unesco's share in the U.N. technical
assistance programme. In the laboratory,
water from a 60,000-gallon tank is pumped
through steel troughs equipped with plate-glass
observation windows so that studies can be
made of the behaviour of scale models of
dams, locks, canals and other forms of water¬
way construction.
MATHS PROBLEMFOR EDUCA¬
TORS: Present-day teaching of mathema¬
tics, particularly in secondary schools, is
inadequate according to reports presented
in Geneva recently at the 19//i Internation¬
al Conference on Public Education con¬
vened by Unesco and the International
Bureau of Education. Educationists from
74 countries attending the conference de¬
clared that to correct this situation more
qualified teachers were needed, as also
were new textbooks and new methods
adapted to scientific progress and relating
figures to facts in everyday life. Pupils,
they said, should be encouraged to experi¬
ment with mathematical processes instead
of having ready-made adult thinking
imposed on them.
O UR CROWDED PLANET: The in¬
crease in the world's population between
1953 and 1954 brought its total to
2,652,000,000, according to estimates recently
published in the United Nations Demographic
Yearbook for 1955. Most highly populated
countries were the Chinese mainland:
583,000,000; India: 377,000,000; the U.S.S.R.:
214,000,000; the U.S.A.: 162,000,000; Japan:
88,000,000; Indonesia: 81,000,000 and Paki¬
stan: 80,000,000. The breakdown for the vari¬
ous world areas was as follows: Asia (exclud¬
ing the U.S.S.R.): 1,451,000,000; Europe (ex-
WANTED-NEW
PEN FRIENDS
FOUNDED four years ago by the
Osaka Unesco Association in
Japan, a group called "Unesco
Pen Pals" now numbers 1,500 young
people mostly schoolboys and girls
and college students who corres¬
pond with friends in 44 countries.
These young Japanese, ranging in
age from ten to thirty, hold regular
meetings when they compare the
letters they receive, hear talks from
visitors to Japan and see foreign
films. They also publish a quarter¬
ly bulletin. They are still seeking
new pen friends who can corres¬
pond in English. Individuals,
schools and groups who wish to
make pen friends in Osaka should
write to : Unesco Pen Pals, the
Osaka Unesco Association, Nishishi-
mizu-machi, Minami-Ku, Osaka,
Japan, giving names, addresses, sex,
age and hobbies. (See page 33 for
list of "Unesco Courier" readers
seeking pen friends.)
EDITORS OF YOUTH MAGAZINES HOLD
FIRST INTERNATIONAL MEETING
EDITORS of youth magazines published in 18 different countries had their first
opportunity to discuss the problems and purposes of their publications when
they met recently in the Unesco Youth Institute at Gauting, near Munich,
Germany.
The 30 young editors agreed that their magazines could in many ways con¬
tribute to education for international understanding, in particular by satisfying
the desire of young people the world over to learn more about other countries
and to understand international problems. Many editors stressed the role their
magazines could play in education for citizenship by presenting different view¬
points and encouraging constructive criticism.
Discussions on common technical problems took place and contacts were estab-
ished for further exchanges both of periodicals and information that could help
to improve magazines' content and form, which, it was stressed, must be adapted
to present-day economic and social changes.
eluding the U.S.S.R.): 404,000,000; North and
South America: 357,000,000; Africa:
210,000,000; Oceania: 14,400,000.
SPARE TIME ARTISTS: Several inter¬
national instructional courses in painting
have been given to European workers this
summer through an arrangement between
unesco and the International Federation of
Workers Travel Associations. The courses,
held in Austria, Belgium, Italy and the
United Kingdom, aimed to encourage
workers to draw and paint in leisure time.
They were attended by men and women
from nine European countries.
T
ELE-CLUBS FOR JAPAN: Japan is
launching a UNESCO-sponsored pilot experiment
in the use of television for rural adult educa¬
tion patterned after an earlier experiment
carried out in France with unesco co-opera¬
tion. Some 40 community viewing groups, or
"tele-clubs", will be formed this year in
schools and civic centres in areas covered by
the transmitters of Tokyo, Nagoya and Osaka
to test the validity of applying to Japanese
conditions the, experience gained in the for¬
mation of French rural tele-clubs. (For a
story on French rural TV see The unesco
courier May 1956; U.S. July).
MORE HORSES ON WHEELS: Horses
and mules are being replaced by tractors
on the world's farmlands, but the camel
still holds its own as a pack and draught
animal, according to the Food and Agricul¬
ture Organization's latest Yearbook.
Nearly 500,000 more tractors are being
used each year (figures for the U.S.S.R.
not included) and in 1954, tractors in use
totalled 7,100,000 (4,497,000 in North Ame¬
rica alone). While the horse and mule
population dropped from 93,100,000 before
World War II to 74,700,000 in 1953/1954,
camels increased from 7,800,000 to
9,700,000 over the same period.
G UIDE TO CLOUDLAND: A unique
work will shortly be at the disposal of weather
experts and students of meteorology. It is an
International Cloud Atlas on whose prepa¬
ration the U.N. World Meteorological Orga¬
nization has spent several years. The Atlas
will be in two volumes, one having some
200 pages of text and the other 247 photo¬
graphs with captions. An abridged Atlas also
being prepared will contain about 100 pages
of text and 72 photographs.
1,300 MILLION READERS: About
half the world's population, some 1,300
million people, is literate and each year
some 25 million more people learn to
read. Three quarters of the world's
books come from only ten countries and
70 per cent of the world's translations are
produced in only four languages: English,
Russian, French and German. These were
some of the facts underlined by Dr. Luther
H. Evans, Director-General of unesco,
addressing the XIV Congress of the Inter¬
national Publishers Association in Florence,
Italy, Dr. Evans told the Congress, which
was attended by nearly 1,000 publishers
from 17 countries, that Unesco's concern
was for people everywhere to have full and
free access to the printed word a task
needing the co-operation of governments,
the publishing industry and the public.
B ETTER SCIENCE DICTIONARIES:
More than half of the one million scientific
reports and papers issued each year are pub¬
lished in languages that more than half the
world's scientists cannot read. The production
of scientific dictionaries one of the major
tools required by nations expanding industriali¬
zation and scientific research involves serious
problems of compilation and reproduction.
Now, however, such dictionaries can be pro¬
duced at a fraction of their usual cost through
a new method developed by unesco based
both upon a low-cost photo-offset printing
process and a co-operative compilation system.
The new system was recently tested in Egypt,
in relation to physics definitions in English,
and Arabic, by Mr. R.W. Jumpelt who has
been helping to set up a Centre for Scientific
Terminology at the headquarters of Egypt's
National Research Council.
S FAMILY OF 76: Rumania became
UNESCO's 16th Member State after the
Rumanian Minister in London had deposit¬
ed .his government's instruments of accept¬
ance of the Unesco Constitution at a cere¬
mony in the Foreign Office in London,
where the- Constitution is kept.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
TEN YEARS AGO
UIESI'H
SHIP
'Unesco Courier' binders
now available
In response to widespread demand we now offer subscribers
special binders for The UNESCO COURIER. These are hand¬
somely produced in half-cloth with the spine In an attractive
blue, and the title and UNESCO colophon embossed In gold.
Each binder will hold I 2 issues. Copies can be bound easily
at home, and once in place are held securely. Issues can be
removed at will. A series of stick-on gold embossed labels will
accompany each order thus enabling readers to use binders for
any year desired.
PRICE : S2.50, 12/6, French fr. 600, Belgian fr. 100. Price
includes special packaging and postage. Orders can be placed
in other currencies through your local UNESCO agent.
HOW TO ORDER BINDER
1. Remittances should be sent to UNESCO agent in your
country, or direct to UNESCO (DPV), I 9, avenue Kléber,
Paris, 1 6", France. (For payments in French francs: CCP
12598.48 Librairie Unesco, 19, avenue Kléber, Paris, 16«)
2. Remittances must be accompanied by wrapper of latest
issue of UNESCO COURIER received. For CCP orders
wrapper should be addressed separately.
3. Supplies are limited. Offer Is reserved for subscribers only.
If you are not a subscriber, your subscription must accom¬
pany order for binders.
On November 4, 1946, twenty
nations created The United
Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization to
serve the cause of progress
and peace
*
TODAY
Unesco's seventy -six member
states are working together to
achieve this aim
To mark this year's anniversary
The UNESCO COURIER
is publishing a special issue :
UNESCOTHE FIRST TEN YEARS
A frank appraisal
Don't miss this issue
Subscribe today to The
'Unesco Courier*
Annual subscription rate 8/-, S2.50 or 400 French francs
BABEL
BABEL is publishing a special issue for October 1956 on "Machine the assistance of UNESCO, can be ordered from the following address :
Translation of Languages" (MT). Research in this field, hardly a decade BABEL-Verlag, BONN, Hausdorffstrasse 23, Germany.
old, has been dealt with only in sources intended for the specialist
Price per single issue: Annual Subscription:
but press reports have given rise to controversies and speculation.
BABEL now offers to translators and linguists authoritative information
Canada 	 Can. S 0.75
France	 Fr. 850France Fr. 250
on the objectives and realities of MT research and presents first-hand
accounts by leading scientists of recent experiments in the United
States and Great Britain. Italy	 Lir. 400 Italy	 Lir. 1400
BABEL, published by the International Federation of Translators with
BABEL THE INTERNATIONAL
Spain Ptas 25
JOURNAL OF TRANSLATION
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
BEHIND THE SCENES at the American Museum
of Natural History, New York, an army of scientists,
technicians, artists, craftsmen and others plan and
construct strikingly realistic exhibits. Inset, exhibit
for the Hall of the Giant Sloth first takes shape on
drawing board of staff designer. Above, technicians
Install flying bird group. Below, America's largest
and most powerful cat, the Jaguar, exhibited In
showcase representation of authentic Mexican site
Box Canyon, near Caraymas, western Sonora. (See
page 13 for a peep behind some museum showcases
Into places which are " out of bounds " to visitors)
American Museum cf Natural History, New York
HHHBIE^HiHHHHHHHHI
]]>
</page>
</document>
