<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068918eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
BURGESS
ESTRELLA
H
LAMINE KONTE
,
VIGLIETTI
XENAKIS m m
WM
C H O Ri*-
r t
ÍJISíS
Vi < T 1
r»n1«^
; »i
oi t u ¡ - *
n /r./ A/ */ t( . , ht
r«
- .
f ^ « © f O |a> 9 9
?7
9 Cù
9 1
0
* «1 1- d 0
1*1®
le
*-
1
© o 0
*5 «< © 1
0
® Q 0 |® o
&*»,
rj .
V j S II» |o * * ,i ^H
ÄAtU*l
0 9 Q & 0 Q 9 0 C j
'i
h iv tt. ta w
1{B*-
e^ (V
=0
*j-"frj
G* IV«y-t« ^Iiu, 1
MUSIC ON THE MOVE
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live
44 Afghanistan
The man with the rose
The music of Afghanistan has assimilated
influences from an exceptionally wide range
of origins and periods. Incorporated in it
are elements of ancient types of music from
India, Turkey and Russia, as well as traces
of ancient Greek music and certain musical
forms close to those of medieval Europe. It
is thought that some unusual features of the
music of the high valleys of the Pamir moun¬
tains may be traced back to the ancient
civilization of central Asia. Above, Afghan
craftsman in the bazaar at Tashkurgan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
A window open on the world
Editorial
'W
'ITHOUT music, life would be nothing." Nietzsche's
aphorism neatly encapsulates the importance of music in
human history, a subject so vast that this issue of the
Unesco Courier can only attempt to trace a few of the many directions in
which music is moving today the context in which it is created,
produced and listened to.
In the West it is widely felt that music is going through a period of
crisis. It is true that the experimental work of modern composers, in
conjunction with technical innovations, has transformed the conditions
in which both popular and so-called serious music is created through the
mysterious and inexplicable process which Anthony Burgess examines
in this issue. For a modern composer like Iannis Xenakis, scientific
thought is part and parcel of creative renewal, as his own work amply
demonstrates.
While some forms of contemporary musical experimentation are
taking place in relative isolation, other traditional forms are today
acquiring a range and significance they have never had before. In Latin
America this is happening with protest songs and the "nueva canción",
new songs which have emerged from a specific historical situation, and,
as Uruguayan composer Daniel Viglietti describes, have had a conti¬
nent-wide impact.
Musical feedback between continents can be fruitful. It is, for
example, a not uncommon misconception that African music is pro¬
duced within a rigid tradition. How far this is from the truth emerges
from the testimony of Lamine Konte, an African "griot" or musician-
storyteller who in this issue describes the wealth of modern musical life
in Africa and the vitality of its traditional components. He stands at a
cultural crossroads between Africa and Europe, and draws inspiration
from both continents.
China is a country with an especially long musical tradition. An
instrument such as the Chinese lute is surrounded by a pattern of
symbolism which has been recorded in writing since very early times. In
this issue we publish a text on the subject by the great Dutch orientalist
Robert H. van Gulik.
The development of the electronic media (cinema, television, re¬
cords, radio) has vastly increased the accessibility of music worldwide,
so that it is now possible to speak of a "phonosphere", as does our
contributor Mikhail Tarakanov. This phenomenon is not without risk.
In addition to the danger of noise pollution and, eventually, of the
weakening of the creative sensibility to which Professor Nils L. Wallin
draws attention, there is also the possibility that certain forms of
production may distort or debase musical values. The long association
of cinema and opera, whose moments of fulfilment and of tension are
here analysed by Dominique Jameux, is a fascinating example of a
phenomenon in which such risks may arise.
Finally, it is impossible to overemphasize the role of music as a form
of social communication. The pianist Miguel Angel Estrella is a leading
figure among those who are trying to bridge the gap between so-called
classical and popular music, the product of a false antithesis. By
designing a concert hall in which listening ceases to be a passive activity,
a musician-architect like Xenakis is also opening wider the gates of
access to music.
Cover: score of Achorripsis (1956-1957), a work by Iannis Xenakis for 21
instruments. This "stochastic" music is entirely composed on the basis of the
calculation of probabilities. Length 7 minutes.
Photo © All Rights Reserved
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
April 1986
39th year
4 Science and music
An interview with Iannis Xenakis
9 'Nueva canción'
Latin America's song without frontiers
by Daniel Viglietti
12 The mystery of melody
by Anthony Burgess
14 Music for all
by Miguel Angel Estrella
17 Folklore and phonosphere
by Mikhail E. Tarakanov
18 On wings of song
The lute and the crane in Chinese tradition
by Robert Hans van Gulik
21 The griot, singer and chronicler of African life
by Lamine Konte
26 When opera takes to the screen
by Dominique Jameux
31 The modern soundscape and noise pollution
by Nils Lennart Wallin
34 Year of peace: 4
2 A time to live ...
AFGHANISTAN: The man with the rose
? i> ? ? C
A A : ^ * r r f r r r * 'i i
a
A A A A A A
1**3**** r* * * * * * »*»ff »»if »f»»»
AAAAA\AAAA
mWiïm
Unesco's first 40 years
To mark Unesco's fortieth anniversary, the next issue of the Unesco
Courier will be a double number containing an anthology of extracts
from some of the best articles to have appeared in the magazine since it
began publication.
Published monthly in 32 languages English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish A selection in Braille is published
by Unesco French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish quarterly in English, French,
The United Nations Educational, Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque Spanish and Korean
Scientific and Cultural Organization Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. German Persian Korean Bulgarian ISSN 0041-5278
N° 4 - 1986 - DPC - 86 - 1 - 433A
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
c.-
..OH;
co
c,
*V~
Iannis Xenakis, an architect in music and a musician in architecture, has been for over
thirty years a leading composer whose influence has spread throughout the world. Perhaps
more than that of any other living composer, his work illustrates the important role of
scientific thought in the aesthetics of contemporary music. Below, an exclusive Unesco
Courier interview with Iannis Xenakis.
Science and music
An interview with Iannis Xenakis
Iannis Xenakis, besides being a musician
you are also an architect. How do you
account for these twin preoccupations?
I am not really an architect in the profes¬
sional sense of the term. When I worked
with Le Corbusier, a good many years ago, I
was involved in both activities at once. In
particular, I collaborated on the Cité
Radieuse residential complex in Marseilles,
the Convent of Sainte-Marie-de-La-
Tourette in Eveux-sur-1'ArbresIe, near
Lyons, and the city of Chandigarh in India.
And in 1958 I designed the Philips Pavilion
at the World's Fair in Brussels. But since
then I have been concerned with making
music, and occasionally, when the oppor¬
tunity arises, with architecture.
What is your most recent project?
The plan for an experimental concert hall
that I designed with the architect Jean-
Louis Veret. It was short-listed for the Cité
de la Musique music community centre at
La Villette, in Paris, but was not the win¬
ning design. This concert hall is entirely
different from a conventional one. It is a
sort of potato-shape, so as to avoid being
circular, which is very bad acoustically. So it
has a rounded, oval shape, with walls that
bulge slightly. Instead of a fixed floor, there
are cubes one metre wide, each of which
can accommodate two people: the contours
can thus be modified and the levels can be
varied by as much as six metres. This makes
several combinations possible: groupings in
the centre, or several groupings to left and
right, or, again, a traditional stage. The
instrumental performers can accordingly be
placed in the middle, on a platform of
cubes, with the audience all around them.
But it is also possible to shift the focus away
from the centre, or, on the contrary, to
keep everything on one side only. Every¬
thing is possible. Running around the inside
of the walls there is a spiral gallery which
can accommodate the audience and also
musicians, so as to produce a three-dimen¬
sional soundscape. The walls themselves
are perforated with panels which can vary in
their degree of absorbency to obtain the
right degree of reverberation. Moreover,
this entire volume can be made to com¬
municate with another, much larger
volume, which contains it and which opens
outwards, thereby creating a great many
new possibilities for performances. But this
is not mobile architecture. Mobile
architecture never works, because the
machinery gets jammed.
Why is there such a link, in your opinion,
between these two areas of creative activity,
music and architecture?
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
2 2
ra u.
Because architecture is a three-dimensional
space in which we live. Humps and hollows
are very important, in sound as well as in
the visual sphere. The handling of propor¬
tions is essential here. The best architecture
has to do not with decoration but with plain
proportions and volumes. Architecture is
the bare bones. Architecture is something
visual. And in the visual sphere there are
components which relate to what we call the
rational sphere, which is also part of music.
Whether we like it or not, there is a bridge
between architecture and music. It is based
on our mental structures, which are the
same in both cases. Composers, for exam¬
ple, have used symmetrical patterns which
also exist in architecture. If we want to
discover the equal and symmetrical parts of
a rectangle, the most informative way of
proceeding is to rotate it. There are four
directions in which a rectangle can be tur¬
ned, and no more than four.' Such trans¬
formations also exist in music: this is what
was invented in the melodic field during the
Renaissance. You take a melody: (a) you
read it upside down; (b) you invert it in
relation to the intervals; (c) that which rose
towards the upper part of the scale now
descends towards the lower, and vice versa.
To this you must add (d) the recurrence of
the inversion, which was used by the
polyphonists of the Renaissance and which
also occurs in serial music. In this example,
we find the same four transformations car¬
ried out in architecture and in music.
Another example is the Philips Pavilion.
To design this I used ideas borrowed from
the orchestral music that I was composing at
Above, the Philips Pavilion at the 1958
Brussels Exposition, designed by Iannis
Xenakis in what was then a totally new
architectural form composed of hyperbo¬
lic paraboloids. The world premier of
Poème Electronique by the composer
Edgard Várese (1883-1965), with a film by
Le Corbusier, was held in the pavilion dur¬
ing the Exposition.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
^ the time. I wanted to create changeable
spaces, which could be continuously altered
by the displacement of a straight line. This
produces hyperbolic paraboloids in
architecture and masses of glissandos in
music.
Can you give any examples from history of
such a convergence, or even coincidence,
between architectural and musical patterns?
Bartok used the golden section to achieve
his harmonies. The golden section is taken
from the visual sphere. It is a geometrical
proportion, with the additional property
that each term is the sum of the previous
two terms. From the Egyptian pyramids to
the Greek temples, it was used in
architecture as a sort of miraculous key to
the creation of something beautiful.
But for you this correspondence is fun¬
damental?
Goethe said: "Architecture is frozen
music. " If we attempt to go further than this
literary form of words in order to make a
more objective claim, we soon come to
mental structures which fall into the group
category. The rotation of rectangles or
melodies are groups of transformations.
And in fact group theory deals with sym¬
metries, down to the infinitely small level of
particles this is the only means whereby
particles can be identified.
There are thus several levels of corres¬
pondence. The vaguest is the literary level,
that of Goethe; I have mentioned another,
more objective level, with my example of
groups; there are others of a different type
such as that of forming space either in sound
or in architecture by using the acoustic axis
such as glissandos, or the numerical axis.
But there are other possible approaches.
Rhythm, for example. What is rhythm? It
consists of chosen points along an axis,
namely, the axis of time. The musician mea¬
sures time as the walker counts milestones.
The same thing is found in architecture
with a façade, for example. And piano keys
are also architecture. They are regulated in
a constant manner. In one case it is a matter
"" of time , and in the other, of space. So there
is a correspondence between the two. And
this is possible because there is an under¬
lying mental structure which mathemati¬
cians call an "order structure".
Stretching across the top ofpages 4 to 8 Is
the score of" Mycènes Alpha (1978), apiece
of music created by Iannis Xenakis on the
UPIC, a composing machine he invented
(see photo opposite page). The work lasts
approximately 10 minutes.
So in your experiments as a composer, you
draw on experiments in physics, among
other things?
Admittedly, I have not carried out such
experiments myself, but I know that they
are so defined. The surprising thing is that
order structures, isomorphic mapping and
group theory originated with mathemati¬
cians. They created, as it were, a more
searching experimental psychology than the
psychologists of the nineteenth century.
Much later, researchers such as Jean Piaget
discovered that the development of mental
structures in children coincides with these
definitions in mathematics and physics.
In your work as a musician, informatics
plays an important part because of the new
possibilities it opens up. You have even in¬
vented a music-composing machine, the
UPIC. Can you tell us about it?
In the laboratory that I set up twenty years
ago, we developed a system whereby any¬
body at all can compose music by drawing.
It is both a tool for composers and acoustics
experts and a teaching aid for children, who
can learn to think in music without having to
be trained in musical notation learning by
direct experience, in other words. This
could not have been done without informa¬
tics, which yielded possibilities comparable
to those brought by the invention of writing:
preserving thought in symbols. Here, we
can use our machine to preserve musical
thought, since we can also store it.
Do children remain free and unaffected by
the conditioning of a specific musical lan¬
guage?
They do. For example, an Indian or
Balinese child who has learned the tradi¬
tional music of his village will start to think
musically in a different way if he or she uses
this machine. Children can imitate Bach
without having learned musical notation.
Gradually the child assimilates this and
fashions his or her own environment in a
particular style.
How do you use computers at present?
In Diatope (1977), the entire programme of
laser beams and electronic flashes co-ordin¬
ated with the music, which was also pro¬
duced by computer, had been devised by
programming in computation centres.
There were 1,600 electronic lights which
could flash on and off individually in one
twenty-fifth of a second. This cannot be
done by hand: it is too fast and the numbers
are too high. Furthermore, computers and
other new technology available to us can
produce light, so that it becomes possible to
transpose the musical composition into the
visual sphere and experiment with shapes
and movements. The effects of light be¬
come like visible sounds. You can play with
them just as you play with sounds, but in a
spatial dimension instead. The morpholo¬
gical techniques (creating moving or sta¬
tionary shapes) are often the same as in
music. For example, if you want a cloud of
points of light to appear and disappear, you
need to introduce the calculus of prob¬
ability, as I did with sounds. It is the same
technique. But not everything is con¬
vertible...
It should be borne in mind that computer
technology is only a tool. If I use mathema¬
tical functions or even sometimes physical
theories in music, it is because there is a
profound connexion between music and
numbers. All of Pythagorean theory, of
course, is based on this thesis. But it is a
truth which derives from our own mental
structure, nothing more. Once you have
grasped this principle, it is easy to make use
of whole chunks of mathematical thought,
which is already present in music and even,
in some cases, at a much more advanced
stage than in mathematics.
For example, consider what happened
when musicians in the tenth century in¬
vented musical notation, no longer relying
on the vague indications of neumes, but
using the staff and calibrated units of the
characteristics of sound: pitch and duration.
In doing this they transformed sensations
which have nothing to do with spatial sensa¬
tions into spatial notation.
Four hundred years before Nicole
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Oresme and six centuries before the analy¬
tical geometry of Descartes! Music was
ahead of its time. I do not know whether
Oresme or Descartes were influenced by
musical notation, which did exactly what
they did, and yielded even more abundant
possibilities, since pitch and duration have
nothing to do with space, whereas these two
thinkers were working in space. This is only
one instance where musicians, without
knowing what they were doing, have stolen
a march on knowledge and invention in
other areas.
Do you see no sharp dividing line between
traditional musical thinking and the most
modern aspects of contemporary music?
None. There is even a fairly smooth con¬
tinuum which has resulted, for example, in
serial music. The escape from tonal func¬
tions made possible by "dodecaphony", and
later by serial music, was only relative, since
Schoenberg and the Vienna School adopted
self-imposed restrictions in returning to
manipulations of the polyphonic type that
came in with the Renaissance. This was the
criticism that I levelled at the serialist school
in the 1950s. If Schoenberg had been famil¬
iar with the science of his day, including
philosophy, physics and mathematics, he
would have introduced the calculus of prob¬
ability.
So the musician should keep up to date with
contemporary knowledge?
Yes. Of course, this is increasingly difficult.
But even without a thorough knowledge of
every field, he should be familiar with as
Iannis Xenakis with the composing
machine he Invented in 1975 and which
has since won wide acclaim. Known as the
UPIC (Unité Polyagogique Informatique du
CEMAMu), the machine makes it possible
"to compose music through drawing, even
without any knowledge of music or infor¬
matics", with a stylet on the electro¬
magnetic table. It brings musical creation
within reach of everyone and is a useful
educational tool. It enshrines one of the
composer's major preoccupations, the re¬
lationship between forms created in space
and those created in time.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Drawings by Iannis Xenakis of a theatre
and concert hall which he designed in
association with the French architect
Jean-Louis Veret. The building consists of
two volumes: a large multi-purpose area
enclosed by a thin concrete shell (8), in¬
side which is the "potato-shaped" ex¬
perimental music room itself, with its
wood-covered concrete walls. The two
areas communicate by means of pivoting
acoustic panels (1). The building opens
out through sheets of "wavy" glass (4)
onto an elevated platform (6). The project,
initially intended for the "Cité de la Musi¬
que" at La Villette, in Paris, breaks with all
previous conceptions of what a concert
hall should be, and is designed to "receive
music, musicians, their technological
equipment and the audience in three
dimensions".
View from the "Fontaine aux Lions' General access ramp
8
1) Pivoting acoustic panel:
2) Interior ramp for audience, performers,
projection, sound and lighting equipment
3) "Potato-shaped" experimental concert hall
4) Sheets of "wavy" glass
8) Hyperbolic paraboloid shells (thin layer)
5) Helicoid general access and
performance ramp: mJn entrance
9) Outside ramp for movement
\ around the potato-shaped hall
10) Variable relief floor
11) Cloakrooms, rehearsal rooms,
dressing rooms, lifts, etc.
12) Helicoid general access and performance ramp
7) Stage for open-air events
Cité de la Musique, La Villette
Experimental concert hall
and theatre, March 1984
©
O)
ç
ï
(0
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
^ many elements as possible. For the essential
core of knowledge and this is what is mar¬
vellous is easy to impart. For example, if
one talks about degree of order or disorder,
many people know what this means , but not
explicitly. Now, in a film like Battleship
Potemkin (1925), Eisenstein was perhaps
the first to create a mobile art of this kind:
he artistically directs drifting masses of indi¬
viduals, statistical events, since we see
crowds moving one way and then another.
This procedure was followed by other film¬
makers in their turn, notably Abel Gance in
his Napoleon (1926). If you tell people: this
is what happens with clouds or galaxies or
intrastellar gases, they understand im¬
mediately. I believe that there are fun¬
damental concepts which are communi¬
cable.
How do you account for the central place of
scientific thought in your musical aesthetic?
I drew my early inspiration from the culture
of ancient Greece, and especially that of
Athens in the fifth and fourth centuries BC.
This was a period of extraordinary creativ¬
ity in the history of humankind. It saw the
birth of mathematics as we now know it.
From a structural point of view, this ax¬
iomatic, Euclidian science is still continuing
today. There has been no break.
Then there was philosophy. The other
day, I was reading an article about the
formation of the universe. It said that the
whole of science up till now has been based
on causality. But, today, we are starting to
ask the following question: can the universe
have emerged from nothing, without a
cause? Astrophysicists are tending to think
that it did. Accordingly, and this is the
interesting point, the Parmenidean tradi¬
tion is capable of changing and developing.
Besides these influences, there were my
contacts with certain individuals such as Le
Corbusier and Messiaen. Even if he is not a
mathematician, Olivier Messiaen has a kind
of affinity with numbers. This is apparent in
his "modes of limited transposition", and in
his love of Hindu and Greek rhythm sys¬
tems. These two categories of music,
moreover, are mathematical par excellence.
In the sphere of rhythm, which is the hand¬
ling of temporal number in the pure state,
no music has developed further than per¬
cussion in India. African types of percus¬
sion, which are different, are also remark¬
able. With these kinds of music, I feel per¬
fectly at home. I would even say, perhaps,
that I have felt Western music to be more
"exotic" than these .
IANNIS XENAKIS, of Greek origin, is an interna¬
tionally known composer who is also a mathe¬
matician and architect. A former professor at the
University of Indiana, he currently teaches at the
University of Paris I and is director of the Centre
d'Etudes de Mathématique et Automatique
Musicale (C.E.M.A.Mu.) in Paris, which he
founded in 1966. His prolific output of over sixty
works, some of them already classics, includes
every form of musical composition. Among his
works composed in recent years are: Polytope
de Cluny, electronic and laser ray music (1972);
Cendrées, for choir and orchestra (1973); Ais, for
baritone, percussion and orchestra (1980) and
Shaar, for string orchestra (1982). This autumn
his Keqrops, a work for piano and orchestra, will
be performed for the first time, by the New York
Philharmonic Orchestra.
Nueva canción
Latin America's song without frontiers
by Daniel Viglietti
THE history of the peoples of Latin
America and the Caribbean can be
told in song. Apparently the slight¬
est of art forms, a mixture of words and
music full of wit and feeling, songs illumin¬
ate the past centuries of our continent like a
flash of lightning. They tell of arrows loosed
against cannon, and later of peasants with¬
out land and workers without factories.
Even more recently, they are harbingers of
freedom in societies new-born. Song knows
no frontiers: "The great songwriters trans¬
cend geography," observed the Uruguayan
musicologist Lauro Ayestarán. "They cre¬
ate authentic musical units in a way that
El Circo (The Circus), a tapestryby Violetta
Parra, a noted composer and singer of
Chilean popular music as well as a collec¬
tor of Chilean folklore.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
^- races, nations or mere geographical areas
do not (...). Folklore thumbs its nose at
geography."
But not at history. Songwriters are
perhaps the real unifying factors in the poli¬
tical and cultural life of Latin America
today. One reason for this is the extent of
their audience. In a continent where levels
of illiteracy are high , songs can be read with
the ears. As a result of technological pro¬
gress portable transistor radios are ubi¬
quitous, and consequently the popularity of
songs is spreading like seed scattered to the '
winds.
This raises the question of what kind of
seed is being sown, and what kind of harvest
it will yield. In the countries of Latin Amer¬
ica it is impossible to ignore the pervasive
impact of an alienating type of song, for the
most part imported straight from foreign
cultural capitals, or else home-produced
withthe mentality of colonized peoples.
There is undeniable hostility to such trends
as the nueva canción ("new song"). Despite
this censorship, whether direct or indirect,
the song that speaks to the people through
the quality of its message threads its way
through the labyrinth of repression and si¬
lence until it finds receptive hearers. Folk¬
lore, in the traditional sense of the term, is
very close to the strains of the nueva canción
or nuevo canto, questionable expressions
but ones which were accepted by partici¬
pants in the First Festival of New Latin
American Song, held under Unesco aus¬
pices in Mexico City in 1982.
When a rural Ecuadorian, in the heart of
the mountains, listens on his transistor
radio to the Chilean Victor Jara singing his
Plegaria de un labrador (A Farmer's
Prayer), he is, although he may not realize
it, listening to a piece of folklore. Such
songs belong to a group of sometimes
ephemeral phenomena which might be
called "subjective folklore", and which
have not yet been given a place among the
categories made by folklore specialists.
There is also an anonymous mass of sounds
which have left no trace at all, except in
popular memory. To rediscover that
memory, and to recapture the experience of
listening to those sounds, is a task crying out
for new generations of researchers, but
thwarted by a chronic lack of support from
national governments and international
bodies.
The thread of history that stretches un¬
broken from the sounds produced by the
Jew's harp to the cassette recorded by a
singer of nueva canción passes through
stages which are too numerous to describe
in this article. But mention should be made
of the generation of composers and perfor¬
mers which provided a link between that
past and today. And "today" will soon be
"yesterday", if we think of the earliest ven¬
tures of Atahualpa Yupanqui, to take one
notable architect of this continuity between
two periods. A few decades before the ex¬
plosion of the modern media, Yupanqui
would have been a troubadour, a tavern
poet, a wandering minstrel. The amplifica¬
tion of his message (by radio, records, cas¬
settes, cinema, television and video cas¬
settes) has enormously multiplied his im¬
pact. Song, that ancient form of oral com¬
munication, is also taking on a new lease of
life by conquering new spheres of influence
and new publics. Its range and its access to
the media are giving it an added intensity of
purpose and a new potential to affect peo¬
ple and to "heighten awareness".
"New song" is a river through which
several currents swirl. In the late 1950s and
in the 1960s, the Cuban revolution, Che
Guevara and the Chilean experiment pro¬
vided opportunities to develop more direct
and deliberate political messages which
gave added meaning to the term "protest
song". The participants in the First Protest
Song Meeting, held in Cuba in 1967, identi¬
fied more strongly with the aesthetic and
ideological features of the songs than with
the actual term "protest song", which
nevertheless continued to stick for some
time. In the 1970s, other political events in
Uruguay, Chile, Argentina, Nicaragua,
Grenada, El Salvador and Guatemala
boosted the development of this genre.
To sing "from the side of power" was the
novel experience of the Nueva Trova Cuba¬
na, "the new Cuban song" movement,
which set to work with rigour and imagina¬
tion, determined not to yield to the tempta¬
tions of apologetics. The movement was
most successful in the sphere of lyrics,
where it reached poetic heights which were
no obstacle to communication, even with
audiences elsewhere in Latin America. In
musical terms, working in a medium strong¬
ly influenced by the former colonial powers ,
the Nueva Trova began to find its way by
working with the Sound Experiment Group
of the Cuban Institute of Cinema Art and
Industry and with Cuban composer Leo
Brouwer guiding the first steps of the
movement's original singers, Pablo
Daniel Viglietti photographed moments
before the beginning of a concert he gave
as part of Nicaragua's Vacaciones felices
("Happy holidays") programme. The audi¬
ence consisted of children from a poor
district of Managua, the capital.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Portrait ofAtahualpa Yupanqui, one of the
most celebrated composers and singers
of Argentine and Latin American popular
music, by the Ecuadorian painter Oswaldo
Guayasamin (Quito, 1977).
Milanés, Silvio Rodriguez and Noel Nicola.
Launched by such pioneers as Dorival
Caymi and Vinicius de Moraes, the Música
Popular Brasileira a more accurate label
since it does not exclude the purely in¬
strumental has become the Latin Amer¬
ican movement that boasts the richest varie¬
ty of styles and professional possibilities as
well as a relatively wide range of recordings.
As a result, works of great musical value,
such as the songs of Chico Buarque, have
become extremely popular.
It can safely be claimed that nueva can¬
ción today exists throughout "our Amer¬
ica", that voices travel across frontiers and
that we are witnessing the birth of a distinc¬
tive kind of polyphony and the emergence
of a synthesis which is still not widely per¬
ceived, except in the work of certain inter¬
nationally known artists.
Almost all of Latin America has been
subjected to the onslaught of cultural im¬
perialism, and in resisting this it has learnt
to sing of the everyday lives of humble folk,
their joys and frustrations, hopes, sorrows
and festivities, and, when circumstances
make this inevitable, of their suffering in
prison or in exile.
Little has been said of the divided world
of song in those countries where political
conditions have entailed exile, either within
the country or abroad. The nueva canción
of Chile, Argentina and Uruguay, to take
only a few examples, is a kind of duet: one
voice sings within the country, in contact
with harsh everyday reality; the other, in
close contact with the first, sings in exile,
creating and disseminating an itinerant cul¬
ture of resistance.
If we look at this two-sided process in the
case of Uruguay, which has returned to the
path of democracy, we need a wide-angle
lens in order to keep in focus all those who
sang of freedom inside the country. And we
need keen hearing to catch the voices of all
the Uruguayan singers scattered among the
exiled population throughout the world: the
Los Olimareños duo, Alfredo Zitarrosa,
Anibal Sampayo, and many others. The
freedom to create was repressed within our
country from 1973 to 1985, but so it was
abroad, since we were all to some extent
prisoners of a certain attitude towards ex¬
pressing our affliction in song. That "state
of exile" left its mark on our writing. Inside
the country, people sang out of suffering,
but in a spirit of defiance and, with a deter¬
mined gaiety in their creation, they stood
up to be counted in the shadow of the
general danger. (I am thinking of such
groups as Los que iban cantando and Rum-
bo, of Leo Masliah and Rubén Olivera).
Both teams worked in unison, one in the
fiery furnace , the other in the mists of exile ,
to produce a truly passionate counterpoint.
In 1985 the return from exile began, and a
new era called for new songs. In our songs
the oldest among us had to come to terms
with a period when our model democracy
was overwhelmed by oppression. The
young ones, during the dictatorship, had to
sing in a more oblique fashion. And those
who come after us: how will they, in their
turn, have to sing? Facing up to the immedi¬
ate past with eyes wide open? What can we
do now, when "almost" everything is pos¬
sible? In those who chose to stay behind
when they could have left, what strings are
being tuned? In those returning from exile,
what new flowers of song are budding? In
the voices of those who have been released,
what new dreams will take flight on wings of
melody? After the doves and the hawks,
what firebird will come to herald new
songs? Singers of the nueva canción, who
remained, departed or returned, but who
will never be silenced: what new movement
shall we add to the sonata? Or, to choose an
example nearer home, what new stanza
shall we add to the milonga? M
DANIEL VIGLIETTI, Uruguayan composer and
poet, is a leading figure in Latin American music
who abandoned a career as a classical guitarist
in order to write and perform popular songs. A
journalist and a researcher into folk music, he
was imprisoned in his country because of his
songs in 1972, and freed after an international
campaign on his behalf sponsored by such per¬
sonalities as Miguel Angel Asturias, Jean-Paul
Sartre and Mikis Theodorakis. Exiled in 1973, he
settled in France, and returned to Uruguay in
1984 where he was greeted by an immense
crowd of fans and sympathizers. His biography
(by Mario Benedetti) accompanied by an anthol¬
ogy of his songs, was published in French in
1974 under the title Chansons pour Notre Améri¬
que.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
*»
v á
< ~~,/S-The mystery
of
£k.
¿ry Anthony Burgess
«
Text © Anthony Burgess 1986
melody
ANYBODY can write a sort of
melody. Give, as the Chinese do,
each note of the musical scale a
number. Do re mi fa so la ti do : 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 8. You can turn your telephone number
or car registration number into a se¬
quence of notes. This is perhaps not long
enough for a true melody, but it will yield
a theme. A theme may be defined as a
scrap of melody crying out to be de¬
veloped not just into a true melody but
into a whole symphonic movement, into a
whole opera. All music begins with a
germ like that, and it may lie sleeping in a
passport number.
But we all know that the great melodies
of the world are not made in that manner.
The great melodies of the world arrive
without warning. They spring out of no¬
where, and they are only given to the
great musical geniuses.
Perhaps there is an analogy between
the language of speech and the language
of music. In every spoken phrase, even in
a single word, a melody may be lurking.
Take the phrase that comes in a poem by
Edgar Allan Poe "the tintinnabulation
of the bells". Recite that often enough,
and the sheer rhythm regardless of
meaning will generate a musical
phrase.
"La ci darem la mano". Da Ponte gave
that phrase to Mozart in the opera Don
Giovanni, and Mozart heard in it the
melody which begins an exquisite duet.
In one of Beethoven's last string quartets
we hear the question "Muss es sein?"
(Must it be?) and the answer "£5 muss
sein" (It must be!). Beethoven goes to the
trouble of placing the words under the
notes. They are not intended to be sung,
since the musicians are string-players, not
Front cover by Picasso for the first (1919)
edition of Stravinsky's piano arrangement
of his "Rag-time".
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
¿i«
I i
5 LU
II
CD
II
OJ-Q
"Animated Music", a drawing by the French artist Grandville (1803-1847)
which appeared in the illustrated periodical Le Magasin Pittoresque In 1840.
vocalists; the composer is merely being
honest enough to disclose the inspiration
of his theme.
But great melodies are not often bound
to words. Bach's Air on the G String or
the marvellous theme of the Choral Pre¬
lude Wachet Auf are clearly pure sound
which owes nothing to verbal inspiration.
Where did they come from? Anyone
who, like myself, has composed music
may give some sort of an answer. A
melody arrives in the mind. It seems to be
something remembered, something that
has always existed but been long forgot¬
ten. Then it suddenly appears. Occa¬
sionally this melody is genuinely some¬
thing remembered something written
by somebody else. This can cause trou¬
ble lawsuits for plagiarism. There was a
popular song in the 1920s called "Yes,
We Have No Bananas". This is made up
out of Handel's "Hallelujah" chorus, the
folksong "My Bonny Lies Over the
Ocean", and the aria "I dreamt that I
dwelt in marble halls" from Balfe's opera
The Bohemian Girl. Plagiarism? Possib¬
ly. Popular song-writers used to plagia¬
rize all the time. Sheer memory? Possibly
again. Who knows? These things are dif¬
ficult to prove in a court of law.
The truly great tune resembles no
other. It has certainly come from heaven,
or from nowhere, and it usually comes
when unexpected. But it sometimes
comes when it is needed. Imagine that
you are commissioned to compose a sym¬
phony. This is to be performed in two
months' time by a great symphony
orchestra. The least difficult work will be
the orchestration, which will come last.
The most difficult will be finding themes
for the first movement. Here you will
require two main groups of themes, one
aggressively masculine, the other de¬
licately feminine. These themes must be
capable of development that is, turning
into other themes, combining in counter¬
point with other themes, turning into
great soaring melodies. The urgency of
the commission will sometimes force
your unconscious mind into producing
melodic germs full of potential. Or some
little melody composed in childhood will
suddenly present symphonic possibilities.
For another great mystery about melody
is that it is more likely to come to you
when you are seven than when you are
seventy.
The mystery remains. But in an age
like ours, which doesn't approve of mys¬
teries , the production of great melodies is
no longer regarded as one of the jobs of
the composer. Be honest, and consider
which pop or rock song of the last twenty
years contains a genuine melody. You
will hear fine melodies in, say, George
Gershwin or the Beatles, but few in the
music of the Rolling Stones. The sexual
impulse in the rhythm, or the content of
social protest in the words, will seem to
the new generation more important than
sheer melody.
What applies to popular music applies
even more to the music termed serious.
The dodecaphonic composers,' led by
Arnold Schoenberg, showed the way to a
mechanical mode of composition very
popular with the young products of the
music academies. You make a theme out
of the twelve notes of the chromatic
scale a theme of just twelve notes, for
one of the rules is that no note may come
more than once and then you play this
theme backwards or upside down or up¬
side down and backwards. Your musical
skill will lie in the management of tone
colour, of dynamics and climax, but not
in the creation of melody as we used to
know it. You will find such music damn¬
ably hard to sing.
There are people around who say that
there can be no more great melodies.
They say that, with so few notes in the
musical scale, all the original themes
must already have been written and there
is no point in looking for new ones. This is
nonsense. There is still an infinitude of
books to be written out of the twenty-six
letters of the alphabet, and there is still an
infinitude of melodies to be generated
out of twelve notes and the innumerable
rhythmical combinations of these which
wait to be exploited. We have just got out
of the habit of thinking melodically. This
is very bad for us, since there is nothing in
the world more heartening than a great
tune.
Where would the French Revolution
have been without the Marseillaise, a
tune written by a soldier named Rouget
de Lisle, who was suddenly touched by
inspiration? Where would the communist
revolution have been without the Interna¬
tionale (a far inferior tune to the Marseil¬
laise)? But greater than tunes are those
fifty-minute streams of melodic invention
we call symphonies and concertos. These
are always the products of conscious skill
and ingenuity, like works of engineering,
but they could not exist without those
spurts of melodic inspiration from the
unconscious mind. We do not know what
strange inner force is at work spinning
away at themes and tunes, but we bow
down to the results. The great mystery of
music remains.
ANTHONY BURGESS, the British novelist, critic
and man of letters, has devoted much of his
creative energy to music and has composed
many full-scale orchestral works including three
symphonies, as well as The Blooms of Dublin, a
musical version of James Joyce's Ulysses, the
libretto of which is to be published shortly.
Among his most recent published works are
Flame into Being, a study of D.H. Lawrence
(1985), and Homage to Qwertyuiop, a collection
of his essays (1986).
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Music for all
by Miguel Angel Estrella
ONE of the most common prejudices
governing the division of labour in
music, as well as its marketing and
consumption, gives rise to the splitting of
music, musicians and their public into two
warring and apparently irreconcilable fac¬
tions: "popular" as opposed to "classical".
By "popular music" I mean the forms of
music created, sung or danced to by the
people of a country or a region. The word
popular refers to something that "originates
from the people", not something imposed
on it. Thus I exclude from the category of
popular music the soulless consumer pro¬
duct generally associated with the variety
show.
The reality underlying this sterile conflict
cannot be reduced to a mere question of
form. Few people are prepared to admit
that this prejudice springs from an urge to
segregate human beings into social categor¬
ies in defiance of that most universal of all
phenomena art.
This obsolete and snobbish attitude
stands revealed as particularly anachronis¬
tic and reactionary in this day and age when,
one might suppose, the mass media should
be bringing the highest forms of creative art
of all periods within reach of their vast
audience.
But this is not happening. Obscure com¬
mercial arguments, which conceal elitist
attitudes indefensible in other areas of cul¬
ture, separate consumers of music into
those who can choose judiciously what they
will listen to and those who are deprived of
that right and have to be content with
stereotyped works of inferior quality. Low
or non-existent purchasing power and low
standards of literacy or general education
are at the root of this restriction.
It is easy to picture a music-lover living in
a capital city: he buys tickets for concerts
and festivals at which he can appreciate the
performances of the best modern artists and
compare them with recordings made in the
past. He has access to information through
channels which do not necessarily coincide
with the selection that the media impose.
Both his education and the information
at his disposal enable him to choose, and
naturally he seeks out the highest-quality
producers of art and strives to be actively,
or at least passively, involved in the main¬
stream of events in the world of musical
creation, by taking part in the rituals of that
world concerts.
On the other hand, it is very difficult to
imagine one of the thousands or tens of
thousands of country-dwellers or labourers
in Romania, Bolivia, Afghanistan or the
Philippines to take examples from diffe¬
rent continents having any access to this
kind of choice. Such a choice, like all forms
of knowledge, would be one contribution to
a universal vision of human history. And
yet individuals such as these make up the
majority of a country's people.
These population groups, dispossessed of
their ethnic or folk styles of music and be¬
wildered by the bombardment to which
they are subjected by the media, very often
have no choice but to consume pseudo-
artistic products labelled "popular music"
by their main distributors.
This levelling down process now unites
14
most of the world's population. That which
in the past was specific to one area, the
industrialized countries, and to one popula¬
tion group, the city-dwellers, is now, on the
eve of the twenty-first century, interlinking
rural populations, factory-hands and office
workers all over the world. Advertising,
radio, television and records have spawned
this civilization of sound, which is even
threatening to oust written language. And
music is becoming the main vehicle of this
kind of communication. But what kind of
music?
Even in the "developed" countries, we
musicians are aware that disadvantaged au¬
diences believe themselves incapable of
understanding the music of Debussy, Mes¬
siaen, Mozart, Schubert, Krenek or Dutil-
leux (or Astor Piazzolla, Leo Brouwer,
Manolo Juárez, McLoughlin, or Charlie
Parker).
Nevertheless, once the barriers of con¬
vention have been broken down and pre¬
tentiousness and paternalism swept away,
such audiences are highly sensitive to the
essence of the message that these compos¬
ers wished to put across, miraculously trans¬
mitted by the performer. Hence the
tremendous responsibility that devolves on
us musicians as the fundamental negotiators
of this social change, which entails breaking
moulds and leaping over the barriers which
divide us and which cut us off at the same
time from our natural partners in dialogue:
the public.
It would be naive to suppose that
preaching along these lines could bring ab¬
out any radical shift in so entrenched a
structure. The prejudice must be attacked
at its roots. For it is undeniable that we
musicians are trained to fit into an elitist
system which sets itself up as the only possi¬
ble choice. This way of thinking is tanta-
"To take music to the most disadvantaged
audiences, to go to those whose social
and cultural background have hitherto de¬
prived them of this joy and would not nor¬
mallyset foot in a concerthall. " This is one
of the aims of "Musique Espérance", a
movement created by the Argentine pian¬
ist Miguel Angel Estrella. "Musique Espér¬
ance" organizes musical events in factor¬
ies, prisons and schools, and also for the
elderly, for the sick, and for handicapped
children. Left, Miguel Angel Estrella in
January 1983 during a "concert-talk" with
the children of workers at a factory in Bel-
fort in eastern France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
im
9- «¿a. i. "J,°3'"'fJ"-'
f.
ídA
ft
,r A
ê.ïi wies' l
r
,/*~" '"^"""^«w
1^ i ""W
N*
t
I \->*
t»l
4
'Jusf as it should be natural for the music
of Berio to be heard in juxtaposition with
that of CorelIi or Mussorgsky, there is no
reason why the music of Bach should not
be played during a religious service with
Negro spirituals and songs by Rubén
Blades, Leda Valladares, La Melchora
Abalos or ElNegro Mamani... ". Above, The
Song of Songs, an early 17th-century
Flemish engraving after a painting by Cor¬
nells De Vos. On the lectern is the score of
a motet for 5 voices by Daniel Raymond,
cantor at Liège around 1580. Right, Pan
piper in the region of Lake Titicaca, Boli¬
via, during the August festival in honour of
the Miraculous Virgin of the Lake. Left, a
harpistatCuzco, Peru. Below, a concert of
electronic music given by the French com¬
poser Jean-Michel Jarre in the Place de la
Concorde, Paris, on 14 July 1979.
t\\ . - ''"" (V¡i Jf) » »V . " t r 4
~¿^w^Ütt 't^k 're
V:V.^v;*-Ü "Jl \I ' " .1
Ü
¡J
\
«5r
wy
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
^ mount to the fatalistic belief that there will
always be rich and poor.
So first of all the performers must be
made aware of the falsity of this division
between "cultured", "serious" or "intellec¬
tual" music and the other kind. It is essen¬
tial to expose the perversity of this kind of
prejudice, which not only condemns to
mediocrity those who are not invited to the
feast of the elect, but also threatens with
sterility those performers who do not
understand that what gives music its life is
the dialectic between the simplest and most
vibrant forms and those which are most
elaborate and cerebral.
This is the story of our Western music,
and this is the story of music as it has
developed all over the world.
With the exception of a few well-in¬
formed musicologists and those artists who
intuitively realize the truth, few people are
aware of the steady influence of traditional
music on the works of the great composers
of all periods. Nor are they aware of the
social commitment made by many creators
of genius. Each musical era has had its own
reading of the concept of human justice and
solidarity in the development of society.
And each has made different uses of popu¬
lar traditions.
Luther and, later, Bach restored the peo¬
ple to their central place in worship,
through popular church choral music. Dur¬
ing the Enlightenment, music had its in¬
spired leaders with their vision of a society
of greater humanity and justice for all. Such
men as Mozart or Beethoven, each in his
own way, rejected all forms of slavery at a
time when the idea of the democratic State
was beginning to take root.
In the nineteenth century came the
romantic transition to nationalism. And in
our own century composers such as Stra¬
vinsky, Ravel, Bartok, Gian Francesco
Malipiero and Manuel de Falla all belong¬
ing to the so-called "new objectivity" move¬
ment drew inspiration from the spon¬
taneity and immediacy of popular music.
They were opposed to the sometimes over¬
whelming pessimism and density of other
post-Wagnerian trends. Finally, one need
scarcely draw attention to the role of popu-
Flutes made of reed, bone, wood, metal or
terra-cotta, have been a part of musical
tradition throughout the world ever since
prehistoric times. Below, bone flutes
adorned with the feathers of Amazonian
parrots and beetles' wings (Venezuela,
Orinoco basin).
©
16
lar music in the works of Hector Villa-
Lobos, George Gershwin and the Argen¬
tine composer Carlos Guastavino.
Conversely, and to an increasing extent,
musicians in all branches are exploring ways
of developing the technical side of classical
music, and finding in it a source of inspira¬
tion which need not conflict with their
popular calling.
In my country, Argentina, varied and
distinguished branches of popular music are
coming to grips with this influence. Ata-
hualpa Yupanqui is well versed in Creole
tradition but is also a performer of Bach.
Piazzolla, whose early training was similar
to that of Carlos Gardel and Aníbal Troilo,
later sought the counsel of the great French
pianist Nadia Boulanger. The Anacrusa
group, the specifically Argentine express¬
ion of that new syncretic music which ranges
from Chick Corea to Paco de Lucia. Many
more examples could be cited.
So why is there this enduring dichotomy
between classical and popular, when the
two should be inseparable parts of some¬
thing called simply Music, without any
hierarchical segregation? For the good of
music, which is so closely bound up with the
health of society, it is desirable that diffe¬
rent kinds of music should flourish side by
side, without any prejudice between diffe¬
rent genres.
Why should it not be acceptable to orga¬
nize concerts on a satisfactory aesthetic pat¬
tern combining Chico Buarque, Xenakis
and Mono Villegas, Jaime Torres, the
National Orchestra, Susana Rinaldi,
Michel Portal, Patrice Fontanarosa, or El
Cuchi Leguizamón, León Gieco and those
fine pianists Liliana Sáinz and Maurizio
Pollini?
This would at any rate break down the
tyranny of brand labels; for music is not a
commodity. It is a passion which fires its
apostles musicians with the desire to be
witnesses in sound to the spirit of the age.
Just as it should be quite natural for the
music of Berio to be heard in juxtaposition
with that of Corelli or Mussorgsky, I also
think there is no reason why the music of
Bach, during a religious service, should not
reverberate in the same air as Negro spir¬
ituals and songs by Rubén Blades, Leda
Valladares, La Melchora Abalos or El Neg¬
ro Mamani. These last, alas, are unknown
outside the Calchaqui Valleys of Argentina.
For the essence of music is communica¬
tion and communion, energy whose im¬
pulse is directed outwards. And the more
people there are who take pleasure in it, the
better it is for society and, ultimately, for
art.
MIGUEL ANGEL ESTRELLA, ofArgentina, is a
world famous pianist. As wellas giving recitals as
a concert pianist, he has always played to popu¬
lar audiences, including peasant farmers and
Indians in Latin America. Imprisoned and tor¬
tured in 1977, he was freed in 1980 after efforts
made on his behalf by musicians all over the
world, and has since continued his career as a
concert pianist. He is the founder of the Paris-
based association "Musique Espérance" which
aims to bring music and musicians into the ser¬
vice of human rights and to restore to music its
role as a form of social communication.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
by Mikhail E. TarakanovFolklore
and phonosphere
THERE will always be people who claim
that when they listen to instrumental
music or "pure" music it conjures
up no spatial images in their imagination, and
that they experience it only as duration. One
thing is certain, however: it is difficult to con¬
ceive of music as a phenomenon without a
precise image of musicians playing in a speci¬
fic place, whether an enclosed or an open
space. By its very nature, and whatever the
context, music is, and will remain, a perfor¬
mance.
In the USSR, popular music occupies a
prominent position. As we find wherever folk¬
lore has stayed alive, spontaneous musical
improvisation, intended to be heard by a
gathering of people and calling for certain
spatial conditions, is still a major form of cre¬
ative art. Professional art based on oral tradi¬
tion has also been preserved over very wide
areas, in Central Asia and in Transcaucasia,
in the highly elaborate form of the mugam,
epic tales told by renowned artists who have
learned a special technique of singing and
acquired a perfect mastery of the traditional
instruments of the East.
This popular music has conquered new
territory on the stage, on radio, on television
and in records, and in so doing has been
assimilated into the public system of music
consumption. This expansion has had an en¬
couraging impact on the status of music in
general, while at the same time it has pushed
traditional types of creation towards profes
sionalism with the new spatial forms needed
for producing and listening to music and the
professional sophistication that these require.
The creators of folk music have to learn
musical techniques, polish their perform¬
ances and rehearse intensively to prepare for
concerts when they use such specialized faci¬
lities as recording studios, rehearsal rooms,
and the stages of variety theatres. A delicate
problem arises: exposed to the limelight of
professionalism, the spiritual nature of popu¬
lar creative art is likely to wilt, and needs
protection. Folk song and folk dance troupes
are as plentiful in the USSR as they are well-
loved beyond its borders. As a consequence
of this powerful movement to take over folk¬
lore, living folk art is tending to lose its spon¬
taneity and formal continuity and to be turned
into a subject for study and teaching.
Fortunately, a movement is also emerging
to preserve the full authenticity of folk art,
notably through staging performances that
are faithful in all respects to the spirit of popu¬
lar festivals. In many regions folk troupes have
sprung up which are keeping alive the old
styles of singing.
Lastly, new forms are taking shape which
have their roots in oral tradition but are by no
means identical to it. Open-air song festivals
that attract huge crowds are one example of
such a trend. Meanwhile, many popular sin¬
gers and vocal and instrumental groups are
also striving to safeguard the unique charac¬
ter of folk music.
Left, a concert ofpopularmusic and dance
in a vast concert hall at Erivan, capital of
the Armenian Soviet Socialist Republic. In
the Soviet Union, popular music and folk
music are fully Integrated into the public
system of music consumption. This en¬
courages greater professionalism but in¬
evitably creates the risk that some of the
spontaneity and continuity in the creation
of folk arts may be lost.
The masterpieces of folk art are now
reaching more and more people millions of
viewers through television familiarizing
them with the different national styles and
encouraging contact between the hundred or
so nations which make up our country.
It is true that such contacts have a long
history, as is borne out by the tradition of
Russian music of Eastern inspiration dating
back to Rimsky-Korsakov, Borodin and Mus¬
sorgsky; but in the age of the mass media it
has become a phenomenon on a grand scale.
Conversely, the increasing use of sound
production techniques is exerting a growing
influence on the language of music through
the possibilities it affords for manipulating
sound by such means as the special arrange¬
ment of instruments in the concert hall, the
amplification of weak sounds, the "purifica¬
tion" of tone quality, the "broadening" of
sound range, and the combination of pre¬
recorded music or sounds with musicians in
live performance.
Use of these techniques is not confined to
concert performances and the broadcasting
of concerts on radio or television. It also ex¬
tends to the use of music in other fields, some
artistic (soundtracks of cinema or television
films) others not (news or reports on topics of
general interest).
Thus the places where music is listened to
have become more and more numerous,
ranging from the giant stadium to the cinema
auditorium and the radio cassette in the
home.
There is no longer any area of human activ¬
ity from which music can be a priori excluded.
Music, one might justly claim, has won a total
victory over the world in which we live: a
"phonosphere" encompasses the planet. The
problem today is not whether the phono¬
sphere should or should not exist, but how it
can be made more harmonious. The pollution
of daily life by noise, with its consequent blunt¬
ing of auditory and musical sensitivity, has
attained alarming proportions. We must keep
it at bay and, at the same time, allocate a
larger share of the human phonosphere to
music which requires us to listen to it intel¬
ligently and which is charged with meaning.
MIKHAIL EVGENIEVICH TARAKANOV is a
director of research at the Institute of Art of the
Academy of Sciences and of the Ministry of
Culture of the USSR. A specialist in the theory ^""
and history of 20th-century music, he is the -j
author of many published works including The
Style of Prokofiev's Symphonies (1968), The
Musical Theatre of Alban Berg (1976) and The
Works of Rodion Shchedrin (1980).
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
On wings of song
The lute and the crane in Chinese tradition
by Robert Hans van Gulik THE crane is one of the traditional
Chinese symbols of longevity. Just
like the tortoise, it is said to live
more than a thousand years. The express¬
ion "crane age", is a much-used metaphor
for advanced years.
The dark crane is especially credited with
a fabulously long life. The Gu jing zhu
("The Encyclopaedia of the Past and Pre¬
sent") written by Cui Biao in the Jin period
says: "When a crane has reached the age of
oi)
\
?r i
SS-i
s *
«J
fa
o
Ik1
18
i
T
$L
X2P&
one thousand years, it turns a dark blue
colour; after another thousand years it turns
black, and then it is called a dark crane."
Ever since olden times the dark crane has
been closely associated with music. The Rui
ying tu ji (attributed to Sun rou chi of the
Liang period) says: "A dark crane shall
appear at a time when there is a Ruler who
understands music. When in olden times
Huangdi executed music on the Kunlun
mountain for all the Spirits to dance, on his
right side there flew sixteen dark cranes."
Sixteen dark cranes also appear in a story
related by the great historian Sima qian:
"When Duke Ling of the Wei dynasty (534-
493 BC) was travelling to Jin, he halted on
the bank of the river Bu. In the middle of
the night he heard the sounds of a lute being
played. He asked the members of his suite,
but all respectfully said that no one had
heard the sounds. Then the Duke sum¬
moned Master Juan, and said to him: T
have heard the sounds of a lute being
played, but when I asked my suite no one
had heard it. Thus it seems that it is caused
by a spirit or a ghost. Write this tune down
for me.' Master Juan assented and, seating
himself in the correct position, having
placed his lute before him, he listened and
noted down the tune. The next morning he
said: T have obtained the tune now, but I
have not yet learned it. I beg you for one
more night to learn it thoroughly.' The
Duke agreed, and yet another night passed.
On the following morning he reported that
he had mastered the tune. Then they left
that place, and proceeded to Jin. They were
received by Duke Ping (557-532 BC) who
gave a banquet for them on a terrace.
"When all had come under the influence
of the wine, Duke Ling said: 'When on my
way here I heard a new tune; permit me to
let you hear it.' When Duke Ping agreed,
Duke Ling made Master Juan sit down by
the side of Master Kuang, place his lute
before him and play it. But before he was
half through, Master Kuang put his hand on
the strings (to deaden the sounds), and said:
'That is the music of a doomed State; one
must not listen to it.' Duke Ping asked:
'What is the origin of this tune?' Master
Kuang answered: 'It was made by Master
Yan, to please the tyrant Zhou. When king
Wu defeated Zhou, Master Yan fled to the
east, and drowned himself in the river Bu.
Therefore it must have been on the bank of
that river that this tune was heard. Who first
hears this tune, his State will be divided.'
Illustration from a Ming dynasty encyclo¬
paedia shows a musician playing the lute
out of doors with the instrument on his
knees. An incense burner stands on a
small rustic table nearby. Lute playing was
always accompanied by the burning of
fragrant incense.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Duke Ping said: T have a great love for
music. I wish to hear this tune to the end.'
Then Master Juan played the entire tune.
Then Duke Ping said: 'Are there no tunes
that are still more sinister than this one?'
Master Kuang said: 'There are.' 'Could you
play them for me?' The Master answered:
'My lord's virtue and righteousness are not
great enough for that. I may not play them
for you.' But the Duke said again: T have a
great love for music; I wish to hear them.'
Then Master Kuang could not but draw his
lute unto him, and play.
"When he had played once, sixteen dark
cranes appeared and alighted on the gate of
the hall. When he played the second time,
they stretched their necks and cried, they
spread out their wings and started to dance.
Duke Ping was overcome with joy, and
leaving his seat he drank the health of Mas¬
ter Kuang. Having returned to his seat, he
asked: 'Are there no other tunes that are
still more sinister than this one?' Master
Kuang said: 'Yes, there are those by which
in olden times Huangdi effected a great
reunion of ghosts and spirits. But my lord's
virtue and righteousness are not great
enough to allow you to hear this music. And
if you hear it, you will perish.' Duke Ping
said: T am advanced in years, and I have a
great love of music. I want to hear these
tunes.' Then Master Kuang could not but
draw his lute unto him, and play. When he
had played one, white clouds rose in the
northwest. And when he played another,
there was a storm wind, followed by a tor¬
rent, that made the tiles fly from the roof.
All that were present fled, and Duke Ping,
in a great fright, threw himself down near
the entrance of the hall. Thereafter, Jin was
beset by a drought that scorched the earth
for three years in succession."
This story, which is extremely archaic,
not only furnishes a good example of the
relation of the dark crane to lute music, but
also illustrates in a striking way the awe-
inspiring qualities which the ancient
Chinese attributed to this music. Something
of the ominous atmosphere of this old tale
has been preserved in a number of later
ghost stories connected with the lute.
It is only occasionally, however, that we
find faint echos of the magical nature of the
association between lute and crane. In later
times literary tradition replaced this old
belief with purely aesthetic considerations.
When the scholar is playing the lute in his
garden pavilion, a couple of cranes should
be leisurely stalking about. Their graceful
movements should inspire the rhythm of the
finger technique, and their occasional cries
direct the thoughts of the player to unearth¬
ly things. For even the cry of the crane has a
special meaning. It is said to penetrate unto
Heaven: "The crane cries in the marshes, its
sound is heard in the skies," and the female
crane conceives when it hears the cry of the
male.
Detail from an ancient Chinese lute manu¬
al showing the fingerpositions required to
produce notes similar to the sounds made
by animals. Illustration shows "the posi¬
tion of the right thumb to obtain the crying
of a crane about to soar".
The crane is described as having a great
love for lute music. The Qing lian fang qin
ya ("Elegance of the Lute, from the Blue-
Lotus Boat") relates that "Lin Bu greatly
enjoyed playing the lute; whenever he
played, his two cranes would start dancing."
And the same source says about Ye Meng-
de: "Ye Mengde loved the lute, and would
play for a whole day without resting, the
tones of the lute mingling with the sounds of
a brook. Later Ye returned to mount Lu
and sang songs, accompanying himself on
his lute. On one occasion there suddenly
appeared a pair of cranes that gamboled
about and danced in his garden. Ye kept
them, and they did not go away, but started
to dance every time he played."
Several lute tunes hymn the excellent
qualities of the crane. One treatise that
describes cranes in a scholar's garden is
entitled "Song of a pair of cranes listening
to the babbling of a brook". Another tune,
"Cranes dancing in the sky", celebrates the
soaring flight of the crane. The Tian wen ge
qin pu ji cheng ("Collection of Tunes Heard
from the Sky") contains a tune entitled "A
pair of cranes bathing in a brook". The
introductory note added to this tune is not
without interest. "Late in spring I visited a
friend in Sichuan province. A pair of cranes
were dancing in a clear rivulet. I observed
their feathers white as snow, and the top of
their heads red like vermilion. They flut¬
tered up and down, and took their bath
while dancing. Then they spread their wings
and flew high up in the sky, and cried in
harmony in the azure vault, making me
doubt whether they were not Immortals.
Then I drew my lute unto me, and com¬
posed this tune."
The Ming handbook Shen qi bi pu ("Al¬
bum of the Strange and Mysterious") con-
%MKm% ft -k f £
& ft Wf 4M
& n\ & &
& ft 9V « t!r $
ïi& di 4 if ft
cj $( £ & -t. y
¡fe & \V t*7
éî
it
¿7
.»\í->
G=7
19
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
^ tains a tune entitled "Cranes crying in the
marshes". The second half of the introduc¬
tory text says: "The crane is a sacred bird.
Its cries are most clear; they are heard at a
distance of more than eight miles. The pur¬
pose of this tune is to compare the tones of
the lute with the cries of the crane. I kept
two cranes in the bamboo grove surround¬
ing my lute hall. Sometimes, in a shadowy
place, they would dance together, other
times they would fly up and cry in unison.
But they would always wait for the
appropriate time: they did not dance unless
there was a cool breeze to shake their feath¬
ers, and they did not cry unless they could
look up at the Milky Way as if they saw the
gods. When the time was not propitious
they would neither sing nor dance. Recog¬
nizing the spiritual quality of these cranes , I
composed this tune."
Various books give directions about how
to rear cranes and to recognize birds of
' superior qualities. The qualities and outer
marks of good cranes are described in the
Xiang he jing ("The Book of Cranes"), a
book which, though of doubtful authenti¬
city, seems fairly old, and is found in many
compilations of ancient books. Ming trea¬
tises especially abound in discussions about
keeping and rearing cranes, and about how
to make them dance: they may, for in¬
stance, be trained to dance to the clapping
of hands. Chen fu yao (born 1612) says that
excellent flutes can be made from the thigh
bone of a crane: their sound is clear, and in
harmony with the sonorous tubes.
Let me quote one final observation about
the crane: "When staying in a country house
in an empty wood, how could one let a
single day go by without the company of this
refined friend that makes one forget all
worldly things?"
ROBERT HANS VAN GULIK (1910-1967),
Dutch writer and diplomat, was a distinguished
Orientalist with a special interest in Chinese
history. An authority on the Chinese language,
he was also a skilled calligrapher. His scholarly
works include: Sexual Life in Ancient China
(1962) and The Lore of the Chinese Lute (1968)
from which the present article has been extrac¬
ted. He was also the prolific author of detective
stories set in 7th-century China, whose hero,
Judge Dee, ranks with such great fictional detec¬
tives as Sherlock Holmes.
"Take your lute with you and play before
an oldplum tree, " says an ancient Chinese
poem, and according to tradition plum
blossoms appreciate the sounds of the
lute just as much as cranes. The pine tree
is also often associated with the lute, and
when a lute-player is not depictedsitting in
a plum grove he may be shown, as here,
seated on a moss-covered stone beneath
two spreading pines. In left foreground a
man is tuning a four-stringed guitar.
Below, page from a lute handbook show¬
ing a position of the right hand. Legend
above the picture reads, "The right hand,
suggesting a flying dragon grasping the
clouds." Written underneath is "The way
to produce a chord with thumb and middle
finger". Illustrations of finger positions
were usually accompanied by a brief ex¬
planatory note, known as hsing. The hsing
on this page reads: "The dragon is a holy
animal, a pond cannot contain it. Its head
and horns show a noble shape, its trans¬
mutations are inexhaustible. Having
ascended to the throne (an allusion to the
fact that 'Dragon' is a fixed epithet for the
Emperor), the world is prosperous. It
ascends in the air grasping with its claws,
the floating clouds follow it."
sf m * i » £
m m w të f a
L r£*
¿ft Ä
$î ÜB
4&Ä
^
$rft
^
i*
o <b
= Q)
«j o
o o>
©?'
o .ro
? =
ÊE
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The griot by Lamine Konte
2
od
i
©
In traditionalAfrica, the griot is a musician
and singer who is also a kind of chronicler
and historian of the society in which he
lives. His art is transmitted from father to
son. Photo above shows the author of our
article, the noted Senegalese griot Lamine
Konte, singing to his own accompaniment
on a Senegalese Instrument, the kora.
I am, first of all, an African from Senegal,
and secondly I am a Casamançais. I was
born in the area of southern Senegal
known as Casamance, "Casa di Mansa", a
name which is half Portuguese and half Man-
dingo, and which means "the house of the
king". It dates back to the fifteenth or sixteenth
centuries, when the Portuguese were in the
region. More specifically, I come from a family
of musicians or griots. We griots are simul¬
taneously musicians, historians and singers,
and our art is handed down from father to son
and from generation to generation. I grew up
in that world. Then I became interested in
Western culture and acquired a grounding in
Western music, particularly classical music.
This varied background enables me to ex¬
press myself authentically and at the same
time to be on the same wave-length as a
French audience.
I have been told that my father was a
famous griot. I was not fortunate enough to
know him, since he died when I was barely
777/s article is based on an interview with Lamine Konte
by Marc Kerjean, a French radio producer who is a
student and broadcaster of African music, blues and
jazz.
one year old. My father is still a formidable
competitor: all those who knew him are con¬
stantly comparing the two of us. He was an
excellent musician. Soundioulou Cissoko,
who was his fellow performer, is today one of
Senegal's great players of the kora (a 21-
stringed harp-lute). They collaborated
closely.
I did not receive any musical or poetic train¬
ing as such. It comes about spontaneously
when you are born into a family of musicians.
A little African sociology will help to explain
why. Since the Mandingo empire, Mandingo
society has been organized and structured
according to a caste system which has lasted
from the thirteenth century to the present.
Each caste contained men who were parti¬
cularly gifted at a certain craft: there were, for
example, the castes of the griots, the
weavers, the ironsmiths, and the warriors.
When you were born into a family of griots,
hence of musicians, you were ipso facto pre¬
destined to make music, that tradition has
become a thing of the past, now that the
sociological context has evoived: with coloni¬
zation, Africa started to be influenced by other
civilizations, schools were established, and
nowadays a child from a family of griots can ^
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The kora is a 21-string instrument which
produces a sound somewhere between
that of the harp and that of the guitar,
depending on the way in which its strings
are plucked. The sound-box is made from
half a calabash. Along the neck are strung
21 rings to each of which a string is
attached. There are two sets of strings,
separated by a bridge; each set is plucked
by the thumb and index fingerofone hand.
To tune the instrument, the mobile rings
are moved to tighten the strings until the
right notes are obtained. Above, kora-
player Arfan Kouyate and singer Penda
Diabate, during a 1982 concert of Man¬
dingo music in a lecture hall of the Sor¬
bonne, Paris.
^ grow up to be a schoolteacher, a mason, or a
mechanic. But originally, when you were born
into a or/of family, you devoted yourself exclu¬
sively to music. The only activity permitted
outside music was farming, since it was for the
common good.
Music is a universal phenomenon, and all
the musicians in the world began in approx¬
imately the same way: they were people who
had the gift of combining notes in a pattern
that was harmonious to the ear. Since writing
was not current in some parts of Africa, it was
^^ necessary to entrust a social group with the
mm task of reciting history, and thus of acting as
22 the memory of the African people.
It was, accordingly, the task of the griot
community to pass on an oral record of his¬
tory. A musical medium was needed to do
this. The griots made instruments that were
suited to the languages and the rhythms in
use. We owe the griot tradition to the intelli¬
gence of the earliest politicians: they grasped
the fact that one cannot govern a community
without historians, and thus without music.
There are also many legends which tell of the
origins of the griots, but in my opinion they
came into being quite naturally: since they
wanted to make music, they freely indulged
their desire. And this activity has devolved on
them since the reign of Sundiata Keita, the
first emperor of Mali since the fourteenth
century, in other words.
The participation of the griots was neces¬
sary at the major turning-points in a lifetime,
such as birth and marriage. They also sang
the praises of their hosts and knew family
histories. They usually earned a living from
the gifts that they received in return for their
services. It is possible for a griot to bear a
grudge against an ungenerous client, for after
all, he is a man, with a man's weaknesses. But
his essential role is to sing the praises of
individuals without any discrimination on
financial grounds; he sings for the poor fisher¬
man and the rich merchant alike. His aim is to
bring to life the history of the family of his
client, just as his father taught it to him.
Some people believe that griots possess
magic power, but in Africa, magic power be¬
longs rather to iron-smiths. Some griots have
power, since they possess a considerable
store of wide-ranging knowledge and are re¬
ceptive to all forms of culture; when they reach
a certain age, they are necessarily powerful,
but is this magical or is it another kind of
power? It is difficult to give an unqualified
answer. You need to meet a particular griot
personally in order to find out what type of
power he wields.
The "story-telling" griots sing the great tra¬
ditional epics, telling of the warlike deeds of
heroes, their native land, and love. They also
put on shows, since in Africa, there is no
established theatre structure. They are
actors, poets, dancers and mimes, and they
bring all the arts into play in their perfor¬
mances. Since they are highly versatile, one
of their roles is to dance themselves and to
induce a gathering of people to dance. Some,
admittedly, specialize in one or other of these
fields: they express themselves through
musicordancing, or through the spoken word.
But others, while they play music, may also
sing, tell stories and even dance.
In the days when the caste system was
operating strictly, the griots used to meet reg¬
ularly in a family context. That was very com¬
mon. These family reunions were called
"practice sessions". The whole family
gathered together, with all generations pre¬
sent, and they played in order to ascertain
how high their standard was. I know a story
about a gathering of griots in Mali. I believe it is
true, since many people were eyewitnesses to
it. Every seven years, the great griots of Mali
met to repair the roof of a hut. They sang and
played music at the same time, whereupon
the roof flew up into the air as if by enchant¬
ment and landed on the ground. They res¬
tored the roof. Then they started singing
again, and the roof rose up from the ground
and settled on the hut. This phenomenon has
something to do with magic power. But, ulti¬
mately, all forms of expression contain a grain ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
A griot from West
Africa being inter¬
viewed
©3
BL^A
1 ;H
A.
^ 1
i \
Photo © Hoa-Qui, Paris Photo © Hoa-Qui, Paris
©
Four examples of Africa's wealth of tradi¬
tional musical instruments: (1) Bambara
wind Instrument from Mali; (2) a Gabonese
harp; (3) anthropomorphic harp from
Zaire; (4) guitar of the Mangbetu people of
Zaire. The neck is surmounted by a carved
wooden head.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
of magic power, in that they draw on a certain
spiritual force. And so the music and singing
of the Malian griots was able to move the roof
of a hut.
African musical instruments vary from re¬
gion to region. Mali is the cradle of African
music, and since the empire of Sundiata it has
influenced the art of music in other regions.
The instruments found there are more soph¬
isticated than those of northern Senegal,
where 80 per cent of the music consists of
rhythm of drumming, in other words. In a
Wolof group, in northern Senegal, there are at
least fourteen types of percussion, whereas in
a Malian group the percussion is accompa¬
nied by more elaborate instruments such as
the kora or the balafon. The great musicians
of northern Senegal play the halam (a Wolof
name for a five-stringed guitar, a very old
African instrument) and most of them served
their apprenticeship in Mali. In Casamance,
we play the bolong, a sort of three-stringed
kora, which sounds like a double-bass; but
percussion predominates.
No instrument is particularly easy to play
well. The kora, for example, poses problems,
since its music cannot be dissociated from the
Mandingo language. You have to know that
Trumpet-players in the Madagascan group
Hira-Gasy. Instruments ofEuropean origin
are played in many parts of Africa today.
éX.
language in order to play the instrument.
There is no score, and it is played by ear. And
so you have to remember the tunes, and in
order to do this, you have to know the history.
Since history is invariably recounted in Man¬
dingo or Malinke, it is indispensable to know
the language in order to attempt to play the
kora. However, it has recently become a little
more accessible. Many musicians play it while
singing in Wolof or in Portuguese Creole. My
father usually sang in Portuguese Creole. I
personally welcome this move towards a
widening of horizons, and I should like the
kora to become a universal instrument like so
many others.
In Africa there are many kinds of percussion
instruments. Each ethnic group has its own.
The Mandingo, for example, play the koutero,
the Malinke the djembé. In the forest regions
of Central Africa, there are others, different
from those of the savannah. There are as
many types of percussion as there are ethnic
groups.
Until relatively recently, playing a musical
instrument was not an activity for women, who
were expected to sing. If necessary, they
accompanied themselves on a primitive Ma¬
lian instrument made of iron, but that was all.
Usually, a woman sings as an accompani¬
ment to her husband while he plays an in¬
strument. Singing is for women and instru¬
ments are for men. Male African society prob¬
ably considered that it was easier to sing. This
situation has now changed. I was able to
observe this in 1977, at the Second World
Black and African Festival of Arts and Cul¬
tures, held in Lagos, Nigeria: there was an
all-female Guiñean instrumental ensemble
playing the kora and the balafon. I have also
seen a women's orchestra playing modern
instruments such as the saxophone, trumpet,
Western-style percussion, and electric guitar.
I return to my country every year, or at least
every two years. It makes me feel more alive,
it's a tonic and it gives me confidence. The fact
of being "cut off" from my African roots has a
good effect on my music. Not being in my own
country, I can see more clearly what is hap¬
pening there, and this gives me inspiration.
From afar, you can see your country in a truer
light, in greater depth and with stronger affec¬
tion. In my native land I would probably be
taken up with concerns that have nothing to
do with my music. What is more, I do not feel
very far away: I am only four hours' flying time
from Senegal.
In Senegal people listen to all kinds of
mus' - from James Brown to Johnny Halliday.
It's quite a medley. Manu Dibango, the
Cameroonian from Paris or the Parisian from
Cameroon, whichever you prefer, is someone
who is doing a great deal of work for Africa. He
is a great musician. He has long defended the
cause of African music, as I myself and other
African musicians have done. This puts him in
a sympathetic light. He richly deserves his
success, for he has worked very hard. Accord¬
ing to him, we are witnessing "the birth of a
new race, an Afro-European race", and
"European music must not remain in its
ghetto".
I believe that neither European music nor
African music should remain in its ghetto, for
they both need to evolve through their rela¬
tions with each other. Staying in one's ghetto
means failing to develop. The future of the
world lies in the intermingling of people and
cultures. For music, the pattern of develop¬
ment is similar.
It is a mistake to think that for traditional
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
In African music in the past the role of
women was to sing, not to play In¬
struments. But today things have changed
and groups of women musicians are not
uncommon. Right, women musicians from
Mali.
music development means deterioration. In
Africa, traditional music associated with tradi¬
tional instruments does not rule out other
forms of music which are played on Western
instruments. Since colonization 300 years
ago, traditional music has assimilated the
accordion, the harmonica and the guitar. But
until recently this branch of music has been
rejected by Westerners.
Only twenty years ago, people thought that
Africans should confine themselves to playing
the tom-toms! The time has come for Wester¬
ners to adjust their stereotyped view of African
culture and acknowledge the coexistence of
traditional music with other forms of musical
expression. I defend traditional music, for it
can change and develop. And I should like the
form resulting from contact with Western
music to win recognition in France.
It is true that the griot's approach is poles
apart from that of the European musician. In
Africa, music has a social role to play. Its
prime function is to accompany celebrations
and to put across a philosophy. Nothing else!
Westerners relate to music in a wholly diffe¬
rent way. The act of listening is all-important;
they expect the musician to deliver a dis¬
course. In the past few years, however, an
inter-reaction has gradually been taking place
between European and African music. Euro¬
pean audiences no longer react to African
music as if it were a museum piece. And the
Afro-Europeans have realized that they must
not go on repeating the faithfully handed-
down ancestral rhythms on their percussion
instruments if they want to make tradition
relevant to the circumstances of modern
Africa and to a type of music that expresses
urbanization and the mutual impact of
civilizations.
As far as I am concerned, traditional forms
of music are the most important, since they
underlie everything else. I have kept the
polyrhythmic character of African music and
our own special way of communicating with
an audience. By playing and recording in
Europe I have learned a great deal. Every¬
thing must be carefully set up, with studied
arrangements and the quality of sound reg¬
ulated to suit my instruments in short, my
contact with Western technology has been
invaluable. But I regard myself as a messen¬
ger with ideas to communicate to a European
audience. I belong to a different century from
that of my father, and I want society to change
and develop.
LAMINE KONTE, Senegalese griot, is a storytel¬
ler, author and composer of music. The son of
Dialy Keba Konte, a famous griot of the Casa-
mance region of Senegal, he came to Europe in
1971 and embarked on an international career.
He has made more than 10 LP albums including
Chants Nègres, Chants du Monde (Negro-Afri¬
can poems and songs) and La Kora du Sénégal.
He was responsible for the music in Bako, a film
made by Jacques Champreux and Cheikh
Doukoure.
y r * ?
Wm ,
A group of traditional African musicians
performing before an audience of
thousands during the Second World Black
and African Festival of Arts and Cultures
held in Lagos (Nigeria) in 1977.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
When opera
takes to the screen
by Dominique Jameux ALTHOUGH opera and cinema may,
at first glance, appear to be unlikely
bedfellows, these two art forms
have much in common.
Both offer us dramatic representations
which come close to earning the epithet of
"total art", uniting as they do around a
literary text (a scenario or a libretto) and in
a given setting, the combined glories of
light, colour, objects and costumes, and of
the voice and the actor's art. And if, today,
the cinema dominates the field of the audio
visual spectacle, opera can claim to be its
oldest manifestation. Cross-breeding be¬
tween the two is therefore both natural and
frequent, if at times problematic.
The film industry's takeover bid for opera
has a long history. In recent years we have
been offered such opera-films as "Losey's"
Don Giovanni, "Bergman's" The Magic
Flute, "Zeffirelli's" La Traviata and "Ro-
si's" Carmen. The quotation marks seem to
imply some kind of usurpation; and quite
rightly and logically so, since the reality of
the opera-film lies in the adoption by a great
film director of one of the best-known
works of the lyric repertoire and his im¬
pression on it of a vision that is virtually that
of an entirely different author, a phe¬
nomenon to which we shall return later.
In an excellent study published a few
years ago(1), Emmanuel Decaux recalled
the distant origins of this cross-fertilization
between the two art forms. Starting at the
beginning of the century, directors of silent
film days made films based on the libretti of
famous operas, altered or transformed in
varying degrees. In 1909, Regina Badet and
Max Dearly starred in a version of Carmen;
in 1915, in the United States, the famous
vamp, Theda Bara, took the lead in another
Carmen, while, that same year, Géraldine
Farrar played the same role in a Cecil B. de
Mille production.
These early examples of this new genre,
from the age of the silent screen, teach us
that, from the beginning, the makers of
opera-films were quite happy with a situa¬
tion in which music was, to say the least,
placed firmly in the background. Thus, un¬
wittingly, the infancy of the new genre gave
us a foretaste of what it would be in its
maturity. In 1943, for example, Viviane
Romance and Jean Marais were to star in
what was literally a "talking" version of
Carmen, directed by Christian-Jaque.
1 . Fascination de l'Irréel (The Fascination of the
Unreal), by Emmanuel Decaux, Cinématog¬
raphe, November, 1979.
The earliest filmed versions ofoperas took
many liberties with libretti and even with
the musical score. Left, the great Russian
bass singer Fedor Ivanovich Chaliapin
(1873-1938), who created the role of Don
Guixote in Massenet's Don Quichotte in
1910 and sang the same part in a screen
version of the opera made in 1933 by the
German director G.W. Pabst. The film fea¬
tured episodes sung to music specially
composed for the occasion.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
One method of bringing opera to the
screen is simply to film a live performance,
providing "an eyewitness account of an
event and a record for the archives" and
striking "a balance between the quality
one has the right to demand from any
artistic presentation and the touching pre-
cariousness of an operatic performance".
A striking example of this kind of film is
that made of Mozart's Don Giovanni at the
Salzburg Festival in 1953 (above).
"Since television has become part of our
daily lives the opera film has more often
than notbeen designed forshowing on the
small screen." One of the most famous
examples ofan opera film produced for TV
in the studio is the Swedish director Ing-
mar Bergman's version of Mozart's The
Magic Flute (1975) later adapted for the
cinema. Right, Josef Kostlinger in the role
of Tamino.
The filming of opera in a studio with a
brilliant cast anda setting similar to that of
an opera stage has become particularly
widespread in the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many. Right, Mirella Frenl (Suzanne),
Maria Ewing (Chérubin) and Kiri Te Kana-
wa (the Countess) in Mozart's opera The
Marriage of Figaro, brought to the screen
in 1976 by the French director Jean-Pierre
Ponnelle.
At the same time, famous singers were
being invited by the cinema world to leave
an enduring record of their art. One spec¬
tacular example was that of the great bass
Chaliapin who, in 1933, appeared in a film
version of Don Quixote, directed by G.W.
Pabst. The film was designed to capitalize
on his public image (in 1910, he had created
the title role in this opera by Massenet, and
had sung it again countless times), yet, pa¬
radoxically, in the film he neither sang to
Massenet's music nor followed the libretto
by Henri Cain (based on Cervantes' book).
Instead, against a natural setting in Pro¬
vence, Pabst recreated a new story consist¬
ing of episodes sung to music specially com¬
posed for the film by Jacques Ibert.
In this manner, the opera-film hesitantly
groped its way forward. It was as if the film
directors were aware that, even if opera
offered them raw material of high dramatic
potential (and which was sure to have an
impact on the public), its very nature (im¬
possible libretti, the unattractive physiques
of many singers, the artificial nature of op¬
eratic canto and other technical constraints)
made the production of a true opera-film an
extremely doubtful undertaking.
At the same time, and even before the
opera-film industry proper had developed,
its major prerequisites, ingredients which
are still in use today, were falling into
place location filming for greater realism;
the use of playback, essential for exterior
filming and having the additional advantage
of enabling singers to concentrate more on
their acting; the right assumed by directors
to modify original libretti and to make of
them what they considered to be proper
scenarios.
And what of the music in all this? One is
tempted to utter the paradoxical assertion
that, but for the music, the problem of the
opera-film would have been resolved long
ago!
The great value of the opera-film is that it
introduces famous singers to an infinitely
larger public than that which frequents the
opera houses and at the same time creates a
permanent record of their fragile, ephemer¬
al art. But is the opera-film necessary to the
achievement of these goals? We have film
footage of famous singers singing their
favourite arias, set within the framework of
purpose-built and often rather vacuous
stories which generally adopt the style of
the romanticized biography. But does this
matter? Richard Tauber, Jan Kiepura, Lily
Pons, Georges Thill, André Baugé, Maria
Cebotari, Enrico Caruso and many others,
have in this way left behind them film and
sound-track which, with clever editing,
could become commercially viable today.
Thus the stage had been reached in the saga
of the relations between the two art forms at
which the opera-film remained both a fasci¬
nating vision and an inaccessible goal.
It would seem that the first real opera-
film was a version of Leoncavallo's Pagliac-
ci. which was made in 1930 during a tour of
the United States by the company of the
San Carlo Theatre of Naples. In the years
following the end of the Second World War
the practice of filming opera became more
widespread. In these productions three
names frequently recurred: Verdi as com-
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
^ poser, Gallone as director and Tito Gobbi
as the singing star. In 1948, a new version of
Pagliacci was shot in the open air, with the
actor/singer Tito Gobbi and the actress
Gina Lollobrigida, with the dubbed voice of
a singer. The film stated the problem and
offered the solution film stars, unlike
most singers, act well and are credible even
in close-up, whereas opera singers usually
sing better than actors. Dubbing, therefore,
provides the solution, and this was the
method adopted in 1983 by Syberberg for
his Parsifal.
At this point we should, perhaps, ex¬
amine more closely the three types of pro¬
duction that today constitute the corpus of
opera-films and the problems faced, and
sometimes in part resolved, by each of
them.
First of all there is the straightforward
filming of a live performance; that is, the
film which is both, as it were, an eye-witness
account of an event and a record for the
archives. The most striking example of this
type of film is that made at the Salzburg
Festival of 1953 of Mozart's Don Giovanni,
under the baton of Wilhelm Furtwängler.
Its great success was due first to the musical
quality of the production and also to the
discreet manner in which the director, Paul
Czinner, handled his subject. The camera, a
privileged, well-placed spectator, is virtual¬
ly neutral. The orchestra the Vienna
Philharmonic is not, as is often the case,
effaced in the filming. The décor and the
costumes are traditional but beautiful. The
singers, well-rehearsed in their roles, do not
take on the airs of cinema actors. The
sound, in this purpose-built setting, is of
admirable quality.
Of the three types of opera-film, this one
seems to me to be the most satisfactory. It
respects the essential, that is to say the
music; it enables the music-lover, to some
extent, for a modest sum and with no major
loss of quality, to keep abreast of the music¬
al happenings of his time; and, for the nos¬
talgies amongst us, it provides an example
of the art of Mozartian singing of that
period. Live recording also preserves the
balance between the quality one has the
right to demand from any artistic presenta¬
tion and the touching precariousness of an
operatic performance which is, in fact, part
of its magic.
The second category of opera-films are
those made in the studio setting. This has
become an institution in the Federal Re¬
public of Germany, where large, special¬
ized production companies have developed
a veritable "canned opera" industry. It is
usually a by-product of a normal production
of an opera company. A well-established
production, with a brilliant, if not outstand¬
ing, cast, is filmed in a studio in a décor
similar to that of an opera stage but where
the acoustics are better for the initial re¬
cording as well as for the final production of
the sound-track. The mobility of the camer¬
as varies. Sometimes they give the view as
seen from a seat in the stalls, sometimes
they appear to be moving around on the
"stage". The result is a product of a very
definite type, in which the direction is of
fairly limited importance and which is not
without a certain touch of artificiality.
Although they are very professional pro¬
ductions, the films produced at Hamburg at
the instigation of Rolf Liebermann and The
Marriage of Figaro directed by Jean-Pierre
In recent years a number of major opera-
films by talented directors have exploited
all the technical and financial possibilities
of cinema and have made a bid to stand as
artistic creations in their own right. Shown
here are stills from Franco Zeffirelli's La
Traviata (above), Francesco Rosi's Car¬
men (above right), and Joseph Losey's
Don Giovanni (opposite). These recent
productions perhaps mark the start of a
form which can offer the widest public the
most satisfactory "substitute" for the rep¬
resentation of traditional opera.
Ponnelle nevertheless give the impression
of being "opera on the cheap". One of the
problems of opera-films is that aesthetic
considerations are closely bound up with
financial, cultural and sociological factors.
And this, perhaps, is a suitable point at
which to open a parenthesis to consider
exactly what is at stake in the opera-film
"industry".
First of all, opera-films are aimed at a
non-public (people who do not go to the
opera) or at a public delighted to have the
opportunity of seeing again the opera stars
they like to hear singing certain arias, and
this for a modest sum and without going to
an opera house.
Secondly, the enormous increase in the
cost of putting on a opera that has occurred
over the past twenty years has made neces¬
sary growing support from public funds.
This has created a new situation in Europe,
and particularly in France the taxpayer,
who may derive no pleasure from opera,
finds himself paying in part for the opera-
goer's seat. The opera is no longer merely
"elitist", it has also become a tax burden.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The scandalous aspect of this ransom de¬
manded by the operatic institutions from
the non-public modifies somewhat our view
of the opera-film , the justification for which
is that it enables members of this tax-paying
non-public also to have access to the world
of opera. Nevertheless, despite the pay¬
ments they have already made as taxpayers,
they are asked in addition to contribute, no
matter how modestly, to the costs of filming
by paying for their seats in the cinema.
The problem has still not been resolved.
On the contrary, the gap is widening be¬
tween the privileged minority that has ac¬
cess to operatic performances paying a
high price, it is true, but one which repre¬
sents only a portion of the real cost of a seat,
the remainder being paid by taxpayers who
are excluded from these delights and the
non-public which is offered instead, at the
true cost price even if this is lower, a by¬
product of real opera. Far from contribut¬
ing to the reduction of social and cultural
injustice, the opera-film merely emphasizes
its intractable nature.
The advent of television has modified
some of the factors involved but has not
altered the basic problem of the opera-film.
In fact, since television became part of our
daily lives, the opera-film has more often
than not been designed for showing on the
small screen. Ingmar Bergman's The Magic
Flute is a famous example.
The opera-film destined for television
showing has its own aesthetic, cultural and
economic characteristics. The small size of
the screen encourages close-ups and inti¬
mate scenes; the sound is of mediocre qual¬
ity; sub-titling presents difficulties; and the
lighting appears flat and artificial. It is true
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
V
8 '> '.SNv > F
that the entry of opera into tens of
thousands of homes, sometimes more, is to
its credit, particularly since entertainment
in the home is perceived, wrongly, as being
free. But it cannot be denied that the "ma¬
gic" engendered by the gathering of the
public in front of the big screen in a
darkened cinema already less than that
experienced in an opera house is totally
absent from the home. It is well known that
the mere fact of being in the domestic en¬
vironment is enough to remove all sense of
enchantment from a spectacle already lack¬
ing the glitter which has traditionally been
an integral part of it.
Under these conditions, how can televi¬
sion avoid the charge of being associated
with the degradation of the original operatic
experience, which relegates the televiewer,
like the person who sees an opera-film in
One approach to bringing opera to the
screen is to use film actors and dub them
on the sound-track with the voices of
opera singers. This method was adopted
by H.J. Syberberg of the Federal Republic
of Germany when he filmed Wagner's
opera Parsifal in 1981. Above, on set dur¬
ing filming.
the dark of the cinema, to the rank of a
second-class citizen in the world of opera?
The only way in which the opera-film can
be presented to the consumer in such a
manner as to make him forget that he is
being offered only ersatz opera is to devise a
form of filming which provides a "plus fac¬
tor" unique to the cinema, so that the spec¬
tator sees something that is not a lesser
version of the original opera, but something
else, perhaps something better.
This can be achieved by our third categ¬
ory of opera-films the director's film. A
great film director is invited to take in hand
a great operatic score. There will be no lack
of resources, since once we leave the opera
house for the film set we leave behind the
world of public subsidies to enter the realm
where profit is king.
Everything is done to make the opera-
film an original work, an artistic creation in
its own right, standing side by side with the
original and worthy of being called, for
example, "Losey's" Don Giovanni. There
are fantastic décors, sumptuous costumes,
operatic stars duly promoted by press and
show-bizz. The director himself feels free to
do what he will with libretto and score, and
displays a daredevil insouciance that is justi¬
fied as the new approach of an artist of
today to a work of art of the past. The music
may often suffer, to the benefit of the spec¬
tacle, but the filmed work will be able to
compete on equal terms with the original.
And in this way the gap between the élite
and the masses, between a real and simu¬
lated experience, between the genuine and
the imitation, can at last be reduced.
It is only fair to point out that this kind of
opera-film is still in its infancy. Productions
such as Bergman's The Magic Flute (which,
to be sure, has something of both the first
and the third of the three categories of
opera-film we have defined above) have
shown that they can offer us true musical
and dramatic emotion and that those who
have access to the privileged world of opera
should not look down their aristocratic
noses at productions that have given so
much pleasure to so many. Nothing need
stand in the way of further progress .
DOMINIQUE JAMEUX is a French musicologist,
writer and radio producer. Among his published
works are Richard Strauss (1980, new edition
1986), Alban Berg (1980) and Boulez (1984). His
book Lulu (d'Alban Berg) will appear later this
year. With the composer Michel Fano he co-
authored a series of introductory programmes to
contemporary music that were broadcast on
French television in 1981.
A world history of music
30
Specialists from all over the world and from many disciplines are
currently collaborating on a comprehensive world history, Music in the
Life of Man (MLM), sponsored by Unesco and administered through
the International Music Council. Aimed at the layman as well as the
specialist, Music in the Life ofMan will deal with all types of music and
all aspects of musical life throughout history. It will provide descriptions
of the historical development of music and its present state in the main
geocultural regions of the world, taking into account the particular
philosophies or concepts of history of each region, the factors that
influenced its historical development, and the musical linkages within
and between regions. Since the project was formally launched in 1 982,
a series of meetings have been held at which a president and Board of
Directors representing six major international organizations were de¬
signated. A general co-ordinator and regional co-ordinators for the
principal regions were also appointed and tables of contents for the
various regional volumes drawn up. The actual writing is now well
under way. MLM is being written "from within" by scholars from the
cultural regions themselves and edited by an international panel of
experts. The work is scheduled to appear in 1 991 , initially in 3 editions
(English, French and German) but it is hoped that it will eventually be
published in several other languages Russian, Chinese, Japanese,
Arabic and Spanish and in two-volume condensations in as many
tongues as possible. The present plan calls for an edition in 12 large
illustrated volumes, accompanied by a set of recordings in cassette or
compact disc. Ten volumes (nos. II to XI) will be devoted to the cultural
regions, while the other two (nos. I and XII) will contain essays and
indexes of more general concern. At the end of each regional volume
will be "country profiles" of each nation in the region containing the
basic facts of its national life, its culture, its music and its history.
In the words of Barry S. Brook, President of the Board of Directors,
"What makes this unlike any previous world history is its commitment
to equal treatment for all cultures and its enlistment of scholars from all
corners of the earth in the writing and editing process. . . The histor¬
iography of world music will be nhanged radically by the Music in the
Life of Man project."
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The modern soundscape
and noise pollution
by Nils Lennart Wallin
THE demographic explosion in the
modern world, combined with the in¬
creasingly dense network of urban,
industrial, agricultural and air traffic sys¬
tems, has generated such by-products as
pollution and the disappearance of some
animal species.
Another by-product, the nature of which
has not yet been fully explored, is the new
soundscape, created largely by the enor¬
mous increase in non-organic and uninten¬
tional sounds.
When such sounds become positively
disturbing, noise limitation regulations are
established. In this fie|d, governments
often have to balance conflicting rights and
interests. To take one example, reducing
the speed of commuter trains in order to
bring down noise levels must be reconciled
with the need to maintain an efficient transit
system. The problem becomes compli¬
cated when intentional, organic sounds are
objected to: limitations imposed on public
address systems could, for example, be
considered a violation of the right to free
speech.
Attempts to define what is harmful in the
new soundscape inevitably raise questions
of human values and human rights. To
dispel the vague prejudices which often
bedevil such discussions, let us first ex¬
amine, independently of political, ideologi¬
cal, ethical and socio-economic consider¬
ations, the precise effects of sound on the
hearing system.
Auditory loss may affect the system at
two points: the peripheral point (that is, the
ear) and the central point (that is, the re-
Many young people today use portable
tape-recorders to cut themselves off from
the clamour of the streetsometimes in
protestagainst aspects ofurban life which
they find repugnantand listen undis¬
turbed to the music they love. Above, be¬
side the grave of the American pop idol
Jim Morrison at Père Lachaise cemetery in
Paris a young man listens to the famous
singer's voice.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
(fi
f !)
levant parts of the central nervous system,
mainly the brain-stem and the neo-cortex).
The consequences of damage are quite
different in each case.
Most auditory injuries consist of peripher¬
al loss, in other words reduced hearing
capacity with respect to frequency range
and intensity. Changes in this capacity can
be measured and diagnosed, and norms
for different age groups are generally
accepted and form the basis for most leg¬
islative regulation and industrial injury
claims. Peripheral loss depends upon two
different kinds of pathological change: con¬
ductive loss (or deafness) is an impairment
of one or more of the sound conductors and
is often caused by otosclerosis. Sensoneu-
ral loss occurs within the cochlea. One
example of this is Meniere's disease;
another is loudness recruitment, the prob¬
able cause of the deafness of Beethoven,
who complained that he could not hear
people speaking and that when they
shouted at him it became unbearable. The
By the 4th month after conception the hu¬
man foetus can hear. During the 5 months
before birth the foetus hears the heart-beat
of the mother and from the 7th month ex¬
ternal sound stimuli are registered. The
mmm development of the child's auditory capa-
cities in the first months after birth are
32 clearly Influenced by the soundscape and
the child's early perceptions of music,
often In the cradle. Right, a Vietnamese
mother rocks her baby.
disease with which we are concerned here
is the sensoneural disorder known as
tinnitus.
Tinnitus is noise-induced hearing loss. It
normally occurs among the elderly but is
increasingly found among younger people.
By the early 1 960s, 35 out of every 1 ,000
Americans suffered from tinnitus to the ex¬
tent that it interfered with their work. Most
lost the ability to hear high frequencies (the
highest notes of the piano).
Noise-induced hearing loss is affected by
a combination of sound intensity (mea¬
sured logarithmically in decibels) and
length of time exposed. The British otolog¬
ist D.R. Hanson recommends one hour as
the maximum permissible exposure to 99
decibels, and 88 seconds for exposure to
1 35 decibels. The average sound level dur¬
ing a two-hour symphony concert can
range from 95 to 97 decibels on the
podium. According to this recommenda¬
tion, orchestral players should never ex¬
ceed one hour's work per day. This of
course is unrealistic, but it does support the
claim of most orchestras that working time
should not exceed five hours, especially in
view of the high attention levels required
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The sonar environment or "soundscape"
influences the development of the audi¬
tory sensibility from childhood on. Far left,
tranquility reigns on the shores of Lake
Titicaca in the Andes, where the only
sounds are made by the water, the wind,
insects and birds. The boat, a tortora,
takes Its name from the lakeside reeds of
which it is made. Left, a totally different
soundscape in a modern city, where life is
dominated by the deafening noise of
traffic.
which can cause both auditory and emo¬
tional stress.
Dr. Hanson has compiled data on noise-
induced hearing loss in young people who
have attended pop concerts and disco¬
thèques or used Walkman devices. There
are clinical cases of deafness being caused
by a sound shock, as when entering a
discothèque.
Tinnitus is a failure of the haircells lining
the basilar membrane of the cochlea. It is
the movement of these cells, in response to
incoming sound waves, which converts the
signals to electrical impulses. The size of
the movement is proportional to the ampli¬
tude of the sound. Haircells in the chinchilla
show irreversible damage after exposure to
pop music at 1 20 decibels for 1 2 minutes or
90 decibels for 3 hours. Different haircells
respond to different frequencies and tinni¬
tus occurs at those frequencies at which the
corresponding haircell has been damaged.
The high-pitched whistle which sufferers
from this disorder often hear is probably a
subjective sound produced by the brain
itself when registering the lack of neuronal
spontaneous background noise from that
part of the basilar membrane where the
haircells are damaged, as a signal to which
the brain must respond.
If the central brain processes are dam¬
aged (perhaps as the result of a stroke) the
perception of sounds and music may be
affected. The resulting disabilities may in¬
clude loss of spatial perception, raised
threshold of attention, inability to define
pitch and co-ordinate movements, and loss
of memory. So far as we know, brain dam¬
age cannot be caused by too much or too
strong sound. However, a complete lack of
auditory stimulation can cause such
damage, especially early in life. Sensory
deprivation leads to the non-development
of neuronal pathways and synapses which
can inhibit sensitivity and the ability to reg¬
ister experience later in life.
On the other hand, while excessive sti¬
mulation may not cause direct physical
damage it can, if not appropriate, create
stress, lack of attention, poor socialization
and the inability to form values. There is
disharmony between neurophysiological
brain patterns and the surrounding social
and biospheric conditions at crucial points
in the development of the personality. As
the physiologist Rainer Sinz, of the Federal
Republic of Germany, has pointed out:
" Early and permanent exposure to music in
the form of a sound level background leads
to the premature practice of ignoring the
noise level in overcrowded urban areas.
This not only raises the threshold of audibi¬
lity, it also reduces the differentiated emo¬
tional processing of music nuances of mod¬
erate intensity. Acoustical stress leads to a
switch-off reaction from attention to frustra¬
tion and, furthermore, to deficit sensitivity
and rudimentary musicality."
Bearing in mind the relationship between
music as a stimulus and the inner neuro¬
physiological clocks, it would appear that
the perfected (and thus quite artificial)
pulse of much synthesized pop music does
not coincide with what mankind, regardless
of culture, has developed as music
breathing and developing in close interac¬
tion with our inner rhythmic pulses. Its
merciless regularity and simplified sonority
are inhuman. The effect of this music in¬
jected directly into the ears through a Walk¬
man may cause other possibly negative
effects. The Walkman enables a young
person to become isolated from the throb¬
bing life of the street in all its complexity.
Such deliberate isolation is of course in
itself a protest at overcrowded and deindivi-
dualizing conditions. However, the con¬
sequence will be a loss of part of the multi¬
modal perception and observation which is
the purpose of our senses in daily life: what
is listened to does not correspond to what is
seen.
The enormous and increasing amounts
of sound which characterize today's sound¬
scape are a physical threat to the auditory
system, when exposure is long and fre¬
quent, and a source of mental and emotion¬
al fatigue which inhibits the development of
ethical, social and intellectual values.
Among the changes to be expected from
such processes is a trend towards strongly
standardized and simplified musical struc¬
tures. The fact that new soundscapes affect
the small child and possibly even the foetus
means that the process of change will
accelerate.
It is easier to prevent physical damage to
the cochlea than it is to prevent tiredness,
poor attention span, stereotyped emotional
patterns and lowered sensitivity to sophisti¬
cated intellectual products. Hence many
countries have enacted legislation which
regulates exposure to high intensity levels
and long continuous noise levels in indust¬
rial work.
In spite of all this, I would go along with
Hanson and Sinz in advising against leg¬
islation affecting pop music, discothèques
and the Walkman. There are strong
sociological reasons why (mainly) young
people engage in these activities: the de¬
sire for solidarity, the desire to belong to a
community, to overcome loneliness, to
escape from and forget reality. These are
good reasons for society not to legislate but
to try, in spite of all the difficulties, whether
from powerful commercial interests, mass
media propaganda, or elsewhere, to meet
the needs of young people by modifying
some aspects of pop music, to offer them
challenging alternatives, to convince
musicians in the pop industry of the need to
modify the music (as some musicians have
already done) and also the industry itself.
Let us not forget that one of the reasons
why people like music is their need to break
silence. We need to make noise but pre¬
ferably below 90 decibels.
NILS LENNART WALLIN, of Sweden, studied
musicology, philosophy and ethno-anthropology
at the Universities of Uppsala and Stockholm
and music at the Schola Cantorum, Bale. A "^"
teacher of music, the history of music and music o o
criticism, he is a former director-general of the
Swedish National Concerts Institute, (1963-
1970), of the Stockholm Philharmonic Orchestra,
and of Stockholm's concert hall (1970-1976).
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Year of Peace: 4
Olof Palme, the Prime Minister of
Sweden, was assassinated on 28
February 1986. The text below con¬
sists of extracts from a speech he
made on 21 October 1985 at United
Nations headquarters in New York
during the fortieth session of the UN
General Assembly. We publish this
text as a tribute to Olof Palme's life¬
long dedication to the ideals of the
United Nations.
... Peace is, of course, the fundamental aim
of the United Nations. We have come to
recognize that peace is certainly more than
the absence of military violence. It is also
stability in relations between States, based
on the observance of legal principles. One
field where co-operation between States is
absolutely necessary is the fight against
terrorism in all its forms, these cruel
slayings of innocent civilians.
The rule of law is of vital importance to
peaceful international relations. In particu¬
lar, this is strongly felt in the smaller coun¬
tries. When the integrity and independence
of one small country is violated, it often
sends a vibration of anger and anxiety
through the hearts and minds of the citizens
in other small countries. For them, the rule
of law and the observance of our common
commitments under the Charter are seen
as imperatives for a future in peace and
security. (...)
In our era of growing international inter¬
dependence we have to recognize that
threats to peace frequently originate from
conditions inside the countries. Misery,
hunger, denial of basic human rights, are
the causes of political and social upheaval.
(...)
Brutal violations of human rights occur in
many countries, but in South Africa they are
written into the very laws of the country. In
this way the policy of apartheid is unique in
all its moral abomination. Apartheid is
doomed, as is South Africa's illegal occupa¬
tion of Namibia. While fearing that it will end
in a chaos of destruction and bloodshed for
which the white régime will bear full respon¬
sibility, we should not abandon the hope
that a peaceful transition to a non-racial
democratic society may still be possible
through dialogue and agreement. It is the
duty of the outside world to assist this strug¬
gle for freedom (...).
We are witnessing massive migrations
on an unprecedented scale between States
and between continents. The reasons are
many, among them hunger, war, natural
disasters, persecution. The cultural
clashes that are inevitable in this process
have led in many countries to a renewal of
chauvinism and racism. It is time we be¬
came more attentive to this particular
danger. We are helped in this task by the
rising anger, enthusiasm and readiness to
act demonstrated by some people of the
younger generations. It does honour to
them (...) that they have adopted the watch¬
word "Don't touch my pal". There are many
adults, in and out of Government, who
would do well to listen and take notice.
For many people around the world the
United Nations stands for something very
concrete, a significant element in their per¬
sonal everyday life.
A child in Africa learns to read in a school
financed by Unesco. A farmer in Asia re¬
ceives a sack of seed labelled "FAO" the
Food and Agriculture Organization of the
United Nations or "WFP" World Food
Programme. The United Nations Develop¬
ment Programme (UNDP), with its technic¬
al projects, touches almost every develop¬
ing country in the world. Refugees in all
continents are protected by the activities of
the High Commissioner for Refugees.
Women fighting for equality and dignity are
encouraged by discussions in United Na¬
tions forums such as the recent Nairobi
Conference. Many civilians in many coun¬
tries have felt more secure because of the
presence of United Nations peace-keeping
forces. If, as we sincerely hope, the initia¬
tive taken by the World Health Organization
(WHO) and the United Nations Children's
Fund (UNICEF) to immunize all children in
the world against serious infectious dis¬
eases by 1990 is crowned with success,
innumerable families will think of the United
Nations as a benefactor.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 78 French francs. 2 years (valid only in France):
144 French francs. Binder for a year's issues: 56 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed ar¬
ticles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER. Photo capitions and headlines are written
by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published
in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produ¬
ced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris: (2) University Microfilms (Xe¬
rox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (30 NCR. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-ln-chlef: Olga Rodel
Managing Edltor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English:
Roy Malkin
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille: Frederick Potter
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special pro|ects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-
Chief in Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian:
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic(Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
34
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C 1 - Avril 1986 -
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de l'UNESCO - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A.. Z.l. route dÉtampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
just P"
bitsHedby
Unesco
jora-
nd Lus sut^e}_rt cot-
boteVt^T^i0-"«ansPott
ñauo
na\ lot^tional
Vu^<oY>
..*^
opet
atot
the
^0tSns and eSVi;nd tout
corpora*0* of ^stf« a ;^ the
atvd tVie
been
in w
theV
bave
cüUutaV
d W
socro
ed
cou^eS
%**.*-«^^
incluí
the
vj\tb
tAon-pt
ot'vt-
corpor**ns
cttVtS«L
actW^ to^ñstn
î°%r so«a\ toTndus«v
counts
in
tbe
a\teed
\3ticsco
wiQ2-3-l02W «rYlftanCS
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor In your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collingwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications : Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals : Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent : United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
175, 5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth St., Melbourne, Victoria 3000. AU¬
STRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHA¬
MAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box N-3138. Nassau. BAHRAIN. The
Arabian Agencies and Distributing Co.. AI Mutanabi St., P.O. Box 156,
Manama. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq Build¬
ing, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola. Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University ot the
West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown. BEL¬
GIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only : N.V. Handelmaatschappij
Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deume-Antwerpen. French edition and
general Unesco publications agent : Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060
Brussels. CCP 000-0070823-1 3. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre. P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552 Merchant
Street,. Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine
St. West, Montreal, Qué. H3H 1M7. CHINA. China National Publications
Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 83, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O Box 1 722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVA¬
KIA. S.N.T.L., SpaJena 51-113 02, Prague 1; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B.
790-111-27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahramcni literatura, 11 Souke-
nicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only : Atta Verlag .-Publishers, Hurbanovo nam.
6,693 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG, Tidssknft-
service. 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1 970 Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB REPUB¬
LIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb St.,
Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa. Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10;
Suomalainen Kiqakauppa Oy. Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. FRAN¬
CE. Librairie de l'Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans. CCP 12598-48.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postlach 140. 710
Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G D.R. FED. REP. OF
pERMANY. For the Unesco Couner (German, English, French and Spanish
editions) : Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basartstrasse 57.
D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Presbytenan Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.. P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The
Unrversity Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd.. 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat St.. Abderdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock
Rd., Kowtoon. Hong Kong Govt. Information Services, Publication Centre,
Baskerville House. 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kuttura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B.
149-H-13Ö9. Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjom Jonsson and Co., H.F.
Hatnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg. Ballard
Estate, Bombay 400036; 17 Chrtaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a. Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-
500001 . Sub-depots : Oxford Book and Stationery Co.. 1 7 Park St., Calcutta
7001 6; Sandia House, New Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and
Culture. Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Rd , New Delhi. 110001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto Iskandardinata
111, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37. Jakarta Pusat. IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 28 Vassal Shirazi St.. Enghélab
Ave., P.O. Box 314/1466, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, 1188
Englab Ave.. Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158. P.O. Box 11365-4498.
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzies Bookshop, Al Rashid St., Baghdad. IRELAND.
The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Rd., Walkmstown,
Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A B.C. Bookstore Ltd , P.O Box 1 283. 71 Allenby Rd., Tel
Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librena Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.), Via
Lamarmora 45. Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence JAMAICA. Sangster's
Bookstores Ltd., P.O. Box 366. 101 Water Lane, Kingston; University of the
West Indies Bookshop, Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 1 1 3. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd., Quran House,
Mfangano St., P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commis¬
sion for Unesco. P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop
Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait, for the Unesco Courier : Faratalla Press Agency,
P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O.
Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. UBERIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd.. P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIECHTENSTEIN. Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B.
5-9494 Schaan. UBYAN ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. Agency tor Development of
Publication and Distnbution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Lib¬
rairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book
Service, Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichin, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Co-operatrve Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-1 1 . MALTA.
Sapienzas, 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30
Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte
Cario. NEPAL Sajha Prakashan Polchowk. Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS.
Keesing Boeken B.V., Joan Muyskenweg, 22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Am¬
sterdam. NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200.
Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government PuWismg P.O. Box
1 4277-Kilbimie Wellington, 1 30, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1 721 Chnstchurch;
Alma St.. P.O. Box B57. Hamilton; Pnnces St.. P.O. Box 1104, Dunedm.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of
Ibadan. P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Book¬
shop of Lagos: The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY.
Johan Grundt Tanum. P.O.B. 1 1 77 Sentrum - Oslo 1 , Narvesen A/S; Subscrip¬
tion and Trade Book Service, P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad. Oslo 6; Unrversitets
Bokhandelen. Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem. Oslo 3. PAKIS¬
TAN. Mirza Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729,
Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book Development
in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29-
PHILIPPINES. National Book Store. Inc.. 701, Rizal Ave., Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch,
Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL. Dias &
Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
F007SEYCHELLES. Nabonal Bookshop, P.O. Box 48. Mahé; New Sarvice
Ltd.. Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131. Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay.
Njala University and Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SING¬
APORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Time« Jurong, 2 Jurong Port
Rd., Singapore 2261. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modem Book¬
shop and General, P.O. Box 951. Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. For the
Unesco Couner (single copies) only : Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. F007SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop. 100 Sir Chittampa-
lam Gardiner Mawata. P.O.B. 244, Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop.
P.O. Box 111 8. Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungel.
Hovbokhandet, Regenngsgatan 1 2, Box 1 6356, 1 0327 Stockholm 1 6. For the
Unesco Couner : Svenska FN Förbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 1 50 50 S-1 04. 65
Stockholm; WennergrervWilliams, Box 30004-S-104. 25 Stockholm; Esserte
rxteknttscentralen. Gamla Brogatan 26. Box 62-101 20 Stockholm. SWIT¬
ZERLAND. All publications : Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich; Librairie
Payot, Rue Grenus 6. 1211, Geneva 11, OOP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also
in Lausanne, Baste, Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zürich. TANZA¬
NIA. Dar-es- Salaam Bookshop, P.O B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd.. 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O.
Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panrt. Mansion 9, Rajdamnem Ave., Bangkok;
Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD ANO
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair,
Trinidad W 1. TURKEY. Haset Krtapevi A.S., IstklAI Caddesi, No 469. Posta
Kutusu 21 9, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. P.O. Box 71 45.
Kampala. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O.. P.O. Box
276, London SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester. Birmingham, Bristol; for sctentrfic maps only : McCarta Ltd,, 122
King's Cross Rd.. London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd St.. New York. N.Y. 10017. Orders for books and periodicals : P.O. Box
1 222. Ann Arbor. Ml 481 06. USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimrtro-
va 39, Moskva 113095. YEMEN. 14th October Corporation. P.O. Box 4227.
Aden. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zatozba,
Zoprtaneva 2. Lubfana: NoW, Terazije 27/11. Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distnbuöon Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664 Lusaka. ZIMBAB¬
WE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Ave.. Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
i ¡ * * » «
* "V I * !
,i . . <
ai
iv ¿
jiL'J,.»,
iVU'v«
i »
14.' '
/ r'-
Acoustics, the science of sound and of its effects on people, is of
great importance to contemporary music in its search for new
sound effects. These two photos show the spectrograph^ analy¬
sis of the voice of a young Frenchman saying the word "Unesco"
(above) and (below) the phrase "Bonjour aux amis de l'Unesco"
("HellO, friends Of UneSCO"). Phoio <C) In Camera. Paris
3 ¿iA»H
ft «
i
t
A Ai.'
'in |H
i
i1''.i il.
]]>
</page>
</document>
