<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068956eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
1955
(8th year)
Price : 7d (U. K.)
-30 francs (France)
AWAKENING
CONTINENT
Latin America in new perspective
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Austin
Ti/huahua
^Nuevo Lan
m*a±
P^
TO %,
"^""Christi ,
Brownsville r, i
Matamoros " " /
M e/x
Jacksonville
S.'a»s
>S!Petersbiirg¿r
andp
\West Palm Beach
vw*
Key West0
as*0"
BK'HAMA i? ,í;
:cbr.) >
Ä
	J>.	fl/fer^s;^iäfA>n/3?* .Vj-i .*;	- - //- -¿Ä -$-	,A
injpsche
"',:'V
era/cruz.
Tspatíi
ampe^.m \ ^y^p?*$^&'
Kini
^>>,
¿df-?1"" Guate^f^
HONDURAS^ ' \ _ ^ J1',^ 2 H
arnat
7'Sp
Il g a.-fl'	£g,g a
^Barbuda (Br)'*
(Br.)
¡(Sí.,
oupé(F^)Sr.üuadel i
iqkunicaÎBr.y '
UN ESCO
IN LATIN
MEXICO. Regional Fundamental Education ECUADOR
" Centre for Latin America established at Patz
cuaro. Over 160 trainees already graduated Guayaquil
' with students from Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, LaLipvtpd
Colombia, Costa Rica, Cuba, Ecuador, El ofQmy. '
Salvador, Guatemala, Haiti, Honduras, Mexico, F*Paruí¿s( "^"ö...?
Nicaragua, Panama, Paraguay, Peru, Uruguay,
' Venezuela. Scientific and technical documen-
' "ation centre created in Mexico City. Feeds
science data to universities, industries.
GUATEMALA. Development
school system. See page 1 6.
EL SALVADOR. Two technical assistance
missions completed: education for better
living in the San Andres Valley; improvement
I of primary schools (village life) and secondary
schools (vocational guidance and job training).
NICARAGUA. Technical assistance in teach¬
er training and fundamental education.
COSTA RICA. Developing a Pan-American
Highway boom town. See page 24.
CUBA. HQ (Havana) for Unesco's Regional I
Office in the Western Hemisphere.
So
VENEZUELA. Technical assistance in train- -»
i ing statisticians. j
COLOMBIA. Model public library at Mede
lin. 200,000 people go to schoolby
radio. See page 18.
ECUADOR. Centre of Ex-Unesco Fellow¬
ship Holders actively campaigning for better
children's reading material. Technical assis¬
tance in training mathematics, physics, chem-
iicry and biology teachers. Andean High¬
lands Project. See page 4.
PERU. Technical assistance in science teach¬
ing; development of "60-cent laboratory".
Andean Highlands Project. See page 4.
BOLIVIA. Experiment in primary schooling.
La Paz. Youngsters taught to read and write
in 50 days. Andean Highlands Project. See
page 4.
BRAZIL. Technical aid in nuclear physics
(cosmic rays), agricultural chemistry, electro¬
nics, geology, cellulose production, technology
in Rio de Janeiro. Survey of mineral resources
of the "Dry Polygon" (See Page I 0). Confer¬
ence on Public Libraries in Latin America
in October 1951 at Sao Paulo called by Orga¬
nization of American States and Unesco.
URUGUAY. Unesco mission to set -up
|| scientific and technical documentation centre
at Montevideo now completed. Centre oper¬
ating under Uruguayan direction. Headquar¬
ters for Unesco's Regional Science Co-oper¬
ation Office for Latin America.
HAITI. Marbial Valley pilot-project in educa¬
tion.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
ffHESCÜ
Number2- 1955
8th YEAR
ner
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
Latin America in new perspective
4 'LAND HUNGER' ON THE TOP OF THE ANDES
An ambitious U.N. project affecting 7,000,000 Indians
By Alfred Metraux
10 BRAZIL'S POLYGON OF DROUGHT
A wasteland rich in mineral resources
By E. Aubert de la Rue
UNESCOS' IN LATIN AMERICA
By Daniel Behrman
16 (I) THE MAYANS MODERNIZE
Weaving ancient designs the modern way
18 (II) DON QUIXOTE OF THE RADIO
200,000 campesinos go to school "by radio"
24 (III) BOOM TOWN ON THE PAN-
AMERICAN HIGHWAY
Education guides community development
in Costa Rica
27 ON LOOKING INTO A MOCHICAN URN
A fabulous record of life in ancient Peru
By Jorge Carrera Andrade
33 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Brief notes on education, science and culture
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Pans 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemln
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not copyrighted maybe reprinted from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/.; $ 1.50 or 300 French frs.
MC. 35.1 89. A
*
Unesco Courier. N' 2. 1955
THE COVER : Almost in the centre of the
Bolivian Altiplano lies Lake Poopo, 12,140
feet above sea level. Here a train is crossing
a causeway bound for Patino tin mines now
nationalized by Bolivian government. In this
region of the Andes with its impressive spec¬
tacle of gigantic peaks capped with snow all
year round, an ambitious programme is under
way to resettle many unemployed Indian mine
workers in more fertile zones. (Photo Almsay).
THE AWAKENING CONTINENT
The average traveller leaves for Latin America convinced
by what he has read and heard that he will find one-
half of the population dancing the samba, the rumba,
the bamboco or whatever the local variation may be while
the other half sleeps under trees.
The average traveller is always disappointed.
A new wind is blowing through Latin Americathrough a
continent of many contrasts, with its mountain-tops under
perpetual snow and - sweating tropical lowlands, with its
great modern metropolises and its hinterland villages, with
its famous- writers, poets and thinkers and its more than
70,000,000 illiterates.
The phrase Latin America alone is a handy one, but it is
misleading. It tends to make an outsider place, let us say,
Colombia and Mexico within the same pigeonholes; and that
is as false as saying that Frenchmen and Yugoslavs are
exactly alike because they are continental Europeans. Latin
America's common language (with the exception of Brazil)
and common historical heritage are a tremendous advantage
today in modernizing a continent. But national differences
remain great; in the past, they were so great that it was
quite normal for a country to be in closer relations with
Europe or North America than with its own neighbours.
Our average traveller is bound to return home convinced
that Latin America stands poised on the brink of an eco¬
nomic revolution. The vagaries of world markets have
taken the easy profit out of one-crop economies. World
War II shut Latin America off from its traditional sources of
everything from type-writers to vacuum cleaners. Many a
country was, forced to choose between building its own
industries or do without and chose to build. In the Brazil
of fifty years ago, the rubber industry meant a naked Indian
tapping a tree somewhere in the Amazon for crude rubber to
be shipped immediately abroad. Modern Brazil makes
1,500,000 tyres a year. Colombia is now the fourth Latin
American country to produce its own iron and steel and it is
producing it on a site where ten years ago campesinos
ploughed the soil with oxen.
Latin America cannot be judged by the book standards of
"economic underdevelopment." The statisticians can prove
that production and standards of living are low and must be
raised, but their statistics cannot show_ one salient fact:
Latin America has, on its own soil, sizeable islands of modern
economies. The situation in many of these countries is that
of a colony, but with the "mother country" also placed within
the same borders.
In such a situation, technical assistance rendered by the
United Nations can make a tremendous impact on Latin
America. First there is the "blast furnace" of economic
potential which is merely waiting to be tapped. Secondly,
the "international expert" finds himself at home the moment
he steps off his airliner. A Mexican working in South Ame¬
rica or a Peruvian in Central America speaks the same
language and in many respects thinks the same way as the
people he is working with. There is the barrier of national
differences, true, but when it is overcome by men of goodwill
the results are often dazzling.
In Latin America, the United Nations and its agencies have
been able to undertake a wide range of missions (conducted
in many places by Latin Americans) to attack the immediate
and profound problems that hamper economic development.
Their work ranges from research in nuclear physics to
teaching adults to read and write. After a period of five
years, its fruits are worth a close examination.
In this issue, the Unesco Courier presents a few examples
of some of the results achieved. There are scores of others,
all of them exciting and fraught with significance. The
following pages are an attempt to help readers 'get a glimpse
of an old continent in new perspective.
JOSE DE BENITO.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
LAND HUNGER
ON THE TOP OF THE ANDES
by Alfred Metraux
THE fate of some 7,000,000 Andean Indians who live at alti¬
tudes which soon leave other men breathless and dizzy, is
today the deep concern of three Latin American republics
and the United Nations. At stake is the future economic develop¬
ment of Bolivia, Peru and Ecuador.
The Indian problem facing these three., countries is in many
ways identical since the region inhabited by the Quechuas and
the Aymarás forms a geographical, economic, social and cultural
unity. For this reason an effort to improve the living conditions
of the Indians is being made on an international basis.
For the past three years a vast international project of the
United Nations has been under way to help Bolivia, Peru and
Ecuador meet some of the most urgent problems facing the In¬
dians living in the Altiplano (high plateau). The Andean High¬
lands Project one of the biggest in the U.N.'s world programme
of technical assistance has been entrusted to the International
Labour Organization with UNESCO, the Food and Agriculture
Organization and the World Health Organization co-operating.
From the beginning it was obvious that the many problems of
the entire Indian population could not be attacked at the same
time. The problems had to be sifted out and given priorities.
Investigation showed that over-population, and as a result a seri¬
ous shortage of land, was the main cause of the stagnation of
Indian life.
The Bolivian Government for example has been carrying out an
important land reform programme in recent years. An answer bad
to be found to the question posed by thousands of Indians who
could not be granted land and who did not have the skills to
earn their living in industry. Bolivia looked eastward to the im
mense sub-tropical plains around Santa Cruz. A few years ago
these rich plains were almost inaccessible, but Santa Cruz is now
linked to Cochabamba (6,000 feet up in the Andes) by a new
road. This road may well open new horizons to Bolivia's economy
once people are brought into the almost deserted plains.
Bolivia's President Victor Paz Estenssoro has announced a plan
for settling this new untapped territory with Indians from the
highlands, miners who can no longer find work in the tin mines,
and even soldiers. By settling soldiers on state land Bolivia is fol¬
lowing the example of ancient Rome.
To carry out a plan of such scope, the difficulties of which
can easily be imagined, Bolivia needed outside help. Reception
centres for new arrivals, schools and dispensaries have to be set
up. The U.N. has been asked to supply technicians for such tasks
and equally important, to help train the technicians of the future.
At Pillapi, in Bolivia, a large estate has been transformed into
an experimental agricultural centre. Co-operatives are being orga¬
nized there to enable Indians to purchase livestock, seeds and
farm tools. A public health service has been set up and the
idea that Indians would oppose modern medical treatment has
proved completely false. Schools have been opened on the farms
and a permanent fundamental education centre is to be built.
The efforts of the Peruvian Government to open up the rich
subtropical Tambopata Valley on the eastern flanks of the Andes
are aimed at the same goal settlement of the Andean Indian
to give him a fair chance. In the following article. Dr. Alfred
Metraux, Unesco anthropologist who headed the first mission to
this region describes some of the problems and explains how the
opening up of new lands could transform the Indian's existence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
A DEAD WORLD
of rocks, glaciers and
sand seems to move
by under the eyes of
airline passengers fly¬
ing over the great
chain of the Andes.
But this seemingly
dead and desolate
land is inhabited by
men whose ancestors
resisted the over¬
whelming forces of
nature for thousands
of years. Here they
even built a great civi¬
lization. Today, how¬
ever, the men of the
mountains are look¬
ing for a new destiny.
(Photos Almasy and ILO)
The Indians who live in the
high Andes are a marked
people. Centuries of slavery,
misery and humiliation have crush¬
ed themand even their once fa¬
mous pride is gone. Today, their
problems are countless and any
improvement in their conditions
seems almost hopeless unless a
total transformation is brought
about in their way of life.
One of the greatest problems fac¬
ing the Indians today is the
snortage of fertile land and as a
result the migration of many fami¬
lies to the Eastern (Amazonian)
siue of the Andes.
After the slaughter carried out
by the Spanish Conquistadors, the
Indian population, which had di¬
minished to an alarming degree,
became stable ; then, during the
19th Century it began to rise ra¬
pidly. This fact amazes anyone
who has had any experience of
Indian living conditions. The An¬
dean Indians are reputed to be
among the most unhygienic peo¬
ples on earth ; unfortunately, this
is no great exaggeration. The mere
inventory of the diseases afflicting
them is enough to cause a shudder.
Yet not even the filth and a high
infant mortality rate has preven¬
ted their population growth from
keeping pace with that of other
groups in Latin America.
Demographic pressure however
has made "land-hunger" all the
more acute. They are hemmed into
lands which the white man left
them and their plots have been so
frequently divided and sub-divided
by inheritances that Indian farms
are now measured in so many
"furrows".
On lands farmed for thousands
of years and given no rest, yields
are rarely good. To
make matters worse, (Continued
farming is always a , on
risky business at high next page.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
LAND HUNGER' (Continued)
altitudes. A sleet storm or one night
of frost can wipe out a harvest. The
misery of the Indians would be unbear¬
able if they did not have an "escape
route" migration.
Last year, a sudden' night frost
destroyed all the crops sown on the
banks of Lake Titicaca (the highest
navigable lake in the world, 12,500 feet
above sea level). The following morn¬
ing, the Indians told us that many of
them were leaving for the coast.
What else could they do?
But even when the Indian leaves his
home in the mountains he is not much
better off. He heads for the cities on
the coast, hoping to And a job as a
labourer or a porter, or any other
unskilled work. Most of the Indians
speak no Spanish and all of them are
illiterate. They make their long trek
to the west on foot through one of the
most desolate lands in the world. The
lucky ones are those who have enough
money to pay for transport and cram
themselves and their families into open
trucks.
To the Indian, the city is a new and
hostile environment where he has to
look haphazardly for work. For days
and sometimes weeks he wanders
through the streets, sleeping on door¬
steps and living on chuno (dehydrated
potatoes) or the grain which he carries
in a sack. Even in Lima, the Peru¬
vian capital, thousands of Indians
cluster around open-air kitchens,
chewing coca leaves to stave off hun¬
ger, while they wait, dejected and im-
' BOWLER HAT' with turned-up leather brim worn by this old woman is the usual
headgear of Bolivian Indians who live In the upper valleys of the Andes. It was originally
inspired by the shape of the hats worn by the Spaniards in Colonial times. (Photo ILO.)
passive, until someone hires them for
a labouring. job.
The evolution of the Indians into a
rootless labouring class aroused the
concern of the Peruvian Government
which then considered the possibility
of re-settling these landless farmers
on the unoccupied eastern slopes of the
Andes. For this reason, Peruvian au¬
thorities asked for United Nations
technical assistance to aid in settling
the Tambopata Valley with Aymara
Indians from the overcrowded banks
of Lake Titicaca where population
density may reach 150 persons per
square mile.
This plan has created a good deal
of controversy in Peru and elsewhere.
It is an accepted belief almost a
dogma that life in the warm lowlands
is fatal to Andean Indians. Dr. Carlos
Monge a famous Peruvian physiologist,
has devoted a lifetime to proving that
the. lungs and other organs of Indians
living at an altitude of between 10,000
and 15,000 feet have been modified by
evolution and adapted to rarified air.
There were many good reasons to fear
that changing this environment might
prove disasterous to the health of the
Indians.
Spanish chroniclers of the 16th
Century tell us that the Incas who
once reigned over Bolivia, Peru and
Ecuador shared this belief. When
they deported entire Indian peoples
from one end of their empire to the
other, the Incas always tried to dupli¬
cate previous living conditions.
It is too early to say whether or not
this biological inability of the Indian
to adapt himself to life at sea-level is
as absolute as we have been told or
whether settlement on virgin land
along the branches of the Amazon is
really possible. The question is vitally
important for the future of these
peoples. The task assigned to the
LLAMA CONVOY CROSSING ONE OF THE HIGH ANDEAN
«SS3*' - -J
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
| *#-
WtW ¿M+m[ X;^74|
Hf\JkAj
^^L_ d"\
B^ttb nfc- ^H ^Jf
^^^ SA>
-
DANCE STEPS of Indians are an ancient
heritage. Here village men follow mono¬
tonous round of movements. (Photo Verger)
teWÄiftfl*;
BAREFOOT BALLET is suggested by group of Indians using same house building methods
( as their Inca ancestors. Men leaping into the air are pressing down the earth inside a
wooden framework to make walls waterproof, while others dig out more earth. (Photo ILO.)
first United Nations team in the An¬
dean Highlands was to make an on-
the-spot study of the Tambopata
Valley, which slopes away towards the
Amazon Basin and the Madre de Dios
Province, to determine if it could be
settled by the Aymarás at present
condemned to work on their tiny plots
of barren land.
As the crow flies, the Tambopata
Valley on the Bolivian border is a
next-door neighbour of the Andean
plateau. It is however separated by a
formidable barrier the chain of the
Andes which must be passed through
deep, narrow gorges where the sun sel¬
dom penetrates. Only Dante's Inferno,
as it was conceived by the great
illustrator Gustave Doré, can give an
idea of the landscape of the Sandia
Valley which leads to Tambopata. It
is a great crack in the earth running
from 5,000 to 10,000 feet deep. Along
one flank, there is a winding path
which zig-zags down towards a foam¬
ing torrent only to climb back up again
to dizzy heights. Raimondi, the fam¬
ous 19th century geographer, who
was an authority on bad roads, called
this one of the worst he had seen in all
Peru.
After an exhausting four-day march,
the traveller suddenly finds himself
face-to-face with the Tambopata
Valley. It is another world gentle
mountains, thick forests singing to the
tune of hundreds of brooks, prairies of
tall grass and a bluish ridge of peaks
deployed towards the great Amazon
plain.
One hundred years ago, this Andean
Arcadia was deserted when Sir Cle¬
ment Markham visited it to hunt for
the Cinchona plants (the source of
quinine). Today, between 4,000 and
5,000 Indians (no exact census has yet
been taken) have settled there to live
in relative prosperity from their coffee
and other tropical crops.
We visited these coffee plantations.
The bushes were sturdy and well cared
for. Everyone had enough to eat and
huts were larger and better built than
on the high plateaux. Without any
private or government aid, these
pioneers had conquered the forest.
They were Indians from the
villages of Moho and Coni- (Continued
ma beside Lake Titicaca. on
They had been born and next page.) .
PLATEAUX IS DRIVEN FROM BEHIND BY TWO INDIAN RIDERS. THESE "CAMELS" OF THE NEW WORLD ARE BRED AS BEASTS OF BURDEN AND FOR THEIR WOOL. (Photo Almasy)
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
'LAND HUNGER' (Continuel)
REED CANOES are woven by Indians of Lake Titicaca as there is no
wood thereabouts. These craft are sufficiently stable to resist the
terrible storms that often whip this 130-mile long lake more
than 12,500 feet above sea level into a fury. (Photo Almasy.)
MARKET DAY in Bolivian village of Chunumake centre of coca
production brings Indians with their produce to sell or barter.
Although Bolivia is in the torrid zone, these plateau villages have a
comparatively cold climate because of their height. (Photo Almasy.)
raised in the cold mountain air and
later they had worked the rocky soil
of the dry puna with their short hoes.
The contrast between their birthplaces
and the valley where we met them was
particularly striking.
Are these mountaineers a living de¬
nial of all the pessimistic theories
concerning the conservatism, the lack
of initiative and the physiological
inadaptability of the Andean Indians?
They are, but what really counts is how
these Highlanders have learned to
become excellent tropical farmers.
The Conima Indians told us proudly:
"We were the ones who opened up i.he
Yungas of Bolivia." This is not quite
the case, but it is true that thousands
of Conima Indians have settled in the
Yungas, the tropical valleys in the An¬
des behind La Paz, the Bolivian capital.
These warm lands produce an excellent
grade of coffee and their soil is among
the richest and the most fertile of all
Bolivia.
The pioneers of Tambopata had all
learned the lessons of the Yungas.
They had worked there as farmers and
as small land-owners until they were
forced to return to their native villages
by political disputes. There, they also
returned to their old misery, but they
were not discouraged. Carrying their
food supplies on their backs, they
crossed the Andes and, as soon as they
had found land similar to their old
holdings, they began to clear away the
NARROW ROADS,
only links between
fertile valleys of the
Eastern Andes, are
very often squeez¬
ed between sheer
rock walls and dizzy
precipices. Here, a
meeting with another
vehicle calls for intri¬
cate manoeuvring.
(Photo A. Metraux.)
8
jungle. Once they had planted maize
and sweet potatoes on burned-over
clearings, some of them returned to the
bi rren highlands while others worked
old gold placers abandoned by the
Spaniards. At harvest time, they
returned and found their fields blan¬
keted with maize. They had succeeded
in gaining a foothold in the valley and
now they were safe. Then they cleared
more land and started to grow coffee.
These pioneers became leaders of the
settlers and helped the Indians who
followed in their footsteps. Much of
their success must be credited to the
"ayni", the Aymarás' system of coope¬
rative aid to each other. The "ayni"
can mean a loan to a member of the
community faced by heavy expenses
for example, a funeral or a wedding.
It can also mean relatives or friends
getting together to sow or bring in a
harvest. Thanks to the help of the
"ayni", a new settler in Tambopata can
keep going until his first harvest. Lat¬
er, he repays the community.
The Indian settlers at TambopaTa
have not severed all links with their
native mountains. Every year, they
return for their village festival to
breathe "fresh air" and eat their tra¬
ditional food. They jealously cling to
the tiny plots which they have inherit¬
ed at home even though yields are
dubious.
Many of these settlers lead a double
life, economically speaking, at least.
During part of the year, they are tro¬
pical planters and, the rest of the time,
they are Andean peasants. They are
the backbone of the Indian element
settling virgin territories. Indian colo¬
nization has not always given good
results up until now because it has
been carried out without any help and
on a hit-or-miss basis. But it is true
that if the plan now under .considera¬
tion does bear fruit, its first result
will be to bring to the surface the la¬
tent energy, sobriety and courage of
the Andean Indian.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
¿rPw
V*** ^ a. W._ *"* ">
r*4^
LUNAR LANDSCAPE in the Andes
has been scoured out by rain and wind.
Buried in these mountains are great
mineral riches which would have
remained inaccessible were it not for
the Indians. They alone are able to
work at great altitudes, unaffected by
the bjeak desolation. (Photo Almasy.)
\fr$- V
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
BRAZIL'S POLYGON
WHERE EVERY
DROP COUNTS.
In the parched soil of
Brazil's arid north
eastern region a farm¬
er reaches water after
digging into the dried-
up bed of the River
Serido, near Parelhas.
Though important mi¬
neral deposits exist
'In plenty, water
is still the most
precious commodi¬
ty In this land of
drought and famine
OF DROUGHT
To a Brazilian, the word Nordeste
automatically evokes the spectre
of drought and famine which
. periodically afflict the great wastelands
in the northeastern part of his country.
This ill-fortune is all the more tragic
because, by the normal rules of geo¬
graphy, the Nordeste should have the
same damp, rainy climate as its
neighbour, the Amazon Basin. And,,
as if this grim climatic twist was not
itself a sufficient threat, another prob¬
lem overpopulation weighs heavily
on the area. The several million
inhabitants try vainly to make a living
from farming and stock-raising which
are always at the mercy of the weather.
These 300,000 square miles of parched
land cover some parts, or in some cases
the entire territories, of eight Brazilian
states, running from the north of
Bahia to the Piaui. They have been
termed "The Polygon of Drought" and
their unfortunate inhabitants are
generally referred to as Los Fla-
geUados (Those who scourge them¬
selves) because of the obstinacy with
which they cling to their lands despite
the hostile climate.
The geography and the problems of
this hard, austere region which has not
10
by
E. Aubert de la Rue
been able to keep step with the rest
of Brazil (except for the Amazon
Basin), have made it a curious and
picturesque land with many grandiose
aspects.
Not all of northeastern Brazil is so
badly off, however. Even though the
coastal zone of the state of Ceara
suffers from a shortage of moisture,
the shores on the east receive a fair
share of rain. Along this humid, pri¬
vileged fringe no more than 30 miles
in width, sugar cane is produced on a
large scale. Here, in a tropical green
setting, is Recife, the main city
of northeast Brazil and its principal
port, with its contrasts between archaic
old Brazil and the dynamic young
country of today.
But this smiling facade is misleading.
Behind it stretches the sertao, the
backlands where the rainfall is ex¬
tremely variable. Some parts of the
sertao are near desert while others, at
a higher altitude, receive a heavier
rainfall which serves mainly to water
the caatinga, an Indian -word which
the Brazilians use to describe the weird
vegetation so well adapted to this
hostile climate.
The caatinga consists mainly of
twisted dwarf trees, many of them
bristling with thorns, and surrounded
by a no-man's-land of cactus. Here
and there, barrigudas grotesque, pot¬
bellied trees lend a comic note to
the inhospitable brush. Lumbering
for construction and firewood has made
heavy inroads into the caatinga, to say
nothing of land clearing, frequent
forest fires and the ravages of goats.
Around towns, it has been reduced to-
a carpet of brush plants, each one more
thorny than its neighbour. When the
vaqueiros the close-mouthed cowboys
of the Nordeste drive their herds
into these pastures for grazing,
they dress in leather from head to foot
and the bellies of their agile horses are
protected by leather aprons.
These riders of the caatinga, in their ,
red outfits and their goatskin three-
cornered hats, have no easy life. Often,
they have to "harvest" the cactus
themselves and singe off its thorns
before they can feed their animals. To
provide for lean years, they actually
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
Hostile landscape
The hostile, unsmiling landscape of Brazil's
Polygon of Drought has served as a setting
and an inspiration for some of the country's
most powerful and realistic modern literature.
Novels have depicted the harsh, violent life
here. Perhaps the most famous book on this
region is "Revolt in the Backlands" (Os
Sertoes) by Euclides da Cunha. This tells the
story of the campaign waged by the Brazilian
authorities against the rebel leader Antonio
Conselheiro, whose partisans followed him
with fanatic devotion to the death. This is
the land of the coatingo, the weird, twisted
dwarf trees and dried-up scorched plains, such
as that in the Ceara region (left) bounded by
the Sierra da Uruburetama in the distance.
In, years of serious drought, sad processions
of retirantes (below) who have sold their
herds and abandoned their homes, cross these
burning wastes heading for kinder regions.
raise fields of non-spiny cactus which
serve as fodder for stock.
Other crops, too, can be raised in
this unsmiling land mainly maize,
manioc, cotton and sisal which can get
along in rocky soil and a hard climate.
Even though most of the year is dry,
river beds still keep enough humidity
to support some farming. Planted
with beans, sweet potatoes or squash,
they form winding green ribbons run¬
ning through the scorched backlands.
There is water all year round only
in the majestic Rio Sao Francisco,
which has its sources in the rainy
north. In the Polygon of Drought, it
hurtles over the Paulo Afonso Falls
which will soon become northeastern
Brazil's major supplier of electricity.
Throughout the region, rainwater
and flood waters are now being stored
painstakingly behind dams. The entire
country is studded with reservoirs,
large and small,' and, at many points,
they have made life much easier for
the Nordestinos who can now raise
crops on irrigated land.
When the rains come to the caatinga,
they cover this spiny
jungle with a miraculous ' on on
coating of tender leaves ne*1 P°Se)
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
BRAZIL'S POLYGON
OF DROUGHT
(Continued)
FLUVIAL
FRONTIER
between two Bra¬
zilian states, Ser-
gipe and Alagoas,
is the broad Sao
Francisco River.
Here, it nears the
sea, 1,800 miles
from its source.
almost overnight. This happens
usually between December and March
after seven or eight months of almost
total drought. -In only a matter of
days, the winter setting of the Polygon
(accompanied by temperatures of 105°
Fahrenheit, of course) is replaced by a
green landscape which has nothing of
the tropics about it. The coconut
groves around the villages and the
relentless heat of the sun are the only
reminders that the Equator is close.
The economy of northeastern Brazil
is handicapped more by the irregu¬
larity of this rainfall rather than by
its dearth. When the rains come, they
fall, in torrents which are greeted
joyfully by the Polygon's people. True,
they, spell a rich harvest for the imme¬
diate future... but they also wash away
huge quantities of arable topsoil.
In some years, the long-waited rains
never materialize. If this happens two
or three years running as * was the
case from 1951 to 1953then disaster
strikes. Herds are wiped out, entire
towns go hungry and the backlanders
from the Polygon set out for more
fortunate regions. Each one of these
droughts touches off a chaotic mass
exodus.
The Government has vainly tried to
channel this exodus into neighbouring
Maranhao which is thinly populated.
Instead, the flagellados flock down to
the booming south of Brazil. And the
miserable parade of retirantes, who
PART-TIME PROSPECTORS of northeastern Brazil are the garlmpelfos
who forsake farming during the dry season to uncover the mineral riches
of the soil. Already the region is producing more than 20 different mine¬
rals of economic importance. With primitive, home-made equipment
(top right), prospectors dig up deposits of tantalite and beryllium or search
for fluorine (left) and other minerals which bring good prices on the world
market. Group of ^arimpelrcs (bottom, right) have sold their minerals at
weekly market In Parelhas and now wait to be taken back home by truck.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 2. 1955
LOCAL INDUSTRIES make maximum use
of the few above-ground natural resources
offered by the " Polygon of Drought ". Pot¬
tery is a thriving craft and, as shown in photo
above, jars and pitchers are in great demand in
this land of thirst. Pitchers and bowls dis¬
played outside a potter's house in the Ceara
region (above, left) show the variety and
artistry of these products. Although Brazil's
chief tobacco growing area Is round Bahia, to
the south of the dry Nordeste, the plant is also
widely grown around Paraiba, in the Nordeste's
coastal region. Leaves, twisted Into thick rolls
(below, left), find a ready sale in the market at
Crato (below), In the neighbouring state of Ceara.
have sold their herds and abandoned
their homes, covers the tracks of the
backlands as it crawls south in jolting,
lurching truckloads into already over-
populated cities.
The arrival of these waves of fla-
gellados and their families, who flood
into the cities, raises all kinds of prob¬
lems, for many are unable to find
work. Some remain homesick for their
native caatinga and, when the rains
come to the Nordeste, they return home
i again but even poorer than the day
they left. Brazil's leaders believe, and
rightly so, that mining can help bolster
the economy of the Polygon. This
belief is not merely a wild hope: it is
based on the discovery of several rare
minerals in the region during the past
15 years. Although it has not been
thoroughly prospected, the Polygon is
already producing about twenty differ¬
ent minerals of economic importance.
This mining is carried on mainly by
garimpeiros, self-taught prospectors
who work on their own with primitive
equipment. Under these conditions it
is tough work and in the torrid climate
of the Nordeste, the miners often .have
to haul the water they need by mule-
back. But they persevere and their
doggedness often pays off. Each of
them hopes to have the same luck as
Vicente Paulo, a labourer who made a
strike, quite by accident, at Sao Vicente
in the state of Paraiba, in 1941. Thous¬
ands' of garimpeiros followed him and,
in a few years, pulled out five tons of
nuggets and gold dust. At present,
however, prospectors are concentrating
on beryllium, tungsten, .lithium and
other minerals which bring high prices
on the world market and which can
be worked relatively easily in surface
deposits.
Garimpeiro prospecting is seasonal
work and depends to a large extent on
the weather. If the rains come on
schedule, the prospectors stop harvest¬
ing minerals and work their farms. In
dry years, their ranks swell, for many
a farmer turns to mining to keep his
family alive. Unfortunately, their pri¬
mitive methods of working lead to a
sheer waste of minerals.
Prospecting in the Polygon, now a
local affair, should be extended to
cover the entire dry belt of northeast
Brazil and experienced engineers
should be sent on the spot to guide the
garimpeiros. In addition, these pro¬
spectors should be trained and given
proper equipment, and their efforts co¬
ordinated. Under such conditions, min¬
ing in the Nordeste, where there are
now only a few well-equipped mines,
would cease to be a mere '"picking" of
minerals. And it would enable this
land handicapped by its climate to pull
its weight in the economic life of Bra¬
zil a goal towards which the Bra¬
zilian Federal Government is now
turning its efforts.
Photos published on pages 10 to ID are copy¬
right by the author, Edgar Aubert de la Hue.
'J he drawing on page 11 is taken front Josué
de Castro's booh, "Geography of Hunger".
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
When a geologist
turns detective
Dr. Edgar Aubert de la Rue, a French geologist,
went to Brazil in 1953 after the Brazilian
Bank of Industrial Development had request¬
ed technical assistance from the United Nations.
His mission was to help pave the way for future
teams of geological prospectors in the northeast of
the country where a complete geological survey had
never been made.
During his career he has covered most of North
America, South America and Australasia, and be¬
fore arriving in Brazil he had been scientific adviser
to the French Government research station in the
Kerguelen Islands in the Antarctic. He spent his
first two months in Brazil . at Rio de Janeiro,
working with Dr. Paiva Leite, Director of the Na¬
tional Bank for Economic Development, and with
the Brazilian Department of Mineral Production to
collect known geological data on north-east Brazil.
Then he disappeared into the "Polygon of Drought",
travelling by jeep.
His work consisted of indicating likely deposits
for intensive prospection in the future. This meant
not only surveying on his own and taking photo¬
graphs he took some 2,000 during the year he spent
in Brazil but also following up clues left by the
local prospectors.
On a typical day, Dr. Aubert de la Rue began
work in the town of Arcoverde, an important road
junction in the centre of the State of Pernambuco.
He had already lost two days in Arcoverde, ironi¬
cally enough, because the dry Polygon was experienc¬
ing one of its torrential rainy seasons and roads
had been washed out. He had used this time to
visit the local prefect and to glean as much infor¬
mation as he could about the region's mining. The
prefect was helpful. He introduced the geologist to
the tailor of Arcoverde, the town's main mineral
dealer, and the tailor was very obliging. He offer¬
ed Dr. Aubert de la Rue samples of titanium,
asbestos, beryllium, mica and iron ore. But, when
the geologist asked where the samples came from,
the tailor only smiled politely.
Dr. Aubert de la Rue took the samples and
walked down to the market place. One farmer
recognized them. They came from the Municipe
(county) of Sertania, about 20 miles west on the
Petrolandia road.
The geologist made an early start. In the Poly¬
gon, there is no point looking at stones after
11 a.m. when the thermometer goes up to 105°
Fahrenheit in the shade if there is any shade.
Minerals are literally too hot to be touched.
When Dr. Aubert de la Rue reached the village
he was seeking, he struck up a conversation with a
cattle hand who seemed to know where the samples
came from. The vaqueiro tethered his horse and
climbed into the jeep. They struck out across
country navigating by landmarks as the jeep
picked its way through clumps of cactus so high
that ranchers in the region sheath their horses'
bellies with leather aprons.
Four miles away, they arrived at a farmhouse.
The farmer was hospitable and he offered to lead
them to his mine. In the mountains next to his
land, he showed them a hole 10 feet deep: the
family mine. Whenever the family needed cash, he,
his wife, and their seven children went out to the
mine and dug up a load of asbestos. Dr. Aubert de
la Rue marked the uncharted mine on his map and
continued to prowl around the region. In the muni¬
cipe, he came across a few samples of titanium
and some extremely favourable indications of the
presence of uranium.
The next day, he left Arcoverde and headed for
a new destination, making a 200-mile jump with his
jeep over the Polygon under the afternoon sun.
Then the same process began all over again. It
was to continue for 12,000 miles.
LARGEST RIVER in the Brazilian Nordeste is the Rio Sao Francisco photographed
trolina (on far bank) and Juazeiro. It is the only river in the region in which thert
SPINY BARRIER of cactus and dwarf trees, the only vegetation that
resists the climate of the Nordeste. After the December rains a
miraculous coating of leaves mantles the dusty soil in green.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
POLYGON OF
DROUGHT (cont'd)
'' .>*:
here as it flows past two towns, Pe¬
ls a flow of water all the year round.
VERSATILE PALM with spiral trunk is put to many uses by the people of the backlands. Its leaves provide a
kind of wax, its trunk is used for house building and from its seeds the poorer people brew themselves a kind of coffee.
I x V " * A
LEATHERCLAD COWBOY, the Voqueiro, is a traditional figure
in the region. These riders of the caatinga protect themselves from the
raking thorns with leather outfits that cover their bodies and legs.
SUN-BAKED ROCKS lie around like handfuls of pebbles cast at
random by a giant. Within their shade a few spindly plants and
trees have taken root, finding enough moisture in the barren soil.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
..In Latin America, Unesco can mean a jeep
I slithering over muddy tracts and fording
I streams in Costa Rica's rainy season,
or a man on horseback riding up into the hill
country of Colombia. It can be a Catholic
brother writing a textbook or a scientist
studying the nutritive values of plants. It
can mean a mechanic installing a lathe or
a teacher introducing eight-year olds to the
printed word." This is what a Unesco cor¬
respondent, Daniel Behrman, found as he
watched Unesco's technical assistance experts
in action in seven Latin American countries
where they are often known simply as "Los
Úneseos." Mr. Behrman was sent on a special
Unesco mission to bring back a first-hand,
realistic report on the results of technical
assistance in Mexico, Guatemala, Costa Rica,
Colombia, Bolivia, Peru and Brazil. Here,
and in other lands of Latin America, the
combined efforts of teachers, broadcasters,
botanists, agriculturists and other experts
are revolutionizing the lives of countless
people today. In the articles that follow,
Daniel Behrman describes what he saw in
Guatemala, Colombia and Costa Rica. A full
account of his trip has appeared in "When the
Mountains Move," a pamphlet published
by Unesco. (Price: $0.75 ; 3/6 ; 175 fr.)
WHEN Don Pedro de Alvarado marched south from
Mexico into Guatemala in 1523 at the head of a
handful of conquistadores, he discovered a people of
weavers in the Mayan Highlands. They used stick-looms^
nothing more than a warp with one end tied around the
weaver's hips as he worked squatting on his heels, but then-
dyes and their designs were astonishing. Each of the Quiche
Indian villages on the plateau wove its own huepiles, blouses
for village women with a wealth of symbolic birds, animals,
human figures and geometric designs.
The Quichés were an adaptable people. When the Span¬
iards brought in the European foot loom, they had no
trouble operating it and duplicating it themselves. On these
new looms, the inhabitants of Quezaltenango, San Marcos,
San Pedro Sacatepéquez and other towns in the highlands,
continued to weave the ancient Mayan designs taught by
their elders.
GUIDING HANDS of skilled ceramics teacher aid those of
an apprentice in the Guatamala City Industrial Institute for
Boyscentre of an industrial education plan directed by govern¬
ment authorities and an international team. (Unesco photos.)
The stick-loom slowly became a curiosity. There was no
limit to the designs that a weaver could create with it, but
it was slow and unproductive. A Quiche woman using a
stick-loom needs almost two months to make a huepil which
she can sell on the old textile market at Quezaltenango for
25 quetzales (the quetzal is on par with the U.S. dollar) . She
takes her work with her wherever she goes, snatching a few
moments from her kitchen or from her fields to unroll the
loom and attach it to a tree.
The foot loom was a vast improvement, but the weavers
had to pay a penalty even for this timid step towards pro¬
ductivity. The fantastic designs of the Mayans, riots of reds
and yellows made with dyes whose secret is lost today, took
too much time to pick out. The weavers turned to sim¬
plified stylized patterns for the sake of production. Unfor¬
tunately, these simplified designs offered little that could not
be reproduced by machine. The goods of the highland
weavers vanished from the markets of the capital at Guate¬
mala City and Guatemala's oldest art began to die out. To
make matters worse, the gain in production had not offset
the loss in quality. A weaver still could produce only three
yards of cloth a day at 30 centavos ($.30) a yard. Whether
he used a food loom and sacrificed art to productivity, or
whether his wife stubbornly clung to her stick loom, the
Quiche weaver was caught in an economic vice.
Then, several years ago, a stranger came to Quezaltenango,
Guatemala's second largest city and the capital of its textile
country. He was Jean-Charles Hugoné a French scientist
and industrial engineer, and he had come into the highlands
as a member of a Unesco technical assistance mission work¬
ing with Guatemala on industrial education. Mr. Hugoné
had had more than 35 years of textile experience, including
a decade in Argentina.
The problem he found in the Mayan Highlands was
obvious : the weavers had to raise production enough to earn
their living and, at the same time, preserve Mayan designs,
their best stock in trade, from extinction. Mr. Hugoné had
had the germ of an inspiration one day in Guatemala City
when he and Dr. Ernest Cofino, director of the city's biggest
orphanage, were going over the institution's vocational
training classes. While the two men were taking inventory
of a storeroom, they saw the frames of an old Jacquard loom
rising out of the darkness.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
The Jacquard was perfected in the early days of the 19th
Century by a Frenchman from Lyons, Joseph Marie Jacquard,
and it was one of the precursors of modern "thinking ma¬
chines". This invention is a loom attachment which works
the warp threads automatically to form a design while the
weaver merely throws his shuttle. Its principle is somewhat
that of the player piano the design is punched out on a
paper sheet which is then fed into the Jacquard. Anything
can be woven with a Jacquard portraits, landscapes or even,
as in the case of a museum piece in Lyons,, the last will of
King Louis XVI.
This seemed to be a way out for the highland weavers, but
there was one big stumbling block. A Jacquard can cost
from $500 to $1,000 and no craftsman working his family
loom in an adobe house at San Pedro Sacatépequez could
envisage such a capital investment.
At this point, Mr. Hugoné decided to become a bricoleur
an untranslatable French word for a poet of the machine
age, a man who can take a few lengths of baling wire, an
odd board and an old stove lid and convert them into a new
heating system for his home or an automatic gearbox for his
car. He sat down with a Guatemalan carpenter and, between
the two of them, they built a "national Jacquard" out of
wood at a cost of $75. When new weaving classes were
started by Dr. Cofino at the orphanage, the home-made
Jacquard was ready for use. As for the carpenter, he began\
to make Jacquards on his own and found ready buyers A
among weavers in Guatemala City.
Then Mr. Hugoné left for the highlands 120 miles west of
the capital. There, he embarked on a double life. At
Quezaltenango, he and the director of the city's pre-vocation-
al and industrial school, concentrated on training weavers to
work power looms in the big textile mills on the outskirts of
the city. But, three days a week, Mr. Hugoné was in San
Pedro Sacatépequez, 30 miles to the west, over a road climb¬
ing through the clouds. There, he worked with Raymundo
Sanchez, director of a spinning and weaving school, and
taught future craftsmen to follow their ancestral trades.
Quezaltenango needed good factory hands; San Pedro want¬
ed craftsmen and there was a potential market for the pro¬
ducts of both.
Within two years, the number of pupils at the school in
San Pedro has risen from 28 to 72. Students first learn then-
trade at the age of twelve. They start with a simple pattern
of wavy lines but, by their second year, they are already
working on Mayan designs. This, of course, could be learned
in the home of any of the 2,000 weavers of San Pedro, but
the course does not end with the looms. The school teaches
weavers cost accounting to help them run their one-man
businesses. It also teaches them the technique of transfer¬
ring their Mayan designs onto the paper "brain" of the Jac¬
quard. This machine in their shops will not prevent them
from maintaining their independence.
The weavers of San Pedro have strong ideas about inde¬
pendence, Mr. Sanchez told me. Even though they earn only
an average of 90 centavos a day as compared to $1.25 in
textile mills they prefer to work for themselves. It is his
hope that the home-made Jacquards will raise production to
5 yards of cloth per day, and, at the same time, open new
markets for their work. The town, by word-of-mouth, has
learned of the school's methods and local weavers have re¬
quested a night school. The Jacquard may turn out to be
the last link in the chain of Mayan designs going back to the
ideographs, or word pictures.
In the textile section of Quezaltenango's pre-vocational
school, a model factory is being developed with the help of
donations from mill owners. The school's electric loom is a
gift from one mill and it now has ten foot looms for instruc¬
tion purposes. In addition, there is a compact laboratory
for conducting precision tests of materials.
The school intends to introduce the descendants of the
Mayan weavers into the modern production line.
"We now train our own workers," the director of one of
the biggest mills in the Quezaltenango region, told me. "They
learn quickly, but they come to us without any experience
with machinery. It is the same process as learning how to
repair watches by yourself first, you have to break a few.
That is exactly what happens with our looms. Ten years
ago our workers were incapable of understanding the instruc¬
tions they were given," he 'explained. But a few years ago
the mill opened its own school for adult workers. "Today,"
said the director, "80 per cent of our workers are literate and,
in fact, we will only hire literate people. This is more than
just a question of production in one textile mill. It is the
economic growth of the country which is at stake."
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
LOS
UNESCOS'
©
Father José Salcedo first broadcast to his
parish in 1948 with a home-made transmitter.
Today he is the director of one of the world's
biggest programmes of adult education by radio.
In 1947, a slender young Catholic priest arrived in a
forgotten hamlet perched high in the Andes of Colombia
to take up his duties as assistant pastor of the Parish of
Sutatenza. Father José Joaquin Salcedo brought to his first
ministry a restless, driving urge to improve the lot of
Colombia's campesinos who scrape their livelihood from
incredible farms hugging dizzy mountain slopes. He also
brought his amateur radio transmitter.
At that time the village consisted of eighty souls, but it
was the largest community in a parish of 9,000 whose geo¬
graphy is typical of the Colombian Andes. Sutatenza Parish
grows coffee in its warm valleys and raises sheep on its bald,
chilly peaks. Some plots are so steep, local legend goes, that
farmers seed them by shotgun.
The mountaineers were leading a grim life. They farmed
their plots as their ancestors had always farmed them,
harnessing themselves to their plough on slopes too steep to
be worked by animals and the land was washing away
under their feet. They lived within windowless walls in
what Father Salcedo later was to call "anti-hygienic fort¬
resses." Only one peasant in three could read or write.
Alcoholism was common. There was no diversion but drink,
and as often as not Saturday night in a taberna ended in a
brawl with the principals finishing in the Guateque hospital
down in the bottom of the valley.
Father Salcedo believed there was no point in preaching
sermons against the tabernas; instead, he decided to compete
with them. In August of 1947 on the village square of
Sutatenza, he introduced them to the motion-picture screen.
The people of Sutatenza thought they were in another world;
long after the show ended, they huddled enchanted around
the projector to stare respectfully.
Father Salcedo had gained a foothold. To consolidate it,
he drew up plans for a permanent theatre. The village of
Sutatenza offered its help, but it was not enough and there
was no way of making a general appeal to the parish for
volunteer masons and carpenters... not until Father Salcedo,
who had built his first radio at the age of 13, decided to try
his amateur transmitter.
Thus, in May of 1948, Radio Sutatenza made its first
broadcast, which was picked up by only three receivers. The
priest asked campesinos to help him build the Sutatenza
theatre and promised to record the voice of every man who
aided him. Soon he was broadcasting the campesinos' own
voices back to their amazed families and sixty men a day
were coming to Sutatenza to work on the theatre, bringing
materials with them and money when they could.
With the theatre finished, Father Salcedo sought the help
of the campesinos in developing what was to become the
4ÍX
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
Radio
radio school. One day, the radio announced that farmers
could make their contributions in chickens. Father Salceno
received more than 800 and had to hire a truck to haul them
to market in Bogota. Money was also forthcoming, and by
1949, he was able to buy a 250-watt transmitter. There were
enough radios for fifteen schools and the priest started
broadcasting an educational programme once a week.
Now, after seven years, Father Salcedo's home-made
transmitter has been transformed into Acción Cultural
Popular, one of the world's biggest programmes of adult
education by radio.
Acción Cultural Popular now broadcasts its lessons six
hours a day to 200,000 pupils scattered over twelve of
Colombia's sixteen departments and overflowing into
neighbouring Venezuela and Ecuador. The radio schools are
served by 6,000 specially built receivers and 10,000 more are
on the way. Within the near future attendance at these
remarkable schools is expected to rise to 1,000,000.
The programmes still go on the air from Sutatenza, but
they are now carried by a 25-kilowatt transmitter, the most
powerful in all Colombia. The Colombian Government is
backing Acción Cultural Popular to the amount of $800,000
a year and Unesco is now participating through the United
Nations technical assistance programme.
Besides the studios and the transmitter in the transformed
village of Sutatenza, Acción Cultural Popular now occupies
most of the seventh floor of the biggest office building in
Bogota. From an office with a panoramic view of the
mountains of Guadelupe and Monserrate, Father Salcedo
continues to direct its work.
" I asked Father Salcedo how he could explain the pheno¬
menal growth of Acción Cultural Popular in so short a time.
"Any work which meets a basic need of the people must grow
in direct proportion . to this need", he replied. "Here, it is
the need of 7,000,000 people in a country of 12,000,000 for lite¬
racy and general culture. It is not surprising that the
number of pupils in the radio schools has risen to 200,000."
From the outset, he has had the support of the hierarchy
of the Church and of public opinion. "Some men in educa¬
tion have had reserves about our methods", Father Salcedo
explained, "but they have now come over to our side because
we are introducing scientifically-tested materials in the radio
school. It is exactly for this reason that we requested
technical assistance from Unesco to make our teaching
methods more scientific."
The receiving sets used in the radio schoolrooms are
marvels of simplicity battery-powered shortwave receivers
manufactured for Acción Cultural Popular by Dutch and
American companies. They can be tuned to only one sta¬
tion, Radio Sutatenza, a precaution taken to preserve the life
of their batteries. Still on the theory that culture should
not be given away for nothing, Acción Cultural Popular sells
a set and its batteries to a radio school at cost price, the
equivalent of $18. Each school, however, receives a free
supply of chalk, an eraser, textbooks and an alarm clock
so that pupils will know when to turn on their set.
These little 4-tube sets put in a hard day's work in the
radio schools, most of them nothing more than rooms set
aside in adobe homes. The house of the most educated
campesino in a hamlet is always chosen for this honour, and
its owner is given the title of Auxiliar Inmediato. It is this
"immediate auxiliary" who takes attendance, turns on the
radio when school begins, and writes lessons on the black¬
board according to instructions given him by the unseen
radio teacher. He is one of the key men in Acción Cultural
Popular, this remote-controlled teacher. The auxiliaries are
always the farmers with the most modern ideas in their
communities, and the distinction of leading the radio schools
lends them even greater influence as forces for bettering the
villages.
Programmes begin at ten minutes to six in the morning,
the only time that most men can spare from their fields.
Depending on the day of the week, the morning programme
of one hour and twenty-five minutes consists
of classes in reading and writing, hygiene, (Continued
history, religious instruction or civics, always on next page)
RADIO SCHOOL files into its "classroom" adobe walled hut of a Colombian farmerfor an early morning
lesson. Colombia's remarkable educational programme, Acción Cultural Popular, goes on the air at 6 a.m.,
the only time that busy farmers can spare from their fields, but repeats its lessons later in the day. Heads
bent over their notebooks, old and young work conscientiously. School is a serious business. (Unesco photos.)
18 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Don Quixote of the Radio (Continued)
followed by a news broadcast. This programme is recorded
on tape and repeated at 3.50 p.m. for women and again at
5 p.m. for any men who might have missed the morning
class.
In the evening, Radio Sutatenza is on the air from 6.15 p.m.
to 9.p.m., but school is over. Then it offers music both
classical and popular news, variety shows, religious talks
and a half-hour's drama on the theme of history, science,
travel in Colombia or problems affecting farmers.
When I visited two members of Unesco's technical assis¬
tance mission in Colombia,
Brother Fulgencio and Bro¬
ther Idinael, both Brothers
of the Christian Schools, they
were working on posters to
be distributed to the several
thousand class-rooms which
now constitute the radio
school.
The studio itself suggests a
school, but one without
pupils. This is only normal,
for its classes are as far as
600 miles away. Even in the
adjoining parish of Tibirita,
the schools are not very
accessible except by jeep.
There is no easy guided tour
to a radio school.
At 4.30 on a drizzling
morning, Brother Idinael and
I were sharing a thermos of
coffee by candlelight in his
workroom. We had an hour's
jeep drive ahead of us to the
Gusvita Radio School, 13
miles away. We did not have
much time to linger over
breakfast, because school be¬
gan at ten minutes to six.
We arrived with a few
minutes to spare and left the
jeep on the road. I followed
Brother Idinael down a slip¬
pery path, scarcely wide
enough for two persons. We
saw an adobe farmhouse with
a radio antenna strung from
two rough-hewn poles next
to it and a basketball court
in an adjoining field (vir¬
tually every school has a
court; one has even asked
Radio Sutatenza how to go
about buying a generator so
that it can play night
games) . The sound of a bell
carried over our heads and
into the hills. As we drew
near, we could see a young
farmer earnestly striking a
one yard length of railway
rail hanging from a low
branch the school bell used in every one of Colombia's radio
schools and the most inexpensive one available.
Alfredo Segura was the auxiliar inmediato of the Gusvita
School. At 21, he is typical of the young generation of
Colombian farmers trained in the government's rural exten¬
sion courses. He was fiercely proud of the school; to make
room for the class, he and his family had all moved into the
other room of their house. The benches and the blackboard
were his own work. The young auxiliary was doing mis¬
sionary work himself to help his neighbours vaccinate their
cattle and spray their fields with fungicide.
We asked him if life had changed at all for nearby families
since the radio school opened in 1953. He smiled.
"Everyone likes it except the tabernas," he told us. "People
always used to live by themselves here, but now we get
together. We feel that we belong to a village. People go to
school now or play basketball. Before, everyone used to get
drunk, especially on Sundays."
SCHOOL BELL AT DAWN: "The sound of a bell carried over
our heads and into the hills. As we drew near, we could see a young
farmer earnestly striking a one-yard length of railway rail hanging
from a low branchthe school bell used in Colombia's radio schools."
By now, the class was beginning to arrive. There were no
tardy scholars. They filed into the house in silence, 22 in
all, and sat down at their benches; the children scattered
among the adults (children attend certain radio schools in
villages too far removed from any ordinary school).
Mr. Segura turned on the radio. After a short wait, it came
to life with a morning message from,Accion Cultural Popular.
Then the voice of a distant teacher filled the little room lit
by the half-light of the morning.
"Auxiliaries and pupils of the Radio Schools of Colombia,
please let us have your attention... We are now going to
open our reading class for ,
beginners... Auxiliary, clean
the blackboard and be ready
with your chalk and eraser...
Pupils, prepare your text¬
books, open your copybooks
at to-day's lesson... Auxiliary,
go over the lessons."
The voice stopped and, for
a moment, an interlude of
music came from the radio.
Then the voice returned to
the room:
"Pupils... open your copy¬
books... hold your pencils at
the correct angle... Now
write what I dictate to you...
Auxiliary, write the same on
the blackboard... Write... in
small letters... ca... Now
write... co... faster, a little
faster... now all write the
last one... cu..."
The music returned and
the voice told the auxiliary
to correct the work of the
pupils'. The lesson went on
for fifteen minutes. Then,
advanced pupils were asked
to open their books. The .
class speeded up, there were
fewer interludes, and it
concluded with a short his¬
tory lesson. This was follow¬
ed by a talk on agriculture
and then the morning classes
ended with the news.
The sight of this class
obeying an unseen teacher
was uncanny. Every time
the music began, every head
bent down over every desk.
Pupils worked conscien¬
tiously without a whisper or
a nudge. School was serious
business for these people.
Campesinos are now fami¬
liar with their radios, but
they do not take the radio
school for granted. I had
heard from Father Salcedo
about an early campaign to
better, housing conditions. While on the road to Tibirita
with Brother Idinael, I saw houses with whitewashed walls
and tiled roofs dotting the valley, and many of them had
windows.
The introduction of contour ploughing in the Andes has
been the goal of another radio campaign and the deadly
vertical furrows in the mountains, nothing more than
spillways for rain, are slowly beginning to disappear. At the
Rosales school near Sutatenza, Brother Idinael asked the
auxiliary if he had noticed any improvement since he began
his contour ploughing. He told us that he had only
begun this year, but he could already see a difference.. "Now,
when it rains, the land stays in one place."
It would take weeks to obtain a complete picture of the
results of the radio schools in Sutatenza Parish alone. The
isolation of the mountaineers madevit possible for Acción
Cultural Popular to win them over, but it also renders ridi¬
culous any attempt to keep track of the work through an
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nf 2. 1955
ordinary system of school inspection. In the Andes of
Colombia, Radio Sutatenza may be all that a campesino ever
hears of the rest of the world.'
But the campesinos learn to write and they write letters, to
Acción Cultural Popular. The letters pour in at the rate
of 150 a day and they are a useful key to the popularity of
various programmes. They also show how deeply the radio
school has penetrated the inaccessible world of the cam¬
pesino.
They write about everything. Some thank the school for
taking them out of their solitude or for weaning husbands
away from tabernas. And some ask practical, down-to-
earth questions: what's good for a bad grippe, how do you
cure a lame horse, how should a common-law couple go about
marrying, what can be done about a disobedient daughter,
how can children be educated if there is no school available,
how does a wife get money out of a stingy husband. Every
letter receives a reply, although Acción Cultural Popular does
not pretend to have a solution to every question.
Nor does anyone maintain that a radio set in an adobe
hut is a panacea for the campesinos' intellectual and moral
ills. After a few days in Sutatenza,"you are bound to hear
the story of how one of the parish's most conscientious
auxiliares inmediatos lost his temper one night on the
mountain and mauled a neighbour so badly that his victim
had to be hospitalized. The auxiliary was sentenced to serve
two years... and there is now a radio school at nearby
Guateque Prison.
There are only 90-odd miles separating the Tenza Valley
from what was once the almost-deserted village of Belencito
in the north of Boyaca. In those 90 miles, you pass from
an ox-cart agricultural economy to the newest steel mill in
Latin America. At Belencito, in the surrealistic shadows of
coke ovens, conveyor belts and a 270-foot high blast furnace,
Acción Cultural Popular is beginning another experiment in
radio education.
In 1945, Belencito was a wide place on a country road,
nothing more than a church and a few huts. That year,
geologists were prospecting 22 miles north of Belencito at
Paz de Rio in a narrow canyon of the Chicamocha River.
They discovered that the canyon was hemmed in on one side
by a wall of coal and on the other by a wall of iron ore. As
for the hills overlooking Belencito itself, they were brimm¬
ing with limestone. In other words, bringing together
the raw materials needed to charge a blast furnace and
produce iron required the sum total of 22 miles of trans¬
port. With this unique endowment,
Colombia is now becoming the fourth (Continued
Latin American country (the others are on next PaSe)
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Don QuiXOte (Continued)
Standing
Room Only in
the village
theatre
ROCKET fired by Father Salcedo signals
the start of a play at his Cultural Theatre.
VILLAGERS of Sutatenza queue up to
see plays which educate and entertain
Brazil, Chile and Mexico) to join the ranks of the world's
producers of steel. The Empresa Siderúrgica de Paz de Rio,
scheduled to be in production by the end of 1954 will have
3,000 workers in the Belencito steel mill and 2,000 more in the
mines of Paz de Rio. The sun-baked hamlet of Belencito
still stands, but it is a museum piece inside the 4,000-acre
enclosure occupied by the plant.
The conversion of Colombian raw materials into iron and
steel is only half of the story of Belencito. Equally dramatic
has been the conversion of campesinos into steel workers.
When the mill goes into production, its labour force will be
almost entirely Colombian and recruited from the sleepy
farm villages surrounding it. Financed partially by the
Colombian Government, the plant has trained its own
workers. But its personnel problems will not end when
shifts go home for the day. Near Belencito, a worker's city
is going up for married men and their families. If the men
are to make the transition from the hoe to the rolling
mill, their wives must adapt themselves to an entirely new
sort of life that of an ordinary modern community.
To pave the way for this adaptation, the company has
enlisted the aid of Acción Cultural Popular which has
assigned to Belencito its former programme director, Father
Alejandro Rodriguez, the first collaborator of Father Salcedo
in the radio schools of Sutatenza. Father Rodriguez is a
year younger than the Director of Acción Cultural Popular,
an institution where youth decidedly has its say. At 32, he
presents the same fusion of philosopher, technician and
priest as his director and closest friend, although he bears
no physical resemblance whatsoever to him. Father Rodri¬
guez is tall and husky, and his deeply sun-burned face
contrasts with the near-ascetic pallor of Father Salcedo.
Both men, however, share a fascination for fast driving over
mountain roads a national pastime in Colombia. If it were
not for Father Rodriguez, Father Salcedo would be the
undisputed holder of the Sutatenza-Bogota record.
Father Rodriguez first went on the air in 1949 when Father
Salcedo was called away on a trip to the United States and,
VOLUNTARY HELP built the theatre in 1948 following an appeal broadcast by Father Salcedo. The priest
promised to record the voice of every man who aided him. Soon he was broadcasting the farmers' own voices
back to their families and 60 men a day were coming to work. There is always a "full house". (U.N. photos.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
i
LIMITED SEATING for only 500 people does not prevent as many as 700 from crowding theatre for film
shows or plays. Even after all seats are taken, latecomers still pack the entrance for a glimpse. (U.N. photos.)
even though he had had no radio experience, he took over
Radio Sutatenza successfully for a month. Then, in 1951, he
received a Unesco international fellowship to enable him to
study the use of the radio in adult education in Canada
where he worked under Dr. J.R. Kidd, Director of Adult
Education at Toronto. Dr. Kidd gave the priest a thorough
view of what Canada had been able to accomplish. For two
months, Father Rodriguez worked at Antigonish, Nova
Scotia, observing radio techniques in public service in a hard,
bleak country living on poor soil. Then, after visiting Laval
University in Quebec where he studied the organization of
credit co-operatives for farmers, Father Rodriguez spent
three months in Toronto watching the Farm Radio Forum
of the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation in operation.
"Canada taught me a great deal about the orientation of
our radio schools in Colombia," Father Rodriguez told me.
"We want to be able to broadcast a Farm Radio Foprn
ourselves, but you have to assume a certain degree of edu¬
cation among your listeners before you can put on such a
programme. We have a long job of fundamental education
ahead of us; in the end, we hope to reach the point where
the Canadians are now. More than anything else, Canada
convinced me that we were on the right track."
Following his stay in Canada, Father Rodriguez travelled
to Spain, France and England, concentrating on the organi¬
zation of broadcasting and on its technical side. Then he
went back to his microphone in Sutatenza until early in 1954
when he left to direct Radio Belencito. , Father Rodriguez is
starting on a modest scale in the new mill town with a
1-kilowatt long-wave transmitter and 200 receivers. The
purpose of long-wave transmission is to enable owners of
private radios to hear school programmes. Radio Belencito
will fit into a new network of long-wave transmitters being
established by Acción Cultural Popular at seven widely
scattered points in Colombia.
Although Radio Belencito will retransmit certain basic
programmes of Radio Sutatenza, its objectives are not quite
the same. In Belencito, Father Rodriguez intends to use the
radio to help mould a colony of campesircos-turned-steel
workers into a living community. Besides its classes, Radio
Belencito will broadcast programmes for neighbourhood cen¬
tres in the steel town. The radio will serve the community
as theatre, orchestra and forum and, to supplement it, spare-
time teachers will be trained as neighbourhood leaders the
urban version of the auxiliar inmediato.
Radio Belencito also will produce a regular series of pro¬
grammes to tell the story of iron and steel. The purpose of
these shows is to give workers a clear idea of how their jobs
fit into the complex pattern of steel production.
"Fifty per cent of our workers are illiterate," an official of
the Belencito plant told me. "They learn quickly and their
mechanical aptitude is high, but we want them to understand
what they are doing and why they are doing it. This is
extremely important to them and to us. The Colombian
economy needs this steel mill and we want our workers to be
integrated into this new aspect of our economy."
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
'Los Úneseos'
0
PENSIVE FARMER
reflects on changes for
the better that have come
to his valley. Here, with
other Costa Rican farm¬
ers, he listens to speaker
at a community develop¬
ment meeting which de¬
cided to provide funds
and manpower for public
works. (Unesco photo.)
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
BOOM TOWN
on the
Pan-American
Highway
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
PEASANT ARTISTS of Costa
Rica decorate their oxcarts with
intricate traditional designs
painted in vivid colours. Pat¬
terns on wheels, like one shown
here, form a brilliant kaleidos¬
cope as the carts move along.
(Photo Dr. Esteban de Varona).
ON a road map of Central America,
the Pan-American Highway
stands out as the main artery
flowing through nearly the entire
length of the Republic of Costa Rica,
whose total area is only 20,000 square
miles.
The highway enters Costa Rica
from the north at the Nicaraguan
border, crosses the tropical northern
provinces, climbs up to the rich table¬
land surrounding San José, the capital,
and then winds through alpine scenery
until it reaches San Isidro del General,
its present southern terminal.
Before this last section of the road
was opened in 1948, it took three days
on horse-back, over the steep paths of
the Cordillera de Talamanca, to cover
the 85 miles separating San José
from San Isidro and the green Valle
El General. The people of the valley
lived isolated from their fellow-
countrymen, and in many regards
they " were abandoned. But the
highway has changed all that. Back
in 1948, San Isidro, "capital" of the
region, consisted merely of a few
farms and a- big weather-beaten
church with a strange Moorish
steeple painted bright-red. Today, it
is a prosperous little town with 5,000
inhabitants.
At all hours of the day, horsemen,
ox-carts, tractors, jeeps, trucks and
cars jam its unpaved streets. Frame
houses have sprouted up like the
coffee, maize and sugar-cane in the
rich soil of the valley.. There is a big
market under construction, a hand¬
some " new primary school for 700
children, an abundance of shops and
cafés, and even an agency hiring out
auxiliary-engined bicycles which lends
a strange European air to this boom
town in the heart of Central America.
Outside the town is one of the
busiest airports in Costa Rica. Single-
engined planes fly 30 scheduled
flights a day in and out of San Isidro,
mainly hauling crops, livestock and
passengers from outlying valley villa¬
ges to the terminal, of the highway.
In San Isidro, it is possible to sit down
to lunch and eat á plate of beans
grown by a farmer who still uses an
ox-drawn plough and transported by
air to a few hundred yards from your
restaurant table.
This is the key to the dilemma of
the Valle El General : it has developed
so fast that all phases of its develop¬
ment have not been able to maintain
the same furious pace. The soil of the
valley is rich, but there are not enough
roads over which to haul the produce
to market. Bridges are scarce and
those that do exist cannot take heavy
loads. Farmers are relatively well off
the per capita income of Costa Rica
is one of the highest in Central
America their crops have " grown
faster than new schools for their
children, pure water supplies for their
homes, electricity for their villages and
health services" for their families.
It was this contrasting picture of
prosperity and primitive conditions
which led the Government of Costa-
Rica, early in 1952, to select the Valle
El General as one of the two zones
for a pilot project in rural education
(the other being La Lucha, 30 miles
south east of San José). "Pilot pro¬
ject", in this case, meant an imagina¬
tive experiment in social education,
encompassing all the educational, eco-
'*nomic, sociological and health factors
that were hindering the progress of the
zones. To organize the experiment,
the Costa Rican authorities were
assisted by two members of an educa¬
tional mission sent into the country
in 1951 by Unesco under the United
Nations technical assistance pro¬
gramme : Adrian Cruz Gonzales," a
United States citizen from Puerto Rico,
and Max Minano Garcia, of Peru.
Their official titles were "specialist
in primary education" and "expert in
rural education". But the farmers of
the Valle El General simply refer to
them as "los Úneseos" and Mr. Cruz
enjoys telling the story of the day
when a farmer hailed him from a
nearby field. The man did not know
his name. He simply called out :
"Unesco!".
Working in the two zones, Mr. Cruz
and Mr. Minano have refused to make
any pedagogical or administrative
distinction between "primary educa¬
tion" and "community development".
They maintain, after nearly three
years of practice, that it is almost im¬
possible to separate the two; that rural
living standards cannot be raised
without improving village schools and,
conversely, that schools cannot be
improved without enlisting the whole¬
hearted help of the communities.
The results of this fundamental
education work are as varied as they
are unusual : a new steel bridge over
the Rio El General, schools, libraries,
sports grounds, agricultural centres,
water supply systems, roads, radio
installations for educational broadcasts,
health and hygiene campaigns... It is a
complex project, co-ordinated by a
network of thirteen pilot villages.
As far as teaching is concerned,
there are eleven adult education
centres among the thirteen pilot
villages, with a total of 300 pupils.
Their course leads to a primary school
diploma which has a good deal of im¬
portance in the valley. In one San
Isidro hotel, the owner has proudly
framed his own in the dining room.
i
Besides teaching reading and writ¬
ing, the centres
make life more (Continued
enjoyable in the on next page)
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Boom Town
(Continued.)
valley, mainly through encouraging
football, volleyball and basketball
teams. In El General Viejo, the foot¬
ball fever has caught on to such an
extent that the village team takes the
field with its members wearing, across
their chest, the emblem "Club Unesco."
Villages have participated in cam¬
paigns to improve their schools, rais¬
ing money through lotteries and
bazaars. At Los Chiles, the school¬
master, 34-year-old Cerlindo Alvarado,
went even further. In April 1954, he
organized not only a bazaar but also a
bull-fighta dangerous sport in Costa
Rica... for the bullfighter! There is no
kill in a Costa Rican corrida. Instead
the toreros swarm into the ring and
try to ride the bull's back, to pull his
tail or to make dangerous passes with
their capes. At this particular fight,
Mr. Alvarado, village schoolmaster and
father of six children, acted as torero...
and he raised a total of 900 colons
(approximately 140 dollars) through
his efforts.
But there are many other things
to do besides fighting bulls. At Los
Chiles, Mr. Alvarado's day usually lasts
from seven in the morning until ten at
night, teaching children and adults.
In his spare time, he farms the school
lands and wields a hammer and saw as
he helps to build additional rooms for
his school-house, using lumber bought
with the proceeds of his bull-fighting.
Hand in hand with community de¬
velopment over the past two years has
come a reorganization of primary
education. Preliminary investigations
had disclosed that the weakest point
in the Costa Rican school system was
a shortage of trained teachers. But
materials were deficient as well. The
MIXED TRAFFIC uses main street of San Isidero del General, in Southern
Costa Rica. Recently constructed Pan-American highway has brought a boom
and prosperity to this little townand also problems. Community facilities
water supplies, roads and marketsare still lacking. (Unesco photo).
AMATEUR BULLFIGHTER is Cer¬
lindo Alvarado, a teacher who took to
the ring to raise money to build an
additional wing for his school. Here
he is putting in some practice on
a not-so-fierce steer. (Unesco photo).
average pupil, during his six years in
primary school, reads only seven or
eight books, learning most lessons by
heart.
In 1952, Mr. Cruz began to work
with his Costa Rican assistant Mr. Boli¬
var Moya on a plan to strengthen
these weak points. They started with
60 teachers and 1,800 children in the
two zones of the Valle El General and
La Lucha. The following year they
expanded their campaign to include 83
teachers and 2,200 children. Then, in
1954, a wave of enthusiasm swept the
district and their work was extended
to the entire province of Cartago, co¬
vering a total of 700 primary school
teachers and 20,000 pupils.
The foundation of their plan lay in
on-the-job training for teachers al¬
ready in service. In practice, this had
to be translated into an incessant
round of seminars, visits, meetings and
"teaching-by-correspondence".
Gradually the plan took shape.
A new curriculum was drawn up and«
submitted to teachers and school
inspectors for criticism. It took a
practical approach, adapting the teach¬
ing methods of the school to the re¬
alities of Costa Rican life. One example
under the old curriculum, pupils
learned how to do sums in dollars and
pounds before they were introduced to
the Costa Rican colon; in the new
system, they begin with weights and
measures used in Costa Rica.
At the same time schools have
expanded their facilities : playgrounds
have been built, books have been
bought for their libraries as well as
radio receiver sets for listening in to
educational programmes. The Mini¬
ster of Education made a special
visit to San Isidro. He was so im¬
pressed by the results achieved that it
was immediately decided to launch
two new fundamental education pro¬
jects in 1955, one in Turrialba and the
other in San Carlos.
The people of the Valle El General
are proud of their achievements.
These are mainly due to their own
drive and enthusiasm. Unesco's tech¬
nical assistance experts have merely
helped to release and to guide this
latent force for community develop¬
ment. Yet the- people of the valley
still pin the label "Unesco" on their
schools, their markets, their new
bridges and their football teams. The
internationalism of this little corner of
Costa Rica is amazing. In San Isidro's
new primary school, built by the Gov¬
ernment, each classroom bears the
name of a Latin American republic
and the assembly hall is called "Uni¬
ted Nations Room."
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2.
Fabulous record
of ancient Peru ON LOOKING
INTO A MOCHICAN URN
by
Jorge Carrera Andrade
All tfie photos of ancient Peru¬
vian Art on the following pages
and on page 36 are published by
of Nathan Cummings.
T
he little Peruvian
port of Trujillo lies
perched on a shal¬
low cliff beside the
valley where the Moche
river cuts its way
through to the sea. Be¬
hind the town the baked
brown landscape is dot¬
ted with yuca, bean and
pumpkin plantations. Away
in the far distance, cooler to
the eye, the Andean peaks
loom in the sky, their snow-
covered summits glittering.
Here, in the Central Andean
river valleys of the Moche,
the Chicama, the Viru and
the Santa, for a period of
more than five hundred years
at the dawn of the Christian
era the Mochican civilization
grew, flourished and was
finally almost obliterated.
Little remains today except
the stories and history por¬
trayed by the Mochican cera¬
mists on the jugs and vases
which they have left behind.
Ceramics was the dominant
craft of the Mochicas, and in
this they made a greater
advance than was to be
found anywhere else in South
America during that epoch.
The achievements of this
civilization are those of a
people having ample leisure
to develop highly specialized
skills, and at the same time
enjoying security from both
strife and external
aggression. Food was abund¬
ant and the valleys were rich
in raw materials such as fine
quality clays and easily work¬
ed copper, gold and silver
ores. But little is known of
the political, social and reli¬
gious institutions which gave
Mochican society its stability.
Fortunately their realistic ce¬
ramic art, supported by other
archaeological evidence, off¬
ers the most complete pictor¬
ial document left to us by
any prehistoric
American civi- (Continued
lization. on next
The degree of
artistic perfection
page)
WINGED WARRIOR on stirrup-spout vessel. Figure is painted in red on a
cream-yellow backgroundtwo colours most commonly used by the Mochican potters.
siVeS*:*1**"-^'"' I
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
ON LOOKING INTO
A MOCHICAN URN
(continued)
achieved by these master potters
and the practical character of the
Mochican pitchers, jugs, carafes
and vases are astonishing. The
craftsmen modelled everything
which captured their imagination
men and animals, birds, fruits,
vegetables and the humblest
objects of everyday life.
The genius which lay in the
hands of the Mochican ceramists
created a fascinating panorama of
art in which there are many scenes
representing the life led by this
ancient people. Describing some of
these varied works, Alan R. Sawyer, of the Art Institute of
Chicago, has written : "We meet dignified leaders, stalwart
soldiers and humble craftsmen, blind men, cripples and men
ravaged by disease. We can watch heavily-laden llamas and
see balsa rafts propelled across rippling waters. A frog stares
out of heavy-lidded eyes. An owl sits holding a wriggling
field mouse in his beak, a king-fisher alights holding a
freshly-caught fish, and a small sparrow searches for his
food among the corn stalks. We can see a doctor tending
his patient and a mother caring for her child."
Unquestionably the result is a fascinating record of the
craftsman's real and imagined world,' and also of the whole
civilization which flourished at that time.
The Mochicas devoted themselves to agriculture, the build¬
ing of aqueducts and the plastic arts. But prior to their
advent, more than two thousand
years ago, an even older civilization,
the Cupisnique, flourished in the
same river valleys. It produced
earthern vessels with horizontal,
stirrup-shaped handles mounted
over the neck. This Cupisnique
pottery was made from rough clay
with orange colouring and adorned
with religious symbols such as the
cat: the supreme deity. Then came
the Salinar civilization which in¬
troduced ceramic painting. Blood-
red and cioud-white colouring
together with animal motifs lent
an element of drama and realism to these primitive
ceramics. The Salinar school represented a technical
advance in the working of clay and baking in open kilns.
Evidence of this can be seen today in the Archaeological
Museum at Chiclin where the results of the excavations
made in 1941 by Larco Hoyle in the Upper Chicama valley
are on view.
The early Mochican ceramics show naturally enough a
strong Salinar influence but up to the year 600 A.D. the
Mochican craftsmen developed and improved their work.
Their imaginative paintings went beyond material things and
illustrated their ideas of a spiritual world and an after life.
This creative thought was radically transformed about the
year 600 when the whole existence of the Mochicas was at
first threatened and eventually engulfed by the Tiahuanaco
people who swarmed out of the southern highlands where
the borders of Peru and Chile now meet.
The arts, agriculture and the pursuits of peace fell into
decay and gave place to military pursuits. The ceramic
motifs lost their naturalness and became even more abstract
in character. The objects protrayed were stylized in cold
intellectual attitudes. The Tiahuanacos, who finally overran
the whole of .the Moche country,
brought with them a massive, geo¬
metrical type of pottery which today
would be called cubist.
The standards set by the Mochi¬
cas did not disappear. After three
centuries they flowered once again
in the ceramics of the Gran Chimu.
The Chimu civilization with its
twenty river valley
settlements, its tremen- (Cont'd on
dous brick wall and page 30).
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
^y 41
BP*BB BbJ aVJ
i. y* yj
J||mJp <
!rtà.
IK. f
»S jÉj
iSSfejP^ i "^pt.: \ ' '^BPW^ jNb\ J
~^5bbJ 1
1 r m
F ¿sTfll
&AJsBBbI Sb&, :
I
' 1k J BB
B* .-<****' J
^B
Bjfc. -' ' a** ^äl
'BP vSí B
jí^ B
BB&:
Bkk. v -v>.
^VbP^p
3JB
. :Al¿i Y"
SL ' .. mfl
à& YA" A ' " '- .A ' .Y:
Er^/J ÊKÊ'm-
r w ' /jBJt r-\ \ ^bb
Bl
PI
mf
CHARACTER 1
CLAY: With skill
fingers Mochican cet
mists captured the d
ferent physical typ
and characters of the
fellows, from t
kneeling warrior (tc
right) holding his w
N
ed
if-
es
sir
he
P.
ar
id
; I /
S*': club, and the negro
p-^bV V: 4 - » figure (top, Jeft) to
the tatooed beggar
(bottom, left) being
attacked by a puma.
^rBjBpm
^Bf *^ SP
' ' - am |
'
^¿y *" ' *B^B BFfl
F -~jfl i^^H b\^
,« 4 H
.. 1
a :'
1
wBfe.- .^Banlr ^BÊa-M
^IflBBBk M-i ^k iflfl|
^
a#
Af ^
çfif 1
'\¿rJp ni
BOTTLE shaped in form of a
humorously rotund man. Exam¬
ple of domestic pottery styles.
^^*'¡,
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
¡ÄXJ!»'
PORTRAIT VESSELS with handle
spouts often depicted the features
of a dead personthe Mochican
equivalent of a "death mask"and
were placed in tombs for use during
the "journey to the next world."
CHALICE shaped like a fox's head
is combined with a rattle in handle.
ON LOOKING INTO
A MOCHICAN URN
(continued^
strong-points designed for defending the forty mile-long
southern frontier and its awe-inspiring capital of Chan
Chan, succumbed in its turn to the military power of the
Incas in the second half of the fifteenth century.
The multiform pitchers and other vessels characteristic of
the Chimu period, and the coloured ceramic work of the
Tiahuanaco era were replaced by the larger jars and vases of
the Incas. For a hundred and fifty years the Incas extended
and consolidated their empire. Under their benevolent
despotism local cultures continued to flourish and high
technical artistic standards were maintained. In 1532 the
impact of western civilization brought native Andean culture
to an abrupt end.
Throughout this disturbed period of history art reached its
highest expression in the work of the Mochican potters.
Their work challenges comparison in quality of line drawing
with the pottery of classical Greece, and in ceramic sculpture
with the tomb figures of ancient China. The large number
of Mochican pieces which have come down to us suggests
that their pottery was an art' prac¬
tised by almost an entire people.
The Mochican funeral ceramics
portrayed every scene and episode
of human existence in order that
the dead man should remember, in
after life, his own activities on
earth. Tombs have yielded hundreds
of vessels of every form, adorned
with human figures performing the
most menial duties of everyday life,
each in its way a record of history.
30
It is in this manner that the story
of Mochican civilization has been
brought to life.
Each vessel in this chronicle . of
clay represents a scene which en¬
ables us to follow the life of a
Mochica from birth to death. One
vase-may portray a house, another
a family, while a third may show
people eating, sleeping, making love
attending a funeral.
Life then was one of abundance.
The humbler people are shown as
fishermen or farmers while the
warrior-nobles are depicted pur¬
suing the deer and the most extra¬
ordinary birds whose savoury
flesh later bedecked the banqueting tables. The
paintings of religious scenes are characterized by a wealth
of ornaments, bells, rattles and trumpets, together
with a variety of costumes, coats of mail and plumed helmets.
Crowds climb the winding path to the temple on the hill
and there prostrate themselves before Ai-Apec, the god in
jaguar form, lord of the animal kingdom and the defender of
the people.
No facts or details have been forgotten by the craftsman,
and his work is executed with the scrupulousness of the true
historian. The customs, beliefs and social structure of the
Mochican people are displayed here for all to see. Their pre¬
dilection for ancestor worship and their belief that death
was a voyage to another unknown world, are clearly shown.
Legends, such as The Flood, are seen to have been in common
circulation.
The Mochicans traded with neighbouring* countries and
sailed the seas in rafts made from balsa wood. They had a
postal system where the couriers carried sacks of painted
beans on which were inscribed messages. Medical treatment
was given and surgical operations performed. Lawbreakers
were severely dealt with, being stoned, or killed by being
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
ANIMISTIC ART of the
Mochicans revealed their
skill in capturing the forms
and expressions of birds and
animals of the Andean region.
Two vessels shown here,
Toucan (below) and a deer
head with human body (right)
are from Chimbóte Valley.
CHALICE for religious ce¬
remonies shaped like a man
wearing a long garment: rare
item of Mochican pottery.
thrown from a rock. Apart from their pottery the Mochicans
worked in wood, copper, bone and other materials. As can be
seen in their ruins the temples were adorned with multi¬
coloured murals. They were also skilled weavers.
Certain rounded vessels found in Mochican tombs show
signs that some "revolving" movement was used in their
production and this supports the belief that the lathe, and
possibly the wheel might have been used by this people to
round off blocks of clay. In any case there is no mystery about
the methods of modelling used by the Mochican potters.
Having extracted the finest quality clay from the river banks
the craftsman would shape and model his figure, drawing on
his imagination or from life. The model would then be baked
and covered with a fresh coating of clay so as to form a
mould divided into two parts from which the vessels in
their final form would be shaped. Afterwards the potter
added the base, the handle and the neck. Then, with a bone
spatula a heritage from- the Cupisnique civilization he
would smooth the surface and paint it red.
Subsequently the model was exposed to the air, and then
fired in an open kiln to ensure the maximum degree of oxi¬
disation. It was this treatment which gave the characteristic
yellowish hue to all Mochican pottery. Finally, the article
was re-polished to give it added lustre and was then ready
for use.
Often the vessels found in tombs portrayed the dead man
in lifelike relief, revealing profound
anatomical knowledge" and psycho¬
logical penetration on the part of
the craftsman. The myriad forms
used in the Mochican ceramics show
that their pottery was an imagina¬
tive art. The potters were not only
marvellous portrayers of animals
witness their life-like frogs, their
comic birds, their powerful stags'
heads or their formidable - sea
monsters but they were also think¬
ers and poets.
The symbol of wings was used
to give the idea of speed ; the '
demon of drink would be used to
Af^^rA portray rapture ; erotic scenes
would convey the ideas of fertility
^m and death. Messengers and cour-"
iers were shown as humming
birds in flight ; an old woman
became a hallucinating owl, and a
motionless owl an idiot. Phantom-
pfl like fauna weaved in the depths
of the sea. Woman, as a mother,
was shown standing between a
newly-born infant and a skeleton. From the mountain to the
snail, from the whale to the mollusc the entire Mochica world
has been brought to life through its ceramic art.
The art of the Mochicas can still be seen today in the Na¬
than Cummings Collection of Ancient Peruvian Art, part of
which has recently been on exhibition at the Art Institute
of Chicago. Some 200 selected items were exhibited the first
public showing of the collection anywhere in the world. This
collection, comprising some 1,500 objects, including pottery
and articles in gold, silver, bronze, stone, wood, bone and
other materials, is one of the most important groupings of
ancient Peruvian art outside Peru. Its exceptionally large
and representative group of Mochican ceramics is outstand¬
ing, and presents a vivid record of the evolution of this re¬
markable civilization.
Unfortunately, the peoples of ancient Peru did not possess
a system of writing or a calendar with which to record their
history. The Spanish chroniclers showed only a limited
interest in preserving the oral traditions which had survived.
Consequently the story of the Mochicas and other early An¬
dean cultures were all but lost in the looting of graves which
took place after the fall of the Incas. Modern archaeologists
are still today confronted with many unsolved problems.
Laborious work has yielded some of the story of the Mochicas
but there is still much more hidden which remains to be
uncovered in the future.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 2. 1955
From the Unesco Newsroom
M,R. TOR GJESDAL who
has been principal director of
the United Nations Department -
of Public Information in New
York since 1946 has now taken
up a new post as director of
unesco's Department of Mass
Ccmmunication. Mr. Gjesdal
was born at Dyvaag, Norway, in
1909. He studied law at the
University of Oslo, and journa¬
lism in different European
countries. He was a foreign cor¬
respondent and a war correspon¬
dent in Western and Eastern
Europe, North Africa, the Mid¬
dle and Far East and Indone¬
sia for Norwegian newspapers
from 1929 to 1940; press officer
of the Norwegian Army High
Command in 1940; press attaché
of the Norwegian Legation in
Washington, from 1940 to 1941;
director-general of the Norwe¬
gian Government Information
Services in London and Oslo
from 1941 to 1945; diplomatic
correspondent in London from
1945 to 1946; and principal di¬
rector of the United Nations De¬
partment of Public Information
in New York since 1946.
* TRANS-ATLANTIC
TEACHERS: A new kind of
teaching job was created re¬
cently that of educational
director on trans-atlantic
ships sailing between New
York and European ports.
Appointed by the U.S. Coun¬
cil on Student Travel, these
directors will work with stu¬
dents travelling on vacation
time tours and will help ¿o
introduce "first-time" travel¬
lers to Europe to the cultural,
social and political back¬
ground of countries they will
visit.
Mr ROTECTING MAN'S
HERITAGE : Fifty nations have
now signed the Hague Conven¬
tion for the Protection of Cul¬
tural Property in the Event of
Armed Conflict. Prepared by
Unesco and adopted at an in¬
ternational conference in May
1954, the Convention sets up
what amounts to a "cultural
Red Cross" under which works
of art, monuments and historic
buildings would receive similar
protection as is now given to
hospitals, ambulances and me¬
dical personnel in time of war.
(See Unesco Courier, n* 7, 1954).
FROM SCHOOLS TO
SCHOOLS : Dutch school¬
children collected a total of
10,400 florins (about $ 2,900)
to provide gifts for schools in
India, the Gold Coast and
Libya, in recent months.
They obtained the money by
selling Unesco Gift Coupons
a form of international
money order which can be
sent as a gift to educational
and cultural institutions in
other countries.
\\jORLD ANTI - POLIO
NETWORK: A round-the-glo-
be network of research labora¬
tories to study various polio
strains is being set up by the
World Health Organization of
the United Nations. Scientists
will seek to develop control mea¬
sures applicable to different
parts of the world. A report on
the latest facts known about
the disease and statistics on its
frequency are being published by
WHO.
CRIPPLED CHILDREN:
Over the past 18 months,
visitors to United Nations
headquarters in New York
_ have contributed $ 31,600 to
help Korean children by
buying gift stamps issued by
Unesco at a sales coun¬
ter in the lobby of the Gen¬
eral Assembly building.
The money is being used to
equip a special ward at a
new centre for handicapped
chûdren being built by the
American Korean Foundation
and the UN Korean Recon¬
struction Agency. The ward
is expected to be ready for
use in late summer.
IL1 S.S.R. LANGUAGES :
Sixty vernacular languages are
used in teaching in the U.S.S.R.
In the Russian Soviet Federated
Socialist Republic alone, forty-
four languages are used in the
schools. The Russian language
is taught in all schools in the
Republics of the Soviet Union
not later than the third year of
compulsory education.
TOO FEW SCHOOLS :
More than half of the world's
children do not attend school.
In a single region South
Asia and the Pacific
55,000,000 boys and girls of
school age out of a total of
95,000,000 are deprived of
any chance of schooling.
Educational leaders from 15
countries in this area met to
discuss this challenging prob¬
lem at a UNESCO-sponsored
conference in Bombay. The
educational situation reveal¬
ed by the conference and the
proposals put forward for
meeting it are outlined in a
new Unesco publication,
"Compulsary Education in
South Asia and the Pacific"
Obtainable from National
Distributors of unesco publi¬
cations price: % 1; 6/-; 300
Fr. fr.
ÄaY 9 9 9' : The nine
hundred and ninety-nine cate¬
gories of diseases and causes of
death officially listed by medical
statistics have just been review¬
ed and brought up to date.
The aim was to improve the
accuracy of health statistics and
to show more precisely which
ailments are most costly to the
community. This revisionthe
seventh of the original list was
- made by an international confer¬
ence convened by the World
Health Organization at Unesco
House, Paris.
WINGS OVER THE
WORLD: A new postage
stamp featuring a pair of -
wings soaring over the world
has now been put on sale by
the U.N. Postal Administra¬
tion. It pays tribute to the
International Civil Aviation
Organization (I.C.A.O.), a
U.N. Specialised Agency that
helps to set world-wide stan¬
dards for aviation, reduces
red tape for international air
services and offers technical
aid to help governments to
build up their aviation ser¬
vices.
!_ ERN CHANGES: Pro¬
fessor F. Bloch, Director-Gene¬
ral of the European Organization
for Nuclear Research (C E.R.N.)
has resigned and will be replac¬
ed later this year by Dr. J.C.
Bakker of the University of
Amsterdam. C.E.R.N., which
was set up through Unesco's
initiative, is building an inter¬
national centre for nuclear
research at Geneva to house the
world's most powerful ins¬
truments to explore matter and
energy. Twelve nations now
participate in C.ERN. (See
Unesco Courier, N° 12, 1954).
WORLD CRIME PROB¬
LEM : An international
congress on Crime Preven¬
tion and Treatment of Delin¬
quents will be held in Gene¬
va this year from August 22
to September 3. - Main points
for discussion by the Con¬
gress are minima rules for
the treatment of prisoners,
recruitment and training of
prison personnel, open insti¬
tutions, prison work and
juvenile delinquency.
Governments of eighty-four
countries, members of the
United Nations and others,
have been invited to send
delegates, and representatives
of the UN Specialized Agen¬
cies and of some fifty non¬
governmental organizations
will also attend. This will
be the first international
meeting held since the work
previously carried out by the
International P enal and
Penitentiary Commission was
taken over by the United
Nations. (.See Unesco Cou¬
rier "Human Rights and
the law breaker"N° 10,
1954.)
M. HEATRES UNDER THE
TREES: This summer theatre¬
goers in Budapest will have a
choice of twenty-five open-air
theatres for their evening's
entertainment. The opera, for
example, will transfer its sce¬
nery and orchestra to a stage
under the trees in the Zoolo¬
gical Gardens, where there is
room for 3,500 spectators.
WIPING OUT MALARIA:
An all-out war against ma¬
laria is going on in Indonesia
when a World Health Orga¬
nization team, headed by
experts from Greece, India
and Italy, is aiding govern¬
ment action. Operations
such as the spiaymg of
D.D.T. inside houses and in
all places where malaria-
bearing mosquitos may lurk
have been going on in an
area with a population of
some 200,000 people.
1^ IIERISH THE HAND :
A new filmstrip which shows
the need for respecting and
protecting nature's resources is
now being used by the Inter¬
national Union for the Pro¬
tection of Nature in its world¬
wide campaign. The filmstrip
entitled "Cherish the Hand that
Feeds Us", was produced with
Unesco's help. It is intended
for schools, clubs and youth
groups, and in the Middle East
where a special campaign is
going on, it is being distributed
along with explanatory book¬
lets by Unesco s Science Co¬
operation Office in Cairo.
INTERPRETERS'
SCHOOL: Interpreters and
translators are now being
trained at the Sorbonne Uni¬
versity in Paris for work at
international meetings and
assemblies. Two hundred
students supervised by some
forty professors are attend¬
ing a special two-year course.
At the end of the first year,
they will chose to specialize
in either translation or inter¬
pretation.
1^ EW READER' LIBRA¬
RIES: The Government of
Bombay State has set up a net¬
work of libraries in towns and
villages where people who have
just learned to read can conti¬
nue their studies and increase
their knowledge. More than
1,000 libraries have been open¬
ed in villages. Special libraries
have been opened for the use of
women and children.
STUDENT FESTIVAL :
Concerts, plays, ballet, folk
dances and art exhibitions
are being presented by stu¬
dents from 14 countries in an
international cultural festival
organized in Montpellier,
France, by the French Gene¬
ral Association of Students.
The Festival includes con¬
certs by university orchestras
from France, Italy and the
Sarre and plays staged by
drama groups from Brussels.
Geneva, Paris, Salamanca
and Stockholm. Classical
music ensembles from the
universities of Mainz and
Madrid contrast with jazz
groups from Harvard and
. the Free University of Berlin.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
Sir,
As a teacher, I sincerely applaud
your magnificent publication and
the work it is doing in the field of
education and human betterment.
The Unesco Courier really deser¬
ves to be known and read in every
country. I have just finished read¬
ing your issue on Crime and Justice
(No.10 , - 1954) where you publish
short biographies of "Seven Apostles
of Prisoners' Rights." You might
have added one extraordinary
Spanish woman reformer Concep¬
ción Arenal who lived from 1820
to 1893.
Despite misunderstanding, opposi¬
tion and difficulties of every kind
Concepción Arenal devoted her
whole life to bettering the lives of
prisoners. For 30 years she visited
prisons and founded an organization
called "The Voice of Charity." Her
book "Manual del Visitador del
Pobre" (Guide for Visiting the Poor)
was translated into many languages,
and her work had great influence
on improving the status of prison¬
ers.
Luisa Buren de Sanguinetti.
Buenos Aires,
Argentina.
Sir,
I was very interested by an article
published in the Unesco Courier
(No. 8/9, 1954) on -"Science Teaching
With Odds and Ends," by Daniel
Behrman. My interest was two¬
fold: firstly, in the story as such
and secondly because of the ideas it
gave me for my work of equipping
our schools in Morocco with science
teaching materials.
I should be grateful if you would
send me more detailed information
(sketches, photographs, models, pre¬
cise technical facts etc.) on what
has been achieved in this field.
J. O. Nuss.
Chief Inspector
of Science Teaching,
Rabat, Morocco.
Sir,
By reading the Unesco Courier, I
am able to know of conditions in
many parts of the world. In order to
promote closer understanding- with
each other, I want to correspond
with the people of the world and
share with them opinions and in¬
formation. I shall appreciate it
very much if you Iwill give me an
opportunity to have friends in
foreign countries through the
Unesco Courier.
I am a Filipino, 18 years old. My
hobbies are stamp and coin collect¬
ing, singing, reading and sports.
Hospicio Bayona, Jr.
Silliman University,
Dumaguete City,
Philippines.
Sir,
On page 34 of the Unesco Courier
(No. 10, 1954,) there are references
to the "adoption" of farms by
schools in the City of Birmingham.
The impression given by these notes
is that something new and original
is being done ("success for their
venture"), and that Birmingham
schools should have credit for it.
One of my non-British colleagues
was extremely interested in these
notes, because nothing similar had
been done in his own country; but
he was equally surprised to be told
that "farm adoption" has been prac¬
tised by many town schools in
England for at least 25 years.
The "adoption" idea is good; but
in England it is not new, and the
Birmingham schools might even feel
faintly embarrassed at wearing the
mantle of originality which the
Courier has cast upon them.
CR.P. Gillett.
Unesco Institute
for Education,
Hamburg, Germany.
Sir,
My husband recently sent our
copy of the Unesco Courier to the
Science Master at the grammar
school in England from which he
has now retired. The following
extract from the reply of his col¬
league will, perhaps, interest you:
"Thanks for the Unesco Courier.
I am most impressed by it; quite the
best, and most informative account
of the present position of Atomic
Energy I have seen. I am trying to
persuade the Librarian to buy a
copy for all the VI Form one each
I mean. What a boon it can prove,
if we only have enough sense to use
it for peaceful purposes/'
Mrs. J. A. Thorne.
Paris, France.
Sir,
Would it not be a good idea, seeing
that the , Unesco Courier is now
smaller in page size, to plan to
supply hard board covers to keep
them in:
l.So that schools and homes can
keep the issues as they come out.
This prevents them being
thrown around and torn, and
gives the home or the school a
definite place to put the issues.
2. So that at the end of a suitable
period, say 6 months, they may
be bound and form a permanent
book.
In this case purchasers of the
* binder covers would be supplied
with an index for the period.
I could visualise that these books
would be a valuable addition to any
library, but most particularly in
schools. It might also help to in¬
crease the circulation, once people
see what a wonderful book they
make.
Fred Massey.
Fair Vale, N.B.
Canada.
Sir,
The Unesco Courier is greatly
appreciated here and it is unani¬
mously considered the most inter-
resting of all United Nations publi¬
cations. It is read by large num¬
bers of teachers, by persons inter¬
ested in science and culture and by
many members of the general
public.
We find that its international
outlook, its treatment of important
world problems and specially its
directness appeal to the readers and
arouse their interest in the ideals
and goals for which Unesco stands.
Maria Emma Castro.
Buenos Aires,
Argentina.
Unesco's National Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER can be
obtained ore listed below Other Unesco
Distributors ore listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna 1.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
5 5 1-3 Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P.O.
Box 244, Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 47 J,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor
regade, Copenhagen, K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Ctiro.
Ethiopia : International Press Agency*
P O B. 120, Add.s-Ababa.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, I 9, Avenue
Kléber, Pans- I 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb fur Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Librairie H. Kauffman, 28, Rue
du Stade, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon. s
India : Orient Longmans Ltd., Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots . Oxford Book
& Stationery Co., Scindi-a House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Hima¬
laya House, Bombay 7. Rs 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NV.,
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iran : Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstem's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road, P.O. Box 5154. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldmgs._
Japan ; Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J.I. Bahous and Co , Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Korea : Korean National Commission for
Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
Liberia : J, Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia
Malayan Federation and Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., ' P O. Box 135,
Singapore.
Malta : Saptenza's Library, 26, Kingsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N V Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout 9. The Hague.
New Zealand: Unesco Publications Centre
100, Hackthorne Rd., Christchurch.
Nigeria : CM S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass, 7,
Oslo. >
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs. 3.
Philippines : Philippine s Education Co,
Inc , 1 1 04 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila. 3.00
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Lid.,
(Book Dept.), Wacermolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hov-
bokh-nde*, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand : Suksapan Par.it, Arkarn 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H,M. Stationery Office, .
P.O. Box 569, London S.E.I.
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Service, 475
5th Ave, New York 17, NY.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
"...A Window open on the World"
The Unesco Courier
COMING IN NEXT MONTH'S ISSUE
Marionettes in
different lands
The story oí their development from
antiquity to today
Puppets that inspired great works
of literature
Puppets of the Orient
Puppets as a great medium of
education
DON'T MISS THESE FUTURE ISSUES
MAN AND THE DESERT. An
exciting 60-page issue on the
latest world-wide efforts to make
the desert bloom. Developments
in solar energy, wind energy,
fresh water from sea, soilless
cultivation, artiflcal rain-mak¬
ing, myths about living in the
tropics, old rain gods of primi¬
tive peoples.
MEN AND FISH. Exploiting
new resources from the sea.
Latest developments in marine
research. International action
to harvest sea crops. Fish as a
symbol in different nations and
in history.
HOW NATIONS SEE THE
FOREIGNER. How the French
farmer sees the stranger. A
Chinese looks at Americans. A
Britisher dissects British char¬
acter, etc.
WELCOME STRANGER. Inter
national fellowships and ex¬
change of people between coun¬
tries as one of the most power¬
ful roads to building peace
and international understanding.
Unesco's exchange programme.
Student exchange, teacher ex¬
change, workers abroad. Vaca¬
tion abroad.
WHAT'S WRONG WITH OUR
TEXTBOOKS ? Distortion of
history in school books. Textbook
publishing an unknown great
industry.
ARE WOMEN INFERIOR
BEINGS ? The advance in wo¬
men's status in recent years in
education, politics, society.
SUBSCRIBE TO THE UNESCO COURIER TODAY. - English, French, Spanish, U.S. editions
ONE FULL YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION AT THE AMAZINGLY LOW PRICE OF:
300 French ¡ranes ; 6/- ; $1.50 or equivalent in local currency (U.S. edition $2.50).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
LAST TESTAMENT
OF A NATION
OF POTTERS
Long before the Spaniards reached Peru and at
least 700 years before the Inca Empire flourished,
ancient civilizations on the Pacific coast, like
the Mochicas and the Nazcas, developed an
extraordinary art of ceramics. The brightly
coloured and decorated urns, jugs, pitchers and
vases of these ancient craftsmen present a fabu¬
lous record of every day life in the Peruvian
river valleys many centuries ago. For the story
of these people and the art of their potters
see "On Looking into a Mochican Urn," page 27.
]]>
</page>
</document>
