<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068988eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
'#', M
EXPLORING
THE OCEANS
WITH SCIENCE
1?
PF P .Ü
y : M
1955
(8th year)
Price : 7d (U. K.)
30 m francs (France)
36 PAGES
In this issue :
* FISH MIGRATION DETECTIVES
* PLANKTON-BREAD FROM THE SEA
* WORLD PLAN FOR MARINE RESEARCH
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ALI .HANDS ON DECK WHEN TUNNY STRIKE
Everyone, in cltrdu)gsftni! captain and the cook, has
a coupfe -of h*urs-of feverish, bacTt-breaklng work
a Pácm^J^nay boat-melts â school of fish.
Live sardines are thrown into the water as bait
and when the fitrH^strTke the* sardines, thg*. g¿
into a frenzy, strike at anything and cajj^thus be
pulled ÎHtcK^be boat wrtfisimple barbiess hooks.
XWjAKsJLLpt íatíeíí- "'tiïTta ", rr qjfsTOf the Hebest of
r"s8!»fl>tfffsT»ut little is ttifÉüa of its migratory M!&>*-
spawning habitsr^g&cray- "fishery ,J»*iii«gists and -
other srfentisu,a^rxi«rying out special studies
of the tunny as part- «f a world-wide campaign to.
nake betterTJse of marine re^oiÄ&e«Sf»Sae page 12.
Photo Black St.irJl&pho^
*.í
..**. ^
^*^^«.
W®*¿>
^**^'49!w
^*t&
1 "M^Uk. 	
...
Ü^^l
' «*«r,J*,c" ?C -, , *v
r
n
.. *Hr
*B$C
l^'''::-
" v ^WhS,
,:-*l*<
PMPfc-
* -1*
* ! - - Ml
--at. , W «k.
::.-:: 1
\
ÉÉ
¿"J . ^B
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
Courier
A WINPOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
CONTENTS
Number 5 - 1955
8th YEAR
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
By Gerald Wendt
4 THE METEORA
Rock pinnacles "hung in the air"
By Prof. G.A. Sotiriou
9 THE SUGAR BOWL IN THE DATE PALM
U.N. helps Iraq create a new industry
By Georges Fradier
12 SCIENCE AND THE SEA
Harvesting instead of hunting the sea's resources
16 STRANGE FACTS ABOUT NEPTUNE'S REALM
By François Le Lionnais
18 HUNTING THE WHALE
The largest creature living or extinct
By David Gunston
21 MIGRATING MAMMOTHS
Playing tag with Antarctic whales
By Paul Budker
23 BREAD FROM THE SEA
Farming the world's last frontiers
By Charles Drummond
27 ASH IN MYTH AND LEGEND
Symbols of tenacity, vitality and fertility
By Jean Marabini
32 UNESCO IN PICTURES
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
'Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not copyrighted ma/ be reprinced from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/-; $ 1.50 or 300 French frs
or equivalent (U.S. edition $ 2.50)
MC. 55.1 91. A
COVER PHOTO
PRIZE PREY of underwater spear and
spring-gun fishermen in the Mediterranean
is the meru. Weighing as much as 45
pounds, these fish swim with mouths
agape, taking in whole octopi and lobsters.
(Photo Rapho-Rebikoff)
Although nearly all nations have shores touching the sea
most of the human race has never seen the ocean and
few know it well. Yet it is humanity's great unused
resource, and moreover, a truly international one.
The land is divided among nations ; the sea belongs to
mankind. A few miles, adjacent to the shores, are under
local control but they form a microscopic fraction of the 139
million square miles of the ocean surface about two and
a half times the entire land area of the earth. Its total
volume is 328 million cubic miles, a figure which far surpasses
the human imagination. The entire human race of more than
2,000 million persons, for example, could be contained in one-
tenth of a single cubic mile !
This incredibly vast storehouse of mineral and food
resources has hardly been tapped to meet man's needs. It
provides, for instance, less than one per cent of the world's
food. Every cubic mile of seawater contains 750 tons of
nitrogen, 225 tons of phosphorus and nearly two million tons
of potassium three major agricultural fertilizers. Equally
important is the rich plant-life of the sea : scientists
calculate that a square mile of sea produces an average of
13,000 tons of vegetation per year, and a world total of
probably five times that of vegetation on land.
Most of the sea plants are microscopic and simply serve
to feed the fishes. But they are already recognized as
potential food both for men and for domestic animals. Much
more needs to be learned about their varieties, the conditions
under which they grow best, and their nutritional value ;
methods must be invented for cultivating and harvesting them
But the major practical objective of océanographie research
will be an increase in the availability of fish for human food.
The U. N. Food and Agriculture Organization has estimated
that the world's total annual production of fish and all sea
foods, excluding whales, is about twenty-six million metric tons
per year. The amount of fish caught and consumed could be
increased many times if fishing were no longer an essentially
primitive method of finding food, much as hunting was for
our ancestors who roamed the woods in search of game.
Many privately endowed and government institutes have
developed new methods of studying the ocean depths, and
revealed strange forms of deep-sea life. Recently inter¬
national organizations like the Pacific Science Congress, the
Indo-Pacific Fisheries Council, and F.A.O. have called
attention to the research that is still needed, and especially
to studies that will increase the world's food supply.
It is for this reason that Unesco is organizing a broader
international attack on the problems of the sea as it has suc¬
cessfully done for the problems of the arid lands. As early
as November 1953, Unesco participated in the studies on the
development of océanographie research in the Indo-Pacific
region and last September at meetings of marine biology
scientists in the Latin American region. Two months later,
a programme of aid to océanographie research on a world¬
wide scale, prepared in accord with F.A.O. was approved by
Unesco's General Conference in Montevideo, Uruguay.
To co-ordinate this programme, Unesco is now setting up
an International Advisory Committee on Marine Sciences. A
first meeting of scientists was held in Rome in May. As
in other fields of its work, Unesco cannot solve the complex
problems of the sea all by itself. No human institution can.
Unesco looks at the task ahead as a co-operative venture of
long-term international research. It will serve as a world¬
wide link between the many organizations now dealing with
these questions on a national, inter-governmental or inter¬
national level and help to organize, encourage and co-ordinate
research along specific lines.
The rich resources of the sea will not be truly mastered
until oceanography develops as a co-ordinated group of
sciences as reliable as the other exact sciences. This is a
vital need for the future with a world population of 4,000
million persons foreseen by the end of the present century
well within the lifetime of our own children.
Gerald WENDT.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Closer to heaven
than to earth
The vast rock piles of the Meteora tower above the vil¬
lage of Kastrani on the edge of the Thessaly plain (above).
This stone forest of giant pinnacles was chosen by mediev¬
al ascetics as a place of retreat from the world. The
monks who first climbed these rocks felt they were much
closer to heaven than to earth, as did the Stylites, the
famous ascetics of the East who spent their whole lives
perched on the columns of ancient temples. On the
Meteora, the monks built hermitages, churches and,
later, great monasteries, some of which are still occupied
today. Monastery of St. Stephen (right) stands perched
on the cliff-edge and dominates the town of Kalabaka,
which, eight centuries ago was called Staghi, a contraction
of three Greek words meaning "home of the saints".
In the far distance glitter the snow-covered peaks of
the Pindus mountains. Ancient engraving (opposite
page) depicts religious buildings on the Meteora during
most flourishing period of monastic life. (Meletzis photos.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
THE METEORA
Rock pinnacles 'hung in the air'
by Professor George Sotiriou
Member, Athens Academy and Director, Byzantine Museum
IN many places where men are striving to preserve and restore the ancient sites and monu¬
ments which form part of the world's cultural heritage, Unesco helps to organize and
support their work. In particular it has encouraged efforts to make cultural treasures
easily accessible to visitors from other lands. The need for new roads along which visi¬
tors could easily travel to the ancient sites was emphasized by Unesco missions which studied
the problems of restoring and enhancing the ancient monuments of Syria and Lebanon in
1953. A recent achievement in this respect is now reported from Greece where a fine new
road today leads to the Meteora, the fantastic rock formations on the edge of the plain of
Thessaly. Below, Professor George Sotiriou describes the strange land of the Meteora and
the medieval monasteries which crown their pinnacles.
In the north-west corner of the plain
of Thessaly, some eight hours
journey by road, north of Athens,
stands one of the strangest sights in
the world: the Meteora, a group of
gigantic black rocks rising up in the
sky like vast pillars or massive ruins.
The early inhabitants of the region
gave these rocks the name of "meteora"
("hung in the air") because they seem
to be suspended in space, each separate
from the others, at the entrance to a
mountain-girt valley leading into the
heart of the Pindus range.
Some geologists maintain that in very
ancient times Thessaly was a lake and
the Meteora were part of its rocky
banks. Great earthquakes split these
rocks apart, while on the eastern rim
of the Thessalonian plain an enormous
fault brought into being the lovely vale
of Tempe and the two great mountains
Olympus and Ossa. The waters of this
lake formed the river Peneus which
flows through Tempe into the gulf of
Salonika.
Nowadays it is easy to climb these
rocks and visit the great monasteries
built there centuries ago. Only a few
years ago the ascent still had to be
made in nets, which the monks hauled
up on pulleys from above, as depicted in
certain old prints. In earlier times,
sectional wooden ladders were used,
hooked into the rock, and naturally
enough the ascent was not without
danger. Today, however, visitors can
climb up safely by way of spiral stair¬
cases hewn into the rock. A recently
made road now leads almost to the foot
of the rock stairs.
It is quite understandable that me¬
diaeval ascetics should have chosen the
Meteora as a place of retreat from the
world. The monks who first clambered
up these rocks no doubt
felt that they were much » _ IT".
closer to Heaven than to
earth, as did the Stylites,
on next
page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THE METEORA
(Continued)
Nowadays it is possible to reach the Meteora monasteries by climb¬
ing spiral staircases hewn Into the rock. Eighteenth century engrav¬
ing (right) shows the hazardous means of ascent to the Varlaam monas¬
tery by sectional wooden ladders hooked into the smooth surface
of the rocks. Materials and food were hauled up In baskets. Even
a few years ago, visitors to some of the monasteries were still pulled
up in nets which the monks raised by cords and pulleys. Below,
the Varlaam monastery as visitors see ¡t today. On opposite page,
the Hermitage of St. Nicholas. What look like huge birds' nests
on the cliff face are monks' cells, supported by slender wooden poles.
Insets in text on these pages are a series of saints' heads reproduced
from the frescoes in the little monastery of Ipapanti.
the famous ascetics of the East, who
spent their lives perched on temple col¬
umns. A small basket attached to a
length of rope, in which the pious
would place morsels of food, was the
hermit's only link with the outer world.
The first monk of the Meteora was
known by the name of "Ho tou Stylou",
that is to say "he of
the column", because
the cave which was his
hermitage lay beneath
a rock shaped like a
pillar.
It is probable that
ascetics and monks
sought refuge in the
caves of the Meteora at
a very early period, but
the first historical ref¬
erence to the mon¬
asteries of the Met¬
eora appears in an
edict of the Byzantine
Emperor, Manuel Comnenus, dated 1143,
which speaks of the foundation of the
Sketis at Staghi. This was the name of
the little town, now called Kalabaka,
which lies at the foot of the rocks.
"Staghi" is derived from the contrac¬
tion of three Greek words "eis tous
aghious", meaning f'home of the
saints", and it is clear that, there, the
saints were the monks.
Gradually several hermitages were
founded; then, on the Doupiani rock a
church was built. Every Sunday all
the ascetics gathered there for the
celebration of Mass and thus a sort of
monastic community came into being.
However, it was only during the 14th
century that the great monasteries
were founded, and from these emerged
many eminent figures
who played an im¬
portant role in the or¬
ganization of monastic
life on the Meteora.
Mention should be
made of the Cénobite
Athanassios, who was
honoured as a saint
after his death, and
King John Doukas Pa-
leologus, who became a
monk under the name
of "Joasaph". Atha¬
nassios founded the
monastery of the
Transfiguration which is still the most
important and is known as the "Me-
teoron" or "Great Meteor". In it are
the tomb of Athanassios and the
portrait of Joasaph.
At the same period several other
monasteries were founded: St. SJephen,
Varlaam, Holy Trinity, the little mon¬
astery of the Ipapanti (Visitation), and
that of Ayia Rosani. There are also
several small monasteries in inacces¬
sible spots on the site of former
hermitages. Some of these are now in
ruins.
Only five of these monasteries can
now be visited: the Great Meteor,
Varlaam, Holy Trinity, St. Stephen and
Ayia Rosani. They are all built in the
usual form of Eastern monasteries.
The entrance consists of a large
courtyard, in the middle of which
stands the main church the Katho-
likon with the chapels, the sacristy,
the refectory and occasional guest¬
rooms. Surrounding the courtyard are
the monks' cells.
A deep peace reigns. Several cen¬
turies seem to have dropped away, and
yet the past is not dead. The monks
with their mediaeval look complete the
illusion. In silence they go to and fro
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 5 1955
about the tasks assigned to them,
faithful guardians of an age-old tra¬
dition.
The monastery of St. Stephen is the
best preserved of those that remain
today. The view from here across the
Tempe Valley to the Pindus mountains
is magnificent, and many travellers
make short stays at the monastery,
before crossing the mountains which
separate Thessaly from Epirus.
Inside the Katholikon, another world
is revealed to the visitor's astonished
gaze the world of Christ and the
Saints as they appeared to the imagi¬
nation of those monks who, from the
14th to the 19th century covered the
inside walls of the church with frescoes
of scenes from the Holy Writ. As parts
of these frescoes fell into disrepair, they
were restored by the monks, so as to
preserve the unity of the whole. Pre¬
cise rules laid down in which part of
the church certain holy personages
were to be depicted. Thus the central
dome was reserved for Christ the Sav¬
iour, the "Pancrator", who reigned over
all. The Blessed Virgin
is depicted in the altar
apse, and the rest of
the walls are almost
entirely covered with
scenes from the life of
Christ and the Virgin.
The ante-naves of
the monastery chur¬
ches are full of frescoes
depicting the lives of
the saints their mar¬
tyrdoms and the mir¬
acles they performed.
Painted in vivid co¬
lours, with a realism
that is moving in its simplicity, these
frescoes serve as a continual reminder
that the path of holiness is a hard one.
The frescoes in the ante-nave of the
Varlaam church are remarkable. They
date from 1566 and are the work of the
painter Frangos Katalanos. The mar¬
tyrdom of various saints is depicted
with an extraordinarily life-like vigour.
On the north wall, the priest Sisoes
contemplates with horror the skeleton
of Alexander the Great, lying at his
feet. The inscription reads: "Sisoes,
renowned among ascetics, on seeing the
exhumed body of that great and glo¬
rious King of the Greeks, Alexander,
shudders at the thought of how glory
decays with passing time ; sadness
comes over him and he laments: "Oh
Death! Alas! who can escape thee?"
On the east wall
appears a vast fresco of
the Last Judgment.
Thus the monks al¬
ways had before their
eyes three ideas: ine¬
vitable Death; Paradise
awaiting the faithful;
Hell, the fate of sin¬
ners.
Hours can be spent
in the contemplation of
these memorials to the
life' and work of many
simple and devout
Christians who have
passed from this world with their
hearts and minds entirely given up to
an ideal which they steadily sought to
preserve and also to hand on to future
generations.
Asceticism was the ideal of the monks
who made their homes on the hard
rocks of the Meteora.
From the heights, they contemplated
the vanity of human life far below
them in the valley, while the blue sky,
filled with the chanting of Vespers,
inspired them with mystic joy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
THE METEORA
(Continued)
Stories from the lives of the saintstheir
martyrdoms and the miracles they performed
are painted in some of the monastery churches
with a realism that is moving in its simplicity.
Among the most remarkable frescoes are those
at Varlaam, from which the painting of
St. George in military habit (above) is taken.
They date from I 566 and are the work of the
painter Frangos Katalanos. Right typical high-
perched monastery of the Meteora.
SIC TRANSIT
GLORIA MUNDI
Sisoes, a famous
priest of ancient ti¬
mes stands before the
tomb of Alexander
the Great and con¬
templates the mighty
conqueror's remains
with sadness detail
from a fresco at Var-
laam. Inscription
reads: "Sisoes, renow¬
ned among the asce¬
tics, on seeing the
exhumed body of the
great and glorious
King of the Greeks,
Alexander, shudders
at the thought of how
glory decays with
passing time; sadness
overcomes him and
he laments: "Oh
death ! Alas ! who
can escape thee ?"
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
New industry in Iraq
The sugar bowl hidden
in date palms
by
Georges Fradier
m ciENTiFic experiments carried out under the United Na-
KJ tions Expanded Programme of Technical Assistance
have paved the way for an important new industry in Iraq.
Iraq has been importing 80,000 tons of sugar a year; while,
for want of a market, thousands of tons of Iraqi dates were
allowed to rot. Then a Swiss expert sent by Unesco led the
way in experiments to manufacture" sugar from dates. As a
result, Iraq is on the way to saving $16,000,000 annually spent
for imported sugar.
As the result of the pioneer work of a Swiss scientist, sent
to Iraq by Unesco, the country will soon begin the manu¬
facture of sugar from dates, and some $16,000,000 annually
spent for imported sugar can be saved.
Photos Roger Viollec
For thousands of years, dates have grown in abundance in
Iraq and have constituted the principal food for the people
of the region and for desert dwellers generally in Asia and
Africa. Iraq, in fact possesses well over 150 varieties and pro¬
duces about 80 per cent of the world's dates. The dàte-palms
are cultivated as lovingly as hot-house flowers by farmers
who spare neither their wealth nor their labour. Sixty-five
million palms line the banks of the Tigris and the Euphrates
and sprawl out into handsome forests around Basrah.
Dates are the Bedouin's staff of life but, in Iraq, their
influence is not merely economic. Iraqi poets sing of the
date the way other poets under other skies write verses to
fields of wheat, to vineyards or to olive groves. Your true
connoisseur can distinguish 169 varieties of dates, some of
them bearing such charming names as ashqar, the blonde;
asabiil arus, the fingers of the fiancee; saadah, happiness or
ishaqi, the lovers.
In a "good year", Iraq may harvest as much as 400,000 tons
of the fruit. This should be a source of considerable wealth.
But in these "good years", date prices fall so low that distri¬
butors cannot even afford the luxury of moving the fruit to
market in Basrah you can often buy a ton of dates for 4
dinars ($11.20).
Despite progress in fruit preservation and in packing, which
has helped date producers to gain a foothold in certain
markets, they have been unable to solve what, at first sight,
seems to be a permanent case of overproduction.
This situation has been a constant source of worry to the
directors of Iraq's big fruit-producing company, the Date
Association. Recently it also began to worry /c
Dr. Herman Mohler, head of the Unesco team on next
of scientists sent to Baghdad in 1951 to help PaBe)
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The sugar bowl hidden
in the date palms
(Continued)
Anyone who had visited Baghdad thirty years ago would have
some difficulty in recognizing it from a present-day description.
"A university at Baghdad ?" he might exclaim, "An engineering
school ? Physics laboratories ? Why, I remember Baghdad it
was an unhealthy town and not a very safe one." A visit today
would change his ideas. Within a few years, a modern city
with spacious avenues has replaced the swamps and the empty
lots he knew. Iraq is no longer an old land with three-quarters
of its territory lying wastëTbut a new countryand a rich one.
The efforts of the Government, aided by the U.N. Technical
Assistance Programme, have helped to give Iraq many new
looks. One of these is the sight of students working in the
physics laboratory of the Baghdad College of Science, under
Professor Hermann Mohler (above). Professor Mohler, a
Swiss expert sent by Unesco, initiated experiments to manu¬
facture sugar from dates pointing way for a new Iraqi industry.
Below, trunk of a date palm. (Photos Unesco and Viollet)
establish courses in natural science and to initiate research
on a university level at the school which is emerging as the
University of Baghdad.
Dr. Mohler learned that Iraq on the one hand was letting
thousands of tons of dates rot for want of a market and, on
the other hand, was importing more than 80,000 tons of sugar
a year, at a price ranging from $196 to $244 a ton. He knew
that the sugar content of the date is 81 per cent, although
it is true that this sugar is not the pure saccharose extracted
from the sugar cane or the sugar beet, but a compound of
glucose and fructose. Date syrup might be extremely nu¬
tritious but it seemed useless for any practical purposes, for
example in the manufacture of sweets, both from the stand¬
point of taste and the dark brown colour.
Still, a sugar content of 81 per cent no matter what kind
of sugar it was, looked impressive. Dr. Mohler was more
impressed than a layman would have been for, as former
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
| ^ü*1» »
"'«* -tl-,- ÄS Sixty-five million
date palms
Palm groves are a common sight
in many parts of the Middle East,
but they are exceptionally profuse
in Iraq. Here, 65 million palms
line the banks of the Tigris and
the Euphrates in thin ranks, sprawl¬
ing out in some places into hand¬
some forests. Iraq has a rich
variety of datesnearly 170 kinds.
(Photos Unesco and Viollet)
chief of Zurich's municipal laboratory, he was well aware of
Swiss research during the Second World War on the produc¬
tion of fruit sugar. A few experiments in the laboratory of
the school proved to his satisfaction that dates could be used
on an economically-sound basis to produce a white sugar
which no palate could distinguish from ordinary sugar.
This was heartening, but it wasn't enough. More conclu¬
sive experiments were required on an industrial scale.
Dr. Mohler knew that the refining equipment he needed to
carry them out existed in Switzerland. At his suggestion the
Date Association shipped to Zurich three tons of fruit and
a few weeks later, Swiss laboratories sent back one ton of
clear white sugar.
This new product was immediately distributed in Baghdad
to manufacturers of sweets and to pastry shops. Its tests
turned out to be a small-scale triumph: a few weeks later,
an official reception was held in the capital and its guests
were served cakes and sweets, all made out of "national
sugar".
Since then, a company has been founded by the Date
Association, the Agricultural Bank and the Iraqi Agricultural
Fund to put the dates-to-sugar process on a business basis.
Its first factory, now under construction, will be equipped to
produce 9,000 tons of sugar a year. Dr. Mohler believes this
factory will also be able to produce an inexpensive syrup
which will provide emergency food in a period of famine. As
for the by-products of the factory, the company's directors
have already announced that they will be used for animal
feed.
For the first time in history, it appears, Iraq will obtain the
full benefit of its most precious agricultural resource. As for
the technical assistance mission, it will have demonstrated
once again the value of scientific research to economic pro¬
gress.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
KING OF OCEAN GAME Is the tunny, (also called the "tuna") unique among the important food fishes of the world because it is a truly oceanic fish,
living, spawning and dying on the high seas. Scientists know little about tunny and their migratory habits, but what they do know suggests that here is
a group which may comprise ultimately the most important food fishery in the world, for they are distributed in commercially important quantities over
a greater area of the oceans than any other group of food fishes. Above, French tunny fishermen at work in the Bay of Biscay. Below, A giant tunny
being hauled aboard by Nova Scotia fishermen. Tunny fishing is a new, thriving industry in Eastern Canada. (Photos Black Star-Rapho and Acme)
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
AND THE SEA
The mystery of the sea:
"To me the sea is a continual miracle
the fishes that swim the rocks the
motion of the waves the ships with
men in them. What stranger miracles
are there?"
The challenge of the sea:
"Faithful to no race after the manner
of the kindly earth, receiving no
impress from valour and toil and self-
sacrifice, recognizing no finality of
dominion, the sea has never adopted
the cause of its masters like the land."
The men of the sea:
"The fishers shall mourn, and all
they that cast angle into the brooks
shall lament, and they that spread nets
upon the waters shall languish."
These words by Walt Whitman,
Joseph Conrad, and the prophet
Isaiah express the three aspects
of man's relationship with the sea that
surrounds him; our relative ignorance
of its character arid resources; our
difficulties in trying to exploit it for our
benefit; and the penalties we may have
to pay if we exploit it recklessly,
without thought or understanding.
These are the matters which concern¬
ed a recent international conference
called by the United Nations.
All over the world and right through
the year the conference table is in
action. Any problem which crosses an
international border may come to it.
These issues and the decisions which
are made affect and shape our lives.
Sometimes that may sound like a
pretty extravagant claim even though
it's perfectly true in every case if we
bother to trace the line from the
conference table to our own front door.
On this occasion, however, there's no
difficulty. This recent meeting was
held in Rome at the headquarters of
the United Nations Food and Agri¬
culture Organization (FAO).
Its subject is stated in rather formi¬
dable words: "An International Tech¬
nical Conference on the Conservation
of the Living Resources of the Sea." In
other words, a number of experts from
different countries got together to try
and make sure that we can continue to
get that fine fresh flounder for dinner
any time we feel like it. Which would
suggest that perhaps the fish in the sea
aren't as plentiful as we imagine or
at least that we're consuming them at
such a rate that a dangerous shortage
lies ahead.
In a sense that's the way it is. For
instance a British fisherman recently
told a U.N. reporter : "I've been work¬
ing on a British trawler in the North
Sea ever since I was a boy. I can re¬
member, just after the first world war,
we used to take an average of over 30
cwt of fish every day. These days we
think we're doing well if we take in an
average of 13 cwt. And that, mind you,
despite the fact that our fishing me¬
thods are better today."
Despite the fact? It is, perhaps,
more accurate to say because of the
fact. Dr. D.B. Finn, Director of the
Fisheries Division at FAO, describes
some recent developments in fishing
technique and relates them to the
matter of marine resources:
"Throughout early literature there
are many references to the inexhaust¬
ible bounty of the sea," he says. "And
indeed this opinion was shared by some
of the early naturalists. Nowadays
things are different. We can traverse
in a few days stretches of ocean that
formerly took us months and this
makes distant fishing grounds much
more accessible. We have' taken sub¬
marine-detecting devices and turned
them into fish-finding apparatus.
There is hardly a modern fishing vessel
afloat that does not have an echo-
sounding device for locating fish. We
now have the floating trawl, the Danish
seine, and immense nets that a few
years ago would have been impossible
to handle and experiments are under
way with an electrical method of flsh-
SEAFOOD ESSAY on dietary value offish is this
.Chilian schoolgirl's contribution to Government-
FAO eat-more-fish campaign. (U.N. photo).
ing which would even eliminate a hook
or a net.
"All this has led to an increase in
production. The most recent, and
more accurate, estimates of FAO in¬
dicate that it was about 27 million
metric tons in 1953. However, while it
is estimated that the sea could, overall,
produce more than it does there are
nevertheless places in it where the re¬
turn of fish caught no longer pays for
the effort put into fishing. And so it
is brought home that the resources of
the sea are not inexhaustible in the
economic sense. While it might be im¬
possible for man by his fishing effort
ever to exterminate fish he can, by
over-fishing, so reduce the take that it
no longer pays."
So what should be our approach to
the problem? Obviously we're not
going to abandon our very effective
modern techniques and return to the
idyllic methods of Isaac Walton who,
despite the title of his famous book,
was really a very incomplete angler.
Millions of people in the world need
more protein in their diet and they
HEAVY LADEN with a record catch of
sprats, a fishing boat ties up alongside the jetty
at Concarneau, Britanny. (Keystone photo.)
could get it from fish if we could
assure a continuing, cheap, and abund¬
ant supply.
One man who knows from spectacul¬
ar personal experience how valuable
the sea is as a source of food is Dr.
Alain Bombard of France. In 1952,
Bombard lived for weeks off raw fish,
the tiny living organisms called plank¬
ton, and even the salt water itself,
when he sailed in his open rubber raft
"The Heretic" all the way from Monaco
in the Mediterranean to Barbados in
the West Indies.
Speaking on a United Nations radio
programme a short time ago, Bombard
said: "The problem for me was can
you survive at sea with only the pro¬
ducts of the sea. And the results prove
that the sea can give you to drink and
to eat, and also a supply of vitamins."
Dr. Bombard's epic voyage made him
an expert layman as it were, on the
subject of fishing and marine resources,
and from what he says it may be ne¬
cessary to change the present pattern
of fishing, under which we still have to
hunt for fish. We may have to adopt
a pattern under which fish are deliber¬
ately and scientifically cultivated.
Bombard said: "At present fishing is
empirical but now we must go about
SEA HARVEST, glistening and wriggling,
is hauled aboard a deep sea trawler. Captain
opens the mouth of the big net. (USIS photo.)
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND THE SEA
(Continued)
it scientifically. Fishermen are just
like prehistoric men and animals
merely searching. We must cultivate
fish just as we breed cows, horses and
ducks. But the big difficulty is to
change the habits of men because fish
culture will kill the fisherman. You
must explain to him 'you must be now
no more a fisherman like a hunter in
prehistorical time but also a cultivator
a farmer.' That's difficult the most
difficult, I think. The scientists un¬
derstand well but the fisherman... my
goodness!"
But even if large-scale fish cultiva¬
tion is accepted as an ultimate objective
a lot of research will be necessary be¬
fore it can become a practical un¬
dertaking. And the same applies even
to the much more likely matter of
conserving the naturally developed
stocks of fish in the sea. At present we
simply lack sufficient knowledge of the
sea and its resources.
Tracking the tunny
Dr. Finn puts it like this: "Unfor¬
tunately there is far too little
knowledge among the fishery
biologists and scientists to make the
answer easy or in some cases even
possible. Great strides are being taken
in the development of this knowledge
by some countries. In others relatively
little attention is being paid to it. But
the fact that a specific fisheries refer¬
ence was given to FAO by its member
nations the first time in history that a
world-wide body has received such a
reference is a sign that more and
more attention is being paid to the
subject."
But what are some of the specific
lines of research that must be followed?
The migration habits of fish is one. We
know a lot about the migrations of
some species but in the case of the
tunny (or "tuna"), for instance, which
is perhaps the richest sea food of all,
the known facts are few.
One of the technical papers present¬
ed by Unesco at the Rome conference
was by the British hydrographer John
B. Tait. "The temperature of the sea,"
Dr. Tait says, "exerts marked and often
decisive influence on all fishes through¬
out their lives. It undoubtedly go¬
verns spawning and it has an effect on
the development and growth of larval
and baby fishes. Salinity the salt-
content of the sea is another influence.
It can affect not only the fish them¬
selves but the various marine organisms
on which they feed.
TV in the depths
r-j-t hen there are the currents of the
I sea both horizontal and vertical.
A They control the distribution of
temperature and other physical pro¬
perties of the sea on which all marine
life depends. They control the dis¬
persal of fish eggs and of the youngest
fishes before they are able to swim
under their own power. And there is
the bottom of the sea itself its struc- ,
ture and topography. Different species
of fish favour mud' bottoms, sandy
bottoms, and gravel bottoms. Because
14
of the technical difficulties involved in
observing fish near the .bottom we
have, in the past, been severely han¬
dicapped. But now, with the deve¬
lopment of under-water photography
and television, there is promise of great
progress in this aspect of marine in¬
vestigation."
Dr. Finn summarizes these and all
the other considerations in this subject
like this : "All these problems have
their technical and scientific side. It is
a matter first of trying to measure the
continuous forces which reduce a popul¬
ation of fish and then to contrast these
with the other continuous forces that
build up a population of fish."
One technical conference, of course,
is not going to find the answers to all
the problems. But there have already
been several conferences recently in¬
ternational organizations like the Pa¬
cific Science Congress and the Indo-
Pacific Fisheries Council have called
attention to the research that is still
needed, and especially to studies that
will increase the world's food supply
and there will be many more. And
between conferences all the time
practical research will continue to be
done by individual' scientists and
scientific organizations in many lands.
To help in this work the Natural
Sciences Department of Unesco has
now organized an Advisory Committee
on Marine Sciences and Mr. J.A. Mus-
sard, head of Unesco's Division of
Scientific Research, has described its
functions as follows: "One aim is to
establish a bridge between the different
disciplines involved in océanographie
research. The phenomena of the oceans
are of a physical character, also of a
chemical character, and there are
other disciplines like meteorology which
are also involved. And we think that
FRENCH FISHERMEN cleaning a sea bass.
These fish can grow to more than six feet in
length. Their livers are a rich source of
vitamins. (Office des Pêches Maritimes photo.)
some interesting results could be
achieved if the research which is being
carried through separately in these va¬
rious disciplines is co-ordinated.
"The second aim is to mobilize
science to find through scientific means
the solution of practical problems
which are being faced by the fisheries.
And the third aim of this programme
is to establish also a bridge between the
under-developed countries, which rely
very much on fisheries, but do not have
the scientific equipment to develop this
kind of research, and institutions in the
scientifically advanced countries which
could aid these underdeveloped lands."
.*-r¿
ICELAND IS SURROUNDED by some of the richest fishing grounds in the world. Photograph
shows salted cod, which has been cut and gutted aboard trawlers, drying in sun. (USIS photo)
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' S. 1955
A LARGE BARRACUDA caught on lines trail¬
ed by a cargo and passenger-carrying schooner
plying among the Grenadine Islands in the Carib¬
bean Sea. (Central Office of Information photo)
LOWERING A GIANT RAY Into an aquarium tank. These immense fish can weigh as much as
1,500 lbs. and have a span of up to 10 feet or more. Expert fishermen are employed to catch them
for aquariums. Contrary to general belief, the safest place to grab a sting ray is by the tail tipthe
stinger is near the root of the tail. If its tail, is held the ray cannot use its stinger. (USIS photo)
The Advisory Committee on Marine
Sciences, which held a preparatory
meeting in Rome early in May, will co¬
ordinate a co-operative, long term in¬
ternational research programme now
being prepared under Unesco's auspices.
This programme will include activities
such as the mapping of the ocean
bottom, study of the soils and sedi¬
ments there, analysis of the ocean
depths and waters in many areas,
knowledge of the temperature varia¬
tions and ocean currents, special cha¬
racteristics of the shallow waters in
bays and near rivers, the changes with
the seasons and with the weather.
Also to be studied are the conditions
governing plant growth, the types of
animal life at various locations, depths
and temperatures, the diseases and pa¬
rasites of plant and animal life, and
especially the methods for increasing
the resources of edible fish in accessible
areas and those nearest the great cen¬
tres of population.
Thus, when the Advisory Committee
meets for the first time in Tokyo next
October, its members are expected to
include specialists in physical and che¬
mical oceanography, marine biology,
geology, submarine topography and
maritime meteorology as well as in the
different kinds of oceans: arctic, ant¬
arctic, tropical and temperate seas, etc.
There is also a legal aspect of marine
conservation. In fact, the conference
on the conservation of marine resources
held in Rome stemmed from the need of
tho United Nations International Law
Commission for technical information
to help it in its work of codifying the
law of the high seas and of territorial
waters. Fishing rights have always
been a rather complicated legal matter
and history records numerous disputes
between countries over where and
where not their respective fishing fleets
may cast their nets.
THE PORPOISE is a friendly creature. Here at an oceanarium on the southern Californian coast
one of them is fed by hand. It appears to need no lessons in " showmanship " (Black Star photo)
Close to anarchy
One of the Law Commission's pro¬
posals is that an International
Fisheries authority should be es¬
tablished within the framework of the
United Nations. In its report to the
last General Assembly of the UN . the
Commission said: "The task of this
proposed authority would be to set up,
at the request of any interested state,
systems regulating fisheries in any.
given area of the high seas for the
purpose of protecting the fishing
resources of that area against waste
or extermination. There is an urgent
necessity for international legislation
on the conservation issue. This is
significant of the present state of opi¬
nion, and of the widely felt need for
the removal of what is considered by
many to be a condition approaching
anarchy.
So the prospects are hopeful both
for the survival of fish in the sea and
for all of us who like to have some on
our plate now and again. As Dr. D.B.
Finn has summed up the situation: "It
is quite within man's technical ability
to arrive at a state where he has suffi¬
cient knowledge to treat the sea as he
does his farm land. Then, instead of
hunting the wild stocks of the sea in a
random fashion, he will be able to ma¬
nage his take of the crop so that he
may achieve its full abundance."
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
STRANGE FACTS ABOUT
NEPTUNE'S REALM
E
VERYONE knows that fish breathe
through their gills but not so
many people know that there are fish
which have both gills and lungs and
can live either in water or on land
according to circumstance. These fish
are known as dipnoi and it may be
that the transition from aquatic to
terrestrial existence was first made by
animals of this type.
Walking on the sea
In the Sargasso Sea in
the North Atlantic
ocean a sea slug spends much
of its time crawling under
the waves, much as flies
walk on the ceiling. The body
of the slug clings to the sea's
surface by capillary action.
It is admirably camouflaged
as the upper part of the body
which is turned to the sky is
blue and, therefore, birds
cannot distinguish it. The
underside is white and is
thus unseen by fish. Were it
not for this protective co¬
louring it would not survive.
Tree-climbing fish
The anabas, or climb¬
ing perch, lives in
the swamps of South Asia
(India, Malaya and Indo¬
china). This strange fish
can crawl over dry land for
several hours and can climb
trees with the help of its fins.
Cure for malaria
Two types of fish, cal¬
led the guppy and
the gambusia, feed mainly
on mosquito larvae which
they find on the surface of
the water. As they devour
enormous quantities of larvae
they have been acclimatised
in many parts of the world
to help in clearing mosquito
infected areas.
Longevity champions
The age of a scaly fish can be
determined by examination of
its scales, in much the same way as
the age of a tree is calculated by the
number of concentric rings in a sec¬
tion. Contrary to popular opinion it
seems that no fish reaches the age of
100. Carp may live from 25 up to a
maximum of 50 years and two sheat-
fish were known to have lived for more
than 50 years in England. The pike is
also a long-lived fish. On the other
side the stickleback, a European river,
fish, lives for less than two years.
Wanteda Jonah
This strange piece of research
was conducted with a view to
discovering a new method of preserving
whale meat. A British physiologist
decided that the only sure way was to
swim up to a whale which was prepar¬
ing to surface for the last time and
plant a metal recording thermometer in
its stomach. This odd task was
successfully accomplished and it was
found that when sea water was allowed
to enter the body of a whale the meat
was oetter preserved and the flavour
improved. The method was later
adopted by whaling crews.
Duels in the deep
When the sperm whale, which
may weigh anything up to 70
tons, hunts the giant squid a conflict
develops which, for size, is unmatched
Ibs^
by François Le Lionnais
in the world. The squid is sometimes
over 30 feet in length and its tentacles
measure another 20 feet. It usually
lives 1,500 feet below the surface of the
ocean and the sperm whale plunges to
this depth to hunt and fight it. No
man has ever witnessed the undersea
duel between these two monsters, but
when sperm whales are caught, the
scars of wounds inflicted by the squid's
suckers are often seen on their backs
and fragments of squid are found in
the whale's stomach.
A male gives birth
The sea horse is a curious little
fish which has a hçad like a
horse and a body resembling a cater¬
pillar. It belongs to one of the few
species of living creatures !"*. which
pregnancy is the function of the male
and not of the female. At the moment
of impregnation the female lays her
eggs in a pocket situated in the
stomach of the male. The gestation
period is two months and to judge by
the contortions which accompany it the
confinement of the male sea horse is
apparently as painful as for any other
female.
Fertility record
The fertility of certain fish is
phenomenal but there can be
no question that the record holder is
the turbot which can lay up to 12 mil¬
lion eggs at one time. Obviously the
majority of this offspring cannot hope
to find food and are thus
condemned to disappear be¬
fore they can reproduce
themselves. However, if the
world turbot population were
a hundred times greater than
it is there would be an ap¬
preciable addition to the hu¬
man food supply.
Sexual habits
Differences between
the sexes are fre¬
quently more striking in fish
than they are in mammals.
For example the male cera-
tiae can only exist by at¬
taching himself to the sides
or the head of the female.
Eventually the male becomes
firmly fastened to the female
and cannot be removed
without tearing the tissue.
Usually each female carries
two or three males. A simi¬
lar phenomenon is found
with the deep sea fish, the
photorynus spiniceps, where
the male spends his entire
life attached to the female
like a small horn on the
forehead.
Sexual differences are even
sharper in the lower animal
species such as the bonellia,
a worm which is found off
the European coasts. The
female may attain, when
extended, a length of over
six feet. For a long time in¬
vestigators were unable to
discover any males of the
species, but about the middle
of the nineteenth century it
was found that the male,
which only measured from 1/25 to
1/12 of an inch in length entered the
mouth of the female, made his way
towards the middle of her body and
lived thereafter as a parasite inside
his mate.
Seas and oceans : a few figures
The seas and oceans occupy
approximately 72 % of the
surface of the globe. In terms of
statistics the overall area is about
200,000,000 square miles of which the
land mass occupies some 56,000,000
square miles (including rivers and fresh
water lakes) and the seas and oceans
take up the remainder. The average
depth of the seas and oceans of the
world is something like 12,000 feet, but
this can only be an approximate
figure as large ocean areas in the Arctic
which lie under the ice have not been
systematically explored in depth.
Although only 2 per cent of the land
(Continued on page 30)
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
Old vs. New
Hazardous hand harpooning from a
four-oared boat is depicted (left)
in this early nineteenth century
French print. Above the modern
method: one man and a harpoon
gun. To get into position for firing
the catcher ship makes use of a
device working on the asdic prin¬
ciple which gives the whale gunner
a continuous account of the unseen
whale's movements. Below, a spot¬
ting seaplane is loaded on a giant
factory ship. More recently use
has been made of helicoptersmore
effective for sighting and easier to
stow away (Unilever's magazine
"Progress", Keystone and Norwegian
Foreign Information Office photos)
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
HUNTING
THE WHALE
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
by David Gunston
Whales have been hunted for
something like ten centuries
but only within living memory
has there been a scientifically or¬
ganized whaling industry. The whale
has been aptly described as a
mammal with an unfortunate eco¬
nomic background. The larger spe¬
cies are extremely valuable, and as
they are free and wild they are not
subject to any form of international
control. Thus they became the goal of
quick profit seekers. Only recently was
effective protection introduced, but not
before unbridled exploitation had led to
serious depletion of world whale stocks.
The history of the whale since about
1600 has been a tragic story and species
after species have been completely
wiped out. First the whalers caught
their quarry from the shore, then off¬
shore, and finally throughout the
oceans of the world, often thousands of
miles from their home base. Only a
hundred years ago whales were being
caught off the Scottish coast and in the
North Atlantic. Hull on the east coast
of England was once a busy whaling
port. But gradually whales diminished
in the off-shore waters and towards the
end of the nineteenth century it looked
as if this type of whaling was coming
to an end after a brief heyday.
New lease of life
In 1904 the Norwegian whaling
captain, Abraham Larsen, gave the
industry a new lease of life, and in
consequence the hunted whales a much
smaller chance of survival. He opened
up new whaling grounds in the icy
waters bordering on the South Polar
land mass. By the use of modern ships
and new techniques he hoped to have
an endless supply of whales for the
taking, but the blue and fin whales
which he found were only the remnants
of a one time enormous world whale
population.
Antarctic whaling was largely pio¬
neered by the Norwegians but other
nations soon joined the whale hunt.
However, in 1912 when the world's whal¬
ing fleet had 141 factory ships, no fewer
than 37 sailed under the Norwegian
flag.
In the years prior to the first world
war, and in the years following the
war, whale hunting in the Antarctic
was unrestricted and an international
free-for-all prevailed. The economic
crisis of 1930-31 had its effect on the
whaling industry as the whaling fleet's
18
record catch coincided with falling
prices and heavy losses were incurred.
More serious than this, however, were
the grave inroads made on world
stocks by unrestricted whale hunting.
Cosmetics and hormones
At the commencement of the second
world war in 1939 the world whale
population reached its lowest ebb.
Even so, the remaining whale popula¬
tion is still a valuable economic res¬
ource and the industry which turns
whales into food and raw materials
can ill be spared. This knowledge has
not, nevertheless, prevented the hunt¬
ing and killing of all species of oil-
bearing whales with the result that
they have been driven, if not to the
verge of extinction, then at least to a
dangerous economic level. Only three
or four species now survive in any
numbers.
The main targets today among the
remaining species are the enormous
blue whale. equal in weight to 17 ele¬
phants and the largest animal the
world has ever known the slightly
smaller fin whales and an occasional
sperm whale. Although oil remains the
principal object of whaling there has
been a great increase in the number of
by-products and these account to a
large extent for the mammoth size of a
modern floating factory which costs in
round figures about three million
pounds sterling (approximately nine
million dollars).
In the world to-day there is an
urgent need for fats, especially edible
ones, and this situation is likely to re¬
main for a long time to come. Prior to
the 1939-1945 war whales provided
about 3 % of the world's edible oil pro¬
duction. Though this figure has now
risen to about 10 % it is still only a
marginal source of supply and is liable
to be superseded in the future by vege¬
table oils, and possibly by synthetic
products.
Whale oil is at present used in mak¬
ing margarine, cooking fat, cosmetics,
lubricating oils, soap and many other
products. At a price of around ninety
pounds sterling (approximately 270
dollars) a ton it is assured of a ready
market. Whales also provide valuable
by-products such as hormones, insulin,
meat and bone meals, fertilisers, poultry
and stock feed, vitamin extracts and
whalebone for brush making.
In recent -years there has been a
(Continued on page 20)
CAPTURED WHALE carrying a marker harpoon with the house
flag of the ship and two small oil lamps. (Keystone photo)
STRANDED on a beach in Long Island (USA) a whalebone whale reveals his enormous mouth. Whalebone, or baleen whales, are named
for the flexible baleen or series of thin plates to scoop up food which hang in parallel rows on either side of the mouth (Keystone photo)
hoto«)
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
HUNTING THE
WHALE (Cont'd) Vanishing Quarry
growing demand for whale meat. Pre¬
viously hundreds of thousands of tons
of meat, after the oil had been extract¬
ed, were thrown back into the sea as
useless. In fact whale meat has the
highest protein content (85 %) of any
edible meat and provides a staple food
for the whalers themselves and other
peoples such as the Eskimos and the
Japanese. Attempts were made to po¬
pularize whale meat on the British
market but these did not meet with
much success and in common with
another fish, the snoek, whale steak be¬
came rather a music hall joke. Recent
research has improved methods of
preserving and processing whale meat
and it may yet prove to be of import¬
ance in the industry.
To gain a good idea of the present
status of the whale fishing industry it
is necessary to trace some of its recent
history. With the opening-up of new
fishing grounds in the Antarctic, the
increasing scope for development and
the perfection of the open sea whaling
technique, the industry was a highly
profitable one until about 1930. The
old-fashioned methods of hunting from
shore bases in South Georgia and the
Falkland Islands were dropped and the
factory ship, which processed whales
far from land, and acted as a parent
vessel for small tuglike catchers, came
into its own. South Africa became the
jumping-off point for. the whaling
fleets, and today tankers from South
Africa feed the fleets thus enabling
them to stay at sea for several months.
But the ocean could not be expected
to go on yielding liquid gold for ever.
Too many countries were sending
whaling fleets to the Antarctic and the
mad scramble for returns which ensued
soon had its effects. Attempts were
made by Norway and Britain to keep the
total annual catch within reasonable
limits, but these were not successful.
Further new whaling fleets appeared in
the fishing grounds with the result
that more and more ships were catch¬
ing fewer and fewer whales.
In the 1930-31 (season some 40,000
whales were killed for an oil yield of
564,000 tons. By the 1938-39 season the
size of the whaling fleet had more than
doubled but the yield was only 13 %
higher : 46,000 whales were killed for a
return of only about 550,000 tons of oil.
Following the outbreak of war in 1939
the whales were left to themselves. But
nature was not to be hurried, and the
long ravaging which had taken place
since 1904 had by no means been made
A RUSSIAN
whale catcher
bringing her haul
of whales back to
the factory ship.
This Russian whal¬
ing fleet, during
one Antarctic
season caught a
total of no fewer
than3,092whales.
(Keystone photo).
20
up when the whalers returned in 1945
to resume their work. As most of the
British and Norwegian factory ships
had been sunk during the war it was not
until the 1947-48 season that a fully-
equipped whaling fleet once again set
out from Europe. Weather conditions
were good during that season and
31,000 whales were taken for a yield of
302,000 tons of oil. Since that time
catches have been high and oil produc¬
tion good.
In efforts to restrict the annual
slaughter of whales International Con¬
ventions designed to fix a maximum
annual target were signed in 1944 and
1946 by those countries interested in the
whaling industry. These conventions
imposed a total limit of 16,000 "blue
whale units" for the entire Antarctic
whaling fleet in one season. The blue
whale is used internationally as the
standard measurement of whale
catches. One "blue whale unit" is
equivalent to one blue whale, two fin
whales, two and a half humpback
whales or six sei whales.
Industry's last chance
The maximum catch figure is con¬
trolled on the whaling grounds by
means of a floating headquarters.
Here the day-by-day catches are to¬
talled and announcements are given
regarding the closing of the season
when reports indicate that the limit of
16,000 is in sight. Despite this inter¬
national whaling agreement there are
many people who believe that the
maximum catch is still far too high to
allow for the future safety of the
whales.
The great cost of building and
equipping a whaling fleet today has
tended to limit the number of new
countries sending whaling ships into
the Antarctic. At present Japan, Nor¬
way, the Netherlands, South Africa, the
U.K. and the USSR send independent
fleets to the far south for four or five
months of the year. An International
Whaling Commission has been es¬
tablished and agreement has been
reached on many technical points.
All measures of international control
are of the utmost value and the guid¬
ing principle of such control must be
to restrict the annual catch to the ap¬
proximate surplus of nature. This is
not, of course, easy to judge and in the
absence of precise knowledge safety
would appear to be the best policy.
The potential value of the world
whale population is now universally re¬
cognized ; all that remains is a realiza¬
tion of the need for care in its hand¬
ling. Certainly one lesson cannot be
forgotten : in every area with the
exception of the Antarctic, whales have
vanished through lack of foresight in
not controlling the numbers of whales
killed. The industry and the world
cannot afford to let it happen again,
for this would be the last time.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
One whale equals
seventeen elephants
MIGRATING
MAMMOTHS
SCIENTISTS PLAY TAG
WITH ANTARCTIC WHALES
by Paul Budker
Assistant Director, National Museum of Natural History, Paris.
As shown above the giant blue whale, the largest animal the
world has ever known, is equal to 3 dinosaurs, 17 elephants,
133 oxen. (Courtesy "Progress", the Unilever magazine)
SEI WHALE MEASURING UP TO 56 FT.
SPERM WHALE MEASURING UP TO 65 FT.
Crossing the waters of the southern latitudes during the
month of October the surface of the long ocean swells
will be broken here and there by the sudden appear¬
ance of giant black humps shooting clouds of spray high
into the air. These humps betray the presence of vast
underseas hulks of hundred ton whales. At this time of the
year the whales are on the move southwards to their summer
feeding grounds in the Antarctic seas. This whale migra¬
tion occurs regularly every year, and to enable scientists to
study the fascinating story of the whale's life many of these
ocean mammals which pass by will carry, embedded in the
flesh below their immense dorsal fins, a thin steel cylinder
engraved with essential scientific data concerning their first
contact with man.
This amazing story of scientific detection is only today
revealing the surprising history of the controlled mass
movement of whales, to and fro, from the tropics to the
poles : a continuous rhythm which has, without doubt, been
carried on in the same way for centuries past. However, it
is only since the beginning of the present century that
precise facts have come to light on this previously unknown
pilgrimage across the oceans of the world.
HUMPBACK WHALE MEASURING UP TO 65 FT.
FIN WHALE MEASURING UP TO 90 FT.
BLUE WHALE MEASURING UP TO 100 FT.
Summer dining room
Early in January the whales have arrived in their
summer sea pastures and the whaling season opens.
In whaling parlance Antarctica comprises the entire
area from the South Pole northwards as far as latitude 40
south. It is here in this vast expanse of ice and ocean,
among some of the most inhospitable waters in the world,
that the whalers hunt and pursue their prey. Each year at
precisely the same time the fleets arrive on the edge of the
ice floes, and each year the vast schools of whales keep an
exact rendezvous with their killers. In some ways it is a
tragic story of man's inhumanity to an inoffensive denizen of
the ocean depths.
What is the impulse which drives the whales southwards
year after year? They come down to the Polar Seas for a
specific purpose. As the pack ice retreats southwards with
the coming of warmer weather, the ice floes break up and
the temperature of the water rises above freezing point to
about 35 degrees Fahrenheit. For the Antarctic wastes these
are summer conditions and a tiny shrimplike creature (Eu-
phausia superba), popularly known as krill thrives in them.
These minute organisms move along in million-strong masses.
The krill might well be described as the whalebone whale's
bonne bouche and every summer hundreds of tons are
consumed, or rather sifted through the whalebone tilters of
the Blue and some other species which do not possess teeth.
(Continued on next page.)
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
M I G R AT I N G
MAMMOTHS
(Continued)
The Antarctic in the summer season serves as a vast dining
room for the whale schools. When the whales arrive from
the northern tropical waters they are "lean" and hungry, but
after a diet of krill they fatten out and put on a few tons in
weight in preparation for the long journey before them.
In March and April, when the weather in the Antarctic
begins to grow cold and the autumn gales start to sweep across
the ice pack the whales begin to turn their noses to the north
and head for the tropic seas. This is their honeymoon
period and they move into the" balmy equatorial waters to
mate. From April until October the whalebone whales are to
be found cruising usually in couples in the tropical waters.
The vast schools have been dispersed and there is enough
evidence to show that they practise a type of seasonal mono¬
gamy. Not only is their mating carefully organized but
tropical whaling stations have established that throughout
this period the whales do not consume any food at all.
Numbers of whales, mainly of the Humpback variety, have
been examined and their stomachs have been found to be
quite empty. It is generally supposed that the whales live
throughout this mating period on the reserves which they
have accumulated during their long feast of krill in the
waters of the Antarctic.
As the month of October approaches a new impulse makes
itself felt, and the whales gather together, and, driven by an
internal rhythm which governs their wandering life, once
again begin their southerly peregrination towards the Polar
Seas. On their next journey northwards to the tropics the
mother whales will give birth to the infants which were
conceived in the same warm waters 11 months before. The
full cycle will have been completed.
Bachelors on the prowl
That is the story of the migration of the whalebone
whales, but the ivory toothed sperm whales have a very
different saga. These sperm whales maintain their
permanent headquarters in the tropics where they lead a
somewhat dissolute existence. Notoriously polygamous, each
male usually cruises in company with a harem of females
while on the outskirts of the group prowl the marauding
bachelors.
Few sperm whales make the long journey down to the
south, and those that do are usually solitary males who have
been ousted by their younger and more vigorous rivals, or
else hermit-like types who decide to forgo the pleasures and
vanities of the balmy equatorial waters and seek consolation
in a sterner life in the glacial waters of the south.
To garner the data which was essential for any study on
the migration of whales it was obviously of the first impor¬
tance to establish some system of checking or control. While
it was easy enough to ring or mark birds and small fish, such
a procedure with a hundred-ton whale posed a very different
problem. To catch a whale without injuring it, to fix a
mark and then to give the animal its liberty again was
patently an enterprise fraught with the greatest complexity
and danger. However, the problem was eventually solved
and the method now used has yielded the most fascinating
results.
The mark used on whales consists of a thin steel cylinder
slightly under a foot in length. Engraved on it are indica¬
tions giving the time and the plaee where the whale was
marked. The steel cylinder is fired at the whale from a
special calibre gun which is effective for the purposes of
penetration up to a distance of 50 yards. The projectile has
to be aimed so that the steel bullet will lodge in the muscular
masses lying under the layers of blubber in the area of the
whale's dorsal fin. Here, the cylinder becomes embedded and
will stay in place for years without harming the whale.
Cases have occurred where whales have been captured with
22
marks on them which have been placed between 15 and 19
years earlier.
In case it may be thought that this process might cause the
whale suffering, or give rise to infection, the biologists work¬
ing on the Enern in 1953, under the direction of Professor
Johan Ruud, the Director of Oslo Whale Institute, were
particularly careful to smear the outside of the cylinders used
for marking with penicillin.
The marks are recovered from the carcasses of the whales
during the normal course of whaling operations. Sometimes
the mark is seen when the dead whale is dragged aboard
the factory ship ready for flensing, and sometimes it is not
discovered until the carcass is in the processing chambers
after the meat has been treated. It is obviously preferable if
the mark is found when the whale is on the flensing deck
as this permits exact identification. In order to aid in
discovery some marks have nylon threads attached to them
which serve to catch the eye of the flensers.
Creatures of regular habits
Modern methods of whale marking started in the
1932/33 whaling season and since that time they
have been continued every year. Between 1932 and
1938 a total of 5,350 whalebone whales and sperm whales
were marked, principally in the Antarctic. In 1950 the
William Scoresby, oceanic research vessel of the British
Discovery Committee, took part in marking operations, and
in the course of a whaling cruise in 1953 the whale catcher
Enern with Professor Ruud and other scientific colleagues
aboard, concentrated on perfecting the marking process.
Although the information has only recently been firmly
established it is now well known that whales are not scatter¬
ed indiscriminately throughout the Antarctic. They tend to
concentrate in distinct zones which have been numbered
from 1 to 6. Here they return regularly after each northerly
migration. According to each particular species this regular¬
ity of appearance is more or less constant and can now be
considered as a general rule governed by certain exceptions.
The whale marking system has provided the biologist with
information of the utmost importance on the age and growth
of whales in addition to data on their migratory habits.
Dr. N. A. Mackintosh of the British National Institute of
Oceanography has observed that whale marking has proved
beyond any possible doubt the existence of a regular whale
migration between the Antarctic and the tropical seas. It
has also shown that after each migration the whales return
to their same zones. An interestingv piece of whale history
has been recorded by S. G. BrowrïN He relates that a whale
marked in 1938 was captured in 1954 less than one degree of
longitude away from the exact spot where it was marked
sixteen years before.
Nations on the watch
Of the various types of whales the Humpbacks are
apparently the most regular in their migratory habits,
since none have ever been captured outside the
marking zones. Rorquals and Blue whales also show a
remarkable degree of regularity each year in their return to
the Polar Seas.
Whale marking can be of considerable value to the whaling
industry and all countries interested in these problems have
expressed the desire to intensify marking operations under
the auspices of the British National Institute of Oceano¬
graphy. The work already carried out by the Enern was
accomplished with the aid of whaling companies from Nor¬
way, the Netherlands, South Africa and the United Kingdom.
In addition Australia, Japan, New Zealand and the USSR
also conduct whale marking. France has a research vessel,
the Orsom I, stationed at Madagascar which has the equip¬
ment necessary for this work, and a laboratory at Pointe
Noire in French Equatorial Africa will soon be in possession
of similar equipment. Thus it can be seen that close inter¬
national co-operation already exists for studying the migra¬
tory habits of the whale. Such co-operation can only lead in
the future to the most fruitful results.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
Farming our last frontier
by Charles Drummond
Specimen of plankton (top) as it comes from the depths of the sea. Left, plankton enlarged many times. All sea life depends on this mass
of minute drifting organisms. The name plankton is derived from the Greek word meaning "wandering". It is the staple food for fish,
and it is also edible by human beings. Right, an enlarged view of a tiny jellyfish only one and three quarter inches in diameter :
one of the myriad forms of sea life which go to make up plankton. (Photos National Geographic Society and Black Star-Rapho'
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Bread from the sea
w
A marine algae named gelidium
cartilagineum from which isinglass, aform
of gelatin, is extracted. (USIS photo)
iTHiN the last dec¬
ade or two marine
biologists and bio¬
chemists have realized
that the possibilities of
producing the additional
food needed with ever-
increasing urgency to feed
the world's hungry mil¬
lions lie in the seas and
oceans. In other words,
man must now farm the
world's "last frontiers",
extensively, intensively.
To farm the seas suc¬
cessfully will be a gigantic
task calling for the closest
integration of the efforts
and achievements of all
branches of science in¬
volved, for although scien-
. tifie knowledge in oceano
graphy is advancing steadily, the science itself is a rela¬
tively young one, originating largely through the 69,000-mile
cruise of H.M.S. Challenger some 80 years ago. It was then
realised that the problems of how to utilize the products of
the seas, to exploit fully its vast riches in food and minerals,
could be solved only by the closest collaboration among the
sciences concerned.
The cessation of World War II and the knowledge that the
world's population is increasing at a rate which threatens to
outstrip the most promising advances of agricultural science
have focussed the attention of many nations on the urgency
of "farming the seas". A great deal of research and much
experimentation have been undertaken successfully by inde¬
pendent organizations, a work which is being steadily
intensified.
Great meadows for all nations
Clearly it is necessary to experiment first in order to
decide on ways and means of utilizing fully the seas'
resources. It is necessary not only to improve existing
fishing grounds but to find (and even create) new ones, not
only to encourage faster breeding but to pin-point those
kinds of fish which are most useful commercially, not only
to discover more ways of utilizing marine plants but to
invent methods of growing and harvesting them.
Despite the many obvious difficulties, especially those of
a financial nature, the idea of farming the seas possesses
several well-defined advantages. These may be summed up
thus:
A. The sea contains great quantities of nutrients which,
properly directed and supplemented where necessary, could
be made to increase (in the first instance) the growth of
planktonic life, and thus in turn stimulate the growth of
marine animal life.
B. In marine agriculture there can be no lack of water
such as besets terrestrial agriculture.
C. It is believed that marine plant diseases, where they
exist, can be more easily controlled in this environment.
D. The seas, comprising 71 per cent of the earth's surface,
are vast enough for all nations, including those which have
no seaboards of their own, to participate in marine agri¬
culture.
Space does not permit the detailing of the many research
expeditions and experiments conducted to probe the poten¬
tialities of farming the seas, but it can be mentioned that
outstanding work in these respects has been (and continues
to be) carried out by various organizations, including the
National Geographic Society, the Marine Laboratories of the
University of Miami, and the Agricultural and Mechanical
College of Texas, as well as by research departments of the
U.S. Department of Agriculture and government bodies of
other nations. Under the impetus of ever-growing need,
science, industry and government are teaming up as never
before to explore and exploit the seas' food reservoirs.
Marine research has long established that algae (comprising
the many varieties of seaweed) and both Zooplankton and
phytoplankton have definite food value. Professor D. W.
Hood, of the Agricultural and Mechanical College of Texas,
in a note to the writer points out that "these plants, if
obtained in large quantities, may be useful for livestock feed,
human food, pharmaceuticals, drugs and other important
biochemicals." He relates how experiments with a fresh
water algae (chorella pyrenoidosa) grown under good condi¬
tions proved that this plant can be made to yield around
50 tons of dry material per acre surface per year, having a
composition of 55 per cent protein. Under similar conditions,
he argues, marine algae could be "farmed" with results
approaching this.
Seaweed, dried and ground fine
During the two world wars, the development of acute
food shortages in many countries brought about nu¬
merous experiments with seaweed, conducted both on
an official basis and individually. In France tests were made
on the use of seaweed gathered on the Atlantic coast, when
it was found that horses could eat as much as 3.3 lb. in a ra¬
tion totalling approximately 17 lb. per day. The French
peasants also made a satisfactory silage from seaweed
harvested along the coasts. An official of the Animal Nutri¬
tion Investigations Department of the Bureau of Animal
Industry (Beltsville, Maryland, U.S.A.) points out that even
in normal times the Laplanders as well as the inhabitants of
the Faroe and Orkney islands use seaweed as a cattle feed.
"The material", he writes, "is dried and then ground
into a fine meal for
Y,"*» ^ ,-'' i"4* mixing with various con¬
centrate feeds. Usually,
however, seaweed consti¬
tutes only one or two per¬
cent of the total mixture."
Most of the nutritional
studies into the uses and
value of seaweed have
focussed on the produc¬
tion of kelp (the slag or
ash obtained by burning
seaweed). Marketed as a
feed supplement, the value
of kelp resides largely in
its iodine content; but though both seaweed and kelp meal
have been proved to be valuable constituents of animal fod¬
der, especially in areas low in iodine, the overall possibilities
of utilizing seaweed directly as a food for domestic animals
are of a supplement-ary value only as far as present-day
research indicates.
The major possibilities of producing great quantities of
food from the seas lie largely in the potentialities of
"plankton", those vast "meadows" of minute living creatures,
both animal and plant, that live in the sea at varying depths,
covering many acres at a time.
Plankton, taken from the Greek word "planktos", means
"wandering", and is the name given by the German scientist
Hensen in 1887 to the swarms of microscopic organisms
which, at the mercy of the seas, drift aimlessly to and fro
with the currents. Plankton is of course also found in rivers
and lakes. Phytoplankton is the name given to plant
plankton. Because many members of animal or Zooplankton
depend directly on these tiny plants for food,
phytoplankton constitutes the basis of animal (Cont'd on
life in the sea. In turn, Zooplankton is eaten by PaBe )
3>
Phytoplankton under the microscope.
(Photo Fisheries Laboratory, Lowestoft)
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 5. 1955
'Skyscraper' tombs
on the ocean floor
Analyzing the microscopic plants and animals of the ocean has become an Increasingly
important part of the science of oceanography and is being carried on In research
laboratories throughout the world. Here, at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography
in California, two working methods are shown. In the first, a plankton net is being
lowered into the sea. Composed of fine silk, this net is equipped with a meter for
measuring the amount of water filtered as it is towed through the sea. In the second,
the diver plunges to the ocean depths for treasure: not gold, but specimens of sand,
rocks and marine flora. The samples thus gathered from the ocean floor will be
analyzed in the laboratory to determine their scientific contribution to oceanic know¬
ledge. Enlarged I 5,000 times here are some of the results of the search. They are
unicellular Diatomesthe most important part of marine plankton, the staple diet of
the fish. They are found in vast quantities in the sea and when they die their shells
fall to the ocean bed where they form a kind of submarine cliff, often hundreds
of feet high. (Photos USIS and Helmcke-Krieger, Max-Planck Gesellschaft)
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Bread
the
from
sea
(Continued)
fish and even by whales. Clearly,
these "floating pastures" are as
vital to marine life as grass is to
land animals. Yet these organisms
are so tiny that it is possible to see
only a few out of the 50,000 or so
found in a single pint glass of
plankton seawater!
It follows, therefore, that if me¬
thods can be devised to increase these pastures, to improve
their nutritional value and also to grow and harvest them
under controllable conditions, an immense food reservoir of
unlimited potentialities lies at hand for the benefit of all.
Scientific investigations have already established the
nutritional value of plankton. It has been proved moreover
that planktonic life is so adaptable that it can reproduce
vigorously in almost all kinds of water or climatic conditions.
This research, much of which has been carried out on
American research ships in the Gulf of Florida and elsewhere,
is however a long-term project with numerous implications.
For instance, it is being used tö tabulate the behaviour of
important ocean currents such as the Gulf Stream (which
we know affects the climate both of Europe and North
America and hence the food-growing potentialities of these
continents), to establish the locations of good feeding grounds
for commercial fisheries, to trace the life histories of
different forms of marine life, to find out how seasonal
changes and water origins affect planktonic productivity and
growth, and many other related aspects.
Plankton has already been put to practical use. At the
Microbiological Research
Institute in Trinidad, fat
is extracted which is
used in the manufacture
of margarine. During
the last war an attempt
to harvest plankton as
human food was made
off the west coast of
Scotland by an eminent
British scientist, but the
attempt did not succeed.
German scientists, how-
e v e r, succeeded i n
producing plankton arti¬
ficially and extracting
fat for use in animal
forage.
Major problem exer¬
cising scientific minds
engaged in planktonic
research is that of dev¬
eloping methods of grow¬
ing and harvesting algae
and plankton under fully controlled conditions.
It is a happy thought not only that research into the seas'
natural resources is being intensified, but that in the train
of advancing developments in the science of oceanography
will come other vital advantages, the most notable of which
will probably be the establishment of new fishing areas
adequately stocked by new planktonic productivity.
Retrieving a sediment trap from the
ocean bed. This instrument is used to
study beach formations. (USIS photo)
NEEDLE
IN A
PLANKTON
STACK
"Sorting out" a collection of
plankton in the marine re¬
search laboratory, Aberdeen,
Scotland. The sea's "float¬
ing pastures" of plankton are
as vital to marine life as
grass Is to livestock. Yet
these organisms are so tiny
that it is possible to see only
a few. out of the 50,000 or
so in a pint glass of plank¬
ton seawater. (COI photo)
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
FISH IN MYTH
AND LEGEND
ILLUSTRATIONS
Since prehistoric times many of the
world's civilizations have sought to
identify their peoples with the
creatures of the sea, to deify them
and to endow them with strange super¬
natural powers. The fish has appeared
as a symbol in the religions, myths and
legends of mankind, and even as a
constellation of stars in the heavens.
Although man has always tracked and
pursued fish with the most ingenious of
weapons and devices, nevertheless the
simple fisherman has always retained a
sense of awe for the wonders of marine
life. The fish has been venerated as a
symbol of tenacity, vitality and fertility.
In Japan, the carp has long been a token
of courage and perseverance and every
year on May 5th, on the occasion of
the Ton-go-sek-ku (the Boy's Festival),
long bamboo poles are raised outside
every house with a son in the family.
On these poles are strung hollow carp
models made of gaily painted paper or
cloth one carp for each son.
by
Jean Marabini
A somewhat similar tradition exists in
the Caucasus. Here, according to an
ancient folklore tale, described by Rus¬
sia's great poet, Alexander Pushkin,
the young men offer pictures of goldfish
(a member of the carp family) to the girl
of their choice.
Legends and stories about the salmon
are to be found among practically all
peoples inhabiting northern latitudes
where the salmon abounds. The vitality,
strength and persistance of this fish is
proverbial. Hatched in fresh water,
they mature in the open sea and then
return to spawn in the very stream
where they were born. This king of fish
will sometimes travel 2,000 miles inland
to spawn. En route it will leap water¬
falls, cut through churning rapids and
wriggle across the shallows. Only death
can prevent it from reaching its goal,
and only death will be its reward when
it has reached it, as most
species of salmon die soon (Cont'd on
after spawning. next page)
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
FISH IN MYTH
AND LEGEND
(Continued)
The Laplanders, who believe in reincarnation, consider the
salmon to be the most noble form into which man can be
reborn. This belief has its reflection in a story told by an
old Lapp fisherman near Lake Inari in Northern Finland.
"Do you see this scar on my head?" he said, "One day I told
my son not to fish in the river, But Lapp boys are no
different from any other boys and he disobeyed me and went
fishing just the same. He speared a salmon, but it was a
strong fish and fought courageously. Though badly wounded
and covered with blood it finally got away. My son returned
in the evening empty-handed and found me lying by the
fire with a wound in my head. I showed him the fresh blood.
Did I not tell you not to go fishing today? Look what you
did when you harpooned me in the river."
Unlike the Lapps the Buddhists in China believed that it
is only evil people who are given fish form in their next
existence. The fish is one of the eight magic symbols of
Buddhism, and it is not without significance that the Chinese
dragon often takes the form of a carp. Many Asiatic
legends describe in various ways the story of the worthy
fisherman who was rewarded because he freed a fish which
was the incarnation of a god.
Similar tales have been told by the Slavs. The story of
the golden fish which rewards the fisherman who spares his
life may well have had the same origin as the Asiatic myths.
However, 2,000 years ago, long
before the introduction of
Buddhism to China these same
tales were being told in India,
and this would seem to indicate
the existence of a maritime civi¬
lization of some form in South
East Asia at the close of the
prehistoric era.
The underlying theme running
through these early myths was
the idea of the sea being a vast
reservoir out of which gods,
saints and kings drew their di¬
vine powers. These concepts were
probably initiated by peoples
whose lives were spent within
sight and sound of the sea, and
it is interesting to note that they
conflict with the later evolution
of religion in India and China,
where, for both the Hindus and
the Chinese, divine power and
authority did not come from the
sea but from the sky. Certain
scholars have concluded from
this that the Indian and Chinese
civilizations borrowed elements
of their culture from this maritime civilization. When
brought into contact with a different environment these
cultural beliefs were changed and transformed, thus the
fish became a dragon in China and a Hindu mythological
serpent god in India.
Another fascinating legend in Eastern Asia was that of
the fish princess, who always carried with her the scent of
the sea. As the story goes, a royal seed on a lotus leaf was
blown by chance into waters where a sacred fish was
swimming. The issue of this chance mating became the
fish princess who, like Cinderella, was held in a form of
slavery until, with her singular charm, she seduced a Prince
by whom she had some wondrous children.
As fish were a symbol of fertility it was quite natural to
portray them as being assexual. The tales of the sea sirens
came from the Far East to the Mediterranean where, as we
know, Ulysses had some encounters in the waters off the
north coast of Sicily, and thence northwards to follow the
shores of the Atlantic where the navigators of those days had
many stories to relate of the appearance of the sirens.
Greek mythology was full of sirens and mermaids, and
despite Christian and rationalist attacks on belief in such
creatures, their fame survived and the beliefs persisted.
They continued to sing their timeless songs in bewitching
voices, and the Nordic water nymphs and Hans Christian
Andersen's little mermaid are but further proofs of the
tenacity of these myths.
A primitive aboriginal myth from Australia, which has also
appeared in various different forms in peasant legends from
other lands, is that of the frog, the moon and the seas.
These Australian primitives imagined the moon as a form of
monstrous frog, and inside the body of the frog were the
seas of the world. The story goes that the frog one day
burst out in laughter when watching the antics of an eel, and
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
thus set free the oceans. It is significant to note, however,
the inter-connection in this story between the moon and
the sea. Perhaps these Australian aboriginals knew of the
relationship between tides and the moon. This frog myth
is also extant in the folklore of other countries, and it
is popularly believed that the frog has the power to reflect
itself in the face of the moon. Whether or not these stories
originated among the aborigines it is difficult to say, but
what is reasonably certain is that traces of the beliefs held
by the seafaring civilization which first inhabited South East
Asia have come to light in the Mediterranean basin and in
the Middle East.
The Philistines had a fish-god called Dagon, and the
Carthaginians worshipped the fish as a symbol of strength,
and had an image of a fish buried with them. The
Egyptians, Herodotus noted, regarded the eel as sacred. The
Chaldeans worshipped the fish-god Cannes which was
supposed to have imparted wisdom to the first men on earth.
Even today in western Syria the old Dagon cult of the
Philistines still lives on in the worship of certain fish which
no fishermen are allowed to catch. Although originating
from a different source it is of interest that the Jews are
still prohibited by their religion from eating fish which have
neither fins nor scales.
There have been, of course, many references to fish in the
Bible, sometimes in natural terms and sometimes in terms
of miracles. The Gospels tell us that the first Christians
were very often simple fishermen, and this in a way would
explain the importance given in the Bible to fish as a source
of food. In its Greek name the fish became an actual symbol
of Christ, as the letters of the Greek word ICTHUS furnished
the initial letters of the phrase "Jesus Christ the Son of God
Saved".
In the early Christian era the martyrs absorbed and
transformed the idea of the symbolism attached to fish and
fertility and made it part of their faith. Also among various
non-Christian peoples there could be seen a similar type of
transformation. In forming the capital letters of their
alphabets the fish appeared in written form. In the
Frankish cemetery at Marchepot in the Somme region of
France, there is a bronze plaque with a fish and dove in the
same group two Christian symbols joined together on a
pagan monument.
Both in past centuries and in modern times the fish has
exercized a considerable influence on everyday language. The
ancient Phoenicians called a hermit by the name of pike, as
this fish was reputed to be and still has the same
reputation today anti-social. Terms referring to fish have
a variety of meanings, but in the majority of countries these
are usually of a disparaging nature "As drunk as a fish"
would serve as a good example. In France an April Fool .
joke is called an "April Fish". In coastal areas, however,
fewer unfavourable words and references to fish are found,
and this can be readily explained by the fact that the
maritime peoples very often depend for their food and keep
on fish and they thus pay a form of tribute by flattering
references in their everyday language.
Whatever may be the final judgment on the facts relating
to the fish as man's first ancestor, there can be no doubt that
the fish has exercized a profound influence on civilization in
all its forms. The fish has provided the key to certain things
of the past, and it may be, as simple Celtic inhabitants
of Amlwch, Wales, believe, that it can also predict the future.
As H.G. Wells once said, "'when humanity has exhausted
itself in dreams and lust for power it may well be that the
only remaining sound on earth will be the murmur of the
sea lapping on deserted beaches." The fish will certainly
then have re-captured their kingdom for all eternity.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
STRANGE FACTS ABOUT NEPTUNE'S REALM (Continued
from p. 16)
surface of the globe rises two and a
half miles above sea level almost 50 %
of the ocean bed lies the same distance
below the surface of the sea. The
world beneath the seas is greater than
the world above them.
Upside-down mountains
The highest mountain in the
world, Everest, rises to a height
of 29,034 feet, but in the Pacific Ocean
near the island of Mindanao in the
Philippines the sea plunges to a fan¬
tastic depth of 35,530 feet. This figure
is the world's record for ocean depth.
At this same point in the Pacific, the
Snellen in 1930 plumbed the greatest
known depth by line. A piece of red
clay was brought to the surface from
the ocean bed 33,000 feet below.
World's tidal contrasts
The Bay of Fundy on Canada's
Nova Scotian coastline has the
distinction of having the largest tides
in the world. Twice every day 100,000
million tons of sea water are swept into
the Bay causing tides which reach a
height of nearly fifty feet. By way of
contrast to this gigantic inrush of
30
water the Mediterranean is practically
tideless.
Ocean wave globetrotters
O cean waves are great travellers
and it has now been discovered
that some will begin their life in the
southernmost seas of the world and
after that traverse a quarter of the
circumference of the globe, some 6,500
miles, before they disappear and die.
Meteorologists are now studying the life
of waves and wave motion and record¬
ing their results. This information has
made it possible to predict in advance
the arrival of hurricanes and storms.
Herrings in History
Throughout the Middle Ages
the herring played an im¬
portant part in the economic
and political life of Europe. In the
thirteenth, fourteenth and fifteenth
centuries the herring shoals were
concentrated in the Sound and the
Belt, the narrow passages between the
North Sea and the Baltic. Ports in
Denmark and Southern Sweden owed
their prosperity to this fact and one
of the reasons for the establishment of
the famous Hanseatic League of North
German towns was the determination of
its members to enter into competition
with Denmark in the herring fishing.
But in the fifteenth century the herrings
were displaced from their usual feeding
grounds and driven into the North Sea.
The reason for this migration is still a
mystery but it is thought to have been
caused by powerful submarine currents
which followed a period of very high
tides. The departure of the herrings
weighed heavily on international
relations at the time as the ports
of Southern Sweden, Denmark and
Northern Germany were impoverished
and the ports in the Low Countries
became prosperous. It has been said
that at the time the Dutch abandoned
agriculture for herring fishing and
thereby improved their shipbuilding
and navigation.
I
Deep Sea Voices
t used to be assumed that silence
was to be found in the ocean
depths but it has now been
proved that they are actually as noisy
as a farm-yard at feeding time. Fish
utter piercing cries. They groan,
cackle and trumpet so that the deep is
filled with a cacophony of sound.
During the 1939-45 war the US Navy
made a systematic study of the noises
made by fish for two very particular
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 5. 1955
reasons. The acoustic mines which
were then being brought into use were
exploded by the vibrations caused by
the noise of ships motors but it was
feared that the sounds made by fish
might also explode these mines. Ultra¬
sensitive microphones had been sunk
deep in the sea near the US coastline
to pick up the noise made by submarine
motors but it was found that these
were also picking up the noises of the
undersea world, thus making it im¬
possible to distinguish the sound of the
submarines. Special electrical filters
were constructed to eliminate the
undersea noises but retaining the
noises made by ships engines.
The study of sounds made by marine
animals is only in its infancy, but
although many mysteries remain to be
solved it is possible to gain a fair idea
of the whole strange . phenomenon.
Fish do not possess vocal cords and so
they produce noises by grinding their
teeth, oscillating their air bladders,
rubbing their bones together and
jerking their heads. It is of some
interest to note that while" the human
muscle can produce only 36 vibrations
per second that of certain fish can
produce up to 2,332.
In old age the "voices" of fish, both
of the male and female, tend to become
lower in tone. In those types which
produce sounds by means of their air
bladder this fact is explained by the
elongation of the bladder with the
consequent lowering in pitch of the
sounds made.
It is now possible to distinguish
certain types of fish by their "voices".
However, this study has not proved as
easy as it was thought at first as when
fish are taken into captivity for the
purpose of recording the sounds which
they make, it is found that they do not
produce the same amount of sound as
when they are at large in the ocean:
some even become quite dumb.
Fish are not the only marine animals
capable of producing sounds. One type
of round shrimp makes a frying noise
by knocking its claws together. This
sound, when made by one shrimp is
practically imperceptible, but it is quite
noticeable when there are some
hundreds grouped together on a rock.
Aircraft made of sea water
Sea water contains between
350,000 and 400,000 tons of mag¬
nesium per cubic mile. In 1941
scientists devised a method of extract¬
ing the metal directly from sea water
by means of a chemical process. One
aircraft contains on an average half a
ton of magnesium and it was due to the
extraction of magnesium from sea
water that aircraft production was
expanded so rapidly during the course
of the Second World War.
Dangers of the sea coasts
DETECTIVES
OF THE SEA
Photos on these pages show re¬
search being carried out at Scot¬
tish Home Department Marine Labo¬
ratory, Aberdeen. I. Hydrography
Department assistant prepares drift
bottles and plots on charts where
they are found. Three thousand of
these bottles are set free each year.
2. Tagged herring which had trav¬
elled 180 miles is examined after
being returned to laboratory. Ob¬
ject is to check migration, move¬
ments of which are shown on charts
in background. 3. The life of the
lobster comes in for a searching
investigation. One of senior scien¬
tific officer's jobs is to advise on
lobster catching restrictions. 4.
Examination of a plaice's earbone
reveals its age. Check on the rate
of tagged fish gives an idea of rate of
fishing and of natural mortality.
5. What did he have for breakfast?
Examination of fish stomach reveals
natural fish foods, thus Increasing
knowledge about distribution of
food organisms for shoals. 6. Fish
landings at Aberdeen are not as
large and lucrative as they were
some years ago. Fishermen are help¬
ing Laboratory investigation, return¬
ing tagged fish and allowing scientists
to take samples of scales and
measure catches. (C.O.I, photos)
has sufficient elasticity so that the
upper levels of water compress the
lower layers. If the lower water was
not compressed the general sea level
would rise by about 100 feet throughout
the world.
E
N
early 2 million square miles of
land in the coastal regions of
the continents and islands would be
submerged if sea water did not possess
a certain degree of elasticity. Although
much less elastic than gas, sea water
Gold not worth the taking
very ton of sea water contains
about three quarters of a grain
of gold and if all the gold were extract¬
ed from the seas and oceans of the
world there would be available 77,000 lbs
of gold for every single person. Unfor¬
tunately the cost of production of this
gold comes to more than it would be
worth.
Killed by their own weight
Large whales can weigh anything
up to a maximum of 100 tons
and this enormous weight when
suspended in water is consequently re¬
duced in conformity with the principle
of Archimedes. Normally, therefore,
whales are supported by the water and
the muscles which they use for
breathing have no need to be par¬
ticularly strong. But once caught on dry
land their soft underbodies are pressed
down so hard on the unyielding ground
by their own weight that it becomes
impossible for them to breathe, and in
the matter of an hour or so they have
been smothered, not for lack of air, but
for lack of strength to expand their
lungs against their own enormous
weight.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Unesco in pictures
Pupils of Professor J.A. van der Beek have now got used to being beaten on the back, pounded on the chest
Lc«ll*llÍlI¡¿ í O IlCíir and seized by the throat (above). If they utter a sound in response to this apparently rough treatment the
professor, founder of a school for deaf-mute youngsters at Bandung on the island of Java the only one of its
kind in Indonesiais delighted. His cuffings, slaps and strangle-holds are all part of a modern method for teach-
^V Î "í ll Í II C 1 1" CyCS ¡ng children born deaf, and therefore mute, how to speak. The school is now a Unesco Gift Project, so
that people in other lands can help it to obtain vocational materials and teaching aids. (Unesco photos)
Farmers' university
in a reclaimed land
Farmers in Ceylon's barren "dry zone" now being
rapidly reclaimed and resettled have their own
rural university at Minneriya, where Unesco, in
collaboration with the Ceylon Government, has set
up a fundamental education pilot project, with library,
classrooms, workshops and a model farm. Techniques
are being developed and people trained in agricultural
extension work, home economics, cottage industries
and health education. Above, Unesco educator
pulls himself across a river. Left farmers perform
the "winnowing dance". (Unesco photos)
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Np 5. 1955
U. IV. planning
for atomic
power era
A new era of power through atomic energy began on December 4, 1954, when the United
Nations General Assembly agreed on the establishment of a new agency for international co¬
operation in developing the peaceful uses of the atom. On August 8,, 1955, scientific
delegates from some 80 countries will meet in Geneva, to study the technical and scientific factors
involved and to explore the means required to develop atomic power on an international scale.
The preparatory committee of this conference met in Unesco House, Paris on May 23. Dr. H. J.
Bhabha of India, will be President of the Geneva Conference, and Dr. Walter J. Whitman of the
United States (above) has been appointed Secretary-General. (Unations Photo)
»»»I VWWW^
fc,A A^mAákákA***. m m. a a^a^^aa^^^^^^.^
Stamp honours
Unesco's work
Collectors can now add a new
stamp to their United Nations
series. Issued by the United Na¬
tions to honour the work of Unesco
and designed by George Hamori of
Israel, the stamp was placed on
public sale on May II. It is issued
in two denominations: 3 cents and
8' cents. Photo shows Mr. Dag
Hammarskjold, U.N. Secretary-Gen¬
eral, left, presenting a folder of the
new stamps to M. René Maheu,
one of Unesco's Assistant Direc¬
tor-Generals. (Unations Photo)
Letters to
the Editor
Sir,
I have long been a reader of the Unesco
Courier which I find an inexhaustible
source of news and reports from the most
diverse corners of the world. But as I
should like to know more about the habits
and customs of different peoples and to
make contacts in all countries, I should be
grateful if you would help me to make
friends in other lands.
I am Lebanese and I could correspond
equally well in English and Krench. My
hobby is stamp collecting and I am in¬
terested in music, dancing, books and sports.
Anièce Elias
B.P. 30,
Beirut,
Lebanon.
Sir,
I wish to take out a subscription to the
Unesco Courier for a friend of mine, but
I should like to remain anonymous. My
friend is always anxious to increase his
knowledge of the world and it will be a
great pleasure for him to draw from the
Courier that aspect of culture which is
indispensable to all thinking and active
members of mankind.
I appreciate the value of each issue of the
Courier. The one I received today on
"Puppets" seems to be well-filled and the
articles in the previous issue on Latin Ame¬
rica were encouraging. "When one realizes
how many men and women and how many
consciences are working to improve the lot
of disinherited peoples, it is some consola¬
tion for the set-backs of humanity...
M. V.
France.
Sir,
I belatedly ran across the articles on Ja¬
pan in your issue No 4/5, 1954, (Aug-Sept,
U.S.). They were very good. I have always
been interested in Japan, and I was very
intrigued with the girl Michiko Jinuma,
about whom you had a full article. If she
speaks English, I would like very much to
correspond with her. Can you give me her
address? I would appreciate it very much.
I am incidentally a graduate student at the
University of California in Los Angeles.
Alan Campbell.
4108 Bledsoe Avenue,
Los Angeles 66,
California.
No address available - Ed.
Sir,
I have just renewed my subscription and
that of the Esperanto Group in Rochefort
to the Unesco Courier. Personally and on
behalf of the members of our Esperanto
Group, I wish to say with what interest and
pleasure we read the Courier. Our interest
would, of course, be doubled if an Esperanto
edition of the Courier was also published.
Pierre Babin
Chairman,
Groupe Esperantiste Rochefortais,
Rochefort-sur-Mer,
France.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom
Under the un flag:
The UN flag flew at sea for
the first time recently when
two modern deep-sea fishing
trawlersthe first of a. fleet of
ten built by the United Nations
Korean Reconstruction Agency
(UNKRA) to help the recovery
of the Korean fishing industry
sailed from Hong Kong for Pu-
san in Korea. The end of fight¬
ing found Korea which was
formerly one the six foremost
fishing countries of the world
stripped of boats, gear and fish-
packing equipment all essen¬
tial to maintaining the health
of the nation, as 80 % of Kor¬
ea's protein diet depends on
fish products. Under UNKRA's
aid plan ten 77-ton trawlers
costing $500,000 are being built
for the Republic's fishing fleet,
and nets and equipment have
also been bought.
* POPULAR 'PILOTO': One
of the largest and fastest de¬
veloping educational institu¬
tions in the city of Medellin,
Colombia, is the model libra¬
ry set up as a public library
pilot project under Unesco
sponsorship. It is especially
popular with children, who,
it is reported, have waited
in long lines after school
hours in the rain-swept
streets and have even barter¬
ed places with one another
so as to be first into the li¬
brary. "La Piloto", as the
Colombian press calls the li¬
brary, had already outgrown
itself six months after open¬
ing, and the question of a
new building is now being
studied.
LLASS OF 55: Thirty-
two teachers who have received
specialized training in health,
agriculture and community de¬
velopment as well as in primary
school teaching methods will
shortly graduate from the na¬
tional fundamental education
centre, set up in the Liberian
back country by the Govern¬
ment and Unesco. Teachers
will return to their home villa¬
ges scattered throughout Libe¬
ria to run primary schools
which will also be outposts in a
campaign to raise rural living
standards. This national fun¬
damental education centre one
of three now being run in Afri¬
ca and Asia with Unesco tech
nical assistance has succeeded
in opening 19 primary schools
in the surrounding district.
PLACE FOR WOMEN:
Nearly 100,000 Japanese wo¬
men were taking courses in
universities or institutes of
higher education last year a
300 per cent increase on 1947
when Japan's new education
law came into force. The
fact that three out of every
hundred girls aged between
19 and 22 now attend univer¬
sities or similar institutions
has led to the creation of
many new educational estab¬
lishments and of openings
for women teachers. There
are now, for instance, some
ISCrheadmistresses of primary
and secondary schools, while
more than 2,000 women serve
on educational committees.
Many Japanese housewives
attend university-organized
summer schools, as well as
family welfare courses.
Global aid plan :
Direct aid, ranging from the ser¬
vices of specialists in cosmic
rays, nuclear physics and the
teaching of social sciences, to
the development of national li¬
braries and the organization of
educational television will be gi¬
ven to 41 countries this year by
Unesco. Nearly $800,000 have
been allocated under a new pro¬
gramme voted by Unesco's Gen¬
eral Conference last December
to cover projects in education,
science and culture in 41 mem¬
ber states, associate members
and non self-governing territo¬
ries. In all, 69 experts are to
be sent out, 46 fellowships
awarded, and 541,000 worth of
equipment provided over the
next 20 months.
* MEET THE U.N: Visitors
to U.N. Headquarters in New
York now also see some¬
thing of the Organization in
action in faraway places
through a special one-hour
programme "Introduction
to the United Nations" de¬
signed to acquaint the pub¬
lic with Ihe U.N.'s aims,
structure and work. It in¬
cludes film-showings, a lec¬
ture and a question and ans¬
wer period. More than 1,000
of the three to four thousand
daily visitors to U.N. can
thus see, for example, how
Philippine efforts to raise
health and educational stan¬
dards are aided by the World
Health Organization and by
Unesco and how the U.N. is
helping to prepare Somali-
land for self-government.
The MISSING FIFTH :
More than a fifth of -food crops
planted by the world's farmers
never reaches the dinner table.
The Food and Agriculture Or¬
ganization (FAO) reports that
insect pests and diseases des¬
troy or seriously damage this
much of plantings each year.
Knowledge of control measures
is, however, increasing, but
there is a new threat of pests
and diseases being spread more
easily from one continent to an¬
other because of improved and
faster international transport.
FAO experts are helping many
countries to organize or expand
control programmes.
SHARING THE ATOM:
A link in the chain of inter¬
national co-operation for the
peaceful use of atomic ener¬
gy was forged at Oak Ridge
Institute of Nuclear Studies,
U.S.A. recently wh$n the
first of a series of classes
for scientists from different
countries began to study
how to handle radio-isotopes.
Thirty-one scientists from
21 countries will attend the
four-week courses at Oak
Ridge. Previous American
and Foreign graduates from
this Institute already are ap¬
plying their training to a
wide range of projects from
cancer therapy to experi¬
ments in the preservation of
perishable food. (See the
Unesco Courier "The Pro¬
mise of Atomic Power",
N°. 12, 1954).
GlVE-AND-TAKE: Tar¬
ascan Indians in the Mexican
State of Michoacan recently
learned some useful lessons
from Pakistani teachers who
were studying fundamental edu¬
cation work in and around Lat¬
in America on a one-year
Unesco fellowship and the
Pakistanis picked up some new
educational techniques for use
back home. One result of their
visit is that some Tarascan In¬
dian families are no longer sleep¬
ing on traditional floor mats,
but on Pakistani charpeys
simple wooden beds with mat¬
tresses made of woven strings.
And Indian fishermen on Lake
Patzcuaro have learned tljat
their nets will last three times
as long if they dip them in the
juice of a certain plant. The
ten Pakistani educators, agricul¬
tural experts and social workers
spent eight months at Unesco's
Regional Fundamental Educa¬
tion Centre for Latin America
at Patzcuaro, Mexico, and also
watched rural development cam¬
paigns in both Puerto Rico and
Jamaica.
* THROUGH THE LENS:
The world of photography
recently went on display in
Paris at what was probably
the most comprehensive in¬
ternational event of its kind
ever held the first Biennial
of Photography, Cinema and
Optics. A series of exhibi¬
tions demonstrated world
progress in photography and
motion pictures, and the
French National Commission
for Unesco sponsored meet¬
ings where leading scien¬
tists, educators, artists and
others who use photography
in their work exchanged
ideas and discussed needs
and the means of meeting
them with experts in photo¬
graphy. The Biennial show¬
ed how developed photogra¬
phy is today as a universal
art form and how important
it is for communicating ideas
and information.
European equals:
Nine countries Denmark, Fran¬
ce, the German Federal Repu¬
blic, Iceland, Ireland, Luxem¬
bourg, Norwaj*, the Saar and
the United Kingdom have
now ratified the -«European Con¬
vention on the* equivalence of
university entrance examin¬
ations. Drawn up by the
Council of Europe in 1953, the
Convention gives 'students who
have passed the entrance exa¬
minations to a university in any
one of the nine signatory nations
an equal right with nationals to
enter a university in one of the
other countries.
Unesco's National Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER can be
obtained ore listed below. Other Unesco
Distributors are listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P.O.
Box 244, Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen, K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
Ethiopia : International Press Agency,
P.O.B. 120, Addis-Ababa.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, 1 9, Avenue
Kléber, Paris- I 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb für Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Librairie H. Kau ffman, 28, Rue
du Stade, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India ¡Orient Longmans Ltd., Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
& Stationery Co., Scindia House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Hima¬
laya House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NV.,
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iran : Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road, P.O. Box 5154. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldings.
Japan : Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J.I. Bahous and Co., Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Korea : Korean National Commission for
Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
Liberia : J. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
Malayan Federation and Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 135,
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kingsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout 9. The Hague.
New Zealand: Unesco Publications Centre
100, Hackthorne Rd., Christchurch.
Nigeria : C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S ,Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass, 7,
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs. 3.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1 1 04 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila. 3.00
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A.B. CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hov-
bokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand : Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London S.E.I.
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Service, 475
5th Ave., New York 17, N.Y.
U
Z
z
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
urn Courier
A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
DONT MISS THESE
FUTURE ISSUES
HOW NATIONS SEE THE FOREIGNER
How the French farmer sees the stranger. A Britisher looks at Americans.
A Britisher dissects British character, etc. Do you have to live among people
to know or understand them?
MAN AND THE DESERT. - An exciting
60-page issue on the latest world-wide efforts
to make the desert bloom. Developments in
solar energy, wind energy, fresh water from
sea, soilless cultivation, artificial rain-making,
myths about the tropics, old rain gods of
primitive peoples.
WELCOME STRANGER. - International
fellowships and exchange of people
between countries as one of the most
powerful roads to building peace and
international understanding. Unesco's
exchange programme. Student and tea¬
cher exchange, workers abroad.
WHAT'S WRONG WITH OUR
TEXT-BOOKS? Distortion of his¬
tory in school books. Textbook
publishinga great unknown indus¬
try.
SUBSCRIBE TO THE UNESCO COURIER TODAY. - English, French, Spanish, U.S. editions
ONE FULL YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION AT THE AMAZINGLY LOW PRICE OF :
300 French francs; 6/-; $1.50 or equivalent in local currency (U.S. edition $2.50).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
kj-p1 «t..:
ROCKS "HUNG IN THE AIR"
One of the strangest sights in the world is the
Meteora, a forest of gigantic black rocks rising out
of the plain of Thessaly, north of Athens. In medie»
val times, ascetics chose the Meteora, a name
which means "hung in the air", as a place of retreat
and built great monasteries on the craggy pinnacles.
For a story on their history and the religious
art, which is preserved in them, see page 4.
(Photo Spyros Meletzis, Athens.)
.<** '"a
m
f ;'P'^|!Ä fite1 > -
:-fr ¿ fM! wm Ml t»V %**
]]>
</page>
</document>
