<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068941eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
NEWCOMER TO PARIS
Three famous landmarks and a newcomer
to the Paris scene are shown in this photo
of Unesco's permanent headquarters being
built on the left bank of the Seine. Beyond
Unesco Conference Bui) ding (foreground)
and Secretariat Building are th Military
College (18th century) ; the E : ffei Tower
(987 feet high ; built t88 !/90) and,
across the Seine, gteaming twin semi-
circular wings of the Palais de Chaillot,
constructed in ! 937. (See page 46)
UNESCO-Louise de Bea
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Vol. X-No. 6 DECEMBER 1956
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
6 WITH THESE TWO HANDS...
12 FROM DREAM TO PLAN OF ACTION
By Ritchie Calder
14 FACING THE HAVOC OF WAR
20 TWO PEOPLE OUT OF THREE
24 A HUMAN APPROACH TO PROGRESS
26 250, 000, 000 CHILDREN WITHOUT SCHOOLS
30 PUBLISHER IN 28 TONGUES
31 FULL AND EQUAL RIGHTS FOR WOMEN
32 REDUCING TENSIONS AND PREJUDICE
34 FREE FLOW OF DEAS-UNESCO'S KEY WORDS
37 PATHS OF KNOWLEDGE FOR ALL PEOPLES
39 ENDING THE WORLD'S COPYRIGHT MUDDLE
40 THE EXPANDING FRONTIERS OF SCIENCE
45 NOT JUST PREACHING PEACE... BUILDING IT
46 NEW UNESCO H. Q. RISES IN PARIS
50 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
*
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cukura) Organization
Editorial Offices
Uneseo, 19. Avenue K) eber, Paris, t 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Desien
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation
Jean Greffier
*
The UNESCO COURIER'S United States of America edition, printed in Paris,
France, is published monthly by the Department of Mass Communication
of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, United
Nations Building. New York 17. N. Y. and is distributed by the UNESCO
Publication Center, U. S. A., 152 West 42nd Street, New York 36 N. Y.,
Pennsylvania 6-0851. Annual subscription price is 82. 50. Seeond-c) ass mait
privileges authorized ac New York, N. Y.
Individual articles not copyrighted may be reprinted by permission from THE
COURIER accompanied by the fof) owing credit tine :"Reprinted from UNESCO
COUR) ER." Reprinted signed articles must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscriptS cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter-
national reply coupon covering postage.
represent the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent te opinions ouf Unesco or those of the editors.
The Unesco Courier
COVER PHOTO
Children shown on the cover are dwarfed
by the huge world globe at the Babson
Institute of Business Administration,
Wellesley, Massachusetts, U. S. A.
Photo by Roy F. Whitehouse,
copyright Babson Institute.
éTHER humanity has progressed or not since thevend of the last w r is a question that bothers
few people. Most of us are quite happy to note
merely that we have survived. Others again, without very
good reason, think progress a matter of course and like
to consider that if humanity scored, for example, 12 marks
at any given moment, it deserves 14 or 15 marks a decade
later. But do they ever stop to define the basis of such
an evaluation, or to explain the total out of which the
marks have been given ?
There is, in truth, no universally acceptable measure of
progress. Nobody believes that men become more hand-
some or wiser over the years, and nobody can tell whether
they are becoming happier. Increases in comforts can be
lightly dismissed as irrelevant in this context. Only one
kind of progress seems incontrovertible : the increase in
the fund of knowledge, either as discovered by research,
or as acquired through education. Knowledge alone will
permit humanity to advance gradually-or perhaps at an
accelerated pace-in areas that still appear to remain
stagnant and that still appear to be closed to it : along the
paths of justice, of peace and of intelligence.
UNESCO is an"Organization for education, science and
culture"which happens to have been founded just ten
years ago. One may therefore appropriately enquire, at
this point, what it has achieved so far. Have education,
science and culture gone ahead during the past decade ?
That science has progressed is beyond doubt-as wit-
ness atomic energy, chemistry, aeronautics and so on. Are
scientists more numerous ? Are they better
at their jobs ? Certainly. Research centres, C ; øøt'd
in particular, have multiplied, the network on
b.. 1 1 nextþøgeof laboratories is more closely woven, more
3
M   L   ! 
11NESC0'S FIRST
TEN YEARS
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
BIRTHPLACE. Under the bombs battering London, the
Ministers of Education of the Allied Governments met to
plan the rehabilitation of educational systems in occupied
or war-devastated areas. Following these deliberations,
representatives of forty-four countries met in London in
November i 945 and there drew up Unesco's Constitution.
TEMPORARY HOME for Unesco since November 1946
has been the Hotel Majestic, in the Avenue Kleber, Paris-one
of twelve great avenues radiating like the spokes of a wheel
from the Place de I'Etoile. Here, Unesco officially came
into existence on November 4, 1946, with 20 member
states. Today it has seventy-seven member nations.
UNESCO'S FIRST
TEN YEARS
(Continued)
ample. Every discovery is the joint work of hundreds ;
the names of one or two individuals become generally
known, the rest remain anonymous.
What about education and culture ? This is harder to
say since humanity as a whole cannot be asked to sit for
an examination. Yet there are thousands of new schools,
many new universities, millions of adults have learned to
read, thousands of tons of books cross frontiers in every
direction. Statistics can. reveal whether there are more
art exhibitions, whether concerts are more popular and
their programmes more varied, whether architectural
monuments are held in greater respect. Ultimately,
however, it is the historians who are the most competent
juges. Given a century's retrospect, they will be able to
4
tell us whether our con-
temporaries have worked
diligently towards the im-
provement of the world.
If-as today we sincere-
ly hope-they can reach
a favourable verdict, they
will not have done so be-
cause of a few isolated
heroes. Progress will not
be credited to one person,
one nation or even one
organization. It will be de-
scribed in collective terms
such as"scientists","phi-
losophy"or"television"and also by the name of UNESCO.
in the same manner in which it is already referred to here.
For in this text it is ubiquitous : one reads of what
UNESCO has undertaken, whom it has brought together. all
of which refers to no reality independent, or outside of
the particular task or meeting. The term"UNESCO"is
simply a shorthand way of describing groups of men and
women, or governments, or associations of scientists, artists,
JULIAN HUXLEY
Director-General of Unesco
from 1946 tao 1948
Copyright Keystone.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
UNESCO PERMANENT HEADQUARTERS, now under construc-
tion near the Eiffel Tower on Paris's Left Bank, includes a
seven-storey, Y-shaped structure and a low, trapezoidal
conference building. When site, which covers seven and a
half acres, is completed in 1957, its architecture will add
a new, modern landmark to the French capital. (See page 46)
teachers, and, occasionally, of certain nations as a whole.
This issue offers a picture of the very wide range of
activities of which first 20, then 50 and finally 77 States
have decided to make a success by pooling their needs and
resources. UNESCO is one of their tools. Neither the
work it does nor the ideas it spreads belong to anybody
in particular.
One might be tempted
to think that it is a matter
of charity meted out by a
supra-national philanthro-
pist to the grateful masses,
but nothing could be more
misleading. The peoples
help themselves. UNESCO's
aid to education ? You
will find that certain coun-
tries have found the ne-
cessary funds, launched
campaigns, built schools,
trained teachers-and per-
haps thanked three or four
international civil servants.
UNESCO contributes to nu-
dear research ? The fact
is that 12 European gov-
rnments have decided to
construct and finance an
international laboratory.
So it continues.
It is true that govern-
ments, scientists and scho-
lars who execute this work
occasionally make refer-
ence to principles or an
ideal which they attribute
to UNESCO. But after all,
they were themselves the
creators of UNESCO. They claim now to derive inspira-
tion from it principles, but these are no doubt their own
most basic ambitions, which UNESCO embodies and main-
tains alive whatever the circumstances.
Let us then speak of"the peoples"rather than of
"UNESCO". And let us think of UNESCO as an aim, an
ideal. It has been put in the service of peace and
progress ; about that, no quarrels are possible.
5
LUTHER H. EVANS
Director-General
since 953
UNESC--= :. ÝorOntloff
JAIME TORRES BODET
Director-Genera)
from 1949 to 1952
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
WITH THESE
TWO RANDS...
2, 600 MILLION PEOPLE must somehow live together and share the resources of the earth.
To an extent which might have seemed inconceivable ven 50 years ago, there has come increasing
realization that the general impoverishment of any area is a matter of vital concern to all areas.
6
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
WITH THESE HANDS (Conf
MEN STRUGGLING TO SURVIVE cannot be expected to regard literacy as an end in itself. Unesco has linked the three"Rs"to the needs
of the illiterate adult-to farming, to the need for better crops, better food, better health and sanitation, in a plan of education labelled"fundamental
education. Today it is being put into practice in many parts of the world with the participation of governments and United Nations Agencies
such as the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), the World Health Organization (WHO) and the International Labour Organization (ILO).
UNATIONS
UNESCG
NOT BY BREAD ALONE does man live. Man also needs the beauty found in line and form and style and music
and poetry. And it is the appreciation of the creative work of others, revealing to him the best that is in his fellow-
men, that Unesco has helped to promote for the past ten years, in the fields of literature, drama, music and art.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
U4ESCO
SHARING OF SKILLS is stressed in aid now being given to economically underdeveloped countries.
Industries are sprouting everywhere but they need skilled workers, foremen, engineers and research scien-
tists. Here, dozens of scientific documents all on a single spool of microfilm, are packed for shipping at
Mexican Documentation Centre, set up with Unesco help, and now serving the whole of Latin America.
CO, I.. London
IN THE SEA there is far more lifte and food than on land yet the
oceans provide only a small fraction of man's food. Plankton from
the sea's depths is one of the great unexploited food resources.
Unesco's Advisory Committee on Marine Sciences is hopeful that
research may eventually lead to its addition to the human diet.
UNESCO
WOMEN OF ALL LANDS are increasingly
offered the newest means of learning, as Unesco
helps to make a reality of the ideal, enshrined in
its Constitution, that all shall have"equality of
educational opportunity without regard to race,
sexor any other distinctions, economic or socia !".
Press Information Bureau. Govt. of India
THE POWER OF THE SUN is a source of
energy into which research is being carried out
in many countries. A semple, sun-ray oven for
cooking food was devised during Indian experi-
ments aimed at solving the desert fuel shortage.
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
WITH THESE HANDS (Confd ;
UNATIONS
THE ATOM showed only an evil face for almost ten years. Today, as a result of international co-operation through the United Nations and Unesco,
it has begun to show a happier one. Atoms-for-peace research has made possible new benefits in medical treatment (left) in industry and agri-
culture. A great new research laboratory at Geneva will soon explore the heart of the atom for 12 European countries as a result of Unesco's efforts.
Right, remote control tongs handle radio-active materiats at recent"Atoms-for-peace"exhibition, organized by the United Nations at Geneva.
USIS
NEEDS OF NATIONS, from elementary vocational instruction to
the training of petroleum geologists, are being met by more than
200 educators and scientists working for Unesco. In 48 countries,
they are carrying out Unesco's share in the U. N. world programme of
technical assistance, demonstrating how education and scientific
research can help to shatter the vicious circle of poverty and ignorance.
UNESCO
LIFE-GIVING WATER for a
parched region. Scientists esti-
mate that one-quarter of the
earth's surface is desert. Devel-
opment of the arid lands is one
answer to the world's increasing
need for food. Unesco's continu-
ing programme of research and
co-ordination is helping scient-
ists and governments to explore
many aspects of the problem.
Renié Zuber
FREE ACCESS TO NEWS
and ideas has been called the
touchstone of all freedoms.
Unesco has promoted"the free
flow of ideas by word and image"
by working to eliminate censor-
ship, reduce tariff barriers to
information materials, press and
cable rates, the newsprint short-
age, and by helping to build up
inadequate information facilities
in under-developed countries.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
II
The Unesco Courier
TO 7, 000, 000 BLIND
throughout the world the
Braille alphabet of raised
symbols is the most powerful
key to human freedom and
scholarship ever devised.
Yet the existence of dozens
of variations of Brailla have
seriously hampered Braille
book production. Unifica-
tion of Braille alphabets is
one of tasks which Unesco
has already completed.
UNESCO
USIS
APPRECIATION OF THE ARTS should begin in
chi) dhood, yet in very few countries have art and music
played an adequate part in the regular school curriculum.
Unesco has brought creative artists and educators toge-
ther to see how this can be brought about, and has helped
the creation of international societies which aim to
foster education through music and also the plastic arts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
 ( ;  ; f, ;,,}, , ;, :,, ;, (,. ; :  ;, :, :'" :,", > J, : :
' :,'' ; {< f <t'1 ?  :  :' ? å\
by Ritchie Calder
Os a recent visit to UNESCO's Paris headquarters, I
made a sentimental journey through the back
streets which we, as delegates to the First General
Conference of UNESCO, ten years ago, had used as a short-
cut from our hotel to the Avenue Kleber. I did not
recognise them. I remembered them as much more
romantic. Now, they were just ordinary, with the paving
stones hard underfoot.
Then I realised that it was not the streets but I who
had changed. In 1946, we paced those pavements in the
company O'f our dreams, talking of all the aspirations that
we were trying to write into the programme of UNESCO.
And all the other delegates, from all the other countries,
. rom all over the world, were likewise walking and talking
and projecting their dreams of what UNESCO should do.
The result was a profession of faith but scarcely a pro-
gramme of action. For we wished on to the infant orga-
nisation every rose-tinted reverie ar. d high-minded hope
and we made life difficult for UNESCO. Yet we were well-
meaning. Remember that we were at the end O'f a
ruthless war which had threatened to destroy our civili-
zation, which had distorted the minds of men with
hatreds and blinded them to the beauties of our common
heritage. Then, exultantly, we saw'''Mankind's Second
Chance."Out of the ruins we came as bearers of embar-
rassing gifts to the cradle of this offspring of the United
Nations ideal.
When, at the end of that conference, some of us woke
up to what we had done (and left undone), I said,"We
have made UNESCO the gift of the entire empyrean, of all
the stars of the firmament, when all that it needed was a
few navigational stars by which to chart its course."
GOVERNMENTS, more realistic than most of their dele-gates, put a price on the dreams we peddled, and it
was not high. But even if it had been ten, or a
hundred times as much, UNESCO still could not have given
substance to our ambitions. Our difficulties were manifest
in the language we had perforce to use : UNESCO, as an
intergovernmental agency, could not have power to execute
and was not given adequate resources to simplement ; so we
had to resort to words like initiate ; stimulate ; facilitate or
investigate.
One example springs to mind : A proposal that UNESCO,
to counteract misleading propaganda and to spread
truth,, culture and understanding, should have its
own world-wide radio network, with its own stations and
its own programmes, penetrating everywhere. Apart
from political difficulties, the broadcasting realists esti-
mated that the project would cost $1, 000, 000, 000 and that
it would take years to build a listening audience. So the
best we could do was to stimulate existing networks with
any facilities which UNESCO might provide and investigate
the radio needs of various countries.
It was the same in other spheres as well. We had
written into the Charter :"Since wars begin in the minds
of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of
peace must be constructed."And we meant it. But there
were 2, 500 million minds in the world. More than half
the population could not read nor write and more than
half the children of school-age had no schools to which
to go. Over 200 countries and territories had different
educational systems-some good, some indifferent and
some barely existing. In the mood in which we were in
in 1946, we would have liked to have given a tutor to
every child !
As one of those"Olympians"of 1946, I came down to
12
earth sooner than most. I shared the chastening experi-
ence of the second conference in Mexico City, when we
started pruning our ambitions and forming a more realis-
tic plan of action. But I did not suffer the disillusion-
ment which comes to dreamers because in the intervening
years, I had the opportunities of an independent observer
o'f seeing the realities of the practical work which UNESCO
can do. I have seen its work in the deserts, in the jungle,
and in the lands which had been forgotten. I have seen
it at work among the common people, just as I have seen
its value to the uncommon people-the educationists, the
scientists, the thinkers and the aesthetes.
TOUR aspirations, in more commonplace attire, have
had to"work for their living"but, from my salutary
experience, I have found the quiet work of devoted
people in the field more rewarding than the resounding
phrases of the conference room.
For instance, ten years ago"fundamental education"
was an unfamiliar concept. We talked about"creating
the climate of literacy"-making an illiterate adult world
sympathetic to the education of the young. A noble
object, but how ?
Today,"fundamental education"promoted by UNESCO
is a working practice. The object, and the example, of
centres like Chao Choeng Sao, in Thailand, and Sirs-el-
Layyan, in the Nile Delta, is to spread"fundamental edu-
cation". And they do. People, even though they are
illiterate, are taught the benefits of knowledge. Men and
women are taught how to till their fields better ; how to
care for the health of themselves and their children ; how
to look after their homes and so'forth.
In learning, they improve their conditions and their
knowledge. Then they want their children to know more
and want schools for them. And they want schools for
themselves and the elements of adult education. The
experience of this sort of thing derives out of the people
and their circumstances-like the singing teacher of
CREFAL, the Fundamental Education Training Centre'for
Latin America, who goes around the villages with her
guitar, singing her instructions in lively, rousing fashion.
Governments have turned to UNEsco not only for experts
to help set up schools, introduce technical and adult
education, and provide radio-teaching for people remote
from schools, but, as in the case of Yugoslavia, for help
in reorganising the educational systems of six republics.
os the first time in the history of mankind-because
UNESCO exists-the picture of the needs of education,
the geography of ignorance, has at last been drawn,
exchange not only of personnel but of experience is
constantly taking place and the'''plan of action"can be
implemented. Principles we discussed in 1946 are be-
ing put into practice.
The"S"of UNESCO stands for"Science". Even ten years
ago we were eminently practical about the"S". The
"Commonwealth of Science", the indispensible exchange
of scientific knowledge, existed before the war in the form
of the international congresses of the many disciplines o'f
science. The machinery of exchanges had, of course,
ceased with hostilities but UNESCO was able to provide
funds--'- :"lubricating oil, not even fuel oil"-which restored
the functions of the congresses and helped to create
international scientific bodies, where needed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Again there was CERN, the European Centre for Nuclear
Research at Geneva. This is costing 200, 000, 000 Swiss
francs-'far more than Unesco could provide. But UNESCO
inspired it, and twelve governments agreed to co-operate
and finance this vital enterprise which will give them-
and the world-the benefit of the"know-why"of the
atomic nucleus, repository of the energy which can be
turned to peaceful uses.
There is the Arid Zone Project. I confess to a personal
"stake"in this because five years ago, at UNESCO's request,
I did a reconnaissance of the problems of desert research
in a tour of the deserts of North A'frica and the Middle
East. But, since then, I have seen UNESCO's work on
desert hydrology, plant ecology, human and animal eco-
logy, wind and solar energy and climatology. A lot of
"-ology", some may say, but it is the information amassed
from experience and research all over the world which
will enable deserts to be wisely developed and produce
sustenance for the world's multiplying population.
And here is one dream which is coming true. I thought
I was dreaming when a French scientist with whom I vas
trudging knee-deep in burning sand in the Sahara said,
"Monsieur Calder, we are walking on water !" Either I
was dreaming or he was suffering from the cafard that
madness which overtakes those who are too long exposed
UNESCO
to the desert. That I was not dreaming and that he was
not mad is confirmed by the reports to UNESCO.
Under our feet was a great fresh-water reservoir, the
nodular sandstone layer of the Albienne Nappe of which
subsequent reports said :"It is now known that in a broad
belt running north and south under the Sahara, it is
possible for artesian wells to be sunk. We can create
man-made oases wherever there is a sufficient area of
cultivable land in the vast dead valleys... And so it shall
be that we will bring life to a howling desert..."
And the desert shall blossom as the rose... A dream
that will become a reality, to be added to many other
achievements of UNEsco, the more significant perhaps
because they are unsung. The help to restore the war-
ravaged schools, museums and libraries ; the conventions
to protect the ancient monuments which are the heritage
of all mankind ; the convention on copyright ; the World
Survey of Education ; the cultural and scientific history of
mankind ; the constant exchange of peoples to learn and
to teach and the manifold activities which are lighting
lamps of understanding throughout the world.
Out of those dreams of 1946 a plan of action has
emerged. From that firmament of stars, UNESCO has
found the stars by which to steer and it will be judged not
by our past hopes but by its future achievements.
13
The Uncsco Courir
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
GREEN TRAGEDY. Naine years ouf continuos warfare in Greece
fond te country with 380, 000 orphans (nearly one-eighth of
lits children) ad 7, 625 oust ouf 10, 000 schools destroyer or badly
damage. Suffering between 1944 ad 1949 wus perhaps even
greater tan rit ha ben dring te previous fouir years. Over
700, 000 Greens ha tao bye evaq. latex (somme ouf hem bey sera,
aboie) froc te war-torn northern province. Governments
and national and international voluntary organizations came
forward with ait, ad Unesco, concentrating on educational
reconstruction, launched appels :"te refuges children need
schools, teachers, ad equipment."In 1947, scientific equip-
muent ad educational material worth :- ; 300, 000 wus suent to
Greece. Schools ère rebuilt ad equipped with Unesco's
ait ad with te fundus rit received froc mamy countries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
I'J years ago, on Novem-
ben 4, ils. t (), the agrce-
T mcnt founding a United
'i at ion s Educational,
M Scientific and Cultural
Organization was rat died
hv 20 states and came
into force. Scholars,
philosophers and artists
greeted this event with a warmth never
before displayed in connexion with an
official body."I have faith in our
UNESCO", said Leon Blum,"because 1
have faith in peace and humanity".
The poet Archibald MacLeish declared :
"This will prove a great and powerful
instrument for the broadest possible
purpose, the purpose of the common
understanding of man for peace."
Born as bombs fell
y T NESCO was begotten by war, andborn during a war. Beneath the
bombs falling on London, the edu-
cation ministers of the Allied countries
dreamt of a world organization devoted
to co-operation and reason. In 1945,
they stated :"Since wars begin in the
minds of men, it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be con-
structed."They then went on to affirm
that"the wide diffusion of culture and
the education of humanity for justice
and liberty and peace are indispensable
to the dignity of man and constitute a
sacred duty which all the nations must
fulfil in a spirit of mutual assistance
and concern". This was their con-
clusion :"The peace must therefore be
founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of
mankind."
Ruins and ration-books
A T that moment, the concentrationcamps in Europe had ot yet dis-
gorged all their surviving inmates,
and starving children still roamed the
streets. In Asia, the silence of death
hung over Hiroshima since August 6,
1945, over Nagasaki since August 8.
The war was over but the peoples were
emerging from it slowly, still inhaling
the cinders of destruction.
In battered London, the ministers
wrote :"The purpose of the Organization
is to contribute to peace and security by
promoting collaboration among the
nations through education, science and
culture in order to further universal
respect for justice, for the rule of law
and for the human rights and funda-
mental freedoms, without distinction ouf
race, sex, language or religion."
Hence in t946, the Organisation was
in being, recogni/. aCCDIl1Illodatcd with
its own budget and secrctaiiat : its ser-
vices in thc cause of international eduea-
tiona !, scientific and cultural coiiabora-
tion were expected. At first, unhappi-
11'little Cl1lllld be achieved. It was an
area ot ruins. ot emergency measures and
of ration-books for a good two-thirds of
the world. Frontiers remained seaied,
or else the nations locked themsclves
into tight power blocs inaccessible from
the outside. In the circumstances,
material considerations took first placé.
Furthermore, the resources of the
fledgling UNESCO seemed tiny when
measured against its world-wide ambi-
tions and in relation to the universal
chaos. Its budget was derided as"less
than the sum spent every year to clean
New York City's subway system". Could
this institution really claim to advance
"the mutual understanding and know-
ledge of nations ?" Was this the ideal
The Unesco Cour rcr
moment to talk of poputar cducatiun,
the spreading otcutture and to promise
heip in"the advancement and diffusion
of knowledge"') Not a few wei !-
meaningsouts preferred to picture the
future in terms of decline and tenor,
and to visualize the Apucalypse.
No rose-coloured future
M EANWHILF, those. who were respon-sable for the first of UNESCO's
tasks also explained calmly that
they were working for the future. No
doubt this was neither a rosy nor a par-
ticularly easy prospect, but rewarding in
effort and potentiel. In other words,
these pioneers beHeved in progress. It is
a faith that allows poor resources and
enormous tasks to be lucidly faced.
At the very outset, in the autumn of
1946, the first Director-General of
UNESCO, Julian Huxley,
defined the Organiza-Cont'd
tion's mission by referen-on
ce to this faith, which at next page
UNATIOI'. iS
KOREAN EXODUS from battle areas in 1950 and 1951 uprooted millions of men, women
children, and created vast emergency food, shelter and relief problems. Since then, the people of
Korea and the peoples of the United Nations have embarked on long-range reconstruction pro-
gramme under direction of UNKRA (U. N. Korean Reconstruction Agency). Restoration of edu-
cational facilities lost during war-33°, of primary schools, 60% of classrooms, 80% of books and
equipment-ranks high in reconstruction programme. Unesco missions surveyed and outlined the
enormous needs and prepared five-year educational rehabilitation plan. Unesco sought"first aid"
for 100 of neediest Korean primary schools by means of its Gift Coupon Scheme, through which
chi ! dren ah over the world helped to provide schools and equipment for Korean youngsters. Today,
Korean schools receive a steady stream of textbooks from the new National Textbook Printing
Plant built at Yong Dong Po through combined efforts of UNKRA, Unesco and the Republic of
Korea Government. This modern plant is geared to produce 30 billion textbooks a year.
i5
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
FACING THE
HAVOC
(Continued)
out minds are like
parched earth'
once excludes easy downheartedness and
false hope :"not a myth but a doctrine
of progress", as he put it.
Critics tried to class the Organization
as a more or less technical body tied to
particular political policies or ideologies.
Huxley rose to this challenge, too.
The goal was to be the evolution of
humanity ; Unesco would make its influ-
ence felt in every field of tea-
ching and intellectual endea-
vour, its utility based precisely
upon its universality."Mean-
while", said Huxley,"any-
thing that can be done to in-
crease the interpenetration of
traditions and their fruitful
union in a common pool will
help, and is itself assuredly
a prerequisite of full progress.
In this light, the work of
UNESCO appears as an essen-
tial intervention at a parti-
cular stage during man's
evolution."
In point of fact, such in-
fluence began by being ten-
tative because the general
trend of events seemed to
indicate at least a slight re-
cession in the tide of human
progress. Twelve nations had
gutted universities, pilfered
libraries, ruined schools and
sacked laboratories to show
as evidence of"cultural dif-
fusion". In order to diffuse
something, one needs a cer-
tain number of props ; books,
for example.
In the first place, therefore,
UNESCO had to undertake the
job of reconstruction, of
make-do and of salvaging.
Appeals for help went out,
donations were pooled and distributed.
From Canada came books for the Orient,
from Great Britain microfilm equipment.
from the United States tons of school
material. Laboratory apparatus was sent
to China, Greece, the Philippines, Poland
and Czechoslovakia. Everything possi-
ble was done, but by 1949, certain things
still appeared to be irreplaceable.
Schools and books had been hard hit
by the war : some belligerents had, indeed,
16
marked them down for destruc-
tion. These words by Stephen Vincent
Benet used to be repeated in 1949 :
"When they burned the books, that was
the beginning, but we didn't know it
until later."The catalogue of loss
was full enough : libraries razed in
Manila, Caen, Louvain, Milan, London,
Shanghai : 537 Czech libraries pillaged
minds are like parched earth."In the
parcels, preserved foods hegan to give
way to scientific works : in one year.
over $1. 000, 000 worth of books were
sent out to help many countries.
Graduaify. UNESCO began to arrange
its reconstruction work along lines that
would allow for more general partici-
SMASHED LABORATORtES and burned-out universities were left
to mark the trail of war's red-hot rake across Europe and Asia. One
of Unesco's first activities therefore was to join in the tremendous job
of salvage and reconstruction. It dug out facts on the most urgent needs
of schools and universities and created its own emergency aid fund
(later replaced by the Unesco Gift Coupon Scheme). Photo shows
equipment in electro-technical department of Vienna's Institute of
Technology-one of institutes aided by Unesco's Scientific Reconstruc-
tion Programme. Here, dummy telegraph pole holds sample insulator
being tested for use on power lines throughout Austria to eliminate
radio static. Large spheres are part of 750, 000 volt transformer.
from the attic to the cellars ; not a single
Polish book left in Poland.
By signing an agreement with a body
which had hitherto concentrated exclu-
sively on distributing millions of food
parcels, UNESCO drew attention to the
fact that intellectual and physical famine
go hand in hand. The president of
the Meiji Gakuin College in Tokyo
wrote back :"We have been cut off from
the rest of the world so long that our
By the time that the needs of
war-ravaged countries seemed
to have become slightly less
urgent, still-required aid began
to come from more humble
sources : the pockets of
schoolchildren. who used
their savings to purchase
"Gift Coupons". Thanks to
such anonymous generosity
thousands of douars coJlected
in 18"donor"countries a)-
lowed schools in 46 states or
territories to buy looks os
apparatus. But the Important
thing, said the organizers. IS
to establish friendiy links.
Can u then be said thaï.
after the first two or three
years, reconstruction became
superfluous ? Nos <tll. for des-
truction had not ceased.
In Greece, nine years ül
continuous fighting ! ett thou-
sands of school buildings in
ruins. Unesco launched re-
peated appeals :"Refugee chil-
dren from the northern Greek
provinces lack schools, tea-
chers and educational mat-
eriaL."In Palestine, there
were eight or nine hundred
thousand refugees and later
over 1, 000, 000. The proh-
lem of displaced persons
appeared again, and called
for even more radical mea-
sures than before. LJNRWA (United Nu.
tions Relief and \Xl arks Agency) supplied
flood, clothes and shelter ; it continues to
function, thus keeping alive an entire
community.
These 900, 000 men, women and child-
ren, however, must live and not merely
exist. They must find
means of subsistence, but Cont'd
also an aim in life. For on
. h'l'page/8
refugees w 1 mg away a
\.. ; >  sea
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
rh, lIll" ('I ( (illlll !
BATTERED BOOKS and empty shelves
from Manila to Milan and from Louvain to
Shanghai revealed war losses of libraries
both from the effects of bombs and shells and
through the depredations of men. In Czecho-
slovakia, 537 libraries were completely
pillaged ; in Poland, not a single Polish book
remained. Unesco helped to restock the
ravaged shelves. In co-operation with other
organizations it arranged the distribution of
more than  1, 000, 000 worth of books in a
single year. In France, where total library
iosseswereestimatedatmorethans6. 000. 000
bomb-damaged library of the small Normandy
town of Valognes (above, left and right)
symbolized the plight of thousands throughout
the ! d. Vaiognes was saved through an
appeal by Unesco to the ! nternationa ! Work
Camp movement. In 1950, 3S Danish and
Swedish students (left) spent a summer
ho ! iday cleaning and repairing its books.
ncluding 16th and 17th century treasures.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
FACING THE
HAVOC
(Continued)
H u ma n ity/5'c u Itu ra
Red Cross'
forccd c\ile in camps. sahation alwavs
hes in hope, which means that it lies
with their children, who personify hopc.
Since 1949. 300 schools have been
opened and equipped within camps in
Syria, the Lebanon. Jordan and the Gaza
region of Egypt. Over 100, 000 pupils
attend these and UNRWA is spending
more than $7 million on them this year.
Unesco has assumed technical responsa-
hi) ity for this educational mission ; spe-
cialist advisers in teacher training, tech-
nical education, handicrafts, domestic
economy and fundamental education
have been sent out. It is another of
those emergency measures which have
become so chronic that one must, a) as.
resign oneself to their continuation.
Whatever overaH solution statesmen
may contemplate, there remains an
urgent, daily problem : over 100. 000
childrcn have the right to work for their
UNESC : O-E :'c S : : h'/\"lh
OVER 5. 000 CHURCHES AND
HISTORIC BUILDINGS were
destroyed or damaged in Europe
during World War II. Thousands
more need the protective care and
skills of chemists. engineers and
archaeologists. Often the countries
with the most historic treasures
have the fewest technicians trained
in conservation work. In 1954,
representatives of 50 countries,
meeting at The Hague, adopted an
international convention prepared
by Unesco for the protection of
cultural property in time of war.
This"cultural Red Cross"conven-
tion came into force in August
t956. Fortheflrsttime. historica !
buildings, museums and libraries
where young peop ! e (Nke this
group in the Nationai Museum,
Amsterdam, right) find civiliza-
tion's roots and heritage, will receive
the same protection traditionally
granted in time of war to hospitals.
own future. like others who are nut
growing up in camps. They stand,
perhaps, for all the children in the world
for rhum this right is still a pipe-dream.
There will soon be nearly enough
schoois. but there is still a shortage of
reaHy we) !-quahtied teachers. This year,
teacher training coHeges wit ! open, and
help must continue.
25, 000 gutted schools
T7 ORE A, next-if onlv it could be the
1."-. end of a depressing list ! The dev-
astated Republic of Korea also
cried out for U. N. he) p. I. ast year, over
$120 mi) hon were stilt needed to rehuiìd
and repair factories, power stations,
roads, farms, hospitals. Twenty-five
thousand schools were gutted during the
war. Together with the U. N. Korean
Reconstruction Agency, C'\ESCO again
braced Useh tor the task ot reconstruc-
tion, which can never he a purely mate-
rial one. It is hclping currenllv to run a
training centre tor rura ! teachers and
has supptied equipment to schools.
Above all, it was instrumenta in found-
ing a printing press in Seoul which is
henceforth to supp) y the 30 million text-
books which arc annually required for
primary instruction in Korea.
Since only a historical sketch is bcing
attempted here, these selected instances
of reconstruction work must suffice.
There'Nould be no need to continue if
war were. in fact, the only agent of
destruction. Rut every ruin is not the
result of war. Ì\len must have a motive
in order to burn hooks, schools or even
works of art. But works of art are
a) so exposed to other dangers.
Paintings. statues, temples, cathedrals,
the whole heritage of mankind is
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
UNESCO
SIX-SECOND QUAKE killed or injured 300 people and
destroyed 3, 000 dwellings in Cuzco, Peru, on May 21, 1950. Cuzco
is three cities-Inca, Spanish Colonial, and modern. Among the
important monuments which suffered damage was the ! 7th-century
Church of Mercy (above). A Unesco mission spent three months
in Cuzco, drew up a plan for preserving and restoring the damaged
monuments within a wider plan of city reconstruction. Unesco has
answered many appeals for advice on restoration problems.
UNATIONS
ONE MILLION ARAB REFUGEES from Palestine are still living
in camps in Syria, Lebanon, Jordan and in the area of Gaza.
Since 1949, Unesco and UNRWA (U. N. Relief and Works Agency)
have opened over 300 schools for about 100, 000 of the refugee
children who live in the tent and hut camps. Unesco has given aid
in teacher training, technical and handicraft training, home econo-
mics and fundamental education. The operation came into being
as an emergency measure... but the emergency is not yet over.
threatened : to keep them intact requires
the restoratory and conservational ser-
vices of permanent agencies. Not that
UNESCO can become the world-wide
guardian of those innumerable treasures
which the various countries cannot
themselves defend against the inroads
of climate and indifference.
The groups of experts which have
been sent here and there in answer to
emergency calls may be compared to
doctors summoned for consultation.
They have attended to the altar-piece
of the Mystic Lamb in Ghent, the da
Vincis in Paris, precious and fragile
paintings on wood in Lisbon, the Cuzco
remains in Peru which the earthquake
of May 21 1950 had half destroyed, to
the Roman mosaics in Israel, and in
Syria and the Lebanon, to cities at once
medieval and modern trying to reconcile
expansion with historic prestige.
In Yugoslavia, the experts set out to
preserve one of Macedonia's most im-
portant religious buildings. The arches
and chiefly the frescoes of Saint Sophia
of Ochrida, a thousand-year-old church
which had been made into a mosque in
1466, were threatened for centuries : for
once it was possible to do something
about repairing the ravages of time.
A threatening spectre
BRUT it cannot be denied that the spec-tre of war continues to haunt those
who have been entrusted with the
care of monuments, paintings or manu-
cripts for posterity-all those objects
without which civilization would soon
have neither roots nor history. In 1952.
UNESCO drafted the text of an inter-
national agreement for the protection of
cultural property in the event of armed
conflict.
Adopted two years later at The Hague
during an inter-governmental conference,
and signed by 50 states, this agreement
was ratified by five governments in May
1956 : three months later, it came offi-
cially into force. Thus humanity has,
in the words of Georges Rouault,
acquired a"cultural Red Cross". For
the first time, it will become possible to
extend to historic buildings, museums,
libraries, protection similar to that
normally given everywhere in wartime
to hospitals and ambulances.
Such a convention clearly marks the
general trend of so many efforts ex-
pended for reconstruction and protec-
tion. In 1954, THE UNESCO COURIER
summed it up as"a tribute paid by poli-
tical power to the rights of art and the
mind".
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Victims of poverty, disease and ignorance
TWO PEOPLE OUT OF THREE
- w F one man lives in opulence and his brother in misery,
if some nations display their wealth while others can
only reveal their poverty, it becomes difficult to talk
of their intellectual and moral solidarity.
UNESCO set out from its earliest days to fight for
equality. Without preaching a Utopian levelling of all
differences, it maintained that all peoples have equal
rights, and that their cultures, their traditions and their
ambitions (despite varying degrees of achievement) are
all equally worthy of respect.
When the United Nations launched its programme of
technical assistance to"underdeveloped countries"in
1950, UNESCO took its share, and was able to put its
struggle for equality of opportunity on a practical footing.
No one rode forth to join this battle with rosy optimism.
In 1950, UNESCO stated the problem in brutally frank
terms, nor is there need to change these terms today :
"Two-thirds of humanity live in the underdeveloped
regions of Africa, Asia and Latin America. Two out of
three men must live on less than $100---occasionally less
than $60-per year. Their diet never exceeds the bare
minimum required to stave off starvation. Their life
expectancy is 40 years-in certain countries, 27 years.
Infant mortality rates run as high as 36 per cent..."Yes,
two-thirds of humanity.
The United Nations technical assistance programme set
as its goal the raising of living standards, the increase of
employment and the improvement of social and economic
conditions which are the prerequisite of progress and de-
velopment. UNESCO took particular interest in two essen-
tial aspects of these conditions for progress : it set out to
prove the value of education and scientific research to
economic development and to show how aid in these fields
may shatter the vicious circle of ignorance and poverty.
Over five years, the sum of $10, 600, 000 has been allocat-
ed to UNESCO technical assistance. More than 450 fellow-
ships have been awarded to young men and women so
that they may become teachers, engineers and scientists
in their own countries. They are the replacements who
must take over from the UNESCO"experts"at the end of
a technical assistance mission.
In the beginning of 1956, there were some 300 of these
experts working in 51 countries. Their work was as varied
as the needs-all urgent-of the governments they were
assisting. A list of these jobs would provide a detailed
picture of the educational needs of nations which must
build both primary schools and universities.
From master weavers and chemists
to psychologists and glassblowers
*r OR this programme, UNESCO has recruited school-
teachers and physicists master weavers and chem-
ests, librarians and radio engineers, psychologists
and glassblowers. In Monrovia, or Baghdad or Damascus,
UNESCO means science professors. In Colombia, it means
aid to rural schools taught by radio. In Brazil or Turkey
Or Pakistan, it means geologists. At Calcutta, UNESCO has
carried its message to engineering students. At Min-
neriya in the wet zone of Ceylon, it has worked among
illiterate farmers. In Iran, it has specialized in technical
education to train men for agriculture and industry. In
Thailand, it has helped in the reform of primary edu-
cation. This diversity of burgeoning activity is merely an
expression of the almost unlimited forms which technical
assistance must take to adapt itself to the practical
requirements of'''economic and social development."
But, at the root of all these missions, there is one com-
mon characteristic : their human value. They succeed
only through close collaboration and friendship. In 1952,
the author of a booklet describing UNESCO technical
20
assistance missions in four countries of South-east Asia
wrote :"Viewed from outside, UNESCO's technical assis-
tance programme is a complicated mechanism of budgets,
projects and agreements couched in legal language. But,
viewed at first hand, it becomes a simple story of men
shedding coats and protocol to do jobs."These jobs all
involve teaching at a human level without any trace of
condescending charity or mere display of knowledge.
In recent years, the"typical technical assistance
expert"has made his appearance and the portrait of this
international specialist can now be sketched quite
accurately. At first, he is truly foreign-and must adapt
himself to ways of living, working and thinking for which
his previous experience as a teacher or a scientist have
not in the least prepared him. But this stage does not
last long : within a few months, he is no more an outsider
and his assistance and advice are not foreign. He uses
his knowledge to solve the problems of his hosts and these
problems soon become as clearly-defined in his own eyes
as those of his own country.
Men on missions who try to
work themselves out of a job
TALE to him and he will tell you of local difficulties
and resources as though he were talking of his own
city or country. His mission may call for him to
demonstrate new methods or to teach a new technique
but, in every case, it is only part of a much bigger picture.
The adventure of social and economic progress in any
underdeveloped country always begins before the arrival
of an outside expert and it always continues after he
leaves. In other words, he must literally work himself out
of a job. His contribution can be measured only in terms
of those he trains to make his own presence unnecessary.
UNESCO authorities have always emphasized that this
assistance does not seek to bring about any magic trans-
formations but rather to stimulate work already begun by
various nations. Even with this limited goal, they admit
that the programme will remain insufficient to meet
world needs for years to come. In addition, therefore, to
its share in the United Nations technical assistance
programme, UNESCO set up in 1955 its own system of
"direct aid to Member states."This aid is not quite the
same : instead of giving absolute priority to economic
development, it stresses social and cultural factors. There
is another difference : while a large share of this pro-
gramme is set aside for underdeveloped regions, it is
available to all UNESCO Member States without exception.
By November 1, 1955, UNESCO had decided to send out
approximately 100 specialists under its direct aid pro-
gramme and to award 80 fellowships.
But, at just about this time, the man who had been
directing UNESCO's technical assistance efforts for five
years warned that, despite these efforts,'''many needs
remain unfulfilled."He wrote :"One should look at tech-
nical assistance without any complacency, in spite of the
considerable results already achieved, and work on the
assumption that it has only covered a small part of the
way to go."
In the face of the vast and urgent needs of two-thirds
of the world, it may well appear that the efforts of this
handful of experts have been dispersed. But there is
another aspect of technical assistance and, from its very
beginning, it has produced another result which, while
difficult to define, is full of promise. The same writer
who refused to judge technical assistance with compla-
cency declared :"If the tasks performed up to date have
encouraged and reinforced the ideal of international co-
operation, that fact alone is sufficient to rank them very
high in that scale of values upon which the future of
mankind depends."
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
i rw Unl'\ ( () Ccur Hr
YUGOSLAVIA :"Globemaker"is working at Zagreb centre which
produces urgently needed school equipment. Unesco has sent many
teachers and technicians to assist Yugoslavia in executing its
long-term educational re-organization and development programme.
NICARAGUA : People m farming communities
will benefit from national pilot proJcct 111 funda-
dental education staffed by Unesco-trained reachers.
LJ'. r'd Ui'.
AFGHANISTAN : Mans more schools are needed to give the country a workable system
of compuhory education. Government has approved Unesco mission plan for educational
reform, and vocational training--vital for country's future economic development-has started.
LEBANON : Psychological test for pupil in labo-
ratory set up by expert on Unesco mission which
aids government revision of educational system.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
'Am bassadors'
.
In
shirtsleeves
October 16 :"A British geology techni-
cian, Mr. E. O. Rowland, whose speciality is
the reduction of pieces of rock to the
thickness of cigarette paper, is arriving in
Pakistan this month on a UNEsco mission.
At Lahore he will instruct laboratory
workers in the technique of'thin-section
cutting of rocks'to make microscopic slides
for use in petroleum geology."
October 8 :"Mrs. Anine Rud, a Dan-
ish librarian and a pioneer in Denmark's
system of using children's libraries as an
aid to classroom work, arrives in Indonesia
this month, on a UNESCO mission. In
Jakarta, she will help to develop children's
and school libraries."
September 26 :"Educators from Bel-
gium, France, the Netherlands and Swit-
zerland have been sent by UNESCO to take
part in Yugoslavia's long-term programme
of educational re-organization and expan-
sion. The educators will lecture and lead
seminars in Belgrade, Zagreb and other
cities. UNESCO will send 11 educators to
Yugoslavia this year. Last year, more than
50 Yugoslav, educators received UNESCO
fellO'wships."
September 14 :"An adviser on English
teaching has arrived in Laos on a UNESCO
mission... September 6 : A former professor
of Palermo University has been sent by
UNESCO to the Engineering School of the
Syrian University at Aleppo... September 6 :
A Swiss expert in home economics is now
working in Kabul with Afghan educators...
September 4 : A Swedish electronics research
engineer has been sent by UNESCO to the
University of Calcutta... August 28 : A Dutch
expert is helping to create a geology
museum in Syria...
These facts taken from recent UNESCO
press releases tell something of the world-
wide programme under which more than
200 educators and scientists ("men and
women who shed coats and protocol to do
their jobs") are carrying out 106 technical
assistance projects at the request of the
governments of 47 countries. UNESCO's
share in the U. N. world programme of
technical assistance for economic develop-
ment, has amounted to $17, 500, 000 since the
programme began. Even so, supply has not
yet caught up with demand : since the
programme was launched five years ago
392 requests for aid have come to UNESCO
from 57 countries.
So far, 544 experts have, been sent on
UNEsco assignments 339 of which have been
completed. to date. UNESCO has awarded
nearly 700 fellowships so that its missions
could eventually be replaced by nationals
of the countries in which the missions were
working. Although technical assistance
stresses a sharing of skills rather than
massive economic aid, equipment must
sometimes be supplied. This year, for
example UNEsco is distributing some
$1, 400, 000 worth of equipment.
COLOMBIA : Textbooks and pos-
ters for classrooms without tea-
chers are devised by Brother
Fulgencio (left) and Brother Idi-
nael assigned by Unesco to work
with Radio Sutatenza's school-of-
the-air, now reaching hundreds
of thousands of isolated pupils.
SYRIA : How to read the mean-
ing of fossil imprints left in rocks
ages ago is discussed at the Syrian
University in Damascus by a
university student and Professor
Raymoon Raven, Dutch geologist
and member of Unesco's technical
assistance team teaching in Syria.
BURMA : Use of the theatre as
a vivid way of bringing home
lessons to Youngsters is one of
the techniques stressed at a
teacher-training centre in Ran-
goon where Unesco has sent a
team of educators to work with
Burma's educational authorities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
23
UNhbLU photos
INDIA : Production-line-in-miniature has been
set up for trai. 1 i ng pu rposes by a Unesco
engineer at the Indian Institute of Technology.
LIBERIA : From all corners of the globe,
Unesco missions have brought science teachers
into new University of Liberia at Monrovia.
LAOS : Age-old traditions of craftsmanship
ripen into modern skills at Savannakhet's
vocational school where Unesco mission works.
GOLD COAST : Book hunger of new lite-
rates is being met by a"vernacular literature
bureau"operated with Unesco mission's aid.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
r-rODAY we hear a great deal about)"international co-operation". What
does it really mean ? Who does
the co-operating ? The answer is Minis-
ters, officials, technicians. We can-
not assume that all the peoples are
consciously co-operating. Often they
are not even aware of the agreement
drawn up on their behalf in the cause
of peace and signed in their name.
The aeroplane... the radio and TV
set... the nuclear reactor. The modern
world is often summed up in these three
marvels. It is a world which laughs
at oceans and mountain ranges, which
is alive with a perpetual flow of ideas,
images and discoveries, and which is on
the threshold of enjoying fabulous riches
wrested from the very heart of matter.
This picture is not false one-it is
merely premature. A splendid machine
may swallow up 1, 000 miles in little
more than two hours, but they may be
1, 000 miles of unexplored jungles.
Hertzian waves flash at even greater
speed across even greater stretches
where no one can receive them. Power
lines stretch over villages still living in
neglect and pylons carrying the mod-
ern power grid are planted in fields
still cultivated by the hoe.
Industrial civilization has girdled the
24
globe so quickly that it has left immense
zones untouched.
In 1951, UNESCO's Director-General
Jaime Torres-Bodet wrote :"We all
remember with horror the concentration
camps, but it appears we do not realize
that more than 1, 200 million human
beings, men and women, still live in
the implacable, invisible prison of ignor-
ance. We distribute the text of the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights
and I am amazed that we dare call it
universal when we know there is not
one man out of every two who is able
even to read it."
No dreams of magazines
or election posters
A T that time, a rather ambitiousphrase was born : the crusade
against ignorance. It meant that
there was general acceptance for the
fact that no longer could forgotten
peoples remain exiled from what we
call progress. The crusade took the
form of literacy campaigns and then
more thorough efforts summed up as
"fundamental education".
Within a few years, these early efforts
produced undeniable results. Certain
countries in Latin America and southern
Asia saw their illiteracy rates drop from
60 to 40 per cent and even lower. In
the Near East, evening classes for adults
sprang up faster than schools, although
schools were being built at a furious
rate-in Syria, for example, where the
government opened 350 in five years.
But no one claimed that ignorance
could be conquered by teaching the al-
phabet and the multiplication table. If
hundreds of millions of men suffered
because of ignorance, it was not because
they were dreaming of arithmetic,
magazines or election posters. They
were suffering from hunger or filth or
sickness-or ail of these at once-and
they were suffering from humiliation.
Under such conditions, fundamental
education was defined as a concerted
attack on precise obstacles whose con-
tinued existence could not be suffered.
These obstacles bore the names of rou-
tine, inertia and isolation. It was not
enough to teach individuals or even pri-
vileged groups : this form of education
had to reach entire villages, and districts.
It quickly became obvious that in
raising the living standards of a rural
village-whether in India or Africa or
Peru-each step led to another. The
pioneers of fundamental education
learned that what we call poverty is not
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
a superficial misfortune growing out of
a single, clear-cut cause to be eliminated
once and for all. Rather, it is a complex
ma/. e of causes almost impossible to
attack one by one.
Farming, livestock raising, hygiene,
cooking, child-care and-according to
the region-weaving, building, pottery
or metalworking : all these must be
taught at the same time as reading and
writing. All these and self-confidence.
Who could take on such a task ? School-
teachers ? Priests ? Village Mayors ? If
they could be trained in this new form of
education, yes, but the methods had yet
to be perfected. Leaders must be trained
so that their teaching and experience
could radiate to every province and
village in their own countries. In other
words, an entirely new type of teacher-
training school had to be devised. These
new schools became known as regional
and national fundamental education
training centres.
The first battle-
vanquish fatalism
TN 1951, the first UNESCO internation-al fundamental education centre was
opened at Patzcuaro, Mexico. A
reporter asked the director of the centre,
Lucas Ortiz, to outline its objectives.
"We intend to show students how to en-
courage the improvement of life in rural
areas through the four cardinal points of
fundamental education", he declared.
"First, man must protect his health.
Secondly, he must make the best use
of the natural resources surrounding
him. Thirdly, he has the right to a
dignified home life, both materially and
spiritually. Fourthly, he has the right
to enjoy leisure and he must be given
the opportunity to do so."The reporter
interrupted :"But what about teaching
him to read and write ?"Mr. Ortiz
answered :"As far as we are concerned,
it is no use teaching a man to read and
write unless you can convince him it
will help solve the problems of his daily
life. We teach literacy when we teach
health, home economics or agriculture."
These were the questions studied by
Patzcuaro's trainees-men and women
from 16 Latin American countries-and
it was in these spheres that they did
practical work in villages surrounding
the centre.
A second centre, destined to serve the
Arab world, was opened in 1953 at
Sirs-el-Layyan in Egypt. In the same
spirit as their predecessors in Latin
America, the students came to Sirs-el-
Layyan. Teachers, social workers, agri-
cultural engineers, nurses and adult
education specialists from Egypt, Iraq,
Jordan. Lebanon, Syria, Saudi Arabia
and the Yemen learned how to put their
sp'ciatixed knowledge to work.
In Egypt ; lS in ! \lcxico, they worked
in"pilot villages". Of course the 1ll ; ljor
task of the trainees at the two centres
was not to bring progress to the
Tdrascans of Patzcuaro or the felldhs of
the Niie Doha. But the students ljuickly
reati/. ed that this"laboratory work"had
to succeed. H they failed during their
two years of study, how could they hope
to succeed later ?
They did not fail. They learned that
the secret of fundamental education lay
in developing a spirit of co-operation
with the people to be educated. They
did not come with handouts nor did
they establish charitable institutions.
Instead, they learned their job and they
acquired a priceless store of practical
experience. This experience taught them
a lesson : the first step to be taken in
helping thé under-privileged of any
country is to free them from fatalism.
People become resigned to misery
because they believe it to be their fate.
They must be taught that misery is not
the work of fate, that sickness, interest
rates, hunger, and infant mortality are
not simply afflictions of destiny.
The Uncsco Courier
National fundamental education cen-
tres in Haiti, in traq. in Thailand, in
Ceylon and in I. iberia have reached the
same conclusion. In lLJ54, a Sirs-ci-
Layyan trainee supplied this answer to
a questionnaire :"Fundamental educa-
tion is not merefy a reform movement
aimed at combating poverty, ignorance
and disease through certain techniques.
It is a revolutionary movement which
sets out to transform the mentality of
scientifically and economically under-
developed peoples. It sets out to
stimulate them to an awareness of their
needs and to give them the will to raise
their standards of hving through their
own resources. It does this by guiding
them and by showing them how to make
use of their forgotten resources and
their hidden strength."
Organizers, educators, leaders of social
progress-a) I of them must be recruited
to head a mass movement. This was the
task laid down for the two international
centres. At present, 228 of them have
been trained at Patzcuaro and 91 at
Sirs-el-Layyan. Thousands are needed.
Some dav, there will be thousands.
CREFAL-UNESCO
TWO OUT OF THREE PEOPLE in the world today are undernourished. One person out of
two in our atomic age is unable to read and write. This is the grim result of a vicious circle of ill-
health, poverty and ignorance. To break this circle and to raise living standards, education is
required-not only in the 3 R's, but also in agriculture, hygiene, home economics, handicrafts
and livestock breeding. This new form of education which has been called"fundamental education"
is desperately short of teachers. In co-operation with other U. N. Specialized Agencies, Unesco
has created regional centres to train leaders in fundamental education who, in turn, train others
when they return to their own countries. At CREFAL (Regional Fundamental Education Centre
for Latin America) at Patzcuaro, Mexico, one of the local Tarascan Indians (opposite page) grapples
with arithmetic problems. Above, an Egyptian girl comes for medicine to the social welfare service
of ASFEC (Arab States Fundamental Education Centre) at Sirs-el-Layyan, Egypt. (See pages 28-29)
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
250, 000, 000 CHILDREN
WITHOUT SCHOOLS
fox every ten children in the
world, five (i. e. over 250, 000, 000)
have no schools, four complete
only a few years of elementary school-
ing and only one has an opportunity
for secondary or higher education,
according to the World Survey of Edu-
cation, published by UNESCO in 1955.
The world's most formidable task in
education and the goal of both
national and international efforts is
therefore free schooling for all
children. UNEsco, aiming to give real
significance to the right to education
proclaimed in the Universal Declar-
ation of Human Rights, has under-
taken three main tasks : improving
education through the exchange of
information, extending education, and
promoting education for international
understanding.
UNEsco has sent educational mis-
sions to survey resources in many
Member States and to suggest how
these might best be used to lay the
foundations of modern school sys-
tems. Afghanistan, Burma, Korea,
Libya, the Philippines and Thailand
are just a few of the countries aided
by UNEsco in this way.
After a UNESCO mission had studied
Thailand's educational system, for
example, the government launched a
ten year plan to improve all aspects
of education. In Chao Choeng Sao
some 70 miles from Bangkok, UNESCO
specialists working with their Thai
counterparts (each adviser works
alongside a Thai teacher) helped to
set up a school system in miniature,
ranging from kindergarten classes to
teacher training colleges. Techniques
proved successful by this experiment
(now four years old) are being extend-
ed to other parts of the country.
In 1955 alone, UNEsco, answering
requests from 22 countries and terri-
tories, sent to each of them teams of
experts in the development of element-
ary education. UNEsco has convened
regional conferences at which teachers
and school administrators have ex-
changed experiences and discussed
common prcf-Jlems. It has published
monographs on primary education in
six countries and studies on the pro-
longation of schooling and the
employment of child labour.
Problem of the year
tf T is estimated that 55% of all
t persons over ten years of age have
never been to school. Pending the
full development of school education
an emergency measure is needed for
these people-estimated at more than
one thousand million-so that they
may begin to help themselves to a
better life.
For the past five years UNESCO has
given high priority to fundamental
education, so called because it aims to
26
give the minimum knowledge needed
by illiterate people to begin to improve
their health, food supply and family
life. (See pages 24-25)
Each year UNESCO sponsors with the
International Bureau of Education an
international conference to discuss
major educational problems. In 1955,
for example, the conference discussed
the financing of public education.
The previous year, discussions had
centered on the teacher shortage and
ways in which teaching can be made
more attractive, as a profession. For
these meetings countries prepare
reports on progress made over the
past year so it is possible for the first
time to have a world-wide picture of
educational developments and needs.
As others see them
UNESCO organized regional confe-
t t rences for educators to discuss
problems common to their own
area : Southeast Asian countries
have concentrated on the introduc-
tion of free and compulsory educa-
tion ; Middle East discussions have
focused on means of introducing
technical education.
The kind of education which can
lead to better international under-
standing aims at developing both a
national civic sense and a sense of
international responsibility. But
"international understanding"cannot
be tacked on to conventional school
programmes. As it has to be an
integral part of an education adapted
to a new situation UNESCO has re-
viewed problems of curricula, methods
and materials and has suggested
solutions. UNESCO seminars and publi-
cations, particularly on the teaching
of history and geography have led
educators and publishers in many
countries to analyse their textbooks
and to invite neighbouring countries
to comment on ways in which they
may feel they have been misrep-
resented. On UNESCO's invitation, 23
Western countries have taken a look
at their textbooks to see how much
is being taught about Asia. Eastern
countries are to make similar studies
of their textbooks about the West.
In U. N. rehabilitation programmes
the need for emergency education is
great. Schools and adult education
classes may offer the first semblance
of normal life in refugee camps or
temporary homes. UNESCO has help-
ed to rebuild education in Greece,
Palestine and Korea. Outstanding
example was aid in education of
Arab refugees, some 160, 000 of whose
children are enrolled in primary
schools and 20, 000 in secondary
schools set up by UNEsco and the
United Nations Relief and Works
Agency (UNWRA). (See THE UNESCO
COURIER, N"7, 1955 ; U. S Oct.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The UneMO Courier
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
PATZCUARO
The Regional Fundamental Education
Centre for Latin America (CREFAL)
was opened by Unesco in 1951 at Patz-
cuaro, Mexico, because the two dozen
or so villages scattered around the
shores of Lake Patzcuaro and on islands
in the lake represented a faithful reflection
of problems confronting Latin America.
More than half the population of Latin
America-that is, 70, 000, 000 human
beings-face these problems of ignor-
ance and poverty. Several courses
of trainees from practically all countries
of Latin America have already graduated
from CREFAL and are now instructing
people in their own countries in ways
of improving standards of living. in
1955, 125 trainees-45 of them women-
from 18 countries studied at CREFAL
and 54 of them graduated in October.
This year the centre has received about
the same number of trainees. Photos,
from feft to right, illustrate three of the
subjects taught at CREFAL-adutt edu-
cation, public health, and improvement
of working and economic conditions.
CREFAL and UNESCO
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
StRS-EL-LAYYAN
The Nile Delta of Egypt, most densely-
populated region on the face of the
earth, offers an ideal testing ground for
fundamental education. Within a radius
of a few miies one can visit and study
a hamlet, a small city and five or six vil-
lages of different sizes. Some may be re-
latively prosperous, others are poverty-
stricken. Some are peopled by small
farmers, others by day labourers and by
landless workers. That is why the
Arab States Fundamental Education
Centre (ASFEC) was created by Unesco
in 1952 at Sirs-el-Layyan in the Menoufia
district of the Nile Delta. Trainees
studying there (they numbered 120 at
the beginning of 1956) will later carry
fundamental education to the Arab
lands of the Middle East. At Sirs-el-
Layyan, however, they already have a
replica of the same kind of peasant
society found, with many variations,
in their own countries and throughout
the Arab world. Photos show (from
ieft to right) a general view of Mana-
wallah, one of the centre's"laboratory"
villages ; irrigation work in the fields ;
and an examination of livestock being
made by the centre's veterinarians.
ASFEC and UNESCO
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
PUBLISHER IN 28 TONGUES
DRING the past ten years over 1, 000 UNESCO publicationes-surveys, handbooks,
studies, monographs, reviews, dictionaries, manuals sud bibliographies, to name
only some of their types-have been produced. UNESCO'S publications-one of
its important programme activities-serve a world-wide audience, composed in the
main of specialists. Some, however, such as THE UNESCO COURIER, explain UNESCO's
aims and interests to the general public.
All the UNESCO fields-the arts, science and technology, libraries and museums,
education, the social sciences, communications and exchange of persons-are covered
by publications. (Details are given in catalogues, several of whose covers are reprodu-
ced here). UNESCO also produces ten periodicals, four of them monthly ones.
UNESCO publications have so far appeared in 28 languages, ranging from Icelandic to
Japanese and from Tamil to Hebrew, although the greatest number have been printed
in English, French, Spanish and Arabic-in that order.
Broadly, they can be classed under three headings :
(1) Facts and figures collected by UNESCO, acting as an information"clearing house".
Examples :"The World Survey of Education" ;"Index Translationum".
(2) Technical information. Examples :"Reviews of Research on Arid Zone Hydro-
logy" ;"Bulletin for Libraries"which supplies libraries with lists of publications for
exchange, and news of library developments.
(3) Special fields of UNESCO action. Examples :"The Universal Declaration of
Human Rights, a guide for teachers" ; three series on race problems.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
D
R ACC, 00]0""",.., the time bill come when dis-
crimination based on these three will be abolished,
together with fear and contempt. At present, however, the
world goes about its business with some men still refusing to
admit that all human beings are born free and equal in dignity
and in rights.
Nevertheless, there are no longer many countries where
women are treated as perpetual slaves-almost as beasts of
burden. It is more and more rare to find statutes declaring
them legal minors and the inferiors of men. But it is equally
rare to find countries where women and men of equal talent
have the same rights and the same opportunities. It is a
fact, however, that since the United Nations and its Specia-
lized Agencies began to exert influence upon governments,
the number of countries where women have the right to vote
has risen from 36 to 72. There are now only 13 countries
which continue to reserve this right for the"stronger sex".
In several other countries, women must be able to write or
show a primary school diploma before going to the polls.
Now one fact is certain : out of every 100 illiterates, 70 or
80 of them are bound to be women. Emancipation must
follow and not precede progress in education. In this field,
UNESCO has worked constantly for the past ten years with
the International Bureau of Education and the International
Labour Organisation. UNESCO has studied the slow erosion
of prejudices and the slow social and psychological evolution
which is paving the way for women to gain full access to
their rights. UNESCO studies have investigated the participa-
tion of women in the political life of both communities and
nations and they have also measured the true influence of
women in economic and cultural life.
Nevertheless, the problem of education has remained the
most urgent. No one has yet contested this statement often
repeated in books published on this question by UNESCO :
"The number of girls receiving an education in a given country
is in direct proportion to the degree of cultural and political
development which that country has attained."
This does not merely mean that we should deplore the
backwardness of nations where girls hardly have the right to
learn to read-if they can find a school. In Europe, for
example, or in the United States, the question takes another
new form. Here, girls have the right to all forms of
education, or nearly all. But they remain in a mi-
nority as soon as a higher level is reached : the percentage
of women among university students rarely exceeds 35 per
cent. This means that the countries proclaiming themselves
as"highly advanced"can still make progress in their"cultu-
ral and political development". UNESCO's goal is not merely
non-discrimination between the sexes or a legal equality
which should be part and parcel of any civilized nation, but
the participation of women in all fields of human endeavour
as"full partners".
c. o, 1. Crown Copyright Reserved
LABORATORY
ASSISTANT
handles radio-active
isotopes with rub-
ber gloves let into
the walls of a"dry
box"at a British
research institute.
This is used when
handling toxic sub-
stances which are
placed in box
through the small
chamberon its right.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
II RED U C I N G..
CONFLICTSU IS
TENSIONS ANS
PREJUD ! CE
32
the International Social Science Bulletin, has been a link
between scientists all over the world, providing a forum
for the discussion of important topics.
*
UNESCO has promoted social science teaching and thetraining of experts in all its branches capable of
, studying social problems objectively and providing
public authorities with a sound diagnosis. It has sent
missions to establish, reorganize or develop teaching at
the university level in many countries. Its investigations
have covered the teaching of the social sciences as a
whole, and some of the first reports it obtained, covering
30 countries and published under the title of.'Contempor-
ary Political Science,"constitute the most extensive and
useful directory in this field today.
Instead of attempting to carry out large-scale research
itself, UNESCO has facilitated research at the international
level, and has collected from organizations and individual
research workers information which it has synthesized..'I .. L-. 'I J........'I'I
- WN the social sciences-the sciences concerned withpeuple and their relationships to each other as groups
and individuals-UNESCO has been trying to organize
international co-operation between relatively new
branches of study in which there are not always enough
specialists to cope with the work waiting to be done.
It has given an important place to the social sciences
principally because their development offers one of the
best ways of promoting mutual understanding between
individuals and nations, of counteracting the evils caused
by ignorance and of finding the causes of tensions and
removing them. It has therefore tried to provide the
organizations and the tools needed by these sciences and
to bring them to analyse and find rational solutions for
some urgent modern problems.
*
BECAuSE most of the social sciences are of recent origin
there has been only little international exchange of
information in this field. Until ten years ago, there
and distributed. It has used
the social sciences to analyse
the causes of tensions that
exist between individuals,
groups and nations. In this
way it has been able to help
several Member States : Stud-
ies in India on tensions
existing between different
religious communities ; a re-
search programme on ten-
sions in the new State of
Israel, and an investigation
of tensions among German
and Japanese youth.
*
UNESCO has used the re-
source of the social
sciences in seeking ways
to smooth difficultés en-
countered by the United
Nations and other interna-
tional organizations in the
course of their rapid growth.
It has enlisted the aid of
historians, jurists, political
scientists, sociologists and
other specialists, to investi-
gate, among other questions.
the present effectiveness of
a number of international
co-operation programmes.
was not a single international
organization covering the
activities of sociologists or
psychologists. UNESCO had
therefore to intervene more
directly in this field than in
many others so as to fill the
many gaps that existed in
the ranks of international
associations, in the now of
information on research and
in the standardization of
technical terms.
*
RINCE 1946 UNEsco has beenresponsible for setting
up international profes-
sional organizations in the
following social sciences :
economics, political scien-
ce, sociology, legal science,
scientific psychology and
statistics. To aid collective
efforts of specialists in dif-
ferent disciplines, special
committees for the distri-
bution and exchange of
information have been set
up with UNESCO's aid.
*
Té establishment under
) UNESCO's auspices of the International Social Science
Council in 1953 created a central co-ordinating
mechanism for all branches of social science, parallel to
the International Council of Scientinc Unions, the co-
ordinating body for all branches of pure science.
*
mach year UNESCO supports the work of the professional
asocial science organizations through grants-in-aid
which make possible conferences, symposia and other
meetings and the publication of their results. In their
turn, the organizations co-ordinate research programmes
among their members and stimulate professional associa-
tions in countries where they need strengthening.
*
UNESCO'S Field Science Co-operation Offices in Cairo,
) J New Delhi, Jakarta and Montevideo have pro-
gressively extended their work to the social sciences
and have added specialists in these disciplines to their
staffs. UNESCO set up a special clearing house for in-
formation in Paris to collect documentation on social
science problems and to keep a register of social science
experts throughout the world. To aid research workers it
has published bibliographical directories and bulletins of
abstracts, aided by an International Committee for So-
cial Science Documentation. Its quarterly publication,
In some countries tensions are liable to be created by
industrialization and the shift of populations from rural
areas. UNESCO considers that by using the knowledge and
methods of the social sciences governments can do much
to improve the conditions under which people adjust
themselves to changes brought about by modern science
and techniques of today. It has surveyed situations of
this kind and has reported on the conditions under which
the impact of social and technical changes can be reduc-
ed and tensions minimised. Since 1953, an International
Research Centre concerned with these questions has been
working in Paris under the International Social Science
Council. UNESCO has also investigated social aspects of
land reform, and population and migration problems.
*
r-r-tHE social sciences can be used to promote human! rights. UNESCO has so employed them in relation to
race problems, for race prejudice, with the discrimin-
atory measures which result from it, is one of the main
obstacles to the implementation of human rights. The
pseudo-scientific justifications for racial discrimination
were denounced in the Race Declaration published in 1950
by an international group of sociologists, anthropologists
and geneticists. Since then three series of UNESCO
pamphlets-The Race Question and Modern Science, The
Race Question and Modern Thought, and Race and
Society-have helped to spread rational concepts about
racial equality.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
POST-WAR JAPANESE YOUTH and its changing attitudes were studied by Japanese social
scientists aided by Unesco in 1951 in one of a series of studies of national behaviour patterns and
the formation of social attitudes. Results, published in"Without the Chrysanthemum and the
Sword", gave a revealing picture of the outlook and ideas of a generation of young people in whose
country the old order had undergone a complete upheaval. Other Unesco research teams have
studied group tensions poisoning relations between different communities in India and problems
concerning the successful assimilation of the thousands of immigrants in the State of tsrae).
Copyright Magnum
33
The Unesco Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
KEY WORDS OF UNESCO
the free flow of ideas &. information
DURING UNESCO'S early days, civi-lized life had only begun to
reassert itself. The railway
map of Europe offered a symbolic
picture of the wounds inflicted on
civilization : it consisted of segments
of lines running from blown-up brid-
ges to burned-out stations and linking
only the most important cities-not
very successfully, at that. Men, ma-
terials, ideas were almost unable to
move. If such a paralysis
had continued, immense re-
gions would have slipped
back into the drear chaos of
isolated villages. People
might not have died, but
they would have vegetated.
Free movement has become
a basic condition for civilized
life. In the language and in
the action of UNESCO, free
flow have become key
words. There must be a
flow-like that of blood in
the arteries, or of electricity.
At first, this meant sparing
no effort to enable ideas to
move again. The network
indispensable to the existence
of centres of study and re-
search had to be re-estab-
lished or else created. Every
break in this current and
every obstacle, whether mor-
al, material or political,
required quick action.
First came books and the
networks linking libraries.
UNESCO has achieved one of
its most clear-cut successes
over the past ten years in
encouraging the exchange
of papers and publications.
among libraries and scientific
institutions. At first, contacts
were established with a few
hundred librairies. In 1955,
the number of these libraries
had risen to more than 10, 000. These
institutions represent more than 100
countries or territories and their
regular exchanges amount to half
the world's annual volume of publica-
tien exchanges. Before the second
world war, there were 50 national
centres maintaining a steady fow of
books and information. UNESCO ac-
tion had already some years ago rais-
ed this number to 65. This year, it is
99. These are the centres which
34
organize the exchange of learned
publications and scientific documents
which are offered by more than 3, 500
institutions.
But other lines had also to be clear-
ed. Political and economic controls
had laid a heavy hand on books and,
at the same time, on newspapers,
films and phonograph records. In
1914, countries had stopped all trade
in articles not required by war. The
TEACHING BY TELEVISION has been encouraged by Unesco
with practical results. The success of an experiment in rural educa-
tion and entertainment conducted by the French National Radio
through tele-clubs in lonely country villages has led to similar
experiments with Unesco participation in Italy and Japan. Unesco
surveys also provide a world picture of the amazing strides in televi-
sion in the past decade, as symbolized by this photo, taken from
the top of a giant television mast at Sutton Coldfìeld, England.
depression of the 1930's saw even
more rigid controls adopted. Then
came the destruction of the second
world war and foreign currency prob-
lems to deal a coup de grace to in-
ternational exchange. Neither books
nor teaching materials nor works of
art were officially considered as
"essential articles."
UNEsco has waged a steady cam-
paign over the past decade to over-
come these obstacles by sponsoring
being applied by 21 nations.
Twelve governments are
applying a second agreement
which came into effect in
1954 and covers audio-visual
materials such as films,
microfilms, sound record-
ings, models, wall charts,
maps and posters. If these
articles are of an education-
al, scientific or cultural na-
ture, they are exempted
from, customs duties, im-
port licences and all quo-
ta restrictions in countries
where the agreement has
come into effect.
In order to meet the prob-
lem of currency shortages,
UNESCO also launched an in-
ternational coupon system in
1948. Under this scheme,
soft currency countries were
able to buy coupons from
UNESCO and sell them to ins-
titutions or individuels ho
were then able to use them
to buy books, films or scien-
tific materials in hard
currency areas. These cou-
pons were backed by UNESCO's
hard currency reserve.
At the beginning of 1956,
38 countries in Africa, Asia,
Europe and the Americas
were participating in this
scheme as either buyers or
suppliers. The total value
of UNESCO coupons issued
exceeded $9, 000, 000.
In all these fields, the response
of governments has demonstrated
that they are becoming more
and more determined to eliminate
obstacles to the free flow of ideas.
Support from the press and public
opinion for UNESCO's campaign has
raised the hope that, sooner of later,
the tools of knowledge will be brought
within the reach of peoples in all
parts of the world.
international agreements. The first
of these went into effect in 1952 and
it eliminated customs duties on the
importing of a wide range of articles :
books, publications and documents ;
works of art and collector's items ;
audio-visual materials destined for
recognized institutions ; scientific ins-
truments and apparatus ; and objects
destined for the blind. At the begin-
ning of 1956, this agreement was
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
T 11, (, \II Ilr
NEWSPRINT SHORTAGE ALARM
was sounded by Unpsco in ! 949whcn
Its Directol'-Gcnel'ol dcclo,'cd"Evcn
if present newsprint minufacturing
capacity ère fully utilized and tlrc
most up to date metlrods applied, it
could not fill immcdiate needs, still
'ess the needs of tomorrow. Unesco
strcssed the need to cncourage rcsearch
into thc possibility of using other raw
materials. At its request, the U. N.
Economic and Social Council discussed
the newspri nt pi'Oblem in 19 S I and
proposed both short-term and long-
term action to meet it. Today the
hunger for books, magazines, newspa-
pers and every kind of printed publica-
tion is greater then ever. Unesco is
conducting studies on aspects of the
newsprint problem, particularly as it
affects underdeveloped areas where
rising literacy is creating new readers-
and new consumers of newsprint. A
long-term programme to expand paper
production has been undertaken by a
sister U. N. agency, the Food and Agri-
culture Organization. Left, huge logs
destined for the pulp mill are guided
down a river in Canada, which is
the wor ! d's largest producer of paper.
,. i : c
UNESCO'S GIFT COUPONS SERVE 50 NATIONS. Since 1951, more than 300 institutions
in 50 countries-mainly in Asia, Africa and Latin America-have received equipment and other
forms of practical aid to the value of S750. 000 through the Unesco Gift Coupon Programme.
Its operation is simple. Unesco selects a list of institutions (schools, universities, laboratories)
needing equipment, and a sponsoring organization-perhaps a women's association in England,
a high school in Holland or a Unesco Club in France-chooses a project from this list and raises
money (through concerts, lectures, film showin'gs or exhibits) to buy Gift Coupons. These are
sent to the chosen project which then buys the equipment it needs, using the coupon as a sort of
international money order. Unesco in turn redeems the coupon for the supplier in his local
currency, In the process, direct contacts are established between the donor and the recipient.
Small boy from India (right) is learning to walk again thanks to Gift Coupons. A victim of infan-
tile paralysis, he is being helped to recover his sense of balance on special apparatus at the Bombay
Society for the Rehabilitation of Crippled Children. French schools and American voluntary
organizations gave equipment to the Bombay Centre through the Gift Coupon Programme.
35
Fui ! r) ßC ; ird or C ; : H'lada.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
What Unesco has done to...
series of educational telecasts aimed at rural populations.
These are helping tele-clubs now springing up in countries
like Japan and Italy.
In April 1956, UNESCO convened the first international
gathering devoted exclusively to education in journalism.
which suggested ways in which UNESCO could help to fill
some of the training gaps, and drew up a plan of action
on a broad international scale.
UNESCO has enlisted the aid of editors, journalists, film
producers and broadcasters to make known what has been
accomplished by peoples who are working to build up
through education, science and culture, a peaceful in-
ternational community based on respect for Human
Rights.
In 1949 UNESCO created the World Braille Council and
aided the unification of Braille in the various languages
of the world, with the aim of creating an easy written
medium for the blind student to learn, read and commu-
nicate in other languages than his own. Results were
published in"World Braille Usage"in 1954.
Man-made barriers to the
free flow of information,
ideas and knowledge between
countries and to the inter-
rational circulation of edu-
cational scientific and cul-
tural materials are legion.
Some obstacles : currency
and travel restrictions, cen-
sorship, quotas and tarifes.
UNESCO tackled the problem
vin three ways : sponsorship
of international agreements
to remove obstacles, action
in co-operation with other
international organizations, publication of studies
focusing public attention on the issues.
As a first step UNESCO tackled the currency problem in
1949 by providing a"Coupons Scheme"under which cou-
pons (a kind of international money order) were made
available for the purchase of books, films and scientific
equipment (later extended to educational travel). Through
the scheme, people and institutions in soft-currency
countries have been able to buy badly needed items from
countries with hard currencies. Coupons worth $9, 000, 000
had been issued by the end of 1955.
UNESCO sponsored an international agreement on the
importation of educational, scientific and cultural mat-
erials. This eliminates customs duties on books, news-
papers, magazines, works of art and a wide variety of
other educational items. Its effect : such materials are
easier to get and cheaper to buy in the 22 countries which
have ratified it to date.
To help remove barriers in particular fields, UNESCO
works with other international organizations. Examples :
-, With the International Telecommunications Union
(iTu) on the question of press rates throughout the world.
The flow of news and information is impeded by the high
and divergent rates between different nations. (A press
message costs 2. 04 cents a word when sent from London
to New York and 5. 54 cents in the opposite direction.)
- With the Universal Postal Union (Upu) on postal
rates and concessions which might be granted to publica-
tions. By the end of 1954 over 30 governments had gran-
ted concessions in response to these efforts.
- With the International Air Transport Association
(latta) to reduce charges on the despatch of information
materials by air. In April 1954 a concession came into
effect whereby books were granted a discount of up to
50% of normal airfreight charges in non-European
regions and up to 33 1/3% within Europe.
The aim of UNESCO at all these conferences is to make
it easier and cheaper for information to circulate from
country to country, whether in the form of a newspaper
sent through the mail or a press despatch sent by cable
or a radio broadcast intended for listeners abroad.
%
People in highly industri-
S t I'h't th alized countries are apt topOI g', e take newspapers, radio, films
and television for granted.
W O'rld'S e d S They are surprised. when""they read, as they did re-
cently in UNESCO's publica-
'. <ii.''.".. i.,'. f'tion"World Communica-
tisons", that Africans, Asians
and South Americans toge-
ter only buy 24% of the
C omm U n IC, I Ion world's daily newspapers,
whereas Europeans buy 38%
and North Americans 24%,
and that while 50% of the
world's radio receivers are in North America, only 11%
are in Africa, Asia and South America.
Striking facts like these have been brought to light and
publicized by UNESCO since it began to make investiga-
tions in 1947 into how many printing presses, film studios,
news agencies, radio stations and receivers and similar
resources existed in different countries. Between 1947 and
1952 UNESCO surveys covered the structure, equipment and
operation of mass communication media in 173 countries
and territories. The facts, widely publicized, have been
used in campaigns and missions, studies and monographs.
With technical assistance programme funds, experts
(and materials) in the communication field have been
sent to underdeveloped countries. By the end of 1955 :
85 fellowships awarded ; missions working in 15 countries.
A study of the Canadian Farm Radio Forum broadcasts
in 1952-53 was put to practical test in India's campaign
for adult education by radio. Specialists from 30 countries
pooled experience and techniques at a UNESCO Seminar on
Visual Aids in Fundamental Education in Sicily, in 1953,
and produced the first catalogue of films and filmstrips for
this kind of education and eight sets of travelling libraries
of visual aids.
UNESCO publications on mass communication questions
have been aimed both at the general public and specialists.
Titles from"Press, Film and Radio in the World Today"
series reveal range and variety of these studies :"Profes-
sional Training of Journalists","Training for Radio","The
Problem of Newsprint and other Printing Paper","Radio
in Fundamental EdMcation","The Film Industry in Six
European Countries","Low-Cost Radio Reception". In
1954 UNESCO published"Television-A World Survey",
covering 44 countries where TV was either in operation
already or in the planning stages. Fourteen more,
countries were surveyed in 1955
As well as improving the
methods and media of mass
communication through co-
operation at the interna-
tional level, UNESCO works
through all means of com-
munication for mutual un-
derstanding between peoples
and countries.
Television is a case in
joint. Several countries ask-
eu for help in arranging the
exchange of TV techniques
and programmes which
could be used to teach about
other peoples and customs. UNESCO and the British
Broadcasting Corporation in 1954 convened the first
seminar ever held on this subject. Producers and edu-
cators from 12 countries took part. In 1955, film and TV
producers met at an international conference in Tangier
to discuss obstacles to the exchange of films and televi-
sion kinescopes.
TV viewing through community tele-clubs (first develop-
ed in France) offers another means of breaking down
isolation within countries and (since the growth of inter-
national TV programme co-operation) within continents.
In 1954 UNESCO and the French TV service produced a
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
PATHS OF KNOWLEDGE
FOR ALL PEOPLES
EVEN when books, films and paintings are able to crossfrontiers, they still have to reach the men and women
who need them the most urgently... and who are
often not even aware of their need. From its earliest
days UNESCO encouraged the growth of libraries in cities
and villages and of mobile libraries, whether transported
by bus or boat, in isolated regions. It organized seminars
and published manuals, to help governments, local
authorities and educators to create new libraries or to
improve existing ones so that they might serve as cultural
centres at a broad level. Then UNESCO passed from
preaching to practice. With the co-operation of govern-
ments and communities, it opened model public libraries
in India, Colombia
and A'frica. The
"oldest"of these,
the Delhi Public Li-
brary, was set up in
1950 ; five years
later, it had loan-
ed nearly a million
books to its 30, 000
regular readers.
Similar assistance
obviously had to be
offered museums as
one of the most
effective instruments
for the spread of
knowledge. For far
too many years, too
many museums con-
sidered their role as
one of jealously
keeping the public
away from the trea-
sures of history on
the pretext that this
was the only way
of preserving them.
The true role of a
museum, however, is
to serve the public
and to contribute to
its education in the
largest sense of the
word. By establish-
ing international co-
ordination for mu-
seums, UNESCO help-
ed them modernize.
With the Interna-
tional Council of
Museums, it has carried out campaigns to bring the people
into museums, so that the people-and not merely a hand-
ful of specialists-might have access to the treasures of
art, history, folklore, science and technology.
Museums can even go to the people. UNESCO organiz-
ed travelling exhibitions of colour reproductions of an-
cient and modern paintings and sent them on an odyssey
to villages and cities, town halls and universities in more
than 60 countries. Other exhibitions took the road to
reveal to millions who had never set foot inside a mu-
seum, the drawings of Leonardo da Vinci, Japanese
prints, Chinese art and Persian miniature. Then
UNEsco opened-through its new series of Art Albums-
an imaginary museum displaying priceless collections
which not even the most seasoned of travellers had been
able to contemplate in their entirety : the Ajanta cave
paintings, Egyptian tombs and temples, Yugoslav medie-
val frescoes, Australian aboriginal paintings, and the
wooden stave churches of Norway.
The gates barring universal access to the wealth of
literature, drama, music and science had to be unlocked.
Despite startling technical progress, we live in an era
where the world's great civilizations still dwell in mutual
ignorance of their achievements.
Masterpieces of literature which form a perfect
EVENT OF THE WEEK for children and adults in outskirts of Medellin, Colombia,
is arrival of bookmobile from the city's model library opened as a pilot project by
Unesco and Government of Colombia in 1954. Carrying more than 5, 000 books,
the bookmobile covers an area of about ! 00 mi ! es, making stops each week at 45 places.
Medellin Public Library has set off a chain reaction in public library development in
Latin America, just as a similar project, the Delhi Public Library, has done in India.
Colombian, Cuban, Dominican, English, French, German.
Greek, Hindi, Italian, Japanese, Marathi, Mexican, Punjabi,
Persian, Sanscrit, Siamese, Spanish, Tamil and Uruguayan.
As far as the theatre was concerned, the main problem
was to set up channels of co-operation and exchange from
one country to another. This liaison task was given to
the International Theatre Institute founded in 1948 and,
since then, national centres have made their appearance
on all continents. Information and research
were also among the Institute's tasks. For
the past seven years, a bilingual quarterly,
"World Theatre,"has reflected a faithful next po. enext ¢cge
picture of theatrical activity. International
37
C^lJl. C. : : >. : : >lUU U lilC
traditions and spirit
of a people often
remain unknawn on
the other side of
national boundaries.
Certain books, rated
as the master works
of a particular civi-
lization, had been
awaiting for cen-
turies the trans-
lators who could
make them known
to the rest of the
world. This meant
an immense under-
taking and UNESCO
made its contribu-
tion by publishing a
collection of repre-
sentative works-
works which private
publishers had hesi-
tated to translate
owing to language
difficulties or limit-
ed sales possibilities.
In March 1956,
seven years after
this work was begun,
UNESCO had publish-
ed translations in
either English, Ara-
bic, Spanish, French
or Persian of works
from 25 sources :
Arabic, Argentine,
Bengali, Bolivian,
Brazilian, Chinese,
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
PATHS OF
KNOWLEDGE
(Continued)
Doors opened to
World's wealth of
music and drama
Theatre Weeks and international fes-
tivals have also been able to bring to
many countries foreign plays which
can help international understanding
and thus serve the cause of peace.
The Institute has paid particular
attention to the influence of the
theatre upon youth and, indeed,
much of its work has dealt with vari-
ous educational aspects of the theatre
and with plays produced by young
people as part of school programmes.
A similar institution, the Interna-
tional Music Council, was created in
1949 with the object of making
known contemporary music and folk
music, of assisting the publication of
works of musicology and of encourag-
ing, among both adults and young
people, the appreciation and the
playing of music. Recordings of tra-
ditional popular music have been
made in 35 countries. In addition,
works have been commissioned from
relatively unknown young composers
and international works on the history
of music have been published.
The role of music in education-a
basic role in the eyes of so many phi-
losophers and yet largely ignored to-
day-has been examined in numerous
studies and in international discus-
sions bringing together educators and
musicians ; various methods have
been put to practical test and recom-
mendations made to authorities.
Returning music to its rightful place
in our culture may be an almost
superhuman task, but it is one well
worth trying.
EAGER YOUNGSTERS took the Medellin Library by storm after a campaign in schools to en-
courage readership. Because of previous ! ack of public libraries and outside bookloan services in
Medellin, many people predicted that there would be no readers for Colombia's model library.
But is has outgrown its present home, is building a bigger and better one. Photos show some
of many extension activities which include children's choir, musical puppet shows, dramatic society,
discussion and study groups, weekly concerts, and exhibitions on art and other subjects. Future
plans include new branch libraries, and services to hospitals, homes for the aged and orphanages.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
END) NE IHE WORLD'S
COPYRIGHT MUDDLE
SUTURE generations of authors and publishersmamy well remember September 16, 1955 as the
day when a small ray of light penetrated the
legal jungle of international copyright protection, a
jungle where many an unsuspecting author had
seen his works swallowed up.
This date marked the coming into effect of the
Universal Copyright Convention sponsored by
UNESCO. Since Sept. 16, 1955 a Spanish author or
publisher, for example, has been able to obtain
copyright protection in the United States with no
other formalities than a line of type bearing the
symbol C, his name and the date of publication of
his work. This holds true, of course, for an Ameri-
can author's works in Spain and for the works of
foreign authors, composers and other creative artists
in all the 21 countries which have to date joined the
Universal Copyright Convention (1).
The Convention came into force three years after
its adoption by an intergovernmental conference
convened by UNEsco at Geneva in September 1952.
Although it is still in its infancy, its effects have
already been felt. The United States, in implement-
ing this international agreement, has wiped out a
provision of its copyright law which stated that full
copyright protection could be granted foreign
authors writing in English only if their works had
been printed from type set in the United States.
The exemption from this"manufacturing clause"
applies to authors in all countries adhering to the
Convention. One of the principal beneficiaries will
be the United Kingdom where existing copyright
laws are now being revised so that the Convention
can be ratified.
Behind the adoption of the Universal Copyright
Convention lies the centuries-old story of the
author's struggle to earn a living by his writing.
The"successful"author is, after all, a relatively
new being : Cervantes kept body and soul together
by working as a tax collector ; Spinoza ground lenses
in Amsterdam for his living and Shakespeare relied
on acting for his main source of income.
The 19th Century saw a wave of national legisla-
tion instituting copyright protection for authors.
Unfortunately, the 19th Century also saw a wave of
international literacy piracy. It became quite
obvious that national law could not protect the
author whose works were being plagiarized abroad
(1) Andorra, Cambodia, Chile, Cosio Rica, France, the Federal
Republic of Germany, Haili, the Holy See, Iceland, Israel,
Japan, Laos, Liberia, Lurc11Ihoury,"foIloco, Pakistan, the Phi-
lippines, Portugal, Spain, Switzerland and the United Stales.
just about as fast as they came off the presses in
his on country.
Back in 1842, one of history's most famed victims
of plagiarism, Charles Dickens, drank a hopeful
toast in New York to"international copyright, the
only turnpike between the readers of two great
nations". But the turnpike had yet to be opened in
the 20th century. It was not until 1946 that the
idea of a universal copyright convention was brought
up at the United Nations and the problem turned
over to UNESCO. It was one of the items of unfinished
business which the U. N. inherited from the League
of Nations.
Preparatory studies revealed two basic reasons for
the failure of previous attempts to build a worldwide
system of copyright protection and, in particular
explained why the Berne Copyright Convention of
1886 and that of Montevideo, signed three years
later, were not as effective as had been hoped.
Firstly, sufficient allowance had not been made for
the fact that certain countries could not adhere to
international agreements because of provisions in
their national legislation and secondly, too little
attention had been paid to the economic effects of
copyright law.
It was with this in mind that UNESCO drew up a
realistic convention. It is a complex technical ins-
trument designed to meet a complex technical
problem, but it expresses certain basic principles
which stand out clearly. Countries which are party
to the Gonvention undertake to give the same
copyright protection to foreign authors as to their
own nationals, if the foreign authors come from a
country adhering to the Convention or if their work
has been published in such a country. The minimum
period for copyright protection is fixed at 25 years,
with the exception of photographs and works of
applied art for which the minimum is 10 years. The
author is given the exclusive right to make or
authorize the translation of his work for seven years
after publication. If no translation has been made
in that period, a country may restrict this right
subject to the fulfilment of certain conditions
protecting authors such as payment and the assur-
ance of a correct translation.
Many of these principles already existed in the
Berne and Western Hemisphere conventions but it
is as part of a worldwide agreement that they can
be most effective. The Universal Copyright Conven-
tion draws the world together and bridges the three
watertight compartments into which it was formerly
divided : the Berne Union countries, the Western
Hemisphere countries and the countries which had
never joined any convention.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
TUE world of tomorrow will be aJL peaceful ne supp rting two or
three times its present population
only if the courage and the determina-
tion of all those who are seeking new
knowledge-especially the men of
science-are mobilized today.
Scientific discoveries are no longer
the monopoly of a privileged elite whose
members used to meet regularly in the
academies of Europe. The great discov-
eries of our time, rather than being the
fruit of the work of a group of scientists
in a given centre, are usually the sum
total of fragmentary results achieved by
scientists on every continent. This geo-
graphic expansion of science, however,
has complicated the problem of co-
ordinating research. It was primarily
40
in order to tackle this problem that
UNESCO established its network of
science co-operation offices. In Monte-
video, Cairo, Delhi and Jakarta, these re-
gional offices have become important
factors in the scientific life of three
immense areas of the world : Latin Ame-
rica, the Near East and southern Asia.
Meagre resources
and total disorder
CREA TED to encourage internationalexchanges and to combat the iso-
lation of universities and labora-
tories they have already supplied a
remarkable impulse to scientific work in
the three regions which they serve.
This is no cause for complacency.
Scientific research must travel a long
road before it is equal to the possibilities
- to say nothing of the needs-of our
modern world. For that matter, research
has never really been well organized in
the past-except for war and destruc-
tion."We worship research", a great
thinker and scientist who recently died
declared a few years ago,"and yet
narrow-mindedness, meagre resources
and total disorder are still the lot of
present-day research."
With the help of international scien-
tific organizations, UNESCO has at least
been able to encourage and co-ordinate
research in certain key fields, such as
nuclear physics and the development of
the world's arid zones.
UNESCO brought into being the
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
S. T. E. P. and Esso.
European Organization for Nuclear
Research and the Organization is now
constructing a laboratory near Geneva.
The 12 nations which founded this
Organization under UNESCO sponsorship
contribute to its annual budget of several
million dollars. Huge accelerators will
be built for research in high energy
particles to add to basic knowledge of
the structure of the atom.
Another international laboratory, the
International Computation Centre, is
being created in Rome. Similar steps
will probably be taken over the next
few years in such specialized branches
of science as cell growth (a contribution
to cancer research) or in developing the
use of radio-isotopes in physics, chemis-
try and biology.
The Unesco Courier
zone research is among the major
projects upon which, it is proposed,
Unesco should concentrate its efforts
and resources for the next five or tcn
years if need be. This is UNESCO's
answer to the recent warning of one of
the scientists collaborating in its arid
zone programme :"Up to the present, the
desert has kept the upper hand and we
have not been able to halt its advance.
Most of the work already accomplished
has been qualitative rather than quanti-
tative : we have still to establish a co-
ordinated research programme capable
of meeting the situation."
UNESCO has also launched research in
other fields. An advisory committee
on the ocean sciences has been set up to
apply our basic sciences to oceano-
graphic study. By grouping together
physicists, chemists, biologists or geolo-
gists for the study of specific problems,
UNESCO may contribute to the develop-
ment of fishing industries or the tapping
of plant and mineral resources in the
oceans. But it will also encourage
additions to human knowledge in a field
where unbelievable gaps still exist.
Hidden wealth of
oceans and forests
SCIENTIFICALL Y speaking, no oceanhuas ever really been studied and
there are great stretches of the
Indian Ocean and the South Pacific
which remain completely unexplored.
During a meeting called by UNESCO at
Tokyo in 1955. one oceanographer re-
called the eternal, universal attraction of
the sea."The study of the oceans,"he
added."is a source of wealth for man."
Other scientists have found equal wealth
in chemistry or in geology or in the
study of virgin forests. The goal of
every branch of science is to conquel
the world, not through violence but
through knowledge.
To scientists, the 15 million square
miles of humid tropical zone also rep-
resent unknbwn territory, even in cases
where they are overpopulated. They
make up one-third of the world's useable
land area, but the study of soils and
forests and hydrological, botanical and
zoological research have barely scratched
the surface in these regions. Here,
too, it is quite clear that while local
economies will be the first to benefit
from research, the scientist must set his
sights higher than the improvement of
agricultural or industrial conditions.
The most urgent need of all is the need
for knowledge.
41
The problem of the world's unproduc-
tive wastelands has become an urgent
one in recent years and the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations has clearly demonstrated the
need for solutions in the face of an
ever rising world population It has
often been repeated that"forest may
precede civilizations, but deserts follow
them". More than one-quarter of the
world's land area is now useless and the
desert is one of the greatest challenges
facing man and science.
Wind & sun energy
for fuel-poor lands
r-rHERE is no easy solution. First, thecausses f the lack rainfall must
be studied in each country facing
this problem. The geologist must step in
to analyse the structure of rocks and the
composition of soils and sands. Under-
ground water tables must be discovered
and a close study made of the plants
and animals which have adapted them-
selves for desert survival. Finally, full
use must be made of the energy of the
wind and the sun-the only natural
resources of fuel-starved lands, and
resources which have been virtually
ignored until now.
The problem of deserts and semi-arid
regions affects no less than 37 nations.
No single country can hope to carry out
all the research implied, but all countries
can benefit from the success achieved
by one. UNESCO's task is to encourage
research aimed at solving this problem
and to teach people to apply the results
of this research to their daily lives.
To halt the advance
of marching sands
T N 1951, UNESCO founded its AdvisoryCommittee on Arid Zone Research
to organize new research programmes
and to bring together information on re-
search already carried out. Meeting suc-
cessively at Ankara, Montpellier, Delhi,
Paris, and Tucson (Arizona), this com-
mittee has conducted symposiums in
subjects vital to the struggle against the
desert : hydrology, plant and animal
ecology, energy sources for arid zones
and soil study.
Over the past five years, UNESCO has
offered financial aid to centres and to
laboratories working to salvage arid or
semi-arid zones. This assistance will in
future be considerably expanded. Arid
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
THE'S'IN UNESCO
Links for world science
It can be said that international scientific activity is
guided today by two organizations-UNESCO and the In-
ternational Council of Scientific Unions (Icsu). Icsu was
set up in 1919 to co-ordinate research in pure science but
its activities were for long hampered by lack of funds.
It has gained new importance through work made possible
by the financial support it has had from UNEsco in the
past ten years, and today it is a centralizing link between
no less than 200 separate Unions.
When UNESCO came into existence some branches of
science still lacked a centralizing agency like Icsu. UNESCO
saw the need for councils on the Icsu pattern for the me-
dical and technological sciences and therefore helped to
establish the Council of International Organizations of
Medical Sciences in 1949 (50 members today) and the
Union of International Engineering Organizations in 1950
(13 members today). Together Icsu and these two newer
international bodies receive total annual subsidies from
UNESCO of about $200, 000 to assist them in their work.
Institute of the Hylean Amazon
As its first attempt to set on foot new kinds of inter-
national scientific co-operation UNEsco proposed to set up
an Institute of the Hylean Amazon. This region of South
America has never been explored in a co-ordinated or
systematic way. Tremendous research possibilities exist
there in many fields : types of wood suitable for building,
medicinal plants, geology, mineralogy and meteorology.
In 1947 eight states signed a convention stipulating that
the Institute would start work after five countries had
ratified it. These five ratifications were never secured and
the project ended in complete failure.
The basic idea, however, was later
revived in the form of a programme
of research for the humid tropical
zone (see next column).
WoHd's arid lands
In 1948 when it was proposed to
establish an Institute of the Arid
Zone, UNESCO, mindful of the lessons
of the Hylean Amazon project, exam-
ined the question cautiously. In
1950 it set up an Arid Zone Advisory
Committee which has since focussed
attention each year on one particular
problem concerning the world's arid
lands : hydrology, plant ecology, the
sources of power available in the arid
zone, particularly wind power and
solar energy, human and animal
ecology, and arid zone climatology.
Other activities have been encour-
aged including the preparation of
maps, and of reports on the purifica-
tion and use of saline water, dew
research, etc. The Arid Zone pro-
gramme is developing smoothly and
the project, important in itself, is
also a significant experiment in
international co-operation. Under
the leadership of the Arid Zone
committee, specialists in many lands
are put in touch with one another
42
through publications and at meetings such as the Wind
and Solar Energy Symposium at New Delhi in 1954 and
last year's meeting of arid zone specialists at Albuquerque,
New Mexico.
Humid tropical zone
Experience gained in launching the Arid Zone project
should serve to guide UNESCO in its new international en-
terprise relating to the humid tropical zone. Surveys of
institutes carrying out humid tropical zone research have
been made and a meeting of specialists engaged in this
type of research was held in March 1956 at Kandy (Cey-
lon), together with a symposium on methods of studying
tropical vegetation. Recommendations from the meeting
outlined the most useful areas for initiating and develop-
ing research. Other meetings of specialists and sympo-
siums will be held and fellowships for specialized training
in foreign institutes will be awarded to research workers.
Experts will be sent to those of UNESCO's member states
who make requests for them.
Exploring the vast oceans
Among deep sea areas we have little knowledge of the
South Pacific and still less of the Indian Ocean which, it
has been said, is less known to us than the surface of the
moon. But recent advances in the basic sciences give
hope that knowledge of the least explored regions of the
world's oceans can be developed, provided co-ordinated
use is made of the new techniques. In 1955, UNESCO set up
an Advisory Committee on Marine Sciences to study me-
thods of developing the scientific study of the ocean and to
supply information which would lead to increased use of
marine resources. It modelled this committee on the Arid
Zone Committee. The marine experts have since made
many suggestions as to where and how research could
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Science on show around the world
Few people would question the importance of science to society or the individual.
Yet educating the public in the achievements of modern science requires ways and
means which are not within the reach of all countries. Unesco has been able to support
the efforts of many governments to improve science teaching in schools. It has also
contributed to science education through articles in specialized publications and in
the general press, and through its travelling exhibitions which have well proved their
worth in all parts of the world.
The first of these exhibitions, (recent discoveries in physics and astronomy) toured
13 Latin American countries between 1950 and 1952. rit consisted of charts, photo-
graphs and also apparatus on which visitors could themselves conduct experiments.
Its success (13 countries visited, 470, 000 visitors) led to the organization of other
travelling exhibitions :"Our Senses and the Knowledge of the World", on display
for four years in the Far East (8 countries, 650, 000 visitors) ;"New Materials", first
shown on the shores of the Mediterranean before leaving for South America (7 coun-
tries visited since 1952, 630, 000 visitors) ;"Man Measures the Universe", touring
Europe since 195-4 (-4 countries, 200, 000 visitors)."Energy and its Transformations",
(photo, left) shown first in Paris in March 956 ; will tour the Far East for three years.
In addition to these exhibitions, each of which had demonstration apparatus
and which sometimes weighed as much as seven tons, Unesco organized a series of
exhibitions made up of photographic panels. These included :"Man Against the Desert"
(shown in Jerusalem in 1953) ;"Zoological Gardens-Wild Life and Mankind" (Indo-
nesia, 195-4) ;"Balance and Unbalance in Nature" (prepared with help from Unesco
by the International Union for the Protection of Nature) ;"The Construction of
Laboratory Apparatus for Schools" (Cairo, 1955).
most usefully be carried out. The use of an international
research vessel operated jointly by a group of UNESCO
Member States has been proposed.
Nations pool their resources
In 1950 UNESCO was asked'''to assist and encourage the
formation and organization of regional research centres
and laboratories."Out of this Conference resolution came
CERN, the European Organization for Nuclear Research,
now building an international laboratory for basic research
into the structure of the atom, at Geneva. (See below)
Another international laboratory project.'catalysed"
even earlier by UNESCO is the International Computation
Centre, but here progress has been disappointingly slow :
the convention establishing the centre in Rome still re-
quires ratification by five more countries to bring it into
force.
During the past two years UNESCO has been studying
problems involved in research into cell growth. Further
steps it now proposes in its programme for 1957/58 in-
clude : the encouragement of contacts between different
disciplines in the field of cell biology, symposia, fellowships
and research, the setting up of centres
for breeding pure lines of laboratory
animals and preparations for a regional
institute for the study of life under coin-
trolled conditions.
- *
Europe's Laboratory for Nuclear Research
Few governments can afford a major nuclear research programme
by themselves. It takes large, expensive and highly organized expe-
ditions to cross the frontiers of atomic science. The only solution is
international collaboration.
It was by being a catalyst for international scientific collaboration
that Unesco was able to bring into being the European Organization
for Nuclear Research and its research centre now being built at Meyrin,
near Geneva.
in n ! 950, Professor Rabi, Nobel prizewinner and member of the U. S.
delegation to Unesco's General Conference in Florence, defined the
idea of an international laboratory which has since found its place in
Unesco's doctrine of international co-operation. He urged that a
centre should be established in Western Europe and devoted to nuclear
research, pointing out that scientists in the U. S. A. and to a less degree
in the United Kingdom had at their disposal facilities which for financial
reasons were not available in the rest of Western Europe and elsewhere.
Professor Rabi urged that Unesco should try to combine nations in
regional groups so as to set up research centres comparable to those
existing in the U. S. A. He thought Unesco should serve as a catalyst
for world science, not operating research centres, but drawing up
preliminary plans and seeing they were satisfactorily carried out.
After several intergovernmental conferences called by Unesco, the
European Organization for Nuclear Research (usually referred to as
CERN from the French title of the temporary body that preceded it :
Conseil Européen pour la Recherche Nucléaire) reached its final form in
a convention now ratified by 12 countries, which came into force at
the end of t954, after three years of preparatory work.
The CERN laboratory is not concerned with atomic energy, but with
basic research on the structure of the atomic nucleus. Study of the
mechanism and behaviour of nuclear forces is focussed on the very
high-energy particles found principally in cosmic rays which reach the
earth from outer space, but which can be created artificially by bom-
barding atomic nuclei with the help of giant machines called particle
accelerators.
So CERN set up teams of leading specialists from its Member
States to design two accelerators : a 600 million electron-volt synchro-
cyclotron and a 25 thousand million electron-volt proto-synchrotron.
The speed of the particles generated in the second accelerator will
approach the speed of light-the absolute ceiling. (See the Unesco
Courier special number on"The Promise of Atomic Power", No. 2,
1954 ; U. S. March, 1955).
This is the first international organization for scientific research
set up by an inter-governmental convention. Its 1956 budget
amounts to about 40 million Swiss francs and the cost of the building
premises and plant, about 200 million Swiss francs, is being contri-
buted by CERN'S 12 member states. The cyclotron is expected to be
finished by the end of 1957 and the more powerful proton-synchrotron
at the end of 1960. Photo, loft. shows one of the two energizing
coils of the synchro-cyclotron electro-magnet being placed over the
pole plates.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
THE'S'IN UNESCO (Cont'd)
Explaining and teaching science
Since 1950 science teaching and dissemination has had
an important place in UNESCO's programme. One of its
most successful activities has been the travelling science
exhibition (see page 43). Inventories of apparatus and
materials for science teaching have also played an im-
portant part in this programme. A series of eight volu-
mes deals with the teaching of science in primary, sec-
ondary and vocational schools, universities and in six
types of technical colleges. These inventories have helped
to solve many problems of equipping school laboratories
in countries now in the throes of development. Published
in several languages they also provide a multilingual
glossary of scientific and technical terms.
In 1948 UNEsco published a little book entitled,"Sugges-
tions for Science Teachers in Devastated Countries"to
aid teachers whose work was handicapped by lack of
equipment. It has since published manuals for instructors
in countries where science teaching is developing for the
first time, explaining how to build simple apparatus using
easily obtainable materials.
To draw the attention of legislators, statesmen, ad-
ministrators and the organs of public opinion to the
social, political and economic consequences and possibi-
lities of science and technology, UNESCO publishes"Impact
of Science on Society."Now in its seventh year, this
quarterly, appearing in English and French, is largely
devoted to original studies on the social aspects of
science (1).
Guiding the steps of research
During the past two years, the development of science
on a really world-wide scale has been helped by the
work of an International Advisory Committee on Scientific
Research. It was established by UNEsco to'''promote in-
ternational co-operation between the national councils
and centres of scientific and technical research in fields
of common interest"and to advise UNESCO's Director-
General on"research and related matters in the Natural
Sciences Programme of UNESCO."The Committee can
advise UNESCO on the order of priority to be given to in-
ternational undertakings and, by organizing meetings
like the one at Milan in 1955 for representatives of
national research centres, it can help to stimulate the
formation of new national research centres in countries
where none so far exists.
Field Science Co-operation Offices
Latin America, the Middle East, South Asia and South-
east Asia-all these vast areas are now covered by scien-
tific missions in the shape of UNESCO's Field Science
Co-operation Offices. The Latin American Office (in
Uruguay since 1949) has done much to co-ordinate and
develop scientific research in this continent through
meetings, courses in modern research techniques, associa-
tions for the advancement of science and science exhibi-
tions. The Middle East Office (Cairo) has helped to solve
thousands of individual problems for scientists and has
concentrated chiefly on arid zone studies. The South
Asia Officie (New Delhi) and South-East Asia Office
(Jakarta) have helped scientists in these vast areas to
overcome many obstacles and to establish contacts with
each other. Set up to aid scientific liaison and becoming,
by force of circumstance, UNESCO liaison offices, they are
now situated in the centre of the latest trend in UNESCO's
policy toward direct participation in the efforts of
Member States, at their request, and a more judicious
implementation of the Expanded Programme of Technical
Assistance.
(1). 4 detailed and impartial account of ten years of science at
VSESCO bru Professor Marcel Florkin is qi"en in the latest issue of
"Impact", (t'olume \'11, So 3, September 1956).
44
CHARTER AGAINST
INJUSTICE
T N December 1948, the U. N. General Assemblyadopted the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights. UNESCO, which had con-
tributed to its preparation, immediately decid-
ed to make this declaration known as widely as
possible-a decision which it is still carrying
out. For UNESCO found in the Declaration of
Human Rights a source of support and encour-
agement. Charged with"reinforcing the mor-
al and intellectual solidarity"IOf mankind,
UNEsco was able to remind the world that such
solidarity could exist only if it were solidly
based upon respect for the individual.
All of UNESCO's activities contribute directly or
indirectly to the realization of human rights.
Through technical assistance and fundamental
education in the less developed countries, it has
worked to improve economic opportunities and
raise standards of living. It has helped to extend
free and compulsory primary education, so that
more and more children might enjoy the right to
education, and to improve teaching methods and
materials. It has aided in the development
of education for international understanding
through seminars, publications and experimental
programmes in schools. It has helped to promote
artistic and cultural activities and the advance-
ment of science, and to bring their benefits
within the reach of more and more people.
For UNEsco, The Universal Declaration of
Human Rights is not only a definition of stand-
ards, but a programme of action as well, and
every task it undertakes is aimed at making a
living reality of the principles of the Declaration.
Above, the U. N. stamp issued for Human Rights
Day (December 10) 1956. Below, the stamp com-
memorating U. N. Day (October 24) 1956.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
a
,
=au
3` 3q ̀ 3, :e ,.,. ' :
. a * e,° :,'- 3 : X :L.. : 4: ·-. , r=·, r ".... ·^', t : ? ̀ . F'. 8 a =  :, :R"s > :·, $. ,£'r` ". It. ^ ;: ̀xii ·a,. if p`...s s''..., `K n : ·, Ha·` r. . r. :·-, .·jazz̀kil.,. :. £' y , ·f : 3x a... e, >n .,, xv .  3'Ri. - a e"`jy,'b3 : i .'k..-, S. : s, ° Y : k Y4 Dus r. · i',, · r, ;. : E\", · . ez ; ; _
,g,, :sur.",, ;..,, 3', 
s L``,H
 :. =z r,.,  : i_ :",, ,., r wF. rut· ;.., ,  .  x..-.,, s . a -, a i3"v :,  : "'_ :, r. ''. :,. . & -.  ;  e. .-.. : ·,. ,. `.x= . : i,.= s=·`. 4,.., G, , r.-, -,, a ",: -a .. _-. . z.. _' , ,.. zF. 3- x".. s..b r. :.^ S.... &r,"3·-. ` ... "r : ,. ; :' : .. :. --_E : 3',. $ :. -... ` `-"p.,  : .-a. _.... e  =. ̀ A, a..,.   «,. a,  : .. _.,, "a", *. , a,.-...,  . ,. s.,.. , ; -.,.. s, 3"- _,  ·.-" `.. -., a...,-... ` ;.
Y T is mankind that counts in the long run. Man
is always the final goal of research. If this
- world is making progress, then it is thanks to
the union of science and of a humanism open to all
traditions and to all spiritual forces. In this respect,
the work now being undertaken on the publication
of a scientific and cultural history of mankind will
serve a use-ful purpose by shedding light on the
unanimity of hopes and the diversity of efforts
which, over the centuries, have built the heritage
we call civilization.
UNEsco has already shown how present-day man
manages to profit only poorly from this heritage.
He teaches his children an almost exclusively
national"history", thus giving them a deformed,
inadequate and occasionally absurd image of the
story of mankind. He painstakingly studies each
relic of'''his''literary or artistic traditions, exalting
their superiority over all other traditions. He boasts
of his great men and preaches their philosophies,
casting only scorn upon the glories and the philoso-
phies of others-when he is aware of their existence.
Realistic exchanges between the cultures of East
and West ; education stripped of political prejudices
and more receptive to the contributions of litera-
ture, the arts and religion without any arbitrary
exclusions : these are the goals sought by the
teachers, the writers and the philosophers who have
been called together on many occasions by UNESCO
to compare curricula and teaching methods. A host
as contacts has been established, books have been
published, and practical results have been achieved
in such fields as textbook revision in some lands.
In carrying out a great part of its work in this
field and in all fields growing out of a broadened
and rejuvenated humanism, UNESCO has received
the assistance of many associations which it
grouped together in 1949 in the International
Council for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies.
The activities carried out with the support of this
council run-from archaeology to the history of reli-
gion, from Hellenism to ethnography or from
Orientalism to medieval philosophy. However, the
objectives of this work are revealed in the review
Diogenes published by the council since 1952.
*
TT AST year, in defining itself as"a crossroads with
signposts indicating where man stands today
among all cultures of which he can be equally
proud to have been the author", this international
review at the same time drew the image of a future
toward which UNESCO must work. This extension of
the domain of the humanities to the fifteen or
twenty centres of civilizations which have given
modern man unequal but equally irreplaceable gifts,
has placed him in a position where he can no longer
afford to grant exorbitant privileges to one centre.
These results could not have been achieved had
UNESCO not declared, ten years ago, that one of its
foundation stones was"the intellectual solidarity of
mankind", and decided that it would favour.'all
action leading to a stronger union of traditions".
Throughout the entire world-and not merely in
45
the 77 countries making up UNESCO in 1956-men
have embarked on this intellectual collaboration
'from which all sources of civilization must benefit.
Over the past ten years, many barriers, once belie-
ved immovable, have fallen and many prejudices
have disappeared. Every time a breach has been
opened in the walls of ignorance, routine and fear,
it is because men have chosen knowledge rather
than resign themselves to a twilight existence.
This is the exploration of all the landmarks in the
last decade of the cultural life of nations. Free,
compulsory education has been given to millions of
children whose fathers never had the right to
schools. Through books, films and the radio, a huge
mass of knowledge has reached an ever-growing
audience. Cities and nations have awakened to
their historical and artistic treasures-and to the
human value of such treasures in general. In every
case, there have been leaders and pioneers-and it
is they who make up UNESCO.
*
su, in this respect, it would be wise to watch in
the future the work of UNESCO fellowship
holders. At present, they number more than a
thousand and, to many of them, their countries
have entrusted special responsibilities upon their
return from study abroad. Whether educators,
scientistes, sociologists, writers or artists, they have
been able to perfect their methods and techniques.
More important, they have acquired experience in
international co-operation. If they teach what they
have learned from this experience, the results of
their apprenticeship will be incalculable : in Europe,
more than 3, 000 workers representing almost every
trade have already been able to visit their counter-
parts in other countries. Students, too, are travel-
ling in greater and greater numbers : an annual
directory published by UNESCO lists more than 50 ; 000
fellowships for foreign students throughout the
world (1).
Here, too, youth organizations have played a
major role o'f which the international work camp
movement is only one example. For the past
decade, their organizations have learned to know
each other, to profit mutually from their experiences
and to settle their differences. Youth has found,
especially in fundamental education work, a chance
to use its generosity and its love of action.
These associations also help to constitute UNESCO,
a UNESCO reinforced by 400 international non-
governmental organizations. Thanks to them and
thanks to the UNESCO National Commissions of Mem-
ber States it is now possible to co-ordinate the efforts
of all men who seek to work for the progress o'f
reason and justice. In this way an immense intel-
lectual network is being built, a network resemblin. g
a nervous system whose sensitive tips reach out to
urate scientists in laboratories, workers in fields and
factories, and students in schools and universities.
It is in this way that modern men can work"in
the service of peace". Not by preaching peace...
but by building it.
(1) Vol. VII, 1956-57 of"Study Abroad"has recently beer
published. Price $2. 00 ; 10/6 ; 500 frs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
Above, scale model of Unesco
Headquarters site, showing
Secretariat Building (top), Con-
ference Building with its con-
certina-like roof and the vast,
paved piazza with an"island"
of grass. Below, architect's
sketch of main building reveals
its supporting concrete co-
lumns. Right, the view of a
structure taken in July 1956.
Modelas and photos R. Szczesnowicz
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
UNESCO, whose Paris headquarters for the past tenyearns has been a hotel near the Arc de Triomphe,
swill soon have a new permanent home on a seven
and a half acre site near the Eiffel Tower, on the left
bank of the Seine.
Comprising two buildings of striking design in a setting
of gardens, trees and patios, the new headquarters is an
architectural innovation for postwar Paris. The larger
of the two buildings, a seven-storey. Y-shaped struc-
ture, 90 feet high, is for the UNESCO staff. It is support-
ed on"stilts"so that it appears to be suspended in the
air, and its reinforced concrete frame is enclosed by
50, 000 square feet of glass in some 950 windows.
Thanks to the Y form, each of the 600 offices overlooks
Paris. The ceiling of each is sound-proofed and slopes
up gradually until it meets a large window. The building
also houses staff meeting rooms, a medical centre, restau-
rant, cafeteria and bar for delegates and stuff. Three
systems of heating-hot water radiators, radiant heat
and temperature-controlled forced ventilation-will be
used to meet the needs of different areas.
In the basement are five radio and television studios,
workshops, a cinema, central heating equipment, a
telephone switchboard with 100 outside and 1, 300 internal
lines, emergency electricity plant and storerooms. Work-
shops where UNEsco documents and publications are print-
ed cover a total surface of 21, 500 square feet.
Standing in the curve of one arm of the main buiding
is the low trapezoidal structure grouping conference halls
and services. The largest of its main halls seats about
700 people, including members of the public. Each hall
is fitted with the latest equipment for simultaneous
interpretation in the four official languages of UNESCO.
The H. Q. was designed by an international team of
architects-Bernard Zehrfuss of France, Pier Nervi of
Italy and Marcel Breuer of the United States-aided by
an advisory committee of five famous architects : Lucio
Costa (Brazil) ; Walter Gropius (U. S. A.) ; Charles Le Cor-
busier (France) ; Sven Markelius (Sweden) ; and Ernesto
Rogers Italy). Chief Engineer in charge of building
operations on the site is the American engineer and
architect, Eugene H. Callison.
The designers were required to complete,
the vacant half of the semi-circular Place
de Fontenoy laid out by the 18th century °"
architect, Jacques-Ange Gabriel, creator p g
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
New Unesco H. Q.
(Continued)
of the Paris Military College and the
Petit Trianon at Versailles. They were
also restricted to a height of seven
storeys. Working under these limita-
tions, they designed a building in the
form of a Y, whose curved prongs form
three unbroken facade, one of which
completes Gabriel's plan for the Place de
Fontenoy.
For the decoration of the new H. Q.,
UNESCO's Director-General is advised by
a committee of art specialists. So far,
six internationally-known artists have
agreed to execute works. Pablo Picasso,
for example, is to produce a mural
covering 1, 100 square feet in the
Conference Building. A monumental
sculpture for the main piazza will be
made by Henry Moore of Great Britain.
France's Jean Arp will do a bas-relief or
some other decorative work on the outer
wall of the library, Alexander Calder of
the U. S. A. will design a mobile for the
garden, Spain's Joan Miro will execute a
ceramic mural, forty feet by six feet, and
Isamu Noguchi (Japan) will arrange the
decoration of the delegates'patio and a
20th-century garden based on traditional
Japanese gardens. A number of UNESCO's
Member States particularly reputed for
their achievements in interior decorat-
ing have been asked to carry out the
decoration of six committee rooms, the
library and the press room.
Floor surfaces of the two buildings add
up to over seven acres, but only one-
eighth of the total H. Q. site is occupied
by buildings, leaving room for gardens,
patios and parking space for cars. Cost
of construction and equipment being
carried out by firms from six countries
is covered by an interest-free loan from
the French Government.
Ground was broken on the new site
(leased to UNESCO by the French Govern-
ment for 99 years at a symbolic annual
rent of approximately two dollars and
eighty cents) in April 1955 and struc-
tural work on both buildings was com-
pleted in July 1956. The installation of
services and the interior decorating are
due to be finished by the autumn of
1957, when the UNESCO staff will move
to the new H. Q. from its present tem-
porary quarters.
When completed, UNESCO's Head-
quarters will undoubtedly become one of
the show places of Paris,"embodying",
as Dr. Luther Evans, UNESCO's Director-
General, has put it, ;"as far as architec-
tural design can, the inheritance of our
past and the hope of our future."
UNESCO
Above, air view of Unesco H. Q. site and Paris Military College
Below, location in Paris of Unesco site. Woods, indicated by
dots, are Bois de Boulogne (left) and Bois de Vincennes. New
Unesco H. Q. extends axis of three famous Paris landmarks-the
Palais de Chaillot, (not shown it diagram, bottom of page), the
Eiffel Tower and the Military College. Dome rising above Unesco
buildings is the Invalides, where Napoleon was buried in 1840.
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Model and photo R. Szczesnowicz
MAXIMUM AIR AND UGHTare assured for offices by design
of main Unesco building. Lifts, services and passages are in a
central core ; all offices look out over Paris. Model shows it as
it will appear when completed. At centre is main entrance.
UNESCO
MASSIVE YET GRACEFUL trapezoidal concrete pillar is one
of supports for Conference Building roof. The wooden forms
into which the concrete was poured have left their marks on the
supports-so that they become a planned decorative element.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Sir,
After reading the article by Dr. E. H.
Ackerknecht,"No'Hocus Pocus'in the
Medicine Man"[THE UNESCO COURIER,
July-August 1956 : U. S. September], I
am convinced that primitive medicine
is on a par with that taught by the great
European Faculties of Medicine. Would
you therefore be kind enough to give
me the address of a good medicine man
who might be able to rid me of my
headaches.
Michel Demaret.
Lithe, France.
Editor's note : If our correspondent cares
to inform us how much he is willing to
spend for his journey, we will gladly supply
At'm with a reliable address in Africa or
Melanesia.
Sir,
In his article"Haunting Museums
Hidden in the Jungle", describing Bahnar
cemeteries in Indo-China, [THE UNESCO
COURIER, September 1956 : U. S., Octo-
ber], Frantz Laforest writes :"Tombs,
now in ruin, have four small megaliths
round them, and also mysterious figures.
These'thinkers'at the corners recall
the korwars of Melanesia. Are these
statues'companions'for the souls of
the dead ? Some represent couples lock-
ed in an embrace. Do they symbolize
a rebirth or a survival ? The wooden
phantoms in these haunting museums
will eventually disappear, taking their
secret with them."These"thinkers",
seated with elbows on knees and head
in hands (in the Solomon Isles, support-
ing the head in the hands is a ritual
gesture used to indicate the spirit of
a dead person) are also found in the
Philippines and in New Guinea where
they represent ancestor spirits which the
living wish to conciliate with offerings,
marks of respect and prayers. The
"thinkers"of the Bahnar cemeteries
resemble much more closely the ancestor
figures of the Philippines and New
Guinea than the korwars of Melanesia,
mentioned in the article. Here also
ancestors are represented but the attitude
is slightly different, a karwar being a
seated man leaning on a shield.
The Bahnar cemetery"thinkers"are
undoubtedly ancestor figures like those
of the Philippines and New Guinea and
I do not think we can say a true
"mystery"surrounds them. This is sim-
ply one minor detail from the amazing
complexity of the mysterious Megalithic
culture to which Frantz Laforest has
referred so pertinently.
Might I, at the same time, congratu-
late you on the general standard of your
articles. You have managed to gain
a large readership without in any way
yielding to the temptation of the facile
solution. Within a world framework of
cultural development you are doing a
remarkable job of popularization.
Without lowering your standards, you
arouse in the non-specialist reader an
interest in questions that the public
generally leaves to experts. You do it
so effectively that the reader feels an
urge to find out still more, to go beyond
the bounds both of the material limit-
ations of your articles, and the limit
of his own knowledge.
Bernard Peirani.
Paris, France.
Sir,
I am president of a small club-the
United Nations Youth Fellowship-
which is a junior branch of the U. N.
Association in Adelaide. Our 150
members include many nationalities,
including Europeans and Asian students.
In our six years of existence we have
had little contact with similar U. N.
youth groups in other parts of the world.
Perhaps we might be able to compare
our activities and interests through
THE UNESCO COURIER, thus gaining ideas
to add more variety and life to our
yearly programmes. Has there been an
issue on international cooking and ways
of eating yet ? I'm sure we have much
to learn here in Australia on that
subject.
A. C. Adams.
North Adelaide,
South Australia.
Sir,
I find that your article,"No Right to
Despise a Fellow Creature"by G. P.
Malalasekera ["Twenty-five Centuries of
Buddhist Art and Culture", UNESCO
COURIER, June 1956 : U. S. August] is an
extract from Buddhism and the Race
Concept written for UNESCO jointly by
Professor Malalasekera and me. I there-
fore have to presume that since you
have published this as an article exclus-
ively by Prof. Malalasekera without
recognition of my authorship, this is
due to inadvertence on your part.
K. N. JayatUIeke.
University of Ceylon,
Editor's note : The editors sincerely regret
the inadvertent omission of Professor Jay-
atilleke's name. The study in question,
scheduled for publication in 1957, is for
the UNESCO series,"The Race Question
and Modern Thought".
Sir,
Aged 16 and a half, I am in the senior
class of a French secondary school. I
have been a subscriber to THE UNESCO
COURIER for the past year, and consider
it a remarkable magazine. Interested
in all questions of a general cultural
nature, particularly ethnography and
archaeology, I have always found your
magazine full of interesting facts.
Furthermore, its articles have the great
advantage of being within everyone's
grasp and it never has the dull and
tedious character of so many scientific
publications.
Leo Hughes.
Strasbourg (Bas-Rhin),
France.
Reserve your UNESCO COURIER at your magazine stand now-25c per copy
Subscribe today-$2. 50 per year-Two years $4. 50
Frill in this subscription b ! ank and mai) it with your check or money order to :
UNESCO PUBLICATIONS CENTER. U. S. A.
152 West 42nd Street, New York 36, New York
Piease enter my subscription for the UNESCO COURIER a One year $2. 50 a Two years $4. 50
Name"""""""""",,,.,,,.,..,,,,,.,,,,,.,.....,.,,""",."",.."""""""""..,.."""."",."",..".,.""""'..'"".".,..,.',.."."""",,,,""".".",."""",.",.,..."",...".."",.."",.",
(please print)
Ad dress".",.,..,.......'"...",.,."..",".",..,.".""""""""""""'",...'...,.".",,,...,,,,,,,,,,,,,'.',,,,,,".",...,."".",,,,..,,."",.",,,,,.,,,,,,,,,,,.,,,,..,",."".".".",.",.",..,,,.,..,...
(pease print)
City.......",'"'""..""""""....""""".........".,..""",..""".""..."....",,,,,,,".,,"""'"''''''Zo ne... .."....... Print)
Letters to the Editor
50
w
U
Z
< (
æ
z
w
""
a
a
"-
2
ã1
< (
"-
Z
z
< (
... J
V>
W
L :)
0 :
o
uw
L :)
è.
. É
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
NEXT MONTH
A SPECIAL
NEW YEAR GIFT
Our January 1957
Issue
TEN PAGES OF FULL
COLOUR PLATES OF
ANCIENT MASTER-
PIECES OF WORLD
ART
An extra-especial
52-page issue devoted
entirely to the art of
I RAN
SPAIN
ITALY
SINGLE COPY PRICE :
50 cents, 2/-, 100 Fr. fro
Subscribers will receive this
special number at no extra
cost. SUBSCRIBE NOW.
Send a gift subscription
to your friends,
Annual rate :
$2. 50 ; 8/- ; 400 Fr. fr.
ADAM AND EVE driven out of Paradise. Detail of
one of Masaccio's great frescoes in the Brancacci
Chapel, Church of Santa Maria del Carmine. Florence.
Taken from the (forthcoming Unesco Album, U Masaccio Ho
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
In th mountain overcooking Cuzco. ancient capit ; \1 oaf the Inc Empire, !.'ant
the.'Rio Villcanota Alley (sown here) the Peruvian Government hats set
up a fundamental education protect. It ins bering. ruin bey teaches strained in the
Regional Fundamental Education Centre four Latin Am !-pica crested in 1951 by
Unesco ant the Mexican Government-. Toddy Unesco"aids sis rational funds-
metal education centre ant support project in 30 cout"iès : (see pare 24)
UNESCO-de R. are.
UNESCO IN THE LAND OF THE INCAS
]]>
</page>
</document>
